<Collection>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0001 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 2320EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Philippines 1stLd-Writethru a0704 03-04 0771</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Philippines, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0704,0790</SECOND>
<HEAD>Attempt to Arrest Governor Tied to Coup Attempt Leaves 14 Dead</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 7 grafs to UPDATE with some rebels surrendering,
30 hostages released. Pick up 7th graf pvs, ``Troops blocked....'
SUBS 2 grafs for final graf to UPDATE with Enrile arraignment
delayed.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos MLA1,5,6</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT H. REID</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MANILA, Philippines (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Officials tried Sunday to arrest a
governor indicted in a recent coup attempt, but his supporters
defended him in clashes that left at least 14 people dead,
including a general, authorities said.
   The trouble began early Sunday when officials sent to arrest
Gov. Rodolfo Aguinaldo in the city of Tuguegarao were taken hostage
in a hotel. Later, government forces stormed the hotel, leading to
a series of clashes later in the day in the city. At least 10
people were reported wounded.
   Aguinaldo, a former lieutenant colonel, escaped, but officials
said Sunday about 200 of his followers had surrendered.
   The military chief of staff, Gen. Renato de Villa, placed the
armed forces on nationwide alert and ordered the military to
capture Aguinaldo ``at all costs.''
   Scattered shooting was still reported late Sunday in Tuguegarao,
capital of Cagayan province 250 miles north of Manila.
   Col. Emiliano Templo told reporters Aguinaldo's followers were
believed to be holding some people hostage in homes near the hotel.
   However, Acting Gov. Melvin Vargas said 10 more Aguinaldo
followers surrendered early Monday and released about 30 hostages
they were holding at a pawn shop. It was unclear if other hostages
were still being held.
   Troops blocked a major bridge south of Tuguegarao, stranding
thousands of travelers. Templo said Aguinaldo's followers included
his private army, government militiamen and army Scout Rangers.
   Marines were flown from Manila on Sunday to reinforce security
in Tuguegarao, a city of more than 80,000 people. Philippine
Airlines canceled flights to the city and schools were ordered
closed Monday.
   In Manila, a homemade bomb exploded late Sunday in the Makati
district, but no injuries were reported and it was apparently
unrelated to the fighting.
   Local Governments Secretary Luis Santos and Brig. Gen. Oscar
Florendo had gone to Tuguegarao to serve Aguinaldo with the arrest
warrant.
   Before dawn, Aguinaldo's supporters surrounded the six-story
Delfino Hotel and took Florendo, chief of the military's civil
relations service, and three aides prisoner and trapped Santos and
others on the second floor.
   About 3 p.m., government forces launched an attack. Florendo,
51, was wounded during the rescue and was dead on arrival at a city
hospital, said defense spokeswoman Lourdes Ilustre.
   Santos, two mayors, two colonels and a navy commodore were
rescued unharmed, officials said.
   Casualty figures were incomplete, but regional commander Col.
Miguel Fontanilla said at least 14 people died.
   They included 10 killed during a clash at a checkpoint near a
bridge, three in fighting near a gasoline station and Florendo at
the hotel, he said.
   President Corazon Aquino said Florendo ``was killed by one of
the followers of suspended Gov. Rodolfo Aguinaldo .... The act of
cowardice and treachery of Aguinaldo's followers will not go
unpunished.
   ``I call on all our people to continue to reject violence and
uphold our constitutional democracy and the processes of law in a
peaceful manner.''
   In a radio interview at the hotel earlier Sunday, Aguinaldo said
he was a ``victim of injustice .... I don't mind dying as a
villain.'' He threatened to take his followers into the mountains
and become ``a rebel.''
   Aguinaldo was suspended in January as governor of Cagayan
province for allegedly supporting the Dec. 1-9 military rebellion
and had been holed up in his hometown of Gattaran, 45 miles north
of Tuguegarao.
   Aquinaldo told a Manila radio station on Dec. 1 that he was
sending tanks and artillery to the city to support mutineers trying
to oust Mrs. Aquino.
   The governor was indicted along with Sen. Juan Ponce Enrile and
five others in connection with the coup attempt, the sixth and
bloodiest attempt to topple Mrs. Aquino since she took power in
1986.
   Enrile appeared in court Monday to face the charge of
``rebellion with murder'' in connection with the failed coup. But
the arraignment was put off until the Supreme Court decides whether
the charge is valid. The court is to hear arguments Tuesday.
   Aguinaldo was also implicated but never charged in a August 1987
coup attempt. Later, he raised a private army, ostensibly to fight
Communist guerrillas. He ran for provincial governor in January
1988 and was elected by a landslide. Aguinaldo was formerly the
provincial commander of Cagayan and many of the troopers assigned
there are believed loyal to him.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0002 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 2348EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a BC-LOT--SaturdayLotteries     03-04 0756</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-LOT--Saturday Lotteries,0888</SECOND>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<HEAD>ARIZONA</HEAD>
<HEAD>Pick</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PHOENIX (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers in Saturday night's drawing
of the Arizona Lottery's Pick game were 3, 4, 5, 7, 17 and 34 with
a bonus number of 40.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>CALIFORNIA</HEAD>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers picked Saturday night for the
California Lottery's twice-weekly ``Lotto 6-49'' game: 38, 35, 8,
34, 23, 14 and the bonus number, 5.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>COLORADO</HEAD>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DENVER (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the six numbers selected Saturday night
in this week's Lotto drawing:
   4-16-32-37-35-38
</TEXT>
<HEAD>CONNECTICUT</HEAD>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEWINGTON, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning combination picked Saturday
in the Connecticut State Lottery's ``Daily Lottery'' drawing was:
   7-0-6
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Play 4</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEWINGTON, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning combination picked Saturday
in the Connecticut State Lottery's ``Play 4'' drawing was:
   2-9-6-0.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>ILLINOIS</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SPRINGFIELD, Ill. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the Illinois State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   6-0-1
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick Four</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   4-2-4-9
</TEXT>
<HEAD>LOTTO</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   1-20-28-33-46-54
</TEXT>
<HEAD>IOWA</HEAD>
<HEAD>Iowa Lotto</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DES MOINES, Iowa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The numbers drawn in Iowa Lotto game
Saturday were 12, 26, 27, 28, 34 and 35.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto America</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DES MOINES, Iowa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers drawn Saturday night
in ``Lotto America'' are:
   13-14-19-22-46-50
</TEXT>
<HEAD>KANSAS</HEAD>
<HEAD>Kan. Cash Lotto</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOPEKA, Kan. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers in the Kansas Cash Lotto
drawing Saturday night with an estimated jackpot of $47,000:
   1-8-12-17-32-33.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>KENTUCKY</HEAD>
<HEAD>Kentucky Lottery</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOUISVILLE, Ky. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are Saturday's winning numbers
selected by the Kentucky Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Kentucky Cash:
   2-9-5.
   </HEAD>
<HEAD>Weekly Lotto:
   10-11-18-37-40-41
   </HEAD>
<HEAD>MICHIGAN</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DETROIT (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected Saturday in
the Michigan State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   0-2-3
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily-4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   1-2-6-3
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto 47</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   4, 44, 6, 36, 39, 29
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Zinger</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   7-7-1-9-6-3
</TEXT>
<HEAD>MISSOURI</HEAD>
<HEAD>Pick 3</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ST. LOUIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers in Saturday's Missouri
Lottery Daily Pick 3 game:
   4-3-4
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ST. LOUIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers in Missouri's Lotto drawing
Saturday night:
   3-13-17-26-33-38
</TEXT>
<HEAD>NEW JERSEY</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TRENTON, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday night in the New Jersey State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 3</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   3-3-0
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   5-1-8-1
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lottery-Lucky 7</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TRENTON, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday night in the New Jersey State Lottery's Lucky 7 game:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lucky 7</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   5-10-23-25-34-35-55-59-60-72
</TEXT>
<HEAD>NEW YORK</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ALBANY, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the New York State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Number</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   9-6-6
</TEXT>
<HEAD>WinFour</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   6-8-1-5
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lottery Glance-Keno</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ALBANY, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the New York State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Keno</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   3, 7, 8, 9, 15, 17, 20, 21, 24, 31, 38, 41, 56, 58, 61, 63, 65,
68, 72 and 79.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lottery Glance-Lotto</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ALBANY, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the New York State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   11, 16, 31, 35, 40, 49. The supplementary number was 30.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>NORTHERN NEW ENGLAND</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CONCORD, N.H. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the daily New Hampshire, Vermont and Maine lotteries:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 3</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   6-3-7
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   3-1-7-2
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Tri-State Megabucks</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CONCORD, N.H. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers in the
``Tri-State Megabucks'' game for New Hampshire, Vermont and Maine:
   15-17-21-22-26-30
</TEXT>
<HEAD>OHIO</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CLEVELAND (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected Saturday
night in the Ohio Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Super Lotto</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   4-5-32-33-34-40
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Kicker</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   9-7-9-5-0-6
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 3 Numbers</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   9-3-3
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 4 Numbers</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   5-0-8-6
</TEXT>
<HEAD>OREGON</HEAD>
<HEAD>Daily 4</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PORTLAND, Ore. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are Saturday's winning numbers in the
``Oregon Daily 4'' lottery game:
   7-2-4-1
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Megabucks</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SALEM, Ore. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers in Saturday night's
drawing in the Oregon Lottery's Megabucks lotto game were:
   4-12-17-21-39-44
</TEXT>
<HEAD>PENNSYLVANIA</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HARRISBURG (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected Saturday
in the Pennsylvania State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Number</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   9-9-4
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Big 4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   8-2-5-2
</TEXT>
<HEAD>VIRGINIA</HEAD>
<HEAD>Pick 3</HEAD>
<DATELINE>RICHMOND (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   These numbers were drawn Saturday in the
Virginia Lottery's weekly Lottery drawing:
   2, 17, 18, 21, 26, 41
</TEXT>
<HEAD>WASHINGTON, DC</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The following lotteries were drawn Saturday in
the District of Columbia Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lucky Numbers Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   4-3-2
</TEXT>
<HEAD>D.C. Four Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   8-7-3-0
</TEXT>
<HEAD>D.C. Daily Double Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   8, 15
</TEXT>
<HEAD>D.C. Quick Cash Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   35-31-1-3-29-25
</TEXT>
<HEAD>WEST VIRGINIA</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CHARLESTON, W.Va. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the West Virginia State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily 3</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   4-6-3
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily 4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   9-2-1-1
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0003 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 2358EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-BasketballDeath     03-04 0332</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Basketball Death,0346</SECOND>
<HEAD>Star of California College Dies After Collapsing on Court</HEAD>
<BYLINE>JOHN NADEL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Sports Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A college basketball star expected to be
chosen in the first round of the professional draft, died Sunday
after collapsing during a tournament game.
   Hank Gathers, 23, crumpled to the court moments after sinking a
thunderous slam dunk for Loyola Marymount University in a West
Coast Conference tournament game against Portland.
   He appeared to suffer convulsions for a few seconds while his
mother and sister rushed out the stands in front of a hushed crowd
at Gersten Pavilion. Their cries were audible to everyone in the
building.
   He was taken to Daniel Freeman Marina Hospital, where he was
pronounced dead.
   Cardiologist Mason Weiss told a news conference the cause of
death was unknown and an autopsy would be performed.
   Gathers was given medication after a similar collapse during a
game Dec. 9, and doctors said at the time they believed the problem
was an accelerated heartbeat.
   Gathers was one of only two players in Division I of the
National Collegiate Athletic Association to lead the nation in
scoring and rebounding in the same season. As a junior last season,
Gathers averaged 32.7 points and 13.7 rebounds, joining Xavier
McDaniel of Wichita State in 1984-85 as the only NCAA player to
lead the nation in both categories.
   His 1,015 points last season ranked him 11th on the all-time
single-season scoring list.
   A 6-foot-7, 210-pound center from Philadelphia, Gathers was
expected to be a first-round selection in this year's National
Basketball Association draft.
   The game was cancelled with Marymount's Lions leading Portland
25-13 in the first half. The rest of the tournament also was
postponed.
   ``It all happened so fast,'' Portland coach Larry Steele said
after sending his players back to the team's hotel. ``Within two
seconds, everybody realized thatHank needed help. Right now, we're
not even having a thought.''
   Gathers and teammate Bo Kimble lead the nation in scoring this
season.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0004 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 0040EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Suffolk-Plastics     03-04 0321</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Suffolk-Plastics,0334</SECOND>
<HEAD>Appeals Court Overturns Landmark Plastics Ban</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A widely imitated environmental law banning
plastic food containers and grocery bags was overturned by a state
appeals court.
   The Suffolk County law _ intended to rid dumps of long-lasting
plastics _ was invalid because the county failed to prepare an
environmental impact statement, the Appellate Division of the state
Supreme Court said in a unanimous ruling Friday.
   The law was hailed by environmentalists and became the model for
measures around the country after it was passed in 1988 by the
county on Long Island.
   It banned restaurants, bars, grocery stores and other retail
food establishments from using two plastics _ polystyrene, a
foam-like material used for cups, trays and cartons, and polyvinyl
chloride, used for grocery bags.
   ``I am going to lift up my plastic-foam cup and salute the
judges that struck down a law that would have crippled plastics
recycling,'' said Leonard Raskin, a member of the Consumer
Packaging Coalition, an industry group that opposed the law.
   Plastics interests challenged the law because the county hadn't
filed an environmental impact statement.
   Suffolk County Executive Patrick G. Halpin said the county
``felt the benefits were obvious and, therefore, didn't require a
full impact statement.''
   Halpin said the county had yet to decide if it would appeal.
   But plastics industry officials said it the law would force the
use of more paper containers, which also are slow to disintegrate
in landfills.
   ``Switching plastics with paper was nonsense,'' Raskin said.
``Researchers are finding 40-year-old newspapers in California
landfills.''
   The law's chief sponsor, Legislator Stephen C. Englebright,
noted that a state law to protect drinking water requires that all
landfills on Long Island close by the end of the year.
   ``The industry goes in with the specious argument that plastics
are better for landfills than paper,'' Englebright said. ``The
ruling ignores the fact that we aren't going to have landfills.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0005 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 0044EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Chernobyl     03-04 0208</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Chernobyl,200</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ukrainian Legislature Votes to Close Chernobyl</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Ukrainian government plans to phase out
operations at the Chernobyl nuclear power plant over the next five
years, according to reports cited by The Washington Post.
   However, it is unclear whether the Soviet republic's government
has authority over the Chernobyl plant, site of the world's worst
nuclear accident.
   The Post, in its Sunday editions, said an official government
publication reported the Ukrainian legislature recently passed a
resolution to close the power station.
   In April 1986, at least 31 people were killed and hundreds more
sickened when radiation was released after an explosion and fire at
the power plant in the western Soviet republic.
   Soviet authorities have said they would not close Chernobyl
because it would result in an energy shortage in the region and
other Warsaw Pact countries in Eastern Europe.
   However, nuclear power plants in other areas, including Armenia
and the Crimea, have been closed because of increased pressure from
environmentalists.
   The Soviet central government has traditionally had authority
over facilities such as power plants in local Soviet communities.
But recent power-sharing between the republics and Moscow has
encouraged speculation that the decision made in Kiev, the
Ukrainian capital, will stand, the Post said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0006 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 0045EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BRF--HawaiianAir-Pentagon     03-04 0158</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Hawaiian Air-Pentagon,0163</SECOND>
<HEAD>Pentagon Bans Military From Flying Hawaiian Air</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HONOLULU (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Military personnel flying on official duty have
been barred from using Hawaiian Airlines, the Department of Defense
announced.
   Discrepancies in the airline's maintenance practices and
documentation caused the ruling, Pentagon officials said.
   The action was taken Feb. 23 following a scheduled week-long
maintenance inspection by the Defense Department.
   ``The company is meeting with the Military Airlift Command and
intends to resume MAC charters in the near future,'' Hawaiian
Airline spokesman Keoni Wagner said Friday.
   The carrier has been serving the military since 1963.
   ``The discrepancies found during the week-long visit concerned
maintenance practices, procedures and documentation, which were
being done improperly or not at all,'' according to a statement
issued through the Air Force Military Airlift Command office at
Hickam Air Force Base.
   The order bars the carrier from serving individual military
personnel on commercial flights, or from flying charter flights for
military maneuvers.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0007 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 0136EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>d a AM-BRF--YellowstoneBison     03-04 0161</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Yellowstone Bison,0166</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bison Hunt Possible After Animals Stray From Park, Officials Say</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HELENA, Mont. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hunters may be called in to kill some of
the 20 bison that wandered out of Yellowstone National Park late
last week, state wildlife officials said Saturday.
   Park bison are thought to carry the disease brucellosis, which
can cause spontaneous abortion in cattle.
   The animals were spotted by a game warden Thursday night grazing
outside the park's west boundary, said John Cada of the state
Department of Fish, Wildlife and Parks.
   ``A hunt is likely if the bison get in a position where we can
take some,'' Cada told The Associated Press. ``We may take a few to
encourage the others to return to the park.''
   State law allows the controlled hunting of bison that enter
Montana from the national park.
   The policy has aroused the wrath of animal-rights groups, which
objected when the state allowed hunters to kill 569 bison last
winter.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0008 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 0045EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Britain-Hostages     03-04 0225</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Britain-Hostages,0233</SECOND>
<HEAD>Newspaper Reports Iranians in Beirut for Hostage Negotiations</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A London newspaper reported Sunday that a
delegation of Iranian officials has arrived in Beirut on a mission
to free one or more of the Western hostages held in Lebanon.
   The Independent on Sunday said its information came from
unidentified Lebanese and Iranian exiles in London and Paris.
   ``One exile who took part in previous hostage negotiations said
he expected a release within days, but others said a final decision
depended on the outcome of political infighting in Tehran,'' the
paper said.
   The report follows a spate of statements from Iranian newspapers
and officials in recent days saying the hostages should be released
because they are fueling propaganda against Iran.
   The Independent on Sunday reported the Iranian team sent to
Beirut was dispatched by President Hashemi Rafsanjani of Iran.
   Iran's so-called pragmatists, led by Rafsanjani, want to repair
damaged relations with the West. But they are at odds with
hard-line, anti-Western radicals, led by former Interior Minister
Ali Akbar Mohtashemi.
   There are 18 Westerners missing in Lebanon. Most are believed
held by pro-Iranian factions.
   The hostages include eight Americans, four Britons, two Swiss,
two West Germans, an Italian and an Irishman. The longest held is
Terry Anderson, chief Middle East correspondent for The Associated
Press. He was kidnapped March 16, 1985.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0009 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 0048EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Obit-Faulk     03-04 0337</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Faulk,0349</SECOND>
<HEAD>Veteran Newspaperman was Executive Editor of Vicksburg Post</HEAD>
<DATELINE>VICKSBURG, Miss. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Charles Johnson Faulk Jr., who rose from
cub reporter to executive editor of the Vicksburg Evening Post and
Vicksburg Sunday Post in a career that spanned a half-century, died
Saturday at a hospital. He was 74.
   Faulk's career with the Vicksburg newspaper began in 1935 when
he signed on as a cub reporter. Over the years, he was promoted to
city editor, managing editor and executive editor. For the past six
years he wrote a Sunday column.
   Except for a stint in the Navy and 10 years with the state
Highway Department in the 1950s and 1960s, Faulk, a Mississippi
native, worked for the newspaper until the day his final illness
began.
   When he passed the 50-year mark in the field, he wrote that
newspapering, to him, had been ``America at the grassroots. The
greatest 50 years of all time, in the greatest profession of all
time. I call it life in the fast lane. Life on the wide screen.
Three dimensional.''
   Faulk was honored many times during his career, including for
his role as part of the newspaper's team that received the Pulitzer
Prize for coverage of a 1953 tornado.
   He also covered the founding of local industries, integration,
the mechanization of farms and the electrification of the rural
South.
   ``For over 50 years Charlie Faulk was an integral part of the
Vicksburg Evening Post,'' said editor and publisher Pat Cashman.
   ``Charlie was both a gentle person and a gentleman; a person
from an age of graciousness and manners that are often lacking
today. His loyalty to the newspaper and his work are almost without
comparison.
   ``Charlie was a wordsmith who excelled at his craft. His writing
could capture places, events and feelings from long-past days and
make them remarkably alive for many people,'' Cashman said.
   Faulk, a widower, is survived by a brother, a sister, two sons,
a daughter, nine grandchildren and one great-granddaughter.
   Funeral services were scheduled for Monday.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0010 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 0102EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-RacialAttack 1stLd-Writethru a0524 03-04 0797</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Racial Attack, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0524,0819</SECOND>
<HEAD>Witness Disappearance Threatens Racial Murder Trial</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 4th graf, `Hynes maintains ...', with 6 grafs to UPDATE
with protest march, ADD that Hynes' predecessor made deal with
Vento; pick up 5th graf pvs, ```Without him ...'; SUBS penultimate
graf to conform.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By RONALD POWERS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An important witness went ``into the wind,''
apparently skipping town and carrying with him a key part of the
prosecution's case against six white men charged with murdering a
black teen-ager.
   John Vento admitted participating in the Aug. 23 racial attack
on Yusuf Hawkins and agreed to testify for the prosecution _ but he
disappeared in December.
   Jury selection in the case was to start Monday. Brooklyn
District Attorney Charles J. Hynes said he would seek a one-month
adjournment unless the 21-year-old high-school dropout surfaces.
   On Saturday, meanwhile, about 300 people led by Hawkins' father
marched to Vento's home in the mainly white Bensonhurst
neighborhood of Brooklyn to protest prosectors' handling of the
case.
   ``It seems that this case has never been taken seriously by the
district attorney's office,'' said the Rev. Al Sharpton, a march
organizer.
   Police on motorcycles and wearing riot gear separated the
marchers, who arrived in six buses about 2:30 p.m., from
Bensonhurst residents.
   ``Everything was peaceful,'' said Officer Ralph St. Just, a
police spokesman. He reported no arrests.
   Former District Attorney Elizabeth Holtzman had struck a deal to
drop charges against Vento if he would testify.
   Hynes, who took office in January, maintains the loss of Vento's
testimony would not be devastating. But privately, prosecutors say
the case is ``improved immeasurably'' with Vento's participation.
   ``Without him, is it hopeless? The opinion is divided,'' said
one source in the prosecutor's office who spoke on condition that
he not be identified.
   Lawyers for the defendants say even if Vento reappears, Hynes
has suffered a major setback.
   Vento is ``going to be a lowlife with no credibility,'' defense
lawyer Stephen Murphy said.
   Vento was a member of a gang of some 30 young whites _ many of
them wielding baseball bats _ who surrounded the 16-year-old
Hawkins and three of his friends on a street in the mainly white
Bensonhurst neighborhood.
   The gang had assembled out of a mistaken belief that a group of
blacks and Hispanics were about to enter their enclave to attend a
neighborhood girl's birthday party and create trouble. Police said
the whites set upon Hawkins and his pals, who had come to look at a
used car for sale.
   Joseph Fama, 19, is charged with fatally shooting Hawkins in the
chest. Five other whites also have been charged in the killing, and
a seventh is charged with assault. Only Fama is being held without
bail.
   Hynes said Vento ``went into the wind'' around Christmas.
Authorities do not believe he met with foul play. Instead, Hynes
believes Vento ``chickened out'' when faced with the prospect of
testifying against his friends.
   In announcing Vento's disappearance last week, prosecutors tried
to lure him back, saying that if he breaks his promise to testify,
they have sufficient evidence to charge him with second-degree
murder for his role in the attack.
   Murphy, attorney for alleged Bensonhurst ringleader Keith
Mondello, 20, said the credibility of a major witness who
prosecutors admit took part in a murder and then fled after cutting
a generous deal is nil.
   The other defense lawyers agree. ``His decision to abscond will
probably severely undermine his credibility as a witness,'' said
Benjamin Brafman, the lawyer for defendant James Patino, 24.
   ``I have to assume that prosecutors believe he's going to be a
very important witness,'' Brafman said. ``Normally, when a witness
who could be a defendant gets a complete pass, that person is
deemed extremely important by the prosecution.''
   Stanley Meyer, lawyer for the accused triggerman, described
Vento as ``an integral part'' of Hynes' case. He said Vento was
expected to testify that someone put the gun in Fama's hands.
   ``We dispute that,'' Meyer said. ``The thought crosses my mind
that maybe he doesn't want to testify because he doesn't want to
commit perjury.''
   Hawkins' parents said Thursday they felt betrayed by
prosecutors, who they said promised them there would be no deals
with their son's attackers.
   The case has reunited some of the lead characters from another
case that grabbed the city's attention 2{ years ago _ the Howard
Beach case, in which a white mob chased a black man onto a highway,
where he was killed by a car.
   Hynes successfully prosecuted that case, and went on to be
elected Brooklyn district attorney last year, succeeding Holtzman,
who was elected city comptroller.
   Murphy, a scrappy lawyer who speaks in a scream, defended the
only Howard Beach murder defendant who was acquitted.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0011 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 0057EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Panama-Peru     03-04 0327</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-Peru,0337</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<HEAD>Protesters Firebomb Peruvian Embassy Sheltering Noriega Officers</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARIA VICTORIA GONZALEZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Protesters threw firebombs at the
Peruvian Embassy on Saturday, angered because the embassy is giving
refuge to two officers who were allied with ousted dictator Manuel
Antonio Noriega.
   There were no injuries or serious damage in the incident. U.S.
soldiers and Panamanian police restored order.
   The protest was organized by widows of Panamanian soldiers slain
in the Oct. 3 attempt to topple Noriega. They are angered that
Gonzalo Gonzalez and Heraclides Sucre, who are accused of killing
coup leader Maj. Moises Giroldi, have taken refuge in the embassy.
   Protesters also said they were concerned that the Panamanian
government guaranteed safe passage Wednesday to Noriega's family
and several other Noriega associates. Noriega's family left into
exile Friday night.
   Giroldi's widow Adela led about 70 protesters, including other
widows and relatives of officers executed after surrendering during
the insurrection against Noriega, who headed Panama's military
until he was overthrown by the United States in a Dec. 20 invasion.
   The Defense Forces under Noriega had said 10 officers were
killed in the coup attempt. A human rights official estimated the
total number dead at 77.
   Mrs. Giroldi said she doesn't know who threw the firebombs. ``It
was peaceful and that the incidents were provoked by unknown
people,'' she said.
   ``The pressure that we have been applying is sufficient. It's a
matter of being firm with the Peruvian government,'' she added.
   After the embassy incident, the protesters met with Ricardo
Arias Calderon, first vice president and minister of justice and
security. Arias Calderon guaranteed the widows that the government
would not grant safe conduct to Gonzalez and Sucre.
   ``I, along with the foreign minister (Julio Linares), are
offering our apologies to the government of Peru,'' he said. ``It
was a sad incident; it violated international law. There were
troublemakers, unknown people.''
   No Peruvian diplomats were available for comment.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0012 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 0113EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-GreyhoundStrike 4thLd-Writethru a0645 03-04 0966</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Greyhound Strike, 4th Ld - Writethru, a0645,0988</SECOND>
<HEAD>Striker Killed When Crushed by Bus on Picket Line</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 8th graf with police saying fatality appeared
accidental; pickup 9th graf, `Initial reports...</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY24, RED1, RED2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROGER PETTERSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   A striking Greyhound Lines Inc. bus driver was hit by a coach
and killed while picketing Saturday in the second day of a walkout
that has nearly shut down service by the only nationwide bus
company.
   The striker in Redding, Calif., was crushed against a wall as a
temporary driver hired for the walkout was trying to maneuver his
bus around a pickup truck driven by another striker, witnesses
said. Police questioned the driver but didn't arrest him.
   Elsewhere, there were scattered confrontations between strikers
and replacement drivers in the walkout that stranded many travelers
and left hundreds of small communities without public intercity
transportation.
   The Amalgamated Council of Greyhound Local Unions, which
represents more than 9,000 employees, including all 6,300 drivers
and most maintenance and office workers, went on strike Friday
after negotiators in Scottsdale, Ariz., failed to reach agreement
on pay. No talks were scheduled.
   Greyhound Chairman Fred G. Currey said Saturday the company was
operating 25 percent of its routes and would continue increasing
operations each day. He said an additional 700 union-covered
employees had crossed picket lines since noon Friday, pushing to
1,800 the number of union members on the job. Of that number,
however, only about 350 were drivers. The company also has 700 new
hires.
   Union spokesman Jeffrey Nelson disputed Currey's figures, saying
union officials believed just 10 percent of routes were in
operation.
   In the Redding death, police said the replacement driver
continued on the route after the bus hit the striker. He later
flagged down a Highway Patrol officer and was taken in for
questioning, then released without being charged, said police
Officer Steve Fiddler. The officer was unable to explain why the
driver stopped.
   ``We don't believe that he intentionally ran over this person,''
police investigator John Severson said. ``Short of that, we're not
going to say whether he's wrong or right.''
   Initial reports to Greyhound indicated the driver didn't realize
he hit the picket, said company spokesman George Gravley in Dallas.
   Company offials were told the striker was crushed when the bus
backed up as the driver tried to maneuver around a pickup truck
whose driver was trying to block the way out of the terminal,
Gravley said.
   The victim was Robert Waterhouse, 59, of Redding, 30-year
veteran driver planning to retire this year.
   The replacement driver, Theodore Graham, of Portland, Ore., had
worked for two trucking companies and had a safe driving record
with both of them, according to his application to Greyhound,
Gravley said.
   Both union officials and Greyhound's Currey issued condolence
messages to the dead man's family, but Currey went on to suggest
the strikers were at fault.
   Everyone involved, Currey said, ``will have to live with the
circumstances of their behavior, but especially the driver of the
pickup.''
   The condolence statement by Edward M. Strait, president of the
national union, urged strikers and supporters on the picket lines
to be ``extremely cautious.''
   Currey said the company was seeking several court orders against
picket line violence.
   A Pittsburgh judge issued an order Friday limiting picket lines
at the local station to three people.
   In Chicago, where gunshots were fired at a bus and a terminal
the first night of the strike, a judge issued an order Saturday
against picket line violence. Two passengers were slightly injured
by flying glass.
   In Philadelphia, three men threw rocks at a bus late Friday,
breaking windows and bruising a passenger. Police said the rocks
were thrown after the bus, carrying 15 passengers from Washington,
stopped about two blocks from Philadelphia's downtown bus terminal
because several women jumped in front of it. Two men were arrested.
   In Toledo, Ohio, a picket was hit by a bus Saturday, but the
striker wasn't seriously injured and the driver wasn't charged,
police said.
   During the bus line's last strike, in 1983, a striking Greyhound
driver was killed near Zanesville, Ohio, when he was run over while
standing in front of a bus being used to train replacement drivers.
A grand jury declined to indict.
   In an Associated Press interview Saturday, Currey said the
company had put away enough money to weather a strike. Greyhound is
has so many applications for replacement drivers that the company
could resume service on all its routes by the end of March if the
strike last that long, he said.
   Currey refused to say how much was set aside as a contingency,
but called one reported estimate of $54 million ``conservative.''
   Greyhound serves 9,500 destinations, including 9,000 where it is
the only intercity transportation available, nd the strike stranded
many travelers.
   The Interstate Commerce Commission, which regulates Greyhound
and similar companies, kept regional offices in San Francisco,
Chicago and Philadelphia open Saturday to process applications from
smaller bus companies that want to serve Greyhound routes.
   The United Bus Owners of America, representing nearly 1,000
small bus companies, said private operators are prepared to run
buses on Greyhound routes around the country.
   In Chicago, ICC regional officer David Armitage said Saturday
morning he had three applications but didn't have specifics. Glenn
Eady, ICC regional compliance officer in Philadelphia, said his
office had four applications for the Eastern region, which
encompasses 23 states from Maine to Florida.
   In the failed negotiations, the company wanted some pay
increases contingent on increased ridership, safety records and
productivity factors. The union refuses to accept the contingencies.
   Greyhound drivers, who according to the company earned an
average of $24,743 last year, took a 22 percent pay cut three years
ago in negotiations before a leveraged buyout of the company.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0013 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 0148EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Westmar-Teikyo 1stLd-Writethru a0630 03-04 0708</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Westmar-Teikyo, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0630,0728</SECOND>
<HEAD>Westmar College to Become Branch of Japanese University</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 10 grafs to UPDATE with board votes approval; pick
up 9th graf, `Faculty, students ...</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By GREG SMITH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LE MARS, Iowa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Westmar College trustees voted
overwhelmingly Saturday to become a branch of Teikyo University of
Japan, a merger that Westmar's president called a marriage but four
trustees protested by resigning.
   More than two-thirds of the 37-member board approved the merger
after a six-hour session, college President Arthur Richardson said
at a news conference late Saturday. He declined to disclose the
actual vote count.
   The agreement will bring a substantial dowry to the tiny,
century-old college and gives Tokyo-based Teikyo its third branch
in the United States. Teikyo has nine other campuses in Japan, and
branches in England and Holland.
   Robert Rydell of Des Moines, chairman of the board of trustees
until he and three other members resigned to protest the merger
agreement, said he was ``terribly disappointed'' by the move.
   ``They have called it a marriage. But in my judgment the
engagement period was way too short. We didn't have a chance to get
acquainted,'' he said.
   Richardson said the Board of Trustees would dissolve itself in
about 10 days and re-form with at least seven members, the majority
of whom will be Americans.
   The acting chairman of the new board will be Takashi Yamanaka,
chairman of the executive committee at Teikyo's Loretto Heights
University in Denver.
   The agreement clears the way for up to 200 Japanese to arrive on
the 62-acre campus in April or May and join Westmar's 566 students
when classes begin in September, Richardson said. He said up to 200
more would arrive in Le Mars, about 20 miles northeast of Sioux
City, for the fall term in 1991.
   Teikyo has an enrollment of more than 13,000 students. It
already has agreements to buy Loretto Heights from Regis College
and to buy Salem College in Salem, W. Va.
   ``Iowa is `down to earth' and its people have very healthy
minds. I'd like to introduce that to Japanese. It's important to
introduce your Iowa values,'' Yamanaka said earlier.
   Faculty, students and trustees were disappointed Richardson
didn't tell them what was going on until last month. The merger
talks began in November.
   ``It did kind of happen all of a sudden,'' Richardson said.
``But you can't announce a gift you don't have.''
   On the edge of financial collapse in the mid-1980s when
enrollment bottomed out at 417 students, Westmar has been searching
for ``some kind of international arrangement,'' he said.
   Others worried that the United Methodist Church would sever its
relationship with Westmar.
   The college, celebrating its centennial this year, receives
about $90,000 annually from the church.
   Gregory Clapper, a Methodist minister and the school's director
of religion and philosophy programs, said the school's mission is
more important than money.
   ``What has always been more important for many people than the
money which the institution gives to Westmar is the simple,
powerful, symbolic statement: `We are a United Methodist
College,''' Clapper wrote in a letter published in the Le Mars
Daily Sentinel.
   Le Mars Chamber of Commerce President John Boyd, a 1967 graduate
of Westmar, said the Japanese students would help the local economy.
   ``For every $1 spent, that would be turned over seven times. If
a student from Westmar comes in and spends $100 a month, they're
infusing $700 into our economy,'' Boyd said.
   Other residents want the Japanese to stay away.
   ``Our leaders in Washington have been giving in to Japan. Our
ex-president even went over and got paid off after he got out of
office. Also, why should we pay for all the military protection for
Japan and then let Japan come over here and buy us out?'' Don
Eickholt of Hinton said in a letter to the Sentinel, referring to a
recent trip by former President Reagan paid for by a Japanese
company.
   ``I believe they want students schooled in this country so they
will be able to take over,'' his letter said. ``The younger
generation think dealing with Japan is a way to make a buck, and
that is important to them. Who won World War II, I wonder.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0014 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 0543EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i BC-Soviet-Election     03-04 0223</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Soviet-Election,0229</SECOND>
<HEAD>Slavic Republics Head to Polls in Local Balloting</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Millions of Soviets voted throughout the country's
Slavic heartland on Sunday in a test of the Communist Party and
government apparatus' power to withstand rising demands for
democracy.
   Nearly 150 million voters living from the Polish border to the
Bering Strait were to choose candidates for 1,800 seats in the
legislatures of the Russian, Ukrainian and Byelorussian republics.
Thousands of seats in local governing councils also were being
contested.
   The balloting came in a period of increasing political tension
as President Mikhail S. Gorbachev's reforms reached a critical
stage.
   Gorbachev has pressed the Communist Party into giving up its
constitutional monopoly on power, and the national Congress of
People's Deputies meets in a week to debate creating a new and more
powerful presidency. Pro-democracy rallies in Moscow and across the
country have drawn hundreds of thousands of people.
   But hundreds of longtime party and government officials were on
the ballots and official newspapers were full of stories of
campaign tricks and porkbarrel politics as they sought to avoid the
kind of embarrassing defeats they suffered last year in balloting
for the national Congress.
   Balloting in the dominant Slavic republics followed votes in the
Baltic republic Lithuania swept by candidates endorsed by the
pro-independence Sajudis movement, and several other republics.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0015 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 0601EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i BC-Mandela 1stLd-Writethru   03-04 0375</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Mandela, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0668,0385</SECOND>
<HEAD>Precede: LUSAKA</HEAD>
<HEAD>ANC Leader Arrives to Emotional Welcome in Zimbabwe</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: UPDATES throughout with Mandela arriving in Zimbabwe</NOTE>
<DATELINE>HARARE, Zimbabwe (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Nelson Mandela arrived Sunday in
Zimbabwe on the second stop of the South African black leader's
four-nation tour.
   Mandela, 71, vice president of the African National Congress,
was emotionally welcomed at Harare airport by the former guerrilla
chieftain who became Zimbabwe's first black ruler in what once was
a British colony.
   President Robert Mugabe, who long agitated for Mandela's release
from South African prisons, embraced the ANC activist on the tarmac
as thousands of wellwishers cheered to the throb of tribal drummers
when Mandela arrived from Zambia.
   ``You're not a stranger,'' Mugabe declared as school children in
feather head-dresses chanted, ``We're Going to Pretoria to fight.''
   ``You've come home where the 10 million people stand solidly
behind the people of South Africa in the unrelenting struggle,'' he
added.
   Larger-than-life portraits of Mandela festooned lamp posts and
trees on the road to the airport.
   Mandela, freed on February 11 after 27 years' imprisonment for
anti-government activities, will witness first-hand how
white-governed Rhodesia was transformed into black-ruled Zimbabwe.
Aides to the ANC leader say he views Zimbabwe as a possible model
for a future South Africa.
   Mugabe himself spent 10 years in detention under the regime of
Rhodesian Prime Minister Ian D. Smith before he led the seven-year
war that yielded independence in 1980.
   Since then, Mugabe has pursued a policy of reconciliation
between whites and blacks, rival tribes and opposing political
movements. Whites have held Cabinet posts.
   Mandela was to address a rally called by Mugabe to launch his
ruling Zimbabwe African National Union (Patriotic Front) party's
campaign for parliamentary and presidential elections at the end of
this month.
   Later, Mandela will be feted at a government banquet and on
Monday he will visit Heroes' Acre _ a North Korean-built monument
to the 27,000 Zimbabweans killed in the independence war.
   After spending three days in Zimbabwe, the ANC leader is
scheduled to visit ANC facilities, including guerrilla training
camps, in Tanzania.
   He is expected to visit Tambo in Sweden before ending his first
foreign trip since he made a clandestine border crossing in 1962 to
undergo political training Ethiopia.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0016 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 0730EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i BC-Ciskei-Coup 1stLd-Writethru   03-04 0399</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Ciskei-Coup, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0674,0407</SECOND>
<HEAD>Military Takes Over in South African Black Homeland</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Leads with 8 grafs to UPDATE that coup occurred early Sunday,
scene, Gqozo reportedly coup leader, background. Pickup 7th graf
`Ciskei, a...'</NOTE>
<DATELINE>JOHANNESBURG, South Africa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The military in the nominally
independent Ciskei homeland overthrew the government early Sunday,
detained top army officials and placed the Cabinet under house
arrest, an officer announced over local radio.
   Brig. O.J. Gqozo said on Radio Ciskei that the army seized the
government of President Lennox Sebe in a bloodless coup after
repeated pleas from the public.
   More than two hours before the broadcast, South African Foreign
Minister Pik Botha had announced in Pretoria that there had been an
attempted coup overnight in Ciskei, and that all parties had been
asked to remain calm.
   He said he would try to reach Sebe, who the South African Press
Association said was on a trade mission to the Far East. Sebe was
president of the Republic of Ciskei on South Africa's southern
coast since it was declared independent in 1981.
   The presidential palace was deserted, with the doors standing
open, but the capital, Bisho, was calm, reported Louise Flanagan, a
journalist from the independent Albany News Agency.
   Gqozo said Lt. Gen. Kwame Sebe, son of the overthrown president,
had been detained, along with the commander of the defense force,
Brig. S.S. Zwelendaba, and the second in command, Brig. A. Sixishe.
   The radio announcement said Cabinet ministers had been placed
under house arrest.
   Gqozo was the leader of the coup and had been recalled early
this year from Pretoria, where he had been Ciskei's military
attache to South Africa, a Ciskei Radio journalist told the South
African Press Association. The journalist, who was not identified,
said the coup had been led by soldiers at the Jongunso Bomvu
military headquarters in King William's Town, where Gqozo was based.
   Ciskei, a 3,600-square-mile homeland of the Xhosa tribe, is not
recogized outside South Africa.
   South Africa has 10 tribal homelands, designated by the white
minority government as the countries of origin of the black
majority of 28 million. The homelands comprise most of the 13
percent of South African territory where blacks are allowed to own
land.
   Anti-apartheid organizations such as the African National
Congress oppose the homelands system, saying it deprived black
South Africans of their citizenship rights and separate whites and
blacks.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0017 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 0924EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i BC-Philippines-Governor 6th-Writethru   03-04 0615</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Philippines-Governor, 6th-Writethru,a0679,0631</SECOND>
<HEAD>Army Ends Hostage Standoff With Renegade Governor; 14 Killed</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Leads with 15 grafs to UPDATE with 14 killed, 200 followers
arrested, edits to tighten. Pickup 17th graf, `He was...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By EILEEN GUERRERO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MANILA, Philippines (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Government troops in a northern city
Sunday attacked a hotel seized by supporters of a governor who was
indicted in a coup attempt. At least 14 people, including a
general, were killed, officials said.
   At least 10 others were wounded in a series of clashes in
Tuguegarao between government forces and followers of suspended
Gov. Rodolfo Aguinaldo, who escaped during the fighting. His
whereabouts were unknown.
   Aguinaldo, a former lieutenant colonel, was indicted for
rebellion and murder in the Dec. 1-9 failed coup seeking to
overthrow President Corazon Aquino.
   Military Chief of Staff Gen. Renato de Villa placed the armed
forces on nationwide alert and ordered the capture of Aguinaldo
``at all costs.''
   Many of Aguinaldo's followers were members of a militia raised,
trained and equipped by the Aquino administration. About 200 of
them surrendered.
   One of the victims, Brig. Gen. Oscar Florendo, had gone to
Tuguegarao, 250 miles north of Manila, to serve Aguinaldo with the
arrest warrant, said local Governments Secretary Luis Santos.
   Before dawn, Aguinaldo's supporters surrounded the six-story
Delfin Hotel and took Florendo, chief of the military's civil
relations service, and three aides prisoner and trapped Santos and
others on the second floor.
   About 3 p.m., government forces launched an attack. Florendo,
51, was wounded during the rescue and was dead on arrival at a city
hospital, said defense spokeswoman Lourdes Ilustre.
   Santos, two mayors, two colonels and a navy commodore were
rescued unharmed, officials said. Santos said, ``This rebellion is
open defiance of the established authority and they must be brought
to the bar of justice.''
   Casualty figures were incomplete, but regional commander Col.
Miguel Fontanilla said at least 14 people died. They included 10
killed during a clash at a checkpoint near a bridge, three in
fighting near a gasoline station and Florendo at the hotel.
   Mrs. Aquino said Florendo ``was killed by one of the followers
of suspended Gov. Rodolfo Aguinaldo. ... The act of cowardice and
treachery of Aguinaldo's followers will not go unpunished.
   ``I call on all our people to continue to reject violence and
uphold our constitutional democracy and the processes of law in a
peaceful manner,'' she said.
   In a radio interview at the hotel earlier Sunday, Aguinaldo said
he was a ``victim of injustice. ... I don't mind dying as a
villain.''
   He threatened to take his followers into the mountains and
become ``a rebel.'' Aguinaldo had been holed up in his hometown of
Gattaran, about 45 miles north of Tuguegarao.
   He was suspended in January as governor of Cagayan province for
allegedly supporting the military rebellion. He told a Manila radio
station on Dec. 1 that he was sending tanks and artillery to the
city to support mutineers trying to oust Mrs. Aquino.
   The governor was indicted along with Sen. Juan Ponce Enrile and
five others in connection with the sixth and bloodiest attempt to
topple Mrs. Aquino since she took power in the February 1986
uprising against the late President Ferdinand Marcos.
   Cagayan is Enrile's home province and his political stronghold.
   Aguinaldo, a former lieutenant colonel, was implicated but never
charged in the August 1987 coup attempt. Later, he resigned his
commission and raised a private army, ostensibly to fight Communist
guerrillas. He ran for provincial governor in January 1988 and was
elected by a landslide.
   Aguinaldo was formerly the provincial commander of Cagayan and
many of the enlisted troopers assigned there are believed loyal to
him.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0018 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 1106EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ReformBishop     03-04 0714</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Reform Bishop,0734</SECOND>
<HEAD>A Bishop with a Convert's Zeal _ for Reform</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RICK HAMPSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The only bishop to have signed a recent
statement calling for drastic reforms in the Roman Catholic Church
says he's prepared to live with the reverberations.
   ``Christ didn't promise us an easy life,'' Bishop Emerson Moore
said.
   ``What we need is honesty and openness in the church _ true
dialogue,'' he said in an interview. ``If that means I have to
suffer for saying so, that's all right.''
   But so far, he said, ``I haven't been called a heretic. My
loyalty to the Holy Father (Pope John Paul II) and His Eminence
(Cardinal John O'Connor) is certainly not in question.''
   The ``Call for Reform,'' published Wednesday as an advertisement
in The New York Times, urged basic changes in the church, including
the ordination of women and married men as priests.
   Moore is one of seven auxiliary bishops who serves the
archdiocese of New York under Cardinal O'Connor, the most prominent
conservative among American prelates.
   O'Connor said last week he did not believe ``the statement
advances the spirit of the (Second Vatican) Council.'' He also
complained that several of its proposals ``implicitly reject
positions clearly affirmed by successive popes, including Pope John
Paul II, and can but lead to confusion about Church teaching.''
   In theology, causing confusion is a serious charge, and Moore
said O'Connor had told him how he felt about the statement.
   But Moore said he does not fear retribution.
   ``There may be differences of opinion among us, but the
archdiocese has always been a family to me, and supportive of me,''
he said. ``There's leeway to disagree, thank God.''
   Moore, one of 13 black American bishops, was arrested in 1984
for blocking the entrance to the South African consulate in New
York. Moore said O'Connor supported his stand ``even though the
cardinal would not have done that himself.''
   The statement Moore signed was drawn up by several liberal
Catholic groups. Moore said he was particularly impressed with its
complaint that groups are ``marginalized in our church because of
race and ethnic identity.''
   The statement also says the church ``is crippled by its failure
to address fundamental justice issues within its structures'' and
is ``a stumbling block to both its own members and to society.''
   The statement's signers said they see ``theologians silenced,
constructive opposition condemned, loyalty oaths imposed and blind
obedience demanded'' and ``church officials conducting financial
dealings in secret without accountability to the people.''
   The statement asks the pope to share his power. It asserts the
right of priests, nuns and lay Catholics to help select their local
bishops and to be consulted in the development of church policy on
sexual issues.
   The call for reform was initiated by Chicago-based Call to
Action, a group that hopes to collect 100,000 signatures by year's
end. So far the statement has been signed by about 4,500 Catholics,
including a number of prominent theologians and numerous nuns and
priests.
   And one bishop.
   Moore said he received the statement in the mail several months
ago and decided to sign because ``I was interested in its basic
thrust, even though I didn't agree with every statement.'' One
change of which he is particularly leery, he said, is the
ordination of women.
   Margaret McClory of Call to Action said Moore was sent the
statement because he was on the group's mailing list, and that
individual bishops were not asked to sign.
   Moore, 61, converted to Catholicism when he was 15 and became a
bishop at the relatively young age of 44. He supported the
presidential candidacy of Jesse Jackson, although the church frowns
on such political involvement by its clergy, and repeatedly has
asserted that the church has racist tendencies.
   But when George Stallings, a black priest in Washington, broke
away from the church last year and held his own services, Moore
joined the other black bishops in renouncing his move.
   McClory said several Catholics who helped pay for the ad asked
that their names be withheld because they worked for church
institutions.
   Moore said he did not think his own career in the church had
been harmed. Then he added: ``I'd much rather spend the rest of my
life in New York anyway.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0019 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 1116EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Obit-Blitz     03-04 0254</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Blitz,0260</SECOND>
<HEAD>Club Med Founder Dead at 78</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Gerard Blitz, founder of the Club Mediterranee
empire of vacation villages billed as an ``antidote to
civilization,'' has died in a Paris hospital, company officials
said Sunday. He was 78.
   Blitz died Saturday night at Cochin Hospital following a serious
illness, the officials said. The cause of death was not disclosed.
   A Belgian-born diamond-cutter by trade, Blitz created Club Med
in 1950 as a nonprofit association and led the first group of
vacationers to a tent village in Spain's Balearic Islands.
   Club Med villages progressed from tents to straw huts to modern
hotel facilities, prospering with a formula of completely pre-paid,
no-tipping vacations in which clients pay with colored beads for
the few extras like souvenirs or bar drinks.
   With its image of sun, sand and relaxation, Club Med grew into
one of the world's largest tourism groups, with more than 87,000
beds in its resorts.
   Much of the credit for the growth went to Gilbert Trigano, who
supplied tents for Club Med in the early years, joined the company
in 1954 and succeeded Blitz as president in 1963. Blitz remained
honorary president until his death and continued to participate in
the company's planning sessions.
   ``He was an extraordinary man who had an immense understanding
of life,'' Trigano said Sunday. ``He was a man of happiness.''
   Blitz, who was born Feb. 28, 1912, was married twice, first to
Denise Libbrecht and then to Claudine Coindeau. He had four sons
and a daughter.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0020 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 1116EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Turkey-TrainCrash     03-04 0193</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Turkey-Train Crash,0200</SECOND>
<HEAD>Two Passenger Trains Collide; Two Killed, 60 Injured</HEAD>
<DATELINE>POLATLI, Turkey (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two passenger trains collided head-on
Sunday, killing at least two people and injuring 60, the Anatolia
news agency said.
   Causes of the crash in Polatli, 45 miles southwest of Ankara,
were not immediately clear.
   A train from Ankara heading for Istanbul rammed into an
Ankara-bound train from the Aegean coastal city of Izmir, the news
agency said.
   Thirty-three of the injured passengers were hospitalized, four
in serious condition, said Anatolia.
   The engineer of the Ankara-bound train died and rescue workers
later pulled the body of a passenger from a derailed car, the
agency said.
   Anatolia quoted the engineer of the Istanbul-bound train as
saying he stepped on the brakes then jumped from the train just
before impact.
   A passenger fom Izmir, Bulent Isiten, said his train had just
stopped at the Polatli station and was gaining speed before the
collision.
   ``I think the other train was coming at a very high speed,''
Isiten told Anatolia.
   Signal failure or error by one of the engineers may have caused
the crash, said Birkan Erdal, director of Turkey's railway
authority.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0021 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 1116EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Peru     03-04 0157</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Peru,0160</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ninety-Five Guerrillas Captured in Security Operation</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LIMA, Peru (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Army and police units working together
captured 95 leftist guerrillas in the northern Andes, officials
said.
   Elsewhere Saturday, rebels shot and killed an employee of a
government irrigation project at his home in Ayacucho, 230 miles
southeast of Lima, police said.
   And in Huancayo, 140 miles east of Lima, rebels shot and killed
two men and a woman in separate incidents. Police said rebels left
a note on one victim reading, ``This is how thieves die.''
   The 95 Shining Path rebels were captured in Yanama, 215 miles
northeast of Lima in the Black Mountains, an interior department
spokesman said. Arms and explosives were also recovered, he said,
speaking on condition of anonymity.
   The Shining Path has been fighting Peru's elected governments
since 1980. The government says more than 18,000 people have been
killed in the fighting, including police, soldiers, rebels,
government officials and civilians.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0022 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 1117EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--HouseCollapse     03-04 0091</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--House Collapse,0092</SECOND>
<HEAD>House Collapses, Kills Seven</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DHAKA, Bangladesh (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A mud house collapsed during heavy
rains, killing seven members of a family near the southern coastal
town of Cox's Bazaar, police said Sunday.
   Three other people were injured in the collapse, which occured
Saturday on the outskirts of the town, 185 miles southeast of
Dhaka, police said on condition of anonymity.
   Two days of heavy rains disrupted life in Cox's Bazaar, located
on the Bay of Bengal.
   The victims included an 11-day-old infant and its mother, police
said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0023 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 1118EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Britain-Politics     03-04 0196</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Britain-Politics,0204</SECOND>
<HEAD>Conservatives 19 Points Behind; Poll Indicates By-Election Loss</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Conservatives lagged 19 percent behind the
opposition Labor Party in a poll published Sunday, the governing
party's worst showing in 20 years.
   Another poll showed the Conservatives in danger of losing a
formerly safe seat in Parliament in a by-election later this month
in central England.
   A poll published in The Sunday Correspondent showed 52 percent
favored Labor, the first time the survey showed the opposition
party with a majority.
   That was a 4 percent gain for Labor since January, while the
Conservatives dropped four points to garner 33 percent support.
   For the poll, 1,439 adults were interviewed on February 23 and
24.
   A Gallup poll published Friday put the Conservatives 18.5 points
behind the Labor Party _ a 20-year low in the Gallup survey.
   A poll for The Sunday Times in mid-Staffordshire, where voters
will chose a member of Parliament on March 22, showed Labor leading
the Conservatives by 50 percent to 36 percent.
   That poll was based on interviews with 862 adults between
February 28 and March 2.
   No margin of error was given for any of the polls.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0024 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 1120EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Germany-Poland Bjt   03-04 0777</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Germany-Poland, Bjt,0803</SECOND>
<HEAD>Kohl Still Hedging on Border Issue</HEAD>
<NOTE>With LaserPhoto</NOTE>
<HEAD>An AP Extra</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CAROL J. WILLIAMS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WEST BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Chancellor Helmut Kohl of West Germany is
embroiled in controversy over his refusal to categorically accept
the Polish-German border set at the end of World War II.
   It has become a political issue; recognition of the boundary
could cost Kohl votes in the December West German election. But his
failure to renounce any future attempt to regain former territories
lost in the war could delay German reunification.
   Kohl has come under attack from Poland, from the World War II
Allies and from the opposition in West Germany and even in his own
Cabinet for failing to give an unequivocal promise on the border.
   There have been demonstrations in Poland in support of Polish
demands to take part in talks on reunification.
   But the chancellor faces considerable political risk if he
declares the current border inviolable.
   Kohl's Christian Democratic Union is running only a couple of
percentage points ahead of the opposition Social Democrats in
public opinion polls.
   The CDU traditionally has enjoyed the backing of conservative
West Germans, including millions of exiles from territories now
governed by Poland and the Soviet Union.
   More than 12 million ethnic Germans were driven from Silesia and
East Prussia after the Third Reich was vanquished. The lands east
of the Oder and Neisse rivers that were German before the war are
now Polish territory, comprising about one-third of modern day
Poland.
   If Kohl agrees to give up the lands, he could alienate those
voters who provide his party's narrow lead over the Social
Democrats.
   However, Kohl's equivocating has cost the CDU support in East
Germany, where the Social Democrats are expected to win a majority
in March 18 elections.
   West German political parties have been active in the East
German campaign in an attempt to increase their voter base in
anticipation of unification.
   Kohl has to be worried that the addition of a solidly Social
Democratic East German electorate could tip the political balance
and deprive him of his dream of being the first chancellor of a
reunited Germany.
   Recognition of the current German-Polish boundary is likely to
be one of the prices of unification demanded by the World War II
Allies, who will have a say in the shape of a united Germany.
   Under pressure from Washington, where President Bush urged
clarity on the border issue, Kohl last week expressed understanding
for Poland's concern.
   His government also offered to respect the border between Poland
and a unified Germany if Poland drops any claims to war reparations
and promises to protect the rights of its German minority.
   But he has stopped short of saying Germany would never seek
recovery of those lands, saying only a united Germany could
officially recognize its borders in a peace treaty.
   ``In many speeches I have said that no one wants to connect the
unity of the Germans with moving the borders. I don't know what
more I can say,'' Kohl told East German television on Wednesday.
   He urged a declaration be made by both German parliaments to
respect the postwar boundaries, but exile groups claim Kohl still
supported them.
   ``The chancellor has not qualitatively changed his position on
this issue,'' said Horst-Egon Rehnert, spokesman for the
2-million-member Association of Exiles in Bonn. ``We have
absolutely no problem with this statement.''
   The conservatives' view that nothing has been given up has left
moderates and liberals concerned that Kohl still sees the border
question as open.
   Foreign Minister Hans-Dietrich Genscher, whose Free Democrats
are aligned with Kohl in the Bonn government, has promised that
``unification will not be accompanied by any territorial demands.''
   The chancellor's refusal to give in on the issue has won back
some of the arch-conservative vote that strayed to the
ultra-rightist Republicans party last year.
   The Republicans, led by former Waffen SS soldier Franz
Schoenhuber, polled as much as 10 percent in regional elections
last year, but have recently fallen to less than 4 percent support
nationally.
   Schoenhuber has increased pressure on Kohl by demanding eventual
unification with Silesia and East Prussia, offering a political
haven for exiles and others who still seek recovery of the lost
territories.
   Association of Exiles director Hartmut Koschyk warned that if
West Germany renounces claims to the former German lands, those
driven out four decades ago will seek compensation of $59 billion
from the Bonn government for land, homes and other assets left
behind.
   Koschyk also predicted that as many as 500,000 ethnic Germans
now living inside Poland would emigrate to West Germany if their
hopes of unification were permanently dashed.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0025 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 1124EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-TransportationPolicy Bjt   03-04 0753</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Transportation Policy, Bjt,700</SECOND>
<HEAD>National Transportation Policy To Focus on Local Government,
Private Help</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVID BRISCOE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Bush administration will unveil a national
transportation policy this week calling for more local government
and private help to improve air, ground and water transportation
into the next century.
   The long-awaited outline could lead to more toll roads, higher
airline ticket fares, increased gasoline taxes in some areas and
higher bus and mass transit fares.
   Major elements of the policy already have been disclosed by
Transportation Secretary Samuel Skinner, who says he wants to
``remove the heavy hand of government'' from transportation
industries. Formal release is set for Thursday.
   Skinner's department faces formidable problems: overcrowded
airports with about 30 percent of all flights delayed; a maritime
industry in a record slump; highway bridges in need of billions of
dollars in repairs; and an estimated $1 trillion to $3 trillion
demand for airport, railroad, highway and mass transit construction
over the next 20 years.
   Skinner's solutions focus on increasing the nation's reliance
for transport on the private sector and state and local governments
by ``stimulating competition and allowing the magic of the
marketplace to work.''
   But Skinner has said the policy also will commit the federal
government to ``fully using the funds that people have paid in user
charges for transportation, for investments in transportation.''
   The unspent $7.6 billion in the aviation trust fund, collected
from an airline ticket tax, and the $10.1 billion in the highway
trust fund, have been a sore point with transportation industry
officials who say the money is going to offset the federal deficit
rather than to help transportation.
   Some of the strategies Skinner has said will be promoted in the
new policy are increased user fees, which he does not call tax
hikes; increased private investment, including private construction
of toll roads; extending deregulation to the trucking and maritime
industries; and promotion of new technologies, including high-speed
rail systems and ``smart cars'' that are less likely to crash.
   Major points Skinner has disclosed so far from the policy
include:
   _ Promotion of a ``stronger, healthier partnership among
federal, state and local governments,'' with ``regulatory
flexibility,'' which Skinner has said could include new powers to
levy local highway tolls.
   _ A concentration of federal assistance on ``projects of
national significance,'' although the projects will not be
identified in the policy document.
   _ Preservation of existing transportation systems, including the
interstate highway system.
   _ A focus on ``moving people and goods _ not just vehicles,''
with promotion of high-occupancy vehicle lanes for crowded commuter
routes.
   _ Encouragement of technology and innovation in all modes of
transportation.
   Even before it has been released, the policy has attracted
criticism, although Skinner is widely praised for undertaking the
task.
   ``Flexibility sounds like a euphemism for `take care of
yourself,''' Sen. Frank Lautenberg, D-N.J., told Skinner as the
secretary unveiled a portion of his plan before a Senate
appropriations subcommittee last week.
   Sen. Alfonse D'Amato of New York, ranking Republican on the same
subcommittee, said he feared the new policy would not help the
continued development of large mass transit systems that take cars
off the roads and decrease pollution.
   Carole Perkins, spokeswoman for the Association of American
Railroads, said the rail industry supports Skinner's efforts and
appreciates his commitment to treat all industries evenly and get
rid of unneeded regulations.
   But she said railroad officials are looking for specifics and
that it appears the policy will deal mostly in generalities.
   Airline industry officials have said they would like to see a
separate policy outline from the Federal Aviation Administration,
since Skinner's plan will give equal importance to all means of
moving goods and people around the country.
   One problem airline officials say the policy is unlikely to
address is the need for unified noise standards at airports.
   The new transportation policy is contained in a document that
has passed the scrutiny of the White House's fiscal office, the
Office of Management and Budget.
   Skinner told a congressional committee last week that reports
that OMB would impose significant changes in the policy were not
true. He described White House changes as ``wordsmithing'' only.
   The policy is the result of 117 ``town meeting''-style hearings
held in 48 cities over the past year.
   Parts of it already are being implemented, according to
Transportation Department officials, and some of its proposals are
contained in Bush's fiscal 1991 budget, including calls for airport
passenger fees and other increases in revenue from transportation
users.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0026 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 1131EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Who'stheEnemy Bjt   03-04 0784</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Who's the Enemy, Bjt,740</SECOND>
<HEAD>Military Leaders Say America Faces Era of `Violent Peace'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT BURNS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Pentagon is wasting no time offering
answers to one of the most compelling questions raised by the
demise of the Cold War: Who is the enemy now?
   It's drug runners, terrorists, Third World despots and even oil
spills, the Pentagon brass say.
   At the same time, they haven't dismissed entirely the threat of
Soviet attack on the West, even as Moscow begins pulling its troops
out of Eastern Europe.
   The world has entered an ``era of violent peace,'' says Adm.
Carlisle Trost, the Navy's top officer. It is a time of reduced
odds that the superpowers will lob nuclear missiles at each others'
cities, but of more frequent and more lethal conflict among rival
Third World nations, he told Congress recently.
   The message from the Pentagon is that not only is the military
needed for its traditional mission, but that military might must be
tailored to battle exotic new threats, ones not previously
considered big risks to the future of Western democracy.
   It's unclear how this notion will sell on Capitol Hill.
Lawmakers are looking for ways to carve a ``peace dividend'' out of
next year's defense budget. Many see the outbreak of peace as a
chance to rein in the $300 billion-a-year military.
   Some private analysts say the Pentagon legitimately is concerned
by a proliferation of modern arms, including chemical weapons, in
the Third World. But they say military leaders also may be
overstating the immediacy of these dangers.
   A civil war in a Third World country, for example, may pose less
danger to U.S. security now than a few years ago, when Moscow may
have been more likely to exploit such openings for the advancement
of communism, said Alexis Cain, an analyst at the Defense Budget
Project, a non-partisan research group in Washington.
   Even so, instability in the Third World is emerging as one of
the U.S. military's main arguments against stripping it of manpower
and modernized weaponry.
   ``The Pentagon is more desperate for missions now'' that the
world order has shifted, Cain said.
   The military leaders, however, insist it's too soon to relax on
any front.
   ``Perhaps we are at the end of the Cold War. However, this does
not mean the end of ... military rivalry among nations,'' Trost
said. ``It may well mean increased instability ... and violence.''
   A similar view was advanced by Donald Rice, the Air Force
secretary: ``The likelihood that the U.S. military will be called
upon at some time and place to defend U.S. interests in a lethal
environment is high _ but now, more than ever, the time and place
are difficult to predict.''
   Thus the U.S. military must be prepared to act as a force for
stability in every corner of the globe, the Pentagon chiefs say.
   But many in Congress say it's not yet clear just what needs
stabilizing, or if America is best suited for such a role.
   Sen. John Warner of Virginia, the ranking Republican on the
Senate Armed Services Committee and a strong supporter of the
military, told Army Secretary Michael Stone at a hearing Feb. 27
that he'd better find a more explicit mission than ``stability.''
   ``What do you put on a recruiting poster now _ `Join the Army
and become a stability force'''? Warner said.
   Each service's civilian and uniformed chiefs have testified
before Congress in recent weeks on President Bush's plan for a
slight cut in next year's defense budget. And each has ticked off
the same list of security threats said to be replacing the
traditional worry about a Soviet attack on Western Europe or
America:
   _Third World countries with increasingly sophisticated weaponry.
Gen. Carl Vuono, the Army chief of staff, cited Libya as an
example. He said it has more battle tanks than either France or
Britain. Several other countries, including Syria, India and Iraq,
each have more battle tanks than France and Britain combined, Vuono
said.
   _Drug traffickers. Stone told Congress on Feb. 21 that the drug
trade has created ``an unprecedented and perplexing threat to our
national security.'' Compounding the problem, he said, is evidence
that terrorist groups are becoming more involved in narcotics
trafficking as a revenue source and a network for buying arms.
   _Terrorism. Gen. Colin Powell, chairman of the Joint Chiefs of
Staff, acknowledged to Congress that military force is ``only
infrequently'' the right answer to terrorism, but Stone said
terrorism was a ``primary threat'' to American citizens.
   The military says it also can make itself useful at home,
helping civilian authorities respond to disasters such as last
year's Exxon oil spill in Alaska.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0027 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 1203EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p AM-TomClancy     03-04 0307</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Tom Clancy,0316</SECOND>
<HEAD>GOP Approaches `Red October' Author to Run For Congress</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BALTIMORE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   National Republican leaders have urged
best-selling author Tom Clancy to run for Congress, but he says he
is too busy promoting the movie adapted from his book, ``The Hunt
For Red October.''
   ``It certainly deserves consideration, civic duty and all
that,'' said Clancy.
   But he's busy with interviews and promotional appearances for
the film starring Sean Connery that premiered Friday, and said he
has ``not had any time to consider'' a race against incumbent Rep.
Roy P. Dyson, D-Md.
   Clancy, 42, a Republican who lives in southern Maryland's
Calvert County, was asked to challenge the five-term Democrat
during a GOP conference two weeks ago in Princeton, N.J.
   Rep. Vin Weber, R-Minn., announced at a dinner attended by
Clancy that Republicans were urging him to enter the race. Clancy
also was approached by Ed Rollins, chief tactician for the National
Republican Congressional Committee, and other Republicans, The
(Baltimore) Sun reported.
   ``Obviously we'd love to see him run,'' said NRCC spokesman John
Roberts. ``He's articulate and popular.''
   Clancy, whose novels such as ``Red Storm Rising'' and the most
recent ``Clear and Present Danger'' focus on superpower rivalry and
sophisticated weapons systems, was in Princeton for a panel
discussion on strategic weapons.
   Maryland Republicans sound less enthusiastic about a Clancy
candidacy.
   ``We have seven very good candidates for the 1st Congressional
District,'' said Maryland GOP Chairman Joyce Lyons Terhes. ``I feel
that one of them will be the next congressman from the 1st
District.''
   Rep. Helen Delich Bentley, a Republican from Maryland's 2nd
District, noted that some of the Republican challengers in the 1st
District have been working for more than a year.
   Maryland constituents want a congressman ``available to them all
the time,'' she said. ``Is Tom Clancy ready to make that
commitment?''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0028 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 1212EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BlueMoon     03-04 0608</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Blue Moon,0625</SECOND>
<HEAD>`Cultural Landmark' Status Sought for Famous Tavern</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TIM KLASS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SEATTLE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The spirit of the Blue Moon is evident before you
enter the tavern, a hangout for artists, poets, writers and other
specimens of high life and low life for more than half a century.
   The atmosphere is special _ Northwest bohemian _ but is it
enough to designate the tavern a cultural landmark and save it from
the wrecking ball?
   That's the question facing the Landmarks Preservation Board on
Wednesday. The owner of the dingy brick tavern wants to tear it
down along with a strip joint and a house to make way for a
residential and retail complex.
   ``It's a unique tavern and it's a fun tavern, but it's not a
historic landmark,'' said Robert Hannah, president of Westlake
Capital Corp., which bought the building last September. ``All this
stuff about cultural landmark, I think, is stretching the truth.''
   Supporters and the owners of the tavern concede it is
architecturally insignificant. They focus on its past patronage.
   Blue Moon historians count writers Jack Kerouac and and Dylan
Thomas among its former customers. David Wagoner is said to have
written poetry in a back booth; Allen Ginsberg, abstract graffiti
in the restroom; and Jack Leahy, the outlines for short stories on
a wobbly table.
   In January, the Landmarks Preservation Board nominated the Blue
Moon, but late last month the agency's staff recommended that
landmark status be denied. The staff report agreed with Hannah, who
said the tavern failed to meet structural requirements, mostly
because of remodeling in the last 25 years.
   Landmark status would prevent the owners from tearing down the
tavern, and any remodeling would be subject to restrictions.
   The building housing Blue Moon was built as a garage in 1923 and
converted into one of the city's first post-Prohibition taverns 11
years later. Its location was close to the boundary of an area
around the University of Washington where sales of alcoholic
beverages were banned.
   Inside, the clacking billiard balls, raucous laughter, animated
conversation and gurgling taps drown out the bump-and-grind sounds
from Fan Tan Follies, a strip joint next door.
   It's a scene of scruffy sociability among working stiffs, bar
stool leftists, lawyers, professors and students.
   In a New Republic magazine article after her first visit,
Carolyn Kizer described the Blue Moon as ``a grubby oasis just
outside the university's one-mile Sahara. Here, the jukebox roars,
Audrey the waitress slaps down schooners of beer, and poets,
pedants, painters and other assorted wildlife make overtures to
each other.''
   Hannah said it would be too costly to build around the existing
tavern, but he'd like to incorporate the Blue Moon in the $3
million project.
   Blue Moon backers said that would be impossible.
   ``We would look at it only as a last-ditch resort,'' said Walt
Crowley, a television commentator, political activist and former
mayoral aide who helped organize the 1,500-member Forever Blue Moon
Committee.
   He bemoaned the fate of other gritty taverns reopened in newer
quarters.
   ``They had their tummies tucked and their tushes taken up to the
point that they became virtually unrecognizable,'' Crowley said.
``Their integrity has been essentially destroyed.''
   Blue Moon supporters include University of West Florida
sociology professor Ray Oldenburg, author of ``The Great Good
Place.'' He wrote that in the last 40 years, the number of taverns
in the United States has dropped from 152,000 to fewer than 50,000.
   ``What we're really talking about is an endangered species
here,'' Oldenburg said in a telephone interview. ``There is a
cultural tradition here ... an interesting, rather dingy, but worth
keeping kind of place.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0029 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 1226EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Korea-Tunnel     03-04 0421</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Korea-Tunnel,0435</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mine Explodes as Soldiers Search Border Tunnel</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SEOUL, South Korea (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A mine exploded Sunday while soldiers
were exploring a tunnel allegedly dug under the border by North
Korea, killing a sentry dog but causing no other casualties,
officials said.
   The mine, believed to be a booby trap, exploded after soldiers
sent the dog ahead and had groped their way about 700 yards north
through the tunnel, Defense Ministry officials said.
   The army temporarily halted the search, which began Saturday
after engineers drilled into the newly discovered tunnel in the
Demilitarized Zone. It was the fourth underground passageway found
in the DMZ and military officials said they thought there were
about 20 more.
   North Korea has denied digging any tunnels.
   Ministry officials said they believed Communist North Korea
might have installed the booby trap to block the search operation.
   The tunnel was first detected in December in a remote
mountainous region, about 100 miles northeast of Seoul. South
Korean officials said Sunday it was believed to have been dug in
the 1980s, unlike three other tunnels discovered in 1974, 1975 and
1978.
   A government statement said the tunnel indicates North Korea's
strategy ``has been geared to winning a quick victory'' through a
surprise attack.
   ``North Korea intends to break through our front line on the
strength of their superior mobility and fire power, advance
speedily behind our forward areas and occupy Seoul quickly,'' it
said.
   The statement said tunnels were an ``integral component of its
(North Korea's) military strategy for quick action and quick
victory'' and were intended to ``quickly neutralize our major
front-line units.''
   The two Koreas are separated by the 2.5-mile-wide and
155-mile-long DMZ. The border area on both both sides is heavily
fortified by fences, concrete bunkers, mine fields and hundreds of
thousands of heavily armed troops.
   Defense Minister Lee Sang-hoon said Saturday that by analyzing
satellite pictures and other information, South Korea knows of at
least 26 underground ``axis lines'' beneath the DMZ. He said they
are believed to be tunnels.
   Lee said North Korea bought about 30 excavators with
noise-repressing equipment from Sweden after construction noises
led to the discovery of the third tunnel in 1978.
   The Korean peninsula was divided into the Communist North and
capitalist South in 1945 after World War II. No peace treaty was
signed at the end of the three-year Korean War, only an armistice,
and the two nations still are technically at war.
   They remain bitter enemies and no unauthorized communication is
allowed between their citizens.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0030 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 1236EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-India-Kashmir     03-04 0524</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-India-Kashmir,0541</SECOND>
<HEAD>Kashmir Government Plans Elections in Bid to Halt Uprising</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DILIP GANGULY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SRINAGAR, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The government of Jammu-Kashmir state
offered Sunday to hold elections within six months in a bid to halt
a Moslem uprising, and security forces launched new raids on
suspected militant hideouts.
   ``From our side, we are willing to go for a democratic process
to decide who should rule the state,'' Gov. Jagmohan said in an
interview.
   ``But the democratic process now depends on those who are
terrorizing people,'' he said, referring to the Moslem militants
who demand independence from predominantly Hindu India.
   The militants boycotted November's national parliamentary
elections and forced residents in Kashmir _ part of Jammu-Kashmir
state _ to stay away from the polls.
   But Jagmohan, the top administrator of the state, said he had
information that various militant groups were considering giving up
their arms and adopting the democratic process to power. Jagmohan,
a Hindu, uses one name.
   Jagmohan's statement could not immediately be reconciled with
previous statements by militant groups who have rejected everything
Indian in their quest for a separate nation.
   The last state elections, held in 1987, were widely believed to
have been rigged by the governing National Conference party and its
ally, the Congress Party of former Prime Minister Rajiv Gandhi.
   Gandhi's successor, Prime Minister V.P. Singh, sacked the state
government in January, three years before its term was to expire,
and brought it under tighter federal control through the governor's
rule.
   At least 163 people have been killed in Kashmir since the latest
round of secessionist violence flared up on Jan. 20 following a
government crackdown on escalating protests, bombings and attacks
on state officials.
   ``The government is following an iron fist in a velvet glove
policy in dealing with the militants,'' said an intelligence
officer who is one of the five members of a policy-making team on
Kashmir. He spoke on condition of anonymity.
   On Sunday, paramilitary police and soldiers raided homes of
separatist sympathizers and arrested 86 people in Srinagar, the
summer capital of Jammu-Kashmir, said state officials who cannot be
identified under briefing rules.
   State police sources, speaking on condition of anonymity, said
at least 150 people had been detained for interrogation since
Friday.
   Srinagar, a city of 1 million people and the focus of the
militant movement, remained under curfew for the third straight
day. Troops patrolled the streets with orders to shoot curfew
violators on sight.
   The curfew was reimposed in Kashmir early Friday after 49 people
were killed by security troops firing on Moslem pro-independence
demonstrators.
   The secession movement has alternately simmered and flared since
1948-49 when the Moslem-dominated state of Jammu-Kashmir, faced
with accesion to India or Pakistan, chose India.
   India and Pakistan were then one year old, having been
partitioned along religious lines at the end of the British
colonial rule on Aug. 14-15, 1947.
   Pakistan, which claims Jammu-Kashmir, has twice gone to war with
India, in 1948 and 1965.
   Sixty-four percent of the state's 6 million people are Moslems.
Nationwide, Moslems make up 12 percent of India's 880 million
population. Hindus make up 82 percent.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0031 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 1243EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-DraculaRing     03-04 0275</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Dracula Ring,0282</SECOND>
<HEAD>Art Thieves Took Ring Believed To Have Belonged to Dracula's
Family</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A $4 million art theft netted a ring that its
owner says belonged to the family of Vlad the Impaler, the Eastern
European prince who inspired the vampire legend of Count Dracula,
Newsday reported.
   Two men beat up and handcuffed artist-historian Vlaicu Ionescu,
67, in his apartment in Queens, and took his collection of
paintings. They also took documentation on the paintings, leading
police to believe the robbery's masterminds knew what they were
doing, Newsday reported Sunday.
   Ionescu, who fled his native Romania more than 20 years ago,
said the most valuable work stolen in the August robbery was ``The
Barbadori Holy Family with St. John and St. Elizabeth,'' a 1516
painting by Andrea del Sarto worth about $3 million.
   Also stolen were three signet rings that Ionescu said he
acquired in Romania in the 1950s, Newsday said.
   Ionescu believes the rings belonged to three princes from the
14th and 15th centuries and that one, emblazoned with a raven,
belonged to Vlad Dracul of Wallachia, father of Vlad the Impaler.
Wallachia is now part of Romania.
   Vlad the Impaler was known for impaling, boiling alive and
mutilating enemies.
   ``Count Dracula's ring in Queens!'' said the lead investigator,
Detective Richard Byrnes. ``That's like saying `We found the true
cross up on Forest Hills.'''
   The police has contacted art experts worldwide, the FBI and
Interpol. ``We have leads, but no suspects,'' Byrnes said.
   Ionescu told Newsday he wasn't insured. The communist government
of Romania once confiscated art from him, but he thought his
collection would be safe here.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0032 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 1347EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-NantucketGhosts Bjt   03-04 0679</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Nantucket Ghosts, Bjt,0698</SECOND>
<HEAD>Island Abounds With Ghost Stories</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TONY ROGERS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NANTUCKET, Mass. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Maybe it's the bleak setting of
windswept beaches, brooding moors and gray, weatherbeaten houses.
Perhaps it's all the ships lost off the coast, carrying terrified
souls into the stormy Atlantic.
   Whatever the reason, there are ghosts on Nantucket. Just ask the
people with stories to tell.
   ``One person I knew thought it had something to do with the
moisture,'' says Blue Balliett, who compiled 23 ghost sightings
from this tiny island off the coast of Cape Cod and put them into a
book. ``I don't know what it is, but there are a lot of ghosts on
Nantucket.''
   One story tells of a poltergeist residing in a house built in
1808 and once owned, ominously enough, by a man named William
Coffin. Coffin, a prominent wig shop owner, died embittered after
being accused of stealing $21,000 from the Nantucket bank in 1795.
   Twenty-one years after the theft, a convict in a New York state
prison confessed to the crime, but years of accusations and
litigation had left Coffin a broken man. He even sued his distant
cousin, Micajah Coffin, over the matter, and he later wrote that he
had been victimized by ``chicanery,'' ``phrenzy'' and ``moon-struck
madness.''
   Peter Benchley, author of the book ``Jaws,'' spent a summer in
the Coffin house in the late 1960s. He told Balliett that one
afternoon he woke from a nap to see a fire burning in the fireplace.
   A longhaired old man, dressed in 18th-century clothing, was
slowly rocking in a rocking chair in front of the fire. A moment
later, the man and the fire had disappeared, and the rocking chair
lay still.
   Out on the island's windswept eastern coast, the normally
levelheaded Coast Guard officers keeping watch over the
140-year-old Sankaty lighthouse say a spirit haunts their nearby
dormitory.
   Petty Officer Doug Clark says the ghost scatters pots and pans
over the kitchen floor, opens locked doors and spooks the dorm dog,
Jessie.
   ``She'll pop her head up suddenly and look around, and there's
nothing there,'' Clark says. ``She gets on edge, and she won't go
near where the ghost might be.''
   But the hardy Coast Guard men don't put up with too many ghostly
gags.
   ``We'll hear it making loud thumps at night. We just yell,
`knock it off,' and it does.''
   Sometimes, a spirit reluctant to surrender its home to living
residents will get too close for comfort.
   Joanne Shaw, a Nantucket resident since 1972, recalls when she
and her family lived in a 19th-century farmhouse in the center of
the island that was haunted by the ghost of a little girl they
called Emily.
   ``She came down the stairs one day, right in front of me,'' Shaw
says. ``She was about 10 years, with a cloak covering her face. I
watched her for a minute, and then when I started getting scared
she disappeared.''
   The girl stayed mostly in a third-floor bedroom in the house.
She appeared to Shaw and her son, Jimmy, at various times for about
two years, and even if she wasn't visible, the floorboards creaked
as she passed.
   Then came the day Shaw was taking a nap and felt the weight of
someone getting into the bed next to her. Shaw was frozen with fear
for a moment, then jumped out of bed and screamed, ``Get out of
here!'' The ghost never returned.
   The hauntings sometimes jinx real estate deals on the island,
though agents are loath to admit it.
   ``A lot of people won't even look at a house with a reputation
for being haunted,'' said agent Gary Winn.
   ``But we don't have any haunted listings at the moment,'' he
added.
   In June, Balliett's second tome of Nantucket ghost stories will
be published, this time with even more accounts. She didn't intend
to write another such volume.
   ``But all these people who saw the first book came out of the
woodwork,'' Balliett says. ``On Nantucket, almost everyone has a
ghost story to tell.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0033 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 1358EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-ForeignAid Bjt   03-04 0918</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Foreign Aid, Bjt,850</SECOND>
<HEAD>America's Response to a New World: Dollars or Discourse?</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JIM DRINKARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Congress wants to pump up President Bush's
foreign aid budget by as much as $2 billion and shift priorities to
reward new democracies from Nicaragua to Czechoslovakia.
   That move likely will be accompanied by more harsh rhetoric from
majority Democrats about the administration's timidity in seizing
historic opportunities that the United States has sought for more
than four decades in Eastern Europe.
   ``We are facing a radically different world, but the foreign aid
request presented by the administration is changed almost not at
all,'' said Rep. David Obey, D-Wis., chairman of the House
Appropriations foreign aid subcommittee.
   ``We have a president who's unwilling to invest in things he
rhetorically says are important,'' added Rep. Matthew McHugh, D-N.Y.
   The House Foreign Affairs Committee last week formally asked
House budget writers to provide an additional $2 billion for
overseas accounts in the year that begins Oct. 1, bringing spending
authority to $22.8 billion.
   That budget category includes everything from bilateral military
and economic aid to dozens of friendly countries, to payments to
the United Nations and other international organizations, to
operations of the State Department and the Voice of America.
   The administration has proposed $300 million for Eastern Europe
in fiscal 1991, but it has offered few details and it remains
unclear whether the money represents an increase from current
levels or whether it simply continues a three-year program of aide
to Poland and Hungary begun last year.
   The Foreign Affairs Committee estimates the Bush budget would
actually fall $291 million short of maintaining current foreign aid
programs. So they propose additional money to go for economic aide
to encourage the growing of alternative crops in
narcotics-producing countries; additional money for aide to Eastern
Europe, including Peace Corps development assistance; and increased
assistance to Africa, the Eastern Caribbean and Central American
democracies such as Nicaragua.
   Committee Chairman Dante Fascell, D-Fla., wrote that the
additional money is ``the essential minimum required to `win the
peace' for democracy and free markets around the world.''
   Others are calling for creating of a new fund for emerging
democracies, outside the normal foreign aid budget, that could meet
needs of newly eligible recipients who measure up to certain tests
for political, economic and human rights reform.
   ``We've got a new situation,'' said Sen. Sam Nunn, D-Ga.,
chairman of the Senate Armed Services Committee. ``This is what
we've been working for since the days of Harry Truman. I think
we've got to have some new thinking about what we do.''
   Because of budget restraints and Bush's no-new-taxes stance,
there is no new money to spend on aid or anything else. Any
increase in aid must come from cuts in another part of the budget,
and most aid proponents are eyeing Pentagon spending.
   Secretary of State James A. Baker III, in testimony on Capitol
Hill last week, indicated he sees little likelihood of a
substantial increase in the aid budget and suggested instead
cutting aid across the board to current recipients to free up some
new cash.
   But despite the unpopularity of aid among U.S. voters, members
of Congress are betting that the emergence of democratic
governments in formerly totalitarian states will be a politically
safe basis on which to send more money overseas.
   ``Most of our constituents want us to send no money called
`foreign aid' overseas,'' said Rep. Jerry Lewis, R-Calif. But he
added that ``as we go into a build-down within the military, that's
the time to increase our responsibility in foreign affairs.''
   Added Rep. Silvio Conte, R-Mass.: ``We need more resources right
now to take advantage of this unprecedented, perhaps temporary,
opportunity to win the Cold War. ... We will pay dearly for
inaction.''
   Aid proponents also believe that if defense spending for next
year is cut by as much as $10 billion, with most of the savings
devoted to new domestic programs and deficit reduction, public
antipathy to a small foreign aid increase will be reduced.
   The idea of increasing foreign aid also has some powerful
support from the Israeli lobby, which is seeking to avoid cuts in
its own aid by finding money elsewhere to meet the new demands.
   As the top aid recipient in the world _ $3 billion of the total
$10 billion in U.S. bilateral aid _ Israel stands above the pack
when the foreign aid budget gets tight and automatically becomes a
target for cuts.
   In addition to more money, many lawmakers also are calling for a
fundamental rewrite of the programs which send military, economic,
development and food aid around the world. Policies which have for
years been based on countering the communist threat need to be
rebuilt on a new rationale, they say.
   ``We are all still very anti-communist, it's just hard to find a
communist to be against,'' said Rep. Mickey Edwards, D-Okla. ``We
should create an Albanian theme park so people can come see what
communism was all about.''
   Added Edwards: ``We are seeing the world remade in America's
image. We cannot be timid. We have to move very boldly ... to
ensure (the new democracies) do not slip back.''
   ``I think we should take a complete new look,'' said Sen.
Patrick Leahy, D-Vt., chairman of the Senate Appropriations foreign
aid panel. Leahy said U.S. policy goals have grown poorly defined,
and he challenged Bush to show leadership first in setting new
goals, then in paying for them.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0034 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 1408EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Romania     03-04 0488</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania,0503</SECOND>
<HEAD>Lenin Survives Second Day of Demolition Attempts</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto BUC2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAN PETREANU</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUCHAREST, Romania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Crews with jackhammers and blowtorches
tried for a second consecutive day Sunday to bring down Bucharest's
imposing statue of V.I. Lenin, but by nightfall he was still
standing firm.
   The crews succeeded in eliminating most of the concrete
foundation that links the 25-foot, 7-ton bronze statue to its
marble base.
   But engineers on the site said the statue would probably only
come down Monday morning, when there would be enough light to do it
safely.
   About 1,000 people watched the workers transfixed, eagerly
awaiting the banishment of the statue _ a symbol of the 45 years of
Communist rule that ended in December with the ouster of dictator
Nicolae Ceausescu by a popular revolt. Ceausescu was executed
together with his wife, Elena, on Christmas Day after a summary
trial.
   The ruling Provisional Council of National Unity, which acts as
a mini-parliament until national elections scheduled for May 20,
voted Friday night to remove the statue from in front of the
massive, Stalinist-style state publishing house in the recently
renamed Free Press Square.
   Work began early Saturday, but the work crews were surprised to
discover that the statue was implanted deep in its foundation by
thick bronze rods. A wrecking ball failed to move the figure.
   A poster hanging on the motor of one of the cranes being used in
the demolition work displayed the Communist slogan ``March onward,
Comrades,'' with the addition: ``Don't come back, and take the
Securitate with you,'' a reference to Ceausescu's hated secret
police.
   The pink marble base of the statue was covered with blue
graffiti reading ``Down with the statue.''
   The black statue depicts Lenin holding his cap and the lapel of
his overcoat and staring into the distance down a broad avenue
toward Bucharest's Arch of Triumph.
   Authorities said Saturday they had not yet decided what they
would do with the statue.
   About a half-mile to the south in Victory Square, meanwhile,
several hundred people demonstrated against the interim government.
   They were kept well away from the provisional government
building, which was ransacked by demonstrators two weeks ago.
   The military, which did not intervene then, brought out extra
troops to surround the building Sunday and blocked off its entrance
with 15 armored personnel carriers.
   The demonstrators chanted ``Down with Communists!'' ``We want
true liberty!'' and ``We want free TV!''
   Government critics are wary of the Communist past of interim
President Ion Iliescu and other former Communists who ran afoul of
Ceausescu. Critics also complain about the government's allegedly
heavy-handed control of television.
   Gheorghe Higiu, 45, said that the demonstrators had ``as their
first priority supporting the peasants, who form the base of this
country.''
   Higiu said that the demonstrators were demanding faster
privatization of state-owned land, ``which should be distributed
free to each peasant according to his ability to work.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0035 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 1416EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gorbachev'sHome     03-04 0625</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gorbachev's Home,0641</SECOND>
<HEAD>After Voting, Gorbachev Strolls Down Moscow Street _ to His Home?</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Soviet-Elections, Bjt</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto MOSB12</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ANN IMSE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Where does Mikhail S. Gorbachev live?
   At No. 10 Kosygin Street, a pale-yellow building perched on the
highest bank of the Moscow River, with a magnificent view of the
city and the Kremlin _ if you believe Sunday's unusual performance,
when the Soviet president walked back to this heavily guarded
compounded after voting.
   Moscow's filthy air is fresher in this industry-free
neighborhood, which enjoys a luxurious forest surrounding the
Stalinesque wedding-cake skyscraper housing Moscow State University.
   From the street, the yellow edifice appears to be just an
unusually fine apartment building with a swingset on the back lawn.
Next door is the dull gray building that was the home of the late
Alexei Kosygin when he was Soviet premier in the 1960s and 1970s,
and for whom the street is named.
   But from the river below, bay windows and balconies bespeak a
rich residence designed to take private advantage of a stupendous
site.
   Neighbors who watched it being built several years ago say the
five-floor building extends another five stories into the bedrock
of the Lenin Hills. A few hundred yards away, a metro line zips
straight to the Kremlin wall.
   The Pentagon claims the Lenin Hills are laced with civil defense
tunnels, and rumors have long circulated in Moscow that Soviet
leaders have a private underground train line from the Kremlin to
bunkers in this virtual cliff overlooking the capital.
   The unmistakable ZIL limousines used by a handful of top Soviet
leaders only occasionally appear at the blockhouse guarding No. 10
Kosygin Street.
   ``If Gorbachev lives here, he comes and goes underground,'' said
a Westerner who lives in the neighborhood.
   Gorbachev's true home has always been a source of speculation.
The four-ZIL convoy widely assumed to carry the Soviet leader
routinely races down Kutuzovsky Prospect and Rublovskoye Shosse,
far and away the best-maintained roads in a capital whose streets
seem to have more holes than asphalt.
   Police clear traffic from the middle, so-called ``ZIL lane''
every morning and evening to let the limousines sail by.
   Locals say that just past Moscow's outer ring road, they turn
right down an unmarked road visibly guarded by a lone policeman. At
night, the route is brightly lit, standing out in a city short of
street lights and generally shrouded in gloom.
   Gorbachev is widely believed to spend most evenings at a dacha,
or country home, in a well-guarded compound down that road. Like
many areas on the outskirts of Moscow, foreigners are barred from
setting foot in it.
   During the June 1988 summit, President Reagan and his wife,
Nancy, dined with the Gorbachevs at the dacha.
   Gorbachev's rare stroll down a Moscow street Sunday added new
clues, or red herrings, to his trail. The house at 10 Kosygin
Street is variously said to be a guest house or one of Gorbachev's
residences.
   After voting at the Institute of Chemical Physics at No. 4
Kosygin Street, he stopped to speak with passers-by and reporters
waiting for him, both inside and outside the gates of the heavily
wooded grounds of the institute. Then he walked briskly several
hundred yards down the boulevard.
   Hefty security men roughly halted correspondents far from the
security gates, where the small crowd surrounding the leader
shuffled positions and split up, obscuring the whereabouts of
Gorbachev, his wife, Raisa, daughter Irina, her husband, Igor, and
their two children. Several drove away in two limousines parked
outside, and moments later a third ZIL departed from inside the
compound.
   If Gorbachev had just left his city residence, no one could be
sure which long, black vehicle carried him.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0036 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 1429EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Gephardt-Japan     03-04 0513</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gephardt-Japan,480</SECOND>
<HEAD>Gephardt Sees Nothing Concrete in Bush-Kaifu Trade Talks</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MATT YANCEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   House Majority Leader Richard Gephardt
expressed disappointment Sunday that President Bush's weekend
summit with Japanese Prime Minister Toshiki Kaifu produced no
specifics on improving the two countries' deteriorating trade
relationship.
   But Gephardt, D-Mo., said Congress will wait until summer to see
if mutual pledges by Bush and Kaifu to work toward resolving the
disputes produce results before lawmakers move to impose trade
sanctions against Japan.
   ``Nothing has changed,'' Gephardt said of the two-day California
summit, which was hastily called by Bush after trade talks between
the two countries stalled last month and the annual U.S. trade
deficit with Japan fell by only $2.8 billion to $49 billion in 1989.
   Gephardt, who has been a vocal advocate of strong retaliatory
measures against Japan, said he heard no concrete proposals from
Bush and Kaifu when they met with reporters Saturday in Rancho
Mirage, Calif.
   ``How many of these press conferences have we seen over the past
10 years?'' Gephardt said on NBC-TV's ``Meet the Press'' show.
``What you never hear is a specific goal, an action that both sides
are going to take to deal with the problem.''
   Kaifu said after the summit he would ``firmly tackle'' the
product standards, building codes and other structural impediments
that effectively deny U.S. products access to the Japanese market.
   Bush wished him ``great success.'' But asked if more trade talks
between now and June could produce enough movement by the Japanese
to avoid U.S. retaliation, Bush said, ``I hope so, but I don't
know.''
   Commerce Secretary Robert Mosbacher, in a separate interview
Sunday, said both leaders left the summit realizing there are
serious problems on both sides. Japan, he said, now has top
government officials focusing on increasing their country's imports.
   ``Now at the end of the year, if there aren't some major changes
in that, we'll know it was more rhetoric,'' Mosbacher said on
ABC-TV's ``This Week With David Brinkley'' program. ``I believe
they will.''
   Gephardt said Congress will wait until after talks are concluded
on Japanese barriers to U.S. supercomputers, satellites and forest
products before deciding whether to impose new tariffs on Japanese
exports. As part of the 1988 Trade Act, Congress imposed a June 16,
1990, deadline on those talks.
   A summer deadline also exists on Japanese imports of U.S.
semiconductors.
   ``They want to see what actions the Japanese will actually take
as opposed to more promises and then they'll make up their mind as
to what should be done next,'' Gephardt said of his colleagues in
Congress.
   But he added that the overall trade relationship between the two
countries will not improve significantly until the United States
takes a firmer line and establishes targets for reducing the
imbalance.
   ``I would submit to you the Japanese politicians are not able,
in present circumstances, to make the changes in their own society
that many of them know need to be made unless we are willing to
take definitive action to help them do that,'' Gephardt said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0037 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 1439EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-ArtsyInvites 1stLd-Writethru a0691 03-04 0670</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Artsy Invites, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0691,620</SECOND>
<HEAD>Getting on the `A' List for National Gallery Openings</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: SUBS 15th graf, bgng: Since then, to CORRECT Odalique to
Odalisque</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT M. ANDREWS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   If an engraved summons to a White House state
dinner is the ultimate badge of social power, an invitation to a
preview breakfast at the National Gallery of Art is the elegant
passport to a morning spent contemplating the power of the spirit.
   About 500 journalists on the gallery's mailing list are
accustomed to opening envelopes containing glossy reproductions of
a Winslow Homer watercolor, a Frans Hals portrait or the shimmering
pastels of an Henri Matisse oil painting.
   These coveted invitations, surely among the most beautiful ever
dropped into a Washington mailbox, are sent to the reporters and
art critics who write regularly about the dozen or more major
exhibitions that the National Gallery mounts each year.
   Some recipients consider the invitations themselves to be works
of art, worthy of gracing the desks, walls and bulletin boards of
newsrooms around the city.
   No less admired are the buffet breakfasts served in the
Refectory, the seventh-floor penthouse suite of the gallery's
modernistic East Building, where the culinary theme is taken from
the artist of the day.
   At 9 o'clock Tuesday morning, for instance, about 60 journalists
will sit down to a hearty breakfast with a Dutch flavor, a salute
to the gallery's March 11 opening of an exhibition of 97 landscape
prints and drawings by Rembrandt.
   The menu will include pannekoeken, or Dutch pancakes, filled
with spiced apples and covered with powdered sugar and fresh
whipped cream. There will be boiled sweet ham, a platter of aged
Gouda, Edam and Memolette cheeses and small raisin buns called
krantenbollen, served with butter and blackberry preserves.
   If he follows the usual format, gallery director J. Carter Brown
will introduce the curators over coffee and discuss the new show
with his customary wit, good humor and boyish enthusiasm. Then the
crowd will adjourn to the Rembrandt gallery for an unhurried
preview led by experts on the 17th Dutch master's work.
   ``I can't imagine a more civilized way to begin the day,'' said
one press breakfast regular.
   ``We offer culture, good food and good conversation,'' says
gallery spokeswoman Deborah Ziska.
   The invitations are the work of Chris Vogel, production manager
of the gallery's editorial office, and graphics designer Phyllis
Hecht, based on ideas conceived by exhibition curators and public
information specialists.
   Ms. Ziska said it takes six weeks of consultations involving as
many as 10 gallery officials _ including Brown _ before the
invitations are printed and ready for mailing to a nationwide
preview list of 2,500 names, including the local breakfast group.
   ``We like to do something different that will catch people's
eyes,'' said Vogel, who started using artistic images on the
gallery's invitations in 1984.
   That year, for an exhibition of folding screens by Western
artists, Vogel used a panoramic black-and-white photograph by Ansel
Adams for the cover of an invitation in the shape of a miniature
folding screen.
   Since then, he and Ms. Hecht have collaborated to produce about
100 such invitations, with images ranging from Renoir's eye-popping
``Odalisque'' _ a voluptuous harem beauty _ to an amusing
photograph of a weather vane fish waving an American flag, from the
Shelburne folk art museum in Vermont.
   There was no dispute over the choice of an image for invitations
to an exhibition of publisher Walter Annenberg's collection of
impressionist and post-impressionist masterpieces, which is
scheduled to open here May 6.
   That image will be the expected star of the show, Pablo
Picasso's 1905 self-portrait titled ``Au Lapin Agile.'' Annenberg
bought the picture in November, after the exhibition opened in
Philadelphia last summer, for $40.7 million _ the third most
expensive artwork ever sold at auction.
   Vogel is proud of his invitations but doesn't take his work
home. The wall of his house, he said, are reserved for the drawings
of his 4-year-old son, Philip.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0038 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 1501EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People     03-04 0843</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People,0875</SECOND>
<HEAD>People in the News</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY44</HEAD>
<DATELINE>GAINESVILLE, Ga. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Terry O'Kelley, who at age 15 promised
his dying mother that he would keep his six younger brothers
together, said a television movie of his four-year struggle was
``good but sad.''
   ``A Son's Promise,'' will air on ABC on Monday. The movie stars
Rick Schroder as O'Kelley.
   ``It made me sad, showing all the things that had happened in my
life at one time,'' O'Kelley said Saturday. ``I feel they did a
good job.''
   After their mother's death, the boys lived together on their
grandfather's farm until he died. The boys' story captured national
attention, with an outpouring of donations and the creation of a
trust fund.
   In December 1986, a juvenile court judge awarded O'Kelley, now
22, custody of the four oldest brothers: Tommy, now 20; Charles,
19; David, 18; and Jess, 17. The two youngest, Michael and Jason,
remain in foster care.
   O'Kelley is now married and has a son. He lives in a house
adjacent to the farm. Three of his brothers live in a house
constructed on the farm by volunteers after fire destroyed their
mobile home.
   O'Kelley said he and his brothers benefited from the generosity
of ``people that helped us all over the world,'' as well as
proceeds from the movie.
   ``We didn't get rich or anything, but we have the opportunity to
get an education, put a down payment on a first home or anything we
want,'' he said. ``They got us a good start.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>Eds: A version of the following item moved on sports wires.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>FARMINGTON, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Sixteen tennis enthusiasts had a
formidable _ and expensive _ oppponent over the weekend.
   Each paid $1,000 for the privilege of playing Ivan Lendl, the
No. 1 ranked player in the world. Proceeds went to the Fidelco
Guide Dog Foundation of Bloomfield, Conn., which trains dogs for
the blind.
   Letty Landry of West Hartford said she expected to face the
Lendl she'd seen on television _ an Iceman whose steely on-court
style has chilled opponents. But the Lendl she met Saturday at the
Farmington Farms Racquet Club was charming and offered friendly
tips, perhaps because playing for charity is recreation for Lendl,
not work.
   ``When you see me on TV, I am in my office,'' he said. ``I am
concentrating on my job.''
   Saturday's event netted more than $17,000 for Fidelco, said
Julie Augeri, spokeswoman for the foundation. About 50 spectators
paid $75 apiece to watch the matches.
   The Czechoslovakian-born tennis champ has four dogs at his house
in Greenwich, Conn. Lendl said that he plans to breed German
shepherds and will offer some to Fidelco, which trained 37 pairs of
dogs and owners last year.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>DEFUNIAK SPRINGS, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   ``Pappy'' Neal McCormick has
played steel guitar for some of the top names in country music,
including Ray Price, Tex Ritter, Gene Autry, Kitty Wells, Ernest
Tubb and Johnny Cash.
   But one performer who stood out among the rest was the
16-year-old boy who came down from Montgomery, Ala., looking for a
job with McCormick's band after hearing his Pensacola radio show
more than 50 years ago.
   ``His rhythm weren't no good,'' McCormick drawled during a
recent interview at his home near this Florida Panhandle town.
   But he hired the youngster because ``I thought he was a good
singer.''
   So did most country fans, and Hank Williams became a legend
before his career was cut short. Williams died at 29 on Jan. 1,
1953, from a combination of alcohol and a prescription drug he was
taking for back pain.
   At age 80, McCormick still twangs the steel guitar and his
brother, Earl, 83, plays fiddle every Friday and Saturday night.
McCormick was picked to headline a special performance Sunday in
Pensacola to pay homage to Williams.
   McCormick disputes the image of Williams as a rowdy drunkard.
   ``Ol' Hank weren't even a guy like people thought he was,''
McCormick said. ``He was a good-hearted ol' boy as you would ever
come around.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>SEATTLE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Shirley MacLaine hurt her knee while while
dancing the cancan and missed four weekend performances.
   Dan Bean, president of Entertainment Consultants, said the
injury occurred Friday night about 20 minutes before the end of the
revue,``Out There Tonight.''
   MacLaine finished her performance at the Paramount Theater, but
four shows Saturday and Sunday were canceled.

</TEXT>
<DATELINE>BANGKOK, Thailand (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Princess Chulabhorn left Sunday for a
45-day trip to the United States and Canada to meet prominent
scientists and observe scientific activities, the Royal Household
Bureau said.
   An official of the bureau said the princess will attend ``The
Globe 90 Conference'' on the environment later this month in
Vancouver, British Columbia. The princess also will give lectures
in Canada.
   Princess Chulabhorn, 33, has a doctorate in chemistry and is
known for her scientific research. Last year, she was appointed by
the World Health Organization as one of its ``goodwill
ambassadors.''
   She is the youngest of the four children of constitutional
monarch King Bhumipol and Queen Sirikit.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0039 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 1602EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Quayle     03-04 0562</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Quayle,530</SECOND>
<HEAD>Quayle Praises `New Ortega'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOAN MOWER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Vice President Dan Quayle said Sunday a ``new
Daniel Ortega'' appears committed to democracy in Nicaragua but
predicted U.S.-backed contras there will not disband until they
feel more secure.
   Quayle praised the ousted Sandinista leader as being ``very
conciliatory'' after Ortega promised on CBS-TV's ``Face the
Nation'' show to turn over the reigns of Nicaragua's government on
April 25 and to respect its constitution.
   ``I thought it was on target, and perhaps it appears that we do
have a new Daniel Ortega that is truly committed to democracy,''
said Quayle, who was interviewed on the same show immediately after
Ortega.
   He also had praise for former Democratic President Jimmy Carter,
who monitored the Nicaraguan election, as being ``helpful in trying
to promote democracy.''
   Ortega was soundly defeated by President-elect Violeta Barrios
de Chamorro in elections on Feb. 25. He said Sunday he expects her
to establish the country's new government.
   ``The constitution is the one that orders me to turn over the
power to the government that is elected in the elections,'' Ortega
said. The ``new administration and the new president will designate
the corresponding authorities.''
   Asked if he would hand over control of Nicaragua's armed forces
and police, Ortega said: ``I don't have an army here, I don't have
a police force here.''
   Both Chamorro and Ortega have called for the demobilization of
the Contra rebels, many of whom remain at camps in Honduras. The
Contras have said they would remain intact until after Chamorro's
inauguration in April.
   Quayle said the key to demobilizing the 12,000 Contras is a
peaceful transition. While some Contras already have laid down
their weapons and returned to Nicaragua, they have done so on a
voluntary basis, he said.
   ``... When democracy is there, and it appears that it's going to
be, and when the Contras feel secure, they will demobilize,'' he
said. ``That's part of the peace plan.''
   The focus, he said, should be on ``putting the principles of
democracy to work'' rather than demobilizing the Contras.
   A group of Nicaraguans is expected to be in Washington Monday to
ask the Bush administration for $300 million in aid.
   Asked what kind of economic assistance the administration is
considering, Quayle would say only, ``We will meet the demands of
whatever is necessary.''
   On other issues, Quayle:
   _ Said there are ``no negotiations on a quid pro quo basis with
Iran'' for the release of U.S. hostages held in Lebanon by
pro-Iranian Shiite Moslems. He also refused to ``give any little
nuance or any little credibility'' to reports the Bush
administration is somehow engaged in talks to free the hostages.
   _ Called the Bush administration's policy on China a
``disappointment'' in that China ``continues to be a holdout of
political reform.''
   _ Saw no inconsistency in his decision to campaign for
Republican Party candidates who believe in the right to have an
abortion. Although the Bush administration supports a
constitutional amendment banning abortion, Quayle said, ``The
REpublican Party is willing to be open on the issue.''
   _ Said he wished his approval ratings were higher, but he's
given no thought to stepping down as Bush's running mate in 1992 if
his standing doesn't improve at the polls. ``You're way down the
road _ the president makes decisions like that, not me.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0040 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 1611EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Nicaragua     03-04 0542</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Nicaragua,0561</SECOND>
<HEAD>Chomorro's Coalition Claims Fraud Cost It One Legislative Seat</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DORALISA PILARTE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MANAGUA, Nicaragua (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The coalition that defeated the ruling
Sandinistas in last month's general election has charged that vote
fraud cost it one seat in the legislature, a newspaper reported
Sunday.
   The newspaper also said that government helicopters fired
rockets Saturday at the home of a coalition supporter, injuring two
of his children.
   But the government denied that helicopters caused the blast, and
another newspaper said it was caused by a grenade thrown by an
unidentified assailant.
   The charge of election fraud and the report of a helicopter
attack appeared in separate articles in La Prensa, the daily
newspaper owned by the family of President-elect Violeta Barrios de
Chamorro.
   Since Mrs. Chamorro and her United National Opposition coalition
soundly defeated the leftist Sandinistas in the Feb. 25 election,
La Prensa has been considered an unofficial voice of the coalition.
It has strong ties to the top echelons of the new government, which
is to be inaugurated April 25.
   There has been little serious violence in Nicaragua since the
election, but after years of civil war some citizens wonder whether
the transition to a new government and the disbanding of the Contra
rebels will occur peacefully.
   Nicaraguan rebels said Sunday they have taken steps toward
demobilization.
   In a statement in Honduras, where the Contras have camps, rebels
said they are in contact with UNO leaders and that the speed of the
demobilization will depend on guarantees of safety for those
returning to Nicaragua.
   Luis Sanchez, a United National Opposition spokesman, said the
coalition will challenge the results of the latest vote count, La
Prensa reported.
   With the results from 4,383 voting stations counted, or 99.8
percent of the total, UNO had 51 seats in the National Assembly and
the Sandinista Front had 39. Two tiny parties had one seat each:
the leftist Revolutionary Unity Movement and the Social Christian
Party.
   Sanchez accused Sandinista militants of amending the vote counts
to deny UNO an additional seat in the single-chamber legislature,
La Prensa said.
   A front-page story in La Prensa said three Soviet-made
helicopters from the Sandinista air force fired rockets that
injured two children at the home of Trinidad Ubeda, a United
National Opposition activist.
   The report said the attack occurred about noon Saturday in a
neighborhood of Jinotega, a mountain town 100 miles northeast of
Managua. It said Ubeda's two daughters were treated at a hospital
for shrapnel wounds.
   An official in Managua denied the report.
   ``They are trying to affect the prestige of the Sandinista
People's Army,'' a Defense Ministry spokesman said in an interview
with The Associated Press.
   ``It's illogical that we would commit such a stupid action. A
helicopter attack such as the one they describe would have leveled
an entire city block, not just a house,'' he said, speaking on
condition of anonymity.
   He said the incident was under investigation.
   The staunchly pro-government newspaper El Nuevo Diario quoted an
unidentified Interior Ministry source Sunday as saying the children
were hurt when an unidentified person tossed a hand grenade into
the home.
   Attempts by the AP to obtain independent confirmation of the
details of the reported attack were not immediately successful.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0041 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 1623EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-SpearfishingRecall     03-04 0577</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Spearfishing Recall,0596</SECOND>
<HEAD>Historic Recall May Attract Republicans to Democratic Primary</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Stands for Minocqua-dated story listed on the BC-FYI Planner
and the News Advisory.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT IMRIE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ST. GERMAIN, Wis. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A state assemblyman whose district has
been troubled by a dispute over Indian hunting and fishing rights
becomes the first Wisconsin lawmaker to face a recall since 1932.
   State Rep. James Holperin, of Eagle River, meets Sayner
businessman Gene Ahlborn in Tuesday's Democratic recall primary,
which was mandated by a petition drive. Brian Sherren, a St.
Germain resort owner, is running unopposed in the Republican
primary. The general election is set for April 3.
   Holperin's northern Wisconsin district covers much of Vilas and
Oneida counties, two hotbeds for protests against spearfishing by
the Lac du Flambeau Chippewa, one of six Chippewa bands in the
state and the most active at spearfishing.
   Non-Indian anglers complain that the Chippewa spearfishing
discriminates against them and depletes fish populations.
   But Wisconsin's Chippewa bands retain the right to spearfish,
hunt, cut timber and gather food off reservation under 19th century
treaties that ceded northern Wisconsin to the U.S. government.
   Since a federal court upheld those treaties in 1983, Chippewa
spearfishers have been met at northern lakes in the spring by
large, rowdy and sometimes violent protests staged by treaty rights
opponents, forcing the state to spend millions of dollars to
protect tribal members.
   Frustrations have risen on all sides of the issue in the last
year as state efforts to negotiate multimillion-dollar settlements
with the tribes were defeated in tribal votes.
   Opponents of the Indians' rights vented their frustration at
39-year-old Holperin this winter, securing about 6,000 signatures
to force a recall.
   The critics claim Holperin has lost touch with voters on
treaty-rights issues. Specifically, they said Holperin supported a
failed treaty rights agreement with the Lac du Flambeau Chippewa
that a majority of his constituents opposed.
   No state representative has ever been successfully recalled in
Wisconsin. The last recall election was in 1932, when Republican
Sen. Otto Mueller of Wausau retained his seat.
   Observers generally agree Republicans hold the balance of power
in Holperin's district.
   Brian Christianson, Sherren's campaign manager, predicted many
GOP members may take advantage of Wisconsin's open primary law and
vote in the Democratic primary as they try to vent their
frustration over the spearfishing dispute.
   ``Who they will vote for? I don't know,'' Christianson said.
``In that lies the great mystery of the campaign. If Jim Holperin
survives the primary, are those Republicans going to stay with him
in the general election?''
   Christianson said the treaty rights issue doesn't cut a clear
path along party lines.
   ``You have Republicans who are sympathetic with Holperin and
union, blue-collar Democrats against Holperin because they are
sportsmen,'' he said. ``I don't think you are going to see a lot of
voter apathy in this election.''
   Some Republicans want Holperin ousted while others, including
Gov. Tommy G. Thompson, feel a recall isn't the proper forum for
settling political differences over treaty rights, he said.
   Sherren, 40, and Ahlborn, 50, a buyer for a family-owned
wholesale business, are both making their first runs for the
Legislature.
   Reports filed with the state Elections Board showed that from
Jan. 1 through Feb. 19, Holperin's campaign raised $25,705 and
spent $17,480.
   Sherren's report indicated he raised $7,710 and spent $2,946.
   Ahlborn's campaign spending report was not available, but he
said he intended to keep his spending below $10,000.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0042 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 1624EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Poindexter     03-04 0902</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Poindexter,780</SECOND>
<HEAD>Poindexter Could Be Last Major Trial in Iran-Contra Affair</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PETE YOST</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Former national security adviser John
Poindexter goes to federal court Monday for what may be the last
major trial in the Iran-Contra scandal.
   Poindexter faces charges that he conspired with former White
House aide Oliver North and others inside and outside the Reagan
administration to cover up North's secret supply network to the
Contras and U.S. involvement in a shipment of Hawk missiles to Iran.
   Reagan gave videotaped testimony for the trial last month, and
Poindexter's lawyers are expected to play it back in court.
   Poindexter is the highest-ranking official in the Reagan White
House to go on trial in the affair, the biggest foreign policy
debacle of Ronald Reagan's presidency.
   Accused of conspiracy, two counts of obstructing Congress and
two counts of making false statements, Poindexter could face up to
25 years in prison and $1.25 million in fines if convicted.
   Poindexter's fate will be decided by a U.S. District Court jury
of 12 people selected from a pool of District of Columbia
residents. Jury selection begins Monday.
   Iran-Contra prosecutor Dan Webb and defense attorney Richard
Beckler will direct opposing teams of trial lawyers in a
second-floor courtroom of the U.S. Courthouse at the foot of
Capitol Hill.
   U.S. District Court Judge Harold Greene will preside at the
trial, which could last up to eight weeks.
   The indictment deals with Poindexter's assertions to Congress in
November 1986 that he didn't find out that Hawk missiles had been
shipped to Iran in November 1985 until two months after the
delivery. The indictment also alleges that Poindexter sent false
letters to Congress in 1986 that embraced earlier denials that
North was assisting the Contras militarily.
   Poindexter says his recollection of the November 1985 Hawk
shipment was ``very, very fuzzy'' and that while he may have made
incorrect statements, he did not lie to Congress.
   ``My best recollection is ... that I did not remember anything
about, or know anything about the Hawks until January '86,''
Poindexter told congressional investigators in immunized testimony
in 1987.
   The CIA-assisted November 1985 shipment of Hawks was authorized
retroactively by a presidential finding which Poindexter presented
to Reagan for signing after the weapons were delivered. The
politically embarrassing finding depicted the transaction with Iran
as straight arms-for-hostages trade. Poindexter destroyed the
document hours after he told his alleged lies to Congress.
   Former CIA Director William Casey testified the same day,
telling members of the House and Senate intelligence committees the
CIA had been told the cargo consisted of spare parts for oil
drilling fields in Iran. Casey gave no indication the CIA and
National Security Council staff knew that the shipment was arms.
   In connection with the Contra portion of the indictment, Reagan
gave testimony that was favorable to Poindexter. Reagan said ``I am
in total agreement'' and ``in complete support'' of letters
Poindexter sent to Congress.
   Poindexter's letters endorsed information national security
adviser Robert McFarlane gave Congress in 1985 denying that North
was raising money or providing military advice to the Nicaraguan
rebels. McFarlane subsequently pleaded guilty to crimes in
connection with the information he had provided in letters to
Congress.
   Reagan said he hadn't known McFarlane had pleaded guilty in
connection with the letters and said he didn't know the Tower
commission which he appointed had concluded North was assisting the
Contras militarily.
   In his videotaped testimony, the former president said he didn't
think Poindexter had made any false statements in the Iran-Contra
affair.
   In addition, Reagan suggested it might have been all right in
November 1986 as the Iran-Contra affair was unfolding to destroy
documents and withhold information from Congress. That body,
explained Reagan, habitually leaked sensitive information that in
this instance might have jeopardized the lives of U.S. hostages
held in Lebanon.
   Part of the conspiracy charge accuses Poindexter of working with
North to destroy classified documents and records of the National
Security Council.
   North was convicted by a jury last May of three felonies in the
Iran-Contra scandal, sentenced to 1,200 hours of community service,
fined $150,000 and given two years' probation.
   One of the crimes for which North was convicted _ aiding and
abetting an obstruction of Congress _ involved the November 1985
shipment of Hawks for which Poindexter is now charged.
   North is appealing the convictions and the fine while performing
the community service in an anti-drug program.
   Richard Secord and Albert Hakim, businessmen who assisted North
in supplying the Contras and ship arms to Iran, pleaded guilty to
crimes in the Iran-Contra affair and were placed on probation.
   Businessmen Carl Channell and Richard Miller, who raised private
donations for the Contras, pleaded guilty to conspiring to defraud
the government of taxes and were placed on probation.
   The Bush administration stepped in and blocked the use of some
classified material in the case of Joseph Fernandez, the former CIA
station chief in Costa Rica. As a result of the action by Attorney
General Dick Thornburgh, the judge in the case dismissed charges
that Fernandez lied about his assistance to North's Contra resupply
network. Iran-Contra prosecutors are appealing.
   Thomas Clines, a former CIA agent who assisted North in locating
sources of arms and shipping them to the Contras, is under
indictment for alleged tax violations in the scandal and is
scheduled to appear in federal court in Baltimore later this month.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0043 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 1625EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Soviet-Raisa     03-04 0234</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Raisa,0240</SECOND>
<HEAD>In Gorbachev Household, Raisa Runs the Party</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Soviet-Election, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Mikhail S. Gorbachev may run the Soviet Union, but
at home, it's his wife, Raisa, who's in charge of the family's
politics, the Soviet leader joked Sunday.
   Speaking to Soviet TV at the polling station where he voted for
legislators to the Russian republic, Gorbachev said it was
difficult to choose among the many candidates.
   ``I should say that there was a meeting of our party
organization at home,'' he said. ``At our house it's Raisa
Maximovna who's the secretary of the party organization.''
   To the chuckles of reporters and others in Gorbachev's
entourage, Raisa countered: ``Probably they'll remove me soon.''
   Gorbachev, with a grin, said the family managed to reach a
decision and ``come to the polls with a united platform _ if no one
has changed his mind.''
   Raisa, with a laugh, said Gorbachev was after her downfall.
``(He) wants to have me removed. Get it? That's the main thing,''
she said.
   The polling station scene, carried on the nightly news, was a
rare light moment in days of political tension for Gorbachev. His
proposal for a Soviet presidency with vastly expanded powers comes
before the Soviet Congress soon.
   Raisa Gorbachev is seen by many Soviets as a rather domineering
woman who is unwilling to take the retiring role common to wives of
past Soviet leaders.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0044 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 1627EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Chess     03-04 0204</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Chess,0214</SECOND>
<HEAD>Kasparov Clinches Slim Victory In Spanish Chess Tourney</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LINARES, Spain (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   World chess champion Gari Kasparov of the
Soviet Union won his final match, edging out his countryman, Boris
Gelfand, in the eighth City of Linares tournament.
   Kasparov beat Miguel Illescas of Spain in 61 moves late Saturday
to end the 11-round tournament with 8 points, just 0.5 ahead of
Gelfand, 21, who strengthened his reputation as a contender for
Kasparov's world crown.
   Kasparov was awarded 875,000 pesetas ($8,100) and an all-terrain
vehicle for winning the tournament, which pitted 12 of the world's
top players against one another.
   In his final match, 14th-ranked Gelfand drew with countryman
Vasily Ivanchuk, who finished fourth with 6.5 points.
   Valeri Salov was third, with 7 points, after drawing with fellow
Soviet Alexander Beljavsky, who ended up eighth with 5 points.
   Briton Nigel Short was fifth, with 6 points, followed by U.S.
player Boris Gulko and Soviet Artur Yusupov, with 5.5.
   Illescas finished ninth with 4 points, the same as former world
champion Boris Spassky and Lajos Portisch of Hungary. Yugoslavia's
Ljubomir Ljubojevic had three points and finished 12th.
   In other matches Saturday:
   Spassky drew with Gulko.
   Portisch drew with Yusupov.
   Ljubojevic drew with Short.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0045 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 1632EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-India     03-04 0373</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-India,0383</SECOND>
<HEAD>Prime Minister Singh Resigns as Party Chief</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW DELHI, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Prime Minister V.P. Singh resigned as
president of his Janata Dal party, in keeping with earlier promises
to step aside to avoid holding two offices, a party spokesman said
Sunday.
   Singh resigned late Saturday at a party meeting called to
discuss alleged vote fraud by a party leader, spokesman Jaipal
Reddy said. The party leader, Om Prakash Chauthala, was also
accused of inciting violence during a by-election last month.
   In a measure seen as a face-saving move in the absence of
Chauthala's resignation, the Press Trust of India said the party
Sunday recommended the Election Commission repeat balloting in
Meham, Harayana state, where Chauthala was a candidate.
   Reddy denied the prime minister's decision was linked to the
election dispute. He said Singh's decision was in accordance with
his repeated declarations he would not hold two offices to avoid
conflict of interest.
   Singh became prime minister in December, promising to uphold
democracy and respect public institutions, which he said his
predecessor Rajiv Gandhi had ignored. In the past, government
leaders have used benefits for party business, opening them to
charges of misuse of public office.
   A New Delhi English language newspaper, Indian Express, said
Singh's decision would have ``implications for many others in the
Janata Dal'' who hold both a party post and public office.
   Reddy said Singh was asked to continue as party leader until
alternative arrangements are made.
   Chauthala, the eldest son of Deputy Prime Minister Devi Lal, was
appointed to the post of chief minister but was required under
Indian law to seek the voters' mandate to ratify his position.
   News reports said that in the Feb. 27 by-election in Meham, 60
miles northwest of New Delhi, violence broke out when Chauthala's
supporters tried to stuff ballot boxes and intimidate voters.
   A second vote Feb. 28 also was marred by rigging and violence
that left at least 13 people dead, and Chauthala was blamed.
   The by-election was held along with balloting for eight state
legislatures and lawmakers in a federally controlled territory.
Gandhi's Congress Party suffered heavy losses in the elections,
while Singh's Janata Dal and the right-wing Hindu fundamentalist
Indian People's Party made strong gains.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0046 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 1627EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Gorbachev     03-04 0643</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gorbachev,0664</SECOND>
<HEAD>Gorbachev Says Soviet Split Would be Worse than Cultural
Revolution</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Soviet-Election, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ANN IMSE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Mikhail S. Gorbachev said Sunday that the breakup
of the Soviet Union could be more devastating to his country than
the ruinous Cultural Revolution that wracked China for 10 years.
   The Soviet leader spoke to reporters after voting in elections
for the Russian republic. Asked if he could put up with the Baltic
republics declaring independence, Gorbachev said that trying to
disentangle the nationalities of the Soviet Union after decades of
living together would lead to trouble comparable to the upheaval in
China that started in 1966.
   ``Just think of more than 60 million people living outside their
national lands,'' Gorbachev said, referring to the more than 100
nationalities in the Soviet Union.
   ``Just imagine these millions of people on the move,'' he said.
``This will throw the country back. This will bring trouble to
people who have lived in some place for decades, which has become
their second motherland.''
   ``Over these decades, the interests of the republics and the
people have become so entangled that if we now started to divide
the entire country, this would lead to trouble,'' he said. ``It
would be worse than the Cultural Revolution in China. This simply
cannot be allowed to happen.''
   Mao Tse-tung's attempt to revive revolutionary fervor in China
sparked a violent struggle for power that led to the closing of
universities for four years, destruction of antiquities, and a
devastating setback in the country's economic development. An
estimated 1 million people died.
   Ethnic tension and demands for independence from small republics
increasingly threaten Soviet unity.
   The latest unrest was reported in the city of Parkent in the
Central Asian republic of Uzbekistan. Official reports said at
least one soldier was killed Saturday in unrest in the city. It was
not clear what sparked the violence, but Uzbekistan has been the
scene of ethnic unrest in the past.
   The Baltic republics of Latvia, Lithuania, and Estonia have been
campaigning to regain the independence they had before being
annexed by the Soviet Union in 1940.
   Some Lithuanians are calling for their newly elected parliament
to take office and vote on independence this week, before Gorbachev
can win approval for a presidency with vastly expanded powers.
   Separatists fear the more powerful position could be used
against them. Some have said it could lead to restoration of a
dictatorship, because it would allow the president to suspend
republics' parliaments and send in troops without the approval of
local authorities.
   Gorbachev promised Sunday that a revision of his proposal, due
to be published this week, would ease these fears.
   ``There will be no possibility of repeating what happened in the
years of the command-administrative system,'' he said, referring to
the regimes of his predecessors.
   If Gorbachev's proposals are approved by national legislators,
the first president to hold the wider powers _ expected to be
Gorbachev _ would be elected by parliament. Subsequent leaders
would be chosen in a national vote.
   Gorbachev said Sunday that he would not refuse nomination to the
post.
   He also gave some support to nationalists in the Soviet Union,
saying, ``I do not think that the striving for national
independence, self-reliance and sovereignty is ambitious.''
   But he said it should be achieved through a reformation of the
Soviet structure as a federation.
   At a meeting Sunday of the Moscow Tribune, a progressive
citizen's group, member Anatoly Akhutin warned that the presidency
proposal ``is a way of introducing a general state of emergency.''
   Another member, Vladimir Bibler, called for signatures on a
resolution terming the proposal anti-democratic, unless the nation
first establishes a promised multiparty system, a new constitution,
a stronger parliament, and direct popular election of the president.
   Gorbachev has supported all of these, yet none has been
implemented.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0047 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 1706EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Israel     03-04 0522</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel,0540</SECOND>
<HEAD>Israel's Leaders: No Response To U.S. Plan for Talks</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ALLYN FISHER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Israel's four top leaders on Sunday debated
U.S. proposals for opening Middle East peace talks, but they failed
to bridge differences blocking a response to the plan.
   Vice Premier Shimon Peres, leader of the center-left Labor
Party, insisted that the Cabinet vote on the compromises by
Wednesday, but officials in Prime Minister Yitzhak Shamir's
right-wing Likud bloc objected.
   ``In matters pertaining to Israeli survival ... we have to make
decisions by ourselves without a gun to our temple,'' said
Transport Minister Moshe Katzav, a Shamir ally.
   Deputy Premier David Levy, Likud's leading opponent of the
compromises, threatened to resign if the Cabinet agrees to the U.S.
plan.
   Peres said shortly before Sunday's meeting of the ``forum of
four'' _ two leaders from each of the main parties _ that he ould
hold Likud to a Wednesday deadline for putting the U.S. proposals
to a vote by the decision-making Inner Cabinet.
   ``There is no need to wait, the picture is clear,'' he said.
   Labor leaders have threatened to quit the governing coalition if
no decision is made by Wednesday. But Defense Minister Yitzhak
Rabin, another Labor leader, said he could wait until next week for
the 12-member Inner Cabinet to make its decision.
   The ``forum of four,'' which includes Shamir and Foreign
Minister Moshe Arens of Likud and Peres and Rabin of Labor, met for
45 minutes Sunday.
   Rabin later told Israel army radio that they failed to decide on
the proposals by U.S. Secretary of State James A. Baker III because
Likud's ministers remained divided.
   Baker has been trying to bring together Israelis and
Palestinians for preliminary talks in Cairo on Israel's plan for
elections in the occupied West Bank and Gaza Strip. The elections
would be a step toward limited autonomy for the territories, which
Israel has occupied since 1967.
   Baker reportedly wants to start the talks April 2, but Likud has
resisted his proposals to include residents of Arab east Jerusalem
and two Palestinians who were deported by Israel among the
Palestinian negotiators.
   Those proposals were intended to meet PLO demands to include
outside Palestinians in the talks but still meet Israel's demand to
only talk to residents of the territories.
   Likud officials fear the compromises would bring members of the
Palestine Liberation Organization into peace talks, and would raise
questions about Israel's control of Jerusalem. Israel refuses to
talk to the PLO, which it views as a terrorist group.
   According to Israeli news reports, Baker has suggested a new
formula of accepting in principle any negotiator who is a
registered resident of the territories, which could include
deportees or Palestinians with ties to east Jerusalem. Individual
names could be discussed later.
   Deputy Premier Levy remained staunchly opposed to the plan
Sunday.
   ``The formula in essence includes all the dangerous elements
that Likud opposes,'' he said.
   Shamir spokesman Avi Pazner denied earlier reports that the
premier favored Baker's ideas.
   ``The prime minister hasn't told anyone if he supports the
proposals or not. He hasn't had his say,'' Pazner said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0048 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 1722EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Soviet-Election 1stLd-Writethru a0733 03-04 1217</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Election, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0733,1252</SECOND>
<HEAD>Slavic Republics Head to Polls in Key Local Balloting</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos MOSB2,3,4,7</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: INSERTS 1 graf after 4th pvs, `No results...' to UPDATE with
reports from runoffs in Lithuania. Pick up 5th pvs, `Officials
reported...' ADDS 3 grafs with details.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By MARK J. PORUBCANSKY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Millions of Soviets from the Polish border to the
Bering Strait voted Sunday in what President Mikhail S. Gorbachev
said was a struggle between reform and bureaucracy for the
country's Slavic heartland.
   ``I think it is a battle,'' Gorbachev told reporters after
voting in the Lenin Hills area of Moscow, ``but I am convinced that
perestroika will win.''
   Almost 150 million voters were registered to choose among more
than 11,000 candidates for 1,800 seats in the legislatures of the
Russian, Ukrainian and Byelorussian republics. Thousands of seats
in local governing councils also were being contested.
   No results were expected until Tuesday in the three republics,
which comprise the vast majority of the country's territory and
hold more than two-thirds of the Soviet Union's 290 million people.
   In the Baltic republic of Lithuania, meanwhile, pro-independence
activists said results in runoff elections Sunday assured them of
the quorum they need to covene the republic's parliament, where
activists are expected to push for creating a mechanism to secede
from the Soviet Union.
   Officials reported a strong turnout in the Far East region and
the Ukraine, where more than half of registered voters had been to
polling stations before noon. Polls were open from 7 a.m. to 8 p.m.
   There was increased political tension over Gorbachev's reforms
in the weeks leading to the elections.
   Gorbachev has pressed the Communist Party to relinquish its
monopoly on power and pushed for a new, more powerful presidency.
Hundreds of thousands of Soviets have turned out for pro-democracy
rallies.
   In the Slavic republics, reforms _ where they have managed to
get started _ have proceeded more slowly and quietly than in other
areas. There have been neither the concerted drives of the Baltic
republics nor the violence of the Caucasus and Central Asia.
   Gorbachev and Soviet citizens said the local party and
government officials seeking election were among national leaders
most opposed to reforms.
   ``Our elections involve a new type of people, people who have
been given new impetus from perestroika,'' a relaxed, confident
Gorbachev said. ``The essence of it is that it is a people's
referendum on perestroika.''
   The Soviet leader, who was accompanied to the polls by his wife
Raisa, daughter, son-in-law and two grandchildren, urged Soviets to
``come forward and take greater responsibility for themselves.''
   Responding to reporters' questions as he left the polling
station at the Institute of Chemical Physics, the Soviet leader
said it was not particularly important whether the victors were
Communist Party members.
   The 20-million member party is trying to get much closer to the
people, ``and so the question of proportions is not crucial,'' he
said.
   ``It is important that people are there who support perestroika
and are prepared to move this process ahead. Communist or non-party
members, all will be good enough,'' he said.
   Hundreds of longtime party and government officials were
candidates.
   In Russia alone, the ballot contained 25 heads of regional
Communist Party organizations and 36 chairmen or deputy chairmen of
autonomous regions within the giant republic.
   In the days before the balloting, official newspapers were full
of stories of campaign tricks and pork-barrel politics. Officials
sought to avoid the kind of embarrassing defeats they suffered last
year in balloting for the national Congress of People's Deputies.
   Voters in the Ukraine selected a 450-member Supreme Soviet
legislature, Byelorussia chose a 310-member legislature and Russia
elected a 1,068-member congress that will choose a legislature and
leadership from among its members.
   Reformist Communist leader Boris Yeltsin, who voted at a
children's center in central Moscow, told reporters the turnout was
likely to be ``significantly lower'' than balloting for the
national Congress last March. In that race, Soviets were given
their first choice of candidates in more than 70 years.
   Yeltsin was a candidate for a district in his Ural Mountains
home of Sverdlovsk.
   As the Communist maverick appeared, several people waiting for
him whispered among themselves, ``Here comes the president of
Russia,'' a reference to his candidacy for the new post of the
presidency of the republic, to be elected by legislators.
   Voters on the Kamchatka Peninsula of the Soviet Far East, who
were among the first to go to the polls, had as many as 12
candidates to choose from for each seat. In Leningrad, 280
candidates were seeking 34 seats.
   About 3,000 candidates in the Ukraine were vying for 450 seats
in the republic's Supreme Soviet, and in Byelorussia there was an
average of five candidates for each seat, the Tass news agency said.
   Vitaly Boiko, chairman of the Ukrainian election commission,
said from Kiev that as of 6 p.m. more than 80 percent of the 37
million voters had gone to the polls.
   ``In my opinion, it's explained by the fact that people want
perestroika to go faster, they want the formation of the new organs
of Soviet power to be completed,'' he said.
   Sergei Odarych, an election official for the informal Ukrainian
political group Rukh, reported minor irregularities but said the
problems were easily straightened out.
   Ivan Likhach, official of Byelorussian election commission, said
from Minsk that about half the eligible voters had been to the
polls by noon, and turnout was running ahead of last March's
elections.
   ``Activism is higher this year,'' he said.
   Ukrainian Communist Party chief Vladimir A. Ivashko, a member of
the national party Politburo, faced 11 challengers.
   Official reports said 86 percent of candidates in the Russian
elections and 80 percent in the Ukraine were members of the
Communist Party.
   Newspapers have been filled with reports of campaign tricks. The
Workers' Tribune newspaper said workers in one Moscow district were
paving over snow to meet the campaign promise of Mayor Valery T.
Saikin and appease voters who swore they wouldn't vote unless
parking lots were built.
   Saikin, defeated a year ago in national elections, was a
candidate for re-election to the 498-member Moscow city council.
   Balloting in the Slavic republics followed an election in the
Baltic republic of Lithuania swept by candidates endorsed by the
pro-independence Sajudis movement, and several other republics.
   Voters in 28 Lithuanian districts cast ballots in runoff
elections Sunday. Runoffs in the remaining 17 districts not settled
in the Feb. 24 election will be held later in the week, Tass said.
   On Sunday, at least nine deputies to the Lithuanian Supreme
Soviet were elected, eight of them supported by the
pro-independence movement Sajudis, said Longinas Vasiliauskas, a
Sajudis spokesman. Two-thirds of the 140-member parliament must
have been elected before a session can be called.
   Observers have speculated that Sajudis wants a quick parliament
session so Lithuania can vote to secede from the Soviet Union
before Gorbachev gains his expected broad new powers, which include
the right to suspend republic parliaments and send in troops.
   The Soviet Congress meets next Monday to consider Gorbachev's
proposal.
   Vasiliauskas said the Lithuanian parliament would not vote to
leave the Soviet Union immediately but wants to create the
mechanism for secession because ``We don't know what Gorbachev will
do after he's elected president.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0049 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 1728EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-WeatherpageWeather     03-04 0280</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Weatherpage Weather,0288</SECOND>
<HEAD>New Storm Moving Ashore On West Coast</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Stormy weather dominated the West Coast on Sunday as a cold
front moved ashore with rain and snow, and snow also was scattered
around the Great Lakes.
   Snow advisories were issued Sunday for the mountains of northern
California, southern Oregon and western Nevada, and a winter storm
watch was in effect through Monday for east-central and
northeastern Nevada.
   During the day Sunday, mostly rain fell over northern California
and western Oregon, and a few showers also developed over western
Washington state and southern California. The heaviest rain for the
six hours up to 1 p.m. EST was 0.82 of an inch at Crescent City,
Calif., on the state's northern coast
   Farther inland, a vigorous upper-level weather system moved
across Colorado during the night, producing snow in the northern
and central mountains. The Arapaho Basin and Winter Park ski areas
got up to 8 inches of snow, and Vail got 7 inches.
   Light snow fell over parts of Wisconsin and Minnesota, and was
scattered around the lower Great Lakes. Parts of Wisconsin got 2
inches of snow during the night.
   Light snow also fell over Maine and New Hampshire.
   Showers and thunderstorms moved across southern Florida during
the night and were over the Florida Keys by afternoon.
   Afternoon temperatures were still below freezing in the upper
Mississippi Valley, the Great Lakes region and the Northeast, and
northern Michigan had subzero lows during the night.
   Temperatures warmed into the 60s and 70s from Texas to Florida,
and over southern California and southern Arizona.
   Sunday's low for the Lower 48 states was 6 below zero at
Pellston, Mich.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0050 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 1811EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-HotelStrike     03-04 0416</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Hotel Strike,0427</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hotels Scramble to Replace Striking Workers</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HONOLULU (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Strike-bound hotels are flying in support staff
and advertising for replacement workers as they struggle to keep
some of Hawaii's biggest hotels open for tourists.
   The 7,500 members of the Local 5 of the Hotel Employees and
Restaurant Employees Union went on strike Saturday in a contract
dispute against 11 major hotels and resorts in Hawaii.
   The hotels remained open Sunday but many closed their
restaurants and snack shops and curtailed services after the strike
began. The 11 hotels account for one of every five hotel rooms in
Hawaii and two of every five hotel rooms in Waikiki, the state's
main tourist destination.
   Federal mediator Frank Schoeppel said no new contract talks will
be scheduled for at least seven days.
   Tony Rudledge, union president, promised to pressure hotel
management until the union's demands are met.
   ``We may be having some massive sit-ins that the employers may
not like and we may get arrested for trespassing,'' said Rutledge.
``You don't get too far walking in a (picket) circle.''
   Hilton Hotels, owner of Hilton Hawaiian Village, the largest
resort in Hawaii with 2,532 rooms, brought in about 50 managers
from the mainland, said spokewoman Jeanne Park. The hotel also was
hiring temporary replacements.
   Park said the resort almost had the 700 to 750 people it needed
for the day shift Saturday. The hardest spots to fill, she said,
were maids and cooks.
   The Hyatt Regency Waikiki started shifting managers from its
hotels on other Hawaiian islands Thursday, said Joanna Robles,
director of public relations who also was supervising a
housecleaning crew.
   The Hyatt wasn't signing temporary workers, she said.
   Sheraton Hotels started a radio advertising campaign Saturday to
recruit as many as 2,000 temporary workers, said spokeswoman Maggie
Wunsch.
   Neither side expected a quick resolution to the dispute, which
centers on wages and benefits, as well as union demands for a 5
percent room surcharge that would be divided among all workers who
don't get tips and a 15 percent surcharge on all food and beverage
purchases.
   Bill Crawford, executive director of the Council of Hawaii
Hotels, which represents employers, said the union rejected a
four-year deal that called for annual wage increases of 5 percent
plus hikes in benefits that boosted the total package to around 7
percent a year.
   Rodriguez said the union calculated the management proposal at
around 4 percent, which he said was lower than the 5 percent
package offered Friday.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0051 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 1814EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Germany     03-04 0589</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Germany,0608</SECOND>
<HEAD>Communist Campaign Stunt Foiled by Weather</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Germany-Poland, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CAROL J. WILLIAMS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>EAST BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Communist Party leader Gregor Gysi, trying to
boost his party's election standings with a sky-diving stunt,
suffered an early setback Sunday when high winds forced him to call
off his parachute jump.
   Communist Premier Hans Modrow, meanwhile, was headed to Moscow
for talks with a worried Kremlin about trade and security after the
March 18 elections, which are expected to sweep the Communists out
of power and speed unification with West Germany.
   The Communists are running a distant third in the campaign for
parliamentary seats in East Germany's first competitive election in
its 40-year history.
   Gysi addressed a rally in East Berlin's Hellersdorf region, then
suited up for his planned sky-diving stunt, after which he was to
have landed back at the rally site. But the jump was canceled
because of gale-force winds that swept through Berlin over the
weekend.
   Gysi, 41, is attempting to boost the Communist image, which has
been badly tarnished by past corruption and abuses of power. He
drew a capacity crowd at East Berlin's House of Parties for a
campaign appearance before the scheduled jump.
   He promised that Communist lawmakers would fight to ensure that
``40 years of social accomplishments'' are not wiped out by a hasty
merger with West Germany.
   As officials from both sides negotiate how to mesh the two
German economies and societies after four decades of division, East
Germans have become fearful of unemployment, huge rent increases
and other consequences of capitalism.
   East Germany's ADN news agency said Modrow was to meet with
Soviet President Mikhail S. Gorbachev on Monday to discuss
reunification.
   ADN, citing unidentified sources in Moscow, suggested that the
Soviet leadership remains concerned about how German unification
would influence the Soviet economy and security. East Germany has
traditionally been the Soviets' most important trading partner and
defense ally.
   The Soviets have indicated they will allow reunification, but
Gorbachev has said the new nation should be militarily neutral.
West German Chancellor Helmut Kohl says a united Germany should be
part of the NATO alliance.
   West German Foreign Minister Hans-Dietrich Genscher on Sunday
reiterated his view that West Germany should make clear its intent
to respect Poland's current western border after reunification.
   In an interview with the ZDF television network, Genscher
further distanced himself from Kohl, who has refused to provide
Poland a guarantee.
   Genscher's Free Democratic Party is a junior partner in the
government with Kohl's Christian Democratic Union.
   Poland has asked that the two Germanys begin work on a treaty to
recognize the Oder and Neisse rivers as the permanent border
between Germany and Poland. It is afraid a reunited Germany might
press claims to prewar territories that now make up about a third
of Poland.
   Kohl, apparently fearing the loss of arch-conservative voters in
December elections, has refused to provide a guarantee, saying it
would be up to a reunited Germany to decide.
   But he said Friday that he favors a reunited Germany signing a
treaty to fix the border if Poland also agrees to waive all claims
to war reparations and guarantees the rights of ethnic Germans.
   Poland, which already waived such reparations in 1953, has
rejected Kohl's new suggestions.
   In the ZDF interview, Genscher issued a veiled warning to Kohl
that he should not bring into question issues that have already
been resolved.
   The border question was also expected to be a central topic
during the talks between Modrow and Gorbachev.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0052 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 1822EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Westmar-Teikyo     03-04 0384</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Westmar-Teikyo,0397</SECOND>
<HEAD>Small College Merges With Japanese University</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GREG SMITH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LE MARS, Iowa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   For its 100th birthday, a small private
college in northwest Iowa is getting a new name, millions of
dollars and an affiliation with a Japanese university.
   Westmar College's board of trustees highlighted the school's
centennial Saturday by voting to become a branch of Teikyo
University of Japan.
   ``Our community just got bigger and the world just got
smaller,'' Westmar President Arthur Richardson told a cheering
crowd of students, faculty and residents after the board vote.
   Richardson refused to disclose the vote by the 37-member board
but said more than two-thirds agreed to rename the school Teikyo
Westmar University.
   The agreement gives Teikyo its third branch university in the
United States. Teikyo has reached agreements with Regis College to
buy its Loretto Heights campus in Denver and with Salem College in
Salem, W. Va.
   The Tokyo-based Teikyo has nine campuses elsewhere in Japan as
well as branches in England and Holland.
   Richardson said the 566-student college had been seeking an
international agreement since the mid-1980s when the school was in
financial trouble and enrollment dipped to 417.
   Teikyo Westmar University will receive $4 million from Teikyo to
refurbish dormitories and classroom buildings, increase salaries,
hire additional faculty and to enroll as many as 400 Japanese
students by the fall of 1991.
   As many as 200 Japanese are expected to arrive this spring in Le
Mars, 20 miles northeast of Sioux City.
   Richardson said the Westmar College board would be dissolved and
the new board would have at least seven members, the majority
Americans. An acting board chairman will be Takashi Yamanaka, who
is also chairman of the executive committee at Teikyo Loretto
Heights University.
   Richardson was criticized by some for waiting until last month
to inform faculty and trustees about the proposal he began
negotiating last November.
   ``They have called it a marriage. But in my judgment the
engagement period was way too short. We didn't have a chance to get
acquainted,'' said Robert Rydell of Des Moines, chairman of the
board of trustees until he and three other members resigned to
protest Richardson's actions.
   ``It did kind of happen all of a sudden,'' Richardson said.
``But you can't announce a gift you don't have.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0053 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 1836EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Mandela     03-04 0531</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mandela,0549</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mandela Greeted With Cheers in Zimbabwe</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN EDLIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HARARE, Zimbabwe (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Nelson Mandela arrived in Zimbabwe
Sunday to the cheers of thousands of well-wishers and an embrace
from President Robert Mugabe, a former black guerrilla fighter who
like Mandela spent years in jail.
   Mugabe, who long agitated for Mandela's release from South
African prisons, welcomed the South African black leader on the
tarmac at Harare airport as thousands cheered to the throb of
tribal drums.
   ``You're not a stranger!'' Mugabe declared. ``You've come home
where the 10 million people stand solidly behind the people of
South Africa in the unrelenting struggle.''
   Children in feather headdresses chanted, ``We're going to
Pretoria to fight!''
   Mandela said his African National Congress was anxious for talks
with the Pretoria government.
   ``We are trying to convince the white minority that it is
madness that we should be killing one another when we can sit down,
talk and settle our problems,'' he said.
   ``The day they (the South African government) decide to settle
with the acknowledged leaders of the country and the day they
commit themselves to a democratic and non-racial South Africa they
will be accepted in the region, in Africa and other parts of the
world with open arms,'' Mandela said.
   Zimbabwe, a former British colony that won independence after a
bloody guerrilla war, is the second stop on Mandela's four-nation
tour. Mandela, now vice president of the ANC, will leave for
Mozambique in three days and later travel to Sweden to visit ailing
ANC President Oliver Tambo.
   Mandela, 71, was freed Feb. 11 after more than 27 years in
prison for sabotage and plotting to overthrow the white government.
   In Zimbabwe, he will witness firsthand how white-governed
Rhodesia was transformed into black-ruled Zimbabwe. Aides to the
ANC leader say he views Zimbabwe as a possible model for a future
South Africa.
   Mugabe himself spent 10 years in detention under the regime of
Rhodesian Prime Minister Ian D. Smith before he led the seven-year
war that ended with independence in 1980.
   On Sunday, giant portraits of Mandela festooned lampposts and
trees on the road to the airport. One placard displayed at the
airport read, ``Mandela _ destroyer of the apartheid monster.''
   Apartheid is the South African system of racial segregation
under which the 28-million black majority has no vote. President
F.W. de Klerk, who says he wants to bring blacks into the political
system, has lifted bans on opposition groups and initiated other
reforms,
   Speaking to thousands of Mugabe loyalists at a soccer stadium,
Mandela said the key to South Africa's future lies not only in the
black majority gaining the vote, but also in the unity of rival
black factions.
   He pointed to the example of Zimbabwe, where Mugabe formally
merged his political forces last year with those of his chief
rival, Joshua Nkomo.
   Since coming to power, Mugabe has pursued a policy of
reconciliation between whites and blacks, rival tribes and
opposition political movements. Whites have held Cabinet posts.
   Sunday's rally was to launch Mugabe's governing Zimbabwe African
National Union (Patriotic Front) party's campaign for parliamentary
and presidential elections at the end of this month.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0054 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 1950EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brites     03-04 0430</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brites,0447</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bright &amp; Brief</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CHARLESTON, S.C. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   You need two things to be a turkey
calling champion, says Walter Parrott. A good ear and an
understanding wife.
   ``You have to have a good rhythm, an ear for rhythm, tones,
sounds,'' said the defending champion at the National Wild Turkey
Federation meeting.
   And ``you have to have a wife that'll listen to it,'' Parrott
said.
   But Parrott, 34, of Doe Run, Mo., was out-clucked Saturday by
Matt Morrett who strutted off with the national championship.
   The 19-year-old Morrett from Harrisburg, Pa., first competed at
age 6. He's been gobbling up awards ever since.
   Contestants had to give the tree call of a hen turkey, the
assembly call of an old hen, the yelp of a hen in springtime, the
whistle and call of a lost turkey, the cutting of an excited hen,
and the cluck and purr of a hen.
   There was a little actor in the callers as they crouched and
rose, hands cupped around their mouths, imitating the sounds of a
turkey in spring or an old hen calling an assembly of birds.
   Judges concentrated on the sound from behind a white curtain and
their backs to the caller.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>PROVIDENCE, R.I. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two sisters separated in Cambodia were
reunited 16 years later when one of the women happened to go into a
Providence restaurant where the other one worked.
   Sideth Prak, 30, was running the kitchen at the Phnom Penh
restaurant two weeks ago when she noticed one of the customers,
Bhopa Ros.
   The woman's tiny figure and solemn expression were much like her
own. She listened to the woman's voice and went running back to the
kitchen.
   ``I think that's my sister out there,'' she told her husband.
   Bhopa, then 8, had become separated from her family when the
Communist Khmer Rouge arrived in Phnom Penh in 1975. Sideth was
visiting an uncle in another province and was trapped there when
the Khmer Rouge seized power.
   Years later, they both made their way to the United States _
Bhopa settled in Malden, Mass., and Sideth in Rhode Island.
   While in Providence two weeks ago, a Cambodian friend suggested
they eat at the Phnom Penh restaurant where the reunion took place.
   Two days later, Bhopa moved to Cranston to join her sister. She
celebrated her 23rd birthday with her family Friday.
   ``I feel so great,'' she said. ``When I met my sister, I quit my
job. Even if I work here washing dishes ... I don't care. I don't
want to miss any more.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0055 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 1913EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Panama-Injured 1stLd-Writethru a0730 03-04 0216</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-Injured, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0730,0231</SECOND>
<HEAD>List Of Americans Injured in Grenade Attack</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Changes status of 7 men to treated and released. DROPS double
reference for McKinney, adds Jeffrey Warren.</NOTE>
<HEAD>With AM-Panama</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here is a list of American military
personnel injured when a grenade was thrown into a Panama City
discotheque. The list was provided by the U.S. Southern Command.
   
   In satisfactory condition at Gorgas Hospital:
   Spec. Ronald D. Sallis, 22, Army, Chippewa Falls, Wis.
   Pvt. David C. McKinney, 28, Army, Amarillo, Texas
   Airman 1st Class Joseph D. Pelletier, Jr., 20, Air Force,
Bucksport, Maine.
   Airman Warren A. Waters, 22, Air Force, Phoenix, Ariz.
   Petty Officer, 2nd Class Charles L. Curtis, 26, Navy, Shelby,
N.C.
   Petty Officer 3rd Class Calbert Malone, Jr., 23, Navy,
Greenville, Miss.
   
   Treated and released:
   Sgt. Robert A. Burford, 24, Army, Oak Ridge, Pa.
   Spec. Brian P. Fiske, 22, Army, Columbus, Ohio.
   Pvt. Jesus A. Omar, 25, Army, Guam.
   Pvt. Mark A. Hatfield, 24, Army, Clairton, Pa.
   Sgt. Mark G. Sacco, 27, Air Force, Ellwood City, Pa.
   Constructionman Recruit Alex ``U'' Bustamante, 19, Navy Seabee,
Ajo, Ariz.
   Chief Warrant Officer Jeffrey Warren, 27, Mt. Olive, Miss.
   Chief Warrant Officer John Petraroi, 28, Navy, Rahway, N.J.
   Pvt. Derek W. Piquard, 20, Army, de Woodhaven, Mich.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0056 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 2008EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-NuclearShip     03-04 0226</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Nuclear Ship,0233</SECOND>
<HEAD>Soviet Nuclear Ship Proposed for Canadian Grain Shipments</HEAD>
<DATELINE>VANCOUVER, British Columbia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   City Council has been asked
to approve the use of a nuclear-powered Soviet carrier for grain
exports despite the city's declaration as a nuclear-free zone.
   Morflot Freightliners wants to use the nuclear-powered
Sevmorput, an icebreaker-container carrier, for grain shipments
from March through July at Canada's main West Coast port.
   Morflot officials said they wanted to determine the council's
position before before asking Transport Canada for permission. The
issue is on the council's agenda for Tuesday.
   A report by Morflot Freightliners to city council described the
33,900-metric-ton ship as unsinkable and mentioned ``four
protective barriers'' around the nuclear-powered steam plant.
   That failed to mollify Mayor Gordon Campbell and peace and
environmental activists.
   ``I have consistently voted to make Vancouver a nuclear-free
harbor,'' Campbell said Saturday. ``We've told the federal
government we don't want nuclear-powered or nuclear
weapons-carrying ships in Vancouver harbor.''
   ``It's totally, totally outrageous that they are even
considering coming to Vancouver,'' said John Mate of Greenpeace.
   A University of British Columbia professor writing a book on
naval safety said Canada should steer clear of Soviet nuclear ships.
   ``The Soviets' reactor safety record is appalling,'' said
Michael Wallace, a political science professor. ``They are
unbelievably sloppy with quality control, and quality control
problems and nuclear reactors don't go together.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0057 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 1953EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-SelmaMarch 3rdLd-Writethru a0760 03-04 0744</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Selma March, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0760,0758</SECOND>
<HEAD>25th Anniversary Marchers Recreate `Bloody Sunday'</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 7th graf, `The 50-mile...police said,' to UPDATE with
marchers stopping for the night. Pick up 8th graf pvs, `Jackson,
speaking...</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos XSE1, XSE5; LaserColor XSE9</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARVIN HARRIS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SELMA, Ala. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Four thousand people set out Sunday on a 25th
anniversary re-enactment of a historic voting-rights march to
Montgomery, including a replay of a bloody confrontation with
police on a bridge.
   The group returning to the Edmund Pettus bridge was led by such
civil-rights figures as Jesse Jackson and Coretta Scott King. Among
them were some of the original marchers, including U.S. Rep. John
Lewis, Hosea Williams, Albert Turner and F.D. Reese.
   ``We shed a little blood here that made a difference. People are
now registering to vote,'' said Lewis, D-Ga.
   Halfway up the bridge Sunday, smoke was released to simulate
police tear gas and marchers two abreast retreated, some falling to
the ground.
   On March 7, 1965, on the day remembered in civil rights annals
as Bloody Sunday, police used billy clubs and tear gas to turn back
hundreds of marchers on the bridge named for a Confederate general.
   ``Lord knows we're not where we ought to be, but thank God we're
not where we used to be,'' Williams said as he crossed the bridge.
``We've come a long way. But Lord knows we've got a much further
way to go.''
   The 50-mile march will continue in segments each day through the
week before culminating with a rally March 10 at the Alabama
Capitol. After crossing the bridge, most of the crowd turned back
to Selma, leaving several hundred to continue a short distanct
toward Montgomery before stopping for the night, police said.
   Jackson, speaking earlier Sunday from the First Baptist Church
pulpit to about 600 people, said Martin Luther King Jr. did not die
and Nelson Mandela did not languish in a South African prison for
27 years for blacks not to exercise their right to vote.
   ``You cannot walk around here with these unused blessings,''
Jackson said, adding that 35 percent of all blacks eligible to vote
are unregistered. ``God has given us all these votes. When you drop
them they become snakes and go to Washington and bite us.''
   Two weeks after the 1965 violence at the bridge stopped the
first march, King and other notables led a second march _
authorized by a federal judge and protected by thousands of federal
troops _ all the way to Montgomery. The events, including Ku Klux
Klan violence against the march, galvanized Congress to pass the
1965 Voting Rights Act.
   The law lowered voting barriers to blacks across the South and
eventually led to a sharp increase in the number of both black
voters and black officeholders. In Selma alone, the number of black
registered voters has climbed from about 600 in 1965 to 10,800 now.
Three of the five members of the Dallas County Commission are
black. Four of the nine members of the Selma City Council are black.
   ``We have another bridge to go across now, the racial bridge,
the bridge at Selma High,'' Jackson said.
   At the high school, about 150 black students staged a sit-in
last month that led to a weeklong, systemwide halt of classes while
other blacks intermittently occupied City Hall.
   The protests stemmed from the white-majority school board's
refusal to extend the contract of the 75 percent black system's
superintendent, Norward Roussell, the system's first black school
chief.
   Lewis, who was injured on Bloody Sunday, said the clash on the
bridge ``created a sense of righteous indignation'' across the
country and resulted in demonstrations in more than 80 cities.
   ``The movement created a climate for President Johnson and for
the Congress to say yes while many had a desire to say no,'' said
Lewis.
   Bloody Sunday helped make America ``a little more caring, a
little more sharing,'' said Lewis.
   The Johnson administration had focused itself on Vietnam and the
war on poverty until Bloody Sunday. After the clash, and the death
a few days later of James Reeb, a white Unitarian minister from
Boston who was hit in the head while on a Selma street, Johnson put
the passage of the Voting Rights Act on his priority list.
   Also killed after the march to Montgomery was Viola Liuzzo, a
white homemaker from Detroit shot by night-riding Ku Klux Klansmen
while she drove demonstrators back to Selma.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0058 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 2017EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--Pacific-Quake     03-04 0123</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Pacific-Quake,0128</SECOND>
<HEAD>Earthquake Rocks Uninhabited Region of South Pacific</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WELLINGTON, New Zealand (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An earthquake measuring 7.5 on
the Richter scale struck a remote, unihabited part of the South
Pacific, officials said Monday.
   There were no reports of damage or injuries.
   Dr. Warwick Smith, chief seismologist with the New Zealand
earthquake center, said the quake struck about 1 a.m. local time
Sunday (8 a.m. EST Saturday) and was centered between Fiji and New
Caledonia about 1,200 miles north of Wellington.
   The Richter scale is a gauge of the energy released by an
earthquake, as measured by the ground motion recorded on a
seismograph.
   A quake of magnitude 7 is considered a major earthquake, capable
of widespread, heavy damage in populated areas.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0059 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 2031EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Mexico-Allende     03-04 0198</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mexico-Allende,0203</SECOND>
<HEAD>Allende Widow Leaves Mexico For Chile</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MEXICO CITY (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The widow of former Chilean President
Salvador Allende on Sunday left Mexico, where she has lived in
exile for 16 years, to return to live in Chile, the Mexican news
agency said.
   Mrs. Hortensia Bussi de Allende left for Santiago after thanking
the Mexican government for giving her asylum and suporting
democracy in Chile, said the state-run news service Notimex. Mexico
broke diplomatic relations with Chile after the overthrow of
Allende's elected Marxist government.
   ``Now we need more than ever the support and the unity of the
Chilean people and international help for the democratic transition
to be successful,'' Mrs. Allende told Notimex at Mexico City's
international airport.
   ``Chileans want to live in peace, with justice, liberty and
dignity,'' she added.
   Mrs. Allende left Chile after the Sept. 1973 coup that brought
to power the military dictatorship of Augusto Pinochet. Allende
died of a gunshot wound during the overthrow.
   The Pinochet government is being replaced March 11 by the
elected presidency of Patricio Aylwin.
   Mrs. Allende, 75, has visited Chile several times since 1988,
when the government lifted a ban on the return of exiles.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0060 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 2101EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Japan-US     03-04 0599</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Japan-US,0619</SECOND>
<HEAD>Upbeat Summit Over, Kaifu Returns to Sobering Realities</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ELAINE KURTENBACH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Prime Minister Toshiki Kaifu left behind friendly
talks with President Bush and returned home Sunday to political
realities likely to dampen any post-summit euphoria.
   Japanese officials accompanying Kaifu said the summit in Palm
Springs, Calif. could fortify Kaifu's position as he tries to carry
out pledges of economic reform.
   After his warm welcome in California, however, Kaifu faces a
decidedly cooler reaction in Tokyo, where there is opposition to
trade-related economic reform both in his Liberal Democratic Party
and in the opposition-controlled upper house of Parliament.
   The summit, hastily arranged only a week in advance, had been
widely expected to put Kaifu in the unenviable position of having
to fend off criticism that Japan is dragging its feet in cutting
its $49 billion trade surplus with the United States.
   But during their talks Friday and Saturday, Kaifu and Bush
avoided detailed discussion of specific trade topics under
negotiation.
   Kaifu responded to Bush's request for substantive progress on
both the Structural Impediments Initiative _ talks aimed at
attacking the trade imbalance indirectly through economic reform _
and in other disputed trade areas with a pledge to ``Do my best.''
   ``I told the president I am asking for cooperation and
understanding from my people, from businesses,'' and from involved
government agencies, Kaifu told reporters in the United States.
   Among all three groups, Kaifu faces stubborn resistance to
change and a tradition of cautious, slow decision-making that will
hinder efforts to meet deadlines for progress on trade issues.
   Proposals include streamlining Japan's byzantine distribution
system with its many middlemen, hastening the opening of
price-competitive large stores, and strictly enforcing
anti-monopoly laws.
   Land-use reforms aimed at increasing space for much-needed
housing and at cutting exorbitant land prices could eventually hit
the real estate values underpinning much of Japan's enormous
financial wealth.
   ``The road is not smooth. We are dealing with things both
societies have tried to rectify for decades,'' acknowledged Yukio
Okamoto, director of the First North American Division of the
Foreign Ministry.
   Many Japanese government and business leaders said Sunday they
were happy with the results of the summit, and vowed to work hard
to settle economic conflicts with the United States.
   ``I think the summit was particulary meaningful because
President Bush was considering Japan as a global partner,'' said
Rokuro Ishikawa, president of the Japan Chamber of Commerce and
Industry.
   Yutaka Kume, president of Nissan Motor Co., Japan's second
largest automaker, said: ``It was very useful that the two leaders
discussed economic issues.''
   He added, ``But just consultations between the governments
aren't enough. After returning from the United States, I think the
Kaifu Cabinet must hear views at home, including those of business
circles.''
   Many analysts and officials believe Kaifu, a newcomer to inner
political circles, lacks the clout to build a consensus to back
such extensive reforms.
   Kaifu, 59, belongs to the governing Liberal Democrats' weakest
faction. Despite his party's victory in a Feb. 18 lower house
parliamentary election, he remains heavily dependent on the support
of more powerful party leaders.
   The new prime minister came to power in August to try to restore
the battered image of his party. Prime Minister Noboru Takeshita
resigned last spring to take responsibility for a bribery scandal.
He was replaced by Sousuke Uno, who resigned two months later after
an election defeat in Parliament's upper house.
   Kaifu also must deal with an upper house dominated by a
coalition led by the Japan Socialist Party, which has adopted a
protectionist stance in recent elections.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0061 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 2103EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-EasternStrike 1stLd-Writethru a0753 03-04 0661</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Eastern Strike, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0753,0675</SECOND>
<HEAD>Machinists Rally One Year Later</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 17th graf, `George...the strikers,' to CORRECT spelling
to Kourpias sted Karkis.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By DAN SEWELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hundreds of Machinists union members, their
relatives and other supporters chanted ``one day longer'' Sunday
outside Eastern Airlines headquarters as they marked the first
anniversary of their strike.
   ``The enthusiasm and determination and spirit of the real
Eastern employees has not wavered one bit,'' Charles E. Bryan,
president of Machinists District 100, told the rally. ``It's become
a cause for justice.''
   Hundreds more strikers and supporters rallied at LaGuardia
Airport in New York and other cities with large Eastern union
memberships. Strikers rallied Saturday at Atlanta.
   Most in the Miami crowd, estimated by police at from 500 to more
than 2,000 strong, wore bright red union T-shirts in the rally next
to the union local hall, across the street from Eastern's corporate
headquarters. Police guarded the company buildings, some splattered
red and yellow by paint bombs and some with broken windows.
   The strikers then went to Miami International Airport to march
through the Eastern terminal.
   The strikers' chant ``one day longer'' meant they would endure
one day longer than Texas Air Corp. Chairman Frank Lorenzo, whose
company bought Eastern four years ago and who is the focus of the
bitter strike.
   ``We're making a statement. It's to show people we're still
around,'' said Jim Bertram, a former Eastern flight simulator
technician.
   He and most other Eastern Machinists members, mechanics and
other maintenance ground services workers, have gone on to other
jobs, in most cases for less pay. Though there seems to be no
serious hope for settlement of the strike, the Machinists said they
are showing they won't give in to what they call Lorenzo's
union-busting and his dismantling of Eastern.
   ``I think basically the accomplishment of the strike is a
philosophical, idealistic one,'' said Elaine Segura, a 20-year
Eastern clerk who struck with her husband, Paul, a 23-year
mechanic. ``These people who have suffered for a year still have
the enthusiasm and perserverance. The answer to Lorenzo is still
no.''
   The strike, which came after 1{ years of federal mediation over
a contract calling for wage and work-rule concessions, virtually
shut down Eastern at first when pilots and flight attendants joined
the nearly 9,000 Machinists.
   Eastern filed for Chapter 11 bankruptcy reorganization five days
later and began hiring new workers while trying to rebuild as a
smaller carrier. Today, Eastern has 18,000 employees, compared to
more than 30,000 before the strike, and 800 daily flights, compared
to nearly 1,100 when the strike began.
   The carrier has been losing $2 million a day as it struggles to
emerge from bankruptcy protection. The pilots and flight attendants
ended their sympathy strikes three months ago, but Eastern has
taken only a few back, saying it has no openings.
   The company didn't observe the anniversary, spokesman Robin
Matell said.
   ``The bottom line is a year later, there are no winners, only
losers,'' Matell said. ``There were an awful lot of people who got
hurt.
   ``At least we were able to preserve 18,000 jobs ... to build a
new airline from scratch.''
   Machinists officials continue to hope for a buyout of Lorenzo,
although a series of prospective buyers has backed away in the past
year. Bryan told the crowd that Chicago options trader Joseph
Ritchie remains interested in buying Eastern, and was encouraged by
a bankruptcy examiner's study of Texas Air's Eastern transactions
that resulted in Texas Air's agreement to pay $280 million to
Eastern.
   George Kourpias, the Machinists' union international president,
told the rally the union would continue fighting Texas Air in court
while keeping up food donations and other help to the strikers.
   Bryan urged his members to take heart from the overthrows of
dictators in Eastern Europe.
   ``When you look around, all you've got left is Castro and
Lorenzo,'' Bryan said to cheers, referring to Cuba's Communist
leader.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0062 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 2123EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-MissUSAComplaints     03-04 0303</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Miss USA Complaints,0310</SECOND>
<HEAD>Outgoing Miss USA Says She Was Overworked, Hasn't Received Prizes</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WICHITA, Kan. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   One day after her successor was crowned,
Miss USA 1989 complained she hadn't received all her prizes, was
required to work 12-hour days during her reign and was refused
permission to visit her sick grandmother.
   Last year's winner, Gretchen Polhemus, said she considered
quitting at one point, and advised the new Miss USA to get legal
help before she signs a contract.
   ``I told her to get an attorney. There's a lot of things in that
contract that are unclear,'' Miss Polhemus said.
   Miss Polhemus told The Wichita Eagle in an interview published
Sunday that she threatened to boycott Friday's telecast of the
pageant finals in Wichita unless she received the remaining $5,000
worth of prizes.
   She said she wasn't allowed any sick leave although she worked
12 hours a day, a schedule two or three times more demanding than
promised by pageant officials.
   Miss Polhemus said she wasn't allowed to visit her grandmother
in Arlington, Texas, as preparations were underway for the pageant.
   ``I just wanted to tell her I love her,'' said Miss Polhemus.
The grandmother has suffered three strokes, she said.
   Pageant spokeswoman Sara Meza said she didn't realize the
grandmother was that sick.
   Ms. Meza said Miss Polhemus would have received the rest of the
prizes _ $1,300 in wardrobe expense money, $3,000 worth of airline
tickets and some camera equipment _ even without the new agreement.
They will be delivered in two weeks, she said, adding that pageant
officials renegotiated Miss Polhemus' contract to give her more
days off after she complained.
   At a news conference Saturday, this year's Miss USA, Carole
Gist, 20, of Detroit, said she hadn't signed a contract yet and
hadn't talked to Miss Polhemus.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0063 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 2125EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Uruguay-Duel     03-04 0357</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Uruguay-Duel,0368</SECOND>
<HEAD>Police Official Calls Off Duel, Says Opponent Not Worthy</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MONTEVIDEO, Uruguay (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A police official on Sunday withdrew
his highly publicized challenge to a duel, saying the newspaper
publisher he accused of besmirching his reputation was not a worthy
opponent.
   Saul Claveria, deputy police chief in San Jose Province, said
the publisher became ineligible to duel when he announced last week
he would show up at the planned confrontation, but not actually
fight.
   ``He who refuses to take up arms will not fight, and his
adversary would be a vulgar assassin and would lose the condition
of honorable duelist,'' said Claveria through his attorney, Ariosto
Fernandez.
   He is ``not worthy of the gentlemanly pursuit,'' Fernandez said.
   The publisher, Federico Fasano, was advised of Claveria's
decision Sunday and said the matter ``has ended.''
   Fasano is director of the small leftist daily La Republica in
Montevideo. Claveria challenged Fasano to a duel, permitted by law
in Uruguay, in a disagreement over a story in La Republica.
   The Jan. 24 investigative story on the smuggling of consumer
merchandise reported that two cars involved in distributing
contraband were registered to Claveria.
   Claveria said the cars had belonged to the police department,
and that he had only signed legal papers connected to their sale
months ago. The vehicles apparently now belong to a car rental
agency.
   Fasano claimed his reporters worked ``correctly and ethically''
in writing the smuggling story.
   Claveria challenged Fasano to a duel, and the challenge received
heavy media coverage, both in Fasano's paper and others.
   Claveria retired from the Montevideo police department after
reaching the post of inspector, one of the highest, and accepted a
new post in San Jose, 30 miles east of the capital.
   Dueling in this small South American nation is regulated by a
1939 law that requires seconds, or colleagues of the two men in a
dispute, to try to reach a solution. Failing that, they must
designate a three-member tribunal to arrange a duel site,
witnesses, doctors and other details.
   If a participant is killed in an encounter that meets all the
rules, the other duelist is exempt from punishment.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0064 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 2128EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-SpaceShuttle 6thLd-Writethru a0757 03-04 0815</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Space Shuttle, 6th Ld - Writethru, a0757,0831</SECOND>
<HEAD>Shuttle Atlantis Returns from Military Mission</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 3 grafs for 10th graf pvs, `As 40 mpg...on Saturday,' to
UPDATE with astronauts arriving in Houston, minor damage to
shuttle's heat-shield tiles found. Pick up 11th graf pvs, `Atlantis
returned...</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos EAB1, EAB3, EAB5</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LEE SIEGEL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>EDWARDS AIR FORCE BASE, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Space shuttl Atlantis
landed safely on a California desert runway Sunday, completing a
secret military mission that included the launch of a $500 million
spy satellite.
   ``Congratulations on a great flight, guys, and welcome back,''
Mission Control communicator Steve Oswald said.
   Atlantis, carrying a crew of five military men, plunged through
the Earth's atmosphere in a long fiery dive, flashed over the
California coastline north of Los Angeles and touched down at
Edwards Air Force base at 10:08 a.m. PST.
   With mission commander John O. Creighton at the controls,
Atlantis landed smoothly on a dry lakebed runway. It rolled to a
stop a minute and 15 seconds later on the center line, ending a
4{-day mission.
   Fifty-one minutes after the landing, the astronauts stepped out
of the shuttle into brilliant Mojave Desert sunshine, shook hands
with NASA officials and posed for NASA photographers. A flight
surgeon examined them briefly before they disembarked.
   ``You can probably tell by the smiles on our faces we had a
great time,'' Creighton, a Navy captain, told a crowd of 100 NASA
workers and friends, going on to refer to the many delays before
takeoff. ``It was terrific flight when we finally got off the
ground. I think we accomplished something that was important for
the country.
   ``We had a good time doing it. The space shuttle performed
superbly. And that's a tribute to all the hard work that a lot of
you out there helped put in to make the Challenger the ship that it
is and will continue to be,'' Creighton said, in an apparent
mistaken reference to the shuttle Challenger which blew up after
liftoff Jan. 28, 1986, killing all seven crew members.
   The shuttle pilot, Air Force Col. John Casper, added: ``As one
of the rookies on board, I just say, `Wow! What a fantastic
experience.'''
   Creighton, Casper and the other crew members, Air Force Col.
Richard Mullane, Marine Lt. Col. David Hilmers and Navy Lt. Cmdr.
Pierre Thuot, then boarded two jets for the flight back home to
Houston.
   They arrived Ellington Field, an Air Force base in Houston,
about 7:45 p.m. CST.
   As 40 mph winds kicked up dust, NASA crews towed Atlantis off
the unpaved dry lakebed landing strip to prepare it for a piggyback
jet ride to Kennedy Space Center, Fla., on Saturday.
   NASA spokeswoman Lise Malone said a preliminary inspection
showed about 62 of Atlantis' heat-shield tiles suffered ``dings,''
but that the count likely would change Monday.
   Atlantis returned to Earth as a weather front packing high wind
moved toward Edwards Air Force Base, threatening unacceptable
conditions for the touchdown.
   But by landing time the wind had dropped to an acceptable level
of 21 mph with gusts to 25. The temperature was 62 degrees.
   The shuttle's characteristic twin sonic booms reverberated over
the desert as the spacecraft approached. However, unlike most
previous missions, police across a wide area of Southern California
said they received no reports that the booms were heard elsewhere,
indicating that the shuttle took an unusual path toward Edwards.
   While the shuttle was descending from orbit, it experienced a
pressure dip in a hydraulic system that controls flaps and
steering. The astronauts switched to backup systems. Later, Mission
Control said pressure was restored in the primary system.
   The next shuttle flight is scheduled for April 12 when Discovery
is to begin a five-day mission to deploy the $1.55 billion Hubble
Space Telescope.
   A Pentagon-imposed blackout blocked public announcement of the
mission activities, and because of the secret nature of the
mission, the landing was closed to public spectators. A few hundred
invited guests, however, watched as the shuttle landed.
   Atlantis was launched Wednesday from Kennedy Space Center in
Florida after five delays, four caused by weather.
   NASA sources, who spoke on agreement of anonymity, said the
Atlantis astronauts deployed the spy satellite Thursday. The
satellite, sources said, is capable of taking high resolution
photographs and listening in on electronic communications all over
the world.
   Atlantis was launched on a path that carries it over points on
Earth farther north and south than any previous space shuttle. This
enabled the astronauts to place the satellite in an orbit that will
cover parts of the Soviet Union never before photographed by a
shuttle-launched spy satellite.
   A network of amateur observers, which includes posts in Canada,
Alaska and Scotland, reported Saturday they had sighted Atlantis
and a satellite in separate oribts.
   Atlantis' flight was the 34th shuttle mission and the sixth
dedicated solely to the military.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0065 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 2144EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-SovietJews     03-04 0361</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet Jews,0373</SECOND>
<HEAD>Jewish Groups Criticize Soviets and Secretary Baker</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Politicians and leaders of American Jewish
groups criticized both the Soviet and U.S. governments Sunday in a
plea for the ``immediate evacuation'' of Jews who want to leave the
Soviet Union.
   ``The growth of anti-Semitism in the Soviet Union makes it more
urgent than ever that the United States not throw roadblocks in the
way of migration from the Soviet Union,'' said U.S. Rep. Bill
Green, R-N.Y., at a news conference sponsored by the Zionist
Organization of America.
   Secretary of State James A. Baker III suggested in Washington
last week that U.S. aid to Israel for housing of Soviet Jewish
immigrants be linked to assurances that new settlements won't be
built in the occupied territories.
   Green called the proposal ``offensive.''
   ``Does the United States really take the position there are
areas in the world in which no Jews should be allowed to live?'' he
said.
   Israel maintains it doesn't have a policy of settling Jewish
immigrants in the occupied territories and says that of 12,000
Soviet Jews who came to Israel last year, only 200 have settled in
the West Bank or Gaza Strip.
   Although much of the government-sponsored anti-Semitism has
disappeared in the five years of Mikhail Gorbachev's rule, his
reforms also have unleashed grassroots anti-Semitism in the Soviet
Union.
   Alexander Matlin, vice president of the American Association of
Russian Jews, said his group has received thousands of telephone
calls, letters and eyewitness reports of threats and attacks
against Jews.
   ``Today most Jews are leaving the Soviet Union, not for
political or religious freedom, but simply out of fear,'' he said.
   He and other speakers called on the Soviet Union to honor a
December agreement to allow direct flights to Israel to allow for
more emigration.
   The Soviets, facing strong protests from the Arab world over the
influx to Israel, have so far refused.
   Rep. Ted Weiss, D-N.Y., said Gorbachev should take steps to stop
rising anti-Semitism if he wants U.S.-Soviet relations to continue
to improve.
   ``It would be a mistake to allow a situation to fester which
would make relations worse,'' Weiss said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0066 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 2205EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-GreyhoundStrike 2ndLd-Writethru a0766 03-04 0880</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Greyhound Strike, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0766,0903</SECOND>
<HEAD>Some Strikers Suspend Picketing To Mourn Death</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 6th graf, `Union President...just 95,' to UPDATE with
company saying 350 drivers crossed picket lines; INSERTS 1 graf
after 21st graf, `I was...said White,' to UPDATE with bus sabotage
in Spokane; ADDS 3 grafs at end with details of contract dispute.
No pickup. </NOTE>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Some striking Greyhound Lines Inc. workers stayed off the picket
line Sunday in memory of co-worker killed while picketing, and a
federal official said fewer small companies than expected had
applied to temporarily take Greyhound routes.
   Glenn Eady, regional compliance officer for the U.S. Interstate
Commerce Commission in Philadelphia, said an ICC board approved
four temporary applications Saturday for bus companies in the
eastern region. The region includes 23 states from Maine to
Florida, but none of the companies serves points south of Virginia,
he said.
   ``The response is not what we expected,'' Eady said Sunday.
   ICC offices in Chicago and San Francisco also stayed open during
the weekend to handle applications.
   When the strike by the Amalgamated Council of Greyhound Local
Unions began Friday, it initially stranded thousands of passengers.
But the company brought in temporary drivers and Greyhound Chairman
Fred G. Currey claimed the company kept 25 percent of its routes
running, with the help of some union drivers crossing picket lines.
   The company contends 350 union drivers have crossed picket lines
to work, but Union President Edward M. Strait said Sunday that a
careful count by strikers turned up just 95.
   ``We ... hope that Greyhound management will soon realize that
the only way they will be able to provide the traveling public with
safe and affordable intercity bus transportation is by returning to
the negotiationg table for good-faith bargaining on a fair and
equitable contract,'' Strait said.
   The union, which represents more than 9,000 employees, went on
strike after negotiators in Scottsdale, Ariz., failed to reach
agreement on wage issues. The strikers include the company's 6,300
drivers.
   On Sunday, some strikers in Washington state stayed off the
picket lines in honor of Robert Waterhouse, 59, a union member who
was killed on a picket line Saturday in Redding, Calif. Waterhouse
was crushed against a building by a bus driven by a driver hired as
a temporary replacement.
   Greyhound's Currey said he was told the driver was trying to
maneuver around a pickup truck driven by a striker.
   The replacement driver, Theodore Graham, left the scene. He told
investigators later that he hadn't realized he hit anyone,
according to a statement released Sunday by the Redding Police
Department.
   Pickets trying to slow the bus yelled at the driver and hit the
bus with their signs as it pulled away from the terminal, and the
bus had a minor crash with a striker's pickup truck on the way out,
police said. He later flagged down a Highway Patrol car to report
the minor crash, and was taken in for questioning about the
striker's death, police said.
   No charges were filed, and police referred the case to the
District Attorney for a final determination.
   ``We don't believe that he intentionally ran over this person,''
Redding police investigator John Severson said Saturday.
   The victim was preparing to retire this year, said his wife,
Dorie Waterhouse.
   ``It really wasn't even his strike,'' Mrs. Waterhouse said.
``But he was in there in support of his fellow drivers. He kept
saying, ``It's a matter of self pride.''
   Striking drivers in Olympia, Wash., said they would cancel
picketing Sunday to observe a day of mourning for Waterhouse.
   In addition to the death, there have been a few violent
incidents, including shots fired at a bus in Chicago on Friday.
   In Philadelphia, police said a Greyhound passenger awaited
arraignment Sunday on a charge of simple assault for allegedly
spraying a striker with a pocket tear gas canister. Officer Al
Tenuto said the passenger got in an argument with a striking driver
after getting off a bus.
   In Jacksonville, Fla., a striking Greyhound driver was struck by
a bus Saturday, but was uninjured. The driver, Donald D. White, a
27-year Greyhound veteran, told police the slow-moving bus didn't
stop as he walked across the street.
   ``I was more mad that hurt,'' said White.
   In Spokane, Wash., charter drivers found panels torn open and
electrical wires cut when they went to start their buses Sunday
morning, said Greyhound's area manager, Mike Ford. They were unable
to start the buses, which weren't intended for use on scheduled
Greyhound runs.
   Currey said the company had asked federal courts in five cities
to issue restraining orders against strike's violence.
   Currey led an investment group that paid $270 million for
Greyhound in 1987, then bought Trailways Lines Inc. four months
later for $80 million.
   Before that buyout, the drivers union agreed to a 22 percent
wage cut, but Currey said Greyhound drivers remain the highest paid
in the industry.
   No negotiations were scheduled in the dispute.
   The union contends the company hasn't moved substantially from a
Jan. 10 proposal that was turned down by almost 92 percent of its
membership.
   However Currey said Saturday the company had made two
substantial concessions: agreeing to scrap a proposal for incentive
pay and to ban subcontracting or franchising of routes.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0067 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 2225EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Rooney-CBS 2ndLd-Writethru a0779 03-04 0701</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Rooney-CBS, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0779,0720</SECOND>
<HEAD>Andy Rooney Returns to 60 Minutes</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS grafs 11-13, `Craig Davidson...broadcast,' to CLARIFY
that director of gay and lesbian group was referring to Rooney's
remarks on show Sunday. Pick up 14th graf pvs,`Roy Brunett...'
Brunett is cq.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY18</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Andy Rooney returned Sunday to ``60 Minutes''
after a three-week suspension, saying he was worried he'd be
wrongly remembered as a racist for remarks he says he didn't make.
   Rooney was suspended by CBS without pay Feb. 8 but reinstated
three weeks later.
   Back at his usual show-ending slot, Rooney said it was demeaning
to defend himself because he had a long history of supporting civil
rights. He said he didn't know how to apologize to homosexuals for
a comment he made last year that he hadn't realized would be
offensive.
   Staying at home made him worry about his legacy, he said.
   ``I'd be known for the rest of my life as a racist bigot and as
someone who had made life a little more difficult for homosexuals.
I felt terrible and I've learned a lot,'' the 71-year-old Rooney
said.
   ``What do I say to defend myself? Do I say, `I'm not a racist.'
That sounds like saying, `I'm not a crook.'
   ``How do I apologize to homosexuals for hurting them with a
remark I made that I didn't realize would hurt them?''
   CBS News president David Burke suspended Rooney after The
Advocate, a gay magazine, quoted him as saying that blacks had
``watered down their genes'' because the least intelligent among
them had the most children. Burke never publicly gave a reason for
the suspension.
   Rooney has denied making the remark.
   At the time of the interview, Rooney was being criticized by
homosexuals for his CBS special on Dec. 26 in which he cited
``homosexual unions'' among a list of things that cause
``self-induced'' death. He also drew criticism for a letter to The
Advocate in which he said he found male homosexual acts
``repugnant.''
   The National Association For The Advancement of Colored People
last week said it was satisfied that the remarks attributed to
Rooney were distorted, and didn't reflect his views. The group
declined to comment on Sunday's broadcast.
   Craig Davidson, executive director of the Gay and Lesbian
Alliance Against Defamation, applauded Rooney's comments on the
show Sunday.
   ``Mr. Rooney's anecdotal remarks contain an acknowledgement that
his statements about gay people were unfair and harmful,'' Davidson
said. ``That is what GLAAD has sought all along and we welcome it.''
   Roy Brunett, a spokesman for CBS News, said the network would
not know how many calls it received about the broadcast until
Monday.
   Burke last week reinstated Rooney, whose wry commentary had
ended most each ``60 Minutes'' broadcasts since 1978.
   Rooney began his commentary by reciting a portion of a poem he
remembered from high school in which the writer laments the loss of
his true love. Not working for three weeks since his suspension, he
said, was like losing his true love.
   In his typical biting style, he reiterated that he has opinions
that will continue to upset some people. ``That's what I'm here
for,'' he said, while also questioning why he had become embroiled
in controversy.
   ``In 1970, I wrote the show called `Harry and Lena' for Harry
Belafonte and Lena Horne. I like Lena better than Harry. Does that
make me a feminist?''
   On Sunday, Rooney cited several examples which he said showed he
wasn't racist, including the night he threw out a house guest for
using the word ``nigger.''
   ``I'd feel the same today if anyone used an insulting word about
homosexuals,'' he said.
   Rooney said he was overwhelmed by the calls and letters of
support he had received following his suspension.
   ``What do I do about the kind words heaped on me by friends and
strangers? ... How do I live up to such praise? Let's face it, even
on the nights when I'm good, I'm not that good.''
   During his absence, the program, while still high in the
ratings, dropped in the standings to 18th place last Sunday when it
was beaten by a special rerun of ABC's hit ``America's Funniest
Home Videos.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0068 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 2237EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Bulgaria 1stLd-Writethru a0718 03-04 0580</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bulgaria, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0718,0596</SECOND>
<HEAD>Turks, Moslems Hold Vigil for Restoration of Names</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 13 grafs to UPDATE with protesters ignoring plea
to move, details. Pick up 10th graf pvs, `Demonstrators told...'</NOTE>
<HEAD>With AM-Soviet-Unrest, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROLAND PRINZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SOFIA, Bulgaria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Thousands of ethnic Turks and Bulgarian
Moslems gathered Sunday to press for legislation restoring the
names they were forced to change in a sometimes violent
assimilation drive.
   Participants also threatened a general strike in areas populated
by Bulgaria's 1.5 million Moslems to back demands for a swift
change of names.
   Later in the day, thousands of demonstrators ignored pleas from
ethnic leaders to move from the downtown area. A government
spokesman demanded that the protesters go home.
   The vigil around the Alexander Nevski Cathedral and nearby
Parliament building came on the eve of a parliamentary session
expected to enact a law giving Moslems some rights to their
original names.
   Protesters criticized the draft law, saying it contained
legalistic and bureaucratic hurdles that would slow the procedure.
   In a campaign marked by violence, ethnic Turks were forced under
Communist leader Todor Zhivkov to change their first names and
family names to Bulgarian-sounding ones. They also were prohibited
from speaking their mother tongue or practicing the Moslem religion.
   Last year, about 320,000 Turks immigrated to neighboring Turkey,
when Zhivkov permitted them to get passports. More than half have
since returned.
   After Zhivkov's ouster in November, the new leaders blamed him
for the assimilation drive and in January decided to allow the
Turks to reclaim their former names and gave them greater religious
freedom.
   But no legislation to that effect has been adopted.
   Buses from around Bulgaria Sunday brought protesters to the
capital.
   Ahmed Doan, an ethnic Turkish leader, later urged the protesters
through a police megaphone to leave the square near the Parliament
building and go to a park in the southern part of the city. ``All
our demands are accepted at this stage,'' he told the crowd. ``If
you stay here we are going to hamper adoption of our demands.''
   Fearing counter-demonstrations, Doan and two other Turkish
activists also appealed to demonstrators on state television to
``avoid further tension.''
   Interior Ministry spokesman Yordan Ormankov, also in a televised
statement, condemned groups who ``exert pressure on Parliament''
and told demonstrators to go home. However, as night fell, about
2,000 demonstrators were still gathered at the cathedral.
   Demonstrators told reporters they were angered by reports that
under the proposed new law, Moslems still would have to have
surnames with the Bulgarian endings ``ev'' or ``ov,'' and would
have to request the name change in a lengthy court procedure.
   ``We Want Our Names,'' and ``No Name Change In Court,'' read
placards held by demonstrators, who said they would not leave until
their demands were met.
   ``If we have to go to court to get our names back we would have
to wait at least 20 years,'' shouted a woman from Velingrad, in the
Rhodope Mountains.
   A factory worker in his late 50s said, ``We will stay put. We
have left our homes and factories, and tomorrow all the Moslems
will start a general strike.''
   Doan, who heads the nationwide Movement for Rights and Freedom,
said he received assurances from government leaders the
controversial legislation would be scrapped.
   He said that in a meeting Friday, President Petar Mladenov,
Premier Andrei Lukanov and National Assembly Chairman Stanko
Todorov ``guaranteed there will be short procedures'' under the new
law.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0069 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 2306EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Bush 1stLd-Writethru a0727 03-04 0571</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bush, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0727,520</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush Hails Annenberg's $50 Million Gift to United Negro College
Fund</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: SUBS 2nd graf to CORRECT that Annenberg's father founded
publishing empire and DELETE reference to Reader's Digest</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By TERENCE HUNT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP White House Correspondent</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>RANCHO MIRAGE, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush saluted publishing
tycoon Walter Annenberg on Sunday for setting a ``significant and
marvelous example'' by donating $50 million to the United Negro
College Fund, the largest gift ever for black colleges.
   Annenberg, the 82-year-old former ambassador to Britain whose
father founded a publishing empire that once included TV Guide and
The Philadelphia Inquirer, said wealthy people have an obligation
to help the less fortunate.
   Moreover, Annenberg said, ``It is psychologically important that
blacks indicate to the rest of the population in the country that
they have the capability to teach and serve.''
   The gift was formally announced at a ceremony on the golf course
of Annenberg's estate, a 205-acre desert oasis of manicured lawns,
duck ponds and sculpted shrubs set against snowcapped mountains.
   Bush, the guest of the Annenbergs for two nights, played golf on
his host's course after the ceremony. Then he was returning to
Washington following a four-day trip of politicking, anti-drug
speeches and a summit meeting with Japanese Prime Minister Toshiki
Kaifu.
   Bush said he was very pleased with the summit. ``I like the feel
of it afterwards,'' the president said.
   At the talks, which concluded Saturday, Kaifu said he was
``determined to firmly tackle'' trade obstacles in Japan, which
have fueled tensions between Tokyo and Washington.
   Bush, announcing the gift to the United Negro College Fund,
said, ``I'm delighted to know that my good friend, Walter
Annenberg, has set such a significant and marvelous example with
this gift to this excellent cause.''
   Bush, a supporter of the fund since his senior year at Yale
University 42 years ago, said he was inspired by Annenberg's
generosity, ``exemplifying the very best of what I call the
thousand points of light'' _ a reference to public service and
volunteerism.
   ``I'm indeed delighted to have an opportunity to participate in
this very significant role of support for underprivileged human
beings,'' Annenberg said.
   Discussing his gift at a news conference, Annenberg said, ``If
one segment of the population is behind other segments of the
population, you obviously have a very unwholesome citizenry in the
country.''
   Annenberg, dressed in a kelly-green jacket and lime-green
slacks, said it was ``obligatory that young blacks have a fair
opportunity so as to get into the mainstream of economic affairs of
the country.''
   When a reporter asked Annenberg to explain his remark about
blacks needing to demonstrate that they have capacity to teach and
serve, the questioning was cut off by Christopher E. Edley,
president and chief executive officer of the United Negro College
Fund.
   Edley stepped in front of cameras, saying ``We've limited the
questions.''
   Previously, the largest gift for black education was $20 million
from comedian Bill Cosby in 1987 to Spelman College in Atlanta. The
United Negro College Fund, a consortium of 41 private black
colleges, raised $45.8 million last year for distribution to its
member institutions.
   Bush and his wife, Barbara, also attended a private mass at 7
a.m. at St. Margaret's Episcopal Church.
   A White House spokesman, Jay Allison, said Bush's plans to
attend the regular 8 a.m. service were changed after a local
newspaper identified the church where the president would go.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0070 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 2310EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-MarathonDeath     03-04 0175</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Marathon Death,0180</SECOND>
<HEAD>Runner in Los Angeles Marathon Suffers Fatal Heart Attack on
Course</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A runner in the Los Angeles Marathon died
after he suffered a heart attack near the end of the course,
officials said.
   William McKinney, 59, of the Los Angeles suburb Altadena
collapsed near the 21-mile mark of the 26.2-mile course at about
1:39 a.m. and died an hour later at Midway Hospital, said race
spokesman Bruce Dworshak.
   McKinney had been under a doctor's care for hypertension,
marathon President Dr. William Burke said.
   Paramedics reported that they spotted McKinney running
comfortably at 1:30 p.m., nearly five hours after the marathon
started. McKinney was found in full cardiac arrest nine minutes
later, and paramedics were unable to revive him.
   Marathon officials said it was the first death in the five-year
history of the event, which this year had 18,918 runners.
   Pedro Ortiz of Colombia won the race in 2 hours, 11 minutes, 54
seconds.
   Julie Isphording of Cincinnati was the women's winner, setting a
women's record of 2:32:25.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0071 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 2312EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-FlyingWallendas     03-04 0345</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Flying Wallendas,0357</SECOND>
<HEAD>Legendary Acrobat Family Turns In Final Performance Together</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MANSFIELD, Pa. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Angel Wallenda said goodbye to the
tightwire Sunday night, joining her husband and 3-year-old son for
one last performance before an operation she hopes will arrest the
cancer that claimed her leg.
   Steven Wallenda joined his wife and their precocious toddler
Steven II to the tune of ``Angel of the Morning'' on the tightwire
that has brought the family fame for decades.
   ``You have to overcome a certain fear,'' Mrs. Wallenda, 21, said
after the performance in Mansfield, where the family lives. ``And
I've done that with both the wire and the cancer.''
   In 1987, Mrs. Wallenda was diagnosed with bone cancer, and
doctors were forced to amputate her right leg and fit her with a
prosthesis.
   The cancer spread to her lungs, and she is scheduled to undergo
further surgery March 20 at City of Hope National Medical Center in
Duarte, Calif.
   ``I'm glad I got to do it,'' she said of Sunday's performance.
   This month's surgery will end her career as an aerialist. Her
husband said he and their son will continue the performing
tradition.
   Ticket sales for the performance, which draw about 1,000 people
to Mansfield University, raised more than $3,500 for her medical
bills, supplemented by some $4,500 from a local Vietnam veterans'
group. Steven Wallenda is a veteran of that war.
   Shaky at first Sunday night, Mrs. Wallenda steadied during the
latter part of her walk across the 30-foot steel rope, followed
closely by her husband. A later act featured Steven II in a harness
riding on his father's shoulders.
   Wallenda traces his family's tightwire heritage to the 1600s.
The most famous of the Wallenda acrobats, ``Karl the Great,'' died
after a 1978 fall during a performance in Puerto Rico.
   Steven Wallenda II is the last male performer born with the
Wallenda name and one of the few direct descendants of the original
acrobats.
   The elder Wallenda said he hoped Steven II would follow in his
careful footsteps, but, ``It's up to him.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0072 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 2300EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Hostages 4thLd-Writethru a0784 03-04 0830</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Hostages, 4th Ld-Writethru, a0784,0854</SECOND>
<HEAD>Source Reports Iranian-Syrian Talks on Hostages</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: SUBS 3 grafs for grafs 4-5 to move up U.S. reax, ADD more of
Independent report. Pick up 6th pvs, `The source...' New grafs
20-27 with details.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By LOUIS FARES</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DAMASCUS, Syria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A senior Iranian envoy met Sunday with
Syria's foreign minister and discussed efforts to free Western
hostages held in Lebanon, an informed source said.
   The Syrian source, who refused to be identified further, said
the meeting between Mahmoud Hashemi of Iran and Farouk al-Sharaa of
Syria ``appears to be to coordinate efforts between the governments
of Syria and Iran to gain the release of all the hostages'' held by
pro-Iranian Shiite Moslem militants in Lebanon.
   Syria, Iran's main Arab ally, has been instrumental in helping
release Western hostages in the past. It has 40,000 troops deployed
in much of Lebanon.
   Joe Reap, a State Department spokesman, said of the sources'
reports on the hostages, ``This is the first I've heard of the
latest rumors.''
   Also Sunday, Vice President Dan Quayle denied reports in a
British newspaper that talks have taken place between Iranian
officials and former U.S. government officials, including former
Secretary of State Cyrus Vance, on the release of the hostages.
   The Syrian source said Hashemi, the brother of Iranian President
Hashemi Rafsanjani, delivered ``a very cordial message'' to Sharaa
from Iranian Foreign Minister Ali Akbar Velayati, including an
invitation for him to visit Tehran to meet with Rafsanjani and
Iran's spiritual leader, Ayatollah Ali Khamenei.
   The source gave no other details of Hashemi's trip to Lebanon or
the one-hour meeting with Sharaa.
   But another source noted: ``This appears to be a serious effort,
the first in some time, to end the hostage ordeal ... But I don't
think we'll see anyone out tomorrow.
   ``Nobody can be precise about how long the process will take.
There appears to be a genuine desire by the Iranian President to
end this ordeal. But there are still difficulties,'' said the
source.
   Earlier, the official Syrian Arab News Agency reported that
Hashemi's talks with Sharaa, attended by Iranian Ambassador Hasan
Akhtari, centered on ``bilateral relations and issues of common
interest.''
   Hashemi is director of the Tehran Foreign Ministry's Third
Department, which handles Iran's relations with Syria, Lebanon and
some other Arab states.
   He is a former senior Iranian diplomat in Damascus and former
ambassador to Belgium.
   Rafsanjani, elected president last July, has often used him as
his personal emissary on sensitive missions abroad.
   Sharaa told Peggy Say, sister of American hostage Terry
Anderson, in Damascus last month that he planned to raise the issue
of Iranian help to free the Western captives held in Lebanon next
time he visited Tehran.
   Anderson, chief Middle East correspondent for The Associated
Press, is the longest-held of the 18 Western hostages in Lebanon.
He was kidnapped March 16, 1985.
   Most of the hostages, who include eight Americans, are believed
held by Shiite Moslem groups loyal to Iran.
   In addition to the Americans, there are four Britons, two Swiss,
two West Germans, an Italian and an Irishman held hostage.
   The latest report follows a spate of statements from Iranian
newspapers and officials in recent days saying the hostages should
be released because they are fueling propaganda against Iran.
   A London newspaper reported Sunday that a delegation of Iranian
officials had arrived in Beirut on a mission to free one or more of
the hostages.The Independent on Sunday said its information came
from unidentified Lebanese and Iranian exiles in London and Paris.
   The Independent also reported that talks had taken place in
Muscat, Oman, Ankara, Turkey and Geneva between Iranian officials
and former U.S. government officials, including Vance, on the
hostages.
   Quayle said on CBS's ``Face the Nation'' that the Bush
administration is ``not using anyone to sit down and to negotiate
on a quid pro quo basis with Iran'' regarding release of the
hostages.
   Asked about Vance, who was secretary of state under President
Jimmy Carter, Quayle said: ``We are not using Cyrus Vance to
negotiate for the release of the hostages.''
   ``And I'm not going to say anything that is going to get
expectations up once again. We've been through that so many times,
and I'm just saying once and for all the president obviously wants
them out. He thinks that they should be released,'' Quayle said.
   The Independent said the Iranian team sent to Beirut was
dispatched by Rafsanjani, one of the so-called pragmatists in Iran
who want to repair damaged relations with the West.
   But Rafsanjani is opposed in the Iranian leadership by
anti-Western radicals led by former Interior Minister Ali Akbar
Mohtashemi, and that rift is mirrored in the pro-Iranian group
Hezbollah, believed to be the umbrella for hostage-holding factions.
   One of the Syrian sources noted, ``Let's not forget that
Rafsanjani still faces quite a bit of opposition.
   ``Rafsanjani ... doesn't look like he has the leverage with the
people who count,'' the hostage-holders themselves, he added.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0073 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 2328EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-FakeBomb     03-04 0542</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Fake Bomb,0558</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bomb Scare At Temple Brings Back Sad Old Memories</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ATLANTA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A phony bomb discovered at a synagogue during a
weekend bat mitzvah has troubled Jewish leaders and brought back
memories of a bombing there three decades ago.
   The Temple, on Atlanta's Peachtree Street and featured in the
current movie ``Driving Miss Daisy,'' was evacuated Saturday
morning during a bat mitzvah, service for a 12-year-old girl.
   A bogus bomb, containing wires, a clock and batteries _ as well
as some confusing messages _ was left in The Temple's front
doorway, under a Hebrew inscription proclaiming The Temple a
``house of prayer for all peoples.''
   ``That (inscription) is a sign of welcome _ inclusiveness, not
hatred,'' said Rabbi Alvin M. Sugarman. The phony bomb, he said,
``had the effect of hatred.''
   ``I'm amazed at this,'' said William B. Schwartz, who was
president of The Temple in 1958, when the building was heavily
damaged in a pre-dawn bombing. ``I thought we had come a long way
over the years.''
   Whoever left this weekend's phony bomb ``wanted us to believe it
was a bomb,'' said Atlanta Police Sgt. W.H. Briley. ``He made it to
look like a bomb.''
   The package, according to police, also contained videotapes of
news reports about anti-abortion protests, and several messages,
including some referring to Coretta Scott King, widow of civil
rights leader Martin Luther King Jr.; former First Lady Rosalynn
Carter; and a local TV anchorwoman. The messages weren't
anti-Semitic or racial threats, said police Capt. J.R. Spence.
   ``There were several messages that made no sense,'' he said.
   The Temple, Atlanta's largest Reform congregation with 5,000
members at present, was bombed Sunday morning, Oct. 12, 1958.
Police estimated that 30 to 50 sticks of dynamite were set off just
outside an entrance, and a 20-foot hole was blown in the building.
No one was hurt.
   President Eisenhower ordered FBI Director J. Edgar Hoover to
assist Atlanta Police in investigating, and five men were arrested,
but none was convicted.
   The bomb was intended to quiet clergy support for Atlanta school
integration efforts at a time of racial tension, but it had just
the opposite effect, said Mark R. Jacobsen, present director of The
Temple.
   ``People referred to the bomb as something that unified the
Atlanta community,' Jacobsen recalled. ``The Christian community
and the black community all rallied to The Temple's side to help
rebuild it. The message of love prevailed.''
   Atlanta Constitution editor Ralph McGill won a Pulitzer Prize
for a column about the bombing, condeming ``those so-called
Christian ministers who have chosen to preach hate instead of
compassion.''
   The bombing is depicted in the ``Driving Miss Daisy,'' a movie
about an older Atlanta Jewish woman's friendship with her black
chauffeur.
   About 150 people were evacuated from The Temple Saturday as
12-year-old Pam Epstein was reading from the Torah during her bat
mitzvah. ``I thought I was going to cry, because I wanted this to
be very special,'' she said.
   But the ceremony concluded, with a kiss from Miss Epstein's
grandfather.
   ``That was the amen to the prayer,'' Sugarman said. ``What will
endure here is not the act of hate, but the beauty of a young woman
accepting the adult role of a young Jewish woman.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0074 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 1546EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-SmokingAlternatives     03-04 0414</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Smoking Alternatives,0430</SECOND>
<HEAD>Stop Smoking Firms Capitalize on New Ban on Domestic Flights</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LAGUNA HILLS, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   There's not much puffing on U.S.
airliners these days, and that has Charles Sleichter smiling.
   Sleichter, president of Advantage Life Products Inc. in the
Orange County community of Laguna Hills, thinks the new federal
regulation banning smoking on most domestic airline flights will
boost sales of his company's ``smoking alternative.''
   ``If you look at all the smoking bans, this one gives smokers no
way out,'' he said.
   Advantage is poised to capitalize on that.
   It has planned a $4 million advertising campaign for later this
year and is placing displays of its CigArrest chewing gum in
airport gift shops, along with the slogan: ``Help Me Make It
Through the Flight.''
   The company has not had much success in trying to convince
airlines to let flight attendants offer CigArrest to passengers
undergoing nicotine withdrawal, however.
   Because of industry officials' concerns that passengers will
smash sticky gobs of gum on plane seats, Sleichter said he is
looking at the possibility of marketing the product in another
form: a throat lozenge.
   The law passed by Congress last year bans smoking on all flights
within the United States except a few lasting six hours or longer
to or from Hawaii or Alaska. It went into effect Feb. 25, replacing
an earlier smoking ban on domestic flights of two hours or less.
   Advantage isn't the only company involved in the $285 million
stop-smoking industry that has thought about how the ban will
affect business.
   Officials with Dep Corp., the distributor of Ban-Tron
stop-smoking pills, said they're trying to get airlines to offer
their gum to passengers too.
   Schick Laboratories, the stop-smoking clinic chain, is slashing
fees and creating a television special to focus on the need to quit
smoking in the wake of the ban, company spokesman Ed Butler said.
   But not everyone is capitalizing on the ban.
   Merrell Dow Inc., the Kansas City-based manufacturer of
Nicorette chewing gum, said it has no plans for a major campaign.
   ``I think there has been very little publicity and very little
public controversy (now that) the ban is going into effect,'' said
John F. Banzhaf III, executive director of Action on Smoking and
Health in Washington. The group is an anti-smoking lobby.
   ``I think the reality of it is that it has yet to hit the
smokers,'' Banzhaf said. ``But once it does, I would expect that
companies would capitalize on it.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0075 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 1629EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-Alaska-SovietFlights     03-04 0445</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Alaska-Soviet Flights,0462</SECOND>
<HEAD>Alaska Airlines Encouraged Over Air Talks</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JEFF BARNARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ANCHORAGE, Alaska (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Alaska Airlines executives say they are
encouraged by a preliminary agreement that could lead to the first
scheduled air service to the Soviet Far East by the summer of 1991.
   ``It's definitely a market we think has a lot of potential and
will and should open up,'' Doug Versteeg, vice president for
administration, said Friday from his office in Seattle.
   ``We see tourism as the biggest component of the market.
Tourists we bring to Alaska already each season we think would be
interested in extending their trip to the Soviet Far East.''
   U.S. and Soviet negotiators meeting in London on Thursday
announced an agreement in principle to open commercial air service
between Anchorage and the Soviet Far East cities of Magadan and
Khabarovsk.
   If a final agreement is reached, Alaska Airlines hopes to offer
two to three flights a week during the summer, starting in 1991.
   Versteeg said it was too early to project how many people might
take advantage of the planned service, but he foresaw business
people already traveling between the United States and the Soviet
Union using the routes as well as tourists.
   ``Both countries want to do business,'' he said.
   Gov. Steve Cowper said the memorandum of consultation between
the two countries could lead to regular air travel to other Soviet
cities by American carriers and service by the Soviet carrier
Aeroflot to San Francisco.
   ``Regular air service to the major cities in the Soviet Far East
is the ticket to a permanent relationship with out Soviet
neighbors,'' Cowper said. ``It means expanded trade opportunities,
easier cultural and educational exchanges, and a greater
understanding of our two systems.''
   Talks are to resume in April to prepare a comprehensive
U.S.-Soviet aviation agreement for inclusion in the planned June
summit between President Bush and Soviet leader Mikhail Gorbachev,
said Dennis Fradley, an aide to Sen. Frank Murkowski, R-Alaska.
   Alaska Airlines has been working to establish the routes since
January 1988.
   Alaska Airlines made charter flights to the Soviet Far East in
the 1970s and Aeroflot sends periodic charter flights to the West
Coast, but there has been no regularly scheduled air traffic
between the two countries over the North Pacific, Versteeg said.
   Bering Air currently operates charter flights between Nome and
the Soviet port city of Provideniya.
   Magadan is a city of 160,000 on the northern shore of the Sea of
Okhotsk, and Khabarovsk has 600,000 residents near the borders of
North Korea and China.
   Both are regional capitals as well as commercial centers.
Khabarovsk is the eastern terminus of the Trans-Siberian Railroad.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0076 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 1800EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-Eastern-Transactions     03-04 0184</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Eastern-Transactions,0199</SECOND>
<HEAD>Transactions Between Eastern, Texas Air and Continental
Scrutinized</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Eastern, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In his investigation, court-appointed examiner
David I. Shapiro studied 15 transactions between Eastern Airlines,
parent Texas Air Corp. and non-union sister Continental Airlines.
   In 12 of the 15 cases, Shapiro concluded that Texas Air
short-changed Eastern by buying its assets at unfairly low prices.
   He found, most notably, that Texas Air owes Eastern $150 million
to $250 million for the transfer of the System One computer
reservation system, and $61 million for Texas Air's acquisition of
Eastern in November 1986.
   Among the other transactions studied were:
   _A $16 million Texas Air debt to Eastern, stemming mostly from
legal fees and investment banking fees.
   _Management fees paid by Eastern to Texas Air.
   _Transfers of aircraft from Eastern to Continental.
   _Notes issued by now-defunct People Express Airlines which Texas
Air sold to Eastern.
   _Texas Air's fuel management arrangement with Eastern.
   _Strike contingency fees paid by Eastern to Continental.
   _A $40 million loan from Eastern to Continental.
   _Eastern's payment of cash dividends on preferred stock
guaranteed by Texas Air.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0077 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 1801EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-Eastern-Witnesses     03-04 0212</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Eastern-Witnesses,0218</SECOND>
<HEAD>Witnesses in Eastern Investigation Included Lorenzo, Bakes, Borman</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Eastern, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   About 100 witnesses were interviewed in the
course of an extensive investigation of Eastern Airlines and its
dealings with parent Texas Air Corp. and sister carrier Continental
Airlines.
   They included Texas Air Chairman Frank Lorenzo, Eastern
President Phil Bakes and Frank Borman, former chairman of Eastern
when Lorenzo bought it in 1986.
   Among the other witnesses were: Rolf Andresen, chief financial
officer of Eastern; George Brennan, Eastern's vice president of
marketing; Robert Brokaw, managing director of Merrill Lynch
Capital Markets; Janice Bryant, controller of Texas Air; Roy
Clauss, managing director of Salomon Brothers Inc.; Charles
``Skip'' Copeland, head of the pilots union at Eastern; Robert
Ferguson, senior vice president of Texas Air.
   Also: Mickey Foret, president of Continental; Charles Goolsbee,
senior vice president of Texas Air; David Kunstler, senior vice
president of planning at Eastern; Joseph Leonard, chief operating
officer of Eastern; Thomas Plaskett, chairman of Pan Am Corp.;
Martin Shugrue, former president of Continental and former vice
chairman of Pan Am; Jose Smith, Eastern's senior vice president for
operations; Robert Snedeker, executive vice president and treasurer
of Texas Air; and Edward Upton, former vice president of
maintenance and engineering at Eastern, recently resigned.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0078 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 1840EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-Shearson Advisory   03-04 0054</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Shearson, Advisory,0057</SECOND>
<TEXT>
   Eds: American Express has announced that it will acquire all the
outstanding common stock of Shearson Lehman Hutton Inc. that it
doesn't already own. American Express also said it had terminated
talks with third parties about possible changes in Shearson's
ownership. AM-Shearson will move within 25 minutes.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>AP Business News</BYLINE>
</DOC>
</Collection>
