<Collection>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0001 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 2324EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-AdvertisedBride     11-11 0328</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Advertised Bride,0416</SECOND>
<HEAD>Man Who Advertised For Bride Picks Louisiana Woman</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LAKE CHARLES, La. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   It pays to advertise.
   Just ask John Young, a lonely, 45-year-old convenience store
manager from Clearwater, Fla., who plastered ``wife wanted'' signs
on the side of his car.
   After receiving calls from women in 22 states and two Canadian
provinces, Young has picked Marilyn Dozier of Lake Charles as his
intended.
   But they won't meet until Dec. 5, when they are scheduled to
appear on the Phil Donahue Show in New York City.
   ``I'm 45 ... kind of a homebody,'' Young said Saturday in a
telephone interview with the Lake Charles American Press. ``It's
tough to meet someone who's not a yuppie all wrapped up in a
whiz-bang social life.''
   Young began his unusual advertising campaign about three months
ago, but few people noticed it and he got no calls for two months.
   Then a reporter for the Tampa Tribune in Florida wrote about
him, and the story was picked up by The Associated Press and
printed in newspapers throughout the United States and Canada.
   Ms. Dozier, an employee of Transit Aviation at a Boeing Co.
plant in Lake Charles, said Saturday she saw a story about Young in
her newspaper on Oct. 9 and thought about it for about a week
before deciding to ``call up this nut and see what he's like.''
   After several days of busy signals, she said, shefinally got
Young.
   ``Hello. This is Marilyn Dozier in Lake Charles, La.,'' she
said. ``Have you found any woman who wants to marry you yet?''
   They talked for 45 minutes during that first call. Since then,
Ms. Dozier said, they have talked for two to four hours every
night.
   ``He is an intelligent person with a good sense of humor,'' said
Ms. Dozier, who has a 19-year-old daughter.
   She had planned to fly to Florida on Wednesday to meet Young,
but television changed those plans, she said.
   Young had been talking with four national television shows that
wanted him to make an appearance. He finally decided to accept the
invitation from the Phil Donahue Show.
   Young said that when he told the Donahue people he and a woman
from Lake Charles had decided to meet, they offered to fly both of
them to New York City, provided the couple meet for the first time
on stage, recorded before a television audience.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0002 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 2330EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Japan-Enthonement 6thLd-Writethru   11-11 0799</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Japan-Enthonement, 6th Ld-Writethru,a0733,0952</SECOND>
<HEAD>Emperor Akihito Formally Enthroned in Controversial Rite</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 23 grafs to UPDATE with details of the ceremony;
pickup graf 20 pvs `The government...'</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto staffing</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVID THURBER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In a solemn, centuries-old rite at the Imperial
Palace, Emperor Akihito acceded to the Chrysanthemum Throne on
Monday, becoming the first Japanese monarch enthroned as a symbol
and not a living god.
   Leftist radicals launched 25 separate attacks aimed at
disrupting the ceremony, police said. They fired missiles at five
military bases, including a U.S. naval base, and set fires at
religious shrines and train stations. None of the attacks caused
injuries.
   A massive national security operation involving thousands of
police was mounted to protect the ceremony and the scores of
visiting dignitaries.
   Akihito, wearing a red-brown silk kimono of ancient design, sat
on an elaborate lacquered throne in front of an Imperial Palace
courtyard filled with attendants carrying bows and swords.
   He vowed to uphold Japan's modern constitution, which
fundamentally restructures the world's oldest hereditary monarchy.
   ``On this occasion, I pledge anew that I shall observe the
constitution of Japan and discharge my duties as symbol of the
state and of the unity of the people,'' Akihito, speaking in
colloquial Japanese, told about 2,500 guests in the heavily guarded
palace.
   Seated on her own throne at Akihito's side was Empress Michiko,
also dressed in full imperial regalia.
   Under the cloudless skies, gong and drum attendants played
haunting court music for royal family, officials and guests.
Dignitaries from 158 countries at the ceremony included Vice
President Dan Quayle and Britain's Prince Charles and Princess
Diana.
   The ceremony ended with Prime Minister Toshiki Kaifu, dressed in
swallowtail coat, leading the Japanese guests in three cries of
``banzai!'' - a wish for long life. He led the cheers from a spot
level with the throne to underscore the constitution's emphasis on
popular sovereignty.
   Following the enthronement, Akihito and Empress Michiko were to
change into Western clothes and travel in an open car from the
Imperial Palace to the Akasaka Palace, three miles away. Officials
said nearly 10,000 police would line the route, which passes in
front of Japan's parliament.
   Akihito had begun his morning rituals by offering private
prayers at three wooden shrines inside the Imperial Palace to
announce his enthronement to the Sun Goddess and ancestors.
   Critics say the 30-minute ceremony - and a series of
accompanying rites to be held in coming weeks - are based too
closely on the traditional religious rituals used for Akihito's
father and grandfather, who were enthroned as divinities.
   Japan's postwar constitution stipulates that the emperor is
simply a national symbol.
   In one controversial element of the rite, Akihito's raised dais
is said to be patterned after one used by the sun goddess, from
whom tradition says the Japanese imperial line is descended.
Critics say that is an implied symbol of divinity.
   The government is reportedly spending $95 million on the rites,
much of it for security. Opponents say state funding of the
ceremonies, linked to Japan's indigenous Shinto religion, violates
the constitutional separation of religion and state.
   The radical left has been particularly incensed because of the
legacy of imperial militarism in Japan.
   The projectiles were launched at three suburban bases of the
military and at a base in western Tokyo, police said. No damage was
reported.
   Another missile was fired outside the U.S. naval base at Atsugi,
24 miles southwest of Tokyo.
   Three train fires stopped service on two commuter lines, and in
separate incidents, two major subway lines were shut down because
of smoke.
   Among the other attacks police listed were fires that broke out
at four Shinto shrines in Tokyo, including one less than a mile
from Akihito's residence. Two shrines were destroyed.
   The attacks, including 19 in Tokyo, caused little other damage,
police said.
   On Sunday, two bombs exploded at the house of U.S. Consul
General Gregory L. Johnson in Nishinomiya, in western Japan. Police
said they caused little damage and no injuries. It was not
immediately clear whether the explosions were connected with the
enthronement.
   A record 37,000 police, including reinforcements from a majority
of Japan's 47 prefectures, have been mobilized for security
surrounding the rite. Security was particularly heavy around the
downtown palace.
   The government has not released the names of Japanese
dignitaries invited to the ceremony, because of fear of radical
attacks on their homes or businesses.
   Traffic was sharply restricted or halted along highways and in
areas around the palace, but few tie-ups were reported, in part
because enthronement day was declared a national holiday and many
Tokyoites took advantage of the three-day weekend to leave town.
Airlines reported many flights were booked close to capacity.
   Akihito became emperor immediately upon the death of his father,
Emperor Hirohito, in January 1989, but a period of mourning was
observed before his formal enthronement.
   Akihito, 56, was tutored after World War II by an American
pacifist, and is the first emperor in modern Japanese history to
marry a commoner. He and the empress also raised their three
children themselves, rather than have them raised separately by
aides, as was the imperial custom.
   As with Hirohito's funeral, which was attended by
representatives of 164 nations, the enthronement provided
opportunity for a flurry of diplomatic meetings. Kaifu was
scheduled to meet with about 50 foreign officials.
   On Monday evening, the first of seven banquets scheduled over
five days is to be held at the Imperial Palace, with senior
Japanese officials and foreign dignitaries attending.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0003 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 2332EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-TwinPeaks 1stLd-Writethru a0611 11-11 0429</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Twin Peaks, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0611,0540</SECOND>
<HEAD>Now We Know Who Killed Laura Palmer, Or Do We?</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 8th graf, `In Saturday's ...' to CORRECT spelling to
Horne, sted Horn. Picks up 9th graf, `The debonaire ...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By MARY MacVEAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   David Lynch and Mark Frost pulled off a neat
trick on ``Twin Peaks.'' They revealed Laura Palmer's murderer to
viewers, but neither FBI agent Dale Cooper nor Sheriff Harry S.
Truman was in on the solution.
   If we can trust our eyes - a gamble in the weird and wild world
of ``Twin Peaks'' - then Laura's father killed her and is about to
kill her look-alike cousin.
   Unless, of course, Cooper (Kyle MacLachlan) figures out a vision
he sees at a bar and saves the day.
   Faithful viewers have come to expect virtually nothing to be
what it seems in Twin Peaks, a picturesque but dark little logging
town in the Pacific Northwest.
   And nothing was even as it seemed at ABC. The network had
already promised twice to reveal the killer - first in last
season's finale and then during the two-hour season premiere in
September - before coming through on Saturday, during television
sweeps.
   A shadowy, long-haired man named Bob, whom viewers have seen
only through characters' visions, has been placed at the murder
scene, apparently bludgeoning Laura.
   OK, so then what's going on? It had been hinted that Bob may be
a demonic force requiring a human host. Does Leland think he's Bob?
Does he have two personalities? Why can some people see Bob, and
some only see Leland?
   There's still suspense left, ``Twin Peaks'' fans. And plenty of
plots. Not to worry.
   What of Cooper and Truman (Michael Ontkean)? After all this
work, they arrested somebody else.
   In Saturday's episode, Benjamin Horne, just minutes after
telling his own daughter he had been in love with homecoming queen
Laura, was hauled off for questioning in the murder.
   The debonaire but dastardly dad was always a good candidate for
killer, what with his ownership of a brothel, his sexual wanderings
and dealings with drug dealers.
   Leland, too, was an early favorite suspect among ``Peaks''
freaks. One theory had it that he had molested his daughter,
driving her to drugs and kinky sex. And unable to stand what he'd
done, he killed her.
   Elements of that theory may prove true, based on hints in
Laura's diary. And Leland has already been charged - as Leland, not
Bob - with killing another character.
   Lynch directed Saturday night's episode, and, wearing a trench
coat to match Cooper's, appeared as Gordon Cole, Cooper's
hard-of-hearing boss.
   His show could use some help in the ratings. According to the
latest A.C. Nielsen Co. numbers, the series was third in its time
period last week, with a 7.9 rating and a 16 share.
   A rating point equals 931,000 television households. A share is
the percentage of television sets in use in the time period that
are turned to the show.
   The sweeps, which come up four times a year, are when viewership
is closely measured so local network affiliates can set advertising
rates.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0004 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 2341EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Obit-Zwach     11-11 0195</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Zwach,0207</SECOND>
<HEAD>Former Congressman John Zwach Sr. Dies</HEAD>
<DATELINE>REDWOOD FALLS, Minn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   John Zwach Sr., who served in state
government for 32 years and as a Republican congressman from 1966
to 1975, died Sunday of lung cancer at age 83, his daughter said.
   Zwach, who lived in nearby Lucan in southwestern Minnesota, died
in Redwood Falls Hospital, said his daughter, Barbara Sykora, who
is chairwoman of Minnesota's Independent-Republican Party.
   Zwach began his political career in 1934, when he was elected to
the state House of Representatives. He served there until 1946,
when he was elected to the state Senate, where he served for 20
years and was the majority leader from 1959 to 1966.
   Zwach was elected in 1966 to the U.S. House of Representatives
from Minnesota's 6th Congressional District, which includes
southwestern Minnesota. He retired retired in 1975.
   He held posts on the agriculture and veterans affairs
committees.
   A native of Gales Township, Zwach received a bachelor of science
degree from the University of Minnesota in 1933. He was a
schoolteacher and superintendent for 14 years and also farmed near
Walnut Grove.
   Survivors include his wife, Agnes; four other children; 19
grandchildren and three sisters and four brothers.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0005 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 0021EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Vatican-Weakland     11-11 0288</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Vatican-Weakland,0312</SECOND>
<HEAD>Vatican Nixes Weakland Honor from Swiss University</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MILWAUKEE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Vatican has barred a Swiss University from
giving an honorary degree to a Roman Catholic archbishop because of
his views on abortion.
   Archbishop Rembert G. Weakland said Friday he was disappointed
the Vatican's Congregation of Education ordered his removal from a
list of award recipients without discussing its objections with
him.
   The Vatican told the theology department of the University of
Fribourg that granting Weakland ``a doctorate `honoraris causa' by
a prestigious faculty of theology would only add to the
confusion.''
   ``This prelate has recently taken certain positions relative to
the question of abortion which are not without doctrinal importance
and which are causing confusion among the faithful in the United
States,'' it said.
   It was the Vatican's first public reprimand against Weakland on
the abortion isue.
   Although he has said he respects the church's opposition to
abortion, he suggests anti-abortion demonstrators sometimes lack
compassion and that ``pro-choice'' doesn't necessarily mean
pro-abortion.
   Weakland wrote Oct. 23 to the Rev. Damian Byrne, head of the
Dominican Order in Rome, saying he was withdrawing from
consideration for the degree.
   Faculty members at the University of Fribourg protested the
Vatican's decision and voted on Oct. 24 not to grant any of the
five honorary doctorates that were to have been presented next
Thursday.
   ``To make a decision like this without consulting Archbishop
Weakland indicates that Rome still has not learned the importance
of due process in dealing with individuals, whether bishops or
theologians,'' the Rev. Thomas Reese of Washington, D.C., said in a
telephone interview.
   ``I think the results will be counterproductive and will simply
put Rome in a bad light in the United States,'' Reese said. ``I
have no doubt Archbishop Weakland will now get many more offers of
honorary degrees.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0006 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 0211EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-King-FiestaBowl 1stLd-Writethru a0597 11-11 0310</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-King-Fiesta Bowl, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0597,0371</SECOND>
<HEAD>Fiesta Bowl Could Be Moved from Arizona</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: TOPS with four grafs with possible move to San Diego and
invitation to Notre Dame, picks up 3rd graf pvs, `Arizona has ...'</NOTE>
<DATELINE>PHOENIX (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Fiesta Bowl will move to San Diego's Jack
Murphy Stadium if the participating teams object to playing in
Arizona, the chairman of the selection committee said Saturday
night.
   Don Meyers told The Associated Press that if the game has to be
moved because of the reaction over Arizona voters rejecting Martin
Luther King's birthday as a state holiday, it will be played Jan. 1
in San Diego, three days after the Holiday Bowl in the same
stadium.
   ``We've struck a deal with Jack Murphy Stadium,'' Meyers said.
   ``We feel we've got a shot at (top-ranked) Notre Dame and we
should know by noon, Eastern time, on Sunday,'' Meyers said. On
Nov. 24, the day the NCAA permits official bowl bids, ``we plan to
extend an invitation to the University of Virginia and we're not
aware of any reason for them to turn it down. We will also invite
either Notre Dame or the highest-ranked Southeastern Conference
team that doesn't go to the Sugar Bowl.''
   Arizona has been stung by national criticism since Tuesday, when
voters rejected by a 51-49 margin a referendum which would have
created a paid state holiday honoring the late Martin Luther King
Jr.
   On Wednesday, NFL commissioner Paul Tagliabue said he would
recommend the 1993 Super Bowl be moved from the Phoenix area
because of the defeat of the King holiday. Gov. Rose Mofford
estimated that losing the Super Bowl would cost Arizona $200
million in lost revenue.
   Meyers said 11th-ranked Virginia was extended an invitation to
the Jan. 1 Fiesta Bowl after the team, known as the Cavaliers, beat
North Carolina 24-10 Saturday. An opponent has not been chosen, he
said.
   Jim Copeland, Virginia's athletic director, said it was
uncertain whether the Cavaliers would accept the bid.
   The Fiesta Bowl ``has been an option we've considered all along
but it's been a real difficulty working through that (the King
vote) and I'm not sure we've resolved it yet,'' Copeland said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0007 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 0427EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-Kuwaitis 1stLd-Writethru a0494 11-11 0464</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Kuwaitis, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0494,0581</SECOND>
<HEAD>Kuwaiti Pilots Flying Only Unarmed Training Missions</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf-Offensive, Bjt</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 5 grafs to clarify that Americans quoted are
civilian contract workers, not officials. Pick up 6th graf pvs,
`The Saudis...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By EDITH M. LEDERER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>IN EASTERN SAUDI ARABIA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Saudi Arabia is not allowing
escaped Kuwaiti air force pilots to fly armed training missions
because of fears they would attack Iraqi positions, according to
Americans working with the Kuwaitis.
   More than three months after escaping to the kingdom with most
of their air force, several Kuwaiti military men refused to say why
they were not carrying out armed patrols along with U.S., British
and Saudi pilots.
   A Saudi Ministry of Defense spokesman said the Kuwaitis were
here for training and for safety reasons, and training flights must
be unarmed.
   The Kuwaiti pilots ``very soon are going to fly on armed
missions,'' the spokesman said on condition of anonymity.
   But American civilian advisers working with the Kuwaitis said
the Saudis feared the Kuwaitis would head north and bomb the
Iraqis.
   ``The Saudis won't allow them to. It's very obvious. If they
had, they'd probably go home,'' said Scott Corliss, 30, of Corpus
Christi, Texas, who helps supervise launches of Kuwaiti aircraft at
a base in eastern Saudi Arabia.
   The U.S. Air Force doesn't use missiles on training flights but
does arm F-15 training flights with canon rounds, an Air Force
spokesman said.
   At the moment, the Kuwaitis are flying only A-4 Sky Hawk
ground-attack fighters, all recently emblazoned with the logo
``Free Kuwait.''
   The Kuwaiti pilots who arrived here Aug. 3, a day after Iraqi
troops invaded their emirate, said they were anxious to return home
and ready to die for their country. But they also said they would
never launch a solo attack.
   ``We won't do it because that decision will commit a lot of
countries,'' said Lt. Col. Abdulla Sultan, 40, deputy operations
officer of the Kuwaiti detachment at the base.
   ``We don't want to ignite the war unless it's firm everybody's
ready. If we ignite it and everybody's relaxed, they might turn
against us,'' he said.
   First Lt. Khaled Malallah, 27, an A-4 pilot said: ``I will not
do it ... but we are ready. We are ready to go to fight and die for
our country.''
   Kuwaiti pilots flew 15 Mirage F-1 fighters, 20 A-4 Sky Hawks, 6
Hawk trainers and 15 French-made Gazelle helicopters to Saudi
Arabia, Sultan said.
   One helicopter crashed in Saudi Arabia en route and its two-man
crew was killed. Kuwaiti Defense Minister Sheik Nawaf Al-Ahmed Al
Sabah said in early September that the Air Force lost 8 Mirages, 3
A-4s and 2 helicopters to Iraq.
   Sultan said about 80 percent of the Kuwait air force's planes
are in Saudi Arabia and about 95 percent of its pilots.
   But after three months, he said, the Mirages are still not
flying because of serious problems with spare parts. He said he
hoped to get the first Mirage up in the air next week.
   Wade Zahnd, 35, of Stockbridge, Ga., part of the A-4 ground
support crew, said about half the 35 to 40 Americans working under
contract for the Kuwaiti air force on Aug. 2 are either in hiding
or held hostage by Iraq.
   Zahnd said he escaped on Aug. 13 by driving from Kuwait through
the desert.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0008 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 0608EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i BC-Japan-Explosions     11-11 0144</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Japan-Explosions,0144</SECOND>
<HEAD>Explosions Hit U.S. Consul General's Residence</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two explosions occurred Sunday at the residence of
the U.S. consul general in Nishinomiya, western Japan, police and
U.S. Embassy officials said. There were no injuries.
   Police said they did not know if the explosions were related to
a string of violent acts by ultra-leftist radicals opposed to
Emperor Akihito's enthronement, scheduled for Monday.
   The early evening blasts in the yard outside the residence of
Consul General Gregory L. Johnson were believed to have broken at
least one window, a local police official said.
   A U.S. Embassy spokesman in Tokyo said no one was injured.
   ``We have heard that two people went by on a motorcycle and
lobbed something on to the grounds of the residence,'' the
spokesman said on condition of anonymity. He gave no further
details.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0009 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 1122EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--Britain-Raid     11-11 0166</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Britain-Raid,0167</SECOND>
<HEAD>Police Find Explosives in Cars</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Anti-terrorist police on Sunday discovered an
estimated 50 pounds of explosives and detained an unknown number of
suspects following a raid in north London, police said.
   The explosives, other unspecified weapons and documents were
found in two parked cars, police said. Two apartments also were
raided.
   Anti-terrorism squads have been searching for an Irish
Republican Army cell operating on the mainland since the present
terror campaign began more than two years ago.
   The mainly Roman Catholic IRA is fighting to end British rule in
Northern Ireland. It wants to unite the predominantly Protestant
province with the Republic of Ireland under socialist rule.
   More than 2,000 people were evacuated from homes in the area
during the raid, a spokesman for Scotland Yard said, speaking on
condition of anonymity.
   The spokesman said the people detained under the Prevention of
Terrorism Act were being questioned. He did not say how many had
been detained.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0010 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 1122EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--UnderwearScare     11-11 0175</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Underwear Scare,0182</SECOND>
<HEAD>Suspicious Bag of Underwear Causes Bomb Scare</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Japan-Enthronement, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Trains were delayed for several hours before dawn
Sunday as a bomb squad disposed of a ``suspicious-looking'' paper
bag that turned out to be filled with women's underwear.
   The bomb scare came as police were on top alert against
terrorist activity before Emperor Akihito's coronation, which
begins Monday.
   A police spokesman in Urawa, a Tokyo suburb, said a railway
employee spotted the bag beneath a bridge on the Takasaki Line just
before 2 a.m.
   The bomb squad soon arrived at the scene, froze the bag with
liquid nitrogen and transported it to a nearby river bank for
further investigation. Police found a few dozen pieces of women's
underwear.
   ``I suppose if you would have looked closely enough you might
have been able to tell that it was harmless, but you never know,''
the official said, speaking on condition of anonymity. ``These are
tense times.''
   The investigation led to delays or cancellations of nearly 30
passenger and freight trains, the official said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0011 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 1133EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p AM-OnTo1992 Bjt   11-11 0724</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-On To 1992, Bjt,850</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush Doesn't Look So Unbeatable Anymore</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DONALD M. ROTHBERG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Political Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The one-time reluctance of Democrats to
consider taking on President Bush in 1992 has vanished, wiped out
by a faltering economy and sinking presidential approval ratings.
   ``The question asked six months ago was, `Is George Bush
possibly vulnerable?''' said Bob Beckel, a political analyst who
managed Walter Mondale's 1984 presidential campaign. ``That's now
switched to, `There's no question George Bush is vulnerable. ... Do
we have a horse to take him on?'''
   ``My guess is, along about December, some of the more apparent
guys are going to start calling folks,'' said John White, a former
Democratic Party chairman. His first choice would be fellow Texan
Lloyd Bentsen, who managed to shine in a losing cause as 1988 vice
presidential nominee. If Bentsen doesn't get in, White no doubt
would tilt toward Sen. Sam Nunn of Georgia.
   Six months ago, it was hard to find a Democrat willing to
acknowledge any interest in a 1992 presidential race. But then Bush
saw his public approval ratings plummet as the Persian Gulf crisis
dragged on and as concern about the economy heightened amid his
negotiations with Congress over tax increases. Even Republicans
conceded that Bush had damaged himself with his decision to embrace
higher taxes.
   Now, it looks like the horses are ready to beat down the barn
door in their eagerness to get onto the track.
   Item:
   - Associates of Gov. L. Douglas Wilder of Virginia have formed
the Committee for Fiscal Responsibility in 1992. ``This committee
is not tied to any candidate,'' said Paul Goldman, the Virginia
Democratic Party chairman. But he went on to acknowledge that it
could be transformed into a presidential campaign committee.
   Another Item:
   - Aides to Gov. Mario Cuomo of New York have called people tied
to Rep. Richard Gephardt of Missouri and asked if they thought the
House majority leader intended to run in 1992.
   Pregnant Quote:
   - ``I'm not going as far as to say I'm not a candidate.'' - Sen.
Bob Kerrey of Nebraska.
   Another Pregnant Quote:
   - ``I intend to be active over the next couple of years in our
presidential process. I'm not running for anything.'' - Sen. Tom
Harkin of Iowa.
   Then there are the more traditional quotes. Like Sen. Albert
Gore Jr.'s statement that he will ``sit down and think about it.''
   ``The chances for a Democrat winning the White House in 1992
look a lot better,'' Gore said during a news conference after last
week's elections.
   Gore, Nunn, Gephardt, Cuomo and Sen. Bill Bradley of New Jersey
were on the ballot in 1990. Gore, Nunn and Gephardt won easily. But
the voters played nasty tricks with Cuomo and Bradley.
   The New York governor was re-elected with just 53 percent of the
vote against an underfinanced maverick Republican who barely
finished ahead of the Conservative Party candidate.
   Housing Secretary Jack Kemp said Cuomo was ``scared witless'' by
his narrower-than-expected margin of victory.
   Even Cuomo conceded: ``We didn't get the margins we wanted. We
didn't get that exultant shout that we wanted from the people.''
   But Cuomo and his aides were quick to point out that he did
better than Republican Thomas E. Dewey, who held the previous
record for the highest winning percentage by a governor seeking a
third term.
   Dewey also was a two-time presidential nominee who lost both
times.
   Bradley had an even more uncomfortable election night.
   An overwhelming favorite to win a third term by a landslide
against GOP political novice Christine Todd Whitman, Bradley
squeaked through with 51 percent of the vote.
   Bradley was nearly tossed out by an electorate enraged by
Democratic Gov. James Florio's plans to raise their taxes. That
might tell the whole story, but those who want to diminish the
senator's presidential prospects don't want to let it rest there.
   Bradley was a principal author of the 1986 tax reform bill that
eliminated most income tax deductions while lowering rates.
   ``A lot of us think his tax plan was really a tax rise,'' said
White.
   Pollster Peter Hart saw little permanent damage to either
candidate.
   ``I think it probably makes it a little more difficult to go
fund raising,'' he said. But raising money does not seem that much
of a problem for either Cuomo or Bradley.
   Gephardt, Bradley and Gov. Bill Clinton of Arkansas took
themselves out of 1992 to one degree or another. But such demurrers
are hardly binding.
   Gephardt, who carried Iowa in 1988 but faltered in subsequent
primaries, wrote a letter to his House colleagues when he ran for
majority leader and said he would run not for president in 1992.
Already the rumors on Capitol Hill are that his fellow Democrats,
who believe he has done an excellent job as majority leader, are
telling him not to feel bound by his letter.
   ``As a general proposition, I think nobody ought to throw their
hat in the ring right now because that's the last thing the voters
want to see happen,'' said Mike McCurry, former communications
director for the Democratic National Committee. ``Voters' attention
is going to right to the Persian Gulf after the news of the
buildup.''
   ``Yet, you have start doing the dance. You don't have to start
doing pirouettes just yet, but you at least have to start shuffling
your feet.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0012 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 1144EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p AM-Abortion-Elections     11-11 0765</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Abortion-Elections,850</SECOND>
<HEAD>Both Sides Claim Victories on Abortion in 1990 Elections</HEAD>
<HEAD>RETRANSMITTING a0610 to correct slugline</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-On to 1992, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By WILLIAM M. WELCH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Backers of legal abortions gained strength in
Congress and among governors last week. But abortion opponents won
races too - proving they can still defend incumbents and elect new
allies.
   In the end, 1990 provided something for everyone in the debate
over abortion.
   Abortion rights did not prove to be the political silver bullet
that some had hoped it would be after the Supreme Court revived the
issue last year. But few really thought it would.
   Instead, abortion turned out to be an issue that can effectively
decide some votes - not everyone's vote, but enough to matter in
close races.
   ``Where you have anywhere from 5 to 10 percent of the voters who
are deciding how they vote on one issue, that's dramatic,'' said
Republican political consultant Doug Bailey. ``It clearly was a
decisive factor - not necessarily the decisive factor - in a whole
lot of races, in a whole lot of different ways.''
   While both sides had victories, the issue seemed to have the
most potency for abortion-rights supporters where there were clear
differences between candidates, the candidates made it an issue,
and the races were otherwise competitive.
   ``There is still a political advantage for the pro-choice
side,'' said Democratic pollster Geoff Garin. ``But the results
were slightly less clear cut this time, because the anti-choice
side has learned how to play defense a little bit better.''
   The election also showed that taxes and the economy can crowd
out abortion as a political issue.
   And it showed that voters are capable of ticket splitting on the
issue. In Iowa, voters re-elected both an anti-abortion governor
and an abortion-rights senator. In Oregon, voters rejected
anti-abortion ballot measures while re-electing an anti-abortion
senator.
   ``Where abortion was a fundamental issue, it cut for the
pro-choice candidate,'' said University of Virginia political
scientist Larry Sabato. ``But where other issues took precedence,
then pro-life candidates were able to win.''
   On the abortion-rights side, the premier victories were in
Florida, where Democrat Lawton Chiles was elected governor, and
Texas, where Democrat Ann Richards will be the new governor.
   In Florida, ousted Republican Gov. Bob Martinez had led an
unsuccessful effort to enact restrictions on abortions after the
Supreme Court gave states new authority in its Webster decision
last year.
   Richards strongly supported abortion rights, but the biggest
factor was her opponent himself, Clayton Williams, who made a
series of embarrassing remarks including some considered degrading
to women. Richards won more than 60 percent of the women's vote,
and 25 percent of Republican women crossed over to vote for her,
according to exit polling.
   Abortion-rights supporters also had put a top priority on
re-electing Iowa Democrat Tom Harkin, their point man in the U.S.
Senate. He won easily.
   Abortion-rights forces also won in Minnesota, where
anti-abortion incumbents were defeated by Republican Arne Carlson
for governor and Democrat Paul Wellstone for the Senate. They won
the California governor's race before the first vote was cast -
both candidates supported abortion rights.
   Victories for the anti-abortion side included the election in
Kansas of Democrat Joan Finney over GOP Gov. Mike Hayden, an
abortion-rights supporter, Republican George Voinovich's election
as governor in Ohio; and the re-election of GOP Sens. Mark Hatfield
in Oregon and Jesse Helms in North Carolina.
   Also, abortion foe Wally Hickel was elected governor of Alaska
as an independent and Pennsylvania's anti-abortion Democratic Gov.
Bob Casey was easily re-elected.
   Perhaps the biggest victory for abortion opponents was their
unexpected defeat of Michigan's Democratic Gov. James Blanchard by
state Sen. John Engler, an abortion foe.
   Abortion-rights groups pointed to Nevada's approval of a
proposal to write abortion guarantees into state law, as well as
Oregon's defeat of two anti-abortion ballot measures.
   Abortion opponents also suffered a defeat in Idaho, where Gov.
Cecil Andrus vetoed a tough anti-abortion bill passed by the
legislature. Andrus easily won re-election, and the chief architect
of the bill, Republican Roger Madsen, was defeated for re-election
to the state Senate as abortion opponents lost control of that
chamber.
   All told, the National Abortion Rights Action League counts a
net gain of four governors for their side. They gained two votes in
the Senate - Wellstone and Republican Hank Brown in Colorado, who
replaces retiring GOP Sen. Bill Armstrong, a fierce abortion foe.
   In the House, abortion-rights advocates scored a net gain of
eight seats, according to groups on both sides of the issue.
   ``Obviously, this means that the House will be more closely
divided on abortion-related issues,'' acknowledged Douglas Johnson,
legislative director of the National Right to Life Committee.
   He contended abortion opponents will still be able to sustain
abortion-related vetoes in the House.
   But in the Senate, the abortion-rights side may now approach the
60 votes needed to avoid anti-abortion filibusters.
   Abortion-rights activists also estimate they gained new
majorities in at least one legislative chamber in four states:
Arizona, Idaho, Montana and Florida.
   ``In almost all of the key races, abortion was one of the top
three or four issues,'' said Andy Kohut, president of Princeton
Survey Research Associates Group, who analyzed television network
exit polls.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0013 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 1145EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-RemembranceDay     11-11 0507</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Remembrance Day,0643</SECOND>
<HEAD>Man Sets Himself Ablaze Near Queen at Remembrance Ceremony</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SYDNEY RUBIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A man set fire to himself Sunday and ran down a
street lined with people watching Queen Elizabeth II lay a wreath
at a monument to Britain's fallen war heroes.
   Hundreds of people watched in horror as the 29-year-old man
climbed over a police barrier set up on Whitehall Place to control
crowds gathered for Remembrance Day, which commemorates the
veterans of the two world wars.
   The queen, her husband the Duke of Edinburgh, and dozens of
government leaders including Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher
appeared unaware of the incident, which took place about 400 yards
away.
   ``The man climbed over the barrier ... and ran down Whitehall
setting himself alight as he ran,'' a spokesman for Scotland Yard
said, speaking on condition of anonymity.
   The spokesman said police officers used their coats to beat out
the flames. The man was taken to a nearby hospital, where he was
listed in serious condition. Police did not reveal his identity.
   ``There was a whoosh,'' said Geoff McPherson, a 45-year-old
engineer who saw the incident. ``He was alight fully from his toes
to his head, his arms and every part of his body was covered in
flames. I have never seen anything ignite so quickly.''
   McPherson said police grappled with the man, who tried to dodge
away but was finally tackled.
   A man, a woman, and three children in the crowd were treated
later at a first aid post. The police spokesman said they suffered
slight injuries or shock.
   Simon Halewood, 33, who brought his mother to the ceremony, said
the man seemed to be running directly toward where the queen was
standing.
   ``I got the impression that he was running towards the
Cenotaph,'' said Halewood, referring to the national memorial in
the center of Whitehall dedicated to the ``glorious dead'' of both
world wars and other conflicts.
   The state ceremony was broadcast live on BBC television, but the
incident took place outside camera range.
   The incident occurred as the ceremony had reached its most
solemn moment with the annual observance of two minutes of silence
on the first stroke of 11 a.m. The chimes of Big Ben sounded the
hour. The Horseguards Parade fired a salute.
   The ceremony continued as planned, with the queen laying a
crimson wreath at the foot of the monument.
   ``The man had no placards. He said nothing at all so we have no
idea why he did it,'' the Scotland Yard spokesman said.
   Another police spokesman said that as the man lay on the ground
after being tackled he cried out: ``Think about people now!''
   One witness said flames 8 to 10 feet high leapt from the man's
body.
   ``I saw flames and two legs running, zig-zagging towards the
crowd. It is the most awful thing I have seen in my life,'' witness
Jean Handley said.
   ``A lady near me thought it was a firework. I had seen what
happened but I did not want to say anything to start a panic,'' she
said.
   The 90-year-old Queen Mother, Princess Anne and Prince Andrew
watched the ceremony from a balcony overlooking the street. Like
all the royal family and government dignitaries, the three were
dressed in black.
   After the royal family and dignitaries returned to Whitehall,
columns of old veterans marched by the Cenotaph under gray skies to
the music of pipes, drums and trumpets of military bands.
   The domestic news agency Press Association, reporting from the
Persian Gulf, said thousands of British servicemen took part in
Remembrance Day ceremonies in camps throughout Saudi Arabia and
aboard warships.
   Britain has sent about 16,000 troops to the gulf region.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0014 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 1149EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-ClubSaudi     11-11 0341</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Club Saudi,0432</SECOND>
<HEAD>`Club Saudi' Is An Oasis For Troops in Saudi Desert</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf-Kuwaiti Volunteers, Bjt</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos DHA4,5</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVID F. MARTIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>IN EASTERN SAUDI ARABIA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Desert-weary U.S. Marines now
have a place to unwind and relax, complete with an Olympic-sized
pool, a jogging track and a camel named Sue who's willing to pose
for souvenir snapshots.
   ``It's an oasis within an oasis,'' said Marine Lt. Col. Gary
Ivan Wilson, a reserve liaison officer from Camp Pendleton, Calif.,
who runs the recreation center dubbed ``Club Saudi.''
   The center, located in a rear area away from the front lines,
was built for Saudi soldiers, but has been made available to U.S.
troops by the Saudi government.
   It may well be the only place in Saudi Arabia where you won't
find a Marine carrying his M16 rifle. Weapons can be checked in
metal lockers.
   But security is tight, a reminder that any time Marines are
together they can be targets for terrorists. Seven years ago in
Lebanon, 241 Marines died in their sleeping quarters bombed by a
suicide truck driver.
   ``We remember Beirut and will not let that happen here,'' Wilson
said. ``This can be a vulnerable area.''
   Club Saudi is a far cry from the desert, where troops who need
exercise can do push-ups in the sand or use weights fashioned from
sandbags.
   At the center, soldiers can swim and play water polo, pump iron
in a outdoor area for free weights, jog on a track, play video
games or have a barbecue. They can ride Sue, the
camel-in-residence, or just pose for pictures with her.
   ``It is the first time the Marines have really been able to
relax since coming to Saudi Arabia. They come in tired and worn
out, and by the end of the day, you see them beginning to relax.
Many of them will fall asleep in the lounge chairs,'' Wilson said.
   The center will open a second pool in about a month. In the
meantime, troops can enjoy daily movies, a snack bar and table
tennis. There's a place to tape messages to send back home, and Red
Cross representatives if anyone needs help with a problem back
home.
   The club, with a staff of 60, is open to Marines, Navy and some
British hospital personnel.
   The Marines say it's a much-needed break from their desert
routine.
   ``Before it opened,'' confessed one Marine who did not want his
name used, ``I used to sneak over the wall to use it.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0015 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 1156EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Soviet-KGB     11-11 0415</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-KGB,0485</SECOND>
<HEAD>KGB Renegade Accuses Prime Minister of Snubbing Court System</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ANDREW KATELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   KGB renegade Oleg Kalugin on Sunday accused Prime
Minister Nikolai Ryzhkov of showing disrepect for the Soviet
judicial system by boycotting the trial of a lawsuit against him.
   Kalugin is suing Ryzhkov for stripping his military rank and KGB
Chairman Vladimir Kryuchkov for taking away his pension. He
contends the officials took the action as punishment for his
criticism of the Soviet Union's powerful intelligence agency and
secret police.
   Ryzhkov has not sent a lawyer or other representative to any of
three hearings on Kalugin's lawsuit, including one held Sunday.
   ``I understand when he doesn't respect our country's public,''
the 55-year-old former KGB general told the Moscow City Court,
referring to Ryzhkov. ``History will pass judgment on him for that.
But when he doesn't respect the country's legal organs in which he
works and which he supposedly rules, that's a disgrace which the
court should evaluate as disrepect to the country.''
   Supporters who packed the courtroom applauded.
   Kalugin is among the many Soviet public figures who have
demanded Ryzhkov resign for failing to reverse the country's
economic decline.
   Kalugin's fight with the KGB has made him a popular hero and
helped him win a seat in the 2,250-member Soviet Congress. He has
accused the KGB of resisting reform and continuing to spy on
citizens opposed to the Communist Party.
   After a half-hour session on Sunday focusing largely on
procedure, Judge Nikolai Romanenkov postponed further action on
Kalugin's lawsuit against Ryzhkov until the Supreme Court of the
Russian Federation considers a protest filed by the Soviet
prosecutor's office.
   The prosecutor objected to several complaints in Kalugin's
lawsuit. The judge did not outline the prosecutor's objections.
   The official Soviet news agency Tass said the prosecutor
contended the order to strip Kalugin of his rank was taken by a
collegial body even though it was signed only by Ryzhkov. The court
had earlier allowed Kalugin to file his lawsuit against Ryzhkov
personally.
   The prosecutor also said such an order can be appealed only to
the Supreme Court of the country, not to the Moscow City Court to
where the case was being heard.
   Kalugin's lawyer, Boris Kuzentsov, said the protest by the
prosecutor's office showed authorities were panicking when they
realized ``the court could consider the actions of the prime
minister illegal.''
   Kalugin vowed to continue the fight.
   ``Let's do it again. We'll do it at every level. I'll do it with
pleasure,'' Kalugin told reporters in English, a language he
learned while a KGB agent in the United States from 1958 to 1970.
   If he wins reinstatement, Kalugin's civil lawsuit against the
KGB could become a landmark for Soviet citizens seeking protection
for free speech and challenging the secrecy of government
decisions.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0016 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 1206EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Bush-GulfStrategy Bjt   11-11 0556</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bush-Gulf Strategy, Bjt,650</SECOND>
<HEAD>Troop Buildup in Gulf Sends Message of US Strength to Hussein,
Others</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TOM RAUM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush decided to nearly double U.S.
forces in the Persian Gulf as a signal to Iraq - and the rest of
the world - that the United States has more than enough firepower
to force Saddam Hussein out of Kuwait if necessary, U.S. officials
said.
   ``We had to show the international community we were serious,''
said one official.
   The decision also was prompted by Bush's determination to match
Saddam's own military buildup, the officials said.
   The officials, who spoke on the condition of anonymity, said
Bush's decision to send in more troops and equipment was not made
overnight, but evolved over a period of weeks.
   ``The situation has been evaluated and re-evaluated as time went
on,'' said one official.
   The administration on Thursday announced massive ground, sea and
air reinforcements to the combat power already in the gulf region.
That could mean as many as 200,000 new forces will be added to the
some 230,000 U.S. military personnel already there.
   In announcing the additions, Bush on Thursday said they were
needed for an ``adequate offensive military option'' - words chosen
carefully as a signal to Hussein.
   U.S. forces now in place in Saudi Arabia and on ships in the
gulf already had a limited offensive capability, officials said.
But they said the president wanted to send a forceful new message
to Saddam by emphasizing the word ``offensive.''
   Bush's decision to bolster U.S. forces was motivated, in part,
by Saddam's own buildup in sending nearly half of his
million-strong army to face the United States across the Saudi
border.
   Saddam's dogged refusal to yield to world condemnation, or to
four months of international economic sanctions, was also a factor
in Bush's decision to up the stakes.
   It wasn't that Bush decided at some point that the economic
sanctions weren't having an impact, aides said.
   ``We've always placed an emphasis on the sanctions,'' one
official said. But, he added, ``we want to maintain our
credibility.''
   ``The sanctions are not changing his (Saddam's) mind, even
though they are having an effect on his society,'' the official
said. ``The degree of seriousness with which Saddam takes
international efforts is questionable.''
   Even though Bush still intends to give economic sanctions a
chance to work, there is no evidence that the sanctions are having
their desired effect on Saddam, officials said.
   The United States also is caught between conflicting pressures -
being urged by Britain, Saudi Arabia and Turkey to put more
emphasis on military action and by the Soviet Union to exercise
restraint.
   ``The Soviets are the lynch pin of the coalition,'' one official
said.
   Soviet leaders have acknowledged that force ``could not be ruled
out'' but said they prefer to give diplomacy more time before
pulling the trigger.
   However, Secretary of State James A. Baker III noted that the
international consensus against Iraq was ``solid and unified'' as
he ended a seven-nation diplomatic mission to shore up support for
potential military action in the gulf last week.
   Sending new reinforcements into the region, but announcing that
they would take up to two months to get there, was Bush's way of
trying to accommodate both sides.
   It gives the sanctions more time to work, but also increases the
pressure sharply on Iraq.
   A week before he announced the troop increases, Bush was sabre
rattling as he stumped for Republican midterm-election candidates,
reminding Saddam that he was not ruling out a military action and
even comparing the Iraqi leader to Adolf Hitler.
   But Bush waited until after the elections to announce the
decision to send in more troops. ``He would really have been
accused of taking political advantage if he had announced this a
week ago,'' said one White House aide.
   Bush was to meet with congressional leaders involved with
foreign policy on Wednesday to review the latest developments.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0017 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 1216EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-MapplethorpeImpact Bjt   11-11 0605</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mapplethorpe Impact, Bjt,0756</SECOND>
<HEAD>What Did the Mapplethorpe Verdict Change? Not Much</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOE McDONALD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CINCINNATI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The chief of police has bad news for anyone
thinking the acquittal in the Mapplethorpe obscenity trial means
the city will soften its stand against sexually explicit magazines,
movies, music and art.
   ``What do you want me to tell you? That there won't be another
Mapplethorpe case? There's no way I can say that,'' Chief Lawrence
Whalen said last week in his annual meeting with the
homosexual-rights group Stonewall Cincinnati.
   Free speech advocates were elated Oct. 5 when a jury cleared the
Contemporary Arts Center and its director, Dennis Barrie, of
obscenity charges for showing Robert Mapplethorpe's sexually
graphic photographs. But $350,000 in legal bills nearly crippled
the art gallery.
   A week after the trial, Hamilton County Sheriff Simon Leis
threatened to file charges against a theater showing the film
``Henry and June.'' The steamy account of the love triangle
involving writers Anais Nin and Henry Miller and Miller's wife,
June, is rated NC-17 - no one under 17 may attend.
   County investigators did not watch the film, said Frank Weikel,
a spokesman for Leis. No charges were filed.
   On Oct. 24, two men were taken to court for holding hands in a
parked car. A judge dismissed the charge - disorderly conduct for
creating a physically offensive condition - saying it was too
vague.
   A Cincinnati promoter who staged an Indianapolis concert by 2
Live Crew after a Florida jury cleared the rap group of obscenity
charges says he won't risk a show in his home city.
   Whalen and spokesmen for Leis and county Prosecutor Arthur Ney
say the outcome of the Mapplethorpe case, which cost the city
$14,550, hasn't changed their outlook on cases involving sexually
explicit material. The late photographer's work includes photos
with homosexual themes and nude studies of children.
   ``The sheriff has said repeatedly as long as obscenity statutes
are on the books, he will enforce them,'' said spokesman Frank
Weikel. ``You don't change your attitude in enforcing murder
statutes if one murderer gets off.''
   Richard Buchanan, a lawyer and a member of Stonewall Cincinnati,
isn't surprised.
   ``They don't care that they never win, because if they make it
costly enough for you to defend your rights, that in itself has a
chilling effect,'' Buchanan said.
   At his meeting with about 75 members of Stonewall Cincinnati,
Whalen bristled at suggestions that the Mapplethorpe case was a
waste of tax money. He also denied that it was part of a pattern of
harassing homosexuals.
   Whalen declined to discuss the case against the two men who were
holding hands, citing the possibility of a lawsuit against the
city. But he stressed that the Contemporary Arts Center was
indicted by a county grand jury drawn from the community at large.
   ``How do you know that the grand jury did not include members of
the gay community?'' Whalen said.
   The case against the Contemporary Arts Center produced public
displays of opposition from residents who chafed at efforts to
maintain the clean-cut image of this city that closed all adult
bookstores and movie theaters in the 1970s.
   When ``Henry and June'' opened Oct. 12, a week after the
Contemporary Arts Center's trial ended, about 300 people attended a
weekday afternoon showing. Many said they knew nothing about Henry
Miller, but were there just to anger Leis.
   Steve Liberatore, who arranged 2 Live Crew's concert Oct. 24 in
Indianapolis, laughed at the prospect of a Cincinnati performance.
   ``I'm not sure we would have been interested in bringing it into
Cincinnati, in view of the problems the city has had with rap
groups,'' he said.
   A judge fined two members of the rap group NWA and another
performer $100 each for disorderly conduct last year after they
invited a concert audience to join them in a sex act.
   Record stores stopped selling 2 Live Crew's album ``As Nasty as
They Wanna Be'' in April after Leis said he might file obscenity
charges. A Florida record store owner was convicted Oct. 3 of
obscenity charges for selling the record.
   Tom Thompson, manager of Globe Records downtown, said the
verdict in the Mapplethorpe case was encouraging. But he still has
no plans to sell more copies of ``As Nasty as They Wanna Be.''
   ``It just isn't worth the headache. Why should I sell it and
jeopardize us?'' Thompson said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0018 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 1229EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Obit-StormieJones -URGENT-   11-11 0105</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Stormie Jones,0087</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<HEAD>Teen-age Heart-Liver Recipient Dies at 14</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PITTSBURGH (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Stormie Jones, the first heart-liver
transplant recipient, died Sunday at age 14, the hospital said.
   The Texas teen-ager was rushed to Pittsburgh from Dallas late
Saturday after she complained of flu-like symptoms.
   She was taken to Children's Hospital, where she deteriorated
throughout the morning and died about 9:40 a.m., said a news
release issued by Lynn McMahon.
   Stormie received a heart and liver in a historic transplant
operation Feb. 20, 1984.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0019 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 1232EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Soviet-Guns Bjt   11-11 0580</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Guns, Bjt,0665</SECOND>
<HEAD>Soviets `Armed to Teeth' with 3.6 Million Illegal Firearms</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BRIAN FRIEDMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Law enforcement authorities estimate that Soviets
have 3.6 million illegal guns in their hands, leaving the
increasingly restive population ``armed to the teeth,'' a newspaper
reported Sunday.
   The article in Komsomolskaya Pravda was the latest in a series
of reports about rising lawlessness in the country and appeared
less than a week after a gunman opened fire in Red Square while
President Mikhail S. Gorbachev and other leaders were reviewing
Revolution Day festivities.
   Four months ago, Gorbachev ordered illegal firearms to be turned
in, but the newspaper reported widespread disobedience of the
decree, with the Interior Ministry saying that individuals
surrendered only 20,100 guns, 700,000 rounds of ammunition and 3
tons of explosives.
   Of the 3.6 million illegal firearms in circulation, 25,000 are
rifles, the Interior Ministry said.
   The article was a follow-up to a report in Komsomolskaya Pravda
last week in which the newspaper offered to buy firearms from black
marketeers while keeping their names confidential.
   Since the Communist Youth League newspaper began its offer in
late October, it reported it has been offered ``whole arsenals of
various types of modern weapons,'' including heavy machine guns,
hand grenades, grenade launchers, portable anti-tank launchers and
``a railway car full of weapons.''
   ``Our impression is the country is armed to the teeth,''
correspondent D. Muratov wrote.
   The newspaper said it had turned its investigation over to
Gorbachev, who has deemed it ``very important,'' and forwarded it
to Defense Minister Dmitri Yazov, Interior Minister Vadim Bakatin
and other officials.
   Weapons are stolen not only from arsenals, but also from
armament factories, assembled or in pieces, the newspaper reported.
In addition, weapons that are deemed obsolete or irreparable are
intercepted by black marketeers before they can be destroyed, it
said.
   In a separate report Sunday, the Communist Party newspaper
Pravda said police captured three servicemen who had deserted from
an Interior Ministry unit in Omsk with three submachine guns, five
revolvers and a large amount of ammunition that may have been
headed for the black market.
   Gorbachev's order on surrendering illegal weapons appeared to be
aimed at armed volunteers in such ethnic trouble spots as Armenia
and Azerbaijan, where nearly 500 people have been killed and
weapons such as automatic rifles and rocket-propelled grenades are
common.
   During last month's election campaign in Georgia, politician Gia
Chanturia was wounded by gunmen who fired four shots from a
speeding car.
   In the most visible sign of the increasing gun culture, two
shots were fired on Red Square about 80 yards from Gorbachev during
Wednesday's holiday celebrating the 73rd anniversary of the
Bolshevik Revolution. Soviet newspapers and TV showed plainclothes
officers subduing a man identified as Alexander A. Shmonov, 38, of
Leningrad, who was charged with attempting a terrorist act and
reportedly undergoing psychiatric treatment.
   Guns also are increasingly being used in ordinary crimes as the
Soviet economy deteriorates.
   Nationwide, there were more than 5,000 crimes committed with the
use of firearms this year, a 4 percent increase over 1989, the
newspaper said. That includes a 20 percent increase in the number
of murders, although the newspaper did not report how many people
had been killed.
   ``A situation is quite possible in which people in our endless
lines start shooting at each other,'' Komsomolskaya Pravda said
last week.
   The newspaper urged the government to encourage people to
surrender their guns by offering them cash rewards. In the
meantime, it recommended tighter security at arsenals.
   Vasil Bykov, a member of the Soviet parliament, wrote in an
accompanying article in Komsomolskaya Pravda that the military's
continued production of arms, which exceeds manufacturing levels in
the United States, is leading to national ``self-destruction.''
   He described the glut of firearms as an ``uncontrollable
elemental force (that) will destroy us at the hands of our starving
compatriots.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0020 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 1254EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-India-Hijack     11-11 0592</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-India-Hijack,0724</SECOND>
<HEAD>India Says No Extradition for Burmese Hijackers</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SANTOSH BASAK</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CALCUTTA, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two Burmese students who hijacked a Thai
jetliner will not be extradited as officials consider their request
for political asylum, news reports and officials said Sunday.
   Prosecutors, meanwhile, filed charges against the two men and an
official said they would be given special treatment while in
custody.
   The students commandeered the Thai Airways Airbus 300 on
Saturday with a phony bomb made from soap and wires. They said they
wanted to draw attention to the military's refusal to relinquish
power in Burma to an elected civilian government.
   United News of India quoted unidentified sources as saying the
government has decided not to hand over the students to Burmese
authorities.
   A Foreign Ministry official said the government was considering
their request for political asylum even though it has not been made
formally. He did not say what constituted a formal request.
   ``We do not have any extradition treaty with Burma so we are not
under any obligation to send these boys back,'' said the official,
who spoke on condition of anonymity.
   The plane was hijacked shortly before it was due to land in
Rangoon, Burma, on a flight from Bangkok, Thailand, and was
diverted to Calcutta, about 650 miles northwest of the Burmese
capital.
   All 203 passengers left Calcutta aboard a special Thai Airways
plane Sunday. The Foreign Ministry official said the government
impounded the plane.
   Sixteen crewmen stayed behind for questioning and are not
expected to leave before Monday, airport police inspector Sunil
Mandal said.
   Chief Secretary Manish Gupta, the top civil administrator of the
state that includes Calcutta, said the two students were charged
before a local magistrate with criminal conspiracy.
   He said the hijackers, who identified themselves as Ye Marn, 24,
and Ye Htink Yaw, 22, will be given what is commonly known as ``VIP
treatment'' usually reserved for political figures.
   Jailed politicians in India often get better jail conditions
such as cushioned beds and good food.
   The two hijackers spent the night in a government guest house
where they were interrogated most of Sunday, Mandal said.
   A third Burmese student was supposed to participate in the
hijacking, but the trio ran low on money in Bangkok and could only
afford two plane tickets, the hijackers said. They spoke at a news
conference after surrendering shortly after midnight Saturday.
   The two students said they were unarmed and never had any
intention of hurting anyone. The fake bomb was made out of bars of
soap with protruding wires.
   ``We wanted to draw international attention and international
support for our human rights and democracy (campaign),'' Marn said.
``Our mission has been fulfilled.''
   He said they hijacked the plane to India because of its
democratic tradition, ``and any country which loves democracy
should support our cause.''
   Marn and Htink Yaw said they were students at Rangoon
University. They wore red headbands emblazoned with a fighting
peacock, which they said was the symbol of pro-democracy student
groups in Burma.
   Burma's military government crushed a student-led pro-democracy
movement two years ago and continues to detain large numbers of
people for political reasons.
   The National League for Democracy won a landslide victory in an
election last May, but the military regime refused to step aside
and intensified the suppression of dissidents.
   Freed passengers said the bluejean-clad youths were not
menacing.
   ``These young men did not misbehave with us,'' said Hiromu
Tsuchiguchi, 42, a travel agent from Osaka, Japan.
   ``There was a bloke walking up and down the aisle with something
in his hand and that was the only bitof tension,'' said David
Irwin, 30, of London.
   But after hours of sitting on the tarmac it became ``boring,
tedious. Once we landed it was a non-event, really,'' Irwin said.
   ``There was a little tension at the beginning,'' said John
Cogan, 46, a lawyer from Houston. ``The hijackers moved women and
children to the front and the men to the back of the plane. When
people moved, the hijacker would threaten to push the button'' on
the fake bomb.
   ``But he repeated several times that he meant no harm,'' Cogan
said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0021 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 1301EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-RadioDrama     11-11 0623</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Radio Drama,0806</SECOND>
<HEAD>Philippine Radio Program Airs Real-Life Drama: Overseas Calls</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By EILEEN GUERRERO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MANILA, Philippines (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Lita Belga had not heard from her
husband for months. When she learned he died in a car accident in
Saudi Arabia, she wept. Millions of other Filipinos wept too.
   Mrs. Belga received news of her husband Benjamin's death during
a telephone call to his Saudi employers - paid for and broadcast by
private radio station DZRH.
   The program, called ``Around The World, With Love,'' features
telephone conversations between Filipinos and their relatives
working abroad. The calls are free - on condition that they can be
used on the show.
   The highly popular broadcast has become a real-life soap opera,
a daily litany of money troubles, loneliness, death, and other
family crises.
   ``The beauty of the program is the spontaneity of it,'' said
program host Rey Langit. ``It is true-to-life drama unfolding right
before you. It is both entertaining and educational.''
   There is no shortage of people wanting to use the program to
contact relatives overseas, even though the price is having
personal conversations broadcast nationwide.
   ``You have not been sending money,'' Gloria Abalos said in a
recent call to her husband, Ernesto, in Saudi Arabia. ``I will kill
myself, that's what I'll do. ... I don't care how long you stay
there as long as you send us money.''
   The conversations are often painful. With millions listening,
relatives tried to muster the courage to tell Boy Santos that his
4-year-old daughter had died while he was in Saudi Arabia.
   No one would admit outright the child was dead. But Santos
figured out what they were trying to say.
   ``What have you done to my baby?'' he cried. ``You killed her!''
   Most callers are too poor to afford overseas telephone calls.
Every morning, they come to DZRH's studios to sign up. All but
emergency cases wind up on a waiting list, with a backlog that now
runs about two months.
   Langit says the station makes little profit from the program
because calls are expensive. He places an average of six calls
daily during the six-day-a-week, two-hour program.
   ``The program is both a commitment and moral obligation to give
good advice and help the poor with their problems,'' he said in an
interview. ``They come to us pleading and telling us that we are
their only hope.''
   Mrs. Belga turned to the station after a Filipino who had
returned from Saudi Arabia told her that her husband was dead.
Neither his employers nor the government had notified her.
   ``May I talk to my husband, please?'' she asked the person who
answered the telephone in Riyadh. The reply was in Arabic.
Eventually, another Filipino came to the telephone and confirmed
the death.
   Langit said he reminds callers beforehand that they will be on
the air. Still, many conversations are wrenchingly candid.
   In one call, a jealous husband in Saudi Arabia argued with his
wife until Langit passed the telephone to their young daughter.
   ``Why are you angry at mother?'' the girl asked. ``Mother now
has to wash clothes for other people just to feed us. She weeps day
and night.''
   Langit then scolded the husband about his family
responsibilities.
   ``The success of that call was that I was able to instruct the
guy to say `I love you' to his wife before he hung up,'' Langit
boasted.
   Not all conversations end painfully.
   Once, a 14-year-old girl asked the station to help find her
father, who had abandoned her and moved to the United States.
   ``We really wanted to help her, but how can we when the only
clue she had of his whereabouts was that he worked at a restaurant
in New York with huge glass panes in front,'' Langit said.
   Using a Manhattan hotel directory, the station began calling
restaurants at random. Amazingly, they found the father, working as
a bartender.
   ``You don't know me, but I'm the child you abandoned,'' said the
girl, with a nationwide audience listening in. ``You never sent us
money and that is the reason why I have to sell flowers in the
street and miss school.''
   In a quavering voice, the father replied: ``It is my fault, my
daughter. But you must understand that if I did not remarry here, I
would not have survived.''
   The girl now lives in the United States with her father, Langit
said.
   Cecilia Abogado called her sister Anita in Saudi Arabia, who
complained that her employers beat her.
   `I'm here at DZRH,'' she said. ``Do you remember we used to
listen to other people's problems on the air? Now they are
listening to ours.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0022 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 1311EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Lebanon     11-11 0567</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lebanon,0676</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hrawi Moves To Bankrupt Militias</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MOHAMMED SALAM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BEIRUT, Lebanon (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Elias Hrawi is moving to
bankrupt militia factions as part of a strategy to end the nation's
15-year-old civil war.
   The main objective of the Syrian-backed government is to regain
control of 12 Mediterranean ports used for years by Christian and
Moslem forces to siphon off customs duties, import weapons and ship
goods and possibly drugs.
   ``Without money to pay their fighters, they'll gradually
disintegrate. Moving into their areas shouldn't be a major military
challenge under those circumstances,'' a government source said,
speaking on condition of anonymity.
   But the 41,000 fighters in the estimated dozen militias are not
likely to quietly relinquish the ports along Lebanon's 137-mile
coastline.
   Some main militias have begun withdrawing from the Beirut area
to create a demilitarized zone under a plan by Hrawi and the Arab
League.
   So far, only Nabih Berri's pro-Syrian Shiite Moslem Amal has
said it will disband. Other forces have made no such commitment or
operate beyond the control of Hrawi's government or the Syrians,
which have about 40,000 troops in Lebanon under an Arab League
mandate.
   Among the groups likely to complicate the peace efforts are more
than 5,000 guerrillas in south Lebanon backed by the Palestine
Liberation Organization; the 2,000 Iranian Revolutionary Guards in
east Lebanon, and the fundamentalist pro-Iranian Shiites of
Hezbollah, or Party of God.
   Hrawi ``would face a tough challenge if an allince emerged
between the Lebanese militias and the non-Lebanese factions,'' a
government official said.
   ``With money and weapons, the warlords won't give in easily,''
he explained. ``Arafat won't simply order his fighters to leave
Lebanon and Iran won't be that happy to lose its influence here
either.''
   There are frequent reminders of Lebanon's volatility: the Oct.
21 assassination of Christian leader Dany Chamoun and most of his
family; a car bombing Wednesday in Christian east Beirut that
killed six people, and Israeli raids in south Lebanon on Friday.
   The government hopes that once Beirut has been demilitarized,
the army and Syrian troops can concentrate on gaining control of
other areas, including the ports.
   Sources estimate the militias take $100 million a year in port
customs duties and other taxes, money badly needed by the
financially strapped government.
   The militias also use the ports to bring in weapons and other
goods they sell on the market. They also ship produce from the
areas they control, sources said. The militias have reportedly used
the ports to traffic drugs.
   Once they've abandoned their strongholds in Beirut and lost
their ports, ``militia leaders would be caught between a hammer and
a hard rock,'' a government source said.
   ``They'd have no influence in decision-making and they'd be
without money,'' he explained.
   But Berri and Druse Moslem leader Walid Jumblatt have built up
financial empires amid the chaos of the civil war, which has killed
an estimated 150,000 people.
   Among their commercial enterprises are Jumblatt's Cogeco Co.,
based in the Druse-controlled port of Jiye south of Beirut, and
Berri's Taka (Energy) Co. that imports fuel.
   The government plans to compete on the open market for fuel and
seek to undercut the militia-controlled companies.
   Berri faces a particular problem because his company may lose
the state-owned Zahrani oil refinery near the southern port of
Sidon, which it has used to store imported fuel.
   The Marada, or Giants, militia, fielded by the pro-Syrian
Christian Franjieh clan in north Lebanon, also would lose a major
source of revenue if Hrawi takes control of the port of Chekka,
where the militia has been collecting illegal taxes on cement
imports since 1976.
   Hrawi's forces also will cut the taxes militias levy on goods
entering or leaving their areas.
   Military sources, speaking on condition of anonymity, said
Hrawi's army, led by Gen. Emile Lahoud, has only about 9,000 combat
troops to police Greater Beirut and the three main highways from
the capital.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0023 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 1316EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-KuwaitiVolunteer Bjt   11-11 0563</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Kuwaiti Volunteers, Bjt,0701</SECOND>
<HEAD>Desert Training: Afternoon Rests, No Guns, But High Spirits</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos DHA1-3</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By EDITH M. LEDERER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>IN EASTERN SAUDI ARABIA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Boot camp for the first Kuwaiti
volunteers would astound an American drill sergeant: cheating at
push-ups, weekends off and no weapons in sight.
   ``This isn't going to make us great soldiers, but at least we
can go fight,'' said Ahmad al-Dhafeeri, 21, who dropped out of
Marshall University in Huntington, W.Va., to volunteer for the
Kuwaiti Army whose remnants are now in Saudi Arabia.
   About 600 Kuwaitis in the one-month training program say they
want to be in the first wave to liberate their homeland, even if it
means death.
   ``We are not soldiers, believe me. We are not fighters. We are
not politicians. I think we are lovers, looking and trying to find
a place to live,'' al-Dhafeeri said.
   While some of the 230,000 American GIs deployed in the Persian
Gulf region are still sleeping under the desert stars, most Kuwaiti
tents have rugs on the floor and ice chests.
   About a dozen Bangladeshi cooks were preparing roast chicken for
the Kuwaitis' Sunday lunch while the Americans were partaking of
cold, pre-packaged rations.
   Reveille is at 6 a.m., long after most U.S. Marines are out
doing morning exercises. Every day, the Kuwaitis have a post-lunch
siesta until 3:30 p.m.
   More than 100 cars were in the parking lot, many luxurious
models with cellular phones, for weekend and possible evening
escapes.
   Still, it's tough getting into the military routine for some.
   One volunteer, who gave his last name as al-Odwany, said all the
volunteers are losing weight.
   With daytime temperatures down to the mid-90s, the volunteers
are training more, he said. ``But psychologically we are tired.''
   Col. Sedy Faleh al-Shammey, the Kuwaiti commander, said the main
aim of the intensive training, which was compressed from six
months, was to teach the volunteers to use machine guns.
   Only 10 day from graduation, however, the men had still not seen
a gun.
   `We want it now,'' said al-Odwani, 30, who had been studying for
a master's degree in economics at California State University in
Fresno. He was in Kuwait visiting his family when the Iraqis
invaded on Aug. 2.
   ``We are all anxious ... to get some machine guns and get inside
(Kuwait),'' he said.
   Al-Shammey assured reporters that no volunteer would graduate
without knowing how to fire a machine gun and invited them back to
watch target practice.
   The volunteers' training started with physical fitness and
company-sized units were double-timing through camp out of step
chanting ``God! Our Country! The Emir!''
   Maj. Qubil al-Rawshidi, 42, a burly Kuwaiti Army veteran, led
one company through hand-to-hand combat, showing them how to
karate-chop the necks and pluck out the eyes of an enemy. There was
more enthusiasm than finesse among the volunteers.
   When it came to push-ups, however, many volunteers grunted and
only managed to get their shoulders off the ground. At one point,
the major held his leg under a volunteer's body so he couldn't
cheat.
   Al-Shammey said 7,000 Kuwaitis had volunteered for military
service in Saudi Arabia and at Kuwaiti embassies abroad.
   The Kuwaiti Army set up a training center here which opened with
the current class of 600. Another center in the United Arab
Emirates graduated its first class on Saturday, he said.
   The U.A.E. armed forces headquarters announced in Abu Dhabi on
Sunday that it will continue training more Kuwaitis.
   No decision has been made yet on whether the volunteers here
will be held as a reserve or go on active duty with the 5,000
Kuwaiti troops who escaped and are now massed near the
Saudi-Kuwaiti border, Al-Shammey said.
   The volunteers, aged 21 to 35, want to join their countrymen on
the front line.
   ``The Iraqis have great missiles and they are well trained,''
Al-Dhafeeri said. ``But we are going to win because we are fighting
for a goal and they are fighting like animals. We are fighting to
free our mothers and fathers, our families and our country.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0024 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 1326EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-India     11-11 0637</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-India,0773</SECOND>
<HEAD>New Prime Minister Has Tough Road Ahead</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Prime minister's name is pronounced CHAN'dra SHAY'kur. Both
names are used on second reference.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By ARTHUR MAX</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW DELHI, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   India's new prime minister faces some
awesome challenges ahead, ranging from religious and class strife
to a looming economic crunch in his vast and divided country.
   Chandra Shekhar has never held executive office, his inner
circle lacks governing experience, and he is heading the weakest
government in India's 43-year history as an independent nation.
   He was installed Saturday, three days after his breakaway
faction of the governing Janata Dal party helped bring down the
11-month reign of V.P. Singh.
   The changeover comes as India tries to recover from Hindu-Moslem
rioting, separatist movements are tugging at its border states and
inflation is driving millions beyond poverty into hunger with each
climbing percentage point.
   Chandra Shekhar's government is inherently unstable. His newly
formed Janata Dal (Socialist) party controls just 61 seats in the
decision-making lower house of Parliament.
   It is propped up by the 195 seats of the Congress party led by
former Prime Minister Rajiv Gandhi, who was Chandra Shekhar's sworn
enemy until they joined forces to unseat Singh.
   Cynics say Gandhi will dump the new prime minister as soon as he
believes he can win an election. ``This government will last as
long as Congress wants it to,'' Singh said.
   Chandra Shekhar's immediate task is to grapple with the
religious and social conflicts that have claimed more than 500
lives in two months and which ultimately undid the Singh
government.
   Hindu fundamentalism has swept across India, promoted by
mantra-chanting politicians preaching that Hinduism equals
nationalism and urging Hindus to stand up for majority rights.
   Hindus make up 82 percent of India's 880 million people.
   Riots erupted at the end of last month over a plan by Hindus to
overrun a Moslem mosque in the pilgrimage town of Ayodhya and
replace it with a temple. In two weeks more than 370 people were
reported stabbed, shot or bludgeoned to death, and hundreds more
deaths may have gone unreported.
   The Hindu-Moslem turbulence diverted attention from protests by
upper-caste Hindus over Singh's policy to reserve nearly half of
government jobs for low-caste Hindus. About 150 people, mostly
teen-agers, died in clashes with police or in dramatic suicide
protests.
   The fires of caste and religion were stoked by politicians
bidding for votes among the enormous voting pool of India's
downtrodden masses, where Chandra Shekhar also has traditionally
found his support.
   Separatist insurrections in border areas have escalated in the
last year. Lives are lost with such numbing regularity that daily
newspapers pay scant attention.
   In Punjab, militants are seeking an independent state for Sikhs,
who claim that the Hindus dominating the federal government are
stealing their water and wealth from their northern farming state.
   The separatist movement among one of India's traditionally most
loyal minorities has divided families and villages. At least 2,700
people have been killed by Sikh extremists this year, making 1990
their deadliest year since the insurrection began in 1983.
   Moslems in Jammu and Kashmir, the only state where they are in a
majority, also want to break away. The casualty toll there has
surpassed 1,500 since Indian forces cracked down this year.
   India says both insurrections are being fed by arms and training
from across the border in Pakistan, the nation which constitutes
Chandra Shekhar's biggest foreign policy challenge. Pakistan denies
aiding the separatists.
   In the far eastern state of Assam, the United Liberation Front
of Asom has set up a virtual parallel state dominating the
countryside and extorting vast sums from managers of the rich tea
plantations.
   In the northwest part of Assam, Bodo tribesmen are fighting
another terrorist campaign for autonomy.
   In the far south, 100,000 Tamil refugees have swamped India's
shores in flight from the guerrilla war in Sri Lanka across a
narrow strait.
   In the long run, Chandra Shekhar's government will stand or fall
on the economy, the one issue which unites this diverse nation
which is home to one of every six humans on earth.
   Inflation officially is running at a projected rate of 10
percent. But recent surveys show that in rural areas, the daily
food basket has shot up by 25 percent since July.
   About half the population - more than 400 million people - fall
below the poverty line or hover just above it. Many families
compensate for higher prices by cutting down on meals.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0025 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 1333EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-AcropolisMuseum     11-11 0545</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Acropolis Museum,0684</SECOND>
<HEAD>Italian Architects Win International Competition For New Museum</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By NIKOS KONSTANDARAS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ATHENS, Greece (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The government unveiled plans Sunday for
an innovatively designed museum that some hope could pave the way
for the return of a great Greek treasure - the Elgin Marbles, long
in British hands.
   An international jury picked a design by Italian architects
Lucio Passarelli and Manfredi Nicoletti for a new museum to house
the sculptures from the temples of the Acropolis.
   The design, which beat out 438 other entries, calls for a
low-slung hall that would be big enough to house the Parthenon -
the ruins of which will be visible from inside.
   Sculptures will be displayed suspended in space, in the
positions they occupied in the actual temple, which was built in
the 5th century B.C. Visitors will be able to walk up several
levels, moving up to and around the suspended sculpture as if
passing through the walls of the temple.
   The sculpture depicts a procession in honor of the godess
Athena, a battle between men and centaurs, the birth of Athena and
her contest with the god Poseidon over who would give his name to
the city.
   The building site is at the foot of the Acropolis hill in
central Athens, and the Parthenon will be visible through a
semi-circular ``eye'' set in the sloping ceiling of the
40,000-square-yard building.
   Culture Minister Tzannis Tzannetakis, who announced the result
of the competition, said he did not know when construction will
begin.
   ``We will press ahead to complete it as soon as possible and try
to have it done by 1996,'' he told a news conference.
   He said it was still too soon to know what the cost would be,
but that he would put it ``very vaguely'' between $80 million and
$100 million.
   Tzannetakis said the government will try to raise the money from
the European Community, of which Greece is a member, and private
donors.
   ``Our country faces serious economic problems,'' he said. ``But
the protection of our cultural heritage is our obligation, not only
to history and our ancestors, but toward Europe, of which we are an
inseparable part.''
   The idea of a new museum was first raised in 1976, and the
international competition was announced in May 1989.
   Plans for the museum revived hopes that some of the finest
marble sculpture from the Acropolis could eventually be returned to
Greece. The treasures were removed in the early 19th century by
Lord Elgin, a British diplomat.
   The works, known as the Elgin Marbles, are housed in the British
Museum. The British government has always rejected Greek appeals to
return them.
   But two British members of the 14-member international committee
that chose the winning museum design said the new structure could
justify the return of the priceless sculpture.
   ``My work on this jury was to see that a well-designed museum
was chosen in which one could say that the marbles will be well
cared for,'' said Sir Bernard Feilden, an architect. ``I think we
achieved something. So I hope the marbles will be returned.''
   ``The point is, it seems to be a very good museum to house the
marbles,'' said Jules Lubbock, an architecture professor and art
historian.
   Apart from those in the British Museum, sculptures from the
temples on the Acropolis have been housed in a small museum on the
hill and in the Athens Archaeological Museum.
   Many statues and reliefs that survived earthquakes, fire,
plunder and bombardment have been replaced by copies to protect
them from the air pollution of modern Athens.
   The temples themselves are currently undergoing extensive
restoration work to protect them from the atmosphere and to repair
damage caused by earlier restoration work. Iron rods used in the
19th century to connect blocks of marble have corroded the columns
they were intended to support.
   The restoration work is to be completed in 1995.
   The architects will receive an $80,000 award for their design.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0026 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 1344EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Pope     11-11 0457</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Pope,0555</SECOND>
<HEAD>John Paul Visits Prison of `Living Hell'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARY BETH SHERIDAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NAPLES, Italy (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Pope John Paul II on Sunday visited an
infamous prison known as ``he Living Hell,'' where he prayed with
AIDS victims and urged drug traffickers to go straight.
   John Paul told 300 inmates in the prison chapel that faith could
help them escape an underworld of drug-trafficking, violence and
the Mafia. The theme has marked the pope's five-day visit to the
Naples region, his longest pastoral journey in Italy.
   ``My dear friends, I have come to invite you to have patience,
to seek goodness and mutual understanding,'' the pontiff told the
inmates, most of them in their 20s, clad in jeans.
   ``Think about your families, sorely tried by your condition;
think about those who love you and count on you. Carry a little
serenity within you, even in this place and among yourselves.''
   The 71-year-old Poggioreale prison is the most notorious in
crime-ridden Naples because of overcrowding and poor conditions.
Built for 1,000 prisoners, it housed 2,700 until recently, when
several hundred were transferred to a new prison.
   Many prisoners are detained on drug charges, and 600 are drug
addicts, according to the prison. Among Poggioreale's most famous
inmates was Raffaele Cutolo, a convicted murderer and boss of the
Camorra, the Neapolitan Mafia that controls an international
network of cocaine trafficking.
   On Sunday, the pope saw little of the drudgery that has earned
the prison the nickname ``The Living Hell'' among Neapolitans. A
fresh coat of cream-colored paint covered the prison walls and the
bright white chapel was spotless.
   But a young prisoner, in a short speech, told the pope the
inmates lived in ``sad conditions.''
   ``Above all, when we return to our families, we want to find a
society ready to receive us and to make us feel once again that we
are men, and useful citizens of the community - just like everyone
else,'' the prisoner cried, to the cheers of inmates.
   Several waved small yellow-and-white Vatican flags or olive
branches symbolizing peace. As the pope left, the street-hardened
toughs bent to kiss his ring. They beamed as he warmly greeted
them.
   ``I feel so full of emotion,'' one young inmate told a reporter
before a security guard reimposed himself in front of the
prisoners.
   After the ceremony, the pope walked to the ward reserved for
about 50 AIDS victims. He shook the men's hands and tenderly
stroked their hair, then prayed briefly with them.
   Crime, drugs and unemployment have been important themes of the
pope's trip to Naples, which began Friday. The city has remained a
symbol of urban blight and Mafia power in a nation emerging as a
European economic powerhouse.
   On Saturday, John Paul visited the city's worst slum, urging
residents to ``not give in to evil.'' He also criticized local
politicians for cronyism and appealed for a ``recuperation of
legality.''
   The pope's trip to Poggioreale occurred the day after the
national government enacted measures to limit early releases from
prison.
   An embarrassed Justice Minister Giuliano Vassalli said during
the papal ceremony that the measures ``do not in the least affect
the laws and acts aimed at making prison life more humane and
dignified.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0027 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 1401EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Gulf-GasTraining     11-11 0497</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Gas Training,0638</SECOND>
<HEAD>Soldiers Get A Good Whiff of Gas in Chemical Warfare Training</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Bush-Gulf Strategy, Bjt</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto RM3</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KAREN HAYWOOD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>FORT EUSTIS, Va. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   His eyes teared, his nose ran and his
lungs burned. But Spec. 4 Eric Hackman could do little but endure
te discomfort caused by tear gas wafting through an Army gas
chamber.
   Hackman, 24, of Latrobe, Pa., and other Fort Eustis soldiers got
a good whiff of the gas as part of their training in the use of
masks and clothing designed to protect them from chemical weapons.
   The soldiers had been through the training before. They knew how
to suit up and clear their masks by breathing out hard. But events
in the Persian Gulf were making the refresher course particularly
timely.
   ``In the event he goes to Saudi Arabia and if he doesn't do the
procedure properly, does not clean the mask properly, he could be
exposed to the chemical, get sick - die,'' said Maj. Frank Connor,
chief of the Training Division at Fort Eustis.
   About 230,000 U.S. troops have been sent to the Persian Gulf
since Iraqi President Saddam Hussein sent his army into neighboring
Kuwait on Aug. 2. Saddam has stockpiles of chemical weapons and has
used them against the Kurds in eastern Iraq.
   U.S. soldiers train regularly in putting on their protective
gear and performing their jobs. ``If you are a truck driver, you
have to be able to do your truck driving in an NBC environment,''
said Sgt. 1st Class Larry Price, head of the post's ``NBC'' -
nuclear, biological, chemical - branch.
   Hackman and others volunteered to remove their masks inside the
chamber, a tent set up in a forest clearing. Some commanders
require it as part of the training. Others do not.
   The exercise is intended ``so you will be confident (in the
mask) when you go into the battlefield,'' said Staff Sgt. Marvin
Ward.
   The smell of the gas seeped from the tent and the wind blew it
on those waiting their turn.
   ``Let's get it over with,'' one soldier said.
   About 10 masked soldiers filed into the chamber. When they left
10 minutes later with their masks off, they were bent over,
coughing and waving their hands.
   ``Don't touch your face,'' cautioned Sgt. Donna Niemuth, in
charge of the chamber. ``Look into the wind.''
   Hackman's eyes were redder than most.
   ``You want to rub your eyes,'' said Hackman, of the 155th
Transportation Company based at Fort Eustis. ``Right before I got
out the door, I got a good breath.''
   Spec. 4 Richard Hill, also of the 155th, wasn't as bothered by a
runny nose.
   ``I blew it good before I went in there,'' Hill said. ``It
burns. I want to scratch my eyes. There's a real nasty taste in my
mouth.''
   The tear gas wore off in about 15 minutes.
   The soldiers also spend time in the classroom, learning about
chemical agents much stronger than tear gas.
   Price taught a recent class to members of the Army Reserve's
359th Transportation Battalion based in nearby Hampton.
   Price told them there are four NBC tenets: avoidance, protection
and decontamination, and pulling all three together to perform in a
contaminated environment.
   Chemical warfare agents include nerve gas, blister agents like
mustard agent, and blood agents that strip oxygen from the blood.
They can be fatal or incapacitating, Price said. The effects of
some agents wear off quickly; others can last many years.
   Nerve agents cause loss of muscle control and affect nerve
endings, Price said.
   ``How many of you took Black Flag and sprayed it on a bug?'' he
asked. ``That's what nerve agent does to you.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0028 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 1418EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Obit-Minotis     11-11 0188</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Minotis,0207</SECOND>
<HEAD>Actor Of Ancient Greek Tragedy Dies</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ATHENS, Greece (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Alexis Minotis, Greece's best-known tragic
actor, died Sunday. He was 84.
   Minotis suffered a stroke on Saturday and died early Sunday, the
Athens News Agency reported.
   Minotis was born in Khania, Crete, in 1906 and spent 65 years in
the theater. He was best known for his roles in classical Greek
tragedy. He also wrote essays and was artistic director of the
National Theater for many years.
   Minotis married actress Katina Paxinou during World War II and
they left for the United States. Paxinou had a successful stage and
film career, winning an Academy Award in 1943 for best supporting
actress in the film of Ernest Hemingway's novel ``For Whom The Bell
Tolls.''
   The couple returned to Greece in 1951. Paxinou died in 1973.
   Minotis was removed from the National Theater by the right-wing
military dictatorship in 1967. He returned after its fall in 1974
only to be removed again by the socialist government that came to
power in 1981.
   Minotis last appeared on stage in Samuel Beckett's ``Endgame''
in 1988, in a performance that he also directed. He had planned to
direct Shakespeare's King Lear this winter.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0029 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 1426EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Baker-Canada     11-11 0140</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Baker-Canada,120</SECOND>
<HEAD>Baker To Brief Canadian on Recent Diplomatic Mission on Persian
Gulf</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Secretary of State James A. Baker III will
discuss the Persian Gulf situation with Canada's foreign minister
Joseph Clark on Tuesday, the State Department said Sunday.
   Baker will travel to Bermuda to meet with Clark, State
Department spokeswoman Margaret Tutwiler said in a statement.
   Baker returned Saturday from an eight-day diplomatic mission to
Europe and the Middle East, where he consulted with officials from
nine nations on Iraq's invasion of Kuwait, the subsequent
international sanctions and the U.S. troop buildup in the Persian
Gulf.
   ``The secretary will brief Minister Clark on those meetings and
they will discuss the Persian Gulf in general,'' Tutwiler said.
   Baker will return to Washington the same day.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0030 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 1442EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-UnemployedWinner Bjt   11-11 0445</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Unemployed Winner, Bjt,0538</SECOND>
<HEAD>Unemployed Republican Unseats Democrat With $600 Campaign</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto BX1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By EVE EPSTEIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Donna Lambert, an unemployed factory worker, made
out well in the Massachusetts ``throw-the-bums-out'' election.
Running a $600 campaign, she beat the incumbent for a
$56,000-a-year job as the Middlesex County register of probate.
   ``I am a very nice person who loves people and I am not a
politician,'' said Lambert, 56, a Republican. ``I'm a grandmother
that's been elected to an office.''
   Lambert's Democratic opponent, Tom Larkin, was appointed to the
post by Gov. Michael S. Dukakis in 1989 after his predecessor was
made a judge. He was surprised by the election results, which gave
Lambert a lead of more than 40,000 votes.
   ``She won fair and square. The numbers are clear,'' Larkin said.
   Lambert has been collecting $144 a week in unemployment since
she was laid off from her job with a baby clothes manufacturing
company last June. That job paid $19,000 a year. Her husband works
as an electrical engineer for Polaroid Corp.
   The register of probate's term is six years in Middlesex County,
which includes diverse urban and rural-suburban areas around
Boston. Lambert said she may use the extra money from her new job
to install a swimming pool at home.
   Lambert graduated from high school in Newton, and then did what
she called ``hands-on training'' raising four children. She had a
real estate broker's license at one point, but it has expired.
   ``I think she's in a state of shock. She didn't expect to win,''
said Larkin.
   The register of probate oversees 100 employees and processes
more than 12,000 new cases a year, including divorces, child
support cases and wills. There are eight judges who work full-time
for the court, Larkin said.
   Larkin has two master's degrees, one in psychology and another
in public administration from Harvard University. He also has 10
years of experience as a county commissioner, as well as experience
as the director of special education for the Boston school system.
   Larkin blamed his loss, in part, on the fact that Lambert's name
came first on the ballot. He also said the anti-incumbent
sentiment, which propelled a Republican governor into the
Statehouse to replace Democrat Dukakis, fueled a vote for the
Republican challenger.
   ``It's one way to get off unemployment, but she's going to have
a lot to learn,'' he said.
   Lambert said she has long been involved with the Republican
Party, as a member of the Republican town committee, and said she
has done work at election polls. While working at the polls, she
noticed Republicans never fielded candidates for county jobs.
   ``So I said `That's it, I'll look and see and I'm going to
run,''' she said.
   Larkin spent about $25,000 on the primary campaign, and $5,000
to run against Lambert. His strategy included some television ads,
bumper stickers, and a series of lawyers' breakfasts.
   Lambert's campaign cost $600, and consisted largely of a
letter-writing effort. She had green and beige business cards made
up and mailed them to about 200 people, picked at random from voter
registration lists and the telephone book.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0031 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 1456EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-DayCareTrial     11-11 0569</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Day Care Trial,0714</SECOND>
<HEAD>Child Sex-Abuse Case Drags on in Picturesque Carolina Town</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MICHAEL HOBBS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>EDENTON, N.C. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Colonial-style buildings still line the
business district in this town on Albemarle Sound that once was
North Carolina's colonial capital. The picturesque small town
retains a quaint charm.
   But Edenton also is the site of the state's biggest and most
complicated child-abuse case.
   Prosecutors allege that over the course of a year at the Little
Rascals Day Care Center, 29 children were sexually assaulted by the
owners, employees and a friend of the owner. All seven deny the
charges.
   With more than 400 counts, the case exceeds that of the McMartin
Pre-School trial in California in which the defendants were
acquitted earlier this year. One of those defendants, Raymond
Buckey, was tried a second time, but the prosecution ended with a
deadlocked jury in July and the charges were dropped.
   The McMartin case consumed seven years of court time ad cost
Los Angeles County more than $13.5 million, making it the longest,
most expensive criminal court case in U.S. history.
   Many of Edenton's 5,800 residents are uneasy discussing the case
here. Many have close friends on both sides, and District Attorney
H.P. Williams has asked residents not to spread ``unfounded''
statements about the case.
   ``I'm getting tired of hearing about it,'' said Steve, an
attendant at a service station who wouldn't give his last name. ``I
wish they'd just get going and get it over with. A lot of people
feel that way.''
   The case broke when someone lodged a complaint in January 1989
alleging abuse of children at the center. The state Child Day Care
section in Raleigh revoked the center's license in March 1989 and
one of the center's owners, Bob Kelly, was arrested shortly after.
   Prosecutors allege that children between the ages of 2 and 7
were raped, sodomized and assaulted. The indictments allege that
most of the assaults occurred between September 1988 and January
1989.
   The defendants are Little Rascals co-owners Kelly, 41, and his
wife, Elizabeth Twiddy Kelly, 34; Willard Scott Privott, 40;
Darlene McDonald Harris, 25; and three former employees of the
center - Shelley Alyce Stone, 34; Kathryn Dawn Wilson, 24; and
Robin Boles Byrum, 19. All but two remain in jail in lieu of bond.
   All seven could face multiple life sentences if convicted.
   The case hit a snag in October when the judge handling the case
cited its ``complexities'' and withdrew after the state Supreme
Court overturned his ruling that the defendants should be tried
separately.
   A new judge was selected.
   ``I would say we may not be at square one, but we're certainly
at square two,'' said Joe Cheshire, a lawyer representing Mrs.
Kelly, referring to the new judge.
   The new judge is still looking over the case, Cheshire said
Sunday. ``He is reviewing the file and I assume we are waiting for
a court date at which we will discuss where we stand.'' He said no
decision had been made on whether the defendants would stand trial
together or in small groups.
   Bill Hart, a lawyer from the state attorney general's office
assigned to help prosecute the case, said that the earliest it
could go to trial would be January.
   ``We're hoping (the trial) will only take six to eight weeks,''
Hart said. ``Of course, you never can guarantee about the length of
a trial.''
   Cheshire said that in his opinion, a January trial is``highly
unlikely, seeking as how it's almost Thanksgiving.''
   A civil suit filed against Mrs. Kelly provides a glimpse into
what kind of case the prosecution could present.
   ``We anticipate that some of the children will testify, some of
parents will testify and counselors will testify,'' said C. Everett
Thompson II, a lawyer representing the plaintiffs in the negligence
suit. The suit has been put on hold at the request of prosecutors.
   Some of the children are still troubled, Thompson said.
   ``They're going through therapy, they're getting treatment,'' he
said. ``We think it will be a long time before we really know the
extent of the damage and the scarring that occurred to these
children.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0032 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 1508EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Vietnam-US     11-11 0349</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Vietnam-US,0422</SECOND>
<HEAD>Vietnam Links Base Access to Lifting of Trade Embargo</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BANGKOK, Thailand (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Vietnam has offered to allow the United
States to use a former U.S. naval base if Washington lifts a
26-year-old trade embargo, the official Vietnam News Agency
reported Sunday.
   The offer by Communist Party chief Nguyen Van Linh also applies
to Japan, which follows the boycott, said the agency, monitored in
Bangkok.
   The agency report was based on an interview given by Linh to
Japan's NHK television company.
   The former U.S. base at Cam Ranh Bay, about 175 miles northeast
of Ho Chi Hinh City, formerly Saigon, has been a Soviet military
site since the Vietnam War ended in 1975.
   The Soviet Union has said it maintains no more than a token
presence at Cam Ranh Bay and intends to withdraw completely.
Vietnam's foreign minister, Nguyen Co Thach, has said the
withdrawal would be completed by 1992.
   The trade embargo was imposed on Communist North Vietnam in 1964
and was extended to the entire country following the fall of the
U.S.-backed Saigon government in 1975.
   Washington has had no diplomatic relations with Vietnam since
the war ended. Secretary of State James A. Baker III and Thach met
in October.
   Linh said he hope relations with Japan would improve if ties
with Washington were normalized.
   ``I know that Japan wants to cooperate and do business with
Vietnam, but it is tied to the U.S. policy of embargo. I believe
Japan will be more resolved to do business with Vietnam,'' he said.
   Linh also told the Japanese network that Vietnam would permit
U.S. and Japanese investment around the country, the agency
reported.
   ``If you want to do business, you may invest not only in Cam
Ranh, but in other ports as well,'' Linh was quoted as saying.
   In the news agency report, Linh appeared to confirm reports that
he took part in a three-member delegation that visited Beijing in
September.
   The reported meeting with Chinese Premier Li Peng, would have
been the highest level contact between the countries since their
border war in 1979 following Vietnam's invasion of Cambodia.
   But Linh said Cambodia was just one of the obstacles to
normalization of relations with China.
   ``There has been misunderstanding ... on the Cambodian issue as
well as on bilateral relations. This misunderstanding is being
removed gradually. The two countries have stopped firing at each
other and are conducting cross border trade,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0033 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 1516EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SriLanka     11-11 0231</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Sri Lanka,0250</SECOND>
<HEAD>Governemnt Troops Claim 19 Tamil Rebels Killed</HEAD>
<DATELINE>COLOMBO, Sri Lanka (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Government troops killed 19 Tamil
rebels and one soldier died in at least four battles around Sri
Lanka, military officials said Sunday.
   There was no word on the reported skirmishes from the rebels,
who have waged a seven-year fight against the Sinhalese-dominated
government for an autonomous homeland. The government claim could
not be independently confirmed.
   The officials, who cannot be identified under briefing rules,
said troops destroyed many underground bunkers Saturday, killing
nine militants. Also, one soldier was killed and five were injured
in fighting near Trincomalee, a port city 150 miles northeast of
Colombo.
   Four rebels died when their truck was straffed by a helicopter
gunship Saturday in the northern town of Chavakachcheri, 185 miles
north of Colombo, the officials said.
   They said a naval gunboat destroyed a fishing trawler near the
Pungudutivu village, also in the north, killing four rebels. The
vessel was believed to be used by guerrillas for gunrunning.
   Two rebels were killed near Manmunai village in the eastern
Batticaloa district.
   The officials did not say when the two attacks took place.
   More than 14,000 people have been killed in the civil war.
Tamils claim they are discriminated in jobs, education and the use
of Sinhala language.
   Tamils make up 18 percent of the island's 16 million people. The
Sinhalese comprise 75 percent of the population and control the
government and the military.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0034 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 1522EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Soviet-NATO     11-11 0247</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-NATO,0258</SECOND>
<HEAD>NATO Generals Arrive for Visit, Praise East-West Cooperation</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two NATO generals arrived Sunday in the first
visit to the Soviet Union by high-ranking military officials of the
Western alliance.
   American Gen. John R. Galvin, the alliance's supreme military
commander in Europe, and Norwegian Gen. Vigleik Eide, chairman of
NATO's military committee, were welcomed at Moscow's Sheremetyevo
Airport by Soviet Gen. Mikhail Moiseyev, chief of the general
staff, the official Tass news agency reported.
   Eide told Tass that he was satisfied with the better relations
between leaders of the North Atlantic Treaty Organization and
Warsaw Pact countries.
   ``The present relations between military leaders of the two
blocs are distinguished by their frankness and a sincere desire for
compromises on all issues,'' Tass quoted him as saying.
   ``We should move from confrontation to cooperation to greater
openness and mutual trust,'' Eide said, according to the
independent Interfax news service.
   Galvin and Eide will hold several days of talks with political
and military officials, including perhaps President Mikhail S.
Gorbachev, then go on separate visits to different parts of the
Soviet Union.
   Eide will go to Leningrad to meet with regional military
officials, and Galvin will visit the Kiev Military District and the
Soviet Black Sea fleet in Sevastopol before returning to Belgium.
   Soviet Foreign Minister Eduard Shevardnadze was the first
foreign minister of a Warsaw Pact nation to visit NATO headquarters
in a symbolic end to East-West military hostilities. Moiseyev
visited the 16-member Western alliance last month.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0035 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 1523EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Britain-Miscarriage     11-11 0226</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Britain-Miscarriage,0249</SECOND>
<HEAD>Blood Test Could Target Women Likely to Miscarry</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A simple blood test conducted before pregnancy
might be a new way of identifying women at high risk of
miscarrying, according to research published in a British medical
journal.
   Writing in the Nov. 10 edition of The Lancet, the researchers
said it was the first time that measuring hormone levels before a
woman conceives has been found to predict whether a pregnancy will
be successfully carried to term.
   The doctors tested for the luteinising hormone (LH), which
controls ovulation.
   Dr. Lesley Regan, Dr. Elisabeth Owen and Professor Howard Jacobs
tested 193 women planning to become pregnant. The women ranged in
age from 21 to 43, with a median age of 30.7.
   The obstetricians from the Rosie Maternity Hospital, Cambridge
and University College Medical School wrote that 88 percent of the
women with normal LH levels conceived within 18 months. Only 67
percent of the women with abnormally high LH levels conceived
within that period.
   In the normal LH group, 12 percent of the women suffered
miscarriages. In the high group, 65 percent miscarried.
   The doctors concluded that a raised serum LH concentration in
the early phase of pregnancy confers a substantial risk of
miscarriage. The finding offers the possibility of a simple
predictive test for women before pregnancy.
   An abnormal result could also be used to identify patients that
could be treated to suppress excessive secretion of LH.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0036 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 1543EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Israel 1stLd-Writethru a0631 11-11 0574</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0631,0685</SECOND>
<HEAD>Police Officials Replaced in Temple Mount Shakeup</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: New throughout to UPDATE with police force shakeup, soldier
wounded in West Bank. No pickup.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By GWEN ACKERMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two top police officials were replaced in a
shakeup stemming from last month's Temple Mount killings, officials
said Sunday.
   The Cabinet, meanwhile, discussed a compromise move to allay
international criticism of Israel over the Oct. 8 Temple Mount
shootings, in which 20 Arabs were killed by police gunfire.
   Also Sunday, authorities announced 2,400 more Palestinians would
be banned from entering Israel for security reasons, and an Israeli
soldier was shot and wounded in the West Bank.
   In the police shakeup, Jerusalem police chief Aryeh Bibi and
Rachamim Comfort, commander of the southern police district which
includes Jerusalem, were reassigned.
   Both were strongly criticized in a government report on the
Temple Mount killings. The report, compiled by a three-member
investigating team, condoned the use of live fire on stone throwers
and said Palestinians started the riot, but criticized police for
failing to anticipate the violence.
   In the wake of the report, Police Minister Roni Milo decided to
create a new police district in Jerusalem. Chaim Albaldes,
currently head of the central police district, will become
commander of the new district, thus removing Bibi.
   Comfort was replaced by Rafi Peled, currently chief of the
National Police intelligence department.
   The report had criticized both Comfort and Bibi for bad judgment
and mistaken assessment of intelligence data in the Temple Mount
incident.
   Israel radio reported that Comfort and Peled will work together
for several months, and then Comfort would retire early.
   Bibi's name was not included in the list of new appointments.
The radio said he was expected to be moved to another post which
would not entail a promotion in rank.
   Jerusalem was swept by a wave of Jewish-Arab street clashes
following the Temple Mount shootings. In recent weeks, police
strength in Jerusalem reached 2,000 officers, about one-eighth of
the police force for the entire country.
   In the Cabinet discussion of international criticism over the
Temple Mount shootings, ministers suggested Sunday they would be
willing to welcome a U.N. envoy - if the visit was not directly
tied to a Security Council resolution condemning Irael.
   Foreign Minister David Levy told army radio that a compromise
was being discussed both at the United Nations and with U.S.
officials in Washington.
   He acknowledged the government was trying to head off another
Security Council resolution that could call for specific steps
against Israel, and was hoping to persuade Washington to veto such
a move.
   ``All our efforts are aimed at preventing a negative decision
regarding Israel and we are acting in every way possible including
the strengthening of our understanding with the United States,''
Levy said.
   The decision to ban more Palestinians from entering Israel
brings to 10,800 the number of Arabs from the occupied West Bank
and Gaza Strip who are blocked from visiting or working in Israel.
   The decision was announced by Shmuel Goren, the coordinator for
the occupied territories. He said on Israel radio that the program
would cover Palestinians from ``security and criminal categories,
those who the police and security elements believe constitute a
security risk.''
   Military government spokesman Shmuel Ozenboy said the move would
take effect this week, but he would not be more specific.
   About 110,000 residents of the territories captured by Israel in
the 1967 Middle East war work in Israel. Palestinians have
complained new limits on workers could hurt the territories'
economy since few jobs are available outside Israel.
   The soldier who was wounded Sunday was shot near Bet El, a
Jewish settlement in the West Bank about 10 miles north of
Jerusalem, the army command said. It said assailants in a car fired
at him as he was waiting at a bus stop, and the soldier fired back,
the army said.
   The soldier suffered arm and leg wounds, but they were not
serious, the army added.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0037 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 1559EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ArtMarket     11-11 0564</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Art Market,0730</SECOND>
<HEAD>Art Dealers On Auction Bidding: `The Party's Over'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CATHERINE CROCKER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Last week's contemporary art sales confirmed
that the steam has gone out of the art market, according to art
experts, and more disappointing prices could emerge this week in
sales of works from the estates of Henry Ford II and Greta Garbo.
   The euphoria that once gripped auction rooms is gone amid fears
of a U.S. recession.
   But if the market has fallen, it's far from dead, experts say.
Speculators who didn't know Pissarro from Picasso may have departed
but serious collectors who know art and buy for the long term are
bidding.
   ``What we are missing are the headline-grabbing situations that
we had in the last couple of years,'' said William E. O'Reilly of
Salander-O'Reilly Galleries Inc. ``Now I think we have a more
conservative buying public ... whereas perhaps there was more of a
festival mood about it before.''
   Sotheby's auction of postwar art Tuesday was certainly no
festival.
   Fewer than half of the works offered - 34 out of 77 - were sold,
the rest failing to reach the minimum price the sellers had in
mind. And the total for the sale was $19.8 million, only half of
the lowest pre-sale estimate by the auction house.
   Christie's sale the following night was a bit more upbeat.
Thirty of the 58 lots sold for a total of $36.7 million, against a
pre-sale estimate by the auction house of $47.7 million to $65.4
million.
   Willem de Kooning's ``July,'' a large abstract canvas of
fractured shapes and obscured colors painted in 1956, sold for $8.8
million, well above its high-end estimate of $7 million.
   ``The very top market usually sustains itself,'' said Bonnie
Barrett Stretch, editor of the ARTnewsletter, a biweekly report on
the international art market. ``True masterpieces sustain prices
through thick and thin.''
   That may not bode well for this week's sale of impressionist
paintings since art experts agree that few outstanding works are up
for sale. If sales are sluggish, they say, it will have more to do
with the quality of the art offered than the state of the market.
   Stretch says the absence of great art works has to do with luck
of the draw and a reluctance among some owners to sell in the
current market.
   The art collection of the late Henry Ford II will be auctioned
on Monday at Sotheby's. The most important work is Renoir's ``Cup
of Chocolate,'' an oil on canvas painted about 1878 of a young
woman seated with a cup and saucer at her side.
   The pre-sale estimate for the painting is $15 million to $18
million.
   On Thursday, the art collection of film legend Greta Garbo will
go on the block at Sotheby's.
   Sotheby's is counting on people buying because of the Garbo
name, said Harry Brooks, director of Wildenstein Co. Inc., a New
York art gallery.
   ``But there are really only three important Renoirs and a
Bonnard,'' he said. ``If that sale doesn't do well that doesn't
mean anything because the whole sale is sort of overblown.''
   Christie's will sell a still life by Vincent van Gogh on
Wednesday. ``Vase With Daisies and Poppies,'' painted in the French
town of Auvers shortly before his death in 1890, has a pre-sale
estimate of $12 million to $16 million.
   None of these prices approaches the staggering records set
during the spring auction sales, when van Gogh's ``Portrait of Dr.
Gachet'' brought $82.5 million at Christie's and Renoir's ``At the
Moulin de la Galette'' fetched $78.1 million at Sotheby's.
   The total estimate for the art to be auctioned at the two houses
during the two weeks of major fall sales is $508 million to $665
million. The May series of sales brought $925.7 million.
   Allan Stone, a New York dealer, says the auction rooms had
become ``theaters of the absurd'' in recent years. Not only did
great art realize record-breaking prices but lesser art fetched
higher prices than good art in galleries.
   ``The New Year's Eve party is over. People are doing their
homework,'' he said. The auction houses will have ``to weed out the
material that comes in and offer just the best quality stuff.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0038 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 1606EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Germany-RedArmy     11-11 0273</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Germany-Red Army,0308</SECOND>
<HEAD>Kohl Promises Visit to Troubled Soviet Troops in Germany</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LARRY THORSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Chancellor Helmut Kohl promised to visit Soviet
troops in eastern Germany after Soviet President Mikhail S.
Gorbachev expressed concern over reported problems facing the
soldiers, a government spokesman said Sunday.
   Gorbachev on Saturday ended a two-day trip to Germany during
which he signed a 20-year treaty of non-aggression, friendship and
cooperation.
   But he returned to Moscow without receiving any commitment for
economic aid beyond the $19.5 billion already promised by the
German government and banks.
   Most of the aid is to pay for withdrawing the troops and for
housing and retraining in the Soviet Union.
   On Friday, Gorbachev mentioned in a speech his concern over an
``anti-Soviet flavor'' in German public attitudes toward the
380,000 Red Army soldiers remaining in former East Germany.
   A government spokesman, who spoke on condition of anonymity,
confirmed a report in the conservative Welt am Sonntag newspaper
that Kohl promised he would visit Soviet military camps in the
coming year and speak with the troops. The Soviet military forces
are scheduled to withdraw over the next four years, and there are
reports of poor morale, extortion, desertions and violence among
the soldiers already.
   The two Germanys united on Oct. 3 and the nation became a NATO
member.
   The German magazine Stern, in its most recent edition, said
older soldiers were beating up younger ones to force them to hand
over their pay. It also said the number of suicides among the
troops was high.
   Soviet troops lead closely restricted lives in the German bases,
but there are German news reports that some have deserted to live
in the forests and others are stealing weapons and military
hardware to sell on the black market.

</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0039 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 1609EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People     11-11 0582</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People,0774</SECOND>
<HEAD>People in the News</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY44</HEAD>
<DATELINE>GLENDALE, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Singer David Crosby, comic Jay Leno and
wrestler Hulk Hogan straddled motorcycles Sunday and led thousands
of bikers on ``Love Ride 7'' to benefit the Muscular Dystrophy
Association.
   ``For some crazy reason we feel that if we all ride together
maybe we can come up with enough money and a miracle to whip this
disease,'' Hogan said before heading out for an afternoon
rendezvous in the Malibu hills.
   The wrestler said he got involved because he's a parent and
cares about kids.
   ``I've had mothers call me up and cry and kids beg me to help,''
Hogan said. ``I've seen it all.''
   Last year, the event attracted 7,000 bikers and raised more than
$500,000 for MDA. This year's crowd was estimated to reach 10,000
by the end of the day.
   The ``Love Ride'' is a 100-mile journey from a Harley-Davidson
dealership in Glendale to the Calamigos Ranch in the Santa Monica
Mountains north of Malibu. Participants pledge a minimum $40 and
are treated to an afternoon of food and music, including
performances by Crosby and Jackson Browne.
   Proceeds benefit MDA's six Los Angeles County clinics.
   ---
   NEW YORK (AP) - What's inspiration sound like in the brain of
comedian and actor Robin Williams? Something like ``Bing!''
   Williams says some of his happiest moments have been when his
improvisation comes together while he's doing a stand-up comedy
routine.
   ``When you find that new idea, when you come up with a concept
and find that it works, it's the creation of the moment that's so
incredible,'' Williams said in Sunday's The New York Times
Magazine.
   ``And you know, they've discovered there actually is a slight
endorphin release during creative moments,'' he said, referring to
a brain chemical. ``It's like, Bing! This is part of evolution.''
   Williams, who has been nominated for two Academy Awards for his
roles in ``Good Morning, Vietnam'' and ``Dead Poets Society,''
stars in the movie ``Awakenings,'' which is due out next month.
   ``Awakenings,'' which also stars Robert De Niro, is based on a
book of medical case studies by the neurologist Oliver Sacks.
   ---
   RADNOR, Pa. (AP) - Andy Griffith says he'll take down his
lawyer's shingle after this season, his fifth as the title
character of NBC's ``Matlock.''
   ``I'm financially comfortable. I'm in my 60s and there's no
reason to stay around,'' the 64-year-old actor said in the Nov. 17
issue of TV Guide. ``After this season, I'm leaving, and that's
it.''
   But the show's executive producer, Fred Silverman, said he
thinks the odds are 50-50 that Griffith will sign for another
season.
   Griffith says Silverman is wrong.
   ``I know I want to go home, is all. ... I don't need any
pressure on me, people thinking they see an opening and coming
after me,'' Griffith said. ``I went through that, one season in the
'60s, and I lost all of my determination to quit then. I'd just as
soon not see that happen again.''
   Griffith planned on quitting CBS's ``The Andy Griffith Show'' in
1967 after seven seasons. His contract had expired and he hoped to
prove wrong those who attributed his success in the role of Andy
Taylor ``to some nonsense that I was only playing myself.''
   But the network offered him a salary figure he called
staggering, and he relented.
   Now, Griffith said, ``it's time to wrap it up.''
   ``I've enjoyed the show, but I don't need this grind anymore,''
he said. ``Time to move on. I want to go home.''
   ---
   NEW YORK (AP) - What's money, anyway, reasons Ray Charles, who
says that after all, he can sleep in only ``one bed at a time.''
   In the Nov. 17 issue of People magazine, Charles said he doesn't
buy into some of the praise his peers have heaped on him over the
years, such as Frank Sinatra's once calling him ``the only genius
in the business.''
   ``I'll get all the accolades, but at my best I will never make
half the money Sinatra has made,'' said Charles, known for such
hits as ``Hit the Road, Jack'' and ``What'd I Say.''
   ``But when you break it down, what does it matter? I can only
sleep in one bed at at a time. I can only make love to one woman at
a time,'' he said.
   Charles, 60, has nine children, ages 14 to 40, by seven women,
and seven grandchildren.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0040 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 1610EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-WashStorms     11-11 0538</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Wash Storms,0657</SECOND>
<HEAD>Struggle to Save Downtown Mount Vernon as Flooding Subsides
Upstream</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto staffing</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MOUNT VERNON, Wash. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hundreds of volunteers joined
National Guard and Army Corps of Engineer troops Sunday in a battle
to save Mount Vrnon's downtown from the rain-swollen Skagit River.
   ``We are in a full flood fight,'' said Dave Brookings, Skagit
County assistant flood control engineer.
   But elsewhere, many of the more than 500 residents displaced by
near-record flood levels on seven northwest Washington rivers were
returning home, and most dikes and levees held in low-lying areas.
   Three houses were lost in an isolated resort town, and officials
said damage to roads, bridges and homes and businesses from
flooding Friday and Saturday would run to millions of dollars.
   High water, slides and washouts closed numerous roads and
highways, including the Trans Canada Highway north of Hope, British
Columbia, about 90 miles east of Vancouver.
   No injuries were reported.
   The three-day deluge was produced by the ``Pineapple Express,''
what National Weather Service forecasters call a fall storm route
from Hawaii to the Pacific Northwest.
   In Mount Vernon, with a population of about 14,500, Brookings
said 400 to 500 people filled sandbags as the Skagit River crested
at 35.2 feet, 7.2 feet over flood stage.
   Three to four feet of sandbags were piled atop a 34-foot
revetment protecting the downtown area, Brookings said.
   ``This is all just flat farmland,'' he said. ``After it gets
over the levees, that water just keeps spreading.''
   Downstream, where the Skagit divides before emptying into Skagit
Bay, about 60 people were evacuated late Saturday from Fir Island
and 50 or so left Conway, Brookings said.
   Dozens of people filled sandbags to shore up shaky dikes near
Conway to try to prevent the displacement of an additional 500 to
600 people, he said.
   ``It looks like we've got it under control,'' he said.
   He said approximately 150 people forced from their homes in
three areas near Concrete, about 30 miles east of Mount Vernon and
60 miles north of Seattle, would begin returning home Sunday.
   The Skagit would have risen about 3 feet higher at Mount Vernon
had floodgates not been closed upstream at Seattle City Light and
Puget Sound Power &amp; Light Co. hydroelectric dams, said Larry Merkle
of the Army Corps of Engineers reservoir control center in Seattle.
   In Whatcom County, the most hard-hit by flooding Friday and
Saturday, damage could approach $10 million, said Bill Quehrn of
the county Department of Emergency Services.
   About 200 people were evacuated from Sumas on the Canadian
border and dozens more from Everson, but most were returning Sunday
as the water subsided, Quehrn said.
   ``The towns that were flooded yesterday are drying out,'' he
said. ``It's down to puddles in the street.''
   About 100 people in and around the Lummi Indian Reservation
north of Bellingham were displaced after dikes failed along the
lower Nooksack River.
   A plugged storm drain led to the evacuation of 15 to 20 people
from a dozen homes about 16 miles south of Bellingham, Quehrn said.
   The resulting two-acre pond, as deep as 25 feet, was undermining
a scenic highway and draining toward the homes, which range from
expensive year-round residences to summer and vacation cottages
overlooking Samish Bay, he said.
   At Glacier, 40 miles east of Bellingham, three homes in the
Glacier Springs subdivision tumbled 40 to 50 feet into Canyon
Creek, which eroded the bank.
   In Snohomish County, the main concern was for dikes protecting
Ebey Island, home to about 300 to 400 people in the Snohomish River
east of Everett.
   A few miles upstream, two hours of sandbagging by about 40
people averted major flooding at Snohomish, said Al Amonson, staff
coordinator in the Snohomish County Department of Emergency
Management.
   ``They caught it just in time,'' Amonson said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0041 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 1611EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-MustangRanch     11-11 0388</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mustang Ranch,0469</SECOND>
<HEAD>From the Practical to the Bizarre, It's All For Sale At Brothel
Auction</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SANDRA CHEREB</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MUSTANG, Nev. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A little bit of everything will be for sale
when the Mustang Ranch brothel falls under an auctioneer's gavel
Tuesday, from household items to gaudy relics of America's
best-known sporting house.
   ``We highly encourage the neighborhood yard sale enthusiast to
come out and make a bid on anything they may want,'' said Internal
Revenue Service manager Dierdre Pagni.
   Ms. Pagni conceded that, despite her agency's familiarity with
such sales, it's hard to predict what the turnout will be for the
bankruptcy auction.
   ``We've never done this with the Mustang Ranch before,'' she
said.
   The event is expected to draw curiosity seekers as well as
serious bidders. IRS agents padlocked the 104-room bordello on
Sept. 21, three days after the property owned by Joe and Sally
Conforte was forced into bankruptcy liquidation.
   The government's intent is to recoup a portion of the $13
million in back taxes it says is owed by the Confortes. The auction
has been advertised in newspapers around the country, including The
Wall Street Journal.
   The IRS hopes to get at least $1.8 million, largely from the
sale of the ranch's real estate holdings.
   Two buildings which make up the ranch compound will be sold
separately, as will a 60-unit trailer park in nearby Lockwood and
the 440 acres surrounding the brothel, 10 miles east of Reno just
off Interstate 80.
   So far the brothel has piqued interest as a potential nursing
home, a halfway house and a home for wayward girls. Even a
religious group has inquired about the property, although the IRS
has remained mum on details.
   While Tuesday's auction will cover many of the types of items
found at a typical garage sale, there are others that definitely
are not.
   Amid the lamps, couches and bottles of booze are large paintings
of nude women, a painting of Conforte, boxes of condoms and framed
posters pointing out the locations of Nevada's legal bordellos.
   There even is a picture of heavyweight boxer Oscar Bonavena, who
was gunned down at the gates of the Mustang in 1976 by Conforte
bodyguard Willard Ross Brymer.
   The Confortes started the Mustang Ranch, illegally at first, in
the 1950s. In 1960, local authorities proclaimed it a public
nuisance and burned it to the ground.
   But a decade later Conforte won approval from Storey County to
operate the brothel, paving the way for legalized prostitution in
most rural Nevada counties.
   County commissioners last month revoked the permit allowing
prostitution at the Mustang Ranch, saying they would never again
endure the circus atmosphere that has surrounded it the past 35
years.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0042 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 1618EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-VeteransDay     11-11 0318</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Veterans Day,0384</SECOND>
<HEAD>American Servicemen in Persian Gulf Remember Past Veterans</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Veterans Day, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>IN EASTERN SAUDI ARABIA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   U.S. troops in the Mideast on
Sunday remembered those who died for their country, and some
wondered whether there would be casualties from the Persian Gulf
crisis to mourn next year.
   The human cost of any offensive against Iraq to liberate Kuwait
is ``a question that's on everybody's mind,'' said 2nd Lt. Benjamin
Lacy, 23, of Largo, Fla. He is with the Army's 15th Financial
Support Unit.
   ``It looks like many people will be marching in next year's
Veterans Day parades with a banner saying Desert Shield '90-'91,''
he said.
   Veterans Day was not a holiday for the 230,000 American troops
deployed in the Persian Gulf, but many remembered their fellow
soldiers who fought in previous wars.
   ``I know that we're over here now to protect American interests
and personally myself, I think about the people that served in
Vietnam,'' said 2nd Lt. Tony Ferguson, 31, of Bahama, N.C. He
belongs to the North Carolina National Guard, which was activated
for Desert Shield.
   ``And that's what Veteran's Day is about to me, remembering the
people who gave their lives for our country in the past.''
   For Lacy, Veterans Day ``means many people before me put their
life on the line. Many died, some are scarred for life. It's time
to honor them.''
   Forty-six soldiers have died so far in Operation Desert Shield,
which was launched in response to Iraq's Aug. 2 takeover of Kuwait.
   At a religious service at his desert camp on Saturday night, he
said, the chaplain delivered a homily on Veterans Day and the
importance of honoring those who served their country.
   Sgt. Terry L. Wright, 43, the postmaster of Pinellas Park, Fla.,
arrived here Saturday with the 37th Air Evacuation Unit, a reserve
unit activated about 10 days ago.
   ``I feel bad about having to be here today,'' he said. ``If I
was home, it would be a holiday, and I'd be drinking beer and
putting my feet up.''
   British servicemen also remembered their war dead Sunday on
their country's Remembrance Day. The Irish Hussars, one of the
British regiments, had a small ceremony with bagpipes and a bugler.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0043 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 1624EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-JetSmugglingTrial     11-11 0465</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Jet Smuggling Trial,0565</SECOND>
<HEAD>Trial Of Man Charged With Smuggling Jet Fighters To Begin</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ALAN FLIPPEN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUFFALO, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A shadowy trade in armaments abandoned by
the United States at the end of the Vietnam War will be illuminated
in a trial scheduled to begin this week in federal court.
   Cenon Rey Avelino, a Canadian citizen of Filipino origin, is
accused of trying to smuggle two Cessna A-37 Dragonfly jets from
Vietnam into the United States after selling the jets to undercover
U.S. Customs agents for $306,000.
   The light attack planes, dismantled and crated, were seized a
year ago by Customs agents at Buffalo's international Peace Bridge.
Avelino was later indicted on charges ranging from money-laundering
to violating the Trading with the Enemy Act.
   His trial begins Tuesday before U.S. District Judge John T.
Elfvin and is expected to last about three weeks. Avelino, who has
been held without bail since his arrest, could face more than 10
years in prison if convicted on all charges.
   Avelino, 40, of suburban Toronto, is portrayed in court papers
as a globe-trotting arms dealer who boasted he could obtain a
variety of military hardware abandoned by the United States in
Vietnam.
   The Pentagon has estimated that nearly 1,000 military planes,
including 113 Dragonflys, were abandoned in Vietnam when the United
States pulled out in 1975. Also abandoned were 940 naval ships and
boats, 42,000 trucks, 791,000 M-16 rifles and a large amount of
other assorted weaponry.
   Avelino told the agents he represented the government of Vietnam
and could get $18 million worth of arms from that country,
according to statements filed in court by U.S. Customs and Royal
Canadian Mounted Police officers.
   Federal officials have said they are concerned that Vietnam may
be selling abandoned U.S. arms to Third World countries unfriendly
to the United States.
   At a pretrial hearing last winter, the customs agent in charge
of the case, C.W. Moore, said agents had considered trying to get
Avelino to work for them so the U.S. government could acquire more
of the abandoned arms and keep them from falling ``into the hands
of madmen.''
   That idea was scuttled when the Customs Service and the Defense
Department refused to pay for the scheme, Moore said.
   U.S. Attorney Dennis C. Vacco has said the undercover agents who
dealt with Avelino in Toronto and Jacksonville, Fla., portrayed
American businessmen. He refused to say what reasons the agents
gave for wanting the jets.
   James Harrington, Avelino's lawyer, has said his client is a
legitimate businessman who never concealed his ties to the
government of Vietnam.
   The jets had been sitting idle for 15 years and were in no shape
for combat, Harrington said. He said Avelino understood the agents
wanted them for parts.
   The A-37, according to Air Force manuals, can carry various
combinations of rockets and bombs under its wings. The planes also
could be equipped with 7.62mm machine guns.
   A-37s, which could fly more than 500 mph and higher than 40,000
feet, originally cost U.S. taxpayers more than $1 million apiece
when they were built in the 1950s and '60s.
   Avelino told Customs agents at the border that his cargo
included dismantled jets. But he misrepresented the type of
aircraft and declared their value to be only $36,000, authorities
said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0044 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 1625EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Germany-SoccerRiots     11-11 0271</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Germany-Soccer Riots,0307</SECOND>
<HEAD>Forty Arrested as Soccer Rowdies Rampage in Eastern Germany</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hooligans smashed cars and broke windows after
soccer games in two cities in eastern Germany, and police arrested
40 people, the ADN news agency said.
   Violence broke out after a game in Magdeburg on Saturday between
the local team and Dynamo Dresden, ADN said.
   Before and during the game, which FC Magdeburg won 3-1, there
was no trouble. But rival fans fought outside the stadium after the
game ended, ADN said late Saturday.
   Police moved in to break up the fights and escorted visiting
Dresden fans to the local train station to make their connections
home, it said.
   Later, about 150 mostly young hooligans, some wearing ski masks,
began rampaging through downtown Magdeburg, smashing windows with
rocks, and destroying a car, ADN said.
   The violence abated after police arrested 29 people, the agency
said.
   A day earlier, in Rostock, about 30 soccer holligans rampaged
through the downtown, smashing windows and plundering a liquor
store, after local team FC Hansa beat Sachsen Leipzig 2-1.
   No injuries were reported in the riots, although police arrested
11 people, according to ADN.
   Police said most of those detained in both riots were released
after identity checks. Charges of property damage and disorderly
conduct were expected to be filed against some of them, ADN
reported.
   The riots came one week after fans turned violent in Leipzig
after a soccer match. In that violence, police shot and killed an
18-year-old man. Police said the shooting was in self-defense after
rioters attacked officers.
   Fan violence in the former East Germany has increased recently,
leading officials to consider canceling a game in Leipzig on Nov.
21 between the world champion German national team and former East
German national players.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0045 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 1628EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-WeatherpageWeather     11-11 0261</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Weatherpage Weather,0309</SECOND>
<HEAD>Snow &amp; Rain In Northeast, Warmer In West</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Rain and snow were scattered from the Great Lakes into the
Northeast on Sunday, while parts of the West warmed to record
highs.
   Snow fell over northern Maine during the early afternoon, and
from south-central New York state across east-central New York
state. Snow showers extended over southern and eastern Michigan.
   A winter weather advisory was posted into early Monday over New
York state's western Mohawk Valley and the western Adirondaks. Wind
was expected to gust to more than 30 mph into Monday and produce
wind chill factors below zero.
   Heaviest snowfall during the six hours up to 1 p.m. EST was 1
inch at Limestone, Maine, and Sault Ste. Marie, Mich.
   At the same time atop New Hampshire's Mount Washington, the
highest mountain in the Northeast at over 6,200 feet, the
temperature was 5 above zero and wind gusted to near 115 mph,
producing a wind chill of 46 below zero.
   Rain was scattered over northeastern Illinois and southeastern
Wisconsin.
   Rain also fell along the northern coast of Washington state,
where three days of steady rain had caused extensive flooding.
   Sunday's low for the Lower 48 states was 10 at Gunnison, Colo.,
and Truckee, Calif.
   But other spots in the West hit record highs, including 63 at
Kalispell, Mont.; 86 at Santa Maria, Calif., and 72 at Sheridan,
Wyo. Spokane, Wash., tied its record of 60, set in 1892.
   Elsewhere, Hollywood, Fla., cooled to 51 during the morning for
a record low.
   And Fairbanks, Alaska, chilled to 34 below zero, one degree
below the previous record set last year.
   Temperatures around the nation at 3 p.m. EST ranged from 23 at
Warroad, Minn., to 89 at the San Diego Naval Air Station.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0046 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 1636EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-SpaceShuttle     11-11 0275</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Space Shuttle,0317</SECOND>
<HEAD>NASA Prepares for Atlantis Countdown</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Will be topped after start of countdown at 10:30 p.m. EST</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By MARCIA DUNN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Aerospace Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CAPE CANAVERAL, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   NASA on Sunday prepared for the
launch of the space shuttle Atlantis, which is to carry a spy
satellite into orbit after being grounded for months by fuel leaks.
   The countdown was to begin at 10:30 p.m. EST.
   Atlantis is scheduled to lift off Thursday sometime between 6:30
p.m. and 10:30 p.m. EST. The precise time will not be announced
until nine minutes before launch because of the classified nature
of the military mission.
   Atlantis' five astronauts will deploy the satellite, which
published reports say will spy on Iraq. It is believed to be a
photographic imaging or an eavesdropping spacecraft.
   The mission originally was planned for July, but was put on hold
when Atlantis was found in June to have hydrogen leaks. Columbia
also was crippled by hydrogen leaks, and NASA temporarily grounded
the entire three-shuttle fleet.
   NASA replaced Atlantis' external fuel tank, hydrogen lines
between the orbiter and tank, and valve seals. A fueling test last
month found the shuttle to be free of dangerous leaks.
   During the interim, the Air Force is reported to have modified
the satellite so it could spy on Iraq.
   Atlantis has not flown since March, when it conducted another
secret Pentagon mission. Its upcoming trip will be the 37th shuttle
flight and the seventh mission dedicated entirely to the Defense
Department.
   The flight is expected to last four days. A public blackout will
be imposed throughout the mission, and no information will be
released.
   NASA plans to launch Columbia about two weeks after Atlantis'
mission, if all goes well. Columbia has been waiting for the
astronomy mission since May, when hydrogen leaks halted the first
of four failed countdowns.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0047 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 1640EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People-McCartney     11-11 0137</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People-McCartney,0145</SECOND>
<HEAD>Paul McCartney: `I'm a Ham'</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Paul McCartney says he's a ham and never tires
of the public's adulation.
   ``I like being recognized on the street,'' the singer-songwriter
was quoted Sunday as saying in The New York Times.
   ``I like having lorry (truck) drivers in New York lean out their
windows saying, `Yo, Paul, thanks for the music,''' he said. ``It's
a big city, the capital of the world almost and they all know me.
That's what I did it for. I'm a ham.''
   The ex-Beatle says he sometimes listens to bootleg music, which
is not to say he supports the making of such recordings.
   ``If you start making the alternate takes available, in 10 years
people may not know which was the finished take and which wasn't,''
McCartney said. ``I'd rather avoid the confusion.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0048 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 1643EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BreedingBan 1stLd-Writethru a0648 11-11 0560</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Breeding Ban, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0648,0687</SECOND>
<HEAD>Humane Society Proposes Breeding Ban To Stop Pet Overpopulation</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 8th graf, `It calls...', to delete reference to buyers
being required to neuter pets within a year; ordinance is not
specific on that point.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto FX1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By COLLEEN BARRY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN MATEO, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Local humane society officials are
pressing for an ordinance to ban all breeding of dogs and cats.
It's not that they are against puppies and kittens, they just want
to stop killing 10,000 unwanted animals each year.
   The debate over the proposed breeding ban is shaping into a
class battle fought by responsible pet owners and breeders of
aristocratic pets, and shelter workers who must euthanize thousands
of those pets' poorer cousins each year.
   ``What is radical is what we've been doing, killing animals,''
said Kim Sturla, executive director of the Peninsula Humane
Society. ``I think it's crazy that it's become acceptable to kill
dogs and cats.''
   Under the proposal, believed to be the first of its kind in the
nation, pet owners found in violation would face fines ranging from
$100 to $500. Penalties would be waived if the animals are spayed
or neutered.
   ``It doesn't seem right. If people allow their animals to roam
outside, then I understand why they should be spayed or neutered,''
said Carolyn Varner of San Mateo County, who is selling two
5-month-old registered Persian kittens for $175 each.
   ``But my cats are indoor cats and they aren't allowed to go
breed every time they go into heat.''
   The proposed ordinance, which would apply to unincorporated
areas in this affluent county of 600,000 south of San Francisco, is
designed to reach zero pet population growth.
   It calls for a one-year moratorium on breeding and then
mandatory spaying and neutering of cats and dogs. Pet stores would
still be allowed to import puppies and kittens, but the animals
would have to be neutered.
   Opponents argue that it is unenforceable. Breeders, they say,
would lose a livelihood and animals spayed and neutered to comply
with the new law would be barred from many competitions.
   San Mateo County Supervisor Tom Nolan, the ordinance's sponsor,
said he expects some details may be modified after public hearings
that begin Tuesday before the county board of supervisors.
   But Nolan says the tragedy of euthanizing thousands of animals a
year ultimately outweighs other concerns.
   ``If you put show and prize animals as one value next to an
ordinance that might potentially save 10,000 dogs or cats a year, I
imagine the choice is clear,'' Nolan said.
   Sturla said there are no large-scale breeders she is aware of in
San Mateo County.
   ``I would challenge anybody to show me anyone making a living
off breeding animals, except `puppy mill'-ers,'' Sturla said.
``We're certainly having an impact on somebody's hobby, but we're
not having an impact on anyone's livelihood.''
   And Nolan said he is less interested in catching every violator
than encouraging pet owners to be responsible.
   ``My hope is that ... there will some kind of social sanctions
attached to the person in the neighborhood who lets their dog or
cat go around without being spayed or neutered,'' he said.
   Of the roughly 15,000 animals brought to the shelter each year,
1,500 are returned to their owners and 3,500 are adopted, according
to Humane Society figures. The remaining 10,000 animals are killed.
   As if the statistics weren't attention-grabbing enough, the
Humane Society recently euthanized several animals in front of
reporters.
   ``We're trying to illustrate to the public that 10,000 is not
just a statistic,'' Sturla said. ``They are living, feeling
animals.''
   The reporters ``experienced what we experience every single day.
They got to see fear on the animal's face, to see the animal
tremble and see her defecate in the hallway on the way to the
kennel,'' Sturla said.
   ``What we're attempting to do is drag the euthanization of dogs
and cats out of the closet,'' Nolan said. ``When you see it, you
understand its a barbaric practice.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0049 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 1656EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-VeteransDay 1stLd-Writethru a0647 11-11 0539</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Veterans Day, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0647,640</SECOND>
<HEAD>Veterans Day Ceremonies Made More Solemn by Threat of Mideast War</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Adds 5 grafs with Scruggs remarks and finalists for Vietnam
Women's Memorial</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By W. DALE NELSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Americans paid tribute to the dead of wars
past in solemn Veterans Day ceremonies Sunday at the Tomb of the
Unknowns and the Vietnam Veterans Memorial amid fears that the
nation may be swept into a new war in the Persian Gulf.
   At the Vietnam memorial, Bob Horsch of Rahway, N.J., a veteran
of Army service in Vietnam, said he believed it was ``just a matter
of time'' until the United States was at war again.
   Horsch said he believed the military buildup in the Persian Gulf
was justified by the need to protect American interests and those
of other countries.
   Stephen Reuben of Lapwai, Idaho, a member of the Nez Perce tribe
who also served in Vietnam, declined to say whether the buildup was
a good idea, but also said he fears the country was headed for war.
   ``I am afraid so, but I pray and hope we don't,'' Reuben said.
   Teresa Swain of Hagerstown, Md., when asked if she supported the
buildup, said ``We have to protect our interests.'' As to whether
it would mean war, she said ``I certainly hope not.'' Mrs. Swain
said she has a son-in-law in the Air Force.
   Speakers at the ceremonies, including Defense Secretary Dick
Cheney, paid tribute to the American troops now serving in the gulf
region.
   At Arlington National Cemetery, Cheney laid a wreath at the Tomb
of the Unknowns and addressed a capacity crowd in the adjoining
Vermont marble amphitheater, which seats 5,500.
   ``Those who have been deployed to the Persian Gulf and Saudi
Arabia are probably the best trained soldiers we have ever had,''
he said. ``The nation and the world will be better for their
service.''
   ``People who are concerned about peace must stay prepared for
war,'' Cheney said.
   The ceremonies, held on traditional Veterans Day in advance of
Monday's official national holiday, took place under bright, sunny
skies, with a crisp wind whipping through the flag-draped
amphitheater at Arlington.
   At the Vietnam memorial, an armed services color guard and a
bagpiper playing ``Abide With Me'' accompanied military and
patriotic groups who placed wreaths in front of the 58,000 names
inscribed on the ebony-colored, granite wall. They are the names of
American servicemen killed in Vietnam.
   Col. Robert F. Foley, an Army Medal of Honor winner from
Vietnam, told the crowd ``The situation in Saudi Arabia is a grim
reminder that war is not a thing of the past.''
   The National Park Service estimated the crowd at 5,000.
   Jan C. Scruggs, president of the Vietnam Veterans Memorial Fund,
his voice breaking, spoke of the troops in the Middle East, saying,
``We are very, very proud of them and we do hope that in the event
there is combat they will not get the treatment that the Vietnam
veterans got.''
   Meanwhile the Vietnam Women's Memorial Project announced the
selection of two finalists in its competition for a design of the
memorial, to be built alongside the Vietnam Veterans' Memorial. The
target date for its dedication is 1992.
   One of the winning designs, by sculptor Eileen Rose Barry of
East Islip, Long Island, is a statue of a woman standing by herself
with a helmet in her hand. The other, by landscape architect Robert
Desmond of Arlington, Mass., consists of a white marble block, in
contrast to the black marble of the wall, surrounded by 240 jets of
water.
   Diane Carlson Evans, director of the project, said the two
finalists would be asked to refine their proposals and the final
design would be a collaboration of the two.
   Raquel Ramati, a New York urban designer who served on the
nine-person jury of designers and veterans, said the panel was
split. The veterans favored a representational sculpture and the
designers leaned toward an abstract design.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0050 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 1704EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p AM-MassachusettsGovernor     11-11 0340</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Massachusetts Governor,0405</SECOND>
<HEAD>John Silber Says His Fiery Temper May Have Done Him In</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Note language in penultimate graf</NOTE>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   John Silber, the on-leave president of Boston
University, acknowledges his fiery temper may have cost him the
governor's chair.
   Silber, who was the Democratic nominee, lost Tuesday to
Republican William Weld by about 76,000 votes out of more than 2
million cast.
   Silber, in an article for The Boston Sunday Globe, said he might
have been hurt by outbursts, which drew attention throughout the
race.
   ``These faults hardly add up to a temperament unfit to govern,
but perhaps they cost me 50,000 votes,'' he wrote. ``If they did,
then perhaps I did blow the election, although I am not sure.''
   Silber concluded he was probably the victim of his own testiness
and an anti-incumbent, anti-Democrat mood that swept Massachusetts
on Election Day.
   ``It is tempting to excuse one's performance and also wonder
whether one could have won by doing a little better,'' he said.
   ``Or to put it more bluntly, to take comfort in thinking that
you have just been run over by the locomotive of history or to
experience the disquieting thought that you've blown an election
that you could have won. In my case, I can see evidence for both
diagnoses,'' Silber said.
   Silber acknowledged his vitriolic exchanges with television
newswomen Natalie Jacobson and Lesley Stahl also hurt his campaign.
   In an interview with Jacobson, Silber said he believed the high
number of working mothers led to a generation of abused and
neglected children.
   He also refused to respond when she asked him to name his
strengths and weaknesses.
   Silber spread the blame, saying he was the victim of
``sound-bite'' journalism and a Democratic Party out of step with
voters.
   ``When I began the campaign for the governorship, I said that
although I could do the job, I didn't need it. I still believe
that, and so do my family,'' he wrote.
   Silber, a Texas native, said his outspoken style would better
serve a Texas politician but was ``easily misinterpreted in
Massachusetts.''
   Late in the campaign, Silber referred to Weld as an
``orange-headed WASP'' and a ``back-stabbing son of a bitch.''
Silber apologized for the SOB remark.
   ``In the genteel atmosphere of New England, these were used to
divert attention from more important issues,'' Silber said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0051 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 1727EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BathroomCrosses     11-11 0241</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bathroom Crosses,0283</SECOND>
<HEAD>Pilgrims See Crosses in Bathroom Window</HEAD>
<DATELINE>VIOLET, La. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Crowds of people have been lining up to get
into Leo and Loretta Alphonso's bathroom, where Mrs. Alphonso
reported the images of two crosses appeared on a window shortly
after she finished a series of prayers.
   ``I went in skeptical,'' said visitor Evelyn Rodriguez. ``I
didn't know what to expect but I sure didn't expect that. I was
amazed. I was really amazed.''
   The Roman Catholic archdiocese of New Orleans had not heard
about the crosses, a spokesman said.
   Pilgrims led into the small, darkened room off the Alphonsos'
bedroom report seeing the images of two crosses - one gold, one
white, both about 10 inches high - on the surface of a small,
translucent window.
   Visitors point out that there are no lights in the Alphonso's
back yard that might cause the patterns. Some doubted that a white
street light and a yellow porch light about a half-block away could
be the cause.
   ``Sure, I could see those street lights,'' Ms. Rodriquez said.
``But I don't see how they could have caused the crosses. Those
crosses are absolutely gorgeous.''
   Neighbors said Mrs. Alphonso told them that she had just
finished saying a novena, a nine-day series of prayers, to St. Jude
last week when she went to the bathroom to get something from the
medicine cabinet. As she reached for the door, she saw the crosses
reflected in the cabinet mirror.
   ``It's a beautiful sight, it really is,'' neighbor Dolores
Wattingney said Friday. ``Now, she's had people there to see it all
week. Hundreds of people, especially the last few nights.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0052 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 1728EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Baltics     11-11 0274</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Baltics,0297</SECOND>
<HEAD>Lithuanian Leader Says He Doubts Talks Will Start as Planned</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Lithuania's president, again accusing the Kremlin
of foot-dragging, said he doubts talks will begin at the end of
November as planned to discuss the Baltic republic's independence,
Tass reported Sunday.
   ``The Soviet leadership is forcing a conflict in relations with
Lithuania, evidently not willing to begin talks,'' President
Vytautas Landsbergis was quoted as saying in an interview with the
Soviet news agency.
   Leaders of the Baltic republics met Saturday with Soviet Prime
Minister Nikolai Ryzhkov and discussed the budget of the Soviet
Union and its republics for 1991.
   At a second round of talks Oct. 20, Lithuanian and Soviet
officials agreed to try to start formal negotiations on secession
at the end of November. But Landsbergis said he suspected the talks
won't begin then.
   ``In spite of humiliations, provocations and inadequate behavior
on the Soviet side, Lithuanian representatives are doing everything
possible not to let the preparations for talks to be interrupted,''
the news agency quoted Landsbergis as saying.
   The sides have been divided over whether the meetings by their
delegations could be considered negotiations or merely talks to
plan for negotiations.
   Lithuania wants the Kremlin to agree to certain guidelines
before official talks start, while the Soviet side has said it
considers the negotiations already under way.
   The delegations first met in early October. Lithuania had agreed
during the summer to suspend its March 11 declaration of
independence in return for the Kremlin's assent to begin the
dialogue and end an economic embargo of Lithuania.
   The delegations agreed after their first session to conduct
their economic and trade relations for 1991 as equal partners,
while continuing to discuss Lithuania's move toward independence.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0053 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 1740EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Macedonia-Elections     11-11 0474</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Macedonia-Elections,0538</SECOND>
<HEAD>Macdeonians Vote in Free Elections</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SLOBODAN LEKIC</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SKOPJE, Yugoslavia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Macedonians voted Sunday in the first
free parliamentary elections in more than 50 years in Yugoslavia's
poorest republic.
   The elections are viewed as a crucial test for Yugoslavian
Premier Ante Markovic, a pragmatic economic reformer trying to hold
this fractious country together. Markovic's new Alliance of
Reformist Forces is contesting an election for the first time.
   Opinion polls have shown the alliance about even with the
reconstituted Communist Party. An Albanian nationalist party and
Macedonian nationalists also are vying in the elections for a
120-seat, single-chamber legislature.
   A good showing in Macedonia would boost the alliance's chances
in elections schedled for the coming weeks in the republics of
Bosnia-Hercegovina, Montenegro and Serbia.
   The national news agency Tanjug reported the overall turnout
from the approximately 1.37 million eligible Macedonian voters was
50 percent by 4 p.m. Polls closed at 7 p.m.
   Television said the results were slow coming in from isolated
villages in the mountainous republic, located at Yugoslavia's
southernmost tip and bordered by Albania, Greece and Bulgaria.
   No results were expected until late Monday, election officials
said. Runoff votes will be held Nov. 25 for seats that produce no
outright winner.
   It was the first multiparty vote here since 1938.
   The Communists, now called the Party of Democratic Change,
support Markovic's reform programs and have left open the
possibility of forming a coalition with his alliance.
   The Alliance of Reformist Forces was not formed in time to
contest last spring's first multiparty elections in the northern
republics of Slovenia and Croatia. Center-right parties ousted the
ruling Communists in those republics and now are pushing for
Yugoslavia to be reconstituted as a looser confederacy.
   ``The alliance offers the only chance to keep Yugoslavia
together in the long run and to turn it into a modern, prosperous
democracy,'' said Rode Marinovski, a Skopje lawyer, as he waited to
vote.
   ``I'm convinced we will do very well here,'' said Stojan Andov,
leader of Markovic's party in Macedonia, after casting his vote in
Skopje, the state capital about 275 miles south of Belgrade.
   Markovic's personal popularity grew rapidly after he became
premier in March and helped control inflation. But his free-market
economic reforms have pitted him against the hard-line communist
leadership of the country's largest republic, Serbia.
   Croatian and Slovenian leaders also are wary of Markovic's
efforts to keep the nation more tightly unified as a federation.
   From 40,000 to 50,000 ethnic Albanians working as guest workers
in Western Europe were reported to have returned to Macedonia to
vote, and the Albanian Party of Democratic Prosperity was expected
to do well.
   Ethnic Albanians account for over 20 percent of Macedonia's 2.2
million population.
   Two other nationalist parties are taking part: the Macedonian
Action Party and the radical Internal Macedonian Revolutionary
Organization, which was established 100 years ago to fight Turkish
control of Macedonia.
   The radical nationalists claim Macedonia was unjustly divided in
1913 among Serbia, Bulgaria and Greece. They want to form a
``Greater Macedonia'' that would include regions of Greece and
Bulgaria.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0054 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 1740EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BRF--DeerCosts     11-11 0192</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Deer Costs,0215</SECOND>
<HEAD>Illegally Killed Deer Cost Hunters Money, Truck and Nearly Their
Lives</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CHEYENNE, Wyo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two deer killed illegally cost a pair of
hunters $840, their pickup truck and nearly their lives, wildlife
officials say.
   The hunters recently crossed into Wyoming from South Dakota. On
their way back, they shot two bucks using a spotlight, the state
Game and Fish Department said.
   ``After making the kill, they decided to hightail it across the
border, where they could gut the deer and claim them as being taken
in South Dakota,'' the department said.
   However, about one mile from the South Dakota line, the pickup
veered off the road and rolled down a hill, the department said.
Details of the accident on Nov. 4 were not immediately clear.
   The men, who were not identified by wildlife officials, left the
scene of the accident, which led authorities to the deer. The truck
was destroyed, but they escaped with only bumps and bruises.
   ``It was a bad wreck,'' said Newcastle Game Warden Scott
Talbott. ``They were both lucky they had their seat belts on or
they might have been killed.''
   The hunters were charged with taking deer without a license.
Each was fined $420 and sentenced to six months probation.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0055 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 1740EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--Gulf-BushTrial     11-11 0175</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Gulf-Bush Trial,0180</SECOND>
<HEAD>Algerian Tribunal Plans to Try Bush</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ALGIERS, Algeria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A group of prominent Algerians announced
plans Sunday to hold a tribunal next month against President Bush
on charges including crimes against humanity.
   The group said it plans to hold the proceedings in the Algerian
capital, Algiers, on Dec. 10. Foremost among the charges will be
``threatening peace and world security by his preparation for an
aggressive war against Iraq,'' the group said in a communique.
   The Algerian tribunal will be headed by Ali Ammar Louar, former
president of Algeria's bar association. It will be made up of
academics, lawyers and intellectuals active in human rights, the
group said.
   The tribunal is apparently not sponsored by the Algerian
government. It would have no way of enforcing its sentence.
   In its statement, the group said the U.S.-led economic blockade
of Iraq is a crime under ``terms of the international convention
for prevention of and punishment for genocide.''
   The sanctions, approved by the United Nations, were imposed
after Iraq's Aug. 2 invasion of Kuwait.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0056 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 1744EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Poland     11-11 0294</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Poland,0324</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mazowiecki Calls for Unity on Independence Day</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ANDRZEJ STYLINSKI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WARSAW, Poland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In a speech marking the 72nd anniversary
of the rebirth of Poland, Prime Minister Tadeusz Mazowiecki said
Sunday that Poles should ``rise beyond divisions'' to continue
their unprecedented democratic reforms.
   On Nov. 11, 1918, the Polish Republic was proclaimed following
123 years of partition among the Russian, German and Austrians
empires. Sunday marked the first time the date had been observed as
an official holiday since World War II.
   Poland was invaded by Germany in 1939 and dominated after the
war by the Soviet Union. The Solidarity labor movement forced the
Communists to hold the first free elections in eastern Europe since
the war in 1989.
   In the country's first popular presidential elections Nov. 25,
Mazowiecki is pitted against Solidarity leader Lech Walesa, his
former ally.
   Mazowiecki said history gives his countrymen an important
``source of trust for success in the current struggle,'' but warned
that it also ``obliges us to be responsible for today and the
future.''
   ``We have been carrying out for over a year the vision of Poland
as an independent and democratic state,'' Mazowiecki said.
``Rejecting revolutionary methods, we in fact have made
revolutionary changes of the system.''
   ``I trust that in the name of what we have achieved so far ...
we manage to rise beyond divisions to continue the great task of
transforming Poland,'' he said.
   The rivalry of the longtime allies has deeply divided Polish
society, but both Mazowiecki and Walesa have stressed the need for
national unity in further restructuring of the economy.
   Mazowiecki spoke at Warsaw's Tomb of the Unknown Soldier in
celebrations that marked the restoration of inscriptions
commemorating Poland's 1914-1920 struggle for independence.
   The original inscriptions, bearing the names of battlefields
where Polish soldiers fought successfully the Soviet Red Army, were
removed in 1945.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0057 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 1749EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--Zaire-Accident     11-11 0121</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Zaire-Accident,0110</SECOND>
<HEAD>River Accident Kills 21 in Zaire</HEAD>
<DATELINE>KINSHASA, Zaire (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A small boat carrying 41 passengers
capsized in the Zaire River near Brazzaville, and 21 people were
killed, officials said.
   The boat overturned about 50 yards from shore after leaving
Brazzaville, a western city in this central African country,
officials said Saturday. Fishermen rescued the survivors.
   Authorities gave no information on the cause of the accident,
which occurred Friday.
   It was the second accident in two days on the river.
   On Wednesday, a floating platform that services boats at the
same crossing collapsed. Casualty figures from that accident have
not been released.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0058 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 1835EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Sweden-SovietSub     11-11 0283</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Sweden-Soviet Sub,0331</SECOND>
<HEAD>Soviet Officer: Military Was Prepared to Attack Swedes</HEAD>
<DATELINE>STOCKHOLM, Sweden (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Soviet Union was prepared to use
military force to free a Soviet submarine that ran aground in
Swedish waters nine years ago, a Soviet officer said in an article
published Sunday.
   Vasily Besedin, then the political officer aboard the submarine,
said Soviet warships were waiting in international waters off the
Swedish coast.
   ``They were assigned to force their way through and bring home
the submarine if attempts were made to seize it,'' Besedin was
quoted as saying in the article.
   The Soviet submarine ran aground near a major Swedish naval base
in the Karlskrona archipelago on Oct. 27, 1981. Sweden waited seven
days before returning the vessel.
   Stuck on a rock for all to see, the Whiskey Class U137 submarine
became known as ``Whiskey on the Rocks.'' The incident soured
relations between Sweden and its powerful neighbor for years.
   The article in the Dagens Nyheter newspaper, published in
Stockholm, was an account told to Soviet military journalist
Vladimir Verbitsky.
   Swedish Navy Captain Karl Andersson told the national news
agency TT that the Soviet forces in the area ``would not have had
enough strength'' to take back the submarine. Andersson was one of
the officers who interrogated the Soviet crew.
   ``Also, the political price for an attack against Sweden would
have been too high,'' he said.
   In the article, Besedin echoed Moscow's official excuse that the
U137 made a navigational error. According to Besedin, navigation
standards were low aboard, and the crew had no idea of where it was
when the vessel ran aground.
   Dagens Nyheter said Besedin lost his apartment, his savings, his
wife and was forced to take a job on a road gang when he returned
to the Soviet Union. However, he was allowed back in military
service after a few months and now serves as a political officer at
a coastal unit.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0059 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 1856EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Gulf-Iraq 2ndLd-Writethru a0685 11-11 0593</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Iraq, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0685,0757</SECOND>
<HEAD>Iraq Offers to Attend Summit, But Wants Say on Time, Place, Agenda</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Leads with 10 grafs to UPDATE with Saddam in interview saying
not all countries against him; picks up 7th graf pvs, ```The
proposed ..</NOTE>
<HEAD>With AM-Bush-Gulf Strategy, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SALAH NARAWI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BAGHDAD, Iraq (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Iraq said Sunday it would attend a proposed
Arab summit if the agenda includes the Palestinian question and if
it is consulted on the time and place.
   The Iraqi offer came in response to an appeal by Morocco's King
Hassan II, who said such a meeting would be a ``new and last
chance'' for a peaceful solution.
   Iraq's ruling Revolutionary Command Council, led by President
Saddam Hussein, went into emergency session to discuss the matter,
an official statement read on state television said.
   It said Iraq was willing to attend the summit if it were
consulted in advance on the timing and location and agenda, and if
the topics included the Palestinian question.
   In a separate interview broadcast in London on Sunday, Saddam
repeated his call for an international dialogue on the crisis and
said he did not think the world was united against him.
   He acknowledged that the major powers and ``a number of
countries'' were lined up against Iraq, ``but to say that the world
is unified against Iraq is indeed not a correct thing to say.''
   ``This is not just our impression,'' he said in the Saturday
interview with Britain's Independent Television News. ``In the
statements of the U.S. and Britain, they themselves are voicing
their concern that the unity - so-called unity against Iraq - is
perhaps ... suffering from a split.''
   Asked if Iraq was ready to leave Kuwait, Saddam said:``We are
ready to enter into deep dialogue as to the requirements for
security in our region. ...
   ``If all parties concerned ... sat around one table we are
confident that these parties will reach serious and deep solutions
to all the issues, in the forefront of which will be the
Palestinian issue.''
   In its statement about the possible Arab summit, Saddam's
government also suggested it would not allow certain topics to be
discussed at the gathering, if it takes place.
   ``The proposed summit should not be part of efforts to prepare
the political theater as a cover for American aggression against
Iraq and the Arab nation,'' the Iraqi statement said.
   Unlike an Aug. 10 summit in Egypt, where 12 of 21 Arab League
members voted to send troops to Saudi Arabia, any new summit must
not be a ``cover for bringing in U.S. invasion forces,'' the Iraqi
statement said.
   The summit should be preceded by serious consultations ``among
the principal parties concerned with the subject and with all Arabs
in general,'' it said.
   In calling for the summit, the Moroccan monarch said if there
were war in the Persian Gulf region, it would ``penetrate every
household from the gulf to the Atlantic.''
   ``Let us gather together and see what decisions we can take ...
to give to all what they deserve so that Kuwait returns to what it
used to be and that Iraq is a satisfied and satisfying member at
the heart of our Arab family,'' the king said.
   Morocco has been outspoken among Arab nations in its criticism
of Iraq's invasion of Kuwait. It has sent 1,200 soldiers to Saudi
Arabia and 500 troops to the United Arab Emirates as part of the
multinational military buildup against Iraq.
   Hassan suggested meeting in a week in the Moroccan capital of
Rabat, but the Iraqi response appeared to reject this in favor of a
more neutral site.
   The idea of a new Arab summit has been brought up a number of
times since the crisis broke out, but one has never been agreed on.
Many leaders, including Soviet President Mikhail S. Gorbachev, have
said an Arab solution would be the best way to end the standoff.
   In his statement, the king again criticized Iraq's annexation of
Kuwait.
   ``Iraq cannot erase in one stroke the Kuwaiti state to make it
one of its provinces,'' he said. `` The Kuwaiti people cannot lose
day by day their identity to become Iraqi.''
   The Palestine Liberation Organization issued a statement from
PLO headquarters in Tunisia saying it agreed with King Hassan's
initiative.
   The PLO statement stopped short, however, of saying that PLO
leader Yasser Arafat would attend an extraordinary summit.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0060 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 1917EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-GulfRdp 2ndLd-Writethru a0670 11-11 0859</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf Rdp, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0670,1073</SECOND>
<HEAD>China Said to Warn Saddam It Won't Veto Use-of-Force Measure</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf-Kuwaiti Volunteers, Bjt</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Leads with 11 grafs to UPDATE with Saddam comments on unity
against him; picks up 7th graf pvs, `The Baghdad ...</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos DHA1-3</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   China's foreign minister arrived in Baghdad on Sunday carrying
bad news for Saddam Hussein: China will not block the U.N. Security
Council from authorizing the use of force to drive Iraq out of
Kuwait, a Chinese diplomat said.
   Such a measure has been drafted by the United States, diplomats
and U.S. officials said last week, but had not yet been circulated
among the other permanent members of the Security Council.
   Iraq had reportedly pinned its veto hopes on China.
   Meanwhile, Iraq said Sunday it would attend a proposed Arab
summit meeting if it was consulted on the agenda, timing and
location and if the agenda included the Arab-Israeli conflict.
   ``The proposed summit should not be part of efforts to prepare
the political theater as a cover for American aggression against
Iraq and the Arab nation,'' said an Iraqi statement read on state
television.
   The offer came in response to an appeal by Morocco's King Hassan
II, who urged an extraordinary Arab summit on the gulf crisis. He
said such a meeting would be a ``new and last chance'' for a
peaceful solution.
   In a separate interview broadcast Sunday in London, Saddam said
he did not think the world was united against him.
   The major powers and ``a number of countries'' are against Iraq,
``but to say that the world is unified against Iraq is indeed not a
correct thing to say,'' Saddam said on Independent Television News,
which interviewed him Saturday night in Baghdad.
   ``This is not just our impression,'' he added. ``In the
statements of the U.S. and Britain, they themselves are voicing
their concern that the unity - so-called unity against Iraq - is
perhaps ... suffering from a split.''
   ``The U.S. and Britain pushed the (U.N.) Security Council into
adopting hastily taken resolutions against Iraq and once ...
countries began to realize or gauge things in accordance with the
historical background,'' they began to change their attitudes, he
said.
   Some recent reports have said the U.S. government differs with
some allies -among them China, France and the Soviet Union - on a
timetable for any military action to oust Saddam from Kuwait.
   The Baghdad government also denounced food hoarders and
announced the price of rice would increase, although it did not
specify how much. Iraq has weathered three months of economic
sanctions aimed at breaking its grip on Kuwait, which it overran
Aug. 2.
   Before the embargo, Iraq imported about 70 percent of its food.
In September, it began rationing essential foodstuffs such as rice,
wheat, milk, sugar and cooking oil.
   The Iraqi move to punish hoarders of grain came at a top-level
meeting attended by Saddam, the official Iraqi News Agency said. It
said the punishment would be ``strict'' but gave no details.
   The Chinese foreign minister, Qian Qichen, arrived in Baghdad
for talks with Saddam. Before leaving Jordan, Qian said China
differed with the United States on the use of force and would
pursue diplomacy as long as there was ``a glimmer of hope'' that
conflict could be avoided.
   But a Chinese diplomat in the Iraqi capital, speaking on
condition of anonymity, said Qian would tell Saddam that while
China would not support a resolution authorizing force, it would
not veto it either.
   China has veto power, along with the other four permanent
members of the Security Council - the United States, Britain,
France and the Soviet Union. Iraqi officials had said Saddam's
hopes for a veto rested with China.
   Qian was speaking first with Iraqi Foreign Minister Tariq Aziz
and was to meet with Saddam later Sunday.
   Vice President Dan Quayle flew to Tokyo for the enthronement of
Emperor Akihito, and was expected to hold talks on the gulf crisis
with a dozen world leaders while there. During the flight from
Washington on Sunday, Quayle conferred with U.N. Secretary-General
Javier Perez de Cuellar, who traveled to Tokyo with him.
   A few more foreign hostages were freed Sunday. Eight Italian men
arrived in Amman, Jordan, but hundreds of other Italians and other
foreigners remain captive in Iraq.
   The Italians arrived aboard the same plane that carried David
Lange, the former New Zealand prime minister, who went to Baghdad
to try to win the release of his compatriots. He said 16 New
Zealanders were still in Iraq, but that he hoped for ``good news''
about them.
   Some Western governments, including that of the United States,
have criticized private hostage-freeing efforts by former leaders
like Lange, saying the emissaries are manipulated by Saddam.
   Lange, asked about that, retorted: ``The U.S. has this
remarkable affinity for misjudging the political climate of the
moment.''
   Britain, meanwhile, said it was expelling two Iraqis, apparently
for attempting to break the trade sanctions. The Home Office said
Sunday the two must leave the country by Tuesday ``because of their
involvement in procurement on behalf of the government of Iraq.''
It provided no details.
   In other developments:
   -The State Department said Sunday that Secretary of State James
A. Baker III would discuss the Persian Gulf situation with Canada's
foreign minister Joseph Clark on Tuesday in Bermuda. Baker returned
Saturday from an eight-day diplomatic mission to Europe and the
Middle East, where he consulted with officials from nine nations on
the gulf crisis.
   -Two American hostages released by Iraq on Friday have been
discharged from a military hospital in Wiesbaden, Germany, a U.S.
Air Force spokesman said Sunday. Spokesman Capt. Tom Gilroy said he
did not know whether the two, Don and Brenda Swanke of Westlake
Village, Calif., would return home immediately.
   -Some congressional Democrats on Sunday urged President Bush to
consult closely with allies and Congress before launching any
military offensive to oust Iraq from Kuwait. ``The decision to go
to war ought to be a shared responsibility, it ought not to be made
by one person, even if that person is the president of the United
States,'' said Rep. Lee Hamilton, D-Ind. Senate Majority Leader
George Mitchell, D-Maine, said Congress must vote before America
goes to war. The two spoke in television interviews.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0061 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 1917EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-MysteryIllness     11-11 0326</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mystery Illness,0371</SECOND>
<HEAD>Health Officials Stumped on Student Illness</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BOULDER, Colo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An unknown disease sickened 300 University
of Colorado students over the weekend, and state health officials
said Sunday they suspected food poisoning but could find no common
cause.
   The illness, which broke out Friday night and continued to
plague students Sunday at the on-campus Wardenburg Health Center,
was characterized by vomiting, low-grade fever and diarrhea.
   Officials said those symptoms suggest food poisoning, but the
outbreak perplexed health officials because they had been unable to
find a common food linking the cases. The students ate in several
dormitory cafeterias, as well as off campus.
   The majority of students were treated at Wardenburg for
dehydration and sent home. Two were hospitalized Saturday night,
but health center officials would not comment about them Sunday.
   ``It appears to be a food-borne illness outbreak, centered
mostly in dorm residents,'' said Dennis Lenaway, an epidemiologist
with the Boulder County health department.
   Dr. Paul Simon, a state epidemiologist, agreed that it was
probably food poisoning, but said health officials didn't know what
kind.
   ``It looks to me like it's some sort of infectious disease -
food poisoning caused by an infection,'' Simon said. ``But at this
point we just don't have enough information.''
   If it is an infection-based outbreak, the students could have
eaten the tainted food up to three days before becoming sick, Simon
said.
   ``There are so many dorms involved,'' said Dr. Ingrid Hagan,
Wardenburg's chief of staff. ``I myself saw several patients that
didn't eat in the dorms, they ate off campus. We took only a very
brief history as far as what they ate but there doesn't seem to be
a common denominator.''
   An additional 15 to 18 students went to Boulder Community
Hospital on Friday, said hospital spokeswoman Kathy Stephens. None
of those students was hospitalized.
   County health officials delivered questionnaires to the
dormitories on Saturday in hope of pinpointing what caused the
outbreak.
   ``We hope to narrow it down to a meal, or, even better, a food
item. We're hoping we can get that detailed,'' said Lenaway.
``We'll just have to see how things sort themselves out.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0062 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 1928EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-CopelandTrial     11-11 0327</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Copeland Trial,0389</SECOND>
<HEAD>Prosecutors Seeking Death Penalty in Transient Killings</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JERRY NACHTIGAL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CHILLICOTHE, Mo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A prosecutor said Sunday he will seek
the death penalty for a woman convicted of murdering five
transients to cover up a cattle theft scheme.
   The jury that convicted Faye Copeland on Saturday was to return
Monday to decide between a life sentence or execution.
   Mrs. Copeland's attorney, David Miller, said he will request a
new trial, calling it a ``major issue'' that the judge did not
allow a psychologist to testify about her husband's domination over
her life.
   Mrs. Copeland's husband, 75-year-old Ray Copeland, is scheduled
for trial Jan. 24 on murder charges in the case. A court must first
determine whether he is mentally competent to stand trial. His
lawyers contend he is senile.
   A jury in Livingston County in rural, northwest Missouri
convicted Mrs. Copeland, 69, of five counts of first-degree murder.
   The bodies of the five men were found in fall 1989 near farms
where Copeland had done odd jobs, after a tip from another drifter
who had worked for the couple. All had been shot in the head.
   Prosecutors said the couple had the transients open bank
accounts in their names and buy cattle at various sales. The
Copelands then resold the cattle, keeping the proceeds and killing
the transients before the checks could be traced, they said.
   Townspeople had mixed feelings about Mrs. Copeland's part in the
slayings.
   ``There was feeling both ways,'' said resident Leroy Butts, who
watched portions of the trial. ``A lot of people felt kind of sorry
for her. But all those men were dead and you wonder how she didn't
know anything about it.''
   Mrs. Copeland buried her face in her hands and sobbed after the
verdict was read, saying, ``I never done nothing.''
   Miller said he will call a Kansas City psychologist to testify
about battered-wife syndrome during the trial's penalty phase. The
testimony was ruled inadmissible during the trial.
   Miller said he would also call six other witnesses, including
family members, to show a pattern of domination in Mrs. Copeland's
life.
   The defense had tried to prove she did not participate in the
killings and was not privy to her husband's business dealings.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0063 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 1959EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Stormie-Reax     11-11 0340</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Stormie-Reax,0397</SECOND>
<HEAD>First Heart-Liver Transplant Just Wanted to be an Average
Teen-ager</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TERRI LANGFORD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WHITE SETTLEMENT, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Stormie Jones just wanted to be
an average teen-ager, free of the medical complications and media
glare that came with being the world's first heart-liver transplant
patient, friends said Sunday.
   ``She wished everybody would treat her normal instead of like
she had an operation, because she didn't like everybody asking her
how she felt or if she was feeling OK,'' said Stormie's best
friend, Crystal Millikan.
   On Sunday, Crystal and others who loved Stormie mourned the
death of the 13-year-old girl who had inspired family, friends and
well-wishers with her determination and courage during a six-year
battle with illness.
   ``I'm going to miss her a lot,'' Crystal said at the apartment
complex where she and Stormie had lived with their families in this
Fort Worth suburb.
   Stormie died Sunday at a Pittsburgh hospital where she was flown
Saturday after complaining of flu-like symptoms. She became the
first heart-liver transplant recipient on Valentine's Day, 1984, at
the age of 6.
   She received a second liver on Feb. 20 of this year.
   Crystal, also 13, said Stormie, like most teen-agers, liked to
shop at the local mall and spend nights at her friend's house.
   Stormie had wanted to return to school this year. But after
three weeks in the seventh grade at Brewer Middle School she was
forced home by fatigue.
   Still, she dreamed of becoming a veterinarian and had hoped to
write an autobiography titled ``In The Darkness'' to reflect what
she thought about when she fell asleep.
   Crystal said Stormie recently gave her a poster she had drawn
with a bear and jack-in-the-box with the caption ``Friends are
friends forever.'' As Stormie handed over the poster, she said,
``Don't forget me.''
   Despite her desire to be average, Stormie was considered special
in White Settlement, where a local discount store helped raise
money to pay for her medical expenses.
   The Sam's Club store said it sold out its supply of T-shirts
emblazoned with the caption, ``Texas is known for Stormie
weather.''
   ``I just wanted more for her. She deserved more,'' said
Crystal's mother, Teresa Millikan, who spearheaded the fund-raising
efforts. `She was God's walking angel. She touched so many people's
hearts.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0064 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 2003EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Soviet-Gorbachev 1stLd-Writethru a0659 11-11 0473</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Gorbachev, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0659,0522</SECOND>
<HEAD>Gorbachev, Yeltsin Huddle in Kremlin</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 4 grafs to recast lede, clarifies that two-hour
meeting was one-on-one; Picks up 4th graf, `The popular ...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By BRIAN FRIEDMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Mikhail S. Gorbachev and rival Boris Yeltsin met
Sunday in the Kremlin, and one report said they discussed emergency
measures to feed the Soviet people and reform their crumbling
economy.
   Gorbachev, the Soviet president, and Yeltsin, the president of
the Russian republic, met one-on-one for two hours, the independent
Interfax news agency reported.
   It was their first substantive meeting since an attempt at
reconciliation over economic reform broke down in late summer.
   The earlier failed attempt at reconciliation over economic
policies put Yeltsin's Russian republic on a collision course with
the central Soviet government.
   The popular Yeltsin, whom Gorbachev ousted from the Communist
Party Politburo in 1986, has criticized the Soviet leader for not
reforming fast enough.
   After their private meeting, Gorbachev and Yeltsin were joined
by Soviet Prime Minister Nikolai Ryzhkov and two officials from the
Russian republic, Vice President Ruslan Khasbulatov and Prime
Minister Ivan Silaev, Interfax said.
   The conversation between Gorbachev and Yeltsin was conducted in
a ``businesslike, principled atmosphere,'' Interfax said, without
quoting any sources.
   Among the questions discussed were the Russian republic's role
in possible radical economic reforms and ``urgent measures'' to
provide food and consumer goods, Interfax said.
   The official Tass news agency, also without quoting sources,
said the leaders discussed ``current problems,'' the transition to
a market economy and the union treaty - Gorbachev's plan for
holding the splintering 15 Soviet republics together as a loose
confederation.
   On Nov. 1, Russia began its own 500-day plan for converting to a
free market economy, conflicting with a more cautious plan endorsed
by Gorbachev and approved by the national legislature.
   The republic's legislature also has said that it, and not the
central government, has the right to control Russia's considerable
natural resources of oil, coal and diamonds. Russia comprises about
two-thirds of the Soviet Union.
   The disagreement, which cast doubt on the success of Soviet
economic reforms, has become a matter of sharp public debate, with
pleas to the two leaders to reconcile.
   In a commentary Sunday, Tass said the ``tug of war threatens to
jeopardize all efforts.''
   In a letter published in Sunday's conservative Sovietskaya
Rossiya newspaper, Yeltsin was criticized for his differences with
Gorbachev.
   ``The path you are calling for is not Russia's right path,''
said the authors, a group of veterans from Smolensk region west of
Moscow. ``We condemn the policy of confrontation with the center
that you (Yeltsin) and many Russian parliamentarians are
pursuing.''
   Radical legislator Oleg Kalugin, a former KGB general and ardent
Gorbachev critic, said Sunday that Gorbachev ``has to move closer
to Yeltsin or nothing constructive will come out of it.''
   Gorbachev and Yeltsin stood together on Wednesday's Revolution
Day holiday reviewing the traditional parade in Red Square,
although Yeltsin also marched later that day in anti-government
demonstrations that urged Gorbachev and other Soviet leaders
resign.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0065 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 2044EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BaseBombings 1stLd-Writethru a0661 11-11 0313</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Base Bombings, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0661,0365</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bombs Destroy Two Cars At Air Force Base, Fire Set In Office</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 8 grafs for last 2 grafs, `Sgt. Randy ...' to UPDATE with
details, comment, background; ADDS byline.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By TIM KLASS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>McCHORD AIR FORCE BASE, Wash. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A fire bomb was set off at
an Air Force office building early Sunday and small bombs destroyed
two government-owned cars, officials said.
   The fire did little damage to the Office of Special
Investigations and no one was injured in the car bombings at about
4 a.m. at this base adjoining Fort Lewis near Tacoma, said Master
Sgt. Gloria Rayford.
   No arrests were made, nor were investigators immediately able to
determine who was responsible, Rayford said.
   She said she didn't know whether the three devices were
detonated with timing devices or fuses.
   ``There was no one at the scene when it happened,'' Rayford
said.
   Terrorism was not suspected because no note was left nor did
anyone call to claim responsibility, said Air Force Sgt. Randy
Mitchell.
   The FBI and the Pierce County fire marshall's office were
assisting in the investigation, Mitchell said.
   The Office of Special Investigations handles security at the
5,000-acre Air Force base and crimes above the level of drunkenness
or brawling.
   ``They're sort of the FBI for the Air Force,'' Rayford said.
   Its building is a low structure situated beside a block-long
parking lot and across the street from base headquarters.
   The explosive devices apparently were placed above the left rear
wheel of each of the late-model, brown sedans used by
investigators. Those investigating the bombing said they did not
believe military-type explosives had been used.
   A small piece of pipe, about 1{ inches long with a cap on one
end, appeared to have been blown about 100 feet from one car.
   Security was tight after the bombings, with military police
checking identification on every vehicle entering the base. The
base's military police generally do more more than infrequent spot
checks of vehicles entering the base.
   About 4,800 personnel are based at McChord, and 1,300 to 1,500
civilians work there.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0066 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 2112EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-DailyNews 1stLd-Writethru a0699 11-11 0540</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Daily News, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0699,0644</SECOND>
<HEAD>Striking Daily News Workers Publish ``Real News''</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: INSERTS one graf after 11th graf, `Hoge said ...' to include
background on homeless enlisted. Pick up 12th graf, `Sunday's
edition ...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By DANA KENNEDY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Daily News stepped up its efforts Sunday to
create a network of people across the city to sell the newspaper
despite an aggressive boycott campaign by striking workers.
   The paper ran a full-page ad Sunday saying it had ``immediate
needs for individuals who want to own, operate, and direct their
own work force selling newspapers.'' The ad said in large letters:
``UNLIMITED INCOME.''
   Meanwhile, strikers fanned out over the city to start
distribution of what union officials said were a million copies of
an eight-page, free newspaper titled ``Real News.''
   All the stories in ``Real News'' were written by Daily News
writers who have been on strike since Oct. 25.
   ``We wanted to show that the striking employees are the heart
and soul of the Daily News and that we're capable of producing a
better-quality paper than the scab rag Jim Hoge is putting out
right now,'' said striking columnist Juan Gonzalez, referring to
the Daily News publisher.
   Gonzalez coordinated distribution efforts at the Newspaper Guild
headquarters Sunday.
   Gonzalez said ``Real News'' is aimed at giving the strikers'
version of the labor dispute. The articles detail the history of
the strike, incidents that have involved violece, interviews with
news vendors and profiles of striking pressmen and drivers.
   ``Real News'' will be handed out Monday and Tuesday at churches,
hospitals, hotels, housing projects and subway stations, Gonzalez
said.
   On Sunday, striking staffers distributed ``Real News'' at Giants
Stadium in East Rutherford, N.J., and began dropping off bundles to
other strikers and individual unions.
   The News has published each day during the strike, but
circulation has been a major problem with some vendors refusing to
sell it and others claiming they got no deliveries. Some vendors
have claimed threats by striking drivers.
   Hoge said last week that 600,000 papers were printed each day.
Pre-strike circulation was about 1.09 million copies daily, making
the News the nation's third-largest metropolitan daily.
   On Friday, the poor and homeless were recruited by the paper as
sales people. One recruit, Eddy Nadreau, said the News had called
the Brooklyn shelter where he lives, offering $6 an hour and a
percentage of sales.
   Sunday's edition of the News quoted one newsstand operator, Luis
Rivera, saying that customers were intimidated by two men who came
in, went through stacks of papers and checked the papers everyone
was reading. ``Everyone was scared,'' Rivera said.
   Strikers, on the other hand, are protesting security forces
hired by the Daily News.
   George E. McDonald, president of the Allied Printing Trades
Council, the umbrella group representing the 2,600 strikers in nine
unions, sent a telegram to Mayor David Dinkins and Police
Commissioner Lee Brown requesting a meeting Monday to discuss the
security guards' tactics.
   ``This army of combat-ready troops comprised of men in ski masks
and combat boots and black bodysuits are unleashing a reign of
terror on the streets of New York City,'' the letter read in part.
   ``Troops are using martial arts sticks and other illegal and
life threatening weapons ... These mercenary efforts must be
stopped before they take an innocent life.''
   There was no immediate Daily News comment on the letter Sunday;
spokeswoman Lisa Robinson did not return a call.
   The strike began with a dispute at the paper's Brooklyn plant in
which some drivers walked off the job. As others left, the News
began bringing in replacement workers, calling the job action a
strike.
   The shutdown spread to other unions that have been working
without labor contracts since March 30.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0067 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 2129EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Obit-StormieJones 6thLd-Writethru a0690 11-11 0662</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Stormie Jones, 6th Ld-Writethru, a0690,0803</SECOND>
<HEAD>Teen-age Heart-Liver Recipient Dies at 13</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 8th graf pvs, `An autopsy ...' to UPDATE that preliminary
autopsy was inconclusive. SUBS 3 grafs for last graf, `Ms. McMahon
...' to UPDATE with details on girl's warmth toward fellow
patients. No pickup.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos NY10, NY11, DN3</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CLAUDIA COATES</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PITTSBURGH (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Stormie Jones, the world's first heart-liver
transplant recipient, died Sunday at age 13 after a six-year
struggle that inspired well-wishers across the country.
   The Texas teen-ager was flown to Pittsburgh's Children's
Hospital from Dallas late Saturday after she complained of flu-like
symptoms. At the hospital, Stormie deteriorated throughout the
morning and died at 9:52 a.m., said Dr. Jorge Reyes, a staff
physician.
   ``She deserved more,'' said Teresa Millikan, a family friend who
spearheaded efforts to raise funds for Stormie's hospital expenses.
``She was God's walking angel. She touched so many people's
hearts.''
   Within hours of her arrival at the hospital, Stormie's blood
pressure dropped, Reyes said. She became lethargic, then suffered a
heart attack, he said. Doctors tried for more than an hour to
resuscitate her.
   ``She presented acute respiratory distress and had a cardiac
arrest,'' Reyes told reporters.
   ``Things happened with incredible speed,'' said hospital
spokeswoman Lynn McMahon said. Stormie was alert when she was taken
to Children's Hospital and it had not appeared to be an emergency,
she said.
   A preliminary autopsy performed Sunday was inconclusive, she
said.
   Stormie was 6 when she received a heart and liver in a historic
transplant operation Feb. 14, 1984. The operation was necessary
because she was born with a condition that put her cholesterol
levels at 10 times normal.
   Hepatitis damaged that liver and this year she returned to
Pittsburgh and received a second liver Feb. 20. In July, she was
again treated for hepatitis, which damaged her second transplanted
liver.
   Doctors said it was a mystery how she contracted hepatitis.
   Stormie, of the Fort Worth suburb of White Settlement, and her
mother, Lois Purcell, left Dallas-Fort Worth International Airport
on Saturday evening.
   Millikan said Saturday that Stormie had not been feeling well
since midweek.
   ``She doesn't feel good, she's tired,'' she said. ``She hasn't
been able to sleep for the past three nights. She's had it pretty
rough.''
   Her daughter, Crystal, who was Stormie's best friend, said the
ailing girl never felt comfortable under the media's glare and
wanted more than anything to feel like a normal teen-ager.
   ``She wished everybody would treat her normal instead of like
she had an operation, because she didn't like everybody asking her
how she felt or if she was feeling OK,'' Crystal said, tears
welling in her eyes.
   ``Nobody in the world was as sweet or kind as her. There'll be
nobody like her,'' she said.
   Stormie, who turned 13 in May, had hoped to write an
autobiography titled ``In The Darkness.'' The book was to be
``about my life, my family, all the pet animals I've had,'' she
said earlier this year.
   The blonde teen-ager said she liked frightening books, movies
and television programs, such as the cable horror series ``Tales
From The Crypt'' and the movie ``Pet Sematary.''
   ``I feel better when I write my thoughts down,'' Stormie said.
   Stormie took the experimental anti-rejection drug FK-506, which
has been approved for testing exclusively at the University of
Pittsburgh. A few exceptions have been made for patients elsewhere.
   Until a year ago, Stormie had been taking cyclosporine, an
anti-rejection drug that lowers the body's ability to fight
infection. Researchers say FK-506 is more powerful and causes fewer
side effects.
   Any transplant patient is susceptible to infection because
anti-rejection drugs weaken the immune system, Reyes said.
   ``I wouldn't particularly focus on the FK-506 as a specific
cause,'' he said.
   Stormie was at the hospital for several hours before doctors
could tell her heart was affected, he said. She got some sleep
during the night and asked for water when she awoke, Reyes said.
Her mother was at her side.
   ``She was really with us 100 percent before this happened,''
Reyes said.
   The hospital staff liked and admired Stormie, he said.
   ``She was a happy girl. She certainly enjoyed fighting us as
much as she could,'' Reyes said.
   Stormie once bought a book on Chinese to help her communicate
with a 3-year-old Chinese fellow patient.
   ``She did that kind of thing all the time,'' said Ms. McMahon,
the hospital spokeswoman. ``She was just so highly regarded by
other children. She went to great length to take the time to play
with them and talk with them.''
   Ms. McMahon said the staff planned a memorial service. Funeral
arrangements were pending.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0068 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 2148EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-StatueVandals     11-11 0314</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Statue Vandals,0361</SECOND>
<HEAD>Vandals Damage Statue of Polish Priest and Leave Political Message</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Vandals knocked the head off the newly dedicated
statue of a murdered priest who championed democracy in Poland and
scrawled ``For Lenin, for Stalin'' along the statue base,
authorities said Sunday.
   The 9-foot-tall, 5-foot-wide granite statue was dedicated Oct.
28 in Brooklyn's Greenpoint section to honor the Rev. Jerzy
Popieluszko, a pro-Solidarity Roman Catholic priest killed by
Polish secret police in 1984. More than 50,000 Polish immigrants
live in Greenpoint.
   Many of the 1,000 parishioners attending the 11 a.m. Mass at Our
Lady of Consolation on Sunday wept when the Rev. John Lazar told
them of the vandalism, which occured overnight. No one claimed
responsibility.
   ``Many of the immigrants in the area are from the diocese where
he served,'' Lazar said later. ``Many had heard his pro-Solidarity
and anti-Communist talks firsthand. Some of them knew him.''
   The head of the statue erected at the intersection of Lorimer
Street and Bedford Avenue was found in a nearby trash can, said
police Officer Scott Bloch. The words, ``Za Lenina Za Stalina,''
Polish for ``For Lenin, for Stalin,'' were scrawled in black paint
on the statue base.
   Lazar said it was a ``tremendous triumph'' for many Polish
immigrants to see the statue dedicated at a ceremony attended by
Polish Bishop Joseph Wysocki.
   Now, ``there is shock and disbelief,'' Lazar said. ``Although
the priest has been dead for six years he stays very much alive in
the hearts and memories of the Polish people.''
   He said some Polish residents view the vandalism as an extension
of the violence that caused Popieluszko's death.
   Until the statue was dedicated, private security guards watched
the location because threats had been made that the statue would be
defaced or destroyed, Lazar said.
   Popieluszko, whose sermons bolstered the Solidarity labor
movement when it was outlawed, was abducted Oct. 19, 1984. His
beaten and bound body was pulled from an icy river 11 days later,
shocking Poland and galvanizing the anti-Communist movement.
   Four secret policemen were convicted of the slaying.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0069 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 2152EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ElectricalFire 1stLd-Writethru a0637 11-11 0206</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Electrical Fire, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0637,0219</SECOND>
<HEAD>Underground Electrical Fire and Explosions Disrupt Downtown
Business</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 2 grafs for grafs 3-5, `Pacific Gas...' to UPDATE with
cause of fires traced. Pickup at 6th graf pvs, ``Shoppers fled
...'</NOTE>
<DATELINE>SAN FRANCISCO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Smoky fires and explosions ripped through
underground electrical circuits, closing down one of downtown's
busiest shopping districts for five hours.
   Only a handful of customers lost power, despite the long
disruption of traffic and business in the incident Saturday,
officials said.
   The trouble was traced to a break in a water main, which caused
a short in electrical equipment at the corner of Sutter Street and
Grant Avenue near the southern edge of Chinatown, said Pacific Gas
&amp; Electric spokesman Paul Ward. No one was injured.
   Red smoke began belching out of a manhole at the intersection on
Saturday morning.
   Shoppers fled and merchants closed shop as police, fire, Health
Department and PG&amp;E officials rushed to the scene.
   By early afternoon, it appeared that the blaze had died down,
but then explosions blew manhole covers out of the ground in the
area.
   ``It was pretty scary, I thought the mirrors were going to
break,'' said Chris Qadir, a clothing salesman.
   The blaze finally was contained within the conduit of a backup
electric system.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0070 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 2201EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Japan-Enthronement 3rdLd-Writethru a0701 11-11 0721</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Japan-Enthronement, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0701,0855</SECOND>
<HEAD>Emperor Akihito To Be Formally Enthroned in Controversial Rite</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Leads with 17 grafs to UPDATE with new attacks, including one
at U.S. base; picks up 13th graf pvs, `A record .... TRIMS
thereafter</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Enthronement scheduled between 11-11:30 p.m. EST
</TEXT>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto staffing</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVID THURBER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In a solemn, centuries-old rite at the Imperial
Palace, Emperor Akihito formally accedes to the Chrysanthemum
Throne on Monday, becoming the first Japanese monarch enthroned as
a symbol and not a living god.
   Leftist radicals launched a series of attacks aimed at
disrupting the ceremony. They fired missiles at five military
bases, including a U.S. naval base, and were blamed with setting
fires at religious shrines and train stations. None of the attacks
caused injuries.
   A massive national security operation involving thousands of
police was mounted to protect the ceremony and the scores of
visiting dignitaries.
   Clad in ancient court costume, seated atop an elaborate
lacquered platform under a curtained canopy encrusted with gold
phoenixes and circular mirrors, Akihito will face a courtyard lined
with ceremonial banners.
   Next to him on a smaller platform will be Empress Michiko. Prime
Minister Toshiki Kaifu will lead the 2,500 guests in three cheers
of ``Banzai!'' - ``May you live ten thousand years!''
   Akihito began his morning rituals by offering private prayers at
three wooden shrines inside the heavily guarded Imperial Palace to
announce his enthronement to the Sun Goddess and ancestors.
   Critics say the 30-minute ceremony - and a series of
accompanying rites to be held in coming weeks - are based too
closely on the traditional religious rituals used for Akihito's
father and grandfather, who were enthroned as living gods.
   Under Japan's postwar constitution, the emperor is simply a
national symbol.
   In one controversial element of the rite, Akihito's raised dais
is said to be patterned after one used by the sun goddess, from
whom tradition says the Japanese imperial line is descended.
Critics say that is an implied symbol of divinity.
   The government is reportedly spending $95 million on the rites,
much of it for security. Opponents say state funding of the
ceremonies, linked to Japan's indigenous Shinto religion, violates
the constitutional separation of religion and state.
   The radical left has been particularly incensed because of the
legacy of imperial militarism in Japan.
   The projectiles were launched at three suburban bases of the
military and at a base in western Tokyo, police said. No damage was
reported.
   Another missile was fired outside the U.S. naval base at Atsugi,
24 miles southwest of Tokyo. The base was apparently the target of
that failed attack.
   Three train fires stopped service on two commuter lines, and in
separate incidents, two major subway lines were shut down because
of smoke.
   Fires also broke out at four Shinto shrines in Tokyo, including
one less than a mile from Akihito's residence. Police said all were
believed started by extremists.
   No injuries were immediately reported, but tw shrines were
destroyed.
   On Sunday, two bombs exploded at the house of U.S. Consul
General Gregory L. Johnson in Nishinomiya, in western Japan. Police
said they caused little damage and no injuries. It was not
immediately clear whether the explosions were connected with the
enthronement.
   A record 37,000 police, including reinforcements from a majority
of Japan's 47 prefectures, have been mobilized for security
surrounding the rite. Security was particularly heavy around the
downtown palace, where Akihito began his morning rituals by
offering private prayers to the sun goddess at a wooden shrine.
   Dignitaries from 158 countries expected to attend the ceremony
include Vice President Dan Quayle, United Nations Secretary-General
Javier Perez de Cuellar, Supreme Soviet Chairman Anatoly I.
Lukyanov and Britain's Prince Charles and Princess Diana.
   The government has not released the names of Japanese
dignitaries invited to the ceremony, because of fear of radical
attacks on their homes or businesses.
   Traffic was sharply restricted or halted along highways and in
areas around the palace, but few tie-ups were reported, in part
because enthronement day was declared a national holiday and many
Tokyoites took advantage of the three-day weekend to leave town.
Airlines reported many flights were booked close to capacity.
   Akihito became emperor immediately upon the death of his father,
Emperor Hirohito, in January 1989, but a period of mourning was
observed before his formal enthronement.
   Akihito, 56, was tutored after World War II by an American
pacifist, and is the first emperor in modern Japanese history to
marry a commoner. He and the empress also raised their three
children themselves, rather than have them raised separately by
aides, as was the imperial custom.
   As with Hirohito's funeral, which was attended by
representatives of 164 nations, the enthronement provided
opportunity for a flurry of diplomatic meetings. Kaifu was
scheduled to meet with about 50 foreign officials.
   On Monday evening, the first of seven banquets scheduled over
five days is to be held at the Imperial Palace, with senior
Japanese officials and foreign dignitaries attending.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0071 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 2202EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Gulf-Opposition     11-11 0275</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Opposition,0312</SECOND>
<HEAD>Relatives of U.S. Troops Launch Effort Against Gulf Policy</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Relatives of American troops in the Persian Gulf
set up a new family support group Sunday that opposes a U.S.
military offensive there.
   The Military Families Support Network was organized by the
author of an angry, open letter to President Bush that was
publised in The New York Times. Alex Molnar, the father of a
Marine in Saudi Arabia, says the group has 2,500 members and
chapters in eight states.
   ``This is the first time I know of that military families and
patriotic, mainstream Americans are among the first to voice doubts
over American policy,'' he said in a statement.
   Molnar's letter to the president, published Aug. 23, expressed
concerns and fears about the military buildup in the Persian Gulf
after Iraq's Aug. 2 invasion of Kuwait.
   Molnar, an education professor at the University of Wisconsin in
Milwaukee, said he received a flood of telephone calls after the
letter appeared and decided to form the group.
   The organization has chapters in New York, California, Texas,
Nebraska, Illinois, South Carolina, North Carolina and Tennessee,
Molnar said.
   The group wants Bush to invoke the War Powers Act and allow
Congress to decide whether the United States goes to war. However,
the organization is calling for a diplomatic solution to the
crisis.
   The group also supports United Nations resolutions condemning
Iraq and imposing economic sanctions, but it opposes the massive
deployment of American ground forces or a military offensive.
   Molnar said money raised by the group would be used for an
advertising campaign.
   ``The Vietnam War generation, it seems, is not about to send its
children and family members into another war with questionable
moral grounding, without a cry for public debate and the consensus
of the American people,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0072 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 2232EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SolarRace     11-11 0445</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Solar Race,0555</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rain Puts Damper on Solar Race</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto MAT3</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DARWIN, Australia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Rain put a damper on the first day of
the World Solar Challenge race Sunday, wiping out any chance at the
record pace organizers had predicted.
   Darwin's first consistently rainy day since May delayed the
start by an hour. A crowd of several thousand cheered as the event
got under way with the announcement: ``Gentlemen, start your solar
panels.''
   Mostly overcast conditions persisted as the cars headed south
toward Adelaide, 1,875 miles away. With the 36 cars from nine
countries spread out over 90 miles, a torrential rain forced many
drivers to stop and cover their cars.
   ``It was amazing that the satellite maps showed the only real
cloud over Australia this morning was over Darwin,'' said race
organizer Hans Tholstrup.
   The entry from Western Washington University at Bellingham,
Wash., took the early lead over Biel University of Switzerland.
   The leaders were not expected to cover more than 300 miles the
first day. The winner of the inaugural event in 1987, General
Motors' Sunraycer, traveled almost 450 miles in one day to set a
record.
   Western Washington's car has fore and aft driver positions so
the vehicle can point in either direction to take best advantage of
the sun's position.
   Speeds were expected to pick up once the cloud cover dissipated.
The cars race nine hours each day, usually stopping before 5 p.m.
   Sunraycer, the 1987 winner, averaged 42 mph and hit a top speed
of 71 mph. It reached Adelaide in 44 hours and 54 minutes, over
five days.
   For much of the route through desolate central Australia, there
are no trees, just scrub brush, grass, rocks, and usually plenty of
sun. The temperature in the Outback can exceed 120.
   Entered are 11 cars each from Australia and Japan, eight from
the United States and one each from Canada, Switzerland, Germany,
Denmark, New Zealand and England.
   The prize is a trophy of a globe topped by the sun.
   With oil prices skyrocketing, interest in the solar race is
keener than for the first event three years ago.
   Retired American real estate developer J. Ward Phillips said
more than $23.4 million worth of technology was taking part in what
he grandly described as ``the most significant event in the history
of the universe.''
   The lineup reads like a ``Who's Who'' of engineering and
automotive technology.
   GM is sponsoring the top three finishers in a July university
race from Florida to Detroit. Japan's Honda Research and
Development Co. Ltd. has an entry, and the only British car, under
the name of Phil Farrand, is actually from the Williams Formula One
Grand Prix team.
   The solar car has come so far that GM has unveiled a prototype
production model, the Impact, which it claims will out-accelerate a
Mazda MX-5 sports car to 60 mph.
   Japan's Kyocera Corp., with an 11-member team, estimates it
invested $546,000 to enter its Blue Eagle in this year's race.
   GM spent about $3.9 million on Sunraycer, now housed in the
Smithsonian Institution in Washington, D.C.
   The difference is due to advancements in silicon cells, which
cost a small fraction of the gallium arsenide cells used for
Sunraycer.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0073 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 2300EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-PoliceStandoff 1stLd-Writethru a0704 11-11 0255</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Police Standoff, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0704,0307</SECOND>
<HEAD>Man Wounds Two After Dispute Over Dog, Kills Himself After
Standoff</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 5th graf, `One of ...' to CORRECT that Carr sted
Fillinger was shot trying to calm down gunman and that Fillinger,
sted Carr, was shot while walking by. Picks up 6th graf, `Police
negotiators ...'</NOTE>
<DATELINE>COLUMBUS, Ohio (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A gunman wounded two people in a traffic
dispute over an injured dog, then holed up in his house for eight
hours before killing himself, police said.
   A SWAT team discovered Manuel Ramon dead when it stormed the
house Saturday, police Lt. Edward DeVennish said.
   ``He got into a dispute about a street being blocked because
people pulled over in a car to help a wounded animal,'' DeVennish
said.
   Ramon grew angry when people trying to help the dog wouldn't let
him pass in his car.
   One of the injured, Brendon Carr, 19, of Columbus was shot after
trying to calm down Ramon, witnesses said. The other, Angela
Fillinger, 25, also of Columbus, was shot while walking past the
house near Ohio State University.
   Police negotiators tried to talk Ramon out of the house and
fired tear gas after an eight-hour standoff, DeVennish said.
   Richard Heuring of Cincinnati, a student at Ohio State, said he
was standing next to Carr when the gunman opened fire.
   ``We came outside after we heard screeching tires,'' Heuring
said. ``We saw the dog on the ground. ... We were about to go
inside when this guy got out of his car and was yelling to move the
car.''
   Heuring said he and Carr tried to calm the man.
   ``But the guy shouted, `I don't care about any dog, move the
car!''' Heuring said.
   The injured were listed in fair condition Sunday, a hospital
spokesman said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0074 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 2306EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-OaklandRapes     11-11 0253</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Oakland Rapes,0286</SECOND>
<HEAD>Prosecution of Old Rape Cases Unlikely, Police Say</HEAD>
<DATELINE>OAKLAND, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Prosecution of old rape cases that were
reopened for investigation is unlikely because alleged victims have
been difficult to find or are unwilling to cooperate, police said.
   The 228 cases were reopened in September after it was revealed
one in four reported rapes and attempted rapes last year were
classified by police as ``unfounded,'' meaning police determined
the rapes did not occur.
   Police conceded at the time that some of the victims were never
contacted by investigators after the initial report. Many of the
alleged victims were cocaine users, prostitutes or acquainted with
their assailants, police and rape crisis workers said.
   Subsequent investigation found 79 of 112 alleged rapes reviewed
so far did occur, but the prospect for arrests and prosecution is
slim, Oakland police Capt. James Hahn said.
   In some cases, investigators were unable to contact victims,
either because they gave incorrect addresses or moved. In other
instances, the victims did not respond to investigators or said
they did not want to prosecute.
   ``Some said they were getting their life together and didn't
want to pursue the case,'' Hahn said. ``One lady cursed
investigators.''
   Of 19 cases that remain unfounded, police determined one was
reported by a mother who wanted to prevent her daughter from having
an affair. Another was reported by a person other than the victim,
who told police she had not been raped. Hahn said those were
typical of the reasons the rest of the 19 are still considered
unfounded.
   A review of all 228 cases will be completed by next month and
presented to the City Council, Hahn said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901111-0075 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-11-90 1339EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-ComputerShow Bjt   11-11 0558</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Computer Show, Bjt,0663</SECOND>
<HEAD>New Products, Hype and Recession Talk Expected At Largest Computer
Show</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BART ZIEGLER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LAS VEGAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The computer industry will trot out new
products and crank up its promotion machine as the world's largest
annual computer show opens here Monday. But the hype may be
overshadowed by the looming recession.
   Computer sales have been slowing for several years. With the
economy as a whole entering a slump, the industry's outlook could
darken further.
   Domestic sales of personal computers fell about 25 percent in
September compared with the first eight months of the year,
according to Prudential-Bache Securities Inc.
   However, the economic downturn is not among the dozens of
industry and technical topics scheduled for panel discussions
during the show, called Comdex Fall. In typical trade-show fashion,
the official patter will be upbeat.
   Among issues that will be addressed by industry experts are
multimedia computing, or the use of video, photographs and
animation on computers; a related technology called image
processing; portable computers; and business opportunities in the
``new Europe.''
   The keynote speaker is Bill Gates, the young chairman of
software powerhouse Microsoft Corp. Gates is scheduled to talk
Monday about the evolution of personal computing and its future.
   Gates' company has been in the news this year for its software
that gives International Business Machines Corp. computers and
compatible models many of the ease-of-use features of Apple
Computer Inc.'s Macintosh. Microsoft says it has sold more than 1
million copies of the Windows 3 software since its June
introduction.
   Also scheduled to speak is Gilbert Hyatt, an engineer who in
July was granted a patent for his work in developing the
microprocessor. The patent award called into question the computer
industry's official history, which says the computer-on-a-chip was
invented by several Intel Corp. scientists.
   One of the more important bits of news expected at Comdex won't
be announced at a flashy news conference. Instead, semiconductor
maker Advanced Micro Devices Inc. will give private demonstrations
of its new product, a clone of Intel's extremely popular 386
microprocessor.
   The 386 chip is the brains of an increasing number of IBM
personal computers and compatible models. AMD says its chip is even
better than the original.
   However, the company doesn't plan a full-scale announcment at
the show because it has not set the price or availability date for
the chip, said AMD spokesman David Frink.
   Apart from the panel discussions, one of the major attractions
of Comdex to those in the industry are the acres and acres of
computer products on display. Among the more intriguing devices
will be tiny personal computers called notepads and other portable
computers that recognize handwriting.
   Comdex is billed as the nation's largest annual trade show. It
virtually takes over Las Vegas this week, with 118,000
conventioneers overflowing hotel rooms and more than 1,800 product
exhibitors from 22 countries cramming onto display floors at the
Las Vegas Convention Center and five hotels.
   The 12-year-old gathering is a forum for major computer makers
to attract new distributors for their products. It also is used by
tiny startup companies to gain a foothold in the vast computer
market.
   Though the show is aimed primarily at computer sellers, it draws
computer experts and insiders of all sorts, from trade letter
editors to Wall Street analysts. About 1,800 members of the press
are expected, organizers say.
   However, Comdex appears to be losing some of its luster as a
place for computer companies to make major announcements, some
observers say.
   ``You get lost in the noise,'' said Esther Dyson, publisher of
the computer newsletter Release 1.0 and a Comdex veteran. Plus, she
added, with the growth of other computer industry gatherings,
``It's no longer THE big event of the year.
   ``The industry is getting less cohesive. There are so many
different parts and interest groups,'' she said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
</Collection>
