<Collection>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0001 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 2354EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-PrisonRiot 6thLd-Writethru a0755 04-01 0728</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Prison Riot, 6th Ld-Writethru, a0755,0743</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hundreds of Inmates Riot At English Prison; 50 Injured</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS grafs 5-8 bgng `Hundreds of...' with 7 grafs to CLARIFY
that most of prison appears to remain under control of inmates and
that is is unclear how many prisoners still are rioting; pickup 9th
graf pvs, `Scores of...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By MAUREEN JOHNSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MANCHESTER, England (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   About 700 inmates rioted at a crowded
19th century prison Sunday, occupying rooftops, smashing windows
and setting fires. At least 50 guards and inmates were injured,
police said.
   Television newscasts carried unconfirmed reports that witnesses
had seen up to 12 bodies. A police spokesman said inmates brought
out of Strangeways Prison also reported deaths, but that police
would not be able to confirm this until they reached the center of
the complex.
   The Home Office said no hostages were being held, and police
said talks with prisoners were under way. There was no clear
indication of the cause of the rioting at the medium-security
prison, built in the Victorian era and now one of the most crowded
in Europe.
   Home Office spokesman Charles Keseru said prison officers
regained control of one wing of the jail Sunday evening and found
no seriously injured inmates. The office said 12 injured staff
members and 25 inmates were taken to area hospitals.
   The rioters appeared to have the rest of the complex under
control, however. Prisoners were surrendering to authorities and
about 400 had given up late Sunday night, Keseru said.
   It was not clear how many still were participating in the riot
or the circumstances of the prisoners who were not involved. The
prison was built for 970 inmates but houses about 1,600.
   Hundreds of riot police surrounded the prison and a police
helicopter hovered overhead as flames leaped 20 feet into the air
from the prison gymnasium, where a fire burned out of control.
   Twenty-five firefighters under police protection battled the
blaze as dense black smoke billowed above the building.
   Fires also were reported to have been set in three cells and a
classroom as large groups of inmates rampaged inside. Those fires
later were reported under control.
   Scores of police vans lined side streets around the prison, a
mile from the Manchester city center in central England. The Home
Office, responsible for prisons and law enforcement, said the
perimeter of the prison was secure.
   An office statement said the uprising began in the prison chapel
at 11 a.m., when 300 inmates attacked staff members.
   ``Those prisoners then gained access to the chapel roof and then
broke into the living accommodation in the main prison. Other
prisoners, including those on remand, joined in the disturbance and
staff had to be withdrawn,'' the statement said.
   As many as 80 prisoners reportedly made their way on to the
rooftops of the jail's F wing, the prison chapel and adjoining
buildings. The windows of a central turret linking several wings
were smashed as prisoners made their way to the roof.
   Once there, the prisoners tore roof tiles up and hurled them
into the prison courtyard where there were believed to be groups of
riot police and prison officers.
   The prison, built in 1868, has been criticized as cramped and
inadequate because of the crowding. In response, Home Secretary
David Waddington has announced plans to expand Strangeways.
   Judge Stephen Tumin, chief inspector of prisons, said in a
report last week on Strangeways that one shower a week was the norm
for the inmates and up to 400 men had no work assignments. He said
the most dangerous men were locked up 22 hours a day.
   Last week, two prisoners at Strangeways climbed onto the roof in
a protest, but the reason was not made public.
   The prison serves the local area; one-third of its inmates are
awaiting trial and two-thirds have been sentenced, the Home Office
said.
   Many of Britain's prisons date from Victorian times, and
crowding has become a serious problem. One of the worst previous
riots occurred in May 1989 at Risley Remand Center near Liverpool,
when 54 inmates staged a rooftop demonstration and held off police
for four days.
   The most famous riot in British penal history this century was
at Dartmoor, the jail on the moors of Devon, where fighting over
poor food and conditions in 1932 left 70 inmates and six guards
injured.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0002 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 2356EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-KaiserStrike     04-01 0390</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Kaiser Strike,0401</SECOND>
<HEAD>Thousands of Kaiser Employees Promise to Strike Monday</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PASADENA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Thousands of employees of local Kaiser
Permanente hospitals and medical offices pledged to go on strike
Monday after a weekend negotiating session failed to resolve a
labor dispute, officials said Sunday.
   ``The union has issued a strike alert for one minute after
midnight,'' said Janice Seib, a spokeswoman for Kaiser Permanente,
the nation's oldest and largest health maintenance organization.
   The service employees union representing 11,000 hospital workers
rejected Kaiser's three-year, $44-million contract, and a federally
mediated session produced no new resolutions.
   The union includes licensed vocational nurses, clerks, house
keepers and radiology technicians at seven of the Pasadena-based
Kaiser Permanente Medical Centers and more than 40 satellite
medical offices in Los Angeles and Orange counties.
   Kaiser will draw additional workers from other Kaiser facilities
in San Bernardino, Riverside and San Diego counties that are
unaffected by the strike called by clerical, technical and service
employees, Seib said.
   ``We've already been reducing the number of patients in our
hospitals from 40 to 60 percent,'' Seib said, adding officials have
transferred some patients and postponed non-emergency surgeries and
elective surgeries.
   A six-hour negotiating session with representatives from Service
Employees International Union, Local 399 ended Saturday without an
agreement, Seib said.
   ``The feeling is that we've presented the union with an
extremely fair contract that guarantees they'll always be paid 4
percent higher than any other facility in the area,'' Seib said.
   The contract offer included a 5 percent to 6 percent raise in
the first year and a 3 percent to 5 percent raise during the second
and third year. The offer was approved by the union negotiating
team on Thursday.
   The next day some 5,000 workers, less than half of the union
membership, voted to rejected the contract by a more than
two-to-one ratio, said Tom Ramsay, a union spokesman.
   Kaiser employees accepted a wage freeze three years ago and have
stood by the company during its nine years of financial difficulty,
Ramsay said.
   ``Now that Kaiser is back on their feet and prospering,
employees expected some recognition and didn't get that, and they
were very angry,'' Ramsay said.
   The hospitals affected by the labor dispute are located in Los
Angeles, West Los Angeles, Panorama City, Woodland Hills, Harbor
City, Bellflower and Anaheim, said Seib.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0003 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 0021EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Defector-Slayings     04-01 0308</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Defector-Slayings,0316</SECOND>
<HEAD>Soviet Defector Surrenders in Slayings of Wife, Daughter</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NORTH FORT MYERS, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Soviet defector whose family
joined him in the United States last year after a 9-year struggle
allegedly shot and killed his wife and one daughter and wounded
another daughter, police said Saturday.
   Valentin Bereza, 58, fled to Tennessee after the shootings
Thursday night and surrendered Saturday morning to police in
Nashville, police said. Nashville homicide detective Walter Keeler
Jr. said Bereza was being held for Florida police on a fugitive
warrant.
   Bereza is charged with the premeditated shooting deaths of his
wife, Raisa Bereza, 53, and daughter Elena, 30, as well as the
premeditated attempted murder of his second daughter, Tonya, 17,
the sheriff's office in Lee County, Fla., said Saturday.
   Officers in North Fort Myers said Raisa and Elena Bereza died of
gunshots to the head from a large-caliber handgun. Tonya Bereza was
in fair condition in a hospital recovering from a gunshot to the
face.
   According to Tonya, her father put on his best suit before
announcing that he was ``unhappy with Elena's behavior,'' the
statement said without elaboration.
   ``He gathered his family around the dinner table and told them,
`I'm leaving and I'm going to kill you now,''' Lee County sheriff's
spokesman Robert Graziano said. ``Then he pulled out a gun and
started shooting.''
   Tonya fled the house as Bereza went into another room to reload
the gun, the sheriff's office said.
   Bereza, a civil engineer, defected from the Ukraine in the
Soviet Union in July 1980 and had lived in Fort Myers for about
three years, police said. With help from the U.S. government, Elena
was able to emigrate last May and Raisa and Tonya followed in
September.
   The State Department had been notified after the shooting
Thursday in case he tried to leave the country.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0004 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 0001EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Honduras-Attack 4th-LdWritethru   04-01 0733</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Honduras-Attack, 4th-Ld Writethru,a0619,0757</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.S. Soldiers Attacked in Honduras</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with nine grafs to update with soldiers evacuated;
Pickup 7th pvs, `Jessup said...'</NOTE>
<DATELINE>TEGUCIGALPA, Honduras (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Snipers fired automatic weapons at
a bus carrying 28 U.S. airmen along a mountain road Saturday, and
seven soldiers were wounded, two seriously, U.S. officials said.
   An anonymous caller to the private radio network Radio America
claimed responsibility on behalf of the leftist Morazano National
Liberation Front.
   U.S. Embassy spokesman Terrence Kneebone said U.S. government
personnel in Honduras had been on a precautionary alert ahead of
the second anniversary this week of the burning of the U.S.
consulate in Tegucigalpa to protest the extradition of an alleged
drug kingpin.
   Three attackers fired on the bus six miles north of Tegucigalpa,
the capital, said Maj. Bruce Jessup, a spokesman for U.S. troops
based in the Central American nation.
   ``The Americans did not have time to return fire, although there
were some security personnel on the bus,'' he said.
   Kneebone said that seven soldiers were wounded. He said one
soldier shot in the head was in critical condition, and another
wounded in the stomach was in ``delicate condition.''
   Kneebone said the other five injured soldiers were out of danger.
   He said four of the five were being evacuated by air Saturday
night to the U.S. Southern Command in Panama, ``where they have
better treatment facilities at Gorgas Hospital than in Soto Cano.''
   ``All five are out of danger. In fact, they walked out of the
hospital after receiving first aid treatment earlier in the day,''
he said.
   Jessup said the servicemen are members of the U.S. Air Force,
but he refused to identify them by unit or release the names of the
injured.
   Asked how he knew there were three attackers, Jessup said the
U.S. soldiers had seen them as they fled.
   A White House spokesman, Sean Walsh, said in Washington: ``We
deplore any action against U.S. citizens. We'll be working closely
with the Honduran government on the investigation.''
   The Morazano Front, founded in 1979, is thought to be an arm of
the Communist Party. The group takes its name from Gen. Francisco
Morazan, a former president of Honduras.
   It claimed responsibility for the last major attack on U.S.
forces in Honduras, on July 13, 1989, when a homemade bomb was
thrown at nine U.S. Army military policemen in civilian clothes as
they passed a discotheque in La Ceiba, 200 miles north of
Tegucigalpa. Seven were injured.
   The group has also claimed reponsibility for a dynamite attack
Aug. 27, 1987, on a restaurant in town of Comayagua, near Cano Soto
Air Base. Six U.S. soldiers and six Honduras civilians were killed.
   The front also has claimed responsibility for six other similar
attacks on U.S. targets during the past decade.
   At the time of the attack Saturday, the U.S. soldiers, who were
dressed in civilian clothes, were returning from a brief period of
rest at Tela, a northern resort, to a work site south of
Tegucigalpa, U.S. officials said.
   A U.S. military official had erroneously reported earlier they
were returning to the Soto Cano Air Base, 50 miles northwest of
Tegucigalpa.
   The soldiers with less serious injuries were taken by helicopter
to Soto Cano, where U.S. troops on military maneuvers in Honduras
are frequently based, Jessup said. The uninjured soldiers also were
flown to the base, and all leaves there were canceled, Jessup said.
   The U.S. soldiers have been building roads and airstrips in
Honduras, Jessup said.
   The United States keeps several thousand personnel stationed in
Honduras.
   For about a decade, the U.S. military has frequently conducted
exercises in Honduras, which borders Nicaragua. U.S.-backed Contra
rebels have been living in Honduran jungle camps near the
Nicaraguan border.
   Kneebone said U.S. government had been on a precautionary alert
ahead of April 6, when in 1988 a mob burned the U.S. consulate to
protest the extradition of the alleged drug trafficker, Jose Ramon
Mata Ballesteros.
   Kneebone would not say specifically why U.S. government
personnel had been put on alert. ``We are always monitoring the
security and political environment and so on and we decided to take
these precautions,'' he said.
   Ballesteros, a Honduran citizen said to be linked to Colombia's
Medellin cocaine cartel, was flown to the United States to stand
trial on drug-smuggling charges.
   At the time, protesters demonstrated for several days, claiming
the extradition violated Honduras' constitution.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0005 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 0024EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-NuclearProtest 1stLd-Writethru a0612 04-01 0185</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Nuclear Protest, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0612,0187</SECOND>
<HEAD>Annual Spring Protest Draws 1,600 to Nuclear Test Site, 871
Arrested</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS in 1 graf to UPDATE with 871 arrests; pick up 2nd graf,
`An estimated ...</NOTE>
<DATELINE>MERCURY, Nev. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Authorities arrested 871 anti-nuclear
protesters Saturday for trespassing at an entrance to the Nevada
nuclear test site, a federal Department of Energy spokesman said.
   An estimated 1,600 demonstrators gathered at the highway
entrance on the second day of the protest, an event which has been
held every spring at the Nevada Test Site for a decade.
   The arrestees were transported to the town of Beatty, where they
were cited for trespassing and released, said DOE spokesman Derek
Scammell.
   There were no injuries, he said.
   The energy department oversees nuclear weapons tests at the
underground site in the desert, about 65 miles northwest of Las
Vegas.
   Kathrin Dress of the American Peace Test organization, said the
protesters held a rally earlier in the day and then began their
civil disobedience tactics. The protest will continue through
Monday, she said.
   There were 170 arrests on Friday, Scammell said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0006 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 0036EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Anaya-Reagan 1stLd-Writethru a0616 04-01 0784</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Anaya-Reagan, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0616,0806</SECOND>
<HEAD>Former Governor Says Reagan Comment Probably Triggered FBI, Other
Probes</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 11th graf, `Repeated telephone ...', with 5 grafs to
UPDATE with Apodaca, Lutz comment; pick up 12th graf, `Reagan
spokesman ...'. Toney is cq.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By PETE HERRERA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ALBUQUERQUE, N.M. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Former Gov. Toney Anaya said Saturday
that his calling then-President Reagan anti-Hispanic during the
early 1980s probably triggered a series of federal investigations
into Anaya's administration.
   The prominent Hispanic Democrat, addressing a workshop at the
National Association for Chicano Studies annual conference, said he
made the comment on an economic trip to Mexico in 1983 or 1984.
   Anaya, New Mexico's governor from 1983 to 1986, was investigated
by the FBI, the U.S. attorney's office in Albuquerque and the
Internal Revenue Service. No charges were ever filed against him.
   He said Saturday that he was asked to comment on Reagan and his
policies toward Mexico during a news conference that followed his
meeting with Mexico's president during the trip.
   ``I made the unfortunate statement suggesting that Ronald Reagan
was probably the most anti-Hispanic, and they translated that to
mean the most anti-Mexican, president we'd ever had,'' he recalled.
   John Ehrlichman, who was an aide to President Nixon and who
lives in Santa Fe, read of Anaya's comment while having breakfast
with former Gov. Jerry Apodaca, Anaya said.
   ``He told Jerry Apodaca, `They're going to get him. The feds are
going to get your friend Anaya. They're not going to tolerate
that,''' Anaya said. ``It wasn't days after that the first of many
federal investigations were kicked off.
   ``There were 13 FBI investigations altogether, there were three
federal grand jury investigations, there was one criminal IRS
investigation and two or three instances where we could trace that
the CIA had been used in these investigations,'' Anaya said.
   Anaya said he didn't learn of Ehrlichman's comments until
recently, when Apodaca, also a Democrat, related them to him.
   Apodaca said Saturday night Anaya took Ehrlichman's remarks out
of context.
   Apodaca said Ehrlichman indicated during their conversation that
he thought Anaya made a ``major mistake'' in criticizing Reagan
while outside the United States. Ehrlichman also said the Reagan
administration would ``never let him (Anaya) rest,'' Apodaca said.
   ``We were simply talking about prevailing attitudes in the
administration,'' Apodaca said.
   Repeated telephone calls to Ehrlichman's Santa Fe home Saturday
reached an answering machine. Albuquerque FBI spokesman Doug Belden
referred questions on the issue to U.S. Attorney William Lutz, who
denied that Anaya's remark prompted the federal investigations.
   ``It's untrue,'' Lutz said late Saturday. ``It's unfortunate
that he (Anaya) would attack President Reagan in that manner.''
   Reagan spokesman Mark Weinberg in Los Angeles said there would
be no comment from the former president, and suggested talking to
the FBI.
   During Anaya's term, Lutz conducted an extensive investigation
into the governor's finances. Anaya at the time accused the
prosecutor of using a federal grand jury to investigate the
governor's involvement in land transactions in New Mexico and
Pennsylvania.
   The IRS investigated Anaya's tax liabilities in 1983 and 1984.
According to court documents, the FBI investigated the awarding of
a State Fair concession contract after an unsuccessful bidder told
agents he'd heard a payoff had been made to Anaya.
   Anaya said Saturday that the various federal agencies that
launched investigations repeatedly leaked information to the news
media in their campaign against him, and accused news organizations
of ``fanning the flames.''
   Anaya, acknowledging his administration made many mistakes, said
he believes he was singled out by federal agencies because of
differences with the ``right-wing'' Reagan administration over his
``liberal, left-wing'' philosophy.
   ``We had a progressive agenda and that was not going to set very
well with them,'' he said. ``We had taken on Ronald Reagan
personally.''
   Anaya became the state's 21st governor behind a wave of
bipartisan support. But his four years in office were plagued by
controversy and criticism, often from the media. By the end of his
administration, Anaya's approval rating in public opinion polls had
dipped to about 12 percent.
   He suffered critical reviews for his Good Friday, 1986,
proclamation that New Mexico was a state of sanctuary for Central
American refugees and his Thanksgiving Eve decision that year to
commute the death sentences of the state's five death row inmates.
   Anaya, who was ineligible for a second consecutive term, was
succeeded by Gov. Garrey Carruthers, a Republican.
   Anaya has remained active in the Democratic Party. He is
chairman of the Hispanic Caucus for the Democratic National
Committee and a member of the party's national executive committee.
   He indicated when he left office that he would never again be a
political candidate, but said Saturday that that could change.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0007 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 0358EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-BuffaloTransit 2ndLd-Writethru a0617 04-01 0640</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Buffalo Transit, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0617,0655</SECOND>
<HEAD>Buses, Subways, Shutting Down Due to Funding Shortage</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS in 7 grafs to UPDATE with system completely shut down;
pick up 9th graf, `About 80 ...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By ALAN FLIPPEN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUFFALO, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Buffalo's cash-poor bus and subway system
shut down early Sunday after the city transit authority refused to
consider a county offer to take over the system.
   The last bus finished its run at 3:01 a.m., leaving New York
state's second-largest city the largest U.S. metropolitan area
without any public transit system. More than 120,000 people use
Buffalo's system daily.
   A city labor leader labeled the conflict a ``class struggle''
against selfish suburbanites who didn't want to pay for a system
they don't use.
   Erie County Executive Dennis Gorski said Saturday afternoon he'd
asked a Cincinnati management firm to administer the transit system
for the county if the Niagara Frontier Transportation Authority was
willing to yield control.
   But the authority, meeting with Gorski and city officials
Saturday night, refused to take up the offer and voted 7-2 to shut
down the system, repeating a similar vote take Wednesday.
   Gorski had said a county-run system would eliminate all but a
small core of bus and subway routes, but would be better than no
system at all. ``The alternatives are disastrous,'' he told a news
conference.
   ``You think I want a bus system?'' Gorski asked. ``I don't want
it, but I've got to keep it going.''
   About 80 percent of the transit system's 1,043 workers had
already been laid off by Saturday afternoon, authority spokesman
Daryl Rasuli said.
   On Wednesday, the county legislature rejected a proposed tax on
public utilities to fund transit after vigorous opposition from
business leaders. The next day, the transit agency's board approved
the shutdown 8-1.
   Attempts Thursday and Friday to put together a bailout plan
collapsed. Gorski rejected Mayor James Griffin's proposal to use
county sales taxes for transit; the board turned down Gorski's call
for sweeping service cuts and reorganizing the transit agency.
   The utility tax would have raised $9 million for the transit
system, which costs about $55 million a year to run. It has been
squeezed by declining federal subsidies and had only $89,000 in the
bank as of Saturday night.
   Among the first to be affected by a shutdown would be Buffalo
Sabres hockey fans. About 3,000 of the 16,000 fans expected to
attend Sunday night's season finale against the Quebec Nordiques
would normally have taken the subway to Memorial Auditorium.
   Taxi companies said they would be overworked because only 375
cabs are licensed to pick up people within city limits.
   Without a transit system, more than 12,000 public and private
schoolchildren who normally ride the bus or subway to school would
be stranded, said William Goldbach, assistant city school
superintendent for transportation. Goldbach said it would take 240
school buses to carry those children, but said, ``There simply
aren't enough bus drivers and vehicles available in the area.''
   Some downtown merchants planned to arrange car pools or taxis
for their employees, but others said they were waiting to see what
happened.
   About 110 people attended a noontime rally Saturday sponsored by
the Buffalo Teachers Federation.
   Union President Phil Rumore said the shutdown was a ``class
struggle'' against wealthy suburbanites and business interests
whose lobbying campaign sank the utility proposal.
   ``We're talking about people that have, saying the have-nots
don't need a public transportation system,'' Rumore said.
   Leonard Braun, New York area manager for the federal Urban Mass
Transit Administration, said he knew of no other transit system
that had ever been shut down by its own board for lack of funds.
   But Braun said there was no chance the federal government would
come to the rescue, calling the 1974 decision to provide operating
subsidies for mass transit ``a mistake.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0008 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 0458EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BusDriverShot Advisory   04-01 0042</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bus Driver Shot, Advisory,0047</SECOND>
<TEXT>
   
   Editors:
   
   Note that a0637, BC-Bus Driver Shot, stands as a 2nd
Ld-Writethru to a0635, AM-Bus Driver Shot.
   
   It updates throughout with details on driver's condition and
suspects and adds byline.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>The AP</HEAD>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0009 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 0647EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i BC-Lebanon     04-01 0289</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Lebanon,0297</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tension High in Christian Enclave as Civilians Flee</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BEIRUT, Lebanon (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Thousands of civilians fled their
embattled Christian enclave Sunday, taking advantage of a lull in
two days of ferocious intra-Christian fighting that killed at least
53 people and wounded 133 others.
   Police said a cease-fire called at midnight Saturday took hold,
silencing the heavy guns in the power struggle between rebel army
Gen. Michel Aoun and Christian warlord Samir Geagea for mastery of
the Christian enclave.
   A police spokesman said only minor sniping incidents in east
Beirut and the highlands of the Kesrouan province in the Christian
hinterland marred the truce.
   Long lines of cars packed with civilians fleeing the enclave
with beds, matresses and blankets to Syrian-policed west Beirut
formed at a newly reopened crossing through the city's port.
   The crossing was reopened after a one-year closure, making it
the second link between Beirut's Moslem and Christian sectors
besides the Museum crossing.
   Maronite Catholic Patriarch Nasrallah Sfeir said in his Sunday
sermon: ``Have we all been hit by triple blindness _ the blindenss
of the eye, the blindness of the heart and the blindness of the
conscience?
   ``How can we be blind to (the sight) of homeless families taking
shelter in forests?''
   The new-round of full-scale warfare broke out at dawn Friday
between Aoun's 19,000 army troops and the 6,000 militiamen of
Geagea's Lebanese Forces, shattering a March 3 cease-fire that had
been threatened by sporadic clashes for weeks.
   The casualties in the two days of clashes brought the overall
toll to 829 killed and 2,289 wounded since Jan. 30, when Aoun moved
against Geagea in a bid to crush the only significant challenge to
the general's authority in the 310-square-mile Christian enclave.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0010 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 1119EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>d i AM-BRF--Quake-Party     04-01 0125</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Quake-Party,0129</SECOND>
<HEAD>New Year's Celebrations Come Three Months Late for Quake City</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEWCASTLE, Australia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The festivities came three months
late, but the earthquake-hit city of Newcastle finally celebrated
New Year's Eve.
   The city about 100 miles north of Sydney was hit Dec. 28 by an
earthquake measuring 5.6 on the Richter scale, killing 12 people
and destroying many downtown buildings.
   Most of the New Year's Eve celebrations in the city of 500,000
were canceled as a result, but city officials decided to have a
``re-launching'' of the city on the March 31-April 1 weekend.
   Hundreds of people turned out Saturday night to several belated
New Year's Eve parties thrown by hotels, nightclubs and restaurants
in the New South Wales state coastal city.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0011 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 1122EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--6thFleet-Crash     04-01 0165</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--6th Fleet-Crash,0169</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.S. Navy Jet Goes Down; Pilot Rescued</HEAD>
<DATELINE>GAETA, Italy (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A U.S. Navy jet crashed in the western
Mediterranean during routine operations, but the pilot was quickly
rescued, a 6th Fleet spokesman said Sunday.
   The F-18 Hornet, operating from the U.S.S. Dwight D. Eisenhower,
was flying about 28 miles from the aircraft carrier when it went
down Saturday afternoon, said Lt. Jim Fallin.
   An SH-3 Sea King helicopter operating in the area recovered the
pilot within 10 minutes and returned to the carrier, Fallin said.
   The pilot, whose name was not released, was in stable condition.
The extent of his injuries was not immediately known. The cause of
the accident was under investigation.
   Fallin said the jet was attached to Fighter Attack Squadron 136,
based at Cecil Field, Fla., and that the helicopter was based at
the naval air station in Jacksonville, Fla.
   Both squadrons are embarked on the Eisenhower, which is
operating with the 6th Fleet in the Mediterranean.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0012 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 1125EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>d i AM-BRF--MassWeddings     04-01 0164</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Mass Weddings,0168</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ruler Urges Mass Weddings And Smaller Dowries To Cut Expenses</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SHARJAH, United Arab Emirates (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The ruler of this Persian
Gulf emirate urged his subjects to hold mass weddings and reduce
dowries to cut down on stratospheric marriage expenses.
   ``The problem is that there are several greedy fathers,'' Sheik
Sultan bin Mohammed al-Qassimi said in a Saturday night television
address, criticizing large dowries often demanded by brides'
fathers.
   Wedding celebrations and dowries can run as high as $28,000 in
this oil-rich Persian Gulf nation, prompting some men to seek
Indian, Filipino or Egyptian wives who do not insist on the local
dowry levels.
   Sheik Sultan rejected the idea of a law fixing dowries.
   ``This is not the way to tackle the problem, but it could be
solved by mass weddings, and I am personaly ready to attend such
parties and have them screened live by television,'' he said.
   Sultan also urged old men not to marry young foreign women.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0013 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 1125EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>d i AM-BRF--Cambodia-Boat     04-01 0148</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Cambodia-Boat,0154</SECOND>
<HEAD>Officials Say Cambodians Found in Boat Off Australian Coast</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PERTH, Australia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Customs authorities intercepted a
60-foot boat with 118 people aboard claiming to be Cambodian
refugees, officials said Sunday.
   The boat carrying 100 adults and 18 children was spotted by
plane late Saturday and intercepted at the entrance to King Sound,
about 1,200 miles north of Perth in Western Australia state,
Customs Service spokesman Brian Flanagan said.
   The spokesman said the boat's occupants claimed the vessel left
the southwest Cambodian port of Kompong Saom on March 11 and sailed
via Malaysia and Java, a journey of more than 2,000 miles.
   Those aboard the boat were short on supplies when discovered but
healthy, Flanagan said.
   Customs and quarantine checks were made and further inquiries
were under way, but Flanagan did not say if the Cambodians were
seeking permission to enter or reside in Australia.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0014 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 1132EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>d i AM-BRF--BastilleStrike     04-01 0167</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Bastille Strike,0170</SECOND>
<HEAD>Canceled Opera Rescheduled Amid Outrage by Fans</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A surprise strike by theater technicians at the
ultramodern Opera-Bastille prompted cancellation of ``The
Trojans,'' but outrage among fans who traveled far to see the
performance forced officials on Sunday to reschedule it.
   Some 3,000 people, many from abroad or the provinces, were
turned away from a Saturday show after technicians walked out
earlier in the day to demand better pay and working conditions.
   It marked the first cancellation at the glass-and-tile structure
since the opening performance of Hector Berlioz's six-hour epic two
weeks ago.
   Administrator George-Francois Hirsch offered to reimburse
spectators for the tickets, which ranged from $6.50 to $60. But
many paid speculators much more and demanded the scalp price plus
the cost of transportation and lodging.
   In a statement Sunday, the Opera-Bastille promised to honor the
tickets for a performance Monday and reimburse those not used.
American diva Grace Bumbry was to sing the leading roles of Dido
and Cassandra.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0015 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 1135EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--China-Tibet     04-01 0163</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--China-Tibet,0166</SECOND>
<HEAD>Air Routes Between Katmandu and Lhasa Resumed</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Air routes between Nepal's capital of Katmandu
and the Tibetan capital of Lhasa have been reopened more than a
year after being suspended because of anti-Chinese turmoil in
Lhasa, a news agency reported.
   The cross-Himalayan international route was inaugurated in 1987,
but closed after violent clashes between Tibetans seeking
independence from China and security forces led to the declaration
of martial law in Lhasa last March 8.
   China has since banned almost all visits by foreign diplomats,
journalists and tourists not traveling in an organized tour. It now
allows tour groups of three or more people to travel to Lhasa, but
restricts where they can stay and what they can see.
   China's Xinhua News Agency said Saturday that a Royal Nepal
Airlines Boeing 707 will fly one way from Katmandu to Lhasa every
Wednesday from April 25, and an Air China Boeing 707 will make the
return trip every Saturday.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0016 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 1141EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-TiananmenSquare     04-01 0452</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Tiananmen Square,0461</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tiananmen Square Closed on Day of Proposed Protest</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Mongolia-China, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Thousands of yellow-capped schoolchildren marched
on Tiananmen Square Sunday, but police barred the general public
from entering on a day when dissidents had urged a silent protest
in the plaza.
   The children were bused in to attend ceremonies marking civic
efforts to plant trees and flowers for the Asian Games to be held
in Beijing in September. Many waved the red flags of the Young
Pioneers, a group for teaching social and ideological values.
   The usual crowd of Sunday visitors to the square, mainly Chinese
tourists from outside Beijing, was kept behind police lines on the
outskirts of the 100-acre plaza.
   There were no signs of any attempts to mark the military assault
on the student-held square June 4 that left hundreds and perhaps
thousands of people dead on the streets of Beijing and ended the
seven-week, pro-democracy movement. Campuses in the northwest
corner of the city were reportedly quiet.
   Overseas dissident groups have urged students and other
activists to take a ``protest stroll'' on the square on April 1 and
April 5 to mourn those killed last year. April 5 is the Qingming
Festival, the annual day when Chinese honor their dead. On Qingming
in 1976, thousands of Chinese carried wreathes and flowers to
Tiananmen to honor Chou En-lai, the beloved premier who died that
January, and indirectly protest the ultra-leftist policies of the
government.
   The brutal suppression of that spontaneous show of defiance, in
what is now called the first Tiananmen Incident, led to the
eventual overthrow of the leftist ``gang of four.''
   Organized demonstrations are banned, and the ``stroll'' was
proposed to avoid the certain arrests of those participating in any
public protests against the repressive policies of the current
hard-line government of Premier Li Peng.
   Chinese sources say Communist Party officials in their work
units are telling them to stay away from Tiananmen Square, the
symbolic political center of China.
   There were stepped-up police patrols around the square Saturday
night, and police or soldiers on Sunday manned rooftop lookouts
around the square, peering down on the crowds with binoculars.
   Shortly before noon, thousands of People's Liberation Army
soldiers who have been bivouacked in the history museum on the east
side of the square since June 4 carried out their daily routine of
marching across the square to a dining hall on the other side.
   Also on Saturday, two wreathes dedicated to ``people's heroes,''
an apparent reference to soldiers killed during the attack on
Beijing last June, were placed at the base of the revolutionary
martyrs' monument in the center of the square. It was not known who
brought the wreathes.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0017 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 1157EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-SatelliteWeapons     04-01 0800</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Satellite Weapons,790</SECOND>
<HEAD>Army Pushing Anti-Satellite Arms, But Scaling Back Goal</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-NATO Nuclear Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT BURNS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Army is speeding up development of a
weapon to shoot down enemy satellites but has quietly dropped its
goal of building enough of the ``hit-to-kill'' rockets by the
mid-1990s to knock out all Soviet military satellites.
   The Defense Department asked Congress to nearly triple the
project's budget for the fiscal year starting Oct. 1, to $208
million. That would make it one of the fastest growing U.S. weapons
programs at a time when Congress is hailing the end of the Cold War
as reason to scale back defense spending.
   The Army estimates the total cost of an anti-satellite system at
between $2 billion and $2.5 billion _ most of that to be spent over
the next five years.
   The Army plans to develop two means of attacking satellites:
with kinetic, or non-explosive, warheads fired from 30-foot
missiles based on U.S. territory, and with ground-based lasers.
   The Army has put the kinetic warhead system on a fast
development track. In February it began soliciting bids from
industry to build between 60 and 75 of the weapons. A contractor is
scheduled to be selected in July, and full scale development would
start in 1992.
   The laser program is much further behind.
   While the pace of work on kinetic anti-satellite or ASAT
weaponry is picking up, the size of the eventual system has been
scaled back, according to Army officials.
   Brig. Gen. Morgan Jellett, who is in charge of the ASAT program,
said that until last December the Army had planned to buy 300 of
the weapons, or double the number of Soviet satellites now
deployed. In December it was decided that 60 to 75 weapons would be
enough to attack the most crucial Soviet space targets, he said.
   Congressional debate on the defense budget so far this year has
focused mainly on bigger-cost projects such as the B-2 bomber, the
MX intercontinental ballistic missile and other strategic systems,
and on savings from demobilizing troops. The anti-satellite
program, however, is beginning to draw more attention.
   ``I'm going to do everything I can to scrub it,'' Sen. Dale
Bumpers, D-Ark., a member of the Senate Appropriations Committee,
said in an interview. ``It just doesn't make any sense.''
   Bumpers said the Soviets' limited anti-satellite capability is
no threat to U.S. space interests, and that the Bush administration
should take up the Soviets' offer to negotiate a ban on the systems
before both sides shell out billions to build them.
   The ground-based anti-satellite program, as described by its
managers in recent interviews at the Army's Strategic Defense
Command in Huntsville, Ala., would not violate U.S. arms treaty
obligations, yet critics say it could reignite the superpower arms
race.
   Sen. John Glenn, D-Ohio, said in a March 7 floor speech that he
feared the United States could be sparking a ``superpower ASAT
race'' especially damaging to U.S. space interests, particularly
since the Air Force this year retired its fleet of SR-71 Blackbird
spy planes, which are less vulnerable to attack than low-earth
orbit satellites.
   Even the Army acknowledges that the Soviets probably would
respond to deployment of U.S. anti-satellite, or ASAT, weapons by
fielding their own version to knock out U.S. satellites, improving
defenses for their own satellites and by developing a weapon to
attack the U.S. anti-satellite systems.
   Jellett sought to play down the ``countermeasures'' issue,
saying, ``We don't see those being developed'' anytime soon.
   Yet an October 1989 Strategic Defense Command document outlining
a management plan for ASAT work said that as early as 1996 _ the
projected start of deploying a U.S. anti-satellite system _ Moscow
would have the technical and economic means to respond by
``enhancing the effectiveness of their force (and) degrading the
effectiveness'' of the American system, were it to be operated.
   The 150-pound kinetic warheads, often called ``hit-to-kill''
projectiles because they would literally destroy a target by
ramming it, enjoys the advantage over lasers of being effective in
any weather conditions and of making an easily verified ``kill.''
   The advantage of the laser is that it would produce less debris
in space and could make a covert strike, disabling a satellite by
blinding its electronics system but not causing it to explode.
   Jellett said a laser ASAT weapon could be used, for example, to
covertly disable the Soviet Mir space station, which U.S. officials
claim could be used for surveillance and military targeting.
Jellett said the Mir would be one of the main targets of an ASAT
system, but for the purpose of disabling it, not destroying it.
   The Army work is not part of the Strategic Defense Initiative,
known as Star Wars, which would put weapons in space to shoot down
ballistic missiles.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0018 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 1158EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-AssaultWeapons Bjt   04-01 0742</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Assault Weapons, Bjt,680</SECOND>
<HEAD>New Colt Firearms Owners Considering Resuming AR15 Production</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: Grafs 12-17 EMBARGOED for release at 6:30 p.m. EDT; time set
by source</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By CAROLYN SKORNECK</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The new owners of Colt Firearms are weighing
whether to resume production of the Colt AR15, the popular
U.S.-made, assault-style rifle. The former owners stopped sales to
civilians last year when the government banned imports of similar
weapons.
   Ron Stilwell, executive vice president and chief operating
officer of what is now called Colt's Manufacturing Co., said the
Hartford, Conn.-based company is considering whether to start
producing AR15s for civilians again.
   ``We are evaluating that,'' Stilwell said in an interview. ``We
will have some formal statements on it in the future.
   ``We firmly believe it is a legitimate sporting system and in
fact the only system that can be used for certain national target
matches,'' he said.
   The firearms division of Colt Industries was sold March 22 to a
group of investors, C.F. Holding.
   The Colt AR15 was the most popular U.S.-made semiautomatic
assault-style rifle when the former owners shut down production for
the civilian market in March 1989.
   The action occurred the day after the federal government imposed
a temporary import ban on dozens of foreign-made weapons with
similar characteristics. The import ban became permanent last July
on 43 styles of rifles.
   At the time, Colt Industries spokesman Mike Dunn said, ``We want
to conform to the spirit of the law although we weren't
specifically mentioned in the letter of the law.''
   Dunn said late Friday that Colt never resumed production of the
AR15 for civilian use.
   Susan Whitmore of Handgun Control Inc. said she was disappointed
that Colt's new management may reverse that decision.
   ``They're putting profits over public safety,'' Whitmore said.
``We don't want to see one more assault weapon on the streets, and
this is just going to add to it.''
</TEXT>
<HEAD>EMBARGOED until 6:30 p.m. EDT</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   
   In 1988, Colt produced 17,368 of the AR15s, according to a list
provided by the Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco and Firearms to Rep.
Pete Stark, D-Calif., a gun control advocate. Stark released the
list of U.S.-made semiautomatic assault-style rifles and pistols on
Sunday.
   The AR15 represented the largest domestic production of any
semiautomatic assault-style rifle or pistol, and copies of it made
by other manufacturers totaled 9,411.
   The ATF list of 78,201 rifles and pistols produced in 1988
included 38,108 rifles and an unknown number of Quality Parts
Bushmaster rifles and Ruger Mini 14s, as well as 40,093 pistols.
The ban on imports did not include pistols.
   The second and third largest number of U.S. assault-style
weapons produced in 1988 were the Intratec Tec 9 pistols, at
13,770, and the MAC-11 pistols, at 12,273, according to the ATF
list.
   The 26 types of weapons on the list had at least one of the
following assault-type characteristics: threaded barrels to
accommodate a silencer; flash suppressors that could hide the
shooter's position at night and prevent a loss of night vision;
provisions for mounting a bayonet; and folding or collapsible
stocks.
   The ATF listed such characteristics when it defined 43 types of
foreign-made guns as ``semiautomatic assault rifles'' that it
banned from import last July.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>END EMBARGOED material</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   
   When ATF Director Stephen E. Higgins announced the ban on
imports, he said a study had found that the models were ``not being
used for sporting uses,'' a requirement for imports.
   ATF does not control domestically produced weapons. Congress
does.
   The House Judiciary subcommittee on crime approved a bill two
weeks ago that would outlaw domestic assault-style weapons. The
bill, introduced by Rep. William Hughes, D-N.J., outlaws domestic
and foreign-made assault-style rifles. It also would outlaw
domestic and imported assault-style pistols which can accept a
silencer or a bayonet. The measure, approved 5-3, now awaits action
in the House Judiciary Committee.
   Foreign imports of semiautomatic assault-style rifles were far
outnumbering domestic production even before the import ban was
imposed, according to ATF.
   ATF spokesman Jack Killorin said imports of the 43 styles of
rifles later banned totaled 84,154 in 1986 and 83,695 in 1987.
Although the ATF did not total such imports in 1988, the approved
permits and pending requests skyrocketed in 1989, when the weapons
were banned.
   On April 7, 1989, a month after the temporary ban was imposed,
there were permits approved or requested to import a total of
926,510 semiautomatic assault-style weapons, he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0019 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 1202EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-UnionHousing     04-01 0513</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Union Housing,520</SECOND>
<HEAD>Employee Housing Bill, Originated in Boston, Moves in House</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN DIAMOND</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Legislation that would allow employers for the
first time to provide union workers with housing assistance is on
the fast track toward final passage in Congress this week.
   The bill, sponsored by a Boston hotel workers union local, calls
for a rare amendment to the Taft-Hartley labor law that would allow
employers to set aside money to help workers buy or rent housing.
   ``It's a private-sector initiative. It doesn't cost the
government a penny,'' said Bruce Marks, housing director for the
5,000-member Boston Hotel Workers Local 26. ``It's a pure
partnership to deal with a major social issue: the lack of
affordable housing.''
   The bill is more than a boon to unions, Marks said. Large
employers around the country have been contacting Local 26 asking
for details about the plan; many companies expressing an interest
are in areas where living costs are high, making it difficult to
recruit and keep employees.
   The legislation, carrying the unanimous recommendation of the
House Education and Labor Committee, is on the ``suspension
calendar'' for House floor debate this week _ meaning that it has
been deemed non-controversial.
   In a clear sign of the legislation's ideological breadth, Sens.
Edward Kennedy, D-Mass., and Orrin Hatch, R-Utah, co-sponsored the
bill in the Senate, where it already has received final approval.
   ``It's very important that we join with the Senate in passing
this legislation out of Congress, and I think the full House will
support it unanimously,'' said Rep. William Clay, D-Mo., chairman
of the labor-management relations subcommittee and the House
sponsor of the bill.
   Housing Secretary Jack Kemp and Labor Secretary Elizabeth Dole
are strongly behind the bill, according to Clay and union officials.
   Taft-Hartley, the nation's overriding labor relations law for 43
years, includes anti-corruption provisions that prohibit management
from making direct payments to unions except for certain purposes,
including employee education, health and retirement. The amendment,
up for a vote Tuesday, would add housing to that list.
   In December 1988 the hotel workers negotiated an agreement with
nine Boston hotels calling for wage and work improvements and an
unprecedented housing trust fund. The agreement required the hotels
to contribute 5 cents per hour for every employee into the trust.
Workers would not have to contribute.
   If Congress approves, the fund, now estimated at about $1
million, will be available to pay loan collaterals, help with down
payments, reduce mortgage interest rates, or pay apartment fees or
security deposits.
   Workers will apply to a joint union-management board for
assistance. A formula based on the employee's financial need will
be used to determine whether or how much money the worker receives.
   The contract stipulates that if the Taft-Hartley amendment is
not made by May 31, the trust fund money will revert to a fund used
for conventional union benefits.
   A particular challenge the union faced was a general hands-off
policy in Congress toward the Taft-Hartley Act.
   ``We've always had a fear of opening up the law,'' Clay said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0020 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 1219EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Lithuania-Gloom Bjt   04-01 0705</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lithuania-Gloom, Bjt,0729</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mood in Vilnius Grim as Press Leaves, Army Arrives</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ANN IMSE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>VILNIUS, U.S.S.R. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The mood in the Lithuanian capital was
grim Sunday as the Soviet army moved in dozens of additional
armored personnel carriers just hours after a threatening statement
from Soviet President Mikhail S. Gorbachev.
   The combination of the warning, the reinforcements, Friday's
seizure of a Lithuanian government building by Soviet troops and
the Soviet Union's drive to remove foreign correspondents from the
republic by Sunday night had many people worried that martial law
would be imposed within days.
   ``I fear they are going to start shooting,'' said one
middle-aged Lithuanian woman.
   Last week, Gorbachev said he would use force only if there was a
threat to life. Since then, Soviet authorities have complained of
several sniper attacks on soldiers.
   Lithuanian officials said they can find no evidence to support
the allegations and many fear that the reports are being created to
serve as a pretext for a military crackdown.
   The silence from Western nations in the face of these moves left
little hope of aid from abroad.
   White House spokesman Marlin Fitzwater said last Tuesday the
U.S. government did not want ``to inflame the situation'' by
issuing comments on the Soviet army's actions in Lithuania. The
army rounded up at least 23 Lithuanian deserters last week and has
occupied several buildings.
   In London, an assistant to Lithuania's prime minister, Laima
Andrikiene, was kept waiting while Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher
spoke with Gorbachev on the telephone.
   When Thatcher's conversation with the Soviet president ended,
Ms. Andrikiene's appointment was canceled, another member of the
delegation, parliamentarian Emanuelis Zingeris said.
   Gorbachev has said he fears a break-up of the Soviet Union could
result in chaos and violent conflict. He has said it would uproot
many of the 60 million people who do not live in their ancestral
lands.
   Saturday night, Gorbachev urged Lithuanian leaders to reverse
their republic's declaration of independence, saying they must
recognize their responsibilty for the Lithuanian people's
``security and well-being, for the state of democracy in the whole
country, and stability in the world.''
   He warned that if they refuse, ``the developments may have grave
consequences for all of us.''
   Lithuanian President Vytautas Landsbergis said Saturday night
Gorbachev was ``demanding impossible things,'' but said he would
send a delegation to Moscow on Monday to try to begin negotiations.
   On Sunday, the last foreign correspondents were being rousted
out of the republic. Hundreds of journalists from across the world
obeyed the Soviet government's order to depart, fearing the loss of
their Moscow bureaus if they refused.
   Many said they were depressed at being forced to leave Lithuania
after Gorbachev's warning.
   ``You do get this very sick feeling in your stomach that as soon
as we leave ... it's not going to be pretty,'' said Jonathan
Sanders of CBS.
   ``People in the (Lithuanian) TV station are very nervous,'' he
said. Sanders said the Lithuanian journalists expect their
reporting of the Moscow-Vilnius war of nerves to be halted as soon
as foreign networks are no longer on hand to record a Soviet
takeover of their stations.
   The Soviet army reinforced its garrison in central Vilnius
Sunday with at least 45 armored personnel carriers.
   ``It's the same Brezhnev doctrine at work as in
Czechoslovakia,'' only this time, Gorbachev is moving ``with a
smile, slowly and easily,'' said Algimantas Cekuolis, editor of
ther Lithuanian newspaper Gintasis Krastas, who has become a de
facto spokesman for the independent government.
   He was referring to the doctrine under which late Soviet leader
Leonid I. Brezhnev justified the 1968 Warsaw Pact invasion of
Czechoslovakia.
   Despite the pressure, Lithuanian officials say they are
convinced they will last longer than Gorbachev's authority over a
splintering empire.
   ``Our tactics are to hold on a couple of months,'' Cekuolis
said. He said he hopes for support from other Soviet republics
moving toward independence and from other democratically minded
legislators just elected to the Russian parliament.
   Lithuanians also said Gorbachev risks the loss of respect in the
Soviet Union and in the world if he is unable to assert his
authority without resorting to force.
   ``They are compromising the leadership of the Soviet Union,''
Landsbergis said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0021 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 1226EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-MutineerStockade     04-01 0599</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mutineer Stockade,0618</SECOND>
<HEAD>Boredom, Relaxation For Unrepentant Aquino Foes</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP Extra</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By EILEEN GUERRERO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MANILA, Philippines (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An armed guard watched over prisoners
who tried to topple President Corazon Aquino in December. His shirt
was emblazoned with the face of a mutiny leader and their motto:
``Our dreams shall never die.''
   Other guards mingled freely with more than 50 officers jailed at
Camp Crame following the Dec. 1-9 coup attempt. Guards shared meals
with family and friends of the inmates during visitors' day on a
recent Sunday.
   The prisoners are among 2,143 officers and enlisted men in
custody at various camps nationwide in connection with the
strongest and bloodiest bid so far to topple Mrs. Aquino's
four-year administration.
   Nearly 250 officers and enlisted men remain at large following
the coup attempt, in which at least 113 people were killed and more
than 600 wounded.
   Investigators admit, however, that many others may have secretly
supported the coup attempt. ``We don't know the extent of their
support,'' said one prosecutor who spoke on condition of anonymity.
``We are just working on what we have _ the tip of the iceberg.''
   Despite the gravity of the offenses, the atmosphere at Camp
Crame was more of a family reunion than a maximum-security
stockade. Guards addressed senior detainees with a respectful
``sir'' and played with children of the inmates.
   Four months after the coup attempt, only 81 officers have been
charged. The rest are still undergoing investigation while in
custody under conditions ranging from confinement in a stockade to
being restricted to military camps.
   Those at large include Gregorio ``Gringo'' Honasan, the
charismatic former lieutenant colonel, whose likeness was
emblazoned on the guard's shirt.
   Other fugitives include former Brig. Gen. Jose Zumel, once
superintendent of the Philippine Military Academy, and navy
Commodore Domingo Calajate, valedictorian of his academy class.
   No date has been set for trials, and sessions involving
defendants in previous coup attempts dragged on for months before
verdicts were returned.
   In the meantime, soldiers who had been among the cream of the
officer corps wile away their time at stockades discussing the
country's future and drafting position papers on alternative
government.
   They break the monotony with an occasional bottle of smuggled
liquor. ``We like it here,'' joked one senior officer who spoke on
condition of anonymity. ``We're just waiting for the next coup.''
   Like prisoners of war, inmates maintain a chain of command. At
the Camp Crame stockade, air force Brig. Gen. Jose Commendador, who
led the takeover of an air base near Cebu City, serves as the
acknowledged ``supremo.''
   Commendador even counsels prisoners and their wives about family
problems, once chiding a wife for not visiting her husband at every
occasion.
   Mutineers make no effort to hide their contempt for the military
hierarchy and their former commander-in-chief, Mrs. Aquino.
   In one cell, detainees exercise by punching a makeshift bag
adorned with sketches of the faces of the chief of staff, Gen.
Renato de Villa, and Defense Secretary Fidel Ramos, who has crushed
six attempts to oust Mrs. Aquino.
   Inmates named one cellblock the ``De Villa Detention Center''
and another the ``Ramos Detention Center,'' and joked that's where
they would confine the two if another coup attempt succeeds.
   Cell walls are plastered with posters bearing rebel slogans.
   One of them, titled ``A Filipino's Prayer,'' was patterned after
a prayer to the Virgin Mary:
   ``Hail Cory, an utter disgrace, the U.S. is with you ... pray
for us rebels, coup plotters, loyalists and activists now and at
the hour of the next coup or the strategic stalemate.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0022 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 1241EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Romania     04-01 0306</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania,0316</SECOND>
<HEAD>Thousands Demonstrate Against Romanian President</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BUCHAREST, Romania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Thousands of flag-waving demonstrators
shouting ``Down With Communism!'' marched through downtown
Bucharest Sunday demanding the resignation of the nation's interim
president.
   The demonstrators marched to government headquarters in Victory
Square holding brightly colored kites and chanting ``Down With
Iliescu!'' referring to President Ion Iliescu.
   Before the rally they gathered at University Square to kneel and
pray. The square was the site of heavy fighting during the
revolution that toppled Communist dictator Nicolae Ceausescu on
Dec. 22.
   Speakers at Victory Square accused Iliescu of being a ``closet
Communist'' and of sympathizing with Soviet leader Mikhail S.
Gorbachev.
   Iliescu is head of the National Salvation Front, the dominant
force in the provisional National Unity Council, which will rule
Romania until a new government is chosen after national elections
scheduled for May 20.
   Pre-election polls indicate that the Front is the most popular
political alliance in the country. The elections will be Romania's
first free balloting since 1947, when the Communist Party imposed
its single-party dictatorship.
   The demonstrators were joined by hundreds of bystanders as they
marched through downtown Bucharest, stopping at the major sites of
the Dec. 22 uprising.
   Hundreds of troops and paramilitary policemen stood guard at the
government headquarters and the entrance to the building was
blocked by a line of armored personnel carriers.
   ``We no longer need communism _ let the face of Gorbachev
disappear'' said Haralamb Zupascu, a former political prisoner and
one of the organizers of Sunday's demonstration.
   ``Say NO to the neo-Communist dictatorship of the National
Salvation Front!'' read one banner held aloft by the crowd.
   Meanwhile, the leader of the opposition Liberal Union party, Ion
Bratianu, declared his candidacy for president. On Saturday, Radu
Cimpeanu, the leader of the National Liberal Party, announced his
candidacy in the presidential race.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0023 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 1323EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-DeepCover     04-01 0911</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Deep Cover,800</SECOND>
<HEAD>Former DEA Agent Says Drug War a Sham</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CAROLYN SKORNECK</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Mike Levine is angry.
   The longtime Drug Enforcement Administration undercover agent
contends the war on drugs is a sham run by ``suits'' in Washington
who care more about their jobs than about winning the war or
preserving the lives of agents on the street.
   Levine says they killed the better part of his last major case
while needlessly putting his life and the lives of other agents in
jeopardy.
   If the plan had been carried out, he says, agents could have
arrested leaders of the Corporation, which runs Bolivia's cocaine
operations, and a major Bolivian money launderer in Panama while
seizing at least 38 tons of cocaine at secret air strips in Bolivia.
   But it was not to be.
   So a frustrated Levine, who retired from the DEA last year,
wrote a book about his experiences called ``Deep Cover.''
   ``The whole drug war has now become a political grab bag,''
Levine said in a recent interview. ``All of these people (leading
the war on drugs) have their arms in this grab bag for every reason
you can imagine.''
   The book focuses on a case _ Operation Trifecta _ that ended in
early 1988. It resulted in convictions and long sentences for
several Mexican and Bolivian drug traffickers.
   But Levine says it could have done much more if bureaucrats had
not stood in the way of his plan to buy 15,000 kilos (more than
30,000 pounds) of cocaine with $5 million, allowing him to
penetrate the upper reaches of the Bolivian cocaine trade.
   Among the book's contentions:
   _The agent in charge of DEA's Panama office, Alfredo ``Fred''
Duncan, suggested that the undercover agents stay at a Marriott
hotel, even though the drug traffickers called it the ``DEA hotel''
and refused to do business there. On a later trip, DEA headquarters
insisted that the agents again conduct business at the Marriott.
   _Duncan was asked several times to keep the Corporation's
alleged money launderer in Panama, Remberto Rodriguez, under
surveillance. But when Levine and another agent flew to Panama in
early 1988 to arrest Rodriguez, Duncan professed ignorance about
who he was, where he could be found and even that he'd been asked
to keep track of him.
   _Two months before final meetings between the agents and the
drug traffickers occurred at an undercover house in La Jolla,
Calif., near San Diego, U.S. Customs officials had escorted TV news
crews through the home. The crews filmed the attic where video
monitors and other eavesdropping equipment was set up, and even
took photos of lamps with hidden cameras.
   _Reporters also were on hand for the arrests of the Mexican and
Bolivian drug traffickers near the La Jolla home, and the news was
out all over Latin America long before the agents could arrest
Rodriguez or raid the Bolivian air strips. By the time Levine
arrived in Panama, Rodriguez had disappeared and the air strips had
been abandoned.
   _The DEA balked at Levine's plan because its top officials had
sold Congress on the value of Operation Snowcap, in which DEA
agents are sent to South America to help local officials eradicate
coca crops and cocaine processing laboratories. If his operation
had been successful, Levine says, it would have revealed that
Operation Snowcap was a waste of money and unnecessarily put agents
in harm's way.
   The only reason any of the plan went forward was because Customs
embarrassed DEA into it, offering to put up the money, Levine says.
   The DEA has been tight-lipped about the book, even though the
book criticizes such high-ranking officials as acting administrator
Terry Burke, chief of operations David Westrate and Duncan.
   ``We feel it's inappropriate to debate the merits of the
specifics of his book with anyone and we are not going to have
anything such as this distract us from our mission,'' DEA spokesman
Frank Shults said.
   ``It's unfortunate that a former narcotics agent has taken on
all of his former colleagues,'' Shults added. ``As an individual,
his view is limited to that of an individual and he was never in a
position to know the best direction that the agency should take.''
   At Customs, spokesman David Hoover said, ``We don't have an
official reaction to his book. It's not a cause celebre around
here.''
   To Jim Dozier, the book was real. Now the county attorney in
Montgomery County, Texas, Dozier spent eight years in the DEA after
two years with Customs, all of it in drug enforcement.
   ``Many things rang true in the case that made me grin with
frustrations I had in the past with certain cases,'' Dozier said in
an interview.
   Dozier said he could recall ``many times when you have something
good in hand'' that had to ``go through 15 lines of bureaucrats who
hadn't been on the line in years.''
   Their notion of fiscal restraint once put his life in danger, he
said.
   When he traveled overseas to work on a possible drug connection
at a gambling casino, the government gave him only about $100 to
gamble with. The drug traffickers, meanwhile, were putting $50,000
in chips on the table. Dozier said he allayed their suspicions
somewhat by claiming he didn't gamble, but adds, ``There aren't too
many people like that who don't gamble.''
   The moral: ``If you want to swim around with a bunch of ducks,
you've got to look like a duck.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0024 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 1327EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-EnvironmentalData     04-01 0519</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Environmental Data,490</SECOND>
<HEAD>Independent Data Agency Won't Happen, EPA Chief Says</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MATT YANCEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The head of the Environmental Protection
Agency predicted Sunday the Senate will respond to a threatened
veto by President Bush and reject a House-passed effort to
establish a politically independent bureau for collecting and
analyzing environmental data.
   ``We do not want an independent agency that we have no control
over'' as part of a proposed Cabinet-level Department of the
Environment replacing the EPA, Administrator William K. Reilly said.
   ``We are confident the Senate will not have a provision of that
sort,'' the EPA chief said.
   President Bush in January endorsed a congressional effort
already afoot to elevate EPA to Cabinet status. However, the House,
in approving the bill last week, said it wanted an independent
Bureau of Environmental Statistics in the new department headed by
a civil servant who could be dismissed only for malfeasance.
   White House spokesman Marlin Fitzwater immediately raised the
threat of a veto, saying the House bill ``gives a degree of
independence to this unit of the agency which we feel is
unconstitutional.'' Fitzwater expressed confidence the
administration could sustain a veto in Congress.
   Reilly, appearing on NBC-TV's ``Meet the Press'' program, called
the proposal for an independent data agency a ``slight'' to the EPA
and said it suggests ``that we're not capable of developing quality
information and doing environmental statistical collection.''
   ``One inference I draw from the efforts by some Democrats in the
House to create such an entity is that they don't expect to be in
power very soon,'' he said.
   Rep. John Conyers, D-Mich., who as chairman of the House
Committee on Government Operations is the chief sponsor of the
independent data agency provision, said it would put a halt to
``conflicts of interest'' that had raised questions in the past
about EPA analyses.
   Conyers cited a case last year in which EPA scientists were
directed by the White House Office of Management and Budget to
change their testimony to Congress about global warming because it
did not fit with the administration's view.
   Under the House-passed bill, the Bureau of Environmental
Statistics would function much like the Bureau of Labor Statistics
does under the umbrella of the Labor Department.
   Its head would be named to a four-year term and would not be
subject to dismissal except for malfeasance. Just as with Bureau of
Labor Statistics, administration officials, including the secretary
of the department, would not have authority to review or alter
reports by the new environmental data bureau before they are
released.
   A similar bill elevating EPA to Cabinet status has been approved
by the Senate Governmental Affairs Committee but has not yet been
taken up by the full Senate. Both Bush and sponsors of the measure
had hoped to have it ready for his signature by April 22, the 20th
anniversary of the first Earth Day celebration.
   Neither version of the bill envisions a significant expansion of
EPA as a department rather than a regulatory agency. EPA now has a
staff of about 16,000 employees and budget of $5.5 billion.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0025 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 1328EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Lebanon     04-01 0624</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lebanon,0647</SECOND>
<HEAD>Thousands of Civilians Flee as Cease-Fire Begins</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By FAROUK NASSAR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BEIRUT, Lebanon (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Thousands of civilians fled Lebanon's
Christian enclave Sunday as a cease-fire ended two days of fierce
fighting between rival Christian forces that left 63 dead and 133
wounded.
   Police said an uneasy calm reigned over the major warfronts in
rain-drenched east Beirut and the fog-shrouded highlands of
Kesrouan province in the Christian hinterland northeast of the
capital.
   The truce was negotiated by a three-man Christian mediation
committee backed by the Vatican. It is the 15th cease-fire in two
months.
   A police spokesman said many villages have been nearly wiped out
by shellfire and large sections of several posh mountain resort
towns were gutted, ``yet neither side has gained a single inch of
territory.''
   The spokesman, who could not be named under standing
regulations, said the truce was ``allowing rescue workers to remove
bodies and civilians to flee. The truce seems to be holding, at
least momentarily.''
   The latest round of fighting broke out at dawn Friday, pitting
Gen. Michel Aoun's 19,000 army troops against Christian warlord
Samir Geagea's 6,000-strong Lebanese Forces militia.
   The two days of fighting raised the number of casualties to 839
dead and 2,289 wounded since Jan. 30, when Aoun moved against
Geagea to stamp out the main challenge to his authority in the
310-square-mile Christian enclave.
   The two sides battled with artillery, tanks and multi-barreled
rocket launchers.
   Despite pitched battles and house-to-house fighting, Aoun's army
failed to break through Lebanese Forces defenses in Kesrouan or
east Beirut's Ashrafiyeh and Karantina districts, leaving Geagea in
full control of two-thirds of the Christian enclave.
   Aoun and his troops remain in Metn province, with no airport or
harbor to resupply. Hostile Syrian troops ring all overland inlets
to his territory.
   ``The showdown remains inconclusive on the battleground, but
Geagea is rapidly emerging as the political victor,'' said a
long-time Lebanon analyst, who requested anonymity.
   Tens of thousands of residents emerged from basements and bomb
shelters at first light in east Beirut to examine the destruction
wreaked on their homes and businesses by the two days of fighting.
   Thousands hurriedly packed beds, mattresses and blankets into
taxis and fled to the Syrian-controlled western sector of the
divided capital. Others stockpiled food, water and powder milk,
fearing the cease-fire would not last.
   Police estimate that up to one-third of the enclave's 1 million
inhabitants have fled since Feb. 1.
   ``I couldn't risk staying. They're definitely reloading to start
all over again,'' said Maroun Bustani, a Christian pharmacist,
after he fled with his wife and two children into west Beirut.
   In a Sunday sermon, Maronite Patriarch Nasrallah Sfeir asked:
``Have we all been hit by triple blindness _ the blindness of the
eye, the blindness of the heart and the blindness of the
conscience?''
   ``How can we be blind to (the sight) of homeless families taking
shelter in forests?'' he said at the chapel in Bkirki, where
hundreds of families had taken refuge in the pine forest.
   Aoun and Geagea are both Maronites, a Catholic sect that has
dominated Lebaonon's political life since independence from France
in 1943.
   Geagea has backed the presidency of Elias Hrawi, a Maronite, who
was elected by parliament Nov. 24 with a mandate to enforce an Arab
league-brokered peace plan to resolve Lebanon's 15-year-old civil
war. The accord gives Moslems an equal share of power with
Christians.
   Hrawi fired Aoun as army commander and interim prime minister
but the general has held out in the presidential palace in a
Christian enclave east of Beirut, claiming Hrawi's election is
unconstitutional.
   Aoun also rejected the Arab League peace plan saying it did not
guarantee the total withdrawal of 40,000 Syrian troops from Lebanon.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0026 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 1346EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-RacialAttack     04-01 0539</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Racial Attack,0552</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bensonhurst Racial Attack Going to Trial</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RONALD POWERS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The alleged ringleader of a white mob charged in
the killing of a black teen-ager goes on trial Monday along with
the accused triggerman as prosecutors try to recover from a series
of setbacks in their case.
   Assistant Brooklyn District Attorney Bruce McIntyre, who had
been tipped to present opening arguments, abruptly quit as trial
strategies were being finalized last week, saying he resented being
a ``token'' black at the prosecution table.
   Prosecutors endured another blow three weeks ago when John
Vento, 21, an important witness in the slaying, backed out of a
deal and decided to face second-degree murder charges rather than
testify against his friends.
   Seven other young white men from Bensonhurst have been charged
in the Aug. 23 slaying of Yusuf Hawkins, a black 16-year-old who
was shot after he went with three friends into the largely Italian
neighborhood in south Brooklyn to look at a used car.
   
   Judge Thaddeus Owens ruled last week that alleged triggerman
Joseph Fama, 19, and alleged ringleader Keith Mondello, 20, would
be the first to stand trial, prosecutors said. Jury selection
begins Monday.
   Both men are charged with two counts of murder and face 25 years
to life in prison if convicted. Five of the others have been
charged with murder and other crimes, and the sixth with assault.
   Brooklyn District Attorney Charles J. Hynes says he is baffled
by McIntyre's resignation and regrets Vento's change of heart, but
insists he's confident he has a case he can win.
   Vento's unexpected defection led prosecutors to seek, and get, a
one-month delay in the start of the trials.
   On Monday, the judge plans to speed the proceedings by
impaneling two juries. The panels will sit side by side in the
courtroom, with one deciding the fate of Fama and the other
considering the case of Mondello.
   There may be as many as six trials, defense lawyers and
prosecutors say.
   The murder, labeled racial from the outset by police and
prosecutors, sparked a furor across the city. It is widely viewed
as the most serious racial incident in the city since a December
1986 attack in New York's Howard Beach neighborhood in which a
black man, chased by a gang of whites, ran onto a highway and was
struck and killed by car.
   The Bensonhurst killing apparently was ignited by a dispute
between Mondello and a former girlfriend, Gina Feliciano. As word
raced through the neighborhood that Miss Feliciano had invited a
group of black and Hispanic friends to her 18th birthday party,
Mondello allegedly recruited some of his friends to take on what
they saw as intruders on their turf.
   The gang of some 30 whites, many armed with baseball bats,
mistook Hawkins and his three teen-age friends, all of them black,
as the expected outsiders and set upon them.
   As the gang surrounded the four youths, Fama allegedly stepped
in with his gun and fired four shots, three of which struck Hawkins
and killed him.
   The mob scattered when the shots were fired and Hawkins'
companions _ who are expected to testify at the trials _ were not
hurt.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0027 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 1353EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Trump-TajMahal     04-01 0778</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Trump-Taj Mahal,0801</SECOND>
<HEAD>Trump's Billion-Dollar Casino Opens Monday</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By HENRY STERN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ATLANTIC CITY, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Donald Trump opens the world's
largest gambling hall Monday, and his heavily leveraged
billion-dollar Taj Mahal Casino Resort needs to rake $1 million a
day off the Boardwalk just to pay its debt.
   Its 11 competitors, meanwhile, worry and wonder whether the
42-story Taj Mahal's 3,000 slot machines, 12 restaurants and
$10,000-a-night suites will bring new customers to the Boardwalk or
steal away old business.
   Analysts estimate the Taj Mahal must bring in at least $1
million a day to pay expenses plus interest on $675 million in
bonds Trump took out to finish the casino he took over from Resorts
International in November 1988 after five years of sporadic
construction.
   The casino is opening at a time when Atlantic City's gaming
market has flattened and new competition for the betting dollar is
coming from ``theme'' casinos in Nevada and from new state
lotteries elsewhere.
   Trump, who owns Trump Plaza and Trump Castle casino-hotels, said
the Taj Mahal's 120,000-square-foot floor and the novelty of a
gambling hall named for the 16th century Indian mausoleum will let
him exceed the $1 million figure.
   ``The Taj Mahal will be beyond everything else,'' he said. ``The
three (casinos) occupy a similar niche. They're luxury properties
that cater to high rollers and everybody interested in a good
time.''
   Not everybody sees the Taj Mahal as a magnificent success beyond
its first months, when interest is high and the weather is warm.
   ``When the property first opens, my guess is it will do no
wrong,'' said Marvin B. Roffman, a former gaming analyst for Janney
Montgomery Scott whose published remarks about the Taj Mahal led to
his firing when Trump complained to the brokerage company.
   ``The big question mark is, is it sustainable in the winter
months?'' Roffman said.
   Roffman said he expects a Taj Mahal ``win,'' or gross revenues,
of $35 million to $40 million in its first month. The win does not
take expenses into account, and thus is not profit.
   The Mirage Hotel, helped by the Sugar Ray Leonard-Roberto Duran
fight, took in more than $40 million in its first month of
operation in Las Vegas. Caesars Hotel Casino set Atlantic City's
record with a win of $32.8 million last July.
   Last year's win leader for the year _ Trump Plaza _ took in
$305.7 million.
   Daniel Lee, a gaming analyst with First Boston, also predicted a
$35 million to $40 million win for the first month and expects that
pace to continue. He said he expects a $375 million win for the
year, exceeding $1 million a day, for the Taj Majal.
   ``Is it too leveraged? Probably not,'' Lee said. ``Do I think
he'll default? Certainly not.''
   State Division of Gaming Enforcement Director Anthony Parrillo
said the Taj Mahal has proven it will be financially sound for the
one-year licensing period.
   ``Atlantic City had been loaded with debt on these properties,''
Parrillo said. ``The same can be said for the Taj. That's not to
say it can't be profitable.''
   Casino president Walter J. Haybert said the 5,200-seat Mark
Etess Arena, named after one of two top Taj Mahal executives who
died in a October helicopter crash, will draw convention and event
business in lean months.
   Beyond the gold, green and blue minarets that festoon the casino
and give it that certain Taj Mahal flavor are the city's 11 other
casinos, worried about losing business after a year of only 2.6
percent growth.
   The Showboat Hotel Casino and Merv Griffin's Resorts Casino
Hotel, which are bookends to the Taj Mahal, are banking on their
new neighbor to bring customers to what has been the relatively
barren north end of the Boardwalk.
   Trump said the Taj Mahal might take away rivals' business in the
short run but would lead to long-term growth in a market that had
its first decline in tourist visits since the first casino opened
in 1978.
   Casino Association President Thomas Carver said the other
casinos feel the Taj Mahal could cause a ``tremendous spurt in the
market,'' but also approach the opening with ``a lot of
trepidation.''
   ``Everybody knows that the concentration of interest will be in
that general area,'' Carver said, referring to the northern end of
the Boardwalk. ``The specific gravity of the town may change.''
   The wild card in the game is Trump himself and his
name-in-the-news quality that accelerated with his recent marital
breakup.
   Trump admits the gossip accounts for many of the 1,500 media
credentials issued for the opening. ``It's a strange phenomena but
someday we'll figure it all out,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0028 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 1415EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Butterfat     04-01 0474</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Butterfat,440</SECOND>
<HEAD>Congress Weighing Lower Milk Subsidies for Excess Butter</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DIANE DUSTON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Americans' desire for low-fat food is posing a
new threat in Congress to dairy farmers whose surplus butter ends
up in government warehouses because consumers don't want it on
their table.
   Under consideration as part of the 1990 farm bill is a change in
the price support structure that would cut into the subsidies
received by farmers who produce more milkfat than the market will
bear.
   Introduced by Reps. Charles Stenholm, D-Texas, and Steve
Gunderson, R-Wis., the plan would penalize farmers who produce more
than their limit as part of a nationwide ceiling on milkfat
production.
   However, the bill also would raise the support price _ what the
government pays for 100 pounds of milk if the market price falls
below that amount _ from the current $10.10 per 100 pounds of milk
to $10.60.
   ``While we do that, we also get at the milkfat problem currently
plaguing the dairy industry,'' said Gunderson.
   Currently, price supports drop by 50 cents per 100 pounds when
government purchases for the year are estimated to exceed 5 billion
pounds. The Bush administration wants to continue that system
which, according its estimates, could lead to price supports
dropping to $8.60 by 1993.
   Gunderson's and Stenholm's bill would prevent the administration
from reducing the price support any lower than $10.10.
   The National Milk Producers Federation, which represents dairy
cooperatives, wants a support of $10.60 with no lower price
available. Rep. Harold Volkmer, D-Mo., is leading the support for
that position.
   The House Agriculture dairy subcommittee on dairy, which
Stenholm chairs and Gunderson vice chairs, has set aside Tuesday
for approving the language that would be the dairy title of the
1990 farm bill.
   The solution to the milkfat problem is contentious. Some
subcommittee members and the Bush administration both contend the
Stenholm-Gunderson plan is unworkable.
   Basically, the plan calls for a two-tiered price support system.
   If the government buys more than 7 billion pounds of milk
products that include 260 million pounds of milkfat and 600 million
pounds of powered milk and cheese, the system begins to operate.
   Farmers would get the higher support price for a certain
percentage of their milk and a sharply lower price for the
overproduced portion.
   Tom Theiding, an aide to Gunderson, said farmers could reduce
the amount of milkfat they produce by about one-tenth of 1 percent
simply by changing the feed cows eat. But he acknowledged that cows
have been bred to produce more fat and changing that to higher
protein production will take time.
   Under the Stenholm-Gunderson bill, farmers would be told to
annually reduce their milkfat production from the previous year,
Theilding said.
   ``We're trying to get an incentive out to the farmer that
says,`don't give us butter,''' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0029 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 1424EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People     04-01 0862</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People,0899</SECOND>
<HEAD>People in the News</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY44</HEAD>
<DATELINE>RIVERDALE, Novia Scotia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A tour bus carrying singer Willie
Nelson slammed into a car that crossed into its path on a
slush-covered highway Sunday morning, police said. No one in the
Nelson bus was injured but the driver of the car died.
   The Royal Canadian Mounted Police said Paul Leonard Burtch, 20,
of Lower Sackville, Novia Scotia, was killed when his car crossed
the center line of the Trans Canada Highway six miles east of Truro.
   Nelson and four others who were on the bus were not injured.
They were on their way to Newfoundland for concerts as part of an
eastern Canadian tour.
   Police said the bus was badly damaged but Nelson was able to
make other travel arrangements. They said their investigation was
continuing.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>BERKELEY, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The $15 program was airbrushed to erase
some laugh lines and gray hairs, but the 60,000 crowd reveled in
the real thing when Paul McCartney performed at Memorial Stadium.
   Fans snatched up $300 worth of programs in less than three
minutes in a buying frenzy ``straight out of `Jaws,''' said
salesman Eli Glick. The program featured photographs of the
47-year-old former Beatle that made him look at least 10 years
younger.
   But many fans at Saturday's concert were as gray-haired as their
idol.
   ``Fandom is for all ages,'' said Vivian Kiss, 40, who met
McCartney in 1983 after haunting the Oxford Street studio in London
where he recorded ``Give My Regards to Broad Street.''
   For Jim Juanis, 36, the concert had a different significance. He
was 13 years old when the Beatles played Shea Stadium in New York,
and his mother wouldn't let him attend.
   ``She said I was too young,'' Juanis said, adding: ``Paul
McCartney crosses all age barriers. You can compare his music to
Gershwin or Beethoven. He is a musician for all time.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Fans snapped up 2,500 tickets to Madonna
concerts in the first minute of sales and 60,000 tickets in just
over one hour, a ticket agency said.
   ``She's a sensational performer and her popularity is huge,''
said Fred Rosen, chief executive officer of Ticketmaster, the
nation's largest computerized ticket outlet.
   The sultry pop idol was to perform two concerts May 11 and 12 at
the Los Angeles Sports Arena. When those sold out Saturday, two
more shows were added for May 13 and 15 and they also sold out,
said publicist Larry Solters. Tickets for a fifth date, May 16,
will go on sale Wednesday.
   In all, half a million tickets went on sale nationwide for
Madonna concerts in New York, New England, Philadelphia, Chicago
and Houston.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>PAWLEYS ISLAND, S.C. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Publicity grabbing promoters of a
crawfish festival have mailed packages containing live crustaceans
to journalists and celebrities, including David Letterman and
Arsenio Hall.
   Ten 5-pound packages worth about $400 were mailed out last week
to help publicize the annual Pawleys Island Crawfish Festival on
April 27-28, said promoter Cal Harrelson.
   Other mailing-list fortunates included weathermen Willard Scott
of the NBC ``Today'' show, Spencer Christian of ABC's ``Good
Morning America,'' and syndicated columnist Lewis Grizzard.
   Directions on how to cook the crawfish and ``how to pinch the
tails and suck the head'' were enclosed, Harrelson said Friday.
   The boxes contained packets of spices, a warning label advising
against consumption of dead crawfish, and a plea of caution when
placing them in boiling water ``because they tend to jump around a
bit,'' he said.
   About 30,000 people attended last year's feast and Harrelson
said he hopes to break the 50,000 mark this year.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Prince Philip, Queen Elizabeth II's husband,
attended a gala benefit performance of Andrew Lloyd Webber's new
Broadway musical ``Aspects of Love'' and went backstage to greet
the cast.
   Proceeds from Saturday's performance at the Broadhurst Theater
will benefit three youth organizations. The prince visited as
patron and trustee of the Duke of Edinburgh's Award Scheme.
   The show opens April 8, but preview performances began two weeks
ago.
   The prince met Lloyd Webber and his wife, actress Sarah
Brightman, and members of the cast.
   The prince, who is also president of the Worldwide Fund for
Nature, said in a speech Friday at the United Nations that
population growth has created an environmental crisis that, in
unchecked, could be ``more devastating than any nuclear holocaust.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Entertainer Dolly Parton recently sold her
three-bedroom home in the Hollywood Hills, at close to the $2
million asking price, according to her real estate agent.
   Miss Parton also has a home in Tennessee, where she spends most
of her time, but she is likely to buy another house in Los Angeles
after she completes a 70-city concert tour with Kenny Rogers.
   Miss Parton bought the house, just off the Sunset Strip, about
four years ago, and has thoroughly remodeled the place, said agent
June Scott.
   ``It was a very personal house to enhance her relaxation, and
she liked it so much that at one point she nearly didn't sell it,''
Ms. Scott said.
   The buyers were described only as ``a local couple.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0030 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 1423EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-RomanianAnti-Semitism     04-01 0368</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romanian Anti-Semitism,340</SECOND>
<HEAD>Romanian Rabbi Says Anti-Semitism on Rise Following Ceausescu Fall</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RUTH SINAI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The firing squad that executed Romanian
dictator Nicolae Ceausescu last December killed official
anti-Semitism in that nation, only to allow a more dangerous form
to surface, the country's chief rabbi says.
   ``Before, the anti-Semitism was from above. Now, it's from
below,'' Rabbi Moses Rosen said. Rosen was in Washington to ask for
help in combating the anti-Semitism finding new expression among
Romanians since the revolution that overthrew Ceausescu.
   Rosen, the leader of Romania's Jewish community for the last 42
years, met with an old friend _ Deputy Secretary of State Lawrence
Eagleburger. Eagleburger in 1984 interceded on the elderly cleric's
behalf when Ceausescu was about to arrest him.
   Rosen said he described to Eagleburger the resurgence of the
fascist Iron Guard organization, which conducted pogroms against
Romania's Jews in 1941.
   Speaking in an interview, Rosen said young disciples of the
organization have been coming back to Romania from exile in the
United States, Canada and other countries. In Canada, he said, some
of the group members received paramilitary training.
   There were 400,000 Jews left in Romania after World War II,
about half the pre-war population. Now only 20,000 remain, most of
them over 60.
   Rosen said he had received threats on his life in letters mailed
to his home in Bucharest, as have other Romanian Jews. A synagogue
was destroyed recently in a town near the border with Hungary, he
said.
   Rosen said that while he had been reassured by the government
that it would punish those responsible for anti-Semitic acts, he
was not sure how effective the authorities could be.
   ``There is a power vacuum, a breakdown of law and order,'' he
said. This was evident in an outbreak of vicious street violence
earlier this month between ethnic Hungarians and Romanians in the
province of Transylvania.
   Echoing a scathing editorial Rosen wrote recently in one of his
country's major newspapers, the rabbi said of the Jews' enemies:
   ``What do they want from us? What harm does it cause if we wait
for our graves to be here, next to those of our parents and
forefathers?''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0031 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 1428EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r e AM-Opera     04-01 0548</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Opera,0558</SECOND>
<HEAD>Season Premiere of First Part of Wagner's Ring Cycle</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MIKE SILVERMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The curse that hangs over Wagner's magic golden
ring and brings misfortune to his characters seemed to extend to
the production as well at the Metropolitan Opera's first
performance of ``Das Rheingold'' this season.
   At a crucial moment in the final scene on Saturday night, the
greedy giant Fafner reaches to snatch the ring from a pile of
treasure. Instead, it fell to the stage and rolled away from him,
coming to rest perilously close to the orchestra pit.
   There it remained for the rest of the opera, symbolic of how
this production, for all its musical splendor, remains hampered by
stage effects that sometimes seem amateurish or misguided.
   The Met wanted a traditional, literal-minded `Ring Cycle,'' free
from the psychological and political interpretations fashionable in
Europe in recent years. That's OK, but it puts a tremendous burden
on the sets and projections by Guenther Schneider-Siemssen and the
lighting by Gil Wechsler to seem truly magical where Wagner called
for magic.
   In Scene Three of ``Rheingold,'' for example, the vicious dwarf
Alberich is supposed to change into a serpent, then a toad, by
means of a helmet fashioned out of the gold he has stolen from the
Rhinemaidens. Surely in an age of stage wizardry that has brought
us ``Phantom of the Opera,'' his transformation could be managed
more convincingly than to have him visibly sneak off stage behind a
cloud of smoke each time.
   The serpent, by the way, has a new wrinkle this season _ he
emits showers of sparks that make him livelier, if not particularly
scary. We'll see if there has been any similar tinkering with the
dragon that figures in the third opera of the cycle, ``Siegfried.''
Up to now, he has looked rather disgusting but not realistic enough
to be frightening.
   Musically, the performance, with a mostly familiar cast, was
just about all one could hope for.
   James Morris' Wotan remains a pillar of vocal strength, and
Ekkehard Wlaschiha's Alberich was a good match for him. Siegfried
Jerusalem repeated his wonderfully slimy interpretation of Loge,
the god of fire, but he sounded more raspy than mellifluous in his
upper register. That doesn't matter much for Loge, but it makes one
wonder how he'll cope with the heroic demands of the young
Siegfried, a part he'll sing for the first time at the Met in a
couple of weeks.
   Helga Dernesch found Fricka, Wotan's nagging wife, a congenial
role for her waning vocal resources, since it requires no high
notes. Mari-Anne Haggaender was lovely as her sister, Freia, and
Alan Held made a good impression as the god Froh. Kaaren Erickson,
Diane Kesling and Meredith Parsons were an unusually vivid trio of
Rhinemaidens, and Matti Salminen and Jan-Hendrik Rootering made a
formidable pair of giants.
   The Met orchestra, conducted by James Levine, has polished its
playing of this work brilliantly over the last three seasons.
   The performance was recorded by television cameras for broadcast
as part of the complete ``Ring Cycle'' on four consecutive nights
beginning June 18 over the Public Broadcasting Service.
   The next installment, ``Die Walkuere,'' will be broadcast over
the Texaco radio network on Saturday afternoon, April 7.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0032 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 1439EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-HistoricDrive-In     04-01 0487</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Historic Drive-In,0505</SECOND>
<HEAD>66-year-Old Drive-In Serves Up Slice of History</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SPRINGFIELD, Ill. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Decades before McDonald's flaunted its
golden arches, a roadside diner that looked like a beached tugboat
lured customers with old-fashioned root beer and a new-fangled
idea: a drive-up window.
   Clarence Donley boasts his Maid-Rite Sandwich Shop has ``the
world's first and oldest drive-up window,'' although experts on
commercial architecture say that claim would be hard to prove.
   Still, the 66-year-old building is listed on the National
Register of Historic Places with such prestigious Springfield
monuments as Lincoln's Tomb, the Statehouse and the Executive
Mansion.
   ``In terms of fast-food chains, it is one of the oldest existing
restaurants in the country,'' said Michael B. Jackson, an architect
with the Illinois Historic Preservation Agency.
   Drive-up restaurants like Maid-Rite, antecedents of today's
major fast-food chains, began popping up across the country in the
early 1920s.
   The Springfield building opened in 1924, Donley said. The shop
became part of the Maid-Rite chain, whose claim to fame is a
sandwich of crumbled, steamed ground beef and onions, when the
chain was founded a couple of years later.
   Today, about 100 Maid-Rites are scattered across the Midwest,
but the Springfield one is the only one still operating out of its
original building.
   The original red and white, wood-framed structure was narrow and
shaped like a tugboat. It had three stools at its counter and room
for, at most, 13 skinny customers in wood-benched booths.
   Donley bought the shop 19 years ago and in 1985 expanded the
store to almost three times its original size.
   ``It hasn't lost its historical significance because of the
addition,'' Jackson said. ``I think they did a good job of
preserving the original form of the building.''
   Jackson, who is also a spokesman for the Washington, D.C.-based
Society for Commercial Archeology, said the claim that the
Maid-Rite drive-up window is the oldest is ``not unreasonable,''
but would be difficult to substantiate.
   He said the organization's newsletter may carry a notice asking
if anyone knows of an older drive-up window.
   Donley prides himself on not giving in to the whims of the
fast-food culture. He still serves the same basic menu of Maid-Rite
loose-meat hamburgers, french fries and root beer in a frosty mug.
   That menu has brought Maid-Rite and Donley an almost cult-like
following.
   ``They come from all over, California, Florida,'' he said.
``They'll come back and ask me to make up a quart of the Maid-Rite
meat so they can freeze it and take it home with them.''
   Melvin Boyd, 68, and his wife, Bonita, 63, said they had been
coming to Maid-Rite for almost 40 years. Their 35-year-old son,
Les, said he eats there at least once a week.
   Mrs. Boyd said the shop's faithful crowd of lunch-time regulars
has nothing to do with its historic architecture. ``If this place
is a landmark, it's because it makes such great hamburgers,'' she
said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0033 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 1451EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brites     04-01 0593</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brites,0612</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bright and Brief</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   April Fools' Day pranksters changed the famed
``Hollywood'' sign to Hallywood _ as in Ha Ha Ha _ but police had
the last laugh and put the sign to rights before the morning mists
lifted Sunday.
   Police officer K. Moore said someone used a camouflage parachute
``and twisted it around the first `O' so that it sort of looked
like an `A.''
   He said officers took the parachute down at about 7:30 a.m. An
early fog, combined with the groggy first morning of
daylight-saving time, kept most residents from seeing the change.
   ``I think it was kids, playing a joke on April Fools' Day, said
police Sgt. Robert Plassmeyer.
   The original sign, replaced in 1978 by a steel replica, once
read ``Hollywoodland.'' It was erected on Mount Lee in 1923 to
advertise a real estate development.
   Since losing the ``land,'' it has been altered several times: To
``Hollyweed'' by advocates of marijuana legalization; ``Ollywood,''
a cover-up reference to Oliver North and the Iran-Contra affair;
``Holywood'' during a Los Angeles visit of Pope John Paul II; and
``Caltech'' by students from the California Institute of Technology
in Pasadena.
   The Hollywood Chamber of Commerce, custodian of the sign, has
expressed concern in the past over pranksters scaling a chain-link
fence and clambering over the sign's 55-foot-high letters.
   The chamber will alter the sign temporarily for a price. Fox
Broadcasting Co. paid a reported $27,000 to add lights and the word
``Fox'' to make the sign read ``Fox Hollywood'' for one week in
1987.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   You say you're stressed out, fed up and just want
to scream? You say you're stuck on that gerbil wheel of life and
don't know how to get off? It may be time to join the Lighten Up
Club.
   For $5 you can join the Boston-based club and get a ``Bold
Card'' (which reads ``we're all No. 1 and we never expire,'') five
spare ``cents of humor,'' the club logo button (nose, glasses and
fake arrow), a newsletter and support.
   The club, with more than 1,000 members in the United States and
abroad, was started by a workplace consultant two years ago on
April Fool's Day to help people reduce stress through humor.
   Kathy Rolfe, 44, formed the club after holding a succession of
jobs involving stress training, after observing legions of unhappy,
anxiety-ridden people made miserable by their jobs.
   ``I remind them work is not what it's all about,'' said Rolfe.
``I tell them they can have your body but they can't have your
mind. I try and give people back control of their happiness.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>RENTON, Wash. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A 10-year-old boy has won his battle to
keep the American flag flying.
   Shayne Wooten had been ordered by the new manager of his
apartment complex to take down a 3-by-5 flag that flew outside his
bedroom window. The flag, a gift from his grandfather, had been
there for a year.
   On Friday, the president of the Dallas company that owns the
Windsor complex said the manager misunderstood the rule banning
signs and banners and the prohibition wasn't meant to include the
American flag.
   Pat Holder, president of Lexford Properties, said Shayne can
keep the flag flying. ``My hat's off to him,'' said Holder, an
ex-Marine who said he flies the American flag outside his own
office.
   Shayne's mother, Sharon Curry, said her son called the commander
of a local Veterans of Foreign Wars post for help. He encouraged
Shayne to refuse to take down the flag.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0034 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 1452EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SouthAfrica     04-01 0652</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-South Africa,0668</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mandela Offers to Meet With de Klerk; Indicates Division in ANC</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto PMB1</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MOTHERWELL, South Africa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Nelson Mandela on Sunday offered
to meet with President F.W. de Klerk to discuss how to end
violence, but said police conduct will determine when the African
National Congress decides to talk with the government.
   Mandela indicated to reporters that he is having differences
with fellow leaders within his anti-apartheid organization, though
he refused to discuss it publicly.
   Authorities said eight more people died in the past 24 hours
during black factional fighting and clashes between protesters and
police in Natal province.
   Addressing an estimated 300,000 people in this southern black
township outside Port Elizabeth, the acting leader of the ANC
appealed to whites to condemn police shootings of black
demonstrators.
   ``Whites here have become used to police shootings of black
demonstrators,'' Mandela said.
   He defended the ANC decision to cancel April 11 talks with the
government in protest of a clash last Monday between police and
protesters that killed more than 10 blacks and injured 400 in
Sebokeng, south of Johannesburg.
   ``Depending on the response of police,'' the ANC and the
government could work out a new date for formal talks, he said.
``The actions of the police against peaceful protest in various
parts of the country are in direct conflict with the public
positions being taken by the government.''
   Mandela was nearly crushed by black people surging forward to
touch him, as marshals fought to push him to the speaker's platform
on an open field in the township.
   De Klerk has said he is studying a report on the shootings in
Sebokeng but that in the meantime, talks should be held on avoiding
further violence. He said he had told Mandela: ``my door remained
open and he was welcome to meet with me.''
   At a news conference after the rally, Mandela said he is willing
to meet with de Klerk to discuss the violence but gave no specific
time. He indicated it would follow his visit Monday and Tuesday to
southeastern Natal province, where five years of black factional
fighting has intensified in the past week, causing scores of deaths
and hundreds of injuries.
   Mandela also said he hoped, during his two-day trip, to meet
with Mangosuthu Buthelezi, although he was persuaded by Natal ANC
officials to cancel a Monday a joint peace rally he had suggested
holding with the Zulu homeland leader.
   The ANC executive in Lusaka, Zambia announced Saturday it
canceled the meeting Mandela and an ANC delegation were to have
held with the president on April 11. The discussion was to have
focused on obstacles to negotiations about an end to white minority
rule.
   During Sunday's news conference, Mandela was questioned
repeatedly about two cancellations in two days of his initiatives.
He would not talk about specifics, or explain what the
cancellations meant to his position as deputy president of the ANC.
But he acknowledged that he had differences of opinions with other
ANC leaders.
   ``I do not intend discussing any differences among black
leaders,'' he said. ``But I prefer addressing the question to the
particular person involved and not through making use of the public
media for settling disputes.''
   Mandela, released from 27 years imprisonment on Feb. 11, is the
effective head of the ANC while President Oliver Tambo recovers in
Sweden from a stroke. But events of the past two days suggest he
may not have the freedom to pursue initiatives without approval of
younger, more militant ANC leaders.
   Differences of opinion and lack of coordination among the
internal and exile leaders have also increased since the
organization was legalized Feb. 2.
   Sometimes leaders deny events have occurred or insist that
statements haven't been made after journalists have witnessed and
reported them. Some officials issue statements on behalf of the
ANC, but refuse to identify themselves or say who has authorized
the statement.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0035 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 1500EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-RollsRide     04-01 0293</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Rolls Ride,0302</SECOND>
<HEAD>Man Uses Bogus Check To Buy Rolls-Royce</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PORTLAND, Ore. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A smooth-talking man in a cashmere coat
took an auto dealer for a $38,000 ride, using a bogus cashier's
check to buy a Rolls-Royce, authorities said.
   Dave Remer of Modern Classics Inc., said he had a ``gut feeling
something was amiss'' before he gave away the keys to the 1979 tan
Rolls-Royce Silver Wraith. But he gave them away anyhow.
   Police are seeking a man they identify as Frank Adrian Lewis,
34. He was picked up by police on a traffic violation shortly after
the car was ``sold'' but was released a few hours later.
   Two weeks ago, Remer said, a man believed to be Lewis showed up
and started tossing around his knowledge of Rolls-Royces. He looked
like a Rolls customer, wearing a cashmere topcoat and dark blue
suit. His voice had an air of educated authority.
   The deal was struck and Remer accepted a cashier's check that
apparently was cut for $10 and altered by high-quality photocopy
machines.
   Remer said he delivered the Rolls after Lewis told him his
wife's Ferrari was in the shop and friends couldn't give him a lift
to the dealership because they had lost the keys to their Mercedes.
   Police say Lewis was pulled over for a traffic violation about
an hour later and jailed when police learned he was driving with a
suspended license. Later that night, he was released and reclaimed
the Rolls.
   ``He's still got it, but he ain't that good,'' said fraud
detective Pat Kelley, who believes the car will be spotted sooner
or later.
   Police in Federal Way, Wash., are working a case where the
identical check number was used in a fraud there, Kelley said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0036 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 1514EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-NATO-Nuclear Bjt   04-01 0819</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-NATO-Nuclear, Bjt,790</SECOND>
<HEAD>Lance Missile Problem for NATO</HEAD>
<HEAD>Ed: Final 4 grafs EMBARGOED for 6:30 p.m. EDT use</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SUSANNE M. SCHAFER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Military Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The United States is considering ``bold,
imaginative'' proposals to deal with controversial NATO plans for a
new short-range nuclear missile in Europe, a senior administration
official said.
   The idea of updating the Lance missile _ which would be based on
West German soil and used to halt a Soviet thrust through central
Europe _ has run into trouble in Congress.
   It also has encountered fierce public opposition in West Germany
in light of moves toward democracy in Poland and Hungary, and by
the prospects for German reunification.
   A NATO meeting last spring in Brussels nearly collapsed over the
issue, when U.S. and British officials pressed for the
modernization of the Lance but ran into stiff opposition from West
German and other alliance members.
   In the end, the alliance smoothed over the matter by agreeing to
postpone a decision on deploying the missile until 1992.
   But the surge of change in Europe _ and pressure in Congress for
slashing the U.S. military budget _ is forcing open the debate once
again.
   In his 1991 Pentagon budget, Defense Secretary Dick Cheney has
asked Congress for $112.2 million to develop a new short-range
missile as a replacement for the aging, ground-based Lance
currently deployed throughout Europe.
   Faced with the prospect of a balky Congress and another
intra-alliance showdown over the issue at the annual spring session
of NATO's Nuclear Planning Group, officials on both sides of the
Atlantic are working on alternative ideas, said the U.S. official,
who spoke Friday on condition of anonymity.
   The official declined to elaborate, nor would he answer directly
when asked whether U.S. officials were contemplating dropping the
idea of moving ahead with the Lance modernization.
   But he said a host of informal ideas are being studied. He
emphasized that no formal administration decisions have been made
on the missile issue.
   ``Cables are flying all around,'' the official said. ``We're
looking for bold, imaginative proposals to present at the NPG
(Nuclear Planning Group.)''
   The session is informally scheduled for next month.
   The official pointed out that it is an alliance matter that must
be dealt with within the framework of negotiations inside the NATO
partnership.
   ``We don't have anything hard and fast yet,'' the official said.
   ``But it's clear that the alliance isn't sitting on its hands,''
he added. ``We know that the world has changed.''
   In an interview earlier this month with the publication Defense
News, Gen. Colin Powell, the chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff,
said he had not discussed alternative Lance deployments, such as
basing unassembled missiles in Britain.
   The Lance issue opens a Pandora's box of questions, since it is
not the alliance's only short-range nuclear missile.
   Such missiles have not been included in any superpower arms
control negotiations, but the West Germans would like to see them
introduced into the process.
   Formally, the alliance has said it will not enter into such
talks until after the East-West conventional force reduction talks
are implemented.
   The alliance's military strategy is based on the concept of
``flexible response'' _ the idea that it must have a land-based
nuclear capability to respond to a Soviet assault.
   The removal of the intermediate-range nuclear missiles under the
INF U.S.-Soviet missile accord left the short-range nuclear weapons
as the major land-based system.
   There are 88 Lance missile launchers in Europe, each with a
range of less than 100 miles. The updated version of the weapon
would be able to reach targets up to 280 miles away.
   Most of the 88 launchers and their 700 warheads are based on
West German soil.
   But U.S. military officials have warned recently that despite
the changes that have swept the Warsaw Pact, they've seen little
reduction in its stockpile of tactical nuclear weapons.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>The following is EMBARGOED for use at 6:30 p.m. EDT</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   
   A panel of congressional leaders, scholars, former government
officials and retired military officers has suggested the
administration's $112.2 million request for the Lance program
``would be better spent elsewhere.''
   In a report sponsored by the Johns Hopkins Foreign Policy
Institute, the group said the U.S. nuclear guarantee and the
presence of a ``substantial number'' of U.S. troops in Europe will
continue to serve U.S. interests ``for years to come.''
   The study, put forward to a group of defense writers by Sen.
William Cohen, R-Maine, and former Defense Secretary Harold Brown,
said, however, that the ``mission, number and structure of
short-range nuclear forces should be reviewed prior to the opening
of talks on these weapons.
   ``In view of U.S. budgetary constraints and West Germany's firm
opposition to deploying new short-range, nuclear-armed missiles,
the group concludes that funds requested in the fiscal 1991 budget
for the Lance modernization program would be better spent
elsewhere,'' a statement by the group said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0037 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 1517EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-GridironDinner 1stLd-Writethru a0666 04-01 0767</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gridiron Dinner, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0666,690</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush Joins Washington Press Corps' Annual Satirical Romp</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: SUBS 16th graf pvs, bgng: The more, to CORRECT attendance
figure to more than 600, sted 1,000</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By CHRISTOPHER CONNELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Gridiron Club served up broccoli, satire
and song in the press corps' annual spring skewering of President
Bush and droves of the capital's mightiest politicos.
   It was, as Gridiron President David S. Broder of The Washington
Post put it at Saturday's skit, ``the night of the long
butter-knives.''
   The reporters-turned-song-and-dance-persons inflicted a few of
the cuts on themselves, singing:
   ``We're journalists of
   ``Seniority
   ``There aren't many hacks
   ``As important as we...''
   But mostly they aimed their banter and bile at figures who
marched across the world stage in the past 12 months, from the
president to Manuel Noriega to Mikhail Gorbachev.
   It was the 105th annual installment of the Gridiron dinner.
Every president since Benjamin Harrison in 1892 has attended at
least one.
   Barbara Bush didn't turn up in a henna-haired wig, as she did in
reality at last year's show, but the first lady did get to hear a
skit in which a Barbara Bush character sang:
   ``The man that I married can sometimes be
   ``A little too far to the right of me. ...
   ``If George spoke with your voice,
   ``His lips would read pro-choice --
   ``Like mine.''
   The more than 600 guests at the white-tie dinner found sprigs of
broccoli alongside the buffalo steaks on their plates _ a culinary
poke at the president's recent refusal to eat the leafy vegetable.
   If anyone missed the point, a journalist posing as a 7-foot
stalk of broccoli was led on stage by a chef shouting, ``Room
service for President Bush!''
   Bush, in an end-of-the-show turn on stage, poked fun at his own
gullibility in taking a phony call from someone pretending to be
the president of Iran.
   ``I never thought I'd hear from Elvis again,'' Bush said to
laughter from the audience.
   Bush also gave a vintage sample of the clipped, pronoun-less
Bushisms that comedians love to mimic.
   ``San Francisco earthquake. Not my fault,'' Bush said. ``San
Andreas fault.''
   The show also saluted East European democracy and skewered
Democrats' foibles from Congress to City Hall.
   Clarabelle Clown cavorted on stage and Howdy Doody (alias House
Majority Leader Richard Gephardt) sang:
   ``It's Richard Gephardt time,
   ``It's goody two-shoes time. ...
   ``If honesty won't fly,
   ``Then we will learn to lie!''
   The stage Democrats hired ``Roger Ailment,'' a parody of Bush
campaign consultant Roger Ailes, to teach them to ``play rough,
like Republicans do.''
   Pundits posing as Bill Bradley, Mario Cuomo, Al Gore and Jesse
Jackson sang:
   ``We won't run _ don't make us...
   ``We shan't run _ we're bound to fail.
   ``We'd rather wait and run against Danny Quayle.''
   To the strains of ``They All Laughed,'' former president Jimmy
Crter and Nicaraguan President-elect Violetta Chamorro did a duet
with the refrain, ``Peanut Man, we've got the last laugh now.''
   And on a local note in this capital where Mayor Marion Barry is
under indictment for cocaine possession, two actresses posing as
hizzoner's ex-companions Karen Johnson and Rasheeda Moore sang:
   ``Our boyfriend's back ...
   ``Hey, la, de, la, His Honor's back. ...
   ``Hey, you tried to put him down.
   ``Yah, but he still runs this town.''
   On the international front, the Manuel Noriega character sang:
   ``I'm a Yankqui Doodle Dandy,
   ``A vet'ran of the CIA,
   ``A covert nephew of our Uncle Sam.
   ``How can you treat me this way? ...
   ``Why'd you have to send your army,
   ``And those damn boom boxes?
   ``What happened to the good old times?''
   Later, in a reference to the recent opening of a McDonald's
fast-food restaurant in Moscow, a Gorbachev stand-in sang:
   ``You deserve a break today!
   ``Eat Beeg Mac and plastic tray!
   ``At MacGorby's!''
   A couple masquerading as Ronald and Nancy Reagan crooned ``Easy
Street'' about the ex-president's recent $2 million speaking gig in
Tokyo:
   ``Easy Street! Can't be beat.
   ``Lux-ur-ee is our song.''
   Initiated into the club of 60 leading Washington journalists
Saturday night were Thomas J. Brazaitis of The Plain Dealer of
Cleveland, Anne L. Groer of The Orlando Sentinel, Cragg Hines of
the Houston Chronicle, Frank Jackman of the Daily News of New York,
Charles J. Lewis of Hearst Newspapers, Kathy Lewis of The Houston
Post and Ronald J. Ostrow of the Los Angeles Times.
   AP Vice President Walter R. Mears was the music chairman of the
show, with Richard T. Cooper of the Los Angeles Times and Susan
Page of Newsday the skit producers.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0038 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 1523EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-EastGermany     04-01 0886</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-East Germany,0913</SECOND>
<HEAD>Modrow: East Germans Afraid of Being Sold Out During Unification</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARK FRITZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>EAST BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   East Germans are becoming restless with worry
that they will be plunged into poverty when their nation is unified
with West Germany, the country's outgoing Communist premier said in
an interview published Sunday.
   Hans Modrow, who stands to lose his job in the coming weeks when
a new government takes office, said West German Chancellor Helmut
Kohl is backing away from promises to East German voters that their
money would be worth the same as West German marks.
   Modrow said Kohl was able to influence the outcome of the East
German elections by promising prosperity to East German voters if
they elected candidates who favor the chancellor's plan for quick
unification.
   ``Inevitably a situation has therefore developed which
contradicts all that Chancellor Kohl repeatedly said during the
election campaign,'' Modrow was quoted as saying by the West German
Bild newspaper.
   Modrow told the paper that East Germans are ``becoming
increasingly upset'' that they will be short-changed by the
monetary merger. He said Kohl should bear responisibility for any
strikes or demonstrations.
   Some believe the debate over the conversion rate could affect
the outcome of West Germany's general election later this year and
determine how many more East Germans flee their country for the
West.
   East Germans reacted with alarm this weekend after the West
German central bank announced it was proposing an exchange rate of
two East German marks for one West German mark as part of a plan to
merge the nations' currencies.
   Following a meeting between the East German Christian Democrat
chairman, Lothar de Maiziere, and Social Democrat deputy chief,
Markus Merkel, both men said they rejected the proposed 2-1
monetary union rate.
   ``Our goal is a money exchange of 1-1,'' de Maiziere told
reporters. ``I see no clear or understandable reason to change that
position.''
   Merkel said the Social Democrats reject the 2-1 proposed rate as
``totally unacceptable.''
   Meanwhile, the head of East Germany's Labor Union Federation,
Helga Mausch, told the official news agency ADN that the
organization was urging its 8.6 million members ``to fight for
their rights and demonstrate next week,'' against the proposed
exchange rate.
   East Germans, who have amassed large savings because of a
shortage of consumer goods under the Communists, were hoping for a
1-1 conversion, based on election campaign speeches made by Kohl
and other conservatives.
   Kohl said Saturday he never promised an equal exchange of East
German marks for West German marks, but Modrow said Kohl did.
   ``He promised it again and again,'' Bild quoted Modrow as
saying. ``The voters clearly saw it that way. The outcome of the
election was as a result of those promises.''
   East Germans voting in their first free elections on March 18
overwhelmingly chose a Christian Democrat-led, conservative
alliance that Kohl helped organized.
   Kohl made regular trips to the East to campaign for the
coalition.
   The Christian Democrats continued to negotiate Sunday with the
second-place finisher in the election, the left-leaning Social
Democrats, on forming a coalition that would dominate East
Germany's new 400-member Parliament.
   Modrow leads the overhauled Communist Party that embraced a form
of democratic socialism after the old Stalinist regime was
overthrown during last year's mass demonstrations.
   The Communists finished a distant third in the elections. The
new Parliament is expected to convene for the first time this week.
   Under the exchange rate established by the former Communist
regime, three East German marks bought one West German mark. The
East German mark is non-convertible, however, and has virtually no
value in Western markets.
   Karl Otto Poehl, the chairman of West Germany's Bundesbank, said
Saturday the state bank's plan for a 2-1 conversion actually raises
the value of the East German mark. Small savings accounts of up to
2,000 marks ($1,175) still would be exchanged at a 1-1 rate, Poehl
said.
   Kohl's government, facing elections in December, is trying to
walk a fine line between living up to election promises to East
German voters without placing too great an economic burden on West
German voters.
   East Germany's collapsing economy and the nearly 500,000 East
Germans who fled to the West since January 1989, were main factors
in the revolt that ousted the old Communist regime.
   Some officials, including Ulf Fink of Kohl's Christian
Democratic Union, have predicted that anything less than a 1-1
conversion could cause a new exodus of East Germans to the West.
   ``Another exodus would be more costly than a general 1-1 rate
for all savings,'' Fink was quoted by the Neue Osnabreucker Zeitung
as saying.
   West German financial experts say it will cost hundreds of
billions of marks to improve obsolete industries and repair roads
and communications in East Germany.
   Much of that burden is expected to affect the wealthy West
German economy, possibly resulting in rising inflation, a decline
in the value of the powerful West mark and perhaps new taxes.
   Proponents of a 1-1 conversion say it is necessary to allow East
German workers and elderly people living off savings accounts to
maintain adequate living standards in a unified Germany.
   East Germans currently depend on heavy government subsidies for
housing, food and employment. The subsidies will be quickly phased
out in the new free-market economy when unification comes.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0039 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 1548EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-GreyhoundViolence-Chronology     04-01 0799</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Greyhound Violence-Chronology,0826</SECOND>
<HEAD>Greyhound Violence Reports</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Bus Driver Shot, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DALLAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are major incidents of violence recorded by
Greyhound Lines Inc. since the bus drivers strike began March 2,
according to company attorney Melanie Scofield and other reports.
   The company has reported at least 70 bomb threats, 29 shootings
and numerous other incidents of threat or vandalism, such as vacant
buses set on fire.
   The union denies a role in the violence and cites at least 60
violent incidents by replacement drivers against strikers. One
striker, Robert Waterhouse, was killed March 3 on a Redding,
Calif., picket line when he was crushed by a bus driven by a
replacement. But the driver was not charged.
   Here are the major attacks on buses listed by Greyhound:
   March 2 _ Two shots fired into Greyhound's main Chicago
terminal. No injuries.
   March 3 _ Driver reports hearing a loud noise like an explosion
about a mile northeast of Wytheville, Va. An inspection of the
vehicle reveals a bullet hole in the lower left corner of the
windshield. No injuries.
   March 3 _ Shot fired at bus as it leaves another bus station in
Chicago. Two people slightly injured by flying debris.
   March 3 _ A bus en route to Cleveland is fired on at a toll gate
in Indiana. The shot penetrates a radiator screen on the back of
the bus. No injuries.
   March 9 _ Three shots fired at a bus carrying 29 passengers from
Cleveland to Louisville, Ky., on Interstate 71 between Columbus,
Ohio, and Cincinnati. Passengers transfer to another bus and
continue on to Cincinnati.
   March 9 _ A driver en route from Phoenix to Los Angeles hears a
``pop'' and finds a bullet hole in the door of the bus. The driver
says a car in front of the bus begins flashing its lights moments
before the shooting. No injuries.
   March 11 _ Shot hits a bus traveling from Detroit to St.
Petersburg, Fla., about 12 miles south of Jacksonville, Fla.,
injuring eight people.
   March 12 _ A bus traveling from New York to Boston via Hartford,
Conn., is shot at as it travels on Interstate 84. A single bullet
penetrated the middle hatch of the baggage bin. No injuries.
   March 12 _ A Greyhound-owned Trailways bus parked in a storage
yard in Fresno, Calif., is set on fire with a road flare. No
injuries.
   March 13 _ A sniper opens fire on a moving Greyhound bus in
Chicago, hitting the door with one bullet and a front window with
another. No injuries. Passengers are transferred to another bus
bound for Memphis, Tenn.
   March 14 _ Two shots strike a window of a Greyhound bus carrying
48 passengers traveling outside Chattanooga, Tenn. No injuries.
   March 18 _ A bus was fired on in downtown Cleveland. No injuries.
   March 19 _ Glass shattered in front door of Tallahassee, Fla.,
terminal by pellet or BB.
   March 20 _ Two shots hit driver's front window, and one hits
passenger front window while bus with 50 passengers passes through
Roanoke, Va., en route to Christianburg terminal. No injuries.
   March 21 _ A single shot strikes the right passenger door of a
bus carrying 30 passengers in San Antonio. No injuries.
   March 21 _ A bus is pelted by rocks while traveling near Las
Vegas. An elderly passenger was slightly injured by flying glass.
   March 22 _ In St. Louis, Mo, three shots strike at the driver's
window of a bus carrying 19 passengers. No injuries.
   March 22 _ Four shots fired at bus carrying eight passengers in
Collinsville, Ill. Two hit driver's front window; two more hit left
side of bus. No injuries.
   March 22 _ Bus fired upon 15 miles east of Lake Charles, La. The
bullet penetrated a rear air filter. No passengers were aboard.
   March 23 _ A bus carrying 59 passengers in Cleveland is fired
upon with bow and arrow. No injuries.
   March 26 _ A shot was fired at a crowded Greyhound bus terminal
in Amarillo, Texas. No injuries.
   March 26 _ A bullet destroys the right-hand mirror of a bus
carrying 32 passengers near Orlando, Fla. No injuries.
   March 29 _ A bus carrying 26 passengers is fired upon near
Tulsa, Okla. No injuries.
   March 30 _ A bus driver arriving in Harrisburg, Pa., from
Pittsburgh, discovers a bullet had struck the bus near the baggage
compartment. No injuries.
   March 31 _ The driver of a bus traveling from Nashville, Tenn.,
to Louisville, Ky., is shot by a man in a passing pickup on a
highway near White House, Tenn. The driver is critically wounded.
No passengers are injured. The bus belongs to Southeastern
Trailways, an independent company, but operates on a Greyhound
route with Greyhound passengers under a pooling arrangement.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0040 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 1638EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>d a AM-BRF--PlaneCrash     04-01 0144</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Plane Crash,0148</SECOND>
<HEAD>Pilot Dies When Small Airplane Hits Broadcast Tower</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HIGHLAND, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A single-engine plane struck a 300-foot
broadcast tower atop a fog-bound mountain and crashed Sunday,
killing the pilot, state police said.
   The pilot was the only one aboard the Cessna, which crashed
shortly before noon on Illinois Mountain in the town of Highland,
about 50 miles north of New York City, according to state police
reports.
   The pilot's name was not released and plane's origin and
destination were unknown, state police said.
   Witnesses said the eastbound plane was about 40 feet above tree
level when it hit the tower owned by Five States Tower Co.
   The crash did not disrupt broadcasting, said Jerry Lademan of
WEOK in Poughkeepsie, one of several stations that use the tower.
The plane hit 130 feet up on the 300-foot tower, Lademan said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0041 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 1547EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-TaxProtest 1stLd-Writethru a0670 04-01 0852</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Tax Protest, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0670,0870</SECOND>
<HEAD>Thatcher, Kinnock Blame Extremists For Anti-Tax Protest That
Turned Into Riot</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 8 grafs to UPDATE with new scuffle, 86 citizens
hospitalized. Pickup 9th graf `Detective Chief...'; INSERTS graf
after 21st graf `The new...' to ADD earlier Glasgow protest. Pickup
22nd graf `Critics have...'; EDITS to trim.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto LON3</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By EDITH M. LEDERER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher and opposition
politicians on Sunday blamed extremist groups for turning a
carnival-like anti-tax protest in Trafalgar Square into one of
London's worst riots this century.
   On Sunday, about 100 protesters chanting ``No poll tax!'' and
``Can't pay, won't pay!'' clashed with police for a second day when
Home Secretary David Waddington toured the scene of Saturday's
riot. Four people were arrested.
   A protest by 40,000 people against a new local tax turned
violent Saturday when thousands of militants smashed windows, set
cars ablaze and battled police for several hours. Hundreds of
people were injured and hundreds were arrested.
   The so-called community charge, which took effect Sunday in
England and Wales, replaces a property tax with a levy on each
adult and increases the amount many pay by up to a third. Critics
say it's unfair because Britain's richest man, the Duke of
Westminster, pays the same rate as his gardener.
   Ms. Thatcher told reporters of her ``absolute horror'' at
Saturday's violence.
   ``People have a right to demonstrate peacefully. This was taken
over by some extreme groups who used violence with no consideration
for others or their property,'' she said near her country residence
in Chequers.
   Labor Party chief Neil Kinnock, whose party is 28 points ahead
of Mrs. Thatcher's Conservatives, said those who caused the
violence must be ``treated as criminals'' and punished.
   Scotland Yard launched a top-level investigation into the
six-hour street battle which sent 58 police and 86 civilians to the
hospital, injured 22 police horses and caused hundreds of thousands
of dollars of damage.
   Detective Chief Supt. Roy Ramm, leading the investigation, said
341 people had been arrested for offenses including arson, robbery,
serious assault, criminal damage and looting.
   The heart of London looked like a war zone after a battle on
Sunday.
   Clean-up crews cleared rubble and burned-out cars from the
streets and strollers wandered past boarded-up restaurants, pubs
and shops whose windows had been smashed. Many victims were among
Britain's most exclusive names: Liberty's, Burberrys, Mappin and
Webb, Dickens and Jones.
   In Trafalgar Square, a pall of black smoke was still rising from
construction cabins on the side of a seven-story building
undergoing renovation which had been set on fire by the protesters.
The South African Embassy across the street had smashed windows and
one window area blackened by a firebomb that missed setting the
building ablaze.
   ``We are supposed to be the violent ones, in the U.S.A.,'' said
tourist Harold Eaton of St. Louis, surveying the scene. ``I am
surprised that something like this could happen in what is such a
civilized place.''
   The Independent on Sunday newspaper called it the worst riot in
central London this century. Scotland Yard said it was one of the
worst but nobody had yet researched whether it was the worst.
   Chief Inspector Graham Bartlett, a 24-year police veteran who
was kicked in the eye and hit on the head when he went to rescue a
man who had been knocked out, said it was ``the most severe''
attack on police he had ever seen, worse than the 1981 Brixton riot
in south London.
   David Meynell, Scotland Yard's deputy assistant commissioner,
blamed the ``sustained and savage violence'' on about 3,500 people
who were among a crowd of 40,000 at a rally in Trafalgar Square.
Organizers put the crowd at 200,000.
   ``I thought yesterday you saw a patch of anarchy coming to
London,'' Meynell told a news conference. ``Certainly there were
some anarchists there and other extreme elements.''
   Meynell said the clashes began when some demonstrators heading
up Whitehall to Trafalgar Square stopped at the corner of Downing
Street, where Mrs. Thatcher has her official residence, and tried
to storm the barricaded entrance to the street.
   Of those injured, he said, only two police officers and two
civilians remained hospitalized Sunday.
   Steve Nally of the All-Britain Anti-Poll Tax Federation, which
organized the rally, said on Sky Television News that police
overreacted to provocation by a small number of demonstrators at
Downing Street.
   The new tax is part of Mrs. Thatcher's crusade to bury British
socialism by hitting at its last bastion _ local government. The
levy, which went into effect in Scotland a year ago, has been
greeted with frequent demonstrations, some violent.
   The ugly scenes in London overshadowed a huge, peaceful
demonstration Saturday in Glasgow, Scotland, where at least 20,000
people protested the tax.
   Critics have dubbed it the poll tax after a per-capita tax that
set off a peasants' revolt in 1381.
   Many councils _ Conservative as well as Labor _ have set charges
far higher than the government's estimate of $450, claiming the
government failed to consider that inflation would rise above 8
percent.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0042 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 1603EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Brazil     04-01 0608</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brazil,0627</SECOND>
<HEAD>Politicians Join Forces to Knock Down Anti-Inflation Plan</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TODD LEWAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>RIO DE JANEIRO, Brazil (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Brazilian political parties are
joining forces to knock down key provisions of President Fernando
Collor de Mello's drastic economic austerity plan, on which
Congress begins voting Monday.
   In the first serious hurdle to Collor's 2-week-old
administration, Congress will grapple with the 26 measures that
have paralyzed Brazil's economy and raised fears of social
instability. Lawmakers have two weeks to scrap or alter the plan.
   Collor, Brazil's first popularly elected leader since 1960,
decreed the country's fifth and most radical austerity package
March 16 to curb 4,853 percent annual inflation and jump start
Brazil's stagnant economy.
   But the plan _ which freezes savings accounts above $1,200 for
18 months, severely tightens the money supply, raises taxes and
utility rates, and slashes government spending _ has run into
mounting opposition.
   Brazil's Communist Party, the leftist Workers Party and the
center-left Democratic Labor Party have condemned the package. In
addition, five centrist parties holding a solid majority of about
400 votes in the 570-member Congress have demanded substantial
changes.
   Voting is expected Monday and Tuesday on four of the less
controversial measures.
   Voting on the heart of the plan is expected to be held later in
the week or early next week.
   Under pressure from labor unions, businessmen and voters, party
leaders have expressed support for increasing the limit of bank
withdrawals. The freeze has caused a brutal shortage of currency,
causing consumer demand to drop near zero and triggering massive
layoffs.
   Unions estimate that more than 200,000 Brazilians have lost
their jobs since the plan was implemented. Hardest hit were
construction and auto industry workers, including 19,000 laid off
in southern Parana state and 11,000 in Rio de Janeiro.
   ``We won't disfigure this plan, but there will be corrections,''
said Rep. Marco Maciel of the right-of-center Liberal Front Party.
   Collor, however, has said the plan is ``nonnegotiable'' and
warned he will veto any alterations by Congress.
   ``The president does not want a confrontation, but he won't
allow the plan to be watered down,'' said Rep. Renan Calheiros,
leader of Collor's tiny National Reconstruction Party, which holds
just 24 congressional seats.
   Collor can veto any Congressional amendments to his plan, but
Congress can overide his veto with a simple majority.
   Collor's aggressive posture had earned him public support and
unofficial backing from Congress, but Brazilians are grumbling
increasingly about layoffs and a delay in receiving March wages.
   Now, even Collor's allies in Congress are pondering whether or
not to hedge their bets and soften the package.
   ``We're receiving an average of 800 angry letters a day from
people asking the government to let them take their money out of
their savings acounts,'' said Rep. Ibsen Pinheiro of the Brazilian
Democratic Movement Party, which holds a House majority. ``It has
an effect on your vote.''
   Collor's wage policy is also under attack. This month, workers
received a 73-percent pay raise to cover for March's 84 percent
inflation, and they will not be reimbursed for cost-of-living
increases in the first two weeks of April.
   ``Nothing is unnegotiable,'' said Sen. Fernando Henrique
Cardoso, of the left-of-center Brazilian Social Democracy Party.
``The untouchable nature of the plan has been revoked.''
   But analysts fear any tinkering with the economic measures might
undermine Collor's credibility and hurl the economy into chaos.
   ``Collor has shot his bolts,'' wrote a political commentator,
Villas Boas Correa, in the Rio daily Jornal do Brasil. ``The
rejection of the package or major changes in it will be
unacceptable to Collor and lead to an institutional crisis of
massive proportions.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0043 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 1613EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Belgium-Extradition     04-01 0219</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Belgium-Extradition,0225</SECOND>
<HEAD>Belgium's Most Wanted Fugitive Extradited From Brazil</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BRUSSELS, Belgium (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Patrick Haemers, Belgium's most-wanted
fugitive, was extradited from Brazil on Sunday to face trial for
kidnapping a former prime minister and staging 12 holdups in which
four people were killed.
   Haemers, 37, was flown in a Belgian air force C-130 transport
plane that made a refueling stop in the Canary Islands.
   He was arrested in Rio de Janeiro with his wife, French-born
Denise Tyack Du Bon, 35, and Belgian Axel Zeyen, 34. They also were
extradited.
   The plane landed at an air force base in Koksijde, 75 miles west
of Brussels, and the three were driven to the nation's criminal
police headquarters in Brussels.
   Brazilian authorities kept Haemers' departure date a secret. As
a further precaution, guards spirited him out the back door of his
prison.
   Haemers escaped from a police van in 1987 in Brussels and eluded
authorities until he was caught in Rio last May. At the time of his
escape, he was charged with 12 holdups in which four people were
killed and four injured.
   He also is charged with kidnapping former Prime Minister Paul
Vanden Boeynants in Brussels in early 1989. The politician was
released unharmed a month after his family paid an undisclosed
ransom.
   No trial dates have been set.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0044 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 1613EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-US-Iraq 1stLd-Writethru a0683 04-01 0548</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-US-Iraq, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0683,520</SECOND>
<HEAD>Senators Urge U.S. Crackdown on Iraq</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: INSERTS 1 graf after 15th graf pvs, bgng: Specifically,
Cohen, to RESTORE Bingaman comment</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By JOAN MOWER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The United States should crack down on Iraq
for allegedly trying to circumvent American restrictions on nuclear
technology shipments and for using chemical weapons, three senators
said Sunday.
   ``I think ... there should be sound and fury and all we're
hearing now is the sounds of silence'' from the Bush
administration, said Sen. William Cohen, R-Maine, the ranking
Republican on the Senate Intelligence Committee.
   ``I think we ought to take action, and not simply allow it to be
(a) headline one day and then fade off into nothing the next,''
Cohen said on ABC-TV's ``This Week With David Brinkley'' program.
   ``I don't think we've done enough,'' Sen. John McCain, R-Ariz.,
said on CBS-TV's ``Face the Nation.''
   McCain said the Iraqis must be forewarned that the United States
``will exercise all options, including that of military, if
necessary, to prevent this enormous threat from continuing if they
acquire the nuclear weapons we think they are maybe three to four
years away from.''
   Iraq's president, Saddam Hussein, must be stopped on his
``messianic mission'' to become a dominant force in the Middle
East, McCain said.
   U.S. and British intelligence forces broke up an alleged Iraqi
smuggling ring in London last week. Officials claimed the Iraqis
were trying to obtain U.S.-made nuclear triggers for atomic
weapons. Five people were charged in an indictment that claimed an
Iraqi government agency was involved in the scheme.
   Iraq's ambassador to the United States, Mohamed Al-Mashat, said
his country does not have nuclear capability and denied it was
trying to build a nuclear bomb.
   McCain challenged the Iraqi's denial.
   ``The facts are the Iraqis have for over a decade been
attempting to acquire nuclear capability,'' he said. The Israelis
bombed a Iraqi nuclear facility in 1981.
   Moreover, McCain charged the Iraqis have failed to abide by the
nuclear non-proliferation treaty to which they are signatories.
   Both McCain and Cohen said the Iraqis' statements have to be
taken with a grain of salt in light of their denials they used
chemical weapons in the Iran-Iraq war and in efforts to put down
Kurdish nationalists.
   ``The Iraqis gassed some 5,000 Kurds back in 1988, thousands
more Iranians,'' Cohen said.
   Congress could do something about the situation, the senators
said.
   Specifically, Cohen cited a proposed law that would penalize
American companies doing business with Middle Eastern countries
working to acquire chemical weapons and nuclear capabilities.
   Sen. Jeff Bingaman, D-N.M., also appearing on the ABC program,
said ``I think we need to get tough, not just with those Middle
Eastern countries, but also with those that are supplying them.''
   McCain said Congress might be more willing now than in the past
to impose sanctions on such companies.
   ``I think that finally we're beginning to focus, hopefully with
the assistance of the Soviet Union, on the enormity and the
immensity of the challenges that this ... presents us with,'' he
said.
   Exposure of the smuggling ring prompted President Bush to
express his concern about the spread of nuclear weapons in the
Middle East. And the State Department registered its fears with the
Iraqi ambassador.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0045 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 1615EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Israel-Settlements     04-01 0654</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel-Settlements,0679</SECOND>
<HEAD>Shamir Plans Up to Five New Jewish Enclaves in Occupied Lands</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ALLYN FISHER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Caretaker Prime Minister Yitzhak Shamir has set
in motion plans to quickly start five more Jewish settlements in
the occupied territories, an aide said Sunday.
   The action is bound to fuel tensions with the United States,
whose leaders have renewed warnings that the settlements in the
occupied West Bank and Gaza Strip are an obstacle to peace.
   Shamir, head of the right-wing Likud bloc, acted as his
political rival, Labor Party leader Shimon Peres, sped up efforts
to form a new governing coalition without Likud.
   President Chaim Herzog asked Peres to put together a new
coalition after the Likud-Labor Cabinet led by Shamir collapsed
March 15 in a parliamentary vote of no confidence triggered by a
dispute over Middle East peacemaking.
   Yossi Ahimeir, a Shamir aide, said of the premier's plans for
settlements: ``We are talking about completing the picture of eight
settlements decided by our government, and there's no doubt that
sooner or later they will be established.''
   Israel radio said former Defense Minister Yitzhak Rabin of the
left-of-center Labor Party had postponed construction of five of
the settlements in response to American protests. The defense
minister has final say on when settlements will be built.
   Ahimeir noted that Shamir was now acting as defense minister, a
post he took over after Rabin's resignation from the Cabinet on
March 13 during the crisis that led to the government collapse.
   ``If there were artificial delays until now, they will be
removed,'' Ahimeir said in a telephone interview. Ahimeir said the
settlements were authorized by a Cabinet decision more than a year
ago.
   Labor legislator Avraham Burg said Shamir also wanted to
confiscate additional land for settlements and enlarge the present
Jewish enclaves around Hebron, where clashes have occurred between
settlers and Palestinians.
   Burg told The Associated Press that Shamir's plans were in line
with the Likud philosphy of not giving up any land in the occupied
territories, even in exchange for peace.
   ``Part of the plan is to kill the peace process,'' he said.
   Since capturing the West Bank and Gaza during the 1967 Middle
East War, Israel has built 143 settlements that are home to 75,000
Jews. About 1.7 million Palestinians live in the occupied lands.
   An additional 120,000 Israelis have been moved into
neighborhoods built in the Israeli-annexed sector of Jerusalem,
where 140,000 Palestinians live.
   Three settlements have been opened since Shamir was re-elected
premier in November 1988. These are Ofarim and Tsoref, started May
10 in the West Bank, and Kfar Darom, started about the same time in
Gaza.
   Five others, agreed on as a compromise between Shamir and Peres
when they formed their coalition government, have not been built,
and their names and sites have not been disclosed.
   Ahimeir confirmed a radio report that Shamir has named Michael
Dekel, a veteran Likud activist and former deputy defense minister,
to be in charge of building the new settlements.
   The radio said Dekel still needs permits from the military
government in the occupied teritories and the Justice Ministry,
which controls land purchases. In the past, some settlements have
been started by putting up fences and moving in mobile homes.
   Peres, meanwhile, was seeking to break a 60-60 deadlock with
Likud to win a majority coalition in the 120-member Parliament, by
trying to enlist defectors from Likud, Israeli media reported.
   By law Peres has about 10 more days to form a government and
then can ask Herzog for an extension. This could give Herzog an
opportunity to ask Shamir to form a government.
   Israeli newspapers noted that Rabin, Labor's No. 2 leader, could
also be assigned to form a government if Peres fails.
   Rabin is more popular with religious swing parties, largely
because of his tough policies aimed at putting down the
27-month-old Palestinian uprising in the occupied territories.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0046 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 1622EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Lithuania Bjt   04-01 0799</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lithuania, Bjt,0825</SECOND>
<HEAD>Soviet Armored Vehicles Unloaded From Trains, Move Through Vilnius</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos VIL1,2,4,5,6, MOSB1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ANN IMSE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>VILNIUS, U.S.S.R. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Dozens of newly arrived Soviet military
vehicles lumbered through Lithuania's capital Sunday, but defiant
republic leaders resisted the increased pressure to renounce their
declaration of independence.
   The Lithuanian parliament's Presidium met to consider its next
moves, and Deputy Prime Minister Kazimieras Motieka told reporters
the government ``remains ready to negotiate and discuss any
questions with the Soviet Union except that of independence.''
   The last Western correspondents were ousted from the Baltic
republic Sunday night on orders of the Soviet government, leading
some Lithuanians to express fears of an impending crackdown by the
Soviet military.
   Soviet President Mikhail S. Gorbachev urged the rebellious
republic in an appeal Saturday night to renounce its March 11
declaration of independence and enter into talks with the Kremlin
on the basis of the Soviet Constitution. He warned that a refusal
may result in ``grave consequences for all of us.''
   The Lithuanian parliament was scheduled to meet Monday morning
to forge a response.
   Lithuanian President Vytautas Landsbergis rejected Gorbachev's
appeal, saying the Soviet leader was demanding ``impossible
things.''
   ``It cannot be now demanded that we annul everything that we
bore in our hearts,'' he said in remarks carried Sunday by the
official Soviet news agency Tass.
   But Landsbergis said he would send negotiators to Moscow on
Monday to try to set up a meeting with Soviet officials.
   Western reporters counted almost 30 armored vehicles being
unloaded from trains that arrived near the Vilnius airport. Others
drove through the city, their treads slicing into the asphalt,
apparently on their way to a nearby base. Soldiers peered out of
the lookouts.
   The reinforcement of the Vilnius garrison came in broad daylight
when many residents were out for Sunday strolls to savor the spring
sunshine.
   Motieka complained that the Soviet army had refused to inform
the Lithuanian government about its activities.
   ``This situation must be changed,'' he said, according to
William Hough, an American lawyer who attended the news conference.
   An additional column of some 15 armored personnel carriers had
moved through Vilnius in the early morning hours, Lithuanian
officials said. A duty officer at the republic's interior ministry
said the vehicles rolled into a military base in central Vilnius
just three miles from the parliament building.
   Eduardas Potashinkas, an activist and Lithuanian TV editor, said
many concerned residents had called the television station and
Lithuanian radio to report troop movements overnight.
   Western journalists saw 30 to 40 armored personnel carriers, or
APCs, full support vehicles and soldiers being unloaded from a
train near the airport north of Vilnius at about noon Sunday.
   ``There was a big transport that came by train. There were a lot
of APCs, over 20 of them at least, and also trucks. It looked like
they were beginning to unload,'' a local photographer said on
condition of anonymity.
   Later Sunday, 28 APCs, eight trucks, two jeeps and a tanker
could still be seen at the station, while other vehicles were
driving through the city. Reporters estimated that at least 45
military vehicles had been brought to the city since midnight
Sunday.
   Gorbachev, in his first formal appeal since the Lithuanian
crisis began, said the republic's chosen path towards independence
was ``ruinous and will only lead to a dead end.''
   In an 18-line statement addressed to the Lithuanian Supreme
Soviet, Gorbachev charged Lithuanian leaders with taking steps that
``are openly challenging and insulting to the entire (Soviet)
Union.''
   ``I propose that the Lithuanian Supreme Soviet immediately annul
the illegal acts it has adopted,'' Gorbachev wrote in his appeal,
which was prominently played Sunday on the front pages of major
Soviet newspapers.
   Landsbergis, in separate comments broadcast on Lithuanian radio,
said Gorbachev's ``strongly worded appeal to the Lithuanian
parliament is extremely surprising'' and contained ``open threats
to the safety of the Lithuanian nation.''
   The Council of the Federation, a new group of leaders from the
Soviet republics formed to advise the president on nationalities
issues, directed Gorbachev on Friday to tell Lithuania that it must
rescind laws contradicting the Soviet Constitution before talks on
secession could begin.
   The constitution provides a republic with the right to secede
from the Soviet Union but offers no mechanism for secession.
   Gorbachev has promised Lithuania and other independence-minded
Soviet republics to establish such a mechanism, but the measure
presently before the Soviet legislature gives the Soviet government
final authority in such issues.
   On Friday, nearby Estonia pledged to join Lithuania in its drive
to regain independence lost when the three Baltic republics were
annexed by the Soviet Union in 1940 after Moscow occupied them
under terms of a secret Hitler-Stalin pact.
   The third Baltic republic, Latvia, is expected to pursue
independence next month.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0047 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 1647EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Bush-SlainTrooper     04-01 0203</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bush-Slain Trooper,180</SECOND>
<HEAD>President Visits Funeral Home to Pay Respects to Slain State
Trooper</HEAD>
<DATELINE>GLEN BURNIE, Md. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush and his wife, Barbara,
flew by helicopter here Sunday to pay their respects to the family
of a Maryland state trooper slain last week while on patrol.
   The Bushes went inside the Singleton Funeral Home to view the
body of Corp. Theodore D. Wolf, 40, a decorated, 16-year veteran of
the Maryland State Police force whose killer or killers have not
been apprehended.
   Bush met with the trooper's widow, Virginia, and his three sons,
Ted, 16, Greg, 14, and Nick, 12.
   Reporters were not allowed into the funeral home.
   The Bushes spent about 10 minutes inside before departing by
motorcade back to nearby Baltimore-Washington International
Airport, where his Marine One helicopter was waiting to return him
to the White House.
   Wolf was found slumped over the wheel of his patrol vehicle with
the lights flashing, reportedly after he had stopped an auto for
speeding on Interstate 95 north of Washington, D.C.
   A stolen car was later found six miles away, abandoned, with
Wolf's burned ticket book inside.
   Bush has called repeatedly for the death penalty for those who
kill police officers.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0048 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 1700EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Kashmir     04-01 0281</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Kashmir,0290</SECOND>
<HEAD>Four Militants Killed in Kashmir, Soldier Reported Slain</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Jagmohan as one name is correct.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>JAMMU, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Security forces shot and killed four Moslem
militants who ambushed them Sunday in a southern Kashmir town,
state officials said.
   In another attack, extremists reportedly shot to death a
paramilitary soldier.
   At least 24 militants were arrested in the Kashmir valley, where
Moslems are leading a growing campaign to secede from
Hindu-dominated India, the state officials said on condition of
anonymity.
   The latest killings raised to 243 the number of people killed in
the valley since Jan. 20, when state authorities began a crackdown
on the Moslem movement.
   Officials of Gov. Jagmohan's office in Jammu, the winter capital
of Jammu-Kashmir state in India's far north, said four militants
were shot and killed Sunday in the town of Anantnag after they
ambushed a police patrol.
   Two automatic rifles and some ammunition were found near their
bodies, the officials said.
   In the city of Srinagar, the center of the unrest, militants
shot and killed a paramilitary soldier in a crowded suburb, the
United News of India news agency said.
   The militant campaign in Kashmir originally began in 1947, when
the British-ruled subcontinent was split into India and mainly
Moslem Pakistan and the ruler of the former princely state of
Kashmir chose union with India.
   Kashmir is dominated by Moslems, however, and the militant
campaign has flared over the years. They originally sought union
with Pakistan, but they have recently been demanding independence
with neutrality.
   Moslems make up 64 percent of the state's 6 million people.
Nationwide, Moslems comprise 12 percent of India's 880 million
people, and Hindus make up 82 percent.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0049 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 1705EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-McLaughlinTrial     04-01 0813</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-McLaughlin Trial,0838</SECOND>
<HEAD>Police Officer's Bizarre Murder Trial Nears End</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By FRANK BAKER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>EXETER, N.H. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A police officer who was consumed with
hatred every time he looked out his window and saw his next-door
neighbor eventually shot him to death to settle a 13-year grudge,
prosecutors say.
   Defense lawyers in the trial of Robert McLaughlin contend that
the 18-year Hampton police veteran was insane _ a ``zombie'' _ two
years ago when he walked around to Robert Cushing's house and
opened up with two shotgun blasts when he answered the door.
   But prosecutors in the 4-week-old murder trial say McLaughlin,
49, is a cold-blooded killer who was angry at Cushing over an old
police-brutality charge. The case could go to the jury by the
middle of the week.
   Cushing, a 63-year-old former schoolteacher and prominent real
estate agent, was killed by two shotgun blasts after opening his
front door in Hampton the night of June 1, 1988. The slaying
shocked residents and for nearly three months, police had no solid
leads.
   Then, McLaughlin, an 18-year veteran Hampton police veteran,
turned himself in, saying he pulled the trigger. The surrender
stunned the community, particularly Cushing's family.
   ``When we were out in the back yard grieving, mourning the loss
of our father, he could see us out his windows,'' Robert Cushing
Jr. said at the time. ``It's sick to think the murderer was
watching us from his windows. It's like voyeurism on our grief.''
   But there was more stunning news to come.
   A year ago, McLaughlin's former wife, Susan Cook, was convicted
of being an accomplice to the murder and given a mandatory sentence
of life in prison without parole. She is appealing.
   The next month, during pretrial hearings, McLaughlin startled
onlookers by testifying that Cook actually had killed Cushing.
Later, shortly before his trial was to begin, McLaughlin's lawyers
produced letters written by Cook to McLaughlin from her jail cell.
In them, she said she killed Cushing.
   ``Babe, I pray they find you innocent; they've got to,'' said
one letter. ``You didn't kill Mr. Cushing, I did, and I know you
said you'd never tell and you'd protect me.''
   Shortly after the letters were made public, McLaughlin's lawyers
dropped out of the case without explanation and the trial was
delayed until new lawyers could be found.
   Cook continued to write to him for a time, signing her letters,
``All my love.'' Then, inexplicably, she filed for divorce and
obtained one earlier this year.
   McLaughlin's trial opened on March 5 in Rockingham County
Superior Court.
   Prosecutors claim that, with Cook's help, the defendant planned
and carried out the murder to settle a long-simmering grudge.
   ``The initial resentment grew into an ugly hatred,'' Assistant
Attorney General Michael Ramsdell said in opening arguments.
``Robert McLaughlin hated (Cushing) every time he looked out his
window and saw him working in his garden or sitting on his back
deck. He released that hatred on June 1, 1988.''
   The grudge, prosecutors say, began when McLaughlin and another
officer investigated a traffic accident outside Cushing's home in
which an elderly woman driver was cited for driving violations.
Cushing, who had been an onlooker, was arrested on a disorderly
conduct charge.
   The driver, who has since died, claimed she was arrested because
she had told Cushing she would testify on his behalf. At her trial,
she accused McLaughlin and another officer of brutality, saying
they ripped her raincoat while trying to pull her out of her car.
   A group of residents, led by Cushing's son, pushed to have both
officers fired on brutality charges, but both were eventually
cleared.
   Defense attorney Steven Shadallah told the jury that McLaughlin
``should not be held criminally responsible for what happened. The
killing was a product of delusional thinking in a man who was out
of touch with reality.''
   Shadallah argued that the night of the killing, McLaughlin,
under severe stress from his job, drank heavily, took a heavy dose
of tranquilizers and watched ``Apocalypse Now,'' a violent Vietnam
War movie _ a combination that induced him to commit the murder.
   He said Cook helped McLaughlin plan the slaying after he stated
his intention to kill his neighbor.
   ``She is the one who suggested wearing disguises ... using a
getaway car ... to serve as a lookout. She directed him to the
front door,'' he said. ``He didn't even know to run after the
killing; his wife had to tell him.
   ``This man was a zombie on June 1, 1988.''
   Hampton Police Chief Robert Mark, called as a defense witness
last week, remembered McLaughlin as a ``cop's cop.'' But Mark and
other witnesses said McLaughlin suffered from severe stress that
caused him to attempt suicide on one occasion.
   Shadallah said several traumatic experiences contributed to the
stress, including McLaughlin's accidental shooting of one of his
best friends at age 15.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0050 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 1705EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Nicaragua-Devaluation     04-01 0185</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Nicaragua-Devaluation,0192</SECOND>
<HEAD>Nicaragua Devalues Currency 6 Percent</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MANAGUA, Nicaragua (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Nicaragua devalued its currency by 6
percent and raised gasoline prices by 11.8 percent on Sunday, the
government announced.
   The new rate of exchange for government and official
transactions is 47,000 cordobas per dollar.
   The official exchange rate had been 44,170 cordobas per dollar
since Jan. 21, when the cordoba was last devalued. Sunday's
devaluation was the sixth this year.
   The black market rate, which is illegal but widely tolerated,
has reached 120,000 cordobas per dollar.
   Nicaragua began a tough anti-inflation program last year that
includes frequent devaluations to keep prices of exports low and
imports expensive.
   Gasoline prices increased from 77,400 cordobas to 86,500
cordobas a gallon, or the equivalent of $1.84 a gallon.
   On Feb. 25, Violeta Barrios de Chamorro defeated President
Daniel Ortega in Nicaragua's presidential elections. Chamorro's
opposition coalition trounced the Sandinistas, in large part
because of dissatisfaction with high inflation and unemployment.
   The government routinely raises gasoline prices along with
devaluations because the Central American country is dependent on
fuel imports and must pay scarce dollars for supplies.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0051 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 1710EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BuildingBlast 1stLd-Writethru a0680 04-01 0397</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Building Blast, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0680,0401</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hartford's First Skyscraper Comes Tumbling Down</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: INSERTS 1 graf after 9th graf pvs, `The tower...', to add
background on how parts of old building would be used. Picks up
10th graf pvs, `Preservationists have...'.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto HF2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By STEVE FEICA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HARTFORD, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In just a matter of seconds Sunday, the
city's first skyscraper disintegrated in a flash of flame, a loud
rumble and a billowing tidal wave of smoke and dust.
   The 11-story Hartford-Aetna Building, its metal skeletal innards
laced with explosive charges, crashed into a heap of twisted steel
girders and dusty concrete chunks at 7 a.m., to the applause of
hundreds of spectators.
   Despite the efforts of preservationists who fought to save the
building, the 78-year-old building was knocked down to make way for
a 45-story office tower.
   The demolition went off like clockwork. A man's voice boomed
``five seconds'' over a loudspeaker and precisely five seconds
later the blast, with a resonating rumble that shook the ground,
brought the building down.
   The building was brought down by implosion, in which explosives
are carefully spaced to ``pull'' a building in on itself to keep
debris from flying off the demolition site.
   Spectators, some crammed onto a pedestrian walkway, others
perched on cars or in side streets blocked off by police, oohed,
ahhed and applauded as the building fell in spewed a cloud of dust
that swept over the downtown area.
   The demolition ended the debate between the Society for Savings,
which plans to erect the new office tower, and preservationists who
had argued that the city's first skyscraper should be saved.
   The Hartford-Aetna, on the corner of Asylum and Main Streets,
was the sixth of 11 buildings razed to create the site for the
proposed tower.
   The tower was approved in August, but the city council
stipulated that architecturally significant materials from the
bottom two floors would be incorporated into the lower floors of
the new building.
   As proposed, the old materials would form the facade on the
first two stories of the building's fronts on Main and Asylum
streets.
   Preservationists have ridiculed the project. Michael Kerski,
executive director of the Greater Hartford Architecture
Conservancy, scoffed at the plan to preserve the old building's
first two floors.
   ``How do you blow something up and then piece it back
together?'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0052 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 1725EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Bush-Church 1stLd-Writethru a0662 04-01 0173</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bush-Church, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0662,170</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bushes Attend Communion Service</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: Adds graf with later activities</NOTE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush and his wife, Barbara, attended
a communion service Sunday at St. John's Church across Lafayette
Park from the White House.
   They were joined at the 8 a.m. Episcopal service by Bush's
sister, Nancy Ellis, and four dozen other worshippers.
   They heard a short sermon about John 11:18-44, the story of
Lazarus, by Susan Keller, a parish intern.
   Bush often attends services at St. John's when he is at the
White House on Sundays. He usually spends weekends at Camp David,
Md., where he attends a military chapel.
   The Bushes stayed home this weekend to attend Saturday night's
Gridiron Club dinner, an annual affair held by the Washington press
corps.
   The Bushes later Sunday attended a private party at the home of
journalist Charles Bartlett and flew by helicopter to a Glen
Burnie, Md., funeral home to pay their respects to the family of a
Maryland trooper slain while on patrol last Thursday.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0053 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 1736EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Colombia-Guerrillas     04-01 0416</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Colombia-Guerrillas,0430</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rebels Ambush Two Patrols, Kill Six Policemen</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TOM WELLS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOGOTA, Colombia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Leftist guerrillas ambushed a police
patrol in a northern town with a dynamite explosion, killing five
officers and wounding 11, a newspaper reported Sunday.
   In another attack northeast of the capital, El Tiempo newspaper
reported that one officer was killed and four were wounded.
   The newspaper said both attacks occurred Saturday. Officials
were not available Sunday to confirm them, but such reports by the
newspaper generally been reliable in the past.
   The newspaper said the National Liberation Army was responsible
for both attacks.
   In one, the insurgents exploded dynamite on a dirt road as a
police truck was passing, killing five policemen and wounding five,
El Tiempo said.
   The attack was near the town of Curumani in the state of Cesar,
300 miles north of the capital, Bogota.
   Six civilians on a bus following the police truck also were
wounded, the report said. A woman on the bus died of a heart attack
a few hours later, El Tiempo said.
   The newspaper said that in the second attack, the guerrillas
killed one policeman and wounded four others near the town of Tibu
in Norte de Santander state, 320 miles northeast of the capital.
   The National Liberation Army has become the most active and most
violent of five leftist guerrilla groups in Colombia. It is headed
by a former Catholic priest, Manuel Perez.
   Authorities say the group regularly attacks army and police
patrols. It has blown up the country's main oil pipeline dozens of
times in the last three years.
   The group has said it will never negotiate peace with the
government.
   However, another guerrilla group, the People's Liberation Army,
released the Venezuelan president's brother-in-law to show its
interest in reaching a settlement with the government, El Tiempo
quoted a governor as saying.
   Norberto Rodriguez was kidnapped by the guerrilla group eight
months ago near the Colombian city of Cucuta on the Venezuelan
border. He was released Friday.
   The group freed Rodriguez, a former Venezuelan counsel, to show
it is serious about seeking peace talks with the national
government of President Virgilio Barco, Gov. Eduardo Yassaf was
quoted by El Tiempo as saying.
   Yassaf, the governor of Norte de Santander, said the guerrillas
stated their interest in talks in a communique they sent him.
   Another guerrilla group, the April 19 Movement, surrendered its
weapons two months ago after nearly a year of peace talks with the
government.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0054 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 1817EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-BusDriverShot 1stLd-Writethru a0706 04-01 0860</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bus Driver Shot, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0706,0885</SECOND>
<HEAD>Driver Critically Injured in Attack on Bus on Greyhound Route</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 5 grafs to UPDATE with further description of
business relationship between Greyhound and Southeastern Trailways;
RECASTS lead. Pick up 5th graf pvs, `About 6,300...</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NS1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PHIL WEST</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NASHVILLE, Tenn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The driver of a Southeastern Trailways
bus taking a Greyhound route was shot and critically wounded,
prompting strike-plagued Greyhound on Sunday to rule out contract
talks until a week has passed without gunfire.
   ``It's an open-and-shut case of terrorism,'' said Fred G.
Currey, chairman and chief executive officer of strike-plagued
Greyhound Lines Inc. ``We will not negotiate with people who are
involved in terrorism.''
   Representatives of striking Greyhound drivers denied
responsibility, but Currey said he would refuse to reopen talks
until a week goes by without a shooting.
   The bus belonged to Southeastern Trailways, an independent
company, but operated on Greyhound routes with Greyhound passengers
under a pooling arrangement that existed before the strike, said
Greyhound spokesman George Gravley.
   Southeastern Trailways has been carrying more Greyhound
passengers than usual in recent weeks because of the strike, said
Greyhound's Nashville Division general manager, Larry M. Glasscock
Jr.
   About 6,300 Greyhound drivers nationwide went on strike March 2,
and the company has reported 29 shooting attacks on its buses, 70
bomb threats and more than 100 other incidents. A picket was killed
March 3 in Redding, Calif., when he was crushed as a bus driven by
a replacement driver was backing up. There were no charges filed in
that incident.
   A $100,000 reward that Greyhound offered last week for
information on strike-related violence will be offered in this
case, Gravley said.
   The driver, David E. Bryant, 58, of Cincinnati underwent six
hours of surgery Sunday at Vanderbilt University Medical Center.
None of the 46 passengers was injured in the attack late Saturday
on the bus heading from Nashville to Louisville, Ky.
   One of two men in a pickup truck that pulled up alongside the
bus opened fire with a .44-caliber or .45-caliber handgun on
Interstate 65 near White House, Tenn., about 30 miles north of
Nashville, authorities said.
   The bullet entered the bus through a front window and struck the
driver, a member of the union on strike against Greyhound, state
Trooper Randy Pack said.
   Hospital spokesman Wayne Wood said the driver was in critical
but stable condition.
   ``It's now a matter of just waiting and sort of seeing what
happens,'' Wood said. ``If everything goes perfectly his arm will
not need to be amputated. If there's a problem, unfortunately, that
still could happen.''
   Three of the passengers refused to board another bus for
Louisville and were returned to Nashville on vans.
   Greyhound officials told leaders of the striking Amalgamated
Transit Union on Thursday that Greyhound would return to the
bargaining table on Monday.
   But on Friday, the company announced that it was calling off the
meeting, citing continuing violence.
   ``They say they don't condone it,'' Currey told a news
conference, ``but yet they don't do anything to stop it.''
   The chairman flew from Dallas, where Greyhound is based, to
Nashville early Sunday, but has unable to visit the driver.
   Joe Semmes, an executive board member for the union's Local 1613
in Nashville, said the shooting could not have been the work of
union members because the driver is a union member.
   ``This shooting last night leads me to believe it is outside
work and not related to any of our unions whatsoever,'' he said.
``This Southeastern Trailways is a member of the same labor
organization we are.''
   Currey said striking drivers must have been involved in the
latest shooting, because until the strike began, Greyhound buses
hadn't been fired on in the three years he has controlled the
company.
   Semmes said Southeastern Trailways drivers were honoring picket
lines by refusing to drive buses into terminals in Nashville and
Knoxville. Instead, supervisors must do that job, he said.
   Semmes blamed the shootings on ``demented people.''
   ``They hear Mr. Currey say he won't negotiate while this
violence continues,'' he said. ``And they say `here's a good chance
I can stir up a lot of trouble.'''
   Currey said he wanted to meet with Gov. Ned McWherter to see
what measures can be taken to increase safety aboard Greyhound
buses. He said he had offered to place two-way radios in buses that
could be monitored by state troopers after shootings in Hamilton
County, but said the governor had shown no interest. Authorities in
at least two states, Florida and Ohio, installed radios aboard
buses after shootings there.
   Currey said that, in the meantime, off-duty police will be
riding Greyhound buses across Tennessee.
   An investor group that bought Greyhound in March 1987 purchased
Trailways Lines Inc. four months later and merged the two under the
Greyhound label, but the purchase did not affect 34 small, regional
bus companies around the country that also use the Trailways name.
   Greyhound spokeswoman Liz Hale said Southeastern Trailways was
not affected by the merger.
   By using non-striking and newly hired drivers, Greyhound
increased its routes Sunday to 54 percent of its pre-strike runs.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0055 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 1845EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Australia-Explosion 1stLd-Writethru   04-01 0229</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Australia-Explosion, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0648,0236</SECOND>
<HEAD>Gas Explosions Force Evacuation of Thousands in Sydney</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: UPDATES thruout with fire out, other details; no pickup.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>SYDNEY, Australia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Gas explosions ripped through a
cylinder plant in a suburb Sunday night, touching off a huge fire
and forcing officials to evacuate thousands of people from nearby
homes and close the international airport.
   Police Chief Superintendent Dennis Gillian said it was
``remarkable'' that no was killed or injured by the blasts.
   The fire burned for eight hours before firefighters extinguished
it just before dawn and allowed people to return to their homes.
   The blasts occurred about 8:45 p.m. at an unidentified gas
cylinder plant in St. Peters, a neighborhood about four miles south
of downtown Sydney.
   The flames, which shot hundreds of feet into the air, quickly
spread to a nearby asphalt factory, witnesses said. Homes within a
two-mile radius of the fire were evacuated, forcing several
thousand people to find other accomodations for the night.
   Intense heat from the explosions and fire melted power lines
near the site.
   Authorities evacuated Kingsford Smith International Airport,
about one mile away in the suburb of Botany, and closed plane
routes over Sydney.
   They said the airport would not be reopened until the blaze was
put out and authorities were sure that no further explosions were
likely.
   The cause of the fire was under investigation.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0056 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 1849EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-CBS-Musburger     04-01 0458</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-CBS-Musburger,0473</SECOND>
<HEAD>Brent Musburger Fired After CBS Contract Talks Break Down</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RICK WARNER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Sports Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DENVER (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Brent Musburger, the primary voice of CBS Sports
in the 1980s, was fired by the network Sunday after negotiations on
a new contract broke down.
   The network announced that the broadcast of Monday's college
basketball championship will be the last CBS assignment for
Musburger, who had been scheduled to cover major-league baseball
this summer.
   ``I was surprised, but it was a great run and I have a million
memories, and I leave behind a lot of good friends,'' Musburger
said in a statement read by Jimmy Tubbs, his personal assistant.
``At this time, I'm going to take an extended vacation, and I'll be
working again someday, somewhere.''
   Ted Shaker, executive producer of CBS Sports, said network
officials believed Musburger's workload was too heavy, but that the
broadcaster resisted attempts by CBS in contract talks to have him
cut down.
   ``It's a difficult decision,'' said CBS Sports President Neal H.
Pilson. ``It's never easy to deal with individuals with whom you
have personal or business relationships.''
   Musburger has been reported to earn between $1.6 million and $2
million per year from CBS. Pilson said he wouldn't describe the
negotiations as ``a squabble over money,'' but refused to say what
was in dispute.
   Pilson said negotiations for a new contract had been going on
for several months between the network and Todd Musburger, who
represents his brother. He said the Musburgers had asked for a
decision by Sunday.
   Both Musburgers were unavailable Sunday but Tubbs, Musburger's
assistant for 5{ years, said it had been apparent for several days
that talks weren't going well.
   ``It wasn't right out of the blue,'' Tubbs said. ``Negotiations
had been going on and they just broke off.''
   Broadcasting the National Collegiate Athletic Association
basketball game between Duke and the University of Nevada, Las
Vegas, will be the final CBS assignment for Musburger, the network
said in announcing the decision. Musburger's 5{-year contract was
to expire in July.
   Musburger is in his sixth season as lead play-by-play man for
the NCAA basketball tournament and has been host of ``The NFL
Today'' since 1975. He has anchored the Masters golf tournament,
the NBA finals, the Pan American Games and late-night coverage of
the U.S. Open tennis tournament.
   Musburger, who has been with CBS Sports since 1975, was
scheduled to become the main voice for CBS' baseball coverage,
which begins April 14. He also was in line to host the network's
coverage of the 1992 and 1994 Winter Olympics.
   Industry speculation on a possible baseball replacement for
Musburger centered on Al Michaels, said to be unhappy with his
status at ABC. Michaels was unavailable to comment Sunday.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0057 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 2017EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Israel-SovietJews     04-01 0362</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel-Soviet Jews,0372</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hungarian Airline Resumes Flights for Soviet Immigrants</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GWEN ACKERMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Three flights with Soviet Jews arrived from
Budapest on Sunday after the Hungarian state airline backed off its
refusal to fly the immigrants to Israel.
   However, Gad Ben Ari, the spokesman for the quasi-governmental
Jewish Agency that is responsible for immigrants, said the
situation was still confused for Jews wishing to come to Israel via
Budapest.
   Malev airline cut off ticket sales and flights to Soviet
emigrants last month because of threats from a pro-Iranian group
called the Islamic Jihad for the Liberation of Palestine. The group
threatened any airline that transported Soviet Jews to Israel.
   Palestinians and Arab governments have expressed fears that the
large number of Jewish newcomers would be settled in the
Israeli-occupied territories.
   Ben Ari said charter flights from the Soviet Union have not been
resumed. But he said immigrants with Malev tickets bought in the
Soviet Union for Tel Aviv can fly into Budapest and then continue
from there with the airline on regular flights.
   No Malev tickets are being sold to Soviet immigrants in Hungary,
however. Those who fly the Soviet airline Aeroflot to Budapest must
wait for room on one of the special daily flights to Tel Aviv on
Israel's El Al airline, the spokesman said.
   The flow of immigrants via Budapest resumed Friday when a few
Soviet Jews arrived at Ben-Gurion Airport near Tel Aviv after Malev
decided to honor their tickets bought in the Soviet Union, Ben Ari
said.
   On Sunday, a large group of Soviets arrived in Tel Aviv from
Budapest on two Malev fights and one by El Al Israel airlines,
officials at the airport said.
   Malev's decision to cut off flights worried Israeli officials,
since the Hungarian capital has been the exit route for Soviet Jews
coming to Israel.
   The number of Soviet Jewish immigrants has greatly increased
because of eased exit policies and fears of growing anti-Semitism
in the Soviet Union. The United States also has tightened its
immigration policies.
   Israeli officials have estimated that up to 750,000 Soviet Jews
may immigrate to Israel in the next few years.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0058 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 2017EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-SocialClubFire     04-01 0566</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Social Club Fire,0580</SECOND>
<HEAD>Report: City Owns At Least 52 Buildings Housing Clubs</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Realty Reality, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   At least 52 drinking and dancing clubs listed by
the city as ``nuisances'' are on city-owned properties, making
government the biggest landlord of the illegal establishments,
according to published reports.
   A crackdown began after 87 people died March 25 at the Happy
Land Social Club, an illegal social club in the Bronx, in an arson
fire that was the deadliest blaze in the United States since 1977.
   The bodies of 48 of the victims were flown Sunday from Kennedy
International Airport to Honduras aboard a DC-8 chartered by the
American Red Cross. In all, 79 of the victims were believed to be
Hondurans.
   ``Most of them went to the United States with high hopes, and
they came back dead. We are very sad,'' said Honduran President
Rafael Leonardo Callejas, who went to San Pedro Sulla to be with
dozens of grieving relatives.
   A grand jury on Friday indicted 36-year-old Cuban immigrant
Julio Gonzalez on charges of murder, arson, attempted murder and
assault. He is accused of starting the fire with gasoline after
being rejected by a former girlfriend who worked at the club.
   In the latest citywide social club sweep from Friday night to
early Sunday, Social Club Task Force members visited 356 clubs and
found 122 of them open, said police Sgt. Diane Kubler. They issued
54 vacate orders, 132 summonses and 193 notices of violation. One
person was arrested.
   Clubs such as the Wanda Social Club, which was slapped with a
vacate order Friday night, are a particular embarassment to the
city. The city is the landlord.
   The New York Times, citing police records, reported Sunday that
52 of the 1,255 clubs listed as ``nuisance'' establishments were in
properties owned by the city, including two in Housing Authority
projects. The records portray the city as the largest landlord of
such clubs.
   Buildings, finance and Department of Housing Preservation and
Development records indicated there were 46 to 66 social clubs in
city-owned buildings, department Commissioner Felice Michetti told
the Times.
   Department inspectors were surveying them, she said.
   City-owned residential buildings house as many as 46 illegal
clubs, the Daily News said Saturday, basing its report on a review
of Buildings Department and real estate records as well as reports
from inspections by city agencies.
   The News said the number could increase as city officials check
contradictory listings of illegal clubs.
   The city inherited the clubs along with vast numbers of tenants
and abandoned buildings, said Lee Jones, a spokesman for Mayor
David N. Dinkins.
   ``Is it embarrassing?'' Jones said. ``It's something we're going
to have to deal with.''
   In the event of death or injury in a fire or other calamity, the
city might be liable in lawsuits involving such establishments, the
Times said.
   Ms. Michetti said there were two grounds for city action. If the
tenant doesn't have a bona fide lease, ``we can bring an eviction
action,'' she said. Otherwise, the city can move for a vacate order
and ultimately padlock the property for violating fire and building
codes or selling alcohol without a state license.
   The city has moved against two other city-owned social club
tenants besides the Wanda, the Times said. Authorities last week
issued a vacate order for a club in Manhattan and closed another in
the Bronx.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0059 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 2021EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ColdFusion     04-01 0635</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Cold Fusion,0655</SECOND>
<HEAD>Cold Fusion Conference Concludes With Unanswered Questions</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PEG McENTEE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SALT LAKE CITY (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Cold fusion's early promise of a clean,
inexpensive energy source has faded as scientists struggle to
understand the complexities of a phenomenon that continues to elude
definition, researchers said.
   At the conclusion Saturday of the National Cold Fusion
Institute's first international conference, about 200 researchers
agreed only that a year of experimentation had produced some sort
of nuclear process.
   ``We're not in a position now to say it's practical,'' said
Charles Scott of Tennessee's Oak Ridge National Laboratory. ``It
doesn't mean we won't be able to some day, but we certainly can't
do it today.''
   Still, many scientists left the three-day conference convinced
the results of experiments substantiate claims made a year ago by
chemists B. Stanley Pons of the University of Utah and Martin
Fleischmann of England's University of Southampton.
   The two men's seeming breakthrough was questioned when
researchers in other laboratories had trouble duplicating their
results. While many scientists say they doubt cold fusion exists,
experiments continue around the world.
   ``I think we should have the courage to say, if we feel so, that
it is cold fusion,'' said physicist Guiliano Preparata of Italy's
University of Milan.
   ``It has been proven to the extent that these phenomena are
real, although they are not controllable ... the world is
well-advised to take it seriously,'' Preparata said.
   Pons said that while it was still too early to draw any
conclusions about a practical application, the work must go forward.
   ``You can't deny there's something here,'' he said. ``It may be
a huge thing, it may not, but you have to look at it.''
   Pons and Fleischmann announced in March 1989 that they had
produced a nuclear fusion reaction by immersing a palladium and
platinum electrode in deuterium oxide, or heavy water, then
charging the device with electricity.
   They said deuterium atoms fused, giving off energy in the form
of excess heat. At the time, it was suspected that sea water, which
contains deuterium, might provide an inexhaustible source of fuel
for the process.
   Nuclear fusion powers the stars. Traditionally scientists have
believed that fusion could occur only at extremely high
temperatures. Cool, small-scale fusion would provide a convenient,
limitless source of power and be one of the greatest scientific
discoveries of all time.
   The Utah Legislature appropriated $5 million to establish the
National Cold Fusion Institute last August and to pursue patents to
protect the state's commercial interests.
   However, the federal government has declined to fund the center
and only two private companies are known to have donated money.
   Institute Director Fritz G. Will said that while deuterium is a
vital part of the phenomenon, the possibility that the fusion
reaction occurs inside the palladium electrode could leave
prospects for a practical application ``dead in the water'' because
of the rare metal's cost.
   Even so, many scientists said, the results of experiments in the
United States, Japan, Italy, India and elsewhere pose intriguing
questions about the nature of the nuclear processes that seem to be
occurring.
   Many reported they'd observed excess heat, while others said
their experiments had produced nuclear ``signatures'' such as
tritium, neutrons and gamma rays.
   ``The big question is, what kind of fusion is going on?'' said
Edmund Storms of Los Alamos National Laboratory in New Mexico.
   Storms, who has detected tritium in his experiments, suggested
that more than one nuclear process might be taking place in the
electrodes.
   The conference was not without skeptics. But even Richard
Petrasso of the Massachusetts Institute of Technology in Cambridge,
who'd dismissed cold fusion as highly improbable, acknowledged that
results so far warrant further research.
   ``I'm still skeptical, but I think there are some exciting
things that need to be explained,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0060 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 2020EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Israel-Uprising     04-01 0502</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel-Uprising,0518</SECOND>
<HEAD>More Arabs Killed By Other Arabs Than by Israeli Soldiers</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ARIEH O'SULLIVAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   More Palestinians were killed by fellow Arabs
than by Israeli soldiers during the first three months of 1990, and
analysts said Sunday the figures reflect a decline in clashes with
the army.
   According to a report issued by the Israeli Information Center
for Human Rights in the Occupied Territories, 37 Palestinians died
in inter-Arab violence. It said 30 Palestinians were shot to death
by soldiers in confrontations in the 27-month-old uprising against
Israeli rule of the occupied West Bank and Gaza Strip.
   The report noted that both tallies were lower than for the final
three months of last year. During that period, army gunfire killed
64 Palestinians, and 43 were slain by fellow Arabs, said the
center, which used figures compiled by The Associated Press to
prepare its report.
   Palestinians killed by other Arabs were accused of dealing in
drugs or prostitution, or of being Israeli informants, which Moslem
fundamentalist groups consider crimes against the uprising.
   Arieh Shalev, a former commander of the Israeli-occupied West
Bank, said the lower figures this year were a result of the decline
in confrontations between soldiers and Palestinians during the
uprising, known as the intefadeh.
   ``The intefadeh is different,'' he said. ``There are no more
mass violent protests. Most of it is stone-throwing.''
   An army spokesman, who could not be identified under
regulations, said the reduction in the number of Palestinians
killed by army gunfire was due to stricter rules for opening fire
on Palestinian demonstrators.
   ``Things have changed from the beginning of the intefadeh when
there was not much experience with this kind of unrest,'' he added.
He said only officers or unit commanders are allowed to open fire _
and then only after firing warning shots.
   Sari Nusseibah, a leading Palestinian activist in Jerusalem,
said the army had learned killing Palestinians hurt its image.
   Nusseibah said the underground leadership in the occupied West
Bank and Gaza Strip had tried to curtail inter-Arab killings, and
that the execution of suspected collaborators was something
``extraneous'' to the uprising.
   Shalev, in his telephone interview, said in some cases
Palestinians were using the uprising to settle unrelated disputes.
   In the latest violence, a 24-year-old Palestinian prisoner was
strangled Sunday in the Ketziot prison in southern Israel by a
fellow inmate who accused him of collaborating with Israeli
authorities, Arab reporters said.
   His death raised to 202 the number of Palestinians slain by
other Arabs during the uprising. At least 670 have been killed by
Israelis, and 43 Israelis have also died.
   In the West Bank, Arab reports said Murshed Fawzi Abu Hafiza,
27, the village leader in Alar, was found shot to death in his car.
He had been attacked several times as a suspected collaborator.
   The reports said two friends who were with him told police he
was killed when his gun accidentally discharged. Only Palestinians
who work with Israel are allowed to have guns.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0061 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 2026EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-WeatherpageWeather 1stLd-Writethru a0725 04-01 0301</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Weatherpage Weather, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0725,0307</SECOND>
<HEAD>April Fool's Day Weather No Joke in Louisiana, Arkansas</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 4th graf, `In Louisiana ...,' with 3 grafs to UPDATE
with no injuries in Oak Grove, quote; picks up 5th graf,
`Thunderstorms south ...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Strong thunderstorms in parts of Louisiana and Arkansas took the
roof off a building, downed trees and power lines and left hail up
to 3 inches deep.
   A cold front advancing through the central United States brought
up to 4 inches of wet, heavy snow to eastern North Dakota, winds
gusting to 49 mph in Sioux Falls, S.D., and gusts to 46 mph in Ord,
Columbus and Kearney, Neb.
   Showers and thunderstorms fell over southern Arkansas, northern
Louisiana and northwestern Mississippi.
   In Oak Grove, La., thunderstorm winds ripped the roof off a
trucking company building, said West Carroll Parish Deputy Wayne
Yates.
   ``It rained real hard and the wind really came up. It made a
mess. We had some trees and sheds blown across the roads,'' Yates
said. No injuries were reported.
   Winds also downed trees and power lines north of Bastrop, La.
   Thunderstorms south of Magnolia, Ark., left the ground covered
with dime-size hail 2 to 3 inches deep.
   Thunderstorms also developed in the southern High Plains.
Scattered rain showers fell from eastern Wisconsin to central
Kentucky. Light rain and drizzle dampened the lower Great Lakes
region and the middle Atlantic Coast states, and fell across
south-central and southeastern Texas.
   Ahead of the cold front, sunny skies prevailed in Kansas and
Missouri. Skies were also mostly sunny in the West and the
Southeast.
   Heavier rainfall during the six hours ending at 1 p.m. EDT
included 1.54 inch at Cotulla, Texas.
   The low temperature for the Lower 48 states was 17 degrees in
Gunnison, Colo.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0062 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 2047EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-WhiteSupremacists     04-01 0259</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-White Supremacists,0265</SECOND>
<HEAD>Protesters Outnumber Members Three-To-One at Supremacist Meeting</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PEORIA, Ill. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A meeting of a fledgling white supremacist
group led by a Bradley University student turned into a shouting
match when about 30 protesters turned up at the public library to
ridicule the gathering.
   No violence was reported and no arrests were made at Saturday's
meeting by about 10 members of the American White Supremacist Party.
   Leader Matt Hale began reading a prepared script saying ``Blacks
are an unproductive race that is destroying America. They will be
stopped ...'' when the protesters interrupted him with laughter,
shouts and singing.
   A police officer stood at the back of the room through most of
the meeting, and intervened when the two groups began yelling at
each other.
   Hale ``has a right to say what he wants, as far as we're
concerned,'' said protester Ibaad Rahman, a Bradley University
senior. ``But he has no right to infringe on the rights of other
people. He has no right to outcast any race or religion.''
   Hale attempted to start a chapter of the white supremacist group
on the Bradley campus in February, but college officials prohibited
it. Hale has continued his efforts to form a party chapter off
campus.
   Hale, who says he supports race segregation, said he planned to
hold another meeting later this month.
   ``I wish more white people would come,'' Hale said. ``I am here
to speak to white people. I hope in the future our enemies, the
communists (referring to the protesters) desist from our meetings.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0063 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 2047EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Broadcasters     04-01 0266</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Broadcasters,0275</SECOND>
<HEAD>Cable Crackdown May Not Happen, Broadcasters Told</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT BYRD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ATLANTA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Despite consumer complaints about service and
rates from some cable TV companies, Congress is unlikely to
``re-regulate'' the industry, lawmakers told the nation's
broadcasters Sunday.
   Sen. Dennis DeConcini, D-Ariz., told the National Association of
Broadcasters convention that said a new ``must-carry'' rule,
forcing cable companies to carry local stations, could pass the
Congress.
   And Rep. Cardiss Collins, D-Ill., predicted, ``We are going to
have a little, small, re-regulation bill.''
   ``If you're looking for major re-regulation of cable, I don't
see it _ and technology will make that decision obsolete,'' said
Rep. Tom Tauke, R-Iowa, one of six Congressmen at the National
Association of Broadcasters convention.
   Tauke was referring to Direct Broadcasting Satellite _ proposed
high-power satellite services that can beam dozens of
customer-selected channels direct to home antennas no more than 18
inches across.
   ``High-power DBS is going to happen. It's inevitable,'' said Tom
Rogers, president of NBC Cable, a partner in the recently announced
``Sky Cable'' venture.
   Sky Cable hopes to launch its service with as many as 108
channels of programming available to some 4 million homes in 1993.
   Rogers said that while his service ``is technologically capable
of being competitive to cable, the marketing scheme we've focused
on is not intended to be directly competitive with cable.''
   The company is considering having at least some customers
ordering Sky Cable through their local conventional cable operator.
And, he said, for the cable industry, since DBS is inevitable,
``it's better to be a part of it.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0064 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 2049EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SriLanka-Tamil     04-01 0602</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Sri Lanka-Tamil,0622</SECOND>
<HEAD>Underground Leader in Sri Lanka Leaves Hiding</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DEXTER CRUEZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JAFFNA, Sri Lanka (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The country's top Tamil guerrilla
leader emerged Sunday from his jungle hideout, where he had spent
2{ years commanding a guerrilla battle against Indian soldiers.
   ``We have successfully foiled the Indian military
intervention,'' Velupillai Prabhakaran, 35, said at a military camp
run by the Liberation Tigers of Tamil Eelam, the group he heads.
   ``I do not think there is any more need for me to live an
underground life,'' he said.
   The last Indian soldiers left Sri Lanka a week ago after 30
months of a deadlocked jungle war against the Liberation Tigers.
   The withdrawal marked a turning point in relations between
ethnic Tamil militants and the government, which is dominated by
the country's Sinhalese majority.
   ``The Sinhalese people should realize the blunders of the past
and be prepared to resolve our problems on the basis of human
justice and righteousness,'' the burly guerrilla leader said in the
Tamil language.
   ``If, on the other hand, justice is denied to our Tamil people
and if oppression is unleashed ... we will not hesitate to resume
the armed struggle to uphold the freedom of our people.''
   Prabhakaran wore a green camouflage uniform and carried a
revolver in an open holster. At least 50 guerrillas wearing
bulletproof vests stood guard with automatic rifles. Snipers were
posted on the roof of the building where the news conference was
held.
   The Liberation Tigers and the government, which both wanted the
Indians out, reached a peace accord last summer. Now, the Tigers
have moved out of the jungles and swamps into areas vacated by the
Indians to share policing duties with the government forces they
once fought.
   But the Tigers have not given up their demand for independence,
and the government has not announced what the political future of
the Tamil-dominated north and east will be.
   ``There is peace and a cessation of hostilities between the Sri
Lankan armed forces and the Tamil Tiger fighters,'' Prabhakaran
said. ``But the fundamental problems of our people have not been
resolved. Once concrete actions are taken to remove the causes and
conditions that led to Tamil resistance, then the question ... will
be resolved forever.''
   The Tamil war for an independent nation began in 1983, touched
off by decades-old complaints of discrimination by the Sinhalese in
jobs, education and use of the Sinhalese language.
   Many militant groups, including Prabhakaran's, were based in the
southern Indian city of Madras, where they were bolstered by the
sympathies of India's 60 million Tamils.
   In July 1987, India brokered a peace accord between the Sri
Lankan government and the militants, giving the Tamils limited
autonomy in exchange for an arms surrender.
   India sent in peacekeeping soldiers to carry out the agreement.
But the Liberation Tigers renounced the accord, and the Indian
forces were caught up in vicious battles.
   At least 11,000 people, including 1,150 Indian soldiers, have
died in the Tamil insurgency.
   In addition, the Tamil autonomy drive has generated a
nationalist Sinhalese backlash, and that anti-government campaign
has killed at least 7,000 people.
   Prabhakaran's last appearance in public was in August 1987, soon
after he returned from New Delhi after talks with Indian government
leaders.
   An eighth-grade dropout, Prabhakaran learned guerrilla warfare
at a training camp in Lebanon run by the Popular Front for the
Liberation of Palestine, headed by George Habash.
   Last summer, reports of Prabhakaran's death in a gunbattle with
his No. 2 man, Ajith Mahathiya, surfaced in Sri Lanka and India.
Asked Sunday about those reports, Prabhakaran just laughed.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0065 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 2105EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BRF--RollerCoasterCrash     04-01 0162</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Roller Coaster Crash,0165</SECOND>
<HEAD>Officials Investigate Roller Coaster Crash That Hurt 35</HEAD>
<DATELINE>KANSAS CITY, Mo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A roller coaster on which two cars
crashed remained closed Sunday as experts tried to determine the
cause of the accident that injured 35 people.
   A train of six cars on the ride at Worlds of Fun amusement park
stopped about 100 feet from the end of the ride Saturday, and the
following train slammed into it.
   At least 35 people, mostly teen-agers and young adults, suffered
injuries ranged from bruises to a broken leg, Green said. Nine
people were admitted to hospitals overnight, five for observation,
he said.
   Each of the trains carried 24 people.
   The $3 million Timber Wolf roller coaster, built by Dinn Inc.,
was shut Sunday as engineers and electricians checked the
equipment, Green said. The experts weren't immediately able to
determine what caused the accident, which occurred on the first day
the park opened for the season, he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0066 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 2111EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Netherlands-USOfficer     04-01 0451</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Netherlands-US Officer,0463</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dutch Guards Reportedly Foil Attempt To Free U.S. Sergeant</HEAD>
<DATELINE>UTRECHT, Netherlands (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Dutch prison guards foiled an
attempt by 12 Americans, including several servicemen, to seize a
U.S. Air Force sergeant imprisoned on charges of killing his wife,
television reports said Sunday.
   A Justice Ministry spokesman reacted by warning of ``a serious
diplomatic conflict,'' according to Dutch television.
   Television reports said the incident occurred Friday after the
Dutch High Court ruled that Sgt. Charles Donald Short could not be
extradited to the United States to stand trial on the murder
charges.
   The 12 U.S. citizens, including several members of the U.S. Air
Force, were waiting in several cars with U.S. license plates
outside a jail in the central Dutch city of Utrecht, the television
said. Short was due to return there from the High Court ruling in
The Hague, 37 miles away, according to the report.
   Prison guards who saw the Americans asked them what they were
doing, and the guards were told the men were waiting for Short to
take him to the United States, apparently for trial, the report
said.
   There was no immediate word of how the guards thwarted them or
whether the Americans were armed.
   The television report quoted a Justice Ministry spokesman as
saying, ``The (12) Americans are way off the mark here. They should
keep their paws off Short, or else there will be a serious
diplomatic incident.''
   The spokesman was not identified in the report. A security guard
at the ministry said no spokesman could be reached until Monday.
   The television report quoted Short's unidentified defense
attorney as saying the Americans were trying to mount ``a little
Panama.'' It was a reference to the U.S. invasion of that nation in
December to topple dictator Manuel Antonio Noriega.
   Short was arrested on April 1, 1988, and accused of killing his
Turkish-born wife, cutting her body into pieces and dumping the
remains in plastic bags in Monnikendam, 56 miles from the U.S. Air
Force base at Soesterberg. He was serving there with the 32nd
Tactical Fighter Squadron.
   He was transferred to U.S. military police a few days later, but
he was eventually handed back to Dutch authorities for trial.
   The High Court ruled Short's extradition would be illegal since
he could be sentenced to death if convicted of murder by a U.S.
court.
   However, it is still unclear whether Dutch courts will be
legally competent to try him. If not, he could be released,
according to the television report.
   The United States asked for Short's extradition soon after his
arrest. But Dutch law, which has no capital punishment, routinely
bans extradition in cases that could lead to the suspect being
executed.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0067 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 2126EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BRF--Lightning-Suspect     04-01 0140</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Lightning-Suspect,0146</SECOND>
<HEAD>Man Wanted In Wife's Stabbing Hit By Lightning</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ST. PETERSBURG, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A man sought for questioning in the
stabbing of his wife was in critical condition Sunday after being
struck by lightning, authorities said.
   Kevin Callahan's wife, Janet, was in critical but stable
condition at the same hospital, Bayfront Medical Center.
   Her husband was found semiconscious at 8 a.m. Saturday on a
fishing catwalk at the Gandy Bridge, police said. He muttered to
rescuers that he was wanted by police, the Pinellas County
Sheriff's Department said.
   Doctors determined he had been hit by lightning, said sheriff's
spokeswoman Marianne Pasha.
   Mrs. Callahan was stabbed in the throat and back with a large
butcher knife on Thursday, police said.
   St. Petersburg police charged Callahan, 32, with aggravated
battery Saturday afternoon as he lay in a hospital bed.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0068 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 2139EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-RapeRemark     04-01 0197</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Rape Remark,0203</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rape Victim Says Assailant Quoted Williams During Attack</HEAD>
<DATELINE>AUSTIN, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A woman told authorities a man who sexually
assaulted her at knifepoint quoted Republican gubernatorial nominee
Clayton Williams, who last weekend compared foul weather to rape,
police said.
   According to the police report, the man told the 30-year-old
woman she should ``relax and enjoy it ... Like Clayton Williams
said, it's inevitable.''
   The woman was bound and sexually assaulted by the man, who broke
into her apartment and waited for her to return home Thursday
night, said police Sgt. Hector Reveles. Police had no suspects in
the attack.
   Williams drew criticism from Democrats and women's groups for
comparing foggy, drizzly weather on his ranch to rape.
   ``If it's inevitable, just relax and enjoy it,'' he told
cowhands and reporters March 24.
   Williams apologized for the remark.
   Asked Sunday to comment on the attack, Williams' press
secretary, Bill Kenyon, said Sunday, ``This violent incident is so
awful and appalling that out of respect for the victim we have no
comment.''
   The Democratic candidates, State Treasurer Ann Richards and
Attorney General Jim Mattox, meet in a runoff April 10 for their
party's nomination.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0069 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 2141EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-ImportedWines     04-01 0228</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Imported Wines,210</SECOND>
<HEAD>FDA Requiring Fungicide-Free Certification For Some Wine Imports</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The U.S. government is requiring some French
and Italian vineyards to certify that their wines do not contain
traces of a fungicide not approved in the United States before
shipping the wines to this country, a spokesman said Sunday.
   ``We have found a little bit of Italian sparking wine and some
French wine that contains traces of a fungicide not approved in the
United States,'' said Food and Drug Administration spokesman Bill
Grigg.
   He said there is no ban on the wines, but the vineyards involved
must retain independent testing labs to certify that the wines are
fungicide-free before shipping them to the United States.
   The FDA will conduct spot tests on the wines to reaffirm the
certifications, he said.
   The fungicide, procymidone, is made in Japan and is applied to
grapes while they are growing rather than to the wines themselves,
said Grigg.
   Grigg said he did not have figures on the amount of wine
involved, but that it was a tiny percentage of total exports from
the two countries to the United States.
   He also said there is no indication that the fungicide _ which
is approved for use in Europe _ constitutes a health risk. But
because it has not undergone U.S. clearance procedures, he said, it
cannot be allowed.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0070 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 2150EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-SovietJews-Rally     04-01 0479</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet Jews-Rally,0493</SECOND>
<HEAD>120,000 Demonstrators Demand Emigration Freedom for Soviet Jews</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Israel-Soviet Jews</HEAD>
<HEAD>By CHRIS SHERIDAN</HEAD>
<HEAD>Associated Press Writer</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An estimated 120,000 demonstrators gathered
outside the United Nations Sunday to voice support for Soviet
Jewish emigration and to express rage at reports of growing
anti-Semitism in the Soviet Union.
   The ralliers, who packed Dag Hammersjold Plaza, also called for
direct flights from Moscow to Tel Aviv.
   The rally came six days after Malev, the Hungarian airline,
halted flights between Budapest and Tel Aviv because of threats by
the radical group Islamic Jihad to attack airliners carrying Soviet
emigres. The airline resumed limited flights from Budapest to Tel
Aviv Sunday, but still wasn't running direct charter flights from
Moscow.
   Arab nations have asked the Soviet Union to slow the tide of
emigrating Soviet Jews.
   ``To stand resolute against these terrorist threats is to defeat
their cowardly perpetrators,'' said President George Bush, in a
statement read at the rally. ``Soviet Jews must be allowed free and
unimpeded transit as well as direct flights to Israel.''
   Several other prominent politicians and dignitaries addressed
the crowd, which police estimated at 120,000. They included New
York City Mayor David Dinkins, Sen. Alfonse D'Amato, R-N.Y., New
York State Attorney General Robert Abrams, novelist Elie Wiesel,
Israel's Consul General Uriel Savir, former Mayor Edward I. Koch
and refusenik Natan Scharansky, who emigrated from the Soviet Union
in 1986.
   Messages of support were sent by Vice President Dan Quayle, New
York Gov. Mario Cuomo, Sen. Daniel Moynihan, D-N.Y., Sen. Bill
Bradley, D-N.J., and Cardinal John O'Connor, head of the New York
Archdiocese.
   Each of the speakers praised the Soviet Union for allowing
greater emigration, but also cautioned that the battle continues.
   ``When you hear that there are wonderful leaders in the Soviet
Union, don't believe this,'' Scharansky told the ralliers. ``It is
you who made all these changes possible, it's your struggle to
change our future.''
   Under Mikhail Gorbachev's leadership, Soviet authorities have
let thousands of Jews leave the country. In 1986, only 914 were
allowed to emigrate.
   Thousands of Jews are presently trying to leave the Soviet Union
for Israel. But there are no direct flights between the Soviet
Union and Israel, so emigres must travel via third countries, such
as Hungary or Czechoslovakia.
   Speakers expressed alarm over reports that anti-Semitism is
growing in the Soviet Union.
   ``Jews are terrified over threats to their life and limb,'' said
Rabbi Haskel Lookstein, the chairman of the Greater New York
Coalition for Soviet Jewry, the rally's sponsor.
   ``We say to Mikhail Gorbachev, we have nothing against you or
the Soviet Union. But we demand that you crush the anti-Semitic
savages in your country,'' he said.
   ``Bigotry among some Soviets is becoming their first exercise in
free thought,'' said Mayor Dinkins. ``But Soviet Jews haven't come
so far to be disappointed so soon.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0071 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 2238EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Helicopter-Gunshots 2ndLd-Writethru a0716 04-01 0790</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Helicopter-Gunshots, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0716,0806</SECOND>
<HEAD>Blockade of Indian Land Remains After Helicopter Shooting</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: INSERTS one graf after 5th graf pvs, `State police
failed...,' to UPDATE with Indians' conditions for allowing
investigators on their land. Pick up 6th graf pvs, `A National
Guard... </NOTE>
<BYLINE>By MIKE HENDRICKS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ALTONA, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   State police with shotguns blockaded a
Mohawk Indian community Sunday for a third straight day since
gunfire forced down a Vermont National Guard helicopter and wounded
a doctor on a medical mission.
   While the blockade of the Ganienkeh Mohawk Territory continued,
negotiators were trying to work out an agreement to investigate the
shooting, which wounded a civilian doctor aboard the helicopter.
   The Indians, insisting that a police investigation would be an
invasion of the Ganienkeh territory, said they would die to protect
the sovereignty of their community near the Canadian border, about
150 miles north of Albany.
   Hundreds of troopers were outside the community. State police
said several armed Mohawks, several with AK-47 assault rifles, were
seen inside the isolated and secretive traditional Indian community
where an estimated 40 families live.
   State police failed again Sunday to persuade the Indians to
allow investigators into the area, but said they would resume the
negotiations Monday.
   An Indian spokesman, Daryl Martin, said late Sunday the Indians
would be willing to allow an independent investigation team onto
their land, as long as the results were reported simultaneously to
both sides. State troopers wouldn't be excluded from the team, as
long as the Mohawks believed they could be impartial, Martin said.
   A National Guard crew flew the damaged helicopter off the
Ganienkeh land and back to Vermont Sunday afternoon, said state
police Capt. Richard Garrant. The Mohawks had allowed a crew on the
territory to repair the craft.
   Two state police helicopter overflights of the Ganienkeh land
Saturday determined that the shots were fired by a gunman standing
near a building on the territory, said state police Maj. Robert Leu.
   Daryl Martin, a spokesman for the Indians, insisted the shots
did not come from the encampment.
   Mohawk roadblocks were set up beside police blockades after the
shooting to keep authorities from coming onto the settlement,
Martin said. State police patrolled blockades on the four roads
leading into the encampment.
   The crew chief of the National Guard helicopter, Sgt. Kris
Samples, saw a man fire a rifle at the chopper, Leu said. Samples
flew with state police investigators Saturday and pointed out where
he saw the gunman, Leu said.
   Another witness, a man who had been driving a pickup truck on a
nearby road and heard the shots, corroborated Samples' account, Leu
said. Investigators took aerial photographs of the area, Leu said.
   Tensions spiked Saturday afternoon when talks broke off and the
Mohawks said they were preparing for violence. By nightfall,
though, tensions eased and negotiators were preparing to continue
their discussions.
   State police want permission to send three investigators onto
the Ganienkah land for one hour, but the Indians, like other
Mohawks in northern New York, claim federal or state authorities
have no jurisdiction on their land.
   ``Sovereignty is the bottom line,'' said Dennis Curtin, a
Plattsburgh attorney representing the Indians. ``The position of
the Indians is that no outside investigation is going to be done on
the territory.''
   Trooper Richard Garcia said the helicopter was flying at about
200 feet when it was fired on about 11:30 a.m. Friday. Dr. James
Van Kirk, 27, was recovering from a gunshot wound at Vermont
Medical Center in Burlington, where he works.
   Three military crew members, Van Kirk and a civilian nurse were
aboard the UH-1 helicopter, which was flying from Burlington to
Massena, N.Y., to pick up a seriously ill patient. Snow forced the
helicopter to abort its mission and it was returning to Vermont
when the shots were fired.
   The Ganienkeh encampment has its roots in a centuries-old land
claim by the Mohawks, who say the land is among 9 million acres in
New York and Vermont wrongfully taken from them in the 18th century.
   The state gave the Mohawks the use of the Ganienkeh land in 1977
as part of a settlement that ended a three-year Mohawk occupation
of land at Moss Lake, about 100 miles southwest of Altona.
   In October 1974, a 22-year-old man and a 9-year-old girl were
shot and wounded while riding in cars near Moss Lake, and the
Indians also refused to cooperate. No one was ever charged.
   State Attorney General Robert Abrams sued the Ganienkeh Indians
to try to close a bingo hall that opened in 1988. Busloads of
people normally travel on weekends to the territory to play
high-stakes bingo, but the buses were turned back at the roadblocks
throughout the weekend.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0072 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 2232EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Greece 1stLd-Writethru a0708 04-01 0378</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Greece, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0708,0391</SECOND>
<HEAD>One Dead, Four Injured As Gunman Opens Fire on Socialists</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS thruout to UPDATE with details on dead and injured;
ADDS statements by government and parties, details; no pickup</NOTE>
<DATELINE>IRAKLION, Greece (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An attacker in a passing car Sunday
fired at a barricade erected by socialists campaigning on Crete for
next week's national elections, killing one person and wounding
four, police said.
   The socialists erected the roadblock to stop conservative New
Democracy party leader Constantine Mitsotakis from approaching
Iraklion's city center to address a rally, police said.
   A police official identified the dead man as Manolis Iakoumakis,
37, a cook who lived in Iraklion. The injured were in stable
condition at the city hospital, he said.
   No one had been arrested in the shootings, said the official,
who spoke on condition of anonymity.
   The Panhellenic Socialist Movement said the dead man and one of
the four injured were party members.
   New Democracy claimed that one of the wounded, journalist Costas
Papagiorgiou, was one of its supporters.
   New Democracy spokesman Nikos Anastassopoulos accused the
socialists of instigating the violence by setting up the barricade.
   ``We fear that there is a scheme to create tension in the last
days of the election campaign,'' he said in a telephone interview.
   Anastassopoulos said socialist supporters had not heeded
repeated calls to remove the barrier.
   A spokesman for the Panhellenic Socialist Movement alleged that
the shots were fired from a car in the New Democracy entourage.
Anastassopoulos said he could not comment on the claim because he
had not been fully briefed.
   Mitsotakis' entourage passed through the roadblock shortly after
the shooting, and the rally was held as scheduled.
   Socialist leader Andreas Papandreou, the former premier, accused
New Democracy of ``systematized provocation. '' He called on his
supporters to help restore calm.
   On Saturday, Premier Xenophon Zolotas fired National
Intelligence Chief Dimitris Angelopoulos. The premier said
Angelopoulos had been slow in briefing him on allegations that
intelligence agents were jamming broadcasts of a television station
allied to the socialists.
   President Christos Sartzetakis dissolved the 300-member
parliament on March 12 in preparation for the elections.
   New Democracy had held 148 seats and the socialists had held
128. The Communist Party held most of the remaining seats.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0073 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 2241EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-SyphilisContacts     04-01 0444</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Syphilis Contacts,0456</SECOND>
<HEAD>Study: Tracing of Sex Partners Unlikely To Control Syphilis</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By A.J. HOSTETLER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PHILADELPHIA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Efforts to notify the sex partners of
syphilis patients is unlikely to control the spread of the disease
because many of those infected have multiple anonymous partners,
according to a study released Sunday.
   The results, reported in Monday's issue of the Annals of
Internal Medicine, suggest that efforts to fight AIDS by notifying
patients' partners is likely to fail, too, said an accompanying
editorial in the journal.
   The 1988 study, conducted by Oregon health officials and the
U.S. Centers for Disease Control focused on 146 syphilis-infected
adults treated over four months. Overall the patients were able to
identify an average of just one in five of their sexual partners,
according to the report.
   Twenty-eight percent of the patients reported exchanging sex for
drugs or money, and that group accounted for 72 percent of the
unlocatable sexual partners.
   ``A strategy of controlling syphilis which relies solely or
mostly on partner notification is doomed to failure because it is _
at most _ only 20 percent effective,'' said one of the study's
authors, Dr. David Fleming of the Oregon Health Division.
   Oregon state law requires that syphilis cases be reported to
county and state health officials.
   Each patient had an average of five sex partners during the
study period whom they could not identify sufficiently for partner
notification, the study found.
   In contrast, a comparison group of 164 Oregon adults with
gonorrhea, which is also sexually transmitted, reported an average
of less than one anonymous sex partner.
   Syphilis, a chronic, sexually transmitted disease, is at its
highest national rate in 40 years, infecting about 16 people out of
every 100,000. In 1988, 39,000 cases were reported, according to
the CDC.
   Because of syphilis' long infectious period and the likelihood
that some patients engage in prostitution or drug use, the
researchers said partner notification won't control its spread.
   Because AIDS is prevalent among those with multiple sex partners
and intravenous drug users, partner notification for those patients
will be ``fraught with the same problems,'' Fleming said.
   Instead, contact tracing should be supplemented by vigorous and
aggressive voluntary screening and educational programs, the
researchers said.
   ``Despite a medical treatment for syphilis, the resurgence of
this disease in the heterosexual population may be an alarming
prelude to an epidemic of AIDS in the same population,'' the
researchers wrote.
   The editorialist, Allan Brandt of Harvard Medical School, said
that despite calls for mandatory contact tracing of AIDS patients,
the Oregon study points out ``the great uncertainty that (partner
notification) effectively serves the goals of public health and
welfare.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0074 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 2248EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-PlaneCrash 3rdLd-Writethru a0735 04-01 0500</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Plane Crash, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0735,0512</SECOND>
<HEAD>Plane Crashes, Sets Houses on Fire</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 10 grafs to UPDATE with flight plan suggesting
plane may have had a passenger, other details; RESTORES dropped
word `person' in lead. Pick up 10th graf pvs, `Lee Hill...</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By SCOTT MAXWELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOULDER, Colo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A light plane swooped out of the foothills
and crashed into a vacant home and several outbuildings, killing at
least one person and setting three buildings on fire.
   The twin-engine private plane smashed into the only vacant home
in the neighborhood, said city spokesman David Grimm. It hit four
or five garages and other outbuildings, setting the home and two of
the outbuildings on fire.
   Paint stored in one of the buildings fed a fierce blaze.
   Firefighters recovered one body from the wreckage of the plane,
Grimm said, adding that it was burned beyond recognition.
   A flight plan raised the possibility there was a passenger on
the plane, but searchers failed to find a second body, authorities
said after nightfall Sunday.
   Eyewitnesses reported seeing a twin-engine plane obviously in
trouble.
   ``The engine was screaming wildly,'' said Gary Faris, who
watched from his back yard. The plane swooped low along a ridge,
its wing dipping low.
   ``It went out of sight and a second later we heard the impact,''
Faris said.
   The plane crashed between 3 p.m. and 4 p.m. MDT on the northwest
edge of Boulder, a city of about 100,000 that is 30 miles northwest
of Denver.
   A flight plan filed for the Cessna 421-C indicated it took off
from the Denver area at 1:50 p.m. Sunday to take a passenger to
Granby, across the Continental Divide in the Colorado Rockies, then
return to Denver, said Verlin B. Tranter, an investigator for the
National Transportation Board.
   Investigators had yet to determine if the plane made it to
Granby and was returning or had turned back with two people on
board, he said. The plane was owned by Skyways Associates of Raton,
N.M.
   Lee Hill, a spokesman for Boulder Community Hospital, said one
man was admitted shortly after the crash with hip injuries.
   The man, Harold Parks, 54, was working in his garage when the
plane crashed, said Steve Davis, a Boulder County deputy sheriff
and Parks' stepson, who saw the plane crash and rushed over to find
Parks lying on the ground.
   ``He appeared to be OK,'' Davis said. ``I kicked in a door
looking for my mom, who was gone. My stepfather said he heard a
loud explosion and was literally blown out of the garage about 40
yards.''
   Also Sunday in Highland, N.Y., a single-engine plane struck a
300-foot broadcast tower atop a fog-bound mountain and crashed,
killing the pilot, state police said. The name of the pilot, alone
aboard the Cessna, was withheld.
   Broadcasting from the tower 50 miles north of New York City was
uninterrupted, said Jerry Lademan of WEOK in Poughkeepsie, one of
several stations that use the tower.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0075 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 2302EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-NaziProsecution     04-01 0476</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Nazi Prosecution,0493</SECOND>
<HEAD>Son Attacks U.S. Agency For Extraditing Father on War Crime
Charges</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ALLISON J. PUGH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEWTON, Mass. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The son of a man extradited for Nazi war
crimes confronted the federal investigators who helped send his
father to Yugoslavia at an international conference Sunday on the
Holocaust.
   Radoslav Artukovic said the Nazi-hunting Office of Special
Investigations built the case against his father, Andrija
Artukovic, by relying on forged documents.
   Officials of the OSI, a U.S. Justice Department agency whose
role in the extradition is under federal investigated, deny the
allegation.
   The fifth annual Boston College law school conference on the
Holocaust and human rights law was attended by prosecutors,
academics and Nazi hunters, including Beate Klarsfeld of France. In
the Holocaust during World War II the Nazis systematically killed 6
million Jews, as well as homosexuals, Gypsies and others considered
undesirable.
   Andrija Artukovic was extradited in 1986. Dubbed the ``Butcher
of the Balkans,'' he was convicted in Yugoslavia of ordering the
deaths of more than 1,000 people and of complicity in hundreds of
thousands of other concentration camp deaths. He died of natural
causes in a prison hospital in 1988 while awaiting execution.
   Artukovic claims his father was innocent and has repeatedly
questioned the extradition.
   On Sunday, the Los Alamitos, Calif., stockbroker and former
military police investigator accused the OSI team of relying on
falsified evidence from a communist country in order to extradite
his father.
   The elite unit was able to extradite the senior Artukovic
because extradition is performed at the request of a foreign
country. It doesn't require due process in a U.S. court.
   Artukovic said he had State Department cables suggesting the OSI
solicited the Yugoslavian request for his father's extradition.
   OSI Deputy Director Bruce Einhorn denied the accusations at the
conference.
   ``OSI does not operate a service for begging and demanding
extradition from other countries,'' he said. ``Other countries are
grown up ... they have to make the decision about whether they want
someone extradited.''
   Artukovic also accused the OSI of holding back facts that would
have discredited affidavits from several witnesses whose testimony
was crucial to the extradition.
   In addition, Artukovic said, OSI officials misled a Los Angeles
court by de-emphasizing the office's role in soliciting information
from Yugoslavia about Artukovic.
   The Justice Department has confirmed in written replies to
members of Congress that internal auditors in the Office of
Professional Responsibility have begun investigating the
allegations.
   Einhorn declined to comment on the investigation.
   ``As far as were concerned, we think the case should be over,''
he said. ``We deny that anyone at OSI committed any misconduct. We
believe our office acted properly and we believe the courts''
support that.
   Artukovic said he undertook his crusade because he wants his
father's body back from the Yugoslavian government, which has
refused to return it.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0076 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 2314EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Nepal     04-01 0388</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Nepal,0401</SECOND>
<HEAD>Pro-democracy Protesters Take to Nepal's Streets</HEAD>
<DATELINE>KATMANDU, Nepal (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Pro-democracy protesters pressed their
demands Sunday as people marched through the capital area with
sticks and knives, doctors went on strike and lawyers rallied at
the prime minister's office.
   Prime Minister Marich Man Singh Shrestha reshuffled his Cabinet,
where divisions have surfaced over how to handle the growing
protest movement.
   In the Katmandu suburb of Patan, men, women and children poured
into the streets demanding an end to alleged police brutality.
   Two demonstrators were killed by police gunfire over the two
previous days, and 20 were wounded.
   On Sunday, hundreds of protesters carried sticks, metal rods and
kitchen knives.
   Residents had dug trenches overnight and erected barricades on
major streets to prevent police from sending reinforcements. During
the day, police removed many of the large mounds of boulders, logs
and garbage cans placed across the streets.
   At least 14 people have been killed in Nepal since Feb. 18, when
the movement for multiparty democracy was launched by two banned
political parties in this Himalayan kingdom. Hundreds of people _
including doctors, lawyers, students and journalists _ have been
arrested.
   Doctors, nurses and other workers went on strike at hospitals in
the Katmandu Valley on Sunday, defying a government warning that
employees of essential services should not strike.
   Only skeleton staffs remained on duty to deal with emergency
cases.
   About 250 lawyers marched to the prime minister's office to
demand the release of 64 jailed attorneys. Shrestha was not in his
office, and the protesters left a memo demanding the detainees be
freed by Wednesday.
   One marcher, speaking on condition of anonymity, said the
lawyers also were demanding that government forces stop shooting
women and children and investigate all cases of police gunfire
since the protests began.
   The demonstrators seek to change Nepal's system of non-partisan
government, which divides power between King Birendra and the
National Assembly.
   Shrestha reshuffled his Cabinet on Sunday following the
resignation of Foreign Minister Shailendra Kumar Upadhyaya, who
said the government should have held talks with the protesters.
   Shrestha dropped nine of the 29 members in the Council of
Ministers.
   Government-owned Radio Nepal gave no reason for the firings. But
well-placed sources, speaking on condition of anonymity, said the
sacked ministers had differences with the prime minister. They did
not elaborate.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0077 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 2314EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-FuelSpill 1stLd-Writethru a0737 04-01 0671</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Fuel Spill, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0737,0690</SECOND>
<HEAD>RETRANSMITTING to restore writethru designation.</HEAD>
<HEAD>Fuel Slick Threatens Water Supplies in Pittsburgh, Other
Communities</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: INSERTS 2 grafs after 5th graf pvs, `The company said...,'
with governor declaring state of emergency. Pick up 6th graf pvs,
`The 30-mile-long...</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By JIM STRADER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PITTSBURGH (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A 30-mile-long fuel slick left a town of about
15,000 people without normal water Sunday, and threatened water
supplies in Pittsburgh and dozens of other cities dependent on the
Allegheny and Ohio rivers, authorities said.
   The slick moving sluggishly down the Allegheny northwest of
Pittsburgh resulted from a landslide that cracked a pipeline
Friday. The pipeline released a mixture of gasoline, kerosene and
lesser amounts of other fuels into a tributary creek at Freeport
about 35 miles northeast of Pittsburgh.
   Buckeye Pipeline Co. estimated it lost about 98,000 gallons of
fuel from the 10-inch-wide pipeline linking Linden, N.J., and the
Pittsburgh suburb of Coraopolis.
   The company said it recovered about 20 percent of the spilled
fuel, and the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency estimated that
75,600 gallons leaked into Knapp Run Creek, then into the
Allegheny. The cleanup continued Sunday.
   Pennsylvania Gov. Robert P. Casey on Sunday declared a state of
emergency along the section of the Allegheny affected by the spill.
   ``Suffice it to say, there is still a high level of concern,''
Casey said. ``But we believe the situation is being dealth with
adequately.''
   The 30-mile-long slick was at least five miles northeast of
Pittsburgh, city water department engineer Alex Sciulli told an
evening news conference.
   ``This spill has been very difficult to track,'' Sciulli said.
   Many water treatment plants cannot filter out the fuels in the
spill, said Allegheny County Health Director Albert Brunwasser.
Officials were trying to develop a treatment program, he said.
   In Harrison Township, a city of about 15,000 people nearly 35
miles northeast of Pittsburgh, residents had to rely on water
brought by truck and tanker to community fire stations, said county
Deputy Fire Marshal Nat Mastro.
   In a worst-case scenario, about 50,000 people in more than 30
communities that get their water from the Allegheny could be
without it by Monday, Mastro said.
   In Pittsburgh, officials said they expected to shut down the
city's water intakes, leaving at least a three-day reserve.
   Mayor Sophie Masloff has asked all residents in the city of
about 400,000 people to reduce water use, Sciulli said. If
residents cooperate, the reserve could last an additional two days.
   ``We feel we're in very good shape,'' Sciulli said.
   Officials in other communities were not as optimistic.
   Brackenridge Emergency Management Director Dennis Vrotny said
fire departments in his community and others were drawing as much
water as possible from tributaries to the Allegheny to add to their
reservoirs.Vrotny said coperation from residents was essential.
   ``I don't think it's going to hold if people don't conserve
now,'' he said. ``As it is, we're losing ground fast.''
   The water system in Brackenridge, a community of about 4,000,
serves 30,000 people, Vrotny said.
   Eight municipal water authorities that draw supplies from the
Ohio up to 12 miles northwest of Pittsburgh were asked to begin
saving water in case the slick reaches them, said Beaver County
Emergency Services Director Russell Chiodo. The Ohio flows out of
the juncture of the Allegheny and Monongahela in Pittsburgh.
   The authorities serve about 40,000 people, Chiodo said. ``We
want them to be conservative as all heck right now,'' he said. ``We
don't know what's going to happen.''
   Eighty-five cleanup workers from Buckeye Pipeline and
contractors used absorbent pads attached to floating booms to
remove oil from the Allegheyny said Charles Kleeman, the EPA's
Pittsburgh administrator.
   The state Department of Environmental Resources and county
health laboratories tested river water samples to determine the
extent of pollution and whether the fuel-laced water was flammable,
Kleeman said.
   Federal, state and county emergency management officials said
experience from a 4 million-gallon spill two years ago on the
Monongahela helped this weekend's cleanup.
   The spill has not affected the Monongahela.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0078 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 2027EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f BC-ChryslerStock     04-01 0176</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Chrysler Stock,0183</SECOND>
<HEAD>Iacocca Urges Managers to Buy Chrysler Stock</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DETROIT (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Chrysler Corp. Chairman Lee Iacocca is
encouraging about 100 top managers to buy company stock, tying
their personal finances to the company they run, a Chrysler
spokesman said.
   ``It started with just a feeling on our top management's part
that our management should take greater stock in the future of the
company by sharing in the same risks and rewards as the
shareholders,'' Steve Harris, director of Chrysler's corporate
public relations, said Sunday.
   The program, which affects about 100 top executives, began a few
weeks ago, Harris said.
   The move comes with Chrysler stock standing at $16.62{ a share
on the New York Stock Exchange, down about 37 percent from its high
over the past year.
   Harris said the program aims at making the executives
accountable, something Chrysler has been stressing in the last year.
   In July, Chrysler asked 2,000 top executives to voluntarily put
into escrow up to 10 percent of their salary, as part of a
$1-billion, 15-month cost-cutting program.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0079 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 1404EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-Britain-Broadcasting Bjt   04-01 0761</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Britain-Broadcasting, Bjt,0788</SECOND>
<HEAD>More Telly For Britons, But Fewer Couch Potatoes Tuning In</HEAD>
<HEAD>Also moved in advance.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LESLIE SHEPHERD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   When there were only four television channels in
Britain, watching ``telly'' was the country's favorite pasttime and
viewers boasted British programs were the best in the world.
   Now that government deregulation is bringing a smorgasbord of
conventional and satellite TV channels to British homes, studies
show audiences have dropped by 10 percent. Half of those still
watching grumble about the programming.
   It's a paradox that is troubling an industry in upheaval as the
latest target of Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher's selloff of
state-owned or regulated enterprises.
   Until last year when publisher Rupert Murdoch introduced
satellite television to Britain, television was neatly carved among
four networks _ two run by the state-funded British Broadcasting
Corp. and two by private companies.
   Now, legislation before the House of Commons calls for
auctioning off all the commercial TV franchises and the creation of
a fifth land-based TV channel.
   It is the most radical overhaul since commercial networks were
first allowed to compete with the venerable BBC in 1955.
   A private consortium, meanwhile, is about to launch Britain's
second satellite TV network, British Satellite Broadcasting, to
compete with Murdoch's money-losing Sky Television.
   All that's missing are the viewers.
   Britons still watch an average of about 25{ hours of television
every week. But that's a 10 percent drop from five years ago,
despite the arrival of overnight television in 1987 and then Sky.
   ``Some of this (drop) is attributable to video, but the same
period saw a considerable increase in alternative leisure
activities _ taking two or more holidays, eating out,'' said Barry
Cox, director of London Weekend Television.
   Bernard Bennett, LWT's controller of research, thinks ``the
existing cake will have to be carved up in a larger number of
portions'' to accommodate the new channels.
   First on the air will be British Satellite Broadcasting, the
international consortium awarded the government franchise to use
the five satellite channels allocated to Britain under an
international treaty.
   The $2 billion consortium is the second-largest private sector
investment project in Britain after Eurotunnel, the tunnel under
the English Channel between England and France.
   The five BSB channels, including a movie channel trumpeting
deals with six of the top eight Hollywood studios, will go
head-to-head beginning April 29 with the four channels of Sky
Television. Sky already is losing $3.2 million a week.
   ``Neither of us has any clue whether there's room for one or
room for two,'' admitted BSB spokesman Edward Bickham.
   ``On a financial basis, we have the ability to spread the risks
of the project across a number of major companies. No one has to
bet their business on BSB.''
   Referring to an industry study showing 44 percent of viewers
saying they find nothing appealing when they want to watch
television, Bickham said, ``We believe there's a lot of room for
extra choice.''
   ``We're not trying to take over the market from the (four
existing) generalist channels, but offering a complimentary service
alongside,'' he said.
   BSB expects to be in 1 million of Britain's 22 million homes by
the end of the year and in 3 million, its break-even point, by the
end of 1991.
   Channel 5, the proposed new land-based commercial channel,
probably will not begin broadcasting until the mid-1990s because of
a wrangle over the type of transmission system. Even then, it will
reach only 70 percent of households, and all their video recorders
will have to be retuned to avoid interference.
   At present the BBC carries no advertisements and the two
commercial networks do. There are 15 regional franchises awarding
to companies that broadcast on the commercial networks. They will
all be put on the auction block in 1993.
   There's no guarantee that any of the existing companies, such as
London Weekend Television, makers of ``Upstairs Downstairs,'' or
Granada Television, which brought out ``The Jewel in the Crown,''
will retain their franchises.
   In fact, Michael Grade, chief executive of the existing Channel
4 commercial network, predicts few of the present companies will
have the money to compete with the powerful consortia bidding
against them.
   ``They may make what they know to be a sensible bid and still
lose to a group which is much more optimistic or has simply got its
sums wrong,'' Grade told a recent American Chamber of Commerce
luncheon.
   ``Is it really right, I ask, to hand out broadcasting licenses
to people who, for whatever reason, may simply be offering too much
money for them?''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0080 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 1635EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-Boesky     04-01 0439</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Boesky,0457</SECOND>
<HEAD>Former Arbitrager Due for Release This Week After Serving Two
Years</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Ivan F. Boesky, Wall Street's most notorious
felon, will be a free man this week.
   The former arbitrager is due for release on Wednesday, just over
two years after he entered prison for his role in the nation's
biggest insider trading scandal, a source close to Boesky said
Sunday.
   This week's date has limited practical meaning, though. The
source, who spoke on condition of anonymity, said Boesky was
released into home custody about six weeks ago and has been
required only to make weekly visits to a Brooklyn halfway house.
   Wednesday's release ``does mean that he won't have to report
back in their once a week,'' he said.
   The source would say only that Boesky was living somewhere in
the New York area and was in good spirits. Boesky owns a 75-acre
estate north of New York City, which he has been renovating
recently.
   ``I think his state of mind is quite good,'' the source said.
   A call to the federal Bureau of Prisons to confirm the release
date was answered by a recording saying the office would reopen
Monday morning. Officials at New York City's Metropolitan
Corrections Center said only the federal office would confirm the
release date.
   In November 1986, Boesky paid $100 million to the Securities and
Exchange Commission and agreed to plead guilty to one felony to
settle charges related to Wall Street's biggest insider-trading
case.
   He was sentenced to three years in prison but is being released
a year early for good behavior.
   Boesky was sent to the minimum-security Lompoc Federal Prison
Camp in California in March 1988, where he earned 11 cents an hour
for working on a prison cleanup crew. Last December, he was
transfered to the Brooklyn halfway house.
   After his formal release this week, Boesky will have to report
to a probation officer once a month for six months, the source said.
   As for his future, the source said he didn't think Boesky would
make any plans until after giving testimony in the racketeering and
fraud case against former junk bond pioneer Michael Milken.
   Boesky agreed to testify against Milken as part of his plea
bargain with federal authorities. The case against the former
Drexel Burnham Lambert Inc. executive has been delayed and may not
go to trial before next year.
   In addition to helping the government's case against Milken's,
Boesky also provided information that resulted in a record $650
million plea-bargain settlement by Drexel. Drexel is being
liquidated following its parent's decision to file for Chapter 11
bankruptcy protection in February.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0081 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 2038EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>d f BC-Obit-Robinson     04-01 0109</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Obit-Robinson,0115</SECOND>
<HEAD>Former U.S. Shoe Executive Dead</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CINCINNATI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Harry S. Robinson II, a retired 35-year
veteran of the United States Shoe Corp., died Friday. He was 69.
   Robinson died of cancer at his home. He had been credited as a
key figure in the recent growth of U.S. Shoe, a Cincinnati-based
company whose businesses include footwear, eyeglasses, contact
lenses and women's apparel.
   During his career, Robinson served as advertising manager and as
a vice president and president of the company's Red Cross Shoe
Division. He was group vice president when he retired.
   He also was a past president of the Speech and Hearing Center of
Cincinnati.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0082 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 1922EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f BC-Southmark     04-01 0451</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Southmark,0472</SECOND>
<HEAD>Southmark Strikes Deal with Creditors</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DALLAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Southmark Corp. and its unsecured creditors have
agreed on a new bankruptcy reorganization plan, the real estate
holding company said Sunday.
   The agreement, to be filed with the U.S. Bankruptcy Court in
Dallas, calls for a quicker payout to creditors than the company
offered in its original reorganization proposal.
   The new plan also restructures some securities and proposes a
reduction in payout to Southmark's equity holders, the company said.
   ``Since filing Chapter 11 last July, our objective has been to
avoid lengthy and expensive litigation and to provide prompt
distributions from the estate,'' Board Chairman Arthur G. Weiss
said in a statement.
   The unsecured creditors had presented the biggest obstacle to a
reorganization plan put forward by Southmark in January. That plan
called for the company to sell nearly all of its assets except for
its Houston-based thrift, San Jacinto Savings Association.
   Southmark officials then projected total payments to creditors
of $284 million.
   Unsecured creditors, mainly holders of over $1 billion in
Southmark's junk bonds, were unhappy with the size of the planned
payout and the company's proposal to use securities instead of cash
to satisfy claims. They proposed the complete liquidation of
Southmark.
   Junior debtholders and equity holders also opposed the original
plan, arguing that they would not fare as well as senior
debtholders.
   The new reorganization plan retains a controversial deal
Southmark made with federal thrift regulators to retain control of
San Jacinto.
   Under the new plan, the company's senior creditors will receive
up to $75 million in cash, as well as secured notes and stock in
the reorganized Southmark, the company said.
   The reorganization and future management of the company will be
supervised by a new board of directors to be elected by the
creditors.
   Holders of subordinated debt will receive stock in the
reorganized company and other considerations. Senior and
subordinated creditors will share in proceeds that may be received
by Southmark from litigation resulting from the company's failure.
   Southmark's current common and preferred shareholders will
receive a portion of common stock of the reorganized company.
   Southmark's bankruptcy filing, made in Atlanta and moved to
Dallas, listed total assets of $1.046 billion, secured debt of
$152.4 million, unsecured debt of $1.051 billion and other
liabilities of $190.9 million.
   The unsecured creditors' committee said unsecured claims against
Southmark were closer to $1.5 billion, The Dallas Morning News
reported Saturday.
   Non-thrift assets the company has proposed selling include
insurance, oil and nursing home companies, interest in casinos in
Atlantic City and San Juan, Puerto Rico, and numerous real estate
partnerships. They were acquired mainly through financing provided
by high-risk, high-yield junk bonds sold by Drexel Burnham Lambert
Inc.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900401-0083 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-01-90 2024EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f BC-Poling-Japan     04-01 0197</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Poling-Japan,0204</SECOND>
<HEAD>Poling Says Japan Has Certain Advantages Over U.S. Automakers</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DETROIT (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The new chairman of Ford Motor Co. says there is
some truth to the perception that Japanese automakers turn out a
better quality product than their U.S. counterparts.
   ``If you look at the Japanese, I think we're equal to some and
not as good as the best,'' Harold ``Red'' Poling said in an
interview published in Sunday's editions of The Detroit News. ``Our
objective is to get there. That says you get the reality and you're
going to get the perception.''
   Poling, who took over as chairman last month, said he doesn't
believe the Japanese have a technological edge over America's Big
Three automakers, but he said there is a disparity in operational
costs.
   ``Can we get plants in the United States to produce vehicles as
inexpensively as the Japanese do? You bet. But that requires
shutting down your plants and starting from scratch. We can't do
that.
   ``We have a workforce, we have retirees, we're committed to
pensions and we're committed to health care. And that gives us a
serious noncompetitive disadvantage going in. We have to deal with
that somehow.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
</Collection>
