<Collection>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0001 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 2359EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a BC-LOT--SaturdayLotteries     06-10 0894</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-LOT--Saturday Lotteries,1060</SECOND>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<HEAD>CALIFORNIA</HEAD>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SACRAMENTO, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers picked
Saturday night for the California Lottery's twice-weekly ``Lotto
6-49'' game: 17, 30, 47, 27, 20, 28, and the bonus number, 44.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>CONNECTICUT</HEAD>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEWINGTON, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning combination picked Saturday
in the Connecticut State Lottery's ``Daily Lottery'' drawing was:
   0-1-9
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Play 4</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEWINGTON, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning combination picked Saturday
in the Connecticut State Lottery's ``Play 4'' drawing was:
   3-3-0-1.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>DELAWARE</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DOVER, Del. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   These Delaware lotteries were drawn Saturday
night:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   7-9-6
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Play Four</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   3-7-7-0
</TEXT>
<HEAD>FLORIDA</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected Saturday in
the Florida Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Cash 3</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   0-3-4
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   15-27-18-46-29-37
</TEXT>
<HEAD>ILLINOIS</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SPRINGFIELD, Ill. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the Illinois State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   9-8-9
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick Four</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   4-7-7-9
</TEXT>
<HEAD>LOTTO</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   12-14-17-36-41-53
</TEXT>
<HEAD>INDIANA</HEAD>
<HEAD>Lotto Cash</HEAD>
<DATELINE>INDIANAPOLIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday night in the Hoosier Lottery's Lotto Cash game:
   1--13--15--16--40--43
</TEXT>
<HEAD>IOWA</HEAD>
<HEAD>Iowa Lotto</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DES MOINES, Iowa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers drawn Saturday night
in ``Iowa Lotto'' are:
   8-11-15-24-27-38.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto America</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DES MOINES, Iowa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers drawn Saturday night
in Lotto America are:
   1-26-29-48-49-51
</TEXT>
<HEAD>KANSAS</HEAD>
<HEAD>Kan. Cash Lotto</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOPEKA, Kan. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers in the Kansas Cash Lotto
drawing Saturday night with an estimated jackpot of $105,000:
   3-9-10-18-29-30
</TEXT>
<HEAD>KENTUCKY</HEAD>
<HEAD>Kentucky Lottery</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOUISVILLE, Ky. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are Saturday's winning numbers
selected by the Kentucky Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Kentucky Cash:
   4-8-2.
   </HEAD>
<HEAD>Lotto:
   17-18-23-24-25-33.
   </HEAD>
<HEAD>MARYLAND</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BALTIMORE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   These Maryland lotteries were drawn Saturday
night:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   4-4-8
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Play Four</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   2-4-8-5
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   16-28-30-31-41-42
</TEXT>
<HEAD>MASSACHUSETTS</HEAD>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BRAINTREE, Mass. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers drawn Saturday night
in the ``Massachusetts Daily Lottery'' were:
   1-9-6-1
</TEXT>
<HEAD>MICHIGAN</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DETROIT (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected Saturday in
the Michigan State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   8-4-0
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily-4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   1-1-7-6
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto 47</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   11, 13, 17, 30, 44, 46
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   The Zinger number was:
   1-3-9-7-6-2
</TEXT>
<HEAD>MISSOURI</HEAD>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ST. LOUIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers in Missouri's Lotto drawing
Saturday night:
   5-6-9-10-27-30
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 3</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ST. LOUIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers in Saturday's Missouri
Lottery Daily Pick 3 game:
   0-7-5
</TEXT>
<HEAD>NEW JERSEY</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TRENTON, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday night in the New Jersey State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 3</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   8-7-6
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   7-2-4-4
</TEXT>
<HEAD>NEW YORK</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ALBANY, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the New York State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Number</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   0-9-1
</TEXT>
<HEAD>WinFour</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   0-4-3-0
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 10</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ALBANY, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday night in the New York State's Pick 10 game:
   5, 22, 25, 29, 31, 33, 34, 37, 38, 39, 41, 43, 44, 46, 50, 54,
56, 57, 66, 78.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ALBANY, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday night in the New York State Lottery's Lotto Game:
   11, 18, 31, 32, 33, 52. The supplemental number is 46.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>NORTHERN NEW ENGLAND</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CONCORD, N.H. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the daily New Hampshire, Vermont and Maine lotteries:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 3</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   3-7-4
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   8-1-7-3
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Tri-State Megabucks</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CONCORD, N.H. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers drawn Saturday
in the ``Tri-State Megabucks'' game for New Hampshire, Vermont and
Maine:
   10-16-17-24-34-39
</TEXT>
<HEAD>OHIO</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CLEVELAND (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected Saturday
night in the Ohio Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 3 Numbers</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   6-6-5
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 4 Numbers</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   9-6-5-2
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto Glance</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CLEVELAND (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected Saturday
night in the Ohio Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Super Lotto</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   9-22-25-35-37-40
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Kicker</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   0-6-3-8-8-6
</TEXT>
<HEAD>OREGON</HEAD>
<HEAD>Daily 4</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PORTLAND, Ore. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are Saturday's winning numbers in the
``Oregon Daily 4'' lottery game:
   8-3-2-4
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Megabucks</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PORTLAND, Ore. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are Saturday's winning numbers in the
``Oregon Megabucks'' lottery game:
   3-11-17-23-33-40
</TEXT>
<HEAD>PENNSYLVANIA</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HARRISBURG (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected Saturday
in the Pennsylvania State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Number</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   2-8-9
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Big 4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   9-3-3-9
</TEXT>
<HEAD>RHODE ISLAND</HEAD>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CRANSTON, R.I. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers in the Rhode Island
daily lottery drawing for Saturday were:
   6-8-0-5
</TEXT>
<HEAD>VIRGINIA</HEAD>
<HEAD>Pick 3</HEAD>
<DATELINE>RICHMOND (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   These numbers were drawn Saturday in the
Virginia Lottery's Pick 3 game:
   (9-0-1)
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<DATELINE>RICHMOND (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   These numbers were drawn Saturday in the
Virginia Lottery's Lotto game:
   (3-4-7-9-10-35)
</TEXT>
<HEAD>WASHINGTON</HEAD>
<DATELINE>OLYMPIA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are winning numbers selected Saturday in the
Washington State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   2-9-5
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   9-13-16-27-33-41
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Quinto</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   King of Diamonds, Eight of Spades, Five of Spades, Five of
Hearts, Eight of Clubs (Cards do not need to be in that order to
win.)
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Friday's Daily Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   9-7-8
</TEXT>
<HEAD>WASHINGTON, DC</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The following results were drawn Saturday in
the District of Columbia Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lucky Numbers Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   4-1-7
</TEXT>
<HEAD>D.C. Four Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   0-2-6-3
</TEXT>
<HEAD>D.C. Daily Double Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   45, 34
</TEXT>
<HEAD>D.C. Quick Cash Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   32-4-1-13-38-8
</TEXT>
<HEAD>WEST VIRGINIA</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CHARLESTON, W.Va. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the West Virginia State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily 3</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   5-2-5
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily 4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   1-9-2-4
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0002 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 0010EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-2LiveCrew 2ndLd-Writethru a0588 06-10 0625</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-2 Live Crew, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0588,0639</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rappers Perform Without Incident Despite Arrest Of Record Seller</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUB 6th graf to UPDATE with first of two Saturday night shows
beginning. Pick up 7th graf, `We're gonna ...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By TRACY FIELDS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MIAMI BEACH, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   2 Live Crew took X-rated pokes at local
law officials, but performed without incident just hours after a
record store owner was arrested for selling the rap group's ``As
Nasty As They Wanna Be.''
   ``This city has a lot greater problems to deal with than who is
performing at Club Nu,'' City Commissioner Bruce Singer said before
Friday night's show.
   The Miami rappers played for 45 minutes to a packed house at
Club Nu, which holds about 1,500. They took profanity-laced verbal
jabs at Broward County Sheriff Nick Navarro and Gov. Bob Martinez,
who have attacked the group's sexually explicit lyrics.
   On Saturday, about 150 anti-censorship activists staged a brief
protest at the Coral Gables home of Jack Thompson, an attorney who
has campaigned to get 2 Live Crew's records removed from area music
stores.
   The protestors left after about 15 minutes when police
responding to neighbors' complaints told the group they lacked a
permit for the demonstration, said police Sgt. Dennis Koronkiewicz.
Coral Gables is a suburb of Miami.
   About 15 police officers and a small crowd of several hundred
people were on hand as the rappers performed an early, clean show
for patrons of all ages Saturday night at Hollywood's Club Futura.
Band members expected a larger audience and a livelier show during
an adults-only set later Saturday at the club.
   ``We're gonna do 2 Live, nasty as they wanna be,'' band leader
Luther Campbell vowed, speaking of the second show.
   A spokesman for Hollywood police said that would be fine _ at
least in the short run.
   ``We are not going to jump up and stop the show and run the risk
of having some kind of wild riot and have to take a lot of people
to jail,'' Ed Cunningham said Saturday. ``If something happens that
appears it does violate the judge's order, we'll document it and
we're going to forward it to the judge or the state attorney's
office for Broward County.''
   U.S. District Judge Jose Gonzalez ruled Wednesday that the
million-selling album, released more than a year ago, is obscene by
community standards in Broward, Dade and Palm Beach counties.
   That cleared the way for Friday's arrest of Charles Freeman,
owner of E-C Records, who sold copies of the recording to an
undercover deputy. He faces a first-degree misdemeanor charge and
is free on $100 bond.
   If convicted, he could be jailed for a year and fined $1,000.
   Both Freeman and Campbell said they had gotten supportive phone
calls Friday from rock star Frank Zappa, a vocal opponent of
censorship.
   Campbell also pledged his financial, legal and moral support to
retailers who have problems after selling the record. He is owner
and president of 2 Live Crew's record label, now called Luke's
because of copyright problems with the former name Luke Skyywalker.
   The obscenity ruling brought new interest in the group, a
promoter said.
   ``Until this trial, we never could have booked this group on
such short notice, with no time (to advertise) and still expect a
full house,'' said Club Nu promoter Bob Slade. ``They're more
popular than ever now.''
   Campbell was enjoying all the free publicity.
   ``I can't pay for this advertising,'' he said at a Friday news
conference held in the two-story building he recently purchased to
house his recording empire.
   ``As Nasty As They Wanna Be,'' a double album, has sold more
than 1.7 million copies.
   ``The machines are running right now,'' Campbell he said,
smiling.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0003 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 0842EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a BC-TankerBlast     06-10 0477</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Tanker Blast,0488</SECOND>
<HEAD>Containment Booms Arriving at Supertanker Wracked by More
Explosions</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MICHAEL GRACZYK</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>GALVESTON, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A supertanker continued to burn out of
control Sunday morning in the Gulf of Mexico after being hit by
more small explosions overnight, authorities said.
   The U.S. Coast Guard's Atlantic Strike Team from Mobile, Ala.,
and other spill response groups were bringing a high-seas barrier
boom and other supplies, including foam, in an effort to quench
flames from the blast andfire Saturday that killed at least two
crewmen.
   ``The fire has been burning steadily out of control all night,
but is still confined to aft section of the ship, at the deck house
area,'' said Petty Officer Richard Miles in Galveston.
   ``Fireboats are still cooling its decks. It had a few minor
explosions last night, including a couple of explosions around
midnight with no debris but a lot of smoke, and a couple of them in
the early-morning hours today.''
   Although authorities said the 853-foot-long tanker was not in
immediate danger of spilling its 38 million gallon cargo of light
crude oil, crews were making a push Sunday to extinguish the blaze
and begin salvaging the petroleum. The ship is 57 miles southeast
of Galveston.
   The Mega Borg's owners have dispatched 10 firefighting vessels
to spray foam on the vessel in an effort to bring the fire under
control and contracted for an airplane to spread dispersants over
about 7,000 gallons of oil spilled so far, said Todd Nelson of the
Coast Guard.
   An oil sheen trailed about 11 miles in a quarter-mile wide path
from the tanker, the Coast Guard said.
   Flames shot hundreds of feet high from the ship's air vents and
thick, black smoke could be seen from 40 miles away after the 1
a.m. engine room explosion.
   In addition to the two confirmed dead, two crewmen remained
missing Sunday and were presumed dead after a search for them was
called off. Seventeen other crew members were injured; two were
hospitalized in fair condition and the others were treated and
released. The ship had a crew of 41.
   The Coast Guard's strike team arrived about 10 p.m. Saturday and
were beginning to assess the situation, said Miles.
   Chief Warrant Officer Mike Shoul, also in Galveston, said it
remained uncertain if the fire had reached the Mega Borg's oil
cargo or was still consuming fuel from the ship's engines.
   The blast occurred as part of its cargo was being transferred to
a smaller tanker. Although oil booms were available if needed,
authorities said the tanker was in no immediate danger of breaking
up or sinking.
   The Houston-Galveston area is home to several major refineries
but the Coast Guard said it didn't know the refinery or refineries
that were the Mega Borg's destination. The tanker is operated by
Mosvolds Shipping of Farsund, Norway.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0004 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 0911EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a BC-2LiveCrew     06-10 0421</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-2 Live Crew,0434</SECOND>
<HEAD>Two Members Of Rap Group 2 Live Crew Arrested On Obscenity Charge</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HOLLYWOOD, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two members of the rap group 2 Live Crew
were arrested on obscenity charges early Sunday after leaving an
adults-only concert at a local nightclub.
   The charges come four days after the Miami group's album ``As
Nasty As They Wanna Be'' was declared obscene by a federal judge
and two days after an area record dealer was arrested for selling
the album.
   Bandleader Luther Campbell and band member Chris Wongwon were
taken into custody by Broward County sheriff's officers on a
misdemeanor charge of violating local obscenity laws by performing
parts of the album declared obscene, said Al Gordon, a Broward
sheriff's spokesman.
   He said arrest warrants would be issued Monday for the other two
members of the group.
   Gordon said the arrests were made several blocks from the
nightclub to avoid any problems with their fans. When the arrest
was made at 3:05 a.m., Campbell and Wongwon ``were cooperative and
went through the process without incident,'' Gordon said.
   ``When you go on television and announce that you're going to do
what you please, that's fine,'' Gordon said. ``But if you do it in
Broward County and it is in violation of Florida state statutes,
you aregoing to be arrested for it.''
   The performers were taken to the Broward County Jail in Fort
Lauderdale for booking, then were released without bond after
signing promises to appear in court on a date to be set later,
Gordon said.
   About 15 police officers and a crowd of about 300 people were on
hand Saturday night as the rappers performed an early, clean show
for patrons of all ages at Hollywood's Club Futura. About 400
people showed up for a livelier, adults-only set later Saturday
night at the club.
   At the first show, many of the young concert-goers shouted
explicit versions of the songs, even when the rap group left out
profanity.
   No incidents were reported at either show.
   The Miami-based group has sold more than 1{ million copies of
``As Nasty As They Wanna Be.''
   U.S. District Judge Jose Gonzalez ruled Wednesday that the
album, released more than a year ago, is obscene by community
standards in Broward, Dade and Palm Beach counties.
   That cleared the way for Sunday's arrests, as well asa Friday's
arrest of Charles Freeman, owner of E-C Records, who sold the
record to an undercover deputy. He faces a first-degree misdemeanor
charge and is free on $100 bond.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0005 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 1038EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a BC-LinerGrounded 1stLd-Writethru a0639 06-10 0252</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Liner Grounded, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0639,0255</SECOND>
<HEAD>Liner Grounded in Dense Fog Near Woods Hole, Mass.</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: UPDATES throughout with Coast Guard saying passengers in no
immediate danger, evacuation preparations are under way. No pickup.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>FALMOUTH, Mass. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Nearly 700 passengers were stranded
Sunday morning on an ocean liner that was grounded and taking on
water in dense fog off Woods Hole, officials said. Preparations
were under way for an evacuation.
   The 617-foot Bermuda Star ran aground at about 8:30 a.m. at the
Cleveland Ledge Light in Buzzards Bay, about two miles from shore,
the Coast Guard said.
   Petty Officer Charles Tebo of the Wood's Hole Coast Guard
station said the 680 passengers did not appear to be in immediate
danger, but the skipper of the vessel had asked that they be
evacuated. He said the 380-person crew will probably stay on board.
   The vessel was taking on water and officials were trying to find
where the water was coming in, Tebo said.
   Tebo said ferries and commercial boats would aid the Coast Guard
in evacuating the passengers.
   Coast Guard boats also sent booms to the area to contain an oil
spill from the ship's motors. The extent of the spill was not
immediately known.
   ``As far as we can tell, the passengers are in no immediate
danger at this point in time,'' Tebo said. ``I'm sure they're a
little scared and concerned.'' No injuries were reported.
   The liner's home port and itinerary were not immediately known,
Tebo said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0006 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 1121EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Pakistan-Violence Bjt   06-10 0826</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Pakistan-Violence, Bjt,0852</SECOND>
<HEAD>Violence in Bhutto's Province Raises Fears of Martial Law</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SHARON HERBAUGH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ISLAMABAD, Pakistan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Gang violence in Prime Minister
Benazir Bhutto's home province has taken 400 lives in a month, and
many Pakistanis fear it endangers their country's brief experiment
with democracy.
   Ms. Bhutto, who campaigned for a decade to free Pakistan from
military rule, has been forced to call out the army in Sindh, her
native province in southern Pakistan.
   No one knows who is killing whom. Private armies, drug gangs and
ethnic militias operate at will. Kidnappings, indiscriminate
shootings and armed robbery are commonplace.
   Police have arrested more than 3,300 people in a weeklong sweep
of Sindh province, the heart of the country's financial and
industrial base.
   Critics and supporters agree a lasting solution depends on Ms.
Bhutto's ability to make peace with an ethnic political movement
that nearly brought down her government last year by withdrawing
its support.
   ``Her long years of trials ... have conditioned her to think
invariably in terms of `them' and `us,''' a government official
said on condition of anonymity.
   ``She has to stop playing party politics. She has to stop acting
merely as the leader of the Pakistan People's Party and start being
the prime minister of Pakistan. If she can't, she'll be lucky to
last six months.''
   If Ms. Bhutto fails, observers say, more than her 18-month-old
civilian government will be in danger.
   Pakistan has spent more than half its 43 years under military
rule and concern is growing that the army will feel it necessary to
take over again.
   At center stage in the bloody drama are the Mohajirs, Moslem
Indians who moved into Pakistan during the 1947 partition that
ended British colonial rule of the subcontinent and made two
nations.
   Most of the Mohajirs settled in Karachi and Hyderabad, the two
largest cities of Sindh province. They were poor and landless, but
well-educated, and soon got the best jobs.
   Although they make up only 6 percent of Sindh's 20 million
people, they dominate the cities and control the labor unions of
the highly industrialized region.
   Native Sindhis were increasingly shut out politically and
economically, and their resentment led to street fighting.
   Violence increased in the early 1980s because of the
``Kalashnikov and heroin culture,'' a reference to the automatic
rifles that entered the country during the war in Afghanistan and
the growth of the drug trade.
   On May 27, now called ``Black Sunday,'' police tried to flush
out Mohajir militants holed up in the old walled section of
Hyderabad. The operation turned into a bloodbath that cost 180
lives and set off a five-day wave of terror in Karachi that took
nearly 200 more.
   Ms. Bhutto faced accusations from all quarters that she had done
too little to stop the bloodshed, and called out the army.
   Military officers agreed to arrest the troublemakers and seize
their weapons regardless of ethnic or political affiliations. They
insisted there be no interference from the provincial government,
which is led by the prime minister's party.
   Sources said the army also was pressing for military, not
civilian, courts to decide punishment.
   In 1958 and 1977, the military justified coups on grounds
politicians were corrupt and more interested in outmaneuvering each
other than serving Pakistan.
   Most observers agree a coup against Ms. Bhutto is unlikely.
Since taking office in December 1988, she has built good relations
with the army and its chief of staff, Gen. Mirza Aslam Beg.
   Many officers also believe ruling the country corrupted the army
and led to the involvement of some officers in the narcotics trade.
   ``People are asking me, `Why doesn't the army take over and save
us from slaughter?' But I say that is the job of the present
government,'' Beg said. ``We can control the situation in three
days, but that may not be a lasting solution. Martial law is not a
permanent solution.''
   If the violence does not abate in a few months, however, many
fear the army will have no choice.
   ``Even talking about martial law, given the abysmal track record
of military rule in Pakistan, is a poor reflection of the
disappointing performance of Ms. Bhutto's party, a disappointment
that seems to have shaken the confidence of even its most ardent
supporters,'' said political analyst Mushahid Hussain.
   Ms. Bhutto and the Pakistan People's Party blame the current
violence on the Mohajir Qami Movement, a small party that formerly
supported her government.
   Its leaders said her party treated them shabbily during the
10-month alliance and withdrew support last November, forcing a
no-confidence vote in Parliament that Ms. Bhutto barely defeated.
   Analysts, critics and supporters agree an understanding between
Ms. Bhutto and the Mohajir Qami is the only way to resolve the
crisis.
   That does not appear likely for the moment. The Mohajir Qami,
which is believed to have armed up to 30,000 members and sent them
underground, has shown no desire to talk.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0007 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 1121EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--Turkey-Quake     06-10 0067</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Turkey-Quake,0069</SECOND>
<HEAD>Quake Shakes Istanbul</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ISTANBUL, Turkey (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A moderate earthquake jolted this city
early Sunday morning, but no damage or injuries were reported.
   The semiofficial Anatolia news agency said the quake measured
4.6 on the Richter scale and struck at 2:36 p.m.
   The Richter scale guages the amount of energy released by a
quake, as measured by the ground motion recorded on a seismograph.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0008 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 1122EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--PapersBurned     06-10 0109</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Papers Burned,0109</SECOND>
<HEAD>Opposition Party Burns Newspapers</HEAD>
<DATELINE>KUALA LUMPUR, Malaysia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An opposition party that believes
its statements have been distorted by several newspapers protested
by burning copies of the papers in a bonfire, a news agency
reported Sunday.
   As papers published by the Utusan Melayu Group and the New
Straits Times Group burned, 2,000 members of the Pan Malaysian
Islamic Party shouted ``God is Great,'' then said prayers, the
official Bernama news agency said.
   The protest occurred Saturday in Alor Star, 240 miles northwest
of Kuala Lumpur. The two newspaper groups, which are owned by Prime
Minister Mahathir's governing party or its members, publish five
papers.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0009 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 1122EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--PapersClosed     06-10 0147</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Papers Closed,0149</SECOND>
<HEAD>Nigeria's Military Government Shuts Two More Newspapers</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LAGOS, Nigeria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The military government reportedly has
shut down two more newspapers in its crackdown on opposition
following an abortive coup.
   Employees of the two papers said state security agents arrived
at the Vanguard and Champion newspapers Saturday, ransacked
offices, seized documents and detained some editors and
administrative personnel.
   On Friday, President Ibrahim Babangida's government closed New
Breed magazine, which had published a letter written by one of the
alleged coup plotters who remains at large.
   Immediately after the April 22 coup attempt, authorities closed
several newspapers and detained several journalists. Some of the
reporters remain in detention without charge. Several lay leaders
of Christian organizations and university professors also have been
detained.
   The rebel troops who attempted the coup said they wanted to end
domination of the West African nation by Moslem northerners.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0010 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 1122EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--Defector'sDivorce     06-10 0160</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Defector's Divorce,0163</SECOND>
<HEAD>Court Denies Divorce for Defector from Taiwan</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A court has refused to grant a divorce to a
fighter pilot who defected from Taiwan last year, leaving his wife
and two children behind.
   Last week's edition of Youth Reference News, seen in Beijing on
Sunday, said an Intermediate People's Court in the northeastern
city of Shijiazhuang ruled that Lt. Col. Lin Xianshun and his wife,
Chen Xuezhen, did not qualify for a divorce because they had
married for love and had a good relationship.
   The decision, handed down May 23 and not previously reported,
apparently did not take into account the couple's unusual
separation.
   Lin crash-landed his F-5E jet fighter in a rice paddy in
southeastern China's Guangdong province on Feb. 11, 1989.
   Official mainland reports later said that Lin, then 35, wanted
to return to his family's ancestral home and was frustrated that
Taiwan's regulations do not allow soldiers to visit the mainland.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0011 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 1124EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-AnimalBill     06-10 0507</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Animal Bill,480</SECOND>
<HEAD>House Panel Considers Jail Terms for Attacks on Animal Research
Centers</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DIANE DUSTON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Animal rights protesters who attack farms or
research labs could spend up to three years in federal prison under
a bill being considered this week by the House Agriculture
Committee.
   ``I want to emphasize that this bill deals only with terrorist
acts,'' said Rep. Charles Stenholm, D-Texas, sponsor of the
measure. ``It brings the full weight of our laws against the
extremists who have gotten out of control.''
   The Farm Animal and Research Facilities Protection Act is
scheduled for a committee vote Thursday. Stenholm wants it included
in the 1990 farm bill.
   The measure applies to facilities or premises where an animal is
kept for food, agriculture, research, testing or education.
   It makes it a federal crime to:
   _Disrupt the activities of the premises.
   _Steal or damage property or animals.
   _Enter a facility with the intent to commit a violation.
   _Remain in a facility despite notice that entry was forbidden.
   Violators could be fined up to $10,000 and jailed for up to
three years, or both.
   Any person harmed by a violation may recover damages and court
costs.
   Stenholm's office released a list of 91 incidents between 1981
and last January, ranging from bomb threats and trespassing to
break-ins and arson, that were linked to groups associated with the
animal rights movement.
   Most were associated with the Animal Liberation Front, also
known as Band of Mercy or Animal Liberators, which often announces
its responsibility after various protest actions.
   ``No matter how good and righteous you think your cause is you
do not have the right to take the law into your own hands,'' said
Stenholm. ``Those who choose to disrupt lawful agricultural and
scientific research activities through violent means should face
legal sanctions that are commensurate with their actions.''
   Rep. Charles Rose, D-N.C., another member of the House
Agriculture Committee, has proposed an amendment to the Animal
Welfare Act that would set fines but no jail time for damage to
research facilities or farms.
   It also includes a provision that allows for temporary removal
of an animal from a research facility to document whether the
animal is being treated properly, according to existing law.
   If a person who has broken into a facility proves animals are
being mistreated, then the facility would have to reimburse the
person who committed the offenses for any court costs.
   Rose's bill also allows people to file lawsuits on behalf of
animals.
   Legislation similar to Stenholm's was approved by the Senate
last November. Under that bill, violators could be fined up to
$5,000 and jailed for up to one year, or both, unless a person is
harmed by the protest.
   In that case the penalty would be up to a $10,000 fine and 10
years in jail. If someone's life is put in jeopardy, those
responsible could be fined $25,000 and jailed for 20 years. Those
convicted would have to pay for any damages caused by the protest.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0012 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 1125EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p AM-LouisianaSenate     06-10 0626</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Louisiana Senate,600</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ex-Klan Leader Claims He's Moving Senate Debate to the Right</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KEVIN McGILL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BATON ROUGE, La. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Former Ku Klux Klan leader David Duke is
claiming credit for shifting debate to the right in the U.S. Senate
campaign here.
   Duke often lashes out at the media for focusing on his past as a
klansman and a neo-Nazi. But the publicity is helping him win
points in conservative Louisiana as he works to unseat three-term
Democratic Sen. J. Bennett Johnston.
   ``The overzealousness to attack me, what they've done is they've
made people aware of my issues,'' said Duke, who is running as a
Republican without the blessing of the state party's leadership.
   An April survey commissioned by Gannett News Service found
Johnston was supported by 44 percent of those questioned, Duke by
21 percent and state Sen. Ben Bagert, the GOP's official candidate,
8 percent. The survey, which had a 3.5 percentage point margin of
error, found 27 percent undecided.
   Democrat Willie Singleton, a black state representative from
Shreveport, is considering joining the race but has until July to
make up his mind.
   Louisiana's Oct. 6 open primary is a candidate free-for-all
without regard to party. If Johnson does not get 50 percent of the
vote, he could be forced into a runoff with the second-place
finisher in November.
   Johnston has urged Bagert to drop out of the Senate race to
reduce the likelihood of a runoff between himself and Duke. But
Bagert rejected that suggestion and told Johnson to ``stop
whining.''
   Bagert maintains Duke can't win because of the tremendous
negative image created by his past ties to neo-Nazis such as Ralph
Forbes, now a candidate for lieutenant governor in Arkansas.
   As recently as a year ago, Duke was selling Nazi literature out
of his legislative office _ clearing out his inventory, he said at
the time.
   Duke now runs an organization called the National Organization
for the Advancement of White People. He repeatedly says he has
broken ties with the klan and the Nazis and is now focusing on
equal rights for all.
   Duke was elected to the state House last year by campaigning
against taxes, against affirmative action, against minority
set-asides in government contracts and for welfare reform.
   Now he hopes to unseat Johnston by portraying the senator as too
liberal for Louisiana tastes _ a tack also taken by Bagert.
   Johnston accuses Bagert and Duke of running a
``Johnny-One-Note'' campaign that harps on Johnston's role in
helping defeat former President Reagan's nomination of Robert Bork
to the Supreme Court.
   Johnston said Duke's right-wing rhetoric ``has not affected my
issue orientation'' but that it ``certainly appears to have
affected Mr. Bagert's.''
   Johnston and Duke both point to a recent Bagert campaign
commercial in which Bagert pounds fist in hand and demands reforms
that would make the poor work for their welfare.
   ``People all over the state are greeting me saying that every
time they see his commercial it makes them think of me,'' a
grinning Duke said last week.
   Bagert bristles at the notion that he's copying Duke or that he
is a newcomer on the welfare reform bandwagon. He first introduced
welfare overhaul legislation as a House member in 1976, he said.
   His latest proposals have been overshadowed by a brouhaha
stirred up when Duke gained House passage of a bill last month to
outlaw affirmative action programs that award jobs, promotions and
scholarships on the basis of race.
   The vote enraged the Legislative Black Caucus, and Gov. Buddy
Roemer quickly promised to veto the bill if it got through the
Senate.
   Still, House passage brought more publicity to Duke and a
complaint from Bagert that the ex-klansman is getting free
publicity from the media.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0013 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 1135EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-CentralAsia     06-10 0932</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Central Asia,0968</SECOND>
<HEAD>Talk Grows in Central Asia of `Decolonization' by Soviets</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MORT ROSENBLUM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Special Correspondent</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TASHKENT, U.S.S.R. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A murderous land dispute among ethnic
cousins in Central Asia has shaken loose a word that generations of
Soviet leaders have rejected out of hand: decolonization.
   Since the 1920s, when Stalin redrew borders and declared Moslems
freed of backwardness, Moscow has considered the five Central Asian
republics as much a part of the union as mother Russia.
   It was heresy to call them colonies _ and outright blasphemy to
suggest that they might leave the union.
   But now, encouraged by new freedoms, Asians are returning to
their mosques, reviving long dormant traditions and, in their own
languages, speaking of themselves as colonized people.
   More and more, the question is arising whether a Soviet Union
fraught with crises elsewhere can satisfy, and pacify, an
increasingly restive region where a slight spark ignites explosion.
   Officially, little has changed. Local Communist Party
governments, still firmly in control, insist that Central Asia's
future lies within the Soviet Union. The Kremlin agrees.
   Apart from strategic minerals and rich agricultural land,
political imperatives suggest no Soviet government would lightly
relinquish its own territory.
   Pragmatic Asians realize that separating themselves from the
Soviet Union would be as complex as unweaving a Bukhara carpet. But
in a turbulent situation no one controls, and few understand,
Soviet leaders face hard choices they would rather not confront.
   Ethnic rioting between Uzbeks and Kirghizis _ set off by a
dispute over land _ brought thousands of troops into the Fergana
Valley, the most densely populated part of the country. Soldiers
sprayed gunfire at crowds.
   ``Moscow does not have enough troops, and it will not be able to
manage if anything really blows,'' said a respected Soviet
ethnographer who agreed to speak his mind if assured of anonymity.
   Central Asia stretches from the Caspian Sea to China, an area
half as big as the United States. Uzbekistan, with 19 million
inhabitants, is the third-most populous Soviet republic.
   Michael Rywkin, a New York professor raised in the ancient city
of Samarkand and author of ``Moscow's Muslim Challenge,'' put it
bluntly in a recent interview:
   ``There are pogroms against Russians. They've left villages and
now they're leaving the cities. Soviet leaders face the same
dilemma as Charles de Gaulle in Algeria, whether to just get out.''
   Russians began settling in Tashkent a century ago when czarist
troops secured most of the region. After the revolution, Soviet
professionals brought education, industry and health care.
   Despite official rhetoric about a single people, Europeans and
Asians have remained largely separate. A few Asian men have
European wives, but almost no Moslem women marry outsiders.
   Most Asians say their hostility is not toward the outsiders
themselves, but rather the stifling system that condemns them to an
alien style of life with few choices.
   Economists and sociologists acknowledge that, unless perestroika
brings significant and rapid improvement, a rising tide of jobless
youth will wash over the government's barriers against desperation.
   As more Russians leave, analysts say, industry and services will
suffer, making the problem worse.
   Young Asians, long silent in fear of reprisal, are speaking out
with growing vehemence.
   ``We don't want Communists or their damned system,'' said a
youth in Samarkand, distraught over impending military service.
``They should go peacefully, orderly. But Ukbekistan must be free.''
   Even party officials worry that the growing tension threatens
their traditional values.
   In Moscow, Bakhtiyur Khamidov, a senior member of the Uzbek
mission to the central government, shook his head sadly at the
riots pitting his people against Kirghizis.
   ``We have always been such a hospitable people; it is in our
blood,'' he said. ``You can imagine how bad conditions have gotten
for this to have happened.''
   Khamidov assures that the Communist Party is in control and has
an economic plan to overcome the crisis, but others, speaking
privately, are far less confident. Many see a widening gulf between
Moscow's vision of a seamless state and the realities of Central
Asia.
   The issue is less about politics than a choice between two
diametrically opposed ways of life.
   Since the days of the Silk Road, Central Asian Moslems have
lived as traders and farmers, shaping their lives around the Koran
and the rigors of life at the edge of a fiercely hot desert.
   The mosque outranks party headquarters. Lack of meat for guests
at a son's wedding feast is cause for lasting shame. Diluting their
language means turning their backs on 10 centuries of tradition.
   As Uzbeks and Kirghizis fought, Soviet Interior Minister Vadim
Bakatin denounced both sides as ``cave dwellers.'' To many Moslems,
that was yet another example of uncomprehending imperial hauteur.
   When Russians huddled in the forests, any Asian scholar will
remind visitors, Samarkand beamed civilization to the world.
   Rywkin argues that the Asian republics, historically ruled by
conquerors and local emirs, do not have the democratic traditions
to seek independence in the manner of the Baltic states.
   Rather than a process of negotiation, there will likely be
bubbling ferment that will boil over regularly.
   Edward Allworth, also a New York professor who writes on Central
Asia, agrees. ``If any charismatic figure emerges waving a green
(Islamic) flag, people will rally behind him,'' he said.
   His friend, Anvar Khadyrov, an Uzbek professor of philosophy at
Tashkent University, opposes any such nationalist fervor, but he is
a scholar who knows his people.
   ``Yes,'' he said, when asked whether Allworth was right. ``I am
afraid they would follow.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Mort Rosenblumm is roving AP special
correspondent based in Paris.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0014 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 1151EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-BudgetTalks     06-10 0645</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Budget Talks,620</SECOND>
<HEAD>Budget Negotiators Seek Spark to Move Talks Ahead</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ALAN FRAM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Democrats had made the point before. But at a
testy moment in last week's budget talks, Democratic Sen. Wyche
Fowler let the Bush administration hear it again, this time from a
different source.
   ``The problem is that the public is hearing one thing and seeing
another,'' the Georgia lawmaker read from a piece of paper as
administration officials listened.
   ``He is being told that all is well and happy, but you must pay
more taxes, you must sacrifice. Yet he sees his government failing
to sacrifice. He simply does not believe his government. ... It is
the failure of the administration to tell the people the truth.''
   Fowler was quoting George Bush, who as a Texas congressman took
to the House floor in 1968 to complain about a proposal by
Democratic President Lyndon B. Johnson to boost taxes and cut
spending.
   It's come to that in this spring's budget summit between the
White House and congressional leaders. Four weeks into the talks,
Democrats are still complaining it is Bush himself who must
convince a skeptical public that harsh steps are needed to battle
the gargantuan federal deficit.
   A lot of technical ground has been covered. But there is at
least another week to go of nuts and bolts descriptions of the
government's fiscal health chart before hard bargaining begins.
   ``So far, the animals have been snorting and pawing the earth,
taking stock of each other and the situation,'' said Rep. Bill
Frenzel, R-Minn., one of the negotiators. ``I don't know how much
more this war dance needs to go on, but obviously we need something
to precipitate decision-making.''
   One problem is nobody seems to know just what it will take to
get Democrats and Republicans trading offers about tax increases
and spending cuts in this election year.
   ``It's a political year, and some degree of paranoia exists over
who's going to move on what issues,'' says House Budget Committee
Chairman Leon Panetta, D-Calif.
   According to one pessimistic school of thought, the political
pressures are so great that nothing will be agreed to until
December, after the elections.
   A lack of a budget deal by then will trigger crippling spending
cuts under the Gramm-Rudman deficit reduction law, forcing Bush and
lawmakers to deal with the problem.
   ``It may well be that in order for Congress to get serious about
this problem, we're going to have to have'' the Gramm-Rudman cuts,
said Sen. Phil Gramm, R-Texas, another bargainer.
   Few negotiators say they agree with that scenario.
   ``You have available the option of waiting for some form of
crisis,'' said Richard Darman, the White House's budget director.
``The trouble with that is it's irresponsible.''
   There is no certainty, however, about how to avoid that crisis.
   Darman and another GOP negotiator, Sen. Pete Domenici of New
Mexico, want bargaining to commence in about a week. Frenzel wants
negotiators to set a deadline for completing the talks, preferably
by the end of June. They believe that with Congress in a short
election-year session, lawmakers will need a head start to enact
whatever package emerges from the talks.
   Democrats talk less about deadlines and more about the need to
lay the political groundwork for what could be $45 billion to $60
billion worth of spending cuts and tax increases.
   They insist that Bush has to prepare the public to make
sacrifices and persuade members of Congress to vote for unpopular
measures.
   And they say the president must present a new deficit-reduction
plan of his own, now that the administration says the budget he
introduced in January is outdated.
   ``There is certainly a consensus that no matter how slowly we're
moving, we're ahead of most of our colleagues and certainly the
public in realizing the size of this problem,'' said Fowler.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0015 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 1223EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-MiriamMakeba     06-10 0348</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Miriam Makeba,0357</SECOND>
<HEAD>After Three Deades of Exile, South African Singer Comes Home</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto JOH1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GREG MYRE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JOHANNESBURG, South Africa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   South African singer Miriam
Makeba, who won international acclaim during her 31 years in exile,
had an emotional homecoming on Sunday.
   Ms. Makeba, often called ``Mama Africa'' and ``the Empress of
African Song,'' left South Africa in 1959 and has lived since in
the United States, France, Guinea in West Africa and most recently
in Belgium.
   ``I'm very happy to be home,'' she told an airport news
conference. ``But I think I'll be even happier when I can come back
to sing before my people, where I'll not have to explain my songs
because they will understand.''
   Ms. Makeba, who said she would spend one to two weeks visiting
family and friends, did not plan to perform during her stay.
   She was greeted by a crowd of fans and friends including leading
South African musicians who joined her in singing ``God Bless
Africa,'' the anthem of the anti-apartheid movement.
   Ms. Makeba is best known for songs that emphasize traditional
African rhythms.
   Entertainer Steve Allen helped launch her career in the United
States and she often toured with singer Harry Belafonte during the
1960s. In 1987 she performed with singer Paul Simon on his
``Graceland'' concert tour.
   One of her several marriages was to political activist Stokely
Carmichael.
   While a resident of Guinea, she represented the country at the
United Nations. After she made a 1976 U.N. speech denouncing the
policy of apartheid, or racial segregation, South Africa's
government-run radio and television refused to broadcast her songs
until last year.
   Ms. Makeba tried to return to South Africa in 1960 for the
funeral of her mother. But her passport was revoked and she was not
allowed to enter the country.
   ``I never understood why I couldn't come home,'' Ms. Makeba
said. ``I never committed any crime.''
   Many long-exiled South Africans have been allowed to return to
the country in recent months as part of the reforms instituted by
President F.W. de Klerk.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0016 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 1246EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-SavingTrees     06-10 0537</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Saving Trees,530</SECOND>
<HEAD>New Federal Policy: Let 'Em Grow</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVID BRISCOE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Trees and other foliage should have the right
of way over highway billboards, the Bush administration is telling
states in a reversal of a 13-year-old federal policy.
   It's a message the advertising industry doesn't want to hear.
Environmentalists, on the other hand, are delighted.
   Since 1977, government policy has been to allow states or
advertisers themselves to chop down vegetation from public land to
improve the visibility of outdoor advertising.
   But the Federal Highway Administration, in a May 18 memo, told
its regional administrators that the agency needed to conform with
the Bush administration's new National Transportation Policy of
``minimizing the negative side effects'' of transportation on the
environment.
   ``It is Federal Highway Administration policy to be sensitive to
environmental concerns; therefore such vegetation clearance can no
longer be endorsed,'' the agency said.
   Since states maintain highway rights of way, the FHWA can't
impose policy on billboards.
   Barbara Orski, director of the FHWA right-of-way office, said in
an interview last week that regional administrators would work with
each state to change laws or rescind any agreements with the
industry.
   ``The Federal Highway Administration likes to do things in
cooperation with the states,'' Orski said. But, she added, ``Where
federal funds are used to procure rights of way, it is inconsistent
to allow people to cut trees. ... We're sending them a forceful
message consistent with the president's policy.''
   She said no highway departments had indicated opposition to the
new policy, but it is possible not all have had time to consider it.
   The advertising industry reacted swiftly.
   ``To allow the vegetation to grow to where it covers billboards
is the taking of property and cannot be done without
compensation,'' said Roland McElroy of the Outdoor Advertisers
Association of America.
   ``We oppose illegal cutting and are not opposed to control over
the cutting of vegetation,'' he said, but added that allowing
vegetation to grow indiscriminately could pose a distraction to
drivers straining to read ads or other signs.
   He said some billboard companies put up sprinkling systems to
help vegetation along highways and plant trees behind billboards.
   The association says Minnesota, North Dakota, Pennsylvania and
Tennessee have laws that allow clearance of trees and plants from
in front of billboards.
   Fourteen other states have agreements with the industry to allow
it: Alabama, California, Connecticut, Georgia, Kentucky, Louisiana,
Michigan, Mississippi, New Jersey, New Mexico, North Carolina,
South Carolina, Virginia and Wisconsin.
   Most other states prohibit the cutting or poisoning of trees to
help advertisers, and some outlaw highway billboards altogether.
   Environmentalists have called the tree-clearing practice
``legalized vandalism.''
   ``We're delighted that FHWA has reversed its 13-year-old policy
of permitting states to develop programs that favor billboards over
trees,'' said Edward T. McMahon, president of Scenic America, a
group that supports highway beautification and other environmental
causes.
   He said trees that could be saved by the new federal policy
range from 100-year-old eucalyptus in California to crabtrees in
North Carolina that have been the subject of public protests.
   Bills calling for a moratorium on new billboards on federal
interstates and other major highways have been introduced in the
Senate and House.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0017 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 1255EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Lebanon-Iran     06-10 0499</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lebanon-Iran,0520</SECOND>
<HEAD>Caviar and Calls to Martyrdom At Iranian Trade Fair</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DONNA ABU-NASR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BAALBEK, Lebanon (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In an odd mix of commercial boosterism
and Islamic solidarity, Iran staged a huge trade fair here Sunday
to show its support for Moslems fighting the Christians in
Lebanon's 15-year-old civil war.
   Among the wares on display were racy underwear to be worn under
women's all-concealing chadors and children's books praising bloody
Islamic martyrdom.
   An Iranian deputy minister of commerce, identified only as
Zaferian, said the event was designed to ``indicate the special
concern that officials in Iran feel for the Moslems of Lebanon.''
   Lebanon is the only country outside Iran where the late
Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini's brand of Shiite Moslem fundamentalism
has taken root. Although Lebanon's 1.2 million Shiites make up the
country's largest single sect, they have long languished at the
bottom of the social ladder.
   Iran backs Hezbollah, or Party of God, an extremist faction that
advocates the establishment of an Iran-style Islamic state in
Lebanon.
   The trade fair was staged in this ancient Roman-built city in
east Lebanon's Bekaa valley, which is Hezbollah's main stronghold.
Some 2,500 Iranian Islamic Revolutionary Guards are based here.
   The sprawling exhibition took up a seven-story building plus
surrounding empty lots. Zaferian said 180 companies took part.
   The event had many of the trappings of a standard commercial
gathering. ``We do export the best, try us,'' read one company's
English-language banner.
   Other items weren't quite the usual trade-fair fare, however.
The display by the Islamic Republic's cultural department, which
took up a whole floor, featured offerings such as a children's book
called ``The Footprints of Blood.''
   The book's narrator is a slain martyr's soul who invites
youngsters to take the glorious path of martyrdom for ``the
preservation of Islam.''
   Other goods included silk carpets with price tags in the
thousands of dollars and caviar at upwards of $100 a pound.
   Despite the strict Islamic dress code, there was a selection of
wedding gowns featured plunging necklines and off-the-shoulder
party dresses with prices from $200 to $600.
   ``We're not backward,'' a chador-clad Hezbollah woman said. ``We
also wear such dresses _ but under the chador.''
   A nearby stand diplayed lacy women's underwear in shocking pink
and purple.
   Under Islamic code, woman in the company of men other than their
husbands, brothers and fathers are to cover their hair and wear a
loose smock that fully covers the arms and legs.
   Iran's ambassador to Syria, Mohammad Hussein Akhtari, said
Moslem nations should trade among themselves so that ``we will not
have to extend our hands to the colonialists and the enemies of
Islam'' _ a refernce to Western powers.
   Iranian radicals oppose Iranian President Hashemi Rafsanjani's
efforts to mend ties with the West to attract badly needed foreign
investment and technology.
   In his speech, however, Zaferian praised Rafsanjani's $112
billion, five-year reconstruction plan. He said the merchandise on
display was ``a sample of the enormous success of this economic
policy.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0018 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 1257EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-CrownJewels     06-10 0438</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Crown Jewels,0451</SECOND>
<HEAD>British Crown Jewels Hidden in Lake in World War II, Newspaper
Says</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The most precious gems among Britain's crown
jewels were hidden in a lake at Windsor Castle during World War II
to keep them out of German hands if the country was invaded, a
newspaper reported Sunday.
   The Sunday Telegraph said the only people who knew of the hiding
place were King George VI, who chose it, and Sir Owen Morshead, his
librarian.
   The king, father of Queen Elizabeth II, died in 1952 and
Morshead in 1977.
   The newspaper said that in 1940, when a German invasion was
anticipated, the king ordered the royal jewelers to take the gems
from the Tower of London to Windsor Castle, about 20 miles west of
London.
   The king and Morshead then wrenched the most important gems out
of their settings with pliers and other tools provided by a
chauffeur, according to the newspaper.
   ``The gems, including the Koh-i-Noor diamond, were then wrapped
in cotton wool, placed in a tin and submerged in one of the lakes
at Windsor. There they remained until the defeat of Germany and for
a long time only the king and Sir Owen knew,'' wrote the
newspaper's anonymous columnist, Mandrake.
   The Koh-i-Noor is an Indian diamond of 108 carats presented to
Queen Victoria in 1849. Its name means Mountain of Light.
   The wartime hiding place of the jewels, which today are on
public display at the Tower of London, has always been a mystery in
Britain.
   But the Sunday Telegraph said it had discovered that the facts
were revealed in 1972 in a book that was never translated from
French _ a biography of the military leader Jean-Marie Lattre de
Tassigny by his widow, Simonne.
   The newspaper said it was told of the story by Lattre de
Tassigny's British aide, John Saint-Clair Smallwood, who said he
accompanied the general and his wife on a visit to Windsor in 1949
at Morshead's invitation. Smallwood said Morshead related the
secret to them as they gazed out of the castle windows onto the
grounds where there was a round pond.
   According to the newspaper, Smallwood related that Morshead said
the king told him the crown jewels represented ``the honors and the
kingdom of England'' and must not fall into German hands.
   The report did not say where the crown jewel settings were kept
during the war.
   Most of the crown jewels date from the restoration of the
monarchy after the death of Oliver Cromwell, who overthrew King
Charles I and died in 1658. Cromwell had the original crown jewels
sold or melted.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0019 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 1317EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-SpoletoFestival     06-10 0512</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Spoleto Festival,0531</SECOND>
<HEAD>Artsfest Closes With Record Box Office, Looking To 1991</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BRUCE SMITH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CHARLESTON, S.C. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A resounding box office bonanza helped
the 14th annual Spoleto Festival U.S.A. reassure the world that
this historic seaport battered by Hurricane Hugo less than a year
ago is back on its feet.
   ``It's been a difficult festival but absolutely worth the
effort,'' general manager Nigel Redden said. ``I think people will
be taking a message back home that Charleston is fine and it is
wonderful.''
   A Sunday night concert and fireworks display at Middleton Place
Plantation was to formally close the annual festival, which
included 110 performances ranging from grand opera to jazz to
avant-garde mutimedia events.
   More than $1.6 million in tickets had been sold as Spoleto
entered its final weekend. That topped the record of $1.46 million
set last year.
   The spector of Hurricane Hugo, which inflicted $5.9 billion
damage in September, helped promote the arts festival.
   ``The hurricane certainly did bring some people here,'' Redden
said. ``There were people who heard about Charleston and wanted to
find out how it was doing _ to express some solidarity, in a way.''
   The hurricane damaged festival offices and the auditorium where
major Spoleto events are staged. The city's historic district has
been largely renovated, but recovery in outlying areas has taken
longer.
   Highlights of the 17-day festival included performances of the
five-hour Wagner opera ``Parsifal.''
   It was directed by festival founder Gian Carlo Menotti. The
Pulitzer-prize winning composer also directed a reprise of last
year's hit, ``The Marriage of Figaro.''
   Another highlight was the premier of ``The Hydrogen Jukebox'' _
a collaboration between composer Philip Glass, poet Allen Ginsberg
and visual artist Jerome Sirlin.
   Spoleto also featured jazz and classical concerts, ballet and
drama.
   Glitches included conductor Leonard Bernstein canceling his
appearance at an opening concert gala because of a bout with
pneumonia. Actress Kitty Carlise Hart, chairman of the New York
State arts council, also took ill and could not deliver a speech
during opening ceremonies.
   The hype bolstered by Hugo helped draw record numbers of
reporters and critics, organizers said.
   Typically, critics disagreed about Spoleto's hits and misses.
   For example, The New York Times termed ``The Hydrogen Jukebox''
``if nothing else, a triumph of stage technology,'' but called
Glass' music ``bland'' and the Ginsberg's text ``so much verbal
sludge.''
   USA Today called it ``the festival's greatest hit'' and The
State newspaper in Columbia suggested it was ``a stunning work,
powered by the words of Ginsberg more than anything else.''
   With the so-called hurricane festival behind them, Spoleto
organizers are looking to next season _ the year Menotti turns 80.
   ``We are absolutely planning to celebrate his 80th birthday and
planning to do one of his operas if not more than one of his
operas,'' Redden said.
   Menotti, best known for his opera ``Amahl and the Night
Visitors,'' founded the South Carolina festival in 1977, two
decades after founding The Festival of Two Worlds in Spoleto,
Italy, in an effort to merge European and U.S. culture.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0020 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 1346EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p AM-CaliforniaGovernor     06-10 0679</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-California Governor,650</SECOND>
<HEAD>With AM-Women in Politics Bjt</HEAD>
<HEAD>Wilson Allows Feinstein Only Moments to Savor Victory</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DOUG WILLIS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SACRAMENTO, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Dianne Feinstein had just hours to
savor her victory in California's Democratic primary for governor
before Republican Pete Wilson had his first ad of the general
election campaign on TV.
   In the fight for the top prize of the 1990 elections, Wilson's
opening shot was a good-natured spot designed to leave voters
laughing by putting Feinstein's own words to work for her new rival.
   ``You're wonderful,'' Feinstein tells Wilson in a quote dredged
up from 1985.
   Feinstein found the commercial ``sort of amusing'' although the
quotation was taken out of context, said her spokeswoman, Dee Dee
Myers.
   Most observers expect the tenor of the campaign to turn meaner
quickly as Feinstein and Wilson, who differ little on major issues,
try to draw distinctions between one another.
   The battle for the California governor's mansion is at the top
of both parties' 1990 priority lists. Each wants to be holding the
power of the governor's office when the state's congressional
districts are redrawn next year. California could pick up six more
congressional seats as a result of the 1990 Census.
   Wilson, a two-term U.S. senator, faced only token opposition in
the GOP primary and emerged from last week's elections with $3.5
million in the bank. Feinstein, the former San Francisco mayor,
spent every dollar she raised plus $3 million she and her husband
loaned to her campaign in a hard-fought primary.
   She doesn't have any money now to counter Wilson's commercials,
but even Wilson acknowledges Feinstein has the undisputed advantage
in charisma.
   Feinstein's primary election campaign generated excitement in
part because she was bidding to become the first woman to win a
major-party nomination for governor in California.
   But she also was a more accomplished and dynamic speaker than
her primary opponent, state Attorney General John Van de Kamp, who
closely resembles Wilson in both appearance and personal mannerisms.
   Feinstein said she plans to make Wilson's fund-raising an issue,
describing him as the favorite candidate of ``the Republican big
cigars'' and special-interest political action committees. She
claims GOP fat cats pressured a reluctant Wilson to run for
governor just a few weeks after he won re-election to a second
Senate term in 1988.
   Wilson brushed off his opponent's criticisms.
   ``Yes, I confess, I enjoy an occasional cigar, but I don't think
it should become a campaign issue,'' he quipped. He added that none
of his supporters could compare with Feinstein's wealthy investment
banker husband, Richard Blum, whom he described as ``the biggest
cigar'' in the race.
   Similarly, Wilson brushed off Feinstein's assertion that he was
a reluctant candidate, persuaded to run because he was the only one
who could keep the governor's office in GOP hands when Gov. George
Deukmejian retires.
   ``What hurts my feelings is that she doesn't remember my prior
efforts and how long I've wanted to be governor,'' said Wilson, who
finished fourth in a 1978 GOP gubernatorial primary.
   ``My campaign that year was a haven for people who hate
crowds,'' he joked.
   California has had few races in recent years in which the
major-party candidates started the race as close together on the
issues.
   Wilson is a moderate Republican with high ratings from
environmentalists and who is pro-choice on abortion. Feinstein is a
moderate Democrat who supports the death penalty and is viewed by
liberals as being too close to big business interests.
   Although Wilson is pro-choice, Feinstein has been criticizing
his Senate votes on abortion funding. She effectively used the
abortion issue in the primary against Van de Kamp, who also was
pro-choice, declaring that only a pro-choice woman can be trusted
by women to never compromise on abortion rights.
   The only independent poll so far on the race, taken before the
primary last Tuesday, gave Wilson a lead of 7 percentage points.
But that was conducted while Feinstein and Van de Kamp were
pounding each other and Wilson was coasting to a primary-election
victory over three political unknowns.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0021 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 1351EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Canada-MeechLake     06-10 0638</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Canada-Meech Lake,0660</SECOND>
<HEAD>Canadian Constitutional Accord Faces One Last Stumbling Block</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JEFFREY ULBRICH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TORONTO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The action in French-speaking Quebec's fight for
special status shifted Sunday to the province of Newfoundland,
which ultimately will decide the fate of an accord recognizing
Quebec's special character.
   Canada's provincial leaders on Saturday night signed a
constitutional accord on the issue, a clear victory for Quebec
Premier Robert Bourassa.
   But Newfoundland Premier Clyde Wells said he was angry both
about the secretive nature of the seven days of grueling
negotiations in Ottawa and the outcome. He said he signed the
agreement against his convictions, because he did not want to be
solely responsible for killing it.
   Wells said he would submit the accord to his Cabinet and
majority party in Newfoundland and they will decide whether to
submit it directly to the legislature or call a referendum.
   The proposed constitutional amendment is aimed at winning
Quebec's endorsement of the 1982 Canadian constitution. Quebec,
which is home to a quarter of Canada's 26 million people, said the
1982 document did not take into account the province's special
French nature.
   When first signed in 1987, the leaders imposed a three-year
deadline for ratification of the Meech Lake agreement by the
legislatures of all 10 provinces. That was accomplished in eight
provinces.
   But elections brought new governments to Manitoba and New
Brunswick, which subsequently did not ratify the accord, and
Newfoundland, which withdrew its ratification.
   Those three provinces have until June 23 to push the accord
through their legislatures, or the deal dies.
   Premier Frank McKenna of New Brunswick promised his province's
endorsement. Premier Gary Filmon of Manitoba and the opposition
party leaders with whom his minority government must deal have said
they will rush the proposal through mandatory public hearings and
on to the legislature.
   That leaves Newfoundland as the main potential stumbling block.
On Saturday night, Wells urged Newfoundlanders _ if they vote on
the agreement _ to be generous in their consideration of Quebec's
position.
   ``But don't give up your right to make the decision on the basis
of conscience,'' he said.
   He also had a word of admonition for Quebec.
   ``Having recognized that Quebec is a distinct society, I say to
my friends in Quebec: I believe it is the responsibility of all the
citizens of Quebec to place Canada first and recognize that, like
all of the other provinces, Quebec is second,'' he said.
   The constitutional amendment would have no immediate practical
effect but would oblige the Supreme Court to consider the
province's distinctiveness when considering specific laws under
challenge. It is also a symbol of enormous significance to
French-speaking Quebecers.
   Bourassa had steadfastly resisted efforts to change the clause
in the agreement declaring Quebec a ``distinct society.''
   ``English Canada has finally recognized and accepted us for what
we are,'' he said Saturday night. ``It was a great battle, but the
stakes were worth it.''
   Quebec leaders did not specifically say the province would
secede if the accord is not approved, but nationalism is on the
rise in Quebec and there is a growing sentiment for separation of
some sort.
   The accord is the same as the one signed by Prime Minister Brian
Mulroney and the 10 provincial premiers at Meech Lake, near Ottawa,
in 1987. This time, however, the document is accompanied by a
non-binding letter of understanding covering several contentious
issues.
   ``This is a happy day for Canada,'' a beaming Mulroney said
Saturday evening. ``The agreement before us will reintegrate Quebec
into the Canadian constitutional family.''
   The accord also includes a new constitutional amending formula,
closely tied to a widespread desire for reform of the national
Senate. In addition, it expands the provinces' powers to opt out of
some federal-provincial spending programs and covers Supreme Court
nominations, immigration and constitutional conferences.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0022 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 1558EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People SUB a0670 06-10 0168</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People, SUB, a0670,0171</SECOND>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS first item to CORRECT spelling of Shepard in last graf</NOTE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Actress Kate Jackson has quietly left Los
Angeles for a farm in Virginia and put her Benedict Canyon home up
for sale, it was reported Sunday.
   Jackson, a native of Birmingham, Ala., moved to Keswick, south
of Charlottesville, Va., said the Los Angeles Times, quoting
unidentified sources.
   Jackson has starred in the television series ``Charlie's
Angels'' and ``Scarecrow and Mrs. King.''
   Last September, she announced she was ``recovering nicely'' from
a modified mastectomy she had undergone two weeks earlier. Since
then she has filmed the television movie ``The Stranger Within.''
   The hillside Benedict Canyon home can be reached by three
flights of stairs or a cable car, and features four bedrooms and
six baths. Jackson bought the 1.5 acre property in 1983 for
$485,000. The asking price now is more than $2.3 million.
   Actress Jessica Lange and actor-playwright Sam Shepard also make
their home near Charlottesville, Va.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0023 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 1709EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Czechoslovakia-Results     06-10 0244</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Czechoslovakia-Results,0267</SECOND>
<HEAD>Official Results From Czechoslovakian Election</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Czechoslovakia, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PRAGUE, Czechoslovakia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the results of the
Czechoslovak election announced Sunday by state television. Each
party name is followed by its percentage of the vote total and its
preliminary seat allocation.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>___</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   For House of the People, a 150-seat chamber of the bicameral
federal parliament which is ivided into 101 seats for Czechs and 49
for Slovaks:
   Overall:
   Civic Forum and Public Against Violence _ 46.6 percent, 87 seats
   Communists _ 13.6 percent, 24 seats
   Christian Democratic Union _ 12 percent, 20 seats
   Moravia-Silesian Society _ 5.4 percent, 9 seats
   Slovak National Party _ 3.5 percent, 6 seats
   Coexistence (minority party) _ 2.8 percent, 4 seats
</TEXT>
<HEAD>___</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   For the House of the Nations, which is divided into two equal
75-seat parts, one for Czechs and one for Slovaks:
   Overall:
   Civic Forum and Public Against Violence _ 45.9 percent, 82 seats
   Communists _ 13.7 percent, 24 seats
   Christian Democratic Union _ 11.3 percent, 20 seats
   Slovak National Party _ 3.6 percent, 9 seats
   Moravian-Silesian Party _ 6.2 percent, 8 seats
   Coexistence _ 2.7 percent, 7 seats
</TEXT>
<HEAD>___</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   The overall totals are combined results from the Czech and
Slovak republics. A 5 percent minimum vote was required in one of
the two republics to get seats. The Moravia-Silesian Society,
Slovak National Party and Coexistance, while finishing with less
than 5 percent nationwide, surpassed that mark in either of the
country's two republics.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0024 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 1613EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Brazil-Economy     06-10 0490</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brazil-Economy,0507</SECOND>
<HEAD>RETRANSMITTING a0685 to fix computer garble in slugline</HEAD>
<HEAD>Economy Minister: Court Decision Could Lead to New Austerity</HEAD>
<DATELINE>RIO DE JANEIRO, Brazil (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The economy minister said the
government might impose new austerity measures following a Supreme
Court decision suspending a presidential decree that would have
blocked wage increases.
   The court ruling last Wednesday was a sharp blow to the
government's anti-inflation program, begun in March to bring down
annual inflation of almost 5,000 percent.
   A cornerstone of that plan was a presidential decree restricting
the power of regional labor courts to award large wage increases in
worker-management disputes.
   Congress, which must approve presidential decrees, voted down
the measure on May 31. But last week President Fernando Collor de
Mello reintroduced the decree.
   The Supreme Court then voted 9-0 to suspend the measure for 30
days. In a month the court will rule on whether, according to the
constitution, the government can reissue a decree already rejected
by Congress.
   However, the suspension vote was seen as a sign the court would
rule against the government.
   As a result of the suspension, local labor courts can award wage
settlements as they see fit.
   On Thursday, the labor court in Sao Paulo granted 10,500 port
workers a 30 percent wage increase. In the same city, Brazil's
largest, 12,500 metal workers are striking for a 166 percent raise.
   But Economy Minister Zelia Cardoso de Mello told the Folha de
Sao Paulo newspaper Saturday the government will have to implement
recessionary measures if high salary increases are granted and then
passed on in higher prices.
   She did not say what those measures might include.
   Also in the article, Cardoso de Mello admitted for the first
time that the cost of living had increased, but denied workers had
suffered substantial wage losses to inflation.
   ``There is a slight inflationary tendency but it is dropping,''
she said.
   The economy minister told businessmen to ``resist, resist,
resist'' demands for pay raises from workers, saying increases
would start a new inflationary spiral.
   Inflation has dropped sharply since Collor de Mello launched his
package of emergency economic measures on March 16, the day after
he took office. The measures included freezing all bank deposits of
more than $1,200 for 18 months.
   In recent weeks, however, there have been signs of renewed
inflation.
   The Institute Foundation of Economic Research reported last week
that the cost of living in Sao Paulo, a city of 14 million, rose by
8.5 percent in May. A survey published Saturday by the Folha de Sao
Paulo daily showed food prices rose by 6.4 percent in the first
week of June alone.
   Thousands of workers have gone on strike in recent weeks,
seeking to make up losses to inflation.
   Alexandre Barros, a political consultant, said Sunday that
inflation would probably be 10 percent to 13 percent in June. He
said several major banks were working with projections of 20
percent inflation for August.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0025 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 1752EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-CivilWarShipwreck 1stLd-Writethru a0651 06-10 0649</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Civil War Shipwreck, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0651,600</SECOND>
<HEAD>New Photographs of Monitor Wreckage Expected Soon</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: Subs 12th graf, ``The best xxx to CORRECT spelling of Keeney,
conforming 2nd reference to cq first reference</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By JEFF BARKER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Civil War buffs may soon have clearer pictures
of the Union ship Monitor, which sank in a gale off the North
Carolina coast 128 years ago after its celebrated battle with the
Confederate ship Merrimack.
   For the first time in 11 years, the government is allowing an
undersea photographer to dive to the wreck 16 miles off Cape
Hatteras.
   Photographer and author Rod Farb of Cedar Grove, N.C., arrived
at the site with a film crew last week, beating out a Philadelphia
rival seeking to become the first to dive to wreck since French
explorer Jacques Cousteau did it in 1979.
   Cousteau's expedition was hampered by bad weather and poor
visibility, and little or no usable footage was produced.
   Government scientists disclosed in interviews last week that
portions of the ship's hull have collapsed, but that the wreck is
``stable.'' Some scuba divers had expressed fears that the wreck
was in danger of collapsing.
   The wreck of the Monitor was discovered by researchers in 1973.
The Merrimack, renamed the Virginia, was destroyed by its crew to
keep it from being captured by the Union.
   The National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, which is
responsible for safeguarding the wreckage, said Farb was blessed
with good conditions when he and his crew made their first dive.
   NOAA refused to allow private Monitor expeditions after
Cousteau's dive, saying the 220-foot depth posed ``a serious and
unreasonable risk'' that its own divers would not take. The
concerns were based on tricky currents, and the knowledge that at
certain depths nitrogen in the breathing air can impede divers'
motor skills.
   The agency reversed its position after one of its administrative
law judges ruled last November that it had exaggerated the nitrogen
problem. ``A significant number of trained scuba divers''
frequently penetrate to 220 feet, the law judge said.
   Before permitting Farb's dive, NOAA researchers disclosed Friday
that they descended to the wreck in a submarine on June 1 and 2 to
make a ``visual record'' to ensure that artifacts are not tampered
with.
   Tim Keeney, NOAA director of ocean and coastal resources, said a
10-foot tiger shark was patrolling the wreck.
   ``The best word to describe the condition is that we believe
it's stable,'' Keeney said of the ship. ``The hull of the vessel is
not made of thick metal and there are parts that have caved in.
However, there is armor plating surrounding the vessel, and that is
almost totally intact on the port side.''
   Irv Garrison, an NOAA marine archaeologist who was on the
submarine, said the Monitor is ``pretty beat up,'' even for the 128
years it has spent at the bottom of the sea.
   ``Time is one thing,'' Garrison said. ``But she's also right in
the area of a shipping lane, and every destroyer that went by may
have dropped a load on her. She might have been depth-charged,
which would be an ironic fate for an old Civil War boat.''
   In the race to photograph the wreck, Farb beat out Gary Gentile,
a Philadelphia scuba diver who filed 11 permit applications and
wrote more than 50 letters to NOAA since 1984.
   Gentile actually won a permit first from the agency, but decided
to wait until the weather improved at the end of June to make the
dives. Peter Hess, Gentile's attorney, said his client thought he
had assurance from Farb that Gentile could go first.
   Gentile still plans to photograph the site in several weeks, but
Hess said it won't be the same. ``Do you remember the second guy to
cross the Atlantic? I feel like he's robbed us of the fruits of our
victory,'' Hess said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0026 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 1630EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Mandela 1stLd-Writethru   06-10 0625</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mandela, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0659,0639</SECOND>
<HEAD>American Jewish Leaders Praise Mandela's Views on Israel</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 4 grafs to UPDATE with Mandela departure without
commenting to reporters.; pickup 4th graf pvs, `Several U.S....'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By CLARE NULLIS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>GENEVA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   U.S. Jewish leaders who met with Nelson Mandela on
Sunday praised the black nationalist for recognizing Israel's right
to exist and said he should be warmly welcomed when he visits the
United States.
   The Jewish leaders said their meeting with Mandela exceeded
their ``fondest expectations,'' even though they said he called for
direct talks between Israel and the PLO and urged Israel to
surrender the occupied territories.
   Henry Siegman, executive director of the American Jewish
Congress, told journalists after the 2{ hour meeting that Mandela
said his African National Congress ``accepts unequivocally the
existence of the state of Israel, not only de facto but also its
legal right to exist ... within secure borders.''
   There was no immediate comment from Mandela. Officials said he
left on a Swissair flight for Frankfurt, West Germany.
   Several U.S. Jewish groups recently said they would protest
Mandela's visit to the United States because he compared the
struggle of Palestinians to that of black South Africans and
publicly embraced PLO chairman Yasser Arafat.
   The Jewish delegation made a special trip to Geneva to seek
clarification of Mandela's position on Israel before his visit to
the United States.
   Siegman said the meeting, which lasted 90 minutes longer than
expected, put an end to the concern over Mandela's positions, even
though the Jewish delegation disagreed with his views on talks
between Israel and the PLO.
   Siegman said the ANC deputy president criticized the Israeli
government's treatment of Palestinians and called on Jeruslaem to
hold direct talks with the Palestinian Liberation Organization to
settle the 30-month-old Palestinian uprising in the territories
occupied by Israel.
   Speaking at a news conference, Siegman quoted Mandela as saying
that Israel's borders should not encompass the Golan Heights, the
Gaza Strip and the West Bank, which were captured by Israel in the
1967 Middle East War.
   Mandela's views are certain to be unpopular with the new
right-wing government now being formed in Israel. It opposes any
territorial concessions to the Palestinians and favors pursuing a
peace plan that would give only limited autonomy to the 1.7 million
Palestinians in the occupied lands.
   Nevertheless, Siegman, who coordinated the visit of the Jewish
leaders to Geneva, said the Jewish community should ``join actively
and vigorously in extending a warm welcome'' to Mandela during his
10-day U.S. visit.
   He said Mandela, who arrives in the United States on June 20,
said he would ``welcome'' an opportunity to visit Israel if invited
by the government.
   Siegman said Mandela was ``extraordinarily forthcoming and
enthusiastic'' at the private meeting, held at a secret location.
ANC representatives could not immediately be contacted for comment.
   ``I will probably raise my voice and proclaim he (Mandela) is a
friend,'' said Abraham Foxman, national director of the
Anti-Defamation League of B'nai B'rith. ``The meeting exceeded our
fondest expectations. No Jewish organization should have any
reservations about ... the visit.''
   Al Vorspan, senior vice president of the Union of American
Hebrew Congregations, said Mandela's visit should be a ``real
celebration'' of his freedom after 27 years in prison. Mandela was
freed from prison as part of South African President F.W. de
Klerk's reform program.
   The 71-year-old ANC leader was in Switzerland as part of a
six-week tour of Europe and North America to press the West to
maintain sanctions against South Africa and its system of racial
segregation.
   The American Jewish Congress, National Jewish Community
Relations Advisory Council, American Jewish Committee,
Anti-Defamation League of B'nai B'rith and Union of American Hebrew
Congregations were represented at the meeting.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0027 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 1634EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-High-TechPizza Bjt   06-10 0485</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-High-Tech Pizza, Bjt,0498</SECOND>
<HEAD>High-Tech Pizza Pie In the Sky</HEAD>
<HEAD>Laserphoto Staffing</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By VERENA DOBNIK</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Pizza makers are slinging the high-tech pie of
the 1990s across America _ nitrogen-frozen, credit-card ordered via
satellite and with pineapple and bacon on top.
   Forget pepperoni and mushrooms with extra cheese. Make it
spinach, duck, goat cheese and cauliflower _ in California, that is.
   The state-of-the-art pizza methods _ all already in use _ were
touted over the weekend at the National Pizza and Fast Food Show in
Manhattan, where the American version of the Italian dish was
introduced in 1895.
   In Albuquerque, N.M., drive-up dining is a pizza order made
through a car window into a TV monitor at Nunzio's and, 60 seconds
later, a pie down a pneumatic chute.
   The pizza of the next decade will not only fill the ovens of
America, but its computers, too: from Japan, a computer for the
lazy diner that takes home-delivery orders for far-out pizza
fantasies. It tells the cook to sprinkle 2.85 ounces of cheese on
the pepperoni and mushrooms _ but only 2.62 ounces, if there also
are olives and onions and ....
   On the U.S.-designed, Japanese-made TEC computer, an employee
can punch purple, green and orange keys for toppings, desired
thickness, and instantly-produced directions to the address of the
caller.
   For the personal touch, the pizza computer also will deliver a
record of the customer's last order to the employee, who can ask,
``How did you enjoy your pineapple-and-Canadian-bacon pie?''
   But forget ordering six toppings; this computer balks at more
than five.
   Meanwhile, at the entrance to the parlor, the specials of the
day are mouthed by a robot at the door.
   Nay-sayers, however, are nibbling away at the idea of
quick-baked, mass market munching.
   ``There's a re-emergence of upscale, deep-pan pizza with varied
toppings,'' said Charlie Bowen, director of sales and marketing for
Lucks, a Seattle-based oven manufacturer. ``The pizza nuked in two
seconds is not what people are looking for.''
   The traditional stainless-steel oven will take pizza into the
next millennium, said Bowen, rather than the newest conveyor-belt
oven baking 70 pizzas per hour, or one that cooks with circulating
heat.
   For the cash-poor, credit-card rich _ and hungry on the road _
it's a pizza pie in the sky: Indesys, Inc. of Sunnyvale, Calif., is
supplying the nation's pizza vendors with rooftop dishes and
electronic boxes that beam a client's card code to a satellite.
   The satellite relays the signal for a check of the credit card
number to clear the prospective pizza eater,
   And, from Murray Hill, N.J., Airco uses liquid nitrogen to chill
out the forgetful pizza lover who otherwise might reach into the
freezer past a pizza's prime.
   To quick freeze a pie, liquid nitrogen at minus 320 degrees is
sprayed on a pizza for several minutes, said Bill Bartley, a
company engineer.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0028 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 1656EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Soviep-Unrest(1spLd-Writethru(a0656     06-10 0678</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviep-Unrest( 1sp Ld-Writethru( a0656,0296</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mass Rallies Broken up in Kirghizia; Death Toll Now 115</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: New thruout to UPDATE death toll, TV footage; No pickup.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By BRIAN FRIEDMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Police broke up attempts to organize nationalistic
rallies Sunday in the Central Asian republic of Kirghizia after a
week of ethnic clashes that have left 115 people dead, officials
said.
   The border city of Osh in western Kirghizia, where fighting
between ethnic Kirghiz and Uzbeks broke out last weekend, was
reported calm Sunday. At issue was the allocation of land for
housing in the densely populated, poor region.
   The ethnic violence was only the latest to confront Soviet
President Mikhail S. Gorbachev. Nationalities in several republics
have taken advantage of Gorbachev's reforms to vent frustrations
over political and economic woes.
   In Osh, armored personnel carriers sat at each intersection and
Interior Ministry troops patrolled the streets, said Rauf Duseyev,
duty officer at the Osh Communist Party offices.
   But unrest continued Saturday in nearby regions, especially in
Uzgen, which is predominantly Uzbek, Soviet TV reported Sunday
night.
   In Frunze, the capital of Kirghizia and 195 miles north of Osh,
students trying to organize rallies in the capital's main square
were turned back by Interior Ministry troops and police, said Ivan
Pavlov, a party official.
   Rallies in Frunze last week turned into demonstrations against
the republic's leaders. There were also calls for residents to join
the battle against the Uzbek population in Osh.
   Early Sunday, officials from the Communist Party and the
government visited student and worker dormitories to talk them out
of holding the rallies, Pavlov said from Frunze.
   Armored personnel carriers rolled along the main streets of
Frunze in districts where trouble had broken out earlier, and all
was quiet, he said.
   Overnight in Frunze, 11 students threw stones at a police patrol
from a dormitory window and were beaten by the truncheon-wielding
officers, Pavlov said. There were no serious injuries, and no one
was detained in the incident, he said.
   Since the Kirghiz-Uzbek unrest began on June 2, 115 people have
died, 468 have been wounded, the Soviet television newscast
``Vremya'' reported Sunday night.
   The Soviet army newspaper Red Star said about 500 houses have
been burned down. It also said 512 people were arrested, including
47 for curfew violations and 11 for possession of firearms.
   Rioting flared in Osh, a 3,000-year-old city of 210,000 people,
when Uzbeks, one-third of the population, discovered that Kirghiz
were being given parcels of land for housing. Housing is critically
short in the republic.
   The fighting between the Sunni Moslem groups spread to districts
around Osh, and thousands of troops were sent in to reinforce local
police.
   Soviet troops sealed off the border to prevent thousands of
Uzbeks from crossing into Kirghizia to join the battle, and curfews
were imposed in the region, including Osh, Frunze and border areas
inside Uzbekistan.
   Soviet and local officials have appealed repeatedly for the
residents of both republics to remain calm. In the district of
Nauket, near Osh, elders of the Uzbek and Kirghiz communities met
over the weekend to ask youths to cool their tempers, Komsomolskaya
Pravda reported.
   Monday was declared a day of mourning in Osh.
   Although public transportation resumed in Osh over the weekend,
shooting was reported in the suburbs, Komsomoloskaya Pravda
reported.
   Footage of burned-out shells of homes and charred autos was
shown on the newscast. Yet, it also featured Kirghiz and Uzbek
residents of Osh discussing the situation together, in an apparent
effort to portray instigators of the violence as extremists.
   In the Kirghiz town of Uzgen, 35 miles outside Osh, shooting and
arson attacks continued Saturday, the newspaper said. Some of the
worst bloodshed has occurred in the Uzgen district, where
two-thirds of the deaths were reported.
   Red Star said an Interior Ministry officer was shot to death at
a local post in the Osh region. It said it believed bands of
citizens who had obtained police uniforms and guns were roaming the
region and firing at civilian targets to provoke the population.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0029 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 1701EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Soviet-Thatcher 2ndLd-Writethru   06-10 0722</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Thatcher, 2nd Ld-Writethru,a0683,0741</SECOND>
<HEAD>RETRANSMITTING a0695 to fix computer garble in lede</HEAD>
<HEAD>Armenians Mob Thatcher on Visit to Earthquake Zone</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 7 grafs to UPDATE with Thatcher returning to
London, details of Leninakan visit; pickup 7th graf pvs, `Local
officials...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By MAUREEN JOHNSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LENINAKAN, U.S.S.R. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Crowds of Armenians broke through
police lines and surrounded British Prime Minister Margaret
Thatcher when she arrived Sunday to open a new British-built school
in this earthquake-devastated city.
   Tens of thousands of people lined the route of the British prime
minister's motorcade to the school, in a section of Leninakan wiped
out in the December 1988 disaster that claimed an estimated 25,000
lives in northern Armenia.
   Some people stood on piles of rubble to see her.
   Mrs. Thatcher returned to London late Sunday evening after a
four-day visit to the Soviet Union largely intended as a gesture of
support for President Mikhail S. Gorbachev, with whom she met
Friday in Moscow.
   Plans for an afternoon walking tour and a wreath-laying ceremony
in Leninakan were canceled after worried officials said they could
not guarantee they could control an ebullient crowd estimated at
100,000, packed into the main square.
   As a compromise, she rode in the front seat of a bus to see
shanties, rubble and half-finished buildings in the city. Apartment
blocks ripped apart in the earthquake gaped open and piles of
shattered concrete and twisted metal, pushed back by boulders,
surrounded the shanties.
   The metal-frame, single-story Lord Byron School, built to
accommodate 800 children, is on the site where the earthquake
virtually flattened a previous school. Of the city's 37 schools, 31
were destroyed by the quake.
   Local officials said that some people who left the city after
the earthquake are moving back to Leninakan to enroll their
children in the new school.
   Mrs. Thatcher stepped from her limousine when she reached the
school, but was forced back into the car as the crowd broke through
shaky police lines and surged around her. The limousine then edged
to the deserted back of the $7 million school, named after the 18th
century English poet.
   Once inside, Mrs. Thatcher talked to a group of 4- and
5-year-olds orphaned by the quake. ``Never forget what you learn
here, it will last you all your life,'' she told them.
   In opening the school, Mrs. Thatcher said:``People all over the
world joined in relief work, moved by the belief that what you were
suffering was more than you could bear.''
   ``The horror has made a very deep impression on people through
the world ... television brought into our homes pictures of
devastation and suffering almost beyond comprehension,'' she said.
   Children gathered outside the school tossed red, orange and
white carnations at her and shouted: ``We love you!''
   Mrs. Thatcher's husband, Denis, and Kenneth Baker, Britian's
education secretary at the time of the quake, had to leave their
cars and struggle through crowds for more than 500 yards to reach
the school.
   In the blazing Transcaucasian sun, people stood on roofs of
surrounding shanties, holding banners demanding control of the
Nagorno-Karabakh region, center of the bloody dispute between
Armenia and neighboring Azerbaijan.
   Nagorno-Karabakh is predominantly ethnic Armenian, but belongs
to Azerbaijan. Several hundred people have been killed in the
dispute over the area, and thousands have been forced to flee their
homes in violence that erupted in February 1988.
   Leninakan, a city in northwestern Armenia near the
Soviet-Turkish border, was severely damaged by the earthquake. An
estimated 16,000 people died and all but about 300 of its buildings
were destroyed.
   The city had a population of about 226,000 before the
earthquake. About 108,000 people now live here but local officials
said former residents are slowing drifting back.
   Efforts to rebuild Leninakan have been slowed by a sporadic
economic blockade from Azerbaijan. Materials for the Lord Byron
school were sent through Soviet Georgia, to the north of Armenia.
   ``We may stay homeless, but we will not leave Karabakh alone,''
said one banner displayed for Mrs. Thatcher. ``Red Army _ hands off
Karabakh,'' read another.
   Hundreds of people hung out the windows of partly built four- or
five-story apartment buildings near the school.
   As Mrs. Thatcher's motorcade tried to leave the school, at one
point it was forced to halt completely, but the prime minister
appeared unconcerned.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0030 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 1848EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Mandela-CIA     06-10 0403</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mandela-CIA,0415</SECOND>
<HEAD>Source: CIA Tip Led to Mandela's Arrest in 1962</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ATLANTA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A CIA tip to South African intelligence agents
led to the 1962 arrest of anti-apartheid leader Nelson Mandela, who
remained imprisoned until this year, according to a report
published Sunday.
   The CIA had a ``deep cover'' agent in the Durban, South Africa,
branch of Mandela's African National Congress, Cox News Service
reported. Mandela, who had gone underground, was arrested on Aug.
5, 1962 while trying to leave Durban after secretly attending a
dinner party there.
   Mark Mansfield, a CIA spokesman in Washington, said Sunday that
agency policy ruled out any official comment on the allegations.
   Edward Ndlovo, a member of the ANC delegation in Geneva,
Switzerland, dismissed the report, noting that CIA ties to the
Mandela arrest have been rumored for years.
   ``That's an old, old story. I'm sure the press must have dug it
up from newspaper cuttings from about five years ago,'' Ndlovo said.
   The report quoted an unidentified former U.S. official as saying
that Paul Eckel, then a senior CIA operative, had told him within
hours of Mandela's arrest that the capture was ``one of our
greatest coups.''
   The former official said Eckel told him: ``We have turned
Mandela over to the South African security branch. We gave them
every detail, what he would be wearing, the time of day, just where
he would be. They have picked him up.''
   Eckel, who retired about 10 years ago, died in 1986.
   Ndlovo said that when the allegations first surfaced, the ANC
did not pay any attention to them. ``We just disregarded it. It's
neither here nor there.''
   The ANC had been a legal, peaceful organization for 48 years
when it was outlawed in 1960. Mandela went into hiding and helped
launch a sabotage campaign a year later.
   He was convicted of leaving South Africa illegally, then tried
in 1964 along with other ANC leaders and convicted of sabotage and
plotting to overthrow the government. He was freed in February.
   The report said the CIA's concern over Mandela arose from the
belief that his activities against the South African government
could harm U.S. interests. The two nations had signed a military
agreement, and South Africa also was providing uranium to the
United States.
   The late CIA Director William Casey in 1986 denied published
reports that the United States has given South Africa intelligence
on black nationalist groups.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0031 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 1850EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Kuwait-Elections     06-10 0502</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Kuwait-Elections,0521</SECOND>
<HEAD>Kuwaitis Vote on Body Denounced by Opposition</HEAD>
<DATELINE>KUWAIT (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Kuwaitis on Sunday elected 50 members of a
transitional parliament in voting boycotted by opposition leaders,
who are challenging the government's claim that the new body will
advance democracy.
   No results were available late Sunday, and it was unclear when
results would be announced.
   Unofficial estimates after the polls closed at 8 p.m. put the
turnout at about 55 percent in this small, oil-rich state on the
Persian Gulf.
   Kuwait used to pride itself on having the only Western-style
parliament among the conservative Arab countries of the Persian
Gulf, but the government dissolved it in 1986 after strong
parliamentary criticism of the government.
   The opposition boycotting the elections, led by about 30
deputies from the dissolved parliament, insist on the restoration
of the original 50-member legislature instead of the 75-member
transitional chamber, which includes 25 members appointed by
Kuwait's emir, Sheik Jaber al-Ahmed al-Sabah
   Diplomats had said anything more than 40 percent at the polls
should be considered a success for the government's plan to set up
the interim 75-member National Council, given the boycott and the
abstention of many Kuwaitis on summer vacation.
   The diplomats said it would be difficult to determine how many
abstentions could be attributed to the opposition boycott.
   The emir decreed the new interim chamber to pave the way for the
restoration of a fully elected parliament.
   However, opposition figures had argued the National Council
would be unconstitutional and ineffective.
   The vote results were expected to produce a pro-government
chamber that fosters cooperation between the executive and
legislative branches of government.
   The all-male electorate, estimated at about 62,000, was choosing
50 deputies from among 348 candidates. Kuwait's population is 1.7
million.
   Only those over 21 who can trace their Kuwaiti citizenship back
at least 30 years can vote. Women have not been enfranchised in
this conservative Islamic society.
   Within four years, the interim chamber is charged with
suggesting controls to prevent the kind of strong criticism of
ministers that prompted the government to dissolve the parliament
in 1976 and 1986.
   The 1986 suspension came at the height of the eight-year
Iraq-Iran war, when Kuwait was almost dragged into the hostilities.
But a U.N.-mediated cease-fire end the conflict in 1988.
   Then, with the democratic revolutions in Eastern Europe over the
past year, activists in Kuwait began pressing for the restoration
of parliament. The interim chamber was a compromise solution by the
emir.
   Throughout its campaigns, the opposition has insisted that its
allegiance to the emir remains firm.
   Before Sunday's election, the opposition held a series of
meetings in defiance of laws banning public gatherings. Authorities
arrested 15 opposition leaders, but they were later released. Later
meetings were allowed to take place.
   The candidates are mostly new to politics. They overwhelmingly
belong to pro-government tribes in outlying areas.
   But they include 20 onetime deputies who were members of
parliaments elected since Kuwait's 1962 post-independence
constitution.
   Only Arab reporters were allowed into Kuwait to cover the
elections.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0032 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 1743EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-TankerBlast-Lightering     06-10 0503</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Tanker Blast-Lightering,0517</SECOND>
<HEAD>Lightering Poses Potential for Disaster, Coast Guard Says</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Tanker Blast, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HOUSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Coast Guard, noting a rise in the practice of
transferring oil between ships in the Gulf of Mexico in recent
years, said they have been bracing for a disaster.
   But the disaster officials feared was a collision, not the
series of explosions that rocked the 853-foot supertanker Mega Borg
on Saturday, killing two crewmen and leaving two others missing and
presumed dead.
   As oil imports to the United States rise, the Coast Guard said
the delicate art of ``lightering,'' or transferring oil from a
larger ship to a smaller one, has been practiced more frequently in
the gulf.
   Shippers say the transfers are necessary because the deep-water
crude oil carriers are too large when fully loaded to navigate the
relatively shallow Texas ship channels.
   As the Norwegian supertanker was transferring crude oil to the
smaller tanker Framura on Saturday, an explosion set fire to the
larger vessel. The blast occurred after the Mega Borg had unloaded
2.9 million of its 41.2 million gallons of oil, authorities said.
   The Coast Guard estimates that lightering operations off the
Texas coast increased 200 percent between 1986 and 1988, the last
year for which figures were available. From about 20 a month in
1986, transfers had jumped to an average of 77 a month by August
1988.
   More than a dozen oil transfer operations may be under way
simultaneously off the coast of Galveston on some days, officials
said. Although no major problems with lightering have been reported
in the gulf, they said the disaster potential is increasing.
   As the number of transfer operations continues to rise, so does
the possibility of a major oil spill along the Gulf Coast, Lt.
Cmdr. Frank Whipple of the Coast Guard's Galveston marine safety
office said earlier this year.
   ``It just takes one slip to cause a catastrophic accident,'' he
said.
   Concern, however, has focused on the possibility of a collision
between the two ships that must maneuver close to each other during
the transfer.
   Officials worried a collision could pierce the hull of one of
the tankers, causing a massive oil spill.
   Coast Guard officials, aware of the increasing risks, said they
recently began closely watching the number and frequency of
lightering operations off the Texas coast.
   Following the 10.9 million-gallon Exxon Valdez oil spill in
Alaska last March, the Coast Guard ordered its marine safety
offices throughout the nation to review disaster prevention and
response plans.
   The agency requires a day's notice of arriving vessels and
lightering schedules must be filed. Coast Guard inspectors said
they visit the ships at owners' expense for safety inspections.
   Coast Guard officials met in January with lightering workers to
discuss procedures, safety and the risk of a spill off the Texas
coast.
   Industry officials estimate that 1.6 billion to 2.1 billion
gallons of oil are lightered along the Louisiana and Texas coasts
every year, with at least half that amount off Galveston.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0033 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 1810EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-TankerBlast-Survivors     06-10 0429</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Tanker Blast-Survivors,0442</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tanker Blast Survivors Speak Escape Through Smoke and Darkness</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Tanker Blast, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LAKE JACKSON, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Crewmen from the Mega Borg,
recounting their escape from the burning supertanker, told of
feeling their way through darkened corridors amid acrid smoke and
explosions.
   Ravishanker Navampally, an engineer on the 853-foot Norwegian
ship, said he was just about to go to sleep early Saturday when he
heard a loud noise and felt a strong vibration rock the crew
quarters.
   The Calcutta, India, native said lights crashed down on him as
he struggled from his cot and felt his way into the corridor.
``There was smoke. I didn't see fire,'' he said.
   Jose Emerson Bacinillo, a motorman from the Philippines who has
spent 12 years at sea, said he woke to the cries of his friends.
   A power failure plunged the vessel into darkness, forcing crew
members to feel their way along smoke-filled corridors to the deck.
   ``No light,'' said Bacinillo. ``I just walk in the alleyways,''
he said, demonstrating how he felt his way along the walls. ``I am
scared also.''
   The supertanker, which had 38 million gallons of light crude
aboard, continued to burn out of control Sunday in the Gulf of
Mexico after being hit by more explosions, authorities said. Two
crewmen were killed Saturday, and two others were missing and
presumed dead.
   John Angelo Estibeiro of India, a mechanic and pipe fitter on
the vessel, said he is assigned to the same section of the ship
where Coast Guard officials said the first blast occurred.
   ``I work during the day. If I worked at night, I may have been
trapped in there,'' Estibeiro, 25, said while eating lunch Saturday
at Brazosport Memorial Hospital in Lake Jackson.
   ``There is no escape at night. You don't know where to run,'' he
said in broken English.
   Estebeiro said he went off duty at 8 p.m. Friday. Several hours
later, he felt the ship shake.
   ``I was just on my way to go to sleep,'' said Estibeiro. ``My
door was open. I heard a thump, and the lights fell on the floor
because of the vibration.''
   He rushed to the deck, along with most others on the tanker, and
waited while a nearby crew boat came to the rescue.
   Two of the crewmen who escaped the fire and explosions were
admitted to Brazosport Memorial Hospital; 15 others were treated
for abrasions and smoke inhalation and released.
   The two who were admitted were in fair condition Sunday at the
hospital about 15 miles north of Freeport, officials said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0034 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 1814EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Brite-BeingFrank     06-10 0666</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brite-Being Frank,0699</SECOND>
<HEAD>Life Interesting For Family With 12 Members Named Frank</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ALAMEDA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Say hello to Frank J. Manibusan and his
brother, Frank.
   And their brother, Frank.
   And their other brother, Frank.
   And his brother, Frank, and one other brother: Frank.
   Then, of course, there are their children:
   Frank, Frank, Frank, Frank, Frank and Frank.
   Frankly speaking, there are 12 Franks in all, at the moment _ 13
if you count the patriarch, 58-year-old Francisco.
   But hold on a minute. The sons and grandsons all have middle
initials:
   J. J. J. J. J. J. J. J. J. J. J. and J.
   It isn't that their parents are sadistic pranksters who thought
they'd have a good time at their son's expense, and that the joke
was so funny the sons all played it on their sons. Not at all.
   They just didn't want to play favorites.
   ``As long as we keep having boys, they'll all be named Frank
J.,'' laughed Barbara Manibusan, who's married to Frank John
Manibusan, son No. 1.
   It didn't start out as a plan. It just ended up that way,
explained Lolla Manibusan, who gave birth to all six boys and to
two girls.
   Plagued by miscarriages _ seven in all _ Lolla Manibusan was
told that babies weren't in her future.
   But after three miscarriages, she gave birth to a healthy boy.
   The couple, both from Guam, named him after the father, figuring
he was a special _ and only _ child.
   But they were blessed again with another boy.
   ``We couldn't have him feeling bad,'' said Lolla Manibusan,
reflecting on her frank decision. So he, too, was equipped with the
``F-word'' _ as the family likes to refer to it. They thought he'd
be the last. But fate had other plans.
   ``When the third one showed up, we said, `There are two kids
named after their dad _ what's going to happen?''' recalled dad
Manibusan.
   Fair's fair, he finaly decided.
   ``I never dreamed it was going to be like Morton Salt _ when it
rains it pours,'' Lolla Manibusan said at a Sunday family gathering
at the parents' home.
   There is a distinction between the Frank J.'s. The J's are
different. For the sons it's John, Joseph, Jesse, Jerry, Jady, and
Joseph Haley.
   All Manibusans, every last Frank son (they range in age from 23
to 34), have settled down in Alameda.
   Life can get a little complicated for a bunch of guys with the
same name.
   There was the time that Frank John went before a judge to clear
a traffic ticket. No sooner did officials plug the name, Frank
Manibusan, into the computer than it spewed out a ton of tickets.
   ``The judge wouldn't believe me that I had only four warrants,''
he joked.
   There can be a the light side, too.
   Can't do jury duty? Not to worry. Which Frank are the
authorities going to chastise? And if one bro is out of cash, who
cares? He need only tear out a check from his sibling's wallet.
   ``We don't leave no checks laying around,'' explained Frank Joe,
No. 2 son, while his brothers and father nodded enthusiastically in
agreement.
   While they get in trouble for the other's problems, they also
get some rewards.
   Imagine Frank John's surprise when he got to work the day after
his brother Frank Jady made the papers because the governor gave
him an award for helping out in the Oct. 17 earthquake.
   ``They said, `Hey, Frank, I saw you in the newspaper. You're a
hero.' I said that's my brother Frank Jady.''
   Then his brother Frank Joseph made the papers for chasing a
robbery suspect down the city streets waving a bat.
   When Frank Joe made the paper another time for chasing a second
bad guy _ this one toting a gun _ Frank John's employer, Pacific
Bell, wrote a story about his heroics.
   The anecdotes never stop, in the lives of the male Manabusans,
to be perfectly frank.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0035 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 1854EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-FarmBill     06-10 0552</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Farm Bill,580</SECOND>
<HEAD>House Panel Wrapping Up Work on 1990 Farm Bill</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DIANE DUSTON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Members of the House Agriculture Committee
plan to finish their work on the 1990 farm bill this week, while
their counterparts in the Senate engage in open warfare over
commodity prices.
   The last big issue in the House committee is the conservation
section of the bill, which Chairman Kika de la Garza, D-Texas, said
would be completed Tuesday.
   That's the day the Senate committee is to go public with its
arguments over price supports, something the members have avoided
in all their other work on the bill that sets agriculture policy
for the next five years.
   Most problems with other sections have been resolved in closed
meetings between the Democratic and Republican staffs.
   When the staffs couldn't resolve the commodity price support
problems, committee Chairman Patrick Leahy, D-Vt., appointed a
``working group'' of himself, Sens. Bob Kerrey, D-Neb., David
Pryor, D-Ark., Richard Lugar, R-Ind., Bob Dole, R-Kan., and Thad
Cochran, R-Miss.
   When the group couldn't resolve the problems, the chairman
decided to go to open session and settle the matter through voting.
   ``I think we will end up getting a bill reported out,'' Kerrey
said last Friday. ``It won't be what Lugar wants. It won't be
exactly what I want.''
   Kerrey took the lead among the Democrats in the committee who
proposed increasing price supports 1 percent in 1991 and allowing
other increases in the four subsequent years based on inflation
rates.
   Lugar's proposal represented the Bush administration's position
that price supports should be frozen at 1990 levels.
   Kerrey said his proposal would cost $13 billion in 1991. ``We
only got $10.6 billion from the Budget Committee,'' he said.
   He said, however, that Leahy had told him he wouldn't take a
bill to the full committee unless it had support of all the
Democrats on the panel, was within the budget and could bring in
some of the Republicans.
   ``I think we have every disagreement settled except for the loan
rates,'' said Kerrey.
   Lugar told reporters early last week that he would not accept
anything other than a freeze in target prices and loan rates. He
said if Democrats wanted to make an issue of it, they would find
themselves in a floor battle that could lead to a one-year
extension of current law.
   ``The administration wants a one-year extension,'' said Kerrey.
   Agriculture Secretary Clayton Yeutter has said repeatedly that
an extension would be acceptable because international trade talks
known as GATT, to be completed in December, could create a need for
a change in support policies anyway.
   In a session with reporters last Friday, Rep. Charles Stenholm,
D-Texas, a subcommittee chairman on the House Agriculture
Committee, pointed out the some problems with an extension.
   ``Why would you want to go through the same debate twice within
a 12-month period,'' he said. ``There's no such thing as a simple
one-year extension when you are dealing with the quirks in the law
and the budget summit.''
   Congress and the White House have been talking for weeks about
ways to reduce the federal deficit in what is being referred to as
a budget summit.
   `'You have to have certainty in the agriculture program,'' said
Stenholm. ``In a one-year extension, there's no certainty.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0036 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 1823EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Israel-Desecration 1stLd-Writethru   06-10 0465</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel-Desecration, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0702,0481</SECOND>
<HEAD>80 Graves Desecrated in American Jewish Cemetery</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 5 grafs to ADD date of oldest graves. Pickup 5th
graf pvs, `Some 80...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By ARIEH O'SULLIVAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Vandals desecrated 80 tombstones in the
American section of the more than 2,500-year-old cemetery on the
biblical Mount of Olives, police said Sunday.
   Police took the cemetery's Arab guard in for questioning after
the desecration was discovered early Sunday. A police spokesman
said there were no suspects.
   Israel television said, however, that police suspected
Palestinian nationalists were behind the attack.
   Jewish tradition holds that the Mount of Olives is where the
Messiah will appear and the Prophet Ezekiel will blow the trumpet
of resurrection. Many prominent rabbis are buried in the cemetery,
the largest and oldest Jewish graveyard in the world.
   Rock-hewn tombs at the foot of the mountain date back to the
time of King Solomon's temple, which was destroyed by the
Babylonians in 586 B.C.
   Some 80 tombstones or raised limestone graves were smashed,
crushed or toppled in two sections of the graveyard, located on the
side of the biblical mount in annexed east Jerusalem overlooking
the walls of the Old City.
   Flowers and memorial candles were strewn over the site, and the
names of many of the deceased could not be read because of the
damage.
   ``The must have come here with 12-pound hammers. I don't know
how they didn't hear this,'' Yonatan Shamai said, pointing to Arab
homes some 50 yards away.
   ``I heard the report on the radio. It sent chills down my spine.
I had to come and see for myself,'' said Shamai, a 43-year-old
diamond worker.
   He said his father is buried in the graveyard, but his tomb was
not among the damaged.
   Jerusalem Mayor Teddy Kollek denounced the desecration and
warned that it may further disrupt Jewish-Arab relations in the
city, already severely harmed by the 30-month Palestinian uprising.
   ``An attack on such a sensitive site is destructive for efforts
to encourage understanding and tranquility that we are trying to
establish between Jews and Arabs in the city,'' Kollek said in a
statement.
   The incident follows a wave of similar desecrations, including
one in southern France and one in the northern Israeli port of
Haifa.
   After the desecration of 34 graves in the French town of
Carpentras last month, two members of a Jewish Messianic cult
desecrated more than 300 Jewish graves in Haifa with spray-painted
slogans calling on Arabs to kill Jews.
   The two confessed and said they had hoped that Arabs would be
blamed for the destruction. One was sentenced to three years in
prison, and the other was found psychologically unfit to stand
trial.
   Although suspects were questioned in the French case, no one was
charged.

</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0037 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 1830EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Soviet-Unrest 1stLd-Writethru a0656 06-10 0686</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Unrest, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0656,0705</SECOND>
<HEAD>RETRANSMITTING a0697 to fix computer garble in slugline</HEAD>
<HEAD>Mass Rallies Broken up in Kirghizia; Death Toll Now 115</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: New thruout to UPDATE death toll, TV footage; No pickup.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By BRIAN FRIEDMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Police broke up attempts to organize nationalistic
rallies Sunday in the Central Asian republic of Kirghizia after a
week of ethnic clashes that have left 115 people dead, officials
said.
   The border city of Osh in western Kirghizia, where fighting
between ethnic Kirghiz and Uzbeks broke out last weekend, was
reported calm Sunday. At issue was the allocation of land for
housing in the densely populated, poor region.
   The ethnic violence was only the latest to confront Soviet
President Mikhail S. Gorbachev. Nationalities in several republics
have taken advantage of Gorbachev's reforms to vent frustrations
over political and economic woes.
   In Osh, armored personnel carriers sat at each intersection and
Interior Ministry troops patrolled the streets, said Rauf Duseyev,
duty officer at the Osh Communist Party offices.
   But unrest continued Saturday in nearby regions, especially in
Uzgen, which is predominantly Uzbek, Soviet TV reported Sunday
night.
   In Frunze, the capital of Kirghizia and 195 miles north of Osh,
students trying to organize rallies in the capital's main square
were turned back by Interior Ministry troops and police, said Ivan
Pavlov, a party official.
   Rallies in Frunze last week turned into demonstrations against
the republic's leaders. There were also calls for residents to join
the battle against the Uzbek population in Osh.
   Early Sunday, officials from the Communist Party and the
government visited student and worker dormitories to talk them out
of holding the rallies, Pavlov said from Frunze.
   Armored personnel carriers rolled along the main streets of
Frunze in districts where trouble had broken out earlier, and all
was quiet, he said.
   Overnight in Frunze, 11 students threw stones at a police patrol
from a dormitory window and were beaten by the truncheon-wielding
officers, Pavlov said. There were no serious injuries, and no one
was detained in the incident, he said.
   Since the Kirghiz-Uzbek unrest began on June 2, 115 people have
died, 468 have been wounded, the Soviet television newscast
``Vremya'' reported Sunday night.
   The Soviet army newspaper Red Star said about 500 houses have
been burned down. It also said 512 people were arrested, including
47 for curfew violations and 11 for possession of firearms.
   Rioting flared in Osh, a 3,000-year-old city of 210,000 people,
when Uzbeks, one-third of the population, discovered that Kirghiz
were being given parcels of land for housing. Housing is critically
short in the republic.
   The fighting between the Sunni Moslem groups spread to districts
around Osh, and thousands of troops were sent in to reinforce local
police.
   Soviet troops sealed off the border to prevent thousands of
Uzbeks from crossing into Kirghizia to join the battle, and curfews
were imposed in the region, including Osh, Frunze and border areas
inside Uzbekistan.
   Soviet and local officials have appealed repeatedly for the
residents of both republics to remain calm. In the district of
Nauket, near Osh, elders of the Uzbek and Kirghiz communities met
over the weekend to ask youths to cool their tempers, Komsomolskaya
Pravda reported.
   Monday was declared a day of mourning in Osh.
   Although public transportation resumed in Osh over the weekend,
shooting was reported in the suburbs, Komsomoloskaya Pravda
reported.
   Footage of burned-out shells of homes and charred autos was
shown on the newscast. Yet, it also featured Kirghiz and Uzbek
residents of Osh discussing the situation together, in an apparent
effort to portray instigators of the violence as extremists.
   In the Kirghiz town of Uzgen, 35 miles outside Osh, shooting and
arson attacks continued Saturday, the newspaper said. Some of the
worst bloodshed has occurred in the Uzgen district, where
two-thirds of the deaths were reported.
   Red Star said an Interior Ministry officer was shot to death at
a local post in the Osh region. It said it believed bands of
citizens who had obtained police uniforms and guns were roaming the
region and firing at civilian targets to provoke the population.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0038 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 1841EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-GraffitiNight     06-10 0545</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Graffiti Night,0560</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tradition Remains Strong Despite Cruising Limits</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By COLLEEN BARRY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MODESTO, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Cruising thrived for one special night in
the town that styles itself the Cruising Capital and inspired the
film ``American Graffiti.''
   ``It's pure hysteria,'' Ray Brooks, 48, said as he pulled his
1928 Ford truck onto McHenry Avenue for its first pass of the night
Saturday in this central California city's annual Grafitti Night.
   No matter that it took as long as three hours to negotiate the
five-mile McHenry cruising strip among some 25,000 vintage and late
model cars. On Graffiti Night, speed takes a back seat to showing
off cars and meeting dates.
   ``I think what's special about the night is all the people,''
said Tom Greco, 45.
   Passers-by flocked like moths to the flashing purple and blue
neon spark-plug wires on Greco's 1929 Ford. Not to be deprived of
cruising's rites just because they were on foot, a pair of
pedestrians answered the wail of a tractor-trailer horn with blares
from fog horns they carried.
   People came from miles around to join the revelry. An estimated
70,000 to 80,000 pedestrians made the sidewalks as prone to
gridlock as the avenue. Still, the crowds parted easily for Larry
Wooldridge, who had a 14-foot python around his neck.
   More than 200 police officers patrolled in cars and on foot.
Police Lt. Dennis Puthuff said 85 people were arrested, mostly for
drinking in public, though one person was held for felony assault
with a deadly weapon.
   Following the plot of the 1973 film ``American Graffiti,''
directed by Modesto native George Lucas, high school seniors 15
years ago established Graffiti Night on the first Saturday after
graduation.
   Many regard the film as a documentary of sorts on the cruising
tradition, and say it established this city of 130,000 as the
Cruising Capital.
   As longtime cruiser Bill Miller of Phoenix puts it, ``Cruisers
revere Modesto.''
   Modesto's primacy as the cruising mecca was threatened by the
approval in March of two ordinances to limit the gasoline-guzzling
pastime. The rules impose fines for loitering on foot and for
passing (on wheels) checkpoints more than twice. Supporters said
the cruising tradition popularized in the 1950s is no longer good
natured when influenced by 1990s-style vandalism, drugs and gangs.
   Graffiti Night, however, is the one time each year the fines
don't apply, and revelers took full advantage.
   ``We are the original Graffiti people,'' said Pam Vieira,
Turlock High School class of 1962.
   Vieira and her companions spent much of the evening watching the
parade from the back of their 1954 Chevy pickup truck after it
overheated in the crawling traffic.
   They weren't alone. Parking lots became impromptu vintage
automobile shows while late model cars dominated the strip,
diluting what many identify as the true cruising experience.
   ``That's not what cruising's about. It's about talking to the
guy in the car next to you or the girl in the car next to you. If
the stereo's blaring, how are you going to get to know them and
marry them,'' said Charlotte Mallory, 44, with her husband in a
1960 Morris Minor.
   They met while cruising in San Leandro, and reared two teen-age
daughters ``in the back seat of a car cruising,'' she said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0039 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 1932EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Tunisia-Election     06-10 0252</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Tunisia-Election,0265</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ruling Party Certain to Win As Opposition Boycotts Elections</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By HABIB FAKHRI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TUNIS, Tunisia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The ruling Constitutional Democratic Rally
Party seemed certain to win Sunday's balloting for 246 municipal
councils in elections boycotted by opposition parties.
   The ruling party's candidates were contested by independent
candidates in only 19 municipalities, leaving abstention as the
only way for most of the 1.7 million voters to express discontent
with President Zine el Abidine Ben Ali's rule.
   It was unclear if a significant number of voters boycotted the
polls, which closed at 6 p.m. Observers said voting for the 3,774
seats took place in an atmosphere of calm.
   Officials said preliminary figures on voter turnout would
probably not be available until Monday. Official results might take
longer.
   Right-wing and left-wing parties announced a boycott of the
elections while Islamic Fundamentalists were banned from the
balloting.
   In the last legislative elections, held in 1988, the ruling
party won every seat in the national assembly. Opposition parties
later accused the party of abusing its control of state funds,
transport and mass media.
   The Constitutional Democratic Party has held power since French
colonial rule ended decades ago.
   Municipal and regional elections will be held Tuesday in
neighboring Algeria, the first time that nation's ruling National
Salvation Front has faced a challenge from opposition parties.
   The officially recognized fundamentalist Islamic Salvation Front
is expected to pose the strongest challenge to the Front, which has
ruled Algeria since independence from France in 1962.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0040 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 1943EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-FBISlaying     06-10 0743</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-FBI Slaying,0776</SECOND>
<HEAD>Sister Recalls Slain Woman's Liaison With FBI Agent Who Reportedly
Killed Her</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROB WELLS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>FREEBURN, Ky. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A woman searching for her pregnant sister,
a onetime FBI informant, learned the sister had been strangled
after a lovers' quarrel with a married FBI agent, the woman says.
   Susan Daniels Smith, 28, dropped out of sight last June after
threatening to expose the two-year affair and her pregnancy to the
agent's wife, said sister Shelby Ward. Her body was found last week.
   ``She wanted him to leave his wife. She was threatening to tell
his wife about the baby and he was scared to death,'' Mrs. Ward
said.
   The FBI agent admitted killing the woman during an argument and
was expected to plead guilty to manslaughter this week, she said.
No charges have been filed, but law enforcement authorities
speaking on the condition they not be identified confirmed Mrs.
Ward's story.
   Greg Jones, an FBI spokesman in Washington, refused to comment
on the case. When asked whether he knew of any cases where an FBI
agent was charged in a homicide, he said: ``I don't believe there
ever has been.''
   The agent, identified by Mrs. Ward and other sources as Mark
Putnam, ``confessed to killing my sister and where he put the
body,'' Mrs. Ward said. She said she and her brother, Billy Joe
Daniels, were briefed on the case last week.
   Human skeletal remains found at the dumping sight are those of a
white adult female, officials said. Mrs. Ward said authorities told
her the remains are her sister's.
   Outraged at the plea agreement, Mrs. Ward defied prosecutors'
wishes and discussed the case with The Associated Press.
   ``It's cold-blooded murder to me,'' she said.
   She threatened to file a lawsuit against the agent, and possibly
the FBI, seeking damages to help support Ms. Smith's children, ages
8 and 4.
   The victim was an eighth-grade dropout who married at age 15 and
was later divorced, her sister said.
   She was an FBI informant who testified in a bank robbery case
and worked on a vehicle-theft case, Mrs. Ward said.
   Ms. Smith and the agent met during her work as an informant, her
sister said. The victim told of the affair, naming Putnam and
saying he was a married FBI agent.
   She was last seen June 8, 1989, after traveling to Pikeville to
meet the agent at a motel three days before, Mrs. Ward said.
   ``She was possessed by him ... madly in love with him,'' the
sister said. ``We tried to get her to date other people and she
didn't even want to talk about it.''
   Authorities did not say whether the fetus' death would result in
added charges.
   ``She was even going to name it after him, if it was a boy,''
Mrs. Ward said.
   The agent told authorities he strangled Ms. Smith during an
argument on their way back to Freeburn, Mrs. Ward said.
   Her nude body was dumped the next day off the side of a rural
road in Harmond Branch, about five miles north of Pikeville, she
said.
   Mrs. Ward reported her sister missing on June 12, after the
agent called ``in a panic'' and said Ms. Smith had gone to Chicago.
   Mrs. Ward said she suspected foul play when her sister's purse,
clothes and makeup were found at the motel.
   ``That was a new outfit. She would have put it on if she was
going to go somewhere,'' Mrs. Ward said.
   The agent allegedly said he stripped the body because the victim
was wearing his clothes when she died.
   Putnam reportedly was transferred from Pikeville to Miami in May
1989. The killing took place during a trip back to Kentucky for
court proceedings in a case he worked on.
   Attempts to reach Putnam for comment were unsuccessful.
Directory assistance in Miami had no listing for him and FBI
officials there referred all calls to Washington headquarters.
   Putnam has been on administrative leave for at least a month,
said sources who spoke on condition of anonymity. He faces a
possible 16-year prison term.
   Mrs. Ward said she and her brother were told of the agent's
confession and the plea arrangement by Pike County prosecutor John
Paul Runyon, state police Capt. Gary Rose and Kentucky FBI
supervisor Terry O'Connor.
   ``The family's been wondering all this time,'' Mrs. Ward said.
``And all this time, (she has been) laying over there, nothing but
her skeleton.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0041 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 2031EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Britain-Attack     06-10 0301</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Britain-Attack,0317</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bomb Injured Baby, Link Sought to Animal Rights Groups</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Animal Rights, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BRISTOL, England (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A bomb placed on an animal researcher's
car exploded Sunday in this western English city and seriously
injured a nearby 13-month-old boy, police said.
   No one immediately claimed responsibility, but authorities said
they were investigating any connection with a bomb attack Wednesday
on the car of a veterinarian near Salisbury.
   After the first attack, a telephone caller claimed
responsibility for an animal rights' group.
   The baby injured Sunday was identified as John Cupper. He
suffered burns, shrapnel wounds and a partially severed finger,
police said.
   The boy's father, James Cupper, and the driver of the car,
Patrick Headley, escaped injury.
   Headley, a psychologist at Bristol University, has been involved
in research projects on sheep, according to Press Association,
Britain's domestic news agency.
   Deputy Chief Constable John Harland of Avon and Somerset Police
said detectives were investigating links with Wednesday's bomb
attack on the veterinarian's car.
   In last week's incident, a bomb set fire to a car driven by
Margaret Baskerville, a veterinarian employed by the Ministry of
Defense's Chemical Defense Establishment at Porton Down, near
Salisbury in southern England.
   That facility uses mice and guinea pigs in experiments on
countermeasures for chemical and biological warfare agents, the
Ministry of Defense said.
   Mrs. Baskerville escaped injury.
   Chief Inspector Bryan Saunders, a spokesman for Avon and
Somerset Police, said police were warning all people involved in
animal research to ``take every precaution, in particular to check
their vehicles for suspect devices.''
   Sunday's attack came the same day up to 50,000 animal rights
activists rallied in Washington to promote the humane treatment of
animals in the wild, on farms and in research laboratories.
   Many marchers advocated an end to using animals in medical
research.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0042 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 1953EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-WeatherpageWeather     06-10 0148</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Weatherpage Weather,0151</SECOND>
<HEAD>Cold Front Brings Scattered Showers to the West</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   A cold front brought scattered showers from the northern Rockies
to Southern California, and rain also fell in the southern
Applachians and western New England.
   Showers and a few thunderstorms developed from western Arkansas
to southeastern Nebraska and scattered thunderstorms formed along
the Gulf Coast.
   Rain fell in New Mexico, Colorado, Nevada, Idaho and Washington
state. San Diego had its second straight day of record rain, with
.4 inch falling, easily surpassing the total of .14 on the same
date in 1957.
   Skies were sunny from the southern High Plains to Georgia and
across the upper Mississippi Valley and the upper Great Lakes
region. Strong northwesterly winds blew over the upper Great Lakes
region and the middle Atlantic Coast.
   The low for the Lower 48 states was 44 degrees in Olympia, Wash.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0043 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 2021EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-MedicareFraud     06-10 0747</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Medicare Fraud,0773</SECOND>
<HEAD>Lawsuits Claim Insurer Bypassed Laws On `Working Aged'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BRIAN MURPHY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The nation's health-care system for the elderly has
been bilked of huge sums _ perhaps billions of dollars _ by private
insurance companies that refuse to pay their share, according to a
series of legal actions.
   In lawsuits by federal officials and a Miami law firm, a
Chattanooga, Tenn.-based insurer, Provident Life and Accident
Insurance Co., is accused of circumventing an 8-year-old revision
in Medicare policy designed to make insurers pay 80 percent of
medical costs for working people 65 and older.
   Previously, the so-called ``working aged'' had 80 percent of
their medical bills paid by Medicare.
   The lawsuits were filed quietly 14 months ago, but are just now
moving into the courtroom.
   The attorneys from the Miami law firm said their lawsuit accuses
four other private insurers of such tactics, while the U.S. Justice
Department has become involved only in the Provident action.
   The lawsuits allege that the insurance company knowingly paid
only 20 percent of the bill and counted on Medicare to cover the
rest. The 1982 revisions were made to ease financial pressure on
the $97 billion-a-year program.
   ``This is fraud, pure and simple,'' said Miami attorney Luis
Bustamante, who says he uncovered the Medicare losses while
representing a client in 1983.
   ``It's a monster,'' Bustamante said in an interview last week.
   The Senate Governmental Affairs Committee's permanent
subcommittee on investigations is scheduled to begin hearings next
month on the allegations.
   But there is discord among the accusers. Bustamante and
colleagues in the Stinson, Lyons, Gerlin &amp; Bustamante law firm of
Miami claim the Justice Department merely copied their action
against Provident after reviewing piles of documents and
depositions the Miami law firm gathered.
   Justice Department officials did not answer numerous calls to
their Washington office last week seeking comment.
   ``The whole Medicare system is based on trust. It's so open for
abuse,'' said Bustamante.
   Bustamante said he first learned of the Medicare problem while
representing Miami trucking executive Armlon Leonard. Leonard, 67,
was severely injured in a 1983 car crash and spent 15 months,
including a year in intensive care, at Miami's Jackson Memorial
Hospital before he died.
   His medical bill: $800,000.
   While reviewing Leonard's medical bills, Bustamante said, he
learned that Provident Life and Accident Ins. Co. did not uphold
its $1 million policy, claiming it was reduced to $50,000 of
coverage after Leonard turned 65 and became eligible for federal
coverage.
   Bustamante says his probe indicated that some companies never
started picking up the increased tab for the ``working aged''
required under the amended law. The companies allegedly would allow
Medicare to pick up 80 percent, then send only 20 percent, instead
of sending 80 percent themselves and allowing Medicare to get a
refund.
   Bustamante filed a False Claims Act lawsuit in Miami in March
1989, alleging Provident was failing to pay its required 80 pecent
of Leonard's bill.
   The 127-year-old federal False Claims Act, broadened in recent
years, allows private citizens to file fraud allegations against
the government or act as whistle blowers when federal programs are
abused.
   The Justice Department reviewed Bustamante's claim and the
accompanying mass of documents, and eventually filed its own action.
   ``Everything was there and more,'' said Leon Weinstein, a former
special agent for the office of inspector general of the Department
of Health and Human Services assigned to the Bustamante case.
   Both lawsuits have been transferred to Chattanooga, Tenn.,
Provident's home base, but a judge stayed Bustamante's suit in
favor of the federal action.
   Bustamante said his investigation has turned up stacks of
evidence of Medicare fraud, including depositions and internal
documents at Provident.
   Provident says it's not going to talk about the legal action,
for now.
   ``The company's position is that we're not discussing this while
it's in litigation,'' said Provident spokeswoman Jennie Storey.
   But the company has denied wrongdoing in court documents and is
vigorously fighting the action.
   On Monday, Provident is scheduled to appear at a hearing in
Chattanooga on its request to block the author of a memo from
testifying in court in the Justice Department case.
   Medicare officials have said that underpayments by private
companies could run into the billions of dollars.
   Bustamante's lawsuit also names Prudential Insurance Co. of
America, based in Newark, N.J.; Jefferson-Pilot Life Insurance Co.
of Greensboro, N.C.; Atlanta-based Blue Cross and Blue Shield of
Georgia; and Pan American Assurance Co. of New Orleans.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0044 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 2041EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Russia-Conservatives     06-10 0417</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Russia-Conservatives,0438</SECOND>
<HEAD>Conservatives Organize for Russian Party Meeting</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARK J. PORUBCANSKY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Conservative Communists critical of Soviet
President Mikhail S. Gorbachev's reforms organized Sunday to fight
for control of a new party for the largest Soviet republic, a
spokesman said.
   If they succeed, they will be heading on a collision course with
the Russian republic's government, whose new president is radical
reformer Boris N. Yeltsin.
   The unofficial North-West news service of Leningrad reported
that radical reformers picketed the entrance to the House of
Political Education in that city, where Sunday's meeting took place.
   The session of almost 600 party members was called to prepare
for a conference of all Russian Communists scheduled for Tuesday in
Moscow. They picked a slate of candidates for that meeting and
drafted a proposed platform criticizing national policies.
   Organizers say there are more than 1.5 million national party
members in the Soviet Union's largest republic. Most republics also
have their own parties within the national organization.
   As the giant Russian republic seeks its place in a rapidly
changing union, it is founding its own party too. Russians say they
need the party because their interests have long been secondary to
national concerns and they have lost their identity.
   However, as in most other republics, the Russians are expected
to form a party under the umbrella of the Soviet Communist Party.
   In the secession-minded Baltics, the Communist parties have
broken with the Kremlin.
   If the conservatives gain control of the new Russian party, they
would exercise broad power over policies and party apparatus in the
republic that includes 52 percent of the Soviet population and
three-quarters of its land.
   Vladimir Komarov, a spokesman for the conservatives, said their
proposed platform is consistent with resolutions approved in April
at an initial gathering in Leningrad.
   Those resolutions accused Gorbachev's economic advisers of
orienting reforms toward a ``small group of people.''
   ``The path they propose leads to a full break with socialism,''
the document said.
   The Leningrad group proposes to push the Soviet Union out of its
economic crisis in party by relying on scientific and technological
advancements, Komarov said.
   The gathering also agreed on a list of more than 100 candidates
it is promoting for the Central Committee of the new Russian
Communist Party. Komarov said about 80 percent of them are workers
or peasants.
   It is unclear how much support the Leningrad group has among
Russian Communists, but their meeting represented a minority of
rank-and-file party members.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0045 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 2041EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-GasPrices     06-10 0165</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gas Prices,0171</SECOND>
<HEAD>Another Rise in Gas Prices, Survey Says</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Gasoline prices took another small hike
upward nationwide, according to a survey of service stations
released Sunday.
   The average price for a gallon of gas, including all taxes, was
117.96 cents as of Friday, according to the Lundberg Survey of
nearly 13,000 stations nationwide.
   The average price marked a rise of 1.91 cents from the last
survey May 18. The May 18 price was a hike of 2.4 cents over the
previous check.
   The survey had a holiday break giving a three-week lag between
the last check and the one released Sunday. It usually is conducted
each two weeks.
   Gas prices generally rise during the summer as drivers hit the
road for vacations, increasing demand.
   The average price at self-serve pumps: regular unleaded, 106.50
cents per gallon; premium unleaded 123.65; and regular leaded
106.18.
   For full-service pumps: regular unleaded 132.40 cents per
gallon; premium unleaded, 146.01; and regular leaded, 128.60.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0046 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 2043EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-StJames-People 1stLd-Writethru a0711 06-10 0192</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-St James-People, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0711,0193</SECOND>
<HEAD>Susan Saint James Has Baby Boy in Connecticut</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: CHANGES `St.' to `Saint' throughout to conform with actress's
preference.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>TORRINGTON, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Television actress Susan Saint James
gave birth to a baby boy Sunday, a spokesman at Charlotte
Hungerford Hospital said.
   Saint James, who lives in Litchfield, had an 8-pound, 14-ounce
boy at about 10:30 a.m., said spokesman hospital Richard Bisi. Both
mother and child were doing fine, he said.
   Saint James, 43, has had a long career as a television actress.
Most recently, she co-starred with Jane Curtin on CBS' situation
comedy, ``Kate and Allie.'' She starred in ``McMillan and Wife''
with Rock Hudson from 1971-1977.
   Saint James won a best supporting actress Emmy playing an
offbeat secretary in ``The Name of the Game,'' which ran from
1968-71. She also appeared in such movies as ``Carbon Copy'' and
the vampire spoof ``Love at First Bite.''
   This is Saint James' third child with her husband, former
Saturday Night Live producer Dick Ebersol. She has two children
from a previous marriage.
   The couple plans to name the baby Edward Bright Ebersol, a
hospital spokesman said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0047 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 2043EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-RacialAttack     06-10 0470</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Racial Attack,0489</SECOND>
<HEAD>White Teens Face Sentencing in Racial Slaying</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RONALD POWERS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two white teen-agers convicted in the mob
slaying of a black youth face sentencing Monday as community
leaders try to prevent any resumption of the racial violence that
erupted at the end of their trial.
   In a killing that fueled already simmering racial tensions,
16-year-old Yusuf Hawkins was shot in August after he and three
black friends were chased by a mob in Bensonhurst, a predominantly
white Brooklyn neighborhood.
   Joseph Fama, 19, was convicted May 17 of second-degree murder
and other crimes, including riot, unlawful imprisonment and illegal
weapons possession.
   He faces a maximum of 32 and two-thirds years to life in prison.
   A second jury acquitted Keith Mondello, also 19, of murder and
manslaughter charges on May 18, but found him guilty on the lesser
charges of riot, unlawful imprisonment and discrimination.
   Prosecutors want Justice Thaddeus Owens to give Mondello
consecutive sentences, which could keep him in prison from 5 1-3
years to 16 years.
   If his sentences run concurrently, Mondello, the alleged
ringleader of the attack, could serve as little as 1 1-3 years to
four years in prison.
   After the conviction of Fama, who some witnesses said fired the
fatal shot, the city remained calm. But when Mondello's acquittal
on the murder charge came, mayhem erupted in the courtroom and in
the streets.
   Crowds of blacks assembled across Brooklyn, hurling rocks and
bottles and blocking traffic. Several white news reporters were
injured, none seriously.
   The Rev. Al Sharpton, a flamboyant civil-rights activist
described by some as a headline-hungry rabble rouser, has adopted
the role of peacemaker.
   ``We don't have to like each other, but we have to live with
each other,'' Sharpton said recently from the steps of City Hall.
   To back up his appeal for racial calm, Sharpton canceled the
weekend protest marches he has staged in Bensonhurst.
   Leaders of the largely Italian-American neighborhood promised to
work with the black community to help heal racial conflicts.
   ``Bensonhurst will show the world that people who have been
represented as enemies can come together and live the life of the
lamb, not the lion,'' said state Assemblyman Frank J. Barbaro.
   After the sentencing on Monday, Owens is scheduled to conduct a
final pretrial hearing and begin jury selection in the trial of
John Vento, 21, another accused member of the gang.
   Initially, Vento was the cornerstone of the prosecution's case.
He admitted joining the mob and agreed to testify against other
participants in exchange for immunity from prosecution.
   But Vento backed out of the deal and fled the city shortly after
Christmas. He surrendered to the FBI in Dayton, Ohio, in March. A
few days later, he was charged with murder and other crimes in the
attack.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0048 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 2045EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ConnickTrial     06-10 0484</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Connick Trial,0497</SECOND>
<HEAD>Racketeering Trial For New Orleans District Attorney To Begin</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KEVIN McGILL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW ORLEANS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   District Attorney Harry Connick goes on trial
Monday on federal charges he helped an arrested bookie continue his
gambling operation, an accusation Connick calls ``pure D baloney.''
   In addition to Connick, actor Paul Burke, who starred in
television's ``The Naked City;'' former federal prosecutor Patrick
Fanning; businessman Wilson Abraham; convicted bookmaker Walton
Aucoin and Aucoin's alleged employees, Steve Bertolino and William
Condon, are on trial in U.S. District Court.
   If convicted of racketeering and aiding an illegal gambling
operation, Connick could be sentenced to 25 years in prison and
fined $250,000.
   ``I did nothing wrong,'' Connick said last December when he was
indicted. ``The allegations are pure D baloney.''
   Prosecutors from the Justice Department in Washington are
handling the case, but Connick blamed New Orleans' native U.S.
attorney, John Volz, for the indictment. Volz and Connick have had
well publicized feuds over the years and Connick said the charges
against him were the result of a Volz vendetta.
   ``He knows it's a damn lie and everyone else who knows me knows
it's a damn lie,'' Connick said after his arraignment last year. He
has since been mum on the subject, saying he'd prefer to present
his case at trial.
   Volz began the federal investigation of Connick. He said he
turned the case over to Washington prosecutors to avoid any
appearance of bias or conflict of interests involving Connick or
Fanning. Fanning once was an assistant to Volz.
   In the indictment, Aucoin, Bertolino and Condon were accused of
owning and conducting a New Orleans-based illegal interstate
gambling operation that netted up to $2,000 a day.
   Fanning, Abraham and Burke were charged with aiding the
operation by helping Connick cook up an excuse for returning the
seized records Aucoin needed to keep it going. Aucoin was arrested
in December 1988.
   Connick has said he acted in accordance with state criminal
procedures, which allow defendants to see evidence against them so
their attorneys can prepare a defense.
   Connick, district attorney in New Orleans since 1973, is up for
re-election this fall.
   The father of Grammy-winning jazz musician Harry Connick Jr., he
made news nationally last year when he joined state Attorney
General William Guste in asking a federal court to revive
Louisiana's harsh anti-abortion law, not enforced since the 1973
Roe vs. Wade decision of the Supreme Court.
   The effort failed.
   Two people indicted in the gambling case along with Connick
pleaded guilty last week. Aucoin's daughter, Darlene Peake, and
Iris Ethridge, a bank employee who handled Aucoin's account at a
suburban New Orleans bank, pleaded guilty to helping conduct an
illegal gambling business.
   Federal prosecutors agreed to drop a more serious charge of
racketeering in exchange for the women's cooperation. A charge of
perjury against Ms. Ethridge also will be dropped, attorneys said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0049 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 2049EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-All-AmericaCities     06-10 0395</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-All-America Cities,0407</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ten Cities Given Designation as All-America Cities</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By AL BRAVO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PHOENIX (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Ten cities from eight states _ from little Hamlet
in North Carolina to a suburb of Los Angeles _ were designated
All-America Cities by the National Civic League.
   The winners were announced Saturday night after the finalists
gave presentations before a 12-member panel Friday and Saturday.
   The top 10: Abilene, Texas; Bakersfield, Calif.; Charlotte,
N.C.; Coeur d'Alene, Idaho; Hamlet, N.C.; Harrisburg, Pa.; Sioux
City, Iowa; Southgate, Calif., near Los Angeles; South St. Paul,
Minn.; and Tampa, Fla.
   The 30 finalists were picked from a record 113 entries, said
Chris Gates, vice president of the civic league.
   The All-America designation goes to cities that demonstrate an
ability to solve local problems through community leadership,
citizen participation, government, civic education and philanthropy.
   Each delegation gave a 10-minute presentation, spotlighting
three projects its city has undertaken to show leadership and
cooperation between private and government factions.
   ``We are very proud,'' said Mayor Abbie Covington of Hamlet,
with a population of 6,640. The town, about 100 miles southwest of
Raleigh, had never competed in the All-America Cities program.
   ``Thirty percent of our citizens are on a fixed income,'' said
Ms. Covington. ``This just shows the support we can get from our
folks.''
   Among the three projects highlighted in Hamlet's presentation
was the regeneration of the town's hospital.
   With a decline in patients and cuts in Medicare, the hospital
was slowly dying, Ms. Covington said.
   But 4,000 of Hamlet's inhabitants signed a petition calling for
the hospital to remain open and citizens formed a committee to show
support for it. That led to a new lease for the hospital and caused
a new 65-bed nursing home to locate in the southern town.
   The town also expanded its library with donated funds from
citizens and re-established a railroad festival.
   The other cities produced presentations that spotlighted efforts
to combat drug abuse and economic problems.
   The other 20 finalists were Brooklyn Center, Minn.; Beatrice,
Neb.; Binghamton, N.Y.; Chattanooga, Tenn.; LaCrosse, Wis.;
Birmingham and Gadsden, Ala.; Tempe, Ariz.; San Francisco; Montrose
and Ouray, Colo.; Fort Lauderdale, Fla.; Oak Park, Ill.; Wichita,
Kan.; Thibodaux, La.; Baltimore, Rockville and St. Mary's County,
Md.; and Flint and Midland, Mich.
   The 41st annual competition, a program of the National Civic
League, was sponsored by The Allstate Foundation.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0050 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 2054EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-SkydiverDeath     06-10 0293</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Skydiver Death,0305</SECOND>
<HEAD>Parachutist Dies In Leap From Skyscraper</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LYNN BERRY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PHILADELPHIA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two skydivers leaped off the 54th floor of a
partly built downtown skyscraper Sunday, and one man died when his
parachute failed to open, police said.
   Robert Morris, 26, of Mount Joy in southeastern Pennsylvania was
pronounced dead at the scene, police said.
   Rod Stoltzfus, 27, landed safely in a parking lot across the
street just after dawn and left the scene, police said.
   Stoltzfus called his pastor and went with him to see Morris'
family before contacting police, said Detective James Mooney.
   No charges were filed against Stoltzfus, who returned to his
Manheim home, Mooney said.
   Lt. Giacomo Giovinetti said police would wait to decide whether
to file charges until they talk to Stoltzfus, who was expected to
return for questioning.
   ``We're going to find out just what the circumstances were,''
Giovinetti said. ``We're also going to talk to the district
attorney.''
   Giovinetti said charges could include risking a catastrophe,
causing a disturbance and disorderly conduct.
   ``It's an irresponsible act, but it's not so cut and dried,'' he
said. ``Someone obviously lost a loved one. I don't think we should
be insenstive about this. They could have injured people on the
ground, too.''
   The pair jumped off the Mellon Bank building at 5:50 a.m.,
police said.
   Stoltzfus, who learned to parachute in the Army, has been
skydiving for seven or eight years, said his brother, Brian, 17.
Morris also was experienced, and the two were good friends, the
brother said.
   On Aug. 26, a parachutist identified as a New York waiter jumped
off the building's 47th floor.
   Three skydivers jumped off another skyscraper in 1986 while it
was under construction; none was arrested.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0051 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 2101EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-SuicideMachine-Adkins     06-10 0522</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Suicide Machine-Adkins,0539</SECOND>
<HEAD>Janet Adkins Mourned by Family, Friends</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CAROL ANN RIHA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PORTLAND, Ore. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A woman who used a controversial machine
to commit suicide rather than live through the mental destruction
of Alzheimer's disease became a ``pioneer in the battle for death
with dignity,'' her minister said Sunday.
   Friends and relatives gathered at the First Unitarian Church
here for a memorial service for Janet Elaine Adkins, 54, who died
last Monday in Michigan.
   An exceptional woman in life, ``Janet would become famous in
death,'' said the Rev. Alan G. Deale.
   ``The public attention that her death has received is an
indication of the level of interest in this phenomenon,'' he said.
   ``I have supported Janet's right to decide when she would end
her life,'' Deale said, adding that the Unitarian Church supports
``death with dignity.''
   The Unitarian Universalist Association in 1988 adopted a
resolution that, acknowledging circumstances in which the inherent
dignity of life may be compromised, supported the right to die in
accordance with one's own choice.
   ``She desired control over her own decision in this matter,''
Deale said.
   ``To die a little later, or a little sooner, does not matter,''
he said. What matters is ``to live bravely, to love wisely, to see
how beautiful the trees are, and even the sea _ to enjoy the world
...''
   Mrs. Adkins had planned the joyful, hourlong ceremony before
traveling to Michigan, where Dr. Jack Kevorkian hooked her up to
the suicide machine he invented. She touched a button, releasing an
anasthetic followed by a lethal injection. Seconds later, she was
dead.
   ``Janet loved life, but she didn't fear death,'' said her
friend, Judy Humiston. A spiritual person, Mrs. Adkins saw death as
a passing into the next phase of her search for the ultimate truth,
Humiston said.
   ``She did not fear death _ because we understand that life and
death are necessary to reach heaven,'' Deale said.
   Humiston was one of three friends who spoke of their
relationships with Mrs. Adkins, remembering her passion for life
and her love of good conversation, challenge, philosophy, music,
travel, teaching and tennis.
   ``Janet loved to win,'' Carol Rehmke recalled with a smile.
``Janet taught me to play chess and we played by mail. She won the
first game and I won the second. And we never played the third
game.''
   Humiston, who knew Mrs. Adkins for 28 years, recalled how they
had been young mothers together.
   They discussed their roles as wives and mothers _ and later,
their roles as women as well, Humiston said, noting how Mrs. Adkins
always challenged others to ask questions and to grow.
   ```I admired her ability to show life with such an optimistic
and determined viewpoint,'' Humiston said.
   According to Mrs. Adkins' wishes, a quartet played a movement
from String Quartet No. 2 in D by the 19th century Russian composer
Alexander Borodin.
   Mona Warner and Ryc Williamson, on guitar and bass,
respectively, performed the popular song, ``When I Need You.''
   Deale urged everyone to sing joyfully the closing hymn _
Beethoven's Hymn to Joy _ as Mrs. Adkins had asked.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0052 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 2105EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-TankerBlast-Scene     06-10 0361</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Tanker Blast-Scene,0371</SECOND>
<HEAD>Explosions Continue Aboard Stricken Supertanker; Sea Ablaze</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Tanker Blast, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MICHAEL GRACZYK</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>GALVESTON, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Thirty-six hours after an explosion
ripped through a supertanker and set it ablaze, more blasts rocked
the Mega Borg, sending burning debris into the sky like Roman
candles and leaving oil pools burning on the Gulf of Mexico.
   The entire superstructure _ about the rear one-fifth of the ship
_ was engulfed in flames. The fire's intensity had buckled the
castle-like structure's steel walls and partially collapsed the
ship's stack. The superstructure, blackened by fire Saturday, was a
grayish white Sunday.
   Two thick columns of dark gray smoke, changing to deep black
after a ball of flame would erupt from the blaze, rose more than
2,000 feet into the sky.
   The stern was no more than 5 feet above the water's surface,
where pools of brown oil burned. The ship, apparently at anchor,
listed slightly to port.
   At midday Sunday, two fireboats, occasionally joined by a third
vessel, appeared to be focusing more on keeping the burning oil
from spreading and keeping the cargo tanks cool than on
extinguishing the flames, which licked from the front of the
wheelhouse toward the cargo tanks.
   One fireboat, with ``Rescue One'' emblazoned on its side, shot
two large streams of water to the starboard side, concentrating on
the cargo decks.
   The other fireboat, the Carolyn Chouest, kept its two streams on
the burning sea around the stern. A third boat helped when the fire
on the water surface flared or when oil debris from an explosion
flew beyond the immediate area.
   Water from hoses poured from the decks and over the gunwales.
   The tattered remains of the ship's flag, clearly visible on the
stern Saturday, were lost in the smoke and flames Sunday.
   Four Coast Guard boats patrolled a perimeter several hundred
yards around the ship Sunday, with several supply boats standing by.
   Trails of brown oil lingered hundreds of yards away from the
ship, and slicks of light crude oil were visible as far as 16 miles
away.
   Smoke from the fire could be seen 35 miles away.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0053 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 2110EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Greece-Bomb     06-10 0256</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Greece-Bomb,0268</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bomb Damages Offices of U.S. Company in Greece</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ATHENS, Greece (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A blast from an anti-tank missile rocked a
building housing offices of the U.S.-based Proctor &amp; Gamble Co.
late Sunday, causing damage but no injuries, police said.
   No one claimed immediate responsibility, but authorities said
they suspected a leftist group known as November 17.
   There have been several bomb blasts in Athens over the last
month. There have been no injuries from the attacks.
   Police initially said Sunday's blast was caused by a bomb that
went off in the eight-story building, which also houses a Fiat
motor showroom and local distributors of the Italian automaker.
   Later, police said they believed the blast was caused by an
anti-tank missile slamming into the second floor offices that
belong to the U.S. multinational. The Cincinnati-based company
makes household cleaners, pharmaceuticals and other products.
   Its offices and the motor showroom on the ground floor were
damaged in the blast, authorities said.
   In February, the November 17 group stole two World War II
bazookas from the Athens War Museum. Experts said at the time that
the weapons were serviceable.
   In the past, the group has declared its opposition to
multinational corporations in Greece. It has been blamed for
killing 14 people since 1975, but none of its members has been
arrested.
   Last month, November 17 claimed to have set off several
incendiary bombs in an Athens suburb.
   In the latest previous blast, a bomb went off June 1 and
destroyed five cars. That attack went unclaimed.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0054 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 2113EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Bush 4thLd-Writethru a0744 06-10 0804</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bush, 4th Ld-Writethru, a0744,810</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush Meets Mexican President on Trade Issues</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: Retransmitting a0744 to fix writethru designation to 4th sted
3rd</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By CHRISTOPHER CONNELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush dined privately with Mexican
President Carlos Salinas de Gortari at the White House Sunday night
and laid the groundwork for formal negotiations to lift trade
barriers between the two countries.
   A White House spokesman said both presidents believe their
countries would ``derive substantial and long-term benefits'' from
a trade pact.
   The statement by White House press secretary Marlin Fitzwater
stopped short of announcing the start of formal negotiations to
forge a free trade pact, but administration officials said they
expect that announcement to come Monday.
   Both presidents declined to answer reporters' questions about
free trade as they posed for photographers on the mansion's North
Portico facing Pennsylvania Avenue.
   They went inside for a reception with top U.S. and Mexican
economic officials, including, on the U.S. side, Treasury Secretary
Nicholas Brady, Commerce Secretary Robert Mosbacher, trade
representative Carla Hills, national security adviser Brent
Scowcroft and Vice President Dan Quayle.
   Later, they dined alone in their second White House meeting in
less than nine months.
   Salinas, who is in the United States on a private visit to
address the Business Roundtable, will meet with Secretary of State
James Baker III and members of Congress on Monday, and will resume
``consultations on the free trade issue'' in those meetings,
Fitzwater said.
   Summing up the presidents' private meeting, Fitzwater said:
``Both leaders believe that the United States and Mexico would
derive substantial and long-term benefits from a comprehensive
bilateral trade agreement. They agreed that bilateral efforts to
maximize trade and investment opportunities can and should
complement the trade liberalization achieved in the Uruguay Round
of the GATT (General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade).''
   They also discussed the recent superpower summit, the fight
against drug trafficking and other issues. Bush reiterated the U.S.
desire for ``close cooperation with Mexican authorities'' in the
drug fight, said Fitzwater.
   Administration officials said beforehand that the Bush-Salinas
meeting would be followed by a formal announcement on Monday of
negotiations to create a free trade pact. The officials asked not
to be identified.
   Bush earlier Sunday declined to predict how long it might take
to achieve a free trade agreement with Mexico.
   ``I want to talk to him first before I can say on that,'' Bush
told reporters as he walked off the golf course at Andrews AFB in
suburban Maryland earlier Sunday. But he called the meeting with
Salinas ``very important.''
   If successful, the trade negotiations could bring all of North
America _ 335 million people _ into a single market free of tariffs
and other barriers to trade. The United States and Canada entered a
free trade agreement two years ago.
   Bush has close ties with Salinas, who paid a formal state visit
to the White House last Oct. 3. This time, their get-together was
an informal one, with the two presidents dining without aides
present.
   Preparatory trade discussions are expected to begin shortly with
an eye toward launching the formal negotiations before Bush and
Salinas next meet in Monterrey in December. Two-way U.S.-Mexican
trade now totals about $52 billion a year, but experts say it has
the potential to go much higher.
   The reform-minded Salinas, 42, a Harvard-educated economist, is
seeking to invigorate Mexico's economy. A free trade agreement
could spur job creation south of the border and ease pressures that
lead Mexicans to look for work in the United States illegally.
   But it would require dismantling tariffs and other barriers
erected decades ago to protect Mexican industry from competition
from its rich American neighbor.
   U.S-Mexican ties have been strained by the recent jailing in
California of a Mexican physician, Humberto Alvarez Machain, who is
accused of complicity in the murder of a U.S. Drug Enforcement
Administration agent in 1985.
   Bush said last month the United States played no role in
abducting the doctor. But a DEA agent subsequently testified in Los
Angeles that the agency had authorized a plan for Mexican police to
kidnap the physician and deliver him across the border.
   Salinas and Bush both were elected in 1988. They met as
presidents-elect in November that year in Houston, and then again
last October as heads of state.
   On Monday, Bush will welcome East German Prime Minister Lothar
de Maiziere to the White House for talks on the new Germany and
Europe. It will be the first meeting between a U.S. president and
the head of East Germany, which until a few months ago was a
hard-line communist state. Bush had dinner at the White House
Friday night with West German Chancellor Helmut Kohl.
   Bush and his family held a christening in the Rose Garden on
Sunday for Walker Bush, the president's 12th grandchild.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0055 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 2114EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-2LiveCrew 1stLd-Writethru a0703 06-10 0655</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-2 Live Crew, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0703,0668</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rappers Arrested After Nightclub Performance</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 15 grafs to UPDATE with comments from sheriff,
lawyer. Pick up 13th graf pvs, `Deputies had...</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto MH1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TRACY FIELDS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>FORT LAUDERDALE, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A rap group kept its promise to
sing lyrics from an album ruled obscene and authorities kept their
word, arresting two members of 2 Live Crew on Sunday after an
adults-only concert.
   The early-morning arrests came four days after a federal judge
declared obscene the Miami group's album ``As Nasty As They Wanna
Be,'' and two days after a local record dealer was arrested for
selling the popular recording.
   Broward County sheriff's deputies arrested 2 Live Crew leader
Luther Campbell, 29, and singer Chris Wongwon, 26, shortly after
the show at a Hollywood nightclub.
   ``We didn't want to create any commotion in there, so I told
them to let them get out of there and arrest them away from the
premises,'' said Sheriff Nick Navarro, who has led a campaign to
ban sales of the group's records.
   Deputies pulled over the rappers' limousine a couple of blocks
away from the club, said sheriff's spokesman Al Gordon.
   Only Campbell and Wongwon were taken because the group split up
after the performance, heading in different directions in three
vehicles, Gordon said.
   ``We didn't have enough deputies to cover them,'' he explained,
adding that arrest warrants for members Mark Ross and David Hobbs
would be issued Monday.
   Campbell and Wongwon were booked at the Broward County Jail on
the misdemeanor charge of violating a prohibition against obscene
performances. The charges were based on the group's performance of
material from the album, which has sold more than 1.7 million
copies.
   They were freed without bond. No court appearance was set. If
convicted, they could face up to a year in jail and a $1,000 fine.
   Bruce Rogow, 2 Live Crew's lawyer, said the arrests amounted to
police harassment. The rappers themselves had left for a concert in
Phoenix and could not immediately be reached for comment.
   ``To have a dozen sheriff's officers spending all this time over
some dirty lyrics seems to me to be obscene,'' Rogow said.
   Plainclothes deputies were inside the club early Sunday as the
rap group led the crowd in chanting repeated insults aimed at
Navarro, but Gordon said the arrests were not meant as retaliation.
   ``They announced on TV newscasts they were going to do the songs
which the judge has ruled obscene,'' Gordon said. ``That's pretty
much the same reason we arrested the shopkeeper.''
   E-C Records owner Charles Freeman sold a record and a tape
version of the album to an undercover deputy Friday in front of
news photographers. He faces a first-degree misdemeanor charge and
is free on $100 bond.
   Gordon said the arrests were in keeping with Navarro's
``contention that if you break the law in Broward County, you're
going to jail.''
   Deputies had been checking area record stores since the
Wednesday ruling by U.S. District Judge Jose Gonzalez, Gordon said.
The only copies of the double album they located were those
confiscated in Friday's arrest, he said.
   About 15 police officers and 300 fans were on hand Saturday
night as the rappers performed an early show for patrons of all
ages at Hollywood's Club Futura. At that show the group performed
what it calls the ``clean'' version of the album's songs, omitting
the controversial lyrics. Many of the young concert-goers shouted
the ``nasty'' lyrics themselves.
   About 400 people showed up for the later, adults-only ``nasty''
set early Sunday.
   In nearby Miami Beach on Friday night, 2 Live Crew performed the
``nasty'' lyrics at another adults-only nightclub show. That
performance went off without incident or arrest, despite the fact
that the club was in Dade County and therefore covered by the
judge's ruling. The ruling declared the recording obscene in
Broward, Dade and Palm Beach counties.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0056 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 2123EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Nicaragua-Contras     06-10 0402</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Nicaragua-Contras,0419</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rebels Prefer Home to Development Centers</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By FILADELFO ALEMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>EL ALMENDRO, Nicaragua (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Contra rebels demobilizing after a
9-year-war are shunning development centers the government
established as part of a peace agreement. Instead, they're going
back home.
   ``Very few of us are going to go to the center because we prefer
to see our people, whom we've gone years without seeing,'' said
Filemon Cruz Lopez, an 18-year-old who said he joined the rebels
eight years ago.
   ``We want to know what has happened in our homes,'' he said.
   Cruz was one of about 800 Contras, including six commanders, who
turned in their weapons Saturday in a mass demobilization attended
by President Violeta Barrios de Chamorro and Managua archbishop
Cardinal Miguel Obando y Bravo.
   Despite the last-minute push, the rebels did not meet the Sunday
deadline they had agreed to for completion of the demobilization.
   Officials of the U.N. Central American peacekeeping force and
the International Verification and Support Commission, which are
overseeing the demobilization, said Saturday it would take about 10
days before all the fighters are disarmed.
   Demobilization began May 7 under an agreement between the rebels
and the government, but the process had been twice suspended.
   Waiting in line to turn in his AK-47 rifle to the U.N. troops,
Cruz said he would return to Susucayan, in the northern province of
Nueva Segovia, to work with his father, a farmer.
   Daniel Lozano, chief of operations for the verification
commission said: ``Only 10 percent of the demobilized and disarmed
rebels here have said they want to go to the development poles. The
rest prefer that we take them home.''
   Sonia Blandon, 19, said she turned in her weapons three days ago
and was going to live in Las Colinas, two miles south of El
Almendro.
   ``I have family that has lived here always. In addition, I have
nothing to fear. The army has left also,'' she said.
   The government agreed to create more than 20 development centers
in war zones and invested $47 million in U.S. aid in economic and
social infrastructure.
   Manuel Garay, a 36-year-old rebel fighter and former farmer from
Plan de Grama, Jinotega, said he expected few problems when he
returned home.
   ``I haven't done anything bad to anyone from my place,'' he
said. I don't owe anyone anything there. I believe I can return and
go back to my work.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0057 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 2131EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Britain-Blast 2ndLd-Writethru a0690 06-10 0611</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Britain-Blast, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0690,0627</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bomb At Army Barracks Injures 17; Another Explosion in NIreland</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 4 grafs to UPDATE with explosion in Northern
Ireland. Pickup 4th pvs, ``This should...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By LESLIE SHEPHERD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A bomb exploded in a military barracks rented for
a birthday party, injuring 17 people, and police said Sunday the
attack had ``all the hallmarks of the IRA.''
   The explosion came just before midnight Saturday at the
Honorable Artillery Company barracks, a turreted Victorian building
near London's financial district. All of those injured were
civilians.
   In Northern Ireland, an off-duty member of the Ulster Defense
Regiment was seriously injured Sunday when a bomb exploded beneath
his car, the Royal Ulster Constabulary said. No group claimed
responsibility, but members of the locally raised British army
regiment have been targets of frequent Irish Repubican Army attacks.
   There also was no claim of responsibility for the bombing in
London, but police said it was similar to previous attacks by the
IRA, which targets British soldiers and military installations.
   ``This should invoke abject contempt for the IRA throughout the
whole of the United Kingdom and the Republic of Ireland,'' Prime
Minister Margaret Thatcher told reporters on a flight back from a
four-day visit to the Soviet Union.
   Scotland Yard said London blast was caused by a ``bomb of some
sort.'' Detective Chief Superintendent Derek Willison, deputy head
of the police force's anti-terrorist squad, said the device had
been planted on the roof of the building in the previous 24 hours.
   The explosion ripped through the ceiling of the third-floor bar
below, showering shattered glass and debris on the 30 guests
attending the black-tie party.
   Twelve women and five men were treated for cuts and shock at
nearby St. Bartholomew's Hospital and released. Hospital spokesman
David Dalton said two women were kept overnight for observation of
possible concussions.
   If the explosion was the work of the IRA, it would be the latest
in a series of attacks that have been aimed at military targets but
have killed or injured civilians.
   In the last two weeks, the IRA has killed six people, including
two Australian lawyers who were shot to death in the Netherlands.
The IRA later said it mistook them for British soldiers.
   It also has killed a British army recruit who was standing on a
train platform, a British army major in West Germany and a retired
reserve policeman and his wife in Belfast.
   The IRA wants to end British rule over Northern Ireland and
unite the predominantly Protestant province with the mainly Roman
Catholic Republic of Ireland.
   Police said the only connection between Saturday's party and the
military was that the host's father was a member of the army
reserves. It was a 21st birthday party for a Cambridge University
law student, Mark Venn.
   Capt. David Venn said his son's party had been held in another
part of the building and guests decided to have a nightcap at the
bar before going home.
   ``I was standing by the bar getting some drinks when there was
an explosion and a flash of light. I looked at the floor _ pieces
of glass, bits of plaster,'' he said.
   The barracks' bar was not open to the general public, and on
most Saturday nights it is full of reserve soldiers.
   ``There was no warning and there has been no claim, so it is
hard to say, but it has all the hallmarks of the IRA,'' said
Willison, the detective.
   The Honorable Artillery Company is part of Britain's volunteer
reserve force, which can be called on in time of national emergency
to reinforce the full-time army.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0058 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 2140EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Philippines     06-10 0338</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Philippines,0352</SECOND>
<HEAD>Few U.S. Servicemen Take Offer To Return Dependents</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MANILA, Philippines (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   About 210 U.S. military personnel
have asked to send their families home from the Philippines because
of threats by Communist rebels to kill Americans, a military
spokesman said Monday.
   Air Force spokesman Lt. Col. Ron Rand said as of Thursday, about
150 service members at Clark Air Base and 60 at Subic Bay naval
base had taken advantage of the special offer to send dependents
home at government expense before their tour of duty is over.
   He said that represented about 3 percent of those eligible at
Clark and less than 2 percent at Subic. The offer was made earlier
this month by Adm. Huntington Hardisty, commander of U.S. Forces in
the Pacific.
   Rand said there has been no time limit set on the offer.
   Hardisty made the offer after Communist rebels killed two U.S.
airmen on May 13 near Clark Air Base, 50 miles north of Manila. A
Marine was killed near Subic naval base a week earlier, but police
said the motive was robbery.
   The Marxist New People's Army has vowed to kill Americans until
all U.S. troops leave the Philippines. The United States maintains
about 40,000 troops, Defense Department civilians and military
dependents at six installations here.
   U.S. personnel have been barred from leaving Clark Air Base
because of the security threat.
   The New People's Army has been waging a 21-year-old insurgency
to establish a Marxist state.
   Also Monday, two gunmen shot and killed the personnel chief of
the Philippine military's Narcotics Command in an ambush near his
home in suburban Paranaque, police said.
   Col. Rogelio Dumlao was driving to work when two gunmen with .45
caliber pistols opened fire, killing him instantly, police said.
   The police Capital Command said they were uncertain whether the
assailants were Communist rebels or common criminals.
   The Nacotics Command not only tracks down drug offenders but has
been used to hunt right-wing military dissidents responsible for
the six coup attempts against President Corazon Aquino.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0059 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 2144EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Afghanistan-Crash     06-10 0081</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Afghanistan-Crash,0085</SECOND>
<HEAD>Jet Fighter Crashes In Residential Area, Seven Killed</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ISLAMABAD, Pakistan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An Afghan air force jet crashed into
a densely populated neighborhood in the Afghan capital Sunday,
killing the pilot and six other people, state radio reported.
   Kabul Radio said the jet fighter crashed in Macrorayon, or
``small town,'' an area of apartments constructed by the Soviet
Union. Several apartments were badly damaged and three vehicles
caught fire, the radio said.
   The report gave no other details.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0060 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 2147EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-HongKong-Gold     06-10 0033</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Hong Kong-Gold,0034</SECOND>
<HEAD>Gold Opens Lower in Hong Kong</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HONG KONG (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Gold dropped 61 cents an ounce on Hong Kong
markets Monday, opening at $356.07. It closed at $356.68 Saturday.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0061 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 2206EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-EastBlocElections 1stLd-Writethru a0692 06-10 0474</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-East Bloc Elections, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0692,0486</SECOND>
<HEAD>New Governments Have Some Echos of Prewar Past</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with six grafs to UPDATE with Socialists ahead in
Bulgaria; pickup graf 7, `In Poland...'</NOTE>
<HEAD>With AM-Czechoslovakia, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GEORGE JAHN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PRAGUE, Czechoslovakia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Eastern Europe's first free
elections in decades have largely silenced the Communists, but not
old strains of nationalism and other familiar songs of a more
distant past.
   During the past last months, elections have been held in East
Germany, Hungary, Romania, Czechoslovakia and Bulgaria, with much
of the balloting coming on the heels of revolution.
   In Czechoslovakia, official results Sunday showed Civic Forum
and its sister organization _ Public Against Violence _ won free
elections on Friday and Saturday. The two paries spearheaded
November's pro-democracy revolution.
   To many people in Prague, Civic Forum's founder, Vaclav Havel _
a prominent playwright and former dissident _ evokes memories of
Tomas Garrigue Masaryk, who founded an independent Czechoslovakia
in 1918.
   In Bulgaria, reform Communists who recast themselves as
Socialist Party members took a commanding lead over the opposition
in initial projections of Sunday's vote. It was Bulgaria's first
free elections in 58 years.
   A Socialist victory in Bulgaria would be a return to the prewar
past. Bulgaria's Communist Party was even older than its Soviet
counterpart and was a strong political presence in Bulgaria for
nearly 100 years.
   In Poland, as elsewhere, popular pressure forced the Communists
to loosen their grip on power. After partially free elections last
year, Poland's government fell to control by Solidarity, the
broad-based movement born of labor unrest in 1980.
   After being suppressed along with Solidarity, the Roman Catholic
Church _ as it was in the past _ is again a powerful political
force.
   The picture is clouded in Romania. Although the Communist Party
formally collapsed in the wake of the bloody December uprising that
toppled dictator Nicolae Ceausescu, former Communist officials
dominate the freely elected National Front government.
   But other aspects of the Romanian political scene are
reminiscient of earlier times.
   Supporters of President Ion Iliescu paid him the kind of the
homage normally accorded to past dictators. One slogan displayed by
supporters was: ``Iliescu, When You Appear The Sun Shines.''
   Hungary's first post-Communist government is that of Prime
Minister Jozsef Antall's Democratic Forum, which won the March 25
elections on a platform of democracy.
   Antall placed heavy emphais on Hungarian pride in national
traditions and customs shared by no other people. That was reminder
of leaders past, including Miklos Horthy, who came to power in the
1930s and also played on nationalist concerns.
   The transition back to the future is perhaps most palpable for
East Germans.
   After a popular movement forced out longtime Communist
authorities, they are readying for union with West Germany,
creating one Germany for the first time since World War II.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0062 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 2221EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Soviet-Space     06-10 0188</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Space,0196</SECOND>
<HEAD>New Module Docks with Space Station</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A high-technology module intended to help produce
semi-conductors docked Sunday with the Soviet space station Mir,
the Tass news agency said.
   The Kristall module was launched from the Baikonur site in
Soviet Central Asia on May 31, but problems with its docking
engines had prevented previous attempts to attach it to the Mir
complex, manned by cosmonauts Anatoly Solovyov and Alexander
Balandin.
   The launch also had been delayed a few times in recent days
because of computer problems, Tass said.
   Approach and docking were controled by scientists on the ground
and was completed Sunday afternoon.
   Kristall ``is intended for the production of high-quality
semiconductors in conditions of weightlessness for the radio
electronic industry,'' Tass said.
   It also contains equipment to conduct astrophysical,
geophysical, biological and biotechnological experiments, Tass said.
   Semiconductors produced in zero gravity can be used in solar
batteries aboard Mir, Tass said. The Kristall module reportedly
contains enough material to produce several solar battery elements.
   Scientists want to compare the quality of the material produced
in orbit with that manufactured on Earth, Tass said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0063 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 2226EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-TankerBlast 5thLd-Writethru a0732 06-10 0855</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Tanker Blast, 5th Ld-Writethru, a0732,0875</SECOND>
<HEAD>New Explosions Hit Fire-Ravaged Supertanker</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: RECASTS lead. INSERTS 1 graf after 7th graf, ``There
certainly ...,' to UPDATE with stern stabilized; picks up 8th graf,
`The latest ...' INSERTS 2 grafs after 11th graf, `Thousands of
...,' to UPDATE with airplane dropping dispersant, oil distributor
to pay for cleanup; picks up 12th graf, `Seventeen of ...'</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto HT4, LaserColor HT2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MICHAEL GRACZYK</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>GALVESTON, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A series of powerful explosions Sunday
aboard a blazing supertanker that was carrying 38 million gallons
of oil sent burning crude spilling into the water, officials said.
   ``This is a real big one,'' Coast Guard Chief Petty Officer Todd
Nelson said. ``We've got burning crude oil rolling off the stern
into the water.'' Authorities also said they were concerned that
the ship's stern appeared to be listing.
   The five explosions hit nearly 1{ days after a blast and fire
killed at least two crew members and forced evacuation of the
853-foot-long Norwegian tanker Mega Borg in the Gulf of Mexico.
They were the latest in a series of smaller explosions that began
Saturday afternoon.
   The ship's stern, where the fire was concentrated, has dropped
by 58 feet since the first explosion Saturday, indicating either
that the cargo had shifted or the Mega Borg was taking on water,
Coast Guard Lt. Cmdr. Frank Whipple told a Sunday evening news
conference.
   ``We're uncertain what that means,'' Whipple said earlier.
   ``It's not good,'' said Nelson. ``We don't know the possibility
of it sinking.
   ``There certainly is a larger chance of the ship sinking than
before the explosions,'' he said. ``We're still optimistic that the
ship and cargo can be saved if there is an effective firefighting
operation.''
   By 9 p.m., the stern had stablized at 5 feet above the
waterline, said Coast Guard Petty Officer Howard J. Holmes.
   The latest blasts, which began late in the morning and ended
around 12:30 p.m., came shortly after members of a salvage team
boarded the crippled ship to begin a full-scale assault on the
blaze. They were off the ship before the blasts began, and there
were no reports of injuries.
   Members of the Smit America Galveston Bay Salvage Team, hired by
the ship's owners, were able to shut off some valves to the ship's
tanks, Whipple told an earlier briefing.
   A spill about one mile long north of the vessel and one about 20
miles long to the south were visible Sunday evening. Prevailing
currents and winds were expected to push the oil towards a 150- to
200-mile stretch of Texas coast between Freeport and Corpus Christi.
   Thousands of feet of containment booms were being brought in as
a precaution in case a larger spill developed. The tanker, 57 miles
southeast of Galveston, held 38 million gallons of light crude oil.
   A commercial C-130 airplane dropped dispersant over parts of the
spill within a five-mile radius of the tanker late Sunday, Holmes
said. Dispersants are used to make oil break up more quickly.
   ELF, a Houston-based oil distributor that was going to market
the Mega Borg's cargo, is paying for the cleanup, Holmes said.
   Seventeen of the 41 crew members rescued were injured, none
seriously, in Saturday's explosion. Two remained hospitalized
Sunday in good condition.
   The Coast Guard's Atlantic Strike Team from Mobile, Ala., and
other spill response groups brought a high-seas barrier boom and
other supplies, including foam, to the ship.
   Four Coast Guard cutters were in place around the supertanker
Sunday, Whipple said. Two Smit America ships were spraying water on
the Mega Borg's deck to keep the ship as cool as possible, while
two other salvage team ships were in position.
   Whipple said a full-fledged assault on the fire was scheduled
for early Monday morning, when two other Smit America ships were
expected to arrive at the scene. The full complement of salvage
ships was expected to blanket the aft section with
fire-extinguishing foam.
   The Mega Borg's owners also have contracted for an airplane to
spread dispersants over about 7,000 gallons of oil spilled so far,
Nelson said.
   Fireboats worked through Saturday night spraying water to cool
the decks of the supertanker, said Petty Officer Richard Miled in
Galveston. There were several minor explosions overnight, he said.
   Flames shot hundreds of feet high from the ship's air vents and
thick, black smoke could be seen from 40 miles away after the
engine room explosion at 1 a.m. Saturday.
   In addition to the two confirmed dead, two other crewmen
remained missing Sunday and were presumed dead after a search for
them was called off. Coast Guard Chief Petty Officer Rich Muller
said the missing men from the crew of 41 were probably still aboard
the ship.
   The blast occurred as part of its cargo was being transferred to
a smaller tanker.
   The tanker, operated by Mosvolds Shipping of Farsund, Norway,
was bound from Palanca, Angola. It was scheduled to travel to Aruba
after its Galveston port of call.
   A telephone message left Sunday seeking comment from the Mega
Borg's U.S. agent, Biehl and Co. of Galveston, was not immediately
returned.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0064 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 2236EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Peru-Election 5rdLd-Writethru a0764 06-10 0874</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Peru-Election, 5rd Ld-Writethru, a0764,0905</SECOND>
<HEAD>Fujimori Wins in Peru, Vargas Llosa Concedes</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 11th pvs, `Vargas Llosa's...' to CORRECT spelling of
aide to Barnachea. Pickup 12th, ``It has...'</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos LIM1,3</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MONTE HAYES</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LIMA, Peru (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Alberto Fujimori, a political unknown four
months ago, soundly defeated celebrated novelist Mario Vargas Llosa
in a presidential runoff Sunday and promised to improve the economy
of this bankrupt nation.
   Vargas Llosa conceded defeat. He wished Fujimori success in
trying to turn the country around, fight drug trafficking and
battle a decade-old guerrilla insurgency.
   Voting took place despite a wave of attacks in one Andean region
by Maoist guerrillas who had vowed to sabotage the balloting. One
voting station was bombed, and at least five people were killed and
eight injured in separate attacks.
   Exit polls gave Fujimori, 51, an agricultural engineer and
former university rector, a 13-to-19 point lead.
   The projections ``give us overwhelming support,'' Fujimori said
at a news conference two hours after polls closed. He invited all
political parties to participate in his government in areas where
agreements could be reached.
   He said he recognized the ``titanic task'' of governing Peru and
invited all political parties to participate in his government in
areas where agreements could be reached.
   Fujimori said his government would stress economic development
over military and police repression as the best way to fight both
leftist subversion and cocaine trafficking.
   He did not indicate where the money would come from for economic
development. The treasury is running a $100 million current
deficit, and the nation has a $20 billion foreign debt.
   Before 1,000 supporters outside his campaign headquarters,
Vargas Llosa conceded, wishing Fujimori ``success in the difficult
responsibility the Peruvian people have placed on him.''
   ``Respectful of democratic traditions, I accept the decision of
the Peruvian people.''
   Vargas Llosa's chief political aide, Alfredo Barnechea, called
it a protest vote.
   ``It has not been a vote for a political program but a vote to
stop Mario Vargas Llosa,'' Barnechea said after the televised
projections were released.
   Fujimori, the son of Japanese immigrants, was vying with the
center-right Vargas Llosa to replace populist Alan Garcia, whose
five-year term ends July 28. Garcia, leader of the Aprista Party,
is ineligible to serve a consecutive term.
   The election comes as Peru is weathering its worst economic
crisis of the century. The impoverished Andean nation also is being
bloodied by the savage, leftist insurgency that has claimed nearly
20,000 lives.
   The independent polling firm Apoyo gave Fujimori 51.1 percent to
37.8 percent for Vargas Llosa, with 11.1 percent blank and null
votes. POP, another independent polling firm, showed Fujimori with
56 percent and Vargas Llosa 36.5 percent. POP put blank and null
votes at 7.5 percent.
   Both firms based their projections on 100 percent of the vote
nationwide. Both firms said their surveys had a 3 percent margin of
error.
   The polls closed at 3 p.m. local time (4 p.m. EDT). Official
returns were not expected for at least three weeks because of poor
communication with mountain and jungle regions.
   Nearly 10 million Peruvians are registered to vote, and the law
requires them to cast ballots.
   As the polls opened Sunday morning, armored helicopters
crisscrossed Lima's sunny skies. Tanks and troop carriers patrolled
the streets of the capital, home to a third of Peru's 22 million
people.
   The Shining Path guerrillas, a Maoist group, bombed a polling
station and killed at least one voter in Huancayo, a rebel
stronghold in the Andes mountains, reporters there said.
   Guerrillas exploded at least nine other bombs in the city 120
miles east of Lima, police said. Voter turnout was very low in the
city of 100,000.
   In a separate attack, rebels Sunday shot and killed three
brothers, police said. A note found on one of the bodies said,
``This is how informers die.''
   The body of a fourth man was found Sunday, police said. They
said they had no further information.
   Rebel threats crippled transportation in three other mountain
cities.
   Vargas Llosa, 54, ran on a free-market platform. He pledged
harsh austerity measures to revive Peru's moribund economy and ease
hyperinflation, running at 2,000 percent annually.
   Fujimori, is an independent like Vargas Llosa. He called for
food subsidies and price controls and attacked Vargas Llosa's
proposal for an economic ``shock'' program.
   Support for Vargas Llosa and Fujimori was deeply divided along
class and geographical lines, polls indicated.
   Vargas Llosa was favored to win the April 8 first round, but
Fujimori's popularity surged. Fujimori took a close second in the
field of nine candidates and forced a runoff by denying Vargas
Llosa a majority.
   Some pollsters said voters were inclined to cast a vote based on
their opposition to one of the candidates.
   ``I'm voting for a Peruvian, not a Japanese,'' said Norma
Olivas, a nurse, referring to Fujimori's Japanese roots.
   But Edith Vargas, who runs a curbside sandwich stand, cast her
vote for Fujimori, saying: ``Vargas Llosa is in debt to the people
with money, the capitalists.''
   In some areas of the country, election officials suspended the
requirement that voters dip their index fingers into indelible ink
after casting ballots.
   In past elections, rebels have sometimes cut off the fingers of
people who voted.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0065 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 2243EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-WorldCup-Clash     06-10 0355</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-World Cup-Clash,0367</SECOND>
<HEAD>English, Irish, German Fans Clash With Police in Italy</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: A version has also been filed on the sports wire</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By VICTOR L. SIMPSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CAGLIARI, Italy (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Riot police wielding batons clashed with
groups of rowdy English-speaking soccer fans in a series of
skirmishes Sunday night on the eve of a World Cup game between
England and Ireland.
   Earlier Sunday, police in Milan in northern Italy clashed with a
group of apparently drunken German soccer fans before West
Germany's match against Yugoslavia.
   At least 23 people were reported injured and 39 fans detained in
the clashes in Milan and in the city of Cagliari, on the island of
Sardinia.
   In Cagliari, baton-wielding police charged into crowds of soccer
fans gathered Sunday night on the main streets. The fans ran from
the police, but at least three young men were taken from the scene
in police cars.
   A police officer, who refused to give his name in keeping with
Italian practice, said the authorities moved in to disperse the
crowds of soccer fans after one of the fans threw a bottle and hit
a woman in the head.
   At least 23 people, including eight police officers were injured
and 36 taken into custody during the clashes in downtown Milan,
police said.
   The skirmishes in Cagliari came late Sunday night after a day of
calm on the eve of Monday's match between England and Ireland.
Italian authorities had sent an additional 3,200 police to Sardinia
because they feared that English fans, notorious for being rowdy,
would turn violent.
   The three men who were picked up were not immediately identified
by either name or nationality by the authorities.
   Fourteen English fans arrested Friday for street violence
remained in custody and British authorities told their Italian
counterparts that eight of the fans had previous police records,
the Italian news agency ANSA reported.
   Some 8,000 English fans were expected in Sardinia for the match
with Ireland.
   English club teams have been barred from European cup
competitions since Liverpool and Juventus fans rioted during a 1985
match in Brussels. Thirty-nine people were killed.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0066 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 2249EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Bulgaria-Elections 3rdLd-Writethru a0748 06-10 0716</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bulgaria-Elections, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0748,0740</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bulgarians Vote in First Free Elections in 58 Years</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: INSERTS two grafs after 6th graf, `The Communist...' to ADD
background on opposition party. Pickup pvs 7th graf, `The
Association...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By ROLAND PRINZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SOFIA, Bulgaria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The ruling Socialist Party, formerly the
Communist Party, held a commanding lead over the opposition in
initial projections of Sunday's voting in Bulgaria's first free
elections in 58 years.
   The winner in the balloting will set the tone for what is
expected to be a coalition government.
   The ruling Socialist Party, formerly the Communist Party and
once Moscow's most loyal follower, favors slow economic reforms.
The main opposition alliance, the Union of Democratic Forces, wants
a swift move to a Western-style market economy.
   Reform Communist leaders such as President Petar Mladenov and
Defense Minister Dobri Dzhurov enjoy considerable popularity after
ousting longtime dictator Todor Zhivkov in November.
   In Bulgaria, unlike other East bloc countries where street
demonstrations brought down Communist regimes, reform Communists
engineered the nation's drive to democracy.
   The Communist Party also has a long and successful tradition in
Bulgaria. The party predates its Soviet counterpart and captured 20
percent of the vote in the nation's last free elections in 1932.
   Political observers said the Union of Democratic Forces lost
potential supporters because of its poor leadership.
   In one instance, coalition leeder Zhelyu Zhelev refused on
nationwide television to sign an agreement with the Socialists for
a peaceful campaign. The pact had previously been initialed by
other leaders of the Democratic Forces.
   The Association for Free and Fair Elections, a Bulgarian
monitoring group, gave the Socialists 48.3 percent of the ballots
against 34.9 percent for the Union of Democratic Forces and 8.3
percent for the Agrarian Party. The association has 10,00 people
monitoring the elections.
   Its projection was based on results from 37.7 percent of the
vote cast in the 200 races that will be decided by a proportional
vote. The forecast was supported by the U.S. National Democratic
Institute for International Affairs.
   Half of parliament's 400 seats are allocated on the basis of
proportional representation while the other 200 go to candidates
who receive more than 50 percent of the vote in direct balloting.
   The West German polling organization Infas also said the
Socialists were leading the opposition coalition in the elections,
state media reported.
   In areas heavily populated by the 1.5 million ethnic Turk
minority, the Movement for Rights and Freedoms led by Ahmed Dogan
apparently received about 80 percent of the vote, the state BTA
news agency reported.
   BTA said final official results were expected to be released by
late Monday.
   The main task of the unicameral parliament, the Grand National
Assembly, will be to write a new constitution to usher in
democratic and economic reforms.
   The Central Electoral Commission said late Sunday that at least
84 percent of Bulgaria's 6.4-million eligible voters cast ballots.
   Bulgaria, a country of nearly 9 million, last held multiparty
elections in 1932.
   There were scattered reports of irregularities, including
allegations of stolen ballot papers and last-minute campaigning,
banned under electoral law. In some polling stations, voting was
suspended because of a shortage of ballot papers, officials said.
   Electoral Commission President Zhivko Stalev said voting was
only delayed to put new ballot papers in booths.
   ``Given the fact that these are the first free elections, and
against the background of the elections as a whole, I would say
that those minor infractions could not be regarded as something
discrediting the elections as a whole,'' he said.
   In the race, 3,143 candidates from 38 parties vied for seats in
the Grand National Assembly.
   Sofia residents began voting as soon as polls opened at 7 a.m.
The voting stations officially closed at 6 p.m. but remained open
in some areas so all those on line could cast ballots.
   Thousands of Bulgarian and foreign observers monitored the
voting.
   A runoff is set for June 17 in constituencies where no candidate
wins a majority.
   The assembly's goals will be to deal with growing inflation, a
$10 billion foreign debt and acute shortages of basic consumer
items including sugar and cheese.
   With Sunday's election, Bulgaria becomes the fifth Soviet bloc
nation to hold multiparty balloting in the last four months after
decades of one-party Communist rule.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0067 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 2252EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Panama-Endara     06-10 0299</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-Endara,0314</SECOND>
<HEAD>Panamanian President Marries Law Student</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ALINA GUERRERO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Guillero Endara married a
23-year-old law student Sunday, declaring he loves three things in
this world: God, the Panamanian people and his bride.
   Among the guests of honor at the 54-year-old president's wedding
were ambassadors of the United States, Latin American and European
countries. Endara was installed during the U.S. invasion of Panama
by U.S. forces that overthrew Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega.
   About 250 people waited outside the Metropolitan Cathedral in a
heavy rain to throw rice at the newlyweds when they emerged from
the two-hour, Roman Catholic ceremony.
   As the president and his bride, Ana Mae Diaz, made their way
from the church to the presidential palace next door, the
umbrella-carrying crowd chanted ``Congratulations!'' in unison.
Some shouted, ``Endara, friend, the people are on your side!''
   The couple met at a university rally after Panama's 1989
elections. Endara won that election, but Noriega annulled the
results. After the invasion, Noriega was brought back to the United
States to face drug-trafficking charges.
   Endara was widowed one year ago. He has a daughter, Marcela de
Yap, and a grandson Javier Yap, who was the ring bearer at the
ceremony.
   After the traditional ceremony, Diaz threw her bridal bouquet of
white flowers from the presidential palace's balcony to the crowd
below.
   Endara declared that there are three things he loves, ``God, the
Panamanian people and Ana Mae.''
   Endara and Diaz kissed eight times during and after the
ceremony, which was attended about 250 invited guests.
   Leaving the church, Diaz greeted wellwishers. ``I'm very
happy,'' she said. ``I'm going to work for the country.''
   Endara wore a black suit, white shirt and gray tie. The bride
wore a traditional white wedding gown.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0068 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 2257EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Japan-Election     06-10 0237</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Japan-Election ,0244</SECOND>
<HEAD>Opposition Socialists Win Special Japanese Election</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Japan's largest opposition party, the Socialists,
won a special election Sunday for a seat in Parliament's upper
house after campaigning for abolition of the sales tax.
   The voting was the first for a national office since the
governing Liberal Democrats won an election for the more powerful
lower house in February.
   In Sunday's vote, Socialist Shigeko Mieno defeated Norihiko
Sumiyoshi, who belongs to Prime Minister Toshiki Kaifu's party.
   With 95 percent of the vote counted, Ms. Mieno, 64, a former
member of the Chikushino municipal assembly, had 829,913 votes.
Sumiyoshi, a 43-year-old former member of the Fukuoka state
assembly, had 717,577 votes, the election committee said.
   The seat for southern Japan's Fukuoka state had been held by
Socialist Akira Ono, the upper house vice president, who died of
illness on April 19.
   Ono was elected for a six-year term in July, when the Liberal
Democrats lost their majority in the 252-seat upper house for the
first time in their party's 34-year history. The governing party
now has 110 seats, and the Socialists have 73.
   Ms. Mieno told reporters her victory resulted from her strong
appeals for abolition of a 3 percent sales tax imposed in April
1989. The tax was seen as a major factor in the Liberal Democrats'
upper house election loss in July.
   The Liberal Democrats have agreed to revise the tax.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0069 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 2258EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-EGermanLeader     06-10 0577</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-E German Leader,0594</SECOND>
<HEAD>East German Prime Minister Addresses World Jewish Congress</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RAUL REYES</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   East German Prime Minister Lothar de Maiziere
said Sunday he understands Jewish concerns about a unified Germany,
but said they are unfounded in this new era.
   ``Against the background of the past, I have full understanding
for many Jewish citizens' anxieties for a united Germany,'' de
Maiziere said in a speech to members of the World Jewish Congress.
   ``Nevertheless, I wish to emphasize: no one needs to have
misgivings or even fears of a united Germany,'' he said. ``Germany
today is totally different from Germany between 1933 and 1945.''
   ``National socialism, as all dictatorships, could flourish only
behind curtains of whatever kind. There can be no torture chamber
in a common European home with all its doors and windows widely
opened to all sides,'' de Maiziere said.
   The World Jewish Congress, which represents Jewish organizations
in 70 countries, released de Maiziere's speech translated into
English.
   Before the dinner, de Maiziere met privately with congress
President Edgar Bronfman, and the two held a joint news conference.
   Bronfman said he was not overly concerned a united Germany might
theaten the Jewish people.
   ``But being a Jew,'' he added, ``and having lived through the
(Nazi) era, I'm never going to be totally relaxed about the
situation.''
   Through a translator, de Maiziere said Nazi-type atrocities
``are possible only under a totalitarian system and I suppose, as
far as totalitarian regimes are concerned, we have thoroughly
learned our lesson.''
   De Maiziere was in New York to meet with representatives of the
Conference on Jewish Material Claims, set up in 1951 to negotiate
reparations to Israel for the deaths of 6 million Jews at Nazi
hands.
   ``To us, attention to our Jewish fellow citizens is not an issue
of social services or budgeting; it is a matter near to our
heart,'' de Maiziere said in his speech. ``We shall, as soon as
possible, provide the general conditions for specific negotiations
on indemnification.''
   The East German compensation could reach into the billions of
dollars, but might be limited by the country's financial problems.
   East Germany ended nearly 45 years of communist rule with its
first free elections in March, and is uniting with West
Germany.Economic union is scheduled for completion by July, and
West Germany is expected to assume many of its financially strapped
neighbor's liabilities.
   Under a 1952 agreement, West Germany has paid more than $40
billion in reparations to Israel, Jewish groups and individual
claimants.
   The Luxembourg Agreement called for West Germany to pay
two-thirds of the total compensation.
   But East Germany's communist leaders, citing Nazi persecution of
communists, refused to accept responsibility or pay the remaining
third of the claims. After World War II, East Germany was dominated
by the Soviet Union, which lost at least 20 million lives to the
Nazis.
   One of the first acts of the new democratic East German
parliament was to concede a share of the blame for the Nazis' deeds.
   ``All we can do is to try to learn our lesson from that period
in German history and to keep alive memory of the victims and to
fight passionately even the slightest manifestation of
anti-Semitism, racism in general and xenophobia wherever they may
crop up,'' said de Maiziere.
   On Monday, he was to head to Washington for the first White
House meeting between an East German prime minister and a U.S.
president.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0070 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 2305EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-GroundedTanker     06-10 0402</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Grounded Tanker,0411</SECOND>
<HEAD>Oil From Spill Reaches Sandy Hook</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Tanker Blast, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JEFFREY GOLD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEWARK, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Tar balls from a major oil spill washed up
on a New Jersey beach about 25 miles away Sunday, but the Coast
Guard increased its estimate of how much oil will be recovered.
   A significant quantity of tar balls hit about a mile of Sandy
Hook beach on Sunday, said Manny Strumpf, a spokesman for the
Gateway National Recreation Area. The beach was closed to visitors
during cleanup.
   Tar-like balls found Saturday on another beach nearby were being
analyzed to determine if they came from the spill, said David
Roach, city health officer of Long Branch, several miles south of
Sandy Hook.
   Coast Guard Capt. Robert North said the cleanup will recover
more than half the 260,000 gallons that leaked Thursday from the
British tanker BT Nautilus into a heavily used shipping channel
between Bayonne and the New York City borough of Staten Island.
   Hundreds of workers using five vacuum trucks, miles of
containment booms and about 80 vessels have already recovered
104,000 gallons of the heavy industrial fuel from the shores and
waters of the Kill Van Kull, the Coast Guard said.
   Usually less than 20 percent of a spill is recovered, but cool
weather and cool water, which congealed the oil, plus a swift
response, helped the cleanup, said Coast Guard Lt. Cmdr. Paul A.
Milligan.
   The heavy No. 6 heating oil does not evaporate quickly, and
workers were able to keep most of it boomed against the Bayonne
shore, where vacuum trucks could suck it out of the water, he said.
   The busy Kill Van Kull fully re-opened to shipping Sunday
morning.
   Oil was found washed up Friday and Saturday on several New York
City beaches, including 800 pounds of oil globs on one Staten
Island beach alone, but none was closed Sunday, Strumpf said.
   A Coast Guard board of inquiry was to begin hearings Monday on
the Nautilus grounding and other incidents which, since Jan. 1,
have dumped more than 1 million gallons of oil into the waters of
New York harbor, four times the amount spilled last year.
   New Jersey and New York also were investigating the Nautilus
grounding. Nautilus first mate Geoffrey Frederick Gregory of
England was charged in New Jersey with operating a vessel under the
influence of alcohol or drugs.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0071 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 2311EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Korea-US     06-10 0312</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Korea-US,0325</SECOND>
<HEAD>Radicals Say Death Squads Formed to Kidnap U.S. Ambassador</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KELLY SMITH TUNNEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SEOUL, South Korea (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Thousands of militant students staged
violent anti-government protests Sunday and radicals said ``death
squads'' have been formed to kidnap the U.S. ambassador.
   About 9,000 students threw firebombs and stones at police in
Seoul and six other cities Sunday to mark the anniversary of 1987
anti-government protests that brought widespread democratic reform.
   ``Drive out U.S. troops,'' screamed radicals hurling firebombs
at police. ``Overthrow (President) Roh Tae-woo!''
   At least six students were injured and about 200 arrested
nationwide, the Yonhap news agency reported.
   In Seoul, radical leaders told The Associated Press that
students in Kwangju have formed ``death squads'' to kidnap U.S.
Ambassador Donald P. Gregg and block the reopening of a U.S.
cultural center.
   At least 60 students in Kwangju have volunteered for the squads,
said one radical student leader, speaking on condition of anonymity.
   Gregg, a former CIA station chief in Seoul and aide to then-Vice
President Bush during the Iran-Contra affair, was scheduled to fly
to the southern city of Kwangju on Monday to reopen the center at a
new location. The center was closed after sustaining 29 attacks
over 10 years by protesters hurling stones and firebombs.
   ``We will not allow the U.S. imperialists to reopen the cultural
center,'' the student said.
   Three students wrapped in South Korean flags were arrested
Sunday about 100 yards from the cultural center after scattering
anti-American leaflets, Yonhap reported.
   In October, six students wielding iron pipes and homemade
explosives attacked Gregg's residence in Seoul. Gregg and his wife
were inside but escaped unharmed.
   Anti-American sentiment is particularly strong in Kwangju where
citizens claim Washington condoned the suppression of a 1980 civil
uprising against the martial law government. Some 200 civilians
were killed and at least 1,700 injured in the uprising.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0072 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 2321EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Yacht-Americans 1stLd-Writethru a0642 06-10 0311</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Yacht-Americans, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0642,0320</SECOND>
<HEAD>American Sailors Rescued From Striken Yacht</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS thruout with quotes from survivor; ADDS details; no
pickup</NOTE>
<DATELINE>BRISBANE, Australia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two Florida women whose yacht lost
its mast in rough seas off Australia were rescued Sunday, an
official said.
   A Taiwanese cargo vessel picked up the women, and an Australian
army helicopter lifted them off the freighter's deck as the ship
was tossed by 10-foot waves and buffeted by 30 mph winds, the
official of Australia's Federal Sea Safety and Surveillance Center
said.
   Jeannie Talley and Joy-Beth Smith of Crescent City, Fla., had
radioed for help when the mast of their 36-foot yacht snapped on
Thursday.
   Ms. Talley was not seriously injured during the ordeal, but she
reported that her partner apparently broke her leg.
   The rescue occurred 400 miles off Australia's northern coast.
The women had been sailing in their yacht Banshee to Vanuatu, a
nation west of Fiji.
   After the rescue, the two Americans were taken by two Army
Blackhawk helicopters to the Rockhampton base hospital, about 320
miles north of Brisbane.
   Interviewed afterward, Ms. Talley said she suffered from shock
during the ordeal.
   ``It was the first time in my life I have ever been in shock,
and I did not realize it until I was going to go out on deck. ...''
she said. ``I just got outside the hatchway, and all of a sudden I
was paralyzed and weak.''
   ``It was not until the third try before I could go out,'' said
Ms. Talley, a sailor with 20 years' experience.
   She said the sea conditions were the worst she had ever seen.
   ``During the most intense part of the storm, we got rolled over
180 degrees,'' she said.
   Despite the scare, Ms. Talley said she and Ms. Smith plan to
rerig the boat and sail again when weather permits.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0073 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 2324EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-LinerGrounded 2ndLd-Writethru a0735 06-10 0596</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Liner Grounded, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0735,0610</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ocean Liner Runs Aground in Dense Fog; Passengers Evacuated</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: UPDATES throughout with ship freed, passengers arriving at
dock, going to hotels; CORRECTS name to `Scot,' sted `Scott;' EDITS
to tighten.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By FRANCIS HOPKINS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WOODS HOLE, Mass. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hundreds of cruise ship passengers had
to be ferried ashore Sunday after the ship ran aground in heavy fog
and began taking on water, but no injuries were reported.
   The 617-foot Bermuda Star's hull was holed in two places when it
slammed into submerged rocks about two miles from this village
seaport on the southwestern tip of Cape Cod, Coast Guard officials
said.
   None of the 680 passengers or 380 crew members was ever in
danger, said Coast Guard Lt. Peter Keane. ``There was no panic on
board,'' Keane said.
   Passengers, luggage and much of the crew were taken by
commercial ferries across Buzzards Bay to New Bedford. The first
crowded passenger ferry docked in a heavy downpour shortly before 7
p.m., where buses waited to whisk people to hotels in the Boston
area.
   ``We were standing at the information desk (on the boat) when we
heard this crunch,'' said passenger Wilfred Smith, 65, of Colorado,
as he stepped onto the New Bedford pier. ``I said to my wife, `We
hit something.'''
   Scot Graham, a Coast Guard marine safety officer in Providence,
R.I., said the ship was three hours ahead of schedule and off
course when it ran aground in the morning.
   ``I'm sure they didn't want to be where they were,'' Graham
said. ``They should have been more south.''
   Tugboats freed the ship from the rocks at 9:10 p.m., and it was
anchored in Buzzards Bay, where divers patched up the hull holes,
said Coast Guard Petty Officer 1st Class Dan Vineski.
   Earlier efforts to free the ship had been given up to await the
high tide.
   Vineski said moving the ship did not appear to worsen a fuel
spill. Graham said earlier that booms were used to contain an
estimated 1,000 to 1,500 gallons of fuel that spilled from the
ship's engine area, and workers used absorbent material to soak it
up.
   Leakage was stabilized by the vessel holding steady on the
rocks, said Coast Guard Petty Officer Greg Creedon. Flooding aboard
the ship was under control by midday.
   The accident canceled the cruise, but was considered relatively
minor. ``This is a kind of fender-bender for the marine world,''
Creedon said.
   Vineski said the ship's captain, whom he declined to identify,
and other crew members took blood and alcohol tests routinely
required after accidents. He said results were expected Monday.
   The accident occurred as the ship waited in the dense fog for
permission from the Army Corps of Engineers to enter the Cape Cod
Canal leading to Cape Cod Bay, Vineski said. It apparently strayed
too close to shore and ran aground in water less than 30 feet deep,
possibly on a rocky ledge.
   The Coast Guard got a distress call shortly after 8 a.m.,
Vineski said.
   Fog had cut visibility to about one quarter-mile when the
accident occurred, officials said.
   The ship was en route from New York to Halifax, Nova Scotia. A
stop had been planned for Sunday in Provincetown, on the north tip
of Cape Cod.
   The ship, owned by the Bermuda Star Cruise Lines and sailing
under a Panamanian flag, regularly cruises New England during the
summer between the Philadelphia-New York area and the Canadian
Maritimes.
   Woods Hole, near the island of Martha's Vineyard, is a major
center for marine research.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0074 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 2327EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-OhioFlooding     06-10 0315</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Ohio Flooding,0326</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ohio Flooding Shuts Down Section of Interstate</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BUCKEYE LAKE, Ohio (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   High water shut down several miles of
an interstate on Sunday after floodgates at Buckeye Lake were
opened to reduce lake levels, authorities said.
   The body of a man who went rafting down a tributary of the
rain-swollen Licking River was recovered from a logjam.
   About 3,000 people were temporarily evacuated from this central
Ohio village Saturday because of fears an aging retaining wall
would rupture and flood the area.
   ``It's looking a lot better today than yesterday,'' Mayor James
Bartoe said Sunday.
   The lake was 12 inches higher than normal, but had dropped 6
inches since Saturday's heavy rains, said Police Chief Ronald
Small. Floodgates were opened at the lake to relieve pressure on
the wall, sending water into the south fork of the Licking River,
making Interstate 70 to the north impassable.
   Recreational boating was banned on Buckeye Lake until further
notice, Small said.
   Dispatchers for the State Highway Patrol said I-70 was closed
periodically Saturday night and Sunday. The highway was reopened
late Sunday afternoon, said dispatcher Julie Miller.
   The body of Brian Hinger of Newark was recovered in a logjam in
the north fork of the Licking River north of Buckeye Lake near St.
Louisville, Newton Township Fire Chief Jim Glover said.
   Hinger, 21, and a friend had gone rafting Saturday night on an
inner tube when they were entangled in a logjam, Glover said. His
friend, Ardell Hollobaugh, 22, of Newark, was rescued.
   Both men were scuba divers and experience lifeguards, Glover
said.
   Robert Frey, an inspector with the Federal Emergency Management
Agency, examined flood damage Sunday and said he would recommend
that Licking County be declared a federal disaster area.
   Gov. Richard Celeste on Saturday declared Licking County in a
state of emergency, and asked President Bush to declare it a
disaster area.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0075 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 2334EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Obit-Caples     06-10 0233</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Caples,0241</SECOND>
<HEAD>Caples Who Wrote ``They Laughed When...'' Ad Dead at 90</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   John Caples, who as a young copywriter wrote one
of advertising's most famous lines _ ``They Laughed When I Sat Down
at the Piano...'' _ died Sunday. He was 90 years old.
   Caples, who lived in Manhattan, died at Lenox Hill Hospital.
   Caples wrote the famous headline in 1926 for the U.S. School of
Music. The entire headline read: ``They Laughed When I Sat Down At
The Piano...But When I Started To Play!''
   The ad was an instant success and spawned dozens of imitations
over the years that used ``They Laughed when...'' as the
introduction.
   Caples, who went on to become an expert in direct-response
advertising, had worked one year at Ruthrauff &amp; Ryan when he wrote
the famous ad.
   A year after the music school ad, Caples switched to Batten,
Barton, Durstine &amp; Osborn, where he spent the rest of his career.
He went on to become a vice president in 1941 and retired as
creative director in 1982.
   He wrote several books on advertising and was credited with
developing copy testing and research for advertising campaigns.
   The native New Yorker graduated from the Naval Academy in
Annapolis in 1924. He was called back into the Navy during World
War II, and rose to the rank of commander.
   Caples is survived by his wife, Dorothy.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0076 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 2337EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Salvador     06-10 0318</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Salvador,0326</SECOND>
<HEAD>Archbishop Appeals for End to Impunity</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SAN SALVADOR, El Salvador (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Archbishop of San Salvador
on Sunday accused police of torture and appealed for prosecution of
those who abuse human rights.
   ``There is a great clamor against the impunity that _ by the
design, tolerance and perhaps maliciousness of military and
judicial authorities _ reigns in the country,'' Archbishop Arturo
Rivera Damas said in his Sunday homily at the Sacred Heart basilica.
   Rivera Damas, the country's highest Roman Catholic authority,
also condemned the destruction of evidence in the case of six
Jesuit priests, their housekeeper and her daughter who were
murdered by soldiers last November. The Supreme Court said last
week that a lieutenant, one of nine soldiers charged with the
murders, burned pertinent military log books on orders from his
superior.
   ``This is a manifest abuse of power because arms are not in the
hands of the military to impede the functioning of justice, but
rather to assure the application of justice,'' the archbishop said
in comments to journalists following the Mass.
   Rivera Damas denounced what he said was the torture last week of
Carlos Gonzalez Perez by members of the National Guard, one of
three police forces.
   Gonzalez, a Spaniard, was arrested June 4 and held at National
Guard headquarters until he was released into the custody of the
Spanish Embassy on Thursday. No charges were filed against
Gonzalez, who reportedly was a social worker employed by the San
Salvador archdiocese.
   Rivera Damas used the word ``torture'' in describing the
treatment of Gonzalez, but gave no further details. Spanish
diplomatic sources said Gonzalez ``was in bad physical and
psychological shape'' when handed over to embassy personnel.
   Gonzalez was flown to Costa Rica, where he was hospitalized.
   Rivera Damas also condemned murders carried out by right-wing
and leftists hit squads. At least 71,000 people have died in the
decade long civil war.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0077 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 1820EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-DigestBriefs     06-10 0405</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Digest Briefs,0421</SECOND>
<NOTE>Eds: This package does not contain the following items from the
News Digest:
   WASHINGTON _ Animal Rights; MIAMI BEACH, Fla. _ 2 Live Crew;
GALVESTON, Texas _ Tanker Blast.
   ___</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ISLAMABAD, Pakistan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Gang violence in Prime Minister
Benazir Bhutto's home province has taken 400 lives in a month, and
many Pakistanis fear it endangers their country's brief experiment
with democracy.
   Ms. Bhutto, who campaigned for a decade to free Pakistan from
military rule, has been forced to call out the army in Sindh, her
native province in southern Pakistan.
   No one knows who is killing whom. Private armies, drug gangs and
ethnic militias operate at will. Kidnappings, indiscriminate
shootings and armed robbery are commonplace.
   Police have arrested more than 3,300 people in a weeklong sweep
of Sindh province, the heart of the country's financial and
industrial base.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>PRAGUE, Czechoslovakia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The two political groups that
broke the grip of Communist rule on Czechoslovakia won the first
free election in 44 years and on Sunday began considering possible
partners in a new coalition government.
   Official results showed that Civic Forum and Public Against
Violence _ the Czech and Slovak sister organizations that led
November's pro-democracy revolution _ had captured the most seats
in the new federal Parliament.
   The two movements won 169 of the 300 seats in the bicameral
Parliament, but they fell short of the three-fifths majority needed
to make key constitutional and economic reforms necessary to
fulfill the goals of the revolution.
   The Civic Forum, founded by President Vaclav Havel, had said
before the election on Friday and Saturday that it would seek a
coalition government.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Pizza makers are slinging the high-tech pie of
the 1990s across America _ nitrogen-frozen, credit-card ordered via
satellite and with pineapple and bacon on top.
   The state-of-the-art pizza methods _ all already in use _ were
touted over the weekend at the National Pizza and Fast Food Show in
Manhattan, where the American version of the Italian dish was
introduced in 1895.
   In Albuquerque, N.M., drive-up dining is a pizza order made
through a car window into a TV monitor at Nunzio's and, 60 seconds
later, a pie down a pneumaode to a satellite.
   And, from Murray Hill, N.J., Airco uses liquid nitrogen to chill
out the forgetful pizza lover who otherwise might reach into the
freezer past a pizza's prime.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0078 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 1925EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-DigestBriefs 1stAdd   06-10 0428</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Digest Briefs, 1st Add,0441</SECOND>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>GALVESTON, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A series of powerful explosions aboard
the burning supertanker Mega Borg on Sunday sent crude oil spilling
into the water and bursting into flames, authorities said.
   The five explosions, which ended at 12:30 p.m., came shortly
after members of a salvage team boarded the crippled ship to launch
the first step of a full-scale assault on the fire. They were off
the ship before the explosions began.
   ``This is a real big one,'' Coast Guard Chief Todd Nelson said.
``We've got burning crude oil rolling off the stern into the
water.'' Authorities also said they were concerned that the ship's
stern appeared to be listing.
   The latest series of five explosions struck nearly 1{ days after
an explosion and fire killed at least two crew members and forced
evacuation of the 853-foot-long Norwegian oil tanker in the Gulf of
Mexico. The blasts were part of a series of smaller explosions that
began Saturday afternoon.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>FORT LAUDERDALE, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A rap group kept its promise to
sing lyrics from an album ruled obscene and authorities kept their
word, arresting two members of 2 Live Crew on Sunday after an
adults-only concert.
   The early-morning arrests came four days after a federal judge
declared obscene the Miami group's album ``As Nasty As They Wanna
Be,'' and two days after a local record dealer was arrested for
selling the popular recording.
   Broward County sheriff's deputies arrested 2 Live Crew leader
Luther Campbell, 29, and singer Chris Wongwon, 26, shortly after
the show at a Hollywood nightclub.
   ``The deputies let them get a couple of blocks away from the
club and then they pulled the limousine over,'' said sheriff's
spokesman Al Gordon.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Thousands of animal rights activists rallied
in the nation's capital Sunday seeking to promote the humane
treatment of animals in the wild, on farms and in research
laboratories.
   Many marchers advocated an end to the use of animals in medical
research, a goal that top health officials say is misguided and
could end advances in medical research.
   U.S. Capitol Police estimated 24,000 people attended a rally on
the steps of the Capitol following the one-mile march down
Pennsylvania Avenue under sunny skies. But organizers claimed more
than 50,000 people from around the country showed up.
   Marchers chanted ``Animal Rights _ Now.''Many carried banners
and placards with pictures and slogans saying things such as
``Animals Are Not for Wearing,'' ``Fur Is Dead,'' and ``Animals
Have Rights, Too.'' Some even brought their dogs.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0079 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 1843EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-NoyceMemorial     06-10 0442</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Noyce Memorial,0462</SECOND>
<HEAD>Sematech Employees Bid Emotional Farewell to Noyce</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JAN RICH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>AUSTIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Employees of Sematech paid a final farewell to the
late Robert Noyce, the ``Father of Silicon Valley'' who led the
government-industry consortium in a bid to recapture chip-making
leadership for the United States.
   Nearly all 600 of Sematech's Austin employees turned out for
Saturday's ceremony, which company officials insisted on keeping
upbeat rather than somber.
   ``I think it's entirely appropriate for us to laugh this
morning, for us to applaud, for us to cry,'' said Charles Sporck,
Sematech chairman.
   Noyce revolutionized electronics by co-inventing the
semiconductor and later lobbied for the establishment of Sematech,
whose members include 14 leading U.S. semiconductor and computer
companies.
   Noyce, 62, died June 3 after suffering a heart attack at his
Austin home. About 800 people, including other chip industry
officials, Noyce family members, U.S. Rep. J.J. `Jake' Pickle, and
Japanese journalists paid their respects to Noyce.
   Sematech provided the crowd with breakfast rolls, punch and soft
drinks. Many executives also wore Noyce T-shirts, which proclaimed
the late executive a ``teen idol.''
   The ceremony also featured videos of the Silicon Valley pioneer
and testimonials from friends and family.
   ``His inventions literally changed life on this planet,'' said
Sematech spokesman Joe Stroop.
   Other employees were impressed with Noyce's ability to mingle
with them on the job. ``He ate in the cafeteria with us,'' said
Harriett Sickels, a manufacturing specialist.
   ``In most companies you don't even meet the CEO,'' added Ed
Sailor, an equipment maintenance specialist. ``We are a very close
group of people.''
   Kenji Fukasawa, Houston bureau chief of the Japan Economic
Journal, said Noyce enjoyed tremendous popularity in Japan. The
Japanese public has followed memorial events after his death very
closely as well as speculation about Sematech's future, he said.
   Noyce was slated to step down as Sematech chief executive before
his death. In April, a search began to replace Noyce, who had
agreed informally to be Sematech's chairman once a new chief
executive was chosen, Stroop said.
   After becoming chief executive in 1988, Noyce worked to gain
support for the research consortium both within the
microelectronics industry and in the federal government.
   Noyce and Jack S. Kilby, a scientist at Texas Instruments Inc.,
invented the integrated circuit in separate research efforts in the
late 1950s. At the time, Noyce was working for Fairchild
Semiconductor Corp.
   Their invention prompted rapid gains in computer technology by
putting the power of multiple transistors on a single chip. It
helped make possible personal computers, pocket calculators and
microwave ovens.
   Noyce co-founded Intel Corp., the nation's third-largest
semiconductor producer, in 1968.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0080 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 1847EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-Pathe-MGM     06-10 0227</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Pathe-MGM,0236</SECOND>
<HEAD>$50 Million Payment Brings Pathe's Deposits to $200 Million in
MGM-UA Bid</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BEVERLY HILLS, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Pathe Communications Corp. made the
final installment on a $200 million cash deposit toward its $1.2
billion purchase of MGM-UA Communications Co.
   Pathe made its fourth and final $50 million deposit Friday.
Under terms of the purchase agreement, the $200 million is
non-refundable.
   MGM-UA also has been guaranteed a return of $75 million from
distributing three upcoming Pathe films as part of the deal.
   The $20-a-share tender offer had been scheduled to close
Thursday, but Pathe exercised an option to extend it until next
Friday while trying to complete financing arrangements. Pathe can
extend it until June 23 under its agreement with Kirk Kerkorian,
the billionaire who controls MGM-UA.
   Many analysts and entertainment executives questioned whether
Pathe chief Giancarlo Parretti, an Italian financier who had tried
and failed to buy Hollywood companies in the past, could manage to
finance the MGM-UA deal.
   Time Warner Inc. has agreed to lend Pathe half the $1.2 billion,
with the valuable United Artists movie library as security.
Parretti said Thursday he is trying to renegotiate parts of that
agreement to get easier terms.
   Pathe says the balance of the money will be provided by
Comfinance S.A., Paretti's Luxembourg holding company, and other
European companies also controlled by Paretti and his associates.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0081 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 1849EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-A-12Delay     06-10 0201</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-A-12 Delay,0209</SECOND>
<HEAD>Contractors Say Secret Navy Plane Will Be Delayed</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ST. LOUIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The team of defense contractors building the
secret A-12 Navy attack plane says the plane will not be flying by
early next year as originally planned.
   The two St. Louis-base companies, General Dynamics Corp. and
McDonnell Douglas Corp., said in separate statements Friday that
``there will be a delay in the first flight of the aircraft beyond
early 1991 to later the same year.''
   The team said the program itself is sound, however.
   ``The schedule delays permit completing the strong technical
basis of the program before conclusion of final tooling and
production of the development test aircraft,'' General Dynamics
said in a terse statement.
   ``The A-12 industry team is confident that the desired
operational capabilities of the A-12 will be met,'' the company
said.
   ``Further detail is unavailable as the program is classified,
but General Dynamics emphasizes that the A-12 will be superb high
technology aircraft for the Navy.''
   Both companies said they are working on revised schedules and
new estimates of their costs to complete the program. That review,
said both industry giants, could result in substantial adverse
impacts on their second quarter earnings.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0082 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 1853EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-USAir     06-10 0273</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-USAir,0288</SECOND>
<HEAD>Carrier Will Delay Delivery of New Airplanes, Chairman Says</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PITTSBURGH (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The chairman of USAir Group Inc. said the
nation's seventh-largest airline will postpone delivery of a dozen
new aircraft for more than three years because of sluggish business.
   Chairman Edwin I. Colodny said Friday the airline would delay
delivery of the Boeing Co. planes from 1991-92 to 1995.
   ``The economy is soft. Travel is down,'' Colodny told reporters
after a luncheon meeting of the Greater Pittsburgh Chamber of
Commerce. ``I don't think we should fool ourselves and say
everything is rosy. It's not.''
   A Boeing spokesman expressed surprise at the news.
   ``I have never heard of a firm order being delayed like that,''
said Jack Gamble of Boeing Commercial Airplane Group.
   USAir spokesman John Bronson on Saturday confirmed Colodny's
statement and said the planes involved were all Boeing 737s.
   Bronson said the proposal to defer delivery until 1995 was
included in Colodny's recent letter to all USAir employees.
   In exchange for delaying the deliveries, USAir agreed to buy 24
more planes from the manufacturer and purchase options on 56 more
aircraft after 1995, Colodny said.
   USAir has one of the airline industry's younger fleets and will
delay retiring some planes, Colodny said.
   USAir lost $76 million in 1989 after 13 consecutive profitable
years. The airline lost $38 million in 1990's first quarter.
   In last year's annual report, the company said it had
commitments to buy five Boeing 767s before 1992 and 55 Boeing 737s
before 1993.
   Projected spending on new planes was $882 million this year,
$767 million in 1991 and $264 million in 1992, the report said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0083 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 1854EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-American-Attendants     06-10 0225</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-American-Attendants,0237</SECOND>
<HEAD>Airline, Flight Attendents End Hiring Dispute</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DALLAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   American Airlines and its flight attendants have
agreed to settle lawsuits stemming from the carrier's decision to
place foreign attendants on its Latin American routes, according to
a top union official.
   Under a compromise, the company will hire about 200 foreign
nationals as flight attendants on Latin American routes acquired
from Eastern Airlines.
   In turn, American has agreed to use more domestic attendants on
flights departing from its Miami hub to destinations in Central and
South American, according to Cheryle Leon, president of the
Association of Professional Flight Attendants.
   ``We feel it is a good agreement,'' Ms. Leon said.
   A spokeswoman for American reached Sunday said she couldn't
confirm details of the agreement.
   American had sued the union, seeking a court ruling to allow it
to hire foreign nationals. The union filed its own lawsuit, seeking
to block American's plan to hire the foreign attendants.
   The company also has agreed to reduce foreign language
requirements by asking that some, but not all, flight attendants be
required to speak the language of a destination country, Ms. Leon
said.
   The dispute between American and the 17,000-member union began
last year when the airline agreed to buy routes and other assets
for $310 million from Eastern.
   American plans to begin flights into Latin American in July.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0084 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 1906EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f BC-AutoSurvey     06-10 0215</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Auto Survey,0223</SECOND>
<HEAD>Japanese Makers Reportedly Dominate Powers Survey</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DETROIT (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Toyota's year-old Lexus division ranked first in
a survey of car-owners' attitudes about the quality of their 1990
cars, a newspaper reported.
   Japanese makers dominated the top of the ranking, and General
Motors Corp.'s Buick was the only domestic division in the top five
in the J.D. Powers &amp; Associates Initial Quality Study, the Detroit
Free Press reported Saturday.
   The annual survey focuses on car buyers' evaluations of 1990
models after three months of ownership. Lexus took the top rank
with reports of only 82 problems per 100 vehicles.
   Mercedes was second with 84, followed by Toyota with 89;
Infiniti with 99 and Buick with 113. The rest of the top 10 were
Honda, 114; Nissan, 123; Acura, 126; BMW, 130, and Mazda, 130.
   Some automakers use the widely recognized Powers' survey to tout
their performance in ads.
   The Buick LeSabre was the only domestic model ranked among the
10 most trouble-free cars of the 1990 model year. Last year it had
been joined in the top 10 by the Ford Crown Victoria and the Buick
Riviera.
   A spokesman at J.D. Powers in Agoura Hills, Calif., declined to
confirm the report and said results of the survey won't be released
until July.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900610-0085 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-90 1935EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-US-Mexico Advisory   06-10 0033</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-US-Mexico, Advisory,0036</SECOND>
<TEXT>
   Eds: Note the item AM-Bush, 3rd Ld-Writethru, which moved on
general news wires only as a 0726, leads with Salinas arriving at
White House for talks.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>AP Business News</BYLINE>
</DOC>
</Collection>
