<Collection>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901230-0001 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-30-90 0030EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Guatemala-US 1stLd-Writethru a0584 12-30 0398</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Guatemala-US, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0584,0457</SECOND>
<HEAD>US Seeking Extradition of Alleged Cocaine Smugglers</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 9 grafs to CORRECT arrest of extradition suspects
not linked to nation's largest drug seizure. Picks up 9th graf pvs,
`Earlier in ...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By ALFONSO ANZUETO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>GUATEMALA CITY (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The U.S. government announced Saturday it
is seeking the extradition of a mayor and two other men on
cocaine-trafficking charges.
   The embassy news release followed a federal police announcement
of the nation's largest drug seizure in a separate case. Police
said they confiscated more than 5,000 pounds of cocaine worth an
estimated $3.8 billion.
   The extradition request named Zacapa Mayor Arnoldo Vargas
Estrada, 52; Otto Evelio Quiro Davila, 34, and Victor Enrique
Escobar Arias, 37.
   The U.S. Embassy said it informed the Foreign Ministry on Dec.
20 that the Justice Department wants to prosecute the men on
charges of importing and distributing cocaine in the United States.
   ``The government of Guatemala acted rapidly to detain these
individuals,'' the embassy said, referring to the arrests Thursday
in Zacapa, about 90 miles east of the capital of Guatemala City.
   Officials said they seized more than 630 pounds of cocaine with
a value of some $57.4 million dollars when the three men were
arrested.
   The U.S. Drug Enforcement Agency was involved in the arrests,
according to Guatemalan officials.
   The embassy expressed pleasure ``with this cooperation on the
part of the Guatemalan government.''
   Federal police Friday night said they seized 1,522 packages of
cocaine, each weighing 3.3 pounds, in bags and car tires stashed in
several parts of Guatemala City. Five men were arrested in that
case.
   Earlier in the week, the army dismissed Col. CarlosRene Ochoa
Ruiz, as well as Capts. Hugo Leonel Perez Franco and Jose Maria
Flores Montes for alleged involvement in drug trafficking. It
turned their cases over to civilian courts.
   There have been rumors the United States also was seeking
extradition of the officers, but the embassy made no reference to
such a request.
   Vargas, who won re-election in November as mayor for the
National Center Union, denied the charges and told reporters the
allegations were meant to damage the election chances of his
party's standard-bearer, Jorge Carpio Nicolle.
   Carpio Nicolle faces Jorge Serrano Elias in a presidential
runoff vote on Jan. 6.
   The embassy statement said the United States is ``confident that
whoever wins the second round (of elections) will be totally
dedicated to continuing the broad cooperation which our two
governments have shown in this field.''
   Drug trafficking has flourished in this Central American nation
of 9 million people since President Vinicio Cerezo came into office
in 1986 after decades of military rule.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901230-0002 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-30-90 0038EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Robbery-Hostages 1st-LdWritethru a0586 12-30 0221</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Robbery-Hostages, 1st-Ld Writethru, a0586,0234</SECOND>
<HEAD>Man Surrenders After Holding S&amp;L Employees Hostage</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: CORRECTS police chief's name throughout to James Montoya;
CORRECTS spelling throughout of alleged gunman's name to Amburgey,
sted Amburgee.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>TRINIDAD, Colo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A gunman took three people hostage
Saturday when police foiled his attempt to flee a savings and loan
after robbing it. He surrendered four hours later, authorities
said.
   No shots were fired and no one was injured, police said.
   David Amburgey, 33, of Montrose, was arrested shortly after
releasing Century Savings and Loan president Louis Schick, vice
president Don Jones and an unidentified female employee, said
Police Chief James Montoya.
   The gunman entered the savings and loan just before noon and
robbed it of an undetermined amount of cash, which was later
recovered, Montoya said. An employee tripped a silent alarm and two
policemen confronted Amburgey as he tried to leave through a back
door, Montoya said.
   Amburgey, armed with a .22-caliber semiautomatic pistol, went
back inside and took the three hostages, Montoya said.
   He surrendered after a state trooper negotiating the hostages'
release told him police knew who he was and had towed away his
getaway car, Montoya said.
   Amburgey, who was held Saturday night at the Las Animas County
Jail, told police he was out of work and needed money, Montoya
said.
   Trinidad is a small mining town in southern Colorado.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901230-0003 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-30-90 0057EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Mexico-Elections     12-30 0247</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mexico-Elections,0264</SECOND>
<HEAD>Officials Reject Five Election Results</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MEXICO CITY (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Election victories claimed by the governing
party in five small Yucatan state towns were thrown out Saturday
and new votes were ordered.
   The state Electoral College also declared the opposition
National Action Party the victor in the town of Dzan during the
Nov. 25 elections.
   Opposition parties have accused the governing Institutional
Revolutionary Party of widespread fraud during recent elections in
the states of Yucatan, Coahuila, Mexico and Hidalgo.
   The government has vowed to clean up the electoral process and
officials have recognized opposition party victories in a few
cities in each state, including the Yucatan state capital of
Merida.
   The government Notimex news agency said the Electoral College
voided the elections in Sucila, Tetiz, Santa Elena, Panaba and
Tekit. It said new elections are to be held within 60 days.
   Officials had earlier declared the governing party the victor in
all but a handful of the 106 municipalities that held elections
Nov. 25.
   Also Saturday, arraignments were held for 25 people arrested
Friday in Valladolid during a protest of alleged election fraud,
Notimex reported. Among those arraigned was National Action Party
mayoral candidate Justo Enrique Herrera Silva.
   Another 114 of those arrested were released for lack of
evidence, according to local officials quoted by Notimex.
   Witnesses said police used to tear gas to disperse protesters,
who seized city hall.
   Notimex said municipal police chief Alfonso Diaz Arzapalo
claimed he was injured, robbed of $500 and stripped of his clothes
during the clashes.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901230-0004 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-30-90 0101EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-GodfatherArrest     12-30 0132</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Godfather Arrest,0127</SECOND>
<HEAD>Teen Charged In Movie Shootout</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A teen-ager was charged in the Christmas Day
shootout at a screening of ``The Godfather Part III'' that left one
person dead and three others wounded, police said Saturday.
   Lawrence Bartley, 17, of Laurelton on Long Island, was charged
Thursday with reckless endangerment and criminal possession of a
weapon, said officer Andrew DiSimone, a Nassau County police
spokesman.
   The shooting followed a shouting match between two groups of
teen-agers at Sunrise Cinema in Valley Stream on Long Island.
   About 700 panicked moviegoers fled when the shooting began about
an hour into the gangster film.
   A 15-year-old boy was shot in the head and died the next day.
Three other bystanders were wounded.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901230-0005 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-30-90 0114EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-PhilippinesFire     12-30 0135</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Philippines Fire,0140</SECOND>
<HEAD>Three US Sailors Killed in Hotel Fire</HEAD>
<DATELINE>OLONGAPO, Philippines (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   At least three U.S. sailors died
early Sunday in a fire that swept through a hotel filled with
American servicemen en route to the Persian Gulf, police said.
   The fire at the Royal Lodge Hotel, about one mile from the
U.S.-operated Subic Bay Naval Base, also killed a Filipino woman.
   Investigators said one of the victims was assigned to the
aircraft carrier USS Ranger, which is part of a convoy that arrived
in the Philippines on Thursday from San Diego on its way to the
gulf. The other two victims were also believed assigned to the task
force.
   The U.S. Navy withheld the names of those killed pending
notification of relatives.
   Police said the cause of the fire was not immediately known.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901230-0006 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-30-90 0137EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-SouthKorea-Chun 1stLd-Writethru a0560 12-30 0275</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-South Korea-Chun, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0560,0303</SECOND>
<HEAD>Disgraced Former President Ends Two-Year Exile to Return to Seoul</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS grafs 3-4 pvs, `The route ...,' with 2 grafs to UPDATE
with Chun arriving at home. Picks up 5th graf pvs, `Dissidents have
...'</NOTE>
<DATELINE>SEOUL, South Korea (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Disgraced former president Chun
Doo-hwan ended two years of self-imposed exile in a remote mountain
temple Sunday to return to Seoul and almost certain political
controversy.
   Chun, who was accompanied by his wife and aides, left the 14th
century Buddhist temple in the snow-capped eastern mountains with a
police escort, news reports said.
   About 2,500 riot police blocked streets and alleyways near
Chun's house in western Seoul to check identifications and prevent
possible protests. Opponents attacked the house repeatedly before
Chun's departure. It has remained under heavy guard during his
exile.
   ``In the future, I will continue to live as an ordinary
citizen,'' said the former general in a statement at the temple.
   Dissidents have asked the government to prosecute Chun,
contending he ordered the military to crush a 1980 pro-democracy
uprising in Kwangju. By official count, about 200 people were
killed in the uprising.
   The former president left Seoul to go into rural exile in
November 1988 after apologizing on national television for abuses
of power during his seven- year rule which ended in 1987.
   Chun left office after accepting opposition demands for direct
popular elections following mass anti-government protests in 1987.
He hand-picked Roh Tae-woo as the governing party candidate, and
Roh won the presidency by a narrow margin in December 1987.
   Roh, a former general who helped Chun seize power in 1980, has
appealed to the nation for mercy for Chun. A dozen of Chun's
relatives and associates have been convicted of corruption and
imprisoned since Roh took office.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901230-0007 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-30-90 0648EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i BC-Algeria-Hijack 3rdLd-Writethru a0600 12-30 0529</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Algeria-Hijack, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0600,0606</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hijackers Arrested After Freeing Passengers</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: RECASTS lead to CLARIFY incident was hijacking</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto PAR16</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RACHID KHIARI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ALGIERS, Algeria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two army deserters who hijacked an
airliner and held dozens of hostages during a two-day standoff
surrendered Sunday after freeing all passengers and crew, the
official Algerian news agency reported.
   The hijackers were taken into custody without violence after
releasing the pilot and co-pilot of the state-owned Air Algerie
Boeing 737, the news agency said. Earlier, 46 remaining passengers
were freed.
   There were no reports of injuries.
   The hijackers' names were not immediately released by
authorities, and the motive for the incident was unclear. The APS
news agency reported the men were deserters from the Saharan town
of Ghardaia, where the flight began late Friday.
   The hijackers, who were armed, had demanded 20 hours' worth of
fuel to fly to another country.
   The jet, carrying 82 passengers and six crew members, was forced
to land in the eastern city of Annaba early Saturday after
officials in Carthage, Tunisia, turned the flight away.
   Egyptian officials refused Saturday to allow the hijackers to
fly there.
   The hijackers seized the aircraft shortly after takeoff from
Ghardaia, a popular winter resort. It was bound for the Algerian
capital of Algiers.
   According to airline officials and accounts by freed passengers,
the pair produced a pistol and submachine gun shortly after
takeoff. One hijacker took control of the cabin and the other
watched over the passengers, forcing the women to the front of the
plane.
   ``The plane started rolling, but not like an air pocket,''
French passenger Paulette Thibule, 67, told the French television
network La Cinq. ``The stewardesses got moving toward the front.
That's when I understood there was a struggle in the cockpit.''
   Talks with the hijackers resumed at dawn Sunday.
   Interior Minister Mohammad Saleh Mohammedi first negotiated the
release of the remaining people on board. A short while later, he
persuaded the two men to surrender, witnesses said. The hijackers
gave up after freeing the pilot and co-pilot.
   Police had surrounded the plane, although other flights took off
and landed at the airport, about 250 miles east of Algiers.
   On Saturday, the two hijackers released 36 passengers, mostly
children, elderly people and foreigners.
   Air Algerie said there were 14 foreign nationals among the
passengers. Kahlouche said the foreigners included French, German,
Italian and Japanese citizens.
   The State Department said no Americans were on the flight.
   Late Saturday, there were conflicting reports about the
hijackers.
   Transport Minister Hassan Kahlouche said the hijackers were
Algerian, and made no political statements or demands.
   But an Algerian official, who spoke on condition of anonymity,
said the hijackers probably were Islamic fundamentalists protesting
a crackdown against an allied Moslem movement in Tunisia.
   Algeria is home to North Africa's most powerful Islamic
fundamentalist movement, which took a majority of seats in local
and municipal elections in June.
   Another Algerian official quoted freed passengers as saying the
hijackers ``showed no physical or verbal violent intentions'' and
made no statements about their motives.
   Algeria has long experience in negotiating the release of
hostages, most recently in April 1988 when mediators won the
freedom of 31 hostages aboard a hijacked Kuwait Airways jet.
   Western officials criticized Algeria for releasing the
hijackers, who killed two people.
   Algerian diplomats played a key role in winning the 1981 release
of Americans held hostage at the U.S. Embassy in Iran. They also
brokered the release of many Western hostages in Lebanon.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901230-0008 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-30-90 1123EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--India-Capsize     12-30 0145</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--India-Capsize,0148</SECOND>
<HEAD>43 Killed As Boats Capsize</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW DELHI, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   At least 43 people, including 32
schoolchildren, drowned when two boats capsized in a river in
eastern India, news reports said Sunday.
   Press Trust of India said 120 people were rescued after
Saturday's accident in Jalmagi river in West Bengal state.
   The reports said the boats were bringing back students and
teachers of several elementary schools from an annual sports
competition at a nearby town, 745 miles southeast of New Delhi.
   Press Trust said the boats were tied together and were being
steered by a teen-age oarsman.
   The boats collided and capsized when the boy lost control in the
turbulent river, Press Trust of India said quoting the district
police chief, D.K. Basu.
   The United News of India said the bodies of 32 children and 11
teachers were found by rescuers.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901230-0009 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-30-90 1126EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--TestTubeBabies     12-30 0158</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Test Tube Babies,0154</SECOND>
<HEAD>Iran's First Test-Tube Babies Born</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NICOSIA, Cyprus (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Iran's first test-tube babies were born
in the city of Yazd in central Iran, the Islamic Rebublic News
Agency reported Sunday.
   The agency, monitored in Nicosia, said the first baby, a girl,
was born to 36-year-old woman at the city's Afshar Yazd University
hospital Saturday morning.
   An hour later, another woman gave birth to twins, a girl and a
boy.
   Dr. Abbas Aflatounian, head of the Infertility Research Center
at the hospital, said the births were by Caesarian section, and
that all three babies and their mothers were in ``perfect
condition,'' IRNA reported.
   Aflatounian said that during the center's year-long
fertilization and insemination programs, 30 successful pregnancies
had been registered.
   Dr. Mohammad Faqihi, the university's chancellor, said there
were about one million infertile couples in Iran, and that 7,000 of
them had applied for help at the center.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901230-0010 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-30-90 1134EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Dinkins'FirstYear     12-30 0478</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Dinkins' First Year,0605</SECOND>
<HEAD>New York Mayor Says 1990 Was A Year Of `Dreams Deferred'</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: RETRANSMITTING to fix cycle designator</NOTE>
<HEAD>With NC Speaker, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CATHERINE CROCKER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Mayor David Dinkins, reflecting on his first
year in office, says he's proud that he maintained the city's bond
rating despite a budget deficit.
   But the city's first black mayor said he wishes he could have
spent less time dealing with fiscal problems and more time on the
social issues that propelled him into office.
   ``I look forward to the day when we will be able to move ahead
on some of the dreams that have been, for the moment at least,
deferred,'' Dinkins said during a recent interview.
   A projected gap of at least $250 million in the city's 1991
fiscal year budget has forced the mayor to cut funds in virtually
every area, from education and street cleaning to libraries and
bridge repair.
   According to a federal report released the week before
Christmas, the New York metropolitan region lost an estimated
100,000 jobs in private industry in 1990, half of them in New York
City.
   The fiscal crisis has made it difficult for Dinkins to devote
time to the city's poor and young, whose plight he promised to
improve during his campaign for mayor.
   Dinkins acknowledged that his inability to focus on social
issues has made some of his strongest supporters impatient for
results.
   A recent New York Newsday poll showed that only 33 percent of
those interviewed approved of his job performance, down from 53
percent in June. The biggest decline in approval came among blacks
- still largely supportive of him but down to 65 percent from 76
percent - and Manhattan residents.
   Dinkins said the high points of his first year included
anti-apartheid leader Nelson Mandela's visit; a decision by the
Democratic Party to hold its 1992 convention here; and his City
Hall speech calling for racial harmony as New Yorkers awaited a
verdict in the first trial in the slaying of a black teen-ager in a
mob attack in a predominantly white neighborhood in Brooklyn.
   While the city's crime rate has soared, with annual city murders
topping 2,000 for the first time, Dinkins said he is proud of his
``Safe Streets, Safe City'' plan to hire thousands of new police
officers.
   But he failed to win the approval of the crime plan by the state
Legislature, which recessed two weeks ago without acting on it.
   Asked about his priorities for 1992, the mayor said he would
focus first on fiscal stability, followed by public safety and then
education, youth services and health care.
   ``There are many more things I had hoped to accomplish,
especially in the areas of human service, that just plain require
money,'' Dinkins admitted.
   How long dreams continue to be deferred, he said, will depend on
``when we get some money.''
   Dinkins also said he believed that in general, more was expected
of him than of past mayors, ``not so much because I am an African
American, per se, but because the coalition that elected me ...
(was) very dissatisfied in the closing years of the stewardship of
my predecessor (Edward Koch).
   ``And they saw this as an opportunity for things to be different
in some particulars. And we don't have the ability to change these
things overnight for a variety of reasons,'' Dinkins said. ``And
especially now, as there's the need ... to cut back and downsize,
it's going to be even more difficult and painful.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901230-0011 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-30-90 1136EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-GangPlot     12-30 0378</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gang Plot,0457</SECOND>
<HEAD>Police Say New Year's Eve Plot to Murder Officers Foiled</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MICHAEL WHITE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A gang's plot to murder police officers on
New Year's Eve has been foiled by the arrests of three young men
and seizure of weapons, police said.
   The alleged plot apparently was in retaliation for police
crackdowns on gang-controlled drug operations in the Van Nuys and
Sylmar areas of the San Fernando Valley, said Lt. Jim Vojtecky.
   ``As early as September, we began getting inforamtion that local
street gangs were getting ... a little irritated, and we had
indications they were going to attempt to kill a cop because we
were screwing up their drug operations in the streets,'' Vojtecky
said.
   Gang violence in the nation's second-largest city reached record
levels during 1990. As of Nov. 30, gang violence had accounted for
315 deaths in 1990, a 12.4 percent jump over 1989, when 303 people
died in gang attacks.
   Vojtecky said tension between police and gangs in the Van Nuys
area has been building for months. Recent information from
informants convinced police that an attempt to kill police would be
made on New Year's Eve, Vojtecky said.
   In early morning raids Saturday, police seized two rifles, one
with a sawed-off barrel, one handgun and 163 rounds of ammunition.
   Sergio Camarena, Cesar Reveles and Hector Aleman, all 18, were
taken into custody. Camarena and Reveles were booked for
investigation of conspiracy to commit murder and Aleman was booked
for possession of a sawed-off rifle.
   The three belonged to the same gang, which Vojtecky declined to
identify in keeping with departmental policy designed to avoid
giving publicity to individual gangs.
   Vojtecky said officers did not have time to determine how the
alleged murder plot was to be carried out.
   Police believe the plot was foiled by the arrests. However, a
bulletin was issued advising officers throughout Los Angeles to be
careful on New Year's Eve.
   Saturday's arrests followed by hours a spate of gang violence in
the region that left a 13-year-old boy dead and a girl critically
wounded.
   The 13-year-old boy was shot while sleeping in the living room
of his grandmother's home in suburban Pomona. Police said the
gunman apparently mistook the youth, visiting from Claremont, for a
member of a local gang.
   The girl was shot in the head when several rounds were fired
through the living room window of her home in southwest Los
Angeles. The 13-year-old was listed in very critical condition at
Cedar-Sinai Medical Center.
   Police Lt. Joe Germain said investigators suspect it was gang
gunfire but did not know if the girl was the intended victim.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901230-0012 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-30-90 1136EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--SexistAds     12-30 0121</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Sexist Ads,0106</SECOND>
<HEAD>South Korea Bans Ads That Discriminate Against Women</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SEOUL, South Korea (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Labor Ministry says classified ads
that discriminate against women will be banned after Jan. 1 and
employers who place them will be fined $3,500.
   In a ruling published Sunday, the ministry said that employment
for jobs calling for ``single'' or ``good-looking'' applicants will
be banned.
   Also illegal will be ads for jobs saying ``Only male college
graduate wanted,'' ``Males welcome'' and ``Completion or exemption
of military service preferred.''
   Feminists consider the ruling long overdue, but say it is
unlikely to force change in South Korea's male-dominated society.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901230-0013 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-30-90 1149EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Soviet-WineRiot     12-30 0231</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Wine Riot,0260</SECOND>
<HEAD>Siberians Riot over Wine, Vodka Shortage Before New Year's</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Tens of thousands of people staged a ``wine riot''
in a Siberian city on Sunday, angry that they would have to
celebrate New Year's without alcohol, Tass reported.
   The shortage of spirits for the New Year's holiday - the most
festive day on the Soviet calendar - ``overfilled the cup of
tolerance of city residents,'' the official news agency said.
   The rioters in Chita, 2,976 miles east of Moscow, blocked
traffic and lit bonfires to protest the lack of wine, vodka and
other goods, Tass said.
   President Mikhail S. Gorbachev and his supporters have warned of
social unrest because of worsening shortages of a variety of goods.
   Food, medicine and consumer goods are so scarce that Gorbachev
has had to ask the West for help, which is arriving from private
charities and governments worldwide.
   Tass said the ``wine riot'' began after people became fed up
after long hours of waiting in line at stores. A crowd went onto
one of the city's main highways, blocked traffic and lit bonfires
made of boards, fences and boxes, it said.
   Protests demanded a meeting with local authorities to complain
about empty shelves in stores selling food and manufactured goods,
interruptions of the water and electricity supplies, corruption in
trade and ``the multi-month `wine famine,''' Tass said.
   Firefighters and police managed to get the crowd to disperse,
but Tass said the situation in Chita, a city of 315,000 people,
``remains uneasy.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901230-0014 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-30-90 1213EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-China     12-30 0656</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-China,0768</SECOND>
<HEAD>Communist Party Adopts Cautious Blueprint for the '90s</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KATHY WILHELM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Communist Party on Sunday adopted a cautious
economic and social blueprint for the 1990s, stressing stability
and self-reliance and rejecting the infatuation with rapid reform
of the 1980s.
   ``We must guard against and overcome the tendency of being
impatient for success, and strive to avoid a recurrence of big ups
and downs in economic life,'' the ruling party's Central Committee
said in a communique adopted at a closed-door, six-day meeting that
ended Sunday.
   The evening television news showed party General Secretary Jiang
Zemin in a dark gray Mao suit presiding over the opening session in
the Great Hall of the People, with 171 full members and 107
alternates in attendance along with several hundred retired party
elders.
   Neither Jiang's opening speech nor the comments of any
individual members were released.
   The meeting was postponed for weeks as committee members argued
over drafts of new Five- and Ten-Year Plans to take effect on New
Years' Day and guide China's centrally planned economy into the
21st century.
   The official Xinhua News Agency's report of the session
indicated the committee did not approve any existing drafts.
Instead, Xinhua said the government will now ``map out'' the plans,
presumably based on the Central Committee communique.
   The blueprint gives priority in state spending to agriculture,
basic industries and infrastructure. It also calls for more
attention to national defense, which received a shrinking share of
the budget during the 1980s.
   Little space is given in the communique to new economic reforms
that would continue China's decade-old program of supplementing
central planning with market forces.
   Reform was one of the key issues dividing Central Committee
members. Party elders such as 86-year-old Chen Yun, who played a
key role in the early years of reform, accused younger liberals of
forgetting that the reforms were intended to strengthen socialism,
not build capitalism.
   Private enterprise and free markets should supplement the state
sector but not replace it, he argued.
   The conservatives appeared to have won, judging from the brevity
of the references to reform and the repeated calls for
strengthening the inefficient, debt-ridden state-owned sector.
   However, a Western diplomat cautioned that it is too soon to
make an assessment. The document may have been drafted with a
conservative slant in order to win passage, while containing enough
references to improving efficiency to allow for real change.
   The only sentence that specifically deals with new reforms says
structural changes are needed in ``the fields of enterprises,
circulation, prices, finance, taxation, banking, planning,
investment and labor and wages'' - a broad list. No detailed
suggestions are made.
   The communique says economic growth should be sustained and
stable, based on the ``principle of doing what is within our
capacity.''
   No targets were set, but Premier Li Peng recently said average
annual growth of 6 percent would be appropriate - down from an
average of nearly 10 percent during most of the 1980s.
   During the 1980s, however, the economy experienced several
swings from too rapid expansion and rising inflation to abrupt
government-ordered slowdowns designed to curb the inflation. Such
swings gave China a reputation for economic instability.
   The battle between Beijing and regional authorities for control
over tax revenues appears unresolved.
   The document says ``overall regulation and control'' of the
economy is needed, but concludes evenhandedly: ``It is necessary to
handle properly the relations between the central and the local
authorities ... And give full scope to the initiative of both.''
   The 1990s will be pivotal years for China, says the document,
which alludes only vaguely to the collapse of socialism in many
other countries.
   ``Success or failure in our efforts ... to greatly promote
economic growth and social progress will have a direct bearing on
the rise or fall of China's socialist system.''
   ``We should strengthen ideological and political work in real
ernest, carry out in-depth education in patriotism, collectivism
and socialism, and re-energize the national spirit.''
   Such calls have become routine since the violent crushing of
last year's massive democracy movement, which is not mentioned in
the communique.
   A single sentence says efforts should be made to ``push forward
political structural reform and expand socialist democracy,'' but
there is no mention of any specific reforms.
   When reformist fever peaked in 1987, there were calls for
separating the party and government functions, but such ideas have
been anathema since the conservative backlash to the democracy
movement.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901230-0015 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-30-90 1238EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-IndustrialOutlookBjt     12-30 0717</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Industrial Outlook Bjt,850</SECOND>
<NOTE>For Release 6:30 p.m. Sunday; Embargo set by source.</NOTE>
<HEAD>New Year Holds Promise for High Tech; Not for Autos and Housing.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVE SKIDMORE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The new year holds promise for high-technology
and medical companies despite the deepening economic slump, but
many businesses tied to automobiles and housing face dim prospects,
a government forecast said Sunday.
   The Commerce Department, in its 32nd annual forecast of winners
and losers in American business, predicted that 110 of 184
manufacturing industries it surveyed would enjoy rising sales in
1991. The rest will see no growth or suffer a drop in sales.
   ``The outlook is generally one of continuing but slow growth for
most sectors (of the economy),'' said Commerce Undersecretary J.
Michael Farren.
   However, the department's forecasts are based on an assumption
that the economy will avoid a recession with a growth in the gross
national product next year in the lower end of a 1 percent to 3
percent range. Nearly all private economists contend the economy
already is shrinking and will continue to do so at least through
the first quarter of 1991 with an annual growth in GNP of around
0.3 percent next year.
   The Commerce Department report said that overall the median
growth rate for manufacturing sales is expected to be positive for
the ninth consecutive year, but by a barely perceptible 0.89
percent, down from an almost-as-dismal 0.95 percent this year.
   The median rate - the point where half of the industries had
bigger sales increases and half had smaller - was far healthier in
1988, 2.1 percent, and 1987, 3 percent.
   The 560-page report, ``U.S. Industrial Outlook,'' was prepared
by 130 analysts using information current through August and
September.
   Retail sales were projected to rise only 1 or 2 percent after
inflation next year.
   ``Consumer-oriented industries are expected to do less well
overall, reflecting the general slowdown in the economy,'' Farren
said. ``Such products as furniture, appliances and household audio
and video equipment are expected to decline.''
   Two key sectors of the economy, construction and motor vehicles,
were expected to have another bad year in 1991, with their weakness
spilling over into a variety of related industries.
   High vacancy rates in office buildings was expected to depress
construction by 15 percent, while hotel construction was predicted
to fall 20 percent. Residential housing construction was expected
to decline 6 percent from 1.22 million units to 1.15 million.
   Car sales probably will fall from 9.5 million this year to 9.3
million, but truck sales likely will rise about 1 percent to 4.7
million, the report said.
   ``The declines in both construction and motor vehicles will have
a significant impact on a number of other major industries,
including building materials, household durables (goods such as
appliances that are expected to last three or more years), steel
and wood products,'' Farren said.
   In addition to the manufacturing industries, the report also
evaluated 166 service businesses, the fastest-growing sector of the
economy. However, Farren cautioned that the performance of services
was much more difficult to forecast and to compare to previous
years.
   Electronic information services, computer software and other
computer services are expected to do the best, while slower
expansion was projected for movie theaters, home entertainment and
legal services.
   In manufacturing, most of the 10 fastest-growing industries are
connected with either health care or high-technology.
   Leather tanning and finishing topped the list, with 9.4 percent
expected growth. But that was considered an anomaly largely
attributed to expected increases in domestic production because of
new duties imposed on leather imports from Argentina.
   Leather tanning was followed by semiconductors, the basic
building block of computer chips, with a projected 8.9 percent
increase in sales, and surgical instruments, up 8.6 percent. Others
in the top 10 were surgical supplies, medicines, diagnostic
substances, poultry slaughtering and processing, biological
products, aircraft and dental equipment.
   At the bottom of the scale was creamery butter, with a projected
sales decline of 14.6 percent. The department attributed the drop
to consumers' worry about cholesterol and weight gain.
   Other shrinking industries were mobile homes, frozen baked goods
except bread, boat building, motors and generators, household
cooking equipment, hardwood and flooring mills, electric housewares
and fans, fabricated metal, and sawmill and planing mills.
   In general, the department said industries linked to export
sales would fare better than businesses tied to the domestic
economy. Farren said foreigners will be encouraged to buy U.S.
goods by the decline in the value of the dollar this year.
   However, Farren conceded that the price of oil, driven up by the
Persian Gulf crisis, likely would keep the U.S. trade deficit,
$109.4 billion in 1989, at about $105 billion in 1990 as well as
next year.
   The report predicted continued business investment, despite the
slow economy as manufacturers try to keep up with overseas
competitors and meet new environmental requirements, requiring new
pollution-control equipment.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901230-0016 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-30-90 1307EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-NewDecadeBjt     12-30 0416</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-New Decade Bjt,520</SECOND>
<HEAD>Last Decade of the Century Begins, Finally</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RANDOLPH E. SCHMID</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   When does a new decade begin, anyway?
   We ushered in the '90s a year ago, but the last decade of the
20th Century is only now about to unfold. Confused?
   Well, you can thank a monk named Dionysius Exiguus. He started
it all many hundreds of years ago.
   The question surfaces every 10 years and for many people the
answer is obvious: the new decades began with the 1990s a year ago
on Jan. 1, 1990 and will end Dec. 31, 1999.
   But don't tell that to the calendar purists.
   ``If you refer to the decade of the '90s, I'm willing to concede
that 1990 is in the '90s. It's obviously not in the '80s,'' says
LeRoy Doggett, a calendar expert at the U.S. Naval Observatory.
   But he explains that this view of a decade in time is simply a
colloquialism with no basis in history.
   ``When we talk about the last decade of the 20th century we get
into a chronological question which forces you to ask: When did the
first century begin?'' he says.
   Doggett provides this explanation.
   The numbering system in our current Gregorian calendar, indeed
in all human calendars, is arbitrary. Someone picked a particular
date or event and started counting from that point. There is
nothing in nature that causes it to be a particular year, or for a
particular day to be New Year.
   That's where the monk Dionysius Exiguus, or ``Dennis the
Small'', got into the act nearly 1,500 years ago. He had been given
the task of developing a set of tables to help local priests and
bishops determine the date of Easter.
   At the time, everything was dated from the accession of the
Roman emperor Diocletian. But Diocletian had persecuted the early
Christians and Dionysius didn't want to commemorate him in the new
tables.
   Instead Dionysius based the tables on the date of Jesus' birth,
which the monk determined had occurred 532 years earlier. Dionysius
called the year of Jesus' birth the year ``1'' and began the count.
   ``So the first decade was 1 to 10, the second was 11 to 20.
Extrapolating from that, we end up starting a new decade with 1991,
which runs through 2000, which completes the 20th century. So the
21st century starts with 2001,'' said Doggett.
   Why didn't Dionysius simply call the first year ``zero'' and
avoid all the confusion?
   ``Well, the number zero was not then in use in the West,''
explained Doggett. Counting was done using either Roman Numerals or
fingers, neither of which includes a zero.
   There's more.
   Many scholars have concluded that Dionysius actually
miscalculated by two to 10 years the actual birth of Jesus. But by
the time those questions were raised, his numbering system was
widely used and was not changed.
   And the year 1991 is not the only year that makes its debut in
the coming 12 months. The Muslim year 1412 begins at sundown next
July 12 and the Jewish year 5752 begins at sundown next Sept. 8.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901230-0017 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-30-90 1318EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Cambodia-Helplessness Bjt   12-30 0704</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Cambodia-Helplessness, Bjt,0890</SECOND>
<HEAD>After Years of War and Occupation, Hope Eludes Many Cambodians</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY6</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SHEILA McNULTY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PHNOM PENH, Cambodia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Peu Dinda, hopping up a hill on one
leg with rusty crutches, says life won't improve for him no matter
who controls Cambodia.
   He is one of the thousands to have lost a part of themselves
during Cambodia's 20-year-old civil war. In this Southeast Asian
country where most people work two or even three jobs to survive,
the former soldier can't find any job at all.
   Without any formal education, he said his only hope is manual
labor. But with only one leg, he fears that's an impossibility.
   ``It's difficult to tell the future,'' said Peu Dinda, who
survives on a meager government war stipend.
   Such feelings of hopelessness grip many Cambodians. Since
gaining independence from the French in 1954, this country has
struggled to survive American bombings, a superpower-sponsored
civil war, a Khmer Rouge genocide and an 11-year Vietnamese
occupation.
   Promises of peace and prosperity with the next government are
greeted with wariness - and weariness.
   World leaders have called a peace settlement by Cambodia's four
warring groups the long sought-after solution to the country's
problems.
   They say a Sept. 10 agreement to share power in a Supreme
National Council - supervised by the United Nations - is what the
country needs.
   Signing the accord is the Vietnam-installed government of Prime
Minister Hun Sen and a coalition that includes the Khmer Rouge,
Khmer People's National Liberation Front and forces of former
Cambodian leader Prince Norodom Sihanouk.
   The council is meant to be a symbolic government, with the
United Nations running the country, organizing a cease-fire,
planning elections, ending all foreign military aid and disarming
the four groups fighting for power.
   But the groups have broken peace agreements in the past.
   Meanwhile, the country is stagnating. Boys march into Phnom
Penh's best restaurants to beg food off the plates of foreigners. A
mother washes her month-old baby under water dripping from a fire
hydrant.
   The bulk of Cambodia's property is so run down that it can't be
rented. Electricity and running water are a luxury; some people
carry buckets of water to their homes up flights of stairs daily.
   There are no official records of the country's per capita income
or unemployment rate, according to Cambodia's mission to the United
Nations in New York. Said the mission's First Secretary, P. Cheng:
``All of the social structure is basically destroyed. Statistics
are not possible.''
   The World Almanac Book of Facts in 1990 cites six-year-old
statistics as its most recent, listing $100 as the per capita
income in 1984.
   Some blame Cambodia's troubles on its history as a political
pawn. The country has been at the mercy of outside powers like
China, the Soviet Union and the United States for years.
   ``American policymakers look at Cambodia through an empty
Vietnamese glass. It is not how to help Cambodia but how to punish
Vietnam,'' said Khieu Kanharith, former editor of a weekly
state-owned newspaper.
   Khieu was referring to the U.S. trade restrictions imposed
against Cambodia because of its 11-year occupation by Vietnam.
   ``The international boycott is keeping us from progressing. The
only one way for us to catch up with our neighboring countries is
with international aid,'' Khieu said.
   Further evidence of a country trapped in the past is just inside
the National Pedriatric Hospital, the country's showcase hospital.
   Dr. Chour Ymeng, the hospital's vice director, pointed to the
sick people lining hallway floors. He showed a visitor the red
blotches dotting a baby - caused by malnutrition, which is easily
preventable.
   Chour said he is one of only a handful of doctors who survived
the Khmer Rouge killing fields. If more doctors had lived, perhaps
more children could be saved today, he said.
   Chour isn't the only one who thinks about what could have been.
The brother of Khmer Rouge leader Pol Pot has spent years picturing
life without the genocidal group.
   Loth Suong lives in a rundown housing project without
electricity to power his refrigerator, a television or even lights.
His brother lives in a Thai beach villa and has yet to be brought
to justice for his genocidal rule.
   ``My brother brought Cambodia down. If the country has no Khmer
Rouge, ordinary people will have a good living standard,'' said
Loth, 79. ``Because I am old, I need only peace. Now I call for you
to give peace to Cambodia.''
   Ros Sopea, a 29-year-old journalism student at Phnom Penh
University, said there aren't enough social services such as
schools or hospitals in Cambodia.
   But she said Cambodia would develop quickly if only the war
would end, freeing the country's estimated 6 million people to
produce enough rice to get ahead.
   Not everyone has Ros' faith.
   Lim Sothy fled Cambodia several months ago. Clutching an English
dictionary, the 18-year-old headed for a refugee camp just inside
Thailand. When last seen, he had about 215 miles, fields of
landmines and border guards to get past.
   But Lim said he had nothing to lose.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901230-0018 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-30-90 1328EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brite-HonorThyLegisla     12-30 0194</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brite-Honor Thy Legislator,0202</SECOND>
<HEAD>Love Your Legislator Day Planned For Wisconsin Churches</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JANESVILLE, Wis. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   As if politicians didn't find enough
opportunities to speak their minds, a man wants people to show
appreciation for their public officials by offering them a pulpit.
   Steven Trueblood is urging 500 Wisconsin churches to declare
Jan. 13 ``Love Your Legislator Day.''
   ``We're asking the churches to invite legislators to the Sunday
service, give them a few minutes to express their views on public
issues and then have a session after the service where church
members can go up to their legislators and thank them for their
service,'' Trueblood said.
   Trueblood, who describes himself as a former felon and drug
dealer, is director of the Freedom Council of America, a Janesville
group that provides volunteer chaplain services to the Wisconsin
and Illinois legislatures.
   He said he became a born-again Christian in 1982 and was later
pardoned by Gov. Tommy G. Thompson.
   ``After the scandal of Watergate, it seems like we lost complete
respect for the position these people serve in,'' Trueblood said.
``The public service arena is filled with dedicated, hard-working
people who deserve to be honored for the position they hold.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901230-0019 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-30-90 1330EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People     12-30 0504</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People,0620</SECOND>
<HEAD>People In The News</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY44</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Comedian Bob Hope, back from the Persian Gulf
region, says the morale of troops in Operation Desert Shield is
high and they're ready for action.
   The 87-year-old entertainer said in a telephone interview from
his home Saturday that the GIs wildly appreciated his efforts and
those of the troupe of entertainers that included Marie Osmond, Ann
Jillian, the Pointer Sisters and his wife, Dolores.
   ``It was just exciting as hell,'' Hope said. ``The morale is
immense. It was just great. They're just all ready.''
   Hope said the only woman allowed to venture into the desert,
because of Saudi restrictions on women, was his wife, who sang
``White Christmas.'' The other female performers did shows on
warships and for the finale Thursday in the tiny island nation of
Bahrain.
   ---
   DALLAS (AP) - Actor Martin Sheen turned autograph hound after
wrapping up a scene in The Dallas Morning News newsroom for an
upcoming miniseries.
   Sheen, who plays a Pulitzer Prize-winning reporter in ``Touch
and Die,'' found himself talking last week to real-life Pulitzer
winner David Hanners, whose winning 1988 story detailed the
investigation of a private airplane crash in poor weather.
   Sheen asked for an autograph, and Hanners penned: ``To Martin:
Don't fly when it rains.''
   Sheen, 50, is playing the lead in the miniseries, which is a
project of Italian, French, German and British producers. The movie
depicts Sheen on the trail of a presidential candidate campaigning
with tainted funds.
   ---
   LOS ANGELES (AP) - Anti-war activist Ron Kovic joined hundreds
of others in a demonstration urging President Bush to set a date
for talks in the Persian Gulf crisis.
   ``I don't want to see another Vietnam in the Persian Gulf,''
said Kovic, whose autobiography ``Born on the Fourth of July'' and
the film made from it described his fight to overcome paralyzing
war wounds.
   ``We don't want our men and women to die in a senseless war,''
he said Saturday outside the Westwood federal building. ``This
(conflict) is not about naked aggression, it's about oil.''
   Kovic estimated that 1,200 protesters appeared at the noon-hour
rally, but a federal building security guard said only 200
demonstrated.
   ---
</TEXT>
<NOTE>Eds: A version moving on sports wires.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>WELLESLEY, Mass. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Rookie Boston Celtics guard Dee Brown
III married Jill Edmondson in a 10-minute private service witnessed
fellow Celtic Robert Parish.
   The couple took their brief vows Saturday in a chapel of
Wellesley Hills Congregational Church. Edmondson's mother, Lisa
Grames, and brother, Mark Bryant, attended the ceremony along with
Parish and an unidentified escort.
   Brown, 22, and Edmondson, 25, plan to live in Wellesley. Last
September, when the couple were looking for a home in the town,
several police officers mistook Brown, who is black, for a bank
robber and forced the couple out of their car at gunpoint. The
police department in the largely white suburb later apologized.
   ---
   DALLAS (AP) - A Mississippi woman has been selected the 1991
Maid of Cotton to preside over Cotton Bowl events and spend six
months as a goodwill ambassador for the U.S. cotton industry.
   Meg Williams, 22, a native of Tupelo and graduate of Vanderbilt
University, edged out finalists from 11 other states Saturday to
earn the National Cotton Council honor. She is the 54th Maid of
Cotton.
   As Maid of Cotton, Ms. Williams earns a $10,000 educational
scholarship and will make her first appearance at the Cotton Bowl
parade on New Year's Day.
   She is majoring in interior design at the Parsons School of
Design in New York.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901230-0020 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-30-90 1423EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Obit-Skaaren     12-30 0293</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Skaaren,0336</SECOND>
<HEAD>Screenwriter Warren Skaaren Dies At 44</HEAD>
<DATELINE>AUSTIN, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Warren Skaaren, a screenwriter who worked
on such blockbusters as ``Batman'' and ``Top Gun,'' has died of
bone cancer. He was 44.
   Skaaren died at home Friday night. He learned how severe his
condition was early this summer, shortly after completing his last
screenplay, ``Beetlejuice 2,'' said W. Amon Burton, his attorney
and friend.
   During the 1980s, Skaaren gained a reputation as one of the
country's top script doctors - a screenwriter who could take over a
troubled script and rewrite it.
   The four films he was best known for rewriting - ``Batman,''
``Top Gun,'' ``Beverly Hills Cop 2'' and ``Beetlejuice'' - together
grossed more than $1 billion.
   ``He understood what the audience needed to have in a story,''
said Mike Simpson, Skaaren's agent and senior vice president of the
William Morris Agency's motion picture department.
   ``He could see the big picture. He had an almost scientific
ability to analyze characters and what their motivation was, and
what the audience wanted and what it expected from those
characters,'' Simpson said.
   A native of Rochester, Minn., Skaaren attended Rice University
in Houston. He graduated with an art degree in 1969.
   Although he rose quickly through the ranks of Hollywood
screenwriters, he chose to live in Austin rather than Southern
California.
   He founded the Texas Film Commission and became its first
director in 1971 while working for then-Gov. Preston Smith.
   In the mid-1970s, Skaaren helped form FPS Inc., a television and
film productions services company in Dallas.
   The company has handled location shooting for the television
series ``Dallas,'' and worked on the film ``Tender Mercies,'' which
was shot in Waxahachie.
   Skaaren is survived by his wife, Helen, and his parents, Morris
and Pearl Skaaren of Rochester, Minn.
   His body will be cremated in a private service, but a public
memorial service will be scheduled in the next two weeks, Burton
said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901230-0021 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-30-90 1518EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Algeria-Hijack     12-30 0491</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Algeria-Hijack,0576</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hijackers Surrender, Ending Hostage Standoff</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto PAR5,6</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RACHID KHIARI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ALGIERS, Algeria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two army deserters who hijacked a
domestic airliner surrendered on Sunday, freeing the last of dozens
of hostages and ending a two-day standoff, officials reported.
   The jetliner's pilot said the two hijackers themselves didn't
seem to know why on Friday they had commandeered the Air Algerie
Boeing 737 carrying 88 people from the Saharan town of Ghardaia to
Algiers. The plane was forced to land in the eastern city of
Annaba.
   The hijackers handed their firearms over to police shortly after
dawn following negotiations with the interior minister, the state
news agency APS reported. The two, identified as deserters from
Ghardaia, then were whisked away in a police car to an undisclosed
location.
   ``I'm very happy with the happy outcome of this affair,'' APS
quoted Interior Minister Saleh Mohammedi as saying. ``The authors
of this hijacking ... will be prosecuted.''
   Their ages were listed as 22 and 23, but their names were not
disclosed and their motivation remained a mystery to their
captives.
   ``It's something I just wasn't successful in bringing up, and I
had a lot of leisure time to discuss with them,'' said Capt. Salim
Zemti, one of the two final hostages released.
   ``They seemed ignorant themselves of the reason behind what they
were doing,'' Zemti said. But he added they may have been
``exasperated with their living conditions and decided to hijack a
plane on the spur of the moment.''
   Zemti said the pair first demanded to be flown to Tripoli,
Libya, but the plane lacked fuel for the trip. They settled for
Carthage in Tunisia, but Tunisian authorities refused them
permission to land.
   They finally touched down Saturday in Annaba, near the
Algeria-Tunisia border.
   Zemti and passengers reported no ill-treatment.
   Local officials in Ghardaia said the two deserted their base
Friday and ran 14 miles to the airport before hijacking the
Algiers-bound flight.
   They speculated the hijacking may have been an attempt to escape
prosecution for desertion. Passengers said the pair spoke little
and used varying regional accents in an apparent effort to mask
their identities.
   Transport Minister Hassan Kahlouche and passengers said the
hijackers made no statements to support reports they were
protesting a crackdown on Islamic fundamentalists in neighboring
Tunisia.
   One passenger said the hijackers ``broke into laughter'' on
hearing such a report Saturday on Algerian radio.
   ``Right now, this only concerns a simple affair of common law,''
APS quoted Kahlouche as saying.
   Air Algerie said at least 14 passengers aboard the plane were
foreigners. Algerian and Western officials said they included
French, German, Italian, British and Japanese nationals. Most of
the foreigners were freed on Saturday.
   The breakthrough came after dawn on Sunday. The hijackers
announced they would free most of the remaining 52 captives, but
planned to hold the pilot and co-pilot and renewed demands for fuel
to fly to another country.
   The interior minister approached the plane and finalized the
release of the captives, witnesses said. After they disembarked, he
then persuaded the hijackers to give up.
   Various reports during the negotiations said the hijackers had
demanded water and enough fuel to fly to Egypt or Libya.
   Egyptian officials said their airports had been ordered to
refuse them permission to land. There was no comment available from
Libya.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901230-0022 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-30-90 1601EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Soviet-Moldavia     12-30 0420</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Moldavia,0468</SECOND>
<HEAD>Moldavian Parliament Agrees to Gorbachev's Measures</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Moldavia, acting to defuse one of the Soviet
Union's most explosive ethnic conflicts, agreed Sunday to comply
with a Kremlin order to reconsider its law making Moldavian the
republic's official language.
   The republic's parliament acted in response to a decree issued
on Dec. 22 by President Mikhail S. Gorbachev, the official news
agency Tass reported.
   Gorbachev also gave the republic 10 days to dissolve a new
national guard and to come up with measures guaranteeing equal
rights for all ethnic groups within its borders.
   Tass said the Moldavan parliament agreed to disband the nationalguard
and to revise a law that Gorbachev said restricted the rights
of minorities.
   Ethnic tension has gripped Moldavia, a largely agricultural
republic bordering Romania, during its push for independence from
the Soviet Union this year. The unrest turned violent last month,
when government troops clashed with activists, leaving four dead.
   Gorbachev said the conflicts had reached ``critical levels,''
and he put part of the blame on the Moldavian Supreme Soviet for
enacting laws that discriminate against minorities.
   Alarmed by rising Moldavian nationalism, two of the republic's
minority groups have begun their own separatist movements.
   The Gagauz, a group of about 150,000 Turkish Christians,
declared a new republic in southern Moldavia. In the eastern part
of Moldavia, more than 300,000 ethnic Russians and Ukrainians have
joined in declaring a new republic along the Dneister River.
   All three groups claim discrimination by Moldavians. In
particular, they resent a new law making Moldavian the official
language and requiring people in dozens of jobs ranging from
doctors to hairdressers to pass Moldavian language tests by 1995.
   Tass did not say how the Moldavian parliament would modify the
law.
   Moldavian is identical to Romanian except for the Cyrillic
script Josef Stalin imposed on the republic. It is spoken by
two-thirds of the republic's residents.
   Soviet hard-liners want Gorbachev to impose a state of emergency
and presidential rule in troubled zones throughout the ethnically
and geographically diverse country.
   Gorbachev said the declaration of the Gagauz and Dniester
republics was illegal under the Soviet and Moldavian constitutions,
as were elections to form legislatures and any actions by those
bodies. The Moldavian legislature has also voted to declare the
elections null and void.
   After residents of the Gagauz region began holding local
elections in late October, the Moldavian legislature clamped a
two-month state of emergency on the region, restricting movement in
and out of the area and banning public rallies.
   Volunteer brigades of college-age Moldavians, who then flocked
to the region to try to stop the separatist movement, were ordered
dissolved by Gorbachev's decree. The volunteers were organized by
nationalist groups, including the Moldavian People's Front.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901230-0023 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-30-90 1613EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-NewDecade Bjt   12-30 0426</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-New Decade, Bjt,0549</SECOND>
<NOTE>Eds: Retransmitting a0622 to fix keyword format, restoring dropped
comma</NOTE>
<HEAD>Last Decade of the Century Begins, Finally</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RANDOLPH E. SCHMID</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   When does a new decade begin, anyway?
   We ushered in the '90s a year ago, but the last decade of the
20th Century is only now about to unfold. Confused?
   Well, you can thank a monk named Dionysius Exiguus. He started
it all many hundreds of years ago.
   The question surfaces every 10 years and for many people the
answer is obvious: the new decades began with the 1990s a year ago
on Jan. 1, 1990 and will end Dec. 31, 1999.
   But don't tell that to the calendar purists.
   ``If you refer to the decade of the '90s, I'm willing to concede
that 1990 is in the '90s. It's obviously not in the '80s,'' says
LeRoy Doggett, a calendar expert at the U.S. Naval Observatory.
   But he explains that this view of a decade in time is simply a
colloquialism with no basis in history.
   ``When we talk about the last decade of the 20th century we get
into a chronological question which forces you to ask: When did the
first century begin?'' he says.
   Doggett provides this explanation.
   The numbering system in our current Gregorian calendar, indeed
in all human calendars, is arbitrary. Someone picked a particular
date or event and started counting from that point. There is
nothing in nature that causes it to be a particular year, or for a
particular day to be New Year.
   That's where the monk Dionysius Exiguus, or ``Dennis the
Small'', got into the act nearly 1,500 years ago. He had been given
the task of developing a set of tables to help local priests and
bishops determine the date of Easter.
   At the time, everything was dated from the accession of the
Roman emperor Diocletian. But Diocletian had persecuted the early
Christians and Dionysius didn't want to commemorate him in the new
tables.
   Instead Dionysius based the tables on the date of Jesus' birth,
which the monk determined had occurred 532 years earlier. Dionysius
called the year of Jesus' birth the year ``1'' and began the count.
   ``So the first decade was 1 to 10, the second was 11 to 20.
Extrapolating from that, we end up starting a new decade with 1991,
which runs through 2000, which completes the 20th century. So the
21st century starts with 2001,'' said Doggett.
   Why didn't Dionysius simply call the first year ``zero'' and
avoid all the confusion?
   ``Well, the number zero was not then in use in the West,''
explained Doggett. Counting was done using either Roman Numerals or
fingers, neither of which includes a zero.
   There's more.
   Many scholars have concluded that Dionysius actually
miscalculated by two to 10 years the actual birth of Jesus. But by
the time those questions were raised, his numbering system was
widely used and was not changed.
   And the year 1991 is not the only year that makes its debut in
the coming 12 months. The Muslim year 1412 begins at sundown next
July 12 and the Jewish year 5752 begins at sundown next Sept. 8.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901230-0024 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-30-90 1620EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Greece-Pardons 2ndLd-Writethru a0632 12-30 0503</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Greece-Pardons, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0632,0561</SECOND>
<HEAD>Government Scraps Plan to Pardon Ex-Dictators</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: New throughout to UPDATE with Papandreou reaction, newspapers
saying president did not back pardon, governing party criticizing
leftists. No pickup. ADDS byline</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By PATRICK QUINN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ATHENS, Greece (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The conservative government reversed
itself Sunday and said it would not go ahead with announced plans
to pardon Greece's jailed military dictators.
   A government announcement said the decision to back down from
the pardons of leaders of the 1967-74 right-wing military
government was made to avoid ``political tension.''
   Prime Minister Constantine Mitsotakis said Friday he decided to
pardon nearly all the remaining jailed former members of the junta
for humanitarian reasons. That provoked cries of outrage from
conservatives, socialists, Communists, and other leftists, both in
Greece and on the island of Cyprus.
   ``The universal condemnation both in Greece and on Cyprus by ...
the overwhelming majority of the people forced the government to a
hasty retreat,'' said Andreas Papandreou, the leader of the main
opposition socialists.
   Approval had been expected by a government committee this week
and by President Constantine Caramanlis, but newspapers reported
Sunday that Caramanlis would not sign such a presidential decree.
His office would not confirm the reports.
   The government's change of heart came at a Cabinet meeting, its
announcement said.
   ``In order to avoid turning this issue into the object of
artificial political tension, it decided to not advance the
procedures for the granting of a pardon,'' the announcement said.
   It said the time for a pardon was not ripe because ``the larger
issues of the land more than ever call for unity.''
   It accused socialists and Communists of trying to take advantage
of the decision to pardon the jailed dictators ``because of their
small-time interests.''
   A protest against the pardons had been planned for Monday.
Papandreou, whose socialist government ruled from 1981 to 1989, had
said he would request an emergency debate in Parliament on the
issue.
   Leftists accused Mitsotakis of repaying a political debt to a
pro-junta rightist group that has backed his New Democracy Party.
   The former rulers themselves never sought pardon or amnesty. But
junta supporters have lobbied for an amnesty since the officers
were sentenced.
   Most politicians, conservative and left-wing, were jailed,
tortured or exiled during the seven years of authoritarian military
rule. Those imprisoned were convicted of treason, torture, or the
murder of pro-democracy student protesters.
   Eight members of the junta are serving prison terms ranging from
20 years to life imprisonment.
   Those serving life sentences include Col. George Papadopoulos,
71, who led the 1967 coup; his brother Constantine; 69; and former
Brig. Dimitris Ioannides, 67. Ioannides, ex-chief of the dreaded
military police, overthrew Papadopoulos in a 1973 coup.
   Under Mitsotakis' proposal, the only junta member who would not
have been pardoned was Ioannides, who also engineered a failed 1974
coup in Cyprus by right-wing supporters of the island's union with
Greece.
   The disastrous coup attempt prompted an invasion of Cyprus by
Turkey, which partitioned the eastern Mediterranean island. It also
caused the junta's collapse and the restoration of democracy in
Greece.
   On Cyprus, nearly all political parties condemned the proposal
to pardon the leaders. Government spokesman Akis Fantis said
Cypriots will always hold the Greek military dictators responsible
for the island's division.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901230-0025 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-30-90 1625EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Britain-Honors     12-30 0529</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Britain-Honors,0648</SECOND>
<HEAD>Queen Honors P.D. James, Ian McKellen, Barbara Cartland</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: EMBARGOED by source until 7 p.m. EST.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Mystery writer P.D. James, actor Ian McKellen and
romance novelist Barbara Cartland joined a former German prisoner
of war on Britain's New Year's honors list Monday for their
services to queen and country.
   Phyllis Dorothy James, one of the foremost writers of detective
fiction, becomes a baroness. She received the only life peerage on
this year's list, which is selected by the government.
   Miss James, 70, whose latest book is ``Devices and Desires,'' is
chairman of the British Arts Council's literature advisory panel
and a member of the board of governors of the British Broadcasting
Corp. She once worked in forensic science services for the Home
Office, which is in charge of law enforcement.
   The 51-year-old McKellen, who receives a knighthood, is one of
the leading British actors of his generation. Renowned for his
Shakespearean roles, he is on tour as the bard's Richard III and as
Kent in ``King Lear.''
   McKellen, who has also done much to raise money for AIDS
charities, said he was ``very surprised and delighted'' with the
honor.
   Barbara Cartland, 89-year-old doyenne of romantic fiction
writers, becomes a dame of the British Empire. Miss Cartland, who
has just finished her 530th book, said she was ``delighted and very
honored'' to be made a dame.
   She said she thought the award probably was not for literary
achievement but for the charity work she did.
   Her daughter, Raine, became stepmother to Princess Diana when
she married Diana's father, Earl Spencer.
   Also named a dame is Lucie Rie, 88, a distinguished potter whose
work is in the collection of many museums, including the Museum of
Modern Art in New York.
   Among 28 others to receive knighthoods are Shakespearean scholar
and literary critic John Frank Kermode, and Terence English,
director of the world-renowned heart transplant research unit at
Papworth Hospital in Cambridgeshire.
   Among those to receive a Royal Victorian Medal, a personal gift
from Queen Elizabeth II, is Walter Gimpel, 64, a former prisoner of
war. He works as a gardener in the Crown-owned Great Park in
Windsor, 20 miles west of London.
   British forces captured Gimpel, then an 18-year-old conscript in
the German army, in 1944 after the German retreat from Paris. The
medal is an honorary award because Gimpel has retained his German
citizenship.
   Malcolm Bradbury, novelist and professor of American studies,
was awarded the title commander of the British Empire, as was stage
and film actor Marius Goring, whose movies include ``The Red
Shoes'' and ``The Barefoot Contessa.''
   The queen bestowed 995 titles and medals - most of them to
people selected by former Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher for the
twice yearly expression of gratitude.
   The list was drawn up before Mrs. Thatcher's resignation, but
the new prime minister, John Major, reviewed it before publication.
The other awards are made in June with the queen's birthday list.
   It is unusual for there to be only one life peerage, but the new
list follows 10 days after Mrs. Thatcher followed custom and
submitted an honors list in conjunction with her resignation. Her
list included seven life peerages.
   Although critics say the ancient honors tradition has been
tarnished by political patronage, a barony, a knighthood or a
British Empire Medal is still a prize to be treasured. There is no
cash reward but to many the rise in status is priceless.
   Barons and baronesses are addressed as lords and ladies and can
sit in Parliament's unelected House of Lords in the company of
Britain's ancient aristocratic families. Knights are addressed as
sir, and their female equivalents are dames.
   An officer of the Order of the British Empire gets to add OBE
after his or her name.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901230-0026 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-30-90 1625EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-EC     12-30 0323</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-EC,0385</SECOND>
<HEAD>EC Foreign Ministers to Meet on Gulf</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf-Iraq, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Foreign ministers of the 12-nation European
Community will meet this week in Luxembourg to examine the
situation in the Persian Gulf, the French Foreign Ministry
announced Sunday.
   The emergency meeting will come on Friday, 11 days before the
Jan. 15 deadline imposed by the United Nations for Iraq to withdraw
its troops from Kuwait or face possible attack by the U.S.-led
multinational force.
   The Foreign Ministry made the announcement on behalf of
Luxembourg's Foreign Minister Jacques Poos, the ministry's
communique said. Luxembourg takes over the rotating presidency of
the EC from Italy on Tuesday.
   Germany's foreign minister, Hans-Dietrich Genscher, had proposed
the meeting. He appealed again Sunday for a fresh diplomatic effort
to try to avoid war in the gulf, but said Iraq must abide by U.N.
resolutions calling on it to withdraw from Kuwait.
   On Sunday, Iraqi President Saddam Hussein insisted anew that any
solution to the crisis must be linked to a resolution of the
Israeli-Palestinian conflict, the official Iraqi News Agency said.
The United States has rejected any such linkage.
   The European decision to meet and discuss the gulf crisis was
welcomed by the Iraqi ambassador to the United States. But the
envoy said Europe should adopt an independent approach to the gulf
crisis.
   ``It is high time for the Europeans to enunciate their own
policy and not to be subservient to the American policy,'' Mohammad
Sadek Mashat told reporters at Amman airport, where he stopped en
route to Washington after consultations in Baghdad.
   Iraq's information minister, Latif Jassim, said in Baghdad
Sunday that Iraq would not initiate hostilities in the gulf.
   ``We will never attack,'' he told reporters. ``But if Bush
starts a war, he will not be able to stop it ... We will show the
world that America is a paper tiger. You will see how the Americans
will kneel down.''
   Jassim also insisted on Iraq's proposed date of Jan. 12 for any
visit by Secretary of State James A. Baker III.
   Washington has said that date is too close to the Jan. 15
deadline for an Iraqi withdrawal. Iraq overran Kuwait on Aug. 2 in
a dispute over land, money and oil.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901230-0027 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-30-90 1629EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Dole-Bush     12-30 0172</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Dole-Bush,180</SECOND>
<HEAD>It's `Make or Break Time' for Bush, Says Dole.</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Sen. Bob Dole, R-Kan., said Sunday it's ``make
or break time'' for President Bush who faces the twin challenges of
the Persian Gulf crisis and the economic recession.
   Dole, who lost to Bush in the 1988 Republican presidential
primaries, played down difficulties Bush has had with conservatives
in his own party. ``I think he should have satisfied most thinking
conservatives; the others you can't satisfy,'' Dole said on
NBC-TV's ``Meet the Press.''
   He said he had heard rumblings that conservatives wanted to
mount a challenge to Bush in 1992, but he had no details.
   Nevertheless, Dole said the current crises could determine how
Bush fares if he runs for a second term.
   ``I think it's make or break time for George Bush,'' he said.
``We've got twin problems,'' he said referring to the gulf and the
economy.
   ``I think he could do very well in the gulf and still go
downhill on the economy,'' Dole said. ``That may be more difficult
to deal with in the final analysis than the gulf crisis.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901230-0028 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-30-90 1633EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Qayle-Golf     12-30 0373</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Qayle-Golf,450</SECOND>
<HEAD>Vice President Will Continue to Play at All-Male Club</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RITA BEAMISH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>RIYADH, Saudi Arabia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Vice President Dan Quayle said
Sunday he stopped playing at an all-white golf course because it
might look bad, but he has no problem playing at a club that
excludes women.
   quayle, who cut short a golf outing Friday at the all-white
Cypress Point Golf Course in Pebble Beach, Calif., said he will
continue to play at burning Tree course outside Washington where
women are barred as members and can't even play as guests.
   Quayle said he is an honorary member of Burning Tree by virtue
of being vice president, but is not a dues paying member.
   ``I've played there before and I'll play there again,''' he said
when asked about the matter by reporters traveling with him to
visit U.S. troops in Saudi Arabia.
   Ironically, Quayle was explaining himself on the issue while
flying to a country that has bars women from driving, or
socializing or working with men.
   Quayle said he decided to cancel a Friday round of golf at
Cypress Point after learning it was the subject of controversy
because of its all-white membership.
   The club was forced to drop out of the 1991 AT&amp;T Pebble Beach
Pro-Am Professional Golf Association tournament because it refused
to change its policies to make sure blacks could join the club. The
club does not bar black members, but said it was unwilling to have
blacks skip over the long waiting list for membership.
   The PGA's new rules hold that no club can host its tournaments
that do not have minority members.
   Quayle said he had not known about the controversy when he
played there on Thursday.
   Asked how he could not know of the issue, which was highly
publicized in the golf world, he said: ``Very few people knew about
it. They knew about it in California. I didn't know about it. I
don't have time to read a lot about golf these days.''
   He noted that blacks can play as guests. ``Cypress Point does
not discriminate,'' he said, adding, however, that ``perceptions
are important and therefore I chose to exercise judgment along
those lines'' in canceling the game Friday after public criticism
arose.
   He did not apply the same standard to Burning Tree.
   ``I'm not going to protest Burning Tree,'' he said. ``Maybe
they'll change. I think it would be a good idea for them to take
women into the club. I don't have any problem playing there in the
meanwhile.''
   Further, he noted, ``There are a lot other very well respected
people that have played at Burning Tree.'' The club's membership
roster long has boasted some of the nation's most powerful men.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901230-0029 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-30-90 1635EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BRF--BodyguardArrest     12-30 0177</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Bodyguard Arrest,0190</SECOND>
<HEAD>Secret Service Agent Arrested for Shoplifting</HEAD>
<DATELINE>VAIL, Colo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Secret Service agent assigned to protect
Vice President Dan Quayle was arrested for shoplifting after
allegedly trying to steal a $280 ski jacket, authorities said.
   Joyce Fletcher of Washington was charged with misdemeanor theft
and released after posting a $300 bond. The charge carries a
maximum penalty of 30 days in jail and a $1,000 fine. She is to
appear Jan. 31 in Vail Municipal Court.
   Police Chief Ken Hughey said Fletcher, 39, was arrested Thursday
after allegedly stuffing the jacket into a shopping bag in a
changing room at the Gart Brothers store.
   Store manager Rick Jones said he followed her when she left and
told an associate to call police. Jones said he saw Fletcher's
Secret Service identification card when she was arrested.
   Allan Cramer, a Secret Service agent in Vail, said the agency
would begin an internal investigation Monday.
   Quayle has been vacationing in Vail, 70 miles west of Denver, on
and off since before Christmas. He left on Saturday to visit U.S.
troops in the Persian Gulf.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901230-0030 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-30-90 1648EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Rushdie 1stLd-Writethru a0640 12-30 0509</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Rushdie, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0640,0604</SECOND>
<HEAD>Report: Rushdie May Travel to Egypt</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 7 grafs to UPDATE with comment from Egyptian
presidential spokesman. Pickup 7th pvs, `Rushdie's supporters...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By GRAHAM HEATHCOTE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Author Salman Rushdie is expected to emerge from
nearly two years of hiding to travel to Egypt early next year at
the invitation of Moslem scholars, a British newspaper reported
Sunday.
   Such a trip would be in defiance of threats by Iranian religious
leaders to kill the Indian-born author for allegedly blaspheming
Islam in his novel ``The Satanic Verses.''
   The report in the weekly Observer newspaper followed Rushdie's
announcement on Dec. 24 that he had embraced Islam and would oppose
further translations of his book and prevent a paperback edition.
   The Observer reported that Egyptian President Hosni Mubarak had
approved the invitation from Egypt's minister for Islamic affairs,
Dr. Muhammad Mahgoub. It said Rushdie would visit there with
leading Moslem scholars.
   A Mubarak press spokesman, Mohammed Abdel-Moneim, said in Cairo
that he didn't know of any such invitation, adding Mubarak is
``preoccupied with much more important issues.''
   The spokesman said he could not rule out that such an invitation
had been made by Mahgoub in his capacity as a Moslem scholar.
Mahgoub was not immediately available for comment.
   The Observer said the move was welcomed by the spiritual head of
Sunni Moslems, Grand Sheik Gad el-Hak. The newspaper quoted him as
saying: ``Rushdie should not be held responsible for any sins he
may have committed before embracing Islam.''
   Rushdie's supporters expressed disappointment Sunday with his
decision to stop further translations and prevent a paperback
edition.
   Rushdie's decision was an attempt to persuade Iranian religious
leaders to cancel the death sentence, issued by the late Ayatollah
Ruhollah Khomeini in Feb. 1989. But Iran has rejected Rushdie's
effort.
   The Sunday Times reported friends of Rushdie ``reacted with
disbelief'' and said their campaign for free speech was ``in
tatters.''
   ``It seems the religious terrorists have won,'' playwright
Arnold Wesker was quoted as saying in The Sunday Times of London.
   Wesker, a leading member of the Rushdie defense committee,
called the development ``incredibly depressing.''
   The newspaper quoted Alan Sillitoe, who signed a statement
defending Rushdie's right to express his ideas, as saying:
   ``The inability to publish the paperback is a blow to writers.
It makes you imagine there will be a time when you will have to
send books up to Bradford (a northern city with has a large Moslem
community) to be stamped in case they have anything offensive in
them.''
   Writer Fay Weldon, who wrote a booklet defending Rushdie, said
she was sad Rushdie appeared to be backing down.
   ``If you appear to weaken, they advance,'' she said.
   However, Frances D'Souza, chairman of the defense committee,
told The Sunday Times: ``What an individual does and what he
chooses to do in a spiritual sense is his own affair. What we are
fighting for is that no person should be condemned to death for
expressing an opinion. That issue remains.''
   Rushdie, 43, a British national, remains in hiding under police
guard. In recent weeks, Rushdie has broken his isolation by several
quick visits to bookstores and interviews.
   The Independent on Sunday, in a telephone interview with
Rushdie, askd him what he would say to those who saw his previous
stand for his novel not just as a defense of literature but also an
attack on religious intolerance.
   ``If they see Islam as an enemy, then they are not my friends,''
Rushdie replied.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901230-0031 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-30-90 1653EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Bangladesh     12-30 0355</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bangladesh,0414</SECOND>
<HEAD>Supporters Demand Ershad's Release; Prisoners Riot</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DHAKA, Bangladesh (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   About 800 supporters of deposed
President Hussain Muhammad Ershad demonstrated Sunday demanding his
release from house arrest, where he was placed while the government
investigates corruption charges.
   The United News of Bangladesh new agency said the rally north of
Dhaka was the first public show of support for Ershad since he was
forced to resign Dec. 6 after two months of nationwide protests.
   The caretaker government of acting President Shahabuddin Ahmed
on Dec. 12 ordered Ershad put under house arrest while a commission
looks into claims of corruption and abuse of power during his
eight-year rule.
   Leaders of Ershad's Jatiya Party gave speeches Sunday on a
highway demanding the release of Ershad and jailed ministers, then
marched through Tongi, 10 miles north of Dhaka, the news agency
said. Some bystanders hooted the demonstration.
   Hasanuddin Sarker, a local Jatiya leader, said the party would
not participate in parliamentary elections set for Feb. 27 unless
Ershad is freed.
   Ershad, a former army general who seized power in 1982, is
confined to a house in the Gulshan diplomatic suburb along with his
wife and 8-year-old son. Bangladesh law permits detention without
charges for 120 days.
   Meanwhile, at least 10 prisoners fled the Dhaka Central Jail on
Sunday while thousands of inmates rioted there, claiming they were
unjustly jailed by military judges during Ershad's administration.
   About 5,000 prisoners paraded inside the jail with the bodies of
three inmates shot to death during an attempted breakout Saturday,
a police official said.
   Guards opened fire when the prisoners broke out of their cells
and tried to smash open the main gate. About 100 prisoners and 12
prison guards were also injured, police said.
   On Sunday, shouts of ``We want punishment for the killers!'' and
``We want food!'' reverberated over the walls of the jail in the
heart of the congested old sector of Dhaka, a city of 3{ million
people.
   While the prisoners were demonstrating, at least 10 climbed the
western wall of the jail and fled down an alley, the United News of
Bangladesh said. It had no information on what they were jailed
for.
   A home ministry official who spoke with the inmates said they
were demanding a blanket amnesty. That is impossible because the
prison population includes murderers, rapists and other hard
criminals, the official said, speaking on condition of anonymity.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901230-0032 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-30-90 1657EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Israel     12-30 0534</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel,0650</SECOND>
<HEAD>Curfews Order Palestinians To Homes in Gaza Following Clashes</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos TLV2,3</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MAX NASH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>RAFAH, Occupied Gaza Strip (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   About 250,000 Palestinians
were ordered confined to their homes in the occupied Gaza Strip on
Sunday following clashes a day earlier that left four Palestinians
dead and at least 90 wounded.
   Eighteen protesters were wounded in clashes with troops in Gaza
City, Arab reports said.
   In another development, Labor Party leader Shimon Peres on
Sunday denied reports that Israeli officials have spoken with
Palestinians about granting autonomy to the Gaza Strip.
   The report Saturday from Amman, attributed to PLO officials,
said Peres and other Israelis had met a Palestinian official and
Saudi businessman last week in Paris about the autonomy idea.
   ``It has no basis,'' a spokeswoman for Peres, Bahira Bardugo,
said in a telephone interview.
   In the occupied West Bank, one Arab died Sunday in a clash
between Palestinian collaborators and Arab activists. Three
Palestinians suspected of being collaborators with Israel fired on
stone-throwing Arab activists in the town of Yaabad, Arab and media
reports said.
   Killed in the shooting was Rabiya Hamarshe, 26, the reports
said. The army confirmed that an Arab was killed by a fellow
Palestinian in Yaabad.
   In the West Bank city of Nablus, Manar Bakir, 19, was killed by
an explosive near the military headquarters, Arab reports said. The
army command confirmed the incident and said the youth died when an
explosive device he was preparing went off.
   Curfews were clamped on Nablus and Ya'bad following the
violence.
   Israel also imposed the curfews in the Gaza Strip to prevent
violence after the clashes Saturday with soldiers - the worst in
Gaza in more than six months. In Rafah, where Saturday's violence
began, streets covered with stones were deserted except for army
patrols and one burning tire.
   Arab merchants staged a commercial strike throughout the West
Bank to protest Saturday's bloodshed. In Nablus, masked activists
marched during the night brandishing pistols, automatic weapons and
posters of PLO chief Yasser Arafat.
   Military officials attributed the tensions to the 26th
anniversary of the founding of the PLO's mainstream Fatah guerrilla
movement on Tuesday.
   The military government closed all schools in the West Bank for
two weeks beginning Monday to ward off any riots marking the
anniversary, Arab reports said.
   Military government spokesman Shmuel Ozenboy said that the
schools were shut for winter vacation, but Arab reporters said the
vacation had been planned for the middle of January.
   The Israeli military defended soldiers' actions in the Gaza
Strip on Saturday, saying they opened fire only when their lives
were in danger.
   The riots began when two masked Arabs were shot dead in Rafah
after refusing orders from troops to halt, and another two
Palestinians were killed as soldiers dispersed stone and firebomb
throwers in the area, Arab and army reports said later.
   The army said a woman initially listed as a riot fatality turned
out to have had a heart attack. Arab reports said 194 people were
wounded while army counts put the number at 90.
   The killing in Yaabad on Sunday brought to 323 the number of
Palestinians slain by fellow Arabs, most on suspicion of
collaborating with Israel.
   At least 785 Palestinians have been killed by Israeli troops or
civilians in the uprising. Fifty-seven Israelis have also been
slain in the violence.
   Also Sunday, the body of an Israeli man was found with his
throat cut in his apartment in the northern port city of Haifa.
   City police commander Yossi Levy told Israel radio he suspected
a political motive in the slaying of Yossi Malchin, 60, but that
other motives were being checked.
   Israel army radio reported later that his adopted Arab son had
been detained.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901230-0033 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-30-90 1707EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Quayle-Golf     12-30 0379</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Quayle-Golf,450</SECOND>
<NOTE>EDS: Retrasmitting a0657 to fix keyword line</NOTE>
<HEAD>Vice President Will Continue to Play at All-Male Club</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RITA BEAMISH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>RIYADH, Saudi Arabia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Vice President Dan Quayle said
Sunday he stopped playing at an all-white golf course because it
might look bad, but he has no problem playing at a club that
excludes women.
   Quayle, who cut short a golf outing Friday at the all-white
Cypress Point Golf Course in Pebble Beach, Calif., said he will
continue to play at burning Tree course outside Washington where
women are barred as members and can't even play as guests.
   Quayle said he is an honorary member of Burning Tree by virtue
of being vice president, but is not a dues paying member.
   ``I've played there before and I'll play there again,''' he said
when asked about the matter by reporters traveling with him to
visit U.S. troops in Saudi Arabia.
   Ironically, Quayle was explaining himself on the issue while
flying to a country that has bars women from driving, or
socializing or working with men.
   Quayle said he decided to cancel a Friday round of golf at
Cypress Point after learning it was the subject of controversy
because of its all-white membership.
   The club was forced to drop out of the 1991 AT&amp;T Pebble Beach
Pro-Am Professional Golf Association tournament because it refused
to change its policies to make sure blacks could join the club. The
club does not bar black members, but said it was unwilling to have
blacks skip over the long waiting list for membership.
   The PGA's new rules hold that no club can host its tournaments
that do not have minority members.
   Quayle said he had not known about the controversy when he
played there on Thursday.
   Asked how he could not know of the issue, which was highly
publicized in the golf world, he said: ``Very few people knew about
it. They knew about it in California. I didn't know about it. I
don't have time to read a lot about golf these days.''
   He noted that blacks can play as guests. ``Cypress Point does
not discriminate,'' he said, adding, however, that ``perceptions
are important and therefore I chose to exercise judgment along
those lines'' in canceling the game Friday after public criticism
arose.
   He did not apply the same standard to Burning Tree.
   ``I'm not going to protest Burning Tree,'' he said. ``Maybe
they'll change. I think it would be a good idea for them to take
women into the club. I don't have any problem playing there in the
meanwhile.''
   Further, he noted, ``There are a lot other very well respected
people that have played at Burning Tree.'' The club's membership
roster long has boasted some of the nation's most powerful men.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901230-0034 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-30-90 1724EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-WeatherpageWeather     12-30 0359</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Weatherpage Weather,0421</SECOND>
<HEAD>Record Cold in West, Record Warm in East, Wet Everywhere Else</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Temperatures hit record lows across the western half of the
nation Sunday, with the coldest 39 below zero, and rain and snow
extended from the southern Plains to New England.
   The record lows contrasted with record highs along the East
Coast.
   At the leading edge of the latest blast of cold air, a cold
front moved through Corpus Christi, Texas, at midday and the
temperature dropped 22 degrees in 15 minutes, from 76 to 54. The
city on the Gulf of Mexico was expected to fall into the 20s during
the night.
   Temperatures dropped to record lows at almost two dozen cities
in California, Colorado, Idaho, Kansas, Minnesota, Nebraska,
Nevada, North Dakota, Oklahoma, Oregon, South Dakota, and Texas.
   The low of 20 at Red Bluff, Calif., toppled a record that had
stood since 1882. The official coldest spot in the Lower 48 states
was a record 39 below zero at International Falls, Minn.
   But along the East Coast, record highs extended from
Jacksonville, Fla., at 81, to Caribou, Maine, at 39. Most of the
records were in the 60s and 70s, including 70 at Elkins, W.Va.,
usually a cold spot in the Appalachians.
   Snow fell over Michigan, eastern Wisconsin, much of Illinois,
northern Indiana, the southeastern third of Missouri, the
northwestern half of Arkansas, southeastern Oklahoma and
northeastern Texas.
   Freezing rain fell from central Texas across northwestern
Louisiana, from southwestern through northeastern Arkansas, western
Kentucky, from southwestern through east-central Indiana and
northwestern Ohio.
   Rain extended from the upper Texas Gulf Coast across parts of
Louisiana, Arkansas, Tennessee, Kentucky, Indiana, Ohio, West
Virginia, Pennsylvania, New York, Vermont and New Hampshire.
   Thunderstorms were scattered over the central Gulf of Mexico
states.
   Heavier rainfall during the six hours up to noon included 1.49
inches at Pittsburgh; 1.48 inches at Bowling Green, Ky.; 1.34
inches at Louisville, Ky.; 1.17 inches at Fort Campbell, Ky.; and
1.05 inches at Lexington, Ky.
   In the Northwest, a new storm was moving inland and at midday
snow was falling from the Washington coast across northern Idaho
and western Montana.
   Two days of rain and snow melting caused flooding in Indiana,
northern Ohio and western Pennsylvania. Evacuations were widespread
in Indiana.
   Temperatures around the nation at 3 p.m. EST ranged from 15
below zero at Devils Lake, N.D., to 87 at Fort Myers, Fla.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901230-0035 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-30-90 1730EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Korea     12-30 0387</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Korea,0451</SECOND>
<HEAD>Former Korean President Ends Self-Exile, Says He Wants Ordinary
Life</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KELLY SMITH TUNNEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SEOUL, South Korea (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Former authoritarian ruler Chun
Doo-hwan said Sunday he wants only to live as ``an ordinary
citizen'' now that he had ended two years of self-imposed exile.
   However, radical student leaders have renewed demands that Chun
be prosecuted for alleged corruption, human rights violations and
abuses of power. They called Chun ``a symbol of suppression'' and
blamed him for crushing a 1980 pro-democracy uprising in Kwangju in
which at least 200 people died.
   About 2,500 police guarded streets and alleyways near Chun's
Seoul home. About 150 supporters, some waving welcome placards,
greeted Chun and his wife, Lee Soong-ja, when they arrived earlier
in the day.
   Chun returned to the capital from a remote 14th century Buddhist
temple in the eastern mountains where he had gone two years ago to
atone for past wrongs.
   ``In the future, I will continue to live as an ordinary
citizen,'' the former general said in a statement. o At Seoul's
Yonsei University, 30 radical student leaders issued a statement
pledging to ``fight and crush'' what they called President Roh
Tae-woo's plot to perpetuate Chun's 1980-87 government.
   Roh, a former general who helped Chun seize power in 1980, has
appealed to the nation for mercy for Chun. News reports said Roh
sent an orchid plant to Chun's home Sunday with a message reading
``ushering out the past, ushering in the new.''
   Chun left Seoul to go into exile in November 1988 after
apologizing for alleged corruption, human rights violations and
abuses of power during his rule. Nationwide demonstrations in 1987
forced Chun to call elections and step down.
   More than a dozen of Chun's relatives and associates were
convicted of wrongdoing and imprisoned. Roh's government never took
action against Chun, who said he was innocent.
   Chun was a founder of Roh's Democratic Liberal Party. Some
observers feel his return is an orchestrated effort by Roh to
consolidate the party, which has been riddled by factional
fighting.
   Opposition leader Kim Dae-jung has said he would not oppose Chun
resuming a normal life, but he warned the former president to avoid
politics.
   In 1987, mass anti-government protests forced Chun to accept
opposition demands for direct popular elections. He hand-picked Roh
as the governing party candidate and Roh won the presidency by a
narrow margin in December 1987. Chun now claims credit for ``the
country's first peaceful transfer of power.''
   Even after his exile, dissatisfied dissidents and students
staged violent protests demanding his arrest. Police guards were
deployed outside the temple where he sought refuge.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901230-0036 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-30-90 1815EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-SriLanka-Truce     12-30 0337</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Sri Lanka-Truce,0390</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tamil Rebels Offer Indefinite Truce</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PATRICK CRUEZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>COLOMBO, Sri Lanka (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Tamil rebels on Sunday offered the Sri
Lankan government an indefinite New Year's truce, saying peace
talks could begin if the proposed cease-fire takes hold.
   A statement issued by the Tamil Tigers' office in London said
the rebels will unilaterally stop their attacks at midnight Monday.
   ``In case the government fails to respond to our peace
initiative, our national liberation army will reserve the right to
defensive armed actions,'' the statement said.
   There was no immediate government reaction. The truce offer was
the top story in the Sunday Observer, a government newspaper that
has taken a strong stand against the rebels.
   A senior Defense Ministry official, speaking privately, said:
``So far as we are concerned, our military operations against the
Tigers are continuing as usual.''
   On Thursday, Deputy Defense Minister Ranjan Wijeratne rejected
the possibility of a cease-fire and said peace in 1991 would depend
on the government's efficiency in liquidating the Tamil Tigers.
   At least 14,000 people have died in fighting since the rebels
began their violent campaign for a separate homeland in 1983.
   The rebels accuse the Sinhalese Buddhist majority of
discriminating against the Tamils, who are mostly Hindus. Tamils
make up 18 percent of the population of 16 million on this island
off the southern coast of India.
   Sunday's was the first cease-fire offer by the rebels since they
scuttled a 13-month long truce with the government and resumed
fighting June 11. At least 4,000 people have died in violence since
then.
   In an interview last week from London, senior rebel leader
Sathasivam Krishnakumar had said the cease-fire might last only a
few days and would be linked to a demand that government troops
remain in their barracks.
   But the Tigers' statement Sunday set no conditions for the
indefinite cease-fire and declared it a goodwill gesture.
   ``Our unilateral decision to observe a cease-fire has placed the
entire responsibility with the Sri Lankan government as to whether
to maintain peace or to continue to wage war against our people,''
it said.
   The government controls several major towns in eastern Sri
Lanka, but the Tigers move easily in the jungles and dominate the
north.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901230-0037 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-30-90 1816EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Quayle-Gulf 1stLd-Writethru a0647 12-30 0553</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Quayle-Gulf, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0647,650</SECOND>
<HEAD>With AM-US-Gulf Bjt</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: Top 10 grafs new with meeting details; pickup 8th prv, ``The
Pentagon xxx SHOULD STAND FOR AMS</NOTE>
<HEAD>Quayle Talks With Saudis, Seeks More Money for Military Effort</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RITA BEAMISH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>RIYADH, Saudi Arabia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Vice President Dan Quayle told Saudi
King Fahd on Sunday that the United States expects more financial
support from the oil-rich nation for U.S. military efforts against
Iraq and the Arab ruler seemed to agree, U.S. officials said.
   They said no figures were mentioned in the two-hour meeting, but
that U.S. officials left with the impression there will be no
problem getting more money with the Saudis.
   ``They have been forthcoming on that subject,'' said one senior
administration official. ``The impression that was left was that
they would continue to be forthcoming. They don't want any
perception of any reluctance on that issue.''
   Quayle, who was not available to reporters after the late night
meeting, had said in advance that he intended to tell Saudi leaders
``they will have to be making more contributions.''
   The vice president's three-day visit began just 16 days before
the United Nations-imposed Jan. 15 deadline for Iraq to withdraw
its troops from Kuwait or face possible war..
   The U.S. official, who discussed the Quayle-Fahd meeting on
condition of not being identified by name, said the two were ``in
virtually complete agreement on what needed to be done'' in terms
of forcing Iraq out of Kuwait.
   ``There was no reticence'' on Fahd's part to the idea of
launching a war against Iraq if President Saddam Hussein does not
withdraw, the official said.
   The official said Quayle also assured Fahd that, despite
reluctance expressed by some members of Congress, ``President Bush
would have the latitude to do what he felt he had to do,'' after
Jan. 15 - including a military strike.
   Quayle met separately with Fahd and the Saudi deputy prime
minister, Crown Prince Abdullah, shortly after his arrival.
   He planned to meet with Kuwait's exile emir on Tuesday after a
New Year's Day visit to some of the more than 300,000 U.S. troops
in the region.
   The Pentagon previously has projected the cost of Operation
Desert Shield, as the deployment is called, at $8.2 billion through
the end of 1990. The costs are expected to increase, however,
because of the additional troops currently being deployed. A
full-scale shooting war has been estimated to cost as much as $1
billion to $2 billion a day.
   ``You are seeing other nations making contributions .. I will
thank (the Saudis and Kuwaitis) for the contributions they have
made thus far, but point out that more contributions will have to
be made ... because the crisis is going to continue,'' said Quayle.
   So far, Saudi Arabia has contributed $9 billion, nearly half of
it in cash and the rest in military support for U.S. troops in
Saudi Arabia, according to the State Department. Kuwait has given
$2.5 billion, U.S. officials said.
   Saudi Arabia also has spent $3.9 billion and Kuwait $3.3 billion
to help countries such as Turkey and Egypt that have suffered
severe economic repercussions from the U.N.-imposed economic
sanctions against Iraq.
   Quayle will spend much of New Year's Day visiting with U.S.
troops in the gulf.
   Among those deployed to the region are units of the Indiana
National Guard in which Quayle served during the Vietnam War. He
was later embroiled in controversy over whether he used family
connections to get into the Guard unit rather than risk being
drafted and sent to Vietnam.
   Asked about President Bush's comment to Time magazine that he
has a ``gut feeling'' Saddam Hussein will withdraw by the deadline,
Quayle said he was not as optimistic.
   ``I hope he does. But I certainly do not see any information
that he will do so. Saddam Hussein has always done the unexpected
... let's hope he does the unexpected again,'' said Quayle. But he
added, ``if force is required, it will be swift, it will be
massive, it will be certain.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901230-0038 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-30-90 1820EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-RightToDie 1stLd-Writethru a0664 12-30 0652</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Right To Die, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0664,0801</SECOND>
<HEAD>Court Blocks Father From Moving Daughter</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: RECASTS lead making `fuss' to legal strife.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By SCOTT CHARTON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOUNT VERNON, Mo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The father of a brain-damaged patient
at the hospital where Nancy Cruzan was allowed to die after a court
fight has been blocked from moving his daughter to a state where
her feeding tube could be removed with less legal strife.
   Pete Busalacchi says his daughter, Christine, should be allowed
to die. But Don Lamkins, director of the Missouri Rehabilitation
Center, contends Ms. Busalacchi has mental functions and responds
to commands.
   Ms. Busalacchi, 20, has spent 3{ years in a vegetative state
similar to that of Ms. Cruzan, who was buried Friday after becoming
a focus of national debate and a landmark U.S. Supreme Court ruling
on the right to die.
   The case renewed warnings Sunday from euthanasia opponents that
a ``tidal wave'' of death for hopeless patients would result from
the Cruzan case.
   Lamkins said Sunday that the 10-day restraining order issued
Saturday will give doctors time to examine Ms. Busalacchi. Lawrence
County Judge Scott Sifferman scheduled a Jan. 8 hearing to hear
results of the tests.
   There are parallels in the Cruzan and Busalacchi cases. Both
young women suffered severe brain damage in car crashes. Their
parents contended there was no sign of recognition, pain or emotion
in either patient. And neither left written instructions about
being kept alive in case of debilitating illness or injury.
   Busalacchi said Sunday that he was angry and frustrated about
the legal action.
   ``My feeling is my daughter died a long time ago, and all that's
left is just a machine,'' Busalacchi said from his home in St.
Charles, Mo., a suburb of St. Louis.
   Busalacchi said he had hired a lawyer and planned to fight.
   ``I will not see my daughter held prisoner in Missouri,'' he
said.
   The U.S. Supreme Court, ruling in its first right-to-die case,
said June 25 that Missouri could require ``clear and convincing''
evidence that Ms. Cruzan, 33, would not want to be kept alive in
her vegetative state. Her relatives returned to state court with
three witnesses whose testimony led to a judge's permission to
remove Ms. Cruzan's feeding tube on Dec. 14.
   She died 12 days later.
   Busalacchi said he spoke Sunday morning with Ms. Cruzan's
father, Joe, who ``told me to be strong and offered to help in any
way he could.''
   Busalacchi expected to move Christine on Saturday to
Minneapolis, where specialists were to decide whether her tube
should be removed under state provisions that recognize ethical
decisions by doctors.
   Dr. Ronald Cranford of Hennepin County Medical Center in
Minneapolis, one of Ms. Busalacchi's doctors, said Saturday it
would be the first case he knew in which a person was transferred
from a state with a highly restrictive right-to-die law to another
state to allow removal of life-support equipment.
   Cranford, a neurologist and medical ethicist who has been a
consultant in the Busalacchi case, said Ms Busalacci is incapable
of any conscious thoughts or deliberate actions. The finding is
based on the medical records and his personal observations.
   In an affidavit filed with the judge Saturday, Lamkins said
there was ``scientific and observational evidence'' that Ms.
Busalacchi was ``cognitive of her surroundings and does have some
mental functions.''
   He said that on Dec. 19, on a nurse's command, the young woman
waved at him.
   ``She waved only one finger. When the nurse said `You can do
better than that,' or words to that effect, Christine Busalacchi
waved at me with all her fingers, clearly aware of what was said to
her and of her surroundings.''
   The father rejected Lamkins' observations.
   ``Yes, her fingers can move. But it doesn't happen on command.
It doesn't happen with consistency,'' he said. ``They also say she
can smile at you, but it's no smile that you or I would
recognize.''
   Activists raised protests Sunday.
   ``Certainly this has set off the tidal wave we warned about,
since there is no clear and convincing evidence in Christine's case
that she would want to die,'' Rita Marker, director of the
International Anti-Euthanasia Task Force, said Sunday from
Steubenville, Ohio.
   ``We have to realize that much of this debate has to do with
relieving the family of a burden,'' she said.
   Kay S. Dowhower, Washington-based director of governmental
affairs for the Evangelical Lutheran Church in America, said Sunday
that denominations which supported the Cruzans should also
sympathize with Busalacchi, who in the early 1970s had to decide to
take his terminally ill wife off life-support equipment.
   The Evangelical Lutherans joined four other major denominations
in supporting the Cruzans.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901230-0039 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-30-90 1833EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BRF--StolenTurtle     12-30 0169</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Stolen Turtle,0192</SECOND>
<HEAD>Boy's 6-Foot Ninja Turtle Stolen</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DALLAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A $50 reward is being offered for the safe return
of Michelangelo - a 6-foot wooden Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtle last
seen wishing passersby a merry Christmas.
   Four-year-old David Moor's life-size statue was stolen just
before Christmas.
   ``I felt sad,'' David said. ``Maybe the policeman will find it
for me and bring it back.''
   Rex Gash, David's neighbor and a carpenter, said it took him
four days to cut the wood and paint the replica of the character.
   ``I didn't know what a Mutant Ninja Turtle looked like before I
did this,'' Gash said. ``I watched the movie one night and made
sketches the next day.''
   Gash said he gave David the statue about a week before
Christmas.
   ``He was just as excited as he could be,'' Gash said. ``He was
jumping up and down.''
   David and his mother, Nancy Moor, put the statue with a holiday
greeting outside their home and it was stolen a few days later.
Witnesses said they saw a car speed away with it. Gash is offering
the reward.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901230-0040 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-30-90 1844EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Panama     12-30 0250</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama,0269</SECOND>
<HEAD>Panama's President Clashes With Parliament Over Security Agency</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Guillermo Endara has
rejected the National Assembly's callfor an investigation of a new
security agency that he reportedly set up with help from the CIA
and without legislative approval.
   The assembly on Saturday created a commission to investigate the
Council of Public Security and National Defense. It also criticized
Endara for ``disrespectful and excessive'' treatment of a deputy
who questioned his creation of the agency without legislative
approval.
   The Miami Herald and the Washington Post reported recently that
Panama formed an intelligence agency with help from the CIA and the
Taiwanese and Venezuelan security services.
   Endara late Saturday accused the lawmakers of ``trying to meddle
in matters which are the private affairs of the executive branch.''
   ``It seems that some legislators are interested in getting rid
of a service of security and defense information which reports
directly to the president,'' Endara said.
   He denied that the new council, created by executive order in
February, was involved in espionage.
   A Dec. 25 Washington Post story said the agency was created in
July, had 100 members and was being established with the help of
the CIA.
   Many Panamanians are suspicious of the agency, the Post
reported, because the CIA also once maintained a relationship with
Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega. The strongman was overthrown in last
December's U.S. invasion.
   The story said the agency's director was Menalco Solis, a former
law partner of Endara who was also treasury minister in Noriega's
puppet civilian government in 1984-85.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901230-0041 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-30-90 1847EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Philippines-Fire     12-30 0205</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Philippines-Fire,0235</SECOND>
<HEAD>Fire in Philippines Hotel Kills Three American Servicemen</HEAD>
<DATELINE>OLONGAPO, Philippines (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Fire swept through a two-story
hotel packed with U.S. servicemen en route to the Persian Gulf on
Sunday, and police said three Americans and a Filipino woman were
killed.
   Two other Americans were injured in the fire, which broke out
about 1:30 a.m. at the 34-room, two-story Royal Lodge Hotel, one of
many around the Subic Bay naval base filled with sailors shipping
out to the gulf.
   Mike Pusing, spokesman for the city government, said the cause
had not been determined but arson was suspected.
   Investigators said one of the dead was an enlisted man assigned
to the aircraft carrier USS Ranger, part of a convoy that arrived
at Subic Bay from San Diego on Thursday on its way to the gulf.
   The other American victims also were believed assigned to the
task force, the largest to sail from the west coast of the United
States since World War II.
   The U.S. Navy withheld the names of the dead pending
notification of relatives.
   U.S. Embassy spokesman Stanley Schrager said the two injured
were in stable condition at the base hospital. Witnesses said
dozens of Americans fled the hotel in their nightclothes.
   The hotel is about a mile from the main gate at Subic, which is
about 50 miles west of Manila, Pusing said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901230-0042 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-30-90 1901EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Argentina-Pardons 1stLd-Writethru a0672 12-30 0522</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Argentina-Pardons, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0672,0603</SECOND>
<HEAD>Argentines Bitterly Divided on Pardons</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 7 grafs to UPDATE with crowd estimate of 40,000
sted 15,000; DELETES 6th pvs `The pardons...' as redundant; pickup
graf 9 pvs ```We here...'</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto BAI1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ED McCULLOUGH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUENOS AIRES, Argentina (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   About 40,000 Argentines rallied
outside President Carlos Menem's office Sunday to protest his
pardon of key figures who served in the military dictatorship
during the 1970s ``dirty war'' on leftists.
   Menem's action Saturday revealed a nation still bitterly divided
over a painful period of its history.
   Roman Catholic Bishop Jaime de Nevares said the pardons mocked
justice, broke the law and trampled on human rights. Another church
leader, Archbishop Antonio Quarracino, said they were necessary and
``make me happy.''
   The two rival factions of the General Labor Federation,
Argentina's major labor group, were also divided.
   Recent polls showed up to 80 percent of Argentines opposed the
pardons.
   The pardons included Mario Firmenich, 42-year-old co-founder of
the Montonero terrorist movement; and former Presidents Jorge
Videla, 65, and Roberto Viola, 66, who ruled the country from the
1976 coup until 1982; and nine other officials.
   Sunday afternoon, about 40,000 people - a cross-section of ages,
income levels, political parties and professions - gathered outside
Menem's office waving banners and angrily denouncing the pardons.
   ``We're here to tell him that we haven't forgotten what
happened, and we won't forget,'' said protester Daniel Sossa. He
said his aunt was arrested during the 1976-83 dictatorship and
never heard from again.
   Menem, himself jailed without charge during the period, told
reporters: ``They can have all the marches they want. ... That
doesn't bother me. I believe it was best for my country. Period.''
   Videla, freed Saturday after more than five years in prison,
attended Mass at a chapel near his apartment Sunday and handed
reporters a short statement that said in part: ``I ask God to
extinguish forever the hatred among Argentines with the goal that
we all may reconcile ourselves in peace, union and liberty.''
   Viola, Videla and six other senior officers were pardoned for
crimes including torture, illegal detention and murder. Former
finance minister Jose Martinez de Hoz and two former civilian
officials, all of whom had been jailed on other charges, were
included in the pardon.
   Menem said the pardons, by ending a justification for military
restiveness, would allow Argentina to look ahead. But many said
they merely reopened wounds.
   ``The pardons do not leave the past behind, but take us back to
the worst failures of our past,'' said former President Raul
Alfonsin, leader of the main opposition party, the Radical Civic
Union.
   ``This is the saddest day in Argentine history,'' he said.
   Urban terrorist attacks in the 1970s and the military junta's
heavy-handed response still wrench Argentina's national psyche
seven years after the return to democracy with Alfonsin's election
in October 1983. Menem was elected last year.
   Alfonsin and the Congress gave amnesty to hundreds of
lower-ranking officers, after three military uprisings against his
government to protest pending trials of soldiers accused of rights
abuses.
   A fourth rebellion to protest Videla's imprisonment was crushed
by the government Dec. 3. Menem had earlier promised the military
that the pardons were in the works.
   The military insists it was forced to use unconventional methods
to stop the leftist guerrillas. Many claim the military used the
insurgency as a pretext for repression.
   At least 8,960 alleged leftists disappeared and were presumed
executed. Human rights put the death toll at about 30,000.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901230-0043 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-30-90 1902EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ConcertArrests 1stLd-Writethru a0670 12-30 0391</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Concert Arrests, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0670,0475</SECOND>
<HEAD>Punk Fans Rampage in Los Angeles, Rap Fans Brawl in Chicago</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: CORRECTS typo in `anti-Semitism' in last graf.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Punk rock fans ordered to leave an
overcrowded concert hall went on a rampage, ripping out seats,
hurling bottles at police and smashing the windows of stores and
offices outside, authorities said Sunday.
   A police officer was cut on the head by a bottle and several
concertgoers were injured in the Saturday night melee at the
Classic Theater in North Hollywood, officials said. Firefighters
briefly turned hoses on the crowd to restore order.
   Three people were arrested, one for vandalism, one for an
alcohol-related offense and another on a felony warrant.
   Assistant Fire Chief Jim Mullen said nearly 1,900 people had
jammed into the theater, several hundred more than its capacity,
and fire officials ordered it closed at about 8:30 p.m.
   ``I've been doing this for 10 years and as soon as I saw the
police and their truncheons, I knew the show was over,'' said Peter
Firestone, drummer for the show's headline act, Bad Religion.
   Most fans left quietly when ordered to, but a brawl erupted and
about 200 seats were damaged in an ensuing rampage, Mullen said.
Some fans started a fire in a trash can on the second floor, but it
was quickly put out, he said.
   Outside, fans smashed windows in shops, offices and a bank
building. Property damage was estimated by police at about $20,000.
   Concert producer Bryan Meckelborg said 1,325 tickets had been
sold to the event.
   Meanwhile, in Chicago, police and concertgoers clashed after a
Saturday night performance by the rap group Public Enemy. Five
people, including four officers, were injured and 18 arrests were
made.
   The melee began early Sunday after the concert at the Aragon
Ballroom on the city's north side ended.
   Several anti-war demonstrators began speaking into a bullhorn
across the street from the concert hall, protesting the United
States' military buildup in the Persian Gulf in response to Iraq's
Aug. 2 invasion of Kuwait.
   ``They began chanting anti-war slogans so, of course, the people
started to listen,'' said police Lt. Paul Lewis.
   ``The more people came out, the more traffic built up, until
finally it was stopped in all directions and the officers asked
(the protesters) to stop using the bullhorn until it was cleared,''
he said. ``At that point, the crowd began throwing things and soe
of them jumped into the fray.''
   Lewis said he didn't know how large the crowd was. The 15 men
and three women arrested were charged with mob action and released.
Court dates were set for Jan. 29.
   Public Enemy recordings have been banned in some cities because
of charges of anti-Semitism and violence in the lyrics.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901230-0044 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-30-90 1910EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-US-Gulf 2ndLd-Writethru a0667 12-30 0776</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-US-Gulf, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0667,850</SECOND>
<HEAD>Congressional Leaders Urge Bush to Redouble Effort to Avoid War.
^EDS: Subs 24th graf prv, ``Vice President xxx with two grafs, now
beginning ``Meanwhile, aides xxx to update with Quayle meeting
results</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOAN MOWER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Congressional leaders said Sunday the White
House should redouble its efforts to find a peaceful solution to
the crisis in the Persian Gulf because the American people don't
want to fight a war in the region.
   ``The American people are not yet committed to war, and they
want to make certain that President Bush has done everything,
pursued every avenue for peace before the firing starts,'' said
Senate Minority Leader Bob Dole, R-Kan., on NBC-TV's ``Meet the
Press.''
   ``The American people do not want war,'' he said.
   Both Dole and Rep. Les Aspin, D-Wis., chairman of the House
Armed Services Committee, said Bush and Iraqi President Saddam
Hussein must break the stalemate over diplomatic talks between the
two countries.
   Dole said he has received indications from Iraq that Saddam may
be willing to show flexibility on dates for the talks.
   ``People want to make sure that we've tried every other
alternative before going to war, that we tried to solve this every
other way,'' Aspin said on CBS-TV's ``Face the Nation.''
   ``A diplomatic effort really needs to be made and has to be made
before the decision to go to war,'' he said.
   With the U.N. security council's Jan. 15 deadline for Iraqi
withdrawal from Kuwait drawing closer, Rep. Lee Hamilton, D-Ind.,
predicted a ``real intensification of diplomatic effort in the next
few days.''
   Hamilton, chairman of the House Foreign Affairs subcommittee on
Europe and the Middle East, also appeared on the CBS program.
   Hamilton and Dole expressed optimism about a peaceful solution
to the crisis.
   ``My gut tells me that there will be a resolution (of the
crisis) without firing a shot,'' Dole said.
   Added Hamilton: ``There are some straws there that indicate a
diplomatic solution may work.'' He cited fresh appeals by Germany's
foreign minister, Hans-Dietrich Genscher for a new diplomatic
effort to try to avoid war.
   ``People are very, very nervous about the outbreak of war,''
Hamilton said.
   The lawmakers' comments complemented Bush's remark in a Time
magazine interview, to be published Monday, in which he said he has
a ``gut feeling'' that Saddam will withdraw from Kuwait.
   Top Democratic and GOP congressional leaders will meet with Bush
on Thursday, the day that the new Congress convenes.
   Aspin said congressional leaders are going to demand to know if
Bush intends to ask Congress for war-making authority before he
uses force in the gulf.
   ``I think that's a very, very important thing that they (the
administration) commit to do that, that we do have a vote on that
in Congress,'' he said.
   House Majority Leader Richard Gephardt, D-Mo., on Saturday
suggested Democrats might try to cut off money for Operation Desert
Shield if Bush goes to war without seeking congressional authority.
   Gephardt said U.N. sanctions against Iraq should be given at
least 18 months to work.
   But in a prelude to partisan wrangling over the issue, Dole
called Gephardt's proposal ``incredible'' and declared: ``I'd like
him to tell that to the troops in the sands of Saudi Arabia.''
   The Senate's ranking GOP member predicted neither the
Democrat-controlled House or Senate would approve such a
resolution. ``That was a big, big political mistake,'' said Dole of
Gephardt's remark.
   Dole also said the anti-Iraq coalition would likely fall apart
if the United States waited 12 months to 18 months for sanctions to
work. Aspin repeated his skepticism about sanctions. ``I'm not very
bullish on sanctions,'' he said.
   But Dole agreed with Gephardt that America's allies, Japan and
Germany, should pay a larger share of the cost of maintaining more
than 300,000 U.S. troops in Saudi Arabia.
   Meanwhile, aides to Vice President Dan Quayle said he told Saudi
King Fahd in a Sunday evening meeting in Riyadh that the United
States expects more financial support from the oil-rich nation for
U.S. military efforts against Iraq and that the Arab ruler seemed
to agree.
   ``They have been forthcoming on that subject,'' said one senior
administration official. ``The impression that was left was that
they would continue to be forthcoming. They don't want any
perception of any reluctance on that issue.''
   Unless members of Congress vote to stay in session specifically
to tackle the gulf issue, the lawmakers are expected to deal mostly
with formalities when they meet this week before going home until
after Jan. 20.
   Dole said lawmakers should leave Washington unless they agree to
pass a resolution backing the U.N. measure, which advocates force
if necessary. Hamilton cautioned against Congress engaging in a
long debate on the gulf if there is no widespread support one way
or the other. ``It will send a signal of divisiveness. That's not
what we want to do now,'' he said.
   On the deadlock over diplomatic discussions. Dole said Mohamed
Al-Mashat, Iraq ambassador to the United States who is in Baghdad
for consultations, told him in a Saturday night telephone call that
Saddam may be willing to bend on the date.
   ``I had some indication there was some flexibility (by Iraq on
the date),'' said Dole, adding ``there's got to be flexibility'' on
Bush's part as well.
   Iraq has invited Secretary of State James Baker III to meet
Saddam Hussein on Jan. 12, a date the White House has rejected
because it is too close to the U.N. deadline.
   Bush's invitation to Iraqi Foreign Minister Tariq Aziz to come
to Washington last December fell through because of the deadlock
over the Baker visit.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901230-0045 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-30-90 1929EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Israel-Albania-Jews -URGENT-   12-30 0331</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel-Albania-Jews,0370</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<HEAD>Albanian Jews Begin Immigrating To Israel</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Albania</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Albanian Jews are being allowed to emigrate to
Israel and several have already arrived, Israel army radio reported
Sunday.
   Thirty-seven members of one family bound for Israel boarded a
flight Sunday dubbed the ``Flying Carpet'' in Tirana, Albania's
capital, and flew to Rome, said Shula Bahat, a spokeswoman for the
American Jewish Committee in New York.
   ``This is going to save Albanian Jews from total extinction. Had
they remained there, they would have been wiped out in a
generation,'' said Rabbi Marc Tanenbaum, foreign relations
consultant to the committee.
   One Tel Aviv man with relatives in Albania told the radio that
the entire Jewish community of that country was packed and ready to
leave for Israel.
   The Jews are not coming through official Israeli channels, but
are sponsored by Jewish organizations and unofficial agencies, the
radio said, quoting officials it did not identify.
   Yehdua Weinrab, spokesman for the quasi-governmental Jewish
Agency, which is responsible for transporting immigrants to Israel,
refused to comment on the exodus. Immigration Minister Yitzhak
Peretz also refused to comment.
   The Tel Aviv man said some of his 60 relatives in Albania had
immigrated in the past two months.
   The radio quoted unidentified officials who said Israeli Foreign
Ministry delegates in Rome had arranged for the Italian embassy in
Tirana to issue the travel permits.
   But Vladamir Prela, head of the Albanian Foreign Ministry's
press department, denied there was a special program for the
emigration of Jews from Albania.
   ``You may recall that Ramiz Alia (Communist party chief) has
said those Albanian citizens who want to work abroad can leave.
That also, obviously, applies to Jewish citizens,'' he said in a
telephone interview.
   The exact number of Jews living in Albania was not available but
estimated to be about 1,000 of the country's 3.2 million citizens.
   Albania's hard-line Communist government, which took power in
1944, until recently did not permit religious worship. Most of the
Jews there are believed to no longer practice Judaism.
   The Albanian government is now carrying out political reform as
well, including the legalization of some opposition.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901230-0046 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-30-90 1937EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Japan-Earthquake     12-30 0158</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Japan-Earthquake,0162</SECOND>
<HEAD>Earthquake Rocks Tokyo</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A strong earthquake rocked Tokyo and its
neighboring area Monday morning, the Central Meteorological Agency
said.
   There were no immediate reports of damage or casualties from the
8:05 a.m. tremor, police said.
   The earthquake had a preliminary reading of 5.1 on the Richter
scale, said the Meteorological Agency. It was centered in the
eastern part of Chiba Prefecture, a state on the eastern border of
Tokyo.
   The earthquake also registered 3 on the Japanese scale of 7 in
Katsuura and Tateyama, two coastal cities in the state. It was
strong enough to overturn unfastened objects.
   The Richter scale is a gauge of the strength of an earthquake as
measured by the ground motion recorded on a seismograph. A quake
measuring 5 on the scale can cause considerable damage.
   The Japanese scale measures the intensity of an earthquake at a
particular location. It is not convertible to the Richter scale.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901230-0047 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-30-90 1956EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-FlyingCarpet     12-30 0342</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Flying Carpet,0393</SECOND>
<HEAD>Project `Flying Carpet': Albania Allows Jews To Leave</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Albania</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By VERENA DOBNIK</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Thirty-seven members of an Albanian Jewish
family on Sunday became the first Jews to be allowed to leave
Albania under a deal secretly negotiated with the Communist
government, an American Jewish group said.
   On a flight dubbed the ``Flying Carpet,'' the family left the
Albanian capital of Tirana on Sunday, headed for Israel via Rome,
said Shula Bahat, a spokeswoman for the American Jewish Committee.
   ``This is going to save Albanian Jews from total extinction,''
said the group's foreign relations consultant, Rabbi Marc
Tanenbaum. ``Had they remained there, they would have been wiped
out in a generation.''
   In Rome, the family was aided by the Italian government and
representatives of the Jerusalem-based Jewish Agency, Bahat said.
Further details about the family were not immediately known.
   The Jewish Agency, which is financing the resettlement of
Albanian Jews, negotiated in secret with the Albanian, Israeli and
Italian governments to facilitate the immigration, she said.
   The family's departure forged the way to the West for Albania's
500 Jews, most of whom are expected to leave the repressive country
after decades of being cut off from the world Jewish community, she
said.
   Sunday's flight, as well as future flights to the West for
Albania's Jews, has been nicknamed the ``Flying Carpet,'' Bahat
said.
   She said Jews have not been allowed to practice their religion
by Albania's government, one of the last in Eastern Europe to
maintain a political hard line as surrounding countries turned to
democracy.
   ``Jews were cut off and alienated in Albania, which was the
leading Stalinist government in Eastern Europe,'' Tanenbaum said.
``Under that regime, religious and cultural freedom was totally
denied.
   ``The only way the Albanian Jews could keep their tradition
alive was by doing it underground and behind closed curtains,'' he
said. ``This means they can finally breathe fresh air.''
   The negotiations had not previously been made public because the
issue was a delicate one, Bahat said. She did not know when the
negotiations began.
   Other Albanian Jews who want to immigrate are expected to leave
the country within the next three months, she said.
   In the past, some Jews have fled Albania via Greece.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901230-0048 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-30-90 2008EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Pacific-Quake 1stLd-Writethru a0663 12-30 0231</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Pacific-Quake, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0663,0246</SECOND>
<HEAD>Precede RESTON, Va.</HEAD>
<HEAD>Earthquake Shakes South Pacific</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: LEADS thruout to UPDATE with no injuries, minor damage;
PRECEDES; no pickup</NOTE>
<DATELINE>RABAUL, Papua New Guinea (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A strong earthquake hit Papua
New Guinea's New Britain Island in the South Pacific early Monday,
causing minor damage but no reported injuries.
   The earthquake was recorded at a preliminary magnitude of 6.8 on
the Richter scale, according to U.S. Geological Survey scientists
in Golden, Colo.
   New Britain is a narrow, crescent-shaped island with Rabaul on
its northeast tip. The 375-mile-long island, home to about 200,000
people, has a rugged range of mountains with several active
volcanoes.
   Ima Itikarai, who works at the government's volcanic activity
scientific station in Rabaul, said minor damage was reported in
scattered regions of the island.
   ``We have heard some reports of ground cracks, damage to water
tanks and some roofs, and foundations displaced,'' said Itikarai.
``We have not had any reports of injuries.''
   The epicenter of the tremor, which occurred at 5:14 a.m. Monday,
was recorded about 110 miles southwest of Rabaul.
   Although an earthquake with a 6.8 magnitude on the Richter scale
can cause considerable damage, Don Finley of the U.S. Geological
Survey said quakes of such power occur frequently in the area and
typically go unnoticed except by scientists.
   The Richter scale is a gauge of the energy released by an
earthquake, as measured by the ground motion recorded on a
seismograph.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901230-0049 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-30-90 2018EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-WhiteHouseArrests 1stLd-Writethru a063 12-30 0168</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-White House Arrests, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0630,140</SECOND>
<HEAD>Eleven Arrested in Colorful White House Demonstration</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDs: Inserts 3rd graf, ``Among those xxx to include Berrigan
arrest</NOTE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Eleven people were arrested Sunday after they
scaled the north fence of the White House and threw red ink,
simulating blood, into a fountain, according to authorities.
   They were among a group of 40 demonstrators affiliated with the
D.C. Coalition Against the U.S. in the Middle East, according to
Doug Holmes of the uniformed division of the U.S. Secret Service.
   Among those arrested was former Catholic priest Philip Berrigan,
a veteran anti-war activist.
   President Bush was at the presidential retreat at Camp David in
the nearby Maryland mountains at the time of the arrests.
   Holmes said the eleven people were charged with destruction of
government property and unlawful entry.
   Officials said one Secret Service officer suffered a minor
injury during the incident. The 29 demonstrators who did not enter
the White House grounds were not charged.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901230-0050 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-30-90 2028EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Israel-Immigrants     12-30 0341</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel-Immigrants,0397</SECOND>
<HEAD>Israeli Immigration Official Calls For Tent Camps</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Immigration Minister Yitzhak Peretz presented
his plan Sunday for housing tens of thousands of the coming year's
expected 400,000 Soviet Jewish immigrants in tent camps and army
bases.
   Peretz presented his plan to the ministerial committee on
immigration. He he later fielded criticism of the tent camp
proposal on Israel television, calling it ``an emergency plan for a
time of distress.''
   ``I am always afraid that there could be a situation where
immigrants will get stuck at the airport, and we will have nowhere
to put them,'' Peretz said on Israel television.
   The plan, which still must be approved by the Cabinet, calls for
establishing tent camps to house 10,000 immigrants.
   Peretz defended his plan as one based on the successful
absorption of about 200,000 immigrants in 1990.
   ``This is not just a theory or recommendation, but an orderly
and organized plan that promises the proper absorption of 400,000
immigrants,'' Peretz said on Israel television.
   At the meeting, Israel's chief of staff, Dan Shomron, offered to
house 70,000 newcomers in army camps and to clear four training
fields for immigrant trailers.
   ``Such a mission as immigration, I would say, is the most
important mission today, other than security,'' Shomron said on
Israel army radio.
   ``We are talking about a solution for tens of thousands of
immigrants; it is not simple at all for the army. It complicates
things greatly, but it is an important mission, and we will do our
part,'' Shomron added.
   Simha Dinitz, head of the quasi-governmental Jewish Agency
responsible for transporting immigrants to Israel, has rejected
tents as an outdated response to the housing shortage. He has cited
mobile homes and trailers as preferable options.
   The government predicts one million Soviets will arrive by the
end of 1992. Dinitz has said the figure could exceed two million
before the wave of immigration ends.
   Housing is not the only problem the newcomers face. Israel
television reported that the immigration minister's plan is based
on the belief that by the end of 1991, 140,000 immigrants will be
looking for work.
   Another 15,000 will be unemployed and 55,000 will be working at
temporary jobs, the television said.
   Israel already has an unemployment rate that fluctuates between
8.8 and 10 percent.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901230-0051 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-30-90 2130EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Gulf-Iraq 3rdLd-Writethru a0685 12-30 0839</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Iraq, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0685,1056</SECOND>
<HEAD>Iraq: Bush `Must Have Been Drunk' To Think Saddam Would Back Down</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Leads with 5 grafs to UPDATE with Saddam comments on Iraqi TV;
picks up 3rd graf pvs, `Vice President ...; Stands for AM-Gulf Rdp</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto DHR1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ED BLANCHE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NICOSIA, Cyprus (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Iraq's information minister said Sunday
that President Bush ``must have been drunk'' when he suggested Iraq
might withdraw from Kuwait, and boasted: ``We will show the world
America is a paper tiger.''
   The minister, Latif Jassim, also insisted on Iraq's proposed
date of Jan. 12 for a visit by Secretary of State James A. Baker
III. Washington has said that date is too close to the Jan. 15 U.N.
deadline for Iraq to leave Kuwait or face possible force.
   Iraqi President Saddam Hussein delivered a 15-minute New Year's
message Sunday on Iraqi TV in which he invoked both Moslem and
Christian theology in condemning the United States and Saudi
Arabia. CNN carried the broadcast and provided English subtitles.
   ``In this confrontation, there have been those who betrayed
Jesus Christ and who betrayed the principles and values of Islam,
one luring and leading the other,'' said Saddam. `May God curse
them all.''
   ``...As did Judas betray Jesus, so has Bush betrayed through his
aggresion and deep-rooted evil, the teachings of Jesus Christ,''
he said.
   Vice President Dan Quayle told Saudi King Fahd on Sunday that
the United States expects more money from the oil-rich nation for
military efforts against Iraq, and the Arab ruler seemed to agree,
U.S. officials said in Riyadh, Saudi Arabia.
   No figures were mentioned, but U.S. officials left the two-hour
meeting with the impression there will be no problem, they said.
Saudi Arabia has cleared a windfall of billions from rising oil
prices since Iraq's Aug. 2 invasion of Kuwait.
   Quayle also found ``no reticence'' on Fahd's part to the idea of
launching a war against Iraq if Saddam does not withdraw from
Kuwait, one senior U.S. official said.
   An official Baghdad newspaper said Sunday that Iraqis and other
Arabs will attack U.S. and Western targets worldwide if America and
its allies move militarily against Iraq.
   With the Jan. 15 deadline drawing near, foreign ministers of the
12-nation European Community were to meet Friday in Luxembourg to
discuss the Persian Gulf crisis.
   The decision to hold an emergency meeting was announced Sunday
by the French Foreign Ministry. The gathering had been proposed a
day earlier by Germany's foreign minister, Hans-Dietrich Genscher,
who appealed again Sunday for a fresh diplomatic effort to try to
avoid war in the gulf.
   But Saddam insisted anew that any solution to the crisis must be
linked to a resolution of the Israeli-Palestinian conflict. The
United States, Israel and others have rejected any such linkage.
   The Iraqi News Agency said Saddam's renewed call for linkage
came in talks Sunday with Yugoslavia's foreign minister. The
Yugoslav official reportedly was seeking a new peace initiative on
behalf of the non-aligned movement, of which Yugoslavia is the
current chairman.
   The U.S. official with Quayle, who discussed his meeting with
Fahd on condition of not being identified by name, said the two
were ``in virtually complete agreement on what needed to be done''
to force Iraq out of Kuwait.
   Quayle's staff said there were no plans for him to launch any
new diplomatic initiative during his three-day trip to Saudi
Arabia. He was to visit U.S. troops and consult with the exiled
emir of Kuwait.
   Jassim, at a Baghdad news conference, derided Bush's comment to
Time magazine that he had a ``gut feeling'' Iraq might still
withdraw from Kuwait. Iraq will never do so, Jassim said.
   Bush, he said, ``must have been drunk, and drunk people usually
lose their senses.''
   Jassim also repeated Iraq's insistence on the Jan. 12 date for
talks between Baker and Saddam.
   ``Our president has set the date and that is the only
possibility. There is no change,'' said Jassim.
   He said Iraq would not initiate hostilities in the gulf, telling
reporters: ``We will never attack.''
   ``But if Bush starts a war, he will not be able to stop it ...
We will show the world that America is a paper tiger. You will see
how the Americans will kneel down,'' he said.
   A Western diplomat, meanwhile, said U.S. charge d'affaires
Joseph Wilson has stopped his almost daily efforts to talk to the
Iraqis about the date for any direct talks.
   ``There are no forward movements, at least not in Baghdad,''
said the diplomat, speaking on condition of anonymity.
   The European decision to meet and discuss the crisis was
welcomed by the Iraqi ambassador to the United States. But the
envoy said Europe should adopt an independent approach to the gulf.
   ``It is high time for the Europeans to enunciate their own
policy and not to be subservient to the American policy,'' Mohammad
Sadek Mashat told reporters at Amman airport, where he stopped en
route back to Washington after consultations in Baghdad.
   The Iraqi threat of terrorist attacks against U.S. and other
installations came in the al-Thawra daily, which is the mouthpiece
of Iraq's ruling Baath Socialist Party.
   ``Hundreds of thousands of volunteers are now at the highest
state of readiness to fight against the alliance of evil and
aggression,'' said the newspaper.
   The Iraqi News Agency, monitored in Nicosia, quoted the
newspaper as saying that if war breaks out in the gulf, ``the
confrontation will not be confined to the battlefield.''
   Iraq's religious affairs minister, Abdullah Fadil, warned Sunday
that Moslems would retaliate against the United States and its
allies if Islamic holy shrines were hit in any multinational
offensive aimed at driving the Iraqis out of Kuwait.
   ``Every Moslem will be a missile to be thrown against the enemy
once he launches his armed agression against Iraq,'' he told a news
conference in Baghdad.
   U.S. forces in Saudi Arabia have been on heightened alert since
before Christmas.
   A U.S. official said Sunday that the hotel housing the U.S.
command's press center in Riyadh, the Saudi capital, was evacuated
after a telephoned bomb threat. U.S. official said Saudi police
searched the building but found nothing.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901230-0052 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-30-90 2142EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BRF--Birth-Shooting     12-30 0140</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Birth-Shooting,0145</SECOND>
<HEAD>Woman Gives Birth to Healthy Girl After Being Shot</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A pregnant woman was shot in the head and
critically injured during a drive-by shooting Sunday, but doctors
were able to deliver her child, police said.
   Marilyn Colon, 20, and Carlos Ventura, 26, were standing on a
street near the Bronx Zoo early Sunday when a car pulled up and an
occupant opened fire, said police Sgt. Grace Ridley.
   Ventura, who was hit five times, was killed, she said.
   Colon, who was eight months pregnant, was shot in the head.
Doctors at Bronx Municipal Hospital Center operated immediately and
delivered a 5-pound, 11-ounce girl, said Vicki Ciampa, a hospital
spokeswoman.
   ``The baby is doing good,'' Ciampa said.
   Police said they knew of no motive for the shooting and said no
arrests had been made.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901230-0053 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-30-90 2148EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AMGulf-Israel-Jordan     12-30 0241</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Israel-Jordan,0267</SECOND>
<HEAD>Levy Warns United States Of Hostile Forces In Jordan</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Foreign Minister David Levy told a U.S.
lawmaker Sunday that pro-Iraqi forces in Jordan are using it as a
base for anti-American and anti-Israeli activity.
   Jordan is becoming a threat because of ``hostile fundamentalist
factors which are gaining in strength constantly,'' Levy was quoted
as saying by a spokesman for the Foreign Ministry.
   The spokesman, who could not be identified under briefing
regulations, quoted Levy as telling visiting Rep. James Scheuer,
D-New York, that King Hussein of Jordan is concentrating security
forces on Israel's border.
   Jordanian military sources said Thursday they had increased
their forces along the border as a precaution against an attack by
the Jewish state.
   Israeli officials earlier sought to assure Hussein that they had
no plans to attack. They said Jordanian officials were really
worried about pro-Iraqi forces crossing the border into Israel and
creating a pretext for an Israeli strike.
   Israel's chief of staff, Lt. Gen. Dan Shomron, said last week
that Iraq could use Jordan as a springboard for action against
Israel.
   In Sunday's meeting, Levy told Scheuer that Iraqi President
Saddam Hussein had a ``stockpile of missiles which could indeed
reach Israel within a few minutes, and out of consideration for the
U.S. and its soldiers, we take a risk and adopt a low profile.''
   ``It should be noted that Israel will not always maintain only a
low profile,'' Levy said.
   Iraq has threatened to attack Israel with chemical warheads if
war breaks out in the gulf.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901230-0054 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-30-90 2150EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Israel-Lebanon     12-30 0106</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel-Lebanon,0093</SECOND>
<HEAD>Israeli Air Raid on Southern Lebanon Hits Target Near Sidon</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Israeli warplanes bombed guerrilla targets in
south Lebanon on Sunday to wipe out a base used for attacks against
Israel, army officials said.
   The army command said the Israeli warplanes ``attacked and hit a
guerrilla target southeast of Sidon'' and Israeli planes returned
safely.
   The command did not say which guerrilla organization had been
attacked.
   There was no report on casualties or any other details.
   Israel has launched 19 such air raids this year.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901230-0055 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-30-90 2246EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Japan-Soviet     12-30 0295</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Japan-Soviet,0330</SECOND>
<HEAD>Gorbachev to Promote Pan-Asian Summit on Easing Military Tensions</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Soviet President Mikhail Gorbachev said in an
interview published Sunday he seeks a Pan-Asian summit, including
the United States, to discuss ways to ease military confrontations
in the region.
   Gorbachev also told the Asahi Shimbun newspaper that he hoped
Foreign Minister Eduard Shevardnadze would continue to work with
him, despite his Dec. 20 announcement he was resigning.
   ``I consider him one of my closest comrades, and there were no
differences in opinions or views,'' Gorbachev said.
   The Supreme Soviet is to consider Shevardnadze's resignation on
Jan. 8. Meanwhile, Gorbachev said, ``I told him to continue his
work.''
   The aim of an Asian summit would be to demilitarize the region
and create a ``stabilized, neighborly and cooperative zone,''
Gorbachev said in the interview in Moscow on Friday with the
nationally circulated Japanese newspaper.
   ``Such a meeting could not be considered without the
participation of the United States, Canada, Australia and New
Zealand,'' Gorbachev said.
   On unification of the divided Korean peninsula, Gorbachev said
that only North and South Koreans have the right to decide steps
that can lead to that.
   But ``the Soviet Union is ready to participate in any
international framework of cooperation and guarantee if
necessary,'' he said.
   Gorbachev urged the Japanese government to end its policy of
linking all issues between the two countries to its demand for
return of the Soviet-held islands just off Japan's northern coast.
   He said the time has come for both nations to advance toward
conclusion of a peace treaty to World War II.
   Gorbachev is to become the first Soviet leader to visit Japan in
April.
   Asahi said that when asked about the Pan-Asian summit proposed
by Shevardnadze in September, Gorbachev said the date and site
would be discussed at Asian foreign ministerial talks scheduled in
1993 at Vladivostok, home port of the Soviet navy's Pacific fleet.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901230-0056 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-30-90 2250EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Obit-Drackert 1stLd-Writethru a0705 12-30 0238</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Drackert, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0705,0262</SECOND>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS last graf to CLARIFY wife is survivor.</NOTE>
<HEAD>`Dude Ranch' Operator Hosted Celebrity Divorce-Seekers</HEAD>
<DATELINE>RENO, Nev. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Harry Drackert, whose ``dude ranches'' were
briefly home to playwright Arthur Miller, Mary Rockefeller and
other luminaries establishing Nevada residency in order to get
divorces, has died at age 87.
   He died Wednesday at a Reno hospital of heart failure.
   Drackert was among the last survivors of the dozen or so
guest-ranch operators who hosted out-of-state residents drawn to
Nevada by the state's liberal divorce laws.
   The laws, for many years the most liberal in the nation, allowed
a person to get a Nevada divorce after just a six-week residency in
the state.
   From the 1940s to the 1960s, Drackert and his wife, Joan,
operated three guest ranches, including the Donner Trail guest
ranch in Verdi and the Silver Circle Ranch in Reno.
   In February 1962, the Donner Trail ranch gained national
attention when Mary Rockefeller, wife of then New York Gov. Nelson
Rockefeller, moved in for six weeks. Upon her arrival, she
announced she was seeking a divorce from the prominent Republican
presidential candidate.
   Other guests included Miller, author Saul Bellow and Evelyn
Funt, the ex-wife of Candid Camera creator Allen Funt.
   Drackert, a native of Bozeman, Mont., won many saddle bronco
competitions as a rodeo rider in the 1920s and 1930s, and won a
steer decorating championship in 1931 at the Calgary Stampede.
   He also bred and trained horses.
   He is survived by his wife, Joan, a noted trapshooter.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901230-0057 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-30-90 2254EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-StormsRdp 3rdLd-Writethru a0704 12-30 0691</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Storms Rdp, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0704,0853</SECOND>
<HEAD>Flooding in Midwest, New Storm in Northwest</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 4 grafs to move up graf on death toll, which has
risen to 99. Picks up 3rd graf pvs, `Temperatures dipped ...'
DELETES now redundant 11th graf, `Since the ...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By ROGER PETTERSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Flooding forced evacuations and closed roads Sunday in Indiana
and Ohio, and a new storm headed into wind-ravaged Washington state
with a threat of snow and high wind.
   Highways were icy across parts of the Plains and towing services
were kept busy with cars that wouldn't start or stay on the road.
   ``We're getting three to four times the normal number of
calls,'' said Mark Moody at Oklahoma City's AAA.
   Since the start of the season's first strong cold wave on Dec.
18, at least 99 deaths, including 20 in Texas, have been attributed
to the weather.
   Temperatures dipped to numbing lows again Sunday, including a
record 23 below zero at Scottsbluff, Neb., 30 below at Rapid City,
S.D., a record for the whole month of December, and an unofficial
40 below at Porcupine, S.D. Even Honolulu joined in with an
untropical record low of 57.
   Some church services were canceled around Mitchell, S.D., which
hit 24 below, said J.P. Skelly of station KORN in Mitchell.
   Temperatures have dropped below freezing nightly for close to
two weeks in many areas of California. Sacramento has had a record
11 consecutive nights with freezing temperatures.
   ``It's all people are talking about. It's affecting everyone.
People are losing their jobs over it,'' said Lori Segrue, who works
at a vineyard in Kingsburg, south of Fresno.
   California Gov. George Deukmejian declared a state of emergency
in the Santa Cruz Mountains where public water systems were shut
down by the cold.
   Officials said water service had been restored to all but about
10 percent of the San Fernando Valley's 5,000 customers by Sunday
morning. Broken pipes, which caused most of the trouble by draining
storage tanks, will have to be repaired before service is fully
restored.
   Some agriculture experts estimate that the cost of the state's
crop damage caused by freezing weather could total $1 billion.
   Two North Dakota farmers, Clarence Campbell, 79, and his brother
William, 77, were found dead near their farmhouse at Eckelson
Saturday after apparently attempting to walk across a field to a
relative's house and being overcome by the bitter cold, authorities
said. Temperatures dropped to a record 37 below in the area at the
weekend.
   Two days of heavy rain combined with melting snow to push
streams out of their banks in many areas around Indiana. Scattered
evacuations were reported in several communities, including
Indianapolis. Countless roads were closed by high water, officials
said.
   Indiana Emergency Management Director Jerry Hauer said he was
concerned that rivers were still rising and had not crested yet.
Additional rain, sleet and snow fell Sunday.
   ``I'd say we've got a pretty serious situation on our hands,''
Hauer said.
   The flooding will grow worse later in the week, said Al Shipe, a
National Weather Service hydrologist in Indianapolis.
   The Mississinewa River was forecast to crest 5 feet above flood
stage for its worst flooding at Marion since 1958, and Indianapolis
was due to receive the highest levels along the White River since
1964, Shipe said.
   ``It's very grim right now,'' said sheriff's Deputy Ken Lopez in
Delaware County, Ind.
   Dozens of residents were evacuated in two northern Ohio towns
because of high water. Delphos police and fire departments ordered
at least 80 people to leave two trailer courts. Near Cleveland, 30
to 50 people were evacuated along the Chagrin River, said
Willoughby Hills Fire Department Lt. Sandra Thorne.
   In the Northwest, battered by high wind Friday that damaged
coastal property and knocked down trees and power lines, the
weather service issued another winter storm warning for the Puget
Sound area and upgraded a storm watch to a storm warning for
north-central and northeastern Washington.
   Repair crews worked over the weekend to shore up sea walls that
were undercut by Friday's storm.
   The storm also knocked out power to about 150,000 utility
customers from Puget Sound to the British Columbia border. By
Sunday morning, Puget Power Sound and Light Co. still had about
16,800 customers without electricity, said spokeswoman Jude Noland.
   Parts of Arkansas got combinations of heavy sleet, light snow
and some thunderstorms Sunday morning. Benton County had the
heaviest accumulation with 4 to 6 inches of snow and ice and roads
there and elsewhere were slippery.
   Ice buildup knocked tree limbs into power lines and caused
hundreds of new power outages, said Jerol Garrison, a spokesman for
Arkansas Power and Light. He did not yet have exact numbers. That
utility's crews already were working overtime Sunday to repair
damage from an ice storm Thursday.
   An Arctic cold front swept into Texas on Sunday, plunging
temperatures below zero, glazing highways and forming thick fog
that slowed holiday traffic. Amarillo had a record 1 below.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
</Collection>
