<Collection>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0001 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 0002EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-PlanesCollide     12-22 0187</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Planes Collide,0201</SECOND>
<HEAD>Coast Guard Jet Knocks Cessna's Baggage Compartment Off at 4,000
Feet</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Coast Guard jet collided with a small plane 4,000
feet above the Bahamas on Saturday, knocking the twin-engine
Cessna's baggage compartment into the surf, but causing no
injuries, authorities said.
   The Falcon jet was flying at about 4,000 feet on a routine law
enforcement patrol over Bimini island on Saturday morning when its
tail struck the Cessna's baggage compartment, said Lt. Jeff
Karonis, a Coast Guard spokesman in Miami.
   The Cessna carried a pilot and five San Francisco science
teachers.
   ``Considering the impact and everything, everybody involved was
very lucky, said aircraft mechanic Bill Peck, who examined the
Cessna after it safely landed in Miami.
   ``If there had been about five or 10 inches difference in the
way the jet had hit the bottom of the plane, the people on the
plane definitely would have been killed.''
   The belly of the Cessna was scraped where its baggage
compartment was ripped off and about six inches of the jet's upper
tail section broke off, officials said.
   The Federal Aviation Administration was investigating the
incident, Karonis said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0002 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 0049EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i BC-Gulf-Cheney     12-23 0254</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Gulf-Cheney,270</SECOND>
<HEAD>Cheney: `Clock Is Ticking' Toward War With Iraq</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DAMMAM, Saudi Arabia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Defense Secretary Dick Cheney warned
Sunday that ``the clock is ticking'' quickly toward war with Iraq.
   Cheney also appeared to indirectly confirm that U.S. forces,
known to have nuclear weapons aboard naval vessels, also have some
chemical weapons capacity in the Persian Gulf region.
   The secretary is wrapping up a five-day visit to Saudi Arabia
that included classified strategy sessions with commanders and two
days of pre-Christmas troop visits.
   As he had all week, Cheney ducked questions about whether the
United States has decided on a timetable to attack Iraq if Iraqi
President Saddam Hussein ignores a United Nations-imposed Jan. 15
deadline to withdraw from Kuwait. Iraq overran the neighboring
emirate on Aug. 2 and later annexed it.
   ``The clock is ticking as each day goes by and he (Saddam) does
not withdraw his forces from Kuwait,'' Cheney said.
   He told reporters that the American troop deployment in the
region was nearing the 300,000 mark.
   Cheney refused to answer when asked directly if the United
States has chemical weapons in the region. But he referred a
reporter back to his answer to an earlier question, when he said
President Bush had available a ``full spectrum'' of weapons should
he decide to order an attack.
   On another matter, Cheney said he did not believe it was
necessary for American dependents to leave the Saudi Arabian
province bordering Kuwait.
   Britain has recommended that its citizens leave Saudi Arabia's
Eastern Province by the U.N. deadline.
   But Cheney said, ``I don't believe it's unsafe for people who
are here in the Eastern Province of Saudi Arabia.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0003 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 0140EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Right-To-Die 2ndLd-Writethru   12-23 0659</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Right-To-Die, 2nd Ld - Writethru,a0637,0811</SECOND>
<HEAD>Eds.: RETRANSMITTING TO CORRECT designation to 2nd Ld - Writethru,
RESTORE DELETED information on appeal. Pick up 10th graf pvs.,
``The Evangelical ... ``</HEAD>
<HEAD>Churches: Stop Attempts To Intervene In Nancy Cruzan Case</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JERRY NACHTIGAL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOUNT VERNON, Mo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Religious leaders urged prayers for
Nancy Cruzan and her family Saturday and called on anti-euthanasia
groups to stop trying to force the state to resume feeding the
woman, who is in a vegetative state.
   Her father, Joe Cruzan, said Saturday that those protesting on
his daughter's behalf don't understand that if she could express
herself she would say she does not want to live.
   Mark Roebuck, a spokesman for the Missouri Department of Health,
said late Saturday that Ms. Cruzan's condition continues to
deteriorate and will soon be downgraded to critical. She has been
in a persistent vegetative state since she was injured in a car
accident almost eight years ago.
   Doctors predicted Ms. Cruzan, 33, would die within two weeks
after her feeding tube was removed Dec. 14.
   Her father told The Joplin Globe that terminal cancer patients
in the Missouri Rehabilitation Center, where Ms. Cruzan is a
patient, have rejected food and not been force-fed.
   ``We believe that Nancy would reject this treatment if she were
able to make a decision,'' he said. ``She can't, so therefore we
have to make it for her.''
   Anti-euthanasia activists were stymied last week in asking
various courts to force the state to resume feeding Ms. Cruzan.
   Those legal setbacks, snow and bitterly cold weather have
lowered morale among some 15 demonstrators camped outside the
Missouri Rehabilitation Center where Ms. Cruzan is cared for. But
spokesman Andrew Burnett said, ``They're planning on keeping the
vigil up to the end of this ordeal.
   Spokesman Andrew Burnett, director of the anti-abortion and
anti-euthanasia group Advocates for Life, said the protesters were
``planning on keeping the vigil up to the end of this ordeal.''
   In the meantime, the Rev. Patrick J. Mahoney, a Protestant
minister who runs the Center for Christian Activism in Boca Raton,
Fla., an advocacy group, appealed Saturday to the 8th U.S. Circuit
Court of Appeals in St. Louis to get Ms. Cruzan's tube reconnected.
   In his appeal, Mahoney asked the court to order the feeding tube
reconnected until it can determine whether Ms. Cruzan's civil
rights were violated. ``In essence, Ms. Cruzan has been given a
`death sentence' without process of the law,'' the appeal document
said.
   The Evangelical Lutheran Church in America, the United Methodist
Church, the Presbyterian Church (USA) and the Unitarian
Universalist Association of Congregations joined in issuing a
statement supporting Joe and Joyce Cruzan and their other two
daughters, Donna and Christy. The Cruzans are Methodists.
   ``We urge that those who are attempting to disrupt the ruling of
the court and the wishes of Nancy Cruzan and her family end their
activities and join us in respecting the judgments of the courts,
which have thoroughly examined the questions involved in the Cruzan
case and have concurred in the Cruzan family's decision,'' the
statement said.
   The statement also asked Americans to ``lend their prayerful
support to the family of Nancy Beth Cruzan as they face the most
difficult days of their life.''
   Demonstrations at the rehabilitation center and the 19 arrests
there Tuesday only further burdened the Cruzans, said Kay Dowhower,
director of the Evangelical Lutheran Church offices in Washington.
   ``We would hope our statement would be a sign of support and
appreciation for how lonely death and the death process can be,''
Mrs. Dowhower said. ``God and nature should take its own course.
What we have done in this case is prolong the suffering by
sustaining life.''
   The Roman Catholic Church also expressed support for the
Cruzans. In a letter to be published Sunday in The News-Leader in
Springfield, Bishop John J. Leibrecht of the Springfield-Cape
Girardeau Diocese said removing Ms. Cruzan's feeding tube was
``morally permissible.''
   Fourteen demonstrators remained jailed Saturday, still invoking
the name Nancy Cruzan and refusing to eat until she is fed or dies.
   On Friday, Joe Cruzan presented demonstrators huddled outside
the hospital in 15-degree weather with a new coffee maker, filters,
cups and an extension cord.
   ``We are doing what we feel God has directed us to do, and that
is to carry out what we believe,'' he told them. ``We believe we
are in the best position to know what would be Nancy's wishes.''
   Cruzan said he appreciated their prayers and hoped the ordeal
would be over soon.
   ``Let's all pray for a miracle that God will put an end to this
and raise her up out of that bed and we can all go home and have a
merry Christmas,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0004 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 0234EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i BC-HongKong-Fire     12-23 0108</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Hong Kong-Fire,0098</SECOND>
<HEAD>Six Killed, 50 Injured In Fire</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HONG KONG (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Fire raced through part of a nine-story
apartment building early Sunday, killing at least six people and
injuring 50, including 12 firemen, officials said.
   Thirty-nine of the injured were hospitalized, and at least five
were seriously hurt, fire officials said.
   Officials said the fire, which burned for three hours, started
in a second floor apartment of the building in the Shum Shui Po
district of Hong Kong.
   The dead included five men but the sixth victim was burned
beyond recognition, officials said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0005 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 0948EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i BC-Gulf-Capsize 1stLd-Writethru a0641 12-23 0266</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Gulf-Capsize, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0641,0309</SECOND>
<HEAD>Death Toll In Capsizing Raised To 21</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: UPDATES throughout with Navy raising death toll to 21,
memorial service; ADDS byline. No pickup.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By MARCUS ELIASON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HAIFA, Israel (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The death toll in the sinking of a charter
ferry carrying American sailors was raised to 21 Sunday and
included one man whose body had not been recovered, a U.S. Navy
official said.
   The body of the 20th victim was recovered by Israeli divers
earlier Sunday, Haifa police said. Neither of the latest two
victims was identified.
   The ferry capsized Saturday shortly after midnight as it was
carrying 102 American seamen to the aircraft carrier USS Saratoga
from a Christmas shore leave.
   Capt. Joseph S. Mobley, the Saratoga's skipper, told reporters
Sunday about the higher death toll after a tearful memorial service
aboard the carrier.
   ``It is 21 lives lost. We still have the man whom we have not
recovered. We have the utmost confidence that he did perish,''
Mobley said.
   About 1,200 crewmen of the Saratoga, including the 81 survivors
of the accident, attended the memorial service in a hangar aboard
the carrier.
   Two sailors dropped a wreathe into the metallic gray water from
a hangar bay door in front of the mourners. A detachment of Marines
fired three rifle salvos into the cloudy, darkening sky.
   Some of the survivors wiped tears from their eyes as a choir
sang ``America'' and the Navy hymn, ``Eternal Father.''
   The Saratoga and its three escort ships were in the Red Sea as
part of the naval buildup in the Persian Gulf region following
Iraq's invasion of Kuwait on Aug. 2.
   The accident was the deadliest involving U.S. servicemen in
Operation Desert Shield, and it raised the number of Americans who
have died to at least 74.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0006 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 1133EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ChristmasWithoutRyan     12-23 0454</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Christmas Without Ryan,0586</SECOND>
<HEAD>Sadness Tinges Christmas for Ryan White's Mother</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BETH HARRIS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CICERO, Ind. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Preserving the Christmas tradition of a cozy
house festooned with decorations, family pictures and love is even
more important to Jeanne White since her son, Ryan, died from AIDS
last spring.
   ``When you face a crisis like we have, the family is the one
that pulls together and stays together. You cannot do it without
family,'' Mrs. White said.
   The holiday decorations almost didn't come out this year. But
Mrs. White ultimately decided to follow the tradition Ryan loved.
   ``Even though I'm sad a lot, especially this holiday season has
really been rough, I feel like he's just everywhere. He's in every
part of everything I do,'' Mrs. White said.
   It helps that her mother is staying with her this month, and her
sister's family will be in for Christmas Day. Plus, the phone
continually rings with friends from around the country, charities
seeking Mrs. White's endorsement and reporters wanting interviews.
   The chaos is a kind of therapy for Mrs. White, who has taken
another one-year leave from her assembly line job at General Motors
Corp.'s Delco plant in Kokomo.
   ``I don't know whether there'll be a time when I'm tired of
talking about AIDS. ... We keep losing so many friends to it, the
people we have met along the way,'' she said. ``It drains you and
you wonder, out of a lot of the people we met, when are they going
to come down with it?''
   Ryan died April 8 at age 18 after a five-year battle with
acquired immune deficiency syndrome. A hemophiliac, he was 13 when
diagnosed with AIDS that he contracted through a tainted blood
product.
   Hatred and abuse were heaped on Ryan and his family by Kokomo
residents, who fought to keep Ryan out of middle school. He won a
landmark court case to attend school but the family left the school
district anyway, moving to the quiet lakeside home in Cicero, about
20 miles north of Indianapolis. At that school, he was welcomed and
befriended.
   Recently, a group of musicians released a song, ``Colors,'' as a
tribute to Ryan's memory and to promote AIDS awareness. Next up: a
book started by Ryan that chronicles his life and deals frankly
with questions about AIDS. A co-author helped Mrs. White finish the
book after his death.
   ``Ryan White: My Own Story,'' is scheduled for release March 15
by Dial Books, with proceeds going to the Ryan White Fund at Riley
Hospital for Children in Indianapolis. A spring tribute to Ryan is
planned in Los Angeles to benefit the charities who supported him.
   Amid her grief, the 42-year-old Mrs. White remains focused on
the killer disease that took her son away.
   ``It's on my mind a lot. I see more and more hemophiliacs who
are dying or who are coming down with AIDS, and it's like, do I
want to continue to be around all this tragedy?''
   She answers her own question.
   ``You want to motivate some goodness. There are some things I
want to see get done,'' she said.
   ``I want to generate more awareness to where everybody
understands this disease and to make it a disease like cancer, or
anything else, that people can talk about. A disease that maybe we
can have some hope for ... where the end result isn't always
death.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0007 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 1133EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--EtruscanDiscover     12-23 0173</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Etruscan Discovery,0172</SECOND>
<HEAD>Archaeologists Discover Ancient Etruscan Sculptures</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ROME (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Archaeologists have discovered an Etruscan tomb with
unusual statues that could shed new light on the empire that
dominated Italy before succumbing to the Roman Empire, news reports
said.
   The tomb, near Cortona in central Italy, is believed to date to
the sixth or seventh century B.C. It was discovered last week, the
reports said Saturday.
   The regional archaeological superintendent, Francesco Nicosia,
told the Italian news agency ANSA that the discovery was of
``unimagined dimensions.''
   The tomb has seven rooms and is flanked by a terrace with steps
decorated with two statues. One shows a sphinx fighting with a
warrior, and the other depicts a sphinx crushing a man.
   They are the only such Etruscan statues known to exist, and
could shed new light on the Etruscans' contacts with other peoples,
news reports said.
   The Etruscans were known for commercial flair, an elaborate
religion and a brilliant artisan tradition. Etruscan culture
flourished until the 1st century B.C.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0008 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 1135EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--RailAccident     12-23 0166</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Rail Accident,0172</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rail Car Explodes, Killing Seven People</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A railway tanker car loaded with liquid natural
gas exploded near two passenger trains in central Russia, killing
seven people and injuring 48 others, Tass reported Sunday.
   The force of the explosion blew the locomotive from one
passenger train into the path of a second oncoming passenger train,
the official Soviet news agency said. Carriages on both trains
caught fire and 16 were destroyed, Tass said.
   Tass said the tanker car was sitting on a railway siding when it
exploded at Yelnikovo Station near Belgorod in south-central
Russia.
   A ``powerful blast wave'' struck a passenger train sitting on an
adjacent track, and threw its locomotive onto a third track into
the path of the oncoming train, it said.
   All those killed were passengers on the stationery train, which
had been en route from the Black Sea port of Kislovodsk to
Leningrad, Tass said. The oncoming passenger train was traveling
southeast from Moscow to Kharkov in the Ukraine.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0009 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 1142EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Reagan'sPapers     12-23 0726</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Reagan's Papers,860</SECOND>
<HEAD>Reagan Papers Won't Be Available for Years</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By W. DALE NELSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Ronald Reagan Presidential Library is
nearing completion on a California hilltop, but it may be years
before the former president's papers are available to scholars.
   Reagan is the first president to come under a 1978 law that
makes presidential papers the property of the government and gives
the National Archives five years to process them.
   ``We would prefer to use the full five years for processing,''
John T. Fawcett, assistant archivist for presidential libraries,
said in an interview.
   However, some papers may be available before the expiration of
the five years, which would be Jan. 20, 1994, Fawcett said. The law
also requires the agency to ``make such records available to the
public as rapidly and completely as possible.''
   ``Most former presidents tend to want to open these papers
rather quickly,'' the Archives official said. ``There are good
administrative reasons why we should wait five years to begin
opening the papers, but we may do it sooner.''
   Cathy Goldberg, a spokeswoman for Reagan, said from Los Angeles
that Reagan ``is pleased that scholars, students and the public
will have access to the presidential papers of his administration,
but since the library is under construction at this time, the date
of availability has not been determined.''
   Samuel Gammon, executive director of the American Historical
Association, said, ``In general, we are always anxious to see
things as soon as possible, but we do recognize that the National
Archives, in handling presidential libraries, has certain financial
problems and so on.''
   Until Reagan, former presidents owned their White House papers,
except for those of Richard Nixon, which were made government
property b special legislation after the Watergate scandals. Since
the establishment of the presidential library system, beginning
with the Franklin D. Roosevelt Library in Hyde Park, N.Y., other
presidents have donated their papers to the government and they
have generally been available in less than five years.
   Reagan's library, being built near Simi Valley, Calif., is
expected to be completed shortly after his 80th birthday on Feb. 6.
After that, the Archives will begin moving in the papers, which are
now stored in a warehouse in Culver City, Calif. Then the Ronald
Reagan Foundation will install museum exhibits dealing with the
careers of Reagan and his wife, Nancy. Dedication of the library is
scheduled for early November.
   Reagan, the first president to serve eight years since Dwight D.
Eisenhower in the 1950's, left behind a record amount of paper, an
estimated 52,600 cubic feet. Fawcett said more than 20,000 cubic
feet or 40 million pages, almost equal to the entire bulk of the
Nixon papers, were destroyed in a program initiated by the
Archives. These papers were part of the mail to the president from
members of the public. Fawcett said a sample was kept, along with
careful records of the rest. These were the only Reagan papers
destroyed, he said.
   The documents had to be transported farther than any other
presidential papers had, since Reagan is from California. So, for
the first time, the papers were flown. Fawcett said the Archives
considered using trucks or trains, or even barging the documents
through the Panama Canal, but concluded that flying them would cost
about the same as truck transportation and be safer and quicker.
   A staff of 14 has been processing the papers at Culver City. The
library will have a staff of 22.
   Under the law, the former president's personal papers, those not
related to official business, remain his own property. This
category includes papers dealing with his 1984 re-election
campaign. But Fawcett said Reagan, like Jimmy Carter before him,
has decided to deed campaign papers to the government.
   Both Reagan and then Vice President George Bush exercised an
option in the law to shield several categories of papers from
public scrutiny for up to 12 years. These include classified
national security matters, information about appointments to
federal offices, trade secrets, confidential advice of presidential
advisers, information infringing on personal privacy and
information that is protected by other laws.
   Archives is deciding what papers fit into each category. If a
researcher challenges such a classification, Archives must justify
its decision within 30 days.
   Fawcett said archivists will make recommendations to Reagan's
representative, Los Angeles attorney Stephen Blitz, to open up some
of these papers in less than 12 years. For instance, he said, there
may often be no longer any reason to keep advice to the president
on past decisions confidential.
   Blitz' office said he was out of town and not available.
   Bush's vice presidential papers are stored at the Archives in
Washington and may become part of his presidential library, Fawcett
said. Rice University in Houston, the University of Houston and
Texas A &amp; M have all bid to be the site of that library.
   However long it takes for Reagan's papers to become public, it
is certain to be sooner than before the advent of presidential
libraries.
   Abraham Lincoln's papers were not open to public research until
1949, and the Adams family still imposes some restrictions on the
papers of John and John Quincy Adams, Fawcett said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0010 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 1143EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-South-Africa-Violence     12-23 0188</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-South-Africa-Violence,0197</SECOND>
<HEAD>Six Blacks Killed In Attacks</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JOHANNESBURG, South Africa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Five blacks died from gunshot
wounds in the troubled eastern province of Natal and a policeman
was fatally shot in a black township outside Johannesburg, police
reported Sunday.
   The policeman was standing guard outside a residential block for
women in the Alexandra township when unidentified gunmen fired on
the officer, police said.
   In Natal, a policeman fatally shot a black man and wounded
another when he came under attack by an unidentified group outside
Pietermaritzburg, the provincial capital.
   Also, police found the bullet-riddled bodies of two men and a
woman in Kwamakuta, near the port city of Durban. Another man who
died of gunshot wounds was found at Dongonya, about 18 miles south
of Durban.
   The daily police unrest report, which covers incidents from the
previous 24 hours, gave no additional details on the incidents.
   More than 3,000 South African blacks have died in unrest during
1990, the worst year on record. Most of the deaths have occurred in
faction fighting between rival black political groups. But more
than 200 blacks have been killed in clashes with the security
forces.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0011 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 1157EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-PhilippineFuture Bjt   12-23 0714</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Philippine Future, Bjt,0856</SECOND>
<HEAD>Year Ends On Bleak Note, Grim Prospects For Future</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT H. REID</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MANILA, Philippines (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Next year in the Philippines probably
will be a grim one of rising inflation, a declining economy and
political instability.
   After three years of economic growth rates over 5 percent, many
economists predict recession in 1991, with sharp increases in
unemployment, especially if war breaks out in the Persian Gulf.
   Higher oil costs that followed Iraq's seizure of Kuwait on Aug.
2 forced the government to raise consumer fuel prices by more than
45 percent.
   That sent shock waves through an economy already struggling with
double-digit inflation, and there are clear signs the business
community is losing confidence in President Corazon Aquino.
   The Philippines gets 64 percent of its energy from imported oil
and more than 80 percent of it comes from the Middle East.
   New foreign investments declined by 47 percent in the first
eight months of 1990 and the departure of capital rose 342 percent
as financiers moved their money to more stable havens.
   ``We have not only lost our sense of bearings, we have taken
leave of our senses,'' Teodoro Benigno, Mrs. Aquino's former
spokesman, wrote in the Philippine Star. ``The Philippines is now
looked upon abroad as a basket case.''
   Annual inflation of about 12 percent, is expected to reach 16
percent even without war in the gulf. That will lead to demands by
labor for wage increases industry says it cannot afford.
   ``Strikes and demonstrations are going to abound in the months
ahead,'' Political and Economic Risk Consultancy Ltd. of Hong Kong
said in a report last month. ``The government is widely perceived
as being helpless.''
   Aurelio Periquet, president of the Philippine Chamber of
Commerce and Industry, said industrial output could decline 40
percent in 1991 because of higher fuel costs and a chronic energy
shortage.
   Labor Secretary Ruben Torres said recently that unemployment in
this nation of 60 million people may rise to 13 percent from the
current level of 9 percent.
   Thousands of Filipinos have fled jobs in Iraq and Kuwait, not
only adding to the unemployment rolls but reducing remittances, a
major source of hard currency.
   A national election scheduled for 1992, with no clear successor
to Mrs. Aquino in sight, virtually guarantees political
uncertainty. The president has said she will not seek a second
term.
   Mutinous soldiers, after seven uprisings against Mrs. Aquino,
say they will try at least once more to overthrow her. Communist
rebels remain active, but their strength has declined because of
ideological differences and failures in strategy.
   Mrs. Aquino says her government's economic strategy was derailed
by the Persian Gulf and an earthquake in July that killed nearly
1,700 people. Critics blame the looming economic crisis on
government indecision and mismanagement.
   Fearful of domestic unrest, the Aquino government stalled for
nearly 18 months on a pledge to the International Monetary Fund to
reduce the budget deficit by eliminating subsidies on prices of
petroleum products.
   The deficit grew to 60 billion pesos ($2.1 billion), more than
three times the original estimate, causing the IMF to delay new
loans and aid.
   On Dec. 5, the government raised fuel prices 45 percent, more
than the increase for crude oil. That plunged Mrs. Aquino's
administration into a political crisis marked by nationwide
transport strikes and calls for her resignation.
   Foreign exchange has become so scarce, industrialist Raul
Concepcion declared in a recent speech, that even if oil fell to
$20 a barrel, the Philippines still would not have the dollars to
pay.
   ``Our exports, at $8 billion, will be flat,'' he said. ``People
do not seem to be aware of the gravity of the crisis and the
government seems reluctant to open up.''
   Despite the problems, the public appears tired of politics after
years of political upheaval.
   Demonstrations against oil price increases have been minuscule
compared with the ``people power'' uprising of 1986 that drove the
late President Ferdinand Marcos into exile and propelled Mrs.
Aquino to power.
   Jose Luis Alcuaz, a former government telecommunications chief
who organized recent protests of oil prices, said people have been
numbed by a series of problems. ``It's really difficult to organize
now. It will take some time.''
   That may explain, in part, why no clear successor to Mrs. Aquino
has emerged. National elections are scheduled for May 1992.
   Among possible candidates mentioned are House Speaker Ramon
Mitra, Defense Secretary Fidel Ramos, Senate President Jovito
Salonga, businessman Eduardo Cojuangco and former the former
immigration chief, Miriam Defensor-Santiago.
   None seems to have generated public enthusiasm.
   Many Filipinos believe the structure Mrs. Aquino set up early in
her administration is too unwieldy to work, regardless of who is
president.
   In 1986, she re-established a U.S.-style bicameral legislature
and presided over the writing of a new constitution modeled after
the American system of checks and balances.
   Without strong executive leadership, the system proved sluggish
and decisions come only after long, painful processes of
compromise.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0012 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 1201EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Gulf-Maps Bjt   12-23 0521</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Maps, Bjt,0662</SECOND>
<HEAD>Persian Gulf Crisis Has Military's Map Makers Working at Wartime
Levels</HEAD>
<NOTE>With LaserPhoto</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By R.B. FALLSTROM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ST. LOUIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Operating at a wartime pace, the U.S. Defense
Mapping Agency says it has shipped 35 million maps to the nearly
300,000 U.S. troops stationed in the Persian Gulf.
   That may seem like overkill. But the military needs maps of
varying detail and intricacy, with many to be used once and
discarded, the agency says.
   ``We certainly hope it doesn't come to war, but if it were to
become a hostile action, we want our troops to have the best
products they can,'' said Dave Black, the agency's director of
public affairs. ``When the Joint Chiefs of Staff lay out the
requirements, we meet them.''
   Cartographers at the agency's two major production centers in
St. Louis and Brookmont, Md., have been working 10- to 12-hour
shifts, seven days a week, since shortly after the United States
began sending troops to the Persian Gulf as part of Operation
Desert Shield.
   They worked around the clock through Labor Day and Thanksgiving,
and there might not be any extra time at home for Christmas - not
with a Jan. 15 deadline for Iraq to get out of Kuwait or face
possible military action.
   All of Saudi Arabia, Kuwait and Iraq have been committed to
paper, Black said. The agency has had every country in the volatile
Middle East mapped for several years, relying heavily on detailed
satellite photos.
   About 4,500 different maps have been used in the territory
covered by Operation Desert Shield, breaking down the topography
into relatively small coverage areas for pilots, tank commanders,
admirals and ground troops.
   Generally, pilots need the big picture. But pilots of low-flying
aircraft - including helicopters and jets launched from aircraft
carriers - need more specific information about hills and other
terrain than bomber pilots. Soldiers on the ground need to know
where roads and power lines are.
   The number of maps shipped to the gulf include countless spares.
Pilots might mark out a mission on a map, then discard it. Ground
troops do likewise for another reason.
   ``You've got these things folded up and stuffed in your pocket,
so after a sweaty day in the desert they literally come apart,''
said A. Clay Ancell, deputy director in charge of production at the
center in St. Louis, where aeronautical maps are made. Maps for
land and sea are produced at Brookmont, near Washington, D.C.
   Nearly every soldier in the desert has some sort of map. The
first ones began arriving in Saudi Arabia about a week after the
first U.S. troops landed there.
   Thanks to improved technology, map production has already
overstepped what was done during the Korean and Vietnam wars.
   ``During the Korean War, the presses ran 24 hours a day, seven
days a week for years,'' said Otto Stoessel, graphic arts chief of
the aerospace division. ``We turned out a lot of work, but compared
to Operation Desert Shield it was nothing.
   ``We've done 10 times the amount of work in the last two months
than we did during all of Korea,'' he said.
   The Defense Mapping Agency has been in existence since 1972.
Before that, each branch of the service took care of its own
requirements, which often caused duplication.
   About 8,000 people are employed at the centers in St. Louis and
Brookmont, and even before the Persian Gulf crisis they were busy,
said Ancell.
   Maps constantly must be updated, and before last August the
agency also was busy making maps used in the nation's battle to
stop the flow of drugs from South America.
   ``We're always playing catch-up,'' Ancell said. ``If you would
gather up the Joint Chiefs of Staff, none of them would be happy
with the support that their command receives. They always want
more.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0013 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 1204EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ColumbusDispute Bjt   12-23 0739</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Columbus Dispute, Bjt,0887</SECOND>
<HEAD>Christian Groups Divided on Columbus Celebration</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVID BRIGGS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   As much of the nation prepares to commemorate
Jesus Christ's birth, Christian groups have split on whether the
arrival of their faith in the Americas 500 years ago should be
celebrated or mourned.
   The Roman Catholic Church plans a warts-and-all celebration of
five centuries of Christianity for its 55 million members. The
National Council of Churches is planning counterdemonstrations to
protest Christian churches' complicity in ``the perpetuation of
paternalism and racism into our cultures and times.''
   The council says Christians should tear asunder what Christopher
Columbus has wrought in terms of the exploitation of native
populations.
   The group's document has some historians accusing the council of
reviving ``the black legend'' used to condemn Roman Catholic
expansion into the New World during the Reformation. The bloody
16th century religious movement was aimed at reforming the Catholic
Church and resulted in the establishment of Protestantism.
   ``The rationale is that it needs to be a year of repentance and
reflection, rather than a year of celebration,'' said the Rev. Joe
Agne, a leader of the racial justice group that developed the
council of churches' statement.
   The Catholic Church and some other religious groups say the
injustices caused by colonization need to be recognized, but so
should the good the faith has done in this part of the world.
   ``I'm kind of sorry for those who call themselves Christians who
don't think it's something to celebrate,'' said the Rev. James
Hennessey, a priest and historian at Canisius College.
   The national council, which includes most of the mainline
Protestant churches, states what ``some historians have termed a
`discovery' in reality was an invasion and colonization with
legalized occupation, genocide, economic exploitation and a deep
level of institutional racism and moral decadence.''
   Other groups such as Clergy and Laity Concerned, an interfaith
group with 20,000 members, also have said there is little to
celebrate.
   ``I would have to say that although Christianity is a great
thing, the Christian church, as a human institution, has been
responsible for some pretty immense wrongdoing over the years,''
said Mark Reeve, editor of the CALC Report.
   Others, though, accentuate the positive. Said Catholic
Archbishop Edward McCarthy of Miami: ``Already, strong forces have
gathered to characterize Chritianity in the ugliest of terms while
the reality of the church's commitment to the Americas is
unparalleled in the annals of human history.''
   A pastoral letter approved by the Catholic bishops in November -
``Heritage and Hope: Evangelization in America'' - apologizes for
the racism and mistreatment native populations have endured since
Columbus landed. But they added:
   ``Over the centuries, thousands of men and women sought to bring
the good news of Jesus Christ to their times, healing the sick,
educating the ignorant and witnessing to their culture of the
presence of Christ.''
   Rabbi James Rudin, director of interreligious affairs for the
American Jewish Committee, agreed that, on balance, there's much to
celebrate in 1992.
   Although 1492 - the year Jewish people were expelled from Spain
- was a dark moment in Jewish history, the voyage of Columbus paved
the way for ``one of the greatest Jewish communities in history,''
the one in the United States, he said.
   ``From a Jewish perspective, the arrival of Columbus is looked
on with great favor ... because it opened up a new era in Jewish
life,'' Rudin said.
   Some historians say the National Council of Churches document
almost revives the stereotype of the passive ``noble savage'' in
presenting history in stark contrasts of good and evil.
   They point out, contrary to the council of churches document,
some Indian groups at the time engaged in slavery and inhuman
practices such as blood sacrifices.
   ``I see a reverse kind of racism in that nothing good can come
from the people of Europe and only good can come from the people
called primitive,'' said historian Martin Marty of the University
of Chicago.
   Other historians also questioned why the document dwelled on the
evils of Catholic missionary efforts, and failed to specifically
criticize the effects of English colonization or other largely
Protestant efforts in displacing native populations.
   ``You pick on the Spanish because that was part of the
Reformation polemic. The Spanish made good bad guys from the point
of view of Anglo-Saxon tradition,'' said historian James Muldoon of
Rutgers University. ``This is a throwback to the 16th century
Reformation polemic.''
   The Rev. Sam Wynn, head of the Native American International
Caucus of the United Methodist Church, said there's enough blame to
go around.
   For example, he said, a United Methodist district superintendent
led a cavalry massacre of 700 people.
   ``This is not a time to celebrate past events that have
annhilated whole groups of people in the name of God,'' he said.
   But others point out that even dating back to the days of
Columbus, Christian groups were outspoken in raising moral concerns
over issues such as racism and the treatment of native peoples.
   ``Maybe the way we examine ourselves today is due to the
consciousness raising that has occurred in the past 500 years,''
said Maria Luisa Gaston, coordinator of the Catholic celebration.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0014 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 1219EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BalkanWinter Bjt   12-23 0684</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Balkan Winter, Bjt,0876</SECOND>
<HEAD>Democracy Doesn't Provide Food or Fuel for Winter</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto SOF3</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GEORGE JAHN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TIMISOARA, Romania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Romanians and Bulgarians, whose farms
once fed Eastern Europe, welcome freedom after decades of
oppression but are more occupied with the struggle to get enough
food and fuel for the winter.
   They had hoped economic hard times would end with the downfall
of their the old regimes a year ago, but it hasn't happened.
   ``We need food and clothes,'' said Livia Hosszu of Timisoara.
``You can't eat democracy.''
   In Romania, food production has declined 20 percent since
Communist dictator Nicolae Ceausescu was overthrown and executed.
Less is being exported, but much finds its way to the high-priced
black market.
   Only 120 tons of meat were left in Bulgaria's main warehouse by
mid-December. Sofia alone normally needs 7,000 tons a month. Sugar,
cooking oil and potatoes also were scarce or unavailable and energy
was rationed.
   After Ceausescu and Bulgaria's Todor Zhivkov of Bulgaria were
ousted, new governments were chosen in free elections with mandates
for economic reform. They promised a break with the old,
inefficient economics and a taste of the free-market policies that
Western Europe prosperous.
   People in both countries say things have not improved.
   Bulgarians lived relatively well on the food and energy bought
by Zhivkov's liberal borrowing policies, so this has been the worst
winter ever for many.
   Months of political bickering between a weak government and
divided opposition prevented action on measures to improve living
standards.
   Shelves in food store usually are empty. Bulgaria stopped making
payments months ago on a foreign debt of more than $10 billion and
is strapped for cash to import energy.
   ``If I could choose, I'd choose to live in a country where there
is maybe less democracy but more goods,'' said Marina Popova, 27,
who spends much of her time in a stuffy kitchen-living room with
her husband, 3-year-old child and in-laws.
   ``We don't have enough wood to heat the whole house, and that's
why during the day we all live in one room,'' she told a visitor to
Kalugerovo, her village 80 miles southeast of Sofia.
   Little was for sale in the village store: cheese, packets of
rice and cans of fish. A supply van that used to come fully loaded
three times a week now delivers sporadically, said the store
manager, who would not give her name.
   ``It may have been bad while Zhivkov was in power, but at least
our shop was full,'' she said.
   Another resident, Sotyanka Sirakova, said life gets ``worse and
worse'' in Bulgaria.
   Meat has been unavailable for four months and cooking oil for
three, she said in a shabby room she shares with her husband. Mrs.
Sirakova, 52, is an unemployed cleaning woman.
   Romanians suffered severely during the last decade of Ceausecu's
rule, when he exported most of the country's food and raw materials
to pay off the foreign debt.
   A sense of betrayal by the subsequent government is particularly
strong in the western city of Timisoara, 300 miles from Bucharest,
where the the uprising against the dictator began.
   ``The sacrifice was for nothing,'' Anna Kis said of the
unfulfilled promise of better times.
   Mrs. Kis, a 42-year old widow, and Ms. Hosszu, 52, were
interviewed after a four-hour shopping tour in Giroc, the working
class district where some of the first protests occurred.
   Many people spend hours each day foraging for necessities. More
than 100 people waited outside a butcher shop for gristly,
unidentifiable cuts of meat.
   The two women said food rationing, normal under Ceausescu, had
been introduced again in Timisoara.
   They said monthly limits per person were 4.4 pounds of sugar, 2
pounds of oil; 15 eggs; about half a pound of butter; about 3
pounds of flour and one chicken.
   When asked what she had bought, Mrs. Kis pulled a chunk of lard
and a garlic clove from a battered sack.
   ``I wanted some salami or ham,'' she said. ``I also couldn't
find any butter, eggs, flour or rice. You've got a ration card, but
no food.''
   Where food is concerned, she said, there is no difference
between Ceausescu and President Ion Iliescu, who was elected in
May. Iliescu is under increasing pressure to resign, in part
because of the dismal economic picture.
   Many basic items of clothing are unavailable and others are too
expensive, said Mrs. Kis, who earns 2,800 lei ($80) a month. She
said shoes that cost 350 lei a year ago now sell for 1,500 lei, if
they can be found at the official price.
   ``Even on the black market, you can't get what you want much of
the time, and things are three times as expensive as in state
shops,'' she said.
   Homes are warm in Giroc, Mrs. Kis said said, but the peole worry
aout a fuel shortage.
   In the nearby village of Carpinis, nothing but piles of coal
dust remains in the fuel depot.
   ``Only those who know the right people stay warm and fed,'' said
Magdalena Wambach, the village teacher. ``It's just like under
Ceausescu.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0015 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 1230EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-US-ElSalvador     12-23 0589</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-US-El Salvador,650</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.S. Weighs Release of Military Aid Congress Has Set Aside</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GEORGE GEDDA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Citing increased arms shipments to leftist
rebels in El Salvador, the Bush administration may release $42.5
million in Salvadoran military aid which Congress recently set
aside, U.S. officials say.
   Any such move would almost certainly touch off heated opposition
from Democratic lawmakers who have become increasingly impatient
with the continued American role in El Salvador's bloody civil war,
now more than a decade old.
   Of particular concern to administration officials is evidence
that the Farabundo Marti National Liberation Front (FMLN) has
received ``a substantial number'' of Soviet-made SA-14
anti-aircraft missiles, one of which was used to shoot down a
Salvadoran fighter-bomber last month. Another missile shot down an
AC-47 fixed wing gunship two weeks later.
   The officials, who asked not to be identified, said the major
supply source for the FMLN continues to be the Sandinista-dominated
military establishment in Nicaragua.
   Even though the Sandinista government was voted out of office in
Nicaragua in February, arrangements agreed to by President Violeta
Chamorro left the Sandinistas in control of the military.
   The commander in chief of the Nicaraguan armed forces, Humberto
Ortega, has denied any Sandinista role in equipping the FMLN.
   The Bush administration had asked for $85 million in aid for the
Salvadoran military for the current fiscal year. But Congress
approved only half, setting aside the remainder in a bid to promote
a negotiated settlement in El Salvador.
   Congress also was displeased with the pace of El Salvadoran
President Alfredo Cristiani's investigation of the murders of six
Jesuit priests last year.
   The aid could be released if President Bush concludes that the
FMLN is continuing to import substantial quantities of weapons or
is launching attacks non-combatant civilians. Recent FMLN military
campaigns have claimed hundreds of lives, including some
non-combatants, the State Department says.
   Release of the aid also could be approved if the administration
concludes that the conservative Cristiani government is being
threatened by an FMLN military offensive.
   The officials said the status of the $42.5 million in set aside
aid is ``under review'' - meaning the administration is weighing
the possibility of restoring it.
   Congressional sources said administration officials, in publicly
discussing the possibility of releasing the $42.5 million set
aside, are attempting ``to scare the rebels off the battlefield.''
   Recent attempts at negotiating a settlement have bogged down.
The administration says an FMLN demand for the liquidation of the
Salvadoran military and its price for a settlement is unreasonable.
   The U.S. officials said the Soviets have confirmed sending
SA-14s to Nicaragua and Cuba and did not authorize the transfer of
any of these weapons to the FMLN.
   When questioned about an SA-14 launcher found at the site where
the A-37 fighter-bomber was shot down, Soviet authorities confirmed
that the item was supplied to the Sandinista Army in 1986, U.S.
officials said.
   It was the first time the rebels had managed to down a
Salvadoran military aircraft in 11 years of war.
   The FMLN cause seemed doomed last winter after Chamorro's
victory over Nicaragua's Sandinista president, Daniel Ortega. A
U.S. official, reflecting on the continuing Sandinista supply role,
said ``They (the FMLN) are probably pleased and surprised at their
ability to continue to receive supplies.''
   The official added that Cuba also has been supplying the FMLN
and training rebel recruits.
   After the two warplanes were shot down, the State Department
announced on Dec. 7 that it was speeding up shipments of millions
of dollars worth of military equipment to the Salvadoran armed
forces.
   
   If the administration releases the aid, congressional sources
predict an angry reaction from some Democratic lawmakers who will
argue that the case for such action is weak.
   One such source, asking not to be identified, said releasing the
aid makes no political sense for Bush.
   ``Why would the president want to start a fight when he's trying
to line up support behind his Persian Gulf policy?'' the source
said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0016 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 1241EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-SubwaySojourn Bjt   12-23 0433</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Subway Sojourn, Bjt,0559</SECOND>
<HEAD>Three Days on the Subway: No Crime, No Shower, No Kidding</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BETH J. HARPAZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   They saw homeless people, a preacher giving a
lively sermon, an accordion player, a violinist, a man playing a
comb wrapped in wax paper and lots of rats and mice.
   But Charlie Redell and Roy Fox witnessed no muggings or drug
deals during a three-day expedition through the entire subway
system - which they say proves the subway is not the
terror-a-moment adventure that some people expect.
   Redell, 17, and Fox, 51, a family friend, set out Thursday
morning to ride every inch of subway track - 722 miles worth.
   They finished late Saturday, about six hours ahead of schedule,
still riding on the $1.15 tokens they'd put in the turnstyles
Thursday.
   Redell undertook the venture as a project for his humanities
class at Townsend Harris High School.
   ``Many of my classmates live in Queens and have overprotective
parents and they never ride the subway,'' he said. ``My main gal
with the project is to show that everything isn't as horrible as
people say. Roy and I were never bothered once. I never saw a knife
and I never saw a gun.''
   Fox, a former radio talk show host who is now the caretaker of a
city-owned 18th century house in the borough of Queens, says he
``wanted to see just how far a $1.15 token could go. Seven hundred
and twenty-two miles, that's not a bad deal.''
   Fox says others have ridden every route in the subway system on
one continuous trip, but as far as he knows, no one has ridden
every inch of track. To do this, he and Redell went through many
stations more than once, but on different tracks - uptown,
downtown, local and express.
   In addition to the homeless people, musicians and vermin, their
journey included two delays caused by a track fire and a power
failure; a freezing ride in the middle of the night on an elevated
section of track; a large woman dancing vivaciously to country
music blasting from her radio; a man with a huge hole in the seat
of his pants wearing no underwear; a man who kept threatening to
slug his date; and a very drunk fellow named Walter who divulged
his life story.
   ``All part of the free entertainment provided by the T.A.,''
said Fox.
   The Transit Authority had provided them with a list of working
bathrooms, scheduled track work and station concession stands.
   The cuisine turned out to be a lot better than the candy and
donuts they had anticipated buying. One night, Redell's mother met
them at a station with dinner from McDonald's, which she served on
her best china. A photographer who met them periodically when they
beeped his pager brought broiled chicken and fruit, along with a
table cloth and silk flowers. And a television camera crew gave
them hot dogs.
   They slept only a few hours during the three days, however.
   When they finished, they looked like the homeless people they
had shared cars with - hands black with grime, 3-day-old socks
bunched down around their ankles, blue jeans filthy.
   What's next for the adventurers?
   ``A hot shower,'' said Redell.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0017 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 1319EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--PrincessBaptized 1stLd-Writethru a 12-23 0206</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Princess Baptized, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0644,0215</SECOND>
<HEAD>Queen's Granddaughter Baptized</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 3 grafs to add date of princess' birth. Pick up 4th
pvs, `The infant...'</NOTE>
<DATELINE>SANDRINGHAM, England (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Princess Eugenie Victoria Helena of
York, the youngest grandchild of Queen Elizabeth II, was the noisy
center of attention Sunday at her baptism.
   Her cries were heard not only by about 130 people inside the
church of St. Mary Magdalen on the queen's estate, but also by an
estimated 1,500 people listening to loudspeakers placed outside.
   The princess, the daughter of Prince Andrew and the former Sarah
Ferguson, was believed to be the first member of the royal family
to be baptized in a public service. She was born March 23.
   The infant princess wore the silk and Honerton lace christening
robe first worn by Queen Victoria's eldest daughter and by all
royal babies since.
   Princess Eugenie's first tentative cries became increasingly
obvious as the service progressed and she gave a particularly lusty
cry at the moment of baptism, causing a sympathetic ripple of
laughter among the crowd waiting outside in the cold.
   Fifteen members of the Royal Family, now gathering at
Sandringham for their traditional Christmas celebration, attended
the service. Missing was Prince Charles, who was visiting British
forces in the Persian Gulf.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0018 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 1346EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brite-ThreePiggs     12-23 0203</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brite-Three Piggs,0239</SECOND>
<HEAD>Three Little Piggs Arrive In Time For Christmas</HEAD>
<DATELINE>YORK, Pa. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Once upon a time, not so very long ago, in a
hospital not too very far away, came three little Piggs.
   Triplets Thomas, Angela and Brittany are an early but welcome
Christmas present for Thomas and Lottie Pigg, who had tried
unsuccessfully for six years to have children.
   ``It's a blessing,'' said Mrs. Pigg, who had taken a fertility
drug often linked with multiple births.
   The triplets were born at York Hospital on Dec. 14, eight weeks
premature. Their mother went home Sunday, but the triplets, the
couple's first children, are expected to remain in the hospital
until February to gain more weight.
   Thomas, the firstborn, tipped the scales at 3 pounds, 13 ounces.
Angela weighed 2 pounds, 5 ounces. Brittany, delivered last,
weighed in at 3 pounds, 12 ounces.
   The couple, from White Hall, Md., learned in June that they
would be parents of triplets.
   ``We had tried for so long to have children, and everything
failed,'' she said. ``When they told me we were going to have
triplets, I was in shock.''
   Mrs. Pigg said she and her husband have heard ``Three Little
Pigs'' jokes ``every day'' and are bracing for more of the same as
the triplets grow up.
   ``You've got to have a sense of humor about it,'' she said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0019 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 1350EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Endowment-JoePapp     12-23 0812</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Endowment-Joe Papp,950</SECOND>
<HEAD>Obscenity Issue at Center of Rift Between Theater Producer and NEA</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT M. ANDREWS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A friendly, 24-year alliance between the
National Endowment for the Arts and New York theater producer
Joseph Papp collapsed in bitter enmity last month after an
acrimonious exchange of letters over the issue of obscenity in the
arts.
   At the end, Papp had spurned nearly $748,000 in federal grants
and accused NEA chairman John E. Frohnmayer of betraying the arts
community in a futile attempt to ``appease the fanatical zeal of
the religious right.''
   Frohnmayer accused Papp of ``inexcusable and self-serving''
behavior in rejecting the NEA grants to protest a congressional ban
on federal support for arts projects that might be deemed obscene.
   Papp, president of the New York Shakespeare Festival, fired his
parting shot in a Nov. 15 letter asking how Frohnmayer intended to
implement new legislation which dropped the obscenity ban but
requires the NEA to consider ``general standards of decency'' in
its grant-making decisions.
   ``Your past record provides little assurance of an arts
atmosphere free of subtle and not-so-subtle intimidation,'' Papp
wrote.
   Copies of the private, seven-month exchange of letters between
Papp and Frohnmayer were released by NEA headquarters in response
to a Freedom of Information Act request by The Associated Press.
   In separate interviews Thursday, Frohnmayer and Papp made clear
that neither was in a hurry to heal their breach.
   ``If we can restore relations with Saddam Hussein, anything is
possible,'' Papp said in a telephone interview from New York.
   ``I suspect they'll come back at some point,'' Frohnmayer said,
``but I don't propose to do anything about it myself.''
   Papp's battle with the NEA under Frohnmayer's leadership
coincides with serious financial problems at the New York
Shakespeare Festival, which Papp founded in 1954 in a church
basement on the Lower East Side.
   The non-profit theater organization, largest in the United
States, now includes the five-stage Public Theater in Manhattan,
free Shakespeare performances at the Delacorte Theater in Central
Park, an annual Latin festival and numerous other theatrical
ventures.
   Papp received his first federal grant, totaling $100,000 in
1966, a year after the arts endowment was created by Congress.
   Earlier this month, Papp announced the festival will lay off 30
of its 123 employees at the end of the year to save about $750,000
a year - just about the amount of NEA money he had turned away.
``It's totally a matter of economics,'' Papp said.
   The producer's battle with Frohnmayer was fought over
anti-obscenity legislation which Congress passed in October 1989 at
the behest of Sen. Jesse Helms, R-N.C. The NEA chairman has final
authority to decide whether grants are approved or rejected under
the law.
   Papp also objected to Frohnmayer's requirement that grant
recipients sign an anti-obscenity pledge, even though it wasn't
required under the law. The NEA chairman rescinded the pledge after
Congress repealed the obscenity ban last October and substituted
the ``decency standard.''
   Relations between the two men began to sour when Papp wrote
Frohnmayer on April 9 expressing dismay about the obscenity ban and
misgivings about the ``unthinkable if not downright subversive''
act of accepting a $50,000 endowment grant under those conditions.
   Papp rejected the $50,000.
   The mood of the correspondence changed drastically after
Frohnmayer in late June overruled an NEA panel of outside judges
and rejected grants to four controversial ``performance artists''
whose solo stage acts usually deal with gay and lesbian issues,
racism and politics.
   In a four-page, single-spaced letter dated July 3, Papp charged
that Frohnmayer had ``sadly become Jesse Helms' enforcer, a censor,
a role ill-befitting the leader of the arts in America'' by denying
the four grants.
   ``You must realize, dear John, that no matter how far you go,
you will never be able to appease the fanatical zeal of the
religious right,'' Papp wrote.
   Papp urged Frohnmayer to reverse himself and approve the four
grants, even if it meant possibly being fired by President Bush.
   ``Do you want praise from Senator Helms and his cohorts, or to
live by your conscience and to be revered by Americans who believe
in the arts as a crucial part of our democracy?'' Papp asked.
   Frohnmayer didn't write back this time.
   Instead, he rejected the appeals of the four grant applications
- Karen Finley, Holly Hughes, John Fleck and Tim Miller. They sued
Frohnmayer in federal court, charging that he violated the
Constitution by denying the funds for political rather than
artistic reasons.
   On Nov. 1, after Congress imposed the ``decency standard'' on
arts endowment grants, Papp sent Frohnmayer a curt, three-paragraph
letter.
   He wrote that ``unreasonable restrictive measures make it
impossible for the New York Shakespeare Festival to continue its
relationship with the National Endowment for the Arts.''
   Accordingly, Papp said he rejected as ``unacceptable'' NEA
grants totaling $323,000 which had been approved the previous May
and July.
   Because Papp never claimed the funds before the fiscal year
ended Sept. 30, the undisbursed grant money automatically reverted
to the U.S. Treasury.
   Frohnmayer was outraged.
   ``You sat on those grants throughout the duration of the fiscal
year and now tell us that you will not use them, thus denying
$323,000 to some other deserving arts applicant,'' he wrote Papp on
Nov. 5.
   ``Your actions are inexcusable and self-serving,'' he added.
   Frohnmayer served notice he would withdraw three other Papp
grant applications from consideration unless he heard from the New
York producer by Nov. 16.
   In a Nov. 15 letter - the last of the exchange - Papp confirmed
he was withdrawing the three applications for new grants totaling
$375,000. That brought to $748,000 the federal funds - awarded or
applied for - that Papp rejected.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0020 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 1355EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-SpongeFishing     12-23 0543</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Sponge Fishing,0674</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ban Would Kill Biscayne Bay Sponge Fishing But Save the Bay</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KIRK SEMPLE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The sponge fishermen of Biscayne Bay are feeling a
squeeze on their livelihoods. A state proposal in its final drafts
would ban sponge fishing in Biscayne National Park, covering about
two-thirds of the sponge-fertile Biscayne Bay.
   Federal and state officials worry that continued removal of
sponges would seriously threaten the bay's fragile ecosystem.
   The fishermen insist their activity doesn't hurt the bay's
environment - also threatened by shore development and heavy
recreational use - and keeps them and their families alive.
   ``I don't know what I'm going to do,'' said 77-year-old Pedro
``Chico'' Cordova, a Cuban immigrant who fishes with his son in
Biscayne Bay. ``I've been doing this all my life. There's nothing I
can do, except for this.''
   Sponge fishermen have worked Biscayne Bay, which stretches about
50 miles from Key Largo to North Miami, for nearly 1{ centuries.
The fishing continued even after the southern end, south from Key
Biscayne, was declared a national park in 1980.
   A blight in the Mediterranean in 1987 destroyed most of the
Mediterranean sponge population and forced a drastic increase in
prices worldwide. The natural sponges are considered superior to
man-made sponges in some types of cleaning and cosmetic
applications.
   With the price increase, the industry exploded at the prime
Florida sponge fishing sites in Biscayne Bay, Tarpon Springs and
the Florida Keys. By 1989, as many as 30 boats with three or four
men each were pulling sponges from the bay.
   The Mediterranean stock has since revived and the number of
sponge fishermen in the bay has dropped to about 40.
   That's still too many for park rangers.
   ``It's in excess of what the Bay can handle,'' said Richard
Curry, resource management coordinator for Biscayne National Park.
   Park officials say sponges are an irreplaceable component of a
delicate marine ecosystem. They act as water filters and their
porous bodies provide habitats for smaller organisms such as
juvenile fish and crabs.
   Further, commercial fishing is contrary to the mandate of the
National Park Service, the officials say.
   ``We're here to preserve and protect the resources, not preserve
and utilize the resources,'' said Curry, who's studied the bay's
ecosystem for 13 years.
   Responding to the Park Service's concern, the State Fisheries
Commission recently passed the proposal to ban sponge fishing in
the park. It will hold a public hearing on Jan. 8 and fine tune the
plan by its meeting at the end of January.
   The present version of the plan calls for a gradual phaseout of
sponge fishing in the park over the next year. Fishermen will be
able to spend only two out of every four weeks on the water until
Dec. 1, 1991, when the commercial fishing of sponges will be
prohibited entirely.
   Curry says the sponge ban may presage a wider ban on other
commercial fisheries in the bay.
   The Fisheries Commission estimated that fishermen harvested more
than 1,600 pounds of sponges last year.
   Some use environmentally harmful methods of fishing, Curry said.
They spread cooking oil on the surface of the water for better
visibility and, in violation of the law, spend more than the 14
days on the water in boats with poor sanitary facilities, Curry
said.
   In addition, officials say, sponges are being removed much
faster than they can grow back.
   ``The pure numbers of fishermen indicated to us that the
harvesting was in excess of what the bay could handle,'' said James
A. Sanders, park superintendent.
   The fishermen - all Cuban immigrants - are bitter about the
proposed ban and perceive it as a personal attack on their way of
life.
   ``The workers are going to sue the government because you just
can't throw the fishermen out on the street,'' said Cordova, who
grew up in the sponge fishing town of Caibarien, Cuba.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0021 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 1403EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ActivistPriest     12-23 0568</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Activist Priest,0713</SECOND>
<HEAD>No Room at the Inn for Homeless on Lower East Side</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY8</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Columbus Dispute, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PAUL GEITNER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Joseph and Mary walked through streets of
Manhattan's grim Lower East Side, past the makeshift tents of
homeless people and run-down tenements juxtaposed with gentrified
apartment buildings.
   They knock on a door.
   ``We are looking for warmth and a bed for the night,'' Joseph
tells the man who answers, his arm around his pregnant wife.
   ``No,'' came the angry reply. ``Go, I say. For thou are poor,
and there is no bed or rest here for thee.''
   The scene was from an outdoor Christmas pageant staged Saturday
by the Rev. George Kuhn. About 100 parishioners turned out to walk
with the couple, singing hymns and carrying candles.
   But the story of a poor couple seeking warmth is more than a
Bible story: It's one Kuhn hears daily as pastor of St. Brigid's,
across the street from Tompkins Square Park, one of the city's
largest encampments of homeless people. ``Our church opens right
onto a place where 250 people are sleeping every night,'' Kuhn
said. ``So it's very hard to preach the gospel and ignore the
central people in the gospel: the poor.''
   He delivers his message in the streets, marching in
demonstrations for affordable housing, clashing with police and
getting arrested again and again.
   Among the homeless and the squatters, who have learned not to
trust anyone too quickly, he has a reputation as a sincere man who
shares their do-it-yourself spirit.
   ``Here, if something's wrong, you fix it,'' said Calli Tumulty,
a young woman living with a group of squatters in a row of
abandoned city-owned tenements. ``That's what Father Kuhn does. He
tries to fix things.''
   Kuhn, 51, dislikes to be called a radical street activist. His
is a religious pursuit.
   ``As a pastor of a parish, you live in the real world,'' he
said. ``And our real world consists of drugs, AIDS, violence and
homelessness.''
   His church was built by Irish immigrants in 1850. The parish now
is mainly Hispanic, and poverty is still rampant. Colorful murals
put a bright face on otherwise crumbling buildings built more than
a century ago. Creeping gentrification has forced some families out
of their homes while others struggle with escalating rents.
   The struggles of the parish are obvious in Tompkins Square Park,
where on a recent frigid day dozens of homeless people huddled
around trash barrel fires while neighborhood children played on
swings and slides.
   Twice last winter, the city tried to move the homeless out to
shelters. But the homeless returned to their flimsy tents and
shanties. A city count Dec. 13 found 104 people living there. Kuhn
believes the number is more than twice that.
   Kuhn already had four arrests under his clerical collar - for
anti-war and anti-nuclear protests - when he arrived at St.
Brigid's in 1986.
   He stayed out of jail until he got involved last year with a
group of squatters who occupied an abandoned school. He was
arrested three times for crossing a police barricade to take them
food before they were finally evicted.
   Last October, Kuhn was arrested along with 20 others after
squatters attempted to occupy some vacant neighborhood apartments.
   In each arrest, the charges were eventually dropped.
   Kuhn has the tacit support of Cardinal John O'Connor and has
never been reprimanded following any of his arrests, said Joseph
Zwilling, a spokesman for the Archdiocese of New York.
   Kuhn blames the city for moving too slowly, for not taking
drastic measures - like taking over vacant buildings or giving
squatters legal standing - to deal with desperate times. By his
count, the city owns 200 abandoned buildings in the neighborhood.
   ``If anyone doesn't see the public crisis that this city is
facing, with anywhere between 70,000 and 100,000 people homeless,
there's something wrong with them,'' he said.
   Kuhn intends to continue doing what he can for the homeless and
believes most of his 600 parishioners support him.
   ``The only real protection they have is Father George,'' said
Peter Cruz, a church elder.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0022 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 1409EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-GainesvilleSlayings     12-23 0441</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gainesville Slayings,0540</SECOND>
<HEAD>Investigators Hunt for Money as Well as Killer in Gainesville
Slayings</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RON WORD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>GAINESVILLE, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The hunt for the killer of five college
students - which has no end in sight - has also become a search for
dollars.
   Investigators will visit Washington early next month to lobby
for financial aid. They have run up a $3 million tab while checking
out more than 5,500 leads. Some $1.14 million in federal grants
covered only a part of the overtime costs of the six agencies
involved in a task force investigating the killings.
   Officials from the task force plan to meet to meet with Sens.
Connie Mack and Bob Graham, among others, in hopes of getting more
money.
   The Gainesville Police Department is already in the hole for
$309,120 and the other agencies' expenses also are outstripping the
amount of the grants.
   ``A city this size cannot afford that hit,'' said Patrick
Callahan, budget coordinator for the Gainesville Police Department.
   Gainesville police are already cutting back on some programs and
delaying implementation of others to continue paying for the
investigation.
   ``We'll do what it takes. We are not going to base this
investigation on available income,'' he said. ``We'll find the
money, it's that important.''
   The department, he said, is determined to pay for the
investigation for a full year after the murders. That may not be
long enough.
   ``There is nothing I'm aware of at this point in time to allow
me to project when we'll solve this case,'' State Attorney Len
Register said recently.
   The focus has faded from former University of Florida freshman
Edward Lewis Humphrey, for weeks considered a strong suspect. He is
currently serving a sentence in a mental institution for beating
his grandmother.
   Gainesville Police Chief Wayland Clifton said he remains
confident the case will be solved but cautions citizens not to let
down their guard.
   ``Our assumption is he could strike again,'' Clifton said.
   Most of the 65 investigators who remain on the case are taking a
break for the holidays and will return in January. Some Florida
Department of Law Enforcement agents have moved out of motels and
into apartments, telling relatives they could be here a year.
   ``It could be even longer,'' Register said.
   More than 300 investigators came in Aug. 29, after the last of
five victims were found.
   The killings came on the eve of the fall semester's beginning as
students moved into apartments and dorms - the excitement of a new
school year on everyone's minds.
   ``Fall is kind of a semester of dreams. It's the semester you
think you are going to get straight A's; you're going to find the
girlfriend or boyfriend of your dreams; you've got a football team
all set for a new season,'' said Michael Browne, University of
Florida student body president. ``That was all taken away from
us.''
   The murders are still topics of conversation and there is still
fear on the campus.
   The student newspaper, the Independent Florida Alligator,
congratulated students earlier this month for making it through
``the most hellish semester in school history.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0023 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 1411EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-Egypt-Analysis     12-23 0485</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Egypt-Analysis,0598</SECOND>
<HEAD>Egypt's Role Likely To Be Enhanced However Crisis Ends</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP News Analysis</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By WILLIAM C. MANN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CAIRO, Egypt (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Egypt's traditional role as big brother to
the Arabs has never been tested more than during its confrontation
with the other major Arab power, Iraq. Analysts say President Hosni
Mubarak passed the test well.
   No matter how the Persian Gulf crisis ends, they say, Egypt's
role has been enhanced with Saudi Arabia and the smaller Persian
Gulf states.
   Its importance, stemming mainly from its military strength and
the political weight it carries with the West, probably will be
increased for a long time to come.
   A likely scenario would be the oil-rich sheikdoms, especially
Saudi Arabia, financing a standing Egyptian army as the backbone of
regional security in the gulf.
   ``This is not viewed as an Egyptian rent-a-cop, nor is it viewed
as a Saudi bailout,'' said Jim Zogby of the Washington-based
Arab-American Institute. He said political and economic cooperation
would be an integral part of the relationship.
   Egypt already has close to 30,000 soldiers in Saudi Arabia and
the United Arab Emirates, part of a U.S.-dominated multinational
force half a million strong.
   Mubarak and President Bush's administration pieced together the
Arab force, involving Syrian and Moroccan troops as well, after
Iraq's army invaded Kuwait on Aug. 2 and its president, Saddam
Hussein, annexed the emirate six days later.
   Zogby and others said the basis of Egypt's new military
prominence is a general unease with the presence of a
quarter-million U.S. soldiers on Arab soil to protect Arabs from
Arabs.
   Richard Murphy, former assistant secretary of state for the Near
East and South Asia, sees among the Arabs ``a sense of shame that
Arabs fouled the nest, but they want to take care of it
themselves.''
   The notion of American forces remaining in the area after the
crisis ends ``in itself is uncomfortable for everybody,'' said
Murphy by telephone from New York, where he is an analyst for the
Council on Foreign Relations.
   And even if they did stay, he said, ``a United Nations flag
would be more comfortable. But the Saudis want an Arab force.''
   That means to a great extent an Egyptian force. Egypt has a
standing army of half a million men and more than 600,000 reserves.
It is the only Arab force capable of standing up to Iraq's
million-man military.
   In Cairo, the thinking in the Foreign Ministry is that U.S.
soldiers will be necessary for some time after Iraq is driven out
of Kuwait. The gulf Arabs and Egypt need breathing room for
organizing a regional defense force, Egyptian diplomats say.
   They also are talking about how the Arab force must be formed
from within and Egypt's special role in it.
   ``Any Arab security system must emanate from within the Arab
nation,'' Foreign Minister Esmat Abdel-Meguid told an economics and
political seminar at Cairo University. ``It should not be imposed
from outside. If it is, it will definitely fail.''
   Abdel-Meguid's chief aide, Minister of State Butros Ghali, said
the reshaping of Egypt's role extends beyond shoring up weaker
nations with its military might.
   ``One of the first objectives of Egyptian diplomacy once the
gulf crisis is over will be to create a new momentum in favor of
economic integration of the Arab World,'' Ghali told an interviewer
in New York.
   With that, he said, can come political cohesion that would let
the Arabs compete with a united Europe.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0024 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 1417EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People Sub a0666 12-23 0183</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People, Sub, a0666,0186</SECOND>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 1st 2 grafs of LINCOLN, Neb.-dated third item in rdp to
recast, deleting ethnic characterization of actor.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>LINCOLN, Neb. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   After missing his scheduled court date last
week, actor Rodney Grant was finally arraigned on two charges of
unemployment fraud.
   Grant, who appears in the Kevin Costner film ``Dances With
Wolves,'' was arrested in Lincoln on Monday on a year-old warrant
for failing to appear in court a previous time, in December 1989.
Grant, 31, was charged on two counts of obtaining Nebraska
unemployment compensation by making false statements.
   Deputy Lancaster County Attorney Jan Lipovsky said Grant was
apparently unaware of his arraignment Wednesday. After learning
that he had missed that second court date, Grant returned to face
the charges Friday.
   The misdemeanor charges stem from two one-week periods in June
and July 1988, when he allegedly was employed but received
unemployment compensation.
   Grant portrays the bold warrior Wind In His Hair in ``Dances
With Wolves.''
   Judge Richard Williams set a $1,500 personal recognizance bond
for Grant. His next court appearance has not be scheduled.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0025 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 1422EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Chess-WorldChampionsh     12-23 0257</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Chess-World Championship,0313</SECOND>
<HEAD>22nd Game Postponed A Second Time</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LYON, France (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The 22nd and possibly decisive game of the
world chess championship between defender Garry Kasparov and
Anatoly Karpov was postponed a second time, the organizers
announced Sunday.
   A technical time-out was called so the game would not be played
on Monday, Christmas Eve.
   Karpov took his third and final time-out on Saturday, pushing
the 22nd game to Monday. Kasparov has used all his time-outs.
   With Christmas approaching, the president of the International
Federation of Chess, Florencio Campomanas, reached an agreement
with both players to put off the 22nd game until Wednesday.
Regulations permit a technical time-out.
   Kasparov leads the series 11.5 to 9.5 and needs only a draw to
gain the 12 points needed to win and retain the title.
   He will play white in the 22nd game, with Karpov defending with
the black pieces. Kasparov has won the last three times he has
played white in the nine games in Lyon.
   Karpov needs to win the final three games to take the title. He
has won twice in the 21 previous games of this series.
   The two have played to a draw five times in the French portion
of the championship. They drew 10 times in the 12 games played in
New York between Oct. 8 and Nov. 7.
   Even if Kasparov clinches the title by reaching 12 points in the
series, the two Soviet grandmasters will continue playing to see
who wins the majority of the $3 million purse.
   If the overall series ends in a 12-12 draw, the prize money will
be split.
   Kasparov won the title from Karpov in 1985 and defended it in
1986 and 1987. Karpov took the championship in 1975 when American
Bobby Fischer refused to defend the title he won in 1972.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0026 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 1422EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-ChristmasMenu     12-23 0318</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Christmas Menu,0380</SECOND>
<HEAD>Santa May Not Make It But Hot Turkey Dinner Will</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT DVORCHAK</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>IN EASTERN SAUDI ARABIA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   It won't be Christmas dinner at
home with roasted chestnuts and a roaring fire, but Desert Shield
troops will have literally tons of turkey, roast beef and ham to
feast on.
   ``Santa Claus is not going to be around probably to bring
presents, so we're going to have to do something to make it a
special day,'' said Chief Warrant Officer Wesley Wolf, food adviser
for the U.S. military in Saudi Arabia.
   ``It's such a big day. This is really an important meal for us.
We're trying to get a hot meal to everyone,'' Wolf said.
   Hot food is a big morale boost to the service members on duty in
foxholes and guardposts, enduring the flies, heat, scorpions and
desert isolation.
   As a touchof home cooking, the military has prepared 340,000
meals for Christmas. There are 280,000 U.S. troops in Saudi Arabia,
but Wolf over-ordered to make sure he had more than enough for
every service member.
   Ingredients for the Christmas dinner were ordered in September
and arrived a month ago.
   Reinforcements arriving in the country on Tuesday won't have to
worry about missing Christmas dinner either. ``If a soldier walks
in that day, we'll have a Christmas meal for him,'' said Wolf, who
served as a cook in Vietnam.
   Ham will be served, even though pork products are banned in this
Islamic kingdom.
   ``We keep it low profile. We don't make a big deal of it. We
bring it in and handle it ourselves,'' Wolf said.
   The list for Christnmas Day cooking includes:
   35,000 pounds of shrimp plus cocktail sauce; 108,000 pounds of
canned ham; 172,000 pounds of roast beef; 150,000 pounds of rolled
turkey; 4,000 whole turkeys; cranberry sauce; stuffing; 280,000
pounds of glazed sweet potatoes; mashed potatoes; mixed vegetables;
a salad of tomatoes, lettuce and cucumbers; assorted breads; 35,000
pounds of fruitcake; 150,000 pies including apple, peach, pecan,
pumpkin and minced meat; hard candies; mixed nuts; apples, oranges,
grapes, tangerines and pears; coffee, tea, milk, soft drinks and
egg nog; and 500,000 Mars and Snickers candy bars donated by Saudi
Arabia.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0027 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 1447EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Poland     12-23 0317</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Poland,0343</SECOND>
<HEAD>Walesa, New Polish President, Receives Former Communist Leader</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WARSAW, Poland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Lech Walesa on his first full
day in office Sunday received his predecessor, Gen. Wojciech
Jaruzelski, Poland's former Communist leader who had been excluded
from the inauguration ceremony.
   During their 50-minute meeting at Belweder Palace, Jaruzelski
``shared his experiences of performing the presidential office''
with Walesa, according to a brief communique carried by the PAP
news agency.
   Jaruzelski wished the new president well in his ``most
responsible mission,'' PAP said, and Walesa in turn wished his old
foe health and success.
   Jaruzelski, 67, the former Communist Party chief, interned
Walesa and thousands of other activists during the martial law
crackdown that began on Dec. 13, 1981.
   He was not invited to Walesa's inaugural ceremonies, and his
parliament gallery chair was empty when Walesa was sworn in before
the National Assembly on Saturday.
   Walesa, the 47-year-old shipyard electrician and Solidarity
labor leader for a decade, was elected Dec. 9 in the nation's first
popular presidential vote.
   Although condemned internationally and disliked at home for
repressing Solidarity during the 1980s, Jaruzelski, a four-star
army general, remained in power as president after Solidarity took
control of the government.
   As president, Walesa will be chief of state and the military,
and he may gain enhanced powers in a new constitution expected to
be adopted in 1991.
   By means of the 1989 negotiations with the democratic
opposition, Jaruzelski allowed a peaceful transition to a
Solidarity-led government. He was elected president by the National
Assembly in July 1989 but resigned early under pressure to complete
the democratic reforms with national presidential elections.
   During his 17 months as president, he did not interfere with the
government's radical economic and political reforms.
   Although secretive during most of his three-decade political
career, Jaruzelski became more open to the press as president,
granting interviews and allowing television cameras to show his
home life.
   Jaruzelski has said he will devote himself to writing his
memoirs.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0028 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 1449EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-NixonLibrary     12-23 0278</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Nixon Library,0314</SECOND>
<HEAD>Nixon and Elvis, Four Presidents Are Top Postcards at Nixon
Library</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Reagan's Papers</HEAD>
<DATELINE>YORBA LINDA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Richard Nixon opened U.S. dialogue
with China nearly 20 years ago and the effects are still being felt
- even at the gift shop of the Nixon Library &amp; Birthplace.
   The shop recently received a letter from a man in China
requesting its most popular postcard, that of Presidents Nixon,
Ford, Bush and Reagan together at the library inauguration.
   ``The man who sent it talked about Nixon and relations between
China and the U.S.,'' said library spokesman Kevin Cartwright. ``It
was quite a letter.''
   ``He requested that we not send the postcard in any kind of
identifying envelope,'' said Cartwright, alluding to the recent
communist crackdown on the movement for democracy in China.
   The best-selling postcard records the unprecedented public
gathering of four presidents. The second-best seller strikes a
lighter note: It is a picture of the 37th president shaking hands
with Elvis Presley in the Oval Office.
   Earlier this year, Nixon library managers decided to pull the
famous tapes of the Watergate scandal in favor of other exhibits.
However, that hasn't stopped visitors or the flood of gift shop
sales.
   Over 200 autographed copies of Nixon's autobiograhy, ``In The
Arena,'' were purchased one day last week. Library managers
estimate Nixon signed several thousand copies of the memoir of his
political career.
   Although the book has a $21.95 list price, copies are selling
for $10 at the library to encourage readership.
   The Odyssey, a store in Newport Beach which specializes in
autographed items, bought about 100, expecting the value to rise.
   The Nixon library gift shop sells other books penned by the
former president as well as Chinese-made panda bears, porcelain
plates signed by presidents, clothing and quiz cards on the
presidents.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0029 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 1502EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Honduras     12-23 0477</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Honduras,0546</SECOND>
<HEAD>Grocery Stores Closed After Early-Morning Bomb Explosion</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By FREDDY CUEVAS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TEGUCIGALPA, Honduras (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Police barred holiday grocery
shoppers from supermarkets Sunday after a bomb exploded and six
other bombs were deactivated before stores opened. The authorities
blamed guerrillas.
   No one was hurt, and damage was still being added up, said
police spokesman Cesar Augusto Somoza.
   The explosion at 8:15 a.m. (9:15 a.m. EDT) ripped through a
supermarket 200 yards from the President Rafael Callejas' offices,
the spokesman said. The presidential offices were closed for the
holidays.
   A police bomb squad deactivated six powerful bombs at three
other supermarkets, the police spokesman said. Two of the six were
discovered at a grocery store in a mall 300 yards south of the U.S.
Embassy.
   Police ordered supermarkets to stay closed until the afternoon
while they searched for bombs.
   Somoza linked the bombs to an announcement by the Morazan
Liberation Front, which said on the radio Sunday it was beginning
an offensive against Callejas' government for its economic
policies.
   The 11-year-old Morazan Liberation Front detonated two other
bombs earlier this month, police said. The organization, a militant
wing of the Honduran Communist Party, is blamed for numerous
dynamite attacks since 1983.
   Police said they had arrested two front members, Juan Jose Vaca
Nunez, 30, and Marco Tulio Funez Duarte, 31, on suspicion of
bombing and bombing attempts. Both are union leaders at a
subsidiary of the Cincinnati-based banana company Chiquita Brands
International Inc.
   The guerrillas' announcement said they ``initiated an offensive
of solidarity with the people and against those who, not caring
about Hondurans' suffering and oppression, do dirty business in the
name of the governing National Party's structural adjustment
policy.''
   On March 12, barely two months after Callejas' inauguration, his
administration put into effect a series of austerity measures that
have crippled consumers' buying power. The administration approved
a 300 percent increase in electricity, water and phone rates.
   Prices have soared for basic products such as meat, beans, milk,
bread, eggs, and fuel. The cost of gasoline rose 147 percent
between June and September to $5.56 a gallon.
   Callejas introduced the measures in an effort to offset
Honduras' $600 million deficit and make payments on the country's
$3.5 billion foreign debt.
   However, they resulted in raging inflation, calculated at 32
percent for the year by the government and as high as 100 percent
by private economists.
   The Morazan Liberation Front said Sunday it has formed
``detachments of Hondurans to struggle for better living conditions
for Honduras' poor.''
   Police claim that the group detonated two high-powered bombs on
Dec. 12 and 18 that injured one person and damaged three buildings
in San Pedro Sula, 125 miles northwest of Tegucigalpa.
   The group is named for former president Francisco Morazan, who
led an armed movement to unite the five countries of Central
America in the early 1800s.
   The front, born during 14 years of military rule, initiated an
unsuccessful boycott of 1980 legislative elections.
   Members have been accused of wounding at least 15 U.S. soldiers
in dynamite attacks between 1983 and 1989. They have also been
charged with three armed attacks on U.S. military convoys traveling
Honduran highways.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0030 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 1506EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Israel-MassacreTrial     12-23 0385</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel-Massacre Trial,0464</SECOND>
<HEAD>Israeli Blames Killing of Seven Arabs on Mental Illness</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A cashiered Israeli soldier admitted in court
Sunday that he shot and killed seven Arab workers seven months ago
but said his actions resulted from mental illness, not criminal
intent.
   The killings May 20 in the Tel Aviv suburb of Rishon Lezion set
off three days of rioting in the occupied lands in which 13
Palestinians died from army gunfire, refueling the 3-year-old
uprising against Israeli occupation.
   Ami Popper, 21, from Rishon Lezion, admitted the shootings
through his court-appointed attorney, David Krimilovsky, on the
opening day of his trial in Tel Aviv District Court, Israel radio
reported.
   District Attorney Nurit Schmidt, who is prosecuting the case,
said she intended to prove Popper acted in cold blood and would
call witnesses to testify that he behaved calmly during the
shootings, the radio said.
   Popper is charged with killing seven unarmed Palestinian workers
and wounding 11 others in a so-called slave market, a spot where
Arabs gather for hire as day laborers by Israeli employers.
   Popper, armed with an Uzi submachine gun, ordered 50
Palestinians to sit on the ground, then raked them with gunfire.
Arab survivors later said they obeyed his orders because he had a
gun and was wearing Israeli army pants.
   After Popper's arrest, authorities said he was deranged and
despondent over a failed love affair. Army officials said Popper
was dishonorably discharged from service for being absent without
leave.
   Popper's attorney said his client was mentally incapable of
understanding the charges against him, but a panel of five
court-appointed psychiatrists found him competent to stand trial.
Family members later complained they could not afford examination
by independent psychiatrists.
   A former girlfriend, whose name was banned from publication by
the court, testified Sunday that she broke off an affair with
Popper two weeks before the Rishon Lezion killings and that he
threatened to kill himself, the radio said.
   It also quoted the woman as saying Popper came to her on the day
of the shootings and told her ``I did a terrible thing. I fired at
15 Arabs to be far away from you.''
   The woman also said Popper told her that at age 13 he had been
tied to a tree and raped by a man.
   After his arrest, Popper said he had been raped by seven Arabs,
one of whom was a victim in the Rishon Lezion shootings. Family
members said at the time that they'd never heard the story.
   Those killed in Rishon Lezion were from the occupied Gaza Strip,
and rioting began there shortly after the shootings. It later
spread to the West Bank and neighboring Jordan, which has a large
Palestinian population.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0031 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 1508EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Obit-Schocken     12-23 0267</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Schocken,0310</SECOND>
<HEAD>Veteran Haaretz Editor Gershom Schocken Dies in Tel Aviv</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Gershom Gustav Schocken, editor of the
respected Israeli daily Haaretz for more than 50 years and one of
the country's most acclaimed journalists, has died. He was 78.
   Schocken died Saturday at Shiba Hospital in Tel Aviv of what
Haaretz described as a ``malignant disease'' that had been
diagnosed a year ago. An editor at the Hebrew daily declined to
give further details.
   Schocken was born in September 1912 in Zwickau, Germany, and was
the eldest son of Shlomo Salman Schocken, a businessman and art
collector who established the Schocken Publishing Houses.
   He studied economics at Heidelberg University from 1932-1933
and, with the rise of the Nazis in 1933, moved to Palestine, where
he worked for the Anglo-Palestine Bank.
   Schocken's father purchased Haaretz in 1937 and he became a
business manager at the newspaper. Schocken was appointed editor in
1939 and held the post till his death.
   In 1955, Schocken was elected to Israel's Knesset, or
parliament, as a member of the Progressive Party.
   Schocken was one of the founders of Itim, Israel's national news
agency, and he was named International Editor of the Year by the
New York-based World Press Review in 1983.
   ``There never was another journalist like Schocken in Israel,''
a longtime Haaretz reporter, Joel Marcus, wrote in Sunday's edition
of the newspaper. ``A part of Schocken remains within many of us.''
   ``For him, freedom of the press meant first of all the
journalist's duty to be precise, to expose the establishment's
failures and not to be servile in front of it, to write truly about
a true thing and adhere to it,'' Marcus wrote.
   Schocken is survived by his wife, a daughter and two sons. His
funeral was held Sunday in Tel Aviv.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0032 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 1513EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brite-1850sChristmas     12-23 0406</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brite-1850s Christmas,0522</SECOND>
<HEAD>State Museum Decks the Halls for Christmas, 1850s Style</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JANET McCONNAUGHEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW ORLEANS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Mahala Roach tried an innovation for
Christmas 1851.
   ``The children had such a number of gifts that I made a
Christmas tree for them; Mother, Aunt and Liz came down to see it;
All said it was something new to them,'' she wrote in her diary
that year. ``I never saw one but learned from some of the German
stories I had been reading.''
   She didn't describe the tree, but it probably looked something
like the little orange tree in the living room of the ``1850
House'' - the Louisiana State Museum's re-creation of a period
French Quarter apartment.
   ``People used what they had. Mostly either crepe myrtle or mock
orange,'' said Dot Mouton, who led a museum tour.
   Gilded nuts and apples hang from the branches along with lacy
handkerchiefs, a paper doll, a top, a ring, a necklace, a tiny
stuffed bear, small red and gold paper cornucopias, and a few small
wrapped boxes.
   The gilded nuts might have held small gifts.
   ``A lot of people don't realize that the nut was a surprise. You
might have a nut or you might have a little gift,'' said Claire
Conlin, a former history professor who researched Christmases past
for the museum. ``Of course, that was a walnut because it was
easier to glue back together.''
   Most gifts weren't wrapped.
   ``Wrapping wasn't important until the end of the century,'' said
Mrs. Conlin. She said the famous Swedish opera star Jenny Lind,
during a Christmas stay in North Carolina, wrapped her gifts as a
joke.
   Instead of wrapping the presents to keep them secret, they were
kept hidden until the tree was decorated - and children weren't
allowed into the parlor with the Christmas tree until the day they
got their presents.
   In addition to toys around the base of the tree, there also is a
pitcher and sponge.
   ``You notice the candles for lighting on the tree. There would
be a servant at the tree all the time in case of fire,'' said Ms.
Mouton.
   Mahala Eggleston Roach was from Vicksburg, Miss., rather than
from New Orleans, but the customs were the same, said Mrs. Conlin.
She said Mrs. Roach's diary was used because it had so many
Christmas entries.
   ``I've researched a number of places in the South. ... I've also
researched in Chicago during the same period. ... The customs were
very much the same,'' she said.
   One entry in the diary shows that Christmas stockings weren't
hung only for children.
   ``I found in my stockings a beautiful gold cross, a pair of
Etruscan sleeve buttons and two bottles of wine on the table,''
Mrs. Roach wrote in 1860.
   And yes, she probably did hang up both of her stockings.
   ``They seem to have hung up more than one stocking. Even in
sketches, if there are two children in bed, there seem to be four
stockings hung up,'' said Mrs. Conlin.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0033 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 1520EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Bangladesh     12-23 0359</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bangladesh,0404</SECOND>
<HEAD>Students Demand Immediate Trial of Ershad</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By HASSAN SAEED</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DHAKA, Bangladesh (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   More than 1,000 chanting students
marched through the streets of Dhaka on Sunday, demanding the
immediate trial of deposed President Hussain Muhammad Ershad and
his associates, witnesses said.
   ``Ershad must be tried immediately!'' the demonstrators chanted.
   Ershad, a former army general who seized power in a bloodless
coup eight years ago, stepped down Dec. 6 following nearly two
months of often violent street protests.
   In the port city of Chittagong, meanwhile, groups of rival
students fought each other with bombs, revolvers and sticks,
injuring more than 50, police and witnesses said. They said
students also looted and ransacked at least 30 shops in the city.
   Many of those demonstrating Sunday in Dhaka were students from
Dhaka University and had been at the forefront of the drive to oust
Ershad. The former president was put under house arrest Dec. 12,
but has not yet been charged.
   The caretaker government of acting President Shahabuddin Ahmed
also ordered the arrests of three top Ershad aides: Vice President
Madud Ahmed, Deputy Prime Minister Shah Moazzem and Home Minister
Mahmudul Hassan.
   On Friday, police arrested former Industries Secretatry Mosharaf
Hossain and his wife, Zeenat. Police are looking for 11 more top
former officials.
   A student leader, Khairul Kabir Khokhon, warned that there were
still enough pro-Ershad officials in the government to hinder the
country's ransition from dictatorship to democracy. He said the
government must rid itself of all military and civil officials
associated with Ershad's rule.
   The students said they would hold nationwide demonstrations Dec.
26 to press for the trial of Ershad and his associates.
   Witnesses said the clashes in Chittagong erupted when supporters
of the All Party Students Action Committee attacked two colleges to
avenge the beating Saturday of their supporters by members of the
Islami Chattra Shibir, or Islamic Students Organization.
   More than 100 students and at least 30 teachers were injured in
clashes between the two rival groups Saturday.
   Saturday's clashes began when members of the Islamic Students
Organization -which had been agitating for the removal of the
university's vice chancellor - beat up students attending classes.
   A senior police official in Chittagong said on condition of
anonymity that members of the two rival groups were moving around
the city with weapons and sticks.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0034 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 1522EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ElderlyBeatings     12-23 0351</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Elderly Beatings,0412</SECOND>
<HEAD>Six Beaten at Home for Elderly by Pipe-Wielding, Bible-Toting
Attacker</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Emanu-el cq in last graf</NOTE>
<DATELINE>DALLAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Bible-toting assailant broke into a home for
elderly Jewish people Saturday night and attacked six residents
with a pipe, but officials discounted bigotry as a motive for the
assault.
   Police said he made no anti-Semitic comments during or after the
attack, and a Jewish leader said the man simply appeared to be a
``deranged individual.''
   One man and five women, ranging in age from 76 to 90, from the
Golden Acres Home for Jewish Aged were taken to Baylor University
Medical Center. Five of the injured were discharged Sunday, with
one woman remaining for observation, said hospital administrator
Wilbur B. Smith.
   Two of the six suffered concussions, said hospital spokeswoman
Nancy Rhodes. The others had cuts and bruises. Names weren't
released.
   ``They really are basically very stable and doing OK,'' she
said.
   Police said the attacker, in his early 20s, broke into the
255-resident nursing home shortly before 9 p.m. by smashing the
glass of the front door. Carrying a Bible and a four-foot section
of pipe, he went to a second-floor recreation room, where the six
residents were sitting, and beat them.
   ``He told them not to be fearful,'' said Herbert Shore, the
home's retired administrator who rushed there after hearing of the
attack.
   Police were unsure of the man's identity Sunday, saying he had
given thm several names. He was taken to Parkland Memorial
Hospital, authorities said.
   ``He was acting alone and may have been deranged as far as we
can tell,'' Shore said.
   Police said the man would be charged with six counts of
aggravated assault or injury to an elderly person. Both are
felonies.
   ``Clearly, it's a horrible act by what seems, at this hour, to
be a deranged individual,'' said Mark Briskman, regional director
of the B'nai B'rith Anti-Defamation League.
   ``I think it's more random than targeted,'' Briskman said after
talking to police. ``You're talking about a guy who is high on
something. You're talking about an individual, not a group of
individuals.''
   But, he added, ``It is absolutely shocking and despicable if
(the elderly) were targeted because it was a Jewish facility.''
   Rabbi Sheldon Zimmerman of Temple Emanu-el said the nursing home
tightened security a couple of years ago after threats from
skinheads who espouse white supremacist and anti-Semitic views.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0035 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 1525EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Albania     12-23 0440</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Albania,0509</SECOND>
<HEAD>Trials of Rioters Were Fair, Legal Officials Say</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ALISON SMALE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TIRANA, Albania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Legal officials on Sunday responded to
international criticism over harsh sentences meted out to
anti-government rioters, saying the trials were open and all
defendents had access to defense lawyers.
   The officials, in interviews with the state ATA news agency,
also said investigations against some suspects had been suspended
for lack of evidence, while others whose cases went to trial were
found innocent.
   On Saturday, 12,000 Albanians gathered for the first legal
opposition rally, shouting demands for the release of political
prisoners and more reform in their until recently Stallinist land.
   Chants of ``Freedom!'' alternated with cries of ``Democracy!''
and ``We want Albania to be like Europe!'' at the one-hour rally
held in Tirana's Students' City. Speakers also demanded press
freedom.
   Student protests about slum-like dormitories there swelled two
weeks ago into demands for democracy and helped force the ruling
Communists to allow opposition parties.
   Riots erupted in mid-December. Thousands of angry protesters
burned and ransacked stores and other buildings in several cities
including Durres on the coast and Shkodra in the north.
   Nearly 200 of the hundreds arrested went on trial Dec. 19. One
of the more than a dozen sentenced a day later received a 20-year
prison term, while others received 15 years, leading to criticism
from human rights organizations abroad.
   ATA quoted Franc Jakova, and Rustem Syziu, chairmen of the
barristers' college in Shkodra and in Durres as saying all had
defense lawywers at request and free of charge.
   ``The trials have been conducted ... with open doors and the
advocates have performed their duty in defense of the accused
...,'' ATA quoted the two as saying.
   In Durres, 11 cases had been suspended by Sunday and ``some of
the accused are declared innocent,'' they said, according to ATA,
which suggested the trials were continuing.
   The official trade union declared its independence from the
ruling Albanian Labor Party Saturday, in another move documenting
the Communist authorities new tolerance.
   Genc Resuli, head of the union's International Department, said
the labor group pledged to work for higher pay and better working
conditions, including a cut in the work week from six to five days.
   Life in Albania' obsolete factories is said to be abysmal. Many
Albanians complain that rising food prices mean they struggle to
get by on wages averaging $50 a month.
   Resuli said he expected the right to strike to be included in a
new constitution being worked out by a group headed by President
and Communist Party leader Ramiz Alia.
   The union was supportive, however, of the leadership's crackdown
on the rioters despite its independence declaration, ATA reported
Sunday.
   Union head Sotir Kocollari cited a report by his organization
that ``expressed the indignation for the actions of diversion,
plunder and destruction committed by some people,'' during the
riots, said ATA.
   The union approved the rioters' sentences, the news agency said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0036 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 1532EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-Saudi-Religion     12-23 0611</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Saudi-Religion,0746</SECOND>
<HEAD>Since Gulf Crisis, Confrontations with Religious Police Rising</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By NEIL MacFARQUHAR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DHAHRAN, Saudi Arabia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A prominent family has demanded
floggings for four religious policemen who they say forced their
daughter's car off the road and roughed up the 20-year-old student
because they believed she was dressed immodestly.
   The incident is one of several indicating the rising tension
between Westernized Saudis and Islamic conservatives.
   ``The conservatives are reasserting their control,'' one Saudi
diplomat said on condition of anonymity. Issues that link religion
and politics are highly sensitive in the kingdom and no sources
wanted to be quoted by name.
   The rigid Moslems say they are enforcing Islamic laws as
founding prophet Mohammed would have wanted. They are especially
vigilant in enforcing the ban on alcohol and socializing between
the sexes as well as enforcing modest dress for women, which they
interpret as head-to-toe covering.
   Formally known as committees for Encouraging Virture and
Preventing Vice, the police are usually called muttawiin, or
volunteers. They reject wearing bands around their headscarves, as
many Saudis do, as unnecessary adornment. They wear short thobes,
as the Saudi men's robe is called, and some carrylong thin camel
prods.
   The sources said the government, concentrating its forces on the
confrontation with Iraqi President Saddam Hussein, does not want
tension over social issues.
   ``In this kind of environment the last thing the ruling family
wanted to do was start experimenting with society's traditions,'' a
Western diplomat said.
   The government has tried to calm the religious elements that
have criticized the influx of hundreds of thousands of foreign
troops to defend the kingdom since Iraq's Aug. 2 invasion of
Kuwait.
   And in an attempt to diffuse the situation, the government
recently appointed Dr. Abdul Aziz ibn Abdulrahman Al-Saeed
president of the religious police. Al-Saeed was educated at the
Al-Azhar University - the oldest Islamic university - known for
encouraging debate on Islamic Issues.
   Al-Saeed told the Okaz newspaper that the worst excesses of the
religious police would be curbed, but he said the force would be
more active.
   ``They should deal with people nicely and argue with them for
the better, as the Koran prescribes,'' he said, referring to the
holy book of Islam.
   In the latest incident Thursday, the daughter of a prominent
Riyadh family had just left a tennis game in the diplomatic
quarter. She was riding in the car with two foreign maids and a
Sudanese driver, family members said.
   Religious police in another car signaled them to pull over, but
the girl told the driver to dash for home.
   The muttawiin bashed into the car repeatedly in a freeway chase
over several miles, forcing the car to stop.
   When the four would not open their doors, the police - aged 16
to 22 - smashed the windows and hauled out the driver. They pulled
the maids' hair and then tussled with the girl when she tried to
prevent them from driving the car.
   They called her names and accused her of immodest dress and
wearing make-up. The family said her hair was covered and she was
not wearing cosmetics.
   The traffic police interceded and summoned the girl's brothers.
   Under Islamic law, when a girl is unjustly insulted in public
her family has the right to ask for retribution and they asked for
80 lashes.
   Riyadh Governor Prince Salman ordered the four men jailed while
the investigation is under way, the family said.
   A November protest in which 40 women defied the traditional ban
on women driving by taking to the highways of Riyadh proved a
rallying cry among conservatives.
   Religious police have since stationed themselves outside the
diplomatic quarter, near upscale shopping centers and women's
universities. The number of confrontations has jumped markedly and
a few have involved members of the royal family - unheard of
previously.
   Foreign women have had their cars stopped and been jailed
overnight, allegedly for not covering their heads, diplomats said.
   The religious police raided a diplomatic party in Riyadh in
November and their rough treatment of guests prompted an official
protest.
   In late November, police climbed over walls into the villa of a
rich perfume manufacturer in Jiddah where a party involving liquor
and single women was under way. An Islamic judge handed down
sentences of up to two years.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0037 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 1550EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Romania     12-23 0274</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania,0289</SECOND>
<HEAD>Police Scatter Anti-Government Protesters</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BUCHAREST, Romania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Riot police Sunday charged about 200
anti-government demonstrators in the capital, but most of the
protesters regrouped later.
   Other small protests were reported in several other Romanian
cities. There were no reports of serious injuries anywhere.
   A day earlier, about 1,000 anti-government demonstrators rallied
in Bucharest as government officials commemorated the first
anniversary of the fall of Communist dictator Nicolae Ceausescu.
   On Sunday, demonstrators in Bucharest's University Square fled
after several dozen police in riot gear rushed them. The police
charged after a car sped through the crowd and grazed one of the
demonstrators. It was not clear who was in the car.
   Anti-government protests have been growing since President Ion
Iliescu and the National Salvation Front government of Premier
Petre Roman overwhelmingly won democratic elections in May.
   Reforms aimed at moving toward a market economy have driven up
prices, and basic goods are often unavailable, causing widespread
dissatisfaction.
   Also, many Romanians believe Iliescu, who was once a minister
under Ceausescu, and other government officials have not broken
with the authoritarian policies of the past government.
   More than 100,000 students and hundreds of professors across the
nation are symbolically continuing a boycott of classes through
winter vacation. Their anti-government protest began in
mid-December, before winter break began.
   Navigators of the state airline Tarom have been on strike for
higher wages for more than a week, paralyzing all internal flights
and stranding hundreds of international travelers.
   Ceausescu fled on Dec. 22, 1989, as hundreds of thousands of
people were gathering to demand the end of his 24-year rule. He and
his wife were captured and executed Dec. 25.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0038 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 1553EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Germany-ChristmasFren     12-23 0490</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Germany-Christmas Frenzy,0590</SECOND>
<HEAD>Christmas Shopping at Full Tilt in Unified Germany</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Toyless Christmas, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KEVIN COSTELLOE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Never mind the slow Christmas sales in the United
States and Britain. German merchants are enjoying a holiday boom,
fueled by 16.6 million eastern Germans hungry for consumer products
after decades of deprivation.
   Shoppers have been standing a dozen deep at German cash
registers this Christmas season, elbowing and pushing their way to
snatch up everything from expensive video recorders to chocolate
Santas.
   In a weekend report, the German retailers' association estimated
Christmas sales in the united Germany at $18 billion. Nearly 70
percent of the stores surveyed reported sales were up this
Christmas season compared with last year, although no percentage of
increase was given.
   There is ``an overwhelmingly positive mood in the retail
stores,'' the Association of German Retailers said.
   Overall retail sales in Germany for the entire year are expected
to reach $465 billion, up a hefty 12 percent from 1989. The annual
figure will be a post-war record.
   The figures tell only part of the story. Beyond that are packed
stores, harried sales clerks and streets filled with shoppers.
   In downtown Berlin, shoppers from eastern Germany and Eastern
Europe are snapping up everything in sight.
   ``We don't have it,'' say sales clerks fielding dozens of
demands. ``Oh, that's been sold out for a long time.''
   Watches, computer and electronics products and toys are the
leading sellers. Jewelry and other big-ticket items are often in
hot demand as well.
   Berlin's grocery stores are having a hard time keeping supplies
in stock of Christmas baking staples such as almonds and raisins.
   Berlin's Tagesspiegel newspaper said Sunday the city was
enjoying ``the sales of a century.''
   The Tagesspiegel reported that Berlin would see a 30 percent
jump in sales compared with last year. That would be a
record-breaking increase.
   Richard Hennig, the manager of one huge Hertie department store,
told the newspaper that ``hardly any department'' has been left out
of the Christmas sales rush.
   Just how long the good times in Germany can go on remains to be
seen. Recessions are looming in the United States and Britain, two
of Germany's big export markets.
   Many financial experts are predicting an overall economic
slowdown next year, as the full costs of German unification hit the
country's manufacturers and consumers. The countries reunited on
Oct. 3.
   But for now, the buying frenzy is unabated.
   In Berlin's far western section of Staaken, close to former East
Germany, a mother went to a Woolworth store back in November to
search for a Barbie doll accessory for her daughter's Christmas
stocking.
   ``We don't have that because all the people from eastern Germany
are coming over and buying everything up,'' the store clerk said as
he dashed from one customer to another.
   Store detectives are being kept busy, too, by an increase in
shoplifting. A sign in the window of one store in Berlin's Spandau
district said the rise in theft had been ``catastrophic.''
   The demand is also swamping the huge German mail-order houses,
which pride themselves on promptly filling customers' orders.
   Some customers of the Otto catalogue store have been getting
letters saying that the high number of orders ``from East and
West'' have slowed delivery. The house said that as a result, it
could not keep its usual promise of deliveries in time for
Christmas.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0039 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 1558EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-Charles     12-23 0263</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Charles,0309</SECOND>
<HEAD>Prince Charles' Visit is Christmastime Boost for British Troops</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By EDITH M. LEDERER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>IN EASTERN SAUDI ARABIA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Prince Charles climbed into the
high-tech cockpit of a British Tornado jet Sunday and said he'd
love to go for a ride someday, but that he was probably getting too
old.
   The 42-year-old heir to the British throne, who flew with a
Phantom jet squadron in the early 1970s, ran into two members of
his old Royal Air Force unit during a pre-Christmas visit to
British units at an airbase in eastern Saudi Arabia.
   ``It's a Christmas boost for all the troops. We tend to feel a
little bit forgotten out here,'' said Flight Lt. Alan Whyte, 30,
who was with 29 Squadron, the prince's old unit, before switching
from Phantoms to Tornados.
   Wing Commander Andy Moir, 44, who is two years older than the
prince and still flying Tornados, had a short message for him:
``We're prepared and confident.''
   He sat on the edge of the two-seat interceptor as Charles
checked out the aircraft, which has been training to do lower-level
intercepts in tandem with U.S. F-15s.
   The Tornado was armed with four Sidewinder heat-seeking missiles
and four Skyflash radar-guided missiles. A red sign at the entrance
to the hangar said: ``Danger Aircraft Armed.''
   Asked whether he'd like to go for a ride in a Tornado, Charles
smiled and said: ``One day, yes. I think I'm getting too old for
this.''
   Charles said the British airmen and pilots from the 43rd Fighter
Squadron were ``very pleased'' with the cooperation they've gotten
from the Americans.
   ``I wanted to find out how these characters are getting on,''
the prince said after climbing down a flight of movable stairs from
the cockpit. ``They're doing a marvelous job, as always.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0040 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 1606EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BadChoice     12-23 0194</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bad Choice,0218</SECOND>
<HEAD>Car Thieves Nabbed Trying to Steal Undercover Police Van</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LAKELAND, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Of all the cars and trucks in the shopping
mall's parking lot on one of the year's busiest shopping days, a
quartet of would-be car thieves picked on a police surveillance
van.
   ``It was hard to keep from laughing,'' Mike Link, one of three
officers hiding in the back of the van Saturday when one of the
group climbed inside and turned the key.
   The would-be thief was grabbed from behind by a Lakeland police
officer and arrested with his buddies.
   ``He was definitely surprised, because he screamed a lot,'' said
Link.
   The van was part of a special unit, including foot patrols and
undercover cars, dispatched to the Lakeland Square mall to combat
holiday-related parking lot crime.
   Undercover officers first spotted the four suspects walking
through the lot and flipping up door handles. They approached the
van and were about to break in but too many shoppers were nearby,
Link said.
   The thieves moved on to a neighboring strip mall. The police
followed in the 1985 Chevrolet van.
   This time, one of the teen-agers got in, turned the key, and was
nabbed.
   The charges against the four included grand theft and resisting
arrest.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0041 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 1616EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Morocco-Trials     12-23 0158</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Morocco-Trials,0162</SECOND>
<HEAD>At Least 191 To Be Tried This Week in Moroccan Violence</HEAD>
<DATELINE>RABAT, Morocco (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   At least 191 people arrested for taking
part in violent protests this month are to be tried Monday and
Tuesday in Rabat, Fez, Tangier and Kenitra.
   They face charges of rioting, disobedience and disturbing public
order.
   On Friday, 39 people were sentenced in Tangier to jail terms
ranging from two to four months for their part in the riots that
killed at least five people, according to the government's account.
Eleven of the sentences were suspended.
   Labor unions and human rights officials say more than 30 people
died.
   Violence flared Dec. 14 when a general strike called by
disaffected workers and unions degenerated into widespread looting
and arson, most of it apparently committed by people not involved
in the strike.
   The government later pledged to raise workers' salaries, improve
social benefits and conduct an investigation into the violence.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0042 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 1620EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Right-To-Die     12-23 0385</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Right-To-Die,0477</SECOND>
<HEAD>Nancy Cruzan's Father: She Would Want To Die</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MOUNT VERNON, Mo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Nancy Cruzan's parents say they'll face
a difficult adjustment after their daughter's death but welcome an
end to her nearly eight years in a vegetative state.
   The 33-year-old woman remained in deteriorating condition
Sunday, 10 days after a judge allowed her parents to order her
feeding tube removed. Doctors say her condition, brought on by a
1983 traffic accident, is irreversible.
   ``The future right now is a great big question mark,'' her
father, Joe Cruzan said in an interview published Sunday by The
Joplin Globe.
   ``It will be extremely difficult to cope with the transition
after eight years of constant stress when the first thing you do is
to come home and check the mail and the message machine,'' he said.
``It's like coming into a different land.''
   The father urged anti-euthanasia activists camping in freezing
temperatures outside the southwestern Missouri hospital to pray for
his daughter.
   ``I think we should concentrate our prayer on God's will for
Nancy. If he wants her to be healed, he will heal her,'' he said.
``If not, that he will make her death quick and painless.''
   His wife, Joyce Cruzan, said it's time to let go.
   ``At least we'll know Nancy's at peace,'' the mother said.
``Somewhere out there Nancy's still tied to this body by a thread.
We are going to snip that thread and then she will be completely
free.''
   Mrs. Cruzan said her daughter's condition has not changed much
since the nutrition and hydration was stopped Dec. 14: ``We haven't
seen a lot of change; her face may be a little thinner.''
   Doctors have said she likely will die this week. With a feeding
tube, they said, she could have stayed alive another 30 or 40
years.
   A candlelight vigil was held Saturday night at the Lawrence
County jail for protesters arrested Tuesday when they tried to
reach Ms. Cruzan's room. They were released late Saturday,
sheriff's officials said.
   Joe Cruzan told the newspaper that if his daughter could make
the decision, she would reject attempts to keep her alive.
   ``There are people on this floor right here, terminal cancer
patients, whoif they don't want their food, are not force-fed,''
he said. ``I have never had anyone tell me they would like to live
like this.''
   Various courts last week denied attempts by by anti-euthanasia
activists to force the state to resume feeding Ms. Cruzan.
   The Rev. Patrick J. Mahoney, a Protestant minister who runs the
Center for Christian Activism in Boca Raton, Fla., asked the 8th
U.S. Circuit Court of Appeals in St. Louis on Saturday to reconnect
Ms. Cruzan's feeding tube.
   The appeals court has not set a date to hear Mahoney's petition.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0043 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 1624EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Lebanon-Christmas     12-23 0610</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lebanon-Christmas,0783</SECOND>
<HEAD>With New Hopes For Peace, Christmas is Again Celebrated In Beirut</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MOHAMMED SALAM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BEIRUT, Lebanon (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Omar, a Moslem taxi driver, dons his red
Santa Claus suit and fluffy white beard every morning to deliver a
toy store's Christmas gifts in Moslem west Beirut.
   Lebanon, with 17 known religious sects, once observed all
religious holidays. But that tolerance died amid the bloodletting
of nearly 16 years of civil war.
   Christmas celebrations were further muted in 1985, when
pro-Iranian Shiite fundamentalist gunmen cracked down on
``un-Islamic activities.''
   Now, with new efforts to end the civil war, the city's Christian
areas are again celebrating the holiday, and the Moslem sector is
joining in.
   Christmas carols echo through the Hamra commercial district of
Moslem west Beirut, Christmas trees and other festive decorations
are up in the streets just as they are in the eastern Christian
sector.
   Omar - that's the only name he would give - has been hired by
toy shop owner Fawziya Makkouk, a Moslem woman.
   He said he found nothing strange in delivering toys to Moslem as
well as Christian children to celebrate a Christian ritual.
   ``I like children,'' said Omar, who has three of his own. ``I
like making them happy. By delivering the toys I also make some
money. I also get some toys free for my kids.''
   Even now, it's not all sweetness and light. Political rivalries
remain, and the future is uncertain in a city wrecked by war.
   Municipal electricity is rationed to three hours a day because
of battle damage. Garbage is piled up at street corners. Whole
blocks of the city are in ruins.
   And there's real economic hardship after years of fighting, so
most people don't have much to spare for Christmas.
   But for now at least, the fundamentalists of Hezbollah, or Party
of God, and other Christian and Moslem militias have gone.
   Gone too is the Green Line, the forbidding, fortified
demarcation line between Moslem west Beirut and the eastern
Christian sector. It had run like a jagged scar through the city
since civil war erupted in April 1975.
   The militias have pulled out of the capital under an effort by
President Elias Hrawi to end the conflict in which an estimated
150,000 people were killed. The Lebanese Army has moved back in to
restore long-absent law and order.
   There is widespread optimism that Hrawi, backed by the Syrians,
will be able to succeed in bringing peace despite the repeated
failures of similar efforts in the past.
   Most Beirutis are praying that the violence is behind them and
that Christmas will help bring the Lebanese together again.
   For Ghassan Abdallah, a liberal Shiite Moslem businessmen, this
year's celebration is special. He has reserved a table at a
restauarant overlooking the Mediterranean in the Moslem sector for
a party ``with my Christian friends.''
   ``They stopped coming to west Beirut when Hezbollah got rough in
1985,'' he said in an interview. ``But this year we're going to
have a reunion.
   ``I hope the militias will be disbanded altogether so that we
can get rid of them once and for all,'' Abdallah said.
   ``We're not scared of the militias any more,'' said Bassam
Itani, the Sunni Moslem owner of a toy shop in west Beirut's Zarif
district.
   ``Greater Beirut's now under army control and we're really
relaxed. The fundamentalists can't threaten us any more.''
   Mrs. Makkouk, whose store in the Moslem Zaydaniyeh district,
said last year, she hadn't dared to have a Santa in her shop.
   She said business was good now, but pointed to the constant
dwindlind of the Lebanese pound, once the Middle East's most stable
currency.
   The pound was pegged at $2.50 when the war broke out in 1975. On
Friday, it was 890 pounds to the dollar on Beirut's money market.
   Store owners said that a small plastic Christmas tree costs the
equivalent of $25, a set of decorations another $15 and a ``humble
gift'' at least $10.
   ``That adds up to the minimum monthly salary decreed by the
government,'' Mrs. Makkouk said. ``Not many people can afford
that.''
   The currency slide has sent prices sky high in Lebanon, which
imports more than 85 percent of its goods.
   ``This morning a little boy came to me with 800 pounds, which
was the equivalent of $1 yesterday,'' Mrs. Makkouk said. ``He
wanted to buy a toy car. The price last week was 800 pounds because
the dollar was worth that. But now it's changed. I couldn't sell
the toy.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0044 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 1625EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Lebanon-Government     12-23 0560</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lebanon-Government,0643</SECOND>
<HEAD>Lebanon's Premier-Designate Facing Difficulties</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RIMA SALAMEH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BEIRUT, Lebanon (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Prime Minister-designate Omar Karami is
having difficulty forming a national reconciliation government
charged with ending 15 years of civil war.
   The Phalange Party, the biggest right-wing Christian political
force in Lebanon, has joined the nation's main Christian militia in
refusing to participate in Karami's projected cabinet.
   The move dampened Karami's chances of quickly forming a
broad-based new government to replace that of Prime Minister Salim
Hoss, who resigned with his 14-man cabinet on Thursday.
   Both the Phalangists as well as Christian warlord Samir Geagea's
Lebanese Forces militia claim Karami plans to bring in more
pro-Syrian Christians than right-wingers.
   ``Those potential members of the cabinet do not represent the
Christian community. Their wide presence in the cabinet creates an
imbalance in favor of the Moslems,'' said a Phalangist statement
published Sunday.
   ``Such a government will murder reconciliation rather than bring
it about,'' the statement said.
   It was alluding to Elie Hobeika, Geagea's main Syrian-backed
Maronite Catholic rival, and Assad Hardan, a senior official of the
Syrian Social Nationalist Party.
   The party is a secular Lebanese leftist faction that advocates
the merger of Lebanon, Syria, Iraq, Jordan, pre-Israel Palestine,
Kuwait and Cyprus in a greater Syria.
   Syria, the main power broker in Lebanon, has 40,000 troops in
Lebanon under a 1976 peacekeeping mandate from the Arab League.
   Geagea's Lebanese Forces has charged that a cabinet made up of
30 politicians and warlords as President Elias Hrawi and Karami
envisage would be ``a Tower of Babel.''
   The militia also contended that Karami lacked the statesmanship
and national prestige that the U.S.-educated Hoss enjoyed as a
veteran of Lebanese politics for the past 14 years.
   Karami, 55, a Sunni Moslem, surfaced on the political stage only
three years ago, when he inherited the leadership of the northern
provincial capital of Tripoli from his elder brother, the late
Prime Minister Rashid Karami.
   The elder Karami, the longest serving prime minister in
Lebanon's 47 years of independence, was assassinated by a bomb
explosion aboard an army helicopter in north Lebanon June 1, 1987.
   One of Lebanon's three strongest militias, the Iranian-backed
Shiite Moslem fundamentalist Hezbollah, or Party of God, has also
refused to join Karami's government.
   ``The new government is certain to lack the vision and the
minimum degree of harmony required to resolve the nation's woes,''
a Hezbollah statement said.
   Another major militia, Druse warlord Walid Jumblatt's
Progressive Socialist Party, has earlier expressed reservations
about the government change.
   That party predicted Karami's cabinet would be an ``untidy
government that would stumble upon its first steps. This could
create a dangerous power vacuum.''
   The new government, when formed, faces the task of disbanding
the various warring militias and enforcing an Arab League-brokered
peace plan that parliament ratified Aug. 22.
   It also is expected to map out a plan for reconstructing
war-ravaged Beirut and shoring up the economy.
   The new government must also fill 31 vacancies in the
one-chamber parliament by appointment and raise the number of its
seats from 99 to 108 to attain equality between Moslems and
Christians as envisaged by the peace plan.
   Christians have had a 6-to-5 edge in parliament since
independence from France in 1943.
   The present parliament was elected in 1972 for a four-year term.
The civil war, which broke out in 1975, has prevented elections and
the house has repeatedly renewed its mandate.
   Government troops reunited civil war-divided Beirut Dec. 3 by
deploying in the capital and its environs, as a first step in
putting the peace accord into effect.
   The peaceful deployment followed withdrawal of the various
militias from the capital to their respective areas of influence in
north, east and south Lebanon.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0045 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 1628EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>d a AM-BRF--DonationDeclined     12-23 0173</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Donation Declined,0188</SECOND>
<HEAD>Topless Club's Gift Gets Cold Shoulder From Shelter</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DALLAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A homeless mission turned down a $600 gift from a
topless club, saying that accepting the donation would do more harm
than good.
   ``We want people to be involved in giving, but I think the
message you send has to be a clear message,'' said William
Thompson, the Union Gospel Mission's executive director.
   ``It's kind of hypocritical for us to be teaching and preaching
to our guys about moral responsibility and a the same time taking
the benefits of people's moral irresponsibility.''
   Workers at the Dallas Gentleman's Club said they had just wanted
to do something nice.
   ``I just think that the spirit of giving ought to be offered to
everybody,'' club owner Randy Dumas said. ``I guess we were just a
little hurt that they looked down their noses at us.''
   In a letter to the club, Thompson wrote: ``We sincerely
appreciate your concern for the homeless in Dallas. However, the
Union Gospel Mission ministers not only to the physical needs, but
to the spiritual needs as well.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0046 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 1630EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Taiwan     12-23 0216</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Taiwan,0238</SECOND>
<HEAD>Taiwan To End State of War with China in May</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Cheyne in 1st graf correct</NOTE>
<DATELINE>TAIPEI, Taiwan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Nationalist government will formally
end in May a state of war it declared against the Chinese
Communists in 1948, according to presidential spokesman Cheyne
Chiu.
   Nationalist Chinese President Lee Teng-hui announced in his
inaugural speech last May he would declare an end to the state of
war, but he gave no date.
   On Saturday, Chiu said the state of war would end in May 1991.
He told the state-run Broadcasting Corp. of China the move is
expected to help efforts to reunify China and Taiwan.
   They have been separated since the Nationalists retreated to
this island in 1949 after losing a civil war to the Communists.
   Chiu said the Nationalists have no timetable to reunify China,
but ending the state of war will reinforce the government's
determination to achieve a peaceful reunification.
   He urged the Beijing government to respond favorably by
renouncing its threat to use force to reunify China and Taiwan
should other attempts fail.
   ``The Chinese Communists will never win the approval of the 20
million people here (for reunification) if they insist on using
force to resolve the problem across the Taiwan Strait,'' he said.
   Both Nationalists and Communists regard Taiwan as a Chinese
province. The Nationalists continue to regard themselves as China's
legitimate government.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0047 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 1630EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-CellularPhones     12-23 0453</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Cellular Phones,510</SECOND>
<NOTE>For release 6:30 p.m. EST</NOTE>
<HEAD>Cellular Will Reach All Areas of Nation in 18 Months, Officials
Say</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JAY ARNOLD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Cellular phone service should be available
nationwide by mid-1992 now that federal authorities have issued at
least one construction permit for systems in all urban and rural
areas, an industry trade group said Sunday.
   The Federal Communications Commission on Friday issued 20 new
permits, including Tunica County, Miss., and Kosciusko County,
Ind., the only two areas of the country in which cellular systems
had not been authorized, the Cellular Telecommunications Industry
Association said.
   ``We couldn't ask for a much better Christmas present,'' CTIA
President Robert W. Maher said. ``One of our industry's most
important goals is to provide ubiquitous service across America, so
that if you're traveling, you can use your phone anywhere. Building
these ... markets makes that dream a reality.''
   Cellular also will be a boon to those living in rural areas,
Maher added.
   The FCC has designated 306 metropolitan, or MSA, markets and 428
rural, or RSA, markets and said that two cellular operators may be
licensed in each market.
   All of the nation's MSA markets, which cover about 75 percent of
the population, has cellular service, the CTIA said. The 428 RSA
markets cover only about 25 percent of the population but span
about 80 percent of the nation's land mass. Of the 428 RSAs, about
150 have cellular service, the CTIA said.
   The FCC, through a lottery, awarded the last cellular licenses
in December 1989. It now is in the process of awarding construction
permits for the lottery winners, who then have 18 months to
activate their systems. Friday's permit awards assured that by
mid-1992, all areas of the nation should have at least one
operating cellular system.
   The cellular industry also plans to introduce within 12 months
to 18 months an automatic call delivery service that will allow
cellular users to receive calls automatically, no matter where they
are.
   Currently, callers seeking someone who has traveled away from
his or her local calling area must know where that person is in
order to complete a call. With automatic call delivery, a person
``roaming'' outside the home market will send out a locating signal
to the closest cellular system whenever he or she turns on the
cellular phone. Computers then will do the searching and service
authorizations.
   ``If you're up in Chicago and I'm back in Washington and all
I've got is your local Washington number, I'm going to be able to
dial that Washington number ... and that phone call i going to
find you ... anywhere in the United States,'' CTIA spokesman Norman
Black said.
   But before ``seamless roaming'' can be introduced in all areas,
the regional Bell companies will need to receive a waiver from a
1984 consent decree that limits what long-distance and computer
services the Bell companies may provide.
   In September, U.S. District Judge Harold Greene Greene issued a
limited waiver allowing Bell companies in some markets to introduce
``intersystem handoff'' so that callers traveling between some
cities will not have to hang up and dial again as they pass from
one cellular system to another.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0048 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 1637EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Wales-LastMine 1stLd-Writethru a0663 12-23 0614</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Wales-Last Mine, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0663,0814</SECOND>
<HEAD>Welch Miners Fear Hard Times As Region's Last Mine Closes</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: INSERTS one graf after 7th pvs, `The stark..' with details.
Pick up 8th graf, `The local...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT BARR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MAERDY, Wales (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   When Ivor Jones went into the coal mine in
1926, there were four pits operating in Maerdy, and 52 others in
the surrounding Rhondda valleys.
   At 78, he saw the last one close this week, and 280 men lose
their jobs. Twenty others accepted mining jobs elsewhere.
   ``It's a sad bloody moment, this pit closing,'' Jones said as
the last shifts were being worked at the Maerdy colliery.
   ``I went to the soup kitchens when I was 9 years of age. I saw
hard times and depressions. I'm afraid now that it's going to start
all over again,'' he said.
   Work stopped on Thursday. On Friday, Maerdy's miners and their
families marched to the pit behind a brass band, their lodge banner
fluttering damply in the drizzle, to dedicate a plaque to their
mine and a nearly vanished way of life.
   It was a quiet defeat for a town once known as ``little
Moscow,'' where miners flew the red flag at the pit head in the
1920s.
   ``The stark reality is that 300 men, mostly with families, with
an average age of 34, are losing their jobs at Christmas time,''
said the Rev. Norman Hadfield, a former miner who conducted a
memorial service.
   Miners received severance pay based on their length of service,
in some cases exceeding $60,000.
   The local district council and the government-sponsored Welsh
Development Authority are already working on new industries for
Maerdy, but the results may be years away.
   The WDA says it has created more than 700 jobs close to Maerdy,
and a new business park has opened in Ferndale, two miles
downstream. That hasn't lifted the gloom felt by some miners.
   ``There are no prospects for me in another job at the moment,''
said Mike L'Homme, who was losing his job after 10 years.
   ``Very few men have found new jobs to go to and families face a
bleak time here because there isn't any work in the Rhondda,'' said
Eric Price, a miner since 1963.
   Unemployment in Wales is 6.7 percent, compared to 6.0 percent in
Britain as a whole, but it's two points higher in the mid-Glamorgan
region, including the Rhondda valleys.
   South Wales has seen worse. In the general strike of 1926, the
Trade Union Congress gave up after nine days; the miners stayed out
from May until December, at last nearly starved back to work. In
the 1930s, unemployment exceeded 70 percent in some valleys.
   ``When I was working up there, there wasn't even a road to the
mine,'' said Jones, who started mining in 1926. ``You'd walk up the
railroad track in all kinds of weather - hail, snow, whatever -
then you went down in the pit soaking wet, and there was no
protective clothing.
   ``And then if there was an accident, the men had to carry them
down on a stretcher.''
   Jones' son Alun, also a retired miner, sipped pints of bitter in
the Miners' Institute as his father talked.
   ``That pit closing is ripping the guts out of me,'' the son
said.
   In 1913, South Wales produced a third of the world's coal
exports and had 485 working mines.
   The valleys also produced leaders: Arthur Horner, a founder of
the National Union of Mineworkers, was a Maerdy man; Aneurin Bevan,
a Labor Cabinet minister in the 1940s, and the Labor Party's
current leader, Neil Kinnock, both came from nearby Tredegar.
   Mining employment peaked at 272,000 in 1920, and in 1923 the
mines produced 52.25 million tons. By the mid-1930s, production and
employment fell by more than half.
   As late as 1958 there were a dozen working mines in the Rhondda.
Since 1969, there was only Maerdy.
   Maerdy is a grim little town at the head of the narrow valley of
Rhondda Fach, or little Rhondda. At this time of year the sun slips
below the ridge separating it from Rhondda Fawr before 3 p.m.
   Whatever wealth was made in Maerdy, little of it stayed. The
only big building is the Miner's Institute, built in 1905.
   The basic home is a two-story stone row house, two windows wide,
standing row on row up the western side of the valley.
   Backed against greening mountains of rubble, the town evokes
``The Angry Summer,'' a poem about the general strike by Idris
Davies, born three valleys east in Rhymney:
   ``Great are the shadows over the Rhondda
   ``And the mansions built in the shires,
   ``Great are the fortunes made in Gwalia
   ``And the promontories of slag.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0049 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 1638EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-GCCSummit     12-23 0342</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-GCC Summit,0394</SECOND>
<HEAD>Oman Urges Dialogue Before Any Military Stike</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ALY MAHMOUD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DOHA, Qatar (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Oman pressed Sunday for a dialogue with Iraq
before any military strike, but one official insisted the small
state was not breaking with its Persian Gulf allies.
   Official sources at the summit of the six-nation Gulf
Cooperation Council said the Omanis were contending more peace
avenues should be explored before using military force. The
three-day gathering opened Saturday.
   ``This does not mean that the Omanis are opposed to the
consensus that the Iraqi leader should be disciplined forcefully,''
said one official, who spoke on condition of anonymity. ``The
Omanis are partners in the multinational force assembled in eastern
Saudi Arabia to deal with the Iraqis if necessary.''
   The U.N. Security Council has authorized use of military force
to dislodge Iraq if it has not withdrawn from Kuwait by Jan. 15.
   Saudi Arabia and Kuwait, also members of the council, have
insisted there will be no dialogue with Baghdad before the Iraqis
pull out of Kuwait unconditionally and the ruling al-Sabah family
is reinstated.
   The Kuwait government-in-exile has indicated it would be willing
to discuss oil, money and land disputes with Iraq after a full
withdrawal, but has said it will not cede any territory.
   ``The GCC leaders are set against rewarding the aggressor with
any concessions,'' Qatar Foreign Minister Mubarak al-Khater said
earlier. ``They will not engage in any dialogue or hold any
negotiations with the Iraqi leader before his forces are completely
withdrawn from Kuwait.''
   Leaders at the summit were King Fhad of Saudi Arabia; Jaber
al-Ahmed al-Sabah of Kuwait; Khalifa bin Hamad Al Thani of Qatar;
Zayed bin Sultan Al Nahyan of the United Arab Emirates and Sultan
Qaboos of Oman. The sixth member, Bahrain, was represented by Prime
Minister Khalifa bin Salman Al Khalifa.
   Alliance sources said Oman warned that the region was headed for
war, and urged that dialogue and economic sanctions be given a
chance.
   Kuwait at one point urged its Gulf Cooperation Council allies to
break off diplomatic relations with Iraq, but the other members
said it was important to maintain lines of communication.
   The alliance countries, whose economic and security group was
born in 1981, have a joint force of 10,000 troops based in
northeastern Saudi Arabia.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0050 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 1651EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-Fatalities     12-23 0552</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Fatalities,0730</SECOND>
<HEAD>Fatalities in Operation Desert Shield</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NICOSIA, Cyprus (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Seventy-eight American military personnel
have died since Operation Desert Shield began Aug. 7, most of them
in air crashes and accidents. Twenty-one drowned when a ferry sank
off Israel. Two were suicides. Here is a list of the fatal
incidents:
   ---
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Dec. 22 - A soldier was killed in Saudi Arabia when the truck he
was riding in overturned.
   Dec. 22 - Twenty-one sailors from the aircraft carrier USS
Saratoga drowned in the Mediterranean off the Israeli port of Haifa
when the boat returning them to the vessel from Christmas shore
leave capsized in rough seas. Twenty bodies were recovered; another
man was listed as missing and presumed dead. It was the single
biggest death toll from an incident related to Desert Shield.
   Dec. 10 - A Marine died in northeastern Saudi Arabia of a
presumed ruptured brain aneurysm. A Marine died from a presumed
heart attack on the assault ship USS Iwo Jima after physical
fitness training in Bahrain.
   Dec. 9 - An Army private was killed in Saudi Arabia when the
tractor-trailer water supply truck he was driving overturned.
   Dec. 5 - A 20-year-old private with the Army's 20th engineer
brigade was killed when he was hit by a truck at a desert base in
Saudi Arabia.
   Dec. 4 - A Tennessee National Guard lieutenant colonel was found
dead from a gunshot in his tent in Saudi Arabia. U.S. spokesmen
said he shot himself.
   Dec. 1 - An airman with the 4th Tactical Fighter Wing's
engineering squadron was killed in a vehicle accident in Saudi
Arabia.
   Nov. 30 - A Marine corporal with the 4th Marine Expeditionary
Brigade died of an apparent heart attack aboard the USS Shreveport
in the Persian Gulf.
   Nov. 24 - A soldier from the 101st Combat Support Group was
killed when the truck he was riding collided with a civilian car in
Saudi Arabia.
   Nov. 17 - A soldier from the 101st Aviation Brigade was killed
in a truck accident in Saudi Arabia.
   Nov. 9 - A member of the 3rd Marine regiment in northeastern
Saudi Arabia was killed in his sleep when a rifle was accidentally
discharged.
   Nov. 8 - A soldier was found dead in a shower in Saudi Arabia,
but an initial investigation ruled out foul play.
   Nov. 7 - A 1st Cavalry Division soldier died from injuries
sustained trying to free a truck stuck in the Saudi desert.
   Oct. 30 - Ten sailors were killed when a steam line ruptured in
the boiler room of the assault carrier USS Iwo Jima in the Persian
Gulf.
   Oct. 30 - A Marine was killed when his vehicle overturned in the
Saudi desert.
   Oct. 10 - The two-man crew of an Air Force F-111 fighter-bomber
were killed in a crash during a low-level training flight in Saudi
Arabia.
   Oct. 8 - Two fliers of the Alabama Air National Guard were
killed when their Phantom reconnaisance jet crashed in Saudi
Arabia.
   Oct. 8 - Two UH-1 helicopters from the assault carrier USS
Okinawa, carrying eight Marines, vanished during a night training
flight in the northern Arabian Sea.
   Sept. 30 - The two-man crew of an Air Force F-15 Eagle fighter
were killed when the plane crashed during a low-level exercise in
Saudi Arabia.
   Sept. 26 - A sergeant from the 3rd Marine Aircraft Wing died of
a self-inflicted gunshot wound in Saudi Arabia.
   Sept. 20 - A soldier with the 82nd Airborne Division was killed
in a vehicle accident in Saudi Arabia.
   Sept. 14 - An officer from the 24th Infantry Division was killed
when his vehicle crashed in Saudi Arabia.
   Sept. 11 - A machinists' mate died of natural causes aboard the
USS Lasalle in the Persian Gulf.
   Aug. 29 - A C-5A Galaxy transport aircraft loaded with supplies
for U.S. forces in the Persian Gulf crashed shortly after takeoff
from Ramstein air base in Germany, killing 13 crewmen.
   Aug. 21 - An electrician's mate aboard the missile cruiser USS
Antietam was electrocuted while working on the ship's ventilation
system.
   Aug. 12 - An Air Force sergeant died when he was hit by a
military truck on a darkened runway in Saudi Arabia.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0051 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 1656EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Japan-BirthDearth     12-23 0426</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Japan-Birth Dearth,0497</SECOND>
<HEAD>Japan's Population Growth Hits New Postwar Low</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By S.L. BACHMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Statistics that show Japan's population growth
declining to a postwar low are likely to sharpen fears that lagging
birth rates are weakening the nation's economy.
   Preliminary figures released Friday from Japan's 1990 census
show the nation grew by only 2.1 percent from 1985 to 1990. The 3.4
percent growth from 1980-85 was the previous postwar low.
   The Oct. 1 census counted 123,622,541 people in Japan. The
country is still the world's seventh most populous, but it has one
of the world's slowest growth rates.
   Over the past year, the country has been flooded with magazine,
newspaper and television reports that speak of a ``baby shock.''
Officials express fear that with fewer children, the nation will
eventually have trouble supporting the elderly, a growing
percentage of the population.
   Business leaders say industry is already beginning to feel a
labor shortage.
   Birth rates in Japan have been declining since the introduction
of modern birth control after World War II, according to Dr. Makoto
Atoh, director of the Health and Welfare Ministry's department of
population policy studies.
   A housing shortage, high land prices, rising ages at marriage,
and the soaring costs of education and child-rearing have
contributed to the declining rate, he said.
   ``We think the major cause for the decline is the rising
percentage of singles and the rising age of marriage,'' Atoh said.
   Health and Welfare Ministry figures show that 20 percent of
people in their late 20s were single in 1975, but 37 percent in
that age group were single last year.
   Most women believe the high cost of educating children is the
biggest obstacle to having more, said Dr. Naohiro Ogawa, deputy
director of the Nippon University population research institute,
and the consultant for a recent survey by Mainichi newspaper.
   Another factor is cramped housing conditions and the
astronomical prices of new homes. Mechanization in the home,
expanded education and job opportunities have led an increasing
number of women out of the home.
   Some say the refusal of men to change their roles in the home
discourages large families.
   ``Japanese men don't share housekeeping. All the burden is on
the shoulder of women at home, so it's impossible to have more
children,'' said Mariko Mitsui, a Tokyo city assemblywoman.
   A government policy group has considered revamping maternity
leaves, changing housing policies, and improving child care as
measures to get women to have more children.
   Finance Minister Ryutaro Hashimoto, a governing Liberal
Democratic Party leader and a likely future prime minister, caused
an uproar in June when he was quoted as blaming the shrinking birth
rates on the expanded opportunities for higher education for women.
   Hashimoto later denied making the remark.
   Four out of five women questioned in the Mainichi survey said
they opposed government intervention to boost the birth rate, Ogawa
said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0052 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 1701EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Soviet-Baltics     12-23 0289</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Baltics,0315</SECOND>
<HEAD>Lithuanian President Urges Resistance To Soviet Direct Rule</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Lithuanian President Vytautus Landsbergis has told
the pro-independence Sajudis movement that direct Soviet rule may
be imposed, and he urged it to prepared to resist, Tass reported
Sunday.
   The official Soviet news agency quoted Landsbergis as telling
Sajudis-backed lawmakers on Saturday ``there are signs that rule of
this kind has already been introduced surreptitiously.''
   The report did not say what those signs were, although leaders
of independence movements in the three Baltic republics of
Lithuania, Latvia and Estonia have contended in recent weeks that
the Kremlin is preparing to crack down on them.
   Tass quoted Landsbergis, also the Sajudis leader, as urging the
lawmakers to ``develop a detailed program for resistance if the
Soviet Union introduces an overtly occupationist form of rule in
Lithuania.''
   He said attempts were being made to impose a new Union Treaty on
Lithuania ``through threats of bloodshed and use of violence'' and
that it was essential to prepare means of ``resistance,
self-defense.''
   Soviet President Mikhail S. Gorbachev is under increasing
pressure from hard-liners to introduce a state of emergency and
rule by decree in areas troubled by ethnic or political conflict.
   Last week, he told the Congress of People's Deputies, the
national parliament, that he would not hesitate to do so in regions
where conflicts threaten security or people's lives.
   At the same time, Gorbachev is seeking approval for the new
Union Treaty regrouping the 15 Soviet republics in a loose
federation with the central government.
   Landsbergis reiterated Lithuania's refusal to sign the document.
   ``Lithuania has already made its choice and will remain true to
it,'' Tass quoted him as saying.
   Lithuania declared independence on March 11. Since then, the
other 14 republics have also declared some form of independence or
autonomy from the central government.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0053 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 1709EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Guinea     12-23 0310</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Guinea,0346</SECOND>
<HEAD>Constitution to End Military Rule in Guinea Looks Headed for OK</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CONAKRY, Guinea (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A referendum on a new consitution that
would end military rule in this West African nation appeared headed
for approval in a vote Sunday.
   However, critics say the document will allow the military to
keep too much power.
   Several other African countries are also carrying out major
political reform in the wake of the pro-democratic revolutions last
year in Eastern Europe.
   Electoral officials said initial results indicated the
referendum was winning approval. Many areas reported up to 98
percent voting in favor of the document. Final results were
expected Monday.
   The document provides for the military to hand over power to two
political parties, but only after a five-year transition during
which a military-picked council would rule.
   Opponents have criticized the lengthy transition period, the
makeup of the council, and constitutional provisions allowing only
two political parties.
   The government says the two-party provision would prevent
parties from forming along tribal lines. It said the long
transition period is needed for an orderly transfer of power.
   Guinea has been hit this year by strikes by government workers
demanding bigger salaries, university graduates unable to find work
and students wanting larger government grants.
   Last month, police fired on protesting students, killing two and
wounding three.
   Guineans suffered years of brutal repression under Sekou Toure.
He ruled from 1958, when Guinea became independent from France,
until his death of a heart attack in 1984. The military then staged
a coup and Brig. Gen. Lansana Conte took over as president.
   Conte's government is accused of corruption and oppression,
including detentions without trial and torture of political
detainees, according to the London-based human rights group Amnesty
International.
   Guinea's population was estimated at 6.3 million in 1987, but
that does not include at least 2 million Guineans who fled during
Sekou Toure's rule and remain in exile.
   Guinea is rich in minerals but among the poorest countries in
the world.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0054 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 1723EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-Iraq-Blackout     12-23 0273</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Iraq-Blackout,0327</SECOND>
<HEAD>Blackout Drill Darkens Half of Baghdad</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf-US, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BAGHDAD, Iraq (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Authorities cut power to eastern Baghdad on
Sunday night, plunging half the capital into darkness for 15
minutes in a blackout drill testing the city's ability to cope with
air raids.
   Air raid sirens blared at 9 p.m. and the power was switched off
to all of Baghdad east of the Tigris River. The only light was the
glow cast by gas flares from the tall tower of a refinery on the
river's west bank.
   It was the first practice blackout, but senior officials said
Saturday plans were being made for such drills in all the major
population centers.
   Lt. Col. Wa'il Abid Hamudi, operations director at the Civil
Defense Department, told state television such drills will test
Iraq's ability to cope with air raids if it is attacked.
   Hamudi asked the population to comply strictly with instructions
given by news media for carrying out the blackout.
   Residents were told to turn off outdoor lights and use thick
curtains inside to prevent light from being spotted by enemy
planes.
   Motorists were advised to turn off headlights and park when they
hear sirens.
   Street lights would be switched off and store owners were told
to disconnect their neon signs.
   He had said the drill would last for only one minute. However,
instead of relying on people to switch off lights, the power was
simply cut to eastern Baghdad on Sunday night for 15 minutes after
the siren sounded.
   Iraq has stepped up civil defense preparations since the U.N.
Security Council set a Jan. 15 deadline for Iraqi to withdraw from
Kuwait or face military action.
   An evacuation drill was held in Baghdad on Friday to move about
1.5 million people from the eastern half of the capital to havens
outside the city. Officials said similar plans were under way in
other Iraqi cities.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0055 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 1729EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Gulf-Iraq-Defense 1stLd-Writethru a0670 12-23 0480</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Iraq-Defense, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0670,0574</SECOND>
<HEAD>Iraqi Defense Minister: Iraq Ready To Crush Any Attack</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS throughout to UPDATE with Turkish politician's meeting
with Saddam, Turkish military preparations. No pickup</NOTE>
<HEAD>With AM-US-Gulf, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NICOSIA, Cyprus (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Iraq's defense minister said Sunday that
his country is ready to crush any military attack, the official
Iraqi News Agency reported.
   INA said Lt. Gen. Saadi Tuma Abbas was responding to comments by
U.S. Defense Secretary Dick Cheney, who said multinational forces
in Saudi Arabia will be ready to strike if Iraq does not pull out
of Kuwait by Jan. 15.
   ``The U.S. defense minister and those who support him will see
how the earth will be burned under their feet not only in Iraq but
also in Saudi Arabia and other Arab gulf countries,'' Abbas was
quoted as saying.
   Cheney told troops in Saudi Arabia on Saturday that
reinforcements expected to arrive soon would give the United States
the force needed to liberate Kuwait. Cheney, on a Middle East tour
with Gen. Colin Powell, chairman of the joint chiefs of staff,
repeated the claim in Egypt on Sunday.
   Any U.S. strike is expected after Jan. 15, the deadline set by
the U.N. Security Council for Iraq to withdraw from Kuwait or face
possible attack.
   The United States is the largest contributor to a 28-nation
military force of about 480,000 troops sent to Saudi Arabia and the
Persian Gulf region after Kuwait was seized. The multinational
forces face an estimated 510,000 Iraqi troops in the occupied
emirate and southern Iraq.
   Abbas said Islamic holy warriors in Saudi Arabia would join in
the fight against King Fahd's ``treason in the eastern area of
Saudi Arabia.''
   Iraq has appealed to Moslems worldwide for support in its
confrontation with the West, saying Fahd betrayed Islam by inviting
foreign troops to help defend his country, home of Islam's holiest
shrines.
   INA, monitored in Cyprus, also reported that George Habash,
leader of the Popular Front for the Liberation of Palestine, called
on ``all Arab masses and their revolutionary fighter groups to
mobilize to turn Saudi Arabia into a cemetery for the American
invaders.''
   The Syrian-backed Front was kicked out of Iraq 11 years ago
because of a split between Baghdad and Damascus, but it reopened
offices in the Iraqi capital on Saturday.
   Turkish politician Erdal Inonu said Iraqi President Saddam
Hussein told him on Sunday that Iraq increased its forces along its
border with Turkey in response to Ankara's request for NATO air
units, Turkey's semi-official news agency Anatolia reported.
   It quoted Inonu, leader of the main opposition Social Democrat
Populist Party, as telling a news conference in Baghdad after a
two-hour meeting with Saddam that Saddam expressed disappointed
about a recent reinforcement of Turkish forces at the border.
   Saddam claimed the Turkish military moves were imposed by the
United States, according to Inonu.
   Saddam was quoted as saying Iraq had no intention to attack
Turkey nor any ambitions toward Turkish territory.
   The Istanbul daily Hurriyet, meanwhile, reported Sunday that the
Turkish armed forces would go on alert as of Jan. 2.
   It said several air units, including F-16, F-4 and F-5 fighters,
were in the process of being transferred to four military air bases
in southeast Turkey from the western and central Anatolian air
bases. Hurriyet said air forces personnel were banned from taking
any leaves starting in January.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0056 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 1741EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Soviet-Politics 1stLd-Writethru a0683 12-23 0683</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Politics, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0683,0801</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rally Against Dictatorship Starts Critical Week For Gorbachev</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 9 grafs to ADD background on Khrushchev, RECAST
lead to CLARIFY that dictatorship is feared, sted already in place;
pickup graf 9 pvs `As the...'
^By BRIAN FRIEDMAN</NOTE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hundreds of people rallied Sunday to denounce
moves they fear could bring dictatorship to the Kremlin.
   Their protest came at the start of a critical week in which
President Mikhail S. Gorbachev seeks parliamentary approval for
stronger presidential powers.
   Signs carried by some in the crowd of 1,500 people supported
Eduard Shevardnadze, who resigned Thursday as foreign minister to
protest the growing influence of hard-liners and what he said was a
coming dictatorship.
   ``Shevardnadze is with us. Gorbachev is against us.
Shevardnadze, stay with us!'' pleaded one sign, held aloft on a
broken hockey stick.
   Alexander Obolensky, a radical member of the Congress of
People's Deputies, said reformers such as Shevardnadze and
Alexander N. Yakovlev have been forced into the background by
hard-line Communists. Yakovlev retired in August from his post in
the Communist Party leadership.
   ``Shevardnadze, trying to protect the intrigues of our
president, sacrificed desperately his political career,'' Obolensky
said at the rally.
   ``We want to ask you directly, Mikhail Sergeyevich,'' Obolensky
said, addressing Gorbachev, ``you have pushed aside democrats, you
surrendered your faithful supporter, Yakovlev. You lost
Shevardnadze. Who are you going to be with?''
   ``You are losing your allies,'' he said. ``Remember the fate of
Khrushchev, the reformer. Don't expect us to bow our heads
obediently like in 1964!''
   Khrushchev was ousted that year and replaced by Leonid I.
Brezhnev, who reversed many reforms.
   As the Congress begins the second week of its parliamentary
session Monday, it is expected to begin preliminary voting on the
constitutional amendments to strengthen Gorbachev's presidency.
   Gorbachev wants direct control over a reorganized executive
branch of government to deal with a worsening economy and a
fragmenting union.
   He also is expected to make changes in the leadership before the
week is out, including naming a vice president.
   On Saturday, the deputies heard KGB chief Vladimir Kryuchkov
deliver a speech that brought back some of the chill of the Cold
War.
   Kryuchkov said the CIA is gathering information on workers'
movements in the Soviet Union ``for its purposeful masterminding''
and funding of ``anti-Soviet formations'' such as radio stations
that attack the Soviet Union.
   He also lashed out at pro-independence groups in the 15 Soviet
republics, saying they have armed 26,000 fighters. He said
foreigners were trying to topple the Soviet government.
   ``Today, if we undertake decisive actions to restore order, we
have to accept the fact that there could be bloodshed,'' Kryuchkov
said.
   Maria Denisenko, a radical member of the Russian legislature,
attacked Kryuchkov's speech as ``tragic'' at a time when the United
States and other Western nations were sending aid to the Soviet
Union.
   ``The KGB chief clearly showed us that he is going to defend
socialist gains, and he won't stop at anything, including
bloodshed,'' she said. ``If the moment comes, the whole nation
should rise up to defend democracy!''
   The crowd in the small square opposite Moscow City Hall cheered.
   Congress deputy and crusading magazine editor Vitaly Korotich,
who did not address the rally, said in an interview that
Kryuchkov's speech had little relevance.
   ``I think that the KGB, of course, always needs an enemy. I
think if the KGB collapsed, the CIA would die of starvation, and
vice versa,'' Korotich said.
   But Kryuchkov was not the only Soviet official talking tough on
Saturday. Gorbachev issued a decree declaring that separatist
actions by Turkish Christians and Russians in the southwestern
republic of Moldavia were illegal.
   In a presidential decree, he gave Moldavia 10 days to dissolve a
new national guard and to reconsider a law that made Moldavian,
which is similar to Romanian, the republic's official language.
   On Sunday in Kishinev, the capital of Moldavia, a rally of
``reconciliation'' organized by the Communist Party ended in a
brawl after some people shouted at participants, ``Invaders, go
home!'' and tried to seize the microphones, the Tass news agency
reported.
   Soviet television showed shoving matches in the crowd, and Tass
said police intervened to restore order. Afterward, opponents of
the rally marched to the local party headquarters and shouted
anti-Communist slogans, Tass said.
   Moldavia, which borders Romania, has been hit by ethnic tension
during its push for independence from the Soviet Union.
   The Gagauz, a group of about 150,000 Turkish Christians,
declared a new republic in southern Moldavia. In eastern Moldavia,
more than 300,000 ethnic Russians and Ukrainians have declared a
new republic along the Dniester River.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0057 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 1741EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r e BC-Dance     12-23 0361</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Dance,0431</SECOND>
<HEAD>New Soviet Company Dances `Nutcracker'</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: No PMs Planned</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By MARY CAMPBELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The youthful Bolshoi Ballet Grigorovich Company
is performing a most charming version of ``The Nutcracker.''
   The Moscow import adds another variation to this season's New
York City Ballet and Joffrey Ballet performances and American
Ballet Theater's rendition of ``The Nutcracker'' on television
Christmas Day.
   Yuri Grigorovich, artistic director of the Bolshoi Ballet,
announced his new company in October. After performances in Moscow,
the company has been touring America since Nov. 23. Its version of
``The Nutcracker'' runs through Dec. 30 at the Brooklyn Academy of
Music.
   The Saturday night cast was the same as at Wednesday's opening
except for Drosselmeyer, the magician. Oleg Dedogriuk was a spry,
brisk dancer in white wig in this version, not a creaky oldster.
This company doesn't have any aging members, the 60 dancers being
19 to 25.
   It also doesn't have any children. Small dancers dance the
children. And when Drosselmeyer walks in with a nutcracker doll,
it's really Tamara Glasova under his arm, wearing red and a mask
with a wide mouth.
   Marie - called Clara in the original in 1892 - is Oksana
Konobeyeva, who has a sweet face and fine form. She can't hold
balance unsupported so she moved quickly off poses that end on one
toe or held the pose graciously when supported by Dmitry Tuboltsev
as the Nutcracker Prince.
   Tuboltsev, small and slim, has the poise of a dancer noble. He
jumped high and landed lightly and securely. He is clearly a dancer
to watch. Many members of this company are expected to enter the
Bolshoi Ballet.
   The Mouse King, Maxim Knish, also was a fine dancer. Grigorovich
choreographed the mice-toy soldiers' fight less like a fight than a
dance. When the Mouse King was wounded and carried out, he twitched
his claws delightfully, raising childish laughs all over the
auditorium.
   There's no toy Nutcracker and no Sugar Plum Fairy here. Marie
does all the leading ballerina dancing. There are five ethnic
couples who have duets, a form beloved of choreographers making
full-length ballets to Tchaikovsky music. Here, they're Spanish,
Indian, Chinese, Russian and a shepherd and shepherdess from France
who dance pulling a gray sheep on wheels between them.
   They all were very good. And the scenery, the Christmas tree
becoming larger and white, was surprisingly elaborate for a touring
company.
   A Russian conductor, Alexander Lavrenyuk, led the orchestra.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0058 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 1815EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Haiti     12-23 0378</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Haiti,0433</SECOND>
<HEAD>Aristide Officially Declared Winner of Presidential Election</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MICHAEL NORTON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   PORT-AU-PRINCE, Haiti (AP) - The Rev. Jean-Bertrand Aristide, a
leftist who has championed the cause of Haiti's poor, was declared
winner Sunday of the country's first fully free elections.
   With an estimated 50.l per cent of the votes tallied, Aristide
led with with 66.7 percent of the total, according to the Electoral
Council.
   An estimated 75 per cent of more than two million registered
voters had cast their ballots in general elections Dec. 16.
   Runners-up Marc Bazin and Louis Dejoie Jr. had 15.4 percent and
5 percent respectively. Silvio Claude had just over 3 percent, and
the seven other candidates received the rest of the vote.
   ``You have made a sacrifice to show the world the true face of
Haiti,'' Aristide told the nation, speaking Creole, immediately
after the announcement on state-run radio. He spoke from the office
of his center for homeless children.
   The four major runners-up had all conceded defeat by Saturday,
after partial results showed Aristide had won by a landslide.
   ``Things must change, things must change for everyone,'' he
said, repeating the words of Pope Jean-Paul II. His March 1983
visit to Haiti initiated the official Roman Catholic opposition to
the Duvalier dictatorship that ended three years later during a
popular uprising.
   Legislative and local election results have not as yet been
announced. Runoff elections in those races will be held Jan. 20.
   Most analysts believe the National Front for Change and
Democracy, the left-wing coalition which nominated Aristide, will
dominate the two-chamber National Assembly and form a parliamentary
bloc with Dejoie's National Agricultural and Industrial Party. The
National Assembly would thus have a pro-Aristide majority.
   According to the 1987 Constitution, the president must choose
his prime minister from among the members of the parliamentary
majority. The president is head of state, while the prime minister
runs the government.
   From the pulpit of his church St. Jean Bosco, Aristide had won
fame for his defense of the poor and attacks of repressive
government.
   On Sept. 11, 1988, thugs torched his church, killing at least 12
and wounding 70. Aristide was excluded from his Salesian Father
religious order in December 1988, allegedly for fomenting violence.
   After a pro-Aristide rally Dec. 5, an unknown assailant lobbed a
grenade into a crowd, killing seven and injuring more than 50.
   Aristide will inaugurated Feb. 9 on the fifth anniversary of the
fall of dictator Jean-Claude Duvalier, whose family ruled Haiti for
over three decades.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0059 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 1824EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-HeroinKingpin     12-23 0261</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Heroin Kingpin,0281</SECOND>
<HEAD>New York Drug Kingpin and Associates Convicted</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RON POWERS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A drug kingpin who ran what investigators say
was an especially violent operation was convicted in federal court
Sunday of drug conspiracy, racketeering and money laundering.
   Prosecutors say Ricardo Melendez ran a gang that used violence
to maintain discipline within its ranks and raked in as much as $10
million a month peddling heroin and cocaine in some of Brooklyn's
poorest neighborhoods.
   The court heard from witnesses who said they had double-crossed
Melendez andhis top lieutenants and paid for it with maimings and
mutilations - ice-pick stabbings, teeth pulled out, fingers chopped
off.
   Melendez, 30, remained in federal custody to await sentencing,
when he will face mandatory life in prison. No date was set.
   ``We're very happy with the verdict,'' said U.S. Attorney Andrew
Maloney. ``This was a very important drug organization, most of
whom will now be locked behind bars for most of their lives.''
   Melendez's lawyer, Lawrence Hochheiser, had argued the
government failed to prove any conspiracy and maintained the
defendants couldn't run a complex organization.
   Seven members of Melendez's organization, including his No. 2
man, also were convicted Sunday of various charges including
murder, kidnapping and drug conspiracy.
   The federal jury deliberated five days before handing up the
verdicts.
   The three-month trial before U.S. District Judge Arthur Spatt
included testimony from witnesses who told of physical
intimidation, violence and riches.
   One juror was dismissed when deliberations were to begin after
he reported receiving a threatening note at his home. The FBI was
investigating the incident.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0060 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 1824EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Suriname     12-23 0265</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Suriname,0286</SECOND>
<HEAD>Surinamese Army Chief Announces Resignation</HEAD>
<DATELINE>THE HAGUE, Netherlands (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Suriname's former military ruler,
Lt. Col. Desi Bouterse, announced his resignation Sunday as army
commander. The Dutch government warned of a possible military coup
in its former colony.
   In a Dutch TV interview by telephone from Paramaribo, capital of
Suriname, Bouterse said his resignation was an act of defiance
toward President Ramsewak Shankar.
   ``I'm no longer willing to take orders from this kind of a joker
who exposes the dignity of his nation to ridicule,'' Bouterse said.
   Shankar was chosen president of the small, mineral-rich nation
on South America's northeastern coast in free elections in November
1987. His installation in January 1988 ended eight years of
dictatorship by Bouterse.
   In The Hague, a Foreign Ministry spokeswoman said, ``The Dutch
government hopes Bouterse realizes that a coup ... will have a
detrimental effect on development aid.''
   Suriname, a nation of 400,000 people, has been heavily dependent
on Dutch aid. It gained independence from the Netherlands in 1975
and was governed as a Western-style democracy until Bouterse seized
power in a February 1980 coup.
   Bouterse did not say when his resignation would take effect or
who would replace him.
   According to Dutch Television, the Surinamese army was placed on
alert, heightening speculation about a possible Bouterse coup
attempt.
   However, the television also quoted a Surinamese army statement
as saying it would continue ``reconcilatory overtures'' made by
Bouterse toward the Shankar government.
   The Dutch have been at odds in the past with Bouterse, whose
troops shot to death 15 prominent opposition figures in 1983. The
deaths prompted suspension of a $1.1 billion Dutch aid package to
Suriname.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0061 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 1837EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-WeatherpageWeather     12-23 0491</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Weatherpage Weather,0606</SECOND>
<HEAD>Cold Wave Spreads, Record Warm In East, Floods In Southeast</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Still more record lows were established Sunday, many below zero,
while the East Coast had record highs and heavy rain caused
flooding in the Southeast.
   Lows of 20 below zero or colder were reported in Idaho, Nevada,
Utah, Colorado, Wyoming, Montana, Nebraska, South Dakota, North
Dakota, Iowa, Minnesota and Wisconsin, the National Weather Service
reported.
   Temperatures reached 30 below zero in Colorado, Wyoming, South
Dakota, North Dakota and Minnesota.
   Sunday's low for the Lower 48 states was 39 below zero at Craig,
Colo.
   The low of 19 at Bakersfield, Calif., was an all-time record.
The previous record, of 20, was tied Saturday.
   The low of 7 below zero at Albuquerque, N.M., was the city's
first subzero reading on record for December. The low of 11 at Las
Vegas, Nev., also was a record for December.
   Other records were 29 below zero at Alamosa, Colo.; 6 below at
Amarillo, Texas; 17 below at Colorado Springs, Colo.; 16 below at
Denver; 9 below at Goodland, Kan.; 17 below at Grand Junction,
Colo.; 30 below at Huron, S.D.; 7 at Medford, Ore.; 26 at Phoenix;
29 below at Pocatello, Idaho; 25 below at Pueblo, Colo.; 9 below at
Reno, Nev.; 36 at San Diego, Calif.; 27 below at Scottsbluff, Neb.;
28 below at Sioux Falls, S.D.; and 21 at Tucson, Ariz.
   Temperatures began to moderate a bit over the Great Plains
region, with readings in the single digits and teens by early
afternoon. The temperature at Scottsbluff, Neb., finally rose above
zero for the first time in 97 hours.
   But brisk westerly wind blew over the north-central states and
wind chill readings included 44 below zero at Rock Springs, Wyo.,
and 42 below zero at Watertown, S.D.
   Ahead of the cold front marking the leading edge of the arctic
air, unseasonably warm weather extended from the eastern Gulf Coast
into New England.
   Brisk southerly wind helped temperatures warm into the 60s as
far north as southern New Hampshire, with readings in the 70s along
the mid-Atlantic Coast.
   Record highs were 64 at Albany, N.Y.; 64 at Allentown, Pa.; 69
at Baltimore; 61 at Beckley, W.Va.; 65 at Boston; 58 at Burlington,
Vt.; 65 at Concord, N.H.; 59 at Hartford, Conn.; 67 at Newark,
N.J.; 77 at Norfolk, Va.; 66 at Roanoke, Va.; 64 at Scranton, Pa.;
64 at Wilmington, Del.; and 58 at Worcester, Mass.
   Rain and snow fell along the arctic cold front.
   Afternoon showers and thunderstorms developing along the front
extended from extreme southeastern Louisiana to central
Mississippi.
   Showers developing along and ahead of the front prevailed from
northeastern Mississippi across the central Appalachians to New
England.
   Showers and thunderstorms produced locally heavy rain in the
Southeast late Saturday into Sunday morning, causing flooding that
forced evacuations in parts of Alabama, Tennessee and Kentucky.
   Heavier rainfall for the six hours up to 1 p.m. EST included
1.65 inches at Biloxi, Miss.; and 1.17 inches at Centreville, Ala.
   Heavier rainfall for the 24 hours up to 1 p.m. EST included more
than three inches at Chattanooga, Tenn., (3.34) and nearly three
inches at Knoxville, Tenn., (2.74).
   Behind the cold front, a mixture of freezing rain, freezing
drizzle, sleet and snow fell from Louisiana to New York state.
Light snow fell from Arkansas through Missouri and Illinois to
Indiana.
   A winter storm watch was posted for Monday for parts of northern
Vermont, upstate New York and the northern and western mountains of
Maine.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0062 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 1847EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Gulf-Capsize 3rdLd-Writethru a0716 12-23 0656</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Capsize, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0716,0825</SECOND>
<HEAD>Victims of Ferry Disaster Remembered at Memorial Service</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 1 graf for 5th `The bodies...' to UPDATE with Dover Air
Base spokesman saying bodies expected to arrive 10 a.m. EST Monday.
Pickup 6th pvs `Capt. Joseph...'</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos TLV2,3,5,6</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARCUS ELIASON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ABOARD THE USS SARATOGA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Crewmen of the U.S. aircraft
carrier Saratoga bade farewell Sunday to 21 drowned comrades with
tears, salvos of rifle fire and the Navy hymn ``Eternal Father.''
   The shipboard memorial service was attended by about 1,200 of
the Saratoga's crew, including most of the 81 sailors and Navy
airmen who survived the fatal capsize of the chartered Israeli
ferry early Saturday.
   On a table by the podium, 20 white sailors' caps and one chief
petty officer's hat were arranged, symbolizing the lives lost.
   Israeli navy divers recovered the 20th body on Sunday near the
submerged ferry, Haifa police said. Searches continued for the body
of the 21st victim, declared missing and presumed drowned.
   The bodies were later flown aboard a military transport jet to
the Dover Air Force Base in Delaware. They were expected to arrive
10 a.m. EST Monday, a base spokesman said.
   Capt. Joseph S. Mobley, commanding officer of the Saratoga, told
reporters that the Navy had concluded with ``utmost confidence''
that the missing man had perished in the tragedy.
   ``He was definitely on the ferry at the time of the accident, he
was definitely not rescued,'' Mobley said. ``He is not on the ship,
he is not ashore.''
   The ferry Tuvia capsized Saturday shortly after midnight as it
was carrying 102 American seamen to the Saratoga from a Christmas
shore leave. The ship is anchored about a mile off Israel's
northern port of Haifa.
   The mourners gathered in one of the Saratoga's huge aircraft
hangars. Through the open doors, Navy helicopters could been seen
crisscrossing over the Mediterranean in search of the missing body.
   Two sailors dropped a wreath into the metal-gray sea in honor of
the victims, and a detachment of seven Marines fired a 21-gun
salute in three rifle salvos.
   Some of the sailors wiped tears from their eyes as a choir sang
``America the Beautiful'' and ``Eternal Father.''
   Mobley addressed his remarks to the families of the dead.
``There are no words that can express the heartfelt sorrow of this
entire 5,000-man ship,'' he said.
   Later, he told reporters: ``We have suffered a very great
tragedy. Every man on this mighty ship has had his heart in his
throat, tears in his eyes and a knot in his stomach since that
event.''
   The Saratoga task force, based at Mayport Naval Air Station in
Florida, includes the destroyer Sampson, cruiser South Carolina and
combat stores ship Sirius. It has a crew of 6,200 men.
   The ships anchored off Haifa on Thursday for the holidays, with
shore leaves beginning Friday. Some wives and girlfriends who flew
to Israel to be with their men were taken to the Saratoga by
helicopter for the memorial service.
   The Saratoga and its escort ships were in the Red Sea as part of
the naval buildup in the Gulf following Iraq's Aug. 2 invasion of
Kuwait.
   The accident was the deadliest involving U.S. servicemen in
Operation Desert Shield, and it raised the number of Americans who
have died to 78.
   Among the mourners Sunday were U.S. Ambassador William Brown;
Admiral Nick Gee, commander of the Saratoga battle group; Haifa
Mayor Aryeh Gurel; Israeli Chief of Staff Lt. Gen. Dan Shomron, and
Israel's navy commander, Gen. Micha Ram.
   After the ceremony, Mobley talked to reporters and denied
Israeli media reports that one of the victims had been handcuffed
after being arrested ashore for drunkenness.
   ``That is totally false, totally false,'' Mobley said. ``There
was not a man on that ship who was handcuffed or restrained because
we are fully aware of the consequences of such an action.''
   He added: ``I want to assure everyone, particularly the
families, that we would not do such a thing.''
   Reports in the Israeli press Sunday said one man was restrained
by handcuffs when he became hysterical after he was rescued from
the water.
   Three investigations by Haifa police, the Israeli Port Authority
and the U.S. Navy have been launched into the sinking of the
57-foot, double-deck Tuvia about 200 yards from the Saratoga.
   Survivors reported that waves of about three to four feet had
been pouring water over the stern and that two larger waves then
swamped the ferry.
   Israeli officials said that a number of sailors had gathered in
the back of the ferry in anticipation of getting off and may have
destabilized the craft.
   Nineteen bodies were retrieved Saturday, including six brought
up by Israelidivers from the Tuvia. Three dozen sailors were taken
to hospitals, but most have been released.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0063 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 1910EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Israel-Immigration 1stLd-Writethru a0694 12-23 0599</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel-Immigration, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0694,0698</SECOND>
<HEAD>Israeli Officials Demands Emergency Measures To Handle Immigrant
Wave</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS throughout to UPDATE with immigration minister's
comments, other. No pickup</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto TLV1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SERGEI SHARGORODSKY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Israeli officials said Sunday that emergency
efforts are needed to accommodate an influx of Soviet Jews, who the
immigration minister said are ``raining from the sky'' in record
numbers.
   In southern Beersheba, immigrants set up a tent camp to protest
lack of housing. Other Israelis there staged a demonstration to
urge that mobile homes for immigrants not be put near their
prosperous neighborhood.
   About 5,500 Soviet Jews reached Israel in a special airlift from
Thursday through Saturday, with an additional 1,500 arriving
Sunday.
   State television broadcast footage of the unprecedented flood of
immigrants being processed at Ben Gurion International Airport
outside Tel Aviv.
   ``I've never seen anything like this here,'' said Shifra Oren, a
longtime volunteer at the terminal.
   Immigration Minister Yitzhak Peretz said the influx of newcomers
had forced authorities to resort to emergency housing solutions for
the first time since the immigration wave began in mid-1989. He
said about a third of this weekend's arrivals were housed in
hotels.
   Officials attributed the upsurge to fears of political
instability and the economic crisis in the Soviet Union, and to
improved transit through Eastern European countries.
   ``The trick is to get the Jews out as soon as quickly as
possible,'' Seymour Reich, outgoing chairman of the Conference of
Presidents of Major American Jewish Organizations, said after
stepping off a plane.
   Reich said the urgency was partly out of concerns triggered by
Thursday's resignation of Soviet Foreign Minister Eduard
Shevardnadze. The resignation has aggravated fears of growing
unrest in the Soviet Union.
   Jewish groups planned to ask the Bush administration ``to use
every means possible at their command to bring the Jews out,''
Reich added.
   The sense of urgency was pointed up by a government waiver of
the usual ban on Friday evening and Saturday flights, the Jewish
sabbath. Israel's national carrier El Al was ordered to use every
plane available to ferry the Jews from Eastern Europe.
   Simcha Dinitz, chairman of the quasi-governmental Jewish Agency
that handles immigrant transportation, said the rate was expected
to increase to a regular influx of 1,500 Soviets daily.
   Officials expect more than 30,000 Soviets in December, bringing
this year's immigration total to 200,000. That includes all Jewish
immigrants. Israel expects about 1 million Soviets by the end of
1992.
   Uri Gordon, chief of the Jewish Agency's Immigration Department,
urged the government to declare a state of emergency.
   ``We witness a real drama of a people in migration. But we
should remember we will be tested by absorption. We have to declare
a state of emergency in the country and create a new set of
priorities,'' Gordon said.
   ``We should immediately freeze housing prices and each one in
the Israeli society personally has to help. ... The government
alone won't solve the problem.''
   In the Negev desert town of Beersheba, where thousands of
Soviets have settled, eight new immigrant families raised a tent
camp in the southern town of Beersheba to dramatize the housing
crunch.
   ``The allowance they receive is not enough to rent an
apartment,'' protest spokesman Ilya Schneider said. He said a
two-bedroom apartment in the least expensive Beersheba neighborhood
costs $400 a month.
   An immigrant family of three receives $9,000 a year in
government allowance to cover rent, food, clothing, education and
transportation expenses.
   ``There are cases of four, five families renting one apartment,
and this leads to problems ... arguments and even fist fights,''
Schneider said.
   Beersheba city officials said protesters refused to sign rent
contracts, fearing they will run out of money and have no place to
live.
   Israelis in Beersheba's well-to-do Neve Noy area demonstrated to
protest government plans to set up 7,000 mobile homes for
immigrants near their neighborhood.
   The housing crisis has been made worse by slow building starts.
Work has begun on only about 17,000 of 45,000 housing units planned
to be started in 1990, officials report.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0064 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 1912EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Korea     12-23 0207</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Korea,0220</SECOND>
<HEAD>North Korea Hints Talks Off If South Holds Military Exercises</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   North Korea indicated Sunday it will call off the
fourth round of premiers' talks with South Korea if the South goes
ahead with annual military exercises with the United States.
   The official Workers (Communist) Party newspaper Rodong Shinmun
said, ``If the South Korean ruling quarters stage the `Team Spirit'
war game next year again together with the U.S. imperialist
aggressors, they will face a strong denunciation within and without
as the wrecker of the North-South dialogues.'' The commentary was
broadcast in part by the North's Korean Central News Agency,
monitored in Tokyo.
   It called the decision to hold the annual exercises in 1991 ``a
deliberate criminal act totally denying the North-South
dialogues.''
   North Korea broke off talks in the past during the exercises.
   The commentary said the exercises brought the situation on the
Korean peninsula ``to the brink of war.''
   In the highest-level talks ever between Communist North and
capitalist South, the two premiers began meeting in September to
discuss easing tensions and steps toward reunification. A fourth
round of talks is scheduled Feb. 25-28 in Pyongyang, the North
Korean capital.
   The Koreas were divided in 1945. The North invaded the South in
1950, starting a three-year war.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0065 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 1915EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-NorthernIreland 2ndLd-Writethru a0681 12-23 0406</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Northern Ireland, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0681,0470</SECOND>
<HEAD>IRA Announces Cease-Fire for Christmas</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 7 grafs to UPDATE with British official reax to
cease-fire; pickup graf 6 pvs `In Northern...'</NOTE>
<DATELINE>BELFAST, Northern Ireland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The leadership of the Irish
Republican Army on Sunday announced a three-day Christmas
cease-fire, the first in 15 years.
   Britain's Cabinet minister for Northern Ireland, Peter Brooke,
welcomed the cease-fire. He said he hoped it pointed to a lasting
peace in 1991.
   The decision to suspend IRA military activity from midnight
Sunday to midnight Wednesday was announced in a statement issued in
Dublin and released in Belfast.
   ``We have instructed all active service units to suspend all
offensive military action in the British-occupied area for a period
of three days from midnight,'' said the statement, which was signed
P. O'Neill, the pseudonym for the IRA army council.
   ``Our active service units reserve the right to take defensive
actions,'' it added.
   In his comments, Brooke said: ``A cease-fire in Northern
Ireland, albeit brief, is a welcome epitaph to 1990 and maybe a
pointer to achieving a lasting solution in 1991.''
   ``There could ... be no better news on the eve of the New Year
than that the message that terrorism cannot be allowed to succeed
may have taken root, and that recognition has dawned that there is
no future for terrorism,'' he said.
   In Northern Ireland, lawmaker Peter Robinson, deputy leader of
the Democratic Unionist Party, said, ``The IRA calling cease-fires
has nothing whatsoever to do with the community interest, but is to
give themselves the opportunity to reorganize and re-stock. It
should be viewed in that light.''
   Irish Prime Minister Charles Haughey said he ``earnestly hoped''
the move could be extended indefinitely - a development he said
would ``open up great possibilities for progress.''
   The last suspension of the IRA's 20-year-old battle to drive the
British out of Northern Ireland was in December 1974 and lasted
eight months.
   Since the largely Roman Catholic IRA began its guerrilla fight,
2,849 people have been killed in violence.
   The struggle pits Catholic nationalists against Protestant
loyalists determined to retain the predominantly Protestant
province's link to Britain. The IRA wants to unite the province
with the overwhelmingly Catholic Irish Republic.
   ``The leadership of the IRA extends greetings to all those who
suffered as a result of the British-occupied six Irish counties,''
the IRA statement said. ``We are particularly mindful of all the
families who have been bereaved in the last 20 years and of the
political prisoners and their families.''
   Gerry Adams, president of the the IRA's legal political wing
Sinn Fein, said of the cease-fire, ``I welcome the news and hope
that the British forces will respond in kind so that Irish people
can have a peaceful Christmas.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0066 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 1924EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Australia-Weather 1stLd-Writethru a0647 12-23 0254</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Australia-Weather, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0647,0285</SECOND>
<HEAD>Cyclone, Bushfires In Australia</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS thruout to UPDATE with new injuries reported, bushfire
damage, other; no pickup</NOTE>
<DATELINE>SYDNEY, Australia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A cyclone off Queensland state,
bushfires in New South Wales and severe thunderstorms in Victoria
state combined to batter the east coast of Australia over the
weekend.
   Temperatures ranging as high as 113 degrees and gusty winds in
dry conditions fueled fires around Sydney and in other parts of New
South Wales state on Sunday.
   At least five people were injured in the fires, including two
firefighters.
   Thousands of residents were forced to flee their homes as up to
370 fires burned around the city in the worst day of bushfires in
more than 20 years, emergency officials said.
   More than 500 bushfires were burning late Sunday night in the
state, but most were under control.
   At least 20 houses were destroyed, including 13 at Gosford north
of Sydney. Officials said some of the fires may have been
deliberately set.
   On the far north Queensland coast, residents were preparing for
Cyclone Joy, a tropical storm that forecasters are rating as
powerful as Cyclone Tracy, which claimed 50 lives when it hit
Darwin in the Northern Territory on Christmas Day in 1974.
   Cyclone Joy was off the coast Sunday night and expected to start
moving towards the coast later. High winds associated with the
storm have already cut power supplies in the tourist city of
Cairns, where the international airport was closed.
   On the southeast coast, a freak thunderstorm Saturday night
brought down power lines in Melbourne, Victoria's capital. There
were several injuries reported from fallen trees, none of them
serious.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0067 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 1934EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Israel-LibelSuit     12-23 0342</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel-Libel Suit,0407</SECOND>
<HEAD>Israeli Interior Minister Sues Newspaper</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Interior Minister Aryeh Deri said he sued a
leading Israeli daily for libel on Sunday for suggesting he may
have exploited his position to purchase four apartments.
   The article, which was published by the Yedioth Ahronoth daily
six months ago, preceded the opening of a police investigation of
Deri and his aides on suspicion of fraud and mishandling public
funds.
   Deri's ultra-Orthodox Torah Guardians faction is a key member of
Prime Minister Yitzhak Shamir's governing coalition, which relies
heavily on smaller religious parties for majority support in the
120-member Parliament.
   In the suit filed in Tel Aviv District Court, Deri, 31, asked
for $500,000 in damage, state radio and television said.
   ``The moment Yedioth hinted, and quite heavily, that I exploited
my status or state resources to achieve the many assets I acquired,
this I will not pass over lightly,'' Deri said on TV.
   On radio, Deri said, ``This is the first libel suit, others are
on the way. I will fight until the end ... to put things in place
and expose my truth.'' Yedioth Ahronoth editor Moshe Vardi
responded in a statement read to reporters, ``If anyone thinks that
this is the way to quiet the press, he will learn it is a mistake,
and on the matter of the facts, this the court will decide.''
   The newspaper is one of Israel's most widely read dailies. It
has not yet filed a defense statement with the court, the national
Itim news agency reported. No trial date was immediately set.
   According to the radio and Itim, the article in question was
published by Yedioth on June 15.
   It reportedly suggested that Deri and his wife owned four luxury
apartments, and said the ``minister's salary is insufficient to
fund the purchase of this property.''
   Deri has denied ownership of at least two of the apartments, the
reports added.
   Another article published by Yedioth in June accused Deri of
unlawfully funneling hundreds of thousands of shekels to public
councils and religious institutions that supported his party. A
shekel is worth about 50 cents.
   Police later opened an investigation into these suspicions, and
some in Deri's party later threatened to bolt Shamir's coalition
unless the inquiry was dropped.
   Deri said Sunday he learned that the investigation was
``reaching its conclusion.'' He did not elaborate.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0068 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 2010EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-Palestinians     12-23 0189</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Palestinians,0188</SECOND>
<HEAD>Kuwait-Based Palestinians Allowed Rights To Sponsor</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DUBAI, United Arab Emirates (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Palestinians registered as
residents of Kuwait have been given the right to sponsor foreign
nationals who want to stay in the occupied emirate, travelers said
Sunday.
   Indians who fled Kuwait through Dubai en route home, speaking on
condition of anonymity, said thousands of Indians have acquired the
new Iraqi documents allowing them to stay in Kuwait, which Iraq
calls its 19th province.
   Members of the large expatriate population working in oil-rich
countries in the area can acquire residence permits only if they
are sponsored by local citizens, companies or government
departments.
   The sources said the Palestinians have been given the status of
a ``first class'' resident with the right to sponsor other
foreigners.
   Until Iraq's invasion of Kuwait, the Palestinians themselves
were under the sponsorship of Kuwaiti nationals. The sources said
the Palestinians stood by Iraq after it invaded Kuwait on Aug. 2
and now apparently have been rewarded.
   Kuwaiti exiles have accused Iraq of trying to repopulate their
country with Palestinians, Iraqis and others sympathetic to the
occupation.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0069 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 2027EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SriLanka     12-23 0344</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Sri Lanka,0399</SECOND>
<HEAD>30 More Dead in Government Offensive in Sri Lanka</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PATRICK CRUEZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>COLOMBO, Sri Lanka (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   At least 30 more soldiers and Tamil
rebels were killed on the third day of a government offensive,
military officials said Sunday.
   The bullet-riddled bodies of more than 50 Tamils, most of them
women, were found in two villages and in a lagoon in curfew-bound
Batticaloa, 135 miles east of Colombo, villagers said. But it was
unknown who killed the victims.
   In the offensive, government planes pounded a rebel camp at
Telipillai in the Jaffna eninsula on Saturday, killing 17 rebels,
the officials said.
   The Tamil Tiger rebels later killed nine soldiers during the
army's attempt to overrun the camp, according to the military
officials, who cannot be quoted under briefing rules.
   The Jaffna Peninsula, 185 miles northeast of Colombo, is the
Tigers' biggest stronghold.
   The rebels killed four other soldiers, including a captain, in
an ambush Saturday at Weli Oya in the Trincomalee district, about
140 miles northeast of Colombo.
   Villagers contacted by telephone said on condition of anonymity
that 15 of the bullet-riddled Tamil bodies were found in
Kurumanvelli, south of Batticaloa, and 17 at Kirankulam in the
west. They said at least 20 bodies, 15 of them female, were seen
floating in the Batticaloa lagoon.
   Military officials said they knew nothing about the bodies but
would investigate the reports.
   The government's newest offensive in the 7{-year-old war with
the Tamil guerrillas followed Wednesday's killing of Brig. Lucky
Wijeratne. Wijeratne, whose jeep was blown up by a land mine, was
the most senior officer killed in the revolt against the country's
Sinhalese majority.
   The latest deaths brought the toll in the offensive to 131
rebels and 24 government troops, according to government tallies.
   The Tigers, who seldom release casualty tolls, have issued no
statements on the latest fighting.
   More than 14,000 people have died since Tamil militants started
fighting in 1983 for a separate homeland for their ethnic minority.
   Tamils make up 18 percent of the 16 million people in Sri Lanka,
an island off the southern tip of India. They have long accused the
Sinhalese of discrimination in jobs, education and use of the
Sinhala language.
   Sinhalese, who comprise 75 percent of the population, control
the government and the military.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0070 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 2128EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-FatalFire 3rdLd-Writethru a0747 12-23 0325</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Fatal Fire, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0747,0384</SECOND>
<HEAD>Precede SHELDON, Mich.</HEAD>
<HEAD>Father, Six Children Die in House Fire</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 3rd graf, `Fire Capt. ...' to locate fire; Picks up 4th
graf pvs, `Paulun said ...'</NOTE>
<DATELINE>DETROIT (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A father and six of his nine children died in a
fire that started when the family's Christmas tree ignited in their
suburban Detroit home, authorities said Sunday.
   Martin Dellorco and six children between the ages of 4 and 12
were killed in the fire in Wayne County's Canton Township late
Saturday, said Fire Chief Melvin Paulun. Dellorco, 38, escaped at
first and then was killed when he returned to the house in a vain
attempt to save the children, authorities said.
   Fire Capt. Art Winkel said the fire, which apparently started
when the Christmas tree fell over in the family room, spread
quickly through the one-story home in the township 22 miles west of
Detroit. It was unknown how the tree fell or how the fire was
sparked after the fall, Winkel said.
   Paulun said Dellorco's wife, Debbie, 36, and their son Adam, 6,
escaped. Mrs. Dellorco was treated and released at St. Joseph Mercy
Hospital in Ann Arbor, hospital spokeswoman Margaret Kirkby said
Sunday. Adam did not require hospital treatment.
   Paulun identified the Dellorco children killed as Bonnie, 12;
Sara, 9; Katie, 8; twins Megan and Michael, 5; and Robert, 4. He
said the bodies were found throughout the house.
   Dellorco escaped and then ``re-entered to save his children,''
Paulun said. ``He was not successful and he died as a result.''
   The Dellorcos' two teen-age children - Jimmy, 16, and Kelly, 14
- weren't at home when the fire started.
   ``They wanted a big family. Someone was saying they wanted 13 or
14 kids,'' Chris Ruszkiewicz, 17, a neighbor and schoolmate of
Jimmy Dellorco at Plymouth-Canton High School, said Sunday.
   ``This is just awful.''
   Paulun said fire teams found the ranch-style house engulfed by
flames when they arrived about 11:15 p.m. He said intense heat
blocked firefighters from entering the house, and one firefighter
suffered minor burns.
   ``It was just something you can't describe,'' said neighbor Dawn
Ross, 18.
   The fire was under control about midnight, Paulun said.
   He said investigators were continuing their probe Sunday.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0071 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 2142EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Kashmir     12-23 0182</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Kashmir,0191</SECOND>
<HEAD>Soldiers Fire on Buses in Kashmir, Kill Five</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SRINAGAR, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Soldiers fired on two buses in the
Kashmir Valley, fatally wounding at least five passengers, police
and witnesses said Sunday. They said about 10 others suffered
lesser wounds.
   No immediate explanation surfaced for the shooting Saturday, but
the witnesses said Moslem militants attacked army troops in the
same area the previous day.
   One soldier was killed in Friday's attack, according to sources.
   The buses were fired Saturday on about six miles west of
Srinagar on the road linking Baramulla and Uri, police in Srinagar
and residents of the area said. All sources spoke on condition of
anonymity.
   Police and residents said three people died at the scene. Two
more people died Sunday of their wounds, the residents said.
   Srinagar newspapers reported eight people were killed, but there
was no confirmation.
   At least 1,692 people have been killed in Kashmir since Jan. 20,
when India launched a crackdown on an increasingly violent
secessionist movement by Moslems.
   Kashmir is part of Jammu-Kashmir state, the only Indian state
with a Moslem majority.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0072 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 2143EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Spain-Bus     12-23 0123</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Spain-Bus,0117</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ten Die in Spain in Van-School Bus Collision</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ARCHIDONA, Spain (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A van carrying eight Moroccans swerved
head-on into a bus filled with vacationing schoolchildren on a
foggy road, killing 10 people, police said Sunday.
   A civil guard said all eight Moroccans died in the crash
Saturday on the N-331 highway in southern Malaga province. He said
the 58-year-old Spanish bus driver and his son, 28, were also
killed and three schoolchildren were injured, one seriously.
   The bus was taking the children from Malaga to an excursion in
the nearby mountains. The Moroccans were believed to be heading
home from their jobs in France, said the guard, speaking on
condition of anonymity.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0073 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 2149EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-AlcatrazEscape 3rdLd-Writethru a0752 12-23 0538</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Alcatraz Escape, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0752,0668</SECOND>
<HEAD>Escape From Alcatraz: Nearly 30 Years Later, Escapees Still Sought</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 9th graf, `That interest ...' to delete extraneous word,
`aired'; Picks up 10th graf, `A woman ...'</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto FX1</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SAN FRANCISCO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Nearly three decades after three inmates
broke out of the island prison of Alcatraz, debate persists over
whether they made it across San Francisco Bay to achieve the only
successful escape from ``The Rock.''
   Many believe the men drowned in the bay's cold waters. But as
recently as two weeks ago, officials in Florida were still looking
for brothers Clarence and John Anglin and their companion Frank Lee
Morris, the San Francisco Daily Journal said in a report to be
published Monday.
   ``What we're looking at is the possibility that two of the three
escapees, the Anglin brothers, who were raised in this vicinity,
possibly escaped and came back to this area,'' U.S. Marshal W.L.
``Mac'' McLendon in Tallahassee, Fla., told the newspaper, a daily
that covers legal matters.
   Officials began looking for the Anglin brothers in the northwest
Florida area about two years ago and recently confirmed the search
was continuing.
   At least 41 known escape attempts were made at the prison from
1934 until it closed in 1963. But none of the would-be escapees -
with the possible exception of the Anglins and Morris - succeeded.
   The prison, which housed notorious criminals such as Al Capone,
George ``Machine Gun'' Kelly and ``Birdman'' Robert Stroud, is now
part of the Golden Gate National Recreation Area and a popular
tourist attraction.
   In San Francisco, Chief Deputy U.S. Marshal Richard Bippus would
only confirm that interest in the case was high.
   ``It's like a roller coaster,'' Bippus said. ``It goes uphill
and downhill. We're on an uphill right now. Our interest is more
active, let's say.''   That interest was revived in 1989, when a segment
about the June
11, 1962, escape was broadcast on the NBC-TV program ``Unsolved
Mysteries.''
   A woman who identified herself only as Cathy called the show's
tip number and said she recognized Clarence Anglin as a man who
lived on a farm near Marianna, Fla., McLendon said.
   The brothers also were linked to the area by a woman, who
recognized a photo of Clarence Anglin and said he lived near
Marianna. She correctly identified his eye color, height and other
physical features.
   Another witness identified a sketch of Morris, saying it bore a
striking resemblance to a man she had seen in the area.
   In 1986, Clarence Anglin's grandson claimed his grandfather had
died a free man in Iowa more than a decade after the escape and
that the other two men were eaten by sharks during the escape
attempt.
   The breakout from the institution, which prided itself as being
escape-proof, embarrassed prison authorities.
   The men first broke through barred air vents at the back of
their cells, giving them access to an interior utility corridor
separating the two halves of the three-tiered block of cells. All
three were housed on the ground floor.
   In that area, they spent months making things for their escape,
including life vests and at least one rubber raft, apparently using
pilfered raincoats.
   The night of their escape, they put dummies in their beds, broke
through the vents, scaled pipes to the roof, and dropped to the
waters below. Authorities believe they then inflated a raft or
rafts and launched them on chilly waters.
   Two life vests, a wooden paddle and a packet with pictures and
addresses belonging to the inmates later were found floating in the
bay. Some believe the men drowned trying to make the two-mile
crossing.
   But others, including Bippus, believe the items were planted to
throw officials off track.
   ``It would be nice if the Anglin brothers would turn themselves
in and we could get rid of this - and they could stop looking over
their shoulders,'' Bippus said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0074 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 2153EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Abduction     12-23 0240</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Abduction,0265</SECOND>
<HEAD>Seven Arrested After Daughter of Multimillionaire Ransomed</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Dollar figures are Canadian</NOTE>
<DATELINE>NORTH VANCOUVER, British Columbia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Seven people were
arrested in the kidnapping of the daughter of a Vancouver
multimillionaire who was freed after a ransom was paid, authorities
said Sunday.
   Few details were released about the abduction of 30-year-old
Cynthia Kilburn, who was kidnapped from her home in this Vancouver
suburb Friday morning and freed 14 hours later on Saturday. Police
did not disclose the ransom amount.
   Mrs. Kilburn was shaken, but otherwise unharmed during the
ordeal, Royal Canadian Mounted Police in North Vancouver said. Her
4-year-old twins, a boy and a girl who were bound and left at the
home, also apparently were unharmed even though they were left
alone most of the day.
   ``We're fine,'' Mrs. Kilburn's husband, Alan, said Saturday
night. ``It was pretty tense but we're fine.''
   Mrs. Kilburn is the daughter of Jim Pattison, who was chairman
of the Expo '86 World's Fair in Vancouver. His conglomerate, Jim
Pattison Group, owns several auto dealerships, a supermarket chain
and radio stations.
   Three men and four juveniles, including a girl, were arrested
late Saturday and early Sunday at various locations, police Sgt.
Bill Sharp said. Their names were withheld.
   ``We're very grateful to the Lord that everything turned out all
right,'' Pattison said after his blindfolded daughter had been
dropped off on a north Vancouver street corner. ``These kinds of
things make you aware that the world has got some circumstances
that you have to be aware of.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0075 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 2157EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-StormRdp 1stLd-Writethru a0718 12-23 0595</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Storm Rdp, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0718,0754</SECOND>
<HEAD>Roads Icy As Record Cold Continues, Deaths Reach 60</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: CORRECTS overline to conform to 0 deaths in text</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By ROGER PETTERSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Temperatures dropped as low as 39 degrees below zero Sunday as
the arctic cold wave refrigerated the western two-thirds of the
nation and edged toward the East with freezing rain and ice that
sent cars and trucks sliding.
   At the same time, record highs in the 60s and 70s extended from
New England to Georgia.
   Flooding forced the evacuation of hundreds of people in parts of
Kentucky, Tennessee and Alabama, where nearly a foot of rain had
fallen.
   At least 60 deaths had been blamed on the weather since the cold
began Tuesday. Most were traffic fatalities but some died of
hypothermia or from fires blamed on overworked heaters or
fireplaces.
   Hardest hit was Texas with 19 deaths, 16 in traffic accidents.
Many glazed bridges and roadways across the state were covered by
ice up to an inch thick Sunday.
   Ice also spread eastward with the advance of the cold. A
combination of snow, sleet and freezing rain fell on Indiana during
the night and Sunday morning. An ice storm moved into western
Kentucky. Freezing rain also swept across Pennsylvania.
   The coldest spot in the Lower 48 states was in northwestern
Colorado, at Craig, where Sunday's low was 39 degrees below zero,
the National Weather Service said. Denver hit a record 16 below.
   Wyoming's cold spot was Jackson with a reading of 35 below at
midmorning and a wind chill of 60 below. Cheyenne was above zero,
at 5, but the wind chill was 39 below.
   Arizona, the magnet for thousands of ``snow birds'' who annually
flee colder northern states, did not have one reporting station
with a low above freezing Sunday. Phoenix hit a record 26 and
Tucson dropped to a record 21.
   Albuquerque, N.M., dropped to 7 below zero Sunday, the first
time on record the city has gone below zero in December.
   The city that bills itself the ``Ice Box of the Nation,''
International Falls, Minn., took Sunday's low of 29 below in
stride. ``It's business as usual - you have no choice up here,''
restaurant owner Chris Mostad said Sunday.
   The cold air was pressing against a belt of unseasonably warm
air along the East Coast, and was expected to overrun the Northeast
on Monday.
   Record highs included 64 at Harrisburg, Pa.; 67 at Newark, N.J.;
65 at Boston; 58 at Burlington, Vt.; 69 at Baltimore; 72 at
Atlanta, and 73 at Richmond, Va.
   At Topsail Island, N.C. ``People are walking around here with
shorts and T-shirts on,'' said Kevin Hollis.
   ``It just doesn't seem like Christmas with this weather,'' said
Tom Chroniger, hitting baseballs with a friend at Burtonsville, Md.
   In California's Central Valley, the cold threatened about 80
percent of the navel orange crop still on trees, said Cliff Holland
of California Citrus Mutual in Visalia.
   ``Some of the growers I talked to had 14 hours at 26 and below
and that's going to cause damage,'' Holland said Sunday.
   Citrus growers in southern Texas checked their crops for frost
damage from below-freezing temperatures, but there was no immediate
word on crop loss.
   ``I've been here in '83 (during a severe freeze) and it's not
freezing like that at all,'' said Burt Purvis, who works on a
citrus farm near McAllen.
   Too much water, not ice, caused flooding from southern Indiana
across Kentucky and Tennessee into Alabama.
   In northern Alabama, flooding from nearly 1 foot of rain from
Friday night into Sunday chased dozens of residents from their
homes Sunday and rescue workers scurried to aid motorists stranded
on submerged roads.
   ``We can't turn the faucet off,'' said Fred Keeney, a planner
with the Morgan County (Ala.) Emergency Management Agency. ``We
don't really know how many evacuations. ... We've got a lot of
people who have been moved.''
   Flooding in southeastern Tennessee forced more than 450 people
from their homes and 600 were isolated with roads under water and
some bridges washed out, authorities said. The Tennessee Valley
Authority was releasing water from all of its dams after up to 5
inches of rain fell in the region overnight.
   Dozens of people were evacuated in southeastern Kentucky as
streams rose after days of saturating rain. Since Dec. 16, Bell
County has received 6.6 inches of rain, officials said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0076 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 2210EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brite-LotteryTipster     12-23 0221</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brite-Lottery Tipster,0245</SECOND>
<HEAD>Entertainer Correctly Predicts 2-2-2 - But Didn't Buy Lottery
Ticket</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ALLENTOWN, Pa. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Psychic entertainer Jim Karol began
closing his shows about a month ago with a tip: Play 2-2-2 in the
Pennsylvania Daily Number drawing on Dec. 22.
   ``Something just told me to do it,'' he said.
   When the numbers 2-2-2 came up Saturday night, Karol was happy
that those who followed prediction made a little extra money. He's
just sorry he wasn't among them.
   ``That's the part that stinks,'' he said.
   Karol performs on about 100 college campuses each year, at
dozens of charity benefits, company Christmas parties, and fire
company socials. He performed at the White House during last year's
annual Easter Egg Roll.
   He made his lottery prediction over and over - at the
Germansville Fire Company, before members of the Lehigh Valley
Traffic Club, to a Parents Without Partners support group and hotel
employees.
   ``I must have said that at at least 45 shows,'' Karol said. ``I
came in contact with literally thousands of people.''
   After watching Karol perform at the volunteer fire company hall
in Lehigh Township, Kenneth Hantz bought 2-2-2 tickets for
Saturday. Now, he's $1,000 richer.
   The number was popular statewide. Lottery officials said there
were 39,863 winning tickets - resulting in a payout of $13,883,700.
   ``I made so many people money tonight,'' Karol said. ``It's a
Christmas present for all the people.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0077 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 2210EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Iran-Navy     12-23 0125</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Iran-Navy,0123</SECOND>
<HEAD>Iran Merges Navy, Revolutionary Guards Naval Forces</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NICOSIA, Cyprus (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Iran's two naval forces were merged
Sunday in a move to streamline the chain of command and wipe out
overlapping functions.
   Tehran radio, monitored in Nicosia, said the merged naval forces
of the Islamic Revolutionary Guards Corps and the regular navy will
be commanded by Rear Adm. Ali Shamkhani, now chief of the navy.
   President Hashemi Rafsanjani had been trying to merge the two
forces since his election in July 1989, but had to move slowly
because the merger was opposed by the powerful Revolutionary
Guards.
   The merger is believed to be a big step toward a full merger of
the military and air force as well.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0078 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 2225EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Britain-SundayShoppin     12-23 0237</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Britain-Sunday Shopping,0258</SECOND>
<HEAD>English, Welsh Stores Defy Law, Open on Sunday</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hundreds of stores in England and Wales opened in
defiance of trading laws Sunday, taking advantage of one of the
last two shopping days before Christmas.
   The open violations of the law, in some cases advertised in the
newspapers, followed similar openings last week. For the large
stores, drawing thousands of customers, the fines levied against
them are not a hardship.
   Some managers reported ``absolutely fantastic'' business, the
shopworkers' union said it wasn't fair to the staffs, and the Keep
Sunday Special campaign said people were complaining that the shop
openings disrupted family life.
   The issue of Sunday trading has been controversial for years.
Prime Minister John Major said in Parliament last week that the
time was approaching for talks to find a compromise.
   The Keep Sunday Special campaign said it was ``inundated'' with
complaints from chain store staff under ``intolerable pressure'' to
work on Sundays.
   But Roger Boaden, director of the Shopping Hours Reform Council,
said most shop staff working Sunday were volunteers, many on
premium pay rates.
   The Marks and Spencer chain said it would consider opening
stores on Sundays only if it became legal. The chain opened its
branches in Scotland, where it is legal.
   At Hamley's, a big toyshop on London's Regent Street, a
spokesman said trading was ``absolutely fantastic. We had
approximately 1,000 people waiting outside the store when we opened
our doors at 12 o'clock, and it has been non-stop since then.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0079 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 2236EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-China-Cigarettes     12-23 0220</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-China-Cigarettes,0223</SECOND>
<HEAD>Newspaper: Armed Smugglers Spur Illegal Cigarette Trade in China</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Cigarette smuggling by gangs armed with assault
rifles and using high-tech equipment is rapidly spreading along
China's southeastern coast, the official China Daily's Business
Weekly said Sunday.
   It said illegal cigarette trade has become the sole source of
income in some villages, prompting calls for harsher penalties for
smugglers and better equipment for coast guards. The newspaper said
some people also recommended improving the quality of Chinese
cigarettes to reduce demand for foreign tobacco products.
   A Beijing tobacco industry official told the paper that
smuggling has caused a significant cut in state revenue from
tobacco sales, which are tightly controlled by the government.
   The report said officials estimated that smugglers brought 45
million cartons of cigarettes into China last year.
   The newspaper said smugglers with AK-47 rifles, bulletproof
vests and high-frequency walkie-talkies flourished in many coastal
villages. It also said smugglers use satellite navigation devices,
but gave no details of the operations.
   The paper said smokers complain that Chinese cigarettes don't
taste as good as foreign brands and are hard to smoke because they
have poor filters and the tobacco is loosely packed.
   ``You've got to keep on drawing on the cheaper, homemade ones
until your jaw swells,'' one smoker told the newspaper.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0080 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 2308EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Saratoga-Families     12-23 0381</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Saratoga-Families,0477</SECOND>
<HEAD>Families Mourn Deaths of Servicemen Killed in Boat Capsizing</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf-Capsize</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   The roses and birthday card for his 3-year-old daughter arrived
the same weekend naval Airman Larry Clark and 20 fellow servicemen
died in a naval accident half a world away.
   ``If anything happens to me before that day, remember Daddy
loves you very much,'' Clark wrote to his daughter, Tiffany, who
turned 3 on Sunday.
   The 21-year-old resident of Decatur, Ga., went on to tell his
child how he looked forward to watching her grow up.
   Clark and others were killed Saturday when their ferry capsized
as they returned to the aircraft carrier Saratoga following shore
leave near Haifa, Israel. Most of the men were in their early 20s.
   ``I feel like a part of me left when he left,'' said Raymon
Carrington, whose twin brother, Monray C. Carrington was among
those killed. ``My heart aches.''
   The seaman from the Pittsburgh suburb of North Braddock was 22.
   Also in mourning Sunday was Annie Jackson, who initially had
been sure her son, Timothy Jerome Jackson, wasn't among those
killed.
   Her son had promised her he would call everytime the Saratoga
went into port and he went ashore. ``I was sure he was on the
ship,'' she said.
   But Saturday at noon, Navy officers knocked at the door of the
family home in Anniston, Ala., to tell her the 20-year-old fire
control technician had been killed.
   It was the second tragedy in two years for the family of Airman
Apprentice Christopher B. Brown, 19, of the tiny south Georgia town
of Leslie. Brown's brother, Michael, died of leukemia at age 15.
   In Eminence, Ky., townsfolk mourned the death of Airman Brent A.
McCreight, who was well-known in the community as a 6-foot-7-inch
former high school basketball star.
   ``We just loved him here,'' said local resident John Berry,
whose son went to school with McCreight, 23. ``He was just like a
member of the family. They ran around together all the time, and he
worked here for me on the farm.''
   Also among the casualties was Randy L. Neel, 19, an airman
apprentice from Albuquerque who had wanted to become a news
photographer.
   ``He was all excited about being in Israel for Christmas time,''
said his mother, Colleen Neel.
   ``It's the worst thing that could happen to you,'' said Sheila
Settimi, whose son Jeffrey A. Settimi was killed. The 25-year-old
mess management seaman apprentice was a Fort Wayne, Ind., native.
   ``I feel angry in a sense,'' said Mrs. Settimi, who lives in
Hamilton, Ind. ``I don't believe President Bush should have put men
and women in this situation.
   ``And now I've been devastated; our worst fears have come
true.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0081 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 2334EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BabyRescue     12-23 0243</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Baby Rescue,0290</SECOND>
<HEAD>Firefighter Rescues 4-Year-Old Dangling from 3rd Floor</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto LA5</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BURBANK, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A 4-month-old child dangled from a
third-floor balcony in her father's loosening grip, but a
firefighter leaned out and scooped up the child, police said
Sunday.
   ``It was one of the most dramatic things I've ever seen,'' said
neighbor Mario Franchini after the rescue Saturday of the infant
and her father.
   Roldolfo Regaldo, 31, had taken to the balcony of an apartment
house at about 3:30 p.m. after an argument with his wife, and
threatened to jump with the sobbing child, police said.
   Spanish-speaking officers on the ground tried to talk Regaldo
down, while behind a door leading to the balcony other authorities
waited for a signal to jump out and restrain him, police said.
   When Regaldo stood up and moved toward the balcony ledge,
officers grabbed hold of him, but the baby started to slip from his
hand, police said.
   Firefighter Ron Pearlman leaned over the railing and grabbed the
child. Pearlman also nearly fell, but a police officer held onto
him and pulled him and the baby to safety.
   ``When I went in, officers were holding (Regaldo),'' Pearlman
said. ``Next thing I saw was the baby swing up. He still was
holding on to her. I felt, I gotta go get the kid. So I reached
over the side and grabbed the child's shirt.
   ``There was a tug-of-war, and I heard the shirt tear, so I
grabbed an arm,'' he said. ``Then the father let go, so I put my
other arm around her butt and pulled her in.''
   After the struggle, Regaldo was arrested for investigation of
attempting to murder his daughter.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0082 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 1551EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f BC-MovieFreebies     12-23 0261</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Movie Freebies,0296</SECOND>
<HEAD>Theater Chains Raise Ad Revenues by Giving Freebies to Moviegoers</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Advertisers looking for ways to get their
message to moviegoers are turning away from on-screen pitches and
hiring movie theaters to hand out free samples of candy, popcorn
and other goodies.
   United Artists, the largest movie chain with 2,500 screens,
handed out PB Max candy bars this month to patrons entering its
theaters in Los Angeles. UA also was to give moviegoers in its
Dallas theaters free boxes of Smart Foods popcorn.
   Cineplex Odeon, the second largest chain with 1,690 screens,
says it's handing out packs of sugar-free Dentyne chewing gum and
samples of men's cologne at the end of the movie, said Howard
Lichtman, executive vice president of marketing.
   ``If someone doesn't like a product, we don't want them leaving
it on the floor.'' he explained.
   Instead of paying for time on screen, companies pay chains fees
to hand out their products.
   Marketing experts believe this is one idea the audience won't
reject.
   ``People love free samples,'' said Susan Small-Weil, a
specialist in consumer behavior at New York-based ad agency
Warwick, Baker &amp; Fiore. ``In this case, advertising isn't an
uninvited guest. It's a welcome guest.''
   Both UA and Cineplex hope freebies will boost ad revenue lost
earlier this year when Walt Disney Co. and Warner Bros. studios
banned on-screen advertising at theaters that show their movies.
   ``The reduction of on-screen advertising is going to hurt us,''
said Cathy Kasberg, director of promotions and marketing at UA.
``Hopefully, this can give us another avenue for income.''
   UA hopes to hand out different products such as soap, pens and
frozen yogurt every weekend. Other chains have similar plans.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0083 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 1707EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-Forbes-Profitability     12-23 0321</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Forbes-Profitability,0361</SECOND>
<HEAD>Forbes Lists Most Profitable Companies</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Forbes-List</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Athletic footwear maker LA Gear showed the best
longterm profitability of public U.S. companies surveyed by Forbes,
the magazine announced Sunday.
   The Los Angeles-based company averaged an 83.2 percent return on
equity - primary earnings per share divided by common shareholders'
equity per share - in the past four years, according to Forbes'
calculations. In the last 12 months however, LA Gear's return on
equity fell to 27.8 percent, the magazine said.
   St. Louis-based Pulitzer Publishing ranked second with an 80.6
percent average return on equity in the past five years.
Atlanta-based chemical maker Georgia Gulf was third with 78.4
average ROE in the past four years.
   Forbes evaluated the profitability of 1,177 companies in 20
industries for its Jan. 7, 1991 annual report issue.
   Software maker Microsoft Corp., based in Redmond, Wash., was
ranked tops among the largest corporations. Microsoft had an ROE
average of 50.4 percent over the past five years, which landed it
in 16th place on the general list.
   To be considered among the largest companies, a firm had to have
sales of more than $1 billion and a minimum five-year average
return on equity of 22 percent, among other requirements.
   The median company in Forbes' survey had a five-year average ROE
of 14.6 percent, up from 14.3 percent in 1989. The latest 12-month
ROE for the firms dropped, however, from 14.4 percent to 12.1
percent.
   Leading Forbes' list of best-performing stocks was Blockbuster
Entertainment. The Fort Lauderdale, Fla.-based video rental company
had a five-year average stock price increase of 3,060.5 percent,
highest among the 1,078 stocks survey by Forbes.
   Cyprus Minerals, an Englewood, Colo.-based oil, gas and coal
company, had the highest rate of earnings-per-share growth with a
three-year average of 147.8 percent.
   Forbes considers companies with annual revenues of $400 million,
or $600 million for banks or electric utilities, for its annual
report issue. The only exception is biotechnology, where Forbes
waives the minimum. The magazine based its rankings on five-year
averages, but there were some exceptions to the rule.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0084 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 1707EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-Forbes-List     12-23 0173</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Forbes-List,0182</SECOND>
<HEAD>Forbes Most Profitable</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here's the top ten most profitable firms among
the public U.S. companies surveyed by Forbes magazine.
Profitability is based on return on equity - primary earnings per
share divided by common shareholders' equity per share.
   The name of each company is followed by its hometown and
five-year average return on equity in terms of percentage. Those
noted with an `a' are based on four-year numbers and those noted
with a `b' are based on three-year numbers.
   Forbes evaluated the profitability of 1,177 companies in 20
industries for its Jan. 7, 1991 annual report issue.
   
   1. LA Gear, Los Angeles, 83.2a
   2. Pulitzer Publishing, St. Louis, 80.6
   3. Georgia Gulf, Atlanta, 78.4a
   4. Delta Woodside Industries, Greenville, S.C., 63.7
   5. Allegheny Ludlum, Pittsburgh, 63.7b
   6. MagneTek, Los Angeles, 61.6
   7. Teledyne, Los Angeles, 60.9a
   8. Reader's Digest Association, Pleasantville, N.Y., 60.3a
   9. FHP International, Fountain Valley, Calif., 60.2b
   10. WTD Industries, Portland, Ore., 58.7
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901223-0085 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-23-90 1721EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-GasPrices     12-23 0162</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gas Prices,0175</SECOND>
<HEAD>Gas Prices Down An Average of Almost Six Cents</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Gasoline prices across the nation fell an
average of nearly 6 cents a gallon over the last two weeks, the
biggest drop since the Persian Gulf crisis, according to a survey
released Sunday.
   The average price for all grades of gasoline at full and
self-serve stations was 140.27 cents a gallon Friday, a drop of
5.79 cents from Dec. 7, according to oil industry analyst Trilby
Lundberg's survey of 13,600 gasoline stations.
   The average price of regular leaded gasoline at self-serve
stations last week was 125.87 cents a gallon, while regular
unleaded sold for 128.85 cents and premium unleaded was 144.79.
   Full-service regular leaded retailed for 152.31 cents a gallon,
regular unleaded averaged 153.94 cents and premium unleaded sold
for 167.62 cents.
   The first sign of a decrease since the Iraqi invasion of Kuwait
Aug. 2 was the last two weeks in October when prices dipped an
average of .18 cents a gallon.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
</Collection>
