<Collection>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0001 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 2351EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-CoastGuard-Smuggling 2ndLd-Writethru a0755 05-20 0437</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Coast Guard-Smuggling, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0755,0447</SECOND>
<HEAD>Report: Coast Guardsmen Helped Cocaine Smugglers in Florida</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 3rd graf pvs with 3 grafs to UPDATE with Coast Guard
saying it ended alleged conspiracy back in 1988.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Coast Guardsmen in the Florida Keys have worked
for cocaine smugglers, selling them agents' codes and disabling
patrol boats, according to a report broadcast Sunday.
   When they raided smugglers' homes, federal authorities found
records of secret radio frequencies, patrol schedules and codes
used in radio transmissions for every law enforcement agency in the
Florida Keys, NBC's ``Expose'' show reported.
   The report made no mention of when the alleged corruption
occurred. However, Lt. Cmdr. Jeff Karonis, spokesman for the Coast
Guard's southeastern district based in Miami, told The Associated
Press that the Coast Guard had put an end to the alleged conspiracy
back in 1988.
   ``The Coast Guard people involved were brought to justice and
are in jail right now. The system works and they're paying for
it,'' Karonis said after viewing the broadcast Sunday.
   The NBC report cited unidentified federal authorities and Tom
Cash, an official with the U.S. Drug Enforcement Administration in
Miami.
   Federal authorities probing the relationship between smugglers
and Coast Guardsmen named the case ``Operation Tempest.''
   At least 15 guardsmen assigned to the Islamorada station worked
for or with the smugglers they were assigned to catch, NBC reported.
   Admiral Paul Yost, Coast Guard commandant, said he was unaware
of any federal investigation of cocaine involvement in the Coast
Guard, NBC said.
   ``We've got almost no drug corruption _ one or two isolated
cases,'' Yost said.
   Four Islamorada guardsmen who crewed a high-speed boat intended
to intercept smugglers are in jail for taking cocaine from the
smugglers, NBC said.
   Art Sola, commander of the crew that allegedly stole cocaine
from smugglers for themselves, told NBC he and his fellow guardsmen
decided one afternoon to steal a kilogram of cocaine from a load
they found floating in the Atlantic Ocean 15 miles offshore.
   The cocaine was worth as much as $16,000 _ about the same as the
guardsmen's salary.
   ``It's easy. It's very easy. It's a lifestyle down there.
Everybody knows somebody who's involved in drugs or smuggling. It's
very easy to get hooked on,'' Sola said in an interview in jail.
   Another guardsman, Bobby Gosnell, got caught up in drug
smuggling but wound up murdered, NBC said. After he left the Coast
Guard, Gosnell bought a $500,000 home complete with an airstrip,
the station said.
   Gosnell was shot in the chest in a dispute over whether he
should cooperate with the federal investigation, NBC said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0002 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 0021EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-StormieJones     05-20 0225</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Stormie Jones,0234</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<HEAD>Stormie Jones Heading Back to Pittsburgh After Liver Shows
Rejection</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WHITE SETTLEMENT, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Doctors suspect Stormie Jones,
the world's first recipient of a heart-liver transplant, is
rejecting her second transplanted liver, and plan to examine her at
a Pittsburgh hospital, a spokeswoman said late Saturday.
   Stormie, 12, was scheduled to leave her home in this Fort Worth
suburb Sunday for Children's Hospital in Pittsburgh after her liver
enzyme count shot to dangerously high levels, said family friend
Theresa Millikan.
   Hospital spokeswoman Lynn McMahon said in a statement that
doctors suspect Stormie may be rejecting the second transplanted
liver she received Feb. 20.
   Stormie's condition has been constantly monitored since she
became the world's first heart-liver transplant patient on Feb. 14,
1984.
   The youngster's first transplanted liver was damaged by
hepatitus caused by an unknown virus.
   Doctors thought she was progressing well after the second
transplant, but increasing evidence of rejection became clear in
recent tests.
   Stormie's liver enzyme count, a figure used to measure
rejection, was between 550 and 600 on Friday morning, an extremely
high level. By Saturday, it had shot up to 1,300, Mrs. Millikan
said.
   Stormie rested Saturday night at her home.
   ``Stormie is real nervous,'' Mrs. Millikan said. ``She doesn't
want to be stuck with any more needles. She told us she's had
enough.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0003 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 0054EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-BoatAccident     05-20 0175</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Boat Accident,0180</SECOND>
<HEAD>Pleasure Boat Strikes Bridge Pillar on Rain-Swollen Missouri River</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ST, CHARLES, Mo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A pleasure boat struck the underpinning
of a highway bridge Saturday night on the rain-swollen Missouri
River, slightly injuring 22 passengers sent sprawling across decks
by the impact.
   The double-decked boat, the Spirit of St. Charles, struck a
bridge pillar as it tried to turn downstream, said Ray Kemp, public
affairs officer for the St. Charles County ambulance service.
   ``There was a lot of screaming because the impact was pretty
strong,'' he said. ``A little girl fell down some stairs, but she
wasn't seriously hurt.''
   The injured were treated at St. Joseph Health Center, said
Barbara Wussler, the center's community relations director. They
were treated for minor injuries, she said.
   The boat, carrying 217 passengers, returned to a shore of the
river, which crested Friday night at St. Charles 10 feet over its
25-foot flood stage.
   The extent of damage to the boat was not immediately determined.
   St. Charles is about 20 miles west of St. Louis.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0004 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 0113EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-FloodRdp 2ndLd-Writethru a0615 05-20 0780</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Flood Rdp, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0615,0798</SECOND>
<HEAD>Trinity, Red Rivers Continue Carrying Flood Waters To Gulf</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: INSERTS 1 graf after 6th, `The Red ...' to UPDATE with Hot
Springs, Ark., flooding. Pick up 7th graf, `About 1,000 ...' With
AM-Flood-Evacuees, Bjt</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos HT4,3</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN A. BOLT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Flood-swollen rivers in Texas and Louisiana rushed across
thousands of acres of normally dry land to the Gulf of Mexico on
Saturday, and President Bush made a close-up survey of the
destruction.
   Some rain was forecast for parts of Texas, including the
southeast where the Trinity River is in record flood because of
storms weeks ago in northern Texas.
   Flooding and stormy weather have killed 13 people in Texas, two
in Illinois and one in Oklahoma since April 15, and one person was
missing in Missouri. Thousands of people have been evacuated at
various times in Texas, Oklahoma, Arkansas and Louisiana. Estimates
still are being compiled on the amounts of damage to crops and
property but it is expected to exceed hundreds of millions of
dollars.
   Scattered flooding also was reported Saturday in parts of Iowa
and Illinois and residents cleaned up after floods in Indiana and
Mississippi.
   ``In Louisiana we have one commodity ready to harvest, winter
wheat. That's gone in the flooded areas,'' said Larry Michaud, of
the state Agriculture Department. ``There will be extensive damage
to the cotton in the area.''
   The Red River was returning to its banks in Arkansas, but
preliminary damage estimates were rising.
   Heavy rain Saturday caused flooding in Hot Springs, where water
up to 4 feet deep rushed along a downtown street, police said.
Store workers used sandbags to hold back the rain.
   About 1,000 cattle, valued at $700,000, drowned in Arkansas'
Little River County, said Jim Barnes, executive director in the
county for the Agricultural Stabilization and Conservation service.
Damage to homes and other buildings was estimated at $1.5 million.
   Bush, on a weekend visit to Texas, briefly visited the
Livingston Dam on the Trinity River in southeastern Texas, and flew
over flooded areas downstream on the river northeast of Houston.
   ``This is remarkable,'' Bush told Polk County Judge Wayne Baker.
``I remember it was fairly dry here not too many years ago.''
   The Federal Emergency Management Agency announced Saturday that
three more Texas counties were declared disaster areas due to
spring flooding, bringing the total to 41 of the state's 254
counties.
   Flood crests moving down the Trinity had forced managers of the
Livingston Dam to release water through the spillways at the rate
of 100,800 cubic feet per second or 756,000 gallons a second since
Thursday morning.
   An estimated 7,000 people living in scattered, low-lying
subdivisions downstream from the dam were warned a week earlier
that they should evacuate.
   About 100 river miles downstream, at the town of Liberty, the
Trinity was already 5 feet over flood stage, said Sandra Sanford, a
volunteer at the county's emergency services office.
   ``If it rains, we may have some more problems,'' she said.
``We're praying we don't get any more rain storms.''
   ``They realize that the river's still coming up but some people
just don't want to leave,'' she said.
   In Louisiana, officials said the swollen Red River probably has
done most of its damage, but forecasters warned farmers and
riverfront businesses along the upper Mississippi River to prepare
for high water from storms in the Midwest.
   The Red was expected to crest at 40 feet, eight above flood
stage, Sunday at Alexandria in central Louisiana. But levees and
floodgates protect most of area between Alexandria and Avoyelles
Parish, where the Red meets the bigger Atchafalaya River, officials
said.
   At least 90,000 acres _ about 140 square miles _ of farmland has
been flooded in Louisiana, government officials said.
   The Army Corps of Engineers had predicted that 350,000 acres of
farmland and about an equal amount of forest land would be flooded.
However, corps hydrologist Frankie Griggs said those estimates had
not been revised to take into account flood crests a foot lower
than originally expected.
   In western Iowa, more than 200 people living along Perry Creek
in Sioux City, including 77 from a nursing home, were evacuated
early Saturday because of a flash flood, but were able to return
home after sunrise. The flood followed as much as 4.5 inches of
rain overnight.
   Southern Illinois braced for more storms and the prospect of
flash flooding Saturday, as rivers strained to handle the runoff of
almost 7 inches of rain in a little more than a week.
   Most Missouri rivers were receding, but the Red Cross said
Saturday that 208 Kansas City-area homes had been destroyed and 312
suffered major damage.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0005 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 0114EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Israel-Shooting 1stLd-Writethru a0621 05-20 0279</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel-Shooting, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0621,0283</SECOND>
<HEAD>Israeli Kills Seven Palestinians, Wounds 10</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 4 grafs to restore time element to lead, update
that gunman not soldier but civilian, add additional details.
Pickup 5th graf pvs: The deaths ...</NOTE>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A 20-year-old Israeli armed with a U.S.-made
M-16 assault rifle opened fire Sunday on a group of Palestinians
waiting to go to work in a town south of Tel Aviv, killing seven
and wounding 10, Israel radio said.
   It was the bloodiest attack by an Israeli against Arabs since
the start of the 29-month-old Palestinian uprising.
   The radio initially said the gunman was apparently an Israeli
soldier, but later identified the suspect as a 20-year-old
civilian. He escaped in a car belonging to one of the Palestinians,
but was taken into custody after contacting police, the radio said.
   The shooting took place around 6 a.m. Sunday in the town of
Rishon Letzion, south of Tel Aviv, in a park where Palestinian
laborers from the occupied territories wait to be picked up for
jobs in Israel.
   The deaths raise to 688 the number of Arabs killed by Israelis
in the uprising. Forty-three Israelis have also died in the
violence.
   In April 1989, a lone Israeli wearing army fatigues opened fire
with an Uzi submachine gun on a group of Palestinians sitting
outside of the old, walled city of Jerusalem, killing one Arab and
wounding three others.
   A man claiming to be from a radical underground group called the
Sicarites claimed responsibility for the attack. The group has also
claimed responsibility for a number of failed attacks on left-wing
Israelis.
   No arrests were made in the Jerusalem attack.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0006 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 0150EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Prejean-Governor'sCall     05-20 0268</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Prejean-Governor's Call,0276</SECOND>
<HEAD>Governor Telephones Dalton Prejean Shortly Before Execution</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ANGOLA, La. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Gov. Buddy Roemer telephoned Dalton Prejean
shortly before his execution and told the killer he had to die to
serve society, Prejean's lawyer said.
   Prejean requested to speak with the governor and Roemer called
90 minutes before Prejean walked to the death house at Louisiana
State Penitentiary for his execution early Friday, said the lawyer,
John Hall.
   ``The governor said he thought his execution was the only thing
that would serve society and give the proper message back to people
who were thinking about killing police officers,'' Hall said.
   The governor and Prejean talked for about 10 minutes, Hall said.
Roemer already had refused to halt Prejean's execution in
Louisiana's electric chair.
   Prejean, 30, became the first murderer to die under the U.S.
Supreme Court's 1989 ruling that allowed the death penalty for
crimes committed by 16- and 17-year olds.
   Prejean, who was nearly retarded, was executed for the 1977
murder of state trooper Donald Cleveland, killed during a traffic
stop in Lafayette. Prejean was 17 then and had served more than two
years in reform school for killing a taxi driver when he was 14.
   Prejean told Roemer that allowing him live to tell his story to
troubled youngsters could help keep them from lives of crime, Hall
said.
   ``Dalton spoke of his remorse and the sorrow and pain he had
caused others and said he thought he could reach people, that
people could learn from him,'' Hall said.
   Roemer's spokesman, Rusty Jabour, confirmed the conversation
occurred but would not reveal details.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0007 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 0232EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Korea 1stLd-Writethru a0511 05-20 0754</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Korea, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0511,0776</SECOND>
<HEAD>Thousands of Students Barricade University Campus</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Leads with 15 grafs to UPDATE with Sunday protests, police
storming campus. Pickup 9th graf pvs: Students used ...</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos KWG1,2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By C.W. LIM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>KWANGJU, South Korea (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Several thousand riot police firing
tear gas stormed a university campus Sunday to break up an
anti-government rally by 5,000 students and workers.
   Radical students and workers wielding metal pipes, rocks and
firebombs battled police amid a thick fog of tear gas on the campus
of Chosun University.
   Elsewhere in this provincial city, more than 10,000 students
rallied at the national Chonnam University, burning a giant U.S.
flag and shouting insults at thousands of riot police outside the
campus.
   Police officials said a student from Seoul died in a hospital
Saturday of massive head injuries suffered after he jumped off a
speeding train on the outskirts of Kwangju.
   Police said Shin Jang-ho,21, a sophomore at Daeyu Vocational
College in Seoul, was among several hundred students who jumped to
avoid being arrested at the Kwangju Railway Station. Police checked
identities of all students arriving in Kwangju by train, car and
bus in an effort to prevent outsiders from joining the protesters.
   At a downtown hospital where Shin's body was kept, about 500
students, armed with steel pipes and firebombs, stood guard. Police
officials expressed concern the death might further radicalize the
students.
   At Chosun University, about 2,500 riot police supported by four
armored vans firing hundreds of volleys of tear gas stormed the
campus as about 5,000 workers and students were starting an
anti-government rally.
   ``Down with (President) Roh Tae-woo,'' protesters shouted, as
they dashed through thick clouds of tear gas to charge the police
lines.
   About 300 protesters barricaded themselved on the roofs of
several school buildings, pelting police with rocks and firebombs.
   About a dozen police officers were injured and evacuated. Some
women protesters, overcome by the tear gas, were carried into
campus buildings by colleagues.
   At Chonnam University, about 25,000 students held a rally
overnight during which they demanded the ouster of Roh and U.S.
troops based in Korea. ``Yankee go home,'' students screamed
jabbing their hands in the air.
   The students planned to hold a mass anti-government rally Sunday
in central Kwangju with dissident groups. Police said the rally
would be illegal, and they planned to block it.
   Early Saturday, about 3,500 police supported by armored tear-gas
vans surrounded the Chonnam campus and searched all visitors. About
230 students were arrested, police said.
   But as news of the student's death spread, the riot police
withdrew, apparently to avoid provoking protesters.
   The number of students at the school increased sharply after the
police departed.
   Students used tires, school desks, chairs and broken furniture
to erect 10- to 12-foot-high barricades at the university's three
gates. More than 500 students armed with 3-foot-long metal pipes
stood guard inside each one.
   ``Our nation has no hope until (President) Roh Tae-woo and the
United States are ousted,'' student leader Song Gap-suk told a
rally.
   Song, a fugitive being sought by police for instigating violent
protests, said the U.S. military presence in South Korea is a major
obstacle to Seoul's unification with communist North Korea. The
crowd applauded and cheered wildly.
   About 43,000 U.S. troops are stationed in South Korea.
   In downtown Kwangju, several groups of 50 to 100 students hurled
rocks and firebombs at riot police in sporadic clashes during the
day. Police dispersed them with tear gas.
   About 7,000 people rioted in the streets of this city on Friday,
the 10th anniversary of a pro-democracy revolt that was crushed by
the military. At least 200 civilians were killed in the 10-day
uprising, the worst in modern Korean history.
   Friday's protesters attacked police with rocks and firebombs and
demanded the ouster of Roh.
   The anniversary also was marked by protests in more than a dozen
other cities, and police said about 5,300 people were arrested.
   Police said all but 481 of the 4,325 arrested in Seoul had been
released. They said 123 people were arrested in Kwangju and that at
least were 20 injured.
   Anti-U.S. and anti-government sentiment is strong in Kwangju, a
city of more than 1 million people 156 miles south of Seoul. Many
citizens feel the United States stood by and condoned the bloody
suppression in 1980. Washington repeatedly has denied the charges.
   The U.S. cultural center in the city was forced to close last
year after it was attacked by radicals 28 times since the early
1980s.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0008 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 0247EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-HelicopterCrash     05-20 0183</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Helicopter Crash,0189</SECOND>
<HEAD>One Killed in Crash of Marine Corps Helicopter</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SALTON CITY, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Marine Corps helicopter crashed
during a training flight Saturday, killing one of six crew members,
officials said.
   The CH-53D helicopter had mechanical difficulty and crashed
about 15 miles south of Salton Sea, said a statement from the 3rd
Marine Aircraft Wing headquarters at El Toro Marine Corps Air
Station.
   The conditions of the five survivors were not immediately
available. The names of all six crew members were withheld pending
notification of relatives.
   The cause of the crash was under investigation.
   The CH-53D, or Delta model, is known as the ``Sea Stallion.'' It
is powered by two engines.
   In 1985, 17 Marines were lost at sea and presumed dead when a
Sea Stallion crashed off the southern coast of Japan. In 1987, four
Marines survived a fiery crash of a Sea Stallion in the Arizona
desert.
   The helicopter was based at the Tustin station in Orange County
and was attached to Marine Heavy Helicopter Squadron 363.
   Salton City is about 55 miles southeast of Los Angeles.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0009 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 0305EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Romania 1stLd-Writethru a0546 05-20 0926</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0546,0952</SECOND>
<HEAD>Romanians Vote After Violent Campaign Polarized Country</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 6 grafs to UPDATE with polls opening, other
details. Pickup 2nd graf pvs: The elections ...; SUBS 7th graf,
Ballot counting ..., to clarify that preliminary results expected
Monday, pickup 8th graf pvs: State-run television...</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto XBUC5</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By EDITH M. LEDERER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUCHAREST, Romania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Romanians went to the polls Sunday in
their first free elections in more than 50 years after a violent
campaign that polarized and politicized this former hard-line
Communist country.
   Some 12,400 polling places opened throughout the country at 6
a.m., as voters turned out to choose a president and members of a
506-seat, two-chamber parliament.
   ``These elections are a step toward democracy,'' said Alexandru
Georgescu, who cast his ballot for the National Peasants Party, one
of Romania's old parties which was dissolved by the Communists in
1947.
   Georgescu, who also was supervising voting at the Dorobanti
polling station in downtown Bucharest, said some 45 out of 3,600
registered voters in the district cast ballots in the first half
hour after the polls opened.
   ``We're voting for our future and happiness. We hope to get
higher pensions and more medicines,'' Vasile Asafiei, a pensioner,
told The Associated Press.
   The elections drew about 500 foreign observers and the attention
of a world eager to see whether Romania is truly on the road to
democracy. Government officials promised that it would be a clean
election.
   Some feared Romania's history of election fraud and intimidation
would be repeated, including protesters who have a held a four-week
demonstration against the interim government and blocked the city's
main thoroughfare.
   But others said the secret balloting for president and a
two-chamber Parliament will be fair.
   ``The world is watching and that has a cooling effect on those
with hot heads, and it gives a powerful push for those people who
want tolerance and fair elections,'' said one observer, Jim King,
senior vice president of Northeastern University in Boston.
   Gen. Corneliu Diamandescu, first deputy interior minister, told
the daily Tineretul Liber Saturday that 40,000 police and army
troops would be deployed at polling centers to ``prevent or
neutralize manifestations of disorder, acts of hooliganism,
violence or rumors which could provoke panic.''
   The first preliminary results were not expected until Monday,
and the final official tally is due to be released Friday.
   State-run television devoted its entire evening news program
Saturday to coverage of the election and promises by officials that
they would be fair.
   A government statement exhorted the more than 16 million
eligible voters to turn out for the first democratic election since
1937.
   One American observer, Professor Radu Florescu, read a statement
on TV by Sen. Edward M. Kennedy, D-Mass., promising that the United
States would restore Romania's most-favored-nation trading status
if the elections were clean.
   Romania lost the preferential status in 1988 because of human
rights abuses by the regime of Nicolae Ceausescu, who was toppled
in December's popular revolution and executed.
   The latest opinion poll, published Saturday, gave interim
President Ion Iliescu and his National Salvation Front, which took
power during the revolution, an overwhelming 70 percent of the vote
in the three-way presidential race.
   Radu Campeanu of the National Liberal Party had 11 percent,
followed by Ion Ratiu of the National Peasants Party with 7 percent.
   The nationwide poll of 2,250 people was conducted May 11 to 18
by what the state Rompres news agency described as the
non-government and apolitical organization Dacia.
   The Front, a loose grouping of former Communists, workers and
technocrats, says it favors a gradual move toward a free market
economy to avoid high unemployment. The Liberals and Peasants,
backed by young people and intellectuals, favor a more rapid move
to Western-style capitalist economy.
   Seventy parties across the political spectrum fielded candidates
for Parliament, but only half a dozen had a chance of winning seats.
   Romania was the only East European country to break violently
with its Communist past, and its election campaign has been marred
by violence. Several opposition party workers were reported killed,
and Ratiu and Campeanu narrowly escaped being mobbed and lynched.
   Opposition parties have accused the Iliescu government of
maintaining control over radio, television and newsprint, thereby
denying them unrestricted access to the voters.
   King said he believed the government had not done enough to stop
harassment and intimidation. He said he had seen policemen stand
and watch as people were beaten at rallies.
   ``The Romanian society is not a tolerant society,'' said King,
one of 60 observers sponsored by the U.S. Democratic and Republican
parties. ``It has no history of democracy, and it relies in many
key areas on the government to set the tone and the direction for
conduct.''
   Campaigning officially ended Thursday night, and as of Saturday
night no further violence had been reported.
   Only the anti-Communist demonstrators in central Bucharest's
University Square ignored the ban on political campaigning,
repeatedly denouncing Iliescu and the Front as neo-Communists.
   Many of the 700 protesters in the square on Saturday said they
feared the elections will be rigged.
   ``They will fiddle with the votes in the computers, and we are
scared of the outcome,'' said Beatrice Andrei, 23, who has spent 20
days sleeping in the tent-camp in the square.
   The government Saturday night appealed to the demonstrators to
leave the main thoroughfare they have blocked for 28 days to allow
traffic through during voting hours.
   Protest leader Dumitru Dinca said Friday the demonstrators would
remain until Romania has a democratic government untainted by links
to Ceausescu.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0010 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 0411EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a BC-SudanEarthquake     05-20 0144</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Sudan Earthquake,0147</SECOND>
<HEAD>Southern Sudan Struck by Strong Earthquake</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MENLO PARK, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A strong earthquake measuring 7.5 on
the Richter scale struck southern Sudan early Sunday, the U.S.
Geological Survey said.
   ``We have had no reports of injuries or damages, but both could
be expected from an earthquake of this magnitude,'' said Pat
Jorgenson, a spokeswoman for the agency in Menlo Park.
   The temblor's epicenter was near the Nile River about 700 miles
south of Khartoum, capital of the African country, she said.
   The earthquake struck at 4:22 a.m. Sunday, Sudanese time, or
7:22 p.m. PDT Saturday, Ms. Jorgenson said.
   The Richter scale is a measure of ground motion as recorded on
seismographs. A 7.5 magnitude earthquake is considered a major
earthquake and capable of widespread heavy damage, but Ms.
Jorgenson said she did not know how populated the region is.
 
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0011 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 0553EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i BC-Sudan-Earthquake 1stLd-Writethru a0629 05-20 0467</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Sudan-Earthquake, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0629,0480</SECOND>
<HEAD>Precede MENLO PARK</HEAD>
<HEAD>Major Quake Strikes Near Southern Sudan's Largest City</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Writesthru, precedes Menlo Park-datelined story, adds
details, comments by Egyptian geologist, background on region where
quake struck.
^By MIMI MANN</NOTE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CAIRO, Egypt (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A major earthquake rocked southern Sudan
early Sunday near the war-torn region's largest city, which is
crammed with refugees.
   There were no immediate reports of damage or injuries, but
experts said widespread destruction was virtually certain given the
magnitude of the quake.
   Scientists said the quake's epicenter was only 60 miles
northeast of the city of Juba, whose normal population of 125,000
has more than doubled with people fleeing the country's civil war.
   The epicenter was near the Nile River, about 700 miles south of
Khartoum, the capital of the African country.
   Most of southern Sudan is controlled by the rebel Sudan People's
Liberation Army. Western relief workers are posted in Juba and
other major cities still controlled by the government.
   The quake, registering 7.5 on the Richter scale, occurred at
4:22 a.m., said geologist Rashad M. Kebeasy, president of Egypt's
National Research Institute of Astronomy and Geophysics.
   The quake was registered by Egypt's two principal seismic
monitoring stations, Kebeasy said.
   Pat Jorgenson, a spokeswoman for the U.S. Geological Survey in
Menlo Park, Calif., reported identical data.
   ``It's such a big quake that the monitoring stations are
saturated with data, so it's difficult to get everything precise
right now,'' Kebeasy said. ``This is an extremely dangerous
earthquake. It is the first time that such a quake has struck this
area.''
   Kebeasy, an expert on earthquakes in northeast Africa, said the
epicenter lies just west of the Great African Rift, an earthquake
zone stretching 4,000 miles from Mozambique through the Red Sea to
Lebanon.
   Its proximity to the rift accounts for the quake's ferocity,
Kebeasy said.
   ``Warn people to beware,'' he said. ``We can expect large and
very dangerous aftershocks for the next two days,'' he said.
   The Sudan People's Liberation Army launched its rebellion in
1983, demanding greater autonomy and economic reforms for the
country's three southern provinces, whose population is mostly
animist or Christian. The rest of the country is predominantly
Moslem.
   Hundreds of thousands of people, mainly civilians, have died
either from the fighting or the famine it has caused.
   The Richter scale is a gauge of the energy released by an
earthquake, as measured by the ground motion recorded on a
seismograph.
   Every increase of one number, say from magnitude 5.5 to
magnitude 6.5, means that the ground motion is 10 times greater.
   Magnitude 7 is considered a major earthquake capable of
widespread, heavy damage. Magnitude 8 is a great earthquake,
capable of tremendous damage. The October 17, 1989, earthquake near
San Francisco measured 7.1 on the Richter scale.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0012 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 1021EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i BC-Israel-Shooting 4thLd-Writethru   05-20 0825</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Israel-Shooting, 4th Ld-Writethru,a0636,0848</SECOND>
<HEAD>Israeli Kills Seven Palestinians; Rioting Leaves Five More Dead</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Leads with 7 grafs to UPDATE with final police report on
assault saying 7 dead, 11 wounded. Pickup 8th pvs, `Police said...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By ELLEN SACHECHET</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>RISHON LETZION, Israel (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A former Israeli soldier armed
with an assault rifle killed seven Palestinian laborers and wounded
11 on Sunday. The unprovoked attack caused widespread rioting in
the occupied territories that left at least five more Arabs dead
and hundreds injured.
   The assailant, dressed in army pants and a black jacket,
confronted the laborers, ordered them to sit in a line, then opened
fire, police said. The victims apparently followed his orders
because they mistook him for a soldier.
   The army called up reinforcements and imposed curfews on the
entire Gaza Strip and half a dozen refugee camps and cities in the
West Bank, confining more than a million people to their homes.
   But Palestinians wild with anger over the assault on the
laborers outside Rishon Letzion, near Tel Aviv, defied the
stay-at-home orders and attacked army outposts, stoned passing
Israeli cars and blocked roads, Arab reports said.
   Prime Minister Yitzhak Shamir went on Israel radio to condemn
the attack on the laborers and called on Palestinians to ignore
agitators who sought to incite riots in the occupied lands, already
torn by the 29-month-old uprising.
   ``We were all disgusted by the terrible crime that happened
today. It is a cruel crime without any justification,'' Shamir said.
   Police and witnesses said up to 50 laborers were present during
the attack and that seven were killed and 11 wounded, five
seriously. An earlier police report had said that eight
Palestinians died in the attack.
   Police said the shooting of the unarmed Palestinian laborers at
a busy road junction was the gravest incident of its kind in memory.
   They arrested a 21-year-old former soldier who was recently
discharged from the military after serving a jail term for defying
his commander.
   Arab reporters said five Palestinians were killed in Gaza and
two in the West Bank in rioting that followed the assault on the
laborers. Arab hospitals and United Nations clinics in Gaza
reported more than 400 injuries from live ammunition, rubber and
plastic bullets, beatings and tear gas inhalation.
   The army said at least five Palestinians were killed in rioting.
There were no immediate reports of deaths or injuries among Israeli
soldiers.
   In all, it was one of the bloodiest days since the Palestinian
uprising began and could rekindle the violence that had been
declining in the occupied territories in recent months. Before
Sunday's violence, 688 Palestinians and 43 Israelis had died in the
unrest.
   Police said the former soldier who carried out the attack took
his brother's Israeli-made Galil assault rifle.
   They said he hid in the underbrush near Rishon Letzion, a town
five miles south of Tel Aviv, emerging shortly after dawn to
confront a group of day laborers. He ordered to sit in a line.
   Khalil Abu Amsha, 30, a worker wounded in the left arm and leg,
said he was in a car that was flagged down by the gunman. Survivors
said they thought the gunman was a soldier because he wore army
pants.
   ``We thought he wanted to check the car,'' said Abu Amsha,
noting that 20 Palestinians were already seated on the ground when
the car pulled up.
   ``He said sit by your friends. We sat. He said take out your
magnetic (identity) cards. He said, `Do you know why I stopped
you?' We said no. He said, `Good that you don't know.'''
   Then he opened fire.
   Abu Amsha said he managed to roll into a ditch after being hit.
   The attack occurred about 100 yards from the busy Roses
Junction, an intersection outside Rishon Lezion. Arab laborers from
the Gaza Strip gather daily about dawn in a field near the
intersection to be picked up for construction work and other day
jobs jobs in Israel.
   Police said the assailant gave himself up at the home of a
friend. Police said the man gave a motive of unrequited love as the
reason for his attack.
   ``In interrogation, he sounded very relaxed. He didn't express
regret. He sat calmly and explained things,'' said Haim Klein,
police commander of the southern district. ``He spoke of personal
motives that brought him to do this. I don't know if that is
accurate.''
   Speaking on Israel army radio, Klein said the suspect did not
mention political motives, but ``the question arises if they were
personal motives, then why did he attack Arabs and not Jews?''
   Palestinian leaders blamed Shamir's right-wing government for
creating an anti-Arab atmosphere that encouraged extremist acts
against Arabs.
   Faisal Husseini, a prominent pro-PLO activist, said Shamir and
his allies had created a climate for anti-Arab actions.
   ``Even if this man is mentally sick the atmosphere created by
such a government is responsible,'' he told The Associated Press.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0013 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 1136EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-China-Sterilization     05-20 0277</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-China-Sterilization,0285</SECOND>
<HEAD>Authorities Sterilize 5,500 Retarded People in Chinese Province</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   China's first province to approve a mandatory
sterilization law for the mentally retarded performed 5,500
operations in the 14 months after the law took effect, an official
report said Sunday.
   Officials in the northwestern province of Gansu said their goal
was to sterilize most of Gansu's 260,000 mentally retarded
residents by the end of next year, the People's Daily newspaper
said.
   Since the law was enacted in January 1989, Gansu has set up a
diagnostic network and required examination for all couples
planning to marry. It also has sent teams to villages with large
numbers of mentally retarded to ``do ideological work among the
relatives and guardians.''
   Arid, remote Gansu, one of China's poorest regions, has several
large concentrations of mentally and physically handicapped people,
due in part to inbreeding in isolated villages.
   The People's Daily said one county had more than 700 mentally
handicapped people, but that medical teams had sterilized 516.
   China has said it is drafting a national eugenics law to reduce
``the births of inferior and abnormal children to a minimum,''
according to the official China Daily newspaper.
   The paper said the national law also would bar the mentally
retarded or people with hereditary diseases from marrying without
first being sterilized.
   The government says there are 50 million physically or mentally
handicapped people nationwide out of a population of more than 1
billion.
   China does not regard childbirth as a private matter. Healthy
parents in most areas of the country are restricted to one child,
with the timing of the birth decided by local authorities or one's
work unit.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0014 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 1136EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Jordan-Hairdressers     05-20 0330</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Jordan-Hairdressers,0340</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ministry Rescinds Ban on Male Hairdressers</HEAD>
<DATELINE>AMMAN, Jordan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The government rescinded a decree banning
male hairdressers from working in beauty parlors after a court
ruled the order was unconstitutional, an Interior Ministry official
said Sunday.
   ``The ban has been withdrawn and things will go back to what
they were before in a few days,'' the official said in an interview.
   The official, who spoke on condition of anonymity, said the
ministry moved after the Supreme Court ruled last week the ban was
``illegal ... a violation of constitutional provisions which
stipulate equal rights for men and women.''
   The ministry said May 6 it would no longer issue permits for
male ownership of beauty parlors and that male hairdressers could
no longer work in beauty shops.
   The court also overturned the ownership provision of the decree,
and it also was rescinded by the government.
   The decree against men associated with beauty parlors was the
result of pressure by Islamic groups, especially the influential
Moslem Brotherhood Movement, which has the largest bloc in Jordan's
80-seat parliament. Islamic tradition says men and women must not
mingle in public, and women are supposed to keep their hair covered
in the presence of strange men.
   But the ministry ban raised protests from moderate groups. Labor
unions, womens' organizations and human rights activists also
lobbied against the ban.
   Prime Minister Mudar Badran's government had earlier bowed to
demands by Islamic groups that included banning alcohol on Royal
Jordanian Airlines flights to Arab and Islamic countries. But he
rejected calls to close down bars and nightclubs in this
predominantly Moslem country of 3.1 million people.
   The Moslem Brotherhood emerged as the strongest party in
Parliament when it won almost two dozen seats in last November's
elections, the first in more than 22 years. Another dozen
independent Islamic activists were also elected.
   The Brotherhood pledged to introduce stricter Islamic laws, ban
lewd TV programs and limit women's freedom, including prohibiting
women from working.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0015 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 1136EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Obit-ArchbishopCan     05-20 0352</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Archbishop Can,0361</SECOND>
<HEAD>Vietnamese Archibishop Dies</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BANGKOK, Thailand (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Cardinal Trinh Van Can, the Roman
Catholic archbishop of Vietnam's capital city, has died of a heart
attack, the official Vietnam News Agency reported Sunday. He was 69.
   Can died Friday at his office in Hanoi, said the report,
monitored in Bangkok. A funeral will be held at the Hanoi Church on
Wednesday.
   The report said he was the founding president of the Vietnam
Episcopal Council and the apostolic administrator of Hue province,
in central Vietnam, and the dioceses of Hung Hoa, Thai Binh and
Thanh Hoa provinces, in the north.
   The Vatican said Sunday that Pope John Paul II sent a telegram
of sympathy to Vietnam's Auxiliary Bishop Francois Xavier Nguyen
Van Sang.
   Vatican radio called Can an ``unyielding asserter of the truths
of the faith ... (who) with no less vigor defended the
ecclesiastical institutions in the painful political and social
affairs of the country.''
   Can was born March 13, 1921, in Ha Nam Ninh province just
southeast of Hanoi. He entered the priesthood in 1949 and was made
co-adjutor to the archbishop of Hanoi in February 1963 and elevated
to cardinal in June 1979.
   The Vietnam News Agency said Can had presided over the First
Espisocal Congress of reunified Vietnam in 1980, at which an
epistle was issued affirming the Vietnamese Catholic Church's
policy of serving the nation.
   The North Vietnam Communists reunified the country after
toppling the U.S.-backed South Vietnam government in April 1975.
Large numbers of Catholics and other refugees fled the Communist
advance in a boat exodus.
   The authorities have eased restrictions on Catholics and other
believers since Nguyen Van Linh became Communist Party chief in
late 1986.
   However, the official Radio Hanoi reported Friday that
authorities have accused two Catholic priests in the southern city
of Ho Chi Minh of anti-Communist activities and put them under
surveillance.
   The report said authorities on Wednesday decided to force the
Rev. Chan Tin to move from his house and stay at his church and to
put the Rev. Nguyen Ngoc Lan under house arrest at another location.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0016 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 1137EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-China-MassSuicide     05-20 0267</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-China-Mass Suicide,0270</SECOND>
<HEAD>Police Stop Mass Suicide Plan in China</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Police prevented a mass suicide by more than 100
followers of a peasant woman preacher who said the world was coming
to an end and promised salvation, an official report said Sunday.
   The Workers' Daily said the followers, all residents of a
central China village, were prepared to drink poisoned liquor and
pesticides on the orders of Xiong Chenhua.
   The paper said the incident occurred in October in Henan
province's Tongbo Mountain district. Chinese newspapers often
report events weeks or months after they occur, being concerned
less with news than with teaching a lesson.
   More than 20 women were kneeling on the ground in yellow
clothing with red insignia, waiting for Xiong to return from a
meeting with Jesus, when ``more than 10 police descended from the
sky,'' the newspaper said sarcastically. The other followers were
waiting for the women to call them when it was time to take the
poison, it said.
   The brief report gave few details of Xiong's teachings, which
appeared to blend elements of Christianity with superstition. It
said she had been enlisted in 1985 by an older preacher, identified
as Old Woman Chen, who told her and several other women they would
go with her to heaven if they cultivated more believers.
   The women converted more than 100 people over the next few years
and collected regular donations, which they split among themselves,
the report said. It said that even after Xiong and the other women
admitted that they were frauds, the ``embarrassed believers still
said they believed.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0017 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 1142EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-CorporateTaxes     05-20 0633</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Corporate Taxes,560</SECOND>
<HEAD>Corporations Paying Higher Taxes in Wake of 1986 Tax Overhaul</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JIM LUTHER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Tax Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   U.S. corporations are paying higher taxes
since the 1986 tax overhaul but many profitable companies still pay
less than 10 percent of their earnings to the federal government,
congressional auditors have found.
   The average effective U.S. tax rate for 220 large companies rose
from 18.6 percent in 1986 to 27.8 percent a year later, the General
Accounting Office estimated.
   ``The increases ... seem consistent with the intent of the
changes introduced by the Tax Reform Act of 1986,'' which reduced
or eliminated several corporate deductions in exchange for lower
tax rates, GAO said last week.
   Reps. Donald Pease, D-Ohio, and Byron Dorgan, D-N.D., who had
requested the GAO report, hailed the findings.
   ``We're not prepared to make sweeping conclusions at this point,
but based on this report from the first year after tax reform ...
we're encouraged that tax reform is having the effect we
intended,'' the lawmakers said in a statement.
   The report found a narrowing of the wide disparities among how
much different industries pay in federal income taxes. But the gap
still exists.
   For example, the soap and cosmetics industry paid an effective
tax _ taxes paid divided by taxable income _ of 45.8 percent of
U.S. income; the rubber industry, 19 percent; computers, 12.4
percent; and automobile manufacturers, 3.9 percent.
   The effective rates paid by individual companies within an
industry group also vary widely, due not only to a company's
performance in a given year but bookkeeping methods as well.
   Chrysler Corp., for example, reported a 1987 pre-tax profit of
$1.8 billion and paid U.S. income tax of 11.8 percent. Ford had
nearly $5.3 billion in profits and paid 24 percent. General Motors
reported $1.3 billion profit but because of expenditures for
equipment, showed a negative tax rate of 99.9 percent.
   A negative tax rate occurred when 1987 earnings were exceeded by
expenses. In such a case a corporation could receive a refund of
taxes paid in some prior year.
   (GM had a refund of $1,303,800,000, which is stated as a
negative number in calculating the effective tax rate. Dividing the
refund by GM's earnings, $1,304,700,000, equals negative 99.9
percent.)
   Among oil companies, Exxon paid 23.5 percent tax on a $2.4
billion profit; Amoco paid 30.7 percent on profits of $1.2 billion;
and Texaco, whose pre-tax income was shown as a $6.5 billion loss
because of litigation growing from a takeover battle, paid a
negative tax rate of 3.5 percent.
   Overall, GAO found that 41 of the 220 companies had effective
U.S. tax rates in 1987 of less than 10 percent. They included:
Warner Communications, 2.2 percent; Rockwell International, 6.7
percent; International Business Machines, 0.3 percent; and Merrill
Lynch &amp; Co., 0.1 percent.
   On the other hand, 44 companies reported effective rates above
the 40 percent statutory rate that was in effect in 1987. Among
them: J.C. Penney Co., 47.5 percent; Sara Lee Corp., 50.7 percent;
and General Dynamics, 106.4 percent.
   By comparison, the Internal Revenue Service estimates an
individual with income in the $25,000-to-$30,000 range paid an
effective rate of 10 percent in 1987. Those with incomes above $1
million paid an average 28.7 percent.
   The GAO report dealt only with how the new law affected
individual corporations and industry groups. It did not address
whether corporations' share of all federal taxes is rising or
falling.
   A major goal of the 1986 law was to shift about $24 billion a
year of tax burden from individuals to corporations. Other
government reports indicate the shift has been considerably less
than that, due in part to lower-than-expected corporate profits.
   The failure of corporate taxes to meet forecasts is a key reason
that the budget deficit is worsening.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0018 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 1201EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-China-Anniversary     05-20 0365</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-China-Anniversary,0375</SECOND>
<HEAD>Security Stepped up for Martial Law Anniversary</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CHARLENE L. FU</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Police drastically increased security overnight
and set up roadblocks, but the Chinese capital was calm on the
first anniversary of the declaration of martial law that preceded
last year's crackdown.
   The government imposed martial law in Beijing on May 20 last
year, just five weeks after students began the massive
pro-democracy movement that drew hundreds of thousands of Chinese
into the streets.
   Premier Li Peng appeared on nationwide television then saying,
``The anarchic situation is going from bad to worse ... and we are
forced to take resolute and decisive measures to put an end to the
turmoil.''
   The military crushed the pro-democracy movement June 3-4, when
soldiers drove protesters from Tiananmen Square. Hundreds, perhaps
thousands, of people were killed and thousands more wounded.
   Until martial law was lifted on Jan. 11, soldiers or police
armed with semiautomatic rifles were stationed at key intersections
and bridges throughout the capital.
   Unlike April 15, when armed police ringed Tiananmen Square on
the anniversary of the start of the pro-democracy movement, the
plaza was open Sunday and full of people enjoying their day off
under sunny skies.
   The scene was very different overnight, however. At midnight
Saturday, police set up at least 14 checkpoints at major
intersections along Beijing's main thoroughfare, Changan Avenue,
and along a major road that circles central Beijing.
   The police, a few carrying semiautomatic rifles or pistols,
stopped bicyclists and cars, demanding identification papers and
sometimes searching cars and trunks.
   At one checkpoint, police emptied a van carrying about six
people and thoroughly searched the passengers' luggage.
   Three roadblocks were set up near the train station. A police
officer there shook his head when asked if the increased security
was because of the martial law anniversary. He refused to answer
other questions.
   At another checkpoint, a police officer insisted, ``This is
normal,'' when asked about the extra security.
   In the university district in western Beijing, there was no
visible security presence. Students sat at roadside food stalls
outside the gate of People's University eating midnight snacks, and
the gate to Beijing University remained open.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0019 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 1238EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Summit-Arms     05-20 0784</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Summit-Arms,740</SECOND>
<HEAD>Baker Trip Produces Enough for a Successful Washington Summit</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BARRY SCHWEID</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Diplomatic Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Secretary of State James A. Baker III brought
home from Moscow the ingredients of a successful Washington summit
meeting. But he almost flopped on limiting long-range nuclear
missiles.
   According to a senior U.S. official, a cruise deal Baker had
struck with Mikhail S. Gorbachev on Friday morning began to unravel
only a few hours after the Soviet president had said ``agreed.''
   By ``splitting the differences'' on air- and sea-launched cruise
missiles, Baker thought he had resolved one of the toughest
problems standing in the way of a summit declaration to cut
strategic nuclear weapons.
   He had accepted a Soviet proposal to limit airborne cruises with
a range above 375 miles and settled on 880 as the number of
sea-launched weapons to be revealed to the other side.
   The Soviets had taken a stricter line than the United States in
the negotiations. Baker met them halfway in return for excluding a
new U.S. air-to-surface missile called the Tacit Rainbow from any
limitations.
   The upshot: removal of the elusive missiles as an obstacle in
the way of Strategic Arms Reduction Treaty.
   Although the treaty will not be ready for President Bush and
Gorbachev to sign at their May 31-June 3 summit, a declaration on
key issues might be initialed.
   But ``the package that we thought had been put together began to
unravel,'' the official told reporters on Baker's flight home
Saturday night.
   The Soviets were trying to impose restrictions on the Tacit
Rainbow. What had loomed as a success was now in doubt. ``We
genuinely didn't know if we were going to get there,'' said the
official, who spoke on condition of anonymity.
   Baker, who had practiced law in Houston before turning to
politics, decided the solution was to write a letter. It would
assure the Soviets that the Tacit Rainbow carried conventional, or
non-nuclear warheads, and should not be restricted under a START
treaty even though its range will be above 375 miles.
   He telephoned Foreign Minister Eduard A. Shevardnadze, his main
bargaining partner through four days of tough talks, to describe
the letter and also to say if the Soviets tried to limit the Tacit
Rainbow the United States would not accept the 375-mile treaty
range.
   Shevardnadze called back after receiving the letter and said
``this is fine,'' the senior official related. The deal was back on
track.
   The problem apparently was persuading the Soviet military to
allow the Tacit Rainbow to be excluded.
   Baker went on to meet with the foreign minister on Saturday and
then to announce at a news conference before flying home:
   ``I think our discussions have resulted in some real
accomplishments. The progress we have made here makes me optimistic
that we will have a productive summit in Washington.''
   U.S. and Soviet negotiators will go back to the bargaining table
in Geneva this week to try to resolve some of the half-dozen
remaining START problems.
   These include the limits to be placed on ballistic missiles with
multiple warheads and the method of verifying compliance with a
START treaty.
   At the same time, a group of Soviet weapons experts will be here
at midweek to conduct parallel negotiations in Washington.
   A trailblazing accord to end chemical weapons production,
meanwhile, is ready to sign at the summit without further ado.
   Bush provided the impetus last week by offering to end
production of binary weapons _ two chemicals that are deadly when
mixed.
   The Soviets met his two conditions in Moscow.
   They agreed to produce a schedule for the destruction of their
chemical weapons stockpiles. And they accepted Bush's demand that
the two superpowers maintain small arsenals of the deadly weapons
until 40 nations negotiating in Geneva conclude a treaty to end
production and implement it.
   Some 24 nations are believed to either have poison gas or the
capacity to produce it. The U.S.-Soviet accord, Baker said,
``provides a real pathway toward a global ban on horrific weapons
that we already know from bitter experience actually get used.''
   On another front, however, a stalemate is developing.
   Baker failed to speed up a treaty to cut U.S. and Soviet troops,
tanks and other non-nuclear arms in Europe.
   Bush had predicted a year ago that it would take from six months
to a year to wind it up.
   But the Soviets evidently are reluctant to trim their forces in
Central Europe to 195,000 men unless the German army is sharply
reduced, as well.
   The impending merger of East and West Germany is causing anxiety
in Moscow. Memories of the loss of 20 million to 26 million people
in World War II linger on.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0020 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 1240EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Soviet-Baltics Bjt   05-20 0637</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Baltics, Bjt,0656</SECOND>
<HEAD>Lithuanians To Seek Compromise Formula on Monday</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ANN IMSE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Lithuanian lawmakers rejected Soviet President
Mikhail Gorbachev's demand that the republic suspend its
declaration of independence but planned to offer a compromise,
spokesmen said Sunday.
   In Estonia, anti-independence forces planned strikes at major
government-owned enterprises on Monday, but it was not clear how
much support they could muster. Similiar strike calls last summer
interrupted work at only a few dozen businesses in the Estonian
capital of Tallinn.
   Opponents of independence in Latvia, the third Baltic republic,
met in Riga, the capital, to form an alliance. The Soviet army
newspaper Red Star said the group included Communists loyal to
Moscow, military representatives and law enforcement organizations.
   All three Baltic republics were forcibly annexed by the Soviet
Union 50 years ago and now are in various stages of trying to break
free of Moscow's control.
   Gorbachev says the Baltic moves toward independence violate the
Soviet constitution. Lithuania has pushed the hardest, and he has
halted oil and natural gas shipments to that republic as part of an
economic embargo.
   Lithuanian legislators agreed late Saturday to reject
Gorbachev's demand that they suspend their March 11 independence
declaration because it would mean accepting Soviet control over
Lithuania, legislator Zigmas Vaisvilas said Sunday.
   No formal vote was taken on the issue, and the lawmakers planned
to reconvene Monday to draft a counterproposal, said Victoras
Balmusas, a parliamentary spokesman.
   During the debate, Communist legislator Eduardas Vilkas proposed
offering Gorbachev a deal that would suspend or cancel the March 11
declaration of independence in exchange for an end to Moscow's
economic blockade of Lithuania, a promise not to use force and
removal of some Soviet troops, Vaisvilas said.
   But most lawmakers agreed that tampering with the declaration
would be wrong, Vaisvilas said. That was in line with the advice of
Lithuanian Prime Minister Kazimiera Prunskiene, who met with
Gorbachev on Thursday night in Moscow.
   Parliament ordered a committee to work out other compromise
proposals to offer Moscow, Vaisvilas said.
   Gorbachev's had refused for two months to meet with Lithuanian
leaders. But he relented after the republic offered to suspend some
measures relating to the implementation of independence _ not the
actual declaration _ in exchange for negotiations.
   Lithuanian leaders said Gorbachev's decision to see Mrs.
Prunskiene may have been influenced by the fact that she was
meeting the following day with Secretary of State James A. Baker
III. Baker was in Moscow to settle the agenda for the superpower
summit at the end of May in Washington.
   ``It's very clear Gorbachev wanted to show President Bush before
the summit that he has started negotiations and he is not demanding
the same things as in the beginning,'' Vailvilas said.
   Baker told a news conference Saturday night that the United
States was ``encouraged'' by the fact that the two met, but said
results remain to be seen.
   In the Lithuanian capital, Vilnius, independence supporters kept
a vigil outside the parliament building through the weekend to
guard it from pro-Soviet demonstrators, reports said Sunday.
   Lithuanian radio, monitored by the British Broadcasting Corp.,
said the activists sought to prevent a repeat of incidents in
Latvia and Estonia, where opponents of independence tried to storm
government buildings last week.
   In another development, the Estonian news agency ETA said Sunday
that Lithuanian, Latvia, Czechoslovak and Polish lawmakers met near
Tallinn, the Estonian capital, and recommended that the Baltic
states be added to the 35-nation of Conference on Security and
Cooperation in Europe, which produced the Helsinki Accords in 1975.
   However, the delegates were not formally representing their
respective governments, so the move was mainly symbolic.
   ``We are not against the Soviet Union, but it must admit the
right to self-determination for everybody,'' ETA quoted Polish
senator Tadeusz Klopotowski as saying.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0021 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 1305EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-CourtesyCommandments     05-20 0142</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Courtesy Commandments,0153</SECOND>
<HEAD>12 Commandments of Courtesy</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Courtesy Campaign</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are New York Pride's ``Twelve Commandments
of Courtesy'' _ tailor-made to a city of cabs, subways and crowded
sidewalks.
   I will be respectful of other cultures and racial backgrounds.
   I will be hospitable to out-of-towners.
   I will not ``steal'' other people's cabs.
   I will not raise my voice in public (except at sporting events).
   I will try to be patient and wait my turn.
   I will be understanding of cab drivers and all those in high
pressure public jobs.
   I will strive to keep my city clean.
   I will not barrel through crowds unconsciously.
   I will offer my seat to others in greater need.
   I will try to be pleasant in everyday encounters.
   I will try to smile more.
   I will say ``please'' and ``thank you.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0022 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 1340EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Romania-Ceausescu     05-20 0390</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania-Ceausescu,0403</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ceausescu's Children Votein First Free Romanian Elections</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania-Elections, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BUCHAREST, Romania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The jailed children of executed
dictator Nicolae Ceausescu were allowed to vote in Sunday's
elections, the first free balloting following their father's brutal
24-year rule.
   Ceausescu's two sons and daughter are awaiting trial on charges
of complicity in his rule. All three have been jailed since
December and, if convicted, face sentences of up to life in prison.
   They were not handcuffed when they appeared at a police station
in Bucharest to cast their ballots.
   Nicu, 40, Ceausescu's youngest son and once his successor, voted
first. He spent several minutes in the booth before emerging and
dropping a large envelope in the ballot box.
   Nicu goes on trial next weekend on charges of complicity in
genocide in the Transylvanian city of Sibiu, 155 miles northwest of
Bucharest. He was regional Communist party chief there until his
arrest.
   Sporting a black beard and mustache and clad in jeans and a dark
sweater, Nicu declined to speak to reporters at his first public
appearance since being shown on television the night of Dec. 22,
just after his capture.
   Ceausescu's oldest son, Valentin, 43, a nuclear physics
engineer, spent comparatively little time in the booth.
   ``I'm treated like everyone else in prison,'' he said, smiling
and looking relaxed in a jogging suit top and jeans. He had long
long hair, a beard and mustache.
   ``It is very difficult for me to say something concrete about
the elections. It is good, however, that the people are given the
chance to have more options,'' the state news agency Rompres quoted
him as saying.
   Ceausescu's only daughter, Zoia Elena, 38, a mathematician,
looked nervous and came out of the booth after only 20 seconds. She
refused to made a statement.
   Rompres said they were allowed to vote ``as they were under
investigation and still not sentenced and stripped of political and
civil rights.''
   Members of Ceausescu's ruling Politburo who face trial also were
allowed to vote, the agency said.
   Ceausescu, whose rule was marked by repression unparalleled in
the Soviet bloc, was toppled by a popular uprising Dec. 22. He and
his wife, Elena, were tried in secret and convicted of causing the
deaths of thousands while in power. They were executed by a firing
squad on Dec. 25.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0023 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 1355EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-CleanAir Bjt   05-20 0514</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Clean Air, Bjt,490</SECOND>
<HEAD>House Leaders Want Bill Passed Before Holiday</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By H. JOSEF HEBERT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   House leaders hope for swift passage of a
far-reaching clean air bill this week, but only after a likely
showdown over whether to make automakers produce non-gasoline cars
for smog-troubled cities.
   Floor debate was scheduled to begin Monday. ``We would like to
get done before the Memorial Day break,'' House Majority Leader
Richard Gephardt, D-Mo., told his colleagues last week.
   The Senate in April approved a similar bill calling for steep
cuts in acid rain pollutants and new controls on urban smog and
toxic industrial emissions. Both versions would cost the economy
about $21 billion a year when the new controls go fully into effect.
   A concerted effort to toughen the law for the first time in 13
years began in 1989 when President Bush reversed a decade of White
House opposition and announced his support for a comprehensive
package of new controls.
   The powerful House Energy and Commerce Committee _ whose
chairman, Rep. John Dingell, D-Mich., has blocked clean air
legislation in years past _ approved a bipartisan agreement on a
broad-reaching anti-pollution bill in April.
   The bill calls for large reductions in tailpipe pollutants but
is still slightly less stringent than the Senate version in
imposing new costs on the auto industry.
   It is expected to stay generally intact during the upcoming
floor debate, which will include a dozen amendments likely to be
voted on Wednesday and Thursday, according to several congressmen
and congressional staffers.
   ``We're pretty well where we're going to stay,'' Rep. Terry
Bruce, D-Ill., said of most of the major components of the package,
including provisions that will force coal-burning electric
utilities to reduce their annual acid rain emissions by 10 million
tons.
   Bruce and other Midwest congressmen had fought the acid rain
portion of the bill during the committee's debate but gained only
small concessions.
   Key congressmen and staff members met much of last week and
through the weekend in an attempt to work out differences on some
of proposed amendments and avert contentious floor fights.
   The discussions produced a tentative agreement on a proposal
that would require use of a cleaner fuel in dozens of cities to
curb urban smog and a measure forcing a broader phaseout of
ozone-damaging chemicals.
   But participants in the talks said some issues, including an
amendment by Rep. Henry Waxman, D-Calif., to require automakers to
build 1 million alternative fuel cars, will likely have to be
fought out on the House floor.
   Waxman's measure would establish such strict smog-pollution
controls that automakers could not comply without providing cars
capable of burning fuels other than gasoline in nine of the most
polluted cities.
   Arguing it shouldn't have to build such cars because consumers
may not want to buy them, the auto industry overpowered
environmentalists in persuading the Senate to reject a similar
provision.
   ``The fate of alternative fuel vehicles hinges on consumer
acceptance and consumers are flashing a yellow warning light,''
said Thomas Hanna, president of the Motor Vehicle Manufacturers
Association.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0024 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 1357EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Israel-Uprising     05-20 0712</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel-Uprising,0731</SECOND>
<HEAD>Shooting May Reignite Uprising, Palestinians Blame Shamir</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Israel, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SERGEI SHARGORODSKY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Israeli officials condemned the attack on
unarmed Arab workers Sunday and appealed for calm, but Palestinian
leaders said the incident would revive the flagging 29-month-old
revolt against Israeli occupation.
   Palestinian activists said the assault, in which seven Gaza
laborers were killed and 11 wounded by a lone Israeli gunman,
resulted from the anti-Arab climate created by Israel's right-wing
Prime Minister Yitzhak Shamir.
   ``What happened today is a turning point, and there will be more
violence if there is no political solution. We Palestinians will
not allow this to be a forgotten incident,'' said Faisal Husseini,
a prominent pro-PLO activist.
   He said Shamir's policy of building more Israeli settlements and
a harsh policy in the occupied lands and a lack of response to U.S.
proposals for Israeli-Palestinian talks were conducive to acts by
extremists.
   ``Even if this man is mentally sick, the atmosphere created by
such a government is responsible,'' Husseini said.
   The killings, which police said were motivated by personal
rather than political reasons, triggered rioting that left seven
Palestinians dead and hundreds wounded in the occupied Gaza Strip
and West Bank.
   The casualties marked one of the uprising's bloodiest days, and
Israeli officials expressed concern over the prospect of a new
outburst in the rebellion, which had been losing momentum in recent
months. Before Sunday's violence, 688 Palestinians and 43 Israelis
had died in the unrest.
   An army spokesman who demanded anonymity said the ``sheer scope
and intensity of the rioting has not been seen in at least the past
six months.''
   The protests have been declining for months, and one recent army
statement spoke of an ``increasingly weary population which is only
able to give passive support'' to hard-core activists.
   According to Betzelem, an Israeli human rights group, army
gunfire killed 39 Palestinians in the first four months of 1990,
compared with 91 in the first four months of 1989. Figures also
showed that for the first time the number of Palestinians killed by
other Arabs, 37, exceeded the number killed by Israelis, 30, in the
first three months of 1990. The Palestinians killed by fellow Arabs
were accused of collaborating with Israeli officials.
   Israel Television quoted an unidentified Defense Ministry
official as saying Sunday's violence ``is just what the
Palestinians needed to bring the uprising back to the headlines.''
   Military governors in the occupied areas met with prominent
Palestinians, and the West Bank's army commander, Maj. Gen. Yitzhak
Mordechai, spoke in an Arabic-language broadcast. They appealed for
calm and stressed the slayings were the act of a ``deranged
individual.''
   Shamir said he was ``disgusted by the terrible crime,'' and the
slayings were condemned by President Chaim Herzog and many other
Israeli politicians.
   Many warned, however, that the attack would escalate the
intefadeh, or uprising, recalling the Dec. 8, 1987, traffic
accident that gave birth to it. Four Gaza workers were killed in a
collision with an Israeli truck, and Palestinians viewed the crash
as intentional.
   Deddy Zucker, a liberal member of parliament and a paratrooper
in the army reserves, said: ``I think today is the turning point in
the uprising, from the point of view of the price we will all pay.
We have risen to a new point in the uprising ... a new stage.''
   In an apparent effort to create new momentum in the rebellion,
Husseini and other leaders called a hunger strike, demanding a
United Nations Security Council meeting and an international
investigation.
   ``This incident is similar to the days when intefadeh started.
To change it into a stronger intefadeh is mainly dependent on us,''
he said in an interview.
   A statement by Husseini and the other 11 hunger strikers also
called for an international peace force ``to protect the
Palestinians ... until the establishment of a Palestinian state.''
   Riyad Agha, former president of the Islamic University in Gaza,
said: ``It is a tragic day. It gives more blood for the uprising.
It gives a new mechanism ... hatred. Now there is spontaneous fury.
   ``In the past, only a limited number defied the curfew. But now
women, children and men are in a state of hysteria. I can say that
extremism is running wild.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0025 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 1400EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-DrugChief Bjt-1stAdd   05-20 0220</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Drug Chief, Bjt - 1st Add,220</SECOND>
<HEAD>WASHINGTON: with 861.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Asked about the study last October, the Justice Department's
Executive Office of U.S. Attorneys released its own data for 1988
showing that Los Angeles' percentage had increased to 26, from 22
the year before.
   In the Justice data for 1988, four of the 10 areas ranked ahead
of Los Angeles: Brooklyn with 52 percent; Manhattan, 48; Detroit,
39, and Baltimore, 37.
   In that data, Hartford, Chicago, Boston and Philadelphia had 25
percent; Newark, 23 percent; and San Francisco, 18 percent.
   Recommended by Thornburgh for two presidential nominations _ to
the federal court and to head DEA _ Bonner has followed some of the
same paths Thornburgh traveled when he was a U.S. attorney in
Pittsburgh in the early 1970s.
   Early in Bonner's tenure he mounted an unsuccessful move to take
control of the department's independent organized crime strike
force in Los Angeles. Thornburgh waged a similar battle in
Pittsburgh.
   Later, when Thornburgh rejoined the Justice Department as
attorney general he renewed his own decades-old battle to put the
strike forces under U.S. attorneys all over the country.
Thornburgh's aides recruited Bonner to sing the praises of the idea
to reporters.
   Thornburgh's success in doing that led to the resignation of
nearly one-fourth of the government's top organized crime
prosecutors.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0026 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 1401EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-YellowstoneWolves 1stLd-Writethru a0660 05-20 0774</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Yellowstone Wolves, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0660,0790</SECOND>
<HEAD>New Yellowstone Wolf Study Said to Support Restoration Proposal</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 11th graf, `Ludwig Carbyn...', to CORRECT attribution to
quotation to Peek sted Carbyn.</NOTE>
<HEAD>With LaserGraphic</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KURT J. REPANSHEK</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CHEYENNE, Wyo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The return of wolves running wild through
Yellowstone National Park would add to the enjoyment of tourists
and restore a missing link in the park's ecosystem, experts say.
   But ranchers, fearful of livestock losses, oppose reintroducing
the predators, 81,000 of which were killed between 1883 and 1918 in
state and federal extermination programs.
   Now a 600-page study to be presented to Congress this week
predicts little harm to wildlife or livestock near the park if
wolves are returned, according to those familiar with it.
   More important, say the experts, it's time to move beyond
speculation of how wolves would act in Yellowstone.
   ``All of the studies currently going on will not absolve the
need to introduce wolves and let them tell us what to do,'' said
James Peek, a University of Idaho researcher.
   Durward Allen, a Purdue University researcher who has studied
wolves on Minnesota's Isle Royale for 20 years, says the government
is obligated to reestablish the gray wolf ``because it was part of
the aboriginal fauna that we are committed to preserving, as nearly
as possible, in its primitive configuration.''
   Rupert Cutler, president of Defenders of Wildlife, the most
visible proponent of wolves in Yellowstone, hopes the latest study
ends the political debate over wolves that has kept the federal
government studying the predators.
   ``The government studies show we can meet the needs of ranchers
and outfitters while meeting the desire of millions of Americans to
see wolves restored to our nation's best-known national park.''
   Apart from their aesthetic value, the wolves would rein in an
out-of-control elk population that is slowly denuding the park's
northern range, Cutler said.
   In lobbying for wolf restoration, Defenders magazine surveyed 16
North American wolf experts who overwhelmingly called for
implementation of the plan.
   Peek told the magazine that ``Yellowstone is a place where
natural dynamic processes are allowed to be restored and
perpetuated, and the predation process is incomplete without the
wolf.''
   In the latest study, Park Service and Fish and Wildlife Service
researchers examined how 100 to 150 wolves might interact with
grizzly bears and Yellowstone's ungulate populations, such as the
elk and bison. They also analyzed control methods and wolves'
impact on wildlife in Wyoming, Montana and Idaho outside the park.
   Members of the Interagency Grizzly Bear Committee predicted
there would be little if any overall effect either on grizzly or
wolf populations, although some individual bears could be harmed.
   The study also is expected to conclude that over a 20- to
30-year period there could be a 10 percent to 25 percent reduction
in Yellowstone's elk herds, which contain an estimated 31,000
animals, and a 20 percent reduction in bison, which now number
2,000.
   However, the research also notes that the action of predators
increases the general physiology of prey, resulting in increased
reproduction.
   As for hunters in the forests surrounding Yellowstone, the study
says sport hunting would not have to be eliminated for any herd or
species in the Yellowstone ecosystem.
   How wolves outside the park affect livestock depends on how
stringently wolves are controlled, according to the study. There
are an estimated 10,000 cows and 5,000 sheep in the immediate area
of the park.
   Controls currently used in Minnesota and Canada range from traps
to poison, and in Montana wolves that preyed on livestock have been
killed by Fish and Wildlife Service biologists.
   A key to the controls is whether wolves are returned under an
experimental status, as suggested by previous studies, or on their
own, according to Steve Fritts, a Montana-based Fish and Wildlife
Service biologist who helped coordinate the study.
   If wolves returned on their own, they would fall under the
Endangered Species Act, which bans killing of listed animals by the
general public and restricts federal agents to hunt only problem
animals.
   Under an experimental designation, Fritts said, more lenient
rules pertaining to the killing of wolves that leave Yellowstone
could be instituted.
   Regardless of how wolves get to Yellowstone, they belong there,
according to Dave Mech, a wildlife biologist who has studied
Minnesota's wolves since 1969 for the Fish and Wildlife Service.
   ``Yellowstone Park is a place that literally begs to have
wolves,'' he told Defenders' magazine. ``It's teeming with prey.
... Wolves would add an element to the ecosystem that would help
restore it to a more natural state, that would allow the public to
better enjoy the park.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0027 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 1437EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-NewsHourStudy     05-20 0414</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-NewsHour Study,0426</SECOND>
<HEAD>Study Finds `MacNeil-Lehrer' More Conservative Than `Nightline'</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Public television's ``The MacNeil-Lehrer
NewsHour'' features more whites and males and is more
government-oriented and conservative than ABC's ``Nightline,'' says
a group that studied both shows.
   The assertion was made by a liberal media watchdog group,
Fairness &amp; Accuracy in Reporting, in a study released Sunday. FAIR
president Jeff Cohen said that the PBS show has a ``narrow,
pro-establishment guest list'' that ``mocks the original mandate of
public television'' to provide diversity.
   ``NewsHour'' executive producer Les Crystal said the news
program agrees that diversity is important ``and we clearly feel we
can and should do better in that regard.''
   But he disputed what he called FAIR's contention that the show
doesn't criticize the government much and asks one-sided questions.
   ``That's just not true,'' he said Friday. ``We look for
differing points of view and have them on almost all the time.''
   The FAIR study of ``NewsHour'' broadcasts from Feb. 6 to Aug. 4,
1989, was conducted by Boston College sociologists William Hoynes
and David Croteau, who made a study critical of ``Nightline'' last
year.
   The ``Nightline''' report, examining 40 months of the ABC
program from 1985 to 1988, found that 89 percent of its guests were
men, 92 percent were white, and that conservative leaders were the
show's most frequent guests.
   FAIR's new study, entitled ``All the Usual Suspects:
MacNeil-Lehrer and Nightline,'' also compared ABC's program with
``NewsHour'' during the same six-month period the latter was
studied.
   The two professors making the study found that ABC's show has
slightly broadened its guest list since the original study, but
that ``our hopes for significant change were not met.''
   Their ``NewsHour'' study found that of U.S. citizens appearing
as guests, 90 percent of them were white and 87 percent were male.
The figures rose on programs about international politics, it said,
with 94 percent of U.S. citizens appearing to discuss world
politics were both white and male.
   The study offered no racial or gender percentages for guests who
were not U.S. citizens.
   It characterized as ``more representative'' the guests invited
when the show's topic was domestic politics. It said that 26
percent of them were women, but gave no figures on the race of
female guests.
   FAIR's study said the show's guest list was dominated by two
conservative Washington think tanks, with a total of 14 guests
provided by the Center for Strategic and International Studies and
the American Enterprise Institute.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0028 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 1504EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-CambodianGhosts     05-20 0565</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Cambodian Ghosts,0582</SECOND>
<HEAD>Cambodian Students Learn to Leave Their Ghosts Behind</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Tsapatsaris pronounced sah pahtz air' ess</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto BX2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LESLIE DREYFOUS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOWELL, Mass. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The young students remember their native
Cambodia in bright-colored drawings and somber prose. At the same
time, they're leaving behind the ghosts that hid amid the jungle
flowers, banana trees and war.
   ``When my family escaped from Cambodia, my father carried me and
my brother in baskets. We were very young and scared. I remember
the loud noise of the guns and missiles,'' wrote Saroun Bun, 13,
who fled her homeland in 1983.
   She and other immigrants from Cambodia make up nearly 50 percent
of the student body at Joseph G. Pyne public school in Lowell,
where Dorothea Tsapatsaris teaches them English and a little bit
about survival.
   ``I'm no psychiatrist, but you can't see the atrocities they've
seen and not have it surface,'' said Mrs. Tsapatsaris. ``They need
to get it out.''
   Compositions by her students are on display at the city's
cultural center and others have appeared in ``Duck Soup,'' a
children's literary magazine.
   ``I knew these kids had seen slaughter ... but they hide a
lot,'' Mrs. Tsapatsaris said Thursday. ``I like to get to the
core.''
   At their core, they harbor bittersweet memories. They wear
constant smiles and are model English students, but their work
reveals their sorrow.
   ``I miss my home very much, but I rather live in America because
there is no peace right now in my country,'' Sothy Sar, 11, wrote
in her essay ``Happy and Sad Memories of Cambodia.''
   In the mid-1980s, an estimated 17,000 Cambodians came to Lowell,
20 miles northwest of Boston, attracted by job opportunities and
tales from friends prospering in this old mill city turned
high-tech center.
   Sothy was 6 years old when her family fled Cambodia in 1985,
taking the refugee's path to Thailand ``until our name was called
to come to America.''
   ``Everything was quiet and peaceful before the war. In the
morning the rooster crowed to get us up,'' the sixth-grader wrote.
   ``Then the Khmer Rouge came and I saw a lot of people killed.
... My mom picked me up and we ran.''
   The running stopped long ago for most of these kids, who today
wear sweatshirts and bright-colored knee socks to school. But with
just a little prodding their memories catch up.
   ``Many, many ghosts live in Cambodia. ... The ghosts are of all
the dead people,'' wrote one young student.
   ``The ghosts in Cambodia sleep during the daytime, like owls and
bats,'' remembers another. ``They come out at night ... go after
people at night to scare them, eat or kill the people.''
   Steven Centore, a National Park Service worker at the cultural
center, remembers when he served in Vietnam that parents tried to
protect their children by warning of ghosts.
   ``Who are the ghosts? The people who come out at night. Who
comes out at night? The enemy,'' Centore said.
   The students' memories are not only of ghosts. Their drawings
also recall New Year's celebrations, folk medicine and the familiar
daily scenes that were their village lives. And they remember
relatives and friends left behind.
   ``Dear Brother,'' wrote 10-year-old Sem York in an exercise on
letter-writing. ``America is different from Cambodia so much. Do
you love me or not? Brother, do you fight in Cambodia?''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0029 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 1508EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-PassionPlay     05-20 0508</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Passion Play,0528</SECOND>
<HEAD>Passion Play Keeps Traditions _ With Some Updates</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOAN FISCHER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>OBERAMMERGAU, West Germany (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An updated version of the
centuries-old Passion Play premiered Sunday, and for the first time
a married woman was allowed to portray the Virgin Mary.
   In another modern touch, Christ's betrayer, Judas, is portrayed
as a confused and troubled man, rather than simply a greed-driven
mercenary.
   The daylong play, which depicts the suffering and resurrection
of Jesus, was also revised to make changes in its portrayal of
Jews. Many Jewish organizations had complained for decades that it
was anti-Semitic.
   Under new casting rules, Elisabeth Petre, a 37-year-old mother
of two, is one of two actresses alternating this year in the role
of the Virgin Mary.
   Half a million visitors, including 200,000 Americans, are
expected to flock to this Bavarian Alpine village 50 miles south of
Munich for the production, which runs through Sept. 30.
   ``The play is just beautiful. The acting was excellent, and I
loved the way the stage extends outside,'' said Terry Blankenship,
35, a physical therapist from Fayetteville, N.C.
   The audience sits inside the theater, but the stage extends
beyond the roof under the open sky, with a mountain backdrop.
   Some playgoers were returning to Oberammergau for the second
time.
   ``I saw the Passion Play here six years ago, and it was the most
glorious experience,'' said Beverly Seamans, 61, a sculptress from
Marblehead, Mass.
   The last performance, a special jubilee presentation in 1984,
attracted 470,000 spectators, about half of them Americans.
   ``Seeing it is a way of gaining more cultural insight,'' said
Lewis Snyder, 40, of Mason, Mich., who works for a Rhode
Island-based travel agency. ``Some of the people I bring here are
religious, but many are just curious.''
   The Passion Play here dates back to 1633, when the bubonic
plague was raging. Roman Catholic villagers vowed to stage a
Passion Play every 10 years if the plague abated. When it did, it
was considered a miracle.
   Oberammergau, a village of 5,000, is widely known for
woodcarvings and the painted frescoes on its buildings. It is
generally quiet and peaceful _ except during a Passion Play
production.
   ``Americans are our No. 1 customers,'' said Erika Heigl, owner
of a souvenir shop selling cuckoo clocks, beer mugs, porcelain
figures and crystal. All 95 performances of the play have been sold
out for months.
   Among the prominent guests at Sunday's premiere was the U.S.
ambassador to West Germany, Vernon Walters.
   ``I found today's performance enormously impressive,'' Walters
said at a reception held during the long midday intermission.
   Anti-Semitic elements removed from this year's production
include the removal of horns traditionally worn on the heads of
Jewish high priests depicted in the play.
   The new production also emphasizes Jesus' roots as a Jew, which
were formerly obscured. At times he was referred to as a rabbi.
   The changes were made at the urging of the American Jewish
Committee, the Anti-Defamation League of B'nai B'rith and the
National Conference of Catholic of Catholic Bishops.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0030 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 1520EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Pakistan-Kashmir     05-20 0587</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Pakistan-Kashmir,0606</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.S. Urges India, Pakistan to Resolve Kashmir Dispute</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-India-Buildup, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SHARON HERBAUGH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ISLAMABAD, Pakistan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The United States warned its ally
Pakistan on Sunday that if it starts a war with India over the
disputed territory of Kashmir, it cannot count on U.S. backing,
diplomatic sources said.
   Two U.S. envoys _ Robert Gates, deputy national security
adviser, and John Kelly, assistant secretary of state for Near East
and South Asian affairs _ met Sunday with Pakistani officials on
the Kashmir issue.
   The U.S. representatives then traveled to New Delhi, where they
were meeting Monday with Indian leaders.
   India and Pakistan have fought three wars, two of them over
Kashmir, since the two nations were born out of the 1947 division
of the British-ruled subcontinent.
   The division was along religious lines, into Islamic Pakistan
and Hindu-dominated India. But Kashmir, a predominantly Moslem
state, went to India.
   In recent months, a Moslem secessionist movement has flared in
Kashmir. At least 400 people have been killed since the Indian
government began cracking down on the insurgency on Jan. 20.
   ``Our major objective is to help both sides avoid a conflict
over Kashmir ... and to begin the sort of political dialogue which
would not only reduce tensions but lead to a peaceful and permanent
settlement,'' the U.S. envoys said in a statement.
   Pakistan's president, Ghulam Ishaq Khan, met with the U.S.
representatives for 90 minutes, and Western diplomatic sources said
both sides did some tough talking.
   The Americans stressed Pakistan should do nothing that would
start a war with India. If it did, they said, Washington would not
necessarily support Islamabad, said the sources, speaking on
condition of anonymity.
   Pakistan is a close U.S. ally, while the Soviet Union is the
main arms supplier to India.
   The U.S. envoys also expressed concern about militant groups
spearheading the Moslem secessionist movement in Indian-held
Kashmir from Pakistani soil, the sources said.
   The Pakistanis, for their part, suggested Washington was
applying a double standard by criticizing the secessionist groups
but failing to condemn Indian forces' violence against Kashmiris,
the sources said.
   Ishaq Khan told the U.S. envoys that Pakistan is giving only
moral support, not military assistance, to secessionists in
Kashmir, said Foreign Ministry spokesman Abu Fazle. He quoted Ishaq
Khan as saying Pakistan has made several proposals aimed at
reducing border tensions, but that India rejected them.
   Pakistan has called for talks on the Kashmir issue, but New
Delhi has not consented.
   Gates and Kelly were unable to meet with Pakistan's prime
minister, Benazir Bhutto, or its foreign minister, Sabahzada Yaqub
Khan. The two, together with other senior Pakistani officials, are
off on a weeklong tour of the Middle East and North Africa, trying
to drum up Islamic support in the Kashmir dispute.
   The U.S. envoys had hoped to meet with Ms. Bhutto in North Yemen
before coming to Pakistan but the last-minute logistics could not
be worked out, according to U.S. officials. Instead, they met with
the president, the army chief of staff, and the prime minister's
foreign affairs advisers.
   Ms. Bhutto, in Cairo, said Sunday ``more steps should be taken
to make sure that a peaceful solution be found'' to the dispute.
   But she also told reporters her country would support Kashmir's
independence from India ``no matter what the consequences.''
   Both India and Pakistan are suspected of possessing nuclear
weapons technology _ India detonated a nuclear device in 1974 _ so
the dispute over Kashmir is of concern to the superpowers.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0031 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 1538EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Sudan-Earthquake     05-20 0638</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Sudan-Earthquake,0658</SECOND>
<HEAD>Earthquake Hits Southern Sudan, But no Injuries or Damage</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MOHAMED OSMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>KHARTOUM, Sudan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A major earthquake rumbled through the
jungles of southern Sudan on Sunday near the war-torn region's
largest city, but officials said there appeared to be no casualties
and little damage.
   The quake measured 7.5 on the Richter scale. A temblor of that
size is capable of causing widespread destruction.
   The official Sudan News Agency said the earthquake caused no
deaths or injuries. But much of the area affected by the quake is
so isolated that any news might take days or weeks.
   Juba, southern Sudan's largest city, is 60 miles southwest of
the quake's reported epicenter. The region has been hit by famine
as well as fighting between the government and the rebel People's
Liberation Army, and Juba is crammed with refugees from the
7-year-old civil war.
   In Nairobi, Kenya, Bob Koepp, a Lutheran World Federation
official, said a pilot flying relief supplies to Juba returned late
Sunday and said the city had not been seriously affected. He said
there was some ``negligible'' damage.
   ``It wasn't very heavy at Juba. The epicenter apparently was in
the swamps and the ground may have just soaked it up,'' Koepp said.
   Scientists said the quake's epicenter was 700 miles south of
Sudan's capital, Khartoum. It occurred in sparsely populated
territory controlled by the rebels, who hold most of the southern
countryside.
   Relief workers in two rebel-controlled villages, Bor and Torit,
apparently told officials in Nairobi, Kenya, the earthquake caused
no damage there.
   ``It's pretty low area over there, with low buildings and quite
remote,'' Koepp said.
   A crew with Koepp's organization landed in the region with
relief supplies two hours after the quake struck at 4:22 a.m. and
reported seeing nothing amiss.
   Late Sunday, a Khartoum airport tower operator said flights to
the southern city had not been disrupted.
   Pierre-Andre Conod of the International Committee of the Red
Cross said he had no details about injuries or damage. He said
colleagues in Juba had not made their regular radio contact with
Khartoum but cautioned that ``maybe they have a problem with the
antenna. We cannot say it is due to the earthquake.''
   People seeking haven from the war and from famine have more than
doubled Juba's population of 125,000. In recent years, hundreds of
thousands have died in southern Sudan, an area the size of Texas.
   Egypt's two principal earthquake monitoring stations, including
one at the Aswan High Dam, 600 miles south of Cairo and just north
of the Sudan border, recorded the quake at 7.5 on the Richter
scale. The U.S. Geological Survey in Menlo Park, Calif. reported an
identical reading.
   ``It's such a big quake that the monitoring stations are
saturated with data,'' said geologist Rashad M. Kebeasy, president
of Egypt's National Research Institute of Astronomy and Geophysics.
``This is an extremely dangerous earthquake. It is the first time
that such a quake has struck this area.''
   He said ``large and very dangerous aftershocks'' were to be
expected for the next two days.
   The Richter scale is a gauge of energy released by an earthquake
as measured by the ground motion recorded on a seismograph. Every
increase of one number, say from magnitude 5.5 to magnitude 6.6,
means that the ground motion is 10 times greater.
   A magnitude of 7 is considered a major earthquake capable of
widespread heavy damage. Magnitude 8 is a great earthquake capable
of tremendous damage. Last October's earthquake near San Francisco
registered 7.1 on the Richter scale.
   Kebeasy, an expert on earthquakes of northeastern Africa, said
the epicenter was just west of the Great African Rift. That
earthquake zone stretches 4,000 miles from Mozambique through the
Red Sea to Lebanon.
   The proximity to the rift accounts for the quake's magnitude,
Kebeasy said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0032 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 1557EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-HubbleTelescope 3rdLd-Writethru a0683 05-20 0874</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Hubble Telescope, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0683,830</SECOND>
<HEAD>Space Officials `Pleased' With First Hubble Telescope Photo</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: LEADS with 15 grafs to UPDATE with photo comparisons. Picks
up 13th graf pvs, bgng: Theta Carina. Should stand</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By PAUL RECER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>GREENBELT, Md. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   NASA engineers captured the ``first
light'' photograph Sunday of the Hubble Space Telescope and a
scientist said the experts ``were pleased as punch'' with the
spectacular image.
   A camera on the telescope clicked its shutter twice beginning at
11:13 a.m. EDT and the images were relayed to the ground more than
two hours later, giving astronomers their first glimpses of the
view from the $1.5 billion telescope.
   ``It's quite an image. Fantastic,'' James Westphal, the
principal scientist for the camera used in the first photo
exercise, said as one the photos was displayed on a TV screen.
   ``We are just as pleased as punch at this point,'' Westphal
said. ``Our image is significantly better than we were concerned
that it might be.''
   Westphal said the Hubble image revealed a double star that was
previously unseen in ground-based photographs taken at an
observatory in Chile.
   ``We didn't know it was a double star,'' said Westphal, noting
that he had expected the first image to be ``an engineering test.''
   But because of the clarity of the image, he said ``Boy, we could
get lots of science out of this right now.''
   The quality of the photo was a boost for National Aeronautics
and Space Administration officials who have gone through an
unexpectedly troubled checkout and testing period with the costly
telescope, which is in orbit 381 miles above Earth.
   The target for Hubble's first image was a star cluster called
Theta Carina, a group of objects about 1,260 light years from
Earth. The telescope took two exposures, one for a single second
and another lasting 30 seconds.
   Westphal said the 30-second exposure was chosen for analysis
because it gave better detail.
   Engineers manipulated the images while people watched on
television, and it took them over an hour to change the raw
electronic data from Hubble into a photograph on a TV screen.
   ``Nobody has ever done this before, so we had to learn how,''
Westphal said. ``The technical challenge now is to get the
telescope in even sharper focus.''
   The scientists said that eventually they expect to get
photographs at least seven times sharper than the one released
Sunday.
   The image came down as four separate parts of the same photo.
Engineers then used computer instructions to enhance the quality of
each point of light. The initial look at the photo showed very
faint points of light on a gray field.
   After manipulation, the stars were brightened, the background
was darkened and the double star could be seen easily.
   Theta Carina is part of a constellation called Carina, a word
that means ``ship's keel,'' that is visible from the ground only in
the Southern Hemisphere. The star cluster is identified in the New
General Catalogue of stars as 3532 and is thought to be 3 billion
years old. Its distance from Earth is about 7,400,000,000,000,000
miles.
   NASA officials said the first light photo is an important
engineering milestone for the Hubble checkout.
   Engineers have spent a month attempting to align and focus the
instruments of Hubble. They have had to overcome computer problems,
a fouled antenna, a programing error that resulted from an ordinary
math mistake and an unexplained wobble that still is unresolved.
   The checkout, said B.E. Stull of Lockheed Missiles and Space
Co., the prime NASA contractor for the telescope, has been ``a
little more stressful and challenging that we expected.
   ``We certainly expected some difficulties, but we didn't expect
the severity and the number that we got,'' he told The Washington
Post.
   The telescope will undergo another seven months or so of intense
checkout and testing before the full-time programs of scientific
study begin.
   Officials said long break-in periods are not unusual for robot
spacecraft and the testing is even more difficult because of the
precise demands of Hubble, the most powerful astronomical
observatory ever put into orbit.
   Hubble, by working from an orbit above the obscuring effects of
the Earth's atmosphere, will able to look at stars in the far
reaches of the universe, perhaps to point 14 billion light years
from Earth.
   With its 94.5-inch-diameter mirror and powerful light-amplifying
and focusing equipment, the orbiting telescope is expected to
eventually take photos of stars that are 25 times fainter than the
dimmest object visible from Earth. The best Hubble pictures are
expected to have 10 times the clarity of photos taken by the most
powerful ground-based telescopes.
   To accomplish this, the telescope is designed to hold so steady
that its motion in any direction would be less than the thickness
of a sheet of paper. Its pointing system is so accurate that if it
was mounted atop the Washington Monument with a laser gun it could
hold a steady light beam on a dime atop the Empire State Building
in New York City.
   Hubble was carried into space last month by space shuttle
Discovery. On April 25, it was plucked from the shuttle's cargo bay
and left to orbit on its own, 381 miles above the Earth.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0033 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 1558EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--Pope-Beatification     05-20 0128</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Pope-Beatification,0132</SECOND>
<HEAD>Italian Layman Beatified By Pope</HEAD>
<DATELINE>VATICAN CITY (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Pier Giorgio Frassati, a young Italian who
helped the urban poor earlier this century, was beatified Sunday by
Pope John Paul II, who praised him as a model for lay Catholics.
   Beatification is the last major step before sainthood in the
Roman Catholic church.
   About 50,000 people attended the ceremony in St. Peter's Square.
Frassati, who died in 1925, worked with the poor in Turin as the
northern Italian city grew more industrial after the turn of the
century.
   He also inspired many Catholic lay groups, including Catholic
Action.
   Frassati ``realized his lay Christian vocation through multiple
commitments, social and political, in a society in ferment,
indifferent and sometimes hostile to the church,'' the pope said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0034 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 1609EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Korea 2ndLd-Writethru   05-20 0595</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Korea, 2nd Ld-Writethru,a0686,0611</SECOND>
<HEAD>Kwangju Riots Rage for Third Day; 50 Injured, 200 Arrested</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: CORRECTS overline to 50 injured sted dead.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos KWG4,7</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By C.W. LIM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>KWANGJU, South Korea (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Police firing automatic rifles held
off demonstrators hurling firebombs at a police station Sunday as
about 10,000 protesters rampaged in this city for a third day.
   Witnesses and news reports said no one was injured in the attack
on the police station. But authorities said about 50 officers and
protesters were hurt in other clashes, including a student doctors
said may lose his sight after being hit in the eyes by a rock.
   About 200 people were arrested, news reports said.
   Earlier Sunday, thousands of riot police firing tear gas stormed
Chosun University to disperse 5,000 students and workers.
   Police in combat gear fired hundreds of tear gas shells to drive
back the street protesters who charged in groups of up to 1,000 at
a time. Protesters tore up sidewalks for weapons and built bonfires
at a dozen intersections to light firebombs.
   About 40 taxis with headlights on drove through downtown streets
honking their horns to support the protesters. Citizens in doorways
and alleys cheered protesters and shouted insults at police.
   The battles lasted about six hours and covered an area
stretching 1.2 miles from the provincial government headquarters in
the city center. The protesters screamed slogans demanding the
ouster of President Roh Tae-woo and opposing the United States.
   In the attack on the police station, witnesses said police fired
more than 40 warning shots from automatic rifles to drive off about
50 protesters.
   The battle represented an escalation in the clash because it is
uncommon for police to fire or even brandish weapons during
protests. Police trained in riot control do not carry arms, and
automatic rifles are considered military equipment, not riot
control weapons.
   It was the second time in three days that police in Kwangju used
firearms to disperse protesters. On Saturday, officers fired eight
rounds when students attacked two police substations with firebombs.
   At one point Sunday, dozens of students throwing firebombs at
police accidentally set a shop on fire. When a fire truck arrived,
the students used it as a shield to continue their attacks.
   Several students chased by police dashed into a Roman Catholic
church to avoid arrest and parishioners rushed outside to guard the
gate. Even small children joined in the protest, but students urged
them to go home, warning that they might be hurt.
   The protests began Friday on the 10th anniversary of a bloody
anti-government uprising in Kwangju, about 150 miles south of Seoul.
   President Roh, a former army general, was a key leader of the
former martial law government that crushed the 1980 revolt with
military force.
   Kwangju citizens claim U.S. military officials condoned the
military crackdown on the 10-day uprising, which claimed 200 lives
and left more than 1,700 injured.
   The 1980 revolt was the bloodiest in modern Korean history and
seared the psyche of Koreans more than any incident since the
1950-53 Korean War.
   The U.S. cultural center in Kwangju was closed down last year
after being attacked by Korean radicals 18 times since the early
1980s. American officials plan to reopen the center next month.
   Student leaders scheduled a funeral rally Wednesday for a
student activist from Seoul who died Saturday en route to the
protests.
   Police officials expressed concern that such a rally would
provoke more clashes. The deaths of radical leaders triggered
violent protests in the past when students felt police were to
blame.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0035 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 1624EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Germany-Unification     05-20 0465</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Germany-Unification,0483</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bonn Financial Support Likely for Soviet Troops</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KEVIN COSTELLOE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WEST BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A top political adviser to Chancellor Helmut
Kohl recently traveled to Moscow to discuss Bonn's likely financial
support for Soviet troops in East Germany, a government spokesman
said Sunday.
   Kohl's aides have said West Germany might have to temporarily
subsidize Soviet troops as early as this summer, once the West
German mark replaces the East German currency.
   West German willingness to help support the 380,000 Soviet
troops is widely seen as one way to overcome any Soviet objections
to German unification. The Kremlin strongly opposes NATO membership
for a unified Germany.
   West German financial support, even temporary, for Soviet troops
would be a first in the history of the Atlantic Alliance.
   In an interview with the Bonn newspaper Die Welt, Economics
Minister Helmut Haussmann said Moscow agreeing to unity depends on
economic cooperation between the two countries.
   Haussmann was scheduled to travel to Moscow on Monday for talks
with Kremlin officials, the newspaper said. Haussmann said Bonn
wants to help the Soviets in their ``difficult economic reform
process.''
   In a report with the headline ``Secret Mission,'' the West
German news magazine Der Spiegel on Saturday disclosed that Kohl
adviser Horst Teltschik traveled to Moscow on the weekend of May
5-6 for discussions with the Soviet leadership.
   Der Spiegel said Teltschik had discussed ``financial
questions,'' including Bonn's likely financial support for Soviet
troops and the shaky future of East Germany's contracts to supply
the Soviet Union with numerous products.
   A Bonn government spokesman, who spoke on condition of
anonymity, confirmed the trip but denied Teltschik was on a
``secret mission.''
   ``East Germany's supply responsibilities to the Soviet Union are
to be maintained even after unification,'' the spokesman said. ``We
also are seeking ways to guarantee the financing of the Soviet
troops in the German Democratic Republic.''
   The spokesman declined to say with which Soviet officials
Teltschik had spoken.
   Der Spiegel said Bonn is ready to pay $187.5 million a year
toward keeping the Soviet troops temporarily in what is now East
Germany.
   Under current agreements, the Soviet Union buys East German
marks in exchange for so-called transfer rubles at a preferential
rate.
   The East German marks are then used to pay for goods and
services for Soviet soldiers stationed in East Germany. Until now,
goods and services have been relatively inexpensive in East Germany
because of state subsidies.
   Bonn officials say unification poses some economic problems for
the Soviets.
   The West German mark will become East Germany's official
currency as of July 2, and East German subsidies are also starting
to disappear. That means the overall cost of keeping the Soviet
soldiers in East Germany will jump this summer, squeezing the
already badly strained Soviet economy.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0036 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 1625EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Soviet-Armenia     05-20 0259</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Armenia,0268</SECOND>
<HEAD>Armenians Vote in Parliamentary Elections</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Residents of the troubled republic of Armenia
voted Sunday in parliamentary elections that featured a wide choice
of candidates, and runoff balloting is expected in many races, the
Soviet media reported.
   An average of six candidates were registered in each of the 260
parliamentary districts, the Tass news agency reported. Soviet
television said unopposed candidates were on the ballot in only two
districts.
   Preliminary results were not expected until Monday, and final
results will not be available until later this week. A low turnout
of less than 50 percent of eligible voters was reported before
midday, Tass said.
   Few candidates were expected to win enough votes to avoid a
runoff, Tass reported.
   The news agency described the candidates as representing ``all
segments of society,'' including the Communist Party and informal
groups and associations.
   Some political activists favoring greater autonomy for Armenia
had sought unsuccessfully to delay the elections for six months.
   The Soviet TV newscast ``Vremya'' said the campaign was marked
by a ``tense atmosphere,'' noting the thousands of refugees from
ethnic violence with neighboring Azerbaijan, the still-unresolved
dispute with that republic over the territory of Nagorno-Karabakh
and the slow pace of reconstruction from the 1988 Armenian
earthquake.
   One voter interviewed by ``Vremya'' said there was political
confusion in the republic.
   ``All of us have lost our way,'' the unidentified, middle-aged
man said. ``We don't know anymore what to do, what to think, what
is right and what is wrong. We know for sure that everything has
changed.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0037 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 1636EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Afghanistan     05-20 0224</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Afghanistan,0233</SECOND>
<HEAD>Two Diplomats Hurt in Attack on Afghan Capital</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ISLAMABAD, Pakistan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A U.N. envoy and a Yugoslav charge
d'affaires were injured in a missile attack on the Afghan capital
of Kabul, the official Soviet news agency Tass reported Sunday.
   In a separate report, Afghan rebels claimed they had attacked
government positions in southern Helmand province, killing up to 60
soldiers. The MIDIA news agency, operated by the rebel headquarters
in Pakistan, also reported the rebels destroyed several vehicles.
   In the bombardment of the capital Saturday, missiles hit the
Wazir Akbar Khan area, where diplomatic missions are located, Tass
said. The Soviet-backed government blamed the attack on the Moslem
rebels.
   Official Afghan radio Kabul said the missile attack killed two
people and wounded 27.
   The news agency said shelling in the quarter has been fierce in
recent days, and that missiles had fallen near the West German
Embassy and on the grounds of the U.S. diplomatic compound.
   It quoted diplomats as saying the attacks were aimed at
preventing foreign countries from reopening their missions.
   The Afghan insurgents, financed by the United States, Pakistan,
Saudi Arabia and other sympathetic Arab states, have been fighting
for 12 years to unseat the Kabul government.
   But fighting has been sporadic since Soviet troops withdrew last
year after more than nine years of direct military involvement.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0038 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 1640EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-LibraryFlap 1stLd-Writethru a0647 05-20 0745</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Library Flap, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0647,0762</SECOND>
<HEAD>Use of Closed State Library by Governor's Family Draws Ridicule</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: INSERTS 2 grafs after 12th graf pvs, `He withdrew...,' to
UPDATE with newspaper editorials. Pick up 13th graf pvs, `Missouri
Democratic...</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By SCOTT CHARTON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JEFFERSON CITY, Mo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The governor's wife's after-hours use
of the state library to help her 12-year-old son with homework has
generated giggles and jabs from the Legislature and an apology from
her husband.
   One lawmaker jokingly suggested opening the governor's mansion
for public tours the same hours as the state library.
   Janet Ashcroft won't talk about the 2{ hours she and her son
Andy spent in the Missouri State Library on Mother's Day. Her
husband, Gov. John Ashcroft says it was merely a case of a parent
trying to help a child.
   ``I assume that every parent knows that there are times when
their kid isn't as prepared as he ought to be for school, and what
you do is you help 'em,'' the governor said Friday.
   The governor said he was sorry if anybody was offended by their
use of the state library to help Andy finish a report on life in
Elizabethan England.
   ``We've tried not to have an imperial governorship here. We
don't ride around in limousines because we don't see ourselves as
different from the people of this state.''
   Still, the governor acknowledged that other students probably
wouldn't have been allowed after-hours use of the library, a
reference library open on weekdays to the public but used primarily
by lawmakers and state employees.
   Ashcroft said his family didn't mean to disturb anyone, saying
his wife only inquired if a library key was available. A library
employee who didn't have a key called the state librarian and both
showed up to open the library.
   ``They got more than they asked for,'' the second-term
Republican said. ``It may have been that the person responded over
and above what the person would have responded to someone else.''
   State librarian Monteria Hightower said her Mother's Day
activities with her family were interrupted. ``We don't do homework
assignments for children. When the services are closed, they are
closed,'' the librarian said earlier last week.
   The incident drew attention on talk shows and editorial pages
from St. Louis to Kansas City. In the Missouri House, Rep. Doug
Harpool drew laughter when he proposed an amendment to keep state
officials from having the state library opened after hours.
   He withdrew it, saying, ``Nobody would be that rude again,
anyway.''
   ``There are extras which come with being the first family. The
public wouldn't have it any other way. But people in positions of
privilege have to walk a fine line. They should be careful that
they do not overstep the bounds into misuse of privilege,'' The
Kansas City Star said in an editorial last week.
   On Sunday, St. Louis Post-Dispatch columnist Bill McClellan
wrote, ``Now, finally, we have the first scandal of the Ashcroft
administration. We have Library-Gate.''
   Missouri Democratic Chairman Gene Bushmann joined in,
criticizing Ashcroft's vetoes of funds for libraries. He suggested
that Jefferson City's public library might be open Sundays if it
had gotten the state money.
   Ashcroft's office responded that Bushmann's numbers and premise
were wrong, that state funding for libraries has gone up and that
the operating hours of the library in the state capital are a local
matter.
   Democratic Sen. Roger Wilson offered, then withdrew, an
amendment to open the usually closed governor's mansion for public
tours the same hours that the state library is open.
   ``It was an attempt to inject a little humor in this,'' Wilson
said.
   A Republican colleague, House Minority Leader James Talent,
dismissed the incident as ``really a small thing.'' But Republican
Sen. Bob Johnson said, ``This smacks of preferential treatment at a
time that some members of the public think that politicians are too
self-serving.''
   Ashcroft won't discuss what Andy, youngest of three children,
thought about the matter, nor will he confirm it was Andy doing the
homework. The governor didn't answer questions about the library
visit until Friday, saying he didn't know what happened because he
was in church with his other son.
   And he wasn't pleased with the attention the visit attracted.
   Ashcroft told a reporter: ``The more you make of it, the more
difficulty there is for my children. ... I don't think that helps
my children and I very frankly don't think it's a news story.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0039 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 1643EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-EC-Ministers     05-20 0378</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-EC-Ministers,0391</SECOND>
<HEAD>European Community Edges Toward Political Union</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MAUREEN JOHNSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PARKNASILLA, Ireland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   European Community foreign ministers
on Sunday laid the groundwork for closer political integration by
1993 but made it clear that none of the 12 member nations wants a
federal United States of Europe.
   Irish Foreign Minister Gerry Collins described the weekend talks
at Parknasilla, a lavish country resort in southwestern Ireland, as
``a real step forward in defining the shape of a new Europe.''
   ``It is quite clear that we cannot stand still,'' said Collins,
chairman of the two-day meeting. ``A community complacent with its
achievements ... risks faltering and stagnating.''
   But officials said there was no question of community nations
yielding the right to make sovereign decisions on foreign policy.
   Instead, debate concentrated on whether more centralized powers
should be focused on the 12 leaders of government or the
community's assembly, the 518-member European Parliament based in
Strasbourg, France.
   Britain, the most skeptical about the idea of political union,
said it was pleased with the modest approach at Parknasilla.
   ``We don't want to give the Euopean Parliament more powers, and
we are clearly not alone,'' said British Foreign Secretary Douglas
Hurd.
   France was adamant that foreign policy must remain a national
matter.
   ``Today, in 1990, no one is ready to delegate its sovereignty in
foreign policy and security matters,'' French Foreign Minister
Roland Dumas said.
   France and West Germany pitched the community into an
accelerated program for unity with a joint call last month for
``political union'' by 1993.
   The meeting at Parknasilla was the first since the community
leaders at a summit on April 28 agreed in principle to the
undefined French-German proposal.
   The foreign ministers are to meet again to complete draft
proposals for the EC's next summit, to be held in Dublin at the end
of June.
   Britain, France and several smaller nations want the leaders of
government to be the focus of centralized power, while West
Germany, backed by Belgium and Italy, wants increased powers for
the Parliament, diplomats said.
   Jacques Delors, president of the community's strongly pro-unity
executive commission, based in Brussels, acknowledged for the first
time there is no hope of agreement on a federation.
   Ireland currently holds the community's rotating presidency.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0040 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 1653EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-StormieJones 1stLd-Writethru a0693 05-20 0527</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Stormie Jones, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0693,0541</SECOND>
<HEAD>Doctors Examine Troubled Heart-Liver Transplant Patient</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS grafs 5-6, `Mrs. Purcell...', with 6 grafs to UPDATE
with quotes and plans for medication. Picks up 7th graf, `The
girl...'.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto FWX1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CASSANDRA BURRELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PITTSBURGH (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The world's longest surviving recipient of a
heart-liver transplant returned to Pittsburgh on Sunday where
doctors checked signs she may be rejecting her second transplanted
liver.
   ``I've been in the hospital all weekend so this wasn't a
surprise,'' said Stormie Jones of the trip from her suburban Fort
Worth, Texas, home.
   The girl, who will turn 13 on May 31, was hospitalized in Texas
on Friday.
   ``The doctors found her enzyme levels were high, so they wanted
to get it under control before it got to be a big problem,'' said
her mother, Lois ``Suzie'' Purcell, who flew to Pittsburgh with
Stormie on Sunday.
   Mrs. Purcell and Stormie met briefly with reporters at
Children's Hospital of Pittsburgh after coaxing from the hospital
staff, who wanted to assure the public that she was not criticaly
ill. She was admitted in fair condition.
   ``Remember I'm getting paid for this,'' she joked. ``And this is
just for five minutes.''
   Doctors immediately began their evaluation, which is expected to
take several days, said hospital spokeswoman Lynn McMahon.
   ``One of her blood level measurements is elevated and typically
that is something that happens when the body is rejecting a
transplanted liver,'' McMahon said.
   While she's being evaluated, doctors plan to give Stormie higher
doses of an experimental anti-rejection drug she's been taking,
said another hospital spokesman, Susan Cardillo.
   ``While it's disappointing she's had to return, it doesn't have
to be an indication of a severe problem,'' said McMahon.
   The girl received a new heart and liver at Children's Hospital
on Feb. 14, 1984, because of a congenital condition that left her
cholesterol levels 10 times higher than normal. She was 6 years old
when she became the world's first recipient of a heart-liver
transplant.
   Before that operation, Stormie suffered two heart attacks and
underwent two triple coronary bypass operations.
   Stormie underwent her second liver transplant Feb. 20 after
doctors discovered hepatitis damaged her first donor liver. The
hepatitis was caused by an unknown virus. Stormie's heart did not
need to be replaced.
   The success rate of a second liver transplant is estimated at 65
percent to 70 percent.
   Stormie's stepfather, Alan Purcell, said Stormie was especially
discouraged by the possible rejection since she had not felt sick
or had any symptoms.
   ``She's not doing too good this time. She's a little
disappointed,'' Purcell said from the family's Texas home Sunday.
``What do you expect of a 12-year-old child? She's tired.
   ``She's been through more than most humans will ever go through
in two lifetimes. She'd like to be normal for awhile.''
   Pittsburgh surgeons followed Stormie's 1984 operation with two
more attempts at heart-liver transplants, but both patients died
within a few days of surgery.
   Last Dec. 3, doctors at another Pittsburgh hospital performed
the world's first heart-liver-kidney transplant. The patient, Cindy
Martin, 26, of Archbald, Pa., died March 26 of kidney failure
triggered by hepatitis.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0041 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 1705EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Israel-ArabReax     05-20 0508</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel-Arab Reax,0525</SECOND>
<HEAD>Arab States Condemn Israeli Shooting Incident</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Israel, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JAMAL HALABY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>AMMAN, Jordan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Arab states and groups expressed outrage
Sunday over the killings of seven unarmed Palestinian laborers by
an Israeli civilian and called for renewed protests in the
Israeli-occupied territories.
   The shooting Sunday, blamed on an Israeli who had been
dishonorably discharged from the army, set off riots in the
Israeli-occupied territories that left seven other Palestinians
dead and hundreds injured.
   Sunday was one of the most violent days since the start of the
intefadah, the Palestinian uprising that broke out in December 1987
against Israeli military rule in the West Bank and the Gaza Strip.
   Israeli officials themselves condemned the attack, which one
general called a ``tragic act by a deranged individual.'' But many
Arab officials said it represented a pattern of violence against
Palestinians.
   Palestine Liberation Organization chief Yasser Arafat called on
Palestinians in the occupied territories to stage protests in
``every village, every city and every camp of the Israeli-occupied
territory.''
   The PLO chief also urged international intervention to protect
Palestinians against ``the crimes of the Israeli army and
colonialists,'' referring to Jewish settlers in the territories.
   WAFA, the PLO news agency, said the PLO made a formal protest to
the United States on Sunday over the incident, saying it held
Washington responsible for ``Israeli genocide operations'' against
Palestinians. The PLO's permanent representative to Tunisia, Hakam
Balaoui, submitted the protest note to the U.S. Embassy in Tunis.
   In Jordan, Prime Minister Mudar Badran called the shootings a
``criminal act, which is also denounced by all Arabs, all Moslems
and all the people of the world who have a live conscience.''
   Roughly half of Jordan's 3.1 million people come from
Palestinian families who fled or were forced out of their homeland
during the 1948 and 1967 Arab-Israeli wars.
   In Lebanon, Shiite Moslem militia chieftain Nabih Berri, who is
also a government minister, condemned the attack as a ``horrifying
massacre'' and called in a statement for a nationwide protest
strike Wednesday.
   Egypt on Sunday expressed ``deep sorrow'' over the killings,
which it said reflected ``the prevailing climate in Israel and in
Israeli-occupied Arab territories.''
   ``This painful incident no doubt affirms once more the
importance of overcoming all obstacles hindering the peace
process,'' Foreign Minister Esmat Abdel-Meguid told reporters.
   Clovis Maksoud, the ambassador to the United States and the
United Nations from the League of Arab States, accused Israel of
have a ``deliberate plan to expedite through escalating violence
its strategy to crush the uprising.''
   Maksoud said Arab states ``call on the international community
as a matter of utmost urgency to take the necessary measures to
protect the Palestinians in the occupied territories.''
   ``To attribute the immediate cause for today's violent incidents
to a so-called `deranged' person is a cynical and arrogant contempt
of the facts,'' he added.
   Israeli police who arrested the gunman said he was distraught
over personal problems, including a recent breakup with his
girlfriend. His identity was not released pending a court hearing.

</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0042 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 1720EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-TB-AIDS     05-20 0568</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-TB-AIDS,0590</SECOND>
<HEAD>Increase Of Tuberculosis, Due to AIDS, Poses New Health Threat</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Second-Hand Smoke Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By STEPHANIE SCHOROW</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Tuberculosis, a once-deadly disease now largely
forgotten by Americans, is re-emerging as a health threat primarily
among AIDS patients, health officials said Sunday.
   Tuberculosis cases increased 35 percent in Newark, N.J., in 1989
over the previous year, alarming health officials who had noted
with satisfaction a slow, steady decrease in TB cases over the last
few decades.
   On the national level, TB cases rose 5 percent in 1989 over
1988, a jump largely attributable to the AIDS crisis, said Dr.
Philip C. Hopewell, chief of chest service at San Francisco General
Hospital.
   AIDS attacks the body's immune system, and TB is one of the
so-called opportunistic infections that can accompany the disease.
   Hopewell and other health officials discussed the link between
AIDS and TB here during a four-day World Conference on Lung Health,
which ends Wednesday.
   About 4 percent of Americans identified as having AIDS also have
been diagnosed as being infected with tuberculosis, said Dr. Dixie
E. Snider Jr., director of the division of tuberculosis control at
the Centers for Disease Control in Atlanta.
   The American Lung Association estimates 20,000 Americans a year
develop TB, which, worldwide, kills an estimated 3 million persons
each year.
   In parts of Africa, where AIDS already is epidemic, tuberculosis
is also reaching those proportions, said Dr. Annik Rouillon,
executive director of the International Union Against Tuberculosis
and Lung Disease in Paris.
   ``The combination of the two is really catastrophic,'' she said.
   Snider stressed that TB, unlike AIDS, is curable and can be
effectively treated, even in AIDS patients. He called for TB
screening at drug rehabilitation programs, prisons and wherever
else AIDS tests are given.
   He also said physicians should test for TB all persons who test
positive for the HIV virus that causes AIDS.
   ``It's important we get control of the situation,'' he said.
   Dr. Lee B. Reichman, director of the pulmonary division of the
University of Medicine and Dentistry in New Jersey, pointed to
Wyoming, where the CDC recorded no new TB cases in 1989, as proof
TB can still be controlled and cured.
   But unlike AIDS, TB is highly contagious and can be spread by
airborne particles coughed up by a person with untreated,
clinically active pulmonary TB.
   Untreated, TB kills about 50 percent of its victims within two
years, according to the CDC.
   The doctors said minority groups in the United States have
become increasingly susceptible to TB, especially as the incidence
of AIDS among those groups increases.
   Snider stressed that sustained contact is necessary for TB
transmission, although he noted that there had been an increase in
positive TB tests among AIDS health workers.
   Tuberculosis is caused by a bacterium that commonly affects the
lungs but can attack almost any organ. For the last three decades,
it has been preventable and curable through drug therapy, Snider
said.
   He said an estimated 10 million to 15 million Americans have
been infected with the TB germ, but only a small percentage develop
the disease since most have immune systems strong enough to ward it
off.
   Reichman noted that most Americans have forgotten about the
problems of TB. The CDC says TB cases declined an average 6 percent
a year from 1981 to 1984.
   But, Reichman warned, ``TB is back with a vengeance.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0043 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 1736EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Israel 2ndLd-Writethru   05-20 1156</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel, 2nd Ld-Writethru,a0679,1191</SECOND>
<HEAD>Israeli Kills 7 Palestinians; Rioting Leaves 7 More Dead</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 3 grafs to RAISE location of shooting by Israeli;
pickup graf 4 `Police who....' INSERTS 2 grafs after 22nd `In
Tunis...' to ADD State Department reaction. Pickup graf 23rd pvs
`Israeli police...'</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos TLV2,3,6</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ELLEN SCHECHET</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>RISHON LETZION, Israel (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An Israeli who was dishonorably
discharged from the army shot and killed seven unarmed Palestinian
laborers and wounded 11 on Sunday. Outraged Arabs rampaged through
the occupied territories in rioting that left seven more
Palestinians dead and hundreds injured.
   It was one of the bloodiest days since the Palestinian uprising
began 29 months ago and could rekindle the violence that had
declined in recent months.
   The assailant, dressed in army pants and a black jacket,
confronted the laborers at a junction south of Tel Aviv, ordered
them to sit in a line, then opened fire, police said. The victims
apparently followed his orders because they mistook him for a
soldier.
   Police who arrested the shooter said he was distraught over
personal problems, including a recent breakup with his girlfriend.
His identity was not released pending a court hearing.
   Israeli officials condemned the attack, which one general called
a ``tragic act by a deranged individual.'' The army imposed curfews
on the Gaza Strip and most of the West Bank, confining 1.1 million
Palestinians to their homes.
   But, wild with anger, Palestinians defied the curfew and poured
into the streets by the thousands, attacking army outposts, stoning
passing Israeli cars and blocking roads, Arab reports said.
   ``They threw anything they could find at soldiers and came at
them with all they had,'' said an army spokesman. ``Imposing the
curfew on the rioters was a difficult period in which most of the
casualties occurred.''
   Those killed in the rioting ranged in age from 14 to 30. In one
case, Arab reporters said a youth was fatally wounded when he tried
to stab a soldier.
   Hospitals and United Nations clinics in Gaza said 691
Palestinians were treated for injuries from live ammunition, rubber
bullets, beatings and tear gas. Thirteen were wounded, two
seriously, by gunfire in the West Bank, hospitals said. Israel
radio said 11 soldiers were injured.
   The scope and intensity of the rioting, which lasted about 13
hours before subsiding around nightfall, was reminiscent of the
early days of the uprising, when tens of thousands took to the
streets in December 1987.
   It was the bloodiest day of the revolt since 17 Palestinians
were killed in clashes with Israeli troops on April 15, 1988.
Rioting broke out then when PLO military leader, Khalil Wazzir,
known by his nom de guerre Abu Jihad, was gunned downed in Tunis,
reportedly by Israeli commandos.
   Meanwhile, Arab leaders in Israel announced that Monday will be
a day of mourning and that they would hold a general strike to
protest the slayings.
   The army called up reinforcements, and Arabs reporters said
Palestinians were barred from entering Israel to prevent
retaliatory acts.
   The West Bank troop commander, Maj. Gen. Yitzhak Mordechai,
appealed on the radio in Arabic for Palestinians to remain calm.
   Palestinian leaders blamed Prime Minister Yitzhak Shamir's
right-wing government for creating a climate of anti-Arab sentiment
and called for international help in assuring the safety of the 1.7
million Palestinians living under Israeli occupation.
   ``The Israeli government is responsible for (the gunman's)
hatred and crime,'' said a leaflet by the pro-PLO underground.
``This government feeds it own people from their birth until their
death with hatred against our people and their rights for
independence and return.''
   Shamir went on Israel radio to condemn the attack and called on
Palestinians to ignore agitators who sought to incite riots.
   ``We were all disgusted by the terrible crime that happened
today. It is a cruel crime without any justification,'' he said.
   The act was condemned by a broad spectrum of Israeli
politicians, and the 13-member Cabinet considered a proposal to pay
compensation to the victims.
   The clandestine uprising leadership called for a three-day
protest strike. Twelve prominent Palestinian activists met with
Western diplomats, including U.S. Consul-General Phil Wilcox, and
announced a hunger strike.
   They demanded a U.N. Security Council meeting, international
investigation of Israeli occupation practices and ``immediate
international protection'' for the Palestinians living in
Israeli-occupied areas.
   In Tunis, a PLO statement called the shooting a ``massacre'' and
claimed it was the premeditated act of several Israeli soldiers.
   In Washington, State Department spokeswoman Sondra McCarty said:
``We deplore this senseless tragedy and extend our deepest
condolences to the families of everyone touched by this incident.''
   She called on the Israeli army ``to exercise restraint and for
all sides to make efforts to reduce tensions'' following the bloody
clashes in the occupied territories.
   Israeli police and Palestinian survivors said the gunman acted
alone.
   Survivors said the attacker was dressed in army pants and a
black jacket when he arrived at the Roses Junction, five miles
south of Tel Aviv. Palestinian laborers gather there every morning
to wait for day work, usually in construction.
   Survivors said the gunman arrived about 6:15 a.m. and approached
a group of about 50 laborers from the occupied Gaza Strip. He
ordered them to sit in a line and hand over their identity cards
when a white Peugot 504 stopped to let off more Arab workers.
   Fakri Kawara, 27, of Khan Yunis said the gunman told the Arab
driver to restart the car and leave the engine running.
   ``Then he killed him on the spot,'' said Kawara.
   The man then started shooting at those sitting on the ground.
Kawara said the gunman finished his first magazine and while
inserting another the surviving Arabs ran for cover in the
underbrush.
   ``After he killed everyone who was sitting there he started
shooting into the air,'' Kawara said.
   Khalil Abu Amsha, 30, a worker who was in the car and was
wounded in the left arm and leg, said from his hospital bed that he
thought the gunman was a soldier because he wore army pants.
   ``He said sit by your friends. We sat. He said take out your
(identity) cards. He said, `Do you know why I stopped you?' We
said, `No.' He said, `Good that you don't know.'''
   Police said the shooting of unarmed Palestinian laborers was the
gravest such incident in memory.
   They said the suspect is a 21-year-old man who had been
dismissed from the army as ``unsuitable for military service'' in
December 1988. They said he had spent nearly four months of his
18-month service in the stockade for disciplinary offenses.
   Although political motives were not ruled out, police commander
Haim Klein told reporters ``from what we know now his reasons were
personal.''
   He said the gunman told investigators he was suicidal after
breaking up with his girlfriend recently and said he also sought
revenge for a sexual attack made on him by an Arab eight years ago.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0044 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 1755EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SAfrica-Violence     05-20 0437</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-SAfrica-Violence,0454</SECOND>
<HEAD>Police Kill Three Blacks, Wound 12 in Clashes</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GREG MYRE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JOHANNESBURG, South Africa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Police on Sunday opened fire
on black demonstrators returning from a meeting where they decided
to end a boycott of white-owned businesses. Three people were
reported killed and 12 wounded.
   The incident began after thousands of blacks held the meeting in
the Thabong township outside the mining town of Welkom, 150 miles
southwest of Johannesburg. The boycott they decided to end was 11
days old.
   As the crowd returned home, police opened fire without warning,
witnesses said. Maj. Reg Crewe, a police spokesman, said police
used force only after the crowd began throwing stones and setting
houses and shops on fire.
   Three people were killed, according to Crewe and officials at
the Welkom Hospital.
   The hospital also said five patients were admitted with birdshot
and rubber bullet wounds. Seven other people were admitted to
another local hospital, the independent South Africa Press
Association reported.
   After the clash, youths put up barricades of burning tires in
the streets, while police ringed the township.
   Welkom has been the site of racial tension in recent weeks.
   Right-wing whites have established vigilante patrols to
``control'' blacks. Blacks responded with the consumer boycott.
   Black and white mineworkers clashed at a gold mine near Welkom
last week, leaving two whites dead and 14 blacks injured.
   Nationwide, right-wing whites have vowed to resist government
reforms of apartheid, the white government's system of racial
discrimination. Both black and white leaders have warned that
right-wing violence could jeopardize efforts to negotiate a new
constitution that would include the 28-million black majority.
   In other developments:
   _ A black man was killed and nine people injured when police and
soldiers conducted a door-to-door search near the Indian Ocean city
of Durban. Seventy people were arrested and a large quantity of
weapons were seized, the army said.
   _ Police said four blacks were wounded when officers fired on a
crowd lootings shops late Saturday and early Sunday in Virginia,
nine miles from Welkom.
   _ Five black prison guards ended a six-day sit-in protest at the
West German Embassy in Cape Town after receving assurances from the
government that their suspensions would be lifted.
   The five also received pledges that about 400 additional black
prison guards and policemen would be re-instated to their old jobs.
The guards were suspended or fired for taking part in an illegal
strike in March to protest discriminatory treatment.
   The protesters chose the West German Embassy because President
F.W. de Klerk was visiting that country Sunday as part of his
nine-nation European tour.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0045 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 1803EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Lebanon-Israel     05-20 0286</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lebanon-Israel,0296</SECOND>
<HEAD>Israeli Official Says No Hostage Swap Offer Received</HEAD>
<DATELINE>RASHAYA, Lebanon (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A senior Israeli official was quoted
Sunday as saying his government received no offer from a Shiite
militia to swap the remains of two Israeli soldiers for Arab
prisoners.
   The earlier report said the Amal militia had informed the
International Committee for the Red Cross it was making such an
offer.
   ``Israel has not officially been informed of such an offer,''
the unidentified official was quoted as telling the Voice of the
South Radio Station, which speaks for the Israeli-backed South
Lebanon Army militia.
   The official was also quoted as saying Israel and the South
Lebanon Army militia would be willing to consider a swap only if it
involved three Israeli servicemen captured by Shiite militias in
Lebanon in 1986.
   ``Israel will then be more than happy to negotiate and more than
happy to have Western hostages held in Lebanon released as part of
the deal,'' the official was quoted as saying.
   The Arabic language broadcast was monitored in Rashaya, in the
Bekaa valley in southeast Lebanon, close to the border strip that
Israel controls.
   The earlier report said the Shiite Moslem Amal had notified the
Red Cross of an offer to trade the bodies of two Israeli soldiers
for scores of Shiites held by Israel and the South Lebanon Army
militia.
   The report said the pro-Syrian Amal has the bodies of two
Israeli soldiers killed in action during the 1982 invasion of
Lebanon.
   However, ICRC officials in Beirut, who spoke on condition of
anonymity, said Amal made such an offer more than a year ago and
nothing came out of it.
   ``No new moves have been made,'' one official said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0046 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 1816EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Kuwait-Pardons     05-20 0381</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Kuwait-Pardons,0391</SECOND>
<HEAD>Fifteen Pro-Democracy Activists Pardoned in Kuwait</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ABDUL-JALIL MUSTAFA</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>KUWAIT (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Kuwait's Emir on Sunday pardoned 15 pro-democracy
activists accused of holding illegal meetings, the Kuwait News
Agency reported.
   The activists, all arrested in recent weeks for pressing demands
for the restoration of a fully elected parliament, were pardoned by
the Emir, Sheik Jaber al-Ahmed al-Sabah, the report said.
   ``The Emir has issued directives to the effect of ending all
cases initiated recently against a number of Kuwaiti citizens,
including former deputies of the National Assembly,'' the news
agency quoted official sources as saying.
   The arrests began May 8, when veteran opposition leader Ahmed
al-Khatib and seven of his followers were detained at a diwaniya,
which is a kind of town meeting held in a private home.
   The eight, along with three other activists charged with
distributing anti-government leaflets, were released three days
later. The authorities also released on bail a former parliamentary
deputy and one other man, but were still holding two members of the
defunct parliament.
   The move came in response to appeals by a number of Kuwaiti
notables who met with the Emir, the news agency said.
   ``They expressed to the Emir their appreciation for his paternal
and sincere attitudes toward countrymen who, though they differ on
the method of practising democracy, remain good sons and loyal
soldiers of Kuwait,'' the agency quoted the sources as saying.
   The pardon was viewed as a goodwill gesture toward the so-called
``Group of 32,'' the activists who called for a boycott of June 10
polling for the 75-member National Council. They said the
parliament was unconstitutional because the Emir will appoint 25 of
its members.
   More than 80 candidates have withdrawn from the National Council
race since the nomination deadline on May 9, bringing the number of
candidates to 485.
   The Emir issued a decree on April 22 setting up the chamber as a
four-year transitional legislature. It was to assess the country's
parliamentary experiment and propose future steps ``with a view to
averting the repetition of a third crisis.''
   This was a reference to the dissolution of the National Assembly
twice in a decade _ in 1976 and 1986 _ after members of parliament
verbally attacked government ministers, many of them members of the
ruling family.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0047 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 1823EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Yemen     05-20 0197</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Yemen,0204</SECOND>
<HEAD>South Yemen Jettisons Marxist Trappings Before Merger</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ADEN, South Yemen (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Socialist South Yemen, preparing for
its merger with pro-Western North Yemen, pulled down statues of
Marx and Lenin in public squares Sunday.
   Slogans of the ruling Yemeni Socialist Party _ such as ``No
voice can be louder than the voice of the Party'' _ were also
removed from government buildings.
   South Yemen was the Arab world's only avowedly Marxist state
after it gained independence from Britain in 1971. But as
democratization has swept many formerly hard-line socialist
countries, South Yemen has also been making reforms.
   The process accelerated after the ruling party's
Secretary-General Ali Salem al-Beidh pledged himself in November to
a merger with North Yemen within a year.
   Al-Beidh and North Yemeni President Ali Abdullah Saleh have been
speeding up their merger plans and are now set to proclaim unity in
coming days.
   As a gesture of solidarity between the two nations, the Yemeni
Socialist Party's central committee on Sunday announced it was
absorbing into its ranks the Popular Unionist Party, which had been
bitterly opposed to the North.
   The two Red Sea countries fought frequent border battles in
recent years.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0048 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 1836EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-KilaueaVolcano     05-20 0136</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Kilauea Volcano,0140</SECOND>
<HEAD>Kilauea's Lava Takes Another Home</HEAD>
<DATELINE>KALAPANA, Hawaii (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Kilauea Volcano's relentless lava
consumed another home Sunday and continued its slow, destructive
roll through this seaside community.
   The home of Brent Miller, which burned when lava reached it
before dawn, was the 143rd home destroyed in the seven-year
eruption of the volcano on Hawaii Island.
   The residents had evacuated earlier, as the lava chewed its way
through Kalapana. Just 30 homes remain in Kalapana; 67 have been
destroyed since April 4.
   Eight homes lay in the path of the lava ``in a very precarious
position,'' said Bruce Butts, deputy administrator of the Hawaii
County Civil Defense Agency.
   The flows were fed by lava pouring at an estimated rate of
650,000 cubic yards a day from a vent seven miles upslope from
Kalapana.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0049 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 1837EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Soviet-Space     05-20 0256</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Space,0262</SECOND>
<HEAD>Soviet Newspaper Says Cosmonauts Not in Danger</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Cosmonauts aboard the Soviet space station Mir are
not in danger of being stranded in space because of damage to their
craft, a newspaper reported. A U.S. magazine had reported the
problem jeopardized their return to Earth.
   The government newspaper Izvestia on Saturday quoted Flight
Director Yuri Serebranikov as saying some thermal insulation had
peeled off the hull of the Soyuz spacecraft but that ``in no way''
will prevent the cosmonauts from returning to Earth.
   The U.S.-based Aviation Week and Space Technology weekly
reported in its May 21 issue that cosmonauts Anatoly Solovyev and
Alexander Balandin, who have been in space for more than three
months, have no reliable way to return in an emergency because of
damage to the protective blankets that surround the space capsule.
   Serebranikov told the newspaper that some of the insulation
material had peeled off and could be seen by the spacecraft's
television cameras, but he added that there was no urgency in
repairing it.
   During the cosmonauts' next space walk, they will patch the
spot, he said. Izvestia described the repairs as ``routine.''
   Aviation Week interviewed cosmonaut Alexander A. Serebrov who
recently returned from the Mir, and it reported that three of eight
thermal blankets had peeled away, hampering the Soyuz spacecraft's
ability to control temperatures inside. It said the spacecraft has
become cold, and engineers are worried that condensation could
cause an electrical malfunction during re-entry.
   Izvestia, however, reported that temperatures inside the
spacecraft were normal.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0050 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 1845EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-People SUB a0699 05-20 0156</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People, SUB, a0699,0158</SECOND>
<HEAD>People in the News</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY44</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS final item to ADD that ride took place Saturday.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>NASHVILLE, Tenn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Singer-songwriter Steve Earle was
leading the pack when about 200 motorcyclists rallied to promote
handgun safety.
   The bikers rode Saturday to a cemetery where 13-year-old Jeffrey
Johnson is buried. He was killed in a game of Russian roulette in
February.
   The rally was planned ``to remind the public of the dangers of
children and firearms, and remind parents how quickly and how
easily a tragedy like this can happen,'' said Phil Chamblee, a
member of the Nashville Harley Owners Group.
   The bikers carried a headstone they donated for Jeffrey's burial
plot. More Chamblee said Earle, who has four Harleys, sang two
songs at the graveside.
   Earle, who lives in Nashville, is known for country-style albums
``Guitar Town'' and ``Exit O,'' and a departure into rock 'n' roll
with ``Copperhead Road.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0051 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 1853EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-LawSurvey     05-20 0300</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Law Survey,0307</SECOND>
<HEAD>Lawyers on Lawyers: `Obnoxious' but Smart</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Obnoxiousness is the quality lawyers like least
in their colleagues, according to a survey released Sunday.
   The finding was part of a non-scientific mail-in survey
conducted by the National Law Journal of New York City and West
Publishing Co. of St. Paul, Minn., which queried 1,018 lawyers
around the nation.
   Asked what they liked least about other lawyers, 56 percent
cited obnoxiousness; 34 percent, conceit; 29 percent, greed; and 24
percent, inflexibility. The respondents were allowed more than one
answer.
   ``Although these lawyers suggest that intellectual stimulation
... is one of the characteristics they value in the lawyers they
encounter, they also think that the lawyers they encounter are
obnoxious, conceited, greedy and inflexible,'' said the survey.
   Asked what they liked most about other lawyers, the most common
answers were intelligence, 54 percent, and integrity, 46 percent.
   Seventy-nine percent of the respondents said they were satisfied
with their careers and 80 percent said they would become lawyers
again if they had the chance.
   Seventy-five percent said intellectual stimulation is what they
especially like about practicing law. Other answers _ they were
allowed more than one _ included an opportunity to use their
skills, 58 percent; the opportunity to work with intelligent
people, 50 percent; money, 50 percent; and a sense of contributing
to society, 42 percent.
   Asked about the negative aspects of their profession, 56 percent
cited tension and pressure; 54 percent said too many work hours and
not enough personal time.
   ``In analyzing the results of this survey, it must be remembered
that the sample is not representative of lawyers in all areas of
practice or geographic areas,'' the pollsters cautioned. ``This
study is reflective only of the attitudes and opinions of the 1,018
respondents.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0052 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 1903EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SAfrica-Woods     05-20 0316</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-SAfrica-Woods,0327</SECOND>
<HEAD>Banned Journalist Free to Return to South Africa</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JOHANNESBURG, South Africa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Donald Woods, whose book on a
black activist was made into the movie ``Cry Freedom,'' is free to
return to South Africa after being banned for years, his former
newspaper said Sunday.
   The East London Daily Dispatch, where Woods was the editor in
the 1970s, said it had received a letter from President F.W. de
Klerk saying there were no restrictions or pending charges against
Woods.
   ``There really does seem to be a new spirit in South Africa, and
I'm greatly looking forward forward to coming back to experience it
for myself,'' Woods told his former newspaper in an interview from
London.
   Woods befriended Steve Biko before the black activist's death in
police custody in September 1977. A month later, Woods was placed
under a banning order that prevented him from working as a
journalist in South Africa.
   It was illegal for the media to quote Woods in South Africa
until February, when de Klerk announced a series of reforms lifting
restrictions on banned people.
   Woods and his family fled South Africa in 1978 and have been
living in London ever since. Woods' book on Biko, ``Cry Freedom,''
was made into a movie under the same title.
   In Surrey, England, Woods said he was delighted with the news.
   ``It's terrific because home is home,'' he said. ``I was born in
South Africa. So was my great-great grandfather. It's where we come
from, so it's a great feeling to know I can go back there without
charges pending or other legal complications from the South African
government.''
   Woods told the Independent Television News network he wanted to
further look into the death of Biko.
   ``I think the great tragedy of Steve Biko is that if he had been
alive, he'd be part of the mainstream leadership now negotiating
democracy,'' Woods said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0053 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 1916EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ChineseDiplomat     05-20 0613</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Chinese Diplomat,0628</SECOND>
<HEAD>Host Says Former Chinese Diplomat Visiting U.S. Won't Seek Asylum</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JEFF WILSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HACIENDA HEIGHTS, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A former Chinese diplomat whose
sudden flight to the United States aroused concern in Hong Kong
will return to China after a rest in California, his host said
Sunday.
   Xu Jiatun, for almost seven years director of the Hong Kong
branch of the Xinhua News Agency, China's de facto embassy in the
territory, slipped away to Los Angeles three weeks ago. Xu's exact
whereabouts were unknown.
   ``He told me that after he rests for a while he's planning to
make a broad survey and research on American society. He still
wishes to go back to his country and will not ever seek political
asylum,'' said Hsing Yun, the Buddhist monk who is Xu's host.
   Xu, 74, reportedly left without the approval of his government,
but Hsing Yun said he believed Xu had permission to leave the
British colony to visit the United States. He said Xu was carrying
a visa good for up to six months.
   The monk, who is master at Hsi Lai Temple in Hacienda Heights,
20 miles east of Los Angeles, called a news conference because of
persistent questioning by Chinese journalists and published
speculation in Hong Kong.
   Public confidence in Hong Kong's future under Chinese rule has
been shaken by the sudden flight of Xu from the British colony to
the United States.
   Xu directed the Hong Kong branch of the Xinhua News Agency for
nearly seven years. He has been in seclusion since arriving in
California on May 1.
   ``Because we are friends, I do not have the right to ask why he
came or for how long,'' the Chinese-speaking monk told reporters
through an interpreter. ``He said he did not come here to seek
political asylum.''
   The monk dispatched his political consultant, Lu Keng, to San
Francisco to bring Xu to Southern California. Lu told reporters Xu
didn't want to meet with them because questions might focus on
``touchy subjects.''
   ``The first word he said was that he came to have a good rest,
asking if I could find a nice quiet place for him,'' the religious
leader said. He fended off repeated questions as to Xu's
whereabouts.
   A flurry of newspaper stories in Hong Kong linked Xu's departure
to frustrations over the hard-line policies of China's leadership
following the bloody suppression of a pro-democracy movement in
Beijing last June.
   On Thursday the Chinese Foreign Ministry in Beijing broke its
silence and said Xu was merely ``touring and taking a rest in the
United States.''
   The explanation failed to convince many of Hong Kong's 5.7
million residents, who have long been suspicious of China's future
plans for the territory, which reverts to Chinese rule in 1997.
   China has said it will retain Hong Kong's freewheeling
capitalistic lifestyle for 50 years beyond 1997. But many there are
skeptical and fear any opposition to Chinese rule in the territory
will be brutally suppressed like the pro-democracy movement in
Beijing.
   ``If a veteran Chinese Communist Party member like Xu found
himself disillusioned, what else do the ordinary people here have
to count on?'' asked political analyst T.L. Tsim in Hong Kong.
   In 1983, when Xu arrived in Hong Kong, he was the highest-ranked
Chinese official ever named to head the Xinhua office. He was a
member of the party's central committee, and was reported to have
been personally selected for the job by China's paramount leader,
Deng Xiaoping.
   His assignment was to prepare Hong Kong for its eventual return
to China. He gradually cultivated an extensive network of contacts,
particularly among businessmen and the media.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0054 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 1920EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-WeatherpageWeather     05-20 0382</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Weatherpage Weather,0400</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rain in South, Northeast; Torrential Showers Trigger Arkansas
Flooding</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Showers and thunderstorms fell Sunday over the south-central
United States, the Southeast and the Northeast after torrential
rains triggered severe flooding in Hot Springs, Ark.
   Showers fell over much of the Northwest. Snow fell at higher
elevations of northern California and western Nevada; it was heavy
over California's northern Sierra Nevada and Nevada's portion of
Lake Tahoe.
   Showers and thunderstorms fell over eastern Texas, northern
Alabama, middle Tennessee, north-central Florida and southwestern
Georgia.
   A tornado watch was in effect in sections of northeastern Texas,
northern Louisiana and southern Arkansas. Severe thunderstorm
watches were posted for southeastern Texas and parts of Arkansas,
Louisiana, Mississippi, Alabama and Georgia.
   Flash flood watches were in effect in northern Alabama and
central and southwestern Arkansas.
   Overnight thunderstorms in Arkansas drenched the Hot Springs
area with nearly 12 inches of rain, including 4.6 inches in just
three hours Saturday night.
   The severe flooding that ensued caused heavy damage in the
resort city's business district; cars and several bridges were
washed away.
   Little Rock received 2.31 inches of rain Saturday, drowning the
record for the date of 2.23 inches set in 1928.
   Saturday night's thunderstorms were accompanied by seven
tornadoes, including four in Arkansas, in the south-central United
States.
   There were more than 60 reports of hail, including nearly 50 in
Oklahoma, and damaging winds. In Oklahoma, hail as big as baseballs
fell near Cushing and winds gusted to 75 mph in Pryor.
   On Sunday, thunderstorms and showers extended from north-central
North Carolina to the upper Ohio Valley and from the lower Great
Lakes region to southern and central New England. Flood watches
were in effect for southern Vermont and parts of eastern New York.
   Showers and a few thunderstorms also fell over central Nebraska
and south-central South Dakota.
   Rain showers fell in Washington state, Oregon, Idaho, western
Montana and northern California.
   Sunny skies prevailed from west Texas to Southern California and
southern Nevada.
   Strong winds prevailed over the Southeast and the south-central
region. Strong winds also blew over the southern High Plains and
the upper Great Lakes.
   Subfreezing temperatures were reported in Nevada's Great Basin
and the Rockies.
   The low for the nation Sunday morning was 23 degrees in
Gunnison, Colo.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0055 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 1927EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Romania-Elections 3rdLd-Writethru   05-20 1056</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania-Elections, 3rd Ld-Writethru,a0719,1092</SECOND>
<HEAD>Romanians Vote in First Free Elections Since 1937</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: INSERTS three grafs after 6th graf, `Iliescu had...' to
UPDATE with comments from opposition candidates. Pickup 7th graf
pvs, `Ballot counting...'</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos XBUC6,11,12,43</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARY BETH SHERIDAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUCHAREST, Romania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Excited Romanians voted Sunday in
their first free elections in 53 years, and a West German exit poll
predicted an overwhelming victory for interim President Ion Iliescu
and his National Salvation Front.
   The projection, based on an exit poll of 16,000 voters, was
announced on nationwide television while voters were still casting
ballots early Monday.
   According to the poll, Iliescu won 83 percent of the votes for
president, while his challengers _ the National Liberal Party's
Radu Campeanu and the National Peasant Party's Ion Ratiu _ won 11
percent and six percent respectively.
   In the vote for the two-chamber parliament, the Front won a
projected 66 percent, with no other party winning more than 10
percent. The exit poll was conducted by the West German INFAS, a
polling group, at the invitation of the government.
   If the exit poll proves correct, the Front will not have to form
a coalition, but will be able to govern alone.
   Iliescu had no comment on the poll, the state news agency
Rompress reported. But he praised citizens for their high turnout
and calm behavior. He said foreign observers were able to see ``the
virtues of Sunday's truly free elections.''
   Campeanu and Ratiu quickly condemned the poll.
   ``I find the (projected) results exaggerated, monstrously so.
They remind me of the returns in Ceausescu's time,'' Campeanu told
Rompress, referring to Communist dictator Nicolae Ceausescu.
   ``I do not believe they are fair,'' Ratiu said. ``I cannot
imagine that 83 percent of the Romanian people voted for Mr.
Iliescu.'' Ratiu said there were numerous instances of voter fraud
but presented no firm evidence.
   Ballot counting was to begin Monday and preliminary results were
expected Tuesday. Final returns are to be announced Friday.
   Slow-moving lines of 200 people or more snaked out of voting
centers on the clear, windy day as voters chose an heir to the
revolution that ousted the iron-fisted Ceausescu.
   The almost 16 million registered voters were choosing a
president and 506 representatives to the parliament.
   At several Bucharest polling stations, crowds of up to 500
waited patiently to vote after a midnight deadline for polls to
close. The original closing time of 11 p.m. was extended earlier in
the evening when it became clear that the voting was proceeding
much slower than expected, especially in the capital of Bucharest.
   ``Seeing this number of people willing to stand in line at this
time of night gives me great encouragement for this democracy,''
said New Mexico Gov. Garrey E. Carruthers, leader of the U.S.
Presidential Observer Delegation, as he visited polling stations in
a downtown Bucharest high school.
   ``I am voting for the first time in free Romania,'' said a
beaming Ioan Hurmuzachi, 67, waiting outside a Bucharest polling
center. ``I voted in the past under Ceausescu, but it was very
clear it was not real voting.''
   His comments appeared to reflect a universal joy among voters
casting ballots in the first free election since 1937.
   More than 80 parties ran candidates for parliament, but only
half a dozen were considered likely to win seats in the election,
which was by proportional representation.
   Iliescu had been heavily favored to win the presidency. His
Front _ a loose grouping of former Communists, workers and
technocrats that has dominated government since December's
revolution _ had also been expected to lead in the parliamentary
vote.
   The National Peasant Party and National Liberal Party have
emerged as the primary opposition to the Front.
   But the poll by INFAS, a respected West German institute, gave
the Liberals only 9.5 percent to 10 percent of the parliamentary
vote, and the Peasants' Party just 3.5 percent to 4 percent.
   No margin of error was given.
   The election was viewed internationally as a test of whether
Romania's interim government _ which included many former
Communists _ has truly embraced democracy.
   Some 500 foreign observers fanned out across the country to
monitor the election, which opposition parties repeatedly charged
had been unfair due to the Front's domination of politics and media.
   Ratiu said before casting his ballot in Bucharest that ``the
run-up to the election had been totally undemocratic.''
   Campeanu, also voting in the capital, called the elections ``a
great feat'' but added ``there is a fear they will be rigged.''
   Romania is the only country in Eastern Europe to overthrow its
Communist government through a violent revolution.
   Although the pre-election campaign occasionally turned violent,
no incidents were reported Sunday.
   Thousands of police and soldiers were dispatched to keep order
around polling centers.
   The biggest difficulty with the vote appeared to be moving
people through the polling stations quickly. Authorities said
voters took longer than expected to fill in the complex ballots,
and there were apparently not enough voting booths.
   State-run radio and television reported isolated incidents of
pre-stamped ballots being discovered in Bucharest and Cluj. It did
not give details.
   In Brasov, 100 miles north of Bucharest, some voting centers ran
out of ballots by mid-afternoon, the county electoral bureau
reported. Voters were forced to wait while officials transferred
extra ballots from other sites and ordered an emergency printing of
10,000 more ballots.
   The officials said the situation occurred because many people
received permission to vote outside their hometowns and cast their
ballots in Brasov.
   The main issues of the campaign included moving Romania's
centralized socialist system to a free-market economy and
dismantling the Communist system. Industrial workers, more than 40
percent of the labor force, have strongly opposed a rapid change to
capitalism, fearing it could promote unemployment.
   Opposition parties have claimed Iliescu will continue the
Communist system under a new name.
   Another issue was Romania's ethnic minorities, especially the 2
million ethnic Hungarians, who have complained of discrimination.
Tensions between Romanians and ethnic Hungarians exploded in March,
when six people were killed in clashes.
   Among those voting Sunday in Bucharest were Ceausescu's two sons
and daughter.
   The children _ Nicu, Valentin and Zoia Elena _ are under
investigation for crimes connected to their father's 24-year reign
and the revolution. Nicolae Ceausescu and his wife, Elena, were
executed after the revolution.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0056 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 1950EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Quayle-Explosions 1stLd-Writethru a0714 05-20 0172</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Quayle-Explosions, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0714,0175</SECOND>
<HEAD>Smoke Bombs, Firecrackers at Hotel Before Quayle Arrival</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS final graf to UPDATE with Quayle giving speech.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Smoke bombs and firecrackers were set off in the
lobby of a hotel Sunday, two hours before Vice President Dan Quayle
was due to address a Jewish group.
   Quayle hadn't arrived at the Sheraton Centre hotel when the
devices were set off, said John Mulligan, a Fire Department
spokesman.
   There was nothing concrete to link the explosions to Quayle's
visit, said Special Agent Allan Cramer, a Secret Service spokesman.
   There was no fire and no injuries were reported.
   Smoke in the rear of the hotel's main lobby and a loud explosion
were reported to fire officials at 4:41 p.m., Mulligan said. The
explosion, possibly from M-80 firecrackers, blew some of the tiles
out of the lobby ceiling, he said.
   The lobby was evacuated, he said.
   Quayle delivered his speech to The Union of Orthodox Jewish
Congregations of America at about 6:30 p.m. without incident.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0057 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 1959EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-DominicanElection     05-20 0286</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Dominican Election,0297</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dominican Officials Suspend Vote Count Amid Charges of Fraud</HEAD>
<BYLINE>SUSANA HAYWARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SANTO DOMINGO, Dominican Republic (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Election officials
suspended the vote count Sunday in a close presidential race at the
urging of former President Jimmy Carter after charges of vote fraud.
   In a televised announcement, Electoral Board officials read a
letter from Carter, who was an international observer to
Wednesday's balloting. The letter, recommended a halt in the vote
count while voter tallies from several municipalities are reviewed.
   Juan Bosch, 80, has accused his longtime political rival,
incumbent President Joaquin Balaguer, 83, of widespread fraud.
   Balaguer, a conservative, held a 0.5 percent lead after results
were counted from at least 93 percent of the polling stations.
Bosch, though an avowed Marxist, campaigned on a moderate platform.
   Bosch threatened to call for civil disturbances in protest until
election officials agreed to verify the vote count by comparing
tally sheets obtained by political parties at the polling stations
with those received by elections officials. That review began
Saturday.
   Electoral Board president Froilan Tavares said Sunday the vote
count would be suspended until the review was completed.
   In his letter, Carter said he was returning to observe the
laborious process on May 25.
   Tavares said mistakes were committed in several municipalities
which did not return complete tally sheets or had turned in tallies
unsigned by local election delegates, as is required by the
election Board.
   He said there were also other unspecified ``errors.'' Tavares
said the process of rechecking was expected to take several days.
   Before returning to the United States on Friday, Carter said he
had no evidence of fraud but said it was possible that ``honest
errors'' were committed.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0058 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 2013EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Senegal-Grenades     05-20 0142</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Senegal-Grenades,0145</SECOND>
<HEAD>Two Killed, 50 Wounded in Attack on Moslems in Senegal</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DAKAR, Senegal (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two hand grenades were tossed into a group
of praying Moslems, killing two people and wounding about 50, Radio
Senegal said Sunday.
   The radio said the attack occurred Saturday, the second in less
than a week in the Casamance region of southwestern Senegal. On
Thursday, armed men attacked a magistrate's office, killing his
chauffeur.
   Both attacks occurred near Ziguinchor, 250 miles south of Dakar,
in Casamance, the region of this West African nation separated from
the rest of the Senegal by English-speaking Gambia.
   No arrests were reported, and no explanation given for the
attacks.
   In the 1980s, a separatist group frequently clashed with
security forces in the region. More than 100 members of the
movement were killed and hundreds detained before the movement was
suppressed.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0059 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 2024EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-SeaplaneCircumnavigation     05-20 0553</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Seaplane Circumnavigation,0574</SECOND>
<HEAD>He'd Fly Around the World, Landing Only on Water</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TIM KLASS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SEATTLE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A seaplane enthusiast took off Sunday in
``perfect weather'' _ a rain shower _ in his second attempt to be
the first to fly around the world landing only on water.
   Leaving a dock on Lake Washington, pilot Tom Casey nearly
damaged a pontoon because of a fouled rudder line that caused the
one-engine plane to turn toward the shore.
   Casey killed the engine quickly, and the plane gently bumped
into the rocks. After a moment to free the line, he restarted the
engine and was airborne shortly before 11 a.m. PDT.
   Moments earlier, the former Seattle ski equipment and clothing
manufacturer shrugged off the intermittent rain.
   ``Oh, this is perfect weather,'' Casey said.
   Casey, 53, of Everett, said he had sunk everything he owns and
has borrowed $40,000 more to make the attempt. He estimated total
costs at more than $500,000, and has lined up sponsors to provide
money and materials.
   Casey's Cessna U206-G Stationaire II, painted red, white and
blue and dubbed ``Liberty II,'' was modified with tougher floats
and a more powerful engine and propeller.
   ``The security is my biggest concern. I'm not leaving this plane
alone, I'll tell you that,'' he said. ``I'll sleep in it if I have
to.''
   His circumnavigation attempt on a west-to-east route last year
ended about halfway when Liberty I overturned in a windstorm while
parked in Reykjavik, Iceland.
   Casey said he expected to fly an average of six or seven hours a
day and about half the distance alone.
   The rest he plans to fly with observers, including a
government-supplied navigator required for all flights that are not
on commercial air routes over the Soviet Union.
   He expects to make 80 takeoffs and landings on oceans, lakes and
rivers on a route to Anchorage, Alaska, across the Soviet Union
through Moscow and Leningrad, over Scandinavia to London, north to
Iceland and Greenland, south again to Maine and then through the
South and Midwest.
   His return is set for a day before the opening of the Goodwill
Games in Seattle on July 21.
   The toughest part is the 12-stop, 6,000-mile Soviet section,
largely because of the uncertainty of obtaining fuel and any needed
parts or service in remote areas, he said.
   If more miles are needed to make the 24,860 required for
certification as an around-the-world flight, Casey said he might
add a segment or two through Mexico.
   The distance minimum, the length a flight would take along the
Tropic of Cancer, is set by the Federation Aeronautique
Internationale, the official world air record sanctioning body.
   Casey said he had spent two years planning the trip but had been
toying with the idea for a decade.
   His inspiration, he said, was the first round-the-world flight
by two Douglas World Cruisers, also originating and ending in
Seattle, in 1924.
   Casey dismissed the notion that around-the-world flights to set
various records were becoming passe.
   ``I'll be indirectly blazing a trail,'' Casey said.
   ``If I can do it in a float plane, anybody can do it anywhere,''
he said. ``What aircraft can people relate to more than this
aircraft? Anybody can fly this plane. You can go right down and
rent one, just take off.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0060 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 2027EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Sudan-CoupAttempt     05-20 0168</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Sudan-Coup Attempt,0174</SECOND>
<HEAD>Officers Sentenced in Sudan's Failed Military Coup</HEAD>
<DATELINE>KHARTOUM, Sudan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A military tribunal sentenced two
officers to death on Sunday for involvement in a failed coup, but
the country's leader commuted their sentences to life imprisonment,
the official news agency said.
   The Sudan News Agency did not explain why the country's military
leader, Lt. Gen. Omar Hassan el-Bashir, commuted the death
sentences.
   The report said the two officers, an army major general and a
retired police major, were involved in a two-stage coup attempt
that Sudanese authorities crushed in March and April.
   Also on Sunday, 21 other army officers received prison terms
ranging from two years to life in connection with the failed coup.
One officer was acquitted.
   One day after crushing the April 22 coup attempt, 28 active or
retired army officers were executed by firing squads. Fourteen
other army officers were convicted with sentences of up to 15 years
in prison.
   El-Bashir seized power following a military coup on June 30.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0061 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 2032EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Bush 3rdLd-Writethru a0730 05-20 0912</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bush, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0730,930</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush Says Many Issues Remain Unresolved For Upcoming Summit</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: Subs 2nd graf to clarify; NOTE a0730 should have been
slugged, AM-Bush, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0695.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By RITA BEAMISH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PORTLAND, Ore. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush said Sunday that despite
new agreements on arms control, differences on ``a wide array of
subjects'' remain to be debated at his upcoming summit with Soviet
President Mikhail Gorbachev.
   Even though Secretary of State James A. Baker III and his Soviet
counterparts failed to make substantial progress on reducing troops
and tanks in Europe during four days of talks in Moscow, Bush said
he still believes a conventional forces treaty can be completed by
the end of the year.
   ``We've got to get that done,'' he said. ``Until it's totally
finished we've got to stay in close consultation'' with the Soviets.
   Although continuing to voice a measured reaction to the
agreements reached Saturday, the president said that, overall,
``I'm satisfied with the progress made in Moscow that we'll have a
good summit.
   ``In the arms control area, there's been some progress. There
still remain some other problems,'' including the sticky issue of
reducing tanks and troops in Europe, he told reporters traveling
with him on Air Force One from Houston to Portland.
   Other issues of conflict he expects to discuss in the May
30-June 3 summit in Washington, Bush said, include German
reunification and regional problems in Afghanistan and Cuba.
   ``Nobody thought it would be easy, so we're just plugging away
on a wide array of agenda items,'' he said. ``The differences will
be on the agenda.''
   Baker's talks in Moscow resulted in agreement on chemical
weapons reductions and resolution of thorny sticking points on
sea-launched and air-launched Cruise missiles.
   U.S. officials said the arms control agreement will result in
some kind of summit declaration _ short of a formal treaty _ that
would point the way to an overall reduction of 30 percent to 35
percent in U.S. and Soviet long-range bombers, missiles and
submarines.
   The chemical weapons treaty is expected to be ready for signing
at the summit in 10 days.
   Bush refused to clarify conflicting reports about what Secretary
of state James A. Baker III told Lithuanian Prime Minister
Kazimiera Prunskiene while in Moscow. U.S. officials with Baker
denied statements by some sources that he had urged the Lithuanians
to suspend their declaration of independence from the Soviet Union.
   Bush said he would not discuss what Baker might have said in
private, saying only, ``We want to see talks going,'' between
Moscow and the Lithuanian leaders. ``We want to see self
determination of the people of Lithuania.''
   Pressed on the U.S. position regarding whether Lithuania should
go along with Moscow's demand that it suspend the independence
gambit, Bush added that ``There's no point when you're trying to
make progress to discuss every aspect of it in public.''
   Later, in a speech to a law enforcement group, Bush accused
Congress of spawning ``weak imitations'' of his proposals to attack
crime after allowing them to languish for a year.
   ``We must reject those who soft-pedal the need to be hard on
crime,'' Bush said a day in advance of Senate debate on an
anti-crime bill.
   He accused lawmakers of sitting on key anti-crime measures he
first proposed a year ago. But he also acknowledged that Congress
agreed to his request for more federal law enforcement officers,
prosecutors and prisons as part of anti-drug legislation enacted
earlier.
   Bush said he still wants congressional action on his call for
expanded use of the death penalty, fewer burdens on police in
gathering evidence and limits on the length prisoners have for
filing federal appeals.
   ``I urge the Senate and in coming weeks the House to act quickly
and build America up by opposing those who would tear America
down,'' he said.
   Senate Democrats have recrafted Bush's proposals and, with the
support of law enforcement groups, inserted into the package a ban
on the sale and manufacture of nine types of semiautomatic assault
weapons.
   Fred McClure, Bush's legislative liaison, said the
administration now opposes much of the package and will push for a
substitute version by Sen. Strom Thurmond, R-S.C.
   The president visited Portland to attend a fund-raising event
Monday for gubernatorial candidate Dave Frohnmayer, and also for
Sunday's dedication of a memorial to Portland police officers slain
in the line of duty.
   The department has lost 21 officers in its 139-year history, the
last one 6 years ago, the White House said.
   Bush said the administration anti-crime proposal he unveiled in
May 1989 would help free the country from violent crime.
   ``Yet for the past year it has gathered dust in the House and
spawned weak imitations in the Senate,'' he said. ``America
deserves better. So do the 163 police officers who died last year.''
   Conservatives and the National Rifle Association are pushing
hard to remove the proposed ban on semiautomatic assault weapons in
the Democratic bill. Although he has move to restrict imports of
assault weapons, Bush has been unwilling to ban domestically
produced models.
   The Democratic package, however, also includes some provisions
more to Bush's liking. It authorizes the death penalty for 30
federal crimes, including presidential assassination, and reshapes
the sometimes drawn-out post-appeals process under which convicts
seek new trials.
   The bill also fine tunes the nation's money-laundering laws and
reverses Attorney General Dick Thornburgh's decision giving local
U.S. attorneys control over the Justice Department's
organized-crime strike forces.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0062 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 2046EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-RacialTension     05-20 0587</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Racial Tension,0617</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mayor Takes Pulpit, Leads Parade, In A `Bout With Bigotry'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By VERENA DOBNIK</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Mayor David Dinkins pleaded for peace from a
Harlem pulpit Sunday, saying racial tensions threaten to plunge the
nation's biggest city into ``a cycle of fear and frustration.''
   In Brooklyn, about 100 people organized by a civil rights
coalition marched past two Korean-American groceries that have been
boycotted mostly by blacks since January.
   An equal number of boycotters chanted slogans as an estimated
300 police officers guarded the stores and accompanied the
marchers, who called for an end to bigotry.
   The boycott is one of a series of situations or incidents that
have increased racial tensions in the city.
   The most serious involved the slaying by a white mob of a black
16-year-old who went to Brooklyn's Bensonhurst neighborhood with
three friends. A jury's verdict in the case Friday sparked further
polarization.
   The panel acquitted a 19-year-old accused of being the mob's
leader of murder and manslaughter charges, one day after another
jury convicted another 19-year-old of second-degree murder in the
Aug. 23 slaying of Yusuf Hawkins.
   Dinkins, New York's first black mayor, entered the Salem United
Methodist Church in a burned-out section of Harlem just before noon
Sunday, knelt alone before the altar and buried his face in his
hands to pray. Then he stepped to the pulpit.
   ``When Nelson Mandela arrives, I hope he will find a city at
peace,'' said Dinkins, referring to the scheduled visit next month
of the South African apartheid fighter.
   ``Tensions are threatening to plunge New York into a cycle of
fear and frustration that could tear us apart,'' the mayor told
several hundred worshipers.
   ``We all come from somewhere else. We came here to escape
prejudice,'' he said, repeating a theme of earlier recent appeals
for racial harmony.
   Dinkins praised a group of black high school students who last
week defied the boycott and shopped at one of the groceries.
   The boycott was triggered by accusations that a black woman was
attacked in the store by a Korean-American employee who suspected
her of shoplifting.
   ``I believe the boycott can be solved in a peaceful, negotiated
way,'' Dinkins added. ``We need to be free to walk on any street,
free to shop in any store.''
   Dinkins walked out of the church to a roaring, standing ovation.
The congregation sang the civil rights anthem ``We Shall Overcome''
as they swayed and held hands in a chain.
   Later, Dinkins led the Martin Luther King Jr. memorial parade up
Fifth Avenue. Several hundred people took part in the parade, which
was sparsely attended.
   ``This year's parade is more important than any other,'' said
Roman Catholic Cardinal John O'Connor, who greeted the mayor on the
steps of St. Patrick's Cathedral.
   O'Connor said he would try to join labor and church leaders in a
discussion of the city's racial problems set for Tuesday.
   Marchers in Brooklyn's Flatbush section Sunday said they were
neither for nor against the boycott, but wanted to see an end to
racial discrimination and bigotry.
   As the marchers disappeared down the street, the boycotters
chanted, ``What does the fortune cookie say. No money today?''
   The march continued past the site where a Vietnamese immigrant
was seriously beaten by a group of blacks. Police later
characterized that a random confrontation, unrelated to race.
   ``We the people of New York in goodwill say, `No more,'' Norman
Siegel, head of the New York Civil Rights Coalition, said through a
bullhorn.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0063 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 2103EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-CubanFlotilla 1stLd-Writethru a0684 05-20 0580</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Cuban Flotilla, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0684,0593</SECOND>
<HEAD>Flotilla Takes Democracy Demonstration to Edge of Cuba's Waters</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 8 grafs to UPDATE with radio message received in
Cuba, exile reax and details of ceremony, picks up 7th graf pvs,
`Coast Guard...</NOTE>
<DATELINE>KEY WEST, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A flotilla of private boats piloted by
exiles sailed Sunday across the wave-tossed Florida Straits to
rally for democracy on the edge of communist Cuba's territory.
   Cuban patrol boats were waiting, but there were no
confrontations, said Lt. Cmdr. Jeff Karonis, a Coast Guard
spokesman.
   ``It was a very emotional moment for all the Cubans who
particiapted in this,'' said Julio Rebull of Miami. ``We felt we
were right in front of the wall, like the Berlin wall, that
separates our people.''
   Although 34 boats sailed from Key West at sunrise, only 24 made
it all the way to the rendezvous point about 20 miles north of the
Cuban coast by early afternoon, Karonis said.
   The flotilla sailed parallel with the Cuban coast for about six
miles, then headed back across the strait for Key West, said Petty
Officer Luis Diaz.
   Exiles tossed wreaths of flowers and bottles with messages into
the water, Rebull said. For seven minutes, a Catholic priest read
prayers to a Cuban operator monitoring a VHF radio channel from the
lighthouse at Havana harbor, he added.
   ``By just looking and knowing on the horizon that we were less
than an hour away from our homeland, and after talking on the VHF,
everyone was crying,'' said Rebull, 53, a veteran of the 1961 Bay
of Pigs invasion. ``For me personnally, it was the most emotional
moment in my 30 years of exile.''
   Rebull said the Cuban operator acknowledged recieving the
message, but made no further response. The ocean current carried
the messages and flowers north, away from Cuba.
   Coast Guard Cutters on patrol in the Straits monitored the
flotilla by radar, but did not provide an escort, Coast Guard
officials said. They had warned the exiles to protest verbally but
go along peacefully if they were intercepted by Cuban defense
forces, and also warned them that Cuba claims a territorial sea
extending 12 miles or more from the coastline.
   The expedition was billed as a peaceful demonstration against
Cuba's Communist government as well as a celebration of Cuba's
independence from Spain.
   ``It will bring a message of solidarity and support for efforts
seeking democracy in Cuba,'' spokesman Jose Basulto said before the
flotilla sailed.
   Backers had said they expected more than 100 boats to take park.
But Diaz said that no more than 51 signed up, and only 34 actually
sortied out of Key West.
   For reasons ranging from breakdowns to not wanting to buck
5-foot waves in the center of the 90-mile-wide straits, 10 of those
34 stayed on this side, Diaz said.
   It's not the first time Cuban exiles have ventured into the
Florida Straits to protest Castro's government. In September 1988,
two boatloads of exiles left Key West to protest human rights
abuses on the island. Cuban gunboats stopped them 17 miles offshore.
   Coincidentally, as the flotilla headed south Sunday morning, two
Cubans escaping the island on a raft of innertubes were spotted by
a pleasure boat in the Straits about 20 miles east of Key West.
   Karonis said the sunburned pair were picked up by a Coast Guard
boat and brought in to Key West, where they were turned over to
U.S. immigration authorities Sunday afternoon.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0064 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 2146EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Bush-Owl     05-20 0481</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bush-Owl,460</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush Vows Interest in Spotted Owls, But Also in Jobs</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RITA BEAMISH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PORTLAND, Ore. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush said Sunday the jobs of
timber-related workers must be considered before forests are
cordoned off to protect the northern spotted owl.
   Rep. Dennis Smith, R-Ore., said Bush promised him Sunday night
that he would try to schedule a White House meeting in which
logging interests and others could present their case before a
decision is made on whether to protect the owl by listing it either
as a threatened or an endangered species.
   ``There's a lot of people who's livelihood is threatened out
here. ... I want to hear more about it,'' Bush said during a photo
session with Smith. ``We're trying to find out what is the right
thing to do. We've got to be concerned about the human equation as
well as the environmental equation,'' he said.
   A federal inter-agency task force recommended setting aside
several million acres of forest land as preserves to save the
northern spotted owl. The U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service is
deciding whether to list the bird as a threatened or an endangered
series, or to leave it unprotected.
   Locally, estimates have circulated that 28,000 timber-related
jobs could be lost if the preserves are established and put off
limits to logging.
   ``I'm interested in the owl, very much so, and I'm also
interested in jobs,'' Bush said during a second photo opportunity
with Washington GOP congressional candidate Bob Williams. ``So
we'll try to find a balanced approach.''
   He said he was ``determined to come down on the side of people''
and still have a sound environmental policy. ``I want to be known
as the environmental president,'' Bush told Smith, ``But I also
want to be one who's concerned about a person's ability to hold a
job and have a job. There's a lot at stake here in this question.''
   Bush was to talk about the owl issue Monday at a GOP
fund-raising event.
   Smith told reporters that if the spotted owl is declared a
threatened species, then environmentalists ``are going to go out
and find all kinds of owls'' and make more forest areas off limits.
   ``We don't have an endangered species. We have an endangered
subspecies, if even that,'' he said. ``There are millions of owls
in this world. This little puppy just happens to be kind of a
passive kind of an animal that is being run over by the great
horned owl. The bottom line is people are more important than
owls.''
   Smith said at the White House meeting he wants ``to tell the
president what's wrong with the endangered species act.''
   Bush campaigned on a platform promising to be the environmental
president. So far his environmental record has been more
progressive than that of his predecessor Ronald Reagan, but has
drawn mixed reviews from environmentalists.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0065 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 2148EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Taiwan-China 2ndLd-Writethru a0737 05-20 0705</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Taiwan-China, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0737,0723</SECOND>
<HEAD>Taiwan's President Calls For Better Ties With China</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with four grafs to UPDATE with Shih released. Pickup
pvs 6th graf, `Human rights...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By ANNIE HUANG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TAIPEI, Taiwan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Lee Teng-hui on Sunday urged an
end to hostilities with China's Communist government and released
10 political prisoners to mark his inauguration.
   It was the first time a Taiwan president had publicly indicated
a desire to move away from the 40-year-old policy of the ``three
No's'' toward Beijing _ no official contact, no negotiations and no
compromise.
   At his presidential inauguration ceremony, Lee also promised an
amnesty for political prisoners. He pledged the restoration of
civil rights to previously jailed political prisoners _ including
the chairman of the opposition Democratic Progressive Party _
allowing them to run for public office.
   Nine people imprisoned on sedition charges were released Sunday,
including Hsu Hsin-liang, 49, who was jailed last year after
returning from self-imposed exile in the United States.
   Taiwan's best-known political prisoner, Shih Ming-teh, was also
released early Monday morning. He had been jailed in 1979 on
charges of instigating an anti-government riot in the southern port
city of Kaohsiung.
   He had originally refused to allow his family to sign for his
release because he maintains he is innocent, his sister said.
   Human rights groups claim Taiwan has roughly a dozen other
political prisoners.
   Meanwhile, Lee's nomination of the nation's only four-star
general as premier continued to spark protests on Sunday. About
10,000 people, including students and opposition party members,
staged a noisy march through Taipei, smashing windows and throwing
eggs at offices of the military and the ruling Nationalist Party.
   Lee heads the Nationalist Chinese government that has been based
on the island of Taiwan ever since losing a civil war to Communist
forces on the Chinese mainland in 1949.
   The Nationalists still claim to be the rightful government of
all China, and Beijing regards Taiwan as a renegade province.
   Lee proposed establishing ``channels of communication'' and said
the two countries should ``completely open up academic, cultural,
economic, trade, scientific and technological exchange to lay a
foundation of mutual respect, peace and prosperity.''
   ``We hope then, when objective conditions are ripe, we will be
able to discuss the matter of our national reunification,'' he
said. Reunification is a long-standing goal of the Nationalists.
   But Lee said before such relations could be established, Beijing
must renounce the use of force against Taiwan, end its policy of
isolating Taiwan diplomatically, and promote democracy and a free
economic system in China.
   While Beijing previously has indicated it would not meet
conditions set by Lee, the speech clearly was designed to reflect
Taipei's desire to gradually improve relations with its neighbor
across the Taiwan Straits. Recently, civilian and business contacts
have been growing between the two sides.
   The president also expressed a desire to end within two years
the ``Mobilization for the Suppression of the Communist
Rebellion,'' which dates from 1948. The decree has ensured the
Nationalists' monopoly on power by stipulating that legislators
elected before 1949 on the Chinese mainland must stay in office
until they can return to their ``constituencies'' for re-election.
   This has presented obstacles to expanding relations with China
and introducing democratic reforms in Taiwan.
   Lee also stressed his commitment to bring more democracy to
Taiwan, but his nomination of Gen. Hau Pei-tsun as the new premier
has led opposition politicians and intellectuals to question the
government's commitment.
   In recent years, the Nationalist Party has lifted martial law,
allowed multiparty elections and eased press restrictions. But
protesters closely identify Hau, 71, with the party's authoritarian
past and believe his nomination could lead to a resurgence of
military influence.
   Hau was chief of the general staff for eight years before
becoming Defense Minister last year.
   The half-hour presidential inauguration ceremony at the Sun
Yat-Sen Memorial Hall, attended by about 2,600 people, went off
without incident.
   Lee became the first native Taiwanese to lead the government in
January 1988 when he moved up from the vice presidency to succeed
President Chiang Ching-kuo, who died in office.
   Chiang was the eldest son of Chiang Kai-shek, the Nationalist
leader who led the retreat to Taiwan four decades ago.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0066 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 2150EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-FloodsRdp 2ndLd-Writethru a0711 05-20 1171</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Floods Rdp, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0711,1200</SECOND>
<HEAD>Flash Floods Hit Central Arkansas, Strand Residents on Rooftops</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS grafs 8-13, `The storms also ...,' with 6 grafs to
UPDATE that four tornadoes hit area, at least eight other bridges
washed away; CORRECT that 2 feet of water over dams, sted 3;
CORRECT location of Remmel Dam; picks up 14th graf, `Gov. Bill ...'
INSERTS 2 grafs after 27th graf, `Elsewhere ...,' to UPDATE with
Sioux City flooding; picks up 28th graf, `The search ...'</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos HT3,4</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ANDREA WEISGERBER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Flash floods turned streets into rivers in Hot Springs, Ark.,
and pushed lakes out of their banks, sweeping away cars and
stranding residents of lakefront homes on rooftops in yet another
onslaught of high water.
   The flooding followed thunderstorms that began Saturday
afternoon and brought up to a foot of rain and high winds to
central Arkansas by early Sunday morning. The water receded by late
morning, revealing extensive damage along this resort city's
central business district, authorities said.
   ``Cars have been completely immersed and washed away. We've got
a lot of shops and stores that are flooded,'' said police spokesman
Michael McCormick.
   The new floods brought misery to a different part of the region
from the rampage along the Arkansas, Trinity and Red rivers that
has caused hundreds of millions of dollars in losses and killed 13
people in the past three weeks in Texas, Arkansas, Oklahoma and
Louisiana. Floodwaters continued to surge through southern segments
of that region Sunday.
   Floods eased in Missouri, Kansas, Illinois and Indiana. At least
two people died in Illinois, and authorities searched for a woman
missing in flooding in Missouri last week.
   In some parts of Hot Springs, the water had reached the tops of
parking meters before beginning to recede.
   The storms dumped up to 12 inches of rain in Garland and Hot
Spring counties Saturday night and early Sunday. The National
Weather Service said 2 feet of water was pouring over the top of
Remmel Dam at Lake Catherine.
   The storms also brought four tornadoes, including a twister that
destroyed one home, damaged another and destroyed a barn in nearby
Conway County. No injuries were reported. Hail pelted a number of
central Arkansas counties.
   Floodgates at the Remmel Dam and the Carpenter Dam upstream on
Lake Hamilton were fully opened to release water from the lakes
into the Ouachita River. ``They've all overflowed their banks,''
said Ralph Lee, assistant director of Garland County Office of
Emergency Services.
   Residents of low-lying areas in Garland County left their homes
and sought shelter at a National Guard armory and churches, Lee
said. He said there was no estimate available on the number of
people evacuated.
   ``The hardest hit areas are the ones closest to the lakes,'' Lee
said. ``A lot of the lakefront homes have been evacuated and the
ones who waited too late are on top of their homes.''
   Residents were still being rescued from rooftops by boat Sunday
morning.
   The floods caused power outages throughout Hot Springs, and
washed away a landmark 90-year-old iron bridge and at least eight
other bridges in the area.
   Gov. Bill Clinton declared Garland County a state disaster area
after inspecting flood damage in Hot Springs, making assistance
available to flood victims.
   The county was also added, along with Clay County, to a federal
disaster declaration covering 20 other counties hit by flooding,
said Ray Briggler of the state Office of Emergency Services.
   In southeastern Texas, tempers began flaring in flooded
communities along the Trinity River, where sheriffs' deputies were
keeping an eye on joyriders in boats and recreational vehicles.
   ``We've had a couple of incidents that haven't been bad, but
some of the teen-agers, they want to go out with their four-wheel
drives and things,'' said Liberty County sheriff's dispatcher Jo
Griffith. ``We go out and talk to them and tell them they're not
really helping.''
   Waves from boat wakes can cause more damage to flooded homes,
and property owners are angry, said Jim Mitchum of the Liberty
County emergency management office.
   Mitchum said 500 to 700 people per day were being fed from the
county's emergency mobile kitchen and about 60 people stayed at
emergency shelters overnight Saturday in Liberty County. At least
2,000 homes are in 15 to 20 subdivisions in the floodwaters' path,
but Mitchum did not have an estimate on how many actually are
flooded.
   Forty-nine families have not evacuated from subdivisions.
``They're staying in against our recommendation,'' Mitchum said.
   Closer to the Lake Livingston Dam, sheriffs dispatchers in San
Jacinto and Polk County said about 100 homes sustained flood
damage. Many are under water.
   Engineers Sunday were still releasing 100,800 cubic feet per
second of water through the dam, which remained a foot over flood
stage, the Trinity River Authority said. Usually, about 7,000 cfs
of water goes through the dam and 20,000 cfs is enough to cause
flooding.
   Engineers expected the 100,000-plus level to be sustained for at
least the next few days, Mitchum said.
   The Trinity at Liberty is expected to crest at 29{ feet, 5{ feet
above flood stage, by the end of next week and remain at that level
for at least several days, the weather service said.
   In east-central Louisiana, a dike built by hundreds of
volunteers at Vick was credited with saving 30,000 acres and about
300 homes from the raging Red. A similar dirt dike covered with
plastic was expected to protect 300 to 400 homes and 50,000 acres
of cropland.
   About 370 people in five northwestern Louisiana parishes have
had to leave their homes because of flooding by the Red. The river
is expected to crest about 7 feet above flood stage Monday at
Alexandria, and the weather service warned residents to be alert.
   Elsewhere:
   _ In Sioux City, Iowa, firefighters and public works crews
Sunday helped homeowners clean up from a flood by Perry Creek the
day before that left oozing mud several feet deep in parts of the
city. Three bridges remained closed and two may have to be rebuilt.
   Gov. Terry Branstad has declared the city a state disaster area.
   _ The search continued Sunday near Jefferson City, Mo., for a
woman who may have been swept away Thursday by floodwaters on the
Moreau River. The Mississippi River at St. Louis crested at 33
feet, 3 feet above flood stage, and was expected to drop 6 feet by
Tuesday.
   _ In southern Illinois, several homes in Lawrenceville were
evacuated because of the rising Embarras River, which was expected
to crest almost 11 feet above flood stage Sunday.
   _ Rivers continued dropping in southern Indiana. The weather
service predicted an end by Thursday to flooding that last week
reached the highest levels in more than 20 years in some places.
   Flooding on the White River late Friday washed away at least
3,000 feet of water lines in Petersburg. People in the
3,500-resident town were urged to boil water for drinking and
cooking, and water was brought in by tanker truck.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0067 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 2217EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-RevisionistHistory     05-20 0421</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Revisionist History,0437</SECOND>
<HEAD>Pilgrims Sailed in the Pinto? Wait a Minute ...</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BELLEVUE, Wash. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   How's this for revisionist history? The
pilgrims sailed to America in the Pinto. Paul Revere wrote ``The
Star-Spangled Banner.'' Sandra Day O'Connor is chief justice of the
U.S. Supreme Court.
   And Gen. Douglas MacArthur said, ``Give me liberty or give me
death.'' Or was it Martin Luther King Jr.?
   These are samplings of responses from community-college students
to questions that might be asked of immigrants seeking U.S.
citizenship.
   Just five of 119 students at Bellevue Community College managed
a passing grade of 70 percent or better.
   ``This is pretty bad,'' said Aslam Khan, head of the college's
political science department, who administered the test.
   ``Why should we give these questions to foreigners when our own
citizens don't know what is going on?'' asked the Pakistan-born
Khan, who took such a test when he became a naturalized citizen.
   Less than half the students knew that the supreme law of the
land is the Constitution.
   When asked what kind of government the United States has, many
answered ``capitalist,'' rather than a democracy.
   Some said the pilgrims left Europe because they were searching
for something to colonize, apparently forgetting the religious
persecution that prompted them to flee to the New World.
   A decade ago, Khan gave a similar test of 10 questions to 118
students. Six passed.
   ``It's not getting any better,'' he said.
   It may be good for a few snickers when a student identifies
Abraham Lincoln as the principal author of the Declaration of
Independence, but when only one student answers 29 of the 30
questions correctly and just 18 get 60 percent right, everybody
should be concerned, Khan said.
   ``I think people should know what is going on in this country,''
he said. ``We really do need a course in remedial American
Government.''
   For the record:
   _ The Pinta, not the Pinto, was one of three ships used by
Christopher Columbus, along with the Nina and the Santa Maria. The
pilgrims sailed in the Mayflower.
   _ Francis Scott Key wrote the national anthem, while Paul Revere
warned American revolutionaries the British were coming.
   _ Ms. O'Connor is the first woman to serve on the Supreme Court,
which has yet to have a woman chief justice.
   _ Patrick Henry preferred death over tyranny in his famous to
the Virginia House of Burgesses, while MacArthur is remembered for
pledging ``I shall return'' to the Philippines and civil-rights
leader King for his ``I have a dream'' speech.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0068 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 2223EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-East-West     05-20 0378</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-East-West,0394</SECOND>
<HEAD>Czechoslovakia Joins Unprecedented Four-Nation Group</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ALISON SMALE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>VIENNA, Austria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Czechoslovakia on Sunday joined four
other European nations in the first regional cooperation group to
unite NATO, Warsaw Pact and neutral nations.
   The other members of the group are Austria, Italy, Yugoslavia,
and Hungary.
   Representatives of the five nations met in Vienna on Sunday to
discuss ways of furthering cooperation in transport,
communications, the environment, culture and small businesses.
   A senior foreign ministry official from Hungary and the foreign
ministers of the other nations took part in the discussions.
   The organization grew out of cooperation between border regions
of Italy, Yugoslavia, Austria and Hungary that began 11 years ago.
   It is the only regional cooperation organization to unite
neutral nations with countries from the West's North Atlantic
Treaty Organization and the Soviet-led Warsaw Pact.
   The four nations decided to boost cooperation last fall, just
before a peaceful revolution in Czechoslovakia toppled the
Communists and brought a pro-democracy government headed by former
dissidents to power.
   The decision to admit Czechoslovakia was taken in April. Members
of the group said say Romania and Bulgaria have also applied to
join.
   Italian Foreign Minister Gianni de Michelis said at a news
conference that one aim of the organization is to ensure that
Western Europe does not become preoccupied with questions posed by
Germany's reunification at the expense of other regions.
   He said the five nations hope to be among the first to apply for
investment grants to the new bank for European Development and
Cooperation formally founded in Paris on Saturday.
   The five also intend to present to a forthcoming 35-nation
conference in Copenhagen, Denmark, on human rights proposals on
minority rights designed to defuse potential ethnic conflicts,
particularly those in Eastern Europe, de Michelis said.
   During an hourlong televised discussion, the five officials each
stressed the importance of the group as a way to bring together
organizations with diverse affiliations but common pasts and
interests.
   Yugoslavia is nonaligned and in transition between Communism and
democracy. Czechoslovakia and Hungary, moving swiftly toward
Western-style democracy, are still members of the Soviet-led Warsaw
Pact and Comecon. Austria is a neutral member of the European Free
Trade Association, and Italy is in NATO and the European Community.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0069 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 2227EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-DrugPolice     05-20 0254</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Drug Police,0261</SECOND>
<HEAD>Students Tell Undercover Police to Just Say No</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Undercover officers who went to high school
campuses to buy drugs this year say they ran into something never
encountered before: students who told them to just say no.
   All eight young officers who posed as high school students on
nine Los Angeles campuses last semester ran into at least some
students who advised them against using drugs, Police Chief Daryl
Gates said Friday.
   Officer Sonia Caballero added that some students she approached
about buying drugs even told her they don't like to associate with
people who are users.
   Gates said that was the first time in the 17-year history of the
department's twice-a-year high school drug-buy program that ever
happened. He hopes it means the tide may be turning against drug
use among Los Angeles high school students.
   ``I feel we are moving toward winning our war on drugs on the
campuses,'' he said.
   Gates said police made about 165 purchases from 139 dealers at
the nine high schools. He said 120 arrests have been made so far,
with more anticipated.
   Nearly $10,000 worth of drugs, including LSD, amphetamines and
psilocybin, was seized.
   Gates said as many as 300 buys would routinely be made during a
semester in the 1970s, when campus drug use appeared to be at its
height.
   But he acknowledged that buys may be down in part because
students have become more careful because the word is out that
undercover ``narcs'' haunt their campuses.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0070 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 2240EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Canada-TireFire     05-20 0183</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Canada-Tire Fire,0187</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tire Fire Near Montreal Extinguished After Three Days</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   ST-AMABLE, Quebec (AP) _ Firefighters used sand to smother the
last flames of a fire that raged for three days through a dump near
Montreal that held 3 million tires, an official said.
   Mayor Jacques Doyon of St-Amable, a community of 5,000 near the
tire dump, said the fire was extinguished at about midnight
Saturday.
   Doyon said the 16 families evacuated from their homes were being
allowed to return.
   On Thursday, Doyon recommended that people living near the dump
evacute their homes to avoid the thick, chocking smoke that was
drifting toward the area. The town is located 18 miles southeast of
Montreal and 50 miles from the U.S. border.
   The fire began Wednesday and quickly spread over most of the
dump, an area the size of seven football fields. It sent up a
column of thick smoke more than 4,000 feet high.
   
   Provincial police issued a statement Sunday saying investigators
believe the fire may have started in the undergrowth of a nearby
ditch. They said the investigation was continuing.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0071 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 2259EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Tutu     05-20 0192</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Tutu,0198</SECOND>
<HEAD>Appearance by Tutu Disrupted by Jewish Militants</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PASADENA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Activists from the militant Jewish
Defense League heckled Archbishop Desmond Tutu on Sunday, forcing
cancellation of an outdoor reception for the Nobel Peace Prize
winner at an Episcopal church.
   The protesters shouted angry epithets at Tutu, prompting All
Saints Episcopal Church officials to hustle the spiritual leader
away from the area and cancel the outdoor reception.
   ``Tell him to lay off Israel,'' said Irv Rubin, JDL spokesman.
He was apparently referring to Tutu's recent trip to the Middle
East where he urged Jewish leaders to forget the Holocaust and
spoke out in support of a separate Palestinian state.
   ``Why do you hate Jews?'' the JDL members chanted.
   The Rev. Dr. George Regas, rector of the church, said Tutu was
not angered by the demonstrators.
   ``Please let them say what they want to say, because in my
country they are not allowed to do that,'' Regas quoted Tutu as
saying.
   Before the confrontation, Tutu delivered an hour-long sermon to
an overflow crowd. Up to 2,000 people were turned away and watched
the service on closed circuit television sets outside.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0072 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 2317EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Colombia 2ndLd-Writethru a0727 05-20 0675</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Colombia, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0727,0694</SECOND>
<HEAD>Candidates Make Last Appearances in Bloody Colombian Campaign</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 2 grafs for 10th `In the...' to UPDATE with new attack
wounding six; PICKUP graf 11 pvs `Death threats...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By STAN YARBRO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOGOTA, Colombia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Defying death threats from drug
traffickers, Colombia's presidential front-runner spoke to more
than 5,000 supporters at a stadium Sunday near the end of the most
violent race in the nation's history.
   ``We have arrived here to finish the campaign amid all the
difficulties that the violent ones have placed upon us,'' said
43-year-old Cesar Gaviria, referring to drug traffickers.
   ``We have arrived here to defend our democracy, convinced that
the only tool Colombian citizens have to fight the violence is that
democracy,'' he said during his speech at the indoor stadium in
Bogota, the capital.
   The rally was Gaviria's last chance to personally addresss
supporters because Colombian law prohibits public appearances by
candidates during the last week of the campaign.
   During the race for the May 27 elections, three candidates were
killed.
   In less than nine months, gunmen believed to have been working
for drug traffickers have killed Luis Carlos Galan of the governing
Liberal Party, Bernardo Jaramillo of the Patriotic Union Party and
Carlos Pizarro of the April 19 Movement, or M19.
   It was Galan's assassination in August that set off a
U.S.-backed government crackdown on the traffickers, who responded
with a wave of violent attacks.
   Since August, President Virgilio Barco's administration has
extradited 14 drug suspects, killed Medellin cartel leader Gonzalo
Rodriguez Gacha, and confiscated hundreds of properties belonging
to the cocaine magnates.
   Bombings blamed on the Medellin cartel, including urban car-bomb
attacks and an explosion aboard a Colombian jetliner, have killed
about 300 people in the last nine months.
   In the latest attack, a car bomb exploded late Sunday outside a
shopping center in northern Bogota, wounding six people and causing
extensive damage to buildings, officials said.
   Earlier Sunday, gunmen wounded two pedestrians when they sprayed
the police headquarters in the city of Medellin with automatic
weapon fire.
   Death threats forced Gaviria, who replaced Galan as Liberal
Party candidate, to cancel recent campaign appearances.
   Campaign sources said they believed the death threats were from
drug traffickers angry over the candidate's promise to continue a
government crackdown on the country's cocaine cartels.
   During his speech, Gaviria repeated his promise to carry forward
Galan's reform program, including changes in the country's congress
and judiciary.
   Colombians frequently point to the congress as the governmental
branch most corrupted by drug traffickers' payoffs. Traffickers
have also severely damaged the country's judicial system by
bribing, threatening and killing judges.
   ``We are obligated to reform our justice system,'' Gaviria said
Sunday. ``It must be made effective so that we Colombians can
confront the violence that comes from drug traffickers,
narco-terrorists and common criminals.''
   Fifteen bodyguards, their jackets bulging with firearms, crowded
around the candidate as he spoke from a podium 20 feet above the
crowd on the stadium's floor.
   The stiffness apparent in Gaviria's movements suggested that the
red parka he was wearing was packed with bullet-resistant plastic.
   Colombian law prohibits the publication of public opinion polls
during the last month of the campaign. But recent private polls
have shown Gaviria leading his nearest rival by at least 30
percentage points.
   Two other leading candidates, Alvaro Gomez of the independent
National Salvation Movement and Rodrigo Lloreda of the Conservative
Party, also made appearances Sunday at smaller political gatherings
in Bogota.
   Both candidates have said they were willing to end the
government's policy of extraditing drug suspects in exchange for
traffickers' pledge to end their campaign of terrorist attacks.
   Another candidate, Antonio Navarro, was not making appearances
on Sunday. Navarro, who became the candidate for the leftist M19
movement after last month's assassination of Pizarro, said he has
also received death threats.
   Candidates will continue campaigning this week on radio and
television stations. The government donated time on state-owned
television stations for candidates' advertising and speeches so
they could cut down on risky personal appearances.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0073 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 2330EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-PrisonShooting     05-20 0129</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Prison Shooting,0133</SECOND>
<HEAD>2 Prisoners Shot, Killed By Guards at Stateville Correctional
Center</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JOLIET, Ill. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two prisoners were shot and killed by prison
guards quelling a gang fight Sunday night at a state prison,
authorities said.
   Three other inmates were injured by either prisoners or guards
during the 45-minute brawl involving about 10 inmates at Stateville
Correctional Center, said Nic Howell, corrections spokesman.
   The prison was locked down to prevent further violence, he said.
   ``My understanding is the staff shot the inmates as they were
attempting to do harm to other inmates,'' Howell said.
   One of the injured inmates was shot and one was stabbed, said a
worker at Silver Cross Hospital who refused to give her name. No
information was immediately available on the third
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0074 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 2349EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-SchoolDeath 2ndLd-Writethru a0748 05-20 0332</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-School Death, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0748,0337</SECOND>
<HEAD>Assistant Principal Found De,ad in Burned Building</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: New throughout with science teacher arrested, other details.
No pickup. </NOTE>
<BYLINE>By TERESA M. WALKER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CENTERVILLE, Tenn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A high school assistant principal was
shot to death and left in a burning school building Sunday, and a
science teacher was arrested, authorities said.
   Police identified the man arrested as Donald Givens. Other
teachers who gathered outside Hickman County High School the day a
baccalaureate ceremony was scheduled identified Givens as a science
teacher.
   Givens was being held at the county jail in the death of Ron
Wallace, 40, an assistant principal and athletic director at the
school 40 miles southwest of Nashville.
   Wallace, whose body was found in a hallway outside a biology
laboratory, had been shot twice, said police Officer Howard Choate.
The fire appeared to be intentionally set, investigators said.
   ``The only thing we can say is that an arrest has been made, and
that he will be charged with murder, and other charges may
result,'' said Sheriff Frank Atkinson.
   Firefighters found Wallace's body about 9 a.m. CDT Sunday after
a fire was reported at the school, Tennessee Bureau of
Investigation Agent Bill Holt said.
   Hickman County School Superintendent Wayne Qualls said Wallace
had gone to the school ``to straighten things up'' for a
baccalaureate service scheduled for Sunday afternoon. The ceremony
was cancelled, and school officials were considering whether to
postpone graduation ceremonies set for Friday.
   Wallace's daughter was among those to graduate.
   Fire Chief Kenneth Thompson confirmed that the fire appeared to
be arson.
   ``An accelerant was used. We don't know what it was yet,''
Thompson said. He said the fire was started in three different
sections of the school. He said the damage was confined to the
library, the English teacher's library and said the curtain on the
auditorium stage had been set on fire.
   The fire didn't cause structural damage, Thompson said. Damage
was estimated at $150,000.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0075 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 1652EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-EasternEurope-Bank     05-20 0513</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Eastern Europe-Bank,0529</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dutch, Belgians Threaten to Block Signing of Bank Treaty</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Netherlands and Belgium have threatened to
contest the choice of a Frenchman as head of a new development bank
for Eastern Europe and the choice of London as its headquarters.
   The 42 members of the $12 billion European Bank for
Reconstruction and Development voted late Saturday to make Jacques
Attali the institution's first president with London as its
headquarters. Attali won over a Dutch rival.
   The treaty establishing the bank, which will finance Eastern
Europe's transition to a market-oriented economy, is to be signed
in Paris May 29.
   ''As far as we're concerned, there was no vote. It was simply an
opinion poll,'' said Cees Maas, a senior Dutch Treasury official
and head of the Dutch delegation.
   Dutch delegates said they intend to review their position prior
to the treaty signing.
   There were 32 votes among the 42 founding members in favor of
Attali, top aide to President Francois Mitterrand and credited with
conceiving the idea of the bank. His Dutch rival for the chief
executive's job, Onno Ruding, received eight. Two of the bank's
members, the European Commission and the European Investment Bank,
abstained.
   London received 23 votes as the choice for the bank's
headquarters, while Amsterdam and Copenhagen gathered five each.
Other cities in the running to host the institution were Berlin,
Brussels, Dublin, Ljubljana, Madrid, Prague and Vienna.
   It was not immediately clear whether a decision by the Dutch and
Belgians not to sign the treaty would prevent the bank from coming
to life, but officials said privately that such a move certainly
would delay the proceedings.
   The Dutch, backed by six other small Western European nations,
have led a diplomatic offensive against the choices of Attali and
London. They claim the selection was a ``precooked'' decision
cobbled together by the seven leading industrialized countries in
Washington earlier this month.
   ``The G-7 decision offended many people,'' commented one
European official, noting that many of the smaller countries in the
European Community felt they were being left out of the
decision-making process.
   The 12 EC nations hold a controlling 51 percent interest in the
bank. The United States is the bank's biggest single shareholder
with a 10 percent stake. Eastern European countries will hold 13.5
percent.
   The G-7 agreement on Attali and London came after France and
Britain settled a long-running dispute over their respective
rankings inside the International Monetary Fund. That arrangement
gives France equal ranking with Britain.
   Observers at the time said the deal was a trade-off, with
Britain agreeing to the IMF reclassification if France would
support London as the site of the development bank.
   The Dutch made a last-minute proposal on Friday to withdraw
their support for Ruding, a former Dutch finance minister, if the
other EC countries would agree to locate the bank in Amsterdam.
   Under the bank's statutes, two-thirds of the 42 founding members
must ratify the treaty before the bank can start lending to
countries in Eastern Europe. The ratification process must be
completed by next spring.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0076 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 1656EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f BC-Marriot-Sizzler     05-20 0146</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Marriot-Sizzler,0154</SECOND>
<HEAD>Marriot Says Its Considering Restaurant Sale but not Negotiating
with Sizzler</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Marriott Corp. said it still is considering
proposals to sell its family restaurant business but is not
negotiating a sale with Sizzler Restaurants International Inc.
   Marriott said in a statement Saturday that numerous parties,
including Sizzler, have expressed interest in the restaurants and
that it is evaluating their proposals.
   But the company said it was not in negotiations with Sizzler,
``contrary to public statements made by Sizzler.''
   ``No decision to negotiate with any single party has been
made,'' the statement said.
   Marriott officials announced in December their intention to
withdraw from the family restaurant business as part of a corporate
restructuring aimed at focusing the company's assets.
   Based in Washington, D.C., Marriott currently operates over 400
restaurants including those under the names of Bob's Big Boy and
Howard Johnson's.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0077 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 1720EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-WPPSSBonds     05-20 0329</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-WPPSS Bonds,0343</SECOND>
<HEAD>Washington Public Power Supply System Announces New Bond Refunding
Sale</HEAD>
<DATELINE>RICHLAND, Wash. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Washington Public Power Supply System
has announced it will offer $600 million in refunding bonds for
sale the week of June 4.
   The sale announced Friday would be the fourth in the effort by
WPPSS and the federal Bonneville Power Administration to refinance
about $2.8 billion in bonds sold a decade ago to finance
construction of three nuclear power plants. The outstanding
high-interest bonds carry interest rates upwards of 9 percent.
   About $1.6 billion in debt for WPPSS plants Nos. 1, 2 and 3 has
been refinanced through issuance of new bonds carrying interest
rates of from 6\ percent to 7} percent.
   WPPSS spokesman John Britton said Friday there will be at least
one and possibly two more sales after June. He said all sales of
refinancing bonds are to be completed this year.
   It has been estimated that the refinancing effort will save the
Northwest region, which is paying for the WPPSS plants through BPA
electricity rates, about $1 billion.
   Preston Michie, assistant general counsel with Bonneville, said
it was hoped the bonds sold in June would be at about the range of
interest rates received in the previous three sales.
   Previous sales were in October and December 1989 and in March of
this year.
   Senior manager for the June sale is First Boston Corp.
   The supply system, headquartered in Richland, attempted to build
five nuclear power plants in the 1970s.
   Of those, one plant, No. 2 at the Hanford nuclear reservation,
is operating after starting up in late 1984.
   Two others, Nos. 1 and 3, are mothballed because of construction
delays.
   WPPSS terminated the other two plants, Nos. 4 and 5, in 1982,
and defaulted on $2.25 billion in bonds sold for their construction.
   Plants 1, 2 and 3 are being paid for through BPA rates. The
Bonneville umbrella was never extended to plants Nos. 4 and 5.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900520-0078 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-90 1831EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f BC-GasPrices     05-20 0121</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Gas Prices,0126</SECOND>
<HEAD>National Average Up 2.4 Cents a Gallon</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The average price of a gallon of gasoline at
the nation's pumps rose 2.4 cents in the past two weeks, a survey
showed.
   The price was 116.05 cents a gallon in the Lundberg Survey for
the period ended May 18, up 2.4 cents from the average in the
previous survey May 4, industry analyst Trilby Lundberg said Sunday.
   The average includes regular unleaded, premium unleaded and
regular leaded gasoline and all taxes. Lundberg surveys 13,000
stations nationwide.
   Self-serve prices per gallon were: regular unleaded 104.47
cents; premium unleaded 121.65 cents; regular leaded 103.91 cents.
Full-serve prices were: regular unleaded 130.98; premium unleaded
144.51; regular leaded 128.93.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
</Collection>
