<Collection>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0001 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 2331EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-PolarBearFatal     12-09 0237</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Polar Bear Fatal,0276</SECOND>
<HEAD>Man Attacked and Killed by Polar Bear in Eskimo Village</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN ENDERS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ANCHORAGE, Alaska (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A polar bear attacked and killed a man
as he walked with his girlfriend through a tiny Eskimo village on
the Arctic Coast, officials said.
   Officials later tracked down the bear and destroyed it, said
U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service spokesman Bruce Batten. He said
officials were speculating that the bear attacked the man because
it was hungry, Batten said.
   An autopsy on the victim, 28-year-old Carl Stalker, was to be
held in Fairbanks. Federal wildlife officials planned to examine
the bear's remains for possible clues to the attack.
   Stalker was killed early Saturday in Point Lay, a village of
about 160 residents some 200 miles southwest of Barrow and 700
miles northwest of Anchorage. His girlfriend, who has not been
publicly identified, was not injured.
   Such polar bear attacks are rare, Batten said.
   ``We're extremely interested in finding out what we can find out
about this particular bear,'' he said.
   Polar bears migrate from east to west at this time of year, and
during the winter months their principal source of food is seal
meat, said Batten. Unlike brown and black bears in southern
latitudes, male polar bears do not hibernate and spend most of the
winter hunting for food.
   ``They tend to be rather curious and will often be attracted by
motion or activity,'' said Batten. He said some polar bears have
been attracted by smell of garbage at dumps and can create a
nuisance in villages and larger towns.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0002 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 2341EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a BC-LOT--SaturdayLotterie     12-09 0824</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-LOT--Saturday Lotteries,1036</SECOND>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<HEAD>ARIZONA</HEAD>
<HEAD>Pick</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PHOENIX (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers in Saturday night's drawing
of the Arizona Lottery's Pick game were: 1, 6, 28, 32, 36 and 42,
with a bonus number of 30.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>CALIFORNIA</HEAD>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SACRAMENTO, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers picked
Saturday night for the California Lottery's twice-weekly ``Lotto
6-53'' game: 41, 25, 52, 1, 33, 38, and the bonus number, 22.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>CONNECTICUT</HEAD>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEWINGTON, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning combination picked Saturday
in the Connecticut State Lottery's ``Daily Lottery'' drawing was:
   1-3-3
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Play 4</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEWINGTON, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning combination picked Saturday
in the Connecticut State Lottery's ``Play 4'' drawing was:
   4-2-1-7.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>DELAWARE</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DOVER, Del. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   These Delaware lotteries were drawn Saturday
night:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   1-9-9
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Play Four</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   7-3-5-8
</TEXT>
<HEAD>DISTRICT OF COLUMBIA</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The following results were drawn Saturday in
the District of Columbia Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lucky Numbers Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   1-8-2
</TEXT>
<HEAD>D.C. Four Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   6-5-9-5
</TEXT>
<HEAD>D.C. Daily Double Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   33, 42
</TEXT>
<HEAD>D.C. Quick Cash Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   28-26-30-24-18-32
</TEXT>
<HEAD>FLORIDA</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected Saturday in
the Florida Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Cash 3</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   2-5-8
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   01-24-25-45-37-20
</TEXT>
<HEAD>ILLINOIS</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SPRINGFIELD, Ill. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the Illinois State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   0-0-4
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick Four</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   9-4-7-2
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   03 06-20-24-30-52
</TEXT>
<HEAD>INDIANA</HEAD>
<DATELINE>INDIANAPOLIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the Hoosier Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto Cash</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   12-24-37-39-41-44
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Three</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   4-7-7
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Four</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   5-5-4-9
</TEXT>
<HEAD>IOWA</HEAD>
<HEAD>Iowa Lotto</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DES MOINES, Iowa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers drawn Saturday in
``Iowa Lotto'' are:
   1-2-3-5-30-38.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto America</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DES MOINES, Iowa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers drawn Saturday night
in ``Lotto America'' are:
   7-10-14-31-35-37
</TEXT>
<HEAD>KANSAS</HEAD>
<HEAD>Kan. Cash Lotto</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOPEKA, Kan. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers in the Kansas Cash Lotto
drawing Saturday night with an estimated jackpot of $75,000:
   2-13-19-20-27-28
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Kan. Keno</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOPEKA, Kan. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers in the Kansas Keno
drawing Saturday night with a jackpot of $50,000:
   1-2-6-9-19-23-25-29-30-33-35-42-45-46-49-50-52-53-58-59
</TEXT>
<HEAD>KENTUCKY</HEAD>
<HEAD>Kentucky Lottery</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOUISVILLE, Ky. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are Saturday's winning numbers
selected by the Kentucky Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Kentucky Cash:
   9-7-7
   </HEAD>
<HEAD>Lotto:
   7-12-16-26-34-37
   </HEAD>
<HEAD>MASSACHUSETTS</HEAD>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BRAINTREE, Mass. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers drawn Saturday night
in the ``Massachusetts Daily Lottery'' were:
   8-0-2-3
</TEXT>
<HEAD>MICHIGAN</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DETROIT (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected Saturday in
the Michigan State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   7-6-4
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily-4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   3-2-1-1
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto 47</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   6-18-36-41-43-44)
</TEXT>
<HEAD>MINNESOTA</HEAD>
<HEAD>Daily 3</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MINNEAPOLIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers drawn Saturday night in
Minnesota's Daily 3 lottery game are:
   9-8-7
</TEXT>
<HEAD>MISSOURI</HEAD>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ST. LOUIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers in Missouri's Lotto drawing
Saturday night:
   3-5-30-31-42-48
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 3</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ST. LOUIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers in Saturday's Missouri
Lottery Daily Pick 3 game:
   8-7-2
</TEXT>
<HEAD>NEW JERSEY</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TRENTON, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday night in the New Jersey State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 3</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   5-1-4
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   5-3-1-7
</TEXT>
<HEAD>NEW YORK</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ALBANY, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the New York State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Number</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   5-9-6
</TEXT>
<HEAD>WinFour</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   2-9-9-6
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 10</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ALBANY, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the New York State Lottery's Pick 10 game:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 10</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   1, 2, 4, 6, 10, 11, 12, 18, 19, 34, 42, 44, 50, 53, 59, 65, 66,
75, 77, 80.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ALBANY, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the New York State Lottery's Lotto game:
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   3, 15, 21, 27, 40, 53. The supplemental number was 46.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>NORTHERN NEW ENGLAND</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CONCORD, N.H. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the daily New Hampshire, Vermont and Maine lotteries:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 3</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   1-6-7
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   1-7-4-6
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Tri-State Megabucks</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CONCORD, N.H. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers in the
``Tri-State Megabucks'' game for New Hampshire, Vermont and Maine:
   2-5-6-8-14-22
</TEXT>
<HEAD>OHIO</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CLEVELAND (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected Saturday
night in the Ohio Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Super Lotto</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   1-14-18-33-36-50
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Kicker</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   3-2-8-5-4-2
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 3 Numbers</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   7-5-6
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 4 Numbers</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   7-4-9-9
</TEXT>
<HEAD>OREGON</HEAD>
<HEAD>Daily 4</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PORTLAND, Ore. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are Saturday's winning numbers in the
``Oregon Daily 4'' lottery game:
   8-6-4-1
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Megabucks</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PORTLAND, Ore. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are Saturday's winning numbers in the
``Oregon Megabucks'' lottery game:
   2-15-19-32-36-41
</TEXT>
<HEAD>PENNSYLVANIA</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HARRISBURG (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected Saturday
in the Pennsylvania State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Number</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   3-9-3
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Big 4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   2-3-3-8
</TEXT>
<HEAD>RHODE ISLAND</HEAD>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CRANSTON, R.I. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers in the Rhode Island
daily lottery drawing for Saturday were:
   2-2-5-7
</TEXT>
<HEAD>VIRGINIA</HEAD>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<DATELINE>RICHMOND (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   These numbers were drawn Saturday in the
Virginia Lottery's Lotto game:
   2-6-18-25-41-43
</TEXT>
<HEAD>WASHINGTON</HEAD>
<DATELINE>OLYMPIA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are winning numbers selected Saturday in the
Washington State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   3-0-7
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   5-14-30-32-41-44
</TEXT>
<HEAD>WEST VIRGINIA</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CHARLESTON, W.Va. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the West Virginia State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily 3</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   6-8-2
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily 4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   0-8-9-9
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0003 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 2342EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-VanGoghDispute     12-09 0364</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Van Gogh Dispute,0443</SECOND>
<HEAD>Museum Pronounces van Gogh Portrait the Real Thing</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HARTFORD, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Museum officials locked in a battle with
an art critic over the authenticity of a purported self-portrait by
van Gogh say they have new proof, contained in an X-ray of the
painting.
   The X-ray, taken at Hartford's Mount Sinai Hospital, shows the
outlines of a sketch beneath the painting, and officials at
Wadsworth Atheneum say the sketch was clearly done by van Gogh in
the mid-1880s.
   ``With these scientific results, we now have what I believe is
`the smoking pistol' - positive proof that this must be a work by
Vincent van Gogh,'' said museum Director Patrick McCaughey.
   The X-ray and the picture will be exhibited side-by-side on
Tuesday at the museum.
   The authenticity of the 16-by-13-inch painting has been
challenged repeatedly since it was donated to the museum in 1954 by
architect Philip Goodwin.
   Museum officials have maintained it is one of a series of gaunt,
haunting self-portraits van Gogh painted in 1886 through 1888.
   Most recently, Swiss art dealer and critic Walter Feilchenfeldt
insisted the work is a forgery or, more likely, a van Gogh portrait
painted in tribute by another artist. He said the painting ``is not
van Gogh's style.''
   The painting is to be included in an international exhibition
next year.
   ``The international exhibition is what really propelled us into
saying, `Let's sort this painting out once and for all,'''
McCaughey said. ``Let's see if it is worth $17 million or $1.70 -
$1.70 being the value of the frame.''
   The museum said the X-ray disclosed a sketch of a fleshy woman
in a bonnet. The woman looks much like the figures in van Gogh's
series of pictures of Dutch peasants, such as ``The Potato
Eaters,'' McCaughey said.
   ``When the X-ray was turned upside down, there indeed was Mrs.
Potato Eater, or Miss Potato Eater, seated at the pail peeling her
spuds,'' he said.
   Impoverished artists like van Gogh painted over earlier works or
painted on both sides of a canvas to save money.
   McCaughey said it is extremely unlikely a forger would have gone
to the trouble of forging an additional van Gogh underneath the
portrait.
   Feilchenfeldt said of the findings, ``This is, of course,
exciting news, about the X-ray, which I have not seen. But I am
more inclined to believe that these images found underneath could
also be forgeries.''
   The critic has also challenged the authenticity of van Gogh
self-portraits owned by the Metropolitan Museum of Art in New York
and Norway's National Gallery in Oslo.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0004 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 2342EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Rhodes-List     12-09 0384</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Rhodes-List,0403</SECOND>
<HEAD>List of 1991 Rhodes Scholars</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Rhodes Scholars</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the 32 students chosen as American
Rhodes scholars for 1991, listed by district where the application
was filed. The city provided by the candidate may be a hometown or
college town. Applicants may apply either in their home state or
the state where their college is located.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>DISTRICT ONE, NEW ENGLAND</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Jeffrey A. Dolven, New Haven, Conn., Yale University.
   Michael Callahan, Amherst, Mass., Harvard University.
   Kenji Yoshino, Cambridge, Mass., Harvard University.
   David Coleman, North Bennington, Vt., Yale University.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>DISTRICT TWO, MIDDLE ATLANTIC</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Leonard P. Stark, Chesterfield, Mo., University of Delaware.
   Lawrence J. Berger, Ithaca, N.Y., Yale University.
   Carl D. Marci, Allentown, Pa., Columbia University.
   Theresa E. Simmonds, Philadelphia, University of Pennsylvania.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>DISTRICT THREE, SOUTHERN</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Marcus A. Christian, Clearwater, Fla., Williams College.
   Robert J. Esther, St. Louis, Wake Forest University.
   Peter Blair Henry, Wilmette, Ill. University of North Carolina.
   Brad Ronnell Braxton, Virginia Beach, Va., University of
Virginia.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>DISTRICT FOUR, GREAT LAKES</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Sabina Alkire, Champaign, Ill., University of Illinois.
   Jason R. Zimba, Dearborn Heights, Mich., Williams College.
   Jesse Malkin, Berkeley, Calif., Oberlin College.
   Nathaniel N. Urban, Dublin, Ohio, University of Pittsburgh.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>DISTRICT FIVE, MIDDLE WEST</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Kristy L. Parker, Valley Center, Kan., Kansas State University.
   Darcy D. Prather, Hazelwood, Mo., Massachusetts Institute of
Technology.
   Edward S. Pallesen, Lincoln, Neb., Harvard University.
   Todd E. Peterson, Pierre, S.D., Gustavus Adolphus College.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>DISTRICT SIX, GULF</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Micul Thompson, Jackson, Miss., US Air Force Academy.
   Darreld ``Deacon'' Turner, Fairland, Okla., Harvard University.
   Christopher B. Howard, Plano, Texas, U.S. Air Force Academy.
   Gregory Pyung Won Pak, Dallas, Yale University.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>DISTRICT SEVEN, SOUTHWESTERN</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Goodwin Liu, Sacramento, Calif., Stanford University.
   Jeffrey Shesol, Aurora, Colo., Brown University.
   Patricia Lopes, Kailua, Hawaii, Washington and Lee University.
   Jonathan E. Skinner, Santa Fe, N.M., St. John's College, Santa
Fe and also St. John's College, Annapolis.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>DISTRICT EIGHT, NORTHWESTERN</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Scott Lamont Merriner, Anchorage, Alaska, Harvard University.
   Stephen P. Brown, Laka Oswego, Ore., Dartmouth College.
   Wesley D. Sand, Roseburg, Ore., Cornell University and also
Oregon State University.
   Janice Anne Hudgings, Yellowstone National Park, Wyo.,
Swarthmore College.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0005 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 2348EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Israel-NoTourists Bjt   12-09 0516</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Israel-No Tourists, Bjt,0633</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bethlehem 1990: Nothing But Room At The Inn</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By EILEEN ALT POWELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BETHLEHEM, Occupied West Bank (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In the season of Christmas
pilgrimages by Christians from around the world, the town where
Jesus was born has nothing but room at its inns.
   Mayor Elias Freij looks out the window of his office onto the
deserted square at the Church of the Nativity.
   ``Tourists? What tourists?'' he asks rhetorically, sweeping an
arm toward the emptiness. ``This is the worst situation in my
memory.''
   ``With the drums of war beating in the Saudi desert and the
large armada assembling in the (Persian) gulf, people are simply
too scared to come here,'' says Freij, a Greek Orthodox Palestinian
who has been mayor for 18 years.
   He said ``the last straw'' was Israel's decision in October to
distribute gas masks in case of an Iraqi attack. ``Would you go on
holiday to a country where you need a gas mask?'' Freij asked.
   Israel has suffered an overall loss in tourism because of the
gulf crisis. Bethlehem and Arab east Jerusalem are especially
affected because the crisis accompanies what usually is their
busiest season.
   The government had predicted a record year in tourism,
surpassing the previous high of 1.5 million visitors in 1987.
Instead, tourist arrivals have declined by half since Iraq seized
Kuwait on Aug. 2, said Tourism Ministry spokesman Yossi Shoval. He
said the 1990 total would be 1.3 million at best.
   Shoval said the ministry still was trying to woo Jewish
religious groups and Christians pilgrims, but that Israel had
canceled its overseas television advertising ``until the gulf
situation improves.''
   ``There will be Christians here for Christmas,'' he said. ``The
question is how many.''
   On a recent morning in Bethlehem, a single tour bus was parked
in Manger Square. Its seven Italian passengers were alone in the
underground grotto of the Church of the Nativity, kneeling at the
silver star that marks the site of Christ's birth.
   In normal times, pilgrims would be elbow-to-elbow in the church
and the tiny grotto.
   ``Things are so bad that I am not earning enough to feed me and
my wife,'' said Issa el-Boyaji, a man in his 70s who usually makes
his living shining the shoes of pilgrims outside the church.
   He has set aside his brass-inlaid shoeshine box and directs
drivers into parking places around Manger Square, hoping they will
give him small change for his efforts.
   Traditional religious ceremonies are scheduled for the holidays.
They will begin on Christmas Eve with the ceremonial arrival of the
Roman Catholic patriarch of Jerusalem and end with Masses and
Anglican chorale services.
   For the fourth year, Bethlehem will forgo street decorations and
holiday receptions in sympathy with the Palestinian uprising in the
West Bank and Gaza Strip, Freij said.
   The revolt against Israeli occupation, which began in December
1987, has taken the lives of more than 770 Palestinians and 53
Israelis.
   ``With the confrontations, with the desperation, there is
nothing to celebrate,'' the mayor said.
   The drop in tourism has taken its toll on the economy of
Bethlehem, a town of 40,000 people.
   Freij says only one of the six hotels is operating and nearly
all the 80 restaurants are closed. Scores of craftsmen have been
laid off at the 400 workshops that produce olive wood carvings and
mother-of-pearl jewelry.
   Tax collections have fallen off so much, Freij said, that
municipal workers could not be paid in November.
   Fahmi Nashashibi, secretary of the Arab Hotels Association in
Jerusalem and Bethlehem, said he had closed two of his three hotels
for pilgrims in east Jerusalem because more than half the Christmas
bookings were canceled.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0006 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 0051EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-NoriegaTapes     12-09 0427</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Noriega Tapes,0493</SECOND>
<HEAD>Former Panamanian Diplomat Reportedly Focus of Tapes Probe</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The FBI investigation into who leaked tapes of
Manuel Noriega's prison phone calls focuses on a political opponent
who might testify against the deposed Panamanian dictator,
newspapers reported.
   The FBI believes the source of the leak appears to be Jose
Blandon, once an intelligence officer in Panama for Noriega and the
country's former consul general in New York, The Miami Herald and
The Washington Post reported, quoting unidentified sources.
   Blandon denied leaking the government tapes. In an interview
published Sunday in The Post, Blandon said someone in the U.S.
government who wants to sabotage the Noriega trial must have been
responsible.
   ``Somebody in the government was leaking them,'' Blandon said.
Drug enforcement agents were present whenever he had access to the
tapes, and he was allowed to make only written notes, Blandon said.
   Blandon also said he provided prosecutor Patrick Sullivan with a
written summary of the tapes at Sullivan's request. That summary
referred to several calls between Noriega and his lead defense
attorney, Frank Rubino, Blandon said.
   ``I mentioned everything,'' Blandon said, including a
conversation in which Noriega and Rubino discussed how to deal with
Luis del Cid, a former Noriega aide who has pleaded guilty in the
case and promised to testify against his former boss.
   The FBI is trying to determine who gave the tapes to Cable News
Network, which aired some of Noriega's conversations from prison
over the past month. The broadcasts were halted briefly while a
federal judge decided whether Noriega's right to a fair trial would
be jeopardized. After reviewing the tapes, the judge decided to let
CNN broadcast them.
   A spokesman for the U.S. attorney's office in Miami said
prosecutors have not listened to any of the tapes, and would
neither confirm nor deny that prosecutors received Blandon's
summary of the tapes he reviewed.
   FBI agents searched Blandon's home in Houston on Thursday night
looking for telephone logs and documents, both newspapers reported.
   Unidentified sources said Blandon played portions of the tapes
for two officials of the Panamanian government in a Miami hotel
room in March, the Herald said Saturday.
   If the FBI can prove Blandon leaked the tapes, or if the court
determines that prosecutors have been tainted by exposure to
privileged conversations between Noriega and his attorneys, the
government's efforts to try Noriega on drug charges could be
hampered.
   Blandon has been considered a key government witness since he
testified before a Senate committee in 1988 that Noriega protected
U.S.-bound cocaine shipments.
   Blandon's role in reviewing the tapes was revealed after the
government confirmed publicly for the first time in court documents
Friday that DEA agents had studied Noriega's phone calls.
   Noriega is awaiting trial on charges of taking $4.6 million in
payoffs to protect the cocaine trade passing through Panama from
Colombia to the United States.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0007 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 0114EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-FreewayWrecks     12-09 0229</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Freeway Wrecks,0263</SECOND>
<HEAD>Driver Who Thought He Could Drive Through Cars Sets Off Collisions</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HAYWARD, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A man who claimed God told him he could
drive through cars with his flatbed truck hit 18 vehicles and
injured about 12 people Saturday, authorities said.
   A 2- to 3-mile section of the Nimitz Freeway between Hayward and
San Leandro was littered with dented vehicles before Emmet Wheat,
47, hit the center divider with his truck, police said.
   Most seriously injured was 8-year-old Francesca Camus of
Hayward, who was listed in critical condition at Childrens Hospital
in Oakland, authorities said. Camus was ejected from her mother's
van when it was struck by the truck, highway patrol officials said.
   The other injuries were minor, officials said. The accidents
closed a half-mile section of the highway east of San Francisco Bay
for about two hours.
   Wheat, owner of Commercial Auto Wreckers in San Leandro, was
booked for investigation of felony hit-run driving and driving
under th influence of alcohol. He was not injured.
   His wife, Karen, said she spoke to her husband over the truck's
radio just after he rammed into the center divider.
   ``He said the Lord had spoken to him and that the Lord told him
he could drive though the cars,'' she said.
   ``He's been talking about this kind of stuff a lot lately,'' she
said. ``I didn't know he was this bad. I thought he wanted
attention.''
   Highway patrol officers said they found rambling religious
messages signed ``Emmet and the Lord'' on the truck.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0008 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 0121EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-TutuVisit     12-09 0239</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Tutu Visit,0257</SECOND>
<HEAD>Archbishop Tutu Urges Iraq, U.S. to Talk, Not Fight</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LEN IWANSKI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HELENA, Mont. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The United States and Iraq should avert war
in the Persian Gulf by talking out their differences, South African
Archbishop Desmond Tutu said Saturday.
   ``People must make it more and more clear that we are
peacemongers, because peace is so sensible. It's so much more
sensible than war,'' said the Anglican prelate, who won the 1984
Nobel Peace Prize for his opposition to South African apartheid.
   At a news conference, Tutu also urged the United States to
continue its economic sanctions against South Africa ``until the
process of dismantling apartheid is irreversible.''
   Apartheid is South Africa's official police of racial
segregation and discrimination against non-whites.
   Although South Africa's President F.W. de Klerk deserves credit
for some reform, ``the pillars of apartheid still stand firmly in
place,'' Tutu said.
   Tutu came to this ity of 24,000 people to help raise
scholarship money for South African students abroad and for
American Indian students in Montana.
   Tutu heads the 2.6 million-member Anglican Church of Southern
Africa. This was his only scheduled stop in North America while en
route to a convocation in Honduras.
   The visit was arranged by the Montana Logging and Ballet
Company, a Helena-based quartet that mixes music, comedy and satire
to promote political and social causes.
   Tutu wrote liner notes for the group's latest album after
hearing it perform an anti-apartheid song, ``Take the Barriers
Down,'' in 1987.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0009 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 0124EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>d a AM-HorseKicked     12-09 0170</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Horse Kicked,0191</SECOND>
<HEAD>Man Jailed for Kicking Police Horse</HEAD>
<DATELINE>RALEIGH, N.C. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A horse is not always just a horse -
sometimes he's a large police officer.
   That's what a judge said when sentencing a Raleigh man to one
year in prison for assaulting a police officer by kicking Heir
Apparent, a Raleigh police horse.
   ``I can't condone assault on a law officer by kicking his
horse,'' Judge James Fullwood said Friday after sentencing Elijah
Lawrence. ``You created a threat to others as evidenced by you
hauling off and kicking the horse.''
   On Oct. 15, Officer D.A. Brugger was trying to arrest Lawrence
for failing to appear in court when the man kicked the horse twice
in the thigh. The horse reared but wasn't seriously hurt.
   Lawrence was arrested when a police patrol car arrived.
   ``There was no defense,'' said Lawrence's attorney, Tim Blake.
``He kicked it and the officer said, `Don't kick it.' and he kicked
him again.''
   It wasn't immediately known why Lawrence was to appear in court
in the first place or why he allegedly failed to appear.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0010 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 0153EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-King'sDaughter 1st-LdWritethru a0638 12-09 0294</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-King's Daughter, 1st-Ld Writethru, a0638,0326</SECOND>
<HEAD>Yolanda King Snubs Arizona at Last Minute</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with nine grafs to UPDATE that understudy will replace
Ms. King, details on play, moves up background on controversy.
Picks up last graf pvs, `Tucson, Phoenix...'</NOTE>
<DATELINE>TUCSON, Ariz. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Yolanda King, daughter of slain civil
rights leader Martin Luther King Jr., on Saturday canceled her
Arizona appearance in a musical play scheduled for the next day.
   Ms. King, 34, and Attallah Shabazz, the daughter of black
activist Malcolm X, partners in the performing arts group Nucleus,
scheduled the performance months before Arizona voters narrowly
rejected two referendums which would have created paid state
holidays to honor King.
   An understudy from New York would replace Ms. King in ``Stepping
Into Tomorrow,'' scheduled to be performed at the University of
Arizona Sunday afternoon, said Tani Sanchez, a university
spokeswoman.
   The other eight performers would hold a news conference in
Tucson Sunday, Ms. Sanchez said in a statement announcing Ms.
King's withdrawal.
   Ms. King would supply a statement but would not attend the news
conference, she said.
   Ms. King considered canceling in the aftermath of the Nov. 6
vote. Many conventions were canceled and NFL Commissioner Paul
Tagliabue has recommended moving the 1993 Super Bowl out of Arizona
because of the rejection.
   She and Ms. Shabazz said last week that they would go ahead with
the performance in hopes of furthering King's ideals.
   Jahna Cole, Ms. King's Van Nuys, Calif.-based publicist,
declined to say why she pulled out at the last minute.
   Ms. King and Ms. Shabazz wrote and co-direct the musical, which
examines issues such as teen pregnancy, drug abuse, peer pressure
and education.
   Tucson, Phoenix and more than 20 other Arizona cities celebrate
King's Jan. 15 birthday with paid holidays for their municipal
employees. The state honors King on the third Sunday in January
with an unpaid state holiday. Most activists scoff at the unpaid
holiday.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0011 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 0301EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Gulf-Iraq 4thLd-Writethru a0635 12-09 0819</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Iraq, 4th Ld-Writethru, a0635,1038</SECOND>
<HEAD>23 Americans Leave Iraq, More Departures Set For Sunday</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Leads with 4 grafs to DELETE grafs 4 and 5 with references to
second plane, which was empty except for crew when it landed in
Maine; picks up 7th graf pvs, `President Bush ...; SUBS last 3
grafs, `At the...' to UPDATE with 4 grafs to show U.N. vote
postponed. No pickup; Connally plane expected in Houston at 6 a.m.
EST</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto TOK3, BAG1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SLOBODAN LEKIC</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BAGHDAD, Iraq (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Twenty-three Americans headed for home
Sunday after flying out of Baghdad as the first to depart since
Iraq announced it is freeing all foreign captives. One of the 23
shouted jubilantly: ``We're outta here!''
   The group was headed for Houston early Sunday after a brief
stopover in Shannon, Ireland, aboard a Boeing 707 jetliner
chartered by former Treasury Secretary John Connally, according to
airport officials in Shannon. Two British hostages, also on the
plane that left Baghdad on Saturday, got off at Shannon.
   The plane was expected to arrive in Houston early Sunday.
   It was not clear whether the departure of Connally's mission had
been arranged before the Iraqi parliament on Friday approved
President Saddam Hussein's call to free the hostages. The exodus
was expected to get under way in earnest on Sunday.
   President Bush, in Venezuela, welcomed the move to free the
captives, but said Iraq still must get out of Kuwait, which it
overran Aug. 2.
   ``When you don't have Americans there, and if force is required,
that's just one less worry I've got,'' Bush said.
   Iraqi authorities, meanwhile, called on the public Saturday to
``renew their vigilance'' in the face of a possible threat from the
U.S.-led international forces.
   The Interior Ministry had instructed civil defense groups and
provincial officials to prepare for ``any eventuality,'' said the
nightly television news broadcast. Posters warning the population
``not to panic in case of attack'' appeared on walls of buildings
in downtown Baghdad.
   In London, the Observer newspaper reported Sunday that Iraq has
redrawn its border with Kuwait and could withdraw as early as next
month. The Observer, in a story from Washington, said Iraq was
laying claim to an area of the Rumaila oilfield and the islands of
Warba and Bubiyan in the Persian Gulf.
   The report, citing unidentified Arab sources in Washington, said
Iraq has erected a barbed-wire fence around the southern tip of the
oilfield, which extends into northern Kuwait. Iraq has long claimed
the area.
   Iraqi officials said Saturday all the departing detainees still
need exit visas. U.S. officials have asked them to expedite the
processing.
   Americans who had been held at strategic installations as
``human shields'' began arriving in Baghdad Saturday. Many said
they would not feel safe until they were out of Iraq.
   ``I still think of myself as a hostage because I cannot leave
the hotel,'' said Edward Smiley of Los Angeles.
   Smiley, who said he was moved around to six different locations,
described conditions as ``very bad.''
   He said the hostages were forced to sleep in bug-ridden beds and
to eat fish heads for much of the time.
   About 8,000 Westerners had been detained since Iraq's Aug. 2
invasion of Kuwait, including about 600 who were held at stratgic
sites in an effort to deter any U.S. attack. The hostages included
about 900 Americans as well as other Westerners, Eastern Europeans
and Japanese.
   The first group of 17 American hostages was led through passport
control at Baghdad's Saddam Airport by Iraqi officials.
   ``We're outta here!'' shouted a delighted American.
   The airport departure area was littered with broken suitcases,
clothes and other debris left over from a group of at least 200
Vietnamese workers flown to Hanoi earlier in the day.
   A witness who did not want to be named described how Iraqi
customs officials tore through their luggage pulling out food,
carpets and other items.
   The 23 Americans on the flight arranged by Connally also
included members of the U.S. Embassy staff in Kuwait, and three
people who had taken refuge at the ambassador's refuge in Baghdad.
   Connally went to Baghdad on a private mission to obtain the
release of hostages.
   A group of 41 Japanese men whose release was approved before
Sadam's announcemnt also flew to Amman, Jordan, on Saturday aboard
an Iraqi Airways plane. They later left for Tokyo.
   Nur Eldin al-Safi, the head of Iraqi Airways, said the airline
was prepared to fly out all of the hostages within three days if
their travel documents are ready. He said that no foreign carrier
would be allowed to transport them out of Iraq.
   Al-Safi said U.S. officials had chartered one of the airlines'
Boeing 707s to fly to Kuwait Sunday to pick up Americans. The
United States had also chartered a 747 jumbo jet to fly those
Americans and others in Baghdad to Frankfurt, Germany, later
Sunday, he added.
   Meanwhile, the official Iraqi News Agency said Iraq rejected the
dates the United States has suggested for Secretary of State James
A. Baker III's trip to Baghdad for talks with Saddam.
   Iraq proposed Jan. 12 as the date for the Baker trip, the news
agency said. The State Department had suggested he visit on Dec.
20, Dec. 21, Dec. 22 or Jan. 3.
   A Jan. 12 date would come only three days before the deadline
set down in a U.N. resolution demanding an Iraqi withdrawal from
Kuwait. The Security Council measure authorizes use of ``all
necessary means'' to dislodge Iraq after that.
   At the United Nations, the Security Council late Saturday
postponed discussion of a resolution calling for an eventual
international peace conference on the Middle East.
   The council voted 9-4 to adopt a Soviet motion to postpone
consideration of the resolution until Monday. The United States
voted in favor of postponement, while France and China abstained.
   A U.S. veto would outrage Washington's Arab allies in the
anti-Iraq coalition assembled in the Persian Gulf, but Israel will
be equally angered if the resolution passes with a U.S. abstention
or vote in favor.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0012 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 0543EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i BC-Poland-Elections     12-09 0424</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Poland-Elections,0503</SECOND>
<BYLINE>Polls Open in Final Election Vote Between Walesa and Tyminski
^By JOHN DANISZEWSKI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WARSAW, Poland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Poles voted Sunday for their first
popularly elected president, choosing between a national icon, Lech
Walesa, and an emigre businessman who didn't live in Poland until
two months ago.
   Opinion polls showed the Solidarity chief and former shipyard
electrician far ahead of the newcomer, Stanislaw Tyminski.
   But Tyminski's surprise elimination of Prime Minister Tadeusz
Mazowiecki in the first round of voting on Nov. 25 was so
unexpected that few were willing to count him out entirely.
   Tyminski, 42, who owns a Toronto computer and communications
business and leads the fringe Libertarian Party of Canada, began
campaigning in October after 21 years in Toronto and Iquitos, Peru.
   Walesa, 47, voted after leaving Mass in his hometown, Gdansk,
where Auxiliary Bishop Zygmunt Pawlowicz had greeted him as ``our
dear Mr. President.''
   The Roman Catholic church openly endorsed Walesa in the
campaign.
   Polls opened at 6 a.m. and were to close at 8 p.m. (2 p.m. EST)
Reliable projections of results were expected within minutes
afterward based on exit polls conducted throughout the day by state
television and the German polling service Infas.
   Temperatures were around the freezing mark, and snow covered the
ground in the southern part of the country. More than 27 million
Poles are eligible to cast their ballots at 22,000 polling stations
nationwide.
   Spending freely and railing against the economic ``treason'' of
the Mazowiecki government, Tyminski turned the campaign on its head
in the first round of voting.
   But he has been hurt recently as new information surfaced
regarding his links to members of the former Communist Party, his
advocacy of nuclear weapons in a campaign tract and his reported
use of hallucinogenic drugs in the Amazon jungle.
   The president will succeed Gen. Wojciech Jaruzelski, the former
Communist Party chief who imposed martial law on Solidarity nine
year ago this week.
   The new president, who will serve a five-year term, will be in
office while Poland drafts its new constitution next year.
   No date has been set for the swearing-in. If no challenges are
raised to the official results, it could happen by the end of this
week.
   Historically, Poland's presidents were always elected by
parliament.
   Polls last week showed Walesa leading Tyminski by more than a
3-1 margin.
   Out of 13 people interviewed after polls opened in Warsaw, not
one said they voted for Tyminski. However he was believed to have
more support in rural areas.
   The presidency would cap an astonishing personal voyage for
Walesa, who rose from his origins in a poor peasant family to
become a shipyard electrician, then led the Solidarity trade union
movement in the first peaceful revolution to dump a Communist
government.
   Should Walesa win, goes a joke circulating here, Poland would
become a true Communist state - with a worker as president.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0013 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 1015EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a BC-Gulf-Hostages 4thLd-Writethru a0652 12-09 0527</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Gulf-Hostages, 4th Ld - Writethru, a0652-654,0644</SECOND>
<HEAD>Former Texas Gov. Connally Brings Home 21 American Hostages</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS lead to CORRECT that 21 American hostages arrived in
Houston; SUBS 8th graf, `Seven of...', to give background on 22nd
hostage, a Briton who got off flight in Ireland.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto HT1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By WENDY BENJAMINSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HOUSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Twenty-one Americans held hostage by Iraq arrived
in the United States early Sunday to the cheers of nearly 200
relatives and supporters.
   The chartered jet touched down at Ellington Field south of
downtown Houston at 4:40 a.m. CST.
   The crowd, some waving small American flags, applauded and
cheered as the hostages started down the stairway onto the tarmac.
Once off the plane, they were escorted to the nearby U.S. Coast
Guard hangar.
   ``God bless America!'' said former hostage Scott Nelson of Los
Angeles. He said he was held at a munitions plant about 35 miles
south of Baghdad, and was treated well.
   John Remington of Redondo Beach, Calif., who worked for an
American architectural firm in Kuwait, said ``we were treated fine
once you accept the fact that you're being held against your
will.''
   The Iraqi parliament on Friday approved President Saddam
Hussein's call to free all foreign captives. The exodus was
expected to get under way in earnest on Sunday.
   The hostages flew to Houston with John Connally, a former U.S.
treasury secretary and former Texas governor, and Houston oilman
Oscar Wyatt. The two flew to Baghdad last week with $500,000 worth
of medical supplies as a goodwill gesture.
   Seven of the hostages' relatives and three U.S. Embassy
employees were also on board the corporate jet. A 22nd hostage was
also on board when the plane left Iraq, Peter McCleod, a British
subject who got off during a refueling stop in Ireland.
   Connally, who had tears in his eyes as he watched the former
hostages greet their relatives, said that he and Wyatt did not tell
State Department officials about their planned trip to Baghdad, nor
did they ask for their assistance in securing the hostages release.
   ``We knew they would try to discourage us,'' Connally said. ``We
didn't want to be discouraged.'' Connally noted that State
Department officials had discouraged hostages relatives from
traveling to Baghdad.
   Wyatt is chairman of Coastal Corp., which provided the jet and
paid for the medical supplies. The oil company also arranged
Houston hotel rooms for the hostages' families and will provide
flights home for the entire group, said Coastal spokesman Jim
Bailey.
   None of the hostages works for Coastal, Bailey said.
   Wyatt and Connally secured the captives' release before Saddam
announced that all foreigners would be released.
   Connally said he and Wyatt advised Saddam that a release of
hostages at Christmastime would be a show of compassion. Connally
said Saddam replied, ``you will not go home with an empty plane.''
   But filling the plane became difficult because of bureaucratic
delays in obtaining exit visas. Connally said that the hostages
that accompanied him made it on this flight only because they were
able to get clearance first.
   Wyatt said that the Iraqi government had donated $30,000 worth
of fuel to fly the plane home because Wyatt was forbidden by U.S.
economic sanctions to buy fuel directly from the Iraqis.
   About 8,000 Westerners had been detained since Iraq's Aug. 2
invasion of Kuwait, including about 600 who were held at strategic
sites in an effort to deter any U.S. attack. The hostages included
about 900 Americans as well as other Westerners, Eastern Europeans
and Japanese.
   Former hostage Bill Rodebush of McAlester, Okla., said he was
``treated as good as they could'' but added he was moved six times
during his captivity. He refused to say where he was held ``till
all my friends get out.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0014 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 1115EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--CorsicaBomb     12-09 0179</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Corsica Bomb,0170</SECOND>
<HEAD>Nationalist Group Targets Italian Villas on French Island</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BASTIA, Corsica (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Small gas bombs blew apart six vacation
villas under construction, and a nationalist terrorist group
claimed responsibility, police said Sunday.
   The villas, in a tourist complex in Poggio-Mezanna near this
northern Corsican capital, were destroyed Saturday night in
separate blasts, along with two cars bearing Italian license
plates, police said.
   No one was injured in the explosions at the deserted site, where
an Italian-Corsican company is building vacation homes.
   Nationalist inscriptions written in the Corsican language were
found painted on battered walls along with the letter ``R'' - the
signature of the terrorist group Resistenza, which has claimed
responsibility for numerous attacks since it first appeared in
September.
   Resistenza is an offshoot of the Corsican National Liberation
Front (FLNC), which has long targeted vacation centers in its fight
for independence for this French Mediterranean island.
   Eleven villas were destroyed on Friday in a similar incident
near Calvi, also in northern Corsica.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0015 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 1116EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Scarlett'sBonnet     12-09 0199</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Scarlett's Bonnet,0225</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bonnet From `Gone With The Wind' To Be Auctioned</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The black bonnet worn by Vivien Leigh as the
tempestuous Scarlett O'Hara in ``Gone With The Wind'' will be
auctioned this week, the auction house said Sunday.
   The actress wore the Christian Dior creation in the box office
blockbuster and for publicity stills with co-star Clark Gable, who
played Rhett Butler.
   When filming finished, Miss Leigh gave the hat to London theater
critic Alan Dent, her close friend and biographer, a spokesman for
Phillips auctioneers said.
   When Dent died in 1978, Scarlett's bonnet passed to an elderly
couple in Cumbria county, northern England, who had given Dent a
home after he retired.
   Phillips will auction it on Friday in Chester, 180 miles
northwest of London, with some of Dent's letters and theater
memorabilia, said the spokesman.
   John Hayes, a friend of the owners, said they wanted the hat
``to go to someone who will appreciate it.''
   ``It is a unique piece of cinema history and I suppose it would
be a good idea if it ended up in a museum devoted to the art.''
   Phillips' specialists are reluctant to specify the value of the
hat. ``Who knows what its value may be to a collector or museum,''
said Jeremy Lamond, of the collectors' department.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0016 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 1130EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Sinatra's75th     12-09 0722</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Sinatra's 75th,0928</SECOND>
<HEAD>Francis Albert Sinatra, Saloon Singer to American Legend, Turns 75</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JEFF WILSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Frank Sinatra, one-time idol of bobby-soxers
who became a show business legend, evokes nostalgia these days, but
as he turns 75, he's still doing it his way.
   Known as the Chairman of the Board, Ol' Blue Eyes, the Voice,
just plain Frank or simply Sinatra, the crooner is belting out
standards for still another generation of pop music fans.
   On Tuesday, the eve of Francis Albert Sinatra's 75th birthday
celebration, the entertainer returns to an arena near his New
Jersey hometown of Hoboken to begin a yearlong world tour designed
to fulfill a lifetime yearning - performances in the Soviet Union
and possibly China.
   After kicking off his Diamond Jubilee World Tour at the
Meadowlands' Brendan Byrne Arena, Sinatra will gather with his
family at a hotel for a private birthday celebration.
   ``There are no words that can truly describe Frank Sinatra -
magic, charisma and talent - they still don't accurately capture
the aura about him,'' said his former longtime publicist, Lee
Solters.
   Sinatra, who first became popular in the 1940s, continues to get
under our skin, whether he's performing before sellout audiences or
singing from recordings, including two new boxed sets just released
for Christmas.
   ``Fly Me to the Moon,'' ``Strangers in the Night,'' ``You Make
Me Feel So Young,'' ``The Lady Is a Tramp,'' ``New York, New
York,'' ``Summer Wind,'' ``I've Got You Under My Skin'' and ``My
Way'' are Sinatra classics.
   He's won Grammys and Emmys. He collected a special Academy Award
in 1945 for ``The House I Live In,'' a short about religious and
racial tolerance, and the supporting actor Oscar for his role as
Pvt. Angelo Maggio in ``From Here to Eternity.''
   He's appeared in more than 50 movies, including ``Anchors
Aweigh,'' ``On the Town,'' ``Guys and Dolls,'' ``The Tender Trap,''
``High Society,'' ``Pal Joey,'' ``The Manchurian Candidate'' and
``Von Ryan's Express.''
   His hairline has receded over the years, and his waist has
thickened, but his light baritone has only grown deeper and richer.
   The blunt, aggressive son of immigrants has ld a lavish
lifestyle and associated with people whose names could be found in
FBI files. But for each story of him punching someone who had
offended him, there was a story of loyalty and generosity to
friends and strangers.
   He exudes vitality these days. Still, Sinatra may be thinking
about his age. During a toast on an upcoming TV special, he lifts
his glass and says: ``May you all live to be 400 years old, and may
the last voice you hear be mine.''
   Tina Sinatra, his daughter who helped edit the CBS-TV special
``Sinatra 75: The Best Is Yet to Come,'' to be broadcast next
Sunday, conceded she was overwhelmed after going over details of
her father's life.
   ``I was pretty well educated, pretty well aware of his career,
because I've known him all my life, of course,'' she said. ``But
when you do it in a consolidated time it is quite something. It's
emotional. It's fascinating. It's overwhelming.''
   Sinatra, who refuses most interviews, has had good press and bad
press over the years.
   Asked about the entertainer's well-publicized run-ins with the
media, Solters explained: ``He doesn't cater to the press, but at
the same time he's not rude to them intentionally. He's his own
man. He's much maligned. The press will take something and blow it
out of proportion.
   ``The press can take a thread and make a garment.''
   Sinatra isn't bashful and doesn't hesitate to speak his mind.
Most recently, after George Michael complained about the tragedy of
fame, Sinatra wrote an open letter to the pop star telling him to
stop whining.
   ``Frank is a tiger - afraid of nothing, ready for anything,''
Robert Mitchum once said. ``He'll fight anything. Here's a frail,
undersized little fellow with a scarred-up face who isn't afraid of
the whole world.''
   Sinatra has been married four times. A romance with Ava Gardner
led to the end of his marriage to longtime sweetheart Nancy
Barbato, who married him in 1939 and bore three children - Nancy,
Frank Jr. and Christina.
   His tempestuous, on-again, off-again marriage to Gardner ended
in 1953. His name was linked with Lana Turner and Lauren Bacall,
and he was engaged briefly to Juliet Prowse, but he did not marry
again until 19-year-old Mia Farrow came into his life more than a
decade later.
   By that time, he was the firmly established head of ``The Rat
Pack'' or the Clan, a group including Dean Martin, Joey Bishop,
Sammy Davis Jr. and Peter Lawford.
   In 1971, saying he wanted room for reflection, he gave his
``farewell concert'' in Los Angeles. But his retirement ended two
years later with a TV special, ``Ol' Blue Eyes is Back.'' In 1976,
he married Barbara Marx, former wife of Zeppo Marx. Among those
attending: Ronald Reagan.
   ``People often remark that I'm pretty lucky. I don't think luck
as such has much to do with it,'' Sinatra said in a 1957 interview
with The New York Times. ``You've got to have something more
substantial. The competition is too fierce.''
   The lyrics to ``My Way,'' his signature song, express it all for
Sinatra: ``I've lived a life that's full. I traveled each and every
highway. And more, much more than this - I did it my way.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0017 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 1131EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Iran-Rushdie     12-09 0256</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Iran-Rushdie,0271</SECOND>
<HEAD>Iranian Minister: Rushdie Death Decree Irrevocable</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NICOSIA, Cyprus (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An Iranian minister was quoted as saying
Sunday that the death sentence against author Salman Rushdie is
still valid and is irrevocable.
   Mohammad Khatami, minister of culture and Islamic guidance, made
the comment in an interview with the Islamic Republic News Agency,
carried by Tehran radio.
   The late Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini ``passed Islam's sentence
against Salman Rushdie, and this decree, and under no circumstances
can this be revoked,'' Khatami was quoted as saying.
   Rushdie has been in hiding since Khomeini called for his death
in February 1989 for allegedly defaming Islam in his novel ``The
Satanic Verses.''
   Last week, Rushdie made a brief appearance at a London bookstore
to sign copies of ``Haroun and the Sea of Stories,'' a children's
book he wrote while in hiding.
   Tehran and London restored ties in September, 18 months after
relations were broken over the Rushdie affair.
   Khatami's pronouncement was an apparent jab at President Hashemi
Rafsanjani, whose success in downplaying Khomeini's Fatwa, or
religious edict, led to the restoration of Tehran-London ties.
   While the rest of Rafsanjani's Cabinet favors his pragmatic
policies, Khatami is one of the few ministers whose sympathies
extend to the rival anti-Western radical faction.
   The radicals, led by Parliament Speaker Mehdi Karrubi and former
Interior Minister Ali Akbar Mohtashemi, want to continue to use the
Rushdie affair to block normalization of ties with the West.
   The Society of Combatant Theologians, which groups various
hard-liners together, also said in a statement Sunday that the
death decree against Rushdie was irrevocable.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0018 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 1139EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-HousingEffects Bjt   12-09 0635</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Housing Effects, Bjt,720</SECOND>
<HEAD>Effects of Slump in Housing Industry Trickling Through Economy</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN D. McCLAIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The effects of the weakening housing industry
are trickling through the economy, touching not just carpenters and
contractors but thousands of others not directly involved in
building houses.
   For builder Dan Pincus, the downturn means slowing his Brick,
N.J., operation from three or four houses under construction at one
time to just one.
   For Doug Brackett of the American Furniture Manufacturers
Association in High Point, N.C., it means slower furniture sales.
   ``When housing starts are down, furniture sales are down,''
explains Irene Kleeberg of the National Retail Federation in New
York. ``That includes rugs and washing machines, dishwashers and
mattresses.''
   ``Houses are not being sold, and this affects retail sales,''
she continued. ``If you buy a new house, you want new furniture
even if your old furniture is OK.''
   The Commerce Department says housing starts plunged 6 percent in
October to their lowest level since the 1981-82 recession. Starts
were down 12.4 percent during the first 10 months of the year.
   Sales of new homes also were off 3.5 percent in October,
matching the 1981-82 recession-level decline in housing starts. For
the year, sales have fallen 15.8 percent from the same period of
1989.
   And the Labor Department reported on Friday that 62,000 more
construction jobs were lost in November. Over the last six months,
construction employment has dropped by about 250,000, the
government said.
   Robert Villanueva, director of forecasting for the National
Association of Home Builders, said the impact of a weakening
housing industry spreads far beyond the construction industry.
   For every 1,000 houses being built, the total number of jobs
involved is 1,759 man-years, he said. ``That means for one house,
it's almost 1.8 years if one man built the house.''
   But, Villanueva added, actual construction represents less than
half of those jobs. In fact, construction man-years account for
just 627 of the total, including 525 man-years involved in on-site
work - ``the guy actually out there with a hammer.''
   Other industries, including manufacturing building products,
transportation and selling services, represent another 897
man-years, he said. Manufacturing alone accounts for about 23
percent of the total.
   Land develoment - ``clearing the land, trenching it, putting in
the sewers and other utilities'' - accounts for yet another 235
man-years.
   At the same time, slackening demand has brought down prices -
and presumably profits - in various industries.
   ``For example, gypsum prices ... showed about a 6 or 7 percent
decline over the past year,'' Villanueva said. Gypsum is a primary
material for interior walls of houses.
   ``Lumber and wood prices ... also seem to be sliding over the
last six months,'' Villanueva added.
   He said sales of basic construction supplies peaked last
February and have declined 5.5 percent since then. Sales of home
furnishings such as appliances and air conditioners and furniture
have declined 5.3 percent since their March high.
   Nevertheless, economist Sandra Shaber with the Futures Group in
Washington says replacement demand is softening some of the effect
of the housing slowdown.
   ``For certain demographic and economic reasons, replacement
demand is somewhat stronger than it might otherwise be,'' she said.
``That's both because there's a very large group of aging baby
boomers and the difficulties of the affordability of moving.
   ``While this in no way is going to save the appliance or
furniture businesses from suffering during a recession, it can
cushion some of the blow,'' she added. ``Appliances and furniture
might have been even weaker had it not been for a certain amount of
demographically and economically related replacement demand.''
   In fact, Mary Gillespie of the Association of Home Appliance
Manufacturers in Chicago says her organization has been
``hard-pressed to put together a close correlation with appliances
and the downturn in housing.''
   Ms. Gillespie admitted that appliance sales have slowed,
although that was anticipated because of the overall economic
sluggishness. But the downturn has not been in the areas usually
closely related to housing, she added.
   ``For example, ranges,'' she explained. ``Ranges are the first
appliance, the primary appliance, that's tied to new housing. While
housing is down, that, in fact, has not been the case for ranges,
either gas or electric ... Dishwashers are usually closely tied to
new housing. Dishwashers are up 1.4 percent for the year.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0019 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 1143EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-SpotlightonStealth Bjt   12-09 0688</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Spotlight on Stealth, Bjt,790</SECOND>
<HEAD>Glare of Publicity Buffets Secret Navy Plane, Pentagon Brass</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT BURNS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The unfolding story of Pentagon bungling in
the A-12 stealth aircraft program has revealed more than just new
details about the secret Navy attack plane that's been under wraps
for more than six years.
   Emerging evidence of mismanagement in the $50 billion program
also has shown clearly that Defense Secretary Dick Cheney has
failed to break a longstanding and embarrassing pattern of waste
and deception in weapons procurement.
   The Pentagon inspector general and a Navy internal report last
week said technical problems in producing the first prototype plane
were papered over to keep the contract fees flowing.
   Excessive secrecy limited normal program reviews that may have
tipped off Navy managers early on to the plane's problems.
   Now the plane is over budget, overweight and overdue. There is
some doubt it ever will get off the drawing board.
   The A-12 isn't just any plane. It's the Navy's No. 1 aviation
priority, envisioned as the latest U.S. warplane to be built with
composite materials that limit radar reflections and thereby make
it especially difficult to detect by enemy radar.
   It is supposed to replace the Navy's venerable A-6 carrier-based
attack planes in the mid-1990s.
   But the Navy report last week confirmed for the first time that
the plane may be nearly 8,000 pounds heavier than the original
specifications required. The main problem, it said, is ``weight
growth'' due to the thickness of the construction material needed
to make the plane strong enough for landings on aircraft carriers.
   The House Armed Services Committee was scheduled to hold a
public hearing Monday on the A-12's problems, with Navy Secretary
H. Lawrence Garrett III to testify.
   Cheney, back from a European trip, also was expecting a report
Monday from his top deputy on ``corrective recommendations.''
   One of the key executives Cheney recruited to help reform the
arms-buying process - John Betti, a former Ford Motor Co. vice
president - was singled out by the Pentagon inspector general as a
culprit in the A-12 fiasco.
   ``We find Mr. Betti's failure especially troublesome,'' the
inspector general wrote in a report to Congress.
   Betti still has his job, but Vice Adm. Richard C. Gentz, the top
Navy officer overseeing the program, was ordered to retire after
the internal Navy report said Navy managers had failed to tell the
top brass of mounting financial and technical problems in the A-12
program.
   Two other senior Navy officials were transferred to other jobs
and formally censured.
   A major review of the program in April by high-level Pentagon
officials, including Betti, failed to disclose the problems. Betti
shrugged off a warning from one of his own staff members that the
contractors were stumbling and that development costs were at least
$1 billion over the projected $4.8 billion.
   Betti chose to believe the overly optimistic assessments of the
contractors, McDonnell Douglas Corp. and General Dynamics Corp.,
both of St. Louis.
   After being briefed on the program review's conclusions - and
not knowing they were misleading - Cheney publicly assured Congress
that the A-12 was on track and within budget.
   He urged that 620 of the planes be bought for $52 billion.
   Just a few weeks later, on June 1, the contractors dropped their
bombshell: The work was a year behind schedule and far over budget,
and the plane could not meet certain performance standards.
   Shortly afterward, General Dynamics took a $450 million
write-off on the program, and both contractors are pursuing claims
with the Pentagon to recover some unanticipated expenses. They also
want to restructure the contract.
   Al Spivak, a General Dynamics spokesman, said the company had no
comment on the Navy report in which both contractors were accused
of concealing information that would have tipped off the Navy
leadership to the project's problems.
   ``We're still reviewing it and we have nothing more to say at
this time,'' Spivak said Friday.
   McDonnell Douglas did not return a call seeking comment last
week.
   The Navy's A-12 investigation said excessive secrecy helped hide
the problems.
   For example, an internal progress report normally provided to
the office of the Navy secretary was not written because there were
too few people available with the necessary security clearances.
   In her report, Inspector General Susan J. Crawford said the
Pentagon gave the contractors too much latitude, citing a Pentagon
inspector team's January visit to the General Dynamics A-12 plant
in Fort Worth, Texas.
   The inspectors agreed at the end of their visit to turn over
their notes, which General Dynamics reviewed for security
classification. One set of notes was lost; it later was determined
to have contained no secret information.
   ``We question any procedure by which a contractor obtains access
to, and control over, the work product of government personnel
engaged in oversight duties,'' Ms. Crawford wrote.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0020 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 1220EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Bush-SouthAmerica     12-09 0576</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bush-South America,680</SECOND>
<HEAD>``Mature Partnership'' With Latins Closer Now Than Before</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP News Analysis</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GEORGE GEDDA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CARACAS, Venezuela (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two decades ago, when Richard Nixon
was still a relative newcomer in the White House, he said the
United States needed a more ``mature partnership'' with Latin
America. Four presidents later, Nixon's goal may finally have been
achieved.
   After spending eight of the past 13 days in Latin America - two
in Mexico and six in South America - Bush can boast that there is
probably less tension in the relationship than at any time over the
past generation.
   There is general agreement between the United States and Latin
America on shared objectives, particularly on achieving prosperity
through increased trade and investment. These are key elements of
the ``Enterprise for the Americas Initiative'' that Bush promoted
throughout his travels.
   The crowds greeting Bush were generally friendly but not huge.
As Bush headed home on Saturday, he could take comfort in the fact
that the angry mobs that used to stalk visiting American leaders
were largely absent. The ``Yankee go home'' mentality nowadays is
largely limited to student fringe groups.
   Nixon himself was witness to what was perhaps the angriest
anti-American demonstration in Latin American history. It happened
right here in 1958 when Nixon was, like George Bush used to be,
vice president. Nixon barely escaped with his life. Eleven years
later, when Nixon wanted to send Nelson Rockefeller to Venezuela as
part of a fact-finding mission, the Venezuelans told Rockefeller to
say home.
   Bush was able to spend 24 tranquil hours here Friday and
Saturday. Venezuelans who look upon the United States as the enemy
are diminishing in number, and the more benign view of Washington
extends elsewhere in the region.
   In his visits to Brazil, Uruguay, Argentina and Chile, there was
a relaxed camaraderie at almost every stop as opposed to the cold,
formal encounters U.S. officials were accustomed to during periods
of friction over such issues as human rights abuses.
   Bush was able to speak to the national legislatures in four
countries almost without incident. Underscoring the more laid back
approach, Bush went to rodeos in Mexico and Argentina and took a
dip at an Uruguayan beach resort. The past week would have been
almost care free were it not for the repeated intrusions of the
Persian Gulf crisis.
   There are a number of factors contributing to Bush's ability to
breeze through one of the most ambitious Latin American tours ever
undertaken by an American president:
   -One is the end of the Cold War, during which the United States
and Latin America rarely saw eye to eye on how to deal with the
issue of Marxism. Beyond that, few Latins now look on Cuba as the
answer and the U.S. as the problem.
   -Another is the historic embrace of democracy in the region. At
times in the past, the United States seemed to waver in its support
for democracy but no longer, and most Latins applaud the change.
   -In addition, a remarkable consensus has emerged throughout the
hemisphere that Latin economic stagnation is attributable to closed
economic systems which, in Bush's words, have ``smothered growth''
and benefited only those with the right political connections.
   The new breed of leaders, Bush said here Saturday, ``understands
that the road to growth, jobs and rising income is through new
investment, expanded trade and unleashing the energy of
entrepreneurs.''
   Bush brought little with him except encouragement. At each stop,
he reaffirmed his policy of trying to induce the Latins to stick to
their new policies by offering them incentives in the areas of
trade, investment and debt.
   His ultimate goal is a hemisphere-wide free trade agreement.
U.S. officials wonder whether the Latins have the political will to
carry out the reforms they agree are necessary. The Latins wonder
whether Bush's trade goals will be thwarted by protectionist
sentiment back home. How these issues are dealt with will have a
bearing on both hemispheric harmony and prosperity.
   
   -----
   
   EDITOR'S NOTE: George Gedda has covered foreign affairs for the
Associated Press since 1968.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0021 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 1223EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-CancerIncreases Bjt   12-09 0592</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Cancer Increases, Bjt,0728</SECOND>
<HEAD>Lung Cancer Increasing Sharply In Women Who Don't Smoke</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PAUL RAEBURN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Editor</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Lung cancer rates have climbed so sharply in the
United States that the death rate from the disease among
non-smoking women is now higher than the total lung cancer death
rate in women 30 years ago, a study shows.
   ``Cancer is increasing in industrial countries above and beyond
that due to cigarette smoking or aging alone,'' said Devra Lee
Davis, an author of the study and one of the editors of a
collection of studies exploring the recent increases in cancer.
   The increased rate of lung cancer among women who don't smoke
could reflect exposure to second-hand cigarette smoke as well as
exposure to radon, asbestos and possibly air pollution, said Davis,
a researcher at the National Academy of Sciences in Washington.
   According to National Cancer Institute figures, the lung cancer
death rate among all women in 1955 was 5.1 deaths per hundred
thousand women. Davis and her collaborators calculated that the
death rate in women non-smokers by 1985 was 6.1 per hundred
thousand; the total reported lung cancer death rate that year for
women was 26.4.
   Sharp increases are also occurring in brain cancer, a blood
cancer called multiple myeloma and the dangerous skin cancer called
melanoma, Davis said. And the increases are occurring in many
industrial countries, not just the United States.
   ``The changes ar so great over such a short time in so many
countries in men and women that we need to look carefully for their
causes,'' she said. ``These could be very important as clues for
prevention. And it's better to prevent cancer than to cure it.''
   Although the studies emphasize occupational and environmental
exposure, smoking remains one of the single most important causes
of cancer, Davis said. In many industrial countries, it is
responsible for 40 percent of all cancer deaths in men and 30
percent in women.
   Smoking kills an estimated 3 million people each year around the
world, and if current trends continue that will climb to more than
10 million per year by 2020, she said.
   The new studies are collected in ``Trends in Cancer Mortality in
Industrial Countries,'' which will be released by the New York
Academy of Sciences later this week. A copy was obtained by The
Associated Press.
   In addition to the increase in lung cancer among women
non-smokers, Davis mentioned these other examples of cancer on the
rise:
   - Multiple myeloma appears to be increasing in industrialized
countries, possibly as a result of increasing exposure to benzene
in gasoline, although that is not yet scientifically proven.
   ``If I had to bet, I'd bet it was true,'' said Dr. Bernard
Goldstein of the University of Medicine and Dentistry in New
Jersey, whose study suggested the link. ``I thought that
communicating this would be of value because it would alert other
investigators to look at their myeloma cases.''
   - Melanoma is increasing in men much more rapidly than in women,
suggesting some occupational exposure. ``Melanoma has been
associated in some groups of workers with exposure to PCBs,'' said
Davis.
   ``There are a number of cancers where men have higher rates than
women,'' she said. For example, ``more men than women die of
colo-rectal cancer, and their deaths from colo-rectal cancer are
increasing faster for men than women,'' she said. ``When you see it
elevated in men, you have to consider whether occupational factors
are involved.''
   Brain cancer in men and women and breast cancer are also rising
dramatically, Davis said.
   The rise in the cancer rates and death rates is clear, Davis
said. But she emphasized that the links to benzene, PCBs and other
environmental carcinogens remain speculative.
   Many factors could play a role in the cancer increases, she
said.
   They include a genetic predisposition to cancer; lifestyle,
including drinking and smoking; the rate of consumption of
anti-cancer foods like fresh fruits and vegetables; exposure to
X-rays and infectious agents; and other occupational and
environmental factors, she said.
   The studies to be released this week were first presented in
Italy last year at a meeting of the Collegium Ramazzini, an
honorary society of the world's leading authorities of occupational
and environmental causes of disease.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0022 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 1227EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Keating-Glenn     12-09 0641</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Keating-Glenn,740</SECOND>
<HEAD>Glenn Bypasses Ethics Hearing for Gulf Crisis</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KATHERINE RIZZO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Sen. John Glenn last week derided the
administration's Persian Gulf policy, went to secret Intelligence
Committee briefings on the crisis and warned about a shortage of
combat medical personnel.
   What the Ohio Democrat didn't do was attend the Senate Ethics
Committee hearing investigating the ties he and four other senators
had with savings and loan executive Charles H. Keating Jr.
   ``I have a job to do,'' Glenn said. ``Why waste time sitting
down there?''
   In fact, the Ohio Democrat has skipped nearly every ethics
committee session dealing with the so-called Keating Five. Instead,
he relies mainly on briefings from his lawyer.
   His last appearance was Nov. 16, when he issued a defiant
defense: ``John Glenn does not peddle influence. Period.''
   The five senators intervened with federal banking regulators on
behalf of Keating, former head of the failed Lincoln Savings and
Loan. They also received $1.3 million in political donations for
their campaigns and causes from Keating and his associates.
   All the senators have denied that the contributions influenced
their intervention, and say their discussions with federal
regulators on Keating's behalf amounted to routine help for a
constituent. The special counsel prosecuting the case has
recommended that Glenn and Sen. John McCain, R-Ariz., be dropped
from the case.
   Glenn is hardly alone in skipping the televised hearings.
   McCain and Sen. Dennis DeConcini, D-Ariz., have made brief
appearances to watch testimony by their aides and a character
witness.
   Sen. Donald Riegle, D-Mich., last attended Nov. 20 and is said
by a spokeswoman to be monitoring testimony from his office, where
he's planning an agenda for the Senate Banking Committee, which he
chairs.
   Sen. Alan Cranston is in California undergoing radiation
treatment for prostate cancer.
   But Glenn has been the most conspicuous by his presence
elsewhere on Capitol Hill.
   With the massive troop deployment and threat of war in the
Persian Gulf, his committee assignments and longtime interest in
nuclear proliferation have given him plenty to do.
   ``I think my first responsibility is doing whatever I can right
here,'' Glenn said.
   ``I have a background in the military and I think on the Armed
Services Committee people do listen to what I have to say,'' he
said. ``I don't know why people think we should be sitting down in
that (ethics) room all the time when we could be going to war.''
   Last week, while the ethics committee hearing was being
televised live on one cable channel, Glenn could be seen on two
other channels.
   From his perch in the Senate Armed Services Committee hearing
room, Glenn peered down at Defense Secretary Dick Cheney and
criticized the Bush administration policy in the Persian Gulf.
   He called it a ```Chicken Little' approach ... the sky is
falling and the only option is war.''
   Cheney had told the committee that economic sanctions alone
might not be enough to force Saddam Hussein from Kuwait.
   Glenn also asked Lt. Gen. William Odom, former director of the
National Security Agency, about munitions supplies and troop
rotations, and whether ``the American people are willing to support
going to war.''
   A few days later, on ABC-TV's ``Nightline'' program, he sounded
alarms about severe shortages of combat doctors and nurses
throughout the Department of Defense.
   ``Look, this nation may be going to war,'' Glenn said in an
interview. ``Can anyone tell me any more important thing to be
doing than making whatever input I can? That's what I've been
doing.''
   The military manpower subcommittee Glenn heads is looking into
whether the Persian Gulf buildup will require a change in the
nation's long-term plan for reducing the number of people in
uniform.
   He's an expert on nuclear arms and he puts out a newsletter,
``Proliferation Watch.'' This month the publication annotated
current knowledge on Iraq, which the Bush administration claims is
trying to build a nuclear weapon.
   Glenn's reserved seat at the ethics proceeding also was empty
while he conducted a classified intelligence hearing ``in which we
looked into the nuclear claims of the administration.''
   Glenn, who hasn't announced what his political plans will be
when his term expires in 1992, says he's aware of how much is at
stake for him. But he also says he would deserve to be criticized
if he dropped everything to attend the entire ethics proceeding
that began Nov. 15.
   ``To think you have to sit there every second of every day ...
that's not what a Senate job is about,'' Glenn said. ``That's not a
good use of my time.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0023 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 1235EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Soviet-Food     12-09 0573</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Food,0681</SECOND>
<HEAD>Corruption, Distribution Problems Tying Up Badly Needed Food
Supplies</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LESLIE SHEPHERD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The KGB said Sunday it had uncovered plots to
divert food from empty stores and hungry Soviet people, and said it
was filing criminal charges against those responsible.
   Soviet media, meanwhile, said donated foreign food was waiting
in cargo ships on the east and west coasts because of port
congestion, and was piled up at Moscow railway stations due to a
shortage of trucks and drivers.
   The KGB created a special unit last month to control
distribution of donated food supplies and prevent their theft,
after the government put it in charge of the ``battle against
economic sabotage.''
   The official Tass news agency reported Sunday that the KGB had
``exposed and stopped the actions of some officials aimed at
obtaining personal advantages at the expense of state interests
during the storage, transportation and selling to the population of
foodstuffs and consumer goods.''
   Some Western donors had expressed fears that their food aid
could be diverted to the black market, siphoned off by corrupt
officials or left to rot because of inefficient Soviet
transportation and storage facilities.
   ``We held Moscow against the Nazis in late 1941, but now it
seems we have given it up to our home predators who have caught
their prey in their Mafia trade net,'' Stanislav Kondrashov, a
respected Soviet commentator, wrote in the government newspaper
Izvestia.
   Tass said the KGB discovered that a warehouse in the Novgorod
region southwest of Leningrad planned to trade more than 160 tons
of powdered milk for furniture from an unnamed foreign firm.
   The warehouse received the furniture, worth $55,000, and sold it
to its employees instead of distributing it to local stores, Tass
said. The KGB stopped the other half of the exchange, the illegal
export of the milk worth $250,000, Tass said.
   The KGB also discovered that three to five tons of meat were
being diverted daily from a meat plant in the Ukrainian city of
Kharkov to a factory where it was made into sausages for sale on
the black market.
   In addition, it found about seven tons of rice buried in the
Kara-Kalpak Autonomous Region of the Uzbekistan Republic, Tass
said.
   ``Numerous other cases of incomplete deliveries, concealment of
imported and Soviet-made foodstuffs and manufactured goods, as well
as speculation with those goods were exposed,'' Tass said.
   ``Criminal proceedings are being instituted against the
offenders,'' it said.
   Soviet officials maintain that food production is no lower than
last year, and many blame the barren store shelves on a crumbling
distribution system and panicked consumers.
   Many republics and regions across the nation have halted
shipments of food and consumer goods to Moscow and other areas to
protest policies of the central government and keep scarce goods
for themselves.
   Hundreds of tons of food and medicine have been arriving in
Moscow in recent weeks from the United States, Germany, Italy,
Israel, Britain, Switzerland and elsewhere. Much of the donations
have come from private groups.
   Tass reported Sunday that congestion at ports on the east and
west coasts was delaying the unloading of foreign food. Ships
containing flour, sugar, meat and other food from Germany, Belgium
and Cuba were backed up at Leningrad's port.
   ``The situation at Far Eastern ports is especially difficlt,''
Tass said without elaborating.
   The Communist Party newspaper Pravda quoted Nikolai Gavryushin,
head of container and commercial traffic in the Railways Ministry,
as saying the organization of unloading goods at Moscow railway
stations was ``catastrophic.''
   He said as of Saturday, there were 20,000 cargo containers and
300 railway cars with consumer goods and industrial equipment
waiting to be unloaded. He said 101 rail cars with foreign meat
have been standing at the Moscow-Tovarnaya cargo station since Nov.
25.
   Gavryushin blamed a shortage of trucks, drivers and storage
space.
   ``All warehouses of trading establishments are packed to
capacity,'' he said. ``On the other hand, shop shelves are empty.
Why?''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0024 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 1236EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p AM-GOPGovs     12-09 0327</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-GOP Govs,360</SECOND>
<HEAD>Politics, Economy on Agenda at GOP Governors Meeting</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By WALTER R. MEARS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Special Correspondent</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PINEHURST, N.C. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Republican governors gathered on Sunday
for a two-day conference on the political lessons of 1990 and the
headaches of governing what they won.
   The economy is slumping, state budgets face a worsening squeeze,
and the voters already have rebelled against tax increases - six
states rejected incumbent governors in the Nov. 6 elections, and
eight more switched parties in replacing retiring governors.
   For most of the governors who lost, tax increases were a major
problem. For those who won, some of them with anti-tax campaign
themes, budget woes will be an early challenge.
   Vice President Dan Quayle heads the list of administration
officials coming to address the governors and to meet with them in
private sessions. But the administration isn't likely to have much
help to offer for their budget woes, since the federal government
is in the same tax and spending vise that is squeezing states.
   There will be 20 Republican governors, 28 Democrats, two
independents next year.
   Fourteen governors and four governors-elect were due at the
conference.
   One Republican was coming with an aseerisk by his name: J. Fife
Symington of Arizona narrowly led in the Nov. 6 election, but he
didn't get a majority and so faces a Feb. 26 runoff against
Democrat Terry Goddard.
   Politics was the conference keynote, with the governors
conferring first with leaders of the Republican National Committee.
William J. Bennett, newly designated to become party chairman, was
due in his dual role - that one and as outgoing director of the
Office of National Drug Control Policy.
   Florida Gov. Bob Martinez, defeated for re-election, is taking
over the drug policy job. He was not at the conference.
   Formal sessions begin Monday morning, with appearances by
Bennett, Housing Secretary Jack Kemp, Interior Secretary Manuel
Lujan and Environmental Protection Administration head William
Reilly.
   Quayle addresses the conference later in the day, then meets
privately with the governors.
   On Tuesday, party officials and pollsters appear at the final
conference session to discuss what happened in the last elections
and what's likely in the next ones.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0025 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 1238EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-India     12-09 0443</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-India,0540</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hindus, Moslems Fight With Knives, Swords; 14 Killed</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MOHAMMED A. MANNAN</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HYDERABAD, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hindus and Moslems fought Sunday with
knives and swords in a dispute over a mosque, and police opened
fire on rioters, authorities said. At least 14 people were killed.
   A curfew was imposed on the southern city and policemen were
ordered to shoot violators, said police officials, who cannot be
named under briefing rules.
   They said 105 people had been killed since the wave of violence
began on Friday in the city of 2 million people.
   Police opened fire six times during Sunday's street battles,
killing at least one person and wounding 10 others, the officials
said. They said 28 people were hospitalized with stab wounds.
   The rioting came as Hindu fundamentalists made new attempts to
destroy a 16th century mosque in the remote northern Indian town of
Ayodhya, nearly 700 miles from Hyderabad, and replace it with a
temple.
   There also was renewed violence over the issue in the northern
town of Aligarh, 250 miles west of Ayodhya, where police said at
least 29 people were killed on Friday and Saturday.
   Hindus first targeted the Mosque of Babar in October. During
that month and November, more than 380 people died nationwide in
violence related to the dispute.
   Thousands of Hindus have been congregating in Ayodhya for nearly
a week, staging generally peaceful demonstrations near the small
mosque, which Hindu fundamentalists claim was built on the ruins of
an ancient temple.
   United News of India said paramilitary troops foiled an attempt
to blow up the mosque about midnight Saturday.
   A 23-year-old Hindu man was arrested when he approached the
mosque with three packages of dynamite attached to timed
detonators, the news agency said.
   Murlidhar Reddy, a Hyderabad police commissioner, said at least
30 people were killed on Friday and 60 more died on Saturday.
   Residents said the trouble started Thursday night when a Hindu
crowd stoned the house of Majeed Khan, a leader of the Babri Masjid
Action Committee, which is trying to save the Ayodhya mosque.
   Moslems retaliated by attacking Hindus, and both sides
eventually began fighting each other with knives, swords and
sticks, the residents said. They also spoke on condition of
anonymity.
   Hindu fundamentalists say the Mosque of Babar was built on the
ruins of a temple that they claim was razed by Moslem conquerers.
Moslems say the mosque was built on a vacant plot. Archaeologists
and historians are divided on the issue.
   The dispute brought down the government of Prime Minister V.P.
Singh last month. Singh lost support when he stopped Hindus from
destroying the mosque and said he wanted the issue settled in
court.
   Singh's successor, Prime Minister Chandra Shekhar, has been
meeting with Moslem and Hindu leaders in an effort to defuse the
problem.
   Moslems, who make up 12 percent of India's 880 million people,
fear the destruction of one mosque would lead to the demolition of
many other Islamic shrines and structures across the country.
   India is officially secular, but the top government ranks are
dominated by Hindus, whose make up 82 percent of the population.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0026 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 1303EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Bush-Church     12-09 0227</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bush-Church,230</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush Hears Sermon Likening Jackson to Biblical Prophet</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush heard a sermon Sunday likening
Jesse Jackson to John the Baptist and admonishing people to heed
Jackson's calls for racial justice and equality.
   Bush, who returned Saturday night from his weeklong tour of
South America, and his wife Barbara attended a eucharist service at
St. John's Episcopal Church across Lafayette Park from the White
House.
   They heard a gospel about John the Baptist, then a brief sermon
by the Rev. James C. Holmes urging people to listen to Jackson when
he talks about ``the need to turn the racism in our country to
justice.''
   Jackson, who has twice sought the Democratic presidential
nomination, was elected a ``shadow'' senator or lobbyist for the
District of Columbia.
   Holmes said Jackson was criticized in a recent television
editorial as having the right message, but being the wrong
messenger.
   That is the way people often react to a prophet, the preacher
said. ``The message gets under our skin.''
   ``God has always used imperfect messengers,'' he said. ``If we
focus on the imperfections, then we block out the message.''
   Holmes is assistant pastor of the church, which Bush often
attends on the infrequent Sunday mornings he is in Washington.
   The rector, the Rev. John C. Harper, gave thanks for the release
of the hostages in Iraq and Kuwait, and prayed for Bush, the
American troops overseas and ``those who pay counsel to the peace
of the world.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0027 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 1338EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Japan-Space     12-09 0458</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Japan-Space,0559</SECOND>
<HEAD>Japanese Journalist Nears End of Unprecedented Reporting Trip</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAN BIERS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Like many an affluent tourist on an exotic and
expensive jaunt, Toyohiro Akiyama took in the sights, kept his
hand-held video camera ever at the ready, and sent off plenty of
dispatches to folks back home.
   But Akiyama made history while he was at it, becoming the first
journalist and the first Japanese in space.
   Akiyama comes back down to Earth Monday, eight days after
blasting off into space with two Soviet cosmonauts in a Soyuz space
capsule that linked up with the orbiting space station Mir.
   His employer, the Tokyo Broadcasting System, paid the Soviets
$12 million for the round-trip ticket, and spent an additional $25
million on the project.
   Taking along a paying passenger was an important step in the
Soviets' effort to commercialize their space program, and Akiyama's
trip has been a relentlessly commercial affair.
   Japanese corporate sponsors, including a diaper maker and a
toothpaste company, displayed them around the launch pad in remote
Soviet Central Asia and even plastered them on the rocket itself.
   TBS, Japan's largest private broadcaster, has made Akiyama the
center of its universe throughout the course of the mission, airing
nightly prime-time specials and extended weekend coverage of his
expoits.
   Viewers saw the 48-year-old Akiyama get bear hugs from the
Soviet cosmonauts when he arrived at the Mir space station on
Tuesday, unfurling a banner reading ``The First Japanese in
Space.''
   Akiyama did not hesitate to share with viewers such details as
his space sickness upon experiencing weightlessness.
   ``I feel things in my stomach are coming out,'' he reported.
   In a more poetic vein, viewing the Earth from space moved him to
recite some Japanese haiku:
   ``Under the thick cloud there is my country; Approaching, I see
my country in a morning sunshine; Behind me is the space in pitch
dark; Sad is Africa with no cloud or forest.''
   At one point, Akiyama was filmed trying to drink tea from a tube
in zero gravity. He was clearly startled when some drops of tea
that missed his mouth began floating away.
   Much of Akiyama's commentary had to do with the pollution on
Earth visible from the spacecraft. The skies over Japan and the
United States looked dirty and gray, he said.
   ``I'm not trying to make a big fuss calling for environmental
protection, but I honestly think it is beautiful to see where
nature is still preserved,'' he said.
   He also took six Japanese tree frogs into space for experiments
on how they adapt to the weightless environment. TBS said videotape
of these experiments may be shown later.
   TBS, which celebrates its 40th anniversary next year, created a
special department in 1986 to develop the space project. It sent a
staff of 120 camera operators, technicians, correspondents and
producers to the Soviet Union to cover the flight.
   The company expects to lose $7.4 million on the project, even
after accounting for advertising revenues and proceeds from
documentaries and lectures by Akiyama.
   TBS had exclusive rights to cover the eight-day flight. The rest
of Japan's media prominently covered the blastoff but have since
been relatively quiet about the rest of the mission.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0028 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 1343EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Yugoslavia-Glance     12-09 0312</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Yugoslavia-Glance,0355</SECOND>
<HEAD>Yugoslav Republics of Serbia, Montenegro At A Glance</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Yugoslavia-Elections</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BELGRADE, Yugoslavia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are some facts and figures on
Serbia, the largest Yugoslav republic, and Montenegro, the
smallest. The two are the last Marxist-ruled republics. The first
multiparty elections in both republics were held Sunday. Results
were not expected until late Monday at the earliest.
   ---
</TEXT>
<HEAD>SERBIA</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   HISTORY - Constituted at the end of the eighth century. The
medieval Serbian state reached its zenith in the mid-14th century
under Emperor Dusan, who conquered a large part of Byzantine
territory. In 1389 it was occupied by Turkey and remained under its
domination until the early 19th century. Re-established as a
sovereign state in 1878. Fought Balkan wars in 1912-1913,
increasing its territory over present-day Macedonia and Kosovo.
Triggered World War I, and after the war it became part of the
Kingdom of Serbia, Croatia and Slovenia in 1918. After World War
II, became one of the six Yugoslav constituent republics.
   POPULATION - 9.7 million, of which 6.9 million is eligible to
vote.
   ELECTIONS - First multiparty vote since 1938. Polls opened at 7
a.m. (1 a.m. EST) and closed 12 hours later. Forty-four parties
were running for 250 seats for single-chamber parliament, and 32
candidates for the republic's presidency.
   ---
</TEXT>
<HEAD>MONTENEGRO</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   HISTORY - Formed about the same time as Serbia, but in the
course of history was sometimes independent and sometimes under the
rule of Serbia. It also fell under the Turkish domination in the
14th century and was re-established as a sovereign kingdom in the
19th century. Following World War I, was taken over by unilateral
act of Belgrade government and lost independent status. After World
War II, constituted as a Yugoslav republic.
   POPULATION - 632,647, of which 389,455 are eligible voters.
   ELECTIONS - First multiparty vote since World War II. Polls
opened at 7 a.m. (1 a.m. EST) and closed 12 hours later. Ten
parties were running for 125 seats in the single-chamber
parliament, three candidates for president and 14 candidates for
four seats in the collective presidency.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0029 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 1400EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-RochesterSlayings     12-09 0645</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Rochester Slayings,0775</SECOND>
<HEAD>Serial Killing Trial Stranger Than Fiction</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY7</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By HILARY APPELMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ROCHESTER, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The serial murder trial of Arthur J.
Shawcross sometimes seems more like an episode of television's
``Twin Peaks'' than a real-life courtroom drama.
   Throughout the 10-week trial, spectators crowded into the
courtroom to hear watch videotaped hypnosis sessions and hear
testimony on everything from multiple personalities to cannibalism
and the meaning of truth.
   Among the cast of characters in the Monroe County courtroom
drama: a sharp-witted judge, a expert witness who kept wandering
off the topic and jurors sporting matching bow ties. The jury is
scheduled to begin deliberations Wednesday.
   Shawcross, 45, is charged with the murders of 10 women over the
past two years. The burly, gray-haired defendant made an unlikely
centerpiece for the hoopla surrounding him.
   He sat motionless between his lawyers throughout the trial,
staring impassively at the floor.
   Shawcross confessed in January to the 10 slayings and to an 11th
murder in neighboring Wayne County. His lawyers have conceded that
he killed the women, but say he was insane when he did it.
   Jurors watched 12 hours of videotapes in which Shawcross was
purportedly under hypnosis.
   On the tapes, he switched in and out of a high-pitched woman's
voice and told defense psychiatrist Dr. Dorothy Lewis that he was
once a cannibal in medieval England.
   The tapes also show Shawcross speaking as his mother, Bessie,
his sister, Jeannie, his childhood self and a character he
identified as ``Aramus,'' who he said helped him meet girls.
   In sometimes graphic detail, he described incestuous relations
with his sister as a child and wartime atrocities and cannibalism
in Vietnam.
   In the most dramatic portion of the tapes, Shawcross appeared to
relive an incident in which he was sexually abused by his mother.
He told Lewis his mother's voice told him to kill his victims, and
that she ``helped him'' strangle and mutilate one of the women.
   But in videotaped interviews with prosecution psychiatrist Dr.
Park Dietz, Shawcross said he never heard voices or had different
personalities.
   Dietz accused Lewis of creating Shawcross' other personalities
by asking leading questions.
   But Lewis said Shawcross was suffering from post-traumatic
stress disorder that arose from severe childhood abuse and brain
damage. She said the combination caused Shawcross to lose touch
with reality at the time of the slayings.
   But Dietz testified that Shawcross faked mental illness,
modeling himself after the character Norman Bates in the movie
``Psycho.''
   He said Shawcross lied about everything from the murders to his
claim that he had used rubber baby bottle nipples as gun silencers
in Vietnam.
   The psychiatrist said he tested that claim with a semi-automatic
weapon at the Rochester Police Department's gun range.
   ``It didn't silence anything - the report was equally loud with
and without the baby bottle nipple,'' he said with slight smile
that was a departure from his normally stern demeanor.
   Dietz's efficient testimony contrasted sharply with the
stream-of-consciousness testimony of Lewis. Her answers frequently
wandered onto topics like Sigmund Freud's use of hypnotism and the
history of psychiatry.
   Judge Donald Wisner frequently admonished her, saying she would
have to restrain herself ``in order to complete this trial before
spring.''
   Lewis' inability to give simple yes or no answers, as well as
her apparent difficulty remembering dates, times and facts,
provoked a series of standoffs with prosecutor Charles Siragusa.
   ``I can't chew gum and walk at the same time,'' Lewis told a
chuckling jury as she shuffled through the stack of papers on her
lap, trying to find an answer to one of Siragusa's questions.
   ``Is the extent of your organization indicated by the file on
your lap?'' Siragusa asked sarcastically.
   In another exchange, Lewis and Siragusa had a lengthy
philosophical debate over the meaning of truth, as the psychiatrist
attempted to distinguish between intentional and unintentional
falsehoods.
   ``Are you saying that fantasy can be the truth?'' an exasperated
Siragusa finally asked.
   ``I'm saying that having a fantasy can be the truth,'' Lewis
retorted. ``I'm sure you have them.''
   ``And you do as well, is that right?'' Siragusa asked.
   ``Probably very similar,'' Lewis said.
   ``I doubt that,'' Siragusa snapped back.
   ``Can we get back to the case now?'' asked the judge, as the
jury and spectators laughed.
   The jury made its own contribution to the bizarre proceedings -
showing up one day in football jerseys and, a week later, in
matching bow ties.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0030 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 1418EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-CoronadoMystery     12-09 0573</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Coronado Mystery,0702</SECOND>
<HEAD>Scholars Searching for Clues to Mark Coronado's Trail</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MICHAEL BATES</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WICHITA, Kan. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Scholars are having trouble putting
Francisco Vasquez de Coronado on the map.
   They want to add the 16th century Spaniard's route through the
Southwest to the National Trails System, but they aren't getting
much help from the explorer and his party.
   ``Coronado and his men had no idea where they had gone. They
were marching off the end of the known world,'' said Don Blakeslee,
Wichita State University anthropology department chairman.
   Blakeslee and Betty Romero, director of the Rice County
Coronado-Quivira Museum in Lyons, are coordinating the project for
the Coronado Trail Association.
   They've been combing historical documents - including letters
Coronado wrote the king of Spain and accounts by participants - in
hopes of determining which of 30 proposed routes is the right one.
   ``There are plenty of people who have a pet idea where he
went,'' Blakeslee said. ``Every little town anywhere near where he
might have gone would like to be able to claim Coronado.''
   In 1540, Coronado and his entourage - 300 soldiers and some
1,500 Indian guides and camp followers - set out from Mexico to
search for the legendary gold-rich Seven Cities of Cibola.
   For two years, together and in separate groups, they explored
Arizona, New Mexico, Texas, Oklahoma and Kansas. Though they found
no gold, they helped open the region to colonization.
   Romero says she wants her museum to become an interpretative
center for the trail. In April, the museum will sponsor a symposium
for scholars to view exhibits of armor and weapons used by the
conquistadors and debate where Coronado and his men traveled.
   ``We're going to try to throw out as many wrong ideas as we can
in a short period of time,'' Blakeslee said. ``But we haven't yet
gotten all of the people together who need to be in one room
arguing with one another. And we haven't done all of the field
work, which is absolutely critical.''
   Blakeslee said the field work could quickly eliminate some
routes.
   One proposed path the anthropology professor checked out was
obviously wrong. He said he crossed the Cimarron River where the
route's proponent said Coronado crossed. But the canyon the
explorers described was not there.
   Coronado's letters and the other texts offer clues, but few
definite directions.
   ``These records really weren't written to tell anybody how to
get to the places mentioned,'' Blakeslee said.
   Ambiguities in the texts also have frustrated scholars,
Blakeslee said.
   In one passage, the explorers wrote about eating nuts growing in
the area they were traveling through, but did not say what kind of
nuts. One person assumed the nuts were pecans and based a proposed
route on that assumption, Blakeslee said.
   ``You can't base your arguments on assumptions,'' he said. ``You
have to base them on something in the texts. Then you can make an
assumption, if there is any way to test it.''
   Romero and Blakeslee are hoping new information on Indian trails
may play a big role in assembling the jigsaw puzzle that previously
had critical pieces missing.
   Coronado had Indian guides who apparently knew the country
because they were able to lead the hundreds of soldiers to good
water every night of their travels in August in southwestern
Kansas, Blakeslee said.
   By using historical accounts, old maps, letters and other
documents, Blakeslee has established locations for many Indian
trails in the Great Plains.
   Just about everything important in the early history of the
Plains happened along established trails, he said.
   Most of the eight trails already in the system, including the
Santa Fe Trail in Kansas, were established along precisely known
routes, Blakeslee said. Some trails are still marked by wagon ruts
or other physical features.
   But delineating Coronado's trail hasn't been so simple. The
National Park Service was unprepared for the task when ordered by
Congress to study the feasibility of establishing a Coronado trail,
Blakeslee said.
   ``It takes a lot more effort, more manpower and entirely
different techniques,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0031 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 1427EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Chess-Championship 1stLd-Writethru a0674 12-09 0251</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Chess-Championship, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0674,0300</SECOND>
<HEAD>Kasparov Wins 18th Game, Moves into Lead</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS throughout to UPDATE with description of play, last
moves Sunday, next game scheduled for Monday. No pickup.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>LYON, France (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Garry Kasparov on Sunday won the 18th game
in the world chess championship, moving into the lead as rival
Anatoly Karpov abandoned the game in the second day of play.
   The victory gave Kasparov, the defending champion, 9.5 points
against Karov's 8.5 points with a maximum six games left to play.
   The first player to gain 12.5 points wins the championship and
$1.7 million of a $3 million purse. In the event of a tie, Kasparov
retains his title.
   Experts said that Kasparov, playing white, held the advantage
when the game was adjourned Saturday night after the maximum five
hours of play. He made 17 more moves Sunday to win.
   Karpov, weakened with the loss of a pawn he had sacrificed the
day before, resigned in the 57th move.
   Kasparov's victory marked the third time since the start of the
series Oct. 8 in New York that he has moved ahead of his rival, who
also has held the world championship title. He had won the second
and 16th games, but Karpov evened the past leads out with wins in
the seventh and 17th games.
   All the other games have been draws.
   As in the second game, Kasparov surprised his rival with a
stronger opening Saturday. Karpov was hard-pressed to compensate
for the deficit he suffered in sacrificing a pawn. On Sunday,
Kasparov had no trouble exploiting his advantage.
   The 19th game was scheduled for Monday afternoon.
   The first 12 games in the series were played in New York. The
13th game started in Lyon on Nov. 24.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0032 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 1432EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-FloridaJews     12-09 0674</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Florida Jews,0846</SECOND>
<HEAD>Exhibit Recounts Jewish Contributions to Florida History</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto WX6</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BETH DUFF-BROWN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Some Florida Jews suffer a stereotype as ``cranky
Yankees'' who head south for the low taxes and cheap condos, and
have little regard for their cultural heritage.
   Professor Henry Green, head of Judaic studies at the University
of Miami, hopes to change all that.
   ``When you think of Florida and Jews you basically think of
condo commandos searching for early-bird specials,'' Green said.
``But the Jews have been here since the beginning, contributing
since the beginning.''
   The history of Florida Jews has been compiled into an exhibit
entitled ``Mosaic, Jewish Life in Florida.'' It is on display at
Miami's Historical Museum of Southern Florida through Jan. 6. Then
it will travel the state for two years and head to Israel in 1993.
   About 90 percent of Florida's 750,000 Jews live in the three
South Florida counties of Palm Beach, Broward and Dade, making it
the region with the third largest population of Jews in the world,
after Israel and the New York area.
   The exhibit began as a grass-roots project for a Jewish
community center in Plantation, a sleepy suburban city west of Fort
Lauderdale, and blossomed into a collection of thousands of Jewish
artifacts, documents, photographs and oral histories donated by
people from two dozen Jewish communities around the state.
   It has become an official project of the Christopher Columbus
Quincentenary in two years, which marks the 500th anniversary of
the Italian explorer's arrival in the Western Hemisphere.
   Green, director of Mosaic, believes at least five crew members
on Columbus' first voyage were ``conversos,'' Jews who converted to
Christianity in an attempt to save their lives during the Spanish
Inquisition.
   ``We have survived for so long, but you can't perpetuate unless
you know your own history,'' said Beverly Kaiman of Pensacola,
where the state's first Sephardic Jews settled in 1763.
   Her relatives first came to Pensacola, located in the Florida
panhandle, from Russia at the turn of the century. The family
donated a Russian teapot, a ``yahzheit,'' which is a record of
debts owed by relatives, and several photographs to the exhibit.
   Jean Leibert has lived in Miami since 1956. She said the exhibit
showed her ties to the state she didn't know she had.
   ``It's given me more of a strong feeling of being a part of
Florida, like I have roots here,'' she said.
   Leibert said she was surprised to learn that Levy County was
named after one of the first Jewish families in Florida.
   Moses Levy, fleeing anti-Semitism in Morocco, landed in Central
Florida in 1819 and bought 52,000 acres of land near Gainesville. A
strict Zionist, he intended to create a ``New Jerusalem.''
   That plan failed when few Jews answered his ads in European
newspapers. Levy's son, David Levy Yulee, who helped draft
Florida's constitution, was the first Jewish U.S. senator.
   Other little-known facts Mosaic's researchers discovered:
   - Jewish women in the 19th century made their dishes kosher by
washing them with sand and sea water in Pensacola and Miami Beach.
   - In the 1950s, the Jewish owners of the South Beach Blackstone
Hotel on Miami Beach invited black Baptist ministers to be their
guests when the ministers could find no other accommodations in
racially segregated Miami.
   - Key West Jews in the 1890s formed the Committee to Aid the
Cubans, supporting the revolution against Spain. In gratitude,
revolutionary leader Jose Marti paid a courtesy visit to committee
chairman Louis Fine.
   Also part of Mosaic is a U.S. Army-supplied knapsack with
candles and a kiddush cup for ritual prayer.
   The items were used during World War II by Rabbi Sidney
Lefkowitz of Jacksonville, the military chaplain who performed the
first Jewish service in Germany after the Holocaust.
   One old photograph in the exhibit is of Marcus Joseph Weinkle, a
Russian Jew who was called to serve in the Russian army in 1887.
Just before he was to leave, his family the announced he had
suddenly died.
   After he was buried, he crawled out of his grave and took
clothes and money that had been hidden for him and smuggled himself
out of the country through Turkey. Weinkle eventually moved to
Moffit, Fla., where he opened a lumber mill.
   Stephen Whitfield, a professor of American studies at Brandeis
University in Waltham, Mass., said the exhibit was important
because South Florida was the best hope for the future of the
Jewish South.
   ``It's the only spot in the South where Jewish life will be
vibrant, so the caliber and character of that community is
crucial,'' he said.
   The exhibit also could help improve ethnic relations in South
Florida, said Joseph Mensch, a trustee of the historical museum.
   ``Miami is a multiethnic society that must learn to get along
with each other,'' Mensch said. ``This adds to the melting pot that
helps us live together.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0033 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 1449EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brite-WeatherMuseum     12-09 0323</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brite-Weather Museum,0370</SECOND>
<HEAD>National Weather Service Opens Meteorology Museum</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SILVER SPRING, Md. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   For people who think weather forecasts
are worthy of more than idle elevator chatter, the National Weather
Service had opened a museum dedicated to the long and proud history
of meteorology, curators say.
   The National Weather Service Science and History Center opened
last month in suburban Washington.
   ``Weather is always a fascinating subject because we are
helpless in nature. We are in awe of its turbulent state,'' said
Bill Stanley, a federal historian who designed the museum.
   The museum, located in the new offices of the National Oceanic
and Atmospheric Administration, occupies only 1,100 square feet,
has no staff and is open only on weekdays.
   A wall near the entrance displays photographs of cars bobbing
down a flooded street, lightning in a turbulent sky and a funnel
cloud descending on a field.
   A dripping sound comes from simulated rain in the window of a
model 1891 weather office and a voice drones on with the latest
data from the national Weather Radio.
   Television monitors near the entrance show the weather all over
the country.
   The museum also chronicles names and dates in weather recording,
which dates back at least 200 years in the United States, Stanley
said.
   Originally intended to help farmers, weather forecasting became
popular in 1870 through the Army Signal Corps and the U.S.
Department of Agriculture.
   Thomas Jefferson is said to have requested a break while working
on the Declaration of Independence on July 3, 1776, to take his
thermometer outside and check the temperature.
   Since 1940, the weather service has operated under the U.S.
Department of Commerce and the oceanic and atmospheric agency.
   The museum's displays show how the science of meteorology has
progressed from simple weather vanes, barometers, rain gauges and
record books to high-tech devices like geostationary operational
environmental satellite imagers, Stanley said.
   David Ruth, a meteorologist under contract with the National
Weather Service visited the museum recently. He said it was good to
finally see a memorial to his profession.
   ``Well,'' he said. ``It's certainly a lot nicer than what we had
before.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0034 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 1454EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-PeacefulSolution Bjt   12-09 0620</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Peaceful Solution, Bjt,0793</SECOND>
<HEAD>Saddam's Armies Seen As Long-Term Threat Even With Withdrawal</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP News Analysis</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By NEIL MacFARQUHAR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>RIYADH, Saudi Arabia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Some diplomats and other observers
can see the rough outlines of a peaceful solution to the Persian
Gulf crisis emerging.
   But any face-saving formula that induces Iraqi President Saddam
Hussein to withdraw from Kuwait leaves a long-term question: what
to do about his large and powerful military.
   ``We can't accept being next to a country ready to invade any
morning,'' said a senior Saudi diplomat, who like his colleagues
spoke on condition of anonymity.
   A Saudi source knowledgeable on military affairs said Sunday
that the release of hostages by Saddam may signal a planned
withdrawal from Kuwait, and that chances of peace are better than
those of war.
   So far, Saddam has shown no inclination to pull his 460,000
troops from the Kuwait theater and reinstate the Kuwaiti ruling
family, two key U.N. demands.
   But he has agreed to release foreign hostages, which the
Security Council has repeatedly called on him to do. The first
group of them flew out on Sunday.
   The United States is pouring troops into Saudi Arabia, and
expects to have a force of more than 400,000 ready for offensive
action by Jan. 15. That is the deadline the United Nations Security
Council set for an Iraqi withdrawal, authorizing ``all necessary
means'' to get him out after that.
   On the heels of the resolution, Saddam accepted President Bush's
offer to send Secretary of State James A. Baker III to Baghdad, and
agreed to send Iraqi Foreign Minister Tariq Aziz to come to
Washington.
   Then, on Friday, the Iraqi Parliament approved Saddam's call to
release all foreign hostages.
   Washington, for its part, announced it would withdraw all its
diplomats from the embassy in Kuwait, but not officially close the
mission. Iraq had ordered all missions in Kuwait shut, declaring
the country its 19th province.
   Both sides, then, can save face by pointing to diplomatic gains
while downplaying what they conceded.
   ``You leave something vague and one party presents it as a gain
on their behalf and the other party can too,'' said a Middle
Eastern diplomat.
   On Sunday, Britain's Observer newspaper reported that Iraq has
redrawn its border with Kuwait in what could signal plans to
withdraw as early as next month, a newspaper reported Sunday.
   The report said Iraq was laying claim to an area of the Rumailah
oilfield and the islands of Warba and Bubiyan in the Persian Gulf,
which it has long coveted.
   Saudi officials denied the report. But one Saudi diplomat said
Persian Gulf leaders might be willing to pay Saddam money to
assuage him. He claims that Kuwait stole billions of dollars in oil
revenues from Iraq.
   In any event, an Iraqi withdrawal from Kuwait is seen as only
the first step in stripping Saddam of his military capabilities.
   ``If you don't get rid of him now, you'll have to do it two
years from now, or three years from now, or five years from now.
And you'll have to pay a much higher price,'' said the Saudi
source.
   Saddam has threatened to use his chemical arsenal and some
observers believe he could develop a nuclear bomb during this
decade. With that firepower, he could dictate his neighbors'
actions without necessarily moving troops.
   But it would be difficult to send U.S. soldiers into action now
on the basis of a possible future war.
   ``Is it worth American lives to prevent a hypothetical
situation?'' said a Western diplomat.
   Some Saudi officials also are reluctant to push for the total
destruction of Iraq, worried about who might emerge in Saddam's
place.
   The immediate need, diplomats believe, is to concentrate on
winning a withdrawal from Kuwait without an all-out fight.
   ``If to want to get Saddam out of Kuwait without a war, make it
clear to him that you will kill him on Jan. 15,'' said the Saudi
source.
   Then the alliance could look for a formula to contain Saddam.
That might involve Iraqi guarantees of no more aggression, some
economic and military sanctions on Baghdad and a multinational
presence in the region for up to four years while Saudi Arabia
builds a military.
   ``It's like cutting the leaves of a plant that climbed over the
wall,'' said the Middle Eastern diplomat. ``The root is still
there. You have to cut the tree or at least the branches.''
   ---
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   EDITOR'S NOTE: Neil MacFarquhar, now on assignment in Saudi
Arabia, covers Arab affairs for The Associated Press in Nicosia,
Cyprus.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0035 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 1457EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Gulf-Carter     12-09 0335</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Carter,360</SECOND>
<HEAD>Carter Cautions Bush To Be Flexible in Persian Gulf Talks</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Former President Jimmy Carter says U.S.
officials should be flexible and not simply issue ultimatums in
upcoming talks with Iraqi leaders so as to avoid the likelihood of
war in the Persian Gulf.
   ``If the exchanges are to be genuine, it will be necessary not
to lay down patently unacceptable preconditions or unalterable
demands,'' Carter said in an essay to be published in the Dec. 17
issue of Newsweek magazine.
   ``Meetings just to deliver an ultimatum,'' warns Carter, ``will
not be productive; they will likely lead to war.''
   ``We must have some flexibility,'' he said.
   U.S. and Iraqi officials are currently considering when to
schedule face-to-face talks between President Bush and Iraqi
Foreign Minister Tariq Aziz in Washington and Secretary of State
James A. Baker III and President Saddam Hussein in Baghdad.
   The United Nations has authorized the use of force against
Saddam if his troops aren't out of Kuwait by Jan. 15.
   Carter warned that ``some of the goals of both sides have to be
considered'' in any talks to obtain a peaceful resolution of the
Persian Gulf crisis.
   Saddam must withdraw Iraqi forces from Kuwait and return the
Kuwaiti regime to power, as stipulated by the United Nations, said
Carter.
   He noted that Saddam already has agreed to one of the three
basic U.N. demands - the release of foreign hostages. But the
United States and its allies must also make some concessions,
Carter said.
   There may need to be what Carter called ``an independent
settlement of differences,'' possibly an international conference
to address the Israeli-Palestinian question.
   Carter acknowledges, however, that ``strong political reasons''
make it impractical for such a conference to be linked with the
Kuwait issue. Israel opposes such a conference.
   Additionally, Carter suggested the allies might forgive Iraq's
debt and offer a long-term land lease that would give the nation
access to the Persian Gulf.
   On the question of war, Carter said President Bush will be
forced to ``convince'' the American public that Kuwait's liberation
will ``justify the casualties of a major war.''
   And he said most of the major Arab allies would not join in an
attack on Iraq, making the military action an ``American
operation.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0036 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 1500EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i BC-Gulf-HostageChronolog     12-09 0618</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Gulf-Hostage Chronology,0759</SECOND>
<HEAD>Chronology of the Gulf Hostage Situation Since the Iraqi Invasion</HEAD>
<HEAD>With Gulf-Iraq</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NICOSIA, Cyprus (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here is a chronology of the hostage
crisis in Iraq:
   Aug. 2 - Iraq invades Kuwait, trapping tens of thousands of
foreigners.
   Aug. 9 - U.S. troops begin deploying in Saudi Arabia. Iraq
closes its borders, stranding thousands of Americans and other
Westerners.
   Aug. 19 - Saddam Hussein offers to free all foreigners if the
United States promises to withdraw from Saudi Arabia and guarantees
the U.N.-imposed embargo will be lifted.
   Aug. 23 - Iraqi TV shows Saddam talking o Western women and
children and telling them: ``Your presence here and other other
places is meant to prevent ... war.''
   Aug. 24 - Iraqi troops ring the U.S., British and other
embassies in Kuwait and detain about 100 U.S. Embassy staff and
dependents after promising them safe passage from Baghdad.
   Aug. 26 - Fifty-two Americans, wives and children of diplomats
from the embassy in Kuwait, arrive in Turkey after being detained
in Iraq. Three sons of diplomats are turned back by Iraqi
officials.
   Aug. 30 - Diplomats in Baghdad say Iraq will allow planes to
pick up Western women and children only if the aircraft fly food
and medicine into Iraq.
   Aug. 31 - Nineteen Italians arrive safely in Jordan from Iraq,
the first Westerners freed under Iraq's offer to release women and
children.
   Sept. 27 - Iraq threatens to hang diplomats sheltering
Westerners in their embassy compounds.
   Oct. 29 - Iraq allows all French nationals to leave and 257 fly
home.
   Oct. 31 - President Bush declares: ``I've had it'' with Iraq's
treatment of U.S. hostages.
   Nov. 7 - Washington denounces the procession of Western
politicians to Baghdad seeking the release of hostages.
   Nov. 9 - Former German Chancellor Willy Brandt leaves Baghdad
with 177 hostages.
   Nov. 18 - Iraq offers to release all hostages between Dec. 25
and March 25, the most likely period for an allied attack, ``if
nothing mars the atmosphere of peace.''
   Nov. 19 - A group of 136 hostages, mainly Americans, arrive in
London.
   Nov. 20 - Iraq's parliament says all German hostages can leave.
   Nov. 26 - Moscow accuses Iraq of breaking an agreement to allow
1,000 Soviet citizens in Iraq to leave. Iraq's parliament approves
allowing some 60 Swedish hostages to leave.
   Nov. 28 - Seventy-seven Italians are freed through the
intercession of Melchite Catholic Archbishop Hilarion Capucci.
   Nov. 29 - Soviet Foreign Minister Eduard Shevardnadze warns that
Moscow will not hesitate to use force to protect Soviets trapped in
Iraq.
   Nov. 30 - Iraq releases 80 foreigners, including Swedes,
Britons, Finns and others.
   Dec. 2 - Boxing legend Muhammad Ali leaves Baghdad with 15 U.S.
``human shield'' hostages after meeting Saddam. Iraq also releases
25 Belgians.
   Dec. 4 - Iraq says the remaining 3,232 Soviets in Iraq can go.
   Dec. 5 - A group of 18 American and 24 British women arrive in
Baghdad seeking to persuade the Iraqis to free their husbands.
   Dec. 6 - Saddam asks parliament to approve freeing all remaining
hostages.
   Dec. 7 - Iraqi parliament ratifies Saddam's request, clearing
the way for
   Nov. 20 - Iraq's parliament says all German hostages can leave.
   Nov. 26 - Moscow accuses Iraq of breaking an agreement to allow
1,000 Soviet citizens in Iraq to leave. Iraq's parliament approves
allowing some 60 Swedish hostages to leave.
   Nov. 28 - Seventy-seven Italians are freed through the
intercession of Melchite Catholic Archbishop Hilarion Capucci.
   Nov. 29 - Soviet Foreign Minister Eduard Shevardnadze warns that
Moscow will not hesitate to use force to protect Soviets trapped in
Iraq.
   Nov. 30 - Iraq releases 80 foreigners, including Swedes,
Britons, Finns and others.
   Dec. 2 - Boxing legend Muhammad Ali leaves Baghdad with 15 U.S.
``human shield'' hostages after meeting Saddam. Iraq also releases
25 Belgians.
   Dec. 4 - Iraq says the remaining 3,232 Soviets in Iraq can go.
   Dec. 5 - A group of 18 American and 24 British women arrive in
Baghdad seeking to persuade the Iraqis to free their husbands.
   Dec. 6 - Saddam asks parliament to approve freeing all remaining
hostages.
   Dec. 7 - Iraqi parliament ratifies Saddam's request, clearing
the way for the hostages' release.
   Dec. 8 - About 65 foreigners, including 23 Americans, are
allowed to leave Iraq under earlier arrangements.
   Dec. 9 - About 565 foreigners, including 175 Americans, are
freed under the Iraqi parliamentary decree.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0037 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 1506EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People     12-09 0574</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People,0746</SECOND>
<HEAD>People in the News</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY44</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Bruce Willis says he thinks about suing the
supermarket tabloids every day.
   ``What more could they do to me?'' he asks in an interview in
the January 1991 of Vanity Fair.
   Willis says tabloids have printed things he said in jest as fact
and made up stories, like one about him saving an actress on a
runaway horse.
   ``In that movie, there were no horses,'' Willis said. ``People
say, `Why do you care? It makes you look so good.' But if they can
print that lie, they can just as easily print that I had sex with a
goat. A lie is a lie.''
   Given his feelings about tabloid reporters, Willis was asked why
he agreed to play a tabloid reporter in his newest film, ``The
Bonfire of the Vanities'' -a chacter who is a ruthless, boozy
scavenger of stories.
   ``That's why,'' he replied.
   ---
   BOSTON (AP) - Massachusetts Gov. Michael S. Dukakis wishes
people would miss him when he leaves office next month.
   ``I wish I were going out with people feeling somewhat better
about Mike Dukakis than they do right now,'' the former
presidential candidate said in an interview televised Sunday.
   He went on to say that ``despite the difficulty of the past two
years, this is a lot nicer going out voluntarily than being thrown
out, as happened to me in 1978.''
   That year, Dukakis, the incumbent governor, lost a primary
battle to retain his seat. He later regained the governor's office,
but after losing the presidency in 1988 to George Bush, the state's
economy ebbed and his popularity at home plummeted.
   ``I got close to the top of the mountain, unfortunately,
failed,'' he said. ``It's been an extraordinary time and life for
me.''
   ---
   LONDON (AP) - Former President Reagan ended a five-day visit to
Britain over the weekend that included tea with former Prime
Minister Margaret Thatcher.
   Reagan, 79, left London's Heathrow Airport on Saturday with his
wife, Nancy, aboard a private jet.
   During his stay, Reagan renewed his personal ``special
relationship'' with Mrs. Thatcher over tea and cakes at his London
hotel, and visited her successor, John Major, at No. 10 Downing St.
   The Reagans also had lunch with the Queen and Duke of Edinburgh
at Buckingham Palace. And Reagan addressed the Cambridge University
debating society on its 175th anniversary.
   ---
   SAN ANTONIO (AP) - Michigan Gov.-elect John Engler married Texas
attorney Michelle DeMunbrun in a ceremony attended by about 45
friends and relatives.
   Saturday's marriage is the second for both Engler and his wife.
   ``It was very beautiful,'' said Engler as the two emerged from
St. Matthew's Roman Catholic Church.
   ``I'm very, very happy,'' he added later.
   Engler, 42, and Ms. DeMunbrun, 32, met earlier this year through
one of Engler's staff members and became engaged in August, but
they kept their wedding plans secret until the day after Engler
narrowly defeated incumbent Democrat Gov. James Blanchard on Nov.
6.
   ``We didn't want this to become part of the campaign, part of
the commentary of politics, so we didn't tell anybody,'' Engler
said.
   Only a few family members and partners in Ms. DeMunbrun's
Houston law firm of Nathan, Wood and Sommers were told.
   Most of the guests were members of the bride's family. Engler
has said the couple will spend time with his relatives next week in
Michigan.
   They plan to honeymoon in the spring.
   ---
   APPLETON, Wis. (AP) - A little help from local law enforcement
was all the Hager Twins of ``Hee Haw'' fame needed to create a
traffic jam.
   The look-alike singers known for their years on the long-running
program visited northeastern Wisconsin work on a music video for a
tune called ``I'm Wishin' I Could Go Fishin' Forever.''
   The video, with a classic country theme, starts with Jim and
John Hager in hard hats and work clothes in a pickup truck, stuck
in a traffic jam in Ashland, where traffic jams are uncommon.
   ``We called up the police chief and told him what we were doing,
and that we needed a traffic jam,'' Jim said. ``He said, `What
time?' When we got there, he had the main street blocked off and
cars lined up for the traffic jam. It was wonderful.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0038 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 1601EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Soviet-Rally     12-09 0582</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Rally,0687</SECOND>
<HEAD>Thousands March For Human Rights, Remember Sakharov</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto MOSB1,MOSB3</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BRIAN FRIEDMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Religious chants echoed off the walls of KGB
headquarters Sunday as thousands of human rights demonstrators
prayed and wept at a nearby monument to the victims of Soviet
repression.
   Led by three Russian Orthodox priests bearing icons, marchers
carried wreaths, placards denouncing President Mikhail S.
Gorbachev, and photographs of human rights activist Andrei
Sakharov, who died one year ago this week.
   The 3,000 to 4,000 protesters came from near Red Square where
they had rallied to mark Monday's International Human Rights Day.
They shouted repeatedly for Gorbachev to resign and heard radical
politicians deride him as ``His Majesty, Mikhail the Bloody.''
   The five-hour demonstration reached a more somber climax across
the street from the Lubyanka, the secret police headquarters and
former prison, where a monument has been erected to the millions of
innocents who perished under Communist rule.
   More than 10 million people are believed to have been shot or
died from hunger, cold or hard labor in labor camps under previous
Soviet leaders.
   ``Lord, take the souls of these innocent victims under your
protection,'' a small choir chanted as a priest clad in gold robes
and carrying incense walked around the monument.
   Their requiem, amplified through megaphones, reverberated off
the pink, gray and yellow granite facade of the KGB building.
   The 8-foot-long and 3-foot-wide rock monument, hewn from the
Solovetsky Islands in the White Sea, the site of a famous labor
camp, was dedicated in October.
   Lighted candles flickered in the hands of participants, who
stood stoically around the flower-strewn stone in 23-degree
temperatures as dusk fell. Organizers released dozens of doves,
which circled Dzerzhinsky Square.
   The Rev. Alexei Vlasov, whose branch of the Russian Orthodox
Church was formerly forced to operate underground, told the crowd
of Josef Stalin's repression of the clergy.
   He said the KGB harassed believers and ``the church ceased to
become a sacred place or refuge for people where they could confess
their sins.''
   As he spoke, tears rolled down the cheeks of Lydia Terekhov. Wax
from her candle dripped onto a sign held against her chest. The
sign, with a photograph of her 19-year-old son, Igor, said the
young KGB border guard was killed in Armenia in April.
   Mrs. Terekhov is one of dozens of mothers who have become
fixtures at several anti-government demonstrations in Moscow this
year, protesting the deaths of their sons and demanding the
government explain how they died.
   Other marchers mourned the loss of Sakharov, the Nobel Peace
Prize laureate and father of the Soviet Union's human rights
movement, who died on Dec. 14, 1989.
   ``Nobody can possibly replace Sakharov,'' said Lyudmilla
Kocheyeva when asked whether any current political figure can take
up the late nuclear physicist's role as the nation's conscience.
   ``He has very many supporters and many who follow his path,''
she said, waiting to place her candle on the memorial stone.
   Organizers of the rally sent a delegation of lawmakers to place
a wreath on Sakharov's grave in a southwest Moscow cemetery.
   During earlier speeches to the demonstrators near Red Square,
radicals accused Gorbachev of trampling on the human rights of the
country's many diverse ethnic groups.
   Nikolai Ivanov, who was fired as government prosecutor while
trying to expose corruption, said Gorbachev was a ``czar'' who came
to power by being chosen by 15-20 ``senile Politburo members.''
   ``Today, we can call him `His Majesty, Mikhail the Bloody,'
because for decades, the country hasn't experienced such
bloodshed,'' Ivanov said.
   ``Who bore responsibility for pogroms in Sumgait, Fergana, Baku,
Osh and many other places?'' Ivanov asked, referring to the sites
of recent ethnic violence. ``It's Gorbachev himself who is leading
the country to civil war.
   ``Therefore, if we want to defend human rights, we must unite
around such democratic forces as the Russian parliament, headed by
Boris Nikolayevich Yeltsin,'' he said, referring to the president
of Russia, the largest of the 15 Soviet republics.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0039 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 1615EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-TrampDoll-Protest     12-09 0267</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Tramp Doll-Protest,0321</SECOND>
<HEAD>Toy Store Removes Tramp Doll After Protest by Homeless</HEAD>
<DATELINE>STAMFORD, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A national toy-store chain has stopped
selling ``Steve the Tramp'' dolls after some people and others
picketed outside a mall and complained that the character from Dick
Tracy demeans the homeless.
   The doll, sold by the Walt Disney Co., is described on its
packages as an ``ignorant bum ... dirty and scarred from a life on
the streets. You'll smell him before you see him.''
   A protest Friday by 12 people at the Stamford Town Center
persuaded Kay Bee Toy &amp; Hobby to remove the doll from its 1,200
stores, said Ken Cunniff, vice president of advertising for the
California-based chain.
   ``The character would be fine if it was just an old curmudgeon,
but I think the copy on the package goes too far,'' Cunniff said.
   Homeless people and activists in Stamford organized a protest
against the doll after an Episcopal priest, the Rev. Christopher
Rose of Hartford, put the doll at the top of his annual list of
``Warped Toys for Christmas,'' which he circulates to social action
groups.
   ``I'm homeless, and you don't smell me before you see me,'' said
Carlton Whitehorn, one of the protesters on Friday. ``I'd like to
let Disney know that Jesus Christ was homeless, too.''
   The doll is one of 14 figures of criminals and mobsters inspired
by the movie ``Dick Tracy,'' which was produced by Disney's
Touchstone Pictures.
   The package containing the doll reads: ``Hardened and bitter
after a life on the mean streets, Steve the Tramp is a lout who
would just as soon take your life as your wallet. Despite a low
I.Q., he's as dangerous as they come because he doesn't have
anything to lose.''
   In a statement Friday, the Walt Disney Co. defended the toy as
``not intended in any way to represent the homeless.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0040 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 1624EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-HostageStories     12-09 0351</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Hostage Stories,0425</SECOND>
<HEAD>Freed Americans Tell of Fear, Frustration in Occupied Kuwait</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf-Iraq, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BAGHDAD, Iraq (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Some of the Americans freed by the Baghdad
government on Sunday had spent four months hiding from Iraqi
occupation authorities in Kuwait, living by their wits and by the
kindness of Kuwaiti friends.
   Thomas Kreuzman, 38, of Holiday, Fla., who was a contractor in
Kuwait before the Aug. 2 invasion, said he spent 23 days hiding in
an air-conditioning duct with his dog. They lived on dry spaghetti
and sneaked out at night for water, he said.
   About 80 Americans flew from Kuwait to Baghdad Sunday, later
joining a group of about 175 Americans who left the Iraqi capital
for Frankfurt, Germany.
   They spoke to reporters at the Baghdad airport.
   Lyonell Hoffman, 51, of Melbourne, Fla., who was also contractor
in Kuwait, said he hid out in an apartment complex.
   ``I am stunned and still cannot believe it, it seems like a
miracle,'' he said of his release.
   The departing Americans described the systematic looting of the
small, wealthy emirate that had been their home.
   ``It was not an invasion, it was robbery,'' said Kreuzman. ``All
that wasn't tied down was taken away.''
   The Iraqi occupation authorities threatened Kuwaitis who
sheltered foreigners with death. But the Americans said Kuwaitis
repeatedly risked their lives to help them.
   ``I feel guilty for leaving my Kuwaiti friends behind,'' said
Kreuzman.
   Several of the Americans said they had heard gunfire in the city
every night since the invasion - including their last night there,
Saturday.
   Some of the hostages who were detained in Iraq celebrated their
last night in the country with a party at the downtown Al-Mansour
Melia, which was known as the ``hostage hotel'' because many were
held there.
   One American who was held in Iraq said now that he was free, he
wanted to go to Kuwait, not to the United States. Dr. Clem J. Hall
of Newark, N.J., said he wanted to go back to the emirate for his
Yugoslav girlfriend.
   Thousands of Westerners were stranded by Iraq's invasion of
Kuwait, and Iraqi President Saddam Hussein refused to let them
leave.
   In recent months, Saddam had freed hostages on a piecemeal
basis, sometimes in large groups, and sometimes after a foreign
dignitary made an appeal on their behalf.
   On Thursday, he announced he was ready to free all foreigners,
and the decree was approved by the Iraqi parliament on Friday.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0041 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 1633EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Yugoslavia-Elections 1stLd-Writethru a06 12-09 0673</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Yugoslavia-Elections, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0681,0769</SECOND>
<HEAD>Two Yugoslav Republics Hold Key Elections; Vote-Rigging Alleged</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS thruout to UPDATE with boycott by ethnic Albanians,
further claims by Draskovic; no pickup</NOTE>
<HEAD>With AM-Poland-Election, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TONY MITH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BELGRADE, Yugoslavia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Opposition candidates accused the
government of cheating Sunday as the two Communist-ruled republics
held elections that could decide whether Yugoslavia remains united.
   In Serbia, the country's largest republic, the top nationalist
party said it might not accept the election results. The Serbian
Renewal Movement accused the ruling Socialists of permitting
illegal voting, and most ethnic Albanians boycotted the election.
   The Socialists - formerly Communists - faced an array of
center-right nationalists in Serbia's first free elections in more
than 50 years.
   In Montenegro, the smallest republic, 10 parties were
challenging the ruling Marxists.
   Polling stations in both republics opened at 7 a.m. (1 a.m. EST)
and were closing 12 hours later. Results were expected late Monday
at the earliest.
   The outcome in Serbia could shape the entire country's future.
The nationalist Serbian Renewal Movement, led by novelist Vuk
Draskovic, wants to establish free-market capitalism and return the
republic to its once-dominant role in the Yugoslav federation.
   The western states of Croatia and Slovenia, where center-right
parties replaced Communists in spring elections, want more
independence from the federation and have threatened to secede.
   Serbia's current Socialist leader, Slobodan Milosevic, has
refused to discuss the possibility of secession with Slovenia and
Croatia.
   Draskovic, his opponent, says he wants to keep the country whole
but is prepared to negotiate with other republics that favor
separation or confederation.
   Observers say the tensions between Serbia and the Slovenes and
Croats could increase if Milosevic is kept in power, while a
Draskovic presidency could reduce tensions.
   In Montenegro, the ruling Marxists also oppose independence for
Slovenia and Croatia.
   The conflict is only one of many based on ethnic and political
differences among Yugoslavia's six constituent states and two
provinces. The CIA has predicted that the country could break up
within 18 months and has warned of the possibility of civil war.
   Serbian voters were also choosing a 250-member parliament from
among 44 vying parties.
   Draskovic accused the government of allowing some voters to cast
their ballots on Saturday. He said his party protested the alleged
illegality to the electoral commission, but the complaint was
rejected.
   He also claimed envelopes containing mailed-in votes from
soldiers were not sealed and could be tampered with.
   ``If we ascertain that the vote-rigging on Saturday was massive,
we will not recognize the elections,'' Draskovic said. ``Communists
don't know a thing about honesty. They are capable of doing
anything to stay in power.''
   Socialist officials said only a small number of people, mainly
disabled persons and those who had proof they had to be away on
business Sunday, were allowed to vote on Saturday.
   Opposition leaders also claimed the Socialists stopped
registering deaths in Serbia in April, and planned to rig the
election by claiming phantom votes.
   Pre-election polls gave Communists a slight lead over
Draskovic's party. But they also showed that nearly 40 percent of
the 6,865,445 eligible voters were undecided.
   Runoff elections in districts where the leader fails to get at
least 50 percent of the votes are slated for Dec. 23.
   In Kosovo, a semi-autonomous region of Serbia, ethnic Albanians
said they were boycotting the voting to protest direct Serbian rule
that was imposed over the summer when Kosovo's parliament declared
the region's sovereignty.
   People of Albanian origins make up 90 percent of Kosovo's
population of two million.
   ``We have asked our people to stay at home,'' said Ibrahim
Rugova, leader of the Democratic League of Kosovo, which is not
recognized by Serbian authorities and is not fielding candidates
Sunday.
   ``Serbian police control continues ... if we accept the
elections, we accept the suspension of autonomy,'' he said.
   In the Kosovo town of Glogovac, only 13 of 25,000 registered
voters turned out and they were all Serbs, the state news agency
Tanjug reported. Ethnic Albanians account for about 750,000 of the
province's estimated 950,000 eligible voters.
   ``There were hardly any Albanians on the streets today,'' said
Jusuf Buxhovi, an official of the Democratic League.
   In the earlier crackdown, authorities closed the Kosovo assembly
and forced Albanian-language media to stop publishing. Rugova said
thousands of ethnic Albanians were sacked from state jobs.
   Serbia's new constitution allows its leaders to decide whether
Kosovo and the republic's second autonomous region, Vojvodina,
should have self-rule.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0042 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 1646EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Israel 2nd-Writethru a0719 12-09 0645</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel, 2nd-Writethru, a0719,0786</SECOND>
<HEAD>Israeli Soldier Killed When Bombs Explode</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 20 grafs for 4-18 bgng `Two homemade...' to ADD details
of bombing; statement warning of more violence; CORRECTS death toll
to ADD soldier's death Sunday; no pickup</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto JRL1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KARIN LAUB</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An Israeli soldier was killed and two were
wounded when bombs exploded outside military headquarters in the
occupied town of Bethlehem on Sunday, the third anniversary of the
Palestinian uprising.
   In other violence, an Arab was fatally shot as he tried to
strangle an Israeli policeman and grab his rifle Sunday, the army
said. Relatives said he was shot while standing at the door of his
home.
   Soldiers also clashed with masked youths in the West Bank
village of Bani Naim, shooting one protester in the leg, the army
said.
   Two homemade bombs went off in the West Bank town of Bethlehem
early Sunday evening as an army patrol passed the gate of the
military base along the Jerusalem-Bethlehem highway, the army said.
   Troops clamped a curfew on Bethlehem and surrounding villages,
erected roadblocks, and searched for suspects in the area, the army
said.
   Israel army radio said six paratroopers were walking along the
highway in a routine patrol when the first bomb exploded.
   The patrol checked out the explosion, found nothing and
continued walking, the report said. After the soldiers had walked
another 30 yards, the second bomb went off, wounding three
soldiers.
   One of the soldiers suffered critical head injuries and died in
the emergency room of Hadassah Hospital in Jerusalem, said hospital
spokeswoman Ruth Mekel. The two other soldiers were slightly hurt.
   The death brought to 10 the number of Israeli soldiers killed
during the uprising, the army said.
   Curfews confined more than a million Arabs to their homes in the
occupied territories, some for the third straight day, in an army
effort to quell violence on the anniversary of the intefadeh, or
uprising.
   ``At the moment, we have beefed up forces, and increased
patrols, lookouts and roadblocks,'' said a lieutenant enforcing the
curfew on the Dheisheh refugee camp in the occupied West Bank.
   Soldiers fired at stone-throwers breaking the curfew in the Gaza
Strip village of Beni Suhaila, wounding 25-year-old Muhamad Mardi
al-Madani in the right thigh, Arab reports said.
   Relatives said Al-Madani was hit as he stood at the door of his
house. Hospital officials said the bullet severed Al-Madani's
artery and he bled to death. The army also confirmed he had died.
   But the army said he attacked a member of the paramilitary
border police, trying to strangle the officer and take his rifle.
It said the Israeli was slightly injured in the melee by a
ricocheting bullet.
   Sunday's violence brought to 777 the number of Palestinians
killed by Israelis during the uprising and to 54 the number of
Israelis who have died in the violence. Another 316 Palestinians
have been killed by fellow Arabs, most on suspicion of helping
Israel, since the uprising began Dec. 9, 1987.
   The army curfews coincided with a general strike called by
uprising leaders to mark the anniversary. Virtually all shops and
schools and traffic were idle.
   Slogans on walls near Manger Square in nearby Bethlehem called
for 1991 to be ``the year of destroying the enemy.'' They were
signed by the Popular Front for the Liberation of Palestine, a
Marxist faction of the Palestine Liberation Organization.
   Another slogan signed by the fundamentalist group Islamic Jihad
said: ``The language of stones, knives, and bullets is the only
language the enemy will understand.''
   Army radio reported that only Jewish settlers and army patrols
were seen driving in the occupied territories.
   Large sections of the West Bank, including such principal cities
as Nablus and Hebron, as well as virtually all of the Gaza Strip,
were under curfew for the third straight day.
   Masked activists in the Dheisheh refugee camp defied the curfew
Saturday night and marched through the alleys carrying Palestinian
flags, Arab reports said.
   Two jailed Palestinian leaders and a left-wing Israeli
legislator issued a joint statement Sunday saying violence on both
sides will increase if the peace process remains deadlocked.
   ``We are deeply concerned that if negotiations between Israel
and the Palestinians will not start soon, both peoples will find
themselves in a very tragic situation of deterioration manifested
by terror and oppression,'' said the statement.
   The statement was issued by Yossi Sarid of the Citizens Rights
Movement and Palestinian journalists Radwan Abu Ayyash and Ziad Abu
Ziad. The two Palestinians have been jailed by Israel for six
months without trial.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0043 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 1651EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Thailand     12-09 0402</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Thailand,0442</SECOND>
<HEAD>Prime Minister Returns to Power One Day After Resignation</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BANGKOK, Thailand (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Chatichai Choonhavan was renamed prime
minister Sunday, one day after he resigned amid increasing
criticism of his government.
   The maneuver Saturday was apparently an attempt to revamp his
Cabinet.
   King Bhumibol Adulyadej signed a royal decree reinstating
Chatichai as prime minister, Channel 7 television reported.
   Chatichai, 68, a former army general, told reporters Sunday that
he had not been pressured by the military into resigning. He said
he has been in close contact with military leaders.
   All the Cabinet ministers automatically lost their positions
with the prime minister's resignation Saturday. Chatichai now will
choose a new Cabinet, but it remained to be seen whether he would
drop members who had been sharply criticized by the powerful
military.
   There have been increasing attacks on Chatichai's squabbling
seven-party coalition for corruption, ineptitude and internal
squabbling.
   The former Cabinet is continuing to serve in a caretaker
capacity.
   Chatichai, who came to power in August 1988, is the first prime
minister since 1976 to be an elected member of the Parliament.
   The generally popular prime minister has proved a skillful
political player, especially in neutralizing the military, which
for decades intervened by force. But the military has also insisted
on being a ``watchdog'' over state and society.
   Criticism mounted in recent months, with critics pointing to
allegedly massive corruption within the highest levels of his
government and parties within the coalition. Some have also
complained of the government's poor record of helping the country's
poor while allowing entrepreneurs free rein.
   Recently pamphlets have circulated that accuse Chatichai and his
family of corrupt dealings and nepotism.
   Army Chief Gen. Suchinda Kapayoon, armed forces chief Gen.
Sunthorn Kongsompong and others have made tough statements and
threats in recent months.
   Their focus has been on corruption and certain Cabinet members
including Interior Minister Banharn Silapa-Archa, Communications
Minister Montri Pongpanich and Deputy Minister of Education Chalerm
Yumbamrung.
   anharn is secretary-general of Chatichai's own Chart Thai
Party, and Montri holds the same post with the Social Action Party.
   The outspoken Chalerm had angered the military by criticizing
its seizure in June of a government-owned radio truck that officers
said was eavesdropping on military communications.
   There was a major Cabinet shuffle on Aug. 27, but military
commanders demanded even more changes and threatened unspecified
intervention if Chalerm and others were not ousted.
   Another change came Nov. 22, but proved minor. Chalerm, who had
been a minister in the prime minister's office, was merely demoted
to the education ministry slot.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0044 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 1656EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Poland-WalesaProfile     12-09 0561</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Poland-Walesa Profile,0693</SECOND>
<HEAD>From Peasant Hut to President's Palace</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Poland-Election, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DRUSILLA MENAKER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WARSAW, Poland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Lech Walesa. Looking at the
peasant's son, seeing the hut in the potato field where he was
born, recalling Poland's last four decades of communism, the title
would not seem possible.
   But then, this is Lech Walesa.
   Love him or fear him, he epitomizes the contradictory forces
that led Poland out of communism and forever changed the East-West
equation.
   He has uncanny political intuition and personal courage, and he
wants to take the future of his country into his hands. He is
devoutly Catholic and disinterested in the trappings of power or
prestige.
   With workers and rulers alike, he woos with his greatest asset:
He is always himself.
   That includes saying one thing in the morning and another at
night, and then warning others not to pay too much attention to
either ``Walesa.'' He frequently refers to himself in the third
person.
   His charisma edges toward egotism, his self-confidence toward
the autocratic. As fervently as he has fought for democracy, he
believes he ``must reserve my own voice as the final one.''
   That voice comes from a mud-and-marsh hamlet northwest of Warsaw
where in 1943, as World War II raged across the Polish flatlands,
Walesa was born in a tiny three-room hut. The road leading to it is
unpaved to this day.
   Walesa's father died in 1945, his health ruined by forced labor
under the German occupiers, and his mother married her late
husband's brother a year later. With too little land to survive,
the impoverished clan rented out the boys to work for other farmers
and sent young Lech to learn tractor repair at a local trade
school.
   It was not until 1967 that the 24-year-old Walesa, out of the
army and depressed by a broken love affair, sensed time was
wasting. He left home for Gdansk.
   Working at the Lenin Shipyard, a showpiece of People's Poland,
Walesa's life was changed in 1970 by Christmas food strikes during
which dozens of laborers were killed by security forces.
   Already angry about poor working conditions, he was chosen to
lead the shipyard strike committee. Walesa was dismissed in 1976
for criticizing the yard's Communist union, and he began organizing
underground free unions.
   In August 1980, he made his famous jump over the shipyard fence
to lead the strike that gave birth to the East bloc's first free
trade union.
   Martial law ended Solidarity's rocky 15-month existence, and
Walesa was imprisoned until November 1982.
   He received the Nobel Peace Prize the following year but because
he was afraid to leave the country, it was accepted by his wife,
Danuta.
   Walesa vowed that Solidarity would survive underground, and
after strikes in 1988 the union re-emerged as Poland's main
political force.
   Walesa forced the Communist Party to the negotiating table and,
finally, to the dismay of skeptical allies, to give up power. He
picked Tadeusz Mazowiecki as the East bloc's first non-Communist
government leader and then watche from Gdansk as revolution swept
Eastern Europe.
   Last spring, Walesa started to agitate again, this time to
remove a nagging vestige of the old regime - President Wojciech
Jaruzelski - and speed up reforms to stave off popular unrest.
   At first his allies in the government shook their heads, but
soon it was evident that, again, Walesa was onto something. They
began talking about ``acceleration'' too.
   Within months, Jaruzelski announced an early end to his term,
and the first fully democratic nationwide elections in five decades
were scheduled to pick a new occupant for Belweder Palace.
   But Mazowiecki, regarding Walesa's campaign as a rejection of
his own cautious-but-determined path, refused to bow to his
political sponsor and decided to oppose him for president.
   Their bitter falling out created a split in Solidarity that is
bound to linger after the election.
   Walesa seems sorry, but ready to move on.
   ``I am playing as a chess player, five or six moves ahead,'' he
said recently.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0045 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 1656EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Soviet-Lithuania     12-09 0187</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Lithuania,0190</SECOND>
<HEAD>Independent Lithuanian Communist Party Adopts New Name</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Independent Communist Party of Lithuania,
which broke ranks with the Kremlin last year, has renamed itself
the Democratic Labor Party, the official Tass news agency reported
Sunday.
   The party was formed in December 1989 after a split in the
200,000-member Lithuanian Communist Party, with one side remaining
loyal to Moscow and the other reorganizing along social democratic
lines.
   The new Democratic Labor Party has 56,000 members, the official
Soviet news agency said. A weekend convention of 550 delegates in
the Lithuanian capital of Vilnius voted to drop the word
``Communist'' and adopt the new name, Tass said.
   Party leader Algirdas Brazauskas, who is also Lithuania's deputy
prime minister, has been nominated to the new post of party
chairman, it said.
   Lithuania declared its independence from the Soviet Union in
March. Its leadership, along with that of its Baltic neighbors,
Latvia and Estonia, has said it will not sign a Union Treaty
proposed by Soviet President Mikhail S. Gorbachev. The treaty would
preserve the unity of the 15 Soviet republics under strong central
control.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0046 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 1658EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Salvador-Jesuits     12-09 0394</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Salvador-Jesuits,0455</SECOND>
<HEAD>Archbishop: Masterminds of Jesuit Massacre May Never Be Charged</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARCOS ALEMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN SALVADOR, El Salvador (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A judge's decision to close the
investigation into the massacre of six Jesuit priests could mean
the masterminds will never be punished, a Roman Catholic archbishop
said Sunday.
   ``There was not just one mastermind, there are more,'' Monsignor
Arturo Rivera Damas, the archbishop of San Salvador, told reporters
after Sunday Mass.
   Judge Ricardo Zamora on Friday closed his investigation into the
Nov. 16, 1989, murders of six Jesuit priest-professors, their
housekeeper and her 15-year-old daughter.
   He ordered Col. Guillermo Benavides, three lieutenants and four
soldiers to stand trial.
   Judicial sources say closing the investigation makes it highly
unlikely anyone else will be prosecuted for the crime.
   The Jesuits, Roman Catholic leaders and members of the U.S.
Congress who have been monitoring the inquiry contend Benavides is
not the only one behind the killings.
   Rep. Joe Moakley. D-Mass., and the Rev. Jose Maria Tojeira, head
of the Jesuits in Central America, have accused members of the
Salvadoran army command of obstructing the investigation, covering
up evidence and lying to the judge.
   Tojeira said the United States and the armed forces had
pressured the judge into closing his inquiry before anyone else was
implicated. Benavides, he said, acted at the behest of ``a powerful
group within the armed forces.''
   Rivera Damas said everyone involved in the massacre should be
brought to justice. He said moving the case into the trial phase
``is an error because there are others who should also be
punished.''
   ``I think the (Jesuits are) right to disagree with the judge's
decision. I disagree, too,'' Rivera Damas said.
   Benavides is the highest-ranking Salvadoran officer ever charged
with a human rights crime.
   No officer has been convicted of a human rights crime throughout
a decade of civil war in which human rights groups estimate that
30,000 people died at the hands of death squads linked to the
military and the right-wing.
   The Jesuit case has put U.S. policy in El Salvador in the
spotlight.
   Critics say Washington, which has poured billions of dollars
into El Salvador since the war with leftist rebels began in 1980,
has tolerated massive human rights abuses by the armed forces.
   The far right, including many army officers, despised the
Jesuits for their support for a negotiated end to the war and their
belief that it stemmed from repression, poverty and injustice
rather than an international communist conspiracy.
   Two of the lieutenants accused in the case have testified that
Benavides ordered the slayings and the elimination of any
witnesses. Benavides denies the charges.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0047 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 1658EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Europe-Snow     12-09 0354</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Europe-Snow,0406</SECOND>
<HEAD>Heavy Snow Hits France, Spain, Switzerland</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SUE LEEMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Storms dumped heavy snow Sunday in Western Europe,
knocking out services in parts of France, Spain and Switzerland.
Seven people were reported dead from an earlier blizzard in Britain
and Northern Ireland.
   ``Winter has come with a vengeance,'' said a spokesman for the
London Weather Center. ``Conditions are going to be quite nasty.''
   Police said at least four people have died in the freezing
conditions and snow that hit much of northern and central England
on Saturday. Three more died on roads in Northern Ireland, which
was battered by gale force winds, they said.
   Snow and ice made many British roads impassable Sunday, major
rail services were cut and hundreds of thousands of homes were
without electricity and water supplies. Helicopters rescued drivers
stranded along roadways in sub-freezing temperatures.
   In central France, the first winter snow cut electricity and
made driving hazardous. High winds and rain swept the Cote d'Azur
and the French Mediterranean island of Corsica, officials said.
   Heavy snowfalls in northern Spain forced traffic officials to
close dozens of mountain passes.
   Snow in Tessin state in southern Switzerland closed Lugano
airport and disrupted rail traffic, local officials said.
   The London Weather Center spokesman said the cold front that had
dumped snow on France was moving across Belgium and heading for
southeast England, bringing icy winds from the Arctic and ``a
packet of snow.''
   British weathermen predicted more snow for northern and central
England and said icy winds from Europe could extend the arctic
freeze to the southeast.
   Police in County Durham in the north said helicopters had
rescued more than 274 drivers trapped in their cars on a major
route across the Pennine mountain range.
   A helicopter with a paramedic on board set down at the snowbound
Oxfordshire home of Foreign Secretary Douglas Hurd to pick up his
7-year-old son, Philip, and take him to a hospital for treatment of
suspected appendicitis.
   The British army was called out late Saturday to help utility
workers in the Midlands repair power lines cuts that have left half
a million people without power, some for more than 24 hours.
   In Yorkshire in northern England, about 200,000 people were
without electricity, utility companies said. Power supplies to
homes in Leicestershire and Oxfordshire were also hit, said local
officials.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0048 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 1718EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Bangladesh-Ershad     12-09 0365</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bangladesh-Ershad,0416</SECOND>
<HEAD>Caretaker Government Explores Sending Ershad Into Exile</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ARTHUR MAX</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DHAKA, Bangladesh (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The 3-day-old caretaker government is
considering sending ousted President Hussain Muhammad Ershad into
exile, politicians said Sunday.
   The major opposition parties demanded on Friday, one day after
Ershad left office, that the ex-president be tried on charges of
corruption and misusing power during his eight-year rule.
   But Shahabuddin Ahmed, the caretaker president, has approached
the party blocs for their reaction to the idea of letting Ershad
leave the country, a political source said on condition of
anonymity.
   The public response from the main political alliances was
negative.
   Ershad, a former general who seized power in 1982, resigned
following a seven-week campaign for his ouster led by university
students and the opposition political parties.
   He remained secluded in his well-guarded home Sunday. Several
other members of his government were in hiding, fearing they might
be attacked if they appear in public.
   Sheik Hasina, head of the Awami League, reacted cautiously to
the suggestion of sending the president into exile. ``The man or
institution which has done the wrong thing must get punishment. But
it must be by law,'' she told foreign reporters.
   When pressed about Ershad's case, however, she added: ``If he
leaves the country, at least our people will be relieved.''
   Khaleda Zia, leader of the Bangladesh Nationlist Party, insisted
on prosecuting the deposed president.
   ``There should be charges against him. The interim government
should start (the procedings). It should arrest him,'' said Mrs.
Zia in an interview.
   ``I don't think the people will allow it,'' she said when asked
if Ershad should be exiled.
   Shahabuddin, the former chief justice of the Supreme Court, has
said his job as acting president is to maintain law and order and
set up elections. He said he would take no major policy decisions.
   Moudud Ahmed, Ershad's vice president, accused the political
groups of pushing for immediate trials to block Ershad's Jatiya
Party from contesting the elections.
   ``I don't mind facing charges if there is a fair trial on
specific charges. But not if it is to intimidate,'' he told a
reporter at his luxurious Dhaka home. ``I believe this is being
done for political purposes.''
   Moudud also said corruption trials should be extended to civil
servants and to members of previous administrations that governed
Bangladesh after it won independence from Pakistan in 1971.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0049 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 1724EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Obit-Alexander     12-09 0334</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Alexander,0387</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tenor John Alexander Dies Aged 67</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MERIDIAN, Miss. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   John Alexander, a tenor with the
Metropolitan Opera for 27 years who was renowned for his
interpretation of 19th-century bel canto roles, died of a heart
attack, authorities said Sunday. He was 67.
   Alexander collapsed Saturday evening at the Temple Theater in
his hometown of Meridian and was taken to Jeff Anderson Regional
Medical Center where he was pronounced dead of a massive heart
attack, said Lauderdale County Medical Examiner Marl Cobler.
   Alexander recently retired after 27 years as a leading tenor
with New York's Metropolitan Opera. He was an Opera Hall of Fame
member who had performed with orchestras worldwide.
   Alexander was the first American-born tenor to establish a
worldwide reputation for his masterful interpretation of
19th-century bel canto roles, a style of singing that is
characterized by brilliant vocal display and purity of tone and
most often associated with Italian artists.
   ``John was a first-class artist and absolute gentlemen at all
times,'' said Franklin Choset, former artistic director and general
manager of the Mississippi Opera. ``In our profession, that is a
lot more than can be said about people of all his stature.
   ``It's a loss for the entire opera world and I extend my
sympathies to John's family,'' Choset said from his home in Tel
Aviv, Israel.
   Alexander was among a group of artists from Meridian performing
for about 1,500 people at the Centennial Pops celebration, a
fund-raiser for the Grand Opera House.
   Other featured artists included baritone Julian Patrick, soprano
Gail Robinson and baritone Andrew Gainey, all former Meridian
residents known to audiences of the New York City and Metropolitan
opera companies.
   ``He was one of the nicest, warmest and most generous
colleagues,'' Patrick said in a statement. ``He was one of the most
Christian men you could hope to know. We were old, old friends.''
   Alexander trained at the Cincinnati Conservatory after
pre-medical studies at Duke University and service with the U.S.
Air Force. His most influential teacher was the baritone Robert
Weede. In 1952, he made his debut as Faust with the Cincinnati
Opera.
   Five years later, he joined the New York City Opera as Alfredo.
In 1961, he became a member of the Metropolitan Opera as Ferrando.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0050 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 1739EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-TankRampage     12-09 0274</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Tank Rampage,0332</SECOND>
<HEAD>Drunk Soldier Drives Home - In a Tank</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto VIE4</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GEORGE JAHN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>VIENNA, Austria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Police thought they had made the streets
safer by taking away Gregor Hajek's driver's license. But the
29-year-old soldier was back on Vienna streets hours later Sunday -
with a tank.
   ``I wanted to go home,'' Hajek told police shortly after
climbing out of the M60 tank following a 35-mile drive from a town
south of Vienna that ended near his parents home in the Austrian
capital.
   Police said the man had been charged with resisting state
authority and numerous traffic violations. Resisting state
authority carries a maximum penalty of five years in prison.
   En route the driver had tried to ram one squad car attempting to
stop him, ignored several warnings to stop, and drove through a
series of red lights. A police car, siren wailing to warn other
drivers, had followed the tank on the last part of the journey.
   Police said the drama began late Saturday and gave the following
account:
   Hajek's car was stopped for a routine check and police decided
he was drunk. They took his license and drove him back to his
barracks in the village of Zwoelfaxing, south of Vienna.
   Hajek, however, had access to the keys of his M60 tank. Guards
heard a tank starting up shortly after midnight but were unable to
stop the vehicle, which crashed through locked gates and headed
down the freeway toward Vienna.
   Two officers tried to stop the vehicle shortly after it entered
city limits but got out of the way when the tank charged toward
them.
   ``Further attempts to stop him also were in vain,'' a police
report said.
   The tank, which moved at 30 mph, finally stopped on the street
where Hajek's parents live.
   ``So he actually almost did make it home,'' a police spokesman
said dryly. He spoke on condition of anonymity.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0051 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 1744EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Bush     12-09 0189</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bush,180</SECOND>
<HEAD>President Skips `Christmas in Washington' Taping</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An exhausted President Bush stayed home Sunday
night, skipping plans to a attend a Christmas celebration.
   Bush returned Saturday from a weeklong trek through South
America, his third foreign journey in as many weeks. He looked
drawn Sunday morning at a church service, his only public
appearance.
   With the capital enjoying Indian summer-like weather, Bush spent
the afternoon on the White House tennis court, and the exercise
left him ``a little under the weather afterwards,'' John Herrick, a
White House press aide, said. ``He's just feeling a little
exhausted.''
   Bush cancelled plans to attend the taping of a gala ``Christmas
in Washington'' television show at the Pension Building. First lady
Barbara Bush, who passed up the five-nation South American trip,
went without him.
   Bush has a full schedule Monday, including meetings with
President Vytautas Lansbergis of Lithuania and Defense Secretary
Dick Cheney, and a Christmas ball at the White House in the evening
for members of Congress.
   That will kick off a string of eight Christmas parties the
Bushes will host over the next two weeks for several thousand
guests.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0052 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 1746EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r e BC-Opera     12-09 0278</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Opera,0334</SECOND>
<HEAD>Martinucci Excites as Chenier at Met</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: No PMs planned.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By MARY CAMPBELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Nicola Martinucci excited the audience in the
title role of the Metropolitan Opera's first ``Andrea Chenier'' of
the season.
   It is the only role the Italian tenor is singing at the Met this
season.
   Aprile Millo and Sherrill Milnes, also starring, were in top
form Saturday as was conductor Julius Rudel and the Metropolitan
Opera orchestra and chorus.
   Martinucci sang with round, open tones, ringing on top. Much of
the music in this Giordano opera, set in the French Revolution, is
impassioned.
   Martinucci sang it with strong passion. After both his big Act 1
aria and first duet with Millo, applause was sustained. He sounded
a little tired in the last two acts but his singing was still
eloquent and his top notes continued to ring out heroically.
   There is lovely, lush music in ``Andrea Chenier,'' which seems
to be a more popular opera in Europe than America. The Met last
performed it in 1976-77.
   Maddalena, daughter of a countess, falls in love with Andrea
Chenier, a poet. Gerard, a servant in her house, is in love with
her. He waffles about getting Chenier out of the way by denouncing
him; Milnes sings his big aria in a bright, warm voice. He finally
testifies in Chenier's favor at his trial. But Chenier is sent to
the guillotine anyway. Maddalena goes with him.
   Millo sang with a lush tone, while the orchestra's melody
swelled beneath her voice. And she held some ravishing high
pianissimos and, when appropriate, sang with a sweetly pensive
tone.
   Andrea Velis sang an appropriately weasily spy. The third act
aria for the blind woman, giving her young grandson to be a
soldier, is written to pull the heartstrings and Camellia Johnson
presented it effectively.
   It is the first set designed by Austrian Wolfram Skalicki at the
Met.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0053 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 1751EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-MysteryWomen     12-09 0557</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mystery Women,0671</SECOND>
<HEAD>Female Mystery Writers Show Crime Makes No Gender Distinctions</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By STEPHANIE SCHOROW</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CAMBRIDGE, Mass. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   They've gotten away with murder, but
only on the pages of their books.
   Boston-based mystery writers Linda Barnes, Susan Kelly, Jane
Langton and Katherine Hall Page are among the women who continue to
make inroads in the territory carved out by Arthur Conan Doyle and
Raymond Chandler, among others.
   Moreover, their protagonists - whether amateurs puzzled by the
death of a friend or full-fledged private detectives - are named
Liz or Carlotta, instead of Sam or Sherlock.
   ``Women mystery writers are getting more attention,'' said Kate
Mattes, owner of Kate's Mystery Books in Cambridge. ``They go into
areas that men can't.''
   Over the weekend, a number of New England-based mystery writers
gathered at Kate's to greet fans and compare notes on murder and
mayhem.
   Hot-pink copies of Barnes' latest Carlotta Carlyle mystery,
``Coyote,'' were thrust at the author for autographs - which
pleased the writer who was once told by her publisher that writing
a mystery with a female detective ``would be death.''
   Barnes, an established author of the ``Michael Spraggue''
series, said: ``There were no detectives at that time that behaved
the way I felt a real woman would.''
   After a short story featuring Carlotta - a 6-foot, redheaded,
part-time cabbie and part-time private eye - proved to be a hit,
three novels followed.
   Barnes sees no limit to the public appetite for female
detectives.
   ``That's a question that Tony Hillerman or Robert Parker doesn't
have to answer,'' she said, referring to two well-known mystery
writers. ``Most mystery fans read a lot of books. I can't write a
book a day. But many of my readers read a book a day.''
   Cambridge-based author Kelly says female detectives are
overcoming credibility problems with male readers, and publishers,
who once couldn't believe a woman could handle a gun or peer into
the twisted canyons of a psychopath's mind.
   Kelly's creation, Liz Connors, is a free-lance crime writer who
lives in Cambridge. ``Until Proven Innocent'' is her latest
adventure.
   Liz is a tough customer, who can handle herself in a
life-and-death situation, thanks to creator Kelly who has taught
police-report writing at police academies and counts a forensic
pathologist among her frequent dinner guests.
   But not all female mystery writers have female protagonists.
   Langton of Lincoln writes meticulously researched mysteries
often set in well-known New England locations, such as ``Murder at
the Gardner,'' set in the Isabella Stewart Gardner Museum.
   A soft-spoken lady with gray hair, she shudders when asked about
how she likes murdering her victims, saying earnestly: ``I'm a
terribly nice lady. I like solving some puzzles. I hate to bother
with real, actual police work.''
   An upcoming book will feature a battle between developers and
conservationists, she said.
   Page's feisty culinary expert Faith Sibley Fairchild is a
minister's wife, with a baby in tow, who begins to solve mysteries
to fight housebound boredom. In ``The Body in the Kelp,'' she finds
clues in a family quilt.
   Susan Conant, who also trains dogs, has developed Holly Winter,
a dog trainer who finds herself tracking down killers in ``A New
Leash on Death'' and ``Dead and Doggone,'' both aimed at dog lovers
and mystery fans.
   ``As a mystery reader, I found myself reading mysteries by women
written with strong women characters,'' she said. ``To a certain
extent, I like to write those books I like to read.''
   If there is any pattern to female detective fiction, it is that
while male hard-boiled detectives are loners, even single female
detectives ``have some kind of family around them, although it's
not a traditional husband and kids,'' Barnes said.
   ``It's more the way that women live, that friendships are
important,'' she said. ``Carlotta is not concerned with justice as
maintaining relationships. She's concerned about what's going to
happen after the books end.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0054 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 1810EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Chad     12-09 0347</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Chad,0394</SECOND>
<HEAD>Troops Dismantle Camp of Former Libyan POWs</HEAD>
<DATELINE>AM SENENE, Chad (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Troops of the new government Sunday began
dismantling a well-armed camp allegedly used by U.S.-trained Libyan
war prisoners to destabilize Libyan ruler Col. Moammar Gadhafi, a
French report said.
   Agence France-Presse, a news service, reported the camp about
six miles north of the capital of N'Djamena was well-stocked with
Soviet-made weaponry and other arms and communications equipment.
   The United States evacuated about 600 Libyan POWs from Chad to
Nigeria on Friday and Saturday after Idriss Deby's rebel forces
toppled President Hissene Habre earlier this month. Deby is now
interim president.
   Other former POWs returned to Libya, which helped arm Deby's
fighters.
   But the U.S. ambassador to Chad, Richard Bogosian, has declined
to comment on news reports that the soldiers were trained by U.S.
military advisers for commando operations against Libya. The AFP
report referred to the former POWs as ``Libyan Contras.''
   Chadian forces captured the Libyan fighters in clashes in 1983
and 1987. Chad and Libya have been battling periodically in a
border dispute for more than 20 years.
   The camp, surrounded by six-foot walls topped with barbed wire,
contained Soviet anti-tank missiles, sophisticated radio equipment
and about 300 Toyota all-terrain vehicles as well as some mounted
canons, the French news agency reported.
   The camp had been guarded by French marines since the POWs were
evacuated, AFP reported.
   Also Sunday, Libya's foreign minister met with Nigerian
President Gen. Ibrahim Babangida in efforts to return the rest of
the former POWs to Libya, the official Libyan news agency JANA
reported.
   After the meeting in Lagos, Nigeria, Foreign Minister Ibrahim
Bashari of Libya said of the evacuated POWs, ``Those who are in
this situation are held against their will.
   ``They were taken hostage because they have a lot of
information. They were trained and armed to destabilize the
government of their own country or the political system of other
nations.''
   Reports last week said the POWs were flown to Nigeria. On
Sunday, however, reports said the Libyans' final destination was
believed to be Zaire.
   On Sunday, Libya also claimed France had a hand in the airlift
of the prisoners.
   A spokesman at the French Foreign Ministry refused to comment on
the Libyan accusations. Chad gained independence from France in
1960.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0055 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 1839EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Vatican-Saint     12-09 0241</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Vatican-Saint,0281</SECOND>
<HEAD>Widow-Turned-Nun Becomes Canada's First Native Saint</HEAD>
<DATELINE>VATICAN CITY (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Pope John Paul II on Sunday canonized
Marguerite d'Youville, a 18th-century widow-turned-nun who is
Canada's first native saint.
   Her Sisters of Charity, the order she founded in 1737, operates
in Canada and the United States within schools, hospitals and other
social service agencies. It is particularly known for its work at
d'Youville College in Buffalo, New York.
   Nuns from the order or its branches also serve in Haiti, Brazil,
Japan and Africa.
   The saint's seventy years were marked by suffering and hardship.
   She was born Marguerite Dufrost in Varennes, Quebec. Her father
died when she was seven. At 21, she married Francois d'Youville,
who was frequently away from home selling liquor.
   Four of her six children died in infancy. One of them, a
newborn, died a few days after her husband in 1730, leaving her a
widow at age 29.
   When her two sons entered the seminary in 1737, she and three
other women founded the Institute of the Sisters of Charity,
consecrating themselves to the service of God, the sick and the
forgotten poor.
   In his homily during the canonization Mass in St. Peter's
Basilica, the pope said the new saint's life showed how one can be
holy every day and how one can make the ``charity and justice of
God'' triumph in daily existence.
   In April, the pope signed a decree attributing the cure of a
patient suffering from leukemia to the intercession of d'Youville.
Lisa Normand of Gatineau, Quebec, was cured in 1983. A certified
miracle is required for saints who were not martyrs.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0056 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 1856EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-DallasReferendum     12-09 0360</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Dallas Referendum,0438</SECOND>
<HEAD>Voters Reject Referendum, But It Could Be Implemented by Judge</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DALLAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The narrow defeat of a referendum designed to help
minorities win City Council seats could throw the issue back to a
federal judge who has vowed to impose either the same plan or a
similar one, officials say.
   Voters on Saturday rejected by just 369 votes a referendum that
would have created a system to elect 14 council members by
individual districts and elect the mayor at large.
   Under the current system instituted in 1975, eight council
members are elected by voters in individual districts and another
three, including the mayor, are elected by voters citywide.
   Proponents of the plan rejected Saturday said they would seek a
recount because of the slim margin. The final vote was 45,255 in
favor of the plan and 45,624 against it.
   Supporters said the proposed voting system would have helped
ease racial inequities that make it difficult for minorities to get
elected.
   Opponents said the system would have resegregated Dallas. They
backed a plan voters approved in August 1989, calling for 10
candidates to be elected by district and four by region and for the
mayor to be elected by voters citywide. That earlier proposal never
was implemented because a federal judge suggested he would rule it
unconstitutional.
   Now that voters have rejected the plan, U.S. District Judge
Jerry Buchmeyer could call a May election to institute the same
plan or a similar one in which 15 council members would be elected
by individual district and the mayor would be chosen from among the
council.
   ``I assume the judge is going to do what he said he would do,
which is call the election,'' Dallas Mayor Annette Strauss told The
Dallas Morning News.
   Mrs. Strauss was quoted Sunday as saying the judge had indicated
he could make the ruling as early as January.
   It was unclear what the council would do.
   ``We're waiting for Buchmeyer to make a ruling,'' said
Councilman Jim Buerger. ``We have no alternative but to wait for
the judge. This issue has been unresolved for decades.''
   The referendum was held as part of the settlement of a 1988
federal lawsuit brought by Roy Williams and Marvin Crenshaw, who
failed in their at-large council bids.
   The men, both black, charged the existing election system made
it difficult for minorities to win election.
   Black and Hispanic leaders nationwide have long charged that
at-large elections dilute minority candidates' political power and
make it difficult for them to win office.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0057 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 1901EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-DailyNews-Violence     12-09 0341</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Daily News-Violence,0386</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tractor-Trailers Burned; Police Attribute Arson to Daily News
Strike</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Daily News</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Fourteen tractor-trailer cabs were damaged in an
arson fire and five others were vandalized Sunday at a company that
provides paper to the Daily News, authorities said.
   No injuries were reported.
   Police believe the attack on the Baldwin Transportation Co.
trucks was related to the 6{-week-old strike at the newspaper.
   Investigators found a hole cut in the chain-link fence around
the parking lot in the Bronx section, said Lt. Frank Martinez, a
Fire Department spokesman.
   Fire marshals also determined chemicals were used to set the 14
cabs on fire early Sunday, he said. Another five trucks had their
windshields smashed, he said.
   Meanwhile, Nassau County police reported two incidents of
strike-related vandalism. Two stores on suburban Long Island that
sell the News had their doorknobs and locks jammed with unknown
substances, police said. Bumper stickers saying ``Boycott the Daily
News'' were put on their doors.
   After Sunday's incidents, News spokesman John T. Sloan asked
union leaders to stop what he described as a ``desperate campaign
of violence.''
   The News has continued to publish, using management, replacement
workers and union members who have crossed the picket line since
the strike began Oct. 25.
   Its circulation has dropped by more than half, to about 500,000,
and major advertisers have deserted the paper. Publisher James Hoge
has charged the unions with waging a conspiracy of violence against
replacement workers and News dealers and distributors.
   Union leaders have denied any organized conspiracy and denounced
the acts of violence.
   Bernard D. DeLury, the director of the Federal Mediation and
Conciliation Service, has invited both sides to meet with him in
Washington this week.
   Sloan said officials at the paper will call federal officials
``first thing Monday morning'' to arrange a date and time.
   George McDonald, president of the Allied Printing Trade Council,
a union umbrella group, issued a statement Sunday calling the
meeting, ``the most important meeting in the two-year history of
the labor dispute.''
   On Tuesday, Hoge will go to Chicago to appear before the board
of directors of the News' parent company, the Tribune Co. The board
is meeting for the first time since the strike began.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0058 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 1908EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Baker-Soviet     12-09 0349</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Baker-Soviet,400</SECOND>
<HEAD>Baker Takes Shevardnadze To Hometown For Arms Talks</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BARRY SCHWEID</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Diplomatic Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HOUSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Secretary of State James A. Baker III took the
Soviet foreign minister to his hometown Sunday and predicted they
would make progress on a wide range of issues, including the search
for a treaty to cut long-range nuclear weapons.
   While the crisis in the Persian Gulf demands their attention,
Baker and Soviet Foreign Minister Eduard A. Shevardnadze hope to
clear roadblocks to a Strategic Arms Reduction Treaty.
   ``I have no doubt that our talks here in Houston will be
productive and that we will continue to tackle some difficult
issues in a constructive spirit,'' Baker said.
   He and Shevardnadze plan two days of talks on the treaty, the
gulf situation and other U.S.-Soviet issues. They also intend to
visit the Johnson Space Center and talk to the Columbia astronauts
aboard the Shuttle through a special telephone hookup.
   But if the mission is cut short because of poor weather or
trouble with disposing of liquid waste that colorful interlude may
have to be scratched.
   Baker, in an arrival statement at Ellington air field, praised
the Soviets for cooperating with the United States in trying to
force Iraq to withdraw from Kuwait.
   ``On no issue has U.S.-Soviet cooperation been more necessary
than on resolving the crisis caused by Iraq's brutal aggression,''
Baker said.
   A few hours before Baker and Shevardnadze arrived on separate
planes, a group of hostages were brought home by former Texas Gov.
John Connally.
   ``They never should have been taken hostage in the first
place,'' Baker said. ``So while we are heartened by their return,
we will not rest until all hostages from all nations are safely
home.''
   The treaty to reduce U.S. and Soviet long-range nuclear bombers,
missiles and submarines by about 30 percent is nearly finished. The
remaining unsettled issues deal mostly with verification -
procedures to assure compliance with the restrictions to be
imposed.
   When it is finished, President Bush plans to go to Moscow to
sign the treaty at a summit meeting with Soviet President Mikhail
S. Gorbachev.
   Shevardnadze, in a brief statement, said in Russian ``it seems
we have a lot of work ahead of us.''
   Noting that the United States and the Soviet Union have
cooperated in some space ventures, the foreign minister remarked:
``I hope we will further solidify our cooperation on earth.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0059 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 1913EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-WeatherpageWeather 1stLd-Writethru a074 12-09 0202</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Weatherpage Weather, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0745,0219</SECOND>
<HEAD>Sunny or Partly Cloudy Skies Across Most of Nation</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 2nd graf to CORRECT to EST sted EDT.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Fair weather prevailed across much of the nation Sunday, but
rain dampened parts of northwest California, Oregon, Washington,
Idaho and Montana.
   There were no reports of heavy rainfall or measurable snowfall
during the 6 hours ending at 1 p.m. EST. Locally heavy rain late
Saturday and early Sunday caused flooding at Hilo, Hawaii.
   Gale warnings were in effect Sunday over Lake Huron, North
Carolina's coastal waters and the Washington-Oregon coast.
   Highs were in the 50s and 60s in parts of the Midwest, including
50 in Des Moines, Iowa; 52 in Indianapolis, Ind., 56 in Chicago and
62 in St. Louis, Mo.
   Temperatures around the nation at 3 p.m. ranged from 25 degrees
at Jackson, Wyo., to 84 degrees at Oceanside, Calif.
   High temperature records broken or tied Sunday included 54 in
Alpena, Mich.; 50 in Marquette, Mich.; 47 in Duluth, Minn.; 45 in
International Falls, Minn.; and 56 in Fargo, N.D.
   Hollywood, Fla., cooled to 45 degrees Sunday morning, breaking
the city's low temperature record for the date.
   The coldest spot in the nation Sunday morning was West
Yellowstone, Mont., which hit 8 degrees below zero.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0060 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 2006EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Poland-Election 5thLd-Writethru a0722 12-09 0726</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Poland-Election, 5th Ld-Writethru, a0722,0881</SECOND>
<HEAD>Walesa Wins Polish Presidency in Landside</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 25 grafs to UPDATE with latest returns, turnout,
details from scene in Gdansk. Picks up 26th graf pvs, `For
Walesa...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By JOHN DANISEWSKI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WARSAW, Poland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Lech Walesa, the shipyard worker who
helped lead his country out of Communism, swept to a landslide
victory in Poland's first popular presidential vote Sunday,
according to partial returns.
   Walesa defeated emigre businessman Stanislaw Tyminski, a virtual
unknown before the campaign, by 75 percent to 25 percent, according
to the first official results from 165 of the country's more than
22,000 polling stations, the television said.
   Full official results were expected late Monday, but earlier
exit polls predicted a similar outcome.
   ``There are terribly difficult tasks waiting for us,'' Walesa
said as he sipped a congratulatory glass of champagne before the
television cameras and supporters in Gdansk, where his Solidarity
movement began in August 1980.
   ``I hope that we will be building Poland's future together. I
want to behave firmly, I want to firmly correct everything that is
wrong, and make firm accounts for everything that has not been
accounted for yet.''
   Outside, thousands gathered and chanted his name over and over.
They sang ``Sto Lat,'' a song that means, ``May You Live 100
Years.''
   Tyminski declined to concede defeat immediately, saying he did
not trust the polls. He said he would remain active in Polish
politics.
   Outgoing President Wojciech Jaruzelski, who sent Walesa to jail
under martial law nine years ago, sent his congratulations. He
wished the new president ``fruitful activity for the good of our
homeland.''
   Turnout was estimated at 53 percent, compared with about 60
percent in the first round last month, according to preliminary
results.
   The Solidarity leader and 1983 Nobel Peace Prize laureate had
asked voters to give him a broad mandate to lead the country to a
market economy and a European-style democracy.
   The exit polls showed that he did well among all social groups -
nearly doubling the 40 percent he got in the first round in
November.
   Tyminski, who performed well in the first round, appeared to
have been damaged by numerous questions raised about him at the end
of the campaign.
   ``I'm surprised, but I won't make any comments at the moment,''
Tyminski told reporters after inspecting the returns posted at his
home voting district in Pecice, outside Warsaw.
   Walesa had split the Solidarity movement when he opposed Prime
Minister Tadeusz Mazowiecki in the first round of voting Nov. 25.
   But this time, he ran with the backing of the powerful Roman
Catholic Church and virtually all political and social
organizations.
   ``I voted for Walesa. How could anyone vote for a clown?'' said
Jan Grzesiak, 52, a Warsaw building superintendent. ``Walesa is a
worker, he went through hardship and he is an honest man - contrary
to Tyminski.''
   Tyminski, a self-proclaimed millionaire, beat Mazowiecki in the
first round based on his promise to bring Western business know-how
to Poland and improve the economy in a month.
   Although he returned to Poland in September after 21 years in
Canada and Peru, there were reports that he had ties with former
Communist and police operatives.
   Tyminski's political tract, ``Sacred Dogs,'' was co-written with
an ex-correspondent for a Communist Party daily, and he
acknowledged that several ranking campaign aides were party members
or secret-police veterans.
   Also, he failed to clearly explain how he would carry out his
promise to improve the economy. And questions were raised about his
claimed mystical experiences in the Amazon jungle.
   Tyminski, 42, who owns computer-related and communications
businesses and leads the fringe Libertarian Party of Canada, had
railed against the economic ``treason'' of Mazowiecki.
   He appealed especially to young voters not under the spell of
the Solidarity legend and eager for financial success. He also
found votes among farmers, miners and others threatened by the
government's tight-money and profit-or-perish market policies.
   The winner could be inaugurated for a five-year term as early as
this weekend if the results are not contested.
   The president's early tasks include nominating a prime minister
to succeed Mazowiecki, who has asked to resign, and overseeing the
country's first fully free parliamentary elections since World War
II next year.
   Walesa said Sunday night he is considering seven candidates to
succeed Mazowiecki and expects to decide by Wednesday.
   For Walesa, 47, the victory culminated an astonishing personal
voyage: from the child of a dirt-poor peasant family to a shipyard
electrician dismissed for union organizing; from union leader to
political prisoner to presidential candidate.
   Walesa has promised to carry out the same basic aims as
Mazowiecki. But he says he will change the nation's tough economic
reform program to ease problems of farmers and to try to create
jobs for the unemployed.
   He says he would be faster and more effective than Mazowiecki
because he is able and willing to talk to common people.
   ``I am not afraid to confront the masses when I am right. I may
even confront the whole of Poland,'' he said. ``Like it or not, I
do not want to please everybody.''

</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0061 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 2024EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Gulf-American     12-09 0340</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-American,0407</SECOND>
<HEAD>Freed American Hostage Says He Wants to Go to Saudi Arabia</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf-Iraq, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By NESHA STARCEVIC</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>FRANKFURT, Germany (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   After four months hiding from Iraqi
soldiers in Kuwait, Joseph Lammerding of California said Monday he
would like to join American forces in Saudi Arabia.
   Lammerding, 35, was the first of 175 Americans leaving a
U.S.-chartered Iraqi Airways jumbo jet after it landed in
Frankfurt. It left Baghdad on Sunday with the first Americans to
depart under an Iraqi order to release all foreigners.
   ``Now I just want to see Mom and Dad,'' said Lammerding, a
native of Sacramento, Calif. ``I hope to be back in Saudi Arabia
next month.
   He said he would like to be part of the effort to push Iraq out
of Kuwait.
   A slight, bearded man in jeans who carried only a small canvas
bag, Lammerding identified himself as an adviser to the Kuwaiti
military who had lived in the oil-rich nation since 1983.
   Lammerding, three other Americans, and one Briton fled at night
to a villa outside Kuwait City after the Iraqi invasion Aug. 2.
They remained there for more than four months.
   The group learned they were free to leave Saturday night, one
day after the Iraqi parliament approved a decree by President
Saddam Hussein allowing all foreigners to go home.
   Recalling his experience, Lammerding described Iraqi brutality
accompanied by a low level of military professionalism.
   ``Sometimes they (Iraqis) would shoot one member of a family.
Sometimes the entire family. They raped and plundered, literally,''
he said of the treatment of Kuwaitis.
   He said Kuwaitis did their best to hamper Iraqi efforts to keep
control of the country by tearing down street signs and house
nubers, making it difficult for the Iraqis to get around.
   Nighttime visits by Kuwaitis with food and medical supplies
helped his group survive when their own food supplies ran out
several weeks after the invasion.
   The small band of foreigners refused to answer the door when
Iraqi soldiers who had moved into a neighboring villa rang the
bell. ``We played kind of dumb,'' said Lammerding.
   Lammerding gave high marks to U.S. policy in the Persian Gulf.
   ``Many of us feel the U.S. government has done a good job,
especially utilizing the United Nations,'' Lammerding said. He said
Washington should keep up the pressure on Saddam.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0062 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 2045EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ProxyWedding     12-09 0258</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Proxy Wedding,0302</SECOND>
<HEAD>Father Stands Up for Marine Son in Desert Shield</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOLO, Mont. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Marine Sgt. Paul Flemmer is somewhere in the
Persian Gulf, but he and the former Rhonda McWilliams were married
here over the weekend anyway.
   Flemmer's father, Del Flemmer, stood in for his eldest son under
a state provision that allows proxy weddings.
   ``I haven't got married for 30 years,'' the elder Flemmer
quipped just before exchanging vows Saturday with his
daughter-in-law-to-be, Rhonda McWilliams, 25, of nearby
Stevensville.
   The wedding was arranged by mail, telephone and a legal
power-of-attorney. ``Usually, when the groom doesn't show up for
the wedding, the wedding is off,'' said the Rev. Gale Fister, who
conducted the ceremony at Lolo Community Church.
   Flemmer and Miss McWilliams, who have a 1-year-old son, were
scheduled to be married Aug. 30 and Flemmer had been granted a
30-day leave for the occasion. The couple had even purchased a
house in Stevensville, the 25-year-old bride's home.
   Flemmer's leave was canceled abruptly after Iraq invaded Kuwait
Aug. 2. He was sent from his duty station at El Toro, Calif., to
the Persian Gulf on Aug. 27.
   But the bride was determined to have a wedding, with or without
the groom.
   ``We'd heard about the possibility of a proxy wedding, but the
(Marine Corps) chaplain in California said it couldn't be done,''
she said.
   Montana is one of the few states that allows proxy weddings.
   The power of attorney gave Paul's father the legal right to act
as his son's deputy or agent.
   Family members said they would send Flemmer newspaper clippings,
a tape recording, a videotape and photos of the wedding.
   ``When Paul gets back, we'll do it the right way,'' his bride
said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0063 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 2106EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i BC-Poland-Text     12-09 0254</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Poland-Text,0299</SECOND>
<HEAD>Text of Walesa's First Post-Election Message</HEAD>
<DATELINE>GDANSK, Poland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here is a text of a message to Poles by
Lech Walesa broadcast nationwide after early election returns
indicated a landslide presidential victory Sunday. The translation
was done by the Polish Press Agency:
   The elections are over. Another lesson of democracy is behind
us. We can thank and congratulate one another.
   Over the past decade we have together experienced a breakthrough
in the history of our nation. Dreams of entire generations have
become true before our eyes. We have regained freedom. Providence
has given us the privilege of finding peaceful solutions.
   Without blood, through solidarity in action, we have won a free
Poland. It depends entirely on us what we will do with it in the
future. This was forgotten many a time during this (presidential)
campaign.
   Tremendous responsibility will rest with the president. It also
rests with us all. Everyone should start to feel like a host in our
common house, have a tiny part of Poland, his own property which he
will respect and care for. This is the simplest philosophy of
responsibility.
   No professional group, no man will be able to say: `There are no
prospects for me.' In Poland there is enough work for everyone. We
must change and modernize much. This is a new task for
intelligentsia. We must first help ourselves. Europe will
appreciate us for this. An economically developed Poland will be
one of the pillars of peace and calm in Europe, whereas a poor
Poland will meet a wall of disapproval at all borders.
   We are facing a difficult task: to trust in ourselves and win a
measurable success - a success for everyone. I am confident that we
shall do this.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0064 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 2136EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Colombia 3rdLd-Writethru a0765 12-09 0642</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Colombia, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0765,0762</SECOND>
<HEAD>Colombian Army Seizes Rebel Headquarters on Voting Day</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 12 grafs to UPDATE calling election for M-19,
latest election returns; locator for guerrilla base; pickup graf 12
pvs `Officials said....' TRIMS thereafter</NOTE>
<DATELINE>BOGOTA, Colombia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Soldiers bombed and captured the main
base of Colombia's biggest rebel group Sunday as former guerrillas
won a national election for a constitutional assembly. At least 11
people were reported killed in the attack.
   About 400 soldiers, backed by Israeli K-Fir fighter planes and
U.S. Blackhawk helicopter gunships, invaded the main base camp of
the Revolutionary Armed Forces of Colombia, known as the FARC, an
army report said.
   The attack came the same day Colombians voted in a national
election to choose 70 members of an assembly to rewrite the
country's 104-year-old constitution.
   In a humiliating setback to Colombia's two traditional political
parties, the former M-19 rebels, led by Antonio Navarro, had an
insurmountable lead late Sunday with 49 percent of the total votereported.
   The National Elections Office said M-19 had 486,599 votes, or 32
percent of the total.
   The National Salvation Party, a Conservative Party splinter
group led by former presidentital candidate Alvaro Gomez, had
324,997 votes, or 21 percent.
   The rest of the votes were spread thinly among 800 candidates.
   The elections office said that only about 25 percent of voters
went to the polls. It was the lowest voter turnout for a national
election in more than a quarter of a century.
   It was also the first time in Colombia's history that neither
the Liberal Party nor the Conservative Party had dominated voting.
The results are likely to underscore the possibility of social
upheaval unless the government urgently attends to the needs of the
poor.
   The M-19 laid down its arms nine months ago in exchange for
government pardons and the right to form a political party.
   The attack on the FARC headquarters, called ``Casa Verde,'' left
seven soldiers and four air force officers dead, the army
communique said. The air force men were killed when their
helicopter crashed, the army said.
   The report did not say how many guerrillas, if any, were killed
at the base, about 160 miles south of Bogota. A report by the RCN
radio network said as many as 40 insurgents died.
   Officials said Sunday that six rebels and four soldiers were
killed in earlier clashes between the army and other guerrilla
groups.
   Sunday's vote will result in a 70-member constitutional assembly
empowered to make major structural reform to government. Changes
expected include revamping Colombia's battered court system, adding
safeguards to curb congressional corruption, and establishing new
civil rights in this country wracked by drug violence.
   Few people doubt that Colombia's powerful cocaine cartels are
donating money to assembly candidates, but it is difficult to
measure the traffickers' involvement. Candidates rarely mention the
government's 15-month-old war on drug traffickers.
   ``We are at the doors of the most exceptional opportunity to
transform Colombia,'' said President Cesar Gaviria in a nationally
televised speech Saturday evening.
   ``We Colombians can finally devise a way to bring our country
the peace which has been so elusive,'' he said.
   Many voters blame old party bosses for corruption and failing to
curb violence that has killed tens of thousands of people in the
past decade.
   ``Navarro's got my vote, not because I like him, but because I
can't stand the others,'' said Patricia Sanchez, a Bogota educator.
   Politicians have dredged up the M-19's violent past to discredit
the group among voters, particularly its 1985 takeover of the
Palace of Justice in Bogota. That action turned into a battle with
the army that left about 100 people dead, including 11 Supreme
Court justices.
   The M-19 became a legitimate party nine months ago after laying
down its weapons in exchange for a government pardon.
   Some Colombians fear the army, which has been fighting guerrilla
insurgencies for three decades, would stage a coup if the M-19 took
over the constitutional assembly.
   Navarro, a 41-year-old engineer, has tried to convince voters
that his party has never been Marxist and will help guarantee civil
rights.
   Leftist guerrillas disrupted balloting in several isolated
incidents, officials said Sunday.
   Army and police reinforcements were stepped up in major cities
Sunday, and the government provided free transportation to polling
stations.
   Colombia's cocaine bosses were blamed for assassinating three
candidates before presidential elections in May, including M-19
leader Carlos Pizarro. Navarro replaced him.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0065 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 2144EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-EllisIsland     12-09 0435</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Ellis Island,0500</SECOND>
<HEAD>Demonstrators Protest U.S. Deployment Outside Awards Dinner</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By VERENA DOBNIK</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Several thousand anti-war demonstrators rallied
Sunday outside a hotel where 101 Americans, including President
Bush and four former presidents, were honored for their
contributions to America.
   Neither Bush nor former presidents Ronald Reagan and Richard
Nixon, the three targeted by an estimated 3,000 protesters,
attended a dinner in the Waldorf-Astoria Hotel after an awards
ceremony at Ellis Island in New York Harbor. Fellow honorees Jimmy
Carter and Gerald Ford also did not attend.
   Bush and the former presidents were to accept Ellis Island
Medals of Honor at a ceremony to be scheduled later.
   ``We're demonstrating because the awards are being given to war
makers,'' said Scott Scheffer, a spokesman for the Coalition to
Stop U.S. Intervention in the Middle East, which organized the
protest.
   No arrests were reported.
   Honorees who did attend the ceremony inside the recently
renovated immigrant processing center on the island in New York
Harbor included singer Melba Moore, actor Telly Savalas, comedian
Danny Thomas and Cincinnati Reds manager Lou Piniella.
   The 101 Americans being honored include the descendants of
immigrants, slaves and American Indians and represent 36 different
ethnic groups.
   For many attending Sunday's ceremony, it was their first visit
to the hall where immigrants were once processed for entry to the
United States. The hall is now part of the American Museum of
Immigration, which opened in September.
   Piniella, who led his team to a World Series victory this year,
was greeted with shouts of ``Lou!!'' when he accepted his medal.
   Miss Moore saluted the Army officers who slipped the medal
around her neck, then released a joyful whoop under the American
flag.
   Other medal recipients included native American Indian Chief
Oren Lyons of the Onondaga tribe, former Texas Congresswoman
Barbara Jordan, Roman Catholic Cardinal Joseph Bernardin of
Chicago, CBS news consultant Eric Sevareid and Thomas Pickering,
the U.S. Ambassador to the United Nations.
   Traffic was blocked along a one-block section of Park Avenue
during the three-hour demonstration to protest the U.S. military
buildup in the Persian Gulf after Iraq's Aug. 2 invasion of Kuwait.
Several protesters held up banners reading ``Don't spill oil for
blood'' and ``Draft beer not war.''
   The deployment of U.S. troops is ``not for democracy. It's about
oil,'' said one demonstrator, George Kelly. He said he was a World
War II and Korean War veteran and a member of the organization
Veterans for Peace.
   While demonstrators marched outside, Pickering defended Bush's
decision to send U.S. troops to the Middle East.
   ``The president is trying to resolve the situation peacefully,''
Pickering said. ``He has walked the last mile for peace.''
   The Ellis Island Medal was first presented in 1986 during the
100th anniversary of the Statue of Liberty by the National Ethnic
Coalition of Organizations, which represents 66 of the nation's
largest heritage groups.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0066 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 2204EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Gulf-HostagesReturn 1stLd-Writethru a07 12-09 0580</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Hostages Return, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0714,0720</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ex-Hostages Greeted by Cheering Relatives</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 4 grafs for last graf, `Meanwhile, the ...' to UPDATE
with further Connally comments opposing a U.S. military attack.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos HT1, HT3, HT7, HT8</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By WENDY BENJAMINSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HOUSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Former hostages from Iraq shouted ``God Bless
America!'' and families shrieked with delight as they charged to
greet each other across the tarmac at Ellington Air Field on
Sunday.
   Former Treasury Secretary John Connally and Oscar Wyatt, the
chairman of Coastal Corp., which financed the trip, also were
mobbed by family members who covered their faces with
lipstick-marked kisses of thanks and moved the men to tears.
   Connally later said talks with Saddam Hussein revealed a leader
who was ``a very tough man, but he's not a stupid man.''
   ``He said to us he had no argument with the American people, and
he did not want a war. He wanted peace, but he wanted peace with
justice and with dignity,'' Connally said.
   Twenty-one hostages, three U.S. Embassy employees and seven
family members stepped off a Coastal Corp. Boeing 707 before dawn
Sunday to nearly 200 cheering relatives and friends.
   Jackie Nelson, wife of former hostage Bill Nelson of Los
Angeles, kissed Wyatt and Connally on the cheek and said: ``God
bless you. I can't thank you enough. We're so grateful.''
   Nelson, who was held at a munitions plant south of Baghdad,
said: ``God Bless America. There's nothing like it. These people
are marvelous. They have done things our government can't do and
won't do.''
   As the ex-hostages got off the plane, former hostage Jim Vine's
voice rang out above the other. He was seeing his infant son for
the first time.
   ``Oh my God!'' he shouted as he rushed to throw his arms around
his wife, Donna, and son, Evan. The baby was born Sept. 6., barely
one month after Iraq invaded Kuwait.
   Connally and Wyatt said they met with Saddam for 45 minutes in
the presidential palace.
   ``We made an impassioned plea to him, saying to him in effect
that we thought he should release all the hostages,'' Connally
said. ``Mr. Wyatt said that if indeed there's an armed conflict,
the presence of a few hundred hostages would not in any way deter
the armed conflict.''
   They also told Saddam he was being portrayed ``as a vicious,
brutal man, compared to Hitler, and I said the release of the
hostages before the Christmas season would clearly show a concern
and a compassion,'' Connally said.
   The men also donated 15 tons of medical supplies, valued at
$500,000, to Fellowship on Reconciliation, an Iraqi humanitarian
group in Amman.
   Saddam replied as they parted, ``You will not go home with an
empty plane,'' according to Connally.
   That statement touched off a bureaucratic nightmare, in which
hostages scrambled to get exit visas and be transported hundreds of
miles from the strategic locations at which they were held to
Baghdad.
   Connally described how one British subject, Peter McCleod of
London, arrived on the plane ``in his shirtsleeves, with two
pillowcases containing his entire possessions.''
   Some hostages who hoped to ride home with Connally and Wyatt -
who's done business with the Iraqis for 19 years - were forced to
remain because of delays in getting exit visas. None of the
hostages are connected with Coastal.
   The plane left Baghdad Saturday morning, stopped in Shannon,
Ireland, to refuel and drop off McCleod, and flew on to Houston.
   Wyatt and Connally secured the hostages' release before Saddam's
proposal Thursday to release all hostages.
   Later Sunday in Austin, Connally said he opposed a U.S. military
attack on Iraq.
   ``If we become involved in a shooting war in that distant land,
it will be tragic indeed,'' he said in a speech to more than 12,000
people at a graduation ceremony at the University of Texas. ``The
encounter will be fierce with staggering casualties on both
sides.''
   The United States could defeat Iraq in battle ``but lose the
war,'' he said.
   Meanwhile, the first Americans to be freed under the decree
arrived Sunday in Frankfurt, Germany, on a U.S.-chartered flight
from Baghdad. About 175 Americans were among some 325 people aboard
the jumbo jet.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0067 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 2232EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Abdul-Accident     12-09 0244</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Abdul-Accident,0270</SECOND>
<HEAD>Singer Paula Abdul Slightly Injured in Three-Car Crash</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Singer Paula Abdul, one of the world's
highest-paid entertainers, suffered minor injuries in a three-car
crash Sunday, police said.
   Miss Abdul's 1989 black Jaguar rear-ended another car,
triggering a collision with a third car on Laurel Canyon Boulevard
in Studio City, 10 miles north of downtown Los Angeles, said police
Sgt. Al Zardeneta.
   She was treated at Medical Center of North Hollywood and later
released, said hospital spokeswoman Sherry Reese. The former Los
Angeles Lakers cheerleader complained of pains in her head, neck
and upper body, Zardeneta said.
   Miss Abdul's car rear-ended a car driven by Charles Koko, 37, of
North Hollywood, Zardeneta said. Koko's car then rammed the back of
a third car driven by Katherine Butler, 28, of Newport Beach, he
said.
   Koko and Ms. Butler complained of sore necks but were not taken
to a hospital, Zardeneta said.
   ``We don't know how it happened,'' Zardeneta said. ``There are
two options - either she (Miss Abdul) was speeding or she was
following too closely.''
   Miss Abdul's 1989 debut album, ``Forever Your Girl,'' spawned
the hits ``Straight Up,'' ``Cold Hearted'' and ``The Way You Love
Me'' and garnered several American Music Awards and MTV video
awards.
   She also choreographed the films ``Coming to America'' and ``The
Running Man'' and won an Emmy for her choreography on television's
``The Tracey Ullman Show.''
   Miss Abdul ranked 33rd in a list of Forbes magazine's 40
highest-paid entertainers with estimated total gross earnings of
$23 million for 1989 and 1990.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0068 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 2252EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Gulf-Iraq 10thLd-Writethr u 12-09 0815</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Iraq, 10th Ld-Writethru, a0775,1035</SECOND>
<HEAD>Planeload of Hostages Arrives In Germany</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 4 grafs to UPDATE with new quote from American.
Picks up 3rd graf pvs, `Now I....' EDITS thereafter to tighten</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos BAG1,2; FRA1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By NESHA STARCEVIC</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>FRANKFURT, Germany (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The first Americans freed under Saddam
Hussein's order releasing all foreigners arrived in Germany early
Monday. Other former hostages prepared to leave Iraq after more
than four months under guard or in hiding.
   Some of the 175 Americans on the U.S.-chartered Iraqi Airways
jet that landed in Frankfurt were expected to go to a U.S. Air
Force hospital in nearby Wiesbaden. Most planned to return to the
United States on Monday.
   Lorin Hubbard, 66, a Boeing Co. executive held as a ``human
shield'' at an ammunition plant 35 miles west of Baghdad, Iraq,
said he had waited for bombs to fall.
   ``We were hoping they'd blow the place up. ... We had no idea
when we'd get out,'' he said. ``Nobody knew where we were, as far
as I know.''
   ``Now I just want to see mom and dad,'' said Joseph Lammerding,
35, a native of Sacramento, Calif.
   He said he would like to return to the region to help the
U.S.-led military effort against Iraq. ``I hope to be back in Saudi
Arabia next month,'' said Lammerding, who added that he had worked
as a Kuwaiti military adviser.
   ``This is the first time I have had shoes on in over three
months,'' said construction worker Randal Warren, 49, of
Charleston, Mo., who said he hid in the top floor of a Kuwaiti
apartment building and went barefoot to keep quiet.
   The flight also carried more than 90 Britons, about 30
Canadians, and former hostages from Ireland, Greece, Austria,
Argentina, Denmark, Italy, the Netherlands and Switzerland, said
airport officials in Baghdad.
   In all, 324 people were on the airplane, and more than 250 of
them had been stranded since the Aug. 2 Iraqi invasion of the tiny
oil-rich emirate of Kuwait. The rest included family members and
others.
   The Iraqi parliament on Friday approved a decree by Iraqi
President Saddam to free all foreigners in Kuwait and Iraq.
   Robert Vinton, 58, of Santa Fe, N.M, said he was picked up in
Baghdad on Aug. 18 and held at a refinery south of the city.
   ``It was like a gulag,'' he said after arriving in Frankfurt.
   Asked what he wanted most, Vinton replied, ``I think a
hamburger.''
   U.S. officials said they planned to charter another flight in
three or four days to evacuate the rest of the estimated 750
Americans in Iraq and Kuwait.
   Other flights being arranged included British charters to leave
Monday and Tuesday to London, and a flight to Moscow. Airport
sources also said hundreds of Vietnamese workers were at the
airport awaiting departure.
   The first foreigners to leave Baghdad under the decree issued by
Saddam were a group of about 200 hostages, mostly Italians, who
arrived in Rome on Sunday aboard an Italian-chartered jet.
   Western diplomats complained that Iraqi authorities had thrown
up some last-minute bureaucratic roadblocks to the exodus.
   For example, foreigners in cities other than Baghdad were told
they must obtain exit visas from those cities. Those who had been
under work contracts were told that Iraqi law requires them to
present a letter releasing them from their obligations.
   Iraq has refused U.S. requests to waive visa requirements for
freed hostages, and the processing of the visas alone had been
expected to delay some departures for days.
   However, diplomats said Iraqi officials were working quickly
Sunday, processing an estimated 80 exit visas an hour.
   Twenty-one former American hostages landed in Houston early
Sunday after flying out of Baghdad a day earlier aboard a jet
chartered by former Treasury Secretary John Connally, who was in
Iraq on a private hostage-freeing mission.
   Their release was arranged prior to Iraq's decree freeing all
foreigners.
   ``God bless America!'' said one of the arriving Americans, Bill
Nelson of Los Angeles.
   Three U.S. Embassy employees in Iraq also were on the flight,
along with relatives of the former hostages.
   About 8,000 Westerners had been detained since Iraq's invasion
of Kuwait, including about 600 who were held at strategic sites in
an effort to deter an attack.
   Voice of America broadcasts advised Americans in Kuwait,
including those who have been in hiding since Iraq's invasion, that
they could leave on Sunday's charter flights.
   But diplomats said it was not immediately clear if Americans who
had taken refuge in the U.S. Embassy in Kuwait would be allowed to
leave. Iraqi troops have sealed off the embassy since it refused to
close in August.
   U.S. officials said Friday they would evacuate the embassy after
all Americans were out of Kuwait.
   Meanwhile, a London newspaper reported that Iraq has redrawn its
border with Kuwait in what could signal plans to withdraw as early
as next month. The Observer said Iraq was laying claim to an area
of the Rumailah oilfield and the islands of Warba and Bubiyan in
the gulf.
   The report said Iraq has constructed a new international line by
building a barbed-wire fence around the southern tip of the
oilfield, which extends into northern Kuwait.
   Saudi Arabian officials denied the report.
   Iraq has repeatedly linked a resolution of the gulf crisis -
including any withdrawal from Kuwait - to the Palestinian issue.
   But on Saturday night, the U.N. Security Council, facing the
threat of a U.S. veto, postponed until Monday discussion of a
resolution calling for an eventual international peace conference
on the Middle East.
   In another development, Jordan's King Hussein proposed that a
compromise settlement of the gulf crisis could be reached through a
conference of Arabs. In a speech, he welcomed President Bush's
offer to talk with Iraq, and criticized Arab states for refusing to
do so.
   The Bush administration has said the talks are not meant to be
negotiations, but are merely aimed at underscoring the demand that
Iraq go along with U.N. resolutions on Kuwait.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0069 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 2258EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-LightSighted     12-09 0244</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Light Sighted,0286</SECOND>
<HEAD>Body of Rocket Creates Flash over Central U.S. Sky</HEAD>
<DATELINE>OKLAHOMA CITY (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The body of a Soviet rocket created a
brilliant flash of light seen by residents of five states as it
fell toward Earth early Sunday, officials and witnesses said.
   People in Oklahoma, Texas, Arkansas, Kansas and Colorado
reported seeing the light at about 1:45 a.m. EST. Witnesses
described the sighting as a bright, reddish object with a long
tail. Some said they could make out its cylinderlike shape.
   It was the second unusual sky sighting since Friday, when
residents in Illinois, Michigan, Kentucky and Ohio saw a dazzling
blue-green light that scientists later identified as a fireball -
an object similar to a meteor.
   U.S. Air Force Maj. David Griffard of the North American
Aerospace Defense Command identified Sunday's sighting as a Soviet
rocket body. The agency is tracking about 6,500 objects in space
through the U.S. Space Command's worldwide network of radar and
electrical sensors, he said.
   Griffard said the rocket body disintegrated shortly after it
entered the Earth's atmosphere. He said he didn't have any further
information about the rocket.
   Robert Skuy of Tulsa said he pulled his car over Sunday morning
to look at what he first took to be an airplane in trouble.
   ``Then I thought it might have been a missile,'' Skuy said. ``It
was weird because it wasn't falling. That's why I thought it was an
airplane at first. It was kind of like in orbit. All the other
meteorites I've seen have been way high up in the sky.''
   Skuy, like other witnesses, said the light appeared to be at the
altitude of a low-flying plane.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0070 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 2259EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Angola     12-09 0252</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Angola,0277</SECOND>
<HEAD>Angola's Ruling Party Agrees to Give Up Monopoly on Power</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JORGE AMADO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LUANDA, Angola (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Angola's ruling party agreed Sunday to
give up its monopoly on power and usher in pluralist democracy in
this southern African nation.
   The moves are expected to boost peace negotiations between the
government and U.S.-backed rebels. The 15-year civil war has killed
an estimated 350,000 people and wrecked a potentially prosperous
economy.
   The government and rebels are due to meet for a sixth round of
peace talks January in Portugal, the former colonial ruler. Rebel
leader Jonas Savimbi said last week he would be ready to sign a
cease-fire if the ruling party carried through its plans for free
elections.
   The ruling Popular Movement for the Liberation of Angola,
meeting for its third national congress, voted to partially revise
the country's constitution to allow the installation of
``multiparty democracy in Angola before the end of March 1991,''
state radio reported.
   The MPLA, as the party is known by its Portuguese initials, also
recommended changing legislation to allow the creation of
alternative parties, guarantee rights of expression, religion and
association, and freedom of the press.
   Other changes passed by the 700 congress delegates included
economic reforms based on free market principles and private
property, as well as the abolition of the death penalty.
   The rebels have said they want general elections before December
1991, but President Jose Eduardo dos Santos says up to three years
will be needed after a cease-fire to organize a free vote.
   There was no immediate reaction to the congress' decisions from
the rebels.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0071 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 1401EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-Malaysia-Logging     12-09 0639</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Malaysia-Logging,0756</SECOND>
<HEAD>Forests Dwindle in Sarawak</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Loin-Clothed Crusader</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KENNETH L. WHITING</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>KUCHING, Malaysia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Time is running out for saving the
dwindling hardwood forests of Sarawak.
   All virgin timber will be gone in 11 years at the present rate
of cutting, according to the latest report on logging in the rich
Malaysian state in northern Borneo.
   No cry of alarm from outraged environmentalists for a change,
this warning comes from inside the industry. Experts of the
International Tropical Timber Organization blame excessive cutting,
pollution and recklessness by inept loggers.
   The organization represents 19 timber producing nations and 25
consumer countries. Formed in 1986 and based in Yokohama, Japan, it
is often caught in the middle. It has been rebuked by
conservationists for favoring consumers and by producers for taking
a narrow, technical approach to the problem of deforestation.
   The 207-page report has been circulating privately since May. It
has drawn criticism from Malaysian officials and international
environmental groups for not delving into the distress caused by
loggers to nomadic tribes and other jungle dwellers. In a
disclaimer, the study said those who drafted it were ``neither
qualified nor empowered to judge on such matters.''
   Nearly half of Sarawak's 1.6 million people are from some 20
upland native ethnic groups, commonly known as Dyaks. They
traditionally lived with informal systems of land tenure, often
without legal titles.
   The state remains the ultimate land owner and officials have the
power to change ownership and convert land from communal to
individual control. Some jungle communities are unaware of their
changed status until new lease-holders arrive to start felling
trees.
   Chief Minister Abdul Taib Mahmud says logging has upgraded the
skills of natives and helped them prosper. However, an earlier ITTO
report in 1988 said that timber concessionaires and others who
control the industry glean most of the wealth from Sarawak's
forests.
   The current annual cutting rate of about 13 million cubic meters
should be reduced by about 4 million cubic meters, the latest
report suggests. To prevent erosion and protect stream beds from
silting up, logging would have to stop on many steep slopes.
   It faults the state for not having enough forest managers and
says the present system of issuing logging concessions tends to
reward companies that damage the forest in their haste to get the
wood out.
   Malaysia supplied two-thirds of the world's tropical hardwood
logs last year and half of them came from Sarawak, where forests
cover almost 70 percent of the land area in a state that is half
the size of France.
   Most of the logs are shipped to Japan, where many end up as
disposable chopsticks or are converted into plywood and used only
once, as forms for pouring concrete.
   Western environmentalists accuse the government of allowing the
indiscriminate cutting of rain forests. They charge that polluted
rivers, devastated wildlife and displaced tribes are left when the
chain saws and bulldozers finish.
   ``What remains behind is virtually wasteland,'' said a report by
Sahabat Alam, the Malaysian branch of Friends of the Earth.
   Describing the deforestation as catastrophic, the European
Parliament in Strasbourg recently urged the European Community ``to
impose with immediate effect a moratorium on imports of tropical
hardwood from Sarawak.''
   Timber is the backbone of Sarawak's commercial economy, fetching
about $1 billion a year in export earnings. The industry generates
almost half the state government's revenue and employs more than
50,000.
   All forest area is under state government control. About 11.4
million acres is designated ``permanent forest estate,'' which can
be selectively logged but not converted to other uses. An
additional 632,583 acres is set aside in national parks or wildlife
sanctuaries.
   A study completed late last year by the World-Wide Fund for
Nature (formerly World Wildlife Fund) said Sarawak could retain
large tracts of rain forest only if it acted promptly to enforce
conservation measures.
   Among other things, it said loggers seemed to lack procedures to
ensure environmental protection for their concessions and the
social welfare of the people who dwell in them.
   For more than a year, Prime Minister Mahathir Mohamad has hit
back at foreign critics as ill-informed or self-serving.
   ``The thinning of the ozone layer is blamed on logging of
tropical forests,'' he said. ``The fact that the burning of fossil
fuels and release of CFC (chloroflurocarbon) into the atmosphere
occur largely in the rich countries are significantly ignored.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0072 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 1403EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-Loin-ClothedCrusader     12-09 0562</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Loin-Clothed Crusader,0673</SECOND>
<HEAD>Swiss Herdsman Goes Native in Campaign to Save Borneo Rain Forest</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Malaysia-Logging</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GEORGE JAHN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>VIENNA, Austria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The nomads of Sarawak hate bright light.
Bruno Manser shares their antipathy after six years under the
jungle canopy, squinting and squirming as the TV lights flash for
another interview.
   Manser went native in 1984, leaving the safe streets and
clock-work predictability of his native Switzerland to share the
perils of life with the Penan of Sarawak, one of the world's last
nomadic tribes.
   He downplayed the rain forest's dangers and isolation in an
interview in the Austrian capital before jetting to Paris and a
meeting with Danielle Mitterrand, wife of the French president, on
how to save the Sarawak jungle from loggers.
   ``A taxi driver in New York or Los Angeles lives more
dangerously than I did,'' he said, dismissing the bounty set on his
head by several logging companies. ``And about the only thing I
missed in the forest was getting together with Swiss friends and
singing in three-part harmony.''
   His flight from civilization initially took him to lonely Swiss
alpine pastures. There he tended cattle and made cheese - but not
for long.
   ``Even the smallest mountain village has a road,'' the wiry
45-year old said. ``And that road serves as the path for things
that we don't need -- things that we are forced to consume.''
   Manser never thought he'd leave the rain forest. Now, six months
into reacquainting himself with civilization, and near the end of
his exhausting crusade, it seems clear he'd rather be back in the
jungle.
   The hunter who could melt into the trees has become the hunted
as he tours the world's capitals to gather support for a moratorium
on Sarawak logging. There's no place to hide from reporters'
questions.
   ``I'm not here of my own choosing,'' he said. ''I'm here because
my Penan friends asked me to be here.''
   Environmental organizations say about 70 percent of the forest
in Malaysia's Sarawak state has been destroyed since large-scale
logging began in the early 1970s.
   Environmental pressure has slowed denuding of the rain forest in
Brazil and elsewhere. But large-scale logging in Sarawak, on the
northwest coast of Borneo, continues unabated, the organizations
say. About 60 percent of the hardwood harvested goes to Japan, the
rest to other industrial countries.
   Approximately 360 square miles of Sarawak rain forest disappear
each year, the environmental groups estimate.
   They say a particularly diverse environment is being lost,
harboring 2,000 species of flowering plants, 475 different birds
and 200 different mammals.
   But rain forest still covers millions of square miles of the
earth's surface. Thus, say logging advocates, the Sarawak harvest
contributes relatively little to environmentally harmful global
warming thought to be accelerating because of the disappearing
jungle.
   The Malaysian government denies that the loggers cause permanent
damage, asserting that trees are cut down selectively.
   But environmentalists and the Penan say that, because of the
jungle's tangle, one large tree falling takes most of the
surrounding vegetation with it. Bulldozers further mutilate the
forest as they drag logs away, leaving the denuded soil to erode.
   Approximately 300 Penan still roam the woods - holdouts against
Malaysian government pressure.
   After a series of jungle confrontations in the early 1980s with
government forces, more than 5,000 other Penan have exchanged their
nomadic ways for what the Malaysian government says is a better
life of farming.
   Manser disagreed, describing the settlements as tin-roofed
refugee camps seared by the hated tropical sun and with inadequate
and dirty drinking water.
   Hunters and gatherers are ill-suited for a life as rice farmers
and belong in the jungle, he argued.
   ``You really experience a sense of joy, and you see, hear or
smell that someone has come back from the hunt with prey,'' he
said. ``Everybody is happy, everyone talks and tells stories. It's
a lttle bit like paradise.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0073 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 1434EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-Wheeling-Pittsburgh     12-09 0341</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Wheeling-Pittsburgh,0371</SECOND>
<HEAD>Judge Says He'll Confirm Reorganization Plan</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ERIE, Pa. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A federal judge said he will confirm
Wheeling-Pittsburgh Steel Corp.'s reorganization plan this week,
ending five and a half years of litigation and allowing the
steelmaker to stay in business.
   U.S. Bankruptcy Judge Warren Bentz in overruled the final
objections of the at a hearing Saturday. Wheeling-Pittsburgh, which
employs about 7,100 people, has six major plants in western
Pennsylvania, Ohio and West Virginia.
   A lawqyer for the company, M. Bruce McCullough, called the
approval ``long overdue.''
   Denys Cronin, representing the reorganized company's principal
investor, said the plan ``provides a fair result for creditors and
shareholders alike. Now it's time to get back to concentrating on
the company's business.''
   The proposed reorganization plan calls for cash distribution of
about $600 million to creditors. Plan proponents say the
reorganization is viable and will allow the company to compete.
   The plan creates two corporations, a holding company chaired by
New York investor Ronald LeBow, who bought up 86 percent of the
company's secured debt, and an operating arm.
   Wheeling-Pittsburgh Corporation will be the holding company and
Wheeling-Pittsburgh Steel Corp. will be the operating subsidiary.
   James T. Gibbons, the company's reorganization planning
director, estimates that the company, as an ongoing enterprise, is
worth at least $1.1 billion to $1.2 billion.
   Gibbons said operating income over the next five years is
expected to drop somewhat because of the impact of oil price
increases. In spite of that, he said, the company plans an
aggressive $454 million capital improvement program.
   The confirmation came after Bentz overruled final complaints
from the U.S. Farmers' Home Administration. That came after
proponents of the confirmation plan agreed to set aside enough cash
and securities in a separate account to satisfy the maximum amount
of their claim plus interest, should the maximum be awarded later.
   FmHA and Equibank together hold about $44.2 million in loans to
Wheeling-Pittsburgh. They also claim interest on that sum.
   Earlier, Bentz overruled Environmental Protection Agency
objections to the confirmation, saying any penalties to be imposed
later for environmental violations could be worked out in the
normal course of the company's business.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0074 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 1441EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-AutoSales     12-09 0490</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Auto Sales,0600</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ten-Day Sales: Chrysler Backs Off</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By FREDERICK STANDISH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Auto Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DETROIT (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In the auto industry, 10-day sales reports have
long been considered a necessary evil.
   They've even been likened to foul-tasting medicine or income tax
forms, but one of the Big Three automakers, Chrysler Corp. has
decided the necessary evils are perhaps unnecessary.
   Beginning Jan. 15, Chrysler will no longer will issue sales
results three times a month. In moving to put out sales figures
only once a month, Chrysler breaks a nearly 50-year-old tradition
of reporting sales of North American-made vehicles every 10 days.
   The old American Motors Corp., which Chrysler bought in 1987,
broke the tradition once before, but returned to 10-day statements
after numerous leaks came out and corporate officials frequently
made low estimates for sales that would be easy to make.
   After Chrysler announced it would abandon 10-day sales reports,
General Motors Corp. said it was studying the move and Ford Motor
Co. said it would continue with the current system, for now at
least.
   No. 3 Chrysler said producing the reports was too costly, and
they serve ``no major purpose that isn't covered by a monthly
report.''
   But there's much more to it than that.
   Since production of Japanese nameplate cars is expanding in the
United States, year-to-year sales results of those cars look good,
with increases sometimes topping 100 percent. Meantime, the Big
Three are wrestling with excess factory capacity and sales are
sliding.
   So Chrysler, with retiring Chrysler Motors Chairman Bennett
Bidwell heading the charge, has been moaning about unfair
comparisons. GM and Ford, while sympathetic to Chrysler's
arguments, haven't complained nearly as much.
   There have been some arguments that if the Japanese companies
reported sales of all cars and trucks, no matter where they are
made, every 10 days, Chrysler quickly would jump back on the
reporting bandwagon.
   But there appears to be no chance the Japanese companies will do
that. They say sales results can be skewed simply by a delay in a
couple of ships coming over from Japan.
   In January, folks who collect the 10-day numbers, including
other automakers, Wall Street analysts and reporters will have to
become statistical dentists, trying to yank out numbers as
accurately as possible.
   Industry observers are now trying to come up with computer
models that can spit out Chrysler numbers based on production,past
sales rates, market shares, incentives and, perhaps, even weather.
All of those can affect sales during a given 10-day period.
   Those in favor of scrapping the 10-day reports say they are of
questionable value to begin with.
   They say incentives move in and out of the marketplace like
pistons. Cash rebates can inflate sales in one period and make it
look considerably better than the same period a year ago, no matter
what the underlying demand may be.
   In addition, 10 days of selling provides too little information
to draw meaningful conclusions or detect trends.
   Others say the figures can show a lot. For instance, there's no
restriction on using the numbers only for year-to-year comparisons.
If a company slaps a big incentive on one of its slow-selling
vehicles and sales shrink in a 10-day period, the company may start
wondering whether it has a turkey on its hands.
   The bottom line for a lot of number-crunchers is this: Sure the
10-day numbers may not be the most significant in the world, but
they're data that give a picture of an important industry.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0075 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 1504EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-MediaRecession Bjt   12-09 0745</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Media Recession, Bjt,0937</SECOND>
<HEAD>Signs Point to Deepening Media Recession</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SKIP WOLLENBERG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Business Week magazine, CBS News and The Wall
Street Journal close news bureaus and lay off workers.
   Employees at the New York Post take a big pay cut to keep the
paper running. The sports daily The National quits publishing a
Sunday paper. Murdoch Magazines closes the highly touted Men's Life
magazine after a single issue.
   The weak economic environment in which media companies have
operated the past year is no longer just a worry for the business
office. It has produced a marked decline in advertising, led to
tighter travel and expense budgets, and forced layoffs at some
companies.
   The downturn, seen as the worst in 20 years, is expected to be
the main topic of discussion this week at a conference for industry
analysts sponsored by the investment firm PaineWebber Inc. in New
York.
   Most observers see few signs that conditions will improve soon,
especially if the economy worsens.
   Analyst John Morton said newspapers are in a recession and
``things continue to get worse.'' Broadcast industry analyst
Jessica Reif said she doesn't foresee a turnaround in broadcasting
``for another year at least.''
   Magazine consultant Martin S. Walker said it appears 1991 will
be the second consecutive year of flat to declining ad growth for
magazines, which also face higher postal costs.
   ``There is no evidence yet of an upturn,'' PaineWebber analyst
J. Kendrick Noble said about the media business in general. ``It
won't improve until 1992.''
   Capital Cities-ABC Inc., whose ABC television network is making
a strong bid to overtake NBC in the prime-time audience ratings,
said in October that ad spending at the network and its seven TV
stations was ``significantly weaker'' than a year ago.
   CBS Inc. chief executive Laurence A. Tisch said in mid-November
that the company will have a rare loss in the fourth quarter and
lower earnings in 1991. The CBS television network, third in the
prime-time ratings, is expected to have an operating loss in 1991,
Tisch said.
   Advertisers' spending in newspapers was up a slim 0.7 percent
for the first nine months of the year, according to recent
estimates from the Newspaper Advertising Bureau.
   Morton, who works for the brokerage Lynch Jones &amp; Ryan in
Washington, D.C., said newspapers can expect to see advertising
demand get even softer. He said help-wanted advertising, for
instance, will contract as unemployment rises and real estate ads
will slump further as the economy sags.
   Magazine ad pages were off 3.7 percent for the first 10 months
of the year in the 170 consumer magazines surveyed by the Magazine
Publishers of America. Publishers face the prospect of postal rate
increases of 20 percent or more next year.
   ``No immediate recovery is in sight,'' Walker said.
   The media companies are trying to cope by imposing hiring
freezes, curbing expenses and, in some cases, laying off workers.
Some of them are boosting ad rates or cover prices and are trying
to be more creative about attracting ads.
   CBS has cut 40 to 50 employees from its 1,000-person news
division in the past few months, closed bureaus in Chicago and
Denver and slashed payments to its affiliated stations by 20
percent, or $30 million, next year.
   The New York Post persuaded its editorial staff earlier this
year to accept $20 million in pay cuts, which meant many staffers
are working four-day weeks. The newspaper's managers told the staff
the alternative was to close.
   The National, the 10{-month-old sports newspaper that now
publishes editions in 10 major markets, axed its Sunday edition
earlier this month and dismissed 18 news employees, including its
circulation manager.
   The Wall Street Journal recently announced it was closing its
Philadelphia bureau and would dismiss some of the 10 employees who
worked there, the first such layoffs in many years. The Journal is
cutting back space devoted to news, reducing the number of planned
special reports and cutting down on transfers.
   Business Week magazine recently said it would close its Denver
and Sao Paulo, Brazil, bureaus, and eliminated 10 jobs from its
staff of about 250.
   Others have gone much further. Murdoch Magazines closed Men's
Life magazine in October after one issue, saying it was too costly
in the current economic environment to build sufficient advertising
and readership.
   Media companies are trying to raise revenue in a variety of
ways.
   The Journal has raised its cover price by 50 percent to 75
cents, lifted subscription prices by 7.8 percent and hiked national
ad rates by 6 percent. USA Today has boosted its national ad rates
by 5.5 percent, while rates at the New York Times are going up 6.5
percent.
   National ad rates also were raised at the three newsweeklies,
with Time up 6.5 percent, Newsweek up 7 percent and U.S. News &amp;
World Report up 7.9 percent.
   Walker said magazines also are trying to team up with other
magazines to offer advertisers package deals in combinations of
their publications. Newsweek recently struck such an alliance with
Times Mirror Magazines, including Field &amp; Stream and Yachting.
   In the most comprehensive deal to date, Chrysler Corp. signed up
for a multimedia marketing package that could put Chrysler ads in
Time Warner's magazines and its cable TV systems, place its
vehicles in Warner Bros. films and let Chrysler dealers use Warner
Bros. records or Time-Life Books as premiums in promotions to get
people into the showroom.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0076 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 1518EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-MCA-Matsushita Bjt   12-09 0606</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-MCA-Matsushita, Bjt,0748</SECOND>
<HEAD>MCA Looks Ahead and Likes What It Sees</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN HORN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Entertainment Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>UNIVERSAL CITY, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   MCA Inc. has seen how bright the
future can be with its new owner because the entertainment
conglomerate knows how gloomy the past was without it.
   For more than 20 years, an MCA subsidiary labored to perfect the
technology behind the laser disc. MCA's Discovision Associates
developed 1,400 patents at the heart of the compact disc and video
disc players.
   But for lack of a hardware partner like pending new owner
Matsushita Electrical Industrial Co., MCA and partner International
Business Machines Corp. were forced last year to sell Discovision
for $200 million.
   Buyer Pioneer Electronics Corp. of Japan took the Discovision
technology and ran with it. That probably wouldn't have happened if
the Matsushita deal had taken place earlier, MCA President Sidney
Sheinberg said in an interview.
   ``Either we would have been convinced that the laservision
system wasn't going to be the system of the future, or else we
would have had in the family the kind of technology, the kind of
skills and the kind of support that we would have needed to launch
it,'' he said.
   MCA is banking that its new $6.6 billion marriage to Matsushita
will yield a company poised to exploit any future new technologies.
   ``I once told somebody that the first step in planning for the
future is to be sure that you're part of it,'' Sheinberg said.
``And I think by this transaction we have tried to ensure that we
are part of the future.''
   MCA Chairman Lew Wasserman agreed. ``I obviously think that
there are many synergisms - a greater expansion of opportunities -
or I wouldn't have recommended the deal to the board,'' he said.
   If recent blockbuster Hollywood mergers are used as a benchmark,
however, MCA is not guaranteed to become an overnight world power.
   Time Warner Inc., strapped with close to $11 billion in debt,
has not become as dominant as some believed it would, and there are
rumblings the company's music division might be for sale to the
right buyer.
   Australia's News Corp., which owns 20th Century Fox, is
suffocating under $8.1 billion in debt and may sell assets. Sony
Corp.'s $3.4 billion buyout of Columbia Pictures Entertainment in
1989 hasn't rattled Hollywood's rafters either, with Columbia and
sister studio Tri-Star Pictures lagging.
   Pathe Communications Corp. has sold off so many movie rights to
finance its $1.3 billion purchase of MGM-UA Communications Co. that
there's scarcely any money left for growth.
   The distinct benefit of the MCA deal is that it leaves the
company with no shortage of cash.
   ``This one has got one enormous advantage which is rare ... and
that is that there is no financing involved,'' Sheinberg said.
``This isn't like a deal with Giancarlo Parretti,'' the head of
cash-poor Pathe.
   Where will the MCA-Matsushita money go?
   ``I think the global potentials are awesome,'' Wasserman said.
``You certainly have a population of something like 800 million
people in Europe, now that the curtains have come down, with very
little filmed entertainment.''
   He said the music business ``at the moment growing modestly in
the United States but it's exploding overseas.''
   Wasserman and Sheinberg, both under new five-year contracts to
Matsushita, declined to say what companies they might pursue to
broaden the conglomerate's reach. But it seems certain the company
will pursue high-definition television.
   ``It could very well be that the product will be distributed in
a different fashion and instead of (film) prints arriving, it could
very well be that it comes from a big satellite and it's projected
on high-definition television,'' Sheinberg said.
   Asked if he would be interested in companies such as Warner
Music or PolyGram, a division of Dutch giant Phillips N.V.,
Wasserman replied, ``very definitely.''
   There are some bothered by the trend to merge giant companies
with capacities to make the hardware equipment and software such as
movies, music and television shows.
   Arizona's Go-Video filed an antitrust lawsuit to block the
merger of MCA and Matsushita, claiming they are conspiring to
sabotage sales of its videocassette recorders.
   ``If they have control of the software they can control what
kind of format it's released on,'' Go-Video lawyer Joseph Alioto
said. ``If you don't own their hardware, you won't be able to see
the pictures.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0077 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 1528EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-OPEC Bjt   12-09 0553</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-OPEC, Bjt,0681</SECOND>
<HEAD>OPEC Oil Ministers Meet This Week Facing the Unexpected</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SALLY JACOBSEN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BRUSSELS, Belgium (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   OPEC is facing the unexpected as it
meets this week - plunging crude prices brought on by prospects of
an oil glut and reduced military tensions in the Persian Gulf
region.
   But analysts doubt the ministers of the 13-nation Organization
of Petroleum Exporting Countries will be anxious at a strategy
session opening Wednesday to do much to try to hold down production
and lift prices higher.
   ``Everybody is going to wait for the crisis to finish before
taking any concrete measures,'' said Peter Bogin, associate
director for oil markets at Cambridge Energy Research Associates in
Paris.
   ``They're going to be worried that prices are falling, but no
one is going to take action about it,'' he said.
   In late August, the ministers gave the go-ahead for higher
production to make up for the loss of about 4 million barrels of
crude pulled off the market after Iraq invaded neighboring Kuwait.
Both are OPEC members.
   In the four months since the occupation, speculation about the
outbreak of war in the oil-rich gulf region sent prices as high as
$41 a barrel. The cartel's benchmark of $21 a barrel was surpassed,
with a basket of crudes monitored by the group averaging $37.04 a
barrel last month.
   But in recent days, with the easing of tensions, prices have
tumbled to levels not seen since August. At week's end, prices for
North Sea Brent Blend, the most widely traded international crude,
were trading in the range of $25 to $26 a barrel. The benchmark
American brand slipped below $28 a barrel.
   With surging OPEC production, storage tanks have been filled to
the top. But demand has weakened, partly because of
warmer-than-expected weather in the United States and other
oil-importing nations.
   Even so, it was unlikely that OPEC ministers would be quick to
reimpose their quota system and call a halt to overproduction
during their winter conference at cartel headquarters in Vienna. A
monitoring panel will begin work on Tuesday.
   ``They couldn't put the quota system back in,'' said Pierre
Terzian, editor of the Paris-based newsletter Petrostrategies. ``It
would mean the crisis has ended.''
   Said Bogin: ``We're expecting very little. But we think there
could be a lot of backroom conversation about getting ...
production levels down.''
   Terzian predicted, though, that the ministers would signal their
intent to nail production caps back on the producers once the
crisis has ended. ``They must make the market understand that there
will be a halt to the glut if there is a settlement,'' he said.
   Indonesia's oil minister, Ginandjar Kartasasmita, acknowledged
the difficulty the cartel would face in slowing down pumping.
   ``It is not easy to persuade all OPEC members to cut output
after spending a lot to pump oil as much as they could to meet an
emergency,'' he said in Jakarta last week.
   With the suspension of their quota system, the oil-producing
nations turned up the taps. Led by heavyweight Saudi Arabia, the
OPEC nations supplied nearly 23 million barrels of oil a day to the
market in November, according to the International Energy Agency.
   Saudi Arabia, the world's largest crude exporter, pumped an
estimated 7.9 million barrels a day last month, according to the
agency, an arm of the Organization for Economic Cooperation and
Development.
   Private analysts predicted the Saudis will go even higher in
December, possibly reaching as much as 8.5 million barrels a day.
Before the crisis, the kingdom's production quota was 5.4 million
barrels a day, giving the cartel an overall supply ceiling of 22.5
million barrels daily.
   In addition to Saudi Arabia, analysts said Venezuela, the United
Arab Emirates, Iran, Nigeria and Libya have lifted output to help
make up for the loss of Iraqi and Kuwaiti crude.
   OPEC members are Algeria, Ecuador, Gabon, Indonesia, Iran, Iraq,
Kuwait, Libya, Nigeria, Qatar, Saudi Arabia, the United Arab
Emirates and Venezuela.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901209-0078 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-09-90 2147EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-Mexico-Telmex     12-09 0331</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mexico-Telmex,0377</SECOND>
<HEAD>Winner of Phone Company Sell-off Bid Announced</HEAD>
<HEAD>Also moved on general news wires.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN RICE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MEXICO CITY (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An international consortium that includes
Southwestern Bell will pay $1.76 billion for controlling interest
in Mexico's telephone monopoly under a privatization program, the
finance ministry announced Sunday.
   The winning bid of $2.03 a share will give the group 20.4
percent in Telefonos de Mexico, a trouble-plagued system operating
about 4.1 million telephones.
   In addition to St. Louis-based Southwestern Bell, the winning
consortium also includes Mexico's Grupo Carso and France's Cable &amp;
Radio.
   A bid of $1.69 million was offered by a group Acciones y Valores
de Mexico, GTE Corp. of Stamford, Conn., and Telefonica de Espana.
Mexico's Grupo Gentor offered nearly $1.6 billion.
   The government holds more than $4 billion worth of shares in the
company, which is valued at roughly $8 billion. It plans to sell
the remainder of its shares on national and international stock
markets.
   The winners are supposed to post guaranteed funds by Dec. 20,
according to a timetable announced earlier.
   Finance ministry spokesman Jack Rogosiski said all three offers
``were satisfactory.'' The choice ultimately hinged solely on
price, he said.
   President Carlos Salinas de Gortari in September 1989 announced
plans to sell off Telmex as part of a program of privatization to
help revive the national economy.
   The effort seeks to improve phone service, expand the system and
strengthen research and development.
   Earlier Sunday, three cabinet minister signed documents to give
Telmex workers 4.4 percent of the shares.
   The shares are to be turned over to the workers within eight
years, after a $325 million credit from the government is paid off,
according to the government's Notimex news agency.
   Telmex had launched a three-year modernization program to help
make it more attractive to buyers.
   The company in September signed $300 million worth of contracts
with a group led by American Telephone &amp; Telegraph Co. for a new
optic-fiber cable network and terminals.
   Poor service by Telmex, a state monopoly since the mid-1960s,
has often been blamed for helping hold back economic development in
the nation of about 84 million people.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
</Collection>
