<Collection>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0001 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 2327EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Lockheed-Subchaser     07-22 0484</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lockheed-Subchaser,0501</SECOND>
<HEAD>Lockheed Chief Says Cancellation of Aircraft Contract Not All Bad</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Navy announced it was terminating
Lockheed Corp.'s $600 million contract for the P-7A patrol plane,
saying the company had defaulted in its attempt to build a new
anti-submarine plane.
   But the company's head said Saturday that the cancellation had
ridded Lockheed of a costly headache and may even help in the long
run.
   The Navy said in its announcement Friday that Lockheed had
defaulted on the contract in January 1989.
   Under a default, the service can demand a full refund of all
money paid the company or can find an alternative manufacturer for
the P-7A and sue Lockheed for any costs in excess of the contract.
   Lockheed said it would appeal the termination under terms of
default.
   Company Chairman Daniel M. Tellep said he considered it unlikely
that the Pentagon would look for an alternative producer. But the
Navy could still demand a refund of the approximately $200 million
it paid Lockheed before the cancellation.
   Lockheed has incurred costs of about $300 million on the program
so far, Tellep said. Last year, it took a $300 million charge
against profits to pay for expected cost overruns. The company has
already written off the full cost of the program.
   ``If our appeal is successful, as we expect it to be, we will
recover a major portion of the prior $300 million,'' Tellep said.
   ``Lockheed may be far better off than if it built the aircraft
under the Navy's terms even though the company lost the P-7A
program in the dispute with the Navy,'' Tellep said.
   Although the contract was valued at $600 million over four
years, Lockheed officials said the firm was facing a project
overrun as high as $1 billion on the fixed-price contract.
   Tellep said the company expects no further losses.
   He said the cancellation signaled to Lockheed and other defense
contractors that the Pentagon now is unwilling to bail out
contractors facing losses on weapons programs.
   ``The problem we are seeing in the industry once more
underscores the disastrous effects of fixed-price, total-package
procurement,'' he said. ``And it is not beneficial either to the
(Pentagon) or to the contractors.''
   The termination, if it stands, is the latest in a series of
blows against the aerospace firm.
   Since mid-1988, contracts for four military planes, including
the P-3 sub-hunter, have wound down, and defense cuts are looming
because of the national budget deficit and the end of the Cold War.
   Lockheed has also recently ended production of the F-117A
stealth fighter, the C-5B cargo plane and the TR-1 spy plane. Since
mid-1988 about 9,000 workers have been laid off.
   Earlier this year, Lockheed announced it would move some of its
production to Marietta, Ga. by the mid-1990s, at a potential cost
of up to 4,500 jobs.
   Lockheed said the move would save $75 million a year.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0002 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 2332EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-AssaultWeapons     07-22 0254</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Assault Weapons,250</SECOND>
<HEAD>Report: Banned Assault Weapons Being Admitted After Modifications</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Bush administration, saying it has no
choice under the law, has approved importation of some previously
banned firearms that were modified to get around the ban, according
to a published report.
   Relying on documents obtained under the Freedom of Information
Act by the Firearms Policy Project, The Washington Post said
permission has been granted to import new versions of the Uzi,
AK-47, Galil, HK-91 and other assault weapons. The importation of
those weapons was prohibited last year.
   The paper, in Monday's editions, quoted officials as saying the
new versions have been altered to remove flash suppressors, grenade
launchers, bayonet attachments and other military-style features
that made them unsuitable for ``sporting purposes.''
   Once the military-style features were removed ``they no longer
fit the category of semiautomatic, assault-type rifle'' and the
Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco and Firearms had no grounds for keeping
them out, the paper quoted BATF spokeswoman Dot Koester as saying.
   However, the guns still can accept magazines of up to 30 rounds
of ammunition and have pistol-grip type stocks that enable them to
be reloaded quickly.
   Josh Sugarman, director of the group that made the documents
available to the Post, was quoted as saying those features make
them every bit as deadly as the banned weapons and ``makes a
mockery of last year's action.''
   Attempts to obtain a home telephone listing Sunday night for Ms.
Koester were unsuccessful and Sugarman's telephone was answered by
an answering machine.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0003 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 2349EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a BC-LOT--WeekendLotteries     07-22 0871</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-LOT--Weekend Lotteries,1041</SECOND>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<HEAD>CALIFORNIA</HEAD>
<HEAD>Decco</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning playing card numbers picked Saturday night
for the California Lottery's daily ``Decco'' game:
   Hearts: King.
   Clubs: Jack.
   Diamonds: King.
   Spades: 5.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>CONNECTICUT</HEAD>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEWINGTON, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning combination picked Saturday
in the Connecticut State Lottery's ``Daily Lottery'' drawing was:
   0-0-9
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Play 4</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEWINGTON, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning combination picked Saturday
in the Connecticut State Lottery's ``Play 4'' drawing was:
   0-3-2-1.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>DELAWARE</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DOVER, Del. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   These Delaware lotteries were drawn Saturday
night:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   8-4-0
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Play Four</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   9-1-5-2
</TEXT>
<HEAD>FLORIDA</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected Saturday in
the Florida Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Cash 3</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   8-7-3
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   20-29-23-47-40-15
</TEXT>
<HEAD>ILLINOIS</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SPRINGFIELD, Ill. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the Illinois State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   8-9-5
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick Four</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   8-3-5-6
</TEXT>
<HEAD>LOTTO</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   5-8-18-23-45-48
</TEXT>
<HEAD>INDIANA</HEAD>
<HEAD>Lotto Cash</HEAD>
<DATELINE>INDIANAPOLIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday night in the Hoosier Lottery's Lotto Cash game:
   16-20-22-24-29-39
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Ind Lottery Glance</HEAD>
<DATELINE>INDIANAPOLIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the Hoosier Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Three</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   2-5-0
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Four</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   2-4-0-1
</TEXT>
<HEAD>IOWA</HEAD>
<HEAD>Iowa Lotto</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DES MOINES, Iowa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers drawn Saturday night
in ``Iowa Lotto'' are:
   9-12-18-25-26-37.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>KANSAS</HEAD>
<HEAD>Kan. Cash Lotto</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOPEKA, Kan. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers in the Kansas Cash Lotto
drawing Saturday night are:
   3-6-20-21-32-33
</TEXT>
<HEAD>KENTUCKY</HEAD>
<HEAD>Kentucky Lottery</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOUISVILLE, Ky. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are Saturday's winning numbers
selected by the Kentucky Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Kentucky Cash:
   0-0-6.
   </HEAD>
<HEAD>Lotto:
   9-11-15-23-34-38.
   </HEAD>
<HEAD>MARYLAND</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BALTIMORE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   These Maryland lotteries were drawn Saturday
night:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   6-7-1
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Play Four</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   7-0-3-6
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   7-13-17-18-32-34
</TEXT>
<HEAD>MASSACHUSETTS</HEAD>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BRAINTREE, Mass. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers drawn Saturday night
in the ``Massachusetts Daily Lottery'' were:
   7-1-3-1
</TEXT>
<HEAD>MICHIGAN</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DETROIT (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected Saturday in
the Michigan State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   6-7-4
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily-4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   9-5-1-5
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto 47</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   23, 25, 31, 37, 40, 45
</TEXT>
<HEAD>MISSOURI</HEAD>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ST. LOUIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers in Missouri's Lotto drawing
Saturday night:
   9-17-25-26-42-43
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 3</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ST. LOUIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers in Saturday's Missouri
Lottery Daily Pick 3 game:
   5-7-1
</TEXT>
<HEAD>NEW JERSEY</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TRENTON, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday night in the New Jersey State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 3</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   1-0-7
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   7-5-6-2
</TEXT>
<HEAD>NEW YORK</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ALBANY, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the New York State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Number</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   3-8-0
</TEXT>
<HEAD>WinFour</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   1-8-0-4
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 10</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ALBANY, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the New York State Lottery's Pick 10 game:
   9, 10, 12, 19, 20, 25, 26, 30, 34, 36, 47, 52, 64, 68, 69, 71,
73, 74, 75, 79.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ALBANY, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the New York State Lottery's Lotto game:
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   3, 5, 6, 26, 31, 39. The supplementary number was 13.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>NORTHERN NEW ENGLAND</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CONCORD, N.H. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the daily New Hampshire, Vermont and Maine lotteries:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 3</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   7-5-4
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   1-5-5-4
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Tri-State Megabucks</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CONCORD, N.H. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers in the
``Tri-State Megabucks'' game for New Hampshire, Vermont and Maine:
   10-19-20-31-34-39
</TEXT>
<HEAD>OHIO</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CLEVELAND (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected Saturday
night in the Ohio Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 3 Numbers</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   9-9-5
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 4 Numbers</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   8-9-9-1
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto Glance</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CLEVELAND (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected Saturday
night in the Ohio Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Super Lotto</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   15-21-24-29-30-31
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Kicker</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   1-1-2-2-0-9
</TEXT>
<HEAD>OREGON</HEAD>
<HEAD>Daily 4</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PORTLAND, Ore. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are Saturday's winning numbers in the
``Oregon Daily 4'' lottery game:
   6-7-9-7
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Megabucks</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PORTLAND, Ore. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are Saturday's winning numbers in the
``Oregon Megabucks'' lottery game:
   9-19-28-37-39-43
</TEXT>
<HEAD>PENNSYLVANIA</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HARRISBURG (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected Saturday
in the Pennsylvania State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Number</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   7-5-0
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Big 4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   4-1-4-1
</TEXT>
<HEAD>RHODE ISLAND</HEAD>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CRANSTON, R.I. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers in the Rhode Island
daily lottery drawing for Saturday were:
   3-6-7-7
</TEXT>
<HEAD>VIRGINIA</HEAD>
<HEAD>Pick 3</HEAD>
<DATELINE>RICHMOND (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   These numbers were drawn Saturday in the
Virginia Lottery's Pick 3 game:
   6-2-0
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<DATELINE>RICHMOND (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   These numbers were drawn Saturday night in the
Virginia Lottery's Lotto game:
   7-11-12-13-18-34
</TEXT>
<HEAD>WASHINGTON</HEAD>
<DATELINE>OLYMPIA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are winning numbers selected Saturday in the
Washington State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   3-5-9
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   8-9-12-29-31-36
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Quinto</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Five of Hearts, Queen of Diamonds, Ten of Diamonds, Six of
Diamonds, Seven of Clubs.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Friday's Daily Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   4-7-1
</TEXT>
<HEAD>WASHINGTON, DC</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The following results were drawn Saturday in
the District of Columbia Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lucky Numbers Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   7-5-2
</TEXT>
<HEAD>D.C. Four Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   7-1-5-5
</TEXT>
<HEAD>D.C. Daily Double Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   3, 31
</TEXT>
<HEAD>D.C. Quick Cash Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   16-4-28-12-24-8
</TEXT>
<HEAD>WEST VIRGINIA</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CHARLESTON, W.Va. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the West Virginia State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily 3</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   9-6-5
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily 4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   9-4-0-5
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0004 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 2353EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-SouthKorea     07-22 0379</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-South Korea,0388</SECOND>
<HEAD>South Korean Opposition Legislators Resign, Demand New Elections</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SEOUL, South Korea (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The entire opposition in Parliament,
angry about the alliance of the governing party with two smaller
groups, resigned en masse Monday and called for new general
elections.
   The 79 opposition deputies in the 299-member National Assembly
turned in their resignations to Assembly Speaker Park Chun-kyu at
his office in the Parliament building.
   It marks the first time that all of the opposition members in
the National Assembly resigned.
   The mass resignations came at a time when the government of
President Roh Tae-woo has announced its willingness to negotiate a
border opening with Communist North Korea. Preparations are being
made for the first meeting between the prime ministers of the two
Koreas.
   The governing Democratic Liberal Party said the resignations
would not be immediately accepted. Under Korean law, the speaker
can hold the resignations until the next Parliament session in
September, when they would be voted upon.
   The opposition Party for Peace and Democracy, which has 71
seats, and the splinter Democratic Party, with eight seats, said
their legislators and their staffs were resigning and would not
accept their salaries as of Monday.
   Kim Dae-jung, head of the largest opposition party, welcomed
Roh's call for opening the border with North Korea. But he warned
Roh not to make the border opening a partisan issue.
   Opposition forces have charged Roh with using North-South talks
as a means of diverting public attention from domestic problems,
including inflation, land speculation, corruption and the need for
more democratic reforms.
   The opposition's demand for new general elections results from
the merger in January between Roh's party and two former opposition
groups. The opposition contends the merger amounted to a coup,
which vaulted Roh's forces in the Parliament from a minority to
more than a two-thirds majority.
   The opposition lawmakers are also demanding that local elections
be held for the first time since they were abolished 30 years ago.
Local elections are planned for this year, but no date has been set
yet.
   Merger talks are under way to unify a nationwide dissident group
and the two opposition parties by September. If successful, it
would mark the first time South Korea's faction-riddled opposition
have been united under one banner.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0005 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 2354EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-France-ArmsSmuggling     07-22 0298</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-France-Arms Smuggling,0304</SECOND>
<HEAD>Embassy Security Officials Charged With Smuggling Weapons</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MARSEILLE, France (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The security chief at the French
Embassy in Beirut is among three police officers formally charged
with roles in a ring that allegedly smuggled weapons to the French
underworld, a court source says.
   The three, who allegedly bought weapons from Lebanese
militiamen, were charged on Saturday and Judge Patrick Ardid
ordered them taken to a detention house in this port city, said the
source, who would not be quoted by name.
   The Beirut security chief, Jean-Claude Labourdette, 47, had been
posted at the French Embassy since 1984 and was identified by the
other suspects as the ringleader. He was flown to France from
Lebanon on Thursday.
   The other two suspects, Patrick Jacquin, 28, and Jean-Neol
Lebat, 30, were brought back from Washington, where they had been
serving as security officers in the French Embassy. Both had
formerly been posted to the embassy in Beirut.
   Marseille prosecutor Olivier Dropet said last week that
Labourdette was among about 10 policemen implicated so far in the
arms ring, which allegedly sold in Marseille about 100 assault
rifles, automatic pistols and other arms.
   The arms allegedly were purchased in Lebanon, a former French
mandate, and shipped back in diplomatic trunks that were exempt
from exemption.
   The Foreign Ministry ordered an internal investigation of the
scandal but said last week that no evidence was found that any
diplomatic personnel had been involved.
   The gang then allegedly resold the weapons to criminals
including a gang that specialized in armored car robberies. Police
said rocket launchers discovered at Labourdette's home south of
Paris on Wednesday were of a type used in attacks on armored cars.
   Two security guards were killed in a holdup with assault rifles
in Marseille in March.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0006 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 2356EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Lite-LimestoneCapitals     07-22 0334</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Lite-Limestone Capitals,0344</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bedford, Ind., the World's Limestone Capital? No, Says Nebraska
Town.</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BEDFORD, Ind. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Everyone knows Bedford is the Limestone
Capital of the World, right? As it turns out, no one told Weeping
Water, Neb.
   ``It didn't seem real,'' said Janet Demaree, a Bedford resident
who recently traveled to Nebraska only to find Weeping Water touted
as none other than the Limestone Capital of the World. The claim
was right there in the South East Nebraska Visitor's Guide that
Demaree picked up at a motel.
   ``I read it and I thought, `They're telling a lie.' Everyone
knows it's Bedford,'' Demaree said.
   Kay Lindsey didn't know. The city clerk of Weeping Water, a town
of 1,100 about 30 miles south of Omaha, said she had never heard of
Bedford, let alone its claim to limestone greatness. Bedford, with
a population of 18,000, is situated 90 miles south of Indianapolis.
   Many older buildings in Weeping Water are built of native
limestone, and residents celebrate the Fourth of July with a
Limestone@Independence Day celebration complete with tours of
quarries, dancing and fireworks, the tour guide said.
   ``It was like reading our own newspaper,'' Demaree said.
   Bill McDonald, executive director of the Indiana Limestone
Institute, was equally surprised. Apart from Bath, England,
McDonald said he can think of no other area in the world with a
limestone industry as developed as Bedford's.
   But five companies mine limestone in Weeping Water and ``that's
practically what the whole town is,'' Lindsey said.
   There are some distinctions. The Weeping Water stone is taken
from underground mines, rather than quarries as in Bedford, and
most of it is processed into gravel.
   That may be why Bill Finley of the Weeping Water Valley
Historical Society can think of no nationally known building
constructed from Weeping Water limestone.
   Indiana limestone, on the other hand, was used to build the
Empire State Building and the United Nations headquarters in New
York, as well as the Pentagon and National Cathedral in Washington.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0007 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 0012EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Philippines-Quake 1stLd-Writethru a0561 07-22 0782</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Philippines-Quake, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0561,0808</SECOND>
<HEAD>Filipino Miners Search for Survivors, Death Toll Reaches 862</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS thruout to UPDATE with death toll rising to 862, Sunday
developments; no pickup.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By CLARO CORTES</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BAGUIO, Philippines (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Rescue workers said Sunday they were
giving up hope of finding more survivors trapped in the ruins of
buildings here, six days after an earthquake struck, killing 862
people.
   Rescue workers said they would meet later in the day with
Filipino authorities to discuss calling off the search for more
survivors in the ruins of nearly 30 buildings in the mountain
resort of Baguio.
   Willie McMartin of Scotland, leader of a British rescue team,
said his group would decide whether to shift from rescue operations
to recovering the dead.
   McMartin said that tapping sounds beneath the ruins of the Hyatt
Hotel in Baguio had ceased and it appeared that no one remained
alive there.
   The official death toll from Monday's quake rose to 862 as more
bodies were discovered, and more than 3,000 people were reported
injured. But officials said the death toll may surpass 1,000
because hundreds are feared dead in an industrial park and a remote
farming area in Nueva Vizcaya province.
   Hundreds of survivors were flown Sunday to Manila from Baguio,
where food and fuel supplies were running low. The evacuees
included an undetermined number of foreigners, including Jordanians
and Europeans.
   On Saturday, Communist rebels declared a unilateral cease-fire
in Manila and the quake-ravaged north. Right-wing military
dissidents offered to declare a cease-fire if the government
suspended efforts to capture them.
   Many leaders of the dissident movement are graduates of the
Philippine Military Academy in Baguio, one of the towns hardest hit
by the quake.
   In Baguio, Filipino miners burrowed beneath the ruins of the
Hyatt Hotel in a desperate bid to reach any survivors trapped under
the rubble.
   More than 40 people remain unaccounted for at the Hyatt, one of
eight hotels in Baguio which collapsed or were badly damaged in the
quake, which measured 7.7 on the Richter scale.
   Officials had already given up hope of finding more people alive
at the other hotels.
   The rescue efforts were temporarily suspended Saturday after
small aftershocks rattled Baguio, cracking the walls of its
cathedral. The aftershocks were also felt in Manila, 130 miles to
the south.
   The miners strengthened their tunnel and later resumed their
efforts.
   Filipino miners had said earlier that when they tapped against
debris blocking access to the hotel's basement gymnasium, they
could hear distinctive knocks in response.
   But McMartin said the tapping ceased following the aftershocks.
   ``There are no sounds at all,'' McMartin told reporters. ``It
means effectively that the person making the sounds has died.''
   Asked if he believed anyone was still alive at the Hyatt,
McMartin replied: ``No.''
   On Sunday, Roman Catholic masses were said outdoors in Baguio's
Burnham Park because Bishop Ernesto Salgado said it was too
dangerous to worship inside the cathedral.
   Salgado said priests visited collapsed buildings, blessing the
bodies of those who may be entombed there.
   Jose de Jesus, presidential relief coordinator for Baguio, said
135 people were believed trapped inside eight factories but all are
believed dead.
   De Jesus said information on deaths and damage was still
trickling in from remote areas, including Nueva Vizcaya province
where many villages and roads were buried by landslides.
   Philippine pilots who surveyed the areas saw huge columns of
survivors walking over the mountains to safety. Pilots said they
looked like ``columns of ants'' silhouetted against the barren
mountain slopes.
   Reports Sunday said at least 104 people were killed in Nueva
Vizcaya. Villagers said many of the dead were children entombed
while playing on hillsides when the quake struck.
   Presidential spokesman Horacio Paredes said experts believe
trapped survivors would not be able to survive past Tuesday and
officials will soon have to decide when to abandon rescue efforts.
   Radio station DZRH said a group of village chiefs from the
Baguio area complained Saturday that food supplies flown to the
city had not been distributed to them, and people were suffering
from hunger.
   ``It's all just in the newspapers. It's all talk,'' said one
chief, who gave his name only as Panlillo.
   President Corazon Aquino Friday had defended her government
against criticism that relief efforts were poorly organized.
   In Baguio, witnesses said they feared an outbreak of disease if
the government did not increase relief efforts.
   ``There's no sanitation,'' said John Pike, 44, an Australian who
was evacuated to Manila on Saturday. ``The situation is horrible
and not much is being done. In a week there might be an outbreak of
typhoid.''
   Armed gangs were looting and mugging pedestrians at night in
Baguio.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0008 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 0039EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Obit-Pressler     07-22 0179</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Pressler,0185</SECOND>
<HEAD>Father of U.S. Sen. Larry Pressler Dead at 74</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SIOUX FALLS, S.D. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Antone ``Tony'' Pressler, the father of
U.S. Sen. Larry Pressler, R-S.D., died Saturday after a lengthy
battle with Alzheimer's disease. He was 74.
   Pressler spent his life in Humboldt, a town near Sioux Falls
where he and his wife, Loretta, farmed and raised their five
children. In the mid-1970s, he was diagnosed as having Alzheimer's
disease, a progressive neurological disorder with an estimated 2.5
million American victims.
   Pressler died at a nursing home in Salem.
   His son served in the House from 1975 to 1979 before winning the
first of two terms to the Senate.
   ``Tony was very low key,'' said a friend and neighbor, Ed Lias,
58. ``Their children have all done very well. But he seemed like he
expected things like that. He never talked about it.
   ``He spent most of this life right on the farm. He was a very
good family man and a steward of the soil,'' Lias said.
   Funeral services were scheduled for Wednesday in Humboldt.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0009 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 0059EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Brennan'sSuccessor 5thLd-Writethru a0644 07-22 0983</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brennan's Successor, 5th Ld-Writethru, a0644,950</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush Says He'll Move Quickly To Find Brennan Replacement</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: SUBS 22nd graf, ``In addition xxx to fix spelling of Hinojosa</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By JAMES ROWLEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush seized the opportunity Saturday
to replace the Supreme Court's leading liberal by launching a
hurry-up search for the successor to retired Justice William J.
Brennan.
   Conservatives quickly staked their claim for a continuation of
the Reagan legacy on the high court, while liberals expressed
concern that the next appointment would tip the scales on abortion,
affirmative action and other divisive social issues.
   Top candidates to succeed Brennan include Solicitor General
Kenneth W. Starr, federal appellate judges Edith H. Jones and
Patrick E. Higginbotham of the 5th Circuit, William W. Wilkins Jr.
of the 4th Circuit and David Souter of the 1st Circuit.
   A day after Brennan made his surprise announcement, Bush
convened an early-morning meeting with chief of staff John Sununu,
White House counsel C. Boyden Gray and Attorney General Dick
Thornburgh to begin the process of finding a new Supreme Court
justice.
   Following the 75-minute meeting, Bush vowed to make a quick
nomination.
   ``I am going to try to make this determination as soon as
possible. The process is moving,'' the president told reporters as
he left Washington aboard Air Force One to christen a new aircraft
carrier in Newport News, Va.
   Gray and Thornburgh continued the discussions during an
hour-long meeting at the Justice Department.
   Administration officials predicted the review of some 15
candidates would be concluded with an announcement of a nominee in
a week to 10 days.
   Bush is eager to have a candidate nominated and confirmed by the
Senate in time to take the bench for the Supreme Court's next term,
which begins the first Monday in October, officials said.
   Brennan's unexpected departure at age 84 gives the president his
first Supreme Court appointment, as well as an opportunity to
consolidate gains that conservatives made on the high court during
the Reagan administration.
   Before Brennan's retirement, conservatives held a slender 5-4
majority on the high court, but Brennan's successor would give them
a 6-3 majority.
   Bush declined to discuss the names of the candidates under
review or characterize their judicial philosophy.
   Starr, 44, who serves as the Justice Department's chief Supreme
Court advocate, has been considered a prime candidate for the high
court since Bush took office.
   When he gave up a lifetime appointment on the U.S. Circuit Court
of Appeals here to become solicitor general, there was widespread
speculation Starr was positioning himself for the high court.
   Souter, 50, appointed to the New Hampshire Supreme Court in 1983
by Sununu when he was governor of the state, was named to the 1st
Circuit earlier this year.
   He was promoted by Sen. Warren Rudman, N.H., as an alternative
nominee after the Senate killed President Reagan's nomination of
Robert Bork in 1987.
   Wilkins, who chairs the U.S. Sentencing Commission, is a
perennial candidate of Sen. Strom Thurmond, R-S.C., the ranking GOP
member of the Senate Judiciary Committee.
   The list of possible candidates includes other federal appellate
judges: Roger J. Miner and Ralph K. Winter Jr., both of the 2nd
Circuit; J. Harvie Wilkinson III of the 4th Circuit; and Pamela A.
Rymer, a former federal district judge whom Bush recently put on
the 9th Circuit.
   Other possible candidate are Clarence Thomas, a black
conservative recently named to the D.C. Circuit here and Laurence
Silberman, a member of the same court. On Friday, Silberman joined
in a ruling that set aside Oliver L. North's Iran-Contra
convictions.
   He was reportedly passed over for consideration during the
Reagan administration because of concerns he lacked judicial
temperament.
   Also mentioned as a possible candidate is U.S. Trade
Representative Carla Hills. But conservatives are expected to fight
her appointment to the Supreme Court because they suspect she is
pro-choice on the abortion issue.
   In addition, The Washington Post reported in Sunday's editions
that Ferdinand Fernandez, a federal judge from California, and
Ricardo Hinojosa, a federal judge from Texas, are among those being
mentioned. Either would be the first Hispanic on the high court.
The New York Times listed Alex Kozinski, a member of the 9th
Circuit in San Francisco, as one of the federal appellate judges
under consideration.
   Pro-choice groups issued statements mourning Brennan's
retirement from the court, which was hailed by organizations
opposed to abortion.
   The anti-abortion Concerned Women for America said it had sent a
letter to Bush urging appointment of Edith Jones or someone with a
similar legal philosophy.
   Kate Michelman, executive director of the National Abortion
Rights Action League, sought to spur political pressure on Bush to
appoint a pro-choice justice.
   ``Unless there is a massive and unprecedented political
mobilization, Justice Brennan's departure may be a death knell for
the right to choose in America,'' she said in a statement.
   ``Republicans have vowed that their party can accommodate
pro-choice as well as anti-choice proponents. This is the time to
put reality behind that rhetoric,'' she said.
   Thornburgh has long insisted ``there are no litmus tests''
applied by the Bush administration on such issues as abortion
during judicial selection. An administration official, speaking on
condition of anonymity, said that policy holds for this appointment.
   Sen. Joseph R. Biden, D-Del., chairman of the Senate Judiciary
Committee, said he hoped Bush ``will follow the historical practice
of consulting with Senate leaders before making his choice.''
   Ralph Neas, executive director of the Leadership Conference on
Civil Rights, issued a joint statement with conference chairman
Benjamin Hooks calling on Bush to name ``someone who consistently
demonstrated a commitment to equal justice under the law.''
   Sen. Orrin Hatch, R-Utah, and Thornburgh themselves have been
mentioned in the past as possible high-court nominees. Hatch,
appearing Friday night on ABC-TV's ``Nightline'' program,
disclaimed any interest in the job, saying: ``If I had the choice,
I'd rather be in the Senate.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0010 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 0212EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-India-Blast     07-22 0134</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-India-Blast,0139</SECOND>
<HEAD>12 Killed, 50 Injured in Theater Blast</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW DELHI, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A bomb blast ripped through a movie
theater in southern India, killing at least 12 people and injuring
more than 50, news reports said Sunday.
   Press Trust of India said Saturday's explosion destroyed part of
the theater in Bidar, a town 715 miles south of New Delhi in
Karnataka state.
   The news agency said many people were injured in a stampede
after the blast, which occurred on the upper floor just after an
intermission during an evening show.
   It quoted state police chief Chandu Lal as saying investigators
had not determined who planted the bomb. There were no claims of
responsibility.
   Press Trust said it was the first such incident in Bidar, the
site of an important Sikh shrine.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0011 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 0600EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a BC-GirlShot     07-22 0202</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Girl Shot,0206</SECOND>
<HEAD>Stray Bullet Hits Sleeping Nine-Year-Old Girl</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A family outing to an amusement park ended in
tragedy early today when a stray bullet struck a 9-year-old girl as
she slept in the back of her family's car, police said.
   The girl, who was not immediately identified, was listed early
Sunday in critical condition at Brookdale Hospital with a gunshot
wound to the back of her head, said police spokeswoman Sgt. Mary
Wrensen.
   She was not expected to live, Wrensen said.
   The girl, along with her mother, grandmother and two sisters,
returned at 12:45 a.m. to her home in the New York borough of
Brooklyn after an outing to Great Adventure amusement park in
Jackson, N.J.
   With the car parked in front, her father came down and carried
the two younger children upstairs, Wrensen said. When he returned
for the sleeping 9-year-old, he found she had been hit by a bullet
that had passed through the car door, she said.
   About a dozen shots were apparently fired by a disorderly group
who were observed hurling bottles on a nearby corner, Wrensen said.
Police said a 22-year-old man was arrested for questioning four
hours after the shooting.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0012 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 1139EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--CrashSurvivor     07-22 0195</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Crash Survivor,0199</SECOND>
<HEAD>Teen-ager Swims to Safety After Plane Crashes in Ocean</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JOHANNESBURG, South Africa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A teen-ager survived a plane
crash in the rough waters of the Indian Ocean by clinging to a
broken airplane wing and swimming five miles to shore, newspapers
reported Sunday.
   Gustav Smit, 16, was one of four people aboard a private Piper
Chieftain plane that crashed Friday night in bad weather off
Richards Bay on the country's east coast, The Sunday Times and
Sunday Star reported.
   Smit's brother, his sister and his uncle, who piloted the plane,
are presumed dead. A rescue squad found parts of the plane, but an
unsuccessful search for the bodies was called off Sunday.
   Joey van der Walt, a Richards Bay resident, said she found Smit,
covered in blood, collapsed in front of her house when she returned
home Friday night.
   ``Gustav said the plane broke up on impact,'' Mrs. van der Walt
said. ``He grabbed a piece of wing which he clung to until he
reached shore.''
   Smit said his brother, sister and uncle were trapped inside the
plane, which sank quickly.
   Smit remained hospitalized Sunday, recovering from shock and
injuries.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0013 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 1142EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Radio'sTriumph     07-22 0680</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Radio's Triumph,670</SECOND>
<HEAD>VOA's Effectiveness Could Reduce Need For Its Services</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RUTH SINAI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Voice of America has been so successful in its
40 years of chipping away at communism in Eastern Europe that its
role in the region could be diminished as a result.
   The last year has been full of triumphs for VOA. Hundreds of its
European broadcasters, editors and writers have reaped the rewards
of years of exile from their homelands and the systematic
harassment of the friends and relatives they left behind.
   But changes in Eastern Europe are a double-edged sword for VOA.
   With a budget-conscious Congress breathing down its neck, the
Bush administration is considering cutting or consolidating some of
VOA's overseas radio and television services.
   For the time being, however, all agree there is still much to be
done.
   For starters, one East European country _ Albania _ continues to
hold out against the tide of reform. Cracks appeared, however, in
the control of that country's authoritarian communist government
when 4,400 Albanians rushed into several foreign embassies in
Tirana earlier this month and were subsequently allowed to leave
the country.
   Zamira Islami, an Albanian broadcaster at VOA, is certain the
Albanian-language radio programs played a major role in the exodus.
Albanians who have reached refugee camps in Italy say they were
inspired to make a run for the embassies after hearing on VOA of
similar escapes last fall by East Germans fleeing their repressive
communist government.
   Zamira and her sister Isabela escaped Albania six years ago,
cleaving the waters of the Ionian Sea for 12 hours to the island of
Corfu. Their brother disappeared during the exhausting swim, and
the sisters found refuge in the United States.
   Their story is not an uncommon one at VOA, where many employees
braved cold waters, barbed wire fences and attack dogs to escape
communism.
   Miro Dobrovosky, head of the Czechoslovak service, was followed
by a Russian tank down a Prague street late one night in August
1968. It was soon after the Soviets invaded Czechoslovakia to crush
a burgeoning democracy movement, and Dobrovosky was publishing an
underground magazine.
   ``I was carrying 50 magazines in one hand, and a loaf of bread
in the other,'' he said. Suddenly, a tank gunned its engine and
started driving behind him, said Dobrovosky.
   ``I have never been so scared,'' said the burly redhead.
   After a while, the tank driver gave up the chase, but Dobrovosky
decided it was time to get out, taking his family by train to
Vienna.
   Jiri Fisher, a Czechoslovak playwright and actor, defected in
1979 and came to the VOA in 1985. Several weeks ago he returned
home, portraying the character of Vaclav Havel in a stage
production of an autobiographical play by the famed Czechoslovak
dramatist _ who now serves as the country's president.
   Havel, reviled and jailed by the communists, visited the VOA
during a trip to Washington earlier this year. He heaped praise on
the radio station, which he said was the most listened-to in his
country.
   Jiri Sykora says the Czechoslovak service gets hundreds of
letters asking that VOA continue broadcasting. Sykora, an actor and
writer who spent a year in jail for writing an anti-government
manuscript, left in 1969. His program, in which he translates and
sings lyrics of American songs in Czech and Slovak, is a popular
one.
   Responding to changed needs, VOA has augmented its news and
culture programs with scripts about how democratic and free market
systems work.
   VOA officials say East Europeans still rely on the station's
news about the world and about events in the former communist
countries.
   ``They trust us to sort it out. Events are still very confusing
for them'' and journalists are only beginning to learn about the
role of a free press in society, said Dobrovosky.
   VOA, which broadcasts in 43 languages around the world, is now
able to have call-in shows with listeners in Eastern Europe who ask
questions about everything from the heavy pollution in their
countries to how to start a small business.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0014 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 1146EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--VolcanoDeaths     07-22 0132</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Volcano Deaths,0134</SECOND>
<HEAD>Four People Taking Volcano Pictures Found Dead</HEAD>
<DATELINE>GUATEMALA CITY, Guatemala (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The charred bodies of four
people who set out to film the fiery explosions of an active
volcano were found in one of its craters after a three-day search,
authorities said.
   Search crews found the bodies Saturday after family members
reported the group missing two days earlier, said Govanni
Soberanis, spokesman for the fire department in Quetzaltenango, 100
miles west of Guatemala City.
   The foursome had driven to the abandoned town of El Palmar, 120
miles west of Guatemala City, and then set out to take pictures of
the Santiaguito volcano.
   The 11,000-foot-high volcano has been active in the last few
days, spewing out lava, ash and gases that authorities said could
have killed the group.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0015 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 1146EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--Pakistan-Crash     07-22 0114</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Pakistan-Crash,0117</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bus-Van Crash Kills 10 in Pakistan</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PESHAWAR, Pakistan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A bus collided head-on with a van,
killing 10 people and injuring 18, a news report said Sunday.
   The accident occurred late Saturday on a winding stretch of road
near the village of Akhora Khattak, 30 miles east of the border
city of Peshawar, according to The Frontier Post newspaper in
Peshawar.
   The cause of the accident was not known, police said.
   The dead and injured were passengers in the van. Such vehicles
routinely pack at least 20 people into a space designed for 12, the
newspaper reported.
   However, the report did not say how many people were in either
vehicle.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0016 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 1146EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--Australia-Storm     07-22 0130</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Australia-Storm,0132</SECOND>
<HEAD>Storm Kills Woman in Western Australia</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PERTH, Australia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A rainstorm with strong winds killed one
person, ripped roofs off buildings and toppled trees and telephone
poles as it roared through Perth and other towns in Western
Australia, officials said Sunday.
   The Weather Bureau said the storm, with 70 mph gusts, caused
widespread damage on Saturday night to homes and some buildings in
Perth and the nearby towns of Bunbury, Mandurah and Busselton and
Dunsborough.
   Tonia Watson, 29, died in Mandurah when her car slammed into
high-tension electrical poles that had been blown across the road.
   The State Emergency Service said it received more than 100 calls
for help following the storm, which downed trees and telephone
polls and resulted in minor flooding throughout the region.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0017 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 1146EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--Korea-Fire     07-22 0109</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Korea-Fire,0111</SECOND>
<HEAD>Thousands Evacuated During Gas Tank Fire in Korea</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SEOUL, South Korea (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A fire in a gas tank at a refinery
forced the evacuation of thousands of people from their homes
Sunday, newspapers reported.
   No injuries were reported in the fire, which was brought under
control after two hours, allowing the evacuees to return, the
papers said.
   The fire, apparently caused by an explosion in a nearby pipe,
destroyed the tank of butane owned by the Yukong refinery in the
southern city of Ulsan.
   Authorities, fearing the fire could spread or release dangerous
fumes, ordered the evacuation of the 7,000 residents of the
industrial city.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0018 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 1150EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--Pope-Quake     07-22 0152</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Pope-Quake,0156</SECOND>
<HEAD>Pope Calls for Aid For Quake Victims</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CASTELGANDOLFO, Italy (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Pope John Paul II appealed Sunday
for people to send aid to the victims of the earthquake last week
in the Philippines.
   The pope made the request in a speech to a crowd outside his
summer residence in Castelgandolfo.
   ``I ask for aid to be sent to the wounded, to all those left
homeless, I encourage the multiplication of gestures of solidarity
that aim to bring help, comfort and aid to these wonderful people,
in this moment of such suffering for them,'' the pontiff said.
   John Paul said he had followed the news of the temblor in the
overwhelmingly Roman Catholic nation ``with strong distress.''
   ``We are close in our hearts and in our prayers to all those who
have been affected by this tragic event,'' he said.
   More than 1,000 were killed in the earthquake last Monday.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0019 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 1155EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Peanuts 590   07-22 0599</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Peanuts, 590</SECOND>
<HEAD>Peanut Program Showdown Set This Week In House And Senate</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVID PACE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   It's showdown time for peanut farmers this
week as they face a twice-a-decade confrontation with congressional
opponents of the controversial quota system that's largely
responsible for their livelihood.
   Both the House and Senate are expected to vote on proposals to
terminate the supply management peanut program. Opponents contend
it costs consumers of peanut butter and other peanut products $369
million a year.
   ``This is the one vote on a single issue that could have the
most severe economic impact on my district,'' said Rep. Charles
Hatcher, D-Ga., whose district produces more peanuts than any other
in the country.
   ``The only thing comparable would be for the Department of
Defense to announce they were closing Moody Air Force Base and the
Marine base,'' he said, referring to the two military installations
in his district.
   Under the program, the secretary of agriculture each year
determines the volume of peanuts needed to meet domestic demand and
then assigns that quota to farms that traditionally have grown
peanuts. A separate law places sharp restrictions on peanut
imports, forcing manufacturers to buy from American farmers.
   Neither side is predicting victory, although lawmakers in both
camps suggested last week that the Senate offers opponents their
best shot at killing the program.
   The Senate last voted on the peanut program in 1981, when it
survived 51-47. Thirty-three of the 47 senators who opposed the
program that year are still in the Senate, but only 31 of the 51
supporters remain.
   Sen. William Roth, R-Del., who is leading the Senate effort to
abolish the quota system, said Friday that he was ``within striking
distance'' of the 51 votes needed to prevail.
   But Roth conceded, ``eliminating any program is tough in
Congress, no matter what it is.''
   Rep. Richard Armey, R-Texas, who's sponsoring the House
amendment to abolish the program, was less optimistic. But he said
the peanut program may prove to be the most vulnerable of several
farm programs being targeted by a coalition of liberal Democrats
and conservative Republicans.
   Hatcher agreed.
   ``I'm not comfortable,'' he said. ``You just never know.''
   Roth and Armey are offering identical proposals that would
replace the quota system with a more traditional price support
system similar to that used for other crops. The secretary of
agriculture would set a support price each year based on such
factors as peanut demand and cost of production.
   Currently, farmers with peanut quotas are guaranteed $631 a ton
for their crop, farmers who grow peanuts without a quota, mainly
for the export market, are guaranteed only about $150 a ton.
   Georgia and Alabama, which produce about two-thirds of nation's
peanuts, have the most to lose. The Georgia Peanut Commission, for
example, has estimated that termination of the program would cut
the income of peanut farmers by 30 percent.
   The parochial nature of the program, with just seven states
producing 98 percent of the quota peanuts, makes it an attractive
target.
   ``It's sort of like feudalism,'' Roth said. ``Why should those
individuals who have been favored in the past be able to keep other
farmers from participating?''
   Proponents like Hatcher argue, however, that the peanut program
is the one farm program that costs the taxpayer virtually nothing.
And they contend that it provides economic stability to thousands
of small farms and communities in peanut producing states.
   But Armey said he believes that argument is losing its appeal in
Congress because farmers ``are not seen as an underprivileged,
underclass group of American citizens anymore.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0020 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 1158EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-ParentalLeave     07-22 0617</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Parental Leave,590</SECOND>
<HEAD>Parental Leave Veto Said Likely To Withstand House Override Vote</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By WILLIAM M. WELCH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Republican sponsor of a bill guaranteeing up
to three months unpaid leave for workers with new babies or family
emergencies predicts the House won't be able to override President
Bush's veto this week.
   The House scheduled a vote Thursday on Bush's veto of the bill,
which passed the chamber in May with bipartisan support. But
supporters were 46 votes short of the two-thirds majority needed to
override.
   The chief Republican sponsor, Rep. Marge Roukema, R-N.J., said
Friday that she did not believe supporters had picked up the needed
margin.
   ``I just don't see that the votes are there,'' Roukema said.
``This (veto) will go through and we'll come back this fall or
maybe next year with a new bill.''
   House Speaker Thomas Foley, D-Wash., dismissed the suggestion
that by scheduling the vote instead of delaying it that House
leaders had given up on efforts to win an override majority.
   ``No. ... It's usual and customary to take up an override within
a reasonable and short period,'' Foley said.
   Either way, House Democrats are encouraged by recent polls
showing public majorities support the family leave idea and hope to
use it against Republican opponents in the fall elections.
   ``If I were a Democrat, that's what I would do,'' Roukema said.
   The veto was the 13th of the Bush presidency. All have been
sustained.
   Democrats accused Bush of abandoning what appeared to be his
support for job-protected leave that he expressed during the 1988
presidential campaign. He since has said he favors employers making
leave available on a voluntary basis but that he opposes making it
a federal requirement.
   Mary Tavener, lobbyist for one of the business groups opposing
the bill, the National Association of Wholesaler-Distributors, said
her side was confident it would sustain the veto and hoped for an
even larger vote than on the House passage.
   Business leaders met with Bush at the White House last week
where the president reaffirmed his opposition to the measure, she
said.
   ``Part of our strategy is to pick up some of the Republicans who
voted yes on the bill but want to support the president,'' she
said. ``What we would like to see is a very, very strong vote for
the president so there will be a clear message this is not the kind
of legislation that is going to get anywhere in the future.''
   The bill passed the Senate on a voice vote after leaders reached
a bipartisan agreement to avoid a roll call.
   The bill would require business and government employers to
provide workers with up to 12 weeks of unpaid medical leave or with
leave for the care of a new child or an ill child, parent or spouse.
   It would exempt businesses with fewer than 50 workers, and
workers who are among the highest-paid 10 percent within a company.
Employers would have to continue health insurance benefits for
those on leave and restore returning employees to their previous
jobs or equivalent positions.
   Bush said the bill would restrict flexibility needed by American
business to be competitive in world markets. It was strongly
opposed by business groups.
   But backers of the bill said the United States was the only
industrialized nation that does not provide such minimum job
guarantees to workers.
   Washington Mayor Marion Barry on Friday signed a local parental
leave law that includes gay partners in the definition of family
members.
   All District of Columbia legislation is subject to override by
Congress, and there was no immediate indication whether an attempt
would be made to do so in this case.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0021 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 1206EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p AM-KansasGovernor     07-22 0750</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Kansas Governor,740</SECOND>
<HEAD>GOP Governor Battles Property Tax Protest, `Hick' Image</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LEW FERGUSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TOPEKA, Kan. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Republican Gov. Mike Hayden is in a fight
for his political life as he catches blame for rising property
taxes and the scorn of sophisticates who disdain his hayseed image.
   And that's just in the GOP primary.
   If he survives the six-way Aug. 7 primary, Hayden's next
obstacle to re-election is likely to be former Gov. John Carlin,
the front-runner in a three-way Democratic primary. Carlin wants
his old job back after sitting out a term because the state
constitution barred him from serving three consecutive terms.
   Hayden said he knew it would be tough to win re-election when
large numbers of Kansans began protesting sharp property tax
increases late last year.
   As House speaker in 1985, Hayden was one among several major
players when the state revised its property tax system, but he's
catching a big share of the blame for the resulting tax increases.
   ``We knew we would catch the heat because the property tax
increases happened on my watch as governor,'' Hayden said.
   The tax issue, combined with the governor's general unpopularity
in the state's metropolitan areas, has raised speculation that
Hayden could be the first Republican governor nearly two decades to
be denied renomination by his party.
   A June 27-28 poll of 400 likely GOP voters gave Hayden a narrow
46 percent to 37 percent lead over his closest GOP rival, real
estate executive Nestor Weigand. The survey by Tarrance &amp;
Associates of Houston had a margin of error of plus or minus 5
percentage points.
   John Pinegar, Hayden's campaign manager, said Hayden's polling
has never showed the contest to be as narrow as a single-digit
race. Hayden expresses confidence he'll win the primary, possibly
with a majority of the GOP vote.
   Hayden's chief rivals for the GOP nomination, Weigand and lawyer
Richard Peckham, fault the governor for a lack of leadership this
year as the Legislature failed to make changes to ease the property
tax crunch.
   ``Our entire state government is deadlocked in petty political
squabbling, with major problems going unaddressed,'' Weigand said.
``Leadership must come from the top.''
   Peckham echoes the complaint. ``We continue to hear all over the
state heavy-duty frustration over a lack of leadership on Mike
Hayden's part,'' he said.
   Carlin, too, is hammering on the leadership theme.
   ``Mike Hayden has failed to provide leadership at a critical
time in the state's history, and the people are tremendously
frustrated,'' Carlin said. ``He's guided the state from one crisis
to another.''
   Carlin is favored to win the Democratic primary over two
challengers, Treasurer Joan Finney and Topeka Baptist minister Fred
Phelps.
   A March poll on possible general-election matchups showed Hayden
trailing Carlin by 11 percentage points, 44 percent to 33 percent.
The survey, conducted for the Topeka Capital-Journal, had a 4.4
percentage point margin of error.
   Carlin was governor in 1985 when the property tax system was
changed, so that issue may be a wash if he faces off against
Hayden. But Carlin also carries the political baggage of being
twice-divorced and the animosity any governor creates in eight
years in office.
   In the GOP primary contest, the national and state GOP officials
are rallying to Hayden's defense. Hayden has received pre-primary
endorsements from President Bush and Vice President Dan Quayle,
with Bush labeling him ``a national leader whose voice is respected
in Washington.''
   Senate Minority Leader Bob Dole and his wife, Labor Secretary
Elizabeth Dole, have made campaign appearances for Hayden.
   The state GOP has unashamedly thrown its support behind Hayden,
denying the other Republican contenders access to a computer list
of registered GOP voters on grounds Hayden raised the money that
enabled the party to compile it.
   Hayden's problems go beyond the leadership and property tax
issue. The native of smalltown Atwood in northwest Kansas just is
not popular in Kansas' two metropolitan areas, Wichita and suburban
Kansas City.
   Some detractors say they are turned off by Hayden's ``hick''
image, fostered by his twangy voice. Some GOP sophisticates in
affluent Johnson County refer to Hayden as ``Governor Hayseed.''
   Hayden maintains he has built up his support in metropolitan
areas since 1986, and expects to score points for a high-visibility
highway improvement program and his pro-choice abortion stand.
   ``The fact that we're the only pro-choice candidate among
Republicans means the other candidates are dividing the pro-life
vote, and there are more pro-choice than pro-life people out
there,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0022 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 1207EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Britain-Kenya     07-22 0232</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Britain-Kenya,0239</SECOND>
<HEAD>Report Cabinet Ministers Implicated in Murder of Colleague</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   British detectives who investigated the murder of
a top Kenyan minister believe his Cabinet colleagues may have been
responsible for his death, a newspaper said Sunday.
   The Sunday Correspondent, quoting unidentified senior diplomatic
sources, said the motive for Foreign Minister Robert Ouko's death
was his insistence on investigating corruption allegations against
his fellow ministers.
   The weekly described Ouko as an able and admired politician and
an ``adept diplomat with a growing international reputation.''
   It said his death was presented as a suicide but when he was
found near his home in Kisumu on Feb. 13, he had been shot in the
head and his body was partially burnt.
   Kenyan authorities called in detectives from the London police
headquarters at Scotland Yard to investigate the crime.
   The newspaper said that last month that the detectives handed an
interim report to Kenyan authorities, which has not been published.
A final report is now being written and should be completed by the
end of this month.
   The Sunday Correspondent predicted that although the Kenyan
government might not publish the final report, its contents could
end the rule of President Daniel Arap Moi.
   Moi is currently under pressure from aid donors, including the
United States, to make political reforms. Anti-government riots in
Nairobi earlier this month resulted in almost two dozen deaths.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0023 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 1212EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-ExecutedJournalist     07-22 0469</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Executed Journalist,0479</SECOND>
<HEAD>Newspaper Says Reporter's ``Confession'' Led to Execution</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Farzad Bazoft, the Iranian-born journalist who was
hanged in Iraq after being convicted of espionage, might have saved
his life if he had refused to make the confession his captors
demanded, a newspaper said Sunday.
   Bazoft ``believed his interrogators when they told him he would
be released if he confessed,'' reported The Observer, which
employed him at the time of his arrest.
   Bazoft, 31, was executed in Baghdad on March 15.
   Daphne Parish, 53, the British nurse accused with him, refused
his urging to make a joint confession and was sentenced to 15 years
in prison.
   Mrs. Parish was freed July 16 after intervention by Zambian
President Kenneth Kaunda, a friend of Iraqi President Saddam
Hussein. She arrived home on Wednesday.
   Bazoft went to Iraq from London on an official press visit in
the aftermath of the Iran-Iraq war. While there he investigated
reports of a massive explosion at a military installation south of
Baghdad.
   He met Mrs. Parish, who was working in a Baghdad hospital, and
asked her to drive him to the site. Bazoft took photographs and
collected dust samples. He was arrested as he was about to fly home
in September and Mrs. Parish was arrested at her workplace.
   The Observer, which last week interviewed Mrs. Parish about her
10 months under arrest and in prison, said that when she and Bazoft
met in the interrogation center where they were being questioned,
the journalist told her: ``Look, we'll probably be flying out in a
day or so if we get these last points sorted out.''
   The report said Bazoft was suggesting that she also should
confess to being a spy. But when he urged her, ``Do it, do it,''
she replied: ``Look, Farzad. I've told them everything there is. I
have nothing else.'' But he said: ``Tell them everything, Dee, and
we'll be out of here.''
   According to the report, when Mrs. Parish refused to make a
confession her interrogators kicked her, pulled her hair,
threatened her with a length of rubber hose, held a knife in front
of her and blindfolded her. She was also put under pressure to
incriminate a contact in the British Embassy in Baghdad.
   The report said she was shown a videotape of Bazoft's confession
and when she met him again, she asked why he had done it. He
replied: ``Because of the electric shocks. They gave me a prepared
statement.''
   The report went on: ``She had no chance to ask him if the shocks
had been threatened or actually given. But she got the impression
he thought things were looking up, that once he had given them a
confession, he would be free.''
   The report said both pleaded innocent at their trial by a
military court.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0024 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 1403EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Pilots-Alcohol Bjt   07-22 0706</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Pilots-Alcohol, Bjt,0729</SECOND>
<HEAD>Defense to Emphasize Smooth Flight In Drunken Flying Trial</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TONY KENNEDY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MINNEAPOLIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The defense for three former Northwest
Airlines pilots accused of flying while drunk will argue that, in
spite of blood test results, alcohol had no effect on their
performance, lawyers say.
   ``You can't fake a perfect flight and a perfect landing,'' said
William Mauzy, the lawyer for former 1st Officer Robert Kirchner.
``The routine nature of the flight is the best evidence that Mr.
Kirchner was not impaired.''
   The trial of Kirchner, of Highland Ranch, Colo.; Capt. Norman
Prouse of Conyers, Ga.; and flight engineer Joseph Balzer of
Antioch, Tenn., is scheduled to begin Wednesday in U.S. District
Court.
   Assistant U.S. Attorney Elizabeth de la Vega said it's the first
time the federal government has charged a pilot of a commercial
flight with flying while under the influence of alcohol, a felony.
The maximum penalty: 15 years in prison and a $250,000 fine.
   Kirchner piloted the Boeing 727 from Fargo, N.D., to Minneapolis
on March 8. The plane, carrying 91 passengers, left as scheduled at
6:25 a.m., less than seven hours after Kirchner, Prouse and Balzer
were seen drinking at a bar in Moorhead, Minn., adjacent to Fargo.
   A bar patron tipped the Federal Aviation Administration and
Northwest that the crew was ``quite intoxicated'' and might be
piloting an early morning flight, according to records.
   An FAA investigator has testified the crew members smelled of
alcohol at the airport. While he was phoning for instructions, the
plane departed. Another FAA official made a citizen's arrest when
they arrived at Minneapolis-St. Paul International Airport.
   Peter Wold, Prouse's lawyer, said blood-alcohol tests won't be
enough to convict the pilots even though readings for all three
equaled or exceeded 0.10 percent.
   That is the level cited in the 1986 Anti-Drug Abuse Act,
prohibiting operation of a common carrier while under the influence
of alcohol or drugs, as evidence that a person is presumed to be
under the influence. It's also the legal limit for driving a
vehicle in most states.
   Prouse had the highest readings in tests by the FAA and
Northwest: 0.12 percent and 0.10 percent.
   ``There is a presumption that one is under the influence at
0.10, but the issue here is impairment,'' Wold said. ``The charge
is whether they were under the influence, not whether their
blood-alcohol was over 0.10.''
   De la Vega would not comment on her strategy, but Wold and Mauzy
said she is likely to emphasize the blood-alcohol tests and
testimony from people in the bar who observed Prouse drink 19 mixed
drinks _ rum and Diet Cokes _ and Kirchner and Balzer share seven
pitchers of beer.
   Bar patrons said Prouse fell out of his chair and got lost on
the way back to his hotel, investigators said.
   ``The jury may have the inclination to convict based on the
antecedent behaviors,'' Mauzy said. ``We have to make them focus
not on what could have been, but what was _ and that was a
perfectly executed flight.''
   ``We need to make the jury concentrate on the real issue: these
guys' ability to fly,'' Wold said.
   Minnesota-based Northwest fired all three for violating a
company rule by drinking within 12 hours of a scheduled flight. The
FAA revoked their licenses for drinking within eight hours of a
scheduled flight and for having blood-alcohol levels exceeding 0.04
percent.
   The pilots have said they will appeal the revocations.
   The case prompted a few pilots to seek treatment for alcohol
abuse, a union official says, and made some air travelers skeptical
of pilot drinking habits. On April 19, a Northwest flight from
Detroit to Atlanta was delayed four hours after a passenger asked
if a substitute pilot had been ``partying.''
   ``There is no doubt that this has hurt the public's image of the
airline pilot,'' said John Mazor, a spokesman for the Air Line
Pilots Association in Washington, D.C.
   Duane Worth, ALPA president at Northwest, said ``maybe a
handful'' of Northwest's 5,600 pilots sought treatment for
alcoholism following the arrests.
   In North Dakota, the three face state misdemeanor charges
punishable by a $1,000 fine and one year in prison. Trial is set
for Aug. 27.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0025 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 1400EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People-RoseKennedy     07-22 0332</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People-Rose Kennedy,0341</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rose Kennedy Turns 100 in Private Celebration</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HYANNIS PORT, Mass. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A week after a public outpouring of
congratulations for Rose Kennedy's birthday, the Kennedy family
matriarch officially turned 100 Sunday and was honored at a private
gathering.
   In contrast to the gala events of last week _ when the occasion
was used to highlight progress in the area of aid to the mentally
handicapped _ Sunday's gathering was closed to the media.
   Last weekend, family members and 370 guests gathered at the
Kennedy family compound to hear speeches, eat birthday cake, see a
film on Mrs. Kennedy's life and serenade her with her favorite
Irish songs.
   Mrs. Kennedy is ailing and uses a wheelchair and appeared
outside her house only briefly when nearly all the guests had left.
   It was not known how many of Mrs. Kennedy's five surviving
children, her 28 grandchildren and 22 great-grandchildren returned
for Sunday's celebration.
   Gov. Michael Dukakis signed a measure proclaiming Sunday as
``Rose Fitzgerald Kennedy Day'' in Massachusetts.
   The proclamation hailed Mrs. Kennedy as a ``role model for men
and women in this country,'' noting her dedication as a mother and
`` inspiring a generation'' of Kennedys to become active in
politics. It also praised her for her leadership in focusing
attention on mental retardation.
   Mrs. Kennedy, daughter of a former mayor of Boston, married
entrepreneur Joseph Patrick Kennedy in 1914 and had nine children,
four of whom died in tragic circumstances.
   Her eldest son, Joe Jr., was killed flying a Navy mission in
1944, and daughter Kathleen died in a plane crash in France in
1948. President John F. Kennedy was assassinated in 1963, and in
1968 Robert was shot to death in Los Angeles while he campaigned
for the presidency.
   One daughter, Rosemary, was born mentally handicapped and is in
a Wisconsin nursing facility.
   Son Edward is a longtime senator of Massachusetts. Several of
her grandchildren also have entered politics, including U.S. Rep.
Joseph Kennedy II, D-Mass.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0026 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 1245EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-FacultyRecruitment     07-22 0670</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Faculty Recruitment,660</SECOND>
<NOTE>For release at 6:30 p.m. EDT</NOTE>
<HEAD>Faculty Recruitment Becoming Big-Time Sport</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TAMARA HENRY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Education Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Colleges are recruiting topnotch college
professors in much the same way professional sports teams lure star
athletes, the American Council on Education said Sunday.
   Although little can compare with the salary and compensation
offered to athletes, ``star professors'' are being coaxed away from
comfortable positions with promises of higher pay, better research
opportunities, help with housing costs, reduced teaching loads and
even jobs for spouses.
   Such offers were unheard of only a few years ago, but the
council's annual ``state of the campus'' report found that a
shortage of qualified faculty predicted to begin in 1995 already
has begun.
   ``So far, these very attractive recruiting packages are pretty
much for star faculty, really highly qualified faculty who are
going to help make the reputation of the department,'' said Elaine
El-Khawas, the council's vice president for policy analysis and
research who wrote this year's ``Campus Trends, 1990.''
   Colleges and universities ``will have to make more competitive
offers as it gets more difficult to hire the people they want,''
not just the well-known faculty, she said.
   The Association of American Universities said in a recent report
the nation is expected to suffer an annual shortage of 7,500
natural science and engineering doctorates early in the next
century. Shortages of doctorate degrees in the humanities and
social sciences will occur even sooner, it said.
   High-demand academic fields include math, science, computer
science, engineering, business and health, El-Khawas said.
   The council's survey of senior administrators _ primarily chief
academic officers _ found nearly all of them were concerned about
the effects of shortages on at least a few departments or
disciplines, while more than half were worried about the impact on
their institutions generally.
   Existing shortages have worsened in the past year. The survey
said 63 percent of the 364 institutions reported greater difficulty
in getting top applicants to accept positions, while 65 percent
reported it was taking longer to find qualified persons for job
openings.
   Last year, only half the institutions had similar responses.
   Sixty-five percent of all institutions said they have taken
steps recently to improve fringe benefits for faculty, while 79
percent reported efforts to increase the attractiveness of
available jobs to current faculty members.
   ``More competition compels institutions to offer higher
salaries, better research opportunities, help with housing costs,
or reduced teaching loads,'' said El-Khawas. ``The rising cost of
retaining and attracting topnotch teachers and researchers will
increase the pressure on college administrators, students, families
and public policy makers.''
   A common strategy is to offer new faculty unusually high
salaries that El-Khawas said in high-demand fields could average
$40,000. Although they differ with the institutions, salaries for
new faculty usually are in the mid-$30,000 range.
   ``A real faculty star'' who is an expert in laboratory sciences
could negotiate for state-of-the-art labs with two or three
assistants, a certain level of travel and publication funds _ ``a
very large package of benefits,'' El-Khawas said.
   ``If it's a star humanities person,'' negotiations could include
sabbaticals after only two years. Traditionally, sabbaticals are
granted after more than a half-dozen years, she said.
   El-Khawas conceded that such actions could soon lead to tuition
increases or other increased costs, as universities try to cover
the costs.
   To avoid the problem, Donna Waselus said the University of
Pennsylvania last year decided to seek donations to pay for
additional prestigious facility positions. The goal is to have by
1995 200 or more endowed chairs _ $1.25 million per chair.
   The survey found that 41 percent of institutions have hired
faculty in high-demand fields at a salary above their usual scale
or their generally accepted salary range.
   Twenty-five percent of institutions reported hiring new, junior
faculty in a few fields at salaries above those of senior faculty
in the same department.
   Nearly half of the institutions reported having recruiting
situations involving dual-career couples, and about four in 10 have
assisted a spouse's job search.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0027 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 1246EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brite-FamilyReunion     07-22 0416</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brite-Family Reunion,0429</SECOND>
<HEAD>Long-Separated Siblings Reuniting</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CHARLESTON, W.Va. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Larry Grimm's family has been growing
over a span of two decades as he's discovered brothers and sisters
he hadn't known existed.
   Next month, the family picture will be complete when he and
seven siblings meet a sister they haven't seen in more than three
decades.
   ``All of us under the same roof, finally,'' said Grimm, 34, of
Charleston. ``After so many years, the anticipation is huge. It's
like waiting for Christmas morning.''
   The family breakup began when Grimm's mother left when he was
about 1, and his father was serving time in prison for stealing
copper wire from a mine and selling it to buy food for the family.
The children were either adopted or taken in by relatives.
   The family reunion began 21 years ago when a friend told Grimm
and his twin brother, Gary, they had an older brother who lived
just a few miles from them. The friend set up a meeting.
   ``It was just so surprising to learn he existed,'' Grimm said.
``I don't know how many times, when we were bored, Gary and I would
wish we had a brother or a sister to play with.''
   Since then, Grimm has met five other siblings, his birth mother
and the five children she had by a second marriage.
   But he said the puzzle remained incomplete without his sister
Sandra.
   ``When we'd all get together, Bobby (the oldest brother) would
say, `I wonder where little Sandra is?' We'd wonder if she were
living or dead,'' Grimm said.
   But it turns out Sandra was looking for them, too.
   This summer, Sandra Goldman, 37, of Leander, Texas, found Grimm
and his seven other siblings after years of searching, including an
unsuccessful visit to Charleston two years ago.
   One of Goldman's adopted cousins who lives in the area took up
the search on her behalf. At the library, the cousin found an
obituary that led him to an aunt who provided names and telephone
numbers.
   ``She called and said, `This is your sister, Sandra,''' Grimm
said. ``All I could think to say was, `But nobody knows where you
are!' I was just astounded.''
   Grimm said the family will gather in Youngstown, Ohio, Aug. 2
for the reunion.
   ``We're very lucky to have found each other,'' Grimm said. ``But
we never asked to be separated. Think of all the Thanksgivings,
Christmases and birthdays we didn't share. We've got a lot of
catching up to do.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0028 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 1250EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SouthAfrica     07-22 0561</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-South Africa,0580</SECOND>
<HEAD>Blast Damages Governing Party Offices</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GREG MYRE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JOHANNESBURG, South Africa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A blast caused by a commercial
explosive that has become a trademark of attacks by white
extremists damaged the offices of the governing National Party
before dawn Sunday.
   No one immediately claimed responsibility for the explosion, and
no injuries were reported, authorities said.
   A police spokesman, Maj. Mike Lombard, said that about 11 pounds
of the explosive were used in the blast at the deserted offices of
National Party in the central city of Bloemfontein. The explosion
just outside the front of the building damaged doors, windows and
equipment in a front room, police said.
   Whites extremists have claimed responsibilty for a series of
bombings in the past month aimed at blacks and whites who oppose
apartheid.
   Investigators found traces of the commercial explosve used
Sunday in those incidents as well.
   Right-wing whites oppose reforms introduced by President F.W. de
Klerk and his National Party and have vowed to resist any lessening
of white privilege.
   Both de Klerk and African National Congress leader Nelson
Mandela say a widespread guerrilla campaign by white extremists
could undermine efforts for black-white negotiations on ending
apartheid and sharing power.
   Police have arrested more than 10 whites for questioning, but no
one has been charged in any of the attacks.
   In another development, two Sunday newspapers reported that
police have arrested dozens of armed ANC guerrillas who recently
infiltrated the country.
   The Sunday Times and the Sunday Star said the weapons seized
included grenade launchers, mines and combat rifles. The reports
cited unidentified security sources.
   Lombard said a number of people had been detained, but he
declined to release any details.
   ANC leader Walter Sisulu said there have been ``significant''
arrests in the past few weeks and that the detentions go against
the spirit of the talks held between the ANC and the government in
May.
   He also said that ANC guerrillas were still infiltrating South
Africa clandestinely.
   ``People have always been infilitrating here since we launched
our armed struggle'' in 1961, Sisulu told the independent South
African Press Association.
   The ANC supports a guerrilla campaign against the white-led
government, but it has not carried out any major attacks this year.
   The ANC, the country's leading black opposition group, says it
will not suspend or call off its ineffective armed struggle until a
formal treaty is negotiated with the government.
   Chris Hani, leader of the ANC's armed wing, said last week that
the ANC still may have to ``seize power'' if the government refuses
to share power.
   De Klerk criticized the ANC, saying it must desist from such
inflammatory statements if it is sincere about negotiating a new
constitution.
   De Klerk and Mandela met Friday and agreed on a second round of
talks Aug. 6 between the government and the ANC. The two sides met
for the first time in May.
   The ANC says that before formal constitutional negotiations can
begin the government must allow 20,000 ANC exiles to return and
release some 3,000 people conticted of politically motivated crimes.
   Under the current apartheid system, the 5 million whites
dominate politics and the economy and the 30 blacks have no voice
in national affairs. Residential areas, schools and politics are
the main institutions that remain legally segregated. Many other
facilities have been integrated in recent years.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0029 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 1406EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Sweden-Soviet Bjt   07-22 0493</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Sweden-Soviet, Bjt,0506</SECOND>
<HEAD>Treatment of Hijacker Shows New Attitude Toward Soviets</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ANDREW TORCHIA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>STOCKHOLM, Sweden (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The return of 17-year-old Dimitry
Semionov to the Soviet Union for trial on aircraft hijacking
charges illustrates Sweden's belief that justice now is possible in
Soviet courts.
   ``We have assurances from many quarters in the Soviet Union''
that Semionov will be tried according to law, said Foreign Ministry
spokesman Bo Heineback. ``The situation in the Soviet Union is
different from what it was one or two years ago.''
   On Tuesday, Semionov became the first person extradited to the
Soviet Union from Sweden since the end of World War II, when the
Kremlin pressured neutral Sweden into returning some Balts accused
of being Nazi sympathizers.
   Many Swedes criticized the action at the time, believing the
Balts were sent to summary executions. Swedish opposition to the
death penalty prevented further extraditions during the Cold War.
   Sweden tried a 33-year-old Soviet hijacker in 1977 and
imprisoned him for four years rather than release him to Soviet
authorities, then granted him asylum.
   A Baltic seaman who forcibly took over a Soviet fisheries vessel
and sailed it to Sweden in 1986 was put on probation and allowed to
stay.
   Many Swedes vacation in their country cabins during July, and
Semionov's extradition caused little public comment.
   On Thursday, the attorney general's office said it had no
objections to sending a second teen-age Soviet hijacker home for
trial. Spokesman Sten Falkner said the seriousness of the crime
outweighed any humanitarian considerations for Anatoly Michajlenko,
19.
   Michajlenko, accused of hijacking a Soviet airliner with 159
people aboard to Stockholm on June 30, said later he had failed to
report for Soviet military service. Sweden's Supreme Court is
expected to review the case this week.
   Dagens Nyheter, an independent Stockholm daily, said Solveig
Riberdahl, director of public prosecutions, was satisfied that
Michajlenko would not be persecuted for his political views if he
were sent home.
   A third young Soviet hijacker is in Swedish custody and two more
are held in Finland. The Soviet Union has asked that all be
extradited.
   Semionov, who was upset by a family dispute, began the hijack
parade June 9, using dummy explosives to commandeer an airliner
carrying 121 people. If convicted in the Soviet Union, he could be
jailed for five to 10 years.
   Alexandre Koudriachov, third secretary of the Soviet Embassy,
said the extradition reflected a new Swedish policy toward Moscow,
and ``we are very good neighbors now.''
   Heineback, the Foreign Ministry spokesman, said nothing was
different except conditions in the Soviet Union.
   ``This is not a change in Swedish policy,'' he said. ``We regard
hijacking as a serious crime, but if we did not know that Semionov
would not face the death penalty, there would be no extradition.
   ``It doesn't mean that we compare the Soviet Union to our system
or to other Western systems, but it is obvious that things have
changed.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0030 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 1332EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Mandela-Mercedes     07-22 0196</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mandela-Mercedes,0201</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mandela Receives New Mercedes</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MDANTSANE, South Africa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Nelson Mandela on Sunday received
a red Mercedes-Benz, built specially for him by autoworkers who
hailed him as leader of the disenfranchised black majority.
   More than 50,000 blacks attended a rally at a sports stadium in
Mdantsane, a township on the southern coast, where Mandela received
the keys to the 500 SE Mercedes-Benz, valued at more than $80,000.
   Mandela said the fire-engine red car would ``forever remind us
of the blood the workers and people of our country have shed in the
liberation struggle.''
   ``The red color of this car will constitute a daily challenge to
us to stop the violence,'' Mandela said.
   Employees at the Merecedes-Benz plant in neighboring East London
worked overtime without pay to build the car for Mandela. The
German-owned company agreed to donate the vehicle to Mandela,
deputy president of the African National Congress.
   The National Union of Metalworkers presented the car as ``a
small sign of our gratitude to Mr. Mandela.'' The union supports
the ANC, the country's largest black opposition movement.
   The car was being transported by truck to Mandela's home in the
Soweto township outside Johannesburg.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0031 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 1345EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Frank-Ethics     07-22 0558</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Frank-Ethics,550</SECOND>
<HEAD>Frank Accepts Ethics Committee Report, But Will the House?</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN DIAMOND</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Rep. Barney Frank says he accepts an ethics
committee report detailing his ticket-fixing and misleading
statements to a prosecutor about male prostitute Stephen Gobie.
   But what matters this week is whether Frank's colleagues in the
House accept the committee's recommendation and reprimand the
Massachusetts Democrat, thereby meting out the most lenient formal
sanction available to them.
   That question is expected to come in a floor vote this week.
   Frank is not without support in the House. House Speaker Thomas
Foley, D-Wash., is one major backer who predicts the storm
surrounding Frank will quickly blow over.
   But Republicans have made it clear that they will give members
more choices than simply accepting or rejecting the ethics
committee recommendation. Rep. William Dannemeyer, R-Calif., plans
to move an expulsion proposal, and other House Republicans are
expected to propose that Frank be censured.
   Rep. Tom Petri of Wisconsin, a member of the committee who voted
for the reprimand recommendation, said he told the committee that
he reserves the right to vote for censure on the floor.
   ``A censure would be more appropriate than a reprimand,'' Petri
said.
   A censure would be more severe punishment, requiring Frank to
stand before the House while a resolution condemning his conduct
was read.
   Frank said Friday there was every reason to believe the House
would accept the committee recommendation of a reprimand and reject
tougher punishments.
   ``Members of Congress just got this report made available to
them today and it may be a blow to my ego, but I have to report
that a lot of them are a lot less interested in this than a lot of
you,'' Frank told reporters. ``I don't believe this damages my
effectiveness as a member of the House.''
   Frank has worked energetically to show that he can regain his
stature as one of the House's leading liberals. He has fought for
housing legislation, criticized federal banking regulators,
proposed that defense spending be slashed and pushed for increases
in domestic programs.
   ``He was able to make a tremendous comeback, one that I think
nobody could have predicted,'' said Rep. Joseph P. Kennedy II,
D-Mass.
   The committee, which has been investigating the Frank case since
Sept. 11, concluded that Frank improperly fixed 33 parking tickets
_ some of them accumulated by Gobie using Frank's car on personal
business. And the panel said that Frank wrote a misleading memo
that an unidentified friend passed on to a prosecutor overseeing
Gobie's probation on drug and sex offense convictions.
   In the memo, Frank falsely claimed that he met Gobie through
mutual friends when, in fact, he met Gobie in 1985 through an
``escort service'' ad placed in a gay publication. And by claiming
in the memo that Gobie was obeying the law, Frank was concealing
what he obviously knew: that Gobie was involved in prostitution and
that one of his clients was Frank.
   But the committee made three other rulings in Franks favor: that
Frank was unaware, contrary to Gobie's claim, that his own Capitol
Hill apartment was being used by Gobie for prostitution; that Frank
never engaged in sex in the House gymnasium with Gobie or anyone
else; and that Frank did not try to directly influence probation
officers handling Gobie's case.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0032 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 1407EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-JusticeWithoutBrennan Bjt   07-22 0644</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Justice Without Brennan, Bjt,640</SECOND>
<HEAD>Court Swings Firmly To Conservative Side With Brennan's Departure</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RICHARD CARELLI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush's first Supreme Court appointee
likely will strengthen an already-dominant conservative majority
that no longer need battle William J. Brennan's liberal leadership.
   The result: a rightward-moving Supreme Court is expected to grow
even more conservative when addressing such issues as abortion,
civil rights and criminal justice.
   Speaking a month before Brennan's retirement Friday, Justice
Harry A. Blackmun predicted the inevitable departure of the court's
three liberal octogenarians _ himself, Brennan and Justice Thurgood
Marshall _ would leave conservatives in control for half a century.
   ``We shouldn't resent it,'' Blackmun told The Associated Press.
``That's the way the system works. That pendulum swings. It will
stay this way now 40 or 50 years, I'm sure.''
   The impact of Brennan's retirement, in part, is purely
mathematical. The president's stated intention to pick a ``strict
constructionist'' means six rather than five conservative votes
among the nine justices.
   But Brennan's departure may have a more profound impact, one
that goes to the personal dynamics of the court as a political
institution.
   Combining keen intellect and charismatic charm, Brennan was a
master politician and coalition builder who for years blunted
conservative gains.
   Brennan's use of his law clerks as emissaries to the offices of
his fellow justices was a behind-the-scenes fixture as well known
as his memos to fence-sitting court members.
   In recent years, if one or more of the court's conservative
justices _ Byron R. White, Sandra Day O'Connor, Antonin Scalia or
Anthony M. Kennedy _ could be attracted to the liberal side of an
issue, it was Brennan doing the wooing.
   None of the three remaining liberals _ Blackmun, Marshall or
Justice John Paul Stevens _ can assume that role easily.
   ``No one will fill those shoes,'' said A.E. Dick Howard, a
University of Virginia law professor.
   Bruce Fein, a conservative court analyst, predicted the court
without Brennan will become ``a conservative juggernaut.''
   ``The remaining liberals will become dispirited. They just don't
have the strength and winsome character to bring up that fifth
vote,'' Fein said.
   Although less successful against Chief Justice William H.
Rehnquist's conservative leadership since 1986, Brennan still could
claim some victories.
   In the 1989-90 term that ended in June, Brennan led the court as
it upheld a federal affirmative action plan giving minorities
special consideration in awarding television and radio licenses and
struck down a ban on flag burning. Both cases were decided by 5-4
votes.
   The affirmative action ruling surprised and delighted many civil
rights activists who in recent years have criticized the court's
decisions making racial and sexual discrimination more difficult to
prove.
   Brennan, who joined the court in 1956, was a leader of the
liberal majority that through the 1960s expanded individual rights
and mandated greater equality for the nation's minorities.
   But more recently an increasingly conservative court has
curtailed some of the legal doctrines he fashioned, particularly
those that limited police powers.
   Brennan's successor will join a court now more likely to give
greater weight to the frustrations of law enforcement officials
than to the asserted rights of those suspected of crime.
   No legal battleground is more closely or fiercely contested at
the high court than that of abortion. And any new court appointee
is sure to have an impact on the future of abortion in the United
States.
   There appear to be four votes _ Rehnquist, White, Scalia and
Kennedy _ to overturn the court's 1973 ruling in Roe vs. Wade that
established a constitutional right to abortion.
   There also appear to be four votes opposing such a move.
Blackmun, Marshall and Stevens are strong supporters of abortion
rights. And the generally conservative O'Connor has refused so far
to cast the fifth vote to reverse Roe vs. Wade and let states
outlaw abortion.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0033 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 1407EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-NASATroubles 1stLd-Writethru a0689 07-22 0837</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-NASA Troubles, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0689,0855</SECOND>
<HEAD>NASA Hopes Successful Shuttle Flights Will Ease Stigma</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 8th graf, `The problem...', to UPDATE with plans for
Atlas launch scrubbed because of bad weather.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By MARCIA DUNN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Aerospace Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CAPE CANAVERAL, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   It's admittedly a long shot, but
NASA officials are hoping this week's test on Atlantis' fuel system
will find the shuttle free of leaks and ready to fly next month.
   ``If we can fly again, it might take away some of the stigma,''
said David Winterhalter, director of systems engineering and
analysis for NASA.
   Winterhalter and others in the beleaguered space agency say
there's nothing to lose and possibly much to gain _ public
confidence, in particular _ by tightening bolts in Atlantis' leaky
fuel line and repeating the tanking test for a third time. The test
is scheduled for Wednesday.
   ``The public, NASA employees, we'll all be real happy to get the
next successful launch behind us and go on to the next,'' said
Keith Hudkins, chief of NASA's shuttle orbiter program.
   Both Atlantis and Columbia have been crippled by hydrogen leaks
that, until last week, had grounded the three-shuttle fleet. The
leaks, believed to be in different places on each vehicle, were not
discovered until the shuttles were moved to the launch pad.
   Discovery, meanwhile, has its own problems. One of 44 thrusters
was dented when it fell off a work stand Thursday. A new $600,000
thruster will be installed.
   NASA's bad luck with leaks isn't limited to shuttles. On Friday,
a helium leak forced postponement of the launch of an unmanned
Atlas rocket carrying a NASA and Air Force satellite designed to
illuminate Earth's normally invisible magnetic field.
   The problem was corrected by rocket builder General Dynamics,
but plans for a second launch attempt Sunday were scrapped because
of bad weather. Another try may be made Monday.
   John Logsdon, director of the Space Policy Institute at George
Washington University, said it will take more than a successful
shuttle launch to get NASA back on track.
   ``The agency is supposed to be doing more than just getting
shuttles launched,'' he said. ``That's important, but in a sense
it's the minimum requirement.''
   Logsdon expects it will take years for NASA to clear its name
over the debacle created by the Hubble Space Telescope, a $1.5
billion project unable to fulfill its potential because of a flawed
mirror that cannot be repaired until 1993 at the earliest.
   NASA's proposed space station Freedom has come under attack by
Congress, too. A study released Friday shows up to 10 spacewalks a
week will be needed to maintain outside components of the station
unless major design changes are made.
   The Bush administration last week ordered an outside panel of
experts to consider the long-term direction of America's space
program.
   Most of NASA's problems, according to Logsdon, are not of NASA's
making.
   ``They are the reflection of the country not lowering its
expectations at the same time it lowers the budget,'' he said.
   In fiscal 1964, as the agency busily prepared for the Apollo
moon landings, NASA's $5.1 billion budget represented a record 3.85
percent of the federal budget. NASA's budget for the current fiscal
year is $12.3 billion, not quite 1 percent of the federal budget.
   The National Aeronautics and Space Administration is requesting
$15.1 billion for fiscal 1991, which begins Oct. 1. That's 1.09
percent of the federal budget.
   ``The agency has learned to lie to itself about what it can do''
with the available resources, Logsdon said. ``The feeling is if
there's total honesty, they'll lose even more political support and
priority and have an even smaller budget.''
   NASA officials are quick to point out the trouble with Hubble is
totally different from the shuttle problems, all but unavoidable in
such a complex craft.
   ``It doesn't mean when you fail that you're no good at managing.
It means that's the nature of this business,'' NASA Administrator
Richard Truly said during a congressional hearing last week.
   Technicians tightened most of the 48 bolts on Atlantis' leaky
fuel line on Friday in a last-ditch attempt to correct the leak at
the launch pad.
   If no leaks are detected when liquid hydrogen is pumped into
Atlantis' external tank Wednesday, NASA will attempt to launch the
shuttle with a classified Defense Department payload in mid-August.
   If Atlantis must be returned to the hangar for repairs, only one
shuttle can fly before Discovery's October flight with the
sun-probing Ulysses satellite. NASA will either move Columbia back
out to the pad for an early September liftoff or give Atlantis a
new external tank and try for a mid-September launch.
   Nine shuttle flights originally were scheduled for 1990. So far,
only three missions have been flown, but NASA still hopes to get
eight flights finished by year's end.
   ``Each year we're going to fly more than what we're flying this
year. That's the plan,'' Hudkins said. But, he noted, ``We're not
going to fly any shuttle before it's time.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0034 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 1412EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Israel-Europe     07-22 0670</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel-Europe,0691</SECOND>
<HEAD>European Leaders To Hold First Talks With New Government</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By EILEEN ALT POWELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Israel's new right-wing government has its
first encounter with European Community leaders this week at a time
of increasing European pressure on Israel to move foward with
Middle East peace moves.
   The visit starting Monday by the ``troika'' of EC foreign
ministers is to focus on various proposals for resolving the
Israelis' standoff with the Palestinians. It comes as Israel is
seeking trade concessions from Europe, and European leaders are
backing a U.S. peace plan that the government here is resisting.
   Israeli Prime Minister Yitzhak Shamir has called for improving
relations with Europe. But he admits it won't be easy.
   ``We have a lot of problems with Europe, and we have to try to
explain our positions, straighten out (the problems) and move
closer,'' Shamir told reporters last week.
   At their summit in Dublin in June, European Community leaders
renewed their call for an international peace conference that would
include participation of the Palestine Liberation Organization,
which Israel considers a terrorist organization.
   Israel refuses any dealings with the PLO and has repeatedly
rejected an international peace conference, believing such a
meeting could force concessions on the Jewish state.
   After their visit here, the three foreign ministers will travel
to Tunis on Tuesday for talks with the Arab League, whose current
president is Farouk Kaddoumi, chief of the PLO's political
department.
   The visiting foreign ministers, led by Gianni de Michelis of
Italy, are to meet with Shamir and Israeli Foreign Minister David
Levy.
   Italy now holds the rotating presidency of the EC. The troika
also includes foreign ministers Gerard Collins of Ireland, whose
country last held the presidency, and Jacques Poos of Luxembourg,
which will take the post next.
   It is the first official visit by representatives of the
12-nation European Community since Shamir formed his right-wing
government in June.
   J. Gwyn Morgan, the EC delegate to Israel, said in an interview
that ``the purpose is to discuss with the new Israeli government
... their ideas about the peace process and the possibility of
movement.''
   Morgan said the community was coordinating its peace efforts
with the United States and that the visit ``was discussed in great
detail'' with U.S. Secretary of State James A. Baker III.
   Israel has so far rejected Baker's efforts to set up preliminary
peace talks with a Palestinian delegation in Cairo as a step toward
Israel's own proposal for elections in the occupied West Bank and
Gaza Strip.
   Israel introduced the proposal in May 1989 as a way to choose
Palestinians to open talks with Israel on limited autonomy for the
occupied territories.
   But the election idea has become mired in disagreements with
Baker, and the new government's emphasis has shifted to another
aspect of Israel's plan, which urges neighboring Arab countries to
open peace negotiations.
   European diplomats are skeptical as to whether Israel can
improve relations with Arab states until it resolves the 31-month
uprising in the occupied territories.
   The Europeans have been highly critical of Israeli efforts to
put down the Palestinian revolt with force.
   The European Parliament earlier this year called for sanctions
against Israel for its handling of the uprising, in which 723
Palestinians have been killed by Israeli soldiers or civilians.
   So far, a trade conference has been canceled and a meeting to
select new Israeli-European scientific projects has been postponed
indefinitely.
   Israel's goal of expanding trade ties with Europe could be at
risk, too.
   Israel, which has a free-trade agreement with the EC, wants some
modifications so it won't be disadvantaged when a unified European
market is formed in 1992. It has requested a meeting with community
leaders for September, but no date has been set.
   The Jewish state currently exports about $3.2 billion worth of
goods to Europe each year and imports $6.5 billion in European
goods.
   Although Israeli imports represent only a fraction of Europe's
trade, Israel's exports to Europe constitute one-third of its total
foreign sales.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0035 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 1414EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Philippines-Quake     07-22 0573</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Philippines-Quake,0590</SECOND>
<HEAD>Foreign Rescuers Stop Search, Toll Exceeds 1,000</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CLARO CORTES</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BAGUIO, Philippines (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Foreign rescuers stopped searching
Sunday for more survivors in this earthquake-ravaged city after
finding no signs of life in buildings devastated by the temblor.
The death toll surpassed 1,000.
   Several strong aftershocks rocked Baguio and Manila, 130 miles
to the south, hampering recovery efforts. Religious services were
held outdoors because of fears of more damage.
   British and other foreign volunteers said they were abandoning
the search after failing to find signs of life in the Hyatt Hotel,
the last area of Baguio where experts believed there might still be
survivors of the July 21 quake.
   Hopes that some people were still alive at the Hyatt faded after
rescuers no longer heard tapping sounds on walls near the hotel
basement.
   British rescuers said they feared the last of the survivors died
Saturday when aftershocks shifted the rubble, either crushing
victims or depriving them of air.
   ``There are no sounds at all,'' British team leader Willie
McMartin told reporters. ``It means effectively that the person
making the sounds has died.''
   Asked if he believed anyone was still alive at the Hyatt,
McMartin replied: ``No.''
   Filipino authorities said they would keep searching for
survivors but admitted chances of finding any were slim.
   ``The analysis of the foreign experts assisting in the rescue
operations in Baguio City is that the chances are nil for finding
anyone still alive in the wreckage in various buildings in the
city,'' a government statement said.
   ``While we would welcome a continuation of their working with
us, we leave it to them whether to continue their operations in
Baguio. At any rate for the work they have already done, the
Filipino people will be forever grateful.''
   The statement said Philippine recovery efforts would continue
``as long as safety warrants.''
   Figures released Sunday by the Office of Civil Defense, Red
Cross and the Regional Disaster Coordinating Center put the death
toll at 1,043 as more bodies were discovered.
   More than 200 bodies are believed still buried beneath the
rubble of nearly 30 buildings damaged in the quake, which measured
7.7 on the Richter scale.
   Others were believed to have died in scores of landslides across
northern Luzon. In Nueva Vizcaya province, a landslide dammed up a
river and water was threatening to spill over into nearby villages.
   President Corazon Aquino's government has been sharply
criticized for a slow response to the disaster, and it appeared
officials did not want to take the political responsibility for
calling off the search.
   On Sunday, Roman Catholic Masses were said outdoors in Baguio's
Burnham Park because Bishop Ernesto Salgado said it was too
dangerous to worship inside the cathedral. Salgado said priests
visited collapsed buildings, blessing the bodies of those who may
be entombed there.
   Jose de Jesus, presidential relief coordinator, said 373 people
were killed in Baguio alone and another 175 in the surrounding
province of Benguet.
   De Jesus said 135 people were believed trapped inside eight
factories in Baguio but all are believed dead. De Jesus said
information on deaths and damage was still trickling in from remote
areas, including Nueva Vizcaya province, where many villages and
roads were buried by landslides.
   Philippine pilots who surveyed the areas saw huge columns of
survivors walking over the mountains to safety. The pilots
described them as loking like ``columns of ants'' silhouetted
against the barren mountain slopes.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0036 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 1418EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-RhinoDrowns     07-22 0242</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Rhino Drowns,0249</SECOND>
<HEAD>Baby White Rhinoceros Drowns In Lion Country Canal</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WEST PALM BEACH, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A baby white rhinoceros born at the
Lion Country Safari attraction drowned in a 4-foot-deep canal just
eight days after its birth, park officials said.
   The 150-pound female rhino drowned July 11, park wildlife
director Terry Wolf said Friday.
   ``For some reason, she tried to cross a canal,'' he said.
``Unfortunately, rhinos aren't very good swimmers and she drowned.
There was nothing anybody could have done to prevent it.''
   The baby rhino, the 19th born at Lion Country Safari, had been
doing well, Wolf said.
   ``The water situation is always a problem, but the animals need
water,'' he said. ``The adults need it to cool off. And the canals
also provide drainage for the park.''
   A week-old giraffe drowned in another canal on Jan. 4, he said.
Another baby rhino drowned in 1983.
   ``We're evaluating what we can do, but other than lock them up
in a corral, there isn't much,'' Wolf said. Isolating animals can
cause as many problems as it solves, including interfering with
reproduction, he added.
   ``The fact is that animals drown out in the wild,'' he said.
``They die from lots of other reasons. They die from parasites,
from predators, from exposure and from conflicts with others of
their own species.''
   The white rhino is the most common of five rhino species and is
not endangered or threatened, said Wolf.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0037 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 1418EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Finland-Eclipse     07-22 0323</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Finland-Eclipse,0335</SECOND>
<HEAD>Finns Watch `Cosmic Light Show'</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HELSINKI, Finland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Thousands of Finns and tourists stayed
up all night or rose early Sunday to watch a total eclipse of the
sun that momentarily darkened the skies over southeastern Finland.
   Birds suddenly stopped their singing and some flew around
aimlessly in panic during the eclipse, which one observer in
Helsinki described as ``a cosmic light show, equally frightening
and fascinating.''
   The total eclipse occurred at 4:52 a.m. (10:52 a.m. EDT). It was
visible in an arc about 125 miles wide from the northern Baltic Sea
and southeast Finland, across the Kola Peninsula and the northeast
Soviet Union, to the Aleutian Islands near Alaska.
   In Helsinki, the light changed from a summer dawn to dark dusk,
and the eerie scene remained for more than a minute.
   Several thousand people gathered on hills, bridges and rooftops
around the city to watch the eclipse. Sightseeing trips on the Gulf
of Finland were arranged to provide a better view of the northeast
horizon.
   After the total eclipse the sun became gradually brighter,
rising above the clouds on the horizon. People equipped with
special glasses or dark film strips could see the silhouette of the
moon uncovering the surface of the sun.
   At 5:45 a.m. (11:45 a.m. EDT) the sun was completely uncovered
and many observers began to applaud.
   Finnair, the national airline, arranged a dozen special flights
for eclipse-watchers. Private companies also provided flights.
   Ten thousand people, 3,000 of them tourists, gathered in
Joensuu, 310 miles northeast of Helsinki, where the view was best.
   The Ursa Astronomical Association and Helsinki University said
they planned to perform experiments on the effect of the eclipse on
animals and plants.
   Finnish scientists also said they planned to carry out
experiments on gravity.
   It was the fourth total eclipse visible in Finland during this
century. The last one was in 1945 and the next will be in the year
2126.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0038 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 1439EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-US-Ecuador     07-22 0371</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-US-Ecuador,370</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ecuadoran President Arrives For Talks With Bush</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ARY MOLEON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The president of Ecuador arrived in Washington
Sunday to discuss with President Bush his plan for creating a
hemisphere-wide free-trade zone.
   Rodrigo Borja is the first Latin American head of state to meet
with Bush since Bush's announcement last month that the United
States also will move to increase the flow of capital into Latin
American nations. Bush said the effort is designed to further ease
the region's foreign debt burden and promote market-oriented
economies.
   Bush is planning a September visit to Brazil, Chile, Argentina,
Uruguay and Venezuela.
   U.S. officials say the administration's initiative is needed to
build a stronger and more comprehensive economic partnership with
Latin America in order to support what is regarded as a process of
democratic change and growing economic realism there.
   Analysts also view the move as a U.S. effort to counter the
creation of a strong European economic bloc lead by West Germany
and the increasing economic expansion of Japan in Asia.
   Borja will meet Monday with Bush and separately with officials
of the World Bank, International Monetary Fund, and Inter-American
Development Bank.
   Borja, who was invited by Bush, said after arriving that he
brought with him no specific requests.
   He is expected to explore in full Bush's trade initiative in
separate meetings with Secretary of State James A. Baker III,
Treasury Secretary Nicholas Brady and U.S. Trade Representative
Carla Hills.
   The United States is involved in talks with Mexico that could
lead to a free trade with that country agreement similar to the one
negotiated during the Reagan administration with Canada.
   The Colombian Embassy here announced last Friday that the U.S.
had ``signed a framework agreement with Colombia with a view to
establishing bilateral negotiations aimed at creating a free-trade
zone between the two countries.''
   Undersecretary of the Treasury David Mulford told Congress last
Thursday that Bush envisions ``a hemisphere-wide open trade system
that links all the Americas.''
   The achievement of an agreement with Mexico, Mulford added,
``will be a gigantic step forward.
   ``As we have seen in the case of Canada, these agreements can
offer significant and lasting benefits to both sides,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0039 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 1504EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-TopplingLenin Bjt   07-22 0765</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Toppling Lenin, Bjt,0792</SECOND>
<HEAD>Lenin Statues Are Being Toppled, Vandalized, And Now Sold</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BRIAN FRIEDMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In unprecedented attacks on the Soviet Union's
most sacred icon, vandals are defacing and toppling statues of
Vladimir Lenin, and one city is even relegating its statue to the
ultimate capitalist fate: selling it to the highest bidder.
   Weekend reports in the state-run media said statues of the
Soviet founder have been toppled in two dozen towns in the southern
republic of Georgia, ``barbarously disfigured'' in Lithuania and,
to the outrage of local Communists, dismantled and put up for sale
in the Ukraine city of Ternopol.
   All the incidents came in republics that have active
independence movements and growing nationalistic sentiment.
   Under President Mikhail S. Gorbachev's reforms, past Soviet
leaders like Josef Stalin and Leonid I. Brezhnev have been
denounced in the official press, and monuments and plaques in their
honor have been taken down.
   Lenin is still officially lionized. But that doesn't mean all
Soviet citizens hold him sacred.
   In the Georgian capital of Tbilisi, police are guarding the
Lenin statue in the city's central square around the clock to keep
it from suffering the same fate as a bronze monument that was
toppled near the Zemo-Avchalskaya hydroelectric station in another
part of town, the newspaper Soviet Culture reported Saturday.
   ``He was lying looking at me with his frightening, empty eyes,
the creator of my motherland, U.S.S.R. _ Vladimir Lenin,'' wrote
correspondent S. Babayev of the toppled statue. He added that the
plant's labor committee decided to destroy the statue.
   In recent weeks, monuments to the Soviet founder were destroyed
in the Georgian towns of Kodzhori, Kutaisi, Batumi and about two
dozen others. Attempts were made to topple them in the Azerbaijan
capital of Baku and the Armenian capital of Yerevan, Soviet Culture
reported.
   In the small town of Varniai in northwestern Lithuania,
meanwhile, a statue of Lenin in the central square was
``barbarously disfigured'' on Saturday, the official Tass news
agency reported.
   The day was the 50th anniversary of the declaration of Soviet
power in the three Baltic republics, which are trying to break away
from Moscow.
   Tass didn't say exactly what was done to the statue, but called
it a ``crude provocation.'' It said representatives of a ``local
extremist group, the League for Freedom of Lithuania'' claimed
responsibility.
   Official criticism of Lenin is not unheard of.
   In the spring, a bust of him was removed from the chambers of
the City Council in Moscow, where radical reformers won local
elections earlier this year. And one critic suggested this year
that his body be removed from its Red Square mausoleum and buried.
But such attacks were rare.
   In Ternopol, about 200 miles west of Kiev, the City Council
voted 64-0 with 21 abstentions to remove the statues of Lenin and
Karl Marx from the central square and sell them, according to the
newspaper Rural Life. It quoted Ternopol's local party ideologist,
Yelena N. Sosnitskaya.
   City officials also decided to take down statues of Yaroslav
Galan, who fought against Ukrainian nationalism, and Vladimir
Zatonsky, a prominent Soviet Communist Party figure, Tass reported.
Several military monuments are also to be scrapped, it said.
   Mrs. Sosnitskaya told Rural Life that orthodox Communists were
``frightened and indignant'' over the decision to take down and
sell the Lenin statue.
   ``I told them (the city council) that `You have the Bolshevism
syndrome,''' she said. ``If we start breaking and destroying, how
will it all end?''
   She said the move to tear down statues of Lenin and Marx could
have been caused by authorities' failures to put up monuments to
those who helped ``the national rebirth'' of the Ukraine.
   Honoring Ukrainian heroes is all very well, she said, but that
doesn't mean the likes of Marx and Lenin should be tossed aside.
   ``We supported the decision of deputies to put up monuments to
those who really contributed to our area, but as to the
dismantling, we consider it an act of vandalism and barbarism,''
she said.
   Mrs. Sosnitskaya told Rural Life she hoped the Lenin statue
could be saved by invoking laws protecting ``cultural monuments.''
Tass quoted an unidentified city council representative as saying
only a court decision or a referendum could save the statues.
   If the sale goes ahead, Mrs. Sosnitskaya said the statues would
be sold to ``whatever organizations are interested.'' Asked if
there are interested buyers, she replied: ``There are,'' but did
not identify them.
   Removing the statues would cost about $480,000, Mrs. Sosnitskaya
said.
   But, she said: ``We still hope it won't happen.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0040 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 1508EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u o BC-WEA--Temps ADVISORY   07-22 0040</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-WEA--Temps, ADVISORY,0040</SECOND>
<HEAD>Weather Editors</HEAD>
<HEAD>Systems Editors</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   On Wednesday, July 25, 1990, the National Weather Service will
change ``Raleigh'' to ``Raleigh Durham'' in the temperature tables
that have fixture numbers a9500, a9502, a9504, a9505, a9506, and
a9507.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>The AP</HEAD>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0041 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 1517EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-AIDS-Rape     07-22 0318</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-AIDS-Rape,0328</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rape Victim Demands AIDS Tests of Four Defendants</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW PORT RICHEY, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Four defendants in the rape and
beating of a 79-year-old woman will be tested for AIDS in what may
be the first use of a new state law that allows a rape victim to
demand tests of the accused.
   ``This is certainly the first case I've heard,'' said Stephen
Kindland of the state Department of Health and Rehabilitative
Services' AIDS prevention headquarters in Tallahassee.
   Circuit Judge Burton C. Easton agreed Friday to allow the tests
under the law that took effect July 1.
   The test results will not be admissible as evidence if the case
comes to trial.
   Attorneys for the four defendants retained the right to argue
against further tests that the state might seek as evidence to
compare the results with blood and semen found in the victim's home
after the May 9 attack.
   ``Basically, if the victim wants the tests done, the law allows
them to be done,'' said Samuel Williams, who is representing
defendant Jeffrey Joseph Digeronimo. ``But the results must be
released only to the victim and the defendants, and the tests must
be kept confidential.''
   The woman and her husband required hospital treatment after the
attack.
   While the tests will tell the victim whether she is at risk now,
they will not conclusively answer the question.
   The tests detect antibodies to the human immunodeficiency virus,
which causes AIDS, but Kindland said they don't reach a point of 95
percent reliability until six months after contact.
   It is likely the victim and defendants will have to undergo
subsequent tests before doctors can be conclusive, he said.
   Digeronimo, 19; Brian Scott Geiger, 18; Robert Dennis Kaczmarek,
21; and Robert Allan Anderson, 16, each are charged with multiple
counts of armed burglary, kidnapping and sexual battery from a
series of break-ins, including the attack on the elderly woman.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0042 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 1551EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-CaliforniaBudget Bjt   07-22 0824</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-California Budget, Bjt,0853</SECOND>
<HEAD>Record Deadlock Brings Tears, Vigil, Government by Lawsuit</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JENNIFER KERR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SACRAMENTO, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Lawmakers, breaking constitutional
deadlines in their struggle to resolve a record budget stalemate,
are bitterly divided as the courts intervene to order payments to
the poor, disabled and the elderly.
   California's $50 billion budget crisis, an election-year
exercise in stubbornness, pits lame-duck Republican Gov. George
Deukmejian and the Assembly's Republican caucus against the
Legislature's majority Democrats.
   Assemblywoman Maxine Waters, who grew up on welfare in St.
Louis, cried during a floor debate as she recalled her welfare
childhood and accused Republicans of saying ``poor children may not
eat.''
   Assemblyman John Vasconcellos, the budget committee chairman,
said he cried while driving home out of hopelessness and
embarrassment that ``the richest state in the richest nation in the
world's entire history'' is hurting the poor and helpless.
   Deukmejian and the Republicans maintain that Democrats'
unwillingness to live within the state's means would only worsen
the fiscal crisis in future years.
   ``Dog doo'' is what GOP Assemblyman Bill Baker bluntly called a
spending plan passed by the state Senate and rejected by the
Assembly.
   ``Dog Doo II, the sequel,'' is what Baker called a similar
budget proposal that was mostly the product of Assembly Democrats
and was rejected by Assembly Republicans last week.
   ``This is a Band-Aid solution that covers up the problems for
another year,'' said Ross Johnson, the Assembly's Republican leader.
   The budget for the 1990-91 fiscal year that began July 1 is
three weeks overdue with no resolution in sight. Previously, the
latest the state had ever passed a budget was July 19. That record
was set during the recession of 1983.
   Unlike 1983, California's economy this year is relatively
strong. The problem, as both sides agree, is a $3.6 billion gap
between estimated tax revenues and the spending necessary for
current services plus increases for inflation and population and to
maintain a $1.3 billion emergency reserve.
   The agreement ends there.
   Democrats say the problem is caused by exploding populations in
costly programs such as public schools, prisons, aid to the elderly
and AIDS patients, and by the $29 billion in various tax cuts
handed out since 1978.
   Republicans say the problem is runaway government spending,
overly generous welfare programs and a series of initiatives that
have forced minimum spending levels for programs such as public
schools.
   Deukmejian and the Legislature's Republicans, particularly those
in the Assembly, want the gap closed entirely with cuts, refusing
to agree to any tax increases.
   Democrats say cuts would be too harsh in public health, school,
university and mental health programs and want a combination of
some cuts and some tax increases. Neither side is willing to budge.
   Without a budget, state government goes on, but the controller
has no authority to pay bills and issue paychecks.
   However, groups owed money have gone to the federal courts,
which through Friday had ordered payment of $688 million in bills
for Medi-Cal doctors, hospitals and nursing homes, for welfare
mothers, children and for in-home workers.
   California is not the only state with budget problems this year.
The state Senate Office of Research said last week that 24 other
states have had gaps between revenues and expenditures. Fifteen
states chose to raise taxes to solve the problem.
   California's bond rating is currently ``AAA,'' the highest
possible, from the three major rating houses; some states with
budget problems have had their bond ratings lowered.
   Controller Gray Davis warned, ``I think each day we go without a
budget, we run the risk of annoying the credit rating agencies.''
   As the budget standoff continues, many groups have staged
rallies and sit-ins in the Capitol. About four dozen people in
wheelchairs have been arrested in a series of demonstrations in the
governor's office this month.
   Vasconcellos, a Democrat, brought three welfare mothers and
their nine children to the Capitol and asked Deukmejian to meet
with them and explain why he wants to freeze their benefits. The
governor declined.
   Despite the crisis, the Capitol this weekend was nearly empty.
The Senate passed a budget proposal on July 10 and went home until
the Assembly acts. The Assembly rejected a second budget proposal
Thursday and adjourned for the weekend.
   The Capitol is deserted, that is, except for one legislator.
   Democratic Assemblyman Norman Waters began a vigil Friday in the
Assembly chambers. Waters, who faces a tough re-election race in
November, said he'll sit there alone until the budget crisis is
solved because ``compromise can't happen if people don't bother to
show up.''
   Waters could have a long wait.
   Assemblywoman Waters, who is not related, said during floor
debate, ``It will be a cold day in hell before I participate in a
society giving up on its children.''
   Republican Assemblyman Chris Chandler said he partially agreed
with her: ``There are many of us over here who are prepared to stay
here until hell freezes over.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0043 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 1601EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Mohawks 1stLd-Writethru   07-22 0946</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mohawks, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0682,0969</SECOND>
<HEAD>Racism at Root of Indian Clashes in Canada, Mohawks Say</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Leads with 14 grafs to UPDATE with train to carry commuters
past blockade, ADDS population of towns, reservations, CORRECTS
date of shootout in Oka to July 11, sted 12. Pickup 14th, `About
1,000...'
^By DAVID GERMAIN</NOTE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>KAHNAWAKE MOHAWK RESERVATION, Quebec (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Mohawk Indians
embroiled in a land war with the United States and Canada claim 300
years of racism are at the root of their quarrel.
   Government negotiators say it has nothing to do with race.
   They say the latest clash, which left one person dead, stems
from the Mohawks' impatience with the government to resolve land
disputes. The death of two Mohawks in May involved an Indian
dispute over gambling.
   ``Many of our ancestors have died because they've trusted the
white government,'' said Grand Chief Joe Norton of the Kahnawake
Mohawk Reservation south of Montreal.
   The reservation, home to 6,000 Indians, has been closed by
police and Indian blockades since July 11, when police stormed a
Mohawk barricade at the nearby Kanesatake reserve, where 750
Mohawks live, near Oka, Quebec.
   Indians there have blocked roads for four months to stop a golf
course expansion project on land they claim is Mohawk ancestral
territory.
   A Quebec provincial police officer died in a shootout between
police and Indians at Oka. Experts are trying to determine if the
bullet that killed him was fired by an Indian or a fellow officer
during the wild shootout.
   The uneasy standoff between Indians and police continued Sunday
in the small town of Oka and around Kahnawake. Negotiations between
the Mohawks and Canadian officials broke off last week and no new
talks are scheduled.
   ``This is a settler country,'' said Loran Thompson, spokesman
for Mohawks at the Oka barricade. ``People came in and settled our
land, we let them, and then they took it away.''
   In the 17th century, Jesuit missionaries who tried to convert
Mohawks and other tribes in the Iroquois Confederacy called the
Indians ``pagans and savages,'' Thompson said. Canadians and
Americans still view Indians as an inferior race, he claimed.
   The Quebec Human Rights Commission Saturday issued a statement
deploring the ``increase in racial intolerance and the
multiplication of racial incidents'' around Mohawk territory.
   Last week, mobs in Chateauguay, a city of 40,000 people on the
southern border of Kahnawake burned Mohawks in effigy, taunted
Indians at a barricade with war whoops and yelled, ``Damn savages!''
   Chateauguay residents are angry over the Mohawk blockade of the
Mercier Bridge over the St. Lawrence River north of the
reservation. Commuters use the bridge to reach jobs in Montreal.
Their 30-minute commute now takes up to two hours because they have
to cross the river at another bridge.
   On Sunday, Canadian officials announced that beginning Monday a
special train will carry commuters to Montreal in a one-hour trip.
   About 1,000 people gathered outside the barricades in
Chateauguay on Saturday night, the smallest crowd all week. Two men
carried a banner showing a Mohawk in feathers and other Indian
regalia. A circle was painted around the caricature with a slash
through the Indian's face.
   ``The Indian people have always been looked upon as less than
human,'' said Thompson, a member of the militant Mohawk Warriors
Society.
   Members of the group have been accused of inciting violence on
Mohawk territory, including the St. Regis Indian Reservation along
the U.S.-Canadian border. Two Indians died there in May in a
gunfight between opponents and supporters of the reservation's
casinos.
   ``This is a racial war,'' Thompson said, referring to Oka
dispute. ``That's what it all comes down to.''
   John Bray, a spokesman for Canadian Indian Affairs, said the
situation is a dispute between the government and a faction of
Canadians who have legitimate land claims.
   ``This is not a racial war,'' Bray said. ``There's a certain
degree of frustration among the Mohawks. It's their perception of
how the federal government has not moved as broadly or quickly as
the Indian people wish it to be.''
   Extremist Mohawks want Canada to give them 5 million acres of
land in eastern Canada and the United States to hand over another 9
million acres in New York and New England. The Mohawks now have
10,200 acres at Kahnawake, 28,000 acres at St. Regis, 2,000 at Oka
and 700 at the Ganienkeh encampment in northern New York near
Plattsburgh.
   Each Mohawk territory has been blockaded at various times by
police in the past four months. Canadian police and New York state
troopers continue to occupy St. Regis. At Ganienkeh, a military
helicopter made an emergency landing in March after it was hit by
gunfire, prompting an 11-day standoff between Indians and police.
   Chateauguay Mayor Jean-Bosco Bourcier blamed the racial slurs
shouted at Mohawks last week on a ``minority of overly excited
people.'' Bourcier himself was taunted by a mob of about 2,000
people who marched through the town Friday night. The mob blamed
Bourcier and other officials for failing to build a commuter route
to Montreal that would bypass the reservation.
   Some in the crowd yelled racial insults about the Mohawks.
   ``They're ignorant, they're uneducated, they stink,'' yelled one
young man.
   ``I still have friends on the reservation, but a lot of people
in Chateauguay won't stand the Indians any more,'' said town
resident Audrey Pepin.
   Most in the crowd seemed to agree with Bourcier that racism
against Mohawks was limited to a handful of people.
   ``I don't think it's fair to say the people of Chateauguay or
Quebec are more racist than any other,'' said Jean Dorion,
president of the French Nationalist St. Jean Baptiste Society, a
Quebec secessionist group.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0044 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 1603EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Romania     07-22 0331</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania,0344</SECOND>
<HEAD>Thousands of Romanians Rally For Release of Student Leader</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CHRISTINA PIRVULESCU</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUCHAREST, Romania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   About 5,000 protesters shouted slogans
denouncing President Ion Iliescu at a rally Sunday to demand the
release of a jailed student activist.
   The protest _ the second in the capital in two days _ marked the
seven-month anniversary of the uprising that led to the toppling of
Communist dictator Nicolae Ceausescu.
   The demonstrators gathered in the Bucharest's Opera Square, many
of them carrying flowers. ``Down with Iliescu!'' and ``Down with
Communism!'' they shouted.
   Iliescu, a former Communist official, won free elections in May.
But opponents have demanded he step down, saying he has continued
many of Ceausescu's policies, if in an attenuated form.
   The president has repeatedly affirmed his commitment to
democracy and a market economy.
   The jailed student activist, Marian Munteanu, was the leader of
a 53-day round-the-clock anti-government rally in Bucharest's
University Square that was broken up by police last month.
   The police were backed by vigilante coal miners summoned to the
capital by Iliescu to quell anti-government rioters.
   Six people were killed and scores injured in the rioting and
violence that followed after the University Square protest was
broken up.
   Munteanu was arrested on charges of inciting to violence and
remains in detention.
   Sunday's crowd, made up largely of students, shouted ``Try the
miners, not Munteanu!'' A banner read: ``You have not arrested one
student, but all students.''
   Iliescu, whose National Salvation Front won May 20 elections by
a landslide, drew international criticism for the miners' violence
and the detention of Munteanu and other opposition leaders.
   Opposition groups participating in Sunday's rally included the
21 December Association. Its leader, Dumitru Dinca, was also
detained after the unrest in June.
   Iliescu last week said it was up to the prosecutor general to
decide whether Munteanu should be released. Premier Petre Roman
told French President Francois Mitterrand in Paris last week it was
possible Munteanu could be freed.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0045 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 1607EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brite-SnakeVisit     07-22 0193</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brite-Snake Visit,0198</SECOND>
<HEAD>12-Foot Boa Constrictor an Uninvited Guest</HEAD>
<DATELINE>STEPHENVILLE, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Bobbie Gross went out to the garage
to do laundry and ran into an unexpected visitor _ a 12-foot,
25-pound boa constrictor coiled up on an old air-conditioner.
   She screamed for her husband. ``He came out thinking it was just
going to be a little grass snake,'' she said.
   The Grosses were so unnerved that Animal Control officer Monica
Davis said that when she arrived Saturday she found them standing
all the way across the street from their home.
   Ms. Davis said she thought the snake had just eaten. ``He was
real docile and he had a big lump in his middle ... He probably got
a cat or a squirrel.''
   Ms. Gross said she and her husband now believe noises they heard
from the garage Friday night were probably made by the snake moving
around.
   ``We kept hearing these bumps, and we went outside two or three
times, but we never saw anything,'' she said.
   Officials believe the snake is somebody's escaped pet. Ms. Davis
took it to an animal farm for safekeeping until its owner is found.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0046 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 1614EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Tour-Newspage     07-22 0344</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Tour-Newspage,0356</SECOND>
<HEAD>Greg LeMond Captures Third Tour de France Title</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   American Greg LeMond powered his way to a third
Tour de France title Sunday, keeping bicycling's most prestigious
crown and erasing any doubt that he is king in a sport long ruled
by Europeans.
   The victory came a day after LeMond rallied to take the lead
from Italian Claudio Chiapucci. The Italian finished second in the
grueling three-week race.
   LeMond was in command throughout the day Sunday, taking his
second title in a row with relative ease following a dramatic
final-day battle with Frenchman Laurent Fignon last year.
   Cheered by thousands who gathered along Paris' famed Champs
Elysees, the 29-year-old cyclist stayed with the rest of the pack
Sunday. It was enough for him to preserve his two-minute, 16-second
lead over Chiappucci.
   Dutch rider Eric Breukink finished third, 13 seconds behind
Chiappucci.
   ``The last stage wasn't difficult,'' LeMond said. ``But all day,
I was nervous. I didn't want to take chances, but I was impatient
to cross the finish line.''
   It was the culmination of an exhausting 2,112-mile odyssey
around France.
   LeMond has now competed in five Tours, placing in the top three
finishers each time. His 1986 victory made him the first American
to win the race.
   He missed the next two years, in large part because of a
near-fatal hunting accident. However, he scored a roaring comeback
last year by squeaking past Fignon by only eight seconds on the
final day.
   LeMond, a native of Wayzata, Minn., was asked on French
television Sunday if he was trying to match the record of five Tour
de France victories co-held by two Frenchmen.
   ``It's always a dream, but not something I live for, because in
1986 I learned that life changes quickly,'' he answered in fluent
French.
   ``I won in '86, but the next year I almost died,'' he said,
referring to when he was accidentally shot. ``Things can change
just as quickly in the future. You never know. But if I could win
every year, I wouldn't say no.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0047 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 1626EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-RushdieFilm 1stLd-Writethru a0704 07-22 0591</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Rushdie Film, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0704,0607</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rushdie Revenge Film Banned in Britain</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: INSERTS 3 grafs after 7th graf, ``They say...' to UPDATE with
comment from Rushdie defense committee. Pickup pvs 8th graf, `James
Ferman...'</NOTE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   British authorities have banned a Pakistani film
which portrays author Salman Rushdie as a killer and torturer of
Moslems who is finally slain himself, a published report said
Sunday.
   Rushdie, a British subject born into a Moslem family in India,
has been in hiding under guard since February 1989 because of an
Iranian death threat. Many Moslems considered his novel, ``The
Satanic Verses,'' blasphemous.
   The British Board of Film Classification refused to license
distribution of the film because police advised that it could be
criminally libelous, the Independent on Sunday newspaper reported.
   The film, titled ``International Guerrillas,'' portrays Rushdie
as the agent of an Jewish conspiracy against Islam.
   The 3{-hour film depicts him killing and torturing Moslems until
he himself is killed by a bolt of lightning.
   Mohammed Fayyaz, who owns worldwide distribution rights to the
film, said banning it amounted to ``double standards.''
   ``They say this is an independent country, but they ban a film
which gives the real feeling of Moslems,'' the newspaper quoted
Fayyaz as saying.
   A spokeswoman for the Salman Rushdie Defense Committee said
Rushdie believes the film ``should be in the public domain so that
any libel or offense may be dealt with according to the due process
of law.''
   Committee spokeswoman Frances D'Souza also said it was
``debatable'' whether the film would expose Rushdie to increased
danger.
   ``It is also debatable whether the majority of British Moslems
would condone, let alone support, its message,'' she said.
   James Ferman, director of the film classification board, told
Fayyaz the film could be licensed if the Rushdie character were
given a different name and all speeches calling for his death were
excised.
   ``This would turn it into a more traditional entertainment, with
a villain who is an enemy of Islam in a general sense, rather than
a specifically named individual,'' The Independent on Sunday quoted
the letter as saying.
   Lawmakers weighed in on both sides of the issue.
   Max Madden, a Labor Party lawmaker who has been calling on
Rushdie to cancel any further editions of the book, said Sunday
that the ban would ``bewilder and confuse many Moslems who were
unable to go to any court to try to ban `The Satanic Verses.'''
   ``It is further evidence of the need for the government to
clarify the law about the publication of any material thought
capable of inciting relgious, racial or personal hatred,'' he said.
   Conservative lawmaker Anthony Beaumont-Dark, though, said the
banning was ``absolutely right.''
   ``Anything that incites people to violence should be banned _
and I am not a great banner of anything,'' Beaumont-Dark said.
``Surely everybody, Moslems included, must be against incitement to
violence.''
   Rushdie's publisher announced earlier this month that two new
books by him would soon be brought out. They will be his first
since ``The Satanic Verses'' brought death threats from the late
Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini.
   Granta Books, in association with Penguin Books, said it had
acquired world English-language rights to Rushdie's novel, ``Haroun
and the Sea of Stories,'' and to ``Imaginary Homelands,'' a
collection of essays.
   The novel will be published in Britain on Sept. 27 and in the
United States next year.
   The death threats against Rushdie have hampered restoration of
diplomatic ties between Tehran and London, which were effectively
severed in June 1987 after a series of expulsions of diplomats.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0048 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 1635EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People Sub a0718 07-22 0156</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People, Sub, a0718,0158</SECOND>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 1st item in People package to CORRECT ``Golden Girls''
network to NBC, sted CBS. For Release 6 p.m. EDT</NOTE>
<DATELINE>RADNOR, Pa. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Rue McClanahan of NBC's ``Golden Girls'' says
she's finally kicked her addiction to men.
   The five-time bride boasts in the July 28 issue of TV Guide
magazine that she has gone five years without a serious
relationship.
   ``It was a quiet kind of desperation,'' said the 55-year-old
actress. ``I always thought I had to have a man.''
   Ms. McClanahan first married in 1958, a year after she graduated
from the University of Tulsa. She received her fifth divorce in
1985, about the same time she won the role of Blanche Devereaux on
``Golden Girls.''
   ``Playing Blanche changed my life more than anything,'' she
said. ``It helped raise my self-esteem, because Blanche is
convinced she's terrific. And no matter what happens to her, she
always bounces back.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0049 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 1637EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-HealthCare 1stLd-Writethru a0681 07-22 0567</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Health Care, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0681,530</SECOND>
<HEAD>Pepper Commission: Government Should Make Medicare Changes</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: Subs 3rd graf to restore dropped matter ``voted''</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By DEBORAH MESCE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A bipartisan commission on Sunday said the
government should help the elderly poor pay Medicare charges, add
coverage of preventive services to Medicare and order improvements
in supplementary insurance coverage.
   The $2.8 billion package recommended by the Pepper Commission
would add to a $66 billion plan the panel suggested in March that
would provide health care coverage to nearly all Americans.
   The panel voted 11-4 for the latest three recommendations.
   ``People may think that because the elderly have Medicare they
are adequately protected. That's wrong,'' Sen. Jay Rockefeller,
D-W.Va., commission chairman, said in the panel's announcement of
the action.
   The improvements are ``desperately needed to assure older
Americans the same minimum standard of protection we've already
recommended providing Americans under 65,'' he said.
   The panel, created by Congress in 1988 as the U.S. Bipartisan
Commission on Comprehensive Health Care, includes 12 members of
Congress and three White House appointees. It was later renamed to
honor the late Rep. Claude Pepper, D-Fla.
   The commission's larger package of proposals in March was
criticized by some of its own members for failing to recommend
funding.
   In its earlier action, the panel split 8-7 on the plan to
achieve universal access by requiring businesses to provide private
health insurance to their workers or to contribute to a public plan
for employees and non-working dependents.
   At that time, panel members also voted 11-4 for a plan offering
all Americans coverage for long-term care in their homes and for
the first three months in a nursing home.
   The same four who voted against that plan also voted against the
latest recommendations: Rep. Willis Gradison Jr., R-Ohio; Rep.
Fortney ``Pete'' Stark, D-Calif.; John F. Cogan, a senior fellow at
the Hoover Institute in Palo Alto, Calif.; and Rep. Thomas Tauke,
R-Iowa.
   The vote was taken by mail or telephone over the past week,
commission spokesman Philip Shandler said.
   Stark opposed the latest recommendations for the same reason he
voted against the earlier ones _ because the panel didn't propose a
way to pay, his spokesman said.
   The first recommendation would help the near-poor elderly pay
for Medicare premiums and deductibles. Those people are the 8.2
million elderly whose incomes are between the poverty level _
$6,280 per year for an individual _ and 200 percent of poverty, or
$12,560.
   The 3.5 million people over 65 whose incomes are below the
poverty line currently are helped _ or will be when the program is
completely phased in by 1992 _ by Medicaid picking up the Medicare
premiums and deductibles.
   The panel also recommended the extension of Medicare coverage to
screening tests for early detection of breast, colon and prostate
cancer. Other preventive services would be added to Medicare
coverage ``when they are determined to be effective relative to
cost,'' the commission said.
   The commission also recommended new federal standards for
Medigap insurance policies that are intended to supplement Medicare
coverage.
   These standards would require insurers to use more of their
premium revenue for benefits, prohibit insurers from refusing to
sell coverage based on health status and limit commissions for new
policies.
   Insurers also would be required to develop simpler policies that
are easier to understand and that would be standard throughout the
industry.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0050 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 1640EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People Sub a0691 07-22 0200</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People, Sub, a0691,0203</SECOND>
<NOTE>Eds: Subs 4th item in People package to CORRECT to `Lloyd Webber,'
sted `Webber' on second reference in 2nd and penultimate grafs.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>CHICAGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A composer has filed a lawsuit accusing Andrew
Lloyd Webber of stealing the music for the theme of ``The Phantom
of the Opera.''
   Attorneys for Ray Repp, 48, a composer and music publisher from
Trumansburg, N.Y., filed a copyright infringement suit last week in
federal court in Chicago, where a production of the hit musical is
playing and where Lloyd Webber is expected to visit, the Chicago
Sun-Times reported Saturday.
   Repp told the newspaper Thursday that he first heard the score
for the ``Phantom'' a few months ago and was startled by the
similarity between it and his own 1978 copyright song, ``Till You.''
   ``Bar for bar, measure for measure, it was my song,'' Repp said.
   Telephones went unanswered Saturday at the London office of
Lloyd Webber's production company, the Really Useful Group PLC, and
at the administrative office of the Auditorium Theater in Chicago,
where ``Phantom'' is playing.
   About 13,000 recordings of ``Till You'' and about 23,000 copies
of the sheet music have been sold since 1978, said Repp.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0051 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 1642EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-MegaBorg     07-22 0191</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mega Borg,0196</SECOND>
<HEAD>Officials: Mega Borg A Hazard During Hurricane Season</HEAD>
<DATELINE>GALVESTON, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The crippled supertanker Mega Borg, dead
in the water in the Gulf of Mexico, is still a threat to the
environment because it could be torn apart during a hurricane, the
Coast Guard says.
   ``We're in the hurricane season now, and we could get weather
that could break it loose,'' said Cmdr. Frank Whipple, executive
officer at the Coast Guard's Marine Safety Office in Galveston.
   Debris from the ship, and the traces of residual oil left in it,
pose the biggest threat to the environment should a hurricane
strike, officials said.
   An explosion on the Norwegian tanker June 8 killed four crew
members, and over the next few days the burning ship spewed some
3.9 million gallons of crude oil into the gulf.
   It remains 57 miles offshore from Galveston, but is due to be
towed to Pakistan in a few weeks.
   The vessel was sold for scrap to Aylesford LTD of Gibralter for
about $2.4 million, said a spokesman for the Houston law firm of
Eastham, Watson, Dale &amp; Forney, which represents the owner.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0052 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 1714EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-MarcoPolo'sVoyage     07-22 0260</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Marco Polo's Voyage,0266</SECOND>
<HEAD>British Physician Begins Voyage to Retrace Steps of Marco Polo</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HONG KONG (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A British physician left Hong Kong for Shanghai
Sunday in a replica of a 13th-century Chinese vessel to retrace the
voyage of Marco Polo on his return home from China.
   The Chinese ``were once the emperors of the sea...(and) this
voyage is setting out to prove it,'' said Dr. Wayne Moran, 38.
   He said he would try to pinpoint places vaguely described by
Marco Polo to ``piece together the jigsaw puzzle of his sea route.''
   Moran, who lives in Cardiff, Wales, plans to return to Hong Kong
in September after sailing to several Chinese ports. He then plans
to sail to Malaysia, Sri Lanka, Iran, Saudi Arabia, Egypt, Turkey
and Greece on a voyage that will end in Italy.
   The 76-foot junk, Cocachin, took six years to build and cost
about $640,000. It is decorated with intricate Chinese carvings.
   The 75-ton vessel is named after the Mongol princess Marco Polo
escorted to Iran, then Persia, for her wedding. The boat has modern
communication equipment.
   Moran designed the junk from information culled from historical
engravings and descriptions fed into a computer.
   Marco Polo, the 13th Century Venetian trader, sailed home to
Italy after serving for 17 years in various posts in the court of
the Mongol ruler Kublai Khan.
   Moran is accompanied by his wife, three children and a crew of
13. He said he will set the date for the final leg of his voyage
after he returns to Hong Kong.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0053 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 1653EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-WeatherpageWeather     07-22 0376</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Weatherpage Weather,0386</SECOND>
<HEAD>Showers And Thunderstorms In Eastern U.S.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   More rain was scattered across the eastern half of the nation
Sunday after a night of stormy weather, and temperatures fell to
record lows from the Rockies to the Plains.
   Showers and thunderstorms developed in the warm, humid air ahead
of a stationary front curving through the south-central and eastern
states, and along a stationary front extending from southwestern
Texas to eastern Oklahoma.
   Showers and thunderstorms formed over much of the Gulf Coast and
from the Southeast to the lower Great Lakes.
   In the cooler air north of the first stationary front, scattered
showers fell from the upper Mississippi Valley to New England.
   Heavier rainfall in the 24 hours up to 8 a.m. EDT included 2.78
inches at Paducah, Ky.; 2.74 inches at Peoria, Ill.; 2.56 inches at
Springfield, Ill., and 2.45 inches at Columbia, Mo.
   Afternoon temperatures reached only the 60s and upper 50s over
the central High Plains.
   Overnight lows dipped below 60 from northern New England to the
upper Mississippi Valley, and into the 40s and 50s in the northern
and central Plains.
   Record lows were 37 degrees in Cheyenne, Wyo.; 49 in Denver, a
tie; 44 in Dickinson, N.D., a tie; 43 in Great Falls, Mont., a tie;
and 46 in North Platte, Neb.
   Sunday's low for the Lower 48 states was 37 degrees in Laramie,
Wyo., and West Yellowstone, Mont.
   On Saturday, thunderstorm winds gusted to 62 mph at El Paso
International Airport in southwestern Texas, to 69 mph at the small
Deer Valley Airport in north-central Phoenix, and to 70 mph at the
Marion Williamson Airport in southern Illinois.
   The storm in Phoenix downed hundreds of utility poles and left
up to 50,000 customers in the dark at the height of the storm, said
Wayne Kaplan of Arizona Public Service Co. A Salt River Project
official said about 15,000 customers of that utility also lost
service. About 200 customers were still without service Sunday
morning, Kaplan said.
   The storm knocked Phoenix radio station KOOL off the air for an
extended period, and lightning that hit the roof of Phoenix
Newspapers Inc. in downtown Phoenix left it without news wire
services for about three hours, officials said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0054 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 1654EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-BritishOpen-Newspage     07-22 0319</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-British Open-Newspage,0331</SECOND>
<HEAD>Nick Faldo Wins British Open</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ST. ANDREWS, Scotland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Briton Nick Faldo took his second
British Open golf crown Sunday, beating American Payne Stewart by
five strokes and finishing two shots off the tournament record.
   Stewart finished in a tie for second with Mark McNulty of
Zimbabwe.
   It was the second British Open title for Faldo, 33. He won the
British Open in 1987.
   On Sunday, he shot a one-under par 71. He finished the
tournament 18-under par 270.
   Faldo, winner of the last two Masters, had nine consecutive pars
midway through the round to hold off a charge by Stewart. Faldo had
three birdies and two bogeys Sunday.
   His performance was only slightly less consistent than in 1987,
when his 18 pars in the final round helped him claim his first
British Open title at Muirfield.
   Calm weather throughout the weekend removed the teeth from the
oldest course in the world. The sea breezes that often turn routine
shots into adventures were mild, allowing golfers to shoot straight
at the pin on many holes.
   Stewart, winner of the 1989 PGA Championship winner, made a run
at Faldo but could get no closer than two strokes after his fourth
birdie on the 12th hole.
   Stewart finished in a tie for second at 13-under 275 with
McNulty, who had the best round of the day, a seven-under par 65.
   Jodie Mudd shot 66 and tied for fourth with Ian Woosnam of Wales
at 276.
   Faldo started the day at 199, the lowest 54-hole mark in British
Open history. But he failed by two strokes to match Tom Watson's
tournament record of 268 set at Turnberry in 1977.
   Faldo, who won the U.S. Masters in April and came within a
stroke of making a playoff at the U.S. Open in June, had 67, 65 and
67 in his first three rounds on the par-72 Old Course.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0055 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 1708EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Lebanon 1stLd-Writethru a0698 07-22 0450</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lebanon, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0698,0460</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hezbollah Repels Offensive By PLO, Amal Militia</HEAD>
<HEAD>Ed: New thruout to UPDATE with one more dead, more wounded, Amal
accusations of booby-trapping corpses, Iranian mediation efforts;
TRIMS; no pickup</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By AHMED MANTASH</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SIDON, Lebanon (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Iranian-backed fundamentalists Sunday
crushed a joint attack by rival Shiite Moslems and Palestinian
guerrillas, capping two days of close-quarter combat at a
mountaintop town in south Lebanon, police said.
   A police spokesman said 52 people were killed and 135 wounded in
the ferocious battle that turned the town of Jarjou into a
``graveyard littered with uncollected corpses.''
   The spokesman, who cannot be identified in line with standing
regulations, said the casualty toll would rise sharply when
rescuers are allowed to go into Jarjou, the largest town in south
Lebanon's Iqlim al-Tuffah, or Apple Province.
   The new casualties raised the toll of the weeklong clashes
between the pro-Iranian Hezbollah, or Party of God, and the more
secular Syrian-backed to 125 killed and 367 wounded.
   The two factions have been fighting each other intermittently
for three years for leadership of the 1.2 million Shiites who make
up Lebanon's largest sect. By police count, at least 1,166 people
have been killed and 4,009 wounded in the power struggle.
   In a statement, Amal accused Hezbollah's fighters of
booby-trapping corpses in Jarjou. It said one Amal militiaman was
killed when the explosive-laden body of a comrade exploded as he
tried to remove it from the battlefront Sunday evening.
   Iran has stepped in to try to arrange a cease-fire. Allam Riza
Walizadeh, political officer of the Iranian embassy in Beirut,
traveled to the southern city of Sidon for meetings with factional
leaders Sunday.
   A Hezbollah communique Sunday claimed to have ``regained the
whole of Jarjou from Amal and the mercenaries.''
   Amal denied the claim, saying it still held a quarter of Jarjou.
   But police and reporters said Amal and PLO fighters had
withdrawn from the town.
   The term ``mercenaries'' appeared to be an allusion to a
600-member force of Palestine Liberation Organization guerrillas
that was deployed in the region ostensibly to halt the latest round
of Amal-Hezbollah warfare.
   Police said the PLO force, drawn mainly from Yasser Arafat's
Fatah mainstream faction, became actively involved on Amal's side
after a series of grenade-throwing Hezbollah assaults that killed
three guerrillas near Jarjou on Friday.
   An estimated 250 PLO fighters teamed up with 300 Amal militiamen
in a two-pronged storming of Jarjou on Saturday.
   Hezbollah had taken the town from Amal at the outbreak of the
latest round of intra-Shiite fighting on Monday.
   A police spokesman said the PLO's total casualties since their
deployment in the Apple Province on Tuesday stood at nine killed
and 23 wounded.

</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0056 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 1721EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-MercyKilling     07-22 0506</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mercy Killing,0522</SECOND>
<HEAD>`Mercy Killing' Prosecutor Says He'll Now Support Clemency Bid</HEAD>
<DATELINE>FORT LAUDERDALE, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The man who five years ago
convinced a jury that Roswell Gilbert's slaying of his elderly,
ailing wife was murder, not mercy, now wants to help set Gilbert
free.
   ``He should be released,'' says Kelly Hancock, who prosecuted
Gilbert but left the state attorney's office in 1989 for his own
legal practice.
   He says he still believes Gilbert, now 81, was wrong in killing
his 73-year-old wife Emily. And he says Gilbert agreed last month
in a private meeting in prison that the killing was wrong.
   The state never sought the death penalty, and the only
alternative was life in prison with no chance of parole for 25
years.
   ``I prosecuted the crime,'' Hancock told The Miami Herald in an
interview published Sunday. ``I didn't prosecute the man.
   ``I think it's right to take this stand now. I never thought he
should spend 25 years in prison _ which would certainly be a death
sentence.''
   Mrs. Gilbert was suffering from Alzheimer's diasease and
osteoporosis when Gilbert shot her in the head in their suburban
condo on March 4, 1985.
   Gilbert said he killed her to end her suffering. His defense
lawyer told jurors that the killing was ``the greatest act of love
you'll ever witness.''
   Hancock called it cold-blooded murder. ``Base your decision on
the hard, cold facts,'' he told the jury. ``You must follow the law
or your verdict will be a miscarriage of justice.''
   Hancock said the case has never left his mind since.
   On June 20, he went to the Lawtey Correctional Facility to talk
with Gilbert, who suffers from a variety of ailments, including
lung and heart diseases.
   ``I wanted an opportunity to talk to Roswell, to get to know him
on a one-to-one basis, to learn about his background,'' said
Hancock. ``I wanted to find out if he thought I was a fair
prosecutor.''
   Hancock also said he wanted one thing from Gilbert before
helping him seek clemency, and he said he got it: Gilbert admitted
that what he did was wrong.
   ``I don't think he's going to get out and say he did the right
thing,'' he said.
   Hancock says the system of justice that worked when it convicted
Gilbert of murder will work to win him clemency.
   ``If his attorney asks me, I will write a letter and state my
position to the governor,'' he said. ``If a clemency hearing is
held, I will give my opinion at that point.''
   Brad Stark, Gilbert's appellate attorney, said he is seeking a
September hearing by Gov. Bob Martinez and members of the Florida
Cabinet, who sit as the Executive Board of Clemency.
   Peter Dunbar, the governor's chief legal counsel, noted that the
Gilbert case ``has a uniqueness around it'' but said the state
receives 12,000 clemency requests a year. He also said the trial
judge and the chief prosecutor, not just the trial prosecutor,
would have a say if a hearing is granted.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0057 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 1752EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Jordan-Infiltration     07-22 0363</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Jordan-Infiltration,0375</SECOND>
<HEAD>Jordan Says It Killed Palestinian Guerrilla Infiltrators</HEAD>
<DATELINE>AMMAN, Jordan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Soldiers shot and killed four armed
Palestinian guerrillas who infiltrated from Syria, Jordanian
officials said Sunday.
   A police official, speaking on condition of anonymity, said the
heavily armed guerrillas illegally crossed Jordan's northern
border. A military spokesman said the incident occurred late
Saturday.
   The official said the guerrillas carried documents identifying
them as members of the Popular Front for the Liberation of
Palestine-General Command, headed by Ahmed Jibril. The group is
based in Damascus, Syria.
   Mustafa Khmyes, a member of the Marxist group's Central Council,
denied involvement by his organization. He said the documents
carried by the men were probably false.
   An army spokesman told Jordan's official Petra news agency the
guerrillas entered Jordan via an area ``usually used by drug and
arms smugglers,'' two miles west of the Ramtha border post.
   The military spokesman told Petra the guerrillas were killed
when ``our men warned them to stop and they did not respond, which
forced our army to open fire at them and kill them.''
   Jordanian authorities suggested that because the men were
carrying heavy weapons, it appeared that they had targets in Jordan
rather than using it as a route to Israel.
   ``Our group did not infiltrate into Jordan and we did not plan
any assassinations in Jordan,'' Khmyes said from Amman. ``We are
not responsible for this attack.''
   The police official refused to say precisely where the shooting
took place. But he said the four were shot ``a few minutes after
they actually crossed into Jordanian territory.''
   The official said the slain men had four silencer-fitted
handguns, 15 hand grenades and four Soviet-made Kalashnikov assault
rifles.
   It was the third recent report of such an infiltration attempt
on the Jordanian-Syrian border.
   In January, Jordan asked Syria to help prevent incursions by
Damascus-based Palestinian factions. They have been using Jordanian
territory as a path for military attacks against Israel, on
Jordan's western border.
   The Popular Front for the Liberation of Palestine-General
Command opposes Yasser Arafat, chairman of the Palestine Liberation
Organization, and denounces his recent moderate policy of peace
with Israel.
   The government of Jordan supports Arafat's policies.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0058 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 1752EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-GirlShot     07-22 0204</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Girl Shot,0210</SECOND>
<HEAD>Stray Bullet Fells Napping 9-Year-Old</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A stray bullet hit a 9-year-old girl in the head
early Sunday, critically wounding her while she napped in her
family's parked car after they returned to the city after a day at
an amusement park.
   Veronica Corales had stayed in the car with her mother and
grandmother while her father and an aunt took two sleeping cousins
to their apartment in the East New York section of Brooklyn.
   Gunfire erupted and a bullet went through the car door.
   ``I realized after it stopped it was my daughter...'' Deborah
Cosme said. ``When I put my hand under her head, I started to see
blood coming off her head.''
   One man had fired 10 to 12 shots from a 9mm pistol at another
man. It wasn't immediately clear what caused the dispute.
   The shooter ran away. Witnesses later pointed out a man who
returned to the scene and said he fired the shots, and police took
him into custody.
   Veronica was in critical condition at Brookdale Hospital with a
gunshot wound to the back of the head.
   Police said Dorian Daughtry, 22, of Brooklyn, was charged with
attempted murder and first-degree assault.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0059 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 1809EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Obit-Shapiro     07-22 0223</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Shapiro,0231</SECOND>
<HEAD>Writer Stanley Shapiro, Oscar Winner for `Pillow Talk,' Dead at 65</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Oscar-winning screenwriter Stanley Shapiro,
whose string of romantic comedies included ``Pillow Talk,''
starring Doris Day and Rock Hudson, has died of leukemia at age 65.
   Shapiro died Saturday at Cedars-Sinai Medical Center, said Dr.
Robert Miller, a longtime friend.
   The New York City native began his writing career in radio and
television. He switched to movies, and turned out a string of hits
in the 1950s and '60s.
   His flair for light, romantic comedy provided popular starring
vehicles for such actors as Cary Grant, David Niven, Marlon Brando,
Charles Boyer and Dean Martin.
   His screen credits include ``Operation Petticoat,'' ``How to
Save a Marriage _ and Ruin Your Life,'' ``The Perfect Furlough''
and ``Come September.''
   Shapiro also wrote plays, including, ``The Engagement Baby,''
and the novels ``Simon's Soul'' and ``A Time to Remember.''
   His Academy Award-winning ``Pillow Talk'' in 1959, in which a
couple who dislike each other fall in love over a party line, was
the first pairing of Hudson and Miss Day, who went on to make
several other hit movies together.
   Shapiro's last movie, 1988's ``Dirty Rotten Scoundrels,''
starred Michael Caine and Steve Martin as a pair of con men trying
to outdo one another.
   He is survived by his daughter, Sesquia.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0060 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 1810EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Obit-Cox     07-22 0151</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Cox,0157</SECOND>
<HEAD>Retired Federal Judge Dead at 80</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CORPUS CHRISTI, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Retired U.S. District Judge Owen D.
Cox, who in the 1970s ordered the busing of thousands of students
in the interest of desegregation, has died after a long illness. He
was 80.
   Cox died at a nursing home Saturday night.
   A longtime local attorney and prominent member of the Republican
Party, Cox was appointed to the federal bench in 1970 by President
Nixon.
   Cases he handled during his 10 years on the bench included a
desegregation lawsuit against the Corpus Christi Independent School
District. In the 1970s, he ordered the busing of thousands of
students.
   Cox was an assistant Texas attorney general in 1942 and Corpus
Christi city attorney from 1943 to 1947, except for 20 months of
military service during World War II.
   Survivors include two daughters, a son and three grandchildren.
   Funeral arrangements were pending.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0061 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 1812EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Israel-Unrest     07-22 0496</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel-Unrest,0517</SECOND>
<HEAD>Suspected Arab Collaborator Killed, Soldiers Shoot 10</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A dozen masked Palestinians on Sunday beat to
death an alleged collaborator with Israel in Jerusalem.
   At a refugee camp in the Israeli-occupied Gaza Strip, 10
Palestinian teen-agers were shot and wounded by soldiers in a third
day of violence there, Arab sources said.
   In the occupied West Bank, 30 Israelis demanding the right to
build a Jewish settlement in the Arab town of Jericho occupied the
remains of an ancient synagogue. They were dislodged by soldiers
after several hours.
   The 20-year-old Palestinian man was fatally beaten by masked
youths in Silwan, an Arab village within Jerusalem's boundaries,
city police spokesman Uzi Sandori said.
   Arab sources identified the victim as Yasin Mohammed Iskafi.
   Sandori said the slayers apparently suspected that Iskafi, who
worked as a gardener for the city government, was collaborating
with Israeli authorities.
   Residents of the village, speaking on condition of anonymity,
said Iskafi was beaten with clubs embedded with nails.
   Late Sunday, police reported that an elderly Palestinian man in
the Israeli-Arab village of Abu Ghoush near Jerusalem was stabbed
in the chest by two masked assailants.
   ``(The assailants) told the old man he was suspected of
collaborating with Israel,'' Sandori said.
   Iskafi's death brought to 240 the number of Palestinians killed
by fellow Arabs in the 31-month uprising against the Israeli
occupation.
   During the revolt, 723 Palestinians have been slain by Israeli
soldiers and civilians and 45 Israelis have been killed by
Palestinians.
   In the Gaza Strip's Rafah refugee camp, 10 Palestinians, ranging
in age from 15 to 19, were shot in the legs by soldiers in renewed
clashes between troops and stone-throwing youths, Arab hospital
officials said.
   More than 40 Palestinians have been shot and wounded since
clashes between soldiers and stone throwers resumed Friday in the
refugee camp.
   Israeli newspapers reported the army was using Rafah as an
experiment on how to reduce casualties at a time when Israel faces
international criticism over its efforts to put down the
Palestinian revolt.
   ``We don't use our weapons. Even when people are hit with
stones, even when your life is threatened, you restrain,'' one
lieutenant on patrol in Gaza City told Israeli television. His name
was not given.
   The would-be Jewish settlers who took over the site of Jericho's
ancient synagogue waved Israeli flags and signs saying ``Jericho is
ours,'' Israel army radio reported.
   An army spokesman said the Israelis were ordered out because
they did not have a permit to occupy the site.
   The policy of Israel's new right-wing government is to encourage
Jews to settle in the occupied lands. However, new settlements have
been limited following repeated complaints by the U.S. government,
which views the Jewish enclaves as an obstacle to peace.
   Since the West Bank and Gaza were seized in the 1967 Middle East
war, about 75,000 Israelis have moved into 130 settlements in the
occupied territories. More than 1.7 million Palestinians live in
the territories.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0062 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 1818EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Salvador     07-22 0410</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Salvador,0421</SECOND>
<HEAD>Roman Catholic Leaders Urge Break In Salvadoran Peace Deadlock</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CARLOS SANDI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN JOSE, Costa Rica (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Roman Catholic Church leader
appealed to Salvadoran government and rebel negotiators at his
Sunday services to break the deadlock in peace talks aimed at
ending their country's decade-long civil war.
   ``Listen to the clamor of the people who demand peace. Give
peace back to these long suffering Salvadorans,'' Roman Arrieta,
San Jose's archbishop, said in the Mass homily.
   Salvadoran Archbishop Arturo Rivera Damas echoed Arrieta's words
in a similar homily at Sacred Heart Church in San Salvador, warning
that ``our country's social fabric continues tense and torn, and
the mechanism of war continues with its friend-against-enemy
ideology.''
   Guerrilla leaders of the Farabundo Marti National Liberation
Front, also known as the FMLN, and delegates from President Alfredo
Cristiani's rightist government attended Arrieta's Mass before
entering into their third day of talks here.
   ``Let us hope this meeting brings an extraordinary advance in
the search for peace and puts an end to so much pain, so many
orphans and widows in El Salvador,'' Arrieta added. ``May God
illuminate you so that you can attain the conquest of peace.''
   The five-day session, the latest of several rounds since
Cristiani took office in June 1989, has stalled over rebel demands
that El Salvador's military be sharply reduced in numbers and
purged of officers guilty of human rights violations.
   The rebels have also reiterated their long-standing demand that
they have a say in naming the defense minister and the armed forces
commander-in-chief.
   Cristiani has refused to agree to a rebel say in naming military
officials. Guerrillas have threatened to renew fighting if the
talks fail.
   Cristiani's government has also insisted the leftist guerrillas
agree to an immediate cease-fire before military and political
issues can be discussed.
   More than 72,000 people have been killed since the civil war
began in October 1979. The majority of those slain were civilians
suspected of being leftist sympathizers.
   ``Unfortunately, in this fratricidal war, both the soldiers and
the guerrillas are of humble origin, and I ask myself why is it
that the poor have to pay for these tragedies?'' Arrieta said.
   The Salvadoran Army, with about 54,000 members, is the second
largest in Central America after Nicaragua's.
   The United States has been supporting a succession of
governments during the guerrilla war. U.S. military and economic
assistance to the Cristiani government totals $1 million a day.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0063 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 1822EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Israel-Politics 1stLd-Writethru a0707 07-22 0591</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel-Politics, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0707,0607</SECOND>
<HEAD>Peres Scores Key Victory in Party Vote</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS grafs 6-24 bgng `According to...' to ADD vote on
separate candidacies; TRIMS; no pickup</NOTE>
<DATELINE>TEL AVIV, Israel (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Labor Party leader Shimon Peres scored
an important political victory Sunday over his longtime rival,
Yitzhak Rabin, who has been maneuvering to oust Peres as party head.
   ``I fell in love with my party again,'' declared a happy Peres,
whose victory in a key vote came as a surprise even to some of his
own supporters.
   ``The party and the country shall benefit from this victory,''
he said.
   The 1,400-member Labor central committee was called into session
to consider demands by Rabin, Labor's No. 2 man, for a vote soon on
the post of party chairman. Peres wanted it postponed until next
year.
   The committee also voted on how to elect the chairman. Rabin
wanted a candidate for prime minister separate from the party
chairman. Peres opposed that demand.
   According to official results, about 54 percent of the 1,212
Labor members present supported Peres and decided to postpone the
leadership contest, as opposed to Rabin's 46 percent. The vote was
the same against establishing separate candidacies for prime
minister and party chairman.
   Peres, a former prime minister, had argued for delaying the
contest because he felt the center-left party should prepare for a
battle with the rival Likud bloc, and not waste time on internal
struggles.
   Just before official results of the vote were announced at the
end of the seven-hour meeting here, dancing and singing supporters
surrounded Peres, and many kissed and hugged him.
   Rabin has been jockeying to oust Peres since May, when Peres
failed to form a Labor-led government after bringing down the shaky
coaltion with Likud.
   The failure enabled Likud leader Prime Minister Yitzhak Shamir
to form his right-wing Cabinet in early June.
   ``I accept the majority decision,'' Rabin said after the vote.
``I thank the great number of central committee members who saw the
need for a change, but the majority decides. I believe that from
now on, the party should be united ... and organize itself as an
opposition confronting Likud.''
   The two leaders then briefly shook hands.
   Although both Rabin and Peres appealed for party unity, and
Peres promised not to ``settle accounts,'' observers predicted that
Labor will remain split and unable to present a strong opposition.
   ``We will see two organized and hostile camps, with leaders who
hardly speak with each other ... a kind of prolonged war of
attrition,'' said Israel radio's political observer, Hanan Cristal.
``Likud may forget about opposition, it will have an easy life in
the government.''
   Mordechai Gur, a senior Labor member and a Rabin supporter, said
Peres' victory had ``weakened the party.''
   ``We thought we should change the leadership to lead a strong,
active opposition. With Peres it would be very difficult. We shall
do our best, but I'm afraid it would not be as strong as it could
have been,'' Gur said.
   Recent polls have consistantly indicated that Rabin, 68, is
Israel's most popular leader.
   Also a former prime minister, he gained popularity for his tough
stance as defense minister in the last government in dealing with
the 31-month Palestinian uprising in the occupied territories.
   He also is remembered as chief of staff in the 1967 Middle East
war when Israel captured the West Bank from Jordan and the Gaza
Strip from Egypt.
   By contrast, the popularity of the Polish-born Peres, who turns
67 in 10 days, has been on the decline.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0064 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 1832EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-HarlemFire     07-22 0293</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Harlem Fire,0302</SECOND>
<HEAD>Three Children Die in Morning Fire</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Three young children were killed and 23 people
were injured when a three-alarm fire swept through an apartment
building Sunday.
   The bodies of Caprisha Kennebrew, 6, her sister Duwatha, 4, and
brother Devin, 3, were found in a bedroom in an apartment in the
Harlem section of Manhattan, said fire spokesman Efrain Parrilla.
   More than 100 firefighters fought the blaze, which destroyed the
Kennebrews' fourth-floor apartment and two others directly above on
the fifth and sixth floors. Three other apartments were damaged by
smoke.
   The fire was reported at 5:08 a.m. and under control by 6:30
a.m., Parrilla said.
   The children's father, Gaylord Dewese, 45, was in serious but
stable condition with first- and second-degree burns on his face,
arms and hands, New York Hospital's Cornell Burn Center said. The
mother, Sondria Kennebrew, 40, was listed in stable condition at
Harlem Hospital.
   A preliminary investigation determined that the fire was caused
by Devin playing with matches in the bedroom while the mother,
father and two sisters slept in the bed, Parrilla said.
   Quoting the city fire marshal, Parrilla said the boy has a
history of playing with lighters, matches and the stove.
   He said Devin apparently woke his mother to tell her the bed was
on fire and the father tried to put it out; the parents fled but
the children were trapped in the room when the father shut the door
and could not reopen it.
   An older daughter's boyfriend managed to open the door but was
driven back by flames.
   Parrilla said 19 injured firefighters were treated for burns,
heat exhaustion, cuts and bruises, and released. Two police
officers also were treated for minor injuries, authorities said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0065 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 1840EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-DesertDeaths     07-22 0656</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Desert Deaths,0677</SECOND>
<HEAD>Cellmate Says Wood Told Horrifying Tales of Desert Deaths</HEAD>
<DATELINE>EASTLAND, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Randy Wells says he remembers vividly the
chilling, frequent conversations he had in prison with a cellmate
now charged with murder in the killings of six young women found
buried in the desert.
   ``The dude's crazy,'' Wells, 27, said in an interview last week
with the Fort Worth Star-Telegram at the Eastland County Jail 90
miles west of Fort Worth.
   Wells said the man charged in the deaths, David Leonard Wood,
told him he lured his victims to the desert with drugs and that he
thinks he buried one victim alive. He said his information on Wood
led to Wood's indictment.
   Wood claimed he tied his victims between a tree and the bumper
of his truck, which he then used to stretch them before he raped
and choked them, Wells said.
   Wood, a 33-year-old convicted rapist from El Paso, was indicted
July 13 on murder charges in the slayings of six young women and
teen-agers whose bodies were found in shallow, desert graves about
18 miles northeast of El Paso.
   The remains of the victims, ranging in age from 14 to 23, were
found within a half-mile of each other between Sept. 4, 1987, and
March 14, 1988.
   Some were runaways or prostitutes. Police were criticized for
not responding more quickly to reports of their disappearances.
   Wells and Wood were cellmates for nearly two months at the
Eastham Unit of the Texas Department of Corrections. Wood claimed
to have killed 15 women, Wells said.
   ``He'd mumble in his dreams ... I knew he was tore up. He'd stay
up for days,'' Wells said.
   Wells said Wood was particularly haunted by one victim.
   ``I think she was alive when he buried her. He was throwing dirt
on her and it was running over her face,'' Wells said. ``When she
breathed, the dirt came out around her nose and mouth.''
   Wood frequently re-enacted ``dying quivers,'' he said.
   Wood had been a suspect in the killings for some time but police
had insufficient evidence. Authorities said the indictment resulted
from unspecified new information, but Wells said he was the source
of that information.
   Neither El Paso investigators nor prosecutors would comment on
Wells' statements or on whether he and another prison inmate were
responsible for the new evidence that resulted in the indictment.
   Officials said they are under explicit orders not to talk about
any aspect of the case. El Paso County First Assistant District
Attorney Gonzalo Garcia said authorities are ``trying to keep the
publicity down'' and are under a ``self-imposed gag order.''
   But, according to the Star-Telegram, a letter on El Paso
District Attorney Steve Simmons' stationery lauds cooperation in
the case by Wells and James Carl Sweeney _ another prisoner who
acted as Wood's jailhouse lawyer, Wells said.
   Wells' court-appointed lawyer, Gary Lewellen, said Wells' help
did not come free. If Wells continues to cooperate and testifies
against Wood, Wells will receive a 15-year prison sentence for
forgery, Lewellen said. Prosecutors also would not pursue a capital
murder charge against Wells.
   Eastland County District Attorney Emory Walton refused to
confirm an agreement had been made with Wells.
   Wood is jailed in El Paso. He doesn't have an attorney for the
serial murder case yet.
   Wood was arrested in October 1987 and five months later was
convicted of sexual assault for a July 1987 rape.
   The victim testified at the trial that Wood took her to the
desert near where bodies later were found and started digging a
hole behind a bush, then raped her and left her naked in the desert.
   He was sentenced to 50 years in prison and fined $10,000. He had
previous convictions for indecency with a child and rape.
   Wells also was on a return trip to prison when he met Wood. He
had served time for burglary and was serving two years for theft.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0066 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 1841EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>d a AM-BRF--HotelSlaying     07-22 0152</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Hotel Slaying,0155</SECOND>
<HEAD>Man Shot to Death in Hotel Parking Lot</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PHILADELPHIA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An NBC employee was shot to death in his car
in the parking lot of a hotel near Philadelphia International
Airport.
   Frank Willis, 33, of Lawnside, N.J., was behind the wheel of his
car shortly before 6 p.m. Saturday in the parking lot of the Days
Inn hotel in southwest Philadelphia when a woman was seen banging
on his car window, police said.
   The woman opened fire, shooting Willis in the left temple, back
and hands, police said. The woman then fled in a nearby car.
   Homicide Detective Lawrence Nodiff said the assailant used a
small-caliber weapon. He said police did not have a motive or
suspect.
   Willis, who police said was in charge of daily operations for
NBC's satellite distribution control in New York, had traveled to
the hotel for an interview with a job recruiter.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0067 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 1856EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-SpottedOwl     07-22 0531</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Spotted Owl,0549</SECOND>
<HEAD>Task Force Gets First Look At Spotted Owls</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JEFF BARNARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MEDFORD, Ore. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Federal officials trying to balance
Northwest logging jobs against protecting the rare northern spotted
owl got their first close-up look at the birds that officially
become a threatened species Monday.
   ``They are a magnificent creature,'' said Jim Moseley, an
assistant agriculture secretary and head of a committee meeting
with timber industry leaders, government officials and
environmentalists.
   ``And when you see something like that for the first time, and
also to see an old-growth tree for the first time, it's an
experience. It was extremely valuable to me to see that,'' Moseley
said.
   Moseley's committee represents a federal inter-agency task force
charged with devising a plan that balances owl interests against
Northwest timber jobs.
   ``One of the things that's become clear to me: the issue goes
beyond just the spotted owl,'' Moseley said. ``It is an old-growth
issue. Clearly, cooperation between the agencies, between the
state, between private landowners, is something that is ...
recommended.''
   The U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service said last month the northern
spotted owl would be listed as threatened under the federal
Endangered Species Act, which means the government must come up
with a protection plan.
   In the wake of that decision, the Bush Administration created
the task force, which is to report by Sept. 1.
   Each nesting pair of owls needs large areas of undisturbed
old-growth forest to survive. Bush has said he wants to balance the
needs of timber communities against owl protection.
   Representatives of various groups emerged from meetings with the
task force saying they had had a good hearing but doubted if the
panel could accomplish anything significant.
   ``It's probably more wheel spinning, but it's necessary,'' said
Mike Burrill, president of Burrill Lumber in Medford. ``They can't
solve it on their own. The problems were created by laws passed by
Congress.''
   Doug Frank of the environmental group Friends of the
Greensprings said an outside group like the task force is needed to
find a compromise.
   ``When you have a dysfunctional family, you don't expect anybody
in the family to solve the problem,'' Frank said. ``You expect
somebody from outside to come in and help.
   On Saturday, Forest Service biologists led the task force onto
the Butte Falls Ranger district of the Rogue River National Forest
in the Cascade Range, where they saw an adult male spotted owl and
an owlet living in a 14-acre forest patch surrounded by heavy
logging, said spokeswoman Christina McGown.
   The owlet will be a ``sitting duck'' when it's time to leave the
nest, because surrounding clearcuts will leave it vulnerable to its
chief enemy, the great horned owl, said Forest Service biologist
Mario Mamone.
   Scientists have suggested leaving swathes of trees uncut as
protected corridors for owls and other wildlife.
   A panel of federal scientists has recommended placing 3 million
acres of forest off-limits to logging to serve as owl habitats. The
Forest Service has estimated that would cost 28,000 Northwest
timber jobs over the next decade.
   Besides Moseley, the task force includes officials from the
Interior Department, Environmental Protection Agency and Office of
Management and Budget.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0068 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 1908EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BoatingAccident     07-22 0194</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Boating Accident,0199</SECOND>
<HEAD>Three Killed When Boats Collide in River</HEAD>
<DATELINE>KINGSBURG, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two speedboats collided in the Kings
River in central California, killing all three people in one craft
and injuring the two in the other.
   The collision occurred Saturday afternoon when the boat carrying
the three turned in front of the other boat, driven by Mark Anthony
Nichols, 33, of Ventura, said Tulare County sheriff's officers.
   A witness told deputies that Nichols swerved but could not avoid
the other boat. The three people in the first boat all were dead at
the scene, deputies said in a release read by Dispatcher Barbara
Plummer.
   Police did not release their names but said they were a
32-year-old man, a 30-year-old woman and a 2-year-old child.
   Nichols suffered internal injuries and was listed in stable
condition Sunday at Valley Medical Center in Fresno.
   His passenger, Brian Wallet, 24, also of Ventura, was treated
for minor injuries and released.
   Police said the stretch of the Kings River where the accident
occurred is narrow. The portion between Tulare and Fresno counties
is popular for waterskiing and rafting in summer; on Saturday
temperatures topped 100 degrees.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0069 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 2009EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>d a AM-BRF--KillerBoulder     07-22 0138</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Killer Boulder,0141</SECOND>
<HEAD>Boulder Crashes Into Cabin at Estes Park, Killing Two</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ESTES PARK, Colo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A large boulder tumbled down a mountain
at the mouth of a canyon early Sunday and crashed through a cabin,
killing a man and a woman inside, an official said.
   Recent heavy rains were blamed for dislodging the boulder at the
mouth of Big Thompson Canyon, said Larimer County Undersheriff Marv
Schlageter.
   The boulder, estimated in size at 25 feet by 20 feet, tore
through the cabin, knocking it off its foundation, and came to rest
in front of the home about eight miles east of this Rocky Mountain
resort.
   The undersheriff speculated that the couple was sleeping when
the boulder hit sometime before 6:30 a.m. He said the names of the
dead were being withheld pending notification of relatives.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0070 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 2035EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p AM-LegislativeConference     07-22 0444</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Legislative Conference,0458</SECOND>
<HEAD>Legislators Meeting for Week to Discuss Issues</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DENNIS PATTERSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ASHEVILLE, N.C. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Southern legislators arriving for a
reception here were met by 15 people protesting a proposed
hazardous waste facility.
   The protestors stood at the entrance to the palatial Biltmore
House waving signs that read, ``Don't Waste Me and N.C.'' and
``Dirty Bucks Stop Here.''
   The protest was directed at ThermalKEM, which has been selected
to operate North Carolina's hazardous waste facility and which
contributed $10,000 to the four-day legislative conference, said
Lou Zeller of the Blue Ridge Environmental Defense League.
   ``We cannot afford 10 grand to rub elbows with our elected
representatives,'' Zeller said. ``So we came to greet them with our
call for waste reduction.''
   ThemalKEM is listed in the conference program as a contributor,
of an unspecified amount.
   The busloads of arriving legislators included some from
Tennessee, Kentucky, South Carolina and Alabama, which have signed
an interstate agreement with North Carolina to dispose of hazardous
waste.
   The agreement calls for North Carolina to build a hazardous
waste incinerator, a solvent recovery facility and a landfill by
December 1991. The state has picked two potential sites for the
complex in Granville, Rowan and Iredell counties.
   ``We think the deal was bad for North Carolina,'' said Jan
Murphy, who lives about five miles from the potential site in
Iredell County. ``Businesses need to be held responsible for their
own waste.''
   Lawmakers from nearly a third of the nation's legislatures are
here this week to discuss issues from acid rain to redistricting.
   ``It's a great way for us to exchange ideas,'' said state Rep.
Bob Hunter, a North Carolina Democrat who will be installed as
chairman of the 44th annual Southern Legislative Conference
Wednesday night.
   ``It gives legislators a chance to find out how other states are
addressing some of the problems we all share.''
   The North Carolina General Assembly, unable to get final action
on a budget last week, adjourned for five days Friday to let
members attend the conference.
   U.S. Sen. Charles Robb of Virginia will be the keynote speaker,
and federal drug czar William Bennett is to speak on drug abuse in
the South.
   Lawmakers from 16 states as far west as Texas and as far north
as Maryland are to hold sessions on global warming, affordable
housing, preserving rail corridors, long-term health care,
redistricting and judicial activism.
   The idea of holding all Southern state presidential primaries on
the same ``Super Tuesday,'' first tried in 1988, started with the
legislative conference.
   The conference won't be all work. Legislators also can enjoy
white-water rafting, golf, tennis, a mountain rodeo and a dinner
dance.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0071 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 2057EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-BrennanSuccessor 2ndLd-Writethru a0756 07-22 0849</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brennan Successor, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0756,810</SECOND>
<HEAD>Senators Say Bush Should Avoid Abortion `Litmus Test'</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: Subs grafs 6-7, ``Bush met xxx to update with time and roster
of meeting</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By NANCY BENAC</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Republican and Democratic senators alike on
Sunday warned President Bush not to apply an anti-abortion ``litmus
test'' as he searches for a successor to retired Supreme Court
Justice William J. Brennan.
   ``If you have to have someone who wants to overturn Roe vs.
Wade, it's going to be a blood bath getting the nomination
confirmed, and the same is true on the other side,'' predicted
Senate Republican leader Bob Dole of Kansas.
   ``There shouldn't be a single litmus test in picking a Supreme
Court justice,'' Dole said on NBC-TV's ``Meet the Press'' program.
   Sen. Patrick Leahy, D-Vt., a member of the Senate Judiciary
Committee, agreed it would be a mistake for Bush to base his choice
on how prospective nominees views the high court's 1973 ruling in
support of abortion rights.
   Leahy, appearing on CBS-TV's ``Face the Nation,'' said there was
``a very real question ... on whether the Senate would go along
with'' a nominee who had been selected because he or she would vote
a particular way on abortion.
   Bush met for 90 minutes with top lieutenants at the White House
Sunday evening for an update on the search for Brennan's successor,
but no decisions were made, White House spokeswoman Alixe Glen said.
   She said the meeting was attended by Vice President Dan Quayle,
Attorney General Dick Thornburgh, presidential counsel C. Boyden
Gray and White House chief of staff John Sununu.
   The brief session in the president's residence was called to
fill in Bush on what had been done since the president convened a
75-minute meeting Saturday morning with the same three officials to
get the ball rolling on the search.
   A source who was familiar with the meeting said afterward that
it consisted of a review of material being gathered on all
potential nominees rather than an attempt to narrow the field to a
``short list.'' The source spoke on condition of not being
identified by name.
   Sen. Howard Metzenbaum, D-Ohio, said Bush should look for
someone who has ``a good judicial record, judicial temperament.''
   Metzenbaum, appearing Sunday on ABC-TV's ``This Week With David
Brinkley'' program, said he doesn't expect to like Bush's nominee,
but added that there was an ``overwhelming likelihood that whomever
the president sends up will be confirmed'' by the Senate.
   Bush has said he hopes to have a new justice seated on the court
by October to succeed Brennan, who was a leading voice of
liberalism on the Supreme Court for 33 years. Brennan, 84,
announced his resignation Friday, citing his age and health.
   Most senators on Sunday declined to identify their choices for
the high court. But Sen. Orrin Hatch, a Utah Republican who himself
has been mentioned as a possible nominee, had a long list of
possible contenders ready.
   ``I don't think I'm going to be selected, nor do I really want
to be,'' Hatch said on ABC.
   Possible candidates mentioned by Hatch or elsewhere include:
Solicitor General Kenneth W. Starr; federal appellate judges Edith
H. Jones and Patrick E. Higginbotham of the 5th Circuit; William W.
Wilkins Jr. of the 4th Circuit; and David Souter of the 1st Circuit.
   Other federal appellate judges mentioned are: Roger J. Miner and
Ralph K. Winter Jr., both of the 2nd Circuit; J. Harvie Wilkinson
III of the 4th Circuit; and Pamela A. Rymer, a former federal
district judge whom Bush recently put on the 9th Circuit.
   There also has been speculation Bush might want to appoint the
court's first Hispanic justice. Possible candidates would be
Ferdinand Fernandez, a federal judge from California, and Ricardo
Hinojosa, a federal judge from Texas.
   South Carolina Gov. Carroll Campbell and Sen. Strom Thurmond,
R-S.C., called the White House on Saturday to lobby on behalf of
Wilkins.
   ``The South deserves a seat on the Supreme Court,'' Campbell
said in Columbia, S.C.
   But while senators were warning Bush not to use abortion as the
overriding factor in his choice of a nominee, some observers were
predicting that abortion would be a focal point in the Senate's
confirmation debate.
   Conservatives have held a slim 5-4 majority on the court and
liberals fear Brennan's successor could push the court further to
the right and jeopardize the constitutional right to an abortion.
   Professor Eleanor Holmes Norton of the Georgetown University Law
Center said both pro-choice and pro-life advocates regard abortion
as a central issue in finding a successor to Brennan.
   ``You can bet your bottom dollar that sitting in the Senate are
going to be men ... who will insist upon bringing out the views of
the justice on this issue,'' Norton said on ABC.
   Norman Ornstein of the American Enterprise Institute, appearing
on CBS, said if Bush picks someone who clearly opposes Roe vs.
Wade, ``we are going to get that as the focal point of hearings
that will be extended for a long time, probably ... right up into
November.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0072 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 2058EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BeachedWhale     07-22 0238</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Beached Whale,0247</SECOND>
<HEAD>Pygmy Sperm Whale Beaches, Dies</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PADRE ISLAND, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A pygmy sperm whale that appeared
emaciated and had ``cookie-cutter'' shark bites on its body died
Sunday after beaching itself, officials said.
   The 10-foot-long male, weighing 800 to 1,000 pounds, was found
around 8 a.m. Sunday by rangers from the Padre Island National
Seashore on the south Texas coast.
   The mammal died in the early afternoon, said Tony Amos, a
researcher at the University of Texas Marine Science Institute at
Port Aransas.
   ``It looked a little emaciated to me, as if it hadn't been
feeding,'' Amos said.
   ``There were a number of cookie cutter shark bites _ it's a
shark that takes sort of cookie-cutter bites out of whales _ sort
of like the mosquito of the whale world ,'' he said. ``But the
bites themselves are not fatal.''
   Amos said a number of the whale's teeth were broken, which is
very unusual. The whale's body was iced down and trucked to
Galveston, where researchers from Texas A&amp;M University will try to
determine what killed the animal and why it became stranded.
   The pygmy sperm whale is rare along the Texas coast, but Amos
said this was not the first such stranding in the area.
   ``We get one about once every year,'' he said. The last one in
the Corpus Christi-Port Aransas area washed ashore last October.
None of those found stranded has survived.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0073 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 2104EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Poland     07-22 0565</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Poland,0587</SECOND>
<HEAD>Walesa Wins Victory in Battle with Solidarity Rivals</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN DANISZEWSKI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WARSAW, Poland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Lech Walesa won a victory Sunday over
supporters of Prime Minister Tadeusz Mazowiecki in their battle for
the allegiance of grassroots Solidarity groups.
   In recent weeks, the Solidarity movement has become split into
two rival camps _ one supporting Walesa, the Solidarity chairman,
and the other, Mazowiecki, the head of the government.
   The two camps have been battling for control of local Solidarity
Citizens Committees, which have dominated Polish politics since the
Communists lost power last year.
   On Sunday, delegates representing local Citizens Committees
overwhelmingly rejected a proposal to form a centralized federation.
   Supporters of Mazowiecki had wanted the local committees to
create a national federation to support his government, especially
now that it is carrying out painful economic reforms.
   During Sunday's six-hour meeting, an overwhelming majority of
the 136 delegates decided instead to hold occasional national
conferences without creating a standing organization.
   Walesa, in a letter read at the opening of Sunday's meeting,
made clear that he felt victory was his.
   ``A few weeks ago there was an attempt made to centralize the
whole citizens movement. It is good that you did not agree to it.
One must not forcibly create any kind of unclear unity,'' Walesa
said.
   Walesa said he could not attend the meeting because he had
broken his arm while on vacation and his doctor advised him not to
travel. Mazowiecki said he couldn't attend because he had influenza.
   The local Citizens Committees sprang up to wage last year's
successful parliamentary campaign that opened the way to a
Solidarity-led government in August. They have been informally
overseen by a 200-member national Citizens Committee of leading
intellectuals and union activists who served at Walesa's invitation.
   Last month, 63 prominent Solidarity intellectuals and activists
on the national committee broke ranks with Walesa. They called for
disbanding the national body.
   Walesa's critics accused him of acting in an autocratic manner
and trying to make the committees into tools for his widely
expected campaign for president of Poland, a post now held by
former Communist leader Wojciech Jaruzelski.
   The anti-Walesa group, finding itself shut out of control of the
national Citizens Committee, had hoped to persuade local committees
to form a national federation to support Mazowiecki.
   Last Monday, Walesa's opponents, including some major figures of
the Solidarity movement, announced the formation of a center-left
political movement, Democratic Action, which supports the
Mazowiecki government.
   Democratic Action is expected to challenge a pro-Walesa
political group, the Center Alliance, which was formed two months
ago.
   In his letter, Walesa urged the local committees to get ready to
choose their own candidates for upcoming free parliamentary
elections, which are expected to be held by early spring.
   The committees' endorsement is important because most of the
candidates backed by them have won in local and national elections.
   Walesa's remarks appeared to be setting the stage for a battle
with his Solidarity rivals for control of the next Parliament,
which could elect a new president.
   The split within Solidarity emerged after Walesa criticized the
Mazowiecki government for what he considers the slow pace of
political and economic reforms.
   Walesa's former allies accuse him of becoming a danger to
democracy because he stirs emotions against the government at a
time when it faces populist attacks for carrying out difficult
economic reforms.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0074 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 2113EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-SewageShutdown     07-22 0240</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Sewage Shutdown,0246</SECOND>
<HEAD>Sewage Dumped Into New York Waterways As Fire Forced Plant
Shutdown</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Raw sewage spilled into three rivers Sunday
after an electrical fire forced the shutdown of a sewage plant
serving Manhattan and the Bronx, a city spokesman said.
   Officials did not expect any public health problems due to the
shutdown of the Wards Island plant, said Department of
Environmental Protection spokesman Peter Cannavo.
   ``It's only a temporary problem,'' said Cannavo. ``We don't
expect beaches to be affected because the flow of the harbor will
carry it out to sea.''
   Water samples were taken from the harbor, and beaches were
patrolled as a precaution, Cannavo said.
   The fire occurred early Sunday at the Wards Island Water
Pollution Control Plant, causing raw sewage to flow into the Harlem
River, upper East River, and a small section of the Hudson River,
he said.
   The fire caused a circuit breaker to fail at 4:10 a.m. on the
main sewage pump, causing the system to shut down. The system was
expected to be fully operational Sunday evening, Cannavo said.
   He said authorities would continue studying water in the harbor
and local beaches Monday to determine the spill's impact.
   The Wards Island sewage plant handles more than 250 million
gallons of wastewater daily from the west Bronx and Upper East Side
of Manhattan. It is one of the largest of 14 plants that treat the
city's raw sewage.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0075 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 2118EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ABCPresident     07-22 0336</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-ABC President,0346</SECOND>
<HEAD>`Skittish' Advertisers Cost ABC $14 Million in Ad Revenue</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DEBORAH HASTINGS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   ABC lost $14 million in advertising revenue
last season to advertisers that boycotted programs they deemed
offensive, network entertainment President Bob Iger said Sunday.
   ``It's a sorry state of affairs when advertisers are acting as
skittish as they are,'' Iger told a news conference attended by
television critics. ``The networks get the heat, but I really think
it should be the advertisers.''
   The lost revenue was slightly more than 1 percent of ABC's total
advertising revenues of $1 billion for this year, Iger said.
   Iger declined to name the advertisers who withdrew their
commercials, and said the $14 million figure represented the first
time ABC had counted such lost revenue since he took over as
programming chief 16 months ago.
   His remarks were in response to continued questioning about
ABC's refusal to rerun an episode of ``thirtysomething'' that
showed two gay men in bed talking about friends who had died from
AIDS.
   Iger's ``economic'' decision to shelve the installment was
labeled as ``cowardice'' by gay and lesbian groups that have
launched a letter-writing protest.
   Iger said Saturday he pulled the episode because half of
``thirtysomething'' advertisers boycotted its first showing last
season, costing the network more than $1 million.
   Other shows that suffered a similar fate last season included an
episode of ``Roseanne'' that focused on teen-age drinking, Iger
said.
   One sponsor pulled out of that program, Iger said. Thirty-second
commercial spots on ``Roseanne'' usually range from $300,000 to
$400,000, according to trade publications.
   Iger's question-and-answer period with television critics also
covered ABC's upcoming fall and spring schedules.
   With six new shows, ABC has a smaller number of fall programs to
launch than CBS or NBC. ``It makes the task at hand easier,'' Iger
said.
   Of those, ``Cop Rock'' is probably ABC's best hope, Iger said.
The new show about singing police officers has drawn a decidedly
mixed response from ABC's affiliated stations.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0076 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 2121EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-NewABCShows     07-22 0175</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-New ABC Shows,0179</SECOND>
<HEAD>ABC Announces Two Replacement Shows for Spring Schedule</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-ABC President</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   ABC announced two new shows Sunday for its
spring replacement schedule.
   ``STAT,'' by producer Danny Arnold of ``Barney Miller,'' will
feature an ensemble comedy cast in an urban hospital emergency room.
   ``The Principal,'' starring Randy Quaid as a schoolteacher who
reluctantly becomes principal, also features comedian Jonathan
Winters as Quaid's father.
   ``Principal'' is from independent producers Marcy Carsey and Tom
Werner, whose Carsey@Werner Co. is responsible for such hits as
``Roseanne'' and ``The Cosby Show.''
   ``Anything But Love,'' canceled at the end of last season but
then given a reprieve as a 1991 spring replacement series, will
have guest appearances by John Ritter, the former star of
``Hooperman'' and ``Three's Company,'' ABC also announced.
   Bruce Weitz, who played the snarling undercover cop Belker on
``Hill Street Blues,'' also will join ``Anything But Love'' as a
new employee of the fictional Chicago magazine where characters
played by actress Jamie Lee Curtis and comic Richard Lewis work.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0077 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 2125EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-CincinnatiExplosion 1stLd-Writethru a0746 07-22 0397</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Cincinnati Explosion, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0746,0405</SECOND>
<HEAD>Cleanup Delayed at Site of Explosion</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 5th graf, `One of ...,' to CORRECT that both patients at
University Hospital in critical condition, sted one fair and one
critical.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By KEVIN WALZER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CINCINNATI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Federal and state investigators on Sunday
delayed the cleanup of a chemical plant leveled by a deadly
explosion last week.
   BASF Corp. had hoped fire officials could begin removing
hundreds of barrels of chemicals from its plant site on Sunday,
said quality assurance manager Ron Leisner.
   ``But there's a lot of consideration that has to be made in a
situation like this,'' he said. ``We don't even have access to some
of the sites yet.''
   Thursday's blast killed one man, injured at least 68 people and
shattered glass in buildings surrounding the plant on the city's
north side. Buildings in the nine-acre complex were leveled or
gutted.
   Both patients at University Hospital remained in critical
condition Sunday. A third person was in critical condition at
Bethesda Hospital.
   Teams from the Occupational Safety and Health Administration and
the state and federal environmental protection agencies were on the
scene, Leisner said.
   The investigators want ``to make sure the area is secure before
we get too deep into the cleanup and removal of any of the damaged
materials,'' he said.
   Some asbestos was found in the building debris, but no airborne
particles, Leisner said. He said the area will continue to be
monitored for asbestos and other dangers.
   Some of the drums to be removed contain hazardous materials and
could explode if punctured or ignited, said William Murphy, OSHA's
area director.
   He said the Ohio Environmental Protection Agency will not allow
those to be removed from the site, and that any that are
potentially explosive will be moved to an isolated area.
   Officials barricaded the area after a rekindled fire was
discovered next to some barrels Saturday, but the fire was
extinguished and all but a portion of one road was reopened.
   The plant, owned by Inmont Corp. until 1985, was cited four
times after recent OSHA inspections. State inspectors found eight
waste storage problems in a Feb. 27 check.
   Investigators said they could not be sure whether waste
management problems were a factor in the blast. Company officials
said preliminary indications were that it was caused by a piece of
equipment that overheated.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0078 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 2132EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-HemingwayDays     07-22 0223</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Hemingway Days,0229</SECOND>
<HEAD>Resident of Another Key Wins Look-alike Contest</HEAD>
<DATELINE>KEY WEST, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   It took him three tries, but Fred Burnham
finally won the Ernest Hemingway Look-Alike Contest on Sunday.
   Burnham came from Longboat Key, up the Gulf Coast near Sarasota,
to win the 10th annual contest at Hemingway's favorite Key West
bar, Sloppy Joe's.
   He attributed his victory to his shaggy gray beard, reminiscent
of the one the late Nobel and Pulitzer prize-winning novelist
sported in his mature years.
   ``The first year I didn't even qualify,'' said Burnham, owner of
a construction cleanup firm. ``But the camaraderie and good times
kept me coming back.''
   This year's competition drew 63 look-alikes from as far away as
Santa Rosa, Calif., to the contest, part of Key West's Hemingway
Days celebration.
   In the 1930s, Hemingway wrote some of his most famous works at
his Key West home, now a museum. They include ``For Whom the Bell
Tolls,'' ``A Farewell to Arms,'' ``The Snows of Kilimanjaro'' and
``Green Hills of Africa.''
   To honor his literary genius, each year the festival coordinates
a short story competition. ``If You Can Hear This,'' by Pamela Ball
of Tallahassee, bested this year's 620 entries to win $2,000 in
cash and prizes.
   Her fictional story explores a relationship between a woman and
the voice of a radio announcer.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0079 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 2137EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-StateChecks     07-22 0580</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-State Checks,0597</SECOND>
<HEAD>Employees Say State Doesn't Realize Hardship of Late Checks</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ELLEN KNICKMEYER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>OKLAHOMA CITY (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Paychecks to thousands of state employees
are overdue by up to 12 days, and unpaid workers said Sunday that
Oklahoma officials don't realize the severity of their plight.
   ``There are people whose kids are getting hungry,'' said Terry
Delaplain, a mental health aide at the state Griffin Memorial
Hospital in Norman, and mother of a 14-year-old son. ``I have food,
and will have food in the house until Tuesday or Wednesday, but
after that ...''
   ``I don't think they're taking it seriously and I don't think
they have a concept of the problems it's causing,'' said Gerald
May, another mental health aide there. ``They're not giving
straight answers. They're not giving assistance.''
   State finance spokesman Harry Culver said Sunday that prospects
were good for some overdue paychecks to be released Monday. State
payroll processors worked until about midnight Friday and Saturday
and came in early both days to get the checks out despite
processing problems caused by a switch to a new computer system,
Culver said.
   As of Friday evening, about 13,500 paychecks out of a state
payroll of more than 60,000 workers were overdue, some by as much
as 12 days, Culver said.
   ``They told us all week we'd get our Friday paychecks late
Friday,'' said Eric Holmes, a fire and safety officer at Griffin
Memorial. ``They told us Friday it'd be Monday, and Friday evening
they told us they'd be out Tuesday.''
   ``There's one guy who called and said, ``I've only got gas to
make it to work one time, so you call me that one time to come get
my check,''' he said.
   Jeanne Devlin said she and 55 other Department of Tourism and
Recreation employees got their July 13 paychecks on Thursday.
   ``We were told every day we were going to get it, and I went in
there every day and had to reassure my day-care person,'' Devlin,
managing editor of the state's Oklahoma Today magazine, said by
telephone from Stillwater. ``I find it embarrassing.''
   May resorted to a pawnshop to keep his checking account solvent
after, assured he would be paid Friday, he wrote checks for bills.
   ``I got $60 for my VCR and $45 for my guitar,'' he said by
telephone.
   The state issued a letter at midweek for workers to take to
creditors vouching that overdue bills were all but out of the
workers' control.
   But workers said the state hadn't issued the letter on state
letterhead.
   ``They gave us a little voucher that's supposed to pacify the
creditors,'' Holmes said. ``Well, it doesn't pacify the grocery
store, the gas station or anybody else like that. And I doubt if it
pacifies the creditors.''
   The state employees' credit union is making instant loans
available to workers whose paychecks are overdue. But Ms. Delaplain
said some of her co-workers make about $5 an hour _ too little to
have made joining the credit union worthwhile.
   Of those workers, Culver said, ``Well, I suppose they should try
to make other arrangements.''
   The state is trying to come up with numbers that workers can
call for advice about their financial predicament, he said.
   ``I don't know anything that can be done, other than fix the
computer problem,'' he said. ``I guess, you know, each one is a
different case, but certainly our complete concern and sympathy
goes out for anybody in this situation.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0080 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 2145EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-HawaiiEclipse     07-22 0190</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Hawaii Eclipse,0194</SECOND>
<HEAD>Partial Eclipse In Hawaii A Prelude To Total Eclipse Next Year</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HONOLULU (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Many Hawaii residents got glimpses through
breaks in the clouds of a partial solar eclipse, a prelude to a
rare total eclipse that will occur in the islands in less than a
year.
   More than 2,000 people showed up Saturday evening at Bishop
Museum, borrowing from a supply of mirror-like safety filters to
watch the moon block the sun.
   At its peak shortly after 6 p.m,. 62.2 percent of the sun was
blanked out.
   Scientists for several days had been advising residents to avoid
looking directly at the sun, warning that permanent eye damage
could result.
   Besides the opaque filters and welder's goggles used at the
museum, simple pinhole cameras were set up to reflect the eclipse
on the back wall of a box.
   The big show will occur on the morning of July 11, 1991. Hawaii
Island, the southernmost in the chain, will experience a total
eclipse for four minutes, one of the longest in the United States
this century and the last total eclipse in the United States until
2017.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0081 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 2202EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Obit-Turner     07-22 0218</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Turner,0226</SECOND>
<HEAD>Jazz Pianist, Joe Turner, Dies in Paris</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Jazz pianist Joe Turner, who played with such
greats as Louis Armstrong and Benny Carter, has died of a heart
attack in Paris. He was 82.
   Turner, who died Saturday at suburban Montreuil hospital, helped
make famous the ``stride style'' of piano playing. His work earned
him a place in jazz history beside pianists like James P. Johnson,
Fats Waller, Art Tatum and Willie ``The Lion'' Smith.
   Since 1962, he had played in La Calavados, a night club on the
Champs Elysees.
   Turner was born Nov. 3, 1907, in Baltimore. At 18, he left the
city to pursue his musical career in New York.
   A big break came in 1928, when he was hired to play in the Benny
Carter orchestra. He joined Armstrong's group in 1930.
   Turner used to play in Harlem clubs, and in 1935 he replaced Art
Tatum, who was ill. He performed with jazz singer Adelaide Hall and
went on a European tour with her.
   Drafted during World War II, Turner played piano in the U.S.
Army orchestra directed by Sy Oliver.
   After the war, he settled in Europe and played with Rex Stewart.
He had lived in Paris since 1962.
   No information was immediately available about survivors or
funeral arrangements.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0082 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 2257EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-MicrochipArrest     07-22 0197</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Microchip Arrest,0204</SECOND>
<HEAD>Man Arrested in Microchip Case</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HONOLULU (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A man was arrested in the theft of $321,000
worth of state-of-the-art computer microchips, the FBI announced
Sunday.
   Bernard Pornaras of Hollister, Calif., was arrested Saturday
night, the FBI's top agent in Honolulu, Jim R. Freeman, said in a
statement.
   Pornaras is wanted in Santa Clara County, Calif., along with two
other men in the theft of the chips from a northern California
company, Freeman said.
   The three allegedly planned to sell 642 chips worth $500 each in
the Far East, Freeman said. The chips increase computers' memory
capacities.
   A second man, Raymond Reynolds, was arrested in California and
the third suspect, Michael Arnold, remains at large, the agent said.
   Each of the three was charged in a criminal complaint filed
Thursday in Santa Clara County with interstate transportation of
stolen property, which carries a maximum sentence of 10 years in
prison.
   Pornaras was being held pending an appearance before a U.S.
magistrate, Freeman said.
   The arrests were the result of a joint investigation by the FBI,
the Internal Revenue Service, the state Department of Motor
Vehicles and the Santa Clara County district attorney's office.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0083 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 2300EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Korea 1stLd-Writethru a0750 07-22 0736</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Korea, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0750,0754</SECOND>
<HEAD>South Korea Willing To Negotiate North Korean Preconditions</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS thruout to UPDATE with government ministers announcing
they are ready to negotiate with North Korea; no pickup</NOTE>
<DATELINE>SEOUL, South Korea (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   South Korea is ready to negotiate
North Korean preconditions for opening the border to free travel
between the rival nations, South Korean officials announced Monday.
   The decision follows a major policy speech Friday by President
Roh Tae-woo, who proposed to North Korea that the common border be
opened for five days in August on a trial basis to allow free
travel for residents of the two sides. He said open borders could
lead talks on eventual unification of the Koreas.
   Communist North Korea immediately dismissed Roh's proposal as
``fraudulent propaganda.'' It said South Korea must first tear down
``concrete walls'' allegedly built along its border, end national
security laws banning pro-Communist activity, and release
dissidents jailed for promoting unification.
   Three Cabinet ministers Monday proposed that inter-Korea talks
be held Friday to discuss the North Korean preconditions.
   The heavily fortified border between the two Koreas is tightly
sealed, and more than 1.5 million troops are stationed on either
side behind concrete bunkers and barbed wire. There is no mail,
travel or other communication between the two sides.
   Justice Minister Lee Jong-nam, Defense Minister Lee Sang-hoon
and National Unification Minister Hong Sung-chul held a joint news
conference to announce the South Korean policy.
   ``In order to open the border and realize grand national
exchanges, we are ready to discuss any problems related to it,''
the unification minister said on national radio and television.
   Pro-Western South Korea and communist North Korea were divided
at the end of World War II and fought the Korean war from 1950 to
1953. They are technically still at war because no peace treaty was
signed.
   In their announcement Monday, Hong and other ministers said the
discussions should include any problems either side would raise.
They noted that North Korea has a number of legal and systematic
barriers to free travel.
   The North Koreans had also demanded that South Korean radical
students and dissidents be allowed to attend a ``pan-national
congress'' the North plans to hold at the border village of
Panmunjom on Aug. 15 to promote unification.
   The unification minister, Hong, said the Seoul government would
support the Aug. 15 rally if the South Korean delegation would
include ``representatives of all walks of life.'' The North invited
only dissident and radical student leaders from the South.
   Hong also said his government would allow a cross-border march
by any organization on the two sides. South Korea banned such
marches by its dissident groups in the past.
   The justice minister said South Korea can discuss preconditions
North Korea has set in connection of the border opening, but he
noted that Pyongyang also has harsh national security laws and
human rights problems.
   Several prominent South Korean dissident leaders have been
jailed for making unauthorized trips to North Korea in violation of
national security law. North Korea has demanded the release of the
jailed dissidents and the repeal of the law under which they were
punished.
   The justice minister said North Korea also has laws calling for
capital punishment for those supporting South Korea and its
constitution states that the No. 1 goal of the North is bringing
Communism to the South.
   Quoting reports by international human rights groups, Lee said
North Korea is holding 152,000 political prisoners at 12
concentration camps. The prisoners included former prime minister
Lee Kun-mo, former vice presidents Kim Chang-bong and Park
Kum-chul, and ex-national security chief Kim Byung-ha.
   The minister also said North Korea imposes tight domestic travel
restrictions. The North's 21 million people cannot travel beyond
the boundary of a country they live in without prior government
approval, he said.
   The defense minister proposed an on-site joint investigation of
the alleged ``concrete walls'' in the South, along with similar
barriers which he claimed exist along the northern sector of the
border.
   He said the ``walls'' are in fact a series of tank traps built
along several sections of the 155-mile border to block a possible
North Korean invasion.
   North Korea also has anti-tank barriers along the border, the
minister said.
   The defense minister also demanded a joint investigation of four
``invasion tunnels'' allegedly dug by North Korea under the
Demilitarized Zone separating the two Koreas.
   North Korea has denied digging the tunnels.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900722-0084 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-90 2301EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-AlaskaFires     07-22 0395</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Alaska Fires,0409</SECOND>
<HEAD>Smoke From Alaska Wildfires Creating Health, Driving Hazards</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARK BAUMGARTNER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ANCHORAGE, Alaska (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Wildfires burned over more than 900,000
acres of Alaska on Sunday, producing smoke that hampered
firefighting and triggered an air-quality alert in Fairbanks and
much of the rest of the interior.
   Visibility at the Riley Creek Visitors Center at Denali National
Park, 120 miles south of Fairbanks and Alaska's top tourist
attraction, dropped to a quarter-mile at times over the weekend.
   ``The park is up and running as usual but they're cautioning
people not to exert themselves and to spend time indoors,'' said
Park Service spokesman John Quinley.
   People in Fairbanks were given similar warnings.
   No injuries or serious damage has been reported.
   Smoke from wildfires that have already burned more than a
million acres made it impossible to get accurate estimates of the
sizes of some blazes, Quinley said.
   Thick smoke grounded some aircraft used in fighting the
54,000-acre Tok River fire, said Trish Hogervorst-Rukke, a
spokeswoman with Alaska's inter-agency fire information center.
   But the smoke also held down temperatures in the interior and
pushed up the humidity, reducing the intensity of the blazes.
   The Tok River fire, started by lightning three weeks ago,
remained the state's most labor-intensive blaze, occupying 789
firefighters.
   Officials estimate that firefighting statewide is costing
$700,000 a day.
   The Beaver fire, named for a village on the Yukon River,
remained Alaska's largest; on Sunday it was burning a 10-by-48-mile
section of spruce forest, said Hogervorst-Rukke.
   Fires along the Alaska Highway reduced visibility to less than 2
miles in a wide region north of Tok to Fairbanks.
   Authorities said Alaska firefighting crews were also sent to the
Canadian border village of Old Crow, where about 280 people were
evacuated because of fire near the Porcupine River.
   A fire 25 miles northeast of King Salmon was estimated at 1,100
acres and was being fought with specially designed planes from
Canada that fly low, scooping water from lakes and depositing it
over fires.
   The Kanuti Flats fire, about 140 miles north of Fairbanks, was
burning 100,000 acres on Sunday and was within two miles of the
trans-Alaska oil pipeline. Authorities were monitoring the fire but
not fighting it.
   Authorities said there was no danger to the pipeline, which
Quinley said isburied beneath the tundra near where the fire is
burning.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
</Collection>
