<Collection>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0001 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-04-90 2321EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BRF--PlaneCrash     02-04 0131</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Plane Crash,0134</SECOND>
<HEAD>Plane Hits Another While Landing, One Dies</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: First name `Abert' in 3rd graf is cq.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>HOUSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two single-engine airplanes collided as they
tried to land at a small airport Sunday and one crashed, killing
the pilot, officials said.
   The accident occurred around 1:30 p.m. when the planes tried to
land on the same runway at Hooks Airport north of Houston.
   A plane flown by Abert Bulgawicz, 45, of Magnolia came down on
top of a plane flown by Douglas Howze, 36, of Tomball, and severed
the tail of Howze's plane with its propeller, said Harris County
Constable Sgt. Michael Hardin.
   Howze's plane crashed, and he was killed. Bulgawicz and a
passenger landed safely, Hardin said.
   The National Transportation Safety Board was investigating the
accident.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0002 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-04-90 0012EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-RadiationScare     02-04 0288</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Radiation Scare,0299</SECOND>
<HEAD>Experts Check Soviet Cargo Plane in Radioactive Scare</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By WILLIAM C. CRUM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PORTLAND, Ore. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Radiation safety experts checked a Soviet
cargo plane Saturday after crew members reported canisters
containing radioactive uranium hexafluoride might have broken open.
   No leak was found, officials said.
   State safety officials and the Portland Fire Bureau's hazardous
materials team checked for radiation for more than two hours aboard
the Antonov 124, which landed at Portland International Airport
shortly before 1 p.m., said Doug Roberts, a spokesman for the Port
of Portland.
   The material was then turned over to the company that contracted
to bring it into the United States, Roberts said.
   Ray Paris, a radiation safety officer with the Oregon Health
Division, said the 11 Soviet crew members became concerned when
they spotted a milky white liquid collected on the floor under the
nine canisters after the airplane landed.
   Paris said uranium hexafluoride is a white powder. When mixed
with water, it gives off a vapor that can be fatal, he said.
   He said emergency crews checked the crew for respiratory
problems, then checked two Customs agents, crew members and the
airplane for radioactivity.
   All tests were negative, Paris said.
   He said experts determined the liquid formed as condensation on
the outside of the canisters and froze during the flight. It melted
as the airplane landed and dripped onto the floor, mixing with dust
or dirt to form the milky white substance, Paris said.
   Uranium hexaflouride is a chemical compound formed when uranium
ore is treated with sulfuric acid to extract uranium oxide. Roberts
said the material was bound for a processing center in Washington
state to be made into fuel for nuclear power plants.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0003 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-04-90 0052EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-AlabamaStorms     02-04 0176</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Alabama Storms,0182</SECOND>
<HEAD>Storm Flips Tractor-Trailers, Cars; Minor Injuries Reported</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BIRMINGHAM, Ala. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A severe storm spawning at least one
tornado whipped through four counties Saturday night, flipping
tractor-trailers and numerous cars, a state official said.
   No fatalities were reported by early Sunday.
   Bill Brock, director of the state Department of Emergency
Management, said there were reports that seven tractor-trailers
were upside-down at the intersection of interstates 59 and 459 in
Birmingham. He said numerous cars also were reported flipped over.
   He said there were reports of minor injuries.
   Officials confirmed one tornado sighting in the west Alabama
community of Carrollton.
   Brock said emergency officials were trying to confirm reported
tornado sightings in Tuscaloosa, Jefferson, St. Clair and Shelby
counties.
   The storm system moving through the state Saturday evening could
have spawned multiple tornadoes, Brock said. Officials would
probably have to wait for daylight on Sunday to confirm the
reports, he said.
   Brock said there were widespread power outages in the Birmingham
area, and at least one shelter had been opened in west Birmingham.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0004 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-04-90 0108EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u p AM-NewOrleansMayoral 6thLd-Writethru a0634 02-04 0654</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-New Orleans Mayoral, 6th Ld-Writethru, a0634,0672</SECOND>
<HEAD>New Orleans Mayor Wins Re-Election</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto planned</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 2 grafs to UPDATE with final results; picks up 3rd
graf, Barthelemy, New ...'.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By JANET McCONNAUGHEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW ORLEANS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Mayor Sidney Barthelemy won a second term in
a primary election Saturday over a white challenger after a
campaign marked on both sides by accusations of race-baiting.
   In complete but unofficial returns, Bathelemy had 79,995 votes,
or 55 percent, to 65,047, or 44 percent, for his fellow Democrat
Donald Mintz. Two other candidates split the remaining 1 percent.
   Barthelemy, New Orleans' second black mayor, smiled broadly as
he took the podium for a victory statement but became more serious
as he called for New Orleans to join together after a divisive
campaign.
   ``We are in difficult times. We have laid the foundations for
the future. But we cannot build a great city divided,'' he said.
``We all must work together.''
   Barthelemy, 47, did not announce victory until his 46-year-old
opponent, an attorney who had never before run for office, conceded
defeat.
   ``Sidney, to you, congratulations and best wishes. If permitted,
I look forward to working with you in the days ahead,'' Mintz told
supporters at another hotel.
   Barthelemy avoided a runoff by winning more than half the vote.
   Ed Renwick, who was Barthelemy's pollster and WWL-TV's analyst,
said Mintz needed 80 percent of the white vote and 20 percent of
the black vote but got about 75 percent of the white vote and 15
percent of the black.
   Turnout was predicted at 55 percent to 60 percent of New
Orleans' 237,000 registered voters, more than 54 percent of whom
are black.
   Recent polls showed Barthelemy had erased Mintz's early lead and
was about a dozen percentage points ahead.
   Herman J. ``Buster'' Bustamente, a Democrat, and black
businessman Rudy E. Mills Sr., an independent, also ran.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   _greater than
   Barthelemy's easygoing, conciliatory style contrasted with the
hard-hitting intensity of Mintz, who resigned as head of the city's
dock board to make the race.
   Mintz and Barthelemy denied the allegations of race-baiting and
called them evidence that the other side was losing and desperate
for an issue.
   Barthelemy, who was Louisiana's first black state senator and
city councilman at large since Reconstruction, accused Mintz of
being behind fliers depicting Barthelemy as an Uncle Tom. One shows
him with a half-white face; the other shows him robbing the grave
of the late Ernest Dutch Morial, New Orleans' first black mayor.
   Mintz, who is Jewish and wears a lapel pin showing black and
white hands interlinked, vehemently denied the allegations,
boasting of a strong civil rights record, including an Urban League
award to his law firm.
   ``The mayor who said he wanted to bring people together has
sought to divide them,'' Mintz said.
   He said some of Barthelemy's radio advertisements catered to
anti-white racism, and he accused the mayor of anti-Semitic
campaigning because of a flier saying Mintz's civil rights
credentials apparently did not apply to blacks.
   Barthelemy called the anti-Semitism allegation ridiculous,
noting that he has appointed Jews and received a B'nai B'rith award.
   Despite the sharp disagreements, the campaign drew relatively
little attention as it competed with the Christmas holidays, a
record freeze, the Sugar Bowl and the Super Bowl.
   There was never much interest in the issues: the city's high
crime rate, unemployment _ which was above 10 percent for much of
1988 before falling to 6.9 percent in December 1989 _ and the
candidates' experience and competence.
   Until late in December, most of the interest was focused on
Morial, who served from 1978 to 1986 and was widely expected to run
until Dec. 14, when he announced that he would not.
   From then until his death Dec. 23, interest centered on whether
he would endorse either Mintz, a protege of his, or Barthelemy, who
often battled with him when Barthelemy was a city councilman.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0005 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-04-90 0115EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-NuclearAlert 4thLd-Writethru a0632 02-04 0442</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Nuclear Alert, 4th Ld-Writethru, a0632,0449</SECOND>
<HEAD>Low-Level Alert Declared at Pennsylvania Nuclear Plant</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 6 grafs to UPDATE that alert declared over at
12:25 a.m. EST; picks up 7th graf, `The county agency ...'.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>BERWICK, Pa. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Faulty circuit breakers triggered a
low-level alert for more than six hours Saturday at a nuclear plant
in central Pennsylvania, but no radiation was released, Lt. Gov.
Mark Singel said.
   Fire and ambulance crews were called to Susquehanna Steam
Heating Station, but no injuries were reported and no employees
were evacuated from the plant.
   ``It is not all that serious,'' said Karl Abraham, a spokesman
for the Nuclear Regulatory Commission. ``There is no threat to the
public at all or to the workers in the plant.''
   Singel said the circuit breaker failures occurred during a
routine safety check at the plant, and a valve on a cooling water
line did not reopen. Water temperatures in the reactor system
climbed from a normal of about 200 degrees to a high of 252
degrees. The plant was not operating at the time of the safety
check.
   ``The water temperature was rising and there was an insufficient
flow of water through the system,'' Singel said at a news
conference at the state Capitol in Harrisburg. ``It is important to
note that the incident has been completely contained within the
reactor containment.''
   The Level 2 alert declared at 5:53 p.m. meant that a problem had
arisen that could affect the safety of plant operations, said Jim
Siracuse of the Luzerne County Emergency Management Agency. A Level
4 alert is the most severe. The incident was declared over at 12:25
a.m.
   The county agency declared the alert because of the heat level
problems within Unit 1. The reactor was shut down Thursday due to a
leak in the plant's hydraulic control system. The problems were not
related, according to plant spokesman Ira Caplan.
   Plant workers were working late Saturday to cool the reactor
water through another system, according to Caplan. No water or
steam was released.
   Abraham said the unit would not be restarted until NRC and plant
officials had determined the cause of the problem.
   John Comey of the Pennsylvania Emergency Management Agency said
only three or four Level 2 alerts have occurred in Pennsylvania
since the March 1979 accident at Three Mile Island.
   All emergency response personnel in Luzerne and Lackawana
Counties and all municipalities within a 10-mile radius of the
plant have been activated and called into their offices, according
to Comey.
   The plant in Salem Township 15 to 20 miles southwest of
Wilkes-Barre is owned and operated by Pennsylvania Power &amp; Light.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0006 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-04-90 0131EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-FamilySlain     02-04 0305</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Family Slain,0315</SECOND>
<HEAD>Two Men Arrested in Slayings of Family</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CLARKSDALE, Miss. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two men were arrested Saturday in the
slayings of a farm couple and their two children whose bound bodies
were found in their burning home, officials said.
   Anthony Carr, 24, of Clarksdale and Robert Simon Jr. 26, of
Memphis, Tenn., were being held Saturday night at the Clarksdale
Police Department on charges of capital murder.
   They were arrested shortly after 4 p.m. in Clarksdale, about 70
miles south of Memphis, Tenn., said Lt. Kenny Dickerson, a Highway
Patrol investigator.
   Carl Webster Parker, 58, and his wife, Bobbie Jo, 45, and their
children, Charlotte Jo, 9, and Gregory, 12, apparently walked in on
a burglary of their home Friday night, authorities said.
   Investigators said they suspect the fire was set intentionally
to cover the killings and destroy evidence.
   Earlier in the evening, the family had attended Bible study at
Riverside Baptist Church in Clarksdale, where they were members,
their pastor said. Their house is 15 miles from Clarksdale, and
their nearest neighbors are more than a quarter-mile away.
   All were shot between two and four times at close range at about
10:30 p.m., said Quitman County Coroner J.W. Jenkins. He said two
guns were used.
   Jenkins said the girl was raped. ``It looked like she had broken
loose and tried to run,'' he said.
   The Lambert Volunteer Fire Department received a call between
11:15 p.m. and 11:30 p.m. Friday that the Parkers' home was
burning, Assistant Fire Chief Chris Dancy said.
   Firefighters pulled the bodies of the father and two children
from the home before fire gutted it, Dancy said. The three bodies
were in a rear room ``within 5 feet of each other,'' Jenkins said.
   After the fire was extinguished, Bobbie Jo Parker's body was
found in a back bedroom.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0007 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-04-90 0137EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-TaxRollback     02-04 0157</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Tax Rollback,0162</SECOND>
<HEAD>Residents Vote to Lower Tax Bills</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SAN ANTONIO, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   By an overwhelming margin, voters
decided Saturday to lower their tax bills by rolling back a city
property tax hike.
   The measure to cut the hike from 12.1 percent to 8 percent was
passed by a vote of 76,167 to 42,673 in unofficial results, the San
Antonio City Clerk's office said.
   The measure was hotly debated in the weeks preceding the
election. A rollback will cost the city $3.9 million in revenue.
   Mayor Lila Cockrell and the Hispanic Chamber of Commerce had
opposed the rollback. The chamber said it would endanger economic
expansion.
   Election officials had predicted a heavy turnout because it drew
more absentee voters than any previous city election. When the
two-week absentee voting period ended Tuesday, 53,328 people had
cast early ballots.
   Voters in south Texas' Kleberg County and its county seat,
Kingsville, also rolled back tax hikes Saturday.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0008 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-04-90 0142EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-FlightCanceled     02-04 0160</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Flight Canceled,0163</SECOND>
<HEAD>Armenian Quake Relief Flight Canceled</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A flight intended to bring supplies to
Armenian earthquake victims was canceled just hours before takeoff
Saturday, with relief officials saying the Soviet government
refused to let their plane land.
   Members of the United Armenian Fund, a relief organization, said
they were told that ``authorities in Moscow canceled the earthquake
relief flight ... citing `technical reasons.'''
   The flight carrying space heaters donated by the U.S. Department
of Defense, medical supplies, food and winter clothing was
scheduled to take off from Los Angeles International Airport at 3
p.m.
   The UAF previously shipped three loads of relief supplies by
plane to Soviet Armenia, which was devastated by a 1988 earthquake
that killed thousands.
   ``Doctors and relief agencies anxiously await this crucial
cargo,'' the group said in a statement. ``The UAF will take
immediate steps to convey our strong objections to all
participating parties, demanding an immediate resumption of
flights.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0009 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-04-90 0641EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i BC-Soviet-Party     02-04 0177</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Soviet-Party,0181</SECOND>
<HEAD>Thousands Gather For Rally Ahead of Key Communist Party Plenum</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Thousands of demonstrators poured into a Moscow
park Sunday for a rally mounted by pro-democracy groups on the eve
of a Communist Party meeting expected to consider a multiparty
system.
   Police blocked off major streets in downtown Moscow in
anticipation of the legal march.
   People were gathering at Gorky Park early Sunday afternoon, and
police said the marchers were expected to head to a square in
central Moscow near the Kremlin for the rally.
   Among the groups organizing the event were the Russian and
Moscow Popular Fronts, the Association of Moscow Voters, as well as
the progressive Memorial group.
   One objective of the rally is to coordinate pro-democracy groups
ahead of elections on March 4 for the parliament of the Russian
Federated Republic, the largest in the Soviet Union.
   The rally comes one day before a key Communist Party plenum
where Soviet President Mikhail S. Gorbachev is expected to ask the
Central Committee to accept the possibility of competing political
parties.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0010 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-04-90 1148EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-JailPopulations     02-04 0660</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Jail Populations,650</SECOND>
<NOTE>For release at 5 p.m. EST</NOTE>
<HEAD>Some 9.7 million People Jailed in Year Ending June 1988</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CAROLYN SKORNECK</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   About 9.7 million people were thrown in a jail
cell in the United States during the year that ended June 30, 1988,
the Justice Department said Sunday.
   During the same year, some 9.6 million people were released from
jail, and both numbers represented increases of 20 percent over
1983 figures, said the Office of Justice Statistics study.
   The average jail stay was three days, with 39 percent of inmates
spending one day or less behind bars, 23 percent spending two to
four days and 10 percent spending five to seven days, the study
said.
   About 3 percent served more than six months and 1 percent spent
more than a year behind bars.
   On June 30, 1988, the jail population totaled 343,569, or 144 of
every 100,000 Americans, the study said. That rate was 47 percent
higher than the 98 per 100,000 five years earlier.
   The study focused on local jails, defined as locally
administered confinement facilities holding people awaiting trial
or sentenced to terms usually of a year or less. About 51 percent
of the people in jail had not been convicted of any crime when they
were incarcerated, while 49 percent had been convicted, the same
level as in 1983, the study found.
   The census did not include facilities in Connecticut, Delaware,
Hawaii, Rhode Island and Vermont that combine jails with prisons,
which are state or federal institutions.
   The study did not indicate the main charges of the 9.7 million
brought into custody.
   Among the study's findings:
   _Jail populations in Southern states grew 61 percent between
1983 and 1988, to a total of 143,751 on June 30, 1988, while jail
populations in the West increased 58 percent to 91,559; the
Northeast jail population grew by 57 percent to 57,613 and the
Midwest grew by 28 percent to 50,646.
   _The states with the largest percentage increase between June
30, 1983, and the same day on 1988 were Nevada, up 149 percent;
Arizona, 104 percent; Florida and Texas, 93 percent; New Jersey 86
percent; Tennessee, 81 percent.
   _The only places where jail populations declined were Alaska,
down 27 percent, and Washington, D.C., which reclassified an
institution from a jail to a prison.
   _The highest rates of jail inmates per 100,000 state residents
were in Georgia, 276; Louisiana, 255; Florida, 229; California,
227; Tennessee, 222; and Nevada, 222.
   _The lowest rates per 100,000 state residents were in Iowa, 37;
North Dakota, 43; Maine, 56; Nebraska, 72; and New Hampshire and
South Dakota, both 73.
   _The female jail population rose 93 percent during the five-year
period to 30,411 on June 30, 1988. Women still represented only 9
percent of the total jail population, compared with 7 percent in
1983. The male population rose 51 percent to 313,158.
   _The percentage of juveniles in adult jails declined from 0.8
percent in 1983 to 0.5 percent in 1988, reflecting a 3 percent drop
for boys and a 4 percent drop for girls.
   _The racial breakdown of inmates was 43 percent non-Hispanic
whites, 41 percent non-Hispanic blacks, 15 percent Hispanics and 1
percent either American Indians, Alaska natives, Asians or Pacific
Islanders.
   _Of the 667 people who died in jail during the year ending June
30, 1988, a total of 284 (43 percent) were suicides, 274 (41
percent) were illnesses not including AIDS, 66 (10 percent) died of
AIDS, 10 (1 percent) were homicide victims and 33 (5 percent) died
of other causes including accidents.
   _Jail capacity increased 30 percent to 339,633 beds between 1983
to 1988, and the amount of rated capacity that was occupied totaled
101 percent in 1988, up from 85 percent five years earlier.
However, about 40,000 inmates, some 12 percent of the jail
population on June 30, 1988, were being held for other correctional
authorities, including some 26,500 held because of overcrowding
elsewhere.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0011 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-04-90 1207EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-PanamaDefense Bjt   02-04 0656</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama Defense, Bjt,0674</SECOND>
<HEAD>Panamanians Debate Whether U.S. Forces Should Remain to Defend
Canal</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP Extra</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ELOY O. AGUILAR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The U.S. invasion of Panama has once
more raised the issue of whether the United States will maintain a
military presence beyond the year 2000, when the American bases
must close.
   President Guillermo Endara has abolished Gen. Manuel Antonio
Noriega's military, leaving open the question about who would
defend the Panama Canal. Endara has made no public statement about
the issue of the bases.
   The newspaper Panama America newspaper recently suggested the
U.S.-Panama treaties be renegotiated to allow American payments in
exchange for keeping American military bases. The 1977 treaties
provide for the possibility of new agreements on defense of the
waterway.
   Some Panamanians believe the United States must continue to
handle the canal's security after the year 2000.
   The Spanish-language newspaper said, ``The optimum benefit of
leasing the bases would be the possibility of charging (rent) even
before the year 2000.'' Although Panama collects no rent from the
United States, the U.S. bases mean nearly $100 million a year for
Panama's economy in services purchased and other expenditures.
   Some Panamanian military sources say the 58-mile canal is
indefensible because of the immense territory it covers and that
the United States would need only a token security force.
   Some U.S. military sources say the United States might maintain
Howard Air Base, just outside of Panama City, and the Rodman Naval
Base.
   The treaties did away with the old Panama Canal Zone, a 10-mile
stretch across the country along the canal that was U.S. territory,
and stipulate that the canal will be turned over to Panama on Dec.
31, 1999, when the last American soldier is to go home.
   U.S. bases have been in Panama since the beginning of the
century. The United States now maintains 10 military installations
in Panama as part of the Southern Command with 12,000 soldiers.
Another 12,000 were sent in during the invasion.
   Panamanians, who approved the treaties in a plebiscite organized
by former dictator Omar Torrijos, do not dare ask for a revision of
the treaties for fear of sounding anti-nationalist. The topic was
taboo before the U.S. invasion Dec. 20.
   The United States said it invaded and toppled Noriega because
his government had become a threat to U.S. interests and the
operation of the canal, and to bring him to trial on U.S.
drug-trafficking charges.
   Noriega claimed the U.S. government wanted to get rid of him
because he opposed U.S. plans to renege on the treaties and
maintain its large military installations in Panama.
   The United States does not want to appear as if it is going back
on its word. It has said repeatedly that it intends to abide by the
treaties.
   ``I personally do not feel that the United States needs a large
military presence in Panama after the year 2000,'' said one U.S.
Army officer who has been in Panama for years.
   ``A large military presence when the world situation is
changing, could be a political liability for the United States,''
he said, speaking on condition he not be idenfitied. ``The United
States would be criticized as an expansionist power.''
   Maj. Gen. Marc Cisneros, commander of U.S. Army South, the
ground forces in charge of protecting the canal, says the United
States will meet its obligations to leave on schedule.
   ``It is the intention of the United States to fully comply with
the canal treaties,'' Cisneros said.
   Cisneros emphasized the new Panamanian government, ``if it
maintains a democratic system, will be able to run the canal as
efficiently as we have.''
   When Endara abolished Noriega's military forces, he established
in the national police in their place.
   Last month, as stipulated by the agreements, a Panamanian became
adminstrator of the Panama Canal Commission, the U.S. federal
agency that adminsters the canal. About 30 ships daily use the
canal.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0012 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-04-90 1217EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Europe-Storm     02-04 0293</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Europe-Storm,0300</SECOND>
<HEAD>Storm Kills 29 People in France, West Germany</HEAD>
<DATELINE>FRANKFURT, West Germany (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A storm that swept through
northern France and West Germany with hurricane-strength winds
killed at least 29 people and caused widespread property damage,
authorities in both countries said Sunday.
   The storm struck western France on Saturday with gusts up to 104
mph. The region's worst storm in 20 years left 23 people dead,
authorities said.
   Among the buildings damaged was the 12th century cathedral at
Chartres, one of the world's most magnificent Gothic structures.
The wind peeled copper plates from the roof, leaving a
540-square-foot hole over the nave between the two bell towers of
the church, 50 miles southwest of Paris.
   The state-run Electricite de France said that by midday Sunday,
only 160,000 people remained without electricity of the 2 million
or more whose power was cut at the height of the storm.
   Rail and air service, which had been severely disrupted by the
high winds, fallen trees and electric wires, was back to normal
Sunday. Several main highways also had been blocked temporarily.
   Officials said it was too early to estimate the cost of the
damage.
   The storm also struck West Germany on Saturday with winds of up
to 93 mph, leaving six people dead and several injured, including
two people killed by falling trees in the Frankfurt area, officials
said Sunday.
   High winds ripped off the roof of a sport hall near Offenbach
and blew down one wall, injuring four spectators at a handball
game. Downed trees blocked major highways for hours and delayed a
number of trains.
   On Jan. 25, a storm with winds up to 110 mph killed a total of
95 people in Britain, Holland, Belgium, France, the Germanys and
Denmark.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0013 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-04-90 1235EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Soviet-Unrest     02-04 0532</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Unrest,0547</SECOND>
<HEAD>Armenian Delegation Breaks Off Peace Talks with Azerbaijanis</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Soviet-Party, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DEBORAH G. SEWARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Armenian negotiators broke off informal peace
talks with Azerbaijanis and headed home Sunday after accusing them
of pressuring Armenians to evacuate two villages in Azerbaijan, a
participant said.
   Armenian leaders also instructed their negotiators in Riga,
Latvia, that the Armenian All-National Movement had refused to
ratify an agreement to seek a peaceful settlement of the conflict
and exchange information on hostages.
   The talks, held without the participation of the Soviet
government, began Friday with mediators from the people's fronts
movements in the western republics of Latvia, Estonia and
Lithuania. Direct talks followed on Saturday.
   ``Everything went well until there was a pause in the talks.
Then the leaders of the Armenian All-National Movement in Yerevan
told the negotiators to cut the talks,'' said Ints Upmacis, a
Latvian People's Front leader present during the meeting.
   The Armenians headed for Yerevan early Sunday, Upmacis said in a
telephone interview.
   The Armenian political movement in Yerevan accused the
Azerbaijan People's Front of pressing Armenian residents to
evacuate the villages of Azad and Kamo in the Khanlar region of
Azerbaijan, the official news agency Tass reported.
   The residents were told they were in danger of being attacked,
and the Armenians claimed the army said it was unable to guarantee
their safety, Upmacis said.
   ``The Armenian National Movement board does not find it possible
to continue joint consultations in Riga,'' a statement issued by
the movement's press center in Yerevan said. ``Joint consultations
and talks can be possible in the future only on condition of the
termination of such actions.''
   When informed that the Armenians were planning to leave the
talks, the Azerbaijani negotiators agreed to try and verify the
Armenian claim, but Communist Party officials and Soviet army
officials reached in the Azerbaijani capital of Baku said they had
no information to support the charges.
   The Azerbaijani delegation said it was ready to resume talks
with the Armenians and departed for a meeting of representatives of
pro-democracy groups in the Lithuanian capital of Vilnius, Upmacis
said.
   Leaders of the Azerbaijani People's Front in Baku could not be
immediately reached to comment on the Armenian decision to break
off the talks.
   Outbreaks of ethnic violence have plagued the two southern
republics for two years following Armenia's demand for annexation
of Nagorno-Karabakh, a predominantly Armenian enclave located
inside Azerbaijan.
   The latest round of violence began Jan. 13, resulting in the
deaths of at least 214 people and the evacuation of thousands of
ethnic Armenians who lived in Azerbaijan.
   The Soviet Army marched into Baku on Jan. 20 in response to the
violence and the volatile developments prompted leaders of the
three Baltic Fronts to propose peace talks out of concern that the
conflict could jeopardize their own peaceful drive for democracy
and independence in the Baltics.
   Tass said extremist elements in the Azerbaijani People's Front
continued to disrupt efforts of the Communist Party, the army and
other bodies to stabilize the situation in Baku.
   During the weekend, extremists using two armored personnel
carriers fired at helicopters, but there were no injuries, the
agency reported.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0014 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-04-90 1301EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-FamilyPlot Bjt   02-04 0881</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Family Plot, Bjt,0907</SECOND>
<HEAD>Retirees Charged with Son's Murder in Deadly Double-Cross</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By WILL LESTER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>POMPANO BEACH, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Police say Christopher Morris plotted
with his parents to kill his ex-wife to collect $35,000 in
insurance. When they found out the policy had lapsed, authorities
allege, the parents killed him instead _ to collect a $70,000
policy.
   Theron and Leila Mary Morris, transplanted snowbirds from
Detroit with a poodle named Pepe, kept a well-tended yard in their
mobile home community. They were regular churchgoers, friendly,
quick to lend a hand with yardwork.
   And they're charged with murder, accused of killing their
42-year-old son in a deadly double-cross.
   Police say the Morrises schemed with their ex-convict son to
kill his former wife, Sharon, and her 10-year-old daughter for the
insurance. But they turned on their son after they learned that
coverage had lapsed, authorities say.
   The Morrises also were angry their son sold them bogus cocaine
for $1,000 that they had intended to resell, investigators say.
   The couple and Martin Rector, their son's roommate and onetime
prison buddy who is accused of being the triggerman, then conned a
drifter with drinking and blackout problems into confessing to the
crime, police say. The drifter, 40-year-old John Woods, was
released from jail after the three others confessed Wednesday.
   ``I've been doing homicide for 12 years,'' said sheriff's Lt.
Tom Carney. ``It's the strangest, most cold-blooded murder I've
ever seen. It seems they were upstanding citizens, never had a
brush with the law. They look just like any other grandparents you
would find any place in the country.''
   The Morrises' lawyer, Douglas Lambeth, says a different story
will emerge in court: that the Morrises were afraid of Rector and
went along out of fear.
   ``They talked to police,'' Lambeth acknowleged. ``That's
unfortunate for them. But it's not admissible in court. I tell my
clients that the fish would still be swimming in the ocean if they
kept their mouths shut.''
   The alleged murder scheme stunned residents of the Morrises'
mobile home community, north of Fort Lauderdale.
   ``They were good neighbors,'' said John Brennan, a retired
school administrator from Binghamton, N.Y. ``He was a good church
member. When we returned in winter with all that yardwork, he was
the first one to come over and help you clean up.''
   Theron Morris, 76, a retired Chrysler Corp. engineer, and his
wife, 62, who worked for United Air Lines for 23 years, moved to
Florida four years ago.
   Their son was released from prison late last year after serving
time on drug and assault charges. Neighbors said the Morrises were
trying to help him overcome a cocaine habit. They housed him, fed
him, bought him a car and found him a place to live. But there was
tension.
   ``There was arguing, yelling. ... It was kind of like a family
feud,'' said Michael Kern, 23, who lives across the street. Dorothy
Brennan, another neighbor, recalled Theron Morris ordering his son
out of the house and telling him not to return.
   Police say Chris Morris and Rector hatched a scheme to kill
Sharon Morris and her daughter. The two later recruited the elder
Morrises, police say.
   But when Rector went to Sharon Morris' house to kill her, posing
as a flower delivery man, she wouldn't come to the door because
Rector was not in uniform, said Carney.
   Then, police say, the plotters discovered that a $35,000
insurance policy on Sharon had lapsed. So the target of the murder
plot shifted to Chris, who was insured for $70,000.
   On the evening of Jan. 8, the younger Morris went with Rector to
his parents' home. Once there, police say, Rector pulled out a
.38-caliber revolver with a silencer and ordered Morris to the
floor. Morris' father then bound him with duct tape and helped load
him into the back seat of the car, but Chris Morris broke free and
was shot three times by Rector.
   They chased Chris and told him they would take him to the
hospital, but instead they took him to the nearby town of Coconut
Creek, shot him three more times and left him in the car, police
said. Detectives said Mrs. Morris followed in another car, picked
up her husband and Rector and took them home.
   Chris' body was found the next day. The Morrises told neighbors
he was killed by drug dealers.
   Leila Morris ``came over and put her arms around me and cried
and cried,'' recalled Mrs. Brennan. Sharon Morris attended her
ex-husband's funeral, unaware she had once been a target.
   The Morrises housed and fed Rector after Chris' death, gave him
an alibi for the night and said their son had gone out for beer and
cigarettes. But police immediately suspected Rector and said that
under questioning, Rector and the Morrises implicated each other,
then ultimately confessed.
   The insurance money has not been paid.
   Carney said what struck him most was the way the Morrises
described the events. ``They indicated that they had a rough life
with him,'' the lieutenant said. ``They figured they could get rid
of the problem child and pick up $70,000.
   ``But neither of them showed any remorse, any remorse about all
of the details. It was almost like they were talking about
strangers.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0015 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-PX-02-04-90 1412EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-PaperBattle Bjt   02-04 0610</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Paper Battle, Bjt,0628</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mill Town's Future is in Corporate America's Hands</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Money in 6th graf is cq</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto AU1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DIRK BEVERIDGE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MILLINOCKET, Maine (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   For the 7,000 residents of this
turn-of-the-century paper mill town, the outcome of a corporate
battle they don't pretend to understand is in the hands of business
executives they don't know.
   Georgia-Pacific Corp. has made a $3.8 billion bid for Great
Northern Nakoosa Corp., whose mill is the biggest employer in this
remote, northern town. Since the takeover battle began in October,
the paper giants have made promises and engaged in mudslinging to
try to win the favor of Mainers.
   But the citizens of Millinocket don't know who to root for.
   ``Do I believe either one of them? No,'' said Fredericka
Boynton, whose grandfather, father, husband and son worked in the
mill. ``I think they're big corporations and playing that merger
game, and I don't think we're going to win.''
   ``People in the area have been pulled by their heartstrings,''
said Money McGibbon, whose husband worked at the mill for 33 years.
``They're just being tugged from one end to the other, and it's not
fair.''
   Atlanta-based Georgia-Pacific has accused Great Northern of
financially starving Millinocket to the point where the aging mill
may not have a future.
   If it wins the fight, Georgia-Pacific says, it will spend more
than $1 million to determine whether it is feasible to make toilet
paper, paper towels and paper napkins in Millinocket instead of
paper used in books, telephone directories and the like.
   The mill, built in 1900, employs about 900 people, and
Georgia-Pacific says a tissue-making operation could employ 215.
The company said it does not have enough information on the Great
Northern mills and woodlands to make commitments about the
remaining jobs.
   Great Northern, based in Norwalk, Conn., but incorporated in
Maine, has claimed Georgia-Pacific has a secret plan to sell the
Millinocket operations as well as a newsprint mill in nearby East
Millinocket and 2.1 million acres of Maine woodlands.
Georgia-Pacific denies the accusation.
   Great Northern has promised $2.5 billion in improvements for
Maine. Georgia-Pacific calls that a ``pipe dream.''
   At a meeting last month, Georgia-Pacific executives tried to
show their company would be a good corporate citizen. But
townspeople wondered how life would change in this company town
where Great Northern once meant a secure job.
   Residents acknowledged that Great Northern has put more effort
and money into building up its southern mills in recent years.
Employment has been cut in Millinocket.
   ``Before the problems started with Great Northern, you could go
to school here and have a job for life at good wages,'' said
retiree Francis Larkin, who spent his life working for the mill.
   ``The times when they helped us put in the foundations of our
homes are gone,'' said Robert Boynton, Mrs. Boynton's husband, a
retired Great Northern mechanical supervisor.
   Boynton said Great Northern still lends tools to those in need.
   ``If you want a paint brush, you can borrow a paint brush. If I
need a couple of jacks, I'd go in and see the plant engineer,'' he
said. ``I've never known them to refuse anybody. They'll let you
borrow anything.''
   Retirees worry about their benefits if the mill changes
ownership, and a Georgia-Pacific executive acknowledged at the
meeting that he had no answers. Union leaders and rank-and-file
workers worry that jobs could be lost if the merger goes through.
   ``This is all we have got is the Great Northern Paper Co., and
that's all we have known for years,'' Mrs. McGibbon said. ``We're a
little bit leery of someone we don't know.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0016 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-PX-02-04-90 1415EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Poland     02-04 0528</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Poland,0543</SECOND>
<HEAD>Walesa: Probably Will Not Seek Re-election</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Soviet-Party, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>GDANSK, Poland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Solidarity leader Lech Walesa said Sunday
he probably will step down in April as leader of the union he
founded as a shipyard electrician and ultimately led into the halls
of government.
   Walesa, 46, who has served as leader of the East bloc's first
independent trade union since its founding in 1980, made the
statement during a speech before 1,000 supporters after a Mass in
his home city of Gdansk.
   At one point during the rally at St. Brygida's Church, Walesa
was interrupted by heckling from a group of about 50 young radicals.
   Walesa has often spoken about his desire to retire from the
burdens of the union. Some people around him suspect he is
preparing to make a bid for Poland's presidency, replacing Gen.
Wojciech Jaruzelski, if Poland's constitution is altered this year
requiring new presidential elections.
   ``I am publicly saying that I will not run for leadership at the
regional congress (scheduled this week in Gdansk) and, most
probably, at the national congress either,'' Walesa said.
   He had told a news conference Thursday that he was ``tired'' of
his activity and would like to rest for at least two years. But he
stressed then that if radicals threatened to take over Solidarity,
he would stay in the job.
   Solidarity's national congress is to meet in April in Gdansk.
The gathering will be only the second in Solidarity's history. The
union managed to hold one congress in September and October 1981
before it was suppressed in the martial-law crackdown.
   Walesa led the union into a series of talks with the Communist
government that led to the union re-legalization last year, its
participation in elections and then ultimately control of the
government.
   Since it was legalized, its membership has reached about 2
million, or only one-fifth of its 1981 strength.
   Regional congresses have been held in various cities over the
past two months to select delegates to the national congress.
   After Walesa made his comments about not running for union
leadership, some of the young radicals applauded and began
chanting, ``Solidarity Without Walesa.''
   The radicals represented the Confederation for an Independent
Poland, the Federation of Fighting Youth and a self-styled group of
``anarchists.''
   The protesters, using a bullhorn, accused Walesa of limiting
democracy. One of the youths shouted: ``If you continue like this
you will end up like Ceausescu,'' a reference to Nicolae Ceausescu
of Romania, who was overthrown in a violent revolt last year and
executed.
   Asked by spectators about his opinion on the daylong takeover of
Gdansk province Communist Party headquarters last weekend by a
similar group of radicals, Walesa said:
   ``This is not the right way. Every government will use force in
the face of anarchy and danger and must do so. If there is a threat
to the state or the city, then I will get up myself with my belt
and beat you.
   ``You cannot play with Poland. You have to build it,'' he said.
``If we continue with such methods we will get no where because
some general may explode and take advantage of the situation.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0017 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-PX-02-04-90 1418EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Obit-Ferraro'sMother     02-04 0210</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Ferraro's Mother,0217</SECOND>
<HEAD>Geraldine Ferraro's Mother Dies At 84</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Antonetta Ferraro, mother of former vice
presidential candidate Geraldine Ferraro, has died. She was 84.
   Mrs. Ferraro died Friday at her daughter's Forest Hills home of
emphysema and cancer.
   ``I always said I had two role models in life,'' Ms. Ferraro
told New York Newsday. ``One was Eleanor Roosevelt and one was
Antonetta Ferraro. She worked all her life. She worked in
sweatshops when they were really sweatshops. She learned a trade at
13 that put me through law school.''
   Mrs. Ferraro, whose husband, Dominick, died in 1943, had left
the hospital two months ago to be with her daughter and her family.
   The family has set up the Antonetta Ferraro Scholarship Fund at
Marymount Manhattan College in Manhattan, where Ms. Ferraro
graduated.
   ``It's a scholarship fund for girls who have been raised
(solely) by their mothers,'' said Ms. Ferraro, the Democrat nominee
for vice-president in 1984. ``My mother felt she never had an
education, but I always told her she did pretty well by me.''
   In addition to her daughter, Mrs. Ferraro is survived by a son,
Carl, and six grandchildren.
   The funeral was set for Tuesday in the New York City borough of
Queens.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0018 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-PX-02-04-90 1423EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SatanicVerses     02-04 0594</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Satanic Verses,0613</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rushdie Appeals to Moderate Moslems, Says No Offense Intended</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LESLIE SHEPHERD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In a rare public comment from his enforced
seclusion, author Salman Rushdie appealed to Moslems on Sunday to
reconsider their opposition to ``The Satanic Verses,'' saying he
feels their pain but cannot retract his book.
   In a 7,000-word essay, which he said was the hardest piece of
writing he had ever done, Rushdie said he never intended to
blaspheme Islam and regrets the racial tensions that followed the
novel's publication.
   But Rushdie also wrote in The Independent on Sunday that Moslems
who burned his books and staged violent demonstrations were partly
responsible. Rushdie criticized the British government for not
prosecuting a Moslem leader who reportedly advocated his death.
   Rushdie, a naturalized Briton who was born into a Moslem family
in India, has been in hiding under British police guard since Feb.
14, 1989, when Iranian Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini called for
Rushdie's death.
   The decree was not lifted when Khomeini died in June.
   Reaching out to ``the great mass of ordinary, decent,
fair-minded Moslems,'' Rushdie said he recognized that many of them
were shocked and pained by his book, just as he was hurt by their
rejection of it.
   He asked them ``to renounce blood; not to let Moslem leaders
make Moslems seem less tolerant than they are.''
   ``Perhaps a way forward might be found through the mutual
recognition of that mutual pain,'' he suggested.
   His olive branch was rejected by Liaqat Hussain, general
secretary of the Council of Mosques in Bradford, northern England,
which has led the campaign to ban ``The Satanic Verses.''
   ``Mr. Rushdie has suffered no pain. It is Moslems who have lost
their lives and suffered injuries,'' Hussain said. Six people were
killed in India and Pakistan during demonstrations against the book.
   ``I would not go into hiding for my beliefs ... he should be
brave enough to face the world for his principles,'' Hussain added.
   Sunday's essay was Rushdie's fullest defense of his book and
account of his predicament since he went into hiding, although he
has given a handful of interviews and referred to his plight in
book reviews.
   Saying he regretted that the book caused offense, Rushdie added:
   ``Would I have written it differently if I had known what would
happen? Truthfully, I don't know. Would I change any of the text
now? I would not. It's too late.''
   Rushdie said the British government should have prosecuted Kalim
Siddiqui who reportedly urged Moslems meeting in Manchester,
northern England, to raise their hands if they agreed with
Khomeini's death sentence.
   ``I find it upsetting that it's seen to be all right for people
to go around the country calling for my death,'' Rushdie wrote.
   Moslem leaders have repeatedly attacked Prime Minister Margaret
Thatcher's government for refusing to ban the book or prosecute
Rushdie.
   The Independent on Sunday's literary editor, Blake Morrison,
reported that Rushdie looked ``healthy and relaxed'' when they met
at an undisclosed location in England on Wednesday for a separate
interview.
   Rushdie said that in hiding he missed most the ordinary things _
``not being able to walk down a street, not being able to browse in
a bookshop, not being able to go to a movie.''
   He said at times he could not work, but now his writing is going
well, including a children's book, essays and the synopsis for a
novel.
   He said he watches a lot of television, and has become ``an
addict of American football'' broadcast in Britain late at night.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0019 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-PX-02-04-90 1424EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-AmtrakCuts     02-04 0542</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Amtrak Cuts,510</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush Amtrak Cut Proposal Rekindles Old Battle</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN DIAMOND</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   For the sixth consecutive year the Republican
administration in Washington has proposed cutting off all subsidy
for Amtrak passenger rail service.
   And Congress, for the sixth straight year, is expected to refuse
to go along.
   President Bush last week carried on a longstanding tradition
established by his predecessor by proposing to cut the federal
Amtrak subsidy. The move would leave Amtrak about 28 percent shy of
what it says it needs to operate for fiscal 1991.
   Legislators in the Northeast accuse Bush of ignoring the
progress Amtrak has made in reducing its dependence on federal
money and of pursuing a policy that will lead to more crowded
highways and airports.
   ``It's a terrible decision,'' said Rep. Bruce Morrison, D-Conn.
``With the amount of money that is to be saved compared to the
extraordinary public investment that's already gone into improving
the rail infrastructure ... it's really penny wise and pound
foolish.''
   Of Amtrak's $1.9 billion budget this year, $600 million was
supplied by the federal government. In 1981, the federal government
supplied about half of Amtrak's budget.
   ``We're talking about one B-2 worth of expenditures,'' Morrison
said.
   New England is one of the heavy beneficiaries of the
quasi-public rail line established in 1970 by Congress to replace
failing private lines.
   In Connecticut, Amtrak carries 1.2 million passengers per year,
and employs 727 state residents on a payroll of $25 million,
according to Amtrak statistics. Some 422,000 Rhode Island
passengers use the system each year and Amtrak employs 295
residents on $10 million in payroll.
   And in Massachusetts, where Amtrak also is responsible for
commuter service, 1.4 million passengers use the Amtrak system
along with 14 million commuters per year. Amtrak employs 1,710
Massachusetts residents and spends 55 million in payroll.
   Federal Railroad Administration spokeswoman Claire Austin said
the administration opposes a subsidy. But she said Bush strongly
supports rail transportation and she indicated there was no reason
to believe the scenario played out in previous years would change.
   ``We've always requested no subsidy and Congress always makes an
appropriation,'' Austin said.
   Unlike President Reagan, Austin said, Bush supports federal
spending for research into high-speed rail technology, equipment
and safety standards.
   ``That's a different twist that you have not seen in the Reagan
administration,'' according to Austin.
   Rep. Christopher Shays, R-Conn., predicted Congress would again
disagree with the president on the Amtrak subsidy issue. But Shays
said Congress has the same goal: ``We will wean Amtrak from federal
subsidies and we'll appropriate a little less.''
   According to Amtrak, a gradual reduction in federal subsidies
could be accomplished without cutting into rail service.
   ``We've said publicly, and it's mentioned in the president's
budget, that Amtrak has a goal of being self-sufficient for
operational costs by the year 2000,'' said Amtrak spokesman
Clifford Black. The rail line will still need at least $150 million
per year for capital improvements, Black said.
   For now, Morrison said, Amtrak depends on federal subsidies for
survival and so does the region's transportation system.
   ``In the Northeast Corridor, the last thing we need to do is
dump more cars and more air traffic into an already congested
system,'' Morrison said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0020 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-PX-02-04-90 1425EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Nepal     02-04 0277</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Nepal,0285</SECOND>
<HEAD>70 Members of Banned Party Reported Arrested in Nepal</HEAD>
<DATELINE>KATMANDU, Nepal (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Authorities arrested 70 members of the
outlawed Nepali Congress Party as it prepared to launch a campaign
demanding that political organizations be legalized in Nepal, a
party spokesman said Sunday.
   Reports of harassment of other activists have been pouring in
from local districts, and in some places authorities have succeeded
in stopping the party's activities, spokesman Daman Dhunganahe said.
   Speaking at a news conference at party headquarters, he said the
arrests had been made in 10 of the country's 75 districts, but so
far no action had been taken against party activists in Katmandu,
the capital.
   The leftist party, banned 29 years ago, decided recently to
launch a nationwide campaign next week to demand restoration of a
multiparty system.
   The Congress Party was voted into power in 1959, but was
overthrown 18 months later in a royal takeover.
   The country's Western-style Parliament was dissolved, and Nepal
adopted its present ``panchayat'' policy, which bans all political
parties. Candidates elected to a national assembly must run as
independents.
   The assembly elects a prime minister from among its members and
a Council of Ministers, which advises the king, a powerful figure
in Nepal who has the authority to declare a state of emergency or
suspend the constitution.
   Denouncing the Congress Party's planned campaign, Prime Minister
Marich Man Shrestha declared last month that the panchayat system
``is committed to ensure that all citizens enjoy equal civil rights
in an unhindered fashion.''
   He said the party was trying to force its version of democracy
on Nepal ``when there already exists a working democracy in the
country.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0021 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-PX-02-04-90 1427EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-PensionProfits Bjt   02-04 0949</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Pension Profits, Bjt,900</SECOND>
<HEAD>Retirees Cut Out of Huge Pension Profits</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BRYNA BRENNAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The nation's burgeoning pension system owns a
huge chunk of corporate America, but the benefits go to almost
everyone but the retirees the funds are set up to serve.
   Typically described as a nest egg for millions of working
Americans, pension funds also are being used to make a fast buck
for stock brokers, pay off corporate debt and even pressure some
corporations into having social consciences.
   The pension system, buoyed by the bull market of the 1980s, has
grown into an economic force, rising from just $7 billion in assets
in 1950 to $2 trillion today. About half that money is invested in
stocks, with pension funds holding 25 percent of total equity in
the U.S. economy.
   The multibillion-dollar investments make pension funds _ and
those who manage them _ major players on Wall Street.
   ``It's not the retirees who are getting this money. It's the
investment managers or traders, or owners,'' says Karen Ferguson,
director of the Pension Rights Center, a public interest group.
   Documents and about two dozen interviews indicate that the basic
goal of the pension laws, enacted by Congress to protect and
benefit the retirees, has been eroded by the power pensions can
broker on the stock market.
   Robert Monks, the head of the Washington-based pension
consulting firm Institutional Shareholder Services, joined other
experts in saying investment managers are pushed by all sides to
make a quick profit. In fact, there appears to be a growing move by
pension funds to put equity managers on performance-based fees.
This encourages short-term trades that garner commissions for
brokers and, the companies hope, new assets for the funds.
   The 1974 Employee Retirement Income Security Act, known as
ERISA, says all investments must be made to benefit the pensioners.
But the windfall made with pension fund assets rarely reaches the
retiree.
   Companies are allowed to skim off profits through a maneuver
known as ``reversions,'' and they are under no obligation to boost
benefits when the funds prosper.
   ``All the increased volatility on the stock market system with
pension plans hasn't contributed to value for the beneficiaries,''
Monks said. ``The people who are making money are the brokers,
consultants, investment managers. You're not making money for the
people you're supposed to be.''
   Texaco, for example, nabbed $360.9 million in pension surpluses
shortly after merging with Getty Oil Co. in 1984. Occidental
Petroleum skimmed off $238 million from the pensions of its
acquisition, Cities Service.
   Most pension plans provide a monthly income after retirement
based on a portion of wages earned during the later years of
service. In most cases, the basic benefits are neither boosted when
investments do well, nor decreased when they do not.
   Some big businesses, however, do provide ``ad hoc''
cost-of-living increases at the discretion of management.
Owens-Illinois Inc. of Toledo, Ohio, is one such company.
   Ronald C. Boller, the company's vice president and director of
benefit finance, says it provides periodic benefit increases to its
pensioners. But the increases are not directly related to the stock
market, where 70 percent of Owen-Illinois' pension fund assets are
invested.
   And Boller acknowledges that ``we've had a hell of a run in the
markets, where most of the money is invested.''
   ``Formally, technically, the obligation of the company _ the
pension promise _ exists whether the market goes up, down or
sideways,'' he says.
   Ms. Ferguson is among those who say the full surpluses should be
passed on to the retirees, adding: ``Even at low inflation rates
the value of a retiree's benefit will be cut in half in a lifetime
without a cost-of-living adjustment.''
   Michael S. Gordon, a Washington pension lawyer and contributor
to the ERISA law, argues that reversions amount to ``pension
barbarism.''
   But proponents of reversions say the companies deserve the money
as a reward for managing the investments well.
   ``What happens when the market goes bad? The employer is stuck
with the liability,'' said New York pension attorney Jeffrey
Mamorsky.
   That is only partially true. If the employer is unable to pick
up the pension tab it falls to the federal government's Pension
Benefit Guaranty Corporation. That agency has a $1.5 billion
deficit and, should it falter, taxpayers ultimately could shoulder
the responsibility.
   Some pension analysts also are concerned about a growing trend
to use the financial clout of the funds on Wall Street to further
social and political goals. In their view, such investment
strategies _ however laudable the intent _ conflict with ERISA's
mandate that the money be invested solely for the benefit of the
pensioners.
   This trend started about five years ago when many public funds,
those covering public employees, called on their investment
managers to get rid of stock in companies doing business in South
Africa. Pressure also has been placed on some companies to respond
to environmental concerns.
   The public pension funds in New York last year pushed Exxon
Corp. to put an environmentalist on its board after the Valdez oil
spill in Alaska. Texaco last year also agreed to nominate a
director from a list submitted by the California Public Employee
Retirement System.
   Gordon, with a strict interpretation of the ERISA law, says
``wooly-eyed social investment schemes'' should be avoided by
private pension plans, where the goal is to act on behalf of the
retirees.
   ``With public funds, if they can't come through with the
benefits then the (state) legislatures will do some kind of tax,''
he said. ``With private plans, the employer is on the hook.
   ``If his assets aren't around to back it up then there's a crush
on PBGC, which already is in trouble.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0022 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-04-90 1428EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-LungImplant 1stLd-Writethru a0672 02-04 0468</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lung Implant, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0672,0473</SECOND>
<HEAD>Teen-age Girl Who Received Historic Lung Assist Device Still
`Critical'</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 2nd graf to CORRECT that operation took place in
afternoon sted night, correct `supply' to `supplying;' ADDS 3 grafs
with further detail on guidelines, seven-day limit.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>SALT LAKE CITY (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A teen-age girl who was the first human
recipient of a pioneering lung assist device remained in critical
condition Sunday at LDS Hospital.
   The girl received the IntraVascular Oxygenator _ an inch-wide,
20-inch-long bundle of plastic fibers that mimic the lung's task of
supplying oxygen to the body _ during a two-hour operation Friday
afternoon.
   The hospital would report only the girl's condition Sunday. A
nursing supervisor, who spoke on condition of anonymity, said the
patient's family insists that no further information about the girl
be released. The Salt Lake Tribune reported that the girl is 16.
   Guidelines approved by the U.S. Food and Drug Administration in
September limit the implants to seven days in people with acute
respiratory failure who have little other chance of survival.
   The IVOX is designed to give damaged lungs a chance to rest and
recover before it is removed. Its developer, Dr. J.D. Mortensen of
Salt Lake City, says while IVOX cannot really be called an
artificial lung, it represents an important step toward eventual
development of one.
   Implantation of the lung assist device involves insertion of the
IVOX via the neck or groin into the inferior vena cava, the large
vein that brings blood to the heart.
   Two tubes the diameter of a soda straw are attached to the IVOX
bundle _ consisting of 900-1,200 hollow, porous fibers each about
the diameter of a human hair _ and leave the body; one delivers
oxygen to theAkKear-old Hoeflehner after edging Atle
Skaardal of Norway and Franz Heinzer of Switzerland by 0.20 seconds.
   The Austrian, with a faultless run, completed the 3,100-meter
distance in the winning time of 1 minute, 44.57 seconds.
   Hoeflehner, who had won the second downhill race of his career
in Cortina in 1984, said Sunday he avoided mistakes that relegated
him to third place in a downhill on the same track Saturday.
   ``I concentrated on the bottom part, which was the most
difficult, and I avoided the errors which had cost me victory
yesterday,'' Hoeflehner said.
   Two consecutive downhills were raced here to make up for
canceled events in Chamonix and Saalbach.
   Sunday's victory _ the 10th of his career and following two wins
in Val D'Isere last week _ strengthened Hoeflehner's lead in the
World Cup downhill standings and boosted his chances to win this
year's title.
   The Austrian has 131 points and, with only two races left in
this year's competition, holds a commanding lead over Swiss
all-rounder Pirmin Zurbriggen, second with 92 points.
   Zurbriggen, who turned 27 Sunday, was sixth.
   But he widened his World Cup overall lead to 270 points, 58
ahead of Norwegian Ole Kristian Furuseth, who did not start in the
weekend races here.
   ``Helmut looked unbeatable today, but I made a decisive mistake
in the bottom part,'' said Zurbriggen, shooting for a
record-equaling fourth overall title before retiring in March.
   He had placed fifth in Saturday's race, in which hometown
favorite Christian Ghedina captured his first ever World Cup
victory. Ghedina was 15th Sunday.
   Skaardal was satisified with his performance.
   ``I fell short of a second victory, but a second place is
something good in a World Cup race,'' said Skaardal, who won his
first ever downhill in Kitzbuehel this year.
   Heinzer, who was tied with Skaardal in second place, said he
missed a big opportunity to win his first race since Vail in 1988.
   ``I made a few, minor mistakes which still were decisive,''
Heinzer commented.
   His teammate Daniel Mahrer, second in Saturday's race behind
Ghedina, edged a late Italian starter, Danilo Sbardellotto, for
fourth place.
   American A.J. Witt, who had skied to a fourth-place finish
Saturday, was 36th in Sunday's race, 2.55 seconds slower than the
winner.
   Felix Belczyk of Canada was the best North American finisher, in
14th place, 0.86 seconds off the winning time.
   The next men's race will be a super-giant slalom Tuesday at
Courmayeur, Italy.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0023 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-04-90 1433EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-BreakawayCongregation     02-04 0391</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Breakaway Congregation,390</SECOND>
<HEAD>Breakaway Catholics To Allow Female Priests, Birth Control,
Abortion</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Rev. George Stallings said Sunday that his
congregation, in ``taking control of its own destiny'' by breaking
ties with the Roman Catholic Church, would encourage the ordination
of women and allow birth control and abortion.
   Stallings, in defiance of church officials, last summer formed
the Imani Temple, an independent African-American Catholic
congregation. He announced his decision to break all ties with the
Vatican last week.
   Stallings said the departure from Vatican authority would allow
his congregation to set in place ``its own displine and laws, which
will govern our activites.''
   Stallings, after addressing his congregation of several hundred
followers on Sunday, revealed some of those laws.
   ``We will allow for the ordination of women and we will allow
for divorced and remarried Catholics to be in full communion
without having to go through the tedious and potentially damaging
annulment process,'' he said in an interview. ``We will also allow
the use of birth control as well as allow women to decide whether
or not to abort a life.''
   In addition, he said the Imani Temple would permit ``optional
celibacy, which means our priests will be able to decide whether or
not they want to marry.''
   Stallings, citing other occasions in which sects have broken
away from the church, expressed confidence that the Lord would not
abandon his church even if the Vatican does _ in the form of
excommunication.
   ``Just as God has been with other Catholics in their declaration
of independence from the Catholic Church, he will be with us,'' he
told his congregation.
   Later, he said, ``Excommunication in its truest sense means to
be cut off from communion with God. No church, no Pope, no power
can separate anyone from God because God will not allow that to
happen.''
   He defended his church's stance on birth control and abortion,
noting, ``The Bible has nothing to say about abortion or birth
control. The positions we are taking are not counter-Biblical; they
are allowed within the expression of faith.''
   On the subject of ordaining women, he said, ``There is nothing
in the Bible that says women can't be ordained ministers. We know
from the scriptures that women are deaconesses. If anything, the
scriptures advance the cause of women to the higher levels of
ordination.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0024 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-04-90 1433EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-RavenStudies     02-04 0539</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Raven Studies,0554</SECOND>
<HEAD>Quoth The Professor: Ravens Not So Solitary As Once Believed</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PORTLAND, Maine (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The usually shy, solitary raven turns out
to be a gregarious bird in winter, flocking to noisy feasts on
carcasses that serve as ``traveling discos'' because they let male
ravens strut their stuff, a University of Vermont zoologist says.
   Bernd Heinrich, who has donned a bear costume to try to get
closer to the big, black, bashful birds, gathered evidence for his
book, ``Ravens in Winter,'' at his woodland cabin near Mount Blue
State Park in western Maine.
   After more than five years' study and aided by a National
Science Foundation grant, Heinrich wrote the first comprehensive
study of interactions among the birds whose mysterious behavior has
inspired centuries of folklore.
   Heinrich's work began when he observed about 15 ravens feasting
noisily on a moose carcass near his cabin overlooking Maine's
western mountains.
   Ravens are uncommon, solitary creatures that usually fly alone
or in pairs; it seemed impossible to him that those birds, and
those he saw feeding at other carcasses in subsequent days, each
could have found the food individually.
   He was forced to conclude that the ravens apparently were
sharing their valuable winter food sources by recruiting complete
strangers.
   ``It was the most left-wing behavior I had ever heard of in a
natural system,'' the zoology professor wrote.
   Over the years, Heinrich hauled countless deer and moose
carcasses donated by game wardens uphill to his retreat, to be used
as bait for his experiments.
   His field work and studies of marked, captive birds, led him to
theorize that vagrant birds _ mostly juveniles passing through an
area _ ``yell'' to alert one another about newly discovered food
that often is defended by a resident pair of adults.
   Because the vagrants continue to call others in to feed, even
after there are enough young birds present to overwhelm the adults,
Heinrich says that the carcasses may also act as ``traveling
discos'' where the birds can show off their bravery and ability to
find food to potential mates.
   Heinrich believes that dominance is at the core of ravens'
social behavior. In general, he says, the dominant birds tend to be
males, which are larger than females.
   Ravens are shy, which is one reason there has been so little
substantial research on them. Just the sight of an eyeball or the
snap of a twig can send them soaring, Heinrich said.
   That shyness once led Heinrich to don a bear suit to see if he
could get closer to his subjects. He knew that the birds sometimes
allow wolves or coyotes to feed next to them, keeping a wary eye on
their dinner guests but not flying away.
   ``I would have worn a big wolf suit or a big coyote suit if I'd
had one,'' he explains in his cabin, where the bear suit still lies
in a corner. ``But I figured I could most easily mimic a bear. And
there are bears around here, so it was worth a shot, you know.''
   Did it work?
   Heinrich grinned and chuckled.
   ``No. Uh-uh,'' he said. ``They weren't fooled for one second.
They just all took off in alarm like I was a human.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0025 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-04-90 1434EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF-TrainRobbers     02-04 0145</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF-Train Robbers,0150</SECOND>
<HEAD>Train Robbers Captured</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Authorities arrested 59 members of a gang that
robbed trains in southern and central China for nearly two years,
an official news report said Sunday.
   The nationally televised evening news showed four handcuffed
gang members being led off a train in Zhengzhou, capital of Henan
province in eastern China.
   The report said authorities confiscated Chinese cash worth the
equivalent of tens of thousands of dollars from the gang after an
eight-month investigation spanning 15 provinces.
   In one instance, the report said, gang members stole $8,500 from
a passenger on a train to Shanghai. In another case, the gang beat
a policeman patrolling a train and stole his gun.
   The report did not say how many people belonged to the gang.
   People publicly accused of crimes in China often receive lengthy
prison sentences or are executed.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0026 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-04-90 1440EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--CatKilling     02-04 0140</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Cat Killing,0143</SECOND>
<HEAD>Woman Reported Killed Over Messy Cats</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A man accused of strangling his 70-year-old
neighbor Sunday reportedly killed the woman after flying into a
rage because she refused to clean up after some stray cats she fed.
   Masaru Himuro, 60, turned himself in to police after using a
small bath towel to strangle Shinobu Izu, early Sunday morning,
said a police official in Fukuoka, a city on the southwestern
island of Kyushu. He gave no other details.
   However, Kyodo News Service reported that Himuro began drinking
after losing money while gambling Saturday evening.
   It said he went to Izu's apartment to complain she had not
cleaned up the excrement of five or six stray cats she often fed.
   The report said Izu refused to apologize, and Himuro killed her
in a rage, it said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0027 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-04-90 1453EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People     02-04 0918</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People,0953</SECOND>
<HEAD>People in the News</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY44</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Actor Robert Duvall has prepared himself for
roles by hanging out with bums on the Bowery, riding horses with
the Texas Rangers and tramping through a Louisiana swamp with an
alligator hunter.
   He's not sure if it was all worth it.
   ``You could do all the research in the world _ sometimes it pays
off, sometimes it doesn't,'' Duvall says in the March issue of
Smart magazine. ``Sometimes you don't have time. You got to be a
human being up there. That's the most important thing.''
   Duvall, who won an Oscar for ``Tender Mercies'' and starred in
``The Godfather'' and ``The Great Santini,'' says he's a stickler
for detail in his characters and in films in general.
   ``When actors start acting bigger than life, bigger than the
people they play, then they're in trouble,'' Duvall said. ``For
example, I can't even talk about `Gone With the Wind.' You don't
see people in the South like that. It's a joke.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two queens, Elizabeth II and Beatrix, are Europe's
wealthiest women, although the English monarch with an estimated
personal fortune of $8.9 billion far outranks her Dutch
counterpart, a magazine said Sunday.
   Britian's Queen Elizabeth is the fourth richest person and the
richest woman in the world, reported Harpers and Queen magazine.
She has a jewelery collection including 25 crowns and tiaras,
racing horses, a valuable art collection and thousands of acres of
land and mineral rights worldwide.
   Queen Beatrix of the Netherlands weighed in at an estimated $4.7
billion.
   Johanna Quandt, who owns 66 percent of the West German
automotive company BMW, is Europe's third richest woman, the
magazine said. It estimated Ms. Quandt's fortune at $3.5 billion.
   Another German, Grete Schickedanz, owner of Quelle, Europe's
largest mail order company, is Europe's fourth wealthiest woman at
$2 billion, the magazine said.
   Athina Roussel, the 5-year-old daughter of the late shipping
heiress Christina Onassis and French pharmaceutical heir Thierry
Roussel, is No. 7 on the list, although Harpers and Queen said she
will not take control of her $840 million fortune until her 18th
birthday, in 2003.
   Forbes' list of the world's richest people published in October
listed Japan's Yoshiaki Tsutsumi, who made his money in land,
railroads and resorts, as the world's richest individual worth
about $15 billion.
   The Sultan of Brunei and King Fahd of Saudi Arabia have been
reported by Fortune magazine to have more money at their personal
disposal because of the oil riches of their countries. Estimates of
the sultan's wealth have ranged up to $30 billion and Fahd's is
said to be in the $18 billion range.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>BEVERLY HILLS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Comedian Milton Berle is selling his
longtime home here because it contains too many memories of his
late wife.
   ``I didn't have to sell the house,'' Berle said. ``But there are
too many memories there, you know, after being married 36 years.''
   The 81-year-old comic is negotiating to lease a penthouse on
Wilshire Boulevard in Los Angeles for $12,000 a month. The house
sold for more than $3 million cash to the owners of a mortgage
company.
   The 60-year-old home went on the block in October following the
death of Berle's wife, Ruth, in April. They had lived in the house
for 19 years.
   Berle had asked $3.65 million, but apparently the property needs
work.
   ``It has a lot of character but needs updating, and that's what
the buyers plan to do,'' said Yaffa Lerner, who sold the house.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>AUGUSTA, Maine (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Pulitzer Prize winning author James
Michener has bought a summer home in Brunswick, and plans to move
there late this spring, a real estate broker says.
   ``He wanted to have access to a college library for research and
where it would be cool in the summer,'' said Brunswick broker
Deborah Morton.
   Michener, who has written such books as ``Hawaii,'' ``Alaska,''
``Caribbean'' and ``Space,'' began house hunting last fall and
found a condominium unit, but the deal was not closed until
Thursday, Ms. Morton said. She would not disclose the price.
   The 82-year-old author is known for his historical novels, which
combine history, geography and cultures of different regions. While
researching his books, Michener often moves to the area he is
writing about.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>GREENSBORO, N.C. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Journalist Tony Brown told a
predominantly black audience that American blacks are crippled by a
self-imposed ``psychological slavery'' that keeps them from
achieving success.
   Brown said blacks are held captive by a myth: ``If white America
doesn't provide an opportunity for them, they won't have one.''
   ``You are psychologically dependent on someone else,'' Brown
told about 500 people at the annual fund-raising dinner of the
state chapters of the National Association for the Advancement of
Colored People on Saturday night.
   Brown, host of the black affairs television series ``Tony
Brown's Journal,'' said the civil rights movement has brought
changes in laws that were needed to give blacks an equal footing.
   But it takes more than legislation to reverse a 200-year-old
mind-set of inferiority that plagues many in the black community,
Brown said. He urged blacks to take pride in their African identity
and not wait for others to help them reach their economic and
social goals.
   ``If we want to be equal, let's be equal,'' he said. ``We don't
need anybody to give us freedom.''
   Brown also writes a column that appears in 150 black newspapers,
publishes a quarterly magazine, and produces documentary films.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0028 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-04-90 1518EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Soviet-Party 1stLd-Writethru   02-04 1010</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Party, 1st Ld - Writethru,a0649,1036</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hundreds of Thousands Rally Against Party Monopoly on Power</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: INSERTS one graf after 9th, `Trucks blocked ...' to UPDATE
with duration of rally, marchers dispersing; picks up 10th pvs:
According to ...</NOTE>
<HEAD>Laserphoto MOSB1-3</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARK J. PORUBCANSKY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hundreds of thousands of cheering protesters
filled the broad streets of the capital Sunday to demand that the
Communists surrender their stranglehold on power, perhaps the
biggest protest in Moscow since the Bolshevik Revolution.
   The huge gathering came on the eve of a party Central Committee
meeting during which President Mikhail S. Gorbachev is expected to
propose that other parties be allowed to compete for power, a move
likely to spur an intense struggle between hard-liners and
reformers.
   The crowd waved huge white-red-and-blue flags of
pre-revolutionary Russia and held signs warning party officials to
``Remember Romania,'' where a bloody revolt last year toppled the
Stalinist regime of Nicolae Ceausescu.
   The masses stopped next to Red Square for gigantic rally that
was meant to influence the pivotal Communist Party plenary meeting
that opens Monday.
   ``This plenum is the party's last chance,'' declared Boris N.
Yeltsin, a populist Communist leader who promised to place the
crowd's demands before the 251-member Central Committee.
   Others, harkening to the revolution that overthrew the czar in
February 1917 before being swept away by Lenin eight months later,
said a new revolution was under way.
   ``Long live the beginning of the peaceful, non-violent
revolution of February 1990!'' historian Yuri Afanasiev told the
cheering crowd.
   Some demonstrators at the head of the rally chanted ``Politburo
resign!'' Others whistled in derision when they passed the Moscow
city council headquarters on Gorky Street.
   Trucks blocked Moscow's Garden Ring Road for the marchers who
linked arms next to Gorky Park and completely filled eight lanes of
traffic, stretching back more than half a mile. Cordons of
uniformed police blocked cars elsewhere, turning the center of
Moscow into a virtual pedestrian mall.
   In all, the march and rally lasted for about five hours before
participants began to disperse. Police observed the peaceful
proceedings in the historic heart of the capital, but there were no
reports of any disturbances.
   According to published reports, party leader Gorbachev will
propose to the Central Committee that the party give up the
guarantee of power that was written into the Soviet Constitution in
1977.
   The Radio Moscow news service Interfax also said Gorbachev was
planning structural reforms that would reduce the size of the
Central Committee and possibly eliminate the ruling Politburo. He
also was expected to give tacit approval to the concept of private
property.
   The proposals are in the form of a draft platform to be placed
before a congress, theoretically the Communist Party's highest
body, that now is scheduled for this fall.
   Many Moscow observers expected a concentrated effort from
conservatives in the Central Committee to stop the reforms they
believe have brought the Soviet Union to economic ruin and ethnic
strife.
   At least some in the crowd had doubts whether Gorbachev is
committed to radical reforms. ``Mikhail Sergeyevich, whom are you
with?'' one sign asked.
   Yeltsin and other reformers, speaking to the crowd gathered in
front of the Moscow Hotel from the back of a blue flat-bed truck,
demanded that the party and government talk with them about the
Soviet Union's future, as Communist leaders have been forced to do
as changes have swept the former Soviet satellites of Eastern
Europe.
   They also urged a day of similar rallies throughout the country
on Feb. 25. Yeltsin demanded that the party congress be held
earlier, in May or June.
   The rally united reformers from the People's Front organizations
of Moscow and Russia, the Association of Moscow Voters, the
Memorial group dedicated to remembering the victims of Stalin, and
other reformers.
   It marked another step in a rapid solidification of the
reformers' movement. They first came together two weeks ago to form
a group calling itself the Democratic Platform.
   ``We don't have any more time,'' said Nikolai I. Travkin, a
member of the Congress of People's Deputies. ``We don't have time
for disagreements among ourselves.''
   Reformers say they have been scared in recent weeks by the
Soviet military assault on Baku, the capital of the Azerbaijan
republic where a fierce nationalist movement has taken hold; and
threats of attacks on Jews by Russian nationalists.
   ``We are for freedom, but not the freedom of fascists! We're for
freedom, but not the freedom of murderers!'' popular poet Yevgeny
Yevtushenko declared.
   Democratic Platform formally demanded removal of the Communists'
constitutional guarantee on power and a virtual apology for decades
of repression and mismanagement.
   Some of its leaders such as Afanasiev say they are on the verge
of declaring the party incapable of reform, quitting it, and
forming a social democratic party.
   Small, local parties are forming in the Baltic republics, where
legislators already have acted to remove the Communist Party's
monopoly on power, but so far there is no nationwide opposition to
Communist authority.
   Gorbachev said in the Baltic republic of Lithuania last month
that it would be ``no tragedy'' if a multi-party system evolved.
But he continues to insist that it is not a simple solution to all
the country's problems.
   But reform-minded economist Gavriil Popov, also a deputy, told
the crowd that the Communist Party leadership was hindering reform.
   ``We need a free society, with a free economy ... a society of
free people,'' he said.
   The Soviet Union, ruled exclusively by the Communists since a
few months after the 1917 Russian Revolution, is the last remaining
Warsaw Pact nation to give the Communists a guaranteed monopoly on
power.
   The two-daty Central Committee meeting is likely to be the last
one before elections to governing councils in the 15 Soviet
republics and cities and towns, most of which are scheduled to take
place in the next month and a half.
   Top local party officials suffered embarrassing defeats in many
cities in national elections in March, and others could lose
heavily in the local elections.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0029 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-04-90 1522EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Albania     02-04 0425</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Albania,0440</SECOND>
<HEAD>Communist Party Decides on Cautious Liberalization</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Soviet-Party, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>VIENNA, Austria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Albania's hard-line Communist Party
Central Committee plans to introduce some reforms as part of a
cautious move away from total control of society, Albania's state
ATA news agency reported Sunday.
   The committee at a meeting Jan. 22-23 reaffirmed its claim to
power but agreed to give state enterprises more decision-making
authority, permit dual candidacies for some posts and tie wages
more closely to production, ATA said.
   Such tentative moves toward democracy cannot be compared to the
whirlwind of reforms that have swept Communist parties from decades
of rule in some East European countries and forced radical changes
on others in the past few months.
   But they are relatively major developments in the context of
Albania, a closed society and the most conservative European
Communist nation for decades.
   Albania broke with the Soviet Union in 1961 over Moscow's policy
of de-Stalinization and with China in 1978 because of Beijing's
perceived deviation from Marxist-Leninist tenets.
   The ATA report added substance to reports of some shortages this
winter, saying the Central Committee session agreed that ``nothing
can justify the shortage of vegetables, milk and meat in every
city.''
   The dispatch follows unconfirmed rumors in Yugoslavia and Greece
of unrest in the Albanian city of Shkoder Jan. 11 and Jan 14, with
thousands of people reportedly trying to tear down a statue of
Josef Stalin, the late Soviet dictator. Albanian officials denied
the reports.
   The Central Committee resolutions, as reported by ATA, included:
   _Opening up election to seats in Parliament to more than one
Communist-approved candidate.
   _Placing limits on the length of office for some party and
government posts.
   _Extending economic and financial planning ``from the center to
the districts and from the districts to the enterprises,
cooperatives and institutions.''
   _Placing more emphasis on profitablity of state enterprises.
   _Increasing the role of the ``collective garden, small herds and
plots ... in supplying the peasantry. ... Agricultural cooperatives
... can sell agricultural and livestock products at prices set by
themselves, different from the state.''
   The plenum condemned ``the counter-revolutionary process'' in
the Soviet bloc, saying it resulted from ``the instigation and
inteference of Western reaction and of the Soviet Union.''
   At the same time it acknowledged popular support for the
changes, which it blamed on disillusionment with ``revisionist
domination, its bureaucracy and violence.''
   Albanian leaders repeatedly have emphasized that the changes
sweeping Eastern Europe will not affect their country, stressing
that Albania has developed separately from the Warsaw Pact for the
last 40 years.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0030 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-04-90 1605EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-America'sCup     02-04 0686</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-America's Cup,0713</SECOND>
<HEAD>America's Cup Dispute In New York's Top Court</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT BELLAFIORE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ALBANY, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The America's Cup, the most valued prize in
yachting, sits in a most unusual trophy case these days: A vault at
the Morgan Guaranty Trust Co. in New York City.
   It's there because of a legal fight that centers on
sportsmanship, fairness, history and money.
   New York's highest court will decide in the coming weeks whether
the 139-year-old silver trophy goes to the San Diego Yacht Club or
to the Mercury Bay Yacht Club of New Zealand.
   Mercury Bay contends the San Diego club and its skipper, Dennis
Conner, cheated by using a catamaran in defeating the New
Zealanders' 1988 challenge for the cup.
   Mercury Bay contends that Conner, using the lighter and more
maneuverable catamaran, had an unfair advantage and violated the
spirit of the century-old rules that established the America's Cup
competition.
   Those rules, say the New Zealanders, require holders of the Cup
to accept any challenge from any foreign country in a vessel
similar to the one being used by the challenger.
   Mercury Bay sailed in a 132-foot fiberglass sloop and lost to
Conner in two consecutive races off San Diego, described by Mercury
Bay's lawyers as a ``gross mismatch.''
   A catamaran had never before been used in America's Cup
competition. In court papers, Mercury Bay's lawyers quote Malin
Burnham, head ofthe syndicate that financed Conner's ``Stars and
Stripes,'' as saying a catamaran ``would turn this race into a
farce.''
   The New Zealanders want Conner's victory invalidated, with the
trophy awarded to them.
   On the other side is the San Diego Yacht Club and the America's
Cup Organizing Committee, which plans to stage the next defense of
the trophy.
   They claim that Conner's catamaran was legal and that the New
Zealanders are going to court to get a prize they could not win in
the water.
   Mercury Bay also has the backing of the New York Yacht Club,
which had held the cup 132 years and 24 successful defenses, until
Conner lost it to Australia in 1983. Conner, sailing for San Diego,
regained the cup in 1987.
   The rules are contained in an 1887 document known as the ``Deed
of Gift,'' which set up the America's Cup challenge system.
   The deed established the New York Court of Appeals as the final
arbiter of America's Cup disputes. This is the first time a dispute
over the cup has reached the top court.
   Lower state courts were divided on the issue. A trial court
disqualified Conner and gave the cup to New Zealand, but an appeals
court reversed that decision and awarded the cup to San Diego.
   The case has also generated some ill will between the two sides.
Peter Debreceny, spokesman for Fay, said the New Zealanders are
trying to prevent the America's Cup from becoming commercialized.
   He claimed Conner and San Diego wanted to hold on to the cup so
they could hold a financially rewarding ``warmup'' for the
America's Cup off the coast of San Diego in 1991.
   Officials for the America's Cup Organizing Committee deny
Mercury Bay's accusation and say that they were willing to face all
challengers.
   At stake is more than a trophy. The winner gets to host the next
challenge, tentatively scheduled for 1991. That could mean an
economic boost for the host community _ America's Cup matches bring
spectators from around the world _ and considerable prestige for
the owner of the winning yacht.
   About two dozen countries, including such yachting newcomers as
Yugoslavia and Japan, have asked to be among the challengers in
1992.
   ``I think once the legalities are over, the cup will be stronger
than ever,'' said Thomas Mitchell, chief spokesman for the
organizing committee.
   ``I think everyone is keen to see it sorted out so that
sportsmanship, in the end, prevails in one form or another,'' said
Debreceny.
   A decision from the Court of Appeals could come by April. Until
then, the historic silver trophy, 34 inches high and coveted by
yachters worldwide, will stay in its vault on Fifth Avenue.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0031 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-04-90 1619EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SouthPacificHurricane     02-04 0280</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-South Pacific Hurricane,0288</SECOND>
<HEAD>American Samoa Socked by Hurricane Ofa</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: RETRANSMITTING a0705 to fix category code.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>PAGO PAGO, American Samoa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hurricane Ofa, which packed
sustained winds of 132 mph, moved away from American Samoa and
Western Samoa on Sunday, leaving power outages and knocked out
communications in its wake.
   The storm, which passed about 40 miles west of Western Samoa,
was about 125 miles southwest of here at 5 a.m. HST, Richard Lay, a
National Weather Service forecaster in Honolulu.
   Communication has been down on Western Samoa since Friday, and
no information has been received on damages there.
   Western Samoa, a country of 160,000 people, was more in the
storm's line, and damage there is expected to be severe.
   Territorial Gov. Peter T. Coleman, in Hawaii attending a
conference, said Sunday his island was without electricity,
telephone service and water. ``The situation is real bad,'' said
Coleman.
   He spoke after getting a call from a government official on a
cellular phone, the only way to communicate with the island.
   Injuries were minor, with 15 to 20 people being treated for cuts
at American Samoa Hospital, he said.
   More than 200 people were evacuated Saturday from a northern
coastal area of American Samoa because of dangerous high waves.
   Coleman said the waves were returning to normal heights Sunday
and the seas were calm again, but winds remained fierce. The
governor said Pago Pago Airport remained closed.
   High winds knocked out electrical power to about 90 percent of
Tutuila, American Samoa's main island, where most of the
territory's 38,000 residents live.
   There were also reports of minor flooding, said Maiava Hunkin,
coordinator of the Territorial Emergency Management Committee.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0032 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-04-90 1620EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-SovietParty-Glance     02-04 0339</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet Party-Glance,0356</SECOND>
<HEAD>Details of Communist Party Central Committee</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here is a brief look at the Communist Party
Central Committee, which opens a crucial two-day session in Moscow
on Monday:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>COMPOSITION:</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   The Central Committee is made up of leading members of the 20
million member Soviet Communist Party, which according to the
constitution is the leading and guiding force of Soviet society.
   In most recent years, the Central Committee has been made up of
about 300 members, but last year the number was reduced to 251.
   Membership includes leading figures of the Soviet Communist
Party from regional party organizations, the national government
and party organizations, and other prominent figures from the
military, arts and sciences.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>POWERS:</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   The Central Committee is the policy-making body of the party. It
is charged with guiding the party's work between the larger party
congresses that are held every five years. Most major policy issues
are brought before the Central Committee for a policy directive.
   Between congresses, the Central Committee alone has the power to
change the composition of the Politburo, which is responsible for
running the country on a day-to-day basis. It also may change the
party leader.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>SELECTION:</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   The Central Committee is chosen every five years by the
Communist Party congress. Between congresses, members can be
retired and non-voting members can be promoted to voting
membership. The last congress was held four years ago. The next one
is scheduled for fall.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>WHAT'S AT STAKE:</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Perhaps the future direction of the nation. This Central
Committee meeting is widely expected to become an intense struggle
between hard-liners who want to turn back the reforms of leader
Mikhail S. Gorbachev and progressives who want to acclerate them.
Gorbachev reportedly will proposed a multiparty political system,
which would end the Communists exclusive claim to power for the
first time in seven decades. Gorbachev also is expected to give
tacit approval to the concept of private property. The meeting may
represent the biggest challenge of Gorbachev's five years in power.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0033 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-04-90 1622EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Czechoslovakia     02-04 0406</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Czechoslovakia,0420</SECOND>
<HEAD>Religious Services Broadcast Nationwide For the First Time Since
1940s</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PRAGUE, Czechoslovakia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   State radio broadcast a regular
Mass for the first time in four decades Sunday, and the official
news agency said broadcasts of Protestant, Jewish and other Roman
Catholic services would follow.
   In a separate dispatch, the official CTK news agency announced
officials from the new non-Communist government would meet Kremlin
officials in Moscow Wednesday for talks on withdrawing the
estimated 75,000 Soviet troops from Czechoslovakia.
   The terse report did not specify the length of the second round
of the Soviet-Czechoslovak talks or who would be participating in
them. The first round in Prague Jan. 15-16 failed to provide
tangible results.
   Archbishop Frantisek Vanak led worshipers through the Mass in
the church of St. Wenceslas in the northern city of Olomouc, 180
miles east of Prague.
   The service was the first by Czechoslovak radio's department for
religious programs, which was formed after a popular revolution
ousted the country's hard-line Communist leadership and ushered in
non-Communists who promised religious freedom.
   ``This is a continuation of a beautiful tradition, which was
providing great help to those listeners who were not able to attend
the services in a community of believers,'' CTK said, referring to
the regular broadcasts before the 1948 Communist takeover.
   Plans for other live broadcasts include services from other
Catholic churches, Protestant gatherings and from the Jewish
synagogue in Prague, CTK said.
   At Lany, west of Prague, President Vaclav Havel met with the
Dalai Lama and called on politicians around the world to respect
truth and justice.
   Havel invited the Tibetan spiritual leader, winner of last
year's Nobel Peace Prize, to Czechoslovakia for a private visit.
The five-day trip, which began Friday, was vigorously protested by
China, who said it signaled Prague's support for Tibetan separatism.
   The two officials made no mention of the dispute in a joint
statement but called on politicians worldwide to ``act according to
their conscience and the feeling of responsibility to truth and
justice.''
   Under Havel's government, Czechoslovakia has sought a complete
withdrawal of the estimated 75,000 Soviet troops stationed in its
territory by the end of the year, with at least half of them
leaving by mid-May.
   Last week, neighboring Hungary opened negotiations with the
Soviets on a Red Army withdrawal.
   The Soviets arrived in both countries to quash democratic
movements _ the 1956 revolt in Hungary, and the 1968 ``Prague
Spring'' in Czechoslovakia.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0034 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-04-90 1629EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-HUD-Congress 1stLd-Writethru a0653 02-04 0798</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-HUD-Congress, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0653,700</SECOND>
<HEAD>New Information Spurs Renewed HUD Hearings by House Panel</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: LEADS with 15 grafs to UPDATE with committee canceling
appearance by HUD official. Picks up 12th graf pvs, bgng: `I don't</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By WILLIAM M. WELCH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Congressional investigators have unearthed
``additional information'' in the HUD scandal and plan to resume
hearings despite Attorney General Dick Thornburgh's request for a
special prosecutor, according to the chairman of the House panel.
   However, amid concerns about pursuing a separate investigation,
the committee's chairman, Rep. Tom Lantos, D-Calif., announced
Sunday he was canceling an appearance at a hearing Monday by one of
the witnesses, a former top HUD official who has been cooperating
with investigators.
   Lantos had said earlier that while he was pleased with
Thornburgh's request for a prosecutor ``I disagree with him on the
scope'' of the criminal investigation.
   ``My subcommittee will continue to do its best to develop the
issue,'' Lantos said in an interview Friday.
   ``We have unearthed additional information, new information, and
this has prompted us to continue the hearings,'' he said.
   He declined to say what the new evidence involved.
   Thornburgh asked a federal court last week to appoint a special
prosecutor to investigate former Housing and Urban Development
Secretary Samuel Pierce and other former top HUD officials.
   Thornburgh limited the request to the handling of one HUD
subsidy program, however, and ruled out a request by House
Judiciary Committee members that the prosecutor look at potential
perjury by Pierce before the Lantos panel last spring.
   Lantos' committee, which conducted more than 20 hearings last
year into alleged fraud, mismanagement and influence-peddling at
HUD during the Reagan years, was reopening its hearings Monday.
   Lantos said his Government Operations subcommittee on employment
and housing was scheduling more hearings too, and that he has
changed his mind since last fall when he told reporters it was time
to wind down the congressional probe and turn the HUD scandal over
to the courts.
   ``We clearly will do nothing that will interfere with the work
of the independent counsel,'' he said.
   However the committee said Sunday it was canceling the
appearance of one of the scheduled witnesses, former assistant
housing secretary Thomas Demery.
   Jerris Leonard, Demery's attorney, said Demery was prepared to
testify but that he had been informed by the committee Saturday
afternoon that Lantos wanted to cancel the appearance.
   Leonard said he was told Lantos ``wanted to discuss with the
independent counsel, when he or she is appointed, the question of
whether or not Mr. Demery should appear because he is at least a
witness in the investigation of Mr. Pierce's activities.''
   Demery could not be reached for comment Sunday, but on Friday he
said creation of the special prosecutor _ known under the law as an
independent counsel _ had caused him to have second thoughts about
agreeing to testify before the House panel.
   ``I don't have a good handle on how to answer questions that are
now going to be in the purview of the special prosecutor,'' said
Demery, who appeared voluntarily before the panel last year and has
cooperated with investigators.
   As a former top HUD official, Demery acknowledged, he could
become an object of a special prosecutor's investigation.
   Also scheduled to appear was Carol Crawford, the former
associate director of the Office of Management and Budget who
oversaw HUD for the Reagan White House, and James Hamernick, former
director of HUD's office of insured multifamily housing development.
   Hamernick was appearing under subpoena. His attorney, John
McCahill, informed the committee he would invoke a House rule
allowing subpoenaed witnesses to ban cameras and microphones when
he appears, a step Pierce and other witnesses took when invoking
their constitutional rights to refuse to testify on grounds of
self-incrimination.
   Demery was expected to face questioning about his dealings with
Pierce while at HUD and Pierce's decision-making process.
   Congressional investigators continue to be interested in
Pierce's assertion during his voluntary appearance last spring that
he took no direct role in contract awards, a point that was
disputed in the subsequent testimony of other former HUD officials.
   Congressional investigators want to question Hamernick about his
relationship with former Pierce executive assistant Lance Wilson.
After leaving the department and becoming a housing specialist with
the Wall Street firm of Paine Webber, Wilson filed expense accounts
claiming he spent more than $1,000 to entertain Hamernick in a
single month.
   Thornburgh called for an investigation of Pierce and others in
the awarding of grants under HUD's section 8 moderate
rehabilitation program, which provided subsidies for developers to
renovate housing for low-income people.
   Additional witnesses, including HUD inspector general Paul
Adams, are set to appear before the panel Tuesday in a hearing on
alleged abuses at the Passaic, N.J., public housing authority.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0035 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-04-90 1637EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-CensusHiring 1stLd-Writethru a0654 02-04 0603</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Census Hiring, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0654,590</SECOND>
<HEAD>Census Bureau Hanging Out `Help Wanted' Sign</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: Adds graf on how to apply for jobs</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By RANDOLPH E. SCHMID</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Census Bureau is hanging out the ``Help
Wanted'' sign. People are needed across the nation to track down
hard-to-count Americans and the job can pay up to $8 an hour.
   The census takers will scout remote hollows in West Virginia and
island fishing villages in Alaska, seek out beach dwellers in
California and folks living in mountain cabins in Appalachia.
   Only a few weeks before the official 1990 national head count,
the Census Bureau says it will need 315,000 temporary workers in
addition to its usual staff. Many of the temporary workers have yet
to be hired, says Richard Bitzer of the bureau's field division.
   As in 1980, most Americans will receive a census form by mail in
late March, fill it out and send it back. But officials know that
for one reason or another they won't hear from several million
households. Others will send in incomplete forms.
   It will be the job of the census enumerators to track them down
by phone or in person.
   The peak of activity will be in April and May when 200,000
census workers will go into neighborhoods and small towns as well
as across rural America to interview people. Another 115,000
workers will remain in offices tabulating information and
contacting folks by phone, Bitzer said.
   He said a big hiring push will occur in March. New workers will
have about three days of training and will work daily with their
supervisors to help resolve any problems during the count.
   A census taker's life can be anything but boring. Over the
years, the temporary workers have encountered births, family fights
and more than a few other unusual cases, according to records kept
by the Bureau.
   For example:
   _A census taker was helping jail inmates fill out forms when the
guard was changed. Unable to convince the new shift that he didn't
belong there, the man stayed behind bars for several hours until
the warden confirmed his identity.
   _A feeble voice from behind a closed door once asked a census
employee to crawl in a window. She did, and found an 85-year-old
man lying helplessly on the floor. He motioned her to the next
room, saying: ``My census form is in there. It's all filled out.''
She helped him into bed and called a doctor.
   _A worker once conducted an truly ``in depth'' interview, with a
man who was trying to set a world record for being buried alive.
   _A farmer told a census taker he just couldn't stop plowing to
be interviewed. So, each time the tractor came around the farmer
was shouted a question. Two hours later the form was completed, but
the census taker had a sunburn and a sore throat.
   For tracking down the information, the temporary census takers
will earn $4.50 to $8 an hour and, when on the road, 24 cents a
mile.
   In past years many of the workers were housewives, but that pool
of workers has been declining in number and officials have
increasingly had to turn elsewhere, especially to retirees. A law
was enacted last year that keeps postal, federal and military
retirees from losing retirement benefits if they work as census
takers for less than six months.
   Applicants can check on the availability of local census jobs
through the 484 local census offices that have been opened, and are
listed under the U.S. government in telephone directories, or at
state employment service offices.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0036 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-04-90 1640EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Defense-Soviets 1stLd-Writethru a0699 02-04 0717</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Defense-Soviets, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0699,650</SECOND>
<HEAD>Cheney: U.S. Must Deal With Soviet Military Reality, Not Promises</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: INSERTS 2 grafs after 4th graf pvs, bgng: `Intentions can,''
to include Baker's Soviet trip this week. Picks up 5th graf pvs,
Congresssional leaders</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By H. JOSEF HEBERT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Defense Secretary Richard Cheney said Sunday
it ``makes no sense'' to cut major weapons programs despite
political changes in communist countries because ``we have to deal
with Soviet military capabilities and not just intentions.''
   Cheney defended President Bush's proposed continued funding of
the MX and Midgetman missile programs as well as the level of
proposed U.S. troops cuts in Europe.
   Congressional critics have said the two missile programs aren't
needed and more troops should be brought home.
   ``Intentions can change overnight ... and we have to deal with
the Soviets' military capabilities and not just intentions,''
Cheney said on CBS-TV's ``Face the Nation'' program. ``There is
still enormous nuclear capability'' targeted against the United
States and the Soviets have provided no evidence they are prepared
to change that, Cheney said.
   Cheney made his remarks on the eve of Secretary of State James
A. Baker III's trip to Moscow this week, where he is scheduled to
meet with Soviet President Mikhail Gorbachev. Baker also is to meet
with Foreign Minister Eduard Shevardnadze in hopes of laying the
groundwork for a possible new arms reductions treaty President Bush
and Gorbachev could sign this summer.
   Shevardnadze also is expected to respond more formally to Bush's
troop cut offer.
   Congressional leaders, meanwhile, suggested that deeper defense
spending cuts are needed for the fiscal 1991 budget than the
administration proposed last week and that the president's rollback
in the U.S. military presence in Europe does not go far enough.
   Senate Majority Leader George Mitchell, D-Maine, called the
continued spending for the MX missile program ``wasteful'' and
unnecessary.
   ``I don't think there's any chance that the administration's
proposal to fund both (the MX and Midgetman) will be enacted,''
said Mitchell on NBC-TV's ``Meet the Press.''
   Last week three former chairmen of the Joint Chiefs of Staff
told a congressional hearing the administration should cancel plans
to modernize its land-based nuclear missile force _ including the
MX and Midgetman _ if U.S. Soviet agreement is reached on a
strategic weapons treaty.
   The Bush budget calls for $2.5 billion to place the U.S. fleet
of the 10-warhead MXs on rail cars. It also calls for a $202
million for a new missile, the truck-based, single-warhead
Midgetman.
   ``It makes no sense for us unilaterally to cut those program
when there's no military rationale for doing so,'' argued Cheney,
adding that the U.S. response to developments in the Soviet Union
and Eastern Europe should be limited to conventional weapons issues.
   But Cheney and White House chief of staff John Sununu rejected
deeper troop cuts than the president's proposal. Bush proposed a
cutting U.S. combat forces in central Europe from 255,000 troops to
195,000.
   Mitchell said reductions to ``somewhere in the range of
100,000'' should be pursued with the Soviets. House Speaker Tom
Foley, D-Wash., also predicted U.S. troop strength would be
``something closer to 100,000 than 195,000 ... in a matter of a few
years.''
   ``The game is always whatever the White House lays out, they
play `call and raise' on the Hill,'' Sununu said.
   Foley and Sununu made their remarks on ABC-TV's ``This Week with
David Brinkley.''
   On other matters:
   _ Cheney denied playing politics when assembling the list of
U.S. military bases marked for closing. Rep. Patricia Schroeder,
D-Colo., said 90 percent of the bases listed for closing by the
Republican administration were in Democratic districts, but Cheney
said he was unaware of that when the list was compiled.
   _ Congressional leaders agree that the competition is intense
for money from any so-called peace dividend.
   Noting the government's huge deficit, Foley said reduced defense
spending ``may get (us) closer to paying our way'' and that there
are many demands in social programs that also require funds.
   ``For those who think the (peace) dividend will solve a lot of
other problems, they've got to put it into perspective,'' said Sen.
Pete Domenici, R-N.M., noting the size of the federal deficit.
   Domenici, the ranking Republican on the Senate Budget Committee,
also appeared on the Brinkley program.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0037 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-04-90 1639EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SAfrica-Britain     02-04 0192</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-SAfrica-Britain,0197</SECOND>
<HEAD>Shotgun Fires Damages British Embassy</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-South Africa, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PRETORIA, South Africa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Assailants Sunday shot out windows
at the British Embassy here, a day after right-wing graffiti was
spray-painted on the building, an embassy spokesman said.
   There was no claim of responsibility for the shooting or the
vandalism, which may have been in retaliation for Britain's
endorsement of the political reforms announced Friday by President
F.W. de Klerk.
   John Sawyer, a spokesman for the embassy, said three shots were
fired at the building about 2:30 p.m. No one was injured, and the
attackers fled in a vehicle, he said.
   Sawyer said the embassy requested and received extra police
protection following the attack, and it was considering seeking
extra protection at its four other diplomatic offices in South
Africa.
   British Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher was one of many Western
leaders to praise de Klerk for lifting bans on militant black
opposition groups and pledging to free black leader Nelson Mandela.
She invited de Klerk and Mandela to visit Britain.
   Far-right organizations in South Africa were outraged by de
Klerk's actions and vowed to mobilize resistance to the changes.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0038 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-04-90 1656EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Lebanon-AounCult 1stLd-Writethru   02-04 0845</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lebanon-Aoun Cult, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0642,0871</SECOND>
<HEAD>Outgunned and Trapped, Christian General Aoun Now a Cult Figure</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 11 grafs to ADD offensive to crush the Lebanese
Forces, EDITS to conform; pickup 11th graf pvs, `The
Arabic-language...' Version moved in advance Jan. 30 as b0342.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NIC1 of Jan. 31</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Lebanon, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DONNA ABU-NASR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BAABDA, Lebanon (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Increasingly isolated in a Christian
enclave, the rebel general Michel Aoun has become a cult figure.
   Hundreds of his loyalists have paid him homage daily at
Lebanon's shell-shattered presidential palace, which he has turned
into the ``home of the people.''
   Children have smashed open their clay piggy banks at Aoun's feet
while businessmen spill wads of banknotes from plastic bags to aid
what many others see as a hopeless campaign to drive the powerful
Syrian army out of Lebanon.
   To the Syrians and their allies, Aoun is someone whose lust for
power not only blocks efforts to end Lebanon's 14-year-old civil
war but could unleash more bloodshed and destroy what's left of the
country.
   ``A clown, a clever clown,'' the Druse Moslem chieftain Walid
Jumblatt called him.
   Prime Minister Salim Hoss, a Sunni Moslem, described him as
``nothing but a television show.''
   But Aoun is a champion to the young people in the Christian
enclave ringed on three sides by hostile forces and by the
Mediterranean on the other.
   An estimated half of the 1 million Christians trapped inside the
enclave support the general. Others, like the right-wing
Phalangists and the Lebanese Forces militia, oppose him.
   Since Tuesday, Aoun has waged a savage offense in the Christian
enclave to crush the Lebanese Forces but so far has failed to do
so. At least 200 people have been killed and 900 wounded, mostly
civilians, in the deadly fighting that has sent an estimated
500,000 people to basement bomb shelters.
   Before the most recent fighting, young women at the Ouragan
night club in Christian east Beirut would flash V-for-Victory signs
with their fingers as they danced and shout ``Aoun! Aoun!''
   In other discos, youngsters sang ``General, General,'' a paean
of praise for Aoun set to the tune of the Little Richard classic
``Tutti Frutti.''
   
   The Arabic-language song ridicules rival Christian and Moslem
leaders who endorsed an Arab League peace plan in Saudi Arabia last
October under which Elias Hrawi was elected president of Lebanon on
Nov. 24.
   Aoun, whose 20,000 soldiers control the enclave, rejects the
accord on grounds that it does not guarantee the withdrawal of the
40,000 Syrian soldiers in Lebanon.
   They were deployed under a 1976 Arab League peacekeeping
mandate. Aoun charges they betrayed that mandate by openly siding
with the Moslems and leftists.
   All 45 foreign ambassadors accredited in Lebanon have shunned
Aoun since Hrawi's election in November. But the general pledges to
continue the ``war of liberation'' he launched in March 1989 to
drive out the Syrians, even though his forces are heavily
outnumbered.
   At least 929 people were killed and 2,744 wounded before the
guns were silenced by an Arab League cease-fire Sept. 22.
   Hrawi, who has officially removed Aoun as Lebanon's army
commander and interim prime minister, wants the presidential palace
so he can rule from the symbol of state authority. Aoun refuses to
recognize Hrawi as president or vacate the palace, which is mostly
in ruins.
   Some of Aoun's supporters look upon him with a religious fervor.
   ``Jesus Christ is our savior in heaven and Michel Aoun is our
Jesus and our savior on earth,'' a woman commented in a broadcast
by Aoun's Radio Lebanon.
   Some Maronite Catholics even hold christenings and other church
rituals in the palace courtyard, strung with lights that spell out
in Arabic ``God bless our home.''
   The general has come up from his bunker, two stories under the
palace, almost every day to deliver a political sermon to his
followers.
   His speeches, delivered from behind an armored shield draped
with the Lebanese flag, are often interrupted by shouts of ``Syria
get out'' and ``With our blood and souls we sacrifice ourselves to
you, O General.''
   When winter rains soak them, supporters amend the chant: ``With
our flu we sacrifice ourselves to you.''
   Aoun's officers exhort the crowds to shout louder above the
taped cheers blaring from loudspeakers while the TV cameras roll.
   When it looked as if the Syrians were going to attack Baabda in
October, thousands of Aoun's young loyalists formed a ``human
shield'' around the palace.
   About 500 are still camping out in dozens of colored tents
nestled among the trees around the palace.
   With the winter weather, the tents are mostly empty during the
day. But they're crowded at weekends.
   ``We stay up till dawn, dancing,'' said John, who did not want
his full name used because he often slips into west Beirut, the
capital's Moslem sector. ``The best parties we have are the ones we
hold here.
   ``Why shouldn't we party? We've won the battle against the
Syrians,'' he added, seemingly oblivious to prospect of a possible
military assault to dislodge Aoun from the palace.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0039 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-04-90 1716EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-WeatherpageWeather     02-04 0432</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Weatherpage Weather,0445</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tornadoes Pound Central Alabama; Winter Makes Comeback in
Northeast</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Tornadoes pounded a wide span of central Alabama, flinging
tractor-trailer rigs across a highway near Birmingham, and winter
made its presence felt in the Northeast, dropping 16 inches of snow
in Portland, Maine.
   No deaths or serious injuries were reported in the violent
storms late Saturday, said Greg McWhorter, a spokesman for the
Alabama Department of Emergency Management.
   McWhorter said 150 homes and about 15 businesses were damaged in
Fultondale, north of Birmingham. There were reports of five minor
injuries, he said.
   Brian Peters, a National Weather Service meteorologist at
Birmingham, said at least four tornadoes raked the state. Peters
said he surveyed the affected areas early Sunday and found damage
was widespread but scattered.
   ``The damage was not really what would be classified as major
damage,'' he said.
   Near Monroe, N.C., thunderstorm gusts damaged several farm
buildings.
   Advisories for snow were posted for the mountains of Southern
California and the southern Sierra Nevada. Gale warnings were
issued for much of the northern Pacific Coast Sunday and the
mountains of Southern California.
   By late Sunday morning, 16 inches of snow covered Portland,
Maine; 12 inches at Concord N.H. and Syracuse N.Y.; 10 inches at
Montpelier, Vt.; 9 inches at Bangor, Maine; and 4 to 8 inches over
the western Finger Lakes.
   Overnight snowfalls reached as much as 7 inches across southwest
Illinois, and by midmorning there were reports of up to 7 inches of
new snow across the southern Sierra Nevada and the Tehachapi
Mountains of California.
   Snow was falling Sunday afternoon over much of New England,
except along the coastline, across New York state and into northern
and western Pennsylvania; rain extended across the New England
coast, southeast New York state, New Jersey, and parts of
Pennsylvania, Maryland, Delaware and Virginia.
   Showers and occasional thunderstorms pelted the central sections
of the Carolinas, while snow fell in the panhandle and central part
of Idaho. Rain hit southwest California, with rain mixing with snow
or changing to snow in the higher elevations.
   The low temperature for Lower 48 states was 15 degrees below
zero at both Caribou and Houlton, Maine.
   Some cities set record highs for the date, including the place
dubbed ``The Nation's Icebox'' _ International Falls, Minn., which
had a 46-degree reading, 5 degrees higher than the 1968 mark. Cape
Hatteras, N.C., reached 71 degrees, breaking the 69-degree record
set in 1932.
   Temperatures around the nation at 3 p.m. EST ranged from 1
degree below zero at Houlton to 87 degrees at Melbourne, Fla.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0040 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-04-90 1724EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brites     02-04 0458</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brites,0475</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bright and Brief</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LANSING, Mich. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Zoo officials want to give Mac the bison a
home where the buffalo roam.
   Mac, who weighs 1,800 pounds, currently resides in Lansing's
Fenner Arboretum, but Potter Park Zoo officials want to move him
somewhere where he can live with other animals.
   ``That animal's not in a good setting,'' said zoo Director
Douglas Finley. ``It's alone. It should be with other bison.''
   This saddens Wes Goins, who lives next door to the arboretum and
who made friends with the big beast by feeding him apples until Mac
finally ate out of his hand.
   The zoo feeds Mac grass, hay and grain but Goins regularly
treats him to corn and fruit. Zoo officials discourage the extra
feedings.
   ``He eats apples, grapes, bananas, plums. ... I know he likes
kiwi,'' Goins said. ``He's a fruit freak.'' Goins said Mac eats
bananas peel and all, but prefers his apples sliced, his oranges
peeled and his peaches pitted.
   Mac once shared the pasture with antelope, longhorn cattle, deer
and prairie dogs, which have since died or been relocated. Mac
sired several calves with a bison cow, but she died three years ago.
   Goins said he'll visit Mac wherever he goes if they are
separated.
   ``I think if they took him out of here and I went to see him, I
think he'd come if I called him,'' he said.
   City officials will move Mac to a new home if the Friends of the
Arboretum decide that living among other bison would be best for
him.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>DALLAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The newly arrived traveler from South Korea waited
in vain at Dulles International Airport near Washington, D.C., for
a friend to pick him up. There was a good reason.
   ``His ride was in Dallas,'' explained Mary Villalobos, manager
of the foreign-traveler greeting service at the suburban Virginia
airport. ``When they hear `Dulles,' they think Texas. It happens
all the time.''
   Lisa Smith, director of the Washington Airports Task Force, said
the names typically confuse visitors from the Middle East and Far
East. ``If they're not enunciated clearly, it's hard to tell the
difference,'' she said.
   Such confusion may be about to end, thanks to a move to rename
the capital's principal international airport in honor of the late
President Eisenhower, whose 100th birthday will be celebrated in
October.
   Sen. Bob Dole, R-Kan., introduced the resolution last week
urging the Metropolitan Washington Airports Authority to rename the
airport, which bears the name of Eisenhower's longtime secretary of
state, John Foster Dulles.
   Nearly all of the authority board's 11 members support Dole's
proposal, according to board member Michael Barnes. ``My hope is
that the name will be changed by October 14, Eisenhower's
birthday,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0041 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-04-90 1737EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Colombia     02-04 0480</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Colombia,0493</SECOND>
<HEAD>Gunmen Assassinate a Mayor and a Journalist as Army Finds Drug
Money</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By STAN YARBRO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOGOTA, Colombia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Unidentified gunmen assassinated a mayor
and a journalist and shot at a congressman in separate incidents
over the weekend, authorities said Sunday.
   The mayor's body was left draped in a flag of leftist
guerrillas, who have promised a wave of violence leading up to
mayoral and congressional elections early next month.
   Also Sunday, the army said it discovered more than $2.4 million
in cash on a ranch once owned by Gonzalo Rodriguez Gacha, the
Medellin cartel leader killed in a Dec. 15 gunfight with police.
   The money, found Saturday, had been buried on the banks of the
Magdalena River near the town of Guaduas, 43 miles north of Bogota.
Soldiers searching the ranch also found more than 100 weapons, an
army communique said.
   Last November, the army found $5.2 million in cash buried at
another ranch belonging to Rodriguez Gacha, considered the most
violent of the Medellin cartel leaders.
   A Sunday communique from the Norte de Santander state government
office said the mayor of the town of Arboledas, Pedro Jesus
Hernandez, was shot and killed by several gunmen who covered his
body with a flag bearing the initials ELN. The letters stand for
the National Liberation Army, the country's most active leftist
guerrilla group.
   Led by a defrocked Catholic priest, the ELN has been blamed for
the assassinations of three mayors in the past 35 days.
   The group has pledged to carry out a campaign of attacks,
kidnappings and assassinations in northeastern Colombia to disrupt
congressional and mayoral elections scheduled for March 11 and
presidential balloting to be held May 27.
   Hernandez, a member of the opposition Conservative Party, had
been traveling in a car late Saturday on his way to inaugurate a
cafeteria for poor children when the attackers opened fire, the
government communique said.
   Arboledas is a town of 15,000 people 217 miles northeast of
Bogota.
   In Puerto Asis, 322 miles south of the capital, assailants also
suspected of being leftist guerrillas opened fire Saturday on a
Conservative Party congressman, Ernesto Muriel. He escaped the
attack uninjured, the national police said in a communique.
   In the river port of Barrancabermeja, two men traveling on a
motorcycle gunned down a journalist, Cayetano Dominguez, in front
of the offices of Caracol radio network, where he worked, a
national police communique said.
   Police said they were trying to determine the motive for the
Friday night assassination. Since 1977, more than 45 journalists
have been killed in Colombia, the majority of them by drug
traffickers.
   The government declared war on the traffickers in August and
began extraditing suspects to the United States to face
drug-related chargeds. The cocaine lords responded with a terror
campaign that has killed 209 people and included the bombing of a
Colombian airliner.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0042 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-04-90 1744EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-StudentLoans     02-04 0517</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Student Loans,470</SECOND>
<HEAD>Banks, Other Lenders Seek To Reduce Loan Defaults</HEAD>
<NOTE>For Release at 6:30 p.m. EST, time set by source</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By TAMARA HENRY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Education Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Using aggressive tactics that included
garnishing lottery winnings and putting liens on real estate, banks
and other lenders in three years doubled the money recovered from
delinquent student loan borrowers, a study showed Sunday.
   Lenders in the Guaranteed Student Loan Program, which has made
higher education possible for more than 20 million Americans since
created by Congress in 1965, ``introduced innovative procedures to
forestall default'' and increase recoveries from $200 million in
fiscal year 1986 to more than $400 million in fiscal year 1989.
   ``The very magnitude of this program ... has created an urgent
concern to prevent defaults and increase collections from borrowers
who have run into trouble,'' said Pelavin Associates, a Washington,
D.C. research firm that conducted three national studies on the GSL
program for a consortium of guarantee agencies in Colorado,
Massachusetts, Tennessee, Texas and Washington state.
   Government student loan programs have been harshly criticized in
recent years because of spiralling huge default rates, mainly among
trade and vocational schools.
   The GSL program, which is administered by 56 guarantee agencies
that protect private lenders against losses from loan defaults, had
$51.6 billion in student loans entering repayment status in fiscal
year 1988.
   The federal government is the ultimate guarantor of the loans.
Last year, the Education Department announced it would try to
collect more than 100,000 defaulted student loans, worth more than
$300 million. These include loans that were made to borrowers who
have never made a payment on their student loans and also loans to
students who have not made a payment in the five years following
their loan default.
   According to the new studies, eighteen guarantee agencies
improved their recovery rates by more than 10 percent and 22
agencies saw improvements between 5 percent and 10 percent.
   Half the agencies took problem borrowers to court, while 20
states got tough by withholding defaulters' state income tax
refunds. Eighteen states used outside collection agencies to
supplement their own resources.
   Colorado garnished wages. Utah put liens on real estate. Texas
and Illinois did not renew professional licenses for doctors,
nurses, lawyers and beauticians until their debts were resolved.
   California garnished lottery winnings for a few defaulters lucky
enough to win money.
   A study on loan default reductions found that 48 out of 56
guarantee agencies have reduced the percentage of loans in default
since 1986. The federal government rewards low default rates by
tying reimbursement allocations to an annual performance
calculation known as the ``Trigger Rate.'' Twenty-nine of the
guarantee agencies qualified for full reimbursement.
   In other findings:
   _Fourteen guarantee agencies used special procedures to
disqualify troublesome proprietary schools during the past four
years. Texas, Georgia and Oklahoma limited the number of loans
problem schools could process. Eleven states suspended proprietary
schools, and six states terminated schools permanently from the
guaranteed loan program.
   _Four actions were instituted against lenders. Lender violations
included failure to follow administrative procedures, inaccurate
records, and incorrect federal reporting.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0043 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-04-90 1812EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Britain-Jackson     02-04 0381</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Britain-Jackson,0393</SECOND>
<HEAD>Jesse Jackson Hopeful and Cautious About South African Govt's
Reform</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-South Africa, Bjt</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto LON3</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   By GRAHAM HEATHCOTE&equals;
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Jesse Jackson said Sunday that South Africa will
not be accepted internationally until the white-led government of
President F.W. de Klerk abolishes apartheid.
   ``De Klerk cannot stop now,'' the U.S. civil rights leader said
in a sermon at St. James's Anglican church in Piccadilly, London.
``De Klerk must continue beyond to bring about a democratic, open,
non-racial society in South Africa.''
   De Klerk announced Friday that black leader Nelson Mandela will
be freed from prison soon. He also legalized Mandela's African
National Congress guerrilla movement and eased emergency
regulations.
   After preaching at St. James's, a fashionable church and a
center for left-wing causes, Jackson addressed a cheering rally of
about 1,200 people in London's rundown Hackney district.
   He is in London on a three-day stopover on his way to visit
South Africa for the first time since 1979. He is due to have talks
with Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher on Monday.
   Jackson told the church congregation there was hope for the
future in de Klerk's speech. But, he added: ``The caution is that
the structures of apartheid are still in place.''
   A mainly black crowd filled Hackney's Empire Theater three hours
before Jackson arrived.
   ``We don't go to South Africa as tourists or visitors but as
brothers and sisters going home,'' Jackson told them.
   ``We have been separated for so long in the diaspora. Africans
everywhere, in Britain, the Caribbean, the United States and
Africa, are members of one family with an obligation to stand
together to make the world better,'' he said.
   Diane Abbott, the first black woman elected to the British House
of Commons, told the rally that it was pressure from South Africa's
black majority that won Mandela's freedom. ``No one has freed black
South Africans _ they freed themselves.''
   Jackson is to meet with President Kenneth Kaunda of Zambia on
Tuesday and arrive in South Africa on Wednesday.
   The South African visit was arranged before de Klerk's actions
Friday. Jackson was invited by Walter Sisulu, an ANC leader freed
last year after spending more than 20 years in jail with Mandela,
and the South African Council of Churches.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0044 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-04-90 1821EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Bush-Concert     02-04 0088</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bush-Concert,100</SECOND>
<HEAD>White House Event to be Broadcast Feb. 14</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush and his wife Barbara hosted
their third ``In Performance at the White House'' concert Sunday.
   The concert was taped for broadcast Feb. 14 by the Public
Broadcasting Service. It featured opera diva Marilyn Horne,
singer-actress Patti LuPone, singer Jeffrey Osmond, country singer
Gary Morris and the Dick Hyman Trio.
   The theme of the concert was ``A Presidents' Day Party.'' The
earlier concerts were aired around the 4th of July and Columbus Day.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0045 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-04-90 1838EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-TroubledMayor     02-04 0420</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Troubled Mayor,0432</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bradley's Political Mentor Disputes Allegations He Misused Poverty
Funds</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A political mentor to Mayor Tom Bradley
disputed allegations Sunday that he used $336,000 in federal
poverty funds to renovate a dilapidated building he secretly owned.
   The City Council granted loans to Bishop H. Hartford Brookins,
who owned the building through a non-existent corporation, between
1982 and 1985, in apparent violation of city bidding procedures and
despite his refusal sometimes to provide financial information, the
Los Angeles Times reported in Sunday editions.
   In addition, a Bradley aide repeatedly asked two city
administrators to grant special help to the bishop, city officials
said.
   In a telephone interview from Virginia published Sunday in the
Times, Brookins said the office complex initially was acquired by
an arm of the African Methodist Episcopal Church.
   ``The property was in the name of the Southern California
Conference AME Church,'' Brookins said. ``It does exist. Whether it
is incorporated, I don't know.''
   Brookins said he will pay back the city any money he may owe.
But he insisted he has done nothing improper.
   ``I know everything was done aboveboard and signed off by the
city,'' Brookins said. ``That's why I'm not shaking in my boots
right now.''
   Los Angeles City Council members said they will conduct an
inquiry this week into city loans used to renovate the office
complex to see if public funds were misused.
   ``My basic question is what's going on? How come we didn't know
about it earlier?'' Councilman Robert Farrell said.
   Brookins, former AME bishop in Los Angeles and now head of the
church in Virginia, Maryland, and Washington, D.C., acknowledged
that he now owns the office complex. He said the African Methodist
Episcopal Church can have it back by paying him about $900,000 that
he owes on the property.
   Brookins received the loans through the city's Community
Development Department to renovate a run-down building complex for
a jobs and education program.
   Later, the city program was shifted to a dilapidated office next
door while the refurbished building was leased for $10,000 per
month. The complex was refinanced to net the bishop $250,000.
   Bradley has refused to be interviewed about Brookins, but Deputy
Mayor Mark Fabiani said that Bradley is concerned about the
allegations.
   Brookins headed Bradley's first campaign for City Council in
1963 and has been chairman or co-chairman of every Bradley campaign
since. ``I mean literally, if I may, I almost hand-carried Bradley
up his whole political career,'' Brookins said in a 1985 interview.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0046 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-04-90 1838EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Obit-Henke     02-04 0107</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Henke,0109</SECOND>
<HEAD>Former Italian Secret Service Head Dies at 81</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ROME (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Adm. Eugenio Henke, who led the Italian secret
service in the late 1960s when its agents were linked to right-wing
terrorism and coup plots, died Sunday at 81, the ANSA news agency
reported.
   Henke died of a heart attack in a military hospital in Rome, the
report said.
   He led the secret service from 1966 to 1970 and served as
military chief of staff from 1972 to 1975.
   Henke was called as a witness in a number of parliamentary and
judicial investigations and always denied knowledge of any illegal
activity by his agents.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0047 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-04-90 1843EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Obit-Warner     02-04 0146</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Warner,0150</SECOND>
<HEAD>Retired GM Board Member Dies</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BLOOMFIELD HILLS, Mich. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Harold G. Warner, who rose from
General Motors Corp. parts installer to member of the automaker's
board of directors, died of cancer at his home. He was 81.
   Warner, who died Friday, retired in 1973 after a 46-year career
with GM.
   ``In a career that spanned nearly half a century, Harold Warner
contributed greatly to the growth of General Motors, as an
engineer, an administrator and member of the board of directors,''
said GM Chairman Roger B. Smith.
   Warner went to work for GM in 1927, and earned his engineering
degree at the General Motors Institute in Flint. He was named
executive vice president in charge of the operations staff and a
member of the board in 1968.
   Survivors include his wife, Elizabeth, and a daughter. A
memorial service was scheduled for Friday.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0048 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-04-90 1845EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-CristianiProtest     02-04 0223</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Cristiani Protest,0230</SECOND>
<HEAD>Protesters Picket Salvadoran President</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CAMBRIDGE, Mass. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   El Salvadoran President Alfredo
Cristiani attracted dozens of protesters Sunday when he went to
Harvard University, apparently to watch his son play in a squash
match, officials said.
   Harvard spokesman Peter Costa said Cristiani was in town for ``a
private, family visit.''
   Costa said he was told Cristiani's son was a member of Princeton
University's squash team, which was playing Harvard.
   Dozens of protesters opposed to El Salvadoran military policies
demonstrated outside the Harvard gymnasium, banging pots and pans.
   Earlier in the day, protesters gathered outside the Cambridge
hotel where Cristiani was staying.
   The demonstrators brought letters from Cambridge Mayor Alice
Wolf and from the Cambridge, Belmont and Arlington sister city
projects.
   The letters described how recent delegations that visited sister
cities in El Salvador reported continuing human rights abuses by
the military.
   In her letter, Wolf said children often have been the victims of
military raids in Cambridge's sister city of San Jose Las Flores.
   ``Our president, George Bush, frequently justifies the military
aid that our country sends your government on the grounds that you
have at long last brought the armed forces of El Salvador under
democratic civilian control,'' the letter said. ``Judging from
their behavior towards San Jose Las Flores, this does not seem to
be the case.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0049 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-04-90 1845EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Switzerland-Avalanche     02-04 0106</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Switzerland-Avalanche,0110</SECOND>
<HEAD>Italian Killed, Three Injured in Avalanche</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CHUR, Switzerland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   One Italian was killed and three were
injured in a major avalanche that struck Sunday in a Swiss Alps
area frequented by skiers roaming outside prepared runs, officials
said.
   Grisons state police identified the victim as Antonio Ghisetti,
37, of Crema, Italy.
   Police said three Italians were injured when the snowslide hit
at about 6,600 feet on the Piz Uccello peak in the southeastern
state.
   At the time, more than 80 people were skiing outside prepared
runs in the area above the village of Mesocco, east of the San
Bernardino Pass, police said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0050 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-04-90 1846EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-DrugArrests     02-04 0200</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Drug Arrests,0205</SECOND>
<HEAD>Report: Police Restrict Drug Arrests</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Police Department has quotas limiting the
number of drug arrests by individual officers to save overtime pay,
the Daily News reported Sunday.
   The News said narcotics officers are ordered to stop making
arrests for the rest of the month when they reach the unofficial
35-hour overtime limit, which amounts to about three arrests.
   Police Commissioner Lee Brown denied the report. ``We do not
stop making arrests at any point in time because of overtime,''
Brown said.
   ``A guy can reach his 35 hours in the first week or two, then
sit around the rest of the month and do nothing,'' the News quoted
an unidentified narcotics officer as saying.
   ``I've been told in a month when I had great felony arrests that
I was going to be put on the telephone because I'm making too
many'' arrests, said another.
   Brown, however, said department policy merely ``supervises the
distribution of the overtime. It would not be correct if one
officer received all the overtime and another officer did not
receive any.
   ``So it's just a matter of management, to insure that there is
an equal work load.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0051 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-04-90 1849EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-MailBombs     02-04 0383</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mail Bombs,0393</SECOND>
<HEAD>Print Shop Owner Interviewed In Mail Bomb Probe Attended NAACP
Meetings</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GARRY MITCHELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ENTERPRISE, Ala. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The white print shop owner whose
property was searched by the FBI in its mail bomb investigation has
belonged to the NAACP's local chapter for three years, the
chapter's president said Sunday.
   But the attorney for Brian Joseph Fleming, 32, said that
membership was not the reason his client's print shop and home were
searched Friday. Lawyer John Knowles said the searches were
probably related to Fleming's indictment on charges of conspiring
to export weapons, reportedly to Northern Ireland.
   There have been no arrests in the investigation of December mail
bombings that killed 11th U.S. Circuit Court of Appeals Judge
Robert Vance and Savannah, Ga., lawyer Robert Robinson.
   Two other bombs were intercepted at the Jacksonville, Fla.,
NAACP office and the 11th Circuit courthouse at Atlanta. The threat
to the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People
aroused fears that all the bombings were racially motivated. That
concern was heightened by a letter from an obscure group claiming
responsibility for them.
   Fleming, who has come under the scrutiny of FBI agents probing
the mail bombs, has pleaded innocent to an unrelated federal
conspiracy charge and remains free on $50,000 bond.
   Knowles said Sunday he didn't know of Fleming's NAACP connection
and refused to allow his client to be interviewed.
   In Enterprise, Z.I. Fleming Sr., president of the Coffee County
NAACP, said the print shop owner paid the $10 annual dues and
joined the local chapter in 1987.
   ``I know him pretty well. He appeared to me to be interested in
our goals,'' said Fleming, who is black.
   B.F. Garth, another NAACP member, said he saw the print shop
owner during meetings and doubted that Fleming was trying to
infiltrate the chapter.
   ``He participated in discussions and acted like an ordinary
member to me,'' Garth said.
   On Friday, Fleming and his wife, Georgia, were fingerprinted
during separate trips to the police station while the searches were
under way.
   The attention focused on Fleming, who has not been charged in
the mail bomb case, drew the spotlight away from Robert Wayne
O'Ferrell, the salvage store operator whose 11th Circuit appeal in
an employment compensation case attracted the FBI's attention.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0052 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-04-90 1908EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-EastGermany 2ndLd-Writethru   02-04 0732</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-East Germany, 2nd Ld-Writethru,a0711,0750</SECOND>
<HEAD>Communist Party Changes Name, Promiss To Hand Over Millions</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Leads with 7 grafs to RECAST and CORRECT figure to $600
million sted $600,000, ADDS detail. Pickup 6th graf pvs, `The
moves...'; INSERTS 2 grafs after 14th graf pvs, `Modrow said...' to
UPDATE with NATO chief's comment on reunification. Pickup 15th graf
pvs, `Since East...'</NOTE>
<HEAD>With AM-Soviet-Party, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CAROL J. WILLIAMS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WEST BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   East Germany's Communist Party on Sunday
changed its name and promised to hand over $600 million in assets
to the government in an apparent attempt to improve its image ahead
of coming elections.
   Also Sunday, West Germany's foreign minister promised to seek
immediate financial aid to stabilize East Germany's economy while
it adopts democratic reforms that could lead to reunification.
   Hans-Dietrich Genscher, who was born near Halle in what is now
East Germany, also told a political rally in East Berlin that
European neighbors have nothing to fear from a united Germany.
   In pursuit of unification, Bonn appears willing to swear off
future claims to ethnic German regions that are now part of Poland,
Czechoslovakia and the Soviet Union.
   Leaders of East Germany's disgraced Communist Party met and
formally changed its name to the Party of Democratic Socialism. It
previously had been known as the Socialist Unity Party of Germany.
   The party also said it will hand over $600 million from its
private reserves to government coffers because the ``country's
economic situation requires such support,'' the government news
agency ADN reported.
   ADN said the money came from party dues and party-owned
businesses such as printing operations. It did not say what the
party's total reserves are.
   The moves were the latest attempt by the Communists to shore up
their image ahead of the March 18 elections. The first free
balloting in the nation's 40-year history was made possible by a
pro-democracy revolution last year that ousted hard-line Communist
Party chief Erich Honecker on Oct. 18.
   The Communists, who dominate the current interim government
headed by Premier Hans Modrow, are widely blamed for the nation's
economic problems.
   Genscher, noting the dire state of the East German economy, said
Bonn will have to help its struggling neighbor provide health care
and basic goods and services for its increasingly restive citizens.
   ``German unity will not come for free,'' Genscher told a
founding congress of the opposition East German Free Democratic
Party.
   West Germany also is considering other measures to help East
Germany.
   West German Finance Minister Theo Waigel proposed last week that
the West German mark be introduced as the recognized currency in
East Germany to give its 16 million citizens confidence that
reforms are imminent.
   A prominent East German politician, Dresden Mayor Wolfgang
Berghofer, also appealed for immediate currency reform during a
weekend international economics conference in the Swiss resort of
Davos.
   Chancellor Helmut Kohl of West Germany and Modrow met at Davos
to discuss ways that Bonn can aid East Germany until a new
government can be seated and a plan for reunification drafted.
   Modrow said Sunday that his own proposals for German unification
are not dead despite Bonn's rejection of his position that a united
Germany should be neutral. He said his neutrality proposal was only
part of an effort to ``open a dialogue'' on Germany's future.
   In Munich, West Germany, NATO General Secretary Manfred Woerner
said the Western alliance supports German unity but not at the cost
of the alliance.
   Those who call for dissolving the Western alliance risk the
``security and unity'' of Germany and Europe, Woerner, a West
German, told an annual conference of lawmakers, security experts
and government officials from the NATO countries.
   Since East Germany ousted Honecker, opened the Berlin Wall and
lifted travel restrictions, thousands of people have fled to the
West each day as their nation becomes increasingly unstable.
   The departures, averaging 2,000 a day in January, are reducing
the nation's productivity and causing food shortages and reductions
in other services.
   Genscher and the leader of his Free Democratic Party, Otto Graf
Lambsdorff, flew to Berlin to attend the inaugural meeting of the
opposition East German Free Democratic Party and to offer political
support.
   West German politicians also plan to meet next week with other
reformist political parties in East Germany. Lambsdorff urged them
to band together to improve their chances of winning parliamentary
seats in the March 18 voting.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0053 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-04-90 1909EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Dollar-Yen     02-04 0029</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Dollar-Yen,0030</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dollar Opens Up</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The dollar opened at 145.59 yen on the Tokyo
foreign exchange market Monday, up from Friday's close of 144.95
yen.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0054 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-04-90 1926EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-India-Kashmir 1stLd-Writethru   02-04 0510</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-India-Kashmir, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0693,0526</SECOND>
<HEAD>Moslem Militants Renew Attacks With Bombings</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 4 grafs to UPDATE with suspected Sikh militants
killing nine people; pickup 4th graf pvs, `The attacks...'</NOTE>
<DATELINE>SRINAGAR, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Moslem separatists on Sunday blew up a
bus and hurled bombs at an Indian paramilitary patrol, a government
building and the home of a state lawmaker in a new series of
attacks in Kashmir's largest city.
   No one was killed in the attacks, the latest violence since
India launched a crackdown Jan. 20 on the groups that want the
northern region bordering Moslem Pakistan to secede from
predominantly Hindu India. At least 76 people have died since then.
   Also Sunday, police said suspected Sikh militants killed nine
people over the weekend in attacks on two buses in the northern
state of Punjab. Sikh extremists are fighting to make an
independent nation out of the rich farming state, which borders
Pakistan farther south.
   Political leaders in Pakistan demanded that India end the
crackdown in Kashmir and declared Monday a national holiday to show
support for the Moslem militants.
   The attacks in Srinagar came Sunday morning, after authorities
lifted a curfew for 12 hours.
   One woman was injured when a bomb exploded on an empty bus as
passengers were gathering to board, witnesses and a police said.
The bomb destroyed the vehicle and damaged three nearby shops.
   Members of the Jammu-Kashmir Liberation Front, also speaking on
condition of anonymity, said their group was responsible for the
attacks, which included bombs thrown at a paramiliary patrol, at a
government office, the home of a state legislator, and a school.
   There were no further reports of injuries.
   Shops on Sunday stayed shut, respecting a strike call by the
Islamic militant.
   Srinagar, a city of 1 million, is the summer capital of
Jammu-Kashmir state, which has been claimed by both India and
Moslem Pakistan since the two nations were partitioned along
religious lines upon attaining independence from Britain in 1947.
   The two traditionally hostile neighbors went to war in 1948 and
1965 over the territory.
   India has repeatedly charged Pakistan with fomenting the trouble
on its side of the cease-fire line, a charge routinely dismissed by
Pakistan.
   In the Pakistani capital of Islamabad, the demand for an end to
the Indian crackdown came in a rare agreement between governing and
opposition parties.
   Pakistan's combined opposition of right-wing, centrist and
religious parties called for a nationwide strike on Monday in
support of the separatists.
   Prime Minister Benazir Bhutto's government replied by declaring
Monday a holiday in a show of solidarity with them.
   Jammu-Kashmir is the only Indian state with a Moslem majority.
It is composed of the predominantly Hindu southern Jammu region and
the mostly Moslem northern Kashmir sector.
   A western section of Kashmir is controlled by Pakistan along a
cease-fire line where Indian and Pakistani troops face each other,
sometimes at distances of only a few hundred yards.
   Nationally, Hindus comprise 82 percent of India's 880 million
people, but they make up only 32 percent of Jammu-Kashmir's 5
million people.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0055 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-04-90 2119EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>d a AM-BRF--TrafficFatals     02-04 0170</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Traffic Fatals,0173</SECOND>
<HEAD>Five Children, Man Killed in Fiery Accident</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MOUNT VERNON, Mo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Five children and a 20-year-old man
were killed Sunday when the vehicle they were in skidded on a patch
of ice on an interstate, overturned and burst into flames, a state
trooper said.
   The accident happened around 7:30 a.m. as the four-wheel-drive
vehicle was heading west on Interstate 44 near this southwest
Missouri town, according to Highway Patrol Trooper Leslie Crowe.
   The driver, Howard Bouchard, 38, of Denton, Texas, escaped by
kicking out a window, and pulled the children's mother from the
front seat of the burning vehicle, but passersby held him back when
he tried to rescue the others, Crowe said.
   The trooper identified the dead as Edna England, 16; Clara
England, 14; Ella England, 12; Virginia England, 11; and Virgil
England, 10, all of Denton; and Arthur Brown, 20, of Watertown, N.Y.
   The children's mother, Marcella England, 38, and Bouchard were
treated for minor burns at a hospital in Springfield and released.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0056 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-04-90 2025EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Israel-Attack-Reax     02-04 0713</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel-Attack-Reax,0733</SECOND>
<HEAD>Israelis Say Attack Planned, Carried Out At A Sensitive Moment</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Israel-Bus Attack</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SERGEI SHARGORODSKY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Israeli officials said Sunday the attack on a
bus carrying Israeli tourists in the Egyptian desert was a
carefully planned operation carried out at a sensitive moment in
the Middle East peace process.
   In the assault, at least eight people were killed and 17 were
injured when masked men fired machine guns and hurled hand grenades
at the bus on a desert road about 40 miles north of Cairo, an
Egyptian government statement said.
   Prime Minister Yitzhak Shamir, speaking in an interview with
Israel Television, said:
   ``This murderous attack on Israeli tourists in the center of
Egypt is a most serious, shocking event. ... This attack proves
that hostility towards Israel still exists and runs amok in the
region.''
   ``We hope the Egyptian authorities will do everything possible
to find the killers, punish them and prevent further events of this
sort,'' Shamir said.
   The attack came two days before a crucial meeting of Shamir's
hard-line Likud bloc, at which Shamir is to defend his Middle East
peace plan against assaults by a group of influential party hawks.
   Shamir's plan calls for Palestinian elections in the occupied
territories as a first step toward peace. The hawks say the plan,
approved by Israel's coalition government, is too dangerous for the
country.
   If Shamir is successful, a meeting of foreign ministers of the
United States, Israel and Egypt is likely to take place later this
month to prepare for a round of Israeli-Palestinian talks in Cairo.
   However, the attack could strengthen the positions of
hard-liners who want to block Shamir's peace plan and say Egypt
cannot be a fair mediator because of its close links with the PLO.
   Although Israel officially considers the PLO to be a terrorist
group, Likud hard-liners fear Shamir's plan would give it a role in
peace negotiations.
   ``We should not accept any expressions of sorrow anymore. The
Egyptians have to prove they are disassociated only by one way, a
total rejection of the PLO, of PLO institutions, of their meetings
with (PLO leader Yasser) Arafat and terrorists in Egypt,'' Likud
lawmaker Yehoshua Matza said on Israel army radio.
   ``They have lately allowed these groups to operate freely in
Egypt and when there is a free hand and Egyptian instigation every
day, we witness such terrible killings,'' he said.
   Other Likud officials, including some of Shamir's supporters,
were more cautious about blaming Egypt, the only Arab country with
which Israel has peace.
   ``We can say with certainty that these criminals wanted to kill
Israelis, to kill the very idea of coexistence between Israelis and
Arabs,'' said Deputy Foreign Minister Benjamin Netanyahu.
   ``This is not a spontaneous action but a planned one. Apparently
it was necessary to gather intelligence and plan it,'' he said.
   Ehud Olmert, Likud's Cabinet Minister in charge of Arab affairs,
said ``diplomatic links with Egypt are important'' but suggested
Israelis should stop visiting Egypt.
   Olmert's suggestion was supported by several right-wing parties,
such as Moledet and Tzomet. In 1985-1986, Israeli tourism to Egypt
came to a virtual halt for a year following the Oct. 6, 1985,
attack in which an Egyptian policeman shot dead seven Israeli
tourists in the Sinai peninsula.
   Finance Minister Shimon Peres of the left-leaning Labor Party,
Shamir's rival and coalition partner, said Israel should pursue its
peace plan despite the attack. The party has warned it would leave
the government if Likud's hawks block peace efforts.
   ``It is clear that we have to prevail over the murderers and not
leave the fate of peace at the hands of terrorists and madmen,'' he
said on army radio.
   Education Minister Yitzhak Navon, an influential Labor leader,
said the attack was ``an attempt by a radical Arab group ... to
disrupt our relations with Egypt, to disrupt this peace.''
   The leftist Peace Now group issued a statement calling on Jews
and Arabs to ``act together to stop a crazy minority ready to spill
blood in order to stop the peace process.''
   Left-wing Israelis planned to organize a mass pilgrimage to
Cairo for a meeting with PLO members there. The action is designed
to challenge an Israeli law banning unauthorized contacts with the
PLO.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0057 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-04-90 2059EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-SovietExchange     02-04 0315</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet Exchange,0326</SECOND>
<HEAD>Georgians to Participate in `Largest US-USSR Exchange'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LAURAN NEERGAARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ATLANTA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   About 260 people from around Georgia will trade
places with an equal number of Soviet Georgians this April in a
program planned by a group that promotes international exchanges.
   The ``Georgia to Georgia Friendship Exchange'' sponsored by
Friendship Force will be the first time residents from around the
state will take part in such a program, and is a test of the
feasibility of large exchanges, said Atlanta-Tbilsi Sister City
Committee Chairman George Brown.
   Past exchanges have involved only about 25 people, Brown said.
   ``Friendship Force founder Wayne Smith has dreamed of doing this
by the thousands,'' he said.
   Exchanges between the two Georgias began in 1985 when 11 Tbilisi
residents visited Atlanta. The two Georgia capitals, Atlanta and
Tbilisi, later formed a Sister City relationship, and since then
small delegations of residents and city leaders have visited each
other.
   Friendship Force plans to take applications and interview
prospective travelers around Georgia next weekend.
   The 260 Americans who make the grade are to fly to Tbilisi on
April 17 for a 12-day stay. An equal number of Soviet Georgians are
to arrive in Atlanta on April 18 for a week in Atlanta and another
week in other sections of the state.
   The cost for Americans is $1,295, although financial aid will be
available.
   He said Friendship Force workers would try to match hosts and
guests with similar occupations and interests so they could see how
their jobs were performed in the other country.
   ``We hope an elementary school teacher, for example, would be
placed with someone involved with elementary schools so they could
attend class and observe,'' Brown said.
   Brown said that if the exchange goes well, Atlanta-based
Friendship Force hopes to expand the program to other states with
sister cities in the Soviet Union.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0058 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-04-90 2100EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BuchwaldSuit     02-04 0360</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Buchwald Suit,0368</SECOND>
<HEAD>Studio's Financial Documents Show `Coming to America' Hasn't Made
Money</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The hit movie ``Coming to America'' has made
no profit despite $350 million in worldwide ticket sales, according
to financial documents released by Paramount Pictures.
   The documents, released to the Los Angeles Times by court order
Saturday, also show that the movie's star, Eddie Murphy, and his
assistants ran up $5 million in bills for food, travel, lodging and
other expenses during the making of the movie.
   Pulitzer Prize-winning columnist Art Buchwald and producer Alain
Bernheim won a lawsuit against Paramount two months ago that
claimed the studio took the idea for the 1988 movie from a screen
treatment by Buchwald. Paramount was ordered to pay Buchwald and
Bernheim 19 percent of the movie's net profits.
   A financial audit is scheduled during a forthcoming phase of the
trial to determine how much money Buchwald and Bernheim should
receive.
   The records were sealed during the trial at Paramount's request,
but studio officials had testified that the movie was still in the
red.
   Part of the reason, according to the documents, is the priority
system for profit sharing set out in the contracts the studio
negotiates.
   In the case of ``Coming to America,'' the court papers show that
the cost of the film's production, marketing and distribution all
come out of the gross receipts, along with more than $13 million
paid to Eddie Murphy Productions and the 35 percent distribution
fee charged by the studio.
   Charges that Paramount absorbed during the making of ``Coming to
America'' could become an issue in the accounting phase of the suit.
   Charges to production made on Murphy's behalf included: $4,920 a
week for a limousine and driver kept on call around the clock,
$2,200 per week paid for a special motor home for Murphy, $1,592
per week paid to the motor home's driver, $1,500 a week for a
personal trainer and $650 a week for a valet.
   None of those expenses came out of Murphy's $8 million salary,
his 15 percent share of the film's gross receipts, his own travel
and hotel expenses or his $5,000-a-week living allowance.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0059 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-04-90 2113EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Israel-Unrest     02-04 0179</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel-Unrest,0187</SECOND>
<HEAD>Reports: Activists Kill Two Palestinians, Troops Wound Three
Palestinians</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Masked Palestinian activists killed two Arabs
in the occupied Gaza Strip Sunday, and three Palestinians were shot
and wounded by Israeli troops in stone-throwing clashes in the
territory, hospital officials reported.
   Arab journalists in Gaza said Mahmud Abu Ghazal, 55, owner of an
auto repair shop in the Maghazi refugee camp, was shot to death by
an unidentified Palestinian assailant as he was opening his store
Sunday morning.
   Hours later, assailants stabbed to death Atidal Nazir Shaat, a
20-year-old woman from the Khan Yunis refugee camp, Arab reporters
and hospital officials said.
   Arab reports said the motives for the killings were not
immediately known.
   Palestinian activists have slain 176 other Arabs on suspicion of
being pro-Israeli collaborators during the 2-year-old uprising
against Israeli rule in the occupied West Bank and the Gaza Strip.
   There was no immediate Israeli comment on the killings and
woundings Sunday.
   At least 651 Palestinians have died in clashes with Israelis
during the uprising, while 43 Israelis were also killed.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0060 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-04-90 2114EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-MissingPlane     02-04 0234</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Missing Plane,0241</SECOND>
<HEAD>Search Discovers Missing Plane; 4 Dead, Including Congressman's
Children</HEAD>
<DATELINE>COALGATE, Okla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A small plane missing since last week was
discovered Sunday in a southeastern Oklahoma pasture, and the four
people aboard were dead, the Oklahoma Highway Patrol said.
   The plane, which carried state Rep. Bill Brewster's two children
and two others, was discovered about seven miles north of Coalgate,
a town of 2,000.
   Kecia Brewster, 16, and Kent Brewster, 13, had accompanied their
father as he kicked off his campaign for the 3rd Congressional
District seat. They left McAlester on Wednesday night for Ardmore.
   Also on the plane were Herb Pate, 32, publisher of The Madill
Record, and pilot Jack Kirkpatrick, 43.
   Brewster and his wife, Suzie, flew in another plane to Oklahoma
City. A third plane carrying campaign workers and Brewster's other
daughter landed safely in Ardmore.
   Ralph Eddings of Coalgate said the aircraft crashed about 100
yards from his home, but he didn't hear or see anything Wednesday
night.
   ``I didn't have no idea it has been this close until they found
it,'' said Eddings, 80.
   The search for the plane began early Thursday, hours after the
plane failed to arrive in Ardmore.
   Foggy weather and rain had hampered the search for much of the
time, forcing searchers to cover the ground on foot, on horseback
and in four-wheel-drive vehicles while airplanes and helicopters
were grounded.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0061 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-04-90 2108EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Nicaragua 1stLd-Writethru   02-04 0724</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Nicaragua, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0676,0743</SECOND>
<HEAD>Businessmen Pray For Opposition Victory, But Prepare for
Sandinistas</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 10th pvs, `It's a ...' to RESTORE first reference to
Gurdian; picks up 11th pvs, `In recent...'
^By DORALISA PILARTE</NOTE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MANAGUA, Nicaragua (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Nicaraguan businessmen are rooting for
an opposition victory in elections Feb. 25, but they're also
bracing for six more years under the leftist Sandinistas.
   Foreign observers say the vote could go either way. But some
also say that even if the Sandinistas triumph, they will have to
make changes _ especially in their economic policies.
   If they win, the ``force of facts'' will compel the Sandinistas
to reverse their policies of central economic control and state
ownership of major enterprises, one Western European diplomat
observed.
   ``I see in some (Sandinista) commanders a very strong
realization that the private sector has to be strengthened ... and
that the relaunching of the economy here is impossible without its
natural market, which is the United States,'' said the diplomat,
who like others insisted on anonymity.
   Virtually all businessmen are pulling for the U.S.-backed
coalition of 14 parties, the National Opposition Union. The
coalition advocates free enterprise and a market economy but is
also promising social service improvements to woo the left.
   The coalition is dominated by big business but includes a wide
range of ideologies, from conservatives to communists.
   It has promised closer relations with the United States, which
imposed economic sanctions on Nicaragua shortly after the
Sandinistas, with close military ties to the Cubans and Soviets,
seized power in 1979. The United States also backs the Contra
rebels.
   If the opposition wins, it says prospects are good for
attracting $400 million in immediate U.S. investment to help the
war-battered economy. They say most of the money would be spent in
farming and related industries.
   Business leaders say things have to change even if the
Sandinistas win. They say the Sandinistas will have to delete
provisions from the Constitution like the one that says the state
is in charge of ``directing and planning the national economy.''
   ``It's a matter of the Sandinista Front projecting to the world
that it has changed its ideology,'' said Ramiro Gurdian, who is
president of the Agricultural Producers Union.
   In recent years, as the nation plunged deeper into crisis, the
Sandinistas loosened their grip over the economy.
   Gone are gasoline coupons and ration cards. Gone are government
inspectors who boarded buses to confiscate staples from peasants
reluctant to sell produce to the state.
   Critics say this is still not enough. Farmers must still sell at
least part of their crops to the government at a set price and
purchase such things as fertilizer from the state.
   ``They can't keep on like that. They just can't,'' said Gurdian.
``Communism is finished. Everywhere in the world, people are
turning to the free market system. It's only these gentlemen who
insist on continuing to control everything.''
   The Sandinistas imposed an an austerity program to reduce
inflation of 33,600 percent in 1988. But inflation was 1,689
percent last year.
   President Daniel Ortega, who is seeking re-election, said last
week that exports rose from $230 million in 1988 to $298 million
last year and imports dropped from $807 million to $711 million.
   But Nicaragua's currency, the cordoba, had to be devalued 36
times in 1989.
   ``This economy is like a very sick patient, a vegetable that's
kept alive purely through tubes,'' said Gilberto Cuadra, president
of the Superior Council of Private Enterprise, Nicaragua's leading
business group.
   Unlike Gurdian, Cuadra doesn't think he could deal with the
Sandinistas in power until 1996, comparing it to ``a marriage
between a dead person and a live one.''
   ``It just doesn't work,'' he added, saying the Sandinistas have
lost their confidence. ``We have nothing more to do. If things
don't change, it's not worthwhile to keep producing.''
   Business leaders still remember the many coffee farms the
Sandinistas confiscated, some as recently as last year. Many
businessmen say the seizures were acts of vengeance against
Sandinista opponents.
   More recently, the president, in a speech at a political rally,
threatened to confiscate a cooking oil factory managed by the
son-in-law of opposition presidential candidate Violeta Barrios de
Chamorro.
   ``Even if the (Sandinista) Front wins crystal-clear elections,
it still won't attract the trust of foreign investors,'' one Latin
American diplomat said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0062 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-04-90 2116EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Tutu-Harvard     02-04 0423</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Tutu-Harvard,0437</SECOND>
<HEAD>Archbishop Desmond Tutu Appeals To Harvard to Divest</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-South Africa</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CAMBRIDGE, Mass. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Archbishop Desmond Tutu urged fellow
members of a Harvard University governing board Sunday to back
divestment in South Africa until changes promised by that country's
president become reality.
   In a news conference following a closed-door meeting of the
Board of Overseers, Tutu said that much of what South African
President F.W. de Klerk said last week was a declaration of purpose.
   ``Sanctions should remain in place until certain conditions are
met,'' Tutu said.
   In last week's speech, de Klerk promised to free jailed African
National Congress leader Nelson Mandela and lift government bans on
30 outlawed opposition groups.
   Tutu, who won the 1984 Nobel Peace Prize for his anti-apartheid
efforts, welcomed the announcement but tempered his response with
pragmatism.
   ``We'd like to see these things immediately but let's be
realistic. The parliamentary session has just begun,'' the Anglican
archbishop said.
   Tutu said he had asked colleagues on the 30-member Board of
Overseers to press Harvard to withdraw $139 million in investments
in South African companies until Mandela is freed, all exiled
political activists are granted amnesty and the government's policy
of segregation is dismantled.
   The board planned to further consider the divestment issue at a
future meeting.
   The board is less powerful than the university's main governing
body, the Harvard Corp., but is the only alumni-elected panel with
an influence on school policy. The board plays no role in
day-to-day business, but must give formal consent to major
initiaitves and appointments.
   Tutu, who ran for the board on an anti-apartheid slate, was
elected last June along with U.S. Labor Secretary Elizabeth Dole
and actor John Lithgow.
   The archbishop said de Klerk's action last week was sparked by
the growing number of countries that had placed sanctions on South
Africa, a position Tutu said seemed to be catching on among fellow
board members.
   He said he was encouraged by the attention South Africa had
received in the United States amid the historic changes in the
Soviet bloc.
   ``The kind of coverage and response is indicative that, in spite
of what has happened in Eastern Europe, which pushed our case to
the back burner, people here do want to see our situation
resolved,'' he said.
   Asked why he was in Massachusetts rather than South Africa at
such a critical time, Tutu replied, ``Harvard is Harvard. The
things that Harvard does and does not do have an impact far beyond
what you would expect from an educational institution.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0063 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-04-90 2116EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-China-Satellite     02-04 0212</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-China-Satellite,0217</SECOND>
<HEAD>China Launches Telecommunications Satellite</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   China on Sunday evening launched its fifth
telecommunications satellite from the Xichang space center in the
southwestern province of Sichuan, the official Xinhua News Agency
reported.
   The satellite, launched by a Long March 3 rocket, was moving
into its designated orbit and all instruments were functioning
normally, the report said.
   Premier Li Peng, army Chief of Staff Chi Haotian and Central
Military Commission Vice Chairman Liu Huaqing watched the blastoff
either from Xichang or on a monitoring screen at the Beijing
Command Center, the news agency said.
   Like all previous launches, it was not announced publicly
beforehand. It was the 26th launch to put a satellite into space
since China's space program began in 1970.
   Xinhua said the launch ``proves once again that China's
telecommunications satellite technology is mature enough to provide
launching services for the international market.''
   China, which is aggressively promoting its services, in April is
scheduled to put into orbit its first non-Chinese satellite,
AsiaSat, an American-made communications satellite owned by a Hong
Kong-based company.
   That launch was jeopardized by U.S. economic sanctions imposed
after China's crackdown on the pro-democracy movement in June, but
President Bush in December agreed to waive the ban on exporting the
satellite to China.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0064 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-04-90 2208EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-NewAgeCommunity     02-04 0478</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-New Age Community,0492</SECOND>
<HEAD>New Age Community Planned in Hill Country</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DRIFTWOOD, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Texan and his partners want to create
a New Age-style community called the City of Immortals and based on
ideas by Maharishi Mahesh Yogi, leader of the Transcendental
Meditation movement.
   What is now a rustic 250-acre patch of Hill Country would be the
first of what the Maharishi and his followers envision as a
worldwide movement to fashion largely self-contained residential
areas free of crime, pollution _ and anxiety.
   The Maharishi, whose students have included the Beatles,
popularized Transcendental Meditation in the 1960s.
   Construction of the first of 100 homes in the City of Immortals
could begin as early as spring, said Walter Reifslager of Charter
Development Group.
   The homes will be built with essentially toxic-free materials
and gasoline-powered cars will have to be parked on the outskirts
of the community, the Austin man said. There is talk of a
Maharishi-style theme park.
   Homes would cost between $200,000 and the ``seven-figure
range,'' Reifslager said.
   ``We had a concept, and then we heard about the (Maharishi's)
Heaven on Earth approach,'' Reifslager said in a recent interview.
``It so epitomized what we had been thinking about doing ... That's
when we decided to pursue building a Heaven on Earth project.''
   The proposed development between Driftwood and Oak Hill about 30
miles southwest of downtown Austin has raised concerns in this
quiet region.
   ``I can tell you, frankly, that there are people in this
community who are adamant in opposition to these people,'' said
Rev. Joel C. Thielepape, pastor of the nearby Friendship Baptist
Church. ``They feel there is something to be feared by this
development.''
   Thielepape said he has no major problems with the development,
partly because the rural county has been exposed already to
disciples of Transcendental Meditation. A nearby subdivision known
as Radiance was developed several years ago by Transcendental
Meditation practitioners.
   Last December a plan to create a City of Immortals west of
Tulsa, Okla., drew the attention of such groups as the Oklahoma
Cult Awareness Network.
   An unidentified network spokesman told the Dallas Morning News
he was worried that the Maharishi's group is organized along the
same lines as many destructive cults, a claim hotly denied by
Transcendental Meditation backers.
   Reifslager said he and his associates have already interviewed
potential home buyers and that one home has already been designed.
   He said the project is not being marketed strictly to those who
practice Transcendental Meditation, and that no one in the
community will be compelled to practice it.
   The Hill Country is not the only proposed site for
Maharishi-style communities.
   Curtis McDonald, vice president of Heaven on Earth Development
Corp. based in Malibu, Calif., said his company has been working to
locate communities near Houston, Denver, San Francisco, Los
Angeles, San Diego, Washington, D.C.; Toronto and in southeastern
Iowa.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0065 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-04-90 2215EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p AM-YoungAnnouncement     02-04 0290</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Young Announcement,0298</SECOND>
<HEAD>Former Atlanta Mayor To Announce For Governor Monday</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ATLANTA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Former Atlanta Mayor Andrew Young plans to
announce his candidacy for governor of Georgia Monday night, and
said he hopes to win the nomination outright in the primary.
   ``My campaign folk get upset when I say this, but I don't want a
runoff,'' Young told a meeting of the Southside Public Officials
last week, when he revealed his plans to make a formal announcement.
   Young, who is trying to become the state's first black governor,
shares the lead with four-term Lt. Gov. Zell Miller in some
Democratic polls. The race also includes state Sen. Roy E. Barnes
and state Rep. Lauren W. McDonald Jr., who is backed by powerful
House Speaker Tom Murphy and former Gov. Lester Maddox.
   The number of hopefuls in the field likely will make it very
difficult for any candidate to get the 50 percent plus one vote
needed to win the primary outright, said Robert S. Kahn, Barnes'
campaign manager.
   The primary is set for July 17, and a runoff would be held Aug.
7.
   Young has been raising campaign money, without making a formal
announcement.
   ``Fire in the belly, I think, stems from raw ambition,'' he said
in an interview. ``I don't have that. My ambition is to serve, and
I have been driven to serve because that's what makes life
worthwhile.''
   Young said he plans to start the campaign immediately, touring
the state in a van. Campaign workers had planned a flying tour, but
Young rejected it.
   ``They started talking about a tarmac-to-tarmac,'' Young said.
``That's not me. We have to go meet with people.''
   Last fall, Virginia made L. Douglas Wilder the first black ever
elected governor.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0066 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-04-90 2219EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Israel-AttackSurvivors     02-04 0494</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel-Attack Survivors,0508</SECOND>
<HEAD>Survivors Describe Helplessness, Terror During Bus Attack</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Israel-Bus Attack</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Survivors of the deadly attack Sunday on a bus
carrying Israeli tourists in the Egyptian desert described the
terror of being trapped in the vehicle with nowhere to run.
   ``The vehicle became like hell at once, there were shots from
every direction, grenades were thrown inside the bus and everything
was covered with smoke. Holes appeared in several places in the
bus,'' said Dr. Yigal Barak, one of 31 Israelis on board.
   At least eight people were killed and 17 wounded when two masked
men fired machine guns and hurled hand grenades at the bus near
Ismailiya, a city on the Suez Canal 40 miles east of Cairo, an
Egyptian government statement said.
   ``Everyone saw his death in front of his eyes,'' said Barak,
speaking on army radio in a telephone interview from an Ismailiya
hospital. He was not injured.
   ``It seemed like an eternity, but in fact it lasted for several
minutes only. Then there was a total quiet, and only screams were
heard. Bodies were scattered everywhere,'' he said.
   The bus' passengers included a group of doctors and some
officials of Egypt's Tourism Ministry. It was traveling to Cairo
from Rafah, a divided town on the Egyptian-Israeli border in the
Sinai Peninsula.
   Army radio's correspondent in Cairo quoted another survivor,
Miriam Kadmon, as saying the driver of the car signaled to the bus
to stop.
   The guerrillas then smashed the car's rear window and opened
fire. An Egyptian, screaming, jumped off the bus and was shot, she
was quoted as saying.
   Ms. Kadmon said the two men got out of the car, continuing to
fire at the bus and also threw hand grenades at it, army radio
reported.
   Barak said he could not see the attackers but could hear both
firing from outside and from the open doors of the bus.
   ``Several people jumped out and and I'm afraid they were either
wounded or killed,'' Barak said. ``There was a terrible fear and
the feeling of helplessness. Nobody could protect us, nobody
carried any weapons.''
   Barak said Egyptian motorists who passed the scene refused to
stop and a group of police officers and soldiers who arrived later
were afraid to approach the bus, ``because there were several live
grenades around it.''
   Late Sunday, Israel sent a Hercules plane with a medical team
aboard to Cairo to evacuate the victims, the army said.
   Three survivors _ Ms. Kadmon, and Dr. Michael Cooper and his
wife _ returned to Israel early Monday on an El Al Israel airlines
flight from Cairo, but airport police prevented reporters from
speaking with them. The women were not hurt but Cooper suffered a
shrapnel wound to the eye.
   An anonymous caller speaking to a Western news agency in Cairo
claimed responsibility for the attack on behalf of the Organization
for the Defense of Oppressed in Egyptian Prisons, a previously
unknown group.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0067 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-04-90 2225EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-IRS-Scientologists     02-04 0452</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-IRS-Scientologists,0466</SECOND>
<HEAD>IRS Again Investigating Scientologists</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CLEARWATER, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Internal Revenue Service is taking
on the Church of Scientology in federal court, contending that its
worldwide spiritual headquarters in Clearwater is a business and
should be paying taxes.
   Scientologists vehemently disagree, calling the IRS corrupt and
accusing it of pursuing a vendetta against Scientology.
   ``We feel the federal government should investigate illegal drug
running in Florida and should investigate money laundering in
Florida banks,'' spokesman Humberto Fontana told the St. Petersburg
Times in a story published Sunday.
   The Clearwater group pays no Pinellas County property taxes on
its church buildings, and has paid income taxes only once.
Scientologists also are in court with Pinellas County over the
organization's tax-exempt status.
   The federal government has asked for 47 categories of documents
for 1985, 1986 and 1987 that the Scientologists say would number
more than 50,000 pages.
   The Scientologists refused, but did agree to explain some
aspects of their financing in response to specific questions from
the IRS. That material has entered the public file in U.S. District
Court in Tampa.
   A similar case involving the Church of Scientology of California
took 18 years to resolve after the U.S. Supreme Court refused to
hear a Scientology appeal.
   The Clearwater Scientology branch has been secretive about its
finances. But the case has prompted it to disclose for the first
time that their organization pays annual operating expenses of $26
million.
   It said it sends millions of dollars each year to Scientology
organizations elsewhere, including $14.5 million for literature and
supplies, $4.5 million for ``dissemination and expansion,'' $2.4
million for ``advanced technology,'' and $1.3 million for films,
all in 1987, the last year for which the Scientologists provided
figures.
   The Clearwater branch said it pools reserve accounts with more
than 100 other Scientology organizations. The pool in 1987 had
assets of $206 million, liabilities of $165.6 million and a net
worth of $40.4 million.
   According to the new court documents, the Clearwater base has a
staff of 700 to 1,100.
   Scientology began with L. Ron Hubbard, an energetic writer with
flaming red hair who was known for his rollicking Western tales and
fanciful science-fiction stories. In the early 1950s, Hubbard began
writing about a religion that he named Scientology.
   He spread the word about the benefits of ``auditing,'' a sort of
counseling process that involves a device called an E-meter and
thousands of dollars in auditing fees.
   Court records reveal that non-staff Scientologists who persuade
someone to undergo auditing can receive 10 percent of the auditing
fee. Those who persuade someone to take religious training can
receive 15 percent of the course fee.
   In 1987, the Clearwater organization paid commissions of $14.6
million.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0068 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-04-90 2249EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-HomosexualEpithet     02-04 0339</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Homosexual Epithet,0351</SECOND>
<HEAD>Candidate Says He Didn't Know Use of Homosexual Epithet Was
Offensive</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Some readers may find material offensive.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>ANAHEIM, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A California assemblyman who called a
group of homosexual protesters ``faggots'' said he was unaware that
the term was offensive but still refuses to apologize.
   ``I didn't even know that faggot was a derogatory term ...
that's what I've always heard them called. I know that people don't
call them queers any more,'' Assemblyman Gil Ferguson said Saturday.
   ``I won't call them gay, though,'' Ferguson said. ``I don't
think there's anything gay about it. It's depressing.''
   Ferguson, a Republican running for the state Senate, was
picketed by a homosexual rights group earlier in the day during a
campaign appearance in this Orange County community.
   ``I don't care about them,'' Ferguson told reporters. ``I'm a
retired Marine. A couple of faggots out there aren't going to scare
me.''
   Ferguson is running in a special election Tuesday in a heavily
Republican state Senate District, which is split between Los
Angeles and Orange counties.
   He was picketed during an appearance at the Power Community
Church with the Rev. Louis B. Sheldon, who strongly backed
anti-homosexual measures on several city ballots last November.
   Ferguson later said he meant no harm but would not ``back down''
from the comment.
   ``I have learned since this morning that they have style manuals
about etiquette and what you're supposed to call people,'' Ferguson
said. ``I could have called them sodomites.''
   Some of Ferguson's seven opponents attacked his remarks.
   ``That's awful,'' Democrat Janice Graham said.
   ``I might think gays are wrong, but to try to publicly demean
them by using words like `faggots' or `queers.' I think Mr.
Ferguson should have stopped and thought about that,'' said Diamond
Bar City Councilman Gary Miller, a Republican.
   During last year's Republican state convention, Ferguson wrote a
resolution calling on the party to ban clubs based on sexual
orientation. It was rejected by state Republican leaders, including
U.S. Sen. Pete Wilson and Gov. George Deukmejian.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0069 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-04-90 2303EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ReaganAward     02-04 0246</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Reagan Award,0252</SECOND>
<HEAD>Reagan Accepts Award At House of Hope</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ORLANDO, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Former President Reagan praised the House
of Hope for its work with troubled girls and received its first
humanitarian award at a fund-raising banquet Sunday night.
   In presenting the award, shelter founder Sara Trollinger
recounted the Reagans' involvement in the House of Hope.
   While visiting Orlando in 1985, Reagan read an article about the
non-profit shelter, which receives no government money, and sent
the home a personal check for $1,000.
   In September 1987, he presented it with a certificate of
appreciation in promoting children's safety and in 1988 he recorded
a three-minute videotape ``challenging citizens to look to the
House of Hope as a model'' for homes for troubled teen-agers across
the nation.
   Trollinger founded the shelter in May 1985 with just $200. She
started asking for grants and bought the home's current site with a
grant from the Philip Crosby Foundation.
   Crosby underwrote Sunday's banquet so that all the proceeds of
the $300-a-plate dinner attended by 700 people will go to the House
of Hope.
   The shelter, which now houses 19 girls ages 12 to 17, provides a
home and a Christian education. The girls must be willing to give
up alcohol, drugs, rock music and their peers to begin a Christian
life which includes counseling and discipline, Trollinger said.
   ``If I ever saw anyone put by God on this Earth for a purpose it
was Sara Trollinger,'' Reagan said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0070 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-04-90 2316EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ComputerExtortion     02-04 0371</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Computer Extortion,0383</SECOND>
<HEAD>Man Accused of Computer Extortion Says He Was Set Up</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CLEVELAND (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An international consultant arrested by the FBI
on computer extortion charges said he may have been set up by the
United Nations agency he worked for.
   Joseph L. Popp Jr., an anthropologist from suburban Willowick,
told his attorney on Saturday he was working with the backing of
World Health Organization officials who may have set him up as a
``fall guy,'' the lawyer said.
   WHO spokesman Thomas W. Netter said from the U.N. agency's
Geneva headquarters Sunday that the accusation that WHO was
involved in the scheme ``is totally and completely false.''
   Netter said he did not know whether Popp had ever worked for WHO.
   Popp, 39, was arrested Thursday on a federal fugitive warrant
stemming from charges by Britain's Scotland Yard.
   He is charged with mailing 20,000 to 26,000 computer disks
ostensibly providing information about AIDS but actually containing
a ``virus'' program that prevented computers from accessing other
information. The disks were sent to businesses, hospitals and
church organizations, including the Vatican.
   The program ended with a message telling users to send up to
$378 to the Panama post office box of PC Cyborg Corp. for a second
disk making the computer usable again, federal officials said.
   Popp's attorney, John P. Kilroy, said his client told him that
he did not set up PC Cyborg Corp.
   In a statement released through Kilroy, Popp said, ``The sole
reason for the project was to use computers to provide health
education to people around the world to fight the global epidemic
of AIDS. I never made a penny off of this, and I never intended
to.''
   Popp provided AIDS education in Africa under contract with the
WHO, Kilroy said.
   Popp has never been director, shareholder or an employee of PC
Cyborg, Kilroy said, and had no financial interest in the company.
   Kilroy said Popp told him that Cyborg directors are WHO
officials and that some of them have used aliases, apparently to
prevent the project's being traced to them should it fail.
   ``He's certain they're going to deny any knowledge or
participation,'' Kilroy added.
   Popp is being held without bond at the Justice Center in
Cleveland.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0071 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-04-90 1852EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f BC-Earns-Pittston     02-04 0275</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Earns-Pittston,0286</SECOND>
<HEAD>Pittston Co. Reports Fourth Quarter Loss of $18.8 Million</HEAD>
<DATELINE>GREENWICH, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Pittston Co., citing costs of a
settlement of a nine-month strike at its coal division by the
United Mine Workers, reported a fourth-quarter loss of $18.8
million.
   The loss, which amounted to 50 cents a share, compared with net
income of $15.2 million or 40 cents a share a year earlier,
Pittston said. Revenues fell to $404 million in the quarter from
$413 million a year earlier.
   The fourth-quarter results include $16.2 million worth of
special charges, most of which were related to the company's coal
business, Pittston Chairman Paul W. Douglas said Saturday.
   The charge covers costs related to the labor settlement, a
return to normal working operations, some writedowns of coal
assets, the anticipation of losses on certain coal sales contracts
and a reserve for unrelated litigation.
   Douglas said Pittston's coal activities reported a fourth
quarter operating loss of $25.2 million, including the special
charges.
   About 1,500 coal miners who had been working without a contract
for 14 months went on strike at Pittston mines in Virginia and West
Virginia in April.
   After negotiations overseen by federal mediators, the company
and UMW officials reached a tentative contract agreement on Jan. 1.
The agreement has yet to be ratified by UMW members.
   For all of 1989, Pittston's net income fell 92 percent to $3.8
million, or 10 cents a share, from $48.6 million, or $1.26 a share,
in 1988. Revenues rose to $1.63 billion from $1.58 billion.
   Pittston is the parent company of Burlington Air Express and the
Brink's security companies, as well as Pittston Coal Group.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900204-0072 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-04-90 1956EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f BC-PanAm-Teamsters     02-04 0227</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Pan Am-Teamsters,0234</SECOND>
<HEAD>Pan Am Hinting at Possible Deal with Northwest, Union Official
Says</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Pan American World Airways is indicating that it
may announce a deal with Northwest Airlines, the subject of a
bidding war that Pan Am lost to investor Alfred Checchi last year,
a union official said.
   William F. Genoese, director of the Teamsters airline division,
said Pan Am management had leaked word that a major announcement _
probably a deal with Northwest _ will come out of its board meeting
this Tuesday.
   In a statement over the weekend, Genoese said Pan Am's teamsters
will strike the carrier if workers' rights aren't protected in any
kind of merger. The union did not strike after Pan Am imposed a
contract settlement on the Teamsters in February 1988.
   Jeff Kriendler, a spokesman for Pan Am, said the airline's board
of directors had a regularly scheduled meeting on Tuesday, but he
said the company did not comment on topics before the board.
   Pan Am last year offered about $3.3 billion for NWA Inc.,
Northwest's parent, but was outbid by a $4 billion offer from a
group led by Checchi.
   Suffering from years of losses and a small domestic route base,
Pan Am has been looking for a merger partner as a possible solution
for some time and continues to do so, Kriendler said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
</Collection>
