<Collection>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0001 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 2324EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Germany-Election 8thLd-Writethru a0790 12-02 0771</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Germany-Election, 8th Ld-Writethru, a0790,0936</SECOND>
<HEAD>Kohl Wins All-German Elections; Communists, Greens Lose Much
Support</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 15 grafs to UPDATE with final count. Picks up 17th
graf pvs, `Lafontaine blames...</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos FRA2,102, HBG1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TERRENCE PETTY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BONN, Germany (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Chancellor Helmut Kohl's center-right
coalition on Sunday easily won the first free all-German elections
since 1932, buoyed by his popularity as the man who crafted swift
unification.
   In perhaps the biggest surprise, the Greens environmental party
of former West Germany, Europe's best-known ecology movement, lost
all their seats. Only the Greens' sister party in eastern Germany
won seats in the new parliament.
   The balloting capped a breathtaking transformation that began
with a revolt last year against East Germany's Communist government
and led to the merging of East and West Germany on Oct. 3.
   East Germany's former ruling Communist Party, now called the
Party for Democratic Socialism, won 17 seats in the new German
Parliament, but lost much of the support it had earlier this year,
according to final returns.
   A jubilant Kohl was greeted at his Christian Democrat party
headquarters by a throng of well-wishers.
   ``This is a day of great joy,'' he told them. ``This is a great
success and something to be proud of.''
   At the headquarters of the rival Social Democrats, the scene was
somber. ``We have lost the election,'' Kohl's rival Oskar
Lafontaine told his supporters.
   According to final results, Kohl's coalition - the Christian
Democrats, its Bavarian sister party and the Free Democrats - took
54.8 percent of the vote, compared to 33.5 percent for the Social
Democrats.
   Berlin, divided until just over a year ago by the Berlin Wall,
held its own united elections. Social Democrat Mayor Walter Momper
lost to his predecessor, conservative Eberhard Diepgen of Kohl's
party.
   The Christian Democrats and their Bavarian sister party, the
Christian Social Union, increased their parliamentary seats from
305 to 313. The Social Democrats, who had 226 seats before the
vote, captured 239.
   Along with Kohl, Foreign Minister Hans-Dietrich Genscher was
among the big victors. Genscher's Free Democrats, Kohl's junior
coalition partner, will increase their representation from 57 to 79
seats in the 656-seat Parliament. They gained 11 percent of the
vote.
   The Free Democrats and Kohl's party have already said they would
form a new coalition if Kohl won.
   The poor showing of the Greens was one of the biggest election
surprises. Final returns said the Greens across Germany lost all
but eight of their 48 parliamentary seats. In the former West
Germany, they garnered only about 4.8 percent of the national vote,
less than the 5 percent needed for parliamentary representation.
That means the Greens' main leaders will be excluded from
Parliament.
   The Greens' sister branch in former East Germany won about 7
percent of the vote. Under one-time special election laws, small
parties in former East Germany can enter Parliament by chalking up
at least 5 percent on their home turf.
   In West Germany's 1987 federal elections, the Greens won 8.3
percent.
   The Greens, who initially resisted swift German unification,
were one of Europe's first ecology groups whose disarmament
policies brought them support and seats in the federal parliament
in the 1980s.
   But the Greens became rebels without a cause when mainstream
parties embraced ecology as their own theme and disarmament accords
began removing nuclear missiles from Germany.
   The election results include all the votes, but the official
count will be approved later this week.
   Lafontaine blamed his Social Democrats' loss on Kohl's ability
to capitalize on the tumultuous events that began with East
Germany's peaceful revolution in October 1989 and led to
unification.
   ``There were official events which gave the stage to the
government and gave the opposition difficulties in articulating its
program,'' he said.
   Germany last voted freely as one nation in November 1932. Two
months later, Hitler was named chancellor and soon drove through
laws depriving non-Nazis of their seats in parliament. Hitler's
designs triggered World War II, which laid waste to Europe and
carved two ideologically opposed German nations out of one.
   Kohl automatically became the leader of all Germany when the two
states merged on Oct. 3.
   Even as Germans looked to a united future, the election was
shadowed by a reminder of a dark past. Officials were seeking entry
to a Soviet military hospital near Berlin to arrest former East
German leader Erich Honecker.
   Honecker, 78, is accused of personally issuing shoot-to-kill
orders to prevent people from fleeing the Communist state he ruled
with an iron hand for 18 years before being swept from power in
October 1989. A warrant for his arrest was issued on Friday.
   The ARD network said the Social Democrats were badly defeated in
former East Germany, where they won 25 percent of the vote to 57
percent for Kohl's coalition.
   East Germany's former Communists won less than 1 percent of the
vote in western Germany and 9.5 percent in former East Germany.
   In Berlin, last month's street battles between police and
squatters had caused the collapse of the leftist municipal
government, strengthening the conservatives' hand.
   The Christian Democrats, led by Diepgen, had played on voters'
fears of growing lawlessness to triumph on Sunday. They were
projected to win 40.1 percent of the vote. Diepgen said it was
possible his party would form a ``grand coalition'' with the Social
Democrats, led by Momper, who was projected to win 30.3 percent of
the votes, according to the ZDF network.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0002 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 2330EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Germany-Greens 1stLd-Writethru a0737 12-02 0435</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Germany-Greens, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0737,0500</SECOND>
<HEAD>Greens: The End of an Era</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 8 grafs to UPDATE with final results. Picks up 9th
graf pvs, `Pre-election polls ...</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   '
</TEXT>
<HEAD>With AM-Germany-Election, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By NESHA STARCEVIC</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>FRANKFURT, Germany (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Greens of former West Germany, who
gained prominence in the 1980s with ecological and anti-nuclear
causes, were kicked out of the all-German parliament in Sunday's
election.
   Their sister party in former East Germany, running together with
Alliance 90, gained eight seats in the new, 656-member Parliament,
according to final results. Hubert Kleinert, Greens leader in the
outgoing parliament, described the outcome as a ``debacle.''
   ``It's a heavy defeat, and we all must ask ourselves why this is
hapenning,'' he said.
   The Greens, who initially resisted swift German unification,
were one of Europe's first ecology groups whose disarmament
policies brought them support and seats in the federal parliament
in the 1980s. They won 48 seats in the 1987 election.
   But the Greens became rebels without a cause when mainstream
parties embraced ecology as their own theme and disarmament accords
began removing nuclear missiles from Germany.
   ``Our themes interest barely anyone,'' said Greens leader
Christian Stroebele in a first reaction to the ballot results.
   The Greens in western Germany received less than 5 percent of
the vote, the minimum needed to get into the federal legislature.
   The Greens-Alliance 90 list in eastern Germany took 7 percent.
The Alliance includes many prominent members of the pro-democracy
movement that helped topple the former East German Communist
government last year.
   Pre-election polls a few days before the ballot were still
predicting that the Greens would win about 9 percent of the vote.
They got 8.3 percent in 1987.
   Describing the party's campaign as ``amateurish,'' Kleinert
said, ``The party must fundamentally change if we are still to
remain a party in the future.''
   Stroebele said the Greens will have a chance again once the
``euphoria'' of German unification dies down.
   ``There is still a place for the Greens, we must see what
mistakes we made, what we must change,'' he said.
   Rooted in the student movement of 1968, the anti-NATO Greens
mobilized hundreds of thousands of West Germans in massive
anti-nuclear protests in the 1980s. They first got into the federal
parliament in 1983, shocking the political establishment.
   But the Greens leaders later became entangled in bickering about
the party's course, with one wing favoring a more traditional
approach to politics while the other wanted the group to stay true
to its roots.
   Several prominent Greens defected to other parties, while all
mainstream parties embraced the environment as a major theme.
   Under U.S.-Soviet agreements, nuclear missiles began being
pulled out of Germany, leaving the Greens without one of their most
popular campaign themes.
   The Greens also resisted quick German unification and were the
only party that voted against the state treaty this summer that
paved the way for unification.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0003 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 2332EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-PlaneCrash     12-02 0256</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Plane Crash,0288</SECOND>
<HEAD>Head of Canadian Company, Four Others Dead in Plane</HEAD>
<DATELINE>RYDERWOOD, Wash. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The head of a leading logging equipment
company and four other Canadians died in a plane crash in a forest
near this southwest Washington town, officials said Sunday.
   The plane was flying from Nanaimo, British Columbia, to Kelso on
a business trip Friday night for S. Madill Co., said company
spokesman Steve Shaw. He described Madill as a leading manufacturer
of heavy-duty logging equipment.
   Killed in the crash were company President Pat Madill, 42; his
stepdaughter, Leanne Johnson, 19; her boyfriend, Ralph Pomphrey,
20; company pilot Bill Anderson, and his wife Marlene Anderson, all
of the Nanaimo, British Columbia area in Canada, Shaw said.
   Hunters found the lone survivor - Madill's wife, 42-year-old
Kathy Madill - walking in the woods Sunday morning, nearly 38 hours
after the accident happened, said Brian Holmes of the Washington
state Aeronautics Division.
   Mrs. Madill was hospitalized and listed in fair condition with a
broken collarbone, hypothermia and shock Sunday afternoon.
   The company plane, a 10-seater Aero Commander 690, crashed into
a forested ridge west of Ryderwood, about 60 miles north of
Portland, Ore., about 7 p.m. Friday, Holmes said.
   The group was headed to Kalama where Madill has a manufacturing
plant, Shaw said.
   ``It's our plant in the states,'' Shaw said. ``We flew down two
or three times a month, at least.''
   The firm, established in 1911, employs 100 people in Nanaimo and
20 in Kalama, he said.
   Shaw said he began notifying airports and search and rescue
teams Saturday afternoon when officials at the Kalama plant called
to ask about the whereabouts of the company officials.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0004 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 2341EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Germany-Communists 3rdLd-Writethru a0791 12-02 0379</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Germany-Communists, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0791,0447</SECOND>
<HEAD>East German Communists Cling to Parliament</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 9 grafs to UPDATE with final count. Picks up 11th
graf pvs, `A recent ...'</NOTE>
<HEAD>With AM-Germany-Election, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARK FRITZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   East Germany's former Communists managed to win
seats in the united German Parliament on Sunday, but they lost much
of their remaining support in a nation they once ruled.
   The Party of Democratic Socialism, the renamed version of the
party that controlled East Germany for four decades, won 17 seats
in Parliament, according to final results.
   It attracted less than 1 percent of the vote in western Germany,
and more than 9 percent in eastern Germany, according to the
traditionally reliable poll projections.
   That was a sharp drop from the 16.4 percent the party earned in
March, when East Germany held its first free elections and chose
the democratic government that led the nation to unity with West
Germany on Oct. 3.
   Party leader Gregor Gysi put an optimistic spin on the results,
noting that the Communists were strong enough to get into
Parliament. He said they laid a foundation on which to build
support in the West.
   ``It's not so much the quantity, but the quality,'' of support,
he said. ``One now chooses us as the leftist democratic
alternative.''
   The party also captured 9.3 percent of the vote in the Berlin
elections, making it the third-biggest party in the city's
legislature, according to projections from Germany's ARD television
network.
   The party was represented in the all-German parliament formed
out of the legislatures of the two Germanys immediately after
unity. It was apportioned 24 seats based on its level of support in
the east.
   Ironically, Gysi's party did better in eastern Germany than the
party containing many of the pro-democracy activists that toppled
the Communists in last autumn's peaceful revolt. The Buendnis
90-Greens coalition captured about 7 percent of the vote to gain
eight seats.
   A recent political scandal might have had an effect on the
former Communists' drop in support since last March.
   The Communists are widely believed to still control millions,
perhaps billions of dollars in property and cash accumulated during
their 40 years in power.
   A former party official faces charges he tried to hide more than
$680,000 in party assets.
   Berlin's top law enforcement officer, Interior senator Erich
Paetzold, said last week that the party still illegally holds more
than $68 million in bank accounts.
   Gysi has denied the party is hiding its assets and said he is
not aware of attempts by officials to move money out of the
country.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0005 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 2352EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-SchoolShooting     12-02 0225</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-School Shooting,0256</SECOND>
<HEAD>Two Dead, Three Wounded in Shooting at Vancouver-Area High School</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DELTA, British Columbia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A gunman opened fire with a
semiautomatic rifle during an Indo-Canadian cultural event at a
high school, killing two men and wounding three others, police said
Sunday.
   Police Cpl. Rick Franson said an all-points bulletin had been
issued for a suspect last seen in a 1989 grey Chevrolet Astro van.
A second man also was sought for questioning.
   The man in the van fled after 10 to 15 shots were fired just
before midnight Saturday in a high school auditorium in this
Vancouver suburb, about 10 miles north of the U.S. border, Franson
said.
   ``All I know is it was a high-powered semiautomatic rifle,'' he
said.
   A handgun was found at the scene, but the rifle remained
missing, Franson said.
   Authorities identified the dead men as Baljinder Gill, 26, of
Vancouver, and Jasbinder Khak, 27, of Richmond, another Vancouver
suburb.
   Of the three people wounded, two were listed in stable condition
Sunday, and a the third was released after being treated for a
superficial gunshot wound.
   Gunfire erupted after the end of the event, attended by about
400 people at the North Delta secondary school, Franson said.
   ``It didn't sound like gunshots,'' said a woman who was in the
auditorium at the time. ``It sounded like someone banging on the
door.''
   Police believe the gunman may have fired five shots outside the
auditorium and 10 shots inside, Burns said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0006 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 2357EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a BC-LOT--SaturdayLotterie     12-02 0714</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-LOT--Saturday Lotteries,0896</SECOND>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<HEAD>ARIZONA</HEAD>
<HEAD>Pick</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PHOENIX (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers in Saturday night's drawing
of the Arizona Lottery's Pick game were 5, 11, 16, 24, 36 and 38,
with a bonus number of 30.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>CALIFORNIA</HEAD>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SACRAMENTO, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers picked
Saturday night for the California Lottery's twice-weekly ``Lotto
6-53'' game: 2, 40, 28, 35, 50, 44, and the bonus number, 53.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>COLORADO</HEAD>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DENVER (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the six numbers selected Saturday night
in this week's Lotto drawing:
   21, 22, 24, 17, 9 10
</TEXT>
<HEAD>CONNECTICUT</HEAD>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEWINGTON, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning combination picked Saturday
in the Connecticut State Lottery's ``Daily Lottery'' drawing was:
   5-0-4
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Play 4</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEWINGTON, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning combination picked Saturday
in the Connecticut State Lottery's ``Play 4'' drawing was:
   4-5-4-5
</TEXT>
<HEAD>DELAWARE</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DOVER, Del. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   These Delaware lotteries were drawn Satuday
night:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   9-2-6
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Play Four</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   9-4-9-5
</TEXT>
<HEAD>DISTRICT OF COLUMBIA</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The following results were drawn Saturday in
the District of Columbia Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lucky Numbers Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   9-1-9
</TEXT>
<HEAD>D.C. Four Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   8-2-9-6
</TEXT>
<HEAD>D.C. Daily Double Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   7, 9
</TEXT>
<HEAD>D.C. Quick Cash Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   1-26-36-7-6-4
</TEXT>
<HEAD>FLORIDA</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected Saturday in
the Florida Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Cash 3</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   5-6-3
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   40-37-35-23-28-29
</TEXT>
<HEAD>INDIANA</HEAD>
<DATELINE>INDIANAPOLIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the Hoosier Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto Cash</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   1-14-20-22-23-34
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Three</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   7-1-1
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Four</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   9-3-7-7
</TEXT>
<HEAD>IOWA</HEAD>
<HEAD>Iowa Lotto</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DES MOINES, Iowa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers drawn Saturday night
in ``Iowa Lotto'' are:
   6-13-16-22-27-36.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto America</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DES MOINES, Iowa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers drawn Saturday night
in ``Lotto America'' are:
   17-23-26-33-42-50
</TEXT>
<HEAD>KANSAS</HEAD>
<HEAD>Kan. Keno</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOPEKA, Kan. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers in the Kansas Keno
drawing Saturday night:
   1-4-5-6-16-22-27-28-30-32-33-38-40-42-43-45-48-49-55-56
</TEXT>
<HEAD>KENTUCKY</HEAD>
<HEAD>Kentucky Lottery</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOUISVILLE, Ky. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are Saturday's winning numbers
selected by the Kentucky Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Kentucky Cash:</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   8-5-0.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto:
   9-13-30-33-34-42
   </HEAD>
<HEAD>MARYLAND</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BALTIMORE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   These Maryland lotteries were drawn Saturday
night:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   5-8-5
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Play Four</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   0-4-3-0
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   1-17-18-28-44-48
</TEXT>
<HEAD>MICHIGAN</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DETROIT (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected Saturday in
the Michigan State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   6-8-0
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily-4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   8-0-5-1
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto 47</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   6, 24, 25, 29, 40, 41)
</TEXT>
<HEAD>MINNESOTA</HEAD>
<HEAD>Daily 3</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MINNEAPOLIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers drawn Saturday night in
Minnesota's Daily 3 lottery game are:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>MISSOURI</HEAD>
<HEAD>Pick 3</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ST. LOUIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers in Saturday's Missouri
Lottery Daily Pick 3 game:
   4-8-2
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ST. LOUIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers in Missouri's Lotto drawing
Saturday night:
   4-11-18-21-43-48
</TEXT>
<HEAD>NEW JERSEY</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TRENTON, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday night in the New Jersey State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick three</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   7-5-4
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   8-6-2-3
</TEXT>
<HEAD>NEW YORK</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ALBANY, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the New York State Pick 10 Lottery:
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   3, 6, 8, 14, 19, 22, 26, 30, 33, 37, 39, 41, 46, 48, 55, 61, 63,
78, 79, 80.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>NORTHERN NEW ENGLAND</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CONCORD, N.H. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the daily New Hampshire, Vermont and Maine lotteries:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 3</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   5-8-8
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   6-5-9-2
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Tri-State Megabucks</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CONCORD, N.H. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers drawn Saturday
in the ``Tri-State Megabucks'' game for New Hampshire, Vermont and
Maine:
   2-6-27-33-34-35
</TEXT>
<HEAD>OHIO</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CLEVELAND (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the selections Saturday night in the
Ohio Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Super Lotto</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   10-25-31-36-38-53
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Kicker</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   3-4-8-5-0-9
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 3 Numbers</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   2-5-1
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 4 Numbers</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   8-0-2-5
</TEXT>
<HEAD>OREGON</HEAD>
<HEAD>Daily 4</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PORTLAND, Ore. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are Saturday's winning numbers in the
``Oregon Daily 4'' lottery game:
   4-3-7-2
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Megabucks</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PORTLAND, Ore. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are Saturday's winning numbers in the
``Oregon Megabucks'' lottery game:
   1-3-4-20-24-33
</TEXT>
<HEAD>PENNSYLVANIA</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HARRISBURG (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected Saturday
in the Pennsylvania State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Number</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   3-7-2
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Big 4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   1-1-0-0
</TEXT>
<HEAD>VIRGINIA</HEAD>
<HEAD>Pick 3</HEAD>
<DATELINE>RICHMOND (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   These numbers were drawn Saturday in the
Virginia Lottery's Pick 3 game:
   4-9-9
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<DATELINE>RICHMOND (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   These numbers were drawn Saturday in the
Virginia Lottery's Lotto game:
   4-19-20-23-25-39
</TEXT>
<HEAD>WEST VIRGINIA</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CHARLESTON, W.Va. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the West Virginia State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily 3</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   4-3-8
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily 4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   8-2-2-9
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0007 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 0035EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Salvador-Sabotage     12-02 0189</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Salvador-Sabotage,0194</SECOND>
<HEAD>Guerrillas Attack Two Hydroelectric Projects</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SAN SALVADOR, El Salvador (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Leftist guerrillas attacked the
country's two largest hydroelectric generators with mortar fire
Saturday, severely damaging one of the plants, the government said.
   No casualties were reported in either attack.
   A pre-dawn barrage caused an estimated $800,000 in damage to the
5 de Noviembre dam and its turbines, 50 miles northeast of San
Salvador, said Nelson Quijada, spokesman for the state electric
utility, CEL.
   An attack at about the same time on the Cerron Grande project,
13 miles southeast of the 5 de Noviembre dam and also on the Lempa
River, caused minor damage, according to a government communique.
   The 5 de Noviembre project normally generates about 13 percent
of the country's electricity. Its output was cut by half as a
result of the damage from the attack, CEL said. Repairs will take
several months, it said.
   Rebels of the Farabundo Marti National Liberation Front have
regularly attacked electrical lines and power plants in their
11-year-old war against a succession of U.S.-backed governments.
   With such sabotage the rebels wreak economic havoc and
discourage investment.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0008 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 0051EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-CaveSearch 3rdLd-Writethru a0630 12-02 0224</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Cave Search, 3rd Ld - Writethru, a0630,0247</SECOND>
<NOTE>EDS: LEADS with five grafs to UPDATE with spelunkers' names, fix
hospital to hospitals in third graf pvs, `They smiled...' DELETES
now outdated last graf.</NOTE>
<HEAD>Five People Trapped By Flood Waters
Emerge Unscathed From Cave</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN KEKIS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW SCOTLAND, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Three men and two women emerged wet,
shivering but happy late Saturday after being trapped in a cave or
about seven hours by a flash flood.
   The five spelunkers crawled out of Onesquethaw Cave under their
own power at 11:20 p.m. to the cheers of about 100 rescue workers
gathered around the cave's entrance.
   They smiled as rescue workers stripped off their wet clothes and
covered them with blankets. The five were taken to local hospitals
for observation, although officials at the scene said they appeared
healthy.
   ``It's a great feeling of relief. We lucked out. We won,'' said
Jeff Mudge, liaison fire officer for the Onesquethaw Volunteer Fire
Company. ``You don't know how good this feels.''
   Authorities identified the spelunkers as Laura Selicaro, 20;
Lynn Cowan, 22; Peter Bowie, 20; Scott Baisch, 22; and Nicholas
Springer, 20, all members of the Syracuse University Outing Club.
   They were trapped in the mile-long cave when a beaver dam
upstream of the cave's entrance burst at about 4:30 p.m. The cave
is about 10 miles southwest of Albany.
   Rescue squads had searched in vain before the explorers came out
on their own.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0009 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 0112EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-Philippines     12-02 0363</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Philippines,0442</SECOND>
<HEAD>Filipinos Tell Of Food, Medicine Shortages In Iraq and Kuwait</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By EILEEN GUERRERO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MANILA, Philippines (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Filipinos returning from Iraq and
occupied Kuwait told Sunday of long lines for food and of Iraqis
scavenging for scraps thrown away at the airport by departing
foreigners.
   Some of the 437 Filipinos, who arrived here on a flight from
Basra, Iraq, also said Iraqi soldiers were still looting groceries
and homes in occupied Kuwait.
   They said food prices in Baghdad had jumped ten-fold because of
the United Nations sanctions imposed following Iraq's Aug. 2
invasion of Kuwait.
   ``There's so much hunger there,'' Lorenza Panaranda, 30, said of
conditions in Basra, Iraq's second largest city. ``When we threw
away our leftovers, about 10 Iraqis scrambled over our leftovers in
the trashcan at the airport. We left whatever food we had with
them.''
   Gregorio Neri, an Arabic-speaking mechanic who acted as
interpreter for the group in Iraq, said consumers in Basra stand in
line for up to four hours to buy a single loaf of bread.
   ``The life of the Iraqis now is hard,'' he said. ``Filipino
lives may be difficult, but theirs is miserable. I would never
change places.''
   Willie Leola said that when his group, which included five
infants, cleared customs at Basra airport, customs guards asked for
their leftover baby formula.
   The Filipinos arrived aboard an Iraqi Airways jet on a flight
paid for by the International Organization of Migration.
   An estimated 90,000 Filipinos were working in Kuwait and Iraq
before the Iraqi invasion.
   Miss Panaranda, who had worked as a sales clerk in Kuwait, said
she went to Baghdad last month and then to Basra for the flight.
She said shoopers waited for hours to buy limited supplies of food
in Baghdad.
   ``There were queues for food all over,'' she said. ``Instead of
rice, they eat gruel made of corn.'' She said that in one
neighborhood, shoppers were limited to five kilos of rice per
month.
   Conchita Balisi, 27, a former governess in Kuwait, said most
groceries are closed in the occupied city.
   ``Some Kuwaitis go to Saudi Arabia to buy food and then sell it
back in Kuwait,'' she said.
   Lisa Santuyo, a maid in Kuwait, said Iraqi soldiers were looting
homes and shops of food, appliances and other goods to ship back to
Iraq.
   ``At night, there is shooting,'' she said. ``Families would then
pray as they wept. Soldiers go to houses and Kuwaitis are afraid,
especially if Iraqi soldiers find out they have relatives in the
army.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0010 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 0135EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ToddlersShot 1st-LdWritethru a0620 12-02 0209</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Toddlers Shot, 1st - Ld Writethru, a0620,0232</SECOND>
<HEAD>Twelve People Wounded in Drive-By Shooting at Family Gathering</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS lede to CORRECT number of wounded to 12; SUBS 4th graf
to
UPDATE with victim in fair condition. Pick up 5th graf pvs, `The
others...'</NOTE>
<DATELINE>INDUSTRY, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Gunmen firing from a passing car wounded
12 people, including children, when they shot into a group of
people leaving a family gathering, authorities said.
   An 18-month-old boy was hit in the face Friday night and may
lose an eye, Los Angeles County sheriff's Sgt. Bob Olmsted said
Saturday.
   Otherwise, the boy was in good condition at Covina
Intercommunity Medical Center.
   Mary Ann Lopez, 26, was in fair condition after undergoing
surgery for a stomach wound at Queen of the Valley Hospital in West
Covina.
   The others wounded were reported in good condition at various
hospitals.
   The victims had attended a family gathering in the
unincorporated community of Valinda and were in the front yard
saying their good-byes when a truck pulled up in front of the
house, said Deputy Roger Hom.
   Two of three people in the vehicle opened fire with handguns and
shotguns, and then the car sped off, Olmsted said. There were no
arrests.
   Hom said the shooting appeared to be gang-related, but it was
not known if any victims were gang members. The childrens' names
were not released.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0011 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 0336EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i BC-Israel-Attack 1stAdd a0643 12-02 0118</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Israel-Attack, 1st Add, a0643,0099</SECOND>
<HEAD>JERUSALEM: Etti Greenberg.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   She said three Palestinians boarded the bus at the intersection
of Jabotinsky and Modiin Streets in a shopping area of Bnei Brak,
whose residents are primarily ultra-orthodox Jews.
   One of the assailants was killed and two wounded by police fire,
she said.
   The four Israeli passengers were taken to Beilinson Hospital in
neighboring Petach Tikvah, Greenberg added. There was no immediate
word of their condition.
   In a leaflet issued over the weekend, leaders of the
three-year-old Palestinian uprising in the occupied territories had
declared Sunday a ``day of escalation'' against Israel.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0012 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 0431EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i BC-Soviet-Space 1stLd-Writethru a0645 12-02 0478</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Soviet-Space, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0645,0574</SECOND>
<HEAD>First Journalist is Launched Into Space</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Leads with 12 grafs to UPDATE with details, background; picks
up 10th graf, `The flight ...</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By THOMAS GINSBERG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BAIKONUR COSMODROME, U.S.S.R. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A sleek rocket thundered
into the sky over the Central Asian desert Sunday in a joint
Soviet-Japanese mission that carried the first journalist into
space.
   Smoke and tongues of flame engulfed the launch pad as the
150-foot rocket lifted off at 1:13 p.m. (3:13 a.m. EST), hurling
the Soyuz TM-11 capsule and its crew toward a rendezvous with the
Soviet space station Mir.
   Toyohiro Akiyama, the first journalist and first Japanese in
space, joined the mission led by Soviet Cmdr. Viktor Afanasyev and
flight engineer Musa Manarov.
   Japan's TBS television company paid the Soviets $12 million to
send Akiyama, a news director for the network, into space. They
took out $2.2 million in insurance on his life.
   ``All conditions normal,'' said an announcer who gave reports
every 10 seconds as the rocket soared into orbit in a flawless
launch.
   Akiyama was to describe the trip in live radio and television
broadcasts to Tokyo, and conduct sleep studies and experiments to
see how Japanese tree frogs cope in a gravity-free environment.
   Hundreds of foreign journalists watched the launch at the
once-secret Baikonur Cosmodrome, 1,250 miles east of Moscow.
   The space venture by TBS, Japan's biggest private television
company, is a watershed for the two countries, which never formally
ended their World War II hostilities and still dispute ownership of
some islands off the Japanese coast.
   ``If we continue our friendship, it would be good,'' cosmonaut
Afanasyev said at a news conference Saturday.
   Afanasyev and Manarov will replace two Soviet cosmonauts who
have been in the space station for the past four months. Afanasyev
and Manarov are expected to stay in space for six months.
   The eight-day mission was the eighth to hook up with the Mir
space station since it was put into orbit in 1986.
   Fourteen foreign astronauts have ridden into space aboard Soyuz
capsules, but Akiyama is the first paying non-scientific passenger.
   The flight also will boost the Soviet Union's two-year effort to
commercialize its space program.
   ``The Soviets need money,'' Akiyama said. ``Their space industry
has to be competitive, like the French, Chinese and Americans have
started to do. It's quite natural for the Russians to start this
kind of business.''
   ``If I work hard and I'm successful, then I expect to get a
bonus,'' joked Akiyama, TBS' former bureau chief in Washington.
``If I get space sickness, then it should be counted as sick
leave.''
   The journalist was carrying three amulets into space, given to
him by his father, the prime minister of Japan and by the president
of TBS.
   Asked before launch what he was looking forward to most upon his
return in eight days, Akiyama replied: ``I can't wait to have a
smoke.''
   More than 120 TBS reporters, cameramen and technicians were
brought to the cosmodrome to document the flight.
   Soviet officials went out of their way to open to display the
cosmodrome's huge installations for assembling rockets. Foreigners
have been subject to a not-so-subtle sales pitch.
   ``We can launch any satellite from any country ... just bring it
here,'' said Major Gen. Alexei Shumilin, deputy director of testing
at the cosmodrome.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0013 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 0453EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a BC-SpaceShuttle     12-02 0451</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Space Shuttle,0529</SECOND>
<HEAD>Much-Delayed Astronomical Mission Under Way</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAN SEWELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CAPE CANAVERAL, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Columbia shot spectacularly through
a moonlit sky early Sunday, carrying seven astronauts and an
astronomical laboratory into space and helping the nation's space
shuttle program end a frustrating year on an upswing.
   ``It's like an early Christmas present,'' said launch director
Bob Sieck. ``It sure goes a long way to erase the disappointments
that we had this summer.''
   A Soviet Soyuz rocket carrying two cosmonauts and a Japanese
television journalist was launched 84 minutes later, bringing to 12
the number of people in space, the most ever at one time. Two
cosmonauts are on the space station Mir. The Columbia crew hopes to
contact the Soviet crew via ham radio.
   Columbia had been grounded since May by hydrogen leaks, and the
shuttle Atlantis was also delayed by leaks. The launch at 1:49 a.m.
EST came on the fifth attempt to put Columbia and its astronomy lab
in space for a 10-day mission.
   ``It was spectacular to watch it go up,'' said Arthur Davidson
of Johns Hopkins University, principal investigator of one of the
Astro observatory's ultraviolet telescopes. ``We're getting a whole
new look at the universe.''
   The 100-ton spaceship flooded the sky with light visible for
hundreds of miles as it thundered toward a 218-mile-high orbit. The
launch was delayed 21 minutes when the Air Force, which has
responsibility for range safety, sent a helicopter into a layer of
clouds to confirm that visibility was sufficient.
   The unusual helicopter check surprised NASA officials, but Air
Force Col. John Wormington said afterward that it saved the launch
from being postponed.
   The moon shining through the clouds over the Florida coast was
brightened by the shuttle's 700-foot pillar of flames.
   ``We really had a light show coming up. That was really
something,'' said Columbia's commander Vance Brand, at age 59 the
oldest person to reach space.
   It was NASA's sixth shuttle flight this year, three fewer than
planned because of the hydrogen leaks that grounded Columbia and
Atlantis through summer and early fall. Atlantis returned from a
secret military flight less than two weeks ago.
   Astronomers have been waiting anxiously to send up the $150
million observatory since the mission's original launch date in
1986. The mission was delayed until this year by the Challenger
accident.
   As Columbia orbits high above Earth's distorting atmosphere,
four astronomers on board will operate Astro's three ultraviolet
telescopes round-the-clock. An X-ray telescope will be managed by
computer commands sent from the ground.
   The observatory will remain anchored in Columbia's cargo bay
throughout the flight and return to Earth with the shuttle.
   Scientists expect to be surprised by many of Astro's findings
since ultraviolet light and X-rays are invisible from Earth.
   About 240 objects will be studied, including Jupiter, quasars,
binary stars, a supernova and Comet Levy, which is on its way out
of the solar system.
   Columbia's other crew members are pilot Guy Gardner, mission
secialist Mike Lounge and astronomers Ron Parise, Jeffrey Hoffman,
Robert Parker and Sam Durrance.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0014 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 0627EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i BC-Israel-Attack 3rdLd-Writethru a0652 12-02 0410</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Israel-Attack, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0652,0512</SECOND>
<HEAD>Police Kill Palestinian After Four Israelis Stabbed</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 13th graf, `Yaacov Rad ..' to CORRECT name to Raz and
give full title; picks up 14th graf pvs, `The blue-and-white...</NOTE>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Three Palestinians boarded a bus outside Tel
Aviv on Sunday and stabbed four Israelis, one of them fatally,
police said. A policeman then shot to death one of the attackers
and the others were captured.
   Shouting ``Allahu Akbar!'' (God is Great), the Palestinians rose
from their seats and began slashing with knives as the bus passed
through a shopping district between the suburban cities of Bnei
Brak and Ramat Gan, said Tel Aviv police spokeswoman Etti
Greenberg.
   In a leaflet issued over the weekend, leaders of the three-year
Palestinian uprising in the occupied territories had declared
Sunday a ``day of escalation'' against Israel.
   The Palestinians had boarded the bus headed for Tel Aviv at
about 9:30 a.m. (2:30 a.m. EST), Greenberg said.
   When the knifing began, the driver stopped and pulled a pistol
out, and the passengers fled the bus, she said.
   A paramilitary border policeman driving behind the bus then
climbed aboard and opened fire with an Uzi submachine on one of the
assailants, killing him.
   Greenberg said two of the assailants were injured but she did
not know how. Israel army radio said one was shot in the hand, and
the other was beaten by angry Israelis.
   The four injured Israelis were taken by taxi to Beilinson
Hospital, where one of the victims, a 24-year-old man, died of stab
wounds to the heart and lungs.
   A man who was crossing the street when he saw the attack said on
army radio: ``I saw a big commotion on the bus, as though everyone
was beating each other up.''
   ``Then people came out, they were all bloodied. Some looked very
seriously injured, we stopped a taxi and put them in, there was a
man dripping blood from his mouth,'' said the witness, whose name
was not given.
   Passenger Ilana Bardash said she had gotten on the bus outside
her bank and shortly afterward, ``I heard the shouts of Allahu
Akbar.''
   ``I saw three people were injured. The door was stuck. We just
pushed it open and ran outside, and just started shouting for
police,'' Mrs. Bardash said.
   Yaacov Raz, commander of police in the Tel Aviv area, praised
the driver for his ``good, speedy action'' in taking control of the
bus and preventing more stabbings.
   The blue-and-white bus was taken to the Ramat Gan police station
with the dead attacker lying in the aisle. His stockinged, shoeless
foot stuck out from under a sheet into abandoned shopping bags and
pools of blood.
   On Saturday, an Arab woman was shot dead in Jerusalem as she
tried to stab a police officer, who was unharmed because he wore a
flak jacket.
   Also Saturday, a grenade was thrown in a shopping area in
central Tel Aviv. The explosion caused no injuries, Israeli reports
said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0015 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 0656EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i BC-Gulf-IraqSoviets     12-02 0317</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Gulf-Iraq Soviets,0362</SECOND>
<HEAD>Iraq Warns Soviets Not to Send Troops to Gulf</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SALAH NASRAWI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BAGHDAD, Iraq (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Iraq on Sunday warned the Soviet Union that
it could lose its influence in the Arabs world if it sent troops to
the Persian Gulf, the official Iraqi News Agency reported.
   Soviet Foreign Minister Eduward Shevardnadze said Thursday that
Moscow would send troops if Soviets trapped in Iraq were
mistreated. The Soviets previously had said they wouldn't
participate in the U.S.-led multinational force arrayed against
Saddam Hussein.
   An Iraqi Foreign Ministry spokesman charged that Shevardnadze
``seems to be looking for a pretext to send troops to the region.''
   Shevardnadze, speaking at the United Nations, declared that
``everyone should know that we will not hesitate to use force'' to
protect the estimated 3,000 Soviet citizens still in Iraq.
   The Iraqi spokesman, whose comments were carried by the official
Iraqi agency, cautioned the Soviet leadership that it would ``lose
the friendship of 200 million Arabs if Soviet conduct were go
further than it has go so far.''
   The Soviets have two warships and a support vessel in the Gulf
region, but they have not apparently taken an active part in the
naval force blockading Iraq.
   Moscow has a friendship treaty with Baghdad and was its main
arms supplier during the 1980-88 war with Iran. The Soviets have
played a key mediation role in the gulf crisis but failed to
convince Saddam to withdraw from Kuwait.
   Sarkis Arkilian, a Soviet Oil Ministry official, was visiting
Baghdad on Sunday to discuss the status of 3,000 Soviets, mainly
technicians and oil specialists, who have not been able to leave
Iraq.
   Soviet diplomats declined to give any details of Arkilian's
talks with Gen. Hussein Kamel Hassan, Iraq's acting oil minister
and Saddam's son-in-law.
   Some 2 million foreigners, mostly Asians and Arabs but including
several thousand Americans and Europeans, remain in Kuwait and
Iraq.
   They include some 600 Americans, Britons and others held as
``human shields'' at strategic locations to deter attack by the the
force confronting Iraq. No Soviets are believed to be among the
``human shields.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0016 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 0955EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i BC-Gulf-Foreigners 3rdLd-Writethru a0655 12-02 0422</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Gulf-Foreigners, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0655,0509</SECOND>
<HEAD>Muhammad Ali Flies Out With Freed U.S. Hostages</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS throughout to lower number of hostages on plane to 33,
ADD that Belgians flew out on Belgian airliner; EDITS to conform.
No pickup.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>AMMAN, Jordan, (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Former boxer Muhammad Ali flew out of
Baghdad on Sunday with 15 American hostages whose freedom he
secured in talks with President Saddam Hussein, airport officials
said.
   Two Canadians and six British hostages, released seperately by
the Iraqis, were also on the Iraqi Airways flight from Baghdad,
spokesmen for the groups said.
   Airport officials in Baghdad said 10 more Westerners, who were
not further identified, also were on board.
   The officials said 24 Belgians flew to Brussels Sunday afternoon
in a Belgian airliner that had brought medicine to Iraq.
   The Iraqi Airways plane carrying the 33 hostages landed in Amman
at 1:34 p.m. (5:34 EST) after a 90-minute flight from the Iraqi
capital.
   All the Americans were men who had been held at strategic
facilities in Iraq and Kuwait as ``human shields'' against attacks
by the U.S.-led multinational force in the Persian Gulf.
   U.S. Embassy officials welcomed Ali and the American hostages.
U.S. officials had earlier said Ali's trip to Iraq was private.
   The group had originally been scheduled to leave Saturday, but
Ali decided to stay on, hoping to use the good will generated by
President Bush's offer to hold talks with Iraq to win the release
of more Americans.
   Bush offered Friday to send Secretary of State James Baker III
to Baghdad for talks on resolving the gulf crisis, triggered by
Iraq's Aug. 2 invasion of Kuwait. Iraq on Saturday agreed to the
idea of peace talks.
   But the Iraqis apparently refused to free any more of the
estimated 330 U.S. citizens still held in Iraq, at least 100 of
them as human shields. Another 600 remain in hiding in Kuwait.
   Ali, the former world heavyweight boxing champion, spent more
than a week in Baghdad with two aides and two members of the
Coalition to Stop U.S. Intervention in the Middle East.
   He met last week with Saddam and other senior Iraqi officials in
his mission to win the release of hostages.
   Jaber Mohammed, the former boxer's manager, said Saturday that
Ali might return later this month to seek the release of more
Americans.
   On Friday, a group of about 80 foreigners, most of them Swedes,
were released and flew to Stockholm in a chartered Iraqi Airways
jetliner.
   An Ali associate, Arthur Morrison, earlier identified the 15
Americans as George Charchalis of Reno, Nevada; Ralph Leidholdt of
Lakewood, Colorado; Richard Iliff of Roswell, Georgia; Harold
Martin of Tulsa, Oklahoma; Dean Shannon of Cuero, Texas; Bobby
Means of Belle Chasse, Louisiana; R.L. Smart of Liberty, Texas;
Desmond Bailey of Crosby, Texas; Bobby R. Anderson of Round Rock,
Texas; Harry Brill-Edwards of Fort Lee, New Jersey; Sergio Coletta
of Moss Point, Mississippi; and Ken Beasley, Marlin Gillmore, Julio
Loyala and Bill McHann, all of Texas.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0017 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 1020EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i BC-Germany-Election 3rdLd-Writethru a0657 12-02 0584</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Germany-Election, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0657,0692</SECOND>
<HEAD>Kohl Urges Voters to Cast Ballots in Historic Election</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 7 grafs to CORRECT in lead that elections are first
free balloting in 58 years sted 41, and in 7th graf that interview
was published Sunday sted Saturday; pickup 8th graf pvs, `The
first...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By MAUD S. BEELMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BONN, Germany (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   United Germany on Sunday held its first
free elections in 58 years since Adolf Hitler seized power and led
the country into World War II and partition.
   The polls opened under dreary skies with snow and light rain.
About 60 million people were eligible to choose the government for
the newly united nation, but initial reports said turnout was low.
   Germany's leaders were among the first to vote.
   Chancellor Helmut Kohl cast his ballot at noon in his hometown
of Oggersheim, 65 miles south of Frankfurt after attending church.
Kohl and his Christian Democrats are widely favored to win because
of his strong leadership in uniting the two Germanys.
   His main challenger, leftist Social Democrat Oskar Lafontaine,
voted in Saarbruecken in southwestern Germany, the capital of
Saarland state where he serves as governor.
   Kohl said Germans had paid a high price for democracy and urged
them to vote.
   ``Many people fought peacefully for the right to vote freely for
decades. They often suffered prison or worse. This right is one of
democracy's most precious treasures,'' Kohl said in an interview
published Sunday.
   The first projected results were expected at 6:30 p.m. (12:30
p.m. EST), 30 minutes after the polls close.
   The momentous occasion was overshadowed Saturday by disclosure
that an arrest warrant had been issued for former East German
Communist chief Erich Honecker on charges he gave shoot-to-kill
orders at the Berlin Wall.
   Honecker, 78, is accused of personally giving shoot-to-kill
orders at the Berlin Wall, a city justice official said. He said
the warrant links Honecker directly to the deaths of several people
trying to escape East Germany.
   Honecker ruled East Germany for 18 years until a peaceful
revolution in October 1989 swept him from power. The events led to
the unification of Germany on Oct. 3.
   Sunday's vote puts the final democratic seal on the yearlong
drama of German unity that abolished the one-party state of East
Germany and merged it with democratic West Germany.
   Twelve million former East Germans were joining 48 million
former West Germans at the polls. Together, they were electing a
new 656-member Parliament and the first chancellor of reunited
Germany.
   Germany last voted freely as one nation in November 1932. Two
months later, Adolf Hitler was named chancellor and soon rammed
through laws depriving non-Nazis of their seats in parliament.
   The disastrous defeat in World War II left Germany divided.
   Kohl, who as chancellor guided West Germany to unity with its
eastern neighbor, automatically became the leader of all Germany
when the two states merged.
   A poll by the respected Allensbach Institute published Saturday
predicted Kohl's Christian Democrats and their Bavarian sister
party, the Christian Socialists, would earn 42.5 percent of the
vote.
   Kohl's junior coalition partner, the Free Democrats, bolstered
by the growing popularity of their leader, Foreign Minister
Hans-Dietrich Genscher, were likely to receive 10 percent, the poll
said.
   The opposition Social Democrats, still trying to recover from
their early resistance to quick unification, were expected to
receive no better than 34.5 percent of the vote, the Allensbach
poll indicated. No margin of error was given.
   Confident that voters will confirm the course he steered to
unity, Kohl made only one-fourth as many campaign appearances as
Lafontaine, his Social Democratic challenger.
   Voters apparently will not erase communism from Germany's
political scene. The Party for Democratic Socialism, the
reform-minded successor to East Germany's former Communist Party,
is expected to win seats in the new Parliament, acccording to the
Allensbach poll.
   Party leader Gregor Gysi told his supporters that every vote for
his group was a vote to uphold socialist ideals. His comments
appeared in a front-page editorial in Neues Deutschland, the party
newspaper.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0018 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 1130EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Obit-Markert     12-02 0229</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Markert,0263</SECOND>
<HEAD>Founder of Radio City's Rockettes Dead at 91</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SOUTHBURY, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Russell Markert, who founded Radio City
Music Hall's Rockettes and choreographed their high-kicking
routines for 39 years, has died. He was 91.
   Markert, who retired in 1971, died Saturday at Waterbury
Hospital.
   Markert himself was a dancer in Broadway shows in the 1920s. He
was performing in ``No, No, Nanette'' in 1925 when he went to St.
Louis to realize his dream of producing a chorus line of tall
female dancers.
   The group he formed, ``The 16 Missouri Rockets,'' began
performing in St. Louis and later toured as ``The American
Rockets.''
   They attracted the attention of the noted New York showman
Samuel ``Roxy'' Rothafel, who hired them as ``Russell Markert's 32
Roxyettes.''
   When Rothafel was hired in 1932 to open the Radio City Music
Hall in New York's Rockefeller Center, Markert and the chorus line
came along and changed its name to the ``Rockettes.''
   His work was performed by more than 2,500 women.
   Born in Jersey City, N.J., in 1899, Markert began dancing in
grammar school, and later took dance lessons as therapy for a foot
injury he suffered in World War I.
   Nearly 450 Rockettes, alumnae and friends attended a charity
ball honoring his 90th birthday. Proceeds benefited the Russell
Markert Dance Scholarship at the Juilliard School in New York.
   Markert lived alone at a retirement home. Friends said he had no
surviving family.
   The hospital said the cause of death would not be released.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0019 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 1140EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i BC-Chad     12-02 0287</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Chad,0338</SECOND>
<HEAD>Libya Says Deposed Chadian Leader Killed Trying To Flee</HEAD>
<DATELINE>N'DJAMENA, Chad (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The deposed leader of Chad, Hissene
Habre, was killed while trying to flee his country and the rebel
forces that brought down his government, the Libyan news agency
reported Sunday.
   The dispatch by JANA, monitored in Rome, quoted unidentified
sources in the Chadian capital as saying Habre was killed near the
Sudanse border and that several of his aides were arrested. Some of
the aides did manage to escape, it said.
   The report could not immediately be confirmed independently.
   Libya declared earlier that Habre was a ``brigand'' and hailed
the victory of the rebels. It is believed to have helped arm the
guerrillas.
   Diplomatic sources in N'Djamena said on Saturday that Habre fled
the capital on a military cargo plane and flew to Cameroon.
   But JANA said Habre was killed in the area between Tine and Oum
Chalouba near Sudan.
   ``The reports by news media on the escape of Habre with his
family on board an aircraft to a neighboring country were not
true,'' said the brief dispatch. It gave no further details.
   It was not immediately known whether his family had been killed.
   Habre fled after rebel leader Idriss Deby scored a series of
battlefield victories last week.
   Deby rolled into N'Djamena, the Chadian capital, on Sunday in a
black Mercedes escorted by 20 all-terrain vehicles. His guerrillas
began taking over key areas of the city and imposed a curfew after
a day of widespread looting.
   Bada Maldom, vice president of Deby's Patriotic Salvation Front,
held talks with National Assembly President Alingue Bawayeu, the
highest-ranking official left after Habre fled.
   No disclosures were made about the talks. They were believed to
be concerned with handing over power to Deby.
   Deby helped Habre, 48, oust former President Goukouni Oueddei
from power in 1982. He served as defense minister until Habre
accused him of plotting a coup in April 1989.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0020 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 1141EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w BC-Gulf-Baker -URGENT-   12-02 0302</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Gulf-Baker,330</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<HEAD>Baker: U.S. Won't Attack if Iraq Withdraws From Kuwait, Frees
Hostages</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOAN MOWER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Secretary of State James A. Baker III promised
Saddam Hussein on Sunday that the United States will not attack
Iraq if Iraqi troops are withdrawn from Kuwait and Western hostages
are freed.
   ``There has never been any suggestion that force would be used
if the U.N. resolutions are fully complied with,'' Baker said on
NBC-TV's ``Meet the Press'' program.
   ``If he complied with the resolutions, his reward for that would
not be a military attack by the United States,'' Baker said.
   Those resolutions call for the unconditional withdrawal of Iraqi
troops from Kuwait, the release of all hostages and the restoration
of the Kuwaiti government.
   A U.S.-led multilateral force has arrayed more than 350,000
troops against Saddam in the Persian Gulf. U.S. forces, now
numbering more 240,000, are expected to swell to around 400,000 by
next month. And a U.N. Security Council resolution passed last week
authorized force against Saddam if he does not pull out of Kuwait
by Jan. 15.
   Baker said there was an ``excellent chance'' Saddam will quit
Kuwait because he knows he would face devastating military action
if U.S. troops moved against him.
   U.S. officials - including President Bush - have voiced serious
concern about Saddam's possession of chemical weapons and his
program to develop nuclear weapons.
   While the United States remains concerned about Saddam's
weapons, Baker said ``We would have to find a way to address those
issues'' in the aftermath of a resolution of the Kuwaiti crisis.
   Bush has said he wants Baker to travel to Iraq sometime before
Jan. 15 to have talks with Saddam. The president has also invited
Iraqi Foreign Minister Tariq Aziz to the United States next week.
   Baker reiterated the U.S. position that he would not negotiate
on the U.N. resolutions.
   U.S. officials Saturday also said the talks would not be linked
with the Israeli occupation of Arab lands, as the Iraqi government
has demanded.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0021 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 1143EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--Japan-Radicals     12-02 0171</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Japan-Radicals,0176</SECOND>
<HEAD>Man Throws Smoke Bomb At Emperor's Motorcade</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two people threw a smoke bomb and a firecracker at
Emperor Akihito's motorcade Sunday as it headed for the Imperial
Palace in Kyoto after another of the rites of Akihitio's
enthronement, police said.
   A bystander suffered an eye injury as the firecracker landed
among people watching the motorcade pass, said an official of the
Kyoto state police.
   The man and woman, who were arrested immediately, did not
respond to police investigators' questions, the official said.
   He said they might be connected with radical leftists who
declared in leaflets last Thursday that they would ``completely
crush'' the royal couple's visit to Kyoto and nearby Nara.
   Leftist groups oppose the monarchy and say Japan's emperor
system is a symbol of militarism.
   The smoke bomb landed in the road, pouring out smoke a minute
before the car carrying Emperor Akihito and Empress Michiko reached
the spot, the official said. The car slowed, but Akihito might not
have noticed the incident, he added.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0022 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 1158EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-France-Scandals     12-02 0552</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-France-Scandals,0616</SECOND>
<HEAD>Police, Financing Scandals Beset Troubled Government</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PATRICK McDOWELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Accusations that intelligence officers murdered a
homosexual pastor and recruited male prostitutes to entrap public
figures are the latest problems for Premier Michel Rocard's
troubled Socialist government.
   The scandals, and allegations that Justice Minister Henri Nallet
broke fund-raising laws in running President Francois Mitterrand's
1988 re-election campaign, add to other recent woes: student
protests, ghetto riots and Rocard's narrow defeat - by only five
votes - of a no-confidence vote introduced by the opposition.
   One opinion poll indicated half the French people believe
politicians are ``rather corrupt'' and one-quarter think they are
liars.
   ``When the left was elected in 1981, they looked much cleaner
than the right,'' said Pascal Perrineau, assistant director of the
Center for Studies on French Political Life, a private think tank.
   ``Now, many voters are beginning to see the left isn't so
pure,'' he said. ``They appear to have the same morality as the
right. In the end, this only serves Jean-Marie Le Pen.''
   Le Pen, leader of the extreme-right National Front, advocates
expelling Moslem immigrants and denounces the political
establishment as corrupt.
   The controversy about the intelligence agency Renseignements
Generaux (General Information) has fascinated France for months.
The agency's main task is gathering information about threats to
state security, but it also investigates prostitution, narcotics
and white-collar crime.
   On July 19, Joseph Douce, 45, a former Baptist clergyman who
performed homosexual marriages, vanished after two men claiming to
be policemen visited his Paris apartment.
   Three months later, a man gathering mushrooms in a forest
discovered a body half-devoured by animals. An autopsy proved it
was Douce.
   The intelligence service had been investigating Douce, a
militant homosexual expelled from the French Baptist Church in 1975
in connection with a child prostitution ring.
   Two weeks before the abduction, agents fired a shot at the home
of a man they wanted to infiltrate Douce's entourage.
   A police inquiry led to the questioning of three agents. Two
have have been suspended and the third, Inspector Jean-Marc
Dufourg, 34, was fired Nov. 23 after talking about the case in
several media interviews.
   Dufourg claimed his superiors ordered him to hire a young
homosexual to compromise former Justice Minister Pierre Arpaillange
and Philippe Guilhaume, chief of the Antenne 2 television channel.
   Dufourg's allegations led to numerous reports about the
intelligence service.
   It is said to have stolen mail from Communist Party offices,
planted agents in a conservative party's headquarters and burgled
the offices of a prominent anti-racism group.
   Interior Minister Pierre Joxe has authorized a parliamentary
inquiry into the intelligence agency. Afterward, an independent
body will be created to oversee police activities.
   Joxe also has faced pressure because of a best-seller by a
whistle-blowing police inspector, Antoine Gaudino.
   His book, ``The Impossible Inquiry,'' alleges that laundered
money and illegal kickbacks from public works contractors financed
the Socialist election victory in 1988.
   The title comes from Gaudino's frustrated attempts in 1989 to
investigate a Marseille building scandal.
   Gaudino wrote that he and his partner discovered notes from
meetings between Socialist Party leaders and members of a
fraudulent political consulting firm.
   He said they set up a scheme in which contractors would pay a
percentage of project costs as campaign contributions to Socialist
candidates.
   The book plunged Nallet, who had just been appointed justice
minister, into controversy.
   Nallet was Mitterrand's treasurer in the last nine weeks of the
campaign - too short a time, he says, to have learned of illicit
financial activities.
   Joxe suspended Gaudino for ``grave indiscretion.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0023 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 1211EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-RichandPoor     12-02 0645</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Rich and Poor,790</SECOND>
<HEAD>Gap Between Rich and Poor Increasing in Western Nations</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By W. DALE NELSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The United States was not the only Western
industrialized nation to see the gap between rich and poor widen
during the last decade, a government study notes, despite critics'
charges that recent government policies contributed to the growth
of earnings inequality.
   According to a study, which is forthcoming in the statistical
publication Review of Income and Wealth, the same thing was
happening in other countries with different policies.
   ``This may suggest that the causes of greater inequality are
related more generally to phenomena occurring across nations rather
than to specific factors unique to one country,'' say three Census
Bureau economists who authored the study.
   ``The increase in inequality in the United States is well
documented,'' said Gordon Green, assistant chief of the Housing and
Household Economic Statistics Division of the bureau and one of the
authors of the study.
   ``There has been hardly anything available on other countries,
because the data hasn't been available, but the increase in
inequality occurred elsewhere even though their employment
experiences were very different and there were policy differences
and different institutional settings,'' Green said.
   ``We haven't really pinned down exactly what's going on,'' he
said, and further study will be needed to look into the causes.
``Maybe it has something to do with the kind of jobs that are
created and the skill requirements for those jobs.''
   In its annual report on income and poverty, issued in September,
the Census Bureau said the wealthiest one-fifth of families
received 46.8 percent of household income during 1989. This was no
higher than in 1988, but was up significantly from percentages of
44.2 percent in 1979 and 43 percent in 1969.
   ``There seems little doubt that the income distribution has
become somewhat less equal over the past 20 years,'' the bureau
said in that report. It said it did not know why.
   Rep. Lee Hamilton, D-Ind., chairman of the congressional Joint
Economic Committee, said, ``Those at the top of the scale are
receiving an ever-larger share of the pie.''
   The new comparative study says ``evidence now exists that the
phenomenon of growing earnings inequality may have an international
or global dimension.''
   Green was joined in the study by John Coder, a statistician
economist; and Paul Ryscavage, a labor economist.
   They said it did not necessarily reflect the views of the Census
Bureau.
   The study compares earnings of male heads of household, aged 25
to 54, working full-time year around, in the United States, Canada,
Sweden, Australia and West Germany. The figures from the different
countries were not all for the same year, but were all in the
mid-1980's.
   In the United States, the top 10 percent of households had 22.8
percent of the earnings, higher than in any other country. The top
10 percent earned 18.9 percent in Canada, 18 percent in West
Germany, 17.7 percent in Sweden, and 17.4 percent in Australia.
   The lowest 10 percent of Americans earned 3.4 percent, lower
than any of the other countries except Canada, at 2.9 percent.
Australia measured 3.8 percent and West Germany 5.6 percent. The
poor were best off in Sweden, with 6.3 percent of the earnings.
   The economists then used six different methods of measuring
income inequality, applying them to the same group of workers, and
found that the United States was the most unequal of the five
countries by four of the methods. Canada was the most unequal by
the other two. Sweden had the greatest equality by all methods of
measurement.
   Again limiting their study to male heads of household aged 25 to
54, the study found that the share of the top one-fifth in the
United States increased from 34.8 percent in 1979 to 37.4 percent
in 1986, while the share of the lowest fifth dropped from 9.3
percent to 8.5 percent. In Canada, between 1981 and 1987, the
wealthiest fifth increased from 31.4 to 33.4 and the poorest
dropped from 10.5 to 8.5. In Sweden in the same years, the richest
went from 30.8 percent to 30.2 percent and the poorest from 13.7
percent to 13.5 percent.
   In Australia, between 1981 and 1985, the wealthiest went from
30.7 to 31.2 and the poorest from 11.3 to 10.5. In West Germany,
the gain for the wealthiest between 1981 and 1984 was only 30.8 to
31.6 per cent, while the share of the poor dropped only from 12.8
percent to 12.5 percent.
   The average rate of employment growth during the periods
measured was 1.5 percent in the United States, 1.3 percent in
Canada and 1.1 percent in Australia. It was less than half of one
percent in Sweden. In West Germany, employment was declining.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0024 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 1238EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Israel-Attack     12-02 0571</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel-Attack,0743</SECOND>
<HEAD>Palestinians Stab Israelis On Bus Outside Tel Aviv, Killing One</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos TLV1,101</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MAX NASH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>RAMAT GAN, Israel (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Three Palestinians boarded a bus on a
busy street outside Tel Aviv Sunday, knifed a Jewish yeshiva
student to death and wounded three people, police said.
   A policeman killed one of the attackers, and the two others were
wounded.
   Stunned bystanders looked on as frightened passengers, some
dripping blood, poured out of the bus into a busy shopping area in
Ramat Gan, a city adjacent to Tel Aviv.
   It was the bloodiest incident in greater Tel Aviv, Israel's most
populous area, since Arabs began a wave of stabbing attacks on Jews
in October. The attacks followed the poice slaying of Arabs on
Jerusalem's Temple Mount.
   Palestinian militants, in clandestine leaflets, had declared
Sunday ``a day of escalation'' of their 3-year-old struggle against
Israeli occupation of the West Bank and Gaza Strip.
   Knifings have been more common in Jerusalem, home to a greater
mix of Arab and Jewish populations. The coastal Tel Aviv metropolis
40 miles away has been seen as a relatively trouble-free area.
   The three attackers were from the West Bank village of Azmut
near Nablus, army radio said. They had boarded the Tel Aviv-bound
bus in the Jewish suburb of Pardes Katz, and sat in the back seat.
   Soon after boarding, they jumped up shouting ``Allahu Akbar!
(God is Great) witnesses said.
   The driver, David Shelef, said he saw the Arabs in his rear-view
mirror ``jumping in the air, waving knives in their hands and
lunging at the passengers seated in front of them.''
   He said he braked, opened the doors to let out his approximately
20 passengers, and approached the Arabs with his pistol. Shelef
said he fired one shot in the air, told them to sit still and they
obeyed.
   Meanwhile, a bomb disposal officer from the border police, who
was stopped in traffic behind the stalled bus, heard shouts of
``Terrorist! They've stabbed someone! Get out quick, bring the
Uzi!''
   The officer, who did not give his name, said he loaded his
submachine gun and ran to the bus.
   He said he held the Arabs at bay for a few minutes, ordering
them repeatedly in Hebrew and Arabic to keep still.
   But then ``one of them got up and tried to attack me, apparently
with a knife. I was forced to fire to injure him and apparently the
guy died on the spot.''
   Israel army radio said another attacker was hit in the hand with
a bullet and a third was beaten by bystanders.
   The injured Israelis and Arabs were rushed to nearby Beilinson
Hospital. Baruch Heisler, 24, a student at a yeshiva, or religious
seminary, died on the operating table of wounds to the heart and
lungs, hospital officials said.
   The other Jewish victims were identified as Shmuel Cohen, 15,
Becky Malka, 18, and Avisha Cohen, 18. They were said to have
slight to moderate injuries. The attackers were not named.
   Becky Malka said she and a friend had been on a shopping spree
when the attack happened.
   ``We got on the bus and behind us were three Arabs. Suddenly
they shouted `Allahu Akbar' and stabbed us. They had kitchen
knives,'' she said.
   Bystanders and shopkeepers, some of them armed, tried to beat
the attackers as they were taken off the bus. One man was arrested
for attacking the injured Arab as he was carried away on a
stretcher.
   ``Anyone who tries to attack an injured man, whoever that man
is, will be arrested. ... We are not animals,'' said Yaacov Raz, a
commander of the greater Tel Aviv police force.
   Arabs on a Tel Aviv-bound bus would have attracted little
attention, since thousands ride in daily from the occupied
territories to jobs in Israel.
   Yigal Marcus, commander of Tel Aviv police, said Sunday's attack
meant ``Tel Aviv has returned to the map.
   ``If anyone thought they (the Arabs) had forgotten Tel Aviv and
were only trying to stab in Jerusalem, reality has slapped them in
the face,'' Marcus said.
   In the Oct. 8 Temple Mount killings, police opened fire on
Palestinian rioters. The government put the death toll at 20, but
the Palestine Human Rights Information Center has put the toll at
17.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0025 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 1240EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-OlympicNeighborhoods Bjt   12-02 0634</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Olympic Neighborhoods, Bjt,0777</SECOND>
<HEAD>Poor Atlanta Residents Fear They Will Be Victims of Olympics</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LAURAN NEERGAARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ATLANTA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Douglas Dean stopped in front of the stadium site
for the 1996 Summer Olympics, and sighed at the sight of crumbling
homes and crime-ridden streets.
   ``People always say, `What's wrong with the people of
Summerhill? They don't have the Olympic spirit,''' the former state
legislator said of his once-thriving black neighborhood. ``Why
should we give up everything when nobody comes to help us?''
   Dean is among many activists who believe the city, so proud of
its Olympic conquest since it was chosen in September to play host
for the Games, will cover up or bulldoze urban blight before the
world comes to Atlanta in 1996.
   They fear builders will raze pockets of public housing and
crumbling homes to make way for Olympic facilities, adding to the
city's estimated 10,000 homeless.
   Summerhill has seen the phenomenon before. The city razed
hundreds of homes there in 1964 for Atlanta-Fulton County Stadium.
   ``We ha a drugstore, a five-and-dime, anything you needed right
here, but the stadium kicked it all out,'' said Larry Swann, 52,
who grew up in the area and owns a ramshackle Summerhill house.
``There's no telling what they're going to do.''
   Atlanta Olympic officials insist their plans call for no home
destruction but admit the final authority - the still-unformed
Atlanta Committee for the Olympic Games - could change plans.
   ``We're frustrated that we cannot respond with something more
specific,'' said Olympic spokesman Bob Brennan. ``But we got the
Games (11) weeks ago and they're going to be six years from now -
we need a little breathing room.''
   John Leak, vice president of the business-supported planning
group Central Atlanta Progress, said a brochure produced by the
Atlanta Organizing Committee may be a warning: The drawings show
glistening architecture and pristine landscaping but nowhere are
actual pictures of the inner-city areas.
   The two most affected areas are Summerhill and Techwood Homes, a
housing project across from Georgia Tech, where the Olympic
Village, home to 16,500 athletes, will be built. The village later
would provide student housing for Georgia Tech, Georgia State
University and the Atlanta University Center, according to a
committee proposal.
   ``If you just take the pretty drawings that now exist and try to
place them on the sites depicted, there are certain buildings that
are affected,'' he said.
   For example, the plan shows the Olympic stadium built on the
south parking lot of the existing stadium. But drawn to scale, it
would infringe on an existing home for the elderly and a hospital.
   ``Looking at that plan, you also don't see any provision for
cars to be parked. That naturally makes (residents) nervous,'' Leak
added. ``Something's got to give.''
   Activists for the poor say the plans are typical of Atlanta.
They have accused Mayor Maynard Jackson of trying to push the
homeless from downtown. Jackson also supported a recent proposal to
ban begging, although backers of the idea now propose to make
begging a crime only when the panhandler accosts someone.
   ``This is a city that believes in hiding its poor,'' said Sister
Carol Schlicksup of People for Urban Justice. ``The city isn't
going to let the poor be seen by the world. The Olympics is going
to devastate the poor communities.
   ``They keep telling us they have no money to build us the
emergency single-family housing Maynard Jackson promised us,'' she
said. ``But when you talk about Olympics, all of a sudden there's
lots of money.''
   Central Atlanta Progress, residents and activists have protested
to Brennan that the Olympic committee never talked to residents
before creating the Olympic plan.
   They also charge the committee gives more consideration to
richer areas. The AOC agreed to move the Olympic tennis center out
of Blackburn Park after DeKalb County residents protested.
   ``It's a class thing now,'' said Columbus Ward, president of the
Summerhill Neighborhood Planning Unit. ``The upper-class whites who
mainly own homes said they don't want it, they listened. When the
poor blacks who have mostly rental property fuss, they get no
response at all.
   ``Well, we'll stop the stadium if we have to stand in front of
the bulldozers.''
   Brennan said the tennis center could be moved because 25 other
communities asked to play host to it.
   ``We have no intention of moving ahead with any plan without
involving people,'' he said. ``Many of these people have lived
there all their lives, are feeling their homes threatened, and I
can appreciate that.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0026 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 1254EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Calif-NYBudgets     12-02 0564</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Calif-NY Budgets,0690</SECOND>
<HEAD>California, New York Lawmakers Face Fiscal Woes</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Thousands of miles apart but united in a similar predicament,
the California and New York state legislatures convene Monday for
special sessions called for midyear patches on leaky state budgets.
   In Albany, Democratic Gov. Mario Cuomo has proposed sharp cuts
in state spending to deal with an estimated $1 billion deficit in
New York's $50 billion budget for the fiscal year that ends March
31.
   Cuomo has called for state worker layoffs, mandatory and unpaid
employee furloughs and cuts in state aid for education and health
care.
   The situation is less serious in Sacramento, where Republican
Gov. George Deukmejian, who leaves office in January, wants $1
billion in cuts as a fiscal cushion in California's $75 billion
budget. Without those cuts, the budget for the fiscal year that
ends June 30 could just break even or have a small deficit.
   Deukmejian has proposed $600 million in public school cuts, a
$200 million reduction in the income tax credit for renters and a
freeze on state hiring and purchases.
   For New York, this is the third straight year officials have
faced state budget deficits. And next year promises to be no
better: Comptroller Edward Regan has said the state may be facing a
potential deficit of as much as $3 billion then.
   In the past, Cuomo and the Legislature have been quick to turn
to tax increases to help bail themselves out when they learned that
spending had exceeded revenues. Last year, New Yorkers were hit
with a $1 billion tax increase package and earlier this year they
were socked with a record $1.8 billion in new taxes.
   But last month, Cuomo won re-election to a third term with a
lower percentage of the vote than expected despite being opposed by
splintered and poorly funded opposition. The potential 1992
presidential candidate said the message from voters was clear -
they didn't want any new taxes.
   That prompted Cuomo to come forth with a deficit reduction plan
that relies almost entirely on spending cuts. Under the governor's
plan before the Legislature, the state's $9 billion school aid
package would be sliced by $200 million and social service programs
would be slashed by $125 million.
   It provides for the firing of 2,000 state workers and 4,000
other job eliminations through attrition and early retirement
incentives by the end of the fiscal year.
   While legislative leaders have been tinkering with Cuomo's
proposals - particularly in the politically sensitive areas of
school aid and health care spending - both Assembly Speaker Mel
Miller and Senate Majority Leader Ralph Marino have indicated they
don't expect major changes.
   Quick approval of a Cuomo-developed plan would also leave the
governor to shoulder most of the blame for politically unpopular
cuts.
   The California special session coincides with the regular
opening of the regular 1991-92 session, an opening that normally
consists of swearing-in ceremonies.
   Deukmejian, who did not seek a third term this year, would like
lawmakers to approve his ``fiscal austerity plan'' before he leaves
office to assure that his final budget remains in the black.
   Many legislators, particularly majority Democrats, would rather
wait until Republican Gov.-elect Pete Wilson is sworn in Jan. 7.
Deukmejian has been particularly uncompromising in budget debates,
while Wilson has more of a conciliatory reputation.
   The problem occurred this fall when tax revenues for the first
four months of this fiscal year fell more than $400 million below
estimates because of the faltering economy. The budget passed last
summer had a $1.3 billion reserve, but that is expected to be
depleted by the reduced revenues.
   Wilson has remained quiet about the budget. A $1 billion fix now
would help the task he faces just three days after his
inauguration. He must present the Legislature with a proposed
budget for the 1991-92 fiscal year on Jan. 10.
   The state Commission on State Finance last week estimated there
could be at least a $4.3 billion gap between estimated 1991-92 tax
revenues and a current-level budget.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0027 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 1301EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Germany-Elections-Gla     12-02 0340</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Germany-Elections-Glance,0384</SECOND>
<HEAD>A Glance at Germany's Parliamentary Election</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Germany-Election, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BONN, Germany (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Germany on Sunday held its first free
elections in a united country since 1932. Here at a glance are some
issues and statistical data:
   AT STAKE: 656 seats in a united parliament, 328 directly chosen
in their districts and 328 from party lists; head of government, or
chancellor. Also a city council for Berlin, the new capital of
united Germany.
   GETTING IN: A party needed at least 5 percent of the vote to win
seats in the Bundestag, the lower house of parliament. However, the
constitutional court decided that vote counts would be separate for
former West Germany and East Germany.
   NUMBER OF ELIGIBLE VOTERS: 59.9 million - 47.9 million from
former West Germany and 12 million from former East Germany.
   NUMBER OF VOTING DISTRICTS: 328.
   NUMBER OF CANDIDATES: 3,969.
   NUMBER OF PARTIES: 23.
   MAIN PARTIES:
   -Christian Democratic Union, CDU, and its sister party, the
Bavarian Christian Social Union, CSU. They are part of a
center-right alliance that is heading the current government
coalition of Chancellor Helmut Kohl.
   -Social Democratic Party, SPD. The main opposition party,
leftist.
   -Free Democratic Party, FDP, liberal party of the center, the
junior coalition partner in the current government, whose most
prominent member is popular Foreign Minister Hans-Dietrich
Genscher.
   -Greens, a leftist, ecology-oriented party, which is running in
the election on a joint list with Alliance 90, a similar group in
former East Germany.
   -Party of Democratic Socialism, PDS, the leftist, renamed party
of the former East German Communists.
   -Republicans, ultra-rightist.
   TOP CANDIDATES: Helmut Kohl, 60, CDU leader and incumbent
chancellor, who was seeking his third four-year term. Oskar
Lafontaine, 47, SPD, governor of Saarland state. The chancellor is
picked by the party that wins the most seats, or in coalition
talks.
   CAMPAIGN: Was low key, with Kohl enjoying such wide support in
polls that few doubted he would win. By forging ahead full speed
for a quick unification and achieving it on Oct. 3, Kohl made
himself more popular than ever, particularly in former East German
states. Lafontaine, who barely survived an assassination attept by
a deranged woman in April, made soaring unification costs his main
theme.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0028 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 1307EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Soviet-Space     12-02 0621</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Space,0755</SECOND>
<HEAD>First Journalist Travels into Space Aboard Soviet Rocket</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto BAIK1</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Space Shuttle, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By THOMAS GINSBERG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BAIKONUR COSMODROME, U.S.S.R. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Soviet rocket rode a
column of fire into orbit in a picture-perfect launch Sunday,
carrying two cosmonauts and a Japanese television reporter who
became the first journalist in space.
   The liftoff - which also launched a Soviet effort to
commercialize their space program - was right on schedule, under
bright, sunny skies on the remote Central Asian steppes of
Kazakhstan.
   Journalist Toyohiro Akiyama, 48, joined Soviet cosmonauts Viktor
Afanasyev and Musa Manarov in the Soyuz TM-11 space capsule.
Akiyama was a passenger under a $12 million contract between the
Soviet Union and Japan's biggest private television company, TBS.
   Underscoring the commercial nature of the mission, the Soviet
rocket even had advertising slogans for TBS and other Japanese
companies emblazoned on its sides.
   About an hour and a half before the Soviet launch, the U.S.
space shuttle Columbia blasted off from Cape Canaveral, Fla. The
flight, NASA's sixth shuttle mission this year, carried seven
astronauts and an astronomical laboratory into space.
   With two Soviet cosmonauts already aboard the orbiting space
station Mir, the two liftoffs brought to 12 the number of people in
space, the most ever at one time. The Columbia crew hopes to
contact the Soviet crew by radio.
   The Soviet rocket's fiery blastoff shook shook a reviewing stand
about a mile away in this once-secret space installation, 1,200
miles east of Moscow.
   ``I feel fine,'' Akiyama said minutes before the 1:13 p.m. (3:13
a.m. EST) liftoff. During the eight-day mission, he will document
the experience on radio and television for TBS.
   The Japanese television company is spending $37 million on the
entire venture to mark its 40th year on the air, according to
network president Izumi Tanaka.
   More than 120 TBS reporters, cameramen and technicians scurried
about the launch control center and reviewing stand to cover the
launch, even sacrificing a remote-control camera next to the rocket
to watch the flames close-up before it burned.
   Akiyama's wife, Kyoko, called the blastoff ``beautiful,''
although she earlier said she was nervous.
   ``But when I saw their faces on the television screen, I calmed
down and felt happier,'' she said.
   Akiyama, a TBS news director who quit a four-pack-a-day
cigarette habit during the training, was asked before liftoff what
he looked forward to most on his return from the first trip into
space by a Japanese citizen.
   ``I can't wait to have a smoke,'' he said.
   Akiyama, for whom TBS bought a $2.2 million life insurance
policy, carried stationery, a picture of his family and three
Japanese good-luck charms into space.
   Tanaka, the TBS president, said the rocket ``took off just like
a train on schedule.'' He said Akiyama would receive a promotion
when he got back.
   Akiyama will return to Earth with cosmonauts Gennady Manakov and
Gennady Strekalov, the current Mir crew. They will end a four-month
stay in space and be replaced by Manarov and Afanasyev, who will
stay aboard the space station for six months.
   In addition to live broadcasts, Akiyama will photograph
environmental damage on Earth and conduct experiments on Japanese
tree frogs to see how they cope in a gravity-free environment.
   TBS also hopes to arrange a tlephone call Dec. 7 between
Japanese Prime Minister Toshiki Kaifu, Soviet President Mikhail S.
Gorbachev and the cosmonauts.
   Soviet officials and TBS executives have held out the hope that
the flight could improve ties between the two countries, which
never officially ended their World War II hostilities.
   The commercial contract boosts the Kremlin's drive to cash in on
its Soyuz space program in the face of critical economic problems
at home.
   Despite receiving about $30 million from sponsors for several
weeks of live coverage and documentaries about the space program,
TBS will not immediately turn a profit on the venture, Tanaka said.
   ``Yes, we will lose about $7.4 million, but we consider this
loss the cost of TBS' growth,'' he said.
   The mission will be the eighth to hook up with the Mir space
station since it was put into orbit in 1986.
   Although Soviet scientists and 14 foreign cosmonauts have ridden
into space aboard Soyuz capsules, Akiyama is the first
non-scientific paying passenger. Sunday's launch culminates three
years of planning between the Japanese firm and Soviet officials.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0029 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 1322EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Bush-SouthAmerica Bjt   12-02 0589</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bush-South America, Bjt,680</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush Visit To Latin America Highlights Changing Agenda</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Bush departure scheduled 6:45 p.m. EST; top planned</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By GEORGE GEDDA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush's visit to South America this
week comes at a time when American concerns are turning from the
Cold War to economic cooperation in this hemisphere.
   Bush's first stop on his week-long tour was to be Brasilia,
Brazil, following an overnight flight from Washington. His
itinerary also includes Uruguay, Argentina, Chile and Venezuela.
   At each stop he is expected to hail the evolution to democratic
rule in Latin America and to promote his vision of a
hemisphere-wide free trade zone.
   After a decade in whcch U.S. hemispheric policy was dominated by
the political upheaval in Central America, Bush now has the luxury
of having what U.S. officials like to call a ``positive agenda'' in
his dealings with Latin America.
   Skeptics wonder about the utility of his visit at a time of
crisis in the Persian Gulf, but Bush feels it is important to seize
on what he regards as a moment of unique opportunity in hemispheric
relations.
   Bush was to have made the visit in September but postponed it
because of the gulf situation. Secretary of State James A. Baker
III will remain in Washington to deal with that issue.
   Each of the countries on Bush's itinerary except Venezuela began
the last decade under military rule and now has an elected
president. Venezuela has had stable, democratic government since
1958.
   Beyond that, there is an emerging consensus in the hemisphere
that radical economic reform is required to help the region escape
from the ``lost decade'' of the 1980s - a period in which
production, investment and consumption all fell sharply.
   Through his ``Enterprise for the Americas Initiative,'' unveiled
last June, Bush is attempting to promote economic growth by
encouraging more free trade and increased investment. Countries
that adopt reform measures would be eligible for debt reduction.
   The emergence of democratic governments, coupled with the
phasing out of the Cold War and the willingness of most countries
to undertake painful economic reform, has produced an era of
unusual harmony in U.S. relations in Latin America.
   There was a similar period in the early 1960s when President
John F. Kennedy launched the Alliance for Progress, an ambitious
social and economic reform program. But Kennedy's death and a wave
of military coups in Latin America took the steam out of the
Alliance, and hemispheric relations suffered.
   For more the two decades, the relationship was afflicted by
divisive political disputes over such issues as human rights abuses
and economic nationalism.
   During the last decade, there was resentment over U.S. support
for Britain during the Falkland Islands crisis in 1982 and for the
Nicaraguan Contras. As the 1980s ended, hemispheric condemnation
for the U.S. invasion of Panama was widespread.
   Nowadays, the mood between the United States and its neighbors
to the south is far more relaxed. There are fewer divisive issues.
And communist Cuba has far less appeal as a model for other
countries than it once did.
   ``We are at the beginning of a new era,'' says Michael Wilson,
an associate at the Heritage Foundation, a conservative think tank.
Some analysts believe the United States would derive immense
benefits from an economically prosperous Latin America, a
potentially lucrative market for U.S. manufactured exports.
   ``Latin America, rather than Japan, holds the key to the U.S.
trade deficit,'' says Peter Drucker, a professor of the Claremont
Graduate School in California.
   Bush has pleased many Latin countries by recognizing more than
President Ronald Reagan did the need to combat the drug problem by
adopting policies that reduce demand at home. For many years, the
United States had caused resentment by placing more emphasis on
efforts to reduce supply in producing countries.
   No country has received more attention from the Bush
administration than Mexico. Bush has met six times in two years
with President Carlos Salinas, including a two-day visit this past
week in which both stressed their goal of reaching a free trade
agreement.
   Both sides agree there is less tension in the relationship than
at any time in recent memory.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0030 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 1334EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Germany-VotingDay Bjt   12-02 0612</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Germany-Voting Day, Bjt,0776</SECOND>
<HEAD>Eastern Germans Vote For Different Leaders, Same Dream</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto HBG1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARK FRITZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DELITZSCH, Germany (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   They left their homes on a gray, misty
morning to cast ballots for a brighter future. Even families could
not agree on the candidates, but they all voted for the same thing.
   ``We want to have a better life,'' said Hildegard Neumann, 66, a
resident of Germany's most depressed eastern region. ``Life was not
so good for the past 40 years.''
   Delitzsch is one of scores of smoky, smudged cities that stand
amid sprawling processing plants in the south of what was once East
Germany.
   This is Saxony state, the faintly beating heartland of the
former nation's fading industrial sector. It is a stronghold of
Chancellor Helmut Kohl's Christian Democrats, who promise
prosperity soon.
   Mrs. Neumann and her husband, Kurt, voted in Sunday's united
German elections for the party they believe will deliver on its
promise.
   ``We think that the Christian Democrats are the capitalists.
They are also Christians, and we need that,'' the retired
schoolteacher said. She stood outside a poll station on a
cobblestone street made drearier by the fog drifting between
smog-blackened buildings.
   Her husband marked his 69th birthday Sunday. Unlike many older
people, he was not afraid of the end of Communist subsidies that
gave pensioners some security.
   ``Our rent starts to go up in January, 15 percent. Energy and
bus prices go up,'' he said. ``But I'm an optimist.''
   Like Neumann, Kathleen Bobbe celebrated a birthday on Sunday,
her 18th. But she said she didn't think she would exercise her new
right to vote.
   ``I just don't know, there are so many candidates,'' said
Kathleen, whose immediate goal is to go to a good school that will
lead to a well-paying job.
   Her father's brother and his two sisters - the children of a
staunch Communist - gathered with their spouses at his home to
celebrate Kathleen's birthday and talk politics. Most of them
favored Kohl.
   Kathleen's father, Klaus Bobbe, lost a factory job but recently
found work in a metal-working plant in the western German city of
Mannheim. He stays in a rooming house and makes an 11-hour round
trip home on weekends.
   ``A lot of people have given up on this area,'' he said.
   Delitzsch is 12 miles north of Leipzig, where protests against
the Communist government began last year. It is also where the
rallies for German unity began.
   Theodor Arnold, who is married to Bobbe's oldest sister, broke
with most of the family and voted for the left-leaning Social
Democrats.
   He's angry that former Communists still run the factories. He
also said the Social Democrats, the main opposition party, take
human factors into account.
   ``Our prices are now higher than in the West, but we still only
make about a third as much,'' he said.
   Arnold, 40, was 10 years old when his father moved the family
east from the former West German city of Frankfurt. The next year,
1961, the Communists closed the borders and built the Berlin Wall.
   ``My father tried to get us all out again,'' he said. ``It
wasn't too bad. He only had to serve five months in prison.''
   Arnold speaks three languages and mimics American rock and roll
on a guitar he taught himself to play. He collects models of
antique cars, studies birds, tells ribald political jokes, plays
soccer and holds a university mathematics degree.
   He bought a book, ``One Thousand Entirely Legal Ways to Avoid
Paying Taxes,'' to help him understand new Western tax laws.
   Despite education and intellect, he toils in a struggling
aluminum factory.
   ``I was from the West, I had family there, my father was in
prison and I always argued with my professors about the
Communists,'' said the father of two girls. ``It was difficult to
find a job.''
   Despite the Social Democratic Party stickers plastered on his
tiny East German car, it is the more conservative Christian
Democrats who deliver the message that captivates his neighbors.
   The party dominated East Germany's first free national elections
in March, its local elections in May and its state elections in
October.
   On Sunday, Benidikta Henger voted for them again in an election
she said was even more important than the vote for the government
that led the nation to unity.
   ``In March, we knew we were electing a government for only a
short time,'' said the 23-year-old mother of two. ``This one will
be around for a long time.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0031 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 1357EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SouthAfrica     12-02 0479</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-South Africa,0567</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ten People Die in Scattered Violence Nationwide</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TOM COHEN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JOHANNESBURG, South Africa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Ten people died in scattered
violence nationwide, police said Sunday, including five who died in
a gunfight in eastern Natal Province.
   Nelson Mandela, meanwhile, said the African National Congress
would continue its campaign of mass action against apartheid.
   He also reiterated that talks on ending apartheid and giving
political power to the black majority would be threatened if the
white-led government fails to halt chronic violence in black
townships.
   Mandela spoke at a funeral for David Tshoga, who was killed by
police in an illegal protest march. Later, the 300 people attending
marched to the northern suburb of Emmerentia, where Tshoga became
the first black buried at Westpark Cemetery.
   A police unrest report gave few details of four fatal incidents
in the previous 24 hours.
   It said three hacked and stabbed bodies were found in the
Bekkersdal black township southwest of Johannesburg, while a deputy
mayor of the Khayelitsha township near Cape Town was stabbed to
death.
   In many townships, residents oppose local leaders, whom they
consider collaborators with the government and its apartheid system
of racial segregation.
   Five people died in a clash between unidentified groups armed
with guns at Table Mountain in Natal province, and four houses were
also burned. The body of another man with bullet and stab wounds
was found in the area, the report said.
   The province, the traditional Zulu homeland, has been the scene
of fighting between Zulu supporters of the conservative Inkatha
Freedom Party and Xhosas and other blacks linked to the ANC.
   More than 5,000 people have died over five years. In August, the
black factional fighting spread to black townships near
Johannesburg, leaving at least 800 people dead.
   Both groups oppose apartheid, but they differ on the policies of
a future South African government. Inkatha favors a free market
system and promotion of tribal heritage, while the ANC advocates
leftist and pan-tribal policies.
   The ANC renewed charges this week that security forces have been
aiding Inkatha fighters in the violence around Johannesburg.
   It provided a videotape to local journalists that reportedly
showed armed Inkatha members getting out of a police vehicle and
leading a march in Zonkizezwe, a squatter camp hit by unrest in
recent weeks.
   The government declared Zonkizezwe an unrest area Thursday,
giving police wide detention powers and imposing a 9 p.m.-4 a.m.
curfew.
   The ANC refused to say who made the videotape, but claimed it
proved police were aiding Inkatha. Photos made from the videotape
appeared Sunday in South African newspapers.
   The government has denied allegations that police and soldiers
have aided Inkatha, and challenged the ANC to provide proof of
complicity.
   Law and Order Minister Adriaan Vlok said Sunday the Inkatha
members were transported in a police vehicle to negotiate with
Xhosa leaders and police. He said Xhosa leaders also were
transported in a police vehicle for the talks.
   Journalists at the scene told the Sunday Star newspaper that
three Inkatha members had negotiated with police, then left the
area in the police vehicle. The journalists, who were not
identified, said the Inkatha members later came back and dispersed
the crowd of supporters.
   Vlok criticized the ANC for releasing the video.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0032 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 1422EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Germany-Honecker     12-02 0505</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Germany-Honecker,0600</SECOND>
<HEAD>Soviet Approval Needed to Give Honecker to German Police</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Germany-Election, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DEBORAH SEWARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Officials on Sunday sought Soviet approval to
enter a Soviet military hospital near Berlin and arrest former East
German Communist leader Erich Honecker on charges of manslaughter.
   Officials said Saturday they had issued an arrest warrant for
Honecker, who was ousted last year during the peaceful East German
revolution that led to German unity Oct. 3.
   The warrant charges that Honecker personally signed
shoot-to-kill orders for guards at the Berlin Wall during his rule.
It directly links him to the deaths of several people who were
killed trying to flee East Germany, officials say.
   A Soviet diplomat said Sunday that German police need Moscow's
approval to arrest Honecker at the well-guarded hospital compound
where he has taken refuge with his wife. The hospital is outside
Beelitz, a town in former East Germany in a forest 20 miles south
of Berlin.
   Some German officials criticized the Soviets for not turning
Honecker over immediately. There were complaints that the Soviets
were trying to protect their former ally.
   Valery Zhilin, who identified himself as a first secretary at
the Soviet General Consulate in former East Berlin, said he did not
expect permission for Honecker's arrest to be granted on Sunday.
   ``It's a very complicated situation,'' Zhilin said in a
telephone interview. ``It will be decided at the very top.''
   He said that Gen. Boris V. Snetkow, the commanding officer of
the Soviet forces in eastern Germany, was away on a business trip.
   Honecker, 78, conferred with his defense lawyers on Sunday at
the hospital complex. His lawyers maintain he is too ill to stand
trial.
   The arrest warrant was issued Friday and officials began moving
against Honecker on Saturday, the eve of the first free elections
in united Germany in 58 years.
   Walter Momper, the acting Berlin mayor, told the Bonn-based Die
Welt newspaper he believed Honecker would stand trial in 1991.
   Some 200 people died trying to escape East Germany during the
28-year existence of the Berlin Wall and the barbed wire barrier
that separated the two German states.
   ``The Soviet Union must get used to German sovereignty,'' Momper
said in an interview. ``It cannot protect a German citizen from
criminal proceedings.'' The Soviet Union and the other three World
War II allies that defeated Nazi Germany had special rights in the
divided land until unification, when Germany regained its
sovereignty.
   Honecker became a citizen of united Germany when the democratic
west absorbed the once communist state of East Germany on Oct. 3.
   ``The Soviet army cannot act as Honecker's protecting power,''
said Heiner Geissler, a board chairman of Chancellor Helmut Kohl's
Christian Democratic Union.
   Testimony by Honecker could be potentially embarrassing to the
Soviet leadership.
   In a bitter newspaper interview with the eastern Berlin daily
``Wochenpost'' two weeks ago, Honecker blamed ``Soviet authors''
for his downfall on Nov. 18, 1989.
   In November, Honecker told the British weekly the European that
he was being offered as a ``scapegoat'' and said unidentified
``intriguers'' brought him down.
   The ADN news agency, quoting Honecker's lawyers, said Sunday
that he denied ever giving an interview to a journalist of the
London-based daily, and that a conversation he had with the author
of the article was ``of a purely private nature.''
   The news agency ADN reported that Honecker had not registered
for Sunday's national elections and therefore were not eligible to
vote.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0033 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 1430EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p AM-SouthernDemocrats     12-02 0572</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Southern Democrats,670</SECOND>
<HEAD>Sotthern Democrats Showing Increasing Discontent With House
Leaders</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVID PACE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Southern Democrats, whose influence in the
House has been declining steadily in recent years, are showing
increasing signs of discontent with House Speaker Thomas S. Foley
and his leadership team.
   While few Southerners are openly critical of Foley, D-Wash,.
their growing unrest has become evident in the maneuvering for this
week's House leadership elections.
   Rep. Jimmy Hayes, D-La., who is bidding for one of two open
seats on the House Appropriations Committee, has been circulating a
map of the United States among members of the Democratic Steering
and Policy Committee, the Foley-dominated group that makes
committee assignments.
   The map shows the districts of the 10 Democrats who have filled
key leadership and committee posts since House Speaker Jim Wright,
D-Texas, resigned last year.
   All 10 are from districts located north of a line drawn from
Sacramento to Washington.
   ``I think that makes the case clearly,'' said Rep. Claude
Harris, D-Ala., who is campaigning for one of the Southern regional
seats on the steering and policy committee. ``We need more
representation from our region.''
   ``I really see a writing off of the South,'' said Rep. Ed
Jenkins, D-Ga., who was defeated by Rep. Richard Gephardt, D-Mo.,
last year in the race for House majority leader.
   ``They'll accept a socialist a lot easier than they will accept
a conservative Southern Democrat,'' said Jenkins, referring to
Vermont Rep.-elect Bernie Sanders' bid to join the Democratic
caucus.
   ``It is not, I don't think, a conscious thing, but we're simply
not being well represented as a region,'' Jenkins said in an
interview last week.
   After Jenkins lost his bid for majority leader, Foley promised
he would consider Southern conservatives when making appointments
in an effort to ``provide some additional balance in the
leadership.''
   An aide to Foley said Sunday that ``a very great attempt'' has
been made to do fulfill that pledge. He noted that Rep. Beryl
Anthony, D-Ark., served as chairman of the Democratic Congressional
Campaign Committee.
   But ``the leadership still is cognizant of the desire to have a
so-called Southern leadership person ... in the smaller circle,''
said the aide, who spoke only on condition he not be named. He said
the appointment of another Southerner to a leadership position is
also being considered.
   The aide and another Foley staffer predicted Sanders, who ran as
an Independent, would not be elected to the Democratic Caucus.
   Harris, in his bid for the steering and policy seat, has been
reminding his Southern colleagues that they have little say in
committee assignments, in setting the agenda of the House or in
scheduling legislation.
   ``Our problem in particular is that our folks haven't been as
vocal as those from other parts of the country,'' Harris said.
``We've got to get in there and work to make sure our voice is
heard.''
   Southern Democrats like Harris, 50, and Jenkins, 57, say efforts
to land new leadership and committee slots for the region are
particularly crucial now, since much of the South's influence in
Congress comes from aging committee and subcommittee chairman.
   In the appropriations committee, for example, the five
Southerners who chair subcommittees range in age from 60 to 81. On
the tax-writing Ways and Means Committee, only six of the 23
members are from the South, and two of those, both subcommittee
chairmen, are over 70.
   ``If you look at the numbers and see all the people coming on
(major committees) from outside our region ... there's no question
there's going to be fewer and fewer'' Southerners in influential
positions, Harris said.
   Jenkins, who has argued for years that the South is the key that
can unlock the White House for Democrats, said the House
leadership's failure to include Southern conservatives in their
inner councils can only further erode support for the party in the
South.
   ``The end result,'' he said, ``is that they can make these
appointments or they won't have to anyway because it will be all
Republicans.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0034 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 1442EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--UnknownSoldier     12-02 0183</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Unknown Soldier,0195</SECOND>
<HEAD>Soviets Return Remains of Unknown Italian Soldier</HEAD>
<DATELINE>REDIPUGLIA, Italy (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The remains of an Italian Unknown
Soldier who died in the Soviet Union during World War II were
formally given to Italian authorities at a military cemetery on
Sunday.
   The remains symbolized the 90,000 Italians who died on the
Russian front while fighting with the German army against the
Soviets.
   The arrival of the urn at the military cemetery at Redipuglia in
northern Italy marked the beginning of a program in which Italian
remains from World War II are to be exhumed in the Soviet Union and
sent home.
   An accord on the program is to be signed in Moscow in January.
   A Soviet military delegation and Italian President Francesco
Cossiga attended Sunday's ceremony.
   ``The return of the Unknown Soldier is a sign of the times,''
said Defense Minister Virginio Rognoni at the ceremony in front of
a military shrine.
   ``With the disintegration of the walls that divided peoples,
with freedom and dialogue returning to many parts of the world
through perestroika, Italy and the USSR feel like neighbors.''
   About 40,000 people attended the ceremony.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0035 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 1452EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Gulf-Missiles 1stLd-Writethru a0664 12-02 0381</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Missiles, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0664,0438</SECOND>
<HEAD>Iraq Test-Fires Missiles, Allied Forces Take `Precautions'</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf Rdp, Bjt</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: New thuout to UPDATE with Cheney comment. No pickup.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>NICOSIA, Cyprus (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Iraq launched surface-to-surface missiles
Sunday in what appeared to be test firings, U.S. and British
military officials said. Defense Secretary Dick Cheney said they
may have been SCUD missiles.
   There were reports that allied forces in the Persian Gulf went
on alert, but U.S. military officials refused to discuss that.
   In Washington, Cheney confirmed the firings and said they were
apparently SCUD missiles ``or SCUD variants.'' He said the test tok
place entirely within Iraqi territory.
   He said Iraqi President Saddam Hussein has used SCUD missiles in
the past with conventional warheads. But he said the missiles,
which have a range of up to 400 miles, ``could conceivably carry
chamical weapons.''
   ``They're not very accurate - accurate enough to hit a city, not
accurate enough to hit a point target,'' Cheney said in an
interview on ABC-TV.
   The defense secretary said the last such test launch was in
April, four months before the Aug. 2 invasion of Kuwait.
   ``It's, I think, proof again, if anybody needed any, that he
does in fact have ballistic missiles and the capacity to use
them,'' Cheney said.
   The U.S. military's General Information Bureau in Saudi Arabia
released a terse statement about the incident.
   ``We received indications this morning that Iraqi armed forces
conducted activity that included the firing of surface-to-surface
missiles within Iraq,'' the statement said. ``The flight path of
the missiles was away from U.S. and coalition forces.''
   The U.S. and British officials did not say how many missiles
were fired or what type they were. Nor would they say how the
missiles were detected, but they were apparently monitored either
by U.S. spy satellites or AWACS airborne early-warning radar
planes, which are on patrol around Iraq and Kuwait 24 hours a day.
   None of the allied officials would say whether an alert was
ordered among the 240,000 U.S. military personnel and the
150,000-member allied force, including 16,000 Britons, massed in
the region.
   ``We are aware of missile activity within Iraq earlier today and
the necessary precuations were taken by British forces,'' said a
British Defense Ministry spokesman in London, speaking on condition
of anonymity.
   Troops in the region were reported to have been put on ``yellow
alert'' last Thursday when the U.N. Security Council passed a
resolution giving Iraq until Jan. 15 to leave Kuwait or face
possible military action.
   Yellow alert status is one category below full combat alert.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0036 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 1500EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ImageAwards     12-02 0484</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Image Awards,0578</SECOND>
<HEAD>Whoopi Goldberg, Morgan Freeman Honored with NAACP Awards</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Actress-comedian Whoopi Goldberg, rap star
M.C. Hammer and actors Morgan Freeman and James Earl Jones were
among those honored at the 23rd annual NAACP Image Awards.
   The civil war drama ``Glory'' was named best motion picture and
Fox Television's ``In Living Color'' won best TV comedy program at
the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People's
ceremony honoring black achievement.
   The Saturday night award show will be televised Jan. 16 on NBC.
   Recording nominees Oleta Adams, Randy Crawford, Miki Howard and
Dianne Reeves performed a tribute to the late jazz legend Sarah
Vaughan. Vaughan was presented posthumously with a Hall of Fame
Award.
   Miss Goldberg was named black Entertainer of the Year and also
won best supporting actress honors for her role as a spiritualist
in this year's box office smash ``Ghost.''
   Singer Dionne Warwick received the Key of Life Award from
singer-composer Stevie Wonder to recognize her commitment to
fighting AIDS and other diseases.
   In the special awards category, the President's Award for public
service was presented to Antoinette Stroman, 20, who has battled
viral encephalitis. Hall of Fame awards were given to retired
dancer Katherine Dunham and actor Jones.
   Former Los Angeles Dodgers catcher Roy Campanella and Olympic
bronze medalist Anita DeFrantz were recipients of the Jackie
Robinson Sports Achievement Award. Attorney Conrad Lynn took the
Roy Wilkins Civil Rights Award.
   The award for best film actor was presented to Freeman for his
role as a chauffeur in ``Driving Miss Daisy.''
   No award was given this year for best female actress; at the
time the nominations were announced in October, the group said in a
statement that it regretted the paucity of roles for black women
actresses and added that the lack of nominees in the category was a
sign of ``the imbalance and irresponsibility of the film
industry.''
   Oscar winner Denzel Washington received honors for best
supporting actor for his role in ``Glory.''
   In the music category, Quincy Jones won the best album award for
``Back on the Block,'' and Luther Vandross received best male
recording artist honors.
   Best vocal groups honors went to the Whispers for their album
``More of the Night,'' and Etta James won best blues artist for her
singing on ``Stickin' to My Guns.''
   Best rap group was M.C. Hammer for ``Please Hammer Don't Hurt
'Em.'' Anita Baker won best female artist for ``Compositions,'' and
the Winans were named best gospel artists for ``Return.''
   A group called After 7 won the award for best new male group
award for its album ``After 7,'' while En Vogue received the best
new female group honor with ``Born to Sing,'' and best jazz artist
was presented to Jonathan Butler for ``Deliverance.''
   In the TV category, executive producer Keenen Ivory Wayans of
``In Living Color'' won best comedy series and producers Fred
Silverman and Carroll O'Connor were awarded best dramatic series
honors for ``In the Heat of the Night.''
   For TV comedy, Kadeem Hardison and Jasmine Guy were named best
actor and actress for their roles in ``A Different World.'' Blair
Underwood was honored for best dramatic series actor for ``Murder
in Mississippi.'' Alfre Woodard won best actress honors for ``A
Mother's Courage.''
   Producer George Schlatter, who produced Sammy Davis Jr.'s
``Sitieth Anniversary Special,'' received the award for best
variety show.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0037 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 1513EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-Israel     12-02 0395</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Israel,0472</SECOND>
<HEAD>Baker Sends Israel Message of Reassurance</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf Rdp, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Secretary of State James A. Baker III has sent
a message to his Israeli counterpart assuring him that Washington's
overtures toward Iraq do not signify a change in U.S. policy,
Israel radio said Sunday.
   Foreign Minister David Levy, who read the message to the Cabinet
during its weekly meeting, expressed satisfaction with the U.S.
clarifications.
   ``There is no change in the United States' position. There is no
change in its principles against aggression, and there is no change
in its opposition to any kind of linkage between Iraqi aggression
and the Arab-Israel conflict,'' Levy told Israel radio.
   But Levy also warned that if Saddam Hussein is allowed to keep
his weapons of mass destruction he will remain a threat to Israel,
the Middle East and Europe, as well as to the world's economy, the
radio said.
   Baker apparently sent the message to reassure Israel after
President Bush offered to send Baker to Iraq to discuss a peaceful
resolution of the Persian Gulf crisis, which began with Baghdad's
Aug. 2 invasion of Kuwait.
   Bush has also invited Iraqi Foreign Minister Tariq Aziz to
Washington.
   Iraq accepted the offer, but demanded a ``serious and deep
dialogue'' that would include the Palestinian question.
   Saddam has repeatedly declared he would negotiate a withdrawal
from Kuwait if the Israelis pull out of the West Bank and Gaza
Strip, which were captured in the 1967 Arab-Israeli war. The United
States has rejected any such linkage.
   Science Minister Yuval Neeman from the right-wing Tehiya Party
drew criticism for remarks Sunday that any U.S.-Iraq talks would
threaten Israel.
   He said an agreement between Iraq and the United States would
come at Israel's expense, and equated a visit by Baker to Baghdad
with former British Prime Minster Neville Chamberlain's meeting
with Adolf Hitler in Munich prior to World War II.
   At that time, Chamberlain believed Hitler was a rational
statesman and in 1938 signed the Munich Pact, which surrendered
parts of Czechoslovakia to the Nazis without that country's
agreement.
   ``I am very much afraid that from a strong posture that (Bush)
took until now he has now moved into one that could represent
appeasement,'' Neeman said on Israel Television. ``My impression is
that if this will be the process, then we are in the position of
Czechoslovakia and this is what we have to prevent.''
   Levy said Neeman's statements were damaging and did not
represent the opinion of the Israeli government. ``The Cabinet
certainly disagrees with them,'' Levy said.
   Bush made his offer last week after the U.N. Security Council
voted to authorize the use of military force against Iraq if it has
not withdrawn from the oil-rich emirate by Jan. 15.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0038 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 1521EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Soviet-Politics     12-02 0295</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Politics,0328</SECOND>
<HEAD>Gorbachev Replaces Interior Minister</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Mikhail S. Gorbachev on Sunday named
former KGB general Boris Pugo as Interior Minister after relieving
Vadim Bakatin of the job in a possible shakeup of the country's law
and order ministry.
   Gorbachev ``released Vadim Bakatin from the duties of the Soviet
interior minister in connection with his transition to another
job,'' the state news agency Tass reported.
   Bakatin's replacement must be approved by the Supreme Soviet
legislature, the report said.
   The report did not say whether the 53-year-old Bakatin was being
promoted or punished. Officials have said there has been a sharp
rise in economic and violent crime stemming from the nation's
political crisis.
   Gorbachev has been threatening a crackdown for more than a
month. He has also said that he planned drastic changes in the
government structure, especially the Council of Ministers headed by
Prime Minister Nikolai Ryzhkov. The prime minister is widely blamed
for the failure of the government's economic reforms.
   Pugo, 53, was first secretary of the Communist Party in the
Baltic republic of Latvia in 1984-88, but was forced out due to the
growing independence movement there.
   Pugo becomes the most prominent Baltic native in a Communist
Party and government leadership that is dominated by Russians. He
is not considered popular in Latvia, however, because he was deputy
chief and chief of the KGB in Latvia from 1977-84, and has resisted
the Baltic drive for independence.
   The three Baltic republics of Latvia, Lithuania and Estonia have
declared independence this year, but Gorbachev has refused to allow
them to leave.
   Pugo, chairman of the Communist Party's Control Committee since
1988 and strong Gorbachev supporter, was appointed to take
Bakatin's place by presidential decree, Tass reported.
   He was named a non-voting member of the Communist Party
Politburo in September 1989, but was dropped last July during
reforms that drastically reduced the power of the party.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0039 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 1523EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Gulf-Embassy     12-02 0159</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Embassy,150</SECOND>
<HEAD>Inhabitants of U.S. Embassy in Kuwait Get Soft Drink Delivery</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Ten cases of Pepsi were delivered to the
beleagured diplomats at the U.S. embassy in Kuwait, President
Bush's national security adviser said Sunday.
   Brent Scowcroft said U.S. officials still don't know who sent
the Pepsi as well as the cigarettes and food that arrived earlier
in the week. Bush first mentioned the gifts during a nationally
televised news conference on Friday.
   ``We don't have any better handle on why it's happening,''
Scowcroft said on CBS-TV's ``Face the Nation.''
   ``It obviously isn't being done officially because that embassy
is surrounded and has been cut off,'' he said. ``Still no
electicity, still no water but some kind of gesture.''
   A skeleton crew of diplomats, including Ambassador Nathaniel
Howell, and some American citizens have sought refuge at the
embassy compound where they have been since Iraq invaded the
country on Aug. 2.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0040 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 1528EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r v AM-NewsDigest 1stLd-Writethru   12-02 0969</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-News Digest, 1st Ld - Writethru,1178</SECOND>
<HEAD>3:15 p.m. EST Update</HEAD>
<BYLINE>AMs AP News Digest</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>For Monday AMs</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   
   Here are the top stories at this hour from The Associated Press.
The General Desk supervisor is Stephanie Nano (212-621-1602). The
LaserPhoto Desk supervisor is Chuck Zoeller (212-621-1900).
   
   For repeats of AP copy, please call your local bureau or the
Service Desk at 212-621-1595.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>---</HEAD>
<HEAD>We will update:</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   - AM-Germany-Election, a0679, with updated results.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Upcoming:</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   WASHINGTON - The chairman of the Equal Employment Opportunity
Commission said Sunday the federal government will begin
prosecuting job discrimination cases in which individuals used as
``testers'' by civil rights and other community groups charge they
have been illegally denied employment. AM-EEOC-Testers.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>---</HEAD>
<HEAD>GERMAN ELECTIONS:
   </HEAD>
<HEAD>First Free Balloting for United Nation In Nearly Six Decades</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   BONN, Germany - The coalition led by Chancellor Helmut Kohl,
whose deft maneuvering paved the way for German unity, on Sunday
overwhelmingly won the first free all-German elections since 1932,
computer projections indicated.
   Slug AM-Germany-Election. Sent as a0679.
   By Terence Petty. LaserPhoto FRA2, Chancellor Kohl votes; FRA2,
Chancellor Kohl votes; LaserColor FRA102 matching FRA2; SAR1,
opposition candidate Lafontaine votes.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>`We want to have a better life....'</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   
   DELITZSCH, Germany - They left their homes on a gray, misty
morning to cast ballots for a brighter future. Even families could
not agree on the candidates, but they all voted for the same thing.
   Slug AM-Germany-Voting Day. Sent as a0689.
   By Mark Fritz. LaserPhoto HBG1, woman votes in traditional
costume.
   
   With:
   Slug AM-Germany-Honecker from Berlin: German police need top
level approval to enter a Soviet military hospital and arrest
former East German leader Erich Honecker who is wanted for issuing
shoot-to-kill orders at the Berlin Wall, a Soviet diplomat said
Sunday. LaserPhoto BER10, Soviet soldier guards hospital where
Honecker is staying.
   -AM-Germany-Election-Glance
   -AM-Kohl Profile.
   -AM-Germany-Berlin.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>GULF CRISIS:</HEAD>
<HEAD>Iraq Warns Soviets on Troops; 15 More Americans Freed</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   UNDATED - Saddam Hussein's armies rattled nerves around the
Persian Gulf Sunday with the first test of surface-to-surface
missiles since the invasion of Kuwait. The Iraqi president said the
chances of war in the region stand at ``fifty-fifty.'' In
Washington, Secretary of State James A. Baker III said the United
States would not attack Iraq - provided Iraqi troops are withdrawn
from Kuwait and foreign hostages are freed.
   Slug AM-Gulf Rdp. Sent as a0702.
   By Laura King. LaerPhotos AMM2, AMM3, Muhammed Ali arriving in
Amman with released hostages from Georgia and Texas; MLA1, a
release Philippine hostage kissing Iraqi pilot of her flight home;
LaserColor AMM102 matching AMM2; DHR1, Air Force guard mans machine
gun at sundown.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Baker Says U.S. Won't Attack If Saddam Withdraws From Kuwait</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   
   WASHINGTON - Secretary of State James A. Baker III promised
Saddam Hussein on Sunday that the United States will not attack
Iraq if Iraqi troops are withdrawn from Kuwait and Western hostages
are freed.
   Slug AM-US-Gulf. Sent as a0706.
   By Joan Mower. LaserPhoto WX6, Secretary of State Baker and Sen.
Edward Kennedy appearing on Sunday morning news show.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Selective Service Ready To Turn on the Tap - If Needed</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   
   WASHINGTON - Seventeen years after the government's authority
for a military draft expired, the Selective Service System is alive
and well - and on standby.
   Slug AM-Gulf-Dormant Draft. Sent as a0680.
   By Nancy Benac.
   
   With:
   - AM-Gulf-Iraq from NICOSIA, Cyprus - Iraq warns President Bush
not to use proposed talks on the gulf crisis ``as a pretext with
the American people to justify his aggression against Iraq,'' and
again insists the Palestinian issue be discussed. It also warns the
Soviet Union not to send troops to the gulf.
   - AM-Gulf-Iraq-Shortages from MANILA, Philippines - Food
supplies are running so low in Iraq and Kuwait that people must
stand in line for hours or scavenge through the trash in order to
survive, Filipino workers returning from the two countries said
Sunday.
   - AM-Gulf-Marines from CAMP LEJEUNE, N.C.: Thousands of Marine
reservists uprooted from their homes and families have accepted
their participation in Operation Desert Shield with a mixture of
resignation and understanding.
   - AM-Gulf-Missles.
   - AM-Gulf-Israel.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>CHAD: Rebel Leader Rides Into African Capital</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   N'DJAMENA, Chad - Rebel leader Idriss Deby entered the capital
in triumph Sunday, and Libyan news reports said deposed President
Hissene Habre had been killed near the Sudanese border.
   Slug AM-Chad. Sent as a0699.
   By Mahamet Hissene. LaserPhoto NY10; filer of Hissene Habre.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>SPACE: Columbia Astronauts In Orbit, Japan Reporter On Soviet
Flight</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   CAPE CANAVERAL, Fla. - Columbia's astronauts, thrilled to
finally be orbiting Earth, activated telescopes inside the space
shuttle Sunday for more than a week of probing galaxies, quasars
and other hot, turbulent objects.
   Slug AM-Space Shuttle. Sent as a0708.
   By Marcia Dunn. LaserPhotos CSB5,7, Columbia lifts off; HTN1, TV
image of space observatory in shuttle bay.
   
   With:
   BAIKONUR COSMODROME, U.S.S.R.-dated AM-Soviet-Space - A Japanese
television reporter became the first journalist in space on Sunday
aboard a Soviet rocket launched into orbit as part of a Kremlin
campaign to commercialize its space program. LaserPhoto BAIK1,
Soyuz lifts off; NY9, cosmonauts at Saturday news conference.
   - AM-Shuttle-Astronaut Thumbnails, 2 takes.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>BUSH-SOUTH AMERICA: Visit Focus on Economic Cooperation</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   WASHINGTON - President Bush's visit to South America this week
comes at a time when American concerns are turning from the Cold
War to economic cooperation in this hemisphere.
   Slug AM-Bush-South America. Sent as a0687.
   By George Gedda. Bush departure scheduled early evening EST.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>QUAKE DAY: Nothing Shaking But the Leaves on the Trees</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   MARKED TREE, Ark. - A practice earthquake drill featuring a fake
temblor with strictly-on-paper damage totals was about the only
thing shaking Sunday in the region where a scientist has projected
a 50-50 chance of a major earthquake.
   Slug AM-Earthquake Projection Rdp. Developing.
   By Janet K. Isbell. LaserPhoto staffing.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>JAPAN: 100 Years After Birth of Parliament, Japan Struggles With
Democracy</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   TOKYO - Japan has a parliament that rarely decides things, a
leader who rarely leads and an entrenched bureaucracy that is
rarely challenged, but its unique brand of democracy seems to work.
   Slug AM-Japan-Democracy. Sent as a0666.
   By Michael Hirsh
</TEXT>
<HEAD>OLYMPIC NEIGHBORHOODS: In Atlanta, Residents At Future Site Worry</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   ATLANTA - Douglas Dean stopped in front of the stadium site for
the 1996 Summer Olympics, and sighed at the sight of crumbling
homes and crime-ridden streets.
   Slug AM-Olympic Neighborhoods. Sent as a0677.
   By Lauran Neergaard. LaserPhoto AX1, Douglas Dean at future
Olympics site.

</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0041 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 1529EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People-Lancaster     12-02 0183</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People-Lancaster,0202</SECOND>
<HEAD>Burt Lancaster Resting After Stroke</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOS ALAMITOS, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Actor Burt Lancaster was resting at
a hospital Sunday after suffering a stroke that left him weak on
his right side and made his speech difficult, a hospital official
said.
   ``I can say his condition is basically unchanged,'' nursing
supervisor Ardi Smith said Sunday. ``He's having some difficulty
with speech. But at the request of the family, I'm not able to say
more than that.''
   He had been listed in serious condition Friday. At a hospital
news conference Saturday, Jack M. Ostrow, Lancaster's friend and
financial adviser for 44 years, said he was stable, adding that the
77-year-old actor was in ``fine'' spirits.
   ``All doctors have advised it will be several days till they're
able to give a full report as to the nature and extent of his
treatment and recovery,'' Ostrow said.
   Lancaster has starred in more than 60 movies. He won an Oscar in
1960 for his portrayal of an evangelist in ``Elmer Gantry.''
   The actor was visiting a friend at the John Douglas French
Center for Alzheimer's Disease Friday when he collapsed in a chair
and was taken to the hospital.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0042 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 1533EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-Iraq     12-02 0563</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Iraq,0683</SECOND>
<HEAD>Iraq Warns Soviets Against Sending Troops to Gulf</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf Rdp, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ED BLANCHE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NICOSIA, Cyprus (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Iraq on Sunday issued a strong message to
the Soviet Union, warning it not to send troops to the Persian Gulf
to help the multinational force.
   Baghdad also told President Bush not to use proposed talks with
Iraq on the gulf crisis ``as a pretext with the American people to
justify his aggression against Iraq.''
   The statements were among a number of declarations by the
official Iraqi News Agency, the Foreign Ministry, state-controlled
newspapers and parliament. They gave the impression of growing
defiance by Baghdad in the face of mounting international resolve
by Washington and its allies to end Iraq's occupation of Kuwait.
   The message to Moscow came from the Foreign Ministry, the Iraqi
News Agency said. It said it was a response to Soviet Foreign
Minister Eduard Shevardnadze's statement Thursday that ``everyone
should know that we will not hesitate to use force'' to protect the
estimated 3,000 Soviet citizens still in Iraq.
   The same day, the Soviet Union backed a U.N. Security Council
resolution authorizing military force to free Kuwait if the Iraqis
do not get out by Jan. 15.
   An unidentified Iraqi Foreign Ministry spokesman said
Shevardnadze ``seems to be looking for a pretext to send troops to
the region.'' He warned the Kremlin to ``go no further than it has
gone so far.''
   The statement made no overt threat against the Soviets in Iraq
and said they ``enjoy full care and security.''
   The Soviets have two warships in the gulf region, but they have
not apparently taken part in the U.S.-led multinational naval force
blockade of Iraq. The Kremlin has said it would not become
militarily involved unless its forces were under U.N. command.
   Moscow has a friendship treaty with Baghdad and was its main
arms supplier during the 1980-88 war with Iran.
   The Soviets have played a key mediation role in the crisis, but
have also become impatient with Saddam's refusal to withdraw from
Kuwait.
   The comments by Iraqi officials came as a Soviet envoy met with
senior Iraqi officials Sunday seeking the release of Soviet
citizens, mainly oil specialists and technicians.
   There were about 10,000 Soviets, including several hundred
military advisers, in Iraq and Kuwait before the invasion. Most
have been allowed to leave in groups.
   Iraq has blamed ``misunderstandings and bureaucracy'' for the
delays in evacuating the remainder.
   Iraq's ruling Revolutionary Command Council said Saturday it
accepted Bush's offer to send Secretary of State James A. Baker III
to Baghdad for talks on the gulf crisis.
   But it said the talks must include the issue of Israel's
occupation of Arab land.
   The Iraqis have repeatedly linked their occupation of Kuwait
with the ``Palestine issue,'' but the Americans have rejected that
linkage.
   First Deputy Prime Minister Taha Yasin Ramadan said Sunday that
the Bush administration's desire for talks ``indicates a retreat
after grasping that world and Arab public opinion uncovered its
misleading behavior for achieving its own interests,'' the official
Iraqi News Agency reported.
   The Al-Qadissiyah newspaper stressed that Iraq was not
interested in a ``pro-forma meeting, which Bush needs to overcome
his domestic problems and which he might use as a new pretext with
the American people to justify his aggression against Iraq.''
   Bush's overture to Iraq was widely seen as a move to placate
Congressional critics and others counseling against military action
that could result in thousands of casualties and create political
turbulence in the Middle East.
   Bush doesn't appear to have any formula to offer Iraq to induce
it to quit Kuwait and has repeatedly stressed that there is nothing
to negotiate.
   He said Friday that no ``big results'' should be expected from
any talks with Iraq.
   More than 350,000 troops are in the Persian Gulf as part of the
US.-led multinational force. American troops, now numbering more
240,000, are expected to swell to around 400,000 by next month.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0043 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 1545EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-WeatherService     12-02 0586</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Weather Service,0706</SECOND>
<HEAD>Newspaper Says Weather Service Fails On Severe Weather Spotting</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CLEVELAND (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The National Weather Service has fallen short
of its mission to warn the public of savage weather that claims
more than 400 lives and causes $6 billion in damage every year, a
newspaper reported Sunday.
   The federal agency misses two-thirds of all tornadoes,
three-fifths of all flash floods and 40 percent of severe
thunderstorms every year, The Plain Dealer reported.
   Severe storms strike without warning from the weather service
more than 4,000 times and without a preliminary ``watch'' 5,000
times each year.
   Government forecasters failed to issue warnings in two of this
year's most deadly storms in the Midwest - a flash flood in
Shadyside in June that killed 26 people and tornadoes in northern
Illinois in August that left 29 people dead.
   For every five floods that cause at least $500,000 in damage,
three occur without any warning, the newspaper said.
   The newspaper said its investigation was based on an analysis of
weather service internal computer records and other data, including
statistics assembled from 1987 to 1989 by the Services Evaluation
Branch, which grades forecasting offices and trains personnel for
the NWS Office of Meteorology.
   For the last eight years, the agency's own investigations of
disaster foul-ups repeatedly have cited the same causes: A shortage
of forecasters, obsolete equipment, poor communications and, in
some cases, incompetence.
   ``As I look through status reports on existing systems, I don't
have a month go by in which we don't have at least a half a dozen
radars around the country out for a significant period of time ...
because of basic components,'' weather service Director Elbert W.
Friday Jr. told the newspaper.
   He offered little hope for quick improvement.
   ``We're keeping (the weather service) tied together now ith the
proverbial baling wire and chewing gum,'' he said.
   The weather service budget has had only slight budget increases
in recent years, and in some spending categories, cuts have
resulted in sharp personnel cutbacks. The current $330 million
operating budget gives the weather service the same buying power it
had in the 1960s.
   Experts say that advances in technology allow forecasters to
alert the public in advance of all severe thunderstorms, and nearly
all floods and large tornadoes, the newspaper said.
   Friday acknowledged that despite antiquated equipment that is
not to be replaced until 1995, weather offices should be able to
issue warnings for 70 percent to 75 percent of all severe storms,
including tornadoes, thunderstorms and flash floods.
   Data from the Services Evaluation Branch shows that no warnings
were issued for 68 percent of all tornadoes and 64 percent of all
flash floods from 1987 to 1989. Fifty-one percent of all flash
flood warnings were issued after the floods began. Forecasters
failed to warn of 17 out of 27 killer floods. Four of every five
tornado warnings and six of every 10 flash-flood warnings were
false alarms.
   Even when tornado warnings were issued, the public had only an
average seven to 10 minutes to get to safety, the figures showed.
   ``We're not doing too well,'' said meteorologist Bill Lerner,
one of the weather service's official scorekeepers in the Services
Evaluation Branch.
   The weather service has, however, succeeded in the past.
   In February 1982, weather service forecasters in Fort Wayne,
Ind., urged the mayor to prepare emergency shelters and fill
sandbags. Seventeen days later, they predicted a flood within 24
hours and issued an official warning. Floods struck as predicted,
killing 12. But 15,000 people had moved to shelters and local
officials credited the forecasters with saving the city.
   In addition, some of the service's 249 forecasting offices do
better than others, the newspaper said.
   In Shreveport, La., forecasters have accurately issued warnings
for more than 80 percent of all storms there, said chief forecaster
Ernest Ethridge.
   By contrast, Chicago's weather office, which failed to warn of
the Aug. 28 tornado that killed 29 people, has the worst record in
the nation, the newspaper said. In the last three years, it has
issued warnings for only 24 percent of all severe storms in its
jurisdiction.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0044 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 1555EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AP-Testers     12-02 0418</FIRST>
<SECOND>EEOC-Testers,470</SECOND>
<HEAD>EEOC To Accept `Tester' Complaints of Job Discrimination</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DENISE CABRERA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The chairman of the Equal Employment
Opportunity Commission said Sunday the federal government will
begin prosecuting job discrimination cases in which individuals
used as ``testers'' by civil rights groups charge they have been
illegally denied employment.
   The new policy extends the use of testers - long a tactic in
housing discrimination suits - to the federal employment bias arena
for the first time.
   ``It's used in housing cases and used by other state agencies,
and I couldn't see why it couldn't be used by the commission,''
Evan J. Kemp Jr., chairman of the EEOC, said in a telephone
interview.
   ``Testers'' - or individuals from minority and women's groups
who historically have been victims of discrimination - have posed
as renters or home buyers to win housing discrimination suits.
   The Supreme Court in 1982 said such activities were legal even
if the testers did not intend to rent or buy.
   However, the government never has used the testimony of testers
to prosecute job discrimination cases.
   Kemp said the new commission policy, announced Friday, would
address one of the ``weaknesses'' of the EEOC system.
   ``People that apply for a job in answer to a newspaper ad can be
discriminated against and they won't know it,'' under current
circumstances, Kemp said.
   The EEOC chairman said he was confident his agency has the legal
authority to bring the cases because the ``courts address this all
the time and make a determination whether an employer has
discriminated or not.''
   Representatives of the business community could not be reached
for comment Sunday on the new policy.
   But Stephen Bokat of the U.S. Chamber of Commerce told The
Washington Post that ``proving the case'' of job bias against an
employment tester would be ``infinitely more difficult than it is
in the housing context.''
   In housing the ``only issue is whether someone is financially
capable of paying the rent on the property or buying a piece of
property,'' Bokat was quoted as saying in Sunday's editions of the
newspaper.
   In job testing cases, ``there are all sorts of things, how
articulate the person is ... lots more subjective considerations
that go into a decision,'' Bokat said.
   Kemp admitted there may be some difficulties in implementing the
policy and said his agency was still deciding ``how we're going to
work it.''
   There are no current tests set up, Kemp said, but the agency
would initiate proceedings on charges brought by civil rights and
community groups.
   Kemp said the policy was prompted by the case brought by city
and state authorities against a temporary employment agency in New
York City after a report on CBS-TV's ``60 Minutes'' program showing
the use of testers.
   Kemp said he expects the policy to come up during previously
scheduled meetings with representatives of several women's groups
on Tuesday.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0045 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 1600EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brite-DelayedWedding     12-02 0149</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brite-Delayed Wedding,0150</SECOND>
<HEAD>Former Sweethearts Wed After 70-Year Misunderstanding</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DECATUR, Ill. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two sweethearts have married after mending
a disagreement that kept them apart for almost 70 years.
   Charles Jones and Thelma Colvin dated as teen-agers in the
1920s, but a spat at a street party in Springfield ended their
romance - temporarily.
   Jones broke off a two-year relationship with Colvin after seeing
her strolling with another man, despite her protests of innocence.
   When they met again last fall, both widowed, the dispute no
longer mattered. They got married Thursday in Decatur's Macon
County Courthouse.
   ``I still think she was seeing that other guy,'' Jones, 84,
joked.
   His bride, 85, insisted she wasn't.
   ``I just happened to meet a chum I had known in school while I
was out that evening,'' she said. ``There was nothing in it, but
Charles didn't believe me.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0046 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 1618EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-EEOC-Testers     12-02 0425</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-EEOC-Testers,470</SECOND>
<NOTE>EDS: Retransmitting a0717 to restore cycle designator</NOTE>
<HEAD>EEOC To Accept `Tester' Complaints of Job Discrimination</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DENISE CABRERA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The chairman of the Equal Employment
Opportunity Commission said Sunday the federal government will
begin prosecuting job discrimination cases in which individuals
used as ``testers'' by civil rights groups charge they have been
illegally denied employment.
   The new policy extends the use of testers - long a tactic in
housing discrimination suits - to the federal employment bias arena
for the first time.
   ``It's used in housing cases and used by other state agencies,
and I couldn't see why it couldn't be used by the commission,''
Evan J. Kemp Jr., chairman of the EEOC, said in a telephone
interview.
   ``Testers'' - or individuals from minority and women's groups
who historically have been victims of discrimination - have posed
as renters or home buyers to win housing discrimination suits.
   The Supreme Court in 1982 said such activities were legal even
if the testers did not intend to rent or buy.
   However, the government never has used the testimony of testers
to prosecute job discrimination cases.
   Kemp said the new commission policy, announced Friday, would
address one of the ``weaknesses'' of the EEOC system.
   ``People that apply for a job in answer to a newspaper ad can be
discriminated against and they won't know it,'' under current
circumstances, Kemp said.
   The EEOC chairman said he was confident his agency has the legal
authority to bring the cases because the ``courts address this all
the time and make a determination whether an employer has
discriminated or not.''
   Representatives of the business community could not be reached
for comment Sunday on the new policy.
   But Stephen Bokat of the U.S. Chamber of Commerce told The
Washington Post that ``proving the case'' of job bias against an
employment tester would be ``infinitely more difficult than it is
in the housing context.''
   In housing the ``only issue is whether someone is financially
capable of paying the rent on the property or buying a piece of
property,'' Bokat was quoted as saying in Sunday's editions of the
newspaper.
   In job testing cases, ``there are all sorts of things, how
articulate the person is ... lots more subjective considerations
that go into a decision,'' Bokat said.
   Kemp admitted there may be some difficulties in implementing the
policy and said his agency was still deciding ``how we're going to
work it.''
   There are no current tests set up, Kemp said, but the agency
would initiate proceedings on charges brought by civil rights and
community groups.
   Kemp said the policy was prompted by the case brought by city
and state authorities against a temporary employment agency in New
York City after a report on CBS-TV's ``60 Minutes'' program showing
the use of testers.
   Kemp said he expects the policy to come up during previously
scheduled meetings with representatives of several women's groups
on Tuesday.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0047 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 1635EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Poland-Anti-Semitism     12-02 0512</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Poland-Anti-Semitism,0595</SECOND>
<HEAD>Catholic Bishops To Attack Centuries Of Anti-Semitism In Poland</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DRUSILLA MENAKER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WARSAW, Poland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Poland's Roman Catholic bishops will for
the first time issue a pastoral letter attacking the anti-Semitism
that has darkened the country's name for centuries.
   The letter, to be read at all Masses on Sunday, Jan. 20, is the
most explicit statement on Catholic-Jewish relations ever issued by
the Polish church.
   The move comes as anti-Semitism is reappearing in the nation's
political life in the post-Communist era. It also follows criticism
from international Jewish groups who say they are dismayed by
church foot-dragging and concerned about whether its January
statement will condemn specific anti-Semitic incidents.
   The Episcopate Commission for Dialogue with Judaism told the
official PAP news agency Saturday that the pastoral letter
expresses ``regret over any instances of anti-Semitism on Polish
soil.''
   It said the letter recalls Polish-born Pope John Paul II's
teaching that anti-Semitism contradicts Christian values.
   The letter, which caps two years of work by the commission and
is endorsed by the bishop's council, can be expected to carry
enormous weight among Poles, 93 percent of whom consider themselves
Catholic.
   The text was not disclosed. But the Rev. Stanislaw Musial, the
commission secretary, recently issued the first statement by a
ranking church official on Polish Catholic culpability in the Nazi
extermination of 3 million Polish Jews during World War II. He also
spoke of discrimination in Poland before and after the war.
   ``For every Pole of Christian faith who did not stretch his
helpful hand to you in those days and after ... who betrayed you to
the Nazis ... who tried to enrich himself on your fear and
loneliness, for all these, we beg your pardon,'' the priest wrote
in the influential Catholic Tygodnik Powszechny weekly.
   Sources in Poland's religious communities acknowledged there was
disagreement among the bishops about how strong a statement to
issue.
   Jewish groups generally praised the latest plans, but questioned
whether they are enough.
   ``I am very glad something like this will be done, and I hope it
will be sufficiently specific to hit the consciences of many of the
churchgoers,'' said Stanislaw Krajewski, representative of the
American Jewish Congress in Poland and a leader of its tiny Jewish
community.
   ``But I really hope that some specific things are said ... that
`Jew' is used as a word of abuse more generally ... and that the
unfortunate issue of who is Jewish ... was so heavily used during
the presidential campaign.''
   During the current presidential campaign, rumors circulated that
the Catholic Prime Minister Tadeusz Mazowiecki was Jewish or that
Jews dominated his government.
   Mazowiecki's defeat in the first round of voting Nov. 25 was
attributed mainly to discontent with economic reforms, however.
   The American Jewish Congress in mid-November questioned the
delay in issuing the Catholic document and said ``the current
resurgence of anti-Semitism in Poland has not been sufficiently
addressed by the church.''
   Jews have lived in Poland since the 13th century. In the Middle
Ages, the country was a haven for some Jews fleeing persecution
elsewhere in Europe, although even then they suffered widespread
discrimination.
   Poland's 3.5 million Jews were one-tenth of the population in
1939. Only about 500,000 survived the war.
   Afterward, some were threatened and even killed when coming home
to recover family property. Waves of emigration, including a 1968
Communist-backed purge, have reduced the Jewish population to a few
thousand mostly elderly people.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0048 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 1643EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-TradeTalks 1stLd-Writethru a0691 12-02 0589</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Trade Talks, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0691,0702</SECOND>
<HEAD>Trade Officials Seek Solution to Crisis</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: New thruout to UPDATE with new quotes, no progress in
agricultural talks; No pickup.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By MARTIN CRUTSINGER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Economics Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BRUSSELS, Belgium (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Trade ministers searched on Sunday for
an 11th-hour miracle to rescue stalled free trade talks but failed
to make any progress on the biggest stumbling block: how to reduce
costly farm subsidies.
   There was some progress reported on another dispute involving
removing barriers to trade in financial services. But a series of
meetings on the agriculture question yielded no results.
   The activity came as delegates from 107 nations prepared to open
five days of formal negotiations Monday in hopes of completing a
four-year effort to overhaul the world trading system.
   The talks, known as the Uruguay Round for the nation where they
began in 1986, were being held under the auspices of the General
Agreement on Tariffs and Trade.
   Australian Trade Minister Neal Blewett, chairman of the Cairns
Group of 14 major farm-exporting countries, said the entire
bargaining effort was ``in deep crisis.'' He said what happens over
the next 48 hours would likely decide whether the negotiations
could succeed.
   ``There is a general recognition that agriculture is at the
heart of the crisis ... and that blockage is poisoning other parts
of the negotiations,'' he told reporters.
   The Cairns Group, supported by the United States, is attempting
to scale back agriculture subsidies, which cost consumers and
taxpayers $250 billion annually.
   However, the 12-nation European Community and Japan have
resisted, contending the measures go too far and would cause
massive political unrest among farm groups in their nations.
   U.S. Agriculture Secretary Clayton Yeutter held what he termed
``sparring'' sessions with both Ray MacSharry, the EC's agriculture
chief, and Japanese Agriculture Minister Tomio Yamamoto. He said
that neither the Europeans nor the Japanese were signalling any
willingness to compromise.
   ``Unless both Japan and the European Community begin to
demonstrate greater commitment to trade liberalization in
agriculture, I see no way of reaching'' an overall Uruguay Round
agreement, Yeutter said.
   The United States and the Cairns Group are pushing a proposal
that would cut export subsidies by 90 percent, while reducing
internal farm support payments and barriers to farm imports by 75
percent.
   The United States has also been lobbying heavily to get Japan to
show good faith in the farm area by removing its ban on the import
of rice, a barrier that forces Japanese consumers to pay seven
times the world market price.
   Without an agreement in agriculture, U.S. Trade Representative
Carla Hills said Third World nations would walk away from the
bargaining table, dooming the most ambitious reform effort in 43
years.
   On another dispute, officials reported some progress Sunday in
an effort to get countries to extend the GATT coverage to trade in
service industries such as banking and insurance.
   Canadian Trade Minister John Crosbie told reporters that Canada,
with the support of several other countries, would put forward a
proposal Monday to address removing barriers in financial services.
He said the measure had the support of both the United States and
the EC.
   But with just five days to go until the negotiations are
scheduled to conclude Friday, there were still many blank spaces in
the draft 291-page agreement, prompting a growing sense of failure.
   ``We are going to do our best to try to make it work, but it is
going to take an 11th-hour miracle,'' said U.S. Commerce Secretary
Robert Mosbacher, one of four members of President Bush's Cabinet
in Brussels for the negotiations.
   This is the eighth round of negotiations aimed at lowering
tariff and non-tariff barriers to trade.
   The negotiators are also attempting to extend GATT's rules to
trade in services as well as writing rules to govern the theft on
intellectual property rights, principally by Third World nations.
Such thefts of copyrights and patents cost American businesses an
estimated $60 billion annually.
   In all, 107 nations from Austria to Zimbabwe are involved in the
negotiations, either as full-fledged members of GATT or observers,
a category that includes China.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0049 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 1647EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Soviet-FoodAid     12-02 0480</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Food Aid,0573</SECOND>
<HEAD>American Donations of Food and Medical Supplies Arrive in Moscow</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ANN IMSE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   ``To the Soviet people from the people of the
United States - with love,'' read the banners on 40 tons of donated
food and medical supplies that arrived in Moscow Sunday.
   It was the first of many shipments planned by the
Connecticut-based aid organization, AmeriCares, to help relieve
Soviet citizens faced with barren grocery shelves and severe
shortages of imported medicines.
   Soviet television showed soldiers and students unloading cartons
of medical supplies from the Southern Air Transport cargo plane.
   Dr. Vasily Drozdov, head of the Republican Children's Clinic,
said the medicine, for children under the age of three, arrived at
his hospital late Sunday.
   The Soviet Union's chronic shortages of food and medicine have
worsened dramatically this winter. Consumers must wait in long
lines - often for as long as three hours - for basics such as
butter. Sometimes, pushing and shoving breaks out over a scarce
item.
   The shortages are caused in part by the country's transition
from a centralized planning system to a free market, which has not
yet taken hold. The centralized distribution system is breaking
down in anticipation of changes.
   A shortage of foreign currency that forced a cut in imports
earlier this year has also caused shortages, although President
Mikhail S. Gorbachev has now won promises of billions of dollars of
new credits and aid from abroad.
   In addition, the country doesn't have enough rail cars or
refrigerated trucks to transport food from the fields to markets,
nor are there sufficient storage facilities. Theft and diversion to
the black market is rampant.
   Thus, despite normal levels of food production and a spectacular
grain crop, food is not reaching consumers at the usual subsidized
prices.
   Prime Minister Nikolai Ryzhkov gave a televised address after
the evening news Sunday, calling on people to work together to
overcome the food crisis.
   ``Everyone is pulling in different directions,'' he said,
referring to individual republics and regions that are refusing to
sell their food to other districts.
   Soviet television said AmeriCares plans to send 450 tons of food
and medicine. AmeriCares representative Ty Cordova said he would
stay and supervise up to the last shipment to ensure the supplies
are not lost in the black market - or in the constant breakdowns of
the Soviet cargo transport system.
   Drozdov said his clinic so far had received only medicine, and
no food. ``We don't really need food at the moment. Nutrition at
the clinic is all right,'' he said.
   Doctors from the Mayo Clinic in Minnesota and Memorial
Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center in New York City traveled with the
AmeriCares staffers and will discuss further supply needs with
Soviet medical specialists.
   AmeriCares representatives in the United States said an
80,000-pound shipment of food and medical supplies was to be given
to the clinic and two orphanages in Moscow. Another 250,000 pounds
of supplies is scheduled to be sent to the Soviet Union on Dec. 26,
a spokesman for AmeriCares said Saturday.
   Since the Armenian earthquake two years ago, AmeriCares has sent
at least 15 shipments of aid to the Soviet Union.
   Another planeload of food arrived from Germany on Friday for
distribution among hospitals and orphanages. Italy and Austria have
also promised food and medical supplies.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0050 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 1704EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People SUB a0700 12-02 0208</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People, SUB, a0700,0221</SECOND>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS JAKARTA, Indonesia-dated item in AM-People, a0700, to
RESTORE dropped word `said' in 6th graf, `Bali Gov...'.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>JAKARTA, Indonesia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Hindu leader in Bali says British
rock singer Mick Jagger's recent wedding to longtime girlfriend
Jerry Hall was illegal and merely imitated parts of a traditional
Balinese wedding ceremony.
   I Wayan Surpha, chairman of the Indonesian Hinduism Association
in Bali's capital of Denpasar, said Jagger has not yet met
conditions to be a follower of Hinduism, the official Antara news
agency reported Saturday.
   Jagger, 47, and Hall, a 34-year-old model from Texas, married
Nov. 21 in Bali.
   Ida Pedanda Sukawati, a Hindu priest, said he presided over the
ceremony, which included a rite signifying entrance into Hinduism,
the agency reported. The couple also signed a statement indicating
they had converted.
   But Surpha objected, saying, ``It should not be so easy to hold
such ceremony.''
   Bali Gov. Ida Bagus Mantra also said traditional weddings
``should not be given too easily'' to foreigners vacationing in
Bali, the agency reported. Bali is one of the islands that make up
Indonesia.
   Jagger publicist Lisa Somes did not immediately return a
telephone message left Sunday with an answering service for Rogers
&amp; Cowan, a New York public relations firm with which she works.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0051 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 1708EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Bangladesh     12-02 0511</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bangladesh,0592</SECOND>
<HEAD>More Protesters Hit Streets in Bangladesh, Dozens Reported Killed</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DHAKA, Bangladesh (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   More anti-government protesters poured
into the streets Sunday, and an opposition leader said dozens of
people were killed and thousands wounded since emergency rules were
decreed five days earlier.
   The new protests broke out when the government of President
Hussain Muhammad Ershad relaxed a curfew for 12 hours. About 500
university teachers announced they were quitting their jobs to
protest the emergency orders suspending civil liberties.
   The Interior Ministry said security forces broke up ``an unruly
mob'' that tried to ransack stores and burn vehicles in Dhaka's
maintain downtown shopping area. No details were given.
   But in general, the law-and-order situation was improving, the
ministry claimed in a news release.
   After curfew was re-imposed at sundown Sunday, paramilitary
troops in another part of the capital were seen removing the body
of a young man in civilian clothing. Bullet wounds were visible on
his body, but the circumstances of his death could not be
ascertained, according to passerby who spoke on condition of
anonymity.
   State-run television said curfew would be lifted for 15 hours on
Monday, from 6 a.m. to 9 p.m. The government has gradually been
extending the number of hours people are allowed to leave their
homes.
   The government eased press censorship for international news
agencies but cautioned correspondents against ``misreporting.''
   Ershad, who seized power in a bloodless coup in 1982, imposed
emergency rule in an effort to quell six weeks of unrest led by
university students and the two chief opposition parties.
   The leader of the opposition Awami League, Sheik Hasina, said
Sunday in a statement that 17 people were killed in various clashes
around the country on Saturday. She said that brought the death
toll to 75 since emergency rules went into effect Tuesday night.
   About 3,000 people have been wounded, she said.
   Two leaders of her party were arrested on Sunday, she said in a
written statement. She said that brings the number of people
arrested during the state of emergency to 5,000.
   The government has said only six people have been killed since
the emergency was imposed.
   In the past, some opposition claims have been exaggerated, while
some government counts have been understated. No independent
verification of their claims was possible.
   About 1,000 lawyers, artists, students and journalists assembled
in front of National Press Club, shouting ``Ershad must quit!''
``We don't want emergency!'' and ``Down with press censorship!''
More than 100 policemen in riot gear watched but did not intervene.
The gathering broke up peacefully.
   In Chittagong, a port city 125 miles southeast of Dhaka, 300
professors and lecturers at Chittagong University announced their
resignations. Another 200 doctors and teachers at the Sir Salimulla
Medical College in Dhaka also said they were quitting, effective
Monday, according to a statement from the students union.
   Ershad, a 60-year-old former army general, told the paramilitary
Bangladesh Rifles that the opposition campaign has ``no political
objective and it is aimed at destroying the national economy.''
Part of his speech was shown on state-run television Sunday.
   The opposition alliance called for a nationwide transportation
strike starting Tuesday. They also called for the creation of
People's Action Committees in cities and villages to resist the
government and its supporters.
   The opposition is demanding that Ershad step down and allow a
caretaker government to supervise free elections. They claim that
previous elections held since Ershad took power were rigged.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0052 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 1717EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Gulf-Saddam     12-02 0343</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Saddam,0422</SECOND>
<HEAD>Saddam Defends Hostage-Holding, Says He's Open to Talks</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf Rdp, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Saddam Hussein said in a television interview aired
Sunday that he believes the chances of war in the Persian Gulf
stand at ``fifty-fifty,'' but that he is open to talks.
   The Iraqi leader also said Iraq does not posses nuclear arms,
and he defended the holding of foreign hostages.
   The interview, with the French network Antenne 2, was the first
Saddam has granted to a foreign television network since the U.N.
Security Council last week adopted a resolution authorizing force
against Iraq if its troops remained in Kuwait as of Jan. 15.
   The Iraqi president repeatedly refused to respond to questions
about a possible Iraqi withdrawal from Kuwait, which his forces
have occupied since Aug. 2.
   But in the interview, taped in Baghdad Saturday, Saddam said he
was ready to talk with U.S. officials if they came ``in a spirit of
dialogue'' and did not set preconditions.
   He said the holding of an estimated 3,000 Western hostages was
``one of the means that we think is capable of preventing war.''
   He said if the United States wanted the hostages freed, it
should pledge that it will not resort to force prior to March 25.
   The Iraqi president had offered earlier to free all the hostages
between Christmas and March 25 if nothing happens to mar ``the
atmosphere of peace.''
   The Antenne 2 interviewer asked Saddam about the chances of war
in the region. ``Fifty-fifty,'' the Iraqi leader replied.
   Elaborating on that, he cited the U.S. offer to send Secretary
of State James A. Baker III to Baghdad for talks.
   ``If they want to make this meeting a raal path toward dialogue,
then we are closer to peace,'' he said.
   ``But if they want to make this meeting nothing other than a
formal exhibition for the American Congress, the American people or
international public opinion, simply to give themselves good
conscience to say, `There, we've tried to dialogue with Iraq,
without Iraq renouncing its positions' - in that case, we're closer
to war.''
   Saddam denied that his government possessed nuclear weapons, but
said he would let the world know if that were the case.
   ``But we don't possess nuclear arms,'' he said.
   U.S. officials have raised the possibility of Iraq developing
nuclear capability in coming years, and said that would be one
reason to move against Saddam.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0053 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 1723EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Philippines-Bases     12-02 0571</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Philippines-Bases,0668</SECOND>
<HEAD>Critical Round Of U.S. Bases Talks This Week in Philippines</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT H. REID</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MANILA, Philippines (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   U.S. and Philippine negotiators will
tackle the difficult issue of compensation when they resume talks
this week on the future of six American military bases in this
country.
   In preparation for the talks, which Filipino sources say will
resume Tuesday, U.S. officials restricted the movements of the
40,000 U.S. troops, Pentagon civilians and military dependents
living here.
   Last May, Communist rebels killed two U.S. airmen near Clark Air
Base on the eve of an opening round of talks. Despite a standing
threat from the New People's Army, there were no attacks against
Americans during later sessions in September and November.
   At issue in the talks is the future of Clark Air Base, the Subic
Bay naval base and four smaller installations the Americans hold
under an agreement that expires in September.
   Foreign Secretary Raul Manglapus, the chief Philippine
negotiator, has demanded Philippine control over Clark and the
smaller bases next year.
   But the government has left open the possibility of extending
the U.S. stay at Subic, considered the most strategic installation,
for 5-7 years. Filipino officials have said they might let the
Americans keep access to Clark on a commercial basis.
   Chief U.S. negotiator Richard Armitage has acknowledged the
American military presence will be scaled down under any new
agreement. But U.S. officials would like a phasedown period to
vacate the bases, followed by an arrangement under which the
Americans maintain a residual presence.
   Philippine officials say the upcoming round will discuss how
much the Americans will pay for use of the facilities. U.S. sources
familiar with the talks say the Philippine panel has so far not
raised the compensation issue or given any indication of what it
considers an acceptable figure.
   In 1988, the Reagan Administration agreed to seek $960 million
in aid over two years for use of the bases through 1991.
   But last year, Congress cut the Bush Administration's aid
request for the Philippines, provoking charges that the United
States had reneged on its pledge.
   The Philippines would like the new agrement to include
iron-clad guarantees of aid. American officials have consistently
refused to go beyond a pledge to exert their ``best efforts'' to
meet aid targets.
   ``This time we are not talking about an executive agreement but
a treaty, and the best efforts device is not applicable,''
Manglapus said in a recent interview.
   An acceptable compensation arrangement is considered critical to
prospects for approval of the new agreement in the Philippine
Senate.
   Under the 1987 Constitution, any new agreement must be covered
within a formal treaty ratified by two-thirds of the 23-member
Philippine Senate.
   Previously, the status of U.S. bases was formalized under an
executive agreement between chief executives of the two countries.
   Last week, an informal survey conducted by Senate President
Jovito Salonga found 12 senators opposed to allowing the Americans
to stay beyond the September deadline. That would be enough to
defeat any agreement allowing U.S. forces to remain.
   But diplomatic observers believe an acceptable compensation
package, perhaps including trade concessions rather than cash,
would sway enough senators to win agreement.
   Compensation has become all the more urgent for the Philippines
because of the country's economic crisis, worsened by the rise in
world petroleum prices and the effects of an earthquake that killed
nearly 1,700 people last July.
   Finance Secretary Jesus Estanislao and others fear that the
Americans would not exert their influence with the International
Monetary Fund and other lending institutions on behalf of this
country if no agreement on the bases can be reached.
   In addition, recent surveys show growing pro-bases sentiment
among the 61 million Filipinos. If the final package appears
favorable to the Philippines, some senators may switch their stand
rather than face the electorate in the 1992 elections after voting
to shut down the installations.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0054 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 1738EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Gulf-Marines     12-02 0346</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Marines,0415</SECOND>
<HEAD>Marine Reserves Bolster Regular Corps</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf Rdp</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto RA1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By L.L. GRIMMER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CAMP LEJEUNE, N.C. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Thousands of Marine reservists
uprooted from their homes and families accepted their pending
participation in Operation Desert Shield with a mixture of
resignation and understanding.
   ``We all signed up for it and now we've got to do it,'' said
22-year-old Lance Cpl. Kevin Nobis of Waterloo, Iowa.
   Between 10,000 and 12,000 of the 43,000 Marine Corps reservists
in the United States will call this eastern North Carolina base
home during an intense training period before their likely
deployment to the Middle East later this month, said Lejeune
spokesman Maj. Jay Farrar.
   The first group arrived Nov. 26, and the Camp Lejeune Military
Processing Center has inoculated, shaved, shorn and dog-tagged
about 1,000 a day since.
   ``This event is brought to you by Saddam Hussein,'' reads a sign
inside the center just above a cartoon depicting the Iraq leader in
a gun sight.
   ``We sent out roughly 10,000 Marines when this began,'' Farrar
said. ``Now we're bringing that many through again.''
   About 80 percent of the Marine reserves called to action will
join with active duty troops for two to four weeks' training.
   ``People think the reserves are just weekend warriors, but we
really train hard and we know how to do the job. We just need some
practice,'' Lance Cpl. Richard Nordenbrook, 21, of Fairfax, Va.,
said Sunday at an anti-tank missile practice range.
   ``People always talk about them being weekend warriors,'' said
active duty Marine Lt. Mike Nosbisch, 24, of Buffalo, N.Y. ``But
they've got a mission here, too, and that mission is to go to war.
   ``Whether or not people want to hear that, that's what it is.''
   About 50 men trained with live missiles for the first time since
the reservists arrived a week ago.
   As the reserves sat nearby observing the exercise, mortar shells
exploded about 1,000 meters out into the practice range providing a
smoke screen as two armored trucks carrying anti-tank TOW missiles
raced out of hiding and into position.
   The reservists sat out of the action, but if the Camp Lejeune
unit goes to Saudi Arabia, their newest members will go right along
with them.
   ``If my country needs me then I'm here,'' said Nordenbrook.
``None of the active duty troops want to go either, but none of us
are complaining.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0055 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 1738EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>d a AM-BRF--JailBreak     12-02 0150</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Jail Break,0152</SECOND>
<HEAD>Inmates Use Waiting Ladders in Escape</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MARTINEZ, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Six inmates escaped from jail by
climbing ladders construction workers left standing against a wall,
authorities said.
   Four of the men were still at large Sunday, said Contra Costa
County Sheriff's Sgt. Hal Rogers.
   ``Any felon should be considered dangerous, but these men were
not in for such violent crimes as homicide or rape,'' Rogers said.
``They were sentenced for things like robbery or burglary.''
   The six escaped Saturday night, while other inmates set off fire
alarms to distract guards.
   The fugitives knocked out the window of a door leading to a
courtyard with a desk, said Rogers.
   ``The construction people working in that section forgot to put
away the ladders and they just climbed them,'' he said.
   Two of the men were captured shortly after the escape was
discovered just after midnight.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0056 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 1754EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-Iraq-Shortages     12-02 0373</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Iraq-Shortages,0454</SECOND>
<HEAD>Filipinos Tell Of Food Shortages In Iraq and Kuwait</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf Rdp, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By EILEEN GUERRERO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MANILA, Philippines (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Filipinos who arrived from Iraq and
Kuwait on Sunday said Iraqi soldiers are looting grocery stores and
homes, and even scavenging for scraps from departing foreigners.
   They also told of long lines for food and sky-high food prices.
They said food prices in Baghdad had jumped ten-fold because of the
United Nations sanctions imposed following Iraq's Aug. 2 invasion
of Kuwait.
   Some of the 437 Filipinos, who arrived in Manila on a flight
from Basra, Iraq, also said Iraqi soldiers were still looting
groceries and homes in occupied Kuwait.
   ``There's so much hunger there,'' Lorenza Panaranda, 30, said of
conditions in Basra, Iraq's second largest city. ``When we threw
away our leftovers, about 10 Iraqis scrambled over our leftovers in
the trashcan at the airport. We left whatever food we had with
them.''
   Gregorio Neri, an Arabic-speaking mechanic who acted as
interpreter for the group in Iraq, said consumers in Basra stand in
line for up to four hours to buy a single loaf of bread.
   ``The life of the Iraqis now is hard,'' he said. ``Filipino
lives may be difficult, but theirs is miserable. I would never
change places.''
   Willie Leola said that when his group, which included five
infants, cleared customs at Basra airport, customs guards asked for
their leftover baby formula.
   The Filipinos arrived aboard an Iraqi Airways jet on a flight
paid for by the International Organization of Migration.
   An estimated 90,000 Filipinos were working in Kuwait and Iraq
before the Iraqi invasion.
   Miss Panaranda, who had worked as a sales clerk in Kuwait, said
she went to Baghdad last month and then to Basra for the flight.
She said shoopers waited for hours to buy limited supplies of food
in Baghdad.
   ``There were queues for food all over,'' she said. ``Instead of
rice, they eat gruel made of corn.'' She said that in one
neighborhood, shoppers were limited to five kilos of rice per
month.
   Conchita Balisi, 27, a former governess in Kuwait, said most
groceries are closed in the occupied city.
   ``Some Kuwaitis go to Saudi Arabia to buy food and then sell it
back in Kuwait,'' she said.
   Lisa Santuyo, a maid in Kuwait, said Iraqi soldiers were looting
homes and shops of food, appliances and other goods to ship back to
Iraq.
   ``At night, there is shooting,'' she said. ``Families would then
pray as they wept. Soldiers go to houses and Kuwaitis are afraid,
especially if Iraqi soldiers find out they have relatives in the
army.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0057 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 1755EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-GulfExercise     12-02 0312</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf Exercise,0339</SECOND>
<HEAD>Marines Hold Amphibious Exercise</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf Rdp, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KAREN SLOAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>IN EASTERN SAUDI ARABIA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   U.S. Marines began a four-day
amphibious exercise in the Persian Gulf, military officials said
Sunday. They refused to say whether the maneuvers were a practice
invasion of Kuwait.
   Few details were provided about the exercise. Military officials
refused to disclose the exact location of the practice landings,
the number of Marines involved or whether forces from other
countries were taking part. But they indicated that U.S. warplanes
were taking part.
   The maneuvers, codenamed Amphibex, are the fourth amphibious
exercise since Operation Desert Shield began in early August
following Iraq's invasion of Kuwait.
   The military said elements of the 4th Marine Expeditionary
Brigade and the Navy's Amphibious Task Group Two were taking part.
   The exercise is smaller than maneuvers last month, codenamed
Imminent Thunder. That six-day exercise involved thousands of
Marines, sailors and airmen and was described as the biggest since
the U.S. deployment began.
   Saudi Arabian forces participated and British and Saudi combat
aircraft joined American Air Force and Marine squadrons mustered
for the exercise.
   Unlike in Imminent Thunder, the forces taking part in Amphibex
are allowed to fire their weapons in the air and on the ground,
officials reported.
   The Marines are also slated to use helicopters and hovercraft in
the latest exercise, scheduled to end Wednesday.
   Officials declined comment when asked whether Amphibex is a
rehearsal for an actual landing in Kuwait.
   There are more than 240,000 U.S. military personnel deployed in
Desert Shield. Another 200,000 more are en route or being sent
soon.
   Desert Shield's amphibious capability is provided by 45,000 men
of the 1st, 4th and 7th Marine Expeditionary Brigades. They make up
the 1st Marine Expeditionary Force, the largest Marine force
assembled since the Vietnam War.
   An additional amphibious group comprising the 2nd Marine
Expeditionary Force from Camp Lejeune, N.C., will be deployed by
mid-January. It has roughly 45,000 men.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0058 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 1811EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-EarthquakeProjectionR Bjt   12-02 0556</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Earthquake Projection Rdp, Bjt,0687</SECOND>
<HEAD>Drills, Exodus Highlight Quake Watch</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JANET K. ISBELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MARKED TREE, Ark. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The earth stood still Sunday, as usual.
The only thing moving was the stream of jumpy residents fleeing in
fear of an earthquake.
   New Mexico scientist Iben Browning projected a 50-50 chance of a
major temblor along the New Madrid fault for the five days that
began Saturday. The fault's southern end is under this town of
about 3,200 people. It runs northeast to Cairo, Ill.
   Browning, 72, bases his theory on the gravitational pull of the
sun and moon, which he says will be particularly strong during the
period.
   On the basis of that, dozens of people have packed their things
and left town.
   Scientists have scoffed at his projection. But these same
scientists say an earthquake is likely someday.
   So even skeptical residents, like convenience store cashier
Rheba Womack, aren't taking any chances.
   ``If this doesn't happen, I don't want to hear anything else
about earthquakes,'' Mrs. Womack said.
   A few hours later, on Saturday night, Mrs. Womack and her
husband, Scott, left town, joining the temporary migration.
   Those who stayed prayed.
   ``Bless all of us, oh Father, that are upset about the
earthquake,'' said Ira Whitfield when he oened Sunday school at
St. John Missionary Baptist Church.
   Church Deacon Sterling Ivy said he had expected the crowd to be
smaller than usual. It was, what with some people suddenly out of
town and others afraid to leave their houses.
   The same concern has closed schools in parts of Tennessee,
Arkansas, Missouri, Kentucky and Illinois for a few days early this
week.
   Judy Byrd of Evansville, Ind., isn't waiting for local school
administrators to decide. Though she said she doesn't believe
earthquakes can be projected, her 11-year-old son won't be in
school Monday.
   ``He asked me if he could stay home,'' Mrs. Byrd said. ``At this
age, they really worry about everything. War. An earthquake. Water.
The environment. I figured if he really was that worried about it,
it should be up to him.''
   Other people were looking for a more precise warning.
   In Illinois' St. Clair County, residents were watching cats,
dogs and cows for signs of nervousness.
   ``If we notice any exceptional behavior, we will not hold school
Monday,'' said Superintendent Bill Gullick of the county's Marissa
Community Unit School District 40.
   The Chinese have been using that method to anticipate
earthquakes for more than 1,000 years, Gullick said.
   Some people here have chosen to stay put. What they're afraid
of, they say, is worse than any earthquake: looters and bad
publicity for the town.
   Police Officer Jay Woods said looting hasn't been a problem,
especially with a lot of people gone.
   ``I stopped a lady for speeding last night, and she said,
`Officer, I'm just in a hurry to get through Marked Tree.'''
   Woods couldn't bring himself to write her a ticket, he said.
   While residents wrestled with their anxieties about whether to
stay or go, emergency experts in Arkansas were busy Sunday planning
for an earthquake they could believe in.
   In an earthquake disaster drill planned long before Browning's
projection, officials were assessing an imaginary toll of death and
destruction from a hypothetical earthquake. On paper, the quake
laid waste to much of the northeastern part of the state.
   The drill, involving the Arkansas National Guard and other state
and federal agencies, was based on a worst-case scenario of an
earthquake measuring 7.6 on the Richter scale.
   The Richter scale is a gauge of the energy released by an
earthquake, as measured by ground motion recorded on a seismograph.
   The make-believe quake hit Friday. By Sunday, according to the
drill's script, the toll in eastern Arkansas had reached 4,950
dead, 25,097 seriously injured and 98,020 left homeless.
   ``Realistically we would still be in a search and rescue mode,''
said Gary Talley of the Arkansas Office of Emergency Services,
which coordinated the drill.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0059 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 1813EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Poland-Mazowiecki     12-02 0457</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Poland-Mazowiecki,0523</SECOND>
<HEAD>Polish Prime Minister, Defeated for President, Founds New Party</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN DANISZEWSKI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WARSAW, Poland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Prime Minister Tadeusz Mazowiecki on
Sunday urged supporters of his failed presidential bid to vote for
Lech Walesa, but called for creation of a new political party to
oppose the Solidarity leader in the future.
   ``In the face of the irresponsibility that may endanger Poland
and everything we have been struggling for 10 years, we should cast
our ballots in favor of Mr. Walesa,'' said Mazowiecki at the
founding of the new Union of Polish Democracy.
   The prime minister referred to the campaign of Stanislaw
Tyminski, the wealthy emigre who came from obscurity to reach the
presidential runoff election on Sunday, Dec. 9.
   ``This does not mean an agreement with his vision of democracy
in Poland and his style of action,'' Mazowiecki said of Walesa.
   Mazowiecki was an adviser of Walesa's for nine years until
becoming the East Bloc's first non-Communist prime minister in
August 1989. Mazowiecki has said he will leave office when the new
president is chosen.
   Despite his third-place showing in the first round of the
presidential elections Nov. 25, the prime minister received a
hero's welcome from about 1,000 supporters at Warsaw University on
Sunday.
   He was cheered for five minutes in the crowded hall when he
appeared, and frequently was interrupted by applause as he spoke to
the audience that included members of his election campaign
committees.
   ``We didn't win,'' Mazowiecki said. ``But our rationales exist
and are deeply rooted in the society. Our most important task today
is to keep together those millions of friends and to create a
political formation. I am convinced that we will ... be a key
element on the Polish political scene.''
   The party later was officially founded by acclamation by members
of Mazowiecki's campaign committees, and representatives of two
other pro-Mazowiecki groups present: the Citizens Movement for
Democratic Action and the Forum of the Democratic Right.
   Meanwhile, Walesa adviser Zdzislaw Najder, addressing a
conference of local Citizens Committees, criticized Mazowiecki's
camp for having denigrated the Solidarity leader as ``unpredictable
and unsteerable'' in the first round.
   In other political developments, Walesa remained in Warsaw after
a Saturday evening news conference with Tyminski and planned to
attend the funeral of a Roman Catholic bishop. Tyminski scheduled
an evening rally in the northeastern city of Bialystok.
   Earlier, Tyminski went to the 10th anniversary gathering of the
Communist-backed Union of Rural Youth in Warsaw. Among guests at
the gathering was Waldemar Swirgon, a former Central Committee
secretary and leader of the main Communist youth organizations in
the late 1970s and 1980s, the official PAP news agency reported.
   Tyminski has been criticized for ties to the former Communist
elite in Poland. Walesa has termed his candidacy an attempted
``counter-revolution,'' but Tyminski says he accepts support from
various quarters.
   A scheduled nationally televised debate between Walesa and
Tyminski on Sunday night did not take place. Tyminski had insisted
it be postponed until Thursday, and did not appear at the Warsaw
television studio.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0060 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 1829EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-WeatherpageWeather     12-02 0176</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Weatherpage Weather,0162</SECOND>
<HEAD>Snow in Midwest, Rain Dampens South</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Snow fell Sunday on the country's northern midsection and rained
farther south.
   Upper Michigan, central North Dakota, central and southern
Nebraska, northeastern Missouri, west-central Illinois, central
Colorado, southeastern Wyoming and central Montana got snow.
   Fort Collins, Colo., was thrashed by winds gusting to 60 mph.,
the National Weather Service said.
   Rain came to west-central Missouri and poured across
northeastern and east-central Illinois, north-central and southern
Kentucky, Tennessee, northern Alabama, eastern and southwestern
Mississippi, southeastern Louisiana and south-central Arkansas.
   Rain was also scattered in northwestern Washington state.
   And occasional thundershowers intensified the rain that fell
across north central and from central Texas to south central Texas.
   The morning low in the Lower 48 was 18 degrees below zero at
International Falls, Minn.
   Temperatures around the nation at 3 p.m. EST ranged from 5
degrees at Grand Rapids, Mich., to 88 at Harlingen, Texas.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0061 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 1834EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-CaveSearch     12-02 0369</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Cave Search,0442</SECOND>
<HEAD>Five Students Trapped in Cave By Flood Waters Emerge Unscathed</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN KEKIS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW SCOTLAND, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Five college students were surprised,
shivering and shaking when they emerged unscathed after being
trapped by a flash flood for more than seven hours in the depths of
a mile-long cave.
   ``We were all very scared,'' Scott Baisch, a senior at Syracuse
University, said Sunday. ``We thought we would die there.''
   Baisch and four companions had entered Onesquethaw Cave, located
in an isolated area about 10 miles southwest of Albany, about 2
p.m. Saturday.
   They became trapped a little more than two hours later when a
beaver dam on a tiny lake about three miles from the cave entrance
burst, sending a torrent of water cascading down a stream bed and
into the 50-foot-deep cave.
   The cave began to flood when the three men and two women were
about three-quarters of the way in.
   The students had last been seen entering the cave early Saturday
afternoon by another party of spelunkers from Massachusetts, who
alerted police after the dam burst.
   State police divers and other rescuers entered the cave early
Saturday evening, but were turned back by high water after
exploring nearly 500 feet.
   Divers and experienced spelunkers eventually made it in as far
as 850 feet, but the searches were called off temporarily about 9
p.m. while authorities worked feverishly to shore up the dam with
shale to prevent it from collapsing again.
   ``We all thought we were going to drown,'' said Lynn Cowan, a
student at Columbia University who said she's through spelunking.
``At first I just panicked. I had never really considered that I
could die this young.''
   Besides Baisch and Cowan, the group consisted of Laura Selicaro
and Nicholas Springer, both Syracuse students, and Peter Bowie, a
student at Cornell University.
   The five, who said they huddled in a pile to stay warm and
exercised periodically to ward off hypothermia, walked out shortly
after 11 p.m. as search parties were awaiting the go-ahead to
re-enter the cave.
   Horns from several emergency vehicles blared in celebration, and
about 100 rescue workers cheered. The students were taken to local
hospitals, observed for exposure and released.
   ``They knew what happened with the water coming in, and they
just waited it out like they should have and just walked out,''
said Rick Russo of Albany County Dive Rescue. ``They were more
apologetic than anything when they walked out and saw everybody
around.
   ``They kept saying, `We're sorry.' And we said, `It's no
problem. You're alive.'''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0062 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 1846EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Japan-Space     12-02 0352</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Japan-Space,0420</SECOND>
<HEAD>A Cosmic Show: Japan Watches First Japanese in Space</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Soviet-Space, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Japan watched with pride Sunday as the first
Japanese - and the first journalist of any nationality - traveled
into space as a paying passenger aboard a Soviet rocket.
   Television reporter Toyohiro Akiyama's company, TBS, paid $12
million for his ticket to ride. It is spending about $37 million
altogether on the project. In the streets of Tokyo, Japanese
clustered around television sets the company had placed at
strategic locations to view the fiery launch that took place on
steppes of Soviet Central Asia.
   ``It is like a dream,'' said a middle-aged man, watching.
   With single-minded determination - and a huge infusion of cash -
the company assigned 270 staffers to the story, 170 in the Soviet
Union and 100 in Tokyo. Many employees wear badges reading ``Earth
we love'' - the project's slogan.
   With so much money and effort being expended, TBS offered what
amounted to saturation coverage.
   Television viewers saw Akiyama board the craft and heard him say
his farewell - a quick ``ittekimasu,'' the standard Japanese phrase
on setting out that translates roughly as ``Back later.''
   He made his first report two hours after the launch.
   ``Right now I am flying over the Soviet Union. It is becoming
evening. What I can see from the window is darkness. There is a
hazy blue earth below, blackish dark blue. ... The earth is blue
after all,'' he said.
   Although much of TBS' coverage of Akiyama's trip will be
exclusive, other stations were being supplied with footage for news
purposes.
   The Japan Broadcasting Corp., the national public television
network, showed the liftoff on its evening news, but led off its
newscast with another story - Japanese hostages' families visiting
them in Iraq.
   But the space flight was a front-page story in the nationwide
newspaper Asahi Shimbun, which also ran a page of features inside.
   Tomoji Oshima, director general of Japan's Science and
Technology Agency, called Akiyama ``the first Japanese cosmonaut.''
   ``I only pray for his return without any trouble,'' said Izumi
Tanaka, the president of TBS. He said Akiyama, a news director,
would get a promotion after the mission's end, scheduled Dec. 10.
   Akiyama, who quit a four-pack-a-day cigarette habit during
training for the mission, was asked before liftoff what he looked
forward to most on his return. ``I can't wait to have a smoke,'' he
said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0063 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 1850EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Germany-Quotes     12-02 0118</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Germany-Quotes,0114</SECOND>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   ``This is a day of great joy. This is a great success and
something to be proud of.'' - German Chancellor Helumt Kohl, on his
center-right coalition's projected victory in the first free
all-German elections since 1932.
   ---
   ``The party must fundamentally change if we are still to remain
a party in the future.'' - Hubert Kleinert, Greens leader in the
outgoing West German parliament, on his party's ouster from the new
all-German parliament.
   ---
   ``We have another large reason to be happy, and that's the
result in Berlin.'' - Helmut Kohl on the conservative victory in
the election in reunited Berlin.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0064 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 1853EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Germany-Berlin 2ndLd-Writethru a0693 12-02 0353</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Germany-Berlin, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0693,0401</SECOND>
<HEAD>Christian Democrats Lead in Berlin</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 6 grafs to UPDATE projected results. Picks up 8th
graf pvs, `Last month's ...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By KEVIN COSTELLOE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Berlin voters on Sunday gave conservatives the
upper hand in the first all-Berlin elections in 44 years, according
to computer projections.
   The voting marked the final return of Berlin to the city's 4
million people after decades of serving as a pawn of the
superpowers.
   Where Soviet soldiers once faced off against U.S., British and
French forces across the Berlin Wall, there is now one united city.
   Both the ZDF and ARD TV networks projected that the Christian
Democratic Union, under former Mayor Eberhard Diepgen, would win
40.1 percent of the vote and take first place.
   But the party needs support to form a majority in the city
government. Diepgen said his party might try to form a ``grand
coalition'' with the leftist Social Democrats, who were projected
to win 30.3 percent of the vote for second place.
   ``A difficult negotiating period is in the offing,'' said the
ARD television network.
   Last month's street battles between Berlin police and squatters
caused the collapse of the leftist coalition that had governed the
city. The local Greens, the environmentalists, had accused Social
Democratic Mayor Walter Momper of sending in police units to oust
the squatters without consulting the coalition's junior partners.
   The Christian Democrats, in turn, had played on voters' fears of
growing lawlessness.
   Berlin's results reflected the nationwide voting trends, which
gave a resounding victory to the leader of the Christian Democrats,
Chancellor Helmut Kohl.
   ``We have another large reason to be happy,'' Kohl told cheering
supporters in Bonn. ``And that's the result in Berlin.''
   Up until last fall, the authoritarian Communist Party had ruled
in East Berlin.
   Democratically elected governments governed West Berlin under
the protection of the victorious World War II allies: France,
Britain and the United States.
   Berlin has been the focus of many of the problems of German
unification, which has strained housing and social services. People
in former East Berlin are demanding a quick improvement of their
dismal standard of living.
   ``In Berlin, we have to solve a lot of the problems of the
growing together of the two countries more quickly than
elsewhere,'' Diepgen said. ``There is social tension.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0065 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 1907EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Israel-Strike     12-02 0296</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel-Strike,0333</SECOND>
<HEAD>Israeli Unions Strike Over Wage Dispute with Government</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A general strike on Sunday idled Israel's
airports, curtailed radio broadcasts and shut schools, offices and
clinics in a dispute over tax increases and the minimum wage.
   More than 500,000 Israeli government employees heeded the strike
call by the Histadrut Labor Federation after the Cabinet added a
5-percent levy to income taxes to finance Soviet immigration. The
levy was part of a broader package of austerity measures.
   Flights carrying immigrants were to be diverted to military
airfields, said Israel army radio, which was not affected by the
walkout. Workers in essential services heeded government
back-to-work orders.
   Officials of the Jewish Agency, which sees to bringing the
immigrants to Israel, stayed on the job saying they did not want to
add to the newcomers' difficulties.
   Originally the strike was supposed to last 24 hours. But after
overnight negotiations broke down in disagreement Sunday morning,
union leaders said it would continue until a settlement was
reached.
   The main dispute is a government plan to cut the minimum wage by
about 20 percent from $520 a month to $417, and a 20 percent tax on
pension savings.
   ``These are painful issues. The workers cannot be pushed to the
wall,'' said Yisrael Kessar, general secretary of the Histadrut, an
umbrella organization for most of the nation's workforce.
   Aryeh Stein, a spokesman for the Clerks' Unions, said the
pension taxes in effect meant an additional 5 percent pay cut to
wage earners seeking to maintain their pension levels.
   ``We don't object to the special levy for immigrants, but this
should be instead of other taxes and not in addition to them,''
Stein said in an interview.
   Prime Minister Yitzhak Shamir urged negotiations to continue
through Sunday to resolve the dispute.
   The Histadrut represents about 1.5 million workers, but those
employed in private business were exempted from striking, keeping
most banks open and public buses running.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0066 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 1915EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Britain-FilmAwards     12-02 0139</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Britain-Film Awards,0139</SECOND>
<HEAD>`Porte Aperte' Wins Top European Film Award</HEAD>
<DATELINE>GLASGOW, Scotland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Italian film ``Porte Aperte'' was
named European Film of the Year on Sunday during presentations of
the Felix awards, the European version of the Oscars.
   Britain's Kenneth Branagh received the Actor of the Year award
for his role in ``Henry V,'' which was named Young European Film of
the Year.
   Carmen Maura was named top actress for her role in the Spanish
film ``Ay Carmela.''
   ``Porte Aperte,'' a political thriller set in 1930s Italy, was
directed by Gianni Amelio and produced by Angelo Rizzoli.
   The Felix awards were presented in Glasgow, one of its last
events as European City of Culture in 1990.
   Swedish director Ingmar Bergman headed the jury, which included
actresses Deborah Kerr and Jeanne Moreau.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0067 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 1936EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-US-Gulf 2ndLd-Writethru a0706 12-02 0735</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-US-Gulf, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0706,820</SECOND>
<HEAD>Baker: U.S. Won't Attack if Iraq Withdraws From Kuwait, Frees
Hostages</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Inserts 5th graf, ``As he left xxx to update with Bush remark;
subs 13th graf, 13th, ``The U.N. xxx to delete first reference to
Bush, now higher</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By JOAN MOWER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Secretary of State James Baker A. III assured
Iraq on Sunday the United States will not attack that nation if
Saddam Hussein withdraws his troops from Kuwait and frees the
Western hostages.
   Baker, who is preparing to visit Iraq before Jan. 15 for talks
on the gulf crisis, made the promise to Saddam, the Iraqi
president, while insisting there will be no negotiating on the
substance of the U.N. resolutions calling for Iraq to get out of
Kuwait.
   An Iraqi official, hinting that a resolution was possible to the
increasingly tense international standoff over Kuwait, said his
country was willing to discuss ``all the issues.''
   Previously, Saddam has claimed that Kuwait had been annexed as a
new province of Iraq.
   As he left Washington Sunday evening for Brazile, President Bush
declined to respond directly to reporters' questions about details
of pending talks. ``I'm very pleased with the way it's going, but
we'll see,'' was his only response.
   If Saddam meets the U.N. conditions - withdrawal from Kuwait,
freedom for hostages and the restoration of Kuwait's legitimate
government - then there can be discussions of Iraqi grievances
against Kuwait, Baker said on NBC-TV's ``Meet the Press'' program.
   He said talks should be between Kuwait and Iraq, which claims
Kuwait is siphoning oil from an oil field along their common
border. Iraq also contends it was denied a viable port on the
Persian Gulf when Kuwait was created in 1961.
   Moreover, Baker said the United States would not launch an
attack against Iraq to drie Saddam from power if the U.N.
conditions are met.
   ``There's never been any suggestion that force would be used if
the U.N. resolutions were fully complied with,'' Baker said.
   ``That would give some assurance, it seems to me, that if he
complied with the resolutions, his reward for that would not be a
military attack by the United States,'' Baker said.
   Iraq on Saturday said it was willing to receive Baker as long as
the talks were tied with a resolution of Israel's occupation of
Arab lands. But Baker rejected that demand.
   Baker called the issues ``two entirely different questions and
we're not here to link them.''
   The U.N. Security Council passed a resolution last week setting
a Jan. 15 deadline for the use of force against Iraq if no Saddam
doesn't withdraw from Kuwait, and Baker, along with Defense
Secretary Dick Cheney and national security adviser Brent
Scowcroft, on Sunday elaborated on Bush's efforts to find a
peaceful solution to the crisis.
   Aside from offering to send Baker to Baghdad, Bush said Friday
he would ask Iraqi Foreign Minister Tariq Aziz to come to
Washington next week for talks on the gulf.
   Senate Republican leader Bob Dole of Kansas suggested Sunday
that congressional leaders also go to Iraq to show support for
Bush's efforts.
   Baker said officials were discussing arrangements for the
Baghdad and Washington meetings, ``assuming that the meetings are
going to take place.''
   Bush's diplomatic gesture followed a week of hearings on Capitol
Hill during which several former high-ranking military officers
urged the administration to show restraint and give economic
sanctions against Iraq more time to work. The hearings resume
Monday with testimony by the administration.
   But Baker said there was an ``excellent chance'' Saddam would
withdraw from Kuwait once he understands the depth of opposition to
him.
   A U.S.-led multinational force has arrayed more than 350,000
troops against Saddam in the Persian Gulf. U.S. forces, now
numbering more than 240,000, are expected to swell to around
400,000 by next month.
   Abdul Amir Anbari, the Iraqi ambassador to the United Nations,
was asked if his country was prepared to talk about withdrawing
from Kuwait.
   ``We would be willing to talk about all the issues that exist in
the region,'' he said on ABC-TV's ``This Week With David Brinkley''
program.
   ``Our president made it quite clear ... that there is no
exception and we make no reservation and no condition,'' he said
when pressed on the issue.
   Some American officials have questioned whether the Middle East
will ever be safe as long as Saddam remains in power, possesses
chemical weapons and is encouraging a nuclear program.
   Cheney, on the ABC, said the ``overall focus'' of U.S. policy is
``the long-term proposition if Saddam Hussein is not stopped. It's
the prospect of having a man who has acquired an enormous force,''
he said.
   In August, Bush said ``some countries around the world'' hope
Saddam would be overthrown by his own people. And he has said that
Iraq's nuclear program is a threat.
   While the United States remains concerned about Saddam's
weapons, Baker said ``We would have to find a way to address those
issues'' in the aftermath of a resolution of the Kuwaiti crisis.
   The three U.S. officials raised doubts about the sanctions
against Iraq, which Sen. Edward Kennedy, D-Mass., a member of the
Senate Armed Services Committee, has encouraged.
   ``I want to see sanctions work,'' Kennedy said on NBC. ``They
are effective. ... I believe we can avoid war and I believe it is
important we do avoid war.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0068 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 1939EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Chad 2ndLd-Writethru a0730 12-02 0889</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Chad, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0730,1089</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rebel Chief Enters Capital; Report Ex-President Killed</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 5 grafs for 14-15 pvs bgng ```Nothing confirms...' to
UPDATE with Libyan denunciation of Habre; pickup 16th pvs `About
1,000...</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY10</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By HISSENE MAHAMAT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>N'DJAMENA, Chad (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Rebel leader Idriss Deby entered the
capital in triumph Sunday and vowed to establish a new government.
Conflicting reports emerged over the fate of deposed President
Hissene Habre.
   A Libyan news agency said Habre was killed near the Sudanese
border, but diplomats and other sources said Habre and his family
flew in a military plane to Cameroon, west of Chad, before dawn
Saturday. Neither report could be independently verified.
   Deby, who helped Habre lead a coup in 1982, arrived in N'Djamena
in a black Mercedes, escorted by all-terrain vehicles. He refused
to recognize the remnants of Habre's government as the country's
legitimate authority, but declared his Patriotic Salvation Movement
would institute a democracy.
   There were no immediate reports of deaths in the takeover, but
the French relief agency Doctors Without Borders said it treated
120 people hurt in rioting Saturday.
   ``My worry is not to be president of the republic,'' said Deby,
who served as Habre's chief military adviser from 1982 to 1989.
``This country must become democratic, pluralist. The moment has
come to lay down our arms.''
   Deby did not rule out being president, but said the decision
would rest with his party. He said he wants to meet with Alingue
Bawayeu, president of Chad's National Assembly and the
highest-ranking politician left in the capital.
   Deby also urged reconciliation with Goukouni Oueddei, the
president he and Habre toppled in 1982. Oueddei is exiled in Libya.
   On Sunday, Deby met French Ambassador Francois-Xavier Gendreau.
The ambassador, however, declined to say whether he tried to
persuade Deby to negotiate with Bawayeu.
   Last year, Habre accused Deby of plotting a coup, and Deby fled
to Sudan and organized a rebel movement against his onetime ally.
   The official Libyan news agency JANA said Habre and several
aides had been killed between Tine and Oum Chalouba in eastern
Chad, the site of heavy fighting between government soldiers and
rebel fighters last week.
   ``The reports by news media on the escape of Habre with his
family on board an aircraft to a neighboring country were not
true,'' said JANA, monitored in Rome. The news agency cited no
sources, and did not say when Habre had been killed. It provided no
further details.
   But a Patriotic Salvation Movement communique claimed Habre had
sought refuge in Maroua, Cameroon, about 185 miles south of
N'Djamena.
   ``Nothing confirms that he died in any fighting,'' French
Foreign Minister Roland Dumas said in Paris during a televised
interview. ``I even have information to the contrary.''
   Diplomatic sources also said most of Habre's Cabinet ministers
left the capital by vehicle.
   Though the rebels have been armed by Libya in the past, it is
unclear how much help they have received recently from Tripoli.
Libya has denied any involvement in the rebel's recent offensive.
   In its dispatches Sunday, however, the Libyan news agency JANA
called Habre a ``brigand'' and hailed the victory of the rebels.
   ``Habre was an obstacle in the way of national reconciliation
between Chadians and an obstacle to good neighborliness and the
bonds of history and common suffering between Libyans and
Chadians,'' JANA said in the commentary.
   About 1,000 civilians cheered Deby as his Mercedes-led motorcade
pulled into the Place des Martyrs, the central square in the city
of 400,000 people. Others waved and cried out from the streets. The
capital was calm after being pillaged Saturday by looters and army
deserters.
   Deby's second-in-command, Bada Maldom, arrived at the head of an
army of 200 men earlier Sunday.
   He held several hours of talks with Bawayeu at a hotel before
Deby arrived. No details of the talks were disclosed, but they were
presumed to concern a handover of power.
   Under Chad's constitution, Bawayeu leads the country in the
president's absence.
   The rebels, meanwhile, spread throughout the city, taking
control of public buildings and key intersections.
   ``They've moved in, and they're beginning to take over key
points around the city,'' a U.S. Embassy official said on condition
of anonymity. ``There's an effort to exert public order.''
   Three companies of Foreign Legion soldiers landed in N'Djamena
on Sunday, reinforcing France's total troop strength in its former
colony to 1,800 men. This North African country has about 5.2
million people.
   Before the arrival of the bulk of Deby's rebels Sunday, the
Legionnaires appeared the sole sign of authority. Maldom asked
French commanders permission before entering the city.
   On Saturday, the Legionnaires organized Chad government troops -
led by officers sympathetic to Deby - to impose an overnight curfew
and disarm looters.
   Most looters were renegade soldiers or civilians who had picked
up weapons thrown down by thousands of army deserters Saturday.
   France has deployed soldiers in Chad under a defense treaty.
They have taken no part in the fighting, which Paris views as a
Chadian affair.
   The Legionnaires organized the evacuation of 948 foreigners to
Paris on two flights Sunday. Most of the evacuees were French
nationals, but about 50 American dependents were on the flights.
   The passengers, mostly women and children, did not report ill
treatment at the hands of rebels or soldiers, U.S. Embassy
officials in Paris said. The evacuation was voluntary.
   Deby, 38, a brilliant military tactician, broke the morale of
government troops after three weeks of victories in eastern Chad.
The biggest win was on Thursday when the rebels captured Abeche, a
town of 30,000 people 500 miles east of N'Djamena.
   A day later, they routed government soldiers making a last stand
at nearby Oum Hadjer.
   JANA reported Sunday that Habre had requested U.S. military
intervention to save his crumbling government. The U.S. Embassy
official said she was unaware of any such request.
   On Saturday, thousands of people streamed west across the Chari
River to Cameroon. Cameroon closed its border with Chad early
Sunday.
   Habre contended the rebels were backed by Libya, which occupied
two-thirds of Chad in 1980. The Libyans withdrew in November 1981
but made incursions from the north in August 1983.
   In 1986, Libya moved further into northern Chad. Deby
masterminded a series of lightning attacks the following year that
drove the Libyans from the area.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0069 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 2007EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-SpaceShuttle 1stLd-Writethru a0708 12-02 0737</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Space Shuttle, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0708,0889</SECOND>
<HEAD>Columbia's Astronauts Finally in Orbit</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 16th graf, `Scientists still ...' to UPDATE with details
on initial scientific goals.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos CSB5,7</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARCIA DUNN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Aerospace Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CAPE CANAVERAL, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Columbia's astronauts, thrilled to
finally be orbiting Earth, activated telescopes inside the space
shuttle Sunday for more than a week of probing galaxies, quasars
and other hot, turbulent objects.
   The shuttle roared to life at 1:49 a.m. EST Sunday and streaked
through a moonlit sky after six months of trying to get off the
ground. Three hours later, the seven-man crew began the daylong
process of getting the $150 million Astro observatory ready for
operation.
   ``It's like an early Christmas present,'' NASA launch director
Bob Sieck said at a post-launch news conference. ``It's been a goal
all year ... to get Astro and Columbia on orbit. You could say it
took all year to get there, but we're there and we're sure happy
about it.''
   It was the fifth launch attempt for the mission, first scheduled
for 1986 but postponed by the Challenger accident. Fuel leaks
halted three countdowns, including the first one in May, and
telescope problems ended another.
   Thick clouds on Sunday threatened to cause yet another delay.
The Air Force, which is responsible for range safety, dispatched a
helicopter to assure visibility would be sufficient. That check
postponed liftoff 21 minutes.
   Less than 1{ hours after Columbia lifted off, a Soviet rocket
hurtled into orbit with two cosmonauts and a Japanese television
journalist who will join two other men at space station Mir.
   Twelve people consequently are now in space, the most at one
time, and the Americans are hoping to communicate with their Soviet
and Japanese counterparts by ham radio during the mission.
   Scientists who have been working for years on the Astro project
said they could hardly believe it when Columbia finally took off.
   ``We were so used to not getting it off, the idea that it's
actually been launched and it's up there orbiting the Earth is
amazing,'' said Arthur Davidsen of Johns Hopkins University,
principal investigator for one of the telescopes.
   ``We're working minor problems and we're delighted to be working
them after 11 years, believe me,'' said mission scientist Ted Gull.
   The first difficulty involved the instrument pointing system for
the three ultraviolet telescopes. The system's star trackers failed
to work properly in a stowed position, but appeared to operate well
after being elevated in the cargo bay, said mission manager Jack
Jones.
   Later in the day, one of the three trackers had trouble
detecting dim stars and was being readjusted to use brighter
objects for calibration purposes.
   The pointing system was used only once before, for solar
observations in 1985. Numerous problems were encountered during
that mission, known as Spacelab-2.
   ``I had visions of Spacelab-2 dancing in my head,''
astronaut-astronomer Robert Parker told Mission Control.
   There were some telescope problems later, most of which were
resolved quickly, and a computer terminal in the flight deck was
turned off after Columbia commander Vance Brand smelled something
burning. The computer is believed to have overheated.
   Scientists still hoped to make their first scientific
observation by early Monday. Among the early targets are Capella, a
nearby star in the constellation Auriga with an ultraviolet-oozing
corona and a supernova remnant in the constellation Vela that is
considered a bright X-ray source.
   Columbia's seven astronauts are splitting 12-hour shifts during
the 10-day mission, the first shuttle trip in five years devoted
entirely to scientific research.
   Parker and the three other astronomers on board will operate the
ultraviolet telescopes round-the-clock. The X-ray telescope will be
managed by computer commands sent from Goddard Space Flight Center
in Greenbelt, Md.
   The observatory will focus on about 240 high-energy objects in
space - such as quasars, a supernova and even a comet - as Columbia
orbits 218 miles high. Ultraviolet light and X-rays emitted from
such objects cannot penetrate Earth's atmosphere and thus are
invisible from the ground.
   Scientists expect to improve their understanding of the
so-called invisible universe by measuring ultraviolet and X-ray
radiation. In addition to stars and galaxies, Astro will examine
Jupiter as well as Comet Levy, which is moving rapidly out of the
solar system.
   After a year of frustrations - two leaky shuttles, a flawed
mirror on the Hubble Space Telescope, overhauled space station
designs - the astronomy mission is helping NASA finish the year on
an upswing. It is the third shuttle flight in as many months, a
pace not seen since 1985.
   The Soviet rocket - which also launched a Soviet effort to
commercialize its space program - lifted off from the remote
Central Asian steppes of Kazakhstan.
   Journalist Toyohiro Akiyama, 48, joined Soviet cosmonauts Viktor
Afanasyev and Musa Manarov in the Soyuz TM-11 space capsule.
Akiyama was a passenger under a $12 million contract between the
Soviet Union and Japan's biggest private television company, TBS.
   Akiyama, a TBS news director who quit a four-pack-a-day
cigarette habit during the training, was asked before liftoff what
he looked forward to most on his return from the first trip into
space by a Japanese citizen.
   ``I can't wait to have a smoke,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0070 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 2008EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-Foreigners     12-02 0459</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Foreigners,0578</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ali Lands in Jordan With Former Hostages</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos AMM2-3</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By P.V. VIVEKANAND</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>AMMAN, Jordan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Boxing great Muhammad Ali accompanied 15
Americans out of Iraq on Sunday, and a spokesman said Ali plans to
return to Baghdad later this month to seek freedom for others.
   Two Canadians and six British employees of the U.S. Bechtel
Corp. were also on the Iraqi Airways flight from the Iraqi capital.
The Canadians' freedom was secured by a Canadian parliamentary
team, and the Britons said they did not know who arranged their
release.
   Airport officials in Baghdad said 25 Belgians flew to Brussels
on Sunday in a Belgian airliner that had brought medicine to Iraq.
A Belgian parliamentary delegation also left with the freed
hostages, the official Iraq News Agency said.
   The Westerners were the latest to be freed by Iraqi President
Saddam Hussein, who has prevented thousands of foreigners from
leaving Iraq. Some have been held as ``human shields'' at strategic
sites to deter attack by the multinational force in the Persain
Gulf.
   All Americans who flew out with Ali were held at strategic sites
in Iraq. Some had first been in hiding in Kuwait for several weeks.
   Ali, who has Parkinson's disease that hinders his speech, said
nothing as he moved through the crowd of journalists. He met with
Saddam last week.
   ``We are concerned about all other Americans that are yet in
Iraq who would like to come home for Christmas,'' said Arthur
Morrison, a spokesman for the former heavyweight boxing champion.
``We will go back to Iraq for Christmas on behalf of American
families.''
   Morrison said Ali plans to return to Baghdad on Dec. 24. Saddam
has proposed releasing all foreigners between Dec. 25 and March 25
if President Bush pledges not to attack.
   All the Americans with Ali appeared to be in good health.
   ``We were treated very well by the Iraqis at our camp,'' said
Ralph Leidholdt of Lakewood, Colo., who said he was held at an
ammunition factory northwest of Baghdad along with other Westerners
but no Americans.
   Lakewood said spent 73 days as a hostage and 50 days hiding in
Kuwait.
   Sergio Coletta, of Moss Point, Miss., an employee of the
American Bureau of Shipping in Kuwait at the time of the Aug. 2
invasion, expressed concern over ``the many other Americans still
hiding in Kuwait.''
   Coletta said he was held at an industrial site south of Baghdad.
   ``It is fantastic to be free,'' he said. ``But there are
hundreds of others left behind, and I hope that they could also be
free and leave for home.''
   The two Canadians were Bob McKen, 31, of Edmonton; and Tom Wolf,
30, of Rocky Mountainhouse, Alberta. Their freedom was secured by
three Parliament members who visited Iraq last week.
   The six Britons who arrived Sunday identified themselves as
Frank Bennon of Stockport, Bob Fenton of London, Eddie Gore of
Manchester, Marl Treen of Surrey, Alex Barran of Scotland, and John
Brown of Gravesend.
   All six were working at a site near Kirkuk in northern Iraq.
   Fenton said the group was not held as human shields. He said the
group found the Iraqi people ``anxious to avoid war.''
   The travel schedule of the American group was not immediately
known, but U.S. Embassy officials said the former hostages would
leave Amman on Monday for Europe.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0071 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 2040EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-DailyNews     12-02 0334</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Daily News,0393</SECOND>
<HEAD>Violence Besets Daily News Strike</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Daily News strike again was visited by
violence Sunday when pickets threw firecrackers and grew rowdy and
a striker assaulted a newspaper hawker, resulting in arrests,
police said.
   Police also charged two News replacement drivers with illegal
gun possession and said they found an unused pipe bomb near a News
printing plant.
   The unlit, 6-inch pipe bomb was found near a truck lot at the
News' Brooklyn plant. Nearby were two unexploded, M-80 firecrackers
taped to boxes of nails.
   Police had gone there to investigate some explosions, apparently
caused by firecrackers, a police spokesman said.
   The News said that 200 strikers were throwing cherry bombs and
M-80 firecrackers early Sunday.
   The firecrackers were tossed into a secluded area, police said,
and no one was arrested for that. But police spokesman Sgt. Peter
Sweeney said one man was subsequently arrested for striking a
police officer with a bottle and four pickets were arrested for
disorderly conduct because they were ``loud and boisterous.''
   In an unrelated incident, police said two News replacement
drivers were charged with weapon possession after a loaded
.25-caliber pistol was found in the front seat of their truck early
Sunday.
   Police discovered the weapon when summoned to an accident scene.
   ``The danger our drivers face on the streets is real as the
union-perpetrated violence continues,'' News spokesman John Sloan
said. ``But the Daily News does not condone the possession of
weapons or the use of force.''
   In another incident Sunday morning, a striker was arrested after
a hawker was attacked at a Manhattan street corner, police said.
   Sweeney, the police spokesman, said a truck was dropping off
papers when News hawkers were set upon by three people.
   One assailant sprayed an unknown substance into a hawker's face.
A News pressman with 10 years on the job was arrested as a result.
The hawker was treated at the scene.
   The strike by about 2,300 of the News' 3,500 employees began
Oct. 25. The paper has printed every day since, though distribution
has been a problem. Street hawkers were hired after many newsstands
refused to carry the paper.
   During the strike weekday circulation has dropped from 1.06
million to a little more than 500,000, the News said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0072 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 2048EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Egypt-Elections     12-02 0307</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Egypt-Elections,0337</SECOND>
<HEAD>Incomplete Election Results Show Majority for Mubarak's Party</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DALIA BALIGH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CAIRO, Egypt (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Hosni Mubarak's governing party
dominated parliamentary elections, but more than 60 percent of the
races are headed for a runoff, according to partial results
released Sunday.
   The Thursday elections were boycotted by the major opposition
parties to protest allegations the government rigs the votes in its
favor.
   The election was also marred by several clashes between police
and voters. At least four people were killed and dozens injured,
newspapers and police reported.
   The announcement of the complete results were delayed because
ballot counting in the Nile delta town of Toukh was not finished.
   The government's daily al-Ahram newspaper reported Sunday that
Mubarak's National Deocratic Party won 144 seats in the 454-member
People's Assembly, or parliament. Independents won 23 seats and the
small leftist National Unionist Progressive Party took one seat.
   Mubarak will appoint 10 parliamentarians before the legislative
body holds its first meeting.
   Runoffs have been announced for the rest of the seats, 62
percent of parliament.
   Mubarak's party, which has held majorities of more than 75
percent in the three parliaments since he became president in 1981,
is expected to maintain its power in the assembly following the
runoff elections.
   Al-Ahram said there was a 44.71 percent voter turnout. Many
Egyptians do not bother to vote because they see the parliament as
a rubber stamp of the government's policies.
   In the Mediterranean city of Damietta, a security source said
that at least three people died and more than 41 were wounded
Thursday in a clash between police and supporters of an independent
candidate who lost.
   The daily al-Wafd newspaper, linked to the right-of-center New
Wafd opposition party that boycotted the elections, reported Sunday
there were renewed clashes in the Damietta area which left a
3-year-old boy dead and 30 people wounded.
   There were also several other incidents that left about 30
people injured.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0073 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 2049EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People SUB   12-02 0251</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People, SUB,0285</SECOND>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 4th item to CORRECT verb tense in lead, `has been' sted
`was been.' SUBS 5th item to DELETE redundant 3rd graf.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>FOND DU LAC, Wis. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The boyfriend of prison escapee
Lawrencia ``Bambi'' Bembenek has been freed on $100,000 bond from a
Wisconsin jail, but the woman he's accused of helping remains in
Canada awaiting extradition.
   Dominick Gugliatto, 35, a divorced Milwaukee factory worker, is
charged with helping Ms. Bembenek escape July 15 from Taycheedah
state prison. She was serving a life sentence for the 1981 murder
of her husband's former wife.
   He and Ms. Bembenek, a former Milwaukee policewoman, were
captured Oct. 17 in Thunder Bay, Ontario, where she was working as
a waitress under an assumed name. The story of the former model and
Playboy club waitress - how she was convicted of murdering her
then-husband's ex-wife and then how she escaped from prison - drew
widespread attention.
   A Dec. 17 hearing has been scheduled in Thunder Bay on Ms.
Bembenek's attempt to gain refugee status and avoid returning to
Wisconsin. Gugliatto waived extradition and was transferred to Fond
du Lac. His next court appearance is scheduled Thursday.
   ---
   ALBANY, N.Y. (AP) - New York Gov. Mario Cuomo is a grandfather
for the third time.
   The governor's daughter, Maria Cuomo Cole, gave birth Wednesday
to a daughter - Amanda Matilda Cole. The baby was named after the
governor's wife, Matilda.
   Kenneth Cole, a shoe designer, and his wife also have a
2-year-old daughter, Emily Carrie. Another daughter, Margaret, and
her husband, Robert Perpignano, have a 5-year-old daughter,
Christina.
   ``All is well and the family is grateful,'' the governor said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0074 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 2156EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-EC-Finance     12-02 0380</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-EC-Finance,0439</SECOND>
<HEAD>European Ministers Support Central Bank Proposal</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MONZA, Italy (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   European Community finance ministers Sunday
gave broad support to a proposal for a strong, politically
independent European Central Bank.
   ``Basically, the general idea of the draft statute was supported
by finance ministers today,'' Deutsche Bundesbank President Karl
Otto Poehl told a news conference.
   The draft statute sets price stability as its primary goal. It
says both the future European Central Bank and the national central
banks should be free of any political influence.
   The finance officials didn't take any vote, however, at the
informal gathering Sunday. They forwarded the document for
consideration at an EC summit in Rome beginning Dec. 14.
   The meeting was also attended by European central bank
governors, who had drafted the statutes last month.
   The meeting marked the European debut of the British chancellor
of the exchequer, Norman Lamont. Lamont succeeded John Major, who
last week became prime minister.
   Lamont told reporters following the meeting that he was
``hopeful'' a compromise might be reached at the Rome summit, but
he maintained Britain's ``reserve against a single currency and a
single European Central Bank.''
   Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher resistance to moves toward
European unity helped push her from power last month.
   At Sunday's meeting, Lamont said there are ``an immense number
of very complicated issues to be steered through,'' but added that
there was sufficient ground for a ``constructive'' discussion.
   ``It's just my belief that we can find some common ground,'' he
said.
   Other officials at the meeting said they noted a change in the
British position, but it remained unclear whether it was a change
in form or substance.
   A number of issues remain yet to be settled, however, including
the authority of the European Central Bank to independently conduct
an exchange rate policy through interventions in the currency and
monetary markets.
   Poehl downplayed the disagreement on this issue.
   ``We all agree that price stability should be the main
objective, and not exchange rate stability,'' Poehl told the news
conference.
   The draft statute also states that official reserves of the
national central banks would be transferred to the European Central
Bank.
   The central bank would be established during the so-called
second phase toward economic and monetary union of the 12 EC
members, which will start Jan. 1, 1994.
   The Rome summit will start drafting changes to the Treaty of
Rome needed for the creation of an economic and monetary Union. The
summit will also discuss the process toward political union in
Europe.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0075 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 2156EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Kennedy-Awards 2ndLd-Writethru a0761 12-02 0297</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Kennedy-Awards, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0761,330</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dizzy Gillespie, Katharine Hepburn Among Honorees</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: adds 4 grafs from Kennedy Center tribute</NOTE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush welcomed the five performers
and musicians who received the 1990 Kennedy Center honors Sunday,
saying their work underscores the ``crucial role'' art plays in
U.S. society.
   At a star-studded black tie reception at the White House, Bush
honored jazz musician Dizzy Gillespie, actress Katharine Hepburn,
composer Jule Styne, director Billy Wilder and opera singer Rise
Stevens.
   The president paid personal tribute to each award winner,
describing Gillespie as a ``magician of the musical form,'' and
remembering Hepburn for her originality.
   The awards highlight the ``crucial role that art must play in
the fabric of our society,'' he said.
   After his brief remarks, guests circulated at a cocktail party
before leaving for a Kennedy Center gala.
   Bush, meanwhile, left for a five-nation trip to Latin America.
   Hepburn, dressed in black slacks, a black turtle neck and
sensible laced shoes, was swamped with people seeking to have their
picture taken. ``I'm supposed to be adorable,'' she said.
   Asked about the 1990 Kennedy Center honor, she said, ``I don't
think you have words to express how I feel.''
   Stevens said she was ``very excited'' to be at the White House.
Receiving the award was ``a most beautiful surprise,'' she said.
   Once at the Kennedy Center, the five received stage tributes
from - among others - actors Bill Cosby, Jack Lemon, Walter Matthau
and opera singer Marilyn Horne during a show taped for television
broadcast Dec. 28.
   The show, hosted by television newsman Walter Cronkite, included
film clips of the lives and achievements of award recipients.
   Other personalities appearing in the show included columnist Art
Buchwald, actresses Glenn Close and Angela Lansbury and actor Hal
Linden.
   Federal Reserve Board Chairman Alan Greenspan and White House
chief of staff John Sununu were among the government officials in
the audience.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0076 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 2158EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-LennonAssassin     12-02 0331</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lennon Assassin,0431</SECOND>
<HEAD>Killer of John Lennon Says He Regrets Slaying Former Beatle</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ATTICA, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Mark David Chapman, who shot John Lennon to
death 10 years ago, wants the world to know he's sorry.
   ``You can't judge a man's life by one act. Before I became `The
man who murdered John Lennon,' I was basically a decent person,''
the Rochester Democrat and Chronicle reported in its Sunday
edition.
   Chapman, who's serving 20 years to life for killing the former
Beatle, was interviewed in his isolated cell at Attica state
prison.
   ``I'm not an evil person,'' he said. ``Like everybody, there's a
small part within me that's evil, and that's what took over in my
case. My energies turned foul and went toward something
destructive.''
   Chapman said he suffered years of mental dissolution before
killing Lennon. ``Little people'' would speak to him, giving him
advice on how to run his life, he said.
   Chapman said he first got the idea for killing Lennon when he
came across a Beatles picture book in a Honolulu library.
   ``I was looking for a way to vent all the disappointment, my
anger, my rage,'' he said. ``A complete failure in my owns eyes.
And I came across the book ... I opened the book and I saw him -
put yourself where I was - I saw him on the roof of the gabled,
luxurious Dakota apartment. And I became hurt. Enraged at what I
perceived to be his phoniness.''
   Chapman was lying in wait for Lennon outside the Dakota, a
famous apartment building in New York City, Dec. 8, 1980, when the
musician and his wife, Yoko Ono, were coming home from a late-night
recording session.
   ``When his limousine pulled up, he got out and he looked at me.
I'm sure he remembered me,'' said Chapman, who earlier in the day
got the star to sign a copy of the ne ``Double Fantasy'' album.
   ``I walked back into the driveway and took the combat stance,
just the way I'd practiced in my hotel room.''
   Chapman recalled standing there with a ``voice'' inside his
head, whispering, ``Do it! Do it! Do it!''
   ``As he walked past, I aimed right at his back and I pulled the
trigger five times,'' he said.
   Chapman said he has come to feel great remorse for killing a man
he still looks upon as ``a seeker of truth.''
   ``It was an end of innocence for that time. And I regret being
the one that ended it.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0077 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 2145EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-GulfRdp 1stLd-Writethru a0702 12-02 0838</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf Rdp, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0702,1032</SECOND>
<HEAD>Saddam Says Chances Of War 50-50; Iraq Tests Missiles</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 26 grafs to UPDATE with Jordanian foreign minister
meeting with Kuwaiti delegation; CORRECT spelling of Eduard sted
Eduward; MINOR EDITING elsehwere. Picks up 24th graf pvs, `All
the...'
^LaserPhotos AMM2,3, DHR1, MLA1</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By LAURA KING</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Saddam Hussein's armies rattled nerves around the Persian Gulf
Sunday with the first test of surface-to-surface missiles since the
invasion of Kuwait, and Iraq's president said the chances of war
are ``50-50.''
   In Washington, Secretary of State James A. Baker III said the
United States would not attack Iraq - provided Iraqi troops are
withdrawn from Kuwait and foreign hostages are freed.
   Iraq, which has been sporadically releasing captives, let more
go on Sunday. Fifteen freed Americans flew out of Iraq to Amman,
Jordan, with former world heavyweight champion Muhammad Ali, who
secured their release in talks with Saddam.
   A spokesman for the boxer said he planned to return to Baghdad
on Christmas Eve to try to bring out more of the hundreds of
remaining captives, who were stranded when Iraq invaded small,
oil-rich Kuwait on Aug. 2.
   Also in Amman, Jordanian Foreign Minister Marwan Kassem told
Kuwaiti leaders that Jordan favors the total withdrawal of Iraqi
troops from the emirate, according to Kuwaiti reports and a senior
Jordanian official who spoke on condition of anonymity.
   A statement signed by former Kuwaiti Parliamentarian Ahmad
Al-Rabee said the meeting ``was a step towards improving
relations'' between the two nations.
   King Hussein has criticized Iraq's invasion of Kuwait, but has
failed to strongly condemn it like most countries. There was also
speculation some supplies were shipped through Jordan to Iraq in
violation of the U.N.-backed trade embargo.
   The Kuwaiti delegation, which includes lawmakers, journalists
and writers, was scheduled to meet King Hussein and other state
officials.
   Iraq, meanwhile, told the Soviet Union that it could lose its
influence in the Arab world if it sent troops to the Persian Gulf.
That was apparently in response to a warning from Soviet Foreign
Minister Eduard Shevardnadze, who said last week Moscow would send
in soldiers if Soviet citizens trapped in Iraq were harmed.
   The official Iraqi News agency quoted an Iraqi Foreign Ministry
spokesman as saying Shevardnadze ``seems to be looking for a
pretext to send troops to the region.''
   More than 350,000 troops are in the Persian Gulf as part of the
US.-led multinational force. American troops, now numbering more
240,000, are expected to swell to around 400,000 by next month.
   The U.S. military refused to say whether the American forces
went on alert Sunday when Iraq launched surface-to-surface missiles
in what appeared to be test launches.
   The missiles were fired - and landed - in Iraqi territory, U.S.
military officials in Saudi Arabia said in a statement.
   The officials refused to say how the missiles were detected, but
they apparently were monitored either by U.S. spy satellites or
AWACS airborne early-warning radar planes, which are on patrol 24
hours a day.
   The military statement did not say what kind of missiles were
involved, but Defense Secretary Dick Cheney, interviewed in
Washington by ABC-TV, said they were SCUD missiles ``or SCUD
variants.'' He said it was the first such firing since April.
   Cheney said Saddam has used the missiles, which have a range of
350 to 400 miles, with conventional warheads in the past. But he
said a SCUD ``could conceivably carry chemical weapons.''
   The Iraqi test-firing came at a time of already heightened
tensions. The forces in Saudi Arabia were reported to have been put
on ``yellow alert'' - one category below full combat alert - last
week, after the U.N. Security Council approved a resolution
authorizing use of force against Iraq if it does not withdraw from
Kuwait by Jan. 15.
   Saddam, in an interview broadcast Sunday by the French
television network Antenne 2, repeatedly refused to answer
questions about the possibility of a pullout from Kuwait.
   In the interview, the first granted to a foreign television
network since the U.N. resolution was passed, he was asked what the
chances were of war breaking out.
   ``Fifty-fifty,'' he replied.
   But he said he was ready to talk with U.S. officials if they
came to Baghdad ``in a spirit of dialogue.'' That was in apparent
reference to an offer by President Bush last week to send Baker to
Iraq for talks.
   Iraq accepted, but said it wanted to talk about the Arab-Israeli
conflict too. The United States has refused to link any resolution
of the gulf crisis with the Palestinian question.
   Baker said Sunday that if Saddam complied with U.N. resolutions
passed since the crisis erupted four months ago, he would have no
reason to fear attack.
   ``There has never been any suggestion that force would be used
if the U.N. resolutions are fully complied with,'' the secretary of
state said in an interview on NBC-TV.
   Those resolutions call for the unconditional withdrawal of Iraqi
troops from Kuwait, the restoration of the Kuwaiti government and
the release of all hostages.
   The 15 Americans freed Sunday were among 47 foreigners,
including Belgians, Britons and Canadians freed separately by Iraq,
who arrived in Amman aboard an Iraqi Airways flight.
   All the Americans had been held at strategic sites in Iraq and
Kuwait as ``human shields'' against any attack by the multinational
force.
   In other developments:
   -Iraqi Foreign Minister Tariq Aziz met with Yasser Arafat,
chairman of the Palestine Liberation Organization. The Iraq News
Agency said only that they discussed ``developments in the Arab
arena.''
   -Eight British women and one Dutch woman left London Sunday
bound for Baghdad, where they hope to win the release of their
husbands. The British government discourages such trips, but
similar missions have met with success.
   -Filipinos returning from Iraq and occupied Kuwait told of long
lines for food and of Iraqis scavenging for scraps thrown away at
the airport by departing foreigners. Some of the Filipinos also
said Iraqi soldiers were still looting groceries and homes in
occupied Kuwait.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0078 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 2218EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Guatemala 2ndLd-Writethru a0789 12-02 0266</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Guatemala, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0789,0297</SECOND>
<HEAD>Guatemalan Villagers Clash With Army Troops, At Least 10 Killed</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS one graf 5th `But a...' to CORRECT report to 25 dead sted
12; pickup graf 6 `The reporter...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By ALFONSO ANZUETO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>GUATEMALA CITY (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A group of villagers clshed with
government troops in western Guatemala on Sunday. The government
said 10 civilians were killed, but an independent report put the
number at 25.
   The independent news report also said at least 71 were wounded
in the clash in Santiago Atitlan, a small town 110 miles west of
Guatemala City in the province of Solola. Reports were also
contradictory as to what sparked the incident.
   An army news release said many residents of Santiago Atitlan
``revolted'' Sunday ``for reasons that have not been established
yet'' and attacked the police station and a local army post.
   The army news release said 10 civilians were killed and 17
wounded in Sunday's fighting.
   But a reporter for the private television show Noti-7 said 25
people were killed and 71 injured - all of them Indians and most of
them children.
   The reporter said the violence apparently was set off by three
drunken soldiers creating a disturbance in the village. A group of
villagers marched to the army post to demand that they stop, and
shooting followed, the reporter said. He did not elaborate.
   Villagers later held a demonstration, shouting ``we want
justice!'' and demanding that a government-appointed attorney for
human rights come to Santiago Atitlan and investigate, the reporter
said.
   Sunday's violence further raised tensions in a country already
wracked by four decades of leftist guerrilla insurrection and
widespread human rights abuses by government security forces. A
presidential election runoff is set for Jan. 6.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0079 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 2233EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Drive-ByShooting     12-02 0277</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Drive-By Shooting,0324</SECOND>
<HEAD>Family Members Recall Bloody Drive-By Shooting</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KATHRYN DETTMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A man whose family were victims in a drive-by
shooting that wounded 12 people, including three small children,
said Sunday such violence was not unusual in the area.
   Tony Lopez, 60, said assailants opened fire from a passing car
Friday night during a family gathering at his house in Valinda, 20
miles from downtown Los Angeles.
   The family had just been celebrating the homecoming of Lopez'
32-year-old son, Danny, who was back after two years in state
prison.
   ``It was uncalled for, especially hitting little babies,'' Lopez
said of the attack. ``But these things happen around this area.
They just get a kick out of shooting little babies. These guys
deserve to go to the electric chair.''
   Lopez, who was inside his home during the shooting, said it
happened as family members and friends were leaving through a patio
door after a dinner honoring his son.
   Police have no suspects but say it was gang-related.
   Tony Lopez, a diesel mechanic, lost his 21-year-old son,
Leonard, to a fatal shooting this summer.
   ``My boys are not gang members,'' Lopez said. ``They work every
day. I think (the killers of my son) were gang members. Wherever
they see a party, next thing you know, they do things like that.''
   Those hurt in the attack included two 18-month-old boys and one
4 years old. Additionally, a 13-year-old and two 17-year-old boys
were hurt.
   One of the toddlers, 18-month-old James Sainz, was hit in the
face and may lose an eye. He was in good condition Sunday at Covina
Intercommunity Hospital.
   Also wounded was the elder Lopez's daughter, Mary Ann Lopez, 26,
who threw herself over her 18-month-old son, David, Tony Lopez's
wife and two of his sons, four other relatives and two family
friends, investigators and family friends.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0080 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 0336EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a BC-LOT--LotteryState-by- 2ndAdd   12-02 0300</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-LOT--Lottery State-by-State, 2nd Add,308</SECOND>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<HEAD>OHIO</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CLEVELAND (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the selections Saturday night in the
Ohio Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Super Lotto</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   10-25-31-36-38-53
   (ten, twenty-five, thirty-one, thirty-six, thirty-eight,
fifty-three)
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Kicker</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   3-4-8-5-0-9
   (three, four, eight, five, zero, nine)
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 3 Numbers</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   2-5-1
   (two, five, one)
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 4 Numbers</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   8-0-2-5
   (eight, zero, two, five)
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Cards</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   10 (ten) of Hearts
   K (king) of Clubs
   J (jack) of Diamonds
   Q (queen) of Spades
</TEXT>
<HEAD>OREGON</HEAD>
<HEAD>Daily 4</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PORTLAND, Ore. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are Saturday's winning numbers in the
``Oregon Daily 4'' lottery game:
   4-3-7-2
   (four, three, seven, two)
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Megabucks</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PORTLAND, Ore. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are Saturday's winning numbers in the
``Oregon Megabucks'' lottery game:
   1-3-4-20-24-33
   (one, three, four, twenty, twenty-four, thirty-three)
</TEXT>
<HEAD>PENNSYLVANIA</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HARRISBURG (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected Saturday
in the Pennsylvania State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Number</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   3-7-2
   (three, seven, two)
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Big 4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   1-1-0-0
   (one, one, zero, zero)
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Saturday Spin</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HARRISBURG (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In the ``Pennsylvania Saturday Spin'' game,
Jim Aeppli of Tionesta won the grand prize of $100,000.
   Nine finalists won $5,000 each.
   Players are entered in the ``Saturday Spin'' after winning a
ticket in the instant lottery game.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>VIRGINIA</HEAD>
<HEAD>Pick 3</HEAD>
<DATELINE>RICHMOND (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   These numbers were drawn Saturday in the
Virginia Lottery's Pick 3 game:
   4-9-9
   (four, nine, nine)
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<DATELINE>RICHMOND (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   These numbers were drawn Saturday in the
Virginia Lottery's Lotto game:
   4-19-20-23-25-39
   (four, nineteen, twenty, twenty-three, twenty-five, thirty-nine)
</TEXT>
<HEAD>WEST VIRGINIA</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CHARLESTON, W.Va. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the West Virginia State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily 3</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   4-3-8
   (four, three, eight)
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily 4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   8-2-2-9
   (eight, two, two, nine)
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0081 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 2321EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a BC-LOT--LotteryState-by 1stLd-Writeth   12-02 0469</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-LOT--Lottery State-by-State, 1st Ld-Writethru,500</SECOND>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<HEAD>CONNECTICUT</HEAD>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEWINGTON, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning combination picked Sunday in
the Connecticut State Lottery's ``Daily Lottery'' drawing was:
   6-9-4
   (six, nine, four)
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Play 4</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEWINGTON, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning combination picked Sunday in
the Connecticut State Lottery's ``Play 4'' drawing was:
   2-9-2-8.
   (two, nine, two, eight)
</TEXT>
<HEAD>DELAWARE</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DOVER, Del. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   These Delaware lotteries were drawn Sunday
night:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   5-2-3
   (Five, Two, Three)
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Play Four</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   9-0-1-8
   (Nine, Zero, One, Eight)
</TEXT>
<HEAD>FLORIDA</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected Sunday in the
Florida Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Cash 3</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   4-5-8
   (four, five, eight)
</TEXT>
<HEAD>INDIANA</HEAD>
<DATELINE>INDIANAPOLIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected Sunday
in the Hoosier Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Three</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   3-4-9
   (three, four, nine)
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Four</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   0-5-1-9
   (zero, five, one, nine)
</TEXT>
<HEAD>KENTUCKY</HEAD>
<HEAD>Kentucky Lottery</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOUISVILLE, Ky. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are Sunday's winning numbers
selected by the Kentucky Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Kentucky Cash:
   1-1-6
   (one, one, six)
   </HEAD>
<HEAD>MARYLAND</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BALTIMORE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   These Maryland lotteries were drawn Sunday
night:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   4-1-3
   (Four, One, Three)
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Play Four</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   5-0-1-5
   (Five, Zero, One, Five)
</TEXT>
<HEAD>MASSACHUSETTS</HEAD>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BRAINTREE, Mass. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers drawn Sunday night
in the ``Massachusetts Daily Lottery'' were:
   1-0-9-1
   (one, zero, nine, one)
   
   The payoffs based on a $1 bet were:
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Exact Order</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   All four $3,305.
   First or last three $463.
   Any two $40.
   Any one $4.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Any Order</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   All four $275.
   First three $77.
   Last three $77.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>NEW JERSEY</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TRENTON, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Sunday night in the New Jersey State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 3</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   2-0-1
   (two, zero, one)
   A straight bet pays $278, box pays $46 and pairs pay $27.50.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   4-4-9-0
   (four, four, nine, zero)
   A straight bet pays $2,196.50 and box pays $183.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>NEW YORK</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ALBANY, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected Sunday
in the New York State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Number</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   9-9-0
   (nine-nine-zero)
</TEXT>
<HEAD>WinFour</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   4-2-2-2
   (four-two-two-two)
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 10</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ALBANY, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected Sunday
in the New York State Lottery's Pick 10 game:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 10</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   1, 19, 22, 23, 24, 28, 31, 36, 39, 40, 48, 49, 56, 57, 63, 68,
73, 75, 78, 80.
   
   Eds: one, nineteen, twenty-two, twenty-three, twenty-four,
twenty-eight, thirty-one, thirty-six, thirty-nine, forty,
forty-eight, forty-nine, fifty-six, fifty-seven, sixty-three,
sixty-eight, seventy-three, seventy-five, seventy-eight, eighty.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>PENNSYLVANIA</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HARRISBURG (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected Sunday
in the Pennsylvania State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Number</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   0-9-6
   (zero, nine, six)
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Big 4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   6-5-3-9
   (six, five, three, nine)
</TEXT>
<HEAD>RHODE ISLAND</HEAD>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CRANSTON, R.I. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers in the Rhode Island
daily lottery drawing for Sunday were:
   0-1-7-6
   (zero, one, seven, six)
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0082 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 2110EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r v AM-NewsDigest 3rdLd-Writethru   12-02 1073</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-News Digest, 3rd Ld - Writethru,1322</SECOND>
<HEAD>9:15 p.m. EST Update</HEAD>
<BYLINE>AMs AP News Digest</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>For Monday AMs</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   
   Here are the top stories at this hour from The Associated Press.
The General Desk supervisor is George Garties (212-621-1602). The
LaserPhoto Desk supervisor is Stephen Hart 212-621-1900).
   
   For repeats of AP copy, please call your local bureau or the
Service Desk at 212-621-1595.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   ---
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Added as bjts in this update: AM-Obit Copland, AM-ATT-NCR.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   ---
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Also moved:</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   AMMAN, Jordan - Boxing great Muhammad Ali accompanied 15
Americans out of Iraq on Sunday, and a spokesman said Ali plans to
return to Baghdad later this month to seek freedom for others.
AM-Gulf-Foreigners, a0773.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>---</HEAD>
<TEXT>
</TEXT>
<HEAD>We will update:</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   AM-Gulf Rdp, a0702, with Jordan condemning Iraq's invasion of
Kuwait.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>---</HEAD>
<HEAD>GERMAN ELECTIONS:
   </HEAD>
<HEAD>First Free Balloting for United Nation In Nearly Six Decades</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   BONN, Germany - Chancellor Helmut Kohl's center-right coalition
on Sunday easily won the first free all-German elections since
1932, buoyed by his popularity as the man who crafted swift
unification.
   Slug AM-Germany-Election. Sent as a0771.
   By Terence Petty. LaserPhoto FRA2, Chancellor Kohl votes; FRA2,
Chancellor Kohl votes; LaserColor FRA102 matching FRA2; SAR1,
opposition candidate Lafontaine votes; BON8, Kohl and wife at party
headquarters; BON14, Kohl shaking hands with Lafontaine.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>`We want to have a better life....'</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   
   DELITZSCH, Germany - They left their homes on a gray, misty
morning to cast ballots for a brighter future. Even families could
not agree on the candidates, but they all voted for the same thing.
   Slug AM-Germany-Voting Day. Sent as a0689.
   By Mark Fritz. LaserPhoto HBG1, woman votes in traditional
costume.
   
   With:
   Slug AM-Germany-Honecker from Berlin: German police need top
level approval to enter a Soviet military hospital and arrest
former East German leader Erich Honecker who is wanted for issuing
shoot-to-kill orders at the Berlin Wall, a Soviet diplomat said
Sunday. LaserPhoto BER10, Soviet soldier guards hospital where
Honecker is staying.
   - AM-Germany-Election-Glance
   - AM-Kohl Profile.
   - AM-Germany-Berlin.
   - AM-Germany-Communists.
   - AM-Germany-Greens.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>GULF CRISIS:
   </HEAD>
<HEAD>Iraq Rattles Nerves with Missile Test</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   UNDATED - Saddam Hussein's armies rattled nerves around the
Persian Gulf Sunday with the first test of surface-to-surface
missiles since the invasion of Kuwait. The Iraqi president said the
chances of war in the region stand at ``fifty-fifty.''
   Slug AM-Gulf Rdp. Sent as a0702.
   By Laura King. LaserPhotos AMM2, AMM3, Muhammed Ali arriving in
Amman with released hostages from Georgia and Texas; MLA1, a
release Philippine hostage kissing Iraqi pilot of her flight home;
LaserColor AMM102 matching AMM2; DHR1, Air Force guard mans machine
gun at sundown; LON1, gulf protest in London; PAR6, Saddam Hussein
on French television.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Baker Says U.S. Won't Attack If Saddam Withdraws From Kuwait</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   
   WASHINGTON - Secretary of State James Baker A. III assured Iraq
on Sunday the United States will not attack that nation if Saddam
Hussein withdraws his troops from Kuwait and frees the Western
hostages.
   Slug AM-US-Gulf. Sent as a0767.
   By Joan Mower. LaserPhoto WX6, Secretary of State Baker and Sen.
Edward Kennedy appearing on Sunday morning news show.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Selective Service Ready To Turn on the Tap - If Needed</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   
   WASHINGTON - Seventeen years after the government's authority
for a military draft expired, the Selective Service System is alive
and well - and on standby.
   Slug AM-Gulf-Dormant Draft. Sent as a0680.
   By Nancy Benac.
   
   With:
   - AM-Gulf-Iraq from NICOSIA, Cyprus - Iraq warns President Bush
not to use proposed talks on the gulf crisis ``as a pretext with
the American people to justify his aggression against Iraq,'' and
again insists the Palestinian issue be discussed. It also warns the
Soviet Union not to send troops to the gulf.
   - AM-Gulf-Iraq-Shortages from MANILA, Philippines - Food
supplies are running so low in Iraq and Kuwait that people must
stand in line for hours or scavenge through the trash in order to
survive, Filipino workers returning from the two countries said
Sunday.
   - AM-Gulf-Marines from CAMP LEJEUNE, N.C.: Thousands of Marine
reservists uprooted from their homes and families have accepted
their participation in Operation Desert Shield with a mixture of
resignation and understanding. LaserPhoto RA1, Marine vehicle
firing a TOW missle.
   - AM-Gulf-Missles.
   - AM-Gulf-Israel.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>CHAD: Rebel Leader Rides Into African Capital</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   N'DJAMENA, Chad - Rebel leader Idriss Deby entered the capital
in triumph Sunday and vowed to establish a new government.
Conflicting reports emerged over the fate of deposed President
Hissene Habre.
   Slug AM-Chad. Sent as a0768.
   By Mahamet Hissene. LaserPhoto NY10; filer of Hissene Habre.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>SPACE: Columbia Astronauts In Orbit, Japan Reporter On Soviet
Flight</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   CAPE CANAVERAL, Fla. - Columbia's astronauts, thrilled to
finally be orbiting Earth, activated telescopes inside the space
shuttle Sunday for more than a week of probing galaxies, quasars
and other hot, turbulent objects.
   Slug AM-Space Shuttle. Sent as a0772.
   By Marcia Dunn. LaserPhotos CSB5,7, Columbia lifts off; HTN1, TV
image of space observatory in shuttle bay.
   
   With:
   BAIKONUR COSMODROME, U.S.S.R.-dated AM-Soviet-Space - A Japanese
television reporter became the first journalist in space on Sunday
aboard a Soviet rocket launched into orbit as part of a Kremlin
campaign to commercialize its space program. LaserPhoto BAIK1,
Soyuz lifts off; NY9, cosmonauts at Saturday news conference.
   - AM-Shuttle-Astronaut Thumbnails, 2 takes.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>AARON COPLAND: America's Leading Composer Dies</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   NORTH TARRYTOWN, N.Y. - Aaron Copland, the pioneering composer
who used folk songs and jazz in writing plainspoken classics such
as ``Appalachian Spring,'' ``Rodeo,'' and ``Billy the Kid,'' died
Sunday at age 90.
   Slug AM-Obit-Copland. Sent as a0770.
   LaserPhotos NY19, NY20 file photos of Copland.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>TAKEOVER OFFER: AT&amp;T Offers $6 Billion for National Cash Register
Corp.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   NEW YORK - American Telephone &amp; Telegraph Co. disclosed Sunday
it has made a $6 billion takeover offer for NCR Corp., a deal that
would bolster the phone giant's small role in the computer
industry.
   Slug AM-AT&amp;T-NCR. Sent as a0775.
   By Bart Ziegler.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>BUSH-SOUTH AMERICA: Visit to Focus on Economic Cooperation</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   WASHINGTON - President Bush departed Sunday night on a week-long
trip to South America that is aimed at calling attention to the
historic shift in the region to democratic rule and market-oriented
economic policies.
   Slug AM-Bush-South America. Sent as a0756.
   By George Gedda. Bush departure scheduled early evening EST.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>QUAKE DAY: Nothing Shaking But the Leaves on the Trees</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   MARKED TREE, Ark. - The earth stood still Sunday, as usual. The
only thing moving was the stream of jumpy residents fleeing in fear
of an earthquake.
   Slug AM-Earthquake Projection Rdp. Sent as a0746.
   By Janet K. Isbell. LaserPhoto XSIK1, television trucks converge
on New Madrid, Missouri.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>JAPAN: 100 Years After Birth of Parliament, Japan Struggles With
Democracy</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   TOKYO - Japan has a parliament that rarely decides things, a
leader who rarely leads and an entrenched bureaucracy that is
rarely challenged, but its unique brand of democracy seems to work.
   Slug AM-Japan-Democracy. Sent as a0666.
   By Michael Hirsh
</TEXT>
<HEAD>OLYMPIC NEIGHBORHOODS: In Atlanta, Residents At Future Site Worry</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   ATLANTA - Douglas Dean stopped in front of the stadium site for
the 1996 Summer Olympics, and sighed at the sight of crumbling
homes and crime-ridden streets.
   Slug AM-Olympic Neighborhoods. Sent as a0677.
   By Lauran Neergaard. LaserPhoto AX1, Douglas Dean at future
Olympics site.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0083 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 1319EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r v AM-BusinessNewsDigest     12-02 0580</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Business News Digest,0735</SECOND>
<BYLINE>Monday AMs:</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the top business stories at this hour. Bart Ziegler is
the AMs supervisor. If you have questions about the spot news and
feature report, call AP Business News at 212-621-1686.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>---</HEAD>
<BYLINE>TRUMP: Casino Regulators To Examine Taj Mahal Casino's Finances</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   
   ATLANTIC CITY, N.J. - Donald J. Trump's Taj Mahal Casino Resort
must show gaming regulators on Monday it remains healthy despite a
restructuring that will temporarily throw it into bankruptcy court.
   Slug AM-Trump Hearing. New, stands. By Henry Stern. Moving on
FFF- and AAA-level news wires.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>RETAILING: Pier 1's Successful Expansion Is Facing First Test</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   
   FORT WORTH, Texas - The rapid expansion of Pier 1 Imports Inc.,
which began five years ago when the company updated its '60s-style
merchandise and look, is facing its first big sales test - a
lackluster holiday season.
   Slug AM-Pier 1. New, stands. By Business Writer Evan Ramstad.
Moving on FFF-level news wires.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>ALAR: Opponents Say Alar Lawsuit Is Unconstitutional</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   
   YAKIMA, Wash. - Apple growers are striking back at critics in a
lawsuit that could be the first salvo in a nationwide war with
environmental groups over the use of farm chemicals.
   Slug AM-Alar Lawsuit. New, stands. By Nicholas K. Geranios.
Moving on FFF-level news wires.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>MCA: Station Spinoff Will Test How Much Major Market TV Station
Worth</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   
   NEW YORK - MCA Inc.'s plans to spin off its television station
as a separate company just before MCA is swallowed in a
multibillion-dollar deal sets up a unique test of how much a
major-market TV outlet is worth.
   Slug AM-MCA-Station Spinoff. New, stands. By Business Writer
Skip Wollenberg. Moving on FFF-level news wires.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>TIMBER TROUBLES: Once Housing Slump Ends, Spotted Owl Still Looms</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   
   GRANTS PASS, Ore. - The northern spotted owl and a slump in the
homebuilding industry have combined to cause trouble for the
Northwest timber industry in recent months.
   Slug AM-Timber Jobs. New, stands. By Jeff Barnard. Moving on
FFF-level news wires.
   Graphic.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>HOLIDAY CHEER?: Looming Tax Increase Spurs Beer Sale Boom</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   
   MILWAUKEE - Beer distributors are scrambling to find additional
supplies to meet a surge in demand caused by drinkers seeking to
stockpile their favorite beverage before the government doubles the
beer tax in January.
   Slug AM-Beer Boom. New, stands. By Anthony Shadid. Moving on
FFF-level news wires.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>THATCHER: Did She Leave a Better Britain Than She Found?</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   
   LONDON - When Margaret Thatcher left 10 Downing Street for the
last time last week, she said she was proud to be leaving the
country in much better shape than she found it in 1979. But did
she? The debate goes on.
   Slug AM-Thatcher Debate. New, stands. By Cotten Timberlake.
Moving on FFF-level news wires.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>ASIA: Growth Regions Expected To Weather U.S. Economic Storm</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   
   TOKYO - Asia's so-called ``Little Dragons'' - Taiwan, Hong Kong,
South Korea and Singapore - enjoyed explosive growth in the '80s
thanks largely to soaring exports to a thriving American market.
But the Persian Gulf crisis and a looming U.S. recession have the
region worried.
   Slug AM-Asia-US Economy. New, stands. By S.L. Bachman. Moving on
FFF- and AAA-level news wires. Also moved in advance.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>CREDIT MARKETS: Group Says Get Out of Junk Funds Before It's Too
Late</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   
   NEW YORK - Bond Investors Association Inc. is offering some
advice to junk bond mutual fund investors: Get out before it's too
late.
   Slug AM-Credit Markets. New, stands. By Business Writer Dan
Blake. Moving on FFF-level news wires. Also moved in advance.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>TICKER TALK: Could Paper Stock Certificates Go the Way of Silent
Movies</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   
   WASHINGTON - Federal regulators are exploring ways to streamline
the process for getting stocks to the buyer and payment to the
seller - including a reform to replace paper stock certificates
with computerized listings.
   Slug AM-Ticker Talk. New, stands. By Business Writer John M.
Doyle. Moving on FFF-level news wires. Also moved in advance.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   ---
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   For repeats of AP copy, the Service Desk can be reached at
212-621-1595 or 1596.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0084 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 1320EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r v AM-BusinessNewsDigest     12-02 0580</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Business News Digest,0735</SECOND>
<BYLINE>Monday AMs:</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the top business stories at this hour. Bart Ziegler is
the AMs supervisor. If you have questions about the spot news and
feature report, call AP Business News at 212-621-1686.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>---</HEAD>
<BYLINE>TRUMP: Casino Regulators To Examine Taj Mahal Casino's Finances</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   
   ATLANTIC CITY, N.J. - Donald J. Trump's Taj Mahal Casino Resort
must show gaming regulators on Monday it remains healthy despite a
restructuring that will temporarily throw it into bankruptcy court.
   Slug AM-Trump Hearing. New, stands. By Henry Stern. Moving on
FFF- and AAA-level news wires.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>RETAILING: Pier 1's Successful Expansion Is Facing First Test</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   
   FORT WORTH, Texas - The rapid expansion of Pier 1 Imports Inc.,
which began five years ago when the company updated its '60s-style
merchandise and look, is facing its first big sales test - a
lackluster holiday season.
   Slug AM-Pier 1. New, stands. By Business Writer Evan Ramstad.
Moving on FFF-level news wires.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>ALAR: Opponents Say Alar Lawsuit Is Unconstitutional</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   
   YAKIMA, Wash. - Apple growers are striking back at critics in a
lawsuit that could be the first salvo in a nationwide war with
environmental groups over the use of farm chemicals.
   Slug AM-Alar Lawsuit. New, stands. By Nicholas K. Geranios.
Moving on FFF-level news wires.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>MCA: Station Spinoff Will Test How Much Major Market TV Station
Worth</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   
   NEW YORK - MCA Inc.'s plans to spin off its television station
as a separate company just before MCA is swallowed in a
multibillion-dollar deal sets up a unique test of how much a
major-market TV outlet is worth.
   Slug AM-MCA-Station Spinoff. New, stands. By Business Writer
Skip Wollenberg. Moving on FFF-level news wires.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>TIMBER TROUBLES: Once Housing Slump Ends, Spotted Owl Still Looms</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   
   GRANTS PASS, Ore. - The northern spotted owl and a slump in the
homebuilding industry have combined to cause trouble for the
Northwest timber industry in recent months.
   Slug AM-Timber Jobs. New, stands. By Jeff Barnard. Moving on
FFF-level news wires.
   Graphic.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>HOLIDAY CHEER?: Looming Tax Increase Spurs Beer Sale Boom</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   
   MILWAUKEE - Beer distributors are scrambling to find additional
supplies to meet a surge in demand caused by drinkers seeking to
stockpile their favorite beverage before the government doubles the
beer tax in January.
   Slug AM-Beer Boom. New, stands. By Anthony Shadid. Moving on
FFF-level news wires.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>THATCHER: Did She Leave a Better Britain Than She Found?</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   
   LONDON - When Margaret Thatcher left 10 Downing Street for the
last time last week, she said she was proud to be leaving the
country in much better shape than she found it in 1979. But did
she? The debate goes on.
   Slug AM-Thatcher Debate. New, stands. By Cotten Timberlake.
Moving on FFF-level news wires.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>ASIA: Growth Regions Expected To Weather U.S. Economic Storm</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   
   TOKYO - Asia's so-called ``Little Dragons'' - Taiwan, Hong Kong,
South Korea and Singapore - enjoyed explosive growth in the '80s
thanks largely to soaring exports to a thriving American market.
But the Persian Gulf crisis and a looming U.S. recession have the
region worried.
   Slug AM-Asia-US Economy. New, stands. By S.L. Bachman. Moving on
FFF- and AAA-level news wires. Also moved in advance.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>CREDIT MARKETS: Group Says Get Out of Junk Funds Before It's Too
Late</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   
   NEW YORK - Bond Investors Association Inc. is offering some
advice to junk bond mutual fund investors: Get out before it's too
late.
   Slug AM-Credit Markets. New, stands. By Business Writer Dan
Blake. Moving on FFF-level news wires. Also moved in advance.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>TICKER TALK: Could Paper Stock Certificates Go the Way of Silent
Movies</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   
   WASHINGTON - Federal regulators are exploring ways to streamline
the process for getting stocks to the buyer and payment to the
seller - including a reform to replace paper stock certificates
with computerized listings.
   Slug AM-Ticker Talk. New, stands. By Business Writer John M.
Doyle. Moving on FFF-level news wires. Also moved in advance.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   ---
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   For repeats of AP copy, the Service Desk can be reached at
212-621-1595 or 1596.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
</Collection>
