<Collection>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0001 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 2324EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Israel-USEnvoy     08-12 0237</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel-US Envoy,0241</SECOND>
<HEAD>Israel Names New Ambassador To The United States</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The new government Sunday approved the
nomination of Zalman Shoval as its ambassador to the United States,
a Foreign Ministry spokesman said.
   Shoval, 60, a legislator from Prime Minister Yitzhak Shamir's
right-wing Likud bloc, will resign from the parliament, or Knesset,
before assuming his post, the spokesman said.
   The replacement will take effect at the end of September after
the U.S. administration agrees to the nomination in accordance with
diplomatic protocol, he said.
   Shoval himself, speaking on Israel army radio, expressed hope he
would encounter a more positive atmosphere in Washington than did
his predecessor, Moshe Arad.
   The U.S. administration has been increasingly critical of the
Jewish state over its failed peace efforts with the Palestinians.
They have been waging a 32-month rebellion against Israeli
occupation of the West Bank and the Gaza Strip.
   Shoval said the U.S. administration, due to the Persian Gulf
crisis, now appears to realize that ``the Israeli-Palestinian
conflict is not the main reason for conflict in the Middle East and
that Israel is in the end the only stable ally the United States
has in the Middle East.''
   The Polish-born Shoval is an veteran Israeli politician who is
also experienced in diplomacy. In 1955-1957, he worked at the
Foreign Ministry, where he rose from a cadet to the post of deputy
head of the North American desk.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0002 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 2335EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-BikerRally 2ndLd-Writethru a0810 08-12 0669</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Biker Rally, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0810,0685</SECOND>
<HEAD>Violence Dampens Festivities At End Of Motorcycle Rally</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 15 grafs to move up reference to deaths. pick up
16th graf pvs, `Sturgis residents...</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By CHET BROKAW</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>STURGIS, S.D. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Long strings of motorcycles roared out of
western South Dakota on Sunday as the weeklong 50th Black Hills
Motor Classic came to a violence-marred end.
   The event drew an estimated 300,000 bikers to the area. Its
mostly peaceful, festive mood was dampened by a Saturday night
shooting and stabbing brawl involving the Outlaws and Sons of
Silence motorcycle gangs. Three men were injured.
   By Sunday, the event had claimed 11 lives. Nine people died in
traffic accidents, one person was killed by carbon-monoxide
poisoning in a tent, and police shot and killed a knife-wielding
Australian man who charged the officers.
   Law officers issued 1,060 traffic tickets and 2,143 warnings,
and made 202 drunken driving and 73 drug arrests. Officials
reported 133 traffic accidents, 78 involving injuries.
   The fight occurred Saturday night at Gunner's Lounge and Casino
on Main Street, usually a hangout for Hells Angels during the
event, officials said. Two Sons of Silence members were
hospitalized in stable but serious condition Sunday with stab
wounds, said Meade County Sheriff Floyd Cleland. A member of the
Outlaws was treated for gunshot wounds and released.
   The stabbing victims will be charged with aggravated assault,
and the gunshot victim may also be charged, Cleland said.
   ``It sure puts a damper on people having a good time,'' said
Matt Waller of Gillette, Wyo., who operated a food stand near the
Main Street bar where the fight occurred.
   By Sunday morning, the scene on Main Street appeared to return
to normal. Bikers again rode and walked the route around a huge
cluster of motorcycles parked down the center and along the length
of the street.
   The violence didn't take anyone by surprise.
   ``As I've said before, the potential is there,'' Cleland said.
``These people all drink booze, take drugs and carry knives and
guns.''
   ``With this amount of people, you know there's going to be
things happen. There's going to be accidents. There's going to be
fights,'' said Bill Kienast, who works at a truck-building company
in Oshkosk, Wis.
   Marcy Myhre, executive director of the Sturgis Area Chamber of
Commerce's Black Hills Motor Classic Board, noted that last year's
rally drew only 60,000 people.
   The week went well, except for a few incidents of violence, she
said. ``We put a lot of effort into it, and it's too bad things
like that have to happen.''
   Some Sturgis residents have tried to stop the rally, but most
seem to accept and even enjoy the crowds that invade the town of
7,000 one week each year. According to conservative estimates, the
bikers and other visitors spent at least $34 million in the town
and surrounding Black Hills.
   ``A lot of them feel it was a little too much, but a lot of them
realize this is a once-in-a-lifetime crowd, too,'' Myhre said.
   Sturgis residents Ken and Barb Grosch were on Main Street
Saturday night _ before the riot _ recorded images of people and
motorcycles with a video camera.
   ``It's nice to see a small, boring town come alive,'' said Mrs.
Grosch. ``I think it's great, but after a week or so I'm ready to
see them go home.''
   Main Street was the center of activity, with thousands of
motorcycles parked in the middle of the street and at the curb, and
bikers sporting leather and tattoos as they gathered around their
``hogs.''
   Merlin Rosen, a veterinary student from Fort Collins, Colo.,
posed with two boa constrictors wrapped around her neck and arms.
   ``Everybody has to stop and look, and there's always the
attraction of being seen,'' she said.
   Biker gangs weren't the only ones who showed up for the week of
races and other events. There are many motorcycle enthusiasts among
the well-heeled; the late Malcolm Forbes attended last year's rally.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0003 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 2344EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a BC-LOT--SaturdayLotteries     08-12 0826</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-LOT--Saturday Lotteries,0983</SECOND>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<HEAD>ARIZONA</HEAD>
<HEAD>Pick</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PHOENIX (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers in Saturday night's drawing
of the Arizona Lottery's Pick game were 3, 5, 6, 16, 27 and 40 with
a bonus number of 33.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>CONNECTICUT</HEAD>
<HEAD>Play 4</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEWINGTON, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning combination picked Saturday
in the Connecticut State Lottery's ``Play 4'' drawing was:
   0-6-0-1.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEWINGTON, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning combination picked Saturday
in the Connecticut State Lottery's ``Daily Lottery'' drawing was:
   9-6-8
</TEXT>
<HEAD>DELAWARE</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DOVER, Del. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   These Delaware lotteries were drawn Saturday
night:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   8-7-0
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Play Four</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   4-2-9-7
</TEXT>
<HEAD>FLORIDA</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected Saturday in
the Florida Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   17-42-18-10-06-19
</TEXT>
<HEAD>ILLINOIS</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SPRINGFIELD, Ill. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the Illinois State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   2-1-7
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick For</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   1-7-4-3
</TEXT>
<HEAD>LOTTO</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   32-49-28-1-12-37
</TEXT>
<HEAD>IOWA</HEAD>
<HEAD>Iowa Lotto</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DES MOINES, Iowa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers drawn Saturday night
in ``Iowa Lotto'' are:
   7-14-19-24-30-33.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto America</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DES MOINES, Iowa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers drawn Saturday night
in ``Lotto America'' are:
   04-13-16-24-27-33
</TEXT>
<HEAD>KANSAS</HEAD>
<HEAD>Kan. Cash Lotto</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOPEKA, Kan. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers in the Kansas Cash Lotto
drawing Saturday night with an estimated jackpot of $75,000:
   2-3-5-8-17-21
</TEXT>
<HEAD>KENTUCKY</HEAD>
<HEAD>Kentucky Lottery</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOUISVILLE, Ky. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are Saturday's winning numbers
selected by the Kentucky Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Kentucky Cash:
   9-1-7.
   </HEAD>
<HEAD>Lotto:
   5-16-21-22-29-30.
   </HEAD>
<HEAD>MARYLAND</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BALTIMORE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   These Maryland lotteries were drawn Saturday
night:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   1-6-6
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Play Four</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   4-8-4-5
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   06-12-26-41-42-49
</TEXT>
<HEAD>MASSACHUSETTS</HEAD>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BRAINTREE, Mass. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers drawn Saturday night
in the ``Massachusetts Daily Lottery'' were:
   9-4-5-0
</TEXT>
<HEAD>MICHIGAN</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DETROIT (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected Saturday in
the Michigan State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   4-9-6
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily-4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   8-3-7-7
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto 47</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   15, 19, 29, 30, 37, 41
</TEXT>
<HEAD>MISSOURI</HEAD>
<HEAD>Pick 3</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ST. LOUIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers in Saturday's Missouri
Lottery Daily Pick 3 game:
   6-5-2
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ST. LOUIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers in Missouri's Lotto drawing
Saturday night:
   7-25-29-34-38-40
</TEXT>
<HEAD>NEW JERSEY</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TRENTON, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday night in the New Jersey State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 3</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   5-0-6
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   8-5-7-5
</TEXT>
<HEAD>NEW YORK</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ALBANY, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the New York State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Number</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   8-8-4
</TEXT>
<HEAD>WinFour</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   9-9-3-0
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 10</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ALBANY, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the New York State Lottery's Pick 10 game:
   
   2, 9, 11, 18, 20, 22, 24, 26, 28, 31, 36, 43, 45, 52, 53, 63,
65, 68, 72, 77.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>___</HEAD>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ALBANY, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the New York State Lottery's Lotto game:
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   4, 7, 19, 32, 35, 54. The supplementary number was 5.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>NORTHERN NEW ENGLAND</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CONCORD, N.H. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the daily New Hampshire, Vermont and Maine lotteries:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 3</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   3-2-5
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   8-9-9-6
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Tri-State Megabucks</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CONCORD, N.H. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers in the
``Tri-State Megabucks'' game for New Hampshire, Vermont and Maine:
   17-20-22-24-26-31
</TEXT>
<HEAD>OHIO</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CLEVELAND (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected Saturday
night in the Ohio Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Super Lotto</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   14-30-31-32-36-43
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Kicker</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   8-9-2-6-1-2
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 3 Numbers</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   7-1-1
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 4 Numbers</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   3-8-4-7
</TEXT>
<HEAD>OREGON</HEAD>
<HEAD>Megabucks</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PORTLAND, Ore. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are Saturday's winning numbers in the
``Oregon Megabucks'' lottery game:
   9-16-21-23-37-44
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily 4</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PORTLAND, Ore. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are Saturday's winning numbers in the
``Oregon Daily 4'' lottery game:
   0-9-1-2
</TEXT>
<HEAD>PENNSYLVANIA</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HARRISBURG (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected Saturday
in the Pennsylvania State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Number</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   2-7-0
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Big 4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   1-3-2-9
</TEXT>
<HEAD>RHODE ISLAND</HEAD>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CRANSTON, R.I. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers drawn Saturday night
in the Rhode Island Daily Lottery were:
   6-5-0-0
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lot-O-Bucks</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CRANSTON, R.I. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers drawn Saturday night
in the Rhode Island Lot-O-Bucks were:
   3-12-29-30-34
</TEXT>
<HEAD>VIRGINIA</HEAD>
<HEAD>Pick 3</HEAD>
<DATELINE>RICHMOND (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   These numbers were drawn Saturday in the
Virginia Lottery's Pick 3 game:
   3-3-3
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<DATELINE>RICHMOND (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   These numbers were drawn Saturday in the
Virginia Lottery's Lotto game:
   1-20-25-34-37-43
</TEXT>
<HEAD>WASHINGTON</HEAD>
<DATELINE>OLYMPIA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are winning numbers selected Saturday in the
Washington State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   3-6-5
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   13-14-28-29-31-42
</TEXT>
<HEAD>WASHINGTON, DC</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The following results were drawn Saturday in
the District of Columbia Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lucky Numbers Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   3-5-7
</TEXT>
<HEAD>D.C. Four Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   8-4-4-3
</TEXT>
<HEAD>D.C. Daily Double Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   41, 67
</TEXT>
<HEAD>D.C. Quick Cash Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   18-26-33-10-21-1
</TEXT>
<HEAD>WEST VIRGINIA</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CHARLESTON, W.Va. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the West Virginia State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily 3</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   0-5-9
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily 4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   9-2-8-5
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0004 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 2349EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-CitySchools     08-12 1190</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-City Schools,1228</SECOND>
<HEAD>Money Shortages Choking Reform in Big City Schools</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Monday AMs report.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By LEE MITGANG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Education Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   For years, Philadelphia schools have offered students a chance
to study Latin as early as fourth grade. But this fall, fewer kids
will learn their ``amo, amas, amat's'': a tight budget has forced
the layoff of six out of 26 itinerant Latin teachers.
   ``An awful lot of them won't even finish high school, and the
only language they are exposed to is street language. This is the
one opportunity they have to get a little something beyond
that,''said one laid-off Latin teacher, H. Michael Dunn.
   Many such cuts, affecting both innovative programs and
day-to-day operations, await big-city districts across the country
this fall. A check by The Associated Press found that districts
from Philadelphia, Boston and New York to Dade County, Fla., and
Los Angeles face the worst fiscal problems since the mid-'70s.
   ``It's going to be tough to innovate when you're trying to
survive,'' said James Fleming, associate superintendent of Dade
County schools, a district that gained national notice for school
reforms but now faces a $108 million deficit that will likely lead
to more crowded classes.
   With a possible recession looming and worsening state finances
putting a squeeze on school budgets, big-city school officials
everywhere are bracing for teacher hiring freezes, layoffs, and
larger classes.
   ``It's a very bleak fall,'' said Jewell Gould, research director
of the American Federation of Teachers.
   He and others believe next spring could bring even worse news
when districts customarily send out layoff notices.
   One leading reformer called this fall's cutbacks fresh evidence
that political leaders give more lip service than resources to
school improvement.
   ``If snow is piling up in city streets, you get a greater sense
of emergency than if half the kids drop out of school year after
year,'' said Ernest L. Boyer, president of the Carnegie Foundation
for the Advancement of Teaching.
   ``On the one hand, we say education is at the center of what we
hope for and dream about, and we almost get maudlin about it. But
then if something happens, it gets put off as `kid stuff,''' he
said.
   ``This is easily the worst fiscal crisis I have seen in the last
20 years,'' said Fleming of Dade County.
   State funding fell $44 million less than expected, said Dade
County school spokesman Andy Gollan. It's already meant elimination
of a merit schools program where schools devised innovative
programs to help students achieve educational goals.
   Philadelphia, anticipating deficits of $68 million for fiscal
year 1991-92, $170 million in 1993, and $275 million in 1994, has
put on hold reforms including full-day kindergartens, lengthening
the school day and year, and more classroom computers.
   ``It's come to a period where we have to make hard choices,
which are not necessarily popular choices,'' said Leontine D.
Scott, associate superintendent.
   In Boston, a $397 million budget approved last week is $6.4
million lower than last year's. Cuts include 100 fewer non-tenured
teachers, fewer school police, reduced extracurricular and
after-school programs, less funding for a city-financed parent
organization, and reductions in a private industry council that
provides jobs for high-school students.
   The city's schoolchildren are ``treated like second-class
citizens because they don't have the political clout that other
communities have,'' said Boston School Committee member Peggy Davis
Mullen.
   In Los Angeles, a $220 million budget gap earlier this year
forced extensive administrative cuts. The crisis worsened last week
when Gov. George Deukmejian announced he was withholding $465
million in school funds statewide, compelling the district to cut
$77 million more from the 1990-91 budget.
   School officials haven't decided yet how to parcel out the cuts.
But a number of reform ideas have already been shelved or reduced.
   A Bilingual Master Plan designed to help non-English speaking
students in all major subject areas has been only partially funded.
The district is also postponing expansion of its school-based
management program in which more than 60 schools participate.
   ``Devastating would not be too strong a word,'' said school
board member Rita Walters. ``It just socks it to us.''
   New York City's school board must come up with $26.8 million in
instructional cuts this fall after having already eliminated some
350 jobs at the central board.
   ``How that will be done is the unanswered question,'' said Susan
Amlung, a spokeswoman for the United Federation of Teachers.
   The district is likely to cut school aides and
paraprofessionals, measures that the union fears will put more
students in already-overcrowded classes. School officials insist
that won't happen. Kindergarten classes currently average 24.8
pupils, and high-school classes of 40 or more are not uncommon.
   Seattle's $243.6 million school budget has meant eliminating 165
teaching, administrative and other positions, mainly through
attrition.
   ``It's been a difficult time,'' said Seattle schools budget
manager George Steinhofer. ``We've taken a number of reductions in
central administration and this year we took reductions in special
education and bilingual programs. The only place left to look is in
basic educational programs.''
   New Orleans is closing two of its three centers for problem
students, and 60 school employees were laid off to balance the $358
million budget, said superintendent Everett Williams.
   ``That's been the story of our life in this school district for
the past four or five years. I have had no budget that's been an
even budget, where I have been able to start off the year with no
cuts at all,'' he said.
   In Houston, Superintendent Joan Raymond is pushing for a record
18 percent tax rate hike to fund a $797.9 million budget. The
proposed budget would provide a 10 percent pay raise for teachers,
31 new principals and deans, a dropout prevention program, beefed
up security, a principal performance incentive program and funding
of a massive construction program.
   But some taxpayers are resisting:
   ``By no extent of the imagination is the public going along with
this, '' said John Pellicciotti, a board member of the Taxpayers
Coalition of Greater Houston.
   Not all cities are in such dire straits.
   In Atlanta, public schools comptroller Lawrence Thompson said
the district has not had cuts. Next year's budget is $331.3
million, compared with $319.3 million this past school year.
   ``We've been pretty fortunate,'' Thompson said.
   Newark, with a $421 million school budget, has an $8.5 million
shortfall but has largely avoided layoffs. Some assistant
principals and other administrators may be demoted to save money,
said spokesman Kirk Smith.
   Next year, the district will get as much as $50 million in
additional funds as part of a state plan to boost the quality of
New Jersey city schools. But another state plan to shift teacher
pension costs entirely to local districts could cancel out those
gains, Smith said.
   In Detroit, an $889 million budget for the 1990-91 school year
includes such reform initiatives as expanded preschools and special
schools meant to help troubled ninth-graders avoid disciplinary
problems.
   A 5-mill property tax increase and a bond issue approved by
voters last September wiped out the district's $160 million deficit.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>EDITOR'S NOTE _ Lee Mitgang has covered education for the AP</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   since 1981.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0005 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 2352EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Iraq-Kuwait-Editorials     08-12 0913</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Iraq-Kuwait-Editorials,0949</SECOND>
<HEAD>Look at U.S. Editorial Pages' Views of Desert Showdown</HEAD>
<HEAD>With Iraq-Kuwait Rdp</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are excerpts from editorials on the Middle East crisis in
Sunday editions of U.S. newspapers:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Dallas Times Herald</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   The Mideast crisis triggered by the decision of militaristic
Iraq to seize one oil-producing nation and threaten the conquest of
others has, predictably, destabilized the world's energy network.
... What is surprising _ and inexcusable _ is that America enters
this state of confusion without an energy policy any more
comprehensive than the hapless policies of 1973. The Iraqi threat
to one of the world's major oil-producing regions should force the
development of an energy policy designed to secure the nation's
energy needs. ... A national energy policy is long overdue.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>The News Tribune, Tacoma, Wash.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Faster than anyone had bargained for, America is learning what
it will take to defend its national interests in the post-Cold War
era. Neither hawks nor doves of the old school are enjoying the
lesson.
   ... One lesson of Kuwait is that the United States must maintain
enough military strength to protect its commerce and citizens from
pirates like Hussein. This is a depressing prospect for doves who
have been gleefully preparing to cut America's defense budget.
   Middle East events haven't been kind to Cold War hawks, either.
...
   European armies, MIRVed missiles and $800 million bombers aren't
much use against the likes of Hussein. The crises America is likely
to face in the foreseeable future will demand strong airborne and
Marine forces, light armor, tactical air and naval power, much of
it able to move on a day's notice to any trouble spot in the world.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>The Journal-Constitution, Atlanta</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Saddam wants to be seen as a military strongman who gets what he
needs through brute strength. He sees hostage-takingy, correctly,
as the desperate resort of the powerless and not worthy of the
self-proclaimed leader of the Arab world.
   Not yet that is. If they are not actual hostages, the foreign
nationals held by Iraq represent insurance for Saddam. They are his
rainy-day fund, so to speak. If and when his situation
deteriorates, which it will, they will become far more valuable.
They will become, in truth, hostages.
   It is the rule of the Middle East bazaar: Any Americans held
hostage by Iraq become worth what we are willing to pay. The more
preoccupied we become with getting them back, the more unlikely
they will be released at a price we are capable of paying.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Star Tribune, Minneapolis</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   ...By snatching Kuwait, Hussein injected uncertainty into the
worldwide oil system. Uncertainty affects prices because oil
selling today has to be priced at what it will cost tomorrow to
replace it. Uncertainty affects supplies because consumers from the
motorist to the refiner to the gas-pump jockey lay in extra in case
shortages develop, thereby creating supply disruptions. ...
   Whether in the Persian Gulf or at home, bad oil news will be
telegraphed to Americans via their local gas pump. They should get
mad: at themselves if they continue to let their dependence on
imported oil make them vulnerable to madmen.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>The Sunday Journal, Providence, R.I.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   ... It should be said that the Arab League's decision (to send
Arab troops to defend Saudi Arabia) is one of the more hopeful
signs for the future of world peace since World War II. For it
therapeutically destroys the myth of Arab unity _ a fantasy based
on the preposterous but powerful assumption that the various Arab
countries comprise one ``Arab nation.''
   ... (Saddam) has forced fellow Arabs to choose between civilized
international behavior and a bloody-minded Arab dictator.
   It also represents a great personal victory for President Bush
and for U.S. efforts to create a global force to thwart Iraqi
aggression. The President has spent much time and energy trying to
ensure that the world community, and not just the West, condemns
and confronts Baghdad.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>The Sunday Sun, Baltimore</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   There's an immediate lesson to be drawn from the confrontation
in the Persian Gulf. ... The danger of this country's crushing
dependence on imported oil. In part that's a legacy of the Reagan
years but it is also a failure of industry and consumers to
recognize the advantages of alternate energy sources.
   There aren't any quick-fix solutions. The fastest and cheapest
way to respond to the cutback in oil imports would be a national
conservation program. The president, in concert with the nation's
governors and mayors, ought to act immediately to curb profligate
use of petroleum.
   We can no longer remain complacent about importing 50 percent of
our petroleum. This imbalance must be ended. Our future economic
well-being is at stake.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>The Columbus (Ohio) Dispatch</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Although U.S. military experts grow more sanguine as each hour
passes, the wild card in this is the unpredictability of the
volatile Saddam, a man who has used poison gas against the Kurds in
his own country and against teen-age Iranian soldiers. His
volatility makes military planning against him more difficult.
   ... Saddam can rant all he wants, but he is up against
formidable odds. His whole economy is based on the Iraqis' ability
to sell their oil, so as long as the blockade is successful, it
amounts to an economic choke-hold.
   The events played out in the sands of the Middle East will
surely have repercussions on the U.S. domestic front, in terms of
both energy and defense policies.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>
<TEXT>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0006 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 2354EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Iraq-Kuwait-Editorials-1stAdd     08-12 0530</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Iraq-Kuwait-Editorials - 1st Add,0542</SECOND>
<HEAD>UNDATED: defense policies.</HEAD>
<HEAD>The Washington Post</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   It is heartening to see Egypt exercising leadership in the
strategy to force Iraq out of Kuwait. For the United States and
Europe, the primary interest in political stability there is the
flow of oil. Iraq's neighbors have much more at stake. Iraq has
made it clear that its intentions go beyond this month's conquest.
It proposes to make itself dominant among the Arabs. Saddam Hussein
has been claiming, in recent days, to speak for all the Arab world
in a great test of will and of strength with the Americans. But
most of the Arab world denounced him on Friday in the Arab League's
meeting, and now Egyptian forces as well as Americans face him at
the Saudi border.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>The Detroit News</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   No one in Washington, it seems, wants to use the ``H'' word _
hostages _ to describe the several thousand Americans who were
caught in Kuwait and Iraq at the time of the latter's blitzkrieg
conquest of the former two weeks ago. With every day that passes
without their being allowed to leave, however, it becomes harder to
avoid the conclusion that they are being held against their will.
   (President Bush) should set a deadline for the unconditional
release of the Americans. Failure to comply will result in attacks
on Iraqi oil fields and other targets. Harm to any Americans would
be considered an act of all-out war.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>The Philadelphia Inquirer</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   An Arab force on the Saudi border will signal that an attack
will embroil him (Hussein) in an inter-Arab war. It is hoped that
this would also undercut his attempt to portray himself as the hero
who would save Arab oil fields and Muslim holy places from unclean
Western hands.
   ... The real test of global cooperation against Iraq will be if
that blockade holds. It could take months for sanctions to move
Baghdad, and Saddam Hussein will undoubtedly counterattack. He may
use hostages or terrorism, or undermine Arab leaders who stand up
to him. It will take patience, and test White House leadership, to
keep a global blockade going. But the best inspiration to stick
together may come from listening to the words of Saddam Hussein.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Los Angeles Times</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   The crisis provoked by Iraq's invasion of Kuwait has escalated
into the first major confrontation of the post-Cold War era and new
realities, both hopeful and sobering, are emerging.
   Foremost among the latter is the realization that a world
liberated from the threat of nuclear annihilation will not be free
of mortal danger. As the case of Saddam Hussein makes all too
clear, there remain good old-fashioned nationalist dictators every
bit as aggressive and threatening as Stalinist ideologues. ...
   But ... much that has transpired so far should be a source of
hope. The willingness of the vast majority of the world's nations
to directly and collectively engage Hussein's challenge is, as
foreign policy analyst Stanley Hoffman put it, ``quite
remarkable.'' In fact, if the anti-Hussein coalition holds
together, this crisis could, as former diplomat Richard N. Gardner
has said, ``constitute a landmark event in the history of this
century.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0007 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 2359EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-What'sinaTitle     08-12 0691</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-What's in a Title,0709</SECOND>
<HEAD>I Don't Care Who You Call Me, but Get My Title Right</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Monday AMs report.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By KENNETH L. WHITING</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>KUALA LUMPUR, Malaysia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Every Malay who is anybody has a
title, from the duli yang maha mulia seri paduka baginda yang
di-pertuan agong _ that's the king _ to each haji and hajah who
makes the Moslem pilgrimage to Mecca.
   Tun, tan seri and datuk are among the many hereditary or
conferred titles borne by leading citizens.
   Proper ways of addressing a Malay are diverse and complicated.
Family names are relatively unimportant as long as the title is
used correctly. Improper usage may cause offense.
   Some titles are gained at birth, others given as rewards for
service to government or nation. To the ordinary encik (mister),
titles and forms of address can be confusing.
   The king's title means, approximately, ``his most glorious
majesty who is raised most high.'' In English, ``your majesty'' is
usually enough. The queen, or seri baginda raja permaisuri agong,
also is ``your majesty.''
   Malaysia is unique in having a monarchy that rotates among royal
families. Nine of the 13 states have royal families, whose leaders
take turns being king of the entire nation for five years.
   Passing the throne around solved a sticky protocol problem when
Malaysia shed colonial ties with Britain in 1957. None of the nine
state rulers would have been accepted by the other eight as
permanent king and Tunku Abdul Rahman, who was prime minister,
divised the method of sharing glory.
   Children of the state rulers usually are called tunku or tengku,
loosely equivalent to prince or princess. Tunku Rahman, for
example, is of royal descent.
   Niks and megats are those with royal blood on the mother's side.
Syeds and their female counterparts, sharifahs, claim to be
directly descended from the prophet Mohammed, from royal families
of the Malay archipelago, or both.
   A man honored for distinguished service to the nation becomes a
tun and his wife a toh puan. The title is Malaysia's highest order
of chivalry, limited to 25 living men.
   When Prime Minister Dato Seri Dr. Mahathir Mohamad retires,
officials say, he probably will become Tun Mahathir. He is a
medical doctor and was made a dato seri years ago for his
contributions to public life.
   The non-hereditary title tan seri is given to the recipient of
either of Malaysia's two second-highest orders of chivalry for
non-royals.
   Datuks, and the variants datuk seri and dato, are numerous and
their wives are datins. The title is non-hereditary and its basic
meaning is grandfather.
   In higher social circles, practically everybody is a datuk,
whether Malay, Chinese or Indian.
   A common compliment is to call a man dato before he has been so
designated. Few object, except the very modest.
   The highlight of the king's official birthday, celebrated on the
first Wednesday of June, is the conferment of hundreds of awards
and titles. Hundreds more are issued each year by the 13 states,
with datuk in the majority.
   Tuan means sir in Malay, and is used informally to address an
elderly person or someone of prominence or wealth. Tuan yang
terutama, the Malay translation of excellency, is applied to heads
of diplomatic missions and the governors of the four states without
royal families.
   Puan, or madame, often is used to refer to married women. A
single women is called cik.
   Haji and hajah are the titles for men and women who have made a
pilgrimage, or haj, to Mecca and performed certain acts required on
a pilgrimage.
   In Malay usage, bin means ``son of'' and binte means ``daughter
of.'' The part of the name before it is the given name, and the
part after is the name of the person's father.
   Names can be as confusing as titles. The prime minister is
Mahathir Mohamad, the information minister is Mohamed Rahmat and
thousands of others spell the name Mohamat, Muhamat, Muhhammad and
even Mohd.
   In 1988, the goverment decreed the official version of the
prophet's name to be Muhammad. Those already born and named with
other spellings were excused from compliance.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0008 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 0023EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-MatisseCustody 1stLd-Writethru a0644 08-12 0474</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Matisse Custody, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0644,0481</SECOND>
<HEAD>Report: Child Wins Back Matisse Painting</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 4 grafs to CORRECT spelling of Matisse in lead and
restore first reference to artist in 4th graf. </NOTE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The great-granddaughter of photographer Edward
Steichen has won back a Matisse painting valued at $800,000 after a
legal battle with the Museum of Modern Art, according to a
published report.
   But 6-year-old Ariana Rodina Calderone Stahmer probably will
never see the painting in her home because it will be sold to cover
legal bills her family has to pay, The New York Times reported in
Sunday editions.
   The Times said the museum settled out of court on Friday but
terms of the arrangement in federal court in Bridgeport, Conn.,
were not made public. The child's family spent more than $100,000
in legal fees in the dispute, the newspaper reported.
   Henri Matisse presented Edward Steichen with the painting, ``Vue
de Collioure a l'Eglise,'' in 1908 to thank him for helping arrange
the first American exhibition of his works and to commemorate the
birth of Steichen's daughter, Kate.
   Steichen gave Kate Steichen the painting on her 53rd birthday,
and she in turn loaned it to the museum in 1973, the year her
father died. She died in 1988 and the museum and the family have
argued over the painting ever since.
   The museum Miss Steichen donated the painting to the museum. The
family said Miss Steichen bequeathed the painting to her
grandniece, Ariana, who lives in Pennington, N.J.
   ``It's a little bit late,'' said the girl's father, Joel
Stahmer. ``They felt they could wait us out in terms of money. They
were as uncharitable as a charitable organization can be.''
   Richard E. Oldenburg, director of the museum, issued a statement
that said in part: ``Given its long relationship with Edward
Steichen, the museum does not wish to be in conflict with the his
family.''
   Steichen was in charge of the museum's photography department
from 1947 to 1962 and put together a number of exhibitions,
including the widely viewed ``The Family of Man.''
   Ariana's mother, Francesca Calderone-Steichen, told the Times
she was selling the painting, which she had hoped to hang in her
daughter's bedroom.
   ``I feel very sad,'' she said. ``She adored my aunt and this
would have been a way to keep that bond. Now the painting is never
going to be in the house. The only way she'll see it is in a book.''
   In April, when the lawsuit was filed, lawyers for the estate
contended the museum was waging a war of attrition against a modest
estate, a stategy they say would eventually backfire.
   ``Who else is going to lend works to the Museum of Modern Art if
they're afraid they'll treat loans as gifts?'' asked attorney L.
Douglas Shrader, who filed the lawsuit.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0009 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 0016EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Colombia-Drugs 2ndLd-Writethru a0647 08-12 0460</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Colombia-Drugs, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0647,0472</SECOND>
<HEAD>Key Medellin Cartel Figure Killed In Gunfight With Police</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS thruout to UPDATE with Gaviria associate detained,
background; No Pickup.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By STAN YARBRO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOGOTA, Colombia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Police shot and killed a key member of
the violent Medellin cocaine cartel Saturday in a gunbattle in one
of Medellin's exclusive neighborhoods, police said.
   Gustavo de Jesus Gaviria, the cousin of the cartel's leader,
Pablo Escobar, was killed at 4:00 p.m. A local hospital did not
identify his body until four hours later.
   Gaviria, who authorities said was the third most important
member of the drug cartel, exchanged gunfire with police before
being killed, according to a police statement.
   The statement gave no details about how police located Gaviria
in the luxury apartment, which was equipped with bullet-resistant
windows. The apartment was located in southern Medellin's Alaneda
neighborhood.
   A police spokesman said in Medellin that one of Gaviria's
associates, Alexandra Tapias, was detained in the operation,
carried out by a special anti-narcotics police unit.
   Gaviria is the third cartel leader killed in gunbattles with
police during the past eight months.
   He is the main partner of Escobar, the Medellin cartel leader
blamed for a terrorist campaign of bombs and other attacks that
have killed hundreds of people over the past year.
   Police say Gaviria acted as his first cousin's front man in
several business transactions and that several of Escobar's
properties are registered in Gaviria's name.
   Gaviria was wanted for extradition to the United States on drug
trafficking charges.
   The Medellin cartel last month called a truce in a year-long
terrorist campaign, saying it was yielding to Colombian's desire
for peace. The cartel said in a communique that the government
should respond to the peace overture by ending its policy of
extraditing drug traffickers to the United States.
   Colombian President Cesar Gaviria said after taking office last
week that both extraditions and the crackdown on traffickers would
continue.
   All Medellin police officers were ordered to their posts late
Saturday because of fears the cartel may call off the truce
following Gaviria's death.
   Last December, police shot and killed Gonzalo Rodriguez Gacha on
Colombia's northern coast. Along with Escobar, Rodriguez Gacha was
considered one of the cartel's most violent leaders.
   Police shot and killed another major cartel figure, John Jairo
Arias, earlier this year in Medellin. Arias was said to have
coordinated the cartel's terrorist campaign.
   The cartel began the campaign last August after the government
announced its antidrug crackdown in response to the assassination
of a presidential candidate.
   The government has seized hundreds of properties of suspected
traffickers and ordered the extradition of Colombians wanted on
drug charges in the United States. Since August, the government has
extradited 22 drug trafficking suspects.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0010 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 0022EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-BikerRally 2ndLd-Writethru a0643 08-12 0591</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Biker Rally, 2nd Ld - Writethru, a0643,0604</SECOND>
<HEAD>Small-Town Police Undaunted By 300,000-Biker Rally</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 12th graf, `Another shooting...' with 2 grafs to UPDATE
with more shooting details. Restores dropped word `been' in final
sentence of 11th graf. Picks up 13th graf pvs, `Bush said...</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto XSTG2</HEAD>
<DATELINE>STURGIS, S.D. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   All week long the authorities of this town
of 7,000 have struggled to contain an ocean of roaring motorcycles
and tattooed bikers wrapped in enough leather to outfit the women
of Chicago with purses.
   On Friday, when the crowd had swelled to around 300,000, Police
Chief Jim Bush faced one of his most serious challenges _ a
showdown on Main Street between two motorcycle gangs.
   Luckily, the conflict broke off before knives were drawn. And
Bush said the police involvement in cooling tempers was, shall we
say, discreet.
   ``We didn't break anything up. We just kind of stood back,'' he
said.
   The 50th Black Hills Motor Classic, with bikers from every state
and dozens of countries, rattled toward its official close Sunday,
and police in this Black Hills town near the Wyoming border were
breathing many sighs of relief.
   Thursday night, a lead biker of the Outlaws motorcycle gang
smiled at a police officer, cocked his finger like a pistol and
gave him a little ``pow!''
   It was a small gesture, more playful than menacing, but it
signified some of the problems that Sturgis has had to cope with in
putting on the world's largest motorcycle gathering.
   Sturgis, which normally has 10 officers, in 10 days has provided
a year's worth of mayhem.
   Since Aug. 1, hundreds of law enforcement agents have issued 976
traffic tickets, given out 1,918 warnings, arrested 180 people for
drunken driving and 61 others on drug charges.
   They also have handled 116 reported accidents, 65 involving
injuries.
   The rally has been the scene of nine traffic-related deaths.
Police shot to death an Australian man, and a North Dakota woman
died of carbon monoxide poisoning. There have been a few non-fatal
stabbings.
   Law officers interviewed members of the Outlaws and Hells'
Angels Saturday night after one person was wounded in a shooting at
a downtown bar and two people were stabbed after what witnesses
described as a dispute between two motorcycle groups, Meade County
State's Attorney Mike Jackley said..
   The wounded were alive after the shooting at Gunner's Lounge and
Casino and the stabbings near the Sooper Dooper grocery, but their
conditions at a nearby hospital were not immediately available, he
said.
   Bush said he was not surprised by the number of fatalities.
   ``I thought there would probably be more, I really did, with
this many people,'' he said.
   The annual biker festival draws gangs such as the Hells' Angels,
The Bandidos, and the Sons of Silence, as well as clubs sponsored
by Christian groups and Alcoholics Anonymous. The late Malcolm
Forbes was at last year's fest.
   A coroner's jury Friday ruled that three officers acted in the
``scope of their duty'' when they shot Trevor John Hansen, of
Liverpool, Australia.
   Hansen allegedly lunged at them with a knife Tuesday. Police
were responding to a report he had driven his 2-foot-long knife
through the door of a house, broke in and held the knife under the
nose of a resident.
   ``Aside from (the shooting), we have not seen anything really
outside of what we ordinarily have seen,'' said state Attorney
General Roger Tellinghuisen.
   ``Except it's on a larger scale. And that's to be expected.
There are three times as many people here,'' Tellinghuisen said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0011 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 0307EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a BC-DiphteriaCase     08-12 0186</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Diphteria Case,0190</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rare Case of Diphtheria Worries Health Officials</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CLAYTON, Mo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A rare case of diphtheria, diagnosed in an
18-year-old woman, prompted a warning this weekend by worried
health officials.
   Most children are immunized against the potentially lethal
disease when they begin school, but they can outgrow the immunity,
said Dr. Linda A. Fisher, chief medical examiner of St. Louis
County.
   She issued a warning Saturday, asking adults not to overlook the
symptoms of diphtheria, which include sore throat, fever, cough and
difficulty swallowing.
   Diphtheria features the development of a greenish-gray membrane
in the throat. The membrane can block the airway, causing
respiratory failure.
   The woman was listed in serious condition Saturday at St. John's
Mercy Medical Center in Creve Coeur, Fisher said. She was diagnosed
with diphtheria on Friday after showing symptoms for about a week.
   Dr. Farrin Manian, an infectious disease specialist who is
treating the woman, said state records indicate this may be the
first Missouri diphtheria case in 15 years. He said medical
literature showed fewer than five cases in the United States in the
last 10 years.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0012 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 0549EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a BC-DiphtheriaCase     08-12 0192</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Diphtheria Case,0196</SECOND>
<HEAD>RETRANSMITTING to CORRECT spelling in slugline.</HEAD>
<HEAD>Rare Case of Diphtheria Worries Health Officials</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CLAYTON, Mo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A rare case of diphtheria, diagnosed in an
18-year-old woman, prompted a warning this weekend by worried
health officials.
   Most children are immunized against the potentially lethal
disease when they begin school, but they can outgrow the immunity,
said Dr. Linda A. Fisher, chief medical examiner of St. Louis
County.
   She issued a warning Saturday, asking adults not to overlook the
symptoms of diphtheria, which include sore throat, fever, cough and
difficulty swallowing.
   Diphtheria features the development of a greenish-gray membrane
in the throat. The membrane can block the airway, causing
respiratory failure.
   The woman was listed in serious condition Saturday at St. John's
Mercy Medical Center in Creve Coeur, Fisher said. She was diagnosed
with diphtheria on Friday after showing symptoms for about a week.
   Dr. Farrin Manian, an infectious disease specialist who is
treating the woman, said state records indicate this may be the
first Missouri diphtheria case in 15 years. He said medical
literature showed fewer than five cases in the United States in the
last 10 years.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0013 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 0654EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i BC-Iraq-Kuwait 1stAdd a0658 08-12 0200</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Iraq-Kuwait, 1st Add, a0658,0201</SECOND>
<HEAD>NICOSIA: be executed.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Iraq is now enjoying ``an era of pride and happiness,'' Saddam
said.
   But the Iraqi president warned that unless the mujahedat, or
female holy warriors, implement his appeal, ``The future will bring
an era of Americanism and Zionism and the Arab nation will lose its
only chance to establish an infrastructure for the march toward
liberation and an end to the oppression, hunger and slavery.''
   ``Victory depends on success of this for us and our
generations,'' Saddam said. `Today, you have additional
responsibilities to those you had shouldered before. You are called
to take on a special role in all the social and domestic affairs.''
   Saddam said women should now also take it upon themselves to
organize Iraq's economic life.
   ``It is when the economic life is organized in accordance with
the overall plan we seek, that we can consider the battle over in
favor of Iraq and the the invaders deceived, fleeing one after the
other,'' Saddam said.
   ``It is then that we will possess all the potentials to take on
all the amassed forces of evil and those who might be massed in the
next two months,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0014 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 0847EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i BC-Turkey-Iraq     08-12 0401</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Turkey-Iraq,0411</SECOND>
<HEAD>Turkish Premier Asks Lawmakers for Power to Declare War</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ANKARA, Turkey (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The premier said on Sunday he will ask
Parliament for the power to declare a state of war and send armed
forces into combat in the event of an escalation of the Persian
Gulf crisis.
   Premier Yildirim Akbulut made the announcement before the start
of an extraordinary session of Parliament to discuss the crisis
caused by Iraq's invasion of Kuwait and massing of troops on Saudi
Arabia's border.
   A multinational force led by the United States is being sent to
Saudi Arabia to protect that nation against a possible Iraqi
invasion, and some news reports have said that Iraq also is
building up troops on Turkey's border.
   ``This is not an authorization we are going to use now,''
Akbulut said, describing it as a precautionary measure. He told
deputies of his governing Motherland Party that ``we have no
intention of going to war. But we cannot remain indiffeent when
there is a state of war next door to us.''
   ``There is no intention of any agression on our part, this is a
purely defensive measure,'' he said.
   President Turgut Ozal told reporters on Saturday that the
government could ask for war powers authorization ``just in case,
to be prepared for any eventuality.'' This would make it easier to
take fast action in case of a surprise attack, he said.
   Under the Turkish Constitution, approval from Parliament is
required to send Turkish troops abroad in a war or to allow foreign
combat troops to be stationed in the country.
   Sunday's session was sought by opposition parties, which have
been warning the government to refrain from ``a foreign adventure''
that could land Turkey in a war in the region. Parliament had been
on a recess.
   Complying with U.N. economic sanctions against Iraq, Turkey on
Tuesday effectively closed down two Iraqi pipelines through the
country and banned all trade except emergency food and medical
supplies.
   The Turkish military also has been taking measures described by
the nation's leaders as defensive precautions against a possible
Iraqi attack.
   Diplomatic and military analysts say such an attack unlikely
given the size of Turkey's 800,000-strong army, its population of
55 million against Iraq's 17 million, its self-sufficiency in food
and its developed industrial base.
   Also, NATO has assured Turkey it will protect its only Moslem
member in the event of Iraqi aggression.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0015 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 1036EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i BC-SriLanka 3rdLd-Writethru a0661 08-12 0617</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Sri Lanka, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0661,0632</SECOND>
<HEAD>Army Says 116 Moslems Killed In Tamil Assault</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Leads with 15 grafs to UPDATE with Tamil guerrillas denying
they carried out the attacks on Moslems. Pickup 12th, `On Aug...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By PATRICK CRUEZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>COLOMBO, Sri Lanka (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Tamil guerrillas killed at least 116
people in an assault on five Moslem villages in Sri Lanka's
escalating ethnic war, military officials said Sunday.
   A Tamil politician said the attacks were in retaliation for the
killing of 33 Tamil civilians by Moslems using government-supplied
weapons. The Tamil guerrillas claimed the killings were carried out
by pro-government Tamil groups in an attempt to provoke sectarian
clashes between Tamils and Moslems.
   About 50 gunmen threw hand grenades into houses and raked the
Moslem villages with machine-gun fire late Saturday, the officials
said on condition of anonymity. They said 116 bodies were counted
and about 40 people were critically wounded.
   The attacks were on five villages west of Eravur, 125 miles east
of Colombo, the officials said.
   Mohammed Saly, of the Moslem Refugee Relief Organization, said
the assailants ``first hacked to death Moslem priests in a mosque
to prevent them from using the loudspeakers to warn of the attack.''
   They then attacked people in the five villages and shooting
lasted three hours, Saly said.
   Villagers fled into the jungle to escape, he said. Army troops
reached the region on Sunday morning from their camp at Chenkaladi
about three miles away. It was not immediately clear why it took
troops so long to reach the region.
   The largest of the villages attacked was called Saddam Hussein,
after the Iraqi leader who sent building assistance several years
ago, Saly said.
   The Tamil politician, Mahalingam Sivajilingam, said the killings
Saturday were related to fatal attacks on Tamils earlier in the day.
   ``Armed Moslems raided a Tamil refugee camp on Saturday and
abducted and killed 25 Tamil civilians, including seven women,''
said Sivajilingam. Another eight Tamil patients were killed in a
hospital, he said.
   ``This led to the Tamil Tigers attacking the villages ... and
killing innocent Moslems,'' he said. ``The two communities are on
an annihilation spree. Nobody knows how many more will die before
it all ends,'' said Savajilingam, a leader of the Tamil Eelam
Liberation Organization, a former guerrilla group which gave up
arms for politics.
   Lawrence Thilakar, a Tiger leader, said in a telephone call to
the Colombo office of The Associated Press that the attacks on
Moslems were carried out by pro-government Tamil groups to cause
sectarian clashes.
   ``Why should we attack Moslems?'' he asked.
   ``We need the fullest cooperation of the Moslem people, who are
also supressed at the hands of the government. This dangerous game
being played by the government will not last long. Very soon, the
truth will come out.''
   Thilakar spoke from London, where the Tigers maintain a
propaganda office.
   On Aug. 3 Tamil rebels raided another eastern village and gunned
down 140 Moslems inside two Mosques, the military said. The Tamil
Tigers later denied responsibility, but the incident set off
vengeance killings on both sides.
   Tamil insurgents seeking independence from the
Sinhalese-dominated government in Colombo broke a 13-month
cease-fire on June 11. Though Moslems are not directly involved in
the conflict, Tamils suspect them of acting as informers for the
military.
   Before Saturday's incidents, 193 Moslems and about 60 Tamil
civilians had died in the latest round of fighting, according to
the military. Nearly 60 Sinhalese civilians have also died in
attacks attributed to the Tigers.
   Since the fighting resumed, government troops have consolidated
their hold on east coast villages, forcing the Tigers into the
jungle. The Tigers remain in control of the northern Jaffna
Peninsula.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0016 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 1041EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i BC-Britain-Iraq 3rdLd-Writethru   08-12 0593</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Britain-Iraq, 3rd Ld-Writethru,a0666,0611</SECOND>
<HEAD>British Citizen Reportedly Shot Near Saudi Border</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Leads with 4 grafs to UPDATE with Foreign Office saying man
is believed to have been killed. Pickup 4th, `As a...'</NOTE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A British citizen reportedly was shot in Kuwait
near the border with Saudi Arabia, the Foreign Office said Sunday.
   It is believed the man was killed, ``but we do not have
confirmation,'' said Foreign Office Minister William Waldegrave.
   ``If it's true, it's a horrific and tragic incident,'' said
Waldegrave. He said Britain would not be deflected by threats
against its citizens.
   The man was shot Saturday evening, according to reports that
Waldegrave said came from others who crossed the border.
   As a signatory of the Geneva Convention, Iraq ``has a duty to
let people go,'' Waldegrave said in an interview with BBC radio.
   ``Whether you call them hostages, whether you call them
prisoners, whether you call them people who are simply not allowed
their natural rights of free movement, we are _ with our colleagues
in the European Community, and others such as the Russians _
bringing the maximum pressure to get out innocent people who are
non-combatants,'' Waldegrave said.
   A Foreign Office spokesman said the report indicated that a
British subject was shot ``some kilometers on the Kuwaiti side''
over the border.
   ``We have personal details and have notified next of kin. But we
do not yet have a full account of the incident. We do not have
confirmation of whether he is alive or dead,'' said the spokesman,
speaking on condition of anonymity.
   ``We have demanded confirmation and clarification from the Iraqi
authorities and made it clear that if the report is accurate, and
if Iraqi troops were responsible, this is a barbaric incident,
which will deeply shock the world community,'' the spokesman said.
   Roger Tomkys, a senior Foreign Office official, telephoned the
Iraqi ambassador in London Saturday night to lodge a protest, the
spokesman said.
   A number of British citizens crossed the Kuwait-Saudi border on
Friday night. Some said the journey was surprisingly easy, but
others reported moments of fright.
   Adrian King, who was among those returning to Britain on Sunday,
said he had heard a burst of machine-gun fire.
   ``As we got to the border the Iraqis stopped one car that wasn't
with our convoy, there was a short burst of machine-gun fire
obviously to warn them to stop, but we decided to make a quick dash
for it,'' said King, who crossed with his pregnant wife and
two-year-old son.
   King said the convoy he was in encountered many Iraqi troops.
   ``We were absolutely sure we would be picked up. In fact on one
occasion we were going so fast that I believe we caused one tank to
go into another tank,'' he said.
   Others who crossed the border Friday night said they had
encountered little interference from Iraqi troops.
   ``They were not bothering too much with Europeans,'' said Graham
Robb of Aberdeen, Scotland, who arrived at Heathrow airport.
   Robb, who was among 14 people who crossed the border, said: ``We
were stopped a couple of times, slowed down in our cars, but once
they saw the white faces they gave us a smile and waved us on.''
   Duncan Jones, a banker who returned to Gatwick airport Sunday
morning, said the border crossing was ``surprisingly easy.''
   ``I could not believe that we were allowed to drive past as many
tanks and armored vehicles as we did,'' Jones said.
   Ramona Magee of San Diego said she crossed the border with a
British friend
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0017 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 1051EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i BC-Iraq-Kuwait 4thLd-Writethru a0667 08-12 0838</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Iraq-Kuwait, 4th Ld-Writethru, a0667,0862</SECOND>
<HEAD>Briton Reported Shot in Kuwait; Turkey Requests War Powers</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Subs 8-10 pvs, `Britain's Foreign...of anonymity.' to UPDATE
with Foreign Office saying Briton may have been killed. Pickup
11th, `After its...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Britain said Sunday that one of its citizens was reportedly shot
in Kuwait near the border with Saudi Arabia, heightening concern
for the safety of thousands of foreigners who have been trapped
inside Iraq and Kuwait.
   For the second time in two days, Iraqi President Saddam Hussein
urged his people to prepare for hardships that may result from
international economic sanctions designed to punish his country for
invading Kuwait on Aug. 2.
   The Iraqi News Agency said a group of pilots has offered to fly
suicide missions against U.S. ships sent to the Persian Gulf as
part of a multinational being deployed to defend Saudi Arabia
against a possible Iraqi attack.
   In another development Sunday, Turkey's premier said he will ask
Parliament for the power to declare a state of war and send armed
forces into combat in the event of an escalation of the Persian
Gulf crisis.
   Premier Yildirim Akbulut made the announcement before the start
of an extraordinary session of Turkey's Parliament to discuss the
crisis.
   In addition to massing troops on the Saudi border, Iraq
reportedly sent soldiers to Turkey's border after it imposed
economic sanctions on Iraq and effectively shut down pipelines that
carry Iraqi oil through Turkish territory.
   Kuwaiti radio, in a transmission believed to originate in Saudi
Arabia, said an envoy from President Bush delivered a message to
Kuwait's ousted leaders in Saudi Arabia Sunday. The contents of the
message were not divulged.
   Britain's Foreign Office said it believed the British man was
killed in the reported attack Saturday evening, ``but we do not
have confirmation.''
   ``If it's true, it's a horrific and tragic incident,'' Foreign
Office Minister William Waldegrave told BBC radio. Waldegrave said
the report came from unidentified people who had crossed the border
recently.
   A Foreign Office spokesman said the report indicated that the
British subject was shot ``some kilometers on the Kuwaiti side''
over the border.
   ``We have personal details and have notified next of kin. But we
do not yet have a full account of the incident,'' said the
spokesman.
   After its invasion of Kuwait, Iraq sealed its borders and those
of Kuwait, trapping about 3,500 Americans and other foreigners.
U.S. officials have expressed concern for their safety but have
refused to call them hostages, saying negotiations with Iraq about
their return are still under way.
   On Saturday, a 10-year-old California girl was one of 11
Americans who fled to safety in Jordan from Iraq.
   In a statement read on Baghdad radio and television on Sunday,
Saddam urged women to organize their households and economize to
help achieve victory.
   ``Liberation of Jerusalem, Mecca and Medina, this is your
role,'' the Iraqi leader said in the message. Saddam on Friday
declared a jihad, or holy war, on Saudi Arabia and Western nations
moving forces to the Persian Gulf.
   The three cities are considered holiest to Moslems.
   In the statement, read by a government spokesman and monitored
in Nicosia, Saddam said supplies were adequate to withstand the
U.N.-imposed embargo.
   ``Train yourself and the family to take a serious posture in
life where food and clothing will be much less, using only what is
required for honorable living. The nation and future are threatened
by the foreigner,'' he said.
   Saddam said Iraqis should be able to cut consumption of meat,
food and clothing by half.
   ``Any lack of foodstuffs should not be a priority in our
minds,'' Saddam said in the statement. ``Iraqis should concentrate
on war, if it occurs.''
   And Saddam warned against hoarding goods.
   ``We don't have to overload our tables. Let's be frugal,
ascetic. We should not store any foodstuffs,'' he said in the
statement. ``Don't take anything except what is needed for a day or
week. Storage means shortage, a false one, not because supplies
aren't there but because it has been stored.''
   On Saturday, Iraq's Revolutionary Command Council warned that
people selling food on the black market would be executed.
   The Iraqi News Agency said Arab pilots called ``The Group of
Martry Joul Gamal'' said they were ready to carry out suicide
attacks on U.S. ships dispatched to the gulf by foreign nations to
enforce economic sanctions.
   In a telegram sent to Saddam, the group announced its
``determination to be martyrs in protection of Iraq and sanctities
of the Arab and Islamic nation,'' the news agency reported.
   The United States, France and Britain have sent ships to the
gulf region in an effort to force Iraq out of Kuwait. The U.S. has
also committed an estimated 50,000 troops to the operation.
   Egypt and Morocco have also sent troops to Saudi Arabia to face
Iraqi forces massed along that country's border with oil-rich
Kuwait.
   However, in many Arab nations, most notably Jordan, there have
been anti-U.S. protests and an outpouring of popular support for
Saddam.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0018 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 1213EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-SriLanka Bjt   08-12 0692</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Sri Lanka, Bjt,0717</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tamils Blamed For Slaying At Least 119 Moslem Villagers</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DEXTER CRUEZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ERAVUR, Sri Lanka (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Tamil gunmen rampaged through five
fishing villages, butchering Moslems in the street with machine-gun
fire and machetes, military officials said Sunday. They said at
least 119 people were slain.
   The killings were the latest in a round of intensifying ethnic
violence that pits Tamil separatists against the
Sinhalese-dominated government and Sinhalese and Moslem civilians.
   Although Moslems claim neutrality in the war, the government
says Tamils suspect them of siding with the army.
   A Tamil politician said Saturday night's attacks were in
retaliation for the killing of 33 Tamil villagers by Moslems
earlier Saturday. But a spokesman for the Tamil Tigers guerrilla
group denied responsibility for the killings.
   At least 450 villagers have been killed on the once-tranquil
island nation's east coast in a wave of reprisal violence in the
past nine days.
   The victims include 305 Moslems, 85 Tamils and 60 Sinhalese,
according to military officials and politicians.
   In Eravur, one of the villages hit in Saturday night's attack,
puddles of blood were on the sidewalk. Women implored visitors to
help keep them safe, and young men surrounded army officers
demanding weapons.
   ``They have killed everybody,'' one weeping woman told a
delegation of Moslem politicians and soldiers. ``There is no one to
look after us. Please don't leave.''
   Led by Moslem religious leaders, villagers gathered up corpses
in trucks for a mass burial. Residents and military officials on
Sunday said at least 119 people were killed in the five villages
and an additional 40 were injured.
   Brigadier Upali Seneviratne, the top army officer in the
province, said at least 40 Tamil gunmen attacked the villages.
   ``They broke into three groups and shot at everybody in sight,''
he said. The dead included 29 women and 31 children, one of them a
9-day-old girl, he said.
   Residents said the attackers broke down doors and dragged
villagers into the streets.
   After a 90-minute raid on Eravur, the gunmen moved to adjacent
villages, military officials said. One of the villages is called
Saddam Hussein, named after the Iraqi leader who sent construction
aid several years ago.
   The villages are clustered north of Batticaloa on the east
coast, about 125 miles east of Colombo.
   On Aug. 3, gunmen raided another eastern village and massacred
140 Moslems in two mosques. The incident set off a chain of
killings.
   ``The two communities are on an annihilation spree. Nobody knows
how many more will die before it all ends,'' said Mahalingam
Savajilingam, a leader of the Tamil Eelam Liberation Organization,
a former guerrilla group which gave up arms for politics.
   He said Saturday night's killings were carried out by the Tigers
after 33 Tamils at a refugee camp, including eight patients in a
hospital, were killed by Moslems using government-supplied weapons.
   ``This led to the Tamil Tigers attacking the villages...and
killing innocent Moslems,'' he said.
   The Tamil Tigers, the militia fighting for an independent Tamil
homeland in the north and east, deny the charges and say the
killings are being carried out by government agents to discredit
their organization.
   ``Why should we attack Moslems?'' said Lawrence Thilakar, a
Tiger leader, in a telephone call Sunday to The Associated Press in
Colombo. ``We need the fullest cooperation of the Moslem people,
who are also supressed at the hands of the government.''
   Thilakar spoke from London, where the Tigers maintain an office.
   ``This dangerous game being played by the government will not
last long,'' he said. ``Very soon, the truth will come out.''
   Tamil separatists, seeking an independent nation, resumed a
7-year-old war with the Sinhalese-dominated government on June 11
after a 13-month cease-fire.
   At least 3,200 combatants have been killed in the latest phase
of fighting. Hundreds of civilians have also been killed, but there
is no precise figure.
   Tamils, mainly Hindu, make up 18 percent of Sri Lanka's 16
million people. Sinhalese, overwhelmingly Buddhist, comprise 75
percent and Moslems 7 percent.
   An estimated 14,000 people have been killed since 1983 when
Tamil rebels took up arms, claiming they were discriminated against
by the majority Sinhalese.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0019 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 1214EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Pakistan     08-12 0452</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Pakistan,0468</SECOND>
<HEAD>Police Arrest Five Bhutto Associates</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ZAHID HUSSAIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>KARACHI, Pakistan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Police arrested five associates of
ousted Prime Minister Benazir Bhutto, the first cases in what is
expected to be a sweeping investigation of high-level corruption in
her government, police said Sunday.
   Arrest orders also were issued for a sixth person, believed to
be in hiding, police said.
   Earlier, Ms. Bhutto's mother left for London, authorities said.
   Nusrat Bhutto, 65, served as senior minister without portfolio
in her daughter's Cabinet, a position that left her in charge of
Pakistan when the prime minister was out of the country. She was
also served as co-chairman of the Pakistan People's Party.
   Mrs. Bhutto boarded a Pakistan International Airlines flight for
London shortly before dawn but a bomb hoax delayed the departure
for nearly six hours, said an airline official, speaking on
condition of anonymity.
   A family spokesman would not disclose the purpose of the trip,
but party members said Mrs. Bhutto left for London for medical
treatment. They gave no further details.
   President Ghulam Ishaq Khan dismissed Ms. Bhutto's government on
Aug. 6 on charges of political incompetence, mismanagement and
corruption. Ms. Bhutto accused political opponents and the new
caretaker government of planning a ``witch hunt'' against her
family, former government and party stalwarts.
   The military-backed caretaker government headed by former
opposition leader Ghulam Mustafa Jatoi, denied the charges.
   ``No political arrests have been made and we do not intend to
make any political arrests,'' Jatoi's press secretary Hussein
Haqqani said.
   Late Saturday, police in the southern port city of Karachi,
where Ms. Bhutto lives, arrested the five party workers.
   Officials said they are believed to be close associates of Asif
Ali Zardari, who wed Ms. Bhutto in 1987 in a marriage arranged by
her mother.
   During most of her 20 months in office, Ms. Bhutto fended off
accusations that her husband was using his position for profit.
Local newspapers dubbed him ``Mr. 10 Percent,'' a reference to
accusations that he demanded commissions in return for lucrative
contracts.
   Ms. Bhutto and Zardari have repeatedly denied the charges, and
none has been proved.
   The arrested were: Ahmed Fahim Mogul, private secretary to Ms.
Bhutto, Agha Sikunder, regional director of the Pakistan Narcotics
Control Board, businessmen Fauzi Ali Kazmi and Dr. Zulfi Mirza.
They were all arrested on corruption charges, police said.
   Khalid Mustafar Korai, special assistant to the former chief
minister of Sindh Province, was arrested on gunrunning charges,
police said.
   Haqqani said the new 12-member Cabinet is expected to soon
establish tribunals to investigate corruption charges.
   Ms. Bhutto has said she will not appear before any tribunals
appointed by her successors, but would appear before civilian
courts.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0020 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 1215EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SouthAfrica     08-12 0289</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-South Africa,0298</SECOND>
<HEAD>Nine Blacks Killed in Shooting</HEAD>
<HEAD>By SAHM VENTER</HEAD>
<HEAD>Associated Press Writer</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JOHANNESBURG, South Africa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Six men and three women were
killed in gunfire in a hostel south of Johannesburg in what
appeared to be a fight among black factions, police said Sunday.
   Police Capt. Eugene Opperman told the independent South African
Press Association that attackers fired through the windows of two
rooms in a black workers' hostel in Sebokeng Saturday night.
   Four men and three women were killed. Two other men died later
in a hospital. Fifteen people were injured in the shooting.
   Police discovered several Soviet-designed AK-47 assault rifles
and bullet cartriges at the scene.
   Opperman told independent Radio 702 that the motive for the
attack was unknown. ``We can only presume that it is differences
among different black groups,'' he said.
   But he disputed a claim by a township resident that the violence
was between supporters of the African National Congress and the
conservative Zulu-based Inkatha party.
   The shooting follows violence in townships around Johannesburg
between ANC supporters and other residents.
   At least 22 people were killed on July 22 in Sebokeng after
armed Inkatha supporters clashed with township residents who had
been warned by ANC leaders that Inkatha backers were planning to
attack them.
   Earlier this month in Kagiso, east of Johannesburg, at least 12
people were killed in two days of violence between Inkatha backers
and other residents.
   More than 5,000 blacks have died since 1986 in fighting between
Inkatha and ANC supporters in the eastern province of Natal.
   Fears that the conflict may be spreading to other parts of the
country were sparked in recent weeks by the fighting between
Inkatha and opposing groups in areas around Johannesburg.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0021 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 1215EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF-Swiss-Film     08-12 0173</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF-Swiss-Film,0179</SECOND>
<HEAD>Soviet Movie Wins First Prize at Locarno Film Festival</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOCARNO, Switzerland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Soviet film ``Waltz of Chance''
was awarded the Golden Leopard award at the Locarno Film Festival
Saturday night.
   A British film ``The Reflecting Skin'' and the American film
``Metropolitan'' won second prizes.
   ``Waltz of Chance'' was directed by Svetlana Proskourina and
featured unconventional scenes from the everyday life of a woman
who lost faith in the future.
   The jury's decision drew mixed reactions when it was announced
at Locarno's Piazza Grande.
   British director Philip Ridley, 30, was cited for ``The
Reflecting Skin,'' which depicted the nightmares of a child. Whit
Stillmann of the United States, won a Silver Leopard for
``Metropolitan,'' which featured a dialogue among youthful snobs.
   Winners of Bronze Leopards included Miklos Gurban, cameraman of
a Hungarian entry, ``Scruple,'' and Emer McCourt, leading actress
in ``Hush-A-Bye Baby'' produced in Northern Ireland.
   The festival, which drew a record audience of more than 100,000,
was to end Sunday night with the gala screening of Proskourina's
film.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0022 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 1219EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--Malaysia-Car     08-12 0153</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Malaysia-Car,0157</SECOND>
<HEAD>Updated Model of Malaysian Car Launched</HEAD>
<DATELINE>KUALA LUMPUR, Malaysia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Prime Minister Mahathir Mohamad on
Sunday launched a more powerful version of Malaysia's Proton Saga
passenger car.
   The new Proton Saga Megavalve comes with either a 1,300cc or
1,500cc engine. The new engines are 11 percent to 15 percent more
powerful than the earlier models introduced three years ago, said
Mohamed Nadzmi Mohamed Salleh, executive director of Edaran
Otomobil Nasional.
   The Proton Saga is made in Malaysia in collaboration with
Mitsubishi Motor Corp. of Japan. The engine, transmission and some
other parts come from Japan, while the tires, batteries, wiring,
seats and most other parts are made in Malaysia.
   Prices for the car range from about $10,000 for the 1,300cc
model to about $13,000 for the 1,500cc Aeroback.
   ``Taking into account ... the additional features, the new
Proton Saga is still the cheapest buy on the market,'' Nadzmi said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0023 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 1222EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w BC-Baker-Iraq 1stLd-Writethru a0674-a0677-a0681 08-12 0377</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Baker-Iraq, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0674-a0677-a0681,370</SECOND>
<HEAD>US to Intercept Iraqi Oil Shipments, Baker Says</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: Combines pvs; adds byline.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By LAWRENCE L. KNUTSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Secretary of State James A. Baker III said
Sunday that the United States would intercept Iraqi oil shipments
after the exiled Kuwaiti government asked world governments to
enforce United Nations sanctions against Iraq.
   Baker declined to be specific about what the United States might
do and said the plans would be developed over ``the next couple of
days.'' He was careful about the language he used to describe any
possible action.
   ``Let's not use the word blockade '' Baker said. ``Let's just
say we have the legal basis for interdicting these things.''
   In diplomatic parlance, a blockade is an act of war.
   ``I'll give you a word right now. Interdiction. I would suspect
it would begin almost instantly ... now that Kuwait has made the
request.''
   Baker said the government of Kuwait that fled when Iraq invaded
Aug. 2 had ``just requested of us and other nations support for
enforcement of United Nations sanctions ... ''
   ``We now have the legal basis to enforce the sanctions,'' which
call for an embargo on Iraqi exports and imports, Baker said. The
United Nations Security Council approved a worldwide trade embargo
on Iraq and Kuwait on Aug. 6.
   ``We're going to take measures that are necessary and
proportional to enforce the United Nations standards now that we
have a request,'' Baker said.
   Baker had been asked what the United States intends to do about
an Iraqi tanker now off the coast of Saudi Arabia if it moves to
claim Iraqi oil shipped by pipeline across Saudi Arabia.
   He did not comment on the ship specifically, but said that the
United States planned to enforce the United Nations sanctions.
   A State Department spokesman said that U.S. officials gave no
details about the Iraqi vessel.
   ``This was a very specific incident he (Baker) was raising to
illustrate that we do have support from Kuwait and other countries
to carry out the sanctions,'' said the spokesman, who asked not to
be further identified.
   ``We don't know the name of the ship.''
   Baker commented on the ABC television program ``This Week With
David Brinkley.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0024 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 1226EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Kuwait-Diary Bjt   08-12 0883</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Kuwait-Diary, Bjt,0912</SECOND>
<HEAD>`Notes of the Nightmare:' Woman Recounts Ordeal in Kuwait</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   The writer, a 27-year-old bank employee in
Kuwait, kept notes of her experiences after the Iraqi invasion Aug.
2. The Saudi Arabian woman and her family escaped from Kuwait, and
she made her diary available to The Associated Press.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By MAE HAJJAJ</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MANAMA, Bahrain (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   We witnessed the unthinkable: the
invasion and conquest of Kuwait by fellow Arab troops of Iraq's
President Saddam Hussein.
   We first encountered their ugly tanks on the streets of Kuwait
City. Eight days later, we managed to escape to Bahrain.
   Here are my notes of the nightmare:
   Thursday, Aug. 2: As I approached the Gulf Bank, I saw many cars
outside and people were inside to draw cash. Indians, Kuwaitis,
Pakistanis, Eygptians, Palestinians, Americans, and others were
outside the building. Some were yelling ``Go home, go home ... Iraq
has invaded Kuwait.''
   I drove home. Troops were streaming in and heavy vehicles
rumbling down Istiklal (independence) boulevard. Friends called and
told my family to get ready for war. How the hell do you get ready
for war? Fill the bathtubs with water, buy as much canned food as
possible. Buy water, call your kin and see if they have any plans
to escape. Then, wait.
   We turned on the radio and took it along with mattresses down to
the basement.
   Friday, Aug. 3: Whatever little sleep we could have we had. It
was at that point that we heard bombs. Friends invited us to spend
the night at their house. We went. The streets were empty, silent.
   There were about five radio sets tuned to the BBC, another on
Voice of America, Saudi Arabia, Dubai, and Iraq (radio). It was
horrible to hear what they (Iraqi radio) said, especially, since we
knew that they were all lies ... that the Iraqis were in Kuwait to
save its people ...
   Saturday, Aug. 4: We woke up to the sound of bombs. They were
coming from an area called Kifan, where young Kuwaitis had obtained
rifles and were harassing the Iraqis. We were proud of them.
   Friends called and said the Iraqis were looting shops and houses
of rich people who were abroad. They said the Central Bank was
looted too, along with car showrooms.
   We heard distant shelling and were told the Iraqis were trying
to silence Kuwaiti guns at Shuwaikh.
   Sunday, Aug. 5: The Iraqis installed a new government, a joke of
a government, a group of young Iraqis who tried over television to
tell us they were Kuwaiti. Their accent betrayed their real
nationality, despite their white robes and ghutra headgear.
   Wednesday, Aug. 8: We listened to the radio newscast. A friend
called to see if we wanted to leave Kuwait. We refused.
   It was also the same evening that (President) Bush talked. I
cried when Mr. Bush said he wanted the American people to pray for
the men and women who will be fighting for the principles of
freedom and democracy.
   I am Arab, and I felt bad thay we had to ask for foreign help to
defend ourselves against an invasion by fellow Arabs. It was sad,
but I understood it was necessary.
   An American friend of my father's had a heart attack. My sister
and I went to him at hospital immediately. His condition improved
but was anxious to be with the rest of his family.
   Thursday, Aug. 9: I went to hospital to visit the American and
his wife and give them a radio set to listen to newscasts. When I
returned home, a friend of ours, called Nasser, was there to offer
us an escape plan, which we accepted.
   It pained our hearts to leave Kuwait. I am Saudi Arabian, but I
have lived all my years here in this country. Friends told my
father the Iraqis had rounded up foreigners, mainly American and
British, and taken them to Baghdad as hostages.
   Shortly after 11 in the morning Nasser came and picked us up. We
took what we can, some of our gold and important papers and left.
My heart was tearing up as we drove down Fahaheel road, where two
other families in their cars joined us.
   We were stopped at an Iraqi checkpoint. Nasser argued with one
of the soldiers who let us through.
   We saw Iraqi soldiers near the border. Nasser stopped then
turned right to the desert. The soldiers waved to us to get back.
We ignored them. My heart was beating so fast I could not hear
anything. We began to pray. We knew the Iraqis shoot first at the
tires, then come and smash the cars and take occupants out. There
were many destroyed cars along the border. We didn't what Iraqis
did with the occupants. No shots were fired at us, but we couldn't
get over fear.
   Nasser told us to start singing, to overcome fear. The three
cars were running very fast. It took 15 minutes through the desert
to reach the Saudi border, which we crossed into the Khafji region.
   We drove on to Nasser's house there. My father, uncle and aunt
were there. We resumed driving, this time in safer areas. We
crossed the 15-mile causeway on the (Persian) Gulf and entered
Bahrain.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0025 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 1230EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-UN-Children'sSummit     08-12 0564</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-UN-Children's Summit,0583</SECOND>
<HEAD>World Leaders Turn Attention to Children</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DONNA BRYSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>UNITED NATIONS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The world's most powerful people will give
their attention to the weakest at the World Summit for Children
next month.
   Heads of state of 60 countries have agreed to meet at U.N.
headquarters Sept. 29-30 to discuss ways of improving the lot of
millions of children whose lives are threatened by poverty, disease
or malnutrition.
   Officials of UNICEF, the United Nations Children's Fund, is
organizing the summit. James P. Grant, executive director of
UNICEF, said he hoped it would produce global acceptance of the
idea that children have a ``first call'' on society's resources.
   He urged the national leaders to establish such goals for the
1990s as immunizing 80 percent of all children; reducing the number
of children who die before age five by one-third, to 70 deaths per
1,000 live births, and providing safe drinking water for every
child.
   The leaders also will be asked to commit themselves to
eradicating polio and reducing measles by 90 percent over the
decade.
   An international convention on children's rights has been
ratified and will become effective Sept. 3. UNICEF said Bangladesh,
Benin and Sudan ratified it Aug. 3, bringing the total to 22, two
more than required.
   It sets minimum standards for children's health, education and
protection from exploitation.
   In addition to addressing the direct needs of children, Grant
sees the summit as a forum for discussing broader problems that
effect them, such as debt relief. He described efforts by
developing countries to pay their foreign debts as ``an economic
hemorrhaging.''
   ``In sub-Saharan Africa, for example, the economies are in such
bad shape ... in part because of the debt crisis ... that there are
inadequate funds for the social sector,'' he said in an interview
at UNICEF headquarters in New York.
   The summit was proposed in the 1988 UNICEF report on ``The State
of the World's Children.'' Canada, Egypt, Mali, Mexico, Pakistan
and Sweden followed up in February with a formal call for the
meeting.
   President Bush is among the national leaders who plans to
attend. He will deliver the American president's annual annual
address to the U.N. General Assembly the day after the summit.
   ``Children are relatively low on the priority list of most
countries,'' Grant said.
   UNICEF estimates 8,000 children die every day from measles,
whooping cough, tetanus and other diseases vaccination can prevent,
and another 7,000 perish from being dehydrated by diarrhea.
   As many as 4,000 die each day because their mothers do not know
how to breast feed them properly, the agency says. Most of these
deaths occur in undeveloped countries.
   One goal of the summit, Grant said, is to get commitments from
governments to educate parents about the importance of
vaccinations, breast feeding and preventing.
   ``In the 1980s, many countries have demonstrated that it is
possible to achieve many improvements in the health of children''
by marshaling government and the media to educate parents, Grant
said.
   He said 10,000 children were saved every day because of such
campaigns in the last decade, and another 20,000 can be saved each
day in the 1990s if the world makes the commitment.
   The cost of preventing most child deaths would reach $2.5
billion a year by the end of the decade, UNICEF says, or 1 percent
of the amount now spent on arms.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0026 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 1235EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-AIDS-Prostitutes     08-12 0235</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-AIDS-Prostitutes,0242</SECOND>
<HEAD>Some AIDS-Infected Prostitutes Paid Not to Have Sex</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PERTH, Australia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The state Health Department said Sunday
it is paying several AIDS-infected prostitutes not to have sex.
   Dr. Charles Watson, director of Western Australia state's
Disease Control division, said taxpayers were subsidizing ``less
than five'' HIV-positive prostitutes by up to $80 a week as an
incentive to keep them out of brothels and off the streets.
   Watson denied newspaper reports that the payments were as high
as $240 a week.
   He said the payments continued for up to four weeks, until the
male and female prostitutes were retrained for alternative work.
   He said the prostitutes could earn $400 to $800 a week on the
streets.
   ``The money is clearly not a benefit arrangement. It is to
handle emrgency situations or set up possibilities for retraining
into another job,'' Watson said.
   He said the money was paid by the Support, Information,
Educational and Referral Association from AIDS Council funding,
which comes mainly from the Health Department.
   Acquired immune deficiency syndrome is a disease caused by the
human immunodeficiency virus, or HIV. The disease attacks the
body's immune system, leaving victims susceptible to a wide variety
of infections and cancers.
   The virus is most often transmitted through sexual contact.
Other means of transmission include transfusions of tainted blood
or blood products, and the sharing of contaminated hypodermic
needles or syringes by drug abusers.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0027 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 1258EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ElvisAnniversary     08-12 0401</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Elvis Anniversary,0414</SECOND>
<HEAD>Presley Fans Brace for Imitators, Singing Relatives</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By WOODY BAIRD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MEMPHIS, Tenn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Elvis Presley faithful are gathering
again for their annual pilgrimage on the anniversary of his death.
   A week-long lineup of 13th anniversary events includes dances
and musical shows, a Presley impersonator contest and a candlelight
procession past his grave. A 4-year-old Presley imitator is to
perform at an ``Elvis Nostalgia Concert,'' and a four-member band
billed as Elvis cousins planned a show called ``Kin to the King.''
   Presley fell dead on a bathroom floor at his Graceland mansion
Aug. 16, 1977.
   For several years afterward, the anniversary gatherings were
informal, but that began to change when the ground floor of
Graceland opened for public tours in 1982. Now, the anniversary is
the focal point of ``Elvis International Tribute Week.''
   Graceland, the white-columned Georgian residence Presley bought
in 1957, is expected to draw more than 30,000 visitors over the
anniversary week. It attracts more than 600,000 visitors a year and
supports a tourist complex that includes museums and souvenir shops.
   Graceland crowds often include fans with jet-black pompadours,
long sideburns and bespangled bell-bottomed trousers. For
anniversary week, the Elvis dress-alikes are especially common.
   The single largest gathering each year is a candlelight
procession to Presley's grave beside Graceland. The procession
begins at 10 p.m. Wednesday. It generally takes participants four
to five hours to file past the grave in single file.
   Presley fans have formed more than 280 clubs around the world,
including ones in Zimbabwe and Moscow, said Patsy Andersen,
Graceland's fan club coordinator. Many of the clubs send members to
Memphis for the anniversary week.
   ``We've got clubs coming from Hungary, from Germany, Brazil,
Japan, England, Denmark and from all over the United States,'' Ms.
Andersen said.
   While most of the Presley fare is promoted by Graceland, one of
the most popular events, the impersonator contest, has grown on its
own at a Memphis nightclub called Bad Bob's Vapors.
   It runs throughout the week with the winner drawing a trip for
two to Cancun, Mexico.
   The 4-year-old contest generally draws performers who base their
acts on Presley's bespangled jumpsuit period, said Jackie Franklin,
the show's manager.
   Though the performers follow each other closely on stage and
often sing the same songs, particularly ``My Way'' and ``American
Trilogy,'' the audience is generally kind.
   ``No one ever complains,'' she said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0028 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 1259EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-LyingJobApplicants     08-12 0645</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lying Job Applicants,0661</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hesitation May Signal Lying By Job Applicants, Study Suggests</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: `MPORT' in 16th graf is cq</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By MALCOLM RITTER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   People take a split second longer to lie than to
tell the truth when asked about themselves, which may help identify
dishonesty by job applicants, suggests a study presented Sunday.
   Questions about illegal drug use and employment history showed
the effect most clearly when study participants answered true-false
questions on a computer.
   If further research bears out its promise, the effect may be
useful in screening applicants for jobs in law enforcement or
private security, or for security clearances, said study co-author
Michael McDaniel.
   While it could not prove deception by itself, it might signal
areas for extra scrutiny in background checks, he said.
   He spoke in an interview before presenting the work at the
annual meeting of the American Psychological Association.
   McDaniel, a psychologist who consults on human resources issues,
said he did the work independently of his employer, Booz-Allen &amp;
Hamilton Inc. of Bethesda, Md. The same is true for study co-author
Howard Timm of the Defense Personnel Security Research and
Education Center in Monterey, Calif., McDaniel said.
   Other psychologists cautioned that the study was limited by
several factors, but said it contributed to an area that needs
further research.
   The experiment involved 198 students in a criminal justice
class, most of whom hoped to work in law enforcement or security
jobs. They completed a 131-item true-false test, which they were
told was being evaluated as a tool for screening applicants for
security-related jobs.
   They were told to answer the questions as if they were taking it
for a job they wanted. Later, they were asked to complete it again,
but this time to answer as honestly as possible. Confidentiality
was assured.
   Whenever a participant answered a question differently the
second time from the first time, he was assumed to have been lying
the first time.
   Overall, for honest answers, participants took an average of
4.03 seconds from the time the question appeared on the screen to
the time they punched a key in response. Dishonest answers required
an additional three-fifths of a second.
   Lying on the 12 drug use questions, such as whether one had
gotten into a significant amount of trouble from cocaine use, took
an average of 1.1 seconds longer than telling the truth. The
difference for the 12 employment questions, such as whether one had
been fired for poor performance, was .94 second.
   Smaller differences were observed for other categories of
questions on such topics as alcohol use, crime, and possessing such
unlikely virtues as never getting angry.
   McDaniel said he has not yet determined how to analyze the
results of such a test in a job-screening situation. Analysis would
have to account for the fact that people have different average
reaction times to questions, and that some questions take longer to
answer than others, he said.
   Terry Mitchell, a psychologist who has done similar work, said
the new paper will ``stimulate attention to an area of research
that's very important.''
   But Mitchell, president of MPORT Management Solutions in San
Diego, Calif., said deception does not always take longer than
honest responses. A person who simply punches in answers wihout
thinking about the questions, or who has been coached on what
answers to give, will take less time, he said.
   He also cautioned that while response delays might suggest
inaccurate answers to particular questions, that is different from
determining whether a person is basically honest.
   Margaret McManus, who develops personnel selection tests at the
Life Insurance Marketing and Research Association in Hartford,
Conn., called the work a ``reasonably well done, interesting
study.''
   But she said it included relatively few participants, and that
they were students rather than real job applicants. More work is
needed on the topic, she said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0029 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 1306EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Iraq-Nimitz     08-12 0658</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Iraq-Nimitz,0679</SECOND>
<HEAD>Officers Say Carriers May Be Key to Defusing Aggression in Mideast</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto LA9</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVID SEDENO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ABOARD USS NIMITZ (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The presence of U.S. aircraft carriers
in the Middle East could help stop Iraqi aggression, but the
massive floating airports could be vulnerable to chemical warfare,
officers aboard the USS Nimitz say.
   The nuclear-powered carrier, performing flight operations off
the California coast, has cruised the Middle East and the Persian
Gulf area before. In 1981, two of its aircraft shot down Libyan
planes over the Gulf of Sidra.
   One sailor said he hoped the ship would go to the Middle East.
   ``I would like to see something done,'' said Chris Szymanski,
20, a Bedford, Mich., native who works in the galley. ``I would
like to see the Nimitz go, but I know that some of the people would
not like to see the Nimitz go because of their girlfriends or their
marriage.''
   But the Nimitz, which left its home port of Bremerton, Wash.,
last week, had no orders to go to the Middle East.
   Officers aboard the Nimitz say their sister carriers could be a
deterrent to Iraqi leader Saddam Hussein and his million-man
military.
   The carrier Dwight D. Eisenhower and its flotilla recently
crossed the Red Sea into the Indian Ocean. The carrier Independence
and its 13 escort and support ships are in the northern Arabian
Sea, and the Saratoga and its 15-ship battle group are en route to
the Mediterranean.
   Over the weekend, the Pentagon declined to comment on a number
of reports that the aircraft carrier USS Kennedy would be sent to
the Mideast from Norfolk, Va., where it is being supplied for a new
duty cruise.
   The carriers can each carry at least 5,000 men and more than 70
aircraft, including A-6E and FA-18 attack bombers and F-14A
Tomcats. They also carry anti-submarine Sea King helicopters and
E-2C Hawkeyes, whose rotating radar domes provide early warning
capabilities. The ships also have their own missile defense systems.
   ``The carrier has a long arm to deliver weapons, to hit targets,
and it can move around,'' said Cmdr. Bruce Ross, an officer in the
Nimitz's Combat Defense Center, the nerve center of a carrier.
   With four catapults, a carrier can launch an aircraft every 30
seconds. Radar jammers would make it difficult for an enemy fleet
to find the carriers.
   ``I don't know how many wars and how many conflicts have been
prevented in the past 20 years by having a carrier battle group
present off the coast or in a position to strike potential
adversaries,'' said Nimitz Capt. Robert C. Williamson, a 27-year
Navy veteran.
   ``In this particular case, I don't think we desire to have a
conflict or any expansion of the warfare that has taken place right
now, but I do know we will defend (Saudi Arabia) militarily,'' he
said.
   Iraq used chemical weapons in its war with Iran, and U.S. ground
troops are equipped for defense against them.
   Nimitz officials say carriers also can be susceptible to
chemical attack.
   ``If you want to neutralize a carrier, the best thing that (an
enemy) can do is to use chemical weapons,'' said Lt. Cmdr. Tom
Tanner, a combat damage control assistant who helps train sailors
on chemical warfare defense.
   The ship frequently has drills during which crew members don
cumbersome masks. The sailors also are equipped with rubber boots
and gloves and charcoal-lined pants and hooded tops.
   ``By just threatening a chemical attack _ and having to get your
guys onto the flight decks with their suits _ they've met their
mission,'' Tanner said. ``It puts you in a position that cuts down
your effectiveness.''
   But the Nimitz's captain minimized the possibility of Iraq
harming a U.S. Navy battle group.
   ``I don't feel very threatened by Iraqis at all when we're
operating in the Arabian Sea,'' Williamson said.
   ``If I were (Saddam), I'd quit right now,'' he added.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0030 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 1313EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i BC-Iraq     08-12 0286</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Iraq,0311</SECOND>
<TEXT>
   
   Food not available, accumulated in huge quantities more than
needed by families.
   Demand on foodstuffs instead of thinking about normal duties
start thinking about accumulating food.
   Easch family in Iraq including poor families can livefor the
time being without buying clothess for one more year. Instead of
consuming 10 kilos, of meeat monthly, can reduce by haldf, applies
t6o bread and clothes.
   Food diversity is a form of
   Great Iraqi woman will prove to Americans they can defend honor,
homeland with least amount of food and clothes. Iraqis we have
lived together with grandparents and have achieved waht have
weanted in lives, have always been modest in eating and living
methods, very uimportant to us, always lived accordingb to our
standards. Second half of 70s discovered new opportunities in Iraq.
Even war with Iran,..
   Now there is an economic blockade.
   GHave rendered the oil blockade afailure in 1973, Experience
   Any lack of foodstufs shud noit be porioiryt in our minds, shud
concentrate on war if it occurs. No Iraqi should accept that
accumulates more than needs, especially if war occurrs. Have high
hoipoes in women. Role and national message are great.
   Have enough stocks of goods and foodstuffs. Defeat wil be on
side of those who impose economic blopckaede and bring in fleet.
Have not forgotten advise of farmers that shud always be prepared.
   
   
   Called for belt-tightening, has adequate food supplies, perhaps
as long as year but advised people not to hoard, cut consumption by
about half.
   Called on women to take the lead in cutting.
   Any lack shud not be priority, war shud be issue.
   Second address to nation. First called on Arabs of world to aise
and defeat
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0031 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 1324EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Soviet-Republics     08-12 0191</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Republics,0196</SECOND>
<HEAD>Karelia Declares Sovereignty from Russia</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The autonomous republic of Karelia on the border
with Finland has declared sovereignty from both the Soviet Union's
largest republic and from the central Soviet government, Tass
reported.
   Karelia, which includes a large amount of one-time Finnish
territory, is one of 20 ``autonomous republics'' located within the
15 Soviet republics. Russia, in which Karelia is located, is the
largest and most populous republic.
   Karelia, home to 700,000 people, declared that its constitution
and laws take precedence over those of Russia and the Soviet Union,
the official Soviet news agency said Saturday. But Karelia softened
the declaration by agreeing to voluntarily cede some of its powers
to both.
   Karelia's declaration also states the right to independently
decide matters of international relations, and to change its legal
status.
   Tass said the declaration specifically emphasizes that it is not
intended to drive a wedge between the governments of Karelia and
Russia, led by reformer Boris N. Yeltsin.
   Eight of the union republics have declared some form of
sovereignty from the Kremlin. Lithuania has taken the strongest
step, declaring its independence on March 11.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0032 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 1327EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People     08-12 0926</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People,0961</SECOND>
<HEAD>People in the News</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY44</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PALMA DE MAJORCA, Balearic Islands (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Britain's Princess
Diana and her two young sons arrived on this Mediterranean island
Sunday to join Prince Charles for a brief vacation as guests of the
Spanish royal family.
   Charles, who has been staying with friends on the Spanish island
since Wednesday, picked up his family at the airport in a van
driven by Princess Elena, the eldest daughter of Spain's King Juan
Carlos and Queen Sofia.
   Also making the trip to meet the flight were Spain's Princess
Cristina and Sofia's brother, the former King Constantine of Greece.
   This is the third time in four years that Charles, Diana and
Princes William and Harry have spent part of their summer holiday
at the Spanish royal summer residence, Marivent Palace.
   In 1988, the Spanish and British press published pictures of a
bikini-clad Diana diving into the Mediterranean off the royal yacht
Fortuna.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A new television series is bringing Burt
Reynolds back to Southern California, with the actor renting a home
in the upscale Bel-Air section for $40,000 a month.
   Reynolds and his wife, actress Loni Anderson, have spent most of
the past year in Florida, where Reynolds has long owned a ranch.
   But the actor, who sold his house in the Holmby Hills section of
Los Angeles last year, has taken a year's lease on new digs in
Bel-Air as he works on his new show, said Bobbi Ward of Asher Dann
and Associates, who represented him in negotiating the lease.
   Reynolds is the star and co-executive producer of ``Evening
Shade,'' which airs this fall. The CBS show brings a former pro
football player back to his hometown to raise a family.
   Ms. Ward said Reynolds leased the home without his wife's
knowledge, but ``when she saw it, she loved it.''
   The 15,000-square-foot furnished house has eight bedrooms and 11
bathrooms and sits on a two-acre compound with a tennis court and
swimming pool.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Developer Donald Trump claims he's making a
killing now that people think he has no money.
   ``It's good for me to be thought of as poor right now,'' he said
in the September issue of Vanity Fair magazine. ``You wouldn't
believe some of the deals I am making. I guess I have a perverse
personality. ... I've really enjoyed the last few weeks.''
   Trump says he's not upset at being dropped from Forbes
magazine's list of the world's richest men and blames it on a
run-in he had with the magazine's late owner, Malcolm Forbes. The
magazine, which last put Trump's net worth at $1.7 billion, lowered
that estimate to $500 million in April.
   ``(I've) been expecting this attack from Forbes,'' he said.
``You know why? Malcolm Forbes got thrown out of the Plaza by me!
... You'll read about it in my new book. And I didn't throw him out
because he didn't pay his bill.''
   Trump also said he is more popular than ever despite the bad
press he's been getting about his marital woes and cash problems.
   And that popularity has rubbed off on the two women most often
linked with him: his estranged wife, Ivana, and his alleged
mistress, Marla Maples.
   ``I've made a lot of satellites ... whether it's Marla or
Ivana,'' Trump said. ``Marla can do any movie she wants to now.
Ivana can do whatever she wants.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>DEKALB, Ill. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Maggie Kuhn, the 85-year-old activist for
the elderly who founded the Gray Panthers, received an honorary
doctorate from Northern Illinois University.
   Kuhn was given a Doctor of Humane Letters degree in recognition
of her work in fighting against age discrimination, the university
said.
   ``When I turned 80, I made a solemn vow to myself that I would
try to do something outrageous at least once a week,'' Kuhn said at
Saturday's ceremony. ``The current and immediate past
administrations have given me endless opportunities to do so.''
   In 1970, Kuhn and five friends formed the Gray Panthers, which
has lobbied against Social Security cuts and fought for rent
control and better health care for senior citizens. The
organization has grown to more than 70,000 members.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Former Mayor Ed Koch will talk about anything.
Except money.
   The former mayor is out on the national talk-circuit, doing
daily radio commentaries, dishing out opinions on weekly television
news-shows and even talking up a diet drink.
   But as far as his earnings, mum's the word.
   ``I never discuss money. It's gauche,'' he said in a recent
interview.
   Koch is expected to earn nearly $2 million this year, including
$1.6 million from speaking fees of $20,000 a speech, the Daily News
said Sunday. That's a far cry from the $130,000 salary he was
making when he left office last year after 12 years on the job.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>NASHVILLE, Tenn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Singer William Lee Golden says he still
knows very little about why he was voted out of the Oak Ridge Boys'
country music group three years ago.
   The other three members of the group ousted him from the quartet
in March 1987, citing friction among band members. He was replaced
by Steve Sanders.
   ``We've still never had a meeting over that dismissal,'' said
Golden. He now works as a solo performer and with his two sons,
Rusty and Chris.
   The Oak Ridge Boys' biggest hit when Golden was with them was
``Elvira.'' The group's ``No Matter How High'' was No. 1 on the
country music charts in February.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0033 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 1420EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-What'llItCost? Bjt   08-12 0704</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-What'll It Cost?, Bjt,740</SECOND>
<HEAD>How Much to Dispatch U.S. Troops? Maybe $440 Million a Month</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: The numbers in this estimate differ from those in the AM-News
Digest, a9990. These estimates are based on deployment of 50,000
troops, which is the figure used by the analysts.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By WILLIAM M. WELCH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Sending U.S. military forces to Saudi Arabia
will cost an estimated $300 million to $440 million a month,
defense analysts say. And like everybody else, the Pentagon will
feel the bite of fuel bills driven up by the crisis in the Middle
East.
   Higher oil bills could add billions of dollars to Pentagon
spending, other analysts say _ affecting not only troops deployed
in the Persian Gulf but U.S. military operations everywhere.
   Figuring the cost of the deploying troops to Saudi Arabia has
been a slippery exercise for analysts inside and outside the
government. Many were reluctant to give even a ballpark figure
because there are so many unknown factors.
   For one, the number of troops being sent is still uncertain _
50,000 or 250,000. And no one knows how long they will stay.
Besides, some costs already are being paid _ salaries, food,
supplies, fuel and maintenance _ and any increases caused by the
deployment are difficult to measure in advance.
   Pentagon spokesman Pete Williams said simply, ``I have no idea
how much it's costing a day.''
   President Bush sidestepped the issue after announcing he had
sent Americans into the Persian Gulf to help defend Saudi Arabia.
``Whatever it is, we're going to have to pay it,'' he said.
   Lawrence Korb, a former assistant secretary of defense who is
now a defense analyst with the Brookings Institute, estimated the
cost at $10 million a day, or $300 million a month.
   His estimate is based on the deployment of 50,000 people and
three carrier task forces. It gives the costs above what the
Pentagon would spend anyway in salaries and other expenses for
peacetime operations.
   The Center for Defense Information, a group of retired military
officials that often has criticized U.S. military spending as
excessive, estimated that deploying 50,000 troops would cost about
$440 million a month above normal military expenses.
   And if the U.S. sends as many as 250,000 troops, the additional
monthly cost could rocket to $1.69 billion, according to the
center's study.
   Another analyst, a House staffer who works on defense issues
also estimated the cost ``in the hundreds of millions.''
   That's just to maintain defensive positions. If shooting starts,
costs will spiral. Ammunition is expensive and damage to ships,
planes, tanks and other equipment _ not to mention people _ is
incalculable.
   Maintenance costs are likely to skyrocket, too. The Saudi desert
sands present ``hideous conditions'' for equipment, said a Senate
budget analyst who spoke on condition of anonymity.
   ``The maintenance costs are going to be enormous,'' the Senate
analyst said.
   But perhaps the biggest potential cost is fuel. Consumers
already are paying more at the gas pump. For the Pentagon, every
penny per gallon increase adds $100 million in defense spending,
Korb said.
   ``Fuel costs could run in the billions,'' said the House
staffer, who spoke on condition of anonymity.
   House and Senate budget analysts say the Pentagon is working on
cost projections for the operation but has not yet sent them to
Congress. Analysts say the initial costs can be handled by
transferring money between accounts, skimping in some places to
cover the operations.
   After that, the Pentagon may have to go back to Congress and ask
for more money.
   All this is comes while the administration is fighting with
congressional budgetmakers to limit what Congress cuts from defense.
   Saudi Arabia said it is prepared to help defray some of the
costs of maintaining a U.S.-dominated multinational force in the
kingdom. Asked if the Saudis would pay for the fuel used by U.S.
naval and air forces, Saudi Ambassador Prince Bandar Bin Sultan
responded: ``I can't imagine us disagreeing with that point.''
   Elaborating on that, a Saudi source, speaking on condition on
anonymity, said the Saudis were willing to pick up other costs but
were concerned that doing so would create the appearance of hiring
mercenaries to protect their borders.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0034 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 1430EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Hostages     08-12 0562</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Hostages,0580</SECOND>
<HEAD>Shiite Leader Demands Release of 15 Convicted Bombers</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Iraq-Kuwait Rdp, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RODEINA KENAAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BEIRUT, Lebanon (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A senior Shiite Moslem leader appealed
Sunday for Iraqi President Saddam Hussein to release 15 Shiite
Moslems imprisoned for the bombings of the U.S. and French
Embassies in Kuwait.
   The release of the imprisoned men has long been a key demand by
Islamic Jihad, or Islamic Holy War, a Shiite group which holds
American journalist Terry A. Anderson and educator Thomas
Sutherland as hostages.
   ``The 15 (jailed Shiites) reportedly have been moved to Baghdad
and they should be freed,'' said Hussein Musawi. He heads a
pro-Syrian wing of the fundamentalist Hezbollah, or Party of God,
Iran's main ally in Lebanon and an umbrella for several
hostage-holding factions.
   ``The demand of the hostage-holders still stands as well as
other demands,'' Musawi said in a telephone interview from his home
in the eastern town of Baalbek.
   ``The United States, Britain and Germany are all aware of the
(kidnappers') demands. There are interests for the Moslems in
Lebanon and elsewhere in the Middle East that these countries
should take into consideration,'' Musawi said. He did not elaborate.
   The hostages held in Lebanon are six Americans, four Britons,
two West Germans, a Swiss, an Irishman and an Italian. Anderson,
chief Middle East correspondent for The Associated Press, has been
held the longest. He was abducted March 16, 1985.
   Asked whether the kidnappers would harm the hostages because of
the U.S. military deployment in Saudi Arabia, Musawi said:
   ``If the Moslems are cornered by a new U.S. aggression, they
will act. I don't want to go into details.''
   Seventeen Shiite Moslems were convicted for the Dec. 1983
embassy bombings in Kuwait that left five people dead and 86
wounded.
   Of the 17 men convicted in the attack, three were given death
sentences, seven were sentenced to life, four were given 15-year
terms, one was sentenced to 10 years and two were released after
serving two years.
   One of those sentenced to death is Mustapha Youssef Badreddin, a
cousin and brother-in-law of Imad Mughniyeh, said to be the leader
of Islamic Jihad. One of the men sentenced to life is Hassan
Youssef Musawi, Hussein Musawi's cousin.
   Hussein Musawi, who branded Iraqi President Saddam Hussein ``a
Satan, not a hero,'' was instrumental in the release of American
hostages Robert Polhill and Frank Reed in April.
   ``If Saddam is truly anti-American, then he should set these 15
men free at once,'' Musawi said.
   There were conflicting reports about the fate of the 15 convicts
in Kuwait after Iraq's invasion of the oil-rich Arab state on Aug.
2.
   One report said Iraqi troops shot and killed them. Another said
they were removed from Kuwait to a Baghdad prison.
   Kuwait had identified the bombers as members of the pro-Iranian
Dawa party, an Iraqi group seeking to overthrow Saddam.
   Musawi condemned the Iraqi invasion of Kuwait and the U.S.
military buildup in the area.
   ``The Moslem youths should not be deceived. They should confront
Saddam's aggression without cooperation with the great Satan
(America), which also should be confronted by suicide attacks,''
Musawi added.
   ``Saddam is a Satan, not a Moslem leader. The one who waged war
against the Islamic republic (Iran) and Syria and who unleashed
chemical weapons against the Kurds is not a hero but a Satan.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0035 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 1434EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>d a AM-BRF--LegislativePay     08-12 0172</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Legislative Pay,0176</SECOND>
<HEAD>High-Paid Executive Chairing California Panel on Legislative Pay</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SACRAMENTO, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Gov. George Deukmejian selected one of
the highest-paid private executives in the state to head a new
commission to decide how much California's lawmakers should earn.
   Claude S. Brinegar, executive vice president of Union Oil Co. of
California, earned more than $1.6 million last year, according to a
report last week in the San Jose Mercury News.
   But Brinegar, who was U.S. secretary of transportation for two
years, said in a recent interview that his current salary will not
affect his decisions on the legislative salary commission.
   He's known ``low salaries'' too, he said: ``When I went to the
U.S. government as secretary of transportation, I took a Cabinet
post at $60,000, and I lived on it.''
   As chairman, Brinegar will preside over a panel appointed to
judge the adequacy of legislators' current salary of $40,816 a
year. The California Citizens Compensation Commission was created
after voters passed an initiative package designed to halt ethics
abuses.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0036 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 1441EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brite-Flutists'Convention     08-12 0254</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brite-Flutists' Convention,0263</SECOND>
<HEAD>Flutists From Afar Flaunt Flutes At Fling</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MINNEAPOLIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   As many as 2,500 members of the National
Flute Association are expected to come to the Twin Cities for the
organization's 18th annual convention this week.
   Irene Pruzan, marketing director of the more than 4,000-member
flute association and herself a flutist, said there are 1 million
flute players in the United States.
   ``I know this sounds self-serving,'' she said, ``but I think of
flutists as the most intelligent and creative of instrumentalists.''
   ``Our association has more members than any other instrumental
organization,'' she added. ``When clarinetists get together,
there's hardly 200 people there.''
   The convention will consist of concerts, competitions, panels,
workshops and exhibits.
   Among the international participants will be Soviet flutist Oleg
Kudriashov of the Kiev Philharmonic and Conservatory, Benoit
Fromanger from Paris and Andras Adorjan from Germany.
   Specialists in the baroque flute will also perform, along with
jazz and ethnic flute players from the United States and Ireland
and musicians from orchestras such as the Los Angeles Philharmonic,
the Chicago Symphony, the Boston Symphony and the Minnesota
Orchestra.
   Professional flutist Steve Kujala's performance Friday at
Central Lutheran Church as part of the convention will include some
improvisation.
   The purpose of the concert is to highlight the link between 18th
century music and jazz.
   ``Keyboard players back then had to fill out the bass with
chords,'' Kujala said. ``Soloists would improvise with cadenzas and
embellishments. There was far more improvisation then than now, at
least in the classical world.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0037 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 1450EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Pilots-Alcohol     08-12 0626</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Pilots-Alcohol,0643</SECOND>
<HEAD>Jury in Pilots' Trial Weighing Smooth Flight Against Blood-Alcohol
Evidence</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TONY KENNEDY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MINNEAPOLIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   If three former Northwest Airlines flight
officers are to be found guilty of flying while intoxicated, jurors
must conclude they were impaired by alcohol despite their
apparently solid performance.
   With the third week of testimony in the federal trial to start
Monday, defense attorneys have demonstrated that Flight 650 on
March 8 from Fargo, N.D., to Minneapolis-St. Paul was smooth
despite freezing drizzle.
   ``Overall, I don't see any area that I can point to and say they
fell short,'' said Robert Collette, an expert defense witness who
reconstructed the flight based on tape-recorded communications
between the crew and air traffic controllers.
   Assistant U.S. Attorney Elizabeth de la Vega has not uncovered
any problems with the flight. But she has hard evidence that
alcohol was lingering in the pilots' bodies from a night of heavy
drinking which ended for the captain within about seven hours of
the flight.
   Capt. Norman Lyle Prouse has admitted drinking more than 15 rum
and colas and a waitress at the Speak Easy restaurant and lounge in
Moorhead has testified that First Officer Robert Kirchner and
Flight Engineer Joseph Balzer shared seven pitchers of beer.
Kirchner and Balzer left the bar about 10:30 p.m., about an hour
before Prouse, she testified.
   In blood-alcohol tests performed two hours after the Boeing 727
safely landed 91 passengers at the Minneapolis-St. Paul
International Airport, Prouse showed a blood-alcohol content of
0.13 percent _ more than legal limit for driving cars in Minnesota
and other states.
   Each pilot is charged with operating an aircraft while under the
influence of alcohol. The case marks the first time that commercial
pilots have been tried under the 1988 federal law provision
prohibiting operation of a common carrier while under the influence
of alcohol.
   However, unlike state drunken driving laws, the federal law does
not specify an illegal blood-alcohol content.
   ``The issue is not what his condition was the night before or
what his alcohol content was the next day,'' Prouse's lawyer, Peter
Wold, told jurors. ``The government must show their abilities were
impaired. Based on all the evidence, we will show you their
abilities were very good.''
   De la Vega's final witness, behavioral scientist Herbert
Moskowitz, said tests have proven that all humans are impaired by
alcohol when their blood-alcohol content hits a mere 0.01 percent _
the equivalent of half a beer. He said ``significant impairment''
of vision, information processing and short-term memory occur in
all people beginning at blood-alcohol levels of 0.02 percent and
0.03 percent.
   ``Any amount of alcohol reduces or decreases your ability to
perform,'' Moskowitz testified. ``There's no way you can look at
somebody and tell that their brain is operating more slowly, but it
is when you have alcohol in your system.''
   Prouse agreed under cross-examination Thursday that it's
dangerous to fly within eight hours of drinking.
   But he said he did not believe he was endangering any lives when
he ignored a caution from an FAA inspector in Fargo not to fly.
   ``I'd think it was dangerous if I was impaired,'' Prouse said.
   Prouse, 51, said he was accustomed to heavy drinking because he
is an alcoholic. Part of his defense is that he has a high
tolerance for alcohol that makes it harder for him to get drunk.
   A bar patron reported the three crew members to the Federal
Aviation Administration.
   They were arrested when the plane landed in the Twin Cities.
Northwest fired them for breaking the company rule of drinking
within 12 hours of flying, and the FAA has revoked their licenses.
   If convicted, the pilots face a maximum 15 years in prison and a
$250,000 fine.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0038 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 1513EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-CrippledNavajo     08-12 0535</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Crippled Navajo,0551</SECOND>
<HEAD>Former Schoolgirl To Get $120,000 For `Bureaucracy At Its Worst'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LARRY LOPEZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PHOENIX (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The federal government has agreed to pay $120,000
to a crippled Navajo woman who experienced what a judge called
``bureaucracy at its worst'' after being barred by a Bureau of
Indian Affairs high school.
   The settlement, approved last week by U.S. District Judge Carl
Muecke, calls for Lorraine Begay to be paid $20,000 immediately and
$100,000 over the next 15 years. In addition, it calls for $100,000
to be paid to her lawyers, who have worked on the case for six
years.
   Ms. Begay, 23, suffers from progressive arthritis and has to use
a wheelchair. She had sued individual employees of the BIA because
she was barred by law from suing the federal government directly.
   The BIA boarding school at Many Farms on the Navajo reservation
never installed a wheelchair ramp or special toilet she would have
needed to attend.
   The modifications would have cost no more than a few thousand
dollars at most, according to court records, and were supposed to
have been made under a federal law mandating access for the
handicapped. School officials give conflicting reasons as to why
the work wasn't done.
   The government paid for private lawyers to represent the BIA
employees but said initially that it would not pay any judgment if
Ms. Begay won in court.
   Because none of the individual BIA employees was rich, that left
Ms. Begay's lawyers looking at the possibility they could win a big
judgment and then be unable to collect it.
   Muecke, in pre-trial hearings, urged both sides to settle and
hinted strongly that the government should pay.
   At one point, addressing a defense claim that only top-level
officials in Washington were at fault and that Ms. Begay should
have sued them, Muecke replied: ``I find that rather astonishing. I
find that bureaucracy at its worst.''
   Ms. Begay's struggle began about 10 years ago, after juvenile
arthritis confined her to a wheelchair. She wanted to attend the
Many Farms boarding school in northeastern Arizona with her
brothers and sisters.
   The BIA offered to send her to special schools for the
handicapped, hundreds of miles away.
   Ms. Begay refused, saying she did not have the kind of mental
handicaps that the other schools were set up to accommodate.
   ``I am a regular child and want to be in school with all my
brothers and sisters,'' she wrote at one point.
   Ms. Begay, who lives with her mother in a house with no
electricity or runnign water, enrolled instead in a day school 10
miles over bumpy roads from her home. She graduated from high
school two years late, largely because of absences attributed to
her illness.
   Ms. Begay's telephone rang unanswered Saturday and Sunday. She
said in a recent letter to one of her lawyers that she was glad not
to have to go to court.
   James Loss, who heads the civil division of the U.S. Attorney's
Office in Phoenix, referred the call to the Justice Department,
saying lawyers there had made the settlement. Frank Kelly, a
Justice Department spokesman, said Sunday that his agency would
have no immediate comment.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0039 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 1531EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Two-CareerFamilies     08-12 0371</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Two-Career Families,0381</SECOND>
<HEAD>Survey: Many Southern California Workers Want to Quit to Be With
Kids</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Seventy-nine percent of mothers and 39
percent of fathers in Orange and Los Angeles counties would quit
their jobs if they could to stay home with their kids, according to
a poll released Sunday.
   The survey, commissioned by the Los Angeles Times, indicates
that Southern California families are adopting a ``new realism''
about the hardships family life faces when both parents are
full-time wage earners, said a social historian.
   ``We've reached a time when we're more realistic of what the
costs are of full-time employment for two-earner families,'' said
Barbara Dafoe Whitehead, who is a consultant to the Chicago-based
Public Policy Association.
   The telephone poll of 1,000 families was conducted by Mark
Baldassare &amp; Associates July 19-23 and has a margin of error of 3
percent to 5 percent, the Times reported.
   Eighty-seven percent of mothers and 80 percent of fathers rated
family and children as very important, yet many said they cannot
find time to have dinner with their families regularly.
   Fifty-seven percent of fathers and 55 percent of mothers also
said they feel guilty about spending too little time with their
children.
   Many parents interviewed by the newspaper reflected those
statistics in more personal ways.
   ``I've cried on my way to work many times,'' said Benay Clark of
Los Angeles. She said her 2{-year-old daughter, Mallory, often
cries, clings to her and asks why she has to have a job.
   ``Every day is a challenge and a balancing act,'' said single
mother Linda Sonnonstine of Irvine. Sonnonstine, 42, changed jobs
in order to spend more time with her teen-age son.
   Fifty-one percent of the men interviewed said they believe their
work interferes with their parental responsibilities either a lot
or some, and 28 percent said they believe their parental
responsibilities are hurting their careers either a lot or some.
   Thirty-nine percent of the women believe their careers are
interfering with rearing their children a lot or some, and 41
percent believe their parenting duties are hurting their careers.
   Sixty-four percent of the fathers and 72 percent of the mothers
confided that they worry about whether they are good parents.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0040 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 1532EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-AmmunitionBeach     08-12 0389</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Ammunition Beach,0399</SECOND>
<HEAD>Beach Closed After Ammunition Found _ Some May Be From Civil War
Era</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HAMPTON, Va. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A one-mile stretch of beach was temporarily
closed after at least 28 shells _ some of which may date back to
the Civil War _ were discovered in sand dredged from the Chesapeake
Bay.
   Police and fire officials closed Buckroe Beach on Saturday after
a man looking for valuables with a hand-held metal detector found
four 11-inch-long shells. At least 28 shells have been found since
Wednesday, when a Norfolk Dredging employee discovered three shells
along the beach.
   ``Some are missing the nose part or the fuse part. All of them
still have the explosive material inside the shell,'' Fire
Battalion Chief Richard C. Blakeslee said Sunday.
   Police officers guarded the beach area and shooed away would-be
explorers until a two-man team from Langley Air Force Base arrived
late Saturday to dispose of the shells.
   On Sunday morning, officials armed with metal detectors
unearthed eight shells during a sweep of the beach, police said.
Officials reopened a major portion of the beach Sunday afternoon.
   Much of the ammunition is World War II vintage, but officials
said some dates back to World War I and some contained traces of a
powder that was used in Civil War artillery.
   Blakeslee said most of the shells were probably dredged up from
an area that was previously used for target practice.
   Tech. Sgt. S.P. Temme of Langley's Explosive Ordnance Disposal
Unit said it was unlikely that the shells would explode, unless
they were dropped on their nose.
   Blakeslee said some of the shells probably could cause extensive
of damage.
   ``These were designed to take aircraft down,'' he said. ``Once
that black powder portion dries, they can be capable of doing their
job for up to 200 years.''
   The shells were dredged along with tons of sand from the
Chesapeake Bay about two miles offshore, and pumped through a
22-inch wide steel pipe onto the beach. Sand is being dredged from
the bay as part of a nearly $1 million beach replenishment project
that began Aug. 3.
   The Air Force base was unable to offer its larger mine detectors
because they were being transferred to the Middle East to help the
U.S. defend Saudi Arabia from a possible attack by Iraq, Temme said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0041 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 1537EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-USForces     08-12 0612</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-US Forces,620</SECOND>
<HEAD>US Commander Says Troops Alert to Terrorists</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-US Iraq Rdp</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN KING</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MACDILL AIR FORCE BASE, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The commander of the U.S.
military effort in Saudi Arabia said Sunday that his troops would
be on guard against terrorists as well as Iraqi guns and gas.
   Describing the massive movement of troops and equipment overseas
as a ``totally awesome'' undertaking that is moving ahead of
schedule, Gen. H. Norman Schwarzkopf also said that the combined
forces in place in the Middle East could withstand an Iraqi attack
if one occurred now.
   ``I would never tell you that the American forces that are there
are 100 percent out of harm's way,'' Schwarzkopf told reporters at
a briefing at United States Central Command headquarters on this
base near Tampa.
   But, he said, ``We have built up a great deal of force over
there now ... and if they do make an attack they are going to pay a
price for it.''
   Although American ground forces are outnumbered at the moment,
U.S. air and naval power could neutralize any Iraqi attack,
Schwarzkopf said. He added in response to a question that Iraqi
leader Saddam Hussein's call for Arab world resistance to the U.S.
presence would force troops to be on the lookout.
   ``There are several terrorist organizations that have found
haven in Iraq and I have every expectation that they're going to be
asked to do something,'' he said. ``We're paying attention.''
   In October 1983, more than 200 Marines and sailors who were part
of an international peacekeeping force were killed by a terrorist
truck bomb in Beirut. U.S. service members also have been the
victims of terrorist assaults in Western Europe.
   Schwarzkopf opened his briefing by describing the logistical
challenge of transporting U.S. troops and equipment to the Middle
East, 7,000 miles by air and 12,000 miles by sea from the East
Coast.
   Airlifting one heavy division would take 1,538 loads aboard a
C-141 transport and another 269 loads aboard a C-5 transport, the
largest aircraft in the world. For that reason, he said a lot of
equipment was being shipped by sea.
   ``The magnitude of this task, to quote my teen-agers, is
`totally awesome','' Schwarzkopf said.
   Schwarzkopf said the Iraqis were continuing to move
reinforcements into Kuwait. Those forces were taking up defensive
positions and some were ``right down literally on'' the
Kuwait-Saudi border, he said.
   Schwarzkopf said that the Iraqi troops had taken a similar
defensive posture before invading Kuwait on Aug. 2.
   ``There's no question about the fact that they have dug in right
now for a strong defense,'' the general said. But he added: ``They
have the capability to do just about anything they want to.''
   Schwarzkopf said he was confident U.S. troops could perform well
in the desert climate even if Saddam unleashed his arsenal of
chemical weapons.
   ``It's tough, sure, but it's not impossible. It's nowhere near
impossible.''
   Asked whether he expected a chemical attack, Schwarzkopf
said:``Given their record in the Iran-Iraq war I would never
discount that possibility ... We're prepared for everything.''
   He said Iraq has been calling up reserves but that its best
troops were those that invaded Kuwait and are still there.
   Schwarzkopf was in Saudi Arabia last week with Defense Secretary
Richard Cheney but since then had been directing the U.S. military
response from the Florida base, with a deputy command center based
in Saudi Arabia. But he said the main HQ would soon be set up in
Saudi Arabia and that he personally was going.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   EDITORS: John King is part of the national media pool
accompanying U.S. forces to Saudi Arabia.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0042 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 1538EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Iraq-TaxiEscape     08-12 0553</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Iraq-Taxi Escape,0567</SECOND>
<HEAD>N.C. Businessman Recounts Dash to Freedom</HEAD>
<HEAD>With Iraq-Foreigners, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CHARLOTTE, N.C. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Businessman John Norman rode a taxi for
five hours across the Iraqi desert in a harrowing flight to
freedom, chain-smoking cigarettes and nibbling on hard-boiled eggs
as the cab bounced toward Jordan.
   At the border checkpoint, Norman said, he feared for his life
when Iraqi soldiers began firing their automatic weapons after a
broadcast speech by Iraqi President Saddam Hussein.
   ``It was an escape,'' Norman told The Charlotte Observer in a
telephone interview Saturday. ``It wasn't a walk through. I didn't
know whether I was going to leave Iraq alive.''
   Norman, 38, was swept up into the U.S.-Iraqi military
confrontation while working in Baghdad, the Iraqi capital, as a
consultant to an Iraqi state bank.
   He returned to North Carolina on Friday, ending an odyssey that
in three days took him by cab, private car and jumbo jet from
Baghdad to Amman, Jordan, to London to Raleigh.
   A resident of the Raleigh area, Norman was on a 10-month
assignment in Iraq for the accounting firm Ernst &amp; Young. He was
scheduled to leave on a month-long vacation Aug. 2, the day Iraq
invaded Kuwait and the Baghdad airport was closed, stranding Norman
and other foreigners.
   Norman, who stayed at the Sheraton Hotel, said he felt no
immediate threat. But over the Aug. 4-5 weekend, he and his
colleagues sensed a rapid deterioration in their situation as the
United States turned up the heat on Iraq.
   Last Tuesday night, he said, the U.S. Embassy told them to leave
Iraq as soon as possible. But no one was sure whether the borders
were open.
   Although Norman and the others had planned to make a run for it
Thursday, they quickly decided to leave Wednesday.
   After breakfast, Norman hit the streets looking for taxis that
appeared durable enough to make the 300-mile trip to Jordan. He
found three Iraqi brothers, taxi owners, who agreed to take five
Americans and two Britons to Jordan in three cabs and a pickup
truck at a cost of $1,000 per vehicle.
   They didn't know whether they could pass through the Iraqi
frontier. ``We knew some of our compatriots had tried it,'' Norman
said. ``They were not back yet. That was a positive indication they
had gotten through.''
   The group left Baghdad at 12:30 p.m. for a hot, stomach-knotting
ride. Norman remembered the dash through the desert as the worst
part of the journey. ``The anxiety of getting to the Iraqi border _
what would I do next,'' he said.
   They arrived at the border checkpoint at 5:30 p.m., only to go
through repeated searches and passport checks. At one point,
boisterous Iraqi soldiers unnerved the Americans when they fired
their weapons into the air at the end of a speech by Hussein.
   ``It was more like celebration stuff,'' said colleague Pat
Schenning, 47, of Alexandria, Va. ``We were just a little scared at
that point.''
   After four hours of hassles, the border guards cleared the
Americans. About that time, employees from a U.S. bank arrived in
cars and took them to Amman, where they arrived about 3:30 a.m., 15
hours after they had left Baghdad.
   ``They closed the border shortly after we left,'' Norman said.
``I think we were the last people out.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0043 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 1548EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Soviet-Krishnas     08-12 0528</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Krishnas,0544</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hare Krishnas Dance Through Moscow's Gorky Park</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LARRY RYCKMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   About three dozen Hare Krishnas danced and sang
their way through Gorky Park on Sunday, but their advice to live
simply in a material world lost something in the translation in
material-less Moscow.
   The first legal Krishna celebration in the Soviet capital
followed years of official harassment or persecution of devotees.
   ``You don't need meat to be healthy,'' Indra Dyvmna Swami of San
Francisco told a group of curious Soviets gathered around a wooden
cart carrying a colorful tent and a brightly painted statue of the
Krishna god Jaganatha. Red carnations and daisies were strung
together around the cart.
   The crowd of about 100 listened closely, but there likely would
have been more enthusiasm _ and a longer line _ had the cart been
selling meat.
   And when he told them: ``This material world has very little to
offer,'' they nodded in agreement, knowing too well the expanses of
barren shelves in Moscow stores.
   They also enviously eyed his Nike running shoes _ a hot item on
the Moscow black market.
   Although Dyvmna and other group leaders were foreigners, most of
the Krishnas were Soviet citizens.
   The noisy procession through the park interrupted an outdoor
puppet show when the audience became more interested in the
Krishnas. The puppet, apparently peeved, began mimicking their
singing.
   As the Krishnas passed alongside the Moscow River, curious tour
boat passengers craned to see what all the fuss was about. One of
the new advertisements cropping up in Moscow was emblazoned on the
side of the boat, touting Pepsi.
   Parents hoisted children onto their shoulders to get a better
view of the spectacle of Krishnas, draped in their characteristic
robes, twirling, clapping and singing in the path of their cart.
People in foot-powered boats backpedaled and drifted to keep an eye
on things. Dyvmna Swami stopped to autograph Krishna books.
   There were a few rough spots along the way as Krishnas pulling
parallel ropes dragged their creaking cart on a circuitous route
through the wooded park.
   Several times they had to lower the tent on the cart or take a
detour because trees and power lines kept snagging its flag. Dyvmna
Swami lost his translator at one point and briefly had to abandon
proselytizing for more chanting.
   Later, after a Krishna trio belted out a rock version of a
Krishna chant, he tried to resume his sermon to Soviets seated on
wooden benches in an outdoor theater. But the sound system failed.
   Some Soviets walked out when the music ended. Others sat
patiently, waiting for the equipment to be repaired and for the
speeches to begin.
   Dyvmna Swami seemed pleased with the turnout and said that _
glitches notwithstanding _ it was a day to remember.
   ``This is the first year it's legal,'' he said. ``That's quite
historic, actually, considering the history of the Soviet Union.''
Religion of all types was severely restricted until recently, and
providing children with a religious education was a criminal
offense.
   An unofficial demonstration took place last year, but this year,
the Krishnas received permission for the public ceremony.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0044 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 1600EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Colombia     08-12 0596</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Colombia,0616</SECOND>
<HEAD>Killing of Trafficker Represents Major Blow to Cartel</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By STAN YARBRO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOGOTA, Colombia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A drug cartel leader killed by police
was responsible for coordinating terrorist attacks in Colombia and
shipments of cocaine to the United States, police said Sunday.
   Gustavo de Jesus Gaviria, the 41-year-old cousin of the Medellin
cartel's leader, Pablo Escobar, was fatally shot Saturday in a
shootout with anti-narcotics police raiding his apartment in
southern Medellin, according to an official police statement.
   Gen. Octavio Vargas, the operations chief of the national
police, said Escobar delegated Gaviria to manage the cartel's
terrorist bombings and assasinations and its shipments of tons of
cocaine to the United States and Europe.
   ``The damage caused to the cartel by the elimination of Gaviria
is incalculable,'' Vargas said in a telephone interview.
   Vargas, who planned Saturday's raid, said Medellin residents
angered by the cartel's attacks had tipped police off to Gaviria's
whereabouts two weeks ago.
   In the last year the cartel carried out nearly 300 bombings that
left 301 people dead. Early this year, the traffickers' began
gunning down Medellin police, killing 178 of them before the cartel
declared a unilateral truce last month.
   The truce is apparently intended to convince President Cesar
Gaviria, inaugurated Tuesday, to abandon the government's crackdown
on traffickers. President Gaviria is not related to Gustavo Gaviria.
   Vargas said police had taken special care to study the layout of
Gustavo Gaviria's luxury apartment, equipped with bullet-resistant
windows and a closed-circuit television monitoring system.
   Gaviria, wanted in both France and the United States on cocaine
trafficking charges, battled police with his Uzi submachine gun and
an M-14 automatic rifle, Vargas said.
   Witnesses quoted by newspapers said the gunbattle between
Gaviria and police lasted about 15 minutes.
   Police also captured one of Gaviria's associates, Alexandra
Tapias, in the raid, Vargas said. The police statement said that
another woman was also detained. She was not identified.
   Vargas said Gaviria's sister had claimed the suspect's body,
which was to be buried in a Medellin cemetary.
   In the last eight months, authorities have killed two other
cartel leaders in gunbattles. Police killed Jose Gonzalo Rodriguez
Gacha in December and John Jairo Arias earlier this year.
   Medellin police remain on alert, fearing that the killing may
prompt the cartel to carry out retaliatory attacks, the police
statement said.
   Gaviria's name first entered police records in 1976, when he was
arrested along with Escobar and charged with transporting 40 pounds
of cocaine in a car tire.
   A judge subsequently freed the two men without explanation. Four
years later the suspects were considered two of the richest, most
powerful drug barons in the country.
   In 1987, authorities accused Gaviria of responsibility for the
assassinations of two Colombian intellegence police officers. A
judge found him innocent, citing a lack of evidence.
   Last year, a French court convicted Gaviria of smuggling nearly
1,000 pounds of cocaine into the country and sentenced him in his
absence to 20 years in prison.
   The United States has requested Gaviria's extradition on charges
of cocaine distribution and money laundering. In recent years,
Florida authorities have confiscated two of Gaviria's luxury
apartments in Dade County and Miami Beach, according to a report in
Bogota's El Espectador newspaper.
   The Medellin cartel and a rival group in the city of Cali are
responsible for processing and smuggling 80 percent of the cocaine
sold in the United States, U.S. authorities have said.
   Police have called Gaviria the third most important member of
the Medellin cartel, led by Escobar and another trafficking
suspect, Jorge Luis Ochoa.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0045 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 1601EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-EmergencyLanding     08-12 0156</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Emergency Landing,0160</SECOND>
<HEAD>Continental Plane Makes Emergency Landing</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BELGRADE, Mont. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Continental Airlines jet with 157
people aboard made an emergency landing shortly after takeoff
Sunday morning when one of its three engines caught fire, officials
said.
   The Boeing 727, bound for Denver, landed safely shortly after 9
a.m., said Leo Roeske, air traffic manager at Gallatin Field, about
70 miles southeast of Helena in central Montana.
   David Messing, a spokesman for Continental in Houston, said the
passengers left the plane by sliding down emergency chutes, Messing
said. No one was injured.
   Roeske said he didn't know whether the fire was the cause of
engine failure or the result of it. Firefighters put firefighting
foam on the engine after the plane landed.
   The cause of problem would not be known until the engine could
be dismantled and examined, Messing said. He added that the plane
normally flies on two of its three engines.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0046 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 1608EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Iraq-KuwaitRdp 3rdLd-Writethru a0724 08-12 1091</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Iraq-Kuwait Rdp, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0724,1121</SECOND>
<HEAD>Iraq Ties Withdrawal to Surrender of Israeli-Occupied Territories</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 9th graf to include comment from White House. Pickup
10th pvs, `Saddam's proposal...</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos TLV1,DHA1,WX7,LaserColor WX107</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT DVORCHAK</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Saddam Hussein, under international quarantine for his invasion
of Kuwait, said Sunday that one of his conditions for resolving the
Persian Gulf crisis is Israeli withdrawal from the occupied
territories. He said ``many will be burned'' if war breaks out.
   The Iraqi president demanded the withdrawal of U.S. troops from
Saudi Arabia and the end to U.N. economic sanctions against Iraq,
which forced him to ask his people to be thrifty with meat and
clothing.
   At the same time, the United States announced it will intercept
Iraqi oil shipments to tighten the squeeze on Iraq for its Aug. 2
invasion of Kuwait. American and Arab soldiers have been massing to
defend Saudi Arabia from Iraqi expansionism.
   A group of Iraqi pilots offered to fly suicide missions against
U.S. ships in the Persian Gulf. Britain, France and other countries
have joined U.S. warships in the Middle East in an attempt to deter
a possible Iraqi attack on Saudi Arabia.
   In a televised statement read by a spokesman, Saddam suggested
he would tie any Iraqi withdrawal from Kuwait to an Israeli
withdrawal from the occupied West Bank and Gaza Strip and a Syrian
withdrawal from Lebanon. Israel took the territories from Egypt and
Jordan in the 1967 Middle East war.
   ``If America and its allies will not accept this initiative, we
will resist by force,'' Saddam said. ``They will leave this country
with their tails behind them.''
   He also warned: ``If the spark of war is started, many will be
burned.''
   Israel dismissed Saddam's proposal as ``cheap propaganda.''
   Presidential spokesman Marlin Fitzwater said the United States
``categorically rejects'' Saddam's proposals and said it backs the
U.N. Security Council's call ``for the immediate, complete and
unconditional withdrawal of Iraqi forces from Kuwait.''
   ``These latest conditions and threats are another attempt at
distracting from Iraq's isolation and at imposing a new status
quo,'' Fitzwater said.
   Saddam's proposal appeared to be aimed at broadening the debate
over his invasion of Kuwait into a discussion of a host of Middle
East problems, some of which remain unresolved after decades of
talks and war.
   Gen. H. Norman Schwarzkopf, commander of the U.S. Central
Command, told pool reporters that deployment of troops is running
ahead of schedule and U.S. soldiers are aware of possible terrorist
attacks against them in the Middle East.
   He also said of the Iraqis: ``If they do make an attack they are
going to pay a price for it.''
   A U.S. airman died Sunday in Saudi Arabia as the result of an
accident, becoming the first American killed in the desert
operation, the Pentagon said. The dead man was identified as Air
Force Staff Sgt. John Campsi. The Pentagon said the accident is
being investigated but had no further details.
   There were signs the Iraqis are girding for a long siege. One
day after warning that black marketeers in Iraq would be executed,
Saddam urged Iraqi women to cut meat consumption in half and be
frugal with clothing.
   ``What is demanded is that no one stockpile food supplies,''
Saddam said. ``Stockpiles will bring about shortages.''
   A U.N. embargo on trade has choked off incoming shipments of
food, military parts and essential goods. However, the embargo may
allow humanitarian shipments of food.
   Iraq's oil exports have virtually trickled shut. But Secretary
of State James A. Baker III said the United States would honor a
request by the Kuwaiti government in exile to intercept Iraqi oil
shipments.
   ``Let's not use the word blockade,'' Baker said on ABC-TV's
``This Week With David Brinkley.'' ``Let's just say we have the
legal basis for interdicting these things.''
   U.S. and allied warships are poised to meet Iraqi tankers coming
from the Persian Gulf, Red Sea or Mediterranean Sea. Iraq is
dependent on oil exports to buy food and supplies for its 17
million people.
   Iraq is virtually encircled on the ground with the possible
exception of Jordan. Turkish Premier Yildirim Akbulut said Sunday
he will ask Parliament for the power to declare a state of war and
send armed forces into combat if the crisis worsens. He called it a
precautionary move.
   To the south, 10,000 Egyptian and Moroccan troops are joining
50,000 U.S. soldiers moving into Saudi Arabia. Syria, on Iraq's
northwestern border, has also pledged troops.
   To the east, Iraq is still in a state of war with Iran although
a U.N.-sponsored cease-fire has been holding since 1988.
   Iranian President Hashemi Rafsanjani called the takeover of
Kuwait ``one of Iraq's more abominable acts'' but he also said the
U.S. intervention was illegal.
   ``The presence of foreign forces has inflamed the Persian Gulf
and the region has become like a powder keg,'' Rafsanjani said
Sunday.
   In the Jordan city of Mafraq, thousands of people converged for
an anti-American rally organized by the Jordanian Committee in
Support of Iraq. The rallies began after Saddam's call for a ``holy
war'' against Saudi Arabia and Western countries intervening in the
Persian Gulf.
   Police stopped about 50 pro-Iraqi protesters marching on the
U.S. Embassy in the capital city of Amman, dispersing them
peacefully, a witness said.
   An estimated 10,000 Palestinians staged a noisy demonstration of
support for Iraq at a refugee camp in southern Lebanon. Chanting
``Death to America!'' the demonstrators hanged effigies of
President Bush, British Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher and Saudi
Arabian King Fahd.
   A PLO official said 500 refugees at another camp had volunteered
to go to Iraq to fight against an American attack.
   But in Bangladesh, hundreds of people demonstrated outside
Iraq's embassy to secure the safety of 110,000 Bangladesh citizens
trapped in the invasion. Demonstrators shouted ``Iraqi troops get
out of Kuwait!''
   In Israel, stores reported panic purchases of gas masks
following Iraqi threats to attack with chemical weapons.
   A British citizen was reportedly shot in Kuwait near the Saudi
border, and scores of foreigners were returning to their homelands
Sunday with stories of rapes and killings by Iraqi soldiers.
   Britain's Foreign Office said Sunday it could not determine
immediately whether the reported shooting on Saturday night was
fatal. Foreign Office Minister William Waldegrave said the report
came from unidentified people who had crossed the border recently.
   Penelope Nabokov, the 10-year-old California girl who was
detoured by the blitzkrieg on her way to visit her mother, fled to
freedom Saturday and was on her way to meet her parents Sunday.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0047 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 1613EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Iraq-Kuwait-Editorials 1stAdd   08-12 0529</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Iraq-Kuwait-Editorials, 1st Add,0542</SECOND>
<HEAD>UNDATED: defense policies.</HEAD>
<HEAD>The Washington Post</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   It is heartening to see Egypt exercising leadership in the
strategy to force Iraq out of Kuwait. For the United States and
Europe, the primary interest in political stability there is the
flow of oil. Iraq's neighbors have much more at stake. Iraq has
made it clear that its intentions go beyond this month's conquest.
It proposes to make itself dominant among the Arabs. Saddam Hussein
has been claiming, in recent days, to speak for all the Arab world
in a great test of will and of strength with the Americans. But
most of the Arab world denounced him on Friday in the Arab League's
meeting, and now Egyptian forces as well as Americans face him at
the Saudi border.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>The Detroit News</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   No one in Washington, it seems, wants to use the ``H'' word _
hostages _ to describe the several thousand Americans who were
caught in Kuwait and Iraq at the time of the latter's blitzkrieg
conquest of the former two weeks ago. With every day that passes
without their being allowed to leave, however, it becomes harder to
avoid the conclusion that they are being held against their will.
   (President Bush) should set a deadline for the unconditional
release of the Americans. Failure to comply will result in attacks
on Iraqi oil fields and other targets. Harm to any Americans would
be considered an act of all-out war.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>The Philadelphia Inquirer</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   An Arab force on the Saudi border will signal that an attack
will embroil him (Hussein) in an inter-Arab war. It is hoped that
this would also undercut his attempt to portray himself as the hero
who would save Arab oil fields and Muslim holy places from unclean
Western hands.
   ... The real test of global cooperation against Iraq will be if
that blockade holds. It could take months for sanctions to move
Baghdad, and Saddam Hussein will undoubtedly counterattack. He may
use hostages or terrorism, or undermine Arab leaders who stand up
to him. It will take patience, and test White House leadership, to
keep a global blockade going. But the best inspiration to stick
together may come from listening to the words of Saddam Hussein.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Los Angeles Times</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   The crisis provoked by Iraq's invasion of Kuwait has escalated
into the first major confrontation of the post-Cold War era and new
realities, both hopeful and sobering, are emerging.
   Foremost among the latter is the realization that a world
liberated from the threat of nuclear annihilation will not be free
of mortal danger. As the case of Saddam Hussein makes all too
clear, there remain good old-fashioned nationalist dictators every
bit as aggressive and threatening as Stalinist ideologues. ...
   But ... much that has transpired so far should be a source of
hope. The willingness of the vast majority of the world's nations
to directly and collectively engage Hussein's challenge is, as
foreign policy analyst Stanley Hoffman put it, ``quite
remarkable.'' In fact, if the anti-Hussein coalition holds
together, this crisis could, as former diplomat Richard N. Gardner
has said, ``constitute a landmark event in the history of this
century.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0048 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 1615EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Barry-Poll     08-12 0388</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Barry-Poll,380</SECOND>
<HEAD>DC Residents Don't Want Jail Time Or New Trial For Mayor</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Barry Future</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Most Washington residents don't want Mayor
Marion Barry to go to jail, but they don't believe either that he
should be retried on any of 12 unresolved federal charges against
him, poll results published Sunday show.
   A majority of respondents to The Washington Post poll said also
that they do not want Barry to seek another term as mayor or to run
for a city council post.
   Better than half of those asked said they believed Barry should
resign from office immediately.
   A U.S. District Court jury on Friday convicted Barry of one
cocaine possession charge and acquitted him on another. The panel
was unable to reach a verdict on the 12 remaining counts and U.S.
District Judge Thomas Penfield Jackson declared a mistrial.
   The survey of 603 randomly selected residents of the nation's
capital was conducted Saturday for the Post by Chilton Research of
Radnor, Pa. The newspaper did not indicate a margin of error, but
said that because of ``the practical difficulties associated with
doing a public opinion poll in one day,'' the survey results
``should be interpreted with caution.''
   Sixty-four percent of the respondents said Barry should not go
to jail, while 31 percent said he should serve time. The remaining
5 percent either had no opinion or refused to respond.
   Seventy-three percent of the respondents said Barry should not
be tried again. Twenty-three percent favored a new court case and 4
percent either had no opinion or refused to respond.
   Barry has hinted to associates recently that he would not run
for mayor, but might attempt a return to the city council, where he
served for four years before ascending to the city's top office.
   It is too late for him to file as a candidate for the Democratic
nomination in the Sept. 11, primary although he could still run as
an independent in the Nov. 6 general election.
   But 63 percent of the respondents said they would not vote for
Barry. Thirty-two percent said they would, while 5 percent either
had no opinion or did not respond.
   Fifty-two percent said Barry should resign immediately, while 45
percent wanted him to remain in office. Three percent either had to
opinion or refused to respond.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0049 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 1625EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-DeathByChemistry 1stLd-Writethru a0720 08-12 0977</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Death By Chemistry, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0720,950</SECOND>
<HEAD>Chemical Weapons Kill And Maim, But Effective Treatment Available</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: SUBS 6th graf, ``Both chemical ...'' to CORRECT spelling of
`ordnance' and fix typo in `vaporize.'
^By PAUL RECER</NOTE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   For the first time since World War I, American
troops stare across a no-man's land at a potential enemy who has
used chemical weapons and may do so again.
   Iraq is known to have stockpiled at least two chemical weapons.
One burns the skin like liquid fire. The other kills in minutes by
disrupting nervous system functions.
   And Iraq's army, massed along a border across from U.S. troops
in Saudi Arabia, is known to have used at least one of the
chemicals in its war with Iran and against Kurdish dissident groups
in its own country.
   Iraq's burning chemical is thought to be the same mustard gas
that confronted the great-grandfathers of today's U.S. troops in
the trenches of World War I Europe. It worked so well 70 years ago
that civilized nations banned the use of such weapons. Mustard gas
still does its work with ghastly efficiency.
   The other chemical agent, commonly called nerve gas, is a group
of compounds added to the arsenals of war by advances in chemistry
and in biological understanding. It takes but a drop of
concentrated nerve agent, absorbed by the skin, to kill.
   Both chemical weapons can be delivered by bomb, artillery shell
or mine. When the ordnance explodes, the chemicals vaporize,
spreading quickly.
   Mustard, in a gas or droplet form, is readily absorbed by
exposed skin and is quickly taken up by inner layers of tissue.
   ``Initially, there are no symptoms,'' says Lloyd Roberts, a
research administrator at the Army's Institute of Chemical Defense.
``There is a delayed effect.''
   Reactions vary depending on concentrations and individuals, said
Roberts, but generally within one to six hours a victim will
experience itching and reddening of the skin. Within 12 hours, huge
blisters appear. The blisters burst and the skin is sloughed,
leaving large, gaping wounds ripe for infection.
   It is very much like a third degree burn, said Roberts, ``and
that's how we treat it.''
   Dead skin must be pulled away and the wound washed with sterile
solution. Healing is slow and painful. Infection a constant threat.
   ``The eyes are the most vulnerable to mustard,'' said Roberts.
Even a medium exposure causes pain and swelling and the white of
the eye turns an angry red. In heavy exposures, there are severe
lacerations of the cornea. Some soldiers in World War I were
blinded.
   But mustard does its worst damage in the respiratory system.
   ``It tends to be lethal only when inhaled,'' Roberts said.
   Just as it blisters the skin, inhaled mustard gas blisters the
lungs and the airway of the respiratory tract. Breathing becomes
tortured. Patients cough blood. Internal surface tissue dies and
pneumonia becomes a fearful threat.
   Medical care depends on the symptoms.
   A mild dose, said Roberts, causes hoarseness and sore throat and
no treatment is required. For a cough, the Army uses syrups. For
laryngitis, there is sterile steam and bed rest.
   For severe cases, patients are hospitalized for months and
treated aggressively with antibiotics to ward off pneumonia.
   ``Mortality from mustard gas in World War I was about one
percent,'' said Roberts. Now, with modern care, it could be even
less.
   Unlike mustard, that can cause large obvious wounds, nerve
agents are sly, quick killers, attacking the body at the molecular
level.
   Readily absorbed by the skin, nerve gas goes to work
immediately. It kills by disrupting a chemical reaction that occurs
each time a muscle moves.
   Roberts said nerve agents bind to a protein molecule called
acetyclcholinesterase, of AChE, and keep it from doing its job.
   AChE normally destroys another protein molecule called
acetylcholine, or ACh. This molecule is a neurotransmitter that
moves from nerve to muscle each time a voluntary muscle operates.
It also works in the brain to carry signals from cell to cell.
   Normally, when the neurotransmitter has done its job, it is
immediately inactivated by AChE. But if the nerve gas keeps the
AChE from working, then the neurotransmitter builds up and
continues to act on the muscles and brain cells.
   Muscle control is lost. Spasms set in as muscles contract, time
after time. There's weakness and collapse. Respiration is
depressed. Heart beat slows. Convulsions. Unconsciousness. The
diaphragm muscle stops working. Death.
   ``The person suffocates,'' said Roberts. ``Unprotected, a person
is dead within 10 minutes, tops.''
   As with any chemical weapon, the effects depend on the
concentration. After a weak exposure, symptoms can be mild and pass
within hours. A stronger, non-lethal concentration may cause
symptoms that last a day or longer. But there are seldom long-term
effects, said Roberts.
   ``With a nerve agent, if you survive, you can return to duty
within a week,'' he said. ``It either kills you or you recover.''
   One way to modify or even completely block the nerve gas effect
is with a chemical antidote.
   And Roberts said American troops are issued two of these. One is
atropine and the other is called pralidoxime choride. The drugs are
carried in spring-loaded syringes.
   At the first sign of exposure, a soldier can slap the syringe
against a thigh and the drugs quickly enter the body.
   Both atropine and pralidoxime choride, said Roberts, work by
inhibiting the excess ACh neurotransmitter molecule. In effect, the
drugs for a brief time do the job of the acetylcholinesterase that
was attacked by the nerve gas.
   The first line of defense against a chemical attack, though, are
protective garments: boots, rubber gloves, masks and hooded helmets.
   On the battlefield of chemical warfare, survival means every
inch of skin must be covered and every breath filtered _ even in an
Arabian desert where midday temperatures may soar to 110 degrees.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0050 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 1627EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Iraq 4thLd-Writethru a0723 08-12 0692</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Iraq, 4th Ld-Writethru, a0723,0713</SECOND>
<HEAD>Iraq Links Withdrawal to Israeli Surrender of Occupied Territories</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS throughout to bring quotes into line with AP
translation. No pickup.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By WALTER C. PUTNAM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NICOSIA, Cyprus (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Saddam Hussein on Sunday declared
readiness to resolve the Persian Gulf crisis _ if Israel withdraws
from occupied Arab territories, Syria pulls out of Lebanon and U.S.
forces leave Saudi Arabia.
   The Iraqi president also demanded an end to international
economic action against his nation.
   In a statement read by an announcer on Baghdad radio and
television, Saddam said foreign powers intervening in the region
were setting off ``the spark of war'' which would ``burn many.''
   The statement was translated by The Associated Press.
   If the international community wanted foreign forces kept in the
region, he said, they should be replaced by Arab troops ``with the
(U.N.) Security Council making all the arrangements'' on which
nationalities should be involved.
   Saddam said if the United States and its allies did not not
accept his initiative, Iraq would ``resist its evil intentions and
aggressive schemes.''
   ``We will be victorious, with God's help,'' he said. ``The
evil-doers will regret their acts when they are driven out in shame
from the region.''
   He said any Arab force should not include Egypt, which he said
was being used by the United States as a launching pad for
``conspiracies against the Arabs.''
   Egypt and Morocco were the first Arab countries to send troops
to Saudi Arabia to face Iraqi forces massed along that country's
border with Kuwait.
   The Arab deployment came after the United States and other
nations sent ships, planes and thousands of troops to the region to
defend strategic, oil-rich Saudi Arabia.
   In his statement, Saddam called for ``all cases of occupation,
and those cases that have been portrayed as occupation'' to be be
resolved simultaneously, under the ``same principles and
guidelines.''
   He linked any withdrawal from Kuwait to an Israeli withdrawal
from the occupied West Bank and Gaza Strip, a Syrian pullout from
Lebanon, and the resolution of Iran-Iraq land disputes stemming
from their 1980-88 war.
   All of those conflicts have remained intractable in the face of
negotiations, sometimes over a period of years, or outright warfare.
   By bringing them up now, Saddam could be seeking to buy time,
broaden the argument over his conquest of Kuwait, and attract Arab
support by calling for the surrender of the Israeli-occupied lands.
   Israel dismissed Saddam's call as ``cheap propaganda.'' There
was no immediate reaction from Syria, which was unlikely for
strategic reasons to comply with the demand that it leave Lebanon.
   Some Arabs have criticized the United States and others for
sending troops in response to the takeover of Kuwait but not taking
similar action to end Israel's occupation of the West Bank and Gaza
Strip, which it captured in the 1967 Middle East war.
   In his statement, Saddam demanded an end to international
economic sanctions, calling on all nations to freeze immediately
all ``boycott and siege decisions'' against Iraq.
   But even as the Iraqi leader made the demand, the United States
was pledging to tighten the economic noose.
   Secretary of State James A. Baker III said Sunday on ABC that
the United States would intercept Iraqi oil shipments. He said the
move was in response to the exiled Kuwaiti government's call for
world governments to enforce United Nations sanctions against Iraq.
   The U.N. Security Council approved a worldwide trade embargo on
Iraq and Kuwait on Aug. 6.
   The Iraqi president reiterated Baghdad's longstanding claims on
Kuwait, which it annexed Aug. 8.
   When Kuwait, a former British colony, became independent nearly
three decades ago, Iraq refused then to recognize its sovreignty.
``Iraq has never recognized the crime committed by the
colonialists,'' Saddam said.
   Earlier Sunday, in a statement also read on Baghdad radio and
television, Saddam urged the Iraqi people to prepare for hardships
that may result from the international economic sanctions.
   Also Sunday, the Iraqi News Agency said a group of pilots has
offered to fly suicide missions against U.S. ships sent to the gulf
as part of the multinational force being deployed to defend Saudi
Arabia.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0051 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 1629EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Iraq-Defectors     08-12 0188</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Iraq-Defectors,0192</SECOND>
<HEAD>Two Iraqi Pilots Said to Defect to Saudi Arabia</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Iraq-Kuwait Rdp, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NICOSIA, Cyprus (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two Iraqi air force pilots have defected
by flying their MiG warplanes to a base in northern Saudi Arabia,
diplomatic sources in the Middle East said Sunday.
   The sources, who spoke on condition of anonymity, said the
Soviet-built warplanes landed Saturday at the Hafr al-Baten base,
the main center for the foreign troop buildup in Saudi Arabia.
   The U.S. State Department said it had not heard the report. The
Kuwaiti Embassy in Washington said it had heard the report but
could not confirm it.
   U.S. and other foreign countries are sending forces to Saudi
Arabia to defend against any attack by Iraq, which invaded Kuwait
on Aug. 2.
   The diplomatic sources said the planes were MiGs, but they did
not know the precise type. The pilots were not identified, and
there were no other immediate details.
   Iraq has at least 70 MiG-23 ground attack fighters, as well as
70 MiG-21 and 18 MiG-29 fighters. It also has eight MiG-25
reconnaissance planes and a variety of MiG training planes.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0052 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 1648EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Iraq-Anti-US     08-12 0427</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Iraq-Anti-US,0443</SECOND>
<HEAD>Palestinians Protest in Support of Iraq</HEAD>
<HEAD>With Iraq-Kuwait Rdp, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BEIRUT, Lebanon (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   About 10,000 Palestinians demonstrated
Sunday in a refugee camp in southern Lebanon in support of Iraq. A
PLO official said 500 youths volunteered to fight with Iraq against
a possible American attack.
   Another pro-Iraqi demonstration was reported in Jordan. In
Bangladesh, hundreds rallied against Iraqi President Saddam
Hussein's Aug. 2 invasion of Kuwait.
   The demonstrators at Lebanon's Ein el-Hilweh refugee camp
chanted ``Death to America!'' and called Saudi Arabia's King Fahd
an ``American spy.'' They also hanged effigies of President Bush,
British Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher and Fahd.
   Some of the demonstrators marched carrying pictures of Saddam
and Palestine Liberation Organization chairman Yasser Arafat.
   At the end of the protest, a PLO official told the crowd that
500 Palestinians from Ein el-Hilweh, the largest refugee camp in
Lebanon, had volunteered to go to Iraq to fight against a potential
American attack.
   But also Sunday, Hussein Musawi, the head of a pro-Syrian wing
of the fundamentalist Hezbollah, or Party of God criticized
Palestinians for supporting Saddam, whom he referred to as ``a
Satan.''
   Hezbollah is Iran's main ally in Lebanon and an umbrella for
several hostage-holding factions.
   ``Saddam is a Satan, not a Moslem leader,'' Musawi said. ``The
one who waged war against the Islamic republic (Iran) and Syria and
who unleashed chemical weapons against the Kurds is not a hero but
a Satan.''
   In Jordan on Sunday, police stopped about 50 pro-Iraqi
protesters from marching on the U.S. Embassy, a witness said.
   In the northern city of Mafraq, 50 miles north of the capital,
thousands of people converged for a protest rally organised by the
Jordanian Committee in Support of Iraq.
   A large percentage of Jordan's population is Palestinian.
   The small crowd in Amman chanted pro-Iraqi and anti-American
slogans and banging their fists on parked cars.
   Scores of policemen stopped the protesters at a traffic circle
about 100 yards from the embassy and they dispersed without
incident, said the witness, who spoke on condition of anonymity.
   Minor demonstrations have been staged for most of the week in
Jordan, giving vent to a growing wave of anti-Americanism following
the dispatch of U.S. troops to Saudi Arabia to protect the oil-rich
kingdom against possible Iraqi attack.
   In Bangladesh, hundreds of people shouting ``Iraqi troops get
out of Kuwait!'' rallied outside the Iraqi Embassy to secure the
safety of 110,000 Bangladesh citizens trapped in the invasion.
   The demonstrators dispersed after they were allowed to hand over
a protest letter to the Iraqi ambassador.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0053 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 1652EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-India-Kashmir     08-12 0350</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-India-Kashmir,0364</SECOND>
<HEAD>Villagers Say Soldiers Kill At Least 25 Villagers, Rape Women</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SRINAGAR, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Government troops killed 25 people in a
raid on two villages in the Kashmir valley in search of Moslem
separatists who had ambushed an army convoy, residents said Sunday.
   Villagers said at least 50 people were missing, at least 15
women were raped by the soldiers and many people were beaten during
Friday's raids.
   The government said 24 militants were killed by the troops in
the area, but said they were slain in a shootout. It denied the
accusations of rape.
   The Times of India newspaper put the number of dead at 45.
   The army raid followed an ambush on a troop convoy near the
Pazipora and Balipora villages, about 58 miles northwest of
Srinagar, residents said. Reinforcements poured into the villages
in search of the attackers, they said.
   Ghulam Mohammed Butt, one of the villagers, said the troops shot
and killed his two teen-age sons, Farooq and Bashir Ahmed.
   ``We told them we didn't know about the militants, but they
didn't listen,'' he said.
   Other villagers said 15 women who had barricaded themselves in a
house, were raped. At least 50 men who had fled into surrounding
paddy fields and pine forests were missing and feared killed, they
said.
   Girish Saxena, the governor of Jammu-Kashmir state, said troops
killed 24 militants after they came under fire. He said he had not
heard any accusations of rape and that he would order an official
inquiry if the reports were true.
   Security forces in Kashmir often are accused of excesses in
containing the Moslem movement for secession of the valley from
Hindu-majority India.
   At least 985 people have been killed in Kashmir since Jan 20,
when the government launched a crackdown on the insurrection.
   The valley is predominantly Moslem and is part of Jammu-Kashmir
state, the only one of India's 25 provinces with a Moslem majority.
   At least 65 percent of the state's 6 million people are Moslem.
Nationwide, Moslems make up 12 percent of India's 880 million
people, while Hindus comprise 82 percent.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0054 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 1656EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-BarryFuture 1stLd-Writethru a0741 08-12 0696</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Barry Future, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0741,670</SECOND>
<HEAD>Barry's Latest Political Move May Be Abandonment Of Party
Affiliation</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: Subs 5th graf, ``Winning a council xxx to include that Barry
elected to city council in 1974</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By RICHARD KEIL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Mayor Marion Barry is receiving conflicting
advice on whether he should run for city council, but is planning
nonetheless to drop his Democratic party affiliation as a first
step, aides said Sunday.
   Barry, convicted Friday of one cocaine possession charge and
acquitted of another, plans to drop out of the Democratic Party and
register as an independent on Monday, said top Barry aides who
spoke only on condition of anonymity.
   That would be Barry's first step toward reviving his political
career with a campaign for an at-large seat on the District of
Columbia's 13-member council, the aides said.
   Monday is the deadline for switching parties. If Barry becomes
an independent, he would then have to gather the signatures of
2,000 registered city voters before his name could be placed on the
ballot. He would compete for two city-wide council seats with
winners of the Republican, Democrat, and Statehood party primaries.
   Winning a council seat would allow Barry to maximize his future
city pension earnings and let him stay active in local politics,
which he has dominated since he was first elected mayor in 1978. He
had been elected to the city council in 1974.
   ``His life is politics, and he doesn't know anything else,'' one
Barry adviser said. ``If he stays clean, he can contribute a lot.
That's what he wants to do.''
   Barry announced in June that he would not seek a fourth term as
mayor. He has 16 years of city government service and would be
eligible for a full pension after 20 years.
   But Barry's supporters are deeply divided over whether the mayor
should remain in politics, other sources said.
   While some believe Barry has been exonerated and should resume
his political career, others are wary of antagonizing U.S. District
Judge Thomas Penfield Jackson or prosecutors.
   ``There are some, including his top government aides, who
believe he should do nothing to irritate either Jackson or (U.S.
Attorney Jay B.) Stephens, said one associate. ``The feeling is,
`Don't do anything to draw attention to yourself.'''
   Jackson has not yet set a sentencing date for Barry's
misdemeanor cocaine possession conviction, which carries a maximum
penalty of one year in prison and a $100,000 fine. In addition,
Stephens has not yet revealed whether he intends to retry Barry on
a dozen charges against the mayor on which the jury couldn't reach
a verdict.
   Some of Barry's advisers believe the government would be more
likely to pursue the case _ and Jackson would be more inclined to
send the mayor to jail _ if Barry is actively campaigning for
office.
   Stephens has said only that the trial evidence will be reviewed
before he decides whether to pursue the matter, but politics have
been intertwined with the case since Barry's Jan. 18 arrest in an
FBI sting operation. During plea bargain negotiations, the mayor
has said, Stephens insisted that Barry would have to resign his
office as part of any agreement with the government.
   Law enforcement sources have corroborated Barry's account of the
negotiations.
   And there are other, more tangible, indications that a Barry
candidacy might not be in the mayor's best interests.
   A Washington Post poll published Sunday shows that while a
majority of those interviewed believe the government should abandon
is prosecution of the mayor, a greater percentage believe Barry
himself should scuttle any plans to run for office this year.
   In addition, other sources said that Barry's wife Effi is deeply
opposed to the mayor running for office.
   ``She has been referring to politics as a thing of the past,''
said one Barry associate. ``She has said, in so many words, that
she is not interested in another campaign.''
   ``In the end, he will do what he wants to do _ just like he
always has,'' said one longtime Barry associate. ``Making the party
switch will allow him to keep his options open, to test the water a
little while longer.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0055 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 1712EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Iraq-Israel 1stLd-Writethru a0707 08-12 0689</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Iraq-Israel, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0707,0707</SECOND>
<HEAD>Israel Rejects Saddam's Offer for Withdrawal</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Iraq-Kuwait Rdp, Bjt</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 11 grafs to UPDATE with comment from Palestinian
leader, foreign ministry, Arens. Pick up 10th graf pvs, `The
Cabinet...'</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto TLV1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SERGEI SHARGORODSKY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Israel on Sunday rejected as ``cheap
propaganda'' Iraqi President Saddam Hussein's proposal linking a
possible Iraqi withdrawal from Kuwait to an Israeli pullout from
the occupied West Bank and Gaza Strip.
   But Palestinian leaders on Sunday welcomed Saddam's proposal,
saying it would boost their demands for a homeland.
   ``If the Americans will take the initiative seriously, then we
can get something good from a bad situation,'' said Faisal
Husseini, the leading pro-PLO activist in the occupied territories.
   Also Sunday, the Israeli military refused comment on foreign
reports that Israel placed its air force on alert and moved
anti-aircraft missiles to the Jordanian border following threats
from Iraq to use chemical weapons.
   Israeli stores, meanwhile, reported a huge increase in the
purchases of gas masks.
   The Iraqi proposal was Saddam's third attempt in five days to
involve Israel in the Persian Gulf crisis to try to win grass-roots
support in Arab countries.
   In his statement, 11 days after his conquest of Kuwait, Saddam
suggested he would tie any Iraqi withdrawal from Kuwait to an
Israeli withdrawal from the occupied West Bank and Gaza Strip and a
Syrian withdrawal from Lebanon. Syria maintains 40,000 troops in
Lebanon.
   ``I suggest that all cases of occupation _ or cases that are
described as occupation _ be resolved at the same time,'' Saddam
said in a statement read on Baghdad television by an announcer.
   ``Saddam Hussein is trying through all kinds of exercises to do
away with the international force which is confronting him, and to
evade the economic sanctions which are being enforced against
him,'' Prime Minister Yitzhak Shamir's adviser Avi Pazner said in a
statement. ``His so-called initiative is nothing but cheap
propaganda.''
   Saddam's idea was a ``propaganda ploy to divert world opinion
from the main issue: a large country devouring a small neighbor in
naked, unprovoked aggression,'' said Foreign Ministry spokesman
Yosef Amihud.
   Defense Minister Moshe Arens, speaking to foreign reporters in
Tel Aviv before Saddam's demands were made public, said ``there is
no correlation at all between whatever success or lack of success
we may have in dealing with the Palestinian problem and Saddam
Hussein.''
   The Cabinet met Sunday followed British reports that Israel has
placed its air force on alert and a report by the NBC network that
American-made HAWK anti-aircraft missiles have been moved to the
Jordanian border. The military refused to comment on the reports.
   The missile deployment could be linked to media reports quoting
Defense Ministry aide Dan Naveh as saying Iraq had no missiles
armed with chemical warheads and other informed sources as saying
that only the Iraqi air force could strike Israel.
   In Israel, anxiety mounted.
   In ultra-Orthodox neighborhoods, wall posters spoke of a ``state
of war with Iraq'' and called on ``all the boys and girls, youths
and yeshiva students to cancel all vacations... and return to
classes to study Torah and pray.''
   Stores reported a record increase in the purchases of gas masks
and other protective gear.
   ``We have sold hundreds of gas masks since the gulf crisis. A
week ago we would only sell a few per week,'' said Ilan Shalev,
sales manager at Tel Aviv's Gazit safety equipment store.
   An army spokesman said there was no need to begin a mass
distribution of gas masks.
   The spokesman, who spoke on condition of anonymity, said there
were enough masks ``for all citizens of Israel,'' including Israeli
Arabs, as well as tourists.
   There are about 810,000 Israeli Arabs.
   A former Civil Guard commander, Aryeh Biro, said there were no
masks for the 1.7 million Palestinians living in the occupied West
Bank and the Gaza Strip.
   ``For residents of the territories, unlike the Israeli Arabs, we
think we have no masks for them,'' Biro said on Israel army radio.
``We don't need to give them masks because we don't expect danger
in these areas.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0056 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 1720EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-CowboyThief     08-12 0453</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Cowboy Thief,0466</SECOND>
<HEAD>Cowboy Fake Wanted in Indiana, Texas Arrested in Missouri</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DANVILLE, Ind. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Police say a mysterious cowboy with a
black hat and missing fingertips has been brought to justice in
Missouri after leading a band that rustled horses and stole
high-priced saddles from New York to Texas.
   ``Horse stealing and saddle theft are crimes that most people
think died with the Old West. But it is still really big
business,'' said Hendricks County sheriff's Lt. Stephen G. Golden,
who had been tailing the man for months.
   The cowboy, who says his name is William Robert Stanley, was
being held Sunday in lieu of $300,000 bond in a Springfield, Mo.,
jail on theft and other charges. Two accomplices also were arrested
for theft and burglary.
   Indiana police say the real William Robert Stanley is dead, and
the rustler made off with his name.
   Some of the man's fingertips have been either burned or filed
off, making positive identification by fingerprints difficult _ the
arrested man told police he lost the fingertips shoeing horses.
   The tall, slender, sandy-haired man is suspected of stealing
more than 100 saddles and other gear during the past three years,
Golden said. Police also have been trying to trace at least 13
horses that witnesses reported seeing in the cowboy's trailer in
recent weeks.
   Some of the horses and gear were stolen in Oklahoma, Tennessee
and Texas, that shipped north and sold in auction barns in Indiana
and other states, authorities said.
   The real William Robert Stanley, 34, of Irving, Texas, died in
Dallas on Jan. 18 of complications from the treatment of leukemia.
He had been assistant administrator of a hospital in nearby Fort
Worth.
   Golden believes the cowboy went to Stanley's hometown of
Concord, N.H., after Stanley's death and obtained an official copy
of his birth certificate.
   A driver's license in Stanley's name was issued Jan. 26 at
Tulsa, Okla.
   About a week later, Stanley's widow, Ruthie Stanley, got a phone
call from a man claiming to be from the local Social Security
Administration office in Texas. The caller, who Golden believes was
the cowboy, wanted to confirm Stanley's Social Security number.
   Mrs. Stanley said the caller ``was so sorry for my loss, and he
said that I would get a packet of information from Social Security.
I never got one.''
   A duplicate Social Security card was issued April 11 in the
Grand Prairie, Texas, Social Security office, Golden said. The card
was issued even though government computers showed Stanley was dead
and benefits were being paid to his family.
   ``My husband was really an honest person, and it breaks my heart
to see his name drug through the mud,'' Mrs. Stanley said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0057 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 1721EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brite-MotorMansion     08-12 0319</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brite-Motor Mansion,0328</SECOND>
<HEAD>Largest Motor Home Owner Travels the Fair Circuit</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto CO1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PATRICK CULLEN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>COLUMBUS, Ohio (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Joe Harrington is careful where he drives
his motor home, because some cities just aren't big enough for the
two of them.
   Harrington drives what he calls the ``world's largest, most
unusual motor home,'' now on display at the Ohio State Fair. His
house, dubbed ``Ninth Wonder,'' is 12{ feet high, 8 feet wide and
46 feet long.
   Harrington, 60, a former truck driver, spent 17,000 hours in 3{
years building the vehicle, made of parts from five different
trucks.
   The motor home has several remarkable amenities, including an 8
x 16 foot porch that folds under the vehicle, seven stereos with 26
speakers, three refrigerators, three television sets and a central
heating and air conditioning system. The home sleeps five.
   The Charlotte, N.C., resident said he is careful where he takes
his mobile mansion.
   ``Chicago's got too many underpasses,'' said Harrington. ``I
took a TV crew out in it one time and when the first bridge came
up, they were all screaming for dear life.''
   He said he sits up so high _ about 12 feet _ that he must
constantly peer at his speedometer because it can feel like the
home is barely moving.
   Its eight-cylinder, 325 horsepower engine allows ``Ninth
Wonder'' to travel up to 100 mph _ at 10 miles to the gallon,
Harrington said.
   ``Truckers beg me everywhere to pull over at the next stop so
they can take a look at it,'' he said.
   Harrington, who travels to fairs three months out of the year,
said he started hitting the fair circuit in 1988. This is his
second trip to Ohio's fair, which runs through Aug. 19.
   Intrigued passersby can pay $1.00 for a tour. You can't miss
Harrington. He'll be on his porch, grilling food and watching TV.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0058 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 1741EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-GreenBerets-Ammunition     08-12 0603</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Green Berets-Ammunition,0622</SECOND>
<HEAD>Soldiers Stockpiled Munitions in Thailand, Newspaper Says</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SAN FRANCISCO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Green Berets stationed in Southeast Asia
illegally stockpiled millions of dollars worth of U.S. ammunition
and explosives, and some of it may have ended up on Thailand's
black market, a newspaper reported Sunday.
   The San Francisco Examiner also said former Army Special Forces
officers tried to cover up the misuse of U.S. military hardware.
   The stockpiling of tons of bullets, grenades, mines and plastic
explosives occurred as late as last year, the newspaper said,
citing military documents and interviews with investigators and
former members of the elite units.
   ``U.S. Army Special Operations lost control of millions of
dollars of American arms and ammunition over five years,'' said
Mike Bracy, a former sergeant with the Okinawa-based 1st Battalion,
1st Special Forces.
   In two months alone, 1 million dollars worth of ordnance
``dropped off the books,'' he said.
   Bracy and another former battalion sergeant, Bob Finley, claim
they were subjected to harassment, psychiatric observation and
death threats when they tried to alert superiors to the problems,
the Examiner said.
   Finley retired. Bracy was honorably discharged last year after
the office of U.S. Rep. Barbara Boxer, D-Calif., intervened.
   Boxer said the Pentagon inspector general's office told her two
weeks ago its investigation confirmed that munitions intended for
training use were winding up on the black market, and that the
Special Forces were involved.
   The Special Forces, known as the Green Berets, are experts in
unconventional warfare and considered key to extending American
military power into foreign trouble spots. Special Forces units in
Southeast Asia are involved in training soldiers from Thailand, the
Philippines, Singapore, Korea, and Malaysia.
   The Army has denied any wrongdoing by the Special Forces.
   But an Army investigation cited by the Examiner said the 1st
Battalion, 1st Special Forces _ specifically its 80-man Bravo
Company operating in Thailand _ was ``torn by divisions, rumors and
criminal activity.''
   Battalion members are doing business on Bangkok's black market,
and there are lax controls on the main Green Beret stockpile, the
newspaper said, quoting unidentified military and civilian sources.
   Finley and other Bravo Company members said munitions were given
to Thai units, contrary to strict requirements that only the Green
Berets themselves use them.
   Lt. Col. Robert Suchke, commander of the 1st Battalion in 1988
and 1989, said during an interrogation that he didn't know what his
soldiers stored in Thailand, the Examiner said. He also said he
didn't know who controlled the stockpile or who had the key to the
biggest cache, a bunker filled with munitions on a Royal Thai Army
base, according to the paper.
   Bracy, originally assigned to an internal military investigation
of the matter, claimed high-level officers in Southeast Asia either
were involved in illicit activities or ``turned a blind eye.''
   Finley and Bracy _ who collated all the munitions requisition
forms, inventory lists and other documents _ said they took their
evidence and complaints to U.S. military authorities in Japan.
   Bracy said he was ordered last August to immediately halt any
criminal investigation and turn over information to higher-ups.
   Finley said he was ordered to burn records of Bravo Company Sgt.
Maj. Edward Gleason, who started the stockpile in 1984.
   Gleason denied any involvement in criminal activity and claimed
that the stockpile, while against the rules, was a convenience that
avoided the trouble of turning in the ammunition.
   Gleason's court-martial conviction, for threatening to kill a
superior officer, were what initially drew attention to the
battalion's activities, the Examiner said. The newspaper did not
say whether the Gleason case was related to the stockpiling claims.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0059 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 1748EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-OrangutanTrial     08-12 0352</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Orangutan Trial,0365</SECOND>
<HEAD>Animal Rights Groups Say They'll Appeal $4.2 Million Verdict</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT MACY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LAS VEGAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Animal rights activists say they will appeal a
verdict that awarded $4.2 million to a Las Vegas showman secretly
filmed striking the pet orangutans used in his act.
   ``We are appalled,'' said Ingrid Newkirk, national director of
the Washington, D.C.-based People for the Ethical Treatment of
Animals. ``I believe this ruling will be overturned.''
   Entertainer Bobby Berosini said he planned a nationwide
talk-show tour to ``expose the animal rights activists for what
they are: self-serving.''
   But an attorney for the animal rights group promised to appeal
the award handed down late Saturday afternoon by a state jury after
four days of deliberations.
   ``He'll never see a penny of that money,'' said Philip Hirschkop.
   The animal rights group was assessed $2 million in damages on
counts of invasion of privacy and defamation. Jeanne Roush, an
investigator for the group, and former Stardust employee Ottavio
Gesmundo, each was assessed $1 million in damages.
   The jury found the defendants innocent of actual malice and
declined to award punitive damages.
   Gesmundo videotaped scenes of Berosini striking his orangutans
before they went on stage for performances at the Stardust Hotel in
July 1989.
   The videotapes were circulated to animal rights groups including
the Performing Animal Welfare Society of Galt, Calif.
Representatives of those two groups took the tapes to local and
national media, including ``Entertainment Tonight.''
   The performing animal welfare group and its president, Pat
Derby, also were each assessed $100,000 in damages for defamation
and invasion of privacy.
   Berosini said he had to beat the primates with a stick because
they were spooked by dancers in his performance show. He claimed
the adverse publicity from the animal rights groups damaged his
career.
   Animal rights activists had descended on Las Vegas, picketing in
front of the Stardust and encouraging the public to pass up the
show.
   ``I was used as a pawn to make money,'' Berosini said of attacks
by the animal rights groups. ``They were using this as a means of
fund raising.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0060 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 1825EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Iraq-Kuwait-Glance     08-12 0472</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Iraq-Kuwait-Glance,0493</SECOND>
<HEAD>Persian Gulf Crisis At-A-Glance</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Iraq-Kuwait Rdp, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Here, at a glance, are the major developments Sunday in the
Iraqi invasion of Kuwait:
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   SADDAM'S STATEMENT: Saddam Hussein says he is ready to resolve
the Persian Gulf crisis if Israel withdraws from the occupied
territories and Syria pulls out its troops from Lebanon. He says
``many will be burned'' if war breaks out.
   The Iraqi president also demands the withdrawal of U.S. troops
from Saudi Arabia and the end to U.N. economic sanctions against
Iraq, which forced him to ask his people to be thrifty with meat
and clothing.
   Israel rejects Saddam's proposal as ``cheap propaganda.''
Presidential spokesman Marlin Fitzwater said the United States
``categorically rejects'' the Iraqi proposal.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   U.S. MILITARY: A U.S. airman dies in Saudi Arabia in a car
accident. He is the first American killed in the desert kingdom
since President Bush ordered the U.S. military deployment last week.
   Defense analysts say sending U.S. military forces to Saudi
Arabia will cost an estimated $300 million to $440 million a month.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   MILITARY MOVES: Ten thousand Egyptian and Moroccan troops are
joining the 50,000 U.S. soldiers moving into Saudi Arabia. Syria, a
neighbor of Iraq, has also pledged troops.
   Turkish Premier Yildirim Akbulut says he will ask Parliament for
the power to declare a state of war and send armed forces into
combat if the crisis worsens.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   FOREIGNERS IN IRAQ AND KUWAIT: A British citizen is reportedly
shot in Kuwait near the Saudi border, and scores of foreigners
return to their homelands with stories of rapes and killings by
Iraqi soldiers.
   Penelope Nabokov, the 10-year-old California girl who was
detoured by the blitzkrieg on her way to visit her mother, fled to
freedom Saturday and was on her way to meet her parents Sunday.
   An Iraqi spokesman quoted by Baghdad radio said the authorities
have been instructed to ``facilitate the travel of the Arabs and
foreign residents in Kuwait and other cities of southern Iraq.'' It
was not clear whether the spokesman meant foreigners in Kuwait
could leave the country.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   SANCTIONS: U.S. and allied warships poise to meet Iraqi tankers
coming from the Persian Gulf, Red Sea or Mediterranean Sea. Iraq is
dependent on oil exports to buy food and supplies for its 17
million people.
   Secretary of State James Baker says he doesn't believe nations
will ignore the economic sanctions against Iraq because ``the
independence of the industrialized world is at stake.''
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   ANTI-U.S. DEMONSTRATIONS: About 10,000 Palestinians demonstrate
in a refugee camp in southern Lebanon in support of Iraq. Some
chant ``Death to America!'' A PLO official says 500 youths are
volunteering to fight with Iraq against a possible American attack.
   Another pro-Iraqi demonstration is reported in Jordan. In
Bangladesh, hundreds rally against the Iraqi invasion of Kuwait.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0061 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 1808EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-WeatherpageWeather     08-12 0285</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Weatherpage Weather,0294</SECOND>
<HEAD>Showers, Thunderstorms Across Central U.S.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Showers and thunderstorms struck across the nation's midsection
Sunday, dumping heavy rain on Nebraska and Iowa, and temperatures
dipped to record lows in four Florida cities.
   The storms scattered along and ahead of a stationary front
curving through the central United States extended from the Texas
Panhandle through Missouri and southern Iowa to Lake Erie.
   Showers and thunderstorms also fell over Arkansas, isolated
storms dotted the Gulf Coast and the southern Atlantic Coast and
numerous showers and thunderstorms dampened extreme southern
Florida. Dry weather prevailed across the rest of the nation.
   The storms produced locally heavy morning rains in eastern
Nebraska and southwestern Iowa. More than 5 inches of rain has
fallen in Randolph and south of Red Oak in southwestern Iowa.
   Streets were flooded in Kearney and Lincoln, Neb., and the
National Weather Service issued a flash flood advisory for part of
southeast Nebraska.
   Heavier rainfall for the six hours ending at 2 p.m. EDT included
2.3 inches in Lincoln, Neb., and 1.27 inches in Lancaster, Pa.
   The temperature was 66 degrees in Hollywood, Fla., breaking the
low-temperature record for the date of 69 set in 1977. Other
Florida cities were record lows were set or tied were Melbourne (68
degrees, 70 in 1989); Miami (73, tie 1963); and West Palm Beach
(70, tie 1984).
   The nation's cold spot Sunday morning was International Falls,
Minn., where the temperature dropped to a record 39 degrees,
breaking the old record of 40 degrees set in 1951.
   Temperatures were in the relatively balmy 60s in Nome, Alaska,
early Sunday, for a record-tying 24 straight days the high there
has been 60 degrees or above.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0062 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 1836EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-TropicalWeather     08-12 0118</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Tropical Weather,0120</SECOND>
<HEAD>Season's Seventh Depression Washes Out</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The hurricane season's seventh tropical depression
lost its center and degenerated into a tropical wave far off in the
eastern Atlantic Sunday, a forecaster said.
   At 6 p.m. EDT, satellite pictures showed the remnants of the
depression were centered near 8 degrees north latitude and 45
degrees west longitude, or about 1,100 miles east-southeast of
Trinidad.
   The wave still had top sustained winds of 30 mph Sunday evening,
but they were expected to decrease and no further updates were
planned, said Hal Gerrish, a hurricane specialist at the National
Hurricane Center in suburban Coral Gables.
   The Atlantic hurricane season runs from June 1 to November 30.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0063 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 1839EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Germany-Wall     08-12 0622</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Germany-Wall,0639</SECOND>
<HEAD>East German Leader Blames Wall For Deepening German Divisions</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DEBORAH G. SEWARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WEST BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   East Germany's prime minister, preparing to
mark the 29th anniversary the Berlin Wall's construction, said
Sunday it has created German divisions that even unification will
not easily bridge.
   Prime Minister Lothar de Maiziere made his remarks in a
statement released by the official ADN news agency on the eve of
the annniversary of the Wall _ once a notorious Cold War symbol but
now a crumbling relic in an era of reduced East-West tensions.
   De Maiziere said ``the joy over the fall of the Wall should not
allow forgetting the lasting consequences of the division'' of
Germany.
   ``The wall strengthened the distinct developments in both German
states,'' de Maiziere said. ``State unity of Germany will not
immediately lift differences in peoples' thinking and acting.''
   De Maiziere warned his countrymen that ``the rapid disappearance
of the Wall should not lead to expectations that an economic
upswing could occur just as quickly.''
   On Aug. 13, 1961, East German military and paramilitary units
suddenly began laying the foundations for what was to become the
Berlin Wall _ a barrier of concrete, steel and barbed wire dividing
East and West Berlin.
   Communist authorities said the wall was necessary to preserve
East Germany from Western subversion and prevent a mass exodus of
skilled and professional workers to the West.
   More than 2.5 million East Germans had fled to the West from
1949 until the Wall went up. The barrier _ watched over by armed
guards with ``shoot to kill'' orders _ reduced that flow to a
trickle. More than 200 East Germans were killed trying to escape to
the West across the barrier that snaked through Berlin and along
the border with West Germany.
   On Nov. 9, 1989, the reform Communists who ousted hard-liner
Erich Honecker opened the Wall in a last-ditch effort to retain
power. They had hoped to stem a flood of East Germans to West
Germany that had reached more than 200,000.
   By the end of this year, East and West Germany plan to merge to
form one country.
   East Germans enjoyed the most prosperous economy in the Soviet
bloc, but now face a major challenge in trying to catch up with the
West German economic powerhouse. The East German economy is reeling
_ with growing unemployment and factory closings _ as it plunges
into capitalism after 40 years of Communism.
   Richard Schroeder, the Social Democratic caucus leader in the
East German Parliament, said ``the Wall concealed and postponed the
economic ruin'' of East Germany, in a statement released by ADN.
   He said the enthusiasm that greeted the opening of the Wall in
November has disappeared because East Germany has plunged into a
``deep crisis'' following its July 1 economic union with West
Germany.
   The East German press, once forced to praise the country's
Communist leaders for erecting the Wall, joined the new
democratically elected leaders in criticizing the former barrier.
   The Berliner Zeitung said the Wall ``in the long run failed to
bring about'' the economic improvement the former Communist leaders
had promised after building it.
   Numerous ceremonies were planned for Monday in both East and
West Berlin along the 100-mile strip where the Wall once divided
the former German capital.
   Most of the Wall has been removed from the central part of the
city, and the outer ring on the edge of the city is expected to be
gone by 1991.
   On Monday night, the Rolling Stones will perform at an outdoor
stadium in East Berlin. The Japanese symphony orchestra Saito
Kinen, conducted by Seiji Ozawa, will also give what is being
billed as ``The Berlin Wall Memorial Concert.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0064 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 1844EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BRF--IraqiOil     08-12 0202</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Iraqi Oil,0207</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tanker Carrying Iraqi Oil To Dock In New Jersey</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto PX2</HEAD>
<DATELINE>GREENWICH TOWNSHIP, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A tanker loaded with nearly 1
million barrels of Iraqi oil arrived Sunday, but the shipment did
not fall under President Bush's embargo on Iraqi oil, the Coast
Guard said.
   ``It was all bought before the thing started,'' said Coast Guard
Lt.j.g. Jonathan Burton. The shipment was the the first to arrive
in the area since the embargo went into effect Aug. 2.
   The tanker Nautica arrived at Mobil Oil Corp.'s Paulsboro
Refinery in this port across the Delaware River from Philadelphia.
   The Bahamian-registered tanker left Turkey on July 25, more than
a week before Iraq's Aug. 2 invasion of Kuwait, said refinery
spokeswoman Ida Walker. Bush imposed the embargo hours after the
attack.
   Mobil requested instructions from the Treasury Department, which
told the oil company to accept the oil and deposit the payment due
Iraq into a frozen account, Ms. Walker said. She did not know how
much the shipment cost or how much money Mobil was to deposit in
the account.
   Mobil plans to process the crude into a lubricating oil commonly
used in cars and ships, Ms. Walker said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0065 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 1954EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Drugs-Editorial     08-12 0229</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Drugs-Editorial,0237</SECOND>
<HEAD>San Francisco Examiner Editorial Calls for Legalizing Drugs</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SAN FRANCISCO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The San Francisco Examiner, in one of the
first pro-legalization editorials by a big-city newspaper, said
Sunday that the sale and use of drugs should be made legal in the
United States.
   An editorial called the federal war against drugs ``a colossal
waste of effort, money and human resources.''
   ``All anti-drug laws should be repealed,'' it said. ``The war on
drugs should be called off. Just declare victory, play `76
Trombones' and march out. It always gets applause.''
   The federal government last week finished a much-publicized
sweep against marijuana plantations in Humboldt County, about 200
miles north of San Francisco, the first time army troops were used
against drugs in the United States.
   The operation was termed a success by federal officials, the
Examiner noted, although the 1,400 marijuana plants destroyed was
``not enough to put a dent in the supply of marijuana.''
   ``Any way you slice it, there is no denying that this
politician-declared war has been just about effective as the war on
poverty, the war on crime and the war on cancer put together, which
is to say, a complete defeat,'' the editorial said.
   ``The time has come to legalize the sale and use of drugs. Treat
them all like alcohol, which is legal though its sale is subject to
controls.''
 
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0066 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 1956EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Obit-LittleSmokey     08-12 0296</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Little Smokey,300</SECOND>
<HEAD>Smokey II Dies of Cancer</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By IAN WAGREICH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   America's most recent spokesbear for the
prevention of forest fires died of liver cancer in his pen at the
National Zoo, veterinarians determined Sunday.
   The 20-year-old black bear called Smokey II, also known as
Little Smokey, began shaking late Saturday and could not keep his
balance, prompting his keeper to summon veterinarians, said zoo
spokesman Robert Hoage.
   Doctors injected steroids via a blowgun late Saturday, but Hoage
said they had no effect on the bear's condition. Because he was
wild, keepers and veterinarians could not get close enough to
examine him.
   A necropsy, the animal equivalent of an autopsy, was performed
at the zoo Sunday, revealing advanced liver cancer, the spokesman
said.
   Hoage said his death could not be termed premature since black
bears live only to their mid-twenties. The original Smokey the Bear
was 26 when he died in 1976.
   The chocolate brown-colored Smokey II came to the National Zoo
in Northwest D.C. from the Lincoln National Forest in New Mexico.
He was the only breed of its kind to be housed by the zoo.
   Black bears are known to exist in one of four colors; black,
dark brown, cinnamon light brown and silver grey.
   Little Smokey stood about 5-feet-6-inches tall and weighed about
200 to 250 pounds, Hoage said. He was given to the zoo in 1971 by
the New Mexico Department of Game and Fish and was only
1{-years-old at the time.
   The original Smokey also came from the Lincoln National Forest,
although their immediate families were not related.
   Smokey I was flown back to New Mexico after his death and Hoage
said officials were not sure where Little Smokey would be laid to
rest.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0067 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 2000EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-BargeSpill     08-12 0349</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Barge Spill,0357</SECOND>
<HEAD>Barge Buckles, Spilling At Least 20,000 Gallons into Ship Channel</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HOUSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A barge being loaded with heavy fuel oil at an
Arco Petrochemical dock buckled Sunday, spewing at least 20,000
gallons of oil into the Houston Ship Channel, Coast Guard officials
said.
   ``It's unusual in the way that it happened,'' said Coast Guard
Senior Chief Dale Eichmann. ``It was just sitting there at the dock
and apparently, it just started buckling in half. The metal deck
folded down on top of it and cracked it down the middle.''
   No. 6 fuel oil spilled from two center tanks as a crease cut
across the barge at the dock in southeast Houston.
   Cleanup crews from Arco and Lyondell Petrochemical Co. were able
to string containment booms around the area after the 10 a.m.
accident, Eichmann said, and a cleanup company later joined the
effort. Lyondell is a former division of Atlantic Richfield Co.
   ``We got a primary boom out there pretty quick,'' Eichmann said.
``Then we set up two containment booms stretched across the turning
basin and stuck some absorbent pads in the cracks (of the barge)
and that shut down the discharge pretty well.''
   The barge had been loaded with 630,000 gallons of oil, Eichmann
said. It had a capacity of 840,000 gallons.
   David Harpole of the Lyondell salvage crew said another barge
was located adjacent to the ruptured one, helping to cut down the
spread of the oil. A third barge was brought to the area to
transfer remaining oil from the ruptured vessel, he said.
   The Houston Ship Channel remains open, but Coast Guard officials
warned ships in the area to slow down.
   The Coast Guard on Friday completed a two-week cleanup of a
700,000-gallon oil spill that occurred July 28 when a Greek tanker
collided with two barges under tow in the Houston Ship Channel.
   Earlier this year, the Norweigan tanker Mega Borg spilled 3.9
million gallons of Angolan crude into the Gulf of Mexico off
Galveston when an explosion ripped through the vessel, killing four
crewmembers and injuring 17 others.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0068 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 2010EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-India-Caste     08-12 0444</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-India-Caste,0456</SECOND>
<HEAD>Students Riot Over Proposed Caste Quota System for Government Jobs</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ARTHUR MAX</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW DELHI, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A government plan to set aside more
government jobs for low caste Indians has sparked protests against
reverse discrimination by other students.
   Sunday newspapers reported that police arrested scores of
students and took up protective positions at key government
buildings after four days of protests in the eastern state of Bihar.
   Students sabotaged train engines, burned wagons and disrupted
rail traffic in Bihar, the nation's poorest state, the newspapers
said. They also stoned cars, set fire to empty buses and a post
office, and torched several government cars.
   In the capital, Delhi University was virtually emptied by a
student boycott. On Friday, police used tear gas and bamboo clubs
to break up a student demonstration near the government and
Parliament complex.
   The trouble began when Prime Minister V.P. Singh announced in
Parliament on Thursday that a further 27 percent of federal jobs
would be reserved for people from ``socially and educationally
backward classes.''
   That would be in addition to an existing quota of 22 percent for
low caste Hindus and tribes in public service and higher education
jobs, according to a list drawn up after India became independent
in 1947 and included in the Constitution. The quota has never been
filled completely.
   If the government's plan is carried out, 49 percent of
government jobs will be set aside for low castes, and 51 percent
will be awarded purely on merit.
   Singh said he was endorsing a 10-year-old report by an official
commission which recommended expanding the quota for government
jobs for people from disadvantaged classes, defined by their
income, social position and education.
   According to the Sunday Observer newspaper, the disadvantaged
castes identified by the commission comprise 43.7 percent of the
population, or about 385 million people.
   In India's highly structured society, hundreds of castes and
subcastes have been delineated in a strict hierarchy by thousands
of years of Hindu tradition.
   Modern India, an avowedly secular nation whose population is 82
percent Hindu, is pledged to discard the caste system and build an
egalitarian state.
   But the caste system persists, particularly in rural areas,
dictating rules of behavior, occupation and association.
   Singh said implementing the commission's report was ``a
momentous decision for social justice.'' His announcement was
greeted by congratulatory thumping on tables from all sides of the
legislature.
   Critics in the Indian press accused Singh of engaging in a
grandstand populist ploy aimed at boosting support for his party.
Singh's 8-month-old coalition government has been wracked by
infighting, leading some analysts to predict elections as early as
next year.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0069 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 2030EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-US-IraqRdp 2ndLd-Writethru a0775 08-12 1161</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-US-Iraq Rdp, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0775,1,200</SECOND>
<HEAD>Baker Reiterates U.S. Resolve to Block Oil Shipments From Iraq</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: Inserts grafs 9-12, ``Baker was asked xxx to inlude
additional from Baker and Scowcroft on food embargo; edits grafs
30-31 to delete first reference to Scowcroft, now higher</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By LAWRENCE L. KNUTSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The United States, citing the legal authority
of United Nations sanctions, will stop oil shipments from leaving
Iraq and block food and other supplies from entering the country,
the government said Sunday.
   Asked during a golf outing in Maine whether the embargo would
include food, President Bush replied: ``Just watch. Everything.''
   Questioned later on whether a blockade would be considered an
act of war, the president said, ``I consider interdiction of
shipping to be in accord with the Chapter VII action taken by the
United Nations. No point getting into all these semantics.
   ``The main thing,'' said Bush, ``is to stop the oil from coming
out of there and that is what we're going to do.''
   Earlier Sunday, both Secretary of State James A. Baker III and
White House spokesman Marlin Fitzwater had underscored the extent
of the U.S. determination to squeeze Iraq economically.
   The United States will do ``whatever is necessary'' to enforce
the sanctions, Fitzwater said in a written statement issued on
behalf of the president.
   Although neither Fitzwater nor Baker would be specific about any
U.S. action, the secretary of state said the U.S. response would
begin ``almost immediately.''
   Kuwait's government-in-exile asked the world community to
enforce the U.N. sanctions and Baker said that gave the United
States legal authority to halt any Iraqi oil exports.
   Baker was asked by reporters later whether the United States was
considering blocking shipments of goods other than oil to Iraq.
   ``The request that's been received from the legitimate
government of Kuwait is that we, we and the other countries,
countries that support the U.N. resolution, do what we can to
implement these U.N. sanctions,'' said Baker. ``Now those sanctions
go beyond just oil.''
   On the CBS television show ``Face the Nation,'' national
security adviser Gen. Brent Scowcroft was asked about the prospect
of sanctions eventually resulting in ``starving people in Kuwait.''
   ``Well, we'll deal with that when we get to that point,'' said
Scowcroft.
   ``The president has decided that the United States will do
whatever is necessary to see that relevant UN sanctions are
enforced,'' Fitzwater said from Kennebunkport, Me., where Bush is
vacationing. ``The United States will coordinate its efforts with
the governments of other nations to whom the Kuwaiti government has
made similar requests.''
   Baker characterized the contemplated action as an
``interdiction'' rather than a blockade, which in diplomatic
parlance could be considered an act of war.
   Baker, who spoke on the ABC television program ``This Week With
David Brinkley,'' said Iraq now has ``a significant presence'' in
southern Kuwait consisting of about 120,000 troops in nine
divisions.
   ``There's not much to prevent him, if he should decide to do so,
from launching offensive operations from there,'' Baker said.
   But the commander of the U.S. military effort in Saudi Arabia
said Sunday that U.S. forces could repel an attack, even though
they are currently outnumbered on the ground. American air and
naval power could neutralize any Iraqi attack, he said.
   ``We have built up a great deal of force over there now ... and
if they do make an attack they are going to pay a price for it,''
Gen. H. Norman Schwarzkopf said at United States Central Command
headquarters in Florida before leaving for Saudi Arabia.
   The United States, France and Britain have sent ships to the
Persian Gulf region in an effort to force Iraq out of Kuwait and to
defend strategic, oil-rich Saudi Arabia from possible Iraqi attack.
The United States also has committed an estimated 50,000 ground
troops to the operation.
   Egypt and Morocco also have sent troops to Saudi Arabia to
counter Iraqi forces massed along the border in Kuwait.
   Baker would not comment specifically about what the United
States intends to do if an Iraqi tanker now off the coast of Saudi
Arabia moves to claim Iraqi oil shipped by pipeline across Saudi
Arabia.
   In Baghdad, Iraqi President Saddam Hussein warned that ``many
will be burned'' if war breaks out in the Middle East. He linked
any possible Iraqi withdrawal from Kuwait to an Israeli surrender
of the Arab-claimed territories it occupies.
   Hussein also demanded the withdrawal of U.S. and other forces
from Saudi Arabia and an end to international economic sanctions
against his nation.
   Saddam said that if the international community wants foreign
forces kept in the region, they should be replaced by Arab forces
``with the (U.N.) Security Council making all the arrangements'' on
which nationalities should be involved.
   In Maine, Bush said: ``I didn't see anything ... pleasing in
there (Saddam's statement) at all. None. Nothing.''
   Asked whether he would welcome Iran's participation in the
effort against Iraq, Bush said, ``Anybody to help enforce those
sanctions, that's who we want.''
   Fitzwater said the United States ``categorically rejects''
Saddam's demands and repeated U.S. and UN calls for the immediate
withdrawal of Iraqi forces from Kuwait.
   Scowcroft said the United States does not intend to overthrow
Saddam but rather to try to ``affect his behavior.''
   He declined to comment on reported U.S. covert action against
Saddam's government.
   On another subject, Baker said he hopes world pressure on
Baghdad will soon force Iraq to release some 3,500 Americans
detained in Kuwait and Iraq. Americans
   ``We hope they will be allowed to come out soon,'' he said.
``The truth of the matter is that (Iraq) has restricted the right
of all foreign nationals to leave. ... This runs against all
international behavior norms.''
   Abdul Amir al-Anbari, the Iraqi ambassador to the United
Nations, characterized the resolution adopted by last week's Arab
summit in Cairo to condemn Iraq as having ``doubtful validity.'' He
predicted that any Arab force sent to protect Saudi Arabia will be
``nominal.''
   And President Turgut Ozal of Turkey said he is confident his
nation will enjoy the support of the NATO alliance if a shooting
war breaks out with its neighbor, Iraq.
   ``We have a strong army, we can defend ourselves,'' he said.
   Both the Iraqi president and the Turkish president commented
while appearing on ABC television's Brinkley program.
   Meanwhile, the Pentagon released details of the first American
killed in the desert kingdom since Bush ordered the U.S. military
deployment last week.
   The Pentagon identified the dead man as Air Force Staff Sgt.
John Campisi. The 30-year-old aircraft maintenance technician was
from Covina, Calif., and was assigned to Offutt Air Force Base in
Nebraska.
   Pentagon sources who spoke on condition of not being identified
by name said a preliminary investigation indicated Campisi was hit
by a truck on a darkened runway. The sources said Campisi may have
been wearing protective ear covering, inhibiting his ability to
hear the oncoming truck. Further details were not available.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0070 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 2043EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Bush 3rdLd-Writethru a0760 08-12 0807</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bush, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0760,790</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush Rejects Iraqi Conditions, Forms Ties With Syria</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: Inserts grafs 10-12, ``Later in the xxx to include additional
Bush quotes, which also are in AM-US-Iraq Rdp</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By TERENCE HUNT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP White House Correspondent</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>KENNEBUNKPORT, Maine (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush on Sunday firmly
rejected conditions set by Saddam Hussein for ending the Persian
Gulf crisis and put aside differences with Syria long enough to
cement an alliance against Baghdad.
   The White House reacted swiftly to Saddam's demand that Israel
surrender the occupied territories as a partial price for the
withdrawal of Iraqi forces from Kuwait. Saddam also demanded an end
to U.N. economic sanctions against Iraq and the pullout of U.S.
troops in Saudi Arabia.
   White House press secretary Marlin Fitzwater, referring to
Saddam's conditions, said, ``the United States categorically
rejects them.''
   He said, ``These latest conditions and threats are another
attempt at distracting from Iraq's isolation and at imposing a new
status quo.''
   Bush said he was determined that global economic sanctions
against Iraq will choke off its oil exports. The White House cited
a letter from the emir of Kuwait as the legal basis for U.S.
efforts to insure that sanctions ``are immediately and effectively
implemented.''
   While avoiding use of the word ``blockade,'' Bush said the
U.N.-approved embargo ``gave us broad authority, working in
conjunction with others, to do whatever is necessary to see no oil
goes out.''
   In Washington, Secretary of State James A. Baker III said the
United States would intercept Iraqi oil shipments. ``Let's not use
the word blockade,'' Baker said, adding that he preferred the word
``interdiction.''
   Bush, during a golf outing, was asked by reporters whether the
embargo would include food. He replied: ``Just watch. Everything.''
   Asked if he was pleased that Saddam was talking about a
negotiated settlement, even if the terms were unacceptable, Bush
said crisply: ``I didn't see anything to be pleasing in there at
all. None. Nothing.''
   Later in the afternoon, Bush was asked whether he regarded a
blockade as an act of war.
   ``I consider interdiction of shipping to be in accord with the
Chapter VII action taken by the United Nations,'' he said. ``No
point getting into all these semantics. The main thing is to stop
the oil from coming out of there and that is what we're going to
do.''
   Asked whether he would welcome Iran's participation, ``Anybody
to help enforce those sanctions, that's who we want.''
   At his oceanside home, the vacationing Bush pressed ahead with
his telephone diplomacy to isolate Saddam, whose troops invaded
Kuwait on Aug. 2 and now threaten the oil fields of Saudi Arabia.
   Bush, an early riser, called Syrian President Hafez Assad at 6
a.m. Later, the president told reporters, ``I'm very pleased that
we're looking at this in the same way.''
   Likewise, he said Assad declared that he was ``pleased to be
together on this.'' Since arriving here Friday, Bush also has
called Egyptian President Hosni Mubarak, King Fahd of Saudi Arabia
and the emirs of Bahrain and Qatar.
   The United States says Syria continues to support terrorism, and
the two differ sharply over Israel, but in this instance find
themselves solidly united against Iraq. Sensing an opportunity to
topple its longtime foe, Syria went along with the Arab League vote
to send troops to the Persian Gulf as part of an Arab force against
Saddam.
   Bush has committed an estimated 50,000 troops to Saudi Arabia to
face Iraqi forces massed along that country's border with Kuwait.
   Fitzwater, in a written statement, said, ``We join the rest of
the UN Security Council in unanimously calling for the immediate,
complete and unconditional withdrawal of Iraqi forces from Kuwait
and the restoration of Kuwait's legitimate government.''
   He said that Bush had received a letter from Sheikh Jaber
Alahmad Al-Sabah, the emir of Kuwait who fled his country as it was
invaded, asking the United States to enforce sanctions against Iraq
and Kuwait.
   ``In view of the emir's request,'' Fitzwater said, ``the
president has decided that the United States will do whatever is
necessary to see that relevant UN sanctions are enforced.''
   He said the United States would coordinate its efforts with
other nations that have received similar requests from the emir.
   While tracking developments in the tense Persian Gulf, Bush
found time to go boating in foggy Atlantic waters and to go jogging
back and forth for 20 minutes on an undeveloped road off Ocean
Avenue.
   After two days of solid rain, the weather was mostly sunny and
warm. Bush planned an afternoon golf match.
   Accompanied by his wife, Barbara, and nine grandchildren, as
well as his son Neil and other relatives, Bush worshipped at St.
Ann's Episcopal Church.
   A well-wisher called out, ``Doing a good job, Mr. President.''
Bush turned as he walked to the church and gave a thumbs-up signal.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0071 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 2052EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-StrandedAmericans     08-12 0751</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Stranded Americans,0779</SECOND>
<HEAD>Americans Await Word of Loved Ones Held in Iraq, Kuwait</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Iraq-Foreigners, Bjt</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto XCLA1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JONATHAN W. OATIS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   A Milwaukee man made a videotaped plea to Iraqi President Saddam
Hussein to release his wife and daughter, as relatives of Americans
stranded in Iraq and Kuwait awaited word of loved ones Sunday from
the State Department.
   ``I didn't sleep again last night,'' said Marjorie Walterscheid
of Jacksboro, Texas, whose husband, Rainard, was among a group of
Americans being held in hotels in the Iraqi capital, Baghdad.
   Mrs. Walterscheid said she was worried because her husband, who
works for Santa Fe Drilling Co., had not responded to a message she
sent Saturday via the State Department.
   There are an estimated 400 Americans in Iraq and 3,000 in
Kuwait, which Iraq invaded Aug. 2, according to the State
Department. Iraq is not permitting most foreigners to leave either
country.
   Mrs. Walterscheid received word Saturday about her husband and
the other Americans from Michael Saba of Champaign, Ill., a
businessman who was at the hotel and got out of Iraq.
   ``They can come down and swim and they're eating in the finest
restaurant at the hotel, but they can't leave,'' she said.
   Madhavarao Murikipudi, a Milwaukee foundry superintendent and
native of India, made the videotaped plea in hopes of securing the
release of his 40-year-old wife, Prabhavathi, and his 9-year-old
daughter, Sylaja.
   ``All I said was, `Mr. President Saddam Hussein, my name is
Madhavarao Murikipudi,''' said Murikipudi, 47. ``I said my wife and
daughter were on their way to India when they were stranded in
Kuwait.
   ``I had to try,'' he said. ``I hope it gets to him.''
   Murikipudi's wife and daughter were bound for India to visit
relatives when their British Airways flight made a scheduled stop
in Kuwait as Iraqi soldiers were crossing the border. They were
among 39 Americans taken off the plane.
   The State Department has said consular officials have visited
the Murikipudis in Baghdad and they are well.
   A copy of the tape was delivered Frdiay to the State Department
by Rep. Gerald Kleczka, D-Wis., and another was to be delivered to
the Iraqi Embassy in Washington on Monday, Kleczka said in a
statement.
   The congressman said the Iraqi ambassador had agreed to review
the tape and pass the information along to officials in Iraq.
   Donnita Cole of Odessa, Texas, said she still didn't know the
whereabouts of her husband, John Henry Cole, an OGE Drilling Co.
employee last seen Aug. 3 in front of the couple's apartment in a
Kuwaiti village.
   The U.S. Embassy said Cole, 50, was fine Monday, but didn't say
where he was, Mrs. Cole said.
   ``We're just sitting here with absolutely no knowledge, building
all these scenarios in our heads,'' she said. ``That's the hard
part of waiting.''
   That wasn't her only worry. Mrs. Cole has a son in the military
whose unit has been placed on standby to go to Saudi Arabia.
   ``And he told me not to do anything to stop him from going,''
she said, declining to say where he was assigned. ``He says he
wants to go because his father is there, and I don't want him to go
_ because his father is there.''
   In Clarksville, Tenn., members of the 101st Airborne Divison,
some dressed in camouflage, attended a church service Sunday where
they were urged to ``pray for our country like we've never prayed
before.''
   The 101st, based at Fort Campbell, Ky., just across the state
line from Clarksville, had learned the day before that the entire
division would be going to the Mideast.
   About 300 people turned out at the First Assembly of God church,
where the Rev. Billy R. Jones urged them to pray for a quick end to
the conflict begun by Saddam.
   ``I'm really praying for this man that God will just put him
down without bloodshed,'' Jones said. ``I don't know what the
outcome is going to be in the Middle East, but I know one thing. I
know our God is in control.''
   Many in the congregation wept.
   But in the Detroit suburb of Farmington Hills, Patricia Heath
said she was encouraged by the news that Penelope Nabokov, 10, and
10 other Americans had been released Saturday.
   Heath's brother, Kevin Bazner, 36, was aboard the British
Airways airliner seized in Kuwait, along with his wife Dawn,
6-month-old son David and daughter Elizabeth, 6.
   Penelope and the others were released Saturday, but the Bazners
remained behind.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0072 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 2106EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ServicemanKilled 3rdLd-Writethru a0769 08-12 0332</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Serviceman Killed, 3rd Ld - Writethru, a0769,0337</SECOND>
<HEAD>PRECEDE Washington</HEAD>
<HEAD>Accident Claims Life of California Serviceman in Saudi Arabia</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: UPDATES throuhout with interview with slain serviceman's
parents; ADDS byline; No pickup</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By LOUINN LOTA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A career military man from California died
Sunday in an accident during troop preparation in Saudi Arabia,
becoming the first American casualty of the military reaction to
Iraq's invasion of Kuwait, the Pentagon said.
   John Campisi, a U.S. Air Force staff sergeant, was hit by a
truck on a darkened runway, according to the Pentagon.
   Campisi, 30, was an aircraft maintenance technician from Covina,
Calif. He was assigned to Offutt Air Force Base in Nebraska and had
been in the military since he was 18, his parents said.
   Campisi left a wife and four children, two girls and two boys,
his parents said.
   ``The main thing is that he was a wonderful father,'' said
Campisi's mother, Marge Campisi, her voice choked with emotion in a
telephone interview. ``He was involved in everything with those
kids _ scout leader, religious classes. He always made time for his
family.''
   Campisi's' father, Salvatore Campisi, described his son as
having ``the patience of Job.''
   ``It will be very hard on those children,'' the elder Campisi
said.
   John Campisi grew up in West Covina, a Los Angeles County suburb
in the San Gabriel Valley about 20 miles east of downtown.
   He attended St. Christopher's School, a Catholic elementary
school, and Edgewood High School, a public school. The elder
Campisi said his son's favorite sports then were baseball and
wrestling.
   Campisi is also survived by a sister and three brothers. One of
the brothers is a naval chief petty officer and another recently
enlisted in the Navy, Campisi's mother said.
   ``One of them just got back last week or he would have gone
too,'' she said.
   Pentagon sources said Campisi may have been wearing protective
ear wear, impeding his ability to hear the oncoming vehicle.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0073 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 2130EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Iraq-Penelope     08-12 0377</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Iraq-Penelope,0387</SECOND>
<HEAD>American Girl Reunited with Parents after Escape from Baghdad</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A 10-year-old American girl who escaped across the
desert after being stranded by the Iraqi invasion of Kuwait was
reunited with her parents Sunday, and calmly recounted some scary
moments in her ordeal.
   Penelope Nabokov, detained in hotels in Kuwait and then Baghdad,
reached freedom in Jordan on Saturday, and finally rejoined her
parents, Peter and Isabelle, in Paris on Sunday.
   At a Paris news conference, the girl _ a frequent solo flier on
visits to her anthropologist parents _ calmly recounted the moment
she knew she might be in danger:
   ``I realized I was trapped in a war zone when we were moved to
the airport hotel ... from my window we could see all the troops
going into the airport grounds and runways, and we could see lots
of tanks and men with arms.''
   Thousands of Americans and other foreigners were trapped in Iraq
and Kuwait by the Aug. 2 invasion. But the plight of Penelope, from
the Oakland, Calif., suburb of Albany, captured the most public
attention.
   She was flying unaccompanied from France to India, where her
mother was doing research. The British Airways flight had a
stopover in Kuwait, where the passengers were taken into custody by
Iraqi soldiers.
   She and some of the other passengers later were taken to Baghdad
and held in a hotel with a number of Americans, amid speculation
Iraqi leader Saddam Hussein intended to hold Americans hostage. The
U.S. Embassy persuaded the Iraqis to release the girl to Embassy
custody, but the others were kept in the hotel, and all foreigners
were told they couldn't leave Iraq.
   But Penelope, with 10 other Americans in several cars, made a
grueling 72-hour, 660-mile drive to Iraq's border with Jordan,
crossing to freedom at the Jordanian border outpost of Ruweishid on
Saturday.
   The scariest moments, she said in press conference remarks
reported by NBC news, were caused by her fellow travelers'
reactions. Asked when she was frightened most, she said
matter-of-factly:
   ``On the third day, 'cause the (airline) hostesses were starting
to freak out too, and they were getting scared, and so that got me
even more scared. That's when I got hysterical and started crying.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0074 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 2134EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Germany-Capital     08-12 0412</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Germany-Capital,0425</SECOND>
<HEAD>Finance Minister Says Germany Can't Afford to Move Government</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MAUD S. BEELMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BONN, West Germany (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Finance Minister Theo Waigel said
Sunday that a united Germany cannot afford to move its seat of
government from Bonn to Berlin.
   ``I need, at the moment, every mark for the people, for
investments and not for showcase building,'' Waigel said on the
West German television program ``Bonn Direct.''
   He also estimated that a supplementary budget to keep East
Germany afloat the rest of this year would probably need to be
``something over 10 billion marks (about $6 billion).''
   West Germany has already budgeted nearly $16 billion for this
year to cover East Germany's budget deficit.
   East Germany's economic situation grows more dire with each day
as it struggles to shift from 40 years of Communism to a capitalist
economy. The two Germanys merged their economies and the powerful
West German mark became the official currency of both states on
July 1.
   More than 270,000 East Germans are out of work as businesses and
factories fall to the rigors of capitalism and competition with
West German producers. Some experts have predicted up to 3 million
of East Germany's 8 million workforce could ultimately lose their
jobs.
   All-German elections are planned for Dec. 2, but there are
increasing calls for East Germany to exercise a provision of the
West German Constitution for an immediate merger.
   Proponents of that idea say it is the only hope to control East
Germany's economic downward spiral.
   Waigel said it is necessary to differentiate between the capital
and seat of government in a united Germany, according to a
transcript of the program on the West German network ZDF.
   He said moving the government from the West German capital Bonn
to Berlin, Germany's old capital, cannot be financed ``in the
coming years.'' West Germany had not built so many government
buildings in Bonn just to abandon them, he said.
   East and West German negotiators have agreed Berlin will be the
capital of a united nation. But they left open the question of
whether the government would be located there.
   Their agreement must still be ratified by both German
parliaments.
   Waigel, leader of the conservative Christian Social Union, the
Bavarian sister party of Chancellor Helmut Kohl's Christian
Democrats, called the capital fight ``completely superfluous.''
   Klaus Rauen, Bonn's deputy city manager, estimates it would cost
at least $31 billion to relocate government offices and employees
to Berlin.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0075 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 2149EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-CubanRegistry     08-12 0416</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Cuban Registry,0427</SECOND>
<HEAD>Registry of Lost Properties Drawing Entries, Criticisms</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A registry of private Cuban properties seized by
the revolution of Fidel Castro is being compiled in Miami by exiles
eager to return home and recoup their losses if Castro is toppled.
   Hundreds of exiles from as far away as Italy are signing on to
list the farms, homes and businesses they lost to the communist
revolution.
   Others are opposed to the idea of a registry, saying Castro's
die-hard government is even less likely to implement reforms if he
can cite the registry as proof exiles are bent on revenge and
retribution.
   The Expropriated Cuban Properties Registry is a private venture
by Metro-Dade Commissioner Barry Schreiber and the University of
Miami's Research Institute for Cuban Studies. The project was begun
last week.
   ``I think that a number of Cubans, once the system changes, will
want to make demands on their property,'' said Miami professor
Jaime Suchlicki, who is collaborating on the project. ``Once the
regime changes, they're going to say, `I had a house there. I had a
business there. Can I get something out of it.'''
   Registry entries must list the address of the property, say how
it was acquired, how and when it was lost, and give its estimated
value at the time. Applicants must include supporting documents,
such as deeds or wills or affidavits by neighbors or friends who
knew of the property.
   A listing costs $150, with $15 going to the university and the
rest to Schreiber to cover clerical, printing costs and other
expenses.
   The one-page application states that a listing provides no
guarantee that the claim is valid.
   But Schreiber and Suchlicki say the registry will be useful,
especially if Castro falls and Cuba opens up. ``The most likely
scenario is some sort of settlement whereby the Cuban and U.S.
government will sit down and work out a long-term repayment of
these properties,'' said the professor.
   Tony Costa, a director of the Cuban American National
Foundation, which has spoken against the retrieval of nationalized
properties, said the registry will be used by the Castro government
to disparage exiles.
   ``If the goal is to help Cubans, it is negative,'' Costa said.
``The exiles' interest is not to recover properties, but for the
regime to fall.''
   Alberto Muller, a former political prisoner in Cuba, agreed.
   ``It is not the moment to talk about properties,'' he said. ``It
is the moment to talk about freedom, democracy, reconciliation. Not
property.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0076 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 2156EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-GuinnessRecords     08-12 0294</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Guinness Records,0302</SECOND>
<HEAD>Thousands of Tap Dancers, Milk-Walker Go for Records</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY9</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Seekers of immortality through the Guinness Book
of World Records said they broke two records in Manhattan on
Sunday. A man walked 44 miles with a pint of milk on his head and
5,271 tap-dancers performed a choreographed routine.
   ``It was really quite loud,'' said Barbra Lewinski, a
spokeswoman for Macy's, which sponsored the 12th annual mass tap
dance. This year's event was a tribute to entertainer Sammy Davis
Jr., who died in May.
   The tap dancers from across the country filled a city block
outside Macy's department store on 34th Street at noon.
   The dancers said they beat the record set by some 4,877
enthusiasts last August outside the store, as recorded by Guinness.
   The Guinness organization, which certifies new records, could
not be reached for comment Sunday; there was no answer at their New
York office.
   On Manhattan's Lower East Side, another record was challenged as
Ashrita Furman tried to regain the Guinness record for walking with
a full pint of milk balanced on his head.
   The 35-year-old manager of a health food store from the borough
of Queens walked around a track at a city park, and said he broke
the record by doing 43} miles.
   Furman said he beat the record of 40.4 miles set a few months
ago by an Indian, whose name he did not remember. That record had
not yet made the Guinness Book.
   Furman's previous record for balancing a full milk bottle was
32.9 miles on Jan. 17, 1989.
   He also holds Guinness records for yodeling, somersaulting and
pogo-stick jumping _ in 8 feet of water in the Amazon River in
Peru, and on Mount Fuji in Japan.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0077 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 2212EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Caracas-Water     08-12 0247</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Caracas-Water,0254</SECOND>
<HEAD>Breakdown Could Leave Caracas Without Water for Two Weeks</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CARACAS, Venezuela (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The capital's main waterworks suffered
an electrical breakdown Sunday, threatening to leave most of the
city's 4 million people without water for two weeks, the government
said.
   The accident caused an estimated $1 million in damage at the
main water station serving Caracas, officials said.
   It was described as a ``short circuit'' at the plant on the
Mariposa Reservoir 30 miles south of Caracas. No details were
released, and there were no reports of injuries.
   About three quarters of Caracas will be without water while
authorities search for parts and arrange for repairs, said city
water official Victor Medina said.
   Many residents of Caracas have already spent two days without
water because of unrelated repairs on a major pipeline in the city.
   Officials said they would keep hospitals, firefighters and other
crucial services functioning by rerouting water from other suburban
pipelines. A few neighborhoods will receive severely rationed water
through the same system.
   Trucking companies are expected to supply water to large
companies and apartment buildings, but residents of small buildings
and private homes will have a tougher time getting water.
   Government spokesman Luis Vezga Godoy called on residents for
their ``understanding and solidarity.'' He asked businesses,
families and friends to rely on each other for help.
   ``We've never had an accident of this magnitude,'' he said.
   He added that the government was working as quickly as possible
to restore water.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0078 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 2243EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-ForestFires 1stLd-Writethru a0748 08-12 0876</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Forest Fires, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0748,0895</SECOND>
<HEAD>Fires Spread, Over 200,000 Acres Burned in California's Dry
Timberland</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 5th graf, `About 2,800..' to UPDATE with soldiers
entering firefight in Oregon; SUBS 12th graf, `The Finley ..' with
4 grafs to UPDATE with visit to burned town; picks up 13th graf,
`Yosemite firefighters...</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos XYOS1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARY McGRATH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>YOSEMITE NATIONAL PARK, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Lightning fires have
burned more than 200,000 acres of California forest in the past
week, and experts said Sunday it could get get ``much, much worse''
because of the lengthy drought.
   In Yosemite National Park, off limits to tourists since Friday,
two fires had burned more than 15,000 acres. Flames were within two
miles of the Merced Grove, a stand of giant sequoias, and within
two miles of the Badger Pass ski area.
   Across the state, 14 fires were listed as major.
   Fires also burned Sunday in parts of Alaska, Idaho, Oregon, Utah
and Washington state, said the Boise Interagency Fire Center in
Idaho; a fire in south-central Montana was controlled late
Saturday. The national firefighting command center said nearly
20,000 firefighters were at work on fires that had covered 856,000
acres, more than half of that acreage in Alaska.
   About 2,800 Army soldiers have begun firefighting training at
bases in Washington state and Colorado. About 100 soldiers left
Fort Lewis, Wash., on Sunday to relieve fatigued firefighters in
Oregon. About 1,100 more were to follow Monday, said Maj. John
Lundberg, a base spokesman.
   California's worst fire was in Tehama County about 200 miles
north of Yosemite, where two fires not far apart had burned a total
of 124,000 acres. In the Sequoia National Forest, southeast of
Yosemite and northeast of Bakersfield, a fire had burned over
24,000 acres and firefighters worked to protect the communities of
Kernville and Alta Sierra.
   ``The 200,000-acre figure for the state is probably pretty
conservative,'' said Karen Terrill of the California Department of
Forestry. ``What I hear the experts saying is that this could get
to be much, much worse.''
   The largest Tehama County fire, called the Campbell Complex,
covered 112,000 acres.
   ``It's probably going to become twice that,'' Chris Parker of
the CDF said. ``What we're seeing is the culmination of four years'
drought.''
   The Campbell fire was considered only 40 percent contained. The
Finley Lake fire six miles away was burning uncontrolled over
12,000 acres and was expected to join the bigger one, Terrill said.
State Highway 36 in the fire area, east of Red Bluff, was closed
Sunday.
   ``The Campbell is the most difficult to fight, is eating up the
most acreage, and is in an area that hasn't burned for about 50
years,'' she added. ``The Finley Lake fire is incredibly smoky.''
   The Finley Lake fire by Sunday had destroyed 13 trailer homes,
two houses and 27 outbuildings. A total of 127 structures have been
consumed by fires since Aug. 3 across the state, including 66 of
the 84 houses in the town of Foresta, at Yosemite.
   People allowed back into Foresta on Sunday saw the black trunks
of trees rising out of smoldering white ash.
   A firefighter surveying the ruins drove a stake three feet into
the earth, then pulled it out. The end was burned from ground
temperatures of 300 degrees.
   ``To save this town, it would have taken a massive sprinker
system,'' said Len McKenzie, chief naturalist at Yosemite.
   Yosemite firefighters took special precautions to protect the
sequoia trees, some of them 2,000 years old, in Merced Grove. This
included cleaning up forest debris in the area and treating the
trees with a fire retardant.
   But the thick-barked sequoias have lived through other fires,
Terrill noted, and probably could make it easily through another.
   Elsewhere in Yosemite, ``there's a degree of peacefulness, if
you are not caught up in the frantic business of firefighting,''
said Jeff Nicholas, 39, curator of Yosemite's Ansel Adams photo
gallery.
   ``This is the way it should be, quite and peaceful, without the
sound of tour buses,'' he said. The park normally has up to 25,000
tourists visiting on summer weekends.
   The Yosemite fires were about 10 miles west of Yosemite Valley,
the heavily visited site of Half Dome, El Capitan and Bridalveil
Falls.
   In 1987, summer fires in California burned more than 750,000
acres.
   ``Last week, we were saying this would be nothing like 1987.
There was very little humidity then,'' Terrill said Sunday. ``But
it also wasn't the fourth year of drought in the state then.''
   Lightning strikes _ almost 24,000 were counted by detection
equipment from Aug. 3 through the weekend _ were believed to have
caused all of the California fires.
   Elsewhere, firefighters appeared to be winning the battle Sunday
against five major groups of lightning-caused fires that have
burned across 119,420 acres of remote eastern Oregon forest and
range land.
   The town of Burns, Ore., was about four miles from the Pine
Springs Basin Complex of fires that had burned 73,700 acres. The
blaze was 75 percent contained Sunday morning and full containment
was expected by Monday evening.
   Firefighters took advantage of a break in the hot, dry weather
and contained Idaho's larger range fires, including the 65,000-acre
Thorn Creek blaze that damaged several outbuildings.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0079 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 2248EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Liberia 1stLd-Writethru a0726 08-12 0906</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Liberia, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0726,0934</SECOND>
<HEAD>PRECEDE Paynesville</HEAD>
<HEAD>Doe Says He Wants to Stay in Office Another Year</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS thruout to UPDATE with spokesman saying Doe wants to
stay in power; Western reporters detained and beaten; CORRECTS
spelling of task force commander's name; EDITS to trim; DROPS
byline; PRECEDES; no pickup</NOTE>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   The following is based in part on a pool report
from journalists in Monrovia. AP correspondent Michael Goldsmith is
among them.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>MONROVIA, Liberia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Samuel Doe wants to remain in
office for at least a year after regional peacekeepers intervene to
halt the civil war, a spokesman said Sunday. Doe's announcement
reversed an earlier promise to resign by October.
   At least 18 civilians were killed when government soldiers
attacked rebels trying to take an airport.
   Also Sunday, three Western news agency reporters were detained
and beaten by government soldiers who threatened to shoot them as
spies after they crossed through rebel lines. Among the reporters
was Michael Goldsmith, 68, of The Associated Press.
   The reporters were brought under guard to Doe's heavily
fortified mansion, where they were released and met with the
government spokesman.
   Doe's move reverses an earlier offer he made in May to resign
before elections scheduled for October in order to end the
fighting, which has degenerated into tribal warfare and left 5,000
dead, mostly civilians.
   The rebels, who have accused Doe of corruption and human rights
abuses during his 10 years in power, have demanded that he step
down immediately.
   ``The best thing is for Doe to stay,'' his spokesman Selley
Thompson told the reporters Sunday.
   ``If he decided to leave tomorrow there would be a bloodbath.
The soldiers would go on a rampage. It's likely that, if Doe
decided to leave, the government's soldiers might even take power.''
   Thompson said Doe's earlier offer to step down was no longer
valid, and he wanted to keep power for at least a year after the
West African force intervened.
   In Freetown, Sierra Leone, the West African task force was
assembling. It was expected to arrive in Monrovia later this week.
   Three ships carrying 1,000 Ghanaian soldiers arrived Sunday in
Freetown after the leader of the five-nation West African
peacekeeping force launched an urgent appeal for a cease-fire in
the 8-month-old civil war. At least 400 Nigerian troops have
arrived by air in Freetown.
   In Monrovia, rebel leader Prince Johnson told a pool of foreign
journalists Saturday that he was sending a delegation to Freetown
to make arrangements for the peacekeeping force to land in
Monrovia's port, which he has controlled for the past two weeks.
   In the fighting, government troops mounted a successful
counterattack Sunday, dashing rebel hopes of seizing the capital
before the arrival of the West African force.
   Troops from the government's 72nd Battalion advanced behind an
armored car Sunday morning from their camp in the Paynesville
suburb on the city's eastern outskirts and cut off a group of
rebels trying to take Spriggs Payne airfield.
   The rebel troops ran away as government troops advanced. The
government forces opened fire on fleeing civilians.
   ``They killed my papa!'' cried a girl as she fled the fighting.
   One middle-aged man, relieved to be alive, kept gasping, ``Thank
you Jesus, Thank you Jesus.''
   Journalists counted the bodies of 15 civilians, including those
of small children, lying in a half-filled culvert where they had
tried to seek cover. Three other bodies lay in the road nearby.
   The rebel troops from Charles Taylor's National Patriotic Front
had bypassed the 72nd Battalion in its haste to lay siege to the
capital. There were no figures for the number of government or
rebel fighters involved, or for casualties among the combatants.
   Taylor and Johnson are rivals, and their forces have clashed in
the past.
   The three Western reporters were detained by government troops
after they had crossed on foot through Johnson's lines into
government-controlled territory in the center of Monrovia. The
reporters were accused of being spies.
   Soldiers seized watches, wallets and other valuables from the
reporters. Some of the items were later returned by senior
officers, but others vanished.
   Soldiers ripped the shirts off the reporters and forced them to
walk shoeless to the presidential mansion. On the way, they were
slapped, punched and threatened with rifle butts.
   Thompson and senior officers later apologized for the troops'
behavior.
   ``You have to understand they're very nervous,'' said Lt. Col.
Moses Thomas before the reporters were escorted to the Barclay
Training Center. They later made their way back across rebel lines
without incident.
   In his other remarks, Thompson again accused the U.S. military
of intervening in the conflict. He said a U.S. helicopter sprayed
tear gas on government troops in the city center early Sunday.
   The United States has consistently denied any involvement in the
fighting. A four-ship U.S. naval squadron with Marines and
helicopters has been stationed off the coast to help evacuate
Americans and other foreigners.
   Earlier, the Liberian government claimed that Doe's mansion had
been attacked by a U.S. helicopter and fired upon by a U.S.
submarine.
   West African leaders decided at a summit last week in Banjul,
Gambia, to send the peacekeeping troops to Liberia. Doe and Johnson
have welcomed the initiative to end the civil war.
   The West African force will include troops from Ghana, Gambia,
Guinea, Nigeria and Sierra Leone. Lt. Gen. Arnold Quainoo of Ghana
is commander in chief of the West African force.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0080 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 2313EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Parolee-Manhunt     08-12 0295</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Parolee-Manhunt,0305</SECOND>
<HEAD>Alleged Rapist Captured in Manhunt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BERRY, Ala. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A four-day manhunt for a parolee accused of
murdering one woman and raping three others at an isolated
campground ended with his capture Sunday.
   Roy Eugene Perkins, 30, was arrested in the woods just south of
Berry, about 60 miles west of Birmingham, said Robert Flippo, an
aide to Fayette County Sheriff James Lenard.
   About 50 law officers and volunteers took part in the search.
   Officers were conducting a final search of a patch of woods when
they found Perkins. ``One of the officers walked up on him and he
said, `Don't shoot,''' said Ronnie Finch, a reserve deputy.
   Perkins had suffered a bullet wound to the leg that required
treatment at a hospital, but officials said it wasn't serious. He
may have been shot in a struggle with one of his alleged victims
last week, said Finch.
   Six of Perkins' relatives were arrested Saturday night and
charged with hindering prosecution, said Fayette County police Sgt.
Butch Hudson.
   ``They had been giving him food and helping him and we decided
the next time we had any trouble out of them we were going to
arrest them,'' Lenard said.
   The focus of much of the search was a cinder block house tucked
in a campground in the deep woods. Perkins grew up in the woods,
officers said, and all three rape victims were taken to the
camphouse.
   In 1983 Perkins was convicted of second-degree rape and served
seven years of a 10-year sentence at the West Jefferson
Correctional facility before being paroled in May.
   Perkins allegedly raped a teen-age relative in July, assaulted a
23-year-old relative from Tuscaloosa last week, abducted and killed
a woman on Thursday and raped a 31-year-old Fayette County woman.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0081 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 2350EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a w PM-WalterMears ADV14   08-12 0935</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Walter Mears, ADV14,0961</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv 14</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release PMs Tues Aug 14 and Thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>Quayle's South American Trip a Risky Venture</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP News Analysis</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By WALTER R. MEARS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Special Correspondent</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Parked side by side, the twin motorcades
filled the narrow street in Bogota, Colombia, idling in opposite
directions, each with a black, flag-decked limousine flown in from
Washington for the day.
   At a radioed signal, one rolled out, turned sharp left, paused
while Vice President Dan Quayle stepped into the limousine, then
sped from the city to the expressway on a tightly guarded trip to
Catam Military Airport.
   Anyone bent on harming the vice president, in a city where drug
terrorism still is a menace, would have had to pick between
motorcades, and guess at a route out of town.
   Security was intensive at every stop on Quayle's three-day
mission to Latin America last week. There were reinforced Secret
Service guards, SWAT teams, cordons of police and military men in
each nation.
   Rooftops were guarded, routes swept in advance. Even so, the
trip was a bodyguard's nightmare, and some Quayle aides had argued
against it. But agents who surveyed the sites said they could keep
the vice president safe, and they did.
   The government will not discuss security arrangements for the
officials it guards, and that includes costs. Security doesn't come
cheap, especially in a foreign capital where violence is not
uncommon.
   Traveling vice presidents are not usually provided with backup
Air Force jetliners for emergency use when they travel. One was
sent to Bogota for the Quayle visit, in case of trouble with Air
Force Two.
   And while he was in Bogota for the inauguration on Tuesday, at
least four Latin American officials who had come for the ceremony
told him it was safer there than in Lima, Peru, his next stop. They
told him they wouldn't go to the Peruvian capital just then.
   Fleets of five Army helicopters were sent to each city to lift
Quayle and his traveling party to and from the airports. In Bogota,
the weather closed in while the vice president was at the
inauguration of Colombia's President Cesar Gaviria, so he drove out
of town.
   In Lima, helicopters flew Quayle into the city Tuesday night,
landing on the floodlit soccer field of the National Stadium.
Security men prefer it because air routes can be varied, and
motorcades are more vulnerable to attack.
   Hours before Quayle arrived there had been bomb-punctuated
street demonstrations over soaring prices and an austerity program
the new Peruvian government was instituting to try to rebuild a
collapsing economy. The city was in a state of emergency. Visitors
were advised against venturing from their hotels, lest they be
caught up in random violence.
   Early the next morning, an explosion and gunfire could be heard
from the U.S. ambassador's residence where Quayle spent the night.
   None of it altered Quayle's schedule, and he didn't see so much
as a demonstrator. Despite the objections of his security staff, he
insisted on visiting San Pablo Presbyterian Church, in a slum
neighborhood 20 minutes from downtown, to tour a center for orphans
of guerrilla violence in the Peruvian mountains.
   It is operated with support from the Quayles' church in McLean,
Va., and he was determined to go there. Sharpshooters patrolled
slum rooftops, scanning the maze of buildings and shacks as he came
and went.
   Again, no problems.
   As Quayle flew home from Bolivia, with a stop in Haiti, where
random violence also is ordinary, he said there had been warnings
in advance that he would not be well received in the Andean
capitals.
   He said he'd been told that there might be anti-American
demonstrations and security trouble.
   ``That just didn't happen,'' Quayle said. He said it reflects
new attitudes and improving relationships between the United States
and Latin American nations.
   Had he worried about his safety?
   ``I didn't that much, but my wife did, and some others,'' he
said.
   His trip to the capital cities contrasted with the brief,
heavily guarded Bush visit to Cartagena, Colombia, Feb. 15 for the
drug summit with the presidents of the same three nations. That
meeting was held at a Colombian naval base, with 5,000 troops
standing guard, warships offshore and helicopters patrolling
overhead.
   Even so, Bush faced advance criticism for going. He said he
wasn't ``going to do something stupid or macho,'' but was going to
show support for the Colombian government in its drive against the
cocaine cartels.
   Quayle's trip to Bogota, where no such iron security was
possible, renewed that support for a successor government pledged
to continue the anti-drug effort. The visits to Lima and La Paz
were companion pieces in the followup to Cartagena.
   He was the highest ranking U.S. official to visit Lima since
Richard M. Nixon went there as vice president in 1958, and was
jeered and pelted with tomatoes and spoiled fruit. Nixon, like
Quayle, had gone on to La Paz; no vice president had been there
since. None had visited Haiti, Quayle's last stop, since Nixon in
1954.
   The vice president did not go bearing gifts; he carried no new
messages, no new aid commitments. He came home satisfied that by
going, he had demonstrated U.S. support for governments that are
trying to cope with drugs and with economic woes.
   The fact that he went at some risk served to underscore his
point.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Walter R. Mears, vice president and columnist
for The Associated Press, has reported on Washington and national
politics for more than 25 years.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>For Release PMs Tues Aug 14 and Thereafter</NOTE>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0082 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 1425EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-CreditMarkets Bjt   08-12 0597</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Credit Markets, Bjt,0615</SECOND>
<HEAD>Oil Uncertainty Makes Fed Choices More Difficult</HEAD>
<HEAD>Also moved in advance</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAN BLAKE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Iraq's invasion of Kuwait forced economists to
reevaluate their projections, but left many even more convinced
that the U.S. economy is weakening while also facing the
possibility of higher inflation.
   Developments in the weeks preceding the Iraqi invasion already
had economists warning of higher inflation and weaker economic
growth.
   ``In a sense, the oil price increase only reinforces what was
happening before,'' said Alan Levenson, an economist at the Wefa
Group, a Bala-Cynwyd, Pa. economic forecasting firm.
   ``We've been through oil shocks before, now we have to make some
judgments about where the dust will settle this time,'' he said.
   One key to the economy's direction is how the Federal Reserve
will act. As a matter of policy the Fed doesn't disclose its
intentions, but it has enormous power to influence economic growth
through two principal means: controlling the supply of money in the
banking system and adjusting rates banks pay to borrow.
   The spotlight on what the central bank's strategy might be has
brightened because of events in the Middle East.
   Before the Iraqi invasion there were signs of economic weakness,
which suggested the Fed would move to ease credit.
   July's unemployment figures showed the jobless rate reaching a
2-year high; July's Purchasing Managers Index slipped below 50,
indicating that the manufacturing sector might be in decline, and
the Fed's own regional survey showed economic growth was slowing.
   Wholesale prices in July edged down 0.1 percent, the government
said Friday. But analysts said the figures may indicate the last
respite from inflation before the effects of soaring oil costs
linked to the Mideast crisis are felt.
   The Fed is faced with the same choices it had before the oil
price increase. How much should it ease the money supply to offset
economic weakness, but avoid increasing the potential for inflation?
   The weakening economy and higher inflation put the Fed in a
common, but no less troublesome, predicament on how to deal with
interest rates.
   Increasing the supply of money in the economy would lower
interest rates and spur more spending, possibly giving the economy
a dose of vitality. However with more money floating around,
inflation could accelerate. Prices may already be pulled upward
across the economy by the increase in oil.
   Holding back on the money supply, however, could spur higher
interest rates and make it more difficult to buy new cars and homes
and build new factories. Irwin Kellner, chief economist at
Manufacturers Hanover Trust Co., said fears of inflation are
exaggerated. Higher gasoline prices won't remain after the summer
peak driving season ends Labor Day, he said. With less consumer
demand, it will be even more difficult for oil companies to pass
along higher wholesale costs, he said.
   ``It's been our assertion for some time now that the U.S.
economy entered into a recession in the second quarter,'' Kellner
said.
   Assuming the Middle East situation settles down, Kellner said he
expects the Fed to loosen the money supply after its policymaking
Federal Open Market Committee meets Aug. 21.
   ``If it hadn't been for the invasion we would have seen easing
already,'' Kellner said.
   ``The big question is will it stick or not. No we're not going
to return to $20 a barrel anytime soon, but will there be some
decreases?'' Ray Stone, of Stone &amp; McCarthy Research Associates
Inc., said.
   ``The higher oil prices makes it harder for the Fed to ease''
the money supply now, he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0083 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 1600EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-Greyhound     08-12 0576</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Greyhound,0600</SECOND>
<HEAD>Greyhound Chief Determined To See Company Survive</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN A. BOLT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DALLAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Fred Currey's dream Greyhound Lines Inc. is
getting a little frayed around the edges, what with a strike by bus
drivers and others' doubts about his company paying its bills.
   But the man who led the 1987 leveraged buyout of the bus company
remains determined.
   ``You're damned right I believe in the system and you're damned
right I see it rebuilt,'' Currey said during an interview in his
starkly modern office in a Dallas skyscraper. ``I intend to finish
exactly what the hell I started.''
   Others aren't so sure.
   ``We think the company is on the brink of extinction here,''
said Earle Putnam, general counsel of the Amalgamated Transit
Union, the umbrella organization over Greyhound drivers' union.
   Some analysts privately wonder if Greyhound this summer is
building up the cash reserves it needs to survive the winter's
slack travel.
   Greyhound's 6,300 drivers went on strike March 2 after
negotiations broke down over a new contract to replace the one
Currey had negotiated in 1987.
   Three months into the strike, Greyhound filed for bankruptcy
court protection from its creditors, blaming increased legal and
security costs required to combat the initially violent walkout.
   The bankruptcy remains in its early stages, with current
management still running the company. No reorganization plan is due
until October, and since extensions on initial plan deadlines are
frequently granted, Greyhound spokesman George Gravley says the
company's plan should be ready by early November.
   Currey promises a ``high-quality'' plan, ``reorganized around a
viable market.''
   The reorganized Greyhound is likely to resemble the old
Greyhound, streamlined somewhat.
   ``Our strategy at operating this business turned around a dying
business,'' he said, so a reorganization plan will ``employ exactly
the same strategies, updated and enhanced, that we employed''
before the bankruptcy.
   Currey, a career bus executive, led a team of investors in 1987
that paid $270 million for the bus operations of Greyhound Corp.,
since renamed Greyhound Dial Corp. A few months later, the
investors plunked down another $80 million for Dallas-based
Trailways Lines Inc., the largest Trailways franchisee.
   After merging the two operations, Currey ran the nation's only
intercity bus company.
   Ridership had been falling each year before the buyout,
bottoming out at 6.09 billion passenger miles in 1986. After the
buyout, ridership increased each year, hitting 7.48 billion
passenger miles in 1989.
   Greyhound also turned its first profit that year, earning
$730,000 on about $1 billion in revenues after losing about $20
million over the previous two years.
   Although the company has continued to operate using replacement
drivers, the strike slashed ridership and the meager profits.
   Ridership slowly as returned to levels fluctuating between 70
percent and 80 percent of last year.
   ``We're now through the '87 level,'' Currey said, predicting
``it won't take three years'' to recover to profitable levels.
Revenues are covering operating costs, he said.
   But in the transportation industry, travel delayed is travel
lost, and the summer is the busiest time of the year.
   ``The objective indicators are that this company has a very
severe financial problem just operating,'' said the union's Putnam.
   Although he won't provide figures until the reorganization plan
is ready, Currey says Greyhound is building sufficient cash flow to
attract new capital.
   ``We are building cash balances,'' Gravley said. ``We're having
a good summer. Things are going pretty well. Business as usual has
been our theme song.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900812-0084 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-12-90 1850EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-WesternUnion 1stLd-Writethru f0010 08-12 0412</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Western Union, 1st Ld-Writethru, f0010,0423</SECOND>
<HEAD>Western Union Replaces Union Employees</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: EDITS throughout, UPDATES with details on workers represented
by CWA, wages. Also moving on general news wires.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>UPPER SADDLE RIVER, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Western Union Corp. on Saturday
locked out 2,000 employees in the middle of contract talks with
their union.
   The company did not indicate whether the workers would be
rehired if it signs a new contract with their union, the
Communications Workers of America, which represents a total of
2,500 workers at Western Union.
   Western Union said the replacements would not affect its
money-transfer, telex, electronic mail and paper-based message
services.
   ``We sincerely regret that, in the absence of a union contract,
we have reluctantly had to take this defensive action,'' said
Robert J. Amman, Western Union president and chief executive
officer. ``We cannot operate under the ever-present threat of an
employee strike while continuing to bear the cost required to
ensure that the company would survive one.''
   Western Union has a total of 16,000 employees. About half the
employees represented by CWA are recording operators, and the
others are mostly customer relations clerks, clerical workers and
field technicians.
   Dan Beckstead, the chief union negotiator, deplored the lockout,
saying the union had not given the company any indication it
intends to strike.
   ``In fact, we told them we wanted to continue to negotiate in an
attempt to reach an agreement,'' Beckstead said. CWA workers have
authorized their leadership to call a strike.
   Western Union said many of the replaced CWA workers were from
its central telephone bureaus in Bridgeton, Miss., and Reno, Nev.;
its computer centers in Middletown, Va., and Bridgeton.
   It temporarily replaced them with workers from Western Union
headquarters and trained temporary replacements, the company said.
   The company has been negotiating with representatives of the CWA
since July 23. The previous two-year contract expired Aug. 6, but
management and union negotiators have continued to meet to try to
agree on a new pact.
   Management on Aug. 8 proposed a 90-day extension of the old
contract, but the offer was rejected by the CWA.
   The contract issues include wages, health care and job
classifications, as well as Western Union's right to use outside
contractors and hire part-time workers. The operators average about
$10 an hour.
   Beckstead said Western Union has not responded to the union's
latest offer made Friday. The company, however, said the union had
until midnight Sunday to agree to a 90-day contract extension.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
</Collection>
