<Collection>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0001 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 2352EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-TheGleaners     11-18 0861</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-The Gleaners,1142</SECOND>
<HEAD>A Story of Thanksgiving: The Needy Glean Food from Harvested
Fields</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Monday AMs report.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY307 Nov. 15.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CHRISTOPHER SULLIVAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>FAIRHOPE, Ala. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The harvest has been abundant this year -
fat tomatoes, sweet potatoes, melons, pecans and purple-hull peas.
The rains came, as farmers gathered in a spring field prayed they
would.
   ``We were blessed,'' produce grower Louis Lazzari said.
   At Thanksgiving dinner in Annie White's house, the grace her ill
80-year-old husband Jack plans to say will be simple: ``He'll say
he hopes it continues.''
   By that, she meant not just the fecundity of the good earth here
by Mobile Bay, but the sharing of its riches between farmers like
Lazzari and families like hers, families in need, through people
known as ``gleaners.''
   From bean-growing time in the spring to the gathering of mustard
greens, turnips and broccoli in cool weather, farmers invite the
gleaners into their fields to take what's left behind after
harvest.
   On one afternoon this summer, 200 hands picked 16,220 pounds of
tomatoes. Altogether last year, the gleaners, organized by a local
group called Ecumenical Ministries, carried away 100,000 pounds of
vegetables and fruits.
   The pickers must be needy. They cannot sell anything they glean.
And they must share it with someone else in need - such as the
Whites, who cannot pick on their ownbecause they're disabled.
   The rules are as simple as the verses from the Old Testament
that underlie the 10-year-old project.
   ``When thou cuttest down thine harvest ... and hast forgotten a
sheaf in the field, thou shalt not go again to fetch it,'' enjoins
Deuteronomy 24:19-21.
   ``It shall be for the stranger, for the fatherless, and for the
widow. That the Lord thy God may bless thee in all the work of
thine hands.''
   Mrs. White, who at 69 has heart trouble and more other ailments
than she can name, and whose husband has cancer, learned of
Ecumenical Ministries about eight years ago, on a day she was
desperate for food. ``That day, I really didn't have anything to
cook,'' she said.
   ``Before I looked around, it was no time before they were out
with boxes and bags of groceries,'' she said.
   After that, gleaners brought regular deliveries of whatever
vegetable was in season. Without the food, she said, ``I guess I'd
starve.''
   The program began a decade ago with Dot Threadgill, who saw a
television news item about people from a California senior citizens
center who supplemented their diet by picking leftovers in the
fields.
   Mrs. Threadgill's energy seems to keep the gleaning operations
going - and growing, from about 300 pounds of food distributed
during the first year, ``about half of that out of my garden,'' she
said.
   Now, 15 farmers call her or she calls them as harvests near. And
she's learned tricks over the years.
   ``Mechanical harvesters can't pick where they turn, at the end
of the rows,'' she said, referring to potato picking machines. ``So
we know where to be.''
   She scouts the fields, estimating how many gleaners the crop
will feed plentifully - ``We don't want them to use their gas money
and not have sufficient for several days.'' Then she quickly goes
to the ``telephone tree'' to mobilize pickers before the farmer
plows the field under to prepare for the next crop.
   Suzanne Zellner got a call when a turnip patch was offered
recently. She and her husband have five children, the youngest
2{-year-old twins. Besides improving nutrition and stretching
grocery money, gleaning has an educational value, she said,
teaching children ``how to pick, how to know when something's ready
or when it's too ripe.''
   Another regular in the fields is Gussie Winston, 53, who first
went gleaning because her family had nothing to eat, but now makes
ends meet with housekeeping jobs and gleans and cans vegetables for
herself and a list of mostly elderly people unable to get out
themselves.
   ``When you become a gleaner, you're an emissary,'' she said,
looking across a sunny field to pickers stooped at their work.
``You're supposed to see that no one goes hungry.''
   For Mrs. Threadgill, that requires judicious juggling of her
phone list. For instance, she said, ``I know that Mary Jones has 10
or 15 people under her; so I know that if there's only enough for
10 or 15 I don't need to call but Mary ...
   ``And if we get peas for Mary this week, we call somebody else,
and kind of divide around the wealth.''
   And the wealth keeps blooming.
   Around the Fourth of July, one farmer makes sure to call the
gleaners to gather ripe watermelons.
   Just before Christmas last year, a rare spell of extreme cold
brought a call from another farmer who said he couldn't protect all
of his broccoli crop. The gleaners cut 1,200 pounds.
   A grower who has a U-pick operation, with tomatoes planted in a
staggered schedule, offers the gleaners what's left in ``dead-ripe
patches'' that his paying customers picked through the week before.
   Standing in the shade of an old pecan tree on his farm,
60-year-old Louis Lazzari said the vagariesof the market sometimes
open his fields to the gleaners.
   ``This year, one day I sold my broker 240 bushel boxes of beans
and he wanted the next day 340,'' he said. ``I had the beans, some
of the prettiest I ever raised in my life.'' But the going price
wouldn't have covered expenses. ``After I paid the help, I paid for
the box, I paid the freight to the place of business, I don't know
honestly but I may have went backwards.
   ``I could have plowed 'em under,'' Lazzari said. But really he
couldn't. ``It hurts me so bad to see something ... go to waste,''
he said. And he knows there are plenty of people here who haven't
had his good fortune.
   ``I was born in the Depression,'' he said, ``but I never had to
go to bed one day in my life without a decent meal, I'm thankful to
say.''
   Instead of plowing those pretty beans under, he phoned Mrs.
Threadgill.
   Once, a few years ago, Lazzari spontaneously called and offered
sweet corn, 30 big croker sacks full.
   Mrs. Threadgill went back a few days later to thank him with a
cake. ``He said, `You know, I had that big field of corn, and it
wasn't moving. After I gave you that 30 sacks, that evening a man
came and bought the whole field from me.' ''
   ---
   EDITOR'S NOTE - Christopher Sullivan is the AP's Southeast
regional reporter, based in Atlanta.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0002 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 2357EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a BC-LOT-SaturdayLotteries     11-18 0778</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-LOT-Saturday Lotteries,0980</SECOND>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<HEAD>ARIZONA</HEAD>
<HEAD>Pick</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PHOENIX (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers drawn Saturday night for a
$3.5 million jackpot in the Arizona Lottery's Pick game were: 5,
10, 24, 28, 39 and 40.
   A bonus number of 42 also was drawn.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>CALIFORNIA</HEAD>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SACRAMENTO, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers picked
Saturday night for the California Lottery's twice-weekly ``Lotto
6-53'' game: 17, 30, 36, 12, 43, 21, and the bonus number, 29.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>CONNECTICUT</HEAD>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEWINGTON, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning combination picked Saturday
in the Connecticut State Lottery's ``Daily Lottery'' drawing was:
   2-5-2
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Play 4</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEWINGTON, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning combination picked Saturday
in the Connecticut State Lottery's ``Play 4'' drawing was:
   6-6-6-2.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>FLORIDA</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected Saturday in
the Florida Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Cash 3</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   2-6-2
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   09-06-31-34-22-30
</TEXT>
<HEAD>ILLINOIS</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SPRINGFIELD, Ill. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the Illinois State Lottery:
 
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   1-0-2
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick Four</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   1-3-3-3
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   1-2-9-10-11-46
</TEXT>
<HEAD>INDIANA</HEAD>
<HEAD>Ind Lottery Glance</HEAD>
<DATELINE>INDIANAPOLIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the Hoosier Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto Cash</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   19-38-34-44-24-18
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Three</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   9-8-4
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Four</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   0-5-4-1
</TEXT>
<HEAD>IOWA</HEAD>
<HEAD>Lotto America</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DES MOINES, Iowa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers drawn Saturday night
in ``Lotto America'' are:
   2-3-38-39-43-48
</TEXT>
<HEAD>KANSAS</HEAD>
<HEAD>Kan. Cash Lotto</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOPEKA, Kan. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers in the Kansas Cash Lotto
drawing Saturday night with an estimated jackpot of $485,000:
   4-15-17-24-28-33
</TEXT>
<HEAD>KENTUCKY</HEAD>
<HEAD>Kentucky Lottery</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOUISVILLE, Ky. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are Saturday's winning numbers
selected by the Kentucky Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Kentucky Cash:
   3-6-2.
   </HEAD>
<HEAD>Lotto:
   1-8-10-29-32-35
   </HEAD>
<HEAD>MARYLAND</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BALTIMORE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   These Maryland lotteries were drawn Saturday
night:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   4-3-3
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Play Four</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   5-0-3-5
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   11-15-29-32-34-45
</TEXT>
<HEAD>MASSACHUSETTS</HEAD>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BRAINTREE, Mass. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers drawn Saturday night
in the ``Massachusetts Daily Lottery'' were:
   9-9-7-2
</TEXT>
<HEAD>MICHIGAN</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DETROIT (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected Saturday in
the Michigan State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   9-5-7
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily-4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   5-3-8-1
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto 47</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   6, 16, 18, 28, 36, 41
</TEXT>
<HEAD>MINNESOTA</HEAD>
<HEAD>Daily 3</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MINNEAPOLIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers drawn Saturday night in
Minnesota's Daily 3 lottery game are:
   5-1-4
</TEXT>
<HEAD>MISSOURI</HEAD>
<HEAD>Pick 3</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ST. LOUIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers in Saturday's Missouri
Lottery Daily Pick 3 game:
   5-1-9
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ST. LOUIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers in Missouri's Lotto drawing
Saturday night:
   3-15-22-24-46-48
</TEXT>
<HEAD>NEW JERSEY</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TRENTON, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday night in the New Jersey State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 3</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   2-0-2
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   4-0-8-3
</TEXT>
<HEAD>NEW YORK</HEAD>
<HEAD>Pick 10</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ALBANY, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the New York State Lottery's Pick 10 game:
   4, 14, 17, 21, 25, 27, 34, 36, 41, 46, 51, 54, 57, 58, 60, 62,
65, 67, 71, 77.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>NORTHERN NEW ENGLAND</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CONCORD, N.H. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected (day)
in the daily New Hampshire, Vermont and Maine lotteries:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 3</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   3-1-4
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   7-7-6-0
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Tri-State Megabucks</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CONCORD, N.H. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers in the
``Tri-State Megabucks'' game for New Hampshire, Vermont and Maine:
   6-13-15-25-30-37
</TEXT>
<HEAD>OHIO</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CLEVELAND (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected Saturday
night in the Ohio Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 3 Numbers</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   4-1-5
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 4 Numbers</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   7-1-8-4
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto Glance</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CLEVELAND (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected Saturday
night in the Ohio Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Super Lotto</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   3-10-13-18-51-53
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Kicker</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   3-6-8-3-0-9
</TEXT>
<HEAD>OREGON</HEAD>
<HEAD>Daily 4</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PORTLAND, Ore. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are Saturday's winning numbers in the
``Oregon Daily 4'' lottery game:
   6-5-2-3
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Megabucks</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PORTLAND, Ore. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are Saturday's winning numbers in the
``Oregon Megabucks'' lottery game:
   5-12-15-30-37-39
</TEXT>
<HEAD>PENNSYLVANIA</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HARRISBURG (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected Saturday
in the Pennsylvania State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Number</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   6-2-5
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Big 4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   4-9-6-4
</TEXT>
<HEAD>RHODE ISLAND</HEAD>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CRANSTON, R.I. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers in the Rhode Island
daily lottery drawing for Saturday were:
   1-8-6-0
</TEXT>
<HEAD>VIRGINIA</HEAD>
<HEAD>Pick 3</HEAD>
<DATELINE>RICHMOND (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   These numbers were drawn Saturday in the
Virginia Lottery's Pick 3 game:
   2-4-6
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Virginia Lotto</HEAD>
<DATELINE>RICHMOND (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   These numbers were drawn Saturday in the
Virginia Lottery's Lotto game:
   4-6-16-27-31-34
</TEXT>
<HEAD>WASHINGTON</HEAD>
<DATELINE>OLYMPIA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are winning numbers selected Saturday in the
Washington State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   1-9-5
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   3-5-11-12-21-37
</TEXT>
<HEAD>WASHINGTON, DC</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The following results were drawn Saturday in
the District of Columbia Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lucky Numbers Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   9-5-2
</TEXT>
<HEAD>D.C. Four Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   2-2-7-8
</TEXT>
<HEAD>D.C. Daily Double Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   6, 84
</TEXT>
<HEAD>D.C. Quick Cash Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   12-33-5-15-14-6
</TEXT>
<HEAD>WEST VIRGINIA</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CHARLESTON, W.Va. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the West Virginia State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily 3</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   1-2-7
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily 4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   4-4-7-3
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0003 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 2359EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Theologian-Tenure     11-18 0677</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Theologian-Tenure,0823</SECOND>
<HEAD>Controversial Theologian, Denied Tenure, Now Focus Of Academic
Dispute</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Monday AMs report.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By JAY REEVES</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>AUBURN, Ala. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An academic dispute with roots in the
Vatican is growing at Auburn University, a state school known more
for producing farmers and football players than Roman Catholic
rifts.
   The controversy centers on the Rev. Charles E. Curran, who was
selected for an endowed professorship at Auburn although he is the
only American barred by Rome from teaching Catholic theology. His
views on topics such as abortion and contraception have put him at
odds with the Vatican for years.
   But it was Curran's treatment by Auburn President James Martin
that has enraged the university senate, a faculty-staff body.
   Martin denied tenure for Curran, although the post was
advertised as being a tenured - or permanent - position, and hasn't
explained his decision publicly or to Curran. He denies the
conclusion of a senate committee that he violated university tenure
policies.
   ``Thus far he's the most controversial person we have ever
hired,'' Martin said in an interview Thursday.
   The senate scheduled a special meeting for Tuesday to discuss
Curran's treatment, and chairman Gary Mullen said the senate is
likely to take some kind of formal stance against Martin.
   ``The action could range from doing nothing, which is not
expected at all, to requesting tenure ... to a formal censure of
the president,'' Mullen said.
   A blowup over religious beliefs and academic freedom is
uncharacteristic at Auburn, a land-grant school in a mostly
Protestant state with 21,000 students and a reputation for
achievement in agriculture and athletics. Last year, its religion
department had only two full-time teachers and a pair of graduates.
   But academic eruptions are not completely foreign to Auburn in
east-central Alabama. The school was censured in 1983 by the
American Association of University Professors following another
tenure dispute, and the rebuke has not been lifted.
   Curran, author of 20 books on Christian ethics and morality,
lost his last tenured position - at Catholic University in
Washington - in 1986. The Vatican said his dissenting views on
conservative church positions made him unfit to teach theology.
   Among other things, he supports abortion in limited
circumstances.
   Since then, Curran has held temporary posts at Cornell
University and the University of Southern California, where he was
working when Auburn called.
   While Curran's views earned a Vatican rebuff, they have not cut
him off from the rest of the church. Some 750 Catholic theologians
have signed a statement backing him, and the University of Notre
Dame continues to publish his books. He has been president of three
major theological societies.
   ``He's considered quite moderate, actually. He's fairly
conservative,'' said John Ehmann, administrative director of Notre
Dame Press.
   ``Only a right-wing fanatic would refer to Charlie Curran as a
way-out theologian,'' said the Rev. Richard McBrien, head of
theology at Notre Dame. ``The Vatican is way out. He's a
centrist.''
   ``A tiny minority of Catholics in Alabama has influenced an
academic decision at a major state institution,'' said McBrien.
   Curran said his views represent those of the Catholic
mainstream. McBrien said Curran has been a target for Rome since
1968, when he led opposition to a Vatican decree against artificial
birth control.
   Curran's post is a new endowed chair created through a program
approved by the Alabama Legislature. The ``eminent scholars'' plan
is supposed to boost the reputations of state-supported schools by
attracting leading academicians.
   The university advertised the chair nationwide as being a
tenured position -meaning it was a lifetime job except for severe
misconduct. Curran said it was with that understanding that he
decided to take the job, after he was recommended by a search
committee and discussed it with a school vice president.
   ``I wouldn't have gotten near the thing if I didn't think it was
tenured,'' Curran, 56, said last week.
   But Curran said that once he had called Auburn to formally
accept the chair, he was told Martin had decided against tenure.
Curran said he had little choice but to come to Auburn for this
school year, having turned down other job offers in favor of the
Auburn post.
   Martin and Auburn's trustees have denied that any outside
pressure led to the decision. The sole Catholic on Auburn's board,
Bessie Mae Holloway, has denied any involvement in the tenure
decision. But Curran said Catholic Archbishop Oscar Lipscomb of
Mobile told him of twice talking with Mrs. Holloway, although
Lipscomb denies being against Curran's hiring.
   The episode has been a disappointment for Curran, who had hoped
to put his disputes with Rome behind him.
   ``One of my reasons for even thinking of Auburn is it would be a
quiet place where I could fade into the woodwork and do my work,''
he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0004 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 2359EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-HairDonor     11-18 0453</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Hair Donor,0570</SECOND>
<HEAD>Woman Donated Hair to War Effort - Used For Cross Hairs In
Bombsight</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Monday AMs report.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>COLORADO SPRINGS, Colo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   When Americans everywhere were
giving up luxuries for the effort to win World War II, Mary Babnick
Brown gave up something much more personal than a favorite food -
her below-knee-length hair.
   Brown, now 83, was honored Saturday for contributing to the war
effort. In a ceremony at the U.S. Air Force Academy, she received a
special achievement award from the Colorado Aviation Historical
Society.
   What she didn't know back in 1942 was that her hair was used as
cross hairs in a secret bombsight used on bombers.
   Brown said she didn't really want to give up her blond hair, but
caring for it was becoming a lot of work. The government wanted
hair at least 22 inches long. She sent 34 inches - hair that had
only been trimmed, never really cut, for her first 36 years.
   In 1942, she saw an advertisement in a Pueblo newspaper that the
government was looking for women to contribute their hair to the
war effort, she sent an inquiry and quickly received a telegram
asking her to send a sample.
   A few days later, she received another telegram pleading for her
hair. It was exactly what they needed, said officials with the
Institute of Technology in Washington, D.C.
   ``I saw so many people crying their eyes out, not wanting their
sons to go,'' she said. ``I was sad. I wanted to do something for
the war effort.''
   Bill Feder, founder of the International B-24 Memorial Museum in
Pueblo, learned recently that a Pueblo woman had donated her hair,
and he began looking for her.
   He told Brown that her hair was used experimentally as cross
hairs in a bomb-aiming device known as the Norden bombsight.
   The bombsight, invented in the mid-1930s by a Swiss immigrant
named Karl Norden, was essentially a mechanical computer used in
high altitude bombing. The device took into account such things as
altitude, the plane's speed and wind velocity.
   When the target reached the center of the cross hairs, the crew
could drop the bomb with dependable accuracy.
   Used on the B-24 Liberator, the B-29 Super Fortress and the B-17
Flying Fortress, the Norden bombsight was so secret that it was
equipped with explosives, Feder said, and crews were ordered to
destroy it if their bomber ran the risk of falling into enemy
hands.
   At altitudes as high as 20,000 feet, the bombsight cross hairs
were subjected to freezing temperatures and rapid changes in
humidity. Black widow spider webs, which contracted and expanded on
scale under those conditions, were originally used but were fragile
and hard to come by.
   Feder said Brown's fine blonde hair, which had never been
bleached or touched with a hot iron, was unique and shared many of
the qualities valued in the black widow spider's web.
   In addition to the bombsight, her hair was used in scientific
equipment such as humidity measuring devices important in the
production of airplanes and other war machinery.
   The Norden bombsight eventually was replaced by electronic
bombsights, but when the newer devices did not prove accurate
enough to drop radio transmitters along jungle trails in Vietnam,
the Norden bombsight was successfully used to do the job.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0005 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 0017EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i BC-Japan-Volcano     11-18 0241</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Japan-Volcano,0270</SECOND>
<HEAD>Volcano Erupts After Nearly 200 Years Dormant</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Steam and hot mud spewed Sunday from a volcano that
was dormant since causing one of Japan's largest natural disasters
nearly 200 years ago.
   No injuries have been reported since Mount Unzen erupted
Saturday, and no evacuations were reported. The volcano is about
510 miles southwest of Tokyo on the island of Kyushu.
   The eruption also did not appear to worry tourists visiting hot
springs near the crater. The town of Unzen, about 2{ miles from the
volcano, currently has about 3,000 tourists, said Unzen Tourist
Association spokesman Tadakiyo Kato.
   ``All the rooms at Unzen hotels are full,'' Kato said. ``We have
been booked solid because of the autumn tourist season, and no one
has canceled out because of the eruption.''
   The 4,458-foot volcano, composed of several volcanic peaks, last
erupted in 1792, killing 15,000 people in the worst volcano-related
disaster in Japanese history. Many of the deaths were caused by a
huge landslide and tidal waves.
   Scientists and local police refused to make predictions on the
eruption, but said they were preparing for the worst.
   Lava flows are not expected, but ``it is impossible to tell for
certain,'' said an official at the Mount Unzen Observatory, who
spoke on condition of anonymity.
   Twin plumes of steam and ash rose hundreds of yards into the
air. Observatory seismographs recorded temblors too weak to be felt
by humans.
   Mount Unzen is one of 19 active volcanoes in Japan designated as
potentially dangerous and under constant observation by the
Meteorological Agency.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0006 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 0046EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-WeaponsSeized     11-18 0444</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Weapons Seized,0499</SECOND>
<HEAD>Desert Shield Soldier, 3 Others Arrested in Military Weapons
Thefts</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JACKSONVILLE, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An Army soldier who had served in the
Persian Gulf and three other men have been arrested in the theft of
a huge cache of military weapons and explosives, federal and local
officials said Saturday.
   The materiel seized Friday and Saturday from a warehouse and one
suspect's home in Jacksonville included enough military explosives
to destroy an entire city block, said Willi Ellison, agent in
charge of the federal Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco and Firearms in
Jacksonville.
   Michael Tubbs, a U.S. Army Special Forces sergeant, had been
brought back from Operation Desert Shield in Saudi Arabia within
the past several weeks, Ellison said. Tubbs was already facing
possible federal firearms and explosives charges in connection with
a January 1987 incident at Fort Bragg, N.C., in which two soldiers
were jumped and tied to a tree by two masked men who stole their
rifles.
   He remained restricted Saturday to the base at Fort Campbell,
Ky., Ellison said.
   Another soldier, Army warrant officer Jeffrey Jennett, has
already been arrested and charged for the 1987 incident. Jennett
was arrested in Charleston, S.C., on Thursday night and charged in
federal court with assault with intent to commit felony theft and
with stealing an M-16 rifle, Ellison said.
   Also seized Friday and Saturday were military weapons manuals,
magazines describing how to wage urban warfare and make homemade
bombs, and hate materials including videotapes of speeches by Adolf
Hitler, Ellison said.
   ``All the literature focused on just a litany of hate against
Jews, blacks and other minorities,'' Ellison said. ``They were
well-equipped to engage in major warfare.''
   ``Our preliminary indications are that these individuals are
related to the KKK and the Aryan Nation, added John Gordon, deputy
director of police operations at the Jacksonville Sheriff's Office.
   Arrested in Jacksonville on Friday were Michael Tubbs' brother,
John, and Stephen Fussell, a 26-year-old handyman. Both men face
federal firearms and conspiracy charges.
   The seizures and arrests resulted from a multi-state
investigation by federal and local agencies focusing on the theft
of weapons and explosives from military installations, Ellison
said.
   ``This investigation spans several states,'' Ellison said.
``We're talking about Tennessee, Kentucky, North Carolina and
Jacksonville.''
   Much of the firearms and explosives are believed to have been
stolen from U.S. Army posts at Fort Bragg and Fort Campbell,
Ellison said.
   The arsenal recovered at John Tubbs' home and a mini-warehouse
included Soviet AR-15 and U.S. M-16 automatic rifles, thousands of
rounds of ammunition, an anti-aircraft machine gun, anti-personnel
land mines, numerous handguns and shotguns, a 40mm grenade
launcher, hand grenades, smoke grenades, tear gas, dynamite,
blasting caps, booby traps and other high-explosives.
   Ellison and Gordon wouldn't comment on any possible motives the
four men had for stockpiling such destructive material.
   ``The investigation is still continuing, and there may be more
arrests in the future,'' Ellison said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0007 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 0142EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BayAreaNewspapers 3rdLd-Writethru a063 11-18 0488</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bay Area Newspapers, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0630,0574</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tentative Settlement Reached In Bay Area Newspaper Talks</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: INSERTS two grafs after 2nd graf, `management accepted ...'
with details of pact; picks up 3rd graf pvs, ` ``No strike! ...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By JACK SCHREIBMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN FRANCISCO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A tentative settlement was reached Saturday
to avert a strike at the San Francisco Bay area's three largest
newspapers, negotiators for both sides said.
   Management accepted a union proposal at 10 a.m. after
considering it during a short break in negotiations that went
through the night, said Richard Jordan, chief negotiator for the
San Francisco Newspaper Agency.
   The 45-month pact calls for a 3.5 percent to 4 percent annual
wage increase for all unions, according to a report in Sunday's
editions of the San Francisco Examiner. That amounts to $89 per
week more over the course of the contract for craft unions such as
printers and engravers, and $95 for reporters, editors and drivers.
   The contract also included benefits such as tax breaks for
working parents and, for Newspaper Guild employees, the right to
return to work part time after maternity or paternity leave.
Workers also won new protection against hand and arm injuries that
result from repetitive use of computers.
   ``No strike,'' Carl Hall, shop steward and Examiner reporter,
told cheering newspaper workers gathered at strike headquarters
Saturday morning.
   ``That's a group of people that were afraid they were going to
strike but now know they aren't,'' said Tom Wheelan, a driver for
the Examiner and the San Francisco Chronicle.
   The unions representing 4,500 employees at the San Francisco
Examiner, the San Francisco Chronicle and the San Jose Mercury News
had threatened to strike at 5 p.m. Friday. Instead, talks were
continued after both sides agreed that progress was being made.
   ``We're happy for all concerned that there's a settlement,''
Jordan said. ``I think both sides made concessions.''
   Jordan said the the federal mediator told him the union
negotiating committee was unanimously recommending the contract to
its members.
   Leaders of the 10 unions involved in the dispute planned to meet
Monday morning to set dates for ratification votes. Union leaders
indicated the votes would be taken after Thanksgiving.
   The agreement provides for an average $89 a week wage increase
over the term of the contract, which expires in November 1993,
Jordan said.
   Workers represented ranged from reporters and editors to
delivery drivers and press operators. Current top-scale pay is $801
a week for reporters and editors, $669 for clerical and library
workers and $675 for drivers.
   The three papers have a combined circulation of about 1 million.
   ``There were improvements in terms of child care and dependent
care and flexible spending programs,'' which allow a portion of
earnings to be shielded from taxes, Jordan said.
   Other details of the proposal were not immediately released.
   ``Apparently it's a good contract,'' Hall said.
   The negotiations didn't hamper production of the San Francisco
Chronicle and the San Jose Mercury News, both of which were at the
stands this morning. The afternoon San Francisco Examiner combines
with the Chronicle to print a Sunday paper.
   The San Francisco Newspaper Agency runs all departments of the
Chronicle and Examiner except for the news operations.
   San Francisco's last newspaper strike was in 1968 and lasted 55
days. The Mercury News was last struck in 1959, for four months.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0008 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 0511EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i BC-Bush-Europe 1stLd-Writethru a0658 11-18 0514</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Bush-Europe, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0658,630</SECOND>
<HEAD>Precede PRAGUE</HEAD>
<HEAD>Bush To Meet with Kohl, Mitterrand on Eve of Summit</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Tops with 4 grafs with Bush arrival in Germany</NOTE>
<HEAD>Precede PRAGUE</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TERENCE HUNT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP White House Correspondent</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>RAMSTEIN AIR BASE, Germany (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush, keeping the
Persian Gulf crisis at the top of his agenda, flew to Germany today
to meet with German Chancellor Helmut Kohl in advance of the
opening of a 34-nation summit in Paris.
   Bush was met here in a cold rain by Kohl and the two leaders
boarded a helicopter for a flight to Speyer, in Kohl's home region,
where Bush was to attend an organ recital in Speyer Cathedral and
speak in the town square.
   Kohl was then to take the U.S. president to his home in nearby
Ludwigshafen.
   Afterwards, Bush was flying to Paris for dinner with French
President Francois Mitterrand at the Elysee Palace. On Monday, Bush
will join Soviet President Mikhail S. Gorbachev in Paris for the
signing of a landmark treaty to slash non-nuclear weapons in
Europe. non-nuclear weapons in Europe.
   The signing ceremony will be followed immediately by the opening
of a three-day meeting of the 34-nation Conference of Security and
Cooperation, bringing former adversaries of the Cold War together
in a new era of reconciliation.
   Today's stop in Germany retraces some sites visited by Gorbachev
last weekend when he visited Kohl. Bush first will hear an organ
recital at an 11th-century cathedral in Speyer and then go to
Kohl's home in Oggersheim for lunch. A news conference is scheduled
before the meeting ends.
   Aside from the gulf, a prime topic for discussion was the
deteriorating political and economic situation in the Soviet Union,
which is braced for a winter of extreme shortages of food and fuel.
   Kohl announced last week that Germany will provide emergency
food aid to Moscow and he urged other Western nations to do the
same. U.S. officials said the Bush administration is developing
contingency plans to provide emergency supplies.
   From the start of his visit to Prague, Bush put a spotlight on
the gulf crisis, linking the past year of revolution in Europe to
the crisis in the Persian Gulf.
   ``I have this feeling in my heart that no peoples understand
better what is at stake in the gulf than Czechs and Slovaks,'' Bush
said.
   ``You know from your own bitter experience that the world cannot
turn a blind eye to aggression. You know the futility and vain hope
that aggressors can be appeased,'' he said.
   President Vaclav Havel said Czechoslovakia's own history ``has
taught us ample lessons about the consequences of appeasement.''
One-third of Czechoslovakia's territory was ceded in 1938 to the
Nazis in an unsuccessful attempt to prevent Adolf Hitler from
conquering other countries.
   A huge crowd braved cold temperatures and biting winds to see
Bush place a wreath at a memorial in Wenceslas Square, site of many
turning points in Czechoslovakia's turbulent history. Czechoslovak
television estimated the crowd at 150,000 but U.S. officials
claimed the turnout was much larger.
   ``America will not fail you in this decisive moment,'' Bush
promised the crowd. ``America will stand with you.''
   He delivered the same pledge earlier in a speech to the Federal
Assembly. And yet, Bush did not bring any major package of aid,
offering instead a modest package of incentives to spur U.S.
investment.
   Bush was unreserved in paying tribute to the reform movement
that toppled Czechoslovakia's communist rule in a revolution that
began last Nov. 17.
   ``That is why I am here today. We have not forgotten. And the
world will never forget what happened here in this square where the
history of freedom was written,'' the president assured the crowd.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0009 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 0629EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i BC-ArmsTreaty     11-18 0241</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Arms Treaty,0256</SECOND>
<HEAD>Text of Arms Agreement Approved</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARK J. PORUBCANSKY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>VIENNA, Austria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   NATO and Warsaw Pact negotiators Sunday
initialed a landmark treaty to slash non-nuclear weapons across
Europe.
   The initialling approves the text of the Conventional Forces in
Europe treaty, scheduled to be signed Monday in Paris by President
Bush, Soviet President Mikhail Gorbachev and representatives of 20
other nations in the two alliances.
   The leaders will be in Paris for a 34-nation summit of the
Conference on Security and Cooperation in Europe.
   The treaty, billed as the pact that formally ends the Cold War,
limits each alliance to 20,000 main battle tanks, 30,000 armored
combat vehicles, 20,000 artillery pieces, 6,800 fighter planes and
2,000 combat helicopters.
   The 70-page accord also regulates troops movements and permits
mutual inspections.
   Negotiators late Saturday finalized another document that
pledges a regular exchange of information on troop levels, arms
systems and deployment and military budgets, Austria's national
news agency APA reported.
   The pact is also scheduled to be signed Monday.
   The two documents were worked out after 20 months of
negotiations.
   Negotiators originally sought a deal on troop reductions, but
agreed to suspend the talks so the treaty could be ready for
signing in Paris.
   Delegates plan to reconvene in Vienna Nov. 29 to discuss
military personnel cuts.
   Hungarian officials said Thursday the Warsaw Pact, down to six
members after German unification, would cease to function as a
military alliance by July.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0010 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 0659EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i BC-Gulf-SoldierKilled     11-18 0147</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Gulf-Soldier Killed,0154</SECOND>
<HEAD>Soldier Killed In Traffic Accident</HEAD>
<DATELINE>IN EASTERN SAUDI ARABIA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A U.S. soldier was killed when a
truck he was riding in lost its brakes and crashed in eastern Saudi
Arabia, the U.S. military said Sunday.
   The soldier was the 47th member of the U.S. armed forces to die
during Operation Desert Shield since deployment began Aug. 7, five
days after Iraq invaded Kuwait. Most of the deaths have been in
accidents.
   The soldier was from the 101st Aviation Brigade, 8th Squadron,
the statement said. His name was not released pending notification
of his family.
   The military said it was investigating the late Saturday
accident. The five-ton truck was pulling a trailer and went off the
road, the military said.
   A U.S. military statement said the driver was treated for shock
and the other passenger suffered a broken finger. Their names were
not released.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0011 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 0858EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w BC-FrankHospitalized     11-18 0149</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Frank Hospitalized,100</SECOND>
<HEAD>Congressman Barney Frank Hospitalized for ``Probable Heart
Attack''</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Rep. Barney Frank has been hospitalized for
treatment of a ``probable heart attack'' according to an official
at a Boston hospital.
   The Massachusetts Democratic checked himself into Beth Israel
Hospital in Boston on Saturday evening ``after experiencing chest
pains,'' said Douglas Cahn, a spokesman for the congressman.
   ``He had a partial blockage in a major artery cleared last night
and is resting comfortably,'' Cahn said.
   ``He is in intensive care,'' said Judy Taylor, hospital
spokeswoman.
   Taylor said Frank ``is being treated for chest pains and a
probable heart attack.''
   Cahn said Frank ``was alert and conversing'' with family members
who visited him last night.
   Officials and aides did not say how long the five-term
congressman would be hospitalized.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0012 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 0955EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i BC-Bush-Kohl     11-18 0345</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Bush-Kohl,350</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush, Kohl Discuss Anti-Iraq Coalition in Brief News Conference</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TERENCE HUNT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP White House Correspondent</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>OGGERSHEIM, Germany (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush visited with
Chancellor Helmut Kohl on Sunday and called on Germany to help
``keep the coalition together'' in the Persian Gulf crisis. Bush
said a united Germany should be an economic power and ``a
tremendous force for peace.''
   Bush said he'd made no special request of Kohl to bolster
Germany's role in the anti-Iraq coalition. ``He made very clear
that he'd like to see a peaceful resolution to this question, and
so would I,'' Bush said.
   Kohl said, ``We talked about the challenge to the international
community in the Middle East ... we were in agreement that it is
very important indeed that the international community here stand
together, stand fast,'' against Iraq's invasion of Kuwait.
   In some radio remarks broadcast during Bush's visit, Kohl had
stressed the need to exhaust negotiations before commencing any
military action against Iraq. Bush told reporters he felt ``we're
together with Germany'' on matters involving the Gulf crisis.
   Bush downplayed the differing emphasis, saying, ``I think we're
in complete accord here.'' He added, ``We're not ruling any options
out,'' and not ruling any in.
   Standing with Bush among umbrellas in front of Kohl's family
home, the German chancellor said he ``would be most pleased to see
as many American companies as possible'' investing in the region
known until Oct. 3 as East Germany. Kohl said the German
unification ``would not have been possible, indeed would not have
been conceivable,'' without Bush's support.
   Kohl said ``the weather does not correspond at all to the kind
of mood'' between him and Bush.
   Bush thanked Kohl for his ``extraordinary hospitality,'' and
then the leaders took a few questions before giving in to the
elements.
   Bush stopped in Germany on Sunday for an afternoon visit en
route from Prague, Czechoslovakia to a three-day European summit in
Paris. On Monday, Bush and Soviet President Mikhail Gorbachev -
along with the leaders of 20 other nations - were to sign a
conventional forces treaty that reduces troop and arms levels in
Europe.
   From Paris, Bush was flying to Saudi Arabia and Egypt, two key
Arab allies in the Persian Gulf standoff against Iraq. He planned
to spend Thanksgiving Day with U.S. soldiers taking part in the
Desert Shield deployment.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0013 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 1048EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i BC-Bush-Kohl-Text     11-18 0720</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Bush-Kohl-Text,930</SECOND>
<HEAD>With BC-Bush-Europe</HEAD>
<DATELINE>OGGERSHEIM, Germany (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Following is a transcript of the news
conference by President Bush and Chancellor Helmut Kohl outside the
German leader's home:
   Kohl: Mr. President, Mrs. Bush, ladies and gentlemen, allow me
to thank you once again, very warmly, for having met with me here
in my home region. The weather doesn't correspond at all to the
kind of mood we're in and to the overall feeling. But unfortunately
November in Germany means rain but the relationship between the
Federal Republic of Germany and the United States of America is an
excellent one. And this is due first and foremost to the personal
involvement of President Bush.
   I've already said this in my short statement in front of Speyer
Cathedral. The third of October, 1990, the day of German unity,
would not have been possible, would indeed have been inconceivable
without the help and support which we received from the Americans
throughout the century - and we'll never forget this.
   Right now, over the next few years, over the next few decades,
indeed - we, the united Germany want to do our utmost in order to
foster and deepen this relationship, particularly among young
people. We want to promote the exchange of students, of high school
students, scientists, scholars, and this in the closest possible
way. And obviously Mr. President, I would be most pleased to see as
many American companies as possible investing in the new state -
the new federal lander, which was formally the German Democratic
Republic.
   I know that the President of the United States is a very busy
man, indeed, but if perhaps in one of your next speeches in front
of the Chamber of Industry and Commerce in the U.S., you were in a
position to introduce a few remarks about the possibilities of
investment in the Eastern part of Germany, in what was formally the
GDR, I think that would be a very good and very beneficial thing.
   Today we talked about a number of issues where we think we can
help each other. We exchanged views and we expressed agreement on
the fact that we hope that the next GATT round, the Uruguay Round,
may be a successful one.
   We're going to work on that one also over the next few weeks and
we talked about the challenge to the international community in the
Middle East, in Kuwait and in Iraq. We were in agreement here that
it is very important, indeed, that the international community
stand together here, stand fast and in a coalition, and this on the
basis of the UN resolutions in the sense that we want to see
respect for international law restored. And we were in agreement
that it is of utmost importance to see a release of all hostages of
all nationalities as soon as possible, and that this, indeed, was
one of the most important prerequisites for any further talks.
   We also said that it was wished that negotiations would lead to
a peaceful outcome of the situation there, but that these
negotiations can only be successful if both sides want their
success and if the consequences of this assault are removed.
   Again, Mr. President, thank you very much for coming here. Thank
you, Barbara. And with all my heart, let me wish you all the best
and the best of success in your very difficult office, and may God
bless you.
   Bush: Thank you, sir, and may we thank you and Mrs. Kohl for
your hospitality. There's something very special about conducting
the kind of discussions we had within the home of two friends in a
warm ambiance and in a setting that lends itself to frank and open
discussions and agreement, as the Chancellor's outlined. And again,
we're very grateful to you for this extraordinary hospitality.
Thank you all very much.
   Q: Mr. President, in your prepared speech today, you said that
Germany, a united Germany, must take responsibility for leadership
in the world. What would you like to see Germany do in the Persian
Gulf crisis?
   PRESIDENT BUSH: The German - I think exactly what Chancellor
Kohl says - keep the coalition together. In my view, they are
fulfilling their roles. And when I was talking about their
leadership, clearly, anybody that takes a look at the map and
understands the realities of the world knows that this united
Germany is, and will be, a tremendous force for peace and certainly
for economic good in the world.
   So I think we're together with Germany, both in the Gulf and - I
have no - I made no special request of Chancellor Kohl at all.
   But I agree with him that this coalition is holding, and should
continue to hold, and that's the best way to get a peaceful
solution - send a solid signal to Saddam Hussein that his
aggression will not be rewarded.
   Q: Do you think you see eye to eye?
   Kohl: (In English): One moment, please.
   Translator: Do you mind if we translated it? .
   Q: Do you think you see eye to eye on -
   Bush: Well, I've read what he's said, and I think we're in very
close accord here. And we're not ruling out any options; we're not
ruling any options in. I want to see a peaceful resolution of this
question.
   Q: Mr. Chancellor in a radio address today warned - (inaudible)
- the Gulf. Did he deliver a similar warning a similar warning to
you?
   Bush: He made very clear he'd like to see a peaceful resolution
to this question, and so would I.
   Kohl: Goodbye (in English).
   Bush: Thank you. A good way to do it. Thank you all.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>
</HEAD>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0014 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 1125EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i BC-Gulf-Exercise     11-18 0305</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Gulf-Exercise,0361</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bad Weather Forces Halt to Amphibious Exercise</HEAD>
<DATELINE>IN EASTERN SAUDI ARABIA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The key amphibious portion of the
Imminent Thunder military exercise was called off Sunday because of
bad weather, but troops in helicopters went ashore in a mock
assault.
   Military officials said the seaborne assault would have gone off
in wartime.
   ``In peactime, there are limitations and you don't want to lose
anybody,'' said Maj. Gen. Harry W. Jenkins, commanding officer of
the 4th Marine Expeditionary Brigade.
   It was not immediately clear when the amphibious landing would
be tried again.
   The helicopter assault and air exercises held on the fourth day
of Imminent Thunder went well, Jenkins told reporters in a media
pool covering the exercise.
   But Marine officers expressed disappointment that the key
amphibious portion of the mock invasion, held about 100 miles south
of the Kuwait border, was called off because of choppy waves
reaching 4 to 8 feet high.
   ``Whenever I don't get to do everything I try to do, that's a
disappointment,'' said Lt. Col. Robert P. McAleer, commanding
officer of the battalion of Marines involved in the drill. ``If we
had had a real-world situation, you always stretch the parameters
of what you can do and what you can't do.''
   The troops in the helicopter assault left the USS Guam despite
winds of 20 to 25 mph. Hovercraft aboard the USS Gunston Hall,
situated 25 miles from shore, were not dispatched because of high
waves.
   Among those who came ashore on helicopter gunships were 34 Saudi
Arabian Marines.
   U.S. and British warplanes provided simulated air support and
cover for the troops. No live ammunition was fired, officials said.
   Imminent Thunder, as the six-day exercises in the gulf are
named, involves about 1,000 troops and 1,100 aircraft - the largest
force of warplanes yet assembled for a Desert Shield exercise.
   The drill is meant to emphasize gaining control of the skies,
which would be critical to smash Iraqi defenses. A key objective of
the amphibious assualt had been to practice an attack from ships 30
miles from shore.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0015 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 1129EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i BC-Bush-Europe 7thLd-Writethru a0670 11-18 0922</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Bush-Europe, 7th Ld-Writethru, a0670,1,100</SECOND>
<NOTE>Eds: INSERTS graf 11, bgng, Following the xxx etc., to UPDATE with
Bush departure for Paris.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By TERENCE HUNT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP White House Correspondent</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SPEYER, Germany (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush today prodded Germany to
play a bigger role in the Persian Gulf showdown with Iraq, urging
this newly united and powerful nation to ``take responsibility for
leadership'' in the world.
   But German Chancellor Helmut Kohl cautioned against a military
solution, urging that ``everything be exhausted that there is to
exhaust with negotiations.''
   ``Whoever believes the problem can be solved militarily must
consider not only the mission, but the end of the whole
undertaking,'' Kohl said in a German radio interview aired shortly
after Bush arrived.
   Under pressure from the United States and other allies, Kohl has
agreed to provide $2.2 billion for the American and allied troop
buildup in the gulf. But citing constitutional barriers, Germany
has not sent any troops.
   ``As Europe forges a new future, Europe must not turn inward,''
the president said in prepared remarks.
   ``Just as a new Europe must look beyond its borders so too must
a united Germany take responsibility for leadership in our
commonwealth of nations,'' Bush said.
   Joining ohl to answer questions later outside the chancellor's
home, however, Bush said he had ``made no special request'' of the
German leader during their private talks about the Middle East.
   When asked what he meant by asserting that the newly reunified
Germany should assert leadership, he replied, ``In my view they are
fulfilling their role.'' He said he agreed with Kohl about the
importance of remaining unified against Saddam Hussein.
   `` ... So I think we're together with Germany in the gulf,''
Bush said.
   Bush said Kohl ``made very clear he'd like to see a peaceful
resolution to this question, and so would I.''
   Following the news conference, Bush departed Germany for a short
flight to Paris, where he joins 33 other leaders Monday for a
conference formally ending the Cold War.
   Earlier, the president was to deliver a speech to an outdoor
audience but was forced to cut it short because of a heavy
downpour. ``The rains are coming so I will conclude mercifully,''
Bush said.
   ``The nations of Europe have overcome conflict and the
partitions that are its bitter fruits,'' Bush said in the prepared
text. ``Now by working together, in the spirit of unity and
determination, we can help achieve the same for the world.''
   Bush arrived at Ramstein Air Force Base to be greeted by Kohl
and a crowd of 400 people braving pouring rain and powerful winds.
The two leaders and their wives then flew by helicopter to the 11th
century cathedral town of Speyer in Kohl's home region.
   Bush began his eight-day tour of Europe and the Mideast on
Saturday with a one-day stop in Prague, becoming the first American
president to visit Czechoslovakia.
   He told reporters flying with him from Prague to Germany that
his visit was ``very moving and very emotional and very good.''
   Bush said Havel's denunciation of the Iraqi invasion of Kuwait
``should be well noted around the world. This country
(Czechoslovakia) has learned it means to be taken over. It just
redoubles my conviction that aggression can't stand.''
   Kohl said it was very important to maintain Western solidarity
in isolating Iraqi leader Saddam Hussein and he urged intensive
efforts so that Iraq quickly frees all foreign hostages.
   Once the hostages are free, he said, ``the chance for
negotiations is far greater.''
   Asked about the firing on Friday of Soviet Prime Minister
Nikolai I. Rhyzhkov by President Mikhail S. Gorbachev, Bush said,
``Very interesting. We'll have a chance to talk to Mr. Gorbachev
about all of that.''
   Bush and Gorbachev will meet over breakfast Tuesday in Paris
amid a 34-nation summit of East and West countries. The two leaders
also will get together Monday morning for the signing of a historic
treating slashing non-nuclear weapons in Europe.
   Bush said the arms treaty ``seems to be overshadowed by what's
happening in the gulf. But it is a significant milestone.''
   On another subject, Bush was asked about reports that William
Bennett, who resigned as national drug control director, will
become chairman of the Republican National Committee.
   Bush smiled and said, ``We're not discussing that. A lot happens
when I leave.''
   Bush's first stop was an organ recital at the Speyer Cathedral,
from where he was proceeding to Kohl's home for lunch.
   In his speech Bush said the revolutions in Europe had brought
``a peaceful conclusion to the divisions of the Cold War.''
   And yet, Bush said, ``New challenges to peace and freedom are
arising from distant shores.
   ``If the world rewards naked aggression; if we ignore the
proliferation of the technologies of mass destruction; if we
conclude that these challenges are not everyone's concern - then we
put at risk everything we have achieved,'' Bush said.
   The president said that ``no people on earth are more thrilled
by your achievement than your friends in America. ... German unity
came, in part, because Americans stood by the free people of
Berlin, from the daredevil pilots of the airlift to a young
president who made his bold declaration on a windswept day before
the Wall.'' He was referring to President John F. Kennedy's 1963
speech at the Berlin Wall.
   Bush also saluted Kohl as ``the man who united Germany.'' Kohl
is facing national elections in two weeks in a bid to become the
first chancellor of a united Germany.
   Aside from the gulf, a prime topic for discussion with Kohl was
the deteriorating political and economic situation in the Soviet
Union, which is braced for a winter of food and fuel shortages.
   Kohl announced last week that Germany will provide emergency
food aid to Moscow and he urged other Western nations to do the
same. The Bush administration is developing contingency plans to
provide emergency supplies.
   From the start of his visit to Prague, Bush put a spotlight on
the gulf crisis, linking it to the past year of revolution in
Europe.
   ``I have this feeling in my heart that no peoples understand
better what is at stake in the gulf than Czechs and Slovaks,'' Bush
said.
   President Havel said Czechoslovakia's own history ``has taught
us ample lessons about the consequences of appeasement.'' One-third
of Czechoslovakia's territory was ceded in 1938 to the Nazis in a
vain attempt to prevent Adolf Hitler from conquering other
countries.
   ``America will not fail you in this decisive moment'' of the
difficult transition from communism to a free market economy, Bush
promised a giant crowd which braved bad weather to attend a rally
at Wenceslas Square Saturday. ``America will stand with you.''
   And yet, Bush did not bring any major aid, offering instead a
modest package of incentives to spur U.S. investment.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0016 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 1140EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-India-Punjab     11-18 0358</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-India-Punjab,0422</SECOND>
<HEAD>Sikh Extremists Kill 43 in Weekend Attacks</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DEEPAK SHARMA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>AMRITSAR, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Sikh extremists demanding independence
for Punjab state killed at least 43 people in a series of attacks
over the weekend, police and news agencies reported Sunday.
   At least 2,830 people have been killed by Sikh militants in
Punjab so far this year. It is the highest yearly toll since the
violent separatist campaign started in 1982.
   A Sikh religious leader and five devotees were fatally wounded
by three Sikh gunmen at a worship service Saturday night at
Balachaur, 100 miles southeast of Amritsar, Press Trust of India
said.
   In another Saturday night attack, four Sikhs approached a police
checkpoint where a Sikh constable greeted them as relatives and
invited them to meet his colleagues, a district police official
said.
   While the group was having tea at the checkpoint near
Hararkalan, 18 miles north of Amritsar, one of the visitors pulled
out an assault rifle and killed five of the six policemen, said
Paramjit Singh, the senior superintendent of police.
   The Sikh constable fled with the killer, said Singh, who spoke
by telephone from district police headquarters in Majitha. He said
four of the slain policemen were Sikhs and the fifth was a
Christian.
   Shortly after sunrise Saturday, Sikh gunmen ambushed a group of
Hindu fundamentalists exercising in a park on the Punjab-Haryana
state border. Nine men were slain and a 10th died of shock during
the attack at Quillewali, 120 miles south of Amritsar, police said.
   Sikh extremists staged a series of other attacks around Punjab
state during the weekend. The victims included Sikh policemen,
their relatives and a Hindu man who was pulled off a bus, Press
Trust and United News of India reported.
   Sikhs, whose faith has roots in both Hinduism and Islam, form
only 2 percent of India's 880 million people, but they have a
slight majority over Hindus in Punjab. Amritsar, in northern
Punjab, is the site of the holiest shrine in the Sikh faith, the
Golden Temple.
   The militants want to establish a Sikh nation, called Kalistan,
or Land of the Pure, in the prosperous farming state on thet
Pakistani border. The militants accuse Hindus, who make up 82
percent of India's population, of discriminating against them
politically and economically.
   Initially, they generally targeted Hindus. But in recent years
they have escalated attacks against Sikhs who serve in the police
forces or who are not considered militant enough.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0017 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 1143EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Soviet-Priest     11-18 0185</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Priest,0209</SECOND>
<HEAD>Orthodox Priest Murdered in Ukraine</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Russian Orthodox priest in the Ukraine was shot
and killed by unknown assailants, the Tass news agency said Sunday.
It was the second killing of an Orthodox priest in three months.
   Tass quoted police as saying that Ivan Kuz, a priest in the
Western Ukrainian village of of Bynliv, was hit by three bullets
fired at close range. His body was discovered in a forest by
residents of the nearby town of Vizhnitsa.
   The report said the priest was seen driving his car to a
religious service in a neighboring district. ``The burnt car was
discovered near the village of Valyava,'' Tass said.
   The motive for the slaying was not known. Tass said police had
ruled out robbery.
   In September, Alexander Menn, a prominent Russian Orthodox
priest and writer who was persecuted for his evangelical
activities, was bludgeoned to death with an ax while on his way to
church.
   Menn's body had been found near his house not far from a railway
station in Zagorsk, the site of an ancient monastery that is a
showplace of the Russian Orthodox Church, Tass reported at the
time.
   Menn's slaying has not been solved.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0018 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 1145EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-ParisSummit Bjt   11-18 0586</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Paris Summit, Bjt,670</SECOND>
<HEAD>Summit Marks Cold War's End, But Threat of Gulf War Looms</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVID CRARY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   East and West meet this week determined to set a
peaceful course for Europe after four decades of tension, but the
celebrations of the Cold War's end are clouded by threat of war in
the Persian Gulf.
   Leaders of the 34 nations of the Conference on Security and
Cooperation in Europe converged Sunday on Paris, where their
three-day summit opens Monday.
   ``For the first time in 40 years,'' said Secretary of State
James A. Baker III, ``Europe will be meeting and discussing and
planning without an artificial East-West divide to block
progress.''
   The nations meet ``at a time when they have an absolutely new
European space in front of them, an absolutely new state of
things,'' said Vitaly Ignatenko, spokesman for Soviet President
Mikhail Gorbachev.
   French Foreign Minister Roland Dumas, describing the summit as
the most important international event since World War II, said it
will ``design the architecture of Europe for the century to come.''
   On Monday, the leaders of NATO and the six nations of the
lifeless Warsaw Pact will sign a treaty slashing arsenals of tanks,
helicopters and other conventional weapons.
   The text of the final summit document has been worked out in
advance, ensuring closer cooperation among the onetime adversaries.
U.S. and French officials say major last-minute modifications are
unlikely.
   Talks on the fringes of the summit could eclipse the conference
itself, focusing on the crisis spawned by Iraq's invasion of
Kuwait. Just as Europe settled into its embrace of peace, the gulf
crisis put much of the world on a heightened military footing.
   President Bush will meet privately with a host of leaders allied
with the United States against Iraq, including Gorbachev, French
President Francois Mitterrand and British Prime Margaret Thatcher.
   The summit will produce sideshows as well.
   Some leaders arrive in Paris under severe domestic political
pressure.
   Thatcher and Mitterrand's premier, Michel ocard, both face
votes by Parliament members during the summit that conceivably
could topple them. Gorbachev continues to struggle against
rebellious politicians and economic troubles.
   Dozens of prominent French people, including a pop singer and a
Catholic bishop, are organizing a rally in Paris on Monday to
protest the deployment of Western troops in the Gulf.
   Monitoring protests will be one of many tasks facing the
10,000-strong security force contingent assigned to the summit.
Anti-terrorist squads, including rooftop snipers, will be deployed,
and thousands of policemen will seal off several blocks around the
conference center, barring any pedestrian or motorist who lacks a
special pass.
   The Conference for Security and Cooperation in Europe was
created with the signing of the 1975 Helsinki Final Act. One result
of the summit will be to institutionalize the CSCE, setting up a
small secretariat in Prague, a center in Vienna for the prevention
of conflict, and an office in Warsaw to help monitor elections.
   The summit document also includes the recommendation that the
heads of member states meet at least once every two years, their
foreign ministers annually and senior officials even more often.
   France is proposing creation of some sort of conciliation
process to resolve differences between member states regarding
ethnic minorities.
   Several participants have stressed that they do not want too
firm a structure for the CSCE to prevent overlapping with NATO and
the European Community.
   ``Let's avoid creating useless structures, whether they be
duplicates of those that already exist or whether their functions
are insufficiently defined,'' Dumas said.
   A conservative Swedish newspaper, Svensa Dagbladet, said in an
editorial that a possible European confederation ``is best built on
the foundation Brussels has laid (the European Community), rather
than the looser CSCE process.''
   Between the formal summit sessions - primarily speeches by the
34 leaders - and the private consultations, most of the
participants will have little leisure time. The one major social
occasion on the agenda is a dinner Tuesday at the chateau of
Versailles, preceded by a ballet performance.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0019 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 1145EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-ParisSummit-List     11-18 0139</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Paris Summit-List,150</SECOND>
<HEAD>With AM-Paris Summit, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here is list of the participants in the Conference
on Security and Cooperation in Europe, which opens Monday in Paris,
in the order in which their leaders will give speeches:
   1. Canada
   2. Italy
   3. Malta
   4. United States
   5. Denmark
   6. Soviet Union
   7. Czechoslovakia
   8. Switzerland
   9. Portugal
   10. Great Britain
   11. Sweden
   12. Netherlands
   13. The Vatican
   14. Turkey
   15. Germany
   16. Poland
   17. Hungary
   18. Yugoslavia
   19. Spain
   20. Belgium
   21. Iceland
   22. Austria
   23. Cyprus
   24. Greece
   25. Ireland
   26. France
   27. Romania
   28. San Marino
   29. Norway
   30. Finland
   31. Monaco
   32. Luxembourg
   33. Liechtenstein
   34. Bulgaria
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0020 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 1147EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Thailand-Grave Bjt   11-18 0528</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Thailand-Grave, Bjt,0653</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mass WWII Grave Found Near Site of `Bridge Over the River Kwai'</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto BK1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TAVORN TUMMACHARTVIJIT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>KANCHANABURI, Thailand (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A mass grave has been discovered
near the site where more than 100,000 Asian slave workers and
Allied prisoners died building a railroad for the Japanese during
World War II.
   The remains of several hundred people have been dug up since
Tuesday, when the excavation began. It is being carried out by the
Pothipawana Songkroh Foundation, which for religious reasons wants
to provide proper burials.
   Several dozen workers were digging Sunday in a sugar cane field
in Kanchanaburi province, about 70 miles west of Bangkok. One skull
was left out overnight - but workers first covered it with paper so
it would not be cold.
   About half the small plot has been excavated.
   The mass grave is about three miles from a bridge made famous in
the 1957 Hollywood movie, ``Bridge Over the River Kwai,'' which
celebrated the heroism of the war captives.
   A foundation official, Santi Assawaseeyotin, said it appeared
the bones had been ``dumped into the ground, because they were
found in some disorder.''
   Santi said the bones were dating back to the World War II era.
   ``We believe they were bones of Asian people as the skulls found
were not big,'' he said. ``There also were children's bones.''
   He said the remains were being brought to the foundation's
office in Bangkok, where they will be cleaned and cremated.
   There was no direct evidence the bones belonged to the World War
II prisoners. No such remains have been found in Kanchanaburi in
recent years.
   Also recovered were metal plates and bowls; on the back of
several were written Made in Japan or Made in Hong Kong. The
Bangkok Post newspaper said some had the year 1939 imprinted on
them.
   More than 100,000 Chinese, Indian, Malay, Burmese and other
Asian slave laborers lost their lives building the railway in
1942-43, along with more than 16,000 British, Dutch, Australian,
American, and New Zealand prisoners of war.
   They died of disease, malnutrition, exhaustion, beatings and
executions.
   The Japanese had the 268-mile line connecting Thailand and Burma
built for their planned invasion of India.
   Ladda Matcha, 38, who lives near the grave, said the owner of a
motorcyle repair shop also near there recently dreamed that the
dead told him they could not breathe and asked him for help.
   The man contacted the foundation, whose representatives secured
permission from the landowner to dig, Mrs. Ladda said. The owner
knew of the remains on her plot, but used it to grow sugar cane.
   Mrs. Ladda's mother, Pab Borngern, 77, said the Japanese
constructed a military camp and tunnel in the area during the war.
   ``When the Indians (workers) died, they just carried them into
the hole they dug up,'' she said. ``At the place where they found
the bones, that was thousands of people buried there. Those peple
died because of fever.''
   The Bangkok Post quoted the landowner's sister, Lek Pailom, 64,
as saying field hospitals for Asian slave workers were in the area.
   ``Every morning, the Indians dug a hole in this area to bury
dead bodies in the evening,'' she said. ``Some days, two or three
bodies were buried, some days more than five.''
   ``This happened throughout the period of the railway
construction,'' she said.
   The discovery of the remains came just before the annual 11-day
River Kwai Bridge Festival. This major tourist attraction of
special shows and exhibitions is scheduled to begin Friday.
   In March, Prime Minister Chatichai Choonhavan responded to
objections by Australian veterans groups and Prime Minister Bob
Hawke by barring shows that a tourism company planned along the
railway. They were to have featured Japanese soldiers supervising
work gangs.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0021 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 1149EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-MoscowArt     11-18 0341</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Moscow Art,370</SECOND>
<HEAD>Five Centuries of Moscow's Art Treasures Go On Display in
Washington</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT M. ANDREWS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Some of Moscow's most precious art treasures
went on display at the Smithsonian Institution in a major
U.S.-Soviet venture celebrating the rich cultural heritage of the
Soviet capital over the past five centuries.
   The exhibition's more than 200 objects span the creative life of
Moscow from a late 15th century icon portraying the ``Miracle of
St. George and the Dragon'' to modern abstract paintings by Vasily
Kandinsky and Kazimir Malevich.
   The show was welcomed Friday to Washington by Robert McC. Adams,
secretary of the Smithsonian Institution, and Soviet Minister of
Culture Nikolay Gubenko, who called it a ``great event'' in
fostering closer ties between Soviet and American citizens.
   Viewing the exhibit will give Americans a chance to ``feel the
Russian soul'' after centuries of mutual ignorance and
estrangement, said Gubenko, a former movie director and artistic
director of Moscow's Taganka Theater, where he still performs as an
actor on weekends.
   The paintings, sculptures, engravings, religious icons,
porcelains, jewelry, ancient weapons and armor, jeweled masterworks
of gold and silver, historic costumes, maps and other objects were
loaned by the State Kremlin Museums, the State History Museum, the
State Tretyakov Gallery and other collections in Moscow.
   Among them is an altar cross of gold and precious gems made in
the Kremlin workshops in 1562 and presented by Czar Ivan IV -
``Ivan the Terrible'' - to the Solovetsky Monastery in northern
Russia.
   Other objects include a 16th century steel helmet that once
belonged to Ivan's son and heir, and a plate made in 1694 of gold,
emeralds and rubies that was given to young Tsarevich Aleksey, son
of Peter the Great, by his grandmother.
   The exhibition, titled ``Moscow: Treasures and Traditions,''
will appear in the International Gallery of the Smithsonian's S.
Dillon Ripley Center on the National Mall until Feb. 3. This is the
second and final stop for the show, which opened last summer in
Seattle.
   Underwritten by The Boeing Co., the show was organized by the
Smithsonian Institution Traveling Exhibition Service and the Soviet
Ministry of Culture in association with the Seattle Art Museum and
the Seattle organizing committee of the 1990 Goodwill Games.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0022 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 1155EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-FaeroeIslands     11-18 0275</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Faeroe Islands,0308</SECOND>
<HEAD>Socialists Beat Conservative Coalition in Faeroese Poll</HEAD>
<DATELINE>COPENHAGEN, Denmark (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The main opposition party made a
strong showing in parliamentary elections in the Faeroe Islands,
and the party's leader said he planned to form a new government,
Danish public radio said Sunday.
   The incumbent conservative coalition led by Prime Minister
Jogvan Sundstein lost four of its 21 seats in Saturday's balloting,
while Former Prime Minister Atli Dam's Social Democrats gained
three, the radio said.
   The Social Democrats now hold 10 of the 32 legislative seats in
the self-governing territory, which is under the Danish crown.
Sundstein's rightist People's Party holds only seven.
   Dam, who was prime minister for three four-year terms between
1970 and 1988, said he planned to form a new coalition government
with one or two of the other main parties.
   ``We will talk with all the parties. There are many coalition
possibilities,'' Dam said in a radio interview.
   There was no immediate comment from Sundstein.
   The Faeroese constitution forbids minority administrations, and
the government must command at least 17 seats.
   The elections, only the second early poll in 40 years, were
called to break a political deadlock on how to rescue the
foundering economy.
   Sunstein's People's Party, which came to power in the 1988
ballot and formed a coalition with the Unionist and the Republican
parties, dropped one seat in the election.
   The volcanic archipelago of 18 islands located about halfway
between Scotland and Iceland in the North Sea has a population of
47,000.
   The six parties represented in the Loegting, or parliament, are
split both ideologically along left-right lines and on the question
of separation from Denmark.
   At 85.9 percent, turnout among the 330 eligible voters was
slightly lower than it had been in the past four elections.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0023 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 1157EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-ABakery'sWoes Bjt   11-18 0560</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-A Bakery's Woes, Bjt,0700</SECOND>
<HEAD>Famous Moscow Bakery Struggles to Survive</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto MOSB2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ANDREW KATELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Rain seeps through cracks in the ceiling and
spiders spin webs above vats of dough at Bread Factory No. 14, once
the Filipov Bakery, whose raisin buns have been famous since
czarist times.
   Women and teen-agers toil at open ovens, with no protective
gloves or masks. They work in a rat-infested neighborhood and live
in crowded dormitories.
   Managers of the 150-year-old bakery, one of 33 in Moscow, say
they want to make improvements but are caught between the
dissolving structure of Soviet Communism and a new economic order
not yet formed.
   The bakery's plight illustrates the difficulties Soviet
businesses and workers face in converting from a centrally planned
to a market economy.
   Leonid Vorobyev, the bread factory's 47-year-old director, is
trying to figure out how to fit into the plan the Soviet
legislature adopted Oct. 19 for switching to a market economy.
   He also is pondering how to attract foreign capital to modernize
the bakery, how much to pay his workers and how much to charge his
customers when prices are freed from their artificially low fixed
levels.
   Vorobyev is worried, and so are his employees.
   In a stormy meeting with the workers, who demanded to know what
their salaries and positions would be, he said: ``Give me results
and the money will be there.''
   The manager, who has been in the baking industry 25 years, said
in an interview afterward: ``We and they are afraid of a (free)
market. What will it be like?''
   Under current conditions, it's amazing the bakery produces
anything edible.
   Economic planner Tatiana Zimina said the 200 workers make 20
tons of baked goods daily, using worn-out equipment 20 years old.
There are 19 varieties, from white bread to the famous raisin
rolls.
   Rats that infest the neighborhood are attracted by the aroma of
baking bread and by flour spilled on the floor.
   Bakery workers, 70 percent of whom are women, have no machines
for moving sugar, margarine and flour from heavy steel vats to the
mixers, so they do it by hand.
   Those who work the unsealed ovens have the worst job.
   Blasts of hot air pound their faces. The only ventilation is a
window that cannot be fully opened because too much heat would be
drawn from the ovens.
   The women, some with scars from burns on their arms and hands,
slit the tops of molded loaves with knives and slide them into the
ovens on trays.
   Because of the difficult conditions, pay averaging $324 a month,
and a six-day week, the bakery has trouble attracting workers and
is 40 people short. Most employees are older women or teen-agers.
   A vacant apartment building next to Bread Factory No. 14 looks
as if it had been bombed or is in the process of being razed, with
broken glass, dirt and plaster piled knee-deep on the floors.
   In August, a construction crew digging nearby cut a natural gas
pipeline, forcing the bakery to shut down for a few days.
   Vorobyev and his fellow managers want to hire their own drivers,
bypassing unreliable state truckers, and are negotiating with
foreign companies to renovate the plant.
   They also are negotiating with the Soviet bureaucracy to improve
working conditions and keep more of the profit, most of which now
goes to government ministries. Workers got pay raises in September.
   Ms. Zimina said her goal is for the workers to own the factory.
   ``We dream about privatization,'' she said, but added that
bureaucrats stand in the way.
   The Russian republic's government approved private ownership of
many factories in September, but the bread ministry later excluded
large bakeries, including Factory No. 14.
   Another difficult problem is changing the psychology of workers,
many of whom seem disinterested in increasing production or
streamlining the operation.
   The factory's bookkeeper, a powerful employee in a Soviet
business, is 78 and not enthusiastic about change, Ms. Zimina said,
adding:
   ``How can she do anything new or fight the bureaucracy?''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0024 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 1203EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i BC-Bush-Schedule     11-18 0092</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Bush-Schedule,100</SECOND>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Here is a brief look at President Bush's schedule for Monday, as
he continues his eight-day trip to Europe and Saudi Arabia:
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>Paris, France</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Breakfast with British Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher.
   Signing of a treaty cutting conventional forces in Europe.
   Opening session of summit meeting of leaders from the 34 nations
in the Conference on Security and Cooperation in Europe.
   News conference.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0025 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 1208EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-ScotusNotebook Bjt   11-18 0443</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Scotus Notebook, Bjt,520</SECOND>
<HEAD>A Supreme Court `Photo Op' Goes Uncaptured</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RICHARD CARELLI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Call it the photo opportunity that got away -
and a rare one at that.
   When Justice David H. Souter replaced the retired William J.
Brennan, the court's nine members gathered for an official portrait
taken by a photographer for National Geographic magazine.
   Photographers and camera crews from various news organizations
also were invited for the session but waited in another room until
the official shot had been taken.
   At one point, while the National Geographic photographer changed
some equipment, the prim and proper Justice Sandra Day O'Connor,
standing behind a seated Justice Byron R. White, struck a pose
found in countless family albums.
   She stealthily raised her right hand close to White's head and
extended her index and middle fingers. To eyewitnesses standing in
front of the black-robed justices it fleetingly appeared that
White, the court's gruff senior member, had grown rabbit ears.
   O'Connor, who once agreed with a friend's assessment that ``with
Sandra there ain't no Miller time,'' may be heeding the
much-publicized advice she received years ago from former
Washington Redskins running back John Riggins at a black-tie
dinner. ``Loosen up, Sandy baby,'' she was told.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   ---
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Not Much to Argue About</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Since beginning its 1990-91 term last month, the court has been
spending less time on the bench hearing oral arguments due to a
shortage of available cases. The justices' increased selectivity
last spring is why.
   The number of cases that have arrived since Oct. 1 - more than
1,800 - is running slightly higher this term than last. And the
justices have granted full review to 44 so far, a few more than
last term.
   But when the current term began, only 57 cases were available to
be argued, compared to the 81 available the previous October, and
the 105 the year before.
   Some court watchers are grumbling about those cases granted. The
legal issues they raise seem comparatively lackluster, some say.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>---</BYLINE>
<HEAD>Don't Call Him Chief</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   The court is very close to announcing the man selected to head
its 76-member police force. The new top cop's title, however, will
not be the same as his retired predecessor. ``Chief of Police'' has
been scrapped in favor of ``Inspector.'' It seems one chief is
enough for the court, although the duplication never bothered Chief
Justice William H. Rehnquist.
   The same may not have been true for retired Chief Justice Warren
E. Burger. During his tenure, the police force's leader was called
Captain.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>---</BYLINE>
<HEAD>Souter Has Three Clerks, No Permanent Secretary</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Justice Souter now has three law clerks and has hired a fourth
who will join his staff soon.
   The three already on board, and their respective law schools,
are Paul Salamanca of Boston College, John Sullivan of Columbia
University and Peter Spiro of the University of Virginia.
   Salamanca has to be one of the nation's luckiest young lawyers.
When he took a job with Souter some months ago he expected to be
working for a newly seated and little-known member of the
Boston-based 1st U.S. Circuit Court of Appeals.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0026 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 1220EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Lebanon     11-18 0400</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lebanon,0463</SECOND>
<HEAD>President Makes First Visit to Christian Heartland Since Election</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BEIRUT, Lebanon (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Elias Hrawi crossed into
Lebanon's Christian heartland Sunday, his first such visit since
his election a year ago and a dramatic illustration that the city's
dividing lines are eroding.
   The Syrian-backed Hrawi, a Maronite Catholic, attended Mass in
the chapel of Maronite Patriarch Nasrallah Sfeir's seat in Bkirki,
12 miles north of Beirut.
   A convoy of jeeps carrying troops swept ahead of the president's
shining black, bullet-proof Mercedes as it passed through the
Museum crossing, once the only link between the mainly Moslem and
Christian sectors of the sprawling metropolitan area.
   The motorcade sped without incident through streets lined with
scores of battle-scarred, high-rise apartment buildings used as
sniper nests during 15 years of civil war.
   At Bkirki, known for its soaring statue of the Virgin Mary,
Hrawi sat in the front row of worshipers.
   Sfeir warned in his sermon against the ``domination by one side
over the other, which could tip the balance required for peaceful
coexistance.''
   Hrawi and Sfeir then held a 40-minute conference behind closed
doors. The president said afterward, ``We have reached an
understanding over all issues facing the nation. My government will
be fair to all.''
   The patriarch's sermon appeared to reflect fears among the
Maronite community, their ranks depleted by a year of fighting in
their heartland, that a peace plan brokered by the Arab League to
end the civil war might herald Moslem domination of power.
   It was within the framework of that peace accord that Hrawi was
elected president by parliament last Nov. 24.
   In September, he signed into law constitutional reforms
envisaged by the plan that gave Moslems an equal share of power
with the Christians.
   The Maronites, the largest Christian sect, have dominated the
government, army, parliament, judiciary and financial sector since
Lebanon gained independence from France in 1943, when they were
thought to be the majority.
   The Moslems, who now make up about 55 percent of Lebanon's 4
million inhabitants, have pressed for equality in the civil war
that claimed more than 150,000 lives since 1975.
   On Oct. 13, Hrawi's army backed by Syrian troops crushed an
11-month mutiny against his government by rebel Christian Gen.
Michel Aoun. That removed the last obstacle facing the peace plan.
   The Syrians maintain 40,000 troops in Lebanon under a 1976 Arab
League peacekeeping mandate.
   After Aoun's ouster, Hrawi's government dismantled Beirut's
Green Line and reopened nearly all crossings between the Moslem and
Christian sectors.
   It also set a deadline of midnight Monday as a deadline for
Moslem and Christian militias to evacuate the capital and its
environs to proclaim a unified ``greater Beirut.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0027 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 1223EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Israel-Politics     11-18 0506</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel-Politics,0587</SECOND>
<HEAD>Protests as Cabinet Approves Religious Legislation</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GWEN ACKERMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Cabinet overrode opposition protests and
approved legislation Sunday to restrict ``indecent advertising''
and public transport on Jewish holy days.
   Prime Minister Yitzhak Shamir agreed to the measures to draw the
ultra-orthodox Agudat Israel party into his coalition government
   A coalition agreement signed Friday also provides for
restrictions on abortion and a ban on the breeding and sale of
pork, in line with Jewish religious law.
   The curbs on advertising and transport were approved for
parliamentary scrutiny with only one vote against, by Agriculture
Minister Rafael Eitan. Agudat Israel has been promised speedy
passage of the laws through the Knesset (parliament).
   The law on transport will forbid buses to operate between
sundown Friday and sundown Saturday and high holidays - a measure
strongly opposed by those who travel to and from remote settlements
on weekends.
   Currently, buses generally do not run on holy days. But those
serving outlying areas have to set out before the holy day is
finished in order to meet their schedules.
   The law on advertising is supposed to curb nudity on public
billboards, and carries a six-month prison term for offenders.
   Such an ad is defined in the coalition agreement as ``a picture
of naked men and women, a picture containing a stimulation of
sexual arousal or a temptation to commit sexual relations, or a
picture of nude parts of the body which offends the religious
belief or feelings of the public... or which harms minors or their
education.''
   Bus stops and billboards featuring scantily clad women have
frequently been defaced by orthodox Jews seeking to impose their
moral code on Israel's secular majority.
   Fifteen members of the liberal Shinui (Change) party protested
outside the Cabinet office, and the socialist Kibbutz Arzi
movement, representing some 80 socialist kibbutzim (collective
farms), warned the legislation could lead to a ``cultural war''
between secular and religious Jews.
   Shinui legislator Avraham Poraz claimed Shamir's Likud Bloc was
``selling the secular public to Agudat Israel,'' and that the laws
``will take us back to the Middle Ages.''
   Health Minister Ehud Olmert acknowledged the laws were
unpopular, but said: ``In the present political circumstances, we
have no choice but to pay this price.''
   Roni Slavtau, director-general of the Advertisers' Union, said
the curb on advertising was ill-defined.
   ``What is indecent? If they define as indecent ads of high
esthetic value that fulfill different cultural criteria of the 20th
century, there will be some disagreement here,'' he said.
   Legislator Shulamit Aloni, head of the left-wing Citizen Rights
Movement, said the new laws were aimed ``to force us into chains of
coercion. I am very, very worried.''
   Little criticism was heard from the main opposition, the Labor
Party, which had offered Agudat Israel much the same legislation
when it was trying to form a coalition with the party.
   Agudat Israel's four seats give Shamir's right-wing coalition a
majority in the 120-member Parliament. Since it was formed in June,
the government has ruled with 60 seats, plus tacit support from the
two members of the rightist Moledet (Homeland) party.
   However, the respite may not last. Eitan's two-member Tzomet
(Crossroad) party is dissatisfied that the government has not met
his demand for electoral reform.
   Shas, a six-member religious party, is threatening to quit the
coalition, saying it is dissatisfied with the government's handling
of Arab-Israeli peace efforts.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0028 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 1240EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SouthAfrica     11-18 0397</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-South Africa,0457</SECOND>
<HEAD>Seven Killed in Scattered Violence</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JOHANNESBURG, South Africa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Seven people died in scattered
violence nationwide, including two after a clash between police and
protesters in Johannesburg, police and news reports said Sunday.
   African National Congress leader Nelson Mandela, meanwhile,
urged supporters to step up a campaign of strikes, protests and
other mass action to force an end to apartheid.
   ``We are a forgiving people but we are not slaves,'' Mandela
told 15,000 cheering, singing people at a stadium south of
Johannesburg. ``My call to you is to intensify the struggle. ...
Boycotts, stayaways, strikes civil disobedieance, marches and
meetings are all legitimate peaceful means of struggle.''
   Police fired tear gas, rubber bullets and birdshot on Saturday
when about 700 protesters in the Johannesburg city center ignored
an order to disperse and hurled bottles and stones.
   Two people died of gunshot wounds in a hospital late Saturday
night, police said. At least fifteen people were injured, including
eight protesters, six police officers and a traffic officer, police
said.
   The government-run South African Broadcasting Corp. said one
policeman was seriously injured and six police vehicles were
extensively damaged.
   The protesters had planned to march against black leaders in
townships, but police banned the march. Many blacks allege the
councils collaborate with the white-led government to perpetuate
the apartheid system of segregation.
   President F.W. de Klerk has pledged to end apartheid and
negotiate a new constitution that would give the black majority a
share of political power.
   But Mandela on Sunday accused the government of calling for
reform while trying to preserve political and economic power for
the white minority.
   A man was shot to death Sunday in the black township of Soweto
while on his way to a rally by the conservative Inkatha Freedom
Party. Police said the unidentified assailants fled.
   Fighting pitting Zulu supporters of Inkatha against Xhosa and
other blacks linked to the ANC has killed more than 800 people in
Johannesburg townships since August. The clashes have eased
recently.
   In an unrest report for the previous 24 hours, police said
Sunday that three people died in separate incidents throughout the
country.
   One man was shot to death in Wembezi township in eastern Natal
Province, and the bodies of two people were found in Germiston
township near Johannesburg, and in Nkelethu township in eastern
Cape Province.
   The Broadcasting Corp. also reported unrest in the Crossroads
township near Cape Town that left one man dead and 20 squatter
dwellings burned. The township has been hit by violence over poor
living conditions.
   Laws segregating residential areas remain in effect, and most
blacks live in squalid townships.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0029 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 1240EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Britain-Nuclear 1stLd-Writethru a0691 11-18 0313</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Britain-Nuclear, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0691,0353</SECOND>
<HEAD>Report: Cracks in British Nuclear Submarines</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Deletes 3rd graf to remove redundancy.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   At least two and possibly three of the four
nuclear-powered submarines that carry Britain's Polaris nuclear
missiles have developed cracks in their cooling systems, newspapers
reported Sunday.
   They said repairs to correct the fault will probably reduce the
number of patrols and might halt them entirely.
   The four subs carry 16 Polaris nuclear missiles each. It is
policy to have at least one on patrol at all times. If none can be
at sea, Britain has no effective nuclear deterrent until new, more
powerful submarines to carry U.S. Trident missiles are ready in
1995.
   The Observer weekly said there are cracks in the nuclear reactor
cooling systems of two of the vessels, HMS Revenge and HMS Renown.
It said that a third, HMS Repulse, may also be cracked.
   ``When the remaining Polaris submarine, HMS Resolution, returns
from patrol later this month, there may be no boat ready to replace
her,'' The Observer said.
   The Ministry of Defense on Sunday denied the nuclear capability
had been undermined by the reactor problem.
   ``The Polaris deterrent is being maintained, at sea and on
patrol,'' a department spokesman said on condition of anonymity.
   He declined to discuss ``technical'' matters, or the operational
deployment of the Polaris fleet.
   The Observer attributed its information to lawmaker John McFall
and defense and industrial sources. McFall, a Scot, has contacts
among the submarine personnel at their base on the west coast of
Scotland.
   The Sunday Times quoted McFall as saying serious problems
existed in three of the four submarines. It said senior officials
at the Defense Ministry admitted the defects.
   The weekly quoted John Large, a nuclear engineer, as saying the
trouble was caused by metal in the reactors that had hardened and
become brittle.
   In all, Britain has 22 nuclear-powered submarines.
   Five other submarines - Warspite, Churchill, Conqueror, Valiant
and Courageous - are being decommissioned and scrapped. At least
two of them had cracks in the reactor cooling systems.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0030 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 1242EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p AM-TermLimits Bjt   11-18 0545</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Term Limits, Bjt,0675</SECOND>
<HEAD>Kansas City's Term Limit Could Create Some Wild Politics</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Katheryn in 12th graf is cq</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By SALLY STREFF BUZBEE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>KANSAS CITY, Mo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Voters wanted new faces. And that's what
they're going to get.
   Political observers anticipate as many as 50 candidates may run
for nine elected municipal posts being vacated because voters
approved a two-term limit this month. Moreover, some black and
Hispanic residents plan to challenge the term limit in court.
   While incumbents warn that the limit could put more power in the
hands of city hall bureaucrats, others say they're looking forward
to a needed switch.
   ``It'll be a breath of fresh air,'' said Charles Wheeler, a
former mayor who helped get the issue on the ballot.
   ``It's going to be a zoo,'' countered the Rev. Emanuel Cleaver,
one of nine incumbents who will lose seats on the 13-member
council.
   Unlike term limits recently approved in Oklahoma, Colorado and
California, Kansas City's measure is retroactive. Anyone who
already has served two consecutive four-year terms can't run in
April, when the municipal election will be held.
   The nine incumbents losing jobs have spent between eight years
and 21 years governing the city of 450,000.
   Three already had planned not to seek re-election, including
three-term Mayor Richard Berkley, who serves as an ex officio
voting council member; and Cleaver and another council member, both
of whom plan to run for mayor.
   None said they would wait four years and run again, as the law
allows.
   Besides those running for mayor, just one said he will
definitely seek another political office. At least two are looking
for other work.
   Incumbents are not the only ones worried that the new council,
made up of beginners and lame ducks, will be too weak to control a
large city staff.
   Katheryn Shields, a first-term council member who plans to run
again, said council members already struggle against an
unresponsive bureaucracy.
   ``Now we'll have a situation where the staff, if they disagree
with a council member on something, can simply say, `Hey, they're
going to be gone in two years or three. We can wait them out,'''
she said.
   Others worry that term limits will dilute the power of the
city's minorities. Four of the soon-to-be-ousted incumbents are
black and one is Hispanic. The other four are white, including the
mayor.
   Citizens in two districts plan to file a lawsuit claiming that
the term limits violate the federal Voting Rights Act. They say it
was unfair for voters citywide to decide the fates of candidates
from particular districts. The mayor and six other council members
are elected citywide, and six are elected by district.
   ``Many people in those (black) districts feel it will be a long
time before they can elect candidates who had the same kind of
experience and influence, and maybe never,'' said Cleaver, who is
black.
   Still others think the term limit won't have much effect on the
city's underlying political structure. They say the powerful
political clubs that endorse candidates will simply reach down to
the next available person.
   ``Everybody acts like 50 philosopher-kings are going to step
forward to run for office,'' Shields said. ``But there aren't 50
philosopher-kings out there. It probably will be the same caliber
of people.''
   She contends the limit will merely succeed at getting rid of
certain council members who are disliked citywide but considered
virtually unbeatable in their districts.
   To Wheeler and others, that would be enough.
   They say the current council is unaccountable to voters -
neglecting to ask their opinion on how tax money should be spent
and using favoritism to decide what city projects should be done.
In addition, one city council member served a 30-day federal prison
sentence in 1988 for failing to file a federal income tax return in
1983.
   ``We need a clean slate,'' Wheeler said. ``This is going to give
us that.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0031 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 1243EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-MGMGrandFire Bjt   11-18 0549</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-MGM Grand Fire, Bjt,0747</SECOND>
<HEAD>Scars Remain 10 Years After 87 Died in MGM Grand Hotel Fire</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TIM DAHLBERG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LAS VEGAS, Nev. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Ten years after crawling to safety from
his hotel room through 21 floors of choking smoke, Dennis Casey
will be in church to mark the day the MGM Grand Hotel burned.
   Time and a $50 million remodeling job to the 26-story resort -
now known as Bally's - have dimmed memories of one of the nation's
worst hotel fires, which killed 87 people Nov. 21, 1980.
   But mental scars remain for survivors like Casey.
   ``You always wonder why you lived and they died,'' the
Pittsburgh public relations executive said. ``I have nightmares
about it, I'm not ashamed to admit that. I see a therapist for it
on a regular basis.''
   Explaining that he'll attend church Wednesday, as he has done
every anniversary of the fire, Casey said: ``I go at the exact
Eastern time of the fire and I say a prayer for those that lived
and died. It's my way of remembering the people in the hotel.''
   The 2,800-room resort now boasts one of the finest fire safety
systems of any high-rise. And tough state retrofit laws passed
after the disaster forced other Nevada hotels to also install
top-of-the-line sprinkler and fire safety systems.
   But on the morning of the blaze, the then 7-year-old resort had
no sprinklers and an array of code violations.
   Casey and some 4,000 others were inside when a short circuit in
a delicatessen pie case sparked a smoldering blaze that went
unnoticed for hours.
   In a restaurant next to the deli, a vacationing Illinois
firefighter, Kurt Schlueter, was sitting down to breakfast with
fellow firefighter Dave Beshoar and his brother when guards first
noticed the fire and began to evacuate the restaurant.
   Two other friends were on their way down from a 12th-floor suite
the five had rented for a weekend of fun and gambling in Las Vegas.
The two were later found dead.
   ``A security guard came in said there was a small problem next
door and asked us to leave,'' said Schlueter, a lieutenant in the
Western Springs, Ill., Fire Department. ``By the time we got to the
front of the restaurant, we could see smoke piling up on the
ceiling and we knew what was happening.''
   A few people kept gambling in the casino, but the firemen and
security guards hustled most of the guests toward the exits as the
main floor began filling quickly with dark, acrid smoke.
   By the time Schlueter and the Beshoars had gotten to the front
door, they had been forced to their knees by the smoke. Suddenly,
shortly after 7 a.m., the lights went out and the blaze exploded
into a fireball that flashed across the casino floor at an
estimated 17 to 19 feet a second.
   ``Dave and I were the last ones out before the fireball hit,''
Schlueter said. ``We heard a loud click, all the lights went out
and it was pitch dark. All of a sudden there was a massive heat
that pushed us clear out the door. If we hadn't been right at the
door, we would have been trapped in there.''
   A handful of people were killed by the fireball, but the toxic
smoke from the casino's synthetic furnishings would prove far more
deadly.
   Smoke billowed up elevator shafts to the top of the hotel and
was trapped on the upper floors of the tower. Of the 61 people who
died in their rooms or in hallways, 60 were on the 19th floor or
above.
   Figuring he would die if he stayed in his room, Casey doused
himself with water from a bathtub and put a wet towel around his
face. Opening his door, he saw the body of a woman lying in her
doorway.
   ``I crawled to her body and felt her neck for a pulse,'' Casey
said. ``She was dead. It was the first time I fully realized that I
might die and I began to cry. You've got to remember that no more
than five minutes earlier I had been asleep.''
   Six months later, the MGM had a $5 million sprinkler and safety
system, and the melted, charred slot machines had been replaced by
a glittering new casino. Actor Cary Grant was the first guest to
check in.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0032 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 1308EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-ArmsTalks     11-18 0456</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Arms Talks,0540</SECOND>
<HEAD>NATO, Warsaw Pact Initial Conventional Forces Accord</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Arms Treaty, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARK J. PORUBCANSKY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>VIENNA, Austria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Negotiators from NATO and Warsaw Pact
countries initialed an agreement Sunday to detroy tens of
thousands of non-nuclear weapons and build a peaceful Europe on the
ruins of Cold War conflict.
   The ceremony in Vienna's Hofburg Palace, the site of
negotiations for the past 20 months, means the treaty is ready to
be signed by President Bush, Soviet President Mikhail S. Gorbachev
and other heads of state Monday in Paris.
   ``From this treaty, the Soviet Union is ceasing to become a
militarized state with all the consequences of that - economic,
political and social,'' said Oleg A. Grinevsky, Soviet ambassador
to the talks.
   ``All the wealth of our society can be used for the benefit of
the people instead of building up an expensive and sometimes
useless war machine.''
   Before initialing the 160-page treaty, representatives of the 16
NATO and six Warsaw Pact countries exchanged thick packets of
information on the size of their arsenals in Europe.
   Officials said they could not yet release the figures in those
documents, but they said that more than 100,000 pieces of military
hardware would probably be destroyed.
   ``No battle in the history of mankind ... destroyed such an
immense number of tanks, armored combat vehicles, artillery and
combat aircraft,'' Grinevsky told reporters.
   No agreement was included on numbers of combat soldiers. A
U.S.-Soviet understanding on the number of soldiers each may have
in Europe was overtaken by German unification, and negotiators will
go back to work in Vienna Nov. 29 in an effort settle that
question.
   The Warsaw Pact countries - the Soviet Union, Poland,
Czechoslovakia, Hungary, Romania and Bulgaria - will have to
destroy many more weapons than the Western alliance to reach the
quotas, which are equal for both sides.
   The countries will have 40 months to eliminate the weaponry from
the moment the last nation ratifies the treaty.
   Destruction of such a large number of weapons will make it
difficult for any country to attack another, said U.S. Ambassador
James Woolsey.
   The United States and its allies began the negotiations in March
1989, determined to cut into the Soviet Union's ability to launch a
surprise attack, Woolsey said.
   But about six months later, a tide of revolution began that
swept away Eastern Europe's hard-line Communist rulers.
   The arms talks took on a broader meaning as the Warsaw Pact
allies broke away from Soviet domination and began defining an
independent position in the heart of Europe.
   Officials of Warsaw Pact countries now say the Eastern alliance
is likely to end its military business in mid-1991 and transform
itself into a loose political alliance.
   But even if the Warsaw Pact ceases to function militarily, its
individual countries still are bound by its terms.
   The treaty limits each alliance to 20,000 main battle tanks,
30,000 armored combat vehicles, 20,000 artillery pieces, 6,800
fighter planes and 2,000 combat helicopters.
   The accord also regulates troop movements from both alliances
and permits mutual inspections across Europe from the Atlantic
Ocean to the Ural Mountains.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0033 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 1339EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-Exercise Bjt   11-18 0516</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Exercise, Bjt,0638</SECOND>
<HEAD>High Winds, Waves Force Cancellation of Mock Amphibious Assault</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos D0D1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT DVORCHAK</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>IN EASTERN SAUDI ARABIA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Imminent Thunder maneuvers
were supposed to be a dress rehearsal for war, but 10-foot waves
forced the U.S. Marines to postpone the amphibious landing portion
of a mock invasion Sunday.
   Officials said the landing wold probably have gone off in a
real war.
   One hovercraft from the USS Gunston Hall was launched in the
choppy Persian Gulf, but it sputtered in a heavy spray and
sometimes disappeared behind waves before the seaborne assault was
scrapped.
   ``It's real disappointing,'' said Gunnery Sgt. Mike Pupkar, who
services the hulking landing craft. ``But it isn't worth hurting
people and wrecking equipment on a day like (this).''
   The landing was rescheduled for Monday morning.
   Meanwhile, 14 CH-46 Sea Knight helicopters from the USS Guam
ferried about 400 troops to shore at exactly the scheduled time
Sunday morning. Among them were 36 Saudi Arabian marines. The wind
and helicopter blades kicked up stinging sheets of sand.
   Overhead, hundreds of U.S., British, French and Saudi attack
jets and surveillance planes provided cover and air support. No
live ammunition was fired.
   Maj. Gen. Harry W. Jenkins Jr., commanding officer of the 4th
Marine Expeditionary Brigade, told reporters the exercise was a
success despite the inability to use the hovercraft to assault a
barren stretch of Saudi beach.
   ``One of the training objectives for this exercise was to bring
all these allied forces together and make sure we're all talking to
one another,'' Jenkins said. ``I'm pleased we've had as few
glitches as we've had. ... We don't want to risk anybody if we
don't have to.''
   The commander of the battalion of U.S. Marines that was supposed
to board hovercraft expressed disappointment when the exercise was
aborted.
   ``Whenever I don't get to do everything I try to do, that's a
disappointment,'' Lt. Col. Robert P. McAleer said. ``Anytime you
get cut out of an exercise it's not a good day for you.''
   Despite being unable to use landing craft to get Marines ashore,
officers said it didn't affect the outcome of the mock invasion and
changed their mission only slightly.
   ``By the time naval gunfire got done with this area, there
wouldn't be much opposition left,'' said Marine Capt. David Dysart,
30, a company commander whose troops were assigned the task of
securing a road junction.
   Under U.S. military rules, this section of the six-day exercise
was covered by several media pools.
   The Marines have done three other amphibious practices on the
Arabian peninsula, but this one was the first on Saudi soil and it
involved the highest concentration of warplanes assembled since
Operation Desert Shield began.
   According to news reports, Imminent Thunder was supposed to be
held as close as 10 miles from the Kuwaiti border. The actual
landing was about 100 miles south of Kuwait, reportedly after
complaints from Iraq and in the United States that it might provoke
Saddam Hussein.
   ``They moved the goalposts,'' said Marine Maj. John Toolan of
Brooklyn, N.Y.
   The amphibious assault was supposed to commence 25 miles
offshore in a tecnhique called ``over the horizon'' because shore
can't be seen when the hovercraft are launched.
   But winds of 20 to 25 mph stirred up choppy waves estimated at 4
to 10 feet high. Marines were first forced to endure a tedious
wait, then got the word of cancellation over a loudspeaker.
   ``If it was the real thing, we could probably go,'' said Cmdr.
Bill Marshall, captain of the USS Gunston Hall.
   But, he said, ``We're not going to put them in the water if it's
not safe to do that.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0034 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 1350EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-HolocaustMeeting 1stLd-Writethru a070 11-18 0539</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Holocaust Meeting, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0707,0686</SECOND>
<HEAD>Survivor: Rising Anti-Semitism Adds Urgency to Message</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 6th graf, `The was...', to CORRECT `The' to `He.'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By BILL STIEG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PHILADELPHIA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The news of 1990 saddens Robbie Waisman yet
strengthens his resolve.
   When the Holocaust survivor reads about the desecration of
Jewish cemeteries in France, former Ku Klux Klan leader David Duke
making a strong bid for the U.S. Senate, and neo-Nazis in the
Pacific Northwest, he wonders:
   ``If this happens when there are still survivors, what will
happen when we're gone?
   ``The world lost 11 million people, of which 6 million were
Jews. ... To think people look at that and still have that hate. It
leaves one completely aghast. Why? Why?''
   Now a hotelier in Vancouver, British Columbia, he has spent much
of the past seven years reminding people of the Nazis' slaughter of
6 million Jews.
   He was one of several speakers being featured during the two-day
conference that began Sunday, marking 45 years since the end of
World War II. ``Captive and Free: Lessons of the Holocaust for
Today and Tomorrow'' was organized by the Interfaith Council on the
Holocaust, which is devoted to preserving the memories and lessons
of those years of genocide.
   By the spring 1945, Waisman at 14 had spent nearly one-third of
his life in concentration camps, the last eight months at
Buchenwald in Germany. He lost both parents and four brothers in
the Holocaust.
   When U.S. troops arrived to liberate the camp, he recalled in a
telephone interview last week, he thought he was dreaming. When two
soldiers with brown skin approached, he thought he was dreaming. He
had never seen black men.
   In 1983, he saw pictures of soldiers in a magazine article about
the liberators. One of them was Leon Bass, a former Philadelphia
high school principal who, Waisman learned, was active as a speaker
on the Holocaust. He was one of the black men Waisman had seen 38
years before.
   Waisman called Bass - who was a corporal in the 183d Engineer
Combat Battalion, part of the Patton's Third Army - and they got
together and talked for hours.
   ``We have sort of shared a moment in time where we just glanced
at each other,'' Waisman said, ``and 40 years later we met again
and became very close friends.''
   Bass was at first dubious that Waisman truly remembered him; he
certainly remembered no faces.
   ``When I came into the camp, I did not see him,'' Bass said. ``I
saw all the walking dead in front of me. He was looking out the
window, all skin and bones.''
   Bass said he has seen enough in 65 years not to be disheartened
by current events.
   ``If people don't stand up to racism, we would go downhill,'' he
said. ``Maybe we haven't moved as far ahead as we might have moved,
but if we hadn't tried, we would be farther down the hill.''
   John Raines, the Interfaith Council's co-chairman and a Temple
University religion professor, said a rash of anti-Semitic
incidents in Europe made Sunday and Monday's conference more
timely.
   ``Clearly what we are seeing in Eastern Europe is the revival of
very ancient hatreds,'' he said.
   As the communist bloc dissolves, he said, people revert to old
nationalistic loyalties and traditional religions.
   ``An unfortunate part of those traditional religions in Eastern
Europe and Russia is anti-Semitism,'' he said.
   Waisman, who moved to western Canada to get as far away as
possible from Europe and the memories, broke nearly four decades of
virtual silence in 1983 after hearing that a teacher in Alberta was
telling students the Holocaust never happened. He now speaks
frequently on the subject.
   ``You have no idea how gratifying it is,'' Waisman said. ``I
speak about the camps and I have to dig back into my memory. It's
painful as hell .... But when you speak to the students, and they
come up afterward, and they write you letters, the pain is worth
it.'
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0035 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 1401EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Vatican-Gulf     11-18 0210</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Vatican-Gulf,0218</SECOND>
<HEAD>Greek Catholic Archbishop Goes to Iraq About Hostages</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf Rdp</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ROME (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Syrian-born Catholic leader Archbishop Hilarion
Capudji left for Baghdad on Sunday to ask Iraqi leader Saddam
Hussein for the release of all foreign hostages.
   Upon his departure from Rome, Capudji stressed that he would
place special emphasis on the release of Italian hostages because
of ``Italy's consistent political support of and moral and
humanitarian treatment toward the Palestinian people.''
   Since it occupied Kuwait on Aug. 2, Iraq has been holding
hundreds of foreigners to try to prevent an attack by the U.S.-led
alliance in the Persian Gulf.
   The 68-year-old archbishop is the spiritual head of the
3,000-member Melchite-rite Catholic community of Jerusalem.
   Melchite Catholics are Arab Christians who formed an
eastern-rite branch of the Roman Catholic Church. The branch
recognizes the primacy of the pope but enjoys a wide degree of
independence from the Vatican.
   Many Christian members of the Palestinian Liberation
Organization are Melchite.
   Capudji also said he hopes to convince Hussein that war in the
gulf would have ``apocalyptic consequences'' and that a peaceful
solution must be found to the crisis that began when Iraq invaded
Kuwait on Aug. 2.
   With the archbishop were members of Italian Catholic
organizations and peace groups.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0036 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 1404EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Soviet-Military     11-18 0410</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Military,0487</SECOND>
<HEAD>Military to Reform in Three Stages</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Arms Treaty, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN IAMS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Soviet military plans to cut its manpower and
weaponry to make the armed forces more efficient and less of a
burden on the state, the chief of staff was quoted as saying
Sunday.
   A draft of the 10-year, three-stage restructuring plan has been
forwarded to the Supreme Soviet legislature, said Gen. Mikhail
Moiseyev, the armed forces chief of staff. He made his comments in
an interview with the military newspaper Red Star.
   The newspaper also quoted an official identified as only Col. M.
Ponomarev as saying: ``Today, we have no apprehensions, nor do we
suspect any nation of planning a war against the Soviet Union. This
has allowed the Soviet leadership to adopt a new military-political
doctrine of reasonable sufficiency.''
   The first stage of the restructuring, which depends on the
signing of the Geneva and Vienna arms agreements, calls for the
total withdrawal of Soviet troops from Czechoslovakia, Hungary,
Mongolia and Germany by 1994, Moiseyev said.
   Under the plan, civil defense units will be scrapped, along with
the military's road construction units and some other construction
units.
   The second stage, to take place from 1994 to 1995, calls for the
formation of a new strategic grouping of armed forces on Soviet
territory, a reorganization of the central command structure, and a
realignment of military districts.
   The third and final stage calls for a 50 percent cut in
strategic offensive weapons by the year 2000. It envisions
enhancing Soviet military efficiency by combining units with
similar tasks and weapons.
   It calls for eventually cutting the size of armed forces from
the current 4 million to at least 3.2 million. About 1,300
generals, 22,000 officers, and 250,000 non-commissioned officers
would return to civilian life.
   Moiseyev said the restructuring will make the armed forces
``less of a burden on the state and more efficient at the same
time'' and would reduce it ``to the corresponding level of real
military danger and with the new political, economic and social
environment.''
   In the draft plan, pay raises will be given next year to all
ranks. Ordinary soldiers, who now receive only $13.50 a month, will
get $54 to $63.
   Officers and non-commissioned officers, whose pay averages $360
to $720, will get pay increases of about 25 percent.
   The draft will continue, Moiseyev said, but alternative service
will be allowed for those who object to service on religious
grounds.
   Ponomarev said the conditions were right, both domestically and
internationally, to carry out military reforms. Although there is
no immediate threat of war with the West, he said, the previous
stockpiling of weapons still posed a danger.
   ``We cannot remain indifferent to this and therefore disarmament
has become the call of the day,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0037 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 1411EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brite-MagazineCovers     11-18 0176</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brite-Magazine Covers,0187</SECOND>
<HEAD>Time Mag Personalizes Its Covers, For You, Jane Smith!</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: For 3 p.m. release EST</NOTE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Time magazine will make each of its 4 million
subscribers a cover subject this week.
   Through the magic of computers, the magazine has incorporated
each reader's name into its cover design to illustrate a story on
junk mail.
   ``Hey, Jane Smith. Don't miss our really interesting story on
the junk mail explosion!'' reads a sample cover from the Nov. 26
issue, released Sunday.
   Newsstand copies will carry the cover line: ``Hey, you at the
newsstand ....''
   The cover story says that 63.7 billion pieces of third-class
mail were delivered nationwide in the past year.
   But the tactic works. The article says that last year, 92
million Americans responded to direct-market pitches, a 60 percent
jump in six years.
   Over the course of a lifetime, the average American professional
will devote 8 months to sifting through direct mail offers, the
article said. About 43 pounds of junk mail is generated for each
adult American. Forty-four percent is thrown away, unopened.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0038 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 1417EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Colombia-Kidnappings     11-18 0609</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Colombia-Kidnappings,0709</SECOND>
<HEAD>Kidnapping Reporters Is Drug Mafia's Latest Intimidation Scheme</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By STEVEN GUTKIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOGOTA, Colombia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Like hundreds of other Colombians under
threat from drug traffickers, Francisco Santos traveled in a
chauffeur-driven, bullet-resistant car.
   But the precautions weren't enough. On Sept. 19, a group of
gunmen forced the car to stop, killed the driver and abducted
Santos, news editor of Colombia's biggest-selling newspaper, El
Tiempo.
   Santos, 28, is one of nine journalists who have been abducted in
the past three months by the Medellin cocaine cartel.
   The traffickers, having already resorted to bombings and
assassinations, are attempting a more subtle form of intimidation.
Some reporters belong to Colombia's most influential families.
   In one communique, the cartel threatened to kill its hostages if
the government launches a new offensive against traffickers.
   An anonymous caller to El Tiempo warned that a dead journalist
would be ``sent to the presidential palace in a plastic bag'' if
President Cesar Gaviria didn't establish direct negotiations with
traffickers.
   Why are reporters the target?
   ``The cartel wants access to the media,'' said one source close
to the investigation. He asked not to be identified.
   Cartel leaders have said the kidnappings are a response to human
rights abuses by police. They said security forces in Medellin,
Colombia's second largest city, were torturing and murdering their
associates.
   Whatever the reason, the abductions are taking a heavy toll not
just on the kidnapped reporters and their families, but on
journalism itself.
   Aside from the hundreds of people murdered by drug traffickers,
``freedom of expression has been our most noteworthy casualty,''
wrote Rafael Santos, Francisco's brother, in a recent editorial.
   ``The drug war has been a Colombian journalist's nightmare,'' he
added. The Medellin gang has killed about 30 reporters, including
Guillermo Cano, publisher of the Bogota daily El Espectador.
   That newspaper's main offices were all but destroyed by a
powerful bomb blast set off by drug traffickers last year.
   Many reporters are afraid to write stories about drugs. Those
that do write don't use bylines.
   Journalists who speak out against the cocaine mafia have grown
accustomed to guns, bodyguards and armored cars.
   ``Those who have shown the most bravery in working under these
conditions are either dead or in exile,'' El Espectador columnist
Jose Salgar wrote recently.
   Until the first week of November, many Colombians believed the
kidnapped journalists would soon be returned to their homes.
   A group of political and church leaders were engaged in a public
exchange of letters with a lawyer for the Medellin cartel.
   The lawyer, Guido Parra, outlined the cartels' demands: amnesty,
an end to extraditions and U.N. mediation in Colombia's drug war.
   The polite exchange between Parra and the church and political
leaders offered hope of a solution.
   But the leaders insisted that the drug barons' demands could not
be considered until all the hostages were released.
   The cartel responded Nov. 7 by abducting journalists Maruja
Villamizar and Beatriz Guerrero from their car in northern Bogota.
The kidnappers murdered the journalists' driver, Angel Maria Roa.
   In short order, the negotiations were called off.
   All along, the Gaviria administration has refused to negotiate
with the cartel.
   ``No issue is debatable under force,'' said one senior official,
who spoke on condition of anonymity.
   Another casualty of the kidnappings has been the optimism which
accompanied Gaviria's ascension to the presidency on Aug. 7.
   Former president Virgilio Barco left office saying the cartel
had been ``severely debilitated.''
   Peace talks between the government and armed groups - both on
the left and right - appeared to be bearing fruit. The country was
preparing for a national assembly to reform its 104-year-old
constitution.
   The violence, which had claimed tens of thousands of Colombian
lives in the past decade, seemed to be diminishing.
   One of Gaviria's first moves as president was to prohibit
extraditions to the United States of drug traffickers who
surrender.
   The kidnappings seemed an unlikely response to Gaviria's
concessions. But they underscored the cartel's ability to make life
difficult for many Colombians, despite a series of government
victories in the drug war.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0039 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 1417EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Summit-Gorbachev'sTro Bjt   11-18 0669</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Summit-Gorbachev's Troubles, Bjt,780</SECOND>
<HEAD>Soviet Leader Arrives at Summit with Uncertain Prospects</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP News Analysis</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BRYAN BRUMLEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Mikhail Gorbachev enters the 34-nation East-West
summit fresh from a major government crisis at home and with
uncertain prospects for what could be a hungry and tumultuous
Soviet winter.
   Gorbachev said before leaving Moscow that the Conference on
Security and Coopration in Europe would be ``major landmark in the
history of our continent.''
   But the real action was back in the Soviet Union.
   On Thursday, Gorbachev became the first Soviet leader ever
summoned before parliament to account for his failures. And on
Friday, he proposed a new government structure.
   The disarray within the Soviet empire could hardly contrast more
sharply with the first CSCE summit. That session, held in Helsinki
in 1975, produced the so-called Helsinki Accords, which defined the
human rights obligations of the participants and ratified the
presence of Soviet ground forces and pro-Moscow regimes throughout
Eastern Europe.
   Soviet power and prestige may have reached their peak during
that year. It was the summer of the U.S.-Soviet joint space
mission, a few months after the inglorious American withdrawal from
Vietnam, the year a pro-Soviet government came to power in Angola,
a time when Communists were strong in Italy, France and Portugal.
   For now, Gorbachev has turned his attention to the meeting in
Paris, where the scheduled highlight is a treaty that ostensibly
slashes East-West conventional armies in Europe.
   The pact in fact consecrates the retreat of most Soviet ground
forces behind their own borders by the end of 1994.
   The collapse of the Soviet Bloc over the past 15 months has
outpaced conventional forces negotiations, and diplomats already
are talking about a follow-up treaty to keep up with events.
   Another highlight of the 34-nation conference was to be the
signing of a non-agression pact between the North Atlantic Treaty
Organization and the Kremlin-led Warsaw Pact. This agreement, too,
would have seemed impossible three years ago, but today recognizes
established fact.
   Gorbachev arrives in Paris straight from Rome, one of the many
West European capitals he has visited in the past month seeking
financial and moral support.
   President Bush already has told officials to draw up plans to
rush food to Moscow if needed, and British Prime Minister Margaret
Thatcher commissioned a fund to convey British industrial know-how
to the Soviet Union.
   No one knows whether such aid will bolster Gorbachev.
Confronting the revolt this week in the formerly tame Supreme
Soviet legislature, Gorbachev announced not simply that he was
dumping the unpopular Prime Minister Nikolai Ryzhkov, but that he
was changing the very structure of government.
   The Council of Ministers that Ryzhkov heads will be scrapped,
along with the newly created Presidential Council.
   Gorbachev announced plans to enhance the Federation Council, a
body that previously had little power but has the virtue of
including representatives from the 15 Soviet republics.
   By boosting the power of the Federation Council, Gorbachev
effectively embraced a proposal put forward by his rival, Russian
President Boris Yeltsin, to form a government made up of
representatives from the 15 Soviet republics.
   Gorbachev's solution, however, did not seem to move the Soviet
Union closer to his stated goal of a government of laws rather than
unchecked power, and fit the pattern of his increasingly stopgap
measures to prop up central power.
   Although the Helsinki summit of 1975 ratified the borders of
postwar Europe, those borders are again in flux. The demolition of
the Berlin Wall just over a year ago removed a frontier that two
generations of Soviet leaders struggled to preserve.
   Now the borders of the Soviet Union itself are threatened, as
the three Baltic republics of Lithuania, Latvia and Estonia, along
with the Caucasian republics of Armenia and Georgia seek outright
independence, and Moldavian nationalists agitate to reunify with
Romania.
   In Russia, by far the largest Soviet republic, Yeltsin and his
Russian government are waging what promises to be a successful
campaign for control of state-owned oil and gas fields, as well as
other natural and industrial resources.
   The Ukraine, the second largest Soviet republic, is also getting
restive, and is likely to win enhanced rights if it agrees to
Gorbachev's proposal to sign a new Treaty of Union, replacing the
1924 charter that united the Soviet republics.
   Despite the promise of Western aid, it is not clear what if
anything Bush and the other leaders will be able to offer the
Soviet Union, or whether there is anything they could do to bolster
Gorbachev's collapsing authority.
   ---&equals;
   EDITOR'S NOTE: Bryan Brumley, Moscow bureau chief for The
Associated Press, has covered Soviet affairs since 1981.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0040 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 1432EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Congress-EastTimor     11-18 0270</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Congress-East Timor,280</SECOND>
<HEAD>Lawmakers Urge Administration To Help Stem Repression in East
Timor</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   More than half the members of the House are
asking Secretary of State James A. Baker III to use U.S. influence
to reduce the ``atmosphere of fear and repression'' in the
Southeast Asian nation of East Timor.
   A group of 223 House members signed a letter to be sent to Baker
on Monday that calls attention to reports of arrests, detention,
torture and other human rights violations on the island nation in
the last year.
   ``We believe that it is of great importance that United States'
concern over the Timor situation be stressed at this time,'' the
letter said.
   East Timor is a former Portuguese colony that was annexed by
Indonesia in 1975.
   The group likened Indonesia's takeover of East Timor to Iraq's
occupation of Kuwait.
   The lawmakers, including 53 Republicans, cited reports of
detentions of pro-independence demonstrators following an October
1989 visit to East Timor by Pope John Paul II.
   They also said human rights advocates were beaten by Indonesian
police after their meeting with the U.S. ambassador to Indonesia
during a visit to the country in January.
   The letter also points out the potential for periodic cycles of
hunger and malnutrition brought on by ``Indonesian military
policies such as restrictions on where Timorese villagers can farm
their crops.''
   ``The United States should use its influence to help ensure that
humanitarian needs of this nature are promptly addressed,'' the
lawmakers said.
   Additionally, the United States ``should support a process of
peace talks that could lead to negotiations without preconditions
among parties directly involved,'' the letter concluded.
   The letter was spearheaded by Rep. Tony Hall, D-Ohio, chairman
of the House Select Committee on Hunger.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0041 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 1446EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People     11-18 0593</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People,0774</SECOND>
<HEAD>People In The News</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY44</HEAD>
<DATELINE>RADNOR, Pa. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Actor Malcolm-Jamal Warner thinks he's ready
for life after ``The Cosby Show'' - behind the camera.
   ``I've been preparing to be a director since I was 17,'' Warner
says in an interview published in the Nov. 24 issue of TV Guide.
``I knew I had to learn it.''
   Warner, now 20, has starred as Bill Cosby's son, Theo, on the
hit series for seven years.
   ``Where do I go from here? To think that I reached my peak as a
teen-ager would be a sad and scary thought.''
   He directed his first episode of ``The Cosby Show'' last spring
and is set to direct two more episodes this season. He's
negotiating to direct a feature film, already has directed six
music videos and is co-producing four television children's
specials.
   ---
   DALLAS (AP) - The glare of success has started to melt the
mysterious facade of Dallas-based rapper Vanilla Ice, whose rap
single ``Ice Ice Baby'' hit No. 1 on the pop chart.
   The Dallas Morning News described numerous contradictions in
Vanilla Ice's record-company biography and interviews in a story in
Sunday's editions.
   The 22-year-old white entertainer in a genre dominated by blacks
has described a colorful teen-age background of gangs, motorcycles
and rough-and-tumble street life in lower-class Miami
neighborhoods.
   But the newspaper quoted numerous sources as saying he was their
classmate at R.L. Turner High School in Carrollton, an affluent
Dallas suburb. The student is identified in yearbooks as Robert Van
Winkle.
   Vanilla Ice would not comment on whether his given name is
Robert Van Winkle, but said he went to Turner in his junior and
senior years.
   He has said repeatedly that he won three national motocross
championships for Team Honda in Florida. A Team Honda
representative said there is no record of a team member named
Robert Van Winkle or Vanilla Ice. A representative of the American
Motorcycle Association said its records show a racer named Robert
Van Winkle from Carrollton, but he never won a national title.
   Asked if Vanilla Ice had embellished his biography, publicist
Elaine Schock said: ``Yeah, he may have exaggerated a little. ...
I've known artists who have done much worse. A lot of artists do
this.''
   ---
   NEW YORK (AP) - Nearly a quarter of a century has passed since
the last time Topol played Tevye, the dairyman hero of ``Fiddler on
the Roof,'' but he's not complaining about repeating himself.
   ``I really have enjoyed it,'' the 55-year-old actor said of the
show's Broadway revival, set to last for three months.
   ``I am now at the age I used to aim for. The years that went by
since I first played it have been an experience that made me enjoy
it more than when I was younger,'' the Israeli actor said in an
interview in Sunday's editions of The New York Times.
   The play last appeared on Broadway in 1964. Topol starred in the
London production in 1967.
   He's well aware that ``Fiddler'' has since become a popular high
school play.
   ``I've met 200 guys who played Tevye. You can't surprise anyone
with the story,'' he said.
   ---
   BURCHARD, Neb. (AP) - The winner of a $23.1 million Lotto
America prize has moved to a new life in Colorado - with no
forwarding address, thank you - to escape donation seekers,
investment counselors and even relatives.
   Edwin Frahm, 51, won the prize in June while he was working on a
construction project in Topeka, Kan. His wife was working at the
time as a housekeeping supervisor in Beatrice, Neb.
   They quit their jobs and stayed on a Burchard-area farm owned by
Frahm's mother.
   But a month ago, they decided to get out of Nebraska, according
to Frahm's son, Lee Frahm, who lives in the Denver area. He said
his father doesn't want to talk about the move, and he won't reveal
the location of the Colorado ranch his father bought.
   Friends and neighbors in the Burchard area say the Frahms left
to escape the harassment that followed the monetary bonanza.
   ``There were so many people coming after they won it. People
trying them, begging for money. You'd get tired of that after a
while,'' a neighbor said.
   Wayne Cacek, another neighbor and friend, said relatives were
pressuring Frahm to buy his mother's farm.
   ``He figured the best thing to do was to move on and let someone
else take over the home place,'' Cacek said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0042 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 1522EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Yugoslavia     11-18 0569</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Yugoslavia,0655</SECOND>
<HEAD>Nationalists Accuse Communists of Vote-Rigging</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DUSAN STOJANOVIC</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SARAJEVO, Yugoslavia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Nationalist parties accused
Communists in the Yugoslav republic of Bosnia-Hercegovina of
rigging elections Sunday. The contest could make or break
Yugoslavia's future as a federation.
   Foreign observers, in Sarajevo to monitor the republic's first
free vote since 1938, confirmed there were irregularities. But they
said they were probably because of poor organization.
   ``Many people came to vote, but were not on the lists, which
caused a lot of nervousness,'' said Joseph D. Dwyer, of the Hoover
Institution at Stanford University.
   ``I don't think it was a bad intention by any party, but just
poor organization,'' added Dwyer, who visited 15 polling stations.
Western observers said Saturday they were impressed by the
organization of the balloting.
   The republic's electoral commission also said it was checking
the claims.
   Voter turnout was reported low. Only 30 percent of the voters
had been to the 5,000 polling stations by 3 p.m. (9 a.m. EST.)
Polls opened at 7 a.m. and closed at 8 p.m. (2 p.m. EST).
   First official results were not expected until the end of the
week.
   In a rare show of unity, Serb, Croat and Moslem nationalist
parties accused Communists of tampering with electoral lists just
before polling stations opened.
   Bosnia-Hercegovina, an ethnic melting pot of 4.2 million people
whose feuds sparked World War I, is a microcosm of Yugoslavia
itself.
   The republic is at the heart of the country's bitter rivalries
both geographically and politically, and it could play a pivotal
role in deciding Yugoslavia's political future.
   Radovan Karadzic, leader of the Serbian Democratic Alliance, one
of three nationalist parties, claimed thousands of non-Communist
voters were struck from lists and replaced by known Communists from
outside Bosnia.
   Stjepan Kljuic, leader of the Croatian Democratic Union and Alia
Izetbegovic, president of the Moslem Union for Democratic Action,
backed Karadzic's claims of fraud.
   The reformed League of Communists, currently in power, denied
the charges.
   ``The (nationalist) parties are inventing accusations against us
because they know they will lose,'' League leader Nijaz Durakovic
said. He predicted that Communists would capture at least 30
percent of the republic's 240-seat bicameral assembly.
   A small group of voters gathered at the electoral commission's
headquarters after they found their names missing from electoral
lists in Sarajevo.
   ``I've lived at the same address for 20 years and I always voted
in single-party elections. Now, mysteriously, my name is gone,''
said retiree Dragan Djordjic.
   The state news agency Tanjug said problems with the voting lists
were evident in northwestern Bosnia.
   Some 3 million voters could choose among 1,551 candidates from
40 parties for parliament and among 28 candidates for the
seven-seat republican presidency.
   No single party seems likely to win a clear majority in Sunday's
first round. First official results were expected late next week,
and run-off elections will be in two weeks.
   In the struggle to shape the country's future, the Western
republics of Croatia and Slovenia, where center-right parties
ousted Communists in spring elections, are pushing for more
independence, or even secession, from the federation.
   They are pitted against Serbia and the other poorer, southern
republics who want a strong central government. Serbia and
Montenegro are still in Communist hands ahead of Dec. 9 elections.
   Bosnia has so far charted a neutral course between the two
feuding blocs as mounting ethnic tensions in Yugoslavia's six
republics and two provinces have pushed the federation to the brink
of collapse.
   The vote has set the nationalist parties against the reformed
Communists and federal Premier Ante Markovic's Alliance of
Reformist Forces, promoting cross-ethnic policies and a united
Yugoslavia.
   Sarajevo is best known as the site that sparked World War I in
1914 after Austrian Archduke Franz Ferdinand was assassinated by
young Serbian nationalist Gavrilo Princip.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0043 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 1544EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Israel-Violence 1stLd-Writethru a0705 11-18 0387</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel-Violence, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0705,0442</SECOND>
<HEAD>Palestinian Headmaster Shot in Schoolyard, Called Collaborator</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 6 grafs to UPDATE with details, correct information
on school. Pickup 7th pvs, `The deaths...'</NOTE>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Palestinian headmaster was shot dead in front
of his pupils in a schoolyard Sunday for allegedly collaborating
with Israel, Arab reports said.
   Another Arab was killed in the occupied West Bank village of
Jabaa by armed Palestinians, the army said.
   Masked assailants shot the headmaster, 31-year-old Saleh Salem
Hijazi, in the head as he finished an English lesson and was
leaving the class in the Rabah el Adaweyeh girls' high school in
the Gaza Strip town of Rafah, the reports said. The army confirmed
the killing.
   Graffiti painted on the school walls claimed responsibility on
behalf of a group calling itself el-Fahed el-Aswad, which means
Black Leopard.
   Itim, the Israeli news agency, said it was the third time an
alleged collaborator has been killed inside a Gaza Strip school in
recent months.
   Arab reports said the assailants in Jabaa were collaborators who
were armed by Israel to defend themselves. The dead man was
identified as Muhammad Sharaim.
   The deaths brought to 302 the number of Arabs killed by fellow
Palestinians, most on suspicion of collaborating with Israel.
   Some 773 Palestinians have been killed by Israeli army and
civilian gunfir in the 35-month-old uprising. Fifty-two Israelis
have died in the violence.
   At least five Palestinians were wounded by Israeli army gunfire
in scattered stone-throwing riots in the occupied territories,
including an 8-year-old girl hit in the hand, Arab reports said.
   At the weekly Cabinet meeting, Economics Minister David Magen
proposed halving the Arab labor force in Israel by fining employers
who hire non-Israelis.
   With unemployment running at 9 percent, Magen believed his
proposal would open 50,000 jobs for the country's 92,000 people out
of work, including 19,000 recently arrived Soviet immigrants.
   More than 100,000 Palestinians from the occupied territories
work in Israel. According to Magen, about 70 percent of them do not
have the special work permits needed to prove they have no criminal
or anti-Israel political background.
   A spate of Arab knife attacks on Jews has prompted calls for
Arab workers to be replaced by Soviet immigrants.
   Magen told Israel army radio his proposal would boost the West
Bank and Gaza Strip economy as ``tens of thousands will prefer to
find work near their homes because they can't work by Israeli law
in Israel.''
   Left-wing legislator Dedi Zucker said Jerusalem shopkeepers were
being forced to fire Arab employees and post signs saying ``We
don't employ Arabs here.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0044 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 1611EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>d a AM-BRF--PipeBombs     11-18 0166</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Pipe Bombs,0182</SECOND>
<HEAD>Pipe Bombs Explode at Motel and Department Store, No Injuries</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SANTA ANA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A pipe bomb hidden in a borrowed stereo
blew up when the stereo was plugged in at a motel and an apparently
unrelated bomb exploded on a store roof, police said Sunday.
   ``It's kind of unusual to have them so close together,'' said
Sgt. Bob Ensley, but he doubted the explosions were at all
connected.
   The booby-trapped stereo went off when Kathy Dastrup plugged it
in at her motel room. Ms. Dastrup, 32, suffered only minor injuries
because she was bending near a table at the time, said Ensley.
   An acquaintance, 21-year-old Herman Nathaniel Belkins, who had
borrowed the stereo, was sitting on a couch 12 feet away and was
uninjured.
   Ensley said he did not know who loaned Belkins the equipment.
   About 90 minutes earlier Saturday evening, a pipe bomb exploded
on the roof of a Kmart store.
   Police released no additional information on the store blast,
and all calls to Kmart offices went unanswered Sunday.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0045 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 1610EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Gorbachev 1stLdWritethru a0699 11-18 0579</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gorbachev, 1st Ld Writethru, a0699,0705</SECOND>
<HEAD>Precede VATICAN CITY</HEAD>
<HEAD>Gorbachev: `New Ideas' Have Emerged To Avoid War In Gulf</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Summit-Gorbachev's Troubles, Bjt</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS thruout to UPDATE with Gorbachev comments on the gulf
crisis, details. Changes byline.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By STEPHEN R. WILSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ROME (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Soviet President Mikhail S. Gorbachev said Sunday he
is convinced there is a peaceful way out of the Persian Gulf crisis
and that ``new ideas'' have emerged to avert war.
   Efforts for a political solution in the gulf figured prominently
in Gorbachev's brief stay in Rome and his talks with Pope John Paul
II, who said he was praying the world will be spared the
``horrors'' of a military conflict.
   Gorbachev renewed his invitation to the Polish-born pope, first
made during their historic talks a year ago, for a papal visit to
the Soviet Union.
   The pope later told reporters he hoped to go but would not
commit himself to a date.
   ``The right moment will come,'' said John Paul, whose efforts
for religious freedom contributed to the revolutionary changes in
Eastern Europe.
   Vatican officials said the trip could not take place before
1992, stressing that the Vatican first needs to assess the number
of faithful, priests and bishops and the overall state of the
church in the Soviet Union.
   For Gorbachev, who was greeted by large and friendly crowds, his
brief stop gave him a respite from his political and economic
troubles at home.
   He signed a 20-year friendship treaty with Italy which includes
a non-aggression clause, won commitments of nearly $5 billion over
five years in support for the Soviet economy, and received a
$450,000 human rights prize from an Italian foundation backed by a
mineral water company.
   Much of his day was spent in talks on the crisis caused by
Iraq's Aug. 2 invasion of Kuwait.
   After signing the friendship treaty at the Quirinal presidential
palace, Gorbachev said it was a ``test'' for the international
community to try to resolve the gulf crisis peacefully.
   ``I am convinced that we will succeed in finding a way out of
this deep crisis,'' he said, speaking in Russian which was
translated into Italian.
   ``There are new ideas which need to be examined. We are headed
to the quest of a solution to this grave crisis which involves
everyone.''
   Gorbachev did not elaborate on the new ideas. His spokesman,
Vitaly Ignatenko, said they were discussed in the private talks
between Gorbachev and Premier Giulio Andreotti.
   The Soviet spokesman said Gorbachev and the pope stressed the
need for U.N. involvement and the importance of the role played by
Arab countries.
   Ignatenko said Gorbachev would discuss the ideas with President
Bush, German Chancellor Helmut Kohl, French President Francois
Mitterrand and other leaders during the East-West summit opening
Monday in Paris.
   The spokesman said Gorbachev stressed that the United Nations
``still has the chance to increase the pressure on Saddam
Hussein.''
   Andreotti's spokesman, Pio Mastrobouoni, said the two leaders
agreed that efforts to avoid a military conflict in the gulf must
continue.
   ``One cannot be resigned to the need to resort to force unless
absolutely necessary,'' he quoted Andreotti as saying.
   Gorbachev termed his talks with the pope ``very satisfying'' and
said they discussed ``the most important problems in Europe and the
world.''
   In its communique, the Vatican said the talks were ``open and
very friendly,'' adding that it viewed the audience as a
continuation of the dialogue started during Gorbachev's first visit
on Dec. 1, 1989.
   Those historic talks paved the way for the establishment of
official Moscow-Vatican ties in March and the exchange of
ambassadors.
   Gorbachev kept his promise to the pope for enactment of a
freedom of religion law which, among other things, legalized the
long suppressed Ukrainian Catholic Church. The Ukranian issue had
been a major impediment to a papal visit.
   Ignatenko quoted Gorbachev as saying his next meeting with John
Paul would ``perhaps, or probably, be in the USSR.''
   Gorbachev was accompanied to the Vatican by his wife Raisa, who
wore a gray suit. For last year's visit, she wore a red dress,
raising eyebrows here.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0046 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 1629EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>d a AM-BRF--BarneyFrank     11-18 0172</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Barney Frank,0175</SECOND>
<HEAD>Congressman Suffers Mild Heart Attack</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   U.S. Rep. Barney Frank was resting comfortably
Sunday in an intensive care unit after suffering a mild heart
attack while exercising at a health club, hospital officials said.
   The 50-year-old Massachusetts Democrat checked himself into Beth
Israel Hospital on Saturday night complaining of chest pains.
   An examination showed blockage of a coronary artery and an
angioplasty was performed, the hospital said.
   ``I'm pleased to say treatment seems to be working,'' said Dr.
William Grossman, a Beth Israel cardiologist. ``He has no other
medical problems.''
   Frank, who was easily re-elected this month to a sixth term, was
being treated in the hospital's intensive care unit.
   Dorothy Reichard, a Frank aide, said Saturday he ``had been
working out, he had been in the gym and started to feel some chest
pain and decided to go to the hospital.''
   National attention focused on Frank last summer when the House
reprimanded him for actions stemming from his relationship with a
male prostitute.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0047 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 1635EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-BritishSailor     11-18 0187</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-British Sailor,0207</SECOND>
<HEAD>Officer Gets A Week Vacation After 21 Hours In Water</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf Rdp</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MANAMA, Bahrain (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   British sailor Chris Boorman gained a
week's holiday with his family in England after surviving 21 hours
bobbing in the Persian Gulf earlier this week, a Royal Navy
spokesman said Sunday.
   ``We've sent him for about a week. We want him to have a quiet
leave without undue pressure,'' said spokesman Anton Hanney. He did
not give Boorman's hometown.
   He described Boorman's physical and mental condition as very
good after the incident on Nov. 12, in which the sailor fell
overboard from the HMS Cattistock, one of the Royal Navy's Armilla
Patrol ships deployed in the standoff against Iraq.
   Boorman, a petty officer, described his ordeal as a ``freak
accident.'' He managed to tread water, swim and float on his back
for 21 hours. For 18 of them, his companions thought he was ashore.
   The minute they realized he was missing, Royal Navy warships and
six helicopters launched a search operation in the waters.
   It was shortly after that the USS Blue Ridge, command and
control vessel of the U.S. armada, found him 50 miles southwest of
Dubai's Jebel Ali late Tuesday.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0048 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 1637EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-India-IMF     11-18 0194</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-India-IMF,0221</SECOND>
<HEAD>India Yet To Formally Apply For IMF Gulf Hardship Loan</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW DELHI, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The International Monetary Fund has
offered India a $400 to $450 million loan to compensate for
hardship suffered under U.N. sanctions against Iraq. India said
Sunday it hadn't decided whether to accept.
   ``We are undecided, it is too early to say yes or no'' said
Finance Secretary Bimal Jalan.
   The loan was approved Friday by the Washington-based world body,
but it was not reported in the India media.
   India had pleaded with the IMF in September to modify terms of
assistance to countries under the Compensatory and Contingency
Financing Facility to inlcude hardships faced by the oil crisis.
   ``The IMF accepted our argument and saw the logic in it,'' Jamal
said.
   India increased the price of gasoline and other petroleum
products by 25 percent on Oct. 10. Two days earlier, the government
announced a fuel cut by 15 percent and warned of other harsh
measures to adjust to the gulf crisis.
   The government had calculated that the gulf crisis would cost
India $2.4 billion in higher fuel bills over the next 12 months,
based on an average of $25 per barrel. But the price of oil has
hovored near $40 a barrel, upsetting India's crisis planning.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0049 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 1644EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Obit-Maw     11-18 0150</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Maw,0174</SECOND>
<HEAD>Former Utah Governor Herbert Maw Dies At Age 97</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SALT LAKE CITY (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Herbert B. Maw, who served two terms as
governor in the 1940s, died Saturday. He was 97.
   He died in a Salt Lake City nursing home of old age, said his
son, Warren Maw.
   Maw was born March 11, 1893, in Ogden, the Territory of Deseret,
three years before Utah became a state.
   He received a law degree from the University of Utah in 1916 and
a doctorate from Northwestern University in 1927.
   During World War I Maw served as a pilot and was among the
Army's first Mormon chaplains.
   A Democrat, he was elected governor in 1940 and served two
terms.
   At age 93, Maw was still practicing law. In an interview in 1984
he said he still walked three miles a day, a habit from the days
when he couldn't afford a trolley ride.
   He is survied by two sons and two daughters, 19 grandchildren
and 31 great-grandchildren.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0050 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 1644EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Obit-Richlin     11-18 0210</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Richlin,0226</SECOND>
<HEAD>Oscar-Winning Screenwriter Maurice Richlin Dead at 70</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SANTA MONICA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Maurice N. Richlin, an Oscar-winning
screenwriter of ``Pillow Talk'' who helped create the clumsy
Inspector Clouseau in ``The Pink Panther,'' has died of cancer. He
was 70.
   Richlin died Tuesday at St. John's Hospital and Health Center,
nursing supervisor Ruth Brymer said over the weekend.
   Richlin and his writing partner, Stanley Shapiro, won an Academy
Award for the 1959 romantic comedy ``Pillow Talk,'' which starred
Rock Hudson and Doris Day.
   That same year the duo had a second nomination in the same
category, best story written for the screen, for ``Operation
Petticoat,'' starring Cary Grant and Tony Curtis.
   With Blake Edwards, Richlin wrote ``The Pink Panther,'' the 1963
comedy featuring Peter Sellers as a bumbling French detective.
   Richlin, a native of Omaha, Neb., attended the University of
Missouri and served in the Army during World War II.
   After the war he moved to Los Angeles, where he worked as a
reporter for the Los Angeles Times and the Hollywood Citizen News.
   Before taking up screenwriting, he turned his talents to radio,
writing scripts for such popular series as ``Burns and Allen,''
``The Edgar Bergen Show'' and ``The Amos and Andy Show.''
   Richlin is survived by his wife, Louise, six children and three
grandchildren.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0051 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 1647EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-WeatherpageWeather     11-18 0233</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Weatherpage Weather,0255</SECOND>
<HEAD>Cold In East, Stormy In Alaska</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   A storm threatened parts of Alaska on Sunday with a possibility
of a blizzard, and a cold front chilled the East Coast as far south
as North Carolina.
   Alaska's storm was moving inland Sunday from the northern Bering
Sea.
   Winter storm watches were in effect through Monday for the
northern Seward Peninsula and the lower Kobuk Valley, along the
Arctic Coast and for the lower Yukon Valley. Blizzard conditions
were possible along the coast.
   A cold front prevailed from Maine to North Carolina, bringing in
brisk northwesterly wind.
   Gale warnings were posted along the coast of Maine, New
Hampshire, Massachusetts, Rhode Island, Maryland, Delaware,
Virginia and northern North Carolina.
   Afternoon temperatures ranged from the 50s over the Carolinas to
the 30s across much of the northern Atlantic Coast region.
   A frost warning was posted overnight into Monday morning for the
midlands of South Carolina, with frost and freeze warnings for the
mountains and foothills.
   Elsewhere, a weak upper-level weather disturbance produced a few
light showers over Missouri during the afternoon, and showers
associated with a cold front over the Northwest spread over
southwestern Oregon and northwestern California.
   Above the Arctic Circle, Sunday's sunset was the last glimpse of
the sun for 65 days. The next sunrise will be 1:05 p.m. AST on Jan.
23, according to the National Weather Service.
   Sunday morning's low for the Lower 48 states was 18 at Elkins,
W.Va.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0052 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 1659EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-CrosbyAccident     11-18 0142</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Crosby Accident,0144</SECOND>
<HEAD>Singer David Crosby Breaks Bones in Motorcycle Spill</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Rock musician David Crosby suffered broken
bones in a weekend motorcycle spill and was hospitalized in stable
condition Sunday, officials said.
   Crosby's left leg, left ankle and left shoulder were broken but
he was doing well at Cedars Sinai Medical Center, said hospital
spokesman Ron Wise.
   Crosby is a founding member of the group Crosby, Stills &amp; Nash,
which later became Crosby, Stills, Nash &amp; Young.
   The 49-year-old Crosby went down on a curve while riding through
the Los Angeles suburb of Encino on Saturday and skidded about 40
feet, said police Officer Leona Thomas.
   The motorcycle was apparently speeding on the 25 mph road, she
said
   ``He says his throttle got stuck,'' Thomas said.
   Crosby was not wearing a helmet, she said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0053 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 1727EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-Oman     11-18 0449</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Oman,0533</SECOND>
<HEAD>Sultan of Oman Forms Council, Promises More Democracy</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MEREDITH CAMPBELL</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MUSCAT, Oman (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The sultan of Oman marked his 20th year in
power Sunday by offering to create a council of representatives to
give residents of this desert monarchy more say in government.
   Sultan Qaboos became the latest Arab monarch to indicate a
willingness to allow greater democracy. Saudi Arabia and Kuwait's
government-in-exile earlier made such offers.
   The sultan, in a speech before thousands of Omanis, said the
council, known as the Majlis al-Shura, would be created within a
year and would be made up of representatives from the country's 42
provinces.
   He did not say whether they would be elected or appointed.
   The Majlis al-Shura is described in the Koran, Islam's holy
book, as a consultative council to help rulers manage affairs of
state. Normally its members are society elders chosen by the ruler.
   Oman, a nation of 1.5 million, already has a State Consultative
Council whose 55 members were chosen by the sultan. Qaboos implied
the two bodies would exist side by side as he did not say the
existing council would disappear.
   ``This is another step on the road of participation that serves
the aspirations of the citizens,'' he said.
   Iraq's Aug. 2 invasion of Kuwait has made the gulf sheikdoms
uneasy about maintaining their hold on power and exposed them to
Western scrutiny, and some have made concessions to their
populations.
   In neighboring Saudi Arabia, King Fahd announced Nov. 8 that a
consultative council would be formed, a move Saudi kings have
discussed periodically for decades but never acted on.
   In October, exiled Kuwaiti leaders met in Jiddah, Saudi Arabia,
and told politicicians that a rebuilt Kuwait would be more
democratic.
   In Oman and Saudi Arabia, the monarch is the center of the
power, serving as his own prime minister. The two leaders observe
the Islamic tradition of a weekly ``majlis,'' an open meeting at
which the ruler and princes listen to petitions from their
citizens.
   The United Arab Emirates and Qatar also have Shura Councils.
   Among the Islamic countries on the Arabian Peninsula, only
Kuwait had a Western-style elected parliament, although it had been
dissolved at the time of the invasion of Kuwait.
   The sultan's speech came during a weeklong celebration of his 20
years in power and his 50th birthday. Nightly fireworks light up
the skies while floats carrying musicians and Arabian tableaux
drift through the streets.
   On Sunday, British-made attack planes zoomed over a military
parade at Maidan al-Fateh Stadium. About 1,000 Dhofar tribesmen,
bare-chested and wearing indigo loincloths, performed acrobatic
feats for the king, tossing their swords 30 feet into the air.
   Speaking after the parade, Qaboos called for Iraq to leave
Kuwait but stressed his wish for a peaceful settlement.
   As part of an economic reform package, Qaboos offered incentives
for small businesses and said this oil-producing country needed to
diversify its economy.
   Like the other gulf nations, Oman relies heavily on an
expatriate workforce, one third of the country's population,
according to Western diplomats. Most foreign workers are from the
Indian subcontinent.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0054 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 1744EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-OfficialScofflaw     11-18 0249</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Official Scofflaw,0278</SECOND>
<HEAD>Traffic Official Owes $1,967 on Tickets And Refuses To Pay</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PHILADELPHIA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A former state senator who now is assistant
budget director of Philadelphia Traffic Court owes $1,967 in
traffic fines and says he has no intention of paying.
   ``Why ... should I pay,'' T. Milton Street told The Philadelphia
Inquirer, using an expletive to emphasize his resolve. ``My rights
have been violated. They violate people's rights (at Traffic Court)
every day.''
   Besides, he said: ``I don't have any money.''
   The newspaper dug up 19 tickets dating from 1984 for violations
ranging from driving without a license to driving unregistered and
uninspected vehicles, including a taxicab. The newspaper reported
Saturday that the violations also include running a stop sign,
abandoning a vehicle and reckless driving.
   Street was hired by Traffic Court President Judge George Twardy
last year at an annual salary of $30,000.
   ``Holy cripes!'' Twardy said when the newspaper informed him of
Street's tickets. ``That's a disgrace.''
   The judge said he will issue an order Monday that all court
employees clear up ticket problems or risk disciplinary action.
   Street seemed unconcerned. ``Think I'm the only one here got
tickets? A lot of people here got tickets,'' he said.
   Street contended the court violated drivers' rights by requiring
them to post collateral in the amount of their fines before an
appeal hearing.
   ``I'm not paying for a hearing,'' he said.
   Street said he saw no contradiction in his situation with the
court.
   ``I'm the most capable person in the city that's available to do
this job,'' he said. ``I'm better than anybody else.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0055 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 1755EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Vietnam-Clinic     11-18 0436</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Vietnam-Clinic,0535</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.S. Veterans Build Clinic in Town Destroyed by U.S. Bombs</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BANGKOK, Thailand (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Nine U.S. veterans of the Vietnam war
have returned to an old battlefield to rebuild a clinic destroyed
by American bombs, the official Vietnam News Agency reported
Sunday.
   The veterans worked with local residents to erect a 10-room
clinic at Yen Vien, about six miles east of Hanoi, the national
capital, the report monitored in Bangkok said.
   The Veterans Vietnam Restoration Project, based in Garberville,
Calif., put up the $30,000 construction cost. The North Country
Clinic of Arcata, Calif., is providing medicine and other supplies.
   The clinic opened Oct. 20 to serve more than 30,000 residents of
Yen Vien and seven surrounding villages, the agency reported. Yen
Vien was ``razed by U.S. carpet bombing'' ordered by President
Nixon in December 1972 to pressure the Communists into a peace
agreement.
   The bombing of the Hanoi and Haiphong harbor areas became known
as the Christmas bombings.
   The veterans group was led by John Baca, 41, who won the Medal
of Honor for saving his squadron from a 1968 grenade attack by a
North Vietnamese soldier.
   Baca covered the grenade with his helmet and lay on top of it.
He was severely wounded.
   Art James, 41, was an infantryman in Baca's squad in the 1st Air
Cavalry who suffered shrapnel wounds in that explosion. James was
among the veterans rebuilding the clinic in Yen Vien.
   James said he had found the Vietnamese a forgiving people.
``Forgiveness is part of a message I need when I go back to
America,'' he said.
   Some of the veterans see the project as a way to influence
Washington to end its economic embargo and normalize relations with
Vietnam, said Cherie Rankin, a 44-year-old psychotherapist from
Norwood, Mass., who was a Red Cross worker in Vietnam in 1970-71.
   ``The other reason was to try to do something constructive in a
country where I was involved in doing something destructive,'' she
said.
   John Burns, 43, said he returned ``to find some peace of mind,''
and because ``we learned nothing about Vietnam before, except for
what our government told us.''
   ``I wanted very much to come back and learn about Vietnam and
find the truth about the people ... and this has been the most
incredible experience of my life,'' he was quoted as saying.
   Burns served in Vietnam in 1967-69 with the 45th Combat Engineer
Battalion attached to the 1st Air Calvary.
   The report said it was the third clinic built by the Veterans
Vietnam Restoration Project. Two were constructed last year, at
Vung Tau, 60 miles southwest of Ho Chi Minh City, formerly Saigon,
and at Vinh, in central Vietnam.
   The U.S. government has eased restrictions on the activities of
American humanitarian groups in Vietnam since August 1987, in
return for Vietnamese cooperation in accounting for missing
American soldiers. Many U.S. veterans have returned in recent years
to visit old battlefields and see the country under Communist rule.
   For the first time, a group of Vietnamese army veterans visited
the United States this year to share experiences with U.S.
veterans.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0056 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 1757EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-Jordan-Ortega     11-18 0190</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Jordan-Ortega,0201</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ortega: King Hussein to Meet President Bush in Paris</HEAD>
<DATELINE>AMMAN, Jordan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Former Nicaraguan President Daniel Ortega,
who met with King Hussein on Sunday, said the monarch planned to
meet President Bush in Paris to discuss the Persian Gulf crisis.
   Bush arrived in Paris on Sunday to address an extraordinary
34-nation summit that will start Monday.
   ``They must look for a solution through dialogue and
negotiations,'' Ortega said of the two leaders.
   Jordanian Information Minister Ibrahim Izzeddine refused to
confirm the report. Hussein's other aides were not immediately
available for comment.
   Hussein, whose country is heavily reliant on Iraq and has been
hurt by the U.N. economic sanctions, has been a self-appointed
mediator for the crisis.
   He met with Bush several days after Iraq invaded Kuwait Aug. 2.,
but Bush was not receptive of Hussein's call for foreign troops to
stay out of the region and allow Arab leaders to settle the
dispute.
   Ortega arrived in Amman on Saturday after a four-day visit to
Baghdad, where he met President Saddam Hussein. Ortega said he was
going home Monday to Nicaragua, where he leads the leftist
opposition Sandinista National Liberation Front.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0057 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 1814EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-POWs     11-18 0171</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-POWs,0180</SECOND>
<HEAD>Iran Says Almost 240 POWs Due Home This Week</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NICOSIA, Cyprus (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Iraq is sending 239 Iranian prisoners of
war back home by Wednesday as the two nations resume their exchange
of POWs, Iran's official news agency reported Sunday.
   The Islamic Republic News Agency, monitored in Nicosia, said
Iran is ready to release 100 Iraqi prisoners of war per day as a
sign of goodwill.
   Foreign Minister Ali Akbar Velayati announced Saturday after
returning from a two-day trip to Baghdad that the exchange of
prisoners from the 1980-88 war was resuming.
   Velayati was the highest-ranking Iranian to visit Baghdad since
Iran's 1979 Islamic revolution.
   Up to 100,000 prisoners of war have yet to be repatriated.
   An exchange started in August after President Saddam Hussein of
Iraq accepted Iran's conditions for establishing a formal peace. He
was apparently seeking peace on his eastern border while building
up his forces in the west in the confrontation over his Aug. 2
invasion of Kuwait.
   Iraq suspended the exchanges in September without explanation.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0058 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 1837EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Saudi-TrafficDeath 1stLd-Writethru a077 11-18 0133</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Saudi-Traffic Death, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0770,0130</SECOND>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 2nd graf, `Trad E. Nazer...,' to CORRECT that driver was
nephew, sted son, of consul-general.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The nephew of Saudi Arabia's consul general
here surrendered to authorities following a hit-and-run accident
that killed a 73-year-old woman, police said Sunday.
   The driver, Trad E. Nazer, 20, was accompanied by his uncle,
consul-general Hassan Nazer, when he turned himself in shortly
after the accident late Friday, said Sgt. Jim Boudreau. He was
booked on vehicular manslaughter charges and released on $30,000
bail soon after the accident Boudreau said. Diplomatic immunity
would not apply in this case, the officer said.
   The woman was crossing a street when Nazer's car struck her,
police said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0059 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 1840EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-FarmSubsidies     11-18 0292</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Farm Subsidies,0330</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.S. Official Says Farm Subsidies Agreement Is Distant</HEAD>
<DATELINE>STOCKHOLM, Sweden (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   U.S. Secretary of Agriculture Clayton
Yeutter said Sunday that prospects for an international agreement
on reduced agricultural subsidies are bleak.
   The dispute over farm subsidies, pitting the United States
against France and Germany, is threatening to jeopardize a
four-year effort to reform the global trading system.
   Speaking of an agreement on subsidies, Yeutter told Swedish
national television: ``The chances of success are very, very slim.
We hope that something will change in the next couple of weeks to
alter that assessment.'' He spent the last week meeting with
European officials to seek a farm subsidies agreement. Officials
had hoped to resolve the issue in time for global trade talks
scheduled to open in Brussels, Belgium, on Dec. 3.
   The United States and other big farm exporters, like Argentina,
want the agriculture agreement to include 75 percent cuts in
subsidies and 90 percent cuts in customs tariffs.
   The 12-member European Community, including France and Germany,
has offered to agree to a 30 percent cut in farm subsidies over 10
years. Sweden and other European countries that are not members of
the EC have agreed to subsidy cuts of up to 50 percent.
   The global trade talks, known as the Uruguay Round for the
country where they were launched in 1986, involve 105 nations.
   U.S. Trade Representative Carla Hills warned Thursday that a
failure of the trade talks in Belgium would increase tensions among
trading partners and could frustrate international cooperation on
issues ranging from the gulf crisis to the environment.
   The Bush administration has a lot riding on the trade agreement.
U.S. officials believe that removing trade barriers is the best
hope for lowering huge U.S. trade deficits by expanding overseas
sales.
   Farmers in Europe have staged noisy protests in recent weeks to
assure their governments do not buckle under to pressure to lower
farm subsidies.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0060 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 1857EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Japan-Emperor     11-18 0246</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Japan-Emperor,0271</SECOND>
<HEAD>Radicals Set Off Bombs as Throng Cheers the Emperor</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   More than 100,000 people thronged to the Imperial
Palace on Sunday to cheer newly enthroned Emperor Akihito, but
radicals set off several bombs near a shrine he is to visit.
   Akihito, Empress Michiko and other royal family members,
protected by bulletproof glass, came out onto the palace balcony
eight times during the day to greet the well-wishers, which the
Imperial Household Agency numbered at 109,800.
   Loud shouts of ``Long live the emperor!'' rang through the
palace courtyard as he finished his short statement giving thanks
to the crowds.
   Akihito became emperor immediately after his father, Emperor
Hirohito, died in January 1989. His formal enthronement Nov. 12
followed a mourning period. Enthronement-related ceremonies are to
continue into December.
   At least four explosions occurred Sunday near the Grand Shrines
of Ise, 180 miles southwest of Tokyo, which Akihito is to visit
next week, said an official of Mie Prefectural Police who spoke on
condition of anonymity.
   No injuries or major damage were reported in the explosions, two
of which occurred at the Ujiyamada railway station and two along a
railway track near the station.
   The emperor and empress are to use the railroad when they travel
to Ise to pray to the sun goddess on Nov. 27-28. Japan's line of
emperors is said to have descended from the sun goddess Amaterasu.
   Radicals claimed responsibility for dozens of explosions and
fires in Tokyo during Akihito's enthronement. None caused serious
injuries.
   The radicals oppose the monarchy as a remnant of Japan's prewar
imperialism.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0061 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 1900EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People-McCartney     11-18 0266</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People-McCartney,0315</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ex-Beatle's Birth Certificate Sold for $18,000 at Auction</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By WENDY BENJAMINSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HOUSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A 26-year-old Beatles fan who got interested in
the group almost a decade after it broke up paid $18,000 Sunday for
what's said to be Paul McCartney's birth certificate.
   ``I'm just a Beatles freak and I had to have it,'' said Brian
Taylor of Washington, D.C. ``It's a hobby that's gone a little too
far.''
   After paying Simpson's auction house a 10 percent fee and
Texas's 8.25 percent sales tax, Taylor will pay $21,285 for the
document. The auction house said it had determined the document is
authentic.
   It took less than a minute for Taylor to outbid his two
competitors, one at Simpson's and one bidding by telephone.
   The birth certificate took a long and winding road from
Liverpool to Houston via the singer's stepmother, Angela Williams,
who sold it to an American investor for an unknown amount.
   The certificate shows that on June 18, 1942, at 107 Rice Lane,
James Paul McCartney was born to James McCartney, a ``centre lathe
turner (aircraft factory),'' and Mary Patricia McCartney, of 10
Sunbury Road, Liverpool, England.
   Taylor, a student of urban planning at Virginia Commonwealth
University, in Richmond, said he got interested in the Beatles when
he was about 13 years old. He has all their records, including some
rare recordings, he said.
   Taylor said he would ``show it all my friends,'' then keep the
document in a safe deposit box.
   He refused to discuss the source of his money, but said, ``I had
a paper route as a kid.''
   If the pop star wants his birth certificate back, he should
bring his checkbook, Taylor said.
   ``Sure, I'll sell it to him,'' he said. ``I would have to talk
about (the price) to Mr. McCartney himself.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0062 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 1908EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Okinawa-USBases     11-18 0239</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Okinawa-US Bases,0254</SECOND>
<HEAD>Socialist-Backed Candidate Elected Governor of Okinawa</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Socialist-backed candidate who wants the United
States to abandon its military bases on Okinawa was elected
governor of the island prefecture Sunday.
   Masahide Ota, 65, backed by the Socialists, Communists and other
opposition parties, defeated Junji Nishime, a conservative who has
been governor of Okinawa for 12 years.
   In nearly compete returns, Ota had 330,924 votes to Nishime's
300,739.
   Nishime, 69, was backed by Prime Minister Toshiki Kaifu's
Liberal Democratic Party and the moderate opposition Democratic
Socialist Party. His third four-year term expires Dec. 9.
   Okinawa, site of some of the bloodiest fighting in World War II,
is host to 35,000 of the 64,000 U.S. troops based in Japan. Okinawa
is the southernmost major island of Japan, about 900 miles
southwest of Tokyo.
   In a poll earlier this year by the prime minister's office,
about 60 percent of Okinawans said they felt the U.S. bases were
unnecessary or dangerous for Japanese security. Another 29 percent
supported the bases.
   Ota, a professor of sociology at Ryukyu University in Okinawa,
campaigned against the bases.
   He also opposed Kaifu's proposal to send Japanese soldiers to
the Persian Gulf where they would have non-combat roles in the
international force opposing Iraq. Kaifu's proposal died in
Parliament because of strong objections by the opposition.
   The election committee said an estimated 75.3 percent of the
830,000 eligible voters turned out, compared with 74.1 percent in
the last election in 1986.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0063 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 1908EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Iran-FemaleInspectors     11-18 0224</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Iran-Female Inspectors,0243</SECOND>
<HEAD>Canadian Agency Won't Send Women To Inspect Iranian Grain Ships</HEAD>
<DATELINE>VANCOUVER, British Columbia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Female grain inspectors will
no longer board Iranian ships here after the crew of one vessel
refused to allow an Agriculture Canada official on board without a
veil.
   A federal official said recently that the action was the only
solution to a sensitive cultural and religious issue. But a woman's
organization decried the policy as reinforcing bias against women.
   ``The Canadian position when dealing with a country like Iran,
which has certain cultural-religious practices, is that we should
be as non-confrontational as much as possible,'' said Kingsley
Chong, Agriculture Canada district manager.
   ``Whenever there is an Iranian ship in port, operational
requirements permitting, then we will avoid sending women aboard.''
   The policy arose after an incident on Oct. 16 when two Canadian
inspectors tried to board the Iran Jamal, an Iranian ship docked at
a British Columbian port. One of the inspectors was a woman. The
crew barred her from boarding until she put on a veil.
   ``Here we have a case where Canadian women are being forced into
being culturally sensitive by being barred from doing their job,''
said Sunera Thobani of the Vancouver Status of Women committee.
``It is clearly a case of discrimination against women.''
   Canada shipped $256 million worth of grain to Iran in 1989,
about 9 percent of all Canadian grain shipments last year.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0064 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 1918EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BRF--Gulf-NOW     11-18 0161</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Gulf-NOW,0154</SECOND>
<HEAD>NOW Board Condemns Military Buildup in Gulf</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The National Organization For Women on Sunday
condemned the U.S. military buildup in the Persian Gulf.
   The national board of NOW, which held policy meetings in Boston
over the weekend, adopted a resolution calling on Congress to act
``assertively'' to encourage withdrawal of troops from the gulf,
according to NOW spokeswoman Ellen Zucker.
   The statement contends both Kuwait and Saudi Arabia are
``despotic, clan-run monarchies'' that ``systematically oppress
women, denying them the basic human right of self determination,
freedom of speech, association, transportation and dress.''
   ``Although NOW does not support the invasion of Kuwait by Iraq,
we are appalled at the possibility that lives should be lost to
defend the oppressive regimes of Kuwait and Saudi Arabia,'' the
resolution said.
   NOW urged the administration and Congress to develop a national
energy policy that reduces American reliance on oil.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0065 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 1920EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Colombia-Violence     11-18 0142</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Colombia-Violence,0131</SECOND>
<HEAD>Councilman Killed, Congressman Wounded in Colombia</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BOGOTA, Colombia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Assassins killed a city councilman and
wounded a governing party congressman in a northern city Sunday,
police said.
   Unidentified gunmen in Apartado opened fire on Jesus Maria
Velasquez, a councilman for the city, and Elkin Garcia Castrillon,
a congressman and member of the Liberal Party, according to a
police statement.
   Velasquez was killed immediately. Garcia was being treated for a
slight bullet wound in a hospital in Apartado, near the border with
Panama.
   The two men were meeting together in the city when the attack
occurred. The police statement gave no other details.
   Massacres and other political violence have plagued Apartado and
the surrounding region, where both leftist guerrillas and
right-wing death squads are active.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0066 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 1924EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-CNN-NoriegaTapes 4thLd-Writethru a0771 11-18 0893</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-CNN-Noriega Tapes, 4th Ld-Writethru, a0771,1020</SECOND>
<HEAD>Supreme Court Rejects CNN Bid To Broadcast Noriega Tapes</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: To UPDATE with comments from Noriega's attorney, inserts new
grafs 12-13: Noriega's defense ....</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By RICHARD CARELLI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Supreme Court refused by a 7-2 vote Sunday
to give Cable News Network permission to broadcast tape recordings
of conversations between Panama's Gen. Manuel Noriega and his
lawyers.
   The court rejected an emergency request by CNN that was aimed at
lifting a federal judge's order forbidding the broadcasts until he
could determine what the tapes disclose.
   The emergency request had called the Nov. 8 order by U.S.
District Judge William Hoeveler in Miami an unconstitutional
``prior restraint'' of free speech. But only two justices -
Thurgood Marshall and Sandra Day O'Connor - agreed with that
assessment.
   Voting against CNN were Chief Justice William H. Rehnquist and
Justices Byron R. White, Harry A. Blackmun, John Paul Stevens,
Antonin Scalia, Anthony M. Kennedy and David H. Souter.
   The Justice Department had joined with Noriega's lawyers in
opposing the request.
   In addition to the emergency request, the court also turned down
a formal appeal filed by the cable network, in a one-sentence
order.
   CNN President Tom Johnson called the court's decision ``a loss
of a battle in a continuing war against censorship.''
   Johnson said the network would immediately turn the tapes in its
possession over to Judge Hoeveler. He said CNN is ``confident that
after he reviews them he will decide on the merits to deny the
prior restraint.''
   ``CNN is committed to establishing its full freedom to telecast
newsworthy information to the American people and it will pursue
this case vigorously in order to do so,'' Johnson said.
   Floyd Abrams, CNN's attorney in the case, said the court's
decison ``has left an opening through which defense lawyers and
prosecutors may try to muzzle news articles.''
   ``The refusal of the court to hear the case does seem to
countenance brief prior restraints of a few days duration based on
almost no showing of need at all by the courts,'' Abrams said.
   Noriega's defense attorney, Jon May, said CNN had opened a
``Pandora's box'' with its First Amendment challenge.
   ``We think its a correct ruling,'' May said. ``This is a case of
the messenger shooting itself. To whatever extent the media may
complain this is a significant adverse decision, CNN has only
itself to blame.''
   In a dissenting opinion for himself and O'Connor, Marshall said
``this case is of extraordinary consequence for freedom of the
press.''
   ``Our precedents make unmistakably clear that any prior
restraint of expression comes to this court bearing a heavy
presumption against its constitutional validity and that the
proponent of this drastic remedy carries a heavy burden of showing
justification for its imposition,'' Marshall said.
   ``I do not see how the prior restraint imposed in this case can
be reconciled with these teachings,'' Marshall said. ``Even more
fundamentally, if the lower courts in this case are correct in
their remarkable conclusion that publication can be automatically
restrained pending application of the demanding test established by
(a 1976 decision that severely limited the power of judges to
impose such restraints) then I think it is imperative that we
re-examine the premises and operation of (that decision).''
   Jane Kirtley, executive director Reporter's Committee for
Freedom of the Press, said she was ``stunned'' by the decision,
which she called ``truly unprecedented.''
   ``The fact that the court would be willing to tolerate a prior
restraint in these circumstances signals a new era in First
Amendment jurisprudence,'' Kirtley said. ``It will have a
far-reaching impact going beyond this case extending to many cases
in state and federal courts around the country.
   Bruce Sanford, an attorney for the Society of Professional
Journalists, said the court's decision is ``troublesome because it
seems inconceivable that Noriega's counsel would ever be able to
prove that his right to a fair trial was in jeopardy because of the
CNN tapes.''
   Walt Wurfel, a spokesman for the National Association of
Broadcasters, said his group was ``very disappointed'' with the
court's decision. ``We view the lower court's order as prior
restraint,'' he said.
   The Bush administration Saturday had urged the high court to
leave intact Hoeveler's order. Solicitor General Kenneth Starr, the
government's top-ranking courtroom lawyer, argued in written briefs
that the restraining order was justified to give the judge time to
determine whether seven tapes in CNN's possession might interfere
with Noriega's ability to receive a fair trial.
   Noriega, who is awaiting trial on charges of taking $4.6 million
in payoffs to protect cocaine trade through Panama, is being held
in a federal prison near Miami. Federal prison authorities monitor
and tape record all inmates' telephone conversations except those
between an inmates and their defense teams. But the CNN tape
recordings reportedly contain some conversations between the
deposed Panamanian leader and his defense lawyers.
   Sunday's high court order, issued without any explanatory
opinion, does not necessarily preclude the possibility that some
day the court will rule that Hoeveler's order did violate CNN's
free-speech rights.
   The court conceivably could have refused to help CNN because of
some procedural reason. The cable network might carry its legal
battle back to the court at some later date.
   But meanwhile, CNN is under court order not to broadcast those
portions of its tapes divulging Noriega's conversations with his
lawyers. If those conversations are broadcast, CNN could be cited
with contempt of court and fined heavily.
   The federal government lost a much-publicized battle over a
prior restraint in 1971 when the Supreme Court allowed The New York
Times and The Washington Post to publish the so-called Pentagon
papers detailing American involvement in Vietnam.
   In a key 1976 decision stemming from pretrial publicity in a
Nebraska murder case, the court ruled that forbidding the news
media from publishing or broadcasting information in its possession
almost never can be justified.
   The court in that decision called such prior restraints -
sometimes referred to as ``gag orders'' - the ``least tolerable''
measures of assuring fair trials.
   In seeking the prior restraint against CNN, Noriega's lawyers
argued that broadcasting the tapes would poison their client's
fair-trial rights in two ways: through pretrial publicity and by
compromising his relationship with his lawyers.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0067 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 1925EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--Spain-Bomb     11-18 0141</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Spain-Bomb,0139</SECOND>
<HEAD>Two Police Killed by Bomb in Basque Region</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BILBAO, Spain (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A bomb hidden by Basque terrorists in a
parked van exploded Sunday as police drove by, authorities said.
Two officers were reported killed and two wounded.
   The van was parked on a highway near Santurce, seven miles north
of the northern industrial city of Bilbao, said a police official,
who was not identified under standing rules.
   The bomb was set off by remote control. Police blamed the
radical separatist group ETA, which has carried out similar attacks
in the past, the official said.
   ETA, the Basque language acronym for Basque Homeland and
Liberty, has claimed responsibility for killing more than 600
people since 1968, including 19 this year.
   The group seeks independence for the three-province Basque
country of northeastern Spain.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0068 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 1956EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Spain-Franco     11-18 0284</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Spain-Franco,0315</SECOND>
<HEAD>Thousands Gather At Monument To Franco</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RICHARD LORANT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MADRID, Spain (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Thousands of Spaniards sang old fascist
songs and railed against democracy Sunday at a statue of Gen.
Francisco Franco on the 15th anniversary of the dictator's death.
   The crowd of about 5,000 included Fascists, neo-Nazis, nostalgic
middle-aged adults, white-haired Spanish Civil War veterans, and
many clean-cut teen-agers too young to remember Franco's 36 years
in power.
   Franco died at 83 on Nov. 20, 1975. He became head of state
following the victory of his Nationalist rebel army in the 1936-39
civil war.
   His daughter, Carmen Franco Polo, attended the hourlong rally,
as did Blas Pinar, the leader of the Francoist National Front
party. The party has no representation in parliament.
   A woman opened the rally by reading a poem of lament:
   ``Spain, poor Spain. You were so beautiful. Now you're degraded.
... Be patient, you will be as you were before - clean, saintly and
purified. The dirty sinners will be plucked out.''
   A Roman Catholic priest prayed for those who ``fell for the
fatherland'' during the Civil War. The rally closed with stiff-arm
salutes and the singing of the Spanish fascist battle hymn, ``Face
to the Sun.''
   In past anniversaries, youths have smashed car windows and set
trash barrels on fire, but police said there was no violence at
this year's event.
   The ralliers expressed nostalgia for Franco's repressive Spain,
where leftists and other non-conformists had no place. They said
Franco did better than later leaders at controlling crime,
terrorism and unemployment.
   Since Franco's death, Spain has moved gradually into the
European cultural and economic mainstream. A Socialist, Felipe
Gonzalez, has been prime minister since 1982.
   Supporters of Jean-Marie Le Pen's National Front party, the
ultraconservative party in France, attended the rally in combat
fatigues.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0069 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 2023EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Philippines-Bombing     11-18 0138</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Philippines-Bombing,0124</SECOND>
<HEAD>Four Explosions Shake Filipino Justice Secretary's Home</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MANILA, Philippines (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Four explosions rocked the home of
Justice Secretary Franklin Drilon early Monday, but the official
and his family were not injured, police said.
   The explosions occurred at 4:05 a.m. at Drilon's home in the
fashionable Greenhills district of suburban San Juan, less than one
mile from Camp Crame, headquarters of the national police.
   The blasts shattered widows and damaged the roof but caused no
injuries, police said.
   There was no claim of responsibility.
   Drilon's department supervises the National Bureau of
Investigation and other offices involved in criminal
investigations. He also serves as chairman of the Cabinet Security
Committee, which advises President Corazon Aquino on security.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0070 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 2029EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-Baker 3rdLd-Writethru a0765 11-18 0472</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Baker, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0765,540</SECOND>
<NOTE>Eds: To UPDATE with Baker-Shevardnaze meeting; inserts new grafs
4-8: Baker later ....; picks up 4th graf pvs: Baker commented ....;
deletes as outdated 9th graf pvs: Baker also ....</NOTE>
<HEAD>Baker Calls Iraqi Hostage Offer `Cynical Manipulation'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PATRICK McDOWELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Iraq's offer to free all foreign hostages by March
25 is ``just further cynical manipulation of innocent people's
lives,'' U.S. Secretary of State James A. Baker III said Sunday.
   Iraqi President Saddam Hussein ``never should have taken them in
the first place,'' Baker said.
   ``He has it in his power to release them immediately, as the
United Nations and indeed the international community are
demanding, and I think this is just further cynical manipulation of
innocent people's lives.''
   Baker later met with Soviet Foreign Minister Eduard Shevardnadze
for two hours in anticipation of a meeting Monday between President
Bush and Soviet President Mikhail Gorbachev.
   Both officials declined afterward to say whether the Soviet
Union would back a U.S.-proposed resolution in the U.N. Security
Council authorizing the use of force against Iraq.
   ``I cannot say that we have reached any decisions,''
Shevardnadze said. ``Tomorrow these discussions will continue at a
presidential level. It's not so simple that we can just come out
and announce something.''
   Baker told reporters after the meeting to ``stay tuned'' and
indicated an announcement could come Monday night.
   ``I have pointed out before the importance of maintaining to the
extent we can a common approach and a common understanding with
respect to this problem, and we're working on that,'' he said.
   Baker commented on the Iraqi announcement just before meeting
British Foreign Secretary Douglas Hurd, one of series of talks on
the eve of a three-day European summit. Baker was seeking support
for the U.S. stance against Hussein.
   After his talks with Baker, Hurd said Saddam's offer was just a
``further demonstration of the policy of the human shield,'' in
which Iraq has placed hostages in strategic places to try to
discourage an attack.
   ``Why doesn't he let them go this week?'' Hurd said of Saddam
and the hostages.
   White House Press Secretary Marlin Fitzwater said the
announcement appeared deliberately timed by Saddam as an effort to
divert attention from President Bush's planned Thanksgiving visit
with troops in the Persian Gulf region.
   ``He (Saddam) does it all the time,'' Fitzwater said, referring
to other earlier gestures by Saddam in freeing foreigners. ``We
want all the hostages released.''
   Earlier, Baker said the United States was not sure whether Iraq
is armed with highly accurate Soviet-made SS-12 missiles capable of
carrying chemical warheads.
   ``We would be concerned about that if it is confirmed,'' Baker
told reporters after talks with French Foreign Minister Roland
Dumas.
   ``As of yet, it has not been confirmed. It is something we are
inquiring into,'' Baker said.
   The Washington Post reported Friday that a Western diplomat in
Baghdad reported that the Soviets had given Iraq some of the SS-12
medium-range missiles. The diplomat said he did not know how many
missiles were sent or when they were sent.
   Baker also discussed a possible U.N. resolution with the foreign
ministers of Romania and Finland, both current members of the
Security Council.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0071 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 2055EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-ArmsTreaty 1stLd-Writethru a0680 11-18 0698</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Arms Treaty, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0680,850</SECOND>
<HEAD>Arms Cuts Will Erase European Fear of Surprise Attack</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: To CORRECT figure to 30,000 sted 20,000 for limit on on
armored combat vehicles, SUBs 10th graf: - Armored combat ....;
serves as 3rd Ld-Writethru to b0450 which moved in advance.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT BURNS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A landmark arms treaty cutting non-nuclear
forces in Europe is far from the final step in disarmament, but it
offers one over arching reward: the end to fear of a massive
surprise ground attack.
   It also may open the way for the eventual elimination of U.S.
and Soviet nuclear weapons from Europe, some analysts believe,
although that issue is strongly debated.
   The Conventional Forces in Europe, or CFE, treaty scheduled to
be signed Monday in Paris alters the military balance in Europe
mainly by erasing Moscow's ability to mass huge numbers of tanks
and other heavy armor in central Europe.
   ``It is the definitive end of the surprise attack option'' for
the Soviets, said Jonathan Dean, a former U.S. representative to
East-West conventional arms negotiations.
   NATO and Warsaw Pact negotiators in Vienna initialed the
document on Sunday, ending 20 months of talks.
   From the start of the Cold War and the creation first of NATO in
1949 and then the Soviet-led Warsaw Pact alliance, the military
landscape of Western Europe has been dominated by fear of a ``bolt
from the blue'' communist-bloc ground assault.
   To eliminate that perceived threat, the CFE treaty - limiting
the weapons of 22 countries and covering European territory from
the Atlantic Ocean to the Ural Mountains - requires the Soviets to
drastically reduce their forces, including:
   - Tanks, from about 41,000 before the treaty negotiations began
in 1989 to 13,150. Moscow already has reduced its tank holdings in
the territory covered by the treaty to about 21,000, mainly by
moving its best models east as replacements for older ones.
   The allowable number tanks for all of Eastern Europe will be
20,000. The United States and its NATO allies also will be allowed
20,000 tanks. That will require a cut of about 4,000 for NATO,
although more than 1,000 of the top-of-the-line American M1-A1
tanks already are being moved from Europe to Saudi Arabia.
   - Armored combat vehicles, from the 32,300 now deployed by the
Soviets to 30,000. NATO will not have to make any cuts in this
category, which includes such war-fighting machinery as the U.S.
Bradley Fighting Vehicle used to move infantry, protect maneuvering
tanks and help consolidate gains in an offensive.
   - Artillery pieces, providing the essential firepower for a
combat operation, from about 52,000 for the Soviets before the CFE
negotiations began, to 13,175. The Soviets already have reduced to
18,300. NATO will stay at its current level of 18,500.
   Those three weapon categories - tanks, armored combat vehicles
and artillery - are especially important to the military balance in
Europe because they form the core of non-nuclear offensive
capability for both the Soviets and NATO.
   Once the treaty is implemented, neither side will be able to
marshal enough firepower within striking range of the other to
launch a land invasion without setting off warning bells months, or
even years, in advance, analysts say.
   Because most of the cuts will be made by the Soviets, no
significant cost savings will be felt immediately by the NATO
countries, according to the Institute for Defense and Disarmament
Studies, a research group based at Brookline, Mass.
   The treaty does not include cuts in military personnel in
Europe. A U.S.-Soviet agreement last February to limit each side to
195,000 foreign troops in central Europe, plus an additional 30,000
U.S. troops elsewhere in Europe, has been abandoned. The plan was
overtaken by events, including the Soviets' declared intent to
withdraw all their forces from central Europe within four years,
the newly unified Germany's agreement to limit the size of its
armed forces, and the dissolution of the Warsaw Pact as a coherent
military force.
   Just last month Washington announced it would unilaterally
withdraw 40,000 troops from Western Europe and close some of its
bases there. Then on Nov. 8, President Bush ordered about 100,000
U.S. Army combat forces from Europe to Saudi Arabia as
reinforcements against Iraq. That cuts U.S. Army strength in Europe
by one-half, although it was presumed that some of those troops
would later return to Europe.
   Most of the weapons to be withdrawn from Europe under the CFE
treaty will be destroyed, although the treaty permits some to be
converted to non-military or military support purposes.
   Neither the Soviets and their Warsaw Pact partners nor the
United States and its NATO allies will be required to destroy any
attack helicopters limited by the treaty. Those in excess of the
2,000 permitted by the treaty can be converted to noncombat roles.
   For other combat aircraft, the Soviets will be required to
eliminate about one-third of their inventory in the area covered by
the treaty. No cuts are required of the NATO countries because they
already are well below the treaty limit of 6,800 combat aircraft.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0072 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 2119EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ShipRiot     11-18 0277</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Ship Riot,0319</SECOND>
<BYLINE>FBI Arrests Two Trawler Crewmen In Shipboard Riot
^By JOHN ENDERS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ANCHORAGE, Alaska (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two crewmen from a factory trawler were
in federal custody Sunday facing assault charges after a shipboard
riot over unpaid wages.
   The skipper and the chief engineer of the 205-foot Arctic Hero
barricaded themselves inside the wheelhouse and engine room,
respectively, after about seven of the 45 crew members rampaged
through the vessel Friday, Coast Guard and FBI officials said.
   James R. Smith Jr., 26, and Reginald Collins, 28, both of
Seattle, were being held in the Unalaska Department of Public
Safety Jail in Unalaska, adjacent to Dutch Harbor in the Aleutian
Islands, the FBI said. They were to be brought here for arraignment
on the federal charges.
   The incident occurred in international waters in the Bering Sea,
100 miles west of Dutch Harbor, which is 800 miles southwest of
Anchorage.
   Damage to the Seattle-based ship, which catches and processes
fish, was estimated at $25,000. Three crew members were treated for
minor injuries.
   The Coast Guard intercepted the vessel Friday after the captain
called for help. The Arctic Hero was escorted to Dutch Harbor,
where it was boarded Saturday by FBI, Coast Guard and National
Marine Fisheries Service agents.
   Skipper Keith Dillon said the men rioted because the ship's
owner, Palmco Pacific Corp. of Hawaii, failed to pay them on time,
though he told them their paychecks were waiting on shore.
   Most of the crew stayed in their cabins during the disturbance.
   Dillon said the rioting crew members quit the trawler's fish
processing line and, armed with clubs and fire axes, beat the chief
engineer. They allegedly broke into a locker, drank some beer and
took over parts of the vessel.
   The chief engineer kept control of the vessel by locking the
engine room doors from the inside.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0073 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 2120EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r e BC-Theater     11-18 0482</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Theater,0588</SECOND>
<HEAD>Topol Stars in a Revival of `Fiddler on the Roof' on Broadway</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: No PMs planned.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By MICHAEL KUCHWARA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Drama Critic</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   It has been more than 25 years since Zero Mostel
first trudged across the stage of the Imperial Theater as Tevye the
philosophical milkman in ``Fiddler on the Roof.''
   There have been a lot of Tevyes since then, from Herschel
Bernardi to Jan Peerce, but the role has been co-opted in recent
years by Topol, the Israeli-born actor who starred in the London
production of the musical as well as the movie version.
   Now, after a long national tour, Topol has arrived on Broadway
where ``Fiddler'' opened Sunday at the Gershwin Theater. It's no
surprise to report that star and show both hold up well. In fact,
this is a glorious revival, with Topol delivering a genuine star
turn. And the material hasn't grown old at all.
   ``Fiddler on the Roof'' was the last great musical in the
Rodgers and Hammerstein tradition, a style R&amp;H developed and
perfected in the 1940s with such classic shows as ``Oklahoma!,''
``Carousel'' and ``South Pacific.''
   ``Fiddler,'' which originally opened in New York in September
1964, has that same extraordinary integration of story and song.
There is not a wasted moment in the musical.
   Songs - music by Jerry Bock and lyrics by Sheldon Harnick - are
used to explain character or advance plot. The story, which Joseph
Stein artfully adapted from the stories of Sholom Aleichem, serves
as a framework for those musical numbers. And everything was tied
together perfectly by Jerome Robbins, whose original direction and
choreography have been faithfully reproduced here by Ruth Mitchell
and Sammy Dallas Bayes.
   There quite simply isn't a better opening scene in the American
musical theater. In that one song, ``Tradition,'' the musical's
underlying theme, the ties that bind together the small Jewish
community in the turn-of-the-century Russian village of Anatevka,
are brilliantly stated.
   The story of how those ties start to unravel, torn apart by
personal, social and political upheavals, are brilliantly
delineated by Bock, Harnick, Stein and especially Robbins.
   Topol's Tevye is more aristocratic than Mostel's milkman. He has
a commanding voice, full and deep, and he moves with an authority
that makes the eventual destruction of his world and the dispersal
of his family especially poignant. Yet Topol doesn't miss a moment
of the show's humor, never forgetting the man's indecisiveness,
whether he is arguing with his wife or with God.
   The dances remain first-rate, particularly Teyve's dream
sequence in which Motel the tailor is chosen as the husband for his
oldest daughter.
   Marcia Lewis makes a wonderful Golde, shrewish yet ultimately
sympathetic. There are some sharp cameos particularly Ruth Jaroslow
as the busybody matchmaker, Mark Zeller as the butcher Lazar Wolf
and Tia Riebling as the sweet-voiced Hodel.
   Boris Aronson's original designs, with their echoes of Marc
Chagall paintings, remain as evocative as ever, particularly
Teyve's house which spins around the large stage and opens
gracefully to reveal its homespun interior to the audience.
   At one of the final preview performances, the audience was swept
up into the show as soon as the curtain rose. Many of them began
humming along with the score. They knew what to expect, and this
revival delivers it.
   The one surprise may be that this ``Fiddler on the Roof'' turns
out to be as good as they remember the musical to be.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0074 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 2134EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Gunther'sGoodbye     11-18 0336</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gunther's Goodbye,0404</SECOND>
<HEAD>Famed Animal Trainer Bids Goodbye To The Big Top</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto staffing</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TARA BRADLEY-STECK</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PITTSBURGH (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   For two years, animal trainer Gunther
Gebel-Williams has been bidding farewell in what has arguably been
one of the longest exits in entertainment history.
   But his honest-to-gosh last goodbye under the Big Top scared him
more than the beasts whose many scars he carries.
   ``Don't cry. Don't make it hard on me,'' the star of Ringling
Bros. and Barnum &amp; Bailey Circus said to his son, Mark, in the
grand finale of Sunday's show.
   His daughter, Tina, who also performs in the circus, hugged him
and handed him a box of tissues as the audience at the Civic Arena
gave him a standing ovation.
   The circus, not known for understatement, unfurled banners
shouting, ``Gunther,'' and life-size posters of the man humbly
billed as the ``Golden Gladiator,'' ``Teutonic Tiger Trainer,''
``Caesar of the Circus'' and ``Lord of the Rings.''
   Eighteen elephants reared back and formed a line, each animal
with its front legs on another's back.
   The trainer, who came from Germany 22 years ago, explained
recently why he's leaving the Big Top at age 56:
   ``Everybody asks me, `Why now?' I want to step down when I am
really good. I don't want to be like Ali, Sugar Ray Leonard,
`Another fight, another fight.' ... Every show is always a risk for
me. How long can you take that? There are always young tigers.''
   On Sunday, Gebel-Williams thanked fellow performers, circus
owner Kenneth Feld, the audience and other circus owners from
around the world who came to pay tribute. The crowd sang ``Auld
Lang Syne,'' the traditional conclusion of the circus' two-year
tour, as Gebel-Williams skipped off waving goodbye.
   In his 21 years with Ringling Bros., Gebel-Williams has
performed 11,697 shows before an estimated 100 million people. He
appeared in Madison Square Garden more times than Frank Sinatra,
Jack Dempsey or any other entertainer and has a plaque to prove it.
   Son Mark, 20, will carry on the act - with African and Indian
elephants, white Lippizaner horses, zebras and camels - but without
Gebel-Williams' tigers. The trainer is so devoted to the tigers -
and so fearful that they won't transfer their devotion to his son -
that they will retire with him to his winter home in Venice, Fla.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0075 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 2150EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SKorea-Politics     11-18 0272</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-SKorea-Politics,0298</SECOND>
<HEAD>South Korean Opposition Lifts Legislative Boycott</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SEOUL, South Korea (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The top opposition party is ending its
four-month-old boycott of parliament, the party leader announced
Monday.
   Kim Dae-jung, head of the largest opposition Party for Peace and
Democracy, said the party's 70 national legislators would take
their seats in the National Assembly later in the day.
   The other opposition party in parliament, the splinter
Democratic Party, said members had not decided whether to follow
suit. That party has eight legislators.
   ``There are numerous tasks and issues waiting to be resolved,''
Kim told a news conference. He said rival political leaders had
reached agreement on ending the boycott, including a key pledge to
hold local elections in 1991.
   ``If the regime fails to fulfill its promise on all the issues
affecting people's lives, it should be prepared to resign,'' Kim
said.
   The 78 opposition members of the 299-member parliament resigned
en masse in July, charging President Roh Tae-woo's governing
Democratic Liberal Party with railroading bills and reneging on
democratic reform.
   The boycott was effectively ended over the weekend after rival
political leaders reached agreement on holding the local elections.
   South Korea has not had local elections since they were
abolished by an authoritarian regime 30 years ago.
   The opposition had also demanded the cancellation of governing
party plans to change South Korea's system of government from
presidential to parliamentary. Critics said it was a ploy by the
governing party to prolong control of power.
   That matter was settled earlier this month after a rival faction
within the governing party revolted against the president and
announced its objection to a change in the system of government.
Roh backed down and promised not to push for the change.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0076 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 2152EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-GasolinePrices     11-18 0195</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gasoline Prices,0213</SECOND>
<HEAD>Gasoline Prices Record Biggest Drop Since Gulf Crisis Began</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The average price of gasoline fell almost a
penny a gallon over the past two weeks - the biggest drop
nationwide since the Persian Gulf crisis began - according to a
survey released Sunday.
   Prices dropped for all grades except leaded regular at full
service pumps, the Lundberg Survey of 13,500 stations found. The
survey compared prices Nov. 16 with those of Nov. 2, when the
survey was last conducted.
   The national average for all grades of gasoline was 145.98
cents, a drop of about .94 cent a gallon since Nov. 2.
   Trilby Lundberg, who directs the survey, attributed the drop to
recent declines in wholesale prices.
   The survey found average prices at self-service pumps were
135.10 cents for regular unleaded, 151.19 cents for premium
unleaded and 131.61 cents for regular leaded.
   Averages at full-service stations were 157.76 cents for regular
unleaded, 171.41 cents for premium unleaded and 154.90 cents for
regular leaded.
   Lundberg said that while the Nov. 2 survey showed drops in some
parts of the nation, the latest survey reflected drops nationwide.
It was the first significant drop in price since Iraq invaded
Kuwait Aug. 2, she said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0077 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 2204EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-ChronicFatigue 1stLd-Writethru a0772 11-18 0432</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Chronic Fatigue, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0772,0523</SECOND>
<HEAD>Blood Test Developed for `Yuppie Flu,' Researcher Says</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS grafs 12-13, `In any case...,' to ADD name of cell
checked for in blood test. Pick up 14th graf pvs, `Levy said...</NOTE>
<DATELINE>CHARLOTTE, N.C. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A blood test has been devised to help
doctors diagnose chronic fatigue syndrome, a flu-like illness some
have dubbed ``yuppie flu,'' a scientist said Sunday.
   Dr. Jay Levy of San Francisco announced the development at a
national conference on the disease here. He predicted the
mysterious illness will be the ``disease of the '90s'' as the
public and the medical community become more aware of it.
   ``It takes about decade before the public wakes up and realizes
that this is not going to go away,'' Levy said.
   The weekend conference, titled ``Unraveling the Mystery,'' drew
400 people including researchers and people afflicted with the
ailment.
   Chronic fatigue syndrome is characterized by fatigue,
exhaustion, joint and muscle aches, and an array of other problems
that persist for more than six months, and often for years.
   Tens of thousands of Americans believe they have chronic fatigue
syndrome, although the extent of it is uncertain. Some researchers
believe the disease may be centuries old and it's just been
misdiagnosed all this time.
   Because it has been widely reported among well-educated women in
their 30s and 40s, the syndrome was dubbed ``yuppie flu.''
   An effort to discover how widespread it is, an inter-agency
coordinating commmittee has been formed, said Dr. Walter Gunn, a
chronic fatigue syndrome researcher at the Centers for Disease
Control in Atlanta.
   Levy, an AIDS researcher at the University of California at San
Francisco, led a group that developed a blood test for the disease.
   Levy said his team was unable to find one virus that caused the
illness. Some research has linked the syndrome to a retrovirus, one
of the family of viruses that causes AIDS.
   ``Because of the immune profile of these patients, we believe
there has been an infection by some agent, though this agent may no
longer be in the body,'' Levy said. ``Or it may be hidden. It
cannot as yet be identified.''
   In any case, he said, the immune system of chronic fatigue
patients is activated for months or years, creating high levels of
a particular white blood cell, caled the CD8&plus; cytotoxic T cell.
   The persistence of the white blood cell causes symptoms of a
viral infection, Levy said.
   The CD8&plus; cytotoxic cells appear to be the major cell type
activated in the disease - a signature unique to chronic fatigue
syndrome, Levy said. So the blood test checks for high levels of
those cells.
   ``This is a way to distinguish those with fatigue alone from
those with an immune reaction that causes chronic fatigue,'' he
said.
   Levy said the level of the white blood cells along with an
examination of the patient's medical history could determine
whether a patient is suffering from the syndrome.
   Levy and other researchers suggested the syndrome be renamed
``chronic immune activation syndrome'' to reflect their findings.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0078 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 2209EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-GamblingLandRush     11-18 0311</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gambling Land Rush,0379</SECOND>
<HEAD>Legalized Gambling Brings Land Rush to 3 Colorado Mining Towns</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CRIPPLE CREEK, Colo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Gamblers whose game of choice is
real estate won big in this old mining town by betting correctly
that state voters would approve a referendum to allow limited
gambling here.
   Colorado voters on Nov. 6 allowed limited-stakes gambling for
this town below Pikes Peak as well as in Central City and Black
Creek.
   Before Election Day more than 50 properties changed hands in
Cripple Creek. The prices paid were up to 10 times their previous
price, the Teller County assessor's office said.
   At least 27 lots in the town's historic district - its future
gambling district, sold for nearly $1.9 million, the Rocky Mountain
News reported Sunday.
   The winner so far in that gamble seems to be Norbert Larsen, a
Cripple Creek construction worker.
   Larsen bought 10 lots in the historic district for $40,000 in
July. He sold them Oct. 26 to the Seravalli family of Daytona
Beach, Fla., for $200,000, records show.
   ``(If) you don't gamble, you don't win,'' Larsen said. ``It's
all gambling. Some people are going to make their money gambling on
land, some on running a business, some playing poker... I won.''
   The Seravallis snapped up at least 20 of the 27 lots in the
historic district. John Seravalli Sr. and his twin sons, John Jr.
and Joseph, put up $1.2 million for the prime properties, the paper
said.
   Central City and Black Hawk are two former mining towns about 25
miles west of Denver.
   The referendum makes it legal in the three towns to make wagers
up to $5 on such games as blackjack and poker.
   Some property owners are still holding out for an irresistible
offer.
   Vern ``Terp'' Terpening, who has owned Terp's Leather Goods in
Central City for more than 40 years, wants $4.5 million for his
12,000 square feet on Main Street, plus two houses and property in
town. The propety was assessed at $1.7 million two years ago.
   ``I've heard all these stories about the outrageous amounts of
money I've been offered, and nobody's sorrier than me they're not
true,'' Terpening said. ``I'd love to hear some outrageous
offers.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0079 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 2213EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Bush-Europe 5thLd-Writethru a0756 11-18 0988</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bush-Europe, 5th Ld-Writethru, a0756,1,030</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush Seeks Support for Gulf Policy, Asks Germany to Take More
Active Role</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: To UPDATE with Baker-Shevardnadze meeting, subs 9th graf pvs:
Bush is ....; with new grafs 9-13; picks up 10th graf pvs: White
House ....; cuts last 3 grafs to tighten.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By TOM RAUM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush on Sunday began a series of meetings
with allied leaders aimed at solidifying support for his Persian
Gulf policies. He urged German Chancellor Helmut Kohl to take a
more active role in confronting Iraq's ``challenges to peace and
freedom.''
   During a rain-drenched half day in Germany, Kohl cautioned Bush
against pursuing a military solution before exhausting all avenues
of negotiation. Bush said he, too, would like to see a peaceful
solution to the crisis.
   The president then traveled to Paris for a 34-nation summit of
North American and European nations. It was the third stop on an
eight-day trip highlighted by the signing Monday of a conventional
forces treaty with the Soviet Union and Thanksgiving dinner with
U.S. troops in Saudi Arabia.
   French President Francois Mitterrand hosted Bush for Sunday
dinner and the Iraqi invasion of Kuwait was high on the agenda.
Mitterrand, like Kohl is stressing a non-ilitary outcome to the
Persian Gulf crisis.
   During the 45-minute dinner, Bush and Mitterrand agreed ``that
it is necessary to pursue and strengthen the action taken in the
framework of the U.N. Security Council,'' Mitterrand spokesman
Hubert Vedrine said.
   In Rome, meanwhile, Soviet President Mikhail S. Gorbachev said
``new ideas'' have emerged to avert a war in the Persian Gulf. ``I
am convinced that we will succeed in finding a way out of this deep
crisis,'' he said.
   Gorbachev did not elaborate.
   Bush and Gorbachev planned to meet over breakfast Tuesday.
   
   Bush is seeking to build support for a United Nations resolution
authorizing military action to drive Iraq's Saddam Hussein from
Kuwait. So far, the Soviets have not agreed.
   Secretary of State James A. Baker III and Soviet Foreign
Minister Eduard Shevardnadze both declined to say after meeting
Sunday if the Soviets would support the U.S.-proposed resolution on
using force against Iraq.
   ``I cannot say that we have reached any decisions,''
Shevardnadze said. ``Tomorrow these discussions will continue at a
presidential level. It's not so simple that we can just come out
and announce something.''
   Baker told reporters after the meeting to ``stay tuned'' and
indicated an announcement could come Monday night.
   ``I have pointed out before the importance of maintaining to the
extent we can a common approach and a common understanding with
respect to this problem, and we're working on that,'' he said.
   White House press secretary Marlin Fitzwater shrugged off Iraq's
announcement that it would release the hostages it has been
holding, letting them go in groups between Christmas and March 25.
   ``We want all the hostages released,'' Fitzwater said in Paris.
``He (Saddam) does it all the time,'' the spokesman added,
referring to other earlier gestures by Saddam in freeing
foreigners.
   Fitzwater called the Saddam offer to release hostages after
Christmas ``another cynical attempt by him to manipulate families'
hopes and fears.''
   He claimed the announcement appeared deliberately timed by
Saddam as an effort to divert attention from Bush's planned
Thanksgiving visit with troops in the Persian Gulf region.
   Baker said Saddam ``never should have taken them in the first
place.''
   Bush landed early Sunday evening at Orly Airport in Paris after
visiting Kohl's home region of Oggersheim.
   Although Bush and Kohl sought to gloss over their differences,
the two clearly came down on different sides of the issue of using
force in the Persian Gulf.
   ``We're not ruling out any options, we're not ruling any options
in,'' Bush said at a joint news conference with Kohl outside the
German leader's home in this suburb of the industrial city of
Ludwigshafen.
   But Kohl urged that ``everything be exhausted that there is to
exhaust with negotiations.''
   ``Whoever believes the problem can be solved militarily must
consider not only the mission, but the end of the whole
undertaking,'' Kohl said in a German radio interview aired shortly
after Bush arrived.
   Bush, asked whether Kohl had delivered a similar warning during
their private session, said: ``He made very clear he'd like to see
a peaceful resolution to this question and so would I.''
   ``Clearly, anybody that takes a look at the map and understands
the realities of the world knows that this united Germany is and
will be a tremendous force for peace and certainly for economic
good in the world,'' Bush said.
   The Bush administration is looking to Germany to do more in the
U.S.-led effort to drive Saddam from Kuwait.
   ``Just as a new Europe must look beyond its borders, so too must
a united Germany take responsibility for leadership in our
commonwealth of nations,'' Bush said in remarks prepared for a
rain-shortened speech in the nearby 11th century cathedral town of
Speyer.
   Although the driving rainstorm forced Bush to conclude his
speech before he got to the part on the Persian Gulf, White House
aides said the president stood by the remarks.
   Under pressure from the United States and other allies, Kohl has
agreed to provide about $2 billion to assist front-line nations
like Turkey and Jordan whose economies are battered by the economic
boycott of Iraq.
   But, citing constitutional barriers, Germany has not sent any
troops.
   Kohl, with national elections set for next week, may have been
emphasizing his distaste for military action for domestic political
purposes. But White House aides traveling with Bush privately
voiced disappointment with his remarks, particularly coming during
the president's visit.
   Rain dogged Bush throughout his six-hour visit to Germany, and
he and Kohl were drenched as they stood on an uncovered raised
wooden platform in the town square of Speyer.
   ``I see the rains are coming. So I will conclude, mercifully,''
Bush told his audience of 1,500, many of them huddled under
umbrellas. The rain also prompted Kohl to cut short a joint news
conference later in the day, but not before he put in a pitch for
U.S. investment in what used to be East Germany.
   Despite their differences on the Persian Gulf, Bush praised Kohl
as ``the man who united Germany.'' For his part, Kohl called Bush:
``One of the great architects of how Europe looks today.''
   Earlier, as he flew to Germany from Prague, Czechoslovakia, Bush
called Gorbachev's plan to dump his prime minister and give himself
more power ``very interesting.''
   Gorbachev on Saturday won tentative approval from Soviet
lawmakers for a radical reorganization of the executive branch that
will result in the dismissal of Prime Minister Nikolai Ryzhkov.
   ``We'll have a chance to talk to Mr. Gorbachev about all of
that,'' Bush told reporters aboard Air Force One.
   Bush and Gorbachev will be among NATO and Warsaw Pact leaders
signing a historic treaty slashing non-nuclear weapons in Europe.
The two superpower leaders will also have a private breakfast on
Tuesday.
   Bush said the arms treaty, which was initiated Sunday in Vienna
by NATO and Warsaw Pact negotiatiors, ``seems to be overshadowed by
what's happening in the Gulf. But it is a significant milestone.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0080 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 2214EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Nicaragua 1stLd-Writethru a0741 11-18 0617</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Nicaragua, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0741,0739</SECOND>
<HEAD>Troops Clear Rama Road, Nicaraguan Govt Says It Uncovered Plot</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 8 grafs to UPDATE with vice president saying
crackdown unjust; picks up 6th graf pvs, `About 200...</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By RODOLFO GARCIA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MANAGUA, Nicaragua (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Police and troops armed with machineguns on Sunday cleared sections
of a strategic jungle road blocked
for more than two weeks by protesters supporting the former Contra
rebels.
   In a communique broadcast on radio and television late Saturday,
President Violeta Chamorro said she had ordered the army to clear
the Rama Road, which connects the eastern Caribbean coast with
Managua and western Nicaragua.
   The statement, read by the information minister, Danilo Lacayo,
indicated the government planned a crackdown on the protests that
have left 24 people dead in the south and central regions of the
country.
   In her communique, Mrs. Chamorro also accused former Contra
leader Aristides Sanchez Herdocia of plotting the recent protests.
She said he had orchestrated ``a broad plan against peace.''
   Sanchez, who is under arrest in Managua, was a director of the
U.S.-backed Nicaraguan Resistance that battled the former leftist
Sandinista government for nine years.
   Vice President Virgilio Godoy, who is at odds with Mrs.
Chamorro, met with 18 protesting mayors Sunday and said the
government should be responding to the protesters with political
answers, not arrests.
   ``The government should seek a way to satisfy the popular
demands without showing it is humiliated or that it is losing
authority,'' Godoy told the mayors.
   He called their actions ``a beautiful movement of civic,
patriotic and peaceful protest with a popular base.'' He added that
the government crackdown was intended ``to simplify and hide the
responsibility of seeking solutions to the problems''
   About 200 soldiers and police, backed by helicopters, on Sunday
were tearing down barricades on the strategic 200-mile-long
highway, where at least 13 barriers had been erected.
   Most of the troops were armed with automatic weapons and some
rode in armored cars. The operation was peaceful, reporters at the
scene said.
   In her statement, Mrs. Chamorro said: ``Faced with the existence
of this dangerous plan and the need to reestablish free
transportation along the Rama highway, the government ... ordered
the forces of public order ... to normalize transit ... with the
total clearing of all of the highway.''
   The protesters want the government to fulfill promises of land
and aid made to the former rebels. They also want members of the
Sandinista opposition removed from key military and police posts.
   The Sandinistas still control security in Nicargua, despite
losing a Feb. 25 election to Mrs. Chamorro, who took office in
April. Rebels laid down their weapons in return for the promises of
assistance.
   But by the government's own figures, barely 3,000 of the 20,000
rebels have received land.
   In her communique, Mrs. Chamorro said Sanchez had tried ``to
manipulate the demands of the demobilized rebels with the intention
of destabilizing the country.'' She did not elaborate on her
allegations.
   On Saturday, a convoy of armored cars, police patrols and
anti-riot vehicles rolled into Santo Tomas, about 75 miles east of
Managua, to dismantle the barricades. They started work on Saturday
afternoon.
   Rosa Jimenez de Farjardo, owner of a boarding house in Santo
Tomas, said the convoy apparently met with no resistence.
   Anti-riot police used tear gas Thursday to dislodge a group of
protesters on a stretch of road between Juigalpa and Santo Tomas.
   Town mayors in eastern and southeastern Nicaragua, backed by
former Contra rebels, launched the protest movement Nov. 1 to
demand that Mrs. Chamorro's administration break all ties with the
leftist Sandinistas.
   They demand the firing of the Sandinista army chief, Gen.
Humberto Ortega. They also have asked for the replacement of the
minister of the presidency, Antoio Lacayo, and Interior Minister
Carlos Hurtado.
   Protesters have also taken over churches and public buildings.
   Eighteen mayors have formed a Committee to Save Democracy to
back the demands. As many as 75 out of Nicaragua's 147 mayors are
said to be supporting them. They have been negotiating over the
demands with the government.
   ``If we don't arrive at a satisfactory agreement, we will meet
with all the mayors of the country to find a more energetic
posture,'' said Armando Incer, a leader of the protest movement.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0081 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 2235EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-FloridaExecution     11-18 0235</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Florida Execution,0267</SECOND>
<HEAD>Killer Scheduled for Electric Chair Monday Morning</HEAD>
<DATELINE>STARKE, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The U.S. Supreme Court refused Sunday to
stop the execution of a man sentenced to die in the electric chair
for killing a businessman for $5,000.
   The execution of Raymond Robert Clark was scheduled for 7:01
a.m. Monday ast Florida State Prison.
   The justices voted 8-1 against two separate emergency requests
on Clark's behalf Sunday evening. The lone dissenter was Justice
Thurgood Marshall, who opposes the death penalty in all
circumstances.
   Defense attorney Billy Nolas said Clark had no other avenues of
appeal left.
   Clark, 49, was convicted of the 1977 shooting death of a
businessman. He and a teen-age accomplice abducted David Drake from
a St. Petersburg bank parking lot, drove him to a secluded area and
shot him twice in the head after Drake wrote them a $5,000 check,
according to trial testimony.
   At the time, Clark was on parole after serving 10 years of a
life sentence for killing a 14-year-old homosexual lover.
   Two weeks after Drake's disappearance, his family received a
call demanding $10,000 ransom to return Drake unharmed, and police
used a wiretap to trace the calls to Clark.
   On Saturday, the 11th U.S. Circuit Court of Appeals in Atlanta
granted Clark a reprieve until 7 a.m. Monday, but rejected his
appeal, sending the case to the U.S. Supreme Court.
   The execution would be the 25th in Florida since the state
resumed executions in 1979, and the 142nd nationwide since the U.S.
Supreme court reinstated the death penalty in 1976.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0082 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 2251EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Gulf-Flight 2ndLd-Writethru a0749 11-18 0504</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Flight, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0749,0637</SECOND>
<HEAD>Americans From Kuwait Arrive in Iraq</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with plane arriving in London, 136 aboard, quote from
American; picks up 10th gra pvs, `President Saddam
^With AM-Gulf Rdp</NOTE>
<DATELINE>BAGHDAD, Iraq (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A U.S.-chartered jetliner carrying 136
passengers, most of them Americans who had been living in Kuwait,
arrived in London early Monday.
   Gatwick airport officials said the flight had 75 passengers from
the United States, 10 New Zealanders, six Australians, two Danes,
eight Germans, 12 Canadians, seven Irish, 12 Britons, two South
Africans, one Polish woman and a French person.
   Many of those fleeing were the wives and children of Kuwaitis,
saying they could no longer stand the horror the emirate had become
since Iraq's invasion Aug. 2.
   ``For four months we have been in hiding,'' said an American
woman who would not give her name. ``People are starving and they
need food, but people who have food are frightened of giving it to
them because they would be accused as collaborators.''
   The woman, on the verge of tears, said her husband was still
hiding in Kuwait and she did not know where he was.
   ``I stayed as long as I could,'' another woman from San
Clemente, Calif., said before the plane left Baghdad. ``Kuwait went
from the top to total destruction.'' The woman also refused to give
her name.
   They had been among up to 2,000 Westerners believed still
trapped in Kuwait.
   A spokesman at London's Gatwick Airport said the Americans would
spend the night in London and travel to the United States later
Monday.
   An earlier report from Baghdad when the plane left said there
133 passengers. The discrepancy was not explained.
   Diplomats said 123 of the passengers aboard the
American-chartered Iraqi Airways Boeing 747 had been in Kuwait and
arrived earlier in the day by plane.
   Also Sunday, about 40 Soviets left Iraq on board a separate
Aeroflot flight.
   President Saddam Hussein refused to allow up to 20,000
Westerners to leave the country right after the invasion of Kuwait,
but later relented and said women and children who wanted to leave
could go.
   Many stayed behind with their husbands, whose travel has been
generally restricted.
   The women leaving Sunday said their fear and the deteriorating
situation in Kuwait drove them to leave.
   ``I was scared, I didn't believe this could happen to Kuwait.
The country was a utopia,'' said the woman from San Clemente.
   A British woman named Julie who refused to give her last name
said she gave up after spending more than 100 days there.
   ``You know, you lose hope. It's a simple as that. You just
think, `What the hell am I staying here for? Why aren't they doing
anything?'''
   The women interviewed said many Westerners were hoping for an
attack, and some Iraqi troops appeared reluctant to face the
Americans.
   Julie said one night during an unexpected blackout Iraqis ran
into her building shouting, ``Hide us, hide us. The Americans are
coming.''
   ``They don't want to be there. They don't have a choice,'' she
added.
   Said the San Clemente woman: ``I hate to say I want war to come
to any country. But there were times I wished the Marines would
come.''
   Antoinette Rogers, a 21-year-old Irish woman married to a
Kuwaiti, said she spent 45 minutes talking to a British friend in
hiding before leaving.
   The friend said he was on the verge of cracking and turning
himself over to the Iraqi authorities because he had already spent
115 days in hiding.
   ``Let us at least walk around,'' she quoted him as saying. ``Let
me walk around half an hour every day. Just let me walk around.
I'll do anything for that.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0083 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 2254EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-GulfRdp 3rdLd-Writethru a0761 11-18 0767</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf Rdp, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0761,0972</SECOND>
<HEAD>Iraq Promises To Free Hostages If `Atmosphere of Peace' Holds</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 5th graf, `The latest ...' to show flight landed in
London, 136 sted 133 aboard; picks up 6th graf pvs, ```I stayed
...</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto DOD1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LAURA KING</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Iraq promised Sunday to release its remaining foreign hostages
over three months starting on Christmas unless something ``mars the
atmosphere of peace.'' President Bush said he hoped for peace but
left open the prospect of war.
   There has been speculation that any military move to drive Iraq
out of Kuwait would take place in the first several months of the
year, and the Iraqi offer to free the hostages during that time
appeared aimed at staving off such a strike.
   In a move meant to underscore U.S. readiness for war, American
troops tried to stage a fullscale practice assault on a stretch of
Saudi beach on Sunday. High winds and heavy seas, however,
prevented hovercraft from making landings. In more limited
maneuvers, troops came ashore by helicopter while U.S. and British
warplanes provided simulated air cover.
   Thousands of foreigners were stranded by Iraq's Aug. 2 invasion
of Kuwait, but hundreds have since been selectively released by the
Baghdad government.
   The latest mass departure was Sunday, when 136 people flew into
London from Iraq early Monday on a U.S.-arranged flight. Officials
at the U.S. Embassy in Baghdad said the passengers included 75
Americans, many of them wives and children of Kuwaiti nationals.
   ``I stayed as long as I could,'' said a woman from San Clemente,
Calif., who would not give her name. ``Kuwait went from the top to
total destruction.''
   The official Iraqi News Agency said the decision to free the
rest of the hostages came at a meeting presided over by Saddam. The
foreign ``guests'' - as it calls the captives - would be allowed to
leave beginning Dec. 25, it said.
   ``The last batch ... would leave the Iraqi territories on March
25 unless something would take place that mars the atmosphere of
peace,'' said the news agency.
   The White House dismissed the move as another ploy by Saddam,
and repeated its demand that all the captives be unconditionally
freed.
   White House press secretary Marlin Fitzwater, in Paris with the
president, called the move a ``cynical attempt... to manipulate
families' hopes and fears.''
   Western governments in the past have denounced efforts by Saddam
to use the captives as leverage in the gulf crisis.
   Bush, in Germany en route to Paris, conferred with Chancellor
Helmut Kohl about the anti-Iraq alliance, which has assembled tens
of thousands of troops in the gulf region.
   Bush called on the German leader to help ``keep the coalition
together.'' Kohl, in a radio interview, underscored the need to do
everything possible to resolve the gulf crisis diplomatically
before resorting to force.
   Although Bush has spoken in strong terms about the possibility
of a military strike, he played down any differences of opinion.
   ``We're not ruling out any options, we're not ruling any options
in,'' he said.
   Bush and Soviet President Mikhail S. Gorbachev were to join
leaders of 20 other nations in Paris signing a conventional forces
treaty that reduces troop and arms levels in Europe. From Paris,
Bush was flying to the Mideast, and planned to spend Thanksgiving
with U.S. soldiers in the gulf region.
   Gorbachev, who met with Pope John Paul II at the Vatican before
leaving for Paris, said he believes there is a peaceful way out of
the gulf crisis.
   ``I am convinced that we will succeed in finding a way out of
this deep crisis,'' Gorbachev said, speaking in Russian that was
translated into Italian. The Vatican said the pontiff, in the
meeting with Gorbachev, expressed hopes that war could be avoided.
   Secretary of State James A. Baker III, meanwhile, conferred with
French Foreign Minister Roland Dumas about a potential U.N.
resolution authorizing force against Iraq.
   Dumas repeated the French position that the U.N. economic
embargo is the best way to force Iraq to relinquish Kuwait. Baker
said such views did not mean the coalition was divided.
   ``Let me suggest to you that I'm not aware of any countries,
going back to the very beginning of this crisis, who have taken the
position under any and all circumstances that the option of force
should be ruled out,'' Baker told reporters.
   The U.S. amphibious landing exercise that was canceled Sunday
was to have been the centerpiece of the six-day Imminent Thunder
maneuvers. But if it had been war instead of practice, the
amphibious landing would have gone ahead despite high winds and
heavy seas, U.S. military officials said.
   One of the landing craft was launched from the USS Gunston Hall,
but it wallowed in seas of up to 10 feet. The exercise was
rescheduled for Monday.
   The maneuvers were held about 25 miles off the Saudi coast, 100
miles south of the Kuwaiti border. Iraq had denounced the exercises
as ``provocative'' after reports they would be held as close as 10
miles from Kuwait.
   In other developments:
   -The U.S. military on Sunday announced the death of the 47th
U.S. soldier in Operation Desert Shield. Officials said the
soldier, whose name was not released pending notification of kin,
was killed late Saturday when a truck he was riding in crashed in
eastern Saudi Arabia.
   -Two brothers and a sister of a U.S. hostage arrived in Jordan
Sunday en route to Baghdad. The State Department had urged
relatives of hostages not to accept an Iraqi invitation to visit,
but William Stevenson of Panama City, Fla., whose brother John is a
captive, told reporters at the Amman airport: ``This is strictly a
family business.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0084 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 1508EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-ServiceSurvey     11-18 0371</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Service Survey,0415</SECOND>
<HEAD>Poll: Despite Business Efforts, Customers are Widely Unhappy with
Service</HEAD>
<NOTE>For release 6:30 p.m. EST, Sunday.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By JONATHAN YENKIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Whether it's handling complaints from irate
shoppers or pampering hotel guests, customer service has become a
top priority for most American executives, according to a poll
released Sunday.
   About half the customers have noticed, according to the poll.
   The poll, commissioned by John Hancock Financial Services and
conducted by Louis Harris and Associates Inc., surveyed both
consumers and senior executives from service-oriented businesses,
such as retailers, utilities and financial services companies.
   The poll found the vast majority of executives placed a premium
on quality customer service, but 50 percent of the consumers said
service is improving.
   That number was the highest it has been in the 19 years the
Harris group has surveyed attitudes on service.
   Forty-five percent of the customers polled, however, still feel
quality is declining. Moreover, 51 percent reported declining
personal attention from service providers, and 60 percent perceived
declining value for the money they spend.
   ``There is a big gap there,'' said Stephen L. Brown, president
of Hancock. ``You have to assume the customer is always right in
this case.''
   The poll also asked the public to rank various service
industries on how well they respond to customer complaints. From
top to bottom they were: retailers;
leisure-entertainment-hospitality; banks; telecommunications;
utilities; health care; other financial institutions; and insurance
companies.
   Brown, whose company specializes in insurance, said he was not
surprised by the low ranking of his industry.
   Insurance is a ``complex product,'' he said. ``It lends itself
to misunderstanding. It's difficult to deliver the service people
expect.''
   Four out of five senior executives said quality service can help
increase their market share and profitability and would encourage
customers to buy other products and services from their companies.
   Also, 95 percent of the executives have made quality service an
``explicit part of their business plan,'' and 91 percent said they
have taken steps to monitor quality service and customer
satisfaction.
   Some executives have been able to drive this message down to
every level of their organizations, but ``I don't think it's been
done at a lot of companies,'' Brown said.
   The survey questioned 500 executives and 1,250 consumers around
the country in July and August. The poll had a margin of error of
plus or minus 3 percent.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0085 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 1719EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-S&amp;LFraud     11-18 0574</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-S&amp;L Fraud,0676</SECOND>
<NOTE>For Release 6:30 p.m. EST; Time Set By Source. Also moving on
general news wires.</NOTE>
<HEAD>House Panel Says Justice Not Giving Priority To S&amp;L Fraud Probes</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVID PACE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Justice Deprtment has not given the
investigation and prosecution of fraud in the multibillion dollar
savings and loan scandal the priority the public demands, a House
panel concluded in a report released Sunday.
   The Government Operations subcommittee on commerce, consumer and
monetary affairs said the department repeatedly has misled Congress
over the past two years about funding needed to catch and jail
savings and loan crooks.
   In addition, the report said, the department has failed to
address issues that have hampered investigation and prosecution of
savings and loan fraud, such as the FBI's lack of document subpoena
authority and inadequate pay for FBI agents and prosecutors.
   ``The Justice Department's rhetoric concerning its priorities
has not matched its willingness to address a number of issues ...
which continue to adversely affect the U.S. government's ability to
apply the criminal justice system to culpable individuals,'' Rep.
Doug Barnard, D-Ga., chairman of the subcommittee, said in a
statement.
   ``I have great difficulty in accepting that a person who commits
substantial fraud against a S&amp;L or bank may completely escape
investigation and prosecution if that person committed the offense
in most areas of the United States that did not receive enough
additional resources,'' he said.
   Doug Tillett, a spokesman for the Justice Department, said he
could not comment on the report until the department has a chance
to review it.
   But he noted that in the past 13 months, 519 individuals have
been charged in major savings and loan fraud cases - those
involving losses of $100,000 or more - and 355 have been convicted.
   Congress authorized $75 million in the 1989 savings and loan
bailout legislation to beef up prosecution of individuals who
looted thrift institutions, but the administration sought and
Congress appropriated only $50 million for fiscal 1990.
   In its fiscal 1991 budget, the administration initially sought
to increase that allocation only by $1.8 million. But after
complaints from Congress, President Bush announced last June he
wanted to double the $50 million in fiscal 1991.
   Congress ultimately appropriated $176 million to the Justice
Department and the Internal Revenue Service for S&amp;L fraud
investigation and prosecution during the fiscal year that began
Oct. 1.
   But even with the extra money, according to Barnard's
subcommittee, the FBI still is $8 million short of what it needs to
hire the agents and support staff its division offices requested in
1989 for S&amp;L fraud enforcement, and $26 million short of what it
needs to deal with a backlog of more than 21,000 inactive S&amp;L
cases.
   ``These past failures to ask for sufficient funds have resulted
in more delays, more stale cases and many cases which may not be
brought because of statute of limitations problems or fading
memories,'' the report said.
   The House subcommittee recommended that federal bank regulatory
agencies make 140 to 180 examiners and attorneys available within
the next four months to help the FBI and federal prosecutors
eliminate the backlog of financial fraud cases.
   The panel also recommended that Congress upgrade the pay of
federal law enforcement agents and prosecutors to reduce the rapid
personnel turnover that is ``seriously delaying and negatively
impacting'' investigation and prosecution of financial fraud,
especially in New York and California.
   In another area, the subcommittee said Congress should grant the
FBI the authority to subpoena documents related to savings and loan
fraud. Currently, federal prosecutors must impanel a grand jury to
issue a subpoena during an ongoing investigation each time the FBI
requires documents.
   While the FBI already has document subpoena authority in drug
cases and has been seeking similar authority in S&amp;L fraud cases
since 1988, the report said opposition from key federal prosecutors
apparently has kept the Justice Department from seeking the
appropriate legislation.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
</Collection>
