<Collection>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0001 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 2343EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-TeenKilled     04-15 0228</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Teen Killed,0239</SECOND>
<HEAD>NJ Suburb Calm Following Wake For Shot Teen</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ENGLEWOOD, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hundreds of people turned out Sunday for
the wake of a black teen-ager whose shooting by a white policeman
sparked a rampage last week in a suburban town.
   ``My son, my son, they shot him in the back,'' 16-year-old
Phillip Pannell's weeping father, Phillip Sr., said as he was led
out of the Community Baptist Church.
   A candlelight vigil the day after Pannell was shot Tuesday in
Teaneck turned violent as scores of black youths rampaged and
looted businesses.
   It had been feared more violence would break out Sunday, but
police said both Teaneck and Englewood were calm.
   Black Muslim leader Louis Farrakhan attended the wake.
   A funeral service for Pannell was set for Monday at the same
church.
   Pannell was shot by Teaneck Police Officer Gary Spath, who was
responding to an anonymous tip that a teen-ager was brandishing a
gun.
   Spath has since been suspended with pay and Wayne Blanco, the
officer who responded with Spath, has been temporarily relieved of
his duties, acting Bergen County Prosecutor John Holl said.
   An autopsy showed that Pannell was shot once in the back. An
investigation showed that Spath's .38-caliber service revolver had
been fired twice, and that Blanco's revolver was not fired.
   A grand jury is to begin considering the case Tuesday.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0002 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 2350EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Lites     04-15 0364</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Lites,0380</SECOND>
<HEAD>On the Light Side</HEAD>
<DATELINE>FAYETTEVILLE, N.C. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Have flower girl, need wedding.
   Six-year-old Elizabeth Gregory wants to be a flower girl so much
that her mother placed a classified ad searching for a wedding in
which her daughter can participate.
   ``Planning a wedding? Darling six year old wants to be your
flower girl. Fayetteville or surrounding area. Parents will supply
dress of choice,'' reads the ad in the Fayetteville Observer-Times.
   ``She's had three friends who have been flower girls and she had
a little boyfriend who was a ringbearer,'' said the child's mother,
Anne.
   ``She'd say, `When is my turn going to be?' _ because they've
learned about turns in school _ and `Mom, do you think I'll ever be
a flower girl?'
   Mom took matters into her own hands by placing the ad.
   ``We don't have any friends or family planning a wedding anytime
soon, so I thought it wouldn't hurt to give it a try,'' she said.
   Elizabeth described the ideal flower-girl outfit: a blue and red
dress with lots of ruffles, a bouquet of different-colored tulips
and a bow for her hair.
   Most of all, Elizabeth said, she would be a good flower girl.
She can walk straight, sprinkle petals, stand still and be quiet.
And she won't get nervous at the last minute and balk at walking
down the aisle, she said.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>DALLAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Barbecued alligator and rattlesnake skewers were
among the delicacies dropped from the menu for a party at the
Dallas Zoo.
   Organizers chickened out.
   ``It got too controversial. It's not very kosher to be grilling
a rattlesnake when you have them in the zoo,'' said Nick Barclay, a
chef for the event whose buffalo and venison ideas also were
rejected.
   What finally was approved for zoo patrons who paid up to $3,000
a couple was a main course of chicken breasts.
   Sistie Stollenwerck, chairman of the April 6 gala to open the
Wilds of Africa habitat, said organizers could not be too wild in
their choices.
   ``The zoo is about preservation and conservation,'' she said.
   To hammer home a safari theme, ushers worked in gorilla costumes
and waiters wore pith helmets.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0003 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 2352EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a BC-LOT--SaturdayLotteries     04-15 0702</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-LOT--Saturday Lotteries,0827</SECOND>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<HEAD>ARIZONA</HEAD>
<HEAD>Pick</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PHOENIX (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers in Saturday night's drawing
of the Arizona Lottery's Pick game were 6, 9, 14, 20, 29 and 35,
with a bonus number of 19.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>CALIFORNIA</HEAD>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers picked Saturday night for the
California Lottery's twice-weekly ``Lotto 6-49'' game: 22, 20, 39,
33, 45, 6 and the bonus number, 36.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>CONNECTICUT</HEAD>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEWINGTON, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning combination picked Saturday
in the Connecticut State Lottery's ``Daily Lottery'' drawing was:
   2-4-7
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Play 4</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEWINGTON, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning combination picked Saturday
in the Connecticut State Lottery's ``Play 4'' drawing was:
   7-1-6-5.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEWINGTON, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers selected Saturday in
the Connecticut State Lottery's ``Lotto'' drawing were:
   14-21-25-40-41-44
</TEXT>
<HEAD>FLORIDA</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected Saturday in
the Florida Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Cash 3</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   2-4-8
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   33-35-5-34-7-24
</TEXT>
<HEAD>IOWA</HEAD>
<HEAD>Iowa Lotto-1st Ld Writethru</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DES MOINES, Iowa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Nobody picked all the winning numbers in
Saturday's ``Iowa Lotto'' drawing. The winning numbers were:
   14-16-18-23-26-39.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto America</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DES MOINES, Iowa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers drawn Saturday night
in ``Lotto America'' are:
   4-22-24-37-50-53
</TEXT>
<HEAD>KANSAS</HEAD>
<HEAD>Kan. Cash Lotto</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOPEKA, Kan. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers in the Kansas Cash Lotto
drawing Saturday night:
   3-4-19-20-29-32
</TEXT>
<HEAD>KENTUCKY</HEAD>
<HEAD>Kentucky Lottery</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOUISVILLE, Ky. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are Saturday's winning numbers
selected by the Kentucky Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Kentucky Cash:
   1-1-1
   </HEAD>
<HEAD>Lotto:
   4-20-23-38-40-42
   </HEAD>
<HEAD>MICHIGAN</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DETROIT (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected Saturday in
the Michigan State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   5-5-2
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily-4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   3-1-9-9
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto 47</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   2, 10, 12, 18, 27, 38)
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   The Zinger number was:
   5-0-2-0-6-7
</TEXT>
<HEAD>MISSOURI</HEAD>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ST. LOUIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers in Missouri's Lotto drawing
Saturday night:
   1-7-11-37-43-47
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 3</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ST. LOUIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers in Saturday's Missouri
Lottery Daily Pick 3 game:
   1-6-7
</TEXT>
<HEAD>NEW JERSEY</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TRENTON, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday night in the New Jersey State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 3</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   6-8-5
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   8-0-5-2
</TEXT>
<HEAD>NEW YORK</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ALBANY, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday night in the New York State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Number</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   8-1-5
</TEXT>
<HEAD>WinFour</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   8-2-9-7
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 10</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ALBANY, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday night in the New York State Lottery's Pick 10 game:
   2, 3, 4, 6, 7, 11, 16, 18, 20, 21, 28, 30, 39, 49, 56, 61, 63,
68, 70, 80.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ALBANY, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday night in the New York State Lottery's Lotto Game:
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   1, 17, 22, 30, 32, 38; the supplemental number is 35.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>NORTHERN NEW ENGLAND</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CONCORD, N.H. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the daily New Hampshire, Vermont and Maine lotteries:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 3</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   1-7-6
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   3-3-1-7
</TEXT>
<HEAD>OHIO</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CLEVELAND (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected Saturday
night in the Ohio Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Super Lotto</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   23-24-36-40-42-44
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Kicker</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   5-2-7-0-0-9
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 3 Numbers</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   6-6-3
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 4 Numbers</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   9-9-5-4
</TEXT>
<HEAD>OREGON</HEAD>
<HEAD>Daily 4</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PORTLAND, Ore. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are Saturday's winning numbers in the
``Oregon Daily 4'' lottery game:
   5-7-2-7
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Megabucks</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PORTLAND, Ore. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are Saturday's winning numbers in the
``Oregon Megabucks'' lottery game:
   15-28-29-32-41-44
</TEXT>
<HEAD>PENNSYLVANIA</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HARRISBURG (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected Saturday
in the Pennsylvania State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Number</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   1-8-0
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Big 4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   6-0-2-2
</TEXT>
<HEAD>VIRGINIA</HEAD>
<HEAD>Pick 3</HEAD>
<DATELINE>RICHMOND (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   These numbers were drawn Saturday in the
Virginia Lottery's Pick-3 game:
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   9-5-2
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<DATELINE>RICHMOND (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   These numbers were drawn Saturday in the
Virginia Lottery's Lotto game:
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   4-9-16-24-25-29
</TEXT>
<HEAD>WASHINGTON, DC</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The following lotteries were drawn Saturday in
the District of Columbia Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lucky Numbers Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   7-0-9
</TEXT>
<HEAD>D.C. Four Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   2-2-4-5
</TEXT>
<HEAD>D.C. Daily Double Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   38-46
</TEXT>
<HEAD>D.C. Quick Cash Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   4-6-22-23-27-33
</TEXT>
<HEAD>WEST VIRGINIA</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CHARLESTON, W.Va. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the West Virginia State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily 3</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   1-5-9
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily 4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   3-1-8-3
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0004 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 2352EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-EmergencyLanding     04-15 0133</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Emergency Landing,0137</SECOND>
<HEAD>USAir Flight Makes Emergency Landing</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PITTSBURGH (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   About 60 passengers and crew members on a
USAir flight were forced to evacuate on emergency chutes Sunday
after a flight attendant smelled smoke in the rear of the cabin, an
airline spokesman said.
   Flight 2370 from Louisville to the Greater Pittsburgh
International Airport, with 54 passengers and six or seven crew
members aboard, landed in Pittsburgh around 3:30 p.m., said USAir
spokesman John Bronson.
   A woman suffered a scraped knee when left the plane on a chute,
Bronson said.
   Maintenance workers later found that the smell came from burnt
oil that leaked from a malfunctioning rotary shaft of an air
conditioning unit, the spokesman said.
   ``It was a relatively minor problem,'' Bronson said. ``They
erred on the side of caution.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0005 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 2355EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-EXP--DNA-Crime     04-15 0919</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-EXP--DNA-Crime,0953</SECOND>
<HEAD>Defense Attorneys Challenging Reliability of DNA Testing</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Monday AMs report.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By JAMES ROWLEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The use of DNA identification to link suspects
to crimes is being successfully challenged by defense attorneys in
a small but growing number of cases.
   At issue are the reliability of the tests and the way they are
conducted.
   ``In the last year, I am aware of at least seven or eight cases
where after the defense got an expert involved, the prosecution has
withdrawn the evidence,'' says lawyer Peter Neufeld, who
successfully challenged DNA test results in a New York City murder
case last summer.
   The judge in the case cited problems with the laboratory
analysis.
   Since it was first introduced in a U.S. criminal court in 1987,
DNA testing has been presented in 200 cases in at least 36 states.
   The FBI opened its own DNA lab in late 1988 to test samples for
state and local police departments. Since then bureau experts have
presented evidence that has helped convict 44 people.
   ``With everything we have seen so far, we are gaining confidence
in the DNA identification's utility in serving the criminal justice
community,'' said John Hicks, head of the FBI's laboratory division.
   The tests compare genetic material extracted from tissue or body
fluids found at crime scenes with DNA from a suspect's blood.
   While law enforcement authorities hail DNA identification,
defense lawyers have won several victories by exposing what courts
found to be flaws in testing procedures.
   Among them:
   _ The Minnesota Supreme Court refused in November to admit DNA
test results in a murder case, saying the laboratory of Cellmark
Diagnostics in Germantown, Md., did not meet standards for
scientific reliability.
   _ In December, prosecutors in Maine were forced to withdraw DNA
evidence in a sexual assault case and drop charges.
   Defense experts testified there were flaws in procedures used by
Lifecodes Corp. of Valhalla, N.Y., to match DNA in the defendant's
blood with that extracted from a semen sample taken at the crime
scene.
   _ On March 8, a judge presiding over an Oregon rape case refused
to admit DNA test results from the FBI lab, ruling there was too
much scientific controversy over the tests' reliability and too
much danger of confusing jurors with technical details.
   Spokesmen at the two commercial DNA laboratories defended their
procedures, as did Hicks.
   Hicks said computer imaging at the FBI lab ensures that a match
is properly read by the tester. In addition, two examiners must
find that the DNA patterns match before positive results are
declared, he said.
   Michael Baird, director of forensic testing at Lifecodes, said
the court decisions have not discredited the technique or the
procedures' track record.
   ``We are talking about whether the approach itself is correct as
opposed to what's being done in a particular case,'' Baird said.
``There have been situations where portions of the evidence were
not ruled admissible, but the technology itself has been
admissible.''
   ``The issue is not so much should it be accepted as evidence but
how and under what circumstances,'' said Janlori Goldman, a staff
attorney for the American Civil Liberties Union's privacy project.
   DNA testing isn't exclusively a weapon for prosecutors.
   Of more than 500 tests completed by the FBI, 36 percent excluded
the suspect in question, Hicks said.
   Public defenders in Washington commissioned DNA tests that
recently exonerated a man whose rape conviction was overturned
because his DNA did not match that taken from a semen stain found
on the woman's clothing.
   Thousands of other tests performed by Cellmark and Lifecodes
have exonerated defendants or encouraged them to plead guilty, said
Mark Storolow, a spokesman for Cellmark.
   ``As a form of evidence it must be very, very powerful because
it results in a lot of plea bargaining,'' he said.
   Rape cases are the most common application of DNA testing in
criminal investigations because hospitals routinely take semen
samples from victims.
   The test can also be useful in solving murders, enabling police
to determine, for example, that blood on a suspect's clothing was
from the victim. It also is used for paternity tests.
   ``When it goes to the identity of the person, that's when it's
particularly relevant,'' said Jay B. Stephens, the U.S. attorney in
Washington.
   To check for a match, scientists use enzymes to ``cut'' DNA
strands into small pieces and place them on laboratory gelatin. The
fragments move along the gelatin and form patterns similar to the
price-code bars on supermarket merchandise.
   Each person, except for identical twins, has a singular genetic
makeup so the pattern should be unique.
   Based on the size of the test sample and data taken from DNA
tests drawn from samplings of the population, scientists calculate
the odds against a pattern being repeated.
   Neufeld and other lawyers argue that laboratories use
less-than-objective criteria for deciding that two DNA patterns
match.
   In the Maine case, expert witnesses questioned the procedures
Lifecodes used to adjust for a phenomenon called ``bandshifting'' _
in which the fragments do not move evenly along the gelatin.
   Thomas Caskey, a medical professor who is starting a DNA lab at
Baylor University in Houston, dismisses those who question the
reliability of tests.
   ``It is extremely easy to determine whether one has a match
between the suspect and the forensic specimen,'' he said.
   But Neufeld argues that like other scientific evidence, DNA
should be subject to rigorous court scrutiny, particularly if it's
used to determine if a person is going to prison.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0006 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 2359EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-KeatingtheWitness     04-15 0819</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Keating the Witness,0844</SECOND>
<HEAD>He Gets His Day in Court, With Much at Stake</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Monday AMs report.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By MIKE FEINSILBER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Judge Stanley Sporkin leans way back in his
swivel chair, pops another chunk of ice from a paper cup into his
mouth, stares at the ceiling.
   He is presiding over a hearing into a dicey, enormously costly
matter, but you couldn't tell it by his demeanor.
   He stretches, he yawns, he slumps, he wears his half-frame
glasses on his forehead. He chews ice.
   At his side, millionaire Charles H. Keating Jr., is the witness,
laying out his claim that clumsy, overzealous regulators foolishly
seized his Lincoln Savings and Loan Association, an act likely to
cost taxpayers $2.5 billion. Left alone, it would have prospered,
Keating says.
   Moreover, according to Keating, the larger S&amp;L crisis is of the
government's own making. He claims regulators took control of S&amp;Ls
that could have survived, ruined the business and needlessly put a
multibillion-dollar load on taxpayers' backs.
   The estimated cost of the bailout has just been raised to $325
billion, including interest payments for 40 years. There goes the
peace dividend, some say.
   Sporkin, a U.S. District Court judge, has to decide whether to
let Keating's claim come to trial.
   Keating, tall, trim, square-shouldered, wearing rimless glasses,
looks like a Sunday school superintendent.
   He is famous for three tactics: filing suits; spending what is
necessary to get what he wants; and hiring his antagonists, often
at big salaries.
   His very name raises goosebumps on political skin. Five senators
are hurting because they accepted $1.3 million in campaign
contributions from Keating, then met with him to hear his
complaints about heavy-handed federal regulators.
   Keating didn't help them when, taking note of the rumors that
his money ``influenced several political figures to take up my
cause,'' he said ``I certainly hope so.''
   Whatever aid he got from the senators, it was not enough to
prevent the takeover of his S&amp;L empire, based in California.
   The regulators declared Keating's highflying tactics made
Lincoln unsafe and unsound and put its depositors at risk, their
money dissipated in junk bond gambles. They said he used a complex
tax scheme to funnel Lincoln's deposits into his Arizona real
estate ventures.
   His testimony is peppered with aggressive words:
``preposterous,'' ``reckless,'' ``vendetta.'' He says the
examination of his books by the Federal Home Loan Bank Board was
``vicious,'' even ``savage.''
   He says he ran a ``non-traditional'' S&amp;L. He says the government
was out to destroy him. He says the U.S. League of Savings
Institutions, resentful of the competition, lobbied against him.
   On the stand Thursday, to prove evil motivation, he cited a memo
from one regulator.
   ``Even our lawyers are finally getting the message,'' it said.
``Under every document is another scam, and they seem to finally
understand what type of thieves we are dealing with and why we need
to get them out.''
   Keating brought out that the author of the memo, Kevin
O'Connell, is the son of the William B. O'Connell, who was
president of the league at the time. Kevin O'Connell, a witness for
the government, was seated at the government table.
   Sporkin acted like a man who could not believe his ears. He
chuckled. He pointed to the younger O'Connell.
   ``It was this gentleman's father who was president of the U.S.
League?'' he asked, unbelievingly.
   O'Connell said nothing. Later, he told reporters the memo was
``self-explanatory.''
   If Sporkin rules in Keating's favor, the entire S&amp;L bailout
could be thrown into question. It would lend credence to Keating's
view that S&amp;L takeovers created a glutted real estate market,
jeopardizing additional S&amp;Ls, which saw the value of their
mortgages fall.
   The government asked Sporkin to quash Keating's suit, a motion
which could be routinely disposed of. Sporkin set aside two days
for a hearing. Then he set aside six more days. Now, the hearing
had run through its 23rd day.
   Between these two, Keating and Sporkin, has developed a rapport,
courtroom spectators say. Sporkin understands finances. An
accountant before he was a lawyer, he was chief of enforcement at
the Securities and Exchange Commission and chief counsel to the CIA
before he became a judge.
   Keating is solicitous to him. Before the House Banking
Committee, Keating exercised his Fifth Amendment rights to remain
silent, but is eager to make his case in Sporkin's court.
   Every so often, up pops James Murphy, the lawyer hired to
represent the Office of Thrift Supervision, successor agency to the
Home Loan Bank Board.
   He argues that Keating keeps veering into areas that have no
relevance. This is a hearing on a motion, not a trial.
   Sporkin waves him off. ``I'm just listening and I believe I have
a responsibility to listen,'' he tells Murphy. ``Plus,'' he says,
grinning, ``it's a lot more interesting than a lot of things I have
to listen to.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0007 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 2354EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-CabKillings 2ndLd-Writethru a0718 04-15 0554</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Cab Killings, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0718,0567</SECOND>
<HEAD>Another NYC Cabbie Shot To Death</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS in 6 grafs to UPDATE with investigators leaning against
linking killing to three previous; picks up 4th graf, `A task ...'
Changes `Montes de Oca' to `Montes De Oca' throughout to conform
with spelling given by police</NOTE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Police on Sunday were investigating whether a
cab driver found shot to death in his taxi was the fourth victim of
a serial killer.
   Rafael Montes De Oca, 38, was found in his car at 11:55 p.m.
Saturday in the Bronx, police said. He was shot in the head at
close range, as were three other private car-service drivers killed
in the Bronx since March 7.
   Police had not ruled out that the killer believed responsible
for the previous three slayings may have struck again, said police
spokesman Hugh Barry.
   But police at the 48th Precinct, which is investigating the
latest killing, were leaning against connecting it to the others.
   ``There are certain consistencies in the other cases which are
not present in this one,'' said Lt. James Malvey, the precinct
commander. ``We became convinced there is no connection.''
   A detective in the precinct said investigators were treating the
latest slaying as a separate incident, ``but they're not ruling (a
connection) out definitely. It's too soon.'' The detective spoke on
condition of anonymity.
   A task force of more than 30 officers formed last week to probe
the homicides was investigating the Montes De Oca killing, Barry
said.
   It was not immediately determined if any money had been stolen
before the killing.
   A fifth cab driver, Dennis Forbes, was shot during a robbery
Wednesday and died the next day. But his death was not believed to
be related to the others. Detectives said Montes De Oca and the
other three slain drivers had all received calls to pick up
passengers, while Forbes picked up a passenger on the street.
   Montes De Oca had worked for Seaman Car Services of Manhattan
for about two years.
   He had gone to a Bronx address to pick up a passenger, said
Leslie Rivera, a Seaman dispatcher. ``We didn't hear from him
since,'' she said. ``We were notified by another driver that he was
shot.''
   She said Montes De Oca had a pregnant wife and four children.
   ``Everybody here is devastated,'' said Raul Morel, another
dispatcher.
   Like other cab companies, Seaman has lost taxi drivers because
of fear instilled by the string of killings. Ten to 15 percent of
its 350 drivers no longer work at night, Rivera said.
   ``Everybody takes extra measures, but what can you do,'' Morel
said. ``The only precaution that we take is when you see the
people. If you see a person that you don't like, you don't take
them.''
   Mayor David Dinkins offered a $10,000 reward on Thursday for
information leading to the killer or killers.
   The Guardian Angels, meanwhile, announced that one member of the
group would begin riding with each driver for two car services on
their overnight runs Sunday night.
   ``We look upon these car services as the lifeline in these
communities,'' said Lisa Sliwa of the Angels, a volunteer group
known for its red berets and controversial crime-fighting tactics.
``Without them, there's no way for people like nurses who work late
to get around.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0008 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 0001EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Church-Leaks     04-15 0608</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Church-Leaks,0628</SECOND>
<HEAD>Underground Fuel Tanks at Bomb-Shelter-Building Sect Spring Leaks</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CORWIN SPRINGS, Mont. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Underground fuel tanks belonging to
a sect that built huge bomb shelters in anticipation of an
apocalypse have begun leaking, jeopardizing a nearby trout fishery,
state officials said Saturday.
   The leaks at the Church Universal Triumphant's 750-person
underground bomb shelter, amounting to as much as 20,000 gallons so
far, pose a major threat to the fishery near the northern border of
Yellowstone National Park, authorities said.
   ``We're putting on a full-court press as an administration,''
said Steve Yeakel, chief of staff for Gov. Stan Stephens.
   Yeakel said the increasingly large spill had become ``very
serious,'' and the state planned to go to court Monday for an
injunction to force the controversial religious group to focus all
its resources on repairing the damage already done and averting
further contamination.
   Small amounts of the fuel have reached Mol Heron Creek but no
major damage has occurred so far, officials said Saturday night.
   The creek is considered a blue-ribbon fishery and one of the
last remaining cutthroat trout spawning areas along the Upper
Yellowstone River.
   The church has been preparing for nuclear Armageddon and its
local population has mushroomed since its spiritual leader,
Elizabeth Clare Prophet, warned members that March and April are
dangerous times. She suggested they come to Montana to prepare for
a possible nuclear war or accident.
   The sect sponsors two housing developments at Emigrant in
southwestern Montana, where Park County officials say as many as 45
private underground fallout shelters exist.
   Initially, church officials disclosed that 4,000 gallons of
diesel fuel leaked last Tuesday from a 20,000-gallon underground
storage tank, and a large-scale cleanup was under way.
   On Friday night, state officials learned of a second leaking
tank, and by early Saturday had been advised that from 10,000 to
12,000 gallons of unleaded gasoline had leaked into the soil.
   By Saturday evening, Park County officials said church officials
had told them about a third leaking tank and of church plans to
launch a major effort to pump out and exhume all buried fuel tanks.
   Doug Rogness of the state's Underground Storage Tank program
said previously that the church had registered 35 underground tanks
at the bomb shelter complex within the last six months. He said
they had a total capacity of 634,500 gallons of diesel fuel,
unleaded and regular gasoline.
   Also buried on the site are a number of 30,000-gallon propane
storage tanks.
   ``It's a helluva mess,'' said Steve Pilcher, chief of the
state's Water Quality Bureau. ``The (bomb shelter) site is a
disaster anyway.''
   He said that latest estimates put the total leakage at between
12,000 and 20,000 gallons of fuel, ``and 15,000 gallons is
unaccounted for and going downhill'' near the creek.
   He said a fuel ``sheen'' began showing up on the creek about
noon Friday but, so far, leakage reaching the creek had been
minimal. The fuel absorbed into the soil, however, ``poses a
significant threat to the fishery. ... We're going to do everything
possible to see that doesn't happen.''
   Yeakel said Park County officials had been told the state would
put all necessary resources at its disposal if necessary.
   He said state officials were mobilizing to go into court early
Monday to seek injunctions ``that the first order of business is
that the tanks will be pumped out and removed and that things are
repaired.''
   The state also was being asked to call upon the federal
Environmental Protection Agency to become involved.
   Church members and workers from an environmental cleanup company
were working frantically in knee-deep mud to recapture some of the
leaked fuel, Pilcher said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0009 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 0013EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Philippines 1stLd-Writethru   04-15 0600</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Philippines, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0526,0617</SECOND>
<HEAD>Leaders Of December Coup Attempt Issue Threat To U.S.</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 8th graf, `In a related...' with 5 grafs to UPDATE with
capture of coup leader. Pickup 9th, `The warning...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT H. REID</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MANILA, Philippines (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Renegade leaders of the December coup
attempt on Saturday threatened to do battle with the United States
if Washington intervenes in Philippine affairs.
   ``If the U.S. government is ready and willing to have another
Vietnam experience, then the (mutineers) together with the Filipino
people are willing to give them a fight that they will never
forget,'' said a statement by the Revolutionary Alliance for the
Masses-Soldiers of the Filipino People.
   U.S. jets helped put down the Dec. 1-9 coup attempt that killed
113 people and was believed led by the Alliance. American officials
have repeatedly voiced support for President Corazon Aquino, who
has survived six armed attempts to topple her 4-year-old
administration.
   ``The U.S. government will be solely responsible for whatever
actions we might consider to take against them,'' said the rebel
statement distributed near a military headquarters. ``For as long
as they leave us Filipinos alone in settling our internal problems,
then they are not our enemy.''
   U.S. Embassy spokeswoman Victoria Middleton refused to comment
on the statement until U.S. authorities received a copy. Last week,
the U.S. State Department warned Americans of a heightened
terrorist threat in the Philippines during the Easter holidays.
   The statement was issued amid rumors of a new plot to oust Mrs.
Aquino. Late Saturday, pro-government troops manned positions near
the headquarters of the Philippine armed forces in suburban Quezon
City and the nearby headquarters of the national police.
   Armored personnel carriers were deployed at gasoline stations
near the sprawling camps, which were attacked by mutineers during
December's failed coup.
   Also Saturday, soldiers arrested a leader of the December coup
near his house in Sorsogon province, 370 miles southeast of Manila,
a military report said.
   The military said Capt. Leovic Dioneda, administrative officer
of the Philippine Constabulary, was charged with commandeering two
passenger buses and reinforcing rebel troops during the coup
attempt.
   Officials said Dioneda jumped from a window when troops arrived
but was captured after a brief chase.
   He is among the more than 2,200 mutineers in military custody.
Eighty-one officers have been charged in the December coup.
   In another development, a separate renegade group on Saturday
threatened to attack suspected British ``mercenaries'' allegedly
training Mrs. Aquino's security forces.
   The warning by the Young Officers Union came in an open letter
for the British Embassy dated Friday. Copies were sent to news
agencies.
   Rebels said British military instructors last Wednesday and
Thursday joined troops from Mrs. Aquino's security forces in
staging mock attacks on the palace, the Manila international
airport and the House of Representatives building.
   The rebel group claimed its forces had identified the alleged
British ``mercenaries.'' It urged the British Embassy to order them
to leave the Philippines, saying otherwise they would face
``drastic action.''
   Assistant Press Secretary Horacio Paredes confirmed that
presidential guards conducted an exercise on those days but refused
to say if British instructors took part. The British Embassy was
closed Saturday for the Easter holidays.
   The Young Officers Union is believed to be an offshoot of the
Reform the Armed Forces Movement, which has recently taken the name
Revolutionary Alliance for the Masses.
   Both groups claim Mrs. Aquino's government is incompetent and
corrupt. Mrs. Aquino says the rebels simply want to grab power from
her elected administration, which came to power after the 1986
popular revolt that ousted President Ferdinand Marcos.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0010 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 0318EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a BC-CabbieKillings     04-15 0381</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Cabbie Killings,0392</SECOND>
<HEAD>Another N.Y. Car Service Driver Killed</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A driver for a private car service was fatally
shot at close range in the Bronx borough of New York late Saturday,
the fifth such killing in five weeks, police said.
   Police were investigating whether the driver was the victim of
the same robber believed responsible for three of the earlier
slayings.
   The driver was found dead in his car at 11:55 p.m. in the
Fordham section of the Bronx, said Sgt. Nick Vreeland, a police
spokesman.
   The victim, Rafael Montes de Oca, 38, of the Bronx, was shot in
the head at close range, Vreeland said. He would not immediately
say how many times the victim had been shot.
   The driver, who worked for Seaman Car Services in Manhattan, had
picked up a passenger who called for a ride, said Leslie Rivera, a
Seaman dispatcher.
   ``We didn't hear from him since,'' she said. ``We were notified
by another driver that he was shot.''
   Rivera described the victim as ``a good family man and a good
fellow worker.'' He had four children, and his wife is pregnant,
she added.
   Car-service drivers were shot to death in the Bronx on March 7,
March 14, and April 9th after receiving calls to pick up a
passenger in the early morning hours.
   Investigators believe the three were the victims of the same
person because the drivers were all shot many times in the face and
neck with a .22 caliber gun. Each had been robbed of between $50
and $150.
   A fourth driver was shot in the head Wednesday and died the next
day. But detectives believe that killing was unrelated to the other
three because the victim had picked up a passenger who flagged him
down on the street and because witnesses saw two people running
from the car.
   Like other cab companies, Seaman has lost taxi drivers to fear
instilled by the string of killings. Ten to fifteen percent of its
350 drivers are no longer working at night, Rivera said.
   Mayor David Dinkins offered a $10,000 reward Thursday for
information leading to the killer or killers of the drivers. Police
Commissioner Lee Brown formed a task force of more than 30 officers
to focus on the homicides.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0011 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 0320EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-HospitalShooting 6thLd-Writethru a0609 04-15 0500</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Hospital Shooting, 6th Ld-Writethru, a0609,0513</SECOND>
<HEAD>Gunman Shoots Four, Killing Two, in Emergency Room Rampage</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 4th graf, `Police believed ...', to CORRECT alleged
gunman's age to 46 sted 42; pick up 5th graf, `The father ...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By DAVID SEDENO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN DIEGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A gunman shot four people, killing two, in a
rampage Saturday night through the emergency room of a hospital
where his father died earlier in the day, officials said.
   Police said they arrested the gunman within an hour after the
shootings at Mission Bay Memorial Hospital.
   ``He walked into the emergency room,'' police spokesman Dave
Cohen said. ``He approached the nurses' station, pulled out a
handgun and started firing.''
   Police believed the marauder was a 46-year-old man whose father
died at the hospital early Saturday morning after suffering an
aneurism, Cohen said.
   The father ``was taken into surgery and the aneurism was
repaired, but he went into cardiac arrest on the table and they
were unable to revive him.'' Cohen said.
   Police identified the gunman as Bradford Warren Powers Jr., 46.
   Police said that an emergency room physician, a nurse, an
emergency medical technician and a patient's relative were among
the victims.
   One victim died at the scene and the second, a woman, died after
being transported in critical condition to Scripps Memorial
Hospital in La Jolla, about 10 miles from San Diego.
   The woman later was identified as the nurse, Debbie Burke. The
names of the other wounded were not immediately available.
   Another victim taken to Scripps, a man, was in serious condition
with an abdominal wound, said Karen McFarlane, a nursing supervisor.
   The other person wounded was being treated inside the hospital
where the 5:15 p.m. shooting spree took place.
   Powers, the alleged gunman, later called police in Oceanside,
about 40 miles north of San Diego, from a pay phone and surrendered.
   ``He dialed 911 and stated he wanted to turn himself in, that he
had been involved in a shooting in San Diego,'' said Oceanside
Police Sgt. Terry Dove. San Diego police, however, said their
investigation was continuing, and no charges had been filed against
Powers late Saturday.
   Natom Ohannes, who was across the street from the hospital at a
used car lot, said he was looking at cars when he heard three to
four gunshots.
   ``All of a sudden there were all these police cars and
helicopters overhead. They closed off this road and haven't been
letting anyone out.'' he said.
   Ohannes said he didn't see anyone leaving the hospital.
   ``There were two to three patients in the emergency room at the
time of the shooting,'' said Steve Hall, executive director of the
hospital. ``We immediately closed down our emergency room
operations. ... The patients here at the hospital are being taken
care of.''
   ``I think it's very calm inside right now,'' Hall said. ``I
think people are just know starting to reflect on what things took
place. Things are in order, except for the emergency room.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0012 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 1125EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--AnimalsFreed     04-15 0151</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Animals Freed,0153</SECOND>
<HEAD>Animal Rights Activists Raid Hospital, Free Animals</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MARSEILLE, France (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Animal rights activists raided a
hospital and took away rabbits and dogs destined for use in
experiments, officials said Sunday.
   A local newspaper said an anonymous telephone caller claimed
responsibility for the raid on behalf of the ``Friends of
Animals,'' a group opposed to animal testing.
   The raid occurred Saturday night as local police had their hands
full with a major soccer game between Olympic Marseille and its
biggest rival, Bordeaux. Large police contingents were at the
stadium to avert possible disturbances.
   About 20 rabbits, 15 dogs and several documents relating to the
hospital's animal experimentation program were taken, hospital
officials said. Police said no arrests had been made by Sunday
afternoon.
   In May 1989, about 15 dogs were freed by animal rights activists
who intercepted a truck delivering the animals to another hospital
in Marseille.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0013 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 1144EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-TaxDeadline Bjt   04-15 0751</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Tax Deadline, Bjt,720</SECOND>
<NOTE>For release at 6:30 p.m. EDT</NOTE>
<HEAD>Monday's the Deadline, But Don't Stop Working Now</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JIM LUTHER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Tax Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   You won't be through with taxes for the year
even if you beat the midnight Monday deadline for filing your
federal return. The average American will have to work through May
5 to satisfy the tax collectors.
   If that prediction by the Tax Foundation proves accurate, it
will be the latest ``Tax Freedom Day'' on record and two days later
than 1989.
   The reason is simple, the nonpartisan research organization said
Sunday in announcing the mythical date: ``Tax increases will
outpace the growth in individuals' income during 1990.''
   Tax Freedom Day is the foundation's estimate of how long it
would take an average person to pay his or her state, federal and
local taxes if all income went for taxes until they were all paid
for the year 1990.
   The calculations assume that all taxes are paid by individuals,
including those collected from corporations.
   Until this year, the latest date was May 4, 1981, before a big
tax reduction took effect. The foundation said subsequent watering
down of several deductions, increases in Social Security taxes and
state and local taxes, and a gradual economic slowing will have
wiped out that reduction.
   For the millions of couples and individuals still struggling
with 1989 returns, the Internal Revenue Service announced that its
toll-free telephone service would remain open late Monday night to
answer technical tax questions.
   The Postal Service said most post offices in cities with at
least 30,000 population planned to station clerks at curbside to
receive returns.
   Neither the IRS nor the Postal Service estimated how many
returns were likely to be filed Monday night. However, the IRS said
it expects to receive about 23 million this week _ or one of every
five that will be filed this year.
   About 6 million couples and individuals unable to file their
returns on time were expected to receive a four-month extension by
filing Form 4868 instead. The extension is automatic _ but only if
Form 4868 is accompanied by a check for estimated taxes owed.
   Another 650,000 or so Americans abroad, including military
personnel, qualified automatically for a two-month extension just
by having their main business, home or duty station outside the
United States and Puerto Rico.
   A number of people have tax years that ended on days other than
Dec. 31, 1989, and thus have other filing deadlines. Still others
will simply miss the filing deadline, do nothing about it and
subject themselves to separate penalties for filing late and paying
late.
   Taxpayers who file their returns with the IRS Service Center in
Andover, Mass. _ residents of New England and most of upstate New
York _ have until midnight Tuesday to file. That is because Monday
is Patriots Day, a legal holiday, in Massachusetts.
   When all the returns are counted later this year, they are
expected to total 111 million, an increase of about 1 million from
1989.
   About four of every five returns are qualifying for refunds,
slightly above last year's figure. Refunds are averaging more than
$850.
   If IRS estimates of how long it takes to prepare a return are
correct, procrastinators should not wait too late Monday before
beginning the task. The agency guesses the average person requires
2 hours and 32 minutes to learn about the law and Form 1040,
another 3 hours 10 minutes to fill it out, and 35 minutes to copy,
assemble and mail it.
   That adds up to 6 hours and 17 minutes _ not counting the 3
hours and 7 minutes of recordkeeping required. And that total does
not include the time required to do a Schedule A for itemized
deductions (1 hour and 47 minutes plus recordkeeping), a Schedule B
for interest and dividends (44 minutes) or any other supplemental
form.
   While the conservative Tax Foundation was highlighting the
overall growth of taxes, the Democratic Study Group was marking the
filing deadline by decrying a shift of tax burden away from the
rich.
   The organization, which includes most liberal Democrats in the
House, released an analysis indicating that since 1980, the total
federal tax burden for the three-fifths of the population with low
to middle incomes rose, the next highest 20 percent realized a net
cut of only about $45 and ``the 1 percent of households with the
very highest incomes ... (had taxes cut) by an average of more than
$12,000.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0014 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 1151EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-RuralAIDS     04-15 0806</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Rural AIDS,0835</SECOND>
<HEAD>AIDS Compounded By Distance, Attitudes In Rural Areas</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ELLIOTT MINOR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WAYCROSS, Ga. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   AIDS can still be a dirty word out in the
country, and sufferers in rural areas often live miles from medical
care and face even greater obstacles just to live out their lives,
health officials and activists say.
   ``There's a big stigma ... about being gay, or being a drug user
or being HIV positive,'' said Dr. Ted Holloway, who heads a
16-county health district in southeast Georgia.
   Holloway meets Monday with the National Commission on AIDS,
which is traveling to rural Georgia to study the effects AIDS
outside the big cities, where AIDS patients and their treatment
programs are most concentrated.
   ``We've had people lose their jobs and get kicked out of their
apartments,'' Holloway said. ``There's a lot of self-blame. People
become totally dependent on their families, living in fear about
how people will react to their disease.''
   Some patients, Holloway said, are afraid to tell their insurance
companies. Instead, they try to pay for expensive tests and drugs
out of their own pockets.
   A spokesman for Rainbow Partners, a year-old support group here,
said a friend spent $10,000 in four years for treatment in
Jacksonville, Fla., until he became so sick he had to tell his
employer and file insurance claims.
   ``His employer turned out to be very supportive,'' said the
spokesman, who would identify himself only as Charles.
   He said rural residents tend to think of AIDS as a big-city
problem. ``They see it on TV and say, `We don't have that here,'''
he said. ``Once they meet someone who had AIDS, it becomes
personalized and changes their attitudes.''
   Support programs also exist in Brunswick, Valdosta and Albany,
where Ramona Price, the state's AIDS program manager for 14
southwest Georgia counties, and two others run a group called HIV
Positive.
   The Albany group provides counseling, educational programs and
housing money. This month, the group will train volunteers for a
``buddy system'' to help people sickened by the disease.
   ``There's a lot of red tape when it comes to acquiring state
funds,'' she said. ``If they're sick and bedridden, it's a drain on
the family.''
   Some of Georgia's big cities have AIDS treatment centers,
including an advanced clinic at Atlanta's Grady Hospital. But rural
patients generally do not have easy access to such care, especially
if they are poor.
   Dr. Paul White, district health director in southwestern
Georgia, which has had 97 reported AIDS cases in three years, said
indigent patients from Albany have to make a monthly, 350-mile
round trip to Grady for drugs and treatment.
   ``We need clinics and we need money for drugs,'' White said.
   Holloway said there are an estimated 60,000 people who are HIV
positive in Georgia and 60 percent, or 36,000, need the drug AZT.
This year, the state has federal funds to treat only 150 patients
with AZT, he said.
   Of 3,488 AIDS cases reported in Georgia since January 1987, the
eight-county, 2,736,600-population Atlanta area had 2,549.
Holloway's district, which includes the city of Savannah, has a
population of 275,000, was second with 237 cases. Proportionately,
the incidence of AIDS is about the same in the two regions.
   ``We don't have large gay communities like the big cities,''
Holloway said. ``It's been hard to mobilize community activities
because we don't have that leadership from the gay community.''
   Acquired immune deficiency syndrome attacks the body's immune
system, leaving sufferers prey to various infections and cancers.
   The AIDS virus, also known as human immunodeficiency virus or
HIV, is spread most often through sexual contact, needles or
syringes shared by drug abusers, infected blood or blood products,
and from pregnant women to their offspring.
   According to a January 1990 study by the state, the increase in
the spread of AIDS in rural Georgia is due mainly to drug use and
heterosexual transmission from male drug users to their female
partners.
   Georgia's problem could be getting worse. Health officials fear
that Georgia's syphilis epidemic _ linked to the practice of
trading sex for crack cocaine _ portends a surge in AIDS cases in
years to come.
   In southeastern Georgia, syphilis jumped from 48 cases in 1984
to 500 last year. ``We've talked to HIV-positive crack addicts who
are having sex with 30 or 40 people a month,'' Holloway said.
``There's just got to be transmission occurring.''
   The AIDS commission will visit Waycross and Albany on Monday to
meet with AIDS patients, their families, doctors and health
officials. On Tuesday they meet with health officials and AIDS
patients at a clinic in Macon.
   The 15-member panel, created by Congress in 1988, submitted its
first report to the White House in December, calling for urgent
action to repair the nation's health care system to make it more
responsive to AIDS.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0015 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 1343EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-BombDetectors     04-15 0992</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bomb Detectors,890</SECOND>
<HEAD>Airlines, Airports, Foreign Governments Balk at Bomb Detectors</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVID BRISCOE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   WASHINGTON _ Resistance from airlines, airports and foreign
governments is hindering federal efforts to install sophisticated
bomb detectors at high-risk airports.
   The machines, which scan luggage with neutrons, are very costly,
bulky and not foolproof, critics say. They can't be used on
passengers, and in the two airports where they're installed they
are inspecting only a fraction of the total luggage load.
   But proponents say the devices should be used until better
anti-terrorist technology comes along. They cite sobering
statistics to make their point: three bombs planted aboard
passenger jets killed 548 people during the past 16 months, and
bombs were found or threats made affecting several other flights.
   James Busey, head of the Federal Aviation Administration, has
ordered U.S. airlines to buy and install at airports scores of the
nearly $1 million thermoneutron analysis (TNA) units or any other
machine that can meet its specifications.
   France, Japan and possibly other countries are developing
competing systems, FAA officials say. And a Massachusetts company
has placed portable units using other technologies at some
embassies and foreign airports, but only for hand-carried items and
passengers.
   Plastic explosives that can be molded into virtually any shape
and elude detection in hand or ordinary X-ray searches have
replaced hijacking as the major threat to world aviation.
   The December 1988 bombing of Pan Am Flight 103, which killed all
259 people aboard and 11 more on the ground at Lockerbie, Scotland,
was caused by plastic explosives concealed in a radio-cassette
recorder.
   An explosion destroyed a French UTA jetliner over the Niger
desert last September, killing 171 people. And another bomb aboard
a Colombia jetliner in November over a Bogota suburb took the lives
of all 107 people aboard.
   A bomb was found and defused aboard a Saudi jumbo jet in
November, and several bomb threats have been made against other
airliners, including a Northwest flight from Paris to Detroit in
December.
   Despite these incidents, the TNA devices are in use at only two
of the 40 world airports the FAA considers most likely to be used
by terrorists. Miami has one, as does New York's John F. Kennedy
airport. But at JFK, fewer than 500 of the estimated 75,000 daily
pieces of luggage are inspected by the TNA machine.
   The TNAs are built by Science Applications International Corp.
of San Diego. The machines, which are radioactive and cannot be
used to scan passengers, put out a neutron cloud that penetrates
and interacts with elements of explosives, enabling the machine to
identify them.
   Hadi Bozorgmanesh, SAIC vice president, said the JFK unit has
had a false alarm rate of 2.5 percent. He said since September,
only about 40 bags have had to be hand-searched
   No bombs have been known to slip through and none have been
found, he said, except in test bags that are sent through regularly
to keep a constant check on the unit's reliability.
   The FAA has purchased six TNA units which it eventually will
turn over to airlines or airports, and is expected soon to issue
deadlines for airlines to buy their own. The third FAA unit is to
be installed in London next month.
   But the agency is having difficulty placing the remaining three.
   Airlines think the government, since it is most often the
target, should pay for all of the detectors. Airports say they
don't have space for the 10-ton TNA units which are about the size
of a small bedroom. Some foreign governments don't trust them.
   Busey said the installed units are meeting expectations. But he
told the Presidential Aviation Security and Terrorism Commission
earlier this month that he will review his directives, partly
because effectiveness of the machines may be compromised by all the
publicity they have generated.
   FAA officials said last week, however, that Busey is not likely
to retreat from the orders requiring airlines to purchase the units.
   ``We cannot wait until the perfect system comes along,'' Busey
has told critics.
   Aviation industry officials say the FAA requirements are
premature.
   ``The FAA has yet to show that the machine will fit into airline
and airport operations,'' said Tim Neale, spokesman for the
industry's Air Transport Association.
   Neale said U.S. airlines fear check-in delays caused by the
machines may steer international business travelers to foreign
carriers.
   Northwest Airlines turned down a unit at Detroit, citing
electrical and space problems. The Detroit News, in an editorial,
said Northwest's rejection was based on ``thin excuses.''
   The San Francisco Airport, which uses dogs to search for bombs,
objected to the TNA machine being assigned to a single airline,
said spokesman Ron Wilson.
   ``One airline could claim it had the safest service. We didn't
think that was fair,'' said Wilson.
   German officials balked over reliability of the devices and now
have an agreement to test the JFK unit in May or June. Negotiations
are under way to place one at Manila, where Northwest suggested the
Detroit-bound unit be diverted.
   The seven-member presidential commission itself is raising
questions about the FAA orders. Formed in response to the Flight
103 bombing, the panel is expected to be critical of some
government anti-terrorism efforts in its report due May 15.
   Commission Chairwoman Ann McLaughlin told Busey she is concerned
that the FAA's sweeping orders requiring the devices might have had
a ``dampening effect'' on the development of improved technologies.
   ``There has got to be a better mousetrap out there,'' she said.
   A non-radioactive, portable EGIS detector developed by
Thermedics of Woburn, Mass., checks passengers and hand-carried
luggage. The scanners, sometimes called ``sniffers,'' are used by
the State Department at foreign embassies and by some foreign
airports.
   Costing about one-seventh as much as the TNA units, the EGIS is
so sensitive it can detect minute amounts of plastic explosives,
said Thermedics President John Wood. But it has not been developed
for checked-in baggage and does not meet FAA specifications.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0016 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 1403EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Soviet-Georgia     04-15 0743</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Georgia,0774</SECOND>
<HEAD>In Soviet Georgia, Communists Besieged, Others Splintered</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Lithuania, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CAREY GOLDBERG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TBILISI, U.S.S.R. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Poor Josef Stalin.
   The once all-powerful dictator, sculpted on the facade of the
Institute of Party History here, has white paint resembling runny
marshmallow dribbling from his walrus moustache down the front of
his coat.
   A few feet away on the same building, martyred revolutionaries
who fought for Soviet rule in the Caucasus region have lost their
faces to vandals' chisels.
   Just down Rustaveli Boulevard, the main drag in Tbilisi, a
statue of Soviet founder Vladimir Lenin is still standing _ but
just barely. Georgian Communist Party chief Givi Gumbaridze and
some comrades blocked a recent attempt by hooligans to drag it off.
   It is reputedly the last Lenin statue left on its feet in this
southwestern republic of 5 million people.
   Since Soviet troops sent in with Politburo approval killed 19
protesters in Tbilisi one year ago, it's been hard to be a
Communist in Georgia.
   Vazha Gurgenidze, ideology secretary of the Georgian Communist
Party, said that for days after last year's April 9 clash, ``I
couldn't look my children in the eyes.''
   Although he helped evacuate the wounded from the square, the
attack can morally be pinned on the Communist Party and ``it will
always be with us,'' he said in his office in the imposing,
golden-marbled Central Committee building.
   Gurgenidze denied that Georgia's Communist Party is under siege,
saying its membership of 400,000 has even risen slightly. But after
the clash and the resulting furor, ``We felt immediately that we
couldn't go on as we had been. We had to go with the people,'' he
said.
   The party supports calls for eventual Georgian independence.
Party officials even laid wreaths at the graves of the victims
before anniversary protests last week.
   But Georgia's many independence activists say the Communist
Party is a thing of the past, and is a passive caretaker until
elections this fall.
   Even the official Soviet news agency Tass commented on a
``certain vacuum of power'' in the Caucasus republic.
   Unlike in the Baltic republics, where well-organized popular
movements have stepped in to replace discredited Communists, the
Georgian political scene is a hodgepodge of splinter parties.
   In the past year, and particularly since the Georgian Supreme
Soviet legalized a multiparty system last month, about 120 parties
have sprouted by Gurgenidze's count.
   The opposition parties are split into two camps. One is a
coalition called the National Forum that advocates mass civil
disobedience. The other envisions a parliamentary struggle for
independence like those in the Baltic republics of Lithuania,
Latvia and Estonia.
   Among the most prominent is the Georgian Popular Front, whose
leader, Nodar Natadze, is trying to persuade radicals that they
should run for the republic's parliament.
   Zviad Gamsakhurdia, a former political prisoner now considered
the dean of Georgia's dissidents, said he believes Georgia will be
the fourth of the 15 Soviet republics to secede. ``As soon as the
Baltic states have independence, Georgia will too,'' he said.
   Lithuania's March 11 declaration of independence ``encourages
us, it gives us force and it gives us hope,'' he added.
   But activists also acknowledge that Georgia faces some special
obstacles.
   The republic includes three autonomous regions _ Abkhazia,
Adzharia and Southern Ossetia _ and disputes over their status have
led to several violent ethnic clashes in the last year. In the
bloodiest, more than 20 people died in fighting between Georgians
and Abkhazians last summer.
   According to the law on secession passed this month, such
autonomous regions have enormous say on whether _ and on what terms
_ a republic can leave the Soviet Union.
   ``It's a horrible law,'' Popular Front leader Natadze fumed in
an interview.
   Also, Georgia, unlike the Baltic republics, does not have
widespread international recognition that it was forcibly annexed,
although it is acknowledged that it joined the Soviet Union in 1921
while occupied by the Red Army.
   But what Georgians do have is a ``Don't-tread-on-me'' attitude.
   A few blocks down Rustaveli Boulevard from the Institute of
Party History, a dozen black-garbed women outside the city's main
art museum are holding a vigil that has lasted more than 150 days.
   Their signs proclaim they are demanding punishment for the
officials that ordered the charge that killed their children, and
for the soldiers who did the killing last April 9.
   Asked if they wouldn't eventually just give up, a local activist
said, ``Never. They're Georgians.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0017 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 1411EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brites     04-15 0663</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brites,0690</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bright and Brief</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BISMARCK, N.D. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two hospital orderlies are hiring
themselves out as dates for high school girls left high and dry on
prom night.
   The two Medcenter One hospital workers are asking $100 a date.
For the price, Yancy or Mike will rent a tuxedo, pick up the girl,
meet her parents, present her with a corsage, take her to dinner
and go to the dance.
   ``We're not looking for a profit,'' said 21-year-old Mike. He
and Yancy spoke to The Bismarck Tribune on condition that their
last names not be used to save a girl's friends from finding out
she is with a rent-a-date.
   ``It seems like all the high school guys want to ask out the
same beautiful girl,'' said Yancy, 19.
   Yancy said he attended four proms during his high school days
and Mike three. They both said they knew how to show a girl a good
time.
   ``We'll treat the girls nice, just like if we asked them out
ourselves,'' Mike said.
   Yancy, a pre-nursing student, says his parents think the idea is
great. Even his girlfriend has endorsed it.
   Diana Sursely, a nurse at Medcenter One, has agreed to field
calls from interested girls responding to a newspaper advertisement.
   About three ``sound like they're interested,'' Sursely said
Saturday. ``We've had a lot of hang-ups.''
   The classified said simply: ```Girls. Girls. Girls. Need a tall
dark handsome prom date?'' It then gave a phone number that
connects to Ms. Sursely's answering machine.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WOODWARD, Okla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A wayward nut from a candy bar may
someday bear fruit for Lorene Arnold.
   The almond tree in her back yard apparently began as a nut in
her grandson's candy bar, she said.
   She recalled that she first noticed a weed growing in a planter
by the front door about five years ago. When she pulled it, she
discovered an almond-like seed attached to the roots.
   ``It kind of shocked me,'' she said. ``I poked my finger down in
the hole and replanted it to see what it would do.''
   She said their grandson, Rocky Arnold, then 9, heard his
grandparents discussing the ``weed'' and confessed.
   The seed came from a candy bar, he said, adding, ``Grandma, I
throwed that in there because I don't like the nuts.''
   ``Leave it to grandkids,'' Mrs. Arnold said.
   ``I wouldn't have thought it would sprout after all the
processing,'' she said.
   Mrs. Arnold let the tree grow in the planter for a while, but
eventually moved it to the back yard, where it has thrived and is
now taller than she is.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>CHEYENNE, Wyo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A deteriorated revolver has been unearthed
by construction crews tearing up the main street through Cheyenne's
historic downtown, raising hopes that a bit of the Wild West has
turned up.
   Experts at the state museum refuse to speculate the exact age of
the corroded pistol until a study is completed. But judging from
the location in which it was found, it could be more than a century
old.
   ``I wouldn't want to imagine for a minute that it was the result
of an old gunfight on Main Street. But all things are possible,''
said Steve Cotherman, manager of the Wyoming State Museum.
   The revolver was uncovered Friday at a level lower than buried
streetcar tracks, which were built in the 1890s. Normally, an
object found on a lower level is older, Cotherman said.
   The gun, whose wooden grip is all but disintegrated and the
trigger barely discernible, appears to be a 38-caliber or larger,
he said.
   It is probably a military revolver because it has a lanyard
ring, which was used by officers to attach a fancy string or chain
for military dress purposes, he said.
   While it might be fun to fantasize about the gun's history,
Cotherman said, ``we never speculate on stuff like that. We try not
to perpetuate old legends and myths. The facts are usually not as
romantic.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0018 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 1417EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-FrailElderly     04-15 0367</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Frail Elderly,380</SECOND>
<NOTE>For release at 6:30 p.m. EDT. Time set by source.</NOTE>
<HEAD>Project Aimed at Reducing Frailty Among Elderly</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The government will sponsor a three-year, $2.9
million research project aimed at reducing or preventing physical
frailty in the elderly, two federal agencies announced Sunday.
   The National Institute on Aging and the National Center for
Nursing Research said sites in eight states will be used for the
``FICSIT'' project _ short for Frailty and Injuries: Cooperative
Studies of Intervention Techniques.
   More than 1,500 volunteers will participate in the program, to
include: exercise, ranging from the Oriental practice of tai chi to
aerobic dance; education, to make older people aware of accident
risks and rehabilitation to improve physical conditioning.
   Millions of older people are frail _ lacking strength, mobility,
balance and endurance _ which can make them susceptible to serious
falls, nursing home admissions and a loss of independence,
according to the NIA.
   ``The new trials highlight the fact that frailty and injuries
are not the inevitable outcome of aging,'' said NIA Director Dr. T.
Franklin Williams. ``Instead they are problems for which we have
now found some very viable solutions.''
   Among people over age 75, more than 32 percent are unable to
climb stairs, 40 percent are unable to walk two blocks, 7 percent
cannot walk across a small room and 22 percent cannot lift 10
pounds, the NIA said. Forty-two percent of nursing home residents
cannot get out of a chair without help.
   Dr. Ada Sue Hinshaw, director of the National Center for Nursing
Research, said the project may help identify frail people who have
treatable or preventable disabilities.
   The eight research teams selected for project are:
   David M. Buchner, University of Washington, Seattle; Maria A.
Fiatarone, Hebrew Rehabilitation Center for Aged, Boston; Mark C.
Hornbrook, Kaiser Foundation Hospitals, Portland, Ore.; Meridean
Maas, University of Iowa, Iowa City; Cynthia Mulrow, Audie L.
Murphy Veterans Hospital, San Antonio, Texas; Mary E. Tinetti, Yale
University School of Medicine, New Haven, Conn.; Steven L. Wolf,
Emory University, Atlanta; and Leslie Wolfson, University of
Connecticut Health Center, Farmington.
   A coordinating center at Washington University in St. Louis will
help the teams analyze data and compare results.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0019 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 1424EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People     04-15 0754</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People,0783</SECOND>
<HEAD>People in the News</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY44</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Grammy-winner Michael Bolton says he learned
about music from his older brother's rhythm and blues records.
   ``I grew up singing along with Smokey (Robinson), Marvin Gaye,
Ray Charles, Otis Redding and Stevie Wonder,'' the raspy-voiced
singer said in the April 23 People. ``I had hair down to my waist
and I sounded like a 50-year-old black guy.''
   Bolton, who had a successful career as a songwriter for stars
like Barbra Streisand and Cher, said his own singing career took
off when he returned to his R&amp;B roots.
   His album ``Soul Provider'' has gone platinum and he won a
Grammy in February for his song, ``How Am I Supposed to Live
Without You.''
   ``What I'm doing is keeping the songs I used to give away,'' he
said.
   Yet he says his excitement has been tempered by the breakup of
his 15-year marriage and being separated from his three daughters,
ages 10, 12 and 14.
   ``It's ironic that at the high point of my life and my career, I
have people calling to congratulate me, and on the other phone,
it's lawyers calling about depositions,'' he said.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>LONG BEACH, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Actor Chuck Norris piloted a 50-foot
speedboat to victory in an offshore powerboat race, while a second
actor-laden boat came in fourth.
   Norris, the martial arts film star, averaged 81.2 mph Saturday
in the 140-mile Super Boat class of the 1990 Offshore Powerboat
Races.
   Fellow tough guy actors Don Johnson and Kurt Russell were aboard
the fourth-place boat, ``Team USA.''
   The race was marred by two unrelated accidents in which boats
overturned. Their occupants were rescued by Long Beach lifeguards
and medical teams from the Offshore Professional Tour, race
officials said.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>Eds: A version moved on sports wires.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Former world middleweight champion Rocky
Graziano remained hospitalized in serious condition Sunday, a week
after he suffered a stroke.
   Andrew Banoff, an administrator at New York Hospital-Cornell
Medical Center, said Sunday that Graziano's condition was unchanged
and that Graziano was ``still serious.'' The hospital would not
give out details on his condition.
   This is the third time in seven months the 67-year-old Graziano
has been hospitalized.
   He was first taken ill last October and treated at Lenox Hill
Hospital for mental and physical exhaustion. In February, he had a
heart attack and spent time in NYU Medical Center.
   In an 11-year pro career, Graziano knocked out 52 of 83
opponents. He is best remembered for three fights with Tony Zale
and became world champion in 1947 when he knocked out Zale, who had
beaten him a year earlier. Zale also beat Graziano in their final
fight, in 1948.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>CHARLOTTE, N.C. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   When Sandra Bullock graduated from East
Carolina University in 1986, she headed for New York to become a
struggling actress.
   When ECU celebrates its homecoming this October, she will return
to the Greenville, N.C., campus as star of the NBC series ``Working
Girl.'' That is, unless her Wall Street sitcom crashes in the
ratings this spring.
   ``Then I'll come back as a struggling actress,'' Ms. Bullock
told The Charlotte Observer in a telephone interview from her Los
Angeles apartment.
   The show _ a spinoff of the Oscar-winning movie starring Melanie
Griffith _ is in a spring tryout to see if it will become a part of
NBC's fall lineup.
   Ms. Bullock, 25, beat out Tatum O'Neal and other better-known
actresses for the part of Tess McGill, a secretary turned junior
executive.
   ``I think my begging had a lot to do with it,'' she said.
   In Los Angeles on a visit, she decided to audition for one of
the show's supporting parts, the role played by Joan Cusack in the
movie. Then the network mentioned her for the lead. A week and a
half of auditioning followed.
   Ms. Bullock likens herself to the role she plays in ``Working
Girl'' _ that of an unpretentious woman suddenly thrust into a
high-pressure, high-glamor world. She was a waitress in New York
when she saw ``Working Girl'' _ the movie.
   ``I was waiting on the kinds of people in the movie _
executives, secretaries,'' she says. ``Now I walk into these big
Hollywood studio offices wearing jeans, a T-shirt and sneakers and
think, `What's wrong with this picture?' But I won't stop wearing
the jeans and T-shirts.''
   ```Tess is in the same situation I am. She wants to get ahead,
but she wants to keep her roots intact.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0020 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 1446EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Soviet-KGB     04-15 0427</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-KGB,0440</SECOND>
<HEAD>Armenians Attack Local KGB Headquarters, One Reported Killed</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Armenians assaulted local KGB headquarters with
stones, torches and flare guns in an attack that the agency's chief
branded ``an onslaught by bandits,'' Tass said Sunday. One attacker
was reported killed.
   Saturday evening's assault on KGB headquarters in the Armenian
capital of Yerevan, spurred on by ``provocative calls to liquidate
the KGB,'' lasted two hours, but the rioters did not manage to
break into the building, the official Soviet news agency said.
   Tass said the crowd had been angered by the KGB's arrest of four
Armenians on charges of stealing weapons from a military unit.
   Soviet KGB head Vladimir A. Kryuchkov denounced the incident as
``unprecedented in a civilized society.''
   A group composed mainly of young men broke off from a Yerevan
ecological protest, went to the KGB building ``and started to pelt
its windows with rocks and lit torches,'' Tass reported. It said
flare guns were also used.
   One young man whose homemade explosive device went off in his
own hands was fatally wounded, it said.
   The news agency did not say how many people were involved in the
attack.
   Alexan Akopyan, spokesman for the Armenian National Movement,
confirmed the account of the attack in a telephone interview from
Yerevan. He said the arrests had been part of ``an all-out campaign
against armed banditry,'' run by the Armenian KGB more to gain
approval from Moscow than to cut the crime rate.
   Since Armenia's strained relations with neighboring Azerbaijan
worsened this winter and armed clashes became common, Armenian
militants have staged dozens of raids on the republic's arms depots
to get weapons for fighting the Azerbaijanis.
   The Armenian KGB issued a public appeal warning of the ``special
danger of the provocative actions of the criminal world.''
   Kryuchkov, in a message to the agency's Armenian branch, praised
the men inside the building who held themselves ready to repel an
attack but did not strike back.
   ``Only thanks to their restraint and capable actions was it
possible to avoid more serious consequences and victims,'' his
message said, according to Tass.
   Riots and attacks against KGB, government and party buildings
have become part of a recurring pattern of anti-Soviet riots in
various republics in the southern Soviet Union. Some of the attacks
have been clearly aimed at taking arms from police and KGB stocks,
and others have been intended to force political change.
   Kryuchkov said criminal charges would be brought against the
rioters and those guilty would ``be punished with the full
strictness of the law.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0021 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 1519EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Sartre     04-15 0550</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Sartre,0562</SECOND>
<HEAD>10th Anniversary Of Sartre's Death Prompts Reassessments</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVID CRARY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   France marked the 10th anniversary of Jean-Paul
Sartre's death Sunday with a mixture of praise and suggestions from
intellectuals that many of his leftist political ideas would be out
of place in today's world.
   In commemorative newspaper and magazine articles this week,
Sartre was saluted as one of France's outstanding philosophers and
writers.
   Yet the praise generally was mixed with comments that Sartre's
leftist sympathies and belief that Marxism could be molded into a
viable ideology has been overtaken by recent political events.
   ``If Sartre came back, he wouldn't find the world had simply
changed; it's an entirely different universe he would discover _
without the Iron Curtain or `people's republics,' with communism in
agony,'' wrote Liberation, the leftist newspaper which Sartre
founded in the early 1970s.
   Liberation's Robert Maggiori wrote that Sartre's political work
has become ``a mirror reflecting an epoch that doesn't exist any
more, in a language that isn't spoken any more. A broken mirror in
which nothing can be recognized.''
   Sartre, who would have been 85 on Sunday, openly supported the
Communist Party through the 1930s. He later denounced Stalin's
brutal purges and the Soviets' crushing of the Hungarian uprising
in 1956. But even in subsequent years, he balked at renouncing
communist theory or left-wing terrorists despite his eloquent
advocacy of individual freedom.
   ``The philosopher of liberty, he blindly justified the worst
despotisms of his century and even affirmed, `I have fought all my
life for a society in which I would not want to live,''' wrote
essayist Pascal Brickner this week in Express magazine.
   ``It is, alas, the worst of Sartre that lives today, the
critical spirit gone astray ... the habit of taking up a cause
without considering it,'' Brickner wrote. ``He wasted a large part
of his talent on the esthetics of violence and revolution.''
   Sartre was born in Paris on June 21, 1905, and was raised by his
mother alone after his father died when he was a year old.
   He taught school, studied philosophy, began his decades-long
romance with the writer Simone de Beauvoir, was drafted into the
army, and was a German prisoner of war in 1940-41 before being
freed.
   Some of his greatest works _ his plays ``The Flies'' and ``No
Exit'' and his first major treatise on existentialism, ``Being and
Nothingness'' _ were written in Paris during the war. Brickner,
among others, questioned whether perhaps Sartre had shirked his
duty to the anti-Nazi Resistance by focusing on his work.
   In 1964, Sartre was awarded the Nobel Prize for literature, but
turned it down, seeking to show his contempt for an honor he
considered bourgeois.
   Four years later, he supported French students during
politically inspired riots and founded a Maoist-oriented
publication called ``The People's Cause.'' In 1974, he went to
Germany to visit members of the Baader-Meinhof terrorist group, and
described their actions as ``necessary to achieve a new
organization of the masses.''
   But in 1975, Sartre was virtually out of public view, sick and
going blind, although he made a dramatic visit to Israel in 1976.
He accepted an honorary degree from Hebrew University and declared
that his support for Palestinian guerrilla attacks did not mean he
opposed Israel.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0022 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 1526EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Easter 1stLd-Writethru   04-15 1016</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Easter, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0633,1046</SECOND>
<HEAD>Pope, In Easter Message, Urges Dialogue Between Moscow and
Lithuania</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos ROM1,5,6,8, MOS3,JRL4</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: INSERTS 1 graf after 2nd pvs, `In other...' to UPDATE with
celebrations in Soviet Union. SUBS 4 grafs after 29th pvs, `The
Jerusalem...'' for final 2 grafs.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By FRANCES D'EMILIO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>VATICAN CITY (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In an Easter Sunday salute to man's yearning
for freedom, Pope John Paul II said he hoped Lithuanians would
achieve their goal of independence through ``respectful and
comprehensive'' dialogue with Moscow.
   In other Easter celebrations, Romanians and East Germans gave
thanks for the freedoms won by their pro-democracy revolutions, and
religious leaders called for peace and tolerance in Lebanon and
Israel.
   In the Soviet Ukraine, where Roman Catholicism was banned 44
years ago, Catholics in Kiev were allowed to legally perform Easter
services for the first time in decades.
   The pontiff spoke as Lithuanians waited to see whether Soviet
President Mikihail S. Gorbachev would carry out his threat to
impose economic sanctions on the republic unless it rescinded
independence-oriented actions by Sunday.
   ``In the name of Jesus dead and risen for all men, we ask for
peace for our children in the dear Lithuania nation, while we hope
that their aspirations find confirmation in a respectful and
comprehensive dialogue,'' the pope said.
   He spoke in Lithuanian after delivering his noontime Easter
message from the central balcony overlooking St. Peter's Square.
   Cheers went up from a crowd of 100,000 faithful and tourists in
the square, where the pope earlier celebrated Easter Mass in front
of St. Peter's Basilica. In his speech the pope declared: ``Man of
our time! Only the risen Christ can fully satisfy your
irrepressible yearning for freedom.''
   He said man's ``true dimensions of the spirit have been
discovered anew'' after two bloody world wars and ``years of
dictatorships which have deprived men and women of their basic
freedoms.''
   His message on Lithuania was the latest attempt by the Vatican
to help ease tensions between Moscow and the tiny Baltic republic,
which declared independence on March 11.
   Tass, the Soviet news agency, reported that a Soviet envoy
received by the pope on Saturday had delivered a message from
Gorbachev about the crisis in Lithuania, where four out of five
people are Catholic.
   The Vatican in March opened diplomatic relations with Moscow.
Earlier this month, the Vatican's newly appointed envoy to the
Soviet Union said the Holy See would be willing to mediate the
Lithuanian dispute.
   In his speech, John Paul gave holiday wishes in 55 languages.
The longest greetings went to Lithuania and his homeland, Poland.
   Quoting from the Gospel of John, the pope told his
economically-depressed homeland: ``You have the tribulations of the
world, but have faith.''
   In Romania, tens of thousands of worshipers sang ancient hymns
in packed churches across the nation in an emotional celebration of
their first free Easter in more than four decades.
   In Timisoara, where Romania's pro-democracy revolution started
and where some of the worst fighting occurred, Archbishop Nicolae
eulogized the martyrs of the revolution in a sermon to 2,000 people.
   ``After 45 years during which (Communists) tried to enslave our
soul and history ... we now celebrate in freedom Holy Easter,'' he
said.
   ``So far, when we said `Christ Has Risen,' we thought that one
day better would come, and now it did come due to those who
sacrificed their lives,'' he said.
   Similar services were held in the two Germanys.
   East and West Germans poured through their border in both
directions and packed churches to give thanks for their new-found
freedoms, while thousands of others took part in traditional peace
protests.
   Border guards waved crowds from West Berlin through the
Brandenburg gate checkpoint, where churchgoers headed for Roman
Catholic services at St. Hedwig's Cathedral and Lutheran services
at St. Mary's Church in East Berlin.
   Before East Germany's pro-democracy revolution last year, its
citizens could only dream of visiting friends and relatives in the
West. Independent church leaders were officially scorned.
   In Lebanon, church bells vied with bursts of gunfire in east
Beirut as thousands of Christians celebrated Easter and wondered
whether full-scale fighting would break out again in the battle for
control of their enclave.
   Police said troops of renegade Gen. Michel Aoun and Lebanese
Forces militiamen of Christian warlord Samir Geagea clashed
intermittently.
   The firing drowned out church bells ringing in neighboring
districts and many people were too frightened to venture out for
Easter Mass.
   In Israel, the Roman Catholic patriarch of Jerusalem used his
Easter message to call for equality between peoples, as tension
continued between Jews and Christian Arabs over a Jewish settlement
in the city's Christian quarter.
   In a sermon before hundreds of pilgrims and tourists at the
Church of the Holy Sepulchre, the traditional site of Christ's
crucifixion and burial, Patriarch Michel Sabbah said:
   ``Individuals and peoples are equal in all rights. A people must
not oppress another people nor must a people be dominated by
another people.''
   A few hundred yards away, paramilitary border police guarded a
building in the Christian section of Jerusalem's Old City occupied
Wednesday by a group of 150 Jewish nationalists. The occupation
sparked rioting by Christian Arabs.
   The Jerusalem District Court has ordered the settlers out of the
building, but they are appealing the decision.
   As Ukrainian Catholics held Easter services in Kiev, a
controversial cathedral in the western Ukrainian city of Lvov that
was given back last week to Ukrainian Catholics was closed for
Easter to avoid conflict.
   An announcement by the Ukrainian popular movement Rukh said St.
George's Cathedral, which had been under Russian Orthodox control,
was closed ``to prevent provocations and ease tension during the
holiday.''
   The Ukrainian Catholic faith was outlawed in 1946 by Soviet
authorities after Josef Stalin seized control of the western
Ukraine at the end of World War II. But recently, under Gorbachev's
reforms, it has been practiced openly.
   Soviet TV devoted more than 15 minutes to Easter coverage in the
Soviet Union, Jerusalem and Bulgaria on Sunday night in what Soviet
viewers said was the longest televised Easter report they could
remember.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0023 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 1555EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-FordTrial     04-15 0527</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Ford Trial,0547</SECOND>
<HEAD>Congressman Ponders Next Move in Bank Fraud Defense</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By WOODY BAIRD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MEMPHIS, Tenn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   U.S. Rep. Harold Ford and his lawyers get
their turn this week at countering allegations that he took more
than $1.2 million in political payoffs from two crooked bankers. He
says his defense likely will be brief.
   ``The government does not have a case,'' the Tennessee Democrat
said Friday.
   Ford is charged with conspiracy, bank and mail fraud.
   Since testimony began March 1, witnesses have described a scheme
in which Ford allegedly got loans from banks controlled by C.H.
Butcher Jr., and his brother, Jake, a two-time Democratic candidate
for governor.
   The Butchers are serving 20-year prison sentences for bank fraud
stemming from a 1983 bank failure, the largest in the state's
history.
   Witnesses said few if any payments were ever made on the loans,
which were rolled over into new loans when the notes came due.
   The government says Ford and his family got more than $1.2
million in exchange for unspecified political favors. Ford says the
loans were for $650,000 and it was repaid.
   Ford said his attorney had prepared to call 41 witnesses, but
now may call only the congressman.
   ``It is narrowed down to whether we should close it out on the
bang of Harold Ford taking the stand or whether that is needed,''
he said.
   Prosecutors on Wednesday surprised defense lawyers by resting
their case without bringing to the stand C.H. Butcher Jr., who has
pleaded guilty to two counts of the 19-count indictment.
   Ford's lawyers are to inform U.S. District Judge Odell Horton on
Monday how they plan to proceed. Ford said his lawyers will ask for
a directed verdict of acquittal from the judge but have little
hopes of getting it.
   The jury is scheduled to return Tuesday.
   Ford is on trial with three former Butcher aides, accountant
David Crabtree and lawyers Karl Schledwitz and Douglas Beaty.
   The four can put on independent defenses, but Ford said lawyers
for his co-defendants are working closely with his attorneys.
   Assistant U.S. Attorney Dan Clancy, the lead prosecutor,
declined to comment on the government's decision not to call
Butcher as a witness. Clancy noted, however, that Butcher still can
be called as a rebuttal witness.
   Ford, the only black member of Tennessee's congressional
delegation, has blamed his legal troubles on racists and on a
personal vendetta directed by Clancy, a Republican appointee.
Clancy has denied that allegation.
   First elected to Congress in 1974, Ford has had little
opposition for re-election and he is credited with running a
political organization that can deliver the black vote in his
hometown Memphis, the state's largest city.
   Government witnesses said Ford started getting loans from the
Butchers in 1976 but made few if any payments on them until after
the brothers' banking empire fell.
   Ford generally got the loans without collateral and with little
or no explanation on how he would repay them, government witnesses
said.
   Jesse Barr, a former top aide to Jake Butcher, testified that
Ford was not expected to repay his loans. Barr is serving an
18-year-prison sentence for misapplying bank funds.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0024 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 1605EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SAfrica-Violence     04-15 0595</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-SAfrica-Violence,0613</SECOND>
<HEAD>20 Blacks Die In Factional Fighting in Natal Province</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GREG MYRE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JOHANNESBURG, South Africa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Twenty blacks were reported
killed as factional fighting raged throughout Natal Province
despite stepped up security measures in the region, police said
Sunday.
   Also, state radio said a mixed-race soldier was killed Sunday
morning when his vehicle was ambushed during a patrol in black
township of Mpumulanga in Natal.
   The 20 deaths listed on the police unrest report represented one
of the highest single-day casualty figures since rival black groups
began battling for supremacy in the southeastern province in 1986.
The unrest report, released each morning, covers incidents from the
previous 24 hours.
   About 4,000 blacks have died in the past four years, including
hundreds in fighting that has escalated sharply since February.
   In the worst single attack, police said 10 men were killed and
two wounded in a factional fight at Ngubela, about 80 miles
southwest of the port city of Durban.
   Five men died when fighting erupted over an apparent land
dispute at Ngilayeni, also in Natal, police said.
   The burned bodies of three women and a man were found at three
different locations in Natal, the unrest report said. Police also
found the body of a man who had been shot in Mpumulanga, one of the
most violent areas during recent years.
   The main combatants in Natal are supporters of the African
National Congress, a black nationalist movement, and Inkatha, a
relatively conservative Zulu organization.
   Neutral observers blame both sides for the fighting. The ANC and
Inkatha both have large numbers of young supporters they cannot
control.
   ANC deputy president Nelson Mandela and Mangosuthu Buthelezi,
head of Inkatha and leader of the Zulu homeland, have both made
repeated pleas for peace that have been ignored.
   President F.W. de Klerk announced plans April 2 to crack down on
the fighting. He says the violence in Natal and elsewhere is
threatening his plans to start negotiations on a new constitution
that will increase the role in government affairs of the country's
28 million black majority.
   The government has sent additional police and soldiers to Natal,
including an army battalion made up of Portuguese-speaking black
Angolans. That battalion was one of South Africa's leading combat
units when the country was involved in wars in Angola and Namibia
in recent years.
   Anti-apartheid groups have long opposed the presence of soldiers
in the black townships.
   But Natal residents and anti-apartheid figures, including
Mandela, generally have supported the recent addition of troops
because the fighting has become so intense. Mandela has said the
army is preferable to the police, which the ANC has accused of
being biased in favor of Inkatha.
   However, Walter Sisulu, an ANC leader, said Sunday the
government should not station the battalion of black Angolans in
Natal.
   ``We are sure that their presence will aggravate the situation
instead of bringing peace,'' said Sisulu, head of the ANC's
internal wing. Most of the ANC leadership remains in exile.
   The South African Defense Force said the battalion was chosen
because its members ``are neutral and do not have affiliations
which could be seen to side with factions involved in the unrest in
Natal.''
   Both the ANC and Inkatha oppose apartheid, but differ over
tactics. The ANC has waged a guerrilla campaign, though it is
largely dormant now. The organization favors sanctions, boycotts,
strikes and other confrontational methods to pressure the white-led
government.
   Inkatha does not endorse any of these measures and Buthelezi is
a proponent of capitalism, in contrast to the socialist-leaning ANC.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0025 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 1610EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ChinatownFreeway Bjt   04-15 0688</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Chinatown Freeway, Bjt,0713</SECOND>
<HEAD>Chinatown Contingent Plans Protest Of Underground Freeway Plan</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto FX1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KATHLEEN MACLAY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN FRANCISCO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Chinatown, normally jammed with tourists,
has been suffering financially since October's earthquake smashed
one of the main highways leading to the maze of crowded streets and
bustling shops.
   So when Mayor Art Agnos suggested the crippled Embarcadero
Freeway be destroyed instead of repaired, with a new road built at
ground level or underground, merchants decided they had had enough.
   Activist Rose Pak of the Chinese Chamber of Commerce is leading
the fight to rebuild the 1.7-mile freeway. At her urging, hundreds
of Chinatown merchants planned to lock their doors Monday and show
up at a Board of Supervisors meeting where the freeway's fate was
expected to be decided.
   Agnos argues the freeway is ugly _ it blocks prime views of San
Francisco Bay _ and too expensive to repair and reopen.
   His supporters on the issue include many groups who oppposed it
even before it opened in 1959. They include preservationists and
urban design activists, who say the freeway sacrifices city streets
and alters the character of neighborhoods.
   The freeway survived a 1986 vote to spend $10 million to tear it
down.
   But opponents of the mayor's plan say rebuilding the damaged
highway would take far less time than building a new underground
stretch, and time is the key to recovery of businesses in the
nation's second-largest Chinatown.
   Pak called the plan to shut down the neighborhood's shops and
cafes for a show of force as the supervisors vote on the Agnos
proposal ``a very basic, grass roots, humble gesture.''
   A longtime ally of Agnos, the outspoken Pak is steamed that the
mayor has rejected the message of 10,000 people who signed
pro-repair petitions.
   ``It's a political statement that we're not a silent minority,''
she said.
   Signs supporting the shutdown are posted in store windows
throughout Chinatown.
   Under Agnos' proposal, $120 million would be spent to replace
the elevated roadway with a sunken one leading into Chinatown,
North Beach, Fisherman's Wharf and the rest of the waterfront. He
acknowledges it could take five or six years to complete.
   It would cost far less, an estimated $32 million, to reinforce
and patch up the freeway. The state Transportation Department has
that amount set aside for the repair and is awaiting the city
decision of whether work can begin.
   One supervisor the protesters have on their side at Monday's
meeting will be Tom Hsieh, who says he's outraged by the mayor's
decision.
   It was explained to the board of supervisors in a two-page
release devoid of details such as where the $120 million would come
from, and what Chinatown is supposed to do while the underground
expressway is built, he said.
   ``Some leaders have no idea of the hardship and the trauma
people in that community are facing,'' Hsieh said. ``They lost not
just business, they lost employment.''
   Residents and businessmen in Chinatown ``just went wild'' when
they heard the mayor's plan, he said. ``They're simply panicked.
They have no confidence in the city government that it can take
care of their daily life.''
   At the Golden Gate Restaurant Association, executive director
Cecilia Metz said no vote of the organization's members has been
taken on the freeway controversy, but the sentiment is clear.
   ``No one can wait five or six years,'' she said.
   Joining opposition to the freeway demolition has been the San
Francisco Chamber of Commerce business panel, which voted last week
to support rebuilding the damaged road.
   Harold Lee, executive director of Asian Inc., a non-profit small
business advocacy group, said Agnos' plan will cost him not just in
Chinatown, but with people who own businesses or work in nearby,
less vocal areas as well.
   ``Of course it will hurt Agnos politically,'' he said. ``People
are not stupid.''
   But Agnos insists he's pursuing the best, long-term interests of
the city rather than short-term needs of any one community.
   ``Nobody wants to sacrifice short-term discomfort for long-term
progress, but that's what a great city has to do, or it will become
stagnant,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0026 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 1632EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--MassGrave     04-15 0105</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Mass Grave,0106</SECOND>
<HEAD>World War II Mass Grave Discovered</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SOFIA, Bulgaria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A mass grave containing the remains of
nearly 40 people who apparently disappeared during World War II has
been discovered in southwestern Bulgaria, the official BTA news
agency reported.
   The grave was found near the village of Dobrinishte, on the site
of a hideout used by the anti-Nazi partisan Ivan Kozarev, BTA said
in a dispatch late Saturday.
   ``Local people say the victims are probably some of the
residents of the former Razlog district who went missing in October
1944,'' BTA said, without elaborating on the possible circumstances
of their deaths.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0027 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 1640EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>d s AM-RUN--BostonMarathon Bjt   04-15 0506</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-RUN--Boston Marathon, Bjt,0518</SECOND>
<BYLINE>By BERT ROSENTHAL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Track Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In training for a marathon, Juma Ikangaa likes to
stay just ahead of his running partners.
   ``Juma's what we call a `two-stepper,' '' said Greg Meyer, who
trained for nearly a month with the Tanzanian at Alamosa, Colo., in
preparation for the Boston Marathon.
   ``When training with Juma, he'll always be two steps ahead of
you. Steve Jones is like that. Joan Benoit (Samuelson) is like
that. If you're running with them, they have to get two steps ahead
of you. It's just a habit, I guess.''
   Not so much a habit for Ikangaa, but a good practice.
   ``Whenever I train, I always think about the race,'' he said.
``I think about the hills, I imagine I am running at Boston and I
know I have to push very hard.
   ``Training in your mind is like running the Boston course.''
   Monday, the imagining will stop for Ikangaa. The race, the
oldest continuous marathon in the world, will be run for the 94th
time.
   And Ikangaa, the second-place finisher in the past two Boston
Marathons, goes in as the favorite against a star-studded field,
including Ibrahim Hussein of Kenya, who beat him by one second _ a
half-step _ in the 1988 race.
   Ikangaa has earned the favorite's role and the coveted No. 1 for
Monday's race by being ranked No. 1 in the world for 1989 after
winning the 1989 New York City Marathon in 2 hours, 8 minutes, 1
second, his career best.
   Hussein, who finished fourth in defense of his Boston title last
year, is coming off a second-place finish at Honolulu in December
and a fifth in the Commonwealth Games. He is seeking his first
victory since Boston two years ago.
   The other top contenders also are foreigners, including Rob de
Castella of Australia, the 1986 Boston winner in a course-record
2:07:51; Steve Jones of Wales, the '87 Boston runner-up and '88 New
York City winner; Gelindo Bordin of Italy, the '88 Olympic gold
medalist; Zeleke Metafaria of Ethiopia, the '89 World Cup champion;
Simon Robert Naali of Tanzania, the '89 Honolulu champion and '90
Commonwealth Games third-place finisher; Salvador Garcia of Mexico,
the '89 New Jersey Waterfront winner, and Geoff Smith of Britain,
the 1984-85 Boston champion.
   The leading Americans are Meyer, from Grand Rapids, Mich., the
'83 Boston winner, and Steve Spence of Hanover, Pa., the nation's
leading road racer last year.
   The women's field also has the 1988 gold medalist, Rosa Mota of
Portugal. Mota will be trying to become the first three-time winner
since women officially began competing in the race in 1972. She won
in 1987 and 1988.
   The other top women include Veronique Marot of Britain, ranked
second in the world; Kim Jones of Spokane, Wash., ranked No. 3;
Laura Fogli of Italy, the Olympic sixth-place finisher, and Zoya
Ivanova of the Soviet Union, the '89 Los Angeles winner.
   There is a record field for the race, with a total of 9,362
entries.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0028 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 1641EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-NorthKorea     04-15 0270</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-North Korea,0277</SECOND>
<HEAD>150,000 People Take Part In Rally Marking Kim Il Sung's Birthday</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   About 150,000 North Koreans rallied in North
Korea's capital Sunday as groups countrywide celebrated the 78th
birthday of President Kim Il Sung, official news reports said.
   At May Day Stadium in Pyongyang, Communist North Korea's
capital, 150,000 people listened to speeches glorifying Kim by Vice
President Li Jong Ok and other officials, the North's Korean
Central News Agency reported.
   Kim and his son and heir apparent, Kim Jong Il, were not listed
among those attending the rally.
   Some recent news reports from Beijing have quoted East European
diplomats there as saying the aging Communist ruler may turn over
some of his official posts to his son soon after his birthday.
   But there was no indication of such a shift in the official
North Korean reports, monitored in Tokyo.
   Kim has led the secretive nation since its formation after the
division of the Korean peninsula at the end of World War II, and he
has created a huge personality cult.
   In a birthday editorial Sunday, the Communist Party newspaper
Rodong Sinmun said that through Kim's guidance, ``our nation which
was weak and backward in the past has been able to grow into a
mighty and independent nation.''
   South Korea's Yonhap news agency reported last week that North
Korea had invited about 100 arts ensembles from 60 countries to
celebrate Kim's birthday, designated a national holiday.
   Yonhap said North Korean citizens on Sunday would get a special
ration of goods ordinarily in limited supply in the country, such
as meat, cookies, wine and fruit.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0029 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 1645EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-US-Lithuania     04-15 0411</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-US-Lithuania,390</SECOND>
<HEAD>Senator Leaders Say U.S.-Soviet Trade Improvements Could Be
Threatened</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Senate leaders in both parties warned Soviet
President Mikhail S. Gorbachev on Sunday that carrying out his
threatened economic blockade against Lithuania could derail opening
trade relations between the United States and Moscow.
   Senate Majority Leader George Mitchell, D-Maine, and Minority
Leader Bob Dole, R-Kan., said retaliation by Moscow to Lithuania's
March 11 declaration of independence would jeopardize a trade
agreement President Bush and Gorbachev hoped to sign at a summit in
June.
   The Bush administration, meanwhile, was taking what Secretary of
State James A. Baker III described as a ``wait and see'' attitude
as the Kremlin-imposed deadline for Lithuania to rescind its
declaration of independence passed Sunday night.
   Mitchell, who on Saturday condemned Gorbachev's ultimatum as
``precisely the wrong approach,'' said Sunday he was waiting for
Bush to do the same. But, in an interview on CBS-TV's ``Face the
Nation,'' he also supported the administration's reluctance to
issue specific counter threats.
   ``We ought not to be announcing in advance what we're going to
do when we don't know for sure that they are going to do,'' he
said. ``He has made a threat. He has not yet carried it out. We
don't know what they're going to do.''
   However, Mitchell said ``a wide range'' of possible reactions
could include canceling the summit, slowing down the trade
negotiations and ``in between those ... a whole lot of things that
can be done.''
   Dole, interviewed on NBC's ``Meet the Press'' from Jerusalem,
questioned the wisdom of canceling the summit if the Soviets carry
out their threat to cut off supplies to Lithuania.
   ``On areas where we mutually benefit, arms control, maybe those
should proceed on target,'' he said. ``It would probably be a
little strained summit if, in fact, this continues. But I look at
the arms control issues as being mutually beneficial to the United
States and to the Soviet Union.''
   Any U.S. retaliation, Dole said, should be limited to measures,
such as a trade accord, that are more to Moscow's benefit than to
the United States.
   Mitchell said he and five other senators just back from the
Soviet Union after meeting with Gorbachev and two Lithuanian
delegations last week planned to meet with Bush in the next few
days to give him their impressions.
   ``I think there is room for movement on both sides ... some
possibility of bridging the gap between them,'' Mitchell said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0030 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 1647EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-OilFire     04-15 0198</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Oil Fire,0205</SECOND>
<HEAD>Worker Killed In Tank Explosion</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TAMPA, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An explosion at a tank field killed an oil
worker Sunday and sparked a fire that scorched gasoline tanks and
sent thick black smoke billowing over the city until it was doused,
authorities said.
   The 11:25 a.m. fire at the Port of Tampa was put out by noon by
fireboats, helicopters, about 50 firefighters and 16 vehicles, said
fire department spokesman Matt Ballaban.
   The fire scorched at least three tanks, each holding several
thousand gallons, in the tank field, Ballaban said.
   The unidentified Citgo Petroleum Corp. worker was killed when a
vapor recovery unit exploded. The unit recovers petroleum product
vapors during loading operations for condensation back into liquid
form, Ballaban said.
   No other injuries were reported. Citgo spokesman Kent Young in
Tulsa, Okla., said the employee's name was being withheld pending
notification of relatives.
   Young said terminal operations had been suspended and an
investigation was begun into the cause of the explosion.
   Citgo's Tampa operation has capacity of 241,000 barrels of oil.
It receives oil products by tanker, barge and pipeline; the
products are stored there and loaded into trucks for shipment,
Young said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0031 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 1700EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Bulgaria-Communists     04-15 0286</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bulgaria-Communists,0292</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bulgarian Communists Would Win Plurality In Free Vote, Poll
Indicates</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SOFIA, Bulgaria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The ruling Communists would win if a free
election were held now, but the main coalition of opposition
parties is gaining support among voters, according to an opinion
poll released Sunday.
   The results of the poll released by the semi-official Sofia
Press Agency contrast with the outcome of multiparty elections that
have transformed other Eastern European countries. The Communists
lost overwhelmingly in elections in East Germany and Hungary this
year and in Poland last year.
   While approving free elections and professing to accept full
democracy, the Communists remain in full control in Bulgaria prior
to the elections, scheduled for June 10.
   The Bulgarian poll, based on a survey of more than 3,100 voters
completed Saturday, showed 40.7 percent of the respondents
supporting the Socialist Party, the new name adopted by the
Communist Party after long-time Communist leader Todor Zhivkov was
ousted last year.
   The opposition Union of Democratic Forces drew support from 29.7
percent of those polled.
   The Sofia Press Agency said 5.6 percent of the respondents were
not likely to vote for any group. It did not account for the
preferences of the missing 24 percent, but indicated about 10
percent of those polled supported the Bulgarian National Agrarian
Union, another opposition group.
   The survey showed no erosion of support for the Socialists over
the last month but a gain of 7 percent over the same period by the
Union of Democratic Forces, the press agency reported without
elaborating.
   No margin of error was given for the poll, conducted by the
National Center for Studying Public Opinion in Bulgaria, and no
details on the questions asked were published.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0032 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 1658EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Iraq-Gifts     04-15 0142</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Iraq-Gifts,0147</SECOND>
<HEAD>Parliament Bans Officials From Receiving Foreign Gifts</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BAGHDAD, Iraq (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The national assembly passed a decree
banning government officials from accepting gifts from foreigners,
a newspaper reported Sunday.
   The 250-member assembly approved the new legislation Saturday,
said Al-Thawra, the official newspaper of the ruling Baath Party.
   The law orders government employees to hand over any gift from a
foreign person or organization to the government within seven days
after receiving it.
   The paper said employees who violate the new law could face
imprisonment and a fine ranging from $1,600 to $22,400.
   The newspaper did not specify the prison sentences for
violators. But a lawyer said the sentence would range from one day
to five years in prison.
   Government employees who receive bribes from foreigners in
return for providing specific services can be sentenced to death
under Iraqi law.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0033 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 1702EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Obit-Robles     04-15 0192</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Robles,0199</SECOND>
<HEAD>Marcos Robles, Former Panamanian President, Dies at 84</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Marcos Aurelio Robles, a former
president of Panama who oversaw the construction of a part of the
Pan-American Highway, died in Miami, family members said Sunday. He
was 84.
   Family members say Robles died Saturday after a long illness,
but they did not specify the cause of death.
   Robles was elected president in 1964. He was succeeded in 1968
by Arnulfo Arias, the last elected president of Panama before a
military coup Oct. 11 that year led by Gen. Omar Torrijos. Robles
fled to Miami after the military overthrow.
   Robles was born Nov. 8, 1905, in the western town of Aguadulce.
A member of the Liberal Party, served as a congressman, minister of
justice, treasury minister and an executive with the National Bank
of Panama.
   From 1928-30 Robles worked at the Panamanian Embassy in France.
   He created the Institute for Human Resources and oversaw the
construction of part of the Pan-American Highway, which connects
Panama to the United States.
   Family members said the body would be brought back to Panama for
burial, according to his wishes.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0034 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 1704EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-India-Kashmir     04-15 0479</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-India-Kashmir,0494</SECOND>
<HEAD>Security Forces Clash With Moslem Militants in Kashmir</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By QAISER MIRZA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SRINAGAR, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Indian security forces clashed repeatedly
Sunday with Moslem militants in the capital of the northern Kashmir
region and made dozens of arrests.
   The clashes come at a time of escalating tension over Kashmir
between predominantly Hindu India and Pakistan, a Moslem nation.
The two countries have accused each other of trying to provoke a
war.
   The leader of a powerful, fundamentalist Hindu party warned
Sunday that Moslem Pakistan would ``cease to exist'' if it began a
war with India.
   L.K. Advani, head of the Bharatiya Janata Party, a key member of
the governing left-right coalition, told a crowd in Bombay that
Pakistani interference in Kashmir should be recognized as
``undeclared war by Pakistan,'' the United News of India news
agency reported.
   Advani urged the central government to send ``a strong signal''
to Islamabad.
   Indian police sources, speaking on condition of anonymity,
reported no casualties in at least five clashes Sunday in the
Kashmiri capital of Srinagar.
   Witnesses, however, reported that security forces shot and
wounded a 12-year-old girl on a small ferry on Lake Dul, outside
Srinagar. The girl was hospitalized in serious condition, they said.
   Witnesses said the boat was apparently violating curfew
regulations by taking on passengers.
   Official police sources said 42 suspected militants were
detained during the clashes, but Indian news services reported as
many as 170 arrests. There was no way to reconcile the conflicting
reports.
   Among those arrested, police said, were seven ``area
commanders'' of the Jammu-Kashmir Liberation Front, one of the
Moslem groups leading the movement to establish a separate nation
in Kashmir.
   Security forces have been enforcing a round-the-clock curfew in
Kashmir since April 7, a day after Moslem militants kidnapped three
people. The government refused the separatists' demand to release
three jailed militants in exchange for the hostages. The
bullet-riddled bodies of the hostages were found early last week.
   The United News of India news agency, quoting official sources,
reported that security forces were close to arresting those
responsible for the kidnapping.
   Since April 7, security forces have detained about 1,000
Kashmiris, mostly young men and boys, in their manhunt for the
kidnappers.
   At least 270 people have died since January when the government
launched a crackdown on Moslem separatists in the Kashmir valley.
The situation has led to a deterioration in India's relations with
neighboring Pakistan.
   The countries have fought two wars over Kashmir since gaining
their independence from Britain in 1947.
   Moslem separatists in Kashmir say they want an independent
country, attached neither to Pakistan nor India, whose population
is 82 percent Hindu.
   India's Jammu-Kashmir state is the only state in India with a
Moslem majority, with Moslems accounting for 64 percent of the
state's 6 million people. Nationwide, Moslems comprise 12 percent
of India's 880 million people.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0035 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 1711EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Peru-Violence     04-15 0171</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Peru-Violence,0176</SECOND>
<HEAD>Guerrillas Kill Seven Policemen and Four Civilians in Two Attacks</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LIMA, Peru (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A police truck hit a land mine on an isolated
road Sunday, killing seven officers, officials said. The officials
blamed the attack on the leftist Shining Path gurrillas.
   The blast occured near the town of Chosica, 40 miles east of
Lima, while the officers were being transported to the Andean
mountain hamlet of Yanacoto. They were to replace fellow officers
guarding electrical towers in the mountains.
   The utility towers are a prime target of the Maoist-inspired
guerrillas in their decade-old insurgency.
   Officials also the gurrillas killed four civilians in the Andean
city of Ayacucho, 200 miles southeast of Lima.
   The dead included a 63-year-old woman, her son, a barber and a
student, who were killed between Friday night and Saturday morning
when they were sleeping, police said.
   The government says more than 18,000 people have died since the
Shining Path began its fight in 1980 in the southern Andean
highlands against Peru's elected government.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0036 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 1719EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Israel-Unrest     04-15 0397</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel-Unrest,0420</SECOND>
<HEAD>Curfew Imposed on Gaza Strip, Government Approves Jewish
Settlement</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The army announced Sunday it was imposing a
curfew on the occupied Gaza Strip to prevent demonstrations marking
the second anniversary of the assassination of the PLO's military
chief, allegedly by Israeli commandos.
   The curfew is scheduled to begin Monday morning and will confine
the area's 800,000 residents to their homes, an army spokesman said.
   Also Sunday, the Defense Ministry gave final approval to a group
of Jewish settlers to establish a long-planned settlement in the
Gaza Strip, Israel television reported.
   The settlement, named Dugit, is one of eight Jewish settlements
approved by the government when it took office in November 1988.
   Three of those settlements have already been established.
   Yossi Ahimeir, a spokesman for caretaker Prime Minister Yitzhak
Shamir, said settlers are expected to soon move into Dugit.
   Since capturing the West Bank and Gaza in the 1967 Middle East
War, Israel has built 143 settlements in the occupied territories.
The area is home to 1.7 million Palestinians and some 75,000 Jews.
   The Palestinian uprising's clandestine leadership has called for
clashes Monday to commemorate the second anniversary of the PLO
leader's death.
   ``The underground unified leadership calls on its masses and
strike forces to hold memorial marches and raise Palestinian and
black flags to commemorate the death of Abu Jihad,'' a leaflet
distributed last week said.
   Abu Jihad, Arabic for ``Father of the Holy War,'' was the nom de
guerre of Khalil Wazir, the PLO's chief of military operations.
   Wazir was killed two years ago by a squad of commandos who burst
into his home outside Tuni, Tunisia. It is widely suspected that
the killing was carried out by Israelis. The Israeli military has
never denied the claim.
   The news of his death sparked off massive riots throughout the
occupied territories and especially in Gaza, where some of Wazir's
relatives live.
   At least 673 Palestinians have been killed by Israelis since the
start of the 28-month-old uprising against Israeli occupation.
Forty-three Israelis have also died in the violence.
   Palestinians have killed 207 fellow Arabs during the revolt,
most on suspicion as collaborators.
   Six Palestinians were wounded Sunday in clashes with soldiers
throughout the occupied territories, Arab hospital officials said.
   An army spokesman, who spoke on condition of anonymity, said the
military had no reports of wounded and was investigating the claims.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0037 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 1726EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Obit-Matsunaga 1stLd-Writethru a0632 04-15 0975</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Matsunaga, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0632,900</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hawaii's Sen. Spark Matsunaga Dead of Cancer at Age 73</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: Inserts grafs 10-15, ``Sen. Daniel Inouye xxx to update with
comment; edits next-to-lat graf to delete first reference to
Inouye; subs 4th graf, ``The spokesman xxx to fix style of cemetery</NOTE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Sen. Spark M. Matsunaga of Hawaii, a longtime
advocate for peace and champion of Japanese-Americans seeking
compensation for their internment during World War II, died early
Sunday in Toronto. He was 73.
   The late Democrat's spokesman, Ed Greaney, said in Washington
that Matsunaga died about 2 a.m. He was in Toronto for cancer
treatment.
   Greaney said the senator's body would be flown to Washington on
a military aircraft Sunday and to Hawaii early this week.
   The spokesman said Hawaii Gov. John Waihee asked that the body
lie in state Wednesday in the state Capitol. Burial would be
Thursday or Friday at National Memorial Cemetery of the Pacific at
Punchbowl.
   Matsunaga, who announced in January that he was suffering from
prostate cancer that had spread to the bone, died at Toronto
General Hospital, according to nursing coordinator Olga Muir. The
senator traveled to Canada last week for treatment at an oncology
clinic, according to Greaney.
   The senator's wife, Helene, daughter, Merle, and son, Keene,
were with him when he died, Greaney said.
   The senator has been plagued by medical ailments, including a
heart attack in 1984, a stomach ulcer in 1987, a serious bout with
the flu and back problems in 1988.
   Waihee, a Democrat, has authority to name a successor to serve
until a special election could be held in November. Matsunaga's
term runs through 1994.
   Rep. Daniel K. Akaka, a Hawaii Democrat elected to the House in
1976, is considered the leading choice to succeed Matsunaga.
   Sen. Daniel Inouye, D-Hawaii, said it is not impossible to fill
another's shoes in a particular job, ``but I don't think it's
possible to find someone with Sparky's touch.''
   He said Akaka ``would seem to be the logical choice'' to succeed
Matsunaga.
   Akaka refused to discuss the possibility of his appointment,
saying, ``At this time my deep concern is for his family, and also
in participating to create a most adequate and proper tribute for
this great American.
   ``Sparky's death is an enormous loss for the United States and
people of Hawaii. He was a great American, a peacemaker. He was
distinguished militarily, politically, socially and globally. I'll
remember Sparky as having a human, local Hawaiian touch when it
came to politics.''
   Carolyn Tanaka, press secretary to Waihee, said it would be
several days before the governor began to deal with the issue of a
successor.
   ``When I learned of Spark's passing,'' said Inouye, ``I recalled
a conversation I had with him about three years ago. I asked how he
would like to be remembered, and he said, `I'd like to be
remembered as a friend ... a friend of the war veterans ... as a
friend of the forgotten, those who have no friends ... as one who
supports those who are peacemakers ... as your friend.' I said,
`I'm certain you'll be remembered as a friend of Hawaii.'''
   Matsunaga was known more for his easygoing manner and his warm
treatment of constituents than his impact on legislation. But when
he cared deeply about an issue, he combined skill and perseverance
to win passage.
   In 1988 he engineered passage of a $1.25 billion law that pays
$20,000 to each surviving Japanese-American interned in a U.S.
prison camp during World War II.
   Matsunaga, a Japanese-American who was highly decorated in World
War II, had to overcome opposition to the internment law from some
veterans and from those who objected to its cost. During debate,
the senator was forced to halt his comments in mid-sentence while
telling of an elderly internee killed by a guard as he went to pick
up a softball.
   ``I myself become overly emotional when I think about it even to
this day,'' he said after regaining his composure.
   Matsunaga lobbied for 22 years before persuading Congress in
1984 to establish a U.S. Peace Institute. ``Peacemaking is as much
an art to be learned as war'' was his persistent argument.
   Matsunaga supported a joint U.S.-Soviet exploration of Mars,
sponsored a plan for an International Space Year in 1992 and worked
to make his state a center for space exploration.
   Waihee said Sunday, ``He will be remembered most for his vision
of peace and his faith in the human heart. In his memory we will
carry on his quest. In his spirit we will strive for the highest of
principles and the brightest of worlds.
   ``Senator Matsunaga has been a steady and guiding force
throughout Hawaii's modern history. Sparky warmed our state and
country with his humanitarianism.''
   Matsunaga was first elected to the House in 1962 and the Senate
in 1976.
   When he died, he was the second-ranking Democrat on the Finance
Committee and chairman of its subcommittee on taxation and debt
management.
   Before going to Washington, Matsunaga was a member of Hawaii's
territorial House from 1954 to 1959.
   He was born Oct. 8, 1916, on Kauai Island, the son of immigrants
from Japan.
   After graduating from the University of Hawaii with honors in
1941, Matsunaga joined the 100th Infantry Battalion, which later
became part of the famed 442nd Regimental Combat Team. The ``Go for
Broke'' 442nd would become the most decorated regiment in U.S.
history.
   Matsunaga was wounded twice during World War II. He was awarded
numerous medals, including the Bronze Star and Purple Heart with
cluster.
   Matsunaga was a member of the ``Class of '54'' _ Hawaii
Democrats who came to power before statehood and established a
political dynasty that continues to this day. Inouye was another
member of the class.
   Matsunaga is survived by a wife, Helene Hatsumi Tokunaga, and
five children.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0038 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 1727EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-FerryFire     04-15 0304</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Ferry Fire,0312</SECOND>
<HEAD>Judge Responds to Critics of Ferry Disaster Inquiry</HEAD>
<DATELINE>COPENHAGEN, Denmark (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The judge conducting the inquiry into
the Scandinavian Star ferry fire rejected charges Sunday that the
proceedings were being improperly conducted.
   Authorities said 160 people died in the blaze, which police are
investigating as a case of arson. The 20-year-old ferry caught fire
April 7 in Swedish waters on an overnight trip from Norway to
Denmark.
   Maritime unions in Norway and Sweden have criticized the
hearings, now in their fifth day. They complained attorneys for the
shipowners were dominating the questioning of witnesses and the
captain has been allowed to attend all sessions after testifying as
the first witness.
   The Norwegian captain, Hugo Larsen, admitted he abandoned the
burning ship while some passengers remained alive on board.
   ``We are on the borderland of parody when representatives of the
ferry owners are the ones asking questions during the inquiry,''
Norwegian sailors' union leader, Gudmund Aasheim, told the
Norwegian news agency NTB.
   But Marine and Trade Court President Frank Poulsen, the judge
heading the hearing, said, ``The proceedings are continuing in a
correct and harmonious way.''
   Poulsen said the inquiry came at the request of the Danish
shipowner, VR Da-No Lines, and that the presence of its
representatives was required by law.
   The judge said the purpose of the inquiry was to find the facts
in the case. Witnesses are under oath and have been warned that
their testimony could be used in any subsequent criminal case.
   Representatives of the ferry's insurers, Scandinavian marine
authorities and Norwegian and Danish police are also taking part in
the inquiry. About half of the expected 30 witnesses have testified.
   A commission of Danish, Norwegian and Swedish maritime officials
also is scheduled to hold hearings on the case following the
Copenhagen marine court inquiry.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0039 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 1744EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ChristianScienceTrial 1stLd-Writethru a0664 04-15 0795</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Christian Science Trial, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0664,0814</SECOND>
<HEAD>Christian Science Trial Raises Troubling Issues</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS grafs 3, 19,21,22 to CORRECT Klieman's sex to female,
sted male.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By STEPHANIE SCHOROW</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Christian Science Church says its right to
exist goes on trial this week with two church members charged with
manslaughter for relying on prayer alone to heal their 2{-year-old
son.
   The prosecution will argue that the David and Ginger Twitchell's
son, Robyn, might be alive today had his parents sought medical
attention for his bowel obstruction.
   The Twitchells' attorney, Rikki Klieman, said she will argue
that her clients, far from acting recklessly, sought the only real
cure that was dictated by their most deeply held beliefs.
   The U.S. Supreme Court typically has refused to hear such cases,
and there has been little consensus in similar cases heard in state
courts around the country:
   _ A Los Angeles judge in February acquitted Eliot and Lise
Glaser, a Christian Scientist couple, of involuntary manslaughter
in the meningitis death of their toddler son on grounds of
insufficient evidence.
   _ In August 1989, a Santa Rosa, Calif., jury acquitted Christian
Scientists Mark Rippberger and Susan Middleton of like charges in
the meningitis death of their 15-month-old daughter, but convicted
them of child endangerment.
   _ In Sarasota, Fla., a Christian Scientist husband and wife
received probation for their April 1989 conviction for third-degree
murder for letting their diabetic 7-year-old daughter die without
receiving medical attention.
   On Tuesday, almost exactly four years after Robyn Twitchell's
death, his parents go on trial in Suffolk District Court under the
scrutiny of the Mother Church, world headquarters here of the
Christian Science Church.
   A week before the trial was to begin, the church took out
full-page ads in several Massachusetts newspapers to discuss the
case and explain church doctrine. ``Why,'' the ads ask, ``is prayer
being prosecuted in Boston?''
   John Kiernan, a special assistant district attorney, denies the
case is an attack on Christian Science or a repudiation of
spiritual healing. He said it has nothing to do with freedom of
religion.
   ``The whole idea is to bring to the front: `What is the required
conduct of parents?''' he said. ``We are advocates of children. We
are not persecutors of religious beliefs.''
   When Robyn apparently came down with the flu, the Twitchells
followed church teaching and called a Christian Scientist
practitioner and Christian Scientist nurse to treat him, said
church spokesman Nathan Talbot.
   After four days in which the illness ``ebbed and flowed,''
Klieman said, the boy appeared to get better. A day before he died,
she said, he went outside to play.
   Kiernan argued that an adult may choose to forgo conventional
medical treatment, but a child is not in a position to make such a
decision.
   ``The medical profession is quite clear this condition is
relatively easy to diagnose and the prescribed treatment has a
very, very high success rate,'' he said.
   By relying exclusively on Christian Science healing, the
Twitchells acted with reckless disregard for the health of their
son, he said. The state, he contends, has a duty to protect
children.
   ``(Religious) practice is subject to regulation by the state.
Belief is not. ... There's a whale of a difference, particularly
when dealing with a baby,'' he said.
   The church, founded in 1879 by Mary Baker Eddy, believes that
physical disease, like sin, can be healed by spiritual means alone.
There are about 2,600 Christian Science churches in 68 countries
and the church owns weekly and monthly publications and a
television news show.
   Klieman contends prejudice against the Christian Science church
lies at the heart of the case. ``This district attorney wants to
put the Christian Scientists out of business,'' she said.
   ``Oh, good lord, no,'' Kiernan responded, reiterating that the
heart of the issue was parental conduct.
   Klieman said her clients ``chose a system of health care ...
which they believed was excellent,'' adding that Christian Science
practitioners' care is covered by Blue Cross and Medicare and is
tax deductible.
   She also has argued that a 1971 amendment to state child abuse
and neglect law recognizes spiritual healing as an alternative to
modern medicine, but gives Christian Scientists no guidance on when
a physician must be called.
   Harvard divinity professor Harvey Cox said the case demonstrates
the difficulty in setting the limits of religious freedom.
``There's a feeling within the religious community that the degree
of state involvement and supervision has gone too far,'' Cox said.
   Yet accommodations have been worked out, he said, pointing to
the Amish community, which repudiates modern practices, but
coexists with a modern state.
   Perhaps the middle ground in the Twitchell case will be carved
out by a legal recognition of alternative forms of healing, he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0040 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 1744EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SouthAfrica     04-15 0373</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-South Africa,0382</SECOND>
<HEAD>President To Announce Plans For Scrapping Apartheid Laws</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JOHANNESBURG, South Africa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A leading newspaper reported
Sunday that President F.W. de Klerk plans to make a ``statement of
intent'' this week to eliminate remaining apartheid laws.
   The Sunday Star of Johannesburg, citing ``political insiders,''
said de Klerk was expected to outline his plans in a speech to
Parliament.
   De Klerk has initiated a series of reforms of South Africa's
system of racial segregation since assuming power in August. He
says he wants to dismantle apartheid and negotiate a new
constitution that will include the country's 28 million blacks.
   He opposes a one-man, one-vote system, however, saying it will
replace white domination with black domination. He also has not
spelled out his position on several major apartheid laws.
   They include the Group Areas Act, which segregates neighborhoods
by race; the Population Registration Act, which classifies all
South Africans by race; and the Land Acts, which allocate 13
percent of the land for blacks, who make up 75 percent of the
population.
   The Sunday Star quoted sources as saying that de Klerk is likely
to make a ``statement of intent'' this week to do away with these
measures, but is not expected to scrap them unilaterally. He
apparently would prefer to negotiate the final details with
opposition groups, the newspaper reported.
   The newspaper quoted an unidentified member of Parliament as
saying: ``We are now telling our people _ and they accept it _ that
the next government will be mainly black.''
   The Star said the speech has been timed to increase the momentum
of political reform heading into groundbreaking talks with the
African National Congress guerrilla movement scheduled for May 2-4.
The discussions are designed to clear the way for formal
negotiations on a new constitution.
   Constitutional negotiations would include several opposition
groups in addition to the ANC, the government has said.
   De Klerk legalized the ANC and more than 60 other anti-apartheid
groups in February as part of his effort to launch black-white
power-sharing talks.
   The same month, he freed black nationalist leader Nelson Mandela
from prison. Mandela, deputy president of the ANC, had been
imprisoned 27 years. He was convicted of sabotage and plotting to
overthrow the government.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0041 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 1759EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Britain-Iraq     04-15 0470</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Britain-Iraq,0487</SECOND>
<HEAD>Manufacturer Says Pipes Cannot Be Joined To Make Gun For Iraq</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Eight huge steel tubes seized while en route to
Iraq could not be joined together to form a giant gun or make up
part of a space satellite launch system, their manufacturer said
Sunday.
   A spokesman for Sheffield Forgemasters reiterated the company
had contracted only to supply Iraq with forged steel tubing for a
petrochemical plant.
   British government sources were quoted late Saturday as saying
the pipes match the specifications for a satellite launch system
designed by Dr. Gerald Bull, an American ballistics expert killed
in Brussels, Belgium last month.
   Press Association, the domestic British news agency, quoted the
unnamed sources as saying they had correspondence linking British
industry with Space Research Projects, the Brussels firm which Bull
owned.
   Press Association did not name the government department of the
sources, but The Sunday Telegraph, The Sunday Times, and the
Observer all carried articles quoting Customs sources on the same
subject.
   The pipes were seized last week by British customs officials who
suspected they were parts for a massive gun barrel.
   ``Nobody seems to have taken on board the fact that those eight
pieces do not join up to form one piece,'' said Forgemasters
spokesman Tony Peck.
   ``They are random selections of tubes from a consignment of 26
which, added together, measure 156 meters (170 yards). They cannot
join them together.''
   Sheffield Forgemasters says it agreed to supply 52 sections of
the steel tubing and had delivered 44 to the Ministry of Industry
and Minerals in the Iraqi capital of Baghdad.
   Iraq has also claimed the metal tubes were pipes for a
petrochemical plant. Arms experts have given conflicting opinions
about whether the steel sections could be used as a weapon.
   Peck said the company had permission from the Department of
Trade and Industry to manufacture the tubing and sell it to Iraq.
The department refused to comment Sunday.
   Britain banned all arms sales to Iraq and Iran after the
outbreak of their eight-year Persian Gulf War. Despite the 1988
cease-fire, the embargo remains in effect.
   Bull, 62, a Canadian-born American citizen, was slain March 22.
Belgian police said he was shot twice in the head by an assailant
using a silencer. They said the motive was not robbery because
$20,000 was found in the victim's pockets.
   Bull's company was engaged in space and military research and
international arms sales.
   Western fears about Iraqi arms programs have grown in recent
weeks. On March 28, British customs officials seized U.S.-made
parts for atomic bomb triggers that were bound for Iraq.
   Iraq has confirmed it has chemical weapons, but has denied
seeking a nuclear capability.
   Iraqi President Saddam Hussein recently threatened to use
missiles armed with chemical warheads against Israel if Israeli
forces attacked his country.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0042 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 1804EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Liberia-Rebels     04-15 0263</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Liberia-Rebels,0272</SECOND>
<HEAD>Government Denies Guerrillas Hold Territory</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MONROVIA, Liberia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The government on Sunday denied reports
that rebels controlled any part of the West African nation.
   ``No inch of this nation is under the control of the rebels,''
said Information Minister Emmanuel Bowier. Bowier said journalists
who claim to have visited rebel bases in Liberia were actually in
Guinea or Ivory Coast.
   Recent visitors to the Nimba Country area, which was invaded
from the Ivory Coast by rebels led by Charles Taylor on Dec. 24,
have said the guerrillas are largely in control of the region.
Taylor's forces are seeking to overthrow President Samuel Doe.
   Bowier, in a news briefing Sunday, said government troops had
brought the situation in Nimba under control.
   On Saturday, Brig. Gen. Charles Julu said Taylor's hiding place
had been surrounded and said his troops killed 100 rebels when they
tried to retake Ganta, the Nimba capital. He did not say when the
fighting took place, and there was no independent confirmation of
his claims.
   On Sunday, Julu said there had been no fighting overnight. He
said the county's main towns were in government hands. Julu said
nothing about Taylor.
   The fighting in Nimba has sent more than 150,000 people fleeing
into Guinea and Ivory Coast, which border the county.
   International organizations have accused Liberian troops of
killing hundreds of civilians in trying to put down the rebellion.
Guerrilla forces were accused of killing members of Doe's Krahn
tribe in reprisal for the government killings.
   Doe, a former army sergeant, seized power in a 1980 military
coup.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0043 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 1849EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-PapuaNewGuinea-Slaying     04-15 0245</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Papua New Guinea-Slaying,0249</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ex-Official Found Slain in Papua New Guinea</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PORT MORESBY, Papua New Guinea (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The country's former chief
police and prison official was stabbed to death Sunday at his Port
Moresby home, police said.
   Police said three assailants killed Pius Kerepia, who resigned
in December following a campaign by senior officials against his
attempts to reform the corrections department and transfer officers.
   Metropolitan Police Chief Supt. Phillip Taku said the stabbing
was being treated as an assassination. ``It was not robbery,'' Taku
said.
   Kerepia was stabbed in the neck and the left side of the chest,
said police sources quoted by the Australian Associated Press. Taku
said at least 30 people had been detained for questioning, but no
one had been charged with the slaying.
   The news agency said senior officers last year circulated a
petition accusing Kerepia's administration of corruption and sexual
scandal, but an investigation into the allegations has not been
completed.
   After stepping down, Kerepia continued to maintain a high
profile as a member of a government discussion group set up to
resolve a revolt on the copper-rich island of Bougainville.
Landowners who are demanding compensation from the government over
one of the world's largest copper mines have fought with government
troops for almost a year.
   Kerepia was Papua New Guinea's first police commissioner at
independence in 1975, and he later served as secretary of the
department of works before being appointed corrective services
commissioner in 1986.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0044 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 1853EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Chemicals-BirthDefect     04-15 0408</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Chemicals-Birth Defect,0418</SECOND>
<HEAD>Lawsuit Links Chemical Pollution to Birth Defect Causes</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PAMPA, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A negligence lawsuit stemming from a deadly
explosion at a chemical plant has produced evidence linking
pollution to Down's syndrome.
   Between 1980 and 1985, six children were born with Down's
syndrome in this small Panhandle area. The Texas Department of
Health and U.S. Centers for Disease Control have said the number is
``significantly more than expected'' in a population of 25,000. The
agencies found no cause for the birth defects.
   More than 250 people from Pampa and nearby Kingsmill have joined
a lawsuit against Hoechst Celanese Corp., alleging negligence in
three deaths and numerous injuries from a 1987 explosion at its
chemical plant.
   On Friday, Dr. John Denko, an Amarillo pathologist, submitted a
report to state District Court in Houston in the lawsuit, saying
the number of Down's cases probably ``is related to the
environmental pollutants from the Celanese site.''
   Another Pampa area doctor told the court in a letter obtained by
The Pampa News that in 1985 he noted ``something most unusual'' in
the number of Down's cases in the area.
   Dr. Gerald H. Holman of the Growth and Genetics Program for
Infants, Children and Adolescents in Amarillo said he was concerned
about ``alarming'' levels of environmental pollution and related
health problems.
   Vernon Hartline, an attorney for Celanese, said the company's
tests show environmental factors have nothing to do with the Down's
cases.
   On Friday, Celanese offered findings by three doctors who said,
``It is uncertain whether one of the children discussed by Dr.
Denko even has Down's syndrome.''
   ``The so-called `general health epidemic' is, in large part,
merely an amalgamation of a number of health conditions that have
nothing to do with one another,'' the report said.
   It said the incidence of Down's cases in Pampa are ``for the
most part absolutely normal,'' and any increase is due ``as likely
as anything else, to chance.''
   The U.S. rate of Down's syndrome cases among young women is one
in 1,500 and for women in their late 20s and early 30s about one in
1,000. In the 1980s, the number of births among Pampa women was 347
to 484 a year. Because of the low number of births, no more than
two Down's syndrome babies should have been born between 1980-85,
Holman said.
   Plaintiffs in the lawsuit have asked to be considered a class,
but the court hasn't ruled on the motion.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0045 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 1855EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Burglary-Death     04-15 0192</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Burglary-Death,0198</SECOND>
<HEAD>Man Dies After Awakening to Burglar</HEAD>
<DATELINE>OLD ORCHARD BEACH, Maine (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Canadian tourist dropped dead
in his motel room after a burglar intruded, and a 19-year-old man
was arrested on burglary and theft charges, state police said
Sunday.
   A burglar late Saturday entered a Concorde Motel first-floor
window near the head of the bed in which Tyler J. Crandall, 45, of
Knowlton, Quebec, and his wife, Donna, were sleeping, said state
police spokesman Stephen McCausland.
   As the burglar entered, Crandall's wife ``awakened, saw a man
coming in and screamed,'' McCausland said, and her husband got out
of bed, collapsed and died. The burglar fled.
   Crandall's body was taken to a Biddeford hospital for an
autopsy. Five state police detectives were called in along with the
state attorney general's office, which investigates possible
homicides.
   Adrien S. Veilleux, 19, of Buxton was arrested early Sunday
after two other burglaries were reported at a condominium only
blocks from the motel.
   Police called to the scene and using a tracking dog arrested
Veilleux seven blocks away, McCausland said.
   Veilleu was being held on three counts of burglary and two of
theft.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0046 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 1855EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Infant'sBody 1stLd-Writethru a0639 04-15 0170</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Infant's Body, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0639,0171</SECOND>
<HEAD>Police Making Drug Arrest Find Dead Infant in Car Trunk</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: New throughout to specify charges; tightens; no pickup.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>NORWALK, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Police found the body of an infant in the
trunk of a car after stopping the driver to make a narcotics
arrest, authorities said Sunday.
   The infant was wrapped in several layers of cloth, and appeared
to have been dead for several days, police said.
   The driver, Mary Sue Perkins, 30, of Wilton, was arrested
Saturday night and charged with posession of narcotics, interfering
with a police officer, attempted assault and destruction of
evidence, according to a police statement.
   Police would not say Sunday whether Perkins was believed to be
the infant's mother, and the drugs allegedly involved were not
identified. Police also charged her with reckless driving and
driving with a suspended license.
   The state medical examiner's office is to conduct an autopsy
Monday.
   Perkins was being held on $75,000 bond at the Norwalk police
station, pending arraignment Monday.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0047 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 1925EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-India-Punjab     04-15 0421</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-India-Punjab,0435</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bomb Explodes Near Hindu Temple, Killing Five</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DEEPAK SHARMA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>AMRITSAR, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A bomb hidden in a tractor exploded
outside a Hindu temple Sunday, killing five people and injuring 25
as they watched a popular television show at a nearby TV shop,
police said.
   The police blamed Sikh militants.
   In addition, 11 suspected Sikh militants were killed throughout
the northwestern state of Punjab, Press Trust of India reported.
   Sikh separatists, claiming discrimination by Hindus who dominate
the government, have killed about 570 people so far this year in
their campaign for a separate homeland for their religious sect.
   The bomb exploded in the Punjab town of Ludhiana after a Sikh
man parked the tractor, Ludhiana Police Superintendent H.S. Khera
said.
   The dead included a Sikh shopkeeper and a Sikh woman and her
8-year-old grandson who had come to watch the television show,
Khera said. The faiths of the other victims were not immediately
known.
   No one was in the temple at the time of the blast, Khera said.
   The victims were among a crowd of about 50 people who had
gathered to watch a popular TV serial at the shop beside the temple
gate, Khera said.
   In the past, Sikh extremists have planted bombs near TV shops
and timed them to explode when crowds gather for the weekly showing
of ``Mahabharata.'' The long-running Hindu epic draws vast
audiences of all faiths throughout India.
   Khera said a Sikh man in his early 20s parked the tractor beside
the temple gate at 9 a.m., 15 minutes before the show began. About
10 minutes later, the tractor caught fire and while some of the
crowd tried to extinguish it, the bomb exploded, Khera said.
   Ludhiana, 70 miles southeast of Amritsar, has a mixed Hindu and
Sikh population. Amritsar is the capital of Punjab, which borders
Pakistan.
   Press Trust of India reported that 11 suspected Sikh militants
were killed throughout the state since Saturday night.
   Six of the militants were killed in a shootout with security
forces in Tarn Taran, the report said. One suspected separatist was
apparently killed in inter-gang rivalry, it said, while the
remaining four were killed in separate incidents around the state.
The report could not be confirmed immediately.
   Sikhs have a slight majority in Punjab, but nationwide they make
up only 2 percent of India's 880 million people. The militants
claim they are discriminated against culturally and politically by
Hindus, who dominate the government and make up 82 percent of the
population.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0048 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 1929EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Britain-Mandela 1stLd-Writethru   04-15 0721</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Britain-Mandela, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0677,0738</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mandela To Thank Supporters at Huge Pop Concert</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto LON4</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: INSERTS 4 grafs after 12th graf pvs, `Mrs. Thatcher...' to
UPDATE with reports that Mandela saying he intends to meet Thatcher
later this year, reports that De Klerk plans to rescind apartheid
laws. Pickup pvs 13th graf, ``About 72,000...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By SYDNEY RUBIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Nelson Mandela is to take center stage in a
televised pop concert Monday at Wembley Stadium to thank millions
of people around the world for supporting him and the fight to end
apartheid in South Africa.
   Mandela was imprisoned in South Africa when 70,000 spectators
filled the stadium nearly two years ago to mark his 70th birthday.
   Twenty top performers are scheduled to play at Monday's concert,
including Grammy Award-winner Bonnie Raitt, Neil Young, Soul II
Soul, The Neville Brothers, Simple Minds, Miriam Makeba, Peter
Gabriel, Anita Baker and Tracy Chapman.
   Among those attending are U.S. Democratic politician Jesse
Jackson and Neil Kinnock, leader of Britain's opposition Labor
Party.
   Mandela, deputy president of the African National Congress, has
not accepted an invitation to meet with Prime Minister Margaret
Thatcher, an outspoken opponent of sanctions against South Africa's
white-led government.
   Mandela, now 71, was released in February after spending 27
years in prison. He was convicted of sabotage and plotting to
overthrow the government. The ANC leader, accompanied by his wife,
Winnie, arrived in London early Sunday on his first visit to
Britain since 1962, the year he was arrested.
   ``It is an honor and a pleasure for me and my delegation to be
on British soil,'' he told reporters at Heathrow Airport.
   ``We have always looked forward to this occasion, an occasion
when we can thank the British people for the support which they
have given us in the cause of our anti-apartheid struggle,'' he
said.
   Mandela was quoted as telling Press Association, the domestic
British news agency, that the sole purpose of his two-day visit was
to attend Monday night's sold-out concert at north London's Wembley
Stadium.
   ``I won't be meeting any British politician as far as I am
aware. This is not to single out Mrs. Thatcher,'' Mandela was
quoted as saying before leaving his home in the black South African
township of Soweto.
   The British government has had almost no contact with the ANC
and that policy has not changed, a Thatcher spokesman said.
   Mrs. Thatcher has consistently resisted most sanctions against
Pretoria, saying they would hurt the black majority more than the
ruling white minority. After Mandela's Feb. 11 release from prison,
Mrs. Thatcher urged international sanctions be eased to encourage
South African President F. W. de Klerk to make more reforms.
Britain unilaterally lifted a ban on new investment in South Africa.
   In reports issued late Sunday, the BBC and the British domestic
press agency, Press Association, said Mandela intends to meet with
Mrs. Thatcher later this year. They quoted Karen Talbot,
spokeswoman for the British-based Anti-Apartheid Movement.
   There was no response from Mrs. Thatcher's office.
   Also Sunday, a leading South African newspaper, the Sunday Star
of Johannesburg, reported President F.W. de Klerk plans to make a
``statement of intent'' to South Africa's Parliament this week to
eliminate remaining apartheid laws.
   The newspaper reported de Klerk is not expected to scrap the
measures unilaterally, but apparently would prefer to negotiate the
final details with opposition groups.
   About 72,000 people have paid $33 each to attend the four-hour
concert titled ``Nelson Mandela _ An International Tribute for a
Free South Africa.'' Mandela is scheduled to speak near the end of
the show.
   The concert will be beamed live or by taped delay to 26
countries, but not to South Africa, where concert organizers are
upholding sanctions against the South African Broadcasting Corp.
   Neither will it be seen in the United States, concert organizers
said. They said U.S. television networks turned it down as too
political, but there was no immediate comment by U.S. network
officials.
   The concert's organizers _ the Nelson Mandela International
Reception Committee and Freedom Productions _ said 50 percent of
the profits will be donated to six charities.
   On June 11, 1988, more than 70,000 people attended the 10-hour
Wembley rock concert honoring Mandela. It was broadcast to an
estimated 750 million people in 60 countries, including the United
States.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0049 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 1929EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Philippines-Clash     04-15 0088</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Philippines-Clash,0090</SECOND>
<HEAD>12 Killed in Northern Philippine Battle</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MANILA, Philippines (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Communist and government forces
clashed in a northern province and 11 rebels and one soldier were
killed, the military said Sunday.
   A military communique said at least five other government
soldiers were wounded during the pre-dawn battle Saturday in the
mountain town of Rizal in Cagayan province, 220 miles north of
Manila.
   The rebels belonged to the New People's Army which has been
waging a 21-year-old insurgency to establish a Marxist state in the
Philippines.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0050 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 1922EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-WeatherpageWeather     04-15 0245</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Weatherpage Weather,0255</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rainy Easter Sunday Across America</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Thundershowers and rain made Easter Sunday a damp holiday in
sections of the West, East and Midwest, and the weather was
unseasonably cool in the upper Midwest.
   Scattered snow fell in northeast Minnesota and northeast upper
Michigan.
   Heavy rain fell in southeast New York state. Between 2 a.m. and
8 a.m. EDT, the New York City area received up to 1.35 inches of
rain. But by afternoon, the rain had moved out over the Atlantic
Ocean.
   Rain showers Sunday afternoon reached from Maine to New Jersey.
Rain and occasional thundershowers fell on eastern North Carolina.
   Rain showers and thunderstorms extended over eastern North
Carolina, and from northeast Oklahoma to southeast Kansas, southern
Missouri and northern Arkansas. In Tulsa, Okla., thunderstorms
produced small hail and gusty winds.
   Rain showers also extended over eastern Missouri, southern
Illinois, southwest Indiana and southeast Lower Michigan, as well
as in northeast Montana, along the northern coast of California and
the southern coast of Oregon.
   Temperatures were unseasonably low in the northern Plains and
the upper Mississippi Valley. In Huron, S.D., the mercury dropped
to a record 17 degrees. The old mark for the date was 18 degrees in
1962.
   Temperatures around the nation at 3 p.m. EDT ranged from 33
degrees in Sault Ste. Marie, Mich., to 93 degrees in Phoenix.
   The low temperature for the Lower 48 states Sunday morning was
15 degrees in Melette, S.D.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0051 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 1940EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>b a AM-Obit--Garbo 1stAdd a0706 04-15 0053</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit--Garbo, 1st Add, a0706,0052</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<HEAD>NEW YORK: was 84.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   ``New York Hospital announces with great sadness the death of
Miss Garbo. She passed away today,'' said Andrew Banoff, a hospital
spokesman.
   He said services will be private, and at the family's request,
he provided no other information about Garbo's death.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0052 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 1941EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>b a AM-Obit--Garbo 2ndAdd a0708 04-15 0129</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit--Garbo, 2nd Add, a0708, a0706,0126</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<HEAD>NEW YORK: Garbo's death.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   The Swedish-born star began her career in silent films and
reigned as the supreme movie queen throughout the 1920s and '30s.
She was rated by some critics as the finest screen actress of all
time.
   Miss Garbo never acted again after her retirement, but her
luminous performances in 24 films kept her name alive and made her
a favorite of younger generations who saw in her an ethereal ideal
of the ultimate woman.
   While ``Camille,'' and ``Ninotchka'' became film festival
staples, the woman known worldwide simply as ``Garbo'' remained
shuttered in her Manhattan apartment or at various retreats in
France and Switzerland.
   She had rarely suffered from any illness. A health food
enthusiast, she enjoyed long walks.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0053 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 1959EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Spain-Basques     04-15 0288</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Spain-Basques,0294</SECOND>
<HEAD>Basque Nationalists Mark National Day</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SAN SEBASTIAN, Spain (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Basque political leaders on Sunday
called for an independent state as thousands marked the national
day of the violence-torn region.
   Police said more than 20,000 people attended rallies held by the
northern three-province region's four main nationalist parties,
which hold 53 of 75 seats in the regional parliament.
   ``These are manifestations of a single reality _ our will to be
a nation and to decide our fate by ourselves,'' said regional
parliament leader Jose Antonio Ardanza in San Sebastian. The
rallies commemorated Aberri Eguna, which translates from the
ancient Basque language as Day Of The Basque Motherland.
   More than 10,000 people sang the Basque national anthem and
chanted pro-independence slogans at a march in Pamplona, capital of
the neighboring region of Navarre. Some nationalists want Navarre
to be part of any future Basque state.
   Ardanza, addressing a rally in San Sebastian attended by
thousands of members of his Basque Nationalist Party, criticized
his Socialist coalition partners for failing to support a
pro-independence proclamation signed Feb. 15 by the his party and
three others.
   Another proclamation in 1987 denounced terrorism. The only
regional party that refused to sign the terrorism proclamation was
the Herri Batasuna, widely considered the political arm of the
armed separatist group ETA. ETA has claimed responsibility for
nearly all of the more than 600 killings in political violence in
22 years.
   Under Spain's 1978 constitution, the three Basque provinces,
which have more than 2.1 million inhabitants, form one of the
countries 17 ``autonomous communities.'' But their true autonomy is
limited since they are dependent on the Madrid government for
nearly all their funds and lack formal representation in a national
legislative body.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0054 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 2008EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Dollar-Yen     04-15 0031</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Dollar-Yen,0031</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dollar Opens Higher in Tokyo</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The dollar opened at 159.15 yen on the Tokyo
foreign exchange market Monday, up from Friday's close of 158.42
yen.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0055 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 2042EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Israel-US 1stLd-Writethru   04-15 0621</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel-US, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0648,0637</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dole Says U.S. Charity Should Start At Home</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS grafs 11-12 pvs, `Abraham Foxman...' to CORRECT title,
second reference; picks up 13th pvs, `Dole has...'</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto JRL1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GWEN ACKERMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Senate Republican leader Robert Dole said
Sunday that the United States has to take care of its own homeless
before granting Israel's request for loans to house Soviet Jewish
immigrants.
   ``Charity starts at home and that means America,'' Dole, R-Kan.,
told a news conference. ``We are going to give $400 million to
Israel for housing guarantees when we have 3 million homeless in
America and no program for them?'' he asked rhetorically.
   Dole has been the Bush administration's point man in attempts to
reduce foreign aid. Israel is already the largest recipient of such
funding, getting about $3 billion a year.
   The Jewish state is seeking the $400 million in U.S.-government
guaranteed housing loans to help absorb the onslaught of Soviet
Jewish immigrants. Israeli officials say as many as 500,000 may
arrive over the next three years.
   The prospect of mass immigration has angered the Arab world ever
since Israel's caretaker Prime Minister Yitzhak Shamir suggested
earlier this year that Israel needed to retain the occupied lands
to settle the wave of Soviet Jews.
   President Bush made any U.S. aid for immigration purposes
conditional on an Israeli guarantee that the money would not help
settle Soviet Jews in territory Israel occupied during the 1967
Middle East War, including east Jerusalem, the West Bank and Gaza
Strip.
   Bush said in early March that the United States didn't recognize
Israel's annexation of the eastern half of Jerusalem. Israel has
declared unified Jerusalem its capital, and most Palestinians want
east Jerusalem as the capital of an independent Palestinian state.
   The Senate passed a non-binding resolution March 22 confirming
that Jerusalem should be Israel's capital. Dole protested the
Senate decision and said he was going to state his position on the
Senate floor this week.
   ``I conclude (the resolution) was ill-timed,'' he said. ``All it
does is stir up rhetoric. The Arab countries only wanted to discuss
the resolution and not the peace process.''
   Dole claimed that Jerusalem Mayor Teddy Kollek had agreed that
the Senate decision came at a bad time and served no useful
purpose. Kollek could not immediately be reached for comment.
   Abraham Foxman, U.S. director of the B'nai B'rith's
Anti-Defamation League, called Dole's intention to protest the
Senate resolution ``insulting.''
   ``It is inconceivable that he should lead a campaign based on a
chorus of criticism in the Arab world,'' Foxman said in a statement
released in Jerusalem Sunday.
   Dole has headed a delegation of five U.S. senators whose visit
to Israel was the last stop on a Middle East tour to promote peace.
Other countries on the itinerary included Egypt, Syria, Jordan and
Iraq. The group was scheduled to return to Washington on Sunday.
   Others in the delegation were James McClure, R-Idaho; Alan
Simpson, R-Wyo.; Frank Murkowski, R-Alaska; and Howard Metzenbaum,
D-Ohio.
   The senators, reflecting on Israel's current political crisis,
stressed that the country urgently needed a government that would
launch peace talks with the Palestinians.
   Metzenbaum criticized the Israeli electoral system that is
stalling government formation and said he was leaving with no more
optimism for peace.
   Metzenbaum saw no readiness for arms control in the Middle East
and said that international supervison over the weapons industry
was not even discussed with Shamir.
   However, Murkowski, who earlier celebrated Easter Sunday in a
Jerusalem church, had a more optimistic message:
   ``This is really what Easter is all about, an opportunity for a
new beginning,'' he said. ``I think we leave with that challenge
and communicate that challenge to you.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0056 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 2044EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Easter-US 1stLd-Writethru a0692 04-15 0771</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Easter-US, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0692,0791</SECOND>
<HEAD>Easter Celebrations: A Dirge and a Chorus of Hallelujah</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: UPDATES throughout with quake survivor taking part in egg
hunt, prayers said for hostages in Lebanon, editing; no pickup.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY9</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Easter, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By THEASA TUOHY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Charlton Heston read Scripture at the Hollywood Bowl, and gay
activists wearing veils in memory of AIDS victims joined the
traditional parade along New York's Fifth Avenue as millions of
Americans celebrated Easter Sunday.
   A boy whose leg was amputated during the San Francisco Bay
earthquake hunted Easter eggs, thousands of homeless people
received free meals and prayers were said for the release of
hostages held in Lebanon.
   Many celebrated Easter by attending services or attending family
reunions. In Southern California, sunrise services drew thousands
of people, but in Chicago only about 100 shivering worshipers
showed up before dawn for lakefront services.
   At the 70th annual sunrise service at the Hollywood Bowl,
Heston, who portrayed Moses in the movie ``The Ten Commandments''
and Judah Ben Hur in ``Ben Hur,'' read the Bible. Actress Connie
Stevens recited an Easter poem from a stage festooned with flowers.
   Chants of ``Hallelujah'' wafted down from the Hollywood Hills to
the Los Angeles basin below. The spectacle, broadcast worldwide,
included a tribute to new religious freedom in Eastern Europe and
closed with the release of hundreds of white ``birds of peace.''
   More earthly needs were addressed on Los Angeles' Skid Row. The
Union Rescue Mission dished up 1,500 pancake breakfasts and
hundreds of needy children received Easter baskets, spokesman Alex
Akar said. Missions expected to serve dinner to more than 10,000
people.
   In Baltimore, several hundred homeless people sat down at St.
Andrew's Orthodox Church to an Easter supper of ham with all the
trimmings.
   ``Easter is the most important day for the Orthodox Church,''
said parishioner Suzanne Stratton.
   The Chicago Christian Industrial League served Easter dinner to
hundreds of homeless people and others who gathered at the
80-year-old organization's South Side shelter complex. The Little
Brothers-Friends of the Elderly prepared noon meals for about 1,500
elderly people, about half at their homes.
   At New York's famed Plaza Hotel, owner Donald Trump and his
wife, Ivana, patched up their highly publicized marital differences
long enough to greet guests at a fund-raiser for AIDS victims.
   At one point, the two were seen holding hands while ascending
the grand ballroom steps.
   Mrs. Trump, who manages the Plaza, posed with two people
costumed as ``Mr. and Mrs. Bunny'' on the front steps of hotel as
she viewed a parade by 20 models of spring fashions by top
designers.
   ``... We are trying to think of tradition, but people have to
join forces against AIDS,'' said Mrs. Trump.
   Part of Fifth Avenue was closed for the traditional Easter
parade Sunday morning. Some of the hundreds of strollers wore
frills and bonnets, but most wore raincoats and umbrellas because
of threatening weather.
   About 25 to 30 gay activists carrying dark umbrellas and wearing
black veils and hats marched along the avenue beating a drum
shrouded in black in memory of AIDS victims. They maintain the city
is not providing enough money for AIDS research.
   At St. Patrick's Cathedral, Roman Catholic Cardinal John J.
O'Connor told reporters his Easter wish was for peace across
America.
   ``We so desperately need it. I think an awful lot of good people
are trying to bring it about,'' O'Connor said. ``The crime rate
continues to soar; the murders occur on the map all over the
country; the violence attributable to crack and other reasons. I
think an awful lot of people are desperate for peace.''
   Among those seeking peace were families of the eight American
hostages being held in Beirut.
   In Norristown, Pa., the family of Joseph Cicippio lit candles
and prayed as a priest blessed a shrine to the hostages.
   One by one, family members carrying candles and photographs of
the hostages walked solemnly to billboards erected on the lawn at
the home of Cicippio's brother, Thomas. Cicippio was abducted Sept.
12, 1986.
   ``To be in prison is bad. To be forgotten is worse,'' said the
Rev. Bede Ferrara. ``We are here to send the word ... that we in
America care.''
   In Richmond, Calif., the injured boy, 6-year-old Julio Berumen,
took part in an egg hunt just two weeks after he began walking on
his own with the help of a prosthesis and metal brace, said his
grandfather, Ricardo Berumen.
   Julio's mother was among 42 people killed when Interstate 880
collapsed during the Oct. 17 earthquake. Doctors amputated one leg
to free him from the wreckage.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0057 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 2116EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Nepal-Democracy 1stLd-Writethru   04-15 0787</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Nepal-Democracy, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0630,0813</SECOND>
<HEAD>Multiparty System Is First Step, But Doubts Linger</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP Extra</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 4 grafs to UPDATE with talks failing, protesters
refusing to let politicians leave site of talks. Pickup pvs 5th
graf, ``Tens of...'
^By VIJAY JOSHI</NOTE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>KATMANDU, Nepal (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   People power scaled the majestic
Himalayas last week and a king bowed to a street revolution,
promising multiparty democracy.
   A political stalemate is holding up the reform, however, and
some fear Nepal's movement toward freedom will be turned back.
   Early Monday, negotiations between opposition and government
leaders collapsed and hundreds of angry protesters camped out
around the site of the talks, refusing to let the politicians leave.
   On April 8, two days after the bloodiest crackdown in Nepal's
modern history, 44-year-old King Birendra gave in to the popular
revolt, declared the press to be free and released political
prisoners.
   Tens of thousands of Nepalis, their faces painted red in
celebration, danced through the streets of the capital, shouting
``Victory! Victory!''
   Their tears of joy dried quickly. The 17 million people in this
landlocked nation of breathtaking beauty face serious questions.
   How can they establish true democracy in a country where the
king is all-powerful and viewed by many as a living god? What means
should they use?
   The questions are not new.
   Three decades ago, Nepal experimented with multiparty politics
for 18 months. The experiment ended abruptly when Birendra's
father, King Mahendra, dismissed the government and banned
political parties, which he accused of corruption and incompetence.
   Now the Nepali Congress Party, which Mahendra banned, has
returned to haunt his son. Joining with a leftist coalition, the
party led the movement for democracy that drew hundreds of
thousands of people into the streets.
   Doctors, pilots, government workers, students and intellectuals
conducted strikes. The movement peaked April 6 and the goverment
cracked down. Up to 200 people were killed when police opened fire
in Katmandu and elsewhere.
   Two days later, a special television broadcast told the story:
The king was establishing a multiparty system. In exchange, the
opposition announced an end to its agitation.
   New battle lines have been drawn since then.
   After the television announcement, Birendra invited the
opposition to join an interim government that would prepare for
elections. Foreign Minister Pashupati Rana said the king's role
would be diminished.
   Opposition parties balked and have threatened to return to the
streets unless the king dissolves the partyless National Assemby,
or Rashtriya Panchayat, and scraps the constitution.
   Under the system established by his father, Birendra dominates
the government. He appoints one-fifth of the National Assembly and
has a say in the nomination of candidates for the other, elected
seats.
   The constitution gives him control of the executive, legislative
and judicial branches of government.
   Observers say the opposition's first job will be among the most
difficult: to nullify, or at least limit, the king's power.
   ``We have scored a victory, no doubt, but we have not staged a
French Revolution,'' said Dilli Raj Regmi, co-founder of the Nepali
Congress Party. ``The scenario has not totally changed and we still
have limited rights.''
   He described the monarchy as ``useless.''
   The opposition ``held all the trump cards and should have
demanded dissolution of the Panchayat and the abolition of the
constitution'' from the beginning, said Lok Raj Baral, a professor
of political science at Tribhuvan University, the only one in Nepal.
   Unless the opposition acts quickly, Baral said, the result will
be ``the same old game of palace intrigue,'' a reference to
Birendra's past record of playing one political group against
another.
   Krishna Prasad Bhattarai, president of the Nepali Congress
Party, said ``we have to go step-by-step.'' The agitation was
stopped to avoid further bloodshed and because ``we are a
responsible party,'' he said.
   Bhattarai added, however, that if he ``does not meet our
demands, the king will lose his crown.''
   He said Birendra's concession is only the first step toward
wider democracy that can be achieved only after general elections.
There are no indications when elections will be held.
   ``We are willing to wait one month, one year or three years or
ad infinitum,'' Bhattarai said.
   Others might not share his patience.
   Nepal, with a per capita gross national product of about $160 a
year, is one of world's poorest countries and 75 percent of the
people are illiterate.
   During the crackdown April 6, tens of thousands of angry men
threw rocks and sticks at police, set fire to government buildings
and smashed windows throughout the capital.
   Baral said: ``The people now are ready to assert their rights
because they have tasted the power of mass movement. Once the
people's movement has started, no army or police can stop them.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0058 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 2138EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People-Trumps     04-15 0230</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People-Trumps,0236</SECOND>
<HEAD>Trumps Together on Easter Sunday</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Billionaire Donald Trump was at his wife Ivana's
side during an AIDS fund-raiser at The Plaza hotel Sunday,
apparently the first time the couple have been seen together in
public since their much-publicized split.
   The Trumps later held hands as they ascended the stairway from
the hotel's grand ballroom to a suite where they shared an Easter
Sunday lunch with their children and in-laws, said a hotel employee
speaking on condition of anonymity.
   After the lunch the two left The Plaza together. Mrs. Trump runs
the famed hotel next to Central Park.
   The appearance came amid an escalating legal battle over the
Trumps' split, which has been the subject of front-page stories in
New York tabloids since it was disclosed in February.
   Last week, Mrs. Trump's lawyers asked permission to question
Marla Maples, the woman with whom Trump has been linked, and sought
to limit Trump's access to his wife's diaries and correspondence
from him to her.
   Mrs. Trump's lawyers filed a lawsuit last month challenging
Trump's claim that she waived her right to half his fortune _
estimated at as much as $5 billion _ in a series of postnuptial
agreements, the last signed in 1987.
   Trump's attorneys say the agreement, which gives Mrs. Trump $10
million and their $12 million mansion in Greenwich, Conn., is
ironclad.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0059 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 2138EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Obit-Bruce-Gardyne     04-15 0393</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Bruce-Gardyne,0407</SECOND>
<HEAD>Lord Bruce-Gardyne, Former Treasury Minister, Dies</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Baron John Bruce-Gardyne, a former treasury
official in Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher's first
administration, died Sunday after a long illness, the prime
minister's office said. He was 60.
   The cause of death was not announced, but he underwent surgery
for a brain tumor last year.
   Bruce-Gardyne, known as Jock, was a fierce advocate of
monetarist policies and served as treasury minister for 21 months
for Mrs. Thatcher. He served as minister of state in 1981 and
economic secretary from 1981-83.
   ``He was a marvelous colleague, loyal, but always retaining an
independent mind,'' Mrs. Thatcher said Sunday.
   ``He was never afraid to challenge orthodoxy although it was
always done with good humor. He was among the first in the
Conservative Party to rediscover the importance of monetary policy
and of encouraging market forces and competition.
   ``He will be remembered, too, as a fine journalist, clear,
incisive and witty,'' she said. ``The astonishing courage and
cheerfulness with which he faced his final months won the hearts of
all his friends.''
   An avid cyclist, Bruce-Gardyne refused his ministerial car on
most occasions and travelled around London on what the Times called
``a deplorable old bicycle.'' He was forced to stop riding his
bicycle in early 1989 when his illness was discovered.
   Born to an old Scottish land-owning family, Bruce-Gardyne was
educated at Winchester school and Oxford University's Magdalen
College.
   He joined the diplomatic service and worked in London and Sofia,
Bulgaria, from 1953 to 1956 until quitting the foreign services for
journalism.
   Bruce-Gardyne worked as Paris correspondent for the Financial
Times before going into politics.
   He was elected as a Conservative member of Parliament from 1964
to 1974, and again from 1979 to 1983, when boundary changes
dissolved his district. After failing to win nomination for the
next election, he retired from Parliament and was created a life
peer.
   Bruce-Gardyne continued to work, largely as a political and
financial commentator, and spoke about his illness.
   ``Nothing could be more absurd than to say it is brave of me,''
Bruce-Gardyne said recently. ``To bang out an article on my
typewriter is like saying it's brave for an alcoholic to take
another swig of whiskey.''
   Bruce-Gardyne is survived by his wife, Sarah, and two sons and a
daughter.
   There was no immediate information on funeral services.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0060 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 2226EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-USVolcanoes     04-15 0295</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-US Volcanoes,0307</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hawaiian, Alaskan Volcanoes Active</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Lava from Hawaii's Kilauea Volcano destroyed another home Sunday
and threatened 60 more, and Redoubt Volcano in Alaska erupted again
but caused little disruption.
   A Kilauea lava flow destroyed a home in Kalapana around 11 a.m.
It was the 80th home burned to the ground since Kilauea began its
latest eruption seven years ago.
   Another lava flow was headed toward 60 homes in a Kalapana
subdivision, and an evacuation notice was posted for residents
there, said Hawaii Island Civil Defense spokesman Lanny Nakano. The
notice urges residents to leave their homes because they may be
destroyed within 24 hours.
   ``We have to protect residents, that's our concern now,'' Nakano
said.
   By midday Sunday, a lava flow from the north was about 150 yards
from the next home in the subdivision, Nakano said. Another flow
from the west was running alongside a flow that destroyed two homes
in the subdivision last week, he said.
   Some residents were fleeing their homes but others were holding
out, Nakano said. Barricades were being extended several miles to
keep the curious away from the area.
   Damage from Kilauea, which began its current eruption in January
1983, is estimated at more than $20 million.
   In Alaska, Redoubt's latest blast sent ash more than seven miles
into the sky, but winds carried it away from Anchorage, Alaska
Volcano Observatory officials said. Redoubt is 115 miles southwest
of Anchorage.
   The eruption, classified as moderate, occurred at 2:49 p.m.
   Business continued as usual Sunday at Anchorage International
Airport, officials said. A series of eruptions around Christmas
slowed or diverted holiday air traffic and mail.
   Sunday's was the first sizable eruption since April 7. Redoubt
erupted in mid-December after slumbering for 25 years.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0061 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 2227EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-EastEuropean-Interns 1stLd-Writethru a0645 04-15 0668</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-East European-Interns, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0645,640</SECOND>
<HEAD>Eastern European Interns Get Eye-Opening Experience in Congress</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: Subs graf 11, ``Both Krukowski xxx to CORRECT spelling of
Krakow</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By JOAN MOWER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The halls of Congress have become one big
laboratory for a handful of Eastern Europeans who are spending
three months learning how democracy works _ or doesn't work, as the
case may be.
   ``I didn't realize the Congress works so slowly to make
policy,'' said Miroslaw Luczka, a member of the Polish senate's
investigations bureau in Warsaw.
   ``Capitol Hill is not as simple as I thought,'' said Luczka, who
as an intern with the Senate Budget Committee has been following
the tortuous legislative course of President Bush's request for
$800 million in aid for Panama and Nicaragua.
   ``They probably won't get that money for months,'' said Luczka.
The measure has yet to be approved by the Senate.
   For the interns _ most of them Poles _ learning the nuts and
bolts of Congress has been an eye-opening experience.
   Several of them have had a chance to visit congressional
districts and attend town meetings. And Slawomir Gorecki, 30, had a
hand in helping to draft legislation that Rep. David Dreier,
R-Calif., will introduce to encourage investment in Eastern Europe.
   Overall, they say their stay has been informative, useful and
pleasant _ with a couple of exceptions.
   Marian Lemke, assigned to the offices of Rep. Dennis Hastert,
R-Ill., and Sen. Bill Bradley, D-N.J., said he was gun-shy about
the press after a magazine reporter quoted him out of context.
``But I'm willing to try again.''
   They've also been surprised by certain things, such as the power
and size of congressional staffs.
   ``I didn't realize Capitol Hill was such a big machine employing
44,000,'' said Marek Krukowski, 30, who spent time in the office of
Rep. Larry Craig, R-Idaho.
   Both Krukowski and Zdobyslaw Milewski, a teacher in Krakow, were
shocked by the amount of power lawmakers turn over to their staff.
   ``They are so dependent on their staff,'' Krukowski said. ``In
Poland, politicians rely on their own knowledge.''
   His colleague said he can't get used to seeing staffers sign a
boss' name to a letter or document.
   They also wonder at the hectic life of a member of Congress.
   Milewski, 33, has worked in the offices of Sen. Barbara
Mikulski, D-Md., and Rep. Paul Kanjorski, D-Pa. His assessment?
   ``It might be exciting for a month; after that, tiring. ... It's
a hard job to be in Congress,'' Milewski said. The philosophy
instructor is trying to write a article about the average day in
the life of a lawmaker. His conclusion is that their isn't any.
   Other surprises include:
   _The close relationship between a lawmaker and his constituents.
Luczka said he watched the politician and the people interact at a
town meeting in Bucks County, Pa., when he visited with Rep. Peter
Kostmayer, D-Pa. Milewski said he was surprised that people call
their representatives by their first name.
   _The powerful role of the press. The Poles say there is too much
theater and not enough attention to issues, with politicians
playing to the television cameras and courting news coverage. The
other side of the coin is irresponsible reporting, they say.
``Reporters need to be more careful about the facts,'' Milewski
said.
   _The advances of technology. The interns are agog at such
technological innovations that make it possible to print the entire
proceedings of Congress the next day in the Congressional Record.
In Poland, computers, copiers and facsimile machines are few and
far between, the interns said.
   In fact, a 12-member delegation headed by the Joseph Stewart,
the secretary of the Senate, recently visited Poland to assess the
technical needs of that country's Parliament. The plan is for
Congress to come up with equipment for the Poles.
   Catherine Messina of the National Forum Foundation, a group that
raised private money to pay for the East European interns, said the
feedback on the program has been ``overwhelmingly positive.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0062 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 2231EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Taiwan-Earthquake     04-15 0116</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Taiwan-Earthquake,0119</SECOND>
<HEAD>Strong Quake Jolts Taiwan</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TAIPEI, Taiwan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A strong earthquake shook north and
eastern Taiwan early Monday. There were no immediate reports of
major damage or casualties, police said.
   The Central Weather Bureau said the quake registered 6.1 on the
Richter scale. The epicenter was off the coast about 33 miles
northeast of the Taiwanese town of Hualien.
   The tremor was felt in the capital of Taipei, 112 miles
northwest of Hualian, the bureau said.
   The Richter scale is a measure of ground motion as recorded on
seismographs. Every increase of one number means a 10-fold increase
in intensity. An quake with a magnitude of 6 is capable of causing
widespread damage.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0063 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 2258EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Obit-Garbo 5thLd-Writethru a0721-722 04-15 1077</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Garbo, 5th Ld-Writethru, a0721-722,1108</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<HEAD>Greta Garbo Dead</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: INSERTS 1 graf after 13th graf, `She suffered ...,' to UPDATE
with doorman comment about recent appearance; picks up 14th graf,
`When Miss ...' INSERTS 2 grafs after 14th graf of 1st Add,
`According to Broman ...,' to UPDATE with neighbor comment; picks
up 15th graf, `For most ...'</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos NY20,24,25,26,27 LaserColor 21</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RAUL REYES</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Greta Garbo, the legendary screen star who
turned her back on Hollywood in 1941 and became as well known for
her passion for privacy as for her sculpted beauty and husky
vibrato, died Sunday. She was 84.
   ``New York Hospital announces with great sadness the death of
Miss Garbo,'' said hospital spokesman Andrew Banoff.
   At the family's request, he provided no other information other
than that she died Sunday. He declined to say when she entered the
hospital or at what time she died.
   Ben Buttenweiser, a neighbor and friend of Miss Garbo, said the
actress hadn't been well lately and had had dialysis treatments,
but didn't know the nature of her illness. Banoff declined to say
whether Miss Garbo had been treated for kidney trouble.
   The Swedish-born star began her career in silent films and
reigned as the supreme movie queen throughout the '30s. Some
critics considered her the finest screen actress of all time.
   Actor Jimmy Stewart recalled Sunday night that Miss Garbo had a
certain mystique about her.
   ``It was a combination of the way she looked, her voice and the
beautiful way she moved,'' Stewart said. ``As an actress and as a
person she had this very special thing about her that I think sort
of set her apart ...''
   He said he never really got to know Miss Garbo, but was always a
fan.
   ``I think her mystique was her privacy,'' said comedian Milton
Berle. ``She was a wonderful actress and she was very glamorous.''
   Berle said that during his days in vaudeville, he wore clothes
like Miss Garbo's on stage.
   After her retirement at age 36, Miss Garbo never acted again,
but her luminous performances in 24 films kept her name alive and
made her a favorite of younger generations who saw in her an
ethereal ideal of the ultimate woman.
   While ``Camille,'' and ``Ninotchka'' became film festival
staples, the woman known worldwide simply as ``Garbo'' remained
shuttered in her Manhattan apartment or at various retreats in
France and Switzerland.
   She suffered little illness through most of her life, and was a
health enthusiast who enjoyed long walks.
   Carl Peterson, a doorman and elevator operator at her Manhattan
apartment building, said she didn't look well when he last saw her
early last week. ``She had gray hair and was very thin,'' Peterson
said. ``She looked very pathetic.''
   When Miss Garbo traveled it was with the air of a phantom,
slipping in and out of airports, wearing dark glasses and a slouch
hat pulled down. She was usually only a few steps ahead of
persistent photographers who stalked her incessantly and
occasionally managed to steal a quick shot of ``The Face.''
   Her most-remembered line was in ``Grand Hotel'' when she said,
``I want to be alone.'' She was also reputed to have said the same
to reporters, although she once insisted to a friend that what she
had said was, `I want to be let alone.''
   In comments published in Life magazine in 1989, Garbo described
herself as a ``sour little creature.''
   ``I don't want any kind of attention from anybody, except that I
know that someone likes me, and that's nice. Otherwise, it's
sickening,'' she said.
   Rumors of love affairs were plentiful but she never married and
in her later years allowed only a few long-time friends to
penetrate her solitude.Few would discuss the star, knowing they
would lose her friendship if they did. But those who did comment
indicated they had never been allowed to know her secrets.
   She was born Greta Lovisa Gustaffson in Stockholm on Sept. 18,
1905, the daughter of an uneducated laborer who was often ill or
unemployed. After her father died when she was 14, she left school
to become a barber's helper and later a $25-a-month department
store clerk.
   While clerking in the hat department, she was chosen to appear
in a filmed hat advertisement. Stagestruck, the 17-year-old Greta
enrolled in Stockholm's Royal Dramatic Theater Academy and haunted
film studios seeking work. She won several bit parts, the first in
a 1923 comedy titled ``Peter the Tramp.''
   But her big break came when Mauritz Stiller, then Sweden's
leading director, visited the Academy and discovered the tall,
angular beauty. He made her his protege, changed her name to Garbo
and starred her in his 1924 silent movie, ``The Atonement of Gosta
Berling.''
   The film depicted her wrapped in furs and huddled in a
horse-drawn sled as it sped away from a pack of pursuing wolves. At
the first sight of Miss Garbo on film, Stiller said, ``Her face.
You only get a face like that in front of a camera once in a
century.''
   Stiller's film caught the attention of Hollywood movie tycoon
Louis B. Mayer, who offered the director a contract at
Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer studios. Stiller agreed on the condition that
Miss Garbo be signed, too.
   She stepped onto American soil in 1925, and from her first
American appearance in the silent film, ``The Torrent,'' Miss Garbo
captivated audiences.
   Her career soared with such silent films as ``Flesh and the
Devil,'' ``The Divine Woman,'' and ``Woman of Affairs'' but when
talkies began studio officials feared her voice might not please
audiences. They were wrong.
   Talking pictures revealed her throaty, sensual voice and further
enhanced her appeal. She became an international sensation, drawing
rave reviews in ``Mata Hari,'' ``Grand Hotel,'' ``Queen Christina''
and many more.
   Many film buffs can recite her first spoken line, to a bartender
at a waterfront saloon in ``Anna Christie'':
   ``Gimme a viskey _ ginger ale on the side _ and don't be stingy,
baby.''
   Response to the sight of her chisled features and lithe body
sometimes was so frenzied that the phenomenon became known as
``Garbomania.''
   By the 1930s, she was reportedly earning between $250,000 to
$300,000 a picture.
   Her leading men included some of the greatest stars of the time
_ Clark Gable in ``Susan Lennox,'' John Barrymore in ``Grand
Hotel,'' Fredric March in ``Anna Karenina,'' Robert Taylor in
``Camille,'' and Charles Boyer in ``Conquest.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0064 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 2259EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Obit-Garbo 5thLd-Writethru 1stAdd 04-15 0586</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Garbo, 5th Ld-Writethru, 1st Add, a0711, a0714,0601</SECOND>
<HEAD>NEW YORK: in ``Conquest.''</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   At various times she was reported to be ready to marry actor
John Gilbert, maestro Leopold Stokowski, health food enthusiast
Gayelord Hauser and director Rouben Mamoulian. But as she had said
early in her career, ``Marriage? I have said over and over again
that I do not know.''
   Her career began to wane in the late 1930s but bounced back with
the comedy ``Ninotchka,'' which prompted marquees across America to
blaze ``Garbo Laughs!'' But her next attempt at a humorous role in
``Two-faced Woman'' flopped and Miss Garbo announced her retirement
in 1941.
   In 1949, she went to Italy to film ``La Duchesse de Langlais,''
but the project was delayed and eventually fell through.
   Miss Garbo, a millionaire through many investments, had no need
to work again. She never did.
   Although nominated four times for Academy Awards, she didn't win
one until 1955 _ a special Oscar for ``a series of luminous and
unforgettable performances.'' She did not appear to collect it.
   She became an American citizen in 1951 and moved her permanent
home from Hollywood to Manhattan, where she sometimes used the name
Harriet Brown. She also maintained a residence in Klosters,
Switzerland.
   ``Garbo watchers'' would wait hours outside her apartment,
hoping to catch a glimpse of her.
   Details of her private life rarely leaked out, but in the 1940s
she was linked with Russian-born entrepreneur George Schlee, whose
wife, Valentina, designed Miss Garbo's clothes. She purchased an
apartment in the Schlees' building; the entrepreneur was soon
traveling alone with Miss Garbo, although he remained married.
   The relationship lasted nearly 25 years until Schlee died in
1964.
   Her enduring popularity was evident when in the 1960s dozens of
``Garbo Festivals'' were held worldwide. But Miss Garbo, as always,
remained aloof.
   In a rare interview, in 1928, she said, ``There are many things
in your heart you can never tell to another person. They are you,
your private joys and sorrows, and you can never tell them. You
cheapen yourself, the inside of yourself, when you tell them.''
   When she saw the words in print, Miss Garbo was furious with the
writer. ``I do not like your story,'' she said.
   However, in 1985, Sven Broman, a Swedish magazine publisher and
Garbo biographer, released details of conversations he said he had
had the summer before with the actress.
   According to Broman, Miss Garbo said she longed to return to
Sweden, but feared the resulting commotion.
   Neighbor Buttenweiser said he had known the actress for 35
years. He said he sometimes discussed world developments with
Garbo, but said she wouldn't talk about her film career.
   ``She wanted to know about Germany, about Europe. She wanted to
know what was going on in New York,'' said Buttenweiser. ``She was
a very interesting person.''
   For most of her life, the actress apparently decided to let her
films speak for her.
   ``The result of our life should bear witness to what we are,
what we will do, what we can achieve,'' she said as a budding
teen-age star. ``And our work tells this best in its own language.
Mine happens to be the language of the motion picture screen.''
   New York Hospital spokesman Banoff said the family had asked
that, instead of flowers, donations be made to a kidney treatment
center at the hospital.
   He said he didn't know who the family members were, but
neighbors said Miss Garbo had a niece.
   He said services would be private.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0065 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 2307EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-PoliceKillings 1stLd-Writethru a0669 04-15 0553</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Police Killings, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0669,0566</SECOND>
<HEAD>Marchers Protest Police Killings in Houston</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 5 grafs to UPDATE with Sunday demonstration; picks
up 6th graf, `Former Officer ...' Ester in 3rd graf cq</NOTE>
<DATELINE>HOUSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   About 50 people planted a black cross Sunday near
the spot where one of two blacks were killed last fall by police
officers, including one who faces a murder trial Monday.
   More than 200 people marched through downtown Saturday to
protest the killings. During the two-block procession, children
carried placards shaped like tombstones, which bore the names of
people killed by officers.
   ``We're here today to say that these young black children do not
have targets painted on their backs,'' said Ester King, a member of
the National Black United Front.
   The march was organized by the Ida Lee Delaney-Byron Gillum
Justice Committee. Ms. Delaney, 50, and Gillum, 24, both black,
were fatally shot within two weeks of each other last fall by city
police officers.
   On Sunday, about 50 members of the committee planted a black
cross in cement near the University of Houston campus where Gillum
was killed.
   Former Officer Alex Gonzales, 25, goes on trial Monday in Dallas
for Ms. Delaney's death. The case was moved because of extensive
publicity in Houston.
   Ms. Delaney was heading to work on a freeway when Gonzales and
two other off-duty officers in an unmarked car chased her pickup
truck for several miles after she had cut in front of them. After
Ms. Delaney pulled over, she opened fire and exchanged shots with
Gonzales, investigators said.
   Authorities said Gonzales and his companions were not in
uniforms and had been at a nightclub for several hours before the
Oct. 31 shooting. Hospital records showed Gonzales was drunk when
he sought treatment for gunshot wounds to the abdomen, authorities
said.
   All three officers were fired, but only Gonzales was indicted,
on a first-degree murder charge. All are appealing their firings to
independent arbitrators.
   If convicted, Gonzales could be sentenced to 99 years in prison.
   Earlier this month, grand jurors declined to indict former
Officer Scott Tschirhart, 27, for the Nov. 15 slaying of Gillum, an
off-duty security guard.
   Tschirhart, who is white, fired eight shots at Gillum _ four in
the back _ after Gillum reached for a gun during a traffic stop,
according to the officer. Gillum was the third black killed by
Tschirhart during his seven years on the force. He was dismissed
after an internal investigation of the Gillum case.
   Grand juries declined to indict the officer after the 1985
shooting death of a man who had tried to stop Tschirhart from
arresting a woman, and after the 1983 shooting death of a suspected
car thief who had rammed the officer's patrol car and started
shooting.
   During Saturday's rally, marchers chanted, ``Justice for Ida,
Byron too. The next one they shoot might be you.'' And later,
``HPD, have you heard? This is no Johannesburg.''
   The marchers were demanding a civilian review board of abuse by
police, the appointment of a special prosecutor and a new grand
jury investigation of Tschirhart.
   Marchers vowed to carry their protests to Dallas on Monday.
   ``This is not a threat. This is a warning. We need justice,''
said Robert Mohammed, who heads the Houston mosque of the Nation of
Islam.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0066 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 2307EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SoccerRemembrance     04-15 0256</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soccer Remembrance,0262</SECOND>
<HEAD>30,000 Remember Britain's Worst Sports Disaster</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LIVERPOOL, England (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   About 15,000 of England's noisiest
soccer fans were silent Sunday, honoring 95 people who died a year
ago at the Hillsborough stadium in Britain's worst sports tragedy.
   Liverpool's Anfield stadium _ about 60 miles north of the
neutral Hillsborough stadium _ was transformed from a soccer field
into a makeshift church as fans, Liverpool players and relatives of
the dead attended a memorial service.
   Most of those killed were Liverpool supporters.
   Loud, match-day chanting was replaced by prayers and quiet
thoughts of the those who died at Hillsborough in the Football
Association Cup semifinal game between Liverpool and Nottingham
Forest, a match that should have been one of the highlights of the
season.
   And at 3:06 p.m., the 15,000 fell silence for a minute to
remember those who were crushed or suffocated when police opened a
stadium gate to alleviate crowding outside the stadium. As the
crowd rushed into the already filled terrace, or standing-room
section, many were crushed against anti-riot fences and barriers
circling the field.
   The tragedy has led to plans to improve crowd control at English
soccer grounds, including the compulsory switch to all-seat
stadiums.
   But those measures were a long way from the thoughts of the
supporters and their families at Anfield Sunday.
   ``Liverpool, its city and its football clubs, are renowned for
their family spirit,'' Liverpool's Roman Catholic archbishop, Derek
Worlock, said. ``So we were all filled with horror and distress at
what happened that Saturday afternoon.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0067 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 2332EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Deaths 1stLd-Writethru a0730 04-15 0907</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Deaths, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0730,0934</SECOND>
<NOTE>Eds: ADDS obits on Bruce-Gardyne and Harris. AMs separates moved
a0721-a0722 on Garbo, a0683 on Matsunaga, a0679 on Robles, and
a0727 on Bruce-Gardyne.
^By The Associated Press</NOTE>
<HEAD>Greta Garbo</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Greta Garbo, the legendary screen star who
turned her back on Hollywood in 1941 and became as well known for
her passion for privacy as for her sculpted beauty and husky
vibrato, died Sunday. She was 84.
   The Swedish-born star began her career in silent films and
reigned as the supreme movie queen throughout the '30s. Some
critics considered her the finest screen actress of all time.
   Actor Jimmy Stewart recalled that Miss Garbo had a certain
mystique about her.
   ``It was a combination of the way she looked, her voice and the
beautiful way she moved,'' Stewart said. ``As an actress and as a
person she had this very special thing about her that I think sort
of set her apart.''
   After her retirement at age 36, Miss Garbo never acted again,
but her luminous performances in 24 films kept her name alive and
made her a favorite of younger generations who saw in her an
ethereal ideal of the ultimate woman.
   While ``Camille,'' and ``Ninotchka'' became film festival
staples, the woman known worldwide simply as ``Garbo'' remained
shuttered in her Manhattan apartment or at various retreats in
France and Switzerland.
   Her most-remembered line was in ``Grand Hotel'' when she said,
``I want to be alone.'' She was also reputed to have said the same
to reporters, although she once insisted to a friend that what she
had said was, `I want to be let alone.''
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Spark Matsunaga</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Sen. Spark M. Matsunaga of Hawaii, a longtime
advocate for peace and champion of Japanese-Americans seeking
compensation for their internment during World War II, died of
cancer early Sunday in Toronto. He was 73.
   Matsunaga, a Japanese-American who was highly decorated in World
War II, was first elected to the House in 1962 and the Senate in
1976.
   He was known more for his easygoing manner and his warm
treatment of constituents than his impact on legislation. But when
he cared deeply about an issue, he combined skill and perseverance
to win passage.
   In 1988 Matsunaga engineered passage of a $1.25 billion law that
pays $20,000 to each surviving Japanese-American interned in a U.S.
prison camp during World War II.
   After graduating from the University of Hawaii with honors in
1941, Matsunaga joined the 100th Infantry Battalion, which later
became part of the famed 442nd Regimental Combat Team. The ``Go for
Broke'' 442nd would become the most decorated regiment in U.S.
history.
   Matsunaga was wounded twice during World War II. He was awarded
numerous medals, including the Bronze Star and Purple Heart with
cluster.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Marcos Robles</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Marcos Aurelio Robles, a former
president of Panama who oversaw the construction of a part of the
Pan-American Highway, died after a long illness Saturday in Miami,
family members said Sunday. He was 84.
   Robles was elected president in 1964. He was succeeded in 1968
by Arnulfo Arias, the last elected president of Panama before a
military coup Oct. 11 that year led by Gen. Omar Torrijos. Robles
fled to Miami after the military overthrow.
   Robles was born Nov. 8, 1905, in the western town of Aguadulce.
A member of the Liberal Party, served as a congressman, minister of
justice, treasury minister and an executive with the National Bank
of Panama.
   He created the Institute for Human Resources and oversaw the
construction of part of the Pan-American Highway, which connects
Panama to the United States.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>John Bruce-Gardyne</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Baron John Bruce-Gardyne, a former treasury
official in Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher's first
administration, died Sunday after a long illness, the prime
minister's office said. He was 60.
   The cause of death was not announced, but he underwent surgery
for a brain tumor last year.
   Bruce-Gardyne, known as Jock, was a fierce advocate of
monetarist policies and served as treasury minister for 21 months
for Mrs. Thatcher. He served as minister of state in 1981 and
economic secretary from 1981-83.
   ``He was a marvelous colleague, loyal, but always retaining an
independent mind,'' Mrs. Thatcher said Sunday.
   Bruce-Gardyne worked as Paris correspondent for the Financial
Times before going into politics.
   He was elected as a Conservative member of Parliament from 1964
to 1974, and again from 1979 to 1983, when boundary changes
dissolved his district. After failing to win nomination for the
next election, he retired from Parliament and was created a life
peer.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Thurston Harris</HEAD>
<DATELINE>POMONA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Thurston Harris, whose songs ``Over and
Over'' and ``Little Bitty Pretty One'' were smash hits in the
1950s, died of a heart attack at a rest home Saturday. He was 58.
   Harris achieved fame that quickly faded to obscurity, but he
never gave up hope of a comeback, said relatives and his agent.
   He was preparing to sue to obtain the rights to some of his
recordings and had a contract for an October concert at the Greek
Theater in Los Angeles, said Steve Brigati, Harris' manager and
agent for the past three years.
   ``He was singing `Over and Over' all evening long,'' in
preparation for the concert, said Rosemary Mingo, a resident at
Cook's Care Facility here.
   Harris never got any royalties for his songs, said his daughter,
Jewel Rene Harris.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0068 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 2323EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-HospitalShooting 2ndLd-Writethru a0735 04-15 0531</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Hospital Shooting, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0735,0544</SECOND>
<HEAD>Gunman Charged With Murder in Hospital Shootings That Killed Two</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 7th graf, `Also killed ...', with 1 graf to UPDATE with
trainee's name; picks up 8th graf, `Dr. Michael ...' SUBS grafs
11-12, bgng `The elder ...', with 4 grafs to UPDATE with details on
suspect's behavior Saturday morning; picks up 13th graf, `Police
said ...'</NOTE>
<DATELINE>SAN DIEGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A man was being held Sunday in the shooting
deaths of two people during a rampage in a hospital emergency room
where his father had died hours earlier, authorities said.
   Bradford Warren Powers Jr., 46, was being held for investigation
of murder and investigation of attempted murder, said San Diego
police agent J.C. Webber.
   He surrendered shortly after the shooting spree Saturday evening
at Mission Bay Memorial Hospital, Webber said.
   Webber said the shootings apparently were sparked by the death
of Powers' father, who died at the hospital Saturday morning.
   Deborah Burke, who had worked as a nurse at the hospital for
about five years, died during surgery at Scripps Memorial Hospital
in La Jolla, said Dr. Brent Eastman, director of trauma services.
   Ms. Burke died of a single gunshot wound to the chest, Eastman
said.
   A Mission Bay emergency room trainee, Edward Thomas Rooney, 30,
died at the scene from multiple gunshot wounds, Deputy Coroner Dan
Matticks said.
   Dr. Michael Hughes, an emergency room physician, suffered a
superficial gunshot wound to the abdomen and a gunshot wound to his
right hip, and was in good condition Sunday, Eastman said.
   Frederick Mowrer, 38, the father of a patient who was being
treated in the emergency room, was treated at Mission Bay for a
superficial gunshot wound to the buttocks and released Saturday.
Mowrer, a New Mexico attorney, and his wife had taken their
2-year-old daughter to the emergency room with flu symptoms.
   Powers was in the emergency room Saturday morning with his
father, Bradford Warren Powers Sr., who died about 5 a.m., said
Jeffrey Simmons, a Mission Bay Hospital spokesman.
   The younger Powers had argued with hospital staffers Saturday
morning, but had not threatened violence, said Dr. Harry Henderson,
hospital chief of staff-elect.
   ``He was certainly concerned that his father had died and was
perhaps concerned that he did not receive proper care,'' Henderson
said. ``We didn't think it was going to be anything out of the
ordinary.''
   The elder Powers had suffered an abdominal aneurysm and required
emergency surgery, Henderson said Sunday. But the younger Powers
had told doctors not to operate, saying the 75-year-old man would
not be able to survive the surgery because of his age and his
medical condition, Henderson said.
   Henderson said the man would have died without the operation. He
said the surgery was successful but the man died of cardiac arrest
on the operating table.
   Police said Powers returned to the emergency room about 12 hours
after his father's death and began randomly firing a handgun.
   Police Sgt. Ernest Ullrey of Oceanside, about 40 miles north of
the hospital, said Powers called the department from a pay phone
about 6 p.m., saying he wanted to confess.
   Officers arrested Powers at the phone booth, Ullrey said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0069 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 2333EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-MrsBush-Wellesley     04-15 0301</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mrs Bush-Wellesley,0311</SECOND>
<HEAD>Wellesley Students Oppose Barbara Bush Scheduled Commencement
Speech</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: `Nanerl Keohane' in 3rd graf is cq.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>WELLESLEY, Mass. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The selection of first lady Barbara Bush
as the commencement speaker at Wellesley College is being protested
by students who say she doesn't ``embody the Wellesley experience.''
   Mrs. Bush is scheduled to speak at graduation ceremonies June 1
at the all-woman school in this Boston suburb.
   ``To honor Barbara Bush as a commencement speaker is to honor a
woman who has gained recognition through the achievements of her
husband, which contradicts what we have been taught over our years
at Wellesley,'' said a petition signed by 150 students.
   The petition was recently presented to college President Nanerl
Keohane.
   Senior Susie Cardenas, who helped organize the petition drive,
said Mrs. Bush is ``not representative and does not embody the
Wellesley experience _ what we're trying to go after in life.
   Wellesley spokeswoman Laura Stavis defended the invitation.
   ``The point of fact is (Mrs. Bush holds) a very important
position,'' Stavis said. ``She is and continues to be involved in
crucial issues, literacy, volunteer programs for the needy and the
homeless. I feel she speaks with her own voice.''
   Anna Perez, a spokeswoman for Mrs. Bush's office in Washington,
said Sunday she would have no comment on the students' petition.
   Not all students agreed with the protest.
   ``I think it's fabulous we can get someone that prestigious to
speak,'' said junior Carrie Workman. ``I don't think you can write
her off as just marrying a famous man.''
   Other students expressed concern about the presence of security
and Secret Service agents on campus on graduation day.
   ``It's a private day,'' said senior Helen Yannatos. ``It's what
we worked for years for. It will take away from it in a sense.''
  
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0070 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 1633EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-DigestBriefs     04-15 0711</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Digest Briefs,0737</SECOND>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>VATICAN CITY (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In an Easter Sunday salute to man's yearning
for freedom, Pope John Paul II said he hoped Lithuanians would
achieve their goal of independence through ``respectful and
comprehensive'' dialog with Moscow.
   In other Easter celebrations, Romanians and East Germans gave
thanks for the freedoms won by their pro-democracy revolutions, and
religious leaders called for peace and tolerance in Lebanon and
Israel.
   The pontiff spoke as Lithuanians waited to see whether Soviet
President Mikihail S. Gorbachev would carry out his threat to
impose economic sanctions on the republic unless it rescinded
independence-oriented actions by Sunday.
   ``In the name of Jesus dead and risen for all men, we ask for
peace for our children in the dear Lithuania nation, while we hope
that their aspirations find confirmation in a respectful and
comprehensive dialogue,'' the pope said.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   You won't be through with taxes for the year
even if you beat the midnight Monday deadline for filing your
federal return. The average American will have to work through May
5 to satisfy the tax collectors.
   If that prediction by the Tax Foundation proves accurate, it
will be the latest ``Tax Freedom Day'' on record and two days later
than 1989.
   The reason is simple, the nonpartisan research organization said
Sunday in announcing the mythical date: ``Tax increases will
outpace the growth in individuals' income during 1990.''
   Tax Freedom Day is the foundation's estimate of how long it
would take an average person to pay his or her state, federal and
local taxes if all income went for taxes until they were all paid
for the year 1990.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>SAN FRANCISCO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Chinatown, normally jammed with tourists,
has been suffering financially since October's earthquake smashed
one of the main highways leading to the maze of crowded streets and
bustling shops.
   So when Mayor Art Agnos suggested the crippled Embarcadero
Freeway be destroyed instead of repaired, with a new road built at
ground level or underground, merchants decided they had had enough.
   Activist Rose Pak of the Chinese Chamber of Commerce is leading
the fight to rebuild the 1.7-mile freeway. At her urging, hundreds
of Chinatown merchants planned to lock their doors Monday and show
up at a Board of Supervisors meeting where the freeway's fate was
expected to be decided.
   Agnos argues the freeway is ugly _ it blocks prime views of San
Francisco Bay _ and too expensive to repair and reopen.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The boos drowned out Dianne Feinstein when she
told California Democrats, ``Yes, I support the death penalty.''
But the former San Francisco mayor was betting that her stand would
draw cheers from voters worried about drugs and crime.
   Her judgment is echoed in campaigns from California to the
Eastern seaboard, from the Sun Belt to the Rust Belt. It is an
election year in which death and politics are locked in a
rhetorical embrace and candidates engage in macabre numbers games.
   In a campaign ad, Republican Gov. Bob Martinez of Florida
proclaims he has signed ``some 90 death warrants.'' But only five
people have been executed since Martinez took office in 1987.
   ``As district attorney and attorney general he's put or kept 277
murderers on death row,'' said an ad for John Van de Kamp, who says
he personally opposes capital punishment. Nobody's been executed in
23 years in California, where Van de Kamp and Feinstein are
battling for the Democratic nomination for governor.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>SYRACUSE, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The amorous escapades of a 10,000-pound
Asian elephant named Indy have captured the attention of the zoo
world.
   The 18-year-old pachyderm has impregnated two females at the
Burnett Park Zoo. Babe is expected to deliver her baby around the
last week of April and Romani is due in July 1991.
   That's earth-shaking news for the continent's zoos, where just
62 calves have ever been born in captivity. It's also a sign of
promise for the 35,000 to 45,000 Asian elephants that remain in the
wild as an endangered species.
   ``North American zoos are getting serious about reproducing
elephants. The two pregnancies at Syracuse is evidence we are
making progress,'' said Tom Foose, conservation director for the
American Association of Zoological Parks and Aquariums.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0071 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 1331EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-ValdezPrinciples     04-15 0582</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Valdez Principles,0597</SECOND>
<HEAD>Corporate Guidelines for Environmental Behavior</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Social Resolutions</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The ``Valdez Principles,'' 10 rules for
corporate conduct regarding the environment, have become a focal
point of the shareholder activist movement this year.
   They were composed by the Coalition for Environmentally
Responsible Economies, a consortium of environmental organizations
and social investors that include the Sierra Club, National Audobon
Society, National Wildlife Federation and the controllers of New
York City, New York State and California, who manage large pension
funds that invest in stocks of many companies.
   Although the principles are named after the Exxon oil spill that
fouled Valdez, Alaska, in March 1989, the CERES group says it began
formulating them well before then. They were released last
September.
   So far no company has pledged to become a signatory to the
principles, but many have expressed interest and some have promised
to provide progress reports on how they plan to adhere to them. The
CERES group intends to release a corporate guide for how to become
a signatory later this month.
   Here are the principles as provided by CERES:
   1. Protection of the Biosphere: Minimize and seek to eliminate
the release of pollutants that cause damage to the air, water, or
earth or its inhabitants. Safeguard habitats in rivers, lakes,
wetlands, coastal zones and oceans and minimize contributing to the
greenhouse effect, depletion of the ozone layer, acid rain or smog.
   2. Sustainable use of natural resources: Make sustainable use of
renewable resources, such as water, soils, and forests. Conserve
nonrenewable natural resources through efficient use and careful
planning. Protect wildlife habitat, open spaces and wilderness,
while preserving biodiversity.
   3. Reduction and Disposal of Wastes: Minimize the creation of
waste, especially hazardous waste, and wherever possible recycle
materials. Dispose of waste through safe and responsible methods.
   4. Wise Use of Energy: Make every effort to use environmentally
safe and sustainable energy sources to meet our needs. Invest in
improved energy efficiency and conservation in our operations.
Maximize energy efficiency of products we produce or sell.
   5. Risk Reduction: Minimize environmental, health and safety
risks to employees and communities in which we operate by employing
safe technologies and operating procedures and by being constantly
prepared for emergencies.
   6. Marketing of Safe Products and Services: Sell products or
services that minimize environmental impacts and are safe as
consumers use them. Inform consumers of environmental impacts of
products or services.
   7. Damage Compensation: Take responsibility for harm we cause to
the environment by making every effort to fully restore the
environment and to compensate persons adversely affected.
   8. Disclosure: Disclose to employees and to the public incidents
relating to operations that cause environmental harm or pose health
and safety hazards. Disclose potential environmental, health or
safety hazards posed by operations and take no action against
employees who report conditions that create a danger to the
environment or pose health and safety hazards.
   9. Environmental Directors and Managers: Have a person qualified
to represent environmental interests on the board. Commit
management resources to implement these Principles, including
funding an office of vice president for environmental affairs or an
equivalent executive position, reporting directly to the CEO, to
monitor and report upon implementation efforts.
   10. Assessment and Annual Audit: Conduct and make public an
annual self-evaluation of progress in implementing these Principles
and in complying with all applicable laws and regulations
throughout worldwide operations. Work toward timely creation of
independent environmental audit procedures completed annually and
made available to the public.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0072 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 1521EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-Tax-IRAs     04-15 0148</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Tax-IRAs,0154</SECOND>
<NOTE>For release after midnight Sunday EDT</NOTE>
<HEAD>Americans Doubled IRA Contributions to $31.5 Billion, Money Says</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Americans will have put $31.5 billion into
Individual Retirement Accounts by Monday's 1989 tax filing
deadline, Money magazine reported.
   The latest year's total is more than double the $15 billion
added to IRAs in 1988 but lags well behind the record $50 billion
invested in 1986, the year before Congress reduced the
deductibility of contributions, the magazine said.
   The total amount held in IRAs rose $72 billion in the last year
to $465 billion, Money said. Earnings from existing investments
accounted for $40.5 billion of the increase.
   Of the $31.5 billion of new money put into retirement accounts,
the magazine said investors put $17.5 billion into mutual funds.
Such funds now are the most popular form of investment, accounting
for 24 percent of all IRA funds.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0073 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 1554EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-OilFire     04-15 0183</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Oil Fire,0193</SECOND>
<HEAD>Worker Killed In Tank Explosion</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TAMPA, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Citgo Petroleum Corp. worker was killed
Sunday morning in an explosion in a tank field at Port of Tampa,
authorities said.
   The worker died when a vapor recovery unit exploded, igniting a
fire that scorched tanks full of gasoline before it was brought
under control. Fire boats, helicopters and ground personnel sprayed
foam on the tanks to keep them from catching fire, said Tampa Fire
Department spokesman Matt Ballaban.
   ``It did threaten them for a time, but we were able to
extinguish it with foam,'' Ballaban said.
   The fire sent thick black smoke billowing across Tampa. Ballaban
said 16 fire units and some 50 firefighters brought the blaze under
control in less than an hour.
   There were no other injuries reported.
   The employee's name was being withheld pending notification of
relatives, said Citgo spokesman Kent Young in Tulsa, Okla.
   ``Terminal operations are being suspended,'' Young said. ``An
investigation is under way to determine the cause of the
explosion.''
   Citgo's Tampa operation has capacity to hold 241,000 barrels of
oil.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0074 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 1641EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f BC-USWest     04-15 0248</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-US West,0258</SECOND>
<HEAD>US West Files First Stock Offering to Raise $525 Million</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ENGLEWOOD, Colo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   U S West Inc. has filed plans to make
its first stock offering in its six-year history to raise about
$525 million for several projects, company officials said.
   In a filing with the Securities and Exchange Commission Friday,
U S West disclosed plans to offer 14 million new shares of common
stock.
   The stock fell 25 cents Thursday on the New York Stock Exchange
to $74.75. The new shares will be offered after a 2-for-1 stock
split, which the company announced on April 6.
   The split and the stock offering are designed to raise interest
in the company among small investors, a company spokesman said.
   Money raised by the sale will help fund several pending projects
including expansion of core-phone service in the company's 14-state
service region, U S West said. The money also will help the company
expand its financial services arm and finance cable television
projects in Hong Kong and Great Britain, it said.
   The offering will bring the total number of outstanding US West
shares to 389.1 million.
   Englewood-based U S West was one of the seven Baby Bell
companies formed by the breakup of American Telephone &amp; Telegraph
Co. in 1984.
   The company's stock performance has been lower than the six
other Baby Bells. Its stock rose about 149 percent from 1984
through last month, compared with about 176 percent for the group
as a whole.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0075 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 1804EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f BC-China-InterestRates     04-15 0240</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-China-Interest Rates,0250</SECOND>
<HEAD>China Lower Deposit Rates in Effort to Boost Economy</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Interest rates on bank deposits were reduced by
1.26 percentage points in a move aimed at stimulating China's
sluggish economy.
   The People's Bank of China said Sunday the new rates would apply
to deposits by individuals, enterprises and institutions, the
official press reported.
   It follows a decision by the central bank to lower interest
rates on business loans, also by 1.26 percentage points, on March
21.
   The interest rate on a one-year deposit will fall to 10.08
percent from 11.34 percent, while the rate for a three-year deposit
will drop to 11.88 percent from 13.14 percent.
   Lower deposit rates could encourage people to put less of their
income into savings and spend more, giving the economy a needed
boost.
   Tough austerity measures imposed in late 1988 have succeeded in
reducing inflation from a high of more than 30 percent to about 4
percent in February, but at the cost of a sharp economic slowdown
that has chilled consumer demand and led to thousands of plant
closures.
   In recent months the government, concerned about economic
recession, has begun easing its tight credit policies and
increasing the money supply to bail out debt-ridden companies.
   People's Bank Governor Li Guixian said the reduction of interest
rates on loans in March would cut enterprise debt burdens by 17
billion yuan a year, or the equivalent of $3.6 billion.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900415-0076 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-15-90 1849EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f BC-Sudan-IMF     04-15 0223</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Sudan-IMF,0233</SECOND>
<HEAD>Official: Sudan Disagrees With IMF Proposals</HEAD>
<DATELINE>KHARTOUM, Sudan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A senior official said Sudan does not
intend to accept the economic reform program proposed by the
International Monetary Fund, which includes a sharp devaluation of
the country's currency.
   Col. Salah el-Din Karrar, a member of the ruling 15-man military
council, was quoted by al-Sudan al-Hadith newspaper as saying the
government will accept only its own economic reform program.
   ``We will not back out on our economic program whether there is
agreement or disagreement with the IMF,'' he said.
   The IMF declared Sudan ineligible for loans in 1986. The
military government, which came to power June 30, has held two
inconclusive rounds of talks with the international agency. The
next round of talks start May 5.
   Karrar gave no details of the government's program except to say
it was a counterproposal to an IMF proposal. He said a recent IMF
proposal to devalue the Sudanese pound was unacceptable.
   The IMF proposed that the official exchange rate be devalued to
15 pounds to the dollar from 4.5 pounds currently, and the tourist
rate be changed to 30 pounds to the dollar from 12.10 pounds,
Karrar said.
   The Sudanese government is burdened by a $13 billion foreign
debt. The 7-year-old civil war in the south costs the government $1
million a day.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
</Collection>
