<Collection>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0001 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 2335EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-2LiveCrew 1stLd-Writethru a0762 07-08 0534</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-2 Live Crew, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0762,0545</SECOND>
<HEAD>Newspaper Photographers, Reporter Injured in Melee at Club</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS grafs 12-16, bgnning ``2 Live...' with 7 grafs to UPDATE
with protest at Austin concert; no pickup</NOTE>
<DATELINE>DALLAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A dispute with promoters prompted the rap group 2
Live Crew to cancel a concert, triggering a melee by unruly fans
that injured two newspaper photographers and a reporter.
   The rappers, whose album ``As Nasty As They Wanna Be'' has been
ruled obscene by a Florida judge and banned in San Antonio, refused
to play Saturday night at the Longhorn Ballroom after a promoter
refused to pay them in advance.
   Shortly afterward, about 50 people went on a rampage, breaking
chairs and throwing bottles.
   Security guards forced the protesters outside, but several
windows in the front of the building were broken and some cars were
vandalized before about 50 police in riot gear arrived and
dispersed the crowd, witnesses said.
   The ruckus lasted about 12 minutes.
   Dallas Times Herald photographers Jesse Hornbuckle and Cedric
Thompson, assigned to cover the concert, were treated for minor
injuries at Methodist Medical Center in Dallas early Sunday.
   Reporter Mindy Donnelly was hit in the head and lost a tooth cap
but didn't require treatment.
   Hornbuckle said up to 10 fans attacked him as he attempted to
photograph a smaller group attacking Thompson. Cameras and other
equipment belonging to both photographers were destroyed by the
fans.
   Hornbuckle salvaged one roll of film, and his picture of a fan
being restrained by guards appeared in one edition of Sunday's
Times Herald.
   A car belonging to another Herald reporter was vandalized. The
fans also smashed the windshield of a KXAS-TV remote broadcast van.
   Bob Lowder, a spokesman at the Longhorn, referred all inquiries
about the payment dispute and possible refunds to the show's
promoters. They promoters did not return telephone calls Sunday.
   Lowder said a damage estimate wasn't immediately available. But
he said crews had cleaned up most of the mess in time for an AIDS
benefit at the club Sunday afternoon.
   2 Live Crew performed Sunday night at the Club XS in Austin,
with a ``clean'' concert at 7 p.m., and an unexpurgated show set
for 11 p.m. for fans age 21 and over. The 860-seat club was sold
out for the late show, said promoter Jerry Latouf.
   About 10 picketers from the American Family Association gathered
in front of the Austin club. They carried placards denouncing the
group's explicit lyrics.
   The group held up signs reading ``2 Lewd Crew'' and ``Women Are
Not Sexual Toys.'' They also chanted ``2 Live Crew, Too obscene.''
   Band leader Luther Campbell asked the mostly male crowd of about
150 people if they had seen the protesters outside and then read
off an obscene message he asked the crowd to deliver them on their
way out.
   Latouf said the group was paid in full before the first show.
   ``That's standard operating procedure in the entertainment
business,'' Latouf said. ``You pay the group half of their money
when you book them and the other half 10 minutes before they go on
stage.
   ``I can't imagine not paying a band before they go on,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0002 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 2351EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-EmergencyLanding     07-08 0257</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Emergency Landing,0265</SECOND>
<HEAD>No Serious Injuries in Emergency Landing of United Airlines Flight</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BILLINGS, Mont. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A United Airlines flight with 83 people
on board made an emergency landing Sunday after the plane lost
cabin pressure en route from Chicago to Spokane, Wash., officials
said.
   There were no serious injuries, but 16 people were taken to two
hospitals for treatment of earaches and nausea. All were treated
and released.
   The traffic control tower at Billings Logan International
Airport said it received the pilot's call for medical help just
before 2:30 p.m. and sent out a request for all available
assistance.
   A dozen fire trucks and ambulances were on hand when the Boeing
737-300 made a safe landing and taxied to a stop just east of the
terminal.
   United Flight 793 had 78 passengers, three flight attendants, a
pilot and co-pilot, said Ray Anderson, the airline's Billings
manager.
   The plane was at an altitude of about 37,000 feet and flying
over Miles City, 146 miles east of Billings, when lost some if its
pressure, said Tom Binford, assistant director of aviation here.
   Anderson said pressure stabilized on the plane when it reached
an altitude of 19,000 feet.
   It already had been a bumpy flight from Chicago, said passenger
Mary Burnham of Newtown, Conn., who was flying with her husband and
two children to visit friends in Missoula.
   ``Everybody knew something was wrong,'' Burnham said after the
landing. ``You could feel it in your ears. They wanted to land in
Miles City, but there wasn't enough runway.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0003 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 2352EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-France-Germany     07-08 0282</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-France-Germany,0290</SECOND>
<HEAD>French Troops To Stay In Germany At Least Four More Years</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   France plans to keep troops in Germany for at least
four more years and is intent on remaining Western Europe's top
military power, the country's defense minister says.
   The Cabinet minister, Jean-Pierre Chevenement, speaking on a
radio show Sunday, rejected any suggestion French troops withdraw
from Germany by the end of the year.
   ``That won't happen for at least four or five years,'' he said,
adding that withdrawal even then would depend on actions of the
Soviet Union and coordination with Western allies.
   Chevenement said the eventual withdrawal of the 50,000-strong
unit called French Forces in Germany would fit in with plans to
reduce France's armed forces by 35,000 men.
   The defense minister stressed that these tentative withdrawal
plans have no bearing on French troops in Berlin, whose status is
governed by a Four Powers agreement, nor on a newly formed joint
French-German brigade.
   Chevenement recalled that France refused to endorse a
declaration at last week's NATO summit stipulating that the
alliance would use nuclear weapons only as a last resort.
   ``It was in our interests to refuse to go along with this idea
that one uses nuclear weapons as a last resort, when all would be
lost,'' he said.
   France would stick with its ``completely opposite'' strategy of
nuclear deterrence, he said. ``This is extremely important for
France and for Europe.''
   France ``is the biggest military power in Europe'' after the
Soviet Union, Chevenement said, and must maintain all its
capabilities.
   ``In five years, there will be a strategic void, which is very
dangerous because a void of arms can lead to outside interference.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0004 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 2352EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-ChernobylVictims     07-08 0206</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Chernobyl Victims,0209</SECOND>
<HEAD>Victims Of Nuclear Accident In Cuba for Treatment</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MEXICO CITY (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   About 1,000 Soviet children with health
problems caused by the 1986 Chernobyl nuclear plant explosion are
in Cuba for medical treatment at a specially designed center, the
country's news agency says.
   The group of 300 children that arrived Sunday was the fourth to
come to Havana this month for treatment of illnesses related to the
Ukrainian power plant disaster, Prensa Latina said in a dispatch.
   The agency said Cuban President Fidel Castro had welcomed a
group of 255 who arrived on July 2. It said about 1,000 children
from the Chernobyl area are being treated in a specially designed
medical center.
   ``We have all the conditions to do it and we are doing it very
gladly,'' Castro told reporters, according to the news agency.
   The medical center, called Pioneer City, is located east of
Havana on the oceanfront. The complex includes 520 houses, two
hospitals, 15 dining halls, amusement parks, video and movie
houses, the agency said.
   At least 31 deaths are officially blamed on the April 26, 1986,
explosion and fire at the Chernobyl nuclear plant. The actual toll
is much higher and includes people stricken with radiation-related
diseases.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0005 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 2354EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-HormoneResearcher     07-08 0438</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Hormone Researcher,0450</SECOND>
<HEAD>Human Growth Hormone Researcher Tells of Inspiration</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MILWAUKEE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Watching his parents grow old in a nursing home
helped motivate Dr. Daniel Rudman to seek out a new use for a
hormone therapy his research team found can reverse some of the
damage of aging.
   Researchers at veterans' hospitals in Milwaukee and Chicago, led
by the 62-year-old endocrinologist, found that injections of human
growth hormone, a once-rare protein made through genetic
engineering, will help old people build up sagging muscles, take
off flab and grow more youthful-looking skin.
   Their findings were published last week in the New England
Journal of Medicine.
   While his work in the field of hormone therapy has drawn
attention in the past, ``I'll tell you, this is the one that's
brought the most interest,'' Rudman said. ``This type of work
really touches a nerve center.''
   Rudman was among a group of physicians in the 1960s and 1970s
who used human growth hormone taken from pituitary glands in
cadavers to treat children whose growth is retarded because they
don't make enough of the protein.
   The results ``were truly remarkable,'' Rudman said. The children
not only grew quickly but also lost fat and rapidly grew lean
muscle, he said.
   During that period, Rudman visited his parents in nursing homes
and was shocked by the poor medical care given to the residents.
   ``It was obvious to me that medical conditions in nursing homes
were primitive compared to the kind of medicine that younger people
get,'' he said.
   On a hunch, Rudman said he decided to use the same blood test he
was using for children to check for levels of human growth hormone
in the elderly.
   He interested other endocrinologists in his idea of testing the
effect of human growth hormone on the elderly and began some
limited testing in 1980, he said.
   Rudman began a pilot study at the Veterans Administration
Medical Center in North Chicago, Ill., and continued it when he
moved to the Clement J. Zablocki VA Medical Center in Milwaukee and
the Medical College of Wisconsin in 1988.
   All of the 12 healthy men ages 61 to 81 who had deficient levels
of growth hormone and were given additional amounts of the hormone
for six months showed significant physical improvements, Rudman
said.
   Their muscle mass grew, their skin became thicker and more
youthlike, and their fat mass shrunk, removing the effects of an
estimated 20 years of aging.
   However, Rudman cautions that the treatment is not the fountain
of youth, and should not be used routinely until questions are
answered about its long-term effects and possible hazards.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0006 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 2354EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Non-VotersPoll     07-08 0256</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Non-Voters Poll,0263</SECOND>
<HEAD>Many of California's Non-Voters Tell Pollsters They're Just Too
Busy</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Most people in California are too busy doing
other things to bother voting in elections, according to a
newspaper survey.
   Too much to do was the most frequent response given by 2,260
people polled by telephone for the survey, which was conducted by
the Los Angeles Times. The poll's margin of error was 3 percent.
   About 35 percent of those who were registered to vote but did
not said they were too busy, the newspaper reported Sunday. A lack
of interest in politics, the next most common reason, was cited by
8 percent.
   In last month's state primaries, about 14 million who were
eligible to vote failed to do so. About 4.9 million people did vote.
   Non-voters, whether registered or not, share many qualities with
those who do vote, having the same range of views on abortion,
capital punishment and taxes, the newspaper reported.
   They also were split evenly between support of Dianne Feinstein,
the Democratic candidate for governor, and Republican candidate
Pete Wilson.
   Where they seem to differ is how they perceive voting. For the
non-voters, the practice is seen as more trouble than it's worth,
pollsters said.
   Among unregistered non-voters, 22 percent said they were too
busy and 21 percent said they did not care. Other reasons given by
both groups were dislike of the candidates and the feeling that
voting doesn't matter.
   Most non-voters are young, with 56 percent under age 40, the
poll showed.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0007 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 2359EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-SriLanka-War Bjt   07-08 0694</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Sri Lanka-War, Bjt,0735</SECOND>
<HEAD>President Gets Public Support for War on Tamil Rebels</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP Extra</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DEXTER CRUEZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>COLOMBO, Sri Lanka (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Ranasinghe Premadasa has
switched from negotiating to fighting in the 7-year-old Tamil
rebellion and has gained broad public support.
   Thousands of people send money to a fund for soldiers' families
each day and young men stand in line to join in the army. The main
opposition party, which called Premadasa's conciliation a joke, has
expressed support for the new policy.
   After three weeks of fierce fighting, however, advancing
government troops are bogged down by land mines and booby traps in
the east and are pushed to the wall in the north.
   At least 2,109 combatants have died in the new battle for
control of the north and the east, where guerrillas of the
Liberation Tigers of Tamil Eelam militia want a separate nation
they would call Eelam.
   It began June 11 and ended a 13-month truce during which
Premadasa tried to talk the Tigers into laying down their arms in
exchange for limited autonomy.
   The cease-fire had been tenuous, and the Tigers began accusing
the government early in June of trying to wreck negotiations.
   On June 11, they overran dozens of police stations in the east
and captured 850 policemen. The military says the Tigers killed at
least 330 of the officers; the rest are also feared dead.
   Premadasa's government established a fund to help families of
the policemen and other members of the security forces who have
been killed.
   Sri Lankans have contributed 40 million rupees ($1.05 million)
to the fund and other donations have been received from Sri Lankans
in the United States, Japan and Britain, the Defense Ministry said.
   No breakdown is available, but most of the money is thought to
come from the ethnic Sinhalese majority that has dominated Sri
Lanka since the island republic, then called Ceylon, became
independent of Britain in 1948.
   At military headquarters in Colombo, thousands of young men have
been lining up to join the army.
   Defense Minister Cyril Ranatunge said 30,000 volunteered after
newspaper advertisements appeared two weeks ago.
   ``We must finish this Tamil problem once and for all,'' said
Bandaragama Rajapakse, a 18-year-old Sinhalese waiting in line.
   Anura Bandaranaike, president of the opposition Sri Lanka
Freedom Party, said in Parliament: ``We stand solidly behind the
forces today. Our hearts go out to them.''
   Ranjan Wijeratne, the deputy defense minister, predicted the
government eventually would be able to disarnits, unlike Indian
troops, who moved large columns of soldiers,'' Wijeratne said.
   Indian soldiers were sent to Sri Lanka in July 1987 to oversee a
surrender of arms by Tamil guerrillas as part of an India-brokered
accord between Tamil groups and the government of Junius R.
Jayewardene, Premadasa's predecessor.
   Most Tamil militias gave up their arms, but the Tigers soon
reneged and took to the jungles. The Indians followed and were
drawn into a two-year guerrilla war in which more than 1,100 of
their soldiers were killed.
   The last Indian troops withdrew in March at Premadasa's request.
   Last year, Premadasa put down a two-year rebellion by radical
Sinhalese who accused the government of making too many concessions
to the ethnic Tamil minority.
   Sinhalese make up 75 percent of Sri Lanka's 16 million people
and control the military as well as the government. Tamils, 18
percent of the population, claim discrimination in jobs, education
and language.
   Tamil separatists have fought from the jungles and swamps since
1983. At least 13,000 people have been killed in the war.
   Premadasa, a Sinhalese, crushed the extremists in his own ethnic
group. Their leaders were arrested and died in what were officially
described as shootouts or escape attempts. Thousands of followers
and suspected supporters were killed by pro-government bands that
roamed the villages and countryside.
   ``We have learned from our past experiences and are now capable
of destroying the rebels,'' Col. Parami Kulatunga said in the
northern town of Vavuniya, one of the main sites of the latest
fighting.
   Lakshman Jayakody of the opposition, a former defense minister,
said: ``At the moment, I don't think we have any choice other than
war.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0008 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 0027EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-DrummondDeath     07-08 0307</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Drummond Death,0314</SECOND>
<HEAD>Two-Time Artificial Heart Recipient Dies Of Multiple Organ Failure</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TUCSON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Michael Drummond, the first person to successfully
receive an artificial heart as a bridge to transplant of a human
heart, died Saturday night nearly two months after receiving a
second artifical heart implant.
   Officials at University Medical Center said Drummond, 30, of
Phoenix, died of multiple organ failure. His condition was
downgraded to critical on Friday night after doctors discovered his
liver had failed.
   Drummond was the first person to successfully undergo a
bridge-to- transplant and recover from a subsequent heart
transplant.
   He also was the youngest man to receive an artificial heart
device when he had the Jarvik-7 artificial heart implanted Aug. 29,
1985. Drummond suffered a stroke, but recovered and received the
heart of a 19-year-old Texas man nine days later.
   Drummond had been undergoing dialysis treatments for kidney
failure for several weeks, and was fighting an infection. He had
been placed on a ventilator to assist his breathing, but died at
7:35 p.m., said hospital spokeswoman Jan Howard.
   Drummond received his second artificial heart May 21. He
developed complications in February after undergoing emergency gall
bladder surgery and had developed right-sided heart failure.
   Dr. Jack Copeland, head of the hospital's transplant team, said
in 1987 that Drummond was a ``modern hero who accepted the risk of
the total artificial heart bridge to transplantation when no
previous patient had survived.''
   His remarks were made at a Washington, D.C., ceremony in which
Drummond presented the artificial heart that had been implanted in
his chest to the Smithsonian Institute's National Museum of
American History.
   ``I guess I am sort of a part of history, but not by choice,''
Drummond said during the ceremony. ``It's possible 100 years from
now that the artificial heart will be as routine as a blood
transfusion.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0009 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 0126EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-YellowstoneFire 1stLd-Writethru a0591 07-08 0263</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Yellowstone Fire, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0591,0265</SECOND>
<HEAD>Yellowstone Park Fire Grows, But Firefighters Get Upper Hand</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: UPDATES throughout with fire growing but expected to be
contained by Monday; includes new quotes and other details.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>YELLOWSTONE NATIONAL PARK, Wyo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A fire burning for three
days in Yellowstone National Park spread across 220 acres on
Saturday, but officials were confident it could soon be fully
contained.
   By Saturday night, firefighters had contained about 60 percent
of the lightning-caused blaze in the park's northeastern section
and expected to have it fully under control by Monday evening, said
park spokeswoman Marsha Karle.
   ``We don't expect it to move anymore,'' she said. ``It may burn
back on itself, but unless the winds increase or humidity drops
dramatically, it looks like it's not going anywhere. We almost have
a line all the way around it.''
   About 315 firefighters were deployed to battle the park's first
major blaze of the summer, Karle said. Ground crews were helped by
drops of fire retardant and water from helicopters and airplanes
over the lower east slopes of Mount Washburn and by cooler
temperatures and light winds, she said.
   Crews have had difficulty gauging the parameters of the fire,
which started Thursday afternoon and had spread to an estimated 100
acres by late Friday, she said.
   ``It's been very smoky and hard to see,'' Karle said. ``It's
been hard to get real good fix because the terrain is steep, rocky
and hard to get around.'' No structures have been threatened, but a
couple of hiking trails in the area were closed.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0010 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 0229EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-FireworksAccident     07-08 0172</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Fireworks Accident,0175</SECOND>
<HEAD>Six Injured in Finale of Bay City Fireworks Festival</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BAY CITY, Mich. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A 10-inch rocket misfired during the
finale of the Bay City Fireworks Festival on Saturday night,
igniting other fireworks in a pit area and injuring five workers
and a policeman, police said.
   At least two of the six men were admitted to a hospital with
burns, but the extent of their injuries was not immediately known.
The injured include a Michigan State police detective, and one of
the workers was treated and released, said Bay Medical Center
spokeswoman Gerrie Wolverton.
   Spectators said at least one of the men was engulfed by flames.
   Gov. James Blanchard apparently had left the fireworks' pit in
Veterans Memorial Park just minutes before a rocket exploded while
being fired from a mortar tube at about 11 p.m., police said.
   ``It exploded just as it was clearing the mortar tube,'' said
Linda Collier, a Bay City policewoman. ``It blew low and ignited
three or four other firecracker shells near it.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0011 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 0415EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a BC-2LiveCrew-Melee     07-08 0305</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-2 Live Crew-Melee,0314</SECOND>
<HEAD>Melee Erupts as Crowd Waits for 2 Live Crew Concert</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DALLAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   About 50 fans of the rap group 2 Live Crew
rampaged Saturday night when a concert was canceled, smashing
tables and chairs and hurling bottles at the stage, witnesses said.
   Several people suffered minor injuries, but no arrests were
reported.
   Police declined to provide any details on the disturbance.
   More than three hours after the concert was to begin at the
Longhorn Ballroom, an unidentified person announced over the public
address system at 11:15 p.m. that the band would not appear if they
did not get paid, witnesses said.
   Twenty minutes later, the band's stagehands began packing up
their equipment.
   A man jumped up on the stage and demanded his money back, and
the crowd of 540 turned surly when security guards dragged the man
away, witnesses said. About 50 people turned violent, smashing the
wooden chairs and tables, while most of the crowd spilled out of
the building, witnesses said.
   Security guards soon forced the protesters outside. Several
windows in the front of the building were broken by missiles and
some cars in the parking lot were vandalized before some 50 police
officers in riot gear arrived and dispersed the crowd, witnesses
said.
   The ruckus lasted about 12 minutes.
   2 Live Crew, whose album ``As Nasty As They Wanna Be'' has been
ruled obscene by a Florida judge and banned from record shops in
San Antonio, Texas, never came on stage.
   An estimate of the amount of damage was not immediately
available.
   Earlier, a state district judge, Merrill Hartman, nullified a
fire marshal's order forbidding the concert. The Dallas Fire
Department moved Friday to shut the Longhorn, saying it was a
private club that couldn't sell tickets for a public event without
dance or theater permits.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0012 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 1135EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Vietnam-SovietAid Bjt   07-08 0825</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Vietnam-Soviet Aid, Bjt,0848</SECOND>
<HEAD>Vietnam Faces Crisis In Loss of Soviet And East European Aid</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PETER ENG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HANOI, Vietnam (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Vietnam is being driven toward economic
crisis by a large reduction in aid from the Soviet Union and
Eastern Europe, its only major allies in the past decade.
   Aid from non-Communist countries began drying up when Vietnam
invaded Cambodia in December 1978, and it cannot turn to the
International Monetary Fund or World Bank because of U.S.
opposition.
   Commercial concerns have become paramount in Moscow and
Communist rule has collapsed in Eastern Europe, so agreements
extending aid in the name of ``socialist fraternity'' will not be
renewed at the end of this year.
   ``Our relations were not balanced and not mutually beneficial,''
said Anatoly Voronine of the Soviet Embassy. ``We had to spend a
lot of money for that friendship. We need to commercialize our
cooperation.''
   Jozef Hanculak, charge d'affaires of the Czechoslovak Embassy,
said about 90 percent of Vietnam's credits had come from the Soviet
bloc. He said the interest rate had been only 2 percent or 3
percent a year, but going international rates would apply to future
credits.
   Prime Minister Do Muoi told the parliament June 28 that citizens
must be more self-reliant and tighten their belts because foreign
aid ``that we ... have relied upon for many years now is being
reduced rapidly.'' Cheap imports and huge loans for state
expenditures no longer will be available, he said.
   Vietnam signed a friendship treaty with Moscow shortly before
invading Cambodia and has called the alliance the cornerstone of
its foreign policy.
   The Kremlin now seeks better relations with Hanoi's archrival
China, however, and has lessened support for Vietnam on political
issues, including Cambodia.
   Voronine said military aid would be reduced significantly
because Vietnam no longer is threatened.
   Diplomats said Vietnam's alliance with the former Soviet
satellites was based solely on common ideology and was bound to
collapse when the political and economic systems in those nations
changed.
   ``Vietnam's relations with East European countries will be on
new conditions,'' said ambassador Dietmar Grumbach of East Germany.
``This applies for economic, cultural and other fields of
cooperation, because one thing is clear: The political and
ideological bases of our countries are different.''
   Vietnam has been expanding trade with Britain, Japan, South
Korea and other non-communist countries and its military withdrawal
from Cambodia in September improved relations with the European
Community. Last year, France became the first EC country to resume
aid, and in May, Italy pledged $97 million.
   The economy still may suffer severely because Vietnam cannot
attract enough help to replace the Soviet aid that is ending, a
senior government economist said, on condition of anonymity.
   He said the Soviets had abandoned some projects they started,
and they and the East Europeans canceled some orders for Vietnamese
goods.
   Foreign traders say a reduction in fertilizer supplies from the
Soviet Union is hurting rice production and there are signs of
problems caused by smaller deliveries of Soviet petroleum.
   Most of the 180,000 Vietnamese guest workers in the Soviet Union
and Eastern Europe will be returning home as ``labor cooperation''
programs are ended or reduced.
   In 1986-1990, Moscow gave Vietnam about 10 billion rubles ($16.6
billion at the official rate of exchange) in credits for trade and
technical assistance, Voronine said. He said about 3,000 Soviet
technical advisers were in Vietnam, down from a peak of 8,000 to
9,000 in the early 1980s.
   Analysts say Vietnam cannot meet the demand of its old allies
for trade, starting next year, in hard currency at world market
prices.
   Trade with the Soviet Union and Eastern Europe was about 60
percent of Vietnam's total in 1989, said government economist Tran
Van Chu. Vietnam has obtained most of its cotton, steel and
vehicles from the Soviet Union and many basic goods, such as
construction materials and food, from Eastern Europe.
   ``Most everything we see in Vietnam today just isn't going to be
around,'' said Christopher Bruton, a business consultant.
   He said Vietnam has an equivalent problem with its major exports
to Eastern Europe, including agricultural products, clothing and
apparel, because they are of low quality and other buyers are not
interested.
   Carlyle Thayer, a Vietnam scholar, estimated Soviet military
aid, vital to a nation with no armaments industry, totalled $1.3
billion last year.
   Moscow is said to have removed most combat aircraft from Cam
Ranh Bay, once its largest overseas base, and Foreign Minister
Nguyen Co Thach of Vietnam said all Soviet troops would leave the
country by 1992.
   Analysts said Vietnam might benefit from the change in the long
run.
   ``The Soviets ditched a lot of cash and got very little out of
it,'' Bruton said. ``Vietnam got shoddy products and technology. It
was a disaster for both sides. Vietnam has to recognize now that it
is a Southeast Asian nation and it lives and dies on its relations
with the region.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0013 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 1138EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--Burma-AIDS     07-08 0120</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Burma-AIDS,0122</SECOND>
<HEAD>Burma Has 324 AIDS Virus Carriers</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BANGKOK, Thailand (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   More than 300 Burmese have tested
positive for the AIDS virus, the Burmese government said in its
first report on the disease.
   The Health Department began blood tests in 1985 and found the
first carrier of the AIDS virus in 1988, spokesmen told a news
conference Thursday. A text of a state radio broadcast that quoted
them was seen in Bangkok on Sunday.
   The spokesmen said that as of December 1989, 324 of the 25,701
people randomly tested were virus carriers. The carriers were
mostly drug addicts.
   The spokesmen said no AIDS patients were being treated,
suggesting none of the carriers has developed symptoms of the
disease.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0014 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 1138EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--Vietnam-Floods     07-08 0106</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Vietnam-Floods,0108</SECOND>
<HEAD>Flash Floods Cause Havoc in Vietnam</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BANGKOK, Thailand (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Flash floods set off by record rains
killed or injured 300 people in Vietnam's northern province of Son
La, the official Vietnam News Agency reported.
   The report did not specify how many people died. It quoted
initial reports that the floods ruined 1,140 acres of riceland,
damaged hundreds of irrigation canals and 15 bridges.
   Prolonged rains reached a record of more than 27.5 inches in
some areas over an unspecified period, said the report, dated
Saturday and seen Sunday.
   Son La, which borders Laos, is not far from from the national
capital, Hanoi.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0015 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 1139EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--India-Floods     07-08 0140</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--India-Floods,0143</SECOND>
<HEAD>Monsoon Floods Kill 74 in India, Dislocate 500,000 in Bangladesh</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW DELHI, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Heavy monsoon rains over the past week
in western and northern India have killed at least 74 people and
washed away hundreds of houses, news reports said Sunday.
   In neighboring Bangladesh, about 500,000 people were either
homeless or stranded because of floods.
   Press Trust of India said air force helicopters were dropping
food packets to marooned villagers in western Rajasthan state where
the rains caused the Jajori River to overrun its banks.
   The summer monsoon causes floods in many parts of the Indian
subcontinent every year. In Bangladesh, where two major rivers of
the subcontinent form a delta before emptying into the Bay of
Bengal, floods are a perennial problem.
   In 1988, at least 1,400 people died because of flooding in
Bangladesh.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0016 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 1139EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--BusCrash     07-08 0120</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Bus Crash,0125</SECOND>
<HEAD>British Tourist Bus Flips Over, 36 Hurt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LYON, France (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A tour bus carrying British vacationers to a
holiday in Spain flipped on its side Sunday, injuring 36 people,
authorities said.
   The accident occurred five weeks after a double-decker British
tourist bus returning from Spain flipped over at high speed on the
same highway, killing 11 people and injuring 61.
   Only one of those hurt in the latest accident was reported in
serious condition.
   The accident occurred on a major north-south highway as the bus
was bringing 67 passengers from Hamilton, Scotland, to Spain.
   The bus driver, who was not injured, said he lost control of the
vehicle but did not know why, police said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0017 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 1144EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-BreastCancer     07-08 0543</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Breast Cancer,550</SECOND>
<HEAD>Study Recommends More Aggressive Response To Breast Lumps</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DEBORAH MESCE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Physicians need to act more aggressively on
the initial complaints of women _ especially younger women _ who
find lumps in their breasts, a study of breast cancer malpractice
claims and lawsuits indicates.
   The study by the Physician Insurers Association of America found
that in 69 percent of cases where claims were paid because breast
cancer diagnosis was delayed, the patient had discovered the lump.
   ``The physician needs to be impressed by such findings and order
follow-up studies,'' said the report.
   ``This study indicates that self-discovery often may be ignored,
especially in younger women where the incidence of malignancy is
thought to be less than in older women'' and is more difficult to
detect, the study said.
   The study reviewed 273 paid claims reported by 21 member
companies of the association. All of the cases involved a delay in
diagnosis of breast cancer.
   Women with breast cancer have best chances of surviving when it
is discovered and treated in earliest stages.
   The study, released at the association's annual meeting in May,
was discussed by members of the study committee in telephone
interviews last week.
   Though breast cancer is more common among older women, the study
indicates that delayed diagnosis in younger women results in the
majority of lawsuits. Nearly 70 percent of the cases involved women
under age 50, and 40 percent were filed by women under 40.
   The most common reason for delay in diagnosis was that ``the
physical findings at examination failed to impress the physician,''
the report said. This was the case for 55 percent of the women.
   The second most common reason, found in 35 percent of cases, was
that mammogram reports were negative. In 14 percent, mammograms
were inconclusive.
   ``Doctors have to be more suspicious of the incidence of cancer
in the breast ... and can't depend entirely on the mammogram,''
said Dr. Sylvan H. Eisman, a distinguished professor emeritus of
clinical medicine at the University of Pennsylvania School of
Medicine, who directed the study.
   The American Medical Association had no comment on the findings.
   The study suggests that a biopsy always follow any suspicious
findings.
   ``It's foolish not to do it (a biopsy) if there's reasonable
cause of suspicion,'' Eisman said.
   The study also found that family history was unknown in 37
percent of the cases, though women with a family history of breast
cancer are at higher risk of getting the disease themselves.
   Lack of communication among physicians involved in a case also
can contribute to delays in diagnosing cancer, ``as each often
thinks the other is the responsible physician,'' the study said.
   The study stressed the importance of self-examination by women,
thorough examinations by a physician and regular mammograms.
   The American Cancer Society recommends a mammogram for women at
around age 35 and regular mammograms every one or two years
beginning at age 40 and annually after age 50.
   Among American women, breast cancer is the leading type of
cancer and is second only to lung cancer in cancer deaths.
   The cancer society estimates that breast cancer will be
diagnosed in 142,000 women in the United States this year and will
cause 43,000 deaths.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0018 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 1207EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-US-Israel     07-08 0387</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-US-Israel,380</SECOND>
<HEAD>Baker Invites Levy To Meet Him in Paris</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BARRY SCHWEID</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Diplomatic Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HOUSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Secretary of State James A. Baker III has invited
Israeli Foreign Minister David Levy to meet with him next week in
Paris to try to get Mideast negotiations started.
   Whether Levy accepts depends on his health, diplomatic sources
told The Associated Press on Sunday. The foreign minister is
recovering from surgery for a circulatory disorder.
   It would be the first substantive talks between the Bush
administration and the new Israeli government.
   Baker will be in Paris for talks July 17-18 on German
unification with Soviet Foreign Minister Eduard A. Shevardnadze and
the British, French, West German and East German foreign ministers.
   Baker suggested in a letter he sent to Levy on Thursday that
they meet July 17 or 19. He told Levy he knew the foreign minister
had a reputation as a ``problem-solver'' and described himself as
one, as well, the sources said.
   ``We badly need a peace process in the Middle East,'' Baker said
Sunday on ABC-TV's ``This Week With David Brinkley'' program. He
said he had proposed the Paris meeting with Levy ``to begin
discussions to this effect.''
   Baker's last attempt to open Mideast negotiations stalled in
March over his attempt to persuade Israel to accept participation
by Palestinian Arabs deported from the West Bank and others who had
homes in East Jerusalem.
   Israeli Prime Minister Yitzhak Shamir objected to those
Arab-approved provisions because he saw them as challenging
Israel's retention of Jerusalem as its capital and the West Bank.
   Baker told Levy he was anxious to have a meeting in Paris
provided the foreign minister's health permitted. The sources said
Levy had not responded yet, and that a decision depended on what
his doctors decide.
   ``Hopefully, he will be able to go,'' the sources said.
   The Israeli government has been eager for talks with the Bush
administration, which lately has taken a cool stance toward it.
   U.S. strategy is to push the Israelis to accept Baker's formula
for the elections Shamir proposed last year to hold among
Palestinians on the West Bank and in Gaza.
   In the letter Baker reiterated the provisions Israel found
objectionable and said they had been adapted at the behest of the
Palestinians ``because we thought it might be helpful.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0019 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 1209EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-DwarfTossing Bjt   07-08 0766</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Dwarf Tossing, Bjt,0785</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dwarfs Lobby to End `Degrading' Fad</HEAD>
<BYLINE>BY MITCHELL LANDSBERG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Angela Van Etten uses the five D-words to describe the most
bizzare barroom fad of the 1980s. ``It's dangerous, it's degrading,
derisive ... dehumanizing ... and it engenders discrimination,''
she says.
   Ms. Van Etten's disgust is aimed at dwarf-tossing, the strange
``sport'' that evolved in Australia and became popular in this
country a few years back. She is herself a dwarf, a vocal member of
the Little People of America. And she is one reason there may be a
sixth D-word for dwarf-tossing.
   Dead.
   Ms. Van Etten, a lawyer who writes law books in Rochester, N.Y.,
is one of several short-statured people who have lobbied
relentlessly in favor of a bill to effectively ban dwarf-tossing in
New York state.
   The bill, similar to one that became law in Florida last year,
would ban the practice in any place that serves liquor. Since
dwarf-tossing has never been terribly popular in places that don't
serve liquor, the ban pretty much gives it the hook.
   The bill awaits Gov. Mario Cuomo's signature. He said last week
that he was studying it and hadn't made up his mind.
   It may be moot. Members of Little People of America, the
organization for dwarfs founded by actor Billy Barty in 1957, have
kept a close watch on exhibitions of dwarf-tossing across the
country. They say it has virtually stopped, at least for now.
   ``It may be a fad that's faded out,'' said Heidi Heinrich, an
office manager in Tallahassee, Fla., who has been a national leader
in the fight against dwarf-tossing.
   Ms. Heinrich is aware of only one exhibition of dwarf-tossing in
recent months _ an event in South Carolina that occurred while the
state Legislature was considering a bill to criminalize the
practice. The bill was defeated.
   Dwarf-tossing, as the name suggests, is a practice in which
people of average height pick up dwarfs and heave them as far as
they can. It also has produced an offshoot _ dwarf-bowling, in
which small people are put on skateboards and rolled into bowling
pins. In many cases, the dwarfs are paid to take part.
   ``I find it somewhat hard to understand,'' Ms. Van Etten says,
``but I think people are willing to go along with it because the
dwarfs agree to it.''
   That, of course, is not reason enough for Ms. Van Etten or many
other dwarfs, who say that all small people suffer from the acts of
a few.
   ``It perpetuates the whole image that we're playthings _ you
know, the jesters in the king's court,'' Ms. Heinrich said.
   Ms. Van Etten calls it ``intolerable, really, even if these
people are willing to be thrown. If you picked out any other
minority group, do you think it would last five minutes? Can you
imagine a Jew toss? Or a black toss?''
   Critics say the practice is not only offensive but dangerous.
Many dwarfs have brittle bones to begin with, and even a strong
human body wasn't made to be a projectile.
   Dwarf-tossing is believed to have begun in this country around
1985. It reached a peak of notoriety last year, when it was
featured on an episode of television's ``L.A. Law.'' A dwarf lawyer
on the show was put in the position of defending the practice in
court.
   In real life, it's not easy to find anyone to defend
dwarf-tossing. Promoters and practitioners tend to travel around
and keep a low profile. One promoter who will gladly discuss the
issue is Baird Jones of New York, but Jones approaches
dwarf-tossing from a slightly unusual perspective. His
dwarf-tossing contests were presented as avant-garde art _ a way of
tweaking the values of mainstream America.
   Jones says dwarf-tossing is ``more akin to a lynching than
anything else. That's what we were mocking. When we did it, we were
saying, `Can you believe that in a civilized society this is
occurring?'''
   For a while, it was all the rage in some of Manhattan's
trendiest nightclubs. But no more _ the glitterati have gone on to
more tasteful pursuits, such as nude juggling.
   ``I haven't done anything recently with it, because once that
bill got started ... none of the clubs wanted it,'' Jones said.
``I've been turned down at all the clubs whenever I've proposed
it.''
   That suits little people just fine.
   ``I hope it's a passing threat and there will be movement on to
other concerns,'' Ms. Heinrich said. ``This was just a first step
toward making society realize that we deserve acceptance. We're not
freaks.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0020 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 1224EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p AM-GeorgiaGovernor Bjt   07-08 0696</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Georgia Governor, Bjt,0715</SECOND>
<HEAD>Is Andrew Young Headed for Runoff for Georgia Governorship?</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DICK PETTYS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ATLANTA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Former Atlanta Mayor Andrew Young remains a
Democratic front-runner in his bid to become Georgia's first black
governor, but experts see large hurdles in his path even if he
finishes first in the July 17 primary.
   Young's problems include the unspoken issue of race, the
likelihood of a runoff after the five-man primary and Lt. Gov. Zell
Miller.
   Miller, Young's leading white opponent, has won substantial
support from blacks and liberal whites over the past 16 years as
the state's lieutenant governor.
   While the primary campaign has been free of racial references, a
Miller-Young runoff could produce racially polarized voting that
would tip the election to Miller, said Atlanta pollster Claibourne
Darden.
   ``Racism is there. It just hasn't been brought up,'' Darden
said. ``And it won't be brought up by any opponent of Andy's. But
Andy's black and Zell's white, and even a black-and-white TV shows
that. It's inherent in the election. It never needs to be spoken.''
   Georgia requires a runoff if no candidate receives more than 50
percent of the vote. But the law is under challenge in a federal
court suit filed by black legislators and civil rights activists. A
judge is scheduled to hear arguments beginning Monday.
   Young is not participating in the lawsuit. At one time, he
opposed runoffs, but he now says they ensure the emergence of a
strong Democratic nominee.
   For the moment, Young and Miller are nip-and-tuck for the lead,
according to the latest poll, conducted last month by The Atlanta
Journal-Constitution. It showed Young and Miller with 30 percent
each.
   State Sen. Roy Barnes, a lawyer courting the conservative and
environmental vote, had 12 percent; state Rep. Lauren ``Bubba''
McDonald, a hardware store owner backed by state House leaders, had
6 percent; and former Gov. Lester Maddox had 4 percent.
   Young is hoping to accomplish in Georgia what L. Douglas Wilder
did in Virginia last year when he became the nation's first elected
black governor. And during the campaign, he has taken only glancing
attacks from opponents _ despite eight years as mayor of Atlanta
when he came under fire for his management style and for the city's
crime rate and other urban problems.
   ``There's been a lot of carefulness not to make charges against
Young that could be interpreted as racial,'' said Michael Binford,
associate professor of political science at Georgia State
University. ``The white candidates are really cautious. They don't
want anything to appear racially motivated because they know
they're going to need black voters in the fall.''
   The most likely Republican challenger in November is state Rep.
Johnny Isakson, an Atlanta real estate executive.
   Young, whose core support is among blacks and liberal whites,
has attempted to capture the attention of conservative, white
voters by telling businessmen in economically strapped areas he can
recruit industry as easily for southern Georgia as he did for
Atlanta.
   Blacks made up 21.8 percent of the state's registered voters in
1988, last year for which complete figures are available, but 24.2
percent of the population.
   Young also has taken pains to secure the votes of abortion
rights advocates, reminding voters he is pro-choice. So is Miller.
   The campaigns are well financed. In figures released last month,
Young's contributions were second only to Miller's _ $2.76 million
compared with $3.68 million.
   Campaign spokesmen said about one-third of Young's money came
from out of state. Disclosure reports showed the givers included:
talk show host Oprah Winfrey, $10,000; entertainer Bill Cosby,
$15,000; sportscaster Howard Cosell, $500; musician Herb Alpert,
$5,000; and Jacqueline Kennedy Onassis, $1,000.
   Financial disclosure reports for June, released Friday, show
Young has kept the most money for the final days of the primary
campaign, with $464,581 on hand. Miller had $309,619 in cash, and
Barnes had $221,725 left in the bank.
   Miller has made legalizing a state lottery one of his principal
campaign issues. The Atlanta Journal-Constitution poll in June
found 72 percent of those sampled favored a lottery.
   Young says he favors letting the people vote on a lottery but
personally opposes the idea.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0021 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 1234EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brite-GreenPorch     07-08 0183</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brite-Green Porch,0187</SECOND>
<HEAD>Woman Can Keep Lime Green Porch</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DEARBORN, Mich. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A woman was ticketed because one of her
neighbors was offended by her bright, lime-green porch _ but now
she can keep her choice of paint because both the neighbor and the
city have backed off.
   ``The green porch stays green _ I feel terrific,'' said Judith
Lubeski.
   A city inspector ticketed Lubeski, 47, in May after receiving a
complaint from an unidentified neighbor who took offense at the
shade of green highlighting the otherwise white colonial-style
house.
   But now the resident is unwilling to testify in court, which
means Lubeski cannot be charged with a misdmeanor, city spokesman
Doyne Jackson said Friday.
   According to Dearborn law, homes in a neighborhood must be
similar in appearance. Jackson said the ordinance is meant to
regulate the style of homes and garages and may need to be
rewritten to clarify that there is freedom of choice in color.
   Until then, he said, ``if someone decides to paint their garage
shocking orange and there is a citizen complaint, this could happen
again.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0022 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 1251EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-SovietRockets     07-08 0351</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet Rockets,350</SECOND>
<HEAD>Soviet Rockets May Be Used to Send Up U.S. Satellites</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HOUSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Bush administration has agreed to let Soviet
rockets be used for launching commercial U.S. satellites, officials
confirmed Sunday.
   Launches would be undertaken by a private Australian real estate
company, the Cape York Space Agency, from a base in northern
Australia operated by a U.S. firm, according to a report in Sunday
editions of The New York Times.
   Confirming that account, Secretary of State James A. Baker III
said on the ABC television program, ``This Week With David
Brinkley,'' that ``the president's made a decision that an initial
launch can go forward.''
   On another Sunday interview program, President Bush's national
security adviser, Brent Scowcroft, said, ``This doesn't have
anything to do with the U.S. space program,'' which has recently
seen a $1.5 billion orbiting telescope crippled by a mirror ground
to the wrong formula and National Aeronautics and Space
Administration engineers unable to fix a hydrogen fuel leak in its
space shuttles.
   The Soviet rocket program is ``just another one'' of several
commercial launching ventures operated by China, France and U.S.
companies, Scowcroft told interviewers on the CNN program,
``Newsmaker Sunday.''
   Baker and Scowcroft were interviewed in Houston where Bush and
other leaders of the world's top seven industrial powers are
holding their annual economic summit.
   The Bush administration already has permitted the launch of an
American communications satellite from a Chinese rocket.
   According to the report in The Times, the National Space
Council, chaired by Vice President Quayle, approved a set of
recommendations under which a division of United Technologies Corp.
would be granted an export license to operate a launch base at Cape
York, Australia for the Australian company.
   Soviet Zenit rockets could be launched by 1995, with engineers
supplied by the Soviet space agency Glavkosmos, the newspaper said.
Cost of the enterprise was said to be $500 million.
   U.S. rocket suppliers were said to object to facing competition
from a new quarter, and the space council's conditions were said to
include provisions guarding against unfairly low pricing of the
Soviet rockets.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0023 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 1312EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Israel-Unrest     07-08 0435</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel-Unrest,0449</SECOND>
<HEAD>Assailant Stabs Israeli Policeman</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ALLYN FISHER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An assailant ambushed and stabbed an Israeli
policeman in the back Sunday near a church in the walled Old City
marking the legendary burial place of Jesus, police said.
   The officer, identified as Moshe Tadji, 24, was in moderate
condition at Jerusalem's Hadassah Hospital with a punctured lung
after undergoing surgery to remove the knife, a hospital
spokeswoman said.
   Police shut the city's stone-walled gates after the 11:00 a.m.
attack for an hour and detained dozens of Palestinians in the area
for questioning.
   The assault came on a day designated by Palestinian underground
leaders in a leaflet for ``distinguished escalation'' as part of
the 31-month-old uprising against Israel.
   Police Minister Roni Milo of the right-wing Likud bloc rushed to
the scene from the weekly Cabinet session and vowed police would
use tougher measures to prevent further attacks.
   ``We see this attack in a very grave light,'' Milo said on
Israel radio.
   ``There are new methods of action that will be carried out as
soon as possible,'' he added, without elaborating.
   Police and witnesses said Tadji, who routinely works in
Jerusalem's square-mile old city, was ambushed by a youth with
black curly hair and wearing blue jeans and a yellow shirt, outside
the Holy Sepulcher church in the Christian Quarter.
   The church is held by Catholics to be the burial site of Jesus.
Protestants believe the burial place is outside the walled city in
a shrine called the ``Garden Tomb.''
   Doctors later said they removed an 8-inch-long kitchen knife
from Tadji's back and that he was in moderate condition, Hadassah
spokeswoman Yael Bossem said.
   The area of the Holy Sepulcher has been a source of Arab-Jewish
tensions following the settlement established by a group of armed
Israelis in a nearby building in April.
   The Supreme Court later ordered most settlers evicted after
strong protests from the United States, but allowed about 20 to
remain pending resolution of a tenancy dispute in the building.
   Israel captured East Jerusalem, with the West Bank and Gaza
Strip, in the 1967 Middle East war. Jerusalem was annexed shortly
afterward. The city is home to more than 350,000 Jews and about
140,000 Palestinians.
   During the uprising, 723 Palestinians have been killed by
Israelis and 45 Israelis have been slain by Arabs. Another 232
Palestinians have been killed by fellow Arabs as alleged
collaborators with Israel.
   Also Sunday, Israel reopened a Palestinian vocational college in
Abu Dis in the West Bank as part of a plan to reopen colleges shut
during the uprising to prevent unrest.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0024 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 1336EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--Egypt-Iran     07-08 0186</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Egypt-Iran,0191</SECOND>
<HEAD>Report: Iran and Egypt to Consider Restoring Ties</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CAIRO, Egypt (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Iran's foreign minister will visit Egypt
amid signs the two countries are considering restoring ties, a
report said Sunday.
   The state-owned Al Messa newspaper said in an unattributed story
that Iran has sent Egypt a message of thanks for the supplies sent
following the earthquake that killed about 40,000 people last month.
   ``I learned that Iran has sent a message to Egypt through
Geneva, thanking it for its help sent to the victims of the
earthquake,'' Al Messa's editor-in-chief, Samir Ragab, wrote in a
front-page article.
   ``Relations between Egypt and Iran will improve in the coming
days, and the Iranian Foreign Minister Ali Akbar Velayati will
visit Cairo in the next few days after accepting an invitation''
from his counterpart, Ragab said.
   Ragab gave no further details on the reported meeting.
   Iran severed diplomatic relations with Egypt in 1979 to protest
its peace treaty with Israel signed in March of that year.
   Despite the absence of ties, Mubarak sent several planeloads of
supplies for the Iranian victims of the killer earthquake.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0025 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 1341EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Philippines-Americans     07-08 0382</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Philippines-Americans,0392</SECOND>
<HEAD>US Embassy Warns Americans To Stay Away From Nightclubs</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT H. REID</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MANILA, Philippines (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The U.S. Embassy has warned Americans
to stay away from the city's nightclub district because of
unconfirmed reports that Communist rebels may try to kill U.S.
nationals there, a U.S. spokesman said Sunday.
   Embassy spokesman Stanley Schrager said the advisory was issued
after a bar owner received a letter last week, purportedly from the
New People's Army, threatening attacks on Americans in the city's
Ermita district.
   ``We don't know whether the letter is valid or not,'' said
Schrager. ``But we have a policy of advising Americans every time
we receive any indication of a threat.''
   Relatively few Americans frequent bars in the Ermita district,
located about two blocks from the U.S. Embassy. The district
includes several foreign firms.
   Ermita, a high-crime center of drugs, prostitution and petty
street crime, is popular with Australians, West Germans, French and
Scandinavian tourists, who are easily mistaken by Filipinos for
Americans.
   The U.S. Embassy estimates there are between 120,000 and 140,000
Americans in the Philippines, including 40,000 affiliated with the
American military.
   At least eight Americans are believed to have been slain by the
New People's Army since April 1989. Last month, suspected rebels
kidnapped Peace Corps volunteer Timothy Swanson, 26, of Cheyenne,
Wyo. on the central island of Negros.
   Also last month, the United States suspended Peace Corps
operations because of rebel threats. Swanson was abducted June 13
but U.S. officials learned of it only two weeks later after trying
to contact him about the suspension order.
   On Friday, a statement purportedly from the Negros rebels said
Swanson and a Japanese aid worker kidnapped in May would be
released this month. The statement said both were safe and had been
cleared of spy charges.
   If the statement was authentic, it would be the first public
acknowledgement from the rebels that they were holding Swanson and
the Japanese worker, Fumio Mizuno.
   The statement warned that Peace Corps volunteers would no longer
be permitted to work on Negros because some of them had been spying
for the Philippine military.
   Schrager said the United States welcomed reports that Swanson
was alive but had no way of verifying whether the statement was
really from the guerrillas.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0026 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 1343EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Summit-Trade     07-08 0741</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Summit-Trade,700</SECOND>
<HEAD>With AM-Summit Rdp</HEAD>
<HEAD>Summit Push On To Resolve Farm Subsidies Dispute</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARTIN CRUTSINGER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Economics Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HOUSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Bush administration is determined to resolve
a nasty dispute between the United States and Europe over farm
subsidies at this year's economic summit.
   Without a compromise on agriculture, the administration
believes, an ambitious four-year effort to overhaul the global
trading system could end in failure.
   Those talks, being held under the auspices of the 97-nation
General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade, hold out tremendous promise
of expanding trade opportunities for American farmers and
businesses by removing existing barriers and bringing more products
under the rules of the global trading system.
   In an era when the United States has suffered through six
consecutive years of $100 billion-plus trade deficits, it is no
wonder that the administration is searching for ways to boost U.S.
exports.
   U.S. Trade Representative Carla Hills paints failure of the
trade liberalization talks in almost apocalyptic terms of ``gravely
diminished prosperity'' for both rich and poor nations alike as
countries turn inward and erect trade barriers.
   The talks, known as the Uruguay Round for the country where they
began in 1986, face an end-of-the-year deadline for conclusion with
the final bargaining session scheduled for Brussels in early
December. However, with only six months left, none of the major
issues has been resolved.
   U.S. negotiators are seeking to phase out all trade-distorting
farm subsidies, to dismantle barriers to trade in services, a
high-growth area where the United States is extremely competitive
and to crack down on copyright piracy, estimated to cost American
companies $60 billion annually.
   But of all the issues, agriculture is seen as the key. That is
because Third World countries have balked at agreeing to U.S.
proposals on removing barriers to trade in services and beefing up
their enforcement of copyright laws unless they win expanded
markets for their farm products.
   The farm subsidy battle is also draining government treasuries
with the cost to U.S. taxpayers and consumers put at $75 billion
annually and the cost to the 12-nation European Community running
an even higher $125 billion annually.
   The United States is pushing for a complete phase out of
subsidies in three areas _ export subsidies paid by governments to
make their country's products cheaper on world markets, domestic
price supports paid to farmers to boost production and barriers
erected to keep products out, thus boosting the price to a
country's consumers.
   The European Community, however, has balked at this approach,
expressing a willingness only to consider reducing the aggregate
total of farm subsidies and charging that the U.S. proposals could
mean pushing 2 million to 3 million of their less-efficient farmers
off the land, a politically unacceptable result.
   The dispute over farm subsidies turned bitter at a May session
attended by U.S. and European officials.
   Frans Andriessen, the community's top trade official, told
reporters in Houston that continued pressure by the United States
would backfire and make it even harder to reach a compromise.
   ``If the pressure is exaggerated, it makes it more difficult to
negotiate,'' Andriessen said.
   The United States, however, is holding firm to its position that
it will accept nothing less than an agreement which addresses all
three areas.
   The Bush administration has tried to paint the European
Community as the lone holdout in the farm battle. But Japan is also
holding back on the question of removing all market barriers, which
would submit the protected Japanese rice market to foreign
competition.
   About the only thing that is certain is that Bush will have his
hands full in convincing his economic summit partners to come
around to the U.S. position. Japan, West Germany, France, Britain
and Italy all have reasons for protecting farm subsidies. At the
economic summit, Bush can count only on Canadian Prime Minister
Brian Mulroney for full support for the U.S. position.
   But Hills said the United States has no intention of dropping
its effort for global agricultural reform, seeing success here as
the key to achieving ultimate victory with the total Uruguay Round.
   ``The Uruguay Round holds the promise at a magical moment in
history of being the ultimate competitiveness machine. It will
provide an enormous boost for emerging democracies in Eastern
Europe and Latin America,'' she told reporters at a pre-summit
briefing. ``It holds a real prize not only for us but for the
vitality of the global trading system in the 21st Century.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0027 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 1351EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Summit-Notebook     07-08 0457</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Summit-Notebook,450</SECOND>
<HEAD>With AM-Summit Rdp</HEAD>
<HEAD>Cowboys, Heat Hot Topics In Houston</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HOUSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Who was that cowboy?
   Kabun Muto, head of Japan's powerful Ministry of International
Trade and Industry, delighted his American hosts by showing up at a
Houston nightspot in full Western regalia, down to a string tie and
Texas-size silver belt buckle.
   Muto fit right in at the Cadillac Bar, known for bar maids who
pour tequila out of gun holsters and have shot glasses affixed to
the bandoleers crisscrossing their chests.
   Commerce Secretary Robert Mosbacher, who along with his wife
Georgette was hosting a dinner party at the bar for Muto, was
wearing a pair of borrowed jeans because the former oil man from
Houston had forgotten to pack his own for the summit.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   ``Houston's Hot!'' the billboards proclaim. No kidding. But the
VIPs coming to town won't break a sweat.
   The seven world leaders are scheduled down to the minute during
the three-day event, and summit director Fred Malek said Sunday
only 18 minutes will be spent standing in the heat.
   ``We expect that the heat will not be an issue because almost
every event will be conducted indoors,'' Malek said.
   Western leaders will have to sweat through an arrival ceremony
at Rice University on Monday. Because of the heat, the schedule has
been shortened, and the outdoor portion will last only 18 minutes.
   Houston highs have been in the low 90s with humidity of 80
percent. With some delight, however, Malek noted that Washington
highs last week were over 100 degrees.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Oops. NASA, a hometown hero in Houston, has an elaborate exhibit
at the economic summit's media center to tout its past glory and
future endeavors.
   Like the Hubble Space Telescope.
   The exhibit prominently proclaims the Hubble ``potentially the
most dramatic single advancement in astronomy since the invention
of the telescope.''
   ``And it still is,'' said Celeilla Coleman, a National
Aeronautics and Space Administration spokeswoman. ``It's just a
temporary setback. Wait and see, and they'll fix it.''
   The $1.5 billion Hubble was launched April 24 and NASA announced
June 27 that its two main mirrors would not focus properly. A
manufacturing error was suspected, and a corrective shuttle mission
will be required before the space telescope can produce the images
it was supposed to capture.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   At the press center set up for the thousands of reporters
covering the summit, one enterprising group has moved the standard
news release into the computer age.
   An organization with the imposing title of ``The Eminent Persons
Group on World Trade'' put their message promoting global free
trade talks on a floppy disk.
   For the computer illiterate, they thoughtfully provided a
printed copy of all the information contained on the computer disk.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0028 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 1401EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Lebanon-Hostages 1stLd-Writethru a0668 07-08 0924</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lebanon-Hostages, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0668,0953</SECOND>
<HEAD>Scenario For Hostage Release Under Consideration</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 4th graf pvs, `He spoke...' with 3 grafs to UPDATE with
source saying release not expected for several days. Pick up 5th
graf pvs, `At least...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By FAROUK NASSAR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BEIRUT, Lebanon (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Iran has decided to use its influence
with Shiite Moslem kidnappers to free one of 16 Western hostages
they hold, and a scenario for the release is being worked out, a
source close to the fundamentalist Hezbollah said Sunday.
   ``The decision was taken in Tehran to release the hostage. The
details on where, when and how are now under consideration in
Lebanon,'' the source said on condition of anonymity.
   The source would not speculate on who would be released, or
answer any other questions. ``We have to wait for a communique
(from the kidnappers),'' he said.
   Another source close to the command of Syrian troops in Beirut's
Moslem sector said he did not expect a hostage to go free before
the middle of the week.
   ``We haven't been contacted yet about arrangements of the
release. It usually takes two to three days after such contact to
have the hostage out,'' the source said. He also requested
anonymity.
   The Shiite source spoke just before Israeli warplanes struck a
Hezbollah base in southern Lebanon in their 14th air raid on
targets in Lebanon this year.
   At least two people were killed and seven wounded in the raid on
a position between the villages of Jarjou and Ein Bouswar, two to
three miles north of Israel's self-designated security zone in
southern Lebanon.
   It was not clear if the hostage-holders would cancel the
reported plan for a hostage release in retaliation for the raid.
   Moslem fundamentalists accuse Western governments, especially
the United States, of bias toward Israel and hold them responsible
for Israel's actions against the Arabs.
   Hezbollah, or Party of God, is believed to be an umbrella for
underground factions holding most of the Westerners.
   Newsmen and photographers maintained a vigil at their offices
and outside major Syrian army positions, awaiting word from the
kidnappers to confirm reports of an imminent hostage release.
   Hostages released in the past were turned over to the Syrian
army command, driven to Syria and then flown from there to their
homes. Their releases followed statements from the kidnappers
announcing who would be freed and when.
   Syria is the main power-broker in Lebanon. It has 40,000 troops
in northern and eastern provinces as well as Moslem west Beirut.
But it has little influence on the hostage-holders.
   Tehran's official Islamic Republic News Agency reported Saturday
that a Western hostage would probably be released soon. It said
that most likely the hostage would be one of the Europeans.
   The hostages include six Americans and 10 Europeans _ four
Britons, two Swiss, two West Germans, an Irishman and an Italian.
   The longest held is Terry Anderson, chief Middle East
correspondent for The Associated Press. He was kidnapped March 16,
1985.
   The 47-word report from IRNA, monitored in Nicosia, Cyprus, was
attributed to unidentified sources. The headline read: ``A European
Hostage May Be Released Soon.''
   The report said the sources ``hinted that he is most probably a
European national.''
   A source close to the Syrian army command said that if any
hostage were released, it would probably be the Irishman, Brian
Keenan.
   The source, who spoke on condition of anonymity, refused to say
why he thought Keenan, who also holds a British passport, would be
the one.
   Keenan, 39, was kidnapped in Moslem west Beirut April 11, 1986,
as he walked from his home to the American University of Beirut,
where he taught English.
   Diplomats in Tehran said in recent interviews that Iranian
President Hashemi Rafsanjani has renewed a push to get the captives
freed.
   No group has claimed the abduction of Keenan, of Belfast. But
when American educator Frank Reed was released from captivity in
April he said he had seen Keenan.
   Another American, Robert Polhill, also was freed in April, but
he apparently was held by other kidnappers.
   Keenan's sister, Elaine Spence, told the British Press
Association in London that she held hope her brother would be
freed, but that no firm word was available yet.
   ``We have been talking on the telephone to the Foreign Affairs
Department official in Dublin who said they are following up every
possible line of inquiry, but they still have no news,'' she said
from the home of her sister, Brenda Gillham, near Dundonald,
Northern Ireland.
   ``We are getting prepared in case it is all true and we have to
fly out to meet Brian,'' she said. ``But we are not getting our
hopes raised too high. This has all happened before.''
   An Irish government delegation visited Tehran in mid-June. An
Irish Red Cross aid plane was the first to reach Iran after a June
21 earthquake that devastated northwestern provinces.
   After the release of Reed and Polhill, Iran asked for a
reciprocal ``goodwill'' gesture from the United States.
   It suggested that Washington and other Western governments
pressure Israel to free some 300 detainees in Khiam, in southern
Lebanon, and provide firm word on the fate of four Iranians
kidnapped by Lebanese Christians in 1982.
   Lebanese Christian officials say they have been killed, but Iran
insists it has information they are still alive.
   President Bush has said he will not make deals for captives.
   Israel said it would not agree to any deal unless it involves
freeing three servicemen captured by Shiite groups in southern
Lebanon in 1986.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0029 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 1413EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Scowcroft-Fang     07-08 0400</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Scowcroft-Fang,390</SECOND>
<HEAD>Scowcroft Defends China Mission</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GUY DARST</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HOUSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   National security adviser Brent Scowcroft on
Sunday agreed with a leading Chinese dissident that Scowcroft's
controversial secret mission to Beijing last year was a failure, at
least so far.
   ``I think it's premature to say whether the mission was
successful or not,'' Scowcroft said on CNN's ``Newsmaker Sunday''
television program. ``Within the time frame we hoped for, it was
unsuccessful.''
   Scowcroft was responding to a statement broadcast earlier Sunday
from Fang Lizhi, a Chinese astrophysicist who spent more than a
year in the U.S. Embassy in Beijing following China's brutal
suppression of pro-democracy demonstrations last summer in
Tiananmen Square.
   Lizhi, who recently was allowed to go to Britain, said ``I do
not believe that the sending of a special presidential envoy last
December was a successful tactic.''
   Lizhi, in a prerecorded interview broadcast on NBC-TV's ``Meet
the Press'' program, called for close monitoring of China's human
rights record.
   ``There still remain a large number of students held in custody
or in prison,'' he said. ``Some have already been sentenced. These
cases still need to be solved. Moreover, we must not forget those
who have been imprisoned now for more than 10 years, people like
Wei Jing-Sheng.''
   In the wake of the Tiananmen, President Bush announced sanctions
and suspended high-level contacts with the Chinese government. But
he secretly sent Scowcroft to Beijing, saying later it was
important for China not to feel isolated.
   At one point Secretary of State James A. Baker III denied there
had been any such missions, and later was forced to admit he had
lied.
   Scowcroft, here with Bush in advance of Monday's opening of the
Western economic summit, said China's transition to an open
society, interrupted by Tiananmen, ``has perhaps resumed if you
call the release of Fang Lizhi part of that process.''
   But Scowcroft said the administration still wanted China to
``release all those who were peaceful protesters, stop jamming the
Voice of America and resume the course they were on.''
   ``Let's not put those as conditions'' for the United States to
relax its remaining sanctions against China, he added. ``But there
are strong limits as to what the United States can do'' if China
does not change.
   Bush on Saturday said he would not stand in the way of a planned
$5.2 billion loan from Japan to China.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0030 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 1419EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brite--CherryPitSpit     07-08 0279</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brite--Cherry Pit Spit,0287</SECOND>
<HEAD>Reigning Pit-Spitter Licks Competition</HEAD>
<DATELINE>EAU CLAIRE, Mich. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Rick ``Pellet Gun'' Krause did it again
_ hawking a seed 50 feet, 8{ inches to win the International Cherry
Pit Spitting Championship.
   Krause captured his eighth title Saturday by winning the 17th
annual event at Tree-Mendus Fruit Farm near Eau Claire. On the
women's side, four sisters placed first, second, third and fourth.
   Krause, a 36-year-old substitute school teacher from Sparta, was
the champion spitter in 1980, 1983, 1984, 1985 and every year since
1987. His personal best is 72 feet, 7 inches.
   ``Its just a lot of fun. I like doing crazy things and this
ranks up there,'' he said. The key to a good spit, he added, is a
clean pit.
   Krause's prizes included apples off a tree at Tree-Mendus for a
year, a weekend at a hotel, a dinner and $10 worth of gas.
   While this year's spit of a tart cherry pit fell short of his
longest, the victory was the sweetest. His 12-year-old son, Brian,
won the youth division with a spit of 35 feet, 3 inches.
   Fred Fernau, 21, of Stevensville finished second with a spit of
48 feet, 5 inches.
   It was a family affair in the women's division, won by Irene
Grambow, 28, of East Lansing at 30 feet, 5 inches. Her sister,
Eileen Meeks of Brown City, was second at 30 feet, 2 inches;
another sister, Dee Ann Henn of Okemos, was third at 28 feet, 9
inches; and sister Helene Mueller of Burton was fourth, 26 feet 4
inches.
   Contest organizers supplied a rack for pit spitters with
dentures, to catch the flying teeth.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0031 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 1420EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p AM-RunoffSuit     07-08 0621</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Runoff Suit,0640</SECOND>
<HEAD>Eight Days Before Primaries, Judge to Hear Arguments in Runoff
Challenge</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Georgia Governor, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARC RICE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ATLANTA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Just eight days before Georgia's primary
elections, a federal judge will hear arguments Monday in a lawsuit
alleging that the state's majority-vote rule is racially
discriminatory.
   A group of black legislators and civil rights officials, led by
state Rep. Tyrone Brooks, has challenged the system that requires a
runoff if one candidate fails to receive a majority of the votes
cast in elections for state offices.
   The class action suit seeks to immediately impose a plurality
system, whereby the candidate receiving the most votes would be the
winner even if he or she got fewer than half. A hearing is
scheduled before U.S. District Judge Richard C. Freeman.
   If imposed before the primary, such a method would be seen as
helping former Atlanta mayor Andrew Young in his bid against four
others in the Democratic gubernatorial race.
   Young, trying to become Georgia's first black governor, is
thought to have a better chance to win a plurality on July 17 than
a majority in a two-candidate runoff. Current polls put him roughly
equal with the leading white candidate, with each getting about 30
percent support.
   Young, however, is not backing the lawsuit.
   The state has argued that the 1964 law, passed in the wake of
national civil rights legislation, was not rooted in racism but
instead represents a longstanding commitment to the concept of
majority voting.
   Attorney General Michael Bowers chraged, in briefs filed last
month, that the suit was an attempt to ``manipulate'' the
governor's race.
   Laughlin McDonald, an American Civil Liberties Union attorney
representing the plaintiffs in the case, said he will present
evidence that the Georgia system was established as a way to
maintain the power of the state's white Democratic leadership and
disenfranchise blacks.
   ``The white Democratic leadership ... regards it as very
critical,'' he said Friday. ``If you go to a plurality, it will
drive out the white majority.''
   Lawyers in the attorney general's office who are involved in the
suit did not return phone calls for comment late last week.
   Brooks said Friday that legislative debate at the time of the
bill's passage focused on its impact on blacks, and that the
results of elections in ensuing years have provided ample evidence
that the majority requirement discourages black candidates.
   ``We're going to do our best to demonstrate to Judge Freeman
that when the statute was enacted the intent was to keep blacks out
of office,'' Brooks said.
   ``We intend to show that because of the runoff we've been kept
at the bare minimum of the elected officials,'' he said.
   Brooks brushed aside criticism that the suit was timed to aid
Young. He said he has been trying to eliminate the runoff system
since 1984 but has been turned back by his fellow lawmakers.
   ``No matter when you file it, it's going to impact on some
election cycle,'' Brooks said. ``We have elections every two years.
We didn't see any reason not to file it this year.''
   McDonald rejected the notion that the concept of majority voting
was an American tradition.
   ``To say that it is American and constitutional is simply not
so,'' he said. ``The Bill of Rights says that minorities do have
rights.''
   If there were strict adherence to majority voting, he said, ``we
would never have had desegregated schools because that's not what
the majority in the states wanted.''
   The state has argued that the case should be dismissed, or moved
to another judicial circuit, because Brooks has another suit
pending against the state's system of electing Superior Court
judges. The state contends two cases overlap.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0032 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 1425EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Obit-Cullen     07-08 0446</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Cullen,0462</SECOND>
<HEAD>Game Show Host Bill Cullen Dies At 70</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Bill Cullen, a television personality and
game show host whose career spanned such hits as ``I've Got a
Secret,'' ``The Price is Right'' and ``The $25,000 Pyramid,'' has
died of lung cancer at age 70.
   Cullen, who died Saturday at his home in Bel Air, appeared on
radio and television game shows from 1944 to 1988,
   With his crew cut and heavy-frame glasses, he became a familiar
face as a panelist on CBS's ``I've Got A Secret'' from 1952 to
1967. He also was host of the original ``Price is Right'' from 1957
to 1964 on NBC and later on ABC.
   ``Bill was the ultimate host,'' said colleague Dick Clark. ``He
had great humor, intelligence and humanity. Most of all he had the
great talent of making his job look easy.''
   ``He was the best,'' said Clark, who was master of ceremonies
for ``The $10,000 Pyramid,'' while Cullen was host of the nighttime
version, ``The $25,000 Pyramid.''
   ``He certainly created the yardstick of professionalism by which
all other MCs could follow,'' said Cullen's manager, George Spota.
   Cullen's game show resume also includes ``Three on a Match,''
``Pass the Buck,'' ``To Tell the Truth'' and ``The Joker's Wild.''
   He made the cover of the national edition of TV Guide seven
times between 1954 and 1984, including twice in one month in 1964.
   Cullen was working in a garage in Pittsburgh in 1939 when he got
his first job in broadcasting as an unpaid assistant disc jockey.
He later became a regular announcer earning $25 a week.
   In 1943, Cullen moved to New York and became a staff announcer
with the CBS Radio Network. A year later, he became announcer for
the ``Winner Take All'' game show.
   Cullen's first television game show was ``Give and Take,'' a
1952 question-and-answer show on which he was co-host with John
Reed King.
   ``He's spent more time on broadcast air, radio and television,
than anyone else in the business,'' said Spota.
   Bob Stewart, who produced ``The Price Is Right'' for eight
years, said Cullen was in a class by himself.
   ``Professionally, nobody I ever worked with was his peer,'' said
Stewart, a friend for 35 years. ``There was nobody like him nor
will there every be. Off camera, he was the same kind of lovable,
fun, mischievous guy you saw on television.''
   ``I hope never to be a big, really big, star,'' Cullen told The
New York Times in 1958. ``I may never be one in any case. But I've
seen too many big names burn themselves out on television.''
   Cullen is survived by his wife, Ann.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0033 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 1434EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-WhitherAlbania?     07-08 0722</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Whither Albania?,0741</SECOND>
<HEAD>Alabanian Leadership Appears Unshaken</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Albania, Bjt</HEAD>
<HEAD>AP News Analysis</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GEORGE JAHN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>VIENNA, Austria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Albanian leader Ramiz Alia appears
unshaken in his determination to keep tight control over his
limited reform program, despite unprecedented popular resistance to
decades of harsh Communist rule.
   The crisis began when thousands of discontented Albanians
crowded foreign embassies hoping for a chance to begin new lives in
the West. Others took to the streets of the capital, Tirana, in
anti-government protests.
   But by Sunday, the turmoil generated by the asylum-seekers had
not escalated into the kind of unrest that toppled Communists
elsewhere in Europe.
   Potentially more threatening to the regime was dissatisfaction
with its slow, tentative approach to changing the centrally
controlled economy, which has caused Albania's standard of living
to lag far behind its neighbors'.
   Alia began tinkering with the Stalinist economic, political and
social systems he inherited even before the rush on foreign
embassies in Tirana.
   Under a reform program begun in May and recently accelerated,
citizens who previously had no hope of traveling abroad are now
entitled to passports. A ban on religion has been lifted, the death
penalty has been abolished for defectors and modest economic
retooling has been promised.
   The country, long considered the hermit of Europe for its
isolationist policies, has signaled willingness to restore ties
with both superpowers. It plans to join the 35-nation Conference on
Security and Cooperation in Europe after being the only nation on
the continent to boycott it.
   But Alia has offered far fewer reforms than Communists in other
Eastern European countries such as Hungary and Bulgaria, who
voluntarily abolished their monopoly on power and introduced
multiparty democracies.
   Alia told a special session of the Communist Party Central
Committee called in part to deal with the embassy crisis that the
party would remain supreme.
   ``What is of fundamental importance is the fact that the masses
should be led by the party,'' Alia told the meeting over the
weekend. His comments avoided any reference to even limited
political plurality.
   While the Central Committee approved personnel changes in the
party and government, Alia's authority appeared unshaken. Several
longtime Politburo members were replaced with younger men believed
closer to his way thinking.
   The naming of Hekuran Isai as interior and police minister,
however, seemed to indicate a determination to deal harshly with
any challenge from the street of the kind that ended Communist rule
in Romania, Czechoslovakia and East Germany.
   Isai had held the post under Enver Hoxha, the founder of
Communist Albania and Alia's predecessor. The choice disappointed
those hoping for Central Committee appointees not associated with
past repression.
   Police sealed off embassy row over the weekend from new
asylum-seekers, but it appeared they had been ordered to keep a low
profile and avoid further street confrontations as the leadership
sought to weather the storm.
   As part of that strategy, authorities agreed Saturday to let the
more than 5,000 asylum-seekers emigrate under foreign supervision.
The leaders clearly hoped that sealing the embassy district and
providing free access to passports would halt another rush on the
diplomatic missions and end the threat of unrest.
   Alia also announced limited economic reforms to the Central
Committee meeting calculated to alleviate low living standards,
lack of luxury items and shortages of staples _ all of which have
generated widespread dissatisfaction.
   He announced wage increases of as high as 20 percent in some
cases and said tradesmen and shopkeepers could once again work for
themselves, rather than the state. Such moves may be too little too
late, however, particularly under liberalized travel laws allowing
more of the population of 3.2 million to compare their Spartan
existence to life in the West.
   While some of the asylum-seekers appeared motivated by
frustration over political repression, others were clearly
disillusioned by their scramble to make ends meet and ready to risk
all for a better economic life.
   One of the would-be emigres, in a telephone interview with
Hungarian state radio, said he ``just can't make a living'' in
Albania.
   The 28-year-old man said he worked as bricklayer, a chauffeur
and a lathe operator for $60 dollars a month _ not enough to
support his family.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   George Jahn, based in Vienna, has reported on
Eastern European developments for The Associated Press since 1981.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0034 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 1434EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-RescueCrash 1stLd-Writethru   07-08 0132</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Rescue Crash, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0662,0132</SECOND>
<HEAD>Chopper Crashes During Rescue Operation</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: New thruout to CORRECT that chopper crashed Sunday, sted
Saturday.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>PORT MORESBY, Papua New Guinea (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A helicopter en route to
the site of a plane crash slammed into the side of a mountain
Sunday, and the fate of the four people aboard was unknown,
officials said.
   The plane crashed Thursday on a domestic flight, killing eight
of the 12 people aboard. The four suvivors were airlifted off a
mountainside on Saturday, the first day weather conditions
permitted a search.
   Their conditions were not immediately known.
   The rescue helicopter, which was sent to recover bodies and
pieces of wreckage from the downed Douglas Airways plane, crashed
while flying to the plane crash site, 35 miles northwest of Port
Moresby.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0035 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 1453EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Summit-Soviet     07-08 0656</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Summit-Soviet,650</SECOND>
<HEAD>Soviets Looking to West for Credits to Help Reforms</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Summit Rdp, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DEBORAH G. SEWARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Soviet President Mikhail S. Gorbachev is worried
his country cannot make the painful leap from a closely controlled
economic system to a market-driven version without Western help.
   His quest for financial aid will be a major issue at the
seven-nation summit of industrial powers that opens Monday in
Houston.
   But it's a two-part issue: Not only is there the question of how
much the other industrial giants can or want to do, but also the
matter of what a huge cash infusion would accomplish in the Soviet
Union.
   There is no doubt Gorbachev wants help. He has made that clear
in public as well as in recent private letters to President Bush
and British Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher.
   The leaders of West Germany and France are advocating that the
industrial powers approve aid worth $15 billion to bolster reforms
and help Moscow meet payments to foreign firms. The Soviet Union
traditionally has been punctual in meeting payments, but recent
delays have started to erode confidence among foreign investors.
   Bonn already has approved an unconditional loan of $3.1 billion,
and Chancellor Helmut Kohl is apparently growing impatient with
opposition from other leaders to the Soviet aid plan.
   Bush so far has been reluctant to agree to a massive aid program
until Soviet authorities move more decisively from a planned to a
market economy.
   Estimates of how much money would begin to stabilize the Soviet
economy range from $5 billion to $20 billion _ colossal compared to
what Eastern European countries have received to restructure their
economies, but modest given the size of the Soviet economy and its
relatively small foreign debt.
   Moscow's balance-of-payment deficit now tops $2 billion, nearly
half it owed to West German companies. Part of the West German
credit is expected to be used to pay overdue bills.
   Inability to keep food stores stocked has already forced Moscow
to spend an extra 3 billion rubles ($500 million) on food imports.
   And more aid is thought necessary if the Soviet Union is going
to leap from a centrally planned to a market economy.
   Without Western cash, the move to the market could inflict
hardship on the population and more social pressure on Gorbachev.
   Premier Nikolai I. Ryzhkov told the Supreme Soviet parliament in
late May that the consumer market was ``destitute.''
   Ryzhkov, presenting a plan for what he called a ``regulated
market economy,'' warned that if trends continued ``many crucial
decisions, unpopular as they are, will meet an even more embittered
response.''
   The Soviet economy is plagued by inflation and a huge budget
deficit. In the first four months of this year, ethnic unrest and
strikes caused the loss of an estimated 10 million man-hours.
   Pro-market reforms are likely to drop production further as
unprofitable businesses go bankrupt.
   Still, there is hope that Western aid could help keep store
shelves stocked and bolster people's faith that reforms will
improve their lives.
   Soviet reformers are stymied not only by consumer shortages, but
by a 70-year legacy of central planning that allowed only limited
forms of individual enterprise. They are also hampered by decades
of propaganda portraying capitalist economies as ridden with
poverty, unemployment and vicious competition.
   Gosplan, the central agency responsible for running the economy,
has concluded outside aid is needed, but has not made public a
blueprint for how to spend Western money.
   Delegates to the 28th Communist Party Congress under way in
Moscow have shown deep hostility to private property and individual
ownership of factories, although some delegates did support Western
help.
   ``Aid is a good idea. There are big changes in our economy, but
we can't seem to set things straight. Help could make things better
and we should accept this offer,'' said delegate Nikolai V. Mikhug,
a worker from a tube-rolling factory in the Ural Mountains.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0036 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 1502EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Ethiopia-OAU     07-08 0471</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Ethiopia-OAU,0486</SECOND>
<HEAD>Communism's Collapse in Europe to Overshadow African Summit</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN EDLIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ADDIS ABABA, Ethiopia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   African leaders open an annual
summit meeting Monday that will be overshadowed by the collapse of
communism in Eastern Europe.
   Noting political shake-ups from the Baltic to the Balkans, the
51-member Organization of African Unity ministerial council
resolved that its governments pledge themselves to ``full
democratization'' in a continent dominated by one-party states.
   When they gained independence from European colonial powers,
many African Unity countries adopted political systems like those
entrenched at the time in Eastern Europe.
   ``A permitting political environment which guarantees human
rights and the observance of the rule of law would assure high
standards of probity and accountability on the part of those who
hold public office,'' the ministers declared in a draft statement
for the summit.
   The heads of state meet Monday through Wednesday for their 26th
conference.
   Main issues for discussion will be efforts to end South Africa's
racial policy of apartheid, the member states' foreign debts, the
growing plight of refugees and the Middle East.
   But the winds of change in Eastern Europe ``constitute major
parameters which should govern Africa's collective thinking about
the challenges and options before her in the 1990s and beyond,''
the draft declaration said.
   It was prepared by foreign ministers who set the summit agenda
during a three-day meeting last week.
   On the issue of South Africa, the report welcomes President F.W.
De Klerk's recent reforms. But it also noted that ``those changes
only tinker with the system and fall far short of a common
objective of totally dismantling apartheid.''
   The ministerial council said that until Pretoria commits itself
to abolishing apartheid, the international community must continue
to presure South Africa with economic sanctions.
   The ministers painted a grim picture of an African continent
that is ``disintegrating.''
   Food output is down and population growth up, the draft notes.
Per capita income has plunged and exports have dropped. Standards
of living have fallen in tandem with spending on health, housing,
education and other social services.
   By the end of 1989, foreign debt had swollen to $257 billion.
The ministers proposed that foreign powers restructure their
economies to help poorer nations.
   Apart from events in Eastern Europe, a highlight of the summit
will be an address by Nelson Mandela, deputy president of the
African National Congress guerrilla group that is at the forefront
of efforts to end apartheid in South Africa.
   Mandela, 71, who was freed from a South African prison in March,
is expected to thank African leaders for supporting the ANC during
the 27 years he was incarcerated.
   Lask week in Uganda, Mandela and three African presidents
discussed proposals aimed at hastening an end to South Africa's
white rule. They said they would present the proposals to the
summit.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0037 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 1538EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Poland     07-08 0620</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Poland,0642</SECOND>
<HEAD>Workers Call Solidarity Legislators to Task</HEAD>
<NOTE>With LaserPhoto NY5</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By JOHN DANISZEWSKI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WARSAW, Poland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Lech Walesa and Solidarity's rank and file
accused the trade union's Parliament members of forgetting their
roots Sunday at a meeting in the Gdansk Shipyard where the labor
group was born.
   The six-hour meeting, which drew more than 2,000 workers and
their families, was attended by Solidarity parliamentary leader
Bronislaw Geremek and 160 of the lawmakers swept to office by union
endorsement last year.
   Prime Minister Tadeusz Mazowiecki, under increasing attack over
the government's painful economic reform measures, turned down a
request to attend. Instead, he asked workers to come talk with him
Wednesday.
   Held in the workers' hall where the East bloc's first
independent trade union was formed in 1980, the meeting highlighted
the rift between workers in the provinces, and the Solidarity-led
government in Warsaw.
   It took place one day after Mazowiecki and Walesa met at a
secluded monastery outside Warsaw and announced a truce in their
political war over the pace of reforms in Poland.
   But the prime minister remained embattled. Representatives of
Poland's 2.5 million private farmers have given him until Wednesday
to agree to guaranteed minimum farm prices or face a nationwide
road blockade.
   In a partial answer to Walesa's calls for faster political
change, Mazowiecki ousted three former Communists from his Cabinet
Friday and agreed to early parliamentary and presidential elections.
   Only about 100 of the 260-strong Solidarity parliamentary
caucus, known as the Citizens Parliamentary Club, failed to come to
Gdansk to meet with the shipyard workers. Some of those who
rejected the invitation had earlier cited the aggressive tone in
which it was framed.
   About 400 people jammed the hall Sunday and more than 2,000
listened outside over loudspeakers as Walesa addressed the
lawmakers, not mincing words.
   ``Today I hear voices saying, `Who dared to invite the
parliament deputies?'' he said. ``Doesn't this hall have the right
to call you? It has. You started from here.''
   Walesa said Parliament has to be accountable to voters:
   ``The question is whether you are going to be above us ... or
should you first come back and ask what's most important _ not in
your opinion, but in the opinion of those who elected you?''
   He acknowledged the deputies were working ``day and night'' but
said there was a lack of public explanation of their decisions.
   ``One blow from the farmers or the miners will put all those
laws into the wastebasket,'' Walesa said.
   The Solidarity chairman, in his only reference to the talks
Saturday, said he and Mazowiecki discussed how they fell into their
current dispute.
   ``We said bluntly: Because we never talked about what was
supposed to happen after communism, how we would accomplish the
second stage, how we would go along with Poland without forgetting
where we came from,'' he said. ``Today we must return to the
roots.''
   Workers from the Baltic port city's three main shipyards invited
Parliament members to tell them workers' complaints about the
10-month-old Solidarity-led government.
   ``The government is late with everything, and ordinary people
feel helpless facing poverty,'' said Zbigniew Lis, leader of the
Solidarity chapter in the Gdansk Shipyard.
   According to Lis, workers want Communists punished for past
economic and political crimes; the elimination of companies created
by the Communist elite from state property; and a slowdown of the
recession caused by the austerity measures.
   Geremek told the workers it was not surprising they were upset
by the difficulties they face.
   ``Whoever promises there will be a speeding up in public welfare
is speaking an untruth. We are at the beginning of a difficult road
and we must not make any false promises,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0038 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 1544EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p AM-Helms-GanttCommentary     07-08 0405</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Helms-Gantt Commentary,0416</SECOND>
<HEAD>Helms Facing Man He Once Complimented</HEAD>
<DATELINE>RALEIGH, N.C. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   When Sen. Jesse Helms was a television
commentator in the 1960s, he made a flattering assessment of the
first black student to enter Clemson University.
   Now the conservative Republican is being challenged in his
re-election bid by that same man _ Democrat Harvey Gantt, former
mayor of Charlotte.
   In 1963, Helms called Gantt sincere in his desire to obtain an
education and praised him for resisting ``the pose of a conquering
hero.''
   Helms heaped praise on Gantt while directing criticism at James
Meredith, who had become the first black to enter the University of
Mississippi a few months earlier, an event that sparked a major
riot.
   Meredith, who was wounded during a freedom march in Mississippi
in 1965, has changed his views markedly since then and today serves
on Helms' Washington staff. He calls integration a ``con job'' and
blames liberals for blacks' social problems.
   In his commentary 27 years ago, Helms said Gantt ``has
demonstrated that he knows a thing or two about human nature, and,
more important to our way of thinking, that he is sincere.'' The
editorial was broadcast Jan. 29, 1963, on WRAL-TV in Raleigh, The
News and Observer of Raleigh reported Sunday.
   ``He has stoutly resisted the pose of a conquering hero for the
forces of integration,'' Helms said. ``He simply wants, he says, to
be an architect _ and Clemson is the only college in South Carolina
that can teach him how to be one.
   ``He has rejected the fanfare and trappings of the NAACP. He has
turned away from the liberal press and television networks which
would glorify him. He has refused to make pompous speeches and
statements.''
   ``If ever a man put his best foot forward, Harvey Gantt has done
so. His conduct will not cause South Carolinians to relish court
orders relating to integration. But he has done a great deal,
probably more than he himself realizes, to establish respectful
comunications across sensitive barriers in human relations.''
   Helms said Gantt and Meredith were ``a study in contrasts.''
   ``There is a difference in James Meredith and Harvey Gantt _
Meredith as a man handpicked as the showpiece of forced
integration, Meredith as a man who never quite persuaded anybody
that he was really interested in an education, Meredith as a man
constantly and piously parading before the microphone and
television cameras,'' Helms said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0039 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 1550EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-WeatherRadar     07-08 0472</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Weather Radar,0487</SECOND>
<HEAD>Test Shows Weather Radar Malfunctions _ Report</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CLEVELAND (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A test found the National Weather Service's new
computerized radar storm detection system breaks down frequently
and is less reliable than the 33-year-old system now in use, a
newspaper reported Sunday.
   Results of the six-month test rate the 1957-vintage radar system
as 10 times more reliable than the new equipment, called NEXRAD,
The (Cleveland) Plain Dealer reported Sunday.
   The test results were obtained under the Freedom of Information
Act by the union representing weather service employees, the
National Weather Service Employees Organization, it said.
   The test was conducted by the Air Force from March to August
1989 in Oklahoma. The 118-page report said the new radar
malfunctioned every 1.9 days, while the existing radar, called
WSR-57, breaks down on average every 14 days.
   The Air Force testers said failures ``critically degraded the
effectiveness of NEXRAD'' because they occurred during periods when
forecasters especially depend upon radar to detect severe storm
patterns.
   ``Many times in severe weather episodes, when the operators
needed the system to support critical warning operations, the
system was not available,'' the Air Force said.
   The testers said the WSR-57 has ``a demonstrated reliability
approximately 10 times greater than the demonstrated reliability of
the NEXRAD tested.''
   Some 120 NEXRAD units, which can measure wind speed and
direction and rain volume in a storm, are the centerpiece of a $1
billion modernization of the weather service scheduled for the
1990s.
   William Read, head of a team investigating the weather service's
actions during the June 14 storm that caused flash flooding in
eastern Ohio and killed 26, said the conventional radar at
Akron-Canton was unable to determine the storm's severity in time
to post a warning.
   Don Sarreals, special assistant to the NEXRAD program office,
said the weather service is committed to modernization despite the
test results.
   ``The program is supported and we are proceeding to install the
radar,'' Sarreals said. ``We're making progress as rapidly as we
can. When you're building something for the first time, you
encounter various obstacles.''
   He said the first operational NEXRAD will be installed in
October near Oklahoma City.
   ``It's going to go through a vigorous testing period before it's
turned over to the government and commissioned,'' Sarreals said.
   Most problems have been encountered in the computers that
interpret weather data obtained by the radar unit, he said.
   ``The key to the thing is the computer, that's what makes it
unique,'' Sarreals said. ``It's the computer that can dig into the
data.''
   In the eastern Ohio flooding, meteorologists were unable to
determine the potential rainfall in the thunderstorms appearing on
conventional radar, Sarreals said.
   ``You have to make estimates for rainfall now, which are
basically done by humans,'' he said. ``A computer with a high-speed
processor will dig into that with NEXRAD.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0040 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 1550EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-DickTracy     07-08 0180</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Dick Tracy,0185</SECOND>
<HEAD>KCAL Pulls `Dick Tracy' Cartoon Off Air</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Under pressure from Asian and Hispanic
groups, a television station has decided to pull the 1961 ``Dick
Tracy'' cartoon series because two characters are considered ethnic
stereotypes.
   The Disney-owned KCAL had scheduled a 13-week run of the
cartoons to coincide with Disney's release last month of the ``Dick
Tracy'' movie.
   The series ran four weeks before Asian and Hispanic groups
complained about the characters Jo Jitsu and Go Go Gomez, two
detectives who helped Tracy fight crime.
   Jo Jitsu has buck teeth, squints through glasses and
mispronounces the letter ``r.'' Go Go Gomez wears a sombrero and
takes frequent siestas.
   ``It should have been obvious from the very beginning that the
show was offensive,'' said Raul Ruiz, a professor of Chicano
studies at Cal State Northridge.
   KCAL said in a statement that the series had been reviewed
before it was broadcast and was not deemed offensive because the
characters were positive images.
   ``It's not our intention to offend anybody,'' said KCAL program
director Matt Cooperstein.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0041 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 1552EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Summit-NewWorld Bjt   07-08 0830</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Summit-New World, Bjt,840</SECOND>
<HEAD>After Cold War, US Finds Economic Power Matters Most</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP News Analysis</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARTIN CRUTSINGER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Economics Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HOUSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The United States, undisputed leader of the free
world for four decades of Cold War, is adjusting to a new era when
economic power counts more than military might.
   The adjustment process will be nowhere more apparent than in
Houston as President Bush plays host beginning Monday for the
annual economic summit meeting of the world's seven richest
industrial democracies.
   Where the Western allies were once willing to let the United
States set the agenda, the summit countries seem willing, even
eager, to chart their own courses now that America's nuclear
umbrella no longer seems crucial.
   ``1990 is the first year after the end of the Cold War,'' said
Michael Mandelbaum, an international expert with the Council on
Foreign Relations. ``It is a time when the American nuclear surplus
will be less and less important and the American fiscal deficit
will be more important.''
   America is still the wealthiest of the wealthy when measured in
terms of the $5 trillion in goods and services it produces
annually. But Japan, now second with a $3 trillion economy, has
been rapidly closing the gap. Some economists believe it could
surpass the United States by the year 2000.
   Japan has already replaced the United States as the world's
largest creditor country, reflecting its global investment clout.
   America, which began the 1980s as the world's largest creditor
country, is now the biggest debtor. The transformation occurred
largely because Americans transferred billions of dollars into
foreign hands to pay for imported cars, television sets and other
consumer goods.
   Forced now to rely on foreigners to finance its economy to the
tune of about $10 billion a month, the new economic reality has
spurred great domestic debate over whether the United States is
losing control of its destiny to foreigners.
   Bush finds himself at odds with a number of the summit countries
on a variety of issues at this year's summit, ranging from aid to
the Soviet Union to cleaning up the global environment _ and trying
to keep a nasty battle over farm subsidies from scuttling an effort
to reform the world trading system.
   If the farm subsidy fight is not resolved, some analysts fear
that the Cold War could very well be followed by a global trade war
as more and more countries fall to squabbling over trade imbalances
and erect protectionist barriers to keep imports out.
   ``As the compelling drive of the Soviet threat no long forces
the West to work together, the economic forces could drive them
apart,'' said Robert Hormats, a vice president at Goldman Sachs and
a former U.S. ``sherpa,'' the top aide who prepares the summit
agenda for the president.
   The huge U.S. budget deficit has long been a sore point with
America's summit partners who contend that America's profligate
borrowing needs have driven up world interest rates. Now that U.S.
defense spending is no longer seen as critical to keeping world
peace, the size of the budget deficit is likely to be even more of
an irritant.
   Just before the summit, Bush reversed his opposition to tax
increases as a way of solving the deficit problem. While that
change of heart drew catcalls from conservatives in the United
States, many foreign officials have breathed a sigh of relief.
   They view getting the U.S. budget under control as a critical
step in solving some of America's more nettlesome economic problems
as well as providing Bush with sorely needed resources to play a
more active role on the world stage.
   Last year, for the first time, Japan replaced the United States
as the world's largest donor of official foreign aid.
   The U.S. government, constrained by the budget deficit, has
provided what many considered to be rather modest amounts to help
in the economic transformation of former communist countries in
Europe.
   Some foreign leaders see America's budget problems as the real
reason Bush is dragging his feet on giving direct economic support
for Soviet President Mikhail S. Gorbachev's reform efforts.
   Bush is coming to the summit with one new initiative, seeking
support from the other leaders for a U.S. plan to pour economic aid
into fledgling democracies in Latin America _ similar to the
assistance being offered former communist countries in Europe.
   That Bush proposal has been seen as a hopeful sign that the
United States, while no longer able to dominate the economic
agenda, will not draw inward in the coming decade.
   ``Our credibility has been damaged by unwillingness to provide
even modest resources to support democratization in Eastern Europe
and Latin America,'' said C. Fred Bergsten, head of the Institute
for International Economics, a Washington-based research group.
``Budget correction would enable the United States to become a
serious global player and world leader again.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Martin Crutsinger has covered economic issues in
Washington for The Associated Press since 1984.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0042 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 1612EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-CoupleSlayings     07-08 0415</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Couple Slayings,0425</SECOND>
<HEAD>Police Suspect Serial Killer in Virginia Slayings</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NORFOLK, Va. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The slayings of six young people and the
disappearance of another young couple in eastern Virginia may have
been the work of a serial killer, police said.
   All four unsolved cases involve the slaying or disappearance of
young people who were traveling by car in isolated areas. One crime
has occurred annually between April and October since 186, but none
has occurred this year.
   ``They're pretty much convinced it's a serial killer,'' said
Mark Johnson, a College of William and Mary police detective who
has investigated the 1986 slayings of a student at the college and
her friend.
   ``We're just waiting for September or October because we all
agree that's when it will happen again,'' Johnson said.
   ``Basically, they think it's a serial killer,'' agreed Margie
Lauer, whose 21-year-old son, Daniel, was one of the slaying
victims. Mrs. Lauer said FBI and state police agents have told her
in recent weeks ``they felt it was all connected.''
   ``We were expecting something like this,'' Kathy Knobling,
stepmother of another slaying victim, said Sunday after accounts of
the police theory were published in area newspapers. She is a
spokeswoman for a group of the victims' relatives and friends.
   The Virginian-Pilot and The Ledger-Star newspapers, in their
combined Sunday edition, quoted an unidentified souce as saying
that the killer could be someone disguised as a police officer, or
even an actual police officer.
   Here are details of the four cases:
   _In October 1986, Rebecca A. Dowski, 21, a William and Mary
student from Poughkeepsie, N.Y., and Cathleen M. Thomas, 27, a
Virginia Beach stockbroker, were found strangled and stabbed in
Miss Thomas' car along the parkway.
   _In September 1987, Robin M. Edwards, 14, of Newport News and
David L. Knobling, 20, of Hampton were found shot to death on their
first date t Ragged Island Wildlife Refuge in Isle of Wight County.
   _In April 1988, Keith Call, 20, and Cassandra Hailey, 19, two
Christopher Newport College students, disappeared on their first
date. Call's pickup truck was found abandoned on the parkway.
   _In September 1989, Annamaria Phelps, 18, and Lauer, both of
Amelia County, disappeared on their way to Virginia Beach. Lauer's
car was found at a rest stop on Interstate 64 in New Kent County,
and the couple's bodies were discovered in woods nearby six weeks
later. Miss Phelps died of a knife wound but the cause of Lauer's
death was not determined.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0043 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 1613EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Spain-Nuclear     07-08 0152</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Spain-Nuclear,0157</SECOND>
<HEAD>Accident At Nuclear Power Plant</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TARRAGONA, Spain (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An accident was reported Sunday at a
nuclear power plant south of Barcelona, but a regional official
said there had been no radiation leak and the situation was under
control.
   Tarragona civil governor Ramon Sanchez said the accident at the
Vandellos II plant was caused by a leak of vaporized water in the
primary circuit inside the plant's reactor.
   He said the reactor had been shut off gradually, and later the
plant was disconnected from the national electric network.
   ``There was no radiation leak at any time,'' Sanchez said.
   He said the situation was ``completely under control.''
   The plant, in Vandellos on the Mediterranean coast 93 miles
south of Barcelona, has had a number of accidents since it began
operating in 1987.
   Its sister plant, Vandellos I, was shut down in April due to a
serious fire on Oct. 19.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0044 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 1622EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Chad-Elections 1stLd-Writethru a0674 07-08 0482</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Chad-Elections, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0674,0494</SECOND>
<HEAD>Voters Get Choice for First Time In Chad</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 5 grafs to UPDATE with color, voter registration,
quote; pickup 4th graf pvs, `The 4,000...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By MAHAMAT HISSENE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>N'DJAMENA, Chad (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Voters in war-scarred Chad cast ballots
Sunday in the first contested election since independence in 1960,
but opposition parties remain banned and virtually all candidates
were from the ruling party.
   Voters chose among 436 pro-government candidates for the 123
seats in a new national assembly. Most were from the ruling
National Union for Independence and the Revolution.
   ``Democracy, here we are!'' declared an enthusiastic commentator
on state radio, which reported calm, orderly voting throughout the
country.
   Some polling stations in N'Djamena, the capital, were reported
crowded and others nearly deserted as Chad's 3 million eligible
voters had their first opportunity to pick among political rivals.
   Although opposition parties were barred from the elections, the
campaign was lively and hard-fought. Candidates toured city streets
in vehicles equipped with loudspeakers and wooed voters with offers
of low-priced beer or free sugar. In one N'Djamena district, 26
candidates were competing.
   The 4,000 polling stations spread across the vast, landlocked
nation opened at 6 a.m. local time and were scheduled to close at
midnight. Final results were not expected for at least two days.
   The elections are the product of constitutional reforms approved
by 99 percent of the electorate in a Dec. 10 referendum that also
gave President Hissene Habre another seven-year term.
   Habre voted about in his N'Djamena neighborhood, then told
journalists that Chad was entering ``a phase of democratization.''
   ``I hope these processes will be seen through to completion,''
he said.
   Of the 123 assembly seats, five are reserved for women and will
be allocated on a delayed basis if less than five women win seats
outright. Assembly members will serve five-year terms.
   Few senior members of the government or ruling party are seeking
seats in the assembly, which will replace the recently dissolved
National Consultative Council.
   The council had served as national legislature since 1982, but
its members were appointed by Habre and its powers were limited.
Some council members have questioned whether the new assembly will
have greater authority.
   The three-week campaign ended without any reports of serious
political violence, although the state-controlled press scolded
some candidates for wooing support with gifts or emphasizing clan
allegiances rather than issues.
   Chad has a population of about 5.5 million. It is one of the
world's poorest countries, with an annual per capita income of
$200, and has been engaged in civil war almost continuously since
independence from France three decades ago.
   Habre's government is locked in a struggle with Libyan-backed
rebels who stage raids on border outposts from neighboring Sudan.
   The only previous legislative elections in Chad were in 1962,
but the ruling party put up only one candidate for each seat.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0045 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 1623EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Obit-Drummond     07-08 0463</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Drummond,0478</SECOND>
<HEAD>Pioneer Artificial Heart Recipient Dies At Age 30</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ARTHUR H. ROTSTEIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TUCSON, Ariz. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Pioneer artificial heart recipient Michael
Drummond, who received two artificial hearts and one human heart,
has died of multiple organ failure at age 30, five years after his
first transplant.
   Drummond succumbed Saturday night to overwhelming complications
including a blood infection, kidney failure and lung problems
brought on by a combination of a diseased gallbladder and obesity,
said Dr. Jack G. Copeland.
   Copeland called Drummond ``a pal and a friend and a good
patient.''
   In 1987, when his first artificial heart was presented to the
Smithsonian Institute's National Museum of American History,
Drummond said: ``I guess I am sort of a part of history, but not by
choice. It's possible 100 years from now that the artificial heart
will be as routine as a blood transfusion.''
   Drummond and Copeland set medical history in 1985 when Drummond
became the youngest of six Jarvik-7 artificial heart recipients and
the first to undergo an implant as a bridge to human transplant.
   On Aug. 29, 1985 he was given his Jarvik-7 after a viral
syndrome had caused congestive heart failure and Copeland
determined he had only 48 hours to live.
   After 9{ days on the Jarvik heart, Drummond received the donor
heart of a 19-year-old Texas man who died in a motorcycle crash.
   Drummond recovered fully, including from a minor stroke while on
the Jarvik, and led a normal life for 4{ years, resuming work at a
Phoenix-area grocery.
   But he had been on a downhill course since undergoing emergency
surgery Feb. 3 to remove a gangrenous gallbladder that led to a
severe blood infection, a blood clot in the lungs and an episode of
rejection of his artificial heart.
   Copeland replaced Drummond's failing transplanted heart May 21
with a Symbion J-7-70 artificial heart. Within two days of the
second implant other complications developed, including fluid
retention in the lungs and kidney impairment.
   Drummond, 6-foot-2, weighing 268 pounds with an engaging smile
that offset a quiet, stoic demeanor, ``certainly had the fight,''
said Lisa Slayton, a member of the cardiothoracic intensive care
unit's nursing team.
   She said the nursing team had had a good cry after his death.
``We all took care of Mike like he was our brother. He was like
family.''
   Drummond's father, Clarence, said in a wavering voice Saturday
night, ``We're just grateful that the artificial heart was here for
Mike the first time. He wouldn't have had the 4{ years if he hadn't
had (it).
   ``And even this time, there were still things that Mike wanted
to do, and with the artificial heart he had a shot at it, anyway.
It didn't work out, but he had a shot at it.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0046 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 1640EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People Sub a0679 07-08 0199</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People, Sub, a0679,0201</SECOND>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS last graf of DALLAS-dated 4th item in rdp to delete
reference to Peter, Paul and Mary popularizing song; hit single of
`And When I Die' was by another group, Blood, Sweat and Tears.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>DALLAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Former Lovin' Spoonful member John Sebastian is
planning to join singer-songwriter Laura Nyro next month for a
benefit to save dolpins.
   The Aug. 1 concert will help the Dolphin Project, a Florida
environmental group. The group is working to eliminate abuse of
dolphins in captivity.
   ``Money from the concert will go toward a sanctuary in the
Florida Keys to take abused dolphins and dolphins that have been
stranded on the beach and rehabilitate them back to the sea,'' said
Janie Coleman, one the benefit's organizers.
   Sebastian played with the pioneering folk-rock band the Lovin'
Spoonful in the 1960s, known for such hits as ``Summer in the
City'' and ``Do You Believe in Magic.'' He wrote the music for
several films, including, ``What's Up Tiger Lilly?'' ``The Care
Bears Movie'' and music for the television show, ``Welcome Back,
Kotter.''
   Nyro is known for writing such hits as ``And When I Die,''
``Stoned Soul Picnic'' and ``Eli's Coming.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0047 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 1634EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-SAfrica-Extremists 1stLd-Writethru a0656 07-08 0762</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-SAfrica-Extremists, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0656,0780</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bombings Seen as Emergence of Right-Wing Terrorists</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS grafs 5-6 bgng, `The Sunday...'' with 2 grafs to UPDATE
with government saying nine white extremists under detention.
Pickup 7th graf pvs, `Leaders on...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By BARRY RENFREW</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JOHANNESBURG, South Africa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A wave of bombings and attacks
is widely viewed as the start of a terrorist campaign by right-wing
extremists who want to preserve white rule at any price.
   Government and security officials fear the terrorism will be a
major threat to stability as white and black leaders seek a
peaceful solution to South Africa's centuries-old racial divisions.
The right hopes it can preserve white rule by foiling any peace
talks.
   ``What they are doing is to harm the efforts at reconciliation,
as well as the hopes of a peaceful transition to a new society,''
The Citizen newspaper said in an editorial July 5.
   ``South Africa does not need white terrorists any more than it
needs black terrorists.''
   Minister of Law and Order Adriaan Vlok said Sunday nine white
right-wing whites had been detained without charges in connection
with a series of bombings against anti-apartheid targets that began
on April 12.
   Vlok said all nine had been detained under the Internal Security
Act, which allows for indefinite detention without trial. ``The
people arrested are all supporters of a far-right political
ideology, but cannot thus far be connected to any particular
organization,'' he said.
   Leaders on both sides say right-wing attacks could lead to
general racial violence and undermine the peace effort. Black
leaders say they will be forced to strike back if their people are
hurt by the extremists.
   Some extreme right-wing groups have declared war on President
F.W. de Klerk's government for announcing that it wants to end
apartheid and negotiate a new constitution to share power with
blacks.
   Six bombings in Johannesburg in a week, including an attack July
6 on a black bus station that injured 24 people, are seen as the
first major offensive by the right wing. Other attacks in recent
months included random killings of blacks and attacks on Jewish
temples.
   The terrorism has come at a time when such black nationalist
groups as the African National Congress have all but abandoned
violence.
   Government officials say the right poses a far greater threat
than the armed struggle of the ANC and other black organizations.
The ANC campaign, which began in 1961, was largely ineffective
because of the group's internal problems and the superior strength
of South African forces.
   Terrorism by whites is likely to be much more effective and
dangerous, security officials said. Nearly all white men receive
compulsory military training. Guns and explosives are readily
available to whites and the right has numerous sympathizers in the
police and military, they said.
   It also is much easier for white extremists to operate without
suspicion in a society with apartheid laws that give priviliged
status to whites.
   Extremist white groups have taunted the government and police
with their ability to operate easily and elude capture. One stole
scores of weapons from air force headquarters in Pretoria in April
with inside help.
   ``There is no time to plan a counterrevolution; it is now open
war,'' Piet Rudolph, the group's leader, said in a videotape sent
to newspapers. ``We will use every means at our disposal to fight
the de Klerk government, the overthrow of which is the highest
priority to us.''
   Rudolph has claimed responsibility for bombing two offices of de
Klerk's National Party. An organization calling itself the White
Wolves has claimed responsibility for attacks in Johannesburg.
   Police have not broken any of the extremist underground groups
that have claimed responsibility for bombings and other attacks.
   Officials believe the extreme right consists of only a few
hundred people, but security officials say even a handful of white
terrorists could cause havoc. South African press reports say up to
45 extreme-right groups operate in South Africa.
   Conservatives contend de Klerk has no right to end apartheid,
and they demand creation of a state for whites only.
   Several large right-wing political groups have been forming
private armies. The Afrikaner Resistance Movement and similar
groups deny responsibility for the terrorism, but regularly display
their well-armed ``commandos'' or military units.
   Leaders of the right claim South Africa is rushing toward a race
war and that thousands of whites are flocking to their movement.
   ``It will be a holy war,'' Afrikaner Resistance leader Eugene
TerreBlanche said at a recent display of men in Nazi-style
uniforms. ``We know we are heading for a confrontation.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0048 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 1653EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Soviet-Lithuania     07-08 0370</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Lithuania,0380</SECOND>
<HEAD>Soviet Premier to Oversee Early Talks with Lithuania</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Soviet Premier Nikolai I. Ryzhkov will head a
commission to prepare negotiations with Lithuania on granting the
Baltic republic independence, a Lithuanian government spokesman
said Sunday.
   Czeslovas Jurshenas, a spokesman for Prime Minister Kazimiera
Prunskiene and a deputy to the Lithuanian Parliament, said
Lithuania was preparing documents to present at preliminary talks
to set up formal negotiations on the republic's quest to separate
from the Soviet Union.
   Prunskiene told Lithuanian TV viewers on Saturday that she had
spoken by telephone with Ryzhkov. She said he had shown
understanding for three major demands that Lithuania had for the
period leading to formal negotiations, Jurshenas said.
   The spokesman said in a telephone interview that Lithuania wants
Moscow to suspend draft requirements for Lithuanians into the
Soviet army, although any Lithuanian who wanted to join was free to
do so.
   The Baltic republic is also demanding that the Soviet Union
permit normal contact with the outside world, lift travel
restrictions at the one border crossing with Poland and consider
opening a second one, he said.
   Finally, Vilnius wants Moscow to ease the restrictions it
imposed on foreign travelers, especially officials, after Lithuania
declared its independence on March 11, he said.
   Jurshenas also said that Vilnius would like a pledge from Moscow
that the Soviet Union will not interfere with Lithuania's efforts
to establish direct contacts with other Soviet republics.
   Lithuania had been seeking to get supplies from other Soviet
republics without Moscow's authorization after a blockade was
imposed on almost all oil, most natural gas and numerous other
items on April 18.
   But the Lithuanian Supreme Council, or parliament, on June 29
accepted a compromise which traded a 100-day moratorium on the
declaration of independence for an immediate end to the blockade
and the start of negotiations.
   Jurshenas said preliminary talks could start within 10 days.
   Lithuania, an independent nation between the two World Wars, was
forcibly annexed to the Soviet Union by dictator Josef Stalin in
1940 along with neighboring Latvia and Estonia. Those republics are
also seeking to secede from the Soviet Union, but they have
proceeded at a slower pace than Lithuania in breaking with Moscow.

</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0049 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 1654EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Wimbledon-Newspage     07-08 0282</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Wimbledon-Newspage,0290</SECOND>
<HEAD>Stefan Edberg Defeats Boris Becker for Wimbledon Championship</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WIMBLEDON, England (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Sweden's Stefan Edberg beat Boris
Becker of West Germany in a five-set epic Sunday to capture his
second men's tennis championship at Wimbledon.
   A service winner completed an the final on Centre Court, which
ended 6-2, 6-2, 3-6, 3-6, 6-4. Edberg came back from a 1-3 deficit
in the final set to win.
   It was the first five-set men's championship at Wimbledon since
Jimmy Connors beat fellow American John McEnroe 3-6, 6-3, 6-7, 7-6,
6-4 in 1982.
   This was the third consecutive meeting between the two stars for
the Wimbledon championship. Becker, the defending champion, was
playing for his fourth title in six years. Edberg won the title two
years ago.
   In the first two sets, completed in less than an hour, Edberg
looked invincible and Becker nearly invisible. But Becker would not
give up easily, picking up his game and taking the momentum in the
third and fourth sets.
   It was only the second time in his career that Becker has come
back from two sets down to tie a match, then lose. The last time
was also to Edberg in the French Open semifinals last year. Edberg
won 6-3, 6-4, 5-7, 3-6, 6-2.
   As the Swede won Wimbledon for the second time in three years,
he thrust his fists in the air and smiled broadly.
   He and Becker embraced at the net, then Edberg took off his
shirt and heaved it into the stands.
   Becker sat on his chair, looking stunned. He said later if he
had just been able to extend his 3-1 lead in the final set, ``It
would be a different story.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0050 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 1710EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Summit-Cuba     07-08 0288</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Summit-Cuba,290</SECOND>
<HEAD>Soviet Official Says Aid to Cuba Will ``Fade Away''</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Summit Rdp, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HOUSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Soviet official said Sunday his nation will
gradually end the financial aid to Cuba that the Bush
administration says must stop before Moscow gets any U.S. economic
support.
   Gennadi Gerasimov, spokesman for the Soviet Foreign Ministry,
said on CBS' ``Face the Nation'' that subsidies for Fidel Castro's
Marxist government will ``fade away, but not tomorrow.''
   Gerasimov, speaking from Moscow, did not elaborate on plans for
the aid, which he called a ``hidden subsidy'' based mainly on
paying higher than market prices for Cuban sugar and giving Havana
a break on its purchases of Soviet oil.
   ``This is the hidden subsidy, not just cash,'' he said. ``This
is our obligation.''
   Other senior Soviet officials have said in recent weeks that aid
to foreign nations, including Cuba, would be reassessed, although
Moscow has not made an explicit public commitment to any reductions.
   The question of Western financial assistance to Moscow is
expected to be a major subject of debate at the seven-nation
economic summit that opens in Houston on Monday.
   Secretary of State James A. Baker III, interviewed Sunday in
Houston on ABC's ``This Week With David Brinkley,'' said the
Soviet-Cuba situation was one reason President Bush is unwilling to
provide direct aid to Moscow.
   ``We still have major problems with Soviet assistance to Cuba,''
Baker said.
   He added, however, that the administration saw indications that
internal Soviet economic pressures eventually would force a cut in
aid to communist nations.
   ``The Soviets know they are going to have to start pulling
back,'' he said.
   Baker said Moscow spends about $15 billion a year in support of
Third World communist countries.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0051 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 1727EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-EGermany-Terrorism     07-08 0341</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-EGermany-Terrorism,0353</SECOND>
<HEAD>East German Communists Linked With Terrorists</HEAD>
<DATELINE>EAST BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   East Germany's deposed Communist leadership
maintained links with any known terrorist group that would help
destabilize Western nations, the country's interior minister said
in an interview released Sunday.
   Before their ouster last fall, the Communist leaders were
willing to deal with ``all terrorist groups known to us,''
Peter-Michael Diestel told the West German newspaper Die Welt.
   Specifically, the now-disbanded Ministry for State Security, or
Stasi as it is known in German, ``maintained at least informal
contacts'' with the Basque separatist group ETA and the Irish
Republican Army, which seeks to overthrow British rule over
Northern Ireland, Diestel said.
   Die Welt's interview with the conservative politician was to be
published in its Monday edition. An advance text was made available
by the paper on Sunday.
   Diestel spoke after the recent arrests in East Germany of eight
alleged Red Army Faction terrorists wanted for attacks in West
Germany.
   The eight had reportedly been given new identities and sanctuary
by the Stasi, possibly with the knowledge of former Communist Party
chief Erich Honecker and Stasi head Erich Mielke.
   One of the Red Army Faction suspects, Susanne Albrecht, gave
herself up to West German police and reportedly promised to speak
out on the group's structure and earlier terrorist attacks.
   Diestel, who promised further disclosures on East Germany's
former links with international terrorism next week, said, ``We
have arrested more people than you are aware of.''
   He refused to specify whether those were also Red Army Faction
members, or whether any of the detainees were still being held.
   But he did say that in some cases, East Germany's statute of
limitations meant suspects had to be released, while in others
there was insufficient proof.
   Speaking of the former government, Diestel said that ``nothing
was too dirty for them in their political deliberations.''
   ``We hope very much that these weren't contacts aimed at aiding
and abetting international terrorism,'' he said.
   The hard-line Communist regime was ousted in a peaceful popular
revolution late last year.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0052 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 1715EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-WeatherpageWeather     07-08 0432</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Weatherpage Weather,0446</SECOND>
<HEAD>Thunderstorm Damage In Minnesota</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Strong thunderstorms battered Minnesota on Sunday, while rain
also was scattered from the Southwest to the Midwest and over the
Southeast, and temperatures were high across much of the nation.
   Thunderstorms generating wind up to 70 mph damaged buildings,
uprooted trees, knocked down power lines and flattened fields
around Minnesota but no injuries were reported.
   Don Stob, deputy sheriff in Mille Lacs County, said the worst
damage in the county was reported by a farmer about 3 miles
southeast of Milaca, north of Minneapolis and about 33 miles
northeast of St. Cloud.
   ``He had 13 trees down in his yard, a power line down, the roof
off his corn crib and some shingles off his barn. And one of his
hay fields was flattened,'' Stob said.
   Trees were uprooted and power lines torn down all around
Minneapolis, said Mike McCosky, a foreman with the city streets
department. But no major thoroughfares were blocked, he said.
Northern States Power Co. spokesman Sam Macalus said the storm left
more than 60,000 customers in the metropolitan area without power.
   In southwestern Minnesota, strong wind knocked down trees and
power lines in Tracy, leaving much of the town without power. Trees
and power lines also were reported down in nearby Balaton and
Garvin.
   By afternoon, showers and thunderstorms were scattered across
west-central through northeastern Wisconsin and into northern and
central Michigan.
   Showers and thunderstorms also were scattered from southeastern
South Dakota across western Nebraska, across southeastern Wyoming,
eastern and central Colorado, parts of New Mexico, northern and
central Arizona, south-central Utah and south-central Texas.
   In the Southeast, showers and thunderstorms were scattered over
southeastern Louisiana, central Alabama, southern and central
Florida, the North Carolina coast and southeastern Virginia.
   East-central Pennsylvania also got rain.
   Heaviest rainfall during the six hours up to 2 p.m. EDT was 1.43
inches at Pellston, Mich.
   Well to the north, strong thunderstorms produced wind gusts of
almost 65 mph during the night at Fairbanks, Alaska, marking the
eastern edge of cooler temperatures and possibly breaking that
area's heat wave. Temperatures had reached 80 degrees or higher on
the previous nine days.
   Temperatures were high over much of the nation, including an
early reading of 100 degrees at Nashville, Tenn. Temperatures rose
the 90s as far north as Indiana, southern Wisconsin, southern Iowa
and southeastern Nebraska.
   Sunday's low for the Lower 48 states was 37 at both Truckee,
Calif., and West Yellowstone, Mont.
   Temperatures around the nation at 3 p.m. EDT ranged from 56 at
Laramie, Wyo., to 101 at Nashville.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0053 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 1717EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Bolivia     07-08 0692</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bolivia,0715</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.S. Military Escalates Involvement in Bolivian Drug War</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PETER MCFARREN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LA PAZ, Bolivia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The U.S. military is setting up a
sophisticated intelligence-gathering system in Bolivia to keep tabs
on drug traffickers, and it has sent in advisers to help, a U.S.
official said.
   Increased U.S. military presence in Bolivia is part of an
intensification of the anti-drug war, encouraged by promises of aid
from Washington.
   Eugene Castillo, acting U.S. Drug Enforcement Administration
attache for Bolivia, said Friday the U.S. Southern Military Command
would ``reinforce the Bolivian police and DEA operational
capabilities throughout South America.''
   Bolivia, an impoverished South American country of 7 million
people, produces one-third of the cocaine for U.S. and other
foreign markets. Castillo described the new system as
``innovative.''
   ``It gives us ... intelligence and the ability to transmit that
intellingence to affected areas so that operations can be planned
and mounted in a minimum amount of time,'' Castillo said.
   Castillo spoke Friday on condition the story would not be used
until Sunday.
   A computer system, recently installed in La Paz and Santa Cruz,
will link major cocaine centers and provide data on trafficking. It
will also provide a safe way of transmiting information among
anti-drug operations centers.
   It will shortly be installed in three other Bolivian cocaine
centers.
   Currently, the DEA and Bolivian police rely on
Korean-war-vintage radio equipment that can easily be intercepted
by drug traffickers, who use the latest in radio communications
equipment.
   Castillo said the U.S. Military Command is also helping the DEA
and Bolivian police ``formulate and maintain a country-wide
operational strategy'' to prevent the production and export of
drugs and import of chemicals.
   For about a month, three military advisers _ one each from the
U.S. Navy, Army and Air Force _ have been coordinating strategy
with Bolivian police and the DEA. At least 10 other special agents
are training Bolivian anti-drug police.
   The U.S. military is prohibited by the Bolivian and U.S.
governments from directly participating in any anti-drug operations.
   ``The military is only a support force,''' Castillo said. ``All
we are doing is using military expertise to assist us in
intelligence gathering.''
   During a May meeting in Washington, Bolivian leader Jaime Paz
Zamora and President Bush agreed on greater military involvement in
the anti-drug war.
   Paz Zamora agreed to commit 900 soldiers to the effort and to
increase air force and navy involvement. Bolivian military
personnel are already assisting police in anti-drug activities.
   In return, Bolivia was promised $75 million worth of military
equipment and training for 1990-1991.
   But the growing militarization of the anti-drug war has created
opposition in Bolivia and raised concern that a largely peaceful
police enforcement effort could escalate into civil wars such those
in Peru and Colombia.
   ``The participation of the military in coca-producing zones ...
is only producing violence,'' said Felipe Caceres Garcia, a leader
of the coca growers association of Chapare. The region the size of
New Jersey produces 80 percent of Bolivian coca leaves, the base
for cocaine.
   ``In Bolivia, there is no violence, there is no terrorism and we
do not want it to get to that,'' Caceres Garcia said.
   Bolivia's army is better known for coups d'etat and corruption
than combat skills. A military government that took power in 1980
worked closely with cocaine traffickers.
   The army also has a reputation for heavy-handedness. When it is
called in to put down strikes, for instance, bloodshed often
results.
   Coca-growing peasants, militant and well organized, have sworn
they will resist any any military crackdown.
   But those who favor military involvement, including U.S.
Ambassador Robert Gelbard, say army action is needed if ``Bolivia
is going to nip in the bud what is developing into a real national
threat.''
   ``Many Bolivians remember the regime of Luis Garcia Meza in the
early 80s and the instability of the country's democratic
institutions before that and are afraid of a return to those
problems,'' Gelbard said Friday, also on condition the story not be
used until Sunday.
   ``We believe that the broad-based public support of democracy in
Bolivia and the military's clear commitment to democratic
principals poses no threat.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0054 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 1731EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Germany-Rightists     07-08 0423</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Germany-Rightists,0436</SECOND>
<HEAD>RETRANSMITTING TO CORRECT CODING</HEAD>
<HEAD>Former SS Soldier Returns To Politics, Neo-Nazi Held</HEAD>
<DATELINE>RUHSTORF, West Germany (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   West Germany's ultra-rightist
Republican Party on Sunday re-elected a former Waffen SS soldier to
be its chairman, ending a six-week fight over the group's
leadership.
   East Germany, meanwhile, briefly detained the self-proclaimed
``fuehrer'' _ German for leader _ of a group that openly advocates
Nazi ideology.
   The re-election of Franz Schoenhuber and the arrest of Michael
Kuehnen came amid reports of growing activity, particulary in East
Germany, of rightist and neo-Nazi groups.
   West Germany has long had a small but vocal neo-Nazi movement.
Ultra-conservative organizations like Schoenhuber's have sought to
capitalize on economic insecurity and resentment of the country's
immigrant population.
   In East Germany, the ousted Communist leadership regarded
neo-Nazism as a problem afflicting only its capitalist Western
neighbor. But groups of ultra-rightist East German youths wearing
swastikas and giving Nazi salutes have attacked rival gangs, and
there have also been reports of vandalism attacks on Jewish graves
and property.
   Along with Jean-Marie le Pen in France, Schoenhuber is one of
Western Europe's most notorious ultra-rightist politicians.
   At a tumultuous two-day conference, 376 of 563 Republican
delegates voted for Schoenhuber, who resigned as chairman in
mid-May after criticizing the party for drifting too far right.
   Dozens of police sealed off the conference hall in this eastern
Bavarian town as delegates cheered Schoenhuber and booed his main
rivals, Harald Neubauer and Franz Glasauer.
   In his acceptance speech, Schoenhuber said the Republicans under
his leadership would be ``a party of historically purged patriotism
... right-wing, therefore.''
   East Germany banned the Republicans from taking part in the
nation's first free elections last March, and Schoenhuber himself
has been refused entry to East Germany several times.
   The Republicans also adopted a motion banning members of several
neo-Nazi groups from holding office in the party. The motion was
put forward by Schoenhuber, reflecting his publicly expressed
concern that the group will be become identified with neo-Nazism.
   Late Saturday, the East German Interior Ministry reported it had
arrested Kuehnen, a former lieutenant in the West German Army, who
has twice served prison sentences for his neo-Nazi activities.
   Kuehnen, who calls himself a ``fuehrer,'' is West Germany's most
notorious neo-Nazi. He was detained during a rally near the East
German city of Cottbus and released a short time later, according
to the East German news agency ADN.
   He has been charged with propagating ``fascist, militarist''
ideas during a May 1 demonstration by his group near Erfurt, East
Germany, ADN said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0055 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 1732EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-PlantExplosion     07-08 0291</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Plant Explosion,0300</SECOND>
<HEAD>Widow Says Husband Warned of Blast, Identifications Continue</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CHANNELVIEW, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The widow of a millwright killed in an
explosion at the ARCO Chemical Co. said her husband called her half
an hour before the blast, saying workers restarting equipment there
were afraid it might explode.
   Lori Davis, 26, said her husband, Michael, had been working an
extended shift at the plant Thursday for Austin Industrial Inc., a
subcontractor at ARCO Chemical. Davis, 24, called home about 11:15
p.m., she said.
   ``Michael told me they were about to start a compressor that
they had fixed. But they were afraid to do it because they thought
it might blow,'' Mrs. Davis recalled Saturday.
   Davis died in a blast minutes later along with 16 others,
including employees from Austin Industrial, ARCO Chemical employees
and Waste Processors Industries Inc.
   The Occupational Safety and Health Organization and other
ivestigators continued searching Sunday for a cause of the blast,
said Gerald Davis, ACRO Chemical spokesman.
   Harold Sorgenti, president and chief executive officer of ARCO
Chemical, said workers had been repairing an electric compressor
near a 900,000-gallon wastewater treatment tank when the explosion
occurred.
   The tank separates hydrocarbons from water and then a compressor
pumps the sometimes volatile vapors into a pipeline where
impurities can be removed before releasing the gases to the
atmosphere, officials said.
   Mrs. Davis, who married June 9, said her husband phoned her
three times last Thursday to say he was working late.
   She said employees had been working long hours in recent weeks
because the plant was shorthanded.
   `I don't think that work hours had anything to do with this,''
said Earl McCaleb, plant manager. ``It's not all that uncommon to
work 16-hour shifts throughout the industry.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0056 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 1740EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SAfrica-Arrests     07-08 0460</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-SAfrica-Arrests,0474</SECOND>
<HEAD>Nine White Extremists Arrested in South Africa</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-SAfrica-Extremists</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SAHM VENTER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JOHANNESBURG, South Africa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Nine white extremists have
been detained in connection with a series of bombings aimed at
anti-apartheid targets, an official said Sunday.
   Adriaan Vlok, the minister of law and order, said all nine men
had been detained under the Internal Security Act, which allows for
indefinite detention without trial. They have not been charged.
   ``The people arrested are all supporters of a far-right
political ideology, but cannot thus far be connected to any
particular organization,'' Vlok said.
   He identified three of those arrested as Leonard Veenendaal,
Darryl Stopforth and David Rootenberg. He said the other six men
could not yet be named because of the nature of the investigation,
but he did not elaborate.
   Vlok did not say when the arrests were made.
   Since April 12, there have been a series of bombings in which
right-wingers were suspected. The most serious attack was the
Friday bombing of a taxi stand in which 27 blacks were injured.
   Among the targets in the bombings were two offices of the
National Party. That party leads the country's white government.
   Right-wing whites have expressed outrage at President F.W. de
Klerk's plans to end apartheid _ South Africa's system of racial
discrimination _ and share power with the 30-million black majority.
   Both de Klerk and the African National Congress, the leading
black opposition group, have said a terrorist campaign by heavily
armed right-wing whites could undermine black-white negotiations.
   Veenendaal and Stopforth were arrested last year in neighboring
Namibia and charged with killing a security guard at a U.N. office.
Veenendaal and Stopforth escaped from Namibia in December and
returned to South Africa.
   South Africa granted independence to Namibia on March 21, a move
opposed by right-wingers. The United Nations supervised the
transition to independence.
   Also Sunday, the independent South African Press Association
reported that the pro-apartheid Conservative Party said it plans to
defy a government law requiring public facilities to open to all
races by October.
   The Separate Amenities Act, passed in 1953, gave local
governments and privately-owned enterprises the right to reserve
facilities for whites, such as parks, hotels, swimming pools,
bathrooms and recreation centers.
   In a statement after Saturday's Conservative Party meeting,
Pikkie Coetzee, a member of Parliament and chairman of the party's
municipal committee, said the Conservative Party ``also warns the
government very seriously that the friction which will come from
its discontinuation of the Separate Amenities Act will be the
exclusive responsibility of the government.''
   The Conservative Party won 31 percent of the vote in September's
election. It is the official opposition in the white chamber of
Parliament, and the Conservatives control dozens of local councils
throughout the country.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0057 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 1741EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Teachers     07-08 0417</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Teachers,0429</SECOND>
<HEAD>Teachers' Group Stops Challenges to its Abortion Rights Position</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TAMARA HENRY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Education Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>KANSAS CITY, Mo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The National Education Association
soundly defeated all challenges to its abortion rights position as
it concluded a four-day convention Sunday.
   Education Secretary Lauro Cavazos sent his ``warmest greetings''
to the convention and pledged to work closely with the union to
improve schools. The message seemed to signal an end to a feud
between the NEA and the Education Department that began during the
Reagan administration when the department was led by the outspoken
William Bennett, now drug czar.
   Although reluctant to use the word ``abortion,'' a majority of
the 8,100 delegates Sunday defeated an attempt to change the
union's support of family planning, ``including the right to
reproductive freedom.''
   The nation's largest teachers' union also voted to oppose any
legislation that erodes the Supreme Court's abortion ruling or
tries to impede access to information on ``choice of reproductive
health care options.''
   ``Whether you or I agree with abortion is irrelevant,'' said
Robert Chase, a vice president of the nation's largest teachers'
union, during floor debate. ``What is relevant is the right of
women to make the choice for themselves.''
   Robert Pawson, head of Teachers Saving Children, vowed to
continue attempts to ``reform the NEA from within.''
   Pawson said abortion opponents for the first time in 10 years
had been able to get NEA delegates to act on the issue. In the
past, he said abortion rights advocates had prevented debate on the
issue.
   In the daylong session, Kathleen Holzmeister of the Illinois
Education Association lost an effort to forbid abortion counseling
at community-operated, school-based family planning clinics.
   On Saturday, delegates easily defeated an attempt to stop the
union's policy of lobbying for abortion rights.
   Christine Nowak of New York led efforts to eliminate abortion
lobbying from the legislative agenda of the nation's largest
teachers' union. She and others argued that union dues should not
be used for such activity because the NEA's 2 million members have
a variety of views on the issue.
   In a resounding voice vote, the legislative amendment was
rejected.
   In other action, the union put itself on record in support of
giving teachers more authority over their jobs and school
curriculums _ popularly called site-based decision-making.
   The NEA also agreed to write President Bush and Congress in
support of sanctions against South Africa until apartheid is
eliminated, and to encourage pension funds' divestment of companies
doing business in South Africa.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0058 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 1742EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-NixonLibrary     07-08 0492</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Nixon Library,0508</SECOND>
<HEAD>Nixon Library to Screen Researchers, Papers</HEAD>
<DATELINE>YORBA LINDA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Richard Nixon's presidential library
will pick and choose who can do research there and probably will
keep out Pulitzer Prize-winning Watergate reporter Bob Woodward,
library officials say.
   The library also will lack a full set of memos, letters and
other documents from Nixon's White House years when it opens later
this month.
   That's because the originals are in the custody of the
government, and Nixon has chosen to copy only those he considers
important to the library.
   The actions have irked some scholars who say they mistrust a
library where documents will be screened.
   ``Who knows what the Nixon people have screened out?'' said
Stanley Kutler, a Wisconsin history professor who recently
published a book on the Watergate scandal that led to Nixon's
resignation as president on Aug. 19, 1974.
   The library's director, Hugh Hewitt, says every document of any
importance, including many relating to Watergate, will be in the
library. But he acknowledged that Woodward probably wouldn't be
allowed to study them.
   ``I don't think we'd ever open the doors to Bob Woodward, he's
not a responsible journalist,'' Hewitt said.
   ``It would be far more of a taint to let the premises be used
indiscriminately by groups who oppose everything he (Nixon) has
worked for,'' he added.
   Woodward and fellow reporter Washington Post reporter Carl
Bernstein uncovered the White House coverup of the botched burglary
of Democratic National Headquarters in the Watergate complex in
1972.
   Woodward, the Post's assistant managing editor for
investigations, said the suggestion that he or others would be kept
out ``demonstrates that the library will be part of a continuing
cover-up.''
   The Richard M. Nixon Presidential Library will be able to use
its autonomy as a privately run facility to choose the scholars it
allows to do research.
   Of the nation's other presidential libraries, only the
Rutherford B. Hayes library is privately operated. Eight are run by
the National Archives, which will also control the Ronald Reagan
library under construction in Simi Valley.
   The Nixon library's exhibition section will be dedicated July 19
at a ceremony to be attended by President Bush and former
Presidents Reagan and Gerald Ford. The archives will open sometime
next year.
   Hewitt said the library will include a ``Watergate Hall'' and
many documents detailing the scandal, including the 1972 ``smoking
gun'' tape recording in which Nixon says he will ask the CIA and
FBI to halt the Watergate investigation. Excerpts will be played
for visitors.
   That's not enough to satisfy Kutler, who accused Nixon of being
obsessed with secrecy and control.
   The idea that Nixon wants to control the library's contents is
``a presumption on the part of the liberal Nixon haters, '' said
Walter Annenberg, Nixon's ambassador to Great Britain.
   ``That library is going to contain everything, favorable or
unfavorable,'' said William E. Simon, president of the library
foundation. ``Academics and historians have always hated Nixon.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0059 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 1800EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-CrackHouseLaw     07-08 0268</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Crack House Law,0273</SECOND>
<HEAD>Health and Safety Plan for Crack Cocaine Houses Reconsidered</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SEATTLE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A regulation attacking crack cocaine houses by
requiring them to have health and safety plans appears likely to be
replaced with one declaring them health hazards.
   ``The prosecutor was concerned that it looked like we were
permitting an illegal operation,'' said Chuck Kleeburg, King County
director of environmental health.
   the county prosecutor's office proposes replacing the existing
regulation with one designating crack houses a health hazard
because of addiction, toxic exposure and violence. Health officials
could fine landlords and tenants $1,000 for each day a crack house
remained in operation.
   The Board of Health is scheduled to vote on the new plan July 24.
   The original regulation, which was adopted in January and
scheduled to take effect July 1, county police were to inform
health officials when a building was being used for making or
selling the potent crack form of cocaine.
   The owner then was to be notified of an apparent violation of
health regulations, given 10 days to present a plan for reducing
the health and safety risk and ordered to pay a $100 review fee.
   Health officials said they never expected to get a health and
safety plan and would use fines for failing to file health and
safety plans as another way to attack crack houses.
   Police have relied heavily on a state law allowing civil
abatement fe proceedings to close and condemn crack houses after
owners fail to end drug operations. The statute has been used less
frequently by police in the county and suburban jurisdictions.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0060 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 1801EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-SalcidoTrial 1stLd-Writethru a0724 07-08 0411</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Salcido Trial, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0724,0416</SECOND>
<HEAD>Accused Mass Killer Goes On Trial</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 5th and 6th grafs to CORRECT spelling to Angelia sted
Angela</NOTE>
<DATELINE>REDWOOD CITY, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A winery worker is set to go on
trial Monday on charges he slaughtered his wife, two daughters and
four others in a murderous rampage, but the case may be delayed for
two months.
   Ramon Salcido's lawyer, Marteen Miller, said he would ask
visiting San Mateo Superior Court Judge Reginald Littrell to reset
the trial for September. Miller claims his client was illegally
extradited from Mexico a few days after the April 1989 slayings.
   Miller said he would argue that Salcido, charged with seven
counts of murder, had a brain dysfunction that fueled the bloody
killing spree in the Sonoma County vineyard country, 35 miles north
of San Francisco.
   The trial was moved to San Mateo County, south of San Francisco,
in response to a venue change request by Miller, the public
defender for Sonoma County.
   Investigators said Salcido was enraged by what he believed were
infidelities by his wife, Angelia. He said he believed he was not
the father of their eldest daughter, Sofia.
   Three days before the rampage, the marriage had been strained
when Salcido was served with court papers ordering him to pay child
support to his ex-wife in Fresno County, whom Angelia knew nothing
about.
   In a statement to a sheriff returning with him from Mexico City,
Salcido said the killing started after bouts of cocaine and alcohol
use.
   According to his statement, Salcido took his three daughters,
Theresa, 1, Sofia, 4, and Carmina, 3, to a county dump site where
he slit their throats; Carmina survived.
   He then drove to the home of Robert Richards Sr. and his family,
Salcido's in-laws. He knocked his mother-in-law, Marian Louise
Richards, 47, unconscious and then killed her daughters,
12-year-old Ruth, and 8-year-old Marie. Before leaving, he
allegedly stabbed his mother-in-law to death as she regained
consciousness.
   Salcido said he went back to his Boyes Hot Springs home where he
beat his wife and shot her with a .22-caliber pistol as she tried
to get to a telephone.
   Salcido said he thought about killing himself, but decided to go
to the Grand Cru Winery, where he worked, to shoot co-workers
Tracey Toovey, 35, and Ken Butti, 33.
   ``I've killed already so many, I think I'll kill ... the two
other guys,'' the detective quoted Salcido as saying.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0061 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 1801EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-RebelLeader 1stLd-Writethru a0744 07-08 0760</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Rebel Leader, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0744,0777</SECOND>
<HEAD>Charles Taylor Has Gone From College Activist To Rebel Leader</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 18th graf, `Taylor was...' to CORRECT that two of
Taylor's brothers and three sisters live in Rhode Island</NOTE>
<HEAD>With AM-Liberia</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto BX3</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KAREN SCHWARTZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PROVIDENCE, R.I. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   While Charles Taylor was driving rebel
forces against the president of Liberia, his wife was driving their
children to summer camp and trying to rally support for her
husband's rebellion.
   Tupee Taylor hasn't seen her husband for five years. But she is
unflinching in her belief that her husband will overthrow Liberia's
President Samuel Doe.
   The rebels accuse Doe, who gained power of the tiny West African
country in a bloody coup in 1980, of corruption, tribalism, and
brutal suppression of the opposition.
   Taylor, 42, and his forces invaded the West African country from
the Ivory Coast on Dec. 24. Mrs. Taylor learned of the action when
her husband telephoned on New Year's Day.
   ``I wasn't surprised or shocked,'' she said. ``Someone had to do
something. And if anyone would do it I know Charles would be the
one. He's very determined and very, very intelligent.''
   Taylor's forces have continued to tighten their noose on the
capital of Monrovia. Rebels besieging the capital rejected a
cease-fire proposed by Doe and resumed fighting Sunday, rebel
sources said. Doe continued to decline an American offer of safe
passage out of the country.
   And 5,500 miles away, Mrs. Taylor, 29, worked to promote her
husband's cause while trying to maintain a normal life for her
school-age children.
   ``The best I can do is to get as much publicity as I can,'' she
said. ``I am a Christian and I pray a lot. We don't want to be
separated. But it's safer for us here.''
   The Taylors met in the United States through their involvement
with Liberian student associations. She attended Seton Hall while
he graduated from Bentley College with an economics degree.
   ``He always had political ambitions,'' she said. ``He was always
outspoken. He always spoke out about the injustices in Liberia and
the need for democracy. If he is the next leader of Liberia, we'll
have a better future. Things will be different.''
   The Taylors married in Liberia in 1980 and witnessed the coup
that overthrew the late President William Tolbert.
   ``We stayed because that's our country and no matter who came
into power we believed in staying there and restoring democracy,''
Mrs. Taylor said.
   Taylor took a job in Doe's cabinet as director of the General
Services Agency, but became disillusioned and was arrested for
circulating subversive materials in 1981.
   He continued working for Doe's government until 1982, when their
house was ransacked and he was implicated in the first of many coup
attempts, she said.
   The Taylors returned to the United States, where Taylor was
arrested in May 1984 outside Boston and accused of embezzling $1
million from Liberia, a charge his wife claims Doe fabricated.
   Sixteen months later, Taylor fled the Plymouth County House of
Corrections in Massachusetts while awaiting extradition. Mrs.
Taylor said she does not know how he escaped. ``I was happy he
left,'' she said. ``I didn't ask him how he did it.''
   She also said she does not know what her husband did in the 4{
years between his escape and the start of the revolution. ``There
are so many things Charles could have been doing in that process.
Nobody knows,'' she said.
   Taylor was raised in an affluent family in Althington, Liberia,
one of 10 children. Their father was a commissioner of immigration
and later became a judge, said Nelson Taylor, one of two Taylor
brothers and three sisters living in Rhode Island.
   The Taylors' two American-born children, Charen, 9, and Camille,
7, learned of their father's activities accidentally.
   ``I tried to keep it from them because I didn't want to confuse
them,'' Mrs. Taylor said. But Charen read about the rebellion in
the newspaper and ``so they decided themselves ... and they just
started watching the news.''
   The United States and other countries have questioned Taylor's
commitment to democracy and free elections. His credibility has
also been damaged by reports of executions of suspected Doe
supporters.
   Those reports are ``completely false,'' his wife said. ``It
makes you crazy because things get distorted,'' Mrs. Taylor said.
   She said her husband is committed to holding free elections.
   ``If the Liberians wants Charles Taylor as the leader the
Liberian people will vote for Charles Taylor. For right now, he's a
fighter,'' she said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0062 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 1803EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Funeral-Death     07-08 0229</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Funeral-Death,0235</SECOND>
<HEAD>Man Suffers Fatal Heart Attack While Leading Singing At Friend's
Funeral</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MOULTON, Ala. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A 66-year-old man suffered a fatal heart
attack while leading the singing at the funeral of a friend.
   Charles H. Sanford Sr. of Pumpkin Center collapsed Saturday
afternoon during the funeral service for Dee Melson at Elliott
Funeral Home chapel. He died a short time later.
   Lawrence County Coronor Harvey Elliott, who owns the funeral
home, said a minister had finished speaking and Sanford had gotten
up to lead he congregation in a final song when he was stricken.
   ``I was watching him,'' Elliott said. ``He looked up and then
staggered a little bit. I got hold of him and got him out of the
chapel into the hall. I knew it was a desperate situation and
hollered for somebody to call 911.''
   A doctor and registered nurse attending the funeral administered
cardiopulmonary resuscitation to Sanford while awaiting an
ambulance. He was taken to Lawrence County Hospital where he died.
   Sanford was retired from Monsanto Chemical Co. in Decatur and
was involved in church work, gardening and following his passion
for singing, said his son, Charles Jr.
   ``That was one of the things he loved to do the most,'' the
younger Sanford said. ``He was not a professional singer, but he
had a good voice and people liked to hear him.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0063 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 1807EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Canada-Nazis     07-08 0537</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Canada-Nazis,0554</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.S. Helped Ex-Nazis Enter Canada, Study Says</HEAD>
<DATELINE>OTTAWA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   U.S. officials helped at least 39 people,
including ex-Nazis, slip into Canada to build a new life in the
early 1950s to reward them for their work as spies, previously
classified documents indicate.
   A study by Ottawa historian Alti Rodal, completed three years
ago for a federal royal commission that investigated suspected Nazi
war criminals, says the 39 people came to Canada with false
documents and identities from U.S. authorities.
   Ms. Rodal's report was released in heavily censored form in
1987, with several general references to the involvement by U.S.
intelligence officers in resettling alleged ex-Nazis.
   The report said the U.S. officials, who were responsible for
screening Europeans seeking a new life in North America after the
war, misled Canadian authorities about the backgrounds of some of
the emigrants.
   The 39 cases involved mostly Germans who had worked for Nazi
organizations during World War II. They were recruited by the
United States after 1945 as part of an intelligence ring to spy on
the Russian zone of occupied Germany and suspected Communist
sympathizers in the American zone.
   More details of the resettlement plan emerged last week, as
material previously deleted from Ms. Rodal's report was made public
following requests by journalists under the Access to Information
Act.
   There was no CIA spokesperson available Sunday in Washington to
comment on the new details from Ms. Rodal's report.
   Government documents cited by Ms. Rodal show the Royal Canadian
Mounted Police and the External Affairs Department were surprised
when they stumbled on the U.S. plan in 1953-54.
   Lester Pearson, then external affairs minister and future
Liberal prime minister, complained the Americans should have taken
such people into their own country if they wanted them, rather than
dumping them on others.
   Canadian diplomats in Washington were instructed to take the
matter up directly with Allen Dulles, then head of the CIA.
   Washington eventually provided background information on the
people involved and assured External Affairs the information
package was complete.
   But Royal Police memos indicate the police force was skeptical
and thought others may have been smuggled in and never detected.
   One memo from September 1954 noted 35 cases had been discussed
at that point with the Americans, but ``we are not convinced that
the figures which have been given to us in the first instance are
in fact correct.''
   Another memo the same month noted four more cases had been
discovered.
   All involved people were sponsored by the U.S. Army Research and
Resettlement Branch, which played a key role in relocating former
intelligence agents, including Nazi collaborators.
   Ms. Rodal concluded the Americans probably acted with the
knowledge and co-operation of a Royal Police sergeant then
stationed in Karlsruhe, West Germany. He apparently kept the scheme
from his superior.
   At least some had criminal records on grounds of moral turpitude
_ the immigration category then used to exclude suspected war
criminals and Nazi collaborators.
   The 1985-87 royal commission under Justice Jules Deschenes
recommended urgent action against 20 suspected war criminals in
Canada and further investigation of 200 other cases.
   The Justice Department has since initiated three criminal
prosecutions and one civil action. It has 45 other cases under
consideration.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0064 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 1816EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Summit-Briefs     07-08 0324</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Summit-Briefs,300</SECOND>
<HEAD>With AM-Summit-Rdp,Bjt</HEAD>
<HEAD>Briefing For Gorbachev?</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HOUSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Canadian Prime Minister Brian Mulroney said
Sunday that Soviet President Mikhail Gorbachev should be given a
special briefing on the results of the economic summit of
industrialized nations.
   A senior Canadian official, demanding anonymity, said Mulroney
suggested that President Bush, as the host of the gathering,
provide the Kremlin leader with details of the high-level talks.
   The briefing could be done by telephone or letter or through an
emissary, he said.
   The summit leaders, he said, should ``send a positive economic
signal to the Soviet Union which would match the positive
political-military message that came from the London summit of NATO
allies.''
   The leaders of the 16 nations of the North Atlantic Treaty
Organization decided on Friday to reshape the Western military
alliance in response to the political upheavals in Eastern Europe.
They also agreed to invite Gorbachev to speak at the alliance's
headquarters in Brussels.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Melting Ice at the Summit</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HOUSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Environmentalists had a cool idea for a symbolic,
publicity-grabbing gimmick to illustrate their concerns about
global warming: A gigantic block of melting ice.
   Neat. Just the way to grab attention at the economic summit in
sweltering Houston.
   One problem.
   It turned into a puddle twice as fast as expected.
   Houston ice carver Nathan Smith worked all night on 10,240
pounds of ice in a downtown park to make a globe showing all the
continents, surrounded by the flags of the summit participants.
   The final piece was carved at about 8:45 a.m. Less than 8 hours
later, the ice was virtually gone as mid-afternoon temperatures
reached 90 degrees.
   ``Our climate is heating up; our natural resource base is
melting down,'' was the message, according to Wilderness Society
President George Frampton.
   Catherine Moore of the ``Envirosummit'' coalition said
organizers though the ice would last until Tuesday, but they
miscalculated because the sculptor had never done such a project in
heat.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0065 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 1841EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-JailedWoman 1stLd-Writethru a0698 07-08 0455</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Jailed Woman, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0698,0462</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rally For Young Mother Jailed 121 Days For Refusing To Give Up
Kids</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: RECASTS top 4 grafs to move up reference to woman being
permitted to speak to supporters, DELETE implication that
demonstration could have led to her release; picks up 5th graf pvs,
``The demonstrators...</NOTE>
<DATELINE>FORSYTH, Mont. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   About 30 friends and relatives of a
Cheyenne Indian mother jailed in a custody dispute with her
ex-husband demonstrated outside the jail, and she was briefly led
outside to speak to her supporters.
   Tina Cady has been jailed four months for refusing to return her
two small children to their father, who has legal custody, claiming
she fears possible child abuse. The youngsters are on an Indian
reservation, where state courts can't touch them.
   Sheriff's deputies took Cady out to speak to the crowd that
gathered at the jail Saturday, demanding her release.
   ``I really appreciate your support, and I'm sure my kids do,
too,'' she said.
   The demonstrators included Tom Gardner Sr. of Lame Deer, who
served eight years as a judge on the tribal court of the nearby
Northern Cheyenne Indian Reservation. Cady is a member of the tribe
and lives on the reservation in Lame Deer.
   Cady, 26, has been jailed since March 9, when state District
Judge Joe Hegel held her in contempt for refusing to comply with a
court order to return her children to her former husband, Walt
Donges, 34, of Colstrip.
   Donges was awarded custody of the children, 4-year-old Brittany
and 2-year-old Ryan, when the couple divorced last October.
   Cady said that on Feb. 9, when she picked up the children for a
visit, she noticed a large bruise on Brittany's buttock.
   An Indian Health Service doctor examined the bruise and
recommended that Cady not return the children to Donges until an
investigation had been conducted.
   Donges has denied causing the bruise or ever hitting his
children, contending that the girl was bruised because her little
brother bit her.
   The custody battle reached an impasse when Cady took the
children to her parents' home in Busby on the reservation, where
they have remained. The reservation is outside the state court's
jurisdiction.
   Last month, the Northern Cheyenne Tribal Court ordered that the
children would be temporary wards of that court and placed
responsibility for their care with the tribe's social services
department.
   Because of that court action, Cady said that even if she wanted
to she could not return Brittany and Ryan to their father.
   Hegel said in a telephone interview with the Billings Gazette
that he doesn't know if Cady's interpretation of the matter is
correct, but said he is looking for a quick resolution to the
situation.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0066 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 1826EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Lebanon-Israel 1stLd-Writethru a0680 07-08 0723</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lebanon-Israel, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0680,0744</SECOND>
<HEAD>Warplanes Blast Hezbollah Stronghold</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS thruout to UPDATE with Hezbollah firing missiles at
border to retaliate for Israeli air strike, fighting between
Palestinian fundamentalists and Sunni Moslem militia in Sidon. No
pickup.
^By EDMOND SHEDID</NOTE>
<HEAD>With AM-Lebanon-Hostages</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NABATIYEH, Lebanon (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Israeli warplanes blasted a major
stronghold of the Iranian-backed Hezbollah in south Lebanon Sunday
in their second attack on Lebanon-based guerrillas in three days.
   Police said at least two people were killed and seven wounded in
the attack, which followed reports that kidnappers linked to the
Shiite Moslem Hezbollah, or Party of God, might release one of 16
Western hostages they hold.
   In Israel, the military command confirmed the raid. It said in a
communique: ``The target was destroyed and all planes returned
safely to base.'' It gave no other details.
   Eight hours after the Israeli air attack, Hezbollah guerrillas
fired three surface-to-surface missiles from the foothills of Mount
Hermon at the Israeli border with Lebanon, police said. The rockets
exploded but there was no immediate word of damage or casualties.
   Israeli border gunners struck back with a long-range artillery
barrage targeted on the south Lebanese village of Ein Atta, where
the missiles were fired from, police said.
   It was not immediately clear if the anticipated hostage release
would be canceled in retaliation for the Israeli air attack. Moslem
fundamentalists claim Western support of Israel encourages its
attacks on Lebanon.
   Police and witnesses in the market town of Nabatiyeh said four
Israeli jets fired four rockets on a Hezbollah base midway between
the neighboring villages of Jarjou and Ein Bouswar in the lighting
air raid.
   A chain of loud explosions echoed across the area after the
raid, which demolished a three-story house used by Hezbollah as an
ammuntion dump and sniper nest on a hilltop overlooking the two
villages.
   ``The house has been completely destroyed and many victims have
been buried beneath the rubble,'' said a police spokesman, who
could not be identified under standing rules.
   Flames and smoke shrouding the target could be seen from
Nabatiyeh, Ein Bouswar and Jarjou, the spokesman and witnesses in
Nabatiyeh said.
   A Hezbollah statement in Beirut said two party fighters were
killed and many wounded.
   ``General mobilization has been ordered by the party in the area
and all fighters were put on high alert to retaliate for the
monstrous Israeli aggression,'' the statement said. It did not
elaborate.
   Jarjou and Ein Bouswar are two to three miles north of Israel's
self-declared security zone.
   Hezbollah has long been engaged in guerrilla attacks against
Israeli troops and allied Lebanese Christian militiamen policing
the zone.
   The zone's population is predominantly Moslem Shiite. Israel
carved out the buffer area in 1985, saying it was needed to guard
against cross-border raids.
   Israeli jets on Friday attacked bases of radical Palestinian
guerrillas in Syrian-policed northern and eastern Lebanon. Eight
fighters were wounded.
   The targets were positions of the Libyan-funded, Damascus-based
Popular Front for the Liberation of Palestine-General Command.
   The attack last week was the first into Lebanon since Israeli
Prime Minister Yitzhak Shamir formed his right-wing government last
month. Arab governments have called it a ``war government.''
   Sunday's was Israel's 14th air attack this year. By police
count, 16 people were killed and 39 wounded in the 13 previous
strikes since Jan. 19.
   Also in south Lebanon, a street battle broke out late Saturday
afternoon in the port city of Sidon between Palestinian
fundamentalists and Lebanese Sunni Moslem militiamen of the
Nasserite Popular Organization.
   Police said Sunday two people were killed and 21 wounded in the
eight-hour clash that involved automatic rifles, rocket-launched
grenades and mortars.
   They said the clashes between the Ansarullah, anewly founded
Palestinian faction, and the Nasserites were halted by an informal
cease-fire at 1 a.m. Sunday.
   Ansarullah, Arabic for ``God's partisans,'' comprises Moslem
extremists from the Palestinian refugee camp of Ein el-Hilweh, on
the outskirts of Sidon. The faction is allied with Hamas, the
Palestinian resistance group based in the Israeli-occupied Gaza
Strip.
   The Nasserites are the dominant militia in Sidon, a
predominantly Sunni Moslem area. They maintain close ties with
Yasser Arafat's Palestine Liberation Organization, whose efforts to
negotiate a peace with Israel have been openly criticized by Hamas.
   Hamas has been challenging the pro-PLO underground command of
the Arab uprising in the Israeli-occupied West Bank and Gaza Strip.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0067 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 1858EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-NovelSentence     07-08 0430</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Novel Sentence,0444</SECOND>
<HEAD>Judge's Novel Sentence: Write Me From Prison</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HARTFORD, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A judge who wanted vivid descriptions of
criminal life so he could warn young people away from lawlessness
has ordered convicted criminals to write him letters from jail.
   Judge Raymond R. Norko, the presiding judge at the court that
handles serious crimes in Hartford County, recently has been
ordering defendants to write him letters recounting how their lives
led to prison.
   Norko, who promises convicts their names will not be released
with their letters, said he hopes to put together a collection that
he can publish and distribute to schoolchildren.
   ``Maybe to have it in writing would be more vivid and real for
them,'' he said.
   Norko said he has received only three responses, so he has
started handing out the assignment before sentencing.
   One letter he received was written with large, childlike
lettering.
   ``Why I started doing drugs: I wish I could say it was because
my friends were doing it. That was part of it,'' said the letter
from a 23-year-old man who received a suspended sentence and
probation for drug possession. ``The rest was because it made me
feel good.
   ``I wish I could go back a couple of years and start over,'' the
convict wrote. ``I have hurt a lot of people.''
   Another convict wrote a chilling 12-page account of his life of
crime.
   ``Let me start by saying I wish I were in your seat hearing
these words instead of writing them,'' the man wrote.
   The author, now 36 and facing 11 years in prison, described a
boyhood spent stealing cigarettes and sniffing glue, and then using
drugs.
   ``Believe me when I tell you that once I made the choice to do
drugs all my other choices were made for me,'' he wrote.
   After serving time in California, the convict wrote, he returned
to Hartford, where he developed a $500-per-day crack habit. He
wrote that he would often go four days without sleep, and overdosed
so often he was embarrassed to show up at the hospital.
   ``I felt like an idiot every time I went,'' he wrote. ``Then
when it was over and I could leave the hospital, I'd go right out
and get high again.''
   He had this advice for his readers: ``If you're doing drugs now
I won't tell you to stop. You have to make the decision to get help
for yourself. I will, however, tell you one thing your dealer
doesn't tell you. All drugs come with a triple guarantee. 1) Jails
2) Institutions 3) Death.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0068 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 1828EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Handguns 1stLd-Writethru a0664 07-08 0458</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Handguns, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0664,370</SECOND>
<HEAD>Study: Hundreds of Thousands Confronted By Criminals With Handguns</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: Subs 4th graf, ``The study xxx to delete redundant reference
to number in lead and point out that no state and local breakdown
available; subs 9th graf, ``Seventy-two xxx to include accounting
of unknown and reporting category to make percentages add to 100;
subs last two grafs prev with one graf to clarify comparison of
statistics</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By JAMES ROWLEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An estimated 639,000 Americans are confronted
each year by criminals carrying handguns, including 9,200 people
who are killed and 15,000 left wounded, according to a report
released Sunday.
   A Justice Department study of crime statistics covering 1979
through 1987 showed that 44 percent of all people murdered during
the nine-year period were killed by assailants wielding handguns.
   Guns were used in 7 percent of the rapes, 18 percent of
robberies and 22 percent of the aggravated assaults during the
period considered by the department's Bureau of Justice Statistics.
   The study was based on victims' reports taken by the
department's annual National Crime Survey. It did not break down
the figures by state or city.
   In an average year during the period, there were 9,200 murders,
12,100 rapes, 210,000 robberies and 407,600 assaults committed by
criminals with handguns, the Justice Department said. An average of
15,000 people a year are wounded by assailants possessing handguns,
the agency said.
   Fifty-one percent of the murders and non-negligent manslaughters
committed by people with handguns occurred when shots were fired
during an argument or a fight, according to the study.
   It said also that 25 percent of such killings took place during
the commission of another crime.
   In an average year, the Justice Department said approximately 27
percent of the 2.3 million crimes involving weapons of any sort
were committed by people with handguns. Other types of guns
accounted for 8 percent, or 180,100 of such crimes.
   Seventy-two percent of the handgun crimes were committed by
people who were strangers to the victim, the department said.
Acquaintances carrying guns committed 17 percent of those crimes.
Relatives of the victim committed 5 percent of handgun crimes. The
other 6 percent were in the ``unknown'' or ``unreported''
categories.
   Americans living in cities, particularly black men between the
ages of 16 and 24, were more likely to encounter criminals armed
with handguns, the study said.
   The rate of handgun crimes was 5.9 per 1,000 city dwellers
versus 2.7 per 1,000 among suburban residents and 1.7 among
residents of non-metropolitan areas, the Justice Department
reported.
   There were 32 handgun crimes per 1,000 urban black males between
the ages of 16 and 24, compared to 14 per 1,000 for white city
dwellers in the same age bracket.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0069 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 1833EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Kenya-Asylum 2ndLd-Writethru a0697 07-08 0716</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Kenya-Asylum, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0697,0736</SECOND>
<HEAD>Source: Prominent Human Rights Figure Seeks Asylum at U.S. Embassy</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 12 grafs to UPDATE with unconfirmed reports that
three dead in unrest. Pickup pvs 13th graf, `Regarding Muite...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By DIDRIKKE SCHANCHE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NAIROBI, Kenya (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A prominent human rights lawyer under
threat of arrest for his criticism of Kenya's one-party government
has sought refuge at the U.S. Embassy, a source said Sunday.
   Also Sunday, stone-throwing demonstrators confronted police in
Nairobi's commercial center, where a day earlier police had fired
tear gas and live ammunition to disperse a pro-democracy rally.
   Witnesses said they saw at least two people injured Sunday.
There were unconfirmed reports that three people were killed.
   By late Sunday afternoon, at least three trucks carrying scores
of heavily armed troops had moved into the area. Riot police
bearing clubs were seen in surrounding neighborhoods occasionally
firing canisters of tear gas to break up groups.
   In once incident, police using a club beat a man who was
subsequently hospitalized. Elsewhere, a youth was crushed between a
bus and a van in an accident caused when bystanders started
throwing stones at traffic, a witness said.
   Human rights Lawyer Gibson Kamau Kuria, a former detainee who in
1988 won the Robert F. Kennedy human rights award, had gone into
hiding late Thursday after the government detained at least 12
advocates of multiparty democracy.
   It was unclear when Kuria, 43, reportedly moved into the U.S.
mission in downtown Nairobi. But the source, who spoke on condition
of anonymity, said the lawyer was there.
   U.S. officials, including Ambassador Smith Hempstone, refused
comment on the status of Kuria or Paul Muite, another lawyer who
also went into hiding after last week's arrests.
   The United States has criticized the crackdown on the
opposition, and the ruling party's newspaper threatened the U.S.
ambassador with expulsion in an editorial on Sunday that was
titled: ``Shut up, Mr. Ambassador.''
   Saturday, riots erupted after a rally supporting multiparty
democracy turned violent and police dispersed the crowd with
gunfire and tear gas.
   Police pursued demonstrators into Nairobi's commerical center
and the disturbances quickly spread throughout the city. But by
nightfall, only small bands of demonstrators remained, playing
cat-and-mouse with the troops.
   Newspapers said scores of people were injured in Saturday's
violence. Hospitals provided no casualty figures and the government
issued no comment.
   Regarding Muite, his wife and associates said the lawyer was
safe, but would not reveal his whereabouts.
   Philip Kilonzo, Kenya's national police chief, said authorities
still were trying to find the two lawyers. ``We have not given up
our efforts to get them,'' he was quoted as saying in Sunday
editions of the ruling party's English-language newspaper, the
Kenya Times.
   The U.S. State Department protested the arrests in a statement
last week.
   ``These actions only serve to tarnish Kenya's image in the
international community,'' the State Department said in a comment
issued Saturday.
   Previous U.S. suggestions that Kenya consider multipary
democracy have angered the government, which at one point
threatened to curtail Hempstone's movement.
   President Daniel arap Moi has rejected the idea, and Cabinet
ministers have called those backing such moves subversives.
   Moi repeatedly has threatened to arrest opponents. He claims the
existence of about 40 tribes in Kenya would invite tribal-based
parties, leading to ethnic divisions and even warfare.
   On Sunday, the ruling party newspaper responded to the State
Department's recent comments in an editorial. It described
Hempstone as the ``epitome of developed-world conceit of the vilest
kind'' and threatened him with expulsion.
   He ``will have only himself to blame should Kenya find it
necessary to declare him a persona non grata,'' it said.
   ``He should remember that he is a diplomat, a person sent by his
government to promote good will between states, and not an
international political terrorist,'' said the editorial.
``Diplomacy is most effectively conducted quietly, and not through
self-righteous pronouncements.''
   Hempstone seemed unruffled by the editorial, which he described
in a telephone interview as ``an outrageous piece of work.''
   The United States is a major donor to Kenya, whose economy is
heavily dependent on foreign aid. Last year the U.S. gave $61
million in economic aid and $15 million in military assistance,
according to a study prepared by The Heritage Foundation, a
conservative think tank in Washington.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0070 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 1847EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Albania 1stLd-Writethru a0713 07-08 0999</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Albania, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0713,1028</SECOND>
<HEAD>Albanians Settle In For Wait</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 22nd graf `Hungarian TV...' with seven grafs to add
details on scene at Hungarian embassy, Hungarian television
interview with pretender to Albanian throne. Pickup 23rd graf pvs
`In Geneva ...'
^LaserPhotos PAR3, PAR4</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By GEORGE JAHN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>VIENNA, Austria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A promise of freedom secured, thousands
of Albanians in Tirana settled in Sunday for an uncomfortable wait
in crammed foreign embassies surrounded by vigilant police.
   Foreign governments, already pondering the logistics of
evacuating the Albanians in their missions and resettling them
abroad, were faced with the more immediate problem of housing and
feeding them in the meantime.
   More than 5,000 people were sheltered in missions, some of them
overcrowded. The situation appeared worst in the West German
mission, which was overflowing with 3,000 Albanians. The Italian
and French embassies also reported difficulties in taking care of
the refugees.
   A baby girl was born during the night in the West German mission.
   Security forces were back on duty Sunday. They were withdrawn
from the area late last week under foreign pressure following
reports that they had shot at asylum-seekers scrambling up embassy
walls.
   The French Foreign Ministry reported that the diplomatic quarter
was sealed off Sunday by 600 police officers and soldiers who
blocked anyone from getting through. Austrian TV said police
roadblocks had been set up on main roads into Tirana.
   On Saturday, Albanian Foreign Ministry officials told diplomats
that the Albanians in the embassies would be allowed to leave under
foreign supervision.
   The officials said embassy personnel could accompany the
asylum-seekers as they picked up travel documents and left the
country.
   But only those accepted as refugees by foreign countries would
be allowed to leave, the diplomats said. A Hungarian diplomat said
the embassies were told they had to arrange transport for any
Albanians they accepted.
   No departures were expected for days while arrangements were
made for travel documents and transportation.
   There were no reports Sunday of unrest. On Saturday, thousands
gathered near embassy row for silent rallies against Communist
rule, Austria's APA news agency said.
   The turmoil at the embassies appeared to contribute to a
shake-up Saturday of the ruling Politburo and Central Committee.
One Politburo member was dismissed, three other functionaries were
retired and the police minister and minister of war were fired.
   The reorganization was reported by the state ATA news agency and
state-run television. The reports named Hekuran Isai as the new
police minister and Kico Mustaqi as the new minister of war.
   Mustaqi is believed to be more moderate than his predecessor,
but Isai had already held the ministry under the late Enver Hoxha
and was considered close to the founder of Communist Albania. His
reappointment indicated a determination to keep a tight rein on
dissent.
   Some foreign missions lacked sufficient food and water for the
refugees and hygenic conditions were poor, officials said Sunday.
They said Albanian authorities were not allowing foreign
governments to send supplies.
   ``The situation in our embassy, but in other embassies as well,
has become intolerable,'' West Foreign Minister Hans-Dietrich
Genscher told West German television.
   In Paris, the French Foreign Ministry described the situation at
its embassy as increasingly difficult, with inadequate sanitary
facilities and a lack of medicine. There was no word of major
illness.
   The embassy was sheltering more than 500 Albanians, and a French
doctor was seeing 60 patients a day, many of whom were injured
while scaling the compound's fence, said the ministry.
   Italian Sen. Franco Salvi said in Rome after returning from a
private visit to Tirana that 900 Albanian asylum-seekers wanted to
come to his country.
   ``We hope we can welcome them in a dignified way,'' he said.
``We just can't throw them in some camp.''
   The ambassador's wife was forced to buy food at the local market
to feed those in the mission, Salvi said. Two prefabricated huts
were hastily erected on embassy grounds to house some of the
Albanians.
   Hungarian television news showed a small but jubilant crowd in
the Hungarian embassy, waving their passport application forms and
flashing V-for-victory signs.
   A Hungarian diplomat, speaking on condition of anonymity,
described the mood among the approximately 40 Albanians in the
embassy as optimistic.
   He said the Albanians had received a Red Cross shipment of
clothes, were exercising regularly in the embassy garden, and were
filling out forms to receive their travel documents.
   ``We are all set to take the forms to the Foreign Ministry
tomorrow morning and to discuss what the next step will be,'' the
diplomat said.
   Hungarian television also broadcast an interview with Leka I,
the pretender to the Albanian throne who is now an arms dealer in
South Africa.
   Speaking from his farm near Johannesburg, Leka called for the
overthrow of the Communist regime and claimed he had support ``in
the security service, in the army, and ... even ... some party
member supporters.''
   Leka is the son of King Zog, the last Albanian monarch who
abdicated after World War II.
   In Geneva on Sunday, U.N. Secretary-General Javier Perez de
Cuellar said he had sent a Swedish U.N. diplomat to Tirana to
obtain firsthand information on the situation.
   During 45 years of hard-line Communist rule, travel for average
Albanians has been virtually impossible. But Albanian leaders have
sought better ties abroad since 1985, and they recently began to
implement some reforms.
   A package of new regulations that took effect Tuesday entitled
all Albanians over age 16 to own a passport.
   Communist leader Ramiz Alia decreed several measures Saturday to
reform Albania's command economy, including the introduction of
small-scale private enterprise. But he did not mention the embassy
standoff or promise political reforms.
   The reported breakthrough on the embassy crisis came hours after
Albanian legislators guaranteed citizens could leave the embassies
without fear of punishment.
   The parliamentary decree, published by ATA, was the first pledge
with the force of law that Albanians in the foreign missions could
receive passports without fear of prosecution.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0071 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 1858EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-WorldCup-Newspage     07-08 0551</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-World Cup-Newspage,0569</SECOND>
<HEAD>West Germany Wins Soccer's Most Coveted Trophy</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TERRY LEONARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ROME (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Andreas Brehme scored a penalty goal with just six
minutes left Sunday to beat defending champion Argentina and bring
soccer's World Cup trophy back to West Germany for a third time.
   After the match, Argentine coach Carlos Bilardo rushed onto the
field to pull his players away from Mexican referee Edgardo
Codesal. He was being pushed and bumped as players angrily
protested the penalty point that won the match.
   The mostly German crowd of more than 73,000 roared approval when
Codesal signaled that defender Roberto Sensini had fouled striker
Rudi Voeller. Brehme scored, kicking the ball into the lower left
corner of the net past the outstretched goalie, Sergio Goycoechea.
   The win ended years of frustrations for the West Germans, World
Cup runner-up against Italy in 1982 and against Argentina in 1986.
   West Germany has now joined Italy and Brazil as the only
three-time winners of the tournament.
   Argentine defender Nestor Lorenzo left the field in tears with
blood dripping from his mouth. His teammates seemed stunned by the
penalty and the loss that ended Argentina's hopes of becoming the
first team to win two consecutive cups since Italy did so in 1938.
   After the award ceremony, joyous German players took a victory
lap around the stadium, rushing toward the delirious, singing,
cheering, flag-waving German fans and holding the trophy
triumphantly over their heads.
   West Germany's victory comes after a month of heart-touching
triumph and dream-shattering defeats for the other 23 teams in the
finals.
   No other competition stirs passions and national pride as much
as this tournament for soccer's most coveted trophy.
   Italy's state-owned RAI television network, which made live
coverage of the 52 matches available to about 150 countries, said
an average of 400 million viewers saw each game.
   When England lost to West Germany in the semifinals, fans went
on a rampage in nearly 30 English cities. More than 500 people were
arrested and 35 police officers injured in a night of brawling and
vandalism.
   By contrast, in Yaounde, Cameroon, most of the capital's 1
million residents thronged the streets to welcome back the national
team that staged the biggest upset in World Cup history, beating
Argentina 1-0 in the opening match.
   Cameroon also beat Romania and made it to the second round of
the tournament, one the great surprises of the competition.
   World Cup veterans said the 1990 tournament lacked some of the
drama of earlier cups. Still, it had its moments.
   Italy's Salvatore Schillaci mesmerized a nation with his uncanny
ability to find the opening, the ball and the net. The pride of
Sicily was the Cup's top scorer with six goals.
   Cameroon's Roger Milla provided some of the most enduring images
of this World Cup, dancing in the corners after he scored. The
comparatively old, 38-year-old substitute came out of retirement
and off the bench to score four World Cup goals.
   But there were other enduring images, such as blue-helmeted
police using tear gas and truncheons disperse rowdy fans who hurled
stones, bottles or chairs at police, rivals or each other.
   Italian authorities stationed thousands of police at stadiums
and banned the sale of alcoholic beverages on match days in cities
where games were played.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0072 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 1910EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Nicaragua 1stLd-Writethru a0702 07-08 0426</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Nicaragua, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0702,0439</SECOND>
<HEAD>Nicaragua Police, Strikers Face Off After Week of Walkouts</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS thruout to UPDATE with President Chamorro urging
workers to return to job; no pickup.
^By RODOLFO GARCIA</NOTE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MANAGUA, Nicaragua (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Violeta Barrios de Chamorro
on Sunday urged thousands of striking Sandinista workers to return
to the job after police threatened to intervene to reopen shuttered
workplaces.
   But the strikers vowed to keep them shut in the week-old wave of
walkouts to protest government policy.
   ``It is the obligation of all workers to go back to work
tomorrow,'' the president told The Associated Press in an interview
Sunday.
   A police communique, released Saturday evening, said, ``Police
will guarantee workers free access to their respective job sites''
beginning Monday.
   The communique also warned citizens not to disturb the peace,
conduct street demonstrations without permission or block traffic.
   The police warning will not convince an estimated 90,000
strikers to back off from their demands, Sandinista National Labor
Front head Lucio Jimenez told reporters.
   ``Faced with a position of force, we have to respond the same
way,'' Jimenez said Saturday.
   The government has tried to head off the strike with economic
concessions, but workers have held out with political demands.
   On Friday, Finance Minister Emilio Pereira announced a 43
percent wage increase for civil servants in lower pay brackets,
plus cost-of-living increases for 65,000 of the government's
100,000 workers.
   But National Labor Front leader Jose Angel Bermudez said the
offer was an effort to fool state employees.
   ``It's an attempt to get the workers back on the job and buy off
their just demands by means of a solemn joke about salaries,''
Bermudez said. He said inflation will eat up the earnings and
massive firings are in the offing.
   Government agricultural, industrial, service and office workers
are demanding a new minimum wage, job security, protection of
peasant land distributed under land reforms of the former leftist
Sandinista administration, financing for industrial ventures and
the opening of new construction projects.
   Private sector employees have joined the government workers in
demands for more participation in economic policy-making.
   The workers are allied with the Sandinista Front, which remains
the largest single political bloc in Nicaragua.
   The series of strikes is the second in the 2-month-old
administration of Mrs. Chamorro.
   Mrs. Chamorro was the candidate of the U.S.-backed United
National Opposition coalition in the Feb. 25 elections, in which
she beat Sandinista party incumbent Daniel Ortega. She is trying to
reverse his party's centralized government policy and replace it
with free-market strategy.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0073 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 1952EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BRF--BannedBeachBoys 1stLd-Writethru a07eP.Hall'sTexasGentstayedcloseearly
07-08 0166</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Banned Beach Boys, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0758,0162</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mayor Overrules Motion That Would Have Allowed Beach Boys Concert</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: CORRECTS name to Carmen sted Carmon in 3rd graf</NOTE>
<DATELINE>ISLE OF PALMS, S.C. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The mayor of this resort town
overruled a city council decision to allow a Beach Boys concert
here, saying the town's ``silent majority'' opposed the performance.
   After a heated debate, council members Friday night approved by
a 5-3 vote a request by the California group's promoter Rick
Tisdale for permission to sell and distribute up to 15,000 tickets
for the Aug. 26 concert on the beach.
   But Mayor Carmen Bunch said the council ignored pressing traffic
conditions and safety concerns created by the concert. She said the
city's ``silent majority, the type of people who don't attend
meetings,'' were opposed to the concert.
   The Beach Boys decided to move their benefit performance for the
city's fire department to a park in Ladson, about 20 miles inland
from Isle of Palms.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0074 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 1918EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Germany-WorldCup 1stLd-Writethru a0753 07-08 0444</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Germany-World Cup, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0753,0456</SECOND>
<HEAD>Germans Celebrate World Cup Victory</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 16 grafs to UPDATE with one fan killed, one
injured, Nazi salutes in East Germany. No pickup.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By KEVIN COSTELLOE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WEST BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   West Germans poured into the streets drinking
champagne and setting off endless rounds of fireworks Sunday night
to fete their team's 1-0 triumph over Argentina in the World Cup
soccer championship.
   In Berlin, victory celebrations almost matched the madhouse
scenes that accompanied the opening of the Berlin Wall in November.
   Hundreds of people popped champagne corks and trampled on the
bottles, leaving many downtown areas littered with glass. Others
drank beer and danced on car tops.
   Some celebrating East Germans gave the Nazi outstretched-hand
salute.
   In Cologne, West Germany, one frenzied fan jumped out of a
streetcar window and died when he was run over by a car, police
said. Several scuffles with police were also reported.
   In Hamburg, about 20,000 fans massed in the St. Pauli district,
many of them throwing bottles and fireworks at police. At least one
person was injured.
   Thousands of people crowded the elegant Kurfuerstendamm shopping
street in West Berlin, many carrying huge West German flags to
celebrate the victory in Rome.
   ``What a celebration!'' said the announcer on West Germany's ARD
television network. ``I think that for many people, this Sunday
will have more than 24 hours.''
   The soccer victory capped an amazing year for the Germans, who
are expecting full unification of their two nations within months.
   ``East, West: it doesn't make any difference. It's just
Germany,'' said a jubilant Reyk Burghardt, a 20-year-old railroad
worker from East Berlin, as he waved a West German flag.
   In Berlin, the constant sound of fireworks rumbled through the
cool night air, and bright lights flashed across the city.
   ``O-le, O-le, O-le, O-le!'' people shouted at the top of their
lungs, using the Spanish greeting ``Ole,'' a traditional cry in
soccer stadiums.
   ARD television provided live shots of fans waving flags and
cheering wildly.
   ``I can't even hear myself,'' the television's reporter
complained as he waded into the crowd.
   In East Berlin, thousands of raucous youths smashed bottles,
overturned tables, destroyed concession tents and tipped over a
giant keg of beer in the sprawling plaza in front of the Old
Museum, where a 40-foot television screen had been set up.
   Marina Hinz said she felt ``joy, nothing but joy.'' She also
carried a huge West German flag.
   The celebrations stretched throughout West Germany, from
Flensburg in the north to Bavaria in the south. Huge victory
parades blocked city centers in Munich, Stuttgart, Frankfurt,
Cologne and other major cities.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0075 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 1958EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-SummitProtests     07-08 0208</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Summit Protests,200</SECOND>
<HEAD>Protesters Get Early Start at Summit</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HOUSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   More than 3,000 advocates of more spending on
AIDs research marched through downtown Houston Sunday on the eve of
the 16th economic summit of the world's richest nations.
   The demonstrators carried signs and flags from each of the seven
countries attending the summit.
   ``Our message to the world leaders is `Get off the stick and
help health worldwide,''' said Bob Kunst, executive director of
Miami-based Cure AIDS Now, which sponsored the march.
   ``There is no international plan to cure AIDS and that's why we
are here _ to demand it,'' Kunst said.
   Later in the day, protesters demonstrated against protesters in
a park across from the gates of Rice University, where the summit
will commence Monday.
   Anti-abortion demonstrators were mocked by a dozen members of a
separate AIDs group, Act Up, who in turn were derided by a
similarly small contingent from the American Family Association, an
anti-gay group.
   Police drew their riot sticks at one point, but no violence
erupted and no arrests were made.
   The anti-abortion demonstrators, representing 50 Houston area
churches, planted 4,400 crosses in what they called the ``Cemetery
of Innocents'' to symbolize the number of reported daily abortions
in America.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0076 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 2000EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-FireworksInjuries     07-08 0187</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Fireworks Injuries,0192</SECOND>
<HEAD>Six Workers Injured in Finale of Bay City Fireworks Festival</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BAY CITY, Mich. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An aerial rocket misfired, sparking an
explosion that injured six workers at the Bay City Fireworks
Festival, authorities said Sunday.
   About 100,000 people had gathered along the banks of the Saginaw
River Saturday night for the festival's finale and Gov. James
Blanchard had just left the firing area when the accident occurred,
state police said.
   A 10- to 12-inch fireworks shell ``exploded just as it was
clearing the mortar tube,'' said policewoman Linda Collier. ``It
blew low and ignited three or four other firecracker shells near
it.''
   One of the Wolverine Fireworks workers, Terry McPeak, was in
serious condition at Bay Medical Center, hospital spokeswoman
Sharon Dewaele said.
   Technician Patrick Myer and Michigan State Police Sgt. Robert
Harkin were in fair condition, Dewaele said.
   Pyrotechnicians Bob Carrigan and Scott Robertson were treated
and discharged from the medical center, she said.
   The sixth worker, Dave Byer, was taken to Saint Mary's Hospital
in Saginaw where he was in fair condition, said a nursing
supervisor who declined to be identified.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0077 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 1936EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Summit-Rodeo 3rdLd-Writethru a0729 07-08 0602</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Summit-Rodeo, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0729,600</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ride 'Em Cowboy: Bush Hosts Rodeo and Barbecue</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: New throughout with barbeque color, edits to shorten</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By RUTH RENDON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HOUSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   It was bodacious Texas fun.
   With cattle lowing in the background and dust swirling through
the air, the leaders of the free world threw horseshoes, sampled
barbeque and watched cowboys at work Sunday evening.
   President Bush appeared to delight in showing his VIP guests a
country-style evening of entertainment before they turned their
attention to Monday's economic summit opening.
   They tramped through sawdust-covered artificial turf to a
horseshoe pit and took a turn at Bush's favorite pasttime. The
president out-pitched his guests, landing two ringers. Then they
trooped through a buffet line, plates awkwardly in hand, to sample
some of the 3{ tons of meat barbecued for the occasion.
   The president also lined up a rodeo and a rare out-of-town
performance by the Grand Ole Opry for his guests' amusement.
   The men were dressed casually: Bush and Canadian Prime Minister
Brian Mulroney both sported the fancy ostrich cowboy boots made
especially for the economic summit. Japan's leader, Toshiki Kaifu,
showed off an oversize western belt buckle. British Prime Minister
Margaret Thatcher picked her way through the sawdust in
white-and-black heels.
   Cowboys were competing in such events as bareback riding, bull
riding, barrel racing and calf scramble, said Dan Gaddis of the
Houston Livestock Show &amp; Rodeo, an annual affair that draws more
than a million people each winter.
   ``What could be better than a rodeo, great country music and
`the taste as big as Texas,''' said Mike Jolley, president of
Houston-based Luther's Bar-B-Q Inc., which was providing the food
for the rodeo party, which was expected to draw several thousand
people.
   It took 140 workers more than four days to slow cook all that
barbecue, including brisket, sausage, chicken and ribs. Crews also
made more than 1{ tons of coleslaw, potato salad and beans.
   Naturally, there were also 1,250 gallons of barbecue sauce,
pickles and jalapenos, 500 pounds of onions, more than 5,000
servings of cobbler and carrot cake and 650 gallons of lemonade and
iced tea.
   Bush and the foreign leaders were dining on china made by
Austin, Texas, potter Teri Vance Hubbeling, who said she had worked
nearly non-stop since being asked to create the 63 festive plates
with a Texas theme. She designed three different patterns _ a
centered longhorn with green cactus in the background and blue
trim, a race horse with boots in the background and a longhorn with
barbed wire in the background.
   Rocky Carroll, who has made numerous boots for Bush, said he
worked about 40 hours to create each pair of the full-quill ostrich
boots for the visiting leaders.
   The boots sport the seven flags of the participating nations
across the top. Each boot's center front has a Texas flag and
``Houston'' stitched along the bottom. The leaders' initials are
stitched in gold along the side.
   ``These are the finest pair of boots I've ever made,'' said
Carroll, owner of R.J.'s Boot Co. in Houston.
   Carroll also provided the sterling silver belt buckles with gold
inlay, beaver cowboy hats and boot bags. The Grand Ole Opry
presented mandolins for the leaders.
   The Opry performance marked only the second time in 40 years the
country show had left its Nashville home. The first was in 1988,
for a special show in Tampa, Fla., in connection with the Hall of
Fame football game.
   Besides Minnie Pearl and Charley Pride, stars on hand were to
include Loretta Lynn and Larry Gatlin and the Gatlin Brothers.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0078 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 1940EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Argentina-WorldCup     07-08 0350</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Argentina-World Cup,0362</SECOND>
<HEAD>Despite Loss, Argentina Celebrates World Cup Final</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By WILLIAM H. HEATH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUENOS AIRES, Argentina (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Thousands of soccer fans, many
wrapped in the national flag, filled the capital's streets Sunday
to mark their team's second place finish in World Cup soccer.
   The fans shouted, sang, danced and blew horns and whistles to
celebrate, despite Argentina's 1-0 loss to West Germany in Rome.
Argentina was the defending champion.
   ``Win or lose, we love the national team,'' chanted more than
3,000 celebrating fans gathered in the Plaza of the Republic in
Buenos Aires.
   President Carlos Menem, who watched the game on a giant
television screen in Government House, echoed the sentiments of
many fans when he said that West Germany played masterfully.
   However, he also criticized the referee who awarded the penalty
shot that allowed Germany to score its lone goal with just six
minutes left.
   ``Germany took the ball and dominated play,'' said Menem in a
statement. ``Argentina was an incomplete team, and we lost with an
unfair goal because the penalty was not merited.''
   ``As far as the referee is concerned,'' Menem added, ``he should
take up medicine.'' Referee Edgardo Codesal ordered the penalty
shot and expelled Argentina's Pedro Monzon late in the game.
   Jose Maria Pedrazo, a fan, said Argentina ``was lucky to reach
the finals and West Germany deserved the victory _ but not that
kind of victory, not on a penalty.''
   Pedrazo and his wife, Elvira, were in the Plaza of the Republic
joining the celebrations.
   Sunday was treated like a national holiday in Argentina. The
sky-blue and white national flag was hung from windows and
balconies of thousands of high-rise apartments. Many Argentines
called friends to organize parties to watch the game.
   Sidewalk entrepreneurs sold flags, hats, and banners with a
likeness of Diego Maradona, Argentina's team captain.
   Police, seeking to head off a repeat of the vandalism and
looting that followed Argentina's semi-finals victory over Italy,
stationed 5,000 officers in the downtown area.
   Two people were killed and 200 arrested in incidents after the
win over Italy.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0079 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 2004EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ChemicalFirms-Dioxin 1stLd-Writethru a0746 07-08 0547</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Chemical Firms-Dioxin, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0746,0555</SECOND>
<HEAD>Companies Withheld Information on Dangers at Jacksonville Plant</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: CORRECTS city to Jacksonville sted Fayetteville in 3rd graf;
SUBS last graf to CORRECT to nearly 30,000 sted more than 30,000;
no pickup</NOTE>
<DATELINE>JACKSONVILLE, Ark. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two of the country's largest chemical
companies withheld information from employees on the toxic nature
of dioxin wastes at a local chemical plant, a newspaper reported
Sunday.
   Officials of Hercules Inc. and Dow Chemical also knew about
dangers of dioxins, a class of chemicals generally considered
unwanted byproducts that may cause a range of ailments, as early as
1965 and were concerned the government would learn about the
dangers, the Arkansas Democrat reported.
   Hercules operated the Jacksonville chemical plant and Dow
contracted with Hercules to produce herbicides, including 2,4,5-T,
a dioxin-contaminated herbicide. Hercules also made the
dioxin-tainted defoliant Agent Orange at the plant from 1967-70.
   The newspaper said it obtained memos beginning in 1965 from
chemical company officials in Delaware, Michigan, Germany and
Arkansas that show wastes at the Jacksonville plant were tested for
dioxin, which had caused outbreaks of a skin ailment called
chloracne in chemical plant workers in the United States and abroad.
   Hercules, Dow and Jacksonville plant officials knew as early as
April 1, 1965, that dioxin was ``highly toxic'' and ``capable of
inducing a disfiguring disease from dermal (skin) exposure to very
small amounts,'' an internal Hercules memorandum said, the
newspaper said.
   Officials of both Dow and Hercules declined comment on the memos.
   Management didn't tell employees they were working with dioxin
for many years _ not until publicity about the chemical began
appearing _ and then downplayed its dangers, workers told the
newspaper.
   ``They never explained the danger to us. They never stressed the
danger to us,'' said Joe Bolden, who worked at the plant for nine
years.
   He said workers would frequently get burned by the chemicals.
   ``If something got on you, you would go to the laboratory and
they said it's not going to hurt you. Just take a shower,'' Bolden
said.
   ``I remember people talking about dioxin. They said we had it
but not to the extent that it would hurt anybody. I didn't get
anything officially from anybody,'' said Luster Kennedy Jr., a
former plant safety director.
   The newspaper said one memo sent on July 12, 1965, by J.R.
Frawley, a toxicologist at Hercules' corporate office in
Wilmington, Del., to two officials at the Jacksonville plant
summarized a telephone call he received from Earl Farnham of Dow.
Dow was concerned about an ``acnegen,'' or dioxin, causing
chloracne in workers at its 2,4,5-T plant in Midland, Mich.
   ``They are aware that their competitors are marketing 2,4,5-T,
which contains `alarming amounts' of acnegen and if the government
learns of this, the whole industry will suffer. They are
particularly fearful of a congressional investigation and excessive
restrictive legislation on manufacture of pesticides might
result,'' Frawley wrote.
   Vertac Chemical Corp. of Memphis bought the plant in 1976. It
ceased production in 1986 but did not abandon the site.
   The site is 18th on the federal government's Superfund list, a
roster of more than 1,000 of the nation's hazardous chemical sites.
Later this year, incineration is scheduled for nearly 30,000 drums
of hazardous wastes stored at the site.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0080 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 2007EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Hungary-Holocaust     07-08 0374</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Hungary-Holocaust,0386</SECOND>
<HEAD>Monument to Holocaust Victims Unveiled in Budapest</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ALEX BANDY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUDAPEST, Hungary (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A monument dedicated to the 600,000
Hungarian Jews who died in the Nazi Holocaust was unveiled Sunday
at the gates of this city's former Jewish ghetto.
   About 1,000 people, including some Holocaust survivors, attended
the unveiling ceremony for the monument, which stands at the site
of the mass grave of 6,000 Jews killed in Budapest.
   The huge black granite and steel memorial, designed by Imre
Varga, one of Hungary's best known artists, depicts a weeping
willow in the shape of an inverted menorah, the seven-branched
Jewish candelabrum.
   Among the dignitaries on hand were Interim President Arpad
Goencz, Prime Minister Jozsef Antall, World Jewish Congress
President Edgar Bronfman, and film star Tony Curtis. He is the
honorary chairman of the Emanuel Foundation, which raised funds for
the monument.
   ``Over 40 years had to pass before Jews and non-Jews could
gather here to remember the victims,'' said Goencz, a writer and
former political prisoner. He was chosen as interim president in
May by Hungary's new democratically elected parliament.
   ``The crimes of the Nazis cast a shadow over generations. This
was not only a Jewish, but also a Hungarian tragedy.''
   Antall pleaded for reconciliation between Christians and Jews,
adding that ``this common tragedy has poisoned the atmosphere _ a
poison present to this day.''
   He pledged that Hungary's new non-Communist government ``will do
its utmost to let Jews live in Hungary without fear.''
   Bronfman noted that there have been increased signs of
anti-Semitism in Hungary and other countries in Eastern Europe,
which are making the ``painful' transition from a Communist command
economy to a free market system.
   ``Human nature is such that some people require a scapegoat,''
Bronfman told reporters.
   He welcomed the new government's resolute stand against
anti-Semitism and praised the former government for not bowing to
Arab pressure to halt flights by the national airline Malev
carrying Soviet Jews to Israel.
   About 80,000 Jews now live in Hungary, giving it Eastern
Europe's second largest Jewish community after the Soviet Union.
Before the Nazi Holocaust, 1 million Jews lived in Hungary.
   A total of about 6 million Jews died in Hungary and elsewhere
during the Holocaust.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0081 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 2012EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>d a AM-BRF--BabyMurder     07-08 0181</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Baby Murder,0184</SECOND>
<HEAD>PTA President Charged in Death of Infant in her Care</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A PTA president who cared for children in her
home has been charged with murder in the death of a 9-month-old boy
who suffered a fractured skull while in her care.
   Debra Cummings, 32, of Reseda, pleaded innocent Friday in Van
Nuys Municipal Court. Cummings, the mother of a 6-year-old girl and
the president of the Shirley Avenue Elementary School Parent
Teachers Association, was ordered held without bail.
   The infant, Kevin Young, was in Cummings' care almost daily for
six months.
   Cummings told police that Kevin, who died June 16 at a hospital,
apparently fell and hit his head on a coffee table while she was in
another room. But a coroner's report concluded the baby was hit
with hands or fists.
   Authorities said they were investigating the death of another
child who died in Cummings' care. Fourteen-month-old Matthew Cooley
lost consciousness while he was at a park with Cummings last March.
His doctor said his death was the result of a seizure.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0082 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 2009EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-BigDrugRaid     07-08 0449</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Big Drug Raid,430</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.S. Officials Say No U.S. Troops Would Be Used In Reported Drug
Raid</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   U.S. officials stopped short Sunday of denying
a report that plans are being developed for a U.S.-coordinated
military attack on drug lords in South America, but said there has
been no change in the policy of not involving U.S. forces in direct
operations.
   Newsweek reported Saturday it has obtained briefing papers from
U.S. Southern Command headquarters in Panama that envision an
attack coordinated by the Southern Command and using the armies of
Colombia, Bolivia and Peru to attack drug-trafficking targets in
those countries.
   National Security Adviser Brent Scowcroft said on CNN's
``Newsmaker sunday'' that it would be a ``real misnomer'' to refer
to the operations as a ``big drug raid'' as suggested by an
interviewer.
   ``U.S. troops will be used the same way they've always been
used,'' he said. ``That is, when asked for they will help train
local military. They will not be used operationally. In
interdiction and intelligence, for example, in tracking and so on,
yes, we will use the military, as we have been doing it all along.''
   Asked whether the reported operation signals an escalation of
the drug war, Scowcroft said: ``No. Well, hopefully, it's an
intensification, it's not an escalation.
   Newsweek said the attack would involve a massive use of force
applied swiftly and simultaneously to ``the cartel's entire support
structure,'' possibly targeting drug lords' homes, drug-processing
centers and secret airfields used for smuggling.
   U.S. troops would direct the operation but would not take part
in it unless ``the need arises,'' the magazine reported.
   ``Our policies are clear,'' said Defense Secretary Dick Cheney.
``We're doing in Central America, Latin America, what we can to
help those nations that are involved, where there is production. We
only do what they ask us to do. Our involvement is limited in the
sense that no U.S. forces are permitted to go out on operational
assignments and no U.S. forces participate in any activities down
there unless I've personally signed off on their presence in those
countries.''
   Cheney did not respond directly when pressed on CBS' ``Face the
Nation'' to comment on specifics of the Newsweek account.
   ``I suppose you could argue that at present you've got a
situation where the military units in those countries are actively
involved in fighting the drug cartel and we are actively involved
in supporting them ... by coordination and support and
assistance,'' he said.
   Although the plan reportedly is almost ready to be carried out,
Newsweek said members of Congress _ fearful the operation could
escalate into another Vietnam, with high U.S. casualties _ were
unlikely to view it favorably.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0083 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 2014EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Summit-Bush 1stLd-Writethru a0722 07-08 0730</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Summit-Bush, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0722,750</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush Shows Off Houston to Summit Partners</HEAD>
<HEAD>EDs. Leads with 4 grafs with rodeo color; pickup 2nd graf pvs:
``The economic,'' and deletes now redundant 11th graf pvs, `Later,
out'' and subs last 2 grafs to make Kaifu reference conform and
update with World Cup score</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CHRISTOPHER CONNELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HOUSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush showed off his adopted hometown to
his summit partners Sunday, worshipping at church with Britain's
Margaret Thatcher, shooting baskets at his favorite health club
with Canada's Brian Mulroney and landing two ringers in a
horseshoe-pitching display.
   He jogged with local runners in an urban park, sported a new
pair of cowboy boots emblazoned with summit flags and the map of
Texas, and played host at a down-home barbecue and rodeo for his
summit guests and a thousands of others at an arena next to the
Astrodome.
   Mulroney also wore new cowboy boots to the rodeo _ a present for
all the summit leaders from presidential bootmaker Rocky Carroll of
Houston _ and a 10-gallon hat. Mrs. Thatcher opted for white heels,
but Bush assured reporters she, too, had gotten a pair of summit
boots.
   Bush demonstrated his horseshoe prowess by tossing two ringers.
Japanese Prime Minister Toshiki Kaifu pitched a few, too, but with
less success.
   The economic summit was still 24 hours away, and three
summiteers _ France's Francois Mitterrand, Italy's Giulio Andreotti
and West Germany's Helmut Kohl _ weren't even in town yet. But
George Bush was enjoying himself.
   He began the sabbath at St. Martin's Episcopal Church, his
parish from his days here as an oilman and then congressman. It's
near both his old neighborhood and the Houstonian, the hotel where
he now hangs his hat.
   With six priests on the altar, three altar boys and an altar
girl, it was a high church communion service that drew not only
Bush and wife Barbara but British Prime Minister Thatcher, her
husband Denis and Secretary of State James Baker III and Treasury
Secretary Nicholas Brady and their wives.
   The Bushes, the Thatchers and the Bakers all took communion.
Brady, a Roman Catholic, did not.
   Back at the Houstonian, Bush dropped his wife off and traded his
suit and tie for sneakers, a summit T-shirt and gray shorts.
   After a short ride, he alighted from the presidential limousine
in Memorial Park, where he set off down the exercise trail with his
protocol chief, Joseph Reed, Secret Service agents and a pack of
delighted local joggers.
   The entourage quickly swelled to more than three dozen,
including a man pushing a baby in a stroller and a woman with two
small dogs.
   When a reporter called out ``Houston's Hot'' _ the slogan the
city has adopted for its $10 million summit festivities _ Bush took
it literally and replied, ``No, it's not bad yet. Not bad. It's
going good.''
   As he waited beneath a maroon canopy at the Houstonian for
Canadian Prime Minister Mulroney to arrive, Bush displayed a touch
of reticence on summit substance, turning aside reporters' efforts
to question him about a letter from Soviet President Mikhail S.
Gorbachev.
   Bush did join the Canadian leader before the microphones to
announce plans to launch negotiations on an acid rain agreement.
   Mulroney, who normally revels in give-and-take with reporters,
followed his host's lead and beat a fast retreat afterward.
   ``We're going to head on in,'' Bush said, asking if Mulroney was
going to take questions from the Canadian press.
   ``I think the Canadians have been in the heat too long,'' said
Mulroney, turning his heels on a press corps that had stood in the
sweltering heat for 45 minutes.
   The two men had a private lunch with their wives, then the
president took the prime minister over to the Houstonian's
million-dollar health club, where they shot a few baskets and
checked out the other swank facilities.
   Only Mulroney, Thatcher, Kaifu and Jacques Delors, head of the
European Community and the eighth summit principal, were in town
for the rodeo and Grand Ole Opry concert.
   Mitterrand, Kohl and Andreotti were all due in Monday morning,
shortly before the opening ceremonies at Rice University. The West
German and the Italian spent their Sunday in Rome with their eyes
riveted on the World Cup soccer final between West Germany and
Argentina. Kohl was rewarded with a 1-0 triumph for his homeland.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0084 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 2024EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SriLanka     07-08 0446</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Sri Lanka,0461</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rebels Kill Eight Soldiers, Wound 16</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PATRICK CRUEZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>COLOMBO, Sri Lanka (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Tamil rebels detonated mines under a
military truck and an armored car Sunday, killing eight government
soldiers and injuring 16, officials said.
   It was the latest bloodshed in a 27-day-old round of fighting
that has killed at least 2,109 combatants in the separatist war.
   The mines, buried in a road near Vavuniya, 140 miles north of
Colombo, went off as the vehicles passed over them, military
officials said.
   Also Sunday, President Ranasinghe Premadasa appealed to the
international community to help start peace talks with the
separatist rebels. They began a new round of fighting on June 11
for control of the northeastern section of this island nation off
the southern tip of India.
   ``It is only with the involvement of the international community
in a manner acceptable to us that the dialogue can recommence,''
Premadasa told a meeting of government officials in Puttalam, 80
miles north of Colombo.
   The president did not elaborate on his statement, but government
sources said Premadasa was making an indirect request to
international organizations to mediate between the government and
the rebel militia, known as the Liberation Tigers of Tamil Eelam.
   The government has so far maintained that talks can only begin
if the Tamil Tigers lay down their arms.
   In the eastern town of Batticaloa, where the latest round of
fighting began, six charred bodies were discovered Sunday.
Residents of the port town, 135 miles east of Colombo, said the
victims were young Tamil men, most likely civilians.
   Five charred bodies were also found Friday and Saturday in
different places in Batticaloa, residents said on condition of
anonymity.
   It was not immediately clear who killed them, but the killings
have created panick in the government-controlled town.
   The government claims to control most of the eastern districts
after rebels fled into the jungles, but acknowledges the north is
still in rebel hands.
   On Saturday, government troops blew up a rebel ammunition dump
and shot and killed 21 militants in the northeastern district of
Trincomalee, a Defense Ministry statement said.
   The recent round of fighting ended a 13-month cease-fire. The
Tamil Tigers are fighting for the independence of the
Tamil-majority north and east from the rest of Sri Lanka, which is
predominantly Sinhalese.
   Tamils make up 18 percent of Sri Lanka's 16 million people. The
Sinhalese comprise 75 percent of the population and dominate the
government, military and police.
   Tamil militants claim their community is discriminated against
by the Sinhalese majority in jobs, education and the use of Sinhala
language.
   More than 13,000 people have been killed in the 7-year-old
revolt.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0085 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 2058EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-India-Punjab     07-08 0197</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-India-Punjab,0206</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bomb Explosion in Punjab Kills Two, Injures 35</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW DELHI, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A powerful bomb exploded Sunday at a
vegetable market in a town in the northern state of Punjab, killing
two people and injuring 35, news reports said.
   There were no immediate claims of responsibility, but Sikh
separatists seeking an independent nation were believed responsible.
   In other violence, Sikh militants killed at least 11 people on
Saturday and Sunday in Punjab, United News of India said.
   The news agency said the bomb exploded in a shop in the town of
Fatehgarh Churian, 22 miles north of Amritsar, the Sikh holy city.
   Amritsar, which is about 240 miles northwest of New Delhi, is
the focal point of the Sikh separatist movement.
   At least 1,300 people have been killed in Punjab this year in
violence linked to the separatist movement.
   Sikh militants have been demanding an independent state since
1982, accusing India's Hindu majority of political and cultural
discrimination against their community.
   Sikhs represent only 2 percent of India's 880 million people but
are in a majority in Punjab, a prosperous farming state bordering
Pakistan.
   Hindus make up 82 percent of the country's population.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0086 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 2108EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Spain-Bulls     07-08 0272</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Spain-Bulls,0282</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bulls Gore Three, Injure 32 During Famed Festival</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PAMPLONA, Spain (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Three people were gored and 32 other
people slightly injured Sunday in a running of the bulls at the
storied San Fermin festival.
   They were hurt while testing their bravery by running in front
of six bulls through cobblestoned streets for a half-mile to the
city bullring.
   Navarre Hospital said Andres Barani, a 32-year-old Swede living
in Madrid, was gored in the face. It said Jose Luis Place, a
Frenchman, was gored in the buttocks.
   The third man, an unidentified Spaniard, was gored in the left
thigh.
   Navarre Hospital said 32 other runners received treatment for
bruises and scrapes. Dozens of young men took part in the event.
   The bulls run every morning at 8 a.m. and are killed in the
afternoon in bulllfights. Sunday's running was the second in the
weeklong festival.
   The bull running, made famous by American author Ernest
Hemingway, are part of a non-stop drinking and dancing festival in
honor of San Fermin, the city's patron saint. The festival began
Saturday and is to continue through July 14.
   One Spaniard was seriously injured and 58 others received
on-site treatment Saturday.
   The festival, which attracts thousands of tourists from around
the world every year, was the setting for Hemingway's 1926 novel
``The Sun Also Rises.''
   The novel described in detail the rowdy, round-the-clock
festival that awakens with the morning run of the bulls.
   Except during war years, the festival has been held continously
since 1591. Since then, bulls have gored to death 52 people, 13 of
them since 1924 when Hemingway first visited Pamplona.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0087 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 2137EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Japan-Greenpeace     07-08 0331</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Japan-Greenpeace,0343</SECOND>
<HEAD>More Than 30 Boats Join Greenpeace Protest Outside U.S. Base</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   More than 30 Japanese rubber boats, kayaks and
other small craft joined a Greenpeace yacht Sunday in an
anti-nuclear demonstration off a U.S. Navy base near Tokyo, a
Japanese officials said.
   Protesters on the boats shouted, ``Don't bring nuclear weapons
into Japan!'' said an official of the Maritime Safety Agency,
Japan's coast guard.
   Led by the 38-foot Greenpeace yacht Vega, the Japanese boats
formed a circular peace sign in the water, said the official, who
spoke on condition of anonymity.
   The official said nine patrol boats were mobilized to prevent
the protest boats from sailing into the base at Yokosuka, 28 miles
southwest of Tokyo.
   He said there were no clashes between demonstrators and coast
guard patrols.
   The environmental group's yacht carried three crew members from
the United States, New Zealand and Australia and a Japanese
interpreter, the official said. The group has offices in London and
Washington.
   At a park near the U.S. base, about 100 Japanese held a rally to
demand that U.S. Navy ships not bring any nuclear weapons into
Japan, the official added.
   On Friday, the Vega, displaying anti-nuclear signs, trailed the
67,000-ton U.S. aircraft carrier Midway out of Yokosuka, its home
port.
   Faith Doherty, Pacific coordinator for Greenpeace's Nuclear Free
Seas campaign, said the protest marked the start of a 1{-month
voyage around Japan by the Vega to educate people about the dangers
of nuclear weapons and nuclear propulsion.
   The Midway is not nuclear-powered, but many Japanese claim that
it and other U.S. Navy ships using Japanese ports carry nuclear
weapons in violation of a Japanese ban.
   The subject is sensitive in Japan, the only nation ever attacked
with atomic bombs.
   The United States refuses to comment on the location of any of
its nuclear weapons. But the Japanese government has said the
United States would need Japan's permission to bring in such
weapons but never has sought such authorization.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0088 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 2138EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Colombia-Miners     07-08 0294</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Colombia-Miners,0308</SECOND>
<HEAD>Emerald Miners Sign Peace Accord in Colombia</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By STEVEN GUTKIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MEDELLIN, Colombia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Emerald miners have signed a peace
accord, a mining official announced Sunday, after seven years of
warfare that killed an estimated 3,000 people.
   The so-called ``Emerald Wars'' have also exacerbated violence
perpetrated by drug traffickers, leftist guerrillas and private
right-wing armies.
   Four warring groups signed the peace accord, Jose Forero,
manager of Emeralds of Colombia mining company, said in a
communique. The four emerald-mining groups agreed to stop shooting
at each other and allow the courts to decide disputes.
   The groups have been seeking to gain control of the rich emerald
mines in eastern Colombia. Emeralds are one of Colombia's largest
legal exports.
   The war has forced thousands of residents to flee their homes.
Violence has restricted transportation and cut off food supplies.
   There have been reports of alliances and clashes between miners
and drug dealers. Some drug lords reportedly have large investments
in the mining operations.
   In another development in Colombia's second-largest city,
Medellin, six policemen were assassinated since Friday night,
police said Sunday.
   The deaths raised to 136 the number of law enforcement officials
murdered this year in the city, home to the country's leading
cocaine cartel.
   The report said five of the policemen were off-duty, unarmed and
in civilian dress when they were killed. The sixth was in uniform
and patrolling the streets on a motorcycle when he was killed, it
said.
   After one killing, soldiers chased, shot and killed two of the
assassins, the police report said.
   Authorities have blamed the assassinations on drug traffickers
who are fighting a U.S.-backed government crackdown on the cocaine
trade.
   Drug cartels are reportedly paying $4,300 for each assassination
of a law enforcement official.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0089 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 2153EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-SummitRdp 4thLd-Writethru a0769 07-08 1081</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Summit Rdp, 4th Ld-Writethru, a0769,990</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush Says He'll Brief Summit Leaders on Gorbachev Aid Appeal</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Fourth graf new with Bush remark. May stand for AMs.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By TERENCE HUNT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP White House Correspondent</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HOUSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush threw a Texas-style welcome for
Western leaders Sunday on the eve of an economic summit already
divided by an appeal from Mikhail S. Gorbachev for aid to bolster
the crumbling Soviet economy.
   U.S. and British officials dug in their heels against direct
aid. But Prime Minister Brian Mulroney was more sympathetic,
extending commercial credits to Moscow and saying, ``Houston has to
provide the beginnings of an economic response.''
   Bush said he would present a letter from Gorbachev when leaders
of the world's seven richest democracies convene Monday for their
16th annual economic summit. The letter, dispatched July 4, came to
Bush in his role as summit host.
   ``Tomorrow we go to work,'' Bush told a cheering audience after
a festive night of pre-summit partying. ``I think we're all working
for the same thing, for world peace, for harmony in this exciting
world we're living in.''
   To strengthen the Soviet case for aid, foreign ministry
spokesman Gennadi Gerasimov said Moscow was taking steps demanded
by Bush. He said the military was being cut down to size, and that
Moscow's huge subsidies to Cuba would ``fade away, but not
tomorrow.''
   Two of the western leaders delayed their arrivals to attend the
World Cup soccer championship in Rome. Helmut Kohl cheered West
Germany to a 1-0 victory over Argentina, and Italy's Giulio
Andreotti was there to present the trophy.
   Trade and environmental issues were being aired at the summit,
but the question of direct aid to Moscow topped the agenda. The
United States, Japan and Britain said Moscow wasn't ready for aid
from the West, while West Germany, France and Italy were ready to
plunge ahead.
   British Foreign Secretary Douglas Hurd said Sunday: ``We don't
believe that they (the Soviets) have the economic requirements in
place ... which would justify putting huge sums of Western money
into their pockets. Their pockets have got holes in them.''
   Canada was somewhere in the middle. Mulroney was anxious to find
some approach to support Gorbachev.
   ``Where would we be if he were chucked out?'' Mulroney asked.
``If he were chucked out by some of the extreme right influences we
see at play in the Soviet party conference that is ongoing in
Moscow today, I think we would be at an infinitely worse position
than we are today.''
   And yet, Mulroney called Soviet aid to Cuba ``profoundly
unacceptable'' and an obstacle to western aid.
   In a CBS interview, Gerasimov addressed the three main obstacles
Bush has described to direct aid from the United States: Economic
reform, military spending levels and subsidies to Cuba.
   Specifically, he said Moscow's $5 billion annual subsidy to Cuba
would ``fade away, but not tomorrow,'' as the Soviets shift to
market prices for sugar purchases and oil sales. Moreover, he said,
``We are now taking steps to cut our military to size. That is why
they are grumbling, some of the generals.''
   Canada was not ready to provide direct aid, but Mulroney said,
``Yes, we will provide credits ... We want to send out a signal
that this leadership in the Soviet Union is valid and valuable.''
The $2 billion (Canadian, about $1.7 billion in U.S. funds) in
credits have been granted for wheat and other products.
   National security adviser Brent Scowcroft said Gorbachev is
asking for help for a couple years as he implements his economic
reforms.
   ``It will be a time of austerity and troubles, and what he would
like is some assistance to help tide over while those economic
restructuring programs are taking hold,'' Scowcroft said on CNN.
   He said Gorbachev was interested in ``food aid, consumer aid ...
to give some hope to the average Soviet citizen that things are
getting better.'' Asked if the United States would provide that
help, Scowcroft said, ``It's very difficult for the United States.''
   Bush would not describe Gorbachev's entreaty, explaining, ``I
have some responsibilities to be sure that our summit partners are
briefed on that Gorbachev letter before we go public.'' But sources
said the letter was a general appeal for assistance from the West,
but made no specific requests.
   Bush, in his adopted home state of Texas, hosted a home-style
howdy for the arriving summiteers. There were cowboys and barbecue,
bull riding and bucking broncs, at a Sunday night rodeo. And, the
Grand Ole Opry left its hometown of Nashville to be here for a
special broadcast, featuring Minnie Pearl and Loretta Lynn.
   Bush and Mulroney showed up for the festivities in newly made
summit cowboy boots. Margaret Thatcher of Britain wore white heels.
Bush treated his guests to a horseshoe throwing match and threw two
ringers himself. Japan's Toshiki Kaifu tried several pitches, to no
avail.
   The economic summit follows hard on the heels of last week's
16-nation meeting which rewrote NATO war-fighting strategy in
accordance with reduced East-West tensions.
   The nations represented here are Britain, France, Canada, Italy,
and West Germany, Japan and the United States.
   Britain's Hurd said the Soviet's government-controlled economy
wasn't equipped to cope with massive Western assistance. The
summit's message, he said, should be ``mend the hole in the pants
before you fill the pockets with dimes and cents.''
   Secretary of State James A. Baker III _ asked about direct U.S.
aid to Moscow _ said, ``No, that's not right now in the cards.''
Instead, he emphasized that the United States would continue to
give technical assistance such as advice on how to move toward a
market economy.
   West Germany and France have been pressing for a $15 billion
package of Western aid for Moscow. Leaders of the European
Community, meeting in Dublin last month, agreed in principle to
provide assistance but stopped short of committing themselves to a
specific program or amount.
   A formula for compromise has been suggested by Baker. He said
recently the Houston summit could reach agreement on a set of
guidelines and principles for assistance, short of actually sending
aid.
   Bush removed another contentious issue from the summit agenda
when he told Japanese Prime Minister Toshiki Kaifu that the United
States would not object to a resumption of Japanese aid to China.
   Japan, under pressure from Beijing as well as Japanese
businesses, wants to resume at least part of the $5 billion aid
package it promised to China two years ago.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0090 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 2304EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-AbortionAt-A-Glance     07-08 0207</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Abortion At-A-Glance,0211</SECOND>
<HEAD>Key Aspects of Louisiana's Abortion Bill</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Louisiana Abortion, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BATON ROUGE, La. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are key elements of an abortion
bill passed by the Louisiana Legislature. The bill outlaws most
abortions by creating a new simple battery offense. Under the bill:
   _ Simple battery of abortion is the specific intent of
terminating a pregnancy other than to preserve the life or health
of an unborn child or to remove a dead fetus.
   _ Abortion on a rape victim is not a crime, providing the victim
sought medical care from a licensed physician within seven days of
the rape, reported the rape to law enforcement authorities within
seven days of the offense and had the abortion within the first
trimester of the pregnancy.
   _ Abortion performed in an incest pregnancy is not a crime if
the abortion is performed in the first trimester.
   _ Only a licensed physician may perform an abortion in the
circumstances allowed by law.
   Although simple battery in Louisiana ordinarily is a
misdemeanor, with a maximum six-month prison term and $500 fine,
abortionists under this bill would face prison at hard labor for
one to 10 years, with fines of not less than $10,000 or more than
$100,000.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0091 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 2329EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-LouisianaAbortion 12thLd-Writethru a0801 07-08 1009</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Louisiana Abortion, 12th Ld - Writethru, a0801,1032</SECOND>
<HEAD>Louisiana Legislature Bans Abortion in Most Cases</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Leads with 15 grafs to bring up discussion of legislature's
procedure for passing bill, adds quote from anti-abortion
legislator, CORRETS to show Roemer spokeswoman, sted spokesman made
comment; picks up 13th graf, `Saunders said...</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By GUY COATES</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BATON ROUGE, La. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Legislature on Sunday passed the
strictest state abortion bill, which would ban most abortions and
punish doctors who perform them with up to 10 years at hard labor.
   The state Senate earlier had failed to override the governor's
veto of an even harsher measure that would have restricted abortion
even in cases of rape and incest.
   To pass Sunday night's measure, legislators cannibalized a
failing flag burning law and outlawed abortion by creating a new
crime: simple battery of abortion. The bill was hurried through the
Legislature hours after the override failed.
   The bill passed 83-22 in the House after a 32-7 vote in the
Senate. It passes now to Gov. Buddy Roemer.
   The bill bans abortions except in cases of rape, incest or where
the mother's life is in danger. It carries a penalty of up to 10
years in prison and a $100,000 fine for doctors who perform
abortions. It would not penalize the woman who seeks the abortion.
   Simple battery in Louisiana ordinarily is a misdemeanor, with a
maximum six-month prison term and $500 fine.
   Pennsylvania currently has the strictest state abortion law, but
it is less restrictive than the Louisiana bill.
   The Senate earlier had failed to override Roemer's veto of a
bill that didn't allow abortion even in instances of rape and
incest. So Sen. John Saunders amended anti-abortion language onto
an unrelated bill.
   Roemer has indicated he would accept an abortion bill that
contained the rape and incest exceptions. Through a spokeswoman,
Roemer said he had not seen Sunday's bill and would not comment on
it until Monday.
   Abortion rights supporters reacted with incredulity.
   ``We've just seen the Legislature go from the most restrictive
abortion bill in the nation to the most absurd,'' said Terri
Bartlett of Planned Parenthood of Louisiana. ``The only thing that
surpasses it is the mockery of the legislative process.''
   ``Only in Louisiana could you have a flag burning bill become an
abortion bill.''
   Rep. Woody Jenkins, the original bill's author, voted against
the new version because of his belief ``that the unborn is a human
being from the moment of conception and we ought not make
exceptions to the principle.
   ``Even though I could not vote for the bill in the form that
passed out, it is my hope and prayer that it will be used to test
the continued validity of Roe vs. Wade, that it will be used to
stop the senseless killing of millions of unborn children.''
   Proponents of the abortion bill hope it will be challenged all
the way to the Supreme Court, leading to a showdown over the 1973
high court ruling that legalized abortion.
   The bill Saunders chose to amend was another controversial bill
_ one that would lower the penalty to a $25 fine for people who
beat up flag burners. His version of the bill stripped it of the
flag burning provisions and inserted the abortion issue.
   Saunders said his amendment was the only chance the state had of
passing an anti-abortion bill.
   ``I don't want any more abortions than we have to have,'' he
said.
   The Senate sustained Roemer's veto of the earlier bill Saturday
with a 23-16 vote to override, three short of the needed two-thirds
majority.
   The Pennslyvania measure, approved in November, requires a woman
wait 24 hours before getting an abortion, bans abortions based on
the fetus' sex and bans abortions after the 24th week of pregnancy
except to save the life of the mother or prevent ``substantial and
irreversible harm.''
   A doctor convicted under the sex-selection ban or the 24-week
provision could be punished with up to seven years in prison and a
$15,000 fine.
   An even stricter abortion bill was passed in the U.S. territory
of Guam. But it has been blocked for now by court challenges. That
law makes it a felony to perform an abortion or aid in the
procedure, a misdemeanor for a woman to have an abortion and a
misdemeanor for a person to solicit a woman to have an abortion.
   As the Senate began its work Sunday, some 1,000 demonstrators
gathered on the Capitol steps and in the rotunda that separates the
Senate and House chambers. A strong majority appeared to be backers
of the anti-abortion bill, but there were also scores of abortion
rights activists.
   Near the doors of the rotunda, in black spray paint, someone had
scrawled the words ``Stop Killing the Innocent.'' A few feet away,
abortion-rights advocates had taped a poster to the wall that read
simply ``Sustain, Sustain, Sustain.''
   About 300 to 400 of the anti-abortion demonstrators, some
carrying Bibles and singing hymns, began a continuous march around
the Capitol in the 90-degree heat. ``We're marching around the
walls of Jericho,'' one shouted.
   At 3:30 p.m., a sudden thunderstorm came up and sent many of the
demonstrators scurrying for cover.
   Senate President Samuel Nunez said lobbying Saturday and Sunday
was intense, with thousands of telephone calls jamming switchboards.
   ``People were even calling the House switchboard for us becaue
they couldn't get through,'' Nunez said Sunday morning. ``Our
secretaries didn't keep any record of how many were for one thing
and how many were for another.
   ``I did get a call from a woman purporting to be representing
the Vatican. I talked to that woman who wanted me to change my
vote. Naturally, I was suspicious and asked for her phone number. I
said I would call her back. Well, she turned out to be a resident
of Mandeville and works with the Friends of Americas.''
   Friends of the Americas is a non-profit organization set up by
Rep. Woody Jenkins, who is author of the abortion bill. The
organization aids Nicaraguan refugees.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0092 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 1436EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-SolarCarRally     07-08 0537</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Solar Car Rally,0554</SECOND>
<HEAD>GM-Sponsored Solar Car Rally Set for Monday</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By FREDERICK STANDISH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Auto Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DETROIT (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Teams of college engineers begin a race with the
sun Monday.
   Thirty-two college and university teams take off from Orlando,
Fla., for an 11-day jaunt in solar powered cars, hoping to prove
the efficiency of their designs as the auto industry looks for ways
other than gasoline to power vehicles.
   The route covers more than 1,600 miles of secondary state and
county roads in eight states, and the contestants are bound to
attract some curious stares along the way.
   The vehicles are a long way from any assembly line. One of the
chief considerations goes to wind resistance, which means that the
cars hug the ground, are basically flat and have no styling
excesses.
   ``It won't necessarily be the fastest car that wins,'' said
General Motors Corp. Vice President Donald L. Runkle. ``Instead, it
will be the car performing most efficiently.''
   ``The team that can adapt most consistently to the daily routine
will have the best chance of coming out on top,'' said Runkle, who
heads the advanced engineering staff for the giant automaker, which
sponsors the rally along with the federal Department of Energy and
the Society of Automotive Engineers.
   GM and other automakers worldwide have been researching new ways
to power vehicles for years. Much of the research has centered on
fuels other than gasoline, including methanol, methanol-gasoline
mixes, ethanol and natural gas.
   Late last year, GM unveiled its Impact electric car. Its
performance of 0-60 mph in about eight seconds and a cruising range
of about 120 miles on a single charge impressed industry observers.
   Strategy for the race began during the weekend at the Daytona
International Speedway in Florida. The teams went through
qualifying heats to determine the order of start on Monday.
   ``We want to make sure they are all roadworthy,'' GM spokesman
Dave Sloan said Friday.
   Cars are entered from a variety of colleges and universities
ranging from tiny Crowder College in Neosho, Mo., to the University
of Texas and Massachusetts Institute of Technology. Teams from
Puerto Rico and Canada also are entered.
   Each team received $5,000 from GM and $2,000 from the Energy
Department along with whatever funds could be raised through the
school, local and state governments or elsewhere.
   That's only part of the investment. For instance, about $750,000
has been spent on the car from the University of Michigan.
   Vehicles will start each day at 30 second intervals, with the
previous day's winner going first. Average speeds are expected to
be in the 30 mph range. Crews will be allowed to charge batteries
for two hours before and after each day's racing.
   The winner will be the team with the least total elapsed time.
The course passes through Florida, Georgia, Alabama, Tennessee,
Kentucky, Ohio and Indiana before winding up at the GM Technical
Center in Warren, Mich., north of Detroit, on the afternoon of July
19.
   The top three finishers will be sponsored by GM in worldwide
solar car competition later this year in Australia. GM's Sunraycer
solar vehicle won the first worldwide solar car race in 1987.
   The Sunraycer is on display in the Smithsonian Institution.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0093 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 1540EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-GumshoeAccountants 1stLd-Writethru   07-08 0748</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gumshoe Accountants, 1st Ld-Writethru,0780</SECOND>
<HEAD>Accountants Dog S&amp;L Crooks, Hunt For Doctored Books</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 5th graf to restore dropped first reference to Sibley.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By JOHN A. BOLT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DALLAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Robbers do not need guns _ pencil and paper will
do.
   So say two accountants who have built a business of finding
financial fraud.
   ``Put enough zeroes behind a number, and it's amazing how
flexible morals become,'' said James A. Smith, a partner of Smith,
Sibley &amp; Co. accountants.
   The firm, which specializes in the practice known as forensic
accounting, is one of many hired by the federal government to help
clean up the savings and loan industry.
   Smith and his partner, Kenneth Sibley, use traditional
accounting methods, tallying assets and estimating losses, to
detect the value of S&amp;L property and uncover fraud.
   ``It is ... very laborious, number-crunching ... meticulous
attention to detail,'' Smith said.
   But they've had some anxious moments during a few audits.
   Once a distraught executive was told the home office had ordered
him to hand over his books to Smith &amp; Sibley. He began pacing
around the office with a baseball bat.
   He never swung the bat, Sibley said, but it was close.
   Smith was introduced to forensic accounting via the Watergate
scandal.
   He helped unravel a slush fund through which Braniff Airlines
Inc. funneled money to pay bribes to gain South American landing
rights. Accountants discovered Braniff used the same fund for an
illegal contribution to Richard Nixon's 1972 re-election campaign.
   Over the years, forensic accounting has grown to about 15
percent of the firm's work. Sibley is one of 3,000 members of the
National Association of Certified Fraud Examiners.
   As part of a team working under contract with the Resolution
Trust Corp., Smith and Sibley now help determine the value of
assets held by insolvent thrifts that are under government
conservatorship.
   The partners have seen their forensic speciality take on more
importance as companies, especially small ones, realize their
profits are being stolen and call on the accountants for help.
   Fraud occurs in many small businesses because their owners do
not take care to protect their assets. ``They do not mind the
store,'' said Sibley.
   He likes to tell of the doctor who turned over all his
bill-paying to a nurse who used his charge account number to buy
things for herself.
   The doctor never bothered to look at the bills and only
discovered he was being robbed when his accountant asked why his
interest payments were so high.
   But small businesses are not the only victims. Smith and Sibley
related the twisted tale of one crook:
   A teller at a Dallas bank was convicted of making false entries
on the books of a savings and loan and sentenced to prison.
   Two months out of jail, he was working for a construction
company as a controller. He would make out false invoices to
fictitious vendors. After the owner of the company signed the
checks, the thief would blot out the fictitious vendor's name,
substitute his own and deposit them into his own account via night
deposit.
   The checks were always paid despite the obvious altering, and
$600,000 was stolen before the crime was discovered, Sibley said.
   It was too late to save the business; the losses broke the
company.
   The thief fled Texas, but turned up later in the offices of an
international accounting firm.
   ``He was again convicted and sent to the Wynne Prison in
Huntsville, where he wound up participating in the prison farm
accounting office,'' according to Smith &amp; Sibley's history of the
case.
   ``Not surprisingly, a huge shortage was found in the prison
accounting office.''
   Convictions are unusual, Sibley said, because many businesses
want only to recoup their losses and won't go to court.
   Such reluctance, he believes, has led to increased white collar
crime, although Sibley said he senses attitudes are changing.
   ``Management is more and more realizing that they have to send
people to jail,'' he said.
   He believes the attention given to multibillion-dollar savings
and loan scandals has spurred law enforcement agencies' interest in
white collar crime.
   ``In the past, it has not been publicized,'' Sibley said, and
``the lack of prosecution makes it more attractive.''
   Sibley hesitated when asked for specifics about his firm's
methods of tracking money. He preferred to talk in generalities
about access to sales receipts, bank records and numerous other
sources.
   ``Documentation, or in some instances lack of documentation,
builds the case,'' Sibley said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0094 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 1619EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-WineConsumption     07-08 0548</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Wine Consumption,0564</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.S. Wine Sales Down 5 percent 2nd Straight Year</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JACK SCHREIBMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN FRANCISCO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Wine consumption in the U.S. dropped
sharply for the second straight year in 1989, with Mississippians
drinking the least and tipplers in the District of Columbia the
most, a trade publication reported.
   Drinkers in California, New York and Washington, the top three
wine-producing states, drank the most wine per capita, but New
Hampshire was the only state to show a gain in consumption over
1988, according to Wines &amp; Vines.
   Americans last year drank 2.11 gallons of wine per capita, the
lowest consumption of any major wine-producing nation and a 5.8
percent drop from 1988. Consumption in 1988 dropped 5 percent from
1987 figures.
   By comparison, Americans over 21 drank 33.7 gallons of beer,
2.16 gallons of distilled spirits, and about 35 gallons of coffee.
Adult-only wine consumption was 3.03 gallons per capita.
   Reflecting a national trend against alcohol consumption,
individual states posted figures showing as much as a 19.5 percent
drop from 1988. That distinction went to Arizona, where a
half-gallon less of wine per capita was consumed last year than in
1988.
   The domestic wine market, including imports, fell 5.2 percent to
523 million gallons. It was a 64.1 million gallon drop from a high
point of 587.1 million gallons in 1986, the report said.
   Domestic table wines fell 2.6 percent while production of
domestic champagnes dropped 6.3 percent. Last year marked the
fourth straight year of decline for foreign champagne sales in this
country; they were down 7.8 percent to 12 million gallons.
   In 1985, champagne imports to the United States hit a peak of
15.8 million gallons, almost all of it from Italy, France and Spain.
   California wines accounted for 72.8 percent of all wine consumed
in the U.S. last year, while the other 42 wine-producing states
held 12.6 percent of the market. The rest of the market, 14.6
percent, were imports.
   Wines &amp; Vines blamed the market drop on the continuing loss of
ground of generic or jug wines, nearly all of it produced in
California's San Joaquin Valley, and a 16.7 percent dip in wine
cooler sales.
   It was the second double-digit loss in two years for the
coolers, sales phenomenon of the early 1980s that literally rescued
California wine for several years. In 1988 and 1989, cooler sales
fell 33.3 million gallons, falling from 21 percent of wine market
share to 17 percent last year.
   Still, the coolers _ mostly cheap white wine, fruit juice and
carbonated water _ represented one of six gallons of wine sold in
this country last year.
   There were at least three bright spots for the industry,
including a relatively weak U.S. dollar and its built-in price
advantage over imports.
   Blush varietals such as white zinfandel and white grenache,
prime fuels for the top selling white wine segment, continued to
gain market share, while the booming premiums, which cost over $3 a
standard bottle, increased 7 percent, at a slower rate than
previous postings.
   U.S. wine exports were up again in 1989, showing foreign sales
increased to a miniscule 22.1 million gallons in 1989 from 16.9
gallons in 1988. The top two markets are Canada, 5.7 million
gallons, and Japan, 5.5 million gallons.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0095 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 1626EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-WineConsumption-List     07-08 0280</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Wine Consumption-List,0334</SECOND>
<HEAD>With Wine Consumption</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SAN FRANCISCO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here is a table showing per capita wine
consumption in the United States in 1989, by state, according to
federal and California statistics gathered by the trade
publication, Wines &amp; Vines.
   The table lists the state, wine consumption per capita in
gallons in that state and the percentage change in per capita
consumption from 1988.
   Alabama, 1.04, down 7.1.
   Alaska, 2.64, down 5.7.
   Arizona, 2.10, down 19.5.
   Arkansas, 0.77 down 8.3.
   California, 3.75, down 10.1.
   Colorado, 2.28, down 3.8.
   Connecticut, 2.96, down 7.2.
   Delaware, 2.35, down 6.0
   District of Columbia, 5.55, down 11.3
   Florida, 2.47, down 6.1.
   Georgia 1.47, down 5.2.
   Hawaii, 2.62, down 4.7.
   Idaho, 1.80, down 15.5.
   Illinois, 2.17, down 5.7.
   Indiana, 1.19, down 7.8.
   Iowa, 1.12, down 4.3.
   Kansas, 0.78, down 15.2.
   Kentucky, 0.73, down 3.9.
   Louisiana, 1.39, down 1.4.
   Maine, 2.09, down 8.7.
   Maryland, 2.15, down 5.3.
   Massachussetts, 2.99, down 6.6.
   Michigan, 1.82, down 8.1.
   Minnesota, 1.65, down 10.8.
   Mississippi, 0.55, same.
   Missouri, 1.39, down 10.9.
   Montana, 1.76, down 8.3.
   Nebraska, 1.17, down 11.4.
   Nevada, 4.54, down 6.4.
   New Hampshire, 3.12, up 3.
   New Jersey, 3.17, down 1.6.
   New Mexico 1.71, down 12.3.
   New York, 2.64, down 6.0.
   North Carolina, 1.71 down 3.9.
   North Dakota, 1.03, down 8.8.
   Ohio, 1.38, down 8.1.
   Oklahoma, 0.81, down 4.7.
   Oregon, 2.88, down 10.
   Pennsylvania, 1.16, down 2.5.
   Rhode Island, 2.92, down 6.7.
   South Carolina, 1.48, down 6.9.
   South Dakota, 0.88, down 8.3.
   Tennessee, 0.86, down 4.4.
   Texas, 1.57, down 1.3.
   Utah, 0.72, down 5.3.
   Vermont, 3.21, down 7.0.
   Virginia, 1.95, unavailable.
   Washington, 3.18, down 7.8.
   West Virginia 0.66, down 9.6.
   Wisconsin, 1.89, down 6.9.
   Wyoming, 1.29, down 5.1.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900708-0096 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-90 1713EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-Summit-Environment     07-08 0560</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Summit-Environment,0580</SECOND>
<HEAD>Canada, U.S. To Begin Air Pollution Talks This Month</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Summit Rdp Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GUY DARST</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HOUSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush and Canadian Prime Minister Brian
Mulroney said Sunday their nations would begin negotiations on an
air pollution agreement this month.
   The announcement was foreseen a year ago when Bush decided to
seek new controls on the sources of acid rain, an issue Canada has
been complaining about for a decade.
   Both houses of Congress have passed different versions of
legislation requiring utility smokestacks to reduce extensively
emissions of sulfur dioxide and nitrogen oxides, the principal raw
materials causing acid rain.
   Environmentalists monitoring the economic summit welcomed the
announcement and said it was inevitable.
   In a session before the summit officially begins Monday, Bush
and Mulroney set an informal timetable for talks to begin on an air
pollution agreement.
   William Reilly, administrator of the Environmental Protection
Agency, will meet with his counterpart, Robert de Cotret, in
Ottawa, Canada, on July 16, the leaders said. Formal negotiations
should begin shortly after that, they said.
   ``I think this day will be long remembered in the history of our
relationship for the significant departure it constitutes from past
positions,'' Mulroney said. He and other Canadian leaders have been
rebuffed in the past in their attempt to prod the United States
into curbing pollutants.
   A White House announcement said the talks with Canada would
cover monitoring of emissions, exchange of information and
settlement of disputes.
   Scientists on both sides of the border agree about half the acid
rain falling in eastern Canada originates from emissions generated
by utilities and smokestacks in the United States. Because of wind
patterns, about a quarter of the acid rain falling in the
Adirondack Mountains of New York States originates in Canada.
   Former President Reagan argued that not enough was known to
conclude that acid rain was a serious problem; Canada said marine
life in as many as 14,000 lakes is in jeopardy.
   Environmentalists, meanwhile, denounced what they said was the
failure of the seven summit nations to live up to the rhetoric of
last year's meeting in Paris in which they pledged to protect the
world's environment.
   The leaders agreed in 1989 to end production of chemicals that
destroy the earth's protective ozone layer, said George T.
Frampton, president of The Wilderness Society.
   ``The reality is that our forests are being cut just as fast as
they were a year ago, Frampton said. ``Carbon dioxide and other
greenhouse gases are being emitted into the atmosphere at just the
same high volume, or even greater, than that of a year ago.
Population growth and ocean pollution have continued unabated.''
   An environmental coalition of 150 groups is keeping a scorecard
designed to hold governments accountable by publicizing their
records, Frampton said.
   The environmentalists have already ranked the countries
attending the summit.
   West Germany was rated top, followed by France, Britain, Canada,
the United States, Japan and Italy.
   The countries were ranked based on their policies on conserving
energy and reducing the threat of global warming; protecting
biological diversity such as that found in tropical forests,
abating pollution of the oceans, controlling population growth,
helping the cleanup of Eastern Europe and helping develoing nations.
   Germany's high score was ``the best of a bad lot,'' said Jay
Hair, executive vice president of the National Wildlife Federation.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
</Collection>
