<Collection>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0001 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 2336EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-FBIArrest     05-06 0292</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-FBI Arrest,0301</SECOND>
<HEAD>FBI Arrests Alleged Drug Cartel Members in Missile Plot</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   FBI agents arrested several people in a plot to buy
Stinger anti-aircraft missiles for Colombia's Medellin drug cartel,
federal officials said Sunday.
   The cartel may have planned to use the shoulder-fired missiles
to assassinate Colombian president Virgilio Barco, according to one
federal official in Florida, who spoke on condition of anonymity.
   Several people were arrested in Miami over the weekend in an
undercover oparation, said a law enforcement official in Washington
who also demanded anonymity.
   The suspects said they were working for reputed cartel leader
Pablo Escobar, who is wanted by U.S. authorities on
drug-trafficking charges, the source said. The missiles never
changed hands, the source said.
   A man was arrested in the Tampa area after promising undercover
agents he would provide Stinger missiles, the Florida source said.
More than two pounds of cocaine and one personal weapon were seized
in that arrest, the source said.
   The total number of people arrested was unclear.
   Larry Curtain, spokesman for the FBI's Tampa office, refused to
comment on any aspect of the case before news conferences scheduled
for 11 a.m. Monday in Tampa and Miami.
   ABC News reported Sunday that the drug cartel tried to buy more
than 100 Stinger missiles and a thousand machine guns for nearly $6
million.
   The New York Times, in an article Monday, put the number of
missiles involved at 24.
   ABC reported that unidentified sources said the alleged cartel
member had planned to use the missiles to shoot down planes and
helicopters carrying Barco and members of his cabinet. The attack
would be part of a campaign of violence that has already claimed
the lives of three presidential candidates in that country.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0002 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 2338EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-SouthKorea 1stLd-Writethru a0777 05-06 0543</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-South Korea, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0777,0562</SECOND>
<HEAD>Radicals Attack Governing Party Headquarters; Roh Appeals for Calm</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: UPDATES throughout with storming of party headquarters, Roh
speech, opposition statement, ADDS byline. No pickup</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By M.H. AHN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SEOUL, South Korea (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Roh Tae-woo on Monday
appealed to the nation to reject the ``road toward chaos.'' But
even as he spoke, radical students armed with firebombs and pipes
seized the governing party's headquarters.
   Plainclothes police firing tear gas recaptured the building 10
minutes after the takeover, arresting the students. One woman was
led away with blood dripping from her nose and mouth.
   Windows were broken and furniture smashed in the takeover, but
no damage estimate was immediately available.
   ``Right now we are in a difficult time,'' Roh, flanked by his
Cabinet ministers, told a nationwide television audience. ``We are
on a crossroads where the country can either be on a road toward
progress or fall into a road toward chaos.''
   Roh, whose governing party has been losing popularity, said
labor unrest, land speculation, crime and eroding confidence in the
economy were problems that all must work to solve.
   ``This is the time to decide the fate of the nation,'' he said.
   The opposition Party for Peace and Democracy warned Monday that
South Korea ``faces a very dangerous national crisis that threatens
the overall basis of democracy.''
   The party, in a statement, accused Roh of ``a plot ... to
prolong power'' by merging his party with two other opposition
parties. The merger was announced in January.
   Roh said the recent ``heightening of uneasiness'' had been
partly caused by what he called illegal labor strikes at the state
television network and the nation's largest shipyard.
   In the strike at the Hyundai Heavy Industries Co. shipyard,
dozens of workers barricaded inside a huge crane began a hunger
strike Sunday to press their demand for the release of jailed union
leaders, reports said.
   Officials at the shipyard in Ulsan, a port city 200 miles
southeast of Seoul, said they are prepared to negotiate an end to
the protest. But the workers have insisted on the release of the
jailed unionists before talks, the reports said.
   The protests began April 28, when 12,000 riot police fired tear
gas and stormed the shipyard to end the strike.
   In his speech, Roh said the government would guarantee a legal
labor movement, but ``will deal strongly with illegal labor
disputes or collective actions with political purposes.''
   The government maintains some of the recent labor disputes have
been politically motivated.
   He also pledged to build housing for workers and improve welfare
for poor people.
   ``The future of our economy depends on the will and efforts of
the government, business, workers and consumers,'' Roh said. ``The
government alone cannot run the economy.''
   He appealed to workers to refrain from demanding wage hikes
higher than productivity until the economy has recovered.
   Inflation has been increasing at an annual rate of more than 10
percent for the first time in many years and the stock market is at
a two-year low.
   In addition, exports are not selling well. Labor unrest, huge
wage increases and the rise of the South Korean won against the
dollar have hurt the competitiveness of the country's products
overseas.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0003 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 0013EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-AmericanContinental 1stLd-Writethru a0567 05-06 0559</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-American Continental, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0567,0571</SECOND>
<HEAD>Plan Proposed to Settle American Continental Bankruptcy Case</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: RECASTS lead to move up newspaper report on Keating's
resignation. Pick up 6th graf, `Bilby had ...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By MEL REISNER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PHOENIX (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Financier Charles Keating Jr. will resign as
chairman of American Continental Corp., the holding company he
founded which oversaw the failure of Lincoln Savings and Loan
Association, a newspaper reported Saturday.
   James J. Feder, a lawyer for Keating, said Keating will step
down as early as next week to help shareholders recover their
losses, The Arizona Republic said.
   To remain as chairman would be a conflict of interest, Feder
told the newspaper.
   Creditors of American Continental who say they lost more than
$200 million on junk bonds would get $21 million for starters under
a plan to settle the holding company's 13-month-old bankruptcy case.
   Lawyers for Keating, who built American Continental into a $6
billion holding company, complained they weren't asked to
participate in talks which led to the proposed settlement.
   The plan would require the company's failed savings and loan
subsidiary, California-based Lincoln Savings and Loan, to pay $21
million to settle numerous lawsuits against it.
   Lawyers for the Unsecured Creditors Committee of American
Continental and the government's Resolution Trust Corp., the entity
charged with cleaning up the nation's savings and loan mess,
announced their agreement Friday to U.S. District Judge Richard M.
Bilby. The RTC runs Lincoln Savings, which was seized by regulators
in April 1989.
   Bilby had been scheduled to rule Friday on a motion to replace
Keating with a trustee. The judge scheduled preliminary and final
hearings on the plan for June 7-8 and July 19-20.
   More than 50 percent of the creditors must vote on the proposal
for acceptance, and two-thirds must approve it.
   Lawyers handling lawsuits against the companies contend that
23,000 people were steered into risky investments by American
Continental or Lincoln employees and lost more than $200 million.
   The plan would end much of the litigation invlving the holding
company and Lincoln Savings.
   The day before regulators seized Lincoln Savings, American
Continental asked U.S. Bankruptcy Court here for protection from
creditors while it and 11 Lincoln subsidiaries reorganized. The
Chapter 11 action omitted Lincoln, allowing a Federal Deposit
Insurance Corp. takeover of the S&amp;L.
   A securities-fraud lawsuit against Lincoln and American
Continental claims Keating and others conspired in 1983 to buy
Lincoln to divert federally insured deposits to their own use.
American Continental acquired Lincoln in February 1984 for about
$51 million.
   In addition to liquidating the company, the proposal includes
dismissal of the bankruptcy cases of the 11 subsidiaries and of all
claims against Lincoln and its creditors by American Continental's
creditors, Veal said.
   It also calls for a partial resolution of claims by 23,000
investors who held $200 million in Lincoln ``junk bonds'' and for
``unwinding the corporate relationship between ACC and Lincoln by
assigning certain assets of ACC's bankruptcy estate to the RTC.''
The proposal did not identify those assets.
   The settlement doesn't affect an RTC civil lawsuit against
Keating, which similarly accuses him and other Lincoln insiders of
a racketeering conspiracy to buy Lincoln to divert federally
insured deposits for their own use.
   Keating's contributions to influential lawmakers figure in an
ethics probe of five U.S. Senators who met with regulators on
behalf of Lincoln.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0004 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 0023EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-ChildrenHit 3rdLd-Writethru a0631 05-06 0670</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Children Hit, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0631,0686</SECOND>
<HEAD>Car Plows Through Ballfield; Three Children Killed</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: INSERTS two grafs after ninth, `All of ....' to UPDATE with
quote from a team coach. Pick up 10th graf, `Of the ...'</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto CX7</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JAMES REINDL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>RIVERSIDE, Ill. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A speeding car veered through a baseball
field Saturday, killing three young children and injuring nine
other people before crashing into a building, officials said.
   Two of the six children injured were reported in critical
condition.
   ``I saw a car driving through the field, and I saw it hitting
kids,'' said Amy Ulrich, 14, who was babysitting at playground
equipment in Robinson Park in this Chicago suburb. ``It was going
kind of crazy and going real fast.''
   ``We heard people screaming,'' Miss Ulrich said, adding later
that ``We saw kids lying on the ground and parents kneeling by.''
   The car plowed through a fence into a bench on the third-base
line, hitting people on the field before continuing across a busy
street and ramming the glass and steel entrance to a medical
clinic, police said.
   ``Thank God no one was in the area'' of the clinic, said Anthony
Christiano, a police officer in Berwyn, an adjoining suburb where
the clinic is located.
   The driver of the late-model Cadillac, a man who appeared about
50 years old, was coherent after the 1:30 p.m. accident and was
taken to MacNeal Memorial Hospital in Berwyn, Christiano said. He
may have suffered a heart attack or some other medical problem, and
there was no indication he had been drinking, the officer said.
   ``It looked like someone had thrown a bomb in the Little League
field,'' said Riverside Fire Chief Anthony Bednarz.
   All of the injured children were 7 or 8 years old, said Michael
Maggio, spokesman for Loyola University Medical Center in Maywood,
where most were treated. Three were killed, Maggio said.
   Bob Wengerski, a coach of a T-ball team playing on the field,
said youngsters were dragged from the bench.
   ``I saw a car, a large car ... go right past me from behind and
hit the bench where my team was sitting and getting ready to bat.
And (it) took about nine or 10 kids through the restraining fence
out into the field where they dropped off one by one,'' he said.
   Of the six children injured, two were in critical condition at
Loyola, Maggio said. Another child was in serious condition and two
were in fair condition at Loyola, Maggio said.
   One child who suffered minor injuries was taken to La Grange
Memorial Hospital in La Grange, said Nancy Jacobus, a nursing
supervisor.
   Two adults suffered leg injuries and were taken to Loyola, said
Maggio, who identified them as Mike Larmon, 24, a baseball team
coach who was treated and released, and Bruce Anderson, 43, a
parent of one of the dead children. The elder Anderson was admitted
to the hospital and reported in fair condition.
   About 50 people were watching a T-ball game when the accident
occurred.
   The driver was in ``stable but guarded'' condition at MacNeal,
said hospital spokeswman Mary Pappas, who refused to provide
further details. The driver's identity was not released by late
Saturday.
   Roberto Alcantara, 8, of Riverside said he was at bat in the
game when the accident occurred. He said he didn't see where the
car came from, and recalled trying to talk to an injured teammate
afterward.
   ``I tried talking to one but he didn't answer,'' he said. ``I
hope they're OK.''
   T-ball is a type of baseball played by young children where the
ball is batted off a stationary ``tee'' at home plate.
   Helen Kolacki, who lives across from the park, said the field
was oddly quiet until ambulances from several Chicago suburbs began
to arrive.
   ``It was like people laying next to their children, trying to
talk to them or something,'' she said. ``There was one young man,
his foot was moving up and back, but the others were lying still.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0005 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 0033EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-IrvingBirth     05-06 0132</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Irving Birth,0136</SECOND>
<HEAD>Amy Irving Gives Birth to Baby Boy</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SANTA MONICA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Actress Amy Irving has given birth
to a baby boy, the son of Brazilian film director Bruno Barreto.
   Miss Irving, 36, and her new son, Gabriel Davis Barreto, rested
comfortably Saturday, said her publicist Peggy Mulloy.
   A healthy Gabriel was born Friday night at an undisclosed
location in Santa Monica, Mulloy said. No other details were
released.
   Miss Irving and Barreto are not married but they plan to tie the
knot soon, Mulloy said.
   Miss Irving last year divorced producer-director Steven
Spielberg, with whom she has a 4-year-old son, Max.
   She was nominated for the 1983 Academy Award for best supporting
actress for her role in ``Yentl'' and also won acclaim in the film
``Crossing Delancey.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0006 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 0042EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Guatemala-Crash 4thLd-Writethru a0628 05-06 0333</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Guatemala-Crash, 4th Ld-Writethru, a0628,0341</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.S. Civilian Plane Crashes in Guatemalan Capital, At Least 17
Killed</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS thruout to CORRECT scene of crash to southwestern part
of city, typos; ADDS that plane carried clothing; no pickup</NOTE>
<DATELINE>GUATEMALA CITY (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Miami-bound DC-6 cargo plane crashed
Saturday in a crowded residential neighborhood, killing its
three-member U.S. crew and at least 14 people on the ground,
officials said. Several houses were destroyed.
   At least 10 other people were injured when the U.S. civilian
plane crashed into several houses and plowed into a hill shortly
after takeoff. Officials said the plane was carrying snow peas and
clothing.
   Police blocked off much of the southwestern part of the city of
2 million, but rescue efforts were hampered by a series of
explosions caused by several home propane gas tanks.
   The U.S. crew were identified as Capt. Joseph Babody, co-pilot
J. Theodore and flight engineer Dallas White, said the assistant
civil aeronautics director, Natzul Mendez.
   Their names could not be confirmed and hometowns could not be
released pending notification of their families, U.S. Embassy
spokesman James Dickmeyer said.
   Rescuers recovered the bodies of the crew and at least 14 other
people on the ground, said city fire department spokesman Haroldo
Juarez.
   Hospital officials treated at least 10 others on the ground for
burns.
   Dickmeyer said the DC-6 was owned by a the Miami-based Aerial
Transit Inc. The Guatemalan representative of the company is
Translados S.A., he said. The company makes three or four trips
weekly to the United States to transport export goods, he said.
   Jorge Celis, a spokesman for the city's firefighters, said an
engine dropped from the plane, and the pilot apparently had been
looking for a small field for an emergency landing.
   He said an unidentified colleague of the civil aviation
administration gave him the information.
   In another crash, the army said a Guatemalan air force Sikorsky
SA-76 helicopter went down Saturday. Three pilots on board were
slightly injured, the military said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0007 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 0049EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BusShooting     05-06 0171</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bus Shooting,0175</SECOND>
<HEAD>Police: Argument Over Seat on Bus Leaves One Dead</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A passenger on a crowded transit bus shot
another passenger Saturday before fleeing down a street after an
argument over a seat, police said.
   The identity of the slain man, who was shot once in the chest,
was not immediately released, police Sgt. Steven Brock said.
   The violence broke out about 6 p.m. on a Rapid Transit District
bus carrying about 75 passengers in downtown Los Angeles.
   ``A couple of people had a disagreement on the bus,'' Brock
said. ``One of the men pulls a gun and shoots the other man's son,
who was trying to break up the argument,'' he said.
   ``We have a lot of people that saw him,'' Brock said. ``But we
have about five different descriptions.''
   The gunman fled the bus and ran down a street, where he fired on
two unarmed security guards standing outside a nearby building,
Brock said. The shots missed the guards and the gunman escaped.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0008 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 0152EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Iraq-BankProbe     05-06 0253</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Iraq-Bank Probe,0259</SECOND>
<HEAD>Newspaper Reports Grand Jury Probing Bank Loans to Iraq</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CHICAGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A federal grand jury is investigating whether a
U.S. branch of an Italian bank secretly lent billions of dollars to
Iraq for President Saddam Hussein's effort to make his country the
dominant Middle East power, a newspaper reported.
   The Chicago Tribune said in Sunday editions the grand jury in
Atlanta has been looking into possible violations of bank
regulations by Banco Nazionale Lavoro, a Rome bank controlled by
the Italian goverment.
   The grand jury also has been investigating whether an official
of the bank's Atlanta branch fed Iraq more than $2 billion in loans
without authorization from his superiors in Rome, the newspaper
reported.
   The Justice Department has cast a blanket of national security
over the nine-month inquiry, keeping some bank regulators and fraud
investigators in the dark on certain elements, the newspaper said.
   The Tribune said its story was based on court documents and
interviews with law enforcement officials and others.
   The grand jury is expected to conclude its work soon, the
newspaper said.
   Western nations, alarmed at a buildup of long-range missiles in
the Middle East, have imposed restrictions on the sale of sensitive
equipment to Third World countries, but Iraq is exploiting
loopholes to develop a formidable missile arsenal.
   Federal investigators are trying to trace whether some or all of
any Banco Nazionale loans went to Iraq's recent military buildup,
which includes the acquisition of materials for nuclear and
chemical weapons, the Tribune said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0009 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 0721EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a BC-ChildrenHit     05-06 0537</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Children Hit,0553</SECOND>
<HEAD>Car Kills Three Children During Baseball Game</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JAMES REINDL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>RIVERSIDE, Ill. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Three children were killed and nine
people were injured when a speeding car plowed through a park
during a T-ball game and struck a bench crowded with young players
before it smashed into a clinic.
   Two injured children remained in critical condition early Sunday.
   The driver, whose name was not released, may have had a medical
problem, and there was no evidence that he had been drinking,
police said.
   ``It looked like someone had thrown a bomb in the Little League
field,'' Riverside Fire Chief Anthony Bednarz said of the Saturday
accident.
   When the late-model Cadillac appeared, about 50 people were
watching a game of T-ball between teams of 7- and 8-year-olds at
Robinson Park in this Chicago suburb.
   One spectator, 14-year-old babysitter Amy Ulrich, said, ``I saw
a car driving through the field, and I saw it hitting kids. ... It
was going kind of crazy and going real fast.''
   Holding the bloody shirt of one of his players, coach Bob
Wengerski said, ``I saw a car, a large car ... go right past me
from behind and hit the bench where my team was sitting and getting
ready to bat. And (it) took about nine or 10 kids through the
restraining fence out into the field where they dropped off one by
one.''
   One witness said the field was eerily quiet before ambulances
started arriving after the accident, which occurred about 1:30 p.m.
   ``It was like people laying next to their children, trying to
talk to them or something,'' said Helen Kolacki, who lives across
the street from the park. ``There was one young man, his foot was
moving up and back, but the others were lying still.''
   Killed were Holly Rizzi, 8, Colin Anderson, 7, and Ryan Womack,
8, all from Riverside, said Mike Maggio, a spokesman for Loyola
University Medical Center.
   Bruce Anderson, 43, who is Colin's father, was in fair condition
with a leg injury, Maggio said. Another adult, Mike Larmon, 24, was
treated for a leg injury and released. Larmon is a coach of one of
the teams.
   Doctors at Loyola were treating five children, including two in
critical and one in serious condition, Maggio said.
   Another boy with minor injuries was taken to La Grange Memorial
Hospital in La Grange, said Nancy Jacobus, a nursing supervisor.
   The driver, a man about 50, was taken to MacNeal Memorial
Hospital in Berwyn, where his condition was ``stable but guarded,''
said hospital spokeswoman Mary Pappas, who refused to provide
further details.
   After striking the people in the park, the car continued across
a busy street and rammed through the glass and steel entrance to a
medical clinic in Berwyn, an adjoining suburb, said Berwyn
Patrolman Anthony Christiano.
   ``Thank God no one was in the area'' where the car came to rest,
Christiano said.
   The driver may have suffered a heart attack or some other
medical problem, said Christiano. The officer said he found no
indication the man had been drinking.
   T-ball is a type of baseball played by young children where the
ball is batted off a stationary ``tee'' at home plate.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0010 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 1124EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Obit-Goodall     05-06 0437</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Goodall,0456</SECOND>
<HEAD>Sir Reginald Goodall, Leading Wagnerian Conductor, is Dead</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Sir Reginald Goodall, a leading conductor of the
works of Richard Wagner, has died. He was 88.
   His death was announced from a nursing home at Bridge near
Canterbury, where he died on Saturday. The cause of death was not
disclosed.
   Despite his reputation as an interpreter of Wagner, Goodall was
never principal conductor of a leading orchestra or opera company.
   During his career, he worked with the opera companies at Covent
Garden, Glyndebourne, Sadler's Wells and the English and Welsh
national companies.
   He also worked abroad as an assistant to some of the century's
greatest conductors, including Wilhelm Furtwangler, Otto Klemperer,
Clemens Krauss and Hans Knappertsbusch. He coached some of
Britain's finest Wagnerian singers _ Gwyneth Jones, Donald McIntyre
and David Ward.
   Goodall was reclusive _ his Who's Who entry occupied only four
lines _ and after a performance he would leave the podium quickly
for the musicians and singers to receive applause without him.
   He rarely used a baton, preferring to conduct with half-clenched
fists.
   British critics called him the greatest living Wagnerian in
1979, when his performances of Wagner's ``Tristan und Isolde'' with
the Welsh National Opera Company were sold out.
   He was then a frail widower living alone in the Kent
countryside. He was knighted in 1985 for services to music.
   Members of the Wagner family visited Britain to hear Goodall
conduct and called him the greatest conductor of the master's music.
   He was born in the cathedral city of Lincoln, and he studied at
the Royal College of Music and then in Munich and Vienna. He was an
organist, double-bass player and choirmaster.
   In 1945, Goodall conducted the Sadler's Wells premiere of
Benjamin Britten's opera ``Peter Grimes'' but for 20 years he rose
no higher than conductor's assistant for opera companies.
   Rodney Milnes, the country's leading opera critic, wrote: ``It
says a lot about England that this towering genius should have been
on the music staff at Covent Garden for two decades and more,
serving under notably inferior musical directors and being given
virtually nothing to do. All the conductors with whom he is to be
compared are dead.''
   Critics said Goodall's high ideals, long and detailed
preparation of an opera, individual coaching of all the singers and
all the instrumental rehearsals, were too demanding for opera
houses in his own country.
   Goodall gave his last performance at the 1987 Promenade Concerts
in London, where he conducted act three of Wagner's ``Parsifal.''
   His funeral will be in Canterbury on May 14. There was no word
on any survivors.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0011 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 1124EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Jordan-BeautyShops     05-06 0319</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Jordan-Beauty Shops,0330</SECOND>
<HEAD>Jordan Limits Male Ownership of Beauty Parlors</HEAD>
<DATELINE>AMMAN, Jordan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The government, bowing to pressure from
Islamic fundamentalists, announced Sunday that men will no longer
be allowed to purchase beauty parlors or hire male beauticians to
work in them.
   The Interior Ministry order, which took effect Sunday, does not
apply to men who already own such shops or work in them, a ministry
official said.
   The decision came in response to demands by Islamic
fundamentalists in Jordan's 80-member Parliament. The Moslem
Brotherhood, the main Islamic faction, and Islamic independents
hold about three dozen seats.
   ``We've tried to avoid a dispute with Parliament members and at
the same time respond to the demands of the Islamic tide,'' the
Interior Ministry official said in a telephone interview, speaking
on condition of anonymity.
   ``The government has also tried to balance Islamic demands with
the rights of male permit-holders to maintain their source of
income,'' he added.
   The order said the ministry will no longer issue licences for
men to own beauty parlors. It also forbids the hiring of new male
beauticians.
   Prime Minister Mudar Badran's government has already bowed to
other fundamentalist demands. In February, it banned the serving of
alcoholic beverages aboard Royal Jordanian airways flights to Arab
countries.
   But so far Badran has not met Moslem brotherhood demands to
close bars and nightclubs in this Moslem country of 3.1 million
people.
   The Brotherhood emerged as the strongest political party after
winning almost two dozen seats in the Chamber of Deputies, more
than any other faction but not enough to dominate the legislature.
   During November's elections, the first in more than 22 years,
the Brotherhood pledged to introduce stricter Islamic laws, ban
television programs it considers lewd and limit women's freedom,
including their right to work.
   The Jordan-based movement was established in 1950, three years
before King Hussein assumed constitutional powers. It has supported
his monarchy.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0012 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 1124EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SriLanka-Crash     05-06 0186</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Sri Lanka-Crash,0188</SECOND>
<HEAD>6 Killed in Helicopter Crash During Search for Robbers</HEAD>
<DATELINE>COLOMBO, Sri Lanka (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Six air force men were killed when
their helicopter ran out of fuel and crashed during a search for
gunmen who robbed tourists at a jungle resort, military officials
said Sunday.
   The helicopter crew radioed Saturday afternoon that it was
attempting an emergency landing at a military base near Sigiriya,
95 miles northeast of Colombo, the officials said. Radio contact
was lost a short time later, and the air force dispatched more
helicopters for a search.
   The wreckage of the American-made Bell helicopter and the burned
bodies of the six crew members were found Sunday about four miles
from Sigiriya, the officials said, speaking on condition of
anonymity.
   The helicopter had been part of a massive land and air search
for 20 gunmen who stormed into the Sigiriya Village Hotel at
midnight Friday and escaped with $25,000 worth of jewelry, cameras
and clothing from foreign tourists and local residents. The gunmen
fled into the jungle and remained at large.
   The nationalities of the tourists had not been announced.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0013 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 1124EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Judge-Attack     05-06 0245</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Judge-Attack,0250</SECOND>
<HEAD>Storeroom Burned at Home of Judge Who Heard Chinese Hijacker's
Case</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Fire destroyed a storeroom early Sunday at the home
of a judge who upheld the government's decision to extradite an
airplane hijacker to his homeland of China. Police said the blaze
may have been set by an arsonist.
   A police official said a neighbor of Tokyo High Court Judge
Hideo Chigusa was slightly burned while fighting the fire.
   The official, who spoke on condition of anonymity, said
investigators believed someone might have set the blaze because
fire is not used in the storeroom, which is separated from the
house. He said, however, that investigators found no substances or
devices that proved the fire had been set.
   Radical groups had opposed the order for Zhang Zhenhai, 36, to
be sent back to China to face trial for the hijacking of a Chinese
airliner on Dec. 16.
   Zhang contended he hijacked the airliner in a last-ditch attempt
to flee political persecution in China. He had sought political
asylum.
   The order also was opposed by human rights groups, which claimed
that Zhang would face torture and execution in China. China
previously has executed convicted hijackers, but Japan's government
said it had assurances from Beijing that Zhang would be tried under
a law that does not carry the death penalty.
   On April 27, one day before Zhang was sent home, Judge Chigusa
turned down his appeal for suspension of the extradition order.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0014 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 1126EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-NorthernIreland     05-06 0195</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Northern Ireland,0199</SECOND>
<HEAD>IRA Ambush Kills British Soldier in Northern Ireland</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BELFAST, Northern Ireland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Irish Republican Army
claimed responsibility Sunday for killing a British soldier who was
ambushed while patrolling an IRA stronghold and cut down by
machine-gun fire.
   Lance Sgt. Graham Alexander Stewart, 25, of the 2nd Battalion
Scots Guards, died Sunday morning from his wounds, police said.
   Stewart had been in the army for six years and was on his second
tour of duty in Northern Ireland.
   Police said the soldier was hit by machine-gun fire Saturday
while on foot patrol near Cullyhanna village in South Armagh, two
miles from the Irish Republic border. The security forces call the
region ``bandit country'' because of its sympathies with the
outlawed Irish Republican Army.
   The IRA, which is fighting to end British rule and unite the
province with the republic, claimed responsibility for the attack
in a statement to Press Association, Britain's domestic news agency.
   The latest killing brought the known death toll of civilians,
police and soldiers in the past 21 years of violence to 2,797,
including 423 British soldiers and 187 members of the locally
recruited Ulster Defense Regiment.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0015 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 1127EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--TruckAccident     05-06 0146</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Truck Accident,0149</SECOND>
<HEAD>22 Killed in Truck Accident in India</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SIMLA, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A truck carrying Indian border guards fell
into a river in this mountainous district Sunday, killing 22 men,
news reports said.
   Seven bodies were fished from the raging Sutlej River in the
northeastern state of Himachal Pradesh, near India's border with
China. The other 15 were washed away, Press Trust of India and
United News of India said.
   Members of the Indo-Tibetan Border Police searched the area for
survivors but none were found, the reports said. Of the dead, 20
belonged to the border police, which patrols the rocky frontier
area.
   The truck was coming from the border town of Samdhu back to camp
when the accident occurred, Press Trust of India said.
   The cause was under investigation. Fatal bus accidents are
common in India because of bad roads and weather.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0016 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 1127EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--TrawlerSeized     05-06 0167</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Trawler Seized,0172</SECOND>
<HEAD>Navy Commandos Seize Spanish Trawler</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Navy commandos seized a fleeing Spanish trawler and
brought it to port Sunday so its crew could be prosecuted for
fishing illegally in French waters, authorities said.
   Sea patrol aircraft, a navy corvette and a tugboat were used to
intercept the Costa de Irlanda in the Gulf of Gascogne, about 35
miles from the Atlantic coast, maritime authorities said in a
communique.
   The boat, with about 12 people on board, was spotted Saturday
evening and arrived early Sunday at the port of La Rochelle.
   Authorities said the trawler's identification marks had been
covered in violation of international maritime law.
   The official communique said the seizure followed a series of
incidents in which Spanish trawlers operated illegally in the Gulf
of Gascogne.
   In 1984, a French gunboat fired on two Spanish trawlers fishing
illegally in the gulf. Eight Spanish crewmen were injured, and the
captains of the two boats were fined the equivalent of $15,000 each.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0017 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 1146EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-HUD-Pierce     05-06 0758</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-HUD-Pierce,740</SECOND>
<HEAD>House Investigators Fault Justice, Special Prosecutor Probes</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By WILLIAM M. WELCH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   To the chagrin of congressional investigators,
a special prosecutor appointed to probe former Secretary Samuel R.
Pierce Jr.'s tenure at the Department of Housing and Urban
Development is ignoring their latest hearings.
   Arlin M. Adams, the court-appointed prosecutor, said he has
``taken appropriate steps to insulate'' his office from learning of
former HUD official Dubois L. Gilliam's testimony before a House
subcommittee.
   Gilliam, once a deputy assistant secretary of HUD under Pierce
and now serving an 18-month sentence for taking bribes, testified
for three days last week before the House Government Operations
housing subcommittee.
   In his testimony, Gilliam said that Pierce was deeply involved
in steering HUD grants to friends and political allies,
particularly during election years.
   The panel's chairman, Rep. Tom Lantos, D-Calif., characterized
the testimony as contradicting Pierce's sworn statements a year ago
that he did not decide who received federal housing grants.
   After hearing Gilliam's testimony, Lantos accused Pierce of
using discretionary HUD grant programs as a political ``slush
fund.'' He challenged the former secretary to appear before the
panel and offer a point-by-point rebuttal.
   ``I have every reason to believe Mr. Gilliam's testimony until
it is proven to the contrary,'' Lantos said. ``That has not
happened.''
   Adams' action to insulate his staff from the immunized testimony
of Gilliam is a step similar to the one taken by the special
prosecutor during the congressional Iran-Contra testimony of Oliver
North and others. Through it, prosecutors retain an ability to
bring further charges against Gilliam.
   But congressional investigators claim Gilliam's testimony might
provide prosecutors the evidence to go after much bigger fish,
including Pierce.
   ``DuBois Gilliam is no Oliver North,'' said the subcommittee's
staff director, Stuart Weisberg.
   Pierce and three other top aides, including former executive
assistants Deborah Gore Dean and Lance Wilson, have refused to
testify before the panel, invoking a Fifth Amendment protection
gainst self-incrimination.
   Weisberg said he assumed Adams took the step out of extreme
caution and would later review Gilliam's testimony and use it in
his investigation. Adams declined to comment through a spokeswoman,
Terry Dugan.
   The dispute highlights a long-running rift between the
congressional investigators and the Bush administration's Justice
Department over the limited scope of Adams' investigation.
   Currently, Adams' probe is limited only to one HUD program.
Members of the House subcommittee want it broadened to cover the
activity of Pierce and his top aides in all HUD programs and
possible perjury by Pierce in a May 25, 1989 appearance before then
panel before be began invoking his Fifth Amendment rights.
   A Republican on the panel, Rep. Chris Shays of Connecticut, said
the Justice Department has an obligation to investigate Gilliam's
allegations because of the narrow limits that Attorney General Dick
Thornburgh sought on Adams' original appointment.
   ``This committee has done almost everything it possibly can do.
It is now up to the independent counsel and the Justice Department
to do their jobs,'' Shays said. ``And frankly, I have seen very
little evidence to date that they have done their jobs.''
   He complained that Adams, who is just beginning his work, has
been presented with a ``confused'' mandate by the Justice
Department.
   ``If the special prosecutor hasn't been given the responsibility
to look at all of HUD, it clearly rests with the Justice
Department,'' Shays said. ``They have chosen to retain it, and I
think it's about time we started to see some action.''
   Pierce's attorney, Paul L. Perito, took sharp issue with the
committee members' assertion that Gilliam had contradicted Pierce's
statement.
   Perito said Pierce's May 1989 statement that he wasn't involved
in deciding who got grants applied only to the Section 8 moderate
rehabilitation program, which subsidizes developer who renovate low
income housing.
   The Section 8 program was the first of many HUD programs to fall
under allegations of abuse during Pierce's eight-year tenure as a
member of President Reagan's cabinet.
   Perito said Pierce's statement, made without an attorney present
and before he decided to invoke his constitutional rights to not
testify further, did not consider other programs in which he had
legal discretion to award grants.
   ``This committee keeps trying to adjudicate as a court of law,''
Perito said. ``It is not only fanciful, it's defamatory.''
   Thornburgh requested the court to name a special prosecutor only
after House Democrats legally compelled to consider their request
for one. His recommendation to the court was for a narrow
investigation and he specifically recommended against broadening it
to include possible perjury.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0018 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 1157EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u p AM-GenderPolitics Bjt   05-06 0758</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gender Politics, Bjt,750</SECOND>
<HEAD>Gender Becomes Campaign Issue in Gubernatorial Races</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MICHAEL FLEEMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In gubernatorial races across the country,
gender has become an issue as female candidates clash with their
male opponents on abortion, sexism and the importance of putting a
woman in the statehouse.
   Women like Dianne Feinstein in California, Ann Richards in Texas
and Barbara Hafer in Pennsylvania are on the forefront of what some
observers expect to be a breakthrough decade for women in politics.
   There are three women now serving as governors, two of whom are
retiring, and at least 10 women are considered to be serious
gubernatorial hopefuls this year.
   ``It's a testament to the women's movement,'' said Shana Weiss
of the Hollywood Women's Political Committee. ``It's no longer a
symbolic movement but a real kind of recognition that women are
equal players in the political game.''
   Sensing a political change, Feinstein has made the very fact
that she's a woman an issue in her campaign, urging voters to make
history by electing her the state's first female governor.
   ``This is a big moment for me, and a historic one for women,''
she said in announcing her candidacy. ``Much thought and
deliberation preceded this decision. I am a non-incumbent in a race
against two entrenched statewide figures _ a woman in a field of
men.''
   Feinstein faces Attorney General John Van de Kamp for the
Democratic nomination. The likely GOP nominee is U.S. Sen. Pete
Wilson.
   Van de Kamp has responded by pointing to what he calls his
strong record on feminist issues and accusing Feinstein of using
gender to obscure her own record.
   ``If a man were to stand in front of a crowd of men and say,
`Vote for men because as a fellow man I can help men's interests,'
I can be labeled a sexist,'' said Duane Peterson, Van de Kamp's
spokesman. ``I'm sort of surprised she's doing that.''
   The prospect of making history also is a theme in Joan Finney's
bid to win the Democratic nomination for governor of Kansas.
   But in Finney's case, the significance of her becoming the
state's first female governor has been woven into speeches subtly,
rather than offered as a major campaign issue.
   In Texas, meanwhile, there has been nothing subtle about
Richards' Democratic campaign against Republican candidate Clayton
Williams.
   Gender politics had stood in the wings because of Williams'
anti-abortion stand and opposition to the Equal Rights Amendment.
But it took center stage when he revealed he went to prostitutes
when he was a teen-ager and a college student.
   Earlier, Williams said he'd be uncomfortable running against a
woman because he grew up in a ``man's world.'' He also made a
comparison between bad weather and rape and passed it off as a
joke. ``If it's inevitable, just relax and enjoy it,'' he said.
   Williams has denied being a sexist, but acknowledged the remarks
were insensitive.
   ``Clayton's heart is in the right place, even if he doesn't pick
the right words,'' Williams' spokesman, Bill Kenyon, said.
   Richards' campaign has condemned the remarks as insulting to
women.
   ``Clayton Williams has gone to great lengths to be a
stereotypical cowboy, one off those rough-hewn Texans who conquered
the West, let's get up in the saddle and ride off into the sunset
sort of thing,'' said Richards campaign manager Glenn Smith.
   In a number of campaigns, male and female stereotypes have
spilled over into candidates' defenses of issues, most notably
abortion.
   The U.S. Supreme Court's 1989 decision to give states more power
in regulating abortions has helped make abortion rights a key
campaign issue in many races.
   In Pennsylvania, Hafer is running as a pro-choice Republican
against staunchly anti-abortion Gov. Robert P. Casey, a Democrat
seeking a second term.
   In an interview last August, Hafer said she expected male
candidates to shy away from running for governor because of the
abortion issue.
   ``That's a tough issue to talk about,'' she said. ``It's a gut
issue, it's not a nice issue. ... A lot of men wouldn't be
comfortable speaking about it and they know it's going to be an
issue.''
   Though all three California gubernatorial hopefuls are
pro-choice on abortion, Feinstein's campaign has contended that a
female governor would be more likely to strongly defend abortion
rights.
   ``A man can be a staunch defender of abortion rights. Many have
been,'' said Feinstein spokeswoman Dee Dee Myers. ``But there's a
visceral reaction that women have to the issue because they are
women. It's a point of common experience.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0019 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 1158EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-CivilRights     05-06 0670</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Civil Rights,680</SECOND>
<HEAD>Civil Rights Forces Soften Key Portion of Job-Bias Bill</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MIKE ROBINSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Civil rights forces hope to propel a
wide-ranging job discrimination bill past its first House committee
hurdle this week now that they have softened a key provision
opposed by employers.
   ``It will add to our support,'' Rep. Augustus Hawkins, D-Calif.,
chairman of the House and Education and Labor Committee, said after
the lawmakers last week inserted milder language in the bill's
major fair-hiring provision.
   Hawkins, the chief House sponsor, hopes the committee will
approve the bill Tuesday. It then would move on to the Judiciary
Committee before being positioned for House floor action.
   A similar bill is set for floor action in the Senate.
   The bill's provisions range from a ban on racial harassment in
the workplace to new ground rules easing the way for job
discrimination lawsuits against employers.
   The bill was designed to overturn six 1989 Supreme Court
decisions that civil rights supporters say added up to a sharp
setback for minority rights in the workplace.
   As drafted, the bill would have forced employers named in
discrimination suits to justify any hiring practices that
diminished the chances of minorities and women being hired _ height
and weight requirements, for example, in the case of women.
   Businesses would have to prove that the requirement in question
represented a business necessity.
   Conservative critics complained that it would be virtually
impossible for employers to prove that their hiring standards were,
in the bill's words, ``essential to effective job performance.''
   Critics warned that employers would turn to minority hiring
quotas to protect themselves from lawsuits.
   Attorney General Dick Thornburgh in a recent letter to lawmakers
said the measure could usher in such quotas. He said top advisers
to President Bush would recommend a veto.
   The administration is calling for a more modest bill to combat
job bias but it is not making headway in the Democratic-controlled
Congress.
   Bill supporters initially scoffed at conservative complaints
that proving business necessity would be too tough for employers.
Civil rights groups complained that a 1989 Supreme Court decision
skewed the ground rules against the victims of unfair hiring.
   The 1989 ruling, Wards Cove vs. Antonio, involved workers at a
salmon cannery in Alaska. It required those filing suit to prove
that the hiring practices in question _ such as a height
requirement _ do not represent a business necessity.
   The Wards Cove decision broke with longstanding procedures
established under the court's 1971 Griggs vs. Duke Power Co.
decision.
   Under Griggs, employers had to prove business necessity. And
bill sponsors claim employers did not resort to hiring quotas in
that era.
   Hawkins conceded that ``the complaints that have been raised are
bona fide.'' He offered to change the standard from ``essential to
effective job performance'' as it appeared in the original bill to
``bears a substantial and demonstrable relationship to effective
job performance.''
   The committee adopted the change unanimously, with Republican
critics of going along but stopping short of saying they had
changed their minds about the overall bill.
   ``It's still a quota bill,'' said Rep. Steve Bartlett, R-Texas.
   Civil rights forces said, however, that softening the measure
was guaranteed to add support on the House floor.
   ``Before, we had the votes to pass the bill. This will give us
the majority to override a veto in both houses,'' said Ralph Neas,
executive director of the Leadership Conference on Civil Rights.
   Hawkins said he understood that the Senate would adopt a similar
amendment. He said there was now enough support in the House to
override a presidential veto.
   Hawkins said a veto of major civil rights legislation would
force the administration to pay a political price that ``goes
beyond the black vote.'' He said the votes of women and the
disabled would also have to be considered by the White House in
sizing up any veto plans.
   But Bartlett said the measure has ``a bare majority on the floor
_ it's not a veto-proof majority.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0020 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 1201EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-ScotusNotebook     05-06 0629</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Scotus Notebook,620</SECOND>
<HEAD>Supreme Court Shows Conservative Tint in Criminal Law Decisions</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RICHARD CARELLI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Many decisions must be handed down before the
Supreme Court can begin its summer recess in late June or early
July, but the 1989-90 term already has taken on a conservative tint
_ especially in ``law-and-order'' cases.
   Of 17 criminal-law decisions announced by the court so far this
term, defendants have lost 13.
   Justices William J. Brennan and Thurgood Marshall, the court's
most consistent liberals, cast dissenting votes in all 13.
   The court gave police broad new powers to search the homes of
arrested suspects, cut back the appeals rights of prison inmates,
allowed U.S. agents to search foreign homes of non-citizens without
warrants and curtailed self-incrimination protection for people
accused of child abuse.
   Two of the four decisions won by defendants are notable not only
because they focus on significant issues but because Justice Byron
R. White was in the majority.
   Over 28 years, White has earned a reputation as a hardliner who
favors law enforcement forces in criminal cases.
   But in one decision this term, his vote helped forge a 5-4
majority to bolster the rule barring the use at trial of evidence
unlawfully obtained by police.
   And in another, White wrote for a 7-2 court in ruling that
overnight guests in private homes enjoy the same privacy
protections as their hosts against police arrests and searches.
   Two police practices still to be judged: setting up roadside
checkpoints to catch drunken drivers and using anonymous tips to
justify stopping and questioning people.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>___</BYLINE>
<HEAD>Scalia Holds Court in Senate</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Justice Antonin Scalia, who has never been accused of being a
shrinking violet, at first appeared hesitant but soon warmed to the
task of telling a Senate subcommittee what he thinks about
interpreting disputed language in federal laws.
   ``My position is that legislative history (what Congress says
about a bill before passing it into law) is not always unreliable
or unhelpful but I can't tell when it is. ... I tend not to use it
at all,'' Scalia said.
   His remarks came as he and Justice Sandra Day O'Connor appeared
before an appropriations subcommittee last week to present the
court's $19.2 million budget request for next fiscal year.
   Sen. Warren Rudman, R-N.H., noting that discussion of money
matters was concluded in 11 minutes, told Scalia there was some
extra time to fill.
   ``You want me to sing something?'' Scalia asked with a smile.
   Rudman said he'd rather have the justice expound on what he has
written about interpreting federal law.
   ``You really want me to do this?'' Scalia asked before launching
into an extraordinary 15-minute discussion with Rudman and Sen.
Dale Bumpers, D-Ark.
   Scalia noted, and O'Connor reiterated the point, that his views
on the matter are not shared by a majority of the court's justices.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>___</BYLINE>
<HEAD>New Rules, New Color Code</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   The hundreds of appeals reaching the Supreme Court each week are
getting more colorful _ at least on the outside.
   Under rules that took effect in January, briefs filed with the
court must sport color-coded covers of either white, orange, two
shades of green, red, blue, gray, tan, cream or yellow.
   The different colors denote the timing and purpose of the
briefs.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>___</BYLINE>
<HEAD>Vacancies by Decade</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Supreme Court vacancies, created by resignation, retirement or
death, most often are discussed in terms of presidential
administrations. For example, President Carter never got to appoint
anyone to the court.
   But looking at court vacancies decade by decade shows that the
1940s had eight, the 1950s five, the 1960s five, the 1970s four and
the 1980s three.
   What will the 1990s bring? Some guess there will be seven new
justices in place by the start of the next century.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0021 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 1204EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Australia-TrainCrash     05-06 0546</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Australia-Train Crash,0566</SECOND>
<HEAD>Two Trains Collide in Australia, 6 Killed, 90 Hurt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SYDNEY, Australia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A modern, double-decker passenger train
slammed into the back of an old-fashioned steam train that
apparently stalled going up a steep hill Sunday. At least six
people were reported killed and 90 injured.
   The crash occurred at night in a remote area 25 miles north of
Sydney. TV pictures showed that an undetermined number of people
were trapped in the mangled wreckage of the two trains, which were
carrying about 430 people.
   The crash site near the hamlet of Brooklyn is surrounded by
dense bushland, and rescue workers had to drive down a dirt track
to reach it. When they arrived, they found debris from the trains
scattered over a 100-yard area.
   Many injured passengers had to be carried more than 500 yards to
waiting ambulances, witnesses said. At least six of the injured
were reported in serious condition, and some of them were taken to
hospitals by helicopter.
   The dead and injured included passengers on both trains, said
police, who provided the casualty figures.
   The double-decker train, with an estimated 100 people on board,
was traveling from the city of Newcastle to Sydney.
   The steam train, which had been chartered by a group of jazz
fans and had around 330 people on board, also was traveling south
after a one-day trip to Hunter Valley, 100 miles north of Sydney.
   The accident occurred between two tunnels, according to a
spokesman for Gosford police, who did not identify himself.
   Witnesses said the double-decker train, which was powered by
electricity, slammed into the steam train after it failed to make
it up a steep gradient.
   Rob Schwarzer, New South Wales State Rail group manager, said
the cause of the accident was not immediately known, but he agreed
that it may have been caused by the steam train stalling in the
path of the other train.
   Passengers on the double-decker train said it stopped briefly
behind the steam train. ``The driver told us we would be about 10
minutes as the steam train didn't have enough power to get up the
hill,'' Justine Reis said. ``We stayed there for a while, then
started up around a curve and next thing, bang. People were thrown
everywhere. They just got thrown from their seats.''
   Another survivor, student Ben Shaw, said: ``We waited for about
five minutes, then we took off and just hit. People were flying
everywhere.''
   Richard Stohr, a passenger in the second carriage of the
double-decker, said the steam train apparently was not able to make
it up the hill.
   He said his train appeared to be trying to pick up speed to
tackle the hill out of the tunnel when it slammed into the back of
the stationary train. ``A woman just flew past me. Just sailed
past,'' he said.
   ``I think she was killed.''
   Survivors were taken to a Returned Servicemens' Club at Berowra,
about five miles from the crash site.
   Twenty ambulances from Sydney and surrounding areas rushed to
the accident scene to take victims to nearby hospitals.
   Australia's worst rail accident occurred in January 1977, when a
crowded commuter train left the rails and hit a bridge in
Granville, in Sydney's western suburbs. The crash killed 83 people.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0022 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 1229EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Yugoslavia-Croatia     05-06 0505</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Yugoslavia-Croatia,0522</SECOND>
<HEAD>Croatians Vote in Crucial Elections</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DUSAN STOJANOVIC</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ZAGREB, Yugoslavia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Voters in Yugoslavia's second-largest
republic, Croatia, went to the polls Sunday in the second round of
free parliamentary elections that could lead to a secessionist
movement.
   The center-right Croatian Democratic Union, which advocates the
republic's independence from the rest of Yugoslavia, won a
landslide victory April 22 in the opening round of Croatia's first
free elections in more than 50 years.
   A second-round triumph for the Democratic Union is certain to
deepen the split with Serbia, Yugoslavia's largest republic, and
exacerbate tensions that are slowly pulling apart the country's six
constituent republics.
   The voting was to continue Monday, and Croatian electoral
officials said initial results were not expected until that
afternoon.
   In the first round, the Democratic Union won 104 of 131 seats in
the 356-seat, three-house regional parliament. The second round was
scheduled for runoffs.
   The Croatian Communist Party _ renamed the Party for Democratic
Reform _ won only 13 seats in the first round, while the centrist
Coalition for National Accord, considered one of the pre-election
favorites, won just three.
   ``Now every vote counts, and I know Croatians are aware that by
voting for us, thay are voting for peaceful life in the republic
and in Yugoslavia,'' said Ivica Racan, the republic's Communist
leader who over the past six months has steered Croatia to
multiparty democracy.
   Yugoslavia is a loose federation of six republics and two
autonomous provinces fraught with ethnic and ideological tensions.
   Croatia and Slovenia are pushing for closer ties with the West
and democratic reforms. Serbia, meanwhile, has a hard-line
Communist leadership and along with Montenegro continues to follow
a one-party system.
   The center-right DEMOS coalition, which won last month's free
parliamentary elections in Slovenia, was expected Monday to form
the first non-Communist regional government in Yugoslavia in more
than 40 years.
   In Croatia, the Democratic Union's leader, Franjo Tudjman, wants
Yugoslavia's republics to become independent states and establish
relations only if common interests were involved.
   The reform Communists are more cautious. They say the national
federation model is fine for now, but if it fails to reflect the
republic's needs in the future, Yugoslavia should become a
confederation without central rule.
   The 66-year-old Tudjman once was the Yugoslav army's youngest
general, but later spent almost five years in jail after being
convicted of Croatian nationalism and hostile activities against
the state.
   His bid for power has fueled the fierce rivalry that has existed
between Serbia and Croatia ever since Yugoslavia was created after
World War I.
   Serbia's media, strongly influenced by the Communists, brand
Tudjman a secessionist and a fascist.
   Croatia's 450,000 Serb minority, which is haunted by memories of
mass extermination in the Croatian puppet state set up by Nazi
Germany, recently staged several anti-Tudjman rallies. Serbs
represent slightly more than 10 percent of the republic's 4.6
million population.
   Serbs in Croatia say they would demand full autonomy for the
regions where they live if Tudjman's party wins the elections.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0023 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 1254EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Soviet-Patriarch     05-06 0410</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Patriarch,0420</SECOND>
<HEAD>Believers Mourn at Funeral of Russian Orthodox Patriarch Pimen</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ANN IMSE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hundreds of mourners clutching slender white
candles and singing ancient hymns crowded into Moscow's Epiphany
Cathedral Sunday for the funeral of Russian Orthodox Patriarch
Pimen.
   Pimen, head of the Russian Orthodox Church and patriarch of
Moscow and Russia, died Thursday of heart failure after a long
illness. The 79-year-old monk had presided over the church during
years of repression, keeping it cowed but alive.
   Many citizens returned to the church after President Mikhail S.
Gorbachev ordered an end to official harassment. But the once iron
control of the bearded Orthodox priests over masses of simple
peasants has disappeared after the decades of Stalinist terror,
when tens of thousands of churches were closed and many clerics
imprisoned.
   Thousands of believers crowded under the low, vaulted ceiling of
Epiphany Cathedral from Friday night to Sunday to pray for Pimen.
He lay in state, his face covered with a white satin cloth
embroidered in silver, beneath a towering wall of icons, glittering
with gilt and dark paintings of saints.
   The Holy Synod, the leadership of the Russian Church, surrounded
the bier during the funeral service. Immediately behind them stood
several of Mother Theresa's nuns, who have been working in a Moscow
hospital, and officials from other Christian denominations.
   Roman Catholic Cardinal Johannes Willebrands of the Netherlands,
representing the Vatican, World Council of Churches
General-Secretary Emilio Castro and Catholicos-Patriarch of Georgia
Ilya II were among the other dignitaries, the official Tass news
agency said.
   Gorbachev and other Soviet leaders sent messages of condolence.
   Outside the cathedral, aged beggars pleaded with believers for
change in the name of Christ and the memory of Pimen. Police
controlled access to the cathedral, but apparently allowed new
arrivals in as others left.
   The patriarch's body was buried Sunday afternoon in the crypt of
the Assumption Cathedral in the Trinity-St. Sergius Monastery in
Zagorsk, 45 miles from Moscow.
   Pimen started as a provincial priest and advanced rapidly after
World War II, becoming an archbishop and a member of the Holy Synod
in 1960. He became patriarch in 1971. He was elected to the Soviet
parliament in last year's first multicandidate elections.
   The new patriarch will be selected within six months by a
council of church leaders and members. Until then, Metropolitan
Filaret of Kiev and Galich in the Ukraine will serve as acting head
of the Russian Church.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0024 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 1256EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Sugar     05-06 0567</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Sugar,520</SECOND>
<NOTE>For Release at 6:30 p.m. EDT, time set by source.</NOTE>
<HEAD>Sugar PACs Sweeten Coffers of Friendly Congressmen</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DIANE DUSTON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Sugar growers poured more than $3.3 million
into congressional campaigns between 1983 and 1989 to keep U.S.
sugar prices artificially high, a consumer group charged Sunday.
   ``U.S. sugar support policies artificially keep the price of
sugar so high that consumers have spent billions more than they
should have,'' said Ellen Haas, executive director of Public Voice
for Food and Health Policy.
   Officials for the sugar industry acknowledge the campaign
contributions but disputed the contention that consumers are paying
too much for their product.
   ``The program keeps prices stable,'' said Joe Terrell, spokesman
for the American Sugar Alliance. ``Consumers in this country pay on
average about what is paid in developed countries worldwide, or
less in some cases.''
   Eiler Ravnholt, a representative for the Hawaiian Sugar
Planters, said the average price of sugar at U.S. grocery is 39
cents a pound, compared to 42 cents to 44 cents in the other
developed countries.
   ``We do have a definite interest in keeping the sugar program
the way it is, because it keeps prices stable,'' said Ravnholt,
whose organization represents growers in the second largest sugar
cane producing state, after Florida.
   Public Voice said contributions from 17 sugar-producer political
action committees increased after the passage of the 1985 farm bill
setting agriculture policy through 1990.
   After the 1985 vote, the group said, the Sugar PACs increased
their contributions to members of Congress supporting price support
and quota programs by 75 percent. Lawmakers who opposed the
programs saw their contributions from the Sugar PACs fall by 42
percent, Public Voice said.
   Of course, responded Ravnholt.
   ``I would have an awfully hard time justifying to my members
paying money to members who voted against us,'' he said. ``I think
every political action committee does the same.''
   Critics contend that the system of price supports and quotas for
sugar is among the most blatantly protectionist of any U.S. farm
programs. Because prices are controlled through imports, it also is
often a tool of foreign policy.
   When the government wants to lower domestic sugar prices, it
allows more foreign sugar into the market. Many foreign suppliers
are Third World countries whose economies rise and all dramatically
depending their access to the U.S. market.
   Congress is still working on the 1990 farm bill that will set
sugar policy for the next five years. But a House Agriculture
subcommittee has approved a program that soon will be acted on by
the full committee.
   It's key provisions would:
   _Continue the requirement that the sugar program impose no
direct cost to taxpayers.
   _Maintain the current loan rate _ a price guarantee for growers
_ at 18 cents a pound in 1991 with an annual escalation after then
equal to the overall rate of consumer inflation minus 2 percent.
   _Require that at least 1.25 million tons of sugar be imported.
   _Create a new re-export program that would allow Caribbean
countries to sell raw sugar to U.S. processors at a higher price
than the world market would pay. The processors then could sell the
refined product to other countries.
   _Extend the length of loans from 6 months to 9 months.
   _Prohibit countries that sell sugar to Cuba from selling to the
United States.
   _Mandate import quotas on specified products containing sugar.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0025 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 1317EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Small-TownGroceries Bjt   05-06 0476</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Small-Town Groceries, Bjt,0494</SECOND>
<HEAD>Residents Help Owner of Town's Only Grocery Store</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ONEKAMA, Mich. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In a scene reminiscent of the movie ``It's
a Wonderful Life,'' residents of a small town pitched in loans
totaling $85,000 in five days to enable the community's only
grocery store to reopen.
   Ray Franz's store burned in 1988. He rebuilt it with money from
his insurance company but ran out of money to restock and was
turned down by several banks.
   But thanks to his friends and customers in the Upper Michigan
town, Franz will reopen his store Tuesday.
   ``We got to keep this town going,'' said retired postmaster Bill
Green. ``Cripes, when your grocery store is gone, you're dead.''
   The village, population 600, has no movie theater or shopping
mall.
   Franz said the community ``loan'' is overwhelming.
   ``It's incredible is what it is,'' Franz said. ``I can't imagine
this happening anywhere else.''
   Donors were given promissory notes entitling them to a charge
account at the store and a 7 percent discount on groceries that are
charged. When they have charged an amount of groceries equal to
their loan, plus 7 percent, the loan is paid off.
   After the December 1988 fire, Franz battled over insurance
coverage and finally settled out of court. But after paying
attorney fees, he had just enough money to rebuild the
10,000-square-foot Franz Market, which he's owned since 1976.
   Franz, 42, needed an additional $85,000 for inventory but three
banks turned him down.
   ``I was depressed,'' he said. ``But I was too far along to walk
away.''
   John Lyman, an Onekama High School teacher, and Jack Mosora, a
retired car salesman, said they figured it was time to pay back
Franz. He has been president of the village council, chief of the
volunteer fire department, junior varsity football coach, little
league coach and a member of the rescue squad.
   On April 23, they called residents asking for donations and
within five days collected the money. Many checks were for $1,000.
   In the movie ``It's A Wonderful Life,'' townspeople pitch in to
help save the failing savings and loan run by the character played
by Jimmy Stewart.
   John Kline, a retired engineer who lives just outside town,
jumped down from his tractor to write a check for $1,000. One woman
wrote a check on the hood of her car.
   ``It just snowballed,'' Franz said. ``It's embarrassing that the
community has that much confidence in us.''
   ``I love it here. It's the little things, like when you drive
down the street and wave because you know everyone,'' he said.
   Several donors, including the 72-year-old Green, waved off any
talk of promissory notes.
   ``I didn't ask the details,'' Green said. ``I didn't care about
groceries. I figure if there is some day down the road where he can
cut (the $1,000) loose, great. Otherwise, forget it.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0026 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 1425EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Drought-Insects Bjt   05-06 0620</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Drought-Insects, Bjt,0642</SECOND>
<HEAD>Drought Is Starting To Bug The West</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVID FOSTER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Drought-stricken areas of the West bracing for a summer of
rationed water, parched crops and forest fires now face another
plague: hordes of hungry beetles, bees, crickets and grasshoppers
that love hot, dry weather.
   California, in its fourth drought year, just finished a winter
rainy season that yielded only 55 percent of normal precipitation.
Water supplies to central California farmers are being cut in half,
and ``drought cops'' patrol coastal cities, citing scofflaws who
defy lawn-watering bans.
   It's weather only a bark beetle could love.
   The insects are thriving on drought-stressed trees across
California. Last year, they killed trees containing 2 billion board
feet of timber, and state Department of Forestry officials predict
a similar toll this summer.
   ``In drought conditions, the trees don't produce the amount of
pitch they usually do, so when the beetles drill into the trees,
they're more successful at getting in and laying their eggs,'' said
Don Perkins, head of the forestry department's pest management
program.
   The eggs hatch into larvae, which eat the trees from the inside
out, then develop into beetles that fly off and lay more eggs.
   ``They can have three or four life cycles if you have a real
warm, dry spring and warm weather in the fall,'' Perkins said.
   Beetle-killed trees and tinder-dry weather have made
California's fire danger the worst in decades.
   ``We have hundreds of thousands of large kindling stands,'' said
Lisa Boyd, forestry department spokeswoman. ``Things are as dry
right now as we would normally see in August and September.''
   It's not beetles but bees that are annoying Northern California
tourist towns around Lake Tahoe, where swarming yellow jackets last
summer forced people from beaches and back porches.
   Even more bees are expected this summer, prompting the South
Lake Tahoe Chamber of Commerce to declare war. The group is
distributing 5,000 bait traps filled with the insecticide diazinon.
   Populations of the ground-nesting yellow jackets surge if hot,
dry weather occurs in spring when the queen bee is starting her
nest, said Roger Akre, a Washington State University entomologist.
By August, a single queen can hatch out 5,000 workers.
   In northern Nevada, officials are battling Mormon crickets,
which can grow to the size of mice by devouring vegetation, bark,
and virtually anything else in their path.
   ``They're just absolutely voracious,'' said Akre. ``They're
eating-machines.''
   State officials hope to fend off the invasion _ Nevada's largest
since the 1930s _ by spreading poison-laced bran and oil on eggs at
the mouth of canyons. The crickets hatch in the mountains, then hop
down into the valleys to feed.
   East of the Rocky Mountains, winter rains have put a green cast
on much of the Great Plains. But drought persists in North Dakota,
where some farmers have not raised a crop in two years and anxious
citizens hold rain dances and prayer meetings to plead for moisture.
   So far, all they've got are grasshoppers. Lots of grasshoppers.
   In eastern North Dakota, researchers last fall counted 1,700
grasshopper eggs per square yard, compared with a normal count of
200, said Dean McBride, a North Dakota State University
entomologist.
   North Dakota has joined South Dakota and Minnesota, also
infested with grasshoppers, to ask Congress for money to spray
pesticide on the insects' eggs. The grasshoppers can devastate
crops.
   If it's any consolation to residents gone buggy, Akre said, the
drought may eventually limit the populations of insects, which
appreciate rain once they start to feed.
   ``Rain makes the vegetation grow,'' he said. ``Otherwise,
they'll eat themselves out of house and home.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   David Foster is the AP Northwest regional
reporter, based in Seattle.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0027 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 1455EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-GrasshopperChapel     05-06 0472</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Grasshopper Chapel,0484</SECOND>
<HEAD>Prairie ``Grasshopper Chapel'' Is Site Of New Plague Prayers</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Drought-Insects, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>COLD SPRING, Minn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A chapel built by pioneers in thanks
for deliverance from a grasshopper plague is being used more than a
century later by parishioners praying to avert an infestation
expected this year.
   ``Every time there was a crucial problem, the people came
together and prayed and it worked,'' Nancy Wenner, organizer of a
series of nine prayer services that began last week, said Sunday.
``Why couldn't it work today?''
   Roman Catholic settlers in this central Minnesota town built
Assumption Chapel in 1877 as a memorial of thanks for relief from
the swarms of grasshoppers that had devastated their crops for two
years.
   The original frame structure was destroyed by a tornado in 1894,
but the rebuilt granite chapel, used only for special services, is
the focus of renewed prayers as the threat of another grasshopper
invasion looms over the state.
   A plaque above the door to the small chapel shows the Virgin
Mary ascending into heaven above two grasshoppers, their knees bent
in submission.
   Wenner, who runs a hardware store and funeral home with her
husband in the town of 2,000, said the entire community has
suffered under three years of drought.
   ``This is an agricultural area and it's a real concern,'' she
said.
   University of Minnesota researchers say the drought cycle has
fostered conditions favorable for a grasshopper infestation this
year and egg counts have been reported at up to 10 times normal.
Hatches usually begin in May and the winged insects do the most
damage from the end of June through early July,
   Parishioners will gather at the ``grasshopper chapel,'' as they
refer to it, on nine consecutive Thursdays to recite the rosary,
celebrate Mass with pastors of Catholic churches in the area and
pray for rain and relief from the expected infestation.
   Ken Schefers, a rural Paynesville farmer who battled
grasshoppers last year with chemicals, thinks the services are a
good idea.
   ``It's worked in the past,'' he said last week. ``There's no
reason to think God has forgotten us. What we survive on is hope
and prayers most of the time.''
   Relying on hope and prayers isn't new to Minnesota farmers, who
have tried nearly everything in their battle against grasshoppers.
   Some resourceful settlers tried to protect their gardens with
blankets in the 1870s, but the insects soon chomped through them,
according to historical records. Hordes traveled miles each day and
could devour entire wheat fields within hours.
   ``They covered not only gardens and fields, shrubs and trees,
but houses, barns, wagons and fences and were so thick at times on
the railway track that their crushed bodies prevented the wheels
from taking hold and trains were actually stopped,'' according to
an account in ``History of Stearns County.''

</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0028 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 1504EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People     05-06 0982</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People,1021</SECOND>
<HEAD>People in the News</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY44</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CHARLESTON, S.C. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Bob Hope has agreed to appear at a
benefit to aid the Patriots Point Naval and Maritime Museum, which
is plagued by financial problems and suffered damage from Hurricane
Hugo last year.
   Singer Dionne Warwick and pianist Peter Nero are also on the
lineup for the July 3 benefit concert at Johnson Hagood Stadium,
Save the Yorktown organizers said.
   Save the Yorktown is a non-profit corporation of retired
military personnel created to help the state museum; the Yorktown
is an aircraft carrier that is the centerpiece of the museum on
Charleston Harbor.
   Save the Yorktown President William A. Kerr said the group hopes
to raise $700,000 to pay for fire code improvements and other
maintenance on the carrier. That will allow the museum to resume
its camping program in which Boy Scouts and Girl Scouts stay
overnight on the ship.
   The program generates revenue for the museum, which has been
swamped with legal fees from an adjoining hotel-marina project that
went bankrupt before it was completed. The museum also was closed
for several weeks after it was damaged by Hugo in September.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>Eds: For release 6 p.m. EDT.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>RADNOR, Pa. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   `Murder, She Wrote' is entering its final
chapters. Shooting for the seventh and final season of the CBS
series begins in July, and Angela Lansbury is ready to move on.
   ``Too much of a good thing is not good for the health,'' she
said in the May 12-18 issue of TV Guide magazine.
   Lansbury will star in only 13 episodes next season and introduce
the other nine. Then she'll move on to comedy.
   ``We are already working on a half-hour comedy in which I'll
star in the fall of '91,'' she said.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>ASPEN, Colo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A dispute over a hot tub has landed Don
Johnson in hot water.
   The actor refused to pay a $20,762 bill for a hot tub in his
Aspen residence, saying it didn't work. A Vail plumbing supplier
sued Johnson in July for the money, and a Pitkin County judge
recently ordered the actor to pay up.
   The default judgment in favor of Kamen Supplies came after
Johnson's lawyers failed to respond to the lawsuit.
   Johnson said he didn't know about the suit because it got mixed
in with other legal papers involving a lawsuit filed against him by
Star magazine. That lawsuit was over shots fired at a helicopter
hired by the magazine to shoot pictures of Johnson's wedding to
actress Melanie Griffith in June.
   The actor said the Star magazine lawsuit enraged him so much he
didn't even notice the other lawsuit.
   Johnson, who for years played a police detective on television's
``Miami Vice,'' also said who didn't know the meaning of a summons.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>RED CLOUD, Neb. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Eva Marie Saint says she has no plans to
portray a Willa Cather character soon, but that touring the
countryside so lovingly portrayed by the author ``whets your
appetite to read everything she wrote.''
   Miss Saint and her husband, director Jeffrey Hayden, climbed
aboard a school bus Saturday as part of a caravan that rumbled up
and down muddy country roads to retrace scenes from ``O Pioneers!''
and other Cather works.
   The tour was part of the 35th annual spring conference on the
works of Nebraska's Pulitzer Prize-winning author. Miss Cather
moved to Red Cloud in 1883 when she was 9 and lived here until she
was a young woman. The community of 1,300 people is about 180 miles
southwest of Omaha.
   ``I can't fly over the western states without thinking of
Conestoga wagons,'' said Miss Saint, who had never visited Nebraska
before. ``I've played a pioneer lady. They were strong, very
strong.''
   Later Saturday, Miss Saint and her husband gave readings of
Cather's works at a banquet.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>AUSTIN, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Town Lake may get a new name: Lake Lady
Bird, after the widow of former President Lyndon B. Johnson.
   ``We want to put you on the map _ forever,'' Austin Mayor Lee
Cooke told Mrs. Johnson at a dinner Friday to mark the 25th
anniversary of Johnson's inauguration.
   ``Lady Bird Johnson has cultivated beauty, and she has shared it
with us. ... This is our way of saying `thank you' for the many
gifts of beauty, courage and care that she has so generously
brought to our world,'' Cooke said.
   The dinner was at the LBJ Library at the University of Texas.
   Cooke said a majority of the city council has agreed to the name
change. A formal vote is scheduled for Tuesday.
   Town Lake was created on the Colorado River in 1959. But plans
to beautify its shores and create hiking and biking trails
foundered until Mrs. Johnson lent her name, time and money to the
project in 1970.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>Eds: For release 6 p.m. EDT.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>RADNOR, Pa. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Author Dominick Dunne would like viewers of
the NBC miniseries ``People Like Us'' to know that the TV version
is quite different from his book.
   ``It was a best seller. I must have done something right,''
Dunne said in the May 12-18 issue of TV Guide magazine.
   Dunne, who also complained about the way his ``The Two Mrs.
Grenvilles'' was reworked for television, had no say in the script.
``I sold it, and I was paid handsomely,'' he said.
   Dunne's 1988 novel was about a writer who moves in society
circles.
   The script changed the central character, Gus, played by Ben
Gazzara, from an ironic observer to a conventional hero.
   ``If I had wanted it that way, I would have written it that
way,'' Dunne said.
   ``The network felt that Gus should be a participant,'' said the
screenwriter, Kathleen A. Shelley. ``A movie must have one person
for the audience to sympathize with, identify with and care about.''
   The miniseries will air May 13-14.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0029 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 1512EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Pilsen Bjt   05-06 0675</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Pilsen, Bjt,0698</SECOND>
<HEAD>Long-Deferred Celebration Marks U.S. Liberation of Czechoslovak
Town</HEAD>
<NOTE>With LaserPhoto PIL1</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By JOHN DANISZEWSKI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PILSEN, Czechoslovakia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Vaclav Havel led
Czechoslovaks Sunday in paying a belated tribute to U.S. GIs who
helped liberate their nation from the Nazis only to find their
exploits erased later from Stalinist history books.
   Havel spoke at the end of a weekend festival marking the 45th
anniversary of this western Bohemian city's liberation by Gen.
George Patton's U.S. 3rd Army.
   Scores of U.S. veterans took part in the celebration, and
Czechoslovak revelers drove restored World War II jeeps and wore
American Army uniforms.
   Only a year ago, such festivities would have been unimaginable.
   Under the country's hard-line Communist rulers in power at the
time, the official position was that only the Soviet Red Army
liberated Czechoslovakia in 1945.
   But last November's democratic upheaval ended four decades of
Communist rule.
   ``Finally the day has come when we can express our gratitude and
thanks publicly to all those persecuted, forgotten or erased from
world history,'' Havel, a playwright and former political prisoner,
told up to 40,000 people who packed Pilsen's city square for
Liberation Day celebrations.
   ``Many of them ... did not live to see this well-deserved
recognition by our country.''
   It was the first time that the main Czechoslovak observance of
the end of World War II was held in Pilsen. In past years, the
celebrations took place in Prague, the capital, and highlighted
only the Soviet role in the country's liberation.
   It was a moving experience for the many elderly American
veterans who took part. Many were making their first trip back.
   ``They stole our hearts then and they are doing it again
today,'' said Bobby Capps, of Birmingham, Ala., now retired to Lake
Alfred, Fla., who was a member of the 396th Field Artillery.
   ``You can't describe how much love there is.''
   The holiday brought tens of thousands of people to Pilsen from
across western Czechoslovakia to drink the famous Pilsener beer,
eat sausages, hear speeches and indulge in a festival of Americana,
including country and western bands, swing music and a U.S. film
festival featuring ``Patton,'' starring George C. Scott.
   People pasted U.S. and Czechoslovak flags in the windows of
their homes and flew the Stars and Stripes from car antennae.
   ``This is a dream, something genuinely unbelievable,'' said
Czech singer Pavel Bobek, who recalled visiting Pilsen as a
7-year-old and seeing the U.S. troops.
   During a ceremony at city hall, a plaque commemorating the U.S.
liberation was remounted. It had been taken down by Stalinist
authorities at the height of the Cold War in 1951.
   ``All Americans thank Czechoslovakia for putting American
soldiers back in their true place in history,'' said U.S.
Ambassador Shirley Temple Black, the former child film star.
   ``Today America once again stands shoulder to shoulder with
you,'' she told the crowd.
   Earlier, Havel spoke at a Sunday morning ceremony in the small
town of Rokycany, where a plaque was unveiled honoring the troops
of the U.S. 9th Infantry Regiment, 2nd Division, who rolled into
town in their jeeps on May 5, 1945.
   ``Without the truth about the past we cannot live in truth
today, and we cannot truthfully enter a better future,'' he told a
cheering crowd of about 5,000 people.
   Jarka Heinzova, who as a teen-age student knew a little English
and acted as an interpreter for the U.S. troops, recalled how they
affectionately called her ``Jerry.''
   ``They brought us liberty and saved our lives,'' she said,
searching for words in her rusty English. ``We never don't forget
their arrival and what they did for us.''
   Rokycany is near the demarcation line where U.S. troops halted
their eastward advance in the war's closing days as part of the
controversial Yalta Conference agreement, which allowed the Red
Army to occupy much of Eastern Europe.
   Under the agreement, U.S. troops were prevented from pushing on
to liberate Prague, just 50 miles away.
   In 1949, the Communists established full control and set up a
Soviet-style state.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0030 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 1540EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BridgeCollapseAnniversary     05-06 0682</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bridge Collapse Anniversary,0704</SECOND>
<HEAD>10 Years Later: Harbor Pilot Now Crisis Counselor</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PAT LEISNER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TAMPA, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The harbor pilot who was at the wheel of a
freighter that rammed the Sunshine Skyway Bridge a decade ago,
sending 35 motorists to their deaths, now spends his days helping
others cope with tragedy.
   Former Capt. John Lerro is a crisis counselor, helping prisoners
mend their lives, the despondent find hope and rape victims a way
to forgive.
   But he hasn't forgiven himself.
   ``I don't always think about it,'' said Lerro, 47. ``You can't
live life like that, thinking about your screwups. I'm not sitting
at home saying `woe is me.'
   ``But have I forgiven myself for it? I don't know. I'm not very
forgiving of people, including myself. The people who died, died
forever.''
   On May 9, 1980, Lerro was guiding the 609-foot freighter Summit
Venture through the narrow, winding shipping channel of Tampa Bay
when a sudden, blinding squall knocked out the ship's radar and
eclipsed the bridge.
   Lerro was seven-tenths of a mile from the bridge and at a
crucial turning point. He decided to ``shoot for the 800-foot
hole,'' the shipping passage beneath the bridge.
   He missed.
   The ship sheared a bridge support, dropping a 1,400-foot section
of concrete roadway during morning rush hour. Seven vehicles,
including a bus with 26 aboard, plummeted 150 feet into the water.
One man survived after his pickup bounced off the ship's bow.
   ``I made the best decision I could. You couldn't stop with the
wind blowing 60 to 80 knots (about 70 to 90 mph). You'd hit the
bridge for sure,'' Lerro said. ``You keep going. At least you've
got some control.
   ``If it happened again today, I'd do the same thing. But I've
had years to philosophize.''
   He had been at the pinnacle of his career. He was qualified to
guide vessels through the Panama Canal. He was a deputy Tampa Bay
harbor pilot, an expert in maneuvering vessels through the tricky
40-mile stretch between the nation's seventh busiest port and the
Gulf of Mexico.
   He had been scheduled for promotion to full-fledged pilot with a
jump in pay from $45,000 to $100,000 two days after the accident.
   The state took his license a month after the accident but he won
it back _ only to surrender it 11 months later and end his career
at sea when he developed multiple sclerosis.
   Then, he and his wife of 21 years divorced.
   ``Your job is to transcend storms when you're a pilot,'' he
said. ``I had to live with that, with the loss of life. I lost my
health, my identity as a pilot, my job and my wife. Four years ago
I hit bottom.''
   With encouragement from friends, he went back to school and
earned a master's degree in counseling from the University of South
Florida.
   ``I was looking for a way to help myself,'' said Lerro. ``I was
told if you want to feel good, make somebody else feel good. It
works. No matter what their trouble, I've been there.''
   For the past three years, he's been a volunteer at the
Hillsborough County Crisis Center, four hours a day, two or three
times a week.
   ``To bring a smile to the face of someone really hurting touches
the soul,'' he said.
   He lives with his son, Charles, 24. He supports himself on
disability and alimony.
   MS has left him with a decided limp. His gait is slow and
strained, and he tires easily. But he's determined not to let it
beat him.
   A new bridge, built at a cost of $250 million, carries traffic
across the bay. The old one still stands alongside, a gaping hole
in its midsection a grim reminder of the tragedy.
   ``You learn from everything that happens to you,'' Lerro said.
``Sure, I've had a one-two-three punch. But to complain about it
would be a fourth punch. I don't need that. I don't think I'm at
the basis of things yet. I suspect that's spiritual. Maybe that's
where the forgiveness is.''

</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0031 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 1601EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brites     05-06 0328</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brites,0340</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bright &amp; Brief</HEAD>
<DATELINE>KEY WEST, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A celebration including a street fair,
sailing race, parade and an ``ambassadors ball'' concluded Sunday
as the Florida Keys celebrated the eighth anniversary of their
short-lived secession.
   The Conch Republic Independence Celebration commemorated the
island chain's 1982 rebellion when the Border Patrol erected a
traffic-delaying roadblock to search for illegal aliens and drugs.
   The roadblock created long, creeping lines of traffic and
carloads of hot, angry visitors along the single highway linking
the Keys and the mainland.
   Key West officials reacted on April 23, 1982, by gathering at
Mallory Square to declare their secession from the Union.
   They fired verbal salvos at the offending authorities _ then
immediately surrendered, applied for foreign aid and called for a
celebration.
   Presiding over this year's observance was ``Prime Minister''
Tony Tarracino, Key West's colorful mayor, who takes his Conch
Republic post seriously enough to write to Soviet President Mikhail
Gorbachev offering help with glasnost.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>DALLAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A bronze likeness of the Duke is back in Texas
after eight weather-beaten years in California.
   But the statue of John Wayne has returned to the Hoka Hey Fine
Arts Foundry and Gallery near Dublin, southwest of Fort Worth, only
for cosmetic reasons. The foundry cast the statue in 1982.
   After facing the elements outside the John Wayne Airport in
Orange County, Calif., it is being moved to a new terminal building
where it will be inside an atrium.
   Eight years in the open has given the once reddish-brown bronze
a dusty-gray finish. The only bronze color showing was its right
hand where people had touched it on their way into the airport.
   ``Probably a lot of photographs out there in the world are of
people shaking his hand,'' said Wade Cowan, who founded the Hoka
Hey operation with his wife, son and daughter-in-law.
   The statue now has a reddish-brown finish called a traditional
patina, the color most people associate with bronze.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0032 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 1604EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Soviet-Baltics-Glance     05-06 0244</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Baltics-Glance,0249</SECOND>
<HEAD>Independence Moves by Soviet Baltic Republics</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Soviet-Baltics, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here is a look at independence moves by the Soviet
Baltic republics, forcibly annexed by Moscow in 1940:
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   
   LITHUANIA _ The Supreme Council parliament declared its
independence on March 11. The Kremlin has since imposed an economic
embargo of oil, natural gas and other raw materials on the republic
of 3.8 million people, trying to force it to back off some of its
laws that foster independence. Lithuanian officials are pressing
for negotiations with Moscow, which has not responded.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   
   ESTONIA _ The Supreme Soviet parliament on March 30 declared the
Soviet Union an occupying power and pledged to restore full
independence gradually, after an unspecified period. Since then,
Soviet President Mikhail S. Gorbachev has offered Estonia, a
republic of 1.5 million, ``special status'' in a kind of
``confederative'' Soviet Union if it drops its independence bid.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   LATVIA _ The Supreme Soviet parliament declared its independence
Friday, although the measure calls for secession after an
undetermined transition period, during which there presumably would
be negotiations with Moscow. About 54 percent of the population of
2.7 million is Latvian. The rest of the republic's people are from
other ethnic groups, mostly Russians, and many oppose independence.
Gorbachev also has offered the republic special status if it
abandons its secessionist ways. On Saturday, he reportedly tells
Latvia he rejects the independence declaration and may impose
sanctions.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0033 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 1610EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-US-JapanBlame     05-06 0617</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-US-Japan Blame,590</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.S. and Japanese Politicians Urged To Lower their Voices</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GENE KRAMER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A U.S. business group has told Japanese and
American political leaders to stop blaming each other for trade
friction and get down to solving their own problems at home.
   The Commission on U.S.-Japan Relations for the 21st Century,
including corporate chiefs whose firms have prospered in Japan,
listed among domestic problems contributing to U.S. competitive
weakness the high federal budget deficit and the American emphasis
on quick corporate profits.
   ``The harsh rhetoric'' between the two countries is reaching
intolerable levels and risks grave repercussions such as closing of
the U.S. market to Japanese imports and a wave of retaliatory
protectionism, said a study issue last week by the commission.
   The two countries should ``acknowledge that there is blame
enough to go around, get on with expanding the horizons of
cooperation, while working through the disputes that frustrate
both,'' said the report.
   It predicted ``minimum immediate impact'' from current economic
negotiations toward cutting the U.S. trade deficit with Japan _
currently $49 billion _ despite demands from Congress.
   ``Rather than the two governments telling each other what is
wrong, and blaming each other for inaction,'' they now need to
undertake the changes that each pledged at last month's Washington
session on structural barriers, the commission continued.
   Besides protectionism and economic decline, a breakdown of
U.S.-Japanese cooperation could have serious political
consequences, said commission Chairman Edson W. Spencer, former
chief executive officer of Honeywell Corp., chairman of the
U.S.-Japan Business Council and board chairman of the Ford
Foundation.
   His group recommended talks to modernize the 40-year U.S.-Japan
security alliance by adding political and economic cooperation in
Third World development, peacekeeping and environmental protection.
The National Security Council should add coordinating U.S. economic
policy toward Japan and Europe to its security duties, it said.
   The report targeted ``short-term profit pressures'' of American
business as a major culprit weakening U.S. competitiveness.
   ``To increase the domestic savings rate and reduce the cost of
capital it is essential for the U.S. to reduce the federal budget
deficit, to keep inflation low and to thus permit real interest
rates to drop,'' the commission said. It suggested a hefty levy on
short-term gains if the capital gains tax is revised, along with
incentives to boost savings.
   ``There appears, however, to be only one solution for
lengthening the profit horizons of American business,'' it added.
``That is for corporate managers to ignore short-term profit
pressures and educate their shareholders to expect enhanced
shareholder value in a longer term.''
   The commission called itself ``an American group that works for
American interests.'' Sponsors include the U.S.-Japan Business
Council, the Council on Foreign Relations and the Japan Society,
which administers its privately contributed funds from the
U.S.-Japan Foundation, the Pew Charitable Trusts, the Ford
Foundation, the American Express Foundation, the Rockefeller
Brothers Fund and SmithKline Beecham.
   Other members of the commission are University of Tennessee
President and former state Gov. Lamar Alexander; former North
Carolina Gov. James B. Hunt Jr.; National Academy of Sciences
President Frank Press; Peter G. Peterson, former secretary of
commerce, now chairman of the Blackstone Group and director of 3M
Corp. and Rockefeller Center Properties and Chairman of the Council
on Foreign Relations; James D. Robinson III, chief executive
officer of American Express Co.; former Defense Secretary Donald H.
Rumsfeld now chief executive officer of Searle Pharmaceuticals;
Henry Wendt, chairman of SmithKline Beecham; Former Deputy
Secretary of State John C. Whitehead, now co-chairman of Goldman
Sachs and Co.; former Secretary of State Cyrus R. Vance, now an
investment banker and chairman of the Japan Society, and former
Federal Reserve Board Chairman Paul Volcker.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0034 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 1628EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-India-Unrest     05-06 0664</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-India-Unrest,0689</SECOND>
<HEAD>Indian Prime Minister Calls for Crackdown on Separatist Unrest</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN POMFRET</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW DELHI, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Prime Minister V.P. Singh called Sunday
for a crackdown on India's increasingly violent separatist groups,
including punishment for people shouting ``provactive'' slogans.
   More than 1,000 people have been killed in the violence so far
this year.
   In a letter to the heads of India's 25 states, Singh blamed
``anti-India agencies from across the border'' in Pakistan for the
secessionist unrest, which has claimed more than 1,000 lives this
year.
   He said such groups have a ``sinister design'' to throw India
into chaos.
   Singh demanded ``firm punishment'' for people who shout
provocative slogans or religious cries or distribute handbills and
posters that could incite others to violence.
   State intelligence bureaus were ordered to increase their
surveillance of suspicious ``elements and their activities,''
according to a partial text of Singh's letter carried by two Indian
news services.
   Meanwhile in Jammu-Kashmir state, site of a violent Moslem
separatist movement, eight people were kiled in clashes Sunday,
official sources said.
   Security forces said they killed four Moslem secessionists near
India's border with Pakistan, official sources said.
   In the troubled state's summer capital, Srinagar, Moslem
militants killed one man and wounded another who they accused of
being police informers, security forces said. Two more militants
and a woman bystander were killed in other violence around the
state, police said.
   The deaths brought to 349 the number of people slain in
Jammu-Kashmir since Jan. 20, when India launched a crackdown on the
separatist movement by Moslems seeking to establish an independent
state in the scenic Kashmir valley.
   Police officials, who spoke on condition of anonymity, said they
feared more violence on Monday when government workers were to open
their offices in Srinagar for the summer season.
   The winter capital of the mountainous region is Jammu to the
south.
   Posters lining the streets of Srinagar warned government workers
not to go to work. One poster warned that those who came to work
would ``suffer the consequences of a holy war.''
   During a curfew relaxation Sunday, militants and security forces
exchanged gunfire. There were no immediate reports of casualties.
   The crisis in Kashmir has heightened the traditional distrust
and animosity between India and Pakistan.
   India accuses predominantly Moslem Pakistan of harboring and
arming the separatists. Pakistan denies these allegations, but says
it supports Kashmiri Moslems' right to self-determination.
   The two countries went to war over Kashmir in 1948 and 1965.
Both nations have claimed Kashmir since 1947 when British colonial
rule ended and the two states were partitioned along religious
lines. The old princely state of Kashmir had a Moslem majority, but
its ruler was a Hindu who opted to join India.
   Sixty-four percent of Jammu-Kashmir's 6 million people are
Moslems, but nationwide Moslems make up only 12 percent of the
population. Hindus comprise 82 percent of India's 880 million
people.
   In his letter, Singh also accused ``external agencies,'' another
apparent reference to Pakistan, of fomenting a separatist movement
in Punjab state, just south of Kashmir.
   So far this year, at least 746 people have been killed in
violence sparked by a Sikh nationalist movement in Punjab. Indian
news reports said 12 people died Saturday in Punjab, and on Friday,
Sikh nationalists damaged a television tower with a rocket in the
state.
   Police in New Delhi also are investigating Sikh involvement in
three bomb blasts in the capital over the last three weeks that
killed 11 people.
   Singh said the central government had reliable information that
``external agencies aiding and abetting terrorist and secessionist
groups have instructed them to focus on violent acts.''
   He expressed concern that such groups might stir up clashes
between Hindus and Moslems around the country.
   Government figures released in April said 607 people died in
such religious clashes last year, a 750 percent increase over the
previous year. Those figures did not include deaths caused by the
Sikh, Kashmiri Moslem and other separatist movements.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0035 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 1631EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p AM-LukensTaxes 1stLd-Writethru a0684 05-06 0621</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lukens Taxes, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0684,0633</SECOND>
<HEAD>Report Says Congressman Delinquent in State Tax Payment</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Inserts 17th graf pvs, ``In May...' after 3rd graf to move up
background. SUBS last graf to CORRECT spellings of Kindness and
Boehner.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>COLUMBUS, Ohio (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   U.S. Rep. Donald Lukens, fighting for
re-election in this week's primary under the cloud of a sex-related
conviction, has been certified as delinquent by the Ohio Department
of Taxation, a newspaper reported Sunday.
   The tax department certified a personal income tax delinquency
of $1,514, including penalty and interest, against the Ohio
Republican on April 18, The Columbus Dispatch said.
   The Ohio attorney general's office filed a lien April 27 with
the Butler County clerk of courts in Hamilton for collection of the
tax for 1988, the newspaper said.
   In May 1989, Lukens was convicted of contributing to the
unruliness of a minor for having sex with a 16-year-old Columbus
girl. Lukens was sentenced to 30 days in jail and fined $500. He is
free on a $100,000 bond while appealing the conviction. A ruling on
his appeal is expected within a month.
   Lukens faces three opponents in Tuesday's GOP primary. He has
been snubbed by the local GOP, but has refused repeated calls to
resign his office and leave the race.
   The Dispatch said spokesmen for Lukens at first denied the tax
liability but later admitted that it existed when the newspaper
asked for a copy of Lukens' 1988 state income tax return and a copy
of any canceled check for payment.
   ``I don't know what you are talking about,'' Bill Jarrell,
Lukens' chief of staff, first said when asked about the matter.
Jarrell said Lukens had an old tax liability at one time, but said
it was paid.
   If Lukens had a new tax liability, he would have paid it off
during a re-election campaign, Jarrell said.
   ``It's obvious we're not going to let this sit out there,'' he
said.
   ``Buz Lukens is catching up on all of his debts,'' Jarrell said.
``He has paid off over $12,000 of debts. This sounds like ... a
story that was planted by somebody.''
   David Stitt, treasurer of Lukens' campaign, said he shares a
house with Lukens in Middletown and ``we have not received any
mailing. No one has received anything about any tax lien.''
   But when the Dispatch later asked Jarrell to provide
documentation, he said Lukens ``is aware that the taxes are there.''
   ``He has called that office (the Ohio Department of Taxation)
and told them to send him a bill. He knows he owes that money,''
Jarrell said.
   Tax department spokesmen said delinquencies are not certified to
the attorney general's office until attempts to collect the tax
have failed. Spokesmen in the attorney general's office said liens
are not filed with clerks of court until additional tax collection
efforts are unsuccessful.
   Stitt said Saturday that Lukens has been waiting for a federal
income tax refund of about $5,000, based on an amended 1986 tax
return, so he could pay his state tax obligation.
   ``His federal is overpaid, and he was waiting for his refund to
pay that (the state),'' Stitt said. ``We have never been notified
of the exact amount owed the state.
   ``Buz has never reneged on a debt. He will pay everybody off.''
   In formally announcing he was running for re-election last week,
Lukens apologized for what he termed ``a dumb mistake.''
   Also running for the GOP nomination in Lukens' 8th District seat
are former 8th District Rep. Thomas Kindness, state Rep. John
Boehner and Hamilton bond underwriter Mort Meier. The nominee will
be whoever gets the most votes, regardless of whether he receives a
majority. There is no provision for a runoff.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0036 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 1633EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-MuslimCandidates     05-06 0313</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Muslim Candidates,300</SECOND>
<HEAD>Farrakhan Followers Running for Congress, D.C. Posts</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two Nation of Islam followers of Louis
Farrakhan say they will seek seats in Congress in this year's
election, while a third plans to run for the District of Columbia
school board.
   Farrakhan said Muslims are fielding the candidates because
current officeholders, both white and black, in the Washington
metropolitan area have been ineffective in dealing with drugs,
crime and other social problems.
   ``We have watched politicians use the people to get what they
want, then forget the people,'' Farrakhan said at a rally Saturday
at a local housing project where Muslims two years ago launched a
local antidrug program.
   He said Muslims ``have been training for 60 years for this day''
and indicated their direct political involvement may spread to
other cities.
   Abdul Alim Muhammad, Farrakhan's national spokesman and
executive director of the neighborhood antidrug program, said he
will seek the Fifth District U.S. House seat from Prince Georges
County, a Maryland suburb of Washington.
   The seat is now held by Rep. Steny Hoyer, a five-term incumbent
and chairman of the House Democratic Caucus. Prince Georges County
is about 45 percent black.
   ``We think we have an excellent chance of winning,'' Muhammad
said.
   George X Cure, a legal adviser to a group of Muslims who have
fought drug trafficking through an organization called Dopebusters,
said he will run for the District of Columbia's non-voting seat in
the House.
   The seat is being vacated by Del. Walter E. Fauntroy, who is
seeking the Democratic nomination for mayor.
   A third Muslim, schoolteacher Shawn Brakeen, is seeking election
to an at-large seat on the city's school board.
   Muslims generally had shunned political involvement until
Farrakhan's endorsement of Jesse Jackson's unsuccessful bid for the
1984 Democratic presidential nomination. Jewish leaders criticized
Jackson for declining to disavow Farrakhan, whom they view as
antisemitic.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0037 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 1640EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Israel-Colombia     05-06 0850</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel-Colombia,0876</SECOND>
<HEAD>Israeli: Arms for Panama Rebels Wound Up With Colombian Drug Lord</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GWEN ACKERMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A former Israeli army officer wanted by
Colombia on charges of training drug cartel gunmen denied Sunday
that he helped divert a shipment of Israeli-made weapons to a
Colombian drug lord.
   Colombian authorities discovered a cache of Israeli-made Uzi
machine guns and other weapons during a raid in February on a ranch
owned by Gonzalo Rodriguez Gacha, who died in a gun battle with
police in December 1989.
   After the weapons were found, Colombia filed a strong diplomatic
protest with Israel. Israeli officials responded that the weapons
were part of a shipment intended for the Caribbean island nation of
Antigua and Barbuda.
   On Sunday, the Israeli Defense Ministry issued a statement
saying Israel only sold weapons to sovereign nations and approved
arms shipments only after receiving guarantees about their end use.
   ``We have no information on how the weapons were passed to
private hands in Colombia,'' the ministry statement said.
   The New York Times, quoting American and Antiguan officials,
said investigators have traced the arms shipment to two former
Israeli army officers, Yair Klein and Maurice Sarfati.
   The newspaper said Sarfati, an Israeli citizen who used to live
in southern Florida, could not be located for comment. Sarfati is
being sought by U.S. authorities because his produce company in
Antigua defaulted on $1.3 million in loans from the United States,
the Times reported Sunday.
   Israel TV reported Saturday night that Sarfati had provided a
document to U.S. and Antiguan authorities linking Klein to the
diversion to Colombia of 100 Galil automatic rifles, 100 Uzi
submachine guns and other guns.
   A preliminary investigation by Antiguan authorities has
determined that the arms shipment passed through Antigua, a tiny
island 250 miles southeast of Puerto Rico, on April 24, 1989, and
arrived in Colombia five days later.
   But Klein told The Associated Press in an interview Sunday that
the document reportedly provided by Sarfati ``is forged and has no
truth in it.''
   In August 1989, the Colombian government accused Klein and his
Hod Hahanit security company of training gunmen for the Medellin
drug cartel, headed by Gacha and others. Klein contended he had
been helping ranchers defend themselves against leftist insurgents.
   Klein said he has no idea how the arms ended up on Gacha's
ranch, where Colombian police said they found 232 Israeli-made
weapons, including rifles, shoulder-fired rocket launchers and
infrared nightscopes.
   Klein said the weapons shipped to Antigua had been intended for
a survival training camp being set up in the island nation for
Panamanian rebels seeking to overthrow Gen. Manuel Noriega.
   ``When the boat was on the way the operation was canceled and
the weapons were then stuck in Antigua,'' said Klein, a reserve
army colonel who heads the Hod Hahanit private security firm in
Israel.
   According to Klein, the anti-Noriega Panamanians asked for a
refund, but were told their money had already been used to purchase
the weapons. The Panamanians then asked that the weapons be sent to
Panama, Klein said.
   ``The boat then left for Panama, and somehow it got to Colombia
or part of the weapons got to Colombia,'' said Klein, suggesting
that some of the arms may have reached Panama.
   Klein said Sarfati became upset over the change in plans and may
have given authorities a forged document bearing the emblem of
Klein's security firm.
   The Times said financing for the arms shipment was provided by
the New York branch of the Israeli Bank Hapoalim.
   A bank spokesman in Jerusalem, speaking on condition of
anonymity, said the bank had no knowledge of Klein or his firm.
   ``We have no information about the transactions mentioned,'' he
said.
   An Israeli Foreign Ministry spokesman, Baruch Bina, reiterated
Sunday that Israel would offer its ``full cooperation'' to Antiguan
authorities investigating the arms deal.
   The Times said a U.S. Senate Investigations subcommittee is also
looking into the Antiguan affair as part of an inquiry into
allegations that Colombian drug traffickers have used Israeli
weapons and mercenaries.
   Bina said the Israeli government approved the purchase based on
``an official document signed by the (Antiguan) minister of
national security or defense.''
   Bina said the name of Vere Bird Jr., the minister of public
works and national security adviser to his father, Prime Minister
Vere C. Bird Sr., is on the November 1988 purchase order requesting
the arms for the Antiguan defense forces.
   ``Israel acted according to an official document signed by Vere
Bird Jr., with the understanding that the weapons were for his use
solely'' said Bina.
   In Antigua, the scandal has plunged the government into one of
its worst crises since the 81-year-old Bird Sr. came to power in
1956. Bird Jr. has denied any wrongdoing and stepped down from his
post until the matter is resolved.
   The island nation's government announced Friday that a British
jurist, Louis Blomcooper, would head the investigation into the
Israeli arms shipment.
   Bina said that Klein had no connection to the government and
therefore he could not respond to any accusations about his
activity.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0038 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 1646EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-CliffKilling     05-06 0762</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Cliff Killing,0781</SECOND>
<HEAD>Man Appeals Murder Conviction of 2nd Wife Who Died Outdoors</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DIRK BEVERIDGE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PORTLAND, Maine (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A man who became a widower twice under
similar circumstances is appealing his murder conviction in the
second death, arguing that the prosecutor failed to prove that the
body found at the base of a cliff was his wife's.
   Dennis R. Larson is serving a 50-year prison sentence in the
killing of Kathy Frost Larson, 26. Prosecutors says she died in an
80-foot plunge from Otter Cliffs in Acadia National Park on Oct.
11, 1987, four weeks after she married Larson and just seven weeks
after she met him.
   Larson's first wife, Leslee Reynolds Larson, vanished in 1975 in
Montana. Larson told authorities that he was the only witness as
she washed away in Prickly Pear Creek, some 50 miles south of
Larson's hometown of Great Falls. He was never charged in that
death.
   One of the issues in Larson's appeal was the move by a judge to
allow the prosecution to reopen its case midway through the trial
after Larson's lawyer said that prosecutors had not proven the body
in the 1987 death was really that of Kathy Frost Larson.
   Assistant Attorney General Garry Greene said the state will file
a response to Larson's appeal Monday. The Maine Supreme Judicial
Court could hear oral arguments as soon as June.
   Miss Frost met Larson just seven weeks before her death, through
a personal ad in the Bangor Daily News. Three weeks after they met,
they were married, even though Miss Frost's mother worried that her
daughter was being pressured into the move.
   Larson immediately took out a life insurance policy for $300,000
on himself and $200,000 on his bride, with a double payment for
accidental death.
   Mrs. Larson's fatal fall was initially explained by Larson, now
40, as an accident that occurred as the couple were looking for sea
otters after making a bet over who could spot one first. Larson
said he heard a scream and found that his wife had tumbled over the
edge.
   Friends and family were suspicious about Larson's claim that his
wife was walking along the cliffs because she was said to be
terrified of heights.
   Maine State Police also became increasingly suspicious when they
learned about the disappreance of Larson's first wife, Leslee
Reynolds Larson.
   Her body was never found after the 1975 incident in Montana.
Seven years later, she was declared dead and Larson collected some
$20,000 from an insurance policy. Larson married and divorced
another woman before meeting Miss Frost.
   After Larson was questioned several times by police, he changed
his story and said that while he and his wife were on Otter Cliffs,
they got into a fight and she shoved him. He shoved her back, and
she went tumbling off the edge, he said.
   Larson was then charged with murder. At the time, Montana
authorities reopened their investigation into the first Mrs.
Larson's disappearance but found no new clues.
   At a non-jury trial last spring in Hancock County, Superior
Court Justice Jack O. Smith found Larson guilty of murdering Kathy
Frost Larson in an attempt to collect $400,000 from an insurance
company.
   But in his appeal, defense attorney William Ferm argues that
Larson got an unfair trial.
   When the prosecution rested its case during the trial, Ferm
immediately moved for an acquittal, arguing that Assistant Attorney
General Jeffrey Hjelm had failed to prove that the body at the foot
of the cliffs was indeed Kathy Larson.
   Over objections from the defense, the judge then allowed the
prosecution, to reopen its case and present more detailed evidence
that the body was Mrs. Larson's.
   Greene says the judge has the discretion for such action, but
Ferm argues in his appeal that the additional evidence should not
have been allowed.
   Larson's appeal also raises other questions, including whether
the state can prosecute a death in a federal park, and whether the
testimony of two other women who answered Larson's personal ads
should have been admitted.
   Testifying for the prosecution, one woman had said that Larson
discussed marriage on the first date and the second woman said
Larson talked of settling down with her.
   Ferm is also challenging the admission of testimony from an old
friend of Larson's, Richard Balhizer. Balhizer testified that 10
years earlier, during a hunting trip, Larson talked of someday
marrying a foreign woman, having an accident and collecting
insurance money. Ferm said the testimony was too far removed from
Mrs. Larson's death and too prejudicial to Larson.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0039 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 1648EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Obit-Hyde     05-06 0476</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Hyde,460</SECOND>
<HEAD>Washington Post Fashion Editor Dies</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Nina Hyde, who as The Washington Post's
fashion editor shared wine with Yves Saint Laurent, her recipes
with Bill Blass and her tears and pain with Ralph Lauren, Geoffrey
Beene, Calvin Klein, Oscar de la Renta and Donna Karan, is dead at
57.
   But before she died, they and other designers shared their
pocketbooks in her honor. The Nina Hyde Center for Breast Cancer
Research, was founded by Lauren and his friends more than a year
before she succumbed to the disease Friday.
   She had trooped the world with them, the showrooms of Paris and
New York and Tokyo, and even Beijing. But Nina Solomon Hyde had her
own style.
   She didn't own a pair of high heels, wore a Swatch Watch picked
up years ago at an airport novelty shop, and sometimes would show
up in the same outfit three times a week. Her wedding ring was
usually her only jewelry.
   ``Clothes,'' she once observed, ``are important as another way
of looking at ourselves. They are as revealing as how we vote, what
we eat, what we choose to see at the movies. To me, that is why
writing about clothes is important.''
   To that end, she tried to address herself to the general reader,
``the one who doesn't know how to cope with all the choices out
there. The one who is stunned by the prices. The one who is looking
for some reality in the fashion business. The one who is looking
for some help.''
   In recent years, she devoted her experience and energies to a
more compelling concern of women _ detection and treatment of the
disease which was to kill her.
   In 1982, she said, a mammogram was misread at a time when her
chances for full recovery would have been 90 percent. The mistake
was not discovered for three years, when her cancer had spread to
more than a dozen lymph nodes.
   ``When I was first told ... I threw a pen across the newsroom _
I decided to keep the problem to myself,'' she once wrote. ``Now
I've come to the point where I can talk about my cancer, and I talk
a lot.''
   Her crusade prompted Lauren, a longtime friend who himself has
recovered from a life-threatening tumor removed from the lining of
his brain, to launch the research facility in her name at the
Georgetown University hospital. Sixteen other major designers
kicked in as well.
   Mrs. Hyde, once a writer at Women's Wear Daily, came to
Washington in 1961 when she married Lloyd S. Hyde, a childhood
friend, and soon joined the Washington Daily News. She moved to the
Post in 1972 when the News was closed.
   She is survived by her husband and two daughters, Jennifer Hyde
of Washington and Andrea Hyde of San Francisco.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0040 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 1651EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Poland-Baker 1stLd-Writethru a0667 05-06 0751</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Poland-Baker, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0667,0772</SECOND>
<HEAD>Baker Finds Deep Fear of United Germany in Poland</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: New thruout to UPDATE with new quotes. TRIMS. No pickup.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto WAR51</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BARRY SCHWEID</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Diplomatic Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WARSAW, Poland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Secretary of State James A. Baker III
Sunday invited Poland to participate in a six-nation meeting in
Paris to seek a guarantee of its western border from a united
Germany.
   ``I thought it was important to try to come by,'' Baker said of
his six-hour stopover in Poland on his way back to Washington.
   In Bonn on Saturday, the four victorious World War II allies and
two Germanys decided to include Poland in a July session of
unification talks. Baker took it upon himself to convey the
invitation.
   Baker said during his stopover that he gave Polish leaders a
complete report on the meeting in Bonn, Germany, which also
included leading diplomats from the Soviet Union, France and
Britain.
   Officials from the six nations agreed German unification should
move forward without delay and indicated their countries should not
try to impose restraints on what will be Europe's most powerful
nation.
   ``We had a very good discussion with the prime minister and I
believe he is satisfied with the message,'' Baker said of Poland's
Tadeusz Mazowiecki, the East bloc's first non-Communist prime
minister.
   Poland has sought a role in the talks to press its security
concerns, especially the permanence of its postwar western border,
drawn along the Oder and Neisse rivers to include territory from
defeated Germany.
   The rush toward German unification has raised concern in Poland,
where the prospect of a resurgent economic and political power next
door stirs memories of Germany's World War II aggression.
   A senior U.S. official traveling with Baker said later, ``It's
not just a pure border question, it's a fear that history might
repeat itself, and they want to do everything they can as the
process unfolds to prevent that.''
   He said on condition of anonymity that Polish leaders showed
they were determined to secure Poland's border with Germany in a
binding treaty.
   The Poles and Americans were in ``full understanding,'' said
Wladyslaw Klaczynski, the Polish Foreign Ministry spokesman.
   ``Poland would like to get a guarantee from the superpowers
confirming the fact of the inviolability of the Polish border. ...
The formula is not set yet but that demand was not questioned,'' he
said. ``The point is the four superpowers should become an extra
insurance of Polish borders.''
   Baker delivered a formal invitation, signed by West German
Foreign Minister Hans-Dietrich Genscher on behalf of the six-nation
Bonn meeting, asking Polish Foreign Minister Krzysztof Skubiszewski
to address the July unification talks.
   ``At the `two-plus-four' talks, Poland will be allowed to raise
not only strictly border questions but also wider ones, including
the implications of Germany unity for Poland's security,''
Mazowiecki said.
   East Germany has affirmed Poland's borders. The West German
Parliament in March passed a resolution unequivocably confirming
Poland's frontier and said a united Germany should sign a treaty
accepting the border.
   But Polish leaders have said there are procedural differences to
resolve.
   ``There is no controversy about the substance of the issue,''
another senior U.S. official said on condition of anonymity. ``All
of the parties that are involved agree on where that line is now
and should be in the future. The problem is how you go about
establishing that.''
   The Bonn meeting was the first top-level session on unification
among the Germanys and the Allies, which split Germany into two
countries after World War II. Other meetings will be held in June
in Berlin and in September in Moscow.
   On Sunday, West German Chancellor Helmut Kohl's said the first
session produced a ``historic result for Germany and Europe.''
   ``There are no more obstacles to the realization of the right of
self-determination of all Germans,'' Kohl said in a statement.
``After more than 40 years of painful separation, the Germans'
longing to be united in one state is being fulfilled,'' he said.
   But after the talks, one obstacle to swift unification remained
_ Soviet opposition to a united Germany's membership in NATO.
   On Sunday, Lutz Stavenhagen, state minister in Kohl's office,
said it should be made clear to the Soviets that the Western
alliance would change.
   NATO would make disarmament and arms control its priorities,
``things that are very much in the Soviet interest,'' Stavenhagen
said.
   In Poland, Baker also met with President Wojciech Jaruzelski, a
former head of the now-dissolved Communist party, and Solidarity
leader Lech Walesa.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0041 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 1710EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Pakistan     05-06 0222</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Pakistan,0231</SECOND>
<HEAD>12 Killed, 41 Injured in Bombing Near India-Pakistan Border</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LAHORE, Pakistan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A bomb ripped through a passenger train
traveling near the Indian border Sunday, killing at least 12 people
and injuring 41, officials said.
   They said the bomb exploded in a restroom of the train when it
stopped in a station near the city of Lahore, 15 miles from the
Pakistan-Indian border.
   The explosion destroyed a first-class section of the train
packed with 60 people. The carriage was designed to hold 40
passengers, but trains are usually overcrowded in Pakistan.
   Authorities said they had no suspects in the bombing, but
Pakistani newspapers have blamed a rash of bombings in Lahore,
Rawalpindi and Islamabad on Indian secret service agents. At least
four bombs have exploded in those cities in the last month, killing
scores of people.
   Relations between predominantly Hindu India and Moslem Pakistan
have been extremely tense since a Moslem insurgency began to heat
up in Jammu-Kashmir, India's only state with a Moslem majority.
   More than 300 people have been killed in Jammu-Kashmir since
Jan. 20, when Indian troops launched a crackdown on the militants.
   India and Pakistan both claim Kashmir and have fought wars in
1948 and in 1965 over the former princely state that is divided
between the two nations by a U.N.-monitored cease-fire line.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0042 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 1713EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-JewishCongress 1stLd-Writethru   05-06 0615</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Jewish Congress, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0700,0631</SECOND>
<HEAD>World Jewish Congress Opens Its First Meeting On German Soil</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: To ADD details of clashes involving right-wing militants
early Sunday, INSERT 2 grafs after 2nd pvs, `It was...' Pickup 3rd
graf pvs, `In opening...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By GEORGE BOEHMER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WEST BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   World Jewish Congress President Edgar M.
Bronfman on Sunday said a united Germany should teach about its
Nazi past to avoid repeating the ``lowest point ever reached in
man's inhumanity to man.''
   It was the congress' first meeting on German soil since it was
founded in Switzerland in 1936.
   Early Sunday, right-wing militants fought with foreigners in
street clashes in East Berlin. The official East German news agency
ADN said five people were injured and eight people were arrested.
   There has been a rise in racist violence in East Germany,
including rampages through restaurants and public squares by
neo-Nazi skinheads, usually jobless youths with close-shaved heads
shouting epithets against Jews and foreigners.
   In opening the three-day Jewish conference, Bronfmann noted that
Tuesday, May 8, will be the 45th anniversary ``of the defeat of
Nazism, a victory for all mankind.''
   He also reminded the 500 delegates that Berlin was ``the capital
of the Third Reich, the womb of Hitler, a Satan whose name is
associated forever with unspeakable horror.''
   It was at Berlin's Wannsee Villa in January 1942 that leading
Nazi officials plotted the Third Reich's so-called Final Solution
to exterminate Jews worldwide.
   Six million Jews were killed by the Nazis between January 1933
and May 1945, along with hundreds of thousands of others.
   Pointing out that Berlin may now become the capital of a united
Germany, Bronfman said: ``Inevitably, the questions of forgiveness
and of reconciliation arise.''
   ``Reconciliation is possible if we speak the truth. And, the
truth is that only the 6 million Jews who were murdered can
forgive,'' he said.
   Speaking to West German Chancellor Helmut Kohl and other
officials present for the opening ceremony, Bronfman said the
memory of Nazi atrocities was ``painful'' for both sides.
   ``Yours because it is part of your history, ours because it is
the worst thing that ever happened to us _ it is the only real
bridge between us, the only road to reconciliation,'' Bronfman said.
   He said the new generation of Germans should not be blamed.
   ``We do demand, nonetheless, an admission of collective
responsibility. The new Germany must forever teach what happened,
so the lowest point ever reached in man's inhumanity to man, can
never occur again,'' he said.
   Kohl, invited to speak at the opening ceremony, said the
location and date of the conference gave it a ``special meaning.''
The two German states are pushing for swift unification since East
Germany's Communist government was toppled in a peaceful revolution
last fall.
   ``Never may it be forgotten that the genocide of the European
Jews was prepared and directed by the national socialists under the
violent leadership from Berlin,'' Kohl said referring to the Nazis.
   He said it remains the duty of ``all democratic powers, also
those in a united Germany, to fight without compromise against
those who secretly or openly spread prejudice,'' against the Jews
or their religion.
   He said a united Germany will continue to pursue a close and
honest relationship with Israel.
   However, Kohl said that for decades East Germany's Communist
leaders denied responsibility for the Holocaust, leaving it to West
Germany to shoulder the blame. He said that it would now be the
task of school officials in East Germany to deal truthfully in
teaching about Germany's past.
   Also attending the meeting were former East German Communist
Premier Hans Modrow and Gregor Gysi, head of East Germany's
reformed Communist Party.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0043 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 1725EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BrennekeTrial 1stLd-Writethru a0677 05-06 0830</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brenneke Trial, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0677,0848</SECOND>
<HEAD>Jury Foreman Says He Never Doubted Brenneke's Innocence</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 12th graf, `During Brenneke's...,' to fix spelling of
name. SUBS 18th graf, `In his...,' to CORRECT to assistant U.S.
attorney, sted district attorney.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By MARILYNN WHEELER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PORTLAND, Ore. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Jurors never doubted Richard J. Brenneke's
claim of CIA connections or his story about Reagan-Bush campaign
officials trying to get Iran to delay the release of U.S. hostages
until after the 1980 election, the jury foreman says.
   ``We all came away extremely comfortable with the verdict and
extremely convinced that Mr. Brenneke was not guilty of any of the
charges,'' said foreman Mark Kristoff of Beaverton.
   Brenneke, a shadowy figure who has claimed involvement in the
Iran-Contra affair, was indicted on five counts of lying to a
federal judge in Denver in 1988. At the time, he was appearing as a
character witness for Heinrich Rupp, a Denver gold dealer convicted
of bank fraud.
   Brenneke was charged with making false declarations, a charge
slightly stronger than perjury, about his and Rupp's alleged CIA
connections, and about the alleged hostage delay and the key
officials involved.
   The jury returned its verdict clearing Brenneke after five hours
of deliberation Friday. The votes were unanimous in each of the
five rounds of secret balloting, said Kristoff.
   ``There never was a guilty vote,'' Kristoff said Saturday.
   In numerous media interviews, Brenneke has said he had
first-hand knowledge about the Iran-Contra arms deals. Called
before a Senate subcommittee on narcotics and international
relations in 1988, Brenneke claimed to have run drugs from Colombia
to the U.S. as part of a Contra supply operation. He also testified
to having purchased arms in Czechoslovakia for the Nicaraguan
rebels. That testimony was called ``slanderous'' by then-Vice
President Bush, and a 1989 Senate committee report concluded that
Brenneke never had the Central Intelligence Agency connections he
claimed.
   In the testimony in Denver that led to his trial, Brenneke said
he had met Rupp in 1957 when they worked together for Air America,
the CIA proprietary airline. In October 1980, Brenneke told the
judge, he and Rupp helped to arrange a series of meetings in Paris
concerning the 52 Americans taken hostage by Iranian militants in
the U.S. Embassy in Tehran.
   Brenneke told the judge that Rupp had flown George Bush, then
the Republican vice presidential candidate, to the secret meetings.
At his trial last week, however, Brenneke testified he did not
actually see Bush in Paris.
   He claimed that the negotiations were attended by the late CIA
director William Casey, then head of Ronald Reagan's campaign, and
Donald P. Gregg, who at the time was a CIA agent and is now U.S.
ambassador to South Korea.
   During Brenneke's trial, Gregg testified he was at the Delaware
seashore the weekend Brenneke said the meetings took place and
produced snapshots to prove it. A retired meteorologist popped up
among the defense witnesses, saying he had consulted 1980 weather
maps and found Gregg's photographs could not have been taken on the
weekend in question.
   Another defense witness, former National Security Adviser
Richard V. Allen, acknowledged there was concern among the Reagan
camp about the possibility that a hostage release just before the
election could mean a win for Carter. But Allen also said he did
not attend any meeting in Paris.
   In the end, the 52 hostages, seized Nov. 4, 1979, were not
released until Jan. 20, 1981, the day Reagan was sworn into office.
   During deliberations, Kristoff said, the jury did not consider
whether delaying the hostage release might have sabotaged President
Carter's re-election effort.
   ``We kept it simple,'' said Kristoff, an inventory control
auditor for a sportswear manufacturer. ``We didn't want to get
involved in the presidential election. ... That wasn't what we were
trying.''
   Although the jury did not discuss whether the Paris meetings
actually took place, Kristoff said, ``My feeling is that there was
a meeting. Whether those particular people were involved, is
something I can't say.''
   In his closing arguments Friday, assistant U.S. attorney Thomas
M. O'Rourke portrayed Brenneke as a rejected CIA job applicant who
operated on ``the fringes,'' trying to make arms deals, trying to
get into intelligence gathering, but never getting involved in the
real thing.
   Defense lawyers tried to show the government had buried evidence
of Brenneke's work for the CIA.
   After the verdict, defense lawyer Michael Scott said the jury's
finding does not mean that Bush was actually in Paris meeting with
Iranians before the election. The verdict, Scott said, ``means the
jury did not find my client guilty.''
   Former CIA agent Frank Snepp, who in 1977 tried to publish a
book criticizing intelligence operations in Vietnam but was blocked
by the courts, testified that the the agency used front
organizations to conceal government involvement in certain
operations.
   Kristoff said such testimony was key in the jury deliberations.
   ``The main thing we kept coming back to was the term
`deniability,''' said Kristoff.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0044 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 1726EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-KilaueaVolcano     05-06 0357</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Kilauea Volcano,0366</SECOND>
<HEAD>Volcano Flow Pauses at Ocean's Edge</HEAD>
<DATELINE>KALAPANA, Hawaii (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   One arm of the unpredictable lava flow
that encircles this coastal town stalled Sunday as molten rock
pooled in a low spot just short of its expected plunge into the sea.
   Another branch of the flow remained active, moving at up to 30
feet per hour, near a church and store, said Bruce Butts, deputy
administrator for Hawaii County Civil Defense.
   Kalapana, a tiny country town that boasts just one store, was
sealed off, its residents gone because scientists are certain that
lava from Kilauea Volcano will overrun what's left of the community
sometime soon.
   One arm of the flow pooled at the base of sand dunes near Harry
K. Brown State Park, Butts said. It was just a matter of time, he
said, until enough lava amassed to spill over the sand and ooze
into the ocean.
   The Kalapana Mauna Kea Congregational Church and Kalapana Store
and Drive-In were standing Sunday, although Butts said the flow was
active to the west and north of the structures and threatening
both. The town's other church has been moved out of harm's way.
   The seven-year eruption had destroyed 136 homes in Kalapana and
elswhere on the volcano's flank, 60 of them since April 4. In
requesting a federal disaster declaration for Hawaii Island on
Saturday, Gov. John Waihee said damage totals $61 million.
   Residents and reporters were ordered out of the park area
Saturday night, and Civil Defense had to move its command post from
there to a papaya grove on higher ground, Butts said.
   The area was sealed off because unstable winds were blowing
noxious gases from burning asphalt. Lava also was burning trees in
the area and setting off explosions of methane gas in the ground,
Butts said.
   Officials were concerned about a possible health threat when the
hot lava reaches the ocean's salt water and produces steam clouds,
known as laze, that contain hydrochloric acid and other potentially
hazardous chemicals.
   ``Our main concern is the trade winds,'' Butts said. ``As long
as there are trade winds, the laze will be blown away.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0045 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 1730EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Philippines-US     05-06 0585</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Philippines-US,0605</SECOND>
<HEAD>Philippine Investigators Seeking Leads in Slaying of U.S.
Serviceman</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT H. REID</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MANILA, Philippines (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Philippine investigators said Sunday
they had no firm evidence linking Communist rebels to the slaying
of U.S. Marine and were considering other motives for the killing
near the Subic Bay naval base.
   Gunnery Sgt. John Fredette, 34, of La Buena, Calif., was fatally
wounded late Friday on a darkened street in Olongapo, the garrison
town near the U.S.-run Subic Bay base, 50 miles west of Manila.
   The killing led U.S. officials to cancel all off-post leaves and
ban non-essential travel for the 40,000 troops, Defense Department
civilian employees and dependents at the six U.S. bases in the
Philippines.
   In Manila, a spokesman for President Corazon Aquino expressed
the government's regret over the slaying and pledged that the
Filipino military would take all necessary steps to protect
Americans.
   ``We grieve with the family of Sgt. Fredette,'' said Deputy
Presidential Press Secretary Horacio Paredes. ``The military
authorities are taking whatever measures are necessary to assure
the safety of American personnel in the bases.''
   Fredette's slaying follows a warning issued earlier this month
by Philippine officials that the Marxist New People's Army was
planning to kill an American before the May 14 start of talks on
extending the lease for the six U.S. bases.
   Mrs. Aquino has refused to say whether she supports extending
the lease, which expires in 1991. Leftists have called the bases an
infringement on Filipino sovereignty.
   No one has claimed responsibility for Fredette's killing, but
Olongapo police said on Saturday that they suspected Communist
rebels. Fredette's watch and wallet were not taken by the
assailants, police said.
   But on Sunday, Brig. Gen. Gerardo Flores, chief of staff of the
national police, said there was no firm evidence that New People's
Army guerrillas were responsible for the slaying.
   ``The theory that Sgt. Fredette was killed by the New People's
Army is still inconclusive,'' Flores told reporters. ``Our
investigators are zeroing in on other angles.''
   Flores added that Fredette, who had been in the Philippines
about a week on temporary assignment from El Toro, Calif., was shot
with a .38-caliber pistol, while urban guerrillas normally use
.45-caliber weapons in their attacks.
   On Sunday, the Olongapo police were offering alternative
theories.
   Police said they were investigating a possibility that the
killing may have been drug-related because Fredette had been seen
hours earlier talking with some Filipinos who appeared to be high
on drugs.
   Another theory was that the killers may have confused Fredette
for another American who lived near the scene of the shooting,
police said.
   Although police had questioned about 100 people, an investigator
said there were still no firm leads.
   ``All we get are negative results, but troop operations are
continuing,'' said police Sgt. Elmer de Loen. ``We are really
having a hard time.''
   The slaying and restrictions on off-base travel have hurt
businesses catering to U.S. personnel near the bases.
   Sources in Olongapo, requesting anonymity, suggested that police
might be facing political pressure to avoid linking the slaying to
the rebels so that the U.S. military will lift the restrictions,
which threaten the local economy.
   If the rebels were responsible, Fredette would be the sixth
American slain by NPA guerrillas since April 1989, when Army Col.
James ``Nick'' Rowe was assassinated in suburban Quezon City.
   The first attack by Communist rebels on American troops was in
April 1974 when three Navy officers were killed on the edge of the
Subic base.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0046 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 1754EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SouthAfrica     05-06 0467</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-South Africa,0478</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mandela Says Government Must Abandon White Privileges</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto JOH1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GREG MYRE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SOWETO, South Africa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   African National Congress leader
Nelson Mandela said Sunday that black-white negotiations cannot
succeed until the government abandons its insistence on special
privileges and protections for whites.
   Mandela, addressing a mostly black crowd of 50,000 at a soccer
stadium, said last week's groundbreaking talks between his African
National Congress and the white-led government were successful.
   But he said the government's demand of special ``group rights''
for whites and other minorities is unacceptable to the ANC, the
country's most powerful opposition group.
   ``We do not want discussions that have started so well to be
determined by any solution which is based on race,'' Mandela said.
``Any form of racialism is a formula for disaster.''
   President F.W. de Klerk has repeatedly said he wants to
dismantle the country's apartheid policies of racial segregation
and negotiate a new constitution that includes the country's black
majority.
   He has said, however, that a one-person, one-vote system would
lead the 28 million blacks to dominate the country's 5 million
whites and other minorities. De Klerk has said he envisions some
mechanism that would give whites veto power on major policy
decisions.
   Mandela said he wants to meet de Klerk before the two sides hold
further talks and will urge him to abandon the idea of special
rights for whites.
   ``The fact that Mr. de Klerk wants to bring this concept to the
negotiating table means that white South Africa does not yet trust
us,'' Mandela said.
   ``Our duty, both as black and white leadership, is now to go all
out into the country and talk to our people not in terms of black
and white, but in terms of South Africans,'' Mandela added.
   The crowd of 50,000 on this warm, sunny day was significantly
smaller than recent ANC rallies at the same Soccer City stadium on
the edge of Soweto, the huge black township outside Johannesburg.
   When Mandela appeared at Soccer City in February, two days after
his release from prison, more than 100,000 people turned out. When
Walter Sisulu and several other ANC leaders appeared in October
shortly after their release from prison, more than 70,000 attended.
   Mandela said ``some members of the press are going to say that
this rally was not as big as expected because blacks in this
country are not in favor of negotiations.'' But, he added, ``There
is no doubt that our people are fully behind these negotiations.''
   Smaller, more militant black groups such as the Pan Africanist
Congress and the Azanian People's Organization oppose negotiations
with the government and have accused the ANC of ``selling out.''
They say they are only willing to negotiate the direct transfer of
power from whites to blacks.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0047 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 1758EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-EastGermany-Riots     05-06 0315</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-East Germany-Riots,0323</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rightists Clash with Foreign Workers; Five Injured, Eight Arrested</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-East Germany</HEAD>
<DATELINE>EAST BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Rightist extremists and foreign workers
fought street battles with clubs and bottles early Sunday, and the
official East German news agency ADN said five people were injured
and eight arrested.
   A policemen was among the injured, the report said.
   Foreign guest workers are a labor force imported by the former
socialist government, with many of them doing menial or poorly paid
jobs. Some of the workers had long-term contracts with the
government for their services and have been in East Germany for
years, but their future residency status is unclear.
   East Germany has 100,000 foreign guest workers, most of them
Vietnamese and Africans. Many of them contend racism is on the rise
in East Germany.
   Sunday's violence broke out near a housing complex in the
Lichtenberg district where many foreign workers live, ADN said. The
police intervened to prevent the clashes from spreading to other
neighborhoods.
   The fighting apparently began after a group of rightists left a
disco. Police quickly halted the worst of the fighting, but the
report said rival gangs roamed the neighborhood in the predawn
hours.
   At a congress of trade unions on Friday, there were numerous
reports of conflicts involving foreigners and Germans in factories,
many of which are expected to close as East Germany adopts a free
market economy when it unifies with West Germany.
   Foreigners who have lived in their communities since May 5, 1988
were allowed to run for the first time in East Germany's local
elections on Sunday, and 81 were among the more than quarter of a
million candidates.
   Leaflets and posters were plastered overnight in subway stations
and on walls saying ``Germans for Germans'' and ``National
Alternative for Germany.''
   Ultra-rightist parties such as the Republican Party and the
National Alternative were kept off the ballot.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0048 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 1823EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Pope-Lithuania     05-06 0347</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Pope-Lithuania,0358</SECOND>
<HEAD>Pope Urges Baltic States to Hold Talks With Moscow</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Soviet-Baltics, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARY BETH SHERIDAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MEXICO CITY (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Pope John Paul II on Sunday urged the three
Baltic republics of Lithuania, Latvia and Estonia to negotiate with
Moscow in their effort to gain independence from the Soviet Union.
   John Paul said the rights of the republics must be balanced
against the damage that Soviet President Mikhail S. Gorbachev's
policies of economic and political liberalization could suffer.
   ``Things must be resolved by a dialogue, but by an effective
dialogue,'' the pontiff told reporters in a news conference on his
flight from Rome to Mexico. ``One cannot go beyond this at this
time.''
   On Friday, Latvia followed Lithuania and Estonia in declaring
independence from the Soviet Union.
   Leaders of overwhelmingly Roman Catholic Lithuania have been
appealing for international support for their break with Moscow.
   John Paul said the rights of the Baltic nations were violated by
the 1939 pact between the Soviet Union and Nazi Germany that
resulted in Soviet domination of the formerly independent lands.
   ``On the other hand, naturally, there is an international order
_ in this case even the order of Soviet perestroika, which takes
into account the whole dimension of an immense country which is
made up of many peoples,'' said the pope, who was born in Poland.
   ``But certainly perestroika must open itself to _ and I think it
already has opened itself _ to this aspiration of the peoples that
make up the Soviet Union.'' Perestroika is the catchword for
Gorbachev's reform program.
   Gorbachev has called on the Baltic states to withdraw their
declarations of independence and follow a lengthy constitutional
path if they want to secede.
   He has imposed a partial economic embargo on Lithuania in order
to make his point. Estonia and Latvia have taken a more gradual
approach in their quest for independence and have so far escaped
economic penalties from Moscow.
   John Paul met Gorbachev in December, and diplomatic ties between
Moscow and the Holy See were established three months later.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0049 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 1857EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Guatemala-Crash     05-06 0356</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Guatemala-Crash,0373</SECOND>
<HEAD>Crash of U.S.-Bound Plane in Guatemala Kills 19</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto GUA1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ALFONSO ANZUETO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>GUATEMALA CITY (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Investigators on Sunday sifted through the
wreckage of a DC-6 cargo plane that crashed in a residential
neighborhood, killing its three U.S. crew members and 16 people on
the ground.
   Twenty people were injured and 16 houses damaged when the
Miami-bound Aerial Transit plane crashed shortly after takeoff
Saturday.
   The cause of the crash in southwestern Guatemala City was not
known.
   Investigators picked through the wreckage Sunday, and officials
tried to identify the charred bodies of the vicitms.
   An official at Aerial Transit Co. in Miami identified the three
American crew members as Capt. Joseph Babody of Detroit, co-pilot
J. Theodore of Palm Beach, Fla., and engineer Dallas White of Miami
Springs, Fla.
   The plane took off from Guatemala City's international airport
at 2:48 p.m. (4:48 EDT) and crashed into the Monserrat and Loomas
del Rodeo neighborhoods, north of the airport, about five minutes
later.
   The assistant director of Civil Aviation, Natzul Mendez, said
the control tower lost contact with the plane a few minutes after
takeoff.
   He said Guatemala's Civil Aviation officials will conduct an
investigation to determine the cause of the crash.
   Homes caught fire when the crash set off propane tanks used for
cooking, hampering rescue efforts in this city of 2 million.
   Tom Stocks, vice president of Aerial Transit, said there was no
indication of any problem when the plane left Miami on Saturday for
El Salvador and Guatemala. ``They apparently had some problem with
one engine, and as they were making the go-around, apparently it
crashed,'' Stocks said.
   He said he expected a U.S. investigation into the crash.
   ``We operate under U.S. rules _ the Federal Aviation
Administration would be involved,'' Stock said.
   The plane was carrying snow peas and drawback, cloth that is
sent overseas for sewing, he said.
   Aerial Transport flies the Guatemala-Miami route three to four
times a week, and has never had a crash before, he said.
   The transport company flies eight planes, including several
DC-6s, around the Caribbean and Latin America, he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0050 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 1859EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-IMF-Quotas     05-06 0453</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-IMF-Quotas,450</SECOND>
<HEAD>Third World Group Balks at Punishing IMF Delinquents</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CARL HARTMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A group of Third World countries in the
International Monetary Fund on Sunday said an expected agreement on
$60 billion in contributions to the fund should not be linked to
plans that would require 11 developing countries to make their loan
payments current or lose their voting rights.
   ``The proposal for suspension of voting and representation
rights of those members will not serve a useful purpose and is not
acceptable,'' said the Group of 24 Third World nations.
   The group, known as G-24, includes cabinet ministers and heads
of central banks. Sayyed Mohammad Hossein, head of Iran's central
bank, is chairman of the group.
   After a closed session, the group issued a statement addressing
recent U.S.-backed recommendations to link the increased
contribution to making 11 delinquent countries pay $4.3 billion
dollars in arrears they owe the fund.
   It also has been proposed that to get the delinquents to pay up,
the fund could suspend their right to vote.
   Iran is not among the 11 countries in arrears.
   The G-24 statement came as Treasury Secretary Nicholas F. Brady
met with finance ministers from Japan, West Germany, Britain,
France, Italy and Canada. They were trying to reach agreement on
the exact amount of new IMF contributions and other fund business,
including what to do about the arrears.
   On Thursday a senior Treasury official supported a
carrot-and-stick approach that would offer help from a special
program to countries in arrears if they agree to new policies
designed to put them in better shape to pay up.
   Under the proposal, the IMF would suspend the countries' rights
to vote in the fund until they made the payments. IMF voting rights
correspond roughly to a government's contributions, known as quotas.
   The U.S. contribution to the $60 billion in increased quotas
would be about $12 billion. That would not change U.S. voting
rights, since other IMF members also would contribute. The United
States has the largest single voting power, just short of 20
percent.
   However, the G-24 would have enough votes _ just over 15 percent
_ to block an agreement.
   At a news conference presenting the statement, Adeli declined to
say whether G-24 members would vote against the $60 billion quota
increase if it is linked to the arrears plan.
   He added that the group did not want to delay the agreement on
the increased quotas.
   ``If this is taken up in the Interim Committee, the developing
countries would discuss it and hope to reach an agreement,'' he
said.
   The 11 delinquent countries are: Sudan, Zambia, Peru, Guayana,
Honduras, Cambodia, Liberia, Panama, Sierra Leone, Somalia and
Vietnam.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0051 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 1839EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-ChildrenHit     05-06 0561</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Children Hit,0589</SECOND>
<HEAD>Driver in Accident that Killed 3 Won't Talk to Police</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KATHERINE SCOBEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>RIVERSIDE, Ill. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The driver of a car that plowed through a
baseball diamond, killing three children, blacked out before the
tragedy and remembers little, his wife said Sunday.
   The driver, James J. Harasek, 59, refused to answer questions
from investigators, said Don Doneske, police chief in this Chicago
suburb.
   Harasek and eight other people were injured in the accident
Saturday, when his car scattered players at a ``T-ball'' baseball
game for young players.
   Two boys and a girl were killed, and six of those injured were
children. All the children were 7 or 8 years old.
   A woman who identified herself as Harasek's wife, Loretta,
speaking through sobs in a telephone interview, said her husband
remembered little of the accident.
   ``He blacked out, he doesn't remember hitting nothing till he
hit the building, that's when he knew he hit something,'' she said.
``I'm very deeply hurt and so upset I can't even begin to say how
bad I feel.''
   Asked about a report in the Chicago Sun-Times that her husband
had a heart condition, Mrs. Harasek said he had medical problems,
but refused to comment further.
   Harasek's lawyer, Charles G. Levy, refused to comment on his
client's health. The attorney said he had advised Harasek against
talking to the police for the time being.
   Harasek was in fair condition at MacNeal Hospital in suburban
Berwyn and was to undergo surgery on a fractured elbow, said Mary
Pappas, a hospital spokeswoman.
   Two children remained in critical condition Sunday at Loyola
University Medical Center, said Michael Maggio, a spokesman for the
hospital. Three other children were in fair condition and another
was in serious condition.
   One adult remained in fair condition at Loyola; the other had
been treated and released.
   ``Parents are, well, suffering along with their kids,'' said the
Rev. Leon Wagner of St. Mary's Church in Riverside, who knew
several of the children from the church or parish school.
   ``I'm trying to recall which father said, `I wish it was me
instead of him,''' Wagner said.
   St. Mary's was packed during a prayer service for the children
Sunday afternoon.
   Doneske, the police chief, said at a news conference Sunday that
he would ask a Cook County grand jury to order testimony from the
driver and subpoena medical records from the hospital where he was
being treated.
   Mike Lawrence, a spokesman for the Illinois Secretary of State's
office, said Harasek had a June 1989 conviction for speeding.
   Police said Harasek appeared dazed immediately after the
accident.
   ``I asked him what happened and he didn't remember,'' said
Officer Robert Gordon.
   Gordon said he didn't smell alcohol on Harasek, who has a valid
driver's license.
   The accident occurred just as the children were beginning a game
of T-ball, a kind of Little League baseball for young children in
which the ball is set up on a tee in front of the batter rather
than pitched.
   The 1989 Cadillac smashed into a bench full of players and
continued across the field, finally crossing a four-lane road and
smashing into a building.
   On Sunday, the park was empty. Sal Scaletta, a Little League
coach, said the league doesn't play on Sundays. Said Scaletta: ``If
it had happened today, it wouldn't have been a tragedy.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0052 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 1843EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Floods 1stLd-Writethru a0705 05-06 0711</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Floods, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0705,0723</SECOND>
<HEAD>Flooding Worsens In Parts Of Ark., Okla., But Texas Easing</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Subs the 9th graf, ``On the Oklahoma,'' to update lake height
and drain rate.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By ROGER PETTERSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   National Guardsmen helped sandbag against rising streams Sunday
in Arkansas and a reservoir on the Texas-Oklahoma border that
flooded shoreline homes reached a record height and kept rising.
   A record flood crest on the Trinity River in Texas was moving
downstream toward the Gulf of Mexico, but a neighborhood in Dallas
remained flooded out.
   The death toll from the flooding caused by last week's
thunderstorms was six, all in Texas. A total of 12 Texas deaths
have been blamed on weather in the past several weeks.
   Marine Reserves in Arkansas for weekend training at Camp
Robinson joined National Guardsmen and civilian volunteers in
completing sandbagging before dawn Sunday around 25 homes in
low-lying sections of North Little Rock.
   ``We're going to be in fairly good shape today unless the sand
walls that we've made don't hold,'' said city spokesman Joe Smith.
``The water's there but we were able to prepare well enough to keep
the water off of the neighborhoods, we think. We're keeping our
fingers crossed.''
   Emergency personnel in two communities elsewhere in Arkansas
also requested Guardsman to help with sandbagging, said Gary Talley
of the state Office of Emergency Services.
   The worst of the flooding was expected to be more apparent
Monday in the Little Rock area, about 24 hours before the Arkansas
River is predicted to crest 5 feet above flood stage, Talley said.
The river was rising toward a crest 1{ feet above flood stage
Wednesday at Pine Bluff, where about 100 homes had been evacuated.
   Water began slowly receding in western Arkansas, where the Fort
Smith-Van Buren area was hardest hit. The Arkansas River crested at
about 35 feet there Saturday, 13 feet above flood stage.
   On the Oklahoma-Texas border, Lake Texoma topped the old record
of 643 feet above sea level Saturday, nearly 27 feet above normal,
and continued rising Sunday to 644.8 feet even though the Corps of
Engineers was releasing 145,000 cubic feet of water per second. The
lake was expected to crest Monday at about 645 feet, or 5 feet
above the overflow spillways.
   Mobile homes around the lakeshore were inundated and Oklahoma's
Marshall County had only one road leading to the outside because of
high water from arms of the reservoir.
   Despite warnings of submerged power lines, floating propane
tanks, trees, docks and other obstacles, many sightseers toured the
lake by boat, officials said. Wakes from the boats were blamed for
destabilizing some submerged structures, said Marshall County Civil
Defense Director John Martin.
   In Texas, water from the Trinity River still stood several feet
deep Sunday in the Rochester Park area southeast of downtown
Dallas, as residents spent a fourth day waiting for the water to
recede. Flood stage is 30 feet and Sunday the Trinity stood at 43.8
feet in Dallas.
   Rochester Park resident Alester Crumbley said this is the third
time in a year his home has been flooded. He moved back into his
home only two weeks ago after spending $11,000 and several months
rebuilding from two floods last year, he said.
   Flooding continued in several rural counties along the Trinity
south of Dallas, as the record high water washed out levees.
   At Trinidad, about 60 miles southeast of Dallas, the Trinity was
47.5 feet deep Sunday, far above the 28-foot flood stage.
   ``We've still got two main roads closed. We had about 150 people
evacuated from their homes the last couple of days, and as far as I
know, water is still in their homes,'' said a dispatcher from the
Henderson County sheriff's department.
   The Red Cross in Texas counted 723 dwellings destroyed and more
than 2,000 others damaged by flooding in the last two weeks, which
the weather service called the most serious in the state since 1908.
   Conditions returned to normal Sunday for Amtrak, a spokesman
said. Amtrak trains were unable to pass through Dallas for a third
consecutive day Saturday because of flooding on the Trinity, an
Amtrak ticket clerk in Dallas said. Buses had ferried passengers to
trains on opposite sides of the river.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0053 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 1917EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ChicoRiot     05-06 0502</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Chico Riot,0519</SECOND>
<HEAD>Authorities Arrest At least 93 People In Two Days Of Disturbances</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CHICO, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A community festival in this college town
was ruined by two nights of rioting by hundreds of beer-swilling
young people who pelted officers with rocks and bottles and torched
two police cars.
   Police officers called from as far as 60 miles away arrested at
least 93 people while quelling violence at the annual Rancho Chico
Days, authorities said Sunday. Ten police officers and an unknown
number of civilians were hurt in the violence Friday and Saturday
night near California State University, Chico.
   The uproar recalled similar riots last weekend in another
California college town, San Luis Obispo, on the state's central
coast. Riots that led to scores of minor injuries prompted
officials to cancel their annual celebration promoting California
Polytechnic State University at San Luis Obispo.
   Rancho Chico Days, sponsored bybusiness interests to promote
this Sacramento Valley city, includes concerts, picnics and bicycle
races. Residents blamed visiting outsiders drinking and media and
police overreaction for the violence, centered both nights in a
three-block neighborhood near Cal State Chico.
   University officials and other critics had warned that a
disturbance was likely, citing the San Luis Obispo uprising and a
riot during a similar celebration in Chico in 1987.
   Police, school authorities and residents agreed that scores of
beer kegs at neighborhood parties contributed to the riot.
   ``Sure, it was flowing,'' resident Tony LaFrano said of the
beer. ``But everyone knew there was going to be a riot. It was
bound to happen.''
   Police said Sunday that 41 people were arrested Saturday night
after sporadic rock-throwing by scattered bands of youths developed
into car and trash burnings. Most of those arrested were
college-age youths. Late Friday night and early Saturday, 52 were
arrested.
   About 125 officers, some from as far away as Redding, 60 miles
to the north, helped quell the disturbances.
   Chico police Lt. Rich Reed said the police injuries ranged from
minor to serious. Officials did not know how many civilians may
have been injured.
   The first night's rioting erupted after police went to an
apartment complex near the university campus, and confronted about
500 youths at a floating party, many of them apparently drunk on
beer.
   ``It was a just a group of people that got together,'' said
police Capt. Jim Massie. But violence developed as the crowd grew
hostile, he added.
   ``I don't know what sparked it to get it going in that
direction. They were doing their best to hurt the officers'' with
bottles and stones, Massie said.
   Some of the revelers chanted ``Cal Poly,'' a reference to San
Luis Obispo violence.
   University officials and other critics had warned that a
disturbance was likely after a riot during a similar celebration in
1987 and after the San Luis Obispo disturbance.
   The second night of violence also began at an apartment complex,
where police were confronted by an estimated 1,000 people. Rioters
burned two police cars and a motorcycle, Reed said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0054 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 1925EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Quayle     05-06 0148</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Quayle,0152</SECOND>
<HEAD>Quayle Arrives in Italy For Eisenhower Memorial</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ROME (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Vice President Dan Quayle on Sunday began a four-day
European trip to mark the 100th birthday of the late President
Dwight D. Eisenhower.
   Quayle will lead a U.S. delegation visiting Italy, Britain and
France to honor Eishenhower, who was Supreme Commander of Allied
forces in Europe in World War II. Eisenhower was president from
1953-61.
   Greeting Quayle and his wife, Marilyn, at Ciampino Airport were
the U.S. ambassdor to Italy, Peter Secchia, and an undersecretary
in the Italian foreign ministry.
   Quayle was scheduled to meet Monday morning with President
Francesco Cossiga and later give an address commemorating
Eisenhower in the Italian Parliament. He was also to meet with
Premier Giulio Andreotti.
   Before departing for London on Monday, the vice president will
fly by helicopter to the USS Eisenhower, an American aircraft
carrier in the Mediterranean.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0055 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 1958EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-AIDSSuit 2ndLd-Writethru a0729 05-06 0714</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-AIDS Suit, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0729,0730</SECOND>
<HEAD>Marine Feels Mixture of Rage, Relief After Winning Landmark AIDS
Case</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto BX2</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS lead and 6th graf to restore Gaffney's rank, chief
warrant officer.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By DANA KENNEDY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   When a judge ruled in favor of Martin Gaffney in
his AIDS lawsuit against the U.S. government, the Marine warrant
officer didn't do much celebrating.
   Instead, he left the South Weymouth Naval Air Station where he
is a computer specialist and drove to Nantasket Beach. There he
found a deserted strip of sand to walk along and think.
   ``I just kind of turned to the ocean and breathed a sigh of
relief,'' said Gaffney, 40, whose legal battle ended April 26 when
a judge ruled that negligence by Navy doctors in 1981 led to
Gaffney's wife contracting the AIDS virus through a blood
transfusion. She died in 1987.
   Gaffney also lost a 13-month-old son to the disease and has
tested positive for the human immunodeficiency virus that causes
AIDS, although he shows no symptoms.
   Along with relief he feels rage, he said.
   The veteran officer's loyalty toward the military soured after
he sued the government. Gaffney, a chief warrant officer, is still
bitter about FBI investigations into his background and what he
says has been rudeness and betrayal on the part of Navy officials.
   ``At first I was pretty angry,'' he said. ``I felt disgust that
it had taken four years to get to this point. Then I just wished
Mutsuko would have been here to share it.''
   The family's ordeal began in 1981 when Gaffney's Japanese-born
wife, Mutsuko, entered the Long Beach Naval Hospital to have a baby.
   Gaffney's suit claimed Navy doctors botched his wife's pregnancy
by failing to perform a Caesarean section when Mrs. Gaffney was two
weeks late in delivering the baby. The baby, a boy, was eventually
stillborn and Mrs. Gaffney required a blood transfusion. The blood
she was given was contaminated with the AIDS virus.
   If a Caesarean had been performed in time, the judge said, a
blood transfusion would not have been necessary.
   Mrs. Gaffney, 38, died a year before Gaffney filed the $55
million suit in U.S. District Court in Boston. The couple's son,
John, died of AIDS in 1986.
   A second trial has been ordered to determine the amount of
damages. The case is expected to encourage others who believe they
contracted the AIDS virus through medical malpractice to sue. A
date for the trial has not been set.
   Only 6-year-old Maureene Gaffney has escaped infection. It was
the uncertainty over her future that led Gaffney to sue.
   ``I feel confident that Maureene will be taken care of,'' said
Gaffney, who has made plans for his daughter to live with his
brother's family in Lowell if necessary.
   For now, Gaffney lives with his daughter in base housing. When
they moved there, base officials barred her from the day care
center until Sen. Edward M. Kennedy intervened on Maureene's behalf.
   Maureene was admitted recently to a prestigious private school
over 11 other applicants. Gaffney said she sees a therapist
regularly to cope with the loss of her mother and brother. He said
she is aware that her father is infected with the virus, although
they don't discuss it.
   Gaffney said that he has been too busy ``with mundane things''
and the lawsuit since he was diagnosed HIV positive to think much
about his own future.
   ``I'm ready for what's going to happen as far as my own health
going downhill and I'm ready to prepare for it,'' he said. ``I
wanted justice before I left the world and before I started to
deteriorate.''
   Although his doctors recommended he take the drug AZT, which can
slow the progress of the virus, Gaffney has so far refused it. As
long as he is healthy, he said, ``I see no reason to take
medication.''
   Gaffney said that he used to feel so sad and bitter that he only
wanted to live long enough to hear a verdict in his favor. But now
he's changed his mind.
   ``If I was given a choice of going to wherever you go and being
with my wife and sons or staying with my daughter, I'd stay here
with her,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0056 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 1936EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Cyprus-Election 1stLd-Writethru a0659 05-06 0407</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Cyprus-Election, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0659,0416</SECOND>
<HEAD>Parliamentary Elections in Northern Cyprus Could Bring Change</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 13 grafs to UPDATE with 80 percent of vote
counted, centrist National Unity Party leading. Pickup 14th graf
pvs, `The opposition...'</NOTE>
<DATELINE>NICOSIA, Cyprus (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The centrist National Unity Party
appeared headed for victory in parliamentary elections Sunday in
the breakaway state of northern Cyprus.
   The parliamentary elections could have led to a change of power
for the first time since Turkey's 1974 invasion divided this island
into ethnic Greek and Turkish sectors.
   But by Sunday evening, with 80 percent of the votes counted, the
National Unity Party, which backs longtime Turkish Cypriot leader
Rauf Denktash, had a strong lead, garnering 54 percent of the votes.
   An opposition coalition, the National Struggle Party, was taking
44 percent of the votes, and the remaining 2 percent was shared by
the New Cyprus Party and the independents.
   The coalition was seeking to unseat the National Unity Party,
founded by Denktash and in power for 15 years. Analysts had said
said such a shift would help revive stalled peace talks aimed at
reuniting the breakaway Turkish Republic of North Cyprus with the
Greek Cypriots.
   The 100,000 registered voters on Sunday chose among candidates
for the 50-seat parliament. The winners will serve five-year terms.
   Turkish Cypriots declared independence in November 1983. The
state is recognized only by Turkey, which keeps an estimated 30,000
troops in the northern sector.
   In a presidential election two weeks ago, voters in the
breakaway republic gave Denktash a fourth term. He took 67 percent
of the vote.
   The opposition had accused Denktash of intransigence in
reunification talks, raising hopes on the Greek Cypriot side that
an opposition victory would lead to concessions.
   The campaign was marred by unprecedented violence. Party
activists engaged in fistfights, damaged cars and hung their own
posters over rival party ones.
   The opposition coalition comprises the conservative New Birth
Party, mainly supported by settlers from Turkey, the leftist
Socialist Liberation and Republican Turkish Parties.
   The coalition's combined vote in previous elections five years
ago was 61 percent but the divided vote gave them only a minority
of seats in Parliament. The National Unity Party captured 28 seats
with 36 percent of the vote under an election system that favors
the largest party.
   The opposition has also accused the governing party of
corruption, misuse of economic resources and partisanship,
especially in the appointment of civil servants.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0057 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 1953EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Soviet-Baltics 2ndLd-Writethru a0693 05-06 0753</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Baltics, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0693,0775</SECOND>
<HEAD>Latvians Brace for Economic Blockade in Response to Independence</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 7 grafs to UPDATE with pope urging Baltic
republics to negotiate with Moscow. Pickup pvs 5th graf, `Anatoly
Alexeyev...'Minor editing to TRIM</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By CAREY GOLDBERG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>RIGA, U.S.S.R. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Latvian politicians said Sunday they were
steeling themselves for strikes, protests and an economic blockade
now that the Kremlin has reportedly rejected their declaration of
independence.
   The Baltic republic's president, meanwhile, appealed for the
Kremlin to open talks on independence instead of ``just threatening
with blockades.''
   The televised address came a day after Latvia's Communist Party
chief, Alfreds Rubiks, quoted Soviet President Mikhail S. Gorbachev
as telling him he could not accept Latvia's secession and may
impose sanctions.
   ``We understand the situation in Latvia will be very tough, even
critical, this summer,'' said Peteris Lakis, one of the leaders of
the Latvian People's Front, which engineered Friday's declaration.
   Also Sunday, Pope John Paul II urged the three Baltic republics
_ Lithuania, Latvia and Estonia _ to negotiate with Moscow in their
efforts to gain independence.
   The Polish-born pope said the rights of the republics must be
balanced against the damage that Gorbachev's policies of economic
and political liberalization could suffer.
   ``Things must be resolved by a dialogue, but by an effective
dialogue,'' the pope told reporters on a flight from Rome to
Mexico. ``One cannot go beyond this at this time.''
   Anatoly Alexeyev, head of the Interfront Movement of non-Latvian
residents, predicted the Soviets would start an economic blockade
soon.
   Alexeyev, a prominent opponent of secession, said a labor group
representing about 140,000 workers has called a general strike for
May 15 to protest the declaration of independence.
   Neighboring Lithuania declared independence March 11, and
Gorbachev responded by sending Soviet troops to seize some
buildings and by imposing economic sanctions, including an oil and
natural gas embargo.
   Last month Estonia announced its intention to secede but stopped
short of declaring independence and set no date for leaving the
Soviet Union. The Kremlin has imposed no sanctions on Estonia.
   The Soviet Union forcibly annexed the Baltic republics in 1940.
They began campaigning for independence shortly after Gorbachev
began his reforms, and he has offered them a greater say in
economic and political decisions but not secession itself.
   Of Latvia's 2.6 million residents, 53 percent are ethnic
Latvians and 33 percent ethnic Russians. Many of the non-Latvians,
especially Russians, oppose secession.
   ``This was a step into the dark,'' Alexeyev said. ``Nobody knows
where we are going.'' Alexeyev, a Russian, said his family has been
living in what is now Latvia for 200 years.
   The televised address by Anatoly Gorbunov, Latvia's president,
appeared designed to reassure Latvians as well as carry a message
to the Kremlin.
   ``Let's begin by hearing out others' opinions and comparing
arguments and not just threatening with blockades and clinging to
the old,'' Gorbunov said.
   As he left the Latvian TV studio where he taped the address
Sunday, Gorbunov said he had not been in contact with Gorbachev.
   ``I'll call him tomorrow and present once more the essence of
our declaration and our future intentions,'' he said.
   Asked about Rubiks' report of Gorbachev's hard-line stance,
Gorbunov said the account was ``only the opinion of one party, and
on the official level there has been no statement yet.''
   Thousands of anti-independence protesters plan to gather
Wednesday during the celebration of Victory Day, the defeat of Nazi
Germany in World War II, said Viktors Alksnis, a member of
Parliament who opposed the declaration.
   He said he had expected Gorbachev's tough reaction after
Latvia's Supreme Soviet parliament voted for independence instead
of considering the Kremlin's offer of ``special status'' in a
revamped Soviet federation.
   ``No self-respecting government will hold talks with rebels,''
Alexeyev said in an interview. ``Our politicians decided to beat
their fists on the table first, and then try to talk.''
   But Lakis said he suspected Rubiks may have exaggerated the
harshness of Gorbachev's stand, and that he believed the Kremlin
would open talks within several months.
   Opponents of independence painted a darker picture of what to
expect.
   ``Unfortunately, it seems hard times are awaiting us,'' Alksnis
told 200 people who held an impromptu rally Sunday at Riga's
military stadium after a show of hand-to-hand combat, parachuting
and pyrotechnics dedicated to Victory Day.
   Alksnis said he believes that economic sanctions on Latvia had
already begun in practice, because in recent months some Soviet
factories had broken contracts and stopped supplying their Latvian
partners.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0058 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 2032EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-PhoenixCookie     05-06 0208</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Phoenix Cookie,0215</SECOND>
<HEAD>Controversial Diet Cookie Ordered Off Shelves</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JACKSON, Miss. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The U.S. Food and Drug Administration has
ordered a controversial diet cookie taken off the market, citing
``inappropriate health claims.''
   Phoenix International Marketing Co. in Sparks, Nev., has five
days to stop distributing the Phoenix Diet Cookie, which has been
under investigation by authorities in Mississippi and Louisiana.
   ``We feel that it makes inappropriate health claims,'' Jeff
Nesbit, spokesman for the FDA in Washington, said Saturday. He said
the agency hand-delivered a letter Friday ordering the cookie off
the market.
   The FDA and the Mississippi attorney general's office are
investigating the company's claims that the cookie helps prevent
high blood pressure, diabetes, cancer and other diseases.
   The FDA disputes the company's claim that the cookie will speed
the elimination of digested food.
   The cookie, billed as high-fiber and low cholesterol, doesn't
meet FDA standards to be called low-calorie, and in fact has a high
caloric content, Nesbit said.
   If the company refuses to follow the FDA's order, the agency
would seek a federal court order.
   Mississippi is examining what kind of penalty it could levy
against the company for claims that the cookie can help cure
diseases, said Special Assistant Attorney General Trey Bobinger.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0059 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 2037EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Germany-Unification     05-06 0537</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Germany-Unification,0555</SECOND>
<HEAD>Kohl Says Path Cleared For End To `Painful Separation'</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Poland-Baker, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By NESHA STARCEVIC</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>FRANKFURT, West Germany (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Chancellor Helmut Kohl, praising
the results of an international conference on Germany's future,
said Sunday nothing more stood in the way of German unity after
more than 40 years of ``painful separation.''
   At Saturday's conference in Bonn, the four victorious World War
II allies agreed that unification should go forward without delay.
   It was the first top-level unification session among the
Germanys and the Allies _ the United States, Soviet Union, Britain
and France _ which split Germany into two countries after World War
II.
   The conference, Kohl said in a statement, produced a ``historic
result for Germany and Europe.''
   ``There are no more obstacles to the realization of the right of
self-determination of all Germans,'' he said. `After more than 40
years of painful separation, the Germans' longing to be united in
one state is being fulfilled.''
   Soviet Foreign Minister Eduard Shevardnadze, meanwhile, hailed a
new era.
   ``The Cold War is over. Our planet, the world, Europe, are now
embarking on a new road,'' he said.
   Shevardnadze, Secretary of State James A. Baker III and
counterparts from Britain, France and the two German states took
part in the nearly seven-hour talks.
   The sides agreed on several issues, including a timetable for
future meetings and the inclusion of Poland in some of the talks.
Soviet objections to NATO membership by a united Germany remained
the main stumbling block.
   West Germany's foreign minister, Hans-Dietrich Genscher, said
the meeting cleared the way for quick German unification and left
it up to the Germans to determine the pace of the process.
   In an interview with the ZDF television network, Genscher
referred to a statement in which Shevardnadze was quoted as saying,
``The settlements of interior and foreign aspects of German unity
do not necessarily have to come at the same time.''
   The statement, translated by the West German Foreign Ministry,
reflected a significant shift in the Soviet position because it
separated the problem of NATO membership from other aspects of the
unification process, ministry officials said.
   ``It was a surprising formulation that's making our life
easier,'' said one Bonn diplomat, who asked not to be named.
   Genscher said Shevardnadze's ``clear distinction of interior and
foreign aspects of German unity'' reaffirmed the right of the
Germans to alone decide the time of unification.
   ``This requires from the two German states, which now hold
unification in their hands, a high degree of responsibility,''
Genscher said.
   The six foreign ministers at the conference, dubbed the
two-plus-four talks, announced a timetable for further meetings,
with a session in June in East Berlin, in July in Paris and in
September in Moscow.
   The Soviets have called for a neutral Germany.
   The Soviet news agency Tass said the Kremlin opposed German
membership in the North Atlantic Treaty Organization because it
would touch on ``Soviet security interests'' and ``disrupt the
balance of forces in Europe.''
   East Germany has long served as a buffer between the East and
West blocs. The Soviet Union has and estimated 380,000 troops in
East Germany, while the United States has about 250,000 soldiers in
West Germany.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0060 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 2017EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Dollar-Yen     05-06 0039</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Dollar-Yen,0039</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dollar Opens Lower in Tokyo</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The dollar opened at 158.36 yen on the Tokyo
foreign exchange market Monday, down from the close of 158.55 yen
Wednesday, the last day the market was open.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0061 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 2038EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Argentina-Fire     05-06 0205</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Argentina-Fire,0211</SECOND>
<HEAD>33 Die in Fire at Argentina Prison</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BUENOS AIRES, Argentina (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A fire set by inmates swept
through a prison near the city of La Plata, killing 33 prisoners
and injuring 12, officials said Sunday.
   The blaze Saturday night began when prisoners piled mattresses
and furniture against a cell block entrance and set the material on
fire to prevent guards from entering to break up a fight between
two inmates, one of whom had struck a guard, prison warden Julio
Barroso said.
   The two inmates, who were not identified, had argued over who
was the most ``macho'' and one, attempting to prove his
superiority, had called a guard and hit him, prison authorities
said.
   The fire blocked the only entrance to the fifth-floor minimum
security block and filled the area with flames and thick smoke
before prison officials and firefighters were able to break through
and extinguish the blaze, Barroso said.
   Officials said 33 prisoners in the 3,000-inmate Lisandro Olmos
Federal Prison died of burns and suffocation and 12 were
hospitalized, two in serious condition.
   It was not immediately known whether the two inmates who
provoked the tragedy survived.
   The prison is near La Plata, 34 miles south of Buenos Aires.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0062 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 2024EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Breslin     05-06 0574</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Breslin,0597</SECOND>
<HEAD>Breslin Apologizes For Racist Remarks; Asian-Americans Want Him
Fired</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Newsday columnist Jimmy Breslin has apologized
for his racist, expletive-filled newsroom tirade against a reporter
of Korean descent who criticized his column, the newspaper said
Sunday.
   But Breslin's apology, sent to Newsday staffers on Friday as an
internal computer message, failed to quell the brouhaha over his
remarks.
   On Sunday, Asian-American groups called for his resignation for
the outburst against staff reporter Ji-Yeon Mary Yuh, 25, who had
sent him an internal computer message calling his May 3 column
sexist.
   In an obscenity-laced newsroom tirade, Breslin called Yuh
``slant-eyed.''
   ``She's a yellow cur. Let's make it racial,'' Breslin said.
   His remarks, made outside the presence of Yuh, were reported by
the Daily News and in a letter of complaint to Newsday managers
from members of the paper's staff.
   The 61-year-old Pulitzer prize winner's apology said in part:
   ``To the people I work with. I am no good and once again I can
prove it. ... I am sorry. I said things I shouldn't have said. The
racial and sexual insults I spewed are never appropriate.''
   But Helen Zia, president of the New York chapter of the
Asian-American Journalists Association, said the apology was ``very
flip.''
   Zia's group joined the Coalition Against Anti-Asian Violence and
the Organization of Asian Women in demanding that Breslin resign or
be fired, and that he make a formal public apology to Yuh.
   The columnist's apology to the staff came after an internal
system-wide computer reprimand from editor Don Forst _ who called
Breslin's racist and sexist comments ``offensive and inexcusable''
_ and protests by the paper's staff, some of whom heard his
outburst.
   ``This is the worst case of racism I have encountered,'' Yuh, a
native of Chicago who lives in Jersey City, N.J., said Sunday.
   Yuh, who reports for Newsday from Queens, says she has never met
Breslin and has never communicated with him before her message
Thursday _ also sent to Forst and another editor _ which criticized
Breslin's portrayal of the role of women in Thursday's column.
   Breslin said he hated what he called ``official women,''
including his wife, City Councilwoman Ronnie Eldrdige, who he said
devoted too much of her time to official duties and not enough to
the home.
   Yuh messaged Breslin that his column was ``spewing sexism.''
   According to a letter to Newsday editor Anthony Marro, written
by reporter Jessie Mangaliman and signed by 46 staff members,
Breslin stormed into the newsroom Friday after reading Yuh's
message. In addition to the racial epithets, Breslin used coarse
sexual terms to describe Yuh, according to the letter, which
denounced Breslin's ``racist vituperation,'' and called his
behavior ``unprofessional.''
   ``There's a part of me that says, `Let him be suspended,' but
there's another part of me that says, `Let him be fired,''' said
Yuh.
   ``It proves that racism comes in all kinds of packaging, you can
encounter it anywhere, from your colleagues, in the boardroom, from
your neighbors _ not necessarily people in a white sheet,'' she
said, referring to the Ku Klux Klan.
   In a comment about her husband quoted by the Daily News on
Sunday, Eldridge said Breslin ``doesn't believe what he wrote in
his heart, but the way he is, when he knows he's wrong, he lashes
out. He just acts that way.''
   Newsday spokeswoman Chiara Coletti said Sunday the paper plans
no further action against Breslin.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0063 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 2035EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-EastGermany 2ndLd-Writethru a0731 05-06 0794</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-East Germany, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0731,0819</SECOND>
<HEAD>East Germans Vote in First Free Local Elections</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS graf 4-5 pvs, `Hinrich Lehmann-Grube' with 3 grafs
detail on his dual citizenship, CORRECTS style on Hanover. Pickup
6th pvs, `The parties...'</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto BER1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARK FRITZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>EAST BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   East Germans voted in their first free local
elections Sunday, choosing a city councilman from West Germany as
mayor of their second-largest city, early projections showed.
   The conservative party of Prime Minister Lothar de Maiziere
captured the most local government seats, followed by the
left-leaning Social Democrats, according to projections by West
Germany's ARD television.
   The reformed Communist Party, now called the Party of Democratic
Socialism, was finishing a distant third.
   Hinrich Lehmann-Grube, a city council member from the West
German city of Hanover, ran for mayor of Leipzig, and television
projections indicated he was the winner.
   Lehmann-Grube holds dual East and West German citizenship. Since
he became an East German citizen only last month, he was not
allowed to vote in the election. However, anyone who is an East
German citizen over the age of 18 can be elected to office.
   It was not immediately clear whether he would quit his Hanover
post.
   The parties' performances generally reflected the results of the
March 18 national elections, when East Germany's first democratic
government was elected.
   However, de Maiziere's Christian Democrats took only about 34
percent of the vote in local races, according to the ARD
projections, compared to the 41 percent they gained in the March
balloting.
   Local issues dominated individual races, so it was unclear if
any dissatisfaction with the rush to unite the two Germanys was a
factor in the races.
   The Social Democrats were holding much the same total as in the
national elections, and the Christian Democrats' losses appeared to
have been distributed among a group of small, specialized parties.
   The Social Democrats, however, captured the two largest cities,
East Berlin and Leipzig, the ARD projections showed.
   Sunday's turnout was about 80 percent, short of the 93 percent
who voted in the March elections.
   About 250,000 people from 62 parties ran for more than 20,000
councils and municipal posts in 7,784 cities, districts, towns and
villages. About 12.4 million East Germans were eligible to vote.
   The local balloting effectively gives local communities control
of their hometown governments and bureaucracies after four decades
of centralized Communist control.
   Far-right groups were kept off the ballots and foreigners for
the first time were allowed to take part. Radicals plastered
leaflets across the country during the night calling for an
election boycott.
   The balloting followed widespread clashes in East Berlin the
night before between right-wing radicals and foreign workers. Eight
people were reported arrested and five were injured.
   Walter Berghofer, who was elected as Communist mayor of Dresden
in 1986 in elections that were widely presumed to be rigged, lost a
bid to hang onto his office, the projections indicated.
   Sunday's voting was only the second free balloting in East
Germany's four-decade history and brought the revolt against
Stalinist oppression full circle.
   In the last local elections on May 7, 1989, the Communist
government had claimed that candidates it backed won 99 percent of
the vote.
   The protests that followed eventually exploded into the mass
demonstrations that ousted hard-line leader Erich Honecker in
October and opened the Berlin Wall.
   The Christian Democrats won the March elections by promising
prosperity to East Germans through a fast merger with West Germany
and a quick shift to a free market economy.
   Since then, there have been widespread fears that East Germans
will suffer joblessness and lower living standards when they lose
their vast socialist subsidies.
   De Maiziere voted in his home district in East Berlin and called
the elections the ``second important test of democracy in the
country.''
   In the small community of Rosin, voting was interrupted for 30
minutes after an anonymous telephone caller said a bomb would
explode in a school being used as an election precinct. The school
was closed while police searched for a device.
   Police reported another bomb threat near Merseburg, and said a
26-year-old West Berliner was arrested in Hennigsdorf for trying to
plaster leaflets for the outlawed right-wing Republican Party.
   Leaflets and posters were plastered overnight in subway stations
and on walls saying ``Germans' Germany'' and ``National Alternative
for Germany.''
   Right-wing radicals fought street battles with foreigners late
Saturday night and early Sunday in a section of East Berlin where
many foreign workers live.
   Tension between foreign and German workers has been increasing
in recent weeks as East Germany moves toward a free market economy.
   The elections likely were the last for East Germany as a
sovereign state. Unification with West Germany is expected to be
completed next year.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0064 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 2050EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-RainDance     05-06 0362</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Rain Dance,0373</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hundreds Join Rain Dance and Pray for End to Drought</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVE CLARK</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MANDAN, N.D. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Indians, ministers and civic leaders joined
in traditional dances, songs and spoken prayers on Sunday in a bid
for rain to end a drought now in its third year.
   ``Dear God, hear the prayer of your people, no matter what
language we use and no matter what name we call you by,'' said the
Rev. Ben Dove of the Presbyterian Church of Mandan.
   ``We do ask for rain because we do not know how to farm or to
prosper for much longer without the showers we long for.''
   Many of the approximately 200 people attending the ceremony on a
high hill in Fort Abraham Lincoln State Park joined in Indian rain
dances.
   Gov. George Sinner proclaimed Sunday ``pray for rain'' day in
North Dakota. The state has been gripped by drought the last two
years and is emerging from its driest winter this century. Many
churches have included rain prayers in their Sunday services for
some weeks.
   ``A time of drought brings us to the clear reality that we are
not sufficient unto ourselves,'' said Sister Thomas Welder,
president of the University of Mary in Bismarck. ``All of us thirst
and all of us are parched. We long for life-giving rains.''
   Grace Henry of the Fort Berthold Reservation offered a ball of
corn kernels ``to our dear Lord and to the thunderbirds,'' then
said a prayer in the Hidatsa language.
   Wanda Johnson, a Navajo Indian from Crownpoint, N.M., and John
Fox Sr., an elder Arikara, also offered prayers in their native
tongues.
   Five students in traditional Arikara dress danced to the
pounding of a drum and melodic chanting.
   Many of the speakers stressed that Indians and non-Indians are
unified in their dependence on the land.
   ``I am acutely aware that this land in a special way is more
yours as Indians than people like me whose skin is of a lighter
color,'' Dove said.
   ``But my friends, I remind you that we love this land too. ...
We are one people and we are children of one father.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0065 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 2103EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-SpringsteenMuseum     05-06 0245</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Springsteen Museum,0250</SECOND>
<HEAD>Springsteen's Driver's License, Surfboard to be Auctioned</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NR1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TODD RICHISSIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ASBURY PARK, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A defunct museum claiming to have the
world's largest collection of Bruce Springsteen memorabilia is
putting it up for sale, offering the singer's surfboard, draft card
and 1970 driver's license.
   The items are remnants of the Asbury Park Rock 'n' Roll Museum,
which closed its doors last year. The museum wants to sell its
inventory in a package it hopes will go for at least $50,000.
   ``We had a great time doing it, but we can't seem to work it out
where we can keep it open,'' said Billy Smith, an Asbury Park
native who with Stephen Bumball owns most of the museum's
artifacts. ``Hopefully, somebody will buy this stuff and display
it.''
   Smith said he would prefer the collection remain in Asbury Park,
a down-at-the heels resort town once famous for its carnival rides
and boardwalk. It's the setting for several of Springsteen's early
songs.
   Among the items for sale: a rare 1966 unreleased single by
Springsteen's first band, the Castiles; the surfboard; driver's
license, and draft card.
   Along with the Springsteen artifacts are photos of a young John
Bongiovi, who became rocker Jon Bon Jovi.
   The museum was in the Palace Amusement Arcade, where parts of
Springsteen's ``Tunnel of Love'' video were shot. When the arcade
closed last year, so did the museum, and its contents went into
storage.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0066 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 2107EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Mexico-Pope 3rdLd-Writethru a0730 05-06 0803</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mexico-Pope, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0730,0823</SECOND>
<HEAD>Pope Beatifies Five As Tour of Mexico Begins</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: UPDATES thruout with beatifications, REORGANIZES. No pickup.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos MO3,4</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARY BETH SHERIDAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MEXICO CITY (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Pope John Paul II, beginning a mission to
strengthen his church and improve relations with Mexico, beatified
the country's most revered Indian on Sunday and urged Mexicans to
emulate him in their fight to improve society.
   ``You cannot ... remain indifferent before the suffering of your
brothers, before poverty, corruption, the outrages against truth
and human rights,'' said the gold-robed pontiff at a Mass.
   The eight-day visit to Mexico is John Paul's 47th trip outside
Italy as pope, his 10th to Latin America and his second to Mexico.
   At the modern, tent-shaped Sanctuary of the Virgin of Guadalupe,
the pope beatified Juan Diego, a humble Indian honored as the man
to whom the Virgin appeared in 1531.
   John Paul also beatified a 19th-century priest and three Indians
known as the Child Martyrs of Tlaxcala, who died almost 450 years
ago. Beatification is a step toward possible sainthood.
   In a last-minute change of plans, Mexican President Carlos
Salinas de Gortari welcomed the pope at the airport, instead of the
foreign minister. The move emphasized recent warming of relations
between the Vatican and Mexico, which has some of the harshest
anti-clerical laws outside the Communist bloc despite being
overwhelmingly Roman Catholic.
   In his homily, the pope said Catholics ``cannot in fact refrain
from participation in politics, that is, the multiple and various
economic, social, legislative, administrative and cultural actions
destined to promote ... the common good.''
   The pope appeared to be indirectly challenging Mexico's laws
against participation by the church in politics. The 1917
constitution, written after years of revolutionary upheaval, denies
recognition to the church and bars priests from speaking about
politics from the pulpit.
   Despite the restrictions, the pope received a rousing welcome as
he began his tour. More than 200,000 people lined the nine-mile
route through the city to the Basilica of Guadalupe, waving flags
in the Vatican colors of yellow-and-white.
   Spanish tenor Placido Domingo, who lives in Mexico City, sang
parts of the Mass.
   The crowds were smaller than predicted, possibly due to a light
rain. The giant courtyard at the basilica was less than half full
with about 30,000 people when the pope arrived.
   ``I come as a herald of faith and peace, in hopes of boosting
the energy of ecclesiastical communities so that they can be of
service to their brothers,'' John Paul said at the airport after a
13-hour flight from Rome.
   He was welcomed by a mariachi band playing ``Cielito Lindo,'' or
``Little Beautiful Skies,'' one of Mexico's unofficial anthems.
   Salinas, greeting the pope, said: ``Your visit is a new
encounter with the generosity of a nation of many cultures, plural
visions and deep religious sentiments.''
   The president's presence was part of his two-year initiative to
improve relations with the church. Mexico broke diplomatic ties in
1926, after the church sided with conservatives during the Mexican
Revolution.
   ``This is something new and very important,'' the pope told a
news conference during the flight aboard the papal plane. ``We are
making efforts to improve relations between the state and the
church.''
   Salinas named a personal representative to the Vatican in
February, considered a step toward a possible resumption of
diplomatic relations.
   The beatification of Juan Diego came during a campaign by the
pope to strengthen the church in Latin America, home to nearly half
the world's 850 million Roman Catholics.
   Beatification is a step toward sainthood and means Masses can be
celebrated in the person's honor.
   According to legend, Juan Diego carried out-of-season roses to
his bishop from the hill where the Virgin of Guadalupe appeared.
When he opened his white cloak, the image of the Virgin appeared on
it. The Virgin was named patron of the Americas by the church in
1910.
   The beatification emphasized the church's recent efforts to
appeal to the poor and the Indian minority. In the past, the church
backed the ruling classes in repressing Mexico's native population,
which is why restrictions on the church were written into the
constitution after the 1910-1920 Mexican Revolution.
   The pope is trying to inject vigor into a church that is rapidly
losing ground to evangelical sects. Although the church claims 90
percent of Mexico's 85 million people are Catholic, church figures
show the number of Protestants grew more than 500 percent between
1950 and 1980, to 3.29 percent of the population.
   Earlier Sunday, John Paul sent a message to President Bush
urging the United States to welcome Mexican immigrants.
   ``I pray that your nation ... will continue to be the hospitable
land in which many people, including those of Mexican origin, have
been given the opportunity of starting a new life.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0067 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 2109EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Duke-Parade     05-06 0246</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Duke-Parade,0253</SECOND>
<HEAD>Blacks Bow Out of Parade Because David Duke Joins In</HEAD>
<DATELINE>THIBODAUX, La. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Many blacks stayed away from the Thibodaux
Volunteer Fire Department's annual parade on Sunday because of the
presence of state Rep. David Duke, a former Ku Klux Klan leader who
is running for the U.S. Senate.
   Parade chairman Robert Fields was told Saturday that all four
school bands would pull out.
   However, two bands marched, minus their black members.
   ``I did not see any black students. In fact, we didn't see any
blacks in the parade at all. Normally there's a mounted group,''
said KTIB-AM news director Marie Bergeron, who broadcast a
description of the parade.
   Police Sgt. James Hughes said he saw at most 40 blacks among the
thousands who lined the parade route. ``Usually they are more
supportive,'' he said.
   The Lafourche Parish chapter of the National Association for the
Advancement of Colored People and local black ministers had urged
blacks to stay away from the parade because of Duke's presence.
   ``It's amazing the NAACP is so intolerant,'' said Duke, who says
his years as imperial wizard of the Knights of the Ku Klux Klan and
his ties to neo-Nazi groups were youthful errors. ``I think we need
equal rights for all people in America.''
   Duke, one of two Republicans in the race to unseat Democratic
Sen. J. Bennett Johnston, rode in a white convertible with an
entourage of about six, smiling and waving at the crowds.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0068 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 2122EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-US-Hostages 6thLd-Writethru a0746 05-06 0588</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-US-Hostages, 6th Ld-Writethru, a0746, 2 Takes,600</SECOND>
<HEAD>Reed Was Beaten Severely During Captivity After Escape Attempts</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDs: Tops with 5 grafs to include Reed quotes to clarify minor
foot fractures</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By GEORGE ESPER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Special Correspondent</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ARLINGTON, Va. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Freed hostage Frank Reed said Sunday his
Islamic kidnappers beat him so savagely that they broke his nose,
jaw and ribs and tried to break his feet with iron rods after he
tried unsuccessfully to escape twice. He was put in solitary
confinement for more than two years.
   ``Thank God they didn't kill me,'' he said. ``I was one of their
pet whackers.''
   He said his Hezbollah guards hit him more than 200 times in the
head, body and feet after his first attempt to gain freedom and
that he suffered minor fractures in his feet.
   ``They tried to break my feet,'' he said. ``They hit my feet
many times with iron rods and my feet had been slightly broken.''
   Two days later, he tried to escape again and was hit in the back
with such force that his kidneys bled, he said.
   ``This kind of treatment went on and on and on for a long
time,'' he said. ``Then sometime about a year later, one pig of a
man who constantly haggled me broke my ribs, kicked my ribs in on
the right side. I'd managed somehow to push them back lying on my
back.''
   Despite the pain and ``hell'' he went through, he said, ``I did
everything in my power not to cry out and not let them think they
were ever going to get a single advantage on me. And I didn't.''
   Reed said he was chained either to a wall or radiator and that
the first time he sat up on his own was when he was released after
44 months in captivity. He said he and other hostages slept on thin
foam rubber mattresses.
   Reed said he lay on his back for the more than 3{ years except
when he was exercising, eating or making trips to the toilet.
   ``We were blindfolded 24 hours a day. We slept with our
blindfolds on because if we had any collateral with our keepers, we
didn't want to lose it by letting them see our eyes.
   ``We were kept in very familiar places to you, apartment houses
for the most part, in bedrooms. Our bedroom doors were locked, and
when they (the guards) were out, we raised our blindfolds. We were
always on guard when they did come in.''
   Sen. Bob Dole, the Republican minority leader from Kansas who
spoke at the news conference, asked for the help of every foreign
leader, ``everyone who can make a difference'' in bringing about
the release of the remaining six American hostages and 10
Westerners. ``They know who they are,'' he said.
   Sen. Daniel Patrick Moynihan, D-N.Y., who also appeared at the
news conference, urged Israel to release the Moslem prisoners it
holds.
   ``It is in their interest to do and if they're part of the world
nations seeking legality and decency they should now act to bring
it about in Lebanon,'' Moynihan said.
   Syrian and Iranian officials said Sunday the release of any more
American hostages likely hinges on Israel's willingness to free
hundreds of Moslem prisoners, including Sheik Abdul Karim Obeid, a
Shiite cleric kidnapped from his home in 1989.
   President Bush last Thursday again appealed for the release of
``all hostages,'' but sidestepped commenting on whether that should
include 400 Shiites held by Israel.
   MORE
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0069 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 2127EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-US-Hostages 1stAdd a0763 05-06 0828</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-US-Hostages, 1st Add, a0763,850</SECOND>
<HEAD> WASHN: by Israel.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   
   Joining Reed at the news conference was Robert Polhill, a fellow
American educator who was freed April 22. Polhill said he was
shocked when he heard of the brutal treatment of Reed. ``I can't
say I was maltreated,'' Polhill said.
   For the first time, Reed gave graphic details of his days in
captivity. The 57-year-old educator said, ``Our routine was
breakfast, a cigarette, up on your feet. ... After we came back
from the toilet, we were allowed to exercise.''
   When he was first kidnapped, Reed said, he would just lie around
not doing anything but worrying.
   ``I was a layabout trying to wonder about this and wonder about
my school and wonder about my family and worry about my friends. I
said if I don't worry about (myself), I'm in trouble. There ain't
going to be any Frank Reed. I got up and started doing my pushups.''
   He began with just six and worked his way up to a record 103.
``It was part of my will.''
   With some matches he had, he drew a picture of his 9-year-old
son, Tarek, on the back of the door of his cell so that when his
guards opened the door they couldn't see it. On the ceiling, he
drew a picture of his Syrian-born wife, Fahima, known as Fifi. He
was admonished for this.
   ``This is one of the ways I had to kind of remind me to keep
myself going. But I knew in the final analysis if I didn't keep my
life going there certainly wasn't going to be any Fifi or any
Tarek.''
   He said American hostage Terry Anderson looked wonderful,
physically. He last saw Anderson more than a year ago. Anderson,
42, chief Middle East correspondent of The Associated Press, was
abducted March 16, 1985.
   Reed said fellow captives John McCarthy and Brian Keenan were
kept together and were in good physical condition.
   ``They've been fortunate. I spent probably two years, 2{ years
in solitary confinement while they were fortunate to have the two
of them together at all times,'' Reed said. He said McCarthy and
Keenan developed ``one of the unique relationships in the history
of human relationships.''
   Reed talked with reporters after he joined other former hostages
and their families for a brunch and reunion at a hotel in this
Washington suburb. His two daughters by a previous marriage,
Marilyn Langston and Jacqueline Reed, both of Malden, Mass., were
among those present.
   Reed had said he hoped the gathering would focus international
attention on the plight of the remaining hostages held by Islamic
militants in Lebanon.
   Reed revealed details about McCarthy and Keenan for the first
time.
   ``Both of them physically, in terms of muscle development, are
probably in the best shape they've ever been in in their lives,
unlike myself, who kind of in one silent protest, I ended up just
exercising by walking,'' Reed said.
   He said McCarthy and Keenan have been doing an excessive number
of pushups, situps and other exercise. ``In fact, I looked at John
the other day and he looked beautiful. I wished I looked like he
does,'' Reed said.
   He said they had received ``a lot of books, so they're keeping
their minds going.''
   Although Reed said he had been kept for long periods in solitary
confinement, he had reported earlier that his kidnappers treated
him well during the last six months of his captivity.
   ``It was heaven compared to what happened to us previously,'' he
said Sunday.
   Reed, director of the private Lebanon International School in
Beirut, was freed April 30 in Syria, two days after he had last
seen McCarthy.
   Keenan, 39, an Irish teacher of English at the American
University of Beirut, was kidnapped April 11, 1986. Six days later,
McCarthy, a 33-year-old British television journalist, was abducted.
   Keenan's two sisters, Brenda Gillham, and Elaine Spence, were
among those attending Sunday's reunion.
   Reed, smiling and singing, arrived with his wife and son and two
daughters. With his arm around Tarek, Reed said he was looking
forward to a fishing trip with his son at Sebago Lake in Maine.
   ``I'm going to catch some salmon, we hope,'' he said.
   Reed was beaming and cheerful.
   ``I'm feeling OK,'' he said. ``I'm a little weak from not having
lived very much, no living muscles.''
   Reed's doctors reported Saturday they were pleased with how he
looked even though his weight had dropped from about 185 pounds to
about 140. Doctors said their early evaluations were good and they
expected Reed to remain at the Andrews Air Force Base, Md., medical
center probably until the end of the week.
   Joining Reed at the reunion, which was organized by No Greater
Love, a humanitarian organization, were:
   _Peggy Say sister of Terry Anderson.
   _Tom Cicippio, brother of Joseph Cicippio, 59, acting
comptroller at the American University in Beirut, kidnapped Sept.
12, 1986.
   _Jill Morrell, a friend of McCarthy.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0070 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 2129EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-SpaceShuttle     05-06 0140</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Space Shuttle,0143</SECOND>
<HEAD>Space Shuttle Discovery Lands at Warner Robins</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ROBINS AIR FORCE BASE, Ga. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The NASA jet returning the
space shuttle Discovery to Cape Canaveral, Fla., was forced to stop
overnight at Robins Air Force Base because of bad weather at its
destination.
   The shuttle was scheduled to resume its journey Monday if the
weather in Florida improved, said base spokesman Dale Brinkman.
   It was the second weather delay on the trip home for the
shuttle, which is carried atop a specially fitted Boeing 747.
   It was held overnight Saturday at Sheppard Air Force Base in
Texas after taking off from NASA's shuttle landing field at Edwards
Air Force Base in California.
   Discovery was launched from Kennedy Space Center on April 24 and
deployed the $1.5 billion Hubble Space Telescope. The shuttle
landed on April 29.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0071 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 2138EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-HongKong-Gold     05-06 0033</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Hong Kong-Gold,0032</SECOND>
<HEAD>Gold Opens Higher in Hong Kong</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HONG KONG (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Gold rose 64 cents an ounce Monday on Hong Kong
markets, opening at $372.63. It closed at $371.99 Saturday.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0072 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 2146EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Bush 4thLd-Writethru a0762-a0765 05-06 0705</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bush, 4th Ld-Writethru, a0762-a0765,700</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush, Congressional Leaders Set Followup Budget Parley</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDs: Combines pvs; corrects ``agreement'' to ``meeting'' in 12th
graf; edits throughout to tighten</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By CHRISTOPHER CONNELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush agreed with leaders of Congress
on Sunday night to press for full-scale budget negotiations with no
preconditions to bring the widening federa deficit under control,
lawmakers said.
   The congressional leaders emerged from 90 minutes of talks at
the White House saying they would be back later in the week for
further talks with Bush.
   First they need to consult with other members of the House and
Senate, they said.
   But House Speaker Tom Foley, asked if things were now on track
for full-scale budget negotiations with the White House, said, ``I
think that's going to be the outcome.''
   Foley and Senate Majority Leader George Mitchell said they did
not discuss any specifics with Bush, including whether the
president is now willing to budge from his no-new-taxes pledge.
   But Foley said, ``The assumption is that all matters would be on
the table, that we would not enter any talks with preconditions.''
   Mitchell said, ``There was a general agreement that any
discussions will be without preconditions, if and when they occur.''
   Senate Minority Leader Bob Dole said the lawmakers expected to
meet again with Bush ``late Tuesday'' after conferring with other
lawmakers, including leaders of the key budget and tax-writing
committees.
   Congress and the White House have made repeated efforts in
recent years, both with former President Reagan and with Bush, to
forge grand compromises on the deficit.
   Sluggish economic growth and rising interest rates of late have
driven up the deficit, making it harder to meet the Gramm-Rudman
mandate of a deficit no larger than $64 billion for fiscal 1991,
which starts Oct. 1.
   Foley said he expects more lasting results this time.
   ``All of us who took part in this meeting feel that we need a
major and meaningful effort that has been somewhat lacking for
various reasons in past years'' to narrow the deficit for both next
year and over several years, the speaker said.
   ``I think there's goodwill on all sides in attempting to deal
with the fiscal problems the country faces. ... '' said Foley.
``We're going to, I think, find a way to deal effectively with
them.''
   Foley said the congressional leaders, including House Minority
Leader Bob Michel, wanted ``an opportunity to consult with our
membership and to consult again with the president.''
   Stephen Hart, the president's deputy press secretary, said the
White House had no immediate comment on the meeting.
   Bush slipped upstairs to his private quarters with the leaders
after hosting a lecture at which author David McCullough held forth
on the 26th president, Theodore Roosevelt.
   White House Chief of Staff John Sununu and budget director
Richard Darman, portfolios and legal pads in hand, preceded Bush up
the stairs. Treasury Secretary Nicholas Brady came staight from
talks on Capitol Hill with finance ministers from the Group of
Seven nations _ the other major Western democracies.
   Congress has ignored the $1.2 trillion budget blueprint that
Bush submitted Jan. 29.
   ``If we're going to do it, first we have to have an agenda. We
have to know who the players are and what our goals are,'' Dole
said before the meeting.
   Sununu said that with the full House and Senate Budget
Committees having approved Democratic versions of the 1991 budget
last week, it was time to sound out the leaders on where to go next.
   But he insisted there would be no negotiating at this meeting.
``We're not doing anything,'' Sununu said.
   The congressional leaders were among 200 guests at the Roosevelt
lecture.
   Bush sought to play down expectations that had surfaced when
word of the private meeting leaked out last week.
   ``We're not into a negotiation. We're talking process,'' the
president said Thursday.
   The 1990 deficit was supposed to be $99 billion under a budget
deal that Bush and Congress struck in April 1989. But that has been
undone by higher spending and slower than expected growth of tax
revenues, and now the non-partisan Congressional Budget Office
expects the 1990 shortfall to reach $159 billion.
   The deficit in 1989 was $152 billion.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0073 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 2155EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Hostages 1stLd-Writethru a0687 05-06 0745</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Hostages, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0687,0766</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hezbollah Denies Holding Western Hostages</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-US-Hostages, Bjt</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDs: LEADS with 21 grafs to ADD Syrian foreign minister, Iranian
ambassador's comments; MOVES UP reference to Moslem prisoners in
Israel. Pickup 19th pvs, `Bush has...'
^By DONNA ABU-NASR</NOTE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BEIRUT, Lebanon (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An Iranian-backed Shiite Moslem group
Sunday denied holding Western captives but also indicated that more
would not be released unless the United States helps gain freedom
for Moslem prisoners in Israel.
   The statement was made by senior Hezbollah leader, Hajj Abu
Yasser, in an interview broadcast live on the group's Al-Nour radio
station.
   In Tehran, the radical speaker of Iran's Parliament Sunday
denounced the United States as ``the enemy of Islam ... hated by
our people'' and ruled out a resumption of diplomatic relations.
   Mehdi Karrubi's remarks, reported by Iran's official Islamic
Republic News Agency, echoed anti-U.S. statements by other Iranian
leaders.
   The statements were apparently triggered by President Bush's
refusal to make a ``goodwill gesture'' toward Iran and its Shiite
Moslem allies in Lebanon following the recent release of two U.S.
hostages.
   ``Good will has to be replied by good will,'' Kamal Kharrazi,
Iran's ambassador to the United Nations, said in an interview
Sunday on ABC-TV's ``This Week With David Brinkley.''
   On the same program, Syria's foreign minister, Farouk Al-Sharra,
said his government remains committed to exerting whatever
influence it can to win freedom for the remaining hostages.
   But he complained: ``How do you expect (their captors) to be so
humanitarian and release other hostages, when their relatives have
been kidnapped by Israel?''
   That was in reference to the kidnappers' and Iran's demand that
Israel free about 400 Lebanese and Palestinian prisoners, including
Sheik Abdul-Karim Obeid.
   Obeid, a pro-Hezbollah cleric, was abducted by Israeli troops
from his home in southern Lebanon in July 1989.
   Hezbollah, or Party of God, is believed the umbrella group for
extremist Shiite factions holding most of the remaining 16 Western
captives in Lebanon. They include six Americans.
   ``We have repeatedly announced that we have not kidnapped any
hostages. If we were the group holding the hostages, we would have
the courage to announce it,'' Abu Yasser said.
   Asked why his group is accused of holding the hostages, Abu
Yasser replied: ``This could have arisen from the fact that
Hezbollah has never publicly condemned those who employ the method
of hostage-holding because Hezbollah knows the real reasons behind
the hostage issue.''
   ``The one who bears responsibility for this issue is the
American administration because it is the one which instigated this
line,'' he said.
   Abu Yasser said ``thousands of downtrodden Moslems'' were
kidnapped by the U.S.-trained Lebanese army between 1982 and 1988.
Most were seized before any Westerners were abducted in Beirut and
are still unaccounted for, he said.
   ``We are not concerned with condemning those behind the
predicament of the American administration,'' Abu Yasser said.
   He said the United States pays scant attention to the harsh
practices of Israel in the region.
   ``It never condemns Zionist practices in Lebanon or Palestine or
the Golan Heights,'' he said. ``So why should we then take the
stand that serves the interests of the U.S. administration?''
   Abu Yasser said the goodwill initiative of freeing American
captives Robert Polhill and Frank Reed has placed the hostage issue
in a ``realistic framework.''
   Polhill, 55, was freed April 22 after 39 months held by Shiite
Moslem extremists in Lebanon. Reed, 57, was released April 30 after
42 months in captivity.
   ``The release has put the ball in the American court. It has
raised anew the issue of prisoners held by Israel, its surrogates,
the Lebanese army and the Lebanese Forces,'' Abu Yasser said. ``But
we haven't seen any seriousness or concern on the part of the
American administration to bring about the release of those
prisoners.''
   Bush has said Washington will make no move of its own until all
six remaining American hostages held in Lebanon have been freed
unconditionally.
   But he has said the United States would have no objection to
Israel freeing the prisoners and last week offered to help Iran
establish the fate of four Iranians who disappeared in Lebanon in
1982.
   Israel has linked any release of Lebanese or Palestinian
prisoners to freedom for three Israeli soldiers held in Lebanon.
   The six Americans are among 16 Westerners believed held hostage
in Lebanon. The longest-held is Terry Anderson, chief Middle East
correspondent for The Associated Press. He was kidnapped March 16,
1985.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0074 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 2200EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Mongolia     05-06 0459</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mongolia,0473</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mongolian Opposition Groups Agree to Gov't Advisory Role</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KATHY WILHELM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   All but one of Mongolia's opposition groups has
accepted a government offer of an advisory role in the
Communist-dominated legislature, a source said in the Mongolian
capital of Ulan Bator said Sunday.
   Mongolian Foreign Minister Tserenpiliyn Gombosuren meanwhile
signed agreements with China for cooperation in science and
technology, public health and environmental protection.
   He accompanied Mongolian President Punsalmaagiin Ochirbat, who
arrived in Beijing Friday to formally normalize long-strained
relations between the two neighbors.
   Ochirbat and his party then flew to Inner Mongolia, a swath of
steppe and desert just inside China's northern border where 3.5
million ethnic Mongols live. It remained part of China while what
is now Mongolia won independence in a 1921 uprising.
   Ochirbat left Mongolia while hunger strikes or sit-ins were
being staged in more than half a dozen cities, led by one of the
country's new opposition groups, the Mongolian Democratic
Association.
   A source who spoke by telephone from Ulan Bator on condition of
anonymity said the Democratic Association was the lone holdout in
the agreement reached by the government with other opposition
parties.
   Mongolian television announced Saturday that the Social
Democratic Party and the New Progressive Party, which share the
Democratic Association's goal of democratic reform, had agreed to
take part in an advisory council to be established under the
national legislature.
   Ochirbat proposed the council as an alternative to the
opposition's demand that the 370-member legislature resign and a
multiparty legislature be set up until elections are held.
   More than 93 percent of the current legislators are Communist
Party members.
   The Communists agreed to hold multiparty elections this summer,
but the opposition complained that the new election law was biased
in the communists' favor. It said free elections could only be held
if a multiparty, interim legislature was in place.
   Only a few hundred people gathered Sunday in Ulan Bator's
central square for an opposition rally, the source said. Several
dozen Democratic Association members have been holding a sit-in in
the square since Tuesday, but the number of supporters and
onlookers at the scene has never climbed above a few hundred. The
opposition group said sit-ins were also being staged in six other
cities, and hunger strikes in three. Five hunger strikers in one
city were reported hospitalized, but no one was reported in serious
condition.
   The goal of all the protests is an interim legislature, the
source said. He said the opposition group;s leaders were
considering Sunday whether to accept the advisory council
compromise.
   Details such as how the council would function and its size were
not immediately announced. It was expected to be set up immediately
because the legislature meets Thursday.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0075 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 2201EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ShrimpersFight 1stLd-Writethru a0755 05-06 0496</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Shrimpers Fight, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0755,0512</SECOND>
<HEAD>FBI Questions Shrimpers About Gunfight on Gulf</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 16 grafs to UPDATE with quotes from shrimpers, FBI
spokesman. Pick up 11th graf pvs, `The Coast Guard...</NOTE>
<DATELINE>PORT FOURCHON, La. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Federal agents questioned the crews of
five shrimp boats Sunday after tensions between local fishermen and
Vietnamese newcomers erupted into a gun battle on the Gulf of
Mexico.
   ``All the boats that were brought in ... had ramming damage.
There were bullet holes found,'' said Coast Guard Petty Officer
Matt McGovern in New Orleans. No injuries were reported.
   None of the Vietnamese crew members would talk to reporters in
port. But two Louisiana captains blamed the violence on the
newcomers.
   Shrimper Phillip Petronas accused the Vietnamese of opening
fire, and said he responded by trying to ram one of their boats.
   ``I just put my boat in gear and put it wide open and I aimed
it,'' Petronas said. ``When I leave this dock next time, I will
have arms on my boat.''
   Another captain, Allen Gisclair, said the newcomers ignore the
area's fishing etiquette.
   ``They think they can take what you're dragging and move you out
and take over,'' Gisclair said, referring to dragging nets. ``They
don't want to work with you. They try to work against you.''
   Agents from the FBI, Customs Service and Bureau of Alcohol,
Tobacco and Firearms questioned the shrimpers, said Coast Guard
spokesman McGovern.
   No one on the fishing crews was taken into custody, FBI
spokesman Volney Hayes said Sunday. The case was to be turned over
to the U.S. Attorney's office to consider charges, he said.
   Fishing crews told the Coast Guard the confrontation flared
after one shrimp boat got its anchor caught in another's trawling
nets.
   ``As to who shot first, that's all just conjecture right now,''
Coast Guard Lt. Michael Tekesky said Sunday.
   McGovern said the shooting stopped when Coast Guard helicopters
and boats arrived.
   Coast Guard boats escorted the boats Our Mama, Capt. Eleven
Success, Stephen Lynn, Walter James and Freedom One into port
Sunday. The Coast Guard kept watch on the boats Saturday night
after the exchange of gunfire in an area known as Whiskey Pass five
miles off the Louisiana Coast, McGovern said.
   The spokesman corrected earlier Coast Guard reports that
automatic weapons had been involved.
   ``No automatic weapons were found. Just two guns: a shotgun and
a .22-caliber rifle,'' McGovern said.
   The Coast Guard said nine or 10 boats were in the area at the
time of the incident. One boat began sinking, but got pumps from a
Coast Guard helicopter and righted itself, Tekesky said.
   Donald Lirette, president of the Terrebonne Fishermen's
Organization, said Saturday that the fight stemmed from tension
between longtime local fishermen and Vietnamese newcomers.
   He said the arrival in Louisiana of the Vietnamese shrimp
fishing crews had previously caused animosity but little violence.
   ``It's a dog-eat-dog situation when things are like they are
now. Everybody's starving,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0076 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 2206EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-WeatherpageWeather 1stLd-Writethru a0716 05-06 0253</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Weatherpage Weather, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0716,0256</SECOND>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 6th graf to include detail on California heat.</NOTE>
<HEAD>Cooling And Windy In West, Rainy In East</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Rain was scattered over the East on Sunday, and windy, cooler
weather covered much of the West.
   At midday, showers were scattered from central Tennessee across
north-central Kentucky, Ohio, southwestern and north-central
Pennsylvania and northern New England.
   Showers and thunderstorms were scattered over central and
northern New York state, as well as the Florida Peninsula.
   Wind brought cooler temperatures to much of the West, a day
after high wind caused damage and contributed to six deaths along
the coast of Washington and British Columbia.
   Cooler temperatures and gusty wind extended from much of the
Pacific states inland across Idaho, northern Nevada, Utah and
Arizona, moving later in the day into Montana, Wyoming and Colorado.
   But temperatures remained unseasonably warm over coastal
southern California, sending hundreds of thousands of people to the
beaches and making firefighters edgy as humidity dropped in brushy
areas.
   Flooding continued along the Trinity River in Texas, the
Arkansas River in Arkansas and on reservoirs in Oklahoma. Low-lying
neighborhoods were sandbagged in North Little Rock, Ark., and a
neighborhood of Dallas remained evacuated for a fourth day because
of the Trinity River.
   Temperatures around the nation at 3 p.m. EDT ranged from 43 at
Limestone, Mont., to 102 at Ontario, Calif., about 35 miles east of
downtown Los Angeles.
   Sunday's low for the Lower 48 states was 21 at Gunnison, Colo.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0077 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 2220EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Taiwan     05-06 0349</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Taiwan,0361</SECOND>
<HEAD>Thousands Protest Selection of Top General as New Premier</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SHIRLEY LAI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TAIPEI, Taiwan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Thousands of chanting demonstrators surged
through downtown Taipei Sunday in the latest of a series of
protests against the selection of the nation's top general as
premier.
   It was the biggest demonstration since President Lee Teng-hui
offered the post to Defense Minister Hau Pei-tsun five days ago, a
move that has raised widespread fears of greater military
interference in the government.
   Hau, 71, who served eight years as chief of the general staff
before becoming defense minister last year, would be the first
general to head the Cabinet. He is to replace Lee Huan, 73, in two
weeks.
   Members of the the opposition Democratic Progessive Party and 30
other private groups joined the peaceful protest. The demonstrators
shouted ``General comes, democracy goes!'' and ``We oppose military
intervention in politics!''
   Police put the number of protesters at 5,000. Reporters covering
the event estimated the size of the crowd at about 10,000.
   ``A democratic nation should have a civilian Cabinet. We fear a
military premier will lead to authoritarian rule,'' said student
leader Fan Yun.
   Protesters also denounced a news blackout on the protests by the
three government TV stations. Students sprayed protest slogans at
the entrances of the three stations.
   A popular political weekly, the Journalist, editorialized Sunday
that Lee's choice of Hau as premier was ``absurd.'' The magazine's
cover featured a black background with the four bold white
characters for ``heartfelt sadness.''
   Lee has defended the nomination, saying he himself would be in
control of the military forces. He also said a civilian would
succeed Hau to head the defense ministry.
   But opposition politicians claimed Hau would dominate the
government and the military.
   The government has gradually eased its authoritarian grip in
recent years, lifting martial law, allowing opposition political
parties and giving more government posts to native Taiwanese.
   But the general belongs to the governing Nationalist Party's old
guard, which fled to Taiwan in 1949 after losing a civil war to
Communist forces on mainland China.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0078 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 2224EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-HighWind 1stLd-Writethru a0718 05-06 0654</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-High Wind, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0718,0667</SECOND>
<HEAD>Six Dead, Four Missing After High Wind Hits Northwest</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: ADDS 2 grafs at end to account for missing people.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>SEATTLE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   High wind battered the Pacific Northwest during
the weekend, capsizing boats, pulling down power lines and fanning
fires. Six people were killed and four were missing.
   Winds blowing up to 60 mph hit Saturday and early Sunday as
thousands of people took to the water for the Northwest's
traditional opening weekend of boating season.
   Coast Guard crews answered about 60 distress calls in
Washington's inland waterways Saturday. Boats were overturned or
washed ashore, and Coast Guard Lt. Jim Beckham said two sailboats
sank. Their occupants were rescued.
   Authorities at the Rescue Coordination Center in Victoria,
British Columbia, were just as busy with reports of dozens of
swamped or overdue boats.
   At Prince George, British Columbia, wind of up to 54 mph fanned
a brushfire and forced Royal Canadian Mounted Police to evacuate
some 125 houses for about two hours when a subdivision was
threatened. The fire was brought under control with the help of two
water bombers.
   ``At one point the fire was about 100 yards from the houses and
the wind was blowing the fire directly at the houses,'' said RCMP
Constable Paul Bruggerman. ``Then the wind changed and it blew
toward the (Fraser) river.''
   In Washington, subsiding wind and cooler temperatures helped
firefighters battle slash fires on about 220 acres 20 miles west of
Port Angeles near Joyce.
   British Columbia Hydro spokesman Peter McMullen said about
10,000 customers in southwestern British Columbia were without
power at times after wind or falling branches downed power lines.
   The inaugural sailing of a new ferry serving Seattle and
Victoria, the Crown Princess Victoria, was extended by six hours
because fierce wind made docking impossible at Victoria. The B.C.
Stena Line's new ship finally docked at a terminal more than 18
miles from its terminal in Victoria's Inner Harbor. The 750-plus
passengers were bused downtown.
   The wind also delayed other ferries, and about 50 or 60 people
who took a tour of historic homes in the Olympic Peninsula city of
Port Townsend were stranded overnight, said police Deputy Wes
Benson.
   Two of the deaths occurred after a 21-foot boat with four people
aboard capsized on the Columbia River below Kennewick, Wash., said
Coast Guard Petty Officer Sandy Calhoun in Seattle.
   A man and woman swam to shore but the man was struck and killed
by a train as he ran for help, Ms. Calhoun said. The body of a
second man was found hours later washed up on the river bank, she
said. The woman was in stable condition but a 6-year-old boy was
missing.
   One man was killed in British Columbia while learning
para-gliding, the sport of riding the wind on a tethered parachute.
   ``He was taking lessons on the beach, and the parachute was tied
to a log on the beach,'' said West Vancouver Police Sgt. John
Looye. ``The wind came up and forced the parachute to the ground.''
   Coast Guard Lt. Jim Beckham said the bodies of two fishermen
were found washed ashore near their 15-foot boat Sunday morning
about five miles east of Port Angeles on the Strait of Juan de
Fuca, where a sudden weather front brought gale-force winds.
   A man also was found dead on the Nisqually Flats between Tacoma
and Olympia by a Coast Guard helicopter after searchers spotted his
small aluminum boat tied to a tree near the mudflats, Beckham said.
   Coast Guard boats and helicopters searched Sunday for two
fishermen overdue in a 15-foot boat from Sequim, east of Port
Angeles.
   One man was missing and presumed drowned after a 20-foot
pleasure boat capsized Saturday on the mouth of the Fraser River
south of Vancouver. Three other men were rescued after the
fiberglass boat broke apart in rough waters, said Richard
Hendrickson, a Canadian Coast Guard officer.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0079 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 2229EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-DeceasedDecoy     05-06 0231</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Deceased Decoy,0239</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dead Man Still Goes Hunting, His Ashes Inside Friend's Duck Decoys</HEAD>
<DATELINE>FARMINGTON, Ill. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Dean Goddin died in the mid 1980s, but
that hasn't made him miss a single day of duck hunting with his
buddy, Everett Staffeldt.
   In keeping with his last request, Goddin's ashes were placed
inside a pair of 2-foot mallard duck decoys that Staffeldt, a
retired scientist, had originally carved for his own remains.
   Staffeldt and Goddin were long-time friends who often left their
homes in the Chicago suburb of Naperville for hunting trips in
Wisconsin.
   Staffeldt said Goddin became ill with cancer five or six years
go. Shortly before his death, at age 64, he told Staffeldt:
   ``I want you to put me in the decoys, and I want you to take me
hunting every season.'' Staffeldt agreed.
   He and his wife, Arlene, brought the decoys along when they
retired here.
   ``He has a good place here,'' Mrs. Staffeldt said of Goddin.
``He goes hunting with Everett. I put bows on him for Christmas.''
   Staffeldt has his own burial decoys half carved, but says he
must be selective about who else gets put inside a duck. The decoys
are heavy, and he doesn't want to overburden his sons.
   ``If I get a dozen friends in there, they're not going to be
able to take us down to the lake,'' he says.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0080 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 2256EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Israel-Violence     05-06 0257</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel-Violence,0267</SECOND>
<HEAD>Palestinian Killed, Four Wounded in Clashes with Troops</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Soldiers killed a Palestinian high school
student and wounded at least four other Arabs Sunday in clashes
throughout the occupied West Bank and Gaza Strip, hospital
officials and Arab reports said.
   Arabs in the occupied territories shut their stores Sunday as
part of a strike in solidarity with Palestinians held prisoners in
Israeli jails.
   According to the military, 9,986 Palestinians were being
detained as of Tuesday. Nearly 1,000 are being held without trial
under special administrative detention laws.
   In the Gaza Strip town of Rafah, soldiers opened fire on a group
of Palestinian high school students and killed one after their
patrol was attacked, Arab reports said.
   Arab hospital officials identified the victim as Mohammed Khaled
Musa, 17, and said he was struck with bullets in the neck and chest.
   The army confirmed the death but said it was checking the
circumstances of the incident.
   Musa's death brought to 683 the number of Palestinians killed by
Israeli soldiers or civilians during the 29-month-old rebellion
against Israeli occupation. Forty-three Israelis have also died in
the violence.
   Also Sunday, a 37-year-old Palestinian woman suspected of
prostitution was found dead on a roadside in the occupied Gaza
Strip, Arab reporters said.
   Moslem fundamentalists have slain Arab prostitutes as part of a
campaign to purge prostitutes, drug dealers and collaborators from
Palestinian society.
   Her death raised to 211 the number of Palestinians killed by
their fellow Arabs on suspicion of cooperating with Israel or
conducting moral offenses.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0081 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 2312EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-McCarthyMemorial     05-06 0197</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-McCarthy Memorial,0203</SECOND>
<HEAD>Joe McCarthy called a `Credit to Our Nation'</HEAD>
<DATELINE>APPLETON, Wis. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The late Sen. Joseph R. McCarthy, the
Wisconsin Republican censured by the U.S. Senate during his
anti-Communist campaign of the 1950s, was remembered Sunday as ``a
credit to our nation.''
   About 50 people gathered for the annual memorial service at the
grave of the late senator, a native of nearby Grand Chute.
   McCarthy led a Senate committee investigation of what he said
was Communist influence in government and entertainment, calling
prominent people to testify about their alleged party involvement.
   McCarthy was censured by the Senate in 1954 for his conduct
during the investigations. He died in 1957.
   His backers insisted Sunday there was nothing wrong with
McCarthy's actions.
   ``In all, Joe McCarthy publicly named 160 Communists and
pro-Communists,'' said John McManus, spokesman for the
Appleton-based John Birch Society. ``Not in one case did he harm
any innocent person. ... He was a credit to our nation.''
   ``Joe has been leperized by public opinion,'' said the Rev.
Cletus Healy of Milwaukee. ``One of the reasons we are devoted to
him is that we recognize that much of what he said was true.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0082 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 2313EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Italy-Elections     05-06 0263</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Italy-Elections,0271</SECOND>
<HEAD>Local Elections Test Government, Communist Party</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ROME (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   After a campaign marred by violence, Italians voted
in nationwide local elections Sunday that are seen as an important
indication of support for the governing coalition and the
opposition Communist Party.
   At least nine politicians in southern Italy have been killed by
underworld gangs during the campaign. The candidates were either
linked to local scandals or had denounced attempts by the
underworld to obtain government contracts.
   Fifteen regional and 87 provincial governing councils and 6,374
city governments are being contested in the elections. Municipal
elections were not being held in such major centers as Rome,
Naples, Trieste, Catania and Bolzano.
   The polls were open throughout Sunday and Monday.
   The results will have no direct bearing on the national
government but the campaign has fueled bitter squabbling among the
five parties in Premier Giulio Andreotti's coalition as they
attempted to attract support from the 46 million eligible voters.
The Christian Democrat leader warned major shifts in the voting
could cause the collapse of his coalition.
   The coalition also includes the Socialists, Republicans, Social
Democrats and Liberals.
   The voting trends will also be closely watched by the
Communists, Italy's main opposition party, which has been steadily
losing strength since coming to the brink of power a decade ago.
   In March, the Communists decided to enter a transition phase and
have considered changing the party name and dropping its
hammer-and-sickle symbol.
   The move has angered many traditional Communists, and party
leader Achille Occhetto said he would be content with 23 percent of
the vote.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0083 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 1346EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-WordPerfect Bjt   05-06 0849</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-WordPerfect, Bjt,0875</SECOND>
<HEAD>Word-Processing Software Leader Had Humble Beginnings In Utah
Valley</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT MIMS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SALT LAKE CITY (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   When Alan C. Ashton designed a
word-processing program 12 years ago, he hoped only to supplement
his salary as a Brigham Young University professor and better
provide for his 11 children.
   From those visions of a few extra bags of groceries in the
Ashton family's larder sprang what today is WordPerfect, personal
computing's preeminent word-processing software company with $281
million in sales last year.
   Ashton, who left BYU in 1984, won't say how much he earns as
corporate president. Most of WordPerfect's earnings are recycled to
fuel the company's still-phenomenal growth. But in 1988, he and his
family moved into a 17,000-square-foot mansion on three acres.
   ``I'm not even sure how many rooms it has,'' he said. ``But it
certainly is large enough to have a couple of parties going on at
the same time.''
   While insisting ``happiness and joy does not depend on how much
money you have,'' Ashton recounts how WordPerfect has grown _ from
a handful of customers and $36,000 in sales its first year to more
than 4 million users and projected sales of around $400 million in
1990.
   WordPerfect had only two employees _ co-founders Ashton and his
talented graduate student, Bruce W. Bastian _ when it began
operations in 1979 as Satellite Software Inc.
   SSI became WordPerfect Corp. in 1982, Ashton jokes, not only to
gain better name recognition, but to end errant calls for satellite
dish installation.
   Now, the 1,900-employee company has a seven-building campus at
Orem's Timpanogos Research Park, just a few miles from BYU, and is
erecting two more buildings at the site.
   It also boasts an international audience including 53 nations,
offers WordPerfect in 16 languages and is developing Japanese and
Russian versions.
   Ashton says 1990s expected record earnings will be fueled by
sales of the company's latest release of its top-selling word
processor, WordPerfect 5.1, retailing for $495 a copy.
   Also expected to contribute heavily is the new DrawPerfect, a
$495 business presentation graphics package shipped in February,
and the June release of WordPerfect Office 3.0, a $149 upgrade of a
desktop office organization program.
   The company already is well on the way to its $400 million sales
goal, owning an estimated 60 percent of the word-processing market.
In March, WordPerfect had $40 million in sales, capping a record
$108.5 million first quarter.
   Don Willmott, an associate editor and software expert with PC
Magazine, said WordPerfect's success can be boiled down three
things _ quality, customer support and keen marketing.
   ``It's always had an edge up,'' he said. ``It's a superior
product and has excellent support. You get unlimited customer
support for as long as you own their product.''
   While other programs trying to exploit the personal computing
craze that began with the popularity of IBM's PC in the early 1980s
were ``counter-intuitive'' in design, WordPerfect started by
offering a ``cleaner, much friendlier interface,'' Willmott said.
   Other programs are now just as user-friendly, he said, but
WordPerfect's predominance is established for many years to come.
   ``We've seen in so many ways that once you get the installed
base, the momentum keeps going,'' Willmott said.
   Ashton said hard work and luck got WordPerfect off to a fast
start, but employees are responsible for sustained growth since
then.
   Raiding heavily from the cream of computer science graduates at
BYU and the University of Utah, Ashton said WordPerfect has built a
talented, creative work force loyal to the region and the company.
For example, of more than 200 programmers, only a half-dozen have
left the company since its inception.
   The company is privately owned and thus not obligated to
disclose its finances. It won't say what employees are paid, but
Ashton says they know hard work will be rewarded. When WordPerfect
topped $100 million in sales in 1987, for example, Hawaiian
vacations for two were given to about 300 employees.
   Although programmers are the core of development at WordPerfect,
Ashton says the 560 operators manning the company's toll-free help
lines are crucial to keeping the customer base happy, and growing.
   ``We take 12,000 to 13,000 calls a day. I don't think there's
any other company, computer or outside the computer industry, that
is handling that level of support,'' he said.
   Ashton and Bastian, now chairman of the WordPerfect board, have
kept the reins firmly in their grip. Together, they still own 99.8
percent of the company, which remains debt-free thanks to a policy
of using available revenues to fund capital improvements.
   The company also is unusual because of its Utah location, far
removed from California's Silicon Valley, the nation's computer
programming mecca.
   ``We lived here when we started. BYU, the community colleges in
the area, and the U of U (University of Utah) in Salt Lake City
provide great sources of very good people,'' Ashton said. ``And I
think they enjoy living in this location as well. Some that have
worked back East or in Silicon Valley have come back here and very
much enjoy the environment.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0084 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 1347EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-MissouriRiverDrought     05-06 0698</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Missouri River Drought,0722</SECOND>
<HEAD>Key Midwest Waterway Still Low</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SALLY STREFF BUZBEE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>KANSAS CITY, Mo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Missouri has generally recovered from
the drought that crippled farmers, cities and towns two years ago,
but the river that bears its name hasn't been so lucky.
   Dry weather in the Dakotas continues to keep water in short
supply throughout the Missouri River basin, officials say. That
will cause rough traveling this summer for the river barges that
carry grain and fertilizer across Missouri.
   More significantly for the nation, the low water also could
cause problems for the commercially important Mississippi River.
   Complicating the issue is South Dakota's recent decision to file
a federal lawsuit sometime soon against the U.S. Army Corps of
Engineers to force it to keep more water in strapped reservoirs in
the north.
   The Corps says it will negotiate, but that doesn't reassure the
people responsible for drinking water in Kansas City and other
Missouri River towns.
   ``Everybody's going to suffer in some way,'' said Chet Worm,
chief of the reservoir regulation branch of the Corps in Omaha,
Neb. ``The people at the reservoirs up north are suffering now, and
the people downstream could be suffering later.''
   Tracy Mehan, director of the Missouri Department of Natural
Resources, said ``Things are going to be difficult. We're going to
have to tighten our belts in the area of drinking water and
navigation, no question.''
   Already, the Corps has shortened this year's navigation season
on the Missouri and told barge operators they must carry fewer tons
per barge.
   ``Essentially, besides losing about five weeks of the season,
they won't be able to carry as much cargo,'' Worm said.
   The Missouri carries only a fraction of the commercial cargo
carried on the Mississippi each year, about 2.4 million tons
compared to 75 million tons. But the restrictions still have a big
impact on the few companies that operate barge lines there.
   ``We charge by the ton, so if we carry fewer tons per barge, we
lose money,'' said Roger Blaske, co-owner of Blaske Marine Inc., of
Alton, Ill., which operates barges on both the Missouri and
Mississippi.
   But higher costs aren't his main worry.
   ``If they release less water, we may have to quit on the
Missouri altogether,'' Blaske said.
   The river is controlled by a series of six dams between Montana
and South Dakota, designed to control flooding in wet years and
maintain a stable river in dry years.
   South Dakota Gov. George Mickelson contends the small amount of
barge traffic traveling the 730 miles between Sioux City, Iowa, and
St. Louis doesn't justify the low water levels in his state's
reservoirs.
   Although the state of Missouri has received normal rainfall so
far this year, North Dakota, South Dakota and Montana each lacked
both winter snow and spring rains.
   Because of that, the Missouri river received only 80 percent of
its normal spring runoff. About 19.6 million acre feet of water
flowed into the river north of Sioux City, compared to the normal
25 million, Worm said.
   The low water levels have threatened city and rural water supply
systems, left boat ramps far from water's edge and prevented
irrigators from using water in the huge reservoirs, Worm said.
Farther south, about 1,400 boat slips between Sioux City and Omaha
are endangered.
   Mehan says he recognizes South Dakota's legitimate worries, but
says Missouri has water needs, too, and might enter the fight with
legal action.
   ``We would hope to be accommodating to their problem, but we
certainly have to draw the line somewhere,'' he said.
   Many Missouri cities and towns, including Kansas City, St.
Joseph and St. Louis, have improved their drinking water intake
systems in recent years, but that might not protect them if the
Corps cuts back the water flow, Mehan said.
   The effect the low Missouri will have on the Mississippi River
is another question, and a troubling one, officials say.
   ``The Missouri is going to be lower this year than it was last
year,'' said Ken Kruchowski, a spokesman for the Corps in St.
Louis. ``And we had major problems on the Mississippi last year.
We'll just have to wait and see.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0085 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 1348EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-NuclearSavings Bjt   05-06 0773</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Nuclear Savings, Bjt,0799</SECOND>
<HEAD>Researcher Says Nuclear War Fears Mirror Nation's Savings Rate</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By A.J. DICKERSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ANN ARBOR, Mich. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Why save if the end is near?
   ``If people don't think there's a future, they don't save,''
says Joel Slemrod, associate professor of business economics at the
University of Michigan and author of studies comparing nuclear-war
fears with savings habits.
   The higher the fear, the less is saved, he says.
   ``The United States had the highest fear of nuclear war, and our
net private savings rate is near the bottom,'' he said.
   Slemrod's theory differs from most. Economists disagree on
whether there's a single reason for the savings rate.
   One theory for the low U.S. savings rate blames the throng of
baby boomers coming of age, putting off saving to buy and equip
homes and making other major purchases.
   ``You have to look at demographics _ a large portion of the
population in the acquiring phase of life,'' said Virginia
Stafford, spokeswoman for the American Bankers Association in
Washington.
   Another idea is that inflation may make people feel less likely
to squirrel away money that will erode in value.
   Other experts maintain the U.S. savings rate historically has
been lower than other nations because of cultural difference and
federal tax laws, which, for example, can make it more advantageous
to borrow rather than save.
   Robert Dugger, chief economist with the ABA, said some believe
the dismal increase in inflation-adjusted income between the early
1970s and 1990 made people spend more to keep the lifestyle they
wanted _ and that meant less savings.
   Besides, he said, uncertainty about the future could make people
less sure there's any value in saving today.
   That's similar to what Slemrod found in his first study,
published in 1986 in the Journal of Conflict Resolution. He
compared the U.S. net average private savings rate, which includes
households and companies, with fears about the likelihood of
nuclear war between the late 1940s and mid 1980s. To measure fear,
he counted national media mentions of nuclear war and the
``doomsday clock,'' set by the Bulletin of Atomic Scientists since
1947.
   Movements of ``the clock and savings rate were almost
identical,'' he said.
   His second study, to be published in the journal Economic
Inquiry later this year, looked at international Gallup polls that
asked if people thought nuclear war was likely within 10 years. He
compared that with the average net savings rate in Western nations
between 1981 and 1984, the most recent year for which both figures
were available.
   Fears of war were higher in countries where savings were less,
he said. In the United States, the fear index was 54.5, and the
average net private savings rate was 10.4 percent. In Japan, the
figures were 29.4 for fear and 19.3 percent for savings. In
Switzerland, the fear index was 33.9 percent, compared with savings
of 18.9 percent. In Spain, the fear index was 41.8 percent vs. 11
percent for savings.
   The Bush administration is concerned enough about America's
savings' habits to offer its Family Savings Account, which would
enable families to save up to $5,000 a year and not pay taxes on
the interest if they left the account untouched for seven years.
The plan is before Congress.
   Even so, since a 1987 nadir, the U.S. savings rate has edged up,
government and private figures show.
   By one measure, the percent of disposable income that households
save, the rate of 3.2 percent in 1987 rose to 5.5 percent for all
of last year and was 5.9 percent for January, said analyst Ysabel
Burns McAleer of the American Financial Services Association in
Washington.
   Slemrod in part credits improved East-West relations. ``I think
the thaw has been around long enough. The future is more assured
now,'' he said.
   ``It may be boomers are past peak borrowing years,'' Dugger said
of the savings rise. Also, he believes that improved U.S.
productivity is enhancing real income, which contributes to savings.
   ``Thirdly, the Berlin Wall effect is to increase the present
value of future benefits of savings _ so you tend to save more,''
he said.
   Since Slemrod finished his research, the doomsday clock moved.
In March, it was turned back from six to 10 minutes to midnight,
with midnight being doom.
   ``I think the perception right now is that we have a future
again. The deepest part of the Cold War affected people in
hard-to-measure ways,'' said Len Ackland, editor of the Bulletin of
Atomic Scientists.
   ``People do feel freer and sense the possibilities of a better
future, and start preparing for it, and part of that is savings.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0086 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 1456EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-IMF-Investment     05-06 0311</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-IMF-Investment,0322</SECOND>
<HEAD>Third World Leader Seeks Private Investment</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CARL HARTMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Third World countries that have discouraged
private investment must look increasingly to business for help in
developing, said Bernard Chidzero, minister of finance in
Zimbabwe's one-party government.
   ``In my part of the world there are many countries which are
one-party states _ I don't have to mention them, I'm sure you know
them _ and changes are beginning to take place even there,'' he
told reporters Sunday.
   ``I think this should be encouraged and we ought to learn a
great deal from what has happened in eastern Europe,'' he said.
   In the past many governments have discouraged private investment
by their own people as well as by foreigners, Chidzero said. Such
governments have attempted to promote greater public sector control
of the economy and sought to reduce influence over the economy held
by outsiders, he said.
   Chidzero spoke to reporters as chairman of the Development
Committee that brings together industrial and Third World countries
under the auspices of the World Bank and the International Monetary
Fund. The two bodies are holding semi-annual meetings, which end
Tuesday.
   He endorsed the work of the International Finance Corporation,
the World Bank arm that lends directly to private companies rather
than to governments. The corporation wants to double its capital of
$1.3 billion so it can make more loans.
   Chidzero expressed the concern, often heard from African
leaders, that new interest in investment in the liberalizing
countries of eastern Europe will reduce aid for the Third World. He
said he hoped donor countries would not do that.
   ``By leaving the developing countries alone, or siphoning
resources from them into eastern Europe they (would be) creeating a
very dangerous situation, an explosive situation,'' he said.
   ``They would create conditions that are likely to undermine
international peace and security.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0087 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 1536EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f BC-Obit-Bruch     05-06 0092</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Obit-Bruch,0098</SECOND>
<HEAD>Inventor of PAL Color Television System is Dead</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HANOVER, West Germany (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Walter Bruch, a German television
pioneer who invented the PAL color system, has died, the Telefunken
company said Sunday. He was 82.
   Bruch invented the Phase Alternation Line (PAL) color television
system 20 years ago. Telefunken, a West German maker of television
sets, said the system was now being used in 60 countries.
   Bruch had been Telefunken's head of research for many years.
   Telefunken said Bruch died after a long illness but gave no
other details.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0088 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 1627EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-US-IMF-Germany     05-06 0399</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-US-IMF-Germany,0414</SECOND>
<HEAD>West German Minister Says Unification to Help Other Countries</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CARL HARTMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   German unification will help other countries
by increasing German imports and cutting German exports, West
German Finance Minister Theo Waigel said Sunday.
   That trend should help reduce global trade imbalances, including
the United States' big trade deficit, and lead to more stable in
foreign exchange rates, Waigel said.
   ``Germany's wide open borders offer foreign sellers additional
possibilities in a new joint economic and currency area,'' Waigel
said in a statement prepared for a meeting of finance ministers
from the Group of Seven leading industrial countries, or G-7.
   ``They will lead to rising imports, since the typical demand of
East German consumers is in great part for the kind of goods which
come largely from other countries.''
   West Germany's big surplus of exports, along with Japan's, is
the other side of the huge U.S. trade deficit, or surplus of
imports, that reached $109 billion last year.
   West German factories will produce more for sales in East
Germany and less for exports to the rest of the world, Waigel said.
   He said not only western industrial countries but eastern Europe
and the Third World will benefit from the chance to increase
exports to a unified Germany. That should lead to a better balance
of trade and more stability of world exchange rates, he said.
   The seven ministers were meeting at the Capitol rather than in
Brady's Treasury Department, where such sessions have been held
previously. He was scheduled to give them a tour of the building.
   The tour could serve as a reminder that the United States'
expected $12 billion contribution to an increase in International
Monetary Fund resources will need approval from Congress. There is
some Congressional opposition, though the contribution will not add
to the U.S. budget deficit.
   The G-7 ministers were aiming for an agreement on new
contributions to the fund's resources, which are used for loans to
developing countries. Their views were expected to be largely
accepted by the other 145 member governments.
   The IMF and its sister agency, the World Bank, are holding their
semiannual meetings in Washington through Tuesday.
   Waigel predicted an agreement would boost the IMF's resources by
about $60 billion, or 50 percent. That is the figure predicted by
U.S. Treasury officials, although the IMF has sought an increase of
$80 billion.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0089 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 1633EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-US-TobaccoTrade     05-06 0611</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-US-Tobacco Trade,0628</SECOND>
<HEAD>New Round in Escalating Cigarette Export Dispute</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GENE KRAMER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Critics of U.S. cigarette exports told
Congress the nation's reputation as a maker of life-saving medical
miracles is being tarnished with a new image as an exporter of
disease and death.
   ``Free trade is not a license to export lung cancer or ride
roughshod over the anti-smoking laws of other nations,'' Sen.
Edward M. Kennedy, D-Mass., said Friday at a hearing of the Labor
and Human Resources Committee he chairs.
   Kennedy sided strongly with critics of the industry in a growing
debate over whether the U.S. government should continue seeking
expanded foreign markets for American cigarettes.
   The House has scheduled committee hearings later this month on
legislation to prohibit such trade promotion and to require on U.S.
brands sold abroad the same health warning that appears on
cigarette packages in the United States.
   Friday's hearing was the first airing of the issue in the
Senate, where legislation has not yet been proposed.
   The government's success in opening markets to U.S. cigarette
brands in Japan, South Korea and Taiwan and a current effort in
Thailand drew strong praise and support from witnesses representing
the cigarette industry and tobacco-growing states and in a letter
earlier this week from House members to Ambassador Carla Hills, the
U.S. trade representative.
   Their message was that the dispute is not a health issue but a
question of fair trade, of gaining equal rights for U.S. brands to
be sold to people who will continue to use a legal product,
tobacco, regardless of what country it comes from.
   ``Millions of people around the world smoke and will continue to
smoke whether or not American cigarettes are available,'' said Sen.
Mitch McConnell, R-Ky., one of several legisltors testifying from
tobacco-growing states.
   Tobacco was one of the few U.S. exports earning a surplus _ more
than $4.2 billion _ last year to help offset the $109 billion U.S.
trade deficit, he said.
   Accusing the Thai government of hypocrisy, McConnell charged
that it is protecting its tobacco monopoly and planning to expand
its own exports yet ``has the audacity to ask us not to export
cigarettes to Thailand'' for health reasons.
   Kennedy said foreign sales may help multinational tobacco
companies but U.S. tobacco farmers ``are getting the short end of
the stick,'' because most American brands sold abroad are made in
foreign factories using cheap high-tar and high-nicotine
non-American tobacco.
   Rep. Chester Atkins, D-Mass., a co-author of the House
legislation, testified that the industry failed to address the
major issue, its current effort to gain rights to promote U.S.
brands in Thailand even though the Southeast Asian country
prohibits tobacco advertising for health reasons.
   Atkins and Kennedy accused the industry and U.S. administration
of a double standard, seeking rights to lure Asian women and young
people to smoke with forms of promotion forbidden in America, where
smoking is on the decline.
   Dr. Prakit Vathesatogut, director of the Thai Anti-Smoking
Coalition, displayed to the subcommittee wearing apparel such as
shirts and caps bearing U.S. cigarette brand names such as Marlboro
and Winston, which he said are handed out in Thailand, and Thai
advertising depicting smoking as part of a youthful American image.
   ``In the modern-day equivalent of the Opium Wars, our government
is aiming to unleash the Marlboro Man on the Thai citizenry,''
Atkins said.
   The Opium War between Britan and China was fought from 1839 to
1842 over the right of British traders based in India to ship opium
to China. China, which sought to ban the import of opium, lost, and
was forced to permit the opium trade for decades.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0090 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 1723EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-Northwest-Airbus     05-06 0603</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Northwest-Airbus,0630</SECOND>
<HEAD>Records: Airbus Has Problems With Computerized Flight-Control
System</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MINNEAPOLIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Northwest Airlines has had recurring problems
with the computerized flight controls on its new Airbus A320s,
airline and federal records show, but officials say the problems
haven't endangered any passengers.
   In early March, Northwest sent pilots a bulletin advising them
to be aware of possible problems following ``a recent series of
events related to suspected ... failures'' in the cockpit computer
system, the Star Tribune reported Sunday.
   Northwest said last week it is involved in discussions with the
Federal Aviation Administration and Airbus Industrie, the European
consortium that builds the plane, on ways to prevent and correct
the problems, the newspaper said.
   The bulletin ``was issued so crews are not caught by surprise
when something happens,'' said Stuart Henning, vice president for
flight operations.
   FAA officials said the agency is working closely with Northwest
to resolve the problems.
   ``It is a properly certified aircraft,'' said Mort Edelstein of
the FAA's regional office in Chicago. ``Any failures are not out of
the ordinary when you're breaking in an aircraft. But at no time is
safety compromised.''
   An Airbus spokesman did not return a phone call seeking comment
Sunday.
   The A320 is the only commercial aircraft that uses computers to
operate all flight controls. Northwest is the only U.S. airline
flying the aircraft.
   Two A320s have crashed since 1988. The most recent, in February,
killed 92 people in India.
   Airbus has blamed the accident on pilot error, but some Indian
officials have suggested a computer malfunction. The government has
grounded all Indian Airlines A320s pending the report of a
committee investigating the crash and halted further deliveries of
the plane.
   Three people died in an A320 crash in France in 1988.
Investigators have blamed pilot error for both crashes.
   Northwest issued its bulletin three weeks after the Indian
Airlines crash. ``We have had a recent series of events related to
suspected (guidance computer) failures. These failures may not be
easily recognized. This (notice) is meant to heighten pilot
awareness of potential problems,'' the bulletin said.
   The bulletin advised crews to monitor the autoflight system
``with increased vigilance'' and to be aware of poor or improper
response from the autothrust system, which regulates the engines'
speed. Pilots were told to revert immediately to manual thrust if
the autothrust system responded poorly or improperly.
   Northwest has eight A320s in use. Since last July, when it put
the first of them into service, the airline has filed 39 reports
known as ``service difficulty reports'' on the A320 with the FAA.
   The Star Tribune said it got copies of the reports through the
Freedom of Information Act.
   Some of the reports refer to computer malfunctions. At least
nine incidents caused an A-320 to abort takeoff, return to the
airport after takeoff or divert to another airport before the
scheduled landing, the newspaper said.
   FAA records show Northwest pilots were forced to take quick
action on three occasions because of suspected computer
malfunctions.
   Northwest officials said the aborted takeoffs occurred well
within acceptable margins of safety and that in each instance the
pilot could have taken off and flown the plane manually.
   Steve Arnold, a Northwest pilot and A-320 first officer and
spokesman for the Air Line Pilots Association on questions
regarding the plane, said pilots are enthusiastic about the plane.
   ``It's like going from props to jets,'' he said. ``Once you get
into this airplane you look back and say, `What an improvement!'''
   Airbus Industrie is a consortium composed of British Aerospace,
Aerospaciale of France, Messerschmitt-Boelkow-Blohm Gmbh of West
Germany and Aeronauticas Naccionales of Spain.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0091 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 1809EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-US-IMF-Quotas     05-06 0463</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-US-IMF-Quotas,0478</SECOND>
<HEAD>Iran Voices Threat to $60 Billion for International Monetary Fund</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CARL HARTMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A group of Third World countries threatened to
block a $60 billion increase in the International Monetary Fund's
resources because it is linked to a plan to force delinquent
nations to repay their debts.
   The Group of 24 (G-24) Third World countries voted behind closed
doors to issue a long statement on fund policies. It included
criticism of plans to link the increased IMF contribution to making
11 delinquent countries repay $4.3 billion in arrears they owe the
fund. It has been proposed that to get the delinquents to pay up,
the fund could suspend their right to vote.
   ``The proposal for suspension of voting and representation
rights of those members will not serve a useful purpose and is not
acceptable,'' the joint statement said.
   On Thursday a senior U.S. Treasury official supported a
carrot-and-stick approach to the arrears problem.
   It would offer help from a special fund to countries in arrears
if they agree to new policies designed to put them in better shape
to pay up. Until they do, it would suspend their rights to vote in
the fund. The rights correspond roughly to their contributions,
known as quotas.
   The U.S. contribution to the increased quotas would be about $12
billion. The amount would not be added to the federal budget
deficit and would not change U.S. voting rights, since other
members also would contribute.
   Sayyed Mohammad Hossein Adeli, head of Iran's central bank and
chairman of the Group of 24, declined to say whether group members
would vote against the $60 billion quota increase if it is linked
to the plan on arrears.
   ``If this is taken up in the Interim Committee, the developing
countries would discuss it and hope to reach an agreement,'' he
said at a news conference.
   He added that the group did not want to delay th agreement on
the increased quotas.
   The fund classes 130 of its 152 members as developing countries.
The 24 in Adeli's group would have enough votes _ just over 15
percent of the total _ to block an agreement. Voting is based on
quotas, with the largest single voting power _ just short of 20
percent _ in the hands of the United States.
   The 11 delinquent countries are: Sudan, Zambia, Peru, Guayana,
Honduras, Cambodia, Liberia, Panama, Sierra Leone, Somalia and
Vietnam.
   The statements from Adeli and his group came as U.S. Treasury
Sexcretary Nicholas F. Brady was meeting at the Capitol with
finance ministers from Japan, West Germany, Britain, France, Italy
and Canada. They were trying to agree on the exact amount of the
new contributions and other fund business, including what to do
about the arrears.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900506-0092 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-06-90 1946EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-Greyhound 2ndLd-Writethru f0035-37-38 05-06 0791</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Greyhound, 2nd Ld-Writethru, f0035-37-38,0815</SECOND>
<HEAD>Greyhound Calls for Wage Freeze, Scrapping Union Jobs</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: Combines pvs takes; edits to tighten. Also moved on general
news wires.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By KAREN BALL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Labor Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Greyhound is calling for a four-year wage
freeze and the elimination of about 4,500 union jobs in its latest
contract offer in the two-month-old drivers' strike, an executive
for the bus line said Sunday.
   The offer was made Saturday as negotiators met for the first
time since mid-March and a day after the company announced a $56
million loss for the first three months of this year.
   The union called the offer ``greedy'' and an ``insult.''
   Bargaining talks were halted indefinitely following Saturday's
session.
   The company's offer, which outlines a major reduction in
services for the only nationwide bus system, would give drivers
$12.79 an hour rather than their previous 30-cents-a-mile rate,
said Greyhound Vice President Anthony P. Lannie.
   The company's poor financial situation and move to reduce
services are forcing it to eliminate about 2,000 of its 6,000
driver jobs, Lannie said.
   Another 2,500 union jobs would go to the 2,500 non-union
replacement drivers the company has hired since the strike began
March 2, Lannie said, adding that the 500 union members who crossed
picket lines also would be kept.
   The bus line told union negotiators it had immediate openings
for only 620 striking drivers and probably could take another 700
back within a few months.
   The wage offer amounts to a wage cut for some employees rather
than a freeze, contended union president Edward M. Strait. He said
he would not relay the proposal to local union presidents and
rank-and-file members who have been on strike since March 2.
   ``They'd throw me out the upstairs window if I went back with
this. It's an insult. There would be no dignity for the drivers,''
Strait said. ``I would characterize it as greedy ... they don't
care about their employees.''
   Union officials calculated that a driver who normally makes runs
from Washington D.C. to New York would lose more than $30 a day _
or as much as $7,000 a year _ from the company's proposed switch to
an hourly rate, Strait said.
   Before the strike, union drivers had made an average annual
salary of about $24,000.
   Lannie said the $12.79 an hour rate equals what drivers were
making under the 30-cent-per-mile rate. It also would equalize pay
among drivers, he said, adding that the per-mile pay system meant
drivers in different regions earned different amounts.
   The company's six-year proposal provides ``standstill'' wages in
the first four years and 3 percent wage hikes in both the fifth and
sixth years, Lannie said.
   Strait, head of the Amalgamated Council of Greyhound Local
Unions, said he was insulted by the company's attitude during
Saturday's nine-hour bargaining session.
   ``For a company on the rocks, that's going under, they could
have come in and said, `Hey, we're in trouble, can you help us?'
Instead they said, `This is what it's going to be,''' Strait said,
contending that the company was trying to ``bust the union.''
   Strait called on the company to abandon its position of keeping
the replacement drivers, but Lannie said the company would not
compromise on that issue.
   Lannie said the company was forced to propose a wage freeze and
scrap jobs because of the financial problems created by the strike.
   ``We were backed into a corner. They walked off the job in a
fashion designed to shut us down. They are where they are by virtue
of their own actions,'' Lannie said.
   The Greyhound official said the company was not trying to break
the union because the bus line ``has a long history with this
group. We would like to continue that relationship.''
   Lannie and Strait are trying to settle disputes over wages, job
security and seniority issues for the 6,300 striking drivers and
3,000 clerical and maintenance workers who also walked out in March.
   Many of the striking union members who would lose their jobs
under the proposal were part-time drivers, while all drivers under
the new proposal would be full-time, the company official said.
   Lannie said the company proposes to let union drivers who lose
their jobs take their pension funds without penalty, and it also
wants to discuss severance pay with the union.
   Lannie said the company is abandoning charter service in all but
19 of the 197 cities where it was offered.
   The company plans to keep lines running to all but 2 percent of
the cities it served, he said. It plans to reduce its practice of
running additional buses in peak periods when buses are full. Now,
passengers will have to wait until the next scheduled bus departs,
he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
</Collection>
