<Collection>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0001 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 2315EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Navy-Rape     10-21 0347</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Navy-Rape,260</SECOND>
<HEAD>Paper Cites IG Report on Rapes at Navy Training Facility</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   There were at least six rapes of female
students or recruits at the Orlando Naval Training Center during
the 18 months ending June 30, but the Navy has not prosecuted
anyone for them, according to a published report.
   Citing a Navy inspector general's report it obtained Friday by
request, The Washington Post said 24 rapes or sexual assaults were
reported during the 18-month period and that Navy law enforcement
officials ``substantiated or resolved'' eight of the rape cases and
five instances of sexual assault -- including indecent exposure and
attempted rape.
   The report in Monday's editions of the paper said only one of
the 13 cases, an assault case, resulted in court-martial
proceedings.
   The Post said the investigation found that some alleged
offenders, often instructors of supervisors of the women involved,
were returned to their jobs and continued working near the victims.
It said others were transferred from Orlando or released from the
Navy -- avoiding prosecution -- an that some victims may have been
so intimidated by investigators that they did not press charges.
   The IG report was quoted as saying that the Navy's failure to
move against offenders in numerous sex-related cases has
contributed to an atmosphere at the Florida facility that makes
women ``feel like they are second-class members of the Navy.''
   The Post quoted Vice Adm. John S. Disher, the Navy's chief of
education and training, as characterizing the problems cited at
Orlando as occurring ``throughout the entire Navy'' and saying
``much more must be done'' to solve the problem.
   Rep. Beverley B. Byron, D-Md., chairman of the House Armed
Services military personnel and compensation subcommittee, was
quoted as blaming the problems at the training center on ``a
breakdown in leadership and oversight of the leadership.''
   The Post said she received a copy of the report under a Navy
policy that requires such reviews to be provided to Congress 24
hours before they ar released to journalists.
   The paper quoted Vice Adm. Michael Boorda, the Navy's personnel
chief, as saying: ``I've looked at the numbers. They certainly are
not pleasing. But the problem is not being ignored. The training is
being done and the people are aware of the problem. People are
being found guilty and punished. Is the punishment fair or not
fair? That is a personal judgment.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0002 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 2330EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gadhafi-Sudan 1stLd-Writethru a0753 10-21 0340</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gadhafi-Sudan, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0753,0371</SECOND>
<HEAD>Gadhafi Gives Sudanese Rebels Ultimatum</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: DELETES extraneous `he' in 2nd graf</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By MOHAMED OSMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>KHARTOUM, Sudan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Libyan leader Moammar Gadhafi on Sunday
threatened to throw his forces into the battle against
anti-government rebels in Sudan unless the rebels end their revolt
within a year.
   Gadhafi said he would attempt to persuade rebel leader John
Garang - whose rebellion Gadhafi supported in the past - to suspend
his seven-year fight now that Sudan has proposed adopting a
Libyan-style government.
   But Gadhafi said Libya ``will have no option but to stand by the
Sudanese people and government against Garang'' if a cease-fire is
not reached by Oct. 21, 1991.
   The rebels operating in southern Sudan - mostly Christians and
members of traditional African religions - are seeking economic and
political reforms from the Moslem-dominated government and greater
autonomy for three southern Sudanese provinces.
   Gadhafi's comments were made during the closing session of a
six-week conference that recommended Sudan copy Libya's
``jamaheriya'' - or ``republic of the masses'' - system of local
and provincial councils instead of elected officials.
   Military ruler Lt. Gen. Omar Hassan el-Bashir, who led a coup
last year to oust a civilian government, is expected to ratify the
recommendations by the 1,000-member conference.
   Gadhafi, a principal advocate of a pan-Arab state, said Libya,
Sudan and Egypt should forge a political and social union.
   ``Sudan, Egypt and Libya constitute the heart, the main body of
the Arab nation, the movement of which control the movement of the
other Arab states,'' said Gadhafi, whose speech was televised
throughout Sudan.
   Egypt, which follows a parliamentary system, has rebuffed
Gadhafi's earlier calls for unity.
   Gadhafi has unsuccessfully attempted to unify Libya with most
Arab nations since taking power in 1969. He said peaceful rallies
would be staged in all Arab countries beginning Jan. 1 to support
pan-Arab unity.
   Libya has had close relations with Sudan since a 1985 uprising
that overthrew the pro-U.S. President Gaafar Nimeiri. El-Bashir
banned political parties and dismissed the elected parliament.
   Gadhafi admitted Libya trained and armed the rebel People's
Liberation Army, but said he stopped assistance after Nimeiri's
ouster.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0003 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 2336EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Budget-Taxes 5thLd-Writethru a0775 10-21 0899</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Budget-Taxes, 5th Ld-Writethru, a0775,990</SECOND>
<HEAD>Budget Bargainers Narrow Differences on Gasoline Tax; Adjourn
Until Monday</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: SUBS 2nd graf, ``Congressional leakers xxx with talks ending
for night; should stand</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By ALAN FRAM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Democrats and Republicans narrowed differences
Sunday over new taxes on the rich, gasoline levies, and Medicare
cuts, even as Bush administration officials angrily stalked out of
deficit-reduction talks.
   Congressional leaders of both parties negotiated until about
11:30 p.m. Sunday over a $250 billion package of tax increases and
spending cuts in agriculture, student loans and dozens of other
programs. They said they would resume talking Monday.
   ``We've made good progress in many areas,'' said Senate Majority
Leader George Mitchell, D-Maine. But he conceded, ``The remaining
areas of disagreement are important ones.''
   Weekend bargaining saw the two sides move toward each other in
several areas, including the question of how - and how high - to
raise taxes on the rich.
   The talks proceeded on the eve of what lawmakers hoped would be
Congress' last week before adjournment for the year. In the scant
time left, House and Senate leaders say they would still like to
tackle bills dealing with civil rights, air pollution and child
care.
   Budget negotiators seemed willing to raise the income-tax rate
on the wealthy to 31 percent, up from its current 28 percent. They
were also close on proposals to limit the deductions the wealthiest
taxpayers could claim.
   But Democrats were insisting on a 7.5 percent surtax on incomes
exceeding $1 million annually. The proposal, if adopted, would
allow Democrats to claim that rates on millionaires were raised
substantially.
   ``We think it's good public policy and fair,'' said Mitchell.
   Republicans were adamantly against that idea, and instead wanted
higher limitations on millionaires' deductions.
   White House Chief of Staff John Sununu accused Democrats of
being too divided to respond to the latest GOP offer.
   ``We're not going to negotiate with Democrats who can't come to
an agreement among themselves,'' he said as he left the Capitol
with White House budget chief Richard Darman and Treasury Secretary
Nicholas Brady. ``This was a great offer.''
   But Mitchell denied that, saying, ``I can say to you Democrats
are unified.''
   Despite the standoff over taxes, the two sides moved closer in
other areas, said a Democratic congressional official who asked to
not be identified.
   Democrats offered to raise the gasoline tax 5 cents above its
current 9-cent-a-gallon level. Republicans were seeking a 7-cent
increase.
   Democrats were offering to reduce Medicare by as much as $44
billion, $3 billion less than Republicans were demanding.
   In addition, Democrats were seeking to boost the $51,300 wage
cap from which Medicare taxes are deducted to $125,000. Republicans
want to increase the cap to $98,000. The 1.45 percent Medicare tax
is part of the Social Security deduction.
   Republicans have been fearful of late that Democrats have made
the tax-the-rich battle cry their own barely two weeks from
Election Day. Earlier in the day, White House aides said higher
levies on the rich were on the way.
   ``This is one of the all-time false issues, the rich-poor
thing,'' said administration budget director Richard Darman. ``This
compromise in the end will tax the rich.''
   Working against a Wednesday deadline when stopgap spending
authority expires, bargainers were trying to find middle ground
between separate deficit-reduction plans approved by the House and
Senate last week. The Senate bill - preferred by Bush - had more
moderate tax increases on the wealthy, took a bigger bite out of
Medicare spending and doubled the gasoline tax.
   ``We feel very strongly there should be a surcharge and a rate
increase on higher-income levels,'' House Speaker Thomas Foley,
D-Wash., told reporters.
   ``It's got to move in the direction of being fairer in terms of
taxes, in other words, asking the wealthiest Americans to pay their
fair share,'' said House Majority Leader Richard Gephardt, D-Mo.,
who like Darman appeared on ABC-TV's ``This Week With David
Brinkley'' program.
   Darman said Bush would accept a 31 percent rate on the rich, up
from 28 percent, if the rate on those slightly less well-off was
reduced from 33 percent to 31 percent. That tradeoff, eliminating
the so-called bubble, would increase taxes for 700,000 people and
reduce them for 5 million others while raising an estimated $7
billion in additional revenue.
   But Mitchell said Democrats would not accept that offer alone.
   ``It obviously would have to be accompanied by other measures''
so people whose taxes were cut ``would be required to pay something
to offset that reduction,'' Mitchell said on NBC-TV's ``Meet the
Press'' program.
   ``We're not hung up on any one formula, but rather the principle
of fairness,'' Mitchell added.
   The Senate approved a bipartisan budget Friday shrinking the
growth of Medicare by $49 billion over the next five years,
including $17 billion to be directed at the elderly and handicapped
served by the program.
   The House plan, which attracted only 10 GOP votes, limited those
cuts to $43 billion, of which participants would bear $10 billion
in reduced benefits and higher costs.
   The House would leave the 9-cent-a-gallon gasoline tax alone,
while the Senate would raise it gradually to 18.5 cents.
   Democrats have conceded that the final compromise is likely to
include some increase in the gasoline levy. They also have said
another feature of the House bill likely will be dropped: a
one-year delay in inflation adjustments on income-tax brackets and
the personal exemption, which would have caused slight increases in
the tax bills of everyone who pays income tax.
   Virtually certain to emerge in the final product are several
other features the two bills had in common, including higher taxes
on alcohol, tobacco, airline tickets and luxury items such as
yachts and jewelry.
   Spending cuts would be administered to agriculture, student loan
and veterans programs.
   The deficit-reduction bill combined with other savings - mainly
defense cuts and reduced interest payments on the debt - would
lower the deficit by $40 billion for the fiscal year that began
Oct. 1 and $460 billion more over the next five years.
   The budget stalemate cost the government $1.6 million when
agencies shut down over the Columbus Day weekend earlier in
October, the General Accounting Office said in a report.
   The government had closed because in an effort to keep pressure
on budget writers, Bush vetoed emergency spending legislation after
federal authority to spend money had elapsed.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0004 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 2350EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p PM-AbortionPolitics     10-21 0880</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Abortion Politics,1073</SECOND>
<HEAD>Abortion Re-Emerging as Issue in Campaigns</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Monday AMs report.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By WILLIAM M. WELCH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   After taking a back seat to worries about
taxes, the economy and the Middle East, abortion is re-emerging as
a potentially decisive issue in the final days of the 1990 election
season.
   ``It's one of the few issues that's still out there that
distinguishes people,'' said Harrison Hickman, a pollster for
abortion-rights causes. ``I would predict you'll see a lot of
people using it at the last minute to try to push undecided
voters.''
   Conventional political wisdom has held that abortion-rights
candidates had the upper hand this year and that opponents of
abortion were on the defensive after a 1989 Supreme Court ruling
revived the issue. Electoral losses for abortion foes in 1989
contributed to that view.
   Yet abortion hasn't proven to be the ``silver bullet'' for
abortion-rights candidates, in the words of Democrat Donald
Avenson, a pro-choice candidate for Iowa governor. And abortion
opponents point to races where their candidates have stood firm and
are leading - including governor's races in Ohio, Pennsylvania,
Texas and Iowa.
   ``It's not the issue some thought a year ago. On the other hand,
it's more salient this year than it has been in the past in a lot
of states,'' said Doug Johnson, legislative director for the
National Right to Life Committee.
   As a result, some thought abortion was fizzling this year as an
issue.
   But strategists for abortion-rights campaigns say there will be
a flurry of last-minute advertising pushing the abortion issue. In
some races it's already begun.
   Sometimes the push will be on television. But in other cases it
will be more selectively targeted toward young women voters through
direct-mail or telephone.
   ``People are thinking this is a dead issue. I think that's just
a fundamental misunderstanding of this issue,'' said Celinda Lake,
who has conducted polling for abortion-rights candidates around the
country.
   ``It's a last-minute issue,'' she said. ``It's something you lay
out in the last weeks of a campaign.''
   Abortion-rights strategists say their target audience, younger
voters, typically does not pay attention to campaigns until the
final stages.
   Lake says polling shows that increasing economic worries and
lack of trust of Democrats on the economy has caused a drop-off in
support for Democrats among younger women, she said. Abortion may
lure them back.
   ``It's a big drop off - 10 points,'' she said. ``Because of that
you'll see more pro-choice direct-mail geared toward that audience
at the end.''
   In North Carolina's Senate race, both anti-abortion Sen. Jesse
Helms and his Democratic challenger, Harvey Gantt, have been airing
ads on the issue.
   But in most states, it's the abortion-rights candidates who have
been using the issue in television ads.
   In Oregon, Democrat Harry Lonsdale has drawn even in his
challenge to GOP Sen. Mark Hatfield, according to recent polls,
after airing ads that attack Hatfield's opposition to abortion
among other issues.
   One race where abortion hasn't been the factor that was expected
is in Florida, where former Sen. Lawton Chiles is challenging GOP
Gov. Robert Martinez, who opposes abortion. Chiles, who supports
abortion rights, has found the issue uncomfortable for him and
isn't airing ads despite Martinez' seeming vulnerability on the
issue.
   The issue is important in Iowa's Senate race, where Democratic
incumbent Tom Harkin has a double-digit lead over anti-abortion
challenger Rep. Tom Tauke, according to recent polls.
   Harkin has been the abortion-rights point-man in the Senate, and
he led the fight last week to oppose an amendment requiring
teen-age girls to notify their parents before getting an abortion.
Parental consent on abortion tends to gain strong support in most
polls, but Harkin said the overall abortion issue helps him.
   ``The last thing my opponent wants to talk about is the choice
issue,'' Harkin said. ``I'm watching my tracking polls ... and the
number of people viewing his position as extreme is going like
this,'' he added, pointing upward.
   The Senate adopted the parental consent provision on a 48-48
vote, but the amendment was expected to be deleted in later
congressional action. Harkin's side was surprised it drew 48 votes.
   That vote has become an issue in California, where both
candidates for governor are trying to appeal to abortion-rights
supporters. Democratic candidate Dianne Feinstein blasted her GOP
rival, Sen. Pete Wilson, for missing the vote while campaigning.
   Abortion opponents have the upper hand in several races.
   In Kansas, Democratic gubernatorial candidate Joan Finney has
had difficulty explaining her anti-abortion position recently. But
she still leads GOP Gov. Mike Hayden, an abortion-rights supporter,
in the polls.
   Anti-abortion Republican George Voinovich has the lead in Ohio's
governor race, where Democrat Anthony Celebrezze has been
criticized for a startling flip-flop in which he dropped his
long-standing opposition to abortion.
   A September poll by the University of Cincinnati found that the
issue was helping Voinovich more than Celebrezze. Voinovich led
among the 13 percent of respondents who said abortion was the
single most important issue.
   In Iowa's governor's race, Democrat Avenson is running
abortion-rights ads but has yet to catch up with anti-abortion GOP
incumbent Terry Branstad.
   Abortion opponents in Idaho were angered by Gov. Cecil Andrus'
veto of a restrictive abortion bill this year, but he is in strong
shape in his re-election bid.
   It's become more of an issue in Idaho's Senate and House races,
however.
   Idaho Republican Senate candidate Larry Craig surprised his
anti-abortion supporters when he was asked in a debate what he
would do if his wife became pregnant as a result of rape.
   He responded that it was her decision, which seemed at odds with
his opposition to legal abortions. Democrat Ron Twilegar jumped on
the response, saying he wanted all women to have that choice but
Craig seemed to want it only for his wife. Craig says he was
misinterpreted and hasn't strayed from his opposition to abortion.
   Abortion also is an issue in about a dozen congressional races.
   In northern Virginia, for example, Democrat James Moran is
airing abortion-rights ads against GOP Rep. Stan Parris.
   Democrats see the issue helping Moran, the Alexandria mayor,
since the district was won by Gov. Doug Wilder in an important
abortion test last year.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0005 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 2352EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-RudmanProfile     10-21 0674</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Rudman Profile,0846</SECOND>
<HEAD>Senator Who Steered Souter to Court Sits Atop Ethics, Budget
Battles</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY305 of Oct. 18</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Monday AMs report.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By WILLIAM M. WELCH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Sen. Warren Rudman was wearing a big smile and
he didn't mind showing a guest the reason why.
   Walking to a tall window in his Senate office, the New Hampshire
Republican pointed to the unremarkable looking U-Haul parked on the
street below.
   ``See that truck,'' he said. ``That's David's belongings. His
buddies in New Hampshire said, `We'll load it up for you and send
it down.' And there it is.''
   David, of course, is David Souter: the newest Supreme Court
justice. As Souter's long-time friend and mentor, Rudman suggested
that President Bush nominate him, then guided the protege through
his Senate confirmation.
   But more than pride was behind that smile. There was relief. The
truck was evidence Rudman was at last losing the houseguest he'd
put up since the nation was introduced to David Souter on July 23.
   And he could use the break. Rudman, 60, a likeable second-term
senator, has found himself caught in a swirl of major battles.
   Besides shepherding Souter through the Senate, he's been near
the center of budget debates that bear his name. And he's the top
Republican on the Senate Ethics Committee that is weighing the fate
of five senators' involvement in the savings-and-loan scandals, a
decision with enormous political potential.
   ``I'm just on the thin edge,'' Rudman said. ``It's been an
unbelievable time. I'm ready to just go on top of a mountain in a
log cabin. That's what I'm ready for.
   ``It's been a very intensive, satisfying in many ways, three
months,'' he added. ``In some ways, it's been very unsatisfying.''
   Rudman, a moderate Republican, was swept into office with Ronald
Reagan in 1980.
   He unseated Democratic Sen. John Durkin, who four years earlier
had blocked President Ford's appointment of Rudman to a top agency
post. Rudman won the GOP nomination over a wide field that included
John Sununu, who later became governor and now is Bush's chief of
staff.
   Rudman is far more affable and far less ideological than Sununu.
That Souter was Rudman's protege and not Sununu's was of intense
comfort to many Democrats and in no small way eased his
confirmation.
   Rudman is Jewish, and during the confirmation hearings Souter
sought to display his sensitivity on civil rights by mentioning
their private discussions of the discrimination Rudman has felt as
a result of his religion.
   Souter and Rudman go back more than 20 years, when Rudman was
attorney general of New Hampshire and Souter worked for him. Few
brothers are closer, Rudman says. On his office wall are pictures
chronicling the intertwined careers of Rudman and Souter and the
other member of their trio, Tom Rath, a New Hampshire lawyer and
Republican activist.
   ``It was incredible - very satisfying to me,'' Rudman said.
``After all, he's one of my closest friends, very, very close. He's
someone who I set on his path 20-some-odd years ago. I told him he
ought to be a judge. To watch him being sworn in was just
enormously satisfying to me.''
   Less satisfying, he says, is the crisis over the budget.
   He is the Rudman of Gramm-Rudman, a law written with Sens. Phil
Gramm of Texas and Ernest Hollings of South Carolina that is the
nation's shorthand for budget crisis.
   The law imposed the deadline for deficit-cutting that has
triggered political brinkmanship and brought the government to
potential shutdown.
   Rudman is blunt without being a bully, as Sununu is often
called. He points to blame within his own party for the deficit
mess, and particularly faults House Republicans for refusing to go
along with new taxes.
   ``I don't meant this to be funny: I truly understand the new
Politburo in the Soviet Union ... better than I understand the
Republicans in the House of Representatives,'' he said. ``I don't
understand what they're doing. I truly don't understand it.
   ``Divided government is bad enough,'' he said. ``When you have a
divided party within a divided government, it is even more
frustrating.''
   Rudman's background as an attorney general helped earn him the
unenvied seat on the ethics committee, which investigates and
prosecutes senators caught in scandal or misdeeds.
   The panel is now deciding what to do about five senators, the
so-called Keating Five, accused of improperly intervening with
federal regulators on behalf of Charles H. Keating Jr., whose S&amp;L
was near insolvency. Keating contributed $1.3 million to the
senators' campaigns or groups affiliated with them.
   Rudman says he doesn't know when the panel will decide, but
acknowledges the job draws political heat.
   ``Oh sure, this is still a political institution. Everything we
do has some political aspects that relate to it,'' he said. ``Up to
now I cannot say I've seen politics enter into the Ethics
Committee. We'll see how this plays out.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0006 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 2353EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Japan-Taiwan     10-21 0372</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Japan-Taiwan,0426</SECOND>
<HEAD>Japanese Boats Block Taiwanese Delegation to Disputed Islands</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Japanese coast guard boats have turned back two
Taiwanese vessels carrying politicians and athletes toward a group
of tiny uninhabited islands claimed by both nations, officials
said.
   The Taiwanese had sought to land the delegation on the islands -
called the Senkakus in Japan and Diaoyutai in Taiwan - on Sunday to
reinforce their claim to the territory and promote a sports event.
   Taiwan's Premier Hau Pei-tsun said he was displeased by the
Japanese intervention and stressed that his nation ``will stand by
the claim'' to the islands about 120 miles northeast of Taiwan's
capital of Taipei.
   Athletes had planned to plant flags of Taiwan's Nationalist
Chinese government and run a torch relay on the main island before
returning Sunday night. They also intended to publicize the annual
Taiwan Athletic Championships that are scheduled to begin on Friday
in their country.
   The premier said the Nationalist government would seek
diplomatic means to solve the 45-year-old territorial dispute.
   Kiyoshi Harada of the Maritime Safety Agency, Japan's coast
guard, said the Taiwanese vessels entered 12-mile territorial
waters claimed by Japan despite warnings from patrol boats and
helicopters.
   He said the two boats turned back about two hours after entering
the waters. Harada declined to say how many patrol boats and
helicopters were involved or give other details of the incident.
   In Taiwan, the Fishermen's Association in Suao, about 35 miles
southeast of Taipei, said a radio message indicated about 12
Japanese vessels and two helicopters interdicted the Taiwanese
boats about seven miles from the islands.
   The two boats had set out earlier Sunday with a flotilla of 30
fishing boats.
   The islands were claimed by Japan in 1895. But the Nationalists,
who claim to be China's legitimate government, say the islands came
under Chinese sovereignty in 1945 when Japan was defeated in World
War II.
   The United States took over administration of the islands after
the war and returned them, along with Okinawa, to Japan in 1972. A
year earlier, the Communist government in China laid claim to the
islands.
   Japan's Kyodo News Service said Japan tightened patrols after
about 300 Chinese fishing boats approached the islands in 1978 and
claimed territorial rights.
   The latest dispute followed reports that a Japanese right-wing
political group received government permission to renovate a
lighthouse on one of the islands. Hau said last week that the
Nationalists would not tolerate Japan's occupation of the
territory.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0007 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 2355EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-WhalersFightBackII     10-21 1082</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Whalers Fight Back II,1354</SECOND>
<HEAD>Saving the Whales: Iceland's Critics Dispute Its Whale Research</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Monday AMs report.</NOTE>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   On the face of it, the United States government
and environmentalists may seem an unlikely alliance, but allied
they are in their opposition to the resumption of commercial
whaling in Iceland. In the second of two stories, AP Science Editor
Paul Raeburn examines the efforts to blunt Iceland's contentions
that its whales are not endangered.
   ---
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By PAUL RAEBURN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Editor</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>REYKJAVIK, Iceland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   ``A whale is the most beautiful animal
I have ever seen,'' the poet W.H. Auden wrote during a visit to
Iceland in 1936. ``To see it torn to pieces with steam winches and
cranes is enough to make one a vegetarian for life.''
   That kind of revulsion has helped make the global
save-the-whales campaign one of the most dramatic successes of the
environmental movement. An international moratorium on commercial
whaling was instituted in 1986, and environmentalists now are
pushing for a permanent ban on all whaling.
   ``We would certainly be against whaling until we could
definitely show it would not affect the (whale) stocks,'' says
Kevin Chu. ``If there is any doubt, we want to err on the side of
conservation.''
   That's tough talk - and it doesn't come from an
environmentalist. Chu is a foreign affairs officer in the U.S.
State Department's Bureau of Oceans and International Environmental
and Scientific Affairs.
   Asked to describe the U.S. position on whaling, Chu says: ``The
United States is against it.''
   The perhaps unusual consensus among the government and
environmental groups is fueled by two things: concern that whales
are in danger of extinction and the kind of sentiments evoked by
Auden.
   The government takes a strong anti-whaling stance because ``the
only voices we hear are the voices of the environmentalists,'' Chu
said.
   Iceland, one of the three major whaling nations along with
Norway and Japan, argues strenuously that the whales it wants to
hunt are not endangered and that it should be allowed to resume
commercial whaling.
   But even if scientists eventually agree the populations are
indeed not endangered, the campaign to save the whales is unlikely
to die.
   ``Politically, it comes down to a relatively simple thing,''
said William Evans, the U.S. representative to the International
Whaling Commission. ``There are a number of countries and
scientists that believe . . . there is not a justification, or
need, for any country to continue to harvest these animals.''
   ``I'm completely of the mindset that we have to protect oceans
for our own survival, and the whales are a component of this
ecosystem,'' said Sally Shoup of Greenpeace. ``We have to stop this
devastation of the other creatures on the planet if we want to
protect ourselves.
   ``I think whales are special,'' she said. ``I think they are
intelligent creatures. I think Icelanders can understand that as
well.''
   The save-the-whales campaign began in 1972, when the landmark
U.N. Conference on the Environment, in a 53-0 vote, passed a
resolution calling for a 10-year moratorium on whaling. Whalers
killed 46,000 whales that year.
   The United States immediately proposed the moratorium to the
whaling commission, which rejected it. But the U.S. continued to
push. In 1982, the commission finally approved a moratorium,
beginning in 1986.
   ``What we were going to do was take five years of no whaling,''
said Evans, the U.S. representative to the commission. ``Well, we
haven't had five years of no whaling, because Iceland invented
scientific whaling.''
   A clause in the international whaling convention allows the
killing of whales for scientific purposes. Iceland exploited it.
   ``You have the same boats and the same people and you take the
same whales and you sell it to the same people and you call it
scientific whaling,'' said Roger Payne, a noted whale expert and
president of the Long Term Research Institute in Lincoln, Mass.
``It's a joke.''
   Johann Sigurjonsson, senior whale specialist at Iceland's Marine
Research Institute, vigorously disagreed. ``Those who have been
following what we're doing understand the seriousness of what we're
doing,'' he said.
   In 1985, the last year of its commercial whaling operation,
Iceland killed 344 whales. It caught 116 in 1986, and the number
declined to 68 in 1989. This year, Iceland shut down its whaling
operation entirely, but it continues to press vigorously for a
resumption of commercial killing of fin, sei and minke whales.
   Congress has passed several laws that allow the United States to
impose economic sanctions against countries that violate whaling
commission regulations.
   Iceland's critics have argued that the scientific whaling is
merely commercial whaling under another name, and have pressed the
United States to impose sanctions. The United States might be
reluctant to do so, however, because Iceland is the site of a
strategic NATO base.
   Payne said the methods used to estimate whale populations are
highly imprecise, and that the Icelandic scientific research has
``shown us nothing we didn't know before.''
   It could take as long as 100 years to know how many whales can
be captured without reducing the size of a given whale population,
he said.
   The International Whaling Commission has stopped releasing
estimates of whale populations as it undertakes new assessments
because it fears its previous estimates could be wildly inaccurate,
said Martin Harvey, the commission's executive officer.
   The old estimates suggest that since the advent of whaling, the
population of fin whales has been reduced from 548,000 to 120,000,
while sei whales declined from 256,000 to 54,000.
   The commission completed its assessment of minke whales this
year and concluded that about 28,000 are in Icelandic waters,
``which we think is not too far from the number there ever was,''
said Ray Gambell, a whale biologist and the commission's secretary.
Some 600,000 minke whales live in Antarctic waters.
   Sigurjonsson calls the debate over population numbers a stalling
tactic.
   ``You can set catch limits very cautiously,'' he said. ``But to
reject any catch because you don't know the exact figure, that's a
difficult question. And it may take you years to find out the exact
number.''
   ``Part of the problem we're having with Iceland is: What is a
reasonable doubt?'' said Chu, of the State Department.
   ``The scientific committee (of the whaling commission) did say a
take of 200 minkes would probably not harm the stock,'' Chu said.
``It was the `probably' that first catches one's attention. We're
simply not prepared to let the moratorium lapse at this point.''
   Even if the moratorium was lifted or modified, Iceland couldn't
resume commercial whaling until at least 1992, Gambell said. The
commission can't decide until May, at the earliest, to allow
Iceland to proceed. And any such decision would not take effect
until 90 days later - too late for the 1991 season.
   Chu said one alternative might be for the whaling commission to
allow Iceland to resume hunting whales up to a quota, rather than
have Iceland withdraw from the commission as it has threatened to
do. If Iceland withdrew, it no longer would be bound by the
moratorium.
   ``I'm afraid the conservation of whales will suffer if we take
too strong a stand,'' said Chu, who said he was expressing his
personal views, not those of the State Department. ``On the other
hand, I think the United States is not in a position to allow them
some sort of a quota. It would be extremely difficult to bend the
moratorium.''
   Iceland's whalers also may be facing problems on a new front -
at home.
   ``The opinion of the Icelandic public is changing,'' said
Gudmundur Hermansson, who covers whaling for Morgunbladid,
Iceland's largest daily newspaper.
   In 1986, ``probably 80 percent to 90 percent of the public
supported the government,'' Hermansson said. But that figure is
dropping, he said.
   ``Opinion polls show clearly this support was getting less and
less every year,'' Hermansson said. ``I don't think whaling will be
taken up again.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0008 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 2357EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a BC-LOT-SaturdayLotteries     10-21 0788</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-LOT-Saturday Lotteries,0999</SECOND>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<HEAD>CALIFORNIA</HEAD>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SACRAMENTO, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers picked
Saturday night for the California Lottery's twice-weekly ``Lotto
6-53'' game:
   9, 38, 6, 29, 7, 20, and the bonus number, 27.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>CONNECTICUT</HEAD>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEWINGTON, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning combination picked Saturday
in the Connecticut State Lottery's ``Daily Lottery'' drawing was:
   8-8-8
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Play 4</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEWINGTON, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning combination picked Saturday
in the Connecticut State Lottery's ``Play 4'' drawing was:
   9-5-3-5.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>DELAWARE</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DOVER, Del. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   These Delaware lotteries were drawn Saturday
night:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   7-2-0
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Play Four</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   6-0-7-6
</TEXT>
<HEAD>FLORIDA</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected Saturday in
the Florida Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Cash 3</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   3-0-3
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   28-13-18-7-45-9
</TEXT>
<HEAD>ILLINOIS</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SPRINGFIELD, Ill. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the Illinois State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   9-0-6
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick Four</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   5-3-3-1
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   5, 12, 38, 43, 48, 53
</TEXT>
<HEAD>INDIANA</HEAD>
<HEAD>Ind Lottery Glance</HEAD>
<DATELINE>INDIANAPOLIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the Hoosier Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto Cash</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   9-25-38-32-41-21
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Three</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   1-8-7
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Four</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   1-1-4-7
</TEXT>
<HEAD>IOWA</HEAD>
<HEAD>Iowa Lotto</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DES MOINES, Iowa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning Iowa Lotto numbers drawn
Saturday night are:
   2-4-20-25-27-36.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto America</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DES MOINES, Iowa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers drawn Saturday night
in Lotto America are:
   4-19-24-30-38-45
</TEXT>
<HEAD>KANSAS</HEAD>
<HEAD>Kan. Cash Lotto</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOPEKA, Kan. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers in the Kansas Cash Lotto
drawing Saturday night with an estimated jackpot of $70,000:
   1-6-10-15-18-25
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Kan. Keno</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOPEKA, Kan. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers in the Kansas Keno
drawing Saturday night with a jackpot of $50,000:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>KENTUCKY</HEAD>
<HEAD>Kentucky Lottery</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOUISVILLE, Ky. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are Saturday's winning numbers
selected by the Kentucky Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Kentucky Cash:
   4-8-0.
   </HEAD>
<HEAD>Lotto:
   7-9-10-24-33-42.
   </HEAD>
<HEAD>MARYLAND</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BALTIMORE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   These Maryland lotteries were drawn Saturday
night:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   3-9-8
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Play Four</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   4-3-1-6
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   5-11-14-23-33-38
</TEXT>
<HEAD>MASSACHUSETTS</HEAD>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BRAINTREE, Mass. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers drawn Saturday night
in the ``Massachusetts Daily Lottery'' were:
   1-2-0-5
</TEXT>
<HEAD>MICHIGAN</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DETROIT (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected Saturday in
the Michigan State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   0-3-3
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily-4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   8-3-0-2
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto 47</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   6, 22, 23, 28, 35, 42)
</TEXT>
<HEAD>MISSOURI</HEAD>
<HEAD>Pick 3</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ST. LOUIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers in Saturday's Missouri
Lottery Daily Pick 3 game:
   5-1-0
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ST. LOUIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers in Missouri's Lotto drawing
Saturday night:
   4-5-8-10-14-27
</TEXT>
<HEAD>NEW JERSEY</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TRENTON, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday night in the New Jersey State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 3</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   1-8-8
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   0-5-9-5
</TEXT>
<HEAD>NEW YORK</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ALBANY, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the New York State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Number</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   7-8-4
</TEXT>
<HEAD>WinFour</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   0-1-1-8
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 10</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ALBANY, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the New York State Lottery's Pick 10 game:
   5, 16, 17, 21, 23, 35, 40, 41, 46, 47, 58, 61, 65, 67, 69, 70,
71, 74, 78, 80
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ALBANY, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the New York State Lottery's Lotto game:
   16, 20, 21, 33, 37, 52
</TEXT>
<HEAD>NORTHERN NEW ENGLAND</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CONCORD, N.H. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the daily New Hampshire, Vermont and Maine lotteries:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 3</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   6-6-3
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   5-8-9-7
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Tri-State Megabucks</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CONCORD, N.H. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers in the
``Tri-State Megabucks'' game for New Hampshire, Vermont and Maine:
   3-6-12-18-21-33
</TEXT>
<HEAD>OHIO</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CLEVELAND (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the selections Saturday night in the
Ohio Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Super Lotto</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   3-14-18-20-25-35
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Kicker</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   4-3-4-6-2-9
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 3 Numbers</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   9-5-7
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 4 Numbers</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   5-3-2-4
</TEXT>
<HEAD>OREGON</HEAD>
<HEAD>Daily 4</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PORTLAND, Ore. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are Saturday's winning numbers in the
``Oregon Daily 4'' lottery game:
   6-6-2-2
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Megabucks</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PORTLAND, Ore. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are Saturday's winning numbers in the
``Oregon Megabucks'' lottery game:
   2-12-23-39-42-43
</TEXT>
<HEAD>PENNSYLVANIA</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HARRISBURG (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected Saturday
in the Pennsylvania State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Number</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   0-4-3
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Big 4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   9-7-5-9
</TEXT>
<HEAD>RHODE ISLAND</HEAD>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CRANSTON, R.I. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers drawn Saturday night
in the Rhode Island daily lottery were:
   0-8-9-5
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto Bucks</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CRANSTON, R.I. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers drawn Saturday night
in the Rhode Island Lotto Bucks game were:
   2-10-11-22-35
</TEXT>
<HEAD>VIRGINIA</HEAD>
<HEAD>Pick 3</HEAD>
<DATELINE>RICHMOND (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   These numbers were drawn Saturday in the
Virginia Lottery's Lotto game:
   11-25-27-28-38-40.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>WASHINGTON, DC</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The following results were drawn Saturday in
the District of Columbia Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lucky Numbers Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   4-2-7
</TEXT>
<HEAD>D.C. Four Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   7-6-4-8
</TEXT>
<HEAD>D.C. Daily Double Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   66-74
</TEXT>
<HEAD>D.C. Quick Cash Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   9-15-25-32-35-37
</TEXT>
<HEAD>WEST VIRGINIA</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CHARLESTON, W.Va. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the West Virginia State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily 3</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   0-3-4
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily 4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   7-4-5-8
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0009 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 0002EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-WorldSeries-Newspage     10-21 0243</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-World Series-Newspage,0287</SECOND>
<HEAD>Cincinnati Reds Sweep Oakland Athetics in World Series</HEAD>
<DATELINE>OAKLAND, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Cincinnati Reds completed one of the
biggest upsets in baseball history Saturday night, rallying past
the awesome Oakland Athletics by 2-1 and winning the World Series
in four quick games.
   The Reds, who began the season with nine straight victories and
held first place all year, closed it with four wins in a row.
Cincinnati saved its best for last - finishing off the defending
World Series champions despite losing Billy Hatcher and Eric Davis
with first-inning injuries.
   Jose Rijo allowed just two hits in 8 1-3 innings, retiring the
final 20 batters he faced, before Randy Myers got the last two
outs, finishing a series in which Reds relievers pitched 13
scoreless innings.
   It was Rijo's second victory over Dave Stewart and it earned him
the Series MVP award.
   For the Reds, it was their ninth straight World Series win, a
streak that started in the days of the Big Red Machine. They took
advantage of Stewart's first error of the season and scored in the
eighth on Glenn Braggs' RBI forceout with the bases loaded and Hal
Morris' sacrifice fly.
   Barry Larkin tied the score on Braggs' effort and Herm
Winningham ran in for the winning run on Morris' sacrifice fly.
   For the A's, it was a bitter disappointment. They were outhit
45-28 and outscored 22-8 in the Series, and the loss marked only
their second four-game losing streak of the season.
   Willie McGee of the A's scored on a base hit by Carney Lansford
in the first inning, and it was seven more innings before
Cincinnati could get on the board.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0010 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 0027EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-China-Earthquake     10-21 0229</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-China-Earthquake,0259</SECOND>
<HEAD>One Dead, Two Injured in Quake; Heavy Snow Hampering Rescue</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Rescue workers have found only one fatality from
a powerful earthquake that hit northwest China, but heavy snowfall
hampered their search for casualties, the Central Seismology Bureau
said Sunday.
   ``At the moment, we have one dead and two injured, but I believe
there will be more,'' said Li Qianghua of the bureau.
   The temblor, measuring 6.2 on the Richter scale, hit central
Gansu province Saturday afternoon. Another quake measuring 5.1
struck 32 minutes later.
   Thirty percent of the buildings in the area collapsed and nearly
all the others sustained damage making them too dangerous to live
in, Li said.
   Provincial rescue workers arrived in the area during the night
but were confronted by a heavy snowfall. The area is between 6,600
and 9,900 feet above sea level, Li said.
   The quake's epicenter was near the Tianzhu Tibetan Autonomous
County, 124 miles northwest of the provincial capital of Lanzhou
and 750 miles west of Beijing. Aftershocks were felt as far away as
Lanzhou.
   Li said the area was not heavily populated.
   A severe earthquake last April hit an area less than 124 miles
away in neighboring Qinghai province, killing 126 people.
Aftershocks from that quake also were felt in Lanzhou.
   The Richter scale is an open-ended gauge of the energy released
by a quake, as measured by ground motion recorded on a seismograph.
An earthquake measuring 6 can cause extensive damage in a populated
area.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0011 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 0126EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Burma 1stLd-Writethru a0532 10-21 0639</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Burma, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0532,0749</SECOND>
<HEAD>Buddhist Monks Appear to Give in to Military Threats</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS throughout to UPDATE with monks reportedly preparing to
resume ministering to soldiers; no pickup.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By AYE AYE WIN</BYLINE>
<HEAD>Associated Press Writer</HEAD>
<DATELINE>RANGOON, Burma (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Burma's rebellious Buddhist monks, their
monasteries ringed by troops, appeared Sunday to have given in to
an ultimatum by the country's authoritarian rulers to end their
boycott of the military.
   Reports reaching the Burmese capital from Mandalay, the center
of the defiance campaign, said the monks would end their refusal to
minister to soldiers in a formal announcement later Sunday.
   Armed troops cordoned off Buddhist monasteries in the central
Burma city Saturday after the military government said it would
dissolve monks' groups involved in the boycott.
   A state radio announcement repeated throughout the day Saturday,
interspersed with martial music, said ``illegal'' monks'
organizations had been participating in politics, against the rules
of Buddhism.
   ``Such illegal organizations will be dissolved ... from
(midnight) tonight, and members of such illegal organizations are
not eligible to be members of the Sangha,'' Rangoon Radio said. The
Sangha is the main religious governing body in predominately
Buddhist Burma.
   At least six major Mandalay monasteries were surrounded by
troops and police and closed their gates.
   But witnesses contacted by telephone said the gates were opened
and monks came out on their morning alms rounds Sunday without
interference from the troops. Monks traditionally receive offerings
of food from the faithful in the early morning.
   It was not clear whether action would be taken against the
monks, who began their boycott after troops put down an
anti-government demonstration in Mandalay last August. The boycott
spread to other areas, including Rangoon, located 350 miles south
of Mandalay.
   Western observers in Rangoon said the monks refusal to minister
to the soldiers was ``the equivalent of excommunication.''
   The government said ``such organizations have jeopardized the
peace and stability of the country and threatened the breakup of
the central Sangha organization by various means, including
threats, blackmail and boycott.''
   A Western observer in Rangoon said any move against members of
the Sangha is ``bound to cause some kind of popular reaction.'' He
spoke by telephone and on condition of anonymity, like other
observers who commented on the situation.
   About 85 percent of Burma's 40 million people are Buddhist and
some 300,000 monks live in monasteries around the country. In
Buddhist societies, monks are regarded as spiritual leaders of the
community and also play a key role in popular celebrations and
various rites.
   Another Burma expert said the government is challenging Burma's
religious soul and going against traditions that revere the monks.
   ``It's going to be very difficult for the soldiers to fire on
the monks. If ordered to shoot, it will really bring into question
how reliant the soldiers are,'' said Josef Silverstein, a U.S.
political scientist in New Jersey.
   ``If they shoot defenseless monks who are only withholding
religious services as a moral weapon, there could be enormous
street protests. This is morality vs. weapons. What's left for
people whose vote has been rejected by the military?''
   The groups singled out by the government included the Young
Monks' Organization in Mandalay. On Sept. 6, the organization
announced a boycott of religious ceremonies for soldiers and their
families after troops broke up an anti-government protest in the
city a month earlier.
   During the Aug. 8 demonstration troops killed four people,
including two monks, according to Western diplomats in Rangoon.
   From Mandalay, in central Burma, the monks' boycott spread west
to the district of Monya and to some monasteries in the capital,
Rangoon, 350 miles south of Mandalay.
   Monks emerged at the head of anti-government protests during the
1988 pro-democracy uprising, in which the army killed thousands of
people.
   A Western source said about 160 monasteries in the capital have
taken up the protest, involving about 15,000 monks, a quarter of
those in the city. However, it appeared the boycott was most
widespread in Mandalay, where there are about 20,000 monks, he
said.
   Mandalay was a major center of unrest during the 1988 uprising
and monks took over the city administration for several weeks.
   The military government held a national election May 27 that was
easily won by the National League for Democracy, the main
opposition group. But the government has refused to hand over power
and has arrested the main opposition leaders.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0012 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 0254EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Israel 1stLd-Writethru a0533 10-21 0464</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0533,0560</SECOND>
<HEAD>Suspected Collaborator Slain in West Bank</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 4 grafs to UPDATE with three stabbing deaths on
Sunday; pickup 3rd graf pvs, `Assuming Halaf...'</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto XJRL1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ARIEH O'SULLIVAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A retired Palestinian high school principal was
found gagged, bound and stabbed to death Saturday in the occupied
West Bank, and Arab villagers said he was suspected of
collaborating with Israel.
   Three Israeli Jews, including a police officer, died in a
stabbing attack Sunday in a Jerusalem neighborhood, army radio
reported.
   The radio said police apprehended one suspect, but it was not
clear if he was an Arab or Jew. According to the radio, the
attacker first stabbed to death a woman in her 20s, then ran down a
major street and stabbed two other people, including the policeman.
   In the West Bank stabbing death, villagers said Musleh Halaf,
50, was kidnapped five days ago by four masked men in the main
street of Jenin. Halaf had been appointed a councilman by the
Israeli authorities but had resigned the post, villagers said.
   Assuming Halaf was slain as a collaborator, his death raised to
282 the number of Palestinians killed by fellow Arabs since
December 1987, when the uprising against Israeli rule began. Most
were killed on suspicion of working with Israeli authorities.
   Since the uprising began, 761 Palestinians have been killed by
Israeli soldiers or civilians, and 48 Israelis have died in the
violence.
   In Jerusalem, meanwhile, about 100 Israeli women urged
international intervention to protect Palestinians in the occupied
territories.
   The protest followed a decision by U.N. chief Javier Perez de
Cuellar not to send envoys to investigate the killings of at least
19 Palestinians in Jerusalem unless Israel changes its mind and
cooperates with the panel.
   More than 140 Palestinians were also wounded on Oct. 8, when
Israeli security forces fired on protesters on the Temple Mount.
The protesters had thrown rocks at Jews praying at the nearby
Western Wall. About 30 Israeli police and civilians were injured.
   The killings on the Mount, known to Moslems as Haram es-Sharif,
were condemned in a resolution passed unanimously by the U.N.
Security Council despite Israel's attempts to persuade its chief
ally, the United States, to veto it.
   The women, dressed in black and holding placards with slogans
opposing the Israeli occupation, held a silent vigil across from a
police prison in the center of town.
   Police had earlier barred the women from holding their vigil in
Arab east Jerusalem, saying it could incite violence. One woman was
arrested when she and others began shouting slogans.
   ``We have to demand pressure from outside because we've seen a
drastic swing to the right inside Israel and our effect is becoming
less and less,'' said Judy Green, who moved to Israel 10 years ago
from Little Rock, Ark.
   ``Most of us here believe that this occupation is destroying
Israel and is destroying the morality of Israelis,'' she added.
   Israel captured the West Bank and Gaza Strip from Jordan and
Egypt during the 1967 Middle East war.
   ``What we are asking for is some kind of odsend from outside to
shake this country back into its senses,'' said Ruth Cohen as she
held a poster reading: ``Down with the Occupation.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0013 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 0656EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i BC-Israel     10-21 0408</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Israel,0495</SECOND>
<HEAD>Arab Slays Three Israelis in Jerusalem Rampage</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ALLYN FISHER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An Arab wielding a long-bladed knife stabbed
three Israelis to death in a rampage through the streets of a quiet
Jerusalem neighborhood Sunday, police said.
   The 19-year-old construction worker from Bethlehem killed an
woman soldier in uniform, a gardener and an off-duty police officer
who shot him in both legs, Jerusalem Police Commander Aryeh Bibi
said.
   Witnesses heard him shouting ``Allahu Aqbar,'' or ``God is
Great,'' suggesting the attack stemmed from Moslem militancy. It
came 13 days after Israeli gunfire killed at least 19 Palestinians
during a riot on the hallowed Temple Mount.
   The rampage began just before 7 a.m. in the residential
neighborhood of Baka in southern Jerusalem, where the Arab was
employed on a construction job, Bibi told a news conference.
   First to fall victim was an 18-year-old soldier, followed by a
43-year-old man who was walking to his garden nursery carrying
plants, authorities said.
   The attacker then stabbed a 13-year-old boy, slightly injuring
him in his arm, chest and head with his 16-inch blade, police said.
   A 28-year-old officer of the police force's anti-terrorism unit
heard screams and ran out of his house chasing the Arab, Bibi said.
   He said the officer fired two warning shots from his 9mm pistol,
then shot him once in each leg, but the attacker lunged at him and
stabbed him in the chest.
   The attacker was being questioned, Bibi said. He and the dead
Israelis were not immediately identified.
   The wounded boy, Amikam Kovner, was being treated at Hadassah
Ein Karem Hospital.
   The Arab was caught by Baka Jews who turned him over to the
police, Israel radio said.
   Bibi said police reinforcements were ``streaming into the city''
to prevent further attacks and patrol the streets to head off
Jewish acts of vengeance. Israel radio said 2,000 extra police were
being mobilized.
   Bibi appealed for calm, but enraged Baka Jews swarmed into the
streets and attacked at least one Arab laborer who had to be
rescued by police, Israel radio said. They also poured kerosene
into a car belonging to an Arab they said tried to run over a group
of Jews, but did not manage to start a fire, the radio said.
   Baka was an Arab neighborhood until Israel gained control of the
western sector of Jerusalem in the 1948 Arab-Israeli war. It is now
populated by Jews, with a scattering of Arab families who did not
join the 1948 Palestinian exodus from Israel.
   The Temple Mount riots have reignited the flagging Palestinian
uprising in the territories Israel captured in the 1967 Middle East
War.
   During the 34-month uprising, 761 Palestinians have been killed
by Israeli soldiers or civilians, and 282 byf fellow Arabs, most on
suspicion of collaborating with Israel. Before Sunday, at least 48
Israelis had died in the violence.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0014 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 0718EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i BC-Lebanon 1stLd-Writethru a0653 10-21 0376</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Lebanon, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0653,0439</SECOND>
<HEAD>Staunch Aoun Supporter and Wife and two children Slain</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 3 grafs to ADD that Aoun remains in French
Embassy; pickup 3rd graf pvs, `Police said...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By RODEINA KENAAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BAABDA, Lebanon (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Five uniformed gunmen on Sunday shot to
death a staunch supporter of ousted Gen. Michel Aoun and his wife
and two small sons at their home east of Beirut, police said.
   The identities of the gunmen were not known and there was no
immediate claim of responsibility for the slaying of Dany Chamoun,
son of the late President Camille Chamoun.
   The slayings came a week after Syrian and government troops of
President Elias Hrawi's army crushed Aoun's mutiny in Lebanon's
Christian heartland. Aoun remains in the French Embssy, where he
sought asylum when his forces were attacked.
   Police said the assailants, using 9mm pistols equipped with
silencers, riddled the Chamouns with bullets in their fifth-floor
apartment in the hilltop suburb of Baabda.
   Chamoun, 56, Ingrid Abdel-Noor and their son Tarek, 7, died
instantly. The other son, Julien, 5, was taken to a nearby hospital
where he died 15 minutes after admission, police said.
   The Christian leader's 11-month-old daughter, Tamara, escaped
unharmed. Reporters saw her held by her weeping governess at the
Chamoun apartment.
   The assassins arrived in two cars at the entrance to the
nine-story building at 6 a.m. while four guards assigned to protect
the Chamoun family were changing shifts, police said.
   Chamoun, a Maronite Catholic, was one of the most outspoken
critics of Hrawi and Syria's military presence in Lebanon.
   Chamoun inherited the leadership of the righist Christian
National Liberal Party in 1987 upon the death of his father, who
ruled Lebanon from 1952 to 1958.
   The younger Chamoun sought the presidency in 1988, when former
President Amin Gemayel's term expired.
   But parliament was unable to meet to elect a successor and
Gemayel appointed Aoun - who then was army commander - as prime
minister of a caretaker military cabinet until a new president was
elected.
   Hrawi was elected president Nov. 24, 1989, but Aoun rejected
that election on grounds it was held in Syrian-controlled
territory. Aoun contended that his three-man cabinet remained the
only legitimate authority in the country.
   Chamoun, who sided with Aoun, was dismayed when Aoun fled his
command headquarters in the presidential palace in Baabda minutes
after the air-supported attack of Hrawi's troops and the Syrian
army began Oct 13.
   ``I can't believe the general has done this to us,'' Chamoun
said the next day. ``May God help us.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0015 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 1142EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--Italy-Kidnap     10-21 0138</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Italy-Kidnap,0134</SECOND>
<HEAD>Wealthy Property Owner Kidnapped in Sardinia</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CAGLIARI, Sardinia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Police set up roadblocks across this
Italian island Sunday to search for three masked gunmen who
kidnapped a wealthy property owner.
   Giovanni Murgia, 42, was abducted Saturday night as he and a
friend emerged from a small house on one of his properties outside
Cagliari.
   Police said the kidnappers tied the couple up and drove off with
them in the woman's car. The woman was later released, and the
kidnappers headed off with Murgia in another car.
   There was no immediate word on whether the kidnappers had made
contact with Murgia's family.
   Murgia is one of seven Italians in the hands of kidnappers.
Kidnapping for ransom is especially common in Sardinia, where the
mountainous interior offers ideal hideouts.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0016 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 1142EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--Japan-Stabbing     10-21 0143</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Japan-Stabbing,0139</SECOND>
<HEAD>Former Labor Minister Stabbed at Military Ceremony</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A former mental patient wielding a kitchen knife on
Sunday stabbed an official from the governing party as he walked to
a ceremony at a military base, police said.
   The former labor minister, Hyosuke Niwa, was in a coma Sunday
night, said officials at Aiichi Medical University Hospital.
   Niwa, 78, a Liberal Democratic Party parliamentarian, was
attacked at the Moriyama military base in Nagoya, about 170 miles
west of Tokyo.
   The assailant was identified as a 47-year-old mental patient. He
was immediately apprehended.
   A police official, speaking on condition of anonymity, said the
attacker told investigators he recognized Niwa and ``was trying to
kill anyone who is a member of Parliament.''
   Police refused to disclose the name of the assailant.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0017 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 1146EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--Neo-Nazis     10-21 0155</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Neo-Nazis,0150</SECOND>
<HEAD>Neo-Nazis Demonstrate in Southeast Germany</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hundreds of Nazi sympathizers shouted ``Foreigners
out!'' and anti-Communist slogans in a march in the southeastern
city of Dresden, the news agency ADN reported.
   There were no reports of any violence Saturday night as the
protesters snaked through the center of Dresden, a former East
German city 110 miles southeast of Berlin.
   Police estimated that about 350 neo-Nazis took part in the
demonstration, ADN reported. It took place without permission of
city authorities, the agency said.
   The march was led by Michael Kuehnen, a well-known pro-Nazi
activist, the agency said.
   Small groups of neo-Nazis have emerged in the eastern part of
Germany since the Berlin Wall fell a year ago. German leaders have
warned that pro-fascist sentiments, which were suppressed by the
former Communist government, must not be allowed to develop in the
newly united country.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0018 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 1158EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SriLanka     10-21 0319</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Sri Lanka,0363</SECOND>
<HEAD>Troops Kill 20 Rebels in Capturing Strategic Village</HEAD>
<DATELINE>COLOMBO, Sri Lanka (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Government troops captured a strategic
coastal village in northern Sri Lanka, killing 20 Tamil rebels in
an air, naval and ground operation, officials said Sunday.
   The reported capture of Mawaddipuram village on Saturday opened
a passage to Kankesanthurai, a vital, rebel-controlled port one
mile away.
   There was no immediate response to the government claim from the
rebel militia, the Liberation Tigers of Tamil Eelam.
   Military officials, who cannot be identified under briefing
rules, said three soldiers were killed and many more were injured
in the taking of Mawaddipuram, 195 miles north of Colombo.
   They said 20 rebels were killed but did not give further details
of the fighting.
   With Mawaddipuram's capture, the military now claims to control
a wide swath of the western coast in the Jaffna peninsula, a mainly
Tamil area and a rebel stronghold.
   The military launched the offensive in the peninsula, the
northernmost part of the island, on Wednesday. By Saturday, it
claimed to control at least eight rebel camps.
   Officials said more than 100 militants and 14 soldiers had been
killed in fighting until Saturday. The militia disputed the claim.
   Rebel leader Lawrence Thilaker said on Friday that 50 soldiers
and 15 militants were killed.
   Both sides are known to have made exaggerated claims of the toll
in the past. The latest report could not be independently confirmed
because communication with the north is cut off.
   Fighting is also going on in the east, where troops killed six
rebels after ferreting them out of a hideout in Kirankulam village
Saturday, military officials said.
   The latest round of civil war started in August, ending a
13-month cease-fire in the seven-year-old insurrection for a
separate Tamil homeland in the north and the east. More than 14,000
people have been killed.
   The separatist demand stems from the militants' complaint that
the island's Sinhalese majority discriminates against the Tamils in
jobs and education.
   Sinhalese comprise 75 percent of Sri Lanka's 16 million people
and control the government and the army. Tamils account for 18
percent.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0019 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 1202EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--BangladeshProtes     10-21 0142</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Bangladesh Protest,0126</SECOND>
<HEAD>Thousands Hold Anti-Government Demonstrations</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DHAKA, Bangladesh (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Thousands of demonstrators held rallies
and anti-government marches Sunday to press demands for President
Hussain Muhammad Ershad to resign and hold elections under a
caretaker government.
   Riot police backed by paramilitary forces were deployed in key
points in the capital, Dhaka, but did not intervene.
   The nationwide demonstrations, which have been held periodically
since Erhsad assumed power in a bloodless coup in 1982, intensified
after eight protesters were killed in Dhaka in clashes with police
on Oct. 10 and 13.
   Nasim Ahmed, a senior leader of the opposition Awami League
party, claimed that processions held in major cities drew hundreds
of thousands of activists. A senior police officer said the
protests were peaceful.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0020 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 1208EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Pakistan-Elections Bjt   10-21 0659</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Pakistan-Elections, Bjt,0798</SECOND>
<HEAD>Will The Army Let Benazir Bhutto Return to Power?</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY7</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SHARON HERBAUGH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ISLAMABAD, Pakistan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Benazir Bhutto's opponents might bar
her from office even if she gets the most votes in next week's
election, or she could let them take over and risk political
disaster in the economic crunch ahead.
   ``It's not everything that I be prime minister,'' Ms. Bhutto
told a reporter during a break in the campaign.
   ``Why should I raise prices by 40 percent, which is what they
said they'll have to do after the elections? They'll have egg on
their faces and we'll come back smiling next March. They won't last
six months.''
   Economists say Pakistan is in for hard times because of a large
debt, dwindling reserves, higher oil prices and a sharp decline in
exports.
   Whether Ms. Bhutto will be permitted to resume office has been a
nagging question ever since she was ousted Aug. 6.
   President Ghulam Ishaq Khan used his constitutional power to
dismiss her 20-month-old government on charges of corruption and
abuse of power. He called elections three years ahead of schedule.
   Suspicion has grown that martial law will be declared to keep
Ms. Bhutto out of power, although top generals deny it. The army
and the president wouldn't kick her out just to let her return
three months later, the argument goes.
   After 11 weeks of name-calling and nearly a dozen unresolved
court cases, 50 million voters will be eligible to deliver their
verdict Wednesday.
   Despite increasing economic and social problems in this Moslem
nation of 110 million people, Ms. Bhutto has been the only campaign
issue.
   Her Pakistan People's Party and its smaller allies are pitted
against the Islamic Democratic Alliance, a loose coalition spanning
the ideological spectrum and united only by opposition to Ms.
Bhutto.
   At stake are 217 seats in the National Assembly, the law-making
lower house of Parliament that elects the prime minister.
   Pakistani campaigns usually are noisy, but this one has been
relatively quiet, reflecting the cycnicism of an electorate that
has seen too many promises broken and democracy derailed too many
times in the country's 43-year history.
   Few disagree that Ms. Bhutto's administration was disappointing.
   Her inexperience and alleged widespread corruption in her
administration drained the large reservoir of goodwill that made
her the first woman to lead a modern Moslem nation.
   More than anything, both critics and supporters say, her
downfall stemmed from growing reliance on middlemen and a policy of
giving party supporters jobs, contracts and other rewards.
   ``We made mistakes, no doubt about it,'' Ms. Bhutto said in the
interview. ``Any government is going to have differences of
perceptions, but it's in the national interest that they be
resolved.''
   Getting her out of office was easy enough, but the president and
caretaker government made serious miscalculations afterward.
   Ms. Bhutto, 37, was dragged from court to court in an attempt to
prove she was Pakistan's most corrupt and incompetent leader. Her
husband and dozens of supporters were arrested on what they claimed
were trumped-up charges.
   Her opponents portrayed her as a bad Moslem, a traitor who gave
state secrets to India and sympathized with Israel.
   Their main accomplishment was to deflect attention from Ms.
Bhutto's dismal record, revive memories of the military overthrow
in 1977 and subsequent execution of her father, Prime Minister
Zulfikar Ali Bhutto, and cast her as the martyr.
   Her opponents were plagued by internal rivalries, and growing
impatience in the military indicated things weren't going as the
generals had planned.
   Most analysts predict neither side will win a decisive majority,
giving the civilian and military establishment room to form a
coalition government that will keep Ms. Bhutto out of power.
   Still, her political organization could emerge as the largest
single party, as in November 1988.
   Analysts predict the Pakistan People's Party will sweep Sindh,
the former prime minister's home province, and possibly win Punjab,
her opponents' stronghold and the largest and most populous
province.
   The party has been perceived as the party of the poor and
downtrodden since Ms. Bhutto's father founded it nearly 30 years
ago. Ms. Bhutto inherited his mass support.
   She still faces the threat of disqualification because of the
half-dozen court cases pending against her.
   Ms. Bhutto predicted the caretaker government would make a
last-ditch attempt to pressure the special tribunals to exclude her
from politics.
   Even if they succeed, she said, there is still her mother to
contend with.
   ``These little guys think it's that easy to get rid of the
Bhuttos?'' she asked with a grin. ``They shouldn't forget the name
Begum Nusrat Bhutto.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0021 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 1217EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-Suez Bjt   10-21 0697</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Suez, Bjt,0885</SECOND>
<HEAD>Gulf Crisis Proves Again: War's Bad for Business at Suez Canal</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MIMI MANN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ISMAILIYA, Egypt (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   War and rumors of war are bad for
business at the Suez Canal.
   When politics get sticky, revenues go down. In the waning weeks
of 1990, politics are sticky indeed.
   ``When the world is happy, the Suez Canal is happy; when things
go wrong somewhere else, they go bad here,'' said Capt. Adel Abdel
Salam, the canal's chief pilot.
   Oil, the black gold of the Middle East, has been the savior and
bankroll of the Suez Canal since the late 1940s.
   As the strategic connection between Western oil consumers and
Middle Eastern oil producers, the canal felt an immediate impact
when Iraq seized Kuwait on Aug. 2.
   Warships steaming to and from the Persian Gulf keep the waterway
busy, but they don't pay much money. Tankers ferrying oil to Europe
pay a lot, but fewer are coming through.
   Egypt, debt-ridden and deeply involved in the gulf crisis,
desperately needs the dollars the canal should be providing.
   Its most lucrative revenue source is the paychecks sent home by
Egyptians abroad. That is dwindling with the return of about
350,000 workers from the gulf, many of them penniless.
   The assassination of a leading Egyptian politician Oct. 12 in
downtown Cairo devastated an already reeling tourist industry.
Until Aug. 2, tourism was Egypt's second-best source of money.
   For ordinary Egyptians, a problem at the Suez Canal is a
personal misfortune. They view it as a monument to national pride,
much as ancient Egyptians viewed the pyramids and Sphinx.
   ``We dug the canal with our lives, our skulls, our bones, our
blood,'' President Gamal Abdel Nasser said in announcing on July
26, 1956, that Egypt was taking the canal from a British-French
concession.
   The United States had little interest in the canal until its
troops found themselves defending North Africa in World War II.
Afterward, a burgeoning consumer society demanded more oil, ores
and rubber from the East, and they came cheaper via Suez.
   Trouble never has been far from the 101-mile-long ditch linking
the Mediterranean and Red Seas via Egypt's Bitter Lakes and the
Gulf of Suez.
   As many as 20,000 laborers are thought to have died digging the
canal, which was inaugurated in 1869 in an orgy of opulence that
nearly bankrupted the country.
   During the 20th century, Suez often has been at or near the
center of conflict.
   Russian warships passed through it in 1905 en route to
catastrophic defeat by the Japanese off Korea. In World War I,
German U-boats tried to sever England from its colonies east of
Suez by keeping cargo ships from using the canal.
   In 1939, Italian dictator Benito Mussolini used it as a pathway
to conquer Ethiopia.
   Field Marshal Erwin Rommel, Germany's World War II military
genius, was unable to capture the canal and the Persian oil fields
beyond. Germany bombed it 64 times, stopping traffic for 76 days.
   Ships sunk during Egypt's 1967 war with Israel blocked all
traffic for eight years.
   Canal business soured during the 1980s because of the Iraq-Iran
wqar, in which hundreds of oil tankers were attacked in the Persian
Gulf.
   For Egypt, which owns the canal, Iraq's invasion of Kuwait was
far more than a problem between Arab brothers.
   Both countries were good customers of Suez, each year shipping
seven million tons of oil westward. The U.N. embargo ended that.
   Oil that would have passed through the canal to Europe is being
consumed east of Suez by forces sent to confront Iraq.
   Through August, the canal's monthly tanker tonnage averaged more
than 13.5 million tons. In September, the first full month under
embargo, the tonnage was 11 million.
   ``War makes civilization go faster, but on the Suez Canal,
things slow down,'' said Abdel Salam, the chief pilot.'' ``It's not
devastating . . . but yes, we're suffering.''
   How much became evident in September. Ezzat Adel, chairman of
the Suez Canal Authority, said the gulf trouble ould cost $400
million in the fiscal year that started a month before the
invasion. In 1989, canal revenues brought the government nearly
$1.4 billion.
   The crisis brings into focus two persistent irritants for the
Canal Authority: neutrality and nuclear ships.
   Under the 1888 Constantinople Convention, the Suez Canal must
accept all ships, but Egypt interprets one clause as allowing it to
deny access to those likely to endanger Egypt's security.
   That was the basis of a ban on ships flying Israel's flag until
1979, when Egypt signed a peace treaty with the Jewish state, and
on vessels either carrying nuclear weapons or powered by nuclear
energy.
   Iraqi ships now use the canal despite Egypt's strong anti-Iraq
position in the gulf crisis. If war began, Egypt probably would ban
them.
   The nuclear ban is so politically sensitive that nobody will
talk about it.
   In August, as the United States built up its forces to face
Iraq, the nuclear-powered aircraft carrier Dwight D. Eisenhower
passed through the canal to the Red Sea, then returned two weeks
later.
   Egypt did not ask about the carrier's propulsion system.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0022 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 1217EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ChessClub Bjt   10-21 0548</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Chess Club, Bjt,0687</SECOND>
<HEAD>Chess Buffs Follow Their Masters In World Championship</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY6</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PAUL GEITNER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The two greatest minds in chess sit on the stage
in a newly refurbished theater near Times Square, agonizing over
each move in absolute silence.
   But just a short walk uptown, about 30 chess aficionados of all
stripes are gathered in a cramped, run-down lecture room,
second-guessing each move the masters make as the thump-thump-thump
from a nearby exercise studio reverberates through the open
windows.
   ``Is Karpov really taking this long, or is it the computer?''
asks one woman as they wait for the next move to be relayed from
the theater to their board at the Manhattan Chess Club.
   ``That's a very old opening,'' someone else complains. ``Can't
they come up with something original?''
   As world champion Garry Kasparov battles Anatoly Karpov in the
World Series of chess, hard-core fans are getting nearly
instantaneous play-by-play analysis at chess clubs across the
country.
   Game 5 of the best-of-24 World Chess Championship series will be
held Monday, after Kasparov took one of his three allowed timeouts
Friday. Karpov used one of his timeouts after losing game 2. The
other three games ended in draws, making the score Kasparov 2{,
Karpov 1{.
   The two are playing for the crown and the winner's share of a $3
million purse. The first 12 games will be in New York; the rest in
Lyons, France.
   Watching the match at a club with a direct link to the Hudson
Theater, where the series began Oct. 8, is the next best thing to
being there, maybe better, fans say.
   Talking is encouraged at the clubs, and most have arranged for
grandmasters to explain the intricate strategies as each game
unfolds.
   ``Here you can ask questions,'' said Ruth Cardoso, an
international master from Brazil. ``Sometimes it's a stupid
question. But you get an answer.''
   It's cheaper, too. Tickets to the match run up to $100 a game,
while the show at the Manhattan Chess Club is free for members, $10
to non-members.
   The world championship is played every three years, but this one
is an especially intense grudge match.
   Karpov is trying to regain the title that Kasparov, the
highest-rated player in the history of chess, won from him in 1985.
   ``Everybody's excited, even though it's only two Russians
playing each other,'' said grand master Pal Benko, who provided
commentary for Game 4 last week at the 113-year-old chess club.
``No American like Bobby Fischer'' - a club member from the 1950s.
   The Game 4 crowd, mostly men, included players of all levels.
Retired computer programmers sat next to long-haired students in
jeans and carrying backpacks. Businessmen in well-tailored suits
outnumbered the stereotypical ``chess nerds'' in plaid polyester
jackets.
   Almost everybody is holding his or her own mini-chessboard or
writing down the moves as they are announced in chess notation.
   ``Entertainment is part of it, but it's a different kind of
entertainment,'' said Russ Garber, the club's director.
   ``People like to be able to say, `I predicted that Kasparov
would play this move.' So they feel like, `I, too, can think like a
world champion.' ... It's an ego thing.''
   On the wall at the front of the room is a 6-by-6-foot chessboard
with magnetic pieces. Benko stands at the front and rearranges the
markers, sometimes even before the computer operator runs in with a
new move.
   ``I put already the bishop here,'' he says. ``I know the next
move.''
   He's right.
   White's pawn looks vulnerable.
   ``Can he take it, or is it a trap?'' someone asks.
   Benko explores several possibilities before deciding it's not a
trap.
   For most, nothing can match the excitement of watching the two
best players in the world - not computer glitches, shabby
surroundings or dance music pulsating loudly outside.
   ``Chess is a religion to some of us,'' said Bruce Albertson, a
national master. ``This is what we wait for.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0023 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 1220EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-AssaultbyAIDS Bjt   10-21 0641</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Assault by AIDS, Bjt,720</SECOND>
<HEAD>Charges Increasing in AIDS Assault Cases</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By W. DALE NELSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An increasing number of states now have laws
that make it a crime to knowingly expose another person to the AIDS
virus.
   Since 1986, 22 states have passed laws making it illegal to
engage in conduct that could transmit the human immunodeficiency
virus, or HIV, believed to cause acquired immune deficiency
syndrome, according to the AIDS Policy Center at George Washington
University.
   ``The idea of trying to prosecute somebody for attempted
transmission of HIV is increasingly, almost alarmingly, common,''
said Lawrence O. Gostin, director of the AIDS Litigation Project of
the U.S. Public Health Service and a professor at the Harvard
University School of Public Health.
   But, he said, ``when somebody is actually having sex with
somebody, I think the risk is significant enough that prosecutors
are well within their rights to prosecute.''
   While the number of AIDS-related prosecutions nationwide is not
known, the military seems to be having the best success with such
cases, the experts say.
   Last week the Supreme Court rejected without comment an appeal
by Nathaniel Johnson Jr., an Air Force sergeant who was convicted
in a military court of aggravated assault because he had homosexual
relations at McChord Air Force Base, Wash., while knowingly
infected with the virus.
   The Air Force Court of Military Review said at least six
previous courts-martial had been convened based upon AIDS-related
assaults. Such conduct, it said, ``can be analogized to attempting
to put poison in the drink of a victim.''
   The outcomes in civilian courts so far have tended to be
different, Gostin said.
   ``It is enormously problematical to try to reach into the
bedroom and create a criminal prosecution around it, and the only
ones who have been successful in doing that are the military,''
Gostin said.
   Part of reason is because most civilian cases involve biting,
spitting or splashing blood rather than intercourse.
   ``It is virtually impossible - if not impossible - to transmit
the virus that way,'' Gostin said. ``It appears to me to be much
more punitive than effectuating any clear public policy.''
   ``Most of the cases of (infected) men sleeping with people are
military cases,'' said Gostin, who is also executive director of
the American Society of Law and Medicine. ``Often the charge is
willful disobedience of a military order. Sometimes it is assault
or even attempted murder.
   ``In civil court it is very difficult to get a conviction on
those kinds of cases,'' he said. ``If your intention is to kill
somebody else, having sex with them is a highly indirect modus
operandi.''
   Gostin said most cases in the state courts are brought under
general criminal laws rather than specific AIDS-related
legislation. He said he had not found one such case in which HIV
was transmitted.
   James R. Klimaski, a Washington lawyer who specializes in
ilitary law, said the military has an easier time with sexual
cases because it is a much more controlled environment.
   The Defense Department and each service have regulations
governing sexual conduct by service people who know they are
infected with the AIDS virus.
   Under Navy policy, a sailor found to have the virus is given
counseling and ordered to avoid unsafe sexual practices, said Lt.
Beci Brenton, a Navy public affairs officer.
   The sailor signs a statement saying he understands the order,
and any violation is prosecuted as disobeying a commanding officer.
   In Johnson's case, he was dishonorably discharged and sentenced
to six years in prison. His lawyers contend he was never told about
an Air Force policy that HIV-infected military members could be
subjected to disciplinary action for engaging in unsafe sex.
   But Klimaski said it had become ``pretty settled law'' that
knowingly having unprotected sex while HIV-infected can be
prosecuted as assault under the Uniform Code of Military Justice.
   According to the Aids Policy Center, intentionally exposing
someone to the virus is a felony in Arkansas, California, Colorado,
Delaware, Florida, Georgia, Idaho, Illinois, Indiana, Kentucky,
Michigan, Missouri, Ohio, Oklahoma, South Carolina, Texas and
Virginia.
   It is a misdemeanor in Alabama and Maryland. The center said
Nevada, Mississippi and Louisiana passed similar laws without
specifying whether the offense was a felony or misdemeanor.
   The laws vary as to the circumstances in which they apply.
   AIDS attacks the body's immune system, leaving victims
susceptible to a wide variety of infections and cancers. It is most
often transmitted through sexual contact, mostly between homosexual
males.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0024 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 1220EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--HospitalFire     10-21 0187</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Hospital Fire,0190</SECOND>
<HEAD>Medical Research Lost In Hospital Blaze</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Fire swept through a hospital wing early Sunday,
destroying five years of research on muscle disorders and causing
damage estimated at more than $1 million, officials said.
   Sixty firefighters prevented the blaze at Hammersmith Hospital
in west London from spreading to the wards and the adjacent
emergency department.
   Nurses, police and ambulance crews alerted by automatic fire
alarms moved 46 patients, some bedridden, from three wards as smoke
from the research department on the top floor of one wing filled
the hospital.
   One patient suffered from smoke inhalation and was transferred
to Charing Cross Hospital, where he was reported to be ``quite
satisfactory.''
   Police said they are treating the fire, which started in the
unoccupied research wing, as suspicious. Fire crews took 2{ hours
to bring it under control.
   Pioneering research into muscle disorders, led by Professor
Victor Dubowitz and funded by the Muscular Dystrophy Group, had
been carried out in the laboratory.
   Hospital general manager Paul Herbage said: ``The whole area has
been destroyed. Five years of research has been lost.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0025 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 1247EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p AM-FudgeFactor     10-21 0619</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Fudge Factor,740</SECOND>
<HEAD>Who's Hiding Their True Views; Which Way Will They Really Vote?</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Florida Governor Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JILL LAWRENCE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Harvey Gantt isn't worried about watching a
large lead evaporate on Election Day. He doesn't have one.
   Other black candidates have seen their comfortable cushions
vanish at the polls. But Gantt, the black former mayor of
Charlotte, N.C., says his dead-heat race against Republican Sen.
Jesse Helms is different. He maintains he's the one with hidden
support among white voters.
   ``Everybody keeps saying don't you think you need a 15-point
lead because people are going to lie to pollsters,'' said Gantt's
press secretary, Susan Jetton. ``No. Because why would somebody who
voted for Jesse Helms three times in the past lie about voting for
him a fourth time?''
   It's more likely, under the Gantt camp's theory, that a white
rural conservative voter would feel uncomfortable telling people he
supports Gantt - so he'd say Helms but pull the Gantt lever.
   ``We're not worried about the fudge factor,'' Jetton said. ``Any
fudge factor on one side might be balanced by a fudge factor on the
other side.''
   The fudge factor can be defined as a poll respondent's tendency
to hide out in the undecided column or give an answer that's
socially acceptable but dishonest.
   It was illustrated last year by the elections for Virginia
governor and New York City mayor. Black candidates won both races,
but only by fractions of the margins they were expected to get.
   Neil Newhouse, a Republican poll-taker, said it would be a
mistake to assume that all pre-election polls involving minority
candidates are unreliable.
   ``I don't think it's correct to try to extrapolate what happened
in two polarized races - black vs. white, abortion vs.
anti-abortion ... to Cincinnati, Ohio or Waterbury, Conn.,'' he
said. Black Republicans are running for House seats in those two
cities.
   Newhouse predicted race would play little or no role in the two
contests, particularly the heated Cincinnati competition between
Democratic Mayor Charles Luken and former Mayor Kenneth Blackwell,
who is black.
   ``He's been elected city-wide. He has a track record,'' Newhouse
said of Blackwell. ``I'm positive you're not going to see any kind
of turnoff by white voters.''
   In Connecticut, former Democratic congressman Toby Moffett is in
a competitive race with black Republican Gary Franks, an alderman
from Waterbury.
   White voter turnoff was behind last year's unexpectedly narrow
wins for Virginia Gov. L. Douglas Wilder and New York Mayor David
Dinkins. Wilder had a 9-point lead in the polls and won by a
half-point, while Dinkins was ahead 16 points in voter surveys and
won by 4 points.
   Another variation of the fudge factor was evident this year in
strong showings by two unconventional primary candidates considered
socially unacceptable in some circles.
   Outspoken Democrat John Silber won his party's gubernatorial
nomination in Massachusetts by a 9-point margin though polls showed
his opponent with an 11-point lead. And ex-Klansman David Duke
garnered 44 percent of the vote in the Louisiana Senate primary -
not enough to win but far greater than the 26 percent indicated in
the last major poll before the election.
   Undecided voters tilted to Duke and Silber, swelling their vote
totals. In contrast, virtually all of those who were undecided
right before the New York and Virginia elections shunned Dinkins
and Wilder in favor of their white opponents.
   That would ordinarily spell bad news for Gantt, since the
undecided voters who will determine the tight North Carolina race
are almost all white.
   But Geoff Garin, a Democratic pollster, said his research in
North Carolina indicates there is some reason for Gantt to believe
he can get an even break on the undecided vote there.
   ``The undecided voters in North Carolina are not secret Helms
voters,'' he said. ``They are people who don't like Jesse Helms and
haven't figured out exactly what to do.''
   Helms, an outspoken conservative, has hammered at Gantt for his
``extreme liberal values'' and criticizes his support for a women's
right to an abortion. Gantt depicts Helms as an ideologue who votes
against the interests of his state, particularly on education and
the environment.
   Helms pleads with his supporters, meanwhile, to help him out of
``the fix I'm in'' by turning out to vote in large numbers. Said a
key Helms adviser, Carter Wrenn: ``It's looking right now like
that's going to be the deciding factor.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0026 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 1253EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-DepressionProgram Bjt   10-21 0571</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Depression Program, Bjt,0684</SECOND>
<HEAD>One-Day Depression Program Points Sufferers Toward Help</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT W. TROTT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>QUINCY, Mass. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   June recently lost a relative, and her
sorrow would not abate. Then she read an article about a hospital's
daylong program on depression, and found herself among 150
neighbors in need of help.
   Douglas G. Jacobs of Quincy Psychiatric Associates said his
unusual session, which he hopes will be a model for programs
nationwide, provided potent evidence of the wide reach of
depression.
   In fact, three of the people who came to the free session held
earlier this month at Quincy City Hospital were immediately
hospitalized because ``they were in the midst of a suicidal
crisis.''
   Jacobs was concerned but not surprised. He said statistics show
fewer than 30 percent of depressed people ever get help. Although
most people who do seek counseling can recover in six to nine
months, the recovery period involves severe bouts of stress and
disruption at home and work.
   Fifteen percent don't recover; they commit suicide, Jacobs said.
   ``At any time, 7{ (million) to 10 million people suffer from
depression,'' Jacobs said. ``Many depressions go unrecognized, and
the ultimate loss is suicide. We're trying to encourage people to
identify depression in themselves.''
   Jacobs, a psychologist who specializes in suicide research, has
been on the Harvard Medical School faculty for 12 years. He
developed the idea of the one-day program at the hospital as a way
to familiarize people with the symptoms of depression and to
encourage treatment.
   ``This is not a substitute for a psychiatric evaluation. This is
to learn about depression, to learn about the signs and symptoms,''
Jacobs said. ``I'm going to propose this to be conducted statewide
and perhaps nationally. That will take a lot of planning.''
   About 15 participants in the session contacted him or another
mental health professional for follow-up treatment, and in all,
``at least 50 percent could have benefited from treatment,'' Jacobs
said.
   Mental health professionals say doctors need to be more familiar
with the symptoms of depression, which often manifests itself
physically.
   Many have depressed patients and don't know it, said Melvin
Sabshin, medical director for the American Psychiatric Association
in Washington.
   ``A lot of people who have depression start with physical
symptoms,'' said Sabshin. ``Loss of sleep, physical problems of
other kinds - fatigue, general lack of energy, headaches, gastric
problems. They suffer from sexual problems, too.''
   Jacobs called the APA for some guidance on the program, and the
national organization couldn't name a similar endeavor.
   ``The program that (Jacobs) had in Quincy was excellent,''
Sabshin said last week. ``It could be a prototype that we could
consider for a program on a national basis.''
   Every October, the APA promotes National Mental Awareness Week.
Sabshin said once he receives Jacobs' data and discusses the
program with his 75 district branches, a national program may be
established next fall.
   The one-day session in this city just south of Boston consisted
of three, two-hour sessions including a half-hour lecture by
Jacobs, a videotape of depressed people discussing their condition,
informational literature, and a questionnaire. Each participant
also got a brief session with a counselor.
   The set of questions wasn't the kind of test you wanted to pass,
but June, who asked that her real name not be used, joked about it.
   ``It was a very good questionnaire,'' she said. ``Unfortunately,
I did pretty well because of my bereavement. I'm still going
through the grief process.''
   June realizes that the loss of a loved one is an unavoidable
part of life. But people often need help accepting and coping with
such inevitabilities.
   ``I had gone to two counselors, but I felt I needed more help,''
she said. ``Some people have depression all of their life and they
don't always know it.''
   Jacobs stressed that programs such as the one at Quincy City
Hospital aren't the long-term solution to depression. But in a
world of disappointments of varying degrees, every bit helps.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0027 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 1258EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Burma     10-21 0493</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Burma,0551</SECOND>
<HEAD>Monks, Under Threat, End Boycott Against Soldiers</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By AYE AYE WIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>RANGOON, Burma (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Rebellious Buddhist monks on Sunday ended
a boycott on ministering to soldiers after government troops
surrounded their monasteries. Defiant monks were also threatened
with death.
   Reports reaching the capital, Rangoon, from Mandalay, center of
the defiance campaign, said the monks ended their boycott after
troops ringed at least six major monasteries.
   The monks' apparent capitulation also came as Burma's prime
minister, Gen. Saw Maung, gave army commanders the power under
martial law to bring monks before military tribunals for activities
deemed disruptive to Buddhism, official Rangoon Radio said.
   Sentences dispensed by such tribunals range from a minimum of
three years in prison to a maximum of death.
   Monks emerged at the forefront of anti-government protests
during a 1988 pro-democracy uprising that the army crushed, killing
thousands of people.
   Burma held free elections in May, which were easily won by the
National League for Democracy, the main opposition group. But the
military government has refused to hand over power and arrested the
main opposition leaders.
   The state radio said 29 monks attended a ceremony Sunday in
Mandalay formally ending the boycott. Nearly 200 monks in Rangoon
also withdrew in writing their support of the boycott, according to
the broadcast.
   Mandalay is Burma's second-largest city and its religious
center.
   Rangoon Radio said one monk had persuaded an unnamed political
party to press for a speedy transfer of power in Burma and
organized monks to overthrow the government. It said he had
confessed under interrogation to his political activities.
   The state radio broadcast a decree that accused members of
illegal monks' organizations of ``engaging in activities that
disrupt the purification, perpetuation and propagation of
Buddhism.''
   ``Commanders ... have been empowered to investigate, expose and
take effective action against such people,'' it said.
   Armed troops cordoned off Buddhist monasteries in Mandalay, in
central Burma, on Saturday.
   A state radio announcement repeated throughout the day Saturday,
interspersed with martial music, said ``illegal'' monks'
organizations had been participating in politics.
   ``Such illegal organizations will be dissolved ... from
(midnight) tonight, and members of such illegal organizations are
not eligible to be members of the Sangha,'' Rangoon Radio said. The
Sangha is the main religious governing body in Burma, a
predominately Buddhist country.
   The government said the illegal monks' groups have ``jeopardized
the peace and stability of the country and threatened the breakup
of the central Sangha organization by various means, including
threats, blackmail and boycott.''
   Eyewitnesses contacted by telephone in Mandalay said the
monastery gates were opened and monks came out on their morning
alms rounds Sunday without interference from the troops. Monks
traditionally received offerings of food from the faithful in the
early morning.
   A large number of Mandalay monks joined the boycott following
the brutal suppression of an anti-government demonstration in the
city in August. The boycott spread to other areas, including
Rangoon, 350 miles south of Mandalay.
   About 85 percent of Burma's 40 million people are Buddhist and
about 300,000 monks live in monasteries around the country. Monks
are regarded as spiritual leaders of the community and play a key
role in popular celebrations and various rites.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0028 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 1318EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-France-Fashion     10-21 0432</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-France-Fashion,0499</SECOND>
<HEAD>Joyous Summertime at Lacroix Fashion Show</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos PAR1,2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SUZY PATTERSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Christian Lacroix brought spring into bloom Sunday
in a joyous riot of summer shades and shapes at his luxury
ready-to-wear fashion show.
   The young designer from the south of France continued his trend
of favorite silhouettes in luscious, expensive styles and added
some new tricks as well.
   The multicolored striped jersey T-shirt outfits - mainly short
with some long pants thrown in - came out with original panels of
sequined Provencal flowers on shirts and skirts.
   Lacroix also stepped in line with some other designers here,
bringing out clinging bodysuits and bathing suits. A few sported
little ruffled skirtlets.
   A new swirly abstract print called Le Marquis was mixed all over
the place in pique cotton suits and flowing silk crepe outfits.
   Silhouettes ranged from simple pants and beach shirts to the
favorite Lacroix trapeze coats and babydoll dresses.
   Though every color of the rainbow showed up in his line, Lacroix
strongly favored reds, from orange to poppy to shocking pink. He
sometimes combined solids with a wide gridiron pattern or fuzzy
stripes in pants or the modified bubble-shaped skirts he loves.
   Lacroix simplified a few outfits using solids only - buttercup
yellows, lavender, pastels or purple. But often he mixed up bright
solids on pockets, sleeves and lapels.
   The Lacroix exuberance stayed mostly under control, slipping
only a bit in certain flounced, mixed-print outfits rimmed and
underlined by black lace petticoats.
   They looked a bit too flower-child for Lacroix's sophisticated
clientele, who pay high prices for his clothes.
   Issey Miyake scored a solid hit Saturday for artistry and
versatility with his individual approach to fabric and draping. Not
always wearable, the clothes always intrigued as objects.
   In his sporting line, yellow-and-black stretch suits in abstract
designs gave a futuristic cast to the current rage for body
stockings.
   With customary wit, Miyake sometimes added real handbags - with
the purse growing right out of the glove.
   Dinosaur jackets with pointed, folded sleeves in sandy shades of
gazar silk looked anything but prehistoric, marching out over
finely-pleated white skirts.
   Another wild idea featured bicolored tunic-suits in a crimped
fabric. When held above the head, the rounded arm shapes looked
like cheery commas.
   Dressy clothes for the beach were a strong item at Enrico
Coveri's show on Sunday. The beaded, sequined or embroidered beige
fishnet trapeze minis, maxis or pants outfits could look nearly
nude or fine enough for a sunny terrace restaurant.
   As usual, Coveri used plenty of strong color, from flowered body
suits to matching sheer duster tops. Raw silk in sizzling shades of
orange, cornflower yellow, amethyst and shocking pink came out in
fitted shortie suits, some with sleeveless vests or jackets.
   Other options included solid, short satin trench coats, shorts,
beach wraps and bush jacket styles in African colors and patterns.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0029 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 1329EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-2LiveCrew     10-21 0556</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-2 Live Crew,0708</SECOND>
<HEAD>2 Live Crew Jurors Say Music Was Fun, Verdict Was Easy</HEAD>
<DATELINE>FORT LAUDERDALE, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The six jurors who helped 2 Live
Crew beat an obscenity rap say their ``not guilty'' verdict was
almost as instantaneous as it was unanimous.
   The moment they took the case behind closed doors and sat down
to a pre-deliberation lunch, they discovered a common opinion: Not
only was the Miami rap group's music a form of art, it was fun.
   ``We found many of the things very humorous,'' said Beverly
Resnick, 65, a mother of two who gathered briefly with the other
jurors to discuss the verdict after court was adjourned Saturday.
   ``Our feelings were, the musicians in the band were telling the
public how they felt inside of themselves, and they were doing it
with music. We thought it had some art in it.''
   Band leader Luther Campbell and members Mark ``Brother Marquis''
Ross and Chris ``Fresh Kid Ice'' Wongwon each faced up to a year in
jail and a $1,000 fine had they been convicted on the one-count
misdemeanor of staging an obscene performance.
   Assistant State Attorney Pedro Dijols said after the verdict
that he was unsure whether a similar case would be prosecuted in
the future. But he said the verdict showed Broward authorities
needed to do a better job of gathering evidence. Jurors had noted
that the recording police made of the disputed concert was
difficult to hear.
   The charges stemmed from an adults-only show at a nightclub in
nearby Hollywood on June 10. On June 6, a federal judge in Broward
County ruled the group's album ``As Nasty As They Wanna Be'' was
obscene, and on June 8, a merchant was arrested for selling the
album, which includes references to oral and anal sex and sexual
violence against women.
   The jurors said that although they took more than two hours to
finish their meal, elect a foreman, wrap up their debate and fill
out the verdict form, their feelings about the music were never in
doubt.
   ``It was humorous,'' said juror David Gilliland, 26, a mechanic.
``And I do believe humor is an art form.''
   The jurors also said they didn't think race was an issue. 2 Live
Crew is a black group, and part of their defense was that their
music represented their culture, using time-honored devices such as
exaggeration, humor and bawdiness.
   ``I like the music, and my kids like the music,'' said Gertrude
McLamore, 61, a retired cook and the only black on the jury.
   Juror Helena Bailie, 76, a retired sociology professor, said the
band's performance in the face of threatened arrests may have been
an act of political defiance.
   ``Maybe the band felt threatened, and they were thumbing their
noses back,'' she said.
   Foreman David Garsow, 24, said prosecutors made a mistake in
playing tinny, garbled tapes of the concert again and again,
although the words were barely discernible because of the poor
quality of the recordings made by police with pocket-sized
recorders.
   ``It wore us down,'' said Garsow, a one-time musician. ``After
we heard it once, we felt like we didn't need to hear it a third
and a fourth time.''
   But although the tapes ``just weren't clear enough for us to
decide what happened,'' Garsow said the jury heard enough to not be
offended.
   ``As the cross-section of the community that we are, it was just
not obscene,'' he said.
   Charles Freeman, the record-store owner convicted by an earlier
jury of selling obscene material when he sold a ``Nasty'' album to
an undercover policeman, lauded Saturday's verdict, calling it
``true justice.''
   Milt Hirsch, Freeman's trial attorney, said the cases were
different because the prosecution in his had to prove only that the
recording Freeman sold was obscene. In the band's case, ``the state
had no case at all'' since it lacked a videotape or other
conclusive evidence to support the charges.
   ``Unfortunately, in Charles' trial, the only issue was the
obscenity of the record itself,'' Hirsch said. ``Whether this will
come back for consideration at Charles' sentencing is another
question.''
   Freeman faces sentencing on Nov. 2.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0030 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 1336EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-BraveryAwards     10-21 0246</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bravery Awards,250</SECOND>
<HEAD>N.Y., Ohio Youths Receive Bravery Awards</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A 9-year-old Ohio boy who died after boosting
his best friend to safety when they fell through the ice on a
frozen pond was among four recipients to receive 1989 Young
American Medals for Bravery Sunday.
   Attorney General Dick Thornburgh said Andrew William D'Alesio of
Reynoldsburg, Ohio saved his friend's life on Feb. 19, 1989 after
they sank through the ice playing hockey. D'Alesio pushed his
friend to safety, but then fell underneath the ice and died.
   The second recipient of the bravery award was Jason Frank
Guntert, then 17, of Hudson, N.Y. He pulled a woman from a burning,
smoke-filled car that had been involved in an accident.
   Guntert suffered serious burns when he extinguished the flames
on the woman's coat and body with his hands.
   Two other young people also received the 1989 Young American
Medals for Service.
   - Gregory D. Bassuk, then 17, of Chestnut Ridge, N.Y., has
served both the youth and the elderly of his community through a
series of volunteer activities. He has worked as a community aide
for senior citizens and hosted a radio talk show that focused on
youth-related issues.
   - Christopher E. Daly, then 17, of Gaithersburg, Md., has served
his community through membership in various organizations. He
planned a one-day regional conference for teen-agers with
orthopedic disabilities, their parents and their friends.
   The medals program, established in 1950, recognizes young people
for acts of bravery and community service. It directs the
Department of Justice to pick the recipients, who are then given
medals by the president.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0031 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 1336EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Jerusalem-Chronology     10-21 0314</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Jerusalem-Chronology,0376</SECOND>
<HEAD>Clashes In The Holy City</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Israel-Violence, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Palestinian uprising against Israeli
occupation has led to increased clashes between Jews and Arabs in
Jerusalem. Following are some major incidents of recent years.
   
   1989:
   -Feb. 7: A curfew is imposed on the Jerusalem refugee camp of
Shufat after riots and repeated stoning attacks on cars. It is the
first curfew in Jerusalem since the uprising began in December
1987.
   -April 10: A Palestinian is shot to death and two others are
wounded as they sit near the Jaffa Gate entrance to Jerusalem's Old
City. The attack is claimed by a Jewish underground group, the
Sicarites.
   -May 2: Two elderly Israelis are stabbed to death and three
others wounded by a Palestinian at a downtown Jerusalem bus stop.
   -July 6: A Palestinian man grabs the wheel of an Israeli bus en
route to Jerusalem and plunges it over a ravine, killing 16
passengers, most of them Israelis. The Palestinian is jailed for
life.
   -Dec. 30: Police break up an Arab-Israeli human ``peace chain''
around the old city. More than 50 people are injured, including an
Italian peace activist who loses an eye.
   1990:
   -April 11: About 150 Jewish activists take over a Christian
hostel in the Old City's Christian Quarter, sparking several days
of Arab riots in the old walled city. An Israeli court orders most
of the Jews out until ownership of the hostel is sorted out.
   -May 28: A bomb explodes in the crowded Mahane Yahuda market,
killing an Israeli and injuring nine others. Arab cars are stoned
and photographers beaten up.
   -Aug. 6: Police find the stabbed, strangled bodies of two Jewish
teen-agers who disappeared while hitchhiking in northern Jerusalem.
The incident sets off three days of anti-Arab rioting in which an
Arab was killed when his car was stoned and it overturned.
   -Oct. 8: Israeli police open fire on Palestinians on the Temple
Mount after stones were thrown at Jews below at the Western Wall.
At least 19 Palestinians are killed.
   -Oct. 21: An Arab laborer stabs three Israelis to death. Police
believe he may have been trying to avenge the Temple Mount
killings.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0032 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 1348EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-NorthernIreland     10-21 0440</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Northern Ireland,0520</SECOND>
<HEAD>Gunmen Kill Former Soldier, IRA Claims Responsibility</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BELFAST, Northern Ireland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Gunmen killed a former soldier
near a crowded Roman Catholic church, police said Sunday. The Irish
Republican Army claimed responsibility.
   The slaying Saturday night was the fourth within a week
resulting from religious and sectarian strife in Northern Ireland.
   The victim was identified as David Pollock, 30, a Protestant who
left the locally recruited Ulster Defense Regiment several years
ago.
   The gunmen, using a car stolen from a family they had taken
hostage, rammed the vehicle being driven by Pollock in County
Tyrone near the border with the Irish Republic, police said.
   The attack took place just a few hundred yards from Melmount
Church where more than 1,000 Roman Catholic worshipers were just
leaving a service celebrating peace and reconciliation.
   ``It's a miracle that no one else was killed or injured,'' said
The Rev. Patrick Arkinson, the church curate. ``This killing ...
was a direct contradiction of our faith and a violation of the
Fifth Commandment, Thou Shalt Not Kill.''
   Dr. Charles Sullivan, a local doctor, said he went to help the
man but he was already dead, the body slumped over in the driver's
seat.
   The gang fled on foot and then hijacked a second auto from a
woman and her daughter driving home from the church, said a
spokesman for the Royal Ulster Constabulary, the province's police
force, who by custom was not identified.
   The mainly Catholic IRA, which is fighting to end British rule
in the mainly Protestant province and unite it with the
overwhelmingly Catholic Irish Republic, claimed responsibility for
the attack in messages to Belfast media.
   Leading politicians in the province were united in their
condemnation of the shooting.
   Peter Robinson, deputy leader of the hard-line Protestant
Democratic Unionist Party, said: ``There is a tremendous need for
the government to react to this increase in violence, and we must
have a resolute military initiative against the IRA immediately.''
   Seamus Mallon, deputy leader of the moderate Catholic Social
Democratic and Labor Party, called it ``another pointless, brutal
murder which will be as futile and counterproductive as the almost
3,000 murders which have already taken place.
   ``The IRA campaign has become a war of attrition which can lead
to nothing but further suffering.''
   Dr. John Alderdice, leader of the centrist Alliance Party, said
``all the terrorists can offer is to go around destroying people's
lives and families.
   ``I feel angry about it and distressed for the family who is
going to suffer this loss.''
   On Oct. 15, a police dog handler died in the hospital, two days
after he and a fellow dog handler were shot by an IRA gunman in
central Belfast.
   Dermot McGuinness, a Roman Catholic, and former police reservist
Steven Craig, a Protestant, were killed in separate shootings in
north Belfast on Tuesday.
   The IRA claimed responsibility for shooting Craig. The Ulster
Freedom Fighters, an illegal Protestant paramilitary group
committed to retaining British rule over the province, said it
killed McGuinness.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0033 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 1350EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Brazil-Scandal     10-21 0492</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brazil-Scandal,0607</SECOND>
<HEAD>Romantic Scandal Could Lead to Economy Minister's Fall</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KEN SILVERSTEIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>RIO DE JANEIRO, Brazil (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Economy Minister Zelia Cardoso de
Mello could fall victim to a scandal that already has cost the job
of her romantic partner - former Justice Minister Bernardo Cabral.
   The economy minister denies any intention of resigning. On
Friday, President Fernando Collor de Mello made a carefully staged
public appearance with his embattled official, in what was clearly
meant as a show of support.
   But Ms. Cardoso de Mello's job - arguably the most important
Cabinet post in a country whose economy is reeling - is the subject
of much speculation.
   News reports of the affair forced Cabral to resign Oct. 13. Few
predict Ms. Cardoso de Mello's resignation is imminent, but a
concensus is growing that her days are numbered.
   ``Her position is extremely fragile,'' said political consultant
Alexandre Barros. ``If I were a bookmaker, I'd say there is an 80
percent chance she'll be gone within three months.''
   The scandal broke out in late September when Ms. Cardoso de
Mello, 37 years old and single, was disclosed to be having an
affair with Cabral, 58, who has been married for 35 years.
   At a Sept. 19 birthday party for the economics minister, the two
danced cheek-to-cheek at a posh Brasilia club before hundreds of
gawking journalists and dignataries.
   Political scientist Walder de Goes of the Universty of Brasilia
said Brazilian society is extremely sexist, and that ``whispering
and gossip'' about the minister's love life had greatly damaged her
authority.
   ``She can only save her job if she marries Cabral,'' he said.
``Otherwise, she'll be seen as someone foolish and weak, who was
used by an older man.''
   De Goes said Ms. Cardoso de Mello appeared to come unglued
during a Senate hearing Wednesday, when Cabral unexpectedly showed
up during a brief break. Those in the chamber cleared the room to
leave the two alone.
   ``It's obvious she is completely in love,'' he said. ``If the
situation is not resolved, she may be unable to concentrate on the
country's problems.''
   Others say the Cabral affair was merely the last straw, and that
Brazil's continuing economic woes are the primary reason for Ms.
Cardoso de Mello's tenous hold on power.
   Prominent political analyst Janio de Freitas said Collor has
been angry with his economic minister since August, when he
announced inflation would be 3 percent, based on a guarantee from
Ms. Cardoso de Mello.
   ``It was 10 percent, and has gone up since then,'' he said.
``That, along with the romantic scandal, has her with one foot out
the door.''
   He said that if monthly inflation was not in the single digits
by January, the minister's fate would be sealed. September
inflation was 12.58 percent and little decline is expected soon,
especially with international oil prices soaring because of the
Persian Gulf crisis.
   Barros said the only sign in Ms. Cardoso de Mello's favor was
that her dismissal would be seen as a confession the president's
economic austerity policies had failed.
   He said it would also weaken Brazil's position in its talks with
foreign creditors.
   ``If she goes, everything gets very shaky,'' he said. ``That may
at least delay her fall.''
   The minister's firmest show of support last week came from her
mother, 70-year-old Auzelia Martoni Cardoso de Mello.
   ``Brazil needs to learn to pay attention to more important
subjects ... and forget about my daughter's personal life,'' she
said in a newspaper interview.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0034 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 1352EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People     10-21 0812</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People,1037</SECOND>
<HEAD>People in the News</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos NY44, NY4</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Mike Tyson reached an out-of-court settlement
with a parking attendant who claimed the boxing champion punched
him when he refused to let Tyson's white Mercedes-Benz park in a
particular spot.
   Michael Devine, 35, said the terms of the settlement reached
Friday prevent him from disclosing how much money he received. But
it was less than the $250,000 he was seeking, he said, and too
small to make up for his suffering.
   ``It was lousy, lousy,'' Devine said Saturday. ``The settlement
was a lousy amount for all the trauma I've been through. I'm not
fussy when it comes to money, but that was lousy.''
   Telephone calls seeking comment from Tyson's attorney, Howard
Weitzman, were not immediately answered on Sunday.
   The attendant and part time stand-up comedian was working a lot
on Vine street in Hollywood near the Palace nightclub the night of
April 10, 1989. Tyson's driver pulled up in a white Mercedes-Benz
and parked the car in a spot reserved for the club owner's wife,
Devine said.
   Devine said he asked the driver to move the car and the driver
started to do so. Just then, Tyson, who was attending a function at
the Palace, ran out of the club and started yelling at him.
   Devine said Tyson hit him three times in the stomach with the
back of his hand.
   The city attorney declined to prosecute Tyson on misdemeanor
assault charges saying there was not enough evidence for a
conviction. Tyson has denied hitting Devine.
   ---
   LOS ANGELES (AP) - Actor Nicolas Cage is the proud owner of a
1920s castle, complete with at turret, in the Hollywood Hills, a
newspaper reported Sunday.
   The sloe-eyed, 25-year-old actor known for his oddball roles in
movies such as ``Raising Arizona, ``Moonstruck'' and ``Wild at
Heart,'' has purchased the 5,367-square-foot residence in the Los
Feliz neighborhood, according to the Los Angeles Times.
   The castle sits atop a promontory with a 360-degree city view
and the master suite has a black marble fireplace.
   The 11-room home has three bedrooms, 4{ bathrooms and a maid's
quarters, according to the listing by Dorothy Carter and Jodi
Hodges of Douglas Properties. The house was listed for $1,695,000.
   Cage paid about $1.5 million for the gated property, the
newspaper said.
   ---
</TEXT>
<NOTE>Eds: A version moved on sports wires.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Deposed New York Yankee boss George Steinbrenner
took to the airwaves as host of ``Saturday Night Live,'' joking
about his fondness for firing underlings and the World Series upset
win by the Cincinnati Reds.
   In one skit on Saturday's show, he was a store manager who can't
bring himself to dismiss an inefficient employee.
   ``I can't fire people,'' he says. ``It's just not in my
nature.''
   ``Where is it written that if you don't get results right away
you fire someone? ... Only a jackass would do that.''
   The opening sequence featured him dreaming that the New York
Yankees were completing a sweep of the World Series: George
Steinbrenner pitching to catcher George Steinbrenner, George on
first, George on second, George as shortstop, George on third ....
   The show came on just minutes after the Cincinnati Reds -
managed by ex-Yankee manager Lou Piniella - finished their
unexpected World Series sweep of the Oakland Athletics.
   ``I want you to be the first to know,'' he said. ``At 11:15
tonight I bought the Cincinnati Reds.''
   ---
   SANTA FE, N.M. (AP) - Academy Award-winning actress Greer Garson
was honored with a film studio in her name and she said she hopes
it will spread ``understanding and peacemaking among all peoples.''
   Hundreds of actors and prominent New Mexicans turned out
Saturday evening for a dinner to commemorate the opening of the
Greer Garson Communications Center and Studios at the College of
Santa Fe.
   Miss Garson, 82, was unable to attend because she was recovering
from the flu at her Dallas home. But in a telephone call to the
audience, she said wants the center to advance the cause of
communication around the world.
   ``The true value of communication is spreading understanding and
peacemaking among all peoples,'' she said. ``I'm very proud indeed
to be part of the program.''
   The center at CSF was built with a $3 million gift from Miss
Garson and her late husband, E.E. ``Buddy'' Fogelson.
   Among the 650 attending the dinner were actor Cesar Romero,
master of ceremonies Art Linkletter, actor turned producer Tab
Hunter, and Ray Buktenica, star of television's ``Life Goes On,''
who is an alumnus of the college.
   ``She's a dear lady,'' said Romero, who co-starred with Miss
Garson in the 1948 film ``Julia Misbehaves.''
   Romero and others agreed that while Miss Garson is well known
for her acting career, including her 1942 Oscar winning performance
in ``Mrs. Miniver,'' the studio will be a more enduring legacy.
   ``She was a great actress,'' said New Mexico Gov. Garrey
Carruthers. ``While we enjoy her films, her philanthropy is what
will endear New Mexicans to her.''
   ---
   SAN FRANCISCO (AP) - Actress Claire Bloom says she doesn't
understand how actors ``slog on'' in long-running Broadway plays.
   ``I haven't left the theater. It left me,'' says the 59-year-old
actress, who nonetheless maintains a hectic schedule. ``The plays
are not that interesting, the theater district in New York is a
horror and the audiences aren't that terrific there. It's only when
you go off Broadway that you still have enthusiastic people,
younger people and interesting things.''
   In an interview published Sunday in the San Francisco Examiner,
Bloom said she hates repeating a performance night after night but
she will do a short, six-week run.
   During the last week or so, Bloom has performed performance in
Washington, D.C., and three nights with the Los Angeles Symphony as
a narrator for Mendelssohn's version of ``A Midsummer Night's
Dream.''
   On Monday, she is scheduled to appear at San Francisco's Herbst
Theatre in her one-woman show, ``Then Let Men Know: A Portrait of
Shakespeare's Women.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0035 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 1355EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-OhioFire     10-21 0138</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Ohio Fire,0139</SECOND>
<HEAD>Five Children Die in Cleveland House Fire</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CLEVELAND (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A fire trapped five children in their upstairs
bedrooms early Sunday, and all five died of smoke inhalation,
authorities said.
   A woman and her son survived the fire by jumping from a
second-floor window, said Fire Investigator Albert Lugo. The woman
was hospitalized in fair condition with burns.
   The blaze began on the first floor of the 2{-story frame
dwelling in a working-class neighborhood, Lugo said.
   Firefighters found the house engulfed in flames when they
arrived.
   The fire drove back firefighters attempting to rescue people
inside, Lugo said.
   The cause of the fire remained under investigation, he said.
   The dead, four boys and a girl, ranged in age from 2 to 12, said
Cuyahoga County Coroner Elizabeth K. Balraj.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0036 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 1400EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Israel-Lebanon     10-21 0229</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel-Lebanon,0241</SECOND>
<HEAD>Israeli-Allied Militiamen Kill Four Guerrillas</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Israel-Violence, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Israeli-allied militiamen on Sunday killed four
Lebanese guerrillas in a firefight north of Israel's
self-proclaimed security zone in Lebanon, Israeli army officials
said.
   The guerrillas were first seen by an Israeli army patrol before
dawn Sunday near Shaba, a village in the zone's eastern sector
about a mile north of the Israeli border, a military official said
on condition of anonymity.
   The patrol fired and the guerrillas retreated to the north,
apparently planning to leave the security zone, he said.
   In the morning, Israeli soldiers backed by Israeli-trained South
Lebanon Army militiamen found the guerrillas' tracks and launched a
pursuit, the official said.
   ``About four kilometers (2.4 miles) north of the zone, a South
Lebanon Army unit came in contact with the guerrillas and killed
them in a short firefight,'' he said. No militia casualties were
reported.
   The guerrillas were armed with the assault rifles and carried
explosives, the official said. It was not immediately clear to
which organization they belonged.
   Israel carved out the 2- to 10-mile-wide security zone as a
buffer protecting its northern border against guerrilla raids in
1985, when it withdrew the bulk of its forees from Lebanon after a
three-year occupation.
   The zone is jointly patrolled by Israeli soldiers and some 2,500
members of the mostly Christian South Lebanon Army, which is
financed by Israel.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0037 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 1421EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Italy-MoroLetters     10-21 0540</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Italy-Moro Letters,0633</SECOND>
<HEAD>Kidnapped Former Premier's Letters Reflect Bitterness, Despair</HEAD>
<HEAD>By STEPHEN R. WILSON</HEAD>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ROME (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The discovery of 46 letters written by Aldo Moro
while held by Red Brigades terrorists has reopened old wounds from
the sensational 1978 kidnap and murder of the former prime
minister.
   While shedding little new light on the abduction and slaying,
publication of the letters was a chilling reminder of Moro's
bitterness and frustration over the refusal of his Christian
Democrat Party to negotiate his release.
   ``I have been killed three times: by insufficient protection,
refusal to negotiate, inconclusive politics,'' he wrote.
   Moro, kidnapped on March 16, 1978, was murdered 55 days later
and his bullet-riddled body dumped in teh trunk of a car in
downtown Rome.
   Photocopies of 421 pages of Moro's letters to family members,
friends and political figures were discovered Oct. 9 in a Milan
apartment that served as a hideout for the leftist Red Brigades in
the 1970s.
   The safe house had reportedly been used by some of the
terrorists who kidnapped Moro. Police said the letters, along with
two guns, 30 detonators and $50,000 in cash, were discovered by
chance by workers who were restoring the apartment and found the
material in a hollow space behind a wall.
   Political leaders, however, say they are convinced the letters
did not turn up by accident. They question how police could have
missed the hiding place when they raided the apartment in 1978 and
arrested three Red Brigades members.
   Some say they believe the letters were planted in the apartment
later, possibly very recently, in an attempt to discredit certain
political figures, especially President Francesco Cossiga.
   Senate President Giovanni Spadolini, who was a close friend of
Moro, suggested Friday that the sudden appearance of the letters
was a maneuver to destabilize politicial institutions and leaders.
   Prime Minister Giulio Andreotti said Saturday he shared
Spadolini's suspicions and promised authorities would find out who
is responsible. Otherwise, he said, ``someone will have to go'' - a
comment newspapers described as a threat to fire secret service
chiefs.
   The speaker of the Chamber of Deputies, Nilde Iotti, suggested
that Parliament hold a special debate to examine the circumstances
surrounding the appearance of the letters.
   Political commentators said the main target of the alleged plot
appeared to be Cossiga, who was interior minister at the time of
the abduction.
   In one of the letters, Moro criticized Cossiga as being ``out of
place ... hypnotized'' by Andreotti and Communist Party leader
Enrico Berlinguer.
   Cossiga's office said he would not comment out of respect for
the privacy of Moro's family, which sought in vain to prevent the
publication of the letters.
   Arnaldo Forlani, secretary of the Christian Democrats, visited
Cossiga over the weekend to offer the party's solidarity.
   The contents of the letters reiterate much of what had emerged
earlier from other letters, documents and trials. Other than the
attack on Cossiga, the Italian media have focused on Moro's jibes
against other Christian Democrat colleagues.
   Moro wrote that Andreotti, who was also premier at the time,
``moved with ease in relations with colleagues from the CIA.'' He
described the then Christian Democrat leader, Benigno Zaccagnini,
as ``the most fragile secretary'' in the party's history.
   During his captivity, Moro sent numerous letters to his party
and leading political figures asking them to negotiate an exchange
of ``political prisoners'' with the Red Brigades. The government
rejected negotiations.
   Moro was kidnapped shortly after he arranged the ``historic
compromise'' with the Communist Party.
   The accord gave the Communists a direct say in running the
government for the first time since early after World War II. The
deal collapsed after about nine months.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0038 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 1424EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-India-Punjab     10-21 0196</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-India-Punjab,0206</SECOND>
<HEAD>Sikh Politician Assassinated in Punjab</HEAD>
<DATELINE>AMRITSAR, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Gunmen on Sunday assassinated a moderate
Sikh politician in an ambush near his farm in Punjab state, where
Sikh militants are fighting for independence from India, police
said.
   Police said Shishpal Singh, a former state Cabinet minister and
four-term legislator, was killed instantly in gunfire from five or
six weapons.
   The attackers, hiding in a sugar cane field, fired on Singh's
car as it left the farm, seven miles north of the state capital of
Amritsar, said police Superintendent P.S. Gill. Singh's bodyguard,
who was in the back seat, returned fire, but the gunmen escaped.
   Singh, 70, belonged to the Badal political faction, which has
been targeted by the militants for its moderate position.
   In other scattered incidents in Punjab, 11 people were reported
killed in terrorist actions or clashes between militants and
police, news agencies said Sunday.
   Sikh extremists have killed more than 2,400 people this year,
making this the deadliest year since they began a separatist
insurrection in 1983.
   Sikhs have a slight majority in Punjab, a rich farming state
bordering Pakistan, though they are only 2 percent of the 880
million people in Hindu-dominated India.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0039 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 1432EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-IowaDecommissioning     10-21 0546</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Iowa Decommissioning,0715</SECOND>
<HEAD>Battleship Heads To Mothballs Carrying Heroic and Tragic Past</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Budget-Taxes, Bjt</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto RM1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By D.W. PAGE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NORFOLK, Va. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Enemy planes and artillery could not sink
the battleship USS Iowa, but budget tightening and the costly
damage left by a tragic explosion are sending the proud ship back
into mothballs.
   The decommissioning Friday will be the third for the Iowa since
it sailed into combat in World War II, and crew members are looking
on the event with sadness, says the ship's commander.
   ``This crew today would like nothing more than someone to say:
`That's it. Reverse course. You are to make preparations to sail
for the Persian Gulf,''' said Cmdr. John P. Morse.
   But that order is not likely to come.
   In an effort to cut costs in face of a rising budget deficit,
the Navy has decided the Iowa is expendable. The USS New Jersey
also is being mothballed, leaving only two battleships in active
service, the Missouri and the Wisconsin.
   In addition to the cost of operating a battleship, more than $35
million a year, the Iowa has another strike against it: the
expensive scars of the April 19, 1989, explosion in one of its
massive gun turrets that killed 47 sailors.
   The Navy concluded the explosion probably was sabotage by a
gunner's mate who died in the explosion, but a congressional
inquiry found the report to be lacking. Earlier this year, the Navy
reopened its investigation.
   The explosion did not seriously damage the ship itself, but it
would cost $13 million to repair turret No. 2.
   In its glory days in World War II, the Iowa's 16-inch guns
hammered shore fortifications on South Pacific islands, hurling
2,000-pound shells more than 20 miles.
   During the bombardment of the Marshall Islands in March 1944,
the Iowa took two hits from Japanese shore batteries.
   Henry Schwartz was three decks down in turret No. 2 when the
first shell landed that month.
   ``I didn't feel the impact. One shell hit on the turret, the
other on the deck. One guy got hit by a piece of shrapnel, and that
was it,'' said Schwartz, 72, of Indianapolis.
   A fist-sized dent high on the port side of the turret still
marks the Japanese shell's impact.
   When the war ended the following year, the Iowa entered Tokyo
harbor as part of the fleet accepting the Japanese surrender.
   ``We were all at general quarters wondering what was going to
happen ... whether they really were going to surrender or what. It
was pretty tense,'' said retired Capt. Frank Sellers Jr., 77, of
San Diego. He served as the Iowa's gunnery officer in the closing
days of the war.
   The ship was put in mothballs following the war, but was
recalled in 1951 for the Korean conflict. It was retired again in
1957.
   With the planned buildup to a 600-ship Navy under President
Reagan, the Iowa was recalled and refitted as a launch platform for
cruise missiles. Its 16-inch guns were just an added benefit, said
Capt. Fred Moosally, the ship's commander at the time of the turret
explosion.
   Its 17-inch armor was thought impervious to any conventional
weapons, such as the type of missile that damaged several British
ships during the Falklands War with Argentina and killed more than
30 sailors aboard the frigate USS Stark in the Persian Gulf.
   ``Any tinhorn dictator has access to those types of weapons,''
said former Secretary of the Navy John F. Lehman Jr. ``The ship to
send to a crisis area is a battleship. We ought to have learned
that from the Stark and the Samuel Roberts.'' The Roberts was
damaged by a mine in the gulf.
   To Morse, the reasons for keeping the Iowa in the Navy are more
visceral:
   ``This ship has an excitement and a life to it and an emotional
attraction to it more than any of the five ships on which I have
served.
   ``We are very mindful of the thousands of men who have come
before us on this ship. We try very hard to preserve their
integrity and honor. We think we have done that.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0040 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 1510EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-US-Gulf     10-21 0613</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-US-Gulf,690</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mitchell Says Only Congress Can Declare War in Gulf</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOAN MOWER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Senate Majority Leader George Mitchell,
insisting only Congress has the right to declare war, said Sunday
congressional leaders are prepared to return from their break if a
crisis flares in the Persian Gulf.
   Mitchell, D-Maine, reiterated a position that has put Congress
at odds with top Bush administration officials. With more than
200,000 American troops based in Saudi Arabia, lawmakers and the
White House are tussling over which one has the constitutional
right to commit the nation to war.
   ``It is important to remember that under the American
Constitution, the president has no legal authority - none
whatsoever - to commit the United States to war,'' Mitchell said on
NBC-TV's ``Meet the Press'' program.
   ``Only Congress can make that grave decision,'' he said. ``And
in this respect, if the United States is to be committed to war, it
requires action by Congress.''
   Mitchell said he and House Speaker Thomas Foley, D-Wash., have
considered several measures that would bring Congress back into
session should that become necessary because of the Persian Gulf
crisis.
   Congress is supposed to quit for the year after finishing the
1991 budget, probably this week, and stay away until mid-January.
   Secretary of State James A. Baker III told senators last week
that the administration would consult with Congress if military
action were needed in the gulf. But he refused to commit the
administration to getting any advance congressional approval for
any action.
   The administration contends President Bush, as the commander in
chief of the military, has the right to declare war. Moreover,
Baker told the Senate Foreign Relations Committee, that advance
notification to Congress could deprive the military of any surprise
factor.
   In an attempt to clarify the constitutional conflict after the
Vietnam War, Congress passed the War Powers Resolution in 1973. It
requires the president to consult with Congress before deploying
troops into hostilities or when hostilities are imminent.
   Within 48 hours of deploying troops, the president must file a
report to Congress. Additionally, U.S. forces must be withdrawn
after 60 days if Congress has not voted its approval.
   Meanwhile Sunday, the Pentagon said it had no information about
a report that Iraqi troops, tanks and armored vehicles have been
pulling out of parts of Kuwait, positioning themselves closer to
Kuwait's major oil field in the Matla region.
   But Lt. Col. Steve Roy, a Pentagon spokesman, said the report,
which appeared in the newspaper Al-Khaleej, printed in the Sharjah,
one of the United Arab Emirates, was ``entirely possible'' because
Iraqi troops are continually repositioning themselves inside
occupied Kuwait.
   U.S. officials estimate the Iraqis have put some 400,000 troops
in or around Kuwait since Iraqi President Saddam Hussein invaded
Kuwait on Aug. 2.
   In other gulf developments:
   - The Pentagon confirmed the destroyer O'Brien fired a warning
shot across the bow of an Iraqi tanker in the gulf Saturday. U.S.
Navy officials then intercepted the ship, boarded it and allowed it
to proceed. There have been roughly a half-dozen warning shot
episodes since Aug. 2.
   - The Middle East Policy Survey, a newsletter published in
Washington, reported that a few days before Saddam invaded Kuwait,
Bush sent a message to the Iraqi president. The message expressed
the administration's concern for Saddam's troop movements, but said
the United States wanted improved U.S.-Iraqi bilateral relations.
   April Glaspie, the U.S. ambassador in Iraq, delivered the
message to Iraqi Foreign Minister Tariq Aziz and Saddam's
son-in-law, Hussein Kamal, the paper said. Kamal is the minister of
military industries.
   The Washington Post in Sunday's editions quoted sources as
confirming that Bush wrote a presidential message which was
supposed to be relayed to Saddam through Glaspie. The message was
transmitted to the U.S. Embassy in Baghdad on July 28, the Post
said. The newspaper said the exact wording of the Bush document
could not be learned, but sources said it was a mixed message on
policy towards Iraq.
   White House officials could not be reached immediately for
comment on the report.
   - The Washington Post also reported Sunday that Iraqi military
forces are beginning to learn how to operate sophisticated U.S.
Hawk anti-aircraft missiles and radars that were captured in
Kuwait.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0041 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 1512EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-JoggerTrial     10-21 0466</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Jogger Trial,0586</SECOND>
<HEAD>Second Jogger Trial to Open; Defense Cites Defendants' IQ</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SAMUEL MAULL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The second trial in the case of the Central Park
jogger opens Monday with the defense claiming that incriminating
statements at the heart of the prosecution's case were coerced from
mentally deficient boys.
   But the prosecution will contend - as it did in the first trial
- that the two teen-age defendants voluntarily and knowingly made
the admissions, and that they convict themselves with their own
words.
   There are two defendants on trial this time: Kharey Wise, 18,
and Kevin Richardson, 16.
   There were among six teens who were charged with attempted
murder and gang rape in the highly publicized attack on a female
jogger in Central Park on April 19, 1989. They also are charged in
attacks on two male joggers that night.
   In August, the first trial ended in the conviction of three
teens for rape, first-degree assault, robbery and riot, and
acquittals on the charges of attempted murder and sodomy. Yusef
Salaam, Raymond Santana and Antron McCray, all 16, received
5-to-10-year sentences, the maximum for juvenile offenders.
   The victim, now 30, suffered brain damage and testified at the
trial of the first three defendants that she has no memory of the
attack, that she has lost her sense of smell and that her sense of
balance is impaired.
   Despite her lingering problems, she has returned to her job at
the Salomon Brothers investiment firm, where she is now a vice
president.
   Like the first trial, the second will feature written and
videotaped statements the youths made to police and prosecutors
after their arrests.
   In his statements to police, Richardson denied he attacked the
female jogger. He said he tried to help her and that she scratched
his cheek when he got between her and the other youths.
   Wise made two videotapes. In the first he admitted only that he
was with a marauding gang of about 30 youths. In the second, which
he asked to make, he admitted he participated in the attack.
   Wise's attorney, Colin Moore, said he and his client's mother,
Dolores Wise, have rejected plea negotiations because they are
convinced the teen-ager is innocent.
   But Moore was rebuffed Friday when he asked state Supreme Court
Justice Thomas Galligan to allow expert testimony that his client
is not intelligent enough to have knowingly and meaningfully waived
his Miranda rights against self-incrimination. Supreme Court in New
York state is a trial-level court.
   Moore said Wise has an overall intelligence quotient of 73. He
cited cases in which appeals courts held that defendants with an IQ
of less than 75 did not have the capacity to understand what
waiving their rights would mean.
   Galligan said the motion was too late because by law it should
have been made within 30 days of arraignment. He said he saw no
reason to waive that deadline.
   Richardson's lawyer, Howard Diller, has said similar things
about his client. At the teen-ager's arraignment, Diller told the
judge that Richardson ``is not what you and I would call `all
there.' ''
   Wise, 16 at the time of the attacks, faces adult penalties that
could total up to 57 years in prison if he is convicted on all
counts.
   Richardson, 14 when he was arrested, faces the same five to 10
years as the three youths in the first trial.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0042 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 1516EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>d a AM-BRF-DayCareSentence     10-21 0159</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF-Day Care Sentence,0158</SECOND>
<HEAD>Day Care Worker Sentenced to 10 Years' Probation for Formula
Spiking</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HOUSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A former day care center employee has been
sentenced to 10 years' probation for spiking an infant's formula
with rubbing alcohol because she was angry at co-workers.
   Patricia Ann Escarenio, 21, pleaded guilty to injury to a child
in connection with the April 24 incident and was sentenced Friday
by State District Judge Mike Wilkinson. She also was fined $5,000.
   The 4-month-old boy who drank the formula was hospitalized but
authorities said he suffered no lasting effects because he vomited
the concoction.
   Assistant District Attorney Carol Davies said authorities
believe Ms. Escarenio was angered at the boy's mother, her
co-worker at Chuckles &amp; Grins day care center, because of a job
assignment that day.
   Later that day, Ms. Escarenio checked herself into the
psychiatric unit of St. Joseph Hospital and admitted tainting the
bottle, Ms. Davies said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0043 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 1517EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Germany-Nuclear     10-21 0406</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Germany-Nuclear,0467</SECOND>
<HEAD>Shutdown Set For Last Reactor in Old East Germany</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DEBORAH SEWARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The new German government will shut down the last
Soviet-made nuclear reactor in what was East Germany because the
reactor is unsafe, an Environment Ministry spokesman said Sunday.
   The spokesman, Berthold Goeke, said in a telephone interview
from Bonn that the last operating reactor at the Greifswald power
plant in northeastern Germany would be shut down by mid-December.
   Three other reactors at the Greifswald plant and another reactor
at an older plant in Rheinsberg, just north of Berlin, were shut
down earlier this year. All are Soviet-designed plants.
   Soviet-designed nuclear power plants throughout Eastern Europe
have come under heavy criticism from Western environmental
officials for failing to meet safety standards.
   The use of nuclear power is a sensitive issue in Germany, which
has a powerful network of anti-nuclear groups. The 1986 Chernobyl
nuclear disaster in the Soviet Union helped fuel the anti-nuclear
movement.
   Goeke said it would be too expensive to modernize the Greifswald
plant to make it safe and would take nearly two months to shut it
down.
   The Greifswald and Rheinsberg plants also fail to meet European
Community nuclear safety standards that took effect when the
Germanys united Oct. 3.
Goeke said security inspectors have found that the East German
plants were not properly maintained and often were poorly
constructed.
   The environment ministers of both Germanys had decided in the
spring to shut down all nuclear power reactors in what was then
East Germany. Environment Minister Klaus Toepfer informed the
Soviet government of the decision during a visit to Moscow just
after unification.
   Goeke said the German government had allocated $20 million to
build an oil-fueled heating plant in the Greifswald region to make
up for the loss of power when the reactor is shut down. The
oil-fueled plant is scheduled to start operating in mid-December.
   In June, officials shut down part of Greifswald because of
safety problems.
They said the plant management had permitted operation of a
power-producing block at the plant even though a leak had been
discovered in what they called its cleaning system.
   The magazine Der Spiegel reported in January that a nuclear
accident had narrowly been averted at Greifswald in 1976, when fire
destroyed some electrical cables, disabling all but one of 12
water-cooling pumps in one of the plant's four power-producing
blocks.
   The five states on the territory of East Germany derive only 10
percent of their electricity from nuclear power. The majority of
their power plants are fueled by brown coal, which has seriously
polluted much of eastern Germany.
   Clouds of the noxious brown coal emissions also float into
western Germany, prompting protests from environmental activitists.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0044 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 1529EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-RacialShootings     10-21 0520</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Racial Shootings,0660</SECOND>
<HEAD>Convict Charged in Alleged Racial Shooting Goes on Trial</HEAD>
<BYLINE>ByGARRY MITCHELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOBILE, Ala. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Joseph O'Cain remembers lying on the parking
lot, unable to move as he watched his best friend stumble toward
the grocery store door and collapse.
   His friend, Darren Jessie, had been shot in the head, fatally.
O'Cain also had been shot, and left paralyzed from the waist down
by a bullet in the spine.
   Two months after the March 31 shooting in rural Theodore,
sheriff's deputies arrested a white convict who had been out of
prison on parole only a few weeks before the incident. They said he
shot Jessie and O'Cain because he hated blacks.
   Daniel Amos Pilot, 34, goes on trial Monday charged with murder
in Jessie's death and attempted murder in the crippling of O'Cain.
   District Attorney Chris Galanos says the state will present
evidence that the shootings were racially motivated, but has
provided no elaboration. Pilot's lawyer says his client is not
racist and was not at the shooting.
   O'Cain says he and Jessie, 21, were listening to the radio,
sitting in a car belonging to Jessie's girlfriend and waiting for
her to get off work. The store is in a predominantly white
unincorporated area on the western edge of Mobile.
   ``I never thought I'd be shot,'' said O'Cain, now 18 and
struggling to adjust to life in a wheelchair and finish his final
year at Blount High School.
   He said a man approached the car and asked them for marijuana.
   ``We don't mess around with weed,'' O'Cain said. ``He shot me in
the back and I just fell. I never lost consciousness. Darren was
walking toward the store already shot.''
   He said he didn't know his assailant, but said he recognized
Pilot as the shooter.
   ``Some whites out there are good and some are bad; some blacks
out there are good and some are bad,'' O'Cain said. ``I don't want
this hyped into some kind of prejudice thing.''
   Cautious about being in the public spotlight, O'Cain thinks his
attacker should receive the ultimate sentence - ``I think he should
get the chair.''
   However, the charges against Pilot do not carry a death
sentence. But he is classified as a ``habitual offender,'' having
served prison terms in Alabama and Mississippi, which could bring a
maximum sentence of life in prison without the chance of parole if
convicted.
   State officials said Pilot was paroled March 12, after serving
about a third of a 12-year sentence for receiving stolen property.
He reportedly was arrested based on information supplied to
sheriff's deputies by an informant.
   Jim Zeigler, Pilot's court-appointed lawyer, said, ``They've got
the wrong man.''
   He said Pilot planned to present an alibi. ``He says he wasn't
there and doesn't know anything about it.''
   The attorney also said Pilot is not a racist and has affidavits
from two black inmates saying he never hated blacks.
   Jessie's mother, Catherine McCants, said her son went to summer
school to obtain his diploma from Blount High School and had joined
the Army before he was shot. She said he had been scheduled to
leave for military service the month after the shooting.
   Jessie had worked at odd jobs around Mobile, while O'Cain hoped
to become a brick mason, a job that attracts many black craftsmen
in this Gulf Coast area.
   O'Cain's mother, Jacqueline McQuay, said that after her son was
crippled they had to give up their apartment in a housing project
because it had stairs that could not be negotiated with a
wheelchair. They moved in with a relative.
   O'Cain has been going to physical therapy twice a week. A van
takes him to high school classes.
   Michael Davis, a counselor at the Independent Living Center,
said, ``He's just doing extremely well and not harboring any
resentment.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0045 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 1559EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ClarkTrial     10-21 0545</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Clark Trial,0671</SECOND>
<HEAD>State Attorney General Goes On Trial</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RON FOURNIER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LITTLE ROCK, Ark. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Arkansas' attorney general goes on
trial Monday in a case that could see judges, legislators,
reporters and the governor called to the witness stand.
   Whether Attorney General Steve Clark goes to jail may depend on
whether state law required him to report expenditures on his
state-issued Visa card and to be accurate and honest when he did
so.
   There was no such law, his attorney says.
   And Clark claims that discrepancies in his state expense account
records are no more than bookkeeping errors.
   Clark, 43, is charged with one count of felony theft by
deception. If convicted, he could be sentenced to 20 years in jail
and fined up to $15,000. He was charged July 11 and released
without bond.
   He reported as business expenditures on his state credit card
meals with people who say they didn't eat with him or that it
wasn't business. Some who ate with him said they paid the tab.
   The allegations forced Clark in February to give up his
candidacy for the Democratic nomination for governor, improving
Gov. Bill Clinton's re-election chances.
   The state says Clark was financially strapped but wined and
dined family, friends, girlfriends and benefactors. Prosecutors say
political contributions he sought at some of the meals ended up in
his habitually overdrawn personal checking account.
   A congressman, a federal appeals court judge, two state Supreme
Court justices, lobbyists, former Clark employees, more than a
half-dozen members of the Little Rock media and at least 14 state
lawmakers are on the state's witness list. Most of them were listed
by Clark as dining guests.
   Clark, who is finishing his 12th year in office, has admitted
record-keeping errors.
   ``I made a mistake. There's no doubt about it. It was an honest
mistake but I made a mistake,'' Clark said Jan. 31, the day he
reimbursed the state $3,951.29. ``I am sorry, and I apologize.''
   He said records of the lunch and dinner meetings were
reconstructed from notes, his calendar, receipts or memory. He said
he spent less than 30 minutes every 60 to 90 days attempting to put
together the expense reports.
   The attorney general, whose job includes giving state agencies
his interpretation of the state Constitution and statutes, said he
wasn't required to keep those records.
   State employees are required to report and itemize travel and
meal expenses. But elected officials who hold offices named in the
Constitution have long been thought to be exempt from that
requirement.
   Pulaski County Prosecutor Chris Piazza says Clark entertained
supporters on the taxpayers' tab to generate campaign contributions
that ended up in his pocket. ``To support his lifestyle, he would
wine and dine some of his biggest contributors at the state's
expense,'' Piazza said at a pretrial hearing.
   The attorney general's salary is $26,500, among the lowest for
the office in the nation, as mandated by the Arkansas Constitution.
Clark also gets $1,250 a month in public relations money from the
state with no itemized accounting required.
   His deposits in a personal checking account for three years
beginning July 1986 were at least twice as much as his net income,
a state auditor, James Ridgell, said at a pretrial hearing. Clark
deposited less money in each of those three years than he withdrew,
Ridgell said.
   The auditor said $28,564 of state money was spent by Clark on
nonbusiness or personal expenses in the same three years.
   He also said Democratic National Committee member Ed Miller of
Texarkana donated $14,000 to Clark or his campaign in the
three-year period. The money was almost immediately put in Clark's
personal account to pay bills, including an electric bill 18 months
overdue.
   Miller, U.S. Circuit Judge Richard S. Arnold and U.S. Rep. Tommy
Robinson, R-Ark., are among the 249 people subpoenaed for the
trial, which is expected to last three weeks.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0046 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 1603EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-NuclearProject     10-21 0296</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Nuclear Project,0323</SECOND>
<HEAD>University of Missouri Ordered to Shut Down Nuclear Research
Project</HEAD>
<DATELINE>COLUMBIA, Mo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An administrative judge for the federal
Nuclear Regulatory Commission has ordered the University of
Missouri to shut down a nuclear research project, citing a
possibility of danger to the public.
   Administrative Judge Peter B. Bloch said in an order issued
Saturday that the university had failed to comply with nuclear
licensing regulations. ``Hence, I presume that the activities are
unduly dangerous to public safety,'' he wrote.
   Bloch noted that a fire battalion chief had indicated he would
respond to fires at the laboratory but ``might stand by while the
laboratory burned'' because he had not been supplied with a
firefighting plan.
   Bloch said that problem alone would have swayed him to stop the
project.
   The project involves efforts to separate the most long-lived
elements of nuclear waste from short-lived ones that will soon lose
their radioactivity.
   Environmental groups and 10 individuals had challenged the
university's request to the Nuclear Regulatory Commission for
changes in its nuclear licenses. The changes were needed for the
project.
   University spokesman Mary Still said lawyers for the school
hoped to file documents or talk with the judge Monday to end the
temporary shutdown order.
   Still said the university had complied with all federal
regulations regarding the project.
   ``We have an excellent safety record,'' she said.
   Mark Haim, director of the Mid-Missouri Nuclear Weapons Freeze,
said the judge's order was good news.
   ``We are very pleased. It validates what we've been saying all
along.''
   The project began about Feb. 1 and will take four years, said
Truman Storvick, principal investigator for the project. The
university is working under a contract for the project with
Rockwell International, an aerospace, electronics and automotive
technology corporation based in California.
   The project is jointly sponsored by the U.S. Department of
Energy and Japanese firms.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0047 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 1616EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BRF--DiverKilled     10-21 0143</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Diver Killed,0165</SECOND>
<HEAD>Diver Dies in Wreck of USS San Diego</HEAD>
<DATELINE>YAPHANK, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A diver was killed when he ran out of air
in the wreck of the U.S.S. San Diego, a World War I cruiser
submerged upside down 15 miles off the Long Island coast, police
said.
   The diver, whose name was not immediately released, became
separated from a group shortly after 10 a.m. Saturday while inside
the wreckage. He was found a short time later entangled in a guide
line with an empty air tank, Suffolk County police said.
   At least seven divers are known to have lost their lives in the
13,600-ton ship, which lies 80 feet below the surface off the coast
of Fire Island.
   The San Diego is the only U.S. ship sunk by the Germans in World
War I. Six crewmen died during the 1918 attack, caused either by a
torpedo or a mine laid by a U-boat, and 1,108 crew were rescued.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0048 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 1618EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Nicaragua     10-21 0345</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Nicaragua,0392</SECOND>
<HEAD>Curfew in Place to Quell Riots In Nicaragua's Caribbean Region</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RODOLFO GARCIA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MANAGUA, Nicaragua (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The government imposed a curfew in a
large area along Nicaragua's northeast Caribbean coast after
rioting and looting broke out there last week, an official said
here Sunday.
   Information Minister Danilo Lacayo told reporters that
authorities had taken control of the situation in the autonomous
region about 450 miles northeast of the capital. But he refused to
disclose what happened there.
   Newspapers and other media in Managua said riots broke out
Thursday because of food and other shortages in Puerto Cabezas, 450
miles northeast of Managua, and that several people were killed.
   News reports from the isolated, sparsely populated Atlantic
Coast have been contradictory. The area, inhabited mostly by
English-speaking descendants of escaped slaves and Miskito, Sumo
and Rama Indians, has been isolated from the rest of Nicaragua for
centuries.
   Sources said the 11 p.m. to 6 a.m. curfew was imposed Friday.
Most government officials refused to provide information about the
riots, and there are no telephone links to Puerto Cabezas, the main
port in the region.
   The newspaper La Prensa and other pro-government media accused
the opposition Sandinistas of setting off the riots. The Sandinista
media claimed some 300 former Contra rebels of the Yatama Indian
organization did the rioting.
   Radio Sandino said in a broadcast Saturday night the former
Contras looted a warehouse in Puerto Cabezas belonging to a
Moravian Protestant church and stole food there.
   The Contras, including various Indian groups, were backed by the
United States in their fight to overthrow the Sandinistas during
the decade the leftist party was in power.
   President Violeta Barrios de Chamorro led a coalition that
defeated the Sandinistas in Feb. 25 elections. Since taking office
April 25 she has struggled to pull the country out of a grave
economic crisis.
   Under a deal between the government and the Sandinistas, the
Nicaraguan Defense Ministry is still controlled by Gen. Humberto
Ortega, a former Sandinista official.
   The Contras were disbanded shortly after Ms. Barrios de Chamorro
took office, but many of them are having a hard time finding jobs
and settling down. There have been reports that a few former rebels
were still launching attacks against the government.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0049 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 1621EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Gulf-FormerHostage Bjt   10-21 0518</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Former Hostage, Bjt,0672</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ex-Hostage in Tehran Embassy a Quiet Celebrity in Saudi Arabia</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto DHA5</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MORT ROSENBLUM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Special Correspondent</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>IN EASTERN SAUDI ARABIA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   This is Marine Lt. Steve
Kirtley's second time in a Middle East crisis with no rotation date
out. But last time, as a hostage in Iran, he was less confident of
getting home.
   ``I don't understand why some of the younger Marines are so set
on going home right away,'' said Kirtley, of Little Rock, Ark.,
shaking a close-cropped blond head that is fit for a recruiting
poster. At 32, he leads a combat supply company.
   On Nov. 4, 1979, he was asleep at the Marine guards' quarters at
the U.S. Embassy in Tehran when 5,000 Iranians stormed the walls
and seized all 52 Americans inside.
   As a young corporal, he spent 444 days helping calm others while
he was just as worried himself. It has made him a better man, he
said, but he still does not like waiting around.
   ``I sit and I think about the waiting,'' he said of his
experience now in the desert. ``It's kind of like being a hostage.
We're here, and we don't know when the hell we're going home. But
we have it a little better. At least I know I'm going home.''
   Kirtley, who now oversees trucks, learned the hard way what
Middle East deserts can do to machines. During the hostage ordeal,
a U.S. helicopter rescue attempt failed when three helicopters were
disabled in a sandstorm and other aircraft were thwarted by dust.
   The mission, dubbed Desert One, was aborted when the blade of a
helicopter fouled by sand struck a C130 transport plane and
triggered a ball of flame which lit up the nighttime sky.
   After Iran, he lectured to potential recruits. He decided to be
a drill instructor in San Diego. Then he was accepted for officer
training at the University of Florida in Gainesville.
   He was stationed in Hawaii and Camp Pendleton, Calif. For the
last 62 days, he was been within striking distance of the Iraq
border with the 1st Marine Expeditionary Force.
   Kirtley is a moviemaker's Marine, 200 pounds of sculpted bulk,
with corn-colored hair on a sunburned neck. As a football player,
he played lineman for the University of Florida in a Gator Bowl.
   Strict Saudi customs don't bother him. He doesn't drink anyway,
and says his wife's letters are all the female companionship he
needs.
   Kirtley's past has made him a celebrity among the older hands.
For most younger Marines, America's last hostage crisis is vague
history.
   ``They want to know about it,'' he said. ``They ask what
happened, what I did, how it was.''
   Mostly, Kirtley is concerned with getting freight on the road.
His trucks move ammunition, water, food and fuel to Marine units
scattered across a wide sweep of Arabian sands.
   He speaks proudly how the service support group has driven
500,000 miles while moving 27 million pounds in two months.
   Sometimes the idea of imminent war seems to recede, but Kirtley
knows the dangers. In three days, he noted, the Marines will
commemorate the 1983 Beirut terrorist bombing which killed 241 of
their comrades.
   Kirtley's unit is better off than some, with hot food and a
small post exchange nearby.
   Outside his camouflage-netting tent, a smaller shelter is
jokingly labeled in large letters, ``HBO Available.''
   ``I'm luckier, with a company to command,'' he said. ``I can sit
around at night and worry about things ... It keeps me busy.''
   He also thinks about the occasions he is missing. His birthday
was Oct. 18. His wedding anniversary was Aug. 23.
   Asked if he had a word for his mother in Little Rock, Kirtley
allowed himself a rare, brief smile. He replied:
   ``Tell her, `Hi, Mom. I'm doing a little better than the last
time I was here, and I hope to be home sooner.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0050 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 1623EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-GettingDiplomas 1stLd-Writethru a0660 10-21 0519</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Getting Diplomas, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0660,570</SECOND>
<HEAD>or Release at 6:30 p.m. EDT, time set by source</HEAD>
<HEAD>Fewer Dropouts Seek GED Diplomas</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: Subs 3rd graf, ``The number xxx to CORRECT Develop to
Development in name of organization</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By TAMARA HENRY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Education Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Educators say evidence that fewer dropouts
seek high school equivalency diplomas may threaten the nation's
economic future.
   In a study of diploma candidates, the American Council on
Education found 683,000 took the tests during 1989, 7 percent less
than in 1988 and less than 1.3 percent of the 43 million adults
over 18 without a high school diploma.
   The number of candidates aged 18 to 24 declined by 26 percent,
and only half of the drop may be due to the 12.5 percent decrease
in the size of the U.S. population within that age range during
this period, according to the study released Sunday by the
council's General Educational Development (GED) Testing Service.
   ``If young people are choosing to work rather than complete
their schooling, the price may be high for both individuals and
society -individuals lose opportunities for additional training,
advanced education, better jobs, and higher wages, while society
loses the increased productivity of better educated, more highly
skilled workers,'' said the study.
   ``In order to qualify for training, further education, jobs, and
higher earnings, these adults must have opportunities to earn high
school diplomas.''
   Earning diplomas were 376,000 who took the tests, which
represents about 18 percent of all high school diplomas awarded
that year, said the study.
   Program director Douglas R. Whitney and Janet Baldwin, senior
research associate, said the study showed a great need for more
outreach efforts to increase access to programs for high school
completion.
   ``The GED is the gateway to educational and economic opportunity
for millions of Americans,'' said Whitney. ``It's a matter of
national concern that too many adults who would benefit from these
opportunities find their paths blocked by obstacles that could be
removed by more enlightened policies and programs to facilitate
their participation.''
   Since 1942, the GED program has been recognized nationwide by
employers and colleges. Adults must surpass the performance of
about 30 percent of a national sample of graduating high school
seniors to earn equivalency diplomas and qualify for college
enrollment, training programs, jobs and job advancement.
   In other key findings, the study showed:
   -About 200,000 adults, or 33 percent of candidates in 1989, took
the GED Tests primarily to meet educational admissions
requirements, compared with 29.1 percent in 1980.
   -The percentage of candidates who took the tests for employment
reasons declined from 38.6 percent in 1980 to 32.2 percent in 1989.
   -The proportion of Hispanic candidates increased from 6.8
percent in 1980 to 11.2 percent in 1989, while the percentage of
black candidates fell from 17.1 percent in 1980 to 14.2 percent in
1989.
   -The percentage of GED candidates who reported having left
school due to pregnancy or marriage tripled. In 1989, one in five
adults taking the GED Tests, 19.7 percent, cited this reason as the
most important, compared with 6.4 percent in 1980.
   -In 1980, 68.5 percent and in 1989, 69.9 percent reported having
completed 10th grade or higher before leaving high school, while
36.9 percent in 1980 and 38.6 percent in 1989 reported having
completed 11th grade or higher.
   -About three of every four candidates reported having grades
while in school of ``mostly 'C' or better'' in both 1980, 76.8
percent and 1989, 74 percent. More than one in five candidates
reported in-school grades of ``mostly 'B' or better''in 1980, 23.2
percent and in 1989, 21.5 percent.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0051 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 1630EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p AM-FloridaGovernor 1stLd-Writethru a0667 10-21 0571</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Florida Governor, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0667,660</SECOND>
<HEAD>Chiles Runs a Crusade That May Hurt Him</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: Subs 2nd graf, ``Gov. Bob Martinex xxx to update fund-raising
figure from $9 million to $10.2 million</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By DAN SEWELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Democrat Lawton Chiles has made his run for Florida
governor a crusade against big-money politics, and now he may have
to pay the price.
   Gov. Bob Martinez has waged a $9 million campaign, erased his
opponent's lead and is on the move with sharp attacks on Chiles'
Senate record.
   ``We've gone up, and my opponent has declined, and the campaign
is where it was about this time in 1986,'' said a delighted
Martinez. Four years ago, Republican Martinez defeated Democrat
Steve Pajcic, becoming only the second GOP governor in Florida
since Reconstruction.
   Chiles held double-digit leads in the polls shortly after he
joined the race last April. He and running mate Buddy MacKay
declared a campaign against the politics of special interests.
   Chiles has a self-imposed $100 limit on contributions. Some
59,000 people - by far a state record - have donated to his
campaign. But the approach has brought in just over $4 million.
   The latest polls show the race a dead heat.
   In recent days, Martinez has sought to capitalize on the federal
budget mess, calling Chiles and MacKay ``Washington insiders'' and
members of ``the liberal Eastern establishment.'' Chiles was Senate
budget chairman when he retired and MacKay is a former three-term
congressman. Chiles retired at the end of his third Senate term in
January 1989.
   Chiles suggests Martinez is the insider and that it's time for a
change.
   ``I think he senses that people are ready to turn the rascals
out, and he's trying to turn it away from himself,'' Chiles said.
   Both parties consider this a watershed election in the state,
with Democrats, still the majority party, trying to come back after
a decade of Republican gains.
   Chiles is worried about Martinez' commercials.
   Two of them say Chiles repeatedly voted against senior citizens
in the Senate.
   ``I want you all to be my truth squad and go out and set the
record straight,'' Chiles told a meeting of the American
Association of Retired Persons.
   Chiles says his votes reflect the dilemma posed by the federal
deficit.
   He says he helped start many senior programs and increased
funding in most cases, but did cast votes against some
``budget-busters.''
   Martinez says Chiles will raise taxes.
   Chiles said fast-growing Florida will need to increase revenues,
but he first wants to see how Martinez has managed $3.8 billion in
a variety of tax increases since taking office.
   The Republican has turned down all but one Oct. 30 debate
appearance.
   The governor didn't want to be set up in debates sponsored by
pro-Chiles groups, explained Martinez' campaign manager, J.M.
``Mac'' Stipanovich.
   Chiles, 60, used six debates against Democratic primary foe Rep.
Bill Nelson to help push aside questions about his vitality.
   Chiles, who said he was burned out after three terms in the
Senate, takes the anti-depressant drug Prozac.
   Both camps also are seeking big-time help.
   President Bush made two campaign appearances for Martinez. The
governor's staff - which includes presidential son Jeb Bush as
campaign chairman - hopes for another.
   Chiles is calling in Georgia Sen. Sam Nunn to tour the
military-minded Florida Panhandle this week.
   One issue that hasn't been central to the race is abortion.
   Martinez last year called an ill-fated special legislative
session in hopes of further restricting abortion.
   But Chiles says he won't use what polls indicate could be an
effective weapon.
   Most Floridians identify themselves as for abortion rights.
   Chiles personally opposes abortion and has cast anti-abortion
votes in the past, but he supports a woman's choice. After
listening to a female supporter fervently ask him to highlight the
abortion issue, Chiles threw his arms up and said no.
   ``I have to do what my conscience tells me,'' he said. ``I'm
comfortable telling people what my position is, but I'm not
comfortable in making a big deal issue about it.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0052 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 1632EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-McCrea     10-21 0507</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-McCrea,0653</SECOND>
<HEAD>Joel McCrea, Leading Man Best Known For Westerns, Dead at 84</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT JABLON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Joel McCrea's death was seen as an end of a
Hollywood era, another passing of a show business cowboy who
personified the Old West.
   ``He was the last great `A' Western film cowboy,'' said John
Langellier, director of the research center at the Gene Autry
Western Heritage Museum.
   ``Along with Randolph Scott and certainly a few others like John
Wayne and Gary Cooper, he created the strong, silent stereotype of
the rugged Western hero,'' Langellier said. ``There will never be
another like him. His death marks the end of an era.''
   McCrea died Saturday at age 84 in the Motion Picture and
Television Fund Hospital. His wife of 57 years, actress Frances
Dee, and son, Peter, were with him at the time.
   Following private services, McCrea will be cremated and his
ashes scattered at sea, Peter McCrea said. McCrea also leaves sons
Jody and David.
   McCrea's last public appearance was Oct. 1, with first lady
Barbara Bush at a Beverly Hills fund-raising dinner for Republican
gubernatorialcandidate Pete Wilson.
   After her speech, Mrs. Bush went over to McCrea, took his hand,
and said, ``My hero,'' said A.C. Lyles, a friend of McCrea's for
many years.
   ``He lit up,'' Lyles said. ``That summed up everybody's feeling
about Joel.''
   Descended from pioneers - one grandfather fought Apache Indians
and drove stagecoaches - McCrea's early ambition was to own a
ranch.
   ``He loved the outdoors. He loved the West and history of the
West,'' said producer Walter Mirisch, who worked on six films with
McCrea.
   While most of his 87 roles were Westerns, McCrea also was adept
at light comedy and drama. He was the trenchcoat-wearing reporter
in Alfred Hitchcock's 1940 ``Foreign Correspondent.''
   ``He had the quality of childlike innocence, and yet there was a
strength of character that comes through,'' said Peter McCrea.
``When the chips were down, you felt he could handle a situation.''
   One of McCrea's comedies, ``Sullivan's Travels,'' was listed by
the Library of Congress as one of 25 outstanding films worthy of
historic preservation. The 1941 film was written and directed by
Preston Sturges.
   ``I think one reason he appealed to Sturges was his low-key
style,'' Peter McCrea said. ``He wasn't a superstar, and he
wouldn't overwhelm the story. He didn't try to be an actor's actor.
He tried to play the part the way it would be if he were in that
person's shoes.''
   In a 1985 interview, McCrea said he always ``wanted to be the
guy who rode off into the sunset,'' to represent ``right over
evil.''
   Born in South Pasadena, he grew up in Hollywood and got his
start in movies as a volunteer ``horse holder'' for Western stars
Tom Mix and William S. Hart.
   At 12, McCrea got his first paying job riding a horse in a movie
mob scene.
   ``They dressed me up in buckskins and for two days' work I was
paid $5,'' McCrea once said. ``Boy, that appealed to my Scotch
blood. I forgot about wanting to be a cowboy and decided to be an
actor.''
   Bob Ward, a friend who said he first met McCrea in 1947, said
McCrea told him about a conversation he had with cowboy comedian
Will Rogers, who ``told him that he was not a very good actor so
he'd better buy some real estate.''
   In the 1930s, McCrea and his wife bought a ranch in Ventura
County, northwest of Los Angeles, that eventually totalled nearly
3,000 acres.
   McCrea later made millions of dollars when he sold off parcels
to developers. He kept about 300 acres.
   In April 1969, McCrea was inducted into the Hall of Fame of
Great Western Actors in Oklahoma City.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0053 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 1701EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-WarmWeather     10-21 0253</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Warm Weather,250</SECOND>
<NOTE>For release at 6:30 p.m. EDT; time set by source</NOTE>
<HEAD>World Temperatures Set Record Last Spring</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The average worldwide surface air temperature
was the warmest on record last spring, a Commerce Department agency
said Sunday.
   Temperature readings recorded at 63 sites around the globe
during March, April and May averaged more than 1.5 degrees
Fahrenheit above the 30-year average of 54 degrees, said Dr. James
K. Angell of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration's
air resources laboratory.
   The readings were about 0.5 degrees warmer than the previous
highest temperature recorded in the March-May period, Angell said.
   He cautioned that his analysis should not be construed as
confirming claims that global warming is occurring. During the
June-August period, the global surface temperature was only about
0.5 degrees above average.
   He termed that a ``typical value for this season'' over the past
decade.
   The most unusually warm temperatures recorded in the March-May
period were in the Arctic, where temperatures were about 7.2
degrees above average and 4.5 degrees higher than previously
observed, Angell said.
   At the same time, the temperature in the 30,000-foot to
60,000-foot altitude range was about 10.8 degrees below normal,
Angell said.
   He said scientists were trying to determine whether very cold
temperatures in the stratosphere might also be associated with
destruction of the Earth's protective ozone layer in the Arctic
region.
   He said preliminary evaluation of ozone data in the Arctic last
spring showed concentrations 8 percent lower than the average of
the previous decade, and 2 percent lower than in th next lowest
year, 1986.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0054 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 1701EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ToxicDumping     10-21 0240</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Toxic Dumping,0260</SECOND>
<HEAD>Machine Company Must Stand Trial on Felony Toxic Waste Charges</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SAN FRANCISCO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A machine company has been ordered to stand
trial on five felony counts of dumping thousands of tons of
hazardous waste at an old Navy shipyard.
   Judge Charles James issued his ruling on Friday after an
11-month preliminary hearing, which is the longest conducted in an
environmental case in California.
   The civil action against Triple A Machine Shop also is San
Francisco's first felony toxic pollution case, said prosecutor
Steve Castleman, who's in the district attorney's environmental
unit.
   The prosecution is seeking fines of $5,000 to $10,000 for each
day that hazardous waste remains on site at the Hunters Point Navy
Shipyard, a 500-acre facility the company leased from the Navy from
1976 to 1986. According to estimates, it could cost $100 million to
clean up the site.
   The district attorney's office alleges that the company dumped
waste oil and acids, polychlorinated biphenyls, asbestos,
sandblasting materials contaminated with lead and copper and other
hazardous wastes.
   Triple A's attorneys, Fred Blum and Carmen Trutanich, said they
considered the preliminary hearing a success since the number of
felony counts pending against the company was reduced from an
original 16.
   Trutanich added that the Navy should be prosecuted in the case
because it allegedly dumped hazardous materials at the site for
years before Triple A leased the facility.
   ``It's ludicrous that we're going through this now without the
Navy sitting next to me in the defendant's chair,'' Trutanich said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0055 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 1646EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Israel-Violence 2ndLd-Writethru a0704 10-21 0746</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel-Violence, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0704,0902</SECOND>
<HEAD>Knife-Wielding Attacker Kills Three Israelis</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 10 grafs to UPDATE with details, scene of suspect
shown on Israeli television. Pick up 8th graf pvs, `Angry
Israelis...' ADDS 1 graf at bottom on Gaza incident.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos JRL1-3, LaserColor JRL103</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ALLYN FISHER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An Arab laborer shouting ``God is Great!''
stabbed three Israelis to death Sunday as he rampaged through a
Jewish neighborhood, apparently seeking revenge for the Temple
Mount killings, police said.
   One victim managed to shoot and wound the attacker, who was then
seized by furious residents, ending the rampage in the Baka area of
southern Jerusalem, police said.
   The attack inflamed tensions in the capital and brought in a
stream of police reinforcements as vengeance-seeking Jews took
briefly to the streets.
   Police spokesman Aharon Elchayani said his forces would bar
Arabs from traveling into Jerusalem on Monday.
   Two Palestinian factions claimed responsibility for Sunday's
attack, but police said they believed the assailant acted alone.
The suspect was identified as Omar Abu Sirhan, a 19-year-old Arab
laborer from the village of Ubbadiyeh in the occupied West Bank.
   Police said his motive apparently was revenge for the Oct. 8
blood bath on the Temple Mount, in which Israeli police fired at
stone-throwing Palestinians, killing at least 19 of them.
   Avi Cohen, the officer leading the interrogation, said the
attacker seemed to have chosen his victims at random. He said Abu
Sirhan had no known criminal background.
   Israel television showed scenes of Abu Sirhan being led down a
corridor by policemen. He wore a bloodstained hospital smock, his
head and leg were bandaged and his ankles were chained.
   Shouting ``Allahu Akbar'' - Arabic for ``God Is Great'' - the
attacker killed an 18-year-old woman soldier, a 43-year-old garden
nursery owner and a 28-year-old member of an elite police
anti-terrorism unit, police said.
   The off-duty police officer managed to shoot the assailant as he
was being attacked.
   Angry Israeli youths stoned Arab-owned cars on a Jerusalem
highway. Shouts of ``Death to the Arabs!'' resounded in the streets
of Baka.
   Defense Minister Moshe Arens voiced fears that Arab-Jewish
communal violence was reducing prospects of a Mideast peace
settlement. He told Israel television that he feared ``a chasm is
opening.''
   Jerusalem Mayor Teddy Kollek appealed for calm, saying the
attack was ``a tough test of people's patience and tolerance.''
   Some Israeli politicians demanded broader powers for troops and
police to fire on attackers. They also said the off-duty policeman
should have immediately shot the assailant dead. Instead, the
officer fired his pistol in the air, then shot the attacker in the
legs.
   ``If someone attacks with intent to kill, he should be killed on
the spot,'' Agriculture Minister Raphael Eitan said.
   Prime Minister Yitzhak Shamir's senior adviser, Avi Pazner, said
the U.N. Security Council's condemnation of Israel for the Temple
Mount clash created ``an atmosphere that incites extremist actions
against innocent Jewish civilians.''
   After the killings on Temple Mount, known in Arabic as Haram
es-Sharif, leaflets distributed by leaders of the 34-month-old
Palestinian uprising called for vengeance in these ``bloody days of
total escalation.''
   According to police accounts, the rampage began when the Arab
plunged his 16-inch blade into the chest of Iris Azulai, 18, just
outside her home. He then ran to a nearby street where he slightly
injured a 13-year-old boy, then assaulted nursery owner Eli
Eltratz, stabbing him fatally in the chest.
   Police said the assailant used a knife. Israel radio said the
weapon was the bayonet of a Kalashnikov assault rifle.
   The off-duty policeman, Charlie Chelouche, wearing civilian
clothes, fired two warning shots in the air and then shot the
attacker twice in the legs, but was himself stabbed in the chest.
   The two struggled in a dusty lot outside a preschool for 3- and
4-year-olds, where Abu Sirhan was arrested. Afterward, witnesses
covered the bloodstains with dirt.
   Miri Rechtshaffer, a neighbor, said she was in bed when she
heard the first victim screaming: ```I'm being stabbed, I'm being
stabbed!'''
   ``Then I saw her on the street dying, and now she is dead. So
beautiful, killed only two minutes from her home,'' Mrs.
Rechtshaffer said, weeping.
   The slain young woman was buried in Jerusalem nine hours later
in a military funeral attended by about 1,000 mourners.
   ``Iris, my flower,'' cried her mother as the coffin was lowered
and clumps of earth thudded softly onto the pine. Wails rose from
the crowd.
   ``Iris ... her only crime was that she was a Jew,'' said the
chaplain.
   An anonymous phone caller to a Western news agency in Amman,
Jordan, claimed the Islamic Front for the Liberation of Palestine
had carried out the attack in revenge for the Temple Mount
killings.
   A news agency in Jerusalem received a telephone claim on behalf
of the Palestine Liberation Organization's Force 17.
   During the uprising, 761 Palestinians have been killed by
Israeli soldiers or civilians, and 283 by fellow Arabs, most on
suspicion of collaborating with Israel. Before Sunday, at least 48
Israelis had died in the violence.
   On Sunday, an Arab man suspected of collaborating with Israel
was kidnapped by masked Palestinian activists from his Gaza Strip
home on Sunday and shot to death, Arab reports said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0056 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 1702EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Germany-Soviets     10-21 0228</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Germany-Soviets,0260</SECOND>
<HEAD>Lawyer Says 700 Soviet Soldiers on the Run</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Soviet human rights lawyer claims that about 700
Red Army troops, underfed and ill-treated at their bases, have
deserted and fled into the woods of eastern Germany, German media
reported Sunday.
   The German weekly magazine Bunte quoted Moscow defense attorney
Oleg Lyamin as saying some of the soldiers were armed and had been
stealing food to stay alive.
   Lyamin has been defending a Soviet army deserter in Weimar,
about 150 miles southwest of Berlin. A military court on Oct. 12
exonerated the soldier, who claimed he fled his unit when other
troops tried to extort money from him.
   The Berliner Morgenpost on Sunday quoted Lyamin as saying that
nearly 1,000 Soviet soldiers die each year in Eastern European
units due to bullying and brutality.
   He made the charges during ``open door'' day at a Soviet base in
Weimar, the newspaper said.
   There are an estimated 380,000 Soviet soldiers stationed in
former East German territory. The Soviet troops are scheduled to
completely pull out by 1994.
   Living standards of Soviet soldiers have deteriorated in the
months following the July 1 economic union of the Germanys, which
unified politically on Oct. 1. Soviet privates earn about $16 a
month, and prices in the east have risen sharply.
   The Interior Ministry in Bonn last week said 53 Soviet soldiers
have demanded aslyum in Germany. But the number could be much
higher, because it takes weeks for the cases to be registered.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0057 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 1650EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-WeatherpageWeather     10-21 0326</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Weatherpage Weather,0386</SECOND>
<HEAD>Heavy Rain in South</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Rain was scattered across the South on Sunday, and rain and high
wind lashed the Pacific Northwest.
   Showers and thunderstorms associated with a slowly moving cold
front were over Arkansas, Louisiana, and eastern and south-central
sections of Texas during the afternoon, with some locally heavy
rain.
   Showers and thunderstorms also produced locally heavy rain over
northern and central Florida.
   Heavier rainfall totals for the six hours up to 2 p.m. EDT
included 2.31 inches at Shreveport, La.; 1.70 inches at Mayport,
Fla.; 1.37 at Fort Polk, La.; 1.33 at Pine Bluff, Ark.; 1.24 inches
at Daytona Beach, Fla.; 1.11 inches at San Antonio, Texas; and 1.10
at Alexandria, La.
   Killeen, Texas, got 2.99 inches of rain during the 12-hour
period up to 2 p.m. EDT.
   A cold front crossing the northern Pacific Coast region carried
rain and high wind to parts of Washington and Oregon.
   Quillayute, Wash., got 1.49 inches in six hours during the
night.
   Showers were scattered from eastern Washington state into the
northern Rocky Mountains.
   Strong southwesterly wind blew over the northern high Plains,
with a gust to 66 mph during the morning at Livingston, Mont.
   Blustery northwesterly wind carried cold air into Oklahoma and
Texas during the afternoon.
   Temperatures in the 70s extended as far north as the Carolinas
and southern sections of the Ohio Valley.
   But clouds and northwesterly wind kept afternoon temperatures in
the 30s and 40s across the northern half of the Mississippi Valley,
and afternoon readings were mostly in the 40s from the Dakotas to
the northern and central high Plains.
   Temperatures were in the 40s and 50s across much of the West,
and in the 80s in the desert Southwest.
   Overnight temperatures dipped into the teens and 20s in the
Great Basin that includes Nevada and western Utah, and in the
Rockies.
   Readings dipped below freezing during the night across upstate
New York and northern New England, over the Texas Panhandle and
Oklahoma Panhandle, and from the northern and central high Plains
to Minnesota.
   Wheat Ridge, Colo., tied its record low for the date of 23.
   Sunday's low for the Lower 48 states was 3 above zero at
Gunnison, Colo.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0058 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 1706EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-El-Alamein     10-21 0208</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-El-Alamein,0224</SECOND>
<HEAD>Thousands Killed in Tank Battle Remembered</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   EL-ALAMEIN, Egypt (AP) - World War II veterans, diplomats and
dignitaries on Sunday honored thousands of soldiers killed in a
tank battle that stopped Germany's march through North Africa 48
years ago.
   The battles of El-Alamein pitted Axis forces led by Field
Marshal Erwin Rommel against Allied armies of British Field Marshal
Bernard Law Montgomery.
   The Allies lost 13,500 dead and wounded. Half the forces of
Germany and Italy - close to 60,000 men - were killed, wounded or
captured in the battle that turned the tide against Nazi forces.
   The vast desert battlefield 190 miles northeast of Cairo
includes a military museum and separate memorials for the fallen
soldiers from Italy, Germany and the British Commonwealth.
   Since 1978, ceremonies honoring the dead have been held on the
Sunday falling closest to Oct. 23, when the battle began in 1942.
   The ceremony is held at a different monument each year. This
year was Italy's turn.
   Sunday's ceremony opened with prayers at the modernistic Italian
monument atop a seaside hill. A band played solemn music as
officials, diplomats and aged veterans placed wreaths at the
monument.
   Security was heavy, reflecting concerns in the wake of last
week's assassination in Cairo of Rifaat el-Mahgoub, the speaker of
Egypt's parliament.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0059 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 1710EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Britain-TaxProtest     10-21 0306</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Britain-Tax Protest,0348</SECOND>
<HEAD>Demonstrators, Police Accuse Each Other of Prompting Violence</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By EDITH M. LEDERER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Protesters and police on Sunday traded accusations
over who was to blame for violence that marred a demonstration the
day before against Britain's controversial poll tax.
   Saturday's protest was the second violent anti-tax demonstration
this year. An demonstration in Trafalgar Square on March 31 turned
into one of the worst riots in London this century.
   Home Secretary David Waddington demanded a report from police on
the riot Saturday that left six officers and six civilians injured
and resulted in 120 arrests. Five shops were damaged.
   The confrontation began after a a crowd estimated by police at
2,500 left a peaceful anti-tax rally at Brockwell Park in south
London. They marched to Brixton Prison to show solidarity with four
prisoners jailed after the Trafalgar Square riot.
   Dave Morris, coordinator of the Trafalgar Square Defendants
Campaign, which organized the protest, told a news conference
Sunday that police staged ``a pre-planned attack in order to
discredit the poll tax movement.''
   He accused officers of ``incompetence and brutality.''
   Scotland Yard said it stood by the comments made Saturday night
by Deputy Assistant Commissioner John Metcalfe, who blamed the
violence on ``the anarchist movement.''
   ``I've no doubt at all that the people who started the violence
intended it and came to the demonstration intending it,'' he said.
   More than 2,000 extra police were on duty to prevent a
repetition of the Trafalgar Square riot. That rioting left 331
police and 86 civilians injured, caused hundreds of thousands of
dollars in damage, and led to 341 arrests.
   The poll tax is part of Mrs. Thatcher's crusade to wipe out
British socialism by hitting at its last bastion - local
government. Instead of a tax on property owners, the community
charge is paid by every adult, and the amount is determined by the
local council.
   Critics say the tax is unfair because all adults in a district
pay the same charge, regardless of wealth.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0060 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 1711EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BRF--KilaueaVolcano     10-21 0123</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Kilauea Volcano,0114</SECOND>
<HEAD>Lava from Kilauea Overruns Another House</HEAD>
<DATELINE>KAIMU, Hawaii (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Lava flowing from the Kilauea Volcano
burned down a fourth home Sunday in the Kalapana Shores subdivision
and threatened to wipe out what little is left of the coastal
community.
   All seven homes remaining in the subdivision are in immediate
danger of being overrun by the flow, said Hawaii County Civil
Defense administrator Harry Kim.
   The home destroyed Sunday was the first since Thursday as lava
flowed along the coastal area fronting the ocean subdivision.
   The recent loss of homes in Kalapana Shores brings to 180 the
number destroyed since the current volcanic eruption began in
January 1983.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0061 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 1705EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Soviet-Politics     10-21 0608</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Politics,0707</SECOND>
<HEAD>Russian Groups Form Largest Soviet Opposition Movement</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto MOSB1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By THOMAS GINSBERG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   More than 30 Russian groups united on Sunday to
form the nation's largest political bloc opposing the Communist
Party, and the new movement demanded that Kremlin leaders resign.
   National legislators and key officials of the Russian republic
attended the two-day founding conference of the Democratic Russia
Movement, the broadest grouping yet to openly challenge President
Mikhail S. Gorbachev.
   But the conference glossed over sharply divergent views among
the republic's various groups, and gave them the right to pull out
of the movement. The movement's chances of becoming a unified
political force were uncertain.
   Many small parties have been created since the Communist Party
surrendered its constitutionally guaranteed monopoly on power last
February. None, including the new bloc, have anywhere near the
Communists' 18 million members. The new movement joined
Christian Democrats with labor unions, scholars with peasants, and
Red Army officers with disabled veterans. They united around a
sweeping platform that called for Russian sovereignty as well as
the resignation of Gorbachev and his prime minister, Nikolai
Ryzhkov.
   The platform underlined growing disenchantment with the Soviet
leader.
   The conference also formed a commission to organize ``civil
disobedience'' if necessary. It was not clear under what conditions
civil disobedience would be used.
   It delegated another commission to find ways to create a market
economy in Russia, the largest and most populous of the 15 Soviet
republics.
   A fledgling coalition between Gorbachev and Boris N. Yeltsin,
the reformist president of the Russian republic, fell apart after
the Soviet president balked at the radical economic program backed
by Yeltsin.
   ``Gorbachev finally showed that he has moved to the right'' by
rejecting radical economic reforms last week, prominent legislator
Yuri Boldyrev told the 1,272 delegates. They met in a central
Moscow movie theater.
   After his speech, delegates voted by a show of hands to approve
a draft declaration forming the Democratic Russia Movement, then
applauded for nearly a minute in a standing ovation.
   ``The task of the movement is coordination of the activities for
the unity of democratic forces ... to carry out the progressive,
radical political and economic reforms in Russia,'' according to
the draft, published Sunday by the independent Postfactum news
agency.
   The movement will be run by a 21-member Coordinating Council and
will include a Council of Representatives and consultative body to
make sure all members' views are heard, according to the
declaration.
   The draft also ``guarantees the independence of every associated
member ... in choosing his strategy and tactics.''
   The final version will be published next week in the movement's
newspaper, said Oleg Rumyantsev, leader of the Social Democratic
Party of Russia and member of the new Coordinating Council.
   Following the vote, the celebratory air in the hall subsided and
officials proposed several supplementary planks and dozens of minor
resolutions.
   In an indication of disagreements to come, several delegates
demanded that the initial call only for Ryzhkov's resignation be
expanded to include Gorbachev. Others from the floor applauded the
suggestion.
   ``But we have no union, so what does it matter whether the
president resigns?'' an official retorted. A delegate echoed, ``Why
demand either resign? Just create a market economy and the
government will fall anyway.''
   The delegates changed the wording to include Gorbachev, and the
resolution passed by a large majority.
   Cooperation among the various groups was not assured.
   In a survey of 628 delegates taken Saturday by the independent
firm ``Monitoring,'' nearly a quarter said they would not subsume
their own goals to those of the movement. Only 11 percent said they
would follow the movement over their own party, while 57 percent
said they would seek a compromise position.
   The poll gave no margin of error.
   In a poll of support for leaders, Yeltsin was by far the most
popular with 89 percent, followed by Leningrad Mayor Anatoly
Sobchak with 55 percent. Gorbachev received only 8 percent support.
   The poll concluded that delegates were united mainly in their
opposition to the Communist Party and in their support for Yeltsin.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0062 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 1731EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Infants-AIDS     10-21 0301</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Infants-AIDS,0346</SECOND>
<HEAD>AIDS Test Planned for Babies' Blood Without Consent</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PITTSBURGH (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Tests for the AIDS virus will be conducted on
unidentified blood samples taken routinely from newborn infants in
Pennsylvania without parents' consent, a newspaper reported Sunday.
   The program is designed to measure the presence of the virus in
the general population.
   The state Department of Health begins the federal program next
month, but the project will include about 50,000 blood specimens
taken from infants since July 1 and stored, The Pittsburgh Press
reported.
   Dr. Bobby Jones, epidemiology director for the state Bureau of
AIDS, said the state didn't publicize the program because parents
might have refused all medical tests on their new babies.
   ``We don't want it to have an adverse impact on the metabolic
screening we do,'' Jones said.
   Jones said there was no need for the state to announce the
program because parents won't learn the results. The tests will be
performed on samples after they are stripped of the donor's name
and birth date.
   Some parents objected to the additional testing without their
consent; others did not.
   Janice Stifter of Plum said she was unaware the state was
storing her baby's blood.
   ``But it wouldn't have bothered me if I had known,'' she said.
Her daughter, Laura, was born Aug. 10 at Magee Womens Hospital in
Pittsburgh.
   ``They shouldn't be doing any tests without letting us know,''
said Duane Szymanski, father of 11-week-old Samantha. ``They're
using her blood.''
   Mothers complained of being kept in the dark about their babies'
health.
   ``If my child had AIDS and I wouldn't know, if seems kind of
senseless,'' said Robbie Wojciewchowski. ``I really think they
should let the parents know the results.'' Her daughter, Kimberly,
was born Aug. 22 at Allegheny General.
   State figures show 4,226 people have suffered or are suffering
from fully developed AIDS in Pennsylvania since 1981, when records
were first kept. There are no statistics on people found to be
carrying the virus without developing symptoms.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0063 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 1757EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Malaysia 2ndLd-Writethru a0702 10-21 0529</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Malaysia, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0702,0619</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ruling Coalition Takes Early Election Lead</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: New thruout to UPDATE with results, adds background; No
pickup.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto KL1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KENNETH L. WHITING</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>KUALA LUMPUR, Malaysia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Prime Minister Mahathir Mohamad's
ruling coalition was swept back into power in weekend elections,
defeating a loose grouping of opposition parties.
   With all but one seat accounted for, Mahathir's National Front
coalition had 127 seats in the 180-member lower house, to 48 for
the combined opposition. Four seats went to independents.
   ``We are happy that the people have returned us to power with a
more than two-thirds majority. This will enable us to give a
strong, peaceful and stable government,'' said Mahathir, 64.
   It was his third election victory since becoming prime minister
in 1981.The ruling coalition's lost a few seats overall in the
voting.
   Polling started in remote areas of Sabah and Sarawak states on
Borneo on Saturday. The rest of the country voted Sunday.
   Also at stake was control of 11 of the 13 state legislatures.
Sabah and Sarawak hold separate state elections.
   The ruling coalition had controlled all 13 state bodies up to
Oct. 5, when Mahathir called the elections. But the Sabah United
Party, a Christian party, defected from the coalition on Oct. 15.
   In the weekend's voting, the ruling coalition also lost control
of the legislature in Kelantan, the home state of Tengku Razaleigh
Hamzah, a 53-year-old former ally of Mahathir who now heads the
opposition alliance.
   Malaysia has been ruled by a multiracial coalition, based on
parties made up of different ethnic and racial groups, since
independence in 1957.
   Malays comprise about 53 percent of the population of 17.8
million. Chinese make up about 32 percent, with Indians and other
races making up the balance.
   The National Front includes the Malaysian Chinese Association,
Malaysian Indian Congress and seven smaller parties.
   Malaysia has had seven previous elections since independence,
but in those votes, the fragmented opposition made little headway
against the National Front, establishing only regional bases of
power.
   In the weekend vote, however, the electorate for the first time
had an organized alternative representing the same ethnic mosaic as
the National Front.
   But the campaign was largely devoid of issues, focusing instead
on personality attacks.
   The opposition charged the National Front with economic
mismanagement, corruption, indifference to ethnic tensions and
erosion of judicial powers. None of these allegations made much
impact. The opposition also promised sweeping tax cuts.
   Mahathir claims credit for one of the fastest growing economies
in Southeast Asia and he dismissed the other accusations as
groundless. He derided the promised tax cuts as ``the height of
irresponsibility and money politics.''
   In two major upsets, Defense Minister Ahmed Rithaudden was
defeated in the Kelantan state district of Kota Baharu, and
Science, Technology and Environment Minister Stephen Yong lost in
Sarawak.
   The two-thirds majority won by the ruling coalition is necessary
to amend the constitution and symbolic as a measure of the prime
minister's power. In the old Parliament, the coalition held 133 of
the 177 seats. The new one was enlarged by three seats.
   Voting was not compulsory and turnout of the 7.9 million voters
ranged from 60 to 70 percent throughout the country.
   Fifty thousand police officers were on duty and 25,000 on
standby for election day, authorities said. No violence was
reported.
   No outdoor rallies or political processions have been allowed in
Malaysia since race riots after the 1969 elections left hundreds
dead in the streets of Kuala Lumpur. That bloodshed occurred after
Chinese parties made inroads on Malay political dominance.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0064 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 1805EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-TripleSlaying     10-21 0345</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Triple Slaying,0416</SECOND>
<HEAD>Neighbor Sought in Triple Death Arrested in Florida</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HILLTOWN, Pa. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The neighbor of a family found hacked to
death in their beds was in custody in Florida while officials
worked to bring him home to face charges, a prosecutor said Sunday.
   Eric Robert Motis, 19, was arrested late Saturday night in Miami
Beach while driving a car belonging to Louise C. Hoopes, 42. She
was killed with her sons Douglas, 16, and Daniel, 14, as they slept
last Monday, said Bucks County District Attorney Alan Rubenstein.
   The county coroner said they were stabbed and slashed in the
head and neck with a sharp instrument.
   After the bodies were found Monday, Rubenstein described the
victims as members of a classic suburban household who appeared to
have no enemies. Mrs. Hoopes' husband, Howard, died two years ago
from cancer.
   The killer made an effort to be undetected and went in and out
of the darkened house without making noise or damaging anything, he
said.
   Motis had lived across the street from the Hoopes' home with his
parents and grandparents. After the killings, police said they
wanted to question Motis.
   Rubenstein said at a news conference that Motis was charged in a
warrant with three counts of first-degree murder, burglary, robbery
and related offenses. Bucks County authorities have requested his
extradition from Florida ``as soon as possible,'' Rubenstein said.
   Rubenstein said he obtained information that Motis might be in
Miami Beach and sent agents from his office, along with state and
local police, to help track him down.
   Mrs. Hoopes was a part-time secretary at Grand View Hospital in
nearby Sellersville.
   Manny Motis, 47, told authorities last week that his son, Eric,
had played pool with Douglas Hoopes. He described the family as
``the nicest people you'd ever want to meet.''
   In August, the elder Motis reported to Hilltown police that his
son had left home, taking with him two handguns and a truck that
belonged to the father. Eric Motis was arrested Sept. 4 in
Montgomery County and held in the county prison until Sept. 12,
when he was released to Bucks County authorities.
   Hilltown police arrested him Sept. 17 on charges of attempted
theft of gasoline, theft of two handguns and unauthorized use of a
motor vehicle. His father posted $5,000 bail for him and an Oct. 1
preliminary hearing was set.
Eric Motis failed to appear for the preliminary hearing.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0065 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 1807EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Egypt-Election     10-21 0345</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Egypt-Election,0386</SECOND>
<HEAD>Main Opposition Parties to Boycott Coming Election</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ZINA HEMADY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CAIRO, Egypt (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Four of Egypt's main opposition parties
announced Sunday they would boycott next month's parliamentary
elections to protest what they said were unfair voting conditions.
   This would leave President Hosni Mubarak's National Democratic
Party virtually unchallenged.
   The opposition New Wafd, Labor and Liberal parties and the
Moslem Brotherhood are protesting conditions they say encourage
vote-rigging.
   Those include loopholes they said would allow the use of names
of dead and absent voters, and an emergency law that has led to
arrests of thousands of opposition supporters.
   The government denies their claims of election fraud, saying the
emergency law is only being used to combat terrorism and black
market dealings in drugs and currency.
   The state-run Middle-East news Agency quoted Information
Minister Safwat al-Sherif as saying the ruling party welcomed any
dialogue that would help convince the opposition to participate in
the elections.
   At a news conference, the opposition leaders declared that any
opposition candidate who stood for election in defiance of the
boycott would be expelled from his party.
   The four groups held 95 of the 458 seats in the parliament, the
People's Assembly, which was dissolved last week by a national
referendum after Egypt's Supreme Constitutional Court ruled it was
elected under unconstitutional law.
   The court's ruling was in May and the assembly had been in
recess, effectively suspended, since June.
   Using his executive lawmaking powers in the assembly's absence,
Mubarak decreed an election law that appeared to satisfy the
court's stipulation.
   The opposition argues that it was not consulted over the new
law, which it says is still far from satisfactory.
   Only the small leftist National Unionist Progressive Party has
announced it will participate in the Nov. 29 election. There has
been no word yet from four other small parties that have not run
previously.
   The emergency law allows wide powers to the police. It has been
in effect since the assassination of President Anwar Sadat in 1981.
   On Oct. 11, a few days after the old parliament's suspension was
decreed, gunmen assassinated Rifaat el-Mahgoub, the speaker of the
former parliament. But his death apparently had nothing to do with
the current dispute.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0066 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 1813EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-Rescue     10-21 0147</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Rescue,0156</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dutch Frigate Rescues Eight Iranians In Gulf</HEAD>
<DATELINE>THE HAGUE, Netherlands (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Dutch Navy frigate patrolling
the Persian Gulf on Sunday rescued eight Iranians whose ship sank
after colliding with another vessel off the coast of Dubai, a navy
spokesman said.
   The Witte de With, one of two Dutch Navy frigates that are part
of the multinational flotilla confronting Iraq in the gulf, saw the
eight Iranians clinging to wreckage early Sunday off the coast of
Dubai, said navy spokesman Wim Geneste.
   No one was reported missing in the accident. The Iranian ship
had been carrying a cargo of fruit bound for Dubai, Geneste said.
   ``They said they didn't remember what kind of boat hit them,''
he said.
   The man had been in the water about eight hours and one of them
was treated for hypothermia. They were put ashore at the Dubai port
of Mina Saqr, Geneste said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0067 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 1815EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-LiteracyCenter 1stLd-Writethru a0741 10-21 0569</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Literacy Center, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0741,0684</SECOND>
<HEAD>Southern Governors Setting Up New Regional Literacy Organization</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: INSERTS 2 grafs after 7th graf, `Also attending ...' to
UPDATE with governors' comments. Picks up 8th graf, `The report
...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By JANET McCONNAUGHEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW ORLEANS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Officials from 13 Southern states and Puerto
Rico on Sunday labeled their region the least educated in the
nation, and announced formation of the Southern Literacy Forum to
combat the problem.
   ``There are thousands of individual literacy programs out there.
A lot of good is going on, but it's like dipping the Mississippi
River dry with a teaspoon,'' former Mississippi Gov. William F.
Winter wrote in a report released at a news conference.
   ``A center will help us coordinate, on a regional basis, what
has to be one of the most important projects that anybody can be
involved in,'' he wrote.
   In the 13 Southern states, at least 30 percent of adults are
high school dropouts. This is true in only three of the other 37
states, the report said.
   The forum will be an offshoot of the Southern Growth Policies
Board, which southern governors created to develop their economies
and people. The agency is based in Research Triangle Park, N.C.
   The board received the report Sunday from its chairman,
Louisiana Gov. Buddy Roemer, who also announced creation of the
forum.
   Also attending the board's 18th annual meeting were North
Carolina Gov. James Martin and officials from Alabama, Arkansas,
Florida, Georgia, Kentucky, Mississippi, Oklahoma, South Carolina,
Tennessee, Virginia, West Virginia and Puerto Rico.
   ``Literacy would improve the quality of our work force, lower
the unempooyment rates, and make our citizenry have a higher
self-esteem,'' Roemer said. ``It will be helpful to join with our
neighbors and put together a plan to develop literacy opportunities
for the region.''
   ``What the forum does is show which ideas are best and promote
them,'' Martin said. ``It's sort of like blocking and tackling,
we've got to deal with the fundamentals.''
   The report, ``Literacy is Everybody's Business,'' noted the very
meaning of literacy has changed throughout the century.
   ``Today's literacy would seem like higher education to our
grandparents,'' it said. ``In fact, the education that was once
sufficient to enable any ambitious adult to get ahead now can't
even help him hold his place on the assembly line.''
   During World War II, a worker able to read at a 4th-grade level
could manage entry-level jobs. An 8th-grade education was enough to
get by in the mid-1960s.
   Today even entry-level jobs may require some college education.
And farming, a crucial part of the Southern economy, needs more
than a field hand's skills.
   ``Once it was enough to read the ripeness of a tomato or the
sky's forecast of rain. Today's farmer is the chief executive
officer, purchasing agent, personnel officer, and financial manager
of a rapidly evolving, highly sophisticated business,'' the report
said.
   ``At the same time he must be a scientist to select his seed or
stock plants; a computer operator to disburse the proper fertilizer
to his fields or feedstuffs to his livestock; a production expert
to manage the harvest; and a marketing whiz to sell his
commodity,'' it said.
   The report estimated that literacy programs currently are
attended by fewer than 10 percent of Southern adults who need to
improve their reading, speaking and mathematics skills.
   A regional partnership is needed to expand such offerings
because no single Southern state has the money or other resources
to reach and teach all the people who need help, the report said.
   The Southern Literacy Forum will help states put together such
programs, pay for or conduct research to improve them and provide
information, training and other help to local literacy programs.
   The policies board has a $1.2 million budget, 31 percent of it
from state dues and appropriations and the rest from grants,
associate memberships and publications.
   Initial support for the organization will come from $175,000 the
board hopes to raise from foundations and private donors.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0068 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 1840EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-HomecomingTrouble 1stLd-Writethru a0665 10-21 0388</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Homecoming Trouble, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0665,0456</SECOND>
<HEAD>South Dakota State University Homecoming Gets Out of Control</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 4 grafs to UPDATE with about 50 arrested, details.
Picks up 5th graf, `On Friday ...'</NOTE>
<DATELINE>BROOKINGS, S.D. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An estimated 1,000 people roamed city
streets and the South Dakota State University campus, setting
bonfires and throwing rocks and bottles as a homecoming celebration
got out of hand for a second night.
   Police arrested about 50 people on charges ranging from
aggravated assault and intentional damage to property to fleeing
arrest and alcohol violations involving minors. They were being
held Sunday in Brookings County Jail and bond hearings were
scheduled for Monday.
   ``You always have some incidents that occur as a result of Hobo
Day,'' the school's homecoming, said university President Robert
Wagner. But Friday and Saturday night's events were the most
extreme in many years, he said.
   Several hundred people marched across campus toward downtown
Saturday, tearing down signs and light poles. Small fires were
started at two intersections near the campus, and some students
pelted police and firefighters with eggs and beer bottles.
   On Friday, people clogged a street near the campus and
overturned a car, started a bonfire and threw rocks and beer cans
at police.
   ``They just took over the street,'' city Police Chief Dennis
Falken said of Friday night's disturbance in the city of 16,000
people. No injuries were reported Friday and police made some
arrests for underage alcohol consumption, he said.
   Wagner called the violence ``inexcusable'' and said steps would
be taken to teach students to behave better.
   The violence started late Friday when people attending several
off-campus house parties spilled out into the street, Falken said.
   They overturned an old car, tried to start it and then set it on
fire, according to sophomore Kim Fischer, who stopped to watch. She
said people in the crowd pelted police when a tow truck arrived,
throwing bricks, rocks and beer bottles and cans.
   ``They (police) tried to break it up and the kids were just
throwing beer cans,'' said Doug Mikuska, a junior who lives nearby.
``They just left. The cops were outmanned.''
   The crowd moved down the street and started a bonfire at an
intersection.
   ``Then groups of people kept coming and throwing things on -
anything they could get their hands on,'' including a tire and a
doghouse, Falken said.
   Some residents believe violence and mischief have gotten worse
in recent years since the legal drinking age was raised to 21.
Younger students can't be in bars anymore, so thy attend
off-campus house parties.
   Liquor is banned in dormitories at the university, which has an
enrollment of about 7,000.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0069 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 1846EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Gulf-Iraq-Sanctions 1stLd-Writethru a0 10-21 0744</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Iraq-Sanctions, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0739,0907</SECOND>
<HEAD>Iraq Showing Signs of Succumbing to Sanctions</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: INSERTS 1 graf after 10th graf, `The rationing ..' with
gasoline price staying the same, picks up 11th graf pvs, `For the
...</NOTE>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf-Suez, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TERRIL JONES</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NICOSIA, Cyprus (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Iraq's decision to ration gasoline and
motor oil starting Tuesday indicates the worldwide trade embargo on
Iraq is finally taking hold where it hurts most: the petroleum
industry.
   Although Iraq now controls an estimated 20 percent of global oil
reserves, the rationing belies the fragility of Iraq's main
industry and brings into question how long it can keep its army
running.
   Even the government admits that the sanctions are beginning to
hurt.
   ``Day after day, effects of the economic blockade being imposed
on Iraq conspicuously affect it, the formula which was invented by
the U.S. administration for building economic, political and
psychological pressure on the Iraqi people,'' the ruling Baath
Party newspaper Al-Thawra said Sunday.
   ``There is no doubt that this policy has direct impact on the
individual and the family,'' it said.
   The party organ's acknowledgment echoes what Western governments
have hoped for weeks the embargo would achieve.
   ``We believe it is beginning to have an effect, and that it will
have an effect not only on the Iraqi economy but on this massive
military machine (Iraq) has in Kuwait,'' U.S. Defense Secretary
Dick Cheney said Thursday.
   Kuwaiti economist Jassem al-Saadoun estimated last week that the
loss of oil exports alone costs Iraq $54 million a day.
   ``Iraq's inability to sell its oil is the cornerstone of the
embargo,'' said al-Saadoun, head of the al-Shall financial house.
   The rationing move constitutes an Iraqi admission of its
inability to refine oil on its own. Oil Minister Issam Abdul Rahim
al-Chalabi ordered the rationing to conserve additives that Iraq
could no longer obtain because of the ban on imports.
   The price of gasoline is being kept at the pre-sanctions level
of 26 cents per liter, or about $1 a gallon, but motor oil prices
have increased in recent weeks.
   For the moment, food is less of a problem. Iraqi stores and
markets are chock-full of fruits, vegetables, fish, canned goods,
juice, cooking oil, wheat flour and rice, much of it from abroad.
Restaurants do a bustling business.
   But milk, sugar, tea, cooking oil, soap and rice have been
rationed for weeks, and farmers have been urged to plant more grain
on unused lands.
   The two-month-old trade embargo has kept out machinery and spare
parts, oil-producing equipment and materials needed for
construction and agriculture. Building projects have halted,
petroleum production is down 43 percent, and people are being urged
to cut back on electricity use. President Saddam Hussein has even
appealed to citizens to conserve their clothing.
   ``My personal understanding is that the sanctions bite, every
day more and more,'' says Marjatta Rasi, chairwoman of the U.N.
Security Council's sanctions committee.
   ``The functioning of the society will slow down, because they
cannot receive spare parts, even though they have taken everything
they could from Kuwait,'' she said.
   While it is difficult to accurately quantify effects of the
sanctions, experts seem to agree that Iraq cannot hold out more
than a few months.
   Kuwaiti economist al-Saadoun said Iraq likely had consumer and
industrial supplies stockpiled to last three months. ``This means
that six months of the embargo would be sufficient to have the
country explode,'' he said.
   The government, which first distributed food ration coupons for
two months, will issue them for six months starting in November.
   ``Psychologically this is important because the Iraqi government
is preparing the people for a long embargo,'' a Baghdad resident
said.
   The front line of enforcement are the naval ships implementing
the two-month-old blockade.
   Western warships have intercepted about 2,600 vessels, boarded
some 270 and diverted a dozen. Shipping, aviation and military
sources say the naval blockade is virtually impermeable.
   U.S. Vice-Adm. Henry Mauz, commander of naval elements in
Operation Desert Shield, said last week that a small quantity of
goods were trickling into Iraq through Jordan. Some goods arrive in
Aqaba, Jordan's Red Sea port, and are repackaged and sent on to
Iraq, he said.
   Jordan, Turkey and Iraq's erstwhile archenemy Iran have emerged
as the weak links in the embargo chain.
   Soon after the trade sanctions were adopted on Aug. 16, a convoy
of supplies sent by Palestinians left Jordan for Iraq in a cheerful
but flagrant violation of the U.N. order.
   Smuggling, mostly small-scale, from Turkey and Iran began soon
after the embargo, and some Turkish cargo sent to Iran was diverted
to Iraq by Iranian border guards.
   But a senior Turkish official said last week there had been no
increase in traffic to Iran, indicating that Iran is largely
abiding by the embargo.
   ``I don't think there is a great amount of smuggling,'' said the
U.N. Sanction Committee's Ms. Rasi. `I don't think the smugglers
want to take the risk for the Iraqi currency.''
   The Iraqi dinar is not covertible on currency markets and has
been shunned in the wake of the trade ban.
   The air embargo, adopted in late September, is enforced mainly
in Jordan, where Iraq's only commercially scheduled flights arrive.
They are checked by Jordanian authorities as well as U.N.
officials.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0070 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 1856EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BarkSilencer     10-21 0319</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bark Silencer,0382</SECOND>
<HEAD>Scientist Collars Problem of Barking Dogs</HEAD>
<DATELINE>COLLEGE STATION, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A veterinarian has developed a dog
collar he says can silence chronic barkers with a high-frequency
beep.
   ``It's not an electric shock collar. It will not hurt the dog,''
said Jon Hunter, 48, an associate professor of veterinary
physiology and pharmacology at Texas A&amp;M.
   The device needs fine-tuning and its effectiveness is uncertain,
he said. But the principle is simple.
   When the dog barks, a miniature microphone in the collar emits a
burst of high-intensity sound, startling the animal into silence.
The sound is inaudible to most humans.
   ``It will not be so effective that it will stop dogs from
barking completely,'' Hunter said. ``Many people want their dogs to
bark in order to warn them of intruders.''
   ``The people who have tested the collar have said the collar has
had an immediate effect,'' Hunter said. ``It causes the dog to
become distracted from its barking.''
   Hunter's invention was inspired by his experience as an
11-year-old Missouri farm boy.
   ``We were milking cows and a thunderstorm occurred,'' he said.
``When the thunder occurred, the cattle and dogs would seek
shelter.
   ``Later, in attempting to modify the behavior of animals, I
thought of different sounds that would change an animal's
behavior,'' he said.
   In three years of research, Hunter tried electronic simulation
of thunder, explosions and gunfire. But a high-pitched sound few
humans could hear turned out to be the best antidote.
   Hunter said his collar is more humane than other solutions
owners employ. Some fit their pets with electric-shock collars or
subject them to vocal cord surgery. Others may give them away or
even destroy the animal.
   Hunter said he has a contract with a manufacturer whose name he
wouldn't disclose and hopes to have a model on the market in six
months.
   But, already, Hunter said he has been besieged by pet owners
offering their yelping dogs as guinea pigs to test the collar.
   ``I have people call me and say, `Please give me a collar or
I'll have to put my dog to sleep,''' Hunter said. ``We're trying to
help people as quickly as we can, but they want the collar
tomorrow.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0071 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 1934EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-Kuwait     10-21 0435</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Kuwait,0524</SECOND>
<HEAD>Iraqis Deny Taking Medical Equipment from Kuwait</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf Rdp</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   EDITOR'S NOTE: Associated Press reporter Salah Nasrawi was among
a group of reporters flown to Kuwait and permitted to visit a
hospital there Sunday by the Iraqi Information Ministry.
   ---
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By SALAH NASRAWI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>KUWAIT CITY (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A senior Iraqi official said Sunday that
allegations Iraq has taken medical equipment from hospitals in
occupied Kuwait were false.
   Abduljabbar Abdulabbas, the Iraq official in charge of hospitals
in Kuwait -which Iraq calls its 19th province - told reporters that
normal services continue at hospitals in the occupied emirate.
   ``Although medical equipment exceeds by far the needs of the
population, we did not move any of them to other places,'' said
Abdulabbas, a physician who heads Baghdad's health department. He
spoke during a tour of the main maternity hospital in Kuwait.
   The Iraqi manager of the maternity hospital, Qais Abdulsattar,
said the 500-bed hospital is still providing services, including
health care, to prematurely born babies who need to be kept in
incubators.
   The United States and the exiled government of Kuwait have
reported that Iraq moved medical equipment to Iraq, including a
large number of incubators, causing the death of some Kuwaiti
babies.
   Reporters were flown into Kuwait and given a tour of the
hospital Sunday in an attempt to dispel these reports.
   Abdulsattar showed reporters 12 babies in incubators in the main
intensive care unit of the hospital, which is staffed mostly by
Asian and non-Kuwaiti Arab medical staff.
   ``Why should we send incubators to our maternity hospitals in
Iraq? We have plenty of them there,'' said Abdulsattar, who was
sent from Baghdad to run the Kuwaiti hospital.
   Reporters also visited Al-Razi Hospital for bone disease in
downtown Kuwait, where about 30 patients were being treated in the
luxurious 295-bed hospital built by the royal family in 1984.
   Kamal Mustafa, an Egyptian specialist in bone surgery, said most
of the patients are suffering from injuries incurred in industrial
accidents.
   He said he was not considering leaving Kuwait, where he has
worked for more than 25 years.
   ``It's my sacred duty to be near my patients as long as they
need me and I am keen not to let them down at this hard time,'' he
said.
   But many of the foreign and non-Kuwaiti medical staff in the 14
Kuwaiti hospitals and 35 health centers left the small Persian Gulf
state after Iraq took over on Aug. 2.
   Abdulabbas was asked whether the departure of foreign medical
staff will have have any adverse effect on health service.
   ``It was extravagance. Why should a 500-bed hospital have 400
nurses?'' he said.
   Ali Abdulrahim al-Hawail, a Kuwaiti neurologist who heads the
technical section at the newly set up health department, agreed
that the shrinking of the population by more than two-thirds makes
the remaining staff sufficient to run the hospitals and health
centers.
   ``I don't feel the medical service has been affected, but hope
they will continue with the same standard,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0072 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 1936EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-FrenchPilot     10-21 0228</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-French Pilot,0255</SECOND>
<HEAD>Daredevil Pilot Undertakes Hostage Mission</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A daredevil pilot who infuriated French authorities
two years ago with stunt flights over Paris left Sunday on a
private mission to try to liberate French hostages in Iraq.
   Albert Maltret, 54, captured public attention in the summer of
1988 when he made noctural flights over rooftops, monuments and the
Champs-Elysees in a tiny ultralight aircraft, evading authorities
for weeks.
   His flight on Sunday was more conventional - as a passenger in a
Royal Jordanian Airways flight to Amman, Jordan. From there, he
planned to travel on to Baghdad.
   Iraqi diplomats gave him his airline tickets.
   ``I'm undertaking this mission on my own; it's purely
humanitarian,'' Maltret said before leaving.
   An estimated 400 French nationals are believed held hostage in
Iraq and occupied Kuwait in the wake of the Aug. 2 Iraqi takeover.
   In 1988, police staked out airfields for weeks to bring down the
pilot the press dubbed ``le Baron Noir'' -the Black Baron. Finally
captured, Maltret was fined and lost his pilot's license for three
years.
   French authorities briefly jailed him in April for plotting
physical violence to settle a family quarrel.
   Two weeks ago, he volunteered to go to Iraq as a hostage
mediator. He also at one point offered to serve as a mercenary for
Iraq. But Maltret downplayed that offer on Sunday.
   ``My image has been tarnished,'' he said. ``I need to regain
some credit. This mission will help me.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0073 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 1939EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-BudgetFiction 1stLd-Writethru a0681 10-21 0517</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Budget Fiction, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0681,600</SECOND>
<HEAD>Leap of Faith Needed to Accept Deficit-Reduction Assumptions</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Budget-Taxes Bjt</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: INSERTS 1 graf after 7th graf pvs, bgng: From their, to
include current economic figures</NOTE>
<HEAD>An AP News Analysis</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By STEVEN KOMAROW</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Would you believe oil prices falling more than
40 percent next year? How about interest rates in the 5 percent
range by 1992?
   Probably not. But those are only two of the predictions the
budget writers in Washington have manufactured to tout their $500
billion deficit-reduction plan.
   All federal budgets are, by necessity, built on assumptions of
how the ecoomy will perform, because that determines how many
dollars will flow into the Treasury in taxes and flow out for costs
such as unemployment claims.
   But in trying to get the public to accept a huge package of tax
increases and cuts in federal benefits, Congress and the White
House have settled on assumptions that, at the least, strain
credulity.
   For example:
   By the end of 1993, if the budget is passed, the nation should
be enjoying a balanced budget; Treasury bill rates will be 4.4
percent and inflation 3 percent; and the economy will be humming
along with nearly 4 percent annual growth, they agree.
   ``From their mouths to God's ears,'' said Stan Collender, a
budget expert at the accounting firm of Price Waterhouse who
predicted the $500 billion in deficit reduction will look more like
$300 billion when reality unfolds.
   The rate for 12-month Treasury bills was 7.62 percent last week.
The inflation rate soared to 9.5 percent on an annual basis in
September, up from a 6.2 percent annual rate in August. The economy
grew at a barely perceptible 0.4 percent in the second quarter of
this year, down from a 1.7 percent annual growth rate in the 1st
quarter and down from a 2.5 percent annual rate in 1989.
   Even as Congress was struggling to nail down the final deal over
the weekend, government data was emerging that showed the fragility
of their house of cards.
   On Thursday, the government said the cost of living increase for
Social Security and other government entitlements will be 5.4
percent in January.
   Last January, the president's budget assumed it would be just
3.9 percent, and the figure is nearly a point higher than most
recent estimates. Translated into the budget, government costs
increase roughly $2 billion next year and $15 billion over the next
five years.
   Budget negotiators have yet to find a source for that $15
billion.
   One of the reasons for the steep consumer price increases is the
cost of oil, which has soared to nearly twice the $21.15 average
assumed for this year. The budget predicts it will fall back below
$25 next year and then below $22 the following two years.
   Oil prices affect the government directly, too, with military
and civilian agencies operating huge fleets of airplanes, trucks,
cars, etc. Continued high oil prices could add billions more to
those costs over the next five years.
   Economic assumptions aside, some of the budget is just pretend.
The costs of the Persian Gulf operations, $1 billion a month now
and many times that if shooting breaks out, doesn't get counted.
Nor does the huge savings and loan bailout.
   And one of the most questionable assumptions in the budget is
that Congress and the administration will abide by its restraints
on spending.
   ``This package will not have the effect on the deficit that the
(budget) summiteers claim,'' said Jim Miller, former director of
the Office of Management and Budget. ``There are just all sorts of
loophole ways Congress can get away with spending.''
   ---
   EDITOR'S NOTE - Steven Komarow writes on budget matters for The
Associated Press.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0074 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 1955EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Iraq-Mujahedeen 1stLd-Writethru a0675 10-21 0603</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Iraq-Mujahedeen, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0675,650</SECOND>
<HEAD>Iraq Courts Old Foe in Tehran, Expels Mujahedeen Opposing Iran</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: Subs 3rd grasf prv with three grafs, not beginning,
``However, the xxx to include Mujahedeen denial of reports</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By RUTH SINAI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Iraq, responding to a request from Iran,
appears to have expelled members of a major Iranian opposition
group, U.S. officials say.
   Members of the People's Mujahedeen of Iran, the largest group
trying to overthrow the clerical government in Tehran, have
apparently started leaving Iraq for Paris and other European sites,
said the officials who spoke only on condition of anonymity.
   However, the assessment from the U.S. officials was strongly
challenged by Mujahedeen spokesman Farid Soleimani, who telephoned
news agencies to insist that his group remained intact in Baghdad
and elsewhere.
   ``We claim very firmly that none of our members have left
Baghdad involuntarily,'' Soleimani said. ``There are comings and
goings, that's natural, and it has nothing to do with expulsions.''
   The reputed explusion move would be in keeping with Iraqi
attempts to end its economic and diplomatic isolation by courting
Iran, a one-time enemy with which it fought a disastrous eight-year
war until 1988.
   In recent weeks Iraq has ceded many of its war gains, sending
back thousands of war prisoners, withdrawing troops from areas it
captured in the war, and agreeing to share sovereignty over the
strategically important Shatt-al-Arab waterway.
   In return, Iraq asked for permission to hook into a major
Iranian oil pipeline and circumvent the international naval
blockade that's preventing the export of its oil. The Iraqis also
asked Iran for food and medicine.
   Iran has sent some truckloads of food, but has not responded to
the pipeline request, U.S. officials say.
   ``We're very watchful of what kind of relations Saddam Hussein
is able to establish with Iran,'' said CIA Director William Webster
in an interview this week with The Associated Press. ``So far, Iran
is in a kind of win-win situation.''
   Iran and Iraq have restored diplomatic relations and restaffed
their embassies in each others' capitals.
   ``The sense is that with this new understanding between Iran and
Iraq, an organization like that (the PMOI) is not welcome there any
more,'' said another administration official, who spoke on
condition of anonymity.
   Iran's official news agency IRNA reported several times last
month that Massoud Rajavi, the PMOI's Baghdad-based leader, had
asked his people to leave Iraq and was himself leaving for Germany.
   The Mujahedeen sent telexes and communiques from Baghdad denying
the reports as ``garbage allegations'' designed to discredit and
destroy the organization.
   But PMOI representatives in the United States, who used to
bombard reporters with phone calls, interview offers and news
conferences, have all but disappeared in recent weeks. Repeated
calls to their officials have not been returned.
   The group did hold a news conference at U.N. headquarters last
Wednesday to complain about Iran's human rights record, but the
officials refused to discuss their relations with Baghdad despite
repeated questioning.
   The PMOI is no stranger to expulsions.
   Rajavi and his supporters fled to Paris in 1980 after their
former allies, Khomeini and his fundamentalist leadership, turned
on them in a bloody purge of leftists and liberals.
   In 1986, France asked the organization to leave its territory,
under pressure from the Iranian government, and Rajavi moved to
Baghdad.
   There, the PMOI was warmly received and encouraged to form its
own military force, the National Liberation Army. The force
launched incursions into Iranian territory, boasting 15,000
fighters. But claims of the losses they inflicted on Khomeini's
troops could not be verified and were believed to be exaggerated.
   Although they continued to enjoy popularity and support in Iraq,
the organization's power appeared to wane in recent years.
   The PMOI was forced to stop its military activity when Iran and
Iraq agreed on a cease-fire in 1988. Thousands of its supporters in
Iran have been rounded up and executed.
   Iraq has expelled Iranian opposition groups before. The late
Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini spent 15 years exiled in the holy Iraqi
city of Najaf but was asked to leave in 1978 during a moment of
detente in Iraqi-Iranian relations.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0075 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 2002EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-KansasKuwaiti     10-21 0278</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Kansas Kuwaiti,0347</SECOND>
<HEAD>Wichita Woman's Kuwati Husband Freed By Iraq</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MICHAEL BATES</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WICHITA, Kan. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A 3-week-old son he has never seen will be
waiting for Nabil Seyam when he gets back to Wichita this week
after more than two months trapped in Iraqi-occupied Kuwait.
   Carrie Seyam said her husband called her Sunday morning from
Jordan. Hours later, a Wichita television station let her see a
17-second videotape of Seyam talking to reporters there.
   ``He looks good. He looks a little bit tired, but he's the
same,'' she said.
   Seyam talked about his parents and siblings he had to leave
behind in Kuwait. ``I'm going to do my best, hopefully, when I get
back to the States to get my family out,'' he said.
   Seyam knew his U.S. citizenship made him a potential hostage
soon after Iraq invaded Kuwait Aug. 2. Earlier this month, he was
stopped at a checkpoint and taken into custody after soldiers read
his nationality on his driver's license.
   The State Department told Mrs. Seyam they would try to get him
out since Iraq was allowing some Arab-Americans to leave.
   Seyam called from Baghdad on Wednesday to say he was being
released.
   ``It was six o'clock in the morning. The baby had just woke
up,'' Mrs. Seyam said. ``I heard that phone and I just flew out of
bed.''
   The couple, both 29, met when Seyam was an engineering student
at Wichita State University. They married almost 11 years ago.
   By the time he went to work at Kuwait Metal Pipe Industries as a
safety engineer, the Seyams had a girl and a boy to move with them
back to his homeland.
   Mrs. Seyam worked in Kuwait as a teacher's assistant at the
American school. On June 1, more than six months pregnant, she left
Kuwait with her children to visit her parents in Wichita. She
planned to return in August and be in Kuwait for the birth of her
third child. Instead, Yusef was born in Wichita.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0076 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 2003EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-Evacuees     10-21 0200</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Evacuees,0203</SECOND>
<HEAD>Immigration Group Expects 40,000 New Refugees Soon</HEAD>
<DATELINE>AMMAN, Jordan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An international relief agency said Sunday
that it expected up to 40,000 foreigners to flee Iraq and Kuwait
soon and appealed to world governments for $13.5 million in
contributions to repatriate them.
   ``IOM estimates that between 25,000 and 40,000 foreign residents
of Iraq and Kuwait remain in need of international repatriation in
the short term,'' the International Organization for Migration said
in a statement.
   The European Community immediately announced it had allocated
$4.9 million to repatriate thousands of Sri Lankan refugees
expected to cross into Jordan before Nov. 4.
   Neither organization provided an explanation for why the flood
of refugees was expected.
   Not long after Iraq's Aug. 2 invasion of Kuwait, the migration
organization launched a major repatriation program for refugees
from Iraq and Kuwait who had landed in Turkey, Iran, Saudi Arabia
and Jordan.
   The organization said it had flown home 122,307 evacuees since
Sep. 3, including 114,633 from Jordan.
   Jordanian Interior Ministry official Salameh Hammad said last
week that although 100,000 Asian and Arab refugees were stuck in
the country at one point in mid-September, the desert camps are
almost empty now.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0077 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 2033EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-MajorIssues     10-21 0549</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Major Issues,660</SECOND>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Following is a list of major legislation and
issues yet to be resolved as Congress heads toward adjournment of
the 101st session:
   
   BUDGET AND TAXES
   The House and Senate continue their search for a compromise
deficit-reduction package that can be accepted by President Bush.
The government is operating on temporary spending authority that
expires at midnight Wednesday, by which time both sides hope to
have a final agreement.
   The two sides continued to exchange proposed tax packages on
Sunday, but hit a snag late in the day.
   Final passage is needed, as well, on the 13 appropriations bills
financing government agencies in the new budget year, which started
Oct. 1.
   
   ARTS-OBSCENITY
   An $11.7 billion appropriations bill that would reinstate strict
anti-obscenity restrictions on the National Endowment for the Arts
is pending in the Senate. The bill would trim the agency's $175
million budget request by $5 million. Opponents favor a
House-approved proposal to let the courts decide whether federally
subsidized art works are obscene.
   
   CLEAN AIR
   Members of a House and Senate conference are nearing completion
on compromise clean air legislation, which would be the first major
rewrite of the federal air pollution law in 13 years.
   The conferees tentatively approved provisions Sunday to sharply
reduce pollution that causes acid rain, the last major section of
the 700-page bill. Earlier the conferees tentatively agreed on new
auto emission requirements to curtail urban smog and on reductions
in toxic chemical pollution by industry.
   Several minor issues remained to be worked out by the conferees.
The compromise package also still would have to be approved in both
the House and Senate.
   
   CHILD CARE
   Senate leaders and the Bush administration have reached
agreement on the broad outlines of legislation providing assistance
for low-income families. But major differences with the House
remain an obstacle to passage.
   The latest Senate version is a five-year, $15 billion package.
Most of the money would go for an expansion of earned income tax
credits for low-income working families with children.
   
   ASSAULT WEAPONS
   The Senate has approved an omnibus anti-crime bill that would
ban the sale of nine semiautomatic assault weapons. But the House
version contains no such provision. Instead, the House may vote on
a bill to outlaw ownership or sale of semiautomatics the Treasury
Department deemed not suitable for sporting purposes. The
politically influential National Rifle Association opposes both
bills and House sponsors are clearly nervous over whether their
measure could survive on the floor at this stage.
   
   FARM BILL
   A compromise $40.8 billion farm bill covering government
agriculture programs for the next five years awaits final passage
by both the House and Senate. The bill would slash farm spending by
$13.5 billion over the next five years, as part of a larger
deficit-reduction package.
   
   US-EGYPTIAN AID
   Forgiveness of $6.7 billion in past military debt Egypt owes the
United States is part of a $15.5 billion foreign aid bill pending
in the Senate. The move is badly wanted by President Bush as a
reward for the country that has led Arab support for the
multinational military deployment in the Persian Gulf crisis. But
Bush faces a difficult choice over whether to veto the bill because
it includes a sharp cut in El Salvador's military aid that the
administration strongly opposes.
   
   KEATING INVESTIGATION
   The Senate Ethics Committee is pressing ahead with its
investigation of senators who assisted Charles H. Keating Jr. as
his Lincoln Savings and Loan was sinking toward collapse.
   
   CIVIL RIGHTS
   The White house says Bush will veto the Civil Rights Act of
1990, which is aimed at overturning the effects of recent Supreme
Court decisions reversing some affirmative action programs. A veto
override attempt could take place in Congress once Bush has acted.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0078 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 2040EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Salvador     10-21 0364</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Salvador,0433</SECOND>
<HEAD>Church Leader Lauds Cut In U.S. Military Aid To El Salvador</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ANNIE CABRERA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN SALVADOR, El Salvador (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Roman Catholic Church leader
on Sunday praised U.S. lawmakers' decision to cut military aid to
El Salvador, saying the reduction could help force both sides to
end the country's civil war.
   The action on a foreign aid bill ``reflects the awareness that
many things are not going well here and should change, so that the
peace process can end this conflict and establish new bases for a
society in which human dignity is genuinely respected,'' Auxiliary
Bishop Gregorio Rosa Chavez said.
   ``Peace cannot be built with weapons,'' he told a news
conference after the Sunday homily, which the influential
Salvadoran church frequently uses as a platform to speak out
against human rights abuses and put forth its vision of how to end
the decade-old civil war.
   The Senate on Friday approved an amendment to halve the $85
million in military aid to El Salvador the U.S. had budgeted for
the 1991 fiscal year. A similar version of the amendment was tacked
onto a House version of the aid bill.
   Both bills contain a provision that would restore the aid if the
rebels pull out of the negotiations, or if they launch a major
offensive. Another provision would eliminate military aid
altogether if the government breaks off the talks.
   Rosa Chavez said the Senate vote would ``give more viability to
the peace process.''
   So far, all the peace negotiating sessions since President
Alfredo Cristiani took office in June 1989 have ended in deadlock.
The next meeting between representatives of the two sides and a
U.N. mediator is to begin Nov. 4 in Mexico.
   The government has been demanding that the guerrillas stop
fighting and participate in the country's political life.
   Leaders of the Farabundo Marti National Liberation Front rebel
organization want a political agreement on a number of reforms,
including prosecution of officers responsible for atrocities,
before agreeing to a cease-fire.
   Many of the war's 73,000 victims have been civilians suspected
of leftist sympathies, slain by rightist death squads or the
military.
   Congress was probably moved to act by the assassination last
November of six Jesuit priests, their housekeeper and her daughter.
Soldiers have confessed that they shot the priests on the orders of
an army commander.
   The House and Senate bills will have to be reconciled in
House-Senate conference, but the provisions are expected to be in
the final version sent to President Bush.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0079 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 2047EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-CarAuction     10-21 0195</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Car Auction,0206</SECOND>
<HEAD>1933 Packard Model 1006 Dietrich Sold for $745,000</HEAD>
<DATELINE>UNCERTAIN, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A 1933 Packard Model Custom Dietrich
fetched the top bid of $745,000 at an automobile auction Saturday
that drew more than 10,000 spectators.
   The intense bidding on two exclusive car collections owned by
Marshall businessman Gene Ponder and the late oilman Samuel F.
Vaughan III was the talk of this east Texas town, located about 156
miles east of Dallas.
   Vaughan was killed in an Oct. 6 airplane crash at the Uncertain
airstrip.
   Ponder's collection of MGs was recognized as the largest
collection in the U.S. and the second largest in the world.
   Nearly 160 classic automobiles crossed the auction block during
the 12-hour event Saturday. The buyer of the 1933 Packard was from
Philadelphia but his identity was not disclosed.
   Among the top sellers were a 1930 Duesenberg Model J-225 Walker
La Grande Torpedo Phaeton, which sold for $722,500, a 1932
Duesenberg Model J-490 Derham tourister, which sold for $450,000,
and a 1929 Duesenberg Model J-350 Willoughby, which went for
$360,000.
   The weekend auction also attracted more than 600 bidders from
the United States, Switzerland, Germany, Holland, Japan, Columbia,
Canada, France, England and Sweden.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0080 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 2049EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-SaudiPrince     10-21 0170</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Saudi Prince,0180</SECOND>
<HEAD>Prince Says Sanctions Better Than Bloodshed</HEAD>
<DATELINE>RIYADH, Saudi Arabia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Prince Sultan, the Saudi defense
minister, said Sunday he was troubled by the suffering that trade
sanctions were causing Iraqis, but convinced that was a far better
thing than war.
   ``It causes us deep pain to see the Iraqi or any other nation
facing a worldwide trade embargo,'' the prince said to Saudi
newspaper editors. ``But the premise for the embargo is peace, not
war. Perhaps it is meant to spare the shedding of Iraqi blood.''
   Prince Sultan, third in the Saudi leadership after King Fahd and
Crown Prince Abdullah, said the foreign forces amassed following
the Aug. 2 invasion of Kuwait ``brought an umbrella of peace.''
   Any solution to the conflict must include an unconditional Iraqi
pullout and the restoration of the al-Sabah monarchy in Kuwait,
Sultan said.
   He denied any plans to form an Arab-Western security alliance in
the region. ``It is not acceptable that an Arab country enters into
an alliance with a non-Arab foreign power,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0081 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 2109EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-SilencedSinger     10-21 0170</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Silenced Singer,0189</SECOND>
<HEAD>Warbler Arrested for Singing Alone at Mass</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SAN ANTONIO, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A church songbird ordered by a judge
to sing with the rest of the flock or not at all was arrested
during Mass on Sunday for singing from her own repertoire of hymns.
   Elojia Macias was taken to the Bexar County Jail, and later was
freed on $400 bail.
   She was arrested after trying to enter the altar area at Our
Lady of Sorrows Catholic Church, as a morning Mass began, said
Father Alexander Wangler. She sang her own songs in the sacristy as
church officials waited for police to arrive.
   In a lawsuit last week, Wangler accused Ms. Macias of disrupting
church services by singing her own songs, causing ``confusion and
disruption.''
   State District Judge John Specia issued an injunction Thursday
ordering Ms. Macias to cooperate or risk being held in contempt of
court.
   ``We've been arguing with her for months and months,'' Wangler
said Sunday.
   ``She just wants to do it that way,'' he said. ``Friends and
neighbors have talked to her ... she needs help.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0082 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 2132EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Lebanon 1stLd-Writethru a0677 10-21 0779</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lebanon, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0677,0953</SECOND>
<HEAD>Gunmen Slaughter Aoun Aide And Family</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS last 7 grafs, bgng `Chamoun inherited ...' with 13 grafs
to ADD background on Chamoun's career. No Pickup.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos BEI1-3</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RODEINA KENAAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BAABDA, Lebanon (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Gunmen burst into the home of a top
supporter of Christian Gen. Michel Aoun Sunday and shot him, his
wife and two sons to death, police said. Only an 11-month-old girl
survived.
   The daybreak massacre of Dany Chamoun and his family in their
suburban Beirut apartment came a week after a Syrian and Lebanese
government troops crushed Aoun's mutiny in Lebanon's Christian
enclave.
   Chamoun, a Maronite Catholic and the son of late President
Camille Chamoun, was one of the most outspoken critics of President
Elias Hrawi and Syria's military presence in Lebanon.
   He also was at odds with Christian warlord Samir Geagea, whose
Lebanese Forces militia fought a four-month war with Aoun's troops
early this year for mastery of the Christian areas of east Beirut.
   No group immediately claimed responsibility for the slayings,
which were branded by Christian and Moslem leaders alike as an
attempt to block a plan to end the 15-year-old civil war.
   Aoun took refuge a week ago in the French Embassy. France has
granted him asylum, but the Lebanese government insists he stay and
stand trial for alleged crimes, including the theft of $75 million
from the state treasury.
   Five uniformed gunmen, using silencer-equipped 9mm pistols,
riddled Chamoun, 56; his wife, Ingrid Abdel-Noor, 35, and their
sons, Tarek, 7, and Julien, 5, with bullets, according to police.
   They said the 5-year-old was taken to a nearby hospital and died
a short time later. Of the family, only Chamoun's daughter, Tamara,
escaped unharmed.
   Reporters saw the baby being cradled by her weeping Lebanese
governess at the apartment in Baabda, east of Beirut.
   ``I am shocked by the horrific slayings,'' Hrawi was quoted by
several Beirut radio stations as saying. ``That's a crime against
the state aimed at sabotaging efforts to reunite the country and
army after Aoun's ouster.''
   Radios said Hrawi made the comment in Damascus, where he is
talking with Syrian President Hafez Assad on how to enforce an Arab
League-brokered plan aimed at ending the civil war between Moslems
and Christians.
   ``We have declared that the peace process is open to all to join
after the end of Aoun's mutiny and that we should bury the past and
begin a new era of fraternity,'' Hrawi was quoted as saying.
   ``Today's crime is a stab in the back.''
   In Paris, Foreign Minister Roland Dumas expressed horror at the
slayings.
   ``Dany Chamoun had opened a perspective toward reconciliation in
Lebanon,'' Dumas said. ``It's this chance they wanted to
assassinate.''
   Guards had been assigned to protect the Chamoun family around
the clock. The assailants arrived at 6 a.m., as the guards were
changing shifts, police said.
   ``The assailants snuck in at the moment of change and forced the
janitor at gunpoint to climb five flights of stairs to Chamoun's
apartment,'' said a police spokesman.
   The governess answered a knock at the door and the assailants
burst in firing, instantly killing Chamoun and his wife, police
said.
   ``The gunmen then shot the two sleeping sons in bed in an
adjacent bedroom,'' said the spokesman, who could not be named
under regulations.
   The governess, who was uninjured, gave police an account of the
attack. A family maid was also uninjured. Chamoun's hunting dog was
found whimpering over the bodies when rescuers arrived.
   The British-educated Chamoun made his political debut soon after
the outbreak of Lebanon's civil war in 1975. He was appointed
secretary of defense of his father's rightist Christian National
Liberal Party and commander of the party's ``Tigers'' militia.
   Chamoun forged friendships with Druse warlord Walid Jumblatt and
Palestine Liberation Organization Chairman Yasser Arafat's security
chief, Ali Hassan Salameh, who was assassinated in Moslem west
Beirut in 1979.
   These friendships helped free scores of kidnap victims in
Beirut's Moslem and Christian sectors during the conflict.
   Chamoun - who loved hunting, sports cars and scuba-diving -
often advocated diplomacy over the gunbarrel.
   ``Politics sucked him in although he hated politics,'' said his
former aide, Rudolf Paulikevitch.
   Chamoun inherited the leadership of the Christian National
Liberal Party upon the 1987 death of his father, who ruled Lebanon
from 1952 to 1958.
   Chamoun sought the presidency in 1988, but the Parliament was
unable to meet to elect a successor and Aoun, who then was army
commander, was named prime minister of a caretaker military
Cabinet.
   Hrawi was elected as the new president on Nov. 24, 1989, but
Aoun rejected the election, and called Hrawi a ``Syrian puppet.''
Aoun contended that his three-man Cabinet remained the only
legitimate authority in the country.
   Hrawi, Aoun and Chamoun are Maronites, the largest Christian
sect and the dominant power in Lebanon since it gained independence
from France in 1943.
   The Syrian army entered the country in 1976 under an Arab League
mandate to smother the civil war, now in its 16th year. The Syrians
currently maintain 40,000 troops controlling more than 70 percent
of Lebanon's territory.
   Chamoun was dismayed when Aoun fled his command headquarters in
the presidential palace in Baabda minutes after the air-supported
attack of Hrawi's troops and the Syrian army began Oct 13.
   ``I can't believe the general has done this to us,'' Chamoun
said the next day. ``May God help us.''
   Chamoun's first wife, Patti Morgan, an Australian-born former
fashion model, lives in London with their daughter Tracy, 30,
family friends said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0083 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 2158EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Obit-Carvel 1stLd-Writethru a0765 10-21 0334</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Carvel, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0765,0409</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ice Cream Magnate Dies at 84</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: UPDATES throughout with details.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>PINE PLAINS, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Tom Carvel, the founder of the Carvel
chain of 700 ice-cream stores who was widely known for his
gravel-voice pitches for his product in TV and radio commercials,
died Sunday at his home. He was 84.
   Carvel sold the Carvel Corp. chain for more than $80 million
last year.
   He died about 1:30 p.m. at his home in Pine Plains, a rural
community about 100 miles north of New York City, said Jim Winkle
of Riverdale Funeral Home in New York.
   The cause of death was not given. Dutchess County Sheriff
Frederick Scoralick said Carvel's doctor told him Carvel had a
history of heart problems.
   Carvel, who founded Carvel Corp. in 1938, sold his 99 percent
share to an investment bank, Investcorp, in November 1989.
   Based on annual sales, Carvel is the third-largest ice cream
store chain in the country after Dairy Queen and Haagen-Dazs. Based
in Yonkers, Carvel has more than 700 stores, most of them in New
York, Florida, Connecticut, Massachusetts, New Jersey and other
East Coast states.
   The company also owned Nedick's hot dogs and Dugan's bakery
products.
   Carvel was to stay on as a consultant, but stopped making the
commercials promoting Fudgie the Whale and Cookie Puss ice cream
cakes, Flying Saucers ice cream sandwiches and Thinny Thin dietary
frozen dessert.
   Carvel, who also had a home in Ardsley, was spending the weekend
in Pine Plains, where he owned a golf course and was planning a
700-acre residential development. Plans for the project were
stalled last year.
   Born in Greece, on July 14, 1906, Carvel's family emigrated to
the United States when he was 4 years old and settled in New York
City.
   In the 1920s, Carvel played drums in a Dixieland band, worked as
an auto mechanic and drove an ice-cream truck before opening his
first ice-cream store in Hartsdale in Westchester County.
   In the mid-1920s, Carvel developed the first machine for making
soft ice cream, and later sold the machine to store owners.
   In 1955, he did the first of his many ads in which he appealed
to the public in his raspy voice to ``please visit your local
Carvel store.''
   He is survived by his wife, Agnes. They had no children, Winkle
said. Funeral arrangments were pending, he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0084 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 2210EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Philippines-Rebels     10-21 0269</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Philippines-Rebels,0288</SECOND>
<HEAD>Report: Communists, Military Rebels Form Alliance</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MANILA, Philippines (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Military rebels claim they are
forming links with Communists and other disaffected groups and
planning a ``big bang'' to oust President Corazon Aquino before her
term ends in 1992.
   Renegade Maj. Abraham Purugganan made the claim during a
clandestine interview with Filipino reporters last Saturday. By
agreement of the reporters, the interview was made public Monday.
   Purugganan, sought by the government for his role in a coup
attempt last December, said a new coalition, the Democratic Front
for Filipinism, would seek to launch a ``nationalist revolution''
to oust Mrs. Aquino and establish a federal system of government
with a unicameral legislature.
   The Philippines currently has a centralized system of government
with a bicameral assembly.
   ``Definitely we will be moving fast before 1992,'' Purugganan
said. ``We will just have one big bang.''
   Purugganan said the alliance was formed Oct. 17 during a secret
conclave, in which a civilian with the pseudonym Felix Servando was
named chairman.
   The alliance includes the Young Officers Union, a military
faction linked to the December coup attempt, and members of various
Communist organizations.
   Mrs. Aquino has survived seven military revolts since she took
power in the February 1986 ``people power revolution'' that toppled
the late President Ferdinand Marcos.
   In the most recent attempt, military rebels led by Col.
Alexander Noble seized military camps in two cities on the
southernmost island of Mindanao on Oct. 4 but surrendered two days
later.
   Purugganan described Noble's move as a tactical blunder, but
said it did not invalidate the rebel strategy of seeking to promote
a series of uprisings that would inspire civilian support for the
rebels.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0085 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 2221EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-CalifWildfire 2ndLd-Writethru a0768 10-21 0348</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Calif Wildfire, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0768,0414</SECOND>
<HEAD>Retransmitting to correct to 2nd Ld-Writethru</HEAD>
<HEAD>Wildfire Burns In California Forest; Ebbing Winds Give
Firefighters Hope</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 5 grafs to UPDATE with fire's range reduced to 500
acres. Picks up 5th graf, `Blustery Santa ...'</NOTE>
<DATELINE>FONTANA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A fierce wind early Sunday spread a
500-acre wildfire through parts of the San Bernardino National
Forest, but firefighters began to gain on the blaze later in the
day when the wind ebbed.
   The fire, which began Saturday night, burned through brush and
timber in the western part of the forest, said Hal Seyden of the
U.S. Forest Service. The cause of the blaze, in an area ravaged by
fire two years ago, was unknown.
   Two firefighters suffered minor injuries and a house caught fire
in the Simi Valley, Seyden said.
   The blaze began in rugged Lytle Creek Canyon and burned up
5,000-foot San Sevine Ridge, he said.
   Officials initially estimated that the fire had spread over as
much as 2,000 acres but later downgraded that figure to 500 acres,
said Bill Rolls of the U.S. Forest Service.
   Blustery Santa Ana winds up to 50 mph roared through the
mountain canyons, pushing the fire through hundreds of acres
overnight and grounding aircraft, forcing crews to chop fire lines
by hand.
   By afternoon the winds had dropped and were helping contain the
fire by pushing the fire back on itself. Earlier, water-dropping
helicopters and air tankers carrying fire-retardant were aloft on
bombardment missions.
   The blaze halted its sluggish southern advance toward the towns
of Rialto, Fontana and Rancho Cucamonga.
   Thick smoke from the blaze 60 miles northeast of downtown Los
Angeles could be seen on the beach in Santa Monica. Ash fell over
parts of Fontana, some 10 miles south of the fire line.
   Late Sunday, about 500 firefighters worked the fire's northern
edge, which was feeding on heavy, drought-stricken brush and
timber.
   Dirt roads rutted by recent rains were being widened and graded
to help firefighters, who worked mostly by hand, said Mary Bowman
of the Forest Service.
   ``We have a lot of archaeological finds, and they don't want to
put the bulldozers up there unless they have to,'' Bowman said.
``You see pottery shards, arrowheads, stuff like that. We want to
be careful.''
   The fire was burning partially in an area destroyed by a
September and October 1988 fire that burned 5,160 acres of national
forest land.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0086 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 2224EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Greece-Elections     10-21 0307</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Greece-Elections,0313</SECOND>
<HEAD>Government-Backed Candidate Wins in Runoff</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PHILIP DOPOULOS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ATHENS, Greece (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The mayor of Greece's second-largest city
narrowly won re-election Sunday in a runoff vote, marking a gain
for the ruling conservative party.
   Salonica Mayor Constantine Cosmopoulos received slightly more
than 50 percent of the vote to beat Dimitris Fatouros, jointly
supported by socialists and communists.
   Cosmopoulos' victory gave Premier Constantine Mitsotakis'
conservative New Democracy party control of the nation's two
largest cities and more more than 90 other mayoral seats in smaller
communities.
   The Athens election was settled in the first round of voting
last Sunday. Conservative-backed Antonis Tritsis defeated
actress-turned-politician Melina Mercouri by 50.15 percent to 45.78
percent. Ms. Mercouri is a Parliament member for the Panhellenic
Socialist Movement, the largest opposition group.
   The two-stage mayoral and council elections were seen as a
referendum on the government's austerity measures, taken to reduce
the national debt and ease other economic woes.
   Socialist and communist-backed candidates secured 116 mayoral
posts in the first round of balloting. Independents scored seven
victories.
   Official results are not expected before Monday from most of the
143 municipalities holding runoff elections Sunday.
   In the third-biggest city, the port of Piraeus, first-round
elections were won by Stelios Logothetis, the joint candidate of
the socialists and the communist-dominated Coalition of the Left
and Progress.
   After taking office in April, Mitsotakis implemented economic
reform measures that include abolition of inflation-linked salaries
in 1991 and proposals to sell many ailing state industries.
   Greece, a member of the 12-nation European Community, has an
inflation rate of about 22 percent and a public debt officially
estimated at $100 billion.
   The government's belt-tightening measures provoked many strikes,
including five 24-hour general strikes last month.
   The newly elected mayors and local officials take office January
1.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0087 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 2245EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Gulf-Iraq-Britain     10-21 0334</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Iraq-Britain,0390</SECOND>
<HEAD>Former British Prime Minister Meets with Saddam</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DILIP GANGULY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BAGHDAD, Iraq (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Former British Prime Minister Edward Heath
said Sunday he had won agreement from Iraqi President Saddam
Hussein for the release of sick and elderly British hostages.
   During a three-hour meeting, Saddam agreed to release an
unspecified number of Britons, Heath said, adding he did not know
exactly how many would be released. They were to fly out of Baghdad
on Tuesday, Heath said.
   ``At this moment, his staff and mine are discussing lists of
names of possible people who will return to Britain, so therefore I
can't tell you or anybody else of particular names,'' Heath said.
   When he flew to Baghdad on Saturday, the 74-year-old ex-premier
said he was on a private mission to win release of 53 British
hostages identified as ailing or elderly. He met with Iraqi Foreign
Minister Tariq Aziz Saturday.
   Asked about the rest of the estimated 1,400 Britons who are
trapped in Iraq and Kuwait, Heath said, ``I don't think progress
will be made there until there is a removal of fear of lightning
attack by the Americans or anybody else, particularly the
Americans.''
   Thousands of Westerners are being held in Iraq at strategic
locations to deter a possible attack by the U.S.-led multinational
forces.
   Heath said Saddam placed ``very considerable'' emphasis on
diplomatic action in the crisis in order to achieve a stable Middle
East.
   Saddam ``recognizes its intense danger and the disastrous effect
warfare could have on the whole region, and the crisis can have on
the world economy,'' Heath said.
   Heath's trip has drawn fire in Britain, where the government has
refused negotiations with Saddam as long as he holds Westerners
hostage.
   ``Every hint that the West is prepared somehow to do deals or to
move away from unconditional and immediate withdrawal is succor to
Baghdad,'' said David Howell, a conservative member of Parliament
and chairman of the Foreign Affairs Select Committee.
   But Foreign Secretary Douglas Hurd, also speaking on BBC radio
Sunday, said if Heath succeeds in getting hostages freed ``I think
everybody would be glad.''
   ``He's made it clear his mission is humanitarian, that he's not
speaking or negotiating or acting on behalf of the government,''
Hurd said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0088 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 2253EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-CheapWines     10-21 0256</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Cheap Wines,0294</SECOND>
<HEAD>County Call to Ban Cheap Liquor Goes Unheeded</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Skid Row liquor stores have thwarted a
year-old effort to curb sales of cheap, potent wine favored by
street drunks.
   Los Angeles County Supervisor Ed Edelman proposed in September
1989 that winemakers voluntarily stop selling such wines on Skid
Row to combat alcoholism. But many liquor store owners said the
idea was a waste of time.
   ``They'd just drink something else,'' said Jack Simone, owner of
Jack's Market. ``All this hullabaloo about alcohol being the
menace, when it is really crack (cocaine).''
   A pint bottle of the wine sells for around $1.75 and is 18
percent alcohol.
   E.&amp;J. Gallo Winery of California and Canandaigua Wine Co. of New
York, two of the nation's largest producers of cheap wines, agreed
to halt sales to Skid Rows around the country.
   The voluntary ban in Los Angeles was based on a similar program
in San Francisco's Tenderloin district.
   ``The ban has been a complete joke,'' said Mike Neely, director
of the Homeless Outreach Project. ``The price went up. That's about
all that happened.''
   A consulting company found that, in Los Angeles County at least,
``the overall availability of fortified wines in general does not
appear to have changed substantially.''
   Many stores apparently stockpiled the wine anticipating the ban,
said Virginia McLain Rusk of the Ernst &amp; Young.
   Edelman said he favors a mandatory ban if the voluntary effort
fails, but Neely said the best way to fight Skid Row alcoholism is
to provide more counseling and treatment programs.
   ``Banning alcohol is not the solution,'' said Neely. ``They
tried that during Prohibition. What makes them think it will work
in the 1990s?''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0089 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 2306EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-SouthKorea-Protest     10-21 0184</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-South Korea-Protest,0184</SECOND>
<HEAD>Radicals Firebomb Main Intelligence Office</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SEOUL, South Korea (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Radical students firebombed the main
office of a police intelligence agency in central Seoul Monday and
scattered leaflets demanding the government stop spying on
dissidents.
   Police arrested eight of the protesters, who were also demanding
the ouster of President Roh Tae-woo.
   The students hurled about 20 firebombs on the office of the
Agency for National Security Planning. The initial reports did not
say if the attack caused any major damage to the office in central
Seoul.
   Police said a firebomb exploded at an adjacent police station,
burning a motorcycle.
   Government intelligence offices have been the target of protests
by dissidents and radical students since a spy scandal involving a
military intelligence unit surfaced early this month.
   Roh fired the defense minister and head of the military's
Defense Security Command amid revelations that officials had spied
illegally on more than 1,300 dissidents, intellectuals and
opposition legislators.
   In a speech commemorating Police Day, Roh on Monday urged police
to crack down on social unrest and crime.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0090 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 2314EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Baseball-Newspage     10-21 0209</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Baseball-Newspage,0228</SECOND>
<HEAD>Fans Greet Champion Cincinnati Reds</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CINCINNATI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hundreds of screaming fans met the Cincinnati
Reds' chartered jet Sunday night as the World Series champions
returned home after completing one of the biggest upsets in
baseball history.
   At least 500 people gathered at Greater Cincinnati International
Airport and cheered wildly as the door of the plane opened and the
team descended.
   ``It's stirring. It's just overwhelming for all these people to
be out here at this hour of the night,'' Reds owner Marge Schott
said after emerging from the plane to cheers of ``Marge! Marge!
Marge!'' and ``Sweep! Sweep! Sweep!''
   ``They're great fans. I love them,'' she said.
   The Reds rallied past the heavily fancied Oakland Athletics by
2-1 on Saturday night, winning the World Series in four quick
games.
   Pitcher Jose Rijo, who won Games 1 and 4 and earned the Series
MVP award, said he looks forward to repeating.
   ``Next year, we've got to win it again,'' Rijo said. ``This is
too much fun.''
   The city of Cincinnati and the Downtown Council are sponsoring a
parade on Monday along a six-block downtown route, followed by a
rally.
   On Saturday night, raucous fans honked horns, exchanged hugs and
high-fives, and tipped over plastic roadway construction barrels in
downtown Cincinnati. Police estimated the crowd at about 10,000.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901021-0091 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-21-90 1755EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f BC-Colombia-Petroleum     10-21 0272</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Colombia-Petroleum,0282</SECOND>
<HEAD>Colombia Pledges New Incentives for Foreign Oil Companies</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BOGOTA, Colombia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Colombian government plans to
increase incentives for petroleum and gas exploration by foreign
companies, President Cesar Gaviria said.
   ``The government will begin a rapid evaluation of the changes
necessary ... to make exploration of inactive areas more
attractive,'' Gaviria said Saturday while inaugurating a new gas
pipeline in central Colombia.
   Gaviria did not specify what types of changes the government was
considering. The president's comments were reported Sunday by local
news media.
   Current government contracts assign oil exploration to several
multinational companies operating in Colombia. If petroleum
deposites are discovered, the government and the foreign companies
share the cost of developing them.
   Colombia receives 60 percent of the petroleum produced while the
foreign companies take the remaining 40 percent and pay taxes on
their earnings.
   The companies are pushing for a better deal because of the high
risks involved in searching for petroleum in Colombia.
   One of the country's leftist guerrilla groups, the National
Liberation Army, or ELN, has repeatedly sabotaged oil facilities
and kidnapped employees of foreign petroleum companies.
   Gaviria said Saturday that the rebels should abandon the
campaign and participae in next year's assembly to rewrite
Colombia's constitution and reform its democracy.
   Attacks by the rebels on petroleum facilities have caused $520
million in losses and have produced a steep drop in exploration
activity, according to the state oil company Ecopetrol.
   Of the 450,000 barrels of oil produced each day in Colombia,
220,000 barrels are exported. Petroleum, Colombia's leading export,
is expected to earn it more than 1.5 billion dollars in foreign
exchange this year.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
</Collection>
