<Collection>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0001 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 2323EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Hungary 5thLd-Writethru a0752 03-25 1213</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Hungary, 5th Ld-Writethru, a0752,1249</SECOND>
<HEAD>Communists Appear Headed for Defeat in Hungary's Elections</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: ADDS in 7th graf, `In Hungary...' that there are 386
parliament seats and DELETES incorrect figure from 27th graf; ADDS
in 22nd graf, `The Democratic' description of political parties;
pickup 28th graf pvs, `But pre-election...'</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos BUD5,6</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GEORGE JAHN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUDAPEST, Hungary (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hungarians voted Sunday in their first
free elections after 43 years of Communist rule, and early results
indicated the party would lose despite taking a lead role in
democratic reforms.
   ``We will be an opposition party,'' said Rezsoe Nyers, chairman
of the Socialist Party, which was created by reformers to replace
the old Communist Party. ``This, to use a religious term, will be
penance for the party.''
   ``We will come through it, and we will be strong,'' he added.
   Premier Miklos Nemeth, a Communist reformer and a key engineer
of the nation's conversion to democracy, declared before he voted
that he was relinquishing control ``head high and with a clear
conscience.''
   A report by the official news agency said Nemeth won a
parliamentary seat as an independent in a district northeast of
Budapest. But his party appeared to have done poorly elsewhere.
   East Germany held Eastern Europe's first free elections in
decades on March 18, and the Communists were rejected there.
   In Hungary, they competed with 11 other national parties for 386
parliament seats. No party held a clear lead in the early returns.
   Despite occasional showers, voter turnout appeared heavy in
Budapest. Few irregularities were reported by 8 p.m., when polling
stations closed. Several international observers had monitored the
election.
   About 7.8 million people were eligible to vote and Janos Nemeth,
chairman of the Elections Committee, said preliminary figures
showed turnout was more than 70 percent.
   Premier Nemeth, who voted at a state-run kindergarten serving as
one of 11,000 polling stations across the nation, declined to
predict the chances of his Socialist Party, which has governed
since reform-oriented Communists formed it after defecting from
their party in October.
   ``The only thing I hope for is that a strong government is
created,'' Nemeth said, adding that only a government not hamstrung
by the opposition can deal with the nation's ailing economy.
   His comments reflected widespread acceptance, even among
Socialists, that his party would not do well despite its role,
unique in Eastern Europe, in steering Hungary to democratic reform.
   Instead of crediting the Socialists for volunteering to play by
democratic rules, most voters remember the excesses of more than
four decades of one-party rule that have made Communists unpopular
throughout the Soviet bloc.
   ``I won't consider it an act of God if I don't make it into
government,'' Nemeth told reporters. ``I will hand over the reins
head high and with a clear conscience. I don't have bitterness in
my heart but satisfaction.''
   The state MTI news agency reported that Nemeth won a
parliamentary seat in Szerencs, a village about 70 miles northeast
of Budapest, where he ran as an independent.
   With voters able to vote separately for candidates and parties,
Nemeth had one of two chances of election, as an individual
candidate or as a nominee of his party on the Budapest regional
slate. He would be struck from the party list if he won in Szerencs.
   Election results trickled in at election commission headquarters
in the gothic Parliament building and at the election studio of
state television.
   Officials decided to stay with the familiar method of counting
ballots by hand and using computers only to cross-check the tally.
   In East Germany, by contrast, trends were established soon after
polls closed, with West German computer technology quickly
delivering results in a system typical of Western election coverage.
   But Hungarian officials in most districts had tallied less than
25 percent of the vote by early Monday, and final results were not
expected before late in the day.
   The centrist Democratic Forum got the most votes in four
districts and led in nine more. The liberal League of Free
Democrats got the most votes in one district and led in eight
others. The Independent Smallholders, a rural party, led in two
districts and the Socialists led in two others.
   However, no candidate or party gained the absolute majority in
any of the districts where counting was complete, and all of those
Parliament seats were subject to a second round of voting.
   Hungary's last elections were in 1947, when the Communists won a
relative majority, largely through fraud. A year later, they
consolidated power and forced all other parties out of existence.
   Throughout the monthlong campaign, Socialist candidates
attempted to convince the electorate of their commitment to a
multiparty system.
   But pre-election opinion polls indicated the Socialists would
finish no higher than fourth place, with a maximum 10 percent of
the overall vote.
   A poll of 5,000 people published by the state MTI news agency
less than one hour before polls closed indicated the center-right
Hungarian Democratic Forum would finish strongest, with 31 seats.
The poll predicted the liberal Free Democrats would win 30 seats,
the Independent Smallholders 22; the activist liberal League of
Young Democrats 18, and the Socialists eight seats.
   While proposing a variety of solutions on how to complete the
transformation from an ossified command economy to one obeying free
market rules, most of the parties competing in some or all of the
176 districts espouse centrist ideas.
   Election rules call for a second round in case no single party
wins an absolute majority Sunday and expectations were high that
scattered voter loyalties would force a runoff _ tentatively
scheduled for April 8.
   Even new elections, however, were not expected to determine a
clear winner, making a coalition government the most likely
scenario.
   The Socialists were unlikely to play a role much beyond Sunday.
Leading parties such as the Democratic Forum and the Free Democrats
have repeatedly stated they would reject them as government
partners.
   But Democratic Forum Chairman Jozsef Antall refused to comment
Sunday when asked by reporters about possible coalition partners.
   Asked about his thoughts during balloting, Antall, a medical
historian, said: ``We want a free Hungary. And I'm happy that we've
come this far.''
   Free Democrat leader Janos Kis said he expected his party to be
one of the top two finishers.
   As he waited for a polling booth to become free, Kis explained
the ballot to his school-age son.
   Many of more than a dozen voters questioned at random expressed
optimism about the future. But some appeared to carry the scars of
the past.
   ``This is a great day in our country's history,'' declared
Democratic Forum supporter Bela Kiraly, 50. ``I'm sure it marks a
new beginning.''
   His wife, Irene, also 50, said she voted for the Democratic
Forum on the national list of candidates and for the Free Democrats
on the local slate ``because the more diversity in Parliament, the
better.
   ``If any one party becomes too strong, we might return to the
same situation we've had for 40 years,'' she said, referring to
past Communist rule.
   A 77-year old woman refused to give her name and preference, but
suggested she was sceptical that democracy had arrived to stay in
Hungary.
   ``I've survived too many systems to tell anybody who I vote
for,'' she said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0002 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 2330EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-GreyhoundStrike     03-25 0230</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Greyhound Strike,0238</SECOND>
<HEAD>Lawsuit Filed in Death of Picket</HEAD>
<DATELINE>REDDING, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The widow and children of a Greyhound bus
driver who was killed on a picket line have filed a $50 million
lawsuit against the company and the replacement driver of the bus
that crushed him.
   Robert Waterhouse, 59, was killed March 3 on the second day of a
nationwide strike against Greyhound Lines Inc. He was crushed
against a wall by the bus.
   There have been numerous violent incidents since, including
several cases in which gunshots were fired at buses.
   Federal mediators have tried unsuccessfully to restart talks in
the pay dispute between Greyhound and the Amalgamated Council of
Local Greyhound Unions, which represents the 6,300 drivers and
3,000 other Greyhound workers.
   Police are still investigating Waterhouse's death, and the
Shasta County district attorney is expected to decide next week
whether to file criminal charges.
   The wrongful death suit filed in Shasta County Superior Court
names Greyhound and the replacement driver hired for the strike,
Theodore Graham Jr. of Portland, Ore.
   The complaint alleges that Greyhound was negligent in hiring
Graham ``in that Graham was not qualified in training and
disposition to drive a passenger bus.''
   The suit also alleges that the company employed nonunion drivers
in ``an illegal attempt at strikebreaking and union-breaking.''
   Waterhouse was only months away from retirement after 32 years
with Greyhound.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0003 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 2337EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-SovietRotary 1st-LdWritethru a0733 03-25 0540</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet Rotary, 1st-Ld Writethru, a0733,0550</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rotary To Open First Club in Soviet Union</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: UPDATES throughout with comments from Rotary president after
return from Moscow. No pickup</NOTE>
<HEAD>jwhofonscg</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JAMES WEBB</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CHICAGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The first Rotary club in the Soviet Union has
been officially established after several years of
behind-the-scenes efforts, the president of the international
service organization said Sunday.
   A tired but happy Hugh Archer, president of Rotary
International, said three years of contacts between Soviet
ambassadors and Rotary officials from around the world led to his
final journey this weekend through the Soviet bureaucracy.
   ``It was difficult from the standpoint of intrigue, in getting
the word to the person who could help us,'' Archer said in a
telephone interview Sunday night after returning from to Moscow.
   ``Nobody there wishes to speak as an individual. What we had to
do was get a lot of people convinced that it was OK to have a
Rotary club started in Moscow.''
   Archer finally got approval from Soviet officials for a
provisional club that will initially be made up of about 25
business and professional people from Moscow.
   Rotary International, which has over 1 million members in more
than 100 countries, has forged growing links with Eastern Europe in
recent years. In June 1989, Rotary established its first clubs in
Poland and Hungary since World War II, said John O'Brien, a
spokesman for Rotary International, based in suburban Evanston, Ill.
   Archer first met with Soviet officials in December to explore
the possibilities of opening a club in Moscow. He also visited a
group eager to form a club in Tallinn, the capital of the Soviet
republic of Estonia.
   In a key discussion Saturday with Deputy Minister of Foreign
Affairs Vladimir Petrovsky, Archer said he received assurances the
club can meet and select members without surveillance or
restrictions and that it will be allowed to maintain contacts with
clubs in other countries and contribute financially to the
association.
   Rotary's constitution prohibits it from becoming part of another
organization or being restricted by government or political forces.
   ``It all follows from (Soviet President Mikhail) Gorbachev
because of his reforms that sort of paved the way,'' O'Brien said.
``But Rotary has not gone cap in hand begging to open a club.
   The members of the provisional club in Moscow, who have been
holding informal meetings for the past six months, range in age
from 30 to 50. They include two lawyers, three businessmen, a
theater manager and the head of a translation service.
   Archer said the group was delighted when told of the agreement
and immediately began discussing ideas, especially exchange
programs with other countries involving Rotary members, as well as
high school and college students.
   He said the Soviets at first had trouble understanding that they
were expected to help people without receiving anything in return.
   ``The concept of service as practiced by Rotary and other groups
is that you enjoy it'' without expectation of compensation, Archer
said. ``I think they got that idea.''
   Rotary, founded in Chicago in 1905, is a not-for-profit service
organization consisting of business and professional men and women.
It sponsors educational and charitable programs and has a budget of
$56 million for 1989-90.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0004 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 2346EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-GuamAbortion     03-25 0295</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Guam Abortion,0302</SECOND>
<HEAD>Judge Sets Trial Date for Anti-Abortion Law</HEAD>
<DATELINE>AGANA, Guam (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A federal judge on Monday extended a
restraining order against enforcement of the most restrictive U.S.
abortion law.
   U.S. District Judge Alex Munson had issued a temporary
restraining order Friday, a few hours after a group of Guam
residents and medical groups filed a class-action suit. On Monday,
he extended the order until May 8, when a trial on the suit is
scheduled to begin.
   ``We're very happy,'' said Anita Arriola, the plaintiffs'
attorney.
   The law prohibits abortions except when a pregnancy endangers
the life of the mother. It makes it a third-degree felony to
perform an abortion or aid in the procedure, a misdemeanor for a
woman to solicit or have an abortion and a misdemeanor for a person
to solicit a woman to have an abortion.
   The law in this Pacific territory is seen by abortion opponents
as a potential vehicle to challenge the U.S. Supreme Court's Roe
vs. Wade decision that legalized abortion.
   The Guam law provides for a referendum in the Nov. 6 general
election for Guam voters to decide whether to retain or reject the
abortion ban.
   Janet Benshoof, director of the American Civil Liberties Union's
Reproductive Freedom Project defied the law last Tuesday when she
publicly encouraged women seeking abortions to have them done in
Hawaii. She was charged in the territorial Supreme Court with
solicitation to commit abortion, a misdemeanor.
   Among those named in the suit is Gov. Joseph Ada, who signed the
measure into law March 19.
   The plaintiffs include ``Maria Doe,'' a Guam woman who is eight
weeks pregnant and wants an abortion; the Guam Society of
Obstetricians and Gynecologists, the Guam Nurses Association, an
Episcopal priest and three Guam doctors.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0005 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 0012EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Pilots-Alcohol     03-25 0421</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Pilots-Alcohol,0433</SECOND>
<HEAD>Report: 41 Pilots Lost State Driver Licenses</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MINNEAPOLIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   At least 41 pilots of passenger aircraft have
lost their Minnesota driver's licenses in the past seven years
because of alcohol abuse, according to a published report.
   Of those who lost licenses, 28 were employed by Egan-based
Northwest Airlines, the Star Tribune reported in its Sunday
editions.
   Officials of Northwest and the Federal Aviation Administration
declined to comment on the findings, as did a national spokesman
for the Air Line Pilots Association.
   The issue gained widespread attention when three Northwest
pilots were arrested this month after a flight from Fargo, N.D., to
Minneapolis. The pilots were later fired by Northwest and have been
charged with flying an airliner while under the influence of
alcohol.
   The paper made its count using an FAA list of more than 2,000
Minnesota-based pilots who hold an air-transport license, the kind
required of airline captains, and a Class 1 medical certificate,
the highest available. A pilot must hold a transport license to
carry passengers for money, but private pilots also may hold such a
license.
   The pilot list was checked against Department of Public Safety
records and court files for alcohol-related driving violations over
the past seven years.
   Of 41 pilots with alcohol offenses, 25 were convicted of drunken
driving or equivalent charges and 15 pleaded guilty to lesser
charges, which enabled them to avoid reporting their alcohol
violations to the FAA, the newspaper said. It didn't list the
offense of the 41st pilot.
   Ten of the pilots had surrendered their driver's licenses for a
year at some point rather than take blood-alcohol tests.
   The FAA has relied on pilots to voluntarily report alcohol
convictions to the agency. Pilots often don't do so for fear
they'll be diagnosed as alcoholic and lose their licenses to fly,
the paper said.
   A 1987 audit by the U.S. Transportation Department found that
three-fourths of all U.S. pilots who were convicted of
alcohol-related offenses failed to report them to the FAA, as
required.
   Northwest doesn't ask its pilots to report violations to the
company, nor does it routinely check their driving records, which
are available to the public, the Star Tribune said.
   The FAA said last year that it intends to begin matching pilot
names with those on the government's National Driver Register,
which lists drivers whose licenses have been suspended or revoked.
The agency also is seeking authority to cancel the medical
certificates of pilots with multiple alcohol offenses and is
considering testing pilots after accidents.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0006 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 0037EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Hungary 1stLd-Writethru a0531 03-25 0855</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Hungary, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0531,0879</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hungarians Begin Voting in First Free Election Since 1947</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with three grafs with polls opening; Pickup 3rd pvs,
`In a...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By TEDDIE WEYR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUDAPEST, Hungary (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hungarians voted Sunday in their first
free elections since 1947 and seemed determined to oust the
Communists who initiated democratic reform in hopes of gaining
credit at the ballot box.
   Polling stations opened at 6 a.m., with the last scheduled to
close 14 hours later. About 7.8 million Hungarians are eligible to
vote.
   Hungarians will choose a 394-seat Parliament in Eastern Europe's
second free elections, a week after East Germans backed a
center-right movement to lead them to unity with West Germany.
   In a Soviet bloc rushing toward democracy, Hungary remains
unique. While the people forced the Communists in East Germany,
Czechoslovakia and Romania to grant demands for democracy,
Hungary's Communists initiated reform, then changed their name to
the Socialists and said they espoused Western-style Social
Democratic ideals.
   Yet there is little sign voters will reward them. Opinion polls
suggest the Socialists will end up with only about 10 percent of
the overall vote.
   In a year of remarkable reforms begun in the fall of 1988,
Hungary's Communists pointed the way for Eastern Europe by
scrapping their party's guaranteed leading role from the
constitution, legalizing a multiparty system, passing a new
electoral law and altering the country's name and emblem to wipe
out Communist affiliations. Hungary also opened its western border,
allowing thousands of East Germans to flee their homeland and
helping to bring about the fall of East Germany's hard-line
Communist leaders.
   But those changes were overshadowed by memories of 43 years of
Communist rule in Hungary.
   In 1947 elections, the Communists won a relative majority,
largely through fraud. A year later, they consolidated power and
forced all other parties out of existence.
   All opposition parties contesting Sunday's ballot declared
themselves open to almost any coalition scenario, but excluded
governing with the Socialists.
   A popular poster from the Hungarian Democratic Forum, one of the
leading contenders for power, symbolized the anti-Communist,
anti-Soviet slant of the campaign. It showed a bull-necked soldier
with the Russian-language caption: ``Comrades, It's all over.''
   While united in opposition to communism, Hungarians are unlikely
to show a firm preference for any one party. This would require a
second round of voting tentatively scheduled April 8.
   Opinion polls suggested up to 25 percent of the voters were
undecided about whom to back Sunday.
   International groups sent delegations to monitor the elections.
Former Vice President Walter Mondale, leading a 50-member group,
said there were a ``couple of pimples here and there'' in the
campaign, but no major problems.
   The campaign centered mostly on unpleasant economic truths that
are taking the edge off the thrill of choosing a government.
   Most parties agree that the stultified centralized economy
should be converted to one governed by market forces. None can deny
the transformation is likely to bring unemployment and still higher
prices to a country battling double-digit inflation.
   The new government also will inherit a $20 billion foreign debt,
the highest per capita in Eastern Europe.
   Another primary issue was Romania's treatment of its ethnic
Hungarians. At least seven people were killed last week in ethnic
unrest in Transylvania, uniting all Hungarian parties and awakening
fears of neighboring Romania.
   At one opposition rally Friday, a woman expressed concern over
any opposition move to accelerate the total withdrawal of Soviet
troops, saying she feared a possible Romanian military threat.
   Twelve parties garnered enough support to run on the national
list in the complex electoral system forged by the Communists and
opposition last year.
   Seventeen other parties are running candidates on the local
level, with as many as 14 candidates in some races. Twenty-one
parties offered no candidates.
   The six considered most likely to win seats in Parliament are
the Hungarian Democratic Forum, the League of Free Democrats, the
Independent Smallholders' Party, the governing Socialist Party, the
League of Young Democrats and the Social Democratic Party of
Hungary.
   Despite the broad palette of parties, there were only two basic
ideological trends on the political landscape _ the populist
nationalism of the center right, and more radical left-of-center
liberalism.
   The conservative Democratic Forum lays considerable emphasis on
Hungarian traditions and Christian values, which are also espoused
by the smaller Hungarian Peoples' Party and the Christian
Democratic Peoples' Party. Their strength lies largely in
provincial towns outside Budapest.
   The Forum led slightly in the most recent Gallup poll from March
12, with 21 percent.
   Next strongest with 20.3 percent were the Free Democrats, a
liberal party with social democratic leanings that wants to move
Hungary quickly toward a Western-style society. There was no margin
of error cited in the poll.
   Third in the poll with 15.7 percent of support of the 1,000
respondents, were the Independent Smallholders. Their main support
is in rural Hungary, where they have pledged to return land taken
by the Communists to its owners.
   The League of Young Democrats espouses views close to those of
the Free Democrats and hopes to garner 10 percent of the vote.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0007 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 0141EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Cuba-Jamming 2ndLd-Writethru a0629 03-25 0471</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Cuba-Jamming, 2nd Ld - Writethru, a0629,0479</SECOND>
<HEAD>Six Florida Stations Pick Up Castro Speech</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 11th graf to CORRECT town to Donelson sted Donaldson</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By CATHERINE WILSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A speech by Cuban President Fidel Castro that could
be heard on radios as far away as North Carolina raised concern
Saturday that ``the warning shot across the bow'' may have been
fired in the battle over TV Marti.
   The Federal Communications Commission complained to Cuba about
the broadcast over six AM frequencies, said spokeswoman Lorrie
Secrest.
   TV Marti, the U.S.-financed television station, is expected to
begin beaming programs to Cuba this month from a balloon over the
Florida Keys in spite of Cuba's protests.
   Cuba regards the prospect of U.S. news shows, sitcoms and soap
operas as a blatant intrusion on national sovereignty _ or
``tele-agression,'' as Castro calls it.
   In the midst of final preparations for the debut of TV Marti,
Castro's Havana speech popped onto the airwaves Friday night, Ms.
Secrest said.
   U.S. signals have been jammed many times in recent years,
especially when the 5-year-old Radio Marti, the model for the TV
station, was being debated in Congress.
   The Cuban government has threatened retaliation if the Bush
administration went ahead with a 90-day test of TV Marti. Previous
radio jamming from the communist nation has come at different
times, frequencies and power levels.
   ``We are very vulnerable in the United States,'' said Susan
Kraus, spokeswoman for the National Association for Broadcasters.
``We have to wonder if this is the warning shot across the bow
preceding an all-out radio war.''
   Of primary concern to U.S. broadcasters is Cuba's transmitting
potential, including a 1 million-watt and two 500,000-watt
transmitters. The highest power level allowed by FCC licenses is
50,000 watts.
   ``They have the capability of jamming AM stations in more than
30 states, all the way north to the Canadian border and all the way
west to Utah,'' Kraus said Saturday in a telephone interview from
Washington. ``They have demonstrated this in the past.''
   Although stations as distant as Colorado have reported previous
jamming, only two stations, WAMB in Donelson, Tenn. and WYRU in Red
Springs, N.C., had filed complaints by late Saturday night, said
Ms. Secrest.
   She said the FCC is following up on reports that the speech
interfered with the signal of at least six AM stations south of
Palm Beach.
   The Cuban Communist Party newspaper Granma mentioned Friday
morning that Castro's remarks would be broadcast toward to United
States on Friday evening, and the FCC picked up the broadcast at 9
p.m. EST.
   Castro, who has been holding fast against the reforms of the
East Bloc, said in his speech that he recognized the socialist
world has reached a delicate point but added, ``Capitalism hasn't
solved the problems of Latin America.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0008 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 0350EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i BC-Australia     03-25 0478</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Australia,0495</SECOND>
<HEAD>Conservatives Concede Labor Likely to Prevail in Elections</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RICHARD BILL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SYDNEY, Australia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Prime Minister Bob Hawke said Sunday it
appeared his Labor Party prevailed in parliamentary elections and
his conservative opponent, Andrew Peacock, conceded a Labor victory
was likely.
   Hawke, speaking a day after Saturday's vote, said he expected a
one-seat majority in the 148-seat House of Representatives. He said
a ``worst case scenario'' would give Labor 73 seats, and the
conservative coalition 73, with two independents.
   Hawke, clearly surprised by the apparent tight outcome, said
that when final results are in, ``I hope it may be a bit better
than that (one seat). It will give a sense of discipline for sure
and we can do it.''
   Peacock, 51, would not concede defeat. But on Sunday, the leader
of the Liberal and National Party coalition acknowledged Labor had
a better chance of taking the election.
   ``If you are setting a book I suggest the shortest odds would be
regrettably on a hung parliament, followed then by a Labor
government just ahead of a possibility of a Coalition government,''
Peacock said in Melbourne.
   Peacock, who made his second bid for the prime ministership,
emphasized, however, the outcome of six or seven seats in the
states of Western Australia and Queensland still had not been
decided.
   Vote counting, routinely suspended for Sunday, was to resume
Monday. Political leaders said the results won't be known for sure
until Thursday, when mail-in ballots are counted.
   Forty of 70 Senate seats were also contested Saturday, and early
results showed the small Democratic Party made strong gains. The
House, the more powerful chamber, chooses the prime minister.
   Communities with undecided races included the small town of
Kennedy in northern Queensland, where several thousand voters were
unable to cast their ballots because polling booths were cut off by
floodwaters.
   Hawke, 60, has governed for seven years. He campaigned on his
record of economic management, despite dissatisfaction over record
home mortgage interest rates and a $100 billion foreign debt.
   Hawke said the 1990 election would set the course for Australian
politics into the 21st century.
   Australia has 10.6 million eligible voters among its 16.5
million people, and voting is compulsory.
   When vote counting closed Saturday night, Labor appeared to have
won 73 seats, the coalition 70 and the Independents two.
   The independents, the first elected in 24 years, could hold the
balance of power in the House. Labor, which had 85 seats in the
previous lower house, needs 75 seats for a working majority.
   Australia is a close U.S. ally, and President Bush said he hoped
to visit the country before the year's end.
   Hawke came to power in 1983, was re-elected the following year
and again in 1987. He has said that, if re-elected in this race, he
will seek a fifth term before retiring.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0009 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 0452EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>b a BC-ApartmentFire     03-25 0035</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Apartment Fire,0034</SECOND>
<HEAD>BULLETIN</HEAD>
<HEAD>50 Die in New York City Fire</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   At least 50 people died in a fire at a social
club in the Bronx borough, police said Sunday.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0010 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 0541EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i BC-Britain-Runcie     03-25 0371</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Britain-Runcie,0383</SECOND>
<HEAD>Anglican Spiritual Leader Announces Retirement</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Most Rev. Robert Runcie said Sunday he will
retire next January as archbishop of Canterbury, the leader of 70
million Anglicans worldwide.
   Runcie made the announcement during a morning service at
Canterbury Cathedral marking the 10th anniversary of his
enthronement, his London office said.
   Runcie offered his resignation to Queen Elizabeth II in her role
as head of the Church of England, one of 27 self-governing churches
within the Anglican Communion, which also includes 2.5 million U.S.
Episcopalians.
   The Church of England requires its bishops to retire at age 70,
but Runcie said he would step down on January 31, eight months
before his 70th birthday on Oct. 2, 1991.
   The gap leaves time for Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher to
appoint his successor. It is widely believed she will select
someone whose social and economic views are more in tune with her
own.
   Runcie, a liberal prelate, has often spoken against the policies
of Mrs. Thatcher's governing Conservative Party.
   He preached forgiveness after Britain's victory over Argentina
in the 1982 Falklands war, he supported coal miners during their
1984 strike, and in 1985 Runcie said the English church should
contribute millions of dollars to relieve poverty and homelessness
in Britain.
   ``I judge the beginning of 1991 to be the right time for me to
hand over to the next archbishbop of Canterbury,'' Runcie said in a
statement.
   ``The public announcement today will give sufficient time for
the name of my successor to be known well before the end of this
year. I ask for prayers in support of those responsible for making
that choice.''
   Runcie has been credited with holding his church together during
controversy over the ordination of women bishops. About 1,200 women
priests have been ordained by U.S. Episcopalians and Anglicans in
Canada and New Zealand, but the Church of England still does not
permit the ordination of women.
   Runcie's personal envoy, Terry Waite, is among 18 westerners
held hostage in Lebanon. The longest-held is Terry Anderson, chief
Middle East correspondent of The Associated Press, kidnapped March
16, 1985. Waite was trying to negotiate the release of other
hostages when he disappeared in Beirut in January 1987.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0011 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 0551EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>b a BC-SocialClubFire 3rdLd-Writethru a0635 03-25 0179</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Social Club Fire, 3rd Ld - Writethru, a0635,0178</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: UPDATES with 87 dead, details</NOTE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A fire that swept through a packed social club
in the Bronx borough early Sunday killed at least 87 people, fire
officials said.
   The fire was reported at 3:41 a.m. in the one-story Happyland
Social Club in the East Tremont section near the Bronx zoo, fire
department spokesman Lee Rodriguez said.
   At least 100 people were caught in the 20-by-50 foot building
when the fire broke out, according to local radio reports. Many of
the deaths apparently were due to smoke inhalation.
   Assistant Fire Commissioner Robert Ungar said at least 87 bodies
were found inside the heavily damaged club.
   More than 30 firefighters were fighting the blaze and removing
survivors, Rodriguez said.
   An official of the Emergency Medical Services said some patients
were taken to hospitals in Manhattan and the Bronx.
   A neighbor, Lilian Rivera, said the club was frequented by
Dominican immigrants who live in the neighborhood. She said it was
a ``family club'' during the day.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0012 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 0720EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w WashingtonMaintenanceTesting.     03-25 0010</FIRST>
<SECOND>Washington Maintenance Testing.</SECOND>
<TEXT>
   End of Washington Maintenance Testing.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0013 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 0811EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a BC-WorstFires List   03-25 0194</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Worst Fires, List,0211</SECOND>
<HEAD>List of Worst Fires In Recent U.S. History</HEAD>
<HEAD>With BC-Social Club Fire</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Here is a list of some of the worst fires, in terms of lives
lost, in the United States and its possessions since 1950.
   Dec. 31, 1986, San Juan, Puerto Rico, hotel, 96 dead.
   Nov. 8, 1982, Biloxi, Miss., county jail, 29 dead.
   Jan. 9, 1981, Keansburg, N.J., boarding home, 30 dead.
   Dec. 4, 1980, Harrison, N.Y., hotel, 26 dead.
   Nov. 21, 1980, Las Vegas, Nev., hotel, 84 dead.
   June 26, 1977, Columbia, Tenn., jail, 42 dead.
   May 28, 1977, Southgate, Ky., nightclub, 164 dead.
   Oct. 24, 1976, New York (Bronx), social club, 25 dead.
   Dec. 20, 1970, Tuscon, Ariz., hotel, 28 dead.
   Jan. 9, 1970, Marietta, Ohio, nursing home, 27 dead.
   Nov. 23, 1963, Richville, Ohio, rest home, 63 dead.
   Nov. 18, 1963, Atlantic City, N.J., hotel, 25 dead.
   Dec. 1, 1958, Chicago, parochial school, 95 dead.
   Feb. 17, 1957, Warrenton, Mo., home for aged, 72 dead.
   April 16, 1953, Chicago, metalworking plant, 35 dead.
   March 29, 1953, Largo, Fla., nursing home, 35 dead.
   Jan. 7, 1950, Davenport, Iowa, hospital, 41 dead.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0014 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 0926EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a BC-SocialClubFire 7thLd-Writethru a0641 03-25 0781</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Social Club Fire, 7th Ld - Writethru, a0641,0802</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<HEAD>New York City Social Club Fire Kills At Least 87</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: UPDATES throughout with new quotes, injured man described as
'lone survivor,' adds background on previous fires, clarifies that
it was worst fire in continental U.S., since Puerto Rico, site of
1986 fire that killed 96, is U.S. territory. No pickup.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By VERENA DOBNIK</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A suspicious fire swept through a jam-packed,
illegal social club for Latin immigrants in the Bronx early Sunday,
killing at least 87 people, fire officials said.
   The fire, the worst in the continental United States in 13
years, was reported at the Happy Land Social Club near the Bronx
Zoo at 3:41 a.m. and quickly spread through the two-story brick
building. Authorities and witnesses said the panic-stricken victims
were trapped and only one man apparently managed to escape,
severely burned.
   ``This is the worst thing I have seen in my career. It hurt my
stomach. It was sickening,'' said Emergency Medical Services
specialist Christopher McCarthy.
   ``Most of the bodies were in dance clothes,'' he said. ``They
were out to have fun. ... I saw wall-to-wall bodies _ an indication
of mass confusion and panic.''
   The blaze was brought under control by 6 a.m., said a fire
department spokesman, Lee Rodriguez.
   Officials said the fire's rapid spread suggested an accelerant
was used. ``That heavy volume of fire immediately arouses
suspicion,'' said Assistant Fire Chief Robert Ungar.
   One witness heard what sounded like gunshots before the fire.
But Unger would not comment on reports that there was a fight
before the fire broke out or that gasoline cans were found at the
scene.
   EMS Lt. Roy David said he got to the scene just a man believed
to be the lone survivor, apparently the club's disc jockey, was
staggering out.
   ``He walked toward me,'' David said. ``He couldn't talk. He
couldn't say anything. All we could do was treat him.''
   Another witness, Victor Perry, said: ``There were no people
coming out. The DJ's clothes were stuck to his burnt skin which was
coming off.''
   The building received an eviction notice in January because of
improper exits, and was in the process of being condemned, said
Building Commissioner Charles Smith.
   ``The sad part of it is that this did not have to happen,'' said
Mayor David Dinkins, who visited the scene a few hours after the
fire. Many of an estimateed 700 similar clubs operating in New York
City may be unsafe, and are being investigated, he said.
   A fire at another Bronx social club killed 25 people on Oct. 24,
1976.
   Ungar put the death toll at 87 or 88 people. A makeshift morgue
was set up in the building next door, and relatives gathered at the
scene. Authorities said the victims were mostly Latin immigrants,
primarily Hondurans.
   Lynn Schulman, an EMS spokeswoman, said most of the victims died
from smoke inhalation, but added, ``Some people were trampled.''
   She said the survivor was a 25-year-old man who suffered
second-and third-degree burns on his arms and legs and was taken to
Jacobi Hospital in guarded condition.
   Five firefighters, including a battalion chief who broke his
leg, were taken to Jacobi Hospital after inhaling smoke and at
least six other firefighters were treated for minor smoke
inhalation at the scene, she said.
   Perry said three sounds like gunshots were heard just prior to
the fire in the building that housed the club, which was only 20
feet by 50 feet.
   Rosemary Green, whose sister-in-law and cousin were at the club,
said she and other people were coming from a neighborhood birthday
party and going to club when she encountered the scene.
   ``People were screaming. They were all burned. ... We're looking
for friends and relatives and nobody's telling us anything,'' she
said. ``Once you got in the entrance there was no way to get out.''
   The building housed a group that organized children's baseball
as well as adult socializing, said Lillian Rivera, a neighbor who
lives across the street from the club.
   At least 30 firefighters from six companies were called to the
scene, Rodriguez said.
   The fire was the deadliest in the continental United States
since a May 28, 1977, blaze that consumed the Beverly Hills Supper
Club in Southgate, Ky., killing 164 people. A Dec. 31, 1986, fire
at a hotel in San Juan, Puerto Rico, a U.S. commonwealth, killed 96
people.
   Sunday's fire occurred on the 79th anniversary of one of New
York City's worst fires, the Triangle Shirtwaist Co. blaze that
killed 145 people, most of them immigrant workers. The fire led to
reforms governing safety of the workplace.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0015 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 1123EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>d i AM-BRF--Philippines-Shooting     03-25 0143</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Philippines-Shooting,0147</SECOND>
<HEAD>Gunmen Ambush Buses, Three Children Die</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MANILA, Philippines (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Gunmen fired on two passenger buses
in the central Philippines, killing three children and wounding 18
people, a mayor said Sunday.
   Renato Reyes, mayor of Bongabon, told radio station DZMM that
the gunmen attacked the buses Saturday in the town located on the
eastern coast of Mindoro island, about 130 miles southeast of
Manila.
   Reyes said the gunmen might have been members of the New
People's Army, which has been waging a 21-year insurgency to
establish a Marxist state. He gave no reason for his suspicions.
   He said one of the wounded was a soldier and that government
forces were pursuing the gunmen.
   The reason for the attack was unclear, but rebels and other
armed groups have attacked buses in the past because their owners
refused to pay protection money.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0016 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 1123EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>d i AM-BRF--Philippines-Tourism     03-25 0159</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Philippines-Tourism,0163</SECOND>
<HEAD>Report: Ads Halted For Tourist Spot Known For Sex Offenses,
Harassment</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MANILA, Philippines (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The government will stop promoting
the country's third most popular tourist spot because of widespread
child prostitution and other problems there, a newspaper reported
Sunday.
   Ads for Pagsanjan Falls, where parts of the movie Apocalypse Now
was filmed, will be discontinued next month because of illicit
activity and harassment of tourists, the Manila Chronicle quoted
Tourism Undersecretary Rafael Alunan as saying.
   Alunan was quoted as saying officials tried to seek cooperation
from local business groups but failed.
   The scenic falls and gorge, about 30 miles east of Manila, have
drawn about 600 visitors daily since January, the newspaper said.
It described the falls area as the third major tourist destination
but did not name the other two.
   The area around the falls has become a center for child
prostitution, and tourists have complained about boatmen gouging
ferry prices, the newspaper said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0017 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 1123EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--Malaysia-Drugs     03-25 0168</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Malaysia-Drugs,0173</SECOND>
<HEAD>276 People Sentenced To Death For Drug Trafficking In 1980s</HEAD>
<DATELINE>KUALA LUMPUR, Malaysia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The government said Sunday that it
sentenced 276 people to death for drug trafficking during the 1980s
and arrested more than 100,000 people for the offense during that
period.
   Inspector-General Haniff Omar, in a speech quoted by the
national news agency Bernama, also said the government sentenced
240 to life in prison for the offense.
   He did not say how many people actually were executed, but last
month a 41-year-old Malaysian became the 82nd person to be hanged
after being convicted under a tough 15-year-old law against
marijuana, heroin and other drugs.
   Australians, Singaporeans, Filipinos, Thais, Indonesians and a
Briton were also among those put to death under the law, which
calls for the death penalty for anyone caught in possession of more
than half an ounce of heroin.
   During the 1980s, a total of 101,268 people were arrested for
various drug offenses, Haniff said. He gave no further details.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0018 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 1123EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>d i AM-BRF--Bangladesh-Storm     03-25 0143</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Bangladesh-Storm,0147</SECOND>
<HEAD>34 Killed, 800 Injured in Storm</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DHAKA, Bangladesh (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A storm that pounded most parts of the
country during the past two days left at least 34 people dead and
800 others injured, police and news reports said Sunday.
   Power lines snapped, 4,000 mud-and-straw houses were blown away
and thousands of acres of rice crops were uprooted in the storm
that started Friday night, the reports said.
   Most houses in Bangladesh, a country of 110 million people, have
mud walls and floors with roofs fashioned from thin mats of straw
or split bamboo.
   Rice is the main food for the impoverished people of Bangladesh,
one of the world's poorest with an annual per capita income of $160.
   Thousands of people are killed every year in Bangladesh in
frequent natural disasters that range from droughts to floods,
cyclones to hurricanes.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0019 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 1125EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-JailCensus     03-25 0469</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Jail Census,470</SECOND>
<NOTE>For Release 5 p.m. EST, time set by source.</NOTE>
<HEAD>Cells More Crowded Despite New Construction</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JAMES ROWLEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Local jails grew more crowded between 1983 and
1988 as new construction failed to keep pace with a 54 percent
increase in the number of prisoners, the Justice Departmnt said
Sunday.
   The size of housing space for each inmate shrunk 6 percent from
54.3 square feet in 1983 to 50.9 square feet in 1988 despite a 43.7
percent increase in total jail space, according to a study by the
department's Bureau of Justice Statistics.
   A census of the nation's 3,316 jails found that on June 30, 1988
there were 341,636 prisoners living in 17.4 million square feet.
Five years earlier, 223,272 inmates occupied 12.1 million square
feet of living space.
   The bureau's study found that 28 percent of the nation's jails
in 1988 housed more than 40 percent of their inmates in cells that
were smaller than the recommended standard of 60 square feet.
   In 1983, only 23 percent of the jails housed inmates in cells
that were smaller than the standard recommended by the American
Correctional Association.
   The proportion of jails placing five or more people in a
``housing unit'' increased from 24 percent in 1983 to 28 percent in
1988, the study said, and the average occupancy rose from 2.4
inmates per unit to 2.5 inmates.
   In 1988, 61 percent of all jail inmates lived in the most
crowded facilities.
   Local jails hired an additional 29,000 guards _ a 65 percent
increase _ during this period, reducing the ratio of inmates per
guard from 5.0 in 1983 to 4.6 in 1988.
   Jails in New Jersey were the most cramped _ averaging 39.6
square feet per inmate. The most spacious jails were in North
Dakota, where the average inmate had 88.8 square feet of living
space.
   Eight other states had jails with cells that were smaller than
the national average of 50.9 square feet. They were: Virginia,
40.4; Tennessee, 42.3; California, 43.0; Louisiana, 43.1; Georgia,
43.9; Texas, 44.0; Massachusetts, 49.0, and South Carolina, 49.6.
   Besides North Dakota, the largest living spaces for inmates were
in Montana, 76.7 square feet per inmate; Wyoming, 76.1; Iowa, 75.6;
Nevada, 70.5; Idaho, 69.9; Minnesota, 66.8, and Maine, 65.5.
   The rest of the states surveyed had jails with an average cell
size exceeding 50.9 square feet per inmate.
   The study included all locally run facilities for holding
defendants after arraignment in 44 states and the District of
Columbia. Temporary holding cells and lockups were not included in
the study.
   Connecticut, Delaware, Hawaii, Rhode Island, and Vermont were
not included in the study because they have combined jail-prison
systems. Alaska's prison-jail system was also not included, but
five separate local jails in the state were included.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0020 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 1128EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SriLanka Bjt   03-25 0899</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Sri Lanka, Bjt,0926</SECOND>
<HEAD>India's Departure Offers New Chance for Peace _ or More War</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RAJU GOPALAKRISHNAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>COLOMBO, Sri Lanka (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A 42-year-old rift between Sri Lanka's
Sinhalese majority and Tamil minority begins a new and possibly
less hostile chapter this week with the end of India's
pendulum-like intervention in the conflict.
   The last Indian soldiers left Sri Lanka's northeastern shores
Saturday, ending a 2{-year jungle war against the Tamil guerrillas
they once trained.
   Now the Sinhalese-dominated government and Tamils seeking an
independent nation are reassessing their traditional antagonism.
Both sides want to build on the tenuous peace they forged last
summer, a peace that grew out of mutual opposition to the Indian
presence.
   But the durability of their new-found understanding is being
questioned.
   ``I am afraid the peace will break down once the convergence of
their aims ends,'' a Western diplomat said on condition of
anonymity. ``And the convergence ends when the last Indian soldier
steps on a ship for home.''
   The Tamil-Sinhalese discord, simmering since Sri Lanka became
independent from Britain in 1948, spawned a Tamil insurgency in
1983. It also fueled an uprising against the government in 1987 by
ultranationalist Sinhalese who objected to peace overtures made to
the Tamils.
   The twin wars have killed at least 17,000 people and brought
this tropical island, once famed as a sun-and-sand holiday
destination, to the brink of anarchy.
   In the Tamil-dominated north and east, the Liberation Tigers of
Tamil Eelam and other Tamil groups launched a guerrilla war, first
against the Sri Lankan army and then against the Indian
peacekeepers.
   Sinhalese radicals and government forces were locked in a grisly
battle in the south and center of the island. Every morning they
left bodies of victims in remote villages and along the coastal
highway.
   The Sinhalese uprising came to a virtual halt in December after
most radical leaders were killed by Sri Lankan security forces.
   On the Tamil front, the militants and the government reached a
rare understanding: Both wanted Indian forces off the island.
   ``We are both against foreign occupation armies,'' Ajit
Mahataya, the Tigers' second-in-command, told The Island, a Colombo
newspaper. ``This may have helped build up trust that has allowed
us to negotiate seriously.''
   India, encouraged by its own Tamil minority, became involved in
the Tamil war for an independent nation soon after it began in
1983. Most Tamil rebel groups, including the Tigers, were based in
the southern Indian city of Madras and were trained in military
camps in India.
   When the Sri Lankan army stepped up repression against the
Tamils in 1987, India tried to pressure Colombo into calling a
cease-fire.
   The pressure tactics worked _ but with a twist. The Sri Lankan
government agreed to give the Tamils limited autonomy but said
Indian soldiers must enforce a surrender of arms by the guerrillas.
   India, acting on behalf of the Tamils, signed a peace pact with
Sri Lanka on July 29, 1987. Two months later the Tigers repudiated
the agreement, claiming they were not consulted, and turned their
guns on the Indians.
   Soon, India was fighting a full-scale war, at one point pitching
as many as 125,000 soldiers against an estimated 2,000 Tiger
guerrillas and countless part-time fighters.
   At least 1,155 Indian soldiers and about 2,000 Tigers were
killed in battle.
   Last summer, Sri Lanka demanded the Indians leave. The new
government, headed by President Ranasinghe Premadasa, said it could
handle the Tamil insurrection.
   After initial hesitation, India agreed to go.
   ``We are leaving with at least part of our job done,'' an Indian
diplomat said on condition of anonymity. ``We may not have got an
A-plus, but we did not get a C-minus either. We are leaving Sri
Lanka a united nation, and that is a tremendous achievement
considering the situation in 1987.''
   Some analysts believe the Sinhalese-Tamil unity will last.
   ``The government of Sri Lanka does not want to go back to square
one,'' said Neelan Tiruchelvam, a Tamil political analyst.
``Another confrontation will destroy the nation state.''
   At the root of the problem is the Tigers' demand for
independence, which they have not renounced despite the truce with
Colombo.
   Talks center on what kind of power the Tigers will exercise.
Government officials say Tamil areas will form a loose federal
state with considerable local autonomy.
   ``The answer is somewhere between a totally independent state
and the kind of provincial power we have now,'' said Bradman
Weerakoon, President Premadasa's top adviser.
   ``I see a superb chance for coming to terms,'' Weerakoon, a
Sinhalese, said. ``Previous governments had not completely realized
that there were some areas that could be perceived as being
discriminatory to the Tamils. This president realizes that Tamil
demands have some kind of basis.''
   Tamils claim discrimination by the Sinhalese, who form 75
percent of the country's 16 million people and control the
government, military and most employment opportunities. Sinhalese
say the Tamils, who comprise 18 percent of the population, hold
jobs and wealth disproportionate to their numbers.
   Premadasa's efforts to ease ethnic tensions have struck a chord
among the Tigers, but they say they are prepared to return to the
jungle.
   ``We are giving him all the opportunities we can,'' Stanley
Dominic, a senior guerrilla, said from the northern Tiger-held town
of Jaffna. ``If he doesn't use them properly and as a result there
is another war, we are prepared for it.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0021 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 1135EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-PolPotBrother Bjt   03-25 0950</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Pol Pot Brother, Bjt,0976</SECOND>
<HEAD>Brother of Pol Pot Cannot Fathom Evil of Communist Revolutiontary</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DENIS D. GRAY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PHNOM PENH, Cambodia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Saloth Suong devoted his life to
Cambodian Buddhism and royal tradition. His brother tried to
eradicate both, and stands accused of slaughtering 3.3 million
compatriots.
   Saloth Suong's brother is Saloth Sar, alias Pol Pot, whose
primitive Communist revolution ranks in savagery with Adolf
Hitler's holocaust and the mass purges of Soviet dictator Josef
Stalin.
   Saloth Suong, 78, says he is unsure what drove his younger
brother to impose the reign of terror whose victims included
members of their own family.
   He does not want to see his brother again, either for a personal
reunion or as head of the Khmer Rouge guerrillas Pol Pot is said to
still lead.
   ``But I am not afraid if they come. I am too old already for
fear,'' he said. ``I pray often at the pagoda.''
   His 71-year-old wife, Chea Samy, is less fatalistic. The most
prominent mistress of Cambodian classical dance, she works to
preserve the art as a teacher at the Fine Arts University.
   In one of the many tragic ironies of the couple's lives, it was
Pol Pot who tried to stamp out the exquisite dance along with
other, centuries-old cultural legacies.
   ``If they came back they would destroy it again, so I must teach
and document as much as possible,'' she said, sitting beside her
husband in their spartan rooms in a decrepit apartment block.
   Saloth Suong bears a striking resemblance to his infamous
brother. He has the same stocky build, fleshy cheeks and high
forehead, and he says the two were close as boys and young men.
   ``Saloth Sar was a very polite, gentle boy. He respected the old
people and they liked him,'' his brother said. ``I have no idea why
he became so evil. I keep wondering about that. Maybe it was the
things he studied and the friends who influenced him.''
   Pol Pot's father is said to have been a land-owning farmer of
good standing. A cousin who married into the royal family took some
of the nine children, including Pol Pot and Saloth Suong, to Phnom
Penh for studies.
   Through the cousin, Pol Pot is distantly related to Prince
Norodom Sihanouk, the former Cambodian leader imprisoned by Pol Pot
and now chief of the uneasy guerrilla alliance fighting Phnom
Penh's Vietnamese-backed government. The U.S.-backed resistance
includes the Khmer Rouge.
   Saloth Suong says Pol Pot lived with him for years. Chea Samy
bought him food, washed his clothes and helped him with life in the
capital. The cousin connected to the Cambodian royalty proved a
``second mother.''
   With a scholarship in hand, Pol Pot left to study radio
electronics in Paris in 1949 but failed his exams. Much of his time
was reportedly spent talking leftist politics with fellow
Cambodians; some historians say the Khmer Rouge was born on Paris'
Left Bank.
   Saloth Suong says he saw his brother for the last time in the
early 1960s.
   Sihanouk's police were hunting for the fledgling revolutionary,
who fled to the jungle to help organize the ultra-radical movement
he would soon dominate. For years, Saloth Suong thought his brother
had been killed.
   Saloth Suong's own career was spent within the Royal Palace, as
an administrator, protocol official and personal assistant to
Sihanouk's mother, Queen Kossamak.
   Sihanouk was toppled in 1970 and the ensuing five-year war ended
with a Khmer Rouge victory. Saloth Suong, a brother and sister were
forced into agrarian communes, along with the entire population.
The brother died of hunger and illness and Pol Pot's ``second
mother'' starved to death.
   Saloth Suong and Chea Samy say they labored from 5 a.m. to 7
p.m. He cut logs for firewood, she washed 700 dishes daily in a
communal kitchen. Illness sapped their strength.
   In late 1978, while cleaning the communal kitchen, Saloth Sar
watched workers putting up a photograph of the shadowy Khmer Rouge
leader, who had discarded his real name for that of Pol Pot.
   ``At first I didn't recognize him. But some people noted the
resemblance and told me that Pol Pot was Saloth Sar,'' he said,
recalling his feeling of anger.
   ``People asked me: `Why don't you go to Pol Pot. He is a big
man.' But I told them he was not really a brother to me, so I could
not come to him.''
   Vietnamese forces overthrew the Khmer Rouge in late 1978. The
government has said the regime killed 3.3 million people in
executions, famine and civil unrest. Other estimates are lower but
still astounding given Cambodia's 1975 population of about 8
million.
   After the new government was installed in early 1979, Saloth
Suong and his wife returned to Phnom Penh and his brother fled back
to the jungle. Despite his announced retirement in 1985, Pol Pot is
believed to still lead the Khmer Rouge.
   Vietnam said it withdrew all its troops from Cambodia last year,
leaving the government led by Prime Minister Hun Sen to fight the
resistance.
   Saloth Suong lives quietly and works part-time as a keeper of
artistic property at the Ministry of Culture. Late last year he
returned to his native village for a reunion with three surviving
siblings. There was a Buddhist ceremony of gratitude and
remembrance of dead family members.
   The village temple, traditional center of rural life, had been
turned into a hospital by the Khmer Rouge, its images smashed, its
monks derobed. Asked if they were shunned because of their brother,
Saloth Suong laughed gently.
   ``Not at all,'' he said. ``The villagers welcomed us with warmth
because they knew we too had suffered under Pol Pot.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0022 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 1152EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-DeformedPerformer     03-25 0952</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Deformed Performer,0979</SECOND>
<HEAD>Deformed Woman Who Fought For Child Custody Now Battling For
Boardwalk Space</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By HENRY STERN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ATLANTIC CITY, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A legless, armless woman who won
custody of her daughter 14 years ago by changing the baby's diaper
with her teeth now plays ``We Shall Overcome'' and ``Over The
Rainbow'' on this city's Boardwalk by pressing her tongue against a
keyboard.
   However, her music strikes the wrong chord with municipal
prosecutor Steve Smoger, who said Celestine Tate is a ``con
artist'' taking advantage of a special permit given her by the city
by not living up to an agreement to pay a fine in exchange for
being allowed to perform.
   Ms. Tate, a 34-year-old mother of two who lives in Ventnor, said
during a break from a recent performance in front of Bally's Park
Place Casino Hotel that she just wants to play her music.
   ``It's a nice way to occupy my time rather than just sitting
around doing nothing,'' Ms. Tate said in a singsong voice.
   She frequently asks God to bless passers-by who drop quarters
and dollar bills into the bucket in front of her hospital gurney.
   Smoger estimates Ms. Tate earns from $120,000 to $140,000 a
year. Ms. Tate puts the figure at more like $70,000 to $80,000.
   She said her two daughters _ ages 11 and 14 _ attend private
school in Philadelphia, and that she has to pay her $750-a-month
rent plus the expenses of a woman who comes in to help her at a
weekly cost of $158.
   In 1976, Ms. Tate had to prove to a Philadelphia judge that she
could care for the first of those girls after the welfare
department said she lacked the ability to raise the child.
   ``I changed her diaper in court and the judge gave her back to
me,'' Ms. Tate said, adding the child's paternal grandmother forced
her to break up with the girl's father because she was disabled.
``It was the Lord's will that I give birth to her so it must be his
will that I have her.''
   Ms. Tate was born in Philadelphia suffering from birth defects
that left her legs and arms undeveloped. During the interview, she
had to ask her cousin to pull a blue blanket over her when the wind
blew off the Atlantic Ocean onto the Boardwalk.
   ``God gave me ways to use my mouth that people with hands
can't,'' she said. ``I wouldn't trade me with anybody.''
   Ms. Tate reaches the Boardwalk spot with the help of a cousin,
who pushes her gurney two miles from Ventnor. She said she likes to
pass the Boardwalk's rolling chairs en route.
   ``I'll be saying, `Beep, beep,' when I pass them,'' said Ms.
Tate, who laughs and smiles easily, raising her eyes from her
keyboard to see whomever she is talking with.
   She learned her craft in Philadelphia at a music school for the
disabled and came five years ago to Atlantic City, a tourist
destination she remembered as a child and wanted to return to as an
adult.
   Tourists and residents alike seem to gravitate toward her,
filling her bucket as if it it were a wishing well with requests
guaranteed.
   ``I think it's beautiful,'' said Millie Vixson after she floated
a $1 bill into the bucket. ``I admire the idea.''
   Ms. Tate, who is about 4 feet tall and weighs about 170 pounds,
has had to battle repeatedly to preserve a spot on the Boardwalk
and make a living, and her battles may not be over.
   In March 1989, the city gave Ms. Tate a special permit that
exempted her from the city's 80-year-old ordinance barring
Boardwalk panhandling. As part of the agreement, Municipal Judge
Bruce Weekes said she had to pay a $2,600 fine over the next year
for 26 violations. That followed a similar agreement reached in
November 1986 between her and city officials.
   Smoger said she has reneged on her latest agreement. Ms. Tate
freely acknowleges she hasn't paid the fines, arguing that since
that she's not a beggar she shouldn't have to pay them.
   She said she is not worried about possible further legal action
against her.
   ``You're going to lock me up and feed me in jail or I'm going to
eat on my own,'' Ms. Tate said.
   Smoger said he sympathizes with Ms. Tate's disability but grows
tired of sparring with her over her failure to pay the outstanding
fines.
   ``She has done a remarkable job and should be commended for
elevating herself to the position she has,'' Smoger said. ``She's a
con artist. Every benefit that could be bestowed on to her has been
bestowed by the city of Atlantic City.''
   He said he will seek revocation of her license if she does not
pay the full $2,600 when her license comes up for its yearly
renewal in June.
   Smoger defended the anti-begging ordinance as necessary to
prevent the Boardwalk from being swamped with people asking for
money. Ms. Tate said she's an entertainer, not a beggar or a public
nuisance.
   ``I could not be begging with my mouth full,'' she said.
   Her latest court battle involves something different than her
freedom to make a living. She is scheduled for a hearing in Egg
Harbor Township municipal court Friday on marijuana possession
charges. Ms. Tate said she is innocent.
   Howard Mitchell, Ms. Tate's cousin and the most recent relative
to push her gurney down the Boardwalk and watch over her, said he
has faith in the woman he calls ``Teeny.''
   ``I get up and run away from life when I get scared,'' Mitchell
said. ``She keeps my spirit very high. Sometimes I'll just say
`Teeny, thank you.'''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0023 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 1158EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-VABenefits 1stLd-Writethru a0655 03-25 0806</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-VA Benefits, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0655,740</SECOND>
<HEAD>VA Benefits Review Sends Veterans' Groups to the Battlements</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: SUBS 11th graf pvs, bgng: The report, to DELETE extraneous
material</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT GREENE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Disclosure that the Veterans Affairs
Department is reviewing its $12 billion benefits program has caused
more scrambling than a battle alert among veterans advocates.
   The ``enemy'' _ real or imagined _ won't be known until the VA
issues its proposals in the next six weeks. Still, veterans groups
are upset because VA began the review without telling them and
didn't announce it until the Disabled American Veterans obtained
internal VA documents and revealed their existence at a
congressional hearing Feb. 27.
   The American Legion says the disclosure has set back relations
with veterans service organizations that had begun to improve with
the elevation last year of the VA to cabinet level and the
appointment of a new VA chief.
   ``It angers me that the department ... is looking for ways to
eliminate certain benefits, particularly when these deliberations
have been carried out without the knowledge of those who serve as
consumer advocates for veterans,'' Legion Commander Miles S. Epling
said in a letter March 8 to VA Secretary Edward J. Derwinski.
   VA says it is only trying to make the system more fair, that
savings would be plowed back into the financially strapped health
care system, and Congress would have to approve any modifications.
   Furthermore, VA says, there would be increases in benefits as
well as decreases, and any cuts would apply only to future veterans.
   ``I think they should wait until we put a package on the
table,'' said Deputy Secretary Anthony J. Principi, who is leading
the benefits review.
   But try telling that to organizations representing the nation's
27 million military veterans. Tinkering with Social Security could
be easier.
   The VA pays $12 billion a year to 2.2 million veterans, 310,000
widows or widowers, and 1 million dependents or spouses to
compensate for disabilities and death.
   The review follows a General Accounting Office study last July
that said VA paid $1.7 billion in 1986 to compensate for diseases
that arose during military service ``but were neither caused nor
aggravated'' by service.
   The report said Congress ``may wish to reconsider'' whether
eight diseases should be considered as service-connected and
eligible for compensation: arteriosclerotic heart disease,
diabetes, bronchitis and emphysema, arthritis, hemorrhoids,
multiple sclerosis, uterine fibroids and Crohn's Disease.
   Congress did nothing. ``It's not a sacred cow and we'll look at
it some day in the future,'' said Rep. G.V. ``Sonny'' Montgomery,
the Mississippi Democrat who chairs the House Veterans Affairs
Committee,
   The VA is considering the GAO recommendations, although Principi
says the internal review would have been undertaken regardless. VA
says cost-cutting recommendations are balanced by ones to make it
possible for a veteran to be declared 100 percent disabled after 10
years instead of 20 years; for mentally ill veterans to retain
benefits while trying to enter the job market; and by paying a flat
compensation rate for surviving spouses.
   Veterans organizations say they became suspicious of the VA
because of it did not challenge the GAO's conclusions more
forcefully.
   ``VA is not required to examine the nature of certain diseases
or to determine a causal connection to military service,''
Derwinski told GAO in a letter that was part of the report.
   F. David Parker, president of the Paralyzed Veterans of America,
said, ``We will never accept the argument that veterans who served
24 hours every day, always on call, while on active duty in every
corner of the world, should not be compensated for a disability
that was not the result of an actual military duty.''
   The veterans groups say VA is resurrecting proposals made by
groups more interested in slashing the budget than in helping
veterans.
   They say VA had been discussing such proposals as eliminating
cost-of-living payments for people with 10 percent to 20 percent
disability ratings, or even eliminating payments for people in
those lower disability ratings, and means testing for certain
payments.
   ``I think we blew their scenario,'' said John Heilman,
legislative director of the Disabled American Veterans. He said
that without DAV's intervention, VA would have acted behind the
scenes.
   Heilman's group and the PVA claim Principi is carrying out the
agenda of Sen. Alan K. Simpson, R-Wyo., former head of the Senate
Veterans Affairs Committee and a critic of the benefits system.
Principi formerly was a top aide to Simpson, who urged his Senate
colleagues in a letter March 7 ``to keep an open mind and not be
sucked in by the hysterical hype of these professional fundraising
veterans.''
   Principi says there was no secrecy involved. Many proposals were
rejected early in the process, he said, and the VA wanted to settle
on a group of proposals before releasing them.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0024 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 1207EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BreastX-Rays     03-25 0502</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Breast X-Rays,0515</SECOND>
<HEAD>Breast X-Ray Use Increases Sharply, Survey Says</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: For release at 6 p.m. EST.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By MALCOLM RITTER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DAYTONA BEACH, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The share of doctors who use breast
X-rays to look for cancer in symptom-free women has doubled to
nearly 100 percent in five years, marking a milestone in early
cancer detection, the president of the American Cancer Society said
Sunday.
   Ninety-six percent of physicians said last year they used
mammograms to screen symptom-free women at least some of the time,
compared with 49 percent in a 1984 survey, said Dr. Robert
Schweitzer.
   While that does not mean all women are receiving the mammograms
as often as the cancer society recommends, the trend is ``an
important milestone in the road toward that goal,'' Schweitzer said.
   The percentage of doctors who said they met or exceeded the
cancer society's recommended mammogram guidelines tripled, from 11
percent in 1984 to 37 percent in 1989.
   Schweitzer discussed the survey findings at a science writers
conference sponsored by the cancer society.
   Under the society's guidelines, a woman with no symptoms of
breast cancer should get a mammogram between ages 35 and 39, a test
that serves as a ``baseline'' for comparison in future tests. Women
40 to 49 should have a breast X-ray every one to two years,
depending on physical condition and previous mammogram results, and
those age 50 and over should have one every year.
   Mammograms and other cancer screening tests are aimed at finding
cancer in its early stages, when it is more curable.
   The physician survey was commissioned by the cancer society. It
covered 1,029 general and family practitioners, internists and
obstetricians and gynecologists.
   Results were weighted so that the percentages would reflect all
doctors in those specialties now practicing in the continental
United States. The margin of error was generally plus or minus 2
percent to 3 percent.
   Sixty-one percent of physicians said they were giving greater
emphasis to early breast cancer detection in symptom-free patients
than they had five years ago. In 1984, 39 percent had said they
were giving it increased emphasis.
   Forty-four percent said they were putting greater emphasis
specifically on mammograms last year, compared with 14 percent in
1984.
   The survey also found that the number of doctors who check for
blood in the stool, a potential sign of colorectal cancer, rose
from 75 percent in 1984 to 89 percent in 1989.
   Schweitzer said the only screening test not reported to be
widely used was proctosigmoidoscopy, in which a tube-shaped device
is used for inspecting the colon. Forty-nine percent of doctors
reported using that test last year, up from 35 percent in 1984.
   Only 23 percent of physicians said last year that they followed
or exceeded cancer society guidelines for the test, which the
society recommends every three to five years in symptom-free
persons age 50 and over.
   Forty-one percent of doctors said they use chest X-rays to
screen symptom-free patients, a practice the cancer society does
not recommend.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0025 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 1222EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Atwater     03-25 0141</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Atwater,140</SECOND>
<HEAD>GOP Chairman Released From Hospital</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Republican National Chairman Lee Atwater was
released from the hospital Sunday after physicians adjusted the
medication he is taking for a brain tumor, an aide said.
   Atwater, 39, underwent a radiation treatment Saturday at George
Washington University Hospital after being admitted on Friday,
complaining of queasiness, said Leslie Goodman, a spokeswoman for
the Republican National Committee.
   ``He's home and is in good spirits again,'' Ms. Goodman said
Sunday. ``He said he was feeling fine.''
   A small, non-malignant tumor was discovered earlier this month
on the ride side of Atwater's brain after he collapsed during a
speech and was rushed to the hospital. He is taking radiation
treatments five days a week to reduce the tumor.
   Atwater was named head of the RNC after managing George Bush's
presidential campaign in 1988.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0026 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 1244EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-AgentOrange     03-25 0697</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Agent Orange,670</SECOND>
<HEAD>Agent Orange Study Expected This Week</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT GREENE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Government scientists are expected to release
a study this week that will help determine officially whether
Vietnam veterans who were exposed to the herbicide Agent Orange
suffered cancers and other ailments as a result.
   The study by the federal Centers for Disease Control, which the
Veterans Affairs Department says will be released Thursday,
examines the incidence of five kinds of cancer among Vietnam vets.
It is another step in a 12-year battle to gain benefits for
veterans who blame cancers, skin disease and miscarriages in their
spouses on the powerful foliage killer.
   VA Secretary Edward J. Derwinski last November said he would put
off a determination on whether to award benefits until after the
study was completed. Following its release, the study must be
reviewed by a VA advisory committee of outside scientists.
   Derwinski will make a determination at the end of May after the
committee meets, VA spokesman Don Smith said last week. Final rules
should be in place in October. The decision also could influence
legislation in the House and Senate requiring compensation to
veterans.
   Derwinski said in a recent interview that the decision on Agent
Orange will be the most difficult he's made since becoming the
first VA secretary a year ago.
   ``The advice is so terribly conflicting,'' he said. ``There's no
consensus out there.''
   Nearly 35,000 claims have been filed citing Agent Orange as a
cause of disabilities. An additional 230,000 veterans have told VA
they were exposed to the herbicide, which contained highly toxic
dioxin and other suspected harmful ingredients.
   The new Selected Cancers Study by the CDC in Atlanta does not
look at whether veterans were exposed to Agent Orange, which was
sprayed to remove foliage and kill crops.
   According to the VA, the new study will determine whether
Vietnam veterans are at higher risk of developing soft-tissue
sarcoma, lymphoma and nasal, nasopharyngeal and liver cancer. The
study began in 1985.
   CDC spokesman Chuck Fallis said he could not confirm that the
study would be released Thursday, the day given by the VA and the
American Legion.
   VA says the study can be combined with other studies, mostly
dealing with the exposure of industrial and farm workers to dioxin,
to tilt the balance one way or the other regarding a possible
connection to disorders.
   The Legion, however, is telling veterans not to hold their
breaths.
   ``The government has ducked the issue of Agent Orange for more
than a dozen years,'' National Commander Miles S. Epling said. ``We
are tired of waiting for more studies, especially irrelevant ones.''
   The Legion contends the CDC scuttled an earlier attempt at a
study by saying no reliable sample of veterans can be found. The
Legion says CDC has ignored detailed military records of troop
movements and spraying activities that could produce such a study
group.
   A Legion study claims to have established a connection between
Agent Orange and skin rashes and blisters, fatty tissue tumors,
hypersensitivity of the eyes to light, and an increased risk of
miscarriages among spouses. The Legion says the study was too
limited to reach further conclusions regarding other cancers.
   VA says scientific advisers to Congress and the administration
have rejected the Legion study because it relied on questionnaires
filled out by the veterans themselves.
   The Agent Orange issue was revived last May when U.S. District
Judge Thelton E. Henderson said VA had used too rigid a standard _
cause and effect between exposure and disease _ in evaluating Agent
Orange studies.
   Derwinski decided not to appeal Henderson's order that the VA
need only find a ``significant statistical association'' between
exposure and disease before determining to award compensation.
   The VA's outside Environmental Hazards Advisory Committee met in
November to review about 30 studies dealing with herbicide exposure
and its relation to non-Hodgkins lymphoma using the new criteria.
   The group said it could neither find nor rule out a significant
statistical association, giving little guidance to Derwinski.
   Derwinski said afterward he would wait for the new CDC study. He
cited remarks by members of the committee that such a study would
be useful.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0027 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 1255EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Australia     03-25 0465</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Australia,0479</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hawke Confident Of Fourth Term, Peacock Concedes That Is Likely</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RICHARD BILL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SYDNEY, Australia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Prime Minister Bob Hawke's conservative
challenger said incomplete election returns Sunday indicated he was
likely to fail in his attempt to block Hawke from serving a record
fourth consecutive term.
   Hawke, who has governed for seven years, said he and his Labor
Party expected to stay in power with a one-vote majority in the
148-seat House of Representatives after Saturday's balloting.
   Andrew Peacock, the opposition leader of the Liberal and
National Party Coalition, acknowledged Labor probably had the
numbers in parliament.
   ``If you are setting a book I suggest the shortest odds would be
regrettably on a hung parliament, followed then by a Labor
government just ahead of a possibility of a Coalition government,''
Peacock told reporters in Melbourne.
   When counting was halted Saturday night, Labor appeared to have
won 73 seats, the coalition 70 and the Independents two. Labor,
which had 85 seats in the previous lower house, needs 75 seats for
a working majority.
   There was no further counting Sunday, and the earliest results
were expected Monday. The final outcome may not be known until
Thursday, when mail-in ballots are counted.
   Hawke, 60, told a news conference early Sunday that he will
continue in a caretaker capacity and that he expected to form a
government that would keep him in power for another three-year term.
   Hawke, clearly surprised by the close election, said that when
final results are in he expected a one-vote majority but added: ``I
hope it may be a bit better than that.''
   Australia's sagging economy had been the focus of a largely
uneventful five-week campaign during which Peacock told the
country's 10.6 million voters that Hawke's policies could lead to a
recession.
   Peacock criticized the government for record 18 percent mortgage
rates and a $100 billion foreign debt in this nation of 16.5
million.
   Peacock, who at 51 had made his second bid for the prime
ministership, said he would continue planning for the transition of
government because the outcome of six or seven seats in the states
of Western Australia and Queensland still had not been decided.
   Political pundits had said Peacock's political career hung in
the balance, with defeat likely to lead to him being dumped as
leader of the Liberal Party.
   He said his coalition could pick up several of the doubtful
seats, which includes the small town of Kennedy in northern
Queensland, where several thousand voters were unable to cast their
ballots because polling booths were cut off by floodwaters.
   Hawke came to power in 1983, was re-elected the following year
and again in 1987. He has said that if re-elected in this race, he
will seek a fifth term before retiring.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0028 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 1321EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Yugoslavia     03-25 0407</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Yugoslavia,0422</SECOND>
<HEAD>Extra Police Sent to Kosovo, Government Insists No Poison Found</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BELGRADE, Yugoslavia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Troops dispersed hundreds of
demonstrators in Kosovo province Sunday after the government
accused Albanian nationalists of causing a mysterious illness that
sickened hundreds of ethnic Albanian teen-agers.
   The republic of Serbia, which assumed direct control of police
in the southern province Saturday, sent 2,500 police reinforcements
to maintain law and order, Radio Belgrade reported.
   Sreten Lukic, chief of Serbia's police force in Kosovo,
announced a purge of ethnic Albanian policemen who allegedly did
nothing to protect Serbs from attacks last week, the Belgrade daily
Politika Ekspres reported.
   Police Sunday morning dispersed 2,000 members of Kosovo's ethnic
Albanian majority demonstrating near Titova Mitrovica, 24 miles
north of the provincial capital, Pristina.
   Ethnic Albanians also reportedly manned occasional roadblocks,
checking drivers' papers in the poor, rugged province bordering
Albania.
   At Urosevac, 18 miles south of Pristina, about 800 Serbs and
Montenegrins from Kosovo's Slav minority rallied to demand that
police confiscate weapons from all ethnic Albanians, Radio Belgrade
said.
   Nearly 1,000 schoolchildren, most of them members of Kosovo's
ethnic Albanian majority, were hospitalized last week, complaining
of lung and other complaints and alleging they were poisoned by a
mysterious gas.
   At least one Serb policeman and one Serb schoolgirl also
reportedly sought treatment in Titova Mitrovica, north of Pristina,
for the illness.
   A Yugoslav Health Ministry Friday dismissed claims of poisoning,
but ethnic Albanian leaders in Kosovo claimed their investigations
were biased.
   Late Saturday, the federal government announced that the
mystifying incident was ``an action of Albanian separatists''
intended to stir more unrest in Kosovo.
   ``Evidently, this involved a planned action by Albanian
extremist nationalists designed to ... spark further deepening of
nationalist skirmishes with possible tragic consequences,'' the
government said, according to the official news agency Tanjug.
   Military authorities say no trace of poison has been found among
the victims, and in the statement the government did not say what
it thought the illness was or how it was caused.
   More than 60 people have died in ethnic violence in the past
year in the province, which is administratively part of Serbia.
Ninety percent of its population are ethnic Albanians seeking to
regain autonomy lost last year when Serbia assumed direct control
of Kosovo's judiciary and schools.
   Serbia, the largest of Yugoslavia's six republics, argued this
was necessary to protect the Slav minority in Kosovo, the cradle of
Serbia's medieval kingdom.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0029 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 1325EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Mongolia     03-25 0459</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mongolia,0476</SECOND>
<HEAD>Pro-Democracy Groups Rally in Mongolian Capital</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Lithuania, Bjt</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto ULB1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KATHY WILHELM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ULAN BATOR, Mongolia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Thousands of pro-democracy
demonstrators gathered in the capital's central square Sunday to
demand democratic reforms, including an end to government funding
for the ruling Communist Party.
   Speakers also demanded the abolition of party cells in
ministries and schools. Some of the 7,000 people in the square
carried banners reading, ``Democracy is our gun,'' and ``National
Unity.''
   The speakers, who stood in a truck-bed rigged with loudspeakers,
said they invited Communist Party officials to make speeches, but
none accepted.
   The Communist Party, formally called the Mongolian People's
Revolutionary Party, receives about 20 million tugriks a year, or
$6.6 million at the official rate. New political parties that plan
to challenge the Communists in upcoming elections receive no
funding and lack money for offices and basic equipment.
   Demonstrations began in Mongolia in December as Communist
governments throughout the Soviet bloc began to give way to
democratic movements.
   Protesters in Mongolia have won a complete shake-up of top party
and government ranks, and promises of free elections. But the
opposition claims that in talks with the Communist Party authorites
have reneged on their promises.
   The opposition halted those talks last week, claiming that the
government representatives were changed each time talks were held
and lacked the authority to reach agreemenmts.
   ``We will go back if it will be televised live and ... have real
decision-making power,'' said I. Javkhlant, leader of the Mongolian
Democratic Association, one of the opposition groups.
   If not, he said his group will resort to more aggressive
tactics. He did not elaborate.
   It is unclear whether the government will legalize all of the
new opposition groups. A top legislative official indicated
Saturday that only socialist parties would be permitted.
   Mongolia has been a satellite of Moscow since Soviet troops
helped it win independence from China in 1921. But many Mongolians
resent the presence of about 60,000 Soviet soldiers and some 50,000
civilian experts and dependents.
   Moscow plans to withdraw its troops by 1992, and has called home
some of the civilians.
   At Sunday's rally the crowd gave some of its loudest cheers to a
journalist, Dogoodorg, who interviewed former dictator Yumjaagiyn
Tsedenbal in February for the first time since his 1984 ouster.
Like many Mongolians, Dogoodorg uses only one name.
   The interview, aired Saturday night on Mongolian television, saw
the now-feeble Tsedenbal defend decades of harsh rule.
   ``The authoritarian system has its positive side,'' Tsedenbal,
73, said from his Moscow home. He insisted party officials purged
in the 1960s were Chinese spies.
   His Soviet wife, Anastasia, tried repeatedly to stop the
interview, shouting at the reporter and stepping in front of the
camera.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0030 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 1327EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Andrus-Abortion Bjt   03-25 0830</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Andrus-Abortion, Bjt,0853</SECOND>
<HEAD>Idaho's Restrictive Abortion Bill Puts Governor At Center Stage</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BOB FICK</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOISE, Idaho (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Gov. Cecil Andrus, who once pushed for
jailing women and doctors who participated in abortions, now must
decide the fate of another bill that would ban almost all abortions
through civil rather than criminal sanctions.
   The decision puts the three-term Democrat at the center one of
the most divisive issues the country has seen since the Vietnam
War. Within the next three weeks, he will either approve or veto
the most restrictive state abortion law.
   Andrus refuses to discuss his intentions for the bill that would
ban more than 90 percent of the 1,500 abortions performed in Idaho
each year.
   The Idaho Legislature on Thursday gave final approval to a bill
to ban abortions as a means of birth control, allowing them only in
cases of non-statutory rape reported within seven days, incest if
the victim is younger than 18, severe fetal deformity or threat to
the mother's life or health. Women who violate the provisions would
not face sanctions, but the physicians involved could face fines up
to $10,000 for a first offense.
   On the night of the vote, at a party Andrus gave for Democratic
lawmakers, he made a few non-committal jokes about the decision
awaiting him. But his quip about just leaving town and letting the
Republican lieutenant governor handle the bill indicated his
wariness of the issue.
   In the days before that, however, Andrus vehemently reaffirmed
his longstanding opposition to abortion except in the case of rape,
incest and the life of the woman.
   ``Let there be no doubt in anyone's mind as to Cecil Andrus'
position on abortion,'' the governor said when he announced for
re-election just days before the Senate sent him the bill.
   ``I have always opposed legalized abortion,'' said Andrus, who
is Lutheran. ``My views haven't changed.''
   The bill headed to his desk is the one the National Right to
Life Committee wants to test the U.S. Supreme Court's commitment to
legalized abortion.
   It would seem to fit the criteria set by Andrus. Seventeen years
ago, in his first term as governor, he signed legislation in the
wake of the Roe vs. Wade decision that would _ if the Supreme Court
decision is ever overturned _ ban all abortions except to save the
woman's life and imprison the women and doctors involved.
   A leading opponent of the abortion restrictions, Democratic Sen.
Marti Calabretta, said the discussions he's had with Andrus in the
past ``haven't led me to believe he will do anything different.''
   Still, in making his decision, the governor is also juggling
economic and political considerations in the midst of his bid for
an unprecedented fourth term as chief executive.
   Party leaders hoping to attract pro-choice voters in the fall
have been pressuring him to veto the bill that 14 of the 19
Democratic senators and 13 of the 21 Democratic House members voted
against.
   ``It would be damaging for him,'' Sen. Karl Brooks said, citing
public opinion polls showing that while a majority of Idahoans
oppose abortion even more oppose government intervention in the
decision.
   ``He would be out of touch with the party he's in and the state
he governs,'' Brooks said. ``That's bad politics.''
   But at age 58 with 30 years of public service under his belt
both in Idaho and in the Cabinet under Jimmy Carter, Andrus is
anything but bad at politics.
   As Carter's interior secretary in 1980, he successfully guided
the Alaska Lands bill through a national debate to create America's
largest wilderness.
   Eighteen months ago, he stared down the federal government he
once served to end its use of his state as a temporary storage dump
for radioactive waste.
   A one-time logging and mill worker, Andrus served three terms in
the state Senate before making his first, and only unsuccessful,
race for governor in 1966.
   Andrus is a heavy favorite this year to become the state's first
four-term governor. His only announced Republican opponent in the
pro-choice camp is Boise stockbroker Milton Erhart, a political
novice. The likely GOP nominee _ state Sen. Rachel Gilbert of Boise
_ backed the anti-abortion bill.
   Andrus has reportedly been pressured by some of his major
contributors on the potential negative economic impact of the
restrictive abortion law that critics claim would drive doctors out
of a state already seriously short of rural medical care.
   There have also been threats by abortion rights supporters in
other states that if the bill is not vetoed they will boycott
Idaho's No. 1 commodity, potatoes.
   But the independent governor has bristled at threats in the
past, and the latest controversy does not seemed to have changed
that.
   On the eve of the abortion bill's final approval, he told one
supporter who was lobbying him for a veto, ``If you make this one
issue your determination of whether you support me after 30 years,
I don't want your support.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0031 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 1349EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Runcie     03-25 0673</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Runcie,0693</SECOND>
<HEAD>Anglican Leader Announces Retirement</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto LON1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LESLIE SHEPHERD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The archbishop of Canterbury, the Most Rev. Robert
Runcie, announced Sunday he will resign as leader of the world's 70
million Anglicans next Jan. 31.
   Runcie said his ``chief hope'' before retiring was to be
reunited with his envoy, Terry Waite, one of the 18 westerners held
hostage in Lebanon. Waite disappeared in Beirut three years ago
while trying to negotiate the release of other hostages.
   ``My thoughts are very much that we shall be united again,''
Runcie told reporters. ``That's what I pray for before I lay down
this office.''
   Runcie tendered his resignation a few weeks ago to Queen
Elizabeth II, the temporal head of the state Church of England,
said his spokeswoman, Eve Keatley.
   He delayed making a public announcement until Sunday's morning
service at Canterbury Cathedral in southeast England marking the
10th anniversary of his enthronement as the 102nd successor to St.
Augustine.
   The archbishop of Canterbury is spiritual leader of the Church
of England, and 26 other self-governing churches which make up the
Anglican Communion, including the 2.5 million-member U.S. Episcopal
Church.
   The Church of England requires its bishops to retire at age 70,
but Runcie's planned departure date falls eight months before his
70th birthday.
   In a statement Runcie said his early announcement is intended to
give Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher time to appoint his successor
later this year.
   ``I am resigning now because it is 10 years and I think it is
time to leave and hand over to somebody else,'' Runcie told
reporters.
   Mrs. Thatcher will select the new archbishop from a list of two
candidates drawn up by a committee of senior churchmen. She will
then make her recommendation to the queen who will make the formal
appointment.
   Speculation about possible successors has touched on most of
England's senior bishops as well as Archbishop Robin Eames, head of
the Anglican Church in Ireland. Mrs. Thatcher has consulted him in
the past about Northern Ireland.
   The Sunday Telegraph, a conservative weekly which has rebuked
the archbishop in the past, said Runcie would be difficult to
replace:
   ``There seems little prospect of finding anyone who would do
this impossible job any better; partly, it is because he is a
genuinely decent person, intelligent, witty and lacking in
pomposity; in a bureaucratic institution full of self-important and
ruthless men.''
   It is widely expected that Mrs. Thatcher will want to appoint
someone more in step with her conservative views.
   Runcie had frequently been at odds with Mrs. Thatcher's
government, preaching forgiveness for Argentina after the Falkland
Islands War in 1982 and offering moral support to striking miners
during their bitter yearlong strike.
   He urged that more be done for the homeless and for decaying
inner cities, and last year he said Britain was in danger of
becoming a nation of ``pharisees.'' Pharisees were members of an
ancient Jewish party who were denounced by Jesus Christ for
self-righteousness and hypocrisy.
   Runcie has been credited with holding his church together during
a time of falling attendance and a divisive debate over the
ordination of women bishops. Women priests have been ordained by
U.S. Episcopalians and Anglicans in Canada and New Zealand, but are
still not permitted by the Church of England.
   Runcie was born into a working class family which he described
as not particularly religious. He won a scholarship to study at
Oxford University and fought in World War II as a tank commander
where he was decorated for bravery.
   Church historians say he was the first primate to have fought
for his country since the Middle Ages. Runcie said it was the
horrors of the battlefield that inspired him to enter the
priesthood in 1951.
   Mrs. Keatley said Runcie and his wife, Rosalind, a concert
pianist, would retire to St. Albans, 19 miles northwest of London,
where they recently bought a home.
   Runcie told reporters he planned to spend his retirement
reading, watching cricket and spending time with his family.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0032 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 1352EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People SUB a0672 03-25 0219</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People, SUB, a0672,0224</SECOND>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS last item to CORRECT name to `Friz,' sted `Fritz.'</NOTE>
<DATELINE>KANSAS CITY, Mo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   At age 83, Friz Freleng, the man who
helped create a stable of Warner Bros. cartoon characters, could
have long ago said, ``That's all folks!'' and retired.
   But Freleng is still busy tickling America's funny bone.
   Freleng was honored by about 60 cartoon buffs Saturday at a
reception sponsored by the Kansas City Museum in conjunction with a
cartoon animation exhibit.
   Freleng, a Kansas City native, said his latest project is a
pilot television series starring one of his most popular
characters, the Pink Panther.
   He is on the Warner payroll as an adviser to the pilot, which he
said CBS hopes to launch this fall. The combination live action and
animated show revolves around a police officer and his feline
companion, the Pink Panther.
   Freleng directed 266 cartoons for Warner Bros. after being
recruited to Hollywood by his former Kansas City employer, Walt
Disney.
   Among his creations were Porky Pig, named after two chubby
childhood playmates; Yosemite Sam; Sylvester the Cat; Tweety Bird;
and Speedy Gonzales. He was among those who contributed to the
creation of Bugs Bunny and Daffy Duck.
   ``I enjoy all of them,'' Freleng said. ``I guess the most
popular one is Bugs Bunny.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0033 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 1456EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>d i AM-BRF--Tanzania-Socialism     03-25 0175</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Tanzania-Socialism,0180</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tanzanian Intellectuals, Party Leaders Back Socialism</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DAR ES SALAAM, Tanzania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Bucking the trend of multiparty
reform in other parts of the world, intellectuals and officials in
this socialist country ended a three-day conference Sunday by
agreeing to keep their one-party system.
   Intellectuals and party officials, however, acknowledged that
recent events in Eastern Europe and the Soviet Union carried a
message for their East African country.
   Rather than allowing a multiparty system, the participants
agreed, Tanzania should reform its single party to permit greater
participation and end corruption.
   Walter Bgoya, general manager of the Tanzania Publishing House,
said the experience of Eastern Europe showed only the death of
Stalinism, not of socialism.
   Stalinism, he said, was characterized by a cult of personality
and secrecy in government. He urged Tanzania's government to open
itself to public scrutiny.
   The symposium was called to explore the effects of changes in
Eastern Europe and the Soviet Union on Tanzania, which has had a
socialist one-party system of government since independence from
U.N. trusteeship in 1961.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0034 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 1407EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Lithuania-WorldReaction     03-25 0684</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lithuania-World Reaction,0705</SECOND>
<HEAD>Pope Urges Negotiated Settlement in Lithuania</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By STEPHEN R. WILSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>VATICAN CITY (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Pope John Paul II on Sunday appealed for
``sincere dialogue'' to find a just and peaceful solution to the
standoff over heavily Catholic Lithuania's declaration of
independence from the Soviet Union.
   In his first public comments on Lithuania since its March 11
independence declaration, the pope referred to the ``Lithuanian
nation'' and emphasized its centuries-old ties with the Vatican.
   However, John Paul stopped short of recognizing the independence
declaration. Observers said the pope is reluctant to jeopardize the
Vatican's newly forged diplomatic ties with Moscow.
   In Denmark, the government urged an international condemnation
of the Soviet Union for its attempts to cut off Lithuania from the
rest of the world, news reports said Sunday. The Soviet ambassador
in Copenhagen was called to the Foreign Ministry to receive an
official protest note, the reports said.
   In Washington, President Bush's national security adviser, Brent
Scowcroft, said Saturday that any Soviet use of force or
intimidation in Lithuania ``would be counterproductive'' to
U.S.-Soviet relations.
   Scowcroft said the Bush administration would take appropriate
measures in response to what it considered excessive Soviet
pressure or an increase in tensions in the Baltic republic.
   He did not elaborate but said military action was not a likely
option.
   Moscow has sent tanks rumbling through Lithuania's capital in
what legislators there regard as an attempt by the Red Army to
intimidate them so they will reconsider their declaration of
independence.
   The Soviet Foreign Ministry also ordered foreign diplomats,
including two Americans, out of Lithuania and said foreign
journalists would no longer be allowed to travel to the Baltic
republic.
   Lithuania, an independent country before World War II, is of
special interest to the pope because it is the Roman Catholic
stronghold in the Soviet Union. An estimated 2.5 million people, or
80 percent of Lithuania's population, are Roman Catholics.
   The Vatican has never recognized the Soviet annexation of
Lithuania, and there is a Lithuanian diplomatic mission accredited
to the Holy See.
   ``Today Lithuania finds itself at the center of interest of
Europe and the world,'' the pope said in his Sunday noon Angelus
from his balcony overlooking St. Peter's Square. ``Let us pray to
divine providence so that the Lithuanian question finds a just and
peaceful solution through sincere dialogue and in the framework of
the international order.''
   ``May God give light and strength to all all those upon whom
this resolution depends,'' he said, speaking in Italian.
   John Paul, who has often expressed the wish to visit his flock
in Lithuania, noted that he was twice refused permission to make
the trip: in 1984 for celebrations marking the 500th anniversary of
the death of Lithuania's patron saint, Casimir, and in 1986 for the
600th anniversary of the evangelization of the area.
   Monsignor Algimantas Bartkus, rector of the Pontifical
Lithuanian College in Rome, hailed the pope's remarks.
   ``This spiritual and moral solidarity and support gives us the
strength we need at this moment,'' he said in a telephone interview.
   Lithuania has posed a delicate situation for the Vatican, which
only 10 days ago established diplomatic ties with Moscow for the
first time since the 1917 Russian Revolution.
   Bartkus said he understands that the pope does not want to
offend the Kremlin by openly endorsing Lithuania's independence.
   ``We cannot ask for too much,'' he said. ``The Holy Father has
always shown very special attention to Lithuania, and we know he is
on our side.''
   The situation of the church in Lithuania has improved
substantially under Soviet President Mikhail S. Gorbachev. But
Lithuanian Cardinal Vincentas Sladkevicius recently told the
Catholic weekly Il Sabato that the church is ``not yet free'' and
that Lithuania should be independent.
   Gorbachev has invited the pope to visit the Soviet Union, but
the cardinal said he hopes John Paul will travel to Lithuania
separately, perhaps at the time of his trip to Poland in June 1991.
   ``Lithuania is ready for the Holy Father,'' Bartkus said. ``His
visit would probably be the biggest event of the century for
Lithuania.''
 
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0035 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 1416EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Lebanon     03-25 0547</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lebanon,0566</SECOND>
<HEAD>Artillery Duels in Christian Heartland Kill 2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RODEINA KENAAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BEIRUT, Lebanon (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Rival Christian forces fought with
howitzers, tank cannons and rocket launchers on mountaintops
northeast of Beirut on Sunday, and police said three people were
killed and five wounded.
   The artillery battle, and an earlier one on Saturday, threatened
a cease-fire agreement that brought months of fighting to ahalt on
March 3.
   Police said the latest battle began at daybreak and raged past
noon in the highlands of Kesrouan Province, pitting troops of
maverick Gen. Michel Aoun against the Lebanese Forces militia of
Christian warlord Samir Geagea.
   Both sides blamed each other for the fighting, which police
feared could lead to another all-out battle for control of
Lebanon's Christian enclave. The enclave includes 310 squares miles
north and northeast of Beirut.
   ``The truce is fraying. It will definitely collapse if the
accelerating tempo of violations is not arrested,'' a police
spokesman said.
   He said three civilians were killed and five people, including
two militiamen, wounded in the exchanges. That raised the overall
toll since Jan. 30, when Aoun moved against Geagea, to 768 dead and
2,129 injured.
   The fighting underlined the failure of neutral Christian
mediators to work out a political settlement to resolve the power
struggle. The March 3 cease-fire was negotiated by a three-man
Christian mediation committee.
   Shaker Abu Suleiman, spokesman for the committee, accused Aoun
and Geagea of ``issuing shooting orders while claiming a sincere
quest for peace.
   He said the committee, which is supported by the Vatican,
demanded that the fighting be stopped and negotiations resumed to
achieve a ``durable political settlement under no security pressure
by any side.''
   A Lebanese Forces communique said Aoun's gunners blasted its
positions in the summer resort towns of Rayfoun, Feytroun, Ajaltoun
and Ghosta with sustained barrages of tank cannons and 155mm
howitzers.
   Aoun's command said its forces opened up only after their
positions in pine-forested towns of Bekfaya and Ein Tuffaha came
under rocket fire from 40-tube launchers of the Lebanese Forces.
   Police said a pair of Israeli jet fighters, apparently sent to
film the fighting, streaked over the Kesrouan mountains in
supersonic runs. Sonic booms echoed through the capital.
   Israel's air force regularly patrols Lebanese air space, mainly
to monitor movements of Yasser Arafat's Palestinian guerrillas in
south Lebanon and Syrian troops stationed in and around Beirut.
   On Friday night and Saturday, Aoun's 19,000-strong army and
Geagea's 6,000-strong militia fought 16 hours of artillery battles
in Kesrouan that killed three people and wounded eight.
   Patriarch Nasrallah Sfeir, spiritual head of the dominant
Maronite Catholic sect to which both Aoun and Geagea belong,
appealed for an end to the fighting.
   ``The army and the Lebanese Forces must promptly withdraw back
to their barracks,'' Sfeir said in a Sunday sermon at the chapel of
his patriarchal seat in Bkirki on the Kesrouan coastline, 20 miles
north of Beirut.
   ``Have mercy on the people. Stop shooting. Halt this alarming
exodus of Christians,'' Sfeir said, referring to the flight of
hundreds of thousands of Christians from the enclave. ``Do not
finish off the Christians while pretending to defend their
interests.''
   Sfeir urged the remaining Christians to ``rebel in a public
uprising that will force your tormentors to end the war.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0036 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 1441EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Brazil     03-25 0862</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brazil,0892</SECOND>
<HEAD>Brazil's Economic Plan Creates Furor Over Civil Liberties</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KEN SILVERSTEIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>RIO DE JANEIRO, Brazil (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Brazil's new economic plan has led
to the arrest of about 30 businessmen and bankers for ``economic
crimes'' and a police raid on a company that publishes a book
describing tax shelters.
   Several of the arrested businessmen have been held in jail for
days, without being charged and without a bail hearing. Some have
been detained in cells containing people suspected of committing
violent crimes.
   The incidents, critics say, show that President Fernando Collor
de Mello's new economic measures have resulted in serious civil
liberties violations.
   ``We are heading for a dictatorship. The arrests are a flagrant
violation of rights consecrated in the constitution,'' legal
scholar Gofredo de Silva Telles said in a television interview.
   Marcio Tomaz Bastos, former president of the Brazilian Bar
Association, told The Associated Press: ``The new law is a
violence. If you kill someone you can respond to the charge at
liberty. But if you raise the price of a beer you can be jailed for
months without trial.''
   Collor announced his economic plan on March 16, one day after
taking office as Brazil's first popularly elected president in 29
years.
   He passed the package using ``provisional measures,'' which
became law immediately but can be voted down by Congress within 30
days.
   Brazil's Supreme Court is due to hear arguments on Wednesday
regarding the legality of the ``economic crime'' portion of the
plan.
   The measures, designed to bring down record inflation that
reached 2,700 percent in the past year, include a 30-day price
freeze, a new national currency, and a freeze on assets of more
than the equivalent of $1,200 from private savings accounts and
$600 from short-term money market deposits.
   The freeze withdrew an estimated $115 billion from circulation,
about 80 percent af all bank deposits.
   Also included was a controversial provisional measure that
subjects managers and owners of companies that commit ``crimes
against the popular economy'' to two-to-four-year jail terms. The
law does not provide suspects with the right to apply for bail
between the time they are arrested and tried.
   In the 10 days since the plan was passed, at least 30
businessmen and bankers have been arrested and charged with
violating the new law, according to newspaper and television
reports.
   Last week, Antonio Gaspar, manager of an Eldorado supermarket
was arrested in Sao Paulo, Brazil's biggest city, and charged with
economic abuses, the most serious being increasing the price of
some fish by 500 percent.
   On Friday, four members of the prominent Verissimo family, which
owns the Eldorado chain, were arrested in connection with the case.
Those charged were placed under house arrest and presumably will be
tried later.
   Several bank managers in major cities have also been arrested
and jeered by crowds as they were led away by police. The managers
were charged with denying clients the right to withdraw up to the
legal maximum from their bank accounts.
   Public opinion polls show the economic plan has overwhelming
public support. One survey, by the Brazilian Institute of Public
Opinion and Statistics, the nation's leading polling outfit, found
that 94 percent of the people supported jail time for economic
crimes. The company interviewed 2,250 people in Brazil's eight
largest cities. No margin of error was provided.
   Several of the arrested businessmen have been held in jail for
days, some in cells containing people charged with violent crimes.
Others accused of committing economic crimes have been freed on
their own recognizance.
   Police raided the Tama publishing house in Rio on March 19,
seized copies of the book ``Tax Havens,'' which describes various
tax shelters, and charged two of the company's officials with
``inciting tax evasion.''
   Brazil's 1988 constitution prohibits all censorship.
   Four days later, the offices of Folha da Manha, which publishes
the prominent Folha de Sao Paulo newspaper, were raided by heavily
armed federal police agents who arrested two company officers for
allegedly post-dating an invoice to avoid the currency freeze.
   The newspaper has been critical of Collor, publishing a number
of reports during last year's presidential campaign that accused
him of corruption during his 1987 to mid-1989 term as governor of
the northeastern state of Alagoas.
   The paper's owner believes the police action was no coincidence.
   ``Not even during the dictatorship were we victims of violence
like that,'' Folha de Sao Paulo's owner, Octavio Frias, told the
newsweekly Veja, referring to Brazil's 1964 to 1985 right-wing
military regime.
   Rep. Renan Calheiros, congressional leader of Collor's National
Reconstructuion Party, also criticized the raid on Folha de Sao
Paulo. However, he denied it was an attempt to silence the
newspaper.
   He defended the law against economic crimes and the need for
``coercive measures so people don't undermine the economic plan.''
   But others see the raid on the newspaper as part of an ominous
trend that is a natural consequence of the government's law against
economic crimes.
   ``As with the previous case of the Tama officials, I foresee the
federal police, with its new powers, being transformed into an
organ of repression,'' said Barbosa Lima Sobrinho, head of the
Brazilian Press Association.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0037 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 1443EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Scotus-Guard 1stLd-Writethru a0668 03-25 0724</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Scotus-Guard, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0668,670</SECOND>
<HEAD>Minnesota Gets Little Support in Asserting Control Over Guard</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: SUBS 2nd graf pvs, bgng: The justices, to include that
Perpich is governor; and SUBS 5th graf pvs, bgng: It was, to DELETE
extraneous word `policy'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By PHILIP BRASHER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Only six other states are supporting
Minnesota's contention before the Supreme Court that control of
National Guard training missions is a states' rights issue.
   The justices are scheduled to hear oral arguments Tuesday on a
suit by Minnesota Gov. Rudy Perpich challenging the
constitutionality of a 1986 law enacted in reaction to opposition
from some Democratic governors to former President Ronald Reagan's
Central American policies.
   Perpich contends the Montgomery Amendment named after Rep. G.V.
``Sonny'' Montgomery, D-Miss., violates the militia clause of the
Constitution because it denies governors authority to control the
peacetime training of National Guard units.
   The amendment specifically bars governors from withholding
consent to a National Guard unit serving on active duty outside the
country because they don't like the location, purpose or schedule
of the mission.
   It was enacted after several governors said they opposed the
Reagan administration's policies in Central America and did not
want National Guard units from their states assigned to train in
the region.
   Officials from 29 states, including 19 governors, have filed
briefs with the court supporting the Montgomery law. The Supreme
Court last year rejected hearing a similar challenge to it by
Massachusetts officials.
   Perpich, a Democrat, has not viewed the question as a foreign
policy matter but as one of states' rights.
   ``The Montgomery Amendment is an unnecessary federal power grab
that violates an unambiguous command in the text of the United
States Constitution,'' Minnesota officials said in their brief to
the court.
   ``The plain meaning of the militia training clause cannot be
more evident. The authority of training the National Guard is
reserved to the states.''
   Massachusetts and five other states _ Iowa, Maine, Montana, Ohio
and Vermont _ have filed a brief supporting Minnesota's contention.
   Represented by their attorneys general, the states wrote the
Supreme Court that the founding fathers intended for states to
control the militia to prevent abuses by the federal government.
   ``There is no doubt that state control over the militia was an
integral part of the framers' planned structure as a means of
securing the blessings of liberty won in the war of independence,''
according to those states.
   However, the governors of 19 states and attorneys general for 10
more states contend in their own brief filed with the Supreme Court
that Perpich ``is seeking to arrogate to himself a role in foreign
affairs.''
   The 8th U.S. Circuit Court of Appeals ruled in June that the
Montgomery Amendment is constitutional, saying that the state's
power to organize militias ``cannot constrain Congress' authority
to train the guard as it sees fit.''
   In Minnesota's view, Justice Department lawyers contend,
Congress could require National Guard units to fight overseas
without the authority to train them properly.
   American forces have fought in tropical climates nothing like
Minnesota's nearly every time they've been sent into battle over
the past 20 years, Rep. Bill Frenzel, R-Minn., and 23 other members
of Congress said in a brief supporting the administration's
position.
   ``No longer are the militia, if mobilized, likely to fight in
their own states defending their own territory,'' the lawmakers
said.
   The National Guard has been under dual state and federal control
since Congress made it a component of the Army in 1933. Enlistees
enroll simultaneously in the state militia and a reserve unit of
the U.S. armed forces.
   The Army National Guard now provides 46 percent of the Army's
combat units and 28 percent of its support forces. And the Air
National Guard now represents 73 percent of the nation's
interceptor forces, 25 percent of its tactical fighters and 24
percent of its tactical air support.
   States whose governors signed the brief in opposition to
Perpich's suit are Delaware, Florida, Georgia, Idaho, Illinois,
Iowa, Kansas, Louisiana, Maryland, Mississippi, Nevada, New Mexico,
North Carolina, North Dakota, Oklahoma, South Carolina, Texas, West
Virginia and Wisconsin.
   The 23 states whose attorneys general signed the brief are
Alabama, Alaska, Delaware, Florida, Georgia, Idaho, Indiana,
Kansas, Louisiana, Maryland, Mississippi, Missouri, Nevada, New
Mexico, North Carolina, Oklahoma, South Carolina, South Dakota,
Tennessee, Utah, Virginia, Wisconsin and Wyoming.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0038 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 1444EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Nixon-Watergate     03-25 0594</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Nixon-Watergate,580</SECOND>
<HEAD>CIA Ingored His Request on Watergate, Nixon Writes</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Former President Richard M. Nixon says in a new
book that he made the ``inexcusable error'' of asking the CIA to
block an FBI probe of the Watergate break-in but that the CIA
declined.
   Nixon said a decision by then CIA Director Richard Helms and his
deputy, Vernon Walters, to ignore the request discredits
Watergate's ``most serious myth _ the one that ultimately forced me
to resign:'' that the CIA in fact obstructed the FBI probe on his
specific orders.
   In addition, Nixon writes in ``In the Arena,'' his new book
excerpted in the latest issue of Time magazine, he later
``emphatically'' told FBI Director Patrick Gray to go forward with
the investigation.
   Nixon said he made the request to the CIA on the recommendations
of staff members who ``had a personal stake in covering up the
facts.''
   Nonetheless, in an interview with the magazine accompanying the
book excerpts, Nixon said he expects historians to judge him more
by Watergate than by his diplomatic overtures to China.
   ``Historians are more likely to lead with `He resigned the
office,''' Nixon said in the interview. ``The jury has already come
in, and there's nothing that's going to change it. There's no
appeal. Historians will judge it harshly.''
   In the book, Nixon writes that ``the most widely believed myth
was that I ordered massive illegal wiretapping and surveillance of
political opponents, members of the House and Senate, and news
media reporters. All of these charges are false.''
   Another misconception, he writes, was that he ordered the
break-in at the Democratic National Committee. ``Not one piece of
evidence was discovered indicating that I ordered the break-in,
knew about the plans for the wiretapping ore received any
information from it,'' he writes.
   Nixon also denies paying for any cover-up.
   ``It is clear that I considered paying the money,'' he says,
referring to the famous taped conversation he had on March 21, 1973
with White House counsel John Dean. But Nixon adds that he later
ruled out payments.
   Nixon, however, does not directly address in the Watergate
section of the book a key aspect of the ``smoking gun'' tape in
which he and White House Chief of Staff H. R. Haldeman discussed
the FBI investigation.
   That tape, recorded June 23, 1972, six days after the Watergate
break-in, contradicted Nixon's previous statements that he did not
know of White House involvement in the Watergate coverup until the
March 1973 conversation with Dean.
   ``Here was the `smoking pistol' the investigators had been
looking for _ the direct, undeniable evidence that from the very
beginning Nixon had been in on, had approved, had condoned and
supported the attempt to bury the Watergate mess,'' U.S. District
Judge John J. Sirica later wrote in his memoirs.
   Attempting to debunk what he calls ``the myths of Watergate,''
Nixon writes that ``others in my campaign and in my Administration
attempted to cover up'' the connection between the burglary and his
re-election campaign.
   ``I failed to take matters firmly into my own hands and discover
the facts and to fire any and all people involved or implicated in
the break-in,'' he says.
   On a more personal note, the ex-president says that following
his near-fatal attack of phlebitis shortly after his resignation in
August 1974, ``I could see no reason to live, no cause to fight
for.''
   But he recovered physically, spiritually and mentally, he says,
because of strong support from his family and a circle of devoted
friends and through writing his memoirs.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0039 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 1447EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SovietJews     03-25 0456</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet Jews,0473</SECOND>
<HEAD>Foreign Minister Criticizes End of Flights For Soviet Jews</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BUDAPEST, Hungary (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hungary's Foreign Minister Sunday
criticized the state airline for suspending flights of Soviet Jews
to Israel after it received terrorist threats from pro-Iranian
extremists.
   The state airline Malev suspended flights Wednesday and appealed
to the Soviet airline Aeroflot to stop bringing Jewish emigres to
Hungary. The Soviets announced Friday they would comply.
   Both suspensions followed threats by the Lebanese-based Islamic
Jihad for the Liberation of Palestine against airlines that help
fly Soviet Jews to Israel.
   Hungary's Foreign Minister Gyula Horn said Malev's decision to
suspend the flights was made without prior consultation with the
government.
   He called the suspension ``a rush decision'' and added that
bowing to threats could encourage terrorism.
   Malev chief executive officer Lajos Jahoda told the Hungarian
daily Mai Nap the decision was taken to protect passengers and
Malev employees.
   ``We had to take the threats seriously because we consider
safety a priority,'' he was quoted as saying.
   Budapest was the main transit station for Soviet Jews
immigrating to Israel. The Soviet Union does not have direct
flights to Israel and transit stations including Vienna and
Bucharest are used.
   Israel's highest-ranking official on East European Affairs,
Foreign Ministry Assistant Director-General Yosef Govrin, flew to
Hungary Sunday to ask Hungary to reconsider its decision, a foreign
ministry official in Jerusalem said.
   Israel's Foreign Minister Moshe Arens was quoted by the
Hungarian state news agency MTI Saturday as saying Israel hoped
that ``Hungary, which has just become a democracy, will not give an
example for surrendering to terrorism.''
   The Polish National Airlines Lot and Israel's El Al airlines
were expected to provide an alternatate route for immigrants by
adding two weekly flights between Warsaw and Tel Aviv, a Lot
official in Tel Aviv said.
   Israeli officials claimed no knowledge of the move, which was
reported on the front pages of three major daily newspapers.
   El Al spokesman Nachman Kleinman denied special arrangements
were made to increase flights but noted that Lot and El Al have a
standing agreement to add flights as demand warrants.
   Arab nations have criticized the wave of immigration, partly out
of concern that some newcomers may settle in the occupied West Bank
and Gaza Strip.
   Israel has banned publication of Soviet immigration figures, but
before censorship was imposed the government said 16,700 arrived
between January 1989 and Feb. 1, 1990. According to The New York
Times, some 6,000 are expected this month.
   It is estimated that 200 Soviet Jewish immigrants have settled
in the occupied territories.
   Almost 750,000 Soviet Jews are expected to immigrate this decade
following a relaxation in Soviet restrictions and increased
wariness about growing expressions of anti-Semitism in the Soviet
Union.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0040 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 1453EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Syria-Egypt     03-25 0828</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Syria-Egypt,0851</SECOND>
<HEAD>Syria-Egypt Summit Caps Reconciliation</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP News Analysis</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARTIN MARRIS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NICOSIA, Cyprus (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Talks in Libya between presidents Hosni
Mubarak of Egypt and Hafez Assad of Syria sealed the end of a
12-year rift, bringing diplomatic gains for both countries.
   The history of relations between Syria and Egypt is a stormy
one. The two countries were joined for three years as the United
Arab Republic with Egypt's Gamal Abdel Nasser as head of state, but
the union broke down in 1961.
   The one-hour Assad-Mubarak meeting took place late Saturday
during a ceremony at Tobruk marking the 20th anniversary of the
expulsion of British forces from Libya.
   It followed a resumption of diplomatic relations last December.
Ties were broken a month after the late Egyptian president, Anwar
Sadat, flew to Jerusalem in 1977 to begin the process that led to
the Camp David peace treaty two years later, the only such pact
between Israel and an Arab country.
   ``In one sense, it's a defeat for Syria,'' said a Western
diplomat in Damascus. Like other foreign observers, he attributed
the move largely to Assad's desire to escape from diplomatic
isolation after Egypt was readmitted to the Arab League last May
and other Arab nations resumed diplomatic ties.
   But the diplomat, who like other sources in Damascus insisted on
anonymity, said the move also presented opportunities for the
59-year-old Syrian president to persuade fellow Arab leaders to
follow his firm line toward Israel.
   By meeting Mubarak, Assad has shown once again that he is a
master of maneuver in the Arab world, limiting his losses by
joining the Arab mainstream without abandoning his cherished
hard-line policies, diplomats said.
   For Mubarak, the reconciliation with Assad is a big payoff for
his cautious policy of acting as a go-between. He has been working
with Israel, the United States and the Palestinians on the one hand
while trying to improve Cairo's relations with other Arab nations
on the other.
   Syria is the most implacable enemy of the Jewish state and Assad
has vowed to continue building up his forces until he reaches
``strategic parity'' with Israel so the Arab world can negotiate
from a position of strength.
   But the Soviet Union, preoccupied with internal affairs and
economic problems, has told Syria the parity concept is no longer
tenable and said Damascus, a major Soviet client, should purchase
only the weapons it needs for defense.
   Syrian and Soviet military leaders have agreed to the withdrawal
from Syria of an undisclosed number of Soviet military instructors,
an informed Syrian source said.
   Meanwhile, ties between the Soviet Union and Israel have slowly
improved. The two countries have set up modest representation in
each other's capitals and are exchanging low-level visits.
   Earlier this month Assad expressed his dismay, saying the
changes sweeping Eastern Europe were a boon to Israel as the
formerly Communist countries dropped their hostility to the Jewish
state.
   Syria also is at odds with Palestine Liberation Organization
leader Yasser Arafat and has rejected his peace initiative toward
Israel, which is strongly backed by Egypt and the United States.
   There is no sign yet that Assad is cutting support for
Damascus-based, anti-Arafat radical Palestinian factions which have
been fostering relations with Iran _ just in case.
   But Assad appears to want inclusion, at least indirectly, in the
current process involving Egypt, the PLO, the United States and
Israel aimed at holding elections leading to some autonomy for
Palestinians in Israeli-occupied Arab territories.
   Former President Jimmy Carter said after a meeting with Assad
earlier this month that Syria is ready for bilateral talks with
Israel if they include the Golan Heights, taken by Israel from
Syria after the 1967 war.
   Egyptian officials in Cairo said they expect better but still
limited relations with Syria in view of Egypt's close ties with
Iraq, Syria's arch-rival in the Arab world.
   A meeting between Assad and Mubarak after December's resumption
of diplomatic ties was originally expected to take place in Syria.
There were several Syrian reports of an imminent Damascus meeting.
But Mubarak never showed up, perhaps unwilling to be seen as
knocking on Assad's door, perhaps fearing resentment by Iraq.
   Diplomats in Damascus said the Egyptian president would like to
act as a matchmaker between Assad and Iraqi President Saddam
Hussein. But given the deep hostility between two of the Arab
world's most ruthless and ambitious leaders, there were no signs
that there will be an opportunity for reconciliation.
   Intensifying the feud between the Iraqi and Syrian wings of the
Arab Baath Socialist Party, ruling in both countries, Baghdad has
supplied weapons to Lebanon's anti-Syrian Christian leader, Gen.
Michel Aoun, thwarting Assad's effort to impose a pax Syriana on
its war-torn neighbor.
   Syria was the only major Arab country to side with Persian Iran
in its war against Arab Iraq.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   EDITOR'S NOTE: Martin Marris is based in Cyprus and has covered
the Middle East for The Associated Press since 1986.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0041 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 1500EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--Switzerland-Holdup 1stLd-Writethru   03-25 0199</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Switzerland-Holdup, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0682,0205</SECOND>
<HEAD>Record Holdup in Switzerland Nets $26 Million</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: New thruout to UPDATE with more details on the theft,
CORRECTS surname of police spokesman. No pickup.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>GENEVA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Four armed robbers raided a bank in downtown
Geneva on Sunday and got away with the equivalent of $26 million.
The haul was believed to be the largest in Swiss history, police
said.
   The robbers confronted two security guards at the personnel
entrance around 8 a.m. and forced them to turn over the keys of the
main branch office of the Union Bank of Switzerland, police
spokesman Marcel Vaudroz said.
   The thieves then entered the branch and emptied various
safe-deposit boxes, driving off with 400 pounds of banknotes of
various currencies.
   The spokesmen said the men had somehow obtained the keys or
codes they needed to open the boxes they robbed.
   ``It was a well-prepared job and done by professionals,'' he
said.
   Vaudroz said one of the two guards was treated at a hospital for
injuries suffered when he was struck with a rifle butt.
   The gunmen, described as between 35 and 50 years old and fluent
French speakers, remained at large, despite a large-scale manhunt.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0042 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 1508EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Gorbachev-Lithuania Bjt   03-25 0911</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gorbachev-Lithuania, Bjt,0941</SECOND>
<HEAD>Lithuanians See Test of Perestroika in Gorbachev's Policy</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP News Analysis</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ANN IMSE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>VILNIUS, U.S.S.R. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Despite Mikhail S. Gorbachev's show of
force and barrage of demands, Lithuanians keep assuring themselves
the Soviet president will not use force to crush their independence
because his reform program would die with it.
   ``It would be the end of perestroika and Gorbachev's policy and
his authority,'' said Lithuanian Premier Kazimiera Prunskiene. ``I
don't think Gorbachev would take such a measure.''
   Western diplomats and political figures agree.
   ``It would undermine his policy in Europe, end perestroika and
probably not even be successful,'' said one high-ranking diplomat
in Moscow. In an era of reform, Soviet soldiers might refuse to use
force against Lithuanians, the diplomat said.
   In the past week, tanks and armored personnel carriers have
rumbled through the Lithuanian capital Vilnius, and Gorbachev has
issued a flurry of directives to Lithuanians, including a demand
that they turn in all their firearms and stop signing up for
volunteer service.
   Soviet media have painted the Lithuanian government that
declared independence March 11 as pushing the republic either
toward anarchy or political repression. In an interview printed
Sunday, Gen. Valentin I. Varennikov, commander of Soviet ground
forces, charged that independence leaders were preparing to jail
Communists.
   But the streets of the Lithuanian capital have been calm
throughout the political tension, and citizens interviewed on the
streets have expressed few fears of pending military action.
   Gorbachev and his advisers have said they do not intend to use
force in Lithuania. Foreign Minister Eduard A. Shevardnadze, a
close adviser to Gorbachev, told reporters during his trip to
Africa last week that the Soviet Union is ``particularly against
the use of force domestically.''
   But Gorbachev has pledged to keep the Soviet Union together, and
he has been unable to bend the Lithuanians with argument and
political pressure. His tough reaction to the declaration of
independence has added caution to the Lithuanians' confidence that
he won't use force.
   The Lithuanian government on Thursday night appealed to the
world to speak out against any possible use of force by Soviet
soldiers, and early Saturday passed a resolution transferring power
to a longtime diplomat of independent Lithuania in Washington if
the government is detained.
   The Soviet Union ``is accustomed to solving its problems,
externally and internally, with the use of force,'' said Algimantas
Cekuolis, who until independence was declared served as a
legislator in the Soviet parliament.
   Lithuanian officials and Western diplomats say Gorbachev would
risk wrecking his opening to the West, including the nearly
completed agreements on slashing nuclear weapons by 50 percent and
the removal of hundreds of thousands of troops from front lines in
central Europe.
   Sen. Edward M. Kennedy, arriving in Moscow on Sunday, said use
of force would put Gorbachev's relationship with the United States
at risk.
   ``Any resolution of the issue other than through discussions
would have very significant and damaging implications for that
relationship,'' said Kennedy, D-Mass.
   On Thursday, the U.S. Senate passed a resolution 93-0 urging the
Soviet Union to stop intimidating Lithuanians and warning that use
of military force ``would have severe repercussions for U.S.-Soviet
relatons.''
   ``If he uses force in the Baltics, he can't maintain his current
worldwide standing,'' Prunskiene said, ``and relations between the
Soviet Union and other states could not remain the way they have
been until now.''
   A violent reaction also likely would cut the flow of foreign
investment so desperately needed by the Soviet Union's collapsing
economy. Kremlin officials last week for the first time hinted that
the economy is in such bad shape that it might need outright
foreign aid similar to the Marshall Plan that helped Germany
recover after World War II.
   Western credits were temporarily suspended to China after that
country cracked down on pro-democracy demonstrators in Tiananmen
Square. Foreign businessmen, who had been increasingly disenchanted
with China because of growing economic problems, have been
reluctant to return because of uncertainty about the country's
stability.
   Use of force also would cause a ferocious debate within the
Soviet Union, such as the assault by soldiers on peaceful
demonstrators in the capital of the Georgian republic Tbilisi last
April. Nineteen people were killed, and one was shot later for
violating curfew.
   Angry hard-liners want some sort of crackdown on secessionists,
but reformers have thrown their support to Lithuania's parliament.
   The army also might not be totally reliable, if Gorbachev
decided to use it in Lithuania.
   In January, Soviet mothers took to the streets to protest the
mobilization of their sons to restore order in Azerbaijan, a
Caucasus mountain republic engaged in a bitter dispute with
neighboring Armenia. Soviet officials quickly backed down and ended
the mobilization.
   Weighing the costs and benefits leaves Lithuanians wondering:
Why the war of nerves?
   At worst, they worry Gorbachev is preparing the ground for armed
intervention.
   At the least, he is forcing Lithuania residents, from the police
to everyone owning a hunting gun, to take sides publicly and at
personal risk.
   Still, there is hope the issue will be solved peacefully.
   ``If Gorbachev lets them go freely, they'll be so grateful that
they will put up his statue instead of Lenin's,'' said Bill Hough,
an American expert on international law concerning annexation and
is in Vilnius advising the Lithuanian government.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   EDITOR'S NOTE: Ann Imse has reported on events in the Soviet
Union, including the three Baltic republics' drive for
independence, since September 1988.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0043 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 1526EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-CostaRica-Quakes     03-25 0427</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Costa Rica-Quakes,0440</SECOND>
<HEAD>Earthquakes Damage Buildings, Cause Landslides in Costa Rica</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By UFRAN GARCIA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN JOSE, Costa Rica (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two strong earthquakes rocked Costa
Rica Sunday, damaging buildings, causing landslides and sending
panic-stricken people into the streets. No injuries were reported.
   The quakes, measuring 5.5 and 6.9 on the Richter scale, struck
at 7:16 a.m. (8:16 a.m. EST) and 7:23 a.m., according to Waverly
Person, an official at the U.S. Geological Survey in Golden, Colo.
The epicenter of the quakes was located in the Pacific Ocean, 80
miles southwest of San Jose, he said.
   Federico Guendel of the Vulcanological and Seismological
Observatory in San Jose said 60 aftershocks struck in the hour
after the second quake.
   People in San Jose and other cities rushed out of homes and
buildings as the structures rocked violently. Many terrified people
huddled in the capital's streets and parks, waiting for the earth
to stop trembling.
   Plaster, cornices and other adornments on older buildings
crashed into the streets of San Jose. Many windowpanes and shop
windows also shattered.
   A water boiler exploded at the Hotel Balmoral during the
earthquakes and several of the building's walls cracked. Walls also
cracked at the La Merced Roman Catholic Church, one of the
capital's oldest buildings.
   In Alajuela, a city 12 miles north of San Jose, the cupola of
the local cathedral cracked in half during the second quake, and
long fissures appeared in the sides of many buildings.
   The main highway linking San Jose with the Atlantic Coast was
blocked by several landslides and police ordered traffic halted
until further notice.
   A Red Cross news release reported ``considerable'' damage to
buildings in the Pacific Coast port of Puntarenas. Heavy structural
damage also was reported in the nearby village of Cobano. No
details were immediately available.
   A spokesman for the Red Cross, Carlos Gutierrez, said a
nationwide check by his organization, police and the fire
department turned up no casualties.
   The quakes were the strongest in the nation since 1983, when a
pair of temblors measuring 6.2 and 7.3 on the Richter scale rattled
southern Costa Rica, causing widespread panic but no casualties.
   Another quake of 4.7 rocked San Jose in February 1989.
   The Richter scale is a gauge of the energy released by an
earthquake, as measured by the ground motion recorded on a
seismograph.
   A quake of magnitude 5 can cause considerable damage, while one
measuring 6 can cause severe damage. Every increase of one number
of the Richter scale means that the ground motion is 10 times
greater.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0044 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 1601EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>d a AM-BRF--TrailsCenter     03-25 0158</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Trails Center,0161</SECOND>
<HEAD>Trails Center Opens in Independence</HEAD>
<DATELINE>INDEPENDENCE, Mo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two 10-year-old cousins whose ancestors
journeyed west more than a century ago cut a ceremonial ribbon to
open a museum dedicated to the trails pioneers traveled.
   The National Frontier Trails Center commemorates the role that
Independence, established in 1827, played in outfitting travelers
who headed west on the Santa Fe, Oregon and California trails.
   About 200 people watched as Jennifer Zimmerman of Lee's Summit
and Jacob Queener of Independence cut a ribbon Saturday afternoon.
Jennifer and Jacob's ancestors traveled to California in 1856 and
1865.
   Outside the museum, a handful of living-history enthusiasts in
19th century garb milled around a campsite erected for the weekend.
Inside, visitors examined exhibits telling the trails' story
through diary excerpts, journals and letters.
   Construction of the museum was financed with $2.4 million from
the state. The city of Independence picked up other costs, bringing
the total to $3 million.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0045 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 1607EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-India-Kashmir     03-25 0298</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-India-Kashmir,0309</SECOND>
<HEAD>Moslem Militants Hang Abducted Legislator, Politician</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SRINAGAR, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Moslem separatists in Kashmir hanged a
politician and a former legislator, police said Sunday.
   The separatists accused the former legislator of being a police
informer and following ``un-Islamic practices,'' including
womanizing and drinking liquor.
   The body of Ghulam Nabi, a member of the Congress Party of
former Prime Minister Rajiv Gandhi, was found Sunday on a road in
Kullar, 40 miles north of Srinagar, said police officials who
cannot be identified under briefing rules.
   No group claimed responsibility for the killing, but the police
blamed Moslem guerrillas fighting for indepdendence of the
predominantly Moslem Jammu-Kashmir state from Hindu India.
   Police said Nabi was hanged, a method often used by the Moslem
militants to kill their victims.
   The body of former Kashmir state legislator Mir Mustafa was
found by residents Sunday on a road along a rivulet in Srinagar's
Batmaloo area, police said.
   Mustafa was kidnapped by unidentified gunmen who pulled him out
of his car Saturday near his home in Badgam, 12 miles west of
Srinagar.
   At least 197 people, mostly Moslem demonstrators, have been
killed in Kashmir since Jan. 20 when the government launched a
crackdown on separatists.
   The Hezbul Mujahedeen, or the party of the Islamic holy
warriors, is fighting for independence of the predominantly Moslem
Jammu-Kashmir state from Hindu India.
   A man claiming to be the group's spokesman called The Associated
Press office in Srinagar on Sunday and said Mustafa was killed
because ``he was found indulging in un-Islamic acts and was
informing the Indian Intelligence Bureau on our activities.'' The
man refused to be identified.
   Sixty-four percent of Jammu-Kashmir's 6 million people are
Moslem, but nationwide Moslems make up only 12 percent of India's
880 million people, who are mainly Hindu.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0046 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 1618EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Scrolls     03-25 0631</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Scrolls,0649</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dead Sea Scrolls to be Carbon-dated to Settle Controversy</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By NICOLAS B. TATRO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Dead Sea Scrolls, which include some of the
earliest known Biblical texts, will be subjected to carbon-14
dating to discover whether they were written by a Jewish group or
early Christians, officials said Sunday.
   Magen Broshi, custodian of the Israel Museum's Shrine of the
Book, where some of the scrolls are on public display, said at
least 12 of the 799 scrolls will be dated using new carbon-14
techniques.
   The dating would help settle arguments and conflicting theories
about whether the scrolls were the product of a Jewish group known
as the Essenes or a much later group of early Christians, said Orna
Hess, a spokeswoman for the Antiquities Authority.
   Most biblical scholars believe the scrolls date to the second
century B.C. or late third century B.C. based on paleography, or
analysis of handwriting styles, Broshi said.
   ``We relied on paleography. We will now see if this method
agrees with physics,'' Broshi said. ``I don't believe there is any
urgent need but this will keep people happy.''
   Broshi said the testing would quiet critics like Robert
Eisenman, head of religious studies at California State University
at Long Beach, who do not accept the non-scientific dating.
   In a telephone interview, Eisenman demanded that objective
observers be allowed to witness the dating process and that more
than one laboratory carry out the tests.
   He said this was necessary because the scrolls are controlled by
a team of scholars who have a vested interest in preserving their
theories, which are based on the established chronology.
   ``In order to have a fair process, one that would not be open to
future questions, people of differing shades of opinion should be
brought into the process as observers,'' Eisenman said.
   Eisenman has backed the controversial theory that the
unpublished scrolls may be the work of early Christians. His
argument is based on the wording of the texts, such as the use of
certain phrases known to have been common among early Christians
and indirect references to the rule of King Herod the Great.
   Traditionally, the scrolls are viewed as the work of a small
mysterious sect known as the Essenes. Scholars of this traditional
school say they provide an insight into the life and religious
thought of the ancient sect of Jews as well as the roots of
Christianity.
   Ms. Hess said a small fragment had already been dated at
Israel's Weizmann Institute of Science. She declined to discuss the
results or give details as to how large a fragment was tested.
   Broshi said negotiations were under way with a European
university with more advanced techniques to do the main body of
work, which was expected to start within the next few weeks.
   Neither Broshi nor Hess would say which university was involved.
   None of the papyrus scrolls have been previously carbon dated,
because until a few years ago too much material had to be destroyed
in the process, Broshi said.
   The linen wrapping in which some scrolls were found was dated
more than 30 years ago, using primitive techniques. It dated the
cloth to 33 A.D., plus or minus 200 years.
   Scientists can date organic material on the basis of the amount
of radioactive carbon-14 remaining.
   The new carbon-14 technique, called Accelerator Mass
Spectrometry, requires only a small about of parchment for testing.
It was first employed to date a 27,000-year-old wooly mammouth
found in Siberia in 1977.
   The first scrolls were found in caves at Qumran, overlooking the
Dead Sea, in 1947, and others were excavated over a 10-year span
from 11 caves. Some scrolls represent the earliest existing copies
of books of the Bible. Others contain poetry, stories and legal
texts.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0047 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 1632EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brites     03-25 0242</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brites,0249</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bright &amp; Brief</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NASHVILLE, Tenn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In the end, all Karen and Robert Elliott
could agree on was that they cared about their two cats. They cared
so much, in fact, that they made the pets part of their divorce
settlement.
   Davidson County Probate Judge Jim Everett granted the divorce
last week on the grounds of irreconcilable differences. The
agreement includes cat custody and visitation rights.
   The Elliotts had no property to divide, according to court
documents that awarded Robert Elliott custody of the ``two feline
pets ... of great sentimental value.'' Karen Elliott was granted
``reasonable'' visitation rights _ as long as she calls first.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>KEY WEST, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Linda Spanky Gray gave a lively rendition
of a Dizzy Gillespie's jazz tune, Salt Peanuts, to win first place
in the 24th annual Conch Shell Blowing Contest.
   Gray, 37, who is trained in trumpet, slide trombone and French
horn, earned top adult honors in Saturday's contest, which is part
of a three-month celebration honoring the heritage of the
southernmost city in the continental United States.
   The origin of the event dates back several hundred years to when
Calusa Indians and pirates lived in the Keys and used the conch for
communicating. A toot was a signal of survival or distress.
   A total of 38 contestants teased tunes from the tightly coiled
mollusk, including selections such as ``Sentimental Journey,''
``Yellowbird'' and Ludwig van Beethoven's ``Ode to Joy.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0048 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 1649EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Zaire-Angola     03-25 0612</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Zaire-Angola,0631</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.S. Supplies to Angolan Rebels Stepped Up</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT WELLER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>KINSHASA, Zaire (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The United States has stepped up support
for anti-Marxist Angolan rebels and has shipped specially equipped
four-wheel-drive vehicles that could give them an edge, a U.S.
diplomatic source said.
   The rebels in recent months have been facing one of the biggest
offensives in the 15-year-old civil war from the government backed
by Cuba and the Soviet Union.
   ``Three Toyota Landcruisers are being stripped daily here and
outfitted with heavy machine guns. They (the rebels) are going to
use them for hit-and-run attacks,'' said the source, who spoke on
condition of anonymity.
   The vehicles are considered ideal for traveling on the sand and
scrub-covered roads in southeastern Angola, the site of most of the
fighting in the war.
   The source said at least 120,000 gallons of diesel fuel were
also being shipped from Kinshasa to Jonas Savimbi's UNITA (National
Union for the Total Independence of Angola) rebels.
   The United States has pledged to support Savimbi until Angolan
President Jose Eduardo dos Santos agrees to ``national
reconciliation,'' short-hand for accepting negotations that will
lead to power-sharing with UNITA.
   During last week's tour of southern Africa by Secretary of State
James A. Baker III, a senior official traveling with the secretary
reaffirmed his government would not permit the Angolan government
to crush Savimbi's rebels.
   The United States provides about $50 million annually in aid to
the rebels and stepped up assistance after South Africa agreed to
cease UNITA support as part of a regional peace plan.
   In Washington, White House spokesman Bill Harlow said he was
unaware of any stepped up aid shipments to the Angolan rebels.
   During Baker's visit to Kinshasa on Saturday, one of at least
two American C-141 transport planes believed used to resupply UNITA
had disappeared from sight. Both were on the tarmac Sunday morning.
   A week earlier, a reporter passing through the airport counted
four of the camouflaged planes bearing the U.S. flag.
   Baker last week held talks with the Angolan president and Soviet
Foreign Minister Eduard A. Shevardnadze while in Windhoek, Namibia,
for independence celebrations. Baker met Savimbi on Friday night
and Zaire President Mobutu Sese Seko on Saturday.
   Mobutu has been serving as a mediator for the warring parties in
Angola. He brokered a cease-fire last June, but it quickly fell
apart. He continues to allow the United States to supply the UNITA
rebels through Zaire.
   Officials traveling with Baker said no major progress had been
made because the Angolan president continued to insist on terms
that amounted to a surrender by Savimbi, whose forces had not been
defeated on the battlefield.
   Baker has sought to enlist Soviet support in efforts to
negotiate an end to the Angolan fighting, and Shevardnadze has
indicated his government is ready to cooperate in peace efforts.
   Savimbi says the Soviets have been pouring weapons into Angola _
more than $1 billion worth in the last two years _ in a bid to
shore up the Angolan government forces before all Cuban forces have
withdrawn.
   Under a Soviet- and U.S.-brokered agreement between South
Africa, Angola and Cuba, the 50,000 Cuban troops in Angola are to
be pulled out by mid-1991.
   South Africa granted Namibia independence March 21 as part of
the arrangement and has withdrawn support for UNITA.
   Angolan government forces have pushed farther into rebel
territory during an unprecedented rainy-season offensive than ever
before in the war. For the past several weeks there has been heavy
fighting near the strategic southeastern town of Mavinga.
   Four-wheel drive vehicles could give UNITA an edge once the rain
stops in the next month or so.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0049 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 1650EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Telescope-Squirrels     03-25 0874</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Telescope-Squirrels,0902</SECOND>
<HEAD>Like Snail Darter, Red Squirrel Caught in Environmental Limelight</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ARTHUR H. ROTSTEIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TUCSON, Ariz. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   They're few in number, and their sky-island
habitat has long lain undisturbed. But 180 tiny Mount Graham red
squirrels could prove a big obstacle to construction of the world's
most powerful optical telescope.
   The University of Arizona wants nothing more than to coexist
with the mountaintop rodents, an endangered subspecies. But the
builder of a $200 million observatory atop 10,709-foot Mount Graham
is having to tread carefully.
   The 8-ounce squirrel, or Tamiasciurus hudsonicus grahamensis,
has touched off a two-year ecological controversy that has split
the scientific community, pitted one federal agency against
another, and drawn environmentalists into a battle against
telescope proponents from as far away as the Vatican.
   U.S. District Judge Alfredo C. Marquez will hear closing
arguments Monday afternoon on whether a third federal biological
study is needed before construction begins this year on two smaller
telescopes.
   If all goes smoothly, the Columbus Project, a 600-inch-diameter
device expected to be six times more powerful than any telescope in
use, will be built in the mid-1990s on the 8.6-acre tract in the
Pinaleno Mountains 110 miles northeast of Tucson.
   Just 180 of the squirrels, which have been traced back 10,000
years or more, are believed to remain, and Mount Graham is their
only known habitat.
   Opposition groups say perching the telescopes on Emerald Peak,
one of Mount Graham's three peaks, can only assure that the
squirrels become a biological footnote.
   ``It's biologically indefensible to develop on that mountain,''
said Dr. Robin Silver, spokesman for the Maricopa Audubon Society.
``We will win this case. The question is will we win it before the
university wreaks too much destruction on the mountain?''
   The university, argued its vice president for research, Michael
Cusanovich, ``is the most likely participant to provide the basis
for the Mount Graham red squirrel's recovery.'' It spent more than
$200,000 last year on research and monitoring and will put aside
more than $100,000 annually for several years, he said.
   A two-mile access road for the Mount Graham International
Observatory has already been built. But opponents have so far held
up construction of the observatory buildings.
   The squirrels apparently have some militant supporters. One
mailed an anonymous death threat to telescope proponent Conrad
Istock, head of the University of Arizona's ecology and
evolutionary biology department.
   Eleven of the department's 28 faculty members and 41 of 58
graduate students have voiced opposition to the observatory. But
students at the 38,000-student university later voted down by 57
percent to 43 percent a nonbinding initiative opposing the
observatory. Fewer than 5,000 students voted.
   In July 1988, the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service concluded in a
biological report for the U.S. Forest Service, the site's landlord,
that the telescopes could coexist with the squirrel.
   Arizona's congressional delegation then pushed through
legislation ordering the Forest Service to grant the university a
special-use permit allowing construction.
   But an environmental coalition intervened with a lawsuit.
Naturalists have staged demonstrations outside the Vatican Embassy
and the Smithsonian Institution in Washington.
   The university says it will advertise soon for construction bids
for the two smaller telescopes, one of which is partly financed by
the Vatican Observatory. Pope John Paul II is among the Vatican's
astronomy buffs.
   Two biologists who took part in the Fish and Wildlife Service
study alleged in depositions that officials at the agency ordered
researchers to argue in favor of construction.
   The agency's regional director, Mike Spear, upheld the study as
``biologically sound.'' But, last month, after the construction
site was designated as a critical habitat, Spear called for a
review study.
   However, the Forest Service says the congressional act
authorizes the first three telescopes and exempts them from further
review.
   Spear said the Endangered Species Act makes clear there should
be reconsultation before change in the habitat, while Forest
Service regional chief Dave Jolly said Congress intentionally
skirted the Act.
   University officials contend that poor cone crops in recent
years have hurt the squirrel population, that hunting, logging, use
of off-road vehicles and Christmas tree-cutting have been stopped
because of the planned observatory, and that 60 to 80 acres will be
reforested.
   Silver, who is a wildlife photographer, likened the squirrel's
predicament to that of the snail darter, a 3-inch fish that delayed
the Tennessee River dam project for six years during the 1970s
before it was transplanted to the Hiwassee River.
   ``They're very similar in that the developmental groups managed
to ignore ecosystem destruction and focused the issue on one
creature that was easily demeaned in their project,'' Silver said.
   The dam was completed with Congress first amending the
Endangered Species Act in 1978 to allow an exemption from the law,
then exempting the dam from any law that would hinder its
construction, he said.
   Dan Campbell, director of the Nature Conservancy in Arizona,
says Mount Graham has Arizona's greatest density of black bears,
and is the farthest south that elk can be found in the United
States.
   ``It's the general habitat which we really need to protect and
conserve in order to protect the species,'' he said. ``It's like a
lifeboat. If you keep the lifeboat from sinking, then the species
stay there.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0050 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 1649EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-UprisingLove     03-25 0461</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Uprising Love,0475</SECOND>
<HEAD>Israel Enthralled by Scandal of Army Captain and Palestinian Girl</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Television viewers got the latest Sunday about
the affair that is scandalizing Israel _ the case of the Israeli
army captain suspended from his job over alleged trysting with a
Palestinian woman.
   The wronged wife in what's being called the ``Love and the
Intefadeh'' affair appeared as a blacked-out figure on the evening
TV news to support her husband's story that he was really trying to
recruit the dark-haired Arab woman as an informer.
   The story of Capt. Avi Marak and 20-year-old Abir Mattar has hit
newspaper front pages this weekend largely because with the wall of
hatred that has grown between Jews and Arabs in the Intefadeh _ or
uprising _ such a romance seems unthinkable.
   A military source Sunday confirmed that Marak, who was a company
commander for Israel's military government in the occupied West
Bank, is being investigated on suspicion of ``inappropriate
behavior.''
   According to Israeli newspapers, Marak held nightly secret
rendezvous with the young woman from the Christian village of Beit
Jallah near Bethlehem for between four and eight months.
   They usually spent their time together in military jeeps or
pickup trucks, the reports said.
   The trysts ended after Marak's wife, Ricky, found out, the
Maariv daily said. Early one morning, Mrs. Marak went to the home
of the Palestinian woman, who also is married, and the two got into
a scuffle, according to news reports. The captain then hauled his
wife off in a jeep, the reports said.
   But the shadowy figure on the evening news backed her husband's
story that he was recruiting an informer to act against
Palestinians involved in the 27-month-old uprising against Israeli
occupation of the West Bank and Gaza Strip.
   After saying some unpleasant things about Mrs. Mattar's
reputation, Mrs. Marak added: ``This is a relation based on
(military) security.''
   She said her husband ``never told me anything because he doesn't
let me in on military affairs.''
   Marak, who is still being questioned after removal from his post
earlier this month, told Maariv that he had been seeking an
informer. Other newspapers noted Mrs. Mattar's family had a
reputation of assisting Israeli authorities.
   Mrs. Mattar was quoted as saying she wants to divorce her
husband, who is in jail for attempted murder, and marry Marak.
   ``We are happy together,'' she told the Yediot Ahronot daily.
``When Avi divorces his wife, I will also get a divorce and convert
to marry him.''
   Mrs. Marak told newspapers she hopes to keep her marriage
intact. On television, she said she saw her husband's story as
material for a television script she has been writing as a hobby.
   ``I am putting this all in the script,'' she said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0051 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 1719EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Romania     03-25 0410</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania,0427</SECOND>
<HEAD>Airline Office Burned During Anti-Hungarian Protests</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SLOBODAN LEKIC</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUCHAREST, Romania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An office of the Hungarian state
airline was set on fire Sunday in Romania's capital, and protesters
rallied nationwide in anger over purported secessionist plans by
ethnic Hungarians in Transylvania.
   No injuries were reported in the fire, and damage was minor.
   A police officer blamed hooligans, but anti-Hungarian slogans
had been painted on the Malev airline office's facade in the last
week as ethnic tension mounted.
   Several hours later, Hungary demanded Romania take steps against
``terrorist acts'' and protect Hungarian citizens and offices in
this country, Hungary's MTI news agency said.
   Despite Romanian government appeals for calm, anti-Hungarian
sentiments burst into the open Sunday at rallies by several hundred
people in Bucharest, the Romanian capital. Smaller protests were
reported in other Romania towns.
   Romanians fear that a campaign by Transylvania's 2 million
ethnic Hungarians for education in their own language is a veiled
push for autonomy or even union with Hungary, which ruled the
disputed region for centuries.
   Transylvania was given to Romania in 1920 in the aftermath of
World War I; it was briefly ceded again to Hungary during World War
II.
   The post-revolutionary government has ruled out any possibility
of secession for the region.
   Authorities at the scene of Sunday's fire at the airline office
provided few details. A paramilitary police officer standing guard
over burned debris outside told reporters that unidentified
hooligans set fire to the office about 3 a.m. The officer declined
to give his name.
   In the Transylvanian town of Tirgu Mures, where at least seven
people were killed last week and about 300 injured in ethnic
strife, Romanian churchgoers prayed for peace outside the city's
Orthodox cathedral Sunday.
   In Bucharest, about 700 people chanting ``Tirgu Mures is
Romania'' and ``Barbarians behind bars'' circled the headquarters
of the interim Romanian government on Victory Square. Troops and
paramilitary police armed with automatic rifles and batons guarded
the government building.
   Critics say the government, which took control after the
December revolution ousted Communist dictator Nicolae Ceausescu,
has not done enough to control the ethnic unrest.
   With the end of Ceausescu's hard-line regime, both Romanians and
ethnic Hungarians have more freedom to express themselves, and the
new atmosphere has led to clashes.
   ``Ceausescu hated us, but at least we were not afraid to walk in
the streets,'' said a Hungarian writer in Tirgu Mures, declining to
give his name.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0052 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 1829EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Obit-Kazem     03-25 0133</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Kazem,0138</SECOND>
<HEAD>Nasser's Widow Dies</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CAIRO, Egypt (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Taheya Kazem, widow of the late President
Gamal Abdel Nasser, died Sunday, the state-owned Middle East News
Agency and Cairo television announced. She was 66.
   The announcement said she will be burried Monday after a funeral
but gave no further details. President Hosni Mubarak and other
high-ranking Egyptian officials were expected to attend the funeral.
   Nasser, who took power in a military coup and ruled Egypt for 18
years, died on Sept. 28, 1970, of a heart attack.
   Unlike his successor, Anwar Sadat, Nasser did not allow his wife
to take part in public social activities. Jihan Sadat's activities
were prominently published in Egyptian news media at the time of
her husband's rule.
   Sadat was assassinated on Oct. 6, 1981, by Moslem extremists.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0053 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 1804EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-WeatherpageWeather     03-25 0294</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Weatherpage Weather,0306</SECOND>
<HEAD>Clouds and Drizzle Linger Over Mid-Atlantic Coast</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Clouds and drizzle lingered along the middle Atlantic Coast on
Sunday after dumping a record amount of snow. Much of north-central
Texas also was wet.
   The storm that created heavy snow from the lower Missouri Valley
to the middle Atlantic Coast broke snowfall records Saturday in
Philadelphia, with 2.2 inches, and at the Atlantic City
International Airport near Pomona, N.J., with 2.4 inches.
   A day earlier, temperatures in those two areas were in the upper
60s.
   Clouds and light rain remained along the mid-Atlantic Coast
early Sunday afternoon. Light rain and drizzle extended from the
southern High Plains to Arkansas.
   Freezing drizzle fell on parts of northern Texas in the morning
but changed to light rain as temperatures rose during the day.
Heavy showers fell on parts of north central Texas.
   The rest of the nation enjoyed dry weather. Skies were sunny in
the West, and from Montana and Wyoming to the Ohio Valley and the
Great Lakes region.
   Temperatures were only in the 30s in Oklahoma and northern
Texas, as well as the northern and central Plains and the
northeastern United States early in the afternoon.
   But temperatures rose into the 70s and 80s in Southeast and the
valleys and deserts of the Southwest.
   Morning lows were mostly in the teens and 20s from the Rocky
Mountains to New England, with readings in the single digits or
below zero in the northern Rockies and the northern High Plains.
   The low of 13 degrees at International Airport in Kansas City,
Mo., was the lowest for the date in 18 years of record-keeping
there.
   The low for the Lower 48 states was 5 degrees below zero at West
Yellowstone, Mont.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0054 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 1859EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Pyromaniac-Palms     03-25 0267</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Pyromaniac-Palms,0276</SECOND>
<HEAD>Investigators Search for Arsonist who Sets Trees Ablaze</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   More than 100 of this area's trademark palm
trees have caught fire over the last five months, and investigators
suspect an arsonist, possibly working with a driver, is to blame,
officials said.
   Some of the fires have spread to nearby houses or cars, doing
minor damage, said Fire Battalion Chief William Burmester.
   Burmester said he was worried the consequences of future blazes
could be more serious. ``There is always a danger, even with a guy
like this who is not setting large fires,'' he said.
   Most of the 104 fires since October have occurred in early
evening in the adjoining suburbs of Reseda, Canoga Park and
Northridge about 20 miles north of downtown Los Angeles. On several
occasions, trash rather than trees was set on fire.
   The outbreak represents the largest number of apparently related
arsons in memory, arson investigators said. No motive has emerged.
   On Jan. 23, a 16-year-old Reseda boy with emotional problems was
arrested after admitting he set fire to palm trees and trash in
copycat arsons.
   Arson investigator Glen Lucero said there may be other copycats
at work, but suspected that most of the fires were set by one
person or perhaps two people working together.
   ``The fires are set so quickly,'' Lucero said. ``It could be one
guy lighting them and somebody else doing the driving.''
   ``It is almost completely random as far as the locations go,''
said fellow investigator Bill Cass. ``Recently, he's been more
interested in trees than trash. We don't know what that means.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0055 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 1906EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SouthAfrica     03-25 0444</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-South Africa,0456</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mandela Calls For Students To End Boycotts</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GREG MYRE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JOHANNESBURG, South Africa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Nelson Mandela on Sunday urged
black students to return to class and call off anti-apartheid
boycotts that have disrupted schools for the past several years.
   ``Without education, you can forget about liberation,'' Mandela
told an estimated 30,000 blacks in the northern town of Pietersburg.
   The statement appeared directed at young, militant blacks who
have led the school boycotts under the slogan, ``Liberation before
education.''
   ``The tactic of the boycott cannot hope to win our battles in
the educational arena,'' said Mandela, who is deputy president of
the African National Congress, the nation's leading anti-apartheid
group. ``Our stayaways and boycotts are giving the education
departments one long holiday.''
   Since the mid-1980s, black students have staged frequent and
prolonged boycotts to protest the inferior education system for
blacks and to press other grievances. In some parts of the country,
blacks students have attended classes only a few days this year.
Black teachers also have been on strike in some areas.
   The boycotts have coincided with declining test scores by black
students. Last year, only 42 percent of blacks passed their
matriculation examination following their final year of high
school. It was the poorest showing in years.
   Mandela, a lawyer, has repeatedly stressed the importance of
education in recent speeches. He also has criticized the conditions
of black schools, most of which are understaffed and lack proper
materials.
   On Sunday, Mandela also called on blacks to unite, saying
factional violence was diverting attention from the struggle
against apartheid, South Africa's system of racial segregation.
   ``Apartheid has deeply wounded our society, making us enemies of
each other,'' he said.
   More than 300 blacks have been killed, mostly in factional
violence, since Mandela was released from prison Feb. 11 after
serving 27 years for launching the ANC's sabotage campaign.
   President F.W. de Klerk legalized the ANC and other
anti-apartheid groups last month as part of his white government's
program to create a political role for the country's black majority.
   Elsewhere Sunday, the Zulu homeland's leader, Mangosuthu
Buthelezi, said he planned to meet soon with Mandela, an old friend
and now a political rival.
   Supporters of Mandela's ANC and Buthelezi's Inkatha movement
have been battling since 1986 for political supremacy in the
southeastern province of Natal, leaving more than 3,000 blacks dead.
   ``It is violence against democracy and against the black
struggle for liberation,'' Buthelezi told several thousand people
at a stadium in the port city of Durban.
   Buthelezi gave no date for the meeting with Mandela, but he said
it could be as soon as this week.
  
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0056 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 1911EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Afghanistan     03-25 0402</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Afghanistan,0419</SECOND>
<HEAD>Afghan Rebel Commander Killed in Ambush</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PESHAWAR, Pakistan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A key Afghan rebel commander, who was
also known as leader of a drug empire in southern Afghanistan, was
killed Sunday in an ambush outside this border city, Western
diplomats said.
   Nazim Akhundzada and his six heavily armed bodyguards were
gunned down outside a guerrilla compound 10 miles east of Peshawar,
diplomats said on condition of anonymity.
   No one claimed responsibility for the killings, and the
diplomats said they had few details.
   Akhundzada's drug operation took in most of Afghanistan's
southern province of Helmand, Afghan and diplomatic sources said.
   Afghanistan's Marxist government regularly accuses the rebels of
financing their insurgency with large-scale poppy production. The
guerrillas and Pakistan have made similar charges against the
Soviet-backed Kabul government.
   Late last year, Akhundzada reportedly asked the United States
for $2 million a month to stop growing poppies, which can be used
to make opium and heroin. U.S. Embassy officials in Islamabad
denied he was given any money.
   ``It just wasn't true,'' said a U.S. diplomat who spoke on
condition of anonymity. ``He was told that because he was growing
poppies, we couldn't deal with him at all.''
   Afghan rebels have been fighting for almost 12 years to oust
successive Communist governments in Kabul, Afghanistan's capital.
The insurgents are supported by the United States, Pakistan and
several Arab states, including Saudi Arabia.
   The protracted war has been blamed for increased poppy
production, particularly in the lawless border frontier between
Pakistan and Afghanistan.
   Afghan and Western sources said Akhundzada had many enemies.
``It got to be a long list very quickly,'' one diplomat said.
   The commander had a long-standing feud with a rival rebel group,
Hezb-i-Islami, led by the firebrand fundamentalist Gulbuddin
Hekmatyar.
   ``He threw almost all Hezb people out of Helmand province,''
said one Afghan guerrilla leader, who also spoke on condition of
anonymity.
   Akhundzada belonged to Harakat-i-Inqilab-i-Islami, or the
Islamic Revolutionary Movement. It is one of the seven major rebel
groups with headquarters in Peshawar.
   ``He was one of Harakat's strongest and most powerful
commanders,'' said Hamid Karzai, a rebel spokesman.
   Last year, Akhundzada waged a bloody drug war in Helmand
province against a rival commander of Rasul Sayyaf's fundamentalist
Ittihad-i-Islami, or Islamic Unity guerrilla party.
   Akhundzada's death came five days after one of Sayyaf's field
commanders, Painda Mohammad, was killed outside Peshawar, said
Qaribur Saeed, a spokesman for Hekmatyar's party.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0057 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 1916EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-France-Art     03-25 0175</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-France-Art,0181</SECOND>
<HEAD>Modigliani Painting Biggest Prize at Record-breaking Auction</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A 1918 oil painting by Amedeo Modigliani was sold
Sunday for $11.5 million during a record-breaking auction of 20th
century art.
   The Drouot auction house said total sales were $107 million, a
record for Paris.
   The Modigliani painting, ``The Beautiful Shopkeeper,'' claimed
the biggest price, and marked a record sale in France for the
Italian artist. The identity of the buyer was not disclosed.
   ``The Fishermen of Nanterre,'' completed in 1906 by Maurice de
Vlaminck, went for $10.5 million, the second-largest price. A 1953
Picasso, ``Woman and Dog Playing, Blue Background,'' was sold for
$4.4 million.
   Potential buyers in Tokyo were able to participate in the
auction via due to a live television transmission by satellite.
   Of the more than 80 works on sale, 53 were from the private
collection of a Parisian woman identified by the auction house only
as Mrs. Bourdon. These included two Modiglianis, three Picassos,
the Vlaminck, and works by Henri Matisse, Raoul Dufy, Man Ray and
others.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0058 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 1940EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Lithuania 2ndLd-Writethru a0707 03-25 0946</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lithuania, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0707,0978</SECOND>
<HEAD>Precede MOSCOW</HEAD>
<HEAD>Soviet Soldiers Seize Lithuanian Schools, But Talks Under Way</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 27 grafs to UPDATE with Soviet-Lithuanian talks,
details; pickup graf 23 pvs, `At least...' TRIMS thereafter. No
pickup. CHANGES byline.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto VIL2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ANN IMSE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>VILNIUS, U.S.S.R. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Soviet military commanders Sunday sent
soldiers with automatic weapons to occupy two Communist Party
schools in Lithuania but later agreed to discuss building security
with the breakaway republic.
   It was the latest escalation in the war of nerves between the
Kremlin and the leadership of this Baltic republic, which declared
itself independent March 11.
   The commander of all Soviet ground forces, Gen. Valentin I.
Varennikov, accused independence leaders of plotting to arrest
Communists and send them to prison.
   Lithuanian President Vytautas Landsbergis said he talked twice
on the telephone with Varennikov, whose presence in Vilnius was a
sign of Moscow's concern with the situation in the small Baltic
republic. The general reportedly said no more buildings would be
taken overnight but made no promises beyond that.
   The soldiers occupied Lithuania's Institute of Marxism-Leninism
and the Higher Party School.
   The republic's deputy premier, Romualdas Ozolas, said earlier he
feared Soviet forces might storm Lithuania's legislative
headquarters.
   Landsbergis asked for a meeting to receive an explanation about
the building seizures, and Varennikov sent four officers to the
Lithuanian parliament building.
   In a brief news conference afterward, Landsbergis quoted the
officers as telling him the buildings had been seized at the
request of Communist Party members who remain loyal to Moscow.
   ``We expressed surprise and astonishment that the military can
occupy buildings at the request of a political organization, and we
asked if such requests come from other organizations whether they
will fulfill them,'' Landsbergis said. ``We did not receive a
concrete answer.''
   Although Varennikov made no promises not to seize more buildings
Monday, Landsbergis said the two sides agreed to form a joint
committee on control of such buildings. More meetings on the issue
were set for Monday morning, he said.
   Franciskas Benucius, a director of the Higher Party School, said
30 soldiers who arrived there told him they were sent to guard the
building.
   ``I asked, `What are you protecting it from?' and they didn't
know,'' he said.
   The school is used by both the Lithuanian Communist Party that
has broken with Moscow and the smaller group that remains loyal.
Officials expected the school to open Monday despite the soldiers'
presence.
   Despite the increasing tension, there was no sign Sunday that
the Soviet army was trying to round up hundreds of Lithuanians who
deserted. A deadline of Saturday had been set for their return.
   For days, as President Mikhail S. Gorbachev and other Moscow
officials have squeezed the defiant Baltic state, official media
reports have criticized a draft bill in Lithuania's new parliament
that they say could mean imprisonment for those who speak out
against independence.
   Varennikov said workers he met with at a Vilnius electronics
factory were ``convinced that Sajudis is trying to create in the
republic a real dictatorship.''
   Sajudis is the grass-roots political movement that has pressed
for Lithuanian independence from the Soviet Union. Its candidates
won an absolute majority in the parliament that declared
independence, and election commission officials said Sunday it also
won a sizeable majority in voting Saturday for the Vilnius city
council.
   But Varennikov charged Sajudis, headed by Landsbergis, is
conducting an ``open psychological war against dissidents.''
   ``In conditions of this `democracy,' many people are
frightened,'' he said in an interview printed Sunday by the
newspaper Sovietskaya Rossiya, the official newspaper of
Lithuania's giant neighbor, the Russian republic.
   ``And when a law is adopted prohibiting criticism of the
government, you can expect arrests,'' Varennikov said.
   Asked by the paper whether he meant Communists who remained
loyal to Moscow could be arrested, he replied:
   ``All Communists, I think. They already have divided the party,
now it remains to send Communists to prison camps or jails.''
   The Lithuanian government has vowed to establish a fully
democratic multiparty political system that respects all
internationally recognized human rights.
   But it says that as Lithuania establishes its own law, residents
of the republic will be expected to obey it rather than Soviet law.
   Lithuanian leaders accuse Gorbachev of conducting his own
psychological war against them through the media and with a series
of demands and military maneuvers, including a convoy of about 100
army vehicles that roared through downtown Vilnius early Saturday.
   Gorbachev and his advisers have pledged not to use force. But
the Soviet leader has ordered Lithuanians to surrender all firearms
and told them not to sign up for volunteer units under the
republic's government.
   At least 28 Lithuanian deserters were in a refuge organized by
the Lithuanian government at the New Vilnius Psychiatric Hospital
dormitory as Sunday dawned.
   ``We expect that nobody would dare to attack the Red Cross,''
said one of them, 20-year-old Darius Baceulis.
   And if troops do come after them, 19-year-old Arunas Vazinskas
said, life would still ``be better in prison than in the army.''
   Many Baltic draftees have complained of brutality and harassment
by fellow soldiers and officers, especially since their republics
strengthened their drive for independence.
   Landsbergis on Saturday suggested that the soldiers seek
protection in churches, a traditional haven for people seeking to
avoid arrest. But no soldiers appeared to have taken his advice.
Many preferred to stay with friends.
   A Roman Catholic priest preaching at the main cathedral in
Vilnius on Sunday urged believers to remain calm.
   ``Our big enemy would like to make us lose our patience in order
to use force,'' he said. ``I beg you to be calm. Be patient.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0059 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 2012EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-SkinCancer     03-25 0597</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Skin Cancer,0613</SECOND>
<BYLINE>Immune System May Battle Melanoma, Studies Suggest
^By MALCOLM RITTER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DAYTONA BEACH, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two strategies that boost the immune
system to battle the most dangerous form of skin cancer show
promise in early tests with patients, a researcher said Sunday.
   Twenty-three percent of patients showed evidence of some
remission of melanoma after injections in one of the experimental
treatments primed their bodies to attack certain proteins found on
melanoma cells, said Malcolm Mitchell.
   The injections are called theraccines, short for therapeutic
vaccines, because they seek to treat cancer rather than prevent
disease, he said.
   Mitchell, a professor of medicine and microbiology at the
University of Southern California School of Medicine in Los
Angeles, described the work at a science writers seminar sponsored
by the American Cancer Society.
   About 27,600 new cases of melanoma are expected this year, with
6,300 deaths, the society says. Intense exposure to the sun is a
chief cause.
   Mitchell's experimental injections make the immune system seek
out proteins called antigens on cancerous cells. The preparations
are made from melanoma cells grown in the laboratory.
   Injections were done under the skin once a week for four weeks
with a final injection on week six. Patients who responded were
treated with a single monthly booster and semiannual courses of
five more doses.
   In 79 melanoma patients, the treatment produced a complete
remission in 5 percent and a partial remission in 18 percent,
Mitchell said. Another 10 percent showed minor responses, defined
as tumor shrinkage of 26 percent to 50 percent.
   No major side effects were observed, he said.
   Other researchers have reported similar work. ``Clearly this is
an attraactive approach,'' said John Laszlo, the cancer society's
senior vice president for research.
   Mitchell also reported on results from treating melanoma
patients with low doses of interleukin-2, a natural substance used
by the immune system, and a standard cancer drug called
cyclophosphamide. Both drugs were given at about one-third the dose
used in experiments or therapy.
   In 39 patients, the combination produced a 28 percent response
rate, including two complete remissions and eight partial
remissions, Mitchell said.
   Potentially, this treatment could be done by any hospital, and
its results are comparable to a more complex treatment in which
interleukin-2 is combined outside the body with white blood cells
and then reinjected into the patient, Mitchell said.
   In what he called the ``down note'' of his talk, Mitchell said
some other forms of therapy will have to be found to deal with the
spread of melanoma cells to the brain, where they can form new
cancers.
   In a separate presentation, a researcher said a study of 200
people with or without melanoma suggests that six factors define
people at high risk for getting the disease.
   They are blond or red hair, marked freckling of the upper back,
the presence of rough, red bumps called actinic keratoses caused by
to sun exposure, a history of melanoma in other family members,
having had three or more blistering sunburns during one's teen-age
years, and having spent three or more years at an outdoor summer
job as a teen-ager.
   Having any one or two of these factors gives a person a three to
four times increased chance of developing melanoma, said Darrell
Rigel of the New York University School of Medicine.
   People with three or more of the factors run an increased risk
of 20 to 25 times, he said.
   People at high risk should be taught the ways to detect melanoma
early, when it is at a highly curable stage, he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0060 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 2002EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-FireClubs 1stLd-Writethru a0716 03-25 0780</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Fire Clubs, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0716,0799</SECOND>
<HEAD>Illegal Clubs Proliferate Despite Efforts to Close Them</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 11 grafs to UPDATE with mayor promising to close
unlicensed clubs, figures on number of clubs, number of people
killed in city's worst fire. Pick up 10th graf pvs, `Just about...'
DELETES next-to-last graf to conform. </NOTE>
<HEAD>With AM-Social Club Fire, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PAUL GEITNER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hundreds of dangerous and illegal social clubs
thrive in New York despite efforts to close them, because people in
poor neighborhoods have few alternatives for entertainment,
officials say.
   ``People are literally taking their lives in their hands at
these clubs,'' Bronx Borough President Fernando Ferrer said after a
fire Sunday killed 87 people at the Happy Land social club.
   It was the city's deadliest blaze since 145 people were killed
in a fire at a garment factory, the Triangle Shirtwaist Co. of
Manhattan, 79 years ago to the day.
   Authorities said most of the predawn revelers were trapped on a
second-story dance floor and died from smoke inhalation. The
building lacked proper exits and other safeguards.
   The 4-year-old club, which didn't have a liquor or cabaret
license, was shut down for the second time Nov. 1, 1989, by the
city Buildings Department, but reopened illegally, Mayor David
Dinkins said.
   Despite periodic campaigns to close them, social clubs have been
centers of urban problems ranging from noise and double-parking to
gambling, drug dealing and prostitution.
   Mayor David Dinkins estimated there are at least 700 social
clubs in the city.
   They often are rife with building, health and fire code
violations that can lead to tragedy. Six people died in a 1988 fire
at a Bronx club, five in a Brooklyn club fire in 1985, and 25
people were killed in another Bronx fire in 1976.
   ``I don't know what it's going to take _ an army _ to stop them
from going to places like this,'' said newly elected U.S. Rep. Jose
Serrano after visiting the scene Sunday.
   City records reviewed Sunday showed 173 social clubs had been
given orders to vacate, Dinkins said at an afternoon news
conference.
   ``Tonight, we will commence to check those places, see that
they're in fact closed,'' he said. ``We'll see to it that they
certainly aren't open come the next weekend.''
   Just about anyone can go to a social club, despite the term's
implication of exclusivity. An employee usually keeps an eye on the
door, but a club member is generally anyone who walks in on a given
night.
   ``They range from a group of elderly men who get together to
play cards and watch a ballgame on a Sunday afternoon to
full-fledged nightclub operations,'' said Richard Chernela, a state
Liquor Authority spokesman.
   New York State liquor licenses cost up to $5,100 and are good
for three years. But many club operators don't apply for one,
sometimes because they or potential employees may have criminal
records that would disqualify them.
   While the city's licensed bars are required to close by 4 a.m.,
social clubs often stay open until dawn or later, usually to the
distress of nearby residents. Neighborhood residents said Happy
Land stayed open until 6 a.m.
   Often there's a cover charge _ $5 at Happy Land. Often the clubs
sell drinks.
   Many who go to the clubs are looking for a place to socialize
that they can afford and where they feel welcome. But they also
attract a criminal element.
   A state task force reported several years ago that alcohol
consumption is often of secondary importance.
   ``The primary function of these operations has developed into
prostitution, gambling, drugs and trafficking in stolen property,''
it said.
   Just Sunday morning, a police task force in Brooklyn raided
several social clubs and arrested five people for weapons
possession, said Sgt. Tina Mohrmann, a police spokeswoman.
   Some clubs are closed under the city's ``padlock law,'' which
allows police to shutter a location for a year if two crimes are
committed on the site within a 12-month period.
   But the owners _ if they can be found _ are rarely convicted.
Defendants arrested in police raids often end up pleading guilty to
a lesser charge, which then doesn't qualify as a criminal
conviction under the padlock law.
   Even when the clubs are shuttered, the owners often open up
again around the corner or down the street, attracting the same
crowd.
   Then-Mayor Edward Koch put together an interagency task force
after the 1988 fire sparked a public outcry about the dangers of
social clubs.
   ``The ironic thing is that all the legislation is on the
books,'' said Clint Roswell, a spokesman for Ferrer. ``It's just
(an) enforcement problem.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0061 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 2014EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-DrugRing     03-25 0308</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Drug Ring,0319</SECOND>
<HEAD>Alleged Leader Of Drug Ring Pleads Guilty</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WILMINGTON, Del. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A man accused of heading a Sicilian drug
ring that smuggled heroin and cocaine into New York pleaded guilty
to all charges against him, leaving two defendants in a federal
trial.
   Francesco Bellitti, 39, of New York City, admitted to U.S.
District Judge Jane R. Roth on Friday that he was a leader of the
drug ring.
   The Northeast drug ring's heroin and cocaine allegedly was sold
in Delaware through a pizzeria near Claymont in the northeastern
section of the state. Vincent J. Scotto, who owned the pizza shop,
is a former member of the gang turned government witness.
   Belitti faces a maximum sentence of life plus 45 years in prison
and fines of $16.5 million in the case, but could get more time
behind bars because of a prior drug conviction. He is to be
sentenced May 24.
   Belitti pleaded guilty to three charges of distribution of
heroin and one each of conspiracy to distribute cocaine and heroin,
interstate travel to commit a crime and racketeering.
   His attorney, Pat V. Stiso of New York, declined to comment on
his client's sudden change of heart.
   Bellitti also faces deportation after serving his sentence. He
told authorities he illegally entered the United States in 1982
from Mexico.
   According to court papers, Bellitti was convicted in 1973 in
Canada of conspiring to import heroin.
   Federal prosecutor Robert Courtney III told the judge the
evidence in the government's case would establish Bellitti as one
of two men who organized a 20-member ring that distributed drugs
through the Northeast and supervised its operations.
   The other defendants in the trial, Alexis Telesford and
Salvatore Ingrati, both of New York, are accused of helping to set
up drug deals and sharing in profits.
   Testimony was scheduled to resume Monday.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0062 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 2015EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Nicaragua     03-25 0389</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Nicaragua,0401</SECOND>
<HEAD>Nicaraguan Cardinal Deplores Rebel Ambush, Urges Contras To
Disband</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RODOLFO GARCIA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MANAGUA, Nicaragua (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Roman Catholic Church leader Sunday
denounced a rebel ambush in northern Nicaragua that killed 18
people and wounded eight, and he urged the Contras to live up to
their agreement to disband immediately.
   ``This is deplorable. We must hurry so that the agreement signed
in Tocontin become a reality,'' Cardinal Miguel Obando y Bravo said
in a homily.
   Obando y Bravo witnessed the accord between representatives of
the U.S.-backed rebels and President-elect Violeta Barrios de
Chamorro Friday at Tocontin Airport in Tegucigalpa, the capital of
neighboring Honduras.
   ``May the tanks be converted into tractors and that young people
devote themselves to producing, so that life becomes better in
Nicaragua,'' the cardinal said.
   While the agreement was being worked out in Honduras, about 100
Contras attacked an army convoy with rockets, mortars and automatic
weapons in northern Nicaragua near La Pavona, a town of about 3,000
135 miles north of Managua.
   The Defense Ministry said 12 army soldiers, five Contras and one
civilian were killed in the fighting. Another eight soldiers were
wounded, it said.
   ``Maybe news of the agreement had not reached these people (the
rebels) in the mountains,'' Obando y Bravo said.
   Obando y Bravo urged Mrs. Chamorro, who takes office on April
25, and the Contras to name their delegates to a commission called
for in the accord to oversee the demobilization.
   In La Pavona, Army Lt. Benedicto Martinez said the 600
government soldiers in the area were searching for the Contras and
there was scattered fighting around nearby villages. He refused to
give details.
   The attack raised doubts about the viability of the accord,
which was not signed by the Contra's chief military commander,
Israel Galeano. Only Contra negotiator Oscar Sovalbarro and Mrs.
Chamorro's negotiator, Antonio Lacayo, signed the pact.
   The Sandinistas refused to take part in the negotiations, but
President Daniel Ortega said later he backed the agreement. He also
expressed concern that Galeano did not take part in the talks or
sign the document.
   Despite the doubts, the accord was seen as a potential
breakthrough.
   The Contras had said they would not disarm until the Sandinista
army did. The Sandinistas, in turn, had insisted the Contras lay
down their guns first.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0063 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 2017EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-IllegalAliens     03-25 0330</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Illegal Aliens,0342</SECOND>
<HEAD>38 Illegal Aliens Found Hiding in Rental Truck</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CLEVELAND (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Thirty-eight illegal aliens found cramped and
hungry inside a rental truck that broke down in northeast Ohio
might have been brought from Mexico to work at farm nurseries,
immigration officials said Sunday.
   U.S. Immigration and Naturalization Service agents were trying
to determine who brought the men to Ohio, said Robert Brown, head
of the agency's Cleveland office.
   The aliens were flown back to Mexico on Saturday after being
discovered early the same day.
   Authorities suspect the men were hoping to land work with
nurseries, Brown said. Seven of the 38 already had jobs lined up,
he said, declining to say where.
   He said the aliens were ``basically good people who are just
trying to do whatever thay can to make a living for their
families.''
   The men had been carrying counterfeit Social Security and green
cards, which are issued as documentation of an alien's permanent,
legal U.S. residency. Nearly all lived in an area north of Mexico
City, Brown said.
   Each paid $300 to $600 to make the trip, and more than half had
paid up to $60 for counterfeit documents, he said.
   Chardon police said a resident complained early Saturday about a
rental truck seen in the northeastern Ohio village and men acting
suspiciously. When police located the 12-foot-long truck, they
found the aliens huddled in the back.
   Village Interim Police Chief Steve Gazdik said the truck had
broken down and the driver might have fled before police arrived.
   ``It's possible that the driver was an alien as well,'' Gazdik
said. ``But we aren't sure.''
   Gazdik said the group, including two teen-agers, endured cramped
and unsanitary conditions, and may not have eaten for two to five
days.
   He said they may have been headed to orchards and nurseries in
Ashtabula County.
   The truck was rented March 15, and the men boarded in Tijuana,
Mexico, and entered the United States through Southern California,
Brown said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0064 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 2031EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Cancer-PillSales     03-25 0375</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Cancer-Pill Sales,0388</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dying Cancer Victims Selling Pain Pills To Pay For Funeral Costs</HEAD>
<DATELINE>COLUMBIA, S.C. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Dying cancer patients have been raising
money by selling their pain pills to a drug ring, authorities say.
   ``It's a pitiful sight,'' said Sgt. Raymond Lee, a narcotics
investigator with the West Columbia Police Department. ``They're so
poor they're willing to take an aspirin and put up with the pain.''
   Five people were arrested in the case, police said Sunday.
   Drug dealers befriended other patients who refused to sell their
pills, called Dilaudid, and then stole the medicine from them, Lee
said last week. Other times, relatives of patients stole the pills
and sold them for about $25 each to the drug dealers, he said.
   The patients usually are given Dilaudid to ease the suffering
during their final days.
   The dealers sold the tiny yellow pills to heroin addicts for
about $40 each, Lee said. The addicts pound the pills into a
powder, which they inject into their veins.
   Police identified those arrested as Patty Carlini, 34, of West
Columbia, Wanda Oree, 28, of West Columbia, and Karen C. Jackson,
34, Columbia. They were charged with distribution of a controlled
substance, distribution within proximity of a school and conspiracy
to distribute a controlled substance, police said.
   The two others arrested were Nin B. Nissen, 39, of Columbia, and
Ronald Burgess, 44, of Columbia, police said. The charges against
them were not immediately known.
   Most of the cancer patients being treated at the Veterans
Administration Hospital and got their pills free, said West
Columbia Police Chief H.C. Salters.
   ``One cancer patient's profits would range up to $2,500 a month
by selling the drug he had gotten from the V.A. Hospital,'' Salters
said.
   The sick patients who sold the drugs weren't arrested, Lee said.
But officials were investigating some patients who may have been
deceiving doctors by saying they were sick to get drugs to sell.
   ``I don't want to come down hard on the V.A.,'' Lee said. ``But
they've been handing these things out in bundles.''
   The FBI said through a spokesman Sunday that the agency wasn't
investigating the federally-run hospital.
   Robert Athey, director of the hospital, said he was unaware of
the allegations concerning cancer patients.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0065 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 2111EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p AM-Williams-RapeRemark 2ndLd-Writethru a0745 03-25 0596</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Williams-Rape Remark, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0745,0611</SECOND>
<HEAD>GOP Gubernatorial Nominee's Remark Decried</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: DELETES extraneous word, ``enjoy,'' in lead.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By ROD RICHARDSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DALLAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Republican gubernatorial nominee Clayton Williams
said Sunday his off-the-cuff remark suggesting victims of rape
should ``relax and enjoy it'' was insensitive, after initially
downplaying it as just a joke.
   Women's groups and the millionaire rancher's political foes
reacted with outrage. State Treasurer Ann Richards, who is in the
April 10 runoff for the Democratic nomination, said Sunday that
Williams seemed not to realize that rape is a crime of violence.
   While preparing for a cattle round-up at his West Texas ranch
Saturday, Williams compared the cold, foggy weather spoiling the
event to a rape.
   ``If it's inevitable, just relax and enjoy it,'' Williams said
to ranch hands, campaign workers and reporters sitting around a
campfire.
   On Sunday, his campaign issued a statement in which he said: ``I
feel just terrible about this. I had no intention in my heart to
hurt anyone especially those women who have traumatized by rape.
   ``Looking back, I realize it was insensitive and had no place at
the campfire or in any setting,'' the statement said.
   Williams, who is making his first run for public office,
initially downplayed the remark. On Saturday he said it was a joke
and he apologized ``if anyone's offended.''
   Pressed further for an explanation for the remark, Williams
said: ``That's not a Republican women's club that we were having
this morning. It's a working cow camp, a tough world where you can
get kicked in the testicles if you're not careful.''
   Asked if some people might be offended, Williams said: ``I'm not
going to give you a serious answer. It wasn't a serious deal. It
wasn't a serious statement.''
   Marilyn Rickman, head of the Texas Women's Political Caucus,
which has endorsed Ms. Richards for governor, said Saturday that
Williams' remark was inexcusable.
   ``Rape is never a joke with (women) under any circumstance,''
she said. ``I don't think I know any woman who would say, `Hey, sit
back and enjoy it.'''
   ``He needs a brain transplant,'' reacted Joyce Gersh, chairman
of the Houston-area National Organization for Women, which also has
endorsed Ms. Richards.
   ``Anyone who is not sexist would not have come up with that
remark,'' she said.
   Williams' wife, Modesta, and several Republicans defended him.
   ``If the word rape was in a joke, if sex was in a joke, it was
just a joke,'' she said. ``He's about as much of a gentleman, a
caring person, as there is.''
   ``It's an old joke which we've heard a million times,'' said
State Republican Executive Committee member Virginia Steenson. ``He
certainly couldn't have meant that seriously.''
   Williams won the March 13 GOP primary over three major
challengers, spending more than $6 million of his oil, ranching and
business fortune on the campaign. He has said he owns no shoes,
only cowboy boots, and his campaign TV commercials often featured
him wearing a cowboy hat.
   Williams will face either Ms. Richards or Attorney General Jim
Mattox in the November general election. The two Democrats meet in
a runoff April 10, because unlike Williams, neither one gained a
simple majority in their party's primary.
   Ms. Richards said the remark ``questions his ability to
understand the kinds of problems faced by the people of Texas. Rape
is a crime of violence.''
   ``Just because you're in the barnyard doesn't mean you have to
act like Clayton Williams does,'' Mattox said. ``I just think that
women voters are going to remember his attitude about this.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0066 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 2136EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-AmtrakAccident     03-25 0318</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Amtrak Accident,0329</SECOND>
<HEAD>Train Hits Bumper at Station, More Than Two Dozen Reported Injured</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CHICAGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   At least one person remained hospitalized Sunday
after an Amtrak train crashed into a bumper at the end of a track
at Union Station, sending about 60 people to hospitals, officials
said.
   In another accident involving an Amtrak train, a 20-year-old man
was hit and killed in Philadelphia on Saturday night by a train as
he fled railroad police, authorities said.
   The ``City of New Orleans'' train out of New Orleans was
arriving in Chicago with 254 passengers when the accident happened
around 11:30 a.m. Saturday.
   The train hit the bumper block, derailing eight of 10 cars and
tossing passengers and luggage around, Amtrak spokesman John
Jacobsen said in a telephone interview from Washington, D.C.
   ``It was like someone rear-ended you,'' passenger Jim Hewitt
said Saturday.
   About 60 people were treated at hospitals and released,
officials said.
   Terry Frantz, 44, of New Orleans was in fair condition Sunday at
Northwestern Memorial Hospital. He was under observation after
complaining of shortness of breath and strain to his neck and back,
said hospital spokesman James Henri.
   The cause of the accident wasn't immediately determined.
   Butler said the train was traveling at 3-4 mph when it failed to
stop the normal car length from the station, instead crashing into
the concrete-and-steel bumper post.
   In the Philadelphia accident, Samuel Cohn was hit by the
``Connecticut Yankee,'' which was traveling at an estimated 105
mph, shortly after 8 p.m. Saturday, police said.
   Cohn and a group of friends were on the Amtrak right-of-way and
may have been drinking when Amtrak police arrived at 8 p.m., police
said.
   As Cohn fled, he tried to cross tracks in front of the
Washington-to-Springfield, Mass. train, authorities said.
   The engineer, whose name was withheld, didn't see the man in
time, Jacobsen said. The train was delayed half an hour.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0067 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 2138EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-SocialClubFire 5thLd-Writethru a0753 03-25 0992</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Social Club Fire, 5th Ld-Writethru, a0753,1023</SECOND>
<HEAD>Fire Kills 87 at Unlicensed Social Club; Man Charged</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 26th graf to CORRECT spelling to Ungar sted Unger.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos NY7,8,11,16,19,27; LaserColor NY6,15; LaserGraphic
NY25</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By VERENA DOBNIK</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Fire raced through an illegal social club early
Sunday and turned a packed dance floor into a deathtrap of smoke
and flame that killed 87. A man who allegedly had earlier fought
with a club worker was charged with arson and murder.
   The fire, the nation's worst in 13 years, tore through the Happy
Land club, which authorities said lacked proper exits and other
safeguards.
   The 3:40 a.m. fire killed 61 men and 26 women, most of them
Honduran and Dominican immigrants. Most were found on the second
floor.
   ``People literally were stacked on top of each other,'' said
Anthony De Vita, the Fire Department's command chief. ``It was a
firetrap,'' he said of the two-story building in an impoverished
neighborhood near the Bronx Zoo.
   Some of the victims broke a hole through a wall to an adjoining
hall in a desperate attempt to save their lives, said Red Cross
worker Margaret Glugover.
   Julio Gonzalez, 36, was charged with arson and murder in the
case, said Lt. Raymond O'Donnell, a police spokesman. The district
attorney's office later would determine how many counts Gonzalez
would be charged.
   ``We believe the motive in this case was the result of a dispute
he had with a female employee of the club,'' Police Commissioner
Lee Brown said at a City Hall news conference Sunday evening.
   Gonzalez emigrated in 1980 from Cuba during the Mariel boatlift
that brought 125,000 Cubans to the United States.
   Police said Gonzalez went into the club about 3 a.m. and began
arguing with his former girlfriend, who sold tickets near the
entrance.
   ``He's trying to talk her into making up, she's saying `Leave me
alone,''' O'Donnell said.
   A club bouncer evicted the man half an hour later, and police
alleged he returned and started the fire near the entrance.
   The woman employee left before the fire, Brown said.
   At least two women and one man, believed to be the club's disc
jockey, escaped. The man was seriously burned; the condition of the
women was unknown.
   Most of the dead were believed to have suffocated from the thick
smoke, which billowed hundreds of feet, but some were trampled,
said Lynn Schulman, an Emergency Medical Service spokeswoman.
   ``This is the worst thing I have seen in my career,'' said
Emergency Medical Services specialist Christopher McCarthy. ``It
hurt my stomach. It was sickening.''
   ``Most of the bodies were in dance clothes,'' McCarthy said.
``They were out to have fun. ... I saw wall-to-wall bodies _ an
indication of mass confusion and panic.''
   The fire was the deadliest in the continental United States
since a May 28, 1977, blaze at the Beverly Hills Supper Club in
Southgate, Ky., that killed 164 people. A Dec. 31, 1986, fire at a
hotel in San Juan, Puerto Rico, a U.S. commonwealth, killed 96
people.
   The tragedy occurred in East Tremont, a section of the Bronx
borough. Deputy Mayor Bill Lynch described it as an ``economically
disadvantaged, working-class, Latino neighborhood.''
   The building housed a group that organized children's baseball
as well as adult social events, said Lillian Rivera, a neighbor.
   A makeshift morgue was set up at a hall next door. Authorities
took Polaroid pictures of the bodies and showed them to 200 friends
and relatives at a school across the street where the cries and
wails of relatives could be heard outside. Then, the bodies were
moved to a hospital morgue.
   After viewing the bodies, Mayor David Dinkins called the scene
``graphic and sad.''
   Dinkins said a vacate order was issued in November 1988 because
the club lacked a proper sprinkler system, exits, emergency
lighting and signs.
   City records show the club was again ordered closed on Nov. 1,
1989, by the Buildings Department, Dinkins said.
   ``I don't know what subsequent visits were made there,'' the
mayor said.
   The club had no liquor or cabaret license.
   Two neighborhood residents said three gunshots were heard just
before the fire. Robert Ungar, deputy fire commissioner, said he
could not confirm another report that cans of accelerant were found.
   So-called ``social clubs'' proliferate in New York City's poor
neighborhoods, and despite their name many of them admit virtually
anyone who wants to enter, functioning essentially as unlicensed
taverns or dance clubs.
   New York police officials have estimated that alcohol is sold
without a license at more than 200 locations.
   Authorities said the victims tried to escape the windowless club
down a stairway just wide enough for one person. A second stairway
apparently wasn't used, perhaps because it couldn't be reached from
the club.
   Sixty-nine of the victims died upstairs, where the dance floor
was located.
   ``People were screaming; they were all burned,'' said Rosemary
Green, who found the club on fire when she arrived to meet her
sister-in-law and cousin. ``Once you got in the entrance there was
no way to get out.''
   Denise Garcia, 20, a filing clerk who lives in the neighborhood,
said she and her friends avoided the club because they considered
it ``too sleazy.'' The building was rickety and the dance floor
sometimes trembled, she said.
   Ms. Garcia said the club's patrons included many illegal
immigrants.
   The tragedy occurred on the 79th anniversary of the Triangle
Shirtwaist Co. fire in Manhattan, which killed 145 people, most of
them immigrant garment workers, and led to reforms governing
workplace safety.
   EMS Lt. Roy David said he got to the scene just as the male
survivor was staggering out.
   ``He walked toward me. He couldn't talk. He couldn't say
anything. All we could do was treat him,'' David said.
   Five firefighters, including a battalion chief who broke his
leg, were taken to Jacobi after inhaling smoke. Six other
firefighters were treated at the scene for smoke inhalation.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0068 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 2152EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Fire-Family     03-25 0377</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Fire-Family,0391</SECOND>
<HEAD>Honduran Woman's American Dream Shattered by Club Fire</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Social Club Fire</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RAUL REYES</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two and one-half years ago, Alva Romero left
Honduras full of hope that life would be better in the United
States.
   Her dreams came crashing down Sunday when six members of her
family were killed in a fire at an illegal social club that claimed
a total of 87 lives.
   ``We came here to better ourselves but this is what we get,'' a
grief-stricken Romero said moments after confirming that her two
brothers, a sister, her daughter, a cousin and a niece had perished
in the early morning fire at the Happy Land club.
   It wasn't political upheaval or severe dissatisfaction with
Honduras that brought her here, she said. It was, quite simply,
opportunity.
   ``This is America. We all would have a chance to do better
here,'' she said as she dabbed her eyes. ``Now, I don't know. ...''
   Here, the 34-year-old woman worked in people's homes, helping
the elderly and sick to feed and clothe themselves.
   But on Sunday, it was friends and relatives who helped Romero at
a nearby school, where the bereaved were taken to learn the awful
truth. The brothers were 33 and 21 years old; the sister, daughter
and cousin all were 18; the niece, 17. Her husband had remained in
Honduras.
   ``They had been to the club before and they liked it,'' Romero
said. ``It had been three weeks since they had been there.''
   ``And, last night,'' she said, her voice choking with emotion,
``Last night, they all decided to go back to the club. I don't know
why.''
   Nelson Moll, a Red Cross volunteer, said Romero was one of the
first to show up at the school at about 10 a.m. where photographs
of the dead were displayed.
   When she saw the pictures of her family, Romero slumped forward,
devastated by the news.
   ``She looked at the pictures and she just broke down pretty
bad,'' he said.
   Six hours later, after viewing the photographs and the bodies at
the morgue, a still-shocked Romero passively, almost distantly,
answered reporters' questions.
   Will she stay in the United States?
   ``I don't know. Everything is changed. I don't know.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0069 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 2204EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-EGermany     03-25 0516</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-EGermany,0538</SECOND>
<HEAD>Allegations of Secret Police Links Threaten Coalition Talks</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By NESHA STARCEVIC</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WEST BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Efforts to form the country's first
democratic government faltered Sunday because of mounting charges
of past ties between political leaders and the hated secret police.
   Social Democratic Party leader Ibrahim Boehme, the latest
politician to come under suspicion of having collaborated with the
secret police, called for all coalition talks to be suspended until
the allegations are investigated.
   In its latest issue, the West German newsmagazine Der Spiegel
said two former agents of the police, known as Stasi, had denounced
Boehme as a regular secret collaborator.
   Boehme forcefully denied the charge in a letter to members of
the left-leaning party.
   Lothar de Maiziere, leader of the conservative Christian
Democratic Union that won the nation's first free parliamentary
elections on March 18, is also trying to counter reports he, too,
was a Stasi informer.
   The West German newspaper Cologne Express has said de Maiziere
had the code name ``Scerny'' in the files of the secret police, who
for years enforced the repressive tactics of the hard-line
Communist regime.
   De Maiziere, the front-runner to head the new government, has
denied informing for the police.
   An official in charge of dismantling the Stasi has said many
newly elected lawmakers may have been informers.
   East Germany's chief prosecutor has ruled out an inquiry before
the new parliament is actually seated.
   On Sunday, however, Boehme said talks on a government coalition
between the Social Democrats and the Christian Democrats should not
be held until after an investigation. He said the delay would serve
the ``national interest.''
   The Social Democrats came in second in the elections.
   The West German government is urging the two parties to form a
coalition that would ensure the parliamentary majority in East
Germany needed to speed unification.
   Bonn has said it expects the new 400-member East German
parliament to be seated early next month and to name a premier and
Cabinet soon afterward.
   Preparations for a currency union between the German states are
proceeding quickly and the merger will take effect July 1, the West
German Welt am Sonntag newspaper reported Sunday.
   The monetary union, a major step toward full Germany unity,
would replace East Germany's noncovertible currency with West
Germany's powerful mark.
   The newspaper also published a timetable under which East
Germany would assume West Germany's pension system and unemployment
benefits by Sept. 1.
   The paper said the timetable was worked out during talks in Bonn
earlier this month involving West German Chancellor Helmut Kohl and
Finance Minister Theo Waigel, and leaders of East Germany's
Alliance for Germany. The alliance is a three-party group that ran
as a coalition in the elections. It includes the Christian
Democrats.
   Waigel told Welt am Sonntag that East German savers will be able
to change their marks for West German marks at a 1-1 rate ``up to a
certain limit.'' He gave no details.
   The finance minister also said West Germany will assume East
Germany's foreign debt, but the size of the debt was unclear,
according to the newspaper.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0070 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 2218EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a BC-BoatSinking-List     03-25 0229</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Boat Sinking-List,0261</SECOND>
<HEAD>With Boat Sinking</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Names Alaimo and Wallage are cq.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>SEATTLE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here is a list of those missing and presumed
drowned in the sinking of the trawler Aleutian Enterprise on Friday
in the Bering Sea, followed by a list of survivors. The information
was released by the ship's owners, Aleutian Enterprise Ltd.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>MISSING</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   John A. Dieterich, 31, Seattle, chief engineer.
   Nello Marciel, 55, San Diego, mate.
   Matthew J. Schneider, 22, Issaquah, Wash., foreman.
   Robert McCord, 35, Englewood, Colo., fisheries observer.
   Joseph J. Alaimo, 45, Yakima, Wash.
   Robert W. Davis, 26, Renton, Wash.
   Jeffrey A. Houston, 21, Warren, Ore.
   Javier Martin V. Castro, 27, Seattle.
   David J. Jeffries, 19, Fontana, Calif.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>SURVIVORS</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   
   Derek Birdsall, 20, Issaquah, Wash.
   Russel Clifford, 27, Sumner, Wash.
   Michael Evans, 25, Seattle.
   Duane Gallagher, 33, North Bend, Wash.
   Tim Gruenke, 24, Issaquah, Wash.
   John Hobbs, 23, Federal Way, Wash.
   Scott Melton, 22, Kirkland, Wash.
   Todd Mitchell, 20, Seattle.
   Ronald Moe, 22, Issaquah, Wash.
   Walter Meyer, 18, San Diego.
   Harvey Philpot, 20, Hoquiam, Wash.
   Todd Phinney, 21, Issaquah, Wash.
   Matt Price, 19, Aberdeen, Wash.
   Dan Rapalee, 20, Kent, Wash.
   Derrik Santy, 18, Seattle.
   James Savelli, 26, Richland, Wash.
   Gene Schultz, 23, Bellevue, Wash.
   Mark Siemons, 28, Renton, Wash., captain.
   Timothy Thompson, 27, Seattle.
   Armando Valencia, 28, Mercer Island, Wash.
   Brian Wallage, 21, Davis, Calif.
   Douglas Wilcox, 26, Renton, Wash.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0071 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 2237EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-DeltaLaunch     03-25 0178</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Delta Launch,0183</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rocket Launched On Third Attempt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CAPE CANAVERAL, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Air Force on Sunday night
launched a Delta 2 rocket carrying a $65 million navigation
satellite after two earlier postponements, a spokeswoman said.
   The rocket had been scheduled for liftoff Tuesday night, and
that was postponed to Wednesday night. Strong upper-atmosphere
winds forced a second delay.
   The launch at 9:45 p.m. EST was without incident.
   ``Everything looks real good,'' Sgt. Ivey Paige said.
   The satellite separated from the rocket's third stage as planned
and was in a preliminary, relatively low orbit. It was expected to
reach its final orbit in a few days, said Ken Warren, a NASA
spokesman.
   The payload is the seventh in a series of advanced Navstar
satellites launched in the past year from Cape Canaveral. The
navigation system is designed to provide the United States and
allied land, sea and air forces with worldwide three-dimensional
position and velocity information.
   By 1992, the Air Force plans to have 21 of the spacecraft
orbiting the Earth to form a global network.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0072 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 2240EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BoatSinking 1stLd-Writethru a0703 03-25 0824</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Boat Sinking, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0703,0846</SECOND>
<HEAD>Survivors: Fishing Boat Alarm Failed Before Capsizing in Bering
Sea</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: INSERTS 1 graf after 2nd graf to UPDATE with crewmen saying
they'd been given little instruction on using survival suits;
INSERTS 7 grafs after 10th graf, ```The information ...,' to UPDATE
with comments; picks up 11th graf, `The Aleutian ...' DELETES
now-redundant grafs 18-19, `Stevenson said ...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By HAL SPENCER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ANCHORAGE, Alaska (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Survivors of a vessel that listed and
quickly sank in the icy Bering Sea say an alarm failed to sound and
may have cost some of the nine missing crewmen their lives, an
investigator said Sunday.
   ``At least two of the crew I interviewed said they felt that the
delay didn't allow people to search for survival gear or to get to
the deck'' before the fish-processing ship Aleutian Enterprise
rolled and sank within minutes of listing to port Thursday, said
Alaska State Trooper Robert Stevenson.
   Two crew members said they'd been given little or no instruction
in using flotation suits designed to protect against the arctic
waters.
   Stevenson, stationed at Dutch Harbor about 800 miles southwest
of Anchorage, said several survivors told him the alarm system had
not worked for months. Stevenson interviewed 21 of the 22 survivors.
   The nine people from the Seattle-based trawler are missing and
presumed drowned.
   Dan Roberts, executive vice president of Arctic Alaska Fisheries
Corp., the company that operates the vessel, said Saturday he
didn't know why the alarm might have failed to sound or have been
inoperable. Company officials did not return telephone messages
left Sunday with a secretary.
   ``I just went on instinct. The people all around me were
screaming, `Help me! Help me!,'' crewman Derrik Santy told the
Anchorage Daily News Saturday as he waited in line at Anchorage
International Airport for a ticket home to Seattle.
   Santy said he was below deck when the ship began to roll in calm
seas about 60 miles south of Saint Paul Island on Thursday
afternoon. Scrambling to the deck, Santy jumped into the water and
``grabbed anything that floated.''
   He said he was in the water with the other 21 survivors for
about 10 minutes when they were picked up a sister ship, the
Pacific Enterprise.
   Stevenson said ships are supposed to be equipped with general
alarms, some of which sound automatically when the vessel lists too
far. The alarm also can be sounded manually from the wheelhouse, he
said.
   ``The information we have is it just didn't work and hasn't
worked for some time,'' Stevenson said.
   Santy, 18, of Seattle said Sunday that he received little
instruction on using flotation suits.
   ``The only thing they told me about survival suits was they're
in these lockers and that's all,'' he said in an interview with
Seattle television station KING.
   In reply to a question, he said he didn't know how to put the
suits on. ``Shoot, I never saw one before.''
   Crew member Matt Price, 19, of Aberdeen, Wash., said he searched
a locker for a survival suit, but didn't have time to get one.
   ``That was my first time being on a boat and they should have
explained the procedure if it was going to sink,'' Price said.
``They never did that.''
   Stevenson said none of the crew members managed to don survival
suits.
   He said water temperatures in the Bering Sea are in the low 30s
and people die of shock in such cold water ``fairly quickly.''
   The Aleutian Enterprise, a 162-foot, 195-ton cod fishing and
processing factory trawler, sank about 250 miles northwest of Dutch
Harbor.
   The ship, owned by a group of California investors, was operated
by Arctic Alaska. The company operates 22 other vessels, the
largest trawler fleet in the Bering Sea.
   Stevenson said survivors told him some crewmen were pulling in a
netload of fish when the vessel started listing to port. The
skipper, Mark Siemons, slackened the line and, gave full power to
the starboard engine and took other actions in an attempt to right
the 195-ton vessel, Stevenson said.
   ``It didn't work. It continued to list and then capsized. It
sank within five minutes of capsizing,'' he said.
   He said survivors told him a handful of crewmen were off duty
and sleeping below deck when the trawler began to list, and some
were roused by other crew members and the commotion.
   The skipper, meanwhile, managed to radio a sister ship for help.
   Some survivors scrambled into two lifeboats and others clung to
floatation devices or debris until another trawler arrived 15 or 20
minutes later, Stevenson said.
   Coast Guard spokesman Greg Robinson said investigators
interviewed 10 crew members as they arrived at Anchorage
International Airport from Dutch Harbor. National Transportation
Safety Board investigators and lawyers representing the vessel's
owners also participated in the closed interviews, he said.
   The ship had set out from Dutch Harbor on March 2 and was to
have returned Friday.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0073 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 2240EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Brazil-Indians     03-25 0340</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brazil-Indians,0351</SECOND>
<HEAD>Brazil's President Orders Airstrips Dynamited to Keep Off Miners</HEAD>
<DATELINE>RIO DE JANEIRO, Brazil (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Fernando Collor de Mello
ordered the destruction of about 100 clandestine Amazon jungle
airstrips to keep thousands of gold miners from returning to land
reserved for Indians.
   ``Dynamite them, and be fast about it,'' the new president told
federal police chief Romeu Tuma on Saturday while visiting Roraima
state in the northwest Amazon.
   During the trip, his first since taking office March 15, Collor
also visited an Indian village and flew over mining camps ordered
shut by former President Jose Sarney.
   The order to destroy the airstrips was given to keep an
estimated 40,000 miners from returning to lands owned by the
Yanomami Indians, the world's largest remaining primitive tribe.
   Last week, the government reported the end of an 80-day
operation to force miners off Indian lands and onto three mining
reserves. However, Roman Catholic Church officials say some miners
still remain on Yanomami territory.
   Collor promised ``a solution without conflicts'' when about 500
people greeted him at the airport in Boa Vista, the Roraima state
capital, 3,682 miles northwest of Rio de Janeiro.
   ``We must respect, without a doubt, our brother Indians, but we
must also respect those who take from the land what is necessary to
kill their hunger,'' the president said.
   The invasion of Yanomami lands by the miners began three years
ago, when it was discovered the Indians lived on reserves rich in
minerals, especially gold and diamonds.
   The miners have scared away fish and game, polluted rivers and
streams and also brought diseases previously unknown to the
Yanomami.
   Since 1987, the tribe's numbers have fallen from about 9,000 to
7,500 because of malnutrition, venereal diseases and malaria.
Others have died in armed conflicts with miners.
   The government has steadily carved up Indian lands, reducing the
Yanomami to territories totaling 5 million acres on 19 scattered
reservations. The tribe once claimed 23 million acres of the Amazon
forest along Brazil's northern border with Venezuela, Guyana and
Colombia.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0074 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 2245EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Oscars-Eddies     03-25 0141</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Oscars-Eddies,0148</SECOND>
<HEAD>`Glory' And `Roger &amp; Me' Editors Win Awards</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Editors for the movies ``Glory'' and ``Roger
&amp; Me'' were among the winners at the 40th annual Eddie Awards of
the American Cinema Editors.
   Other winners at the awards dinner Saturday night were editors
for ``War and Remembrance, Part 10,'' for ABC-TV in the television
miniseries category and ``In the Heat of the Night'' for NBC in the
television series category.
   Here are the winners:
   Feature Film: ``Glory,'' Steven Rosenblum.
   Documentary: ``Roger &amp; Me,'' Wendy Stanzler and Jennifer Beman.
   Television Special: ``Howard Beach: Making the Case for
Murder,'' Byron ``Buzz'' Brandt, NBC.
   Television Miniseries Episode: ``War &amp; Remembrance, Part 10,''
Peter Zinner and John Burnett, ABC.
   Television Series Episode: ``In the Heat of the Night: These
Things Take Time,'' Buford ``Bud'' Hayes and Victor Lackey, NBC.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0075 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 2302EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Bush-Ford'sTheatre     03-25 0417</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bush-Ford's Theatre,400</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush Attends Fund-Raising Gala</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: puppeteer in 2nd graf uses no first name</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By CHRISTOPHER CONNELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush sat through nearly three hours
of entertainment in historic Ford's Theatre Sunday night and
afterwards quipped that Abraham Lincoln ``would have really enjoyed
this program _ parts of it.''
   The show was an annual fund-raising gala for Ford's Theatre, and
the talent ranged from scat singer Diane Schuur to dancing
puppeteer Christopher to the Gatlin Brothers to Tony Bennett to
comic Jim Morris, who did a wicked imitation of both Bush and his
predecessor, Ronald Reagan.
   The show, ``A Festival at Ford's,'' will be televised on Ted
Turner's Broadcasting System on the night of July 4.
   This April 14 is the 125th anniversary of the night when
Lincoln, the 16th president, was assassinated by John Wilkes Booth
in the presidential box at Ford's Theatre.
   Bush, an avid theater-goer himself, recalled that Lincoln loved
to go to the theater. The night that Booth struck was Lincoln's
tenth visit to Ford's.
   ``He loved entertainment. ... and I believe he would have really
enjoyed this program _ parts of it,'' said Bush, to laughter and
applause from the audience of more than 500.
   The theater, closed after the assassination, remained dark for
103 years until it was restored by Congress and the National Park
Service in 1968 as both a museum and a living theater.
   Rep. Sidney Yates, D-Ill., received the Lincoln Medal from the
theater's trustees for his advocacy of the arts. Frankie Hewitt,
the theater's executive director, said that in recent years, amid
congressional efforts to censor National Endowment for the Arts
grants, Yates had ``quite literally protected the integrity of the
arts for all Americans.''
   Yates, who last week survived a tough primary fight, drew
applause in turn when he applauded Bush ``for the great statement
you made ... in support of the arts.''
   Bush last Friday said he opposes attempts to write into law
anti-pornography restrictions on NEA grants.
   ``I am deeply offended by some of the filth that I see and to
which federal money has gone and some of the sacrilegious,
blasphemous depictions that are portrayed by some to be art,'' Bush
said.
   But he said he prefers to let his new NEA director, John
Frohnmayer, use his discretion rather ``than risk censorship of
getting the federal government into telling every artist what he or
she can paint, or how he or she might express themselves.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0076 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 1450EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-TahoeTourism Bjt   03-25 0541</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Tahoe Tourism, Bjt,0559</SECOND>
<HEAD>Officials Hope Spring, New Hotels Offset Sluggish Winter</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LAURA MYERS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>RENO, Nev. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Unpredictable weather, redevelopment and shaky
attempts to reach new markets added up to a bad winter for the Lake
Tahoe resort in California and Nevada, tourism officials said.
   But officials are optimistic the economy has bottomed out and
that new hotel development at pristine Sierra Lake and possible
events such as the Miss USA Pageant will help Tahoe rebound.
   The number of rooms booked on the California side of the popular
resort fell 8.22 percent in July-December 1989 compared with the
same period in 1988. For January, the figure was 17.6 percent below
January 1988.
   Room tax collections on the California side, which relies on ski
resorts to lure winter tourists, dropped 2.3 percent to $2.9
million in the last half of 1989 compared with the same period a
year earlier.
   The casino-lined Nevada side of the lake showed a 1 percent
increase in room taxes in the same period. Improvement in January
pushed the rise to 2 percent for the seven-month period.
   ``Things were pretty bad this winter,'' Kathleen Farrell,
executive director of the Tahoe-Douglas Chamber of Commerce, said
Friday. ``The lack of snow hurt us and a controversy over how to
market the area exists about whether to go after skiers in the
winter or not and where to advertise.''
   Ski resorts peppered the Dallas-Fort Worth market with ads this
winter to attract visitors who usually go to Colorado slopes, but a
lack of significant snow kept Texans away.
   When storms did hit they typically came on Fridays, causing many
drive-up tourist from northern California to stay home.
   ``The last time I saw such bad timing of storms was six years
ago,'' Ms. Farrell said. ``We'd look out the window and say, `It's
storming. It must be Friday.' That's how it was this winter.''
   In May, the Tahoe tourism authority plans to launch a $320,000
advertising campaign to run through September in Los Angeles to
attract summer visitors to the lake and, with hope, make up for the
poor winter.
   Negotiations are continuing to bring the 1991 Miss USA Pageant
to Reno-Tahoe in February or March.
   ``I think that in the past two months we've already started to
turn the situation around and so things aren't as alarming as they
appear to be,'' said Barbara Klein, executive director of the Lake
Tahoe Visitors Authority at South Lake Tahoe, Calif.
   Ms. Klein said ground will be broken in April and May for two
new hotel projects at South Lake Tahoe, bordering the Stateline,
Nev., casino row that sits above the lake about 35 miles southwest
of Reno.
   About 900 old motel rooms in the city were torn down to allow
construction of a 400-room Embassy Suites hotel and a 320-room
still-unnamed hotel.
   Tahoe tourism authorities also have hired people to greet
passengers flying into the Reno Cannon International Airport and
are putting together mini-vacation packages to lure visitors to
stay longer than a weekend.
   An estimated 2.5 million to 3 million people visit Lake Tahoe
each year with many staying overnight in one of the 11,000 hotel
and motel rooms around the 72-mile shoreline, Ms. Klein said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0077 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 1503EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-Britain-Inflation     03-25 0167</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Britain-Inflation,0176</SECOND>
<HEAD>Treasury Chief Expects Inflation, Interest Rates To Decline</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Britain's top treasury official said Sunday he
expects the nation's 7.7 percent inflation rate and 15 percent
interest rates to be ``materially lower'' by 1991.
   ``In due course, it would be very nice to get inflation down to
nil but inflation doesn't suddenly come down to nil and stay there
forever,'' Chancellor of the Exchequer John Major said.
   Major said in a British Broadcasting Corp. television interview
that inflation and interest rates ``will be materially lower at the
beginning of next year, at the middle of next year, at the end of
next year and in 1992.''
   Britain's inflation rate has sat at 7.7 percent, despite the
government's high interest-rate policy, and economists predict it
could climb as high as 9 percent.
   Major, the treasury's top official, said in his budgetary
statement earlier this month that inflation is worse in Britain
than in other countries because of heavy borrowing and strong
consumer spending.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0078 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 1538EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-HotelStrike 1stLd-Writethru f0014 03-25 0645</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Hotel Strike, 1st Ld-Writethru, f0014,0664</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tentative Agreement Reached in Hawaii Hotel Workers Strike</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 16 grafs to UPDATE with terms of agreement,
comment; Edits to conform; PICKS UP 15th graf pvs, `The strike...;
A version containing some of material moved on general news wires
for Sunday AMs</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By BEN DIPIETRO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HONOLULU (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Workers at 11 Hawaii hotels achieved a goal of
parity with mainland workers under a tentative agreement ending a
month-long strike that left some hotel guests making their own
beds, labor leaders said.
   The deal between Local 5 of the Hotel Employees and Restaurant
Employees and the Council of Hawaii Hotels would give workers an
average pay increase of 10 percent a year.
   The strike affected about one-fourth of the 37,000 hotel rooms
in Waikiki, the state's tourist capital, and about one-seventh of
the state's total number of hotel rooms.
   ``As is the case with all contracts, we didn't get everything we
want, but we did (satisfy) our needs,'' union leader Tony Rutledge
said after the agreement was announced Saturday.
   Nearly 80 percent of workers will be earning nearly as much
money as hotel workers in San Francisco by the time the contract
expires in 1994, Rutledge said, meeting one of the union's main
goals.
   The walkout by 7,500 maids, bellhops, clerks, restaurant and bar
workers and others left some hotel guests doing without room
service and making their own beds as managers struggled to fill the
gaps. Some of the affected hotels offered discounts of up to 20
percent.
   The tentative accord, reached after an all-night bargaining
session, was announced by union and management representatives,
Gov. John Waihee and federal mediator Frank Schoeppel.
   ``This will give stability to the industry for the next five
years,'' said William Crawford, executive director of the
management council and chief negotiator for the hotels.
   The union achieved its main goal of bringing pay in line with
that of mainland hotel workers, union spokesman Roderick Rodriguez
said.
   Union members were to meet Sunday to discuss the settlement and
procedures for ratification. But members were told they didn't need
to wait for formal ratification and could return to work as soon as
their hotels called for them to come in.
   Under the agreement, wages and benefits for non-tipped workers
will increase 7 percent this year and 6 percent each of the next
four years. Tipped workers will get raises totaling 85 cents an
hour over the life of the contract.
   Workers also will get an increase of 99 cents an hour in health
and other benefits to bring the total to $2.29 an hour.
   The union failed to win a 5 percent room surcharge or a 15
percent food and beverage surcharge that would have been divided
among workers, two issues it had labeled critical for a settlement.
   Rutledge said the tentative agreement would add about 40 cents
per hour across the board to the one approved at another Hawaiian
hotel. The union had been seeking increases of about 10 percent a
year for three years.
   Salaries under the old contract range from an average of $3.85
an hour for bellhops to an average of $11.04 an hour for cooks.
   Waihee intervened out of concern for the state's
$6-billion-a-year tourist industry.
   The strike, which began Feb. 24, affected eight hotels on Oahu
and three on the neighbor islands.
   The affected hotels on Oahu were the Hilton Hawaiian Village,
2,523 rooms; Sheraton Waikiki, 1,900 rooms; Hyatt Regency Waikiki,
1,250 rooms; Princess Kalulani, 1,150 rooms; Ilikai Hotel, 800
rooms; Sheraton Moana Surfrider, 793 rooms; Royal Hawaiian, 525
rooms; and Kahala Hilton, 369 rooms.
   Neighbor island hotels affected are the Sharaton Maui, 495
rooms; Sheraton Kauai, 456 rooms; and Kona Hilton, 445 rooms. In
addition, two other hotels, the Turtle Bay Hilton and Royal
Waikoloan, agreed to abide by terms of the settlement.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0079 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 1605EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-MeagerWages 1stLd-Writethru f0002 03-25 0979</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Meager Wages, 1st Ld-Writethru, f0002,1004</SECOND>
<HEAD>St. Joseph Families Await the Minimum Wage Hike</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 2nd graf pvs, `But a...' and 6th graf pvs, `Her
employer..., to CORRECT verb agreement; PICKS UP 7th graf pvs, `I
know...; Also moved on general news wires</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By KAREN BALL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Labor Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ST. JOSEPH, Mo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A sign outside this red bricked town
along the Missouri River proudly proclaims it's the place where the
Pony Express began and Jesse James ended.
   But empty warehouses, vacant storefronts and quiet rail yards
are grim reminders that the glory days for St. Joseph, like many
towns in the manufacturing Midwest, are long past.
   For residents with few skills, the only jobs around are those
paying minimum wage or just above. Hundreds of high paying jobs
vanished when meat packing plants closed and the farm crisis set in.
   Those scraping by at the bottom of the wage scale have been
looking forward to April 1, when the minimum wage goes up 45 cents
an hour, from $3.35 to $3.80. It's the first such hike for the
working poor since 1981.
   ``It doesn't sound like much, really, but it would help us
out,'' said Diane Fanning, who supports an 8-year-old daughter on a
$4.10-an-hour job making beds and doing other chores at a nursing
home.
   Her employer, like businesses across the country that pay above
$3.80 an hour, is faced with the dilemma of whether to provide
raises to rival the hike in the minimum wage.
   ``I know how to stretch a penny; I have to. But there's not much
money to do anything right now, not for the extras, anyway. It
would let us maybe go do something once in a while,'' Fanning said
of a 45-cent raise that would translate into about $18 more a week.
She now takes home around $140 a week, she said.
   Under the measure passed by Congress last year, the 4 million
Americans who make the minimum wage will see the hourly rate go to
$4.25 on April 1, 1991. It also establishes a ``training wage'' for
teen-agers first entering the work force, which will be $3.35 an
hour this year and $3.61 an hour in 1991.
   Had the minimum wage kept pace with inflation since 1981, it
would have been $4.59 an hour in 1989 and $5.28 an hour by 1992,
supporters said.
   ``I've been waiting on this for a long time,'' said Tim
Turrieta, another nurse's aide at the Carriage Square Health Care
Center. ``Our wages have been holding steady, but the economy's
been running away. It's only fair that we get something.''
   ``It's going to let you buy that pair of shoes you've been
looking at but haven't been able to afford,'' Turrieta said.
   But to others, the increase is so long overdue it won't have
much impact. Low-wage workers also fear bigger paychecks might
translate into higher grocery and clothing prices.
   ``After they raise it to where a man can start to make it, I'm
afraid the economy and the price of everything else will just take
off too,'' said Greg Fairchild, who helps support four children on
a $3.60-an-hour cook's job at Burger King. Without his wife's
$865-a-month take home pay as a psychiatric aide, his family
wouldn't make it, he said.
   Though St. Joseph's downtown business district has suffered in
recent years, its three-mile strip of fast food and retail
establishments _ known as the Belt _ has continued to grow.
   The good paying jobs in St. Joseph, a town of 76,000 located 50
miles north of Kansas City, are at the lone meat packing plant left
in town, a wire rope manufacturer, the Mead paper plant and Quaker
Oats.
   ``Being in the heart of the farm belt, we suffered with the
agriculture crisis, but things have improved significantly,'' said
Alan Kenyon, president of the area's Chamber of Commerce.
   He noted that a pet food firm is opening a test facility soon
and that more than 30 stores have just been added to the expanded
shopping mall at the edge of town. Unemployment posted a relatively
low 5.5 percent rate last year, the same level as the entire state.
One county in southeast Missouri suffered a 15 percent jobless rate.
   Merchants here paying low wages don't think workers will get
much benefit from a few more nickels an hour.
   ``The dollars just pass from one hand to another. Who's really
gained from all of it?'' said Clara Lash, who runs the 120-bed
facility where Fanning and Turrieta work.
   Nina Casey, who owns the Sav-On Unclaimed Merchandise and
Furniture store out on the Belt, said the increase won't hurt her
profit margin.
   ``It's no skin off our nose, because we'll just raise the prices
to match it,'' Casey said. ``Your bottom line has to stay the same.
Any third-grader can tell you that. So how does their (minimum wage
workers') purchasing power increase any?''
   She contends nearly all of those workers at the tail end of the
wage scale are using the job as a second income.
   ``No one's making a living off the minimum wage. They can't make
a living at $4 an hour either,'' Ms. Casey said.
   Lash said her ability to pay matching 45-cent raises will depend
on whether Medicaid increases its reimbursement rates.
   ``I can't make promises to my staff that they're going to get
the ripple effect,'' she said. ``I'd love to give it to them.
They're doing a job here that nobody else wants to do.''
   Larry Huston, president of the AFL-CIO's northwest Missouri
region, said the minimum wage will still be too low.
   ``Everybody deserves a livable wage. I wouldn't call $3.35 an
hour that _ or $3.80, for that matter,'' Huston said. ``I don't
know how in the world people get by on that, God bless 'em. They
must be better skimpers than me.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
</Collection>
