<Collection>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900805-0001 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-05-90 2330EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-US-Iraq 8thLd-Writethru a0787 08-05 0882</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-US-Iraq, 8th Ld-Writethru, a0787, 2 Takes, 760-1,350</SECOND>
<HEAD>Agitated President Bush Says Iraqi Aggression `Will Not Stand'</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: Inserts grafs 7-9, ``The Washington xxx with report of
destablization planning</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By TERENCE HUNT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP White House Correspondent</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush said Sunday that Iraq ``lied
once again'' and reneged on its pledge to pull its invading forces
out of Kuwait. Angry and forceful, the president again condemned
Iraq's aggression and said, ``This will not stand.''
   Bush dispatched Secretary Dick Cheney to Saudi Arabia to confer
with leaders of the desert kingdom, administration sources said.
   Bush conferred Sunday evening for 1{ hours at the White House
with his top civilian and military advisers, including Secretary of
State James A. Baker III and Gen. Colin Powell, chairman of the
Joint Chiefs of Staff.
   ``They reviewed the situation in the Gulf,'' said White House
spokesman Doug Davidson. He would not elaborate.
   Bush turned aside reporters' questions about whether Turkey or
Saudi Arabia would shut off pipelines critical to Iraq's oil
distribution, and he refused to discuss any military action the
United States might be planning.
   ``I'm not going to discuss what we're doing in terms of moving
of forces, anything of that nature,'' he said.
   The Washington Post reported in its Monday editions that the
U.S. contingency planning includes planning to destabilize and
eventually topple Saddam from power.
   The account, attributed to unidentified sources, said it could
not be learned what timetable Bush has set for making decisions
about how to implement such a campaign.
   ``We don't comment on options or intelligence matters,'' said
Davidson in response to the account.
   Bush said he would meet Monday at the White House with NATO
Secretary-General Manfred Woerner and British Prime Minister
Margaret Thatcher, on her way home from Aspen, Colo.
   Speaking on condition of anonymity, an administration source
said it hadn't been determined whether Cheney will visit only
Ryadh, the Saudi capital, or other Mideast nations as well.
   Bush praised Japan's decision to join an international boycott
of oil from Iraq and Kuwait, and said he planned to speak again
with Turkish President Turgut Ozal as part of the ``intensive
diplomatic activity around the world.''
   He said he had offered Kuwait's emir, now in exile, ``certain
assurances'' in a telephone conversation on Saturday.
   Bush said his goal is to isolate Iraqi leader Saddam Hussein.
The United States swiftly imposed an economic boycott on Iraq after
its lightning invasion of Kuwait last Wednesday, and Bush has spent
much of his time since then urging other nations to join in
pressuring Baghdad economically.
   ``These are outlaws, international outlaws and renegades,'' he
said of the Iraqi leadership.
   ``There seems to be a united front out there that says Iraq,
having committed brutal, naked aggression, ought to get out and
this concept of their installing some puppet leaving behind will
not (be) acceptable,'' the president said.
   Bush was clearly agitated, cutting short reporters' questions at
times and speaking in terse sentences. He ended the impromptu news
conference with these words:
   ``This will not stand,'' he said. ``This will not stand, this
aggression against Kuwait.''
   Bush said he considered his options ``wide open.'' He was asked
whether Turkey and Saudi Arabia would shut off the oil pipelines
that provide a critical outlet for Iraqi's oil.
   ``There is a strong feeling on the part of the NATO countries to
whom I've talked, Turkey being one of them, that we must have
concerted action to isolate Iraq economically and you can just
assume from there that those matters are being considered,'' he
said.
   Bush said the Iraqis had not pulled back their invading forces,
as they promised Friday they would. The Iraqis ``lied once again.
They said they were going to start moving out today and there is no
evidence they're moving out,'' he said.
   ``I want to see the Arab states join the rest of the world in
condemning this outrage and doing what they can to get Saddam
Hussein out,'' said Bush.
   Asked about Jordan King Hussein's defense of the Iraqi ruler,
Bush said, ``I am disappointed to find any comment by anyone that
apologizes or appears to condone what's taken place.''
   Jordan's monarch said Saturday that other Arab states were
``premature'' in condemning the Iraqi invasion. He called Iraq's
ruler ``a patriotic man who believes in his nation and its future
and in establishing ties with others on the basis of mutual
respect.''
   Arab leaders have warned against foreign intervention, but an
emergency Arab League summit to discuss the crisis initially
planned for Sunday in Saudi Arabia was postponed.
   Bush said an Arab leader ``that I respect enormously' told him
Friday ``they needed 48 hours to find what they called an Arab
solution. That obviously has failed. ... Of course I'm
disappointed.''
   Jordan's prime minister, Mudar Badran, said his natin will not
recognize the new government because that would hinder Arab efforts
to end the conflict.
   Asked how he would prevent the Iraqis from installing its new
government, Bush snapped, ``Just wait. Watch and learn.''
   He also said the Iraqi-installed government in Kuwait would gain
little recognition internationally.
   ``There is no intention on the part of any of these countries to
accept a puppet government. And that signal is going out loud and
clear to Iraq,'' he said.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900805-0002 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-05-90 2336EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-BargeSpill 1stLd-Writethru a0789 08-05 0568</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Barge Spill, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0789,0579</SECOND>
<HEAD>Outbound Traffic Moves from Poert for 1st Time Since Spill</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 10 grafs to UPDATE with two-way port traffic
reopened, number of ships moving; PICKS UP 6th graf pvs, `At a
...'; DELETES redundant or outdated grafs 13-14 bgng `The ship ...'</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto HT5</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SUSAN FAHLGREN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BEACH CITY, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Contractors sprayed oil-eating bacteria
on marshes Sunday while crews vacuumed up heavy sludge that drifted
northward from a spill of up to 700,000 gallons of oil.
   Ships were allowed to leave the harbor for the first time in
more than a week.
   Coast Guard Capt. Thomas Greene said wind pushed a slick of oil
surrounding Houston Point and its sensitive marshes back into
Galveston Bay on Sunday. Some of the oil washed ashore, while
streamers of up to 100 yards in length moved northeast toward
Trinity Bay, a marine area.
   Approximately 315,000 gallons of the refinery oil from the
barge-tanker collision had been collected by Sunday afternoon,
Greene said.
   About 150 contract workers and 90 Coast Guardsmen were working
on the cleanup, which will cost about $5 million, Greene said.
   The oil was spilled July 28 when the Greek tanker Shinoussa
collided with two barges under tow by the Chandy N in the Houston
Ship Channel.
   ``Traffic is moving, just not freely,'' said Scott Inbody, chief
warrant officer of the Coast Guard's vessel traffic service in
Houston. ``We're making sure no vessels meet or overtake each other
in the waters near the accident.''
   The ship channel was opened to inbound towboat traffic Friday.
It had been closed since the accident while the Coast Guard worked
to free the barge that had partially sunk in the collision.
   The Coast Guard hoped to open the channel to unrestricted
two-way traffic by Monday, Inbody said.
   ``We have outbound ships and inbound towboats, pulling or
pushing barges, moving right now,'' he said. About 40 vessels were
waiting to get into the channel and 10 were waiting to leave late
Sunday, the Coast Guard said.
   At a hearing on collision Sunday, Shinoussa crewmen blamed the
Houston pilot who guided them through the channel for bad
directions. The pilot contends the helmsman failed to follow
instructions and steered into the oncoming barges after another
ship passed.
   State officials planned to spread about 150 pounds of the
bacteria around Houston Point and its marshes Sunday. The microbes,
which occur naturally in small amounts, are bred to reduce oil to a
fatty substance that sinks and can be eaten by fish.
   When the oil is gone, the microbes die. The process is called
bioremediation.
   ``We've got oil about 30 feet into the marshlands,'' Texas Water
Commission chairman B.J. ``Buck'' Wynne said Sunday. ``We're trying
to do as much as we can today.''
   Wynne said bacteria used on Pelican Island last week seems to
have been beneficial, but tests have not been completed.
   ``This is different from oil on rocks or oil in open waters,''
Wynne said. ``This is on a living, organic system and it's
absolutely the most sensitive place it can be.''
   Dead crabs, mussels and other small marine animals have been
found on the shore around Houston Point, said Larry McKinney,
director of the resource protection division of the Texas Parks and
Wildlife Department.
   A ban on shrimping in Galveston Bay continued Sunday, but fin
fishing remained open.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900805-0003 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-05-90 2345EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Liberia-War 1stLd-Writethru a0768 08-05 0616</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Liberia-War, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0768,0631</SECOND>
<HEAD>Liberians Hope U.S. Marines Will Land and End Civil War</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS one graf for 4th `The Marines...' to UPDATE with 74 sted
59 people lifted out; pickup graf 5 `The United...'</NOTE>
<HEAD>With AM-US-Liberia, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MICHELLE FAUL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ABIDJAN, Ivory Coast (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Liberians have long hoped that the
hundreds of U.S. Marines who swooped into Monrovia on Sunday to
rescue Americans and shore up Embassy defenses would also help end
their civil war.
   Besieged President Samuel Doe, Liberia's Council of Churches and
rebel leader Prince Johnson all have called on the United States to
use force to help end the conflict. A total of 5,000 people, mostly
civilians, have been killed.
   Johnson's threat Saturday to start detaining foreigners in the
hope of provoking foreign intervention brought the order to
dispatch the Marines to Monrovia.
   The Marines returned to their ships with 62 Americans and 12
people from other countries, leaving behind a group of soldiers to
shore up Embassy defenses.
   The United States has insisted it will not intervene to end the
7-month-long war, but many Liberians have hoped for more.
   When the warships carrying the Marines first arrived off the
Liberian coast two months ago, people danced in the streets of the
capital singing of how the soldiers would save them.
   But the Marines remained offshore and last week Johnson asked
reporters, ``Why does the United States not come to the aid of
Liberia, which looks on America as its motherland?'' His puzzlement
is shared by many people in this West African nation that was
founded by freed American slaves in 1847.
   Johnson said he appealed last week to the U.S. Embassy for
American help to stop the killing of civilians but was told that
the crisis was an ``internal conflict.''
   ``As though the United States had never interfered in the
affairs of other people like those of Grenada, the Philippines or
Panama?'' Johnson argued.
   Appeals for U.S. intervention mounted after early hopes that the
men of rival rebel leader Charles Taylor would quickly take
Monrovia were dashed.
   Doe remains inside his presidential mansion, protected by
loyalist troops, while Johnson and Taylor's forces, once united,
have clashed with each other as the siege of Monrovia continues.
   In June, thousands of peace marchers led by Christian and Moslem
leaders ignored death threats from Doe and demanded U.S.
intervention.
   ``We are appealing to the Congress, to the government and to the
people of the United States of America to come to our aid. This is
an SOS call. Save our souls,'' appealed one of the leaders, Bishop
W. Nah Dixon, when marchers stopped outside the U.S. Embassy.
   Hundreds of the protesters, waving banners reading ``Stop the
Killings,'' came from a refugee center set up at St. Peter's
Lutheran Church. On July 30, Doe's soldiers massacred more than 600
people who sought refuge at that church.
   Many Liberians blame the United States in part for the present
conflict, pointing to the $500 million Washington pumped into the
country to support Doe after he seized power in a bloody 1980 coup.
   U.S. aid continued to pour in, despite reports that Doe rigged
the 1985 elections and allegations of massive government corruption.
   Lethal military aid was suspended in 1986 after Doe's soldiers
massacred more than 2,000 civilians to put down a rebellion. But
U.S. military advisers remained until last month, when Doe accused
them of supporting the rebels and ordered them out of the country.
   Many of Taylor's soldiers joined the rebellion to avenge family
members killed by Doe's soldiers.
   The rebellion began in December when Taylor's forces invaded
from Ivory Coast, accusing Doe of corruption and human rights
abuses.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900805-0004 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-05-90 2350EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BRF--FallsRescue     08-05 0140</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Falls Rescue,0142</SECOND>
<HEAD>Woman Rescued From Brink of Falls</HEAD>
<NOTE>With LaserPhoto</NOTE>
<DATELINE>NIAGARA FALLS, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A woman jumped into the Niagara River
in an apparent suicide attempt Sunday, but changed her mind after
landing in rapids and was rescued 75 yards from the brink of
Niagara Falls, police said.
   Alice Goldman, 38, of Thorn Hill, Ontario, jumped into the river
from a bridge leading to Goat Island above the American Falls, said
Sgt. Donald Compton of the New York State Parks Police. Once in the
water, the woman tried unsuccessfully tried to swim to shore and
clung to rocks, he said.
   After rescuers determined they couldn't reach her from land,
parks police called a tourist helicopter service, and a chopper
lifted her to safety, Compton said.
   She was admitted to Niagara Falls Memorial Hospital for a
psychiatric evaluation.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900805-0005 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-05-90 2351EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a BC-LOT--SaturdayLotteries     08-05 0878</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-LOT--Saturday Lotteries,1054</SECOND>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<HEAD>CALIFORNIA</HEAD>
<HEAD>Lotto 6-53</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SACRAMENTO, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers picked
Saturday in the California ``Lotto 6-53'' game:
   26, 27, 23, 29, 12, 31. The bonus number was 20.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Decco</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SACRAMENTO, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning playing card
numbers picked Saturday night for the California Lottery's daily
``Decco'' game:
   Hearts: Queen.
   Clubs: Ten.
   Diamonds: Nine.
   Spades: Two.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>CONNECTICUT</HEAD>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEWINGTON, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning combination picked Saturday
in the Connecticut State Lottery's ``Daily Lottery'' drawing was:
   6-5-1
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Play 4</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEWINGTON, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning combination picked Saturday
in the Connecticut State Lottery's ``Play 4'' drawing was:
   4-6-9-9.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>DELAWARE</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DOVER, Del. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   These Delaware lotteries were drawn Saturday
night:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   0-8-0
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Play Four</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   0-4-1-9
</TEXT>
<HEAD>FLORIDA</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected Saturday in
the Florida Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   09-19-22-06-41-28
</TEXT>
<HEAD>ILLINOIS</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SPRINGFIELD, Ill. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the Illinois State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   5-3-8
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick Four</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   0-6-6-9
</TEXT>
<HEAD>LOTTO</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   20-22-31-34-39-47
</TEXT>
<HEAD>INDIANA</HEAD>
<DATELINE>INDIANAPOLIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the Hoosier Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Three</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   8-7-4
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Four</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   8-9-8-4
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto Cash</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   9-15-38-44-34-41
</TEXT>
<HEAD>IOWA</HEAD>
<HEAD>Iowa Lotto</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DES MOINES, Iowa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers drawn Saturday night
in ``Iowa Lotto'' are:
   5-19-28-34-37-39.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>KANSAS</HEAD>
<HEAD>Kan. Cash Lotto</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOPEKA, Kan. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers in the Kansas Cash Lotto
drawing Saturday night.
   19-22-25-28-30-31
</TEXT>
<HEAD>KENTUCKY</HEAD>
<HEAD>Kentucky Lottery</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOUISVILLE, Ky. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are Saturday's winning numbers
selected by the Kentucky Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Kentucky Cash:
   8-4-0.
   </HEAD>
<HEAD>Lotto:
   2-8-12-21-22-28.
   </HEAD>
<HEAD>MARYLAND</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BALTIMORE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   These Maryland lotteries were drawn Saturday
night:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   3-6-0
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Play Four</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   0-3-4-3
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   2-7-11-16-41-49
</TEXT>
<HEAD>MASSACHUSETTS</HEAD>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BRAINTREE, Mass. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers drawn Saturday night
in the ``Massachusetts Daily Lottery'' were:
   1-8-4-6
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
</TEXT>
<HEAD>MICHIGAN</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DETROIT (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected Saturday in
the Michigan State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   4-0-3
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily-4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   7-5-0-1
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto 47</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   1, 18, 19, 37, 42, 43
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   The Zinger number was:
   0-0-2-4-3-9
</TEXT>
<HEAD>MISSOURI</HEAD>
<HEAD>Pick 3</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ST. LOUIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers in Saturday's Missouri
Lottery Daily Pick 3 game:
   2-2-6
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ST. LOUIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers in Missouri's Lotto drawing
Saturday night:
   6-12-21-25-28-35
</TEXT>
<HEAD>NEW JERSEY</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TRENTON, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday night in the New Jersey State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 3</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   2-2-2
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   0-5-8-8
</TEXT>
<HEAD>NEW YORK</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ALBANY, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the New York State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Number</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   3-4-9
</TEXT>
<HEAD>WinFour</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   9-0-6-8
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 10</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ALBANY, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the New York State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 10</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   3, 14, 17, 20, 21, 24, 25, 30, 31, 33, 39, 43, 44, 46, 49, 50,
51, 53, 78, 80.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ALBANY, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the New York State Lottery's Lotto game:
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   4, 12, 21, 30, 35, 44. The supplementary number was 41.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>NORTHERN NEW ENGLAND</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CONCORD, N.H. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the daily New Hampshire, Vermont and Maine lotteries:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 3</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   6-5-5
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   2-2-4-8
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Tri-State Megabucks</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CONCORD, N.H. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers in the
``Tri-State Megabucks'' game for New Hampshire, Vermont and Maine:
   1-5-11-12-17-26
</TEXT>
<HEAD>OHIO</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CLEVELAND (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected Saturday
night in the Ohio Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Super Lotto</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   14-18-21-22-28-39
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Kicker</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   3-1-9-3-0-1
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 3 Numbers</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   7-7-4
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 4 Numbers</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   0-7-3-9
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Cards</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Queen of Hearts
   Ace of Clubs
   Seven of Diamonds
   Seven of Spades
</TEXT>
<HEAD>OREGON</HEAD>
<HEAD>Daily 4</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PORTLAND, Ore. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are Saturday's winning numbers in the
``Oregon Daily 4'' lottery game:
   6-7-3-2
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Megabucks</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PORTLAND, Ore. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are Saturday's winning numbers in the
``Oregon Megabucks'' lottery game:
   5-8-17-26-38-44
</TEXT>
<HEAD>PENNSYLVANIA</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HARRISBURG (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected Saturday
in the Pennsylvania State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Number</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   0-7-8
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Big 4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   3-9-4-5
</TEXT>
<HEAD>RHODE ISLAND</HEAD>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CRANSTON, R.I. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers in the Rhode Island
daily lottery drawing for Saturday were:
   0-0-3-2
</TEXT>
<HEAD>VIRGINIA</HEAD>
<HEAD>Pick 3</HEAD>
<DATELINE>RICHMOND (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   These numbers were drawn Saturday in the
Virginia Lottery's Pick 3 game:
   2-4-3
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<DATELINE>RICHMOND (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   These numbers were drawn Saturday in the
Virginia Lottery's Lotto game:
   9-19-25-28-34-35
</TEXT>
<HEAD>WASHINGTON</HEAD>
<DATELINE>OLYMPIA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are winning numbers selected Saturday in the
Washington State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   0-1-2
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   13-18-21-22-25-34
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Quinto</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Ten of Spades, Seven of Spades, Nine of Hearts, Four of Hearts
and Eight of Diamonds.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>WASHINGTON, D.C.</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The following results were drawn Saturday in
the District of Columbia Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lucky Numbers Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   3-1-4
</TEXT>
<HEAD>D.C. Four Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   3-3-4-4
</TEXT>
<HEAD>D.C. Daily Double Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   26, 42
</TEXT>
<HEAD>D.C. Quick Cash Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   4-15-3-2-31-11
</TEXT>
<HEAD>WEST VIRGINIA</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CHARLESTON, W.Va. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the West Virginia State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily 3</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   2-6-6
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily 4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   2-7-9-4
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900805-0006 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-05-90 2354EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Japan-Longevity     08-05 0187</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Japan-Longevity,0190</SECOND>
<HEAD>Japan Sets New Longevity Records</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Japan extended its own world record for longevity
in 1989, with average life expectancy for women increasing 0.38
years to 81.77 and men 0.30 years to 75.91, the Ministry of Health
and Welfare reported.
   Since 1986, Japan has led the world in life expectancy for both
men and women. When the ministry compiled its first longevity
statistics in 1947, the average life expectancy for women was 53.96
and for men 50.06.
   The ministry, in its weekend report, also predicted that 24
percent of women born last year will die of heart attacks while 10
percent are expected to die of strokes and 17 percent from cancer.
   The leading causes of death for men born last year are likely to
be cancer at 26 percent, heart attacks at 20 percent and strokes at
15 percent, it said.
   Japan is one of the most rapidly aging nations in the world in
terms of the average age of its population. The ministry predicted
that 23.6 percent of the Japanese people will be 65 or older in the
year 2020.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900805-0007 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-05-90 0007EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Archbishop-Celibacy 1stLd-Writethru a0661 08-05 0689</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Archbishop-Celibacy, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0661,0705</SECOND>
<HEAD>Priest Resigns Over Same Woman Who Caused Archbishop's Departure</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 3rd graf, `The Rev. ...' to change attribution to bishop
from spokesman; INSERTS 1 graf after 4th graf, `It wasn't known
...' to UPDATE with Woods said to have used parish funds to help
woman; edits 6th graf to conform.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By LAURAN NEERGAARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ATLANTA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Catholic archdiocese announced Saturday that
a priest had resigned because of a relationship with the same woman
whose ``intimate'' ties with Archbishop Eugene Marino forced him to
step down last month.
   The woman, 27-year-old Vicki R. Long, sued the church for
paternity payments stemming from her alleged relationship with a
third priest. The church is paying child support but denies the
priest is the father.
   The Rev. Michael Woods, pastor at St. Jude's Catholic Church in
Sandy Springs, an Atlanta suburb, offered to resign Saturday after
confessing to an intimate relationship with Ms. Long, a Riverdale
lay minister, said Bishop James Lyke, acting administrator of the
Atlanta Archdiocese.
   It wasn't known if the church had accepted Wood's resignation.
   The bishop said Woods used an undisclosed amount of parish funds
to help Ms. Long. In a statement read to his congregation by an
archdiocese spokesman, Woods said his relationship with Ms. Long
has ended, but did not say how long when it had begun.
   Marino, who originally claimed health reasons for his departure
last month, had a two-year relationship with Ms. Long, church
officials said last week.
   Lyke has refused to say whether Marino's relationship with Ms.
Long was sexual, calling it ``intimate.'' Marino, last known to be
recuperating in New York, has not commented publicly.
   Ms. Long has charged that another priest, Rev. Donal Keohane of
Columbus, Ga., fathered her daughter born in 1986. Blood tests
concluded he was not the father.
   Experts say the resignation of Marino, the nation's
highest-ranking black Catholic, will heighten debate over mandatory
celibacy, a church law adopted in the Middle Ages partly to curb
corruption and nepotism in the church.
   ``Celibacy is unrealistic and it's counterproductive now,'' said
Richard McBrien, theology chairman at the University of Notre Dame.
``The priesthood as we've known it is falling apart ... because of
a stubborn refusal to change.''
   Pope John Paul II strongly supports the celibacy requirement.
During his 1987 visit to the United States, he said a priest's love
for Christ must be paramount and is ``at the foundation of our
commitment to celibacy. This love also makes it possible for us, as
servants of God's kingdom, to love our people freely and chastely
and deeply.''
   McBrien noted that there are increasingly fewer qualified
priests in this country. About 15 percent of priests have left the
order since 1970 and officials expect applications for seminary to
decline 40 percent by the year 2000.
   The Rev. Terrence Dosh, national coordinator for Corpus, a
support group for married ex-priests, said Marino's stature draws
attention to a worldwide disregard for celibacy.
   ``In the past 25 years, 19,000 American Roman Catholic priests
resigned and married and 110,000 in the world resigned and married.
It takes the situation of a bishop to draw attention to it,'' he
said.
   Dosh said scholars believe mandatory celibacy has its roots in
the Old Testament call for ritual purity. Women were believed
impure, so priests were forbidden to have sexual intercourse the
night before celebrating eucharist. In 1139, mandatory celibacy was
adopted.
   ``Celibacy is quintessentially anti-woman,'' he said.
   Cathy Grenier of Good Tidings, a Pennsylvania support group for
women and priests, said celibacy is a feminist issue.
   ``The attitude toward women is that if a priest touches a woman
he's tainted,'' said Mrs. Grenier, who married a priest. ``If women
were not believed inherently evil and dirty, there'd be no problem
with marrying us.''
   McBrien said he believed mandatory celibacy would be stopped,
but perhaps in a ``long and bloody'' manner.
   ``Ask a random sample of Catholics whether they are impressed
with the fact that priests don't marry, if it makes them more of a
spiritually credible person. Most would say no, just the
opposite,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900805-0008 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-05-90 0015EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Honduras-Bananas 2ndLd-Writethru a0660 08-05 0513</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Honduras-Bananas, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0660,0530</SECOND>
<HEAD>Army Evicts Striking Banana Workers From Plant</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEDES with 11 grafs to CORRECT that 4,000 workers at
installation at time of eviction, town occupied, more quotes from
military. Pickup 7th graf `Labor Minister...'</NOTE>
<DATELINE>TEGUCIGALPA, Honduras (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hundreds of army troops on Saturday
evicted about 4,000 striking workers who occupied the U.S.-owned
Chiquita banana packing plant for 41 days in a northern town.
Clashes were reported.
   At least two workers were wounded by gunfire and two others were
beaten when the army evicted workers from the installations in La
Lima, 180 miles north of Tegucigalpa, said union spokesman
Alejandro Maldonado.
   A military intelligence source said at least two workers and one
unidentified person were wounded.
   The circumstances of the clashes were not immediately known.
   The 600 troops also occupied La Lima and the government
announced that the Chiquita Brands, which produces and exports most
of Honduras' banana crop, could hire new employees and resume
production.
   Earlier Saturday, the company rejected a proposed 30 percent pay
increase for the workers, who began their strike June 25.
   About 4,000 of the 10,000 striking workers had peacefully
occupied Chiquita offices, workshops and packing and cleaning
installations during the strike.
   The other 6,000 had remained behind closed gates in about 80
camps where they live around the installations. Troops did not
enter the camps.
   ``La Lima has been occupied by the armed forces,'' the military
source said. ``The situation in La Lima is tense, but there has
been no armed response from the workers.''
   He said troops had removed the strikers and remained in the main
installations. On Sunday, he said, a military operation would begin
``in all the banana camps to definitely reestablish order in that
sector.''
   About 300 soldiers arrived in trucks and quickly occupied the
installations. They were reinforced by 300 more soldiers and
police, the source said.
   Labor Minister Rodolfo Rosales Abella, speaking on national
radio and television, said President Rafael Leonardo Callejas and
his Cabinet decided to end the strike.
   ``The government guarantees the right to work of all employees
of the company, union members or not, who desire to renew their
labor,'' Rosales said.
   ``The government also guarantees the right of Chiquita Brand to
contract the necessary personnel for its normal operation,'' he
said.
   The strike ``constituted a threat to the social and economic
stability of the country,'' he said. Cincinnati-based Chiquita
Brand produces and exports 60 percent of Honduras' bananas, the
country's main export.
   Karl F. Koch, general manager of Chiquita Brand International in
Honduras, told The Associated Press on Saturday that his company
``absolutely rejects the new salary demand of 30 percent for the
workers.''
   The strikers Friday rejected a July 28 proposal by the nation's
president for a 25 percent raise, which would have been acceptable
to the company.
   Instead, they demanded a raise of 30 percent. Earlier, they had
asked for a 60 percent increase over the $246-a-month minimum
salary.
   Groups representing 600,000 workers and peasants had threatened
to launch a general strike Monday if the strike is not solved.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900805-0009 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-05-90 0054EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-TropicalWeather 1stLd-Writethru a0551 08-05 0241</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Tropical Weather, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0551,0244</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tropical Storm Diana Gains Strength in Caribbean</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: UPDATES throughout with Diana gaining strength.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Tropical Storm Diana steadily gained strength
Saturday in the Caribbean Sea and was expected to buffet portions
of Belize and the east coast of Mexico's Yucatan Peninsula on
Sunday, meteorologists said.
   Tropical storm warnings were likely in those areas, the National
Weather Service said.
   Meanwhile, Tropical Storm Cesar was crossing the mid-Atlantic
with 50 mph winds and posing no threat to land.
   Late Saturday, Diana was centered near 17.1 north latitude and
84.2 west longitude, or 335 miles southeast of Cancun, Mexico. It
was moving northwest at 14 mph, and that motion was expected to
continue through Sunday, the weather service said.
   Maximum sustained winds were near 40 mph and expected to
increase in strength Sunday, the weather service said. Tropical
storm-force winds extended 80 miles from the center, it said.
   Cesar was centered late Saturday near 23.6 north latitude and
44.7 west longitude, or about 1,300 miles west-northwest of the
Cape Verde Islands off Africa.
   ``Cesar is really not of any concern to anybody,'' said Noel
Risnychok at the National Hurricane Center in suburban Coral
Gables. ``It's position is still way, way out in the Atlantic, and
it's really of no threat or concern to anybody except for maybe
some shipping.''
   The storm was moving northwest at 8 mph with maximum sustained
winds of 50 mph.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900805-0010 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-05-90 0202EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Japan-Quakes     08-05 0195</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Japan-Quakes,0200</SECOND>
<HEAD>Strong Earthquakes Hit Seabed Off Japan</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Three earthquakes struck the seabed far off Japan's
eastern shore Sunday, but no injuries or damage were reported on
the main islands, officials said.
   The Central Meteorological Agency reported that there was no
danger of tsunami, or tidal waves, following the quakes which
measured up to 6.6 on the Richter scale.
   Police in Tokyo and Ibaraki prefectures (states) said they had
not received any immediate reports of damage or casualties.
   The strongest of the three temblors struck 220 miles beneath the
ocean floor off Japan's Pacific coast at 10:36 a.m. (9:36 p.m. EDT
Saturday). It measured 6.6 on the Richter scale at the epicenter.
   It was followed by two aftershocks at 12:25 p.m. (11:25 p.m. EDT
Saturday) and 12:36 p.m. (11:36 p.m. EDT Saturday), the second of
which was estimated at 5.8 on the Richter scale. There was no
magnitude available for the first aftershock.
   The Richter scale measures the magnitude of a quake at its
epicenter according to ground motion as recorded on seismographs.
An earthquake of 6 on the Richter scale is considered severe,
capable of widespread damage near the epicenter.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900805-0011 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-05-90 0402EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i BC-China-Iraq     08-05 0139</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-China-Iraq,0142</SECOND>
<HEAD>China Embargoes Arms Sales to Iraq</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   China will not sell arms to Iraq, the official
Xinhua news agency said Sunday, joining other nations cutting off
trade with the Baghdad government after the invasion of Kuwait.
   Xinhua quoted an unidentified Foreign Ministry spokesman as
saying that since China supported the U.N. Security Council
resolution condemning Iraq's invasion of Kuwait it would
``naturally, not sell arms to Iraq under such circumstances.''
   The brief report did not elaborate on the ministry official's
comment, which it said was in response to a reporter's question on
whether China would embargo arms sales to Iraq after Thursday's
invasion.
   In the past, China has officially denied selling arms to Iraq,
but Western intelligence reports indicate Beijing has supplied
billions of dollars worth of arms, including anti-ship Silkworm
missiles, to Baghdad.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900805-0012 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-05-90 0411EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a BC-PlaneCrash     08-05 0195</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Plane Crash,0201</SECOND>
<HEAD>Two Killed in N.D. Plane Crash</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DONNYBROOK, N.D. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A light aircraft slammed into a hillside
shortly after taking off from a rural road Saturday night, killing
a 32-year-old man and his 10-year-old niece, police said.
   The two-seat, single-engine Cessna took off shortly before 8
p.m., flew over a gulch and crashed into a hillside about 4 miles
north of Donnybrook, said Highway Patrol Officer Gary Burgett.
   The pilot, from Moreno Valley, Calif., had rented the plane in
Minot, 25 miles away, and picked up his niece on a rural road.
Their identities were not immediately released.
   ``As to what happened, I don't know,'' Burgett said. ``We have
to wait for the people to get up there and make a determination.
There was still fuel in the plane, so I don't know.''
   Witnesses saw the plane turning before disappearing behind the
hill, Burgett said.
   The pilot passed a California flying test in July, the patrolman
said.
   ``He was qualified to fly a plane and he was qualified to fly
that type of a plane,'' Burgett said.
   Federal Aviation Administration officials were expected to visit
the crash site Sunday, he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900805-0013 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-05-90 0413EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a BC-CalifQuake     08-05 0155</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Calif Quake,0158</SECOND>
<HEAD>Quake Shakes Santa Cruz Mountains</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SAN JUAN BAUTISTA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A moderate earthquake shook the
Santa Cruz Mountains on Saturday night, but no injuries were
reported.
   The U.S. Geological Survey reported the 11:52 p.m. temblor
measured 4.3 on the Richter scale and was centered near the town of
San Juan Bautista, about 75 miles southeast of San Francisco.
   ``It was just enough to rattle things and make the pots swing.
But it seemed very small,'' said Linda Parker, a clerk with the
Salinas police department.
   The temblor served as another reminder for Northern California
residents of the deadly Oct. 17, 1989, earthquake in the San
Francisco Bay area that measured 7.1 on the Richter scale, killed
67 people and caused billions of dollars in damage.
   Quakes of magnitude 4 to 5 are considered moderate and could
cause some minor damage such as broken china and cracks in poorly
built structures.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900805-0014 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-05-90 0509EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a BC-FatalFire     08-05 0159</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Fatal Fire,0164</SECOND>
<HEAD>Fire In Apartment Building Kills Five</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SCHENECTADY, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A fire roared through a four-story
apartment building where half the residents are elderly, killing
five people, police said Sunday.
   Deputy Fire Chief Steve Spink said three people who escaped the
fire Saturday evening suffered minor injuries. Two firefighters
were treated for shoulder injuries, he said. The building housed 20
residents.
   ``A number of residents had exited, some had jumped and were
injured on the pavement, and a number had to be rescued via
ladder,'' Spink said.
   The cause of the fire was not known, Spink said. The identities
of the victims were not immediately released, pending notification
of their families.
   Most of the building's tenants lived in small apartments or
single rooms, said Ulrich Fellenher, who identified himself as the
building's landlord.
   About 50 firefighters fought the blaze.
   Some residents jumped from upper-floor windows onto the roof of
a building next door, Spink said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900805-0015 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-05-90 0551EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>b w BC-US-Liberia 2ndadd a0678 08-05 0105</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-US-Liberia, 2nd add, a0678,100</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<HEAD>WASHN: through Carle.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   The U.S. action came hours after rebel leader Prince Johnson
said in Liberia that he was ordering the arrest of all foreigners
in Monrovia in hope of provoking international intervention in the
nation's bloody civil war.
   Johnson, whose troops have occupied much of the city in their
battle to oust President Samuel Doe, told reporters the roundup
would begin Monday and single out American, British, Lebanese and
Indian civilians at first.
   Four U.S. warships containing 4,000 Marines had been stationed
off the Liberian coast for weeks, but Washington previously had has
ruled out intervening.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900805-0016 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-05-90 0719EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i BC-Philippines-CoupAlert     08-05 0205</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Philippines-Coup Alert,0210</SECOND>
<HEAD>Military Camps Placed on Red Alert with Coup Rumors</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MANILA, Philippines (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Officials placed most military camps
on full alert Sunday after raw intelligence reports said dissident
soldiers would try to launch another coup bid to topple President
Corazon Aquino, a military spokesman said.
   ``Unconfirmed reports about another coup attempt by rebel
elements prompted the Philippine Constabulary to raise alert
status,'' military spokesman Lt. Col. Cresencio Maralit told
reporters.
   Brig. Gen. Lisandro Abadia, operations chief of the Armed Forces
of the Philippines, said that the red alert status was ordered in
the army, air force and constabulary headquarters in Manila.
   A red alert status means that soldiers are ordered to barracks.
   Maralit did not give details on the reported coup attempt, nor
its duration. Mrs. Aquino has survived at least six coup attepts
during her four-year term.
   On Dec. 1, mutineers belonging to the Reform the Armed Forces
Movement, launched a nine-day coup try that killed 113 people and
wounded about 600 people.
   Since last year's failed coup, renegades have been threatening
to strike, but a devastating earthquake that rocked Luzon island
last month prompted dissidents to offer a cease-fire to help
rebuild the nation.
   Mrs. Aquino rejected the proposal.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900805-0017 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-05-90 0757EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a BC-TropicalWeather     08-05 0226</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Tropical Weather,0234</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tropical Storm Diana May Strengthen; Warnings Posted in Mexico,
Belize</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Tropical storm warnings were posted early Sunday
for the Caribbean coastlines of Mexico and Belize as forecasters
predicted Tropical Storm Diana could strengthen.
   The storm warnings extended from Cancun, Mexico, to Belize City,
including offshore islands, according to a statement by the
National Hurricane Center in suburban Coral Gables. Up to 5 inches
of rain is possible in sections of Mexico's Yucatan Peninsula.
   Heavy rainfall was also possible along the north coast of
Honduras, the center reported.
   Forecasters predicted Diana could intensify Sunday as it moves
through the western Caribbean. Maximum sustained winds early Sunday
were near 45 mph.
   At 6 a.m. EDT, Diana was centered near 17.7 north latitude and
85.4 west longitude, or 250 miles south southeast of Cancun. It was
moving northwest at 14 mph, and that motion was expected to
continue through Monday.
   Meanwhile, Tropical Storm Cesar was crossing the mid-Atlantic
with 50 mph winds and posing no threat to land.
   Cesar was centered at 6 a.m. EDT near 24.2 north latitude and
46.7 west longitude, or about 1,250 miles east southeast of Bermuda.
   ``Cesar is really not of any concern to anybody ... except for
maybe some shipping,'' Noel Risnychok of the hurricane center said
Saturday.
   The storm was moving northwest at 12 mph.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900805-0018 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-05-90 0924EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w BC-US-Liberia 6thLd-Writethru a0690-a0695 08-05 1118</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-US-Liberia, 6th Ld-Writethru, a0690-a0695,1,180</SECOND>
<HEAD>Americans Being Evacuated</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: LEAD with 4 grafs to UPDATE with White House comments on
evacuation; pick up 4th graf, bgng ``Some 225 ...; EDITS to tighten.
^By SUSANNE M. SCHAFER</NOTE>
<BYLINE>AP Military Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   U.S. Marines rescued 59 Americans from the
U.S. Embassy compound in Liberia Sunday without ``any shots being
fired or resistance encountered,'' White House spokesman Marlin
Fitzwater said.
   Two hours after the operation was announced, Pentagon sources
reported the U.S. citizens were safe aboard the USS Saipan, a
helicopter assault ship off the shore of the Liberian capital of
Monrovia.
   ``We've been advised that the initial stages of this morning's
Liberia operation have been successfully completed,'' said
Fitzwater. ``A total of 59 people were flown to U.S. Navy ships
offshore by U.S. Marine Corp helicopters.
   ``The U.S. Marine Corp Reinforced Rifle Co. is in place
providing protection for U.S. citizens. The initial operation went
well and we are unaware of any shots being fired or resistance
encountered.''
   Some 225 Marines were involved in the airborne operation, which
made use of 17 aircraft, including light attack jets, assault
helicopters and transport choppers, to fly the Americans to safety,
the sources said.
   President Bush ordered the evacuation after one of the rebel
leaders trying to oust President Samuel Doe announced he was
ordering the arrest of all foreigners in Monrovia in hope of
provoking international intervention in the nation's bloody civil
war, White House spokesman Marlin Fitzwater said.
   Fitzwater said about 70 U.S. officials and 300 other Americans
were in Liberia and that ``we'll take out as many as want to get
out.''
   The Marine presence ``does not indicate or constitute any
intention on the part of the U.S. government to intervene
militarily in the Liberian conflict,'' the spokesman said.
   The Marines will evacuate the Americans who wish to leave, draw
down the number of U.S. officials at the Embassy and shore up the
embassy's defenses to guard the skeleton staff that will remain
behind, Fitzwater said.
   Meanwhile, Liberian rebel leader Charles Taylor called for
civilians and fighters to mobilize. In a broadcast from a radio
station in northern Yekepa town, Taylor asked all Liberians ``to
defend your country'' and ``oppose all foreign intervention.''
   U.S. officials had begun notifying Americans on that the
evacuation could take place, and military officials expect that
many of the 300 Americans will decline to take part, the officials
said.
   ``It's up to them, whether they want to go, but it seems that
many of them want to remain,'' one official said.
   The Americans were expected to be transported by air to
Freetown, Sierra Leone, the nation on Liberia's northern border.
   Some of the Marine riflemen were also dispatched to two
transmitter sites for diplomatic communications to secure the
safety of Americans workings there.
   Later, the Pentagon sources reported that the Americans located
at both sites had been evacuated. ``We are essentially abandoning
the sites,'' the source said of the transmitters located there.
   A spokesman for Sen. Paul Simon, D-Ill., chairman of the African
affairs subcommittee of the Senate Foreign Relations Committee,
said the senator was informed of the operation by the State
Department at 5:20 a.m. EDT.
   ``The president's action is a proper one, and I support his
decision,'' the senator, who was in Chicago, said in a statement
issued through spokesman David Carle.
   ``It sounds like a sensible operation and an appropiate
response,'' said Sen. Alan Cranston, D-Calif., who also was
notified in advance. Cranston is chairman of the Foreign Relations
subcommittee on East Asian and Pacific Affairs and a member of the
Senate Intelligence Committee.
   Fitzwater noted that the United States had maintained ships off
the Liberian shore for several weeks, but had not taken sides in
the fighting.
   The U.S. ships involved in the operation include the amphibious
assault helicopter carrier USS Saipan; the USS Ponce, an amphibious
transport dock ship; the USS Sumter, a tank landing ship; and the
destroyer USS Peterson.
   About 2,200 Marines, based at Camp LeJeune, N.C., are aboard the
ships.
   Pentagon sources said one radio transmitter site is about 20
kilometers southeast of Monrovia and the other 20 kilometers
northeast of the city.
   The Marines were expected to gather the Americans inside the
embassy compound, where they could be properly identified and
processed for transport by helicopter to the ships waiting off
shore, the sources said.
   The Marine amphibious readiness unit on the Saipan made use of
nine CH-46 ``Sea Knight'' helicopters to transport the Marines and
the Americans, and two CH-53 ``Sea Stallion'' choppers to carry
cargo, weapons and transport vehicles, the Pentagon sources said.
   Four AH-1 ``Sea Cobra'' attack choppers flew to the transmitter
sites to secure the Americans there and security for the air resuce
operation was provided by AV-8B Harrier light attack jets, the
sources said.
   ``They will be shuttling back and forth until it's done,'' the
official said.
   Fitzwater said U.S. forces were sent in ``to immediately secure
the embassy, accomplish the rescue operation, secure and remove
Americans from two communications sites (and) remain as long as
necessary to assure the security'' of remaining embassy staff.
   The spokesman announced the deployment in an early morning
briefing at the White House as Bush monitored developments from the
presidential retreat at Camp David.
   ``The Marines will remain in Liberia as long as necessary to
insure the safety of U.S. citizens in that country,'' Fitzwater
said.
   He said the embassy would remain open with a skeleton staff.
   ``The Marines are there to protect lives. They are authorized
whatever means are necessary to do that. And they are there in a
battle situation. And we have notified the Congress to that
effect.''
   Prince Johnson, whose rebel troops have occupied much of the
city in their battle to oust Doe, told reporters Saturday his
roundup of foreigners would begin Monday and single out American,
British, Lebanese and Indian civilians at first.
   The U.S. transmitters were in territory held by Charles Taylor,
a rival rebel leader who has threatened repeatedly to attack any
foreign troops.
   The first word of a foreigner killed in the conflict had come
Saturday with a report that a Lebanese native who had lived in the
Liberian capital for more than 15 years was shot to death in front
of his wife and four children.
   The fighting in the civil war is centered in Monrovia, where
forces loyal to Johnson are trying to topple Doe, whose troops were
defending Doe's fortified mansion. Forces loyal to Taylor had been
stopped by Doe's troops east of the capital.
   At least 2,000 foreigners, mostly Lebanese and Indian traders,
still live in the embattled capital. Besides the Americans, the
Westerners include a few dozen Britons.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900805-0019 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-05-90 0937EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i BC-Iraq-Kuwait 3rdLd-Writethru   08-05 0810</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Iraq-Kuwait, 3rd Ld-Writethru,a0696,0829</SECOND>
<HEAD>Iraqi-Installed Kuwaiti Government Says Withdrawal Under Way</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: New thruout to UPDATE comment on formerly missing Americans,
reporters in Iraq brought to see returning Iraqi soldiers, Jordan
refusing to back new Kuwaiti government, denial that new government
contains Iraqis. No pickup.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By SALAH NASRAWI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BAGHDAD, Iraq (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The radio of Kuwait's new Iraqi-installed
government claimed that Iraqi troops began pulling out of Kuwait on
Sunday, but the United States said it doubted a withdrawal was
really under way.
   The radio announcement came three days after Iraq invaded Kuwait
and one day after Baghdad said it had replaced the oil-rich
kingdom's ousted monarchy with a new government made up of nine
Kuwaiti army offices.
   Iraq also said Saturday that it was creating a new Kuwaiti army
and that 100,000 Iraqis, the approximate number of soldiers Baghdad
took over Kuwait with, had volunteered for the new military force.
   In other developments:
   _The White House continued to seek the immediate and
unconditional withdrawl of all Iraqi troops, and it thanked the
many nations who have condemned the invasion and imposed economic
sanctions on Baghdad.
   _After several days of debate, Japan on Sunday banned all oil
imports from Iraq and Kuwait and halted Japanese exports to both
countries. Tokyo said it would suspend all loans to Iraq and
Kuwait, ban Japanese investment there, and freeze Iraqi assets in
Japan. Japan, which imports 99 percent of its oil, had relied on
Iraq and Kuwait for more than 11 percent of its oil imports. The
White House hailed Japan's move and said Prime Minister Toshiki
Kaifu called President Bush on Sunday at Camp David to inform him
about the sanctions.
   _Although tens of thousands of Iraqi troops reportedly remained
massed near Kuwait's border with Saudi Arabia, Washington said on
Sunday there was no indication that any soldiers had moved into
Saudi Arabia.
   _The White House said that 11 American oil workers rounded up
after the invasion had been brought to Baghdad, talked with U.S.
Embassy officials, and were in good shape. It said that accounts
for all missing Americans.
   _An unconfirmed report said a warplane from the deposed emir's
air force in Kuwait bombed an Iraqi military headquarters near
Kuwait city. It was not clear where the plane came from or whether
its reported attack caused any damage.
   The radio of Kuwait's new government, monitored in Bahrain,
quoted its ``military correspondent'' as saying the pullout began
at 8 a.m. (1 a.m. EDT).
   Iraqi President Saddam Hussein allowed reporters based in
Baghdad to be taken south to Basra overnight to observe the first
Iraqi troops return home.
   But at the White House, press secretary Marlin Fitzwater said on
Sunday morning: ``We have no independent or confirmable information
on this report (of the withdrawl beginning). Saddam Hussein's
actions in the past have raised serious skepticism about his
intentions.''
   Iraq declared earlier that the provisional government installed
by Baghdad is capable of ensuring security in the occupied country.
   Baghdad television has said the new government is headed by Col.
Ala Hussein Ali and that he holds the positions of prime minister,
commander-in-chief of the armed forces, minister of defense and
interior minister. The other eight members were lieutenant colonels
and majors.
   But Kuwait's embassy in Amman, Jordan, on Sunday dismissed the
new government as ``a list of fake names'' and said Ali is Saddam's
son-in-law.
   A similar report appeared in one of Cairo's leading newspapers,
Al-Ahram. It quoted the Kuwait Embassy in Tunis which said that Ali
works with Saddam's administration in Baghdad.
   The Iraqi news agency carried a Kuwait-datelined statement it
said was from the provisional government, denying any of its
members were Iraqis.
   In Jordan, Prime Minister Mudar Badran said his nation will not
recognize the new government because that would hinder Arab efforts
to end the conflict.
   U.S., French and British warships, meanwhile, steamed toward the
Persian Gulf. President Bush said Friday that if Iraq moved against
Saudi Arabia it would be attacking U.S. ``vital interests.'' On
Saturday, Bush said in Washington that the use of force in
resolving the crisis remains an option. Saudi Arabia ships 1.2
million barrels of oil to the United States daily.
   Fitzwater said on Sunday that there was no indication Iraqi
forces had moved into Saudi Arabia, even though tens of thousands
of them have been reported to be within 5 to 10 miles of the Saudi
border.
   In Washington, Iraqi ambassador Mohammed al-Mashat on Saturday
denied U.S. and other foreign reports suggesting that Iraq plans to
invade Saudi Arabia.
   Saddam ordered the invasion of Kuwait after accusing it of
stealing oil from a field that straddles their disputed border. He
also blamed Kuwait for a fall in oil prices that cost Iraq $14
billion, saying it contributed to the oil glut by cheating on its
OPEC oil cartel production quotas.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900805-0020 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-05-90 1104EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w BC-US-Iraq 3rdLd-Writethru a0699 08-05 0715</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-US-Iraq, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0699,690</SECOND>
<HEAD>White House Seriously Skeptical of Iraqi Withdrawal Claim</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: SUBS graf 9 pvs, bgng ``He declined ..., to delete reference
to recognition of provisional government. Fitzwater was referring
to other matters.
^By TERENCE HUNT</NOTE>
<BYLINE>AP White House Correspondent</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The White House expressed ``serious
skepticism'' Sunday over claims that Iraq was pulling its invading
forces out of Kuwait.
   White House press secretary Marlin Fitzwater also said there was
no indication that Iraqi forces had moved into Saudi Arabia, even
though they were within 5 to 10 miles of the Saudi border.
   President Bush, spending the weekend at Camp David, consulted by
telephone with Saudi King Fahd, Turkish President Turgut Ozal, the
emir of Kuwait and Canadian Prime Minister Brian Mulroney on
Saturday.
   ``The United States continues to seek the immediate, complete
and unconditional withdrawal of Iraqi forces from Kuwait and
restoration of a legitimate government of that country,'' Fitzwater
said.
   ``We continue to consider all options in accordance with that
policy.''
   The radio of the Iraqi-backed Kuwaiti government said Iraqi
troops began pulling out of the oil-rich country Sunday, three days
after they were ordered to invade by Iraqi President Saddam Hussein.
   At the White House, Fitzwater said, ``We have no independent or
confirmable information on this report.
   ``Saddam Hussein's actions in the past have raised serious
skepticism about his intentions,'' the White House spokesman said.
   He declined comment on reports that Jordan's King Hussein had
defended Iraq's president.
   ``We're in the process of trying to work out a solution here and
it does no good, serves no useful purpose, to try to characterize
individual actions,'' Fitzwater said.
   As to a report in The Washington Post that special operations
forces and hostage rescue forces have already been dispatched to
the Mideast and that contingency plans call for sending Stealth
fighters and B-52 bombers, Fitzwater said, ``I can't comment on any
specific military actions or movements.''
   Reporting on the status of missing U.S. citizens, Fitzwater
confirmed that 11 American oil workers rounded up after the
invasion had been brought to Baghdad. He said they had talked with
U.S. embassy officials.
   ``They appear to be in good shape and this accounts for all
missing Americans,'' Fitzwater said. ``They are safe and pursuing
courses of their own free will.''
   One possible avenue of applying pressure against Iraq would be
to close down the pipelines in Turkey and Saudi Arabia through
which most of Iraqi's oil flows.
   ``Clearly they are part of the equation,'' Fitzwater said.
   When asked if Ozal or Fahd had made a commitment to close the
pipelines, Fitzwater said, ``We can't comment on specific actions
or agreements that have been reached in terms of private
conversations.''
   He added, ``I'm not prepared to comment on any conclusions that
they may have reached at this time.'' Fitzwater said the pipelines
apparently are still open.
   Fitzwater discussed developments in the Middle East at an
early-morning White House briefing where he announced that 225
Marines had been sent into Liberia to evacuate Americans and
protect the U.S. Embassy there from the country's civil war.
   Asked if the U.S. action in Liberia carried a message to Saddam,
Fitzwater said, ``I wouldn't link the two. ... There really is no
relationship between these actions in two separate parts of the
world.
   ``It does, of course, point up, that President Bush is extremely
concerned about the welfare of American citizens,'' Fitzwater said.
``We have acted time and again on behalf of their safety. ... I'm
sure that Iraq and other countries are aware of that.''
   Fitzwater said the United States was continuing to encourage
other nations to freeze Iraqi assets and to institute economic
sanctions against Baghdad. The United States also is urging a
freeze on Kuwaiti assets to keep them away from Iraq.
   Arab leaders have warned against foreign intervention and have
sought a diplomatic solution, but an emergency Arab League summit
to discuss the crisis initially planned for Sunday in Saudi Arabia
was postponed.
   Asked if the delay constituted a setback, Fitzwater said, ``It's
difficult to know. The timing is a question for them to consider.
We don't know all of the criteria or concerns that they had about
holding the meeting versus at some later point. So it's just
impossible to say.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900805-0021 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-05-90 1142EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Overeaters-NewOrleans     08-05 0483</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Overeaters-New Orleans,0495</SECOND>
<HEAD>Overeaters Anonymous Celebrates Freedom From Food in Gourmet
Setting</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARY FOSTER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW ORLEANS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Holding the annual convention of Overeaters
Anonymous in this city of rich food might seem like too much
temptation, but for those attending it was more like a testimonial
to the program.
   ``We recognize the irony and some of the temptations it
presents,'' said Jorge Sever, executive director of Overeaters
Anonymous. ``We aren't worried about it, however.''
   A week after the chefs of the American Culinary Federation
staged their 1990 Culinary Mardi Gras, Overeaters Anonymous
gathered this weekend to celebrate the group's 30 years of helping
people recover from compulsive overeating.
   ``It is ironic, but it's really neat in a way. It points out
that our program isn't just about food. It's about how we're living
our lives,'' said Kathy, who has been involved in OA for 10 years.
   Kathy, who like most members of the organization doesn't reveal
her last name, said she weighed 218 pounds when she joined OA. She
now weighs 125, though she's lived in this capital of cookery for
two years.
   ``If you're fit emotionally and spiritually and every other way,
you eat to enjoy it, not because you have to,'' said Kathy. ``New
Orleans is known for its food and its restaurants. I'm sure some of
our members will really enjoy it. Others will avoid it. We all have
to do what's right for us.''
   Organizers said 1,500 people from all over the world registered
for the convention and its nearly 40 meetings and workshops.
   Overeaters Anonymous is divided into nine regions nationally,
said Annette Mambuca, the group's publications editor. The
conventions are rotated among the regions.
   When the southeastern region's turn came, New Orleans was
selected _ ``strictly on the convention facilities and the appeal
it would have for our members,'' Ms. Mambuca said.
   OA isn't the first group finding itself in conflict with New
Orleans' rich food tradition. In March, 24,000 heart doctors
gathered for the American College of Cardiology's convention, and
New Orleans-style banquet menus had to be modified to reduce
cholesterol levels.
   Overeaters Anonymous, which was started in January 1960 in Los
Angeles, is patterned after the Alcoholics Anonymous program.
   ``The program is not really a diet club,'' Sever said. ``We
don't provide a food plan or anything like that for our members. We
offer support, we share in some of their griefs and in their joy of
recovery. Some people feel they need some type of regimentation. In
that case we tell them to see a doctor or a dietitian.''
   OA does not charge fees or dues. Most groups take up a
collection at meetings to cover expenses. The organization doesn't
solicit or accept outside contributions.
   ``I'll never graduate from OA,'' Kathy said. ``Initially I went
to lose weight. I stick around because of the spiritual and
emotional growth.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900805-0022 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-05-90 1142EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--MotherJailed     08-05 0193</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Mother Jailed,0197</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mother Jailed For Locking Children In Apartment for Three Days</HEAD>
<DATELINE>FORBACH, France (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A judge on Sunday jailed a woman who
locked three of her children in an apartment for three days with no
adult care and only a small amount of food.
   Marie-Rose Winterstein, 32, and her boyfriend, Gilbert Risser,
34, were ordered held until a hearing Thursday to determine if they
would be prosecuted for depriving minors of proper care.
   The couple left their apartment in Forbach, near the
French-Belgian border, on Tuesday, taking Winterstein's 5-year-old
son with them. Left behind were Sonia, 12; Natacha, 7, and Michael,
20 months.
   Sonia made meals of noodles and eggs for the first two days,
police said. On Thursday, neighbors in adjoining apartments
responded to Sonia's appeals by passing food to their balcony, but
they didn't summon authorities until Friday because the girl told
them her mother was expected back soon.
   Neighbors said the couple had left the children unattended
before, but for shorter periods.
   The children were reported in satisfactory condition Sunday at a
hospital, where they were to stay pending resolution of the case
against their mother.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900805-0023 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-05-90 1143EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--China-Storm     08-05 0131</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--China-Storm,0135</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tropical Storm Kills 108 in Southern China</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A tropical storm lashed southern China with
strong winds and torrential rains, killing 108 people and flooding
hundreds of thousands of acres of farmland, it was reported Sunday.
   Floods from tropical storm Tasha killed 39 people and injured
335 in Guangdong province alone, the official Xinhua News Agency
reported.
   The storm destroyed 25,200 houses in Guangdong and flooded
353,210 acres of farmland and seven cities from July 29 to Friday,
the report said.
   Another 69 people were killed in Fujian province in floods that
inundated 333,450 acres of farmland and caused damage estimated at
nearly $83 million, it said.
   The two provinces sent teams to the affected areas to help with
rescue and reconstruction work, the report said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900805-0024 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-05-90 1146EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SriLanka     08-05 0410</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Sri Lanka,0425</SECOND>
<HEAD>Government Repulses Rebel Attack, Killing 30</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PATRICK CRUEZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>COLOMBO, Sri Lanka (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Government troops and warplanes on
Sunday repulsed a major assault on a military-held fort in the
heart of Tamil rebel territory, killing at least 30 fighters, the
army said.
   A rebel leader, meanwhile, denied his militia was responsible
for the massacre Friday of 140 Moslem worshipers in two mosques in
an eastern town, a newspaper reported.
   The rebels, who are members of the Tamil minority, are battling
for an independent homeland in this Indian Ocean republic.
   The militants began their fight in 1983, claiming their
community was being discriminated against by the majority Sinhalese.
   At least 14,000 people have been killed during the civil war.
   Tamils, who are mostly Hindu, make up 18 percent of the
population, while the mostly Buddhist Sinhalese, who control the
government and the military, comprise 75 percent of the people.
   Moslems, who make up 7 percent of the population, claim
neutrality in the civil war, but the rebels have accused them of
siding with the government.
   On Sunday, at least 300 rebels attacked an 18th-century fort in
Jaffna city with mortars, rockets and machine guns, the military
reported. Government troops have been holding out in the fort for
55 days.
   Government troops called in air support and the fighting and
intensive air attacks left at least 30 guerrillas dead, the army
said.
   In a statement, the military said no government troops were
killed in the fighting.
   There was no independent confirmation of the casualties and
there were no reports from the rebels.
   The almost 200 soldiers in Jaffna Fort have been under siege
since the fighting began on June 11.
   More than 3,000 combatants and hundreds of civilians have been
killed in fighting since then.
   A rebel leader, meanwhile, denied his group was involved in the
Friday massacre of 140 Moslem worshipers, the Sunday Times
newspaper reported.
   The newspaper said a leader of the Liberation Tigers of Tamil
Eelam, the main rebel militia, said in a telephone interview that
the killing was carried out by a rival Tamil group to discredit the
Tigers.
   The newspaper identified the leader as Karikalan, the political
officer of the Tigers in the eastern district of Batticaloa. Most
rebel leaders use only one name.
   At least 112 of the victims were buried Saturday. Twenty-eight
of the 75 people injured in the attack later died, Sri Lanka's
Sunday Times reported.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900805-0025 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-05-90 1155EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Israel-GasMasks     08-05 0435</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel-Gas Masks,0449</SECOND>
<HEAD>Army Distributing Gas Masks to Civilians</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Iraq-Kuwait, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The army is stepping up its distribution of gas
masks to civilians following Iraq's invasion of Kuwait, Israeli
media reported Sunday.
   An army spokesman confirmed that soldiers have been distributing
protective equipment against a possible chemical weapons attack but
denied the move was linked to the invasion.
   In April, Iraqi President Saddam Hussein threatened to ``scorch
half of Israel with poison gas,'' if his country were attacked. The
Israeli military began an experimnetal distribution of gas masks
shortly following Saddam's threat.
   ``The distribution of gas masks is part of a plan enacted
several months ago and will continue until all residents in Israel
hear explanations of what chemical warfare is,'' the spokesman
said. He spoke on condition of anonymity in keeping with military
regulations.
   He said a mass distribution effort was being considered, but
added that no concrete decisions were made since Thursday's
invasion by Iraq.
   But the left-wing Al Hamishmar newspaper reported that gas masks
would be distributed to hundreds of thousands of homes by the
year's end.
   The Haaretz daily said in a front-page story Sunday that army
officers met secretly this weekend and decided to distribute gas
masks in the Tel Aviv metropolitan area.
   That region, the most densely populated in Israel, is home to
about 1.9 million of the country's 4.5 million people.
   It also reported that the army planned to start marketing
videotapes explaining how to use the equipment.
   This past year an experimental distribution of gas masks was
conducted in two cities, Ramat Hasharon, north of Tel Aviv and
Sefad in northern Israel's Galilee.
   About half-a-million pupils in the nation's 2,200 schools were
also taught how to use special anti-gas kits.
   Israel widely issued gas masks on a trial basis in 1979, but
stopped the practice after it was discovered that the equipment was
often used at masquerade parties and while painting cars.
   But Israelis began taking the issue more seriously after
widespread allegations that Iraq used poison gas against its
Kurdish minority during the eight-year Iran-Iraq war that ended in
1988.
   Iraq is one of four Arab countries believed to have chemical
weapons, and possessed medium-range missiles. Egypt, Syria, and
Libya are also believed to have chemical weapons.
   Israeli leaders, meanwhile, said they were closely following the
military developments in Kuwait.
   Defense Minister Moshe Arens said he saw no need for Israel to
intervene in the conflict but added that if Iraq sent troops into
neighboring Jordan ``this would change the geostrategic situation
for Israel and would require action on our part.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900805-0026 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-05-90 1200EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-China-SoutheastAsia     08-05 0456</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-China-Southeast Asia,0469</SECOND>
<HEAD>China Restores Ties With Indonesia, Seeks Regional Influence</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ELAINE KURTENBACH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Premier Li Peng departs Monday on an official
visit to Indonesia and Singapore, seeking to enhance China's
influence in the region.
   Long ostracized by the West for its violent suppression of
pro-democracy protests and bypassed by the democratic revolutions
that shook its socialist allies, China has sought to exert more
influence in its traditional sphere of influence, Western diplomats
say.
   China's aspirations have been encouraged by U.S. plans to reduce
its military profile in the region, said the diplomats, who spoke
on condition of anonymity.
   ``Beijing is anxious to counterbalance U.S. and Japanese
influence in the region,'' said one diplomat.
   Another diplomat added: ``China ... sees itself as the
pre-eminent power in Southeast Asia, and the pre-eminent cultural
force. It decided it would be best to work on relations close to
home.''
   By securing normal ties with Indonesia and Singapore, Beijing
has also scored a diplomatic coup against Taiwan, which it regards
as a renegade province.
   While none of China's neighbors would accept a Chinese military
presence on their territory, some are welcoming closer diplomatic
ties.
   China and Indonesia are set to resume normal diplomatic
relations on Aug. 8, nearly 23 years after Jakarta suspended ties
with Beijing after an abortive Communist coup it blamed on Chinese
influence.
   Following Indonesia's lead, Singapore is expected to establish
diplomatic relations with Beijing before the end of the year.
   Both Singapore and Indonesia cited the promise of improved trade
ties with Asia's most populous market as one reason for the
rapprochement.
   Indonesia's total trade with China has more than doubled _ from
$421 million to $918 million last year _ since the July 1985
signing of a memorandum of understanding between the two countries'
chambers of commerce and industry.
   Indonesia's foreign minister, Ali Alatas, said he hopes to sign
a new trade agreement during Li's visit Monday through Friday.
   Li's visit to Singapore, scheduled for Saturday through Aug. 13,
is expected to further trade and investment ties developed over the
past decade. Singapore, which is slightly larger than Chicago, is
China's fifth-largest export market, much of it for re-export to
other countries.
   Singaporean businessmen, many of them ethnic Chinese, have been
encouraged by their government to invest more in China's
manufacturing and tourism.
   Beijing's decision to stop supporting anti-government Communist
rebels in the region, with the exception of the Khmer Rouge in
Cambodia, has helped open the ways for better ties with neighboring
states.
   Of the six members of Association of Southeast Asian Nations _
Brunei, Indonesia, Malaysia, the Philippines, Singapore and
Thailand _ only the sultanate of Brunei has not agreed to establish
normal relations with Beijing.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900805-0027 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-05-90 1205EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Spain-Cuba     08-05 0315</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Spain-Cuba,0326</SECOND>
<HEAD>Cuban National Ballet Dancer, Husband Seek Asylum in Spain</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By FRANCISCO CONDE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MADRID, Spain (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A top ballerina with the Cuban National
Ballet and her husband were granted political asylum in Spain, a
police spokesman said Sunday.
   It was the latest strain in relations between Spain and its
former Caribbean colony, already tense over 18 Cubans being
sheltered at Spain's embassy in the Cuban capital of Havana.
   The police spokesman at Madrid's Barajas Airport, speaking on
condition of anonymity, confirmed that dancer Dagmar Moradillo and
her husband, Alfredo Rodriguez, sought and received provisional
political asylum Saturday at the police station. Rodriguez is a
ballet lighting designer with the company.
   The conservative Madrid newspaper ABC also reported the
defections. It said the dancer and her husband had arrived Saturday
from the Spanish Mediterranean isle of Majorca, where the ballet
company performed Friday.
   In an interview with ABC, the 29-year-old dancer said she was
concerned authorities may fire her mother from her job at a Havana
hospital.
   ``Now begins the future, something that didn't exist in Cuba,''
she told the paper. ``It's a no-way-out situation there, no
objectives or possibilities.
   ``That's why we escaped ... we didn't see a future for ourselves
or the children we desire,'' she said.
   The dancer and her husband told the paper they wanted to live in
the United States. They have family in Miami, and the dancer
believes she can continue her career. The couple joined the Cuban
company in the mid-1970s.
   The Spanish-Cuban diplomatic conflict began early last month
when disgruntled Cubans began seeking refuge in foreign embassies
in Havana.
   The conflict is at a standstill, and Cuba continues to refuse to
permit the asylum-seekers to leave the country, said a Spanish
government spokesman, who was not identified in keeping with
Foreign Ministry policy.
   Spain refuses to expel the 18 from its embassy.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900805-0028 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-05-90 1221EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Kuwait-Life     08-05 0339</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Kuwait-Life,0356</SECOND>
<HEAD>^News Trickles Out from Tense Kuwait</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Iraq-Kuwait, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MANAMA, Bahrain (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Invading Iraqi soldiers have looted
banks, supermarkets and car showrooms and an underground resistance
has emerged, said some of the few callers who got through to Kuwait.
   Soldiers went on a looting spree Saturday in stores stocked with
goods unavailable at home, said residents and foreign diplomats.
   Looters who hit car dealerships often drove off with luxury
sedans. Soldiers also targeted banks and supermarkets, callers said.
   Residents said the resistance movement has been distributing
leaflets at mosques to rally support for fighting the invaders.
   Some bloated bodies had yet to be removed from around the
palace, which was bombarded for more than two hours during the
invasion Thursday, residents said. At least 200 people were killed
and wounded during the invasion, diplomats said. Reports that the
toll was at least three times that could not be confirmed.
   Iraq announced Sunday that it was withdrawing some troops.
   Telephone lines went completely dead Friday morning, but a few
phone calls trickled through Saturday.
   Kuwait TV returned to the air Saturday, heavy with support for
the nine-man military Cabinet installed by Baghdad. Its new emblem
is a flame.
   Diplomatic sources said Iraqi tanks and artillery began pulling
out of the city center Saturday.
   But Iraqi tanks shelled al-Beda, a manmade island on the city's
southern coast near the industrial center of Shuaiba, said one
diplomat who insisted on anonymity. He did not know why it was
shelled.
   Otherwise no gunfire was reported Saturday.
   The extent of damage from the invasion could not be determined,
though many landmark buildings were scarred by shell holes.
   A woman living on the Kuwait University campus said the
situation was ``very quiet, almost eerie, and tense.''
   Iraqi soldiers were stopping cars and ``politely'' asking people
to step out so they can check them, said the woman, speaking on
condition of anonymity.
   She also said that workers, especially those at such prime
installations as refineries, were allowed to go to work normally.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900805-0029 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-05-90 1242EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Bush-SouthAmerica     08-05 0245</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bush-South America,245</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush Postpones South American Trip</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush has postponed indefinitely a
five-nation trip to South America in mid-September because of
deficit-reduction negotiations with Congress and other problems,
administration officials said Sunday.
   Bush had been scheduled to visit Brazil, Uruguay, Argentina,
Chile and Venezuela from Sept. 16-22.
   One official said Bush still hopes to make the trip by the end
of the year but that may not be possible. Another official said the
earliest rescheduling of the trip would be within a couple of
months.
   Embassies in each country were notified over the weekend that
the trip was being postponed, the officials said.
   Bush informed Uruguay President Luis Lacalle on Friday, Foreign
Minister Hector Gros Espiell said. Latin leaders expected Bush
during his visit to explain his proposal of a free trade zone from
Alaska to Tierra del Fuego.,
   U.S. Embassies have been working with foreign ministries on
legislation expected to be ready for signing by mid-September, such
as the lifting of bank secrecy laws to allow the investigation of
accounts thought to be related to narcotics trafficking.
   Cancellation of September's visit comes amid the crisis in the
Middle East caused by Iraq's invasion of Kuwait.
   However, officials said the primary reason for the delay were
the budget negotiations scheduled to resume in early September
between the White House and Congress. The nearly three-month-old
talks are at an impasse and were suspended while Congress and Bush
vacation in August.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900805-0030 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-05-90 1249EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People     08-05 0837</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People,0871</SECOND>
<HEAD>People in the News</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY44</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ST. PAUL, Minn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Roseanne Barr told a friendly audience
over the weekend that she must be the ``world's greatest singer.''
   And why does she think that?
   ``Because my voice can stop a (bleeping) nation,'' Barr said
Saturday in her first public stage performance since singing a
shrill rendition of ``The Star Spangled Banner'' in San Diego.
   No hecklers or protesters were in the crowd of about 5,000 at
the Riverfest outdoor stage at Harriet Island.
   One fan carried a sign that read, ``We love you Roseanne.''
   Barr's rendition of the national anthem at a Padres baseball
game drew boos from the crowd. She capped the performance by
grabbing her crotch and spitting on the ground in what she said was
a parody of a baseball pitcher.
   Commenting on the public backlash from her act in San Diego,
Barr joked that she was ``recently released from the Betty Ford
drug clinic.''
   ``I didn't want to be on drugs,'' she said, ``but my publicist
said it would help my comeback.''
   Helen Corbett, a spectator from Bloomington, said there was
``too much of a fuss'' made about Barr's national anthem
performance. ``Half the nation can't sing the national anthem any
better than she did,'' Corbett said.
   Barr's 45-minute, profanity-laced act preceded a performance by
1950s rock 'n' roller Chuck Berry.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>ANDERSON, S.C. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Actress Julia Roberts, who outraged many
upstate South Carolinians by saying the region was racist, now says
she was referring to just one incident.
   ``I was born in the South, so in no way am I trying to create a
stereotype,'' Ms. Roberts said in a statement given to the Anderson
Independent-Mail on Friday.
   Ms. Roberts, who is from Smyrna, Ga., said she was referring to
an incident in which a black friend who entered an Abbeville
restaurant with her was refused service. She added:
   ``I was shocked that this type of treatment still exists in
America in the '90s _ in the South or anywhere else.''
   In an interview in the Aug. 9 issue of Rolling Stone magazine,
Ms. Roberts said Abbeville was ``horribly racist'' and a ``living
hell.''
   Ms. Roberts was in Abbeville in May filming ``Sleeping With the
Enemy.'' She recently starred with Richard Gere in the box-office
hit ``Pretty Woman.''
   More than 100 upstate South Carolina residents last week
contributed money for a $467 ad that appeared in Wednesday's issue
of Variety. The ad appeared under the heading ``Pretty Woman?
Pretty Low.''
   ``Are there racists here?'' the ad said. ``Perhaps some, as
there are throughout the world. But they do not define us.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>AMES, Iowa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Janet Jackson concert scheduled for Sunday
evening at Iowa State University was postponed because the pop
singer is ill, officials said.
   Ms. Jackson, a sister of pop superstar Michael Jackson, was
being treated for an inner-ear infection. A spokesman at ISU's
Hilton Coliseum said the singer also postponed a concert scheduled
for Saturday night in St. Louis.
   Ms. Jackson is on a national tour to promote ``Rhythm Nation
1814,'' her second album.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>DES MOINES, Iowa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Even though Kathy Swanson is suing
Andrew Dice Clay for $6 million, she wants people to know the
comedian who once was her husband used to be sweet.
   Ms. Swanson, who left her family's rural Iowa farm to seek
success in Hollywood, said she and Clay met in 1980. Their first
date included buying a bottle of wine at a convenience store and
sitting in front of a fake log in his fireplace.
   They spent a chaste night together on the sofa, sleeping, she
said.
   ``It was like he tied me to a pedestal. He was very protective
of me, and that was fine at the time,'' Ms. Swanson said in an
interview with The Des Moines Sunday Register.
   They lived together for four years, married in 1984 and were
divorced two years later.
   Although her ex-husband _ whose act has been criticized as
misogynist, homophobic and otherwise bigoted _ always tended to
view women ``as barefoot, pregnant and walking 10 feet behind
you,'' his barbs grew more vehement, she said.
   Ms. Swanson said Clay manipulated her and that she did not get
her own lawyer when they divorced. Her lawyer now, Marvin
Mitchelson, said the divorce decree paid off $4,000 in debts and
paid Ms. Swanson $1,000 a month for 18 months.
   Her suit seeks $3 million in shared property and an equal amount
in punitive damages.
   Clay's lawyers have declined to comment.
   Ms. Swanson, who played Mel Gibson's wife in the movie ``Lethal
Weapon'' and had the lead in a music video for the group .38
Special, said Clay became angry when she considered a movie role
when they were married.
   But despite the court battle, she said she wants people to know
``that I had a wonderful time with Andrew and that I am sorry that
things had to end so bitterly when they were so sweet for so long.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900805-0031 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-05-90 1255EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Barry-Race Bjt   08-05 0950</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Barry-Race, Bjt,950</SECOND>
<HEAD>Barry Trial Focuses Attention on Race Relations in Nation's
Capital</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By W. DALE NELSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The cocaine and perjury trial of Mayor Marion
Barry has focused attention on race relations in the nation's
capital, a city with a 70 percent black population and little
recent history of racial strife.
   ``I think that there is a perception with a substantial number
of the population that he is being picked on unfairly,'' said
Kenneth Robinson, a local attorney who consulted with Barry's
counsel.
   Robinson is white.
   ``I think the Barry trial is just another indication that people
are very, very sensitive to race and how people are treated,'' said
Ethelbert Miller, a poet who teaches at Howard University.
   Miller is black.
   A U.S. District Court jury began deliberating the Barry case
Thursday afternoon. Two members, both men, are white. One of them
has been chosen jury foreman.
   Barry admits that the trial has brought to the surface ``a
simmering amount of polarization and racism that was already
there.''
   Some blacks agree with Barry's claim that he was the target of
overzealous white prosecutors. Others feel betrayed by the mayor,
who had claimed repeatedly that he didn't use drugs.
   ``The majority of whites are just plain annoyed and angry and
just want this guy to go,'' D.C. Councilman Jim Nathanson said
before the trial began. Nathanson, who is white, represents a
predominantly white district.
   For all the talk about racial polarization, Barry is the one who
was often credited with cooling the tempers that erupted after the
assassination of Martin Luther King Jr. in 1968. Ten people died,
1,191 were reported injured and 7,650 were arrested in the city's
worst riots. Washington was then 63 percent black.
   Some black leaders, Jesse L. Jackson among them, have suggested
that the climate exists for a resurgence of racial violence in
Washington if Barry is convicted.
   Barry himself said it will not. ``Those who would even talk
about that don't represent me, don't represent what I stand for,''
he told reporters last week. ``You obviously don't realize that we
have grown as a people the last 20 years. We will not destroy that
which we have worked so hard to build up.''
   ``To equate this to the violence that would occur when a white
man killed Martin Luther King is asinine,'' Robinson said. ``People
will talk about it in bars and on the street, but I just don't
believe that it is going to happen.''
   ``Some of the noise that you hear is sort of par for the
course,'' said Sam Smith, the white publisher of the Progressive
Review, a Washington opinion journal. ``It's just that more people
are paying attention to it now.''
   The presiding judge in the trial, Thomas Penfield Jackson, is
white. One of the prosecutors, Assistant U.S. Attorney Judith
Retchin, is white. The other, Assistant U.S. Attorney Richard
Roberts, is black. Barry's lawyer, R. Kenneth Mundy, is black.
   Barry has called the case ``a political lynching'' and a case of
``satanic, dirt-like tactics.'' Jackson called it part of an ``ugly
pattern'' of ``white judicial leadership attacking black political
leadership.'' NAACP Executive Director Benjamin Hooks voiced a
similar complaint.
   U.S. Attorney Jay Stephens said he believes in trying cases
``regardless of who the person is or what the political priorities
are.''
   The mayor and his allies have also sharply criticized news media
coverage of the case.
   Abdul Alim Muhammad, a Muslim who is running for Congress in
suburban Prince George's County, Md., said, ``What we are
witnessing in D.C. is like an electronic lynching. In some
respects, the media are no better than the red-necked tobacco
chewing members of the Ku Klux Klan.''
   Louis Farrakhan, leader of the Nation of Islam, has shown his
support for Barry by attending the trial despite efforts by the
judge to have him barred as ``potentially disruptive.''
   Barry, who broke into politics as a street organizer in the
civil rights movement, has been mayor for 12 years. He is not
seeking re-election, and six candidates are running to succeed him.
When one of them, City Council Chairman David Clarke, was
introduced at a rally for black South African leader Nelson
Mandela, he was booed by members of the mostly black audience.
Clarke is white.
   Although he still has a loyal following, especially among poor
blacks, Barry is increasingly viewed as an embarrassment by members
of Washington's large black middle class.
   Long-time civil rights advocate and educator Roger Wilkins, a
past political supporter of the mayor, wrote recently in The
Washington Post: ``Marion Barry used the elders and lied to the
young. He has manipulated thousands of others with his cynical use
of charges of racism to defend his malodorous personal failures.''
   Robert Woodson, president of the National Center for
Neighborhood Enterprise, said Barry ``has certainly created a
racial situation out of something that I do not think was. He is
exploiting tensions and in some cases creating tensions that
otherwise would not have existed.'' Woodson, who is black, was a
member of a White House council on private sector initiatives in
the Reagan administration.
   The Rev. James Bevel, a Barry supporter who conducted prayer
meetings in a tent outside the courthouse through much of the
trial, said; ``It is not affecting basic race relationships or
hostilities in black folks toward white people. I don't see that in
the people I'm around.''
   The Rev. A. Knighton Stanley, the black pastor of People's
Congregational Church, said he avoids raising the issue of possible
violence.
   ``Am I uneasy? My answer is yes,'' said Stanley. ``My judgment
is we will not have it, and my prayer is that my judgment is
right.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900805-0032 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-05-90 1253EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brite-CaptainMom     08-05 0175</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brite-Captain Mom,0182</SECOND>
<HEAD>Army Reserve Captain Returns Son's Salutes</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HARRISBURG, Pa. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Discipline is observed more closely in
the Richardson family than in most others.
   Diane Richardson doesn't just give orders to her 19-year-old
son, Don. She expects him to salute.
   ``He calls me `Captain Mom.' I call him `Private Son,''' said
Capt. Diane Richardson, a 15-year member of the Army Reserve.
   For years her son said he wanted no part of military life.
   ``He was emphatic about not joining the Army,'' said Ms.
Richardson, 38. ``He just didn't like being ordered around.''
   But he joined the Army in March. He leaves Aug. 13 for a
one-year tour of duty in South Korea as a private. The chance to
become a food-service specialist changed his mind.
   ``It's going to be an experience,'' Richardson said.
   Even when the two are in uniform, Mom's captain's bars don't
command absolute respect.
   ``It's a usual mother-son type deal,'' she explained. ``He
doesn't speak to me because he doesn't think I'm saying anything.
But he's a good kid.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900805-0033 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-05-90 1341EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Iraq-U.S.Economy     08-05 0340</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Iraq-U.S. Economy,326</SECOND>
<HEAD>Economist Predicts ``Mild Recession''</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-US-Iraq, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LAWRENCE L. KNUTSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Democratic economist Charles Schultze said
Sunday that Iraq's invasion of oil-rich Kuwait could set off a
``mild recession'' in the United States.
   But he said the situation would become far worse if Iraqi power
spreads and it comes to dominate world oil markets.
   Schultze, who was chairman of the Council of Economic Advisers
during the Carter administration, said he did not expect severe oil
and gasoline shortages of the type that developed in 1979.
   He said he does expect higher energy prices.
   ``The main thing we have to do is distinguish what's going on
now, which is bad for our economy, and is going to raise oil prices
and gasoline prices, but is not going to be catastrophic,''
Schultze said.
   But if (Iraq) is let go and what (could) happen in the long run
really happens, then Katy bar the door,'' he said.''
   ``So short run this is not a big deal economically,'' he said.
``Long run we've got real (potential) problems.''
   Schultze made the comments on the ABC television news program,
``This Week With David Brinkley.''
   Schultze said that if Saddam Hussein, Iraq's military ruler,
were to overrun not only Kuwait but Saudi Arabia and the oil-rich
emirates along the Persian Gulf, the Organization of Petroleum
Exporting Countries or OPEC would move from being merely a cartel
to ``really a controlling monopoly.''
   Schultze said that before Iraqi troops stormed across the border
into Kuwait the U.S. domestic economy was ``probably on the edge of
a recession.''
   ``We might have muddled through without one,'' he said.
   Now, he said, ``My guess is that if nothing else happens it
could kick over into a mild recession.''
   ``We wouldn't like it; it would be costly,'' he said. ``But it
wouldn't be huge.''
   ``But if in the longer run the OPEC oil supplies are really
organized by one person, then we could be in trouble in the long
run seriously,'' Schultze said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900805-0034 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-05-90 1346EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Germany-Unification     08-05 0542</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Germany-Unification,0560</SECOND>
<HEAD>Social Democrats May Press for German Unity This Week</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TERRENCE PETTY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BONN, West Germany (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Signs were mounting Sunday that Social
Democrats in the two Germanys _ the second-largest party in both
countries _ may push for a unified Germany as early as this week.
   Horst Ehmke, deputy chairman of the West German Social
Democrats, reportedly suggested the East German Social Democrats
may propose instant unity during a special parliamentary session
this week.
   Asked by the newspaper Bild whether the East German Social
Democrats might make such a move during the Wednesday session in
East Berlin, Ehmke reportedly replied: ``I don't know. I don't
exclude it.''
   The Social Democratic parties in both Germanys are in close
consultation with one another.
   The East German Social Democrats are part of Prime Minister
Lothar de Maiziere's broad coalition government. The West German
Social Democrats are the main opposition to Chancellor Helmut Kohl.
   On Saturday, the head of the West German Social Democrats,
Hans-Jochen Vogel, said West Germany would have to ``respect'' a
decision by East Germany's Parliament for an ``early joining'' to
the west before all-German elections.
   Other West German Social Democrats have echoed that view in the
past two days. The move is most likely an effort to improve the
party's chances of winning the leadership of a united Germany when
all-German elections take place.
   The Social Democrats' apparent maneuvering comes as Kohl presses
to have all-German elections moved up from Dec. 2 to Oct. 14. Under
that scheme, formal unity would occur immediately before the vote.
   Kohl's Christian Democrats want all-German elections to take
place quickly to avoid a potential loss of voter support if the
East German economy collapses.
   Joblessness in East Germany has climbed to more than 240,000
after the July 2 economic merger of the two Germanys and is
expected to move much higher.
   Social Democrats are fighting to keep the elections from being
moved up to Oct. 14.
   But the Social Democrats now say they would accept actual
unification much sooner because of East Germany's economic problems.
   That would allow them to be perceived as embracing a process
they have tried to slow, while still pushing for elections in
December, when the economic woes are expected to be much worse.
   Whether all-German elections occur on Dec. 2 or Oct. 14 hinges
on Kohl's ability to persuade the West German Parliament to make a
constitutional change necessary for the earlier date.
   For that, Kohl needs a two-thirds majority vote he can't manage
without the Social Democrats.
   Oskar Lafontaine, Kohl's Social Democratic rival for the
chancellorship of a united Germany has vowed to block Kohl's plan.
   Kohl himself seemed to acknowledge that pushing the idea through
West Germany's Parliament will be harder than expected.
   ``Kohl's panicky proposal clearly shows that he sees his chances
vanishing every day,'' Lafontaine told the Sueddeutsche Zeitung in
a report released to other news media in advance of Monday's
publication.
   Seiters also announced that Kohl and Hans-Jochen Vogel, federal
leader of the Social Democrats, would meet on Tuesday to try to
reach agreement on the elections.
   The proposal to move up the all-German vote to Oct. 14 was made
public Friday by de Maiziere, following consultations with Kohl.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900805-0035 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-05-90 1355EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Liberia-Rebels     08-05 0551</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Liberia-Rebels,0566</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rebels Say They Almost Fired on U.S. Troops During Mission</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-US-Liberia, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MICHELLE FAUL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ABIDJAN, Ivory Coast (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Liberian rebels said they nearly
fired on U.S. military aircraft Sunday during an evacuation
operation because they had not been informed of the mission.
   Earlier Sunday, rebel leader Charles Taylor appealled to all
Liberians to ``oppose all foreign intervention'' and accused the
U.S. of a mounting ``new colonization'' drive. But he made the
comments before it was clear the U.S. planes were on an evacuation
mission.
   More than 200 airborne U.S. Marines swept into Liberia early
Sunday to evacuate Americans after Taylor's rival, Prince Johnson,
ordered the seizure of foreigners, especially Americans, Britons,
Indians and Lebanese, on Monday.
   Johnson said he hoped to provoke international intervention in
the 7-month-old tribal war targeted at Liberian President Samuel
Doe, who remained holed up in his mansion in Monrovia, the capital.
   Doe on Sunday welcomed the U.S. operation, saying it was needed
to protect American lives. In the past he has asked the 2,100
Marines stationed offshore to help end the conflict.
   Tom Woewiyu, defense minister in Taylor's self-declared
government-in-exile, said the United States in the past has kept
Taylor's rebels informed of its moves but this time said nothing.
   ``We are protesting this,'' Woewiyu said. The United States is
``trying to sneak around and do a wholly clandestine operation
which only confuses the situation ... a situation where an accident
will be caused and someone will blame us.''
   Liberian rebels were just receiving orders to fire on the
incoming U.S. helicopters Sunday when they found out about the
operation, Woewiyu said.
   He said the rebel order to fire was being sent by radio when a
U.S. transmission broke into the frequency identifying the aircraft
as U.S. planes.
   Once it was established the U.S. aircraft were in Monrovia for
an evacuation and permission was given, ``they landed and they have
been doing the evacuation with our forces watching and there has
been no incident,'' Woewiyu said.
   In the confusion during the evacuation, Taylor broadcast an
appeal over radio calling for a mass mobilization by Liberians ``to
defend your country'' and ``oppose all foreign intervention.''
   ``It is evident that all this is orchestrated to keep Samuel Doe
in power,'' Taylor said in the broadcast from a station in the
northern town of Yekepa. ``We are confronted with the challenge of
a new colonization as in the times of slavery.''
   Taylor has a much larger army than Johnson's, but thousands are
young recruits with little training and they have been bogged down
by government troops six miles east of Doe's mansion. Johnson's men
had reached to within hundreds of yards of the presidential
residence when they withdraw to confront Taylor's troops
approaching from their rear.
   Leaders of seven West African states are scheduled to meet in
Banjul, Gambia, on Monday to discuss the conflict and Nigerian
proposals to send in a task force to end the war.
   About 5,000 people, mostly civilians, have been killed in the
fighting. On July 30, about 600 civilians in a Lutheran church
compound were massacred. Witnesses blamed government troops, but
the government said they were rebels dressed as government troops.
   The rebels accuse Doe, who took power in a 1980 coup, of
corruption.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900805-0036 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-05-90 1356EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Dukakis-Presidency     08-05 0402</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Dukakis-Presidency,420</SECOND>
<NOTE>For release 6 p.m. EDT, TIME set by source.</NOTE>
<HEAD>Dukakis Thinks of Giving Presidency Another Go</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN DIAMOND</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Democrats, get out your checkbooks and dig out
those 1988 buttons, the Duke thinks he might want to give it
another try.
   Massachusetts Gov. Michael S. Dukakis, he of the plummeting poll
ratings and slumping state budget, hasn't ruled anything out for
'92.
   In a television interview broadcast Sunday, the 1988 Democratic
nominee sounded like a man ready to get up off the canvas and go
another round.
   ``Can you ever see yourself running for President again?'' the
governor was asked on C-SPAN, a cable TV public affairs network.
   ``Maybe. Maybe,'' Dukakis said.
   ``I don't think you rule it out, I don't think you rule it in,''
he said. ``Kitty and I are still relatively young, we've still got
our health, we've got a lot of energy, it's an exciting and
wondrous world out there these days, as we read about the
cataclysmic changes every day internationally and otherwise.''
   The comments were only a slight advance from what Dukakis has
been saying all along since his crushing defeat at the hands of
George Bush two years ago. ``Never say never,'' has been the
consistent Dukakis line.
   ``I want to keep my hand in public life,'' he said in response
to the latest queries. ``What form that takes I don't know.''
   Marty Linsky, a political analyst at Harvard's John F. Kennedy
School of Government and a longtime acquaintance of Dukakis, found
a dry way of depicting the governor's chances.
   ``There certainly doesn't seem to be much external data for
it,'' Linsky said. He cited a recent presidential preference poll
of Democratic National Committee members in which not a single
member mentioned Dukakis.
   Dukakis is retiring from the governor's office in January after
three terms. Polling data, editorials and political commentary seem
to hold that up as a wise decision.
   Since losing to Bush, Dukakis has come home to a state beset by
budget shortfalls, the specter of tax increases and an electorate
angry with his administration.
   For now, Dukakis said, ``I want to finish up my final year as
governor as strong as I possibly can, leave a good solid state for
my successor, and then Kitty and I will kind of take a look at the
world and decide where we go from here.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900805-0037 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-05-90 1403EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Philippines     08-05 0237</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Philippines,0245</SECOND>
<HEAD>Philippines Places Troops on Alert Following Reports of Coup
Attempt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MANILA, Philippines (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Officials ordered troops to their
barracks Sunday after intelligence reports said dissident soldiers
would make another attempt to topple President Corazon Aquino, a
military spokesman said.
   The spokesman, Lt. Col. Cresencio Maralit did not give details
on the reported coup attempt, nor its duration. Mrs. Aquino has
survived at least six coup attepts during her four-year term.
   ``Unconfirmed reports about another coup attempt by rebel
elements prompted the Philippine Constabulary to raise alert
status,'' Maralit told reporters.
   The red alert was ordered in the headquarters of the army, air
force, constabulary and the Capital Command, said Brig. Gen.
Lisandro Abadia, operations chief of the Armed Forces of the
Philippines.
   The Northern Luzon Command in Tarlac province and the armed
forces training command in Rizal province outside Manila were also
included in the order.
   In a red alert, soldiers are ordered to barracks. Mobile patrols
were stepped up in the capital, said Capital Command chief Brig.
Gen. Marino Filart.
   On Dec. 1, mutineers belonging to the Reform the Armed Forces
Movement, launched a nine-day coup attempt that killed 113 people
and wounded about 600.
   Since last year's failed coup, renegades have been threatening
to strike. But a devastating earthquake that rocked Luzon island
last month prompted dissidents to offer a cease-fire to help
rebuild the nation.
   Mrs. Aquino rejected the proposal.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900805-0038 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-05-90 1414EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p AM-Silber     08-05 0671</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Silber,800</SECOND>
<HEAD>BU President Adds Press to List of Gubernatorial Foes</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By EVE EPSTEIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Democrat John Silber's shoot-from-the-hip style
has transformed him from a candidate who barely qualified for the
Massachusetts primary election ballot into a central character in
its governor's race.
   The outspoken Boston University president dominated headlines
again last week, this time by taking aim at the headline writers.
   Silber stormed into the cafeteria of The Boston Globe to
announce he would stop participating in candidate forums sponsored
by the Globe and by the Boston Herald.
   The reason, he said, was that the newspapers were distorting his
views.
   ``There's one thing to be said for live television,'' said
Silber, who is on leave from his post at BU, where he was president
for 20 years. ``There is no editing, and there is no way of putting
a person's thumb on the scales.''
   And with that, the 63-year-old philosopher and administrator who
refuses to talk political ``plastic'' once again made himself the
issue.
   According to Silber, he is running against a former state
attorney general and the lieutenant governor in the Democratic
primary, as well as a press that focuses mainly on sensational
comments instead of his overall views.
   He has made blunt remarks about everything from welfare to
feminists, giving him a public profile distinctly different from
the Democrat he hopes to replace, retiring three-term Gov. Michael
S. Dukakis.
   The remark that created the biggest furor came during an early
Globe forum on health care. In commenting on how best to distribute
health care funds, he referred to extraordinary and costly health
care measures to prolong the life of the elderly. He then let loose
with what has come to be known as a ``Silber shocker.''
   ``When you've had a long life, and you're ripe, then it's time
to go,'' he said.
   Silber cried foul when one of his Democratic opponents, former
Attorney General Francis X. Bellotti, used the quote in a campaign
ad.
   Back in January, in the midst of putting forth the view that
Massachusetts' welfare policies were attracting people from
out-of-state, Silber said: ``Why should Lowell be the Cambodian
capital of America? It is extraordinary. Why should they all be
concentrated in one place?''
   And more recently, at a forum on women's issues, he said in
response to questions about judicial appointments: ``I would not
put a white supremacist on the court for fear a black could not get
a fair trial in his court. Neither would I put somebody like Louis
Farrakhan on the bench who I think might discriminate against
whites. Likewise, I would not appoint Gloria Steinem to the bench.''
   That brought him criticism for lumping Steinem with Farrakhan
and white supremacists.
   As the newspaper forums progressed, Silber became the issue _
even when he missed one and left the field open for Bellotti and
Lt. Gov. Evelyn Murphy, the third Democrat seeking the governor's
seat.
   After Silber dropped out of the forum, his opponents immediately
said the academic administrator, making his first run for public
office, couldn't take the rough-and-tumble of political debate.
   ``If you can't stand the political heat, John, then maybe you
should get out of the campaign kitchen,'' Murphy said.
   Public opinion polls have shown Silber and Bellotti in a dead
heat, with Murphy slightly behind in the running for the Sept. 18
primary.
   In the Republican race, House Minority Leader Steven Pierce has
held a comfortable lead over his lone opponent, former U.S.
Attorney William Weld. But polls also showed Pierce well behind
Silber and Bellotti.
   Former U.S. Sen. Paul Tsongas welcomed Silber's entry into the
race, anticipating Silber's presence would elevate the level of
debate. But he said Silber must share the blame when the substance
of his remarks is lost.
   ``The media has run with things and has blown certain statements
out of proportion, but `twas ever so,'' Tsongas said. ``That will
always be the case if you speak in terms that lend themselves to
that sort of thing.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900805-0039 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-05-90 1437EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Iraq-WorldReaction Bjt   08-05 0787</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Iraq-World Reaction, Bjt,0809</SECOND>
<HEAD>Japan Imposes Ban on Iraqi Oil</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVID THURBER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Japan on Sunday imposed tough sanctions against
Iraq for its invasion of Kuwait, including a ban on oil imports and
Japanese exports to the two countries.
   The unprecedented Japanese move, which significantly broadened a
U.S.-supported campaign to isolate Iraq for its invasion, followed
an announcement by China that it would not sell arms to Iraq.
   Italy and Spain _ two European Community countries most
dependent on foreign crude oil _ also announced Sunday they would
follow EC guidelines and impose sanctions.
   In Kuwait, the Iraqi-installed provisional government, in a
statement carried by the Iraqi News Agency, told other countries to
refrain from taking ``punishing measures'' against it or Iraq. The
provisional government said countries ``have to remember they have
interests and citizens in Kuwait'' and said it was prepared to
close embassies and cut diplomatic relations with offending nations.
   The United States already has banned oil imports from Kuwait and
Iraq and frozen both countries' assets in the United States.
   Japan said it will suspend loans and ban Japanese investment and
financing in both Iraq and Kuwait, and freeze Iraqi assets in
Japan, chief government spokesman Misoji Sakamoto said.
   Iraq became eligible in February for $2.67 billion in Japanese
government credits, which it had not yet received.
   ``International conflicts must be settled peacefully. From this
standpoint, we strongly denounce the Iraqi military invasion of
Kuwait,'' Sakamoto said. ``The government will fully support
international efforts to settle the dispute through negotiations.''
   In Washington, the White House hailed Japan's decision. It said
Prime Minister Toshiki Kaifu called President Bush on Sunday to
inform him of the sanctions.
   ``These unprecedented measures undertaken by Japan are in step
with those that the United States and other countries have put in
place against Iraq for its blatant aggression against Kuwait,''
White House press secretary Marlin Fitzwater said.
   ``The president welcomed Prime Minister Kaifu's and the Japanese
Cabinet's decision and expressed confidence that such measures will
help intensify international pressures aimed at achieving the
immediate, complete and unconditional withdrawal of Iraq from
Kuwait,'' Fitzwater said.
   On Saturday, Bush telephoned Kaifu to ask for Japan's support in
sanctions against Iraq, and all 100 members of the U.S. Senate
signed a letter urging Tokyo to join other nations that have
imposed sanctions.
   The sanctions, which exceeded those imposed Saturday by the
European Community, are the toughest that postwar Japan has ever
imposed, the Japan Broadcasting Corp. reported.
   News reports said the decision had been delayed because of
differences of views within the government. The Foreign Ministry
reportedly urged the government to join its Western allies in
imposing sanctions, while the trade ministry warned of resulting
damage to Japan's economy.
   Japanese newspapers said some trade ministry officials had
expressed concern that sanctions on Iraq would push up oil prices
in Japan and worsen chances for Baghdad's repayment of $4.6 billion
in outstanding debts with Japan. Much of that is held by the
private sector.
   Japan depends on foreign sources for 99 percent of its oil
needs, and imported an average of 260,000 barrels a day, or 6.2
percent of its total consumption, from Iraq in the first quarter of
this year. It obtained 5 percent of its oil from Kuwait, or 210,000
barrels a day, according to the trade ministry.
   On Friday, the Japanese government instructed banks and other
financial institutions to block Iraqi access to the estimated $20
billion in Kuwaiti assets held in Japan.
   Following that decision, officials initially said they would
wait to decide on further measures until the U.N. Security Council
takes action on a resolution calling for sanctions. The council may
discuss the resolution on Monday.
   In Beijing, the official Xinhua news agency quoted an
unidentified Foreign Ministry spokesman as saying China supported
the U.N. Security Council resolution condemning Iraq's invasion of
Kuwait, and would therefore not sell arms to Iraq.
   Spain's foreign ministry issued a communique Sunday saying Spain
would require government approval for any foreign transfer of
Kuwaiti assets in Spain and would soon freeze Iraqi assets.
   The communique said the measures were in line with the EC
sanctions, which included an oil embargo on Iraq and Iraqi-occupied
Kuwait, a halt on arms sales to Iraq and the suspension of
cooperation with Iraq in the military, technical and scientific
fields.
   Nearly 11 percent of the EC's oil imports last year were from
Iraq and Kuwait.
   In Italy, Justice Minister Giuliano Vassalli said Italy agreed
to freeze Iraqi assets.The government on Friday froze Kuwaiti
assets held in Italy and suspended arms shipments to Iraq.
   The Soviet Union, Iraq's main arms supplier, announced Thursday
it was ending arms sales to Iraq.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900805-0040 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-05-90 1443EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p AM-FloridaRace     08-05 0676</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Florida Race,0696</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ex-Klansman, Impeached Black Judge Join Newspaperman in Florida
Race</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CURT ANDERSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TALLAHASSEE, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A former Ku Klux Klan grand dragon, an
impeached black federal judge and a self-described ``salty old
newspaperman'' are battling in a primary campaign for a state
Cabinet post that they insist won't focus solely on race.
   But the ex-judge, Alcee Hastings of Miami, said the last-minute
entry of John Paul Rogers, former United Klans of America leader,
into the Democratic primary for Florida secretary of state has
forced him to switch to a campaign based on civil rights because of
the emotions a Klansman can stir.
   ``I'm not going to let him get a free ride,'' Hastings said. ``I
didn't want to run a civil rights campaign. The color of my skin
shouldn't have anything to do with the issues I'm presenting.''
   Hastings said he takes Rogers seriously, but can see some humor
in the contrast between an avowed racist and a black liberal former
judge.
   ``If Rogers doesn't burn any crosses in my community, I won't
spit any watermelon seeds in his,'' Hastings said.
   Rogers, who entered the race just before the deadline July 20;
Hastings; and former Tallahassee Democrat editorial writer Jim
Minter are seeking the Democratic nod in the Sept. 4 primary to
oppose Republican incumbent Jim Smith for secretary of state. The
post is one of six Florida Cabinet positions elected statewide.
   The main duties of the job are to run the state's elections,
keep corporate records and file financial disclosure forms turned
in by elected and appointed officials. But there's more to it than
just that: As one of the Cabinet posts, the office also shares
power with the governor on a wide range of statewide issues, from
environmental conservation to education.
   Smith, who only recently switched to the GOP, got more than 2.6
million votes in the 1986 election and will be a favorite against
any of the three Democrats.
   Rogers, a Lake Wales barber and real estate agent, said he left
the Klan 2{ years ago.
   Rogers, who has unsuccessfully run for the state House and for a
couple of local offices, refused to renounce the Klan's supremacist
philosophy but said race and Hastings didn't figure in his decision
to run.
   ``I hope people won't vote for or against me based on race,''
Rogers said. ``I haven't injected it at all, and I don't plan to. I
hope people will vote on the issues.''
   Florida Democratic Party Chairman Simon Ferro has flatly
declared the party would never support the ex-Klansman if he's the
nominee.
   Yet Ferro says he would have no problem backing Hastings, who
was aquitted of bribery charges in federal court but impeached in
1989 by the Senate over claims of an alleged payment to reduce
sentences for racketeers. Hastings has always maintained his
innocence.
   ``He was impeached, but that doesn't take away his rights to
elective office and his right to have the voters judge his
abilities and record,'' Ferro said. ``It does not go to the core
problem of a person belonging to a hate organization.''
   Rogers has tried to turn the tables on Ferro by claiming
discrimination.
   ``I consider this to be highly prejudicial and insensitive
bigotry,'' Rogers said.
   Hastings has concentrated his campaign in South Florida, where
he appeals to solid voting blocs of minorities who agree with his
claim that the government railroaded him.
   ``People are empathetic, sympathetic when they hear the facts of
the case. They are outraged,'' he said.
   Minter hopes to benefit from the clash between his two opponents.
   Minter began covering politics for The Miami Herald in 1968. He
has spent time in state government, including a stint working for
former Secretary of State George Firestone and some time as a
speechwriter for former Gov. Reubin Askew. He resigned from the
editorial board of the Talahassee Democrat to join this year's
campaign.
   ``I'm the Tallahassee pro here,'' Minter said. ``I have been an
insider in state government, and I've covered it as a
newspaperman.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900805-0041 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-05-90 1444EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-EastGermany-Train     08-05 0089</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-East Germany-Train,0091</SECOND>
<HEAD>34 Injured When Passenger Train Derails</HEAD>
<DATELINE>EAST BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A passenger train traveling from Berlin to
Dresden derailed Sunday and four cars tumbled down an embankment,
injuring 34 people, East Germany's news agency said.
   The train was traveling near Boehla, just northwest of Dresden,
when it derailed, ADN reported. Dresden is about 125 miles south of
Berlin.
   The news agency said 34 people were injured and that 25 of them
were taken to a hospital.
   The cause of the derailment was not immediately known.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900805-0042 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-05-90 1453EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-RuralReport     08-05 0683</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Rural Report,690</SECOND>
<NOTE>For release 6:30 p.m. EDT, TIME set by source</NOTE>
<HEAD>Report Criticizes Federal Rural Development Policy</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DON KENDALL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Farm Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A dearth of federal dollars and good program
management means rural and small-town Americans continue to suffer
needlessly from poverty and pollution, a year-long study concludes.
   The report by the Center for Community Change, criticized the
Farmers Home Administration for being run by people lacking
backgrounds in ``finance, civil engineering and organizing,'' and
blamed the Reagan administration for serious funding cutbacks.
   The FmHA, an Agriculture Department Agency that has its roots in
the Great Depression of the 1930s, handles a variety of farm,
housing and community programs.
   ``Federal support for rural development was cut by nearly 70
percent during the Reagan administration,'' said Robert Rapoza, who
directed the study. ``Yet the majority of the remaining funds
failed to reach the neediest rural communities. The federal
response to these communities has been plainly inadequate.''
   The report _ ``Searching for the Way That Works'' _ said rural
problems include:
   _Unemployment, adjusted to include underemployment, is one-third
higher than in the cities.
   _Rural Americans are more likely to be poor. One-third more
rural people than urban residents are below the poverty line.
   _Ninety-seven percent of the nation's rural residents rely on
ground water for drinking. Yet, a 1984 survey by the Environmental
Protection Administration found two-thirds of the wells were
contaminated.
   _Almost two million rural residents live in substandard housing,
usually lacking adequate plumbing.
   _Maternal and infant mortality rates are substantially higher
than in urban areas and are rising at faster rates.
   ``Rural residents are, as a group, less educated, less healthy
and less skilled than their urban counterparts,'' the report
said.''They operate in a comparatively static, more conservative
business environment, and they receive less help from Washington.''
   The center, a non-profit advocacy group for low-income rural
people, conducted the study with a grant from the Ford Foundation.
   Joe O'Neill, a spokesman for the FmHA, said the agency had not
had the opportunity to study the report. But he said, ``We're
always pleased to get these kinds of studies ... and they can be
very useful.''
   The report criticized the FmHA for not targeting more of its
resources to poor communities to help build water and sewer
systems, health centers, fire houses and businesses. These programs
add up to about $900 million this year.
   According to the report, poverty-level communities got only 2
percent to 3 percent of total FmHA loans and grants for water and
sewer facilities between 1985 and 1988.
   The report said one reason for not targeting on the poorest
communities is the way FmHA uses poverty data.
   While the agency adjusts the poverty line upward each year, it
uses 1980 census numbers to determine the average income of
individual communities, it said. Thus, some communities whose
average income exceeded the poverty level in 1980 now fall under
today's higher poverty line.
   The effect, according to the report, is that those communities
qualify for FmHA assistance, even though others are much poorer.
   Programs operated by the Environmental Protection Agency also
were criticized for failing to provide more help for rural areas to
meet federal water standards.
   ``EPA figures indicate that two-thirds of rural water supplies
violate agency drinking water standards,'' said Maureen Kennedy,
principal author of the report. ``Given this need, it is disturbing
that the EPA has naot provided more support to rural areas.''
   The report hedged on recommending a vast reorganization of
federal rural development programs, such as blending them all into
one super agency. But it did propose some administrative changes
within USDA's hierarchy.
   Also, it said many communities lack the know-how for getting
access to federal programs that might help them develop.
   Futher, the report said most FmHA staff people come from
agricultural backgrounds ``despite the fact that these programs
demand training in finance, civil engineering and organizing.''
   Consequently, ``FmHA should strengthen its substantive training
programs, but more importantly, the agency should focus its
recruiting efforts on those with backgrounds appropriate to the
changing needs of the agency,'' the report said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900805-0043 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-05-90 1454EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ZenBakery Bjt   08-05 0648</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Zen Bakery, Bjt,0668</SECOND>
<HEAD>Zen Bakery Turns Cookie Making Into a Religious Experience</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY24</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KILEY ARMSTRONG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>YONKERS, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Food critics often liken Bernard Glassman's
gourmet cakes and tortes to paradise.
   But this Brooklyn-born Zen Buddhist abbot is concerned with
earthly missions, like providing job skills and housing for the
disadvantaged and trying to save South American rain forests.
   Browsers at Bloomingdale's, weekenders in Long Island's
fashionable Hamptons, and diners at Sardi's regularly savor
Glassman's Greyston Bakery goodies, which are sold in 300 gourmet
shops and restaurants nationwide.
   Greyston also provides the Vermont-based Ben &amp; Jerry's ice cream
company with the brownies that go into its Chocolate Fudge Brownie
ice cream.
   And soon, the two socially conscious companies will market a new
chocolate-chip cookie, which they hope will not only taste good but
help save trees in the Brazilian rain forest and provide work for
the homeless in this New York suburb.
   Greyston and its sibling companies have taught job skills to
some 200 homeless and those at risk of losing their homes since
1982.
   Come fall, the company plans to use its profits and federal and
state aid to renovate buildings near the bakery, which will be
owned and managed by the formerly homeless tenants.
   Glassman describes the entrepreneurial effort as a mandala, or
circle of activities, fostering jobs, social action and interfaith
expression.
   The term mandala symbolizes a wholeness for which one strives in
Buddhism, a religion and philosophic system which teaches that
right thinking and self-denial will enable the soul to reach
Nirvana _ a divine state of release from misdirected desire.
   The Zen sect seeks to attain an intuitive illumination of mind
and spirit through meditation.
   All of the profits from the bakery and two other Zen-operated
businesses _ one that trains minority construction workers and
another that trains poorly paid office workers for jobs in the
bakery and construction company _ goes into the Greyston Family
Inn, a Zen-run social services agency.
   Glassman, who became a Zen monk in 1970 and quit his aerospace
engineer job a few years later, oversees agency operations from the
bakery, a former lasagne factory in a rundown section of downtown
Yonkers.
   Glassman, who has slipped on a white smock that identifies him
as the ``sensei'' or teacher, says he started the bakery with
$40,000 from the Yonkers Private Industry Council.
   When it started in 1983, the bakery had sales of $282,000. This
year, Glassman expects to bring in $1.8 million.
   Glassman said initial sales were made on the strength of the
product, not on the activist philosophy, but that's changing.
``Only in the last few years has the fact that we're involved in
social action even been noticed,'' he said.
   Three years ago, Glassman met Ben Cohen, co-founder of Ben &amp;
Jerry's, at a gathering of activist entrepreneurs. The two hit it
off, and the brownie deal was quickly sealed.
   Soon, Greyston will begin making chocolate chip cookies with nut
flour, a leftover from a Ben &amp; Jerry's offshoot that uses Brazil
nuts, grown in the Amazon rain forest, for ``Rainforest Crunch''
candy and ice cream. The businessmen believe that promoting nuts as
a cash crop will encourage Brazilians to maintain the rain forest.
   ``Eat a cookie, save a tree,'' proclaims Glassman.
   Bakery workers, who include 30 non-Zen people from the
neighborhood, come from El Salvador, India, Haiti, Puerto Rico.
   Carmelo Pagan, who worked his way up from dishwasher to bakery
supervisor, calls the company ``amazing _ the friendship, the
togetherness. We're trying to help the community.''
   Millie Medina spun a lemon mousse cake on a pedestal, smoothing
the buttercream, carving a design on the side and piping
sophisticated swirls onto the top. With a shy smile, she said she
used to be on welfare, but now, her friends are impressed by her
achievements.
   ``And,'' she added, ``so am I.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900805-0044 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-05-90 1521EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-PapuaNewGuinea     08-05 0193</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Papua New Guinea,0197</SECOND>
<HEAD>Papua New Guinea, Rebels Sign Peace Accord</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WELLINGTON, New Zealand (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Papua New Guinea and separatists
on the island of Bougainville have signed a peace accord that could
end a two-year war that has claimed more than 100 lives, New
Zealand announced Sunday.
   The reported agreement followed peace talks on a New Zealand
naval supply ship.
   A brief New Zealand government statement said the accord had
been signed Sunday by Papua New Guinea and rebel leaders but gave
no other details.
   The campaign began in 1988 when militants demanding a referendum
on secession. A state of emergency was declared on June 26, 1989,
and hundreds of soldiers were sent to the island in an attempt to
put down the rebellion.
   But government security forces were withdrawn in March of this
year, and a unilateral declaration of independence was made by the
rebels two months later.
   The government had offered to restore essential services but
demanded that general duty police be allowed back on the island.
   Bougainville leaders wanted a resumption of key services such as
health care, education, telecommunications and banking as a
condition for further talks.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900805-0045 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-05-90 1528EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-JailedMarine     08-05 0671</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Jailed Marine,0694</SECOND>
<HEAD>Parents Try To Free Marine Who Confessed To Drug Use Though Test
Was Negative</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT IMRIE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>STONE LAKE, Wis. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Marine who pleaded guilty to using LSD
on a Hawaii military base is serving five years in the brig even
though a urine test showed no trace of drugs in his body.
   The parents of Pfc. Charles Serauskas, 21, of Stone Lake in
northwestern Wisconsin have already spent $20,000 to bring an
appeal. They say their son was still drunk and suffering from
depression when he confessed to using and distributing LSD, or what
he thought was LSD, at a barracks party last Oct. 13.
   Court records indicate that no drugs were found on Serauskas,
and a urinalysis taken just hours his arrest on the night of the
party turned up no sign of the drug. The sample has since been
destroyed.
   ``We are going to fight them,'' said Serauskas' father, Leonard.
``I can't believe in this country you can be convicted when there
is no evidence against you.''
   ``Their son confessed he's guilty,'' countered Capt. Leonard
Ryan, a spokesman for the Marine Corps Air Station at Kaneohe Bay,
Hawaii, where Serauskas was arrested. ``In that case, there doesn't
have to be evidence.''
   Military records show that five other Marines who testified they
received LSD from Serauskas were tested for drugs just hours after
the party, and no evidence of drugs was found in their urine,
either.
   Serauskas made a second confession at a sentencing hearing, but
his family claims he was given bad advice by his military lawyer
who advised him to plead guilty in hopes of getting a lenient
sentence of no more than two years.
   Instead, Serauskas was sentenced to seven years, later reduced
to five years, in the Pearl Harbor guardhouse.
   An appeal is pending before the Military Court of Review in
Washington. If it fails, the case will be taken through civilian
courts, the family said.
   Serauskas drank at least a case of beer and some whiskey at the
party.
   With a confession of intent to use drugs, physical evidence was
unnecessary, the military argued.
   Chief Warrant Office Randy Gaddo, a spokesman for Marine Corps
headquarters in Washington, said a person's intent to commit a
crime is considered to be evidence in both military and civilian
courts, but ``the intent would weigh in with other evidence and
other circumstances.''
   The Serauskas family allege that the military's witnesses were
intimidated.
   ``This case isn't a legal technicality. This case is a lack of
evidence,'' said Robert Finlay, a Hawaii lawyer hired by the family.
   ``He is the farthest thing from a dope dealer that ever was,''
Finlay said. ``Maybe he is guilty as hell, but they sure couldn't
prove it.''
   Finlay said he has found evidence that the five other Marines
were threatened by military officers to testify against Serauskas
or risk being sent to the brig on various charges.
   Military prosecutors acknowledged that the five were questioned
before a panel of seven officers. Court records indicate they were
urged to tell the truth and prison punishment was discussed.
   The five were later given honorable discharges.
   The military judge who reviewed and then denied Serauskas'
motion for retrial made no reference to the threats or the
discharged soldiers. He ruled Serauskas was competent and
understood the implications of his guilty plea.
   In transcripts from his court-martial, Serauskas, an artillery
cannoneer, told the judge he purchased what he believed were 14
doses, or ``hits,'' of LSD from a fellow Marine.
   He told the judge he ate three hits. ``It made me kind of
paranoid, sir, and I felt high, sir; see colors, the walls move,''
he said.
   According to court records, Serauskas had received several
Marine citations during his three-year career. But he also had been
cited for unexcused absences from a therapy program, drunken
driving and making false statements. Before his arrest, his rank
had been reduced from lance corporal to private first class in a
disciplinary action.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900805-0046 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-05-90 1546EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Kuwait-Hostages     08-05 0446</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Kuwait-Hostages,0461</SECOND>
<HEAD>Conflicting Reports on Prisoners Linked to Western Hostages
^With AM-Iraq-Kuwait, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NICOSIA, Cyprus (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Diplomatic sources said Sunday that Iraq
may have executed 15 pro-Iranian terrorists whose freedom was
demanded by factions holding Western hostages in Lebanon.
   But there were conflicting reports of the fate of the
terrorists, who had been held in a Kuwaiti prison until Iraq's
invasion of the emirate Thursday.
   Other diplomats said the Kuwaiti prisoners had been taken to
Baghdad, and a third report said the Shiite Moslem prisoners
escaped during the invasion.
   The pro-Iranian Islamic Jihad, or Islamic Holy War, has
repeatedly demanded that comrades jailed in Kuwait for bombing the
U.S. and French embassies be released before it will free Western
hostages.
   Seventeen men, mostly Iranian and Iraqi Shiite Moslems, were
jailed in Kuwait in February 1984 for the Dec. 12, 1983, car
bombings that killed five people and wounded 86.
   Two were released in February 1989 after serving five-year
sentences. The Kuwaitis have repeatedly refused to free any of the
others, including three who'd been condemned to death but whose
sentences have not been carried out.
   The Kuwaitis have identified the bombers as members of the
pro-Iranian Ad-Dawa, Arabic for Islamic Call, an Iraqi group that
seeks to topple Saddam's government in Baghdad.
   Diplomatic sources in the Persian Gulf, speaking on condition of
anonymity, said Sunday they believed the 15 had been executed
because of their membership in Ad-Dawa. The report could not be
confirmed by official sources.
   However, Kuwaiti Embassy officials in Amman, Jordan, citing
reports from ``reliable, official and political sources in
Kuwait,'' said the prisoners were seized by Iraqis and taken to
Baghdad, apparently to be used by President Saddam Hussein and used
as a bargaining chip.
   A senior Kuwaiti Embassy official, speaking to The Associated
Press on condition of anonymity, said official reports to the
embassy said that Iraq seized the prisoners on Saturday.
   Iraqi Embassy officials said they had no information on that
report.
   Radio Monte Carlo said Arab press sources had quoted a foreign
resident of Kuwait as saying that the 15 were among 1,300 prisoners
who escaped during the turmoil of the invasion. Forty-five
political prisoners were reportedly among the escapees.
   That report also could not be confirmed by oficial sources.
   On Friday, the ABC television network reported that the
prisoners were freed after the invasion, but gave no further
details.
   The Iranian-backed Hezbollah, or Party of God, believed to be
the umbrella group for factions holding 16 Westerners hostage in
Lebanon, withheld comment on that report. The longest held hostage
is Terry Anderson, chief Middle East correspondent for The
Associated Press. He was kidnapped March 16, 1985.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900805-0047 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-05-90 1615EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Iraq-Turkey     08-05 0330</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Iraq-Turkey,0343</SECOND>
<HEAD>Iraqi Official Warns Turkey not to Cut Iraqi Pipeline</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Iraq-Kuwait, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ZEYNEP ALEMDAR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ANKARA, Turkey (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A top Iraqi official warned Turkey on
Sunday not to cut two pipelines in Turkey that carry more than half
of Iraq's total oil exports.
   President Bush had suggested Friday that Turkey could close the
pipelines to protest Iraq's invasion of Kuwait.
   Iraqi Deputy Prime Minister Taha Yassin Ramadan told reporters
that ``a ``a Turkish decision to shut down the pipeline would
create mistrust'' between the two countries.
   ``In the case of an economic embargo or a military intervention,
those who take these actions would be the losing party,'' he added.
   Ramadan met with President Turgut Ozal during his four-hour
visit to the capital of Ankara.
   A spokesman for Ozal, Kaya Toperi, said Ramadan delivered a
message from Iraqi President Saddam Hussein explaining why Iraq
invaded. There was no further information on the message.
   The Turkish presidential office said Ozal, in his meeting with
Ramadan, called on Iraq to adopt ``a realistic and constructive
attitude urgently.''
   President Bush said Friday it was ``certainly an option'' for
Turkey to cut the Iraqi pipelines. Bush spoke by telephone to Ozal
on Friday and Saturday.
   On Saturday, Ozal told reporters: ``There have been no demands
from the United States for the closure of the pipeline. Such a
demand is out of question.
   ``It is wrong to relate the issue (Iraqi invasion) with the
closure of the pipeline,'' Ozal said. ``I explained (to Bush) that
it was not that simple.''
   Ramadan said he believed Turkey would continue to say neutral in
the Persian Gulf. Turkey, which borders both Iran and Iraq,
remained neutral throughout the eight-year Persian Gulf war.
   Iraq exports 2.7 million barrels of oil daily and 1.6 million
barrels of that oil flows through Turkey.
   Turkey obtains 60 percent of its crude oil imports from Iraq.
   Turkey earns $250 million from Iraq annually for operating the
pipeline.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900805-0048 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-05-90 1619EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-US-SaudiTanks     08-05 0538</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-US-Saudi Tanks,0552</SECOND>
<HEAD>American Says Saudis Have Deployed Tanks Toward Kuwait Border</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Iraq-Kuwait Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RICHARD PYLE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Saudi Arabia has deployed 200 to 300 tanks
toward its border with Kuwait, where Iraqi armored forces were
reported to have moved into position, said an American technician
who returned Sunday from Saudi Arabia.
   In addition, he said, the families of American civilian
employees at a Saudi military base in the northern desert had been
moved to Riyadh, the Saudi capital, and ``all others are on notice
to evacuate.''
   The American, who left Saudi Arabia on Saturday, spoke with The
Associated Press, after arriving at Kennedy International Airport,
on condition that he not be identified.
   He said he saw the tanks moving out of King Khalid Military
City, a large Saudi military complex in the desert about 80 miles
southwest of the point where the borders of Iraq, Kuwait and Saudi
Arabia come together.
   A former U.S. commander in the Persian Gulf said the deployed
tanks probably were drawn from a ``rapid deployment force''
maintained at the Saudi base, known as KKMC, by the six member
countries of the Gulf Cooperation Council.
   George B. Crist, a retired Marine Corps general who formerly
headed U.S. Central Command, the overall headquarters for American
forces in the region, said it was ``a safe bet'' that the council
force was ordered into the field. ``That's just what it was up
there for,'' he said in a telephone interview.
   The unit includes two brigades, each with about 5,000 men and
100 or more U.S.-built M-1 and M-48 tanks. One brigade is all-Saudi
and the other consists of single battalions from Kuwait, Bahrain,
Qatar, the United Arab Emirates and the Sultanate of Oman, under
Saudi command.
   The Gulf Cooperation Council set up the rapid deployment force
several years ago as part of a mutual assistance agreement, but
this apparently would be its first use in a battlefield situation.
   The American technician, who works at the base, said the
deployment apparently occurred Friday, a day after the Iraqis
invaded Kuwait and deposed its government, forcing the emir, Sheik
Jaber al-Ahmed al-Sabah, to flee to Saudi Arabia.
   The Iraqis on Friday advanced some troops and tanks to within a
few miles of the Saudi border, according to U.S. officials in
Washington.
   The American said there had been no reports on how far apart the
two forces were.
   The Saudi military complex, which does not appear on maps, lies
off a main north-south road. It is about 35 miles in circumference
and has a population of several thousand people, mostly Saudi
military.
   The source said there had been about 80 American civilian
technicians at the Saudi base, and 30 to 40 U.S. military personnel
training Saudi pilots to fly UH-60 Blackhawk helicopters. There
also is a small contingent of French missile technicians, he said.
   Two Americans who went to Kuwait from the base the day before
the Iraqi invasion found themselves trapped and are still there, he
said.
   ``We were able to talk to them once before the phone was cut
off,'' he said. ``They were in a hotel in Kuwait and the embassy
was telling them just to sit tight.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900805-0049 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-05-90 1634EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Germany-FastForward     08-05 0683</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Germany-Fast Forward,0706</SECOND>
<HEAD>German History Written for Speed Readers</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP News Analysis</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARK FRITZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>EAST BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Just when it seemed it could travel no
faster, the blinding pace of German unification appears ready to
put on another burst of speed. Blink, and you may miss history.
   West German Chancellor Helmut Kohl punched the fast-forward
button once again last week when he said that the two German
nations should elect a single government on Oct. 14.
   That's seven weeks sooner than the already quick Dec. 2 election
date that Kohl proposed earlier this year.
   Then, as now, the opposition Social Democrats in both countries
have opposed the move, saying it would require too much tinkering
with West Germany's election laws.
   But Horst Ehmke, deputy chairman of the West German Social
Democrats, reportedly left open the possibility the East German
Social Democrats may propose an instant unity during a special
parliamentary session this week.
   Asked by the newspaper Bild whether the East German Social
Democrats might make such a move during the Wednesday session in
East Berlin, Ehmke reportedly replied: ``I don't know. I don't
exclude it.''
   Both Kohl's conservative Christian Democrats and the
left-leaning Social Democrats are using the timing and sequence of
German unity to enhance their own political fortunes.
   But behind the bluster is one issue that is pushing the process
ever faster: whether East Germany has the economic strength, or the
political will, to continue as a sovereign nation for very much
longer.
   The young democratic government has become increasingly
distressed over its empty coffers and the plight of its industries
trying desperately to tread water in the nation's one-month-old
free market.
   West Germany, which already has commited $71 billion to
unification, has turned down East German pleas for additional help.
   There is a growing feeling in East Germany that the country
should dissolve itself and unify soon, so its financial situation
becomes the total responsibility of the Bonn government.
   Even if elections for a single government are held on Oct. 14,
actual unification could take place much sooner.
   It is up to East Germany to enact unification. That will be done
when its Parliament approves a clause in the West German
constitution that will allow it to accede to its bigger neighbor.
   Right now, East German joblessness, while climbing, is being
kept artificially low by a West German-financed program to keep
workers on payrolls at shortened hours and lower wages.
   Without that program, unemployment would likely be at more than
10 percent, rather than the 2.7 percent it was officially estimated
at last month.
   Joblessness is expected to eventually top out next year at
perhaps 30 percent or 40 percent.
   Kohl's Christian Democrats want all-German elections to take
place quickly to avoid a potential loss of voter support when the
East German economy collapses.
   For that reason, the Social Democrats are fighting to keep the
elections from being moved up to Oct. 14.
   But the Social Democrats also say now that they would accept
actual unification much sooner because of East Germany's economic
problems.
   That would allow them to be perceived as embracing a process
they have tried to slow, while still benefiting politically from
elections in December, when the economic woes are expected to be
much worse.
   There is another wild card that could, though unlikely, throw
the whole process out of whack.
   Oct. 14 is the date already set for East Germany to elect and
create five state governments so the country can fit into the
federal system in West Germany, which now has 11 states.
   Once those five state governments are created, political
analysts say, they can technically vote individually whether to
unify with West Germany.
   That means a state, if it wants, could decide that its
particular industrial or agricultural economy needs to be attached
to wealthy West Germany right now, not in December.
   That may be another reason why Kohl wants national elections on
the day East German state elections are held, less than three weeks
before the first anniversary of the opening of the Berlin Wall.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900805-0050 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-05-90 1710EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-US-Iraq 6thLd-Writethru-1stAdd a0764 08-05 0591</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-US-Iraq, 6th Ld-Writethru-1st Add, a0764,590</SECOND>
<HEAD>WASHINGTON: he said.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Presidential press secretary Marlin Fitzwater said there was no
indication that Iraq had sent its battle-hardened forces into Saudi
Arabia, a critical world oil supplier, although Sen. David Boren
said there had been minor incursions he described as ``sort of
putting a foot across.''
   Tens of thousands of Iraqi troops were reported massed in Kuwait
near the Saudi border. Rep. Les Aspin, D-Wis., said fresh
intelligence reports indicated an additional 18 Iraqi divisions
moving south toward Saudi Arabia. But Bush said he had not heard
such reports.
   After stepping out of his Marine One helicopter, Bush read a
note handed to him by Richard N. Haass, a National Security Council
senior director for Near Eastern Affairs, before facing reporters.
   Bush, juggling developments in two crisis-ridden regions of the
world, also issued orders for U.S. Marines to evacuate Americans
from war-torn Liberia and protect the U.S. Embassy there.
   He said he did not think any Americans were in ``imminent
danger'' in Kuwait.
   In a thinly-veiled signal to Saddam, Fitzwater said the Liberia
operation demonstrates that Bush ``is extremely concerned about the
welfare of American citizens. We have acted time and again in
behalf of their safety ... I'm sure that Iraq and other countries
are aware of that.''
   Bush spoke earlier Sunday with Japanese Prime Minister Toshiki
Kaifu and praised Japan's decision to ban oil imports from Iraq and
Kuwait, which have supplied more than 11 percent of Japan's oil.
   ``I appplaud Japan's stance, cracking down on the imports from
Iraq,'' said Bush.
   The White House dismissed claims that Saddam was pulling his
troops out of Kuwait three days after an invasion that replaced the
250-year-old monarchy with a new government supposedly composed of
nine Kuwaiti army officers.
   ``We have no independent or confirmable information on this
report,'' Fitzwater said. ``Saddam Hussein's actions in the past
raise serious skepticism about his intentions.''
   Boren, D-Okla., said on ABC-TV that intelligence reports did not
indicate any troop rollback, particularly along the southern border
with Saudi Arabia. ``So if they are taking anybody out, it's
probably just a few people for show,'' he said.
   A U.S. official, who declined to be identified, said it appeared
Iraqi troops were digging in rather than pulling out, building
fortifications in some parts of the conquered country.
   As tensions rose in the region, the Washington Post reported
Sunday that special operations forces and hostage rescue forces
have been dispatched to the Mideast and that contingency plans call
for sending Stealth fighters and B-52 bombers.
   ``I can't comment on any specific military actions or
movements,'' Fitzwater said.
   However, he said the United States ``has extreme concern about
the welfare of our citizens.''
   Asked if the United States had asked Saudi Arabia for access to
military facilities or landing rights to stage a military
operation, Fitzwater said, ``We do not have any U.S. military
staged in Saudi Arabia and we are discussing all options with
them.'' The Saudis have been reluctant in the past to allow any
U.S. military exercises on their soil, not wishing to provoke their
neighbors.
   A senior administration official said there have been numerous
cross-border sorties by the Iraqis into Saudi Arabian territory,
but that they have been very small and very brief incursions.
   Fitzwater confirmed that 11 American oil workers rounded up in
Kuwait after the invasion had been brought to Baghdad. He said they
had talked with U.S. embassy officials and appeared to be in good
shape.
   ``This accounts for all missing Americans,'' Fitzwater said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900805-0051 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-05-90 1803EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Soviet-Baltics 1stLd-Writethru a0715 08-05 0685</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Baltics, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0715,0700</SECOND>
<HEAD>Baltic Republics Moving Toward Greater Autonomy From Kremlin</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 12th graf, `Estonia, meanwhile ...,' with 3 grafs to
UPDATE with economic meeting Sunday in Estonia; picks up 13th graf,
`Estonian Prime ...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By LESLIE SHEPHERD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Their independence declarations may be technically
on hold, but the three Baltic republics continue to whittle away at
the ties that bind them to the Kremlin.
   In the past week, Lithuania and Estonia have begun work on draft
trade treaties with the Soviet Union's largest republic, bypassing
the national government.
   Estonia may recruit its own police force to replace the Soviet
militia. Latvia plans to start privatizing its economy by Oct. 1,
regardless of what the rest of the country does.
   And all three republics have said they will not take part in
negotiations to revise the treaty which binds the Soviet Union's 15
diverse republics together.
   Lithuanian Prime Minister Kazimiera Prunskiene, meanwhile, meets
regularly with Soviet Prime Minister Nikolai Ryzhkov to work out
details for negotiations on Lithuanian independence.
   Steadily, the Baltic leaders have been taking matters into their
own hands. They have been aided by the president of the Russian
republic, Boris Yeltsin, who seized the initiative on economic
reform and pushed Gorbachev into accepting his ``500 Days'' program
for the entire country. The Russian Federation is by far the
largest of the Soviet Union's 15 republics and is home to more than
half of the nation's population.
   While Gorbachev vacationed in the Crimea, Yeltsin took his
holiday on the Baltic Sea in Latvia. He did not spend much time on
the beach, news reports indicate.
   Instead, he met with Baltic leaders and offered to negotiate
republic-to-republic treaties on political, economic, cultural, and
other issues, bypassing the national government.
   Already, Russian Prime Minister Ivan Silayev and Mrs. Prunskiene
have agreed on ``all the key issues that interest our republics''
and have asked their officials to prepare a draft economic treaty
for as early as mid-August, the official Tass news agency reported.
   Eduardas Vilkas, a member of the Lithuanian negotiating
commission, says the economic treaties envisage ``a free common
market.''
   Mrs. Prunskiene was quoted Saturday as telling the Interfax news
service of Radio Moscow that some hitches remain, such as whether
the Russian republic can guarantee to sell oil to Lithuania when
the national government claims ownership of the energy industry.
   On Sunday, representatives of Latvia, Lithuania, Estonia,
Byelorussia, Moldavia, the Russian Federation, the cities of Moscow
and Leningrad, and the district of Leningrad met in the Estonian
capital of Tallinn to begin ``economic cooperation based on
treaties as a first step toward the ideas of a common market,'' the
Estonian News Agency reported.
   The meeting was convened by the Estonian leadership to counter
what the news agency called ``economic pressure from central
authorities in Moscow.''
   Estonia last week won an unpredecented concession from the
national government when Soviet Interior Minister Vadim Bakatin
agreed to give up his control of the republic's Interior Ministry
and let Estonia create its own police force.
   Estonian Prime Minister Edgar Savisaar told the Izvestia
newspaper that ``the Estonian government is now fully responsible
before the population for ensuring public order, protection of
citizens' rights and freedoms on the republic's territory.''
   Latvian Prime Minister Ivar Godmanis, who recently returned from
the United States, said economic experts from the
Indianapolis-based Hudson Institute have agreed to come advise his
government, and Latvian students will be sent to American business
schools.
   ``Latvian private sector and not only farmers need the
investments. If we are to overcome the present crisis, we should
embark on privatization of the Latvian economy by Oct. 1 at the
latest,'' he told the Postfactum news agency.
   Latvia plans to privatize 25-30 percent of the republic's
economy, excluding land and natural resources, within four or five
years. Property will be sold to private individuals or collectives,
including foreign ones, or handed over to public and religious
organizations.
   Lithuania declared independence on March 11, and Latvia and
Estonia both have declared their intention to follow at the end of
unspecified transition periods.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900805-0052 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-05-90 1837EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r e AM-Jazz     08-05 0289</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Jazz,0303</SECOND>
<HEAD>Jazz Fest Presents Jackie McLean's Music</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: No PMs planned</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By MARY CAMPBELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Instead of waiting till the musician was 80, or
gone, Lincoln Center's Classical Jazz series has devoted an evening
to ``The Music of Jackie McLean,'' the 59-year-old alto saxophonist
and teacher.
   The second of five Classical Jazz programs was held Saturday
night before an enthusiastic, mostly young audience which packed
Alice Tully Hall.
   McLean dedicated the evening to Walter Davis Jr., the pianist
who was in Miles Davis' band when McLean joined it in 1951. McLean
finished composing ``Walter Davis Ascending,'' on June 2, the day
Davis died at age 57.
   Allen Palmer, Walter Davis' last pupil, was pianist for the
upbeat piece. Music in the first half of the program was roiling,
with drums, bass and piano all playing full out, each sounding as
though the other two were in accompaniment. Other musicians came in
and out, to make quintets and sextets.
   They included trumpeters Wynton Marsalis and Wallace Roney,
tenor saxophonist Benny Golson, trombonist Curtis Fuller, pianist
Larry Willis and drummer Arthur Taylor. The core group was pianist
Hotep Idris Galeta, bassist Nat Reeves, drummer Carl Allen and
McLean.
   The performance began with excitement and kept up throughout.
The style was bebop to free, with melody. The free part also
sounded purposeful, swinging and thought out.
   Pieces included ``Minor March,'' which Miles Davis recorded
twice, and ``Little Melonae,'' which John Coltrane recorded.
   In the second half, musicians played as a nine-piece band, which
offered greater variety. ``Appointment in Ghana'' had strong pulse
and forward motion with the tune. ``Medley for Dolly,'' McLean's
wife, included a broad melody and slow swinging into a romantic
mood.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900805-0053 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-05-90 1840EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Bulgaria     08-05 0472</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bulgaria,0491</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bulgarian President Appeals to Political Parties</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SOFIA, Bulgaria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Zhelyu Zhelev said Sunday that
he will call immediate meetings with the country's political
parties to try to find solutions for Bulgaria's social turmoil.
   In another development, anti-government protesters in the
self-proclaimed ``City of Truth,'' who helped bring about the
resignation last month of Zhelev's Socialist predecessor, began
dismantling their tent city in downtown Sofia.
   It was not immediately clear how many of the estimated 300
people living there full-time would leave the pro-democracy
encampment. Only a few of the tents, which at one point numbered
about 170, were expected to remain.
   Zhelev said he would immediately call meetings with parties
represented in Parliament ``to find a way out of the crisis,''
according to the state BTA news agency.
   In his televised speech, Bulgaria's first non-Communist
president in 40 years also urged the parties to form a council to
consult with him.
   He called on fellow opposition members to help him find an
answer to Bulgaria's ``economic, political and moral crisis.''
   Zhelev, a philosopher who led the opposition Union of Democratic
Forces in June's free elections, was elected Wednesday by
Parliament.
   Zhelev's election ended the parliamentary stalemate between
Socialists and the opposition over a replacement for Petar Mladenov.
   Mladenov, a Socialist, resigned July 6 after he was accused of
calling for tanks against anti-government demonstrations last year
and amid threats of escalating strikes.
   The demonstrations started Bulgaria on a path of democratic
reform. In November, Communist Party members ousted longtime leader
Todor Zhivkov. They later changed the party's name to the Socialist
Party.
   Zhelev says he favors the formation of a government of experts
supported by both the Socialists and the Union of Democratic
Forces. His statement indicated that some opposition members could
join the government while avoiding a formal coalition.
   The opposition repeatedly has rejected offers of a coalition
from incumbent Socialist Premier Andrei Lukanov, arguing that the
former Communist party must shoulder responsibility for past
political crimes and the rapidly deteriorating economy.
   Zhelev also said Sunday that he would rescind all laws which
violate the Constitution, ``in the first place those which infringe
upon the fundamental rights of the citizens.''
   He said he will soon lift restrictions on Bulgarians to move
freely around the country, including the right to live in the
capital.
   Earlier Sunday, the protesters made clear that they decided to
remove their tents because their main demands have already been met
by the government. That included a request that Zhivkov be allowed
to speak before Parliament about his 35 years in power.
   Anti-government campers in other towns where tents have been
pitched to campaign for greater democracy and other causes said
they would continue their protest.
   The protesters, who have put up 13 tent cities in towns across
Bulgaria, have claimed 250,000 supporters.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900805-0054 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-05-90 1843EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Mountain-Accidents     08-05 0254</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mountain-Accidents,0263</SECOND>
<HEAD>11 Killed in Mountain Accidents</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BERN, Switzerland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Eleven people were killed in a series
of mountain accidents in the Alps on Sunday, rescue services and a
news agency reported.
   Swiss air mountain rescue services said five German climbers who
were roped together fell to their deaths while nearing the top of
11,117-foot Mt. Fruendenhorn. The climbers were not identified.
   On the Italian side of Mount Blanc, a shower of rocks struck two
Japanese climbers, causing them to fall 1,600 feet to their deaths,
the Italian news agency ANSA reported.
   It said the two were tied together as they were attempting to
cross from one mountain shelter to another on the Alpine peak,
which straddles Italy and France.
   ANSA identified the victims as Une Toshiaki, 43, an Alpine
guide, and Wada Kayoka. It said Kayoka's age was not immediately
available.
   The news agency said the two climbers had set out from Chamonix,
in France, with a friend and a French guide. It said Kayoka's
husband was killed two years ago in the same area during a climb.
   A Civil Defense helicopter recovered the bodies. The other two
climbers were rescued unharmed, ANSA said.
   In other accidents, two Czechoslovak climbers were killed by a
rockfall in Bergell in the canton of Grisons, and two others were
injured, rescue services said.
   They also said an Austrian tourist fell to his death while
climbing in the Engadine Alps, and a Swiss climber was also killed
in another accident. Their identities were not released.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900805-0055 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-05-90 1843EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Concert-Robbery     08-05 0172</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Concert-Robbery,0179</SECOND>
<HEAD>Robbers Steal $260,000 from Concert</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MONTREAL (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Three robbers with guns and a fake hand grenade
stole $260,000 in proceeds Sunday after a concert by New Kids on
the Block, police said.
   Police spokesman Jacques Morrisseau said the robbers, who were
armed with revolvers, entered a room in Olympic Stadium where 12
employees were counting money from souvenir sales.
   New Kids on the Block, the teen pop sensation, had earlier
played before a crowd of 57,000 at the stadium.
   The groups usually generates tens of thousands of dollars in
sales of programs, caps and T-shirts before their concerts.
   The robbers handcuffed the employees and placed the fake hand
grenade near a door. They told the terrified employees the grenade
would explode if they tried to open the door.
   The robbers then made off with $260,000 in cash from the
souvenir sales.
   The police bomb squad led the workers out of a rear door half an
hour after the robbery. Police later discovered the grenade did not
contain explosives.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900805-0056 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-05-90 1847EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-WeatherpageWeather     08-05 0347</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Weatherpage Weather,0359</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rain From Southwest To Northeast</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Rain extended from New Mexico to New England on Sunday, with
locally heavy rain flooding some streets and underpasses in Texas.
   Showers and thunderstorms extended over eastern Colorado, across
the Nebraska Panhandle and southwestern Nebraska, western Kansas
and the Oklahoma Panhandle into the northern Texas Panhandle.
   Showers and thunderstorms also reached from southeastern New
Mexico and southwestern Texas across north-central Texas and across
northern Louisiana, southern Alabama and the Florida Panhandle.
   Texas got the worst of the rain, with 2 inches at Fort Worth
between 1 p.m. and 2 p.m. and 2{ inches during the morning over
parts of Comanche County in northern Texas.
   Water was up to 4 feet deep over some low-lying streets in
northern Fort Worth, the National Weather Service said.
   Southwestern Texas also got heavy rain. Several highways near
Eldorado were closed by high water and many low-water crossings
were impassable, the weather service reported.
   Several small rivers in eastern Iowa were at or over flood
stage. The Wapsipinicon River was near its crest at Dewitt and less
than a foot above flood stage. The Skunk River was receding below
below flood stage at Brighton; the Cedar was almost 3 feet over
flood stage at Conesville but receding; the Kickapoo was cresting
about a foot over flood stage at Gays Mills, the weather service
said.
   Showers and storms also reached from northern Mississippi across
Tennessee, Kentucky, West Virginia, southern and eastern Ohio,
western Virginia, Pennsylvania, Maryland, New Jersey and New York
state into western New England.
   Binghamton, N.Y., got an inch of rain in the six hours up to 2
p.m. EDT.
   Elsewhere, showers and storms were scattered over southeastern
Florida, central South Carolina, northeastern North Carolina and
northeastern Illinois.
   Jacksonville, Fla., cooled to 69 degrees during the morning,
tying the city's low temperature record for the date.
   Sunday's low temperature for the Lower 48 states was 38 at
Gunnison, Colo.
   Temperatures around the nation at 3 p.m. EDT ranged from 54 at
Akron, Colo., to 106 at Needles, Calif.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900805-0057 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-05-90 1918EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Thatcher 1stLd-Writethru a0763 08-05 0607</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Thatcher, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0763,0621</SECOND>
<HEAD>Thatcher Proposes Magna Carta For All Europeans</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 4 grafs to UPDATE with Mrs. Thatcher's remarks on
Iraqi invasion of Kuwait. Pick up 3rd graf pvs, `We don't...</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By SANDY SHORE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ASPEN, Colo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   British Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher on
Sunday called for a new Magna Carta that would establish basic
rights for all Europeans, including the Soviets.
   Mrs. Thatcher also renewed her call for the United Nations to
apply a total economic embargo against Iraq unless it withdraws
without delay from its occupation of Kuwait. She said the embargo
only would be fully effective if it were supported by all members
of the United Nations.
   ``Iraq's invastion of Kuwait defies every principle for which
the UN stands. If we let it succeed, no small country can ever feel
safe again. The law of the jungle takes over,'' she said.
   The prime minister devoted most of her remarks to more than
3,000 people at the Aspen Institute to her vision of the new Europe.
   ``The European Community has reconciled antagonisms within
Western Europe; it should now help to overcome divisions between
East and West in Europe,'' she sand at the closing session of the
Institute's 40th anniversary.
   ``We don't see this new Soviet Union as an enemy, but as a
country groping its way towards freedom. We no longer have to view
the world through the prism of East-West relations. The Cold War is
over.''
   At the end of her half-hour speech inside the big blue-and-white
Aspen Music Festival tent, the crowd gave Thatcher a standing
ovation.
   About 1,700 people were seated inside the big top. The rest were
scattered about the lawn outside in the warm, summer air.
   Thatcher traveled to the institute to address its annual
symposium and receive its Statesman Award, which recognized the
prime minister's long reign and her commitment to democracy and
peace.
   Thatcher met with President Bush in Aspen on Thursday before his
opening address at the institute. She is scheduled to travel to
Washington, D.C., Monday for an afternoon meeting with Bush, then
return to London early Tuesday.
   During her speech, Thatcher said Western nations need to help
nations struggling to establish democracy, but at the same time
maintain a secure defense, including NATO and U.S. forces in Europe.
   ``The unity and strength which we in the West have found from
joining together in defense can now be turned to serve more
positive and ambitious purposes,'' she said.
   King John of England was forced by English barons to grant the
original Magna Carta at Runnymede, England, June 15, 1215. It
traditionally has been interpreted as guaranteeing certain civil
and political liberties.
   The prime minister said her proposed European Magna Carta would
``entrench for every European citizen, including those of the
Soviet Union, the basic rights we in the West take for granted.''
   Among those rights: freedom of speech, worship, access to law
and the marketplace, and the freedom to hold democratic elections,
own property, maintain nationhood and remain free of ``fear of an
over-mighty state.''
   She also suggested that the European Community be poised to
accept all Eastern European nations as members ``when democracy has
taken root and their economies are capable of sustaining
membership.''
   ``We can't say in one breath that they are part of Europe, and
in the next our European Community Club is so exclusive that we
won't admit them,'' she said.
   Founded in 1950, the non-profit Aspen Institute gathers leaders
in all parts of society to discuss critical issues of the world.
The symposium this weekend concentrated on topics including health
care and education.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900805-0058 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-05-90 2026EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Iraq-Kuwait 3rdLd-Writethru   08-05 1200</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Iraq-Kuwait, 3rd Ld-Writethru,a0784,1232</SECOND>
<HEAD>Iraq Says Withdrawal Under Way; U.S. Disputes Claim</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: INSERTS one graf after 20th `The White...' to ADD U.N.
sanctions expected, SUBS two grafs for 33-34 bgng `The Iraqi...' to
RESTORE first reference to Saddam; no pickup</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos DXB1,3,NY22,27,WX7</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SALAH NASRAWI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>KUWAIT (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Iraq said it had started withdrawing part of its
invasion force from Kuwait on Sunday, and the Kuwaiti government
installed by Baghdad threatened to retaliate against any nation
that challenges its legitimacy.
   In Washington, President Bush said Iraq had ``lied once again''
in claiming that it was withdrawing its invasion force. The
president said he wanted to see Arab countries join in condemning
the Iraqi invasion.
   Dozens of tanks, armored personnel carriers and trucks carrying
hundreds of soldiers were seen crossing the border back into Iraq
at the Safwan checkpoint, about 30 miles south of the Iraqi port
city of Basra.
   However, thousands of Iraqi soldiers remained behind, tightening
their grip on the oil-rich desert country.
   At his impromptu news conference, Bush said the United States
would not recognize the Kuwaiti ``puppet government'' set up by
Iraq. He refused to discuss any military action the United States
might be planning, and he said his goal was to isolate Iraq
internationally.
   U.S. officials said there was no indication Iraqi troops in
southern Kuwait were preparing to invade Saudi Arabia. But Bush
dispatched Defense Secretary Dick Cheney to Saudi Arabia to confer
with leaders of the desert kingdom, administration sources said
Sunday.
   Diplomats in the Persian Gulf, who spoke on condition of
anonymity, said that up to 80,000 soldiers of the new, largely
Iraqi-staffed ``popular army'' of the provisional Kuwaiti
government were fanning out across Kuwait.
   The television of the Iraqi-installed government in Kuwait,
monitored in Bahrain, showed 30 minutes of continuous footage with
military vehicles rolling back into Iraq, starting at 8 a.m.
   Twelve Arab reporters based in Baghdad were taken into Kuwait on
Sunday by Iraq's Ministry of Information to observe the first Iraqi
troops returning home.
   A senior Iraqi officer, who spoke on condition of anonymity,
said, ``The first phase of pulling out the Iraqi troops from the
dusty desert state began, and we will continue as long as the
security of the troops and situation in Kuwait allows.''
   He refused to give details on how many Iraqi troops remained in
Kuwait, saying there ``are enough to defend the sisterly Arab
countries against any foreign aggression.''
   About 100,000 Iraqi troops were estimated to have taken part in
the initial invasion.
   The reporters could not locate any of the nine members of the
new Kuwaiti provisional military government nor anyone who spoke
for them.
   Roads connecting the Iraqi border with Kuwait city, about 60
miles away, were littered with cars hastily abandoned during the
first hours of the invasion. Many had been smashed by tanks to
clear a path.
   In Kuwait city, at least 30 burned and destroyed vehicles
remained outside the defense ministry, where eyewitnesses said a
battle raged for hours after Thursday's invasion.
   Hospital officials said many soldiers from both sides were
killed during the first day of the invasion. They were unable to
give exact figures, but said at least 300 died.
   Residents said the city was quiet during the daytime, but
gunfire could be heard at night. Most residents remained behind
closed doors, but some people ventured into the streets to search
for food and stared at the Iraqi troops.
   In other developments Sunday:
   _Japan banned all oil imports from Iraq and Kuwait and halted
Japanese exports to both countries. Tokyo said it would suspend all
loans to Iraq and Kuwait, ban Japanese investment there, and freeze
Iraqi assets in Japan. Japan, which imports 99 percent of its oil,
had relied on Iraq and Kuwait for more than 11 percent of its oil
imports.
   The White House praised Japan for joining the many other nations
that have already penalized Iraq for its invasion by imposing
economic sanctions.
   _In New York, the United States urged other U.N. members at
talks to impose broad economic and military sanctions on Iraq.
Western diplomats said the world body is expected to adopt the
measures Monday.
   _The emir of Kuwait, Sheik Jaber Al-Ahmed Al-Sabah, made his
first public statements since fleeing to Saudi Arabia on Thursday.
In a speech broadcast on Bahrain and Saudi television, the emir
pledged that Kuwait would restore its territorial integrity,
independence and sovereignty. He said, ``What makes our hearts
filled with sadness is that the source of this unjustified
agression was not an enemy, but a brother and a close neighbor.
...''
   _Arab nations remained divided over how to react to the Iraqi
invasion, and there was no indication that Saudi Arabia and Turkey
were prepared to close the pipelines in their countries that carry
the oil exported by Iraq.
   In Ankara, the Turkish capital, Iraqi Deputy Prime Minister Taha
Yassin Ramadan warned that shutting down the pipeline ``would
create mistrust'' between Iraq and Turkey.
   Prime Minister Mudar Badran of Jordan, a U.S. and Iraqi ally,
said Sunday his nation would not recognize the provisional
government in Kuwait because that would hinder Arab efforts to
settle the crisis through negotiation.
   In Syria, Iranian Foreign Minister Ali Akbar Velayati met with
President Hafez Assad to discuss ways of ensuring an Iraqi
withdrawal from Kuwait, according to official reports. Syria was
Persian Iran's main Arab backer during its 1980-88 war with Iraq.
   _The White House said 11 American oil workers rounded up after
the invasion had been brought to Baghdad, had talked with U.S.
Embassy officials, and were in good shape. It said that accounts
for all missing Americans.
   Britain said that 35 servicemen taken from their homes in Kuwait
Saturday were being held in a Baghdad hotel and not allowed to
leave the country.
   Iraq invaded Kuwait on Thursday in a dispute over oil and
territory, quickly deposed the monarchy, and seized control of
Kuwait's vast oil reserves.
   The official Iraqi News Agency said the U.N. Security Council
had been notified of the pullout, which it said was in line with an
agreement between Baghdad and Kuwait's provisional government.
   The provisional government, in a statement carried by the Iraqi
News Agency, told other countries to refrain from taking
``punishing measures'' against it or Iraq. The government said
these countries ``have to remember they have interests and citizens
in Kuwait'' and said it was prepared to close embassies and cut
diplomatic relations with offending nations.
   The United States, which remains concerned about the 3,000
Americans still living in Kuwait, has already banned oil imports
from Kuwait and Iraq and frozen both countries' assets in the
United States.
   Baghdad TV has said the new Kuwaiti provisional government is
headed by Col. Ala Hussein Ali. The other eight members were
lieutenant colonels and majors.
   But Kuwait's embassy in Amman, Jordan, on Sunday called the new
government as ``a list of fake names'' and said Ali is Iraqi
President Saddam Hussein's son-in-law. The Kuwaiti Embassy in Tunis
said Ali works for the Saddam administration.
   The Iraqi News Agency carried a Kuwait-datelined statement it
said was issued by the provisional government, denying that any of
its members were Iraqis.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900805-0059 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-05-90 2048EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Iraq-Embargo-List 1stLd-Writethru   08-05 0122</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Iraq-Embargo-List, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0769,0164</SECOND>
<HEAD>Countries That Announced Sanctions in Iraq-Kuwait Crisis</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: ADDS Canada to list as nation that has frozen assets and
banned oil. With AM-Iraq-Kuwait, Bjt</NOTE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here is a list of countries that have announced
sanctions as a result of Iraq's invasion of Kuwait:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>ARMS SALES SUSPENDED:</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Poland
   Czechoslovakia
   China
   Italy
   Soviet Union
   France (sales already suspended because of unpaid debts)
</TEXT>
<HEAD>KUWAITI, IRAQI or IRAQI AND KUWAITI ASSETS FROZEN:</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Norway
   United States
   Britain
   Denmark
   France
   Italy
   The Netherlands
   Spain
   West Germany
   Ireland
   Greece
   Portugal
   Canada
   Japan
   Belgium (recommended)
   Luxembourg (recommended)
   Switzerland (recommended)
</TEXT>
<HEAD>OIL IMPORTS BANNED:</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Japan
   United States
   Belgium
   Denmark
   Britain
   France
   Italy
   West Germany
   Ireland
   Luxembourg
   The Netherlands
   Portugal
   Spain
   Greece
   Canada
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900805-0060 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-05-90 2113EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-UN-Iraq-Kuwait 3rdLd-Writethru a0792 08-05 0574</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-UN-Iraq-Kuwait, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0792,0585</SECOND>
<HEAD>United State Pushes for Iraqi Sanctions at United Nations</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS thruout to UPDATE with U.S. ambassador's comments,
comments from Britain, Cuba; DELETES outdated material thruout; no
pickup</NOTE>
<HEAD>With AM-Iraq-Kuwait, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By VICTORIA GRAHAM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   UNITED NATIONS _ The United States urged other U.N. members at
talks Sunday to impose broad economic and military sanctions on
Iraq. Western diplomats said the world body is expected to adopt
the measures.
   Should the U.N. Security Council impose comprehensive sanctions,
it would be the first time since 1967 it has taken such action
against a member state. The last time such sanctions were imposed
was against the white minority government of Rhodesia.
   Western diplomats said they expected up to 14 positive votes on
the 15-member council for sanctions against Iraq. They said they
expected no vetoes, allowing the legally binding measure to be
adopted, probably on Monday. They said Cuba was the holdout.
   U.S. Ambassador Thomas R. Pickering told reporters after
closed-door talks Sunday that the council discussed ``the absolute
necessity of moving ahead toward a broad resolution of sanctions.''
He said he expected a vote Monday.
   Pickering said the United States had circulated six or seven
drafts of a detailed resolution. It calls for an embargo on Iraq's
oil exports, an embargo on imports to Iraq, and a halt to all arms
and other military supplies for Iraq.
   British Ambassador Crispen Tickell told reporters later that he
detected ``strong support, with the exception of one member, for
action and a vote tomorrow.''
   Speaking of Iraqi President Saddam Hussein, Canadian Ambassador
L. Yves Fortier declared, ``This madman must be stopped.''
   Cuban envoy Ricardo Alarcon said Cuba would vote for sanctions
against Iraq only if the council imposed sanctions on South Africa
for occupying Namibia, Israel for occupying Palestinian territories
and the United States for invading Panama.
   In Kuwait, the Iraqi-installed provisional government, in a
statement carried by the Iraqi News Agency, told other countries to
refrain from taking ``punishing measures'' against it or Iraq. The
provisional government said countries ``have to remember they have
interests and citizens in Kuwait.''
   Kuwait's U.N. Ambassador Mohammad Abulhasan told reporters that
the Iraqi-installed government was employing ``pure blackmail'' by
saying it could not ensure the safety of foreigners if their
governments support sanctions.
   In Aspen, Colo., British Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher
renewed her call for the United Nations to apply a total economic
embargo against Iraq unless it withdraws immediately from Kuwait.
   ``Iraq's invasion of Kuwait defies every principle for which the
U.N. stands. If we let it succeed, no small country can ever feel
safe again. The law of the jungle takes over,'' she said, in
remarks at the Aspen Institute.
   The U.N. role in the Iraq-Kuwait crisis assumed increasing
importance after divided Arab nations cancelled an emergency summit
on the invasion.
   On Thursday, the Security Council condemned Iraq's invasion,
demanded immediate and unconditional troop withdrawal, and
threatened to impose sanctions if Iraq did not pull out.
   Sunday's session was scheduled after weekend meetings of the
council's five permanent members _ the United States, the Soviet
Union, China, Britain and France _ and between the United States
and representatives of the Non-Aligned Movement. They are the
nations with the power to veto proposals.
   The United States contends that stiff sanctions by a united
international front are necessary to punish Iraq and to force it to
withdraw from Kuwait, which was invaded Thursday.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900805-0061 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-05-90 2121EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-PowerOutage 2ndLd-Writethru a0762 08-05 0474</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Power Outage, 2nd Ld - Writethru, a0762,0480</SECOND>
<HEAD>Second Power Outage In A Week Hits Chicago's West Side</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS lead, 5th graf, to UPDATE with power restored. DELETES
outdated reference to repairs. Picks up 6th graf pvs, `About
25,000...; SUBS 11th graf, `Mayor Richard ..' to conform</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By BRENDA C. COLEMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CHICAGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An explosion and fire Sunday at an electrical
substation caused the second power outage in a week on the city's
West Side, cutting off electricity temporarily to about 25,000
customers, officials said.
   The fire was reported just after 9 a.m. at a substation that
Commonwealth Edison had used to supply electricity to customers hit
by last weekend's outage, an Edison spokeswoman said. The previous
outage lasted up to two days and led to sporadic looting in the
West Side, which contains some of the city's poorest neighborhoods.
   ``It was a powerful and serious explosion,'' Edison spokesman
Steve Solomon said of Sunday's blast. An Edison operator at the
site heard a transformer ``trip,'' or shut off because of a
malfunction, then an explosion. He ran outside and saw the fire,
said company spokeswoman Margaret Winters.
   The cause of the fire is under investigation. Winters at first
said sabotage was possible, but later said it was unlikely.
   Power was restored to all customers by 4:35 p.m., Solomon said.
   About 25,000 customers in a 30-block-square area were affected,
plus some customers on the eastern edge of the suburb of Oak Park,
Winters said.
   Manny Patel, manager of a Baskin Robbins 31 Ice Cream Store in
the affected area, said he lost about $4,000 worth of ice cream
last week and would lose twice that amount this week if the power
wasn't quickly restored.
   ``Last week I can understand _ things happen,'' he said. ``But
two weeks in a row, I can't understand. Is this going to be a
weekly thing?''
   Temperatures were in the mid-70s, as they were during the July
28 outage, giving a break to residents whose fans and air
conditioners were left powerless.
   The earlier outage, which came at 10 p.m. Saturday, was caused
by a fire in a malfunctioning generator. It affected about 40,000
customers, including businesses that lost tens of thousands of
dollars in perishables. The utility couldn't restore electricity to
all affected customers until Tuesday.
   Mayor Richard M. Daley and other city officials toured the
blacked-out area Sunday, and a Daley spokesman said the city had
launched several initiatives to help residents cope.
   The Streets and Sanitation Department put up stop signs where
street lights were out, said spokesman Terry Levin.
   ``We also have food inspectors out there to make sure that no
spoiled food gets sold,'' he said. ``We have also been in contact
with all the nursing homes in the area to make sure that there's no
problem with electricity.''
 
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900805-0062 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-05-90 2131EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-OregonFire 3rdLd-Writethru a0786 08-05 0769</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Oregon Fire, 3rd Ld - Writethru, a0786,0788</SECOND>
<HEAD>Oregon Forest Fire Destroys 28 Houses; Thousands Evacuated</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 11th graf to delete `Along the highway' reference, SUBS
final graf pvs, `Elsewhere, fire..., with 6 grafs to ADD
description, quotes; no pickup</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto BND2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By WILLIAM C. CRUM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BEND, Ore. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A fire driven by high winds and temperatures
close to 100 degrees engulfed about 2,800 acres of parched forest,
jumped a 75-foot-wide river canyon and destroyed 28 houses by
Sunday afternoon.
   More than 2,800 people were evacuated Saturday night and Sunday
from at least four motels or resorts and about 2,000 homes in six
subdivisions south and west of Bend.
   The so-called Awbrey Hall fire erupted about 3 p.m. Saturday on
a ridge six miles southwest of Bend, a city of about 19,000 on the
eastern slopes of the Cascade Range in central Oregon. It quickly
raced from treetop to treetop and jumped the Deschutes River.
   Kurt Larson said his family was driving home from a county fair
late Saturday when they heard on the radio their subdivision had
been evacuated. They rushed to their house and grabbed a few
possessions.
   Larson, 45, a millworker, returned to the deserted neighborhood
at 5:30 a.m. to check on his house, which was unscathed.
   ``I felt like the last man on earth,'' he said. ``It was really
eerie.''
   On Sunday, the northern boundary of the five-mile-long blaze was
about a mile away from Central Oregon Community College in Bend. On
the south, it was a mile away from the 325-room Inn at the Seventh
Mountain.
   State and federal fire crews were able to construct a fire line
around all but 3 miles of the blaze's circumference by Sunday
afternoon. The temperature at 4 p.m. in Redmond, near Bend, was 97
degrees, with winds up to 13 mph.
   ``We have 2,800 acres burning actively this morning, and there
are spotting problems already,'' said Forestry Department spokesman
Doug Decker. Spotting occurs when embers are carried through the
air ahead of the fire.
   Lynn Anderson of the interagency fire information center in Bend
said most of the problems were on the northeastern corner of the
fire, the one closest to town.
   About 100 miles south of Bend, a second fast-moving fire forced
the evacuation of a subdivision and the 750 inhabitants of the town
of Chiloquin were placed on alert, Decker said. He said that blaze
had burned a structure, but he didn't know what it was.
   The cause of the Bend fire was under investigation but ``initial
information indicates that it is not arson,'' said Linda Talifson
of the fire information center.
   About 1,000 firefighters were working the fire with 65 fire
engines, 14 bulldozers, six helicopters and six air tankers. The
cost of fighting the fire in its first 15 hours was $646,000,
Decker said.
   Smoke permeated Bend and was evident as far as Madras, 30 miles
to the north. Dave Morman, also of the fire information center,
said the fire had destroyed 28 homes.
   ``The ones I saw were pretty nice homes,'' he said.
   Damage was estimated at more than $4.5 million, said Decker.
   Gov. Neil Goldschmidt declared Deschutes County a disaster area
late Saturday. The Red Cross set up emergency centers for the fire
evacuees at two schools.
   At Bend Senior High School, volunteers arrived in a steady
stream with bags of donated goods such as groceries, disposable
diapers, bedding and pet food.
   ``A small community is very, very great for things like that,''
said the shelter manager, Lois Gumbert, 61, of Klamath Falls.
   Driven from their home, Larson and his wife, Jeanne, decided to
volunteer at the shelter, where firefighters were fed before
heading into the field and worried homeowners waited for updated
damage reports.
   ``We couldn't sleep so we ended up coming down here and helping
the Red Cross set tables for the firefighters,'' Mrs. Larson said.
   Employees of a local furniture and appliance store wheeled a
big-screen television into the cafeteria at Bend High. One woman
brought in a plate of brownies.
   Mrs. Larson said she only had time to gather a few household
belongings, especially irreplaceable items like family photo
albums. Waiting bred worry about the home they left behind to the
whims of the advancing flames.
   ``You could see the ball of fire,'' she said. ``We're hoping
that our house will still be there, but we don't know.''
   Elsewhere, fire bosses in Utah plotted a new assault Sunday on a
fire that has charred more than 5,000 acres in rugged country on
the Uintah and Ouray Indian Reservation near Fort Duchesne.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900805-0063 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-05-90 2149EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-KennedyAssassination 2ndLd-Writethru a07gotthird-placemoneyof$161
08-05 0823</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Kennedy Assassination, 2nd Ld - Writethru, a0785,0841</SECOND>
<HEAD>Man Says His Father Helped Assassinate John F. Kennedy</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Leads with 5 grafs to UPDATE with FBI declining to comment,
notes that conspiracy theories rife since Kennedy's death; CORRECTS
spelling in 3rd graf back to Connally sted Connally; picks up 5th
graf pvs, White said...</NOTE>
<DATELINE>AUSTIN, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An unemployed oil equipment salesman claims
that his late father, a former Dallas police officer, was one of
three men who assassinated President John F. Kennedy in 1963.
   Ricky White scheduled a meeting with reporters Monday in Dallas
to offer evidence he said implicates his father, Roscoe White, in
the assassination, the Austin American-Statesman reported Sunday.
   The Warren Commission concluded that Lee Harvey Oswald, acting
alone, fired the shots that killed Kennedy and wounded Texas Gov.
John Connally. Despite the commission's findings, conspiracy
theories have abounded over 27 years.
   White, 29, said he ``had no conception of ever, ever giving this
story out,'' but decided to do so after the FBI began questioning
him in May 1988 in relation to his claims.
   Woody Specht, FBI special agent in Dallas, refused to comment on
the claims, other than to say: ``You really need to evaluate the
source on these types of things.''
   White said he can prove that his father fired two of the three
bullets that killed the president and that his father, not Oswald,
also killed Dallas police officer J.D. Tippit less than an hour
after the assassination.
   White said Oswald was involved in the plot, but did not fire any
shots. The two other shooters were referred to in his father's
diary only by code names, White said.
   Roscoe White died in a fire in 1971.
   The evidence White reportedly will provide includes a rifle with
telescopic sight that uses ammunition he said is similar to that
used in Oswald's gun; records showing Oswald and White served
together in the Marines; and three faded messages he believes were
sent by U.S. intelligence officials ordering Kennedy's
assassination in Dallas in November 1963.
   Bobby Inman, the former deputy CIA director, viewed the messages
and told the American-Statesman they were not genuine.
   White, an unemployed equipment salesman in Midland, said that he
and his mother read his father's diary, which detailed the
assassination. His mother, Geneva White, is seriously ill and
unable to be interviewed, family members told the newspaper.
   The diary disappeared from his home after it was inspected by
the FBI, White says.
   White said his mother worked briefly at Jack Ruby's Carousel
Club in Dallas. Ruby fatally shot Oswald two days after Kennedy was
assassinated.
   Clues found among his father's effects and available government
records show that Roscoe White and Oswald served together in the
U.S. Marine Corps in the late 1950s, Ricky White said. He said his
father claimed to have become acquainted with Oswald in Japan and
the Philippines.
   He said his father's possessions also included a photograph,
taken by Marina Oswald of her husband, Lee Harvey Oswald, holding a
rifle in the back yard of their Dallas home in 1963.
   Oswald was discharged in 1959 and defected to the Soviet Union.
He returned to the United States in 1962, settling first in Fort
Worth before moving to Dallas.
   The elder White was discharged in late 1962 and joined his wife
and two sons in Paris, Texas. Ricky White says his family later
moved to Dallas where his father sold insurance.
   Dallas police records show that on Oct. 7, 1963, Roscoe White
joined the department as a photographer and clerk, and that he
became a patrol officer in 1964.
   White says his father shot from behind a fence atop the grassy
knoll that was to the right and front of Kennedy's limousine when
he was shot. He says the other two gunmen were behind the limousine
in the Texas School Book Depository, where Oswald also was, and in
a second building.
   As the incriminating evidence began to mount against his father,
Ricky White asked the JFK Assassination Information Center in
Dallas to verify or disprove his father's involvement, center
director Larry Howard told The Associated Press. The information
center is a private group that has pursued the idea of a conspiracy
and coverup in Kennedy's death.
   ``He's actually very courageous to follow this thing through,''
Howard said Sunday. ``The amount of documentation we have to back
his story up is just incredible.''
   Howard said he has been working with White for 1{ years, and
hopes White's story will lead to a new investigation of the
assassination.
   ``I've never been so convinced of anything in my life,'' Howard
said.
   ``We're not saying that we've solved the John F. Kennedy
assassination case but this sure opens the doors to another
investigation.''
   Howard said Americans are fascinated by JFK's assassination. ``I
think they know that it was a massive coverup in the very beginning
and they want to know the truth,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900805-0064 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-05-90 2209EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Iraq-Oil 1stLd-Writethru a0710 08-05 0521</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Iraq-Oil, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0710,0534</SECOND>
<HEAD>Iraqi Oil Export Routes Highly Vulnerable</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS one graf for 6th to CORRECT current capacity at Mina
al-Bakr to 800,000 sted 800,000 million; CLARIFY that capacity is
daily; pickup graf 7 `But with...'
^With AM-Iraq-Kuwait, Bjt</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By MARTIN MARRIS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NICOSIA, Cyprus (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Iraq exports much of its oil through
pipelines across Saudi Arabia and Turkey, with the rest shipped via
the Persian Gulf. All three routes are highly vulnerable.
   The $2.7 billion twin pipeline through Saudi Arabia, which ends
at the Red Sea oil terminal at al-Mu'ajjis, has a capacity of 1.65
million barrels a day.
   The 979-mile pipeline was a central element in Iraq's plan to
seek alternative oil routes during the Iran-Iraq war, when Iranian
raids on gulf shipping almost shut down sea routes.
   Saudi Oil Minister Hisham Nazer has described the pipeline as a
``symbol of the deep ties between the two countries.''
   Another pipeline with a capacity of 1.6 million barrels a day
snakes through 612 miles of southeastern Turkey to the
Mediterranean oil terminal at Ceyhan.
   Oil shipped through the gulf passes through Iraq's Mina al-Bakr
terminal, which when post-war rebuilding work is completed, will
have a design capacity to load 1.6 million barrels a day into
tankers. Its current capacity is 800,000 barrels.
   But with the United States, Japan and the European Community
announcing embargos on Iraqi oil after Iraq's invasion Thursday of
Kuwait, the question is whether President Saddam Hussein will be
able to sell it.
   In addition, the pipelines are highly vulnerable to military
attack and their operation depends on the cooperation of Saudi
Arabia and Turkey.
   So far, those two countries have given no indication of any
willingness to interfere with the oil flow, with Saudi Arabia
reportedly fearful that any such action could provide Baghdad with
a pretext to send its army into the oil-rich kingdom.
   But the possibility remains.
   As for the gulf route, the Iran-Iraq war demonstrated vividly
that it can be virtually shut down by military aircraft, missiles,
gunboats and possibly a naval blockade.
   At times during the eight-year gulf war with Iran, Iraq's oil
output fell below 1 million barrels a day but now it ranks again
among the world's oil giants.
   Iraq itself has increased its production capacity to 4.5 million
barrels a day, although it has kept its output no higher than its
Organization of Petroleum Exporting Countries quota of 3.14 million
barrels a day.
   Kuwait's violation of its OPEC quota was one factor that pushed
oil prices down, sparking Saddam's anger and costing Baghdad losses
of $14 billion, Iraq said.
   Kuwait has an OPEC quota of 1.5 million barrels of oil a day but
had been producing up to 1.9 million barrels a day, and it has
capacity to produce even more.
   Iraq has more than 100 billion barrels of oil reserves, while
tiny Kuwait itself floats on a sea of 94 billion barrels of oil.
   Both countries, however, still rely on foreign expertise both to
extract the oil and to conduct exploration work. The Western
sanctions will eliminate much of this assistance.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900805-0065 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-05-90 2219EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-IdleClinic     08-05 0466</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Idle Clinic,0482</SECOND>
<HEAD>Strict Air Force Standards Leave `Super Clinic' Without Surgeons</HEAD>
<DATELINE>GREAT FALLS, Mont. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A $16 million ``super clinic'' that
opened at Malmstrom Air Force Base three months ago isn't getting
full use because strict Air Force regulations disqualify most local
doctors from working there.
   Airmen and their families are being treated at two local
hospitals _ at greater expense _ by the same doctors.
   ``It's ironic,'' said Dr. Peter Horst, a private urologist.
``The Air Force is perfectly comfortable with us doing the same
work at local hospitals that we can't do at the new base clinic.''
   The clinic has been billed as the first non-hospital in the
military designed for out-patient surgery that civilian hospitals
offer.
   Twenty Great Falls physicians won contracts totaling about
$600,000 to perform surgery at the new base clinic, in addition to
their other work.
   But the Air Force has more stringent standards for physicians
who conduct so-called major surgery, such as hernia repairs, than
either Columbus Hospital or the Montana Deaconess Medical Center.
   Some of the surgeons tabbed to work at the Air Force clinic plan
to upgrade their medical certification, but 12 anesthesiologists
have balked at other Air Force requirements, like a dress code and
mandatory AIDS test.
   Horst estimated the certification would require two to 10 hours
of study and a few hours of testing.
   The problem was discovered in April, when paperwork was being
signed.
   ``We assumed the standards for downtown providers are the same
as for the Air Force, but they weren't,'' said Col. Ronald Burnett,
clinic commander.
   The service standards are more rigorous than at other Montana
hospitals and by the commission that accredits most civilian
hospitals, said Dr. John Highsmith, chief of clinical services at
Malmstrom.
   The reason for the Air Force standards is not clear, but the Air
Force has refused to grant Malmstrom a waiver.
   A primary Air Force requirement is that all doctors working in
high-risk fields to be certified in advanced cardiac life support.
Only one of the 20 Great Falls doctors has such certification.
   ``They obviously have the skills but may need a refresher
course,'' Highsmith said. ``It will be a formality to most of them
_ but it's a required formality.''
   Malmstrom offered a certification course in June, but most of
the doctors could not rearrange their schedules on short notice.
The Air Force is paying $1,500 to run another course Wednesday.
Seven doctors had signed up last week.
   Anesthesiologists are required for major surgery, but the 12
local specialists decided against working at the clinic because of
the dress code and AIDS test, and increased demand for their
services at the city's hospitals, said Dr. Fred Fleming.
   Malmstrom may have to hire resident anesthesiologists, a process
that could take months, Burnett said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900805-0066 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-05-90 2232EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-TropicalWeather 2ndLd-Writethru a0782 08-05 0352</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Tropical Weather, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0782,0361</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tropical Storm Whips Yucutan</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS thruout with storm advancing, two towns hard-hit, 9
p.m. update from Hurricane Center; no pickup</NOTE>
<DATELINE>MEXICO CITY (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Tropical Storm Diana spun off the Caribbean
and across the Yucatan Peninsula with 45 mph winds Sunday. No major
damage or injuries were immediately reported.
   The U.S. National Hurricane Center said the storm had hit the
coast by midafternoon about 70 miles northeast of Chetumal, capital
of Quintana Roo state.
   At 9 p.m. EDT, Diana was centered about 70 miles southeast of
Merida, Mexico. It carried maximum winds of 45 mph and was moving
northwest at 15 mph, according to the center in Coral Gables, Fla.
   Earlier, civil defense officials in Quintana Roo state had
issued a bulletin recommending that ``inhabitants of coastal zones
evacuate areas which could be flooded and homes which could suffer
damage due to weak construction.''
   It said refugee centers had been set up in elementary schools in
the towns of Xcalak, Punta Herrero and Punta Allen.
   People in the towns of Felipe Carrillo Puerto and Jose Maria
Morelos were urged to secure their belongings and move to primary
school shelters if their homes are not sturdy.
   State government spokesman Javier Venegas said those two towns
were the hardest hit.
   Residents of Cozumel and nearby towns were also urged to secure
their belongings and to be ready to move if necessary.
   The storm had crossed Quintana Roo by mid-evening and entered
the state of Yucatan, heading northwest toward the Gulf of Mexico,
said Venegas. However, heavy rain continued to fall, he said.
   Army crews said all federal roads in the state remained open.
Other teams were checking for flooding.
   Officials said they expected the storm to bring high winds and
heavy rains to the peninsula for up to 24 hours before heading on
toward the Gulf of Mexico.
   U.S. Hurricane Center forecaster Bob Case said five to eight
inches rain are possible along Diana's path across the Yucatan.
   The center of the storm was expected to emerge over the southern
Gulf of Mexico by early Monday.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900805-0067 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-05-90 2237EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Record-Suicide     08-05 0656</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Record-Suicide,0676</SECOND>
<HEAD>Outcome of Case Hinges on Credibility of Dueling Experts</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SANDRA CHEREB</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>RENO, Nev. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A judge may be asked this week to decide
whether a faint message was inserted into the blasting soundtrack
of a heavy-metal rock album, and whether that message drove two
troubled youths to try suicide.
   Attorneys for the families of Raymond Belknap and James Vance
concede there is not overwhelming scientific evidence to support
their claim that such subliminal words can be comprehended by a
person's unconscious mind and cause dramatic consequences.
   The families' case against the British rock band Judas Priest
and CBS Records is expected to conclude this week. Then, Washoe
District Judge Jerry Carr Whitehead will decide if the band's
``Stained Class'' album does contain hidden messages and, if so,
whether they contributed to the youths' deaths.
   Belknap, 18, died on Dec. 23, 1985, after firing a sawed-off
shotgun in his mouth. Vance, then 20, blew away the lower portion
of his face; he underwent numerous reconstructive surgeries before
dying on Thanksgiving Day 1988 of complications from his injuries
and a reaction to medications.
   Neither side disputes that the youths drank beer, smoked
marijuana and listened to the Judas Priest album before shooting
themselves.
   And they don't disagree that the use of drugs and alcohol
contributed to the young men's fates.
   There are few additional points of agreement.
   The defense maintains the youths' substance abuse, family
violence, brushes with the law and personality disorders
predestined their suicides.
   Attorneys for the families contend it was the Judas Priest
album, specifically the alleged subliminal message ``do it'' on the
song ``Better By You, Better Than Me,'' a song dealing with
suicide, that pushed them over the edge.
   Ken McKenna and Vivian Lynch, representing the families, offered
the testimony of a University of Michigan psychology professor to
support their case.
   Howard Shevrin said that while the youths had a predisposition
toward taking their lives, they would not have tried without the
subliminal messages. He said such a message issued in the form of a
command, such as ``do it,'' can create a compulsion that renders a
person helpless to deny it.
   ``They had no choice,'' Ms. Lynch said. ``They were compelled to
do what they did. It was totally beyond their control.''
   But Shevrin's testimony relied on the opinion of another
witness, William Nickloff, that the hidden messages exist, masked
by the pounding music.
   Defense attorneys Suellen Fulstone and Bill Peterson challenged
Nickloff's credibility, saying he held a degree in marine biology
and lacked expertise to pass judgment on the music's content.
   The band denies subliminal messages exist on the album.
   Lead singer Rob Halford gave a 10-second courtroom concert,
singing two lines from ``Better By You, Better Than Me,'' to
exhibit his explosive breathing style. He said the alleged ``do
it'' was no more than an exhalation combined with guitars and drums.
   Additional defense witnesses countered that the whole idea of
auditory subliminal messages is nonsense because it is impossible
to record below the frequency of ``white noise,'' a low hissing
found on all recordings.
   Still others said the brain cannot perceive anything it can't
hear.
   ``You hear what you hear,'' Stanford University Medical School
psychiatrist Donald Lunde said. ``We don't have more than one mind
up there. It either hears it, perceives it and registers it or it
doesn't.''
   The judge ruled the song lyrics are protected by the First
Amendment and are not on trial, but allowed the plaintiffs to
present testimony regarding themes found in heavy metal music.
   Ms. Lynch said the music's underlying themes focus on death,
rebellion and suicide, and therefore are relevant because they
enhance the predispositions of listeners, many of whom are
teen-agers.
   McKenna said the plaintiffs won a small victory last week when
Halford said under oath he used reversed lyrics on a song in a
Judas Priest album recorded seven years after ``Stained Class.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900805-0068 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-05-90 1730EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-GasolinePrices     08-05 0417</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gasoline Prices,0431</SECOND>
<HEAD>Gasoline Prices To Distributers Rise On Iraqi Invasion</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Gasoline dealers paid 9.5 cents more per
gallon last week for regular unleaded gasoline following the Iraqi
invasion of Kuwait, a survey of suppliers said Sunday.
   The Lundberg Survey of wholesale prices, the amount gasoline
dealers pay for their product, showed nationwide average prices
checked Friday rose to 76.5 cents a gallon among the most
price-sensitive wholesalers.
   The survey is taken weekly of about 75 percent to 80 percent of
suppliers of refined gasoline in the United States.
   Figures gathered since Friday indicate a weekend of increases.
Rough estimates show prices from the most price-sensitive suppliers
have gone up another 6 cents, survey chief Trilby Lundberg said
Sunday.
   Crude oil bought at last week's higher prices won't be refined
and flowing from U.S. gasoline pumps for about a month. But
Lundberg and an oil company spokesman said increases in the spot
market for gasoline translate into higher pump prices more quickly
during the summer.
   Many oil companies sell more gasoline than they refine during
the heavy-driving summer months, so they have to supplement their
supplies by buying on the volitile spot market, said John Lord, a
spokesman for Mobil Oil Co. in New York.
   ``The refinery industry is cranking out every gallon of gasoline
it can, and still has to buy on the spot market. The impact on the
gasoline distributing system is faster than ever,'' Lundberg said.
   Lord also said many are apparently anticipating higher costs
from the Iraq-Kuwait conflict.
   ``When you know future costs are going to go up, if you can
recover some of those costs today, you're going to do it if the
price will hold,'' Lord said. ``I think that's what's going on in
the marketplace.''
   Other increases over the week for the same grade of gasoline
were 4.73 cents, for 74.5 cents a gallon, for middle-market
distributors and 2.55 cents, for just over 78 cents a gallon, for
the most stable part of the market.
   Since Friday, estimates show prices in the middle market have
risen 3.25 cents, and 3.50 cents for the upper, or most stable,
market, Lundberg said.
   The most price-sensitive are the independent wholesalers that
have few, if any, long-term contracts with gasoline dealers, and
meet demand by getting supplies on the spot market.
   The most stable are those who deliver branded gasoline to
stations under a contract. Their higher base price allows more of a
cushion before changes affect their costs.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
</Collection>
