<Collection>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900617-0001 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-90 2328EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Swindler-Vigil     06-17 0342</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Swindler-Vigil,0353</SECOND>
<HEAD>Amnesty Group Asks Governor to Grant Clemency to Swindler, Simmons</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LITTLE ROCK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Members of Amnesty International on Sunday
called on Gov. Bill Clinton to grant clemency to two men facing
capital punishment, including one who would be the first person
executed in Arkansas in 26 years.
   About 50 members of the human rights group held a 26-minute
vigil on the steps of the state Capital.
   Cynthia Crawford of Little Rock read a statement imploring
Clinton ``not to end the decency of the past 26 years by
reinstituting this brutish form of violence.''
   ``We ask that he heed the words of Mrs. Coretta Scott King, a
woman left widowed by a murderer but who still opposes the death
penalty: `An evil deed is not redeemed by an evil deed of
retaliation.'''
   John Edward Swindler, 46, is scheduled to be executed Monday
night for the 1976 slaying of a Fort Smith policeman. If he is put
to death, he would be the first person executed in Arkansas in 26
years.
   Clinton last week denied Swindler's request that his death
sentence be commuted to life in prison without parole. The U.S.
Supreme Court on Saturday denied 7-2 Swindler's appeal for a stay
of execution.
   On June 25, Ronald Gene Simmons is scheduled to die by lethal
injection for the 1987 slayings of 16 people, including 14 family
members. He has declined to appeal his death sentences, saying he
wants to die.
   ``The members of Amnesty International in Arkansas are repulsed
at this reactivation of this state's machinery of death,'' Crawford
said. ``Just as Amnesty International opposes any use of torture,
we also oppose executions, the ultimate form of torture.''
   There was no counter-protest, but someone in a passing car
shouted out, ``Burn, Swindler, burn.''
   Crawford urged citizens who oppose the death penalty to wear
black armbands on the execution days.
   But the mother of slain Police Officer Randy Basnett said the
execution would not be a sad event for her. ``It will be a very
happy occasion,'' said Peggy Basnett.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900617-0002 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-90 2329EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Obit-Alexander     06-17 0171</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Alexander,0177</SECOND>
<HEAD>Nutrition Specialist Dies at Age 70</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Don Dale Alexander, a nutrition specialist
whose advice included a controversial
cod-liver-oil-and-orange-juice-mixture for arthritis, has died. He
was 70.
   Alexander died Friday of heart complications at Veterans
Administration Hospital in Los Angeles.
   He won acclaim in 1957 for his best-selling book, ``Arthritis
and Common Sense'' and often appeared on television talk shows. His
treatments were described in Life and other national magazines.
   ``Through study, logic and common sense we have decided that
arthritis is basically an oil deficiency in the human body and a
lack of Vitamin D,'' Alexander once wrote.
   He recommended the cod liver oil-orange juice mixture to achieve
the proper level of vitamins and ``lubricating oils.''
   The Federal Trade Commission accused Alexander of making false
and unsubstantiated claims. An FTC examiner characterized
Alexander's claims as ``merely a hodgepodge of scientific folderol
and medical mumbo jumbo.''
   The Norwich, Conn., native attended the Norwich Free Academy and
Trinity College in Connecticut and Columbia University in New York.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900617-0003 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-90 2340EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-GasDeath 1stLd-Writethru a0708 06-17 0168</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gas Death, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0708,0170</SECOND>
<HEAD>Gas Kills One, Sends Eight Others To Hospitals</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS grafs 4-end to UPDATE with conditions. No pickup.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>PHILADELPHIA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A generator spread noxious fumes in a
12-story office building Sunday, killing one man and forcing eight
others to seek hospital treatment, authorities said.
   The natural gas-powered generator was turned on after
Philadelphia Electric Co. switched off power to the Germantown
Savings Bank building in Lower Merion Township just outside
Philadelphia, apparently to allow workmen to make repairs,
authorities said.
   The generator's exhaust pipe was missing a section, allowing
deadly carbon monoxide to escape into the building, authorities
said.
   The victim, who carried no identification, died at Osteopathic
Hospital, according to spokeswoman Susan Soiferman.
   The hospital admitted a firefighter for inhalation of toxic
fumes, she said. He was listed in guarded condition.
   At Lankenau Hospital, doctors treated and released six
maintenance men, nursing supervisor Mary Leraril said. A second
firefighter was treated and released at Bryn Mawr Hospital,
authorities said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900617-0004 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-90 2344EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SriLanka     06-17 0477</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Sri Lanka,0498</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rebels Kill Soldier in Sri Lanka, But Cease-Fire Said Holding</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PATRICK CRUEZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>COLOMBO, Sri Lanka (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Tamil rebels shot and killed one
soldier in a northern town Sunday, but the day-old cease-fire
between government soldiers and insurgents held in other areas of
the country, officials said.
   A second soldier died Sunday of wounds inflicted in a Saturday
sniper attack.
   The government blamed the rebels for several other cease-fire
violations but said they ``could be due to lack of communications
with remote places.'' A spokesman for the rebels said the
cease-fire appeared to be holding.
   A joint government-rebel delegation was scheduled to tour the
cease-fire area Tuesday, the government said.
   The tour was previously scheduled for Monday and no reason was
given for the postponement.
   At least 376 people were killed in northern and eastern Sri
Lanka since Monday, when Tamil Tiger rebels broke a 13-month-old
truce.
   The death toll was compiled from accounts by witnesses, military
sources and rebel officials. The government has acknowledged losing
only 40 soldiers, while the Tigers admit only 72 guerrilla deaths.
   The cease-fire went into effect at 6 p.m. Saturday, five days
after the Tigers besieged about 20 police stations and captured
more than 850 policemen. The government rushed reinforcements to
the area and claimed to have retaken seven stations before the
cease-fire.
   There has been no word on the fate of the policemen, but
military sources and a lone survivor said 137 of the police were
disarmed and massacred by rebels.
   Several cease-fire violations were reported Saturday night and
again on Sunday, but a government communique said, ``reports
indicate the cease-fire has been satisfactorily observed.''
   The soldier killed Sunday was shot in Vavuniya, a town 135 miles
northeast of Colombo, the communique said.
   Another soldier, wounded by sniper fire Saturday night near the
port city of Trincomalee, 147 miles northeast of Colombo, died
Sunday, it added.
   Residents in Batticaloa and Vavuniya said the cease-fire was
generally holding but both the army and the Tigers were on full
alert.
   The previous cease-fire that held for 13 months collapsed after
fighting broke out in Batticaloa, a coastal town 136 miles
northeast of Colombo.
   The Batticaloa police station was the first captured by the
Tigers and is still in rebel hands.
   Ethnic Tamil militants took up arms against the
Sinhalese-dominated government in 1983 in their quest for a
separate homeland.
   The government and the Tigers, the most powerful Tamil guerrilla
group, declared a cease-fire in May 1989 and started negotiations
aimed at giving Tamil greater autonomy.
   More than 11,000 people have been killed since the insurrection
started.
   Tamils who make up 18 percent of Sri Lanka's 16 million people,
are predominantly Hindu and claim the Sinhalese majority, who are
mostly Buddhist, discriminate against them in jobs and education.
   Sinhalese comprise 75 percent of the population.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900617-0005 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-90 2349EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Sununu-NewHampshire     06-17 0845</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Sununu-New Hampshire,0872</SECOND>
<HEAD>Sununu's Influence Still Felt Back in New Hampshire</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Monday AMs report.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By ADOLPHE V. BERNOTAS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CONCORD, N.H. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   John Sununu wields his clout in Washington
these days but his influence still is felt in the state he governed
for six years before being tapped as George Bush's chief of staff.
   New Hampshire's immediate past governor is seen as a smooth
operator who does favors for his adopted home state but leaves few
political fingerprints.
   Some state Republicans express concern that Sununu is meddling
in local politics, but most consider his presence in the White
House to be an asset for the state.
   ``Sununu makes certain New Hampshire's place on the political
map is not forgotten,'' said GOP strategist Tom Rath.
   ``It was not an accident that the first place outside of
Washington that the president visited was New Hampshire,'' Rath
said, referring to a Bush stopover in Manchester not long after he
became president.
   As New Hampshire's governor, Sununu sided early with Bush in the
1988 presidential race. He helped engineer a Bush victory in the
state's earliest-in-the-nation primary and continued the national
campaign with attacks against Democratic nominee Michael Dukakis,
governor of neighboring Massachusetts.
   Sununu's political work continues even now. He had a guiding
role in easing the White House's hands-off policy toward party
primaries, putting the Oval Office behind candidates such as Rep.
Bob Smith, R-N.H., who hopes to replace retiring GOP Sen. Gordon
Humphrey.
   State GOP chairwoman Rhona Charbonneau wishes Sununu had stayed
out of the primary race between Smith and Rye lawyer Tom Christo.
   ``It's good to have a friend in the White House rather than a
foe,'' she said. ``But I truly wish they had kept out of the
primary. I don't believe anybody, not even the White House, should
be involved.''
   Sununu, whose influence also can be seen in some state races,
brushes off the criticism.
   ``We're not trying to pick candidates,'' he says. ``We're trying
to help the process.''
   His wife, Nancy, hasn't kept silent either. She said she
considered challenging U.S. Rep. Chuck Douglas for the GOP
nomination in New Hampshire's 2nd congressional district because
she ``never appreciated his values and his morals.''
   Sununu and his successor in the governor's mansion, Republican
Judd Gregg, have what insiders consider a civil relationship at
best. At a recent New Hampshire business dinner, Sununu sat next to
Senate President William Bartlett, who was considering challenging
Gregg.
   Sununu, 50, is described as Bush's right-hand man, part of a
White House troika with Secretary of State James Baker and budget
director Richard Darman.
   Many doubted the abrasive Sununu would last long in the White
House job after an admittedly rocky start. But now even his critics
have had to admit he appears to be effective and may wield more
power than any other recent chief of staff.
   Most Republican politicians believe it is to New Hampshire's
advantage to have Sununu in the White House.
   ``We may not get everything from the White House, but people at
the White House have the ear of New Hampshire,'' said Bill Zeliff,
a Sununu ally who is seeking the GOP nomination for Smith's
congressional seat.
   Sununu is seen as helping to place New Hampshire operatives in
federal positions, promoting the Seabrook nuclear power plant and
ensuring that important promises are fulfilled.
   When the Navy threatened 1,000 jobs by canceling a $128 million
submarine overhaul at the Portsmouth Naval Shipyard, Maine and New
Hampshire governors and congressional delegations won a pledge by
the Navy to find replacement work.
   Humphrey credits Sununu with making the Navy deliver.
   ``When those promises started to filter down, the Navy
bureaucracy was sidestepping it, so I called Sununu and he got them
to do what they said they would do,'' Humphrey recalls.
   Humphrey said Sununu is clearing similar hurdles for a proposal
the senator is championing to make a wildlife refuge out of some of
the land to be abandoned when Pease Air Force Base closes.
   A string of people with New Hampshire connections have been
appointed to federal posts since Sununu moved to Washington. Most
recently, Wally Stickney, a Sununu friend and associate, was
selected to head the Federal Emergency Management Agency.
   A highly placed Republican, who agreed to discuss Sununu only if
not quoted by name, said Sununu is adept at maintaining a low
profile in the state.
   ``He hasn't left any fingerprints or left anyone with a story
that they can tell that `Sununu sidled up to me, and so on.'''
   Seabrook, the Republican said, falls into that category. Sununu,
champion of the nuclear power plant when he was governor, ``didn't
just go to the Nuclear Regulatory Commission and say, `Give them
the license,''' the source said.
   ``He's been very cautious. But Seabrook got the license, didn't
it? He made sure his feelings on the topic were well known in the
appropriate places.''
   Sununu plays down his role in the licensing of Seabrook.
   ``I was a patient man,'' he said recently. ``I knew the right
thing would happen.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900617-0006 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-90 2349EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-DroughttoDrenched     06-17 1090</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Drought to Drenched,1120</SECOND>
<HEAD>Drought to Drenched: Farmers Hope Latest Cloud Has Silver Lining</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Monday AMs report.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By SHARON COHEN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Two years ago, Carl Marriott's farm fields were dusty, his
soybeans were shriveled, his prospects bleak. This spring, he has a
different brown, sickly crop, but there's a different culprit: rain.
   Yes, rain, the manna from heaven Midwest farmers hoped and
prayed for these past few years, has flooded fields, delayed
planting and damaged crops. But survivors of one _ or even two _
consecutive droughts aren't complaining.
   ``We just roll with the punches. We've got options we can pull
out of the bag when it's wet,'' said Marriott, a southern Illinois
farmer who may lose a quarter of his waterlogged wheat crop. ``When
it's dry, there's nothing we can do.''
   ``We've been biting our tongues,'' said Mark White, a Chariton,
Iowa, farmer whose fields were parched in 1988 and '89, then too
muddy to work all last month. ``I'll take a wet year over a dry
year anytime. At least you've got a chance to grow something.''
   After the most devastating decade in half a century, marred by
drought, high interest rates and plummeting land values, many
farmers have entered the 1990s with one of the wettest springs in
recent times and the brightest outlook in 10 years.
   ``The farmer is in the best shape he's been since 1980,'' said
Gregory Hanson, an economist at the U.S. Agriculture Department.
``We've got rising land values ... rising sales, rising investment.
I'm not trying to paint a Pollyanna picture _ on the other hand,
there's the famous rubber ball theory of economics: What bounced
down is now bouncing up.''
   Though an unseasonably cool, wet spring may prevent a bumper
crop, the economic forecast is promising: cash income for the farm
sector, which includes government subsidies, has been projected at
$55 billion to $59 billion for 1990 _ a record if it reaches the
outer limit and better than last year's estimated $54 billion.
   Hog and cattle prices are at or near record levels, corn prices
are up because the surplus is down, farm exports have increased,
land values are expected to rise about 4 percent in 1990 _ about
the same level they did in 1989 _ and machinery sales have jumped
by 50 percent in the last four years.
   ``When I look at the farm economy, I look at a growth sector,''
Hanson said. ``Ten years ago, it was a sector ready to take a
fall.''
   The national farm debt, which peaked in 1983 at $206 billion,
could dip to as low as $145 billion in 1990, he said.
   Farmers who survived the '80s are smarter and more careful about
their purchases, said Neil Harl, an economics professor at Iowa
State University.
   ``Some have been burned, some were singed, some were just close
to the heat,'' he said. At the same time, he added, ``Lenders are
more cautious and conservative.''
   As the new decade begins, some signs of a turnaround are due to
the weather, some to a reversal in economic fortunes. For example:
   _ In Kansas, a record winter wheat crop is forecast for 1990 _
460.2 million bushels, more than double last year's
drought-battered 213.6 million bushels.
   ``They're laughing,'' Jim Shroyer, extension agronomist at
Kansas State University said of the farmers. ``They're really
looking forward to harvest. This really lifts their spirits.''
   Nationally, winter wheat production is expected to reach a
nine-year high of 2 billion bushels, despite some losses from wet
weather.
   _ In Iowa, land values jumped nearly 45 percent from 1986 to
1989, though they're still far below 1981 peak levels. Less than
one in five farmers had significant money troubles last year,
compared with a third in 1986, Harl said.
   _ In Minnesota, state officials say soil moisture is the best it
has been since November 1986.
   Despite such optimistic signs, drought persists in areas,
including Florida and parts of Colorado. In California, in its
fourth straight dry year, reservoirs are low enough that the state
and U.S. Bureau of Reclamation cut in half the amount of this
year's irrigation water to farmers.
   And in the upper Midwest, even though puddles in the fields make
people smile _ a recent wet spell in North Dakota was dubbed the
``million-dollar'' rain _ they haven't convinced anyone the drought
is over.
   ``By no means are we out of the woods,'' said Tim Edman, special
assistant to South Dakota Gov. George Mickelson. ``If we go back to
the 90-degree-plus windy, dry weather conditions, we could be
facing a proble very quickly just as serious as the last two
years.''
   In 1988, all of South Dakota was declared a drought disaster
area; last year, it was two-thirds of the state.
   While many cursed the drought, others now say rainy, cool
weather is no blessing.
   In Michigan, for example, some apple growers say it's reduced
their crop. In Missouri, a fourth of the corn is in poor or very
poor shape, and planting is five weeks behind schedule. And in
Illinois, pastures with water belly-high to the livestock and
fields too muddy to put a tractor in have farmers worried.
   ``It's rained so much our wheat is full of blight,'' said Herman
Krone, who welcomed then-President Reagan to his shriveled southern
Illinois farm fields in 1988. ``Instead of ripening, it's dying in
standing water. ... It's been 43 years since I've seen something
like this.''
   But it's too early to make dire predictions, and dry, sunny days
last week allowed many farmers to get back into the fields. Some
also say as time runs out to plant corn, they may switch to
soybeans, which have a later growing season.
   That's an option for Marriott, a fourth-generation farmer who
normally would have planted all his corn by now but had completed
less than 5 percent by the second week of June, a situation to
which he's resigned.
   ``Farming is hills and valleys,'' he said. ``You have good crops
some years, and some years, good prices _ seldom together.''
   ``It's either feast or famine,'' said Bill Million, agriculture
extension adviser in Adams County, in western Illinois. ``Farmers
are just taking it one day at a time.''
   Not long ago, Million said, they looked to the skies for
salvation _ rain.
   ``Now they're praying for it to stop _ just a bit,'' he said.
``Typical human beings, we're never satisfied.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Sharon Cohen is the AP's Midwest regional
reporter, based in Chicago.
 
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900617-0007 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-90 2352EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-MandelaasSymbol     06-17 1035</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Mandela as Symbol,1054</SECOND>
<HEAD>Stirring the American Affection for the Underdog</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Monday AMs report.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By LEE BYRD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   On Thanksgiving eve of 1984, Randall Robinson,
a black American, walked into the South African embassy on
Massachusetts Avenue. In voice as smooth as worn saddle leather, he
chatted amiably for nearly an hour with then-ambassador Bernardus
Fourie. When it was time to go, he wouldn't.
   Not until, he insisted, South Africa freed Nelson Mandela and
all its black people.
   That night, in the D.C. jail, Robinson wondered where his first
arrest for civil disobedience would lead. America still was caught
up in its own civil rights debate, arguments raging over
affirmative action and school busing. The Middle East, Central
America, Eastern Europe, the Cold War with the Soviet Union and the
trade war with Japan dominated its global concerns.
   South Africa was as far south on that list as it is on the map.
   No more. Robinson, now 48, is executive director of TransAfrica,
a lobbying group for black Africa. And this week, he is bringing
Nelson Mandela to the United States, to ticker tape and Yankee
Stadium in New York City, to Hollywood and the Coliseum in Los
Angeles, to the Oval Office and Congress in Washington and to all
the front pages in between.
   And when he sends Mandela home, it will be with millions of
dollars to replenish the cash-starved accounts of the African
National Congress, to help it repatriate thousands of poor, exiled
members and re-establish internal operations after three decades of
official banishment.
   Of greater import, it will be with the assurance that this
nation, having lavished its affection on a man who strode so
elegantly from his prison cell onto the international stage last
February, will not retreat from its economic sanctions against the
South African government, no matter how badly the Bush
administration might wish it so.
   Mandela, 71, is coming to pick the fruits of political stardom,
just as Lech Walesa did a year ago. The difference is that Walesa,
the hero of Eastern Europe's flood tide of democracy, arrived the
conquering hero. Mandela, after nearly 28 years in prison, is ``out
of jail but he is not yet free,'' said New York Mayor David
Dinkins, alluding to the South Africa laws that still bar blacks
from full voting privileges and the right to travel and live
wherever they choose.
   So Mandela is sure to stir the special emotion that Americans
reserve for the heroic underdog. That fondness is far less
transitory than the cheers accorded victors, though Mandela may
return one day in that role, too.
   Robinson and other organizers of the Mandela visit have set a
34-event, 8-city agenda that would gladden the heart and tax the
energy of any rock star and any politician, starting with the
ticker-tape parade in Manhattan on Wednesday and ending with a
rally at the Oakland Coliseum 10 days later.
   Other stops include Boston, Atlanta, Miami, Detroit, Los Angeles
and Washington, where Mandela will meet Bush at the White House and
address a joint session of Congress, something no black American
has done.
   Mandela is likely to raise at least $8 million along the way,
from $5 general admission tickets at Yankee Stadium, where 60,000
are expected to flock, to $25,000-per-plate dinners for corporate
and show-business sympathizers. A Washington firm that manages the
financial affairs of athletic superstars, ProServ, expects to gross
another $3 million from the sale of Mandela T-shirts, posters,
coins, souvenir mugs and other promotional items.
   ``All of this,'' said ANC spokesman Victor Mashabela, ``is
powerful and positive.''
   And doubtlessly a little dismaying to the Bush administration,
which will publicly embrace Mandela as heartily as anyone but which
would prefer that his American accolades for courage be shared with
the man who released him, South African President Frederik W. de
Klerk.
   Bush's predecessor, Ronald Reagan, unsuccessfully vetoed the
1986 law that barred most trade with South Africa. Bush has argued,
as did Reagan, that more American commerce would be a greater force
for peaceful change than stiff sanctions.
   Recently, the administration quietly suggested to key members of
Congress that sanctions be relaxed when Pretoria meets the minimum
conditions of the Anti-Apartheid Act, particularly ending the
national state of emergency and freeing all political prisoners.
   Earlier this month, de Klerk lifted the state of emergency in
all but Natal province. But there are still South Africans in
prison for political reasons.
   Congressional leaders declared that it was too soon to consider
easing sanctions and the administration backed down. And the
anticipated outpouring of public support for Mandela during his
U.S. visit is sure to bolster congressional resolve on the issue.
   Mandela, while effusive in his praise for de Klerk's gestures,
continues to insist that they should not be rewarded with any
easing of U.S. economic pressures. ``That would be a grave
mistake,'' he said last week. ``It would be regarded by the people
of South Africa as a stab in the back.''
   Compounding any argument to the contrary by Bush is the
government's embarrassment over a recent report by the Cox News
Service that the CIA was responsible for Mandela's capture 28 years
ago, having tipped the South African government to his whereabouts.
White House spokesman Marlin Fitzwater initially declared ``We find
no value in reviewing a 30-year-old history in this case,'' but his
subsequent plea belied a greater sensitivity: ``This happened
during the (John F.) Kennedy administration ... don't beat me up
for what the Kennedy people did.''
   Mandela, a man of charity toward his aggrievers, is not likely
to rub that one in. He won't need to. He is coming a hero to
Americans known for viewing foreign leaders as either good guys or
bad. By the time he leaves, it may be difficult for George Bush or
anyone else to persuade them to see the conflict between white and
black South Africa in shades of gray.
   Sometime later this summer, de Klerk, too, will come to
Washington. He, too, will dine at the White House. But he will not
hear the roar of the American crowd, the cheers that this week will
belong to Nelson Mandela.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900617-0008 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-90 2355EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-Mandela-MoneyfortheCause     06-17 0968</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Mandela-Money for the Cause,0991</SECOND>
<HEAD>Americans Join Anti-Apartheid Cause</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Monday AMs report.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By JOAN MOWER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   High school students boycott Kellogg's
products. Mineworkers picket Shell Oil offices. A rap music group
cuts a song with the message ``don't buy gold jewelry'' from South
Africa.
   Americans have weighed the arguments on South Africa's racially
separate society, and many have lodged protests, large and small,
against apartheid. Some march; some lobby; some talk with their
pocketbooks.
   ``Do Americans care about sanctions? I'd say so when you have 80
cities, 25 states and 15 countries that have passed binding
measures restricting their investments in or their purchases in
companies that do business in South Africa,'' says Jim Casen of the
American Committee On Africa, a New York-based anti-apartheid group.
   Westchester, N.Y., recently pulled $40 million out of Citibank
to protest that company's rescheduling of South Africa's debt.
Another recent example: the state of New Jersey sold $4.2 billion
in securities of companies involved in South Africa.
   By all accounts, the U.S. sanctions have taken a serious
economic and psychological toll on South Africa. This week, black
leader Nelson Mandela tours the United States with this message:
please keep up the economic pressure.
   ``International trade sanctions alone have probably resulted in
a $2 billion loss annually to the South African economy,'' said
Stephen R. Lewis Jr., president of Carleton College and author of
``The Economics of Apartheid.''
   Although fewer than 1 percent of South Africans are employed by
American companies in South Africa, the sanctions sent the white
government a signal that it ``could no longer kid itself that
United States would come down on its side,'' he said.
   American blacks have played a major role behind the U.S.
sanctions policy. ``The black community has been a key ... and they
have become a firm base of the anti-apartheid movement,'' Casen
said.
   Black politicians, in concert with peace groups, labor and
college students, have spearheaded grassroots campaigns against
U.S. business in South Africa.
   Even on the eve of Mandela's visit, anti-apartheid activists
have maintained pressure. For instance, the Coca-Cola Co. has been
rebuffed in its efforts to support Mandela's eight-city tour.
   ``This company is still profiting from apartheid, and hence we
can't have any relationship with it,'' said Tandi-Luthuli Gcabashe,
coordinator of an international Coke boycott and a member of the
welcoming committee for Mandela in Atlanta. Coke divested its
bottling plants in South Africa in 1986 but still sells its
concentrate there.
   The first organized efforts to use U.S. economic power against
South Africa date from the early 1960s after the Sharpeville
massacre and the jailing of African National Congress leaders,
including Mandela. Mandela was released in February after 27 years
in prison.
   Lewis said South Africa has struck a chord with Americans where
other foreign policy issues have failed because apartheid is so
egregious and so obviously unfair.
   Perhaps the most visible grassroots campaign against South
Africa was organized by Transafrica, the Washington-based Africa
lobby. On Thanksgiving Day 1984, the group began well-publicized
daily marches outside the South African Embassy in Washington,
often ending with the orchestrated arrest of congressmen or
celebrities.
   The marches coincided with increasing violence in South Africa
as that country's white leaders tried to suppress uprisings in the
black communities. Television brought the violence into every
American home.
   The anti-apartheid activists' most striking success came in
October 1986 when Congress passed a comprehensive sanctions bill,
overriding then-President Reagan's veto.
   ``They finally made an impact on the whites,'' said Pauline
Baker of the sanctions. ``The economy was in irreversible
decline,'' said Ms. Baker, a South Africa expert at the Carnegie
Endowment for International Peace.
   The sanctions include a ban on the importation of South African
agricultural products, textiles, uranium ore, iron, steel and coal;
an end to new loans to South African businesses; an end to new U.S.
investment and a shutdown of U.S. oil exports to South Africa.
   Additionally, the United States does not sell Pretoria military
equipment, computer technology and other items that might be used
to enforce apartheid.
   On the eve of Mandela's visit to the United States, there have
been rumblings that the Bush administration might lift some
sanctions. But Congress imposed specific conditions for ending the
sanctions, not all of which have been met. For instance, all
democratic political activity must be legalized before sanctions
are removed, according to the legislation.
   While sanctions have damaged the South African economy and
ultimately contributed to the relaxation of apartheid, experts say,
they have not been totally effective.
   ``Although the South African economy is vulnerable to further
sanctions, it has no realistic `Achilles' heel,'' said a recent
report by the Investor Responsibility Research Center, a group that
monitors business activity in South Africa.
   ``Only a collapse in demand for South African gold or n
effective oil embargo would be likely to have crippling effects,
and neither of these sanctions appears imminent,'' the report said.
   South Africa's economy is fueled largely by the sale of gold and
other minerals, including diamonds. Gold accounts for 45 percent of
South Africa's export earnings.
   Sanctions against gold are relatively ineffective, a General
Accounting Office report said last October. It noted that millions
of dollars worth of South African gold and diamonds reach U.S.
consumers annually in the form of jewelry, which was not banned.
   Some members of Congress have also been upset because the United
States has allowed about 900,000 tons of South African steel to
enter the country despite the anti-apartheid laws.
   ``There is no excuse for the administration to allow even one
ounce ... of such products to enter the United States,'' said Rep.
John Bryant, D-Texas. The administration allows the steel imports
because U.S. lawyers have differentiated between steel and
fabricated steel products like girders and beams.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900617-0009 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-90 2356EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-SpottedOwl     06-17 0768</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Spotted Owl,0787</SECOND>
<HEAD>Owl to Slow Torrid Pace of Logging In Northwest's Virgin Forests</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Monday AMs report.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By HAL SPENCER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSSYROCK, Wash. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A shy little owl is about to slow the
flow of log-laden trucks through this and other timber towns
freckling the Pacific Northwest.
   The federal government is expected this week to list the
northern spotted owl as ``threatened'' by heavy logging on and near
the owl's virgin forest habitat. The action eventually could halt
logging on up to 8 million acres of timber, most of it controlled
by the U.S. Forest Service.
   There is no doubt the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service will list
the owl as threatened and move to protect it, said Sen. Mark
Hatfield, R-Ore. He and other Northwest leaders have searched for
compromise in the long and bitter fight between the timber industry
and environmentalists over the fate of Northwest forests, huge
swaths of which are hundreds of years old.
   ``It's going to throw us into a depression,'' says Norma Craig,
who owns a flower shop here. ``This is a cruel thing to do to
timber families, that somebody back East can make a decision about
an owl and ruin the timber industry.''
   But environmental leaders, whose lawsuits to protect the owl and
its ``old growth'' habitat provoked the major upheaval facing the
timber industry, are elated.
   The spotted owl is the ``canary in the coal mine,'' whose health
gauges the vitality of the canopied, cathedral-like forests where
it nests and roams, said Jim Pissot, director of the Audubon
Society of Washington.
   ``We've been over-cutting for years, and now one of the richest
biologicial treasures in the country, our ancient forest, is
literally on its last legs,'' he said. ``The listing of the spotted
owl will begin its recovery. It's absolutely a disgrace that we've
been cutting these magnificent centuries-old trees.''
   The old trees are prized by loggers for their huge girth and
fine grain.
   The Forest Service estimates that its 12 national forests in
Washington, Oregon and Northern California contain about 4 million
acres of old-growth timber. The Wilderness Society has called the
figure inflated.
   The economic and social impacts of logging limits still are not
fully known. They will depend on several variables, including how
government biologists interpret the Endangered Species Act to
protect owl habitat and on inevitable court challenges, Washington
Lands Commissioner Brian Boyle said.
   The Forest Service is awaiting interpretations before estimating
the size of timber shutdowns. But Forest Service biologist Jack
Ward Thomas and government colleagues recommend that about 8
million acres of mostly federal forests be shut to logging, about
half the federal land now available for logging.
   That would cost the region about 28,000 timber jobs over five
years, a federal study contends, but regional leaders and logging
groups say the employment impact could be much greater.
   Washington Gov. Booth Gardner and Oregon Gov. Neil Goldschmidt
recently commissioned a study on the effects on employment, logging
towns and timber prices.
   Reductions in Northwest timber harvests will have relatively
little impact on the region's overall economy, said Chang Mook
Sohn, Washington state's chief revenue forecaster and Oregon's
former state economist.
   He said logging and milling accounts for 2 percent of employment
in Washington and about 6 percent in Oregon. In California, it
accounts for less than a half percent of total employment, said
Karen Terrill of the California Department of Forestry. ``Oregon
will feel it the most,'' Sohn said.
   Individual timber communities will be greatly hurt, said David
Mendoza, a spokesman for the Washington Department of Employment
Security.
   ``People will be stuck with devalued property and no work,'' he
said. ``Many lack the skills to do other things. It is going to
devastate some of these towns.''
   President Bush said last week he is concerned about the impact
on timber communities but would oppose retraining timber workers at
federal expense.
   The Northwest congressional delegation is confident it will win
a measure, now in conference committee, to ease the pain: a curb on
exports of unprocessed logs from state-owned lands. That would
increase supply to domestic mills squeezed by heavy Asian demand
and falling supplies of private timber due to heavy cutting. By
law, federal timber cannot be exported.
   Even without federal closures, timber workers face hard times,
said Washington's Dan Evans, a former Republican U.S. senator and
governor.
   ``The timber industry has not been completely honest in this
whole thing,'' Evans said. ``Even without the spotted owl
situation, the idea that they could maintain the current level of
cut into the future indefinitely is just crazy.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900617-0010 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-90 2357EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-FlagBurning-Legislatures     06-17 0638</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Flag Burning-Legislatures,0661</SECOND>
<HEAD>Flag Burning Popular, But Most Legislatures Closed for the Year</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By POLLY ANDERSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   A constitutional amendment to protect the Stars and Stripes
enjoys wide popularity in state legislatures, but most of them have
finished their business for the year and won't consider
ratification anytime soon.
   ``There will be overwhelming support,'' said Georgia state Rep.
Bill Lee, chairman of the House Rules Committee. ``I'd lead the
charge.'' But Georgia, like more than half the states, has no
regular legislative session set until 1991.
   An Associated Press survey of state legislative leaders found
strong support in more than half of the nation's statehouses for an
amendment banning flag desecration.
   But skepticism in more than a dozen states, and legislative
timetables, mean there will be no rush to ratification even if
Congress approves an amendment this summer. The delay could give
emotions time to die down and opponents time to regroup.
   The Supreme Court issued its 5-4 decision June 11 _ three days
before Flag Day _ that flag burning is a form of political protest
protected by the First Amendment. The ruling threw out a law passed
by Congress after a similar high court ruling a year ago.
   Republican leaders immediately vowed to press for a 27th
Amendment to the Constitution. They are aiming for a vote before
July 4.
   Such a measure would have to pass Congress by a two-thirds vote
in each house and then be ratified by legislatures in
three-quarters, or 38, of the states.
   An AP survey following the Supreme Court decision found strong
support for the amendment, particularly in the South and Midwest.
   Legislative leaders stressed that the situation could change,
particularly since most votes would take place after the November
elections.
   Among the states where the amendment's chances look good:
Alabama, Arizona, Arkansas, California, Delaware, Florida, Georgia,
Idaho, Illinois, Indiana, Kentucky, Louisiana, Maine,
Massachusetts, Mississippi, Missouri, Montana, Nevada, New
Hampshire, North Dakota, Ohio, Oklahoma, Oregon, Pennsylvania,
Rhode Island, South Carolina, South Dakota, Tennessee, Texas, Utah,
West Virginia and Wyoming.
   In many of those states, legislators angered by last year's
Supreme Court decision have already passed some law or resolution
against flag burning.
   In Pennsylvania, home of Betsy Ross, resolutions asking Congress
to seek a flag-burning amendment easily passed both chambers, and
similar action is predicted on ratification.
   ``In this state, it would be like voting against apple pie or
motherhood,'' said Senate Minority Leader Robert J. Mellow, a
Democrat.
   States where skeptics could force a fight include Alaska,
Colorado, Hawaii, Iowa, Kansas, Maryland, Michigan, Minnesota,
Nebraska, New Mexico, North Carolina, Vermont, Virginia, Washington
and Wisconsin.
   In New York, the powerful Assembly speaker, Democrat Mel Miller,
strongly opposes an amendment and is in a position to block it.
   Only a handful of states have year-round legislatures; by
mid-June, most legislatures have adjourned for the year or are near
adjournment, including most of the states most strongly behind the
amendment.
   Louisiana's House has passed a bill reducing to a token fine the
penalty for beating up a flag-burner. A Senate committee endorsed
that bill last week. But the Legislature adjourns July 9.
   Illinois' Legislature adjourns June 30, but Gov. James Thompson,
a Republican, said Friday he would call a special session to hasten
a ratification vote.
   The last amendment to the Constitution, which lowered the voting
age to 18, took a little more than three months from its passage in
Congress in March 1971 to its ratification by 38 states.
   This time, with all but a handful of legislatures finished for
the year, or nearly so, no such speedy action is possible.
   ``It would be a five-year process if it worked,'' said the
majority leader in the Arizona Senate, Republican John Mawhinney.
``It would not be something that rolled through. We would not push
to be the first state.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900617-0011 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-90 2358EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-McAuliffePlanetarium     06-17 0608</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-McAuliffe Planetarium,0624</SECOND>
<HEAD>McAuliffe Planetarium Opens for Public: Memorial to Her Dream</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Monday AMs report.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By DAVID TIRRELL-WYSOCKI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CONCORD, N.H. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Nearly 4{ years after Christa McAuliffe
died, New Hampshire residents who burst with pride at her
accomplishment and cried in sorrow at her death have a place to
continue her journey.
   The state's official memorial to the Concord High School social
studies teacher, the state-of-the-art Christa McAuliffe
Planetarium, opens to the public this week. It's been open for
school groups since March.
   ``The staff sees this place as a memorial to her dreams, more
than a memorial to her as a person,'' director Clinton Hatchett
said. ``It is a memorial to her goals and what she wanted to do for
education and that is what we have tried to live by in creating our
programs.''
   McAuliffe, chosen from among 11,000 teachers to be the first
private citizen in space, died with six other crew members of the
space shuttle Challenger. The sparkling, pyramid-shaped planetarium
is within sight of her hillside resting place.
   A state commission selected the planetarium as the state's
official memorial to McAuliffe from scores of suggestions, which
included a statue, portrait or state holiday.
   After viewing a demonstration program for the school opening in
March, McAuliffe's husband, Steven, said he thought the planetarium
staff had lived up to his wife's goals.
   ``I know Christa would be delighted,'' he said.
   Thursday's dedication features NASA administrator Richard Truly,
who helped reorganize the space program after the 1986 disaster,
and White House Chief of Staff John Sununu. As governor, Sununu
tearfully led a Statehouse service in McAuliffe's memory.
   One of the most popular items in the $2.6 million planetarium is
its computerized multimedia presentation that allows audience
members to vote electronically on what ``destinations'' they want
to go to and what they want to do when they get there.
   With moving pictures and sound, a demonstration program took
viewers inside the human body, rode them around in an atom and
along a musical journey through geometric shapes. At times the
feeling of motion was dizzying, and spectators held on to the arms
of their seats for balance.
   ``Some groups may spend most of their time not going out beyond
Jupiter, and another group might head all the way out to the outer
solar system right away,'' Hatchett said.
   Hatchett said the system also can be programmed for
presentations on geology, meteorology, art, the history of music or
the demise of the dinosaurs.
   More than 12,000 school children have visited the planetarium
since March. Hatchett said the only complaint he heard was that the
program was too short.
   The planetarium is expected to be a big public attraction, but
it's main goal is to be a classroom, with programs designed for
different age groups and skills and for teacher workshops.
   Hatchett said McAuliffe's memory pervades the building, from the
lobby that features her smiling portrait, to Digital Equipment
Corp. computers donated by the company to run the mind-boggling
programs.
   ``The contractors that have worked on the building and have been
involved in donating time and materials have done it because of
Christa McAuliffe and what she stood for, how the community feels
about the whole situation and her having a dream tha was not met,''
Hatchett said. ``They want to help meet that goal here.''
   Hatchett said it's almost like the teacher-astronaut is looking
over their shoulders.
   ``I don't feel that she is here in any kind of mystical way, but
in our minds, we are always thinking, `How would Christa feel about
this? Would she be happy about this?'''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900617-0012 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-90 2359EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-CommissionMembers     06-17 0377</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Commission Members,0410</SECOND>
<HEAD>list of Commission Members</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: EMBARGOED for noon EDT.</NOTE>
<HEAD>With PM-Work Skills</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Following are the members of the Commission on
the Skills of the American Work Force:
   _ Ira C. Magaziner, commission chairman, president, Telesis.
   _ William E. Brock, commission co-chairman, former U.S.
secretary of labor.
   _ Ray Marshall, commission co-chairman, former U.S. secretary of
labor.
   _ Robert M. Atkinson, director of academic programs, School of
Business and Industry, Florida A&amp;M University.
   _ Owen Bieber, president, United Auto Workers.
   _ Edward J. Carlough, president, Sheet Metal Workers union.
   _ Anthony P. Carnevale, vice president, American Society for
Training and Development.
   _ Paul J. Choquette, Jr., chief executive, Gilbane Construction
Co.
   _ Richard Cohon, president, C.N. Burman Co.
   _ Badi G. Foster, president, Aetna Institute for Corporate
Education.
   _ Thomas Gonzales, chancellor, Seattle Community College
District.
   _ W.J. Holland, Jr., retired Navy rear admiral, president,
Educational Foundation, AFCEA International.
   _ James R. Houghton, chairman, Corning Inc.
   _ James B. Hunt, Jr., former governor of North Carolina.
   _ John R. Hurley, vice president, Chase Manhattan Bank.
   _ John E. Jacob, president, National Urban League.
   _ Thomas H. Kean, former governor of New Jersey, president, Drew
University.
   _ William H. Kolberg, president, National Alliance of Business.
   _ William Lucy, secretary-treasurer, American Federation of
State, County and Municipal Employees.
   _ Margaret L.A. MacVicar, dean for undergraduate education,
Massachusetts Institute of Technology.
   _ Eleanor Holmes Norton, professor of law, Georgetown University
Law Center.
   _ Karen Nussbaum, executive director, 9-5, National Assocation
of Working Women.
   _ Peter J. Pestillo, vice president, Ford Motor Co.
   _ Philip H. Power, chairman, Suburban Communications Corp.
   _ Lauren B. Resnick, director, Learning Research and Development
Center, University of Pittsburgh.
   _ Kjell-Jon Rye, teacher, Bellevue (Wash.) Public Schools.
   _ Howard D. Samuel, president, Industrial Union Department,
AFL-CIO.
   _ John Sculley, chairman and CEO, Apple Computer Inc.
   _ William J. Spring, vice president, Federal Reserve Bank,
Boston.
   _ Anthony J. Trujillo, superintendent, Sweetwater Union High
School District, Chula Vista, Calif.
   _ Marc S. Tucker, president, National Center on Education and
the Economy.
   _ Laura D'Andrea Tyson, Berkeley Roundtable on International
Economy.
   _ Kay R. Whitmore, president, Eastman Kodak Co.
   _ Alan L. Wurtzel, chairman, Circuit City Stores.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900617-0013 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-90 0013EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-PeorianKidnapped     06-17 0264</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Peorian Kidnapped,0272</SECOND>
<HEAD>Parents of Kidnapped Peorian Will Go To Ecuador</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PEORIA, Ill. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The parents of a gold miner kidnapped by
Colombian guerrillas said Saturday they planned to go to South
American so they can work more effectively for their son's release.
   ``It looks like I'm going to have to go and get him out,'' Marge
Heimdal, of Peoria, said in a telephone interview from a location
where she and her two daughters have sought refuge from the news
media.
   Scott Heimdal, 27, who worked for the IMINCO, a gold mining
company in Quito, Ecuador, was kidnapped April 28 while traveling
on business along the Bermeja River near Ecuador's border with
Colombia.
   Officials have said a band of the People's Liberation Army
attacked his canoe, killing the pilot and taking Heimdal and an
Ecuadoran hostage.
   Mrs. Hemidal said ``something big is going to happen in two or
three days _ things will be handled,'' but she would not explain
what she meant.
   In a development Friday, Peoria television station WHOI reported
that Heimdal's kidnapping might not have been a random act of
terrorism, but a plot involving a former mining company employee to
extract money from the company.
   In a four-day fund-raising push last week, the Heimdals raised
$60,000 from Peoria residents, believing it would meet the
kidnappers' ransom demands. But they learned Wednesday that the
kidnappers actually wanted $612,000.
   On Thursday, the Heimdals made public a four-page letter from
their son, in which he said he was being moved daily in the jungle
and surviving on armadillo and monkey meat.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900617-0014 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-90 0024EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-SuicideDeaths     06-17 0160</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Suicide Deaths,0163</SECOND>
<HEAD>Suicide Try Kills Two Women</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HOLTS SUMMIT, Mo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A woman was overcome by carbon monoxide
fumes trying to prevent her mother-in-law from committing suicide,
authorities said Saturday.
   Juanita M. Gordon, 51, died Friday afternoon when she tried to
rescue Maggie E. Gordon, 72, from the mother-in-law's basement
garage in the central Missouri community, said Callaway County
Sheriff Harry Lee.
   The older woman apparently went to the garage, started her car
and got in the back seat. Exhaust fumes filed the garage and the
woman died of asphyxiation, Lee said.
   Juanita Gordon, who made a daily check on her mother-in-law,
went into the garage and tried to save the older woman, but was
overcome by fumes, the sheriff said. She tried to flee and
collapsed at the front door.
   Maggie Gordon was apparently depressed about the January 1989
death of her husband of more than 50 years, Roy, and her own
medical problems, Lee said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900617-0015 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-90 0045EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Bulgaria-Elections 1stLd-Writethru a0545LX 06-17 0564</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bulgaria-Elections, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0545,0580</SECOND>
<HEAD>Former Communists Look to Secure Parliamentary Majority in Runoff
Elections</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with three grafs to UPDATE with polls opening. Pickup
3rd graf pvs: The vote ...</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By ROLAND PRINZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SOFIA, Bulgaria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Bulgarians cast ballots Sunday in an
election runoff that may give former Communists a majority in the
country's first freely elected Parliament in 58 years.
   The main opposition parties have said they won't join in a
coalition government with the ex-Communists.
   But there were indications that leaders of the Socialists _ the
former Communists _ and the opposition might support a government
run by non-partisan technocrats.
   The vote comes one week after an initial round of balloting last
Sunday, the first free elections in Bulgaria since 1932.
   The Socialists won the most seats in the first round, 172 in the
400-seat unicameral Grand National Assembly. The main opposition
alliance, the Union of Democratic Forces, was second with 107
seats, and other opposition groups won a total of 40 seats.
   The Socialists, who carried out democratic reforms after ousting
longtime Communist leader Todor Zhivkov last year, need only 29 of
the 81 seats up for grabs Sunday for a majority.
   Polls open at 7 a.m. and close at 6 p.m. Final results were not
expected until later in the week.
   At final rallies late Friday, Socialist Party leader Alexander
Lilov predicted a ``powerful victory'' in the runoff.
   One opposition leader, Rumen Vodenicharov, told 10,000
supporters that ``the second round is a referendum for democracy.''
   Even if the Socialists win outright, they will be faced with a
strong opposition in parliament and will no longer be able to
expect automatic approval of their policies.
   The mainstream Agrarian Party, a former docile ally of the
Communists during their four decades of rule, earlier this year
declared their independence and have rejected entering any
coalition with the Socialists. Leaders of the Agrarian Party, which
garned only 8 percent of the vote in the first round, have called
on its voters to back the Democratic Front on Sunday.
   In an interview carried Saturday by the Socialist daily Duma,
Premier Andrei Lukanov said ``national consensus is absolutely
necessary. ... With a government comprised only of BSP (Socialist)
members, this cannot be realized.'' He has repeatedly said he would
not head such a Cabinet.
   However, the Democratic Front has repeatedly ruled out a
coalition with the former Communists.
   Front leader Zhelyu Zhelev spoke Thursday of ``a government of
competent people _ of experts'' who are non-partisan.
   That idea, sources said Saturday, is also shared by President
Petar Mladenov and other leading Socialists.
   Ivailo Trifonov, a close associate of Zhelev, hinted there was a
possibility of such a solution.
   While no agreement had been reached within the 16-party
Democratic Front, Trifonov said Friday: ``If we arrive at this
possibility, it should be a government of non-partisan experts.''
   Such a solution would be ``a coalition through the backdoor,''
said a Western diplomat Saturday, who insisted on anonymity.
   The main task of the Parliament will be to draft a new
constitution and enact legislation designed to lead this nation of
9 million out of its deep economic crisis.
   Under Bulgaria's electoral law, half the seats are distributed
according to the percentage of votes each party receives under the
proportional system, The other half go to individual candidates
elected by direct ballot.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900617-0016 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-90 0051EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-SunkenTreasure     06-17 0357</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Sunken Treasure,0366</SECOND>
<HEAD>Underwater Robot Plucks 17th-Century Gold Bar From Ocean</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TAMPA, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A gold bar plucked by an underwater robot
from a shipwreck in 1,500 feet of water off southwest Florida
provides strong evidence that treasure hunters have located part of
a gold-laden fleet sunk in 1622.
   Official seals of the Spanish crown on the 1 pound, 8 ounce bar
indicate it may be part of a fleet of ships lost in a 1622
hurricane in the treacherous waters south of Key West, said marine
archaeologist Robert Marx.
   The bar resembles gold carried by the Nuestra Senora de Atocha,
a galleon discovered in shallow water in the Keys by treasure
hunter Mel Fisher in 1985. That discovery yielded gold and
artifacts worth $400 million.
   The latest wreck is the first intact Spanish galleon ever found
in deep water, the treasure hunter said.
   Seahawk Deep Ocean Technology, founded by Marx in 1986, spotted
the gold bar last week during part of a survey in preparation for
archaeological excavation 75 miles from land, said Seahawk director
Dan Bagley III.
   ``Since gold bars often had marks lending clues to the ship's
identity, our excavation team decided to bring this piece up to
investigate immediately, rather than completing the survey and
coming back,'' Bagley said.
   Of particular interest is the marking ``en rada'' stamped into
the metal, which also was found on some of the Atocha's gold bars.
   Other seals indicate that it was documented gold, not
contraband, being brought back to Spain, Marx said.
   The first artifact retrieved to identify the ship was a bell
recovered last summer by the company's smaller Remotely Operated
Vehicle. But the bar confirms that the ship could yield a major
treasure, Bagley said.
   ``We feel the information we've gleaned from this artifact goes
a long way in help us verify which ship we have,'' Bagley said.
``We are very encouraged by this.
   ``While we are being very cautious and not predicting the name
of the vessel, it appears it was one of the galleons disignated to
carry official treasure in the same time frame the Atocha was
lost,'' Bagley said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900617-0017 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-90 0731EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i BC-Lebanon-Palestinians     06-17 0552</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Lebanon-Palestinians,0571</SECOND>
<HEAD>Four Killed in Fight Between Supporters and Opponents of Abu Nidal</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TYRE, Lebanon (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Fighting erupted Sunday in a Palestinian
refugee camp between rival factions of the guerrilla group led by
terrorist mastermind Abu Nidal, leaving at least four people dead
and 15 wounded, police said.
   The fighting broke out around midnight at the Rashidiyeh refugee
camp, and continued until 9 a.m. when guerrillas from Yasser
Arafat's mainstream Palestine Liberation Organization intervened.
   Supporters and opponents of Abu Nidal _ representing rival wings
of his Fatah-Revolutionary Council _ fought in the narrow alleys of
the shantytown with mortars, machine guns and rocket-propelled
grenades, according to police and Palestinian sources.
   The showdown was the bloodiest in Lebanon between the two
factions since an anti-Abu Nidal mutiny began in the
Fatah-Revolutionary Council ranks three years ago.
   Rashidiyeh, about 50 miles south of Beirut, houses 18,500
Palestinians registered by the United Nations Relief and Works
Agency, as well as a few thousand unregistered refugees.
   The sources, requesting anonymity, said Abu Nidal's opponents,
backed by fighters of the PLO's largest faction, Fatah, occupied a
school run by UNRWA, which cares for Palestinian refugees.
   The three-story school building overlooks the main position held
by Abu Nidal's loyalists.
   The Abu Nidal opponents demanded that his supporters surrender
or risk being dislodged by force, the sources said.
   Forty Abu Nidal loyalists surrendered after the mediation of
representatives of other PLO groups. The Fatah-Revolutionary
Council is outside the PLO, which brings together nine Palestinian
groups.
   The fighting flared up after the shooting death in Rashidiyeh
Saturday of Omar Hamadeh, an Abu Nidal loyalist who was Tyre
regional commander of the Fatah-Revolutionary Council. His
bodyguard, Mohammed Meri, was wounded in the shootout with fighters
from the Fatah group.
   On Friday, a PLO official was shot to death at his home in
Rashidiyeh. No group has claimed responsibility, but a PLO
statement blamed the killing on Israeli collaborators seeking to
provoke clashes between Arafat loyalists and opponents in the camps.
   Fatah-Revolutionary Council and Fatah are at odds because of a
bitter feud over policy between Abu Nidal, whose real name is Sabri
al-Banna, and Arafat.
   The dispute within the Fatah-Revolutionary Council began in 1987
shortly after Abu Nidal moved his headquarters from Syria to Libya.
   Abu Nidal opponents and PLO officials have said that Abu Nidal
had 22 close aides gunned down at his base in Libya. The killings
followed a meeting of the group's ruling politburo and guerrilla
commanders.
   About 300 Fatah-Revolutionary Council guerrillas fled from Libya
to Algeria, forming an opposition group led by Abdul-Rahman Issa, a
member of the politburo, and Atef Abu Bakr, the group's spokesman.
   Issa was wounded in an assassination attempt in Algiers earlier
this year that was blamed on Abu Nidal.
   Most of the Abu Nidal opponents have infiltrated to Lebanon in
the past year.
   Abu Nidal is believed to be in Libya, despite reports that
Libyan leader Col. Moammar Gadhafi was seeking his ouster in order
to distance himself from international terrorism.
   A U.S. State Department report last year described Abu Nidal as
the world's most dangerous terrorist.
   It blamed his group for 34 terrorist attacks in 20 countries
since he split from the PLO in 1973. At least 900 people were
killed or wounded in these attacks, the report said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900617-0018 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-90 1123EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--SAfrica-Violence     06-17 0166</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--SAfrica-Violence,0170</SECOND>
<HEAD>Four Policemen, One Black Youth Killed</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JOHANNESBURG, South Africa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Four black policemen and a
black youth were killed in unrest incidents, police reported Sunday.
   Authorities said the youth was fatally shot Saturday when police
fired on a group of blacks stoning a police vehicle near
Stilfontein, about 100 miles southwest of Johannesburg.
   The youths were attending one of dozens of rallies held
nationwide Saturday to commemorate the 14th anniversary of student
uprisings in Soweto, the huge black township outside Johannesburg.
   For the first time since the 1976 riots, the government
permitted anti-apartheid demonstrations on ``Soweto Day'' without
major police intervention.
   Two policemen were fatally shot in Soweto, a third was killed in
Katlehong township, southeast of Johannesburg, and the fourth was
shot in the northeastern corner of the country, the daily police
unrest report said.
   The report, which covers incidents from the previous 24 hours,
did not say if the attacks on the police were directly related to
``Soweto Day'' activities.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900617-0019 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-90 1123EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--Portugal-Film     06-17 0172</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Portugal-Film,0177</SECOND>
<HEAD>Algerian Film Wins Troia Film Festival</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TROIA, Portugal (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Algerian director Rachid Benhadj won the
best picture award at the sixth-annual Troia film festival Sunday,
and a U.S. documentary on the environment also was honored.
   A jury of international cinema professionals headed by Hungarian
director Marta Meszaros gave Benhadj the Golden Dolphin prize for
the film ``Louss,'' which tells the story of a disabled boy living
with his sister in a remote Sahara Desert oasis.
   The jury awarded a special prize to Argentine director Jorge
Polaco for ``Kindergarten,'' a love story in a Buenos Aires
neighborhood.
   A U.S. film took first place in the festival's Man and Nature
section for films on the environment.
   The documentary, ``Building Bombs,'' looks at the social and
environmental impact of the Savannah River nuclear facility in
South Carolina. The film was directed by Mark Mori and Susan
Robinson.
   The main competition in the festival, held in this southern
Portuguese resort, is for films from countries that produce fewer
than 20 features yearly.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900617-0020 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-90 1124EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-China-Floods     06-17 0239</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-China-Floods,0247</SECOND>
<HEAD>More Than 100 People Die in Floods</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   More than 100 people died in floods caused by
torrential rains in China's southern province of Hunan, an official
newspaper said Sunday.
   A separate report said three people also were killed in
neighboring Jiangxi province.
   The flooding in Hunan knocked down about 16,000 homes, killed
2,905 farm animals and damaged 30,000 water conservancy projects,
the People's Daily reported. It said more than 740,000 acres of
farmland were inundated.
   The newspaper said 39 Hunan cities and counties recorded more
than 4 inches of rain in storms that hit the province between last
Monday and Friday. Heavy rains also hit Hunan earlier this month.
   The official Xinhua News Agency said Xupu county was under 6{
feet of water Friday and that at one point 10,000 people were
trapped in buildings.
   They were moved to safety when the flood waters began to recede
Friday evening, it said.
   The evening news Saturday showed turbulent rivers and peasants
wading through flooded streets and rice paddies, but made no
mention of casualties.
   A China News Service report seen Sunday said three days of
continuous rain last week in Jiangxi province killed three people
and caused the collapse of 236 bridges and 330 homes.
   Southern and central China frequently suffer loss of life and
damage from summer flooding. Last summer nearly 3,000 people were
killed, half in the populous southwestern province of Sichuan.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900617-0021 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-90 1134EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Scotus-What'sLeft Bjt   06-17 0587</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Scotus-What's Left, Bjt,570</SECOND>
<HEAD>Right-to-Die Case Decision Expected Before Court Recesses</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RICHARD CARELLI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The first ``right-to-die'' case to reach the
Supreme Court is among two dozen still awaiting decision by the
justices before they embark on a summer-long recess.
   The court will announce rulings twice this week, on Monday and
Thursday, and could wrap up its term next week.
   The most closely watched case awaiting decision centers on the
asserted constitutional right to withdraw life-sustaining medical
treatment, including feeding tubes.
   The issue is presented in the case of Nancy Cruzan, a
permanently unconscious Missouri woman being kept alive with food
and water supplied through a tube surgically implanted in her
stomach.
   Ms. Cruzan's parents want to end her life, but the Missouri
Supreme Court, bucking a trend among courts nationwide, refused in
1988 to let doctors remove the feeding tube.
   Many experts expect the nation's highest court to issue a
narrowly worded ruling, but whatever the justices say likely will
have an enormous impact in the continuing national debate.
   Also awaiting decision before the end of the term are cases on
the abortion rights of young girls, the future scope of political
patronage, the rights of people charged with child abuse to
confront their young accusers and the validity of federal policies
that favor women and minorities in awarding broadcast licenses.
   The court is studying laws in Ohio and Minnesota that ban
abortions for unmarried young girls unless their parents are
notified beforehand.
   The decisions are not expected to affect the court's 1973 Roe
vs. Wade ruling that legalized abortion.
   The justices have been studying an Illinois dispute over the
power of government employers to base hiring, transfer and
promotion decisions on an employee's political affiliation.
   The court significantly weakened the political patronage system
a decade ago when it barred government employers from firing anyone
_ even some policy-making and confidential government workers _
solely because of their political party unless party loyalty is
required for effective performance.
   But the prior rulings dealt only with firings. Now the court
must say whether the same constitutional protections apply to
hirings, transfers and promotions.
   Cases from Maryland and Idaho ask the court to decide whether
people charged with child abuse have the right to at least one
face-to-face confrontation with their young accusers.
   What the justices must decide is whether the Constitution allows
exceptions to such potentially traumatic encounters.
   In an important test of its continued support of affirmative
action, the court is reviewing the Federal Communications
Commission's policies of giving women and minorities special
preferences when awarding broadcast licenses.
   The policies are being challenged in cases from Florida and
Connecticut as unconstitutionally discriminatory against white men.
   Other controversies expected to be resolved before the court
term ends include:
   _The scope of authority enjoyed by the federal program
protecting the pensions of 30 million American workers to order
employers to restore terminated pension plans. Government lawyers
told the justices a potential financial crisis for the program
hangs in the balance.
   _A freedom-of-speech dispute from Maryland over a ban on all
soliciting at most of the nation's post offices.
   _Whether police violate the rights of motorists suspected of
drunken driving by videotaping their responses before warning them
of their right to remain silent or have a lawyer present. Such
police tactics are under attack in a Pennsylvania case.
   _An Ohio dispute that asks whether the Constitution's
free-speech protections immunize all expressions of opinion, as
opposed to assertions of fact, from libel lawsuits.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900617-0022 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-90 1149EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-WaterlooAnniversary     06-17 0566</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Waterloo Anniversary,0583</SECOND>
<HEAD>Napoleon's Last Stand Restaged On 175th Anniversary Battle of
Waterloo</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT J. WIELAARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BRUSSELS, Belgium (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   About 2,300 weekend soldiers in period
costumes marched back in time Sunday to restage Napoleon's last
stand, the 1815 Battle of Waterloo.
   There was much smoke but no fire, as they redid the battle on
the very site where Napoleon's Grande Armee of 70,000 suffered its
final defeat by more than 100,000 British, Dutch, Belgian, German
and Prussian troops allied under the Duke of Wellington.
   Sunday's ranks featured history buffs of all ages from the
victorious counties as well as France, the United States, Canada
and even the Soviet Union, organizers said.
   At least 80,000 spectators lined the battlefield and sat on the
Butte du Lion, a 130-foot mound topped by a lion overlooking the
farmlands near Waterloo, today a Brussels suburb, where Napoleon
lost his empire.
   They watched soldiers in 19th century uniforms on foot and
horseback moving across grassy knolls, wielding muskets, sabres and
military banners.
   The sound of cannon fire, fifes, drums and bagpipes filled the
air as the soldiers, moving shoulder to shoulder, repeated the
events of June 18, 1815.
   The battle has been revisited in previous years under the
auspices of the British Napoleonic Society, which even supplies a
Napoleon and a Duke of Wellington.
   But Sunday's show was to mark the real event's 175th
anniversary. Among the spectators was the current _ and eighth _
Duke of Wellington, Lord Arthur Valerian Wellesley.
   The festivities began Saturday with a light-and-sound show and
fireworks at the manmade Butte du Lion.
   The Battle of Waterloo is also commemorated in a number of
exhibitions in Belgian museums and in the farm houses that served
as battlefield command posts and headquarters during the fighting.
   Sunday's battle was broadcast live on RTBF, Belgium's
French-language television network. The 90-minute re-enactment
showed soldiers firing and ``dying'' in the fields that roll toward
the French border, 30 miles away.
   Of course, Napoleon lost again.
   After his first defeat in 1814, Napoleon went to the
Mediterranean island of Elba. He returned to mainland France on
March 20, 1815, rounded up an army and set out to fight the allies
in Belgium and regain his empire, whose roots lay in the French
Revolution of 1789.
   The real battle lasted a day and seemed made in Hollywood: The
bad guy might have won if not for the last-minute arrival of
Marshal Gebhard Bluecher's Prussian troops, who turned the tide for
the allies.
   Estimates of the dead at Waterloo range from 12,000 to 50,000
plus 10,000 horses. The injured numbered 40,000, many of whom were
robbed by local townsfolk and riffraff that followed armies around
Europe in those days.
   Napoleon was shipped to the South Atlantic island of St. Helena,
where he died and was buried in 1821. Years later, his body was
returned to Paris.
   The Waterloo battlefield _ an area of 1{ by 3 miles _ was named
a historic site in 1914, and urban development is banned there.
   Even so, this has not prevented a proliferation of tawdry
souvenir shops and restaurants offering ``battlefield specials.''
In recent decades, tourism has dropped sharply from a high of a
million visitors a year in the 1950s.
   Nothing reflects this more than the dilapidated building, next
to the memorial mound, which offers a 360-degree view of the battle.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900617-0023 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-90 1153EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Obit-Turner     06-17 0505</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Turner,0520</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dame Eva Turner, Wagnerian Diva, Dead at 98</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT BARR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Dame Eva Turner, a dramatic soprano of
extraordinary range and power and a memorable star of Puccini's
``Turandot,'' has died. She was 98.
   Miss Turner, who had suffered a broken hip three months ago,
died Saturday at Devonshire Hospital in London, said Katherine
Morgan, a relative.
   Blessed with a powerful voice and an extraordinary range, Miss
Turner was one of the first British sopranos to achieve stardom in
Europe.
   ``Her voice of enormous proportions in its prime, ranging from G
to top D, and her generous personality were admirably suited to the
dramatic soprano roles in Verdi and Wagner,'' the late Harold
Rosenthal, longtime editor of Opera magazine, once wrote.
   Born March 10, 1892, in Oldham, Lancashire, she joined the Royal
Carl Rosa Opera Company in London in 1916. She made her debut a
year later as a page in Wagner's ``Tannhaeuser'' and rapidly took
on lead roles in productions of ``Tosca,'' ``Aida'' and ``Madama
Butterfly.''
   Ettore Panizza, assistant to the great Italian conductor Arturo
Toscanini, heard Miss Turner in a 1924 production of ``Madama
Butterfly'' and arranged an audition.
   Toscanini was enchanted.
   Miss Turner made her debut at La Scala in Milan in 1924 as Freia
in Wagner's ``Das Rheingold,'' and toured with an Italian company
in Germany in 1925.
   ``It was extremely rare for a British soprano to go abroad like
that, and her becoming acknowledged on the continent really paved
the way for some people in the next generation,'' said Katherine
Wilkinson, a spokeswoman for the Royal Opera Company.
   In Brescia in 1926 she made her first appearance in
``Turandot.'' She did not create the role but Franco Alfano, the
composer who completed ``Turandot'' after Giacomo Puccini's death,
said he considered her the ideal singer for the part.
   From 1950 to 1959 she was a professor of voice at the University
of Oklahoma. She then returned to London and was a professor of
voice at the Royal Academy of Music until 1966. She continued to
coach singers until recent years.
   In 1982, she was honored at a 90th birthday celebration at the
Royal Opera House in Covent Garden, where a packed house gave her a
10-minute standing ovation. She was also made an honorary citizen
of Oklahoma in that year.
   She was made a Dame Commander of the Order of the British Empire
in 1962, and was awarded honorary doctorates of music by Manchester
and Oxford universities.
   Some of Miss Turner's performances are preserved on recordings
recently reissued on compact discs. Among them are highlights of
``Turandot'' at the Royal Opera House in 1928, conducted by Sir
John Barbirolli.
   Ronald Crichton, reviewing the recording for The Financial
Times, praised the ``glorious security and thrust'' of Miss
Turner's singing, while Raymond Monelle in The Independent said the
old recordings testified to her ``shattering power.''
   Miss Turner never married and left no immediate survivors.
   Funeral arrangements were to be announced Monday, Miss Morgan
said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900617-0024 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-90 1213EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-DeGaulle     06-17 0399</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-De Gaulle,0412</SECOND>
<HEAD>Neo-Gaullists Honor de Gaulle 50 Years After Resistance Call</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT QUIRICONI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   COLOMBEY-LES-DEUX-EGLISES, France (AP) _ Thousands of people
converged at the memorial to Charles de Gaulle on Sunday to honor
his historic appeal 50 years ago for armed resistance against Nazi
tyranny.
   Former Premier Jacques Chirac, leader of the neo-Gaullist
conservatives, was at the head of the 2{-mile march to the 150-foot
cross of Lorraine on a hillside of this town, where de Gaulle lived
and was buried.
   The march was among numerous ceremonies planned to honor the
50th anniversary of de Gaulle's June 18 appeal.
   ``The day is approaching, my general, when there will no longer
be any of your old companions among those who march toward your
tomb,'' said Maurice Schumann, former spokesman for the Free France
resistance movement de Gaulle headed during World War II.
   ``But that is of no importance. If your old guard has done its
time, your time has barely begun,'' he said at the red granite
memorial.
   On June 18, 1940, de Gaulle made a four-minute radio broadcast
from his London headquarters, appealing to French soldiers and
civilians to resist France's Nazi occupiers.
   ``Must we abandon all hope? Is our defeat final?'' asked the
general, who would later become president. ``No. ... The flame of
French resistance must not and shall not die.''
   On Monday, a Mass is to be celebrated in de Gaulle's honor at
Notre Dame Cathedral in Paris. President Francois Mitterrand is to
lay a bronze plaque inscribed with the June 18 ``appel'' at the
Arch of Triumph, where the tomb of the unknown soldier lies.
   Tens of thousands of people are expected at a sound-and-light
show Monday evening on the Seine River in Paris that will highlight
the great moments of World War II and the Liberation.
   Chirac's Rally for the Republic party, which considers itself
the direct political descendant of de Gaulle's movement, organized
Sunday's event, bringing in five trains and 500 busloads of
Gaullists.
   Batteries of loudspeakers played back other now-historic words
of de Gaulle, at the liberation of Paris or in France's far-flung
colonies. All the colonies were ultimately ceded to independence
under the presidency of de Gaulle, who died in 1970.
   ``The Gaullist language, a half-century after making history,
addresses itself now to those who practice it,'' said Schumann, the
only speaker. ``Submit? Never. Dream? Always.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900617-0025 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-90 1217EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-TongassFuture Bjt   06-17 0930</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Tongass Future, Bjt,0954</SECOND>
<HEAD>Debate Over Future of America's Largest National Forest Nears
Resolution</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Tobe cq in 5th graf</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By BRIAN S. AKRE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JUNEAU, Alaska (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The towering spruce, jagged mountains,
vast glaciers and lush islands of the Tongass National Forest are a
world away from Washington, D.C., where the forest's future is
being decided.
   After four years of debate, federal legislation affecting the
way America's largest national forest is managed is near a final
resolution.
   Last week, the Senate approved additional restrictions on
logging in the Tongass, sending the legislation to a conference
committee to work out differences with a more restrictive House
version.
   The end of the Tongass debate can't come soon enough for
residents of this remote rain forest along the Alaska Panhandle.
Many feel threatened by what they consider a foreign attack on
their way of life.
   ``Congress doesn't live here; they don't really understand the
lifestyle,'' said Tobe Miller, whose husband works for a logging
company in Wrangell. ``We've been painted to be butchers of the
forest, and we find that very offensive.''
   ``They have no comprehension of the size of the forest up
here,'' said Patricia Bickar, a retired teacher in Sitka. ``They
think that the whole thing is going to look like the Iowa wheat
fields when we get through.''
   The Tongass is big, almost beyond comprehension. At 16.7 million
acres, it is larger than New Jersey, Massachusetts, Rhode Island,
Delaware and Connecticut combined. But only 60,000 people call it
home, most within the towns of Juneau, Ketchikan and Sitka.
   Bordered by British Columbia on the east and the Pacific Ocean
on the west, the Tongass is a spectacular landscape of snowcapped
peaks, immense glaciers and ice fields, and thousands of islands
and reefs. Much of it is thickly carpeted with spruce, hemlock and
cedar.
   The forest stretches from the southern tip of the Panhandle 500
miles north to Yakutat Bay, but the combined shorelines of the
mainland and islands total nearly 11,000 miles.
   The forest's top products are wood and pulp, most of which are
sold to Japan. The Tongass is rich in other resources as well,
including fish, gold, silver and other minerals. Its diverse
ecosystem is home to thick populations of grizzly and black bear,
deer and bald eagles.
   Much of the ``forest'' is ice, rock or swampy marsh. Only 56
percent _ 9.4 million acres _ is actually forested. And of that,
only 3.1 million acres is outside protected wilderness areas and
suitable for logging and re-growth on a sustained basis, according
to U.S. Forest Service estimates.
   Only part of that acreage contains the old-growth, high-volume
timber prized by the industry and environmentalists alike. And it's
that land that all the debate is about in Congress.
   The old-growth includes stands of trees hundreds of years old,
which provide valuable habitat for wildlife and shade for prime
salmon-spawning streams.
   ``It is the last and best representation of major, intact stands
of old-growth timber in a temperate rain forest in the world,''
said Bart Koehler, executive director of the Southeast Alaska
Conservation Council.
   To the industry, however, the Tongass is an overripe forest. Don
Finney, general manager of the Alaska Loggers Association, notes
that much of the fiber content of Tongass logs is good only for
pulp production.
   By logging the old trees and carefully managing the second
growth, a more productive forest emerges to help meet the constant
worldwide demand for wood products, Finney says.
   ``Which is fine if all you care about is wood fiber,'' Koehler
responds. ``But there are a lot more values to the forest than
that.''
   In the middle of this debate is regional forester Michael Barton
of the Forest Service. What it boils down to, Barton says, is
values.
   ``There's a segment of the public, both here and down south,
that would like to see Alaska preserved or frozen in time,'' he
said. ``Then there are other folks who are trying to make a home
and a living up here, who want their kids to have jobs up here.
   ``The fundamental issue is should we develop the resources or
should we not?''
   Congress has been debating since the 1970s how to reconcile the
competing needs of the loggers, fishermen, Indians, tourists and
recreationalists who use the Tongass.
   In 1980, Congress set aside 5.4 million acres from logging. In
exchange, it guaranteed the region's two pulp mills a supply of
timber totaling 4.5 billion board feet a decade. It also promised
to appropriate at least $40 million a year for road building and
other assistance to make the timber available.
   The trade-offs to the industry came under fire in the mid-'80s
at the same time as environmentalists raised new concerns about the
biological uniqueness of old-growth forests.
   The Tongass legislation passed by the House last July would
establish 23 new wilderness areas totaling 1.8 million acres, on
which logging and other development would be banned. The bill also
would require 100-foot protective margins, or ``buffers,'' along
major salmon-spawning streams and their tributaries.
   The Senate version would add no wilderness areas, but would set
aside 673,000 acres from logging. It would provide buffers for
major streams, but not for tributaries.
   Both versions would end the annual $40 million appropriation and
the timber-sale guarantee. The House-passed bill also would cancel
two unusual long-term harvesting contracts with the pulp mills
dating back to the 1950s, while the Senate version would modify the
contracts.
   Environmentalists favor the House version, while industry
officials prefer the Senate plan. The White House has endorsed the
Senate bill.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900617-0026 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-90 1233EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a BC-FlashFloods 1stLd-Writethru a0610 06-17 0195</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Flash Floods, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0610,0194</SECOND>
<HEAD>16th Body Found In Eastern Ohio Flash Floods</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: UPDATES throughout with identity of victim, CORRECT that body
found late Saturday said Sunday; delete reference in lead to town
being hit by flood, which largely affected rural area near the
town. No pickup.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>SHADYSIDE, Ohio (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A 16th body was found and 23 people were
still missing from the flash floods that battered parts of eastern
Ohio, officials said Sunday.
   Chuck Vogt, Belmont County coroner's investigator, announced at
a news conference Sunday morning that a 16th victim was found, a
35-year-old woman pulled from the Ohio River 20 miles south of
Shadyside late Saturday.
   Earlier Saturday, the death toll rose to 15 with the discovery
of four victims.
   Officials at the scene revised the number of missing from 34 to
23, said Jim Boling of the Ohio Air National Guard. Previous
reports from Belmont County authorities had given the number as 51.
   Flash floods hit a largely rural area near Shadyside on Thursday
night.
   Vogt identified the latest victim to be found as Sue Humphrey,
35. Her sons Danny, 8, and David, 12, also died.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900617-0027 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-90 1247EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Germany-Terrorism     06-17 0602</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Germany-Terrorism,0622</SECOND>
<HEAD>Terrorist Suspect Lived in East Germany During U.S. Attack</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARK FRITZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>EAST BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A reputed West German terrorist was living in
East Germany with the approval of the secret police when she
allegedly helped bomb a U.S. air base, officials said Sunday.
   West German Federal Prosecutor Alexander von Stahl said he was
investigating whether there was evidence to charge former Communist
leader Erich Honecker and members of his ousted regime with
supporting leftist terrorism against West Germany.
   The disclosure came after the arrests of seven suspected members
of the radical left-wing Red Army Faction, which has been blamed
for dozens of killings, bombings and kidnappings in West Germany in
the past two decades.
   The suspects had been living in East Germany under false names
and some told police that they were in regular contact with the
feared secret police of East Germany's former Communist regime.
   Authorities late Friday captured Sigrid Sternebeck, 40, the
seventh alleged Red Army Faction member arrested in a 10-day span.
She was arrested at her apartment near the East German city of
Frankfurt an der Oder.
   Ms. Sternebeck told authorities that she moved to East Germany
in 1980 and kept in regular contact with the secret police, who
found her a place to live, according to a statement released Sunday
by East Germany's Interior Ministry.
   But she denied that she had any contact with the Red Army
Faction after moving to East Germany, the ministry said through the
government news agency ADN.
   West German authorities say she is linked to the August 1985
death of a U.S. Army soldier who was lured from a discotheque in
Wiesbaden, West Germany, and then shot to death.
   The soldier's identity card was then used to drive a car laden
with explosives onto the Rhein-Main U.S. Air Base near Frankfurt,
West Germany.
   Two Americans were killed in the blast and 20 people were
injured. The Red Army Faction later claimed responsibility for the
soldier's death and the bombing.
   Sunday's editions of the West German newspaper Welt am Sonntag
quoted Stahl as saying he would look into whether there is evidence
to begin preliminary proceedings against former East German
officials for allegedly supporting and harboring terrorists.
   Hans-Juergen Foerster, spokesman for the West German federal
prosecutor's office, confirmed the report and said there already
were ``initial suspicions'' but not enough evidence yet to pursue
extradition.
   Foerster said there was a ``priority'' inquiry involving
Honecker; former Minister for State Security Erich Mielke, the head
of the secret police; and former East German espionage chief Markus
Wolf.
   Honecker's regime was ousted in October by mass demonstrations.
He and Mielke are among several leaders undergoing medical
examinations to determine whether they are competent to face
prosecution in East Germany on charges of abuse of office and
corruption.
   Of the seven terrorist suspects arrested, one of them, Christine
Duemlein, 41, was freed because a West German warrant for her
arrest had expired.
   East German authorities, meanwhile, turned down West German
extradition requests for three other suspected terrorists: Werner
Lotze, Monika Helbing und Ekkehard von Seckendorff-Gudent.
   The Interior Ministry statement gave no reason for the action,
and Foerster said West German authorities would reapply.
   Lawyer Rolf Henrich, who is representing Seckerdorff-Gudent and
Ms. Helbing, questioned whether West German federal police could
legally operate in East Germany.
   Twenty-four core members of the Red Army Faction are still being
sought.
   Two West German bankers, a wealthy industrialist, a West Berlin
judge and a U.S. Army lieutenant colonel were among the people
killed in attacks for which the Red Army Faction claimed
responsibility.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900617-0028 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-90 1311EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Korea-US     06-17 0534</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Korea-US,0551</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.S. Official to Investigate Alleged Korean Anti-Import Campaign</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PAUL SHIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SEOUL, South Korea (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A U.S. official arrived Sunday to
investigate whether the South Korean government is behind a
controversial public campaign that has resulted in a sharp drop in
imports of consumer items.
   Wayne Berman, a counselor to U.S. Commerce Secretary Robert
Mosbacher, is to visit South Korean department stores to check the
accuracy of news reports that high-priced foreign consumer goods
have been removed from shelves and foreign brand-name boutiques
have been closed.
   Despite repeated denials by South Korean officials, U.S. and
West European diplomats in Seoul say they believe the government is
behind the anti-import campaign.
   ``We have evidence that Korean officials were involved. It is
unfortunate that such thing can give ammunition to trade
protectionists in the United States,'' said a U.S. Embassy
official, who spoke on condition of anonymity.
   The official said that although the volume of foreign consumer
goods affected is small, the anti-import campaign is serious
because ``it is visible and can affect the future attitude of
Korean consumers.''
   Imports of consumer goods account for less than 5 percent of
South Korea's total imports, which consist mainly of raw materials
needed to produce goods for export, according to government figures.
   The anti-import campaign began because of South Korea's
worsening trade balance. The country had a trade deficit of $3
billion in the first quarter of this year and may have a deficit in
1990 for the first time since 1985.
   The government and media blamed the worsening trade balance in
part on rising imports of ``luxury'' foreign consumer goods,
although the volume of such products is low.
   The controversy erupted after some foreign consumer goods such
as golf clubs, brand-name clothes and refrigerators suddenly
disappeared from the shelves of leading department stores in Seoul.
   At Hyundai Department Store, owned by the giant Hyundai group
which exported 220,000 cars last year, about a dozen boutiques for
such foreign brand names such as Burberrys, Bally, Lanvin and
Yves-Saint Laurent were closed.
   ``We did it for two reasons _ low profits and new social
obligation,'' said Hyundai's senior manager, Choi Chang-kon. ``We
also considered the mounting public sensitivity against a luxurious
way of life.''
   He denied that the action was ordered by the government but said
Hyundai was aware of the government's repeated calls for austerity
to cope with current economic difficulties.
   Lotte and other leading department stores in Seoul also said
they were planning to close boutiques or reduce the space for
foreign goods.
   One of the most seriously affected products is the U.S.-made
Mercury Sable car, whose sales plummeted with the anti-import
campaign.
   The Sable, made by Ford Motor Corp., became the best-selling
imported car in South Korea soon after it was first introduced last
October. In the last three months of the year 998 Sables were sold,
far more than all other imported cars combined.
   But sales dropped to 105 in May from 280 in February, 224 in
March and 159 in April. Kia Motors Co., the South Korean importer
of the car, said it has lowered its sales projection for this year
from the original 3,000 to 2,000.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900617-0029 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-90 1321EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Iran-Oil     06-17 0400</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Iran-Oil,0411</SECOND>
<HEAD>Iran's Production Capacity To Reach 4.5 Million Barrels A Day</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MONA ZIADE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NICOSIA, Cyprus (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Iran's oil minister said Sunday that his
country's oil production capacity will rise more than 25 percent to
4.5 million barrels a day in two years.
   The announcement in Tehran said Iran is spending hundreds of
milions of dollars to repair damage to the industry from the
1980-88 Iran-Iraq war. Iran's oil industry produces 90 percent of
its foreign currency revenues.
   The minister, Gholamreza Aqazadeh, stressed that Iran would
adhere to the production quota of 3.14 million barrels a day set by
the Organization of Petroleum Exporting Countries, even though its
capacity was larger than that.
   Aqazadeh told a news conference that Iran's output capacity in
March was 3.3 million barrels a day. He said then that Iran would
be able to pump 3.7 million barrels a day by the end of July, up to
4 million barrels a day next year and 4.5 million barrels in 1992.
   His comments were reported by Iran's official Islamic Republic
News Agency and monitored in Cyprus.
   Industry analysts say that much of Iran's infrastructure is
aging and estimate that modernization to increase its output could
cost as much as $8 billion.
   Iran and Iraq have criticized other OPEC members for violating
production quotas and driving down prices _ a practice that costs
their flagging economies millions of dollars a day.
   On Sunday, Aqazadeh blamed Saudi Arabia and Kuwait for
fluctuating oil prices.
   Worldwide prices have fallen below OPEC's benchmark price of $18
per barrel, and analysts have blamed the drop on oversupply. On
Friday, the price for West Texas Intermediate, the benchmark U.S.
crude oil, fell 51 cents to $16.62.
   The cartel's 13 member states agreed in May to cut their
collective output by 1.445 million barrels a day to restore the
benchmark price. They set the overall production ceiling at 22.086
million barrels a day.
   Aqazadeh said Iran will rebuild jetties and reservoirs on
southern Kharg island that were devastated by Iraqi air raids. He
said a petrochemical complex on the Persian Gulf coast will produce
1 million tons of liquefied petroleum gas ``in the coming months.''
   Aqazadeh also said Iran will drill 100 wells in the Caspian Sea,
which it shares with the Soviet Union. The oil reserves there were
``completely independent'' of the Soviet fields, he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900617-0030 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-90 1329EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-CIA-Future Bjt   06-17 0883</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-CIA-Future, Bjt,850</SECOND>
<HEAD>Will CIA Be Able To Adjust To Post-Cold War Era</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOAN MOWER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The CIA is refocusing its operations to look
at issues such as international economic competitiveness, terrorism
and narcotics, but some experts say the agency is moving too slowly
to keep up with changes in the post-Cold War world.
   The collapse of the Berlin Wall and the disintegration of the
Warsaw Pact have tempered the great U.S.-Soviet rivalry and
prompted the CIA to undertake a wide-ranging self-analysis to
determine what it should be doing and where it should be going.
   ``The transformation of our intelligence priorities is
beginning,'' Sen. David Boren, D-Okla., chairman of the Senate
Intelligence Committee, wrote in an opinion piece in Sunday's
editions of The New York Times.
   ``The congressional oversight committees are working with the
CIA to develop an innovative, long-term strategy that sheds cold
war priorities and focuses on language and cultural skills and
economic expertise,'' Boren wrote.
   At CIA's Langley, Va., complex in the bucolic woods overlooking
the Potomac River, a senior intelligence official said there was
``great debate'' under way about the agency's future.
   ``There is more intellectual excitement in this building than
there has been in years,'' the official said in an interview last
week. He asked not to be identified by name.
   At the same time, the official said the CIA was navigating in
``choppy seas'' that make predicting a difficult job, particularly
when foreigners themselves are unclear about their future. For
instance, he said no one had a crystal ball to see that Romania and
Bulgaria would chose communist governments in their elections.
   The agency, meantime, is eyeing nervously budget cuts being made
by Congress in the Defense Department, where most of the money for
intelligence is put, the official said.
   The intelligence budget, which includes money for the CIA's
sister agencies such as the Defense Intelligence Agency and the
National Security Agency, was estimated to be about $28 billion in
fiscal year 1990. The intelligence agencies want to avoid any
proportional hit when defense is pared.
   ``The intelligence community will be scrutinized,'' said Rep.
David McCurdy, D-Okla., chairman of the House intelligence
subcommittee on oversight and evaluation. ``I see cuts in those
areas that primarily support military functions.''
   Covert action _ the area that has brought the agency its
greatest notoriety _ comprises only about 3 percent of the CIA's
budget. The bulk of the agency's work involves analyzing voluminous
data from various sources.
   Practicing their own form of glasnost, CIA officials and some
members of Congress these days speak forthrightly about unique
opportunities in 1990 for re-evaluating operations and goals, as
well as the daunting challenges.
   But they insist intelligence needs will not diminish; they'll
simply be different.
   ``The era of the cloak and dagger may be over, but the cloaks
are likely to multiply and become even more pervasive in their
effort to procure military, industrial and commercial secrets,''
said Sen. William Cohen of Maine, the ranking Republican on the
Senate intelligence panel.
   ``It is time to face new enemies _ drugs, terrorism, poverty,
brush fire wars and pollution of our planet,'' he said.
   And while some spies will come in from the cold, ``many more
will bask and flourish,'' Cohen said.
   Boren agrees. The ``growth area'' is the industrial espionage
that is carried out by foreign governments against private U.S.
companies.
   ``More and more, the aim of espionage is to steal private
commercial secrets for the sake of national economic purpose,''
Boren told the National Press Club recently.
   ``We're going to have to know about foreign governments'
intentions for oil production levels, exchange rates and trade
policies,'' he said. ``We're going to have to protect our own
commercial enterprises against the theft of commercial secrets.''
   David Whipple, executive director of the Association of Former
Intelligence Officers, predicted the intelligence agencies are
``looking forward to a very prosperous future.''
   But some observers are concerned that the CIA, a cumbersome
bureaucracy, may not be up to the task of retooling its operations.
   ``I think they understand the pressure and the demands for
re-examination and a development of the new strategic plan, but I
think they are a long way from accomplishing it,'' McCurdy said.
``I have not been satisfied with the pace of change,'' he said.
   There desperately ``needs to be a new look at the whole thing,''
he added.
   McCurdy said he is concerned that the CIA has too few
independent thinkers, linguists, women and minorities and
``creative geniuses.''
   He complained that the new crop of CIA employees ``all look like
Penn State linebackers.'' He said such conformity is
counterproductive to understanding a changing world full of people
from different races and backgrounds.
   One example might be the restless nationalities in the Soviet
Union. Jeffrey Richelson, author of a recent book, ``America's
Secret Eyes in Space,'' said it frequently takes years to develop a
reporting network that will allow the CIA to know the ins and outs
of, say, politics in Azerbaijan.
   But the agency is optimistic about the future. And CIA Director
William Webster says the man who really counts _ President Bush, a
former CIA director himself, has no gripes.
   ``The president has mentioned that he is pleased with the
product he is getting,'' Webster said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900617-0031 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-90 1422EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-PBS-Campaigns     06-17 0346</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-PBS-Campaigns,320</SECOND>
<HEAD>PBS Considering Free Air Time for 1992 Presidential Candidates</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Public Broadcasting Service is looking at
ways to provide 1992 presidential candidates and the major
political parties free air time beyond the normal news coverage to
present their views, PBS President Bruce Christensen said Sunday.
   ``What we're looking for is the way to increase the political
dialogue,'' Christensen said in a telephone interview from Dallas,
where PBS' board of directors is meeting this week.
   Christensen said just what approaches will be used ``need to be
worked out over the next few months.'' But he said the
possibilities include several ideas recommended Friday to top PBS
officials by the John and Mary Markle Foundation of New York.
   The foundation, which will formally present a feasibility study
to the PBS board on Tuesday, has offered to contribute $5 million
of the estimated $15 million to $20 million that the project would
cost.
   Developed by Alvin H. Perlmutter, an independent television
producer, the Markle study recommends that PBS offer free air time
in blocks ranging from 2{ minutes to 15 minutes to the presidential
candidates and-or the political parties.
   The Markle plan was outlined in Sunday editions of The
Washington Post and The New York Times.
   Perlmutter, who has worked for PBS and NBC, recommended creating
a ``Voters Channel'' production company to prepare expanded
political programing for PBS stations that also would include
``character and competence'' profiles of presidential candidates
and an exploration of their debates.
   Regularly scheduled one-hour programs would be broadcast during
September and October 1992, with half-hour programs airing daily
the week before the November general election.
   The report also recommended that the programs include segments
examining political ads and party activities in the campaign and
the media's coverage of it. And it called for a segment in which
voters could voice their views on the candidates and the issues.
   ``Al made a number of suggestions we'll consider,'' Christensen
said, predicting most of the 337 public TV channels in the PBS
system ``will sign on to what we are doing.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900617-0032 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-90 1428EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-MotherCharged Bjt   06-17 0813</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mother Charged, Bjt,0837</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mother Charged in What Had Been Called Suicide</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto BX2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LESLIE DREYFOUS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BEVERLY, Mass. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Why? That's what Marcia Biancardi's
friends wanted to know long after word of the popular cheerleader's
apparent suicide came over Beverly High School's public address
system on Valentine's Day.
   It was a question that lingered until last week, when the
4-month-old case took a rare twist. Marcia's mother was charged
with taking a shotgun and shooting the 16-year-old as she slept.
   ``All along, we just wanted the facts,'' said sophomore Eric
Wade, who was a year behind Marcia. ``None of us believed it was a
suicide.''
   Now the counselors who initially helped students confront
suicide are trying to help them accept what authorities say was a
homicide.
   The mother, Susan Biancardi, is charged with first-degree murder
and could face life in prison if convicted. Her attorney, Robert F.
Peck Jr., says Mrs. Biancardi was linked to her daughter's death
through ``innuendo, hearsay and suggestion.'' He entered an
innocent plea for her Tuesday.
   He also indicated Tuesday that he did not think his client was
mentally ill and described her as an ``active, loving parent and
wife,'' the Salem Evening News reported.
   ``For some kids there's fear and for some there's anger,'' said
Lauren Terry, who counsels students at Beverly High School, about
15 miles north of Boston. ``For a lot of them, it has finally put a
closure on a long, long spring.''
   When Mrs. Biancardi was arrested last week following an inquest
into her daughter's death Feb. 14, it fell into line with what many
of Marcia's friends had suspected from the start.
   ``Even that first day it was very clear that there were
questions surrounding the death,'' said Kimberly Wilkins, who
directs the community's Project RAP crisis response center.
   ``And that made it really tough for the kids to start going
through the process of grieving.''
   Classmates couldn't make it add up. They didn't understand why a
well-loved girl with a passion for singing, sports and people would
take her own life. Had they missed some hint of suicidal despair?
   There also were questions about how Marcia manipulated the
shotgun to shoot herself in the abdomen, and why, if she pulled the
trigger, there was no trace of gunpowder on her hands.
   ``It's much easier to understand that someone (else) shot a gun.
With suicide, we don't understand why,'' said Terry, whose caseload
has tripled since Marcia died.
   Marcia's father, a bricklayer, was not at home at the time of
the shooting. But her 14-year-old sister was in the house.
Witnesses at the Salem District Court inquest included scores of
the girl's friends and relatives, many of whom were familiar with
the sometimes stormy relationship she had with her parents.
   Stephen O'Connell, spokesman for the Essex County district
attorney, and police said they had ruled out suicide, but declined
to comment on the inquest or any specific problems in the family or
between the mother and daughter.
   ``Yes, we knew her life was not perfect,'' the Rev. Donald
Remick of the Second Congregational Church had said at Marcia's
funeral. ``Though none but God knows all her pain, we do know that
in the midst of the suffering and struggle, a choice was made.''
   The choice, authorities now say, was not Marcia's.
   Mrs. Biancardi was placed under 20 days' psychiatric observation
in a state mental hospital. According to James Fox of Northeastern
University's national crime analysis program, only two or three
times a year, on average, is a mother suspected of shooting a
teen-age daughter in the United States.
   Wilkins said the filing of charges is ``very scary'' for teens
in the area.
   ``Adolescence is typically a time when kids test their parents
and then you have a case ... that raises the possibility of a
murderous potential in all parents,'' said Wilkins.
   In the days after Marcia died, her classmates began pinning
notes, stuffed animals and flowers on her locker.
   School officials, following the advice of experts, quietly
removed the mementos they thought could romanticize or glorify what
at the time appeared to be a suicide.
   ``Now at least it's not something _ a question _ we have to
carry around with us,'' said Richard Cooper, a graduating senior.
``But it's not something we can forget, the loss of our friend.''
   Maybe, counselors said, now is the time to remember.
   Gestures such as the memorial hockey game that administrators
vetoed in the winter seem more appropriate now. Students are
talking about dedicating next year's yearbook and prom to Marcia,
who would have graduated in 1991.
   ``The kids will need a catharsis now, some constructive way to
deal with their grief,'' said Dr. Pamela Cantor, a suicide expert
affiliated with the Harvard Medical School. ``They need to talk
about the fact that a mother is under arrest.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900617-0033 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-90 1437EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People     06-17 0781</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People,0814</SECOND>
<HEAD>People in the News</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY44</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PHILADELPHIA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Madonna, who canceled the first of three
engagements here because of a sore throat, performed the second
show for 14,000 stomping, screaming fans.
   Deafening cheers greeted the singer Saturday as she emerged from
a cloud of smoke on the elaborate set of her ``Blond Ambition''
tour.
   As late as early Saturday afternoon, local promoters were still
awaiting word from the singer's doctor on whether the pop star
would make the Saturday and Sunday night concerts.
   The phone at Electric Factory Concerts rang off the hook
Saturday morning, spokeswoman Julie Vitello said.
   ``It's been murder,'' she said. ``Everyone's so excited about
her appearance and people are just frantic. They want to see her.''
   The Friday night concert was the third canceled in the last
three weeks by the singer, who started the tour six weeks ago. The
throat problem was blamed on a viral infection.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>LEXINGTON, Ky. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Richard Dysart, who plays a senior partner
on NBC's ``L.A. Law'' television series, encouraged real-life
Kentucky lawyers to do more volunteer legal work.
   Dysart, who plays Leland McKenzie on the series, was the keynote
speaker Friday at a banquet for the Kentucky Bar Association.
   Dysart also played McKenzie in a 30-second public service
announcement taped Friday for the KBA. Dysart did the tape free in
hopes lawyers will follow suit and perform more volunteer legal
work.
   ``I say if it gets one Kentucky lawyer to go out to a senior
citizens center and show someone how to fill out a government
medical form, it's worth the effort,'' Dysart said.
   Earlier in the week, American Bar Association President L.
Stanley Chauvin told members at the conference that ``L.A. Law''
presented a distorted view of how the U.S. legal system actually
works.
   Dysart agreed Friday night.
   ``We are an unusual law firm with an unusual specialty,'' he
said. ``We specialize in everything. And for a firm with seven
partners and three associates, we really do get around.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>CHATTANOOGA, Tenn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Bill Cosby, television's well-known
dad, may be a ghost soon, but he was quite visible to tens of
thousands of visitors at the Riverbend Festival on Father's Day
weekend.
   Cosby, wearing a Dad T-shirt saying ``Ghost Dad'' to promote an
upcoming film by that name, kept many of the 100,000 estimated
partygoers spellbound during a 75-minute monologue Friday night,
festival organizers said.
   Part of his routine included asking the audience to ponder the
philosophical question of why humans continue to care for their
young when animals get rid of them after six months.
   The star of ``The Cosby Show'' asked for only one prop _ a chair
with no arms to be placed center stage, said Riverbend chief Bruce
Storey.
   The festival runs through June 24.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>LAKE BUENA VISTA, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Kid is 11 years old, 4{ feet
tall and weighs 57 pounds. But Charlie Korsmo came close to
stealing the show from his elders in the new ``Dick Tracy'' movie.
   ``Wasn't he great!'' exclaimed the Kid's co-star and director,
Warren Beatty, last week after the film had its premiere here.
   Charlie's first movie role was as Jessica Lange's son in ``Men
Don't Leave.'' Initially, he wasn't interested in the role offered
by Beatty in the film based on the square-jawed comic strip
character.
   But Beatty insisted, and the sixth-grader from Minneapolis
finally agreed, partly because ``I hate to go to school.''
   Now, Charlie considers himself ``one lucky kid.''
   ``Everybody says the movie will be a hit, so it will probably
help my career,'' says the slightly built youngster who professes
more interest in becoming a philosopher than a full-time actor when
he grows up.
   ``I would sit around and think a lot _ like inventions and
theories and stuff like that''_ and then give advice to others, he
says of his real goal in life.
   School, he says, is ``boring, takes a lot of time.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>SPICEWOOD, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A slice of the West will become the
South _ at least for a time _ for an upcoming Vanessa Redgrave
movie.
   The little town northwest of Austin is being transformed in a
small Southern town in the 1930s for filming of the movie ``Ballad
of Sad Cafe.'' Much of the town is owned by singer Willie Nelson.
   Shooting is set to begin June 25 on the film, starring Redgrave
and directed by Simon Callow, an actor who played Salieri in the
London stage version of ``Amadeus.''
   The film company has put out a call trying to locate a full
suite of Victorian furniture to lend authenticity to the film,
according to Texas Film Commission officials.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900617-0034 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-90 1440EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Liberia-Talks     06-17 0270</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Liberia-Talks,0278</SECOND>
<HEAD>Government-Controlled Paper Urges Doe Resignation</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Liberia, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>FREETOWN, Sierra Leone (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Sierra Leone's ruling party on
Sunday suggested that Liberian President Samuel K. Doe quit and
leave neighboring Liberia to end the nation's 5{-month-old civil
war.
   The Liberian government and rebels fighting for its overthrow
agreed to a cease-fire Saturday in peace talks in Sierra Leone. But
Doe has steadfastly refused to resign, the rebel's key demand.
   The United States, in the past a supporter of Doe's rule, has
also urged him to step down and leave the country.
   More than 1,000 people have died in the civil war. Doe's troops
largely have been unable to stop the rebels' advance but did drive
them from the country's international airport 10 days ago.
   The Liberian government and the rebels called for the cease-fire
pending further negotiations. Saturday was the fifth day of peace
talks in the U.S. Embassy in Freetown. In a statement issued after
the meeting, the two sides agreed to resume talks next Monday.
   Conference sources, including U.S. diplomats, have said little
progress has been made at resolving the key rebel demand that Doe
resign and leave Liberia.
   In an editorial published Sunday, We Yone, the newspaper of
Sierra Leone's All People's Congress, said, ``How much is Doe
prepared to give?''
   ``When all is said and done, the solution rests with one man,
and the challenge is that of statesmanship,'' it said.
   Journalists traveling with the rebels say the rebels have had
problems controlling their troops since the death of their
U.S.-trained military commander, Elmer Johnson, who was killed in
fighting two weeks ago.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900617-0035 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-90 1447EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BerniceKing     06-17 0513</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bernice King,0527</SECOND>
<HEAD>King's Youngest Daughter Begins Career As Minister, Lawyer</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto AX1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SONYA ROSS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ATLANTA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   When the world last looked, Bernice Albertine
King was a fidgety 5-year-old in white ribbons, piled sorrowfully
in her mother's lap at her father's 1968 funeral.
   Now, the baby daughter of the Rev. Martin Luther King Jr. is a
serene young woman, newly ordained as a Baptist minister and holder
of doctor of law and master of divinity degrees from Emory
University.
   Ms. King, 27, is the only one of the slain civil rights leader's
four children to follow her father's career and join the clergy.
She has a long-range goal of starting a prison ministry that also
would provide inmates with some legal counseling.
   The broader goal of continuing the sweeping social change begun
by her father is not on her agenda, Ms. King explains. But she
understands why people would take her entry into the ministry as a
sign that she intends to go in that direction.
   ``That's part of being who I am,'' she explains. ``I've learned
to live with that.
   ``My father was more concerned with sociology, the sociological
reasons for behavior,'' she says. ``I am more interested in the
psychological. I like to analyze things, to look at how things
happened to figure out why they happened.''
   Ms. King describes herself as an ambitious but private person.
She carries herself with an air so coolly serious that friends
often tell her she needs to lighten up.
   Ms. King said she might begin to do that _ after a summer of
reading the Bible, studying for bar exams and interviewing for jobs
with Atlanta-area law firms.
   She was ordained and received both her law and divinity degrees
all on the same day last month.
   Part of her serious nature, Ms. King said, stems from soul
searching in her early adulthood, when she ``spent a lot of time
running'' from the religious calling she felt at age 17.
   She thought briefly about a career as a television reporter. She
participated in some anti-apartheid protests, went to jail after
one of them. She also attended Democratic conventions, represented
her church at Baptist assemblies and spoke before the United
Nations.
   But by the time Ms. King earned a bachelor's degree in
psychology from Spelman College, she had a clearer idea of what she
wanted to do in life.
   She then enrolled at Emory and, in 1988, gave a trial sermon
that whipped into a weeping frenzy the congregation at Ebenezer,
the Baptist church presided over by both her father and grandfather.
   At her ordination, the Rev. Joseph L. Roberts, Ebenezer's pastor
and one of Ms. King's instructors at Emory, said she has ``not only
the oratorical gifts of her father but the sensitivity of her
father.''
   Ms. King said she considered taking broadcasting courses to
sharpen that powerful speaking ability.
   ``I always felt I needed to work on the way I choose words. I
still have difficulty with that,'' she said. ``And I've always
admired the way (broadcasters) speak.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900617-0036 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-90 1457EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-AIDS-Fauci     06-17 0471</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-AIDS-Fauci,440</SECOND>
<HEAD>AIDS Vaccine Available by End of Decade, Government Expert Says</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARCY GORDON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A vaccine to combat the AIDS virus likely will
be available for widespread use by the end of the decade, a
government AIDS expert said Sunday.
   The Bush administration has come under fire from AIDS activists
and congressional critics for not spending enough money on AIDS
research and moving too slowly in approving new drugs to fight the
disease.
   The federal government is spending $1.16 billion in the current
fiscal year on AIDS research and the administration has recommended
an increase to $1.245 billion in fiscal 1991.
   But Dr. Anthony Fauci, director of AIDS research at the National
Institutes of Health, said Sunday that ``the decade of the '90s
will see some important advances that will have a positive impact
on HIV-infected individuals.''
   ``Over the next several years, you'll see a real acceleration of
vaccine development, and hopefully by the end of the 1990s there
will be a vaccine that is available for widespread use,'' Fauci
said.
   An estimated 1 million Americans are believed to be infected by
HIV, or human immunodeficiency virus, which can develop into the
AIDS disease.
   Fauci appeared on the ABC-TV program ``This Week With David
Brinkley'' in advance of the sixth international AIDS conference,
which starts Wednesday in San Francisco.
   The conference, billed as the largest gathering to date of HIV
scientists, health care workers and policy-makers, will run through
June 24.
   The meeting will be boycotted, however, by 80 organizations
because of U.S. immigration policy that bars entry to people
infected with the HIV virus. The Immigration and Naturalization
Service in April relaxed the ban by allowing 10-day visas for
conference participants, but some groups feel that is not
sufficient.
   A pre-conference demonstration is planned Tuesday outside the
immigration office in San Francisco's financial district.
   While conceding that a cure for AIDS hasn't been found, Fauci
said ``at least a couple of drugs'' have been shown effective in
delaying the full symptoms of the disease in patients at the
earlier stages.
   Dr. Luc Montagnier, an AIDS researcher at France's Pasteur
Institute who also appeared on the Brinkley show, said it will take
at least four to five years to develop an effective vaccine.
   Montagnier said government funding for AIDS research in the
United States has been ``enormous'' in the past two years or so
compared with Europe.
   Fauci said ``we're already starting to see positive spinoffs''
from AIDS research, such as information that can be used in work on
cancer and studies of the immune system.
   The AIDS conference, which coincides with the annual Gay Pride
Week, is sponsored by the World Health Organization, the University
of California at San Francisco, the American Foundation for AIDS
Research and the city-county of San Francisco.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900617-0037 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-90 1523EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Germany-Unification 3rdLd-Writethru a0638-40-42 06-17
0779</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Germany-Unification, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0638-40-42,0802</SECOND>
<HEAD>Parliament Raises Issue of Immediate Unity But Postpones Vote</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: COMBINES urgent series, UPDATES with quotes, ADDS Kohl's
purpose at meeting. No pickup.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By MARK FRITZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>EAST BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Flirting with history on an emotional
anniversary, East Germany's Parliament came dramatically close
Sunday to dissolving the country and uniting with West Germany.
   But the stunning move turned out to be more a symbolic gesture
and acknowledgment that unification was imminent and inevitable.
   The country's first freely elected Parliament voted
overwhelmingly to discuss the final decision of German unification,
but then put off the historic decision that would automatically
result in immediate unification.
   Lawmakers met in a rare Sunday session to debate unification and
commemorate the 37th anniversary of a failed attempt by East German
workers to overthrow Soviet rule.
   With Chancellor Helmut Kohl and other top West German officials
in the hall to mark the anniversary, lawmakers from the German
Social Union proposed the final question of German unification be
placed on the agenda.
   ``The Parliament would like to decide: Resolve to join the
German Democratic Republic ... to the Federal Republic of Germany
on this very day,'' lawmaker Hans-Guenther Schwarz of the German
Social Union told the chamber.
   Lawmakers voted 267-92, with seven abstentions, to take up the
issue.
   But when debate opened, East German Prime Minister Lothar de
Maiziere took the microphone and said he would not support the
measure because of the many questions that need to be addresed
before the two Germanys are united.
   De Maiziere also referred to the June 17, 1953, uprising, in
which an estimated 300 people were killed, as one of the earliest
attempts to unify a nation cut in two by World War II.
   He portrayed the Parliament's action more as a message to the
world as the way German unity will take place.
   ``It appears therefore on this day good and right, to clearly
acknowledge German unity and to describe the way that this will be
done,'' he said in remarks that were greeted with a standing
ovation.
   Lawmakers then voted by an overwhelming show of hands to
postpone the vote on unification, which is likely to come in the
months ahead.
   The two German states are to merge their economies July 2, when
the West German mark becomes the currency of East Germany.
   Banks stayed open through the weekend and hundreds stood in
lines, opening accounts and filling out forms so their money can be
changed to West German marks.
   But the two nations still must find ways to merge their vastly
different legal, economic and social systems, and resolve the key
question of the strategic future of a united Germany.
   The superpowers are to hold talks in East Berlin on Thursday on
the worldwide implications of German unity. The United States
insists that it be a part of NATO, while the Soviet Union is
staunchly opposed.
   East Germany also is expected to face high unemployment as it
moves to a free market and its aging enterprises are forced to
compete.
   The question that lawmakers voted to put on the agenda for
discussion was whether to support Article 23 of the West German
constitution, a method under which the entire country could
dissolve itself and become a part of West Germany.
   The article was written after World War II to allow individual
sections of disputed German territory to decide whether to become a
part of postwar West Germany.
   Kohl and de Maiziere both have supported the article as the
constitutional tool under which East Germany could most quickly
unite with the West.
   Another method favored by other officials would involve both
countries dissolving themselves and writing a new constitution to
form a completely new nation, which would take considerably longer.
   However, when unification comes, it will likely occur when East
German lawmakers vote in favor of Article 23.
   De Maiziere's Christian Democratic Union finished an
overwhelming first in East Germany's first free elections on March
18 by promising to support Article 23.
   But an actual vote on it was not expected for months after the
economic union of the two nations takes place on July 2.
   The original purpose of Sunday's parliamentary session was to
debate changes in the East German constitution that would make it
easier for the two nations to merge their vastly different social
structures.
   However, a broad-based group of left-leaning lawmakers proposed
that East Germany merely adopt the laws of West Germany by annexing
itself to West Germany via Article 23.
   The lawmakers dropped the proposal after consultations with
their parties, but the German Social Union then came in with its
own, similar proposal.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900617-0038 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-90 1528EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Mayors Bjt   06-17 0654</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mayors, Bjt,0672</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mayors Panel Seeks Gramm-Rudman Repeal; Cut In Payroll Tax</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN KING</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CHICAGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   America's mayors Sunday gave initial approval to
a broad, costly domestic agenda that asks Congress to repeal the
Gramm-Rudman deficit-reduction law and cut Social Security taxes
for nearly 120 million workers.
   The more than 70 resolutions approved by the U.S. Conference of
Mayors key policy committee contain repeated pleas for a
multibillion-dollar infusion of federal funds for anti-drug,
housing, education and anti-poverty programs.
   Also endorsed was a resolution asking Washington to give cities
broad powers to regulate billboards alongside federal roads. But
the panel balked at a proposal that would have put the mayors on
record as opposing alcohol and tobacco advertising.
   The resolutions endorsed Sunday will go before the full
conference of more than 200 mayors Wednesday. But the panel's
decisions are rarely changed significantly in those votes, which
set the lobbying agenda for the organization's Washington staff.
   The mayors, who have spent much of the first three days of their
six-day annual meeting criticizing the federal government for
slashing aid to cities, said repealing Gramm-Rudman would force
lawmakers to confront the deficit.
   ``Too many of our members of Congress are using this as a crutch
to hide some of the true problems of our economy,'' said Mayor Paul
Soglin of Madison, Wis. ``A series of budget gimmicks have been
implemented.''
   Under Gramm-Rudman, automatic spending cuts take effect if
Congress and the White House do not meet specified deficit
reduction targets. The mayors complained that city-level services
are the first to feel the automatic cuts.
   ``It has the effect of putting cities and towns, urban programs,
first on the chopping block,'' said Mayor John K. Bullard of New
Bedford, Mass.
   Conference staff said the mayors group _ if the full conference
endorses the proposal as expected _ would be the first organization
of elected officials to call for repeal of Gramm-Rudman. Several
mayors said the organization likely will face criticism for its
stance because Gramm-Rudman is the only mandatory deficit-reduction
mechanism.
   ``The mayors across this nation have got to say this is a
charade,'' said Mayor Lee Robinson of Macon, Ga. ``We've got to say
enough is enough.''
   In calling for the Social Security payroll tax to be cut from
7.65 percent to 6.71 percent, the mayors panel also called on
Congress to remove the cap on outside earnings of Social Security
recipients and stop using the balance in the Social Security trust
fund to mask the true size of the federal deficit.
   Also included in one tax-related resolution approved Sunday was
a statement opposing a capital gains tax cut favored by President
Bush.
   Throughout this year's meeting, big-city mayors have been urging
their colleagues to be more militant in their lobbying of
Washington and to lay claim to a good chunk of expected defense
savings by warning that urban tensions are reaching a boiling point
because of cash-poor anti-poverty programs.
   The first resolution dealing with billboards passed with little
discussion.
   It called on Congress to transfer to the states the power to
regulate and remove billboards alongside federal highways.
   But the proposal to put the mayors on the record in favor of a
ban on alcohol and drug advertising was derailed a day after it was
endorsed by a lower-level committee as part of a minority-health
initiative.
   Support for the measure eroded Sunday after the measure was
amended to oppose all alcohol and tobacco ads. It intially had
sought a ban only on outdoor ads.
   Also scuttled Sunday was a bid by some mayors to call for a
constitutional amendment that cities receive a ``fair and fixed''
percentage of federal revenues if Congress refuses to pass a law
mandating the revenue sharing.
   That idea had sparked a split Satuday between conference
committees on human development and urban economic policy, with the
latter group prevailing in getting the amendment language deleted.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900617-0039 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-90 1540EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brite-MarriageRenewals     06-17 0150</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brite-Marriage Renewals,0155</SECOND>
<HEAD>30 Couples Renew `I Do's' En Masse</HEAD>
<DATELINE>POLAND SPRINGS, Maine (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Thirty couples who have been
married from seven months to 44 years said ``I do'' again as they
gathered for a ``Lovers Weekend'' at a resort in this western Maine
town.
   The couples from all over New England repeated their vows at a
non-denominational, 10-minute service arranged by the Poland
Springs Inn.
   For Frank and Dottie Stewart of Beverly, Mass., it was their
fourth marriage renewal since their first wedding in 1943 in
Virginia. ``We're lovers,'' they said.
   The ceremony Saturday came on the 33rd anniversary of Catherine
and Edward Dufresne's wedding in Haverhill, Mass.
   ``We're still in love,'' he said. Said Mrs. Dufresne, ``We just
couldn't pass up this opportunity.''
   Bill Kazakis and his wife, Joan, of Manchester, N.H., said the
Maine ceremony ``was a chance to say `I don't.'''
   But they didn't.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900617-0040 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-90 1551EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Germany-Kohl     06-17 0481</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Germany-Kohl,0498</SECOND>
<HEAD>Kohl Has Been Pressing for Unity, But Motion Came As Apparent
Surprise</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Germany-Unification, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TERRENCE PETTY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BONN, West Germany (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Chancellor Helmut Kohl has been
pushing harder than anyone for German unity, but even his
government seemed stunned Sunday by East German debate on an
immediate merger with West Germany.
   ``This has caught everyone by surprise. No one expected this,''
said a West German government spokesman, speaking on condition of
anonymity.
   The East German Parliament overwhelmingly voted to take up the
merger issue, but then decided to postpone a final vote.
   Kohl, who attended the remarkable session to commemorate the
37th anniversary of a failed East German uprising against Communist
rule, has been the chief architect of the German unity process.
   He announced a 10-point program in November that laid the
foundations for unity and he orchestrated the coming July 2
economic merger. More recently, he has been pushing for the
election of a single German government as early as December.
   But not even Kohl had predicted East Germany might consider
annexing itself to his country so soon.
   Kohl has clearly stated he wants formal unity to occur this
year. However, he has cautiously avoided making it look like he is
trying make decisions for the East German government.
   During the past two weeks, every time Kohl has been asked when
all-German elections might occur, he has said that's also a
question the East German government must decide.
   Last week, he was pointing out that his government has not even
begun formal talks with East Berlin about the possibility of
joining the two nations under Article 23 of the West German
constitution.
   ``Most certainly we will have to talk about these questions _
what arises from Article 23 and about an election date,'' Kohl said
Tuesday.
   If the East German parliament had approved Article 23, the
country would have automatically joined West Germany.
   Kohl's government has been examining two possible models for
unification: all-German elections as early as December, with a
simultaneous merger of the two countries; or annexation of East
Germany under Article 23 with all-German elections at some later
date.
   East Germany has not expressed an official view about either of
these options, and Kohl's government apparently has not decided
which one it favors.
   Immediate unity could also anger the Soviet Union, which has
380,000 troops on East German soil and does not want to pull them
back until it can build adequate housing and find jobs for the
soldiers.
   Also, Moscow objects to a Western proposal that a united Germany
be a member of NATO.
   A hasty annexation of East Germany while the military allegiance
question is still in dispute would probably create further Soviet
concerns.
   Kohl has told the Soviets many times he wants domestic as well
as global complications of unification cleared up as soon as
possible.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900617-0041 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-90 1559EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Germany-Annexation     06-17 0246</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Germany-Annexation,0252</SECOND>
<HEAD>Text of Constitutional Article to Merge German States</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Germany-Unification, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BONN, West Germany (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The constitutional article at the core
of East Germany's stunning consideration Sunday to immediately join
West Germany has existed since the founding of separate German
states in 1949.
   Article 23 was always viewed as a means toward eventual
reunification of the German people, although that seemed only a
remote possibility more than 40 years ago.
   In East Berlin on Sunday, the East German parliament
overwhelmingly voted to consider the provision but then put off a
vote.
   Under the article, a region must simply vote to dissolve and
join West Germany to become part of the country, with West
Germany's constitution and laws prevailing.
   Article 23 was written _ with the approval of the three
victorious World War II western Allies, the United States, Britain
and France _ to allow individual sections of disputed German
territory to decide whether to become a part of postwar West
Germany.
   East German Prime Minister Lothar De Maiziere's Christian
Democratic Union finished an overwhelming first in East Germany's
first free elections in March by promising to support Article 23.
   As translated into English, Article 23 reads:
   ``This Basic Law (Constitution) applies first of all in the
regions of the states of Bavaria, Bremen, greater Berlin, Hamburg,
Hessen, Lower Saxony, North Rhein Westphalia, Rheinland Palatinate,
Schleswig Holstein, Wuerttemberg-Baden and
Wuerttemberg-Hohenzollern. In other parts of Germany it is to
become effective after their accession.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900617-0042 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-90 1609EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Lottery-ChildSupport     06-17 0350</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lottery-Child Support,0361</SECOND>
<HEAD>State Law Takes Lottery Winnings for Child Support Payments</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PIERRE, S.D. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   One $5,000 winner in the state lottery lost
the entire prize for being behind in child support payments, and
two others lost part of their winnings, state officials say.
   Since 1987, a state law passed when the lottery was created has
cost three winners nearly $7,000, lottery officials said last week.
   Deb Mortenson, public information director for the state Lottery
Commission, said last week that she can't release the names of the
winners who were penalized, but she did give some details.
   In addition to the $5,000 winner who lost it all, a $7,000
winner lost $460 and a $4,000 winner lost $721. The state
Department of Social Services passed the money on to the families.
   The lottery, which features scratch-off tickets, began in
September 1987. Generally speaking, the top prize in the
scratch-off game is $10,000 or less.
   A provision in state law approved with the lottery authorization
allows the deductions. It applies only to winners of $100 or more
who have court judgments against them.
   The lottery automatically checks records in the Social Services
department to compare the names of big prize winners against a list
of names and Social Security numbers. People who were overpaid for
food stamps or Aid to Dependent Children programs are on the list,
too, said Social Services Secretary Jim Ellenbecker.
   ``The only three we've had so far were for delinquent child
support,'' Mortenson said. ``And the only reason people are on that
computer file is that they have a court order against them.''
   Other states collect those debts through their state income tax
programs, Ellenbecker said. Since South Dakota doesn't have a state
income tax, the lottery is just another way of getting that money.
   ``When the lottery legislation was passed, somebody had the
foresight to tack that on,'' Ellenbecker said.
   The amount garnished so far, however, is small compared with the
$40 million in delinquent support payments Ellenbecker said the
state is trying to collect. Some of that goes back a number of
years.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900617-0043 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-90 1635EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--Philippines-Fighting     06-17 0116</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Philippines-Fighting,0119</SECOND>
<HEAD>Communist Guerrillas Kill Seven in Ambush</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BACOLOD, Philippines (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Communist guerrillas ambushed a jeep
carrying government troops Sunday in a remote village on Negros
island in the central Philippines, killing seven people, the
military said.
   A military report said two policemen, two militiamen and three
civilians were slain when 35 New People's Army guerrillas opened
fire on the jeep from a sugar cane field near the town of Canayan,
340 miles southeast of Manila.
   Two people were wounded in the attack and another escaped
unhurt, the report said. The insurgents fled with the victims'
weapons, it said.
   The New People's Army has been waging a 21-year-old insurgency
to establish a Marxist state.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900617-0044 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-90 1637EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--Anti-drugNewspaper     06-17 0174</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Anti-drug Newspaper,0178</SECOND>
<HEAD>Anti-Drug Publication For Young People Making Debut</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SYDNEY, Australia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A free tabloid newspaper with an
anti-drug message aimed at young people will be making its debut
this week.
   Organizers hope RAVE, initially to be distributed through
schools and some commercial outlets in New South Wales state and
the Australian Capital Territory, will become a national youth
publication.
   It is being funded by the New South Wales' Quit For Life
campaign and the National Campaign Against Drug Abuse, but also
aims to attract commercial advertising.
   ``With community concern running high about the use of both
legal and illegal drugs by young people, RAVE opens up
opportunities for business to make a contribution to drug
education,'' said Quit for Life spokesman Terry Slevin.
   Slevin said RAVE has a ``streetwise style'' and avoids using
heavy-handed tactics in talking to youth about drinking and drugs.
   The first 24-page issue will have a print run of 400,000. The
organizers hope to make it a monthly or bimonthly, depending on
reader and advertiser response.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900617-0045 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-90 1832EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--Japan-Violins     06-17 0131</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Japan-Violins,0134</SECOND>
<HEAD>Two Valuable Italian Violins Stolen at Tokyo University</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two Italian violins, together worth more than
$130,000, were stolen from practice rooms of a university during
the past two weeks, police said Sunday.
   Police said they suspected people associated with the university
committed the separate thefts at the Tokyo National University Of
Fine Arts and Music.
   A police spokesman said a student left her $26,600 violin on a
table in a practice room Friday, and instrument was gone when she
returned 90 minutes later.
   Another student left her $106,400 violin in a practice room on
June 5 for a five-minute trip to the bathroom but found it gone
upon her return, police said. Her violin was crafted by Joannes
Gagliano of Italy in 1803, police said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900617-0046 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-90 1833EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brite-FalconFall     06-17 0404</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brite-Falcon Fall,0415</SECOND>
<HEAD>Fledgling Falcon Causes Stir When It Disappears From Perch</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SPRINGFIELD, Mass. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A peregrine falcon chick that became
an instant cable TV star at hatching five weeks ago had viewers
panicking when he disappeared from his nest on the 21st floor of a
downtown skyscraper.
   The moment-to-moment activities of the chick and his brother
have been the subject of 24-hour cablecast here since they hatched
in early May. Their mother and father also are part of the show.
   The camera has caught each stage of the chicks' progress as they
quickly grew to almost their parents' size and started to test
their wings and venture from their nest on a ledge of the Monarch
Place office tower.
   But viewers' delight turned to worry Saturday when one chick
disappeared.
   It later turned out that the chick, apparently on his first
flight, strayed too far from home and could not make it back.
   He eventually landed in the middle of a downtown intersection,
amidst motorists and hundreds of pedestrians attending an outdoor
food festival.
   ``He was pretty stressed out, there were hundreds of people
there,'' said Steve Harris, a veterinarian who happened to pass by.
``He was panting a bit, which falcons do, but he didn't fight us
much. He didn't know enough to fight.''
   Harris took the chick to the Rowley Memorial Animal Hospital,
where he was pronounced in good health. On Sunday, state wildlife
officials returned him to a patio several stories above his nest _
to avoid having a human climb the glass-sided building and face
wrathful falcon parents.
   Harris said the parents probably would find their prodigal son
on the patio and feed him. But his homecoming would likely be
short-lived.
   ``He'll probably try flying again in a few days anyway,'' Harris
said. ``This time he'll probably be more successful.''
   The growing chicks lately had been straying beyond the camera's
view more and more, but when the bird was out of sight for several
hours, worried viewers started calling the cable company.
   ``People get very caught up in this,'' said Brian Lambert,
general manager of Continental Cablevision, which he said is seen
in about 100,000 homes.
   The chicks are the second pair raised on the ledge in this city
of about 152,000 people. Last year the same parent falcons chose
that spot to raise the first two chicks in 50 years to be hatched
in western Massachusetts.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900617-0047 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-90 1842EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brite-BrassBands     06-17 0330</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brite-Brass Bands,0339</SECOND>
<HEAD>Brass Band Festival Attracts Eight Old-Time Ensembles</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DANVILLE, Ky. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In the good old days, just about every
American town had its own brass band. During the first-ever Great
American Brass Band Festival, which ended Sunday, this
south-central Kentucky town was lucky enough to have eight old-time
ensembles.
   ``It was a real coup for Danville and I hope it's done every
year,'' said Steele Gregory, a Danville businessman.
   Activities at the Centre College campus in town began Thursday.
They ranged from displays of antique bicycles to a hot-air balloon
race, a traveling cartoon art exhibit from the Smithsonian
Institution in Washington, D.C., an old-fashioned picnic and even a
Civil War battle re-enactment.
   But the highlight of the weekend was, of course, the music.
   The groups spanned styles and periods, with the Civil War-era
Regiment Band of the 11th North Carolina Troops playing opposite
Danville's Advocate Brass Band, vintage 1890.
   Other ensembles included Saxton's Cornet Band from Lexington,
the Commonwealth Brass Band from Louisville, and the Brass Band of
Columbus from Ohio.
   But the Olympia Brass Band from New Orleans came the farthest
and got the biggest response. When the group led a procession down
Main Street on Saturday to the tune of ``When the Saints Come
Marching in,'' some spectators fell in behind and danced along.
   Milton Batiste, one of the band members, said afterward that it
wasn't necessary to go to New Orleans to capture that atmosphere.
   ``The atmosphere of this music can be experienced in Danville,
Ky., or New Orleans, La., just the same, providing people enjoy
it,'' said Milton Batiste, one of the band members. ``If people
enjoy what we do, the atmosphere is right anywhere we play.''
   Organizers estimated that more than 10,000 people turned out for
Saturday's parade and concert series. Danville Police Chief Mike
Lamb estimated that several thousand attended an open-air musical
church service Sunday morning.
   People came from as far away as Maine and Wisconsin, organizers
said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900617-0048 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-90 1658EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-RussianParty     06-17 0723</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Russian Party,0744</SECOND>
<HEAD>Russian Party Conference Showcase for Communist Disputes</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARK J. PORUBCANSKY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In a preview of a key national congress, Communist
Party members from the nation's biggest republic are holding their
own meeting this week. It is likely to turn into a battleground
over the future of communism and the country under Mikhail S.
Gorbachev.
   The congress opening Tuesday is likely to found a Communist
Party of Russia, distinct from the national party. Previously,
Russian Republic Communists have been folded into the national
organization.
   While Russia's popularly elected congress elected reformer Boris
N. Yeltsin president of the republic and declared sovereignty for
the republic itself, the republic's party members seem to have
little such independent feeling.
   Yet the same disputes over economic and social policies and the
party's future that are tearing at national party unity will be
present at the meeting of the 2,700 Russian Communists.
   Russia, with more than half of the Soviet population and
three-quarters of its territory, is home to 58 percent of the
country's more than 18 million Communist Party members.
   But since the Bolshevik Revolution of 1917, Russia's identity
largely has been submerged in the trappings of Soviet socialism.
Even though each of the other Soviet republics has had its own
party organization within the national party, Russia has not,
largely because Russians had tended to dominate the national and
republic Communist parties.
   Its search for an identity has now taken it in the direction of
founding its own Communist Party, as well as in the direction of
Yeltsin's more radical reforms.
   Conservatives, radical reformers and the party leaders
understand that the Russian party's size makes it vital.
   The 2,700 party members from the Russian republic are the same
group that will represent it when the Soviet Communist Party opens
its 28th national congress on July 2.
   The daily Moskovsky Komsomolets called this week's conference a
``general rehearsal'' for the congress of 4,700 party members from
throughout the Soviet Union.
   Many party members and observers believe the national congress
will result in the first split in the party since Lenin.
   At a meeting June 9-10 in Leningrad, some members called for
Gorbachev and his chief party adviser, Alexander N. Yakovlev, to be
thrown out of the party, the daily Komsomolskaya Pravda reported
Thursday.
   The Leningrad group says it represents at least 1.5 million
party members. It has proposed its own platform and its own slate
for the Central Committee.
   Gorbachev's Communist Party ``has to take responsibility for the
results of perestroika,'' Viktor Tyurkin, a 39-year-old Leningrad
party leader, said in an interview. ``It is not oriented to the
majority of simple working people.''
   Like several generations of Communists before them, Tyurkin and
his comrades believe that Soviet socialism has protected working
people from the whims of the market. While reformers criticize
Gorbachev's economic program for timidity in a time of crisis, the
Leningrad group sees in them a breach of faith.
   Despite the Leningrad group's criticism of Gorbachev, there is a
strong possibility that it will form an alliance with the national
party leadership at the conference, said Vladimir Lysenko, a leader
of the reform-minded Democratic Platform.
   A few months ago, Gorbachev spoke out against the founding of
the Russian party before the national party congress but he now
favors it, Lysenko told the Moskovsky Komsomolets newspaper. The
Leningrad group also favors it.
   Representatives of the Leningrad meetings have been invited to
help write the conference documents but no members of Democratic
Platform have been invited, Lysenko said.
   Democratic Platform is preparing its own set of documents that
its small group of delegates will present at the conference, he
said.
   Vladimir Komarov, a spokesman for the Leningrad group, said it
will have at least 25 delegates to the national conference. Members
of the Democratic Platform say they expect to have a small group as
well.
   Soviet party leaders have given no indication so far what
direction they think the party should take.
   Vyacheslav Shostakovsky, another Democratic Platform leader,
said that even though organizers of the Leningrad meetings do not
have any influential nationwide leaders, they can reach a large
number of Russians frustrated by the failures of reform.
   By such appeals, ``a bloc can be formed that can create a rather
potent threat to political stability,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900617-0049 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-90 1850EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Lebanon-AbuNidal     06-17 0392</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lebanon-Abu Nidal,0408</SECOND>
<HEAD>Four Killed in Fight Between Supporters and Rivals of Abu Nidal</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TYRE, Lebanon (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Rival factions of the guerrilla group led
by terrorist mastermind Abu Nidal battled Sunday with machine guns
and rocket-propelled grenades, killing at least four people and
wounding 15, police said.
   The showdown was the bloodiest in Lebanon between the two
factions since an anti-Abu Nidal mutiny within his
Fatah-Revolutionary Council began three years ago.
   The fighting broke out around midnight in the narrow alleyways
of the Rashidiyeh refugee camp and continued until 9 a.m., when
fighters loyal to Yasser Arafat's mainstream Fatah faction of the
PLO intervened.
   Police and Palestinian sources said supporters and opponents of
Abu Nidal from within his Fatah-Revolutionary Council fought in the
narrow alleys of the shantytown, using mortars, machine guns and
rocket-propelled grenades.
   Rashidiyeh, 50 miles south of Beirut, houses 18,500 Palestinians
registered by the U.N. Relief and Works Agency, in addition to a
few thousand unregistered refugees.
   The police sources, who spoke on condition of anonymity, said
Abu Nidal's opponents, backed by fighters from Arafat's Fatah,
occupied a school run by the U.N. agency.
   The three-story building overlooks the main position of Abu
Nidal's loyalists.
   The opponents demanded that Abu Nidal's supporters surrender or
risk being dislodged by force, the sources said.
   Forty men surrendered after the mediation of representatives
from other PLO factions. The Fatah-Revolutionary Council is outside
the Palestine Liberation Organization, which comprises nine
factions.
   The fighting flared up after Saturday's assassination in
Rashidiyeh of Omar Hamadeh, regional commander of the
Fatah-Revolutionary Council. His bodyguard, Mohammed Meri, was
wounded. His attacker is unknown.
   Arafat's Fatah and the Fatah-Revolutionary Council of Abu Nidal,
whose real name is Sabri al-Banna, are also engaged in a bitter
feud.
   PLO officials and opponents said in 1987 that Abu Nidal had 22
close aides gunned down in Libya in the internal policy dispute.
   Abu Nidal is believed to be in Libya, despite reports that
Libyan leader Col. Moammar Gadhafi was seeking his ouster in order
to distance himself from international terrorism.
   A U.S. State Department report last year described Abu Nidal as
the world's most dangerous terrorist.
   It blamed his group for 34 terrorist attacks in 20 countries
since he split from the PLO in 1973. At least 900 people were
killed or wounded in these attacks, the report said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900617-0050 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-90 1910EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Bangladesh-Strike     06-17 0279</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bangladesh-Strike,0295</SECOND>
<HEAD>Protesters Call for Resignation of Bangladesh Leader</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DHAKA, Bangladesh (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Tens of thousands of protesters took to
the streets throughout Bangladesh during a general strike Sunday to
protest new taxes and demand the resignation of President Hussain
Muhammad Ershad.
   The opposition-sponsored protest shut down schools, businesses
and transportation in at least 21 major cities, including the
capital, Dhaka, a city of 6 million.
   The strike was widely observed, but it was difficult to measure
popular support because many people stayed home or closed shops for
fear of violence.
   More than 50 people were detained by police during the protests,
but there were no reports of violence.
   In Dhaka, thousands of marchers shouted, ``Down with Ershad!''
as riot police patrolled nearby.
   ``Ershad has no right to stay in power. People have rejected the
fresh taxes proposed by his government,'' said Sheikh Hasina,
leader of an alliance of eight parties that called the strike.
   Finance Minister Abdul Munim announced Thursday in Parliament
that new taxes would be introduced.
   Munim said increased taxes were essential to raise funds for
development programs.
   Bangladesh, with a population of 111 million, is one of the
poorest countries in the world with a per capita income of $160 a
year.
   Opposition leaders have labeled the proposed increases
``anti-people'' and have demanded that the government resign and
order new elections under a neutral caretaker government.
   The opposition also accused Ershad, a former army general, of
rigging presidential and parliamentary elections to retain power.
Ershad's Jatiya or People's Party holds a two-thirds majority in
Parliament, but leading opposition parties boycotted the last
elections in 1988.
   Ershad took power in a bloodless coup in 1982.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900617-0051 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-90 1823EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Romania 1stLd-Writethru a0668 06-17 0701</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0668,0726</SECOND>
<HEAD>Demonstrators Return to Bucharest Square After Violence</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos XBUC1,5</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 8 grafs to UPDATE with statement from Interior
Ministry offering dialogue with protesters. Pickup pvs 5th graf,
`Opposition leaders...' EDITS to TRIM</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By ALISON SMALE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUCHAREST, Romania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Anti-communist demonstrators Sunday
returned to a main square where police and miners loyal to
President Ion Iliescu beat people to put down protests last week.
   ``Down with Iliescu!'' ``Iliescu should be put on trial!'' about
100 protesters yelled.
   Soldiers armed with clubs looked on, but they took no immediate
action to disperse them.
   The small group of demonstrators thinned out by midnight after
Interior Minister Doru Viorel Ursu offered to open a dialogue with
the protesters. Ursu was appointed Thursday after his predecessor
was forced to step down partly because of the brutal way in which
police broke up the previous demonstration in the square.
   ``We are waiting for dialogue with you, and we are ready to meet
you wherever you want,'' said the Interior Ministry communique
published by the state Rompres news agency. ``We are convinced we
can live in harmony.''
   The demonstrators earlier Sunday issued a list of demands,
including the release of all those arrested over the past week in
connection with the protest and subsequent rioting and the
publication of a list of people still hospitalized as a result of
the violence.
   The government says 1,021 people were arrested in last week's
protests. There were no reports that miners were among those
arrested.
   The government, having lost badly needed aid from the United
States and Western Europe because of the recent repression,
promised to uphold democratic principles in a statement published
Sunday.
   Opposition leaders say the government of Iliescu, whose National
Salvation Front won last month's free elections by a landslide, is
dominated by ex-communists from the regime of deposed dictator
Nicolae Ceausescu.
   Iliescu is to be inaugurated later this week.
   In Timisoara, about 3,000 people gathered Sunday on a central
square for a service to remember 94 people killed in the western
city in December. The uprising grew into the bloody revolution that
overthrew Ceausescu.
   The service was peaceful.
   Scores of demonstrators appeared in Bucharest on Sunday evening
at University Square, the site of a 53-day protest demanding that
Iliescu and other ex-communists be banned from office.
   Riot police broke up the demonstration Wednesday, the start of
three days of unrest in which six people died and 502 were injured.
   Iliescu called on thousands of coal miners to maintain order,
and they swarmed Bucharest on Thursday and Friday. Swinging iron
bars and cudgels, they attacked anyone they suspected as
anti-government.
   The violence ended after Iliescu thanked the miners ``with all
my heart'' and ordered them home late Friday.
   On Sunday, about 80 troops equipped with submachine guns and
nightsticks stood on the periphery of University Square but did not
interfere. Two buses full of police were parked nearby.
   Opposition leaders said the government was behaving like the
dictatorship it replaced.
   In a statement published in Sunday's newspapers, the government
pledged to play by democratic rules.
   ``The government is prepared to assure appropriate measures for
freedom of political expression for all with the exception of acts
of instigation and of neo-fascist propaganda,'' he statement said.
   ``It also demands that those responsible ensure the total
freedom of operation of the democratic institutions of the press,
radio and television and ... instill firmly democratic institutions
in our country,'' it added.
   The statement appeared to be an attempt to contain damage to
Romania's image abroad and to quiet domestic critics particularly
worried by the miners' attacks on intellectuals.
   Miners smashed the headquarters of opposition parties, ransacked
the home of at least one opposition leader and ordered four
opposition dailies and periodicals to stop publishing.
   The newspapers have not reappeared, raising fears that
opposition voices will not be heard in a society dominated by
Iliescu and his National Salvation Front.
   Western governments and international human rights organizations
condemned the violence of the miners.
   State Department spokesman Richard Boucher said the United
States would withhold all but humanitarian aid, and the European
Community postponed a trade and economic cooperation agreement with
Romania.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900617-0052 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-90 1844EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Israel-Sharon 1stLd-Writethru a0651 06-17 0718</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel-Sharon, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0651,0735</SECOND>
<HEAD>Architects of Lebanon War Named to Defense Committee</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 9 grafs for 8-14 bgng ```This government...' UPDATE with
quote from Arens. Pickup pvs 15, `Sharon, 62.... EDITS to TRIM</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By G.G. LaBELLE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The new right-wing Cabinet on Sunday gave
former generals Ariel Sharon and Rafael Eitan their biggest say in
military policy since both were reprimanded for actions in two
massacres during the 1982 Lebanon invasion.
   At its first meeting, the Cabinet named Sharon, a former defense
minister, and Eitan, chief of staff during the Lebanon invasion, to
the 11-man Ministerial Defense Committee.
   The committee is a forum for debating defense policies and also
includes one representative of each of Likud's government coalition
allies.
   Sharon and Eitan were blamed by an Israeli inquiry for not
anticipating that Israel's Lebanese Christian militia allies would
massacre hundreds of Palestinians if they were allowed to enter
Beirut's Sabra and Chatilla refugee camps in 1982.
   Sharon, a leader of the conservative Likud bloc, also was named
chairman of a Cabinet committee overseeing the immigration of
thousands of Soviet Jews to Israel. Sharon is an advocate of Jewish
settlements in the occupied West Bank and Gaza Strip.
   His appointment has raised fears that he would try to move
Soviet Jews to the occupied areas, worsening already tense ties
with the United States. U.S. officials consider the Jewish
settlements obstacles to peace.
   Israeli officials insisted Sunday that the new Cabinet would
work for peace with Palestinians and for a smoother relationship
with the United States.
   Defense Minister Moshe Arens said he wants to ``improve the
level and scope of dialogue between myself as defense minister and
the Arab Palestinian population in the area, so that together we
try to find the basis of an agreement.''
   ``I know it would be limited and I know we don't agree about
many things ... but what is important here is the very fact of a
dialogue,'' Arens said on Israel Television's Arabic-language
program.
   Police Minister Roni Milo, a Likud member and confidant of Prime
Minister Yitzhak Shamir said: ``This government is interested in
the peace process no less than the preceding government.''
   Likud's coalition government with the left-center Labor Party
fell apart in March because Shamir would not go along with Labor
demands to accept a U.S. proposal for preliminary
Palestinian-Israeli peace talks. The new right-wing government took
power last week.
   Milo said he expected talks soon between U.S. and Israeli
officials to advance the peace process.
   He also warned, however, that the new government would not
accept ``previous processes that were not brought up nicely'' _ a
reference to Secretary of States James A. Baker III's efforts to
organize an Israeli-Palestinian dialogue in Cairo, Egypt.
   Baker urged including at least one Palestinian deported by
Israel as a way to satisfy Palestine Liberation Organization
demands that Palestinians living outside the occupied lands be
included. He also proposed to include some Arabs who have homes
both in the annexed east Jerusalem and in the occupied areas.
   Israel argued such moves would allow the PLO to control the
Palestinian delegation and raise the issue of Jerusalem, which
Israel has declared its ``eternal capital.''
   The new defense committee named by the Cabinet will be headed by
Shamir, 74, a former agent of the Mossad secret service. The
committee also includes Arens and Foreign Minister David Levy.
   Sharon, 62, a hero in the 1967 and 1973 Middle East wars, was
the architect of the Lebanon invasion. He was forced to resign as
defense minister after the Sabra and Chatilla massacre in west
Beirut.
   Israeli-allied Lebanese Christian militiamen, who were bitter
over the murder of their leader, went into the two refugee camps
the day after Israel's army seized control of west Beirut. They
killed more than 800 Palestinians, many of them women and children.
   An Israeli inquiry found that Sharon ``disregarded the danger of
acts of venegance'' in allowing the Christian fighters into the
camps. It found that Eitan failed to investigate reports of a
massacre and did not act to stop it.
   Sharon has repeatedly said he wants the defense minister's post
back, but he has been kept in lesser Cabinet jobs.
   Eitan, 61, a member of the far-right Tzomet Party, has never
been in the Cabinet.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900617-0053 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-90 1939EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Vietnam-Spies     06-17 0328</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Vietnam-Spies,0343</SECOND>
<HEAD>Vietnam Reports Discovery of Anti-Government Groups</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BANGKOK, Thailand (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Vietnamese counterintelligence agents
have uncovered five anti-government rings and arrested dozens of
members after investigating joint ventures with foreign companies,
an official report said.
   The Saturday broadcast, a text of which was seen in Bangkok on
Sunday, was one of a series of recent announcements indicating a
crackdown on dissent in the communist southeast Asian country.
   Hanoi Radio said the groups were discovered when security
services investigated more than 100 companies involved in the joint
ventures with foreign companies.
   The radio said the investigation was part of a drive is intended
to root out people regarded as dangerous to national security.
   The crackdown, spearheaded by the interior ministry, has
included arrests, increased police surveillance and the deportation
of two Americans for alleged anti-government activity.
   The broadcast said that in their inspection of the companies,
security forces had ``discovered many spies who have taken
advantage of various international organizations and corporations
that have investments in Vietnam to infiltrate into the country to
carry out intelligence activities.''
   ``The security forces have destroyed five underground
reactionary organizations and captured tens of their members,'' the
broadcast said.
   It said many documents, books, magazines and other publications
``with reactionary contents'' had been confiscated.
   The broadcast did not elaborate on the alleged spy and
anti-government groups. It did not identify those arrested.
   In the past, Hanoi has charged that the CIA and Vietnamese
expatriates have tried to destabilize the communist government.
   Some Vietnamese officials said the crackdown was ordered to
prevent protests during several anniversaries earlier this year.
These included the 15th anniversary of the communists' victory over
South Vietnam.
   But Western analysts said they believe there is also a sense of
insecurity among hard-line, older communist leaders who fear the
country is being isolated by the fall of communist governments
around the world.
   Vietnam is one of a dwindling number of nations where the
communist party rules without sharing power.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900617-0054 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-90 1949EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-AirShowCrash     06-17 0340</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Air Show Crash,0349</SECOND>
<HEAD>Director of Air Show Dies in Plane Crash</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TED BRIDIS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>OKLAHOMA CITY (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The director of an air show died Sunday
when his plane crashed in a ball of fire while he was performing a
stunt, officials said.
   Tom Jones, 44, a former national champion aerobatic pilot who
was directing the Aerospace America '90 show, was killed in the
1:45 p.m. crash, the show's chairman, Ted Strenczek, said in a
statement.
   ``When it hit, it just exploded,'' said Kevin Ellis, one of
thousands who saw the crash at the Will Rogers World Airport. ``No
matter how fast the trucks got there, he was dead. It was just a
ball of fire.''
   Witnesses said Jones' Soviet-made, civilian Sukhoi-26 stunt
plane apparently did not regain power after he flipped it during an
intentional stall.
   ``It didn't even come out of the stall,'' said spectator Ranee
Woodall. ``I didn't hear his engine.''
   Observers said that just before it crashed, Jones' plane trailed
smoke of a color different than the pure white normally used to
illustrate stunts.
   The plane hit the ground nose-first about 100 yards from the
crowd, estimated at 75,000. No injuries were reported.
   Emergency workers in fireproof suits ran to the crash site, and
Federal Aviation Administration officials were at the plane within
minutes.
   Jones was a member of the 1988-89 world champion aerobatic team,
and was the national aerobatic champion in 1988, said air show
spokesman Mark House.
   The rest of the show, which was in its final of three days, was
canceled, but U.S. military planes performed a salute to Jones.
   Three Soviet planes, which Jones' lobbying efforts had brought
to the show, repeated the tribute. They included the world's
biggest cargo jet, a Soviet Antonov-225 which was displayed but did
not fly at a Wisconsin show last year, and two Soviet Sukhoi-Su 27
Flanker fighter jets, on their second U.S. appearance.
   Jones flew to Moscow twice to persuade the Soviets to bring the
planes to the show here.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900617-0055 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-90 2023EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-LinerGrounded     06-17 0185</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Liner Grounded,0191</SECOND>
<HEAD>Patching Complete, Fuel Unloaded From Liner</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Temporary patching on the hull of the crippled
cruise liner Bermuda Star was completed, readying the vessel for
towing to dry dock in New York, the Coast Guard said Sunday.
   The hull patching was finished Saturday night and the liner's
fuel was transferred to a barge, said Petty Officer Dale Caudoe in
the Marine Safety Office in Providence, R.I.
   Caudoe said the ship probably would be towed to dry dock in New
York for permanent repairs Monday or Tuesday.
   The cruise ship was carrying 1,067 passengers and crew when it
hit a rocky ledge near Falmouth in dense fog June 10. The vessel
was freed later that day and towed to a spot about three miles away.
   The accident ripped the ship's hull and exposed tanks holding
about 110,000 gallons of fuel. About 7,500 gallons spilled, the
Coast Guard said.
   Crews cleaned about 1,000 gallons of fuel that washed onto
Naushon Island and additional oil pockets found later on nearby
Nashawena Island.
   Environmentalists said the oil should pose little threat to
wildlife.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900617-0056 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-90 2023EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-TankerBlast-OilEaters     06-17 0293</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Tanker Blast-Oil Eaters,0302</SECOND>
<HEAD>Microbe Experiment Continues Despite Delay</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Tanker Blast</HEAD>
<DATELINE>GALVESTON, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Oil-eating microbes spread over part of
an oil slick from the supertanker Mega Borg appear to have done
their job, but officials said they launched another experiment
Sunday to make sure.
   On Friday, about 100 pounds of hungry bacteria were spread over
an acre of the slick from the crippled Norwegian tanker that
exploded June 8 in the Gulf of Mexico.
   It was the first use of the process called bioremediation on
open waters.
   A flyover Sunday of the area marked by a buoy showed little oil
in the treated waters, state officials said.
   ``There certainly wasn't any oil over there,'' said Texas Water
Commission Chairman B.J. ``Buck'' Wynne.
   However, Wynne said it could not be determined if the oil was
removed by the microbes or currents, or whether the buoy had moved.
   ``Visually, it appeared there was hardly anything left. It
appears degradation of the oil has occurred,'' said Blanton Moore
of the Texas General Land Office.
   Moore said officials won't know for certain from the first
application, so they started another experiment Sunday by
encircling two areas of the slick with booms, each 15 feet in
diameter.
   Officials plan to spread microbes on one area, but do nothing
with the other. Moore said water samples will be taken from both
areas, and results should be available early in the week.
   Carl Oppenheimer, a University of Texas microbiologist who has
been working on bioremediation for 15 years, has predicted the
experiment will succeed and show that the process should be used on
a wider scale in oil spills.
   Bioremediation uses naturally occurring bacteria to break down
oil into harmless fatty acids eaten by marine life.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900617-0057 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-90 2036EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Japan-Soviet     06-17 0193</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Japan-Soviet,0197</SECOND>
<HEAD>Gorbachev to Visit Japan Early Next Year</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Japan's prime minister announced Sunday that
Mikhail S. Gorbachev will visit in early 1991. It would be the
first trip to Japan by a top Soviet leader.
   Relations have long been soured by a territorial dispute
involving islands at the southern end of the Kuril chain seized by
the Soviet Union at the end of World War II.
   Prime Minister Toshiki Kaifu announced the visit during a
seminar sponsored by the governing Liberal Democratic Party. He
said it was confirmed in a letter from the Soviets saying Gorbachev
would arrive in early 1991. Kaifu gave no exact date.
   Soviet Foreign Minister Eduard Shevardnadze told Japanese
officials in September that Gorbachev hoped to visit Tokyo in 1991
but did not specify when.
   A Liberal Democratic Party official quoted Kaifu as saying at
the seminar that his administration will try to improve relations
with the Soviet Union by negotiating over the disputed islands
while promoting cultural and personal exchanges.
   Though Gorbachev's visit would be the first to Japan by a top
Soviet leader, four Japanese prime ministers have visited the
Soviet Union.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900617-0058 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-90 2045EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-StudentRally     06-17 0235</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Student Rally,220</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rally Kicks Off Week of Black Student Activism</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hundreds of black college students marched to
a rally at a park across from the White House on Sunday to bolster
their call for better education opportunities.
   A handful of civil rights leaders and musicians joined the rally
in Lafayette Square urging a resurgence of black activism to fight
for justice for all students at campuses across the nation.
   ``Whenever young America comes alive, America is always made
better,'' Rev. Jesse Jackson told the crowd.
   Jackson said the fights for self-determination _ like those
democratic movements occurring across the globe _ do not come from
meetings of politicians, they come from the ``blood of common
people.''
   Organizers said the rally day also was designed to kick off a
week of black activism in which students will take to Capitol Hill
to lobby their members of Congress for District of Columbia
statehood, and continued sanctions against South Africa.
   Students say the racial division and tension that occurs at
colleges must be defeated.
   The ``Student Call to Washington'' also includes a rally planned
in front of the U.S. Supreme Court Wednesday.
   The week was organized by the National Collegiate Black Caucus
and several
   other groups including Black Law Students Association, the
African National Congress Youth Division and the United States
Student Association.
   U.S. Capitol Police estimated 850 people participated in
Sunday's Demonstration.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900617-0059 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-90 2041EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Bulgaria 2ndLd-Writethru a0667 06-17 0802</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bulgaria, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0667,0827</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ex-Communists Headed For Bulgarian Victory</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 16 grafs to UPDATE with projected unofficial
results. Pickup pvs 13th graf, `Petar Beron....' EDITS to TRIM</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By ROLAND PRINZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SOFIA, Bulgaria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Ex-Communists appeared on the way toward
winning a parliamentary majority in runoff elections Sunday. It
would be the first victory for a reformed Communist party in the
recent East bloc elections.
   However, the 400-seat unicameral parliament, the first freely
elected legislature in Bulgaria in 58 years, will have a
substantial number of opposition lawmakers and their presence will
mark the end of rubber-stamp approval for policies of the former
Communists.
   The Bulgarian capital, Sofia, appeared to be firmly in
opposition hands.
   The projections of a victory for the former Communists _ who now
call themselves Socialists _ was based in part on incomplete
results from about 30 of the 81 constituencies counted by the
independent Association for Fair Elections.
   The group did not release a total figure for how many seats it
believed the former Communists captured, but it said preliminary
numbers indicated they had won an overall majority.
   First-round results show that in 22 of the 81 constituencies in
Sunday's runoff, the ex-Communists candidates had a substantial
lead over their rivals and in 33 others they had a slight edge.
   Apart from Bulgaria, non-Communist parties have triumphed in
this year's round of national elections in East Germany,
Czechoslovakia, Hungary and Romania after last year's democratic
revolutions. However, in Romania, a party with former Communists in
its leadership won elections last month.
   Although Sunday's voting appeared to go smoothly in most places,
state television reported breaches of electoral procedure in some
constituencies and illegal canvassing near some polling stations.
   Dimiter Ivanov, an activist from the Association of Fair
Elections, told The Associated Press in some cases the number of
people voting exceeded the number of people registered in the
respective precincts.
   The Socialists were the winners in the first round of voting on
June 10, garnering 172 seats. They need to win only 29 of the 81
seats being decided in the runoffs to gain an absolute majority.
   Socialist Party leader Alexander Lilov was a first-round winner,
but Socialist Premier Andrei Lukanov faced a runoff, which he is
expected to win.
   The main opposition alliance, the Union of Democratic Forces,
won 107 seats in the first round and other opposition groups won
40. The alliance and the Agrarian Party, a once docile ally of the
Communists, have both vowed not to join a coalition with the
Socialists.
   In Sofia, the United Democratic Forces won 18 of 26 available
seats in the first round of elections. Association of Fair Election
officials said the alliance added at least another six seats
Sunday, turning the capital into a bulwark of the opposition.
   Socialist and United Democratic Forces officials have said they
might form a government of experts chosen on the basis of their
expertise, rather than their political affiliation.
   Dimiter Popov, secretary of the Central Electoral Commission,
said the commission expects to announce the results Tuesday, the
state news agency BTA reported.
   State television said 75 percent of the eligible voters cast
ballots shortly before the polls closed at 6 p.m. In the first
first round, 91 percent voted.
   Petar Beron, a member of the leadership of the United Democratic
Forces, said in an interview Sunday that he expected the Socialists
to win an absolute majority.
   He noted, however, that whatever shape the new government takes
it is likely to be transitional.
   ``Such a government is usually a caretaker government, but it
cannot rule the country for very long,'' he said.
   Lilov said in an interview published Sunday that his party
favored a coalition of national unity.
   In an interview with the British Broadcasting Corp. that was
reprinted in the Socialist Party daily Duma, Lilov said that if the
opposition refused to join such a government, his party would
approach ``respected personalities'' to form a government of
``experts and professionals.''
   The chief task of the new government will be tackling the
country's $10 billion foreign debt, rising inflation and consumer
goods shortages while gearing the economy toward capitalism.
   The United Democratic Front favors sweeping private ownership
and privatization of agriculture. The Socialists would prefer to
leave some industry government-run for the time being and are vague
on the future status of farming, which is currently
government-owned or cooperative.
   Outside a polling station in the town of Stanke Dimitrov, about
40 miles south of Sofia, a young soldier who refused to give his
name said he voted for the Socialists ``because I want security, I
am scared of the UDF.''
   Analysts say the Socialists represent stability for many and won
a certain popularity after ousting former Communist strongman Todor
Zhivkov last November and initiating reform.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900617-0060 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-90 2053EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-WeatherpageWeather     06-17 0237</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Weatherpage Weather,0245</SECOND>
<HEAD>More Thunderstorms, More Flooding and Summer Temperatures</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Father's Day on Sunday brought more thunderstorms and flooding
to the South and the Midwest.
   Rain showers and thunderstorms were scattered over the northern
half of Florida by midday, as well as over southern Georgia,
Alabama, Mississippi, western Tennessee, southeast Illinois,
southern Indiana and into southern Ohio.
   Showers and thunderstorms also extended over Michigan, as well
as northern Minnesota, eastern North Dakota and northeastern South
Dakota.
   Scattered showers and storms fell across Oregon, northeast
California and southwest Idaho.
   Heavier rainfall during the six hours ending at 2 p.m. EDT
included about an inch at Grand Forks, N.D., and Traverse City,
Mich.
   Flooding continued across east-central Nebraska, where a number
of roads and highways were closed. Only the floods of the 1940s
were higher than the crest on the Elkhorn River at West Point, Neb.
   Flooding was widespread across much of Iowa and northwest
Illinois, where roads and highways also were closed.
   Flood warnings remained in effect on the Mississippi River at
Natchez, Miss., and Red River Landing, Baton Rouge and
Donaldsonville, La., as well as on the Atchafalaya River at Morgan
City, La.
   Temperatures around the nation at 3 p.m. EDT ranged from 53
degrees at Yellowstone National Park, Wyo., to 102 degrees at Wink,
Texas.
   The low temperature for the Lower 48 was 30 degrees at Gunnison,
Colo., and Truckee, Calif.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900617-0061 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-90 2100EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Poland-Solidarity     06-17 0304</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Poland-Solidarity,0318</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mazowiecki Calls For Common Effort to Build Democracy</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DEBORAH G. SEWARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WARSAW, Poland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Prime Minister Tadeusz Mazowiecki said
Sunday that calls by Solidarity members to accelerate reforms
jeopardize government efforts to institute democratic changes.
   Mazowiecki was speaking to leaders of Citizens Committees, the
political arm that Solidarity formed last year to contest
elections, as they met in Warsaw to debate future strategy.
   ``Those who use attacks, poison and hatred make holes in our
common boat of Polish democracy ...,'' Mazowiecki said.
   ``Only by common effort and only by understanding that one has
to build the fundamentals of Polish democracy will we be able to go
through this difficult passage from the old to the new system,'' he
added.
   Mazowiecki, a Catholic intellectual and longtime adviser to
Solidarity leader Lech Walesa, said the Citizens Committees should
act in partnership with other groups to build democracy in Poland.
   Mazowiecki took over as head of Poland's Solidarity-led
government in August, ending 40 years of monopoly rule by the
Communist Party.
   However, he has come under increasing attack by Walesa and
members of parliament for being too slow and too timid in routing
out Communist bureaucrats.
   Walesa has also attempted to bring new people who back his views
into Solidarity's national committee.
   Those efforts have aroused concern among intellectuals who
believe Walesa's new set of advisers are more interested in seeing
the Solidarity leader elected president than in rebuilding
democracy.
   Walesa did not attend Sunday's meeting but sent a letter that
was read before the delegates.
   ``We are passing today from one system to another. The old
system we fought against has been overthrown. A new political
system is only being formed. It should be formed as quickly as
possible, more energetically,'' the labor leader wrote in his
letter.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900617-0062 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-90 2112EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ANPAMeeting     06-17 0190</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-ANPA Meeting,0195</SECOND>
<HEAD>Changing Technology A Topic at Vegas Convention</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LAS VEGAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   About 14,000 newspaper executives are expected
to focus on changing newspaper technology at the 62nd annual
American Newspaper Publishers Association Technical Exposition and
Conference this week.
   The event, which begins Monday and ends Wednesday, features the
largest display of newspaper equipment in the world, with 350
exhibitors displaying their wares over 365,000 square feet of
exhibition space.
   Two Las Vegas newspaper executives, Review-Journal general
manager Dave Osborn and Sun president Brian Greenspun, are to
deliver welcoming addresses Monday at the opening general session.
   The show provides an opportunity for manufacturers and suppliers
to the newspaper and graphics arts business to present their
products and services to an international audience of top newspaper
executives.
   Norman P. Dusseault, vice president and assistant general
manager of the Times Publishing Co. of St. Petersburg, Fla., will
chair the event.
   ANPA Chairman Lloyd G. Schermer is to deliver Monday's keynote
address, ``Challenges Facing Our Business.''
   Recycling, desktop publishing and telephone technology, along
with other advances in the industry, will be the topics of general
sessions and workshops throughout the event.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900617-0063 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-90 2128EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ChurchRobbery     06-17 0407</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Church Robbery,0420</SECOND>
<HEAD>Armed Man Robs Church Congregation</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PHILIPPI, W.Va. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A man armed with a sawed-off shotgun
entered a Baptist church Sunday and robbed the 132-member
congregation as they lay on the floor amid the pews ``for an
eternity.''
   No one was hurt, authorities said.
   The man, wearing a stocking mask and sunglasses, made off with
at least $500, but didn't get the Faith Way Baptist Church's
collection, according to church officials and the Barbour County
sheriff's department.
   The incident just outside this town in northeast West Virginia
occurred around 11:30 a.m., about midway through the morning
service, the sheriff's department said in a statement.
   The pastor's wife, Mrs. Mary Gregory, said the man came in
through the church's basement, where the children were holding
junior church, and walked up the steps to the back of the sanctuary.
   ``He had a gun and he said, `This is a holdup. Everybody get
down.' Everybody looked at him and they were just stunned,'' Mrs.
Gregory said. ``Everybody was down and they were praying and he was
going around the pews and taking billfolds and purses and things.
   ``It seemed like he was there for an eternity, but actually it
was about 10 or 15 minutes,'' she said.
   ``I don't know, for some reason I just thought it was a prank,''
said her husband, the Rev. Downing Gregory. ``I didn't believe him
to be serious about it. All of the sudden, my associate (pastor)
started praying on the platform there with me and then I realized,
`I think we're in trouble.'''
   The man had a congregation member help him collect the wallets
and purses in a bag, Mrs. Gregory said.
   He threatened people the man helping collect the money and the
associate minister, Daniel Jager, who was praying louder than
others in the congregation, she said.
   ``The man was getting irritated,'' Mrs. Gregory. ``They were
praying for him, what he was doing and that it was wrong.''
   The collection, which already had been gathered, was in the
church office and the gunman apparently did not find it, Mrs.
Gregory said. Church officials declined to say how much was
collected.
   In addition to cash, the man made off with several checkbooks
and credit cards, Mrs. Gregory said.
   As he left, the bandit told the congregation members to pray for
15 minutes before getting up from the floor, Mrs. Gregory said.
   Attendance at the service was 132, she said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900617-0064 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-90 2152EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-CruiseDope     06-17 0187</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Cruise Dope,0191</SECOND>
<HEAD>Divers Find 250 Pounds of Marijuana Attached to Cruise Ship's Hull</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Police divers found 250 pounds of marijuana in
steel boxes inside the propeller section of a cruise ship, and
three Jamaicans were arrested for drug trafficking, the Coast Guard
said Sunday.
   The search began just after noon Saturday when the captain of
the cruise ship Holiday reported seeing two scuba divers swimming
under the ship's hull and asked authorities to search for anything
suspicious below the water line.
   The Coast Guard dispatched two patrol boats from Miami Beach and
quickly found and arrested the divers, both Jamaican citizens, plus
another Jamaican man in a nearby motorboat.
   The divers found the four steel boxes, each measuring 2 cubic
feet, inside the grating that covers the cruise ship's propeller
shafts, said Coast Guard Lt. Wayne Ball.
   The Holiday, which had returned to Miami from Jamaica earlier
Saturday, left for Mexico, its next stop, at 10 p.m., six hours
late and minus the steel boxes, Ball said.
   The three men were turned over to Miami Beach police, who
declined to identify them.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900617-0065 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-90 2156EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Colombia 1stLd-Writethru a0674 06-17 0576</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Colombia, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0674,0590</SECOND>
<HEAD>12 Killed in Colombian Drug Hub, Drug Suspect Captured</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS two grafs for graf 3 `The trafficking...' to CORRECT
spelling of Sheuter; pickup graf 5 `Bill Dempsey...'
^By STAN YARBRO</NOTE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOGOTA, Colombia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Gunmen have killed 12 more people in the
violence-wracked drug capital of Medellin, and police said Sunday
they have captured another suspected drug trafficker wanted in the
United States.
   The 10-month-old war between the government and traffickers
heated up again last week when police shot and killed the man they
described as the mastermind of the drug lords' campaign of terror,
and a car bomb killed four people.
   The trafficking suspect, Salomon Sheuter Benitez was captured
Friday in the coastal city of Barranquilla, a police communique
said.
   The communique said Sheuter, 49, is wanted in Pittsburgh on
charges of conspiring to distribute cocaine. He is one of 15
Colombians currently awaiting extradition to the United States.
   Bill Dempsey, a spokesman for the U.S. Marshal service in
Washington, said the person arrested apparently is the same one
listed on a Dec. 14, 1987, cocaine possession and distribution
warrant from Pittsburgh in a state case.
   There was no immediate confirmation of the arrest or details
from other U.S. officials. Sheuter is not on the official U.S. list
of the 12 Colombian drug suspects most wanted for extradition.
   Four more police and two soldiers were shot and killed by
terrorists in Medellin on Saturday, a police communique said
without elaborating.
   Officials were quoted Sunday by a newspaper as saying married
policemen will be transferred out of the city. Police have said the
Medellin cartel is paying more than $4,000 to terrorists for every
police officer they kill.
   A terrorist campaign blamed on the city's cocaine cartel has
killed 116 police officers this year in the city 150 miles
northwest of the capital Bogota.
   In addition, a gunmen killed six civilians, including two
16-year-old girls, in a restaurant in one of Medellin's poor
neighborhoods, police reported. They gave no details.
   However, the massacre was similar to several recently carried
out by unidentified gunmen in neighborhoods known as the recruiting
grounds for the Medellin cartel.
   In a communique last week, the cartel blamed police for the
killings of the neighborhoods' youths. Police rejected the charge,
saying the massacres were apparently the work of rival criminal
gangs.
   The Colombian government has extradited 15 Colombians since
putting the policy into effect in August. The last extradition was
March 29.
   Several U.S. and Colombian officials, speaking on condition of
anonymity, have said the policy has been suspended until the
president-elect, Cesar Gaviria, takes office on Aug. 7.
   The administration of President Virgilio Barco has not commented
on whether the policy has been suspended.
   Traffickers have retaliated for the government's anti-drug
campaign with a wave of terrorist attacks that have left hundreds
of Colombians dead since the war began in August with the
traffickers' assassination of a leading presidential hopeful.
   The government has offered over $400,000 for information leading
to the capture of the alleged chief of the Medellin cartel, Pablo
Escobar.
   On Wednesday, police raided the Medellin apartment of the
cartel's military chief, John Jairo Arias, and killed him after he
fired on them, according to the official report.
   Hours later, a car bomb exploded near a police post in the same
neighborhood. It killed four people, including two suspected
terrorists inside the car, and injured 43 others, police said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900617-0066 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-90 2211EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-TracyBoxOffice     06-17 0522</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Tracy Box Office,0538</SECOND>
<HEAD>`Dick Tracy' Opens to Estimated $23 Million</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RICHARD DE ATLEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HOLLYWOOD (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   ``Dick Tracy,'' the ultra-hyped Disney movie
facing a gremlin and a muscleman as summer box-office enemies, will
make up to $23 million in ticket sales in its opening weekend, it
was estimated Sunday.
   Dick Cook, president of Buena Vista Pictures Distribution for
Disney, said ``Tracy'' was a record opening for the company and had
all the signs of a summer winner.
   The movie, directed by its star, Warren Beatty, received mostly
rave reviews.
   ``The way it's been reviewed, and the favorable way it has been
received _ it is going to do extraordinarily well. And there's a
lot of summer left,'' Cook said.
   He estimated a weekend box-office of $22 million to $23 million,
and said ``Dick Tracy'' would get ``double the amount of business
that any other movie will do this weekend.''
   An industry observer who spoke on condition of anonymity said
the opening was ``not great _ somewhere in between. ... It's not a
bad opening.'' That source estimated the take for ``Tracy'' would
be $22 million.
   Both noted ``Tracy's'' debut against a slate of movies
hothouse-grown to bloom as summer hits: ``Total Recall,'' ``Back to
the Future III,'' ``Another 48 HRS.,'' and the new ``Gremlins.''
   The week's other major opening, Warner Bros.' ``Gremlins 2: The
New Batch,'' featuring Gizmo the gremlin and his deranged cousins,
may earn up to $10.3 million, according to one industry guess.
   Hovering over all this year's summer flicks was the shadow of
the $40.5 million debut last year of Warner Bros.' comic-book hero
movie, ``Batman.''
   The estimated Tracy box office was well below that. It also is
under the $25 million opening for Arnold Schwarzenegger's ``Total
Recall'' in the first weekend of this month.
   ``It's never where you start, it's where you end,'' said Cook of
``Dick Tracy's'' earning power for the summer.
   ``Dick Tracy'' opened at 2,223 theaters around the nation with a
new Roger Rabbit cartoon, ``Rollercoaster Rabbit.'' Admission for
midnight Thursday openings was a T-shirt, sold by theaters for as
much as $20 apiece.
   Disney said it will include the price of the T-shirt in its
box-office gross, despite the protests of others in the movie
industry that it would inflate the numbers.
   ``It is part of the box office, the ticket to the event,'' said
Cook. ``It didn't amount to that much.''
   One source placed the T-shirt boost at $1.2 million to $1.5
million.
   Cook said the opening of ``Dick Tracy,'' starring Beatty as the
comic-strip detective and Madonna as gun moll Breathless Mahoney,
outstripped Disney first weekend earnings for ``Honey, I Shrunk the
Kids,'' which took $14.2 million last year _ against ``Batman'' _
and ``Who Framed Roger Rabbit,'' which took $11 million.
   ``Honey'' went on to earn $130 million domestically; ``Roger
Rabbit'' brought home $160 million as the hit of 1988. Batman
earned $250 million domestically for 1989.
   The sales figures for ``Tracy'' are estimates which include box
office from Friday through Sunday. Final figures including the
actual Sunday gate will not be available until Monday.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900617-0067 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-90 2236EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-MidwestStorms 2ndLd-Writethru a0693 06-17 0887</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Midwest Storms, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0693,0909</SECOND>
<HEAD>Midwest Cleans Up from Severe Thunderstorms, Tornadoes</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 9th graf, `The 11-year-old ...,' to ADD dead girl's
name; SUBS grafs 13-15, `The engineer ...,' with six grafs to
UPDATE with scattered thunderstorms Sunday in parts of Illinois,
width of South Dakota tornado's path, partial South Dakota damage
estimate, CORRECTS to say warning sirens not sounded in most South
Dakota areas hit; picks up 16th graf, `In northeast ...'</NOTE>
<HEAD>With
AM-Flash Floods, Bjt</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto SI1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Midwesterners mopped up or continued battling flood waters
Sunday after tornadoes, thunderstorms and flooding hit parts of the
region, killing an 11-year-old girl in Iowa and a railroad engineer
in Illinois.
   Tornadoes that roared through South Dakota and Nebraska on
Saturday left damaged or destroyed farm buildings and homes and
uprooted trees in their wake. Up to half a foot of rain fell on
already-sodden ground in Minnesota and Nebraska.
   In eastern Iowa, Clear Creek jumped its banks, closing a
two-mile section of Interstate 80 on Sunday. Flooding knocked out
water service to the small town of Manning in the western part of
the state.
   Damage to just the eastern Iowa cities of Bettendorf and
Davenport along the Mississipi River was $21 million, officials
estimated.
   Heavy rains caused the collapse early Sunday of the roof and
part of a wall at the K&amp;M Manufacturing sheet metal plant in
Marshalltown in central Iowa. No one was at the plant at the time,
and there were no injuries.
   Eight inches of rain have doused Iowa over the past week; some
parts of the state got more than 5 inches of rain in a matter of
hours, said forecaster Scott Truett of the National Weather
Service's Des Moines office.
   Weather service flood specialist Ed May said some rivers were
still rising but predicted there wouldn't be much more flooding
beyond farmland.
   ``It's not unusual to have flooding in June. June's a wet
month,'' he said. ``What's unusual is the extent. We've got almost
all of the rivers in two-thirds of the state above flood stage.
That's kind of rare.''
   Michaella Aguiler, 11, was killed when she was swept into a
culvert in the Davenport suburb of LeClaire on the Mississippi
River, authorities said.
   Gov. Terry Branstad declared seven eastern and central counties
disaster areas on Saturday, and sent the National Guard to help
sandbag low-lying areas as rivers and creeks overflowed. Guard
soldiers remained on flood duty on Sunday.
   Heavy rains lashed western Illinois on Saturday. Thirty-two cars
of an 88-car Burlington Northern freight train derailed when a
waterlogged embankment gave way near Morrison, killing the engineer
and injuring three other railway workers, officials said.
   Train workers were trapped in the engine because the locomotive
car they were in came to rest in about 15 feet of water and mud,
said a Whiteside County sheriff's dispatcher who refused to give
her name.
   The engineer was identified as Samuel Jiardina, 61, of La
Crosse, Wis. The injured were treated and released. Damage was
estimated at $2.1 million, including about 600 feet of damaged
track.
   Scattered thunderstorms pounded parts of northern and
west-central Illinois on Sunday night, but no damage or injuries
were reported.
   In southeastern South Dakota, a tornado hit so fast Saturday, it
knocked out power before warning sirens could be activated in most
areas. The twister left a nine-mile-long, three-mile wide trail of
destruction, but no injuries were reported.
   The tornado damaged 30 farms, five of them seriously, said Fire
Chief T.A. Mullinix in Beresford, 35 miles south of Sioux Falls.
One home lost its roof, Mullinix said. The twister also knocked
down power lines and several buildings and barns in Alcester 10
miles east of Beresford.
   Alcester Police Chief Kevin Booker said he got to activate
warning sirens for a few seconds before power was lost.
   Millinix estimated that damage could total at least $1.2 million.
   In northeast Nebraska, cleanup began Sunday in Madison following
a Saturday night tornado that caused widespread damage just hours
after 60 to 80 people had been evacuated from the other side of
town because of flooding, officials said. Accompanying torrential
rains caused widespread flooding throughout the northeast part of
the state.
   Part of the roof of the IBP Inc. meat packing plant in Madison
was torn off by the storm, said a woman who answered the plant's
phone. She wouldn't give her name.
   ``There are trees down everywhere, roofs off of houses all over
town, and gas lines ruptured,'' said Madison police Officer Mike
Bowersox. ``It moved right through the middle of town.''
   There were no reports of deaths or injuries in the community of
2,000 about 100 miles northwest of Omaha.
   Another tornado touched down farther north near O'Neill earlier
Saturday, damaging two farms, in Nebraska's fifth straight day of
severe storms.
   In the southern Minnesota city of Fairmont, heavy rains flooded
streets because sewers were unable to keep up as winds gusted to 60
mph, the weather service said.
   Flooding also hit the basement of Fairmont Community Hospital,
which had to be pumped out by the fire department, said a hospital
supervisor who refused to give her name. The water posed no threat
to patients, she said.
   ``It looked like hurricane winds for a while,'' the supervisor
said. ``It was really bending the trees.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900617-0068 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-90 2236EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-AviancaCrash     06-17 0325</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Avianca Crash,0332</SECOND>
<HEAD>Report: Excessive Air Traffic May Have Contributed to Avianca
Crash</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   On the day an Avianca jet crashed while trying
to land at Kennedy Airport, officials had cleared the airport to
accept more airplanes an hour than a traffic control supervisor
recommended, a newsaper reported Sunday.
   The procedure for controlling the flow of planes into the
airport broke down that day, and may have contributed to the crash
of Avianca Flight 52, Newsday said, citing interviews and documents.
   The fuel-starved Avianca plane crashed in Cove Neck on Long
Island on Jan. 25, killing 73 people, after it had been placed in
holding patterns for more than an hour while flying up the East
Coast from Medellin, Colombia.
   A supervisor at TRACON, the Long Island center that steers
planes into New York-area airports, earlier that day recommended
that just 22 planes an hour be allowed to land at Kennedy, citing
threatening weather. On good-weather days, Kennedy accepts about 60
planes an hour.
   But after consultations with officials, including those at the
Federal Aviation Administration's Central Flow headquarters in
Washington, the landing rate was set at 33 planes an hour,
unidentified sources familiar with the crash investigation told
Newsday.
   ``The flow system fell apart,'' said an unidentified source
familiar with a report by the National Transportation Safety Board.
``It did not work the way it was supposed to work. They
(controllers) were playing a game of catch-up all afternoon. They
never caught up.''
   Investigators said the flow problem alone did not cause the
accident, noting that the Avianca crew did not declare a fuel
emergency, which would have given them immediate landing clearance,
Newsday reported.
   But one investigator, who spoke on condition of anonymity, said
that if a lower landing rate had been set, the Avianca jet might
have been cleared to land earlier.
   NTSB hearings on the crash are scheduled for Wednesday and
Thursday in Melville on Long Island.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900617-0069 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-90 1527EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-TrumpBash     06-17 0489</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Trump Bash,0505</SECOND>
<HEAD>Boardwalk Birthday Party For Trump Day After Missed Bond Payment</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Dollar sign for `s' in headline `DONALD DUCK$!' is cq in 8th
graf. Moved for Sunday AMs on general news wires.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto ACP1 of June 16</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By HENRY STERN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ATLANTIC CITY, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Donald Trump, who turned 44 the day
before he failed to make a critical debt payment, told casino
workers throwing him a huge birthday bash that he's not washed up
in the business world.
   ``Nobody wants to write the positives,'' Trump told about 1,000
cheering employees at his Taj Mahal Casino Resort on Saturday.
``Over the years, I've surprised a lot of people. The largest
surprise is yet to come.''
   Trump, who turned 44 on Thursday, did not specifically mention
his failure Friday to make an estimated $31 million bond payment on
his Trump Castle casino-resort, but criticized news reporters for
focusing on his financial woes.
   News about his debt crunch overshadowed any coverage of gaming
revenues produced last month by the Taj Mahal, which set a citywide
record, he said.
   Trump arrived by limousine flanked by body guards and did not
speak with reporters before climbing onto a stage fronting the
Atlantic Ocean.
   For his birthday, Trump received a chocolate cupcake with a pink
candle and an 8-foot-by-10-foot portrait of himself.
   Those looking for reports in the Taj Mahal of Trump's money
troubles were disappointed. Any newspaper with headlines about
Trump's problems was not for sale inside.
   Outside, newspaper stands on the Boardwalk near the stage were
stocked with New York City papers headlined ``DONALD DUCK$!'' and
``Jilted By Lady Luck.'' Under foggy skies and surrounded by
birthday cards signed by the 13,000 employees at his three casinos,
Trump thanked workers for their loyalty, calling them ``absolutely
fantastic.''
   The Manhattan real estate mogul who also owns the Trump Plaza
Hotel and Casino in Atlantic City left without speaking with
reporters.
   Before he arrived, at least a dozen workers told the crowd that
Trump would weather his problems and they thanked him for providing
jobs. The speeches of support punctuated performances by gyrating
belly dancers, stand-up comedians and a five-piece band.
   Donna Long, a 26-year-old craps table worker at Trump Plaza,
said the rally inspired her.
   ``I feel like this business has its ups and downs,'' she said.
``My boss is a strong man.''
   Trump missed a payment Friday on junk bonds used to finance
Trump Castle and was given a 10-day grace period to make the
payment.
   For the first quarter this year, Trump Castle posted a loss of
$8.4 million, the largest loss among the city's 12 casinos.
   After the Taj Mahal opened in April, Trump Castle's gross gaming
revenue declined 12.3 percent. In May, it fell 17.3 percent
compared to 1989. Despite those losses, the casino was up 0.6
percent in gross gaming revenues for January-May compared to the
first five months of 1989.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900617-0070 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-90 1848EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-PennyFracas     06-17 0600</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Penny Fracas,0619</SECOND>
<HEAD>Economists, Lobbyists Fight Over Whether Pennies Make Sense</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KELLY P. KISSEL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>STATE COLLEGE, Pa. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Frank Orloski didn't believe he was
taking a stand in the debate over whether to eliminate the penny.
But when he looked at the pricing policy of his 36 Quik Mart
convenience stores and service stations, he realized he had already
put his two cents in.
   ``In most circumstances, our prices either end with a nine or a
five or a zero,'' Orloski said last week. ``When we price most of
our merchandise, we either make it so customers get just one penny
back or none. So I guess subconsciously, we do take a stand.''
   The Senate Banking Committee on Wednesday will hear from
economists and retailers on whether the United States should
continue minting a 1-cent piece. If the bill becomes law, cash
transactions would be rounded to the nearest nickel.
   Jim Benfield, a spokesman for a collection of groups whose main
goal is a workable dollar coin, points to people like Orloski in
illustrating the short shrift the penny gets and deserves.
   ``Forty-three percent of all coins required for small
transactions are pennies,'' said Benfield, a spokesman for the
Washington-based Coin Coalition. The figure is based on the minimum
number of coins needed to make every change combination from 1 to
99 cents.
   Members of the Coin Coalition contend the United States loses
$22 million a year in making change. The figure is based on 10
billion cash transactions yearly and a cashier wasting two seconds
per transaction fishing for pennies.
   That adds up to 20 billion seconds, or 5.5 million hours. At $4
an hour for the average clerk, the total loss comes to $22 million.
   Also, if the penny were eliminated, cash register drawers would
have room for the dollar coins the Coin Coalition backs.
   To help his customers, Orloski has small containers of pennies
at the cash registers of half his northeastern Pennsylvania stores,
a trend started by tobacco companies in the 1980s as
point-of-purchase advertising.
   If people don't have exact change, they're encouraged to dip in.
If they have extra change on a future trip, they're encouraged to
return the favor.
   ``They're used. It makes it easier for everyone,'' said Orloski
of Wilkes-Barre.
   Raymond Lombra, a Penn State economist who, like Benfield, will
testify before the banking committee, defends the penny.
   ``The incidence of prices ending in nine or any odd digit is no
accident,'' Lombra said. ``To the average customer, a 99-cent loaf
of bread appears to cost a lot less than a $1 loaf of bread.''
   Any money saved on clerks' wages would be offset if each adult
had one transaction rounded up per day, Lombra said. He said it
would effectively impose a ``rounding tax'' of $3.50 per adult per
year.
   For the nation's 175 million adults, the cost would exceed $600
million. And with government payments tied to the consumer price
index, the rounding tax could increase government spending $1.5
billion in five years, Lombra said.
   ``There's more to it than getting rid of those jars of pennies
that have accumulated in our homes,'' he said.
   The Mint makes more than 10 billion pennies a year, more than
all other U.S. coins combined. Eliminating the penny would
eliminate the argument that the Mint doesn't have the capacity to
produce new dollar coins.
   Pennies are made primarily of zinc, and the zinc industry partly
funds the group that hired Lombra to do research. The new dollar
coins would be mostly copper. The copper industry backs Benfield's
group.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900617-0071 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-17-90 1920EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f BC-Malaysia-US     06-17 0172</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Malaysia-US,0180</SECOND>
<HEAD>Malaysia to Lose 627 Million Dollars If U.S. Ends Trade Privileges</HEAD>
<DATELINE>KUALA LUMPUR, Malaysia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Malaysia will lose about $625
million if the United States withdraws special trade privileges
because of human rights concerns, an official said.
   Deputy Prime Minister Abdul Ghafar Baba on Sunday said Malaysia
receives that amount of quota and tax benefits under current
privileges granted by the United States under the Generalized
System of Preferences.
   The AFL-CIO and some other U.S. organizations have petitioned
the U.S. Trade Representative to withdraw the privileges because of
restrictions on human and labor rights in Malaysia.
   The limits include restrictions on workers in the electronics
industry from forming their own national union.
   Some officials of the Malaysian Trades Union Congress, an
association of trade unions, have backed the AFL-CIO's stand, but
others have opposed it.
   Ghafar told reporters that the Malaysian government will appoint
a lawyer in the United States to defend the privileges and urged
Malaysian trade unions to lobby the U.S. government not to withdraw
them.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
</Collection>
