<Collection>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0001 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 2354EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-NATOSummit     07-01 0883</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-NATO Summit,0907</SECOND>
<HEAD>NATO Leaders Poised To Refocus the Military Alliance</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Sunday AMs report.</NOTE>
<HEAD>With PM-Warsaw Pact, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TERENCE HUNT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP White House Correspondent</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In the tumultuous aftermath of the Cold War,
President Bush and his NATO colleagues gather in London this week
to chart the political and military future of Europe.
   It is a meeting that none of them could have envisioned when
NATO leaders last met 13 months ago to toast the 40th anniversary
of the military alliance _ four decades of keeping the Soviet
threat in check.
   But drastic changes in Eastern Europe have wrought dramatic
alterations in the West's military federation as well.
   The central issue of the meeting, slated for Thursday and
Friday, strikes at the very heart of the Atlantic Alliance.
   How can NATO, after four decades as a military alliance poised
against the Warsaw Pact, transform itself into a mostly political
organization following the collapse of communism in Eastern Europe?
   On a related front, the leaders must deal with Soviet anxieties
about East Germany leaving the Warsaw Pact to join with West
Germany as one nation within NATO. Bush is floating the idea of a
NATO statement of non-aggression toward nations of Eastern and
Central Europe.
   And, at the prompting of France and Germany, they will debate
whether America and her allies should prop up Soviet President
Mikhail S. Gorbachev and his crumbling economy. Bush does not like
the idea of economic aid, but leaders of the 12-member European
Community already have agreed in principle to provide some form of
financial help.
   ``The politics of perestroika helps us all,'' declared West
German Chancellor Helmut Kohl. And French President Francois
Mitterrand said ``Gorbachev's success is in the interest of
everyone.''
   Bush told a news conference on Friday ``It is hard for the
American people to say: Why put X-billions of dollars of money into
the Soviet economy when it's not reformed, when they're spending 18
percent of their gross national product on military and when
they're spending an estimated $5 billion (annually) in Cuba? Some
of our allies might be as concerned about that last point as we
are.''
   The heavy agenda of the NATO meeting will spill over from London
to Houston, where a smaller group of world leaders will meet at the
annual economic summit of the seven largest industrialized nations.
   East-West relations, and particularly the question of a
financial bailout for Moscow, will dominate the three-day Houston
meeting. Trade disputes and environmental problems also will be on
the agenda.
   Japan is expected to urge an easing of sanctions against China,
but the United States opposes that now. An administration official
said Beijing must relax its stand against pro-democracy forces
before any adjustment is warranted.
   But it is the dramatic changes in Europe that will dominate the
London and Houston agendas.
   The Berlin Wall has fallen. Free elections have replaced most of
the totalitarian leaders of Eastern and Central Europe. And Red
Army troops and tanks are preparing to go home.
   Secretary of State James A. Baker III said ``such change brings
in its wake not only great hope but also great uncertainty and some
danger.''
   Bush is concerned that NATO keep up its military guard, albeit
with reduced firepower, as the Soviet threat diminishes. Yet Bush
rejects the idea of getting rid of all nuclear weapons.
   ``I don't want to make Europe safe for conventional war,'' Baker
said, echoing comments by Bush.
   The secretary said NATO would not abandon its longstanding
``flexible response'' strategy of threatening to fire nuclear
weapons first in response to a major Soviet attack with
conventional forces.
   The leaders are expected to order a review to develop a
negotiating position for reducing short-range nuclear weapons in
talks with Moscow. The Kremlin suggests that those negotiations
begin this fall, but NATO insists that they take place only after
an agreement to reduce tanks, artillery and other conventional
forces in Europe.
   NATO chiefs are expected to nudge negotiators from the East and
West to wrap up the slow-moving conventional arms talks and pledge
to make even deeper cuts in a later round of discussions.
   To ease Moscow's fears, West Germany has proposed to keep NATO
forces from what is now East Germany for awhile and to allow the
Red Army forces to remain during that transition period.
   West Germany also is offering Moscow $3 billion in bank credits
and urging the West to contribute funds toward an even bigger
assistance package.
   The funds are viewed by some as a payoff to the Soviets to let
East Germany go. ``This is ransom, but it's a very good way to do
business,'' said Michael Mandelbaum, senior fellow at the Council
on Foreign Relations.
   West Germans credit Gorbachev with kindling Eastern European
reforms, particularly the long-sought goal of German unification,
and they are concerned that a sinking economy might sink Gorbachev,
as well.
   The U.S. view is that it would be a waste of money to pump funds
into an ineffective, state-controlled economy. Baker suggested that
the summit partners in Houston should develop principles and
guidelines for awarding aid to Moscow, but he acknowledged that
some countries may not be satisfied with that.
   ``It may be a case of each country going it's own way,'' Baker
said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0002 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 0045EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-EmergencyLanding     07-01 0153</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Emergency Landing,0157</SECOND>
<HEAD>Northwest Airlines Jet Makes Emergency Landing, No Injuries</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BILLINGS, Mont. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Northwest Airlines jet with 182 people
on board made an emergency landing Saturday at an airport after the
pilot shut down one engine because of an oil leak. There were no
injuries, officials said.
   The 757 was on the way from Minneapolis to Seattle when it
landed safely at Billings Logan International Airport with one
engine, said Tom Binford, assistant airport manager.
   The plane had developed an oil leak in the right engine and
apparently was losing oil pressure when it landed, Binford said.
   The plane landed safely about 4 p.m., he said.
   Passengers went on to Seattle on other flights, a Northwest
spokeswoman said.
   Big jets like the 757 normally don't land in Billings because
there are not enough potential passengers, but the airport's
runways are wide and long enough to accommodate them, Binford said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0003 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 0125EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Fires 2ndLd-Writethru a0622 07-01 0818</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Fires, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0622,0840</SECOND>
<HEAD>President Declares Disaster Areas as Communities Collect
Themselves</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 3 grafs to UPDATE with Santa Barbara fire 100
percent contained. Pick up 4th graf, `Helicopters dropped ...';
SUBS 16th graf to UPDATE with Plumas fire 80 percent contained.</NOTE>
<HEAD>With AM-Days of Fire, Bjt</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos STB1,STB2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RICHARD DE ATLEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SANTA BARBARA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Firefighters surrounded one of
California's most destructive brush fires Saturday, while first
steps were taken to restore ravaged neighborhoods and federal
assistance was offered.
   The 4,900-acre blaze that burned hundreds of homes on the
outskirts of Santa Barbara smoldered northeast of town but was 100
contained. Containment means completion of a fire line.
   ``The golden spike has been driven ... the crews have met nose
to nose,'' Pat Kaunert of the U.S. Forest Service said.
   Helicopters dropped water and ground crews toiled in an area
aptly named Windy Gap as the weather outlook took an unfavorable
turn and hot, dry winds were forecast to return Sunday.
   ``It's a very, very critical portion of the firefight. It cannot
be lost,'' said Santa Barbara County Fire Marshal Michael Bennett.
   In its trail, utility crews went in to restore electricity,
phone and gas service. Residents met to figure out how to cope with
their losses or cleared brush to keep surviving homes safe.
   Gawkers became a problem, jamming streets until California
Highway Patrol officers clamped down, using loudspeakers to order
curiosity seekers out.
   ``We're trying to get Edison and the telephone company in to
restore power and phones,'' said Officer T. Scott. ``They have to
take up the street to do their job and we are getting a lot of
lookie-loos.''
   The fire, which killed a woman, was set about 6 p.m. Wednesday.
Authorities revealed nothing about the arson investigation, but
said the woman's death is considered a homicide.
   In Kennebunkport, Maine, President Bush declared disaster areas
in Santa Barbara and Los Angeles counties. His action makes the
areas eligible for federal grants and loans to assist individuals,
businesses and local governments.
   ``It's a hell of a mess but at least the bureaucracy is in gear,
and going in record time,'' said U.S. Rep. Robert Lagomarsino,
whose district includes Santa Barbara.
   Structural losses in Santa Barbara County were put at $280
million, but county Supervisor Bill Wallace said the value might
top $500 million. So far, 438 homes, 28 apartments, 10 businesses
and four public buildings have burned.
   The declaration for Los Angeles County applied to suburban
Glendale where an arsonist set a fire Wednesday afternoon that
destroyed or damaged 72 homes at a loss of up to $40 million. That
fire was out.
   Elsewhere in the state, a 3,650-acre fire was 90 percent
contained but posed a threat to the community of San Felipe in
northern San Diego County. The arson fire, set Thursday, destroyed
four structures but no homes.
   In Riverside County, a 4,500-acre fire in Cleveland National
Forest was totally contained after burning eight homes. It began
June 19 as a controlled burn but got away. Containment was
predicted for Sunday.
   A new fire was reported in northern California in Plumas
National Forest, where 480 acres burned in heavy timber, the
National Fire Information Center said. Containment was expected
Saturday. The fire was 80 percent contained Saturday, said Tom
Harris, California Department of Forestry spokesman.
   Numerous firefighters suffered injuries in the fires across
Southern California last week. One firefighter died of burns
suffered in a Riverside County blaze, in which another firefighter
was critically burned.
   Santa Barbara's skies were clear of the smoke and soot that
filled them when the fire swept through communities northeast of
town Wednesday night.
   In the hardest-hit areas, people who were burned out began
trying to figure out what to do next.
   The Park Highlands Neighborhood Association met privately in the
home of organizer Douglas Reeves, who said 75 percent of the
neighborhood was destroyed.
   ``We're going to regroup for moral support, but also for any
expertise from the neighborhood to help us,'' said board member
Beverly Mester.
   Elsewhere:
   _Crews created a 47-mile ring of dirt around a fire that
blackened 28,500 acres of pine forest in east-central Arizona. But
officials expected to contain both that fire and a 10,000-acre
blaze in southeastern Arizona with the day.
   _Rugged brush country and hard-to-reach terrain hampered the
efforts Saturday of more than 750 firefighters to control a
5,068-acre blaze in Guadalupe Mountains National Park. Fire
information officer Jim Payne said the blaze was 43 percent
contained Saturday, but officials were unsure when it would be
fully under control.
   _Colorado firefighters began making headway on a series of
lightning-caused wild fires. The largest of the blazes, in
Uncompahgre National Forest, had consumed more than 4,000 acres,
and containment was not expected until Tuesday. The fire was 50
percent contained.
   Brush fires also burned last week in Montana, New Mexico and
Utah.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0004 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 0215EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-MortarExplosion     07-01 0116</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mortar Explosion,0118</SECOND>
<HEAD>Howitzer Shell Explodes Near Home</HEAD>
<DATELINE>FORT LEWIS, Wash. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Howitzer shell fired from Fort Lewis
Army Base landed less than 100 feet from a home Saturday but caused
no injuries, Army officials said.
   Capt. Robert Cravens, a base spokesman, said the shell blew a
crater a couple of feet wide next to a state highway and fragments
tore off several branches from a pine tree in front of the home.
   The shell from a 105mm Howitzer was fired during a demonstration
on the base for ROTC cadets, he said.
   Pierce County sheriff's deputies and military authorities began
an investigation Saturday into why the shell exploded off the base,
Craven said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0005 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 0252EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Philippines-PeaceCorps 3rdLd-Writethru a0655 07-01 0672</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Philippines-Peace Corps, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0655,0693</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<HEAD>U.S. Peace Corps Worker Kidnapped, Embassy Says</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDs: LEADS with 12 grafs to UPDATE with comment from Peace Corps
in Washington, Roman Catholic bishop, identification of missing
volunteer. Pick up 9th graf pvs, `On May...'
^By EILEEN GUERRERO</NOTE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MANILA, Philippines (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The U.S. Embassy said Sunday that
Communist rebels had kidnapped an American Peace Corps volunteer
and were holding him on the central island of Negros.
   Last week, the United States recalled the 261 Peace Corps
volunteers in the Philippines after intelligence reports indicated
that Communist rebels might try to kill or kidnap the volunteers.
   American authorities had said previously that all the volunteers
were accounted for. The volunteers began leaving the Philippines on
Friday.
   U.S. officials identified the missing man as Timothy Swanson,
26, of Cheyenne, Wyo., who had been in the Philippines since
February 1988.
   A retired Roman Catholic bishop said Swanson had been friendly
with New People's Army guerrillas.
   A Peace Corps spokeswoman in Washington, speaking on condition
of anonymity, said ``I have absolutely no information'' about the
kidnapping.
   ``I just can't comment,'' she said. ``It's a very new
situation.''
   Embassy spokesman Stanley Schrager it was believed the volunteer
was abducted June 13. He said the embassy had made unsuccessful
attempts to contact Swanson when the withdrawal of the Peace Corps
volunteers was announced.
   Rev. Antonio Fortich, the retired Roman Catholic bishop of
Negros, said in a telephone interview that Swanson's Filipino wife
told him rebels had taken the volunteer from his home in the
village of Patag. She said she was told to say nothing about the
matter, he said.
   Last week, he said, Swanson's wife received a letter from her
husband saying he was all right and asking her to send some items.
   President Corazon Aquino's press secretary, Tomas Gomez, said he
had no information on the abduction but said it might have been
avoided if the United States had consulted Philippine authorities
on security.
   Schrager said the embassy had dispatched diplomats to the Negros
city of Bacolod. Negros, about 300 miles southeast of Manila, is a
stronghold of the rebel New Peoples Army, which has waged a 21-year
insurgency and seeks to establish a Marxist state.
   On May 29, rebels on Negros kidnapped a Japanese aid worker,
Fumio Mizuno, and are believed holding him in remote mountains near
Bacolod.
   Schrager said the embassy was convinced that the kidnappers were
Communist rebels, but refused to say what contacts, if any, had
been made with the kidnappers.
   The U.S. decision to withdraw the Peace Corps volunteers had
drawn criticism from Philippines officials, who said the United
States was overreacting to the alleged threats.
   The U.S. decision to withdraw the Peace Corps volunteers had
drawn criticism from Philippines officials, who said the United
States was overreacting to the alleged threats.
   On Saturday, Gomez, the president's press secretary, said the
decision to pull out the volunteers could be an obstacle in
forthcoming talks on the future of U.S. bases in the country. The
bases' lease expires in September.
   Gomez said Sunday that U.S. authorities had not shared
information about the reported rebel threat.
   ``They refused to listen to a security briefing,'' Gomez said.
``Maybe if they did that, we could have prevented it.''
   Mrs. Aquino suggested before the kidnapping was dislosed that
U.S. officials should have consulted with Philippines officials
about the withdrawal of the volunteers.
   ``Perhaps had they consulted us, we could have readily
identified the areas that could be classified as high-risk,
low-risk and no risk,'' she told reporters Friday. ``And they could
have remained in the no-risk areas.''
   Communist rebels are believed to have killed eight Americans
since April 1989 but they had made no public threat against the
Peace Corps.
   When the withdrawal was announced last week, U.S. Ambassador
Nicholas Platt said the United States planned to return volunteers
as soon as possible.
   U.S. officials also said the Peace Corps office in Manila would
remain open as a sign that the withdrawal was temporary.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0006 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 0527EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a BC-Mandela     07-01 0456</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Mandela,0469</SECOND>
<HEAD>American Indians Say They Invited Mandela to Return to United
States</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ELISABETH DUNHAM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN FRANCISCO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Nelson Mandela wrapped up his first visit
to the United States by promising to return in October for a look
at the problems of American Indians.
   Two American Indians said they delivered a one-page invitation
and gifts to a Mandela representative as the South African black
nationalist leader arrived at Oakland International Airport for a
rally Saturday.
   The letter outlined several problems and said ``it has been 500
years since the first non-Indians came to this land and began the
destruction of our culture,'' said one of the women, Betty Cooper,
who is the director of the Native American Alcoholism Program in
Oakland.
   Mandela told 58,000 people at Oakland Coliseum that he was
``disturbed'' by what he read. He said he will visit ``the Indian
areas of the country'' for a look at the struggle of American
Indians.
   The rally speech was one of the first occasions Mandela spoke
about the plight of ethnic groups in the United States.
   Chief among the concerns American Indian leaders would like to
tell Mandela about are poverty, unemployment and the lack of health
care plaguing Indians on reservations and in cities, Cooper said.
   ``We told him (in the letter) that we share many of the same
problems of his country and would like to have the opportunity to
share them with him,'' she said.
   Mandela, 71, said he would have looked into the problems before
he completed his eight-city tour in the United States ``but
unfortunately my schedule is very tight. But I can assure the
leaders of the American Indian community that I will return in
October.''
   Cooper and Sally Gallegos, executive director of the
Oakland-based Consortium of United Indian Nations, said they
approached Mandela at the airport but were kept away. They handed
the letter and gifts to a Mandela representative instead.
   The gifts included a sacred blanket and a shawl for Mandela's
wife, Winnie, and some Indian medicine.
   Roger Wilkins, national coordinator of the Mandela tour, said
Mandela already had planned a return visit before he received the
invitation.
   ``The letters from the Native Americans were not the proximate
cause of his decision to come back,'' but since he was coming back
he would look into the issue, Wilkins said.
   Mandela and his wife left Oakland on Saturday for Ireland via
Canada. Earlier Saturday, he took a stroll through downtown Los
Angeles streets. He stopped several times to shake hands with
admirers, including a homeless man in a wheelchair.
   Mandela is touring 14 countries on a round-the-world trip to
raise money for the struggle against apartheid, South Africa's
system of racial segregation.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0007 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 0627EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i BC-Germany     07-01 0473</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Germany,0490</SECOND>
<HEAD>German States Unite Economies, Erase Borders</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARK FRITZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>EAST BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Jubilant East Germans set off fireworks,
drank toasts and flung the currency of their old Communist state
into the air Sunday as the two Germanys united their economies.
   Banks were open for special Sunday hours and thousands of East
Germans lined up to get their new currency, West German marks.
Stores in West Berlin and in border villages in West Germany were
bracing for a crush of shoppers on Monday morning.
   The new treaty merges the two nations into a single economic
entity and sets East Germany on the path to a free-market economy.
Also, all remaining border controls between the two nations were
officially eliminated.
   For many Germans, both East and West, Sunday ranked in
significance with the fall of the Communist government in October
last year and the opening of the Berlin Wall a month later.
   The economic unification marks the effective end of East German
sovereignty and the most important step toward a single Germany.
   The German states now will work on a political treaty that will
likely result in common elections and the creation of a single
nation in December.
   One of the thousands of East Germans who lined up to collect the
new currency was Hans-Joachim Corsalle, 41, who delivers coal for a
living. He withdrew the equivalent of $1,200 in West German marks
from his account to take his family on vacation.
   ``I'm used to standing in line,'' he said. ``Yesterday, for
instance, I waited in line for five hours to get enough gas for the
vacation.''
   Alexandra Meier, 19, saw the day as the beginning of prosperity.
   ``I hope that we'll never have to stand in line again,'' she
said. ``Hopefully, we'll be able to buy whatever we want.''
   East German stores were closed during the weekend as workers
remodeled the former state-owned shops and stocked them with
truckloads of Western products that stand to dominate the newly
opened consumer market.
   East Germany is expected to face widespread joblessness as its
newly independent factories and businesses are forced to compete
with the West.
   Prime Minister Lothar de Maiziere urged optimism and criticized
those who dwell on predictions of massive unemployment.
   ``There will be problems and hardships. But from now on, things
will improve for us,'' he said in remarks prepared for an address
to the nation on Sunday.
   ``Thanks to West Germany, we have opportunities no other East
European country has,'' he said. ``Let's take advantage of them.''
   In an interview with the West German newspaper Bild am Sonntag,
de Maiziere said prosperity will come to East Germany within five
years.
   ``It will happen because it must happen,'' he said. ``Now is the
time to roll up our sleeves and work hard. And we will do that.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0008 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 1122EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--Japan-Landslide     07-01 0106</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Japan-Landslide,0108</SECOND>
<HEAD>Landslide Kills Three People</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A landslide set off by three days of rain crushed a
home and killed three people inside on Sunday in the town of Oita
on Japan's southernmost main island of Kyushu, police said.
   A police official, who spoke on condition of anonymity, said
rescuers found a 59-year-old man, his 58-year-old wife and his
91-year-old mother in the wreckage about two hours after the
landslide hit their house.
   The three were sent to a hospital, but died there later, the
official said.
   Weather officials said more than six inches of rain have fallen
in Oita since Friday.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0009 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 1132EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Germany-Mood Bjt   07-01 0589</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Germany-Mood, Bjt,0611</SECOND>
<HEAD>Sunday Was Unification Day to Many East Germans</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARK FRITZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>EAST BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Germany still has two names, two governments,
two armies. But to many East Germans, Sunday was the day the two
nations became one.
   ``The wall is falling, the borders are open. Now we have West
German money,'' said East Berliner Marita Schulz, 43, after she
withdrew 1,000 new marks from her bank account.
   ``To us, this is it.''
   During the next few months, politicians in both nations will
work out the constitutional mechanics of holding common elections
and forming a single government by year's end.
   But many East Germans saw the opening of the door to Western
commerce and cash as the culmination of last autumn's
demonstrations against Communism, when the hunger for Western
prosperity was an engine that helped drive a revolution.
   The capital was calm and quiet on Sunday, the day the economies
and the social welfare systems of the two German states were
officially merged.
   East Germans did not flock to banks to withdraw their money, and
officials were not predicting a spending spree when stores, now
filled with Western products, opened on Monday.
   Many East Germans planned to make one long-delayed purchase,
such as a car or vacation. But the average amount withdrawn was
only expected to be 800 marks ($490).
   The fear of mass unemployment as East Germany tries to quickly
shift to a free market has brought an air of caution to the country.
   During the day Sunday, East Berlin was positively placid
compared with the raucous, New Year's Eve-style scene that greeted
the coming of the currency union at midnight.
   Thousands of midnight celebrants poured into the city's main
square, Alexanderplatz, where mass demonstrations last fall helped
bring down the former Communist government.
   West Germany's Deutsche Bank, in a publicity stunt that
backfired, opened the doors of its new branch on the square at
midnight to mark the arrival of the currency union.
   It was believed to be the only bank in the country to open
before 8 a.m.
   Thousands of people stood in line, thousands of others crowded
around them and a writhing mass of people packed the door, which
was eventually broken.
   Ambulances took two people away when they became faint.
   The first man in line _ and the first person in East Germany to
withdraw his new West German marks _ was Hans-Joachim Corsalle, 41,
a coal delivery man from East Berlin.
   He took out 2,000 marks ($1,200) and planned to use it to take
his family on vacation. He got a gift basket and a 100-mark bonus
for being the first East German in line.
   ``Never saw a line this long, except for the line at Elvis
Presley's funeral,'' he said.
   Corsalle showed up about four hours before the doors opened in a
modest bid for immortality.
   ``Before I came here I told my wife this is going to enter the
history books,'' he said. ``And it will.''
   Anke Kirchner, 24, a teacher, thought the currency union was the
grimly realistic flipside to the exuberant, idealistic
demonstrations that brought down the Berlin Wall.
   She was at the historic Brandenburg Gate, a symbol of old
Berlin, when the wall was first breached Nov. 9. That celebration
was fun and spontaneous, she said. But the line at Alexanderplatz
was instead a pushing, shoving crush for cash.
   ``I thought it would be nice to come here and be part of the
action,'' she said. ``But this was rather depressing.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0010 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 1154EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r e AM-JVCJazz-StanGetz     07-01 0261</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-JVC Jazz-Stan Getz,0267</SECOND>
<HEAD>Saxophonist Explores Wide Range of Moods</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By WILLIAM GILLEN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   It was the night before the end of the JVC Jazz
Festival, and there was a lot of serious listening going on.
   With good reason.
   Saxophonist Stan Getz delivered the goods Friday night at
Carnegie Hall. He played most of the time he was on stage. He
explored a range of composers and a range of emotions. He played
with horn miked and, on several selections, unamplified.
   He played blues and ballads, rollicking tune, Latin-inflected
ones, too.
   He led, subtly but authoritatively, a superb quartet. On some
numbers, two synthesizers were added, blending easily into the
group's sound.
   Getz, who has fought cancer for a few years, is at the top of
his form; only a handful of saxophonists can play as well or more
expressively.
   The pianist Kenny Barron, whom Getz called ``the other half of
my heart,'' also played forcefully and delicately. Their closing
duet, a Benny Carter tune written for the nation's bicentennial
celebration, topped the evening.
   Also backing Getz up were bassist Alex Blake, who caressed and
thumped his instrument in rousing fashion, and drummer Terri Lynne
Carrington, who played well throughout the night. She took few
solos, but her deft playing supported the group. Playing
synthesizers were Eddie del Barrio and Frank Zottoli.
   The group played selections from a recent album,
``Anniversary,'' as well as from a new one, ``Passionato.'' In
addition, Getz played music composed by, among others, Thad Jones,
Billy Strayhorn, Johnny Mandell.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0011 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 1205EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-DebtorAmerica Bjt   07-01 0863</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Debtor America, Bjt,820</SECOND>
<HEAD>Government Decides It Won't Report All the Economic Bad News</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARTIN CRUTSINGER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The government has come up with a novel
approach for handling bad economic news: it has decided just to
stop reporting it.
   The statistic in question is the annual assessment of America's
global investment standing, which in the past few years has shown
that the United States has gone from being the world's largest
creditor nation to being the largest debtor nation.
   The government says the figure is no longer reliable. Critics
say the Bush administration is playing politics by not releasing it.
   The report for 1989 _ the ``U.S. Net International Investment
Position'' _ was scheduled to be released Monday. But last week,
the government let it be known that because of concern over the
data, the report would not be released this year.
   The Commerce Department's Bureau of Economic Analysis said a
scaled-down version of the investment flows would be made public
but without the key bottom-line figure.
   At the end of 1988, the U.S. debt burden stood at $532.5
billion, up 41 percent from the previous year, the BEA reported
last year.
   That figure reflected the imbalance between what Americans owned
overseas and what foreigners owned in this country.
   Based on information contained in other reports, private
economists expected that America's net debtor position probably
rose by around $110 billion in 1989, pushing America's net debt
close to $650 billion.
   But the BEA release on Monday will not have a figure on
America's net debtor position. There will be enough data provided
on the component parts that make up the figure so that interested
parties will be able to come up with their own unofficial estimate.
But the number will not appear in the report.
   The BEA reasoning: the net debtor number as presently calculated
has so many flaws that it is no longer reliable. BEA officials said
they hoped to have a revamped report with more accurate figures
ready for release in a year.
   Some critics aren't persuaded.
   ``The reason they are not publishing the number is that it shows
the United States in an unfavorable light,'' said Jeff Faux, head
of the Economic Policy Institute, a labor-backed think tank.
   The United States was the world's largest creditor country as
recently as 1983, when it had an investment surplus of $89 billion.
That surplus fell to $3.3 billion in 1984 and disappeared
altogether in 1985, the year the country became a net debtor for
the first time in 71 years.
   The plunge from largest creditor to largest debtor was caused by
the huge merchandise trade deficits the United States piled up
during the 1980s as Americans transferred billions of dollars into
the hands of foreigners to pay for such things as imported cars and
television sets.
   Foreigners now have reinvested those dollars in the United
States in everything from corporate stock and U.S. Treasury bills
to Hollywood movie studios and Iowa farmland.
   That has set off an alarm bells from city hall to Congress over
the ``buying of America,'' with dire warnings that the United
States was in danger of losing control of its economic destiny to
foreigners.
   Allan Young, head of the BEA, denied that he was under any
political pressure from the Bush administration to halt publication
of the net debtor figure.
   ``I am an economic statistician and I decided the number is
inappropriate because of the way it is put together,'' Young said.
``The problem has been increasingly recognized by us and by
others.''
   There have been complaints for a number of years that America's
debtor position was being overstated because the report measured
many of the assets at the historical purchase price.
   That undervalued the worth of U.S. assets in foreign countries,
many of which were purchased decades ago, in comparison with
foreign holdings in the United States, many purchased in the 1980s.
   The BEA is working to produce a report that will give an
up-to-date current value on all assets, both foreign and U.S.
holdings.
   While applauding this effort at statistical consistency, private
economists said they believed the final result will still show the
United States as a net debtor with the amount of debt growing at an
alarming rate.
   Economist C. Fred Bergsten, who is completing a book on
America's net debtor position, said that while the current report
does understate the value of America's holdings overseas, it also
understates foreign holdings in the United States because of errors
in gathering data on foreign ownership.
   ``Our view is that both the asset and liability numbers are
substantially understated and as a result the bottom-line figure is
probably about right,'' said Bergsten, who is head of the Institute
for International Economics, a Washington-based think tank.
   David Wyss, an economist with DRI-McGraw Hill, said the debate
over the exact valuation of the net debtor figure misses the more
important point of America's growing dependence on foreign capital
to run the U.S. economy.
   ``It was a scare number, but people ought to be scared,'' he
said. ``It is a very serious problem and it is one that we aren't
doing anything about.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0012 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 1225EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Soviet-Party Bjt   07-01 0824</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Party, Bjt,0853</SECOND>
<HEAD>Gorbachev Gets Chance at Congress to Sweep Out Old Guard</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ANDREW KATELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Just as Mikhail S. Gorbachev gets his change to
radically overhaul the Communist Party's rusty political machine,
conservatives are challenging his plans to rewrite the rules on who
runs the Soviet Union.
   Conservative delegates will dominate the 28th Communist Party
Congress, which opens Monday, and Gorbachev may not win approval of
the sweeping changes he envisions.
   Some conservatives even are demanding that he leave the top
party job.
   Originally, Gorbachev viewed the congress as a means of cleaning
out the Kremlin's Old Guard, and last year he won approval to hold
the congress a year early to hasten changes.
   Among the main tasks of the congress will be rewriting party
rules to revamp what have traditionally been the most powerful
Soviet institutions.
   The rules affect all 19 million members of the Communist Party,
down to local bosses and the rank and file, and Gorbachev says he
wants changes to give the party a ``second wind.''
   The proposed changes include:
   _ Replacing the general secretary with a party chairman and
first secretary.
   _ Renaming and expanding the party's top body, the Politburo,
thus diluting the power of each member.
   _ Nominating multiple candidates for party jobs.
   _ Restricting elected party officials to two terms.
   The proposed rule changes were published Thursday, and Gorbachev
is expected to offer more details when he opens the congress Monday
with a three-hour report.
   He also wants to press his drive to redirect the party's energy
from managing the economy toward more general policy-setting, and
to transfer management responsibilities to the government.
   But because Gorbachev has introduced a measure of democracy into
the party, he has lost some control over its decisions.
   Conservatives can push their own agenda. Yegor Ligachev, a
Politburo hard-liner, has said renewal ``means the fixing of
boundaries and the cleansing from the party of all those who are
destroying it, who are engaging in a factional, oppositional
struggle and who are participating in anti-socialist movements.''
   The most important proposed rule changes would affect the
249-member Central Committee, the party's policy-making body. The
committee is a bastion of conservative holdovers elected under the
late Leonid I. Brezhnev, party chief from 1964-1982.
   The congress will elect a new Central Committee. Gorbachev had
one previous chance to win control of the committee, at the 1986
congress, but had been in office only 11 months and did not have
enough power.
   Politburo member Lev Zaikov has said 90 percent of the Central
Committee members should be replaced by younger people.
   The Soviet weekly Arguments and Facts analyzed the committee in
February and found that 61 percent of the members were at or beyond
retirement age, 60. More than half the members were elected from
1961 to 1981. Just 29 workers and peasants sit on the committee,
despite the party's claim to represent those those classes.
   There are sizable blocs of military and government ministry
officials, a largely conservative group, and almost half the
members have served more than two terms in central party bodies.
   ``Did the party have any right to expect that it (the Central
Committee) would manifest dynamism, revolutionary energy,
flexibility and exceptional thinking?'' Arguments and Facts asked
rhetorically.
   Gorbachev has called for the congress to trim the committee and
transform it into a standing body that meets almost continuously,
with members chosen from the general pool of party members.
   Under current rules, the Central Committee has no fixed number
of members, meets irregularly and consists of officials
automatically included by virtue of their regular jobs.
   Major changes are also expected in the Politburo. Like the
Central Committee, it also decides policy issues but it meets much
more regularly. It also recommends decisions to the Central
Committee and sometimes makes decisions on its own.
   The Politburo now has 12 full and seven non-voting members.
Gorbachev has eased some conservatives off the body already and
shifted some of its decision-making functions to popularly elected
government bodies.
   Ligachev has complained the Politburo was not consulted about
Gorbachev's controversial plans to shift the Soviet economy to a
market-oriented system or about Soviet policy toward German
unification.
   The draft rules call for the Politburo to be replaced by a
Presidium.
   Although the rules offer no details of its makeup, officials
have said the Presidium would have about 30 members, including the
heads of the Communist parties of the 15 Soviet republics, workers,
peasants, intellectuals, servicemen and party veterans _ to be
elected by the Central Committee.
   The proposed rules also call for splitting the general
secretary's job, now held by Gorbachev, into a chairman, deputy
chairman and first secretary.
   It is not clear which post Gorbachev will seek. But he has made
it clear he wants to retain a top party job in addition to the
national presidency, to which he was elected for a five-year term
in March.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0013 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 1225EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Soviet-Party-Rules     07-01 0414</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Party-Rules,0426</SECOND>
<HEAD>Powers of the Congress: Changes from the Top On Down</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Soviet-Party, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The 28th Communist Party Congress beginning Monday
is the most powerful party forum and is to vote on new rules on the
party's structure and operations. Here are excerpts based on a text
of the proposed rules published Thursday in the party daily Pravda:
   _ The Congress of the CPSU (Communist Party of the Soviet Union)
elects the party Chairman and his deputy.
   _ The Congress elects the Central Committee.
   _ For decisions of political and organizational questions during
the period between congresses, the Central Committee elects from
among its members a Presidium of the party Central Committee.
   _ A plenum of the Central Committee elects from the leaders of
commissions a Secretariat of the Central Committee headed by a
first secretary of the Central Committee.
   _ Elections to party posts are to be conducted by secret ballot,
with no limit on the number of candidates. To win, a candidate must
receive a majority.
   _ Party officials can hold office for no more than two
consecutive terms. The rules don't give the length of terms.
   _ ``Freedom of expression of opinions, juxtaposition of various
views and platforms, open criticism and self-criticism are fostered
in the party.'' But the proposed rules also place limits. ``The
creation of fractions in the CPSU with their own internal
organization and discipline is not allowed, which does not limit
the right of Communists to join together according to platforms in
the course of debate.''
   _ A party member, it says, is free to ``participate in the work
of social organizations and movements whose activity is built on
the basis of the USSR Constitution and does not contradict
socialist ideas.''
   _ ``Communist parties of the union republics are independent. On
the basis of the program and statutes of the CPSU, they work out
their own program and normative documents.''
   _ The rules retain party cells in the armed forces, the KGB and
interior troops.
   _ In a more clear separation of powers, they say: ``Party
organizations and committees don't allow a mixture of functions
with government and management organs, carry out a political line
of the party through Communists working in them.''
   _ Abandoning the party's claim to a monopoly on politics, the
rules say, ``The CPSU, like other social-political organizations,
is fighting for political leadership in society at free elections
to the Soviets of People's Deputies and through other forms.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0014 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 1259EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Germany     07-01 0686</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Germany,0708</SECOND>
<HEAD>Germany Sets off On Bold Adventure, Difficulties Ahead</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Germany-Mood, Bjt</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos BER13,19,28</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KEVIN COSTELLOE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>EAST BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Germany set off on a bold adventure Sunday by
forging a single economy and scrapping internal borders, and
leaders in East and West said difficulties lie ahead.
   East Germans cheered, honked horns and set off fireworks to
welcome their new West German money, which put fancy cars and
vacations to Brazil within reach. Many suddenly had thousands of
dollars' worth of the long-coveted currency.
   At border crossings that once were impenetrable, smiling
families walked, drove and bicycled back and forth without a
policeman in sight.
   More than 200 people were killed as they tried to escape over
the same borders during Communist rule. Erich Honecker, the
hard-line former leader who was toppled last October, is now the
target of a murder probe into the killings.
   In Berlin Sunday, officials reopened eight subway ``ghost
stations'' that hads been shut down by construction of the Berlin
Wall in 1961, another major step toward unifying the city.
   Still, there was sobering talk from officials Sunday, especially
in light of the possibility that East German businesses will start
filing for bankruptcy as early as Monday. Strikes are also expected
as the pressure from Western business builds.
   One East German company, the Elektrowerk Electronicon of Gera,
announced one-quarter of its 5,000 workers would work reduced
shifts beginning Monday.
   There have been predictions that up to 4 million East Germans
could be put out of work as the country struggles to rebuild an
economy ravaged by decades of Communist mismanagement and
inefficiency.
   A majority of the houses were built before the turn of the
century, shortages of materials have left towns in sad disrepair,
and basics like roads and telecommunications are falling apart.
   ``It will take hard work, until we have reached unity and
freedom, prosperity and social balance for all Germans,'' West
German Chancellor Helmut Kohl said in a televised address Sunday
evening.
   ``Many of our compatriots in the German Democratic Republic
(East Germany) will have to get accustomed to new and unfamiliar
living conditions _ and also to a transition period that certainly
won't be easy,'' Kohl added.
   Kohl's address was broadcast by the ZDF and ARD West German
networks, which also reach more than 80 percent of the households
in East Germany.
   Calling for ``national solidarity,'' Kohl also assured fellow
West Germans that they will not be at a disadvantage as the two
nations join.
   There has been increasing concern in West Germany over the high
cost of unification. It will cost hundreds of billions of dollars
to bring East Germany up to full Western standards.
   Also Sunday, West Germany scrapped a 40-year-old program of
government subsidies and handouts for resettlers from East Germany.
   More than half a million East Germans had benefited from the
program since the beginning of last year, culminating in the
dramatic exodus of East Germans to the West last fall.
   East German Prime Minister Lothar de Maiziere delivered his own
television address, in which he urged the country's 16.6 million
people ``not to be led astray by the difficulties, but rather to
recognize and use the opportunities.''
   The prime minister, like his political ally Kohl, said ``the
transition time certainly will not be easy.''
   Many have predicted a ``hot autumn'' as East German workers
return from vacations to find they have no jobs.
   East Germans already are being tempted by everything from
furniture salesman to travel bureaus, including one offering
special tours to Rio de Janeiro and the Caribbean.
   West German Economics Minister Theo Waigel, who traveled to East
Berlin for the start of what he called an ``economic adventure,''
assured East Germans that ``everything is under control.'' He
predicted inflation would not jump.
   His East German counterpart, Finance Minister Walter Romberg,
emphasized there were ``certain risks'' in merging the
world-leading West German economy with its weaker sister.
   Experts predict a huge buying spree would raise inflation.
   Guenther Krause, the chief East German negotiator for the
currency switch, called on his compatriots to ``use their Deutsche
marks cautiously.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0015 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 1301EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Soviet-Hijack     07-01 0358</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Hijack,0370</SECOND>
<HEAD>Report: Hijacker Unwilling To Serve in Soviet Army</HEAD>
<DATELINE>STOCKHOLM, Sweden (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A hijacker forced a Soviet airliner to
land in Stockholm because he did not want to serve in the Soviet
army, the Swedish news agency TT reported Sunday.
   The hijacker said he had a hand grenade and forced the Aeroflot
Tupolev 154 carrying 159 people to land at Stockholm's
international airport Saturday night. No explosives were found,
however, and he gave himself up to the police shortly after the
plane landed, the news agency said.
   The latest in a recent spate of hijackings of Soviet airliners
to Sweden and Finland was carried out by a 19-year-old student from
Leningrad, according to TT.
   Police Inspector Lennart Pettersson said the hijacker made only
one request _ ``to be handed over to Swedish police.''
   During questioning the hijacker said he commandeered the plan to
avoid military service in the Soviet Union and that he would like
to stay in Sweden, TT reported.
   Police had said at first there were four hijackers. Pettersson
said it appeared later that the hijacker traveled in a group of
four, but that only he was involved.
   The airliner was diverted during a domestic flight to Leningrad
from Lvov in the Ukraine. The plane landed at Arlanda airport
outside Stockholm, and the hijacker surrendered two hours later.
   The passengers spent the night near the airport and returned to
the Soviet Union on Sunday, TT said.
   It was the fourth hijacking of a Soviet airliner on a domestic
flight to Finland or Sweden since June 9.
   Each of the three previous hijackings was carried out by young
men who threatened to blow up the plane. No explosives were found.
   In two cases the airliner landed in Finland and the hijacker
asked for political asylum. Finnish authorities have not ruled on
the requests.
   The other hijacker forced a plane to land at Stockholm and said
he acted after a family dispute.
   Depending on the results of a psychiatric inquiry, he could be
deported to the Soviet Union or could be prosecuted in Sweden. If
convicted, he could serve up to four years in jail.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0016 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 1310EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Mongolia     07-01 0561</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mongolia,0577</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mongolian Communist Party Expels, Disciplines Former Leaders</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KATHY WILHELM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Mongolia's ruling Communist Party expelled seven
men who once were among the country's most powerful and feared
officials and disciplined six others, a Chinese report said Sunday.
   China's official Xinhua News Agency quoted the Mongolian party
newspaper Unen as saying those expelled had violated party
discipline and tarnished its reputation.
   All were hard-liners and associates of ousted dictator
Yumjaagiyn Tsedenbal, who for decades maintained tight party
control in all spheres of life in this Soviet-bloc nation.
   Tsedenbal's three decades of rule, ending in 1984, have been
re-evaluated since the start of a democracy movement in December
that produced mass demonstrations, Mongolia's first opposition
parties and a pledge by the Communists to allow free elections and
market reforms.
   The Communist Party, formally called the Mongolian People's
Revolutionary Party, stripped Tsedenbal of his honors this spring
and set up a committee to investigate his surviving associates. The
committee was ordered to report by Saturday, and its findings
apparently led to the expulsions.
   Among the seven was Bugyn Dejid, who was widely feared when he
was in charge of internal party discipline and sat on the party's
decision-making body, the Politburo. He retired in the late 1980s.
   Jambyn Batmonh, who was Mongolia's president and party general
secretary until this spring, was listed among six other officials
put on probation ``because of their failure to fulfil their
duties,'' according to Xinhua.
   The brief report did not explain the terms of probation or the
nature of their failings.
   Batmonh, 64, was prime minister for a decade under Tsedenbal and
succeeded him as party head in 1984, when he also became president.
   In the past two years, however, following the example of the
Soviet Union, Batmonh made tentative moves toward political and
economic reform.
   He stepped down voluntarily from both posts this spring after
months of demonstrations in Ulan Bator by mostly young,
well-educated non-communist activists demanding democracy. The
opposition groups paid him the tribute in April of seeking to
pressure the ruling party to keep Batmonh on as president, saying
they considered him an honest man.
   Also disciplined was Dumaagiyn Sodnom, 56, who resigned in April
as prime minister after six years in office; Sonomyn Luvsangombo, a
former candidate member of the party Politburo who was fired as
head of the State Construction Committee in 1989 amid accusations
of allowing shoddy work; Bat-Ochiryn Altangerel, a former Politburo
member; Paavan Damdin, a former party secretary; and Gelegiyn Adyya.
   Also among the seven expelled were former Politburo members
Tumenbayaryn Ragchaa, Demchigiyn Molomjamts and Damdiny Gombojav;
Bandzragchiyn Lamjav, a former candidate member of Poliburo who
succeeded Dejid in handling party discipline.
   All had retired from their party and government posts in the
past few years.
   Mongolia is preparing to hold its first multiparty elections
ever July 29, with five non-Communist parties contesting the
Communists' monopoly on power.
   The opposition groups have complained in recent weeks, however,
that local election commissions were set up without opposition
participation, that the ruling party continues to receive state
funds and that the media remains under ruling party control.
   The government has rejected their demand that international
observers be allowed to attend the elections.
   Mongolia, a landlocked nation of herdsmen, has been ruled by the
Communists since they seized power with Soviet help in 1921.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0017 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 1312EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Brazil-BusCrash     07-01 0098</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brazil-Bus Crash,0098</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bus Crash Kills 16 in Southeastern Brazil</HEAD>
<DATELINE>RIO DE JANEIRO, Brazil (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A bus crowded with people heading
for a religious festival veered off a road and plunged down a
150-foot hill, killing 16 people and injuring 28, news reports said
Sunday.
   The newspaper O Globo said the accident took place Saturday when
the bus crashed near the city of Jacarei, 230 miles southeast of
Rio.
   Survivors said the accident took place because of low visibility
caused by heavy fog, the newspaper reported.
   Police officials said no report was available on the accident.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0018 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 1319EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-LivingWills Bjt   07-01 0813</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Living Wills, Bjt,790</SECOND>
<HEAD>RETRANSMITTING a0688 to DELETE extraneous matter at bottom</HEAD>
<HEAD>Thinking of a `Living Will'? Get Advice and Be Specific</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DEBORAH MESCE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Since the Supreme Court's right-to-die ruling,
Americans by the thousands have begun heeding the advice of
physicians, lawyers and death-with-dignity advocates to draft a
``living will.''
   ``We've had to get volunteers to help us man the phone lines,''
said Doron Weber, a spokesman for the Society for the Right to Die.
``That's the magic word right now _ living wills.''
   Living wills allow people to spell out in writing how much
medical care _ if any _ they would like to have in the event they
ever become critically or terminally ill and are unable to speak
for themselves.
   The urgency of such advance planning was brought home last week
when the Supreme Court barred the parents of a 32-year-old comatose
woman, Nancy Cruzan, from ordering removal of the feeding tube that
is keeping her alive.
   Doctors say the Missouri woman is irreversibly unconscious, in a
permanent vegetative state that could last for years. Her parents
wanted to have her feeding tube removed, but the court said no.
   The court said states may block family members from ending the
lives of permanently comatose relatives who have not made their
wishes known. The justices indirectly supported living wills by
saying the Constitution guarantees a competent person a right to
refuse medical treatment.
   ``This decision affects just about every member of our
society,'' Weber said.
   The American Medical Association estimates that 70 percent of
all people will be involved in some way at some time in a decision
on whether to prolong or terminate life support.
   The Society for the Right to Die has become a sort of national
clearinghouse for living wills.
   ``We're getting thousands of calls every day, the vast majority
from individuals who want living wills,'' Weber said in an
interview last week.
   Interest in the issue was lively even before the ruling in the
Cruzan case. Before last week's decision, the American Association
of Retired Persons had received more than 100,000 requests for its
booklet ``Health Care Powers of Attorney,'' produced by the
American Bar Association.
   The Society for the Right to Die distributes the appropriate
forms for the 41 states and the District of Columbia that have
living-will laws.
   For people in the nine states that don't have a law, the society
has general forms. Those states are Massachusetts, Michigan,
Nebraska, New Jersey, New York, Ohio, Pennsylvania, Rhode Island
and South Dakota.
   For people in all states, however, the society advises that
individuals be as specific as possible.
   ``It's a very important document,'' Weber said. ``You should say
everything you want to say, whatever your personal instructions
are. ... You have to make your wishes known.''
   The American Bar Association approves of living wills, but
recommends that people also give someone they trust what is called
durable health care power of attorney.
   This is done in a written document and gives the person named
the authority to make health care decisions for an individual in
the event that individual becomes unable to speak for himself or
herself.
   This allows people to cover more contingencies than may be
possible to outline in a living will, and to provide more guidance
for decision-making.
   ``Medical technology changes by the year, if not by the
minute,'' said Nancy Coleman, director of the ABA's Commission on
the Legal Problems of the Elderly.
   A living will provides a certain measure of protection for your
wishes to be carried out, she said, but it doesn't give anyone any
alternative decision-making for you.
   ``If you forgot something or something new (life-prolonging
medical technology) is available that you didn't anticipate ... you
could be in Nancy Cruzan's situation,'' she said.
   While all states and the District of Columbia recognize durable
power of attorney, some states also recognize this power
specifically for health care decisions.
   But the interpretation of most attorneys who practice in these
areas is that you can use durable power of attorney for most health
care decision-making, she said.
   Whether in a living will or in designating power of attorney,
Coleman advises people to ``say whatever they want to say as
strongly as possible.''
   When drafted, these documents should be given to family members,
friends, physicians, religious advisers and ``anyone else you would
want to speak on your behalf,'' Weber said.
   ``You don't want to stash it away in a safe deposit box,'' he
said.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Forms can be obtained from the Society for the Right to Die and
Concern for Dying by writing to them at 250 West 57th Street, New
York, N.Y. 10107.
   The American Association for Retired Persons' booklet ``Health
Care Powers of Attorney'' can be obtained by writing to AARP
Fulfillment, Stock No. D13895, 1909 K Street, N.W., Washington,
D.C. 20049
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0019 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 1334EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brite-July4Survey     07-01 0363</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brite-July 4 Survey,0375</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tots Think Barbara Bush Sewed The American Flag</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KAREN SCHWARTZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PAWTUCKET, R.I. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Fourth of July celebrates somebody's
birthday, George Washington is ``nice and he's dead'' and the
original Stars and Stripes flag was sewn by Barbara Bush, according
to a poll of youngsters.
   More children age 4 to 6 think Mrs. Bush was the flag's
seamstress than Betsy Ross, with 29 percent casting a vote for the
president's wife and 15 percent going with the real McCoy.
   Hoping for a story like this, a toy company surveyed 151
children at day-care centers in Boston, Atlanta, Cincinnati, Denver
and Los Angeles to find out how much they knew about Independence
Day.
   The poll was taken by the Pawtucket-based toymaker Playskool Inc.
   When asked from whom the United States gained independence, the
kids gave answers ranging from ``the King,'' at 56 percent, to the
Indians, 19 percent, the Pilgrims, 18 percent, the Russians, 5
percent, the British, 2 percent, and the Italians, 1 percent.
   When questioned about the meaning of the Fourth of July, 18
percent of the youngsters, who were polled in February, said it was
a holiday _ but weren't sure which one.
   ``It's somebody's birthday,'' said a 4-year-old boy from Denver.
   ``It means celebrating the presidents and they're all very
special,'' said a 6-year-old girl from Boston.
   More than anything else, the children thought July 4 had
something to do with fireworks. While 21 percent said that, none
knew the holiday commemorates the adoption of the Declaration of
Independence.
   Fifty-one percent knew George Washington had something to do
with the presidency, and two kids from Atlanta knew he appears on
money, but others drew their own conclusions.
   A 6-year-old boy from Cincinnati thought Washington was a statue.
   ``He's nice and he's dead,'' said a 5-year-old boy from
Cincinnati.
   ``He was a captain who fights the bad guys,'' said a boy, 5,
from Los Angeles.
   In fact, it was Washington who on Jan. 2, 1776, raised the first
American flag, in Cambridge, Mass. Some kids gave him more credit
than was due _ 3 percent said he made the first flag.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0020 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 1339EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Manchester-By-The-Sea     07-01 0186</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Manchester-By-The-Sea,0192</SECOND>
<HEAD>Manchester, Mass., Officially Becomes Manchester-By-The-Sea</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   MANCHESTER-BY-THE-SEA, Mass. (AP) _ It's official. Manchester
has become Manchester-By-The-Sea, in a sometimes controversial
effort to distinguish it from the four other New England
Manchesters and 18 other Manchesters in the United States.
   As of 12:01 a.m. Saturday, the town's nickname became its
official title, the first name change for a Massachusetts town
since 1907.
   Proponents of the name change hoped to distinguish the town,
population 6,000, from Manchester, N.H., but opponents said it's a
pretentious gesture. Town residents voted 658-625 in favor of the
change, which the Legislature had previously approved.
   The municipality was first incorporated in 1645.
   The town's stationery won't be updated until the present stock
is exhausted. A private collection has been taken up to try to foot
the $600 for changing the town's seal.
   Officials know of no plans to change signs on Route 127 and 128
that run through the town, and the local U.S. Post Office will
remain the same, the Boston Sunday Globe reported.
   However, town T-shirt sellers have happily altered their wares
and are looking forward to increased sales.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0021 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 1413EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Yugoslavia     07-01 0522</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Yugoslavia,0539</SECOND>
<HEAD>Serbia Holds Referendum On Multiparty Elections</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SLOBODAN LEKIC</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BELGRADE, Yugoslavia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   People in Yugoslavia's largest
republic voted Sunday on whether to hold free elections before
adoption of a new constitution that would give it more power over a
southern province.
   Turnout was light on a hot Sunday morning in Belgrade, which
serves as both the seat of the federal government and the capital
of the Serbian republic. Voting will continue Monday, and results
are to be released Tuesday.
   Serbian Communist President Slobodan Milosevic announced the
referendum June 25 for Serbia, the largest of Yugoslavia's six
republics.
   It was preceded by a barrage of propaganda in the state media
calling on voters to support a delay in free elections until after
enactment of a new constitution, for which no date has been set.
   Serbia's Communist authorities in the past have rejected
Western-style pluralism.
   The northern Yugoslav republics of Slovenia and Croatia, in
contrast, held the first free elections this spring in 45 years for
local legislatures. Both elections were won by center-right
parties, which trounced the Communist parties that called the
elections.
   Yugoslavia's other three republics are scheduled to hold free
elections later this year.
   Milosevic claims that multiparty elections cannot be held in his
republic because ethnic Albanians, who make up 90 percent of the
1.7 million inhabitants of Serbia's southern Kosovo province, will
vote for separatists advocating the region's secession.
   At least 60 ethnic Albanian protesters have been killed since
February 1989, when the republic set strict limits on Kosovo's
autonomy and demonstrations resulted.
   The possible elimination of the Kosovo parliament through a new
constitution would make ethnic Albanians a small minority in the
Serbian parliament. Ethnic Albanians do not necessarily want
independence, but do want their previous partial autonomy restored.
   The ethnic Albanians seek restoration of the broader autonomy
they enjoyed under a 1974 constitution that was amended in March
1989. Serbia said the changes were needed to protect the Serbian
minority in Kosovo from alleged harassment by ethnic Albanians.
   The Serbian parliament previously adopted unspecified new powers
to amend measures passed by Kosovo's administration in a further
extension of Serbian control.
   Serbian Communists claim full ethnic Albanian autonomy is the
first step toward Kosovo seceding from Yugoslavia and joining
neighboring Albania.
   A coalition of Serbian opposition parties, described as
``national traitors'' by the government media, have insisted
Kosovo's problems have been caused by the ruling Communists and
that they can only be resolved after a democratically elected
government takes over in Serbia.
   Opposition leaders were attacked and beaten by police when they
tried to stage a protest in front of Belgrade Television to demand
equal access to the media.
   No opposition representatives were present at any of the voting
stations visited by a reporter, but Communist officials claimed
they would be allowed to observe the proceedings if they wished.
   Ethnic Albanian leaders in Kosovo have called on people in
Kosovo to boycott the referendum.
   ``Nothing can be decided without Albanians in Kosovo anymore,''
said Azem Vlasi, a former Communist leader in the province, said in
an interview with the Nedelja weekly.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0022 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 1415EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Israel-Soviets     07-01 0472</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel-Soviets,0487</SECOND>
<HEAD>Cabinet Approves `Emergency Regulations' to Speed Housing</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GWEN ACKERMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Cabinet on Sunday approved a request by
Housing Minister Ariel Sharon for ``emergency regulations'' to
speed the construction of homes in Israel for Soviet immigrants.
   Sharon, who also serves as coordinator of immigration, had
requested the measure to allow the purchase of 3,000 prefabricated
houses, either locally or abroad.
   The prefabricated units are to be set up near nine Israeli
towns, most in the Galilee in the north and in the southern Negev
desert.
   The measure, which is to last for three months, is to be debated
Monday by the Parliament. The Likud bloc of Prime Minister Yitzhak
Shamir, to which Sharon belongs, commands a majority in the
Parliament.
   Israeli contractors have opposed the move, arguing that it will
hurt the local construction industry.
   Sharon has said Israel will need to build 7,000 new housing
units a month to accommodate the flood of Soviet immigrants that
began in the spring of 1989 after the Soviet Union eased exit
permits. Israel's current rate of construction is about 1,660 units
a month.
   A shortage of housing has sent rents skyrocketing and sparked
protests by young Israelis, who say they are being priced out of
the market.
   Sharon's request for emergency regulations has stirred fear
among some politicians that he may try to assume powers currently
delegated to municipal planning councils and zoning boards.
   As defense minister, Sharon led the 1982 Israeli invasion of
Lebanon and was later charged by critics with giving incomplete
information on his military plans to the government.
   The government's legal adviser, State Attorney Yosef Harish,
approved the Cabinet decision only after he was saw the motion
would carry, according to Justice Ministry spokeswoman Eti Eshed.
   ``Harish doesn't think emergency regulations are needed at this
point,'' she said. ``But Sharon convinced the others, and Harish
decided not to oppose the decision.''
   More than 63,000 Soviet Jews have arrived since 1989, and a
total of 150,000 are expected this year.
   Also Sunday, Parliament member Yossi Sarid of the left-wing
Citizens Rights Movement charged that one-tenth of
government-funded construction was going to the occupied West Bank
and Gaza Strip. He did not include funding for Arab east Jerusalem,
which Israel annexed after its capture from Jordan in the 1967
Middle East war.
   Sarid noted there has been widespread criticism in the United
States and Europe to Israel's continued settlement of Jews in the
occupied lands.
   Israeli officials, in response to the criticism, have pledged
that Soviet immigrants will not be directed to the territories.
   ``This is another attempt to lie to the world,'' said Moshe
Horovitz, a spokesman for Sarid's party.
   ``The policy doesn't direct immigrants to the territories, but
people are thrown there without choice because they have nowhere
else to live.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0023 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 1416EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BlackJustice     07-01 0774</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Black Justice,0795</SECOND>
<HEAD>Florida's First Black Chief Justice Targeted by Abortion Foes</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CURT ANDERSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TALLAHASSEE, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Abortion foes are hoping to get
Florida's first black Supreme Court chief justice off the bench in
the November elections because of their disagreement with his
rulings on abortion.
   Leander Shaw officially became the second black chief jurist of
a state's Supreme Court on Sunday. The first black state chief
justice was Pennsylvania's Robert Nix, who has held his state's
highest judicial post for 6{ years.
   The collision between two of society's hottest issues, race and
abortion, isn't lost on the 59-year-old Shaw. But he doubts Florida
Right to Life and other anti-abortion groups are trying to defeat
him because he is black.
   ``I think those who want to defeat me have set Florida up as a
bellwether state,'' said Shaw.
   ``I think they would have picked out any justice on this court
running at this particular time,'' he said. ``It works out that if
they needed a lightning rod, I was going to be it.''
   Shaw, who has served on the court seven years, was named to a
two-year term as chief justice by a vote of his fellow justices in
March. The term began Sunday.
   He is the target of anti-abortion groups because of a decision
he wrote in October. The ruling invalidating a state law that
prohibited single minors from obtaining abortions without
permission of their parents, a legal guardian or a judge. But the
ruling went much further, saying that the right-to-privacy
amendment to the state Constitution meant that government may not
interfere in abortion decisions.
   The justices split 4-3 on the parental permission ruling, and
voted 6-1 in the ruling that the privacy amendment applied to the
abortion issue.
   The ruling came only days before the Florida Legislature met to
consider a number of anti-abortion bills proposed by Republican
Gov. Bob Martinez. The session ended with the resounding defeat of
Martinez's legislation as thousands protested outside the Capitol.
   The disappointing loss led anti-abortion forces to train their
guns on Shaw, the only one of the justices to face a retention
election this year.
   Under Florida law, Supreme Court justices are initially
appointed by the governor, but at six-year intervals voters get to
decide whether to retain them. No Supreme Court justice has been
ousted since the merit retention system began in 1974, but if Shaw
loses it would give Martinez a chance to appoint a conservative
replacement.
   That's the message going out at churches, conservative political
gatherings and anywhere else people opposed to abortion can be
found, said Florida Right to Life President Ken Connor.
   ``All of this effort to elect a pro-life governor will go for
naught if we don't have people on the court who reflect values such
as the sanctity of the family,'' said Connor.
   He said Shaw has shown an ``utter disregard for the right to
life, and an utter disregard for the rights of parents over their
children. He is a classic judicial activist who is making the law,
rather than interpreting the law.''
   The sophisticated organization and fervor of the anti-abortion
forces has Shaw worried. He said last week that he will probably
spend $300,000 to keep his seat.
   ``They would like to beat me, because that would certainly give
them something to take around the country and say, `look what we
did in Florida _ we unseated a Supreme Court justice,''' he said.
``I take them very seriously. I think they are sincere. It is a
very visceral issue with them.''
   But Shaw, who has five children of his own and has been involved
in youth groups, rejects the charge that he is anti-family. He said
voters must look at his overall performance, not just one issue,
and said groups that pressure judges to vote their way on one issue
or face ouster are abusing the merit system.
   Martinez himself has stayed on the sidelines in the Shaw
campaign. When Shaw's selection as chief justice was made in March,
the governor had nothing but praise, saying it was a ``testament to
the progress Florida has made over the years in providing equal
opportunity for all its citizens.''
   Shaw agreed that progress has been made in race relations
despite occasional flare-ups, particularly in Miami with its
volatile mixture of Hispanics and blacks.
   ``The ethnic diversity of Florida necessitates that you have to
make progress (in race relations) or destroy yourself,'' Shaw said.
``I hope I can be a positive role model. I think people could look
at me and say `Well, Leander Shaw did it, I can do it too.'''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0024 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 1420EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Zambia     07-01 0506</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Zambia,0523</SECOND>
<HEAD>Capital Quiet following Coup Attempt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MELINDA HAM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LUSAKA, Zambia(AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Paramilitary police and army troops
patrolled the streets of Lusaka Sunday, a day after mutinous
soldiers mounted an aborted coup to oust President Kenneth Kaunda.
   Authorities insisted repeatedly that no one was hurt Saturday,
but diplomats and witnesses said at least three civilians were shot
dead by guards near Kaunda's residence after they joined crowds
celebrating his reported overthrow.
   The capital and other cities and towns were calm Sunday after
five days of student-led rioting over food price increases. The
students also demanded a return to Western-style democracy.
   Kaunda, 67, flew back to Lusaka Saturday night from the central
copperbelt province city of Ndola facing the gravest political
crisis since he led the British colony of Northern Rhodesia to
independence in 1964 with promises of a better life for all.
   Before he left Ndola, a visibly shaken Kaunda said he would not
budge on his decision last month to more than double the price of
corn meal, a staple.
   He also said he would consult the central committee of the
United National Independence Party, the only legal political
movement in Zambia since a one-party state was imposed in 1972, on
the fate of the coup plotters.
   Kaunda indicated he might act more harshly than in the past when
his foes have been detained, imprisoned or rebuked.
   ``I'm beginning to ask myself whether we have been right in
this, whether we shouldn't take a different stance,'' he said.
   An army lieutenant who identified himself as Mwamba Luchembe of
the Signals Corps was detained by soldiers at dawn Saturday after
making several broadcasts on state radio that Kaunda had been
toppled in a coup.
   Luchembe was being held at Chamba Valley high security prison
outside Lusaka, government sources said. He was identified as a
member of the Bembas, Zambia's biggest tribe, from the northern
Luapula province near the border with Zaire.
   Bembas wield most economic, political and military power, but
like other Zambians many have become disenchanted with rising
unemployment, steep inflation and top-level corruption.
   About the same time as the broadcast, troops in armored
personnel carriers cruised Lusaka's streets with loudspeakers
saying a new president had been installed.
   While Kaunda has referred to ``coup plotters'' since then,
official spokesmen and the government media have reported only two
arrests.
   In addition to Luchembe, police in Ndola also placed in custody
anti-government activist Peter Bwalya for allegedly organizing
protests after the broadcasts.
   State television reported that at least two other soldiers were
with Luchembe when he made the announcements. Their fate was not
known.
   At least five fellow officers were detained later Saturday,
security sources told The Associated Press. They spoke on condition
of anonymity and their report could not be independently confirmed.
   The failed coup followed five days of the bloodiest urban
violence in Zambia's history, triggered last Monday by student
rioting.
   At least 23 people were slain, most of them looters, according
to officials. At least 34 students were detained.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0025 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 1427EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Israel-Bomb 1stLd-Writethru a0693 07-01 0305</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel-Bomb, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0693,0311</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bomb Explodes At Crowded Pedestrian Mall In Jerusalem</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 8 grafs to UPDATE with three slightly wounded,
arrests, CORRECTS site of May 28 explosion to Mahane Yehuda market.
Pick up 7th graf pvs, `That attack...'</NOTE>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A bomb exploded Sunday near a crowded
pedestrian mall in downtown Jerusalem, slightly wounding at least
three people, police said.
   Police said the device was apparently a letter bomb that
exploded inside a staircase mailbox just off Jerusalem's central
Ben-Yehuda shopping mall.
   Officials announced a search for two Palestinian youths seen
fleeing the area just after the blast. At least 11 other Arabs were
rounded up and taken away in a police van, witnesses said.
   Israel army radio said police prevented angry Israelis from
attacking the detainees.
   There was no immediate claim of responsibility for the bombing.
   ``I left a bookstore with my wife and grandchildren. Suddenly we
heard an explosion inside a staircase at a distance of about eight,
10 meters (yards)... My granddaughter was slightly hurt in the
chest,'' Modechai Ativ, a Jerusalem resident, said on Israel radio.
   A series of homemade pipe bombs have been discovered in
Jerusalem in recent days. The last bomb attack in the city was on
June 26 when a bomb that went off at a bus station lightly injured
two Israeli women.
   In the most serious of recent attacks, an Israeli man was killed
and nine people were injured in an explosion at the Mahane Yehuda
market in Jerusalem on May 28.
   That attack was claimed by two Palestinian groups, the
fundamentalist Islamic Jihad and the Syrian-backed dissident
Palestine Liberation Organization faction headed by Col. Said Mousa.
   On June 23, a bomb exploded in a trash can at Ein-Gedi beach on
the Dead Sea, wounding four people, including two German tourists.

</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0026 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 1431EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-US-Trade     07-01 0428</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-US-Trade,390</SECOND>
<HEAD>West Germany Regains Export Leadership Over U.S.</HEAD>
<NOTE>For Release After 6:30 p.m. EDT. Time Set by source.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By CARL HARTMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   West Germany was the world's biggest exporter
for the first three months of 1990, regaining its leadership over
the United States, the International Monetary Fund reported Sunday.
   West Germany increased its exports to $99.8 billion, up more
than 18 percent over the first quarter of last year. The U.S.
increase of nearly 10 percent brought its total to $97.2 billion.
   In 1989, the United States regained first place with $364
billion worth of exports compared to West Germany's $341 billion.
West Germany first forged ahead in 1986.
   Experts say the economic unification of West Germany and East
Germany, which officially began Sunday, could put the united
Germany ahead of the U.S. as the world's biggest exporter for years
to come. The fund gave no figures for East Germany, which is not
among its 151 member countries.
   Japan trailed in a distant third place with $274 billion worth
of exports for 1989 and $68 billion for the first quarter of this
year.
   The United States remained by far the world's biggest importer,
with $125 billion in foreign-made goods coming into the country in
the first quarter of the year. That compared with $118 billion a
year earlier. West Germany's imports also increased, to $78 billion
from $65 billion.
   West Germany had a $22 billion surplus of exports over imports
for the quarter, compared with a U.S. deficit of $28 billion.
Japan, striving to reduce complaints about its big export surplus,
was the only one of the seven major industrial countries to report
a drop in exports for the quarter. It still had a $12 billion
surplus for the period, second only to West Germany's.
   The 22 countries that the fund classifies as industrial had a
total deficit of $32 billion in trade with the rest of the world
for the first quarter of 1990. That was up from $24 billion in the
first quarter of 1989.
   Adding up annual surpluses and deficits for the first time, the
fund reported that the industrial countries had an aggregate trade
deficit with the rest of the world in 1989 of $110 billion, up from
$80 billion in 1988.
   Italy, along with West Germany, reported the most rapid gains in
both imports and exports for the quarter. But because of changes in
exchange rates, Italy increased its deficit to $7.3 billion for the
quarter, compared with $7.1 billion in the first quarter of 1989.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0027 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 1437EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Lithuania     07-01 0564</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lithuania,0581</SECOND>
<HEAD>Lithuania's Oil Refinery Back in Business As Blockade Eased</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Lithuania's sole oil refinery was back in
operation Sunday after the Kremlin eased its embargo on the Baltic
republic.
   Lidia Cheblakova, a duty officer, said the Mazhiekiai Refinery
in northwestern Lithuania was receiving 25,000 tons of oil a day,
compared to the normal, pre-embargo level of 45,000.
   Soviet officials resumed pumping oil to Lithuania on Saturday,
starting to fulfill its promise to lift the 10-week blockade in
return for a moratorium on the republic's declaration of
independence.
   The Soviet government cut off shipments of all oil, most natural
gas and numerous other items to Lithuania on April 18 in attempt to
force it to rescind its March 11 declaration of independence.
   The Lithuanian parliament accepted a compromise Friday that
traded a 100-day moratorium on the declaration for an immediate end
to the blockade and the start of negotiations.
   The subject of Lithuania's came up in Pope John Paul II's
prayers in Rome on Sunday. While he didn't comment on the dispute
over independence, the pontiff prayed that conditions would improve
for Lithuanian Catholics and that there would be a ``victory of the
cross'' in the Soviet republic.
   Ms. Cheblakova said in a telephone interview the full supply of
oil will be resumed as soon as the refinery is ready to receive it.
   Just one of Mazhiekiai's two plants was operating because there
are not enough workers available. Many were released on vacation or
laid off when the blockade started, she said.
   Officials said refined oil from the Mazhiekiai plant, the only
one in Lithuania, would not reach consumers for at least two weeks
for technical reasons. It refines about 12 million tons of
petroleum products a year, a quarter of it used in Lithuania.
   The refinery employs 2,000 people, who were thrown out of work
by the cutoff. The plant processed its last oil April 23 as the
blockade exhausted reserves that came from the single pipeline
feeding the plant from the Russian city of Polotsk.
   The huge plant provided much of the gasoline and industrial fuel
for Lithuania, Latvia, Estonia, the Russian city of Kaliningrad and
parts of Byelorussia before it shut down for lack of oil.
   Lithuania and its 3.8 million people are entirely dependent upon
the Soviet Union for its oil and gas, which it receives at highly
subsidized prices.
   Lithuania and its Baltic neighbors, Latvia and Estonia, were
independent from Moscow between the two world wars, but were
forcibly absorbed back into the Soviet Union by Josef Stalin in
1940.
   All three are seeking to regain their independence, although
Estonia and Latvia have taken a slower approach to separation from
the Soviet Union than Lithuania.
   In his homily, the pope noted that Lithuanian bishops recently
celebrated a special Mass in which ``they implored the crucified
Christ to shorten the days of difficult testing to which Lithuanian
believers continue to be subjected.''
   ``May the Lord give them this grace, assuring the victory of the
cross,'' the Polish-born pope said.
   The pontiff, speaking at a Mass at the Lithuanian college of San
Casimiro in Rome, said the cross ``has become the special symbol of
the Lithuanians: of the people, of the families, of the communities
and all the society.''
   Soviet authorities in the past have refused John Paul permission
to travel to Lithuania, which is overwhelmingly Catholic.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0028 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 1450EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Mandela Bjt   07-01 0642</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mandela, Bjt,0662</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mandela Gets Ecstatic Irish Welcome; Says Sanctions Must Stay</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARCUS ELIASON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DUBLIN, Ireland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Nelson Mandela arrived to a rapturous
Irish welcome Sunday, urging that sanctions against South Africa be
kept up so that apartheid is ended ``not tomorrow but now.''
   The Irish, staunch supporters of the black South African leader,
thronged Dawson Street in the center of the capital as Mandela
arrived from the United States for a ceremony giving him the
freedom of Dublin.
   It was a highly symbolic moment at the Mansion House, seat of
the city's government. Dublin made Mandela an honorary citizen two
years ago, the first capital city to do so, but had to wait until
now for him to get out of prison and accept the honor.
   For the Irish, already geared up to give an ecstatic welcome to
their national soccer team on its return from the World Cup in
Italy, it was a doubly joyous day.
   ``Is this not the greatest day Ireland has ever seen?'' yelled
the master of ceremonies to the crowd outside the Mansion House.
``A double bill _ the Irish team coming home and Nelson Mandela
coming to the Mansion House!''
   Mandela, seated beside his wife, Winnie, inside the Mansion
House, quickly picked up the spirit.
   ``Congratulations to your wonderful football team,'' he said to
applause from the dignitaries.
   ``I have a hope, please allow me to say so, that they did so
magnificently because they knew that in spirit I was amongst them.''
   Underdog Ireland, which had never before qualified for the World
Cup, got to the quarterfinals before losing to Italy 1-0 Saturday.
   Mandela immediately called for the maintenance of sanctions, a
stance likely to win support here but face opposition in Britain,
his next stop. Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher wants sanctions
lifted in recognition of South African President F. W. de Klerk's
reforms, which included releasing Mandela after 27 years in prison.
   At a European Community summit last week, Ireland, which holds
the EC presidency, helped make sure the community's embargo on
imports of South African coal, steel and gold coins remains firm.
   In his speech, Mandela acknowledged de Klerk's reforms, but
added:
   ``Apartheid still remains in place. It is our common duty and
responsibility to ensure that apartheid is ended, not tomorrow but
now. ... We call for the maintenance of sanctions against South
Africa, and solidarity with our struggle.''
   At the airport, he ignored a question about his attitude to the
Irish Republican Army, which is fighting to end British rule in
Northern Ireland and is outlawed in both Ireland and Britain.
   The IRA's legal political wing, Sinn Fein, strongly supports
Mandela.
   Among the guests at the Mansion House was Paul Hill, one of four
Irish people who served more than 14 years in a British prison
until a judge freed them this year, accepting that they had been
wrongly convicted.
   Hill said he felt a comradeship with Mandela, who was jailed for
plotting the violent overthrow of the white regime. ``It was the
affinity of a prisoner with another prisoner who was enduring what
I was enduring,'' he told a reporter.
   Ireland gained its niche in the annals of the anti-apartheid
campaign in 1984, when 11 supermarket workers were fired for
refusing to handle South African fruit. They picketed the store for
nearly three years until they won a court case for unfair dismissal.
   Mandela was expected to meet with some of the group.
   The Mansion House, where Ireland's first independent Parliament
sat in 1919, symbolizes Irish liberation from centuries of British
rule.
   Others who have been made freemen of Dublin are playwright
George Bernard Shaw, Pope John Paul II, and U.S. President John
Kennedy.
   On Monday, Mandela will talk with Prime Minister Charles Haughey
and address the Irish Parliament before flying to London.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0029 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 1459EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People     07-01 0868</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People,0908</SECOND>
<HEAD>People in the News</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos NY44, CIR1</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BEVERLY HILLS, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Actress-singer Pia Zadora and her
millionaire husband, Meshulam Riklis, have sold their $4.7 million
home here, but they won't be hurting for a place to live.
   The five-bedroom, 6{-bath house, once owned by jockey Willie
Shoemaker, sits on a one-acre piece of property and contains 6,370
square feet.
   Miss Zadora and Riklis sold it to an unnamed Italian
industrialist for $4.7 million, according to Sunday's Los Angeles
Times.
   She and her husband own the site of the legendary Pickfair
mansion, where silent film stars Mary Pickford and Douglas
Fairbanks Sr. reigned as Hollywood royalty during the 1920s. That
mansion has largely been razed to make way for a new home, which
will incorporate the fragments of Pickfair that are still standing.
   Riklis and Miss Zadora also own another house in the Beverly
Park section of Beverly Hills and homes in Malibu and New York City.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>For release 6 p.m. EDT</NOTE>
<DATELINE>RADNOR, Pa. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Television producers say Warren Beatty is
losing some of his mystique as he heavily promotes his role in the
movie ``Dick Tracy.''
   ``I would imagine the we-got-to-have-him attitude is somewhat
diminished,'' Jack Riley, executive producer of ABC's ``Good
Morning America,'' said in the July 7 issue of TV Guide.
   ``But actually, now that he's gotten into it, he's a far better
interview than he has been,'' he said.
   Beatty had stonewalled seasoned interviewer Barbara Walters
early on and producers were wary of the once elusive star.
   ``Donahue'' senior producer Lorri Benson said she was
``pleasantly surprised'' by Beatty's openness when he appeared on
the syndicated show. There were no preconditions and no taboo
subjects, and Beatty spontaneously agreed to appear on the show a
second time, she said.
   Riley also was leery of scheduling a Beatty interview. He had
previously dealt with the star when he was touting his mega-bomb
``Ishtar.'' Beatty taped a segment for ``Good Morning America,''
but later made so many demands that the producers ``dumped the
whole thing,'' Riley said.
   The only constraint in the interview for ``Dick Tracy'' was that
11-year-old co-star Charlie Korsmo be on with him.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>TEL AVIV, Israel (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Former pop singer Cat Stevens, now known
as Yusuf Islam, was barred from entering the country on Sunday by
passport officials.
   Airport officials said Islam, who took his name after converting
to the Moslem faith, was turned away as ``an undesirable'' along
with his 8-year-old son, Mohammed, after their British Airways jet
landed about 4 a.m.
   They were met on arrival by passport officials and held at the
airport for about four hours until the flight returned to London,
officials said.
   One official, who spoke on condition of anonymity, said Islam
and his son accepted the decision quietly. The passport agents were
acting on instructions from the Interior Ministry, he said.
   Islam, a British citizen born Stephen Demetri Georgiou, gave up
his singing career a decade ago after his religious conversion. He
had a string of hits in the early 1970s, including ``Peace Train''
and ``Morning Has Broken.''
   He has been in the headlines recently for supporting the death
sentence issued by Iran against author Salman Rushdie.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>CIRENCESTER, England (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Prince Charles left the hospital
Sunday with his right arm in a cast and sling after breaking it
during a polo match.
   ``You can all go home at last,'' he told reporters and
photographers who had staked out the hospital entry since Thursday,
when the heir to the British throne suffered two fractures in his
right arm.
   Princess Diana, celebrating her 29th birthday, was by Charles'
side as he thanked doctors and nurses at Cirencester Hospital.
   ``There is still some pain but the swelling is going down in the
shoulder and the right arm. He is in good spirits,'' said the
prince's spokesman, Dickie Arbiter.
   The 41-year-old prince, an avid polo player for 25 years,
underwent a 45-minute operation to set the two breaks above the
elbow of his right arm.
   Charles was riding his pony, Echo, and playing for his team,
Windsor Park, in the semifinal of the Warwickshire Cup against
Hildon when he fell. Hildon won the match.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>NASHVILLE, Tenn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Attorney Fred Thompson was in court and
had to miss the opening of ``Days of Thunder'' to see his
performance as an auto racing magnate.
   Thompson also may be too busy this week to see the premier of
``Die Hard 2: Die Harder,'' in which he plays an embattled air
traffic controller.
   Thompson, who makes a hobby of playing no-nonsense characters,
was trying to settle a civil matter in Dallas and New Orleans when
``Days of Thunder, starring Tom Cruise, opened.
   The attorney's specialty is defending people accused of white
collar crimes. He has offices in Nashville and Washington.
   Thompson first received national attention when he was appointed
counsel to the Republican minority in the Watergate hearings.
   He says his acting offers is his own form of entertainment.
   ``It's a lot of fun,'' said Thompson. ``Some lawyers take
sabbaticals, or they devote themselves to intensive hobbies. My
`golf' is acting.''
   Thompson also played the head of the CIA in ``No Way Out.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0030 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 1517EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w ColombiansExtradited     07-01 0246</FIRST>
<SECOND>Colombians Extradited,240</SECOND>
<HEAD>Two Colombians Extradited to U.S. on Drug Charges</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two Colombians wanted on U.S. drug-trafficking
charges have been extradited from Colombia and flown to the United
States to stand trial, the U.S. Marshals Service said Sunday.
   Attorney General Richard Thornburgh said in a statement issued
by the marshals office that the action demonstrates ``the continued
determination of the Colombian government to battle the Colombian
drug cartel'' and to ``bring these drug dealing suspects to
justice.''
   The two were identified as Luis Carbacas, 60, charged with
leading a drug ring in North Carolina, and Rafael Juliao, 42,
charged with cocaine distribution in New York City.
   They are among 17 people extradited from Colombia since the
government of Colombian President Virgilio Barco began its drive
against the narcotics cartel last August.
   Carbacas and Juliao were turned over to the marshals service in
Bogota on Saturday evening and were flown to the United States
early Sunday morning.
   Carbacas was among 39 people indicted in 1985 on charges that
included conspiracy to possess and distribute 2 million
methaqualone tablets and more than 1,000 pounds of marijuana.
   He was accused with engaging in a continuing criminal enterprise
as a ring organizer, a violation of the so-called drug kingpin law.
He is to stand trial in North Carolina.
   Juliao, who is being held for arraignment in Manhattan, is
charged with distributing 3 kilograms (about 6.6 pounds) of cocaine
and conspiring to distribute 5 kilograms of cocaine.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0031 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 1518EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Hajj     07-01 0521</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Hajj,0540</SECOND>
<HEAD>Annual Hajj Peaks In Most Peaceful Year Since 1986</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MOHAMMED IBRAHIM</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MECCA, Saudi Arabia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two million Moslems stood in prayer
Sunday on Arafat, the mount overlooking Mecca where the Prophet
Mohammed delivered his last sermon 14 centuries ago, as the annual
Moslem pilgrimage reached its high point.
   For the first time since 1986, the Moslem pilgrimage, called the
hajj, has been free from terrorist attacks.
   Only a small fire at Mina, the tent city five miles from Arafat,
marred an otherwise calm pilgrimage season.
   Witnesses said that on their descent from Arafat they spotted
smoke from a distance. One said they were told it was at Mina, but
it did not appear to be a large blaze. Fire can be a danger during
the hajj because some pilgrims bring kerosene stoves to cook in the
tents.
   Terrorism blamed on Iranian or Shiite Moslems has occurred in
the past three years.
   The worst incident was in 1987, when Iranians clashed with
security forces, leading to the death of more than 400 pilgrims.
The year before, the Saudis confiscated large quantities of
explosives from members of the Iranian contingent.
   The Saudis have since set a quota of 1,000 per million of
population for each Islamic nation. Angered by the quotas, the
Iranians have boycotted the hajj since 1988.
   Last year, some small bombs went off during the hajj, killing
one pilgrim and injuring 16. The Saudis tried and convicted Kuwaiti
Shiite Moslems and beheaded 16 of them.
   Saudi authorities this year reported a growing number of
pilgrims for the hajj. The Saudis said 827,236 pilgrims arrived
from around the world, about 52,000 more than last year and some
30,000 more than 1988.
   They were joined by about half a million pilgrims from Saudi
Arabia and its large expatriate community. An additional half
million people were needed for servicing tasks.
   The deputy governor of Mecca region, Prince Saud ibn
Abdul-Mohsen, who is also deputy chairman of the Central Hajj
Committee, said the ascent of pilgrims by car and foot over the
5.5-mile route from Mina to Arafat was ``perfectly organized and
the flow of traffic was very smooth.''
   He said a few cases of heat fatigue were reported, but were not
serious. Temperatures reached 111 degrees.
   He said the pilgrims used umbrellas and awnings for shade, and
that 8.7 million flasks of iced water were distributed, a pet
project of the Saudi monarch, King Fahd.
   The stand at Arafat is considered the peak of the rituals, and
anyone who misses it will not be considered to have performed hajj.
   The day is spent reading the Koran, the Moslem holy book, and
praying.
   Dawn prayers Monday mark the start of the three-day Eid al-Adha
or Feast of Sacrifice, when sheep are slaughtered by the pilgrims
and Moslems everywhere to commemorate prophet Abraham's offering of
his son to God. Abraham is revered by Moslems as well as by Jews
and Christians.
   The hajj is a pillar of the Islamic faith. Moslems who are
healthy and can afford it are required to perform the hajj at least
once in their lifetime.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0032 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 1528EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-ColombiansExtradited     07-01 0252</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Colombians Extradited,240</SECOND>
<HEAD>RETRANSMITTING a0715 to RESTORE cycle designator</HEAD>
<HEAD>Two Colombians Extradited to U.S. on Drug Charges</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two Colombians wanted on U.S. drug-trafficking
charges have been extradited from Colombia and flown to the United
States to stand trial, the U.S. Marshals Service said Sunday.
   Attorney General Richard Thornburgh said in a statement issued
by the marshals office that the action demonstrates ``the continued
determination of the Colombian government to battle the Colombian
drug cartel'' and to ``bring these drug dealing suspects to
justice.''
   The two were identified as Luis Carbacas, 60, charged with
leading a drug ring in North Carolina, and Rafael Juliao, 42,
charged with cocaine distribution in New York City.
   They are among 17 people extradited from Colombia since the
government of Colombian President Virgilio Barco began its drive
against the narcotics cartel last August.
   Carbacas and Juliao were turned over to the marshals service in
Bogota on Saturday evening and were flown to the United States
early Sunday morning.
   Carbacas was among 39 people indicted in 1985 on charges that
included conspiracy to possess and distribute 2 million
methaqualone tablets and more than 1,000 pounds of marijuana.
   He was accused with engaging in a continuing criminal enterprise
as a ring organizer, a violation of the so-called drug kingpin law.
He is to stand trial in North Carolina.
   Juliao, who is being held for arraignment in Manhattan, is
charged with distributing 3 kilograms (about 6.6 pounds) of cocaine
and conspiring to distribute 5 kilograms of cocaine.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0033 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 1534EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p AM-Buddy'sReturn Bjt   07-01 0688</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Buddy's Return, Bjt,0708</SECOND>
<HEAD>Cianci: Providence Mayor, Felon, Talk Show Host, And Now Mayor
Again?</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT W. TROTT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PROVIDENCE, R.I. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Vincent A. ``Buddy'' Cianci Jr. _
convicted felon, media personality, former mayor _ is trying to
become mayor again.
   And if the 49-year-old independent candidate wins in November,
it will be a journey Cianci says will make him a better leader.
   ``A lot of people say they didn't like me as mayor but they
liked me on the radio,'' Cianci said. ``The radio station made me
listen and made me aware that there were other points of view.
   ``It's kept me sharp and it's kept me current.''
   Elected in 1974, he was forced out of office 10 years later
after he attacked his estranged wife's lover with a fireplace log,
an ashtray and a lit cigarette. He pleaded no contest to two
assault charges, and in April 1984 he received a five-year
suspended sentence and probation.
   After his ouster, Cianci wanted to run in the special mayoral
election and complete his four-year term in the state's largest
city with 160,000 residents. But the state Supreme Court ruled that
his conviction barred him from doing so. The ruling applied only to
the special election and does not prevent Cianci from running today.
   In March 1985, Cianci took up a career as a radio commentator
with WHJJ-AM. His three-hour afternoon talk show, a combination
interview and call-in show, was the state's most popular talk show
until he gave it up to run again. He also did political commentary
for two TV stations.
   Rhode Island political junkies discussed a Cianci return for
months. Even President Bush joined in, asking a Providence
journalist in March: ``How about Buddy Cianci? ... Talk about a guy
who liked to mix it up!''
   Cianci maintains he didn't make a final decision until
Wednesday, the day he announced his bid on the air.
   As proof, he points to his lack of money and staff. On the other
hand, he also notes that dollars are not vital to him at this early
stage _ ``I certainly don't need to get my name known.''
   Darrell West of Brown University's Public Opinion Center said
that a crowded ballot could work to Cianci's advantage. Besides
Cianci, there's another independent in the race, plus Democratic
and Republican candidates to be chosen during primaries in
September.
   ``It could be a good race from Buddy's point of view,'' West
said. ``If there's a four-person race, that probably means 35 to 40
percent is going to win.
   ``It's not as if Buddy has to convince the majority to become
mayor. A lot of people accept that he's got 20 to 25 percent, so he
only needs another 15 percent.''
   Cianci, who puts his core of supporters at 30 percent, managed
to upstage both state political parties with his announcement. He
filed his papers the day of the Democratic and Republican
conventions, effectively stealing their thunder in the next day's
newspapers and broadcasts.
   State Rep. Paul Jabour, who's among the five Democrats vying for
mayor, pooh-poohed Cianci's candidacy, saying: ``A voter is one
thing, and a fan club is another.''
   But state Rep. Frank Fiorenzano opined: ``If it wasn't for the
problems he got himself into, there's probably nothing he could not
have obtained. ... I wish I knew what it was. I would like to get
it and bottle it and give it to myself.''
   State Sen. Victoria Lederberg, another mayoral hopeful,
suggested a new slogan for her campaign: ``Let's keep Buddy on the
air.''
   Still, she said he would definitely liven things up.
   ``I tend to get bored with the race,'' she said. ``With Buddy in
the race, I'm not bored.''
   Cianci's not bored, either. He said his past ordeals and the six
years of public penance have made him more willing to be held
accountable.
   ``I'd probably be the only officeholder in the state under the
most public scrutiny, and I welcome that. It doesn't bother me,''
he said. ``The city of Providence and the people of Providence owe
me nothing. I owe them everything.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0034 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 1538EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ChildAbducted     07-01 0465</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Child Abducted,0478</SECOND>
<HEAD>Missing Infant Found Safe In Missouri; Teen-Ager In Custody</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LINDA FRANKLIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>OKLAHOMA CITY (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An infant taken from a hospital's nursery
more than a week ago was back in her parents' arms Sunday, the
result of an anonymous telephone tip to police.
   ``She's gained a pound since she's been gone and she's healthy
and eats all the time,'' Teresa Morse, 27, said after arriving back
in Oklahoma City with her nearly 2-week-old daughter, Whitney.
   ``I'm just going to take her home and try on all the clothes
she's got, and go shopping and go out somewhere instead of staying
home all the time.''
   The infant, abducted June 20 when she was 2 days old, was found
safe in Butler, Mo. Her parents flew there to get their first-born
child soon after police and FBI agents told them she had been found.
   Police Chief Dave McBride said 18-year-old Heather Brewster of
Butler was arrested and faces federal kidnapping charges.
   Max Geiman, FBI spokesman in Kansas City, said Ms. Brewster was
being held as a federal prisoner in the Clay County jail. Formal
charges will be filed Monday, he said.
   McBride said Ms. Brewster, who is single, had apparently
suffered a miscarriage and had carried on the pretense of being
pregnant.
   McBride said that even though she lives more than 200 miles
away, the woman was familiar with the Oklahoma City area, adding:
``She came here with the intent of taking a baby back.''
   Oklahoma City police Maj. Bob Taylor said 13 infants were
abducted in similar cases nationwide last year, and all were found.
   A woman dressed in hospital scrubs went into the nursery at
Deaconess Hospital late June 20 and told nurses she was there to
check out the baby to take it to the infant's parents. Hospital
officials called police a couple of hours later after discovering
the baby was gone.
   The break in the case came late Friday night when someone from
Missouri called police with ``good, specific information,'' McBride
said. He said he could not go into specifics because that would
reveal the identity of the caller, who was promised anonymity.
   Bates County Sheriff Leonard Hough questioned Ms. Brewster late
Saturday and notified FBI agents after the woman was unable to
answer some questions, McBride said.
   The baby was positively identified early Sunday.
   Bob Ricks, special agent in charge of the FBI in Oklahoma, said
the infant's footprints were sent by facsimile machine to Butler
and a fingerprint expert was sent to check the child.
   ``On the airplane I thought `I'm over it now. I'm just over it,'
'' Mrs. Morse said. ``There's no pain ... (but) it'll probably take
me a while to trust again without being with her all the time.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0035 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 1544EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BabyFound     07-01 0475</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Baby Found,0488</SECOND>
<NOTE>Eds: Retransmitting a0722 to make slug conform to AM-News Advisory</NOTE>
<HEAD>Missing Infant Found Safe In Missouri; Teen-Ager In Custody</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LINDA FRANKLIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>OKLAHOMA CITY (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An infant taken from a hospital's nursery
more than a week ago was back in her parents' arms Sunday, the
result of an anonymous telephone tip to police.
   ``She's gained a pound since she's been gone and she's healthy
and eats all the time,'' Teresa Morse, 27, said after arriving back
in Oklahoma City with her nearly 2-week-old daughter, Whitney.
   ``I'm just going to take her home and try on all the clothes
she's got, and go shopping and go out somewhere instead of staying
home all the time.''
   The infant, abducted June 20 when she was 2 days old, was found
safe in Butler, Mo. Her parents flew there to get their first-born
child soon after police and FBI agents told them she had been found.
   Police Chief Dave McBride said 18-year-old Heather Brewster of
Butler was arrested and faces federal kidnapping charges.
   Max Geiman, FBI spokesman in Kansas City, said Ms. Brewster was
being held as a federal prisoner in the Clay County jail. Formal
charges will be filed Monday, he said.
   McBride said Ms. Brewster, who is single, had apparently
suffered a miscarriage and had carried on the pretense of being
pregnant.
   McBride said that even though she lives more than 200 miles
away, the woman was familiar with the Oklahoma City area, adding:
``She came here with the intent of taking a baby back.''
   Oklahoma City police Maj. Bob Taylor said 13 infants were
abducted in similar cases nationwide last year, and all were found.
   A woman dressed in hospital scrubs went into the nursery at
Deaconess Hospital late June 20 and told nurses she was there to
check out the baby to take it to the infant's parents. Hospital
officials called police a couple of hours later after discovering
the baby was gone.
   The break in the case came late Friday night when someone from
Missouri called police with ``good, specific information,'' McBride
said. He said he could not go into specifics because that would
reveal the identity of the caller, who was promised anonymity.
   Bates County Sheriff Leonard Hough questioned Ms. Brewster late
Saturday and notified FBI agents after the woman was unable to
answer some questions, McBride said.
   The baby was positively identified early Sunday.
   Bob Ricks, special agent in charge of the FBI in Oklahoma, said
the infant's footprints were sent by facsimile machine to Butler
and a fingerprint expert was sent to check the child.
   ``On the airplane I thought `I'm over it now. I'm just over it,'
'' Mrs. Morse said. ``There's no pain ... (but) it'll probably take
me a while to trust again without being with her all the time.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0036 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 1558EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Mandela-US     07-01 0612</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mandela-US,0633</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mandela's Plan to Return Delights Supporters</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Mandela, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JENNIFER McNULTY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN FRANCISCO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Nelson Mandela saluted Californians for
taking economic sanctions against South Africa and pledged to help
American Indians when he returns in October.
   Mandela announced Saturday he would return to the United States
to visit Indian reservations and ``exchange views as to what I can
do to help them in their struggle.''
   ``The Indian people have written to me and explained their
problems, and it is but natural that I should respond to that by
seeing them as I proposed to do,'' Mandela said at a brief news
conference before he left Oakland, finishing his 11-day whirlwind
trip through the United States.
   The announcement was greeted with enthusiasm by the American
Indians, including Rep. Ben Nighthorse-Campbell, the only American
Indian in Congress.
   Indians and South African blacks ``face some similar background
problems,'' said the Colorado Democrat.
   ``The difference I think is that nobody is intentionally
preventing Indians from becoming part of the Legislature,'' he
said. ``In South Africa, they virtually lock black people out of
running from office.''
   Hundreds of Mandela's supporters were disappointed when he cut
short by a day his visit to Oakland in order to make an appointment
with Irish Prime Minister Charles Haughy.
   ``I'm not mad, but it is dismaying to get so close just to be
disappointed,'' said Ethelou Talbert of Oakland.
   Mandela and his wife, Winnie, had to cancel a reception for
Winnie; a $100-a-plate dinner; and a $2,500-per-couple reception.
The events went ahead and organizer Sandre Swanson said she did not
expect to make many refunds.
   ``People were giving for the cause to free South Africa, not
just to see Nelson and Winnie Mandela,'' Swanson said.
   Mandela, 71, deputy president of the African National Congress,
was freed in February after 27 years in a South African prison for
plotting sabotage to overthrow the nation's white government.
   Mandela's representatives said they considered canceling the
entire Oakland visit, but Rep. Ron Dellums, who represents Oakland
in Congress, intervened to save Mandela's sold-out speech before a
crowd of 58,000 at the Oakland-Alameda County Coliseum.
   During his 20-minute Coliseum speech, Mandela hailed
Californians for their role in the movement to persuade
institutions to sell off stock in companies doing business in South
Africa.
   ``We salute the state of California for having such a powerful
political stance on divestment,'' he said, praising students at the
University of California for pressuring officials to divest. ``We
salute the longshoremen for refusing to unload the ship (with South
African cargo) in 1984.''
   Supporters waved black, green and gold ANC flags, beat on drums
and stood to roar their support for the black South African hero of
the anti-apartheid movement.
   ``We are at a true historical junction. We cannot turn back,''
said Mandela, thrusting his trademark clenched fist in the air.
``We will not turn back.''
   Oakland was the final stop on the grueling eight-city
fund-raising tour of the United States, one of 14 countries on a
round-the-world trip.
   Although final fund-raising figures will not be available until
next week, Mandela said the U.S. visit ``has succeeded beyond our
wildest dreams.''
   Total tour estimates range from $3 million to $7 million,
according to organizers. More than $900,000 was raised at Oakland
events, according to Mark Mosher of the Osborn Group, the public
relations company handling media coverage of the visit. But that
figure does not include informal hat-passing and other spontaneous
donations, he said.
   For Mandela, the trip bolstered more than the ANC bankroll.
   ``I feel like an old battery that has been recharged,'' he said
upon his arrival at Oakland International Airport.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0037 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 1558EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brite-CyclingHam     07-01 0305</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brite-Cycling Ham,0314</SECOND>
<HEAD>Man Has Found Way to Enjoy Two Hobbies: Cycling and Ham Radio</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ARLINGTON, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Herb Viegas is a cycling ham _ ham radio
operator, that is.
   The 69-year-old Viegas cycles long distances and talks to people
even farther away at the same time with the ham radio he installed
on his bicycle.
   He said he surprises and confuses some of those he reaches as he
rides along and sends out his greeting: ``Hello, this is WJ5,
bicycle mobile.''
   With his bicycle radio, he has talked to people as far away as
New York and Minnesota.
   ``I put out a pretty good signal, and the guys hear me, and I
get a pile of them wanting to talk to me,'' Viegas said.
   Shortly after retiring from LTV Corp. about 10 years ago, Viegas
took up cycling. He also began tinkering in his workshop at home.
   ``I decided that I didn't want to spend all of my time in
there,'' he said. ``So I thought that I would try to rig a ham
radio for my bike.''
   Viegas had to figure out what kind of regulator to use for the
voltage provided by a generator on the back tire of his 12-speed.
But once he did, he began beaming out his signal.
   ``I rode 4,000 miles last year,'' Viegas said. ``When I'm
riding, I'll talk to people and tell them that I am riding a bike
and can't write their names. I ask them to send me a card.''
   Plenty of cooperative hams have done just that. Cards line a
wall in Viegas' home from points in the world that he has reached.
   One from Fulton, N.Y., reads: ``Herb, you are my first bicycle
mobile contact. You have a great signal and you'd never know that
you were on a bike.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0038 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 1559EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BRF--BillboardBust     07-01 0147</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Billboard Bust,0150</SECOND>
<HEAD>Zoning Violation Fells Anti-Crime Billboard</HEAD>
<DATELINE>KALAMAZOO, Mich. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A billboard featuring McGruff the
crime-fighting dog had to come down last week. It was illegal.
   The billboard was removed Thursday, one day after Kalamazoo
officials said it violated the city zoning ordinance. Adams Outdoor
Advertising Co. also failed to obtain a permit before erecting the
billboard two weeks earlier, city officials said.
   The billboard featured not only McGruff but a telephone number
allowing anonymous callers to report information about suspected
drug dealers. It was sponsored by a neighborhood business
association.
   Deputy City Manager James Perkins said he hoped Adams would
display the billboard _ legally _ elsewhere. But Adams General
Manager Michael Romoser said McGruff's canine countenance wouldn't
appear on other company billboards.
   ``I don't anticipate how it could,'' he said Thursday. ``It
appears all of these good intentions have been for naught.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0039 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 1602EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Japan-Peru     07-01 0297</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Japan-Peru,0309</SECOND>
<HEAD>President-Elect Fujimori Arrives in Tokyo</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Alberto Fujimori, president-elect of Peru, hoped to
revive Japanese econmic aid to his country and travel to his
parents' birthplace during a visit that began Sunday night.
   Fujimori is to have an audience Monday with Emperor Akihito at
the Imperial Palace and meet with Prime Minister Toshiki Kaifu.
   In talks with Kaifu, Fujimori is expected to ask Japan to resume
credits and extend technological aid to help Peru recover from
economic depression.
   ``I wish to re-establish the flowering cooperation with this
great country,'' he said before leaving for Japan.
   Fujimori, an agronomist, was a political unknown before he
defeated celebrated novelist Mario Vargas Llosa in Peru's June 10
presidential runoff.
   He played up his Japanese heritage during the campaign, even
posing dressed as a samurai warrior for news photographers.
   Fujimori's Japanese ancestry has raised hopes the Peru will have
greater access to Japanese aid.
   Peru was the largest recipient of Japanese aid in Latin America
in cumulative until 1988 but dropped to fourth-largest after it
defaulted on payments and Japan cut off its credits.
   Japanese officials have said Japan is willing to help after
hearing Fujimori's plans for dealing with Peru's problems.
   The Foreign Ministry says Peru owes Japan about $1 billion in
government and private credits.
   Japan had extended credits totaling $359 million since 1971. The
last was in 1983 _ a credit of $31.3 million for fishing port
construction, the ministry said.
   During his five-day visit, Fujimori is to confer with Japanese
business leaders before leaving Wednesday for Kumamoto, from where
his parents emigrated to Peru in 1934. Kumamoto is on Japan's
southernmost main island of Kyushu.
   Fujimori leaves Japan Thursday for home. He is to be inaugurated
July 28 for a five-year term.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0040 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 1605EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-China-Census     07-01 0503</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-China-Census,0518</SECOND>
<HEAD>China Launches Largest-Ever Census</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CHARLENE L. FU</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   China on Sunday launched its largest census ever,
mobilizing 7 million people to count the world's most populous
nation.
   For the next 10 days, census takers throughout the country _
from the crowded coastal cities to its desolate western regions _
will be knocking on doors to get the latest count of China's
estimated 1.1 billion people.
   Census-takers arrived at 9 a.m. at Zhongnanhai, the red-walled
compound housing Communist Party headquarters and homes of the top
leaders, the evening TV news reported.
   The report showed two young census workers interviewing
Communist Party General Secretary Jiang Zemin and Premier Li Peng,
running through the standard questions of name, age and address,
even though in their cases the answers are common knowledge.
   Census workers also arrived early at the homes of ordinary
citizens.
   ``They didn't stay very long _ just asked their questions and
left,'' said a 50-year-old worker from central Beijing who gave
only her surname, Kang. ``This was actually their last visit, not
their first. They've come several times already getting ready for
the census.''
   Since spring, officials have been making checks to confirm that
household registrations are up to date. Census workers have also
staged practice runs, visiting families and filling out
questionnaires.
   To ensure the accuracy of the head count, China is sending its
census takers door-to-door for the first time. Previously,
residents were asked to visit census stations for the three
censuses conducted since the Communists came to power in 1949.
   Publicity for the census has been ubiquitous since the spring.
Billboards and banners remind citizens that a successful census
requires their cooperation, and newspaper editorials explain why
it's necessary to count the nation's people.
   For the past two months, government notices posted on a low
green fence in Kang's neighborhood have kept residents informed of
the census proceedings.
   ``It's a very necessary task,'' said another resident, who did
not give his name. ``It's just like a family _ how can you take
care of your family if you don't even know how many of you there
are and what everyone's doing?''
   Kang and others noted that the 21-item questionnaire was more
detailed than that of the previous census in 1982.
   Most, however, said they didn't mind answering questions about
each family member's name, age, education level and occupation as
well as about household features and child-bearing conditions for
women.
   But the same questions strike fear in the hearts of China 20
million-strong floating population, who have moved to cities
without permission, and among those who have had children in
violation of China's strict family planning policy.
   In Beijing, census workers headed out Saturday evening to count
the floating population, many of whom work during the day and
return home late, said Zhu Yilin, head of the municipal census
office.
   Initial results of the census will be published in October, but
it will take nearly two years to process the data they collect.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0041 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 1607EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-MarcosTrial     07-01 0255</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Marcos Trial,0263</SECOND>
<HEAD>Jury Continues Deliberations on Imelda Marcos</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Jurors considering racketeering and fraud
charges against former Philippine first lady Imelda Marcos reviewed
more testimony Sunday in their fourth day of deliberations.
   The jurors resumed their discussions in the early afternoon
after some members attended church services.
   Mrs. Marcos, whose 61st birthday is Monday, is charged with
racketeering, racketeering conspiracy, mail fraud and obstruction
of justice.
   She is accused of helping her late husband, former Philippine
President Ferdinand Marcos, buy jewelry, artworks and four
Manhattan buildings with $222 million allegedly looted from their
homeland's treasury.
   The jurors also are deliberating mail fraud and obstruction of
justice charges against her co-defendant, Saudi financier Adnan
Khashoggi.
   Khashoggi, 54, is accused of allegedly helping the Marcoses hide
ownership of the buildings after a U.S. court order froze their
assets.
   On Sunday, the panel reheard testimony about one of the
underlying racketeering acts, which claims Mrs. Marcos helped to
fraudulently obtain millions of dollars in loans to finance the
four properties.
   The jury, which is sequestered, began deliberations Thursday
afternoon. The three-month trial in U.S. District Court included
testimony from 95 prosecution witnesses. The defense called no
witnesses.
   If convicted, Mrs. Marcos faces up to 50 years in prison and $1
million in fines. Khashoggi could draw a sentence of 10 years and a
$500,000 fine.
   Marcos, who was ousted from power in February 1986, was
originally charged along with his wife but was found too ill to
stand trial. He died in September.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0042 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 1623EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Yeager-RoughLanding     07-01 0219</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Yeager-Rough Landing,0225</SECOND>
<HEAD>Voyager Co-Pilot Jeana Yeager Has Rough Landing In Desert Air Race</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JACKPOT, Nev. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Jeana Yeager, who made history in the
non-stop round-the-world flight of the Voyager in 1986, escaped
injury Sunday after an experimental plane she was co-piloting
caught fire and crashed during an emergency landing.
   Elko County Sheriff's Deputy James Neff said Yeager and pilot
Shirland K. Dickey were about four miles from the airport the
engine caught fire and smoke was detected in the cockpit.
   He said the engine quit while the plane was still a half-mile
out and Yeager and Dickey made a dead stick landing, a landing made
without any power.
   On touching down, the plane left the runway and its landing gear
collapsed, he said, but the 38-year-old Yeager of Nipomo, Calif.,
and Dickey, 48, of Chandler, Ariz., walked away.
   Neff said an unidentified Jackpot volunteer firefighter suffered
minor smoke inhalation while trying to douse a fire in the wreckage.
   The deputy said the pair were flying an experimental
propeller-driven plane in the 8th Annual International E-Z Air Show
and were on the final approach of a 120-mile race between Jackpot
and Wells, Nev.
   Yeager and pilot Dick Rutan set aviation history in December
1986 when they flew the Voyager in a nine-day unrefueled
circumnavigation of the globe.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0043 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 1623EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Israel-Poet     07-01 0205</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel-Poet,0211</SECOND>
<HEAD>Israeli-Arab Poet Released From House Arrest</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Israel</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HAIFA, Israel (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An Israeli Arab poet charged with
identifying with a terrorist organization was released from house
arrest Sunday.
   Shafik Habib, a 49-year-old accountant known for his ``political
poetry,'' was placed under house arrest in mid-June after police
said his poems could incite violence. Publication of Habib's poems
was also banned.
   On June 19, Habib was charged with identifying with an
unspecified terrorist group. No trial date was set.
   The move sparked protests by Arab legislators and the
Palestinian Israeli Writers' Union. Arab intellectuals saying they
feared it could signal a police crackdown on Israeli Arab
nationalists.
   On Friday, Habib appealed the house arrest, saying it restricted
his freedom as an individual and freedom of movement, and harmed
his income.
   Haifa's District Court Judge Micha Lindenstrauss on Sunday
upheld Habib's appeal and ordered the poet released. ``It is enough
that the (military) censor has banned publication of the poems.
Preventing publication is a reasonable solution to guard public
safety,'' Lindenstrauss said in his decision.
   Police officials say Habib's poems call for violence against
Jews and support the 30-month-old Palestinian uprising against
Israeli rule in the occupied West Bank and the Gaza Strip.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0044 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 1626EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Obit-Youngs     07-01 0148</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Youngs,0153</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ruby Youngs, White House Switchboard Operator, Dies at 82</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WINCHESTER, Va. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Ruby O. Youngs, who served as a White
House switchboard operator under five presidents, has died at a
Franklin County retirement home. She was 82.
   Ms. Youngs, who died Friday, worked as a White House operator
for more than 20 years, spanning the administrations of Presidents
Truman, Eisenhower, Kennedy, Johnson and Nixon.
   She retired just before the Watergate scandal ended the Nixon
presidency in 1974.
   Mildred Campbell, who worked with Ms. Youngs at the White House,
said she was a steadying influence on younger operators. ``She was
very intelligent. I thought she was the best,'' Ms. Campbell said.
   Ms. Youngs also served as a switchboard operator for former
American Motion Picture Association chief Jack Valenti.
   Ms. Youngs moved to Roanoke in the 1970s to live near her son,
who has since died.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0045 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 1648EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Obit-Cabre     07-01 0116</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Cabre,0119</SECOND>
<HEAD>Former Bullfighter, Romantically Linked To Ava Gardner, Dies</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BARCELONA, Spain (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Mario Cabre, a former Spanish
bullfighter and actor who in the 1950s was romantically linked to
the late actress Ava Gardner, died in a Barcelona clinic of a heart
ailment Sunday, doctors said. He was 75.
   Cabre was widely known in Spain, not only as a bullfighter, but
also for his romance with Gardner during the film ``Pandora and the
wandering Dutchman,'' which they made together in the Spanish Costa
Brava.
   After retiring from the bullring in 1960 following a 17-year
career, he played leading roles in a number of Spanish films and
plays.
   Cabre also wrote several books of poetry.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0046 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 1704EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Poland     07-01 0637</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Poland,0659</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mazowiecki Announces Plans To Talk With Walesa</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN DANISZEWSKI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WARSAW, Poland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Prime Minister Tadeusz Mazowiecki offered
Sunday to meet this week with Lech Walesa to ease the bitter
political war that has torn the Solidarity movement.
   An aid to Walesa said the Solidarity chairman was aware of the
offer and that arrangements for the meeting would probably be
announced soon.
   Mazowiecki's peace gesture came at a meeting of local Solidarity
Citizens Committees called by his backers in the conflict. Walesa
has accused his former ally of moving too slowly to implement
political and economic reforms.
   Members of Citizens Committees from around the country met
Saturday with Walesa and then Sunday with Mazowiecki to discuss
what direction the Solidarity union movement should take.
   Mazowiecki's backers failed to win enough support to create a
nationwide federation of Citizens Committees behind the government.
Instead, the issue was postponed until a conference July 21.
   Sunday's meeting passed a resolution urging the Solidarity
leader and Mazowiecki to cooperate.
   Taking the floor earlier, Mazowiecki told the local activists
meeting in the parliament building that he was always willing to
talk with Walesa even though he had been attacked by him.
   He said he would call Walesa on condition that the conversation
would be conducted as a ``full partnership'' and not as Mazowiecki
``paying a serf's homage.''
   ``I think that certain issues should be toned down,'' Mazowiecki
said. ``I am proposing to Mr. Walesa to talk this coming week.''
   Mazowiecki said they should talk ``not to remove all differences
between us, because that would not be true, but to talk so that
disputes and battles proceed in a way that does not destroy the
common good of Poland and Solidarity's legacy.''
   Asked later, he declined to elaborate on specific topics for
discussion.
   Walesa aide Krzysztof Pusz, reached at home in Gdansk, said
Walesa was aware of Mazowiecki's proposal.
   ``I think the details should be worked out this week,'' Pusz
said.
   The Walesa and Mazowiecki factions were competing for the
allegiance of the grass roots during the weekend meetings, and the
fight seemed to end in a draw.
   Delegates were not enthusiastic by the call from the Mazowiecki
faction for creating a national federation that would act as a base
of support for the government.
   But in a straw poll Sunday, they also rejected Walesa's proposal
that the Citizens Committees be opened to members of other
political groups.
   The question of the committees' role is important because they
constitute easily the country's strongest political force. In last
year's parliamentary elections and last month's local elections,
virtually all candidates endorsed by the Solidarity Citizens
Committees won.
   Walesa argues that the local committees should admit supporters
of other budding political parties and become forums for discussing
public issues. He also says they should be free to criticize the
government.
   Otherwise, he said, Solidarity could itself become a monopoly
and eventually be taken over by people with dictatorial tendencies.
   Supporters of Mazowiecki accuse Walesa of demagoguery. They want
the local committees to band together to create a national
federation to defend Mazowiecki's government, which is carrying out
difficult economic reforms.
   The 9-month-old government has introduced radical economic
reforms. But it has taken a gradual approach to dismantling the old
Communist power structure and dismissing Communist holdovers,
arguing the alternative would be witch hunts and chaos.
   The prime minister told the meeting Sunday that there is need
for ``political support for this cause taking place in Poland.''
   ``The question is should we slacken and withdraw,'' he said,
``or go further, knowing it will be difficult.''
   At a meeting June 24 of ranking Solidarity members, 63 of
Walesa's oldest advisers broke ranks, accusing him of trying to
make the Citizens Committees into a tool of his widely expected
campaign for president.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0047 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 1707EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-TrumpAssets     07-01 0581</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Trump Assets,0595</SECOND>
<HEAD>Trump's Real Work Is 'Round The Corner: If And What to Sell</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CATHERINE CROCKER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The hard work starts for Donald Trump once the
bankers finish his $65 million bailout plan. The developer will
have to restructure his empire and probably sell some of his vast
holdings to raise cash.
   The banks hope that by deferring about $800 million of his $2
billion bank debt for up to five years, Trump will gain time to
sell his assets in an orderly way.
   ``The banks believe the assets he possesses are valuable enough
to be sold over time at respectable prices and are certainly enough
to keep his operation viable,'' said a source close to the
negotiations.
   A rush sale would have meant low prices that would have kept
Trump from meeting his debt obligations to the banks, the source
added.
   As it is, the value of his assets has been depressed by the
sagging real estate market and the increasingly stagnant Atlantic
City gambling market.
   The developer's properties include Trump Tower, whose marble
shopping arcade has become a big tourist attraction, the ritzy
Plaza Hotel, the Trump Shuttle with its fleet of 17 aircraft, and
casinos in Atlantic City.
   Trump will have to sell some of his assets to raise cash
``unless ... the Atlantic City operations begin to support (his)
debt record and that's the wild card,'' said Edward S. Gordon,
president and chief executive officer of the commercial real estate
firm bearing his name.
   Bankers hope the paperwork for their $65 million loan to Trump
will be completed within 30 days. About 70 banks on Tuesday lent
Trump $20 million immediately so he could meet a midnight deadline
on a $43 million payment on bonds backing one of his casinos.
   In a statement Tuesday, Trump said the bailout deal ``reflects
and confirms the inherent long-term value of our assets including
Trump Tower, the Plaza Hotel, the Atlantic City hotels and the
Trump Shuttle.''
   Trump has has discussed selling his East Coast air service, and
the Trump Princess, the 282-foot yacht he bought for $30 million.
   Business Week reported last month that he is also listening to
offers for Trump Castle, his worst-performing casino, and,
according to real estate sources, thinking about selling the Plaza
Hotel _ which Trump likes to call it ``the ultimate trophy in the
world.''
   Last week the Daily News in New York quoted an unidentified
banker close to the Trump negotiations as saying that Trump's share
in Alexander's department stores would probably be among the first
assets he would sell.
   Trump paid nearly $70 million for a 27 percent stake in the
retailing company and planned to develop its real estate holdings
into huge commercial and retailing centers.
   Also among his assets is Trump City _ 76 acres of undeveloped
land on Manhattan's West Side that was the site of an unused rail
yard. He paid about $100 million in 1985 and wants to build the
world's tallest building, luxury apartments and a shopping mall
there.
   The plan has been presented to the city Planning Commission but
is not yet in the often lengthy land use approval process. It has
been held up, in part, by community activists who oppose the
project for environmental reasons.
   Forbes magazine says Trump values the property at $650 million,
though Forbes puts its worth at $200 million and Business Week says
it would sell for only $160 million.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0048 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 1753EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-NOWConvention 1stLd-Writethru a0744 07-01 0524</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-NOW Convention, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0744,0537</SECOND>
<HEAD>NOW Considers Third Political Party</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDs: SUBS lead to CORRECT name of organization; Fixes TYPO in 5th
graf, ```Washington is...</NOTE>
<DATELINE>SAN FRANCISCO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Proposals to form an alternative to the
``white male-dominated'' Republican and Democratic parties
generated intense interest at a three-day meeting of the National
Organization for Women that ended Sunday.
   Participants at the annual NOW convention listened to
suggestions for a political party to represent feminists,
pro-choice advocates, gays, minorities, ecologists and those
opposed to nuclear power and weapons.
   ``Our friends and our allies called us `suicidal,' and
`naive,''' when the third-party idea surfaced at last year's
convention, NOW Vice President Patricia Ireland said Saturday.
``But are we naive?''
   ``Isn't it time, with a Congress that's 95 percent male, 95
percent white _ with only two `out' gay males, and no `out' gay
females. Isn't it time for a representative democracy?'' Ireland
asked to shouts of approval.
   ``Washington is a company town and we just threatened the
company,'' she said.
   West German Parliament member Petra Kelly, who helped form the
anti-nuclear Green Party in her country in 1979, urged a crowd of
about 2,400 NOW members Saturday to think about becoming an
``alternative political force.''
   ``If not now, when are you going to do it? The time has come,''
Kelly said, criticizing the Democratic and Republican parties as
too similar.
   The established parties protect the interests of the white,
male-dominated bureaucracy, she said.
   ``What a legacy it is they have left us: Bhopal, Chernobyl, Love
Canal, global warming,'' she said.
   NOW President Molly Yard tried to remind the group that a third
party was only one of several election reform ideas being studied
by the organization.
   ``We haven't come to the conclusion that we should have a third
party,'' said Yard.
   ``Yes we have!'' delegates roared back.
   NOW's Commission on Democracy in the Twenty-First Century is
scheduled to make its recommendations for political change at the
NOW convention next summer in New York City.
   Also Saturday, about 500 conference participants staged an
abortion rights rally at Union Square, and listened to speeches by
politicians campaigning against two anti-abortion incumbents.
   ``We are going to do it this year because our message is right
and Jesse Helms is wrong and divisive,'' said Harvey Gantt, a North
Carolina Democrat trying to unseat Helms.
   Pennsylvania Republican gubernatorial candidate Barbara Hafer
said she trusted ``women in Pennsylvania to make important choices
for themselves.''
   About 100 anti-abortion protesters gathered near the rally,
carrying signs that read: ``NOW does not represent me'' and ``Not
NOW, not ever.''
   Yard announced a possible boycott against a major European
chemical company, Roussel Uclaf, if it does not market its abortion
pill, RU-486, in the United States. NOW representatives have
gathered 70,000 petition signatures to pressure the company into
marketing the drug, now sold only in France.
   The National Right to Life Committee has threatened to prevent
manufacture or sale of the drug in the United States by boycotting
pharmaceutical companies.
   The American Medical Association's House of Delegates last week
voted to endorse testing and possible use of RU-486 in the United
States.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0049 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 1756EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SriLanka     07-01 0464</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Sri Lanka,0478</SECOND>
<HEAD>Government Troops Report Capture of Tamil Rebel Base</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PATRICK CRUEZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>COLOMBO, Sri Lanka (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Government troops broke through a
cordon of bunkers and overran a strategic Tamil Tiger base on the
northwestern coast, killing 25 guerrillas, military officials said
Sunday.
   One soldier was killed and 25 wounded in Saturday's operation,
the officials said on condition of anonymity.
   The loss of the base in the village of Marichchukkaddi, 115
miles north of Colombo, is a major blow to the rebels, officials
said.
   They said it was hidden in dense forest and close to the sea,
making it an ideal point for transporting men and weapons.
   Government troops are still battling for control of the northern
Jaffna peninsula, where the rebels have besieged a government
garrison since the latest round of fighting began June 11.
   Since mounting a counteroffensive, government troops claim to
have captured most of this island nation's eastern districts, which
have large Tamil populations, forcing the rebels into the jungles
and swamps.
   In the eastern port city of Batticaloa, 135 miles east of
Colombo, Deputy Defense Minister Ranjan Wijeratne visited troops on
Sunday. He told them the battle was not against the Tamil
population, the military officials said.
   Wijeratne also urged government officials to go into every Tamil
home on a ``win-their-hearts-and-mind campaign,'' the officials
said.
   Since the city was recaptured June 18, Tamil residents have
expressed fears that the mostly Sinhalese troops would launch
reprisals against them.
   During the past four days, government troops captured 75 Tiger
rebels who had mingled with the civilian population after
Batticaloa was recaptured, said local residents, requesting
anonymity.
   They said the rebels were identified by members of rival Tamil
groups from among more than 2,000 young Tamils rounded up by the
soldiers.
   On Saturday, police raided the homes of 10 Tamil parliament
members in Colombo, the capital, to disarm them and their
bodyguards, a military official said Sunday.
   The official said 35 guns and 20,000 round of ammunition were
captured in the raids on homes of deputies from the Eelam
Revolutionary Organization of Students, whose 13 members in the
221-seat parliament support the Tiger rebels.
   The rebels have waged a seven-year insurgency to establish an
independent Tamil homeland in the north and east of this island
nation. They claim the Tamil minority is discriminated against by
the majority Sinhalese in jobs and education.
   Sinhalese comprise 75 percent of Sri Lanka's 16 million people
and control the government and the military. Tamils make up 18
percent of the population.
   The latest fighting between Tamil Tigers and government forces
erupted June 11 after a Tamil man complained to the rebels that he
had been manhandled by Sinhalese police in Batticaloa.
   At least 1,820 people have died in the fighting.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0050 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 1808EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Soviet-Military     07-01 0458</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Military,0473</SECOND>
<HEAD>Defense Minister: Military Must Help Solve Housing Crisis</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DEBORAH G. SEWARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The defense minister said Sunday that the military
must help build housing for the tens of thousands of soldiers and
their families returning from service in the formerly Communist
countries of the Warsaw Pact.
   Dmitri T. Yazov told the government newspaper Izvestia that the
housing crisis facing returning troops was the ``issue of issues''
confronting the Soviet military.
   More than 25,000 soldiers and their families are on their way
back to the Soviet Union from neighboring Czechoslovakia and
Hungary, Yazov told Izvestia. Another 173,600 were already waiting
in dormitories and hotels for permanent housing, he said.
   The Soviet military, along with local government councils,
should ``above all, sharply increase the pace and volume of private
construction'' of new housing to ease the crunch, he said.
   Yazov said that 440,000 apartments are scheduled to be built
within the next five years.
   Already this year, 43,000 troops and their dependents have
returned from Czechoslovakia, Poland and Hungary, adding to the
27,000 withdrawn from East Germany and Hungary.
   The overthrow of Communist rule in all of the East bloc
countries except Bulgaria has accelerated plans announced two years
ago by President Mikhail S. Gorbachev to bring back more than
500,000 troops from Eastern Europe.
   Demands by Hungary and Czechoslovakia that the withdrawal of all
120,000 Soviet troops from their territory be completed by mid-1991
have accelerated the pullout, and the pressure to find housing.
   For strategic reasons, most of the troops are being stationed in
the Ukraine, Byelorussia and Russia, the Slavic republics on the
Soviet Union's western border.
   There is already a critical housing shortage in some areas of
Byelorussia because of the need to relocate thousands of people
whose land was irradiated in the 1986 Chernobyl nuclear disaster.
   In addition, some local groups apparently are not happy about
the prospect of becoming garrison towns.
   Yazov said that informal groups in Ivano-Frankovsk in the
southwestern corner of the Ukraine, near the border with Romania,
had blocked construction of military housing.
   ``It is shameful to hear such things as that,'' Yazov told the
newspaper.
   The United States and Soviet Union have both agreed to trim
their forces in Central Europe to 195,000 each, except for 30,000
U.S. troops to be left in Britain and southern Europe. The United
States has about 310,000 troops in Europe, including 250,000 in
Germany.
   The Soviet Union has about 380,000 troops in East Germany and
Moscow is pressing West Germany to help finance housing
construction once the troops are pulled out.
   Bonn has expressed a willingness to help, and the issue is
likely to be discussed when Chancellor Helmut Kohl vi sits Moscow
July 15-16.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0051 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 1811EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-WeatherpageWeather     07-01 0327</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Weatherpage Weather,0342</SECOND>
<HEAD>Thunderstorms Scattered Across Eastern United States</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Strong thunderstorms were scattered across the eastern United
States from Pennsylvania to Alabama on Sunday, and it was also
raining in the Dakotas.
   Scattered showers and thunderstorms were reported over eastern
South Dakota and southeastern North Dakota, with a few showers and
thunderstorms over Florida and south-central Texas as well.
   Showers and thunderstorms produced an inch of rain at Key West,
Fla., curing the six-hour period ending at 2 p.m. EDT, and half an
inch of rain at Apalachicola.
   Sunny and dry weather prevailed across the rest of the nation.
   Hot weather that has brought 100-degree temperatures to the
Desert Southwest as well as Colorado, Wyoming, Idaho and Montana
the past week also began to affect parts of Alaska.
   Fairbanks reported a record high of 86 degrees Saturday, with
predicted highs of 90 degrees Sunday.
   Temperatures were above 90 degrees Sunday afternoon across much
of the area from the southern Atlantic Coast to the high Plains,
with readings above 100 degrees in Kansas, Colorado and Nebraska.
   Pleasantly mild temperatures prevailed in the upper Mississippi
Valley, the Great Lakes and the Northeast, with readings mostly in
the 70s. Afternoon temperatures were in the 60s from the lower
Great Lakes to New England.
   Readings were soaring into the upper 80s and 90s as far north as
Idaho and Montana, and over 100 in the Southwest. At noon Phoenix
reported 108 degrees.
   Morning lows were generally in the 50s and 60s in the Great
Basin and across the northern half of the country, with lows in the
40s in Idaho, Montana and Colorado.
   The low for the nation Sunday morning was 44 degrees at
Gunnison, Colo.
   Thunderstorms produced locally heavy rain in the Ohio Valley and
the middle Atlantic Coast early Sunday. Flooding was reported in
Valley Head, W. Va., drenched with 2 inches of rain.
   At least sixteen Western cities reporting record highs on
Saturday.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0052 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 1831EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Lockerbie     07-01 0371</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lockerbie,0383</SECOND>
<HEAD>Father of Flight 103 Victim Smuggled Fake Bomb Aboard Flight</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A man whose daughter died in the December 1988
bombing of Pam Am Flight 103 said Sunday he smuggled a fake bomb
past security officials at Heathrow airport and checked it aboard a
flight to the United States.
   In an interview with British Broadcasting Corp. radio, Dr. Jim
Swire said he took the bomb aboard an airliner several weeks ago,
but declined to name the airline.
   Swire said the device was made to resemble the bomb that
exploded on the flight, killing 270 people, including his daughter
Flora.
   The bomb is believed to have had a barometric trigger designed
to detonate at a specific altitude. The Boeing 747, bound for New
York, was at more than 30,000 feet over the town of Lockerbie,
Scotland, when it disintegrated.
   Swire said his device was packed inside a radio-cassette
recorder, but used marzipan icing instead of semtex plastic
explosives.
   ``We actually took marzipan icing because that's pliable and
feels like semtex...and looks similar on X-ray,'' he said.
   ``In addition, it had a dummy detonator which would have shown
up on X-ray, an extra printed circuit board, extra batteries,
pressure transducer and so on, all wired up in a form that would
have worked if the marzipan had been replaced with semtex,'' Swire
said.
   ``Our flight was selected for what they call special security,
and our cases were opened and searched in front of us. The
radio-cassette recorder was picked up, and I was asked whether I
had taken the batteries out, and I correctly replied, `yes, I had
taken the batteries out.' It was then replaced in the suitcase and
is now in America.''
   Swire heads a group of British relatives of disaster victims
called U.K. Families _ Flight 103.
   Transport Secretary Cecil Parkinson said he would call for a
full investigation, and Swire would be invited to meet with
department officials Monday to give details.
   ``We are already conducting a series of regular tests at
airports all over the country,'' Parkinson said.
   A spokesman for Heathrow airport said airport officials are
responsible for screening passengers and carry-on luggage, but
individual airlines are responsible for screening checked baggage.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0053 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 1835EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Bangladesh     07-01 0193</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bangladesh,0203</SECOND>
<HEAD>Heavy Rains Leave Hundreds of Thousands Homeless</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DHAKA, Bangladesh (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Heavy rains lashed southern Bangladesh
Sunday, after a week of flooding that has left hundreds of
thousands of people homeless and miles of crops destroyed.
   In the northern Sirajganj and Bogra districts, about 600,000
people were stranded and thousands of acres of crop destroyed when
rivers overflowed.
   In the southern resort town of Cox Bazar, most streets were
under almost three feet of water until late Saturday, said the
official.
   A district official in Sirajganj, 60 miles northwest of the
capital of Dhaka, said three children drowned Saturday, raising
this year's monsoon death toll to five.
   Displaced villagers have sought shelter on patches of raised
ground and many were living on roofs of concrete houses after their
mud-and-straw huts were swept away, the Bengali-language newspaper,
Ittefaq, said.
   Flooding is an annual problem in Bangladesh, where most land is
only a few yards above sea level.
   In 1988, at least 1,400 people were killed in massive flooding.
   Bangladesh, with a population of 110 million, is one of the
poorest nations in the world. Its annual per capita income is $160.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0054 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 1836EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Norway-Strike     07-01 0234</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Norway-Strike,0246</SECOND>
<HEAD>Striking Workers Shut Down Oil Fields</HEAD>
<DATELINE>OSLO, Norway (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Striking workers began shutting down oil
fields Sunday after last minute talks failed to settle a labor
dispute, the union said.
   The Norwegian Federation of Oil Workers said in a statement it
saw no end in sight to the strike, which began midnight Saturday.
   Norway's North Sea fields produced 1.63 million barrels a day of
oil and 1.8 billion cubic meters of natural gas a month in April.
Norway and Great Britain are Europe's largest petroleum producers.
   Municipalities Minister Johan J. Jakobsen, acting head of
government while Prime Minister Jan P. Syse is abroad, summoned
union leaders and business representatives large Saturday to urge
continued negotiations.
   ``He asked them to keep talking because roughly 25 percent of
Norway's national income comes from petroleum, and a strike could
be grave for our economy,'' said Kjell Finnerud, a spokesman for
the ministry.
   News reports estimated up to $31 million a day in lost income.
   Negotiations resumed, but quickly deadlocked ``because the
Norwegian Confederation of Business and Industry had nothing to
offer anyway,'' the 6,000 member union said in its release.
   The union said the 2.5 percent pay raise offered by the business
confederation was less than half of its demand.
   The confederation said the union's members average annual wage
of $49,000 is already 85 percent higher than the average wage in
mainland industry.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0055 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 1949EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Bulgaria 1stLd-Writethru a0664 07-01 0807</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bulgaria, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0664,0832</SECOND>
<HEAD>Elections Polarize, Rather Than Unite, Bulgaria</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS thruout to UPDATE with student rally, other
developments; ADDS strikers demanding disclosure of election
irregularities; EDITS to trim; No pickup.</NOTE>
<HEAD>An AP Extra</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ALISON SMALE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SOFIA, Bulgaria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The victory of former Communists in
Bulgaria's first free elections has polarized this Balkan country
rather than uniting it.
   Students have begun a nationwide protest that may swell into a
major movement.
   The students first occupied Sofia university June 11, a day
after a first round of elections indicated the Socialist Party _
formerly the Communists _ would triumph over the Union of
Democratic Forces opposition coalition.
   Over the next few days, students at major universities in Sofia
and several other cities joined the sit-in strike.
   On Sunday, about 15,000 students and supporters attended a
downtown rally in Sofia organized by a national strike committee to
back the protesters' demands.
   At first the media, the Socialists and even the Democratic
Forces ignored the students. But now they and their supporters are
taken increasingly seriously as a potential grass-roots revolt in
Bulgaria.
   Striking students claim they have collected 130,000 signatures
on petitions in their support, while a rival Movement of Students
for Democracy says it has gathered 50,000 signatures from strike
opponents.
   The Union of Cooperative Farms, an association of agricultural
cooperatives, has threatened to block the main roads to Sofia with
tractors and other vehicles unless the students end their strike by
July 11.
   Even the protesters agree that change won't come swiftly.
   The lackadaisical air that accompanies much Bulgarian activity
prevails at the university. A few hundred of the 12,000 students
are actually taking part in a sit-in, most lolling on scorched
lawns in the Balkan summer heat.
   The students began their strike to force disclosures of what
they claim were irregularities in last month's elections _ the
country's first multiparty balloting in 58 years.
   Their goals have since expanded to get the state TV director to
resign for alleged bias in reporting and to investigate President
Petar Mladenov's alleged consideration of using tanks against
anti-government protests last winter.
   Behind these aims, however, is a larger goal of creating a
changed society.
   ``The strike has shown the Bulgarian population that some people
can think differently and that it is their right to demand
things,'' said Nevyana Nikolova, an assistant English professor on
strike at Sofia university.
   ``It forces people to take sides, something the Bulgarian has
lacked over the years,'' said her colleague, Julia Stefanova. ``We
don't want a new government, we want a new system.''
   The end of hard-line Communist rule in Bulgaria came not, as in
Romania, Czechoslovakia and East Germany, through street protest,
but in a Communist Party coup in which some comrades ousted party
chief Todor Zhivkov.
   The Communists reorganized as Socialists. After peaceful
demonstrations by the fragmented but quickly growing opposition,
the Socialists initiated negotiations that led to the June
elections.
   In Sofia _ a Democratic Forces stronghold _ nearly everybody,
including most Western diplomats, was shocked by the Socialists'
211-seat victory in the parliamentary elections. The Democratic
Forces won 144 seats.
   Most people in Sofia have a tale to tell about what they call
``manipulations'' by the Socialists to secure votes in the
villages. There are allegations the peasants were warned they'd
lose their pensions, agricultural supplies or other benefits if
they voted for the Democratic Forces.
   Cooler heads recognize the Democratic Forces concentrated too
much on urban areas that the party probably would have carried
anyway.
   Whatever the reason for the loss, it has pitted rural areas
against towns, old against young, worker against intellectual.
   ``Fear of the known and fear of the unknown'' prevailed, said
Stefanova, referring to the opposition's fear of the Socialists'
past and the voters' fear of changes to come.
   Ironically, the outcome also complicated life for the victors.
Socialist Premier Andrei Lukanov has indicated his reluctance to
head a one-party government, preferring a coalition that might have
more chance of attracting sorely needed foreign investment.
   But the opposition is currently adamant it won't help the
Socialists solve the growing economic crisis created by their
mismanagement.
   The new parliament will serve a two-year term and write a new
constitution.
   Amid the anxieties, political intrigue and consumer shortages,
the shadow of Romania's street violence looms large.
   Sofia residents look with apprehension at pictures of the miners
that terrorized students and other government opponents in
Bucharest and hope the violence will not travel south.
   ``Sofia is not yet Bucharest,'' reads the caption on a
front-page picture in the weekly Sofia News. Inside the paper,
journalist Krassimira Ikonomova voices a more widespread sentiment.
   ``We are afraid,'' she writes, ``because we are not yet free
people. We are afraid that the first shy steps toward democracy
could fail, as happened in Romania.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0056 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 1958EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Hostages 1stLd-Writethru a0677 07-01 0372</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Hostages, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0677,0383</SECOND>
<HEAD>Iranian Official Says Reason for Optimism on Hostages</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: INSERTS 3 grafs after 9th pvs, `Mosavian was...' to UPDATE
with Iranian Interior Minister saying earthquake aid will not lead
to improvement in diplomatic relations. Pickup 10th pvs, `Two
American...'</NOTE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A London newspaper on Sunday quoted an Iranian
Foreign Ministry official as saying one of the 15 Western hostages
held in Lebanon could soon be freed.
   The Sunday Correspondent said in a report from Tehran that the
Iranian official, Sayed Hossein Mosavian, refused in an interview
to be more specific or to identify the hostage.
   But it quoted him as sayng, ``It is very optimistic news for
you.''
   The hostages _ six Americans, four Britons, two West Germans,
two Swiss and one Italian _ are believed held by pro-Iranian
extremists.
   Mosavian heads the West European bureau of Iran's Foreign
Ministry, the newspaper said.
   It quoted him as saying the United States and other Western
powers should exert influence on Israel to release Lebanese Shiite
prisoners.
   Israel on Sunday freed 416 Palestinian prisoners from detention
centers in what it called a gesture to mark the upcoming Moslem
holiday of Eid al-Adha, the Israeli army said. It was not known
whether there was any connection between the release and the
Iranian official's remarks.
   The release of Palestinian and Shiite prisoners has been a
longstanding demand of the hostage-takers.
   Mosavian was quoted as saying that Iran's influence in Lebanon
was limited, but that the United States and Britain had
``unlimited'' influence over Israel and its Phalangist allies in
Lebanon.
   In Iran, Interior Minister Abdollah Nouri said Sunday that
despite generous foreign aid for victims of the June 21 earthquake
that left 40,000 dead, Western nations will be disappointed if they
seek political objectives with donations.
   ``Bilateral issues between nations and governments, whether
general or fundamental, are not settled with such things,'' he said.
   Asked whether Iran wanted better relations with the United
States, one of the countries to send aid, Nouri said, ``No.''
   Two American hostages _ Frank Reed and Robert Polhill _ were
freed in April.
   Terry Anderson, chief Middle East correspondent for The
Associated Press, is the longest-held hostage. He was abducted
March 16, 1985.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0057 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 2006EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Iran-AmeriCares     07-01 0369</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Iran-AmeriCares,0384</SECOND>
<HEAD>Second Plane Leaves State With Aid for Iran</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WINDSOR LOCKS, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A relief agency distributed 40 tons
of supplies to earthquake survivors in Iran on Sunday, but the
official in charge of the shipment said it was ``embarrassing'' how
little U.S. aid had gone to Iran.
   A cargo plane with the supplies arrived in Tehran Sunday morning
and relief workers spent about six hours unloading it, said Stephen
Norman, vice president of AmeriCares, a New Canaan-based relief
organization.
   The plane, the second loaded by AmeriCares, left Bradley
International Airport on Saturday. Tacked to the supplies were
small signs reading ``Humanity is one body'' in English and Persian.
   An AmeriCares flight last weekend was the first U.S. relief
effort to reach Iran in 11 years. U.S. government relief supplies
were sent a day later.
   Doyt Conn, AmeriCares project director, said it was
``embarrassing'' that more U.S. supplies were not going to Iran.
``It's saddening. It's a shame,'' Conn said.
   AmeriCares has an abundance of supplies to send _ some were left
behind on Saturday's flight _ but needs nearly $250,000 to charter
the cargo planes for each trip, Conn said.
   ``If we can continue to raise the money to send these planes, we
will continue to do this,'' he said.
   Susan Myrick, the mayor of Charlotte, N.C., and Charleston,
S.C., Mayor Joseph Riley, have appealed to the nation's mayors to
raise money for survivors of the quake that killed at least 40,000
people in Iran two weeks ago.
   ``The concern I have is that people are not really willing to
reach out to the people of Iran'' because of longstanding tensions
with the United States, said Myrick, who was present Saturday for
the departure of the shipment.
   ``These people are just like us. They can't control what their
government does,'' Myrick said. Her city has raised about $1,500 in
donations, an amount she says is not nearly enough.
   When the first shipment arrived and the American gesture of
kindness was revealed, the Iranians ``were stunned. Then they said,
`You are welcome,''' said Katherine O'Sullivan, an AmeriCares
volunteer who speaks Persian.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Contributions can be sent to AmeriCares at 161 Cherry Street,
New Canaan, Conn. 06840.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0058 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 2010EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brite--TallFolks     07-01 0345</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brite--Tall Folks,0359</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tall People Hold Heads High In Moonrakers Club</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KATHIE DIBELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEWARK, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Members of the New Jersey Moonrakers Club
hold their heads high when they get together.
   They never meet in a place where they could bang heads on
doorsills, and they don't have to endure corny comments about
``How's the weather up there?''
   The Moonrakers Club is for tall people who prefer not to raise
the roof. To belong, women must be at least 5-foot-10, and men,
6-foot-2.
   ``It's a chance to walk into a room and stand up straight,''
said Lin Damon, club president, 5-foot-11{.
   ``I always slouched. It helped me gain new confidence. Tall
people become insecure at a young age,'' she said.
   Club rules are strict. If people don't measure up, they don't
get in.
   Applicants are checked in their stocking feet. No 5-foot-7 women
with three-inch spikes need apply, she said.
   Once in, though, allowances are made.
   ``We've had people shrink over the years, and they've maintained
their membership,'' Ms. Damon said. ``But you can't claim you
shrank before you applied.''
   Members share their large-size problems, such as houses with low
ceilings, uncomfortable airline seats and difficulty finding
clothes that fit.
   ``Why do stores think tall people only want to wear polyester?
We will spend money on clothes too,'' Damon said.
   The 100-member Moonrakers Club is part of Tall Clubs
International, a 50-year-old organization that ranks development of
the king-size bed among its biggest achievements.
   The Moonrakers' two tallest women are Maureen Ahlers of
Hackensack and Ann Riesenman of Butler, both 6-foot-3, she said.
Bob Burke of Woodridge leads the men at 6-foot-9.
   About the only thing members of the Moonrakers have in common is
height.
   ``We have different occupations, different levels of schooling
and a lot of different interests,'' said Damon, a purchasing agent
for Williams and Watts, a military procurement and materials firm.
   There's another plus. ``You can start up a conversation at a bar
with another tall person _ `You're tall, you might be interested in
this.'''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0059 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 1957EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Israel 3rdLd-Writethru a0737 07-01 0711</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0737,0732</SECOND>
<HEAD>Israel Releases Prisoners on Eve of Moslem Holiday</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 8 grafs to UPDATE with Iranian Interior Minister
saying West should not expect political benefits from earthquake
aid; Edits to Trim; Pickup 7th pvs, `It was...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By SAID GHAZALI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MEGIDDO, Israel (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Israel freed more than 400 Palestinian
prisoners from detention centers Sunday to mark the upcoming Moslem
holiday of Eid al-Adha.
   Freeing Arab prisoners is traditional on religious holidays. But
the timing of the release raised speculation it may be related to a
report that a Western hostage may be freed in Lebanon or to
Israel's efforts to make peace with Palestinians.
   At Megiddo prison in northern Israel _ site of the biblical
Armageddon _ the first dozen of so Arabs were released in the early
afternoon. Many flashed ``V for victory'' signs from the bus
windows.
   By Sunday night, the army said 416 Palestinian inmates had been
freed from facilities in the Gaza Strip, the Ketziot detention camp
and Megiddo.
   In the hostage report from Tehran, The Sunday Correspondent of
London quoted Sayed Hossein Mosavian, an Iranian Foreign Ministry
official, as saying a Western hostage could be freed soon without
any concession by the West.
   However, Mosavian also told the newspaper that the United States
and other Western nations should exert influence on Israel to free
its many Lebanese Shiite captives.
   In Iran, Interior Minister Abdollah Nouri said Sunday Western
nations sending aid for victims of the June 21 earthquake that left
40,000 dead should not expect political benefits.
   Asked whether Iran wanted better relations with the United
States, one of the countries to send aid, Nouri said, ``No.''
   It was not clear if Israel's Lebanese Christian militia allies
in Lebanon also intended to free prisoners for the Moslem holiday,
which starts Monday. The Israeli-financed South Lebanon Army
militia holds hundreds of Shiite prisoners at the El-Khiam
detention camp in southern Lebanon.
   While Israel also holds Lebanese Shiites within its own
territory, it appeared most of those being released Sunday were
Palestinians arrested in the 30-month-old uprising against Israeli
occupation of the West Bank and Gaza Strip.
   The Eid Al-Adha holidary, or feast of sacrifice, commemorates
Abraham's offer to sacrifice his son for God. In Moslem belief the
son is Ishmael. In Jewish tradition, Isaac was the son offered by
Abraham.
   Dozens of Arab families from the occupied West Bank waited
outside Megiddo prison for husbands, sons and brothers to be
released. But many complained those being freed were almost at the
end of their sentences.
   Subhi Abu Schedem, 18, from Hebron waited outside the prison for
his brother Nader, 16.
   He said Nader had nine days left of a six-month sentence for
stone-throwing and added: ``They only release prisoners who have
two or three days left and not those that have 10 months or more.
This is obvious propaganda.''
   Dan Naveh, a chief aide to Defense Minister Moshe Arens, said
the release of Arab prisoners is part of Arens' plan to coax
Palestinians into peace talks by easing daily hardships.
   Naveh said Friday that prisoners being freed will have served
the majority of a first sentence for participating in riots and
would include juveniles under the age of 14.
   According to army statistics, Israel held 10,430 Arab security
prisoners as of Friday.
   Of these, 4,341 have been convicted and 1,038 are being held
under emergency regulations allowing suspects to be detained up to
a year without charge or trial. The others are awaiting charges or
trial.
   Also Sunday, a new leaflet by the pro-PLO leaders of the
uprising called for Palestinians and Arab countries to boycott
U.S.-made goods to protest American policies in the Middle East.
   In the Gaza Strip town of Rafah, masked Palestinians fatally
stabbed an Arab suspected of collaborating with Israeli authorities.
   The victim was identified as Zaher el-Houl, 30. The army
confirmed the death and said police were investigating.
   El-Houl's death raised to 229 the number of Palestinians killed
by fellow Arabs since the uprising began in December 1987. Most
were suspected of collaboration or of dealing in drugs or
prostitution.
   A total of 721 Palestinians have been killed by Israelis since
the revolt began, and 45 Israelis have died in the violence.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0060 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 2011EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Lousiana-Disinherit     07-01 0363</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lousiana-Disinherit,0375</SECOND>
<HEAD>Louisiana Parents Can Now Disinherit Children</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW ORLEANS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A 165-year-old state law requiring that
children get a minimum share of their parents' estate, the only law
of its kind in the nation, was officially repealed Sunday.
   A parent can now disinherit a child for any reason _ or none _
as long as the child is over 23 and physically and mentally able to
handle his affairs.
   Proponents say it was about time Louisiana residents enjoy the
right to dispose of their property as they see fit. But critics
claim that in an era of divorce and remarriage the new doctrine
will remove an ancient protection for neglected children.
   Moreover, they say, the change will provoke intra-family warfare
and stir up years of litigation in the courts.
   ``This looks like a lawyer's dream and a courtroom's
nightmare,'' said attorney Catherine Soutullo.
   For 165 years, Louisiana has carried forward the philosophy of
France's Napoleonic Code, demanding that children get some portion
of their parents' estate.
   One child was guaranteed at least a fourth; two or more shared
at least half. Parents could cut their children off for only 12
reasons, ranging from failing to ransom parents from captivity to
failing to communicate with a parent for two years.
   Tulane Law School professor Cynthia Samuel said the new law will
expose state courts to ugly lawsuits by children trying to
invalidate a will on grounds that a beneficiary unduly influenced
the parent.
   She also predicted more people would make wills, which they must
do to take advantage of their new power to disinherit.
   ``You'd be amazed how much interest there is out there among
some people who've followed this very closely, and who've been
waiting to do this,'' Samuel said.
   Although Samuel acknowledged the old law sometimes forced
parents to bequeath wealth to adult children who did not need it,
she is more concerned about the loss of protection for children who
did need it.
   The Legislature changed the forced heirship law last year,
primarily at the urging of Chalin Perez, the former Plaquemines
Parish president who has been feuding with the children from his
first marriage for a decade.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0061 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 2012EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-TaxProtest     07-01 0372</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Tax Protest,0379</SECOND>
<HEAD>Thousands Show Up At Statehouse To Vent Anger Against Taxes</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By THOMAS MARTELLO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TRENTON, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Thousands of residents gathered at the
Statehouse on Sunday to protest a new package of higher taxes,
taunting Gov. Jim Florio and President Bush with chants of
``Florio, Bush read our lips: No new taxes!''
   The villain for most of the estimated 4,500 protesters was
Florio, the Democratic governor who proposed a higher and expanded
sales tax, a higher income tax, and increased taxes on items such
as cigarettes and liquor.
   The $2.8 billion tax package will be used to close a budget gap
of more than $1 billion, provide $1.1 billion in added state aid to
public schools and ease some property taxes. All but the income tax
took effect Sunday.
   The state sales tax, which increased from 6 percent to 7
percent, is the second highest in the country behind Connecticut's,
which is 8 percent. The increased tax also was expanded to include
some previously exempt items such as alcohol, cigarettes, telephone
bills, soap and disposable paper goods.
   Many in the crowd, chanting ``Recall, Recall!'' and ``Florio
Must Go!,'' held up rolls of toilet paper, one of several items to
be taxed for the first time.
   But the rally organizers stressed their anger toward a
Democratic governor did not mean they supported Republicans, who
this week attempted to make political hay out of the rally as a
prelude to next year's legislative elections.
   ``They make promises and they don't keep them,'' said John
Budzash, 39, a postal worker from Howell who helped organize the
rally. ``We can't take these tax increases. But the Republicans are
as much to blame as the Democrats.''
   Budzash said the organizers, calling themselves ``Hands Across
New Jersey,'' want the tax hikes repealed and a ``complete audit of
state government to see where our money goes.'' He said by August
the group wanted to give Florio a petition with the names of one
million people against taxes.
   The protest began when Budzash made a telephone call to radio
station WKXW and called for a Statehouse rally. Other listeners
responded and the station, which serves most of the state,
repeatedly plugged the rally.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0062 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 2013EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Newspage-No-Hitter    07-01 0203</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Newspage-No-Hitter, </SECOND>
<HEAD>Pitcher Tosses Another No-Hitter _ And Losses, 4-0</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CHICAGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Andy Hawkins of the New York Yankees pitched the
sixth no-hitter in major league baseball this season and the third
in less than 48 hours on Sunday, but lost 4-0 to the Chicago White
Sox because of errors.
   The only other pitcher to lose a complete-game, no-hitter was
Houston's Ken Johnson against Cincinnati in 1964. The Reds won that
game 1-0.
   With the bases loaded and two outs in the eighth inning,
Chicago's Robin Ventura hit a deep fly to left fielder Jim Leyritz,
normally a third baseman. Leyritz appeared in position to make the
catch, but the ball glanced off his glove for a two-base error,
allowing three runs to score.
   The next batter, Ivan Calderon, hit a fly to right that Jesse
Barfield lost in the sun. The ball bounced off his glove and
Ventura scored to give the White Sox a 4-0 lead.
   On Friday night, Dave Stewart of the Oakland Athletics and
Fernando Valenzuela of the Los Angeles Dodgers pitched no-hitters
in separate games. It was the first time in major league history
that no-hitters were pitched in each league on the same day.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0063 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 2010EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Speeders 1stLd-Writethru a0695 07-01 0645</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Speeders, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0695,600</SECOND>
<HEAD>Government Looks For New Ways To Slow Highway Speeders</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDs: SUBS first three grafs to CORRECT that government, not
insurance group, is looking into proliferation of radar detectors;
SUBS 14th graf, `It unleashes,' to conform as second reference to
Miller</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By DAVE BRISCOE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Government traffic safety experts, in their
never-ending effort to curb highway speeding, hope to use an old
weapon in a new way they believe will convince some heavy-footed
drivers to ease up on their accelerators.
   Federal officials are looking for ways to get stationary radar
units at highway construction sites, dangerous curves and other
areas. The idea is that speeding drivers who use radar detectors
will slow down, not realizing that the nearest trooper might be
miles away.
   Jeffrey Miller, deputy director of the National Highway Traffic
Safety Administration, said the plan would require Federal
Communications Commission cooperation. He said it could turn radar
detectors into safety tools.
   But advocates for radar detectors, which are owned by between 12
million and 15 million drivers, say the gadgets are the best
defense motorists have against radar errors and unwarranted tickets.
   Radar detector opponents, including the government and insurance
companies, categorize the devices with burglary tools. Both, they
say, are used by lawbreakers.
   Brian O'Neill, head of the Insurance Institute for Highway
Safety, said a study conducted in Maryland and Virginia showed that
one out of every eight cars has a radar detector, while nearly a
third of big trucks have them.
   The study showed that 22 percent of cars without the units
exceeded the speed limit, while more than 40 percent of those with
detectors drove faster than the posted limits.
   The study revealed as many vehicles with radar detectors in
Virginia, where they are illegal, as in neighboring Maryland, where
they are allowed.
   Laws banning radar detectors in Virginia, Connecticut, and
Washington, D.C., date back to the 1960s. The only recent statute
is a scheduled New York ban of the units in commercial vehicles.
   In California, state police must pace speeders the old fashioned
way because that state's legislature refuses to allow them to use
radar. However, some local police use it.
   Some insurance companies have tried to avoid accepting customers
with radar detectors. But the Government Employees Insurance Co.
(GEICO) has found it tough to defend its refusal of insurance to
radar detector users. In March, a Maryland court ruled against the
practice, and surcharges for detector users have been struck down
by insurance company regulators in several other states.
   ``We're not interested in people who tell us up front they're
planning to speed. We're not interested in lawbreakers,'' GEICO
spokesman August Alegi said.
   In 1986, Congress rejected a move to force states that raise
speed limits from 55 mph to 65 mph to outlaw radar detectors.
   ``It unleashed such a torrent of irate letters and telegrams
that, so far as I know, nobody in Congress has mentioned the
subject since,'' said the NHTSA's Miller.
   ``When something is that widespread and popular, it's difficult
to attack it successfully,'' he said.
   Miller said speed has been underestimated as a major national
safety problem with the focus on seat belts and anti-drunken
driving efforts.
   The NHTSA is backing an experiment on the Capital Beltway, the
busy freeway that circles Washington, D.C., in which a photograph
is taken of a speeding vehicle and a ticket mailed to the owner.
   The system, in which no tickets will initially be issued, has
raised the concern of the American Civil Liberties Union, the
American Automobile Association and other groups.
   ``There goes due process out the window,'' said Chuck Terlizzi,
Maryland coordinator for the National Motorists Association.
   Government and private safety advocates also are using or
considering other ways of catching speeders, including devices that
employ laser beams or measure speed without emitting a radar beam.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0064 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 2016EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Netherlands-IRA     07-01 0138</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Netherlands-IRA,0143</SECOND>
<HEAD>IRA Denies Involvement in Amsterdam Bombing</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Irish Republican Army denied responsibility
for the bombing of the British tourism office in Amsterdam, the
British news agency Press Association reported Sunday.
   The news agency said it was notified ``through the usual
channels'' that the IRA disclaimed responsibility for the attack,
which damaged windows at the office in the Dutch capital Saturday.
   The building also houses the South African national tourist
office and an office for Spain's Iberia Airlines.
   Dublin's Downtown Radio said it had also received word that
``the IRA categorically denies any involvement'' in the Amsterdam
attack.
   The IRA has attacked British targets in continental Europe as
part of its campaign to drive the British out of Northern Ireland
and unite the Protestant-dominated province with the overwhelmingly
Roman Catholic republic of Ireland.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0065 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 2019EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Philippines-US 3rdLd-Writethru a0749 07-01 0743</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Philippines-US, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0749,0763</SECOND>
<HEAD>American Peace Corps Worker Held by Rebels in Philippines</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: INSERTS one graf after 6th pvs, `Embassy spokesman ...,' to
ADD remarks by Scowcroft that U.S. officials heard of disappearance
last week; Pickup 7th graf pvs: Last week ...</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By EILEEN GUERRERO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MANILA, Philippines (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Communist rebels have kidnapped an
American Peace Corps member, but U.S. authorities said Sunday they
learned of the abduction only after other volunteers were ordered
to leave last week.
   Timothy Swanson, 26, of Cheyenne, Wyo., was taken by gunmen June
13 from his home in Patag, a remote village in the mountains of
Negros Island, Philippine and U.S. sources said.
   Swanson was believed the first Peace Corps volunteer kidnapped
by the rebels and the first American held by the New People's Army
since nine airmen were detained briefly in 1986.
   In Kennebunkport, Maine where he was vacationing, President Bush
called the kidnapping a sign of ``the age of the terrorist.''
   ``We've been very much worried about this,'' he said.
   Embassy spokesman Stanley Schrager said American officials
learned of Swanson's disappearance Saturday after trying to contact
him as part of the evacuation of Peace Corps volunteers from the
Philippines.
   But Bush's national security adviser, Brent Scowcroft, told
reporters, ``We first heard about it maybe a week ago, close to a
week ago.''
   Last week, the United States recalled the 261 Peace Corps
volunteers in the country after intelligence reports indicated that
Communist rebels might try to kill or kidnap them.
   American authorities had said previously that all the volunteers
were accounted for. The volunteers began leaving the Philippines on
Friday.
   Schrager said American officials rushed to Negros to discuss
ways to win Swanson's release, but said the United States would not
pay ransom for the Peace Corps worker's freedom.
   On Sunday, the retired Roman Catholic bishop of Negros, the Rev.
Antonio Fortich, said Swanson had been friendly with New People's
Army guerrillas.
   Swanson's father, Leonard, said in an interview in Cheyenne on
Sunday that his son knew rebels in the area where he worked on a
reforestation project but that he never considered them a threat.
``He tried to be friendly with all the folks in the village and all
who he encountered,'' Swanson's father said.
   ``I was dismayed, of course,'' to learn of the kidnapping, he
said. ``I guess here in Cheyenne we would ask for people's
prayers.''
   According to Fortich, four to eight armed rebels came to
Swanson's home in the Negros mountains last month and told his
Filipino wife, Merly, they were ``borrowing'' her husband. The
couple were married May 29 in a ceremony attended by Swanson's
parents, Leonard Swanson said.
   Fortich said the wife received a note from her husband last week
saying he was well but asking for his glasses, reading materials
and clothes. She left the items in a bag outside their home and a
rebel courier retrieved it at night, Fortich said.
   Swanson asked his wife not to notify authorities and she did so
only after hearing of the order to evacuate Peace Corps members.
   President Corazon Aquino's press secretary, Tomas Gomez, said
the embassy notified Philippine officials of the disappearance
Saturday. Gomez said the kidnapping might have been avoided if the
United States had consulted Philippine authorities on security.
   ``They refused to listen to a security briefing,'' Gomez said.
``Maybe if they did that, we could have prevented it.''
   Schrager said the embassy had dispatched diplomats to the Negros
city of Bacolod. Negros, 300 miles southeast of Manila, is a
stronghold of the rebel New Peoples Army, which has waged a
21-year-old insurgency and seeks to establish a Marxist state in
the Philippines.
   On May 29, rebels on Negros kidnapped a Japanese aid worker,
Fumio Mizuno, and are believed holding him in mountains near
Bacolod. Fortich has been trying to negotiate Mizuno's release.
   The U.S. decision to withdraw the Peace Corps volunteers drew
criticism from Philippines officials, who said the United States
was overreacting to the alleged threats.
   Although the move was expected to have little impact on
international aid programs, the withdrawal was embarassing to the
Aquino government, which is increasingly sensitive to its
international image.
   Communist rebels are believed to have killed eight Americans
since April 1989 but they had made no public threat against the
Peace Corps.
   U.S. officials also said the Peace Corps office in Manila would
remain open as a sign that the withdrawal was temporary.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0066 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 2041EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-ChurchBrawl 2ndLd-Writethru a0724 07-01 0404</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Church Brawl, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0724,0411</SECOND>
<HEAD>Traditionalists Use Force in Effort to Take Over Cathedral</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: RETRANSMITTING TO MAKE 2ND LD-WRITETHRU</NOTE>
<DATELINE>PONTOISE, France (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A fight erupted after Mass at the local
cathedral Sunday when traditionalist Roman Catholics, shoving the
vicar aside, tried to move in to celebrate their own service in
Latin.
   Punches were thrown, the organ sounded and candles went flying
down an aisle as the estimated 60 traditionalists tried to take
over the main altar at the St. Maclou Cathedral following regular
Sunday Mass.
   A policeman tried to mediate the brawl, which continued for more
than an hour, ending when The Rev. Andre Berrere agreed to say his
Latin Mass in a side chapel.
   The incident began about 11:30 a.m. when the group of
traditionalists, organized by the militant Committee Saint
Genevieve of Argenteuil, marched to the main altar of the cathedral
in this northern suburb of Paris.
   The cathedral vicar, the Rev. Jean-Marie Human, surrounded by
altar boys and other faithful, blocked the way to the main altar,
considered by church law the symbol of ecclesiastical authority in
the diocese.
   Several times, the traditionalists tried to shove aside the
vicar, according to witness accounts. At one point, Human sounded
the organs in protest as defenders moved into the choir area,
witnesses said.
   By 1 p.m., the traditionalists gave up the idea of using the
main altar for their Mass. They left after celebrating a Latin Mass
in a side chapel.
   No one was seriously injured in the melee.
   The attempted takeover of the cathedral was the fourth such
effort since the start of the year by the committee, which is
pressing the Pontoise diocese to put an unused chapel at their
disposal for Latin Masses.
   The Second Vatican Council (1962-65) suppressed the use of the
16th-century version of the Latin Mass and established the use of
the local language. The reform was intended to make the ceremony
more accessible to the faithful.
   Some Catholics dislike the new Mass, and have joined the
traditionalist movement of French Archbishop Marcel Lefebvre. He
was excommunicated two years ago for consecrating four bishops in
defiance of papal orders.
   Two years ago, Pope John Paul II urged bishops to provide a
``full and generous'' use of a 1984 decree allowing use of the
Tridentine Mass under special circumstances. His order was an
attempt to reach out to people uncomfortable with the new Mass.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0067 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 2048EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-LightningStrikes 1stLd-Writethru a0759 07-01 0346</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lightning Strikes, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0759,0353</SECOND>
<HEAD>24 Injured When Lightning Hits Pavilion</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: UPDATES throughout with details on scene, names of injured
children, comments; No pickup.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>KINGWOOD, W.Va. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Lightning struck a pavilion where members
of a hunting club huddled for shelter during a Sunday thunderstorm,
and 24 people were injured, at least four critically, officials
said.
   The 25 members of the Kingwood Pike Coon Hunters Club had been
holding bow and arrow target practice and sought refuge from
torrential rains that swept the area about 80 miles south of
Pittsburgh, said Ed Turnley, a Reedsville Volunteer Fire Department
member.
   A bolt of lightning struck a wooden support post on the
tin-roofed pavilion, and it burst into splinters, he said.
   ``It was kind of a state of confusion. People were scattered
everywhere,'' Turnley said. All but one of the injured were
conscious when rescue workers arrived, he said.
   The injured were taken to two hospitals in nearby Morgantown,
Turnley said. The four in critical condition included 13-year-old
David McDonald and 12-year-old Ronald Robinson Jr. Both boys were
from Morgantown.
   Two others, including 8-year-old Brian Plum of Dellslow, were in
good condition, while four others were in fair condition and four
in stable condition. Eight others were treated and released and no
status report was available for the two others.
   The victims complained of chest pains, burns and other ailments
associated with electrical shock, said nursing supervisor Tammy
Henderson at Monongalia General Hospital.
   Thunderstorms, hail and heavy winds raked portions of northern
and eastern West Virginia, knocking out power to 1,000 homes and
business, officials said.
   ``There were trees and power lines down all over the place,''
said Gary Shaver, a dispatcher for the Preston County Sheriff's
Department. ``A tree fell on a trailer and several trees fell onto
roads.''
   ``It's been really bad up here. We've had trees falling through
lines, trees uprooted, lightning. We have some very tired
linemen,'' she said.
   Barbour County, south of Kingwood, got an inch of rain in a
15-minute downpour, said Barbour County Sheriff's Department
dispatcher J.R. Carman.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0068 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 2051EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Bush 3rdLd-Writethru a0751 07-01 0800</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bush, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0751,680</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush Denounces Kidnapping of Peace Corps Volunteer</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 10th graf pvs, Bush hoped, with one graf to show golf
ended upbeat; picks up 11th graf pvs, Earlier Sunday</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By CHRISTOPHER CONNELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>KENNEBUNKPORT, Maine (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush on Sunday decried the
kidnapping of a Peace Corps volunteer by communist rebels in the
Philippines.
   The president, in a brief exchange with reporters after he teed
off on a round of golf, said, ``We've been very much worried about
this.''
   U.S. sources said Timothy Swanson, 26, of Cheyenne, Wyo., was
taken at gunpoint June 13 from his home in Patag, a remote village
in the mountains of Negros Island, Philippine. However, officials
said they only learned of the abduction on Saturday.
   The United States ordered its 261 Peace Corps volunteers home
from the Philippines last week because of terrorist threats.
   ``We pulled them out of there, they're coming out anyway,'' said
the president, who called the kidnapping a sign of ``the age of the
terrorist. It's not good.''
   A U.S. Embassy spokesman in Manila said U.S. officials did not
learn of Swanson's disappearance until Saturday when officials
tried to inform him of the evacuation. But Bush's national security
adviser, Brent Scowcroft, told reporters, ``We first heard about it
maybe a week ago, close to a week ago.''
   Bush, midway through an extended Fourth of July holiday weekend
at his Oceanfront home here, confessed to being in a foul mood on
the day his mother, Dorothy Walker Bush, was celebrating her 89th
birthday.
   ``It's just not one of the big bonanza days,'' Bush said.
   ``It's been that kind of a day. Lost in tennis, no fish, no
particularly good news from around the world. And, you know, just
one of those days.''
   Bush later changed his assessment when he made a birdie on the
13th hole of a local golf course. ``It's the second happiest day of
my life, from a bad day starting off,'' he told reporters who
pressed him on what the happiest day was. He thrust his right thumb
upward and said, ``Barbara.''
   Earlier Sunday, tourists sang ``Happy Birthday'' to Bush's
mother as she emerged from St. Ann's by the Sea Episcopal Church on
the arm of her son.
   ``Thanks for the greeting for my mom,'' said the vacationing
president, clad in a kelly green blazer, dark slacks and white
shoes.
   Mrs. Bush, whose father purchased the property at Walker's Point
that became the family's summer homestead early in this century,
appeared to relish the attention.
   Her birthday also was noted from the altar during the service by
both the rector, the Rev. Laman H. Bruner Jr., and Episcopal Bishop
Edward Chalfant, who delivered the sermon.
   The bishop praised Bush, who is here preparing for a NATO summit
in London this week, for ``your courageous witness'' for world
peace. He said the president over the past year has been ``an
instrument of God for the possibility of world peace and an
unimaginable global harmony.''
   Four generations of Bushes attended the service, including the
president's daughter, Dorothy LeBlond, and her two children, Sam
and Ellie, who helped pass the collection plates.
   The president is a vestryman of the 102-year-old stone church,
which is only open from the last Sunday in June until the day
before Labor Day.
   Bush later played tennis and golf on this third-day of an
extended weekend.
   On Saturday night, Bush received a call from Nelson Mandela, who
``thanked the president for his support for the struggle to end
apartheid'' and for the reception Mandela recived on his American
tour, said White House press secretary Marlin Fitzwater. The deputy
president of the African National Congress visited the White House
last week during his eight-day tour of the United States.
   Bush planned to grapple with issues affecting world peace Monday.
   Vice President Dan Quayle, Secretary of State James A. Baker
III, Defense Secretary Dick Cheney and Gen. Colin L. Powell, the
chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff, will join Bush and Scowcroft
at Walker's Point for a final strategy session before the NATO
summit Thursday and Friday.
   U.S. officials confirmed a report in Sunday editions of The
Washington Post that the United States at the London summit would
propose to eventually remove all 1,400 nuclear-tipped artillery
shells now deployed in West Germany and elsewhere in Europe.
   Bush also will huddle Tuesday with Treasury Secretary Nicholas
Brady and other officials to go over last-minute planning for the
July 9-11 economic summit in Houston with the major industrialized
nations.
   He will depart Kennebunkport for London on Wednesday evening
after a five-day stay in this seaside resort where he has come
every summer of his life except 1944 when he was flying bomber
missions in the Pacific during World War II.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0069 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 2050EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-PeaceCorps-Father 1stLd-Writethru a0775 07-01 0340</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Peace Corps-Father, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0775,0342</SECOND>
<HEAD>Swanson's Father Says Son Knew Members Of New Peoples' Army</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: CORRECTS spelling of Philippines in 6th and final grafs</NOTE>
<HEAD>With AM-Philippines-US</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CHEYENNE, Wyo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Peace Corps volunteer kidnapped by the
New People's Army in the Philippines knew several members of the
Communist group but never believed he would be targeted by the
insurgents, his father said Sunday.
   The U.S. Embassy in Manila said Sunday that Timothy Swanson, 26,
appeared to have been abducted June 13 by members of the rebel
group that has been waged a 21-year insurgency and seeks to
establish a Marxist state.
   Officials said Timothy Swanson's wife received a letter from him
last week saying he was all right and asking her to send some items.
   Leonard Swanson said his son had been stationed on the central
island of Negros since February 1988 and was working in a
reforestation project.
   ``He knew who some of the (New People's Army) people were and
because of the remote location he was assigned to, he tried to get
along with them,'' he said. ``He tried to be friendly with all the
folks in the village and all who he encountered.''
   Swanson and his wife, Lynne, visited the Philippines to attend
their son's wedding on May 29. Peace Corps officials informed them
Saturday that Timothy had been kidnapped.
   ``We were there about a month ago ... and he ackowledged that
yes, the NPA is present and that ... the NPA seemed to be leaving
the Peace Corps volunteers alone,'' he said. ``And, well, the
tensions ... didn't seem to be that present on Negros.''
   Timothy Swanson graduated from Cheyenne East High School in 1982
before attending the University of Chicago, where he studied
geography, his father said.
   Last week, the U.S. government recalled the 261 Peace Corps
volunteers in the Philippines after reports indicated that
Communist rebels might try to kill or kidnap them. U.S. Embassy
officials said they were unable to contact Swanson when the
withdrawal was announced.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0070 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 2116EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Colombia     07-01 0504</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Colombia,0520</SECOND>
<HEAD>Security Intensified After Government Renews Extraditions</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By STAN YARBRO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOGOTA, Colombia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Security was intensified in the capital
Sunday after the government extradited two suspected drug
traffickers to the United States _ the first such extraditions in
three months.
   Additional army checkpoints were set up in downtown Bogota and
patrols were increased apparently out of fear that terrorists
working for the traffickers might try to retaliate.
   The government had not extradited any drug traffickers to the
United States for three months. Officials gave no explanation for
resuming the extraditions.
   Two suspects, Rafael Juliao Fernandez, 44, and Luis Cabarcas,
60, were flown to the United States on a Drug Enforcement
Administration plane early Sunday morning.
   They were turned over to U.S. authorities at the Bogota
international airport late Saturday.
   U.S. Attorney General Richard Thornburgh, in a statement
released Sunday in Washington, said the extraditions demonstrate
``the continued determination of the Colombian government to battle
the Colombian drug cartel'' and ``to bring these drug dealing
suspects to justice.''
   The U.S. Marshals Service said Juliao is being held for
arraignment in New York City on charges of distributing and
conspiracy to distribute cocaine.
   Cabarcas is charged with leading a drug trafficking ring in
North Carolina, the U.S. marshals service said in Washington. He
was among 39 people indicted in 1985 on charges that included
conspiracy to possess and distribute 2 million methaqualone tablets
and more than 1,000 pounds of marijuana.
   Both men were held for six months in a Colombian jail while they
awaited the government's final decision on extradition. Authorities
are currently holding 13 other Colombians wanted in the United
States on drug charges.
   So far, 17 people have been extradited from Colombia to the
United States since the government of President Virgilio Barco
declared war on the drug cartels last August in retaliation for the
assassination of a presidential candidate.
   The Medellin drug cartel responded by declaring a ``total war''
against the government. At least 288 Colombians have been killed in
car bombings and other terrorist attacks since August.
   The most recent attacks have taken place in Medellin, Colombia's
second city, where the world's largest cocaine cartel is based.
Last Thursday a car bomb outside a Medellin police station killed
16 people and wounded 30 others.
   The drug lords have also hired gunmen to assassinate police
officers in Medellin. Two policemen were shot and killed late
Friday, bringing to 152 the number of police killed in the Medellin
region since January.
   In another development, Bogota's El Espectador newspaper
reported Sunday that the government had authorized military judges
to tap the phone line of anyone suspected of having links to drug
traffickers.
   The presidential decree authorizing the taps was one of several
emergency measures adopted last week to fight drug terrorism, El
Espectador reported.
   On Wednesday, the government decreed emergency measures,
including one requiring all Colombian families to register with
police. The Colombian press and many lawyers have criticized the
registration measure, saying it violates Colombians' right to
privacy.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0071 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 2056EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-AirShowCrash 2ndLd-Writethru a0763 07-01 0375</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Air Show Crash, 2nd Ld - Writethru, a0763,0379</SECOND>
<HEAD>Sixth Stunt Show Pilot Killed in Two Months</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: SUBS 4th graf, ```He came...' to CORRECT identification for
source; SUBS 11th graf, `A June 17th...' to ADD location of crash</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By JOHN F. BONFATTI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUFFALO, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A stunt pilot crashed a World War II-era
plane into the Niagara River and died Sunday in the sixth fatal air
show accident in the United States in five weeks.
   The body of the pilot, Giff Foley, 43, was found in the AT-6
plane under 18 feet of water near the river's entrance to Lake
Erie, officials said.
   Foley lost control during a manuever before thousands of people
attending a festival in Buffalo and across the river in Fort Erie,
Ontario.
   ``He came by on his first pass and he went inverted,'' said
Mason Dunn, a sound technician for the Coors Light Silver Bullet
jet team. ``It looked like he was trying to go to the American side
when it looked like he began losing altitude.''
   Also Sunday, a stunt pilot flying a vintage World War II plane
was killed in Ottawa, Ontario. Harry Tope, 47, of Mount Pleasant,
Mich., was completing the bottom end of a loop when the engine of
his Mustang P-51 sputtered and he crashed.
   A pilot crashed and died Saturday in Groton, Conn., while
attempting a stunt takeoff of his 1942 Stearman biplane in an air
show, state police said.
   Federal Aviation Administration spokesman Robert Buckhorn said
he did not have statistics on small plane accidents from last year
and could not comment on whether there have been an unusually large
number of fatal accidents.
   The other accidents, each claiming the life of the pilot,
included:
   _ a June 23, crash of a P-51 Mustang plane during an air show in
Abilene, Texas.
   _ a June 17 crash in Oklahoma City of a Soviet-made Sukhoi-26M,
which failed to come out of an intentional stall during a show in
front of about 75,000 people.
   _ a June 14 crash of a single-engine plane during practice for
an air show in Zeeland, Mich.
   _ a May 26 crash of a jet in a maneuver during an air show in
Tuskegee, Ala.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0072 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 2127EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Stallings-Barry     07-01 0285</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Stallings-Barry,280</SECOND>
<HEAD>Breakaway African-American Sings Support for Barry</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Mayor Marion Barry, under trial on drug and
perjury charges, got a rousing ovation Sunday at the first
anniversary service for Bishop George Augustus Stallings' breakaway
Roman Catholic congregation.
   Stallings, who was barred last week from attending Barry's
trial, praised the mayor in a rousing ceremony that included
traditional African dress, song and dance. The congregation joined
him in singing ``That's What Friend Are For'' to Barry and his
wife, Effi.
   ``They figured that since Mayor Marion Barry couldn't get
bought, he had to get caught,'' Stallings told his Imani Temple
African-American Congregation. ``That's why Mayor Marion Barry is
in trouble right now, he is too smart, too intelligent, too black.''
   Stallings also praised Effi Barry for standing by the mayor
while a parade of witnesses testifies about his alleged drug use
and love affairs.
   ``When I get married I want to find me a woman just like Effi
Barry,'' he said.
   Barry last week faced some of the toughest testimony yet at his
trial and prosecutors released a videotape of the hotel room sting
in which the mayor allegedly smoked crack cocaine.
   On Saturday, Barry was cheered at an anti-drug rally and told
the crowd his legal situation is ``just a matter of good lawyers
and good jurors.''
   U.S. District Court Judge Thomas Penfield Jackson last week said
Stallings and Nation of Islam Minister Louis Farrakhan could not
observe the trial as Barry's guests.
   Stallings, who was excommunicated from the Roman Catholic Church
earlier this year after forming his breakaway congregation for
disenchanted black Catholics, said he plans to join an American
Civil Liberties Union suit Monday with Farrakhan appealing
Jackson's decision.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0073 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 2149EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Fires-Services     07-01 0473</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Fires-Services,0491</SECOND>
<HEAD>Santa Barbara Residents Attend Services After Week of Havoc</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Fires</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RICHARD DE ATLEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SANTA BARBARA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   As firefighting helicopters
thundered overhead, residents attended religious services Sunday to
give thanks and seek solace after an unforgettable week.
   With the fire that ravaged their community finally circled, the
congregation at Coast Community Church of the Nazarene stood and
sang, ``This is the day the Lord has made.''
   ``It's good to be here,'' said Jim Hopper, who helped his
in-laws out of their hillside home, which escaped flames. ``In some
ways it's an act of God we were spared.''
   The widely scattered fires _ ranging from Santa Barbara 200
miles south to San Diego County, killed two people, destroyed or
damaged 520 homes and burned 22,000 acres, officials said.
   The church, just a few blocks from a devastated Park Highlands
neighborhood, is beyond a checkpoint where police threaten to fine
fire-scene gawkers $500.
   The Rev. Ira True told the congregation he had to rely on faith
just to get to his job.
   ``I told the highway patrolman, `I'm here to preach.' He said,
`That sounds like a good idea to me,' and let me in,''' True said.
   True read to the congregation from Isaiah, Chapter 43: ``When
you pass through the waters I will be with you.''
   But he did not read the next verse, perhaps just too much for
this Sunday: ``When you walk through the fire you will not be
burned. The flames will not set you ablaze.''
   The noise from a helicopter also punctuated services at Saint
Raphael's Catholic Church, where many parishioners lost homes.
Churchgoers there heard about the liturgy of rebirth through
baptism.
   ``The liturgy for today is appropriate for what has happened in
Santa Barbara,'' said Rev. Vincent McMurray. ``Let us remember that
through death and death situations, we enter into new life.''
   In the church hall, about 250 boxes of donated clothing awaited
parishioners who needed items.
   Parishioner Rosemary Varesio said many congregation members had
lost their homes, but none had yet come to collect the clothes.
   ``I guess they might not have any place to keep clothing,'' she
said.
   At the Congregation B'Nai B'Rith, flames came within two feet of
the building. Congregation members credit custodian Marian Grodel
with saving both the synagogue and its torahs.
   As flames approached, Grodel turned on the sprinklers, loaded
the temple van with the torahs and drove away.
   ``I had no time to talk,'' said Grodel, ``It was my duty.''
   Temple spokeswoman Evely Shlensky said the regular Sabbath
service on Friday ``was one of thanksgiving and commiseration''
because 18 families in the community lost their homes.
   ``When there is so much destruction you really realize the sense
of community,'' Shlensky said. ``There is the devastation, but the
families were taken care of.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0074 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 2159EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BodyPartsFound 1stLd-Writethru a0786 07-01 0267</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Body Parts Found, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0786,0269</SECOND>
<HEAD>Environmentalist Slain, Mutilated</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 5th graf to CORRECT spelling of name to Oliveira sted
Oliveria</NOTE>
<DATELINE>RACINE, Wis. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Body parts found dumped in two yellow
plastic trash bags along a roadway were identified Sunday as the
remains of an environmental activist last seen canvassing
door-to-door in a rural area.
   Sgt. William Vyvyan of the Racine County Sheriff's Department
identified the victim as James Michael Madden, 24, of Whitefish Bay.
   Vyvyan said Madden had been soliciting donations for Citizens
for a Better Environment when he disappeared last week. He was last
seen Wednesday evening in an area of scattered homes and farms.
   The garbage bags were discovered by area residents Friday along
a highway outside Racine about 2{ miles from where Madden was last
seen, authorities said.
   ``We are just shocked and tremendously saddened. We are numb,''
said Rosemary Oliveira, the environmental group's state
administrative director.
   Madden had worked for the group about two months and was
``extremely well-liked,'' she said. ``He was an avid
environmentalist. He was very devoted to the cause.''
   Asked about the circumstances of the death _ an environmentalist
found in plastic trash bags _ she said authorities had told her the
death is not believed to be related to the organization.
   ``My own feeling is this is some psychopath out there,'' she
said.
   Madden's upper torso was found in one bag and his pelvis and
legs in another, Vyvyan said. His head and arms have not been
recovered, he said.
   Authorities have said there were several stab wounds on the body.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0075 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 2202EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ItchySeas     07-01 0222</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Itchy Seas,0227</SECOND>
<HEAD>Studies Search for Cause and Cure to `Sea Lice' Welts</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WEST PALM BEACH, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   No one knows exactly what is
attacking bathers along a 60-mile stretch of Florida's Atlantic
Coast, but the so-called ``sea lice'' has left beachgoers with
nasty red welts on their bodies.
   Despite the name, health officials aren't certain that insects
are to blame.
   Jack Nolan, of the Palm Beach County Public Health Unit's
epidemiology group, said all officials know is the rash occurs most
often between April and July when the water temperature varies
between 78 and 82 degrees.
   Each spring and summer for the past decade, unsuspecting
swimmers from Deerfield Beach to Jensen Beach have returned home to
have their bodies erupt in welts that look like insect bites and
itch like poison ivy.
   ``It's itchy. It's uncomfortable, and my daughter ran a
temperature with it,'' said Mary Morgan of Boca Raton. ``We do like
the beach, and we'd like to go back. But we're a little leery until
we know what this is.''
   The county and several beach patrols have commissioned studies
to find the culprit and the cure for the ailment, also known as sea
bather's eruption and Gulf Coast itch.
   Pharmacists and beach patrols suggest remedies ranging from
Calamine lotion to Benadryl to a bath in wet oatmeal.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0076 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 2207EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Britain-Concert     07-01 0225</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Britain-Concert,0232</SECOND>
<HEAD>Charity Pop Concert Entertains 100,000</HEAD>
<DATELINE>KNEBWORTH, England (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   More than 100,000 fans were wild
delight as Paul McCartney launched into ``I Saw Her Standing
There,'' and ``Back in the U.S.S.R.'' during an all-star charity
concert.
   Pouring rain failed to dampen spirits at the charity concert at
Knebworth Park, 20 miles north of London late Saturday. Most fans
came prepared with umbrellas and plastic raincoats, but the sun
eventually broke through.
   The lineup included Elton John, Status Quo, Cliff Richard, The
Shadows, Phil Collins, Eric Clapton, Mark Knopfler, Robert Plant
and Pink Floyd.
   All donated their time to help raise the equivalent of $10.5
million for handicapped children and young musicians.
   The money will be divided evenly between the Nordoff-Robbins
music therapy project, which uses music to motivate children with
mental, physical or emotional difficulties, and a new school for
performing arts.
   Despite a heavy downpour as Tears for Fears kicked off the
day-long extravaganza, fans from all over the country were quick to
join in.
   Old favorites Status Quo got the crowd going with ``Rockin' All
Over the World.'' And Cliff Richard accompanied by The Shadows
received thunderous applause for ``Summer Holiday.''
   One of the biggest cheers of the night was for former Beatle
McCartney, who was introduced by James Bond star Timothy Dalton.
   The concert was televised around the world.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0077 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 2220EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Honduras     07-01 0385</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Honduras,0402</SECOND>
<HEAD>Union Optimistic in Negotiations with Chiquita</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By FREDDY CUEVAS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TEGUCIGALPA, Honduras (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The leader of striking Chiquita
employees said Sunday he was optimistic after officials from the
U.S. fruit company joined talks on worker demands for their first
pay increase in six years.
   ``The situation has improved _ mainly because Chiquita is now at
the negotiating table with us,'' union president Rene Ayestas said.
The union represents Chiquita's 10,000 workers in Honduras.
   Ayestas said there have been no results from the talks, which
began Saturday, but added that ``anything could happen if there is
flexibility on both parts.''
   Company officials had no comment.
   Chiquita workers went on strike Thursday and company officials
immediately branded the strike illegal and said they would not pay
higher wages.
   Thousands of other workers _ including those at Honduras' only
oil refinery _ struck in solidarity. The workers are still on
strike and Honduras is likely to run out of fuel early this week if
the labor dispute is not resolved.
   Business and political leaders have voiced fears the spreading
strike could destablize Honduras, the poorest nation in the
hemisphere after Haiti, and President Rafael Leonardo Callejas last
week dispatched a mediating commission.
   The commission and union officials have been talking for a week
but the company only joined the negotiations Saturday.
   The workers, who make an average of $15.32 a day, have asked for
a 60 percent raise. Their last pay increase was in 1984. After a
10-day strike last October, the company agreed to review wages but
has taken no action.
   ``There is a lot of distrust on both sides and they are asking
for many guarantees to any accords,'' said Congressman Mariano
Gonzalez, a member of the presidential mediating commission. ``But
what is important is that they are negotiating directly.''
   The Cincinnati-based Chiquita, formerly United Fruit, has been a
major power in Honduras since the early part of the century. It now
controls about 60 percent of the nation's banana exports. A
subsidiary of New York-based Standard Fruit controls most of the
remainder of the trade.
   Bananas are the leading export of this Tennessee-sized nation of
4.8 million. Honduras was the first Central American nation to be
dubbed a ``banana republic'' after the immense power wielded by
U.S. fruit companies.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0078 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 2308EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-StolenArt     07-01 0642</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Stolen Art,0666</SECOND>
<HEAD>Trail of Art Treasures Reads Like Hollywood Script</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DALLAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Lost treasure. International intrigue. A lone
adventurer.
   The script for a Hollywood movie? Nope, this is a job for Willi
A. Kotre, an investigator who followed a trail of musty documents,
Cold War secrets and just plain luck to discover the lost treasure
of the Quedlinburg Cathedral in East Germany.
   ``But please, don't call me Indiana Jones,'' the soft-spoken
German said.
   The 36-year-old Kotre, a researcher for the Prussian Cultural
Heritage Foundation in Berlin, in May pinpointed a local bank as
the place where a dead former U.S. Army officer's heirs were
keeping the missing gifts of Germany's earliest kings.
   Now, the art's original owner, the Lutheran Church of
Quedlinburg, is suing the family of former Lt. Joe T. Meador for
return of the treasures. Meador died in 1980, bequeathing the
artwork to his brother, Jack Meador, and sister, Jane Cook.
   Lawyers for the church contend Meador stole the treasures in the
final days of World War II, mailed them to the U.S. and kept them
in his hometown of Whitewright, about 60 miles north of Dallas.
German officials want to bring the artwork home as a symbol of
German reunification.
   ``It is very difficult to take a historical account and
successfully trace a missing item to an individual,'' Korte said.
``Usually, you need some kind of postwar event _ like someone
trying to sell the art _ and then you have a case.
   ``That's what happened here.''
   An East German who helped in the case, Gunter Wermusch, told The
Dallas Morning News in a telephone interview from Berlin that Nazi
officials hauled the cathedral's treasures into the cave as Allied
troops approached in early 1945.
   Soon after Korte's search began, a London book dealer offered
one of the missing treasures, a 9th-century illuminated manuscript,
to the researcher's employer.
   Officials said the $9 million offer was rejected in late 1988
because of the price and potential problems from buying art taken
from another country. But it provided a clue that the dealer
apparently worked for a U.S. resident, they said.
   Korte said he began looking for detailed accounts of Army units
near Quedlinburg in April 1945. Spending months in the National
Archives records tracing U.S. operations, he then went to the
National Personnel Records Center in St. Louis, the military's
service records repository.
   More than 1,000 names of soldiers assigned to the area were
found by Korte in over a week of research. He then turned to East
Germans and medieval art experts for further clues.
   Bavarian manuscript dealer Heribert Tenschert in February was
offered the illuminated manuscript, which had been in Europe
without a buyer for two years, the newspaper said.
   Tenschert said he relayed the offer to the Foundation of the
States, a private German cultural group. The foundation paid $3
million to Houston attorney John T. Torigian in April for the
manuscript, said Aoachim Fischer, a foundation director.
   Torigian termed himself a proxy for an unnamed U.S. client,
Fischer said.
   Dealers left out of the sale immediately began talking, said
Korte.
   ``Eventually, I learned the name of the bank, and it was short
work once I had that,'' he said.
   In May, Korte went to the First National Bank of Whitewright,
which was holding the artwork for the Meador family. Bank president
John Farley said he talked with Korte but gave him no information
about the treasures.
   Checks of his lists and a call to a Grayson County veterans'
group produced Joe Meador's name, said Korte. The Germans
negotiated in successive weeks with the bank and Torigian, who
represents the Meador family, the foundation said.
   But talks stalled on June 16, when word surfaced of a second
manuscript in Switzerland that was offered for $500,000.
   A Dallas judge has barred movement of the artwork.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0079 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 1650EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-Taxes 1stLd-Writethru   07-01 0805</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Taxes, 1st Ld-Writethru,0836</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dole: Bush Won't Try To Boost Income Tax Rate</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Inserts new grafs 8-11, ``On the CBS-TV ...,' to UPDATE with
comments from Republican pollster appearing on `Face the Nation.'
Pickup 8th graf pvs. Also moved on general news wires.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By LAWRENCE L. KNUTSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Senate Republican leader Bob Dole said Sunday
he does not expect President Bush to propose increased income tax
rates as part of a program of revenue enhancement.
   Rather, the Kansas lawmaker said he expects Bush to seek to
raise oil import fees and taxes on alcohol and tobacco.
   Sen. Daniel Patrick Moynihan, D-N.Y., said such an approach
clearly would not boost federal income enough to reduce mountainous
budget deficits.
   Moynihan said Democrats were ready to precipitate a $100 billion
forced spending cut next Oct. 1, as required by the Gramm-Rudman
deficit spending law, if Bush does not increase income taxes and
reduce the Social Security payroll deduction.
   New York Gov. Mario Cuomo said, meanwhile, that he believes the
top tax rate should be raised from its present level of 28 percent
to reduce the budget deficit.
   While the Democratic governor and prospective presidential
contender was not specific, he cited 33 percent and 35 percent as
targets for a new top tax rate.
   Dole and Moynihan commented on the ABC television program,
``This Week With David Brinkley.'' Cuomo was interviewed on
NBC-TV's ``Meet the Press.''
   On the CBS-TV program ``Face the Nation,'' Republican political
pollster Linda DiVall said Bush's apparent reversal on the tax
issue had angered many Republicans.
   ``There's been a lot of outrage this week. I don't recall a time
where I've seen more anger within the Republican Party over how a
president has led on a very important topic,'' she said. ``At the
same time, I think many people are saying, `He must know something
more than we do. What comes next?' ''
   She said it was apparent that the administration had
miscalculated potential public reaction to talk of taxes.
   ``I think they underestimated how clearly that `no new taxes''
mantra rang throughout the country, how much people wanted to
believe that,'' she said.
   Dole acknowledged that the president's new willingness to
consider ``tax revenue increases'' is not popular.
   ``But I think there are enough of us in Congress to put a
package together,'' even though it will be ``tough to pass,'' he
said.
   Moynihan said he believes a five-year agreement should be
reached that includes putting Social Security back on a
pay-as-you-go basis ``and stop using that regressive payroll tax.''
   Moynihan is proposing reducing the Social Security payroll tax
while stopping the government from using surplus Social Security
revenues to pay for other programs and, allegedly, to hide the true
size of the budget deficit.
   Asked if Bush is now committed to tax increases, Dole replied:
``I think the president will not go along with an increase in tax
rates.''
   Dole said most Americans believe a tax hike has occurred when a
larger bite is taken out of their pay check.
   He said he believes the increased tax revenue will come from an
oil import fee or from ``sin taxes'' such as those on tobacco
products and alcohol.
   Asked if he believes Bush is committed to such tax increases,
Dole replied: ``Oh, he's committed, no question about it.''
   ``You can't get there that way, Bob,'' Moynihan said.
   Dole was asked if Bush would veto an increase in income tax
rates at any bracket.
   ``I'm not saying he would veto it,'' Dole said. ``The president
now in a statesmanlike way has said, `OK, let's take a look at
revenues.' Now the Democrats are coming back and saying, `Oh, good,
we got him on revenues. Now let's take a bigger chunk out of
defense.''
   Moynihan was asked if Democrats will be the first to propose an
actual specific tax increase.
   ``No,'' he replied.
   ``Our proposal is to cut Social Security and give every working
family in this country an extra thousand dollars in income,'' he
said. ``After that we can talk about other issues.''
   Addressing Dole directly, Moynihan appeared to speak for other
Democrats when he said:
   ``You have a right to tell the president this: If he's as
committed as you think, he's headed for a crisis, he's headed for a
sequester, $100 billion on the first of October _ and close down
the national airports.''
   Moynihan was asked if it is not more likely that the
Gramm-Rudman requirements will not merely be loosened and
liberalized before the Oct. 1 deadline.
   ``I would have to say to my friend ... Bob, don't count on us to
change the number,'' Moynihan said.
   He was asked if the Democrats were ``ready to play chicken, to
go right for the cliff.''
   ``If you want to call it that, yeah,'' Moynihan replied.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900701-0080 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-90 1840EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-WestGermany-Reax     07-01 0578</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-WestGermany-Reax,0597</SECOND>
<HEAD>Kohl Welcomes Economic Union, Citizens Apear Mixed</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Germany, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MAUD S. BEELMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BONN, West Germany (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Monika Pein mailed a letter to a
friend in the United States Sunday, describing the incredible pace
of events in the two Germanys, and stamped it with a commemorative
imprint from the Post Office.
   ``I have just written in the letter that I really cannot grasp
that we (Germany) will again be together,'' said Mrs. Pein, who was
born near what is now Wroclaw, Poland. Her husband was born in East
Germany, near Halle.
   ``We think about this every day. I really cannot believe this,''
she said. ``I had not thought that in my life _ I'm over 50 _ I
would live to see this.''
   Chancellor Helmut Kohl called the economic merger of the two
Germanys that took effect Sunday ``the decisive step on the way to
the unity of our fatherland, a big day in the history of the German
nation.''
   But not everyone shared the enthusiasm, and the day marking the
first and most difficult step to unification passed with little
fanfare in this West German capital.
   The Post Office kept special hours so people could have their
mail stamped with an oval commemorative imprint noting July 1 as
the day economic, monetary and social union between East Germany
and West Germany took effect.
   But a postal worker said it was publicized too late to attract
many people, and only about 80 people had stopped by in the first
few hours.
   Reaction among West Germans to the economic merger with East
Germany and eventual full unification was varied. Some, like Mrs.
Pein, are realizing a dream; others say it is happening too fast
and worry what it could cost; still others, especially younger
people, feel little kinship with their brothers to the East.
   Manfred Brocker, a 43-year-old native of Bonn who says he's
documented political changes over the years with stamps, collected
one more for this historic day, but had mixed feelings.
   ``Basically, it's good,'' he said of the economic merger and
upcoming unification. ``But people are only talking about East
Germany and not at all about the West Germans. Nobody knows what it
will cost us or if it will be good with the currency.''
   ``One worries that it's happening much too fast,'' he said,
complaining there was too little information from the government
over what problems might result.
   And he was also not sure how alike the Germans were after 40
years of separation.
   ``It's a completely different generation,'' he said. ``Perhaps
in 20 years'' the differences will be blurred, he said, ``but not
so fast.''
   Detlef Bloss, born in Weimar, the small East German town that
was capital of Germany's first attempt at representative democracy,
said he was worried a ``catastrophe'' in East Germany could result
because of the large numbers of expected unemployed.
   Experts have predicted that anywhere from 500,000 to 4 million
East Germans could lose their jobs as state subsidies fall to a
market economy. One-third of all businesses are not expected to
survive.
   ``I don't know that it's right. It's all so sudden,'' said
Bloss, who fled to West Germany in 1978. ``The mentality is
different, and the two (economic) systems are different.''
   ``The people in East Germany are very greedy toward Western
money, but they don't know what the future will bring. That is the
problem, that is the worry I have.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
</Collection>
