<Collection>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0001 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 2326EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Cuba     05-13 0236</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Cuba,0244</SECOND>
<HEAD>Cuba Pins Economic Development Hopes On Private Foreign Tourism
Investors</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MEXICO CITY (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Cuban President Fidel Castro is encouraging
foreign investors to develop resort hotels in hopes of offsetting
an economic crisis with tourist spending, the Mexican government
news agency reported Sunday.
   Castro kicked off a new beach resort construction program at the
inauguration of a hotel built by private Spanish investors with
support from the Cuban government tourism developer Cubanacan, the
Notimex agency reported.
   At the inauguration Thursday, Castro said Cuba plans to spend
$10,000 to develop hundreds of beach sites, Notimex reported.
   The government is offering 10 years' tax exemption to private
tourism business developers, Notimex quoted Cubanacan director
Abraham Maciques as saying.
   The newly inaugurated Sol Palmeras Hotel is the first of eight
hotels to be built with private foreign investment and government
money in the cities of Varadero, Santiago de Cuba and Havana, the
news agency said.
   Spanish, Finnish and Soviet investors are working with Cubanacan
to build the hotels, Notimex reported.
   It said 2,000 new hotel rooms, are expected to be ready by the
end of 1990, and most of them will be in four-star hotels.
   The Sol Palmeras is part of a development in Varadero, 60 miles
from Havana, Notimex reported. The hotel has 400 rooms and 32
luxury suites.
   The Varadero tourist center is expected to generate $900 million
a year, the news agency reported.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0002 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 2326EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-SupremacistArrests     05-13 0210</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Supremacist Arrests,0217</SECOND>
<HEAD>Alleged White Supremacists Held in Alleged Plot</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SEATTLE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Three alleged white supremacists accused of
plotting an attack on minorities and homosexuals have been
arrested, the FBI said Sunday.
   Two men were arrested at a Seattle-area motel and a third was
picked up in Coeur D'Alene, Idaho, all on Saturday, Agent Steven
Pomerantz said at a news conference Sunday.
   The arresting agents seized guns, the components of a pipe bomb,
and literature from the white supremacist group Aryan Nations,
Pomerantz said.
   The arrest foiled an attack on minorities and homosexuals
planned for Saturday in Seattle, he said. He refused to give
further details.
   ``We stopped them well before they were able to carry out any
incident,'' Pomerantz said.
   Arrested near Seattle were John Winslow, 29, of LaClede, Idaho,
and Stephen E. Nelson, 35, of Hayden Lake. Arrested in Idaho was
James P. Baker of Coeur D'Alene, where Aryan Nations has its
headquarters.
   The FBI planned to charge the men held in Washington state with
conspiracy, firearms and explosives violations, Pomerantz said.
They were scheduled for arraignment Monday. The other man was
scheduled for a court appearance Monday in Idaho, he said.
   The arrests were part of a counterterrorism investigation
involving the Aryan Nations, Pomerantz said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0003 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 2351EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-NewZealand-Quake 1stLd-Writethru a0664 05-13 0293</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-New Zealand-Quake, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0664,0297</SECOND>
<HEAD>RETRANSMITTING a0403 to fix writethru sequence</HEAD>
<HEAD>Earthquake Damages Buildings in New Zealand</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 2 grafs to UPDATE with officials saying strongest
quake on land in New Zealand in 22 years. Picks up 3rd graf pvs,
`The temblor..'</NOTE>
<DATELINE>WELLINGTON, New Zealand (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A strong earthquake struck
northern New Zealand on Sunday, toppling a two-story building and
cracking concrete beams in a shopping mall but causing no injuries,
officials said.
   The quake in the town of Dannevirke, which measured 6.7 on the
Richter scale, was the strongest to hit New Zealand in 22 years,
according to the government's department of scientific and
industrial research.
   The temblor, which also smashed windows in several buildings,
was felt throughout the region and as far away as the capital,
Wellington.
   Sue Emery, editor of the Dannevirke Evening News, said police
had blocked off the town's main street to clean up the debris from
a two-story building that collapsed and to clear up broken glass.
   There was no power in the town for an hour after the temblor.
   ``The quake felt horrendous,'' Ms. Emery said. ``It's pretty
chaotic here. People are going in all directions.''
   Marion Leiba, a spokeswoman for the Australian Seismological
Center in Canberra, said the epicenter of the quake appeared to be
offshore, roughly 65 miles southeast of the north island town of
Napier.
   Dannevirke police spokesman Les Trigg confirmed that one
building had collapsed and said a shopping mall had been sealed off
after large concrete beams cracked, exposing the steel reinforcing.
   The Richter scale is a guage of the energy released by an
earthquake, as measured by the ground motion recorded on a
seismograph. A quake measuring 6 on the scale can cause severe
damage.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0004 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 0017EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Deaths 1stLd-Writethru a0596 05-13 0218</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Deaths, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0596,0223</SECOND>
<NOTE>Eds: An AMs separate moved on Hoss as a0551</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<HEAD>Leila Hoss</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BEIRUT, Lebanon (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Leila Hoss, the wife of Prime Minister
Salim Hoss and a social worker who cared for Lebanon's orphans and
elderly, died at American University Hospital on Saturday at age 61.
   Sources close to family, who spoke on condition of anonymity,
said she suffered from lung cancer and diabetes.
   Mrs. Hoss supervised an orphanage and a home for the aged in
Moslem west Beirut. She also served on the boards of several
schools that cared for needy children.
   While many other politicians' wives fled Lebanon's vicious
15-year-old civil war, Mrs. Hoss never left the country, even
though her husband narrowly escaped death in three bombings between
1984 and 1989.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>John E. Davis</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BISMARCK, N.D. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   John E. Davis, former North Dakota
governor and U.S. civil defense director, died Saturday at his
winter home in Rancho Mirage, Calif. He was 77.
   Davis, a Republican, served two terms as governor from 1957 to
1960.
   He had been in declining health for some time, and had suffered
strokes, said his son, John E. Davis, Jr. The son didn't know the
exact cause of death.
   Davis served as U.S. Civil Defense director from 1969 through
1977.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0005 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 0020EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-PoliceShooting     05-13 0187</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Police Shooting,0193</SECOND>
<HEAD>Knife-Wielding Man Slain by Police</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HIALEAH, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A knife-wielding man who reportedly
threatened to kill his mother was fatally shot by police after a
standoff that lasted more than four hours Saturday night,
authorities said.
   The standoff began after the man, whom police wouldn't identify,
pushed his mother out of his apartment and barricaded the door
around 4:30 p.m., said police Sgt. Jorge Hierro.
   ``He was armed with a large knife attached to a stick,'' Hierro
said. ``We called in our SWAT team and our hostage negotiating team
and they spent some time out here trying to talk the man into
coming out and surrendering himself.''
   Police in this Miami suburb were told the man had threatened to
kill his mother, Hierro said.
   ``At some point later the man came out of the apartment and
attacked the SWAT officers that were standing outside the door,''
Hierro said. The man was shot by officers.
   The man was airlifted to Jackson Memorial Hospital in Miami
around 9 p.m., and died there minutes later, he said.
   No police officers were injured, Hierro said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0006 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 0026EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Heston-GunControl     05-13 0244</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Heston-Gun Control,0250</SECOND>
<HEAD>Charlton Heston Blasts Proposed N.J. Assault Weapon Ban</HEAD>
<DATELINE>EDISON, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Oscar award-winning actor Charlton Heston
blasted a gun-control bill pending in the state Legislature at an
annual dinner Saturday night sponsored by a sportsmen's association.
   ``New Jersey was the first state to ratify the Bill of Rights,''
Heston told a wildly enthusiastic crowd of 1,300 gun advocates. ``I
will not stand idly by while (Gov. Jim Florio) tries to be the
first one to rescind it.''
   The state Senate next week is to consider a controversial bill
to ban assault weapons, a top priority of the Democratic governor.
Lawmakers who drafted the compromise bill say it would protect gun
collectors and target-shooters but would still be the toughest such
law in the nation.
   Heston, a life member of the National Rifle Association famed
for such biblical screen roles as Moses and Ben Hur, was invited by
the Coalition of New Jersey Sportsmen to speak at its annual ``We
The People'' Liberty dinner at a restaurant in this northern New
Jersey city.
   The 65-year-old Beverly Hills, Calif., resident said he was not
paid for his services.
   ``I get paid for acting and I'm not acting here,'' Heston said.
   Heston told reporters he made the appearance because the
proposed legislation would go farther than laws in any other state
to limit the right to bear firearms.
   ``For that reason, trip across the country was worthwhile,'' he
told a news conference.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0007 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 0108EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-ComicRelief 2ndLd-Writethru a0620-23 05-13 0315</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Comic Relief, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0620-23,0322</SECOND>
<HEAD>Comedy Show Prompts Viewers to Contribute to Homeless</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with six grafs to UPDATE amount raised to at least $4.7
million, ADD quote from producer, ADD amount of average pledge.
EDITS to conform. No pick up.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A parade of comedians, actors and high-kicking
Rockettes prompted cable television viewers and others Friday to
pledge at least $4.7 million to help the homeless.
   ``Comic Relief '90,'' telecast by HBO, was staged at Radio City
Music Hall, the first of the four specials to originate from New
York.
   The previous three shows, all held in Los Angeles, raised more
than $8.7 million.
   The $4.7 million figure did not include pledges from West Coast
viewers, who were watching the program on a tape delay.
   The average pledge was $44.70, up more than $11 over last year,
said Bob Zmuda, president of Comic Relief and a producer of the
show.
   ``People care more and they trust us. They see the dollars
working in their communities,'' Zmuda said of the rise in the
average pledge.
   Home Box Office, a pay channel, lifted the scrambling it
normally puts over its signal so affiliates could carry the show to
basic cable subscribers.
   Comedians Billy Crystal, Whoopi Goldberg and Robin Williams were
hosts of the event, opening the show with impersonations that poked
fun at some of New York's celebrities.
   After taking a few steps with the Rockettes, Crystal and
Williams _ in white tie _ and Goldberg _ in a Rockettes costume _
asked viewers to contribute by calling a toll-free telephone number.
   Throughout the show, celebrities reminded viewers: ``Comic
Relief _ it's no joke,'' referring to the plight of the homeless.
   Canada Dry USA, the soft-drink company, donated $500,000 to the
effort and helped promote the event.
   Zmuda said $700,000 was raised from ticket sales at Radio City
Music Hall.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0008 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 0117EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-ChildrenAttacked 1stLd-Writethru a0627 05-13 0310</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Children Attacked, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0627,0314</SECOND>
<HEAD>Four Children Attacked, Suspect Wounds Self, Police Say</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 8th graf to CLARIFY condition of other children, baby
sitter, when 7-year-old taken to hospital. Pick up 9th graf, `There
were ...'</NOTE>
<DATELINE>LITCHFIELD, Ill. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An 11-year-old boy was slain and three
other children were wounded Saturday, and a man who'd been
babysitting the children was found with apparently self-inflicted
knife wounds, authorities said.
   Law enforcement officers began investigating after a hospital
alerted them that injuries suffered by a 7-year-old girl who had
been brought for treatment might have been caused by an assault,
police said in a statement.
   When police went to the victim's home in this city about 50
miles northeast of St. Louis, they found the slain boy, the man and
the other wounded children, 11- and 13-year-old girls, the
statement said.
   All the children, including the 7-year-old _ were treated at St.
Francis Hospital and released. State police said the man, who is
about 30 years old and considered a suspect, was being treated at
St. John's Hospital in Springfield.
   Police would release no details of the injuries, nor the names
of the victims and the man.
   Police plan to seek a warrant Monday, the statement said.
   Montgomery County Coroner Rick Broaddus said he understood the
suspect was caring for the children while the parents were away.
   The parents came home and rushed the girl to the hospital,
apparently unsuspecting the babysitter might have caused her
injuries, state police said. The other children and the baby sitter
were apparently not hurt when the girl was taken to the hospital,
state police said.
   There were conflicting reports about whether the couple were
parents of all the children.
   Police said they were seeking no one else in the crime. They
declined to comment on any other details of the case.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0009 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 0125EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-People-Clay 1stLd-Writethru a0626 05-13 0376</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People-Clay, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0626,0386</SECOND>
<HEAD>Despite Defections, Clay Appears On `Saturday Night Live'</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: INSERTS 1 graf after 5th, `A guardian ...' to UPDATE with
shouts from audience.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Andrew Dice Clay's trademark lewd, raucous humor
was tempered somewhat by a five-second delay that took some of the
live out of ``Saturday Night Live.''
   ``How are ya?'' Clay said in his opening monologue. ``That's
about all I can say tonight. Know what I mean?''
   Clay poked fun at the controversy surrounding his appearance,
which prompted one cast member and the scheduled musical guest to
drop plans to appear in the show.
   He opened the show with a spoof of the movie classic ``It's A
Wonderful Life.''
   A ``guardian devil'' showed him the ``evils'' that could have
happened if he'd never been born and hadn't appeared on the show,
including a 70-minute monologue by another host.
   Clay's monologue was interrupted by audience members who
shouted, ``Clay, Clay, go away.''
   The tape delay enabled NBC to bleep out obscenities or anything
else the network deemed unsuitable for broadcast. The show airs
live only in the Eastern and Central time zones, and is shown on a
tape-delayed basis in western time zones.
   ``Saturday Night Live'' spokeswoman Rosemary Keenan said there
was ``stepped-up security,'' but there had been no threats made by
those protesting the show.
   NBC security officers used hand-held metal detectors to scan
members of the audience entering the studio. About a dozen police
officers were outside the network's New York studios, but there
were no protesters.
   Clay's act includes explicit sexual references and has been
denounced as homophobic, racist and sexist.
   Nora Dunn, who has been a member of the ``Saturday Night Live''
cast since the 1985-86 season, refused to perform in this week's
show because she considers Clay's humor degrading and repulsive.
   Pop singer Sinead O'Conner decided not to appear after her
publicist was alerted by the National Organization for Women and
the singer reviewed tapes of Clay's act.
   Keenan said that to her knowledge only one NBC affiliate, a UHF
station in Elmira, N.Y., had refused to broadcast the show.
   Keenan said she would not know until Monday if any other of
NBC's 208 affiliates refused to carry the 1{-hour-long program.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0010 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 0135EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Floods 3rdLd-Writethru a0630 05-13 0835</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Floods, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0630,0859</SECOND>
<HEAD>Flood Evacuation Warning Affects 7,000 As Levees Soften, Rain
Falls</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 17th graf, `Upstream in ...' to CORRECT Garland City to
Garland.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos XGR1,DN6</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROGER PETTERSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   National Guardsmen and volunteers rushed to sandbag
water-softened levees Saturday and 7,000 people were under an
evacuation warning because of the worst flooding in parts of Texas,
Oklahoma, Arkansas and Louisiana since the early 1900s.
   Fierce storms dumped 2 to 4 inches of rain on northwestern
Louisiana, where the Red River already was rising from water
draining down from the Oklahoma-Texas border area. Heavy rain also
fell in nearby northeastern Texas and an additional 2 to 3 inches
of rain was possible during the weekend, officials said.
   Poisonous snakes and fire ants driven out of cover by the water
made emergency workers nervous.
   Water had inundated more than 250,000 acres of Arkansas farmland
and more than 18,000 cattle were stranded, officials said. In
Texas, flooding had caused between $500 million and $700 million in
agricultural damage, with millions more to homes and roads.
Hundreds of Texas cattle have drowned in floodwater since Thursday.
   Over the past three weeks, 12 deaths have been blamed on
flooding in Texas and one in Oklahoma.
   The Federal Emergency Management Agency on Saturday declared
four more Texas counties disaster areas from storms and flooding
that began April 15, bringing the total to 29.
   Along Texas' rampaging Trinity River, about 500 residents
voluntarily left subdivisions downstream from the Lake Livingston
Dam after Liberty County Judge Dempsie Henley issued an evacuation
warning for 7,000 people in low-lying areas.
   He said officials projected that four to five times the normal
discharge would go over the dam's spillway when the Trinity's flood
crest reaches the reservoir.
   ``Tuesday through Friday, we will have the crest come in here
and we will have a major, dangerous flood _ the highest in the
history of the county since the lake was built,'' Henley said.
   Already Saturday, every road and bridge leading into the eight
or so housing developments along the Trinity was as much as 6 feet
under water.
   ``The only transportation is by boat,'' said Henley, adding that
some people wanted to stay to guard their property.
   Houston County Judge John Musgrove estimated that at least 500
head of cattle have drowned in his county, which is about 130 miles
southeast of Dallas.
   In Louisiana, forecasters said the Red River would reach a
45-year high in Shreveport by early this week, although no major
flooding was expected in the city.
   The U.S. Army Corps of Engineers said the volume of water
expected to move through the region would exceed that of record
floods in 1927 and 1957, but that levees and other flood control
measures built since then would prevent a disaster.
   Downstream in Avoyelles Parish, National Guardsmen arrived
Saturday to help finish a five-mile levee that about 50 farmers
started building themselves Friday with farm machinery to protect
cropland from the rising river.
   ``That's a major undertaking to build something that long that
fast,'' said Michael Logue, spokesman for the Corps of Engineers
district in Vicksburg, Miss.
   Upstream in Arkansas, volunteers sandbagged a levee at Garland,
where the river threatened U.S. 82, the only major thoroughfare
still open into the Texarkana area from the Arkansas side.
Westbound lanes of Interstate 30 were closed at Fulton, where the
river crested around 34 feet Friday, 7 feet above flood stage.
   ``It's going to maintain a crest like that for at least 72 hours
and maybe longer because we've got rain that will affect the
river,'' said state emergency official Gary Talley. ``Basically,
all the levees along that area are threatened because of the high
water and long crest period.''
   In the northeastern corner of Texas, officials were concerned
about a 4- to 5-mile section of levee holding back the Red River
north of Texarkana.
   ``The levee is continuing to deteriorate a little bit because
the ground is totally saturated from rains. It's like walking on
Jell-O,'' said Dave Hall, Texarkana emergency management
coordinator.
   Some volunteers sandbagging the levees overnight encountered
poisonous snakes.
   ``In addition to worrying about the water pressure on the levee,
it is spooky when you are down there with only a flashlight and
suddenly walk up on a water moccasin or two,'' Hall said.
   Elsewhere in Texas, north of Liberty, wildlife officials
collected a 16-foot alligator that was washed onto a highway
Saturday, said Jim Mitchum, Liberty County emergency coordinator.
   We're not known for alligators in this area,'' he said. ``I
guess it just came out of the swamps.''
   Mitchum said the flooding also brought out floating masses of
fire ants, named for their sting.
   ``And there's nothing like seeing fire ants piled a foot high
coming right at you,'' he said.
   In Oklahoma, forecasters Saturday predicted at least a two-day
respite from rain in the state's southern and eastern sections.
   ``We've switched from a response to a recovery mode,'' state
Civil Defense Director Woodrow Goins said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0011 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 0753EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i BC-Israel-Desecration     05-13 0491</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Israel-Desecration,0505</SECOND>
<HEAD>Jewish Graves Desecrated in Israel</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HAIFA, Israel (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   About 300 Jewish tombstones were desecrated
in a Haifa cemetery with spray-painted slogans, including some that
called on Arabs to ``kill the Jews,'' officials said Sunday.
   National Police Commissioner Yaacov Turner said investigators
were uncertain if the desecration was the work of Arab extremists.
   ``We must deal very sensitively (with the issue)...because no
one can say at this moment who did it and how,'' he said.
   All the slogans were written in Hebrew. Noam Gabrieli, a city
official, said the Hebrew was grammatical and the language was not
typical of that used in Palestinian leaflets. He said the
desecration therefore may have been the work of a mentally unstable
person rather than Arab radicals.
   A police anti-riot squad was sent to the Kfar Samir Cemetery to
prevent any violent demonstrations by relatives and other Israelis
who rushed to the scene after the news was reported on Israeli
radio stations.
   The desecration was condemned by Jewish and Arab leaders alike,
and Mayor Arieh Gurel called on all Haifa residents to keep calm.
   ``This is a sick action from people who learned from the
Neo-Nazis. We will cutoff the hands of those who did this,'' Gurel
told a reporter.
   Gurel and Turner suggested the incident in Haifa was inspired by
the desecration of 34 graves in the French town of Carpentras where
one corpse was dug up and impaled on a umbrella. Four skinheads
were questioned and released.
   The desecretion in Israel took place in two sections of the
Haifa cemetery, apparently during the Jewish Sabbath when guards
were not present.
   Haifa, a Mediterranean port city in northern Israel where 10
percent of the 220,000 population is Arab, has been symbol of
Arab-Israeli coexistence despite the 30-month-old Palestinian
uprising in the occupied territories.
   Yosef Yisraeli, whose mother and mother-in-law are buried in
Kfar Samir, told reporters at the scene ``I saw the horrible sight,
and my blood boiled.''
   Israel radio broadcast an interview with one grieving relative
who weeped uncontrollably as he said, ``Kill them, kill them and
don't kill them gently.''
   Another man, who said he was a taxi driver but declined to give
his name, told a reporter he rushed to the cemetery even though
none of his relatives were buried there because ``I couldn't
believe my ears.''
   The man said he prayed over a grave that had been painted with a
slogan that said ``Mubarak: kill the Jews,'' a reference to
President Hosni Mubarak of Egypt, which has a peace treaty with
Israel. ``I prayed there because Mubarak is supposed to represent
peace,'' he said.
   A memorial for the pre-state Jewish Haganna militia in the older
section of the cemetery was also scrawled with slogans.
   One slogan spray-painted on a grave said: ``Moslem Brothers:
destroy the Jews and Found Palestine.'' Still others called on Arab
villages and Arab leaders such as Iraq's Saddam Hussein to ``burn
the Jews.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0012 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 1007EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i BC-Madagascar 5thLd-Writethru a0643 05-13 0433</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Madagascar, 5th Ld-Writethru, a0643,0444</SECOND>
<HEAD>Soldiers Rout Dissidents From Radio Station in Madagascar</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: New thruout to UPDATE with dissidents captured. No pickup.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By CHRISTIAN CHADEFAUX</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ANTANANARIVO, Madagascar (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Soldiers stormed the national
radio station on Sunday and arrested a handful of dissidents who
occupied the building and claimed in a broadcast that the
government had been overthrown.
   The soldiers fired tear gas and bullets as they retook the
building, and the dissidents apparently returned their gunfire.
   Witnesses reported no casualties, but a Madagascar opposition
group in Paris quoted unidentified people on the island as saying
that 50 people died.
   There were no other reports of disturbances in this Indian Ocean
nation off the east coast of Africa. The government said in a later
broadcast that no coup had taken place and that it remained in
control of the island.
   The government did not say if casualties occurred.
   Witnesses said soldiers took about 10 dissidents from the
state-run Radio Madagascar station in Antananarivo, the capital,
while retaking the building several hours after the dissidents
occupied it early Sunday morning.
   ``There was fighting between the rebels and security forces that
has reportedly ended,'' a U.S. Embassy official said in a telephone
interview from Madagascar. ``The crowd in front of the station has
been dispersed.''
   The official spoke on condition of anonymity.
   Soldiers apparently fired the tear gas to disperse a crowd of
5,000 people who milled around the radio station, located near the
island's Hilton Hotel. It was not known whether they supported the
rebels or were simply curious.
   ``Tear gas canisters were fired off right in front of the Hilton
Hotel,'' a Dutch guest said in a telephone interview in the
afternoon. ``There are still quite a few people in the street at
the moment.''
   fter the dissidents occupied the station Sunday morning, a woman
came on the air and called on the population to rise up against the
government. However, her broadcast was cut off after about 45
minutes.
   President Didier Ratsiraka has led this country of about 10
million people since he was installed by the military in June 1975.
The country gained independence from France in 1960.
   On July 24, 1989, six armed men took over the national radio and
claimed the government had been toppled. However, the government
recaptured the station, and there was no violence elsewhere.
   In their broadcast at the time, those rebels claimed that
opposition political leaders had replaced the president's
government.
   After Ratsiraka was re-elected on March 12, 1989, the opposition
charged the election was fraudulent and demanded his resignation.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0013 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 1117EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Budget-Economics Bjt   05-13 0855</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Budget-Economics, Bjt,790</SECOND>
<HEAD>Economists Fear Big Spending Cuts Could Spur Recession</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARTIN CRUTSINGER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Economics Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush's surprise move to seek a grand
budget compromise with Congress could backfire and hand the
president the very recession he had hoped to avoid, private
economists warn.
   The fear is that cutting the budget deficit by the size being
discussed _ a combination of spending restraints and new taxes in
the range of $60 billion to $100 billion _ would take a lot of
steam out of the economy.
   With economic growth only expected to average an anemic 2
percent this year, such a wallop could easily push the country into
a recession, putting an end to the longest peacetime expansion on
record.
   ``This could be a classic case of doing the right thing at the
wrong time,'' said David Jones, an economist at Aubrey G. Lanston &amp;
Co. in New York.
   Jones predicted that the adverse impact from a budget agreement
would hit in late 1991 or early 1992, at which time the loss of
government spending in both domestic and military programs and
lower disposable income from higher taxes would be enough to
trigger an economic slump.
   ``It would be the worst possible environment for the president
to run for re-election,'' Jones said in an interview last week.
``It could make George Bush a one-term president.''
   However, other economists argued that the president is right to
take the risk of reaching a far-reaching agreement that finally
would resolve the deficit problem that has plagued the country for
nearly a decade.
   These economists believe a successful budget-reduction package
would result in a significant drop in interest rates, reflecting a
reduced government drain on capital markets.
   ``It would be unfortunate if a weak economy deterred the
president and Congress from making a major fix on the budget,''
said Allen Sinai, chief economist of the Boston Co. ``It really is
the right time provided that the Federal Reserve responds to offset
the budgetary restraint.''
   But even the optimists concede that such a scenario will be
difficult to pull off, given the fact that actions such as tax
increases and moves by the Fed to lower interest rates often have
long and unpredictable lag times.
   ``The danger is that fiscal policy (taxes and spending) and
monetary policy (interest rates) won't be coordinated,'' said David
Wyss, senior economist at DRI-McGraw Hill. ``The Fed should really
start loosening now to counteract spending cuts that would go into
effect in October and a tax increase that would take effect in
January.''
   Top Fed policymakers will meet behind closed doors on Tuesday to
map monetary strategy, but few analysts are looking for any
immediate credit easing, given current Fed concerns that inflation
remains a problem.
   The Bush administration has been unsuccessfully pressuring the
Fed for months to ease credit policies, fearing that higher
interest rates would slow the economy and make the administration's
deficit reduction goals unobtainable.
   In January, the administration released a proposed budget for
the 1991 fiscal year, which begins Oct. 1, that projected a deficit
of $100 billion, without any changes in policy.
   The administration proposed a $36 billion package of spending
cuts and modest tax increases to reach the Gramm-Rudman deficit
reduction target of $64 billion.
   The administration's proposal was attacked at the time as overly
optimistic and events so far this year have proven the critics
correct.
   Interest rates have risen higher than the administration's
forecast, raising the cost of financing the $3 trillion government
debt. At the same time, the economy has not grown as fast, bringing
in less tax revenues. In addition, the cost of rescuing failed
savings and loans has skyrocketed.
   White House Budget Director Richard Darman now says the deficit
absent any corrections could soar as much as $100 billion higher
than the $64 billion target, triggering massive, across-the-board
spending cuts in both military and defense programs under the
Gramm-Rudman law.
   Economists are in agreement that arbitrary spending cuts of that
magnitude would be harmful and it would be better to couple less
draconian spending reductions with a package of tax increases.
   The need to raise taxes to cut the deficit is even winning
endorsement among business leaders, normally a group opposed to tax
increases.
   Many of the corporate executives attending the spring meeting of
the Business Council last week in Hot Springs, Va., said tax
increases would be a reasonable price to pay to lower U.S. interest
rates and thus reduce the borrowing costs for new plant and
equipment.
   ``We need more capital and a cheaper price of capital,'' said
Willard Butcher, head of Chase Manhattan.
   Other business leaders said that if Bush failed to get the
deficit under control before the onset of the next recession, it
would be disastrous.
   ``The risks on the other side are terribly worrying,'' said
Lewis T. Preston, head of J.P. Morgan &amp; Co., another large New York
bank. ``If we get a recession of any magnitude, we would be talking
about deficits of $200 billion to $300 billion more than we
currently have and that would be very difficult to manage.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0014 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 1117EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u p AM-RunoffPolitics Bjt   05-13 0787</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Runoff Politics, Bjt,750</SECOND>
<HEAD>Opinions Divided on Whether Southern Runoffs Help, Hurt Blacks</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JILL LAWRENCE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Both Harvey Gantt and Andrew Young are black
Democrats seeking statewide office. But one wants a runoff election
and the other doesn't, highlighting one of the most sensitive
divisions in Southern politics.
   Some analysts call the runoff system racist; others say it
simply assures that a party runs its strongest nominee. They agree,
however, that minority and liberal candidates almost always lose
when forced into one-on-one runoffs with more conservative whites.
   Runoff elections are required in nine Southern and border states
if no primary candidate wins more than 50 percent of the vote on
the first go-round. In North Carolina, the second-place finisher
can demand a runoff if the top vote-getter garners less than 40
percent.
   Gantt, the former mayor of Charlotte, got 38 percent of the vote
in North Carolina's U.S. Senate primary last week. He pleaded with
second-place finisher Michael Easley, who is white, to forgo a June
5 runoff.
   But Easley refused, and is expected to pick up most of those who
supported the other two losing white candidates in the Democratic
primary. The eventual winner will take on conservative Republican
Sen. Jesse Helms in November.
   In Georgia, Young is leading the Democratic gubernatorial field
with about 30 percent of the vote. But he is opposed to a lawsuit
filed last week that seeks to abolish the state's runoff system.
   ``It's heightening the tensions in the state,'' said Merle
Black, a politics and government professor at Emory University.
``It makes it much harder for him to get the share of the white
vote that he needs. He certainly doesn't want the rules changed in
the middle of the game.''
   Georgia's runoff system was instituted in 1964 and sponsors of
the legislation clearly indicated its purpose was to dilute black
political strength.
   But most runoff systems originated early in the century, when
blacks did not vote. The South had virtually no Republican Party,
and a Democratic primary victory was tantamount to election.
Runoffs were used to narrow the Democratic field and unify the
party.
   Many political scientists swear by the principle of majority
rule and some believe the runoff system should be universal.
   ``I don't think you want to get a party nominee who represents
only one-fifth of the party,'' said Larry Sabato of the University
of Virginia. ``I would personally favor a 40 percent or 45 percent
cutoff and having a runoff for all states, because the danger's
always present that you could get a very unrepresentative nominee.''
   Party strength is the reason most often used to justify runoffs.
But some say the one-on-one contests merely prolong vicious party
infighting and can severely wound the eventual nominee.
   ``All the Republican has to do is pick up on all the charges ...
and just continue the fight,'' said Thad Beyle, a political science
professor at the University of North Carolina.
   William Schneider, a political analyst with the American
Enterprise Institute, said the runoffs in many instances are merely
a way for Democrats to avoid nominating blacks.
   ``There's plenty of contest now (from Republicans) in general
elections,'' he said. ``So what is the purpose of the runoff? To
strengthen the party? Not necessarily. There's another unspoken
purpose _ to keep from nominating blacks, or it could be phrased
`weaker candidates.'''
   Schneider called the runoff system ``a terrible, racist idea''
that forces black candidates to prove themselves twice.
   Other analysts say runoffs are not inherently racist, although
racism can color the results. And they say changing the nominating
structure is not the way to deal with that problem.
   ``Eliminating runoffs won't eliminate racism,'' said Earl Black,
a political scientist at the University of South Carolina.
   ``You have to make people confront their biases through
education, through religion, through civil rights demonstrations.
This is how you reach people,'' said Sabato.
   Merle Black, who is Earl Black's brother, said runoffs have
produced many prominent figures who won runoffs after second-place
primary finishes _ among them a young Georgia Democrat named Sam
Nunn, now chairman of the Senate Armed Services Committee.
   By contrast, he and others say the absence of runoffs can have
disappointing results. For example:
   _Ray Blanton, who won a crowded Tennessee primary with barely a
fifth of the vote. He became governor in 1974 and later was
indicted on a variety of corruption charges.
   _Marshall Coleman, who won Virginia's GOP gubernatorial
nomination with 37 percent of the vote and narrowly lost the 1989
general election to Douglas Wilder.
   The nine states that have runoffs if a primary candidate doesn't
get 50 percent are Alabama, Arkansas, Florida, Georgia, Louisiana,
Oklahoma, Mississippi, South Carolina and Texas.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0015 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 1128EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF-InjuredFiremen     05-13 0125</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF-Injured Firemen,0130</SECOND>
<HEAD>Forty-Five Firemen Hospitalized In Printing Plant Fire</HEAD>
<DATELINE>GRIESHEIM, West Germany (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Police said on Sunday that 45
volunteer firefighters were hospitalized after fighting a blaze at
a printing plant.
   Officials suspect the firefighters inhaled fumes from a solvent,
trichloroethylene, released by the fire late Saturday.
   The fire in Griesheim, 12 miles south of Frankfurt, badly
damaged a building containing the solvent, printing machines, paper
and ink, police said.
   The report said the firefighters quickly doused the blaze, which
caused about $240,000 damage.
   All 45 were later taken to a local hospital suffering from
nausea and breathing problems, police said.
   The firefighters were reported in satisfactory condition. They
were being held for medical observation and treatment, police said
in a statement.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0016 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 1128EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--MutineerArrested     05-13 0116</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Mutineer Arrested,0117</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rebel Officer Arrested in the Philippines</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MANILA, Philippines (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Troops captured an air force captain
who allegedly helped mutineers seize a military base during a coup
attempt in December, officials said Sunday.
   Capt. Edilberto Adeva was arrested late Saturday in his father's
home in suburban Las Pinas, officials said.
   Adeva is accused of leading the rebels' takeover of the police
squadron inside Villamor air base, headquarters of the Philippine
air force, during the Dec. 1-9 coup attempt, said spokesman Capt.
William Cacacho.
   It was the sixth and bloodiest bid to oust President Corazon
Aquino. More than 2,200 of the estimated 3,000 mutineers who joined
the failed coup are in military custody.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0017 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 1128EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--BusPlunge     05-13 0068</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Bus Plunge,0069</SECOND>
<HEAD>Two Dead in Bus Accident in the Philippines</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BAGUIO, Philippines (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A bus carrying 44 people slid off a
winding mountain road into a ravine Sunday after the brakes failed,
killing two people and seriously injuring five, police said.
   The bus, operated by the Pantranco line, was traveling to
Dagupan from this mountain resort 80 miles north of Manila when the
accident occurred.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0018 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 1155EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p AM-MurthaChallenged     05-13 0493</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Murtha Challenged,490</SECOND>
<HEAD>Pay Raise Is Ammunition as Veteran Lawmaker Faces Primary
Challenge</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JEFF BARKER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Pennsylvania attorney is using last year's
congressional pay raise to give veteran Democratic Rep. John Murtha
a rare primary challenge.
   Opponent Kenneth Burkley said he was within six to eight
percentage points of Murtha as Tuesday's Pennsylvania primary
neared.
   Murtha, chairman of the House Defense appropriations
subcommittee, denies the race is that close. But he has responded
to Burkley's challenge by using taped television ads with
endorsements from Democratic Gov. Robert Casey and former House
Speaker Tip O'Neill of Massachusetts.
   This kind of ammunition usually is reserved for general
elections _ if it is needed at all.
   Murtha faced no opponent in 1988, and ``this is the first real
primary the congressman has had since 1982,'' said Bill Allen,
Murtha's spokesman.
   Murtha had a primary opponent in 1982 because his industrialized
western Pennsylvania district was combined with a neighboring one
in the redistricting following the 1980 census. He easily defeated
Democratic Rep. Don Bailey.
   Burkley, a Greensburg, Pa., attorney making his first run for
public office, has hit Murtha on the pay raise and on political
action committee contributions.
   ``He's a `Who's Who' of PACs,'' Burkley said.
   In a 380-48 vote on Feb. 7, 1989, the House rejected a 51
percent congressional pay increase proposed by a presidential
commission. Murtha was among the 48 backing the pay hike.
   The issue has long made Democrats nervous.
   ``I think it's an important issue, but it's important for it to
be placed in the context that changes in pay have taken place in a
number of years in which Congressman Murtha has also supported
steps to reduce outside earned income,'' Allen said. ``The second
half of the pay issue is removing conflicts of interest.''
   Last November 1989, the House passed a different, Murtha-backed
bill raising salaries of its members, federal judges and top
executive branch officials by about one-third. The bill bars House
members from accepting honoraria, or speaking fees, beginning in
1991.
   Burkley said Murtha's support of the raise was irresponsible in
such budget-conscious times.
   Burkley has made inroads in the race, although it is difficult
to tell whether the pay raise is a reason why. The candidates split
endorsements from two major party groups, Burkley winning the
surprise backing of the Westmoreland County Democratic Committee
and Murtha capturing support of its Cambria County counterpart.
   Burkley said he knows congressional salaries are politically
sensitive. If he defeats Murtha, he said he does not expect any
support from national Democrats ``if I use the pay raise.''
   Burkley has raised $27,285 in the past 15 months, compared with
Murtha's $256,293.
   Of Murtha's total, $154,320 came from PACs.
   Elected in 1974, Murtha is considered an old-style vote broker
who shuns publicity.
   Also on the Democratic ballot is veterinarian John K. Shrader.
Businessman Willeam Choby faces fellow Johnstown resident Tony
Joseph for the GOP nomination.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0019 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 1318EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-CampaignFinance Bjt   05-13 0763</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Campaign Finance, Bjt,700</SECOND>
<HEAD>Republican, Democrats Target the Other's Favorite Cash Sources</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MATT YANCEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Democrats and Republicans alike are
reaffirming an old adage in their competing proposals for campaign
finance reform: If money is the mother's milk of politics, let's
dry up the other guy's source.
   With serious negotiations between leaders of the two parties in
the Senate scheduled to begin behind closed doors this week, both
are defining ``reform'' as weaning the other from its chief means
of raising cash.
   Republicans describe as ``sewer money'' the estimated $45
million to $60 million in unreported dollars that tax-exempt
organizations, primarily unions, spent last election on so-called
independent, get-out-the-vote drives, largely on behalf of
Democratic candidates.
   Democrats accuse Republicans of wanting to introduce more,
rather than less, money into the political process by ``greatly
expanding the role of wealthy individuals.''
   Both want to increase the roles of their state and national
party organizations as a conduit for money. Republicans, with a
much stronger party infrastructure already in place for raising and
disbursing cash, would do it much faster.
   The two parties also agree on wanting to diminish the influence
of political action committees or PACs _ an institution largely
spawned by the last, post-Watergate round of reforms _ and
Republicans would like to abolish them entirely.
   PACs accounted for $45 million or nearly one-fourth of all the
money spent on Senate campaigns in 1988. Nearly 80 percent of their
contributions went to incumbents. Since there are more Democratic
than Republican incumbents in Congress, Democrats tend to benefit
most from PAC largesse.
   President Bush and Republicans would prefer to eliminate PACs
altogether. But, recognizing that the courts likely would hold such
a broad ban to be an unconstitutional infringement on freedom of
speech and association, they have a fallback position.
   Union, corporate and trade association PACs still would be
abolished. And the amounts that non-affiliated, ideological PACs
such as those operated by the National Rifle Association,
environmental groups and both sides of the abortion issue can
contribute to a candidate would drop from $10,000 to $2,000 per
election cycle.
   To make up for the lost revenue, Republicans would raise the
$25,000 aggregate ceiling on individual contributions to candidates
and parties for use in national elections to $340,000 a year.
   Democrats contend the GOP plan contains a loophole that would
allow individuals to continue contributing even more money into
state party coffers without having to report it to the Federal
Election Commission.
   ``Wealthy individuals and corporations could continue to give
unlimited amounts of money to state party organizations,'' Senate
Democratic Leader George Mitchell of Maine said of the Republican
proposal. ``The practice that occurred in the 1988 elections, when
publicly funded presidential candidates raised upward of $45
million in $100,000 donations from individuals and corporations,
would continue unabated.''
   Democrats would displace PACs with spending ceilings and a
revived public financing scheme paid for by taxpayers
``volunteering'' to increase by $3 what they pay to the Internal
Revenue Service each year.
   PACs would be prohibited by the Democratic plan from
contributing directly to candidates. The limit on those
contributions is now $10,000 from any one PAC to a candidate.
   But the Democrats would continue allowing PACs to give $15,000 a
year to party committees. Under their plan, the national parties
could still collect up to an aggregate $3.5 million a year from
PACs and their senatorial campaign committees could collect another
$1.9 million.
   ``The Democrat bill fails the truth-in-advertising test,'' said
Senate Republican leader Bob Dole of Kansas. ``What we have here in
effect is a big money-laundering scheme.''
   The rhetorical flourishes are expected to diminish once
Mitchell, Dole and four to five other key senators from the two
sides begin negotiating behind closed doors later this week on
seeking a compromise.
   Democrats are adamant that any compromise must contain some type
of firm spending limits on candidates. Never, declare Republicans,
just as vehemently. The average senatorial campaign in 1988 cost
$3.8 million.
   Both parties embraced portions of a bipartisan task force's
recommendations calling for ``flexible'' ceilings but neither has
accepted its suggestions entirely.
   Republicans rejected the task force's suggestion that a cap be
placed on out-of-state contributions, instead adopting as a
substitute the notion that non-resident donors should be limited to
half _ or $500 _ what individuals can give directly to a candidate.
   Democrats, likewise, rejected the suggestion there should be no
cap on small donations from in-state contributors. Candidates could
use those contributions to exceed the overall limits, but only by
25 percent, under their proposal.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0020 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 1338EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ShrimpWars     05-13 0819</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Shrimp Wars,0838</SECOND>
<HEAD>Shrimpers' Cultural Clash Adds to Mounting Woes</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARY FOSTER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW ORLEANS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A recent gunbattle between Louisiana and
Vietnamese shrimpers over choice fishing waters has brought to the
surface the tension each side feels in these lean times for the
industry.
   Increased regulation, dwindling resources, rising costs and
foreign competition, coupled with language barriers and
misunderstood cultural customs, provide more than enough fuel to
ignite an already heated situation in the Gulf of Mexico waters,
people on both sides say.
   ``It's tough for the guys out there,'' said Lt. Col. Charles
Clark of the Louisiana Wildlife and Fisheries Department. ``People
are struggling to survive and it's not ethnic background, it's
who's catching the shrimp that divides people.''
   ``I don't think it's discrimination against the Vietnamese
fishermen,'' said Monsignor Dominic Luong, pastor of Mary Queen of
Vietnam Church. ``I think it is a human thing. You have the
Vietnamese fighting to achieve on the economic scale and you have
the other fishermen trying to do the same thing. The Vietnamese do
keep the rules, but sometimes they don't understand the American
rules. In that situation, tempers flare.''
   A federal grand jury is expected to look into the May 5 incident
in which longtime local fishermen and Vietnamese immigrants
exchanged gunfire and rammed each others' boats. The Coast Guard
officials intervened and briefly confiscated six shrimp boats. No
one was injured in the confrontation.
   For the Vietnamese, who have struggled up from poverty, owning
their own boats is a step up. But for Louisiana shrimpers, a way of
life is rapidly crumbling.
   The costs of shrimping, including fuel, nets and insurance, have
skyrocketed, said Capt. Sandy Dares of Wildlife and Fisheries.
Meanwhile, shrimpers are coming off several bad years and a winter
freeze that kept them landlocked for an extended period this year.
   Shrimpers are particularly bitter over the federal laws that
require they use Turtle Excluder Devices. The TEDs allow the
endangered Kemp's Ridley sea turtle to escape from their nets, but
shrimpers say the turtle isn't caught in Louisiana waters and the
TEDs let half of their catch escape.
   ``They just can't make any money. So how do they pay for the
boat and feed their families?'' Dares asked. ``Then you've got more
regulations showing up every day. Not just the TEDs, but lots of
things, like what they have to have on their boats and how they can
dispose of their waste oil.''
   ``I just can't afford it,'' said Mark Buras, 37, of Port
Sulphur. ``You never did get rich shrimping. One year would be
good, one year bad, one year you'd break even. With the TEDs
they'll all be bad. It's like having a big hole in the middle of
the net.''
   Many U.S. native shrimpers believe the Vietnamese aren't using
the TEDs, according to Donald Lirette of Dulac, president of the
Terrebonne Fishermen's Organization.
   Clark dismisses such talk, as well as shrimpers' charges that
the Vietnamese have bigger boats and use them to drive other
shrimpers away from schools of shrimp when they're found.
   ``I don't think they have bigger boats. If you look at it
there's a lot of equal opportunity out there,'' Clark said. ``When
the shrimp are found it's everyone for himself. But to tell the
truth, when the Vietnamese find shrimp, they're going for it.
They're much more interested in harvesting the resource than in
human compassion.''
   The language barrier is also blamed for many problems. At sea,
shrimpers communicate by radio or shouting at one other.
   ``The Vietnamese only learn the American words for `we found
some shrimp,' said Lirette. ``They monitor the radio and when they
hear that they head there. That doesn't make the guy who found the
shrimp and told his buddy happy.''
   ``In Louisiana, shrimpers never moved that much,'' Clark said.
``They shrimped their own area and that was it. ... The Vietnamese
are very migrant, on the other hand. They go anywhere they hear the
shrimp are. I don't think they've grasped our sense of fair play,
and some of the shrimpers probably hold it against them.''
   Foreign shrimp imports add to the problem, Dares said. About 80
percent of the shrimp consumed in the United States is imported,
and, he said, it's cheaper than what Louisiana shrimpers produce.
   ``No matter what we do they can grow shrimp cheaper than we can
catch them,'' said Kevin Pennison of Houma.
   The economic squeeze for both groups is acute, and for both the
alternatives to shrimping are narrow now, with the state's economy
shrunken because of oil industry problems.
   ``What happened was most Vietnamese came here and had no time to
learn English or develop skills,'' Luong said. ``They had to go
right into the labor market to support their families. For them,
owning their own business or boat is achieving on the economic
scale. They have moved up.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0021 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 1341EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-EastGermany-Refugees Bjt   05-13 0791</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-East Germany-Refugees, Bjt,0818</SECOND>
<HEAD>Romanian Refugees Begin Flooding into East Germany</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARK FRITZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>EAST BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The mess hall is a mess, the army cook is
harried and the jostling line of anxious diners is ready for a
military meal of meat and potatoes.
   These are not East German soldiers on a chow break, however, but
Romanians on the run. Scores are fleeing their East bloc nation
daily for a former Communist country that has moved more quickly
toward reform.
   About 700 Romanians and a few hundred Bulgarians have packed
into two barracks at an East German army base on the outskirts of
Berlin. Hundreds more are housed in a building once used by East
Germany's feared secret police.
   ``Every day there are more. They come here, see the free food
and the free housing, and call home. Then more come,'' Maj. Harry
Kretschmer says as he strolls through a hallway packed with
squalling children and milling adults.
   ``We do not know what to do with them. We are filled to
capacity,'' Kretschmer said.
   East Germany, reeling from a creaky economy and an exodus of its
own citizens to West Germany, suddenly finds itself luring other
East Europeans whose countries do not have a wealthy neighbor to
help them emerge from four decades of oppression.
   The government said it decided last week to begin housing and
feeding the Romanians and Bulgarians who show up daily in train
stations with battered bags of belongings, but no money.
   Many see East Germany as the new threshhold of the West, a
passageway to prosperity.
   ``I came here for work and to escape the Communists,'' says
Taian Neascu, 19, from Bucharest. ``I want to go to West Germany,
and go to America.''
   At least 50 to 70 Romanians daily arrive in East Germany, but
the numbers may be much higher, said Matthias Jahr, a member of the
East Berlin Foreigners Commission.
   Romanians comprise the largest group of refugees, Jahr said,
followed by Bulgarians. The government has no figues on how many
East Europeans have flooded into the country in recent months.
   But the newly opened borders in Eastern Europe have turned East
Germany into a crossroads of commerce and a lure for the
disadvantaged. Thousands of Poles travel daily to Berlin to hawk
wares along streets and in squares.
   Jahr also said his office has received numerous requests for
asylum from Soviet Jews who want to flee a new wave of
anti-Semitism at home.
   The Romanians began arriving in late April, about the time
political strife intensified in their country.
   Some Romanians believe the revolutionary interim government led
by acting President Ion Iliescu will not differ substantially from
the Communist regime that was overthrown in December.
   Scores of Romanians began sleeping in the large train station in
Lichtenberg, the huge foreign quarter of East Berlin.
   ``At first we were ignorant of the problem. Then we found all of
these people sleeping in the train station,'' said Hannelora
Gensch, an East Berlin housing official who runs the complex in the
Beisdorf district.
   Children typically roam subway and train stations, sent by their
parents with cards printed in German: ``We are Romanian, please
help us with money.''
   Many are sick when they arrive, and most are afraid, Mrs. Gensch
said.
   ``We have had to put people in the hospital because of their
fear,'' she said. ``The government has to make a decision on what
to do with these people.''
   The stream comes just as resentment of foreigners is sweeping
East Germany, fueled mainly by fears the country will face
widespread unemployment as it merges with West Germany and converts
to a free market.
   Street clashes between foreigners and East German gangs broke
out in Lichtenberg a week ago.
   One Romanian at the army base, a 36-year-old man who said he
drove a taxi in Constanza, said he left behind three young
children. He said he has no plans to return.
   Kretchsmer said he believes the motives are more economic than
political.
   Some Romanians at the barracks said they fled because they
believed a new crackdown on travel would be imposed after May 20,
when Iliescu is widely expected to win Romanian elections.
   The Romanians and Bulgarians fill two large bunkhouses at the
base. Weapons were cleared out of large store rooms to create more
space, said Kretschmer.
   Most came here on tourist visas, and some said they still
planned to go home.
   Maria Caldarau, 48, said through an interpreter she brought her
six children so they could get better medical attention.
   Jahr said the government should discuss visa requirements with
other East European countries as a way of limiting the flow.
   ``We don't want to build a new wall,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0022 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 1342EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a BC-DiceMan 1stLd-Writethru a0674 05-13 0592</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Dice Man, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0674,0603</SECOND>
<HEAD>Andrew Dice Clay: An Appreciation</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 8th graf, `Same goes...', to CORRECT spelling of
O'Connor. With AM-Dice-SNL. Note contents</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By JAY SHARBUTT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Television Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   On the bright side, the Republic has survived
Andrew Dice Clay's ``Saturday Night Live'' gig. And he even ended
the show wishing his mother and mothers everywhere a happy Mother's
Day.
   But the Dice Man, clad in black threads, a black leather jacket
and smoking a filter cigarette, more resembled the star of a
Brooklyn geek festival than the no-holds-barred Prince of Dirty he
is said to be.
   NBC, aware of his tendency to call women ``bitches,'' verbally
assail gays and even use naughty words, aired Saturday's show on a
five-second delay basis so it could bleep out anything obscene or
worse.
   Dumb move. It should have rigged the tape-delay to say ``tuba''
when bleeping, or even on those occasions it let go what Clay said.
   For example, during his opening monologue, a protesting couple
in the studio audience shouted ``Clay, Clay, go away!'' They were
quickly whisked out by guards. The startled Clay's snappy comeback
was ``shadddup.''
   That figures. His routine stepped out for a short beer when wit
was passed out. Things might have been better had NBC inserted
``tuba'' where he got, well, crude, about one of those ejected. You
would have heard him say:
   ``That's the type a guy that hangs out in the men's room to
smell other people's tuba all day long.''
   Same goes for his thoughts on the furor his appearance on the
show caused, including the boycott of the show by cast member Nora
Dunn and pop singer Sinead O'Connor.
   Push the tuba button. You would have heard him say:
   ``I mean, what do I need _ more p.r.? I couldn't get any more
p.r. if I took out my tuba and wrapped it around the microphone
stand.''
   True, he got bleeped only five times in one skit in which he
played himself explaining sex to his son. No doubt this was because
he used, gosh, crude words to describe the male and female
genitalia.
   But five shots of ``tuba'' would have put him in perspective. He
works dirty because he has no act.
   The show, like its guest host, was an epic in lame, even in such
non-Clay skits as ``The Anal Retentive Chef'' or Dennis Miller's
``Weekend Update,'' on which The Annoying Man appeared and squeezed
a pimple.
   About the only mildly witty moment came when the funny, gifted
Jan Hooks told the audience she lacked the guts to protest Clay's
appearance, but had decided to protest him ``by giving a lackluster
performance.''
   The show predictably spoofed the Clay uproar right from the
start with a take-off of ``It's a Wonderful Life,'' in which the
devil showed Clay what would have happened had Clay not been born.
   Among other things, Frank Zappa would have appeared in his place
on the show and done a 70-minute anti-censorship rap, causing the
show's ratings to plummet and the ax to fall on ``Saturday Night''
after 15 years.
   That wouldn't be such a bad idea. SNL once had a first-rate
cast, a sense of comic danger and inspired routines. All that now
is on Fox Broadcasting's new ``In Living Color,'' a very funny, yet
compassionate show.
   Not much is left of ``Saturday Night Live'' when all it can do
is call on a guy who only can talk dirty, a guy from the land of
Nobody Home.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0023 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 1343EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-US-Philippines     05-13 0655</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-US-Philippines,650</SECOND>
<HEAD>Both Sides Seek Major Concessions in U.S.-Philippines Talks</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Philippines-US Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GEORGE GEDDA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   U.S. and Filipino officials open talks Monday
on the future of their military alliance, with both sides convinced
that major changes are needed if a new base agreement is to be
reached.
   Bush administration officials are sensitive to Filipino
objections about the existing agreement and ``are going to present
an entirely new kind of arrangement,'' Philippines Ambassador
Emmanuel Pelaez said.
   Special U.S. negotiator Richard Armitage will open exploratory
talks on Monday in Manila with Philippines Foreign Secretary Raul
Manglapus.
   The talks come amid heightened tensions in the Philippines
following the murders Sunday of two U.S. servicemen near Clark Air
Base. Including Sunday's victims, eight Americans have died in
politically motivated slayings in the Philippines since April 1989.
U.S. officials blamed communist rebels for the first six slayings.
   The talks are aimed at replacing the 1947 Military Bases
Agreement, which expires on Sept. 16, 1991. At stake is the future
Subic Bay naval base, Clark Air Base and four smaller U.S. military
facilities.
   In an interview last week, Pelaez called the 1947 agreement
``anachronistic'' and said radical changes would be required for
the U.S. presence to continue after next year.
   Pelaez said the talks initially will focus on how U.S. and
Filipino security requirements have been affected by the changing
international situation, particularly the easing of East-West
tensions.
   But security questions sometimes have become overshadowed by
other aspects of the American presence in the Philippines, such as
U.S. monetary compensation to the host government and whether the
existence of the bases infringes on Filipino sovereignty.
   ``The negotiations over base rights in the Philippines have
become largely an issue of price and pride,'' a delegation of seven
House members said in a report after an inspection trip to the
Western Pacific last month.
   The delegation examined possible alternatives to the U.S.
military bases in the Philippines.
   The consensus among American officials is that the functions now
being carried out at the Philippine bases could be ``scattered'' to
multiple sites elsewhere in the region, such as Singapore, Japan
and Guam.
   But the administration is intent on making every effort to
retain its presence in the Philippines. In contrast, Philippines
President Corazon Aquino has been noncommittal, reflecting the deep
divisions among her countrymen.
   Stephen Bosworth, a former U.S. ambassador to the Philippines,
said he is moderately optimistic an agreement can be reached, and
Pelaez shares that view.
   Bosworth believes that a reduced U.S. presence would go a long
way toward easing Filipino concerns about perceived U.S.
infringement on Philippine sovereignty.
   About 40,000 Americans are stationed in the Philippines carrying
out base-related activities.
   Defense Department figures show that the impact on the local
economy of the U.S. facilities is substantial. Combined U.S. Air
Force and Navy spending was $531 million in fiscal 1988.
   But Filipino authorities reacted angrily last year when Congress
cut $96 million from the $481 million aid package the
administration had promised annually as part of the compensation
the U.S. provides for access to the bases.
   Another sore point for many Filipinos is that U.S. servicemen
are rarely prosecuted under Filipino law, since there various legal
ways for U.S. authorities to take jurisdiction.
   But polls show a majority of Filipinos favor a continued U.S.
presence, and that sentiment is shared by countries nearby.
   ``Virtually all countries in the area are happy to have the U.S.
there,'' a U.S. official said last week. But some members of
Congress favor a U.S. withdrawal, noting the Bush administration is
shutting down dozens of bases at home.
   Their sentiment is reinforced by the Center for Defense
Information, a liberal research group.
   David Isenberg, a research analyst at the center, said, ``We
believe that the threat for which the bases were originally
designed is obsolete. The prospect of invasions by `Red' China and
the Soviet Union is now fantasy.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0024 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 1354EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ChimesonTrial     05-13 0558</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Chimes on Trial,0571</SECOND>
<HEAD>Town Sued by Couple for Whom Bell Tolls Too Loudly</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MICHELLE LOCKE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HATFIELD, Mass. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The resonant ringing of the town bell
from a white-steepled church on Main Street has been a venerated
fixture for nearly a century in this 320-year-old New England
farming community.
   But a couple of newcomers who moved next to the bell when it
wasn't working say the hourly clanging is taking its toll on their
sleep. They have sued the town to silence the bell at night. Some
old-timers resent the threat to the time-honored custom.
   ``It's been there for years,'' said Giles Desmond, who runs the
town barbershop. ``It's a tradition.''
   Bringing the civil suit are Richard and Pamela Carnall, who in
August 1988 plunked down $220,000 for a 19th-century house on Main
Street and prepared to embark on life in a small Yankee town.
   In December, the town clock 50 feet from their home was repaired
and they discovered a quaint tradition they hadn't bargained for _
the hourly clanging of an 1,800-pound bell.
   ``It was just keeping me up all night. There were nights that I
didn't sleep at all,'' Mrs. Carnall testified in Hampshire Superior
Court last week. The trial continues Monday.
   The Carnalls are asking a jury to declare the bell a nuisance
and decide whether they are entitled to damages. If a jury agrees,
the couple will ask Judge John F. Murphy to order the bell silenced
from 9 p.m. to 6 a.m.
   Town officials are defending the ringing of the bell, which is
housed in the First Congregational Church tower but owned by the
town. Residents have testified of their fond memories of hearing
the bell calling farmers to the field and children to play for 91
years.
   ``It's something that even if you are in bed at night and can't
sleep, you hear the bell ring,'' George G. Zgrodnick Jr., chairman
of the Hatfield Board of Selectmen, testified Friday. ``And I think
it assures us, it assures me, that there is something working for
the community all the time.''
   Desmond said some in town agree that the bell probably should be
turned off at night, if only to extend a warmer welcome to the
newcomers.
   ``It's like anything else; there's pros and cons,'' he said.
   W. Michael Ryan, the couple's attorney, presented testimony that
the bell is estimated at about 69 decibels, about as loud as a
vacuum cleaner, inside the Carnall home.
   Mrs. Carnall said she and her husband have tried running fans
and machines that produce background noise to drown out the bell.
She said the ringing startles her infant daughter and means that
all three members of the family must sleep in the same room with
the door latched shut.
   The Carnalls have offered to pay for a mechanical device that
would silence the chimes at night, Ryan said.
   Desmond and his wife, Rose, who also live on Main Street,
although farther from the church, said the noise of the bell
depends on which way the wind blows. The Desmonds said they enjoy
the chimes.
   ``I can't believe in a year they haven't got used to it,'' Mrs.
Desmond said. ``There are nights I lie awake and I hear the clock
and I think, well at least I'm in the right place.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0025 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 1359EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ElephantDies     05-13 0483</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Elephant Dies,0500</SECOND>
<HEAD>Zoo Experts Believe Kidney Failure Caused Elephant's Death</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SYRACUSE, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Kidney failure was suspected in the death
of an elephant whose calf was stillborn in a Caesarian section last
month, zookeepers said Sunday.
   Babe, a 36-year-old Asian elephant, died Saturday at Burnet Park
Zoo. The 7,700-pound elephant was taken to Cornell University's
veterinary school, where an autopsy continued Sunday, said Don
Moore, the zoo's curator of mammals.
   Final autopsy results won't be available for a week to 10 days,
though veterinarians may have preliminary lab results by Monday,
Moore said.
   Babe's death has prompted criticism from animal rights activists
angry over the zoo's breeding program. Burnet Park is small by zoo
standards but has an ambitious breeding program.
   ``May God grant her the peace that man never did,'' said Joyce
Goike, president of the Central New York Humane Association. On
Wednesday she asked the zoo to put Babe to sleep rather than
prolong the elephant's suffering.
   Babe's 22-month pregnancy drew worldwide attention from
zookeepers trying to breed endangered Asian elephants in captivity.
   Had the pregnancy been successful, Babe would have been the
oldest elephant to become a first-time mother in a North American
zoo. But after a stalled labor, Babe underwent a Caesarian section
April 23. Her 266-pound bull calf died in the womb when it could
not position itself properly for birth.
   No elephant has ever recovered after a Caesarian section,
zookeepers said.
   Right up to the time of Babe's death, zookeepers were hopeful
she would recover. A day earlier, Babe had been taken off the
critical list and upgraded to stable condition.
   Moore, who helped on the autopsy, said Babe's ``kidneys didn't
look too good'' and that kidney failure probably caused her death.
   Gary MacLachlan, who heads the Onondaga County parks agency that
runs the zoo, said Babe's death will raise questions about the
zoo's decision to breed her. ``This may add fuel to any skepticism
people have had,'' he said.
   Animal rights activists complain about the mortality rate of
newborns at the zoo. Of about 300 mammals born there last year, 59
died.
   The zoo's breeding program will continue despite Babe's death,
said County Executive Nicholas Pirro. A second Asian elephant at
the zoo is expected to give birth in July 1991.
   ``Nothing that has happened will stop us from what the zoo
people believe, and I agree, is the best we can do to preserve this
species,'' Pirro said.
   An Asian elephant expert agreed that Burnet Park should continue
its breeding program.
   ``They're certainly not guilty of anything except incredibly bad
luck,'' said Roger Henneous, senior elephant keeper at the
Washington Park Zoo in Portland, Ore. The Washington Park Zoo, the
nation's premier Asian elephant breeder, has had 24 births in the
past 28 years.
   Only 62 Asian elephants have been born in captivity. The species
numbers fewer than 45,000 in the wild.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0026 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 1400EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Soviet-Baltics     05-13 0597</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Baltics,0614</SECOND>
<HEAD>Lithuanian Premier Pleased With Western Response</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Soviet-Independence, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CAREY GOLDBERG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Lithuania's prime minister said Sunday she
believed she had gained ``de facto recognition'' for her breakaway
republic from the United States and other Western governments she
visited on a 16-day trip abroad.
   Stopping in Moscow on her way home to Vilnius, Kazimiera
Prunskiene said leaders in the five countries she visited
acknowledged Lithuania's right to independence and backed talks to
resolve its standoff with the Kremlin.
   Asked about Lithuania's quest for diplomatic recognition, Mrs.
Prunskiene said: ``This is de facto recognition. The fact that I
came to these countries, that several of them received me on a very
high governmental level, that these consultations occur, that's
already recognition that this is not just an internal affair of the
Soviet Union.''
   Mrs. Prunskiene's trip was part of a growing campaign by all
three Baltic republics to gain full independence. The presidents of
Latvia, Estonia and Lithuania met Saturday to re-establish a
56-year-old political bloc and form a united front in their drive
to secede from the Soviet Union.
   In Vilnius, Lithuanian President Vytautas Landsbergis said on
Sunday that the Baltic leaders also had appealed to Soviet
President Mikhail S. Gorbachev and President Bush, asking both ``to
take our problem into their hearts.''
   Landsbergis declined to release the text of what he called ``a
diplomatic communication,'' but said he and the presidents of
neighboring Latvia and Estonia also had asked Gorbachev to meet
with them.
   The Baltic republics were forcibly annexed by the Soviet Union
in 1940. They have taken advantage of Gorbachev's reforms to wage a
careful, parliamentary push for sovereignty that suddenly took a
sharp turn March 11, when Lithuania defied Moscow and declared its
independence.
   Moscow imposed a partial economic embargo on Lithuania and
threatened the other two republics. The sanctions have forced the
layoff of 12,000 people in Lithuania, according to official reports.
   A tanker carrying 80,000 tons of petroleum was en route Sunday
to the Lithuanian port of Klaipeda to relieve the gasoline shortage
stemming from the blockade, Lithuanian television reported. The oil
was purchased with money from emigre Lithuanians, officials said.
It was not clear whether Soviet authorities would allow the tanker
to dock at Klaipeda.
   Mrs. Prunskiene, traveling as a private citizen, met in
Washington with Bush, and with leaders in Canada, France, Britain
and West Germany.
   Although she was warmly received, the West in general has
adopted a cautious attitude toward the situation in Lithuania,
unwilling to cause more trouble for Gorbachev as he wrestles with
domestic reform.
   White House spokesman Marlin Fitzwater emphasized that Bush's
May 3 meeting with Mrs. Prunskiene did not change the U.S. policy
of not formally recognizing Lithuania as a separate country.
   Mrs. Prunskiene said on Sunday she was heartened that Western
leaders were pushing negotiations between Lithuania and the
Kremlin. ``The fact that they see us, Lithuania and the Soviet
Union, as partners in negotiations is a sign that we're already
seen as a state,'' she said.
   West German Chancellor Helmut Kohl and President Francois
Mitterrand of France proposed in an April 26 letter that Lithuania
temporarily suspend its independence and enter into talks with
Moscow.
   The two sides are interpreting the Kohl-Mitterrand letter
differently but appear to be edging toward a compromise similar to
what it proposes.
   Mrs. Prunskiene reiterated that Lithuania was prepared to
suspend new laws that concern Moscow as a condition for talks and
said she expected the Kremlin to raise its economic blockade of the
republic of 3.7 million.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0027 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 1413EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-DeathPenalty     05-13 0921</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Death Penalty,0943</SECOND>
<HEAD>America Struggles with Death Penalty</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Death Penalty-State By State</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By STEVE WILSTEIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Debate about capital punishment is swirling around the country
as a federal court on Monday considers allowing California's first
execution in 23 years, Louisiana awaits an electrocution Friday and
demonstrators march toward Atlanta.
   The death penalty, outlawed in every other industrial country in
the West, is embroiled anew in arguments that touch on legal,
medical, moral, political and racial issues.
   Emotions are strong on all sides _ relatives of victims who want
to see murderers put to death, prosecutors tired of repeated stays
of executions, opponents who condemn state-sponsored killing.
   ``The death penalty is an issue that has a peculiar degree of
sensitivity in the public mind, even though people don't often see
themselves as potential victims of murders or capital punishment,''
Charles J. Ogletree, Harvard professor of criminal law and former
Washington, D.C., public defender, said in an interview.
   ``It gets a visceral reaction. People are worried about crime, a
seeming loss of control, a criminal system running amok, and they
think the death penalty is an answer to crime.''
   Every major study has concluded that the death penalty does not
deter capital crimes, Ogletree said. Yet polls show most Americans
still support capital punishment _ a fact that politicians haven't
ignored in current elections _ although most people say they would
prefer life imprisonment without parole.
   Former California Gov. Edmund G. ``Pat'' Brown, who wrote a book
last year about his agonizing decisions to grant or withhold
clemency to prisoners facing death sentences, believes the public's
attitude toward capital punishment will change as the pace of
executions increases.
   ``When they start gassing four people a day ... after 20 weeks
of that, people will be ready to get rid of it,'' Brown said.
``People will see the futility of the death penalty.
   ``People are not really in favor of the death penalty, but
they're opposed to the outrageous number of homicides in the
country. They're rightfully frightened and feel frustrated.''
   More than 2,300 prisoners are on death rows around the country,
and their numbers increase nearly every week as the appeals process
blocks executions and more killers are convicted. Thirty-six states
have capital punishment statutes.
   Since the 1976 U.S. Supreme Court ruling allowing states to
resume use of the death penalty, 125 people have been executed _
the latest last Friday in Potosi, Mo., where Winford Stokes died by
lethal injection for killing a woman 12 years ago.
   The pace of executions Brown envisioned does not appear to be
coming soon. Stokes was the fifth person executed this year. From
1984 through 1989, an average of 19 people a year were executed.
   The 9th U.S. Circuit Court of Appeals in San Francisco will hear
arguments Monday on the execution of Robert Alton Harris, convicted
of the 1978 murders of two San Diego teen-agers.
   Harris, scheduled to die April 3 in San Quentin's gas chamber,
was granted a stay four days earlier by 9th Circuit Judge John
Noonan. He said a lower-court judge may have erred in dismissing
Harris' claim of incompetent psychiatric assistance without holding
a fact-finding hearing.
   A psychiatric evaluation also is at the center of a case in New
Orleans, where a man with borderline retardation, Dalton Prejean,
who killed a state trooper in 1977, is scheduled to die in the
electric chair Friday. A state judge last week rejected the latest
attempt to save Prejean, saying ``It is time to let justice be
done'' after 10 stays of execution and 10 years on death row.
   A group calling itself the National Pilgrimage for Abolition of
the Death Penalty is due to arrive in Atlanta on Saturday after a
400-mile march from Starke, Fla., where murderer Jessie Tafero was
electrocuted May 4.
   The group, which will end its march at the Martin Luther King
Jr. Center for Non-Violent Social Change, includes Coretta Scott
King, widow of the slain civil rights leader, and the Rev. Joseph
Lowery, president of the Southern Christian Leadership Conference.
   ``There's no question that the issue of race is foremost in the
minds of many of those who oppose capital punishment,'' Ogletree
said.
   Among the inmates on death row, 43 percent are black, more than
three times the percentage of blacks in the general population,
according to the NAACP Legal Defense and Educational Fund. Of the
125 executed, 41 percent were black.
   The race of the victims also plays a role in whether convicted
killers are sentenced to death, some critics say. More than twice
as many blacks who killed whites were executed since 1973 as blacks
who killed other blacks, NAACP figures show.
   In Chicago, federal prosecutors last week said they will seek
the death penalty for two men charged with killing a drug case
witness in what could be the first execution by the federal
government in 27 years. A 1988 federal law allows capital
punishment for some drug-related homicides.
   Politicians up for election nationwide are lining up on either
side of the death penalty and in some cases their stands on the
issue are expected to play a significant role in the voting.
   In California, for example, pollsters attribute former San
Francisco Mayor Dianne Feinstein's edge in the Democratic primary
campaign for governor in part to her support of the death penalty.
   Her opponent, state Attorney General John Van de Kamp, said he
is personally opposed to capital punishment but he has taken a
strong stand in favor of Harris' execution.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0028 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 1414EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-DeathPenalty-StateByState     05-13 0080</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Death Penalty-State By State,0090</SECOND>
<HEAD>Texas Leads List In Number Of Executions Carried Out Since 1976</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Death Penalty</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Here is a breakdown, by state, of the 125 executions carried out
since the 1976 U.S. Supreme Court ruling allowing states to resume
use of the death penalty:
   Texas: 34.
   Florida: 22.
   Louisiana: 18.
   Georgia: 14.
   Virginia: 8.
   Alabama: 7.
   Mississippi: 4.
   Nevada: 4.
   Missouri: 3.
   North Carolina: 3.
   South Carolina: 3.
   Utah: 3.
   Indiana: 2.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0029 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 1426EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-DemocracyShip     05-13 0637</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Democracy Ship,0658</SECOND>
<HEAD>Goddess of Democracy Docks in Taiwan</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SHIRLEY LAI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>KEELUNG, Taiwan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Taiwanese set off firecrackers Sunday to
welcome the Goddess of Democracy to northern Keelung, where the
radio ship will refuel before heading for the high seas to
broadcast pro-democracy messages to China.
   Authorities, however, gave a cool reception to the ship, sending
no official to greet the crew and refusing to allow Chinese
dissidents to board the vessel.
   A high school band played music while journalists and 300 local
residents crowded the pier to see the ship, scheduled to leave
Monday for international waters to begin 24-hour broadcasts into
China.
   ``We are here because we believe in freedom and democracy for
all the world,'' said Dominique Perreot, the ship's captain.
   China has refused to rule out the use of force to stop the
planned broadcasts and has warned that any help Taiwan gives the
ship would be considered ``an open provocation.'' It also has said
it would arrest those on board.
   The 1,200-ton ship, which left France on March 17, is sponsored
by a coalition of press organizations headed by the French news
magazine Actuel, with funds from several Chinese overseas
communities.
   It is named after the statue made by pro-democracy demonstrators
in Tiananmen Square last May and destroyed during the June 4
military crackdown that left hundreds, perhaps thousands, of
demonstrators dead.
   Yan Jiaqi, chairman of the Paris-based Federation for a
Democratic China, said the planned broadcasts were particularly
significant because they would occur close to the anniversary of
the crackdown in Beijing.
   ``People on both sides of the Taiwan Straits should get together
to fight for China's democratization,'' said Yan.
   Earlier, harbor officials rejected requests from Yan and other
Chinese dissidents to board the ship to welcome the crew. Greetings
took place on the pier, where crew members received flowers from
local residents.
   Although the Taiwanese government is the sworn enemy of
Communist Beijing, tensions between the two sides have eased in
recent years.
   Government officials have said the ship will not be allowed to
return to Taiwan if it makes unauthorized broadcasts. Ship
organizers have said they will need to refuel at a Taiwanese port
after three weeks of broadcasting.
   Although Taiwan has tried to distance itself from the vessel,
its military reported Friday that it had sighted a submarine near
the radio ship and restated earlier pledges to protect the vessel
if it is attacked near Taiwan.
   China accused Taiwan on Sunday of covertly helping the mission:
``The Taiwan authorities that have been active in supporting the
Goddess of Democracy in its illegal activities,'' China's official
Xinhua News Agency said.
   Taiwan's state Broadcasting Corp. of China quoted unidentified
Chinese authorities as saying Sunday that Beijing officials would
arrest any dissidents aboard the radio ship when it begins
broadcasting.
   Chinese authorities also said they would arrest the ship's crew
for violating international laws by making unauthorized broadcasts,
according to a Sunday edition of China Time Express.
   ``Our only protection is the live broadcasts from the ship. If
anything happens, the world will know,'' said Christophe Nick, a
journalist for Actuel.
   The ship will carry a French crew and several journalists, but
no Chinese dissidents. Organizers have prepared taped programming
and say they expect the broadcasts will be heard in Beijing.
   ``This is a private initiative created by a mobilization of
reporters. It serves nobody but press freedom,'' said Robert
Menard, head of the Paris-based Reporters Without Borders. ``We do
not request any support from any government. We just require to
work in peace and independently.''
   The Nationalist Chinese government retreated to Taiwan in 1949
after losing a civil war to Communist forces in mainland China.
While the two sides remain technically at war, indirect trade and
civilian contacts have increased greatly in recent years.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0030 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 1434EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Philippines-Americans     05-13 0399</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Philippines-Americans,0407</SECOND>
<HEAD>Summary of Americans Killed By Communist Rebels</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Philippines-US, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MANILA, Philippines (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here is a summary of attacks by
Filipino Communist rebels on Americans during the 21-year Marxist
insurgency:
   April 13, 1974: Three Navy officers from a construction regiment
were ambushed and killed by guerrillas near the Subic Bay naval
base, 50 miles west of Manila. The victims were inspecting a new
highway project when ambushed by about 16 New People's Army rebels.
   Oct. 28, 1987: Two airmen, one retired Air Force sergeant and a
Filipino civilian of U.S. descent were slain in a series of near
simultaneous attacks near Clark. U.S. officials believe they were
killed in reprisal for American military ambulances having
evacuated Filipino troops wounded in a clash with the rebels near
Clark. The rebels claimed responsibility.
   April 21, 1989: Army Col. James ``Nick'' Rowe was ambushed and
killed as he rode to work at the Joint U.S. Military Assistance
Group in suburban Quezon City. The following day, the commander of
the New People's Army, Romulo Kintanar, claimed responsibility in
retaliation for U.S. ``arrogant trampling'' upon Philippine
independence.
   Sept. 26, 1989: Two American civilians employed by the Air Force
at Camp O'Donnell, 10 miles north of Clark, were ambushed on the
day Vice President Dan Quayle arrived in Manila for an official
visit. Rebels fired M-16 rifles from a commandeered dump truck and
a jeep. Although there was never a claim of responsibility, U.S.
officials believe the rebels were responsible.
   Feb. 21, 1990: American civilian geologist John Robert Mitchell,
42, of Fairbanks, Alaska, was ambushed and slain along with his
Filipino wife and father-in-law on Bohol island. Rebels later said
they were trying to kill the father-in-law because he refused to
pay ``revolutionary taxes'' and that Mitchell was caught in the
cross-fire.
   March 6, 1990: Stewart Frank Raab, 76, a longtime Philippine
resident, was killed by rebels on Masbate island after he refused
to pay ``revolutionary taxes.'' Police identified two longtime
rebel commanders as his killers, but no arrests have been made.
   May 4, 1990: Marine Gunnery Sgt. John Fredette, 34, was slain by
several assailants near Subic. No claim of responsibility was made,
but U.S. officials believe rebels were responsible. Two Filipino
drug addicts were arrested for the killing, but U.S. officials
doubt they were the killers. Civilian prosecutors have refused to
prosecute the two unless police gather more evidence.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0031 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 1435EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-SchoolProductivity     05-13 0552</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-School Productivity,500</SECOND>
<HEAD>Report: Make Schools More Productive, Not Richer</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: `Acanemia,' 4th graf, is cq</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By TAMARA HENRY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Education Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Poor productivity, not meager budgets, is the
main problem of the nation's schools, a noted education researcher
said Sunday.
   Lewis J. Perelman of the Hudson Institute said ``American
schools actually are shortchanging the nation by wasting some $100
billion a year through sprawling bureaucracy and outmoded
technology.''
   In a rebuttal to those who claim increased education spending
will improve student achievement, he said ``More spending on more
of the same education will waste resources, weaken the U.S. economy
and undermine the nation's global competitiveness.''
   In a report released Sunday, ``The `Acanemia' Deception,''
Perelman said the United States spent $3,310 to educate each
student from preschool to grade 12 in 1985. The expenditure is
second only to Switzerland, which spent $3,683. The figures are
based on a special 1985 index of purchasing power of industrial
nations.
   The statistics contradict a recent analysis by the Economic
Policy Institute that said the United States trailed 13 other
industrial nations in spending on elementary and secondary
education.
   The EPI recommended adding at least $20 billion per year to the
nation's kindergarten through 12th grade spending.
   Perelman, a senior research fellow at the conservative Hudson
Institute research group in Indianapolis, said the EPI used
``tortured statistics in an attempt to discredit President Bush's
contention that the focus of education reform `must no longer be on
resources; it must be on results.'''
   Perelman said better academic results do not require spending
more on education, and spending more on education is at least as
likely to cause economic decline as to reverse it.
   He said the United States spent 4.1 percent of its gross
domestic product on kindergarten through 12th grades, yet showed
dismal achievement in mathematics and science.
   South Korea spent 3.1 percent on education; Spain, 2.6 percent;
and the United Kingdom, 4.5 percent _ and all outperformed U.S.
students.
   ``Restructuring education does not require bigger budgets but
different budget priorities,'' he said.
   Key findings of Perelman's report were:
   _U.S. education labor costs were 93 percent of output, compared
with 54 percent for the average U.S. business and 46 percent for
high-tech business.
   _Education invests 100 to 1,000 times less in research and
development or in acquiring technology than most businesses, and
several thousand times less than high-technology industries.
   _Computers have been documented to increase efficiency and
accelerate learning. The report said there are 2 million computers
in the nation's 100,000 schools _ about one for every 20 students.
That compares with 40 million personal computers in homes, or one
for every two homes.
   Among his recommendations, Perelman said:
   _Every education and training institution, organization and
program in the United States should set aside at least 1 percent of
its gross revenues for investment in research and development. The
funds could be pooled in a common fund administered by a new
National Institute for Learning Technology.
   _The goal of the new investment in educational initiative should
be to double the productivity of U.S.
   _Every student in America should have access to a ``distance
learning'' network by the year 2001. He explained that teachers can
instruct a variety of students across the state or country at the
same time with the two-way video.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0032 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 1449EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People     05-13 0862</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People,0895</SECOND>
<HEAD>People in the News</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY44</HEAD>
<DATELINE>FORT WORTH, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The next project for
dancer-choreographer Tommy Tune will focus on humorist Will Rogers,
and Tune says it will nothing like James Whitmore's one-man show.
   ``Oh, Lord, no,'' said Tune. ``It's a big one. Lots of
showgirls, lots of dancers, lots of staircases.''
   Tune, 51, is again working with Tony Walton, the movie and stage
designer who created the set for ``Grand Hotel,'' which has been
nominated for 12 Tony Awards.
   A Dec. 1 opening is planned for the Will Rogers musical, which
has music written by Cy Coleman, whose current hit is ``City of
Angels.''
   ``It's going to be done like the Ziegfeld Follies, but based on
the life of Will Rogers, because he was a star of the Follies,''
said Tune, in his native Texas to perform Friday at a benefit
performance with the Manhattan Rhythm Kings.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Academy Award-winning actress Meryl Streep
and her husband, sculptor Donald Gummer, have bought a two-story,
Spanish-style house here for more than $3 million.
   Miss Streep, a New Jersey native who has been outspoken about
her preference for Connecticut and the East Coast in general, said
the purchase was strictly business.
   ``We bought here because I got a job here. I never made a movie
in Hollywood before,'' the star of ``Sophie's Choice'' and ``Kramer
vs. Kramer'' said in a telephone interview from Burbank, where she
is filming ``Defending Your Life,'' a romantic comedy co-starring
Albert Brooks.
   The 6,469-square-foot house on the city's west side has four
bedrooms, 5{ baths and mountain and canyon views.
   ``We're planning to go home (to Connecticut),'' Miss Streep
said, ``but we found this as a place where we can stay whenever we
come out and I work here again.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>SARATOGA SPRINGS, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   It wasn't the usual commencement
speech jazz that bassist Milt ``The Judge'' Hinton gave at Skidmore
College's 79th commencement ceremony.
   The 79-year-old Hinton, considered the patriarch of jazz bass
players, received an honorary degree Saturday from the liberal arts
college and, in lieu of the usual words of inspiration, played two
songs on his stand-up bass.
   ``In the vernacular of the jazz musician, this is blowing my
mind,'' Hinton said of receiving an honorary doctor of humane
letters degree.
   Hinton, who spent 16 years in Cab Calloway's band and was
schoolmates with Lionel Hampton and Nat King Cole in Chicago,
played ``Joshua Fought The Battle of Jericho'' and ``Old Man Time.''
   He received a standing ovation from the 530 graduates and
approximately 4,000 family, friends and faculty who filled the
amphitheater of the Saratoga Performing Arts Center.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Simon Weston, the badly burned Falklands war
veteran whose courage and optimism made him a celebrity in Britain,
was married at the chapel of his Welsh Guards regiment.
   Weston, 28, married 22-year-old Lucy Titherington on Saturday,
the eighth anniversary of the day he set sail for the Falkland
Islands and the 74-day war that drove Argentine forces out of the
British colony.
   The young guardsman suffered severe burns when the troop ship
Sir Galahad was bombed. He had many operations to rebuild his face
but is still badly scarred.
   Weston, emerging from the chapel near Buckingham Palace,
displayed some of the sense of humor that endeared him to his
countrymen.
   Asked if, after his injuries, he thought he would ever get
married, he replied with a mischievous grin: ``No, I thought I had
more sense.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>ATCHISON, Kan. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Poet Robert Bly refused an honorary degree
from Benedictine College because of a flap over abortion at the
small Roman Catholic school.
   ``I hope everyone will understand this is an act of love for the
college, because it is a remarkable college,'' Bly said to 132
graduating seniors and their families during commencement Saturday.
   Bly objected to protests over a similar degree awarded to Gordon
Parks, a photographer, filmmaker and author who is affiliated with
Planned Parenthood, which supports abortion rights. He said there
should be room for compromise on the abortion issue.
   Anti-abortion advocates said it was inappropriate for someone
associated with abortion rights to receive an honorary degree at
the Catholic school. Parks decided April 27 to withdraw his
acceptance of the degree, saying he did not want the controversy to
detract from the commencement.
   ``By the element that was opposed to his (Parks') coming _ by
their winning, something was lost for everyone,'' Bly told the
audience.
   Bly said his decision was made after negotiations with the
college just 24 hours before the ceremony. But he did not make the
withdrawal public until the commencement ceremony.
   ``In acknowledgement of the withdrawal of Gordon Parks'
acceptance of the invitation to receive an honor, it has been
decided that no honorary degrees will be given this year,''
Benedictine President Thomas O. James told the graduating class.
   School officials declined to comment afterward.
   Bly, a recipient of the National Hope Award and a Guggenheim
fellow, teaches at the University of Minnesota. Parks, who serves
on Planned Parenthood's board of directors, is best known for his
photography and films including ``Shaft'' and ``The Learning Tree.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0033 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 1502EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Bush-Golf     05-13 0251</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bush-Golf,230</SECOND>
<HEAD>Neither Mother's Day Nor Rain Keeps Bush From Appointed Golf
Rounds</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Mother's Day or no, rain or no, President Bush
went on a 4{-hour golf outing with a few pals Sunday.
   Bush got in a soggy round on the Andrews Air Force Base course
with pro golfer Lee Elder, former congressman Thomas ``Lud'' Ashley
and national security adviser Brent Scowcroft.
   The foursome hit the links shortly after Bush, his wife,
Barbara, and Scowcroft attended a communion service at St. John's
Episcopal Church across Lafayette Square from the White House.
   Bush teed off under overcast skies that soon opened up into a
downpour. The presidential party played on for 18 holes. Bush, who
started the round in a pink sweater, finished in a white one, his
hair dripping wet.
   ``Well, that was fun,'' the president said as he walked off the
18th green and paid off a dollar bet to Elder.
   An onlooker asked what Bush shot.
   ``Quite a bit,'' was the president's only reply.
   ``Next time we'll try to get out here when there's a little
sunshine,'' the president told the course manager Andrews, located
in Maryland suburbs outside Washington.
   It has poured during several recent Bush golf outings, both at
Andrews and in Bermuda where he played last month after a meeting
with British Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher.
   White House press aide Jay Allison said the Bushes had nothing
special planned for Mother's Day, except screening a Chuck Norris
movie later Sunday with friends.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0034 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 1504EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>d a AM-BRF--AutoAuction     05-13 0201</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Auto Auction,0206</SECOND>
<HEAD>That's Some Used Car: 1907 Rolls Sells For Nearly $3 Million</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PALM BEACH, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A 1907 Rolls Royce Silver Ghost has been
sold for $2.86 million, a world record price for a Rolls, an
auction spokesman said.
   ``This is the best Rolls there is,'' British businessman Charles
Howard said of the cream-colored car, once owned by the Rockefeller
family. ``I've watched this car for 20 years. I'm very thrilled to
get it now.''
   It and a sister auto, which sold for $2.25 million, are among
only four known to exist.
   They were from the collection of Rick Carroll, who spent 27
years buying and restoring cars and automobile memorabilia before
his death in a car crash last year.
   ``These cars were the blood that made his heart pump,'' said Tom
Ehrbar, a friend. ``He tucked them in at night, literally.''
   People from Florida, Europe and Japan spent nearly $21 million
on 23 other vintage autos _ including seven Duesenbergs, a Bentley,
Packard and a Baby Bugatti _ auctioned Saturday by Sotheby's.
   The highest price paid at auction for any car was $9.8 million
for a 1931 Bugatti Royale, sold in 1987 at Christie's in London.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0035 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 1514EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Dubcek     05-13 0500</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Dubcek,450</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dubcek Says 1968 Uprising Foretold Today's Changes in Eastern
Europe</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KAREN BALL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Czechoslovakia's Alexander Dubcek said Sunday
that the Prague Spring reform movement of 1968, crushed by Red Army
tanks, helped plant the seeds of the revolutionary changes now
sweeping Eastern Europe.
   Dubcek, delivering the commencement address at American
University, also said Czechoslovakia began to fear a loss of
identity after the Soviet invasion of 1968.
   ``An act of violence and malevolence relegated us to the role of
a pawn in a great game of politics,'' Dubcek said. ``Once again, we
were reminded that our country lies at the front line, at the
frontier of the Cold War.''
   But he said the country's push toward reform more than two
decades ago influenced today's changes in Eastern Europe.
   Dubcek said Soviet dissident Andrei Sakharov had written him a
letter shortly before he died last year and recalled the hope that
Prague Spring had given him and the bitterness that followed during
years when ``time stood still.''
   ``But fire burned beneath the ashes. I am convinced that the
breath of truth that the Czechs and Slovaks inhaled ... is the
prologue to today's bloodless revolutions in the countries of
Eastern Europe,'' Dubcek quoted Sakharov as writing.
   ``If that is true, then Prague Spring ... is the source of ideas
that have resulted in the revolutionary changes presently taking
place in our country, which are taking place in the Soviet Union,
in Eastern Europe,'' Dubcek told graduates through an interpreter.
   Dubcek, making his first visit to the United States, met Friday
with Secretary of State James A. Baker III and members of Congress.
He echoed the message Czechoslovakian President Vaclav Havel made
to Congress three months ago, voicing support for reform within the
Soviet Union.
   At a news conference Saturday, Dubcek said President Bush's
proposed $300 million aid package for Eastern Europe was a ``very
helpful'' starting point that would help ``open the doors for new
entrepreneurs.''
   Bush on Saturday also called for creation of a ``citizens
democracy corps'' in which U.S. citizens could help build democracy
in Eastern Europe.
   At Sunday's ceremony, American University also awarded Dubcek an
honorary degree, calling him ``a symbol in the face of tyranny''
for launching the Prague Spring reforms and trying to create a new
``socialism with a human face.''
   Dubcek, who headed his country's Communist Party at the time of
the 1968 Soviet invasion, said the transition to democracy should
be ``smooth, gradual, cultured, civilized.''
   ``We are still searching for a path to make our way in this new
world of new politics,'' he said.
   Dubcek, who now serves as chairman of his country's Federal
Parliament, said he hoped the 21st century would be one of
``maximum creativity and humanity.''
   ``I see the new century as one of great cooperation between
nations, a century marked by the melding of political systems.''
   Dubcek was scheduled to receive a human rights award from an
attorney's group Tuesday.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0036 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 1535EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-India-Storm     05-13 0600</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-India-Storm,0621</SECOND>
<HEAD>Cyclone Batters Farming Region, Kills 450</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto DEL1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN POMFRET</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW DELHI, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The worst cyclone in more than a decade
in India has gutted the economy of a rich agricultural region and
killed 450 people, officials said Sunday.
   The death toll from last week's storm rose with the discovery
Sunday of 151 more bodies littered along the low-lying,
heavily-populated coast of Andhra Pradesh state, Indian media said.
   Officials said the cyclone also killed more than 100,000 farm
animals and caused $600 million in damage to crops.
   Air force and navy helicopters meanwhile continued relief
operations along the southern Indian coast. So far, troops have
distributed 340,000 food packets and sent hundreds of tankers
filled with water to areas that were cut off from outside help for
up to three days.
   Several villages remained marooned and navy craft still could
not reach them. News reports said hundreds of people were still
being rescued from trees where they had taken refuge after the
cyclone hit Wednesday.
   Andhra Pradesh's chief minister, M. Chenna Reddy, described the
situation along the coast as ``very bad.''
   ``The damage has been colossal,'' he told reporters in
Hyderabad, the capital of Andhra Pradesh.
   In all, he said, 6.5 million people had been affected by the
storm, which at its peak tore into the farming region packing winds
of up to 155 mph. Agricultural damage was estimated at $588
million. More than 100,000 farm animals, mainly goats, cows and
water buffaloes, died in the disaster.
   Reports said sea water that contaminated all of the fresh water
wells along the coast began to recede Sunday. But rain, forecast
for much of the region, could set rescue work back, said C. Arjun
Rao, the top relief officer in Andhra Pradesh.
   He said hundreds of trucks with bread and milk were being rushed
to the hardest-hit regions to feed thousands of people who had not
eaten in three days. In all, 9,100 gallons of milk had been
distributed, he said.
   Relief officials said the destruction of last week's storm was
worse than a 1977 cyclone that killed 10,000 people. At least
434,720 acres of rice paddies were rendered useless along with huge
tracts of mangos and bananas.
   ``The stench of dead livestock filled the air. Bloated bodies of
cows and sheep filled farm yards and villages everywhere,'' wrote
the Times of India.
   Appeals went out across the nation Sunday for money for storm
victims.
   Prime Minister V.P. Singh, who made an emergency visit to the
area Saturday, announced the release of $52 million to help in
relief operations. Singh appealed to the public for clothes,
medicine and food, and the government said families who lost
relatives will get $1,470 each.
   Cyclones are the Indian equivalent of hurricanes, and usually
come in the spring just before the rainy monsoon season begins.
   Last week's storm began Tuesday when 33-foot-high tidal waves
and heavy rains bashed the coast of Andhra Pradesh and Tamil Nadu,
two southern Indian states.
   It reached its peak Wednesday as it roared over the low-lying,
densely-populated plain of fishing villages and rice paddies in
Andhra Pradesh.
   Thousands of houses were flattened in the storm.
   Officials credited early satellite warning and the fast
evacuation of 150,000 people with keeping the death toll low
compared with 1977.
   Most of the casualties occurred when houses, mostly made of mud
and straw, collapsed. Some people were carried away by flooded
rivers and others died when electrical wires tumbled down.
   Another 470,000 people were evacuated from the coast and placed
in 530 relief camps, reports said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0037 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 1551EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Madagascar     05-13 0533</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Madagascar,0555</SECOND>
<HEAD>Coup Attempt Leaves 3 Dead in Madagascar</HEAD>
<HEAD>With LaserGraphic</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CHRISTIAN CHADEFAUX</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ANTANANARIVO, Madagascar (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Soldiers thwarted a coup attempt
Sunday by routing about 10 armed dissidents who seized the national
radio station and declared the government overthrown. Three people
were reported killed.
   Soldiers stormed the station in Antananarivo, the capital,
several hours after it was occupied, and arrested the dissidents.
No fighting was reported elsewhere on the Indian Ocean nation off
the east coast of Africa.
   Hospitals reported at least three people died and 15 were
wounded by bullets and grenades in the fighting between the rebels
and troops. Government officials did not confirm the casualties.
   It was the second time in two years that opponents of President
Didier Ratsiraka had seized state-run Radio Madagascar. Ratsiraka
has ruled since 1975.
   The casualties appeared to occur in a crowd of 5,000 people
milling before the radio station. Troops fired tear gas to disperse
them before storming the building about noon, witnesses said. It
was not known whether the crowd supported the rebels or merely came
to watch the confrontation.
   The troops exchanged gunfire with the 11 rebels, who were armed
with automatic weapons, pistols and knives, witnesses said.
   The director of the radio network said eight of his employees
taken hostage were liberated by the troops. No one died inside the
station, he said.
   The dissidents claimed to be members of the previously unknown
Republican Committee of Public Safety, sources said. Their
political beliefs were unknown.
   Gangs of youths roaming the streets later set two cars ablaze
and hurled rocks through windows at the Justice Ministry and the
American Cultural Center, a U.S. Embassy official said on condition
of anonymity.
   ``There were two small display windows that were broken'' at the
center, the official said. ``As far as we know, it came from random
widow breaking. It wasn't directed against the American Embassy or
the cultural center.''
   No Americans were injured, the official said. The center is
about two miles across town from the radio station.
   Rebels seized the station at dawn Sunday, and a woman came on
the air to call on the population to rise against the government.
   She called for the populace to demand that retired Gen. Jean
Rakotoharison, an opposition figure, be named the new president.
   The broadcast was cut off after about 45 minutes, and government
forces surrounded the building. Witnesses said Rakotoharison came
to the station later and declined the offer. The government
announced before the building was stormed that the situation in the
country was normal.
   A Madagascar opposition group based in Paris claimed 50 people
died in the clash between the rebels and soldiers, but those
figures were dismissed by a journalist on the scene as ``completely
false.''
   The journalist said calm had returned to the area around the
station.
   On July 24, 1989, six armed men took over the national radio and
claimed the government had been toppled. However, the government
recaptured the station and there was no violence elsewhere.
   Ratsiraka has led this country of 10 million people since he was
installed by the military in June 1975.
   The country gained independence from France in 1960.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0038 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 1605EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Soviet-China     05-13 0305</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-China,0314</SECOND>
<HEAD>Students Stage Hunger Strikes to Remember Chinese Students</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Scores of students in Moscow and at nearly 50
other universities in the Soviet Union staged hunger strikes this
weekend to honor slain pro-democracy demonstrators in China, it was
reported Sunday.
   Dozens of students camped out in tents on the grass in front of
Moscow State University remembered the Chinese students who fasted
on Beijing's Tiananmen Square a year ago, before the crackdown.
   Students from the university, as well as other institutes around
Moscow, displayed slogans in Russian, Chinese and English, lighted
candles and sang songs during their 24-hour protest that began
Saturday, the Tass news agency reported.
   In a report on the demonstration, a journalist with the TV
newscast ``Vremya'' asked one of the students why he had joined the
hunger strike, the youth replied, ``Because I don't like tanks
running over people.''
   In Leningrad, 34 students joined the hunger strike outside the
Chinese consulate, but it also became a demonstration against the
Kremlin's economic embargo against Lithuania and ``the totalitarian
system'' in the Soviet Union, according to the independent
Northwest news agency.
   Tass reported the students in Moscow mentioned the April 1989
killings of 20 pro-democracy demonstrators by the Soviet army in
Tbilisi, the capital of the southern republic of Georgia.
   ``We demand that our government guarantee that events like those
in Beijing or in Tbilisi never happen here,'' said A. Kiryushin, a
student of the Moscow Chemical Technology Institute.
   According to Tass, Kiryushin said the hunger strike was
supported by students at nearly 50 other universities or institutes
in various Soviet republics.
   Many of the students wore white headbands, recalling those worn
by the demonstrators in China.
   Hundreds if not thousands of people were killed in the June 3-4
crackdown by the Chinese military on demonstators in Beijing.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0039 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 1608EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-BudgetTalks     05-13 0508</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Budget Talks,460</SECOND>
<HEAD>Darman Says White House Willing To Consider Tax Hike, With
Conditions</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Budget-Economics</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: Stands for AM-Budget-Congress listed on AM-News Digest</NOTE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Bush administration indicated a
willingness Sunday to consider tax increases in a budget summit
this week, but only in exchange for a line-item veto or other
measures to give the president more direct control to cut federal
spending.
   ``We shouldn't consider a tax increase independently of major
budget process reform,'' White House Budget Director Richard G.
Darman said. Otherwise, he said, ``the money would be spent and it
wouldn't reduce the deficit.''
   Darman's comments on ABC-TV's ``This Week With David Brinkley''
program were the first public affirmation by a top White House
official that Bush is willing to consider more taxes as part of his
``no preconditions'' pledge to congressional Democrats.
   But White House Chief of Staff John Sununu, who was chastised
last week after commenting that Bush would veto any tax increase,
said on CBS-TV's ``Face the Nation'' show Sunday the administration
is still ``likely to look askance'' at a tax hike.
   Darman tried to lower expectations on how big a
deficit-reduction package might emerge from the negotiations among
26 top congressional and administration officials, scheduled to
begin Tuesday.
   Acknowledging that government spending in fiscal 1991 now
threatens to exceed revenues by $164 billion to $184 billion, he
said a ``realistic'' reduction in the size of that deficit without
forcing the country into a recession would be $45 billion to $55
billion.
   The Gramm-Rudman law requires that the projected deficit going
into the new fiscal year, which begins Oct. 1, not exceed $64
billion.
   ``It's not going to be sensible to try to contract that much in
one year ... in a way that is consistent with continued economic
growth,'' Darman said.
   In addition to a line-item veto repeatedly rejected by Congress,
Darman said the White House wants more authority to cut spending
across the board long after a budget has been approved.
   Congressional Democrats, meanwhile, continued to insist that
Bush go first in putting a tax increase on the table.
   ``We're not going to talk about raising taxes,'' Sen. James
Sasser, D-Tenn., chairman of the Senate Budget Committee, said on
the ABC program. ``I'd like very much and I think the Congress
would like to see the president's proposal for solving this
problem.''
   Darman said that because every solution is politically
unpopular, there is a reluctance by all sides to put anything _
higher taxes, entitlement freezes, spending cuts _ on the table.
   ``The president could start with a moment of silence that could
turn into an hour and half of silence,'' he quipped. ``Eventually,
if people are there seriously and in good faith, things manage to
get on the table; sometimes they get on there anonymously.''
   As examples, Darman cited South Carolina Democratic Sen. Ernest
F. Hollings' suggestion for a value-added tax and a package of
spending and entitlement freezes coupled with higher tax rates for
upper income earners suggested earlier by Rep. Dan Rostenkowski,
D-Ill.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0040 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 1623EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Lebanon     05-13 0220</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lebanon,0226</SECOND>
<HEAD>2 Killed, 16 Wounded in Fighting in Lebanon</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BEIRUT, Lebanon (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Rival Christian forces battled Sunday in
east Beirut and the surrounding hinterland, killing two people and
wounding 16, police said.
   The intermittent clashes intensified after 4 p.m. when Gen.
Michel Aoun's troops and militiamen of Samir Geagea's Lebanese
Forces pounded each others' areas with rocket and artillery fire.
   Police said Aoun's gunners fired dozens of 155mm howitzer shells
into east Beirut's residential district of Ashrafiyeh, Geagea's
main stronghold in the capital, and the militia-controlled port of
Jounieh, 12 miles north of Beirut.
   In turn, Lebanese Forces militiamen fired barrages from
multi-barreled rocket launchers on the Aoun-controlled districts of
Jedeideh and the Death River in east Beirut.
   Both sides also were engaged in heavy fighting in Metn and
Kesrouan provinces northeast of the capital, according to police.
   The hostilities kept all roads blocked for a sixth straight day
between the Aoun-controlled Metn mountains and the rest of the
enclave, under the authority of Geagea's militiamen.
   There was no immediate report on casualties from the afternoon
gunbattles. Police reported two people were killed and 16 wounded
in the overnight-to-dawn clashes.
   The inconclusive intra-Christian war for mastery of the
310-square-mile Christian enclave has claimed the lives of 942
people and wounded 2,622 since it broke out Jan. 30.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0041 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 1632EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-DissidentPriest 1stLd-Writethru a0696 05-13 0273</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Dissident Priest, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0696,250</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dissident Catholic Priest Ordained as Bishop</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: ADDS 2 grafs to INSERT comment from Stallings</NOTE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Catholic priest who broke away from Rome to
start his own African-American Catholic Church has been ordained as
the congregation's first bishop.
   The Rev. George Augustus Stallings, who cut his Vatican ties in
June 1989 and began his own Imani Temple African-American Catholic
Congregation, was ordained by the Rev. Richard W. Bridges,
archbishop and president of the Independent Old Catholic Churches
of California.
   African dancers, gospel singers and more than 1,000 worshipers
participated in the four-hour service Saturday for Stallings.
   Bridges' church split from the Roman Catholic Church during the
1870s over a dispute of papal infallibility.
   Stallings knelt on the decorated stage filled with elaborate
banners, drummers and icons while bishops from The Old Catholic
Church declared him ``a suitable candidate for the office of bishop
in the Church of God.''
   In a printed statement, Stallings said his ordainment would be a
solemn and memorable day in which African-American Catholics
``would formalize and establish their place in history, as an
autonomous and independent Catholic Church.''
   The African-American Catholic Congregation has temples in
Washington, Baltimore, Norfolk and Philadelphia.
   Published reports allege that Stallings was involved in
homosexual relationships with young men and misused funds from a
Catholic parish.
   Stallings has said an article about a 16-year-old boy published
last September was ``scurrilous, baseless and unmerited.''
   When similar allegations were made in a newspaper report last
month, he told his congregation ``God will take care of the
situation,'' although he did not specifically mention the article
in question.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0042 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 1636EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Deng     05-13 0490</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Deng,0506</SECOND>
<HEAD>Deng Meets Mubarak in First Public Appearance in Three Months</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto BEJ2</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Senior leader Deng Xiaoping met Sunday with
Egyptian President Hosni Mubarak for his first public appearance in
three months, dispelling the latest rumors of his death.
   A Chinese reporter said on condition of anonymity that Deng
spoke of last week's rumor on Asian financial markets that he was
dead. ``But here I am today,'' he said.
   The meeting between the leaders lasted about one hour, the
reporter said.
   He said Chinese journalists were told not to report on the
meeting. The national television news failed to mention it, the
first time it has ever been known to keep silent on a meeting
between Deng and a visiting head of state.
   However, more than 10 hours after the meeting ended, the
official Xinhua News Agency issued a brief report, saying Deng met
Mubarak ``as his old friend.'' Xinhua also suddenly made a
photograph of the meeting available, after having refused photo
requests earlier in the day.
   The reason for the earlier news blackout was not clear.
   ``Since my retirement, I have not met visitors,'' Xinhua quoted
Deng as saying. ``But it is not good for me not to meet a few old
friends.''
   It quoted Mubarak as saying, ``We are very delighted to meet
you, an old friend of Egypt. Thank Allah, you enjoy very good
health. I wish you a long life.'' Mubarak, who arrived Friday, left
later Sunday for North Korea.
   Deng, 85, retired in March from his last official post, as
chairman of the state military commission. He speaks with
difficulty and walks unsteadily, and Chinese sources say he has
suffered from cancer for several years.
   But he is still believed to set key policies. President Yang
Shangkun, who held a news conference Sunday before he left for
Mexico said, ``present leaders of the central government are
meeting (Deng) very often in various places.''
   Yang said Deng enjoyed ``very good health,'' and still played
bridge avidly.
   Younger officials, such as Communist Party General Secretary
Jiang Zemin, are believed competing for supporters, preparing for
the day when Deng dies and a power vacuum is left at the top.
   Deng last appeared in public in February, when he met with a
Hong Kong delegation. The Hong Kong stock market dropped slightly
Friday after rumors that Deng was very ill or dead.
   Rumors that another aged leader, Chen Yun, is ill or dead also
have been circulating in Hong Kong. Chen, also 85, is a powerful
figure in the conservative camp and patron of Premier Li Peng.
   Yang is the first Chinese head of state to visit Latin America.
The 82-year-old general will visit Mexico, Brazil, Uruguay,
Argentina and Chile.
   His visit is the latest sign of Chinese efforts to solidify
relations with the Third World. Beijing's ties are strained with
most Western countries following the military crackdown on
pro-democracy protesters in June.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0043 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 1638EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Israel-Desecration     05-13 0724</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel-Desecration,0750</SECOND>
<HEAD>Israelis Visit Desecrated Graves in Haifa Cemetery</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos TLV2,2 CARP4</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ARIEH O'SULLIVAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HAIFA, Israel (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Thousands of weeping Israelis gathered
Sunday at a cemetery where tombstones were marked with slogans
calling on Arabs to ``kill the Jews,'' and a Jew from a nearby town
was arrested as a suspect.
   The desecration followed a similar act last week in the French
city of Carpentras, where 34 graves were violated and the body of a
man was dug up and mutilated.
   About 10,000 people gathered in Carpentras in protest Sunday,
and in Paris Jews clashed with right-wing extremists. Some minor
injuries were reported but there were no arrests.
   Israeli police described the 41-year-old man detained in the
vandalism of 300 graves in Haifa as ``eccentric.''
   The slogans were in black spray paint and in grammatical Hebrew.
   Noam Gabrieli, a city official, said on Israel radio the
language was not typical of Palestinian leaflets distributed during
the uprising in the occupied lands and may have been written by a
mentally unstable person.
   But Haifa police chief Yossi Levi said investigators still could
not determine whether the desecration was a political provocation,
the work of Arab extremists or of a mentally disturbed person.
   ``We do not exclude any direction of investigation,'' Levi said.
``According to visual examination ... the writing seems to be done
by one person, but others may have accompanied or guarded him.''
   Police department head Avi Tiller said police bolstered forces
in the city to prevent possible vigilante reprisals and appealed to
the public to ``show reserve.''
   Riot police were also sent to the Kfar Samir Cemetery to guard
against violent demonstrations by thousands of bereaved relatives
and other Israelis who rushed there after the news was reported on
the radio.
   ``I can't believe this happened in a Jewish state,'' said Sonia
Fuar, pointing at the graves of her parents.
   Moshe Ran, a Haifa restaurant owner, wept beside the tomb of his
son Avi, an Israeli national goalkeeper killed in a 1987 boat
accident on the Sea of Galilee. ``Kill the Jews,'' said a slogan
written on Ran's tombstone.
   The desecration was condemned by Jewish and Arab leaders alike,
and Mayor Arieh Gurel called on Haifa residents to keep calm.
   ``This is a sick action from people who learned from the
Neo-Nazis. We will cut off the hands of those who did this,'' Gurel
said.
   He suggested the Haifa incident was inspired by the desecration
in Carpentras. Four skinheads were detained in that case but later
released.
   The desecration in Haifa apparently took place during the Jewish
Sabbath when guards were not present.
   Yosef Yisraeli, whose mother and mother-in-law are buried in
Kfar Samir, said ``I saw the horrible sight, and my blood boiled.''
   Other slogans said ``Moslem Brothers: destroy the Jews and Found
Palestine'' and called on Arab's leaders such as Iraq's Saddam
Hussein to ``burn the Jews.''
   Wajdi Tabari, an Israeli Arab, said the desecration was a ``very
bad thing that would not help peace or coexistence.''
   ``I don't think a Moslem ... would ever think to do something
like this. We respect graves and cemeteries very much in our
religion,'' Tabari said.
   Haifa, a port city in northern Israel where 10 percent of the
220,000 population is Arab, has been symbol of Arab-Israeli
coexistence despite the 29-month-old Palestinian uprising in the
occupied Gaza Strip and West Bank.
   Right-wing and ultra-Orthodox legislators blamed the attack on
Arabs.
   ``What happened in Haifa must return us all to our good senses,
to know with whom we are dealing and to stop fighting among
ourselves and unite,'' said Rabbi Moshe Zeev Feldman of the
ultra-Orthodox Agudat Israel party.
   In France, the nation's Grand Rabbi Joseph Sitruk led prayers at
the cemetery in Carpentras. Similar ceremonies were held in
Marseille, Lyon, Lille and Drancy, the Nazi deportation center from
where Jews were taken to Auschwitz.
   In Paris, heavily armed riot police lined the streets of Paris
to enforce a ban on a parade by extreme right-wing groups, but some
skinheads demonstrated anyway and others passed out neo-Nazi
literature.
   Dozens of Jewish militants armed with sticks and rocks attacked
a group of skinheads outside the famed Madeleine church. In
Bayonne, three leftist youths hurled eggs and rocks at
right-wingers as they lay a wreath at a Joan of Arc statue.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0044 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 1653EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Lites     05-13 0390</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lites,0408</SECOND>
<HEAD>On The Light Side</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MEMPHIS, Tenn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Contestants came from around the world to
challenge Southerners for the title of best barbecuer, and when the
smoke cleared, an Illinois group walked away with top honors.
   ``This is the first time in the contests' history that we've had
a winner from the North,'' festival spokesperson Deanie Parker
said. ``We've had finalists from other parts of the country and
other countries.''
   Apple City Barbecue not only took the title of grand champion at
the 13th annual Memphis in May World Championship Barbecue Cooking
Contest, but also won for best ribs in its first trip to the
Memphis contest. The team's hometown, Murphysboro, is at the
southern tip of Illinois, farther south than parts of Dixie.
   About 150 teams from 20 states and five foreign countries
participated in the three-day event that ended Saturday night.
   Winners also were named in the shoulder, whole hog and the
``Anything But'' segment for cooking other types of meat. Awards
also went for showmanship and hog calling ability.
   The event is listed in the Guinness Book of World Records as the
world's largest pork barbecue contest, with 55,747 pounds of pork
cooked last year.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>BRATTLEBORO, Vt. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A restaurant's sign has lost some
letters and gained some accuracy, but still isn't local officials'
cup of tea.
   Officials in this southeast Vermont town had been after property
owner Michael Lacroix for months to remove a sign over a restaurant
and motel complex where he's the landlord.
   The sign said, ``STEAK $5.99,'' and could be seen clearly from
nearby Interstate 91.
   Unfortunately, the sign violates the town's zoning ordinance.
And what's worse, the restaurant changed hands, went Chinese, and
stopped selling a $5.99 steak.
   One of the problems is now history, at least: A work crew showed
up at the restaurant last week and took down the S, the K, and the
$5.99. Voila _ STEAK $5.99 became that most Chinese of beverages:
TEA.
   ``Now people have to think about what that means,'' said
restaurant manager James Chu.
   Town Manager Glenn Hill was more hopeful than amused, saying he
still wants the whole sign down.
   ``This might just be work in progress to remove the sign,'' he
said.
   Lacroix, however, said he won't take the rest of the sign down
without a fight.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0045 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 1658EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brites     05-13 0397</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brites,0413</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bright &amp; Brief</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Retransmitting a0712 to fix keyword and overline.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>MEMPHIS, Tenn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Contestants came from around the world to
challenge Southerners for the title of best barbecuer, and when the
smoke cleared, an Illinois group walked away with top honors.
   ``This is the first time in the contests' history that we've had
a winner from the North,'' festival spokesperson Deanie Parker
said. ``We've had finalists from other parts of the country and
other countries.''
   Apple City Barbecue not only took the title of grand champion at
the 13th annual Memphis in May World Championship Barbecue Cooking
Contest, but also won for best ribs in its first trip to the
Memphis contest. The team's hometown, Murphysboro, is at the
southern tip of Illinois, farther south than parts of Dixie.
   About 150 teams from 20 states and five foreign countries
participated in the three-day event that ended Saturday night.
   Winners also were named in the shoulder, whole hog and the
``Anything But'' segment for cooking other types of meat. Awards
also went for showmanship and hog calling ability.
   The event is listed in the Guinness Book of World Records as the
world's largest pork barbecue contest, with 55,747 pounds of pork
cooked last year.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>BRATTLEBORO, Vt. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A restaurant's sign has lost some
letters and gained some accuracy, but still isn't local officials'
cup of tea.
   Officials in this southeast Vermont town had been after property
owner Michael Lacroix for months to remove a sign over a restaurant
and motel complex where he's the landlord.
   The sign said, ``STEAK $5.99,'' and could be seen clearly from
nearby Interstate 91.
   Unfortunately, the sign violates the town's zoning ordinance.
And what's worse, the restaurant changed hands, went Chinese, and
stopped selling a $5.99 steak.
   One of the problems is now history, at least: A work crew showed
up at the restaurant last week and took down the S, the K, and the
$5.99. Voila _ STEAK $5.99 became that most Chinese of beverages:
TEA.
   ``Now people have to think about what that means,'' said
restaurant manager James Chu.
   Town Manager Glenn Hill was more hopeful than amused, saying he
still wants the whole sign down.
   ``This might just be work in progress to remove the sign,'' he
said.
   Lacroix, however, said he won't take the rest of the sign down
without a fight.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0046 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 1716EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Nicaragua     05-13 0383</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Nicaragua,0395</SECOND>
<HEAD>Farmers Say They Will Not Give Up Confiscated Land</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RODOLFO GARCIA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MANAGUA, Nicaragua (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   About 125,000 farmers who under the
former Sandinista government received land confiscated from wealthy
landlords will not give up their plots, a newspaper said Sunday.
   On Thursday, the new government led by President Violeta Barrios
de Chamorro announced that landlords whose property was seized by
the Sandinistas will have six months to file claims.
   She also said all unused agricultural and pasture land will be
rented out on a provisional basis and a commission will study how
much rent will be charged.
   ``They would have to go over the cadavers of the cooperative
members and small producers'' if the government tried to take back
land, according to Daniel Nunez, president of the National
Agricultural Workers Union.
   ``We will not allow the application of these laws which are
totally against the people,'' Nunez said. His comments were
published in the pro-Sandinista Nuevo Diario newspaper.
   The U.S.-backed Mrs. Chamorro has said she will review all laws
passed by the leftist Sandinistas during their 10 years in office.
Mrs. Chamorro, who defeated Daniel Ortega in elections in February,
replaced him April 25.
   The Sandinistas handed out weapons among supporters before
leaving office, and Mrs. Chamorro has ordered the military to take
back those weapons.
   Some civilians began turning in their weapons over the weekend.
Ninety-nine farm workers turned over their rifles to authorities in
La Verbena, about 180 miles southeast of Managua, on Saturday.
   Nunez said 50,000 farm union members will rally outside the
presidential palace to protest Mrs. Chamorro's decree and demand 10
percent of the $300 million in U.S. aid earmarked for Nicaragua be
used for farm credits.
   During its decade in power, the Sandinistas confiscated and gave
away thousands of privately owned farms. The Sandinistas on
Saturday called Mrs. Chamorro's decrees ``dictatorial and
unconstitutional.''
   The government has refused to give public employees a 200
percent raise to make up for inflation. Government workers went on
strike last week after rejecting a government offer of 60 percent.
   Among measures announced Thursday, Mrs. Chamorro suspended a
civil service law that protected employees from being fired and
granted them the right to strike and bargain collectively. She has
said the country is virtually bankrupt.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0047 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 1724EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Mandela     05-13 0624</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mandela,0647</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mandela Defends Wife in First Comment on Controversy</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto LUA1</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LAGOS, Nigeria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   South African black nationalist leader
Nelson Mandela on Sunday defended his wife, Winnie, saying she had
been the victim of the ``most scandalous persecution'' by the
government.
   It was Mandela's first comment on criticisms of Mrs. Mandela,
one of whose former bodyguards is on trial in connection with the
kidnapping and killing of a 14-year-old black activist.
   Three men have testified they were abducted in December 1988
along with the teen-ager and taken to Mrs. Mandela's Soweto house.
They testified she beat them with a whip and her fists and
permitted her bodyguards to assault them.
   The boy, James ``Stompie'' Seipei, was later found dead in a
field.
   Mrs. Mandela has said she was not present during beatings. She
was ostracized for a time by some anti-apartheid leaders over the
activities of her bodyguards and questions over her own involvement.
   A few months later, however, she resumed making joint
appearances with other anti-apartheid leaders, and has been
publicly at the side of her husband since his release from prison
in February.
   Mrs. Mandela has not been charged in the case, and both the
prosecution and defense have said they would not call her to
testify.
   Mandela made no specific reference to the allegations. But he
told a crowd of 30,000 cheering Nigerians: ``Even now as I am
talking to you she is still being persecuted in South Africa.''
   He said Winnie Mandela was ``the victim of the most scandalous
persecution by the government and its agencies.'' Despite
government restrictions on her activities during his 27 years in
prison, she ``fought back against all forms of injustice,'' Mandela
said.
   Mandela thanked the Nigerian government and people for support
during his time in prison.
   Earlier, in the Angolan capital of Luanda, Mandela urged the
West not to end sanctions against South Africa.
   ``Our policy is very clear. We have called on the international
community to isolate South Africa and that is still our position,''
Mandela told a news conference ending a 3{-day official visit.
   South African President F.W. de Klerk is on a European tour,
during which he has been touting progress made in ending apartheid
and arguing that it is time to end the diplomatic and economic
isolation of South Africa.
   The South African government outlawed the African National
Congress in 1960, and the organization began a guerrilla campaign
the following year to overthrow white minority rule and end the
system of racial segregation.
   De Klerk legalized the ANC in February and met with Mandela last
month. Delegations from the government and the ANC reached a broad
agreement to work for an end to political violence an prepare the
way for black entry into government.
   Mandela indicated the ANC was prepared to compromise with de
Klerk on several points, but said demands for full voting rights
were not negotiable.
   ``The demand of one person, one vote is one on which it is
inconceivable to expect us to compromise,'' he said. ``What would
this fight have been all about, if we are not going to press that
demand exactly as it is?''
   He promised the ANC would work to address white fears about
black suffrage.
   ``We mean to remove any concerns ... because it is absolutely
necessary for the future of South Africa to retain white expertise
and skill,'' he said.
   Asked whether he intended to run for president in any future
democratic elections in South Africa, the 71-year-old activist said
he had ``no such ambition.''
   But, he said, ``I will do what the ANC and the South African
people require me to do.''
   On his African tour, Mandela was also traveling to Algeria,
Libya, Egypt and possibly Kenya.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0048 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 1728EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-NBC-SNL 1stLd-Writethru a0698 05-13 0464</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-NBC-SNL, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0698,0473</SECOND>
<HEAD>Top Ratings, Protests Accompany `Saturday Night Live'</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 3rd graf to CLARIFY rating was 8 percentage points
higher than previous high rating sted 8 percent.</NOTE>
<HEAD>With BC-Dice Man</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The controversial Andrew Dice Clay edition of
``Saturday Night'' got its highest overnight ratings this season _
and what an NBC spokesman said Sunday probably was the most
pre-show protests in its history.
   The show, whose guest host is known for a coarse brand of humor
that disparages women and minorities, averaged a rating of 11.6 and
got a 31 percent share of the audience in the 24-city overnight
Nielsen ratings, NBC said.
   That was 8 percentage points greater than the previous
record-holder, a ``Saturday Night Live'' with Fred Savage of ABC's
``The Wonder Years'' as host, which ran Feb. 24, NBC said.
   The highest overnight rating for Saturday's broadcast was in
Chicago, where it had a 17.8 rating and a 37 percent share of the
audience in its time period. In New York, the nation's largest
television market, it averaged a 15.2 rating and a 33 percent
audience share.
   National ratings won't be available until Monday.
   Before the show aired, NBC's New York and Burbank offices got a
total of 1,764 complaints protesting Clay's appearance, with only
198 callers praising Clay, NBC spokesman Curt Block said.
   Asked if that were a record number of protests, Block said he
had no definite figures, ``but I would say that in all likelihood,
it is.''
   An additional 234 protesters called NBC in New York while the
show was on the air, 13 complaining about Clay's language and the
rest about him in general. Thirteen called to praise him, Block
said.
   Clay's appearance on the show, broadcast with a five-second
delay to allow bleeps, provoked both controversy and heavy advance
publicity. The broadcast was boycotted by cast member Nora Dunn and
guest singer Sinead O'Connor.
   Heavy security was arranged for the show, an NBC spokeswoman
said. Guards with metal detectors checked out guests entering both
the show's dress rehearsal and actual broadcast in NBC's studio 8-H
here.
   The only incident in the studio occurred during Clay's opening
monologue, when an unidentified couple began shouting ``Clay, Clay,
go away!'' They were quickly ejected, but not charged with
anything, NBC said.
   Fifteen to 20 protesters from a gay activist group, ACT UP,
demonstrated both in the lobby of NBC's studios in the G.E.
Building in Rockefeller Center, and outside the building. No
arrests were made, NBC said.
   Clay was paid what an NBC official estimated at $5,000 for his
work. During the program, Clay said he was donating that fee to the
``Comic Relief '90'' benefit that HBO televised live Saturday night
from Radio City Music Hall across the street.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0049 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 1725EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Floods 1stLd-Writethru a0691 05-13 0950</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Floods, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0691,0968</SECOND>
<HEAD>Evacuations In Texas &amp; Louisiana, Levee Work Continues In Arkansas</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Inserts one graf after the 11th, ``We don't,'' to update with
Texarkana area improving, and Inserts 3 grafs after the 16th, ``In
neighboring,'' with update on Lake Texoma. Bay in 9th graf is cq.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto staffing</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROGER PETTERSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Flooding forced more residents of low-lying areas to pack up and
leave Sunday in Texas and Louisiana, and county jail prisoners and
volunteers labored to reinforce levees with sandbags in Arkansas.
   A steady, heavy downpour compounded the flood threat in
Louisiana and flooded streets throughout the New Orleans area.
   Record flooding continued in Texas, where 7,000 people had been
urged to leave low communities along the Trinity River. The swollen
Red River continued to put pressure on levees in Arkansas and its
flood crest threatened communities downstream in Louisiana.
Oklahoma flood victims have begun cleaning up, except around gorged
Lake Texoma.
   The leading edge of the flood crest on the Trinity had reached
Lake Livingston, north of Houston. Liberty County officials said
Sunday that water was pouring over the reservoir's spillway at a
rate of 50,000 cubic feet of water per second, more than twice
normal.
   Liberty County Judge Dempsie Henley said officials expect the
flow to double by Tuesday. He issued an evacuation warning, urging
7,000 residents of communities downstream from the lake's dam to
pack up and leave. Many roads in the area were already under water.
   Downstream at the town of Liberty, northeast of Houston, John
Burch and his family frantically packed clothes and supplies
Sunday. They worked standing in water to avoid the many fire ants
driven to high ground by water.
   ``It hit us hard last year and it's going to be worse this
year,'' said Burch, 32. ``Last year, I lost my home and I've got my
trailer 3 feet higher than it was last year, but I expect to lose
it again.''
   Burch said his father's trailer is right on the bank of the
Trinity. He said his father, who doesn't want to leave until the
last minute, awoke to find water a foot deep around his home.
   ``It doesn't bother me,'' said Bay Burch, 70. ``If it gets to
where I get my feet wet, I'll leave,''
   But his 64-year-old wife, Violet Burch, said he was depressed
about losing their possessions. Last July, they lost a back bedroom
of their trailer to flood damage and had to replace walls, floors,
furniture and clothing.
   ``We don't have so much, and he don't want to lose it,'' she
said.
   Along the Texas-Oklahoma border, on the headwarters of the Red
River, only one highway in the Lake Texoma area remained closed
Sunday by record flooding that one week earlier had nearly cut
Marshall County off from the rest of the world. The lake, which had
dropped nearly 5 feet by Sunday, had crested about 27 feet above
normal and flooded homes and cabins and lakeshore recreation
facilities.
   In southwestern Arkansas, Miller County prisoners joined
volunteers and county personnel in sandbagging operations near the
Red River city of Garland.
   ``The levee had two major leaks Friday and Saturday but they've
been repaired and they are expected to hold,'' said Gary Talley of
the state Office of Emergency Services. ``The water is flowing
under the levee and bubbling up on the other side. They're trying
to stack sandbags to try to keep it contained but can't get
sandbags where they're needed because they can't get trucks in
there.''
   Officials asked that a borrowed Texas National Guard helicopter
be diverted from hauling feed to cattle stranded by high water so
it could be used to haul sandbags to Garland.
   The Red River at Garland was expected to rise a half-foot or
more because of heavy rain in the area Saturday, Talley said. If
the levee breaks, about 250 to 300 homes would be affected in the
town of 660, he said.
   In neighboring Hempstead County, dynamite experts cleared trees
in the river to enable a National Guard barge to help feed and
evacuate stranded cattle from islands of high ground along the
river.
   In nearby northeastern Texas, just north of Texarkana, emergency
authorities pronounced the danger from the Red River at bay Sunday
and said if no more rain falls in the coming days, the area will be
out of danger by Tuesday or Wednesday. The river had dropped 2 feet
since cresting Wednesday.
   But Texarkana Civil Defense spokesman Norman Greer said between
50 and 100 National Guardsmen continued Sunday to inspect the
levees, which were waterlogged and precariously soft.
   ``We're not letting anybody walk on them because the least
little thing can set them to rolling,'' Greer said.
   Downstream on the Red River in Louisiana, up to 600 square miles
of land is expected to flood this week and next, and up to a third
of that will be farmland, Sen. Bennett Johnston said Sunday.
   ``It will be a major agricultural disaster. It'll be a flood
event such as we have not experienced since 1945,'' the Louisiana
Democrat said after meeting with Army Corps of Engineers officials.
   The river will flood winter wheat fields ready for harvest, and
soybean fields will be too wet to plant until June at least,
Johnston said. Up to 500 homes and camps between the levees and the
river will be inundated, he said.
   The river hit flood stage _ 32 feet _ Saturday in Alexandria and
was expected to rise an additional 10 feet before cresting on May
21. Rising water had already forced several dozen people to leave
homes in surrounding Rapides Parish, said civil defense director
Bill Godron.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0050 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 1735EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-WeatherpageWeather     05-13 0298</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Weatherpage Weather,0306</SECOND>
<HEAD>Showers And Thunderstorms In East, Snow In Yellowstone</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Showers and thunderstorms spread over the eastern half of the
nation Sunday, thunderstorms spawned a tornado in Nebraska and snow
fell in the mountains of Wyoming.
   Showers and thunderstorms developed in the warm, moist air ahead
of a cold front from the central Gulf Coast to New England and the
lower Great Lakes region.
   Precipitation swept over the central Gulf Coast region, with
very heavy rain reported in some areas. Extensive street flooding
was reported in New Orleans. The city's Chalmette area reported
more then 7 inches of rain and Audubon Park reported more than 4
inches.
   Showers were scattered across the upper Ohio Valley, the lower
Great Lakes and the middle and northern Atlantic Coast states.
   Heavier rainfall totals for the six hours up to 2 p.m. EDT
included 3.60 inches at New Orleans; 1.58 inches at Pensacola,
Fla.; 1.25 inches at Milton, Fla.; and 1.16 inches at Buffalo, N.Y.
During the early morning, Mobile, Ala., got 2.75 inches of rain in
six hours and Milton, Fla., received 1.53 inches.
   Showers associated with a cold front in the north-central part
of the nation spread over Montana, Wyoming and the adjacent Plains.
   Snow fell at higher elevations near Yellowstone National Park in
northwestern Wyoming, with up to a foot of snow reported along the
Cooke City highway.
   Thunderstorms developed in the central Plains and one produced a
tornado near the western Nebraska town of Redington, the National
Weather Service reported.
   Elsewhere, showers associated with a storm system over Vancouver
Island spread over Washington state and a snow advisory was posted
overnight for the Cascade range of Oregon.
   Sunday's low for the Lower 48 states was 25 at Burns, Ore., and
Gunnison, Colo.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0051 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 1745EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Colombia     05-13 0646</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Colombia,0670</SECOND>
<HEAD>Car Bombs Exacted Worst Single-Day Terrorist Toll of Year</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By STAN YARBRO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOGOTA, Colombia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Colombia on Sunday struggled through a
Mother's Day shrouded by the grief of women who had lost children
in a wave of car bombings blamed on drug traffickers.
   Six children were among at least 27 people killed in three car
bombings Saturday. Two of the attacks came in the capital of Bogota
and the other in the southern city of Cali. Some 200 people were
wounded.
   The death toll was the highest this year for a single day of
terrorist attacks, police said. They blamed all three of Saturday's
bombings on drug traffickers.
   ``They were three almost identical attacks using car bombs
detonated by remote control,'' Gen. Octavio Vargas, the police's
chief of operations, said in an interview with the RCN radio
network.
   ``The attacks were prepared by the same organization of drug
terrorists'' accused in other bombings in recent months, he said.
   ``They targeted sites frequented by the civil population, which
has nothing to do with the drug trafficking problem,'' Vargas said.
   In August, the government announced an offensive against the
traffickers following the assassination of presidential candidate
Sen. Luis Carlos Galan.
   The drug cartels responded with an offensive of their own.
Police blame them for hundreds of bombings and other attacks that
have left nearly 300 people dead.
   Saturday's blasts caused thousands of dollars in damage and left
the nearby streets a labyrinth of twisted metal, rubble and bodies.
News accounts of the bombings were filled with descriptions of the
cries of the wounded and the shock of the victims' their loved ones.
   Bogota's El Espectador newspaper told of a 9-year-old girl,
Angela Gonzalez Delgado, who was helping her widowed mother sell
flowers near the site of one of the car bombs in northwestern
Bogota.
   ``They have destroyed my little baby,'' said Angela's mother,
Cecilia Delgado, as she clasped her head and stared at the sheet
covering the girl's body on the street.
   The girl was one of 17 people killed by the two Bogota bombings,
targeting commercial sectors of the working-class neighborhood of
Quirigua and the upper-middle-class enclave of Niza. The Health
Ministry earlier had said 19 people died in Bogota, but police on
Sunday corrected the total to 17.
   The cars, each packed with dynamite, exploded as people shopping
for Mother's Day filled the streets.
   Bogota's El Tiempo newspaper described how another mother,
Azucena de Varela, watched Red Cross workers pull the mutilated
body of her 10-year-old daughter, Carolina, from the rubble.
   ``Dear God, oh dear God, it can't be,'' the woman cried. ``She
was the only one I had and now she has been torn to pieces.''
   Hours after the Bogota explosions, a 200-pound car bomb went off
in Cali, Colombia's third-largest city with 1.5 million inhabitants.
   The explosion in a southern neighborhood in Cali, which came as
couples were flocking to its bars and discos, killed 10 people and
injured 60, police said.
   Vargas, the police chief of operations, also said gunmen working
for the drug chieftains have killed 11 police officers in the city
of Medellin since Wednesday, bringing to 80 the number of police
officers slain in the city this year.
   Police have said the Medellin cartel is paying more than $4,000
for every police officer killed. For members of a special
anti-terrorist unit, the bounty is $10,000, they said.
   Vargas said the Medellin cartel is apparently retaliating for
the police manhunt for its leader, Pablo Escobar, who is believed
to be hiding near Medellin.
   Authorities said they have seized more than 19 tons of cocaine
belonging to the cartel in the last 10 days, with a street value of
$1.35 billion.
   Cartels in Medellin and Cali are responsible for most of the
cocaine that enters the United States, the U.S. Drug Enforcement
Administration has said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0052 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 1741EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Poland-Walesa 1stLd-Writethru a0663 05-13 0748</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Poland-Walesa, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0663,0767</SECOND>
<HEAD>Solidarity Leader Throws Down Gauntlet</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: INSERTS 3 grafs after 6th graf pvs, `In a departure ...' to
UPDATE with Mazowiecki comment, edit for transition. Pickup 8th
graf pvs, `Specifically, Walesa...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By JOHN DANISZEWSKI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WARSAW, Poland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Solidarity leader Lech Walesa said Sunday
he was ready to do battle with former allies in the non-Communist
government, accusing them of being slow in carrying out economic
and political reforms.
   Addressing the national Citizens Committee, Solidarity's
political wing, Walessa said a fight was needed to stir up ideas so
the government does not become too isolated from the people.
   ``I know that I have offended a lot of people,'' Walesa said,
then added defiantly: ``I would like to offend even more.''
   He said he had refrained from directly challenging the
government led by Prime Minister Tadeusz Mazowiecki since it took
office last fall ``because I was convinced that everything would go
on all right.''
   ``Today I return from this leave, because I want to have a war
... A war that gives peace to the society at the bottom.''
   In a departure from the past, Mazowiecki did not attend the
Citizens Committee session _ sending a curt two-sentence note that
said he had promised instead to attend a Mass in Krakow.
   Later, at a meeting at a the Nowa Huta steel mill, Mazowiecki
said the drive for reform, including removal of former Communist
officials, must be part of a peaceful transition.
   ``We are aware of the existence of what one may call the hunger
for justice,'' he said. ``We know that people are unwilling to look
at those who are to blame. At the same time there exists a need for
security and calm.''
   Walesa has pitted himself against what he calls the ``eggheads
in Warsaw,'' saying they are not producing concrete results for
Poles, who expect radical changes from economic and political
reforms.
   Specifically, Walesa has criticized the government he helped
create last August for its slow pace at privatizing the
state-dominated economy and for retaining Communist holdovers in
economic and government jobs.
   Underlying the dispute are hints by Walesa, re-elected last
month as chairman of the 2 million-member trade union, that he
wants to be president of Poland to help accelerate changes.
   His former allies and advisers who now comprise the top echelons
of government have received the notion cooly, with suggestions
Walesa is too impulsive and lacks the cultured presence a president
needs.
   Instead, some Parliament deputies are pushing Mazowiecki as the
proper successor to President Wojciech Jaruzelski. The former
Communist leader's term lasts until 1995, but it is believed he
will step down before then.
   Walesa did not mention any presidential ambitions at the meeting
Sunday, but he made it clear he would not shirk from a fight.
   ``My theory is short: war at the top and peace at the bottom.
But if it is peace at the top, then there will be war at the
bottom,'' he told the assembly at Warsaw University's main
auditorium.
   He said the government had been treating democracy as ``a
steered process'' by telling Poles things were bad but there were
no alternatives and the helm was in ``the best hands.''
   ``The concept ... involves society too little. This means it is
not attractive for society,'' he said.
   Walesa said he preferred a more freewheeling style of democracy
in which individuals or groups could thrash out their differences
through open debate.
   ``I would like to encourage fighting, which means allowing into
the struggle all individuals who have something to say,'' he said.
``In my opinion this is what Poland needs.''
   Walesa told the audience he had been opposed in the past by the
most prominent members of the Solidarity movement _ Mazowiecki and
Solidarity parliamentary leader Bronislaw Geremek _ but had been
proved right.
   Walesa said it was he who persuaded Mazowiecki to become prime
minister and that Mazowiecki originally opposed the idea of a
Solidarity-led government. Walesa also said he begged Geremek ``on
my knees'' to become parliamentary leader.
   The government has implemented a dramatic reform plan intended
to create a market-oriented system out of Poland's failing
socialist economy. After rapid inflation, prices are stablizing but
real incomes have dropped an average of 40 percent by official
estimates.
   Polls have indicated that the popularity of Walesa and the
government have slipped. But they still have wide support and there
have been no significant suggestions of alternative leaders or
policies.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0053 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 1749EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BiasAttack 2ndLd-Writethru a0702 05-13 0393</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bias Attack, 2nd Ld - Writethru, a0702,0399</SECOND>
<HEAD>Three Men Mistaken for Korean Attacked In Tense New York City</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS final graf to restore dropped words in quote, ``and
blind.''</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By PHILIP I. ROSENBAUM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A gang of black men attacked three men who they
thought were Korean early Sunday, seriously injuring one, just
blocks from two Korean-American stores that are targets of a
black-led boycott, police said.
   Police said the injured man, Tuan Ana Cao, 36, said four black
males tried to rob him at a subway station, and that when he fled
they followed him to an apartment building.
   The victim, who is Vietnamese, told police someone on the street
hurled a bottle through a window. When he and two companions, also
Vietnamese, went outside to see what was going on, they found 10 to
15 black people.
   One of them told the Vietnamese, ``Get out of America!''
   He was struck with a baseball bat and was hospitalized in
serious condition.
   ``Some members of this group apparently mistook them to be
Koreans and made racial slurs,'' said police Sgt. Diane Kubler.
``They also cursed them.''
   A few blocks from the site of the incident, two Korean-American
grocery stores have been targets of a black boycott. The boycott
began when a black woman allegedly was assaulted in one of the
stores Jan. 18. She said store personnel had accosted her after she
refused to allow them to inspect her bag.
   Sabine Albert, a spokeswoman for one of the boycott organizers,
the Flatbush Frontline Collective, told reporters Saturday that the
boycott was not racially motivated.
   ``There are 13 Korean-owned stores operating within four blocks
of this vicinity and only two are being boycotted,'' she said. ``So
it's not a racial issue.''
   The boycotters have rejected mediation offers and have insisted
that they want the two grocery stores to close.
   Mayor David Dinkins, who had appealed for racial harmony and an
end to the boycott in a televised speech Friday, called an
impromptu news conference Sunday to discuss the attack.
   ``I didn't expect that I was going to make a speech on Friday
night and it was going to end,'' Dinkins said of the racial strife.
   But he added, ``An eye for an eye, a tooth for a tooth, will
leave us all toothless and blind.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0054 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 1845EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ChildrenAttacked     05-13 0366</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Children Attacked,0378</SECOND>
<HEAD>Baby Sitter Is Suspect in Killing of Boy and Assault on Girls</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Lenard is cq in 2nd graf</NOTE>
<DATELINE>LITCHFIELD, Ill. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A 37-year-old baby sitter stabbed an
11-year-old boy to death and sexually assaulted three girls aged 7,
11 and 13, then apparently turned the knife on himself, authorities
said Sunday.
   Lenard Johnson stabbed himself in the stomach and cut his wrist
and head, said Lt. David Andrews of the Montgomery County Sheriff's
Department. He was under police watch and in serious condition
Sunday at St. John's Hospital in Springfield, authorities said.
   The children were not all siblings, said Andrews.
   The boy was identified as Donald Lee Buske.
   The three girls were in satisfactory condition Sunday at St.
Francis Hospital in Litchfield, where they remained for
observation, said a nursing supervisor.
   The suspect is a partly blind man who lives two blocks from the
boy's home, where the attacks occurred early Saturday, said
Montgomery County State's Attorney Kathryn Dobrinic.
   Dobrinic said Sunday she had not determined what charges would
be filed, but she was certain they would include first-degree
murder.
   Early Saturday, police in Litchfield, a town of about 7,200
south of Springfield, received a call from St. Francis Hospital
that a 7-year-old girl had been brought in and was possibly the
victim of an assault, state police said.
   Litchfield police interviewed the girl at the hospital and then
went to the home of James and Susie Emerson, the parents of the
dead boy. There they found signs of forced entry and met Johnson,
authorities said.
   Johnson did not threaten police officers, said Andrews.
   Johnson had been baby sitting the four children at the Emerson
house.
   The State Journal-Register of Springfield reported the baby
sitter apparently beat and sexually assaulted the 7-year-old girl
before the Emersons returned home.
   When the parents arrived home, the baby sitter left and the
parents took the girl to the hospital, leaving the other three
children at the house, the newspaper said.
   Police had no explanation why the couple left the children alone
when they went to the hospital or why they didn't call police. They
apparently did not know the boy had been killed.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0055 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 1848EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BRF--PlaneFire     05-13 0165</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Plane Fire,0169</SECOND>
<HEAD>Plane Returns to Airport After Fire Caused by Muffins</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A USAir flight carrying 50 people returned to
the airport shortly after takeoff Sunday because of smoke from corn
muffins smoldering in the Boeing 727's kitchen, police said.
   The pilot of Flight 1402 bound for Pittsburgh notified air
traffic controllers at 7:47 a.m., 18 minutes after takeoff from
LaGuardia Airport, that there was a fire in the kitchen, said Port
Authority Police Sgt. Stephen Prospero.
   The pilot, who was not identified, was told to return to
LaGuardia, where emergency vehicles were awaited the landing 20
minutes later. As he landed, the pilot told controllers the fire
was out.
   The smoke apparently was caused by corn muffins that had been
left in the oven, said Port Authority Police Sgt. Dominick
Evangelista.
   After an emergency crew member inspected the area where the
muffins were, the plane taxied to the gate and passengers left
normally.
   The plane later left for Pittsburgh.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0056 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 1851EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Cannes-Film     05-13 0282</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Cannes-Film,0290</SECOND>
<HEAD>Parker Film on Japanese Internment Debuts at Cannes</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto CAN2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SUZY PATTERSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CANNES, France (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Director Alan Parker's testament to the
internment of Japanese-Americans during World War II, ``Come See
the Paradise,'' had its premiere Sunday to thunderous applause at
the 43rd Cannes Film Festival.
   The film, one of 19 competing for the coveted Golden Palm award,
marked a departure from violence for the British-born director,
whose previous works include ``Mississippi Burning'' and ``Midnight
Express.''
   ``I'm always being reproached for showing violence,'' Parker
told a news conference. ``But this is the way I understood it
happened. The Japanese weren't tortured, but crushed.''
   The 1,700 journalists at the screening heartily applauded the
20th Century Fox production as the credits rolled at the Festival
Palace.
   Parker researched, wrote and directed his film, inspired by the
plight of Japanese-Americans interned in camps during World War II
by a U.S. government fearing they might remain loyal to Tokyo.
   ``I think it will bring attention to the camps for people who
don't know anything about them,'' Parker said. ``I hope it will not
be as controversial a film as `Mississippi Burning.'''
   The film focuses on the love story between Dennis Quaid, who
plays an American married to Japanese-American portrayed by Tamlyn
Tomita.
   As Quaid goes off to war, she lives through the destruction of
her father's dignity, joining him in an intern camp before he
finally wanders off into the desert to die.
   ``This history was forgotten, swept under the carpet,'' Quaid
told the news conference. ``It wasn't taught in the high schools,
and it's important that everybody hear about it, because there's a
chance it could happen again.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0057 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 1843EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-MohawkViolence     05-13 0308</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mohawk Violence,0318</SECOND>
<HEAD>Four Arrests in Gambling Violence at Reservation</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ST. REGIS INDIAN RESERVATION, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Four Mohawk Indians
were arrested by Canadian police Sunday in an investigation of a
killing linked to a tribal dispute over gambling on the reservation.
   They were the first arrests in the killing, one of two stemming
from internal disputes on the reservation, which straddles the
U.S.-Canadian border.
   The four were taken into custody for questioning by Quebec
provincial police Sunday morning, and no charges were immediately
filed, said police spokesman Robert Poeti. They were taken to
police headquarters in Montreal, he said.
   The killings May 1 were blamed on factional disputes over
reservation casinos that cater to outsiders, and over who will run
the reservation. Some Mohawks reject outside jurisdiction on their
land, and U.S. state and Canadian provincial police have intervened
rarely in violence there.
   The warring factions have exchanged gunfire, especially at
barricades set up by anti-gambling forces to keep visitors away
from the casinos.
   The four men were questioned in the killing of Harold Edwards,
31, at one such barricade on the Canadian side of the reservation.
   An investigation continued into the shooting of Matthew Pyke,
22, who was killed in the same section of the reservation the same
day, the Canadian police spokesman said.
   Pyke was said to oppose gambling. Some on the reservation have
said Edwards favored gambling, but others dispute that.
   Since the killings, Canadian and New York state police have
sealed off the reservation with roadblocks, keeping non-residents
out and effectively closing the casinos, along with many of the
other businesses on Mohawk land.
   The reservation had been mostly peaceful since the police moved
in after the killings. The exception was a drug raid Thursday by
Canadian officials, who arrested 21 people and seized marijuana and
cocaine worth $800,000 in U.S. currency.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0058 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 1852EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-CincinnatiBell 1stLd-Writethru a0724 05-13 0425</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Cincinnati Bell, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0724,0434</SECOND>
<HEAD>3,000 Workers Strike Cincinnati Bell</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 9 grafs to UPDATE with company spokeswoman saying
Mother's Day calls unaffected. Pick up 9th graf pvs, `All I
know...' A version moved on business wires.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>CINCINNATI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   About 3,000 union workers for Cincinnati Bell
struck over health benefits early Sunday, leaving management
personnel to run operations.
   Talks between Locals 4400 and 4401 of the Communications Workers
of America and Cincinnati Bell broke off after a 14-hour session
Saturday. The union declared a strike at 12:40 a.m., said Mike
Timmerman, Local 4400 area vice president.
   ``We have at least two people picketing outside Bell garages and
some offices, but other than that we have no plans. As far as I
know, no bargaining session has been called,'' Timmerman said.
   Clerical workers, directory assistance operators, splicers,
linemen, installers and repair personnel are striking over health
benefits and a plan that would require workers to pay part of their
health premiums, Timmerman said.
   Though the walkout began on Mother's Day, one of the busiest
calling days of the year, it didn't affect long-distance calls to
Mom, said Bell spokeswoman Cyndi Cantoni. Cincinnati Bell isn't a
long-distance carrier, she noted.
   Dodie Ditmer, bargaining chairwoman for the CWA, said in a news
release that the union believes Cincinnati Bell came to the
bargaining table intending to cause a work stoppage.
   ``If Cincinnati Bell thought she could get health care
concessions from CWA as a Mother's Day present, she has dialed a
wrong number,'' Ditmer said.
   The union scheduled a meeting Sunday afternoon with members to
discuss the strike.
   Ms. Cantoni, the spokeswoman, said the company had agreed with
union bargainers not to discuss the issues keeping both sides apart
``so we can bargain in good faith.''
   ``All I know is that the union does characterize health benefits
as the main issue,'' she said.
   She said 1,000 management workers were called in early Sunday to
take over jobs left empty by the strikers. A total of 4,150 people
work for Cincinnati Bell.
   ``They will fill in, some of them putting in 12-hour shifts, for
the duration of the strike,'' she said. ``I don't think customers
will see a big difference in most services, but they can expect
slower response time from repair and installation.''
   The company serves more than 500,000 customers in the Cincinnati
area and portions of northern Kentucky and southeastern Indiana.
   Cincinnati Bell workers last struck in 1983, when management
employees replaced union workers during a two-week walkout.
Telephone calls weren't affected.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0059 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 1917EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-EastGermany-Executions     05-13 0351</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-East Germany-Executions,0363</SECOND>
<HEAD>Report: Political Prisoners Killed By Guillotine At Nazi Death
Site</HEAD>
<DATELINE>EAST BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Dozens of East German political prisoners may
have been killed by guillotine at a Nazi execution site between
1952 and 1960, the director of a crematorium in Dresden was quoted
Sunday as saying.
   The state East German news agency ADN said the director, Dietmar
Hildebrand, uncovered evidence of up to 62 executions.
   Hildebrand, who took over as head of the Tolkewitz crematorium
six months ago, said he got the information from records kept by
his predecessor.
   East Germany's authoritarian Communist government was toppled
last fall.
   The crematorium director's suspicions were aroused when records
that involved people who had supposedly died natural deaths also
contained documents from the state prosecutor's office, the report
said.
   ``With typical German efficiency, behind the name of each such
record, were the hand-printed letters `Po' in red ink, indicating
they were political prisoners,'' ADN said. The prisoners' cause of
death was usually listed as heart failure, Hildebrand said.
   Hildebrand sought out witnesses to the sentencing and
executions, the report said. He said doctors familiar with the
prisoners' fate told him the condemned were usually tied to a board
without a blindfold, placed under a guillotine and killed. They
were later cremated.
   The doctors were not identified in the report.
   The executions were carried out in the Georg Schumann building
of Dresden's Technical University, which was also used by the Nazis
for executions, the report said. It is now a memorial site to Nazi
victims.
   Hildebrand said he was going public with the information so
those involved in the executions could be brought to justice.
   After East Germany's hard-line government was overthrown,
relatives of some prisoners cremated at Tolkewitz asked about their
remains, ADN said.
   Other relatives whose property was seized by the state after
their family members were sentenced as political prisoners are now
seeking reparations, the news agency said.
   The list of names complied by Hildebrand starts with a man who
died on July 6, 1952, the agency said. It said the final listing
was Jan. 15, 1960.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0060 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 1956EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Philippines 2ndLd-Writethru a0687 05-13 0879</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Philippines, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0687,0904</SECOND>
<HEAD>Two U.S. Servicemen Killed on Eve of Base Talks</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserGraphic NY10, LaserPhoto MLA2</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Leads with 12 grafs to UPDATE with off-base leaves for all
U.S. troops canceled. Picks up 11th pvs, `Armed Filipino...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By EILEEN GUERRERO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MANILA, Philippines (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Suspected Communist rebels killed two
American servicemen near an air base Sunday on the eve of talks
between the United States and the Philippines on extending the
lease on U.S. military bases.
   A third American told reporters he managed to escape.
   The U.S. military canceled all off-post leaves for the 40,000
U.S. troops, Defense Department civilian employees and military
dependents in the Philippines following the attack.
   The assailants escaped, and there was no immediate claim of
responsibility.
   The area near the U.S.-run Clark Air Base has been a Communist
stronghold since the 1940s, and Sgt. Robert Abad of the national
police operations center for central Luzon said authorities
suspected Communist rebels.
   Abad said the Americans, who were wearing civilian clothes, were
slain about 8:30 p.m. (8:30 a.m. EDT) near a hotel a half mile from
the main gate at air base, 50 miles north of Manila.
   An Air Force spokesman, Maj. Wayne Crist, confirmed the killings
but gave no details. He refused to release the names or hometowns
pending notification of relatives.
   Philippine police identified the dead as Airman John Raven, 21,
and Airman James Green, 22. They were assigned to the 8th Aircraft
Generation Squadron on temporary duty here from Kunsan Air Base,
110 miles south of Seoul, South Korea.
   A third American, Airman 1st Class Randall Moore, 23, told
reporters he was haggling with a cab driver for a ride when he
heard shots behind him.
   ``I ducked and ran back toward the hotel,'' Moore said. He said
his unit arrived in the Philippines on May 3 for the annual Cope
Thunder military exercise, which ends Friday.
   Crist said the Air Force ordered all troops back to the base
after the killing. Those living off-base were restricted to
quarters, he said.
   Early Monday, the Navy announced on the military's Far East
Network that restrictions had been imposed at all six U.S. bases.
Navy Rear Admiral Roger Rich issued the order in his capacity as
representative of the U.S. Pacific Command.
   Armed Filipino troops were deployed around Clark after the
killings. It was the first attack on Americans at Clark since
October 1987, when three Americans and a Filipino civilian were
slain by rebels outside the base.
   Including the two men Sunday, eight Americans have died in
politically motivated slayings in the Phillipines since April 1989.
U.S. officials believe all the killings were carried out by
Communist rebels.
   An American officer, who refused to give his name, said the
airmen were waiting for a cab on Samson Street near Clark when two
or three Filipinos approached and shot them in the back of their
heads with .45-caliber pistols. The rebels often use such guns in
street attacks and fire at close range.
   Asked whether it appeared the attackers were rebels, the officer
replied: ``What do you think? Pistols, two or three assailants,
bases talks tomorrow?''
   U.S. and Philippine officials had expressed concern the
Communist rebel New People's Army would try to kill Americans
before the talks, which were to begin Monday on extending the lease
on Clark, the Subic Bay naval base and four smaller facilities. The
lease expires in September 1991.
   On My 4, suspected rebels killed American Marine Gunnery Sgt.
John Fredette near Subic, 50 miles west of Manila.
   U.S. officials barred off-post leaves for U.S. troops, Defense
Department civilians and military dependents following Fredette's
slaying but relaxed the ban a few days later.
   Troops were allowed to leave their garrisons but were required
to be on post and off the streets between midnight and 5:30 a.m.
   The delegations for the base talks will be led by Foreign
Secretary Raul Manglapus and former U.S. Assistant Secretary of
Defense Richard Armitage, who arrived Sunday from Japan.
   The talks are considered an ``exploratory'' phase, after which
the two sides will decide whether to enter formal negotiations.
   Opposition to the bases has been growing because many Filipinos
see them as an infringement on national sovereignty. Several groups
planned demonstrations to demand the bases be closed.
   Capital Command chief Brig. Gen. Marino Filart said he will
deploy at least 500 anti-riot police around the meeting site along
Manila Bay.
   President Corazon Aquino has refused to say whether she will
agree to extend the lease for the bases, among the largest outside
the United States.
   In a nationally televised statement Sunday, Mrs. Aquino again
gave no indication of whether she supports the bases. Nor did she
spell out what her government would demand as the price for
allowing them to stay.
   ``We are entering into these talks prepared to maintain our
friendly relations with the United States, keeping in mind that any
friendship must be based on respect for each other's rights and
adherence to principles,'' Mrs. Aquino said.
   A spokesman for the Philippine delegation, Rafael Alunan, said
the exploratory talks could take as little as a week.
   U.S. Ambassador Nicholas Platt told reporters last week that he
hoped a new agreement could be reached by the end of the year.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0061 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 2000EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-ProstitutionRing 3rdLd-Writethru a0728 05-13 0651</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Prostitution Ring, 3rd Ld - Writethru, a0728,0666</SECOND>
<HEAD>Police Uncover Intricate Male Prostitution Ring</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS grafs 8-9 to move up first reference to police spokesman
Stoner.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>FORT WAYNE, Ind. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Investigators have uncovered a 39-state
male prostitution ring they say was run by a Navy computer expert
that advertised via an electronic network and homosexual magazines.
   The ring was organized by James William Dayton, a computer
scientist at the Naval Avionics Center in Indianapolis who died of
a heart attack March 16, Marion County Prosecutor Steve Goldsmith
told The Journal-Gazette.
   At least 50 prostitutes and 300 patrons are involved, police
estimate. No arrests have been made.
   The ring's clients and prostitutes included Indianapolis banking
executives, a Cincinnati priest and a Marion County police officer,
the paper reported Sunday. The network drew clients and prostitutes
from 39 states, two Canadian provinces, South Korea and Guam,
investigators said.
   Goldsmith called it the largest prostitution ring he's seen,
adding, ``there are so many names. It's so voluminous.''
   An FBI agent who answered the phone in the agency's Indianapolis
office Sunday said the FBI has a policy against commenting on
whether it is involved in investigations.
   Police had suspected Dayton, 44, of being involved in illegal
sexual behavior as early as 1981 and had begun investigating an
alleged prostitution ring in 1985, but met with dead-ends.
   ``It was extremely difficult to infiltrate. ... It had built-in
barriers that prevented undercover officers from infiltrating the
system,'' said Indianapolis Police spokesman Andrew Stoner.
   It was Dayton's death that allowed the case to be cracked,
Stoner said.
   Dayton died in a Tiffin, Ohio, bed and breakfast after having
sex with a man who wanted to join the network as a prostitute,
police said.
   Jim Browning, the Seneca County sheriff's detective who
investigated Dayton's death, searched his car and found 140 pages
of computer-generated job applications for two gay escort services
that listed names, addresses, and phone numbers of men and photos
of nude and partially clothed men.
   Browning notified Indianapolis police, who obtained warrants to
search Dayton's Indianapolis apartment. There they found evidence
of an intricate, computerized system for matching male clients with
male prostitutes.
   Don Smith, a computer expert at Indiana University-Purdue
University at Indianapolis, helped police break the codes to get
access to that network.
   He determined that Dayton had used the computer sign-on Blue Boy
and was the owner-operator of two gay escort services, Muscles USA
and Muscles Midwest.
   Smith found that Dayton sent this message through a computer
network in April 1987: ``Muscles USA is a nationwide service based
in Indianapolis which provides well-built guys to
well-to-do-gentlemen. We are now hiring.'' The message promised at
least $75 an hour, more for body builders.
   Police learned that Muscles USA and Muscles Midwest advertised
in several homosexual men's magazines. The ads gave toll-free
numbers to call for information on gay escorts.
   Diana Hogue, director of public affairs for the Naval Avionics
Center, said there is no indication Dayton used computers at his
job for the prostitution ring or that anyone else at the center was
involved. The center produces advanced electronics systems for the
Naval Air Systems command. Dayton did not have access to classifed
data, she said.
   With Dayton dead, Goldsmith said investigators will target the
prostitutes. ``We're going to start with the most active ones and
we will ask the patrons to cooperate.''
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Editors: Investigators found addresses of men, apparently
clients of the ring, in 39 states, said Jim Browning, a Seneca
County, Ohio, sheriff's detective.
   The are Alabama, Arizona, Arkansas, California, Colorado,
Connecticut, Florida, Georgia, Hawaii, Idaho, Illinois, Indiana,
Iowa, Kansas, Kentucky, Louisiana, Maine, Maryland, Massachusetts,
Michigan, Missouri, Nebraska, New Hampshire, New Jersey, New York,
North Carolina, Ohio, Oklahoma, Pennsylvania, Rhode Island,
Tennesee, Texas, Utah, Vermont, Virginia, Washington, West
Virginia, Wisconsin and Wyoming. Also the District of Columbia,
Korea, Guam and the Canadian provinces of British Columbia and
Ontario.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0062 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 2015EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-AnimalRights     05-13 0397</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Animal Rights,0411</SECOND>
<HEAD>New Law Aimed at Animal Rights Extremists</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOPEKA, Kan. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Gov. Mike Hayden signed a bill aimed at
protecting farms, ranches and research operations from
animal-rights extremists, saying it was one of the first of its
kind in the nation.
   But the bill signed late Saturday has been criticized by at
least one humane organization that believes the legislation may
hinder their efforts to protect animals from cruelty.
   The Farm Animal and Research Facility Protection Act was in
response to militant actions around the nation by some activists,
including vandalism and thefts of animals from farms or ranches and
research operations.
   It threatens up to 10 years in prison and a $10,000 fine for
each violation by those who enter farms, ranches and research
operations and damage property, depending on the amount of damage.
   Hayden said Sunday that Kansas was one of the first states to
pass legislation dealing with damage caused by radical elements of
the animal rights movement.
   The bill was backed by a number of farm groups, including the
Kansas Farm Bureau.
   But an amendment to the act prohibiting individuals from
entering an animal operation to take pictures will hinder
investigations into cruelty to animals, said Wendell Maddox,
regional director for the Humane Society of the United States.
   ``It takes away our power and authority to do something about
cruelty problems,'' he said last week in Kansas City. ``It's more
than obvious their intention is to keep us out of `puppy mills.'''
   The so-called puppy mills, which raise puppies for sale, have
been criticized by animal-rights groups for substandard conditions.
   Maddox said the Farm Animal Act will make organizations such as
his more dependent on assistance from law enforcement agencies.
   ``Law enforcement historically doesn't consider animal abuse a
priority,'' he said. ``Unless we gather evidence, nothing gets
done.''
   Hayden said that before signing the bill he determined it did
not conflict with local humane societies' legal authority to deal
with animal abuse, including a law he signed two years ago aimed at
stopping ``the unethical puppy mills in Kansas.''
   ``I will continue to support efforts to close down these
disgraceful operations,'' the Republican governor said.
   The governor conceded that parts of the act may be considered
unconstitutional and may be challenged in court, but expressed
confidence a follow-up bill cleaning up the measure will pass the
legislature next year.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0063 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 2015EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Israel-Settlement     05-13 0540</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel-Settlement,0557</SECOND>
<HEAD>President Joins Jewish Settlers For Anniversary Celebration</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ARIEH O'SULLIVAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ELKANA, Occupied West Bank (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Chaim Herzog
attended a West Bank settlement celebration Sunday despite appeals
from Israeli left-wingers who said his presence would send a
``wrong message'' to the world.
   In other developments in the occupied lands Sunday, a Jewish
civilian critically wounded a 14-year-old Palestinian boy and
Palestinian uprising leaders issued a new leaflet calling for an
escalation of their struggle.
   Elkana, home to 3,000 settlers, was celebrating the 13th
anniversary of its founding. Settlement leaders called the event a
``bar mitzvah,'' referring to the ceremony marking a boy's 13th
birthday as the age of religious responsibility.
   About 100 protesters from the leftist Peace Now movement lined
one side of the street, singing peace songs and holding lighted
candles and signs reading ``Stop the settlement.''
   A group of settlers across the street jeered at the protesters.
Soldiers in battle gear separated the two groups.
   Tzali Reshef, a Peace Now leader, argued Herzog should not have
come at a time when Secretary of State James A. Baker III's efforts
to advance a dialogue between Israel and the Palestinians have
bogged down.
   ``At a time when Israel refuses to give a positive answer to
Secretary Baker, when it refuses to continue the peace process, it
wants to show the world that it continues with the settlements and
strengthening the existing settlements,'' Reshef said.
   ``This is exactly the wrong message from Israel. The president
should have sent a message of peace,'' he said.
   About 4,000 settlers, many carrying automatic weapons, gathered
at an auditorium decorated with blue-and-white Israeli flags.
   ``To my surprise, demands have been raised that I refrain from
visiting Elkana,'' Herzog told the settlers. ``I have made it clear
in the past that I planned to visit every place in the country to
which I am invited.''
   He said Israeli citizens were divided on the question of the
occupied territories, and it must be decided by a democratic
majority without political pressures.
   Shulamit Aloni, a left-wing legislator, said Herzog's visit may
serve to legitimize the settlements at a time of growing friction
between Israel and the United States over settlement drive in the
occupied territories.
   Israel's caretaker government, led by right-wing Prime Minister
Yitzhak Shamir, recently began construction of two settlements in
the West Bank and Gaza Strip. It also provided funds for a
settlement in the Christian quarter of Jerusalem's Old City.
   The United States has voiced concern about the settlements,
contending that settlements in the occupied lands are an obstacle
to peace in the Middle East. Some 70,000 settlers live amid 1.7
million Palestinians in the West Bank and Gaza Strip, areas
captured by Israel from Jordan and Egypt in the 1967 Middle East
war.
   In the West Bank town of Qalqiliya, an Israeli motorist opened
fire on stone-throwing Palestinian youths, critically wounding
14-year-old Sameeh Abu Sheikh, Israel television and Arab witnesses
reported.
   At least six Palestinians were wounded in clashes with soldiers
in Gaza, Arab hospital officials said.
   The PLO-linked, underground leaders of the 29-month uprising
issued a new leaflet calling for an escalation of their revolt by
using ``stones, Molotovs (firebombs) and anything your hands can
reach.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0064 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 2015EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Dollar-Yen     05-13 0031</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Dollar-Yen,0031</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dollar Opens Lower in Tokyo</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The dollar opened at 152.45 yen on the Tokyo
foreign exchange market Monday, down from Friday's close of 154.15
yen.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0065 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 2015EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-SammyDavis     05-13 0152</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Sammy Davis,0159</SECOND>
<HEAD>Davis Ill at Home; Condition Undisclosed</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BEVERLY HILLS, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Sammy Davis Jr. lay ill at his home
Sunday with terminal cancer.
   No information was released about the condition of the
64-year-old entertainer, who suffers from throat cancer.
   His publicist, Susan Reynolds, said there was nothing new to
report on his condition.
   ``We're not making any announcements. We want to give the family
as much privacy as possible,'' she said.
   Davis is terminally ill, his doctor, Irving Posalski, said
Saturday.
   ``Sammy is resting comfortably with his loved ones around him,
which is as he wants it,'' Posalski said.
   First diagnosed and treated for carcinoma of the throat in
September, Davis suffered a recurrence of the cancer and was
hospitalized for a time at Cedars-Sinai Medical Center.
   He was discharged on March 13 and sent home to be with his third
wife, Altovise. Friday was their 20th anniversary.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0066 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 2023EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Israel-Colombia     05-13 0474</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel-Colombia,0489</SECOND>
<HEAD>Official: Complaint to be Filed Against Colonel Over Antigua Camp</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GWEN ACKERMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A senior Defense Ministry official said Sunday
a police complaint would be filed against reserve Col. Yair Klein
for holding unauthorized talks on the establishment of a military
training camp in Antigua.
   However, the official, speaking on condition of anonymity, said
the complaint did not link Klein with Israeli weapons sent to
Antigua for use at the camp and later diverted to a Colombian drug
trafficker.
   Also Sunday, a Foreign Ministry spokesman said Israel regretted
Colombia's decision to suspend a 28-year-old agreement allowing
Israelis to enter the country without visas. The Colombian move
Friday was in protest of the weapons diversion.
   ``We believe the decision is not justified or helpful and we are
in contact with the Foreign Ministry of Colombia in order to verify
their position,'' said the spokesman, Motti Amihai.
   Israel radio said the complaint procedure against Klein would be
completed in several days, when the Defense Ministry submits
additional documents.
   Klein's attorney, Yigal Shapiro, said there was no clear legal
precedent in some areas covered by the complaint.
   ``We think that Klein did not need an authorization to conduct
the talks, but this will be clarified by the court,'' Shapiro said.
   Shapiro also said Antiguan investigators had promised Klein
immunity if he testified on the Caribbean island about the Israeli
arms diversion.
   ``The Antiguans decided that if he came to Antigua he would have
immunity but they haven't asked him to go yet,'' Shapiro said. ``If
they want Klein to come ... we will go.''
   The four-member Antiguan investigating team headed by the
nation's envoy to the United Nations, Patrick Lewis, questioned
Klein twice during a visit to Israel last week.
   Klein says he tried to set up a training camp equipped with
Israeli weapons on Antigua for Panamanian rebels opposed to the
rule of Gen. Manuel Noriega, who was ousted by U.S. forces in
December.
   The camp never went into operation, and at least some of the
weapons meant for it ended up in the hands of Gonzalo Rodriguez
Gacha, a drug trafficker killed by Colombian police in December.
   The New York Times had named Klein and Maurice Sarfati, an
Israeli owner of a produce business in Antigua, as responsible for
the arms diversion.
   Sarfati, who had acted as an envoy for the Antiguan government
in the deal, was not questioned by the Antiguan investigators.
Sarfati is believed to be in Switzerland.
   Israel's Foreign Ministry said Sunday that at the time of the
weapons sale they had no proof that Sarfati was an Israeli citizen
and are still doubtful.
   Colombian officials say Klein is wanted for organizing, training
and equipping paramilitary groups. He has been declared a fugitive
from justice and may be tried in absentia in Colombia.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0067 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 2035EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-ComicRelief     05-13 0143</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Comic Relief,0148</SECOND>
<HEAD>Comedy Show Prompts Viewers to Contribute to Homeless</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   It was a night for comedy, but the mission was
no laughing matter when the fourth Comic Relief special drew at
least $4.7 million in pledged donations for the homeless.
   Comedians Billy Crystal, Whoopi Goldberg and Robin Williams were
hosts of the event Saturday night, staged at Radio City Music Hall
and broadcast on cable television by HBO.
   They were joined by a parade of comedians, as well as the
high-kicking Rockettes.
   At one point, Williams and Crystal spoofed magicians Siegfried
and Roy. In a sketch mocking Britain's royal family, Miss Goldberg
portrayed Queen Elizabeth, who inexplicably transformed into Tina
Turner singing ``Proud Mary.''
   An early tally showed viewers had pledged $4.7 million for the
homeless. Show organizers were unavailable to provide a final count
Sunday night.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0068 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 2039EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-GoenczSpeech 1stLd-Writethru a0744 05-13 0612</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Goencz Speech, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0744,0627</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hungarian President Anticipates Heated Debate</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 6th graf to CORRECT that speech was given in English,
and official spoke to reporters through translator.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By BETH HARRIS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>INDIANAPOLIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Acrimonious political debate will be the
price of hard-won freedom in Eastern Europe, Hungary's interim
president told a commencement audience Sunday
   Hungary, like other nations emerging from under communism, must
forge ties with its neighbors while maintaining good relations with
the Soviet Union as well, author-turned-politician Arpad Goencz
said in his address at the Butler University graduation.
   Political debate in Hungary is framed by competition between the
center-right Hungarian Democratic Forum and the liberal League of
Free Democrats, Goencz's party.
   ``All that's happened in Hungary is absolutely and finally
irreversible,'' Goencz said. ``The strength of Hungarian democracy
will take place as the result of very harsh debate between
political parties.''
   Goencz, 68, was chosen Hungary's interim president May 2 in the
country's first free elections in at least four decades. He appears
likely to be elected to the largely ceremonial post of president by
Parliament in early June.
   ``We would like to introduce as soon as possible a free-market
economy, and we hope to become full-scale members of the European
Economic Community,'' he said, in a brief address. He delivered the
speech in English, and spoke to reporters afterward through a
translator.
   Goencz expressed concern for ethnic Hungarians elsewhere in
Eastern Europe, particularly in Romania. Hungarians were persecuted
under Romania's toppled Ceausescu regime, and are regarded with
suspicion as that country struggles to form a new political system.
   ``To guarantee collective and individual human rights for ethnic
minorities outside our borders, we have to maintain good
neighboring relations,'' he said. ``We believe in transparency of
borders so ethnic minorities outside Hungary can enjoy the
motherland.''
   Goencz, who was trained as a lawyer and entered politics after
World War II as a member of the then-dominant Smallholders' Party,
has written novels and short stories. He headed the Hungarian
Writers' Union since December.
   He will meet with President Bush and Congress before returning
to Hungary. He indicated economic aid for Hungary will dominate his
discussion with Bush.
   ``Democracy in Hungary will be very strong,'' he said. ``The
first thing we'll need is private investment capital to go into
Hungary, then we can make our own efforts to settle our own
things.''
   When asked to name a dollar figure for the amount of aid he
would seek from the United States, Goencz said, laughing, ``There's
an old Hungarian saying, `The upper limit is the sky to the stars,'
but of course we shall pay back all that we receive.''
   Maintaining neighborly relations with the Soviet Union is
another priority, Goencz said.
   ``We want to make a good connection to the Soviet Union,'' he
said, adding, ``I believe that success of the Hungarian democracy
will depend on its own and not on the fate of Mr. (Mikhail)
Gorbachev.''
   Goencz spent six years in prison on a life sentence for his role
in the 1956 Hungarian revolt. He was released in a 1963 general
amnesty.
   The idea that he would receive an honorary degree from an
American university was a source of delight to him.
   ``Really this whole event, that I stand here now, is so
improbable, that I cannot decide whether to drop a tear or to
cheer,'' he said in accepting his honorary doctorate of humane
letters. ``Quite likely, the proper behavior is to smile with
happiness.''
   Goencz was invited to speak at Butler's commencement by his
friend Dr. Janos Horvath, a former member of the Hungarian
Parliament and an economics professor at Butler.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0069 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 2046EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-RacialAttack 1stLd-Writethru a0716 05-13 0422</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Racial Attack, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0716,0432</SECOND>
<HEAD>Jury Deliberations Continue in Alleged Racial Attack</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 4 grafs to UPDATE with juries recessing for the
night without reaching verdicts. Pick up 4th graf pvs: `The boy...</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By RONALD POWERS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A pair of juries deliberated all day Sunday
without reaching verdicts for two white youths charged in the
killing of a black teen-ager, a case that has heightened racial
tension in the city.
   One jury considered the fate of Keith Mondello, who is accused
of organizing the group of attackers in the Bensonhurst
neighborhood of Brooklyn.
   A second panel deliberated the case of Joseph Fama, who is
accused of firing the pistol shot that killed Yusuf Hawkins, 16.
   Both juries recessed without reaching decisions, and were
scheduled to resume deliberations Monday.
   The boy was shot to death Aug. 23 when he and two friends
ventured into predominantly white Bensonhurst to look at a used car
and were attacked by a group of white youths armed with baseball
bats.
   The trial has set off several emotional demonstrations in a city
preoccupied with several other racial incidents.
   Mondello's lawyer, Stephen Murphy, needed police protection to
wade through the crowd outside the courthouse on Friday night. Two
days earlier, he was punched in the face while leaving the building
for lunch.
   Mondello, 19, was charged with two counts of second-degree
murder, manslaughter, and several other crimes.
   Fama, also 19, was charged with two counts of murder. His jury
was in its sixth day of deliberations.
   The men were tried jointly, but two juries were used because
Mondello identified Fama as the gunman in a statement to police.
   At one point, the Mondello jury sent a note to the judge asking
for a definition of discrimination charges and added, ``We would
also like to know if we could make Mother's Day calls.''
   ``You get your wish on both,'' replied State Supreme Court Judge
Thaddeus Owens.
   The Mondello jury was in its fifth full day of deliberations. On
Saturday, jurors sent a note to Owens saying they were unable to
reach a verdict on some of the charges. Owens ordered them to
continue deliberating.
   On Sunday, with the jurors out of the courtroom, the judge took
Mondello's attorney to task for suggesting the jury's note Saturday
suggested jurors believed his client innocent of murder.
   ``You know people are out there demonstrating,'' the judge told
Murphy. ``All you are doing is adding fuel to the fire with your
talk about acquittal.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0070 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 2105EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-WestGermany-Election     05-13 0506</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-West Germany-Election,0524</SECOND>
<HEAD>Kohl's Party Loses in State Election</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HANOVER, West Germany (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Chancellor Helmut Kohl's
conservative party lost Sunday to the left-leaning Social Democrats
in a state election in Lower Saxony, a setback that may complicate
his goal for quick unification with East Germany.
   Kohl's governing coalition is expected to lose its slim majority
in the upper house of Parliament, West German television reported,
citing nearly complete election returns.
   The upper house, or Bundesrat, acts only as a ratifying body for
laws passed by the Bundestag, or lower house, which is the main
lawmaking body.
   In the Lower Saxony elections, the Social Democrats received 44
percent of the vote to 41.2 percent for Kohl's Christian Democratic
Union, based on the unspecified percentage of returns, ARD and ZDF
television said.
   Official results were not expected until Monday, but incumbent
state Gov. Ernst Albrecht _ a member of Kohl's coalition _ conceded
defeat on behalf of the governing coalition and said he would
retire from politics. Kohl called the loss disappointing.
   Meanwhile, in neighboring North-Rhein Westphalia, incumbent Gov.
Johannes Rau, a Social Democrat, won re-election with 52.1 percent
of the vote, the returns indicated.
   Kohl's coalition _ which includes the Bavarian sister party
Christian Social Union and the centrist Free Democrats _ has only a
one-seat majority, 23-22, in the Bundesrat.
   Representation in the upper house, and its fluctuating number of
seats, is determined based on the political makeup of West
Germany's 11 state governments.
   With Lower Saxony now in the hands of the Social Democrats, the
left-leaning party is set to hold a 23-18 majority edge over the
conservatives and centrists.
   The projected loss of seats by Kohl's party could cause
complications for the chancellor's goal of the quick unification of
the Germanys.
   The defeat followed a loss for Kohl's coalition in January in
Saarland state, where Oskar Lafontaine was reelected governor with
more than 54 percent of the vote.
   Lafontaine is Kohl's top opponent in the national elections in
early December.
   Kohl has been pushing for quick monetary, economic and social
union of the Germanys by July 2.
   However, the Social Democrats have maintained the unification
process has not been properly thought out and could lead to
joblessness, weakening of the West German mark and inflation.
   Hans-Jochen Vogel, the Social Democrats' party chairman, said
Kohl was being repaid for ``negotiating over the heads of the
Germans'' in the unification process and not sufficiently taking
their concerns into consideration.
   Kohl acknowledged the defeat may have been generated in part by
``uncertainty of the costs'' of unification, and blamed the
leftists for fear campaign tactics.
   The state's winner, Social Democrat Gerhard Schroeder, was
quoted as saying he plans to talk with the environmentalist Greens
and the centrist Free Democratic Party about a coalition.
   Free Democrat national chairman Otto Lambsdorff said before the
two state elections that his party would not enter a coalition with
the Social Democrats.
   The Greens and the Free Democrats each received about 6 percent
of the vote, according to TV reports.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0071 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 2124EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-PurdyProm     05-13 0352</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Purdy Prom,0362</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dance at Purdy Prom Could Be Last</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PURDY, Mo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   High school students danced to rock 'n' roll
at this weekend's prom, but the school-sponsored event may have
been the last, because the U.S. Supreme Court has approved a
no-dancing rule.
   The school board in this small Ozark town is scheduled to meet
May 21, and could discuss its dancing ban, which the high court
upheld last month.
   On Saturday night, about 50 juniors and seniors at Purdy High
School and their dates, wearing tuxedoes and party dresses,
traveled to nearby Monett for the junior-senior prom. The theme was
``Hold Onto the Night.''
   It was the last of four dances held since a lower federal court
overturned the ban.
   The event at an enclosed park pavilion included a banquet and a
dance. After the prom some students enjoyed pizza and bowling at a
local bowling alley, said physical education teacher Becky Woods.
   The faculty was invited, and many school board members attended
with their spouses, said Woods, who attended.
   The dance had been scheduled before the Supreme Court ruling.
The board had promised students it wouldn't cancel their plans,
regardless of how the court ruled, Ransom Ellis III, attorney for
the school board, said Sunday.
   The ruling ended efforts by 21 students and parents who sued
four years ago to try to overturn the ban, which has divided
students and residents in this town of about 900 people.
   The ban on dancing at Purdy High, which has an enrollment of
about 230, paralleled the film ``Footloose.'' The movie centered on
a fight in a fictional small town between young people and city
fathers who thought dancing sinful and immoral.
   The Supreme Court rejected arguments that Purdy's ban was
religiously motivated and violated the separation of church and
state.
   Opponents say they hope the school board will voluntarily lift
the ban, but officials have declined to discuss the issue.
   School board President Glenn Garrett and member Alan Keeling,
reached at home Sunday, refused to comment. School Superintendent
Sheldon Buxton would not respond to repeated telephone calls
seeking comment.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0072 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 2127EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Britain-Tanker 1stLd-Writethru a0709 05-13 0325</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Britain-Tanker, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0709,0332</SECOND>
<HEAD>Coast Guard Combats Slick</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: New throughout to UPDATE with Sunday's cleanup. No pickup</NOTE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Five coast guard aircraft dropped detergent to
disperse an oil slick off England's southern coast Sunday after an
estimated 1,000 tons of oil spilled from a tanker that collided
with a British trawler.
   The Brixham coast guard said the slick was reduced to six miles
by three miles from eight miles by 10 miles and authorities
expressed hope the spill would not reach the shore.
   ``We are winning slowly,'' said Commander John Bywater of the
Department of Transport's Marine Pollution Control Unit.
   An estimated 1,000 tons of oil _ or about 294,000 gallons _
leaked from the Liberian-registered tanker Rosebay after it
collided with a British trawler on Saturday, 14 miles south of
Start Point, Devon. No injuries were reported.
   The Rosebay, which was bound from Kharg Island off Iran in the
Persian Gulf to the Swedish port of Brofjorden, remained anchored
about 20 miles offshore Sunday, awaiting repairs before moving on.
   The trawler, the Dionne Marie, arrived safely in the port of
Kingswear, near Dartmouth, Devon, late Saturday night.
   Dakota aircraft operated by the Department of Transport's Marine
Pollution Control Unit sprayed the oil with dispersal agents on
Saturday and Sunday. The planes were guided to the thickest
concentrations of oil by an aircraft using remote sensing equipment.
   Two ships were also on their way with booms and other equipment
ready to scoop oil from the water if needed, Bywater said.
   The British Petroleum Co. Ltd., which is not responsible for the
spillage, sent one of its coastal tankers to help clean up the
slick. A company spokeswoman said its tanker BP Warrior, with a
2,100-ton cargo capacity, would be used to store oil recovered from
the scene
   The department said the Rosebay's tanker's master was able to
halt the spillage by transferring oil from the ruptured tank to
another tank.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0073 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 2139EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-HongKong-Gold     05-13 0032</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Hong Kong-Gold,0030</SECOND>
<HEAD>Gold Opens Lower in Hong Kong</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HONG KONG (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Gold fell $1.65 an ounce on Hong Kong markets
Monday, opening at $368.25. It closed at $369.90 Saturday.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0074 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 2142EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-TireFire 1stLd-Writethru a0761 05-13 0186</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Tire Fire, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0761,0187</SECOND>
<HEAD>Half Million Old Tires Burn; 60 Homes Evacuated</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS lead to CORRECT typo in brought.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>LANCASTER, Ohio (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A fire consumed half a million old tires
and drove 60 families briefly from their homes before it was
brought under control Sunday.
   Investigators suspected arson in the blaze at a two-block
storage area that had been ordered cleared by the city, said Fire
Chief Wilbur Welch.
   Nobody was injured in the fire, which burned for more than 15
hours before being controlled about 5 p.m., Welch said. It burned
at least 500,000 tires, he said.
   About 60 homes in a nearby neighborhood were evacuated for fear
the thick, black smoke from the fire contained dangerous hydrogen
cyanide, he said. Residents were allowed to return after state
environmental officials determined the smoke didn't pose a danger.
   The company that owns the tires recently filed for protection
from creditors under Chapter 7 of the federal bankruptcy code after
the city threatened to make it pay to remove the tires.
   Two buildings, one of which houses a retreading business, were
undamaged.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0075 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 2153EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Dubinin 1stLd-Writethru a0756 05-13 0413</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Dubinin, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0756,410</SECOND>
<HEAD>Soviet Ambassador Describes a World `Changing Rapidly as Never
Before'</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: Inserts grafs 4-5 to note that Dubinin leaving to become
Soviet ambassador to France</NOTE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Soviet Ambassador Yuri Dubinin told George
Washington University students Sunday the class of 1990 is entering
``a unique world, which is changing rapidly as never before.''
   ``Perhaps a Soviet ambassador has more reason to say that since
in my country, a week _ and sometimes a day _ brings changes which
otherwise would have taken years,'' Dubinin said at commencement
ceremonies for the university's Elliott School of International
Affairs.
   But he said the rapid rate of change is also ``true of
international relations in Europe and worldwide.''
   The speech was Dubinin's last scheduled formal public appearance
in Washington before his departure to become the Soviet Union's
ambassador to France.
   Dubinin, who has headed the Soviet embassy here since 1986, is
being succeeded by Aleksandr A. Bessmertnhkh, currently the Soviet
Union's first deputy foreign minister and a veteran expert on U.S.
affairs. U.S. officials have said Bessmertnykh, who served in
Washington from 1970 to 1983, is considered especially close to
Soviet Foreign Minister Eduard A. Shevardnadze.
   ``Perhaps for the first time, mankind now has a chance to rid
itself of the ideological, political and military confrontation
among states in order to address the problems which call for joint
efforts,'' said Dubinin.
   Turning to U.S.-Soviet relations in particular, Dubinin said,
``they have become a proving ground for innovative approaches to
world affairs.
   ``Over the years our best political minds thought of ways to
deceive or defeat the enemy. Now we are learning to think about
each other not as adversaries, but as partners. Indeed, at the
Malta summit, President (Mikhail) Gorbachev said that the Soviet
Union no longer regarded the United States as its enemy.
   ```A new closeness' is how President Bush described our
relationship.
   ``Never has there been a more productive period of
Soviet-American interaction as in recent years,'' he continued.
``We have come to trust each other enough to reveal our military
bases and hardware. We have started to destroy the most
sophisticated nuclear weapons, turning disarmament from a utopia
into reality.
   ``I am sure that the summit between President Gorbachev and
President Bush coming up in just two weeks on American soil will
become a major step in the process of bringing our two nations
closer together and will prove to be an outstanding event of
international life.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0076 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 2152EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Australia-Crocodile     05-13 0140</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Australia-Crocodile,0146</SECOND>
<HEAD>Man Eaten By Crocodile</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DARWIN, Australia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A 10-foot-long crocodile attacked and
ate a 43-year-old man on an island off the north coast of
Australia, police said Monday.
   The man's remains were found Sunday floating in the ocean off
Groote Eylandt, about 360 miles east of Darwin. Police said the
attack occurred late Friday or early Saturday about 800 yards away
from where the body was found.
   Police said the area is known for its large crocodile population.
   Police spokesman Constable Brett Jenkins said searchers had
located the crocodile believed responsible for the attack and shot
it.
   The contents of the crocodile's stomach were sent to Darwin for
further investigation, Jenkins said.
   The dead man was identified as Albert Juzeliunas, 43, a worker
for Telecom, the Australian government communications company.
   No further details were immediately available.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0077 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 2153EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Obit-Bufalino     05-13 0271</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Bufalino,0277</SECOND>
<HEAD>William Bufalino Sr., Lawyer Who Defended Teamsters, Hoffa</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DETROIT (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   William E. Bufalino Sr., a longtime attorney for
the Teamsters Union and its vanished ex-president, Jimmy Hoffa, has
died of heart failure. He was 72.
   Bufalino, who died Saturday at Holy Cross Hospital in Fort
Lauderdale, Fla., maintained homes here and in Pompano Beach, Fla.
He had retired from private practice in 1982.
   Bufalino represented Hoffa, the Teamsters or both in seven
trials and won five of them. The attorney ended his lengthy
relationship with Hoffa in 1971, four years before the labor leader
disappeared outside a suburban Detroit restaurant.
   Bufalino said he never knew what happened to Hoffa, whose body
never was found. He theorized that Hoffa was silenced because he
knew about a CIA-sponsored plot to have the Mafia kill Cuban leader
Fidel Castro in exchange for control of gambling in Havana.
   Bufalino himself served 21 years as president of Teamsters Local
985. He testified before two Senate committees that investigated
links between labor and organized crime in the 1950s.
   Bufalino insisted he never defended any member of the Mafia. He
backed up that assertion by suing then-Attorney General Robert
Kennedy and Sen. John McClellan, D-Ark., saying they damaged his
reputation by placing him with other committee witnesses.
   He also sued the Grosse Pointe Homeowners Association and real
estate agents in 1959 after learning he was prevented from buying a
home under a system of rating the ethnic makeup of would-be home
buyers. Although Bufalino lost the suit, revelation of the
exclusive suburb's so-called point system led to adoption of the
Michigan Fair Housing Act.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0078 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 2156EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-France-Desecration     05-13 0405</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-France-Desecration,0419</SECOND>
<HEAD>Thousands Mourn Desecration; Clashes Between Jews, Skinheads</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Israel-Desecration</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CARPENTRAS, France (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   About 10,000 gathered people solemnly
gathered Sunday to protest the desecration of a Jewish cemetery,
while militant Jews clashed with skinhead extremists in Paris.
   Grand Rabbi of France Joseph Sitruk led prayers at the cemetery
in Carpentras, where 34 Jewish graves were vandalized last week.
The corpse of a recently buried 81-year-old man was impaled on an
umbrella.
   ``From now on, there will always be before and after
Carpentras,'' Sitruk told the crowd that included four government
ministers. ``This day will stay a historic date for our country.''
   Sitruk asked pardon for the desecrators and called on France to
``remember that a democracy doesn't exist by the grandeur of its
principles but by the obsessive quest for the truth.''
   The demonstration came hours after reports that vandals
desecrated 300 Jewish graves in Haifa, Israel with spray-painted
slogans calling on Arabs to ``kill the Jews.''
   Residents of this southern French town, site of a Jewish
community for 2,000 years, observed 15 minutes of silence during
the ceremony. Shops closed their shutters and motorists stopped
their cars.
   Similar ceremonies were held in Marseille, Lyon, Lille and
Drancy, the World War II deportation center where the Nazis packed
Jews on rail cars for transport to Auschwitz.
   At noon, the bells of the Roman Catholic cathedral rang out in
mourning. The synagogue opened for a special service dedicated to
those whose graves were violated.
   Interior Minister Pierre Joxe called on French citizens to
remember the founding principles of their republic.
   ``We will act in all areas to protect France and all those who
live here,'' said Joxe, who has accused far-right politician
Jean-Marie Le Pen of indirect responsibility for the desecration by
creating an atmosphere of racial hatred.
   Le Pen favors expelling France's 3.4 million Moslem immigrants
and once termed the Nazi Holocaust ``a detail'' of history.
   Four members of Le Pen's National Front party attended the
ceremony at the invitation of Jewish leaders.
   Anti-racist groups, trade unions and political parties plan
another rally Monday in Paris.
   Police sent out an appeal for witnesses to assist their
investigation of the Carpentras desecration. Five skinheads were
held for questioning in the crime Friday and Saturday, but all were
released.
   Skinheads in France generally sympathize with neo-Nazi or
neo-royalist groups and generally have shaved heads or
closed-croped hair and wear bomber jackets and steel-toed boots.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0079 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 2218EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-HospitalPicket     05-13 0313</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Hospital Picket,0324</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hoping for Miracle, Husband Begs to Keep Dead Wife on Life Support</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TULSA, Okla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A man begging for time for a miracle to
revive his brain-dead wife picketed Sunday outside a hospital where
doctors prepared to disconnect the woman from a respirator.
   For about 45 minutes Sunday, Bill McFall walked outside St. John
Medical Center with a sign reading, ``Execution, May 9th, 1990.''
   The date apparently referred to the original deadline he
believes doctors set for turning off the machine that circulates
the blood of his wife of 33 years.
   The woman's doctor planned to disconnect her from the respirator
at 9 a.m. Monday, said hospital spokesman Steven Reynolds.
   ``Give God some time,'' asked McFall, who said he was hoping for
a miracle. ``That's all I want.''
   Hospital officials say Isabell McFall, 56, died April 24 of an
aneurysm, or burst blood vessel in her brain. She had been
unconscious since April 17.
   Doctors said she met Oklahoma's criteria to be declared legally
dead: No electrical or chemical activity was detectable in her
brain.
   ``Our policy's based on medical decisions and on state law,''
said hospital spokesman Reynolds. ``This is the first time we've
had anybody protest, or ask that we maintain a relative on support
system past the time of the death.''
   Reynolds said the only reason she was kept on life-support
machines after April 24 was compassion for the family after McFall
requested a day's time to adjust.
   Hospital officials contend Oklahoma statutes don't require them
to obtain McFall's consent to disconnect the machine, though
Reynolds said doctors would like the family's approval.
   McFall said he would never consent. At midweek, he began calling
reporters to try to get help for his fight against the hospital.
   ``The doctors are living by sight. We're living by faith,'' he
said. ``The days of miracles are not over.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0080 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 2227EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-NIreland-Prison     05-13 0253</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-NIreland-Prison,0262</SECOND>
<HEAD>Fighting in Belfast Jail</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BELFAST, Northern Ireland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Protestant prisoners rioted
Sunday in a Belfast jail to demand segregation from Roman Catholic
inmates following the beating of two Protestants by Catholics, a
British official said.
   Protestants then seized control of dining halls in two wings of
Crumlin Road jail and six of them briefly climbed onto the roof,
shouting abuse and throwing tiles at guards, the official of
Britain's Northern Ireland office said.
   By early Monday, about 35 Protestant prisoners remained in
control of a dining hall, said the official on condition of
anonymity.
   A source at the jail said five others had surrendered to the
guards.
   The British official said no staff had been injured.
   Ourside the jail, which holds more than 300 prisoners awaiting
court proceedings, police blocked off Crumlin Road while prison
staff tried to negotiate an end to the disturbance, the Northern
Ireland office said.
   Many of the prisoners are linked to the outlawed Irish Republcan
Army, which is overwhelmingly Catholic, or to outlawed Protestant
paramilitary groups who want to remain under the British flag.
   Both sides have long made demands for segregation, which the
Northern Ireland Office rejects because it fears the prisoners
would effectively run the jail.
   During the campaign, a number of jail staff have been injured in
the prison and the cars and homes of staff have been attacked,
sometimes with gasoline bombs.
   The IRA is fighting to drive the British from the province and
unite it with the Irish Republic.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0081 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 2228EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Romania     05-13 0229</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania,0236</SECOND>
<HEAD>Opposition Party Rallies in Bucharest</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto BUC4</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BUCHAREST, Romania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   About 4,000 people rallied Sunday in
support of opposition presidential candidate Ion Ratiu a week
before the first free elections in half a century.
   Ratiu's National Peasants' Party is the chief rival of the
National Salvation Front, which has dominated the government since
the December revolution that toppled Communist leader Nicolae
Ceausescu.
   The crowd at the rally occasionally broke into shouts of
``Greater Romania,'' an apparent reference to their desire to
incorporate Soviet Moldavia into Romania.
   Also Sunday, several hundred anti-government demonstrators
continued a round-the-clock rally that began in Bucharest's
University Square in mid-April.
   Interim President Ion Iliescu _ whom the demonstrators accuse of
seeking to reimpose totalitarian rule _ said Saturday that he
expected the square to be ``cleaned out'' by the end of the
electoral campaign Thursday. He did not specify what measures the
government might take.
   Iliescu and his National Salvation Front are favored in the May
20 elections. Ratiu, however, told the crowd at the rally that he
and his party will prevail.
   ``If you want to get back to Moscow, then vote Iliescu,'' Ratiu
said, alluding to Iliescu's past as a member of the Communist
Party. Iliescu fell from grace after opposing Ceausescu.
   The other main challenger to the Front is the National Liberal
Party and its candidate, Radu Campeanu.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0082 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 2242EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Congressman-Scientist     05-13 0548</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Congressman-Scientist,0569</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ohio Congressman Urging Exiled German Rocket Scientist to Return</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HUNTSVILLE, Ala. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An Ohio congressman said he's urging a
retired NASA rocket scientist accused of brutalizing Nazi prisoners
during World War II to return to this country from Germany in
defiance of a Justice Department order.
   Rep. James Traficant said 84-year-old Arthur Rudolph's return
would force the Justice Department's Nazi-hunting Office of Special
Investigations to prove the scientist mistreated slave laborers at
a Nazi rocket factory.
   ``They may put him in jail, they may put me in jail for helping
him, but that's what I intend to do,'' the maverick Ohio Democrat
said Saturday at a dinner attended by about 140 supporters and
former colleagues of Rudolph.
   The $20-a-plate event was held to raise money for a possible
legal fight by Rudolph, who surrendered his American citizenship
and left the United States in 1984 under an agreement with the U.S.
government.
   Rudolph, who lives in Hamburg, West Germany, has yet to say
whether he will return.
   Office of Special Investigations Director Neal Sher said last
year that he would fight any attempt by Rudolph to return for a
court hearing.
   This northern Alabama city is home to the National Aeronautics
and Space Flight Center's Marshall Space Flight Center, where
Rudolph and other scientists who worked on Nazi rocket weapons
developed rockets that put Americans on the moon.
   Sher has described Rudolph, who said he belonged to the Nazi
party, as a self-confessed war criminal. But Traficant claims an
Army investigation absolved Rudolph of war crimes in 1947.
   The congressman said Saturday that he is not defending Nazi war
criminals and should not be considered anti-Semitic.
   ``If I thought Arthur Rudolph was a Nazi war criminal, I could
pull the switch ... myself, but that's not what he is,'' he said.
   Traficant has defended John Demjanjuk, a retired Cleveland auto
worker on death row after being convicted of Nazi atrocities. The
congressman has sharply criticized the Office of Special
Investigations for trying to discredit some witnesses in the
Demjanjuk case.
   Traficant on Saturday accused a ``powerful Jewish lobby'' of
trying to intimidate elected officials who might otherwise agree
with his claim the case against Rudolph lacks merit.
   ``The Jewish groups that support the OSI should consider that if
we let this government violate the rights of an old Nazi who is not
a criminal, they could just as easily violate the rights of Jewish
Americans,'' he said.
   Stuart Lewengrub, Southeast director of the Anti-Defamation
League in Atlanta, criticized the congressman.
   ``The manner in which Congressman Traficant addresses the issue
blaming `the Jewish lobby' belies his own denial of
anti-Semitism,'' Lewengrub said in a telephone interview from his
home Saturday night.
   Lewengrub said the case against Rudolph was overwhelming, and
said his attack on ``the Jewish lobby'' was ``as insidious as his
defense of proven Nazi war criminals.''
   Lewengrub said many of those petitioning for Rudolph's return
probably aren't motivated by anti-Semitism.
   Rudolph arrived in Huntsville after World War II with the
Wernher von Braun rocket team. They built missiles for the Army and
then for NASA. Rudolph became manager of the Saturn V rocket
program that first sent astronauts to the moon in 1969.
   Most of the scientists, including Rudolph, retired in the late
1960s.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0083 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 2246EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Nepal     05-13 0264</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Nepal,0276</SECOND>
<HEAD>King Agrees To Revamp Constitutional Comission</HEAD>
<DATELINE>KATMANDU, Nepal (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   King Birendra agreed Sunday to reconsider
the makeup of a constitutional commission he had appointed without
consulting the government, sparking an outcry.
   A high-ranking government official said Sunday that police fired
on a group of students in Baglung, 118 miles northwest of the
capital, killing one and injuring two.
   The students were protesting the transfer of a police officer
who they said was involved in the repression of the pro-democracy
movement earlier this year, the official said.
   On April 6, police fired into a crowd of pro-democracy activists
marching to the palace, and witnesses said at least 200 people were
killed.
   Popular pressure then forced King Birendra to lift a 29-year-old
ban on political parties, dismiss a rubber-stamp government and
disband a partyless system of government known as the Panchayat.
   The king had come under sharp criticism from members of the
interim government for appointing a seven-member constitutional
commission without consulting the government. That was seen as an
attempt on the monarch's part to head off limits on his sweeping
powers under the constitution.
   The king formed the commission Friday, saying it would rewrite
the document to institutionalize a constitutional monarchy and a
multi-party system.
   Prime Minister Krishna Prasa Bhattarai, one of the leaders of
the democracy movement, said he was shocked by the king's failure
to consult the government about the appointments.
   However, the king reportedly assured the prime minister that any
draft of the constitution would be sent to the Cabinet for
revisions.
   Bhattarai's government took office April 19.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0084 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 2254EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-IntegratedProm     05-13 0364</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Integrated Prom,0375</SECOND>
<HEAD>First Integrated Prom Gets High High Marks from Students</HEAD>
<DATELINE>FORT VALLEY, Ga. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Nearly 20 years after Peach County High
School was integrated, black and white students got together
Saturday night for their first integrated prom.
   Many of the 200 students who attended the dance said the change
was long overdue.
   ``Somebody is going to come along every time and break some
tradition that's really stupid, some tradition you don't really
think about because you've always done it,'' said Hope Bickley, a
white 17-year-old. ``I'm glad it was our class that broke it.''
   Ms. Bickley and Ato Crumbly, a black student, are friends who
have known each other since elementary school and march together in
the school band. But although Crumbly said blacks and whites ``get
along fairly well'' at school, they'd never had an integrated prom.
   ``We go to school together, play football together, run track
together, so why can't we socialize together,'' Crumbly said
Saturday at the formal dance in the school gym.
   ``I go out of town a lot in the summer, to Las Vegas and
California,'' he added ``I'd tell (friends) about the prom and
they'd say `What?' And they'd ask, `Do y'all still have to drink
out of separate fountains?''
   All school dances and parties were canceled by the Peach County
school board in the early 1960s when a student apparently was
injured during a prom. Board members also said planning the dances
took time away from schoolwork.
   Without a school-sponsored prom, parents began organizing their
own _ one for blacks, one for whites.
   But three years ago, Peach County's parent-teacher group, the
Better Schools Association, tried to change the board's policy. The
board promptly rejected their request for an integrated prom.
   Last year, the board changed its position, and Saturday's prom
was held without incident.
   ``This prom,'' Crumbly said, ``will be a good experience.''
   Susan Jordan, president of the parent-teacher organization, said
the students set an example for their community.
   ``A child shall lead them,'' she said, quoting the Bible.
``Well, in this case, a group of children shall perhaps lead the
community, and won't that be great? And isn't it about time?''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0085 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 2320EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Philippines-US 3rdLd-Writethru   05-13 0870</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Philippines-US, 3rd Ld-Writethru,a0745,0897</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.S. Official Condemns Killings As Talks on Bases Open</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserGraphic NY10, LaserPhoto MLA2</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 9 grafs to UPDATE with U.S. official condemning
attack, talks opening on base leases; Air Force confirming names.
Picks up 9th graf pvs, `A third...'; minor editing to conform and
trim</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By EILEEN GUERRERO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MANILA, Philippines (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Suspected Communist rebels killed two
American servicemen near an air base Sunday, the day before the
United States and the Philippines opened talks on extending the
lease on U.S. military bases.
   As U.S. and Philippine negotiators gathered Monday at the
heavily guarded Central Bank, the chief U.S. delegate condemned the
slayings.
   ``This brutal and clumsy attempt to drive a wedge between the
United States and the Philippines will fail,'' chief U.S.
negotiator Richard Armitage said before the talks began.
   Armitage, a former assistant defense secretary, blasted the
``lawlessness and banditry'' of the insurgents blamed by
authorities for the killings. The area near the U.S.-run Clark Air
Base has been a Communist stronghold since the 1940s.
   Sgt. Robert Abad of the national police operations center for
central Luzon said the Americans, who were wearing civilian
clothes, were slain Sunday evening near a hotel a half mile from
the air base, 50 miles north of Manila.
   The U.S. military canceled all off-post leaves for the 40,000
U.S. troops, Defense Department civilian employees and military
dependents in the Philippines following the slayings.
   The assailants escaped, and there was no immediate claim of
responsibility.
   The dead servicemen were identified by the Air Force as Airman
John H. Raven and Airman James C. Green. They were assigned to the
8th Aircraft Generation Squadron on temporary duty here from Kunsan
Air Base, 110 miles south of Seoul, South Korea.
   Their hometowns and ages were not immediately released by the
Air Force, but Philippine police said earlier that Raven was 21 and
Green 22.
   A third American, Airman 1st Class Randall Moore, 23, told
reporters he was haggling with a cab driver for a ride when he
heard shots behind him.
   ``I ducked and ran back toward the hotel,'' Moore said. He said
his unit arrived in the Philippines on May 3 for the annual Cope
Thunder military exercise, which ends Friday.
   An Air Force spokesman, Maj. Wayne Crist, said the Air Force
ordered all troops back to the base after the killing. Those living
off-base were restricted to quarters, he said.
   Early Monday, the Navy announced on the military's Far East
Network that restrictions had been imposed at all six U.S. bases.
Navy Rear Admiral Roger Rich issued the order in his capacity as
representative of the U.S. Pacific Command.
   Armed Filipino troops were deployed around Clark after the
killings. It was the first attack on Americans at Clark since
October 1987, when three Americans and a Filipino civilian were
slain by rebels outside the base.
   Including the two men Sunday, eight Americans have died in
politically motivated slayings in the Phillipines since April 1989.
U.S. officials believe all the killings were carried out by
Communist rebels.
   An American officer, who refused to give his name, said the
airmen were waiting for a cab on Samson Street near Clark when two
or three Filipinos approached and shot them in the back of their
heads with .45-caliber pistols. The rebels often use such guns in
street attacks and fire at close range.
   Asked whether it appeared the attackers were rebels, the officer
replied: ``What do you think? Pistols, two or three assailants,
bases talks tomorrow?''
   U.S. and Philippine officials had expressed concern the
Communist rebel New People's Army would try to kill Americans
before the talks, which were to begin Monday on extending the lease
on Clark, the Subic Bay naval base and four smaller facilities. The
lease expires in September 1991.
   On My 4, suspected rebels killed American Marine Gunnery Sgt.
John Fredette near Subic, 50 miles west of Manila.
   U.S. officials barred off-post leaves for U.S. troops, Defense
Department civilians and military dependents following Fredette's
slaying but relaxed the ban a few days later.
   Troops were allowed to leave their garrisons but were required
to be on post and off the streets between midnight and 5:30 a.m.
   The delegations for the base talks were led by Foreign Secretary
Raul Manglapus and Armitage, who arrived Sunday from Japan.
   The talks are considered an ``exploratory'' phase, after which
the two sides will decide whether to enter formal negotiations.
   Opposition to the bases has been growing because many Filipinos
see them as an infringement on national sovereignty. Several groups
planned demonstrations to demand the bases be closed.
   President Corazon Aquino has refused to say whether she will
agree to extend the lease for the bases, among the largest outside
the United States.
   In a nationally televised statement Sunday, Mrs. Aquino again
gave no indication of whether she supports the bases. Nor did she
spell out what her government would demand as the price for
allowing them to stay.
   ``We are entering into these talks prepared to maintain our
friendly relations with the United States, keeping in mind that any
friendship must be based on respect for each other's rights and
adherence to principles,'' Mrs. Aquino said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0086 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 2322EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a BC-LOT--LotteryState-by-State 1stLd-Writethty-two seventy-seven
05-13 0207</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-LOT--Lottery State-by-State, 1st Ld-Writethru-1st Add,196</SECOND>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<HEAD>NORTHERN NEW ENGLAND</HEAD>
<HEAD>Tri-State Megabucks-Winner</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CONCORD, N.H. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Tri-State Megabucks officials say one lucky
person is holding a ticket worth $3.5 million.
   Spokesman Dave Long said the winning ticket was purchased at a
Shop-N-Save in Saco, Maine. He said the winner will receive annual
payments of $173,000 for 20 years.
   People who matched three, four and five numbers won a total of
$491,000 in the New Hampshire, Maine and Vermont game.
   The winning numbers were: 3, 7, 14, 19, 25, 30.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>CONCORD, N.H. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the daily New Hampshire, Vermont and Maine lotteries:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 3</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   0-9-3
   (zero, nine, three)

</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   1-1-6-2
   (one, one, six, two)
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Tri-State Megabucks</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CONCORD, N.H. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers in the
``Tri-State Megabucks'' game for New Hampshire, Vermont and Maine:
   3-7-14-19-25-30
   (three, seven, fourteen, nineteen, twenty-five, thirty)
</TEXT>
<HEAD>PENNSYLVANIA</HEAD>
<TEXT>
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Number</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   7-2-0
   (seven, two, zero)
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Big 4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   1-2-6-9
   (one, two, six, nine)
</TEXT>
<HEAD>RHODE ISLAND</HEAD>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CRANSTON, R.I. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers in the Rhode Island
daily lottery drawing for Sunday were:
   9-8-5-8
   (nine, eight, five, eight)
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0087 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 2018EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>d f PM-BusinessHighlights     05-13 0792</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Business Highlights,0829</SECOND>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A record drop in vegetable costs contributed
to a second straight decline in wholesale prices last month, the
government said.
   The Labor Department said Friday its Producer Price Index for
finished goods fell a seasonally adjusted 0.3 percent last month,
the sharpest decline since August and the third consecutive
moderate report.
   For the first four months of the year, inflation at the
wholesale level was running at a 4.2 percent annual rate, down from
4.8 percent for all of 1989.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Stock prices rocketed to near record-heights as
favorable inflation news and falling interest rates drew investors
to Wall Street.
   The Dow Jones average of 30 blue-chip industrial stocks finished
up 63.07 at 2,801.58 on Friday, short of the record high close of
2,810.15 reached on Jan. 2. It was the biggest one-day advance for
the Dow average this year.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Another big drop in auto demand contributed to
a 0.6 percent decline in retail sales in April, the biggest setback
in six months.
   The Commerce Department said Friday that sales fell to a
seasonally adjusted $148.64 billion last month after a 0.2 percent
decline in March.
   Private economists warned that the lackluster sales likely would
translate into slower economic growth in the months ahead as
businesses face growing inventories of unsold products.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>HOT SPRINGS, Va. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Leaders of top U.S. businesses said the
economy will grow only moderately this year and next but will
manage to stave off a recession.
   Inflation is on the way down, they said Friday, predicting that
the first-quarter annual inflation rate of 8.1 percent will be cut
nearly in half.
   Economic growth will total about 2 percent in 1990 as it
accelerates gradually from 1.9 percent in the first half of the
year to 2.3 percent in the second, according to the Business
Council, 100 chief executives of the nation's largest corporations.
Growth will rise to 2.6 percent in 1991.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Amax Inc., the nation's third-largest coal
producer, has offered $1.25 billion to acquire industry leader
Peabody Holding Co., raising the possibility of a bidding war with
a major Peabody investor.
   The bid on Friday was rejected immediately by Hanson Industries,
which owns 45 percent of Peabody and is attempting to buy the rest.
Hanson responded by raising its offer for the Peabody shares it
doesn't own.
   The remaining 55 percent of St. Louis-based Peabody is owned by
Newmont Mining Corp. of Denver. Hanson, in turn, owns 49 percent of
Newmont.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>DETROIT (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Stroh Brewery Co. wants to buy Heileman Brewing
Co. and form a new No. 3 beer maker, Stroh senior vice president
and chief legal officer George Kuehn says.
   But Heileman President Murray Cutbush replied Friday that he was
skeptical about joining with a company ``that has an absence of
strong senior management, an uncertain direction ... and an eroding
distributor network.''
   Stroh President Roger Fridholm told a business strategists'
group on Wednesday that Stroh still wanted to buy Heileman,
according to a story in The Detroit News that Kuehn confirmed
Friday.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>NORWALK, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Great Northern Nekoosa Corp. Chairman
William R. Laidig, who failed in his effort to thwart
Georgia-Pacific Corp.'s takeover, has resigned.
   Great Northern said Friday it anticipates Laidig's successor
will be Ronald P. Hogan, who is vice chairman of Great Northern and
president and chief operating officer of Georgia-Pacific, which
expects to complete its $65.75-a-share merger next month.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>ATLANTIC CITY, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Donald Trump said his Trump Castle
Casino Resort By The Bay is not for sale despite comments from the
chairman of Hilton Hotels that he is looking into buying the gaming
hall.
   Trump said Friday Trump Castel is ``not for sale at any price.''
He refused to say if Hilton Chairman Barron Hilton had approached
him about selling the casino. Hilton said after the company's
stockholders meeting Thursday that he might be interested in buying
the casino.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A former executive of United Technologies
Corp. was sentenced to six months in prison and fined $5,000 for
conspiring to obtain inside information about Pentagon competition
for a lucrative Navy contract.
   Roger K. Engel, 49, who was vice president of the company's
Norden Systems division in Norwalk, Conn., was sentenced Friday by
U.S. District Judge Claude M. Hilton in Alexandria, Va.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Bond prices staged a huge rally in response to evidence of
moderation in the economy and inflation.
   The dollar fell sharply against the Japanese yen but finished
higher against most other major currencies.
   Grain, soybean and precious metals futures prices closed mostly
lower; livestock prices were mostly higher; pork was mixed and
energy prices fell.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0088 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 1458EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-Wal-Mart-Dakotas     05-13 0709</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Wal-Mart-Dakotas,0735</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dakotans Brace for Wal-Mart's Arrival</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RODD AUBREY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BISMARCK, N.D. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Wal-Mart is coming to the Dakotas. And
like a famous gunfighter of the Old West, the giant discount chain
is drawing respect and fear from its new neighbors.
   The Bentonville, Ark., chain, which owns 1,500 stores in 29
states, plans to open at least a dozen in North and South Dakota
this year.
   Wal-Mart officials won't say where the stores will be located.
However, the company has started construction or filed plans to
build stores in Bismarck, Dickinson, Fargo, Grand Forks, Minot and
Williston in North Dakota, and in Aberdeen, Brookings, Sioux Falls,
Spearfish, Watertown and Yankton in South Dakota.
   ``You can't ignore them,'' says Doug Nelson, who owns a small
women's clothing store in Williston. ``We're taking steps to live
with them until they're no longer the new kids on the block.''
   Nelson will be joining other small businesses in the two states
trying to disarm the consumer attraction to a national powerhouse
with discount prices.
   Some merchants are following the advice of Steve Torok, an
assistant professor of agri-business at the University of Wyoming.
Torok gives lectures to communities preparing for Wal-Mart's
arrival.
   To survive, family-owned businesses need to tout their customer
service _ longer hours, flexible return policies and a friendly
smile, he says.
   Wal-Mart ``won't be able to know people on a first-name basis
and small businesses can,'' Torok says. ``It's free to do and it
really, really will pay off.''
   A smile may not be enough. An Iowa State University study shows
that after four years in a town Williston's size, Wal-Mart takes
$8.3 million from local businesses.
   The same study shows, however, that the store is more likely to
attract shoppers from a wider area _ bringing a new batch of
spendthrifts who didn't come before.
   Richard Stone, an economics professor who conducted the study,
has given lectures in five South Dakota towns awaiting Wal-Marts.
He says the biggest fears are based on rumors.
   ``It's worse here, because they really don't know what the
store's about,'' Stone says. ``It's fear of the unknown more than
anything else.''
   Gary Blythe, executive vice president of the Aberdeen Area
Chamber of Commerce, says business owners have different opinions
about the Wal-Mart moving into town, depending on what kind of
store they own.
   ``Overall, the business community...I think they are excited
about this development,'' he says. ``But at the same time, there is
some concern.''
   Just ask Marc Feinstein, who owns a women's clothing store in
downtown Aberdeen.
   ``I guess it's a free market, they have every right to be here,
but I don't think the governing bodies understand what's
happening,'' he says. ``I really question whether some of the
people interested in some of this growth realize if it's really
growth or just replacement.''
   The business that Wal-Mart will take business away from local
retailers, hurting the Aberdeen economy and benefitting Wal-Mart
headquarters in Arkansas, Feinstein says. He also claims Wal-Mart
has a competitive edge because some of the local taxes it will pay
will be earmarked for parking and improvements that can benefit the
store.
   Wal-Mart counters that it brings about 235 jobs to an
average-sized store, circulating payroll dollars into the community.
   ``There are many paybacks to having a Wal-Mart in a community,''
says public relations coordinator Jane Arend. Aside from hiring
area residents, the store gives scholarships and donates to
charities.
   Some residents are concerned about what Wal-Mart will do to
their neighborhoods. People in Minot asked last week for a fence
between their neighborhood and the store, to improve scenery and to
prevent shoppers from tromping through yards to get to Wal-Mart.
   Williston business people remain optimistic, however. They see
Wal-Mart as a boon for the economy and a chance to attract more
people.
   ``We're just so ready for something new and exciting to
happen,'' says Nikki Roberts, a shoe store manager. ``Things have
been on the down side for so long, this is a big plus for us. It's
drawing more people into town. They can't spend all their hours in
Wal-Mart.
   Adds Nelson: ``Living through the drought has been more
devastating to our community than any new Wal-Mart or supermarket
will be.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0089 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 1905EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-Exxon-KickbackClaims 1stLd-Writethru   05-13 0597</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Exxon-Kickback Claims, 1st Ld - Writethru,f0023,0615</SECOND>
<HEAD>Report Says Manager Claims He Was Fired Over Kickbacks for Charter
Contracts</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 8 grafs to CORRECT that Alexander said he was
fired for saying some employees took gifts but did not say he did
so; picks up 9th graf pvs, `In Anchorage ...'</NOTE>
<DATELINE>SEATTLE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A former Exxon Corp. manager says company
officials received gifts and trips in exchange for awarding
lucrative charter-boat contracts last year as part of the cleanup
of the catastrophic oil spill in Alaska.
   The manager, Bill Alexander, says he believes he was fired for
telling company officials during an internal probe that some
employees had received gifts and favors, the Seattle Times reported
Sunday. He did not acknowledge having done so himself.
   ``I owned up,'' said Alexander, 42, of Baton Rouge, La. ``I
cooperated fully with the investigation. I told them what I knew
and maybe others didn't.''
   Officials of New York-based Exxon denied Alexander's allegations
of widespread kickbacks, the newspaper reported.
   Alexander, a 15-year Exxon employee, was made marine-contract
administrator at Valdez, Alaska, three days after the Exxon Valdez
ran aground in Prince William Sound in March 1989, spilling 11
million gallons of crude oil.
   The practice of trading charter contracts for favors was
widespread and ``pretty flagrant'' during the disorganized early
days of the cleanup, Alexander said.
   ``A lot of people were getting a lot of stuff. There were trips
_ hunting and fishing. Merchandise was passed out,'' he said. Rules
were tightened and the practice tapered off later, he said.
   Alexander said he gave internal investigators the names of
people involved. He said that he did not accept any merchandise
himself but would not say whether he had accepted anything else,
the Times reported.
   In Anchorage, Exxon spokeswoman Jan Cool refused to confirm
whether Alexander had been fired, saying personnel records are
confidential. But she said if anyone was found to have taken gifts
in violation of company policy, appropriate action would be taken.
   `One would hope our people wouldn't take advantage of another
person's desperation to get a job,'' she said.
   Alexander was suspended April 3 from his job in Valdez and fired
April 10, the Seattle Times said.
   On April 25, Exxon sent a letter to its contractors and
suppliers saying company ethics policies would be enforced strictly
and asserting Exxon's right to audit their records, the Times
reported.
   The letter noted employees could not accept offers or gifts ``in
excess of a nominal value'' or offers of boating, fishing or
hunting activities.
   Jim Lewis, an internal auditor for Exxon in Anchorage, said the
timing of the letter was a coincidence.
   He said the internal probe stemmed from a much broader audit of
``how our overall business was being conducted'' in Valdez.
   He said he looked into contracting procedures and Alexander's
relationship with suppliers.
   Lewis refused to say whether Alexander or others received favors
from boat owners but said he submitted a report of his
investigation of Alexander to Gus Elmer, president of Exxon
Shipping Co., last month.
   Elmer could not be reached for comment and Exxon officials in
Houston declined comment, the Times reported. Calls made by The
Associated Press Sunday to Exxon Shipping and to Exxon's corporate
headquarters went unanswered.
   Lewis said he did not know whether Exxon planned further action.
   ``I do know our lawyers have been consulted on this,'' Lewis
said.
   After the spill, Exxon chartered hundreds of vessels, ranging
from small local fishing boats at $1,000 or more a day to a
350-foot factory ship, chartered for $480,000 a month.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900513-0090 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-13-90 1910EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-Exxon-KickbackClaims Advisory   05-13 0047</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Exxon-Kickback Claims, Advisory,0049</SECOND>
<TEXT>
   Eds: Please note f0026, a 1st Ld - Writethru to
AM-Exxon-Kickback Claims, makes an important change in the
original. The Exxon employee who says he was fired did not admit
having received any gifts or favors from boat owners.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>AP Business News</BYLINE>
</DOC>
</Collection>
