<Collection>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0001 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 2340EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-TrappedToddlers     01-07 0168</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Trapped Toddlers,0171</SECOND>
<HEAD>Young Brothers Trapped in Pickup With Dead Father for Hours</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MAUD, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two toddlers spent 12 hours trapped in a
wrecked pickup truck with their dead father after the truck slid
off a rural road and slammed into a tree.
   A Bowie County sheriff's deputy discovered the boys, 4-year-old
Joshua Mills and his 3-year-old brother, Nathan, early Saturday
trying to awaken their father, James Mills, 25.
   ``They were tapping him on the shoulder, telling him, `Daddy,
wake up,''' Jones said. ``I just told them, `Your father's asleep.
Let him sleep.'''
   The truck apparently crashed Friday night during rain and heavy
fog in Maud, about 140 miles northeast of Dallas, and was found at
the bottom of an embankment near a sharp curve in a road, Jone said.
   The boys were treated and released from Wadley Regional Medical
Center.
   Nathan was treated for cuts and bruises. Joshua, who was pinned
in the jump seat of Mills' small pickup, suffered minor frostbite,
officials said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0002 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 2345EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-CultDeaths 4thLd-Writethru a0709 01-07 0830</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Cult Deaths, 4th Ld-Writethru, a0709,0849</SECOND>
<HEAD>Federal Agents Arrest Cult Leader, Seize Weapons</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 14th graf with 3 to UPDATE with search of storage shed
turning up more weapons and hearing set Monday. Picks up 16th graf
pvs, `Investigators said...'</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto GO1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVID SEDENO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NATIONAL CITY, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Federal agents Sunday arrested a
religious cult leader wanted in the slayings of a family of five
and seized numerous weapons, including an AR-15 assault rifle,
authorities said.
   Jeffrey Lundgren, 39, a former Sunday school teacher and tour
guide in the Reorganized Church of Jesus Christ of Latter Day
Saints in Ohio, was arrested outside a motel by agents of the
federal Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco and Firearms and members of the
San Diego Sheriff's Department.
   Also arrested were his wife, Alice Lundgren, and their
19-year-old son, Damon. Three other Lundgren children _ Kristen,
10, Caleb, 9, and Jason, 15 _ were taken into protective custody,
said Andrew Vita, special agent in charge of the ATF office in Los
Angeles.
   Police had the motel in this blue-collar town near the Mexican
border under surveillance since Saturday night, said George
Rodriguez, a special agent for the ATF in Kansas City.
   ``We wanted to make sure they didn't get to Mexico,'' Rodriguez
said.
   Authorities were led to the motel by telephone calls made from a
pay phone to another location they had under surveillance, said
Steven C. LaTourette, a Lake County, Ohio, prosecutor who held a
news conference in Painesville, Ohio, earlier Sunday.
   Officials said Lundgren broke away from the Reorganized Church
and persuaded other members to follow him. The group once lived on
a 15-acre farm near Kirtland, Ohio, where investigators last week
unearthed five bodies, which authorities believe to be those of
Dennis Avery, his wife, Cheryl, and their three children.
   In a statement issued in Washington, ATF officials said
investigators had been searching for Lundgren and the others since
Thursday and made the arrests without incident.
   More than 20 ATF agents and sheriff's deputies participated in
the arrests at the Santa Fe Motel, located on a busy intersection
in National City, which is about 10 miles south of San Diego.
   Motel Manager Steve Liu said Mrs. Lundgren checked in Wednesday
night with the three children, paying cash for the room for six
nights.
   Mrs. Lundgren told Liu she was checking into the motel because
she had argued with her husband.
   ``She said she had wanted to stay in a hotel for a couple of
days so maybe things would cool off,'' Liu said. ``I saw him
(Lundgren) coming back and forth during the last few days and I
thought maybe they were making up.''
   Vita said agents raided the motel room Sunday morning and seized
the AR-15, three handguns, an assortment of hunting knives and
camping and survival gear
   Authorities also searched a storage locker that Lundgren had
rented near the motel. Three more handguns and some smokeless
powder used for reloading ammunition was found, Vita said.
   The Lundgrens apparently were trying to make contact with
relatives they could leave the children with, police said.
   The Lundgrens were being held in the San Diego County Jail
pending extradition to Ohio, where they face charges including
aggravated murder, complicity to murder and kidnapping. They were
to appear in court Monday for a hearing.
   Investigators said the Averys were shot and killed in mid-April
and buried in a common grave in the barn near Kirtland, one day
before Lundgren and his followers left Ohio for a farm near Holden,
Mo.
   Lundgren and 12 of his followers were indicted by a Lake County
grand jury in the killings.
   In addition to being shot, the victims' eyes were covered with
duct tape and some had their hands and feet bound with the tape.
   Dale Luffman, president of the northeast Ohio chapter of the
Reorganized Church of Jesus Christ of Latter Day Saints, said he
did not believe the slayings were part of a sacrifice, but probably
resulted from a dispute over money, sex or fear the family would
leave the cult.
   LaTourette said Friday the Avery family apparently was killed in
a sacrifice necessary under a prophecy of Lundgren's before the
cult could relocate to the wilderness.
   Lundgren worked with the church's historic temple in Kirtland,
established in 1836 by Joseph Smith, founder of the Mormon Church.
Lundgren was a guide in the temple, giving tours to visitors
starting in 1985 when he moved to Kirtland, about 30 miles east of
Cleveland, from Independence, Mo., where the church is based.
   He was stripped of his credentials as a lay minister with the
church in 1987 after he began preaching radical doctrines during
church tours. He and others who followed him left the church and
eventually settled on the farm near Kirtland.
   Though it has roots and some beliefs in common with the Mormon
Church, the Reorganized Church of Jesus Christ of Latter Day Saints
is a separate church.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0003 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 2357EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Suburbs:CrisisofGrowthI-1stAdd     01-07 0535</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Suburbs: Crisis of Growth I - 1st Add,0540</SECOND>
<HEAD>UNDATED: business centers.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Logan himself lives about four miles from his Perimeter Center
office in a four-bedroom house on a half acre in the quiet
community of Sandy Springs. When asked about his commute, he can
barely contain his smugness.
   ``Ten minutes each way, unless there's traffic,'' he allows.
``Then maybe 15. I never have to get on the freeway.''
   Three thousand miles away, sociologist Mark Gottdiener stands on
a desert hill, looking down at what he calls ``The Beast'': Moreno
Valley, Calif., one of the nation's fastest growing communities.
   This is the suburban frontier, 70 miles east of L.A. ``Ten years
ago,'' he says, ``there was nothing down there but rattlesnakes,
coyotes and sagebrush.'' Today, there are 105,000 people. About
1,000 new ones move in a month, and four or five schools open each
year.
   But the principles on which Moreno Valley was developed are
well-established: leapfrog beyond the urban fringe, where land is
cheaper, and build 1,000 houses rather than 10. ``That was the
lesson of Levittown,'' says Gottdiener. ``You can go anywhere and
produce an instant city. You can plunk it in the middle of
nowhere.''
   What you get is the ultimate commuters' community, since there
are few good jobs in Moreno Valley itself. But those who can afford
less than $160,000 for a home are drawn here, despite the long
commutes to jobs in Los Angeles or Orange County.
   When Bill Hampson, pastor of a local church, asks people why
they don't go to church on Sunday, ``the most common answer is
commuting,'' he says. ``A lot of people drive 100 miles a day, and
the weekend is literally their only free time.''
   Baby sitters advertise ``commuter hours'' from 4 a.m. until 7
p.m., and there are brisk sales in commuter paraphernalia such as
books on tape and dashboard coffee mugs.
   Someday, however, Moreno Valley will have its own factories and
office buildings, and already some people are complaining that it
is becoming too congested. Already, ``For Sale'' signs are posted
on farmland in the towns further east, past the San Andreas fault.
   For all their differences, suburbs like Perimeter Center and
Moreno Valley share one striking trait: an isolation from _ and
frequently an antagonism toward _ their central cities.
   For the first time, a generation of suburban Americans lacks an
emotional tie to the city, a feel for its lifestyle, and an
interest or stake in helping solve its vast problems.
   Levittown, for instance, began as an appendage of New York City.
Most of its residents came from there, had relatives there, and
worked there. But today most Levittowners work on Long Island and
spend almost all their time there. To them, the city means
congestion and, above all, danger; despite an increase in suburban
crime, someone in New York City is about eight times more likely to
be a robbery victim than someone on Long Island.
   ``The young people now don't really care about the city, or even
go there very often,'' says Claire Worthing, who used to drive into
the city on weekends for shows at the Apollo Theater in Harlem.
``They just go to the malls.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0004 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 0121EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Panama     01-07 0524</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama,0540</SECOND>
<HEAD>New U.S. Ambassador Calls For Enduring Friendship With Panama</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Deane is cq</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By MARIA VICTORIA GONZALEZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Deane Hinton took over as the new
U.S. ambassador to Panama Saturday and pledged American cooperation
when Panamanians take full operational control of the Panama Canal.
   Also Saturday, former U.S. Attorney General Ramsey Clark said
the death toll from U.S. invasion of Panama is higher than has been
reported. Clark estimated at least 4,000 had died, and called the
reported toll ``an official conspiracy of silence.''
   U.S., Panamanian and hospital sources say at least 500 civilians
are believed to have died in the operation to oust Gen. Manuel
Antonio Noriega and bring him to the United States for trial on
drug trafficking charges.
   Clark, who is gathering information about human rights
violations, did not say how he arrived at his figure of 4,000, nor
did he give any other details.
   ``There is a strong motive for not counting the dead. Humanity
should pay attention to this point,'' Clark said at a news
conference. He did not elaborate.
   Hinton, in an arrival statement, said: ``Let us not look back to
a troubled past but rather let us responsibly face the future.
Together let Panamanians and Americans build our relations on a
basis of mutual respect and enduring friendship.''
   ``Let me stress that Panamanians and Americans must henceforth
cooperate to prepare for the day less than 10 years away for
(Panamanian) operation of the Panama Canal,'' Hinton said.
   Treaties signed by then-President Jimmy Carter and Panamanian
Gen. Omar Torrijos in 1977 gave full ownership to Panama of the
waterway, which the United States built and inaugurated in 1913.
   The agreement put control of its operation under a joint
U.S.-Panamanian commission until the year 2000, when it reverts
completely to Panama.
   Noriega has claimed the United States sought his ouster in order
to renege on the treaties.
   But the Bush administration repeatedly insisted it did not want
to retain control of the waterway, only to get Noriega to stand
trial in the United States for drug trafficking and money
laundering.
   The Ecumenical Committee of Panama said in a statement Saturday
that the U.S. government should repair the damage caused by the
assault.
   It asked that ``the United States accept its responsibility to
repair the damage from the invasion.''
   The appointment of Hinton, an experienced career diplomat, was
seen as another effort by the Bush administration to reconstruct
the extensive damage caused by the fighting between U.S. troops and
soldiers loyal to Noriega and six years of harsh Noriega rule.
   Hinton, 67, a former ambassador to El Salvador and Pakistan,
replaces Arthur Davis.
   He pledged to do all he could to help new President Guillermo
Endara and his government ``fulfill the aspirations of the
Panamanian people for equitable social and economic development and
for the benefits of participatory democracy, respect for human
rights and the rule of law.''
   Panama, he said, ``has a philosophical commitment to the free
enterprise system. And it has demonstrated a firm commitment to the
establishment of democratic institutions and the carrying out of
democratic principles.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0005 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 0121EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ChineseStudents     01-07 0373</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Chinese Students,0384</SECOND>
<HEAD>Chinese Students Meet to Map Strategy Against Bush Veto</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CAMBRIDGE, Mass. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   About 200 Chinese students and a
California lawmaker met at Harvard University on Saturday to
organize opposition to President Bush's veto of legislation
protecting Chinese from deportation.
   Rep. Nancy Pelosi, D-Calif., the bill's sponsor, encouraged
students to pressure federal legislators to override the veto.
   The measure, which received overwhelming support in Congress,
would prevent the Immigration and Naturalization Service from
forcing Chinese students to return to their homeland after their
student visas expire.
   Bush argued that a presidential directive would serve the same
function as the bill. Pelosi said, however, that a directive was
not as strong as an executive order and can be withdrawn whenever
the president pleases.
   Zhao Haiching, chairman of the National Committee on Chinese
Student Affairs, said White House officials had told him the veto
was necessary to give the president flexibility in foreign policy.
   ``What does the administration mean by `flexible?' We don't want
to be flexible with our lives,'' he said.
   Aides to three other federal lawmakers joined Pelosi and the
students on the first full day of three-day meeting sponsored by
the National Committee on Chinese Student Affairs and the Harvard
Chinese Student Association.
   Student leaders estimate that 40,000 Chinese students who
supported the pro-Democracy movement in China by faxing information
from U.S. sources to China during the revolt would be affected by
the bill.
   Students said they were distrustful that Bush's directive would
be maintained in part because of recent secret visits to China by
National Security Adviser Brent Scowcroft and other high
administration officials.
   Pelosi encouraged the students to pressure Congress by making
their case in both chambers, in the media and to the American
people. A two-thirds vote is required in both the House and Senate
to override a presidential veto.
   ``President Bush is wrong to try to cozy up to the leaders in
Beijing who ordered the massacre last June in Tiananmen Square,''
Sen. Edward M. Kennedy, D-Mass., said in a statement delivered to
the group.
   ``We must do everything possible to ensure that these brave
students do not become pawns or bargaining chips in the
administration's future dealings with that repressive regime,''
Kennedy said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0006 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 0121EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-811CargoDoor     01-07 0195</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-811 Cargo Door,0199</SECOND>
<HEAD>Navy Postpones Ocean Floor Search For UAL Jet's Cargo Door</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HONOLULU (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Navy has postponed searching the ocean floor
for the cargo door that tore off a United Air Lines Boeing 747-100
last Feb. 24, creating a hole through which nine passengers were
sucked to their deaths.
   The falling door was tracked on radar and is believed to be
lying in 14,600 feet of water 100 miles southwest of Honolulu.
   The search, originally scheduled for October, has been postponed
until mid-March because of delays in the development of the Navy's
``Orion'' deep-sea search system, said Lt. Bob Anderson, spokesman
for the U.S. Pacific Fleet.
   The system uses sonar and television designed to locate objects
in waters up to 20,000 feet deep. Anderson said engineering tests
and computer calibrations for the search have taken longer than
expected.
   National Transportation Safety Board and Federal Aviation
Administration officials say the door is crucial to determining
what caused the disaster aboard the Honolulu-to-New Zealand flight.
   At an NTSB hearing in April, United officials testified that
they failed to fully inspect the cargo door after making electrical
repairs two months before the accident.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0007 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 0135EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Japan-EastBloc     01-07 0243</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Japan-East Bloc,0250</SECOND>
<HEAD>Japan to Provide $1.8 Billion to Poland, Hungary</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Japan is planning to give more than $1.8 billion in
additional aid to Poland and Hungary, a national newspaper reported
Saturday.
   Japan's government-backed Export-Import Bank will supply $500
million dollars in loans to each of the two Eastern European
countries over the next three years, the Asahi Shimbun newspaper
reported.
   Japan will also allocate $350 million in trade insurance to
cover exports to Poland and other trade expenses, it said, and will
raise its expenditures for trade insurance on exports to Hungary
from $200 million to $400 million.
   Other parts of the $1.8 billion aid package to the two countries
include a $25 million grant in emergency food assistance to Poland
and $25 million in technological cooperation funds to the two
countries, the newspaper reported.
   In November, Japan promised a $150 million loan to Poland for
economic stabilization.
   The newspaper said Prime Minister Toshiki Kaifu is expected to
announce major features of the new aid plan during a speech this
week in Berlin, one stop on his seven-country European trip.
   The two Eastern European countries have sought economic
assistance to help relieve their economic crises and promote
democratic reform.
   Poland has asked Western countries to support its efforts to
control 900 percent annual inflation and to stabilize its currency.
   Western officials also say Poland will face a severe food
shortage this winter if it does not receive assistance.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0008 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 0122EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-OilSpill     01-07 0318</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Oil Spill,0327</SECOND>
<HEAD>Grand Jury Issues Subpoenas in Exxon Oil Spill</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ANN LEVIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEWARK, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Several Exxon Corp. employees have been
subpoenaed to appear before a state grand jury investigating a
spill of up to 500,000 gallons of oil into a shipping channel,
officials said Saturday.
   Subpoenas went Friday to about five Exxon workers in the rupture
Tuesday of a company pipeline filled with home heating oil, Exxon
spokesman Bill Smith said.
   The New Jersey Department of Environmental Protection and the
state Division of Criminal Justice are probing Exxon's role in the
spill that fouled ecologically sensitive marshland, killed at least
150 birds and partially closed the Arthur Kill shipping channel
between Staten Island, N.Y., and New Jersey.
   Christopher Florentz, a spokesman for state Attorney General
Peter N. Perretti Jr., said the investigation focuses on possible
Exxon violations of state ocean pollution laws.
   Florentz would not comment on the subpoenas or other aspects of
the investigation, citing the secrecy of grand jury proceedings.
   Smith said the Exxon employees who were subpoenaed work at the
company's Bayway Refinery in Linden and a distribution terminal in
Bayonne. Exxon will ``voluntarily provide any witnesses they
request,'' Smith said.
   The Coast Guard, which is supervising cleanup of the spill,
estimated 200,000 gallons of oil flowed into the channel. Exxon has
said 500,000 gallons is missing from holding tanks and pipelines.
   Florentz said Exxon has failed to clarify the amount of oil
spilled, the names of employees involved and the sequence of events
leading to the discovery of the leak.
   So-called ``filter fences'' will be installed to clean up
marshland with minimal human and mechanical intrusion, said Howard
Holmes, a petty officer in the Coast Guard's public affairs office.
   ``They don't want to tramp through the natural habitats of the
animals,'' he said.
   Natural wave action will move contaminated water through the
fine-mesh fences, Holmes said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0009 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 0123EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Volcanoes 1stLd-Writethru a0593 01-07 0418</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Volcanoes, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0593,0428</SECOND>
<HEAD>Minor Eruptions Recorded at Mount St. Helens, Redoubt Volcano</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS lead to UPDATE with officials calling Redoubt event
explosion, sted eruption, flight restrictions; SUBS grafs 6-7, bgn
`In Alaska...,' with 4 grafs to give details. Picks up 8th graf
pvs, `The volcano...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Mount St. Helens belched volcanic ash that settled over a
south-central Washington community Saturday, while seismic
equipment detected a small explosion in Alaska's Redoubt Volcano
that prompted flight restrictions.
   The National Weather Service reported a light dusting of ash
south of Yakima, Wash., in the Toppenish area about 80 miles east
of Mount St. Helens.
   ``It was gritty and it was still falling out of the sky,'' said
David Foster of Toppenish, who found his two cars coated with dust
when he awoke Saturday morning. ``It was very fine. You could see
tracks in the street.''
   Steve Malone, a seismologist with the University of Washington
in Seattle, said seismographs and other equipment within the crater
of Mount St. Helens recorded a small eruption at 5:37 a.m. PST.
   The eruption lasted about two minutes and was followed by small
earthquakes that lasted about two hours.
   In Alaska, authorities had no visual confirmation that Redoubt
Volcano emitted ash during a ``small explosive event'' at 2:26 a.m.
AST, the Alaska Volcano Observatory said.
   Seismologist John Davies of the observatory in Fairbanks called
the eruption a ``clearly a minor event'' compared to eruptions last
month and Tuesday.
   But scientists said that during the day the volcano continued to
generate ``a vigorous plume'' of steam and volcanic gas to
altitudes of 12,000 to 15,000 feet.
   The Federal Aviation Administration prohibited air traffic at
altitudes of less than 60,000 feet within 20 miles of the volcano.
   The volcano, 115 miles southwest of Anchorage, rumbled awake in
mid-December after a 25-year silence, spewing ash that disrupted
air traffic.
   An eruption Tuesday, stronger than the ones in December,
prompted precautionary flight cancellations and delays at Anchorage
International Airport.
   Malone said further details on the Mount St. Helens eruption
would not be available until crews could take a closer look at the
readings. The activity doesn't necessarily mean the volcano is
going to become more active, he said.
   Mount St. Helens erupted May 18, 1980, leveling 230 square
miles, leaving 57 people dead or missing and creating an ash cloud
that circled the globe.
   The volcano has had a number of less intense eruptions since
then but has been relatively quiet in recent years.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0010 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 0124EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-MobilDismissal     01-07 0535</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mobil Dismissal,0551</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mobil Throws in Towel on Unsealing Documents in Court Case</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DANIEL J. WAKIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEWARK, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Mobil Oil Corp. abruptly gave up its fight
this week to keep sealed confidential environmental reports sought
by a fired employee who is suing the company.
   Mobil said it dropped its appeal of an unsealing order to speed
the 2-year-old case along, and to put to rest what it called
``recent unjustified speculation'' in the media that it was trying
to hide wrongdoing.
   The papers themselves, several dozen environmental assessment
reports on Mobil's chemical plants and attorney comments about
them, shed little new light on arguments already made by attorneys
for the dismissed employee, Valcar Bowman Jr. of Riverdale, Ga.
   Bowman, then based in Princeton, was fired in April 1986 as
Mobil Chemical Co.'s No. 2 environmental official. Mobil said he
was fired in an economic cutback. Bowman, 47, says it was because
he refused to go along with a cover-up of environmental problems _
an allegation Mobil denies.
   Mobil opposed an effort by attorneys for Bowman and The
Associated Press _ which U.S. District Judge Harold A. Ackerman
allowed to enter the case _ to have the docuents unsealed. He
unsealed the papers, and Mobil appealed to the 3rd U.S. Circuit
Court of Appeals. The company withdrew that appeal Thursday.
   Company attorney Ron Neill said Mobil fought as hard as it to
uphold the principle behind the Environmental Protection Agency's
policy of critical self-assessment, in which industries police
themselves when regulators can't.
   ``If these documents aren't afforded some privacy, people ...
are going to be disinclined to do them if the local newspaper is
going to splash them on the front page,'' said Neill. ``It was
public interest.''
   The promise of secrecy was used as an incentive to recruit
companies to make such reports, said Lee M. Thomas, who was EPA
administrator when the policy was set forth in the mid-80s.
   But when news reports about Bowman's case and the struggle over
the documents' disclosure came to light, Mobil's need ``to defuse
the myth that we were trying to conceal something'' held sway,
Neill said.
   To First Amendment lawyers, it was an important victory.
   If Mobil won, it ``would have created a new class of evidence
shielded from public scrutiny,'' said Thomas Cafferty, an attorney
for the New Jersey Press Association.
   ``This is a very limited and discreet intrusion'' into the
self-critical process, he said. A court decision allowing the
documents to be kept sealed, he said, would have been a serious
departure from the principle that ``evidence introduced in a public
court proceeding is part of the public domain.''
   Thomas said such reports should be released only in ``tightly
controlled situations.''
   ``This may be one of them,'' he said, but added he couldn't tell
if their release in the Mobil case would have a chilling effect.
   As for the papers themselves, they don't go much beyond excerpts
contained in Bowman's court briefs, which have been reported on
previously.
   The briefs quote a Mobil attorney's memo spotlighting
``admissions of non-compliance'' of environmental regulations and
how Mobil executives could be subjected to potential legal action
if they knew about them.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0011 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 0147EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BRF--TankerLeak     01-07 0160</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Tanker Leak,0164</SECOND>
<HEAD>Toxic Truck Leak Prompts Evacuation, Interstate Closing</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SAN ANTONIO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A tractor-trailer truck leaking a flammable,
toxic chemical prompted the evacuation of about 250 families and
shut down a 10-mile stretch of highway Saturday, officials said.
   No injuries were reported.
   The driver of the truck, owned by Montgomery Truck Lines based
in Montgomery, Ala., noticed the leak from his 7,000-gallon tank
about 8 a.m. as the rig was parked at a service station off
Interstate 10 northwest of San Antonio.
   The chemical is cyclohexylamine, a flammable, toxic liquid used
as an anti-corrosive.
   ``If you inhale it, it will burn you,'' said John Longoria of
the Bexar County Fire Department.
   About 80 gallons leaked from the truck before the remainder of
the chemical was loaded into an empty tanker. The interstate was
re-opened and people who were evacuated from within a half-mile
radius of the truck were allowed to return to their homes about 10
p.m.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0012 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 0005EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-US-Colombia 2ndLd-Writethru a0566 01-07 0891</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-US-Colombia, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0566,820</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.S. Carrier Expected to Lead Drug Interdiction Off Colombian
Coast</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: INSERTS grafs 13-15, beginning ``The New York Times xxx to
update with report that Colombians declined to meet with U.S.
delegation</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By SUSANNE M. SCHAFER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Military Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The aircraft carrier John F. Kennedy has been
chosen to lead an anti-drug interdiction effort off the coast of
Colombia, but final decisions about when the warship may be put to
work haven't been made yet, a Defense Department source said
Saturday.
   The carrier and an accompanying guided missile cruiser, the USS
Virginia, left Norfolk, Va., on Thursday to engage in routine
training exercises in the Atlantic, a Pentagon official said, but
he added that a question mark remained as to when and if the
warships would see duty in a proposed U.S.-Colombian anti-drug
interdiction effort.
   ``That's the group. The JFK is the one to be used,'' said the
official. ``But it's still a question when they'd be put to use.''
   Two Colombian radio networks, Caracol and RCN, on Saturday
quoted unnamed Pentagon sources as saying the ships were headed
toward Colombia to begin setting up a blockade to try to stop drug
smugglers.
   But the Pentagon official, speaking on the condition of
anonymity, said the final plans were still being worked out on a
Pentagon proposal to launch a virtual air and sea blockade of the
Colombian coastline as part of an effort to help Colombia curb the
illicit narcotics exports of its drug cartels.
   An administration U.S. official Saturday denied that any
blockade was under way.
   ``Nothing's been initiated,'' in terms of activating such
efforts, he said.
   ``We are consulting'' with the Colombians and will continue to
do so over the next few days, the administration official said. He
declined to say when the heightened military operation might begin,
and said it should not be called a blockade.
   In Bogota, Colombia, the U.S. Embassy said the operation ``being
contemplated is only an increase in what has been done in the
past.''
   ``All operations will be conducted in international waters far
from the Colombian coast,'' the embassy said. ``Contacts with boats
and planes will follow norms dictated by international laws and
practices.''
   ``Formal consulation has not been carried out with the Colombian
government yet, but the least that we want to do is establish
communications ... in order to prevent incidents and, if possible,
share information that is obtained in the operations,'' the embassy
statement said.
   The New York Times, in its Sunday additions, said U.S. officials
had planned to announce details of the drug plans earlier, but that
Colombian authorities refused this past week to meet with an
American team that had been sent to explain the Navy plan.
Administration officials said, however, that they are confident
Colombian President Virgilio Barco Vargas will cooperate with the
U.S. plan.
   Quoting an unidentified administration official speaking on
condition of anonymity, the Times reported that the Colombians
feared that the United States might use its Panama operation as a
precedent to enter other countries in pursuit of people wanted on
American drug trafficking charges.
   The official also said that earlier reports about the dispatch
of a nval force to Colombia had been misinterepreted by the
Colombians as suggesting the United States planned a blockade.
   White House spokeswoman Alixe Glen said U.S. ships had been
scheduled to sail to Colombia to help with the anti-drug effort,
but she did not know when or have any more details on the operation.
   ``We knew the boats were going down there,'' Glen said.
   Later Glen said she had been mistaken, and had since learned
that it was not definite ships would go to Colombia, but only that
they were on a routine operations in the Atlantic.
   Defense Secretary Dick Cheney is expected soon to announce a
White House-approved plan for getting U.S. military forces more
deeply involved in the international drug battle.
   President Bush is scheduled to travel to Colombia in February
for an anti-drug summit of the leaders of the Andean nations.
   A senior Defense Department official said last month the air and
sea effort was expected to be enacted prior to Bush's trip to
Colombia.
   After that report appeared, White House spokesman Marlin
Fitzwater acknowledged that ``final plans were being made.''
   Under the reported anti-drug effort, the Navy was to operate an
aircraft carrier battle group off the Caribbean coast of Colombia
on a rotating basis. Each carrier group would be in position for
one or two months, a time frame similar to normal training
deployments.
   The senior Pentagon official had said that much of the money for
operating the battle group would come from training funds.
   The Pentagon official also emphasized that U.S. Navy fighters
would not be given the authority to shoot down suspected
drug-running planes. That enforcement role, he said, was to be
handled by Colombian officials.
   An aircraft carrier normally has eight or 12 smaller ships as
part of its battle group, along with an aircraft wing composed of
about 3,000 men and dozens of observation and tracking planes, and
those would be in the forefront of the surveillance efforts.
   Pentagon officials long have said the high-tech radar and
surveillance equipment owned by the U.S. Navy would be their main
weapon in keeping tabs on suspected drug dealers' boats and planes.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0013 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 0009EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Cambodia 1stLd-Writethru a0610 01-07 0602</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Cambodia, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0610,0619</SECOND>
<HEAD>Khmer Rouge Claims Attack On Cambodia's Second-Largest City</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: ADDS 9 grafs background.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>BANGKOK, Thailand (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Khmer Rouge guerrillas claimed Sunday
they had attacked Cambodia's second-largest city, setting it ablaze
and forcing government troops to call for reinforcements.
   If confirmed, the reported battle for the provincial capital of
Battambang would one of the biggest clashes in the 11-year-old war
against the Vietnamese-installed government. Most claims by the
Communist Khmer Rouge have proven false in the past, although the
guerrillas have scored significant victories in recent months.
   Khmer Rouge army radio claimed the guerrillas hit the
northwestern city at midnight Friday (noon Friday EST), attacking
the 5th military region's command there and in western Pursat
province and northwestern Banteay Meanchey province.
   The Bek Chan airfield was among the targets reported hit in
Battambang.
   The radio claimed Battambang town ``burned brightly'' from 1
a.m. Saturday and ``the fire was still raging at dawn.''
   At 6 a.m. Saturday, ``we were still fighting throughout
Battambang town, particularly in the strategic places,'' it said.
   ``The Vietnamese enemy and puppets panicked and called tanks
from Route 10 for assistance,'' the radio said. Route 10 is the
main road from Pailin to Battambang town.
   However, the guerrillas attacked and kept pressure on the enemy
forces along Route 10 since they partly routed them from Thursday
morning, the radio said.
   Battambang, the second-largest city after the national capital
of Phnom Penh, is in the province of the same name. The province
borders Thailand and contains some of the key mountain strongholds
of the Khmer Rouge.
   The attack would be the most significant since the guerrillas
seized the rich gem-mining town of Pailin, 45 miles southwest of
Battambang, on Oct. 22 after weeks of intense battle.
   The guerrillas had said the capture of Pailin opened the way for
an attack on Battambang and called on government supporters to
surrender or face the prospect of death in a guerrilla attack.
   The war erupted after Vietnam invaded Cambodia in December 1978
and replaced the Khmer Rouge with another Communist government. The
Khmer Rouge had killed hundreds of thousands of people during its
3{-year experiment with radical agrarian reform.
   The fighting has intensified since late September, when Vietnam
said it withdrew its last troops from the country. Major gains also
have been made by the Khmer Rouge's two guerrilla allies, the
non-communist forces of Prince Norodom Sihanouk and of Son Sann.
   The Khmer Rouge radio also said Saturday that pro-Vietnamese
forces ``will certainly fall'' because their major backers over the
past decade, the East bloc countries, ``are falling apart.''
   For this reason, the radio said, soldiers and government
officials should desert Phnom Penh.
   A text of the broadcast was seen in Bangkok Sunday.
   ``You should let the Vietnamese enemy aggressors fall and die by
themselves,'' it said. ``The only way to survive is to quickly
desert the Vietnamese enemies and flee.''
   The Khmer Rouge have slighted the latest peace plan, an
Australian proposal for a U.N. authority to be established in
Cambodia pending a general election.
   Australia's deputy foreign secretary, Michael Costello,
discussed the plan in a meeting in Bangkok Thursday with Khieu
Samphan, the main Khmer Rouge representative.
   But a Khmer Rouge statement said Khieu Samphan reiterated
long-standing demands at the meeting, including one that the
Vietnamese-installed government allow the guerrillas to share power
in an interim administration.
   The Vietnamese-installed government has said it is willing to
discuss the Australian proposal, but strongly rejected inclusion of
the Khmer Rouge in an interim government.
   Costello left Saturday for Vietnam to continue a tour to promote
the plan.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0014 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 0031EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Colombia-US 4thLd-Writethru   01-07 0676</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Colombia-US, 4th Ld-Writethru,a0592,0691</SECOND>
<HEAD>Radio Says American Warships En Route To Colombia in Blockade
Attempt</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: INSERTS 3 grafs after 12th graf `The daily...' to UPDATE with
report that Colombia balked at U.S. plan. Pickup 13th graf
`Meanwhile, a...'</NOTE>
<DATELINE>BOGOTA, Colombia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Radio networks reported Saturday that
two U.S. warships steamed toward Colombia to set up a blockade to
stop drug traffickers. U.S. officials confirmed the ships were in
the Atlantic but said it was for training exercises.
   In Washington, a Pentagon source said the aircraft carrier USS
John F. Kennedy has been chosen to lead an anti-drug effort off the
coast of Colombia, but that final decisions on when the warship
will be put to work had not been made. The source spoke on
condition of anonymity.
   The U.S. Embassy in Bogota released a statement in response to
the Colombian radio reports, saying the United States is stepping
up air and sea patrols in the Caribbean in an attempt to block
cocaine smuggling.
   But the embassy statement also did not say when the operation
was to start.
   ``All operations will be conducted in international waters far
from the Colombian coast,'' the embassy said. ``Contacts with boats
and planes will follow norms dictated by international laws and
practices.'' It did not say how many ships and planes were involved.
   The radio networks Caracol and RCN, in reports from stringer
reporters, quoted unidentified Pentagon sources as saying the
Kennedy and the cruiser Virginia were headed for Colombia's
Caribbean coast to begin setting up a blockade.
   Caracol and RCN did not not give any details of their sources.
   At the Pentagon, information officer Chris Cimko confirmed the
Kennedy and the Virginia sailed Thursday from their home port in
Norfolk, Va., and said it was for routine training in the Atlantic.
   White House spokeswoman Alixe Glen said U.S. ships had been
slated to sail to Colombia to help with the anti-drug effort. Later
Saturday, she said she had been mistaken and learned that it was
not definite ships would go to Colombia, but only that they were on
a routine operations in the Atlantic.
   A Bush administration official denied any blockade was under
way, but he said U.S. officials were in discussions with the
Colombian government regarding possible stepped-up interdiction
efforts by the U.S. military.
   White House press secretary Marlin Fitzwater said last week that
final plans were being made for U.S. military actions to help
interdict supply routes out of Colombia.
   The daily newspaper El Tiempo said it was unable to confirm the
radio reports. It said a U.S. blockade in the Caribbean made little
sense when cocaine already is being smuggled into the United States
from Pacific waters from Peru and Ecuador, as well as Brazil and
Venezuela.
   The New York Times, in its Sunday additions, said Colombia
balked at the stationing of U.S. naval vessels off its coast.
   The Times said U.S. officials planned to announce the drug plan
earlier but Colombian authorities refused this past week to meet
with an American team sent to explain the Navy plan. Administration
officials said, however, that they are confident Colombian
President Virgilio Barco Vargas will cooperate.
   Quoting an unidentified administration official speaking on
condition of anonymity, the Times reported that the Colombians
feared the United States might use its Panama operation as a
precedent to enter other countries in pursuit of people wanted on
American drug trafficking charges.
   Meanwhile, a communique supposedly from drug traffickers said
Saturday that traffickers will kill the abducted son of a
presidential adviser unless four people arrested by Colombia's
secret police are freed soon.
   The police said they had never heard of the four mentioned in
the communique. The communique was received by fax at the Bogota
headquarters of Caracol, which gave The Associated Press a copy of
the note.
   The kidnapped man is Alvarro Diego Montoya, a Bogota executive
who is the son of presidential adviser German Montoya, Barco's
closest confidant.
   Montoya's son was kidnapped Dec. 20 in Bogota as he was leaving
the offices of his financial services firm.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0015 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 0125EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Korea-Soviet     01-07 0394</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Korea-Soviet,0407</SECOND>
<HEAD>Korean Jetliner Rerouted By Redoubt Volcano Allowed To Fly Over
Soviet Union</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SEOUL, South Korea (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Soviet Union on Sunday allowed a
South Korean jetliner to fly over its territory after a volcanic
eruption in Alaska prevented the plane from taking the North Pole
route to Paris, officials said.
   It was the first time a regular Korean Air flight was allowed to
pass through Soviet airspace en route to Europe.
   The Boeing 747 carrying 290 passengers and crewmen arrived in
the French capital shortly before noon after a 13-hour flight over
Japan's Niigata, the Soviet eastern city of Khabarovsk on the
Chinese border, and Moscow.
   At the request of Korean Air, Moscow allowed the South Korean
plane's flight over its territory Sunday after an eruption of
Alaska's Redoubt Volcano prompted the U.S. Federal Aviation
Administration to prohibit air traffic near the volcano.
   Redoubt is near Anchorage Airport, where the jet was to make a
refueling stop on a North Pole route to Paris.
   The Soviet Union, which recognizes Communist North Korea, has no
diplomatic relations with capitalist South Korea. But Moscow and
Seoul have recently expanded economic and other non-political
contacts in recent years, and early last month the two governments
established a de facto consular relationship.
   Korean Air officials said the Soviet permission for the flight
was temporary but said they would be allowed to use the Soviet
route regularly after the conclusion of an aviation agreement with
Moscow in the first half of this year.
   If the aviation agreement is signed, Korean Air and the Soviet
airline Aeroflot would be able to open regular passenger service
between their two capitals, the officials said.
   At initial talks, Aeroflot indicated that it would start a
weekly flight to Seoul by way of Beijing and Shanghai. Korean Air
plans to fly all of its nine weekly flights to Europe by way of the
Soviet Union, with one flight each stopping over in Moscow and
Khabarovsk, respectively.
   In 1988, several chartered Korean Air flights used Soviet
airspace to transport African and East European athletes taking
part in the Olympics in Seoul.
   In 1983, a Korean Air Lines Boeing 747 from New York to Seoul by
way of Anchorage was downed by Soviet military jets after straying
into Soviet territory near the island of Sakhalin. All 269 people
on board were killed.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0016 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 0145EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Hirohito     01-07 0302</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Hirohito,0312</SECOND>
<HEAD>Imperial Family Marks First Anniversary of Hirohito's Death</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Japan-Coronation</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto TOK1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ERIC TALMADGE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Japan's imperial family and top government
officials marked the first anniversary Sunday of Emperor Hirohito's
death with ceremonies at the Imperial Palace and the late monarch's
tomb.
   The anniversary ended an official one-year mourning period for
the royal household, permitting in the coming months the marriage
of a prince and the elaborate coronation of Hirohito's son, Emperor
Akihito.
   Early Sunday, Akihito and Empress Michiko presided over a quiet
ceremony at an Imperial Palace chamber where, by tradition, an
emperor's spirit is enshrined until his tomb is completed.
   About 115 guests, including Prime Minister Toshiki Kaifu and
leaders of Parliament, attended the rite, during which Akihito read
a short prayer for his father's soul. The Empress Dowager Nagako,
86, did not attend because of hip and back problems.
   Another ceremony was to be held later in the afternoon at
Hirohito's tomb. Construction of the dome-shaped mausoleum in
suburban Tokyo was completed Saturday at a reported cost of $18.5
million.
   Hirohito died of cancer Jan. 7 last year at the age of 87. His
62-year reign was the longest in Japanese history, and covered a
difficult period of militarist adventurism, defeat, foreign
occupation and rapid economic reconstruction.
   Under the postwar constitution, the emperor is a symbolic
figurehead who performs mostly ceremonial functions.
   Akihito assumed the throne immediately after his father's death,
but his official coronation will not be held until November. In a
draft budget for the fiscal year beginning April 1, the government
earmarked $58 million for the enthronement and related ceremonies.
   Prince Aya, who at 24 is Akihito's youngest son, will wed
college sweetheart Kiko Kawashima on June 29. Aya is second in line
to the Chrysanthemum Throne.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0017 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 0633EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a BC-PrisonFight     01-07 0207</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Prison Fight,0213</SECOND>
<HEAD>Melee at County Jail Leaves 27 Injured</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CHULA VISTA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Prisoners battled with makeshift
weapons Saturday night in a 20-minute, racially-charged melee at a
badly crowded county jail that left 27 inmates injured, authorities
said.
   The disturbance began about 9:20 p.m., when some prisoners at
the San Diego County South Bay Detention Center refused to enter
their cells, said county sheriff's Deputy Lori-Anne McNally.
   ``The riot lasted for approximately 20 minutes and it developed
along lines between Hispanics and Black inmates,'' said Sgt. Jim
Cooke, a jail spokesman.
   Twenty-seven inmates were injured, 18 of them seriously enough
to be taken to hospitals, Cooke said.
   ``They tore mirrors off of the wall, light fixtures were torn
down, some of the bunks were disassembled and the parts were used
as weapons,'' Cooke said. ``Whatever they could get their hands on
to create makeshift weapons, that's what was used. Some of the
inmates were stabbed by crudely-made stabbing weapons.''
   The jail jammed to more than four times its intended capacity.
Designed for 192 prisoners, it held 782 on Saturday, Cooke said.
The cellblock where the melee erupted was designed for 24 inmates,
but held 113.
   Chula Vista is just south of downtown San Diego.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0018 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 0650EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a BC-PanamaCorruption     01-07 0366</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Panama Corruption,0374</SECOND>
<HEAD>Newspaper: New Government Prepares 300 Corruption Cases</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Panamanian investigators are preparing more
than 300 corruption cases against officials of the deposed regime,
whose take may have amounted to one-fifth of Panama's national
budget, a newspaper reported.
   Officials with the new civilian government say documents of the
government run by deposed Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega indicated 20
percent of the budget went to pay political employees who never
worked, the Los Angeles Times reported Sunday.
   Along with padding payrolls, former municipal authorities are
being investigated for illegal procurement and other embezzlement
schemes, the paper said, quoting officials who spoke on condition
of anonymity. Investigations also are underway in 12 ministries of
the federal government, including the finance and justice
ministries, officials for those agencies said.
   Three hundred criminal cases being prepared by Panamanian
authorities are based on evidence gathered by the office of
Controller General Ruben Carles, Panama's chief fiscal
investigator, and sent to the Attorney General, the paper said.
   ``The public administration of the Noriega regime was based only
on seeing how much they could steal. And what they stole was
incredible,'' Panama City Mayor Guillermo Cochez said.
   Cochez said his staff has identified and fired employees who
served in Noriega's paramilitary Dignity Battalions. Officials also
are hunting phantom workers _ the no-show cronies who regularly
received government paychecks.
   But corruption prosecutions are hindered by the sabotage of
Supreme Court records by Noriega loyalists early during fighting in
the capital on Dec. 21, the paper said.
   Court employees told investigators they saw several Supreme
Court magistrates setting their own files afire. A blaze swept
through the court offices at the Justice Ministry, destroying most
of the case records.
   Computers, photocopiers, fax machines and filing cabinets were
methodically smashed with axes and iron bars. Other federal
agencies were similarly sabotaged before they were secured by U.S.
forces.
   After the U.S. invasion Dec. 20, about 40 tons of files were
captured and taken to U.S. military bases in Panama for analysis by
the CIA and the U.S. Drug Enforcement Administration.
   Officials in the Controller General's office said half the cases
they have received had been shelved by the Noriega regime.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0019 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 0942EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a BC-SpaceShuttle     01-07 0189</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Space Shuttle,0193</SECOND>
<HEAD>Weather Outlook Worsens for Space Shuttle Launch</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CAPE CANAVERAL, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A worsening weather forecast has
reduced the chances of launching space shuttle Columbia on Monday
to just one in five, NASA said Sunday.
   ``Our weather for Monday doesn't look good,'' shuttle test
director Al Sofge told reporters. He said the main concern was
visibility, with clouds and fog expected to cover the area during
the 54-minute launch window which opens at 8:10 a.m.
   The chance of launching had been calculated at 40 percent on
Saturday, but Sofge said the outlook became bleaker overnight and
cut the chances to 20 percent.
   He said the weather front should move out late Monday,
increasing the odds for a Tuesday launch to 80 percent.
   Sofge said shuttle managers would meet Sunday evening to again
assess the weather and decide whether to proceed with pumping more
than half a million gallons of liquid hydrogen and liquid oxygen
into Columbia's fuel tanks.
   During a 10-day mission, Columbia's five astronauts are to
deploy a Navy communications satellite and retrieve a science
satellite that has been orbiting for nearly six years.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0020 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 1048EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a BC-FosterHomeExplosion     01-07 0151</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Foster Home Explosion,0152</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<HEAD>Seven Dead In Foster Home Explosion, Fire</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CLAYTON, Ala. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An explosion and fire tore through a foster
home in rural east Alabama early Sunday, killing six children and
one adult, officials said.
   Alabama Fire Marshal John Robison said the cause of the
explosion at the private residence was not immediately known. Fire
investigators were at the scene, near the Baker Hill community,
about 20 miles south of Eufaula.
   Robison said six children and an adult were killed in the
explosion and fire, which was reported about 2:15 a.m., but no
victim identifications were immediately available. No injuries were
reported and it was not known whether anyone else was in the house,
he said.
   ``I do not know at this time whether it was a true explosion or
whether it was a fire and then there was an explosion during the
fire,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0021 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 1118EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w BC-Bush     01-07 0476</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Bush,430</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush Takes Sister Jogging, Won't Talk About Colombia</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush, accompanied by his recently
widowed sister, went jogging Sunday morning following church
services, while telling reporters he wasn't ready to talk about
U.S. Navy operations off the coast of Colombia.
   The president went by motorcade to the historic C&amp;O canal in the
Georgetown section of Washington, where joggers often use the
towpath alongside the canal.
   His sister, Nancy Ellis, went with him to walk, but not jog on
an unseasonably warm winter day.
   Reporters asked Bush what the USS John F. Kennedy was doing in
the Caribbean off the coast of Colombia.
   ``I will address myself ... to that question at a future date,''
the president said.
   Pentagon sources said Saturday the aircraft carrier has been
chosen to lead an anti-drug interdiction effort off the Colombian
coast, but final decisions about when the warship may be put to
work haven't been made yet.
   In answer to a second reporter's question that Colombia
reportedly doesn't want U.S. warships off its coast, Bush said ``We
don't know all that.''
   The New York Times, in its Sunday additions, said U.S. officials
had planned to announce details of the drug plans earlier, but that
Colombian authorities refused this past week to meet with an
American team that had been sent to explain the Navy plan.
   Quoting an unidentified administration official speaking on
condition of anonymity, the Times said the Colombians feared the
United States might use its Panama operation as a precedent to
enter other countries in pursuit of people wanted on American drug
trafficking charges.
   Administration officials said, however, that they are confident
Colombian President Virgilio Barco Vargas will cooperate with the
U.S. plan.
   In Bogota, Colombia, the U.S. Embassy on Saturday said the
operation ``being contemplated is only an increase in what has been
done in the past.''
   ``All operations will be conducted in international waters far
from the Colombian coast,'' the embassy said. ``Contacts with boats
and planes will follow norms dictated by international laws and
practices.''
   ``Formal consultation has not been carried out with the
Colombian government yet, but the least that we want to do is
establish communications ... in order to prevent incidents and, if
possible, share information that is obtained in the operations,''
the embassy statement said.
   Bush's sister became a widow when Alexander Ellis II, 67, a
Boston insurance executive, died Dec. 29. The Bushes attended his
funeral last Tuesday.
   Mrs. Ellis attended services with the Bushes at St. John's
church across Lafayette Square from the White House.
   Barbara Bush, who is undergoing daily radiation therapy for an
eye problem, went swimming in the heated White House pool after
church, but did not go on the jog.
   Bush said his sister would walk while he was jogging, and they
would meet up at the finish line.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0022 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 1127EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-DeathWish     01-07 0183</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Death Wish,0187</SECOND>
<HEAD>Convict Wants Death Sentence, Not Life in Prison</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BRUSSELS, Belgium (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A man convicted of murder says he would
rather be put to death than spend his life in prison.
   But the criminal is not likely to get his wish in Belgium, which
has not carried out an execution since 1950.
   Willy De Coene, 42, was sentenced to death after being convicted
in December of murdering a 71-year-old woman in 1986. Death
sentences are automatically reduced to life in prison in Belgium,
and that will probably happen in Coene's case, his lawyer and legal
experts say.
   ``I am waiting impatiently for my execution,'' Coene said in an
open letter that appeared in several weekend newspapers. Even
though he denies killing the woman, he said asking for mercy is
``only for cowards.''
   A death penalty law dating back to 1867 is still on the books in
Belgium, but a longstanding legal tradition makes life in prison
the maximum penalty.
   Several proposals to change the death penalty law, which is part
of a broad code of moral standards, have failed.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0023 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 1127EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--France-BusCrash     01-07 0111</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--France-Bus Crash,0112</SECOND>
<HEAD>British Tourists Hurt When Bus Runs Off Highway</HEAD>
<DATELINE>COMPIEGNE, France (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A bus carrying British tourists home
from a ski holiday in the French Alps ran off a highway Sunday in
northern France, crashing into a ditch and injuring 14 of the
passengers, police said.
   No other vehicle was involved in the crash, which apparently
happened because the driver fell asleep on the Paris-Lille highway
near Compiegne, the officers said.
   Most of the injured, after minor treatment at the scene or at
the Compiegne hospital, were able to resume their trip in another
bus home to Bristol and Nottingham. Three victims remained in the
hospital Sunday.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0024 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 1127EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-India-Explosion     01-07 0171</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-India-Explosion,0176</SECOND>
<HEAD>Crude Bomb Explodes Outside Indian Parliament</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW DELHI, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A small, homemade bomb exploded under a
tree outside Parliament on Sunday, but no one was injured, police
said.
   ``It was a very crude device without much lethal power,'' a
senior police official said. ``There is no damage to person or
property.''
   No one claimed responsibility for the blast, he added, speaking
on condition of anonymity. ``There is no indication of any
organized terrorist group being involved. It may have been
motivated by some mischief-maker.''
   Parliament was not in session when the explosion occurred.
   The police official said bomb experts found no trace of a timing
device, which indicated the bomb was detonated by some sort of
impact.
   He said a shrapnel-shredded blanket was found entwined in the
branches of the tree, which is outside a gate in the wall
surrounding Parliament.
   He said the bomb was probably wrapped in the blanket and either
thrown by an assailant or hidden in the tree, then fell and
exploded.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0025 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 1129EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SouthKorea-US     01-07 0353</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-South Korea-US,0362</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.S. Ambassador Tries to Lessen Anti-U.S. Sentiment</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SEOUL, South Korea (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   U.S. Ambassador Donald Gregg met
Sunday with citizens of Kwangju in an apparent effort to reduce
anti-American sentiment in the city, scene of a 1980 civil uprising
that left hundreds dead.
   Gregg, who assumed his post last year, was the first U.S.
ambassador to visit Kwangju since the 10-day uprising.
   Many Kwangju citizens believe Washington played a role in the
bloody incident by condoning the use of the Korean military to
suppress the uprising. About 200 people died and more than 1,500
were wounded.
   Washington repeatedly denied the allegations, but Gregg's two
immediate predecessors _ James Lilley and Richard Walker _ stayed
away from the city for fear of anti-American violence.
   On Sunday, Gregg had a dinner with dozens of leading citizens,
including Mayor Choi In-ki, at a downtown restaurant. He planned to
meet with dissident and student leaders before returning to Seoul
on Tuesday.
   The South Korean news agency, Yonhap, quoted Gregg as describing
his trip to Kwangju as ``routine and nothing special'' and reported
that the ambassador was expected to try to explain Washington's
position on the 1980 incident.
   Gregg also expressed hope that the U.S. cultural center in the
city, closed last year, would be reopened at a new location before
the end of this year, Yonhap said.
   The U.S. cultural center in Kwangju has been attacked by radical
students 28 times times since 1980.
   Gregg's visit came two days after the U.S. Embassy issued a
statement rejecting former Korean President Chun Doo-hwan's
reference to an alleged U.S. role in the Kwangju incident.
   Dissident groups contend the United States supported Chun's
military dictatorship and condoned the mobilization of soldiers to
put down the pro-democracy uprising in Kwangju.
   Chun said in the testimony that he, then an army general,
decided on the military suppression of the uprising after receiving
information from the United States that the military threat from
communist North Korea was increasing.
   The U.S. Embassy said the United States did not see any evidence
of heightened threat from North Korea at the time.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0026 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 1129EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Philippines     01-07 0341</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Philippines,0350</SECOND>
<HEAD>Aquino Signs Law Expanding Powers of Coup Probe Commission</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By OLIVER TEVES</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MANILA, Philippines (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Corazon Aquino on Sunday
announced a new law substantially expanding the powers of a
presidential commission investigating the December coup attempt.
   Mrs. Aquino said the powers of the commission include the right,
among other things, to look into the bank accounts of supporters of
the failed coup, the most serious of the six attempts made to oust
Mrs. Aquino.
   ``This measure is a sign of our firm resolve to expose and
punish the guilty, pecially if they conspired after being bought
off with 30 pieces of silver,'' Mrs. Aquino said in her weekly
radio program.
   About 3,000 soldiers launched the coup attempt Dec. 1. At least
113 people were killed and more than 500 others were injured in
fighting that lasted until Dec. 9.
   It was the sixth attempt to overthrow Mrs. Aquino since she came
to power in a military-civilian uprising in 1986. Her opponents
have accused her of not acting strongly enough to put down a
long-running Communist insurgency, and not doing enough to improve
the nation's economy.
   The law, which was signed Friday but not made public until
Sunday, gives the five-member commission quasi-judicial powers,
including the right to grant immunity from prosecution to witnesses.
   It also protects witnesses from self-incrimination in testimony
they are forced to give.
   The commission can require the Monetary Board to disclose
information or grant authority to examine bank accounts if it has
``reasonable ground'' to believe the funds were used in the coup
attempt.
   The law provides that the commission's work, which must be
completed in one year, cannot be hampered by court injunctions
except those issued by the Supreme Court.
   The Congress in December granted Mrs. Aquino emergency powers to
deal with remnants of the rebel forces and economic saboteurs.
   Using the powers, Mrs. Aquino last week ordered new registration
for all firearms in a bid to flush out weapons used by rebel
soldiers and their civilian supporters.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0027 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 1131EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Romania-Condemned     01-07 0773</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania-Condemned,0795</SECOND>
<HEAD>Longtime Diplomat Ended Up on Death Row</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TERRY LEONARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUCHAREST, Romania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   For 11 months, Mircea Raceanu spent
most of his time alone in a small cell at a Bucharest prison,
waiting for a firing squad.
   Communist dictator Nicolae Ceausescu branded Raceanu a traitor,
a military tribunal sentenced him to death, and an appeals court
confirmed the sentence.
   Raceanu, a career diplomat who was the No. 2 man on the U.S.
desk at the Foreign Ministry, was arrested Jan. 31, 1989, and
accused of passing secrets to ``a foreign power.'' His case shows
what happened to people who challenged or defied Ceausescu.
   The secret allegedly passed to U.S. diplomats in Bucharest was a
copy of a letter to Ceausescu from six top Romanian Communists
demanding improved human rights and an immediate halt to food
exports in the shortage-plagued country.
   ``I was sentenced to death by the Ceausescu regime on charges of
betraying the interests of the country,'' Raceanu said in an
interview.
   ``I opposed the Ceausescu regime but I never betrayed my
country,'' insisted Raceanu, who refused to list specifics of the
charges against him.
   ``I always made a clear distinction between what is Romania and
Romanian interests and what represented the dictator and his
interests and his regime's interests,'' Raceanu said.
   ``In other words, it was very clear in my mind that Romania is
Romania and not like Ceausescu always wanted to say _ that Romania
is Ceausescu and Ceausescu is Romania.''
   Raceanu, without commenting on whether he passed it on, said the
``letter of the six,'' as it is now called, helped lay a foundation
for the start of a movement against Ceausescu.
   It marked the first time that six senior Communists, including
Raceanu's father, Grigore Ion, were known to have banded together
to protest Ceausescu's tough policies. It hinted at even further
dissatisfaction within the Communist Party.
   The letter criticized Ceausescu for plans to destroy thousands
of villages and for damaging Romania's economy and reputation
abroad.
   ``You started changing the geography of the countryside, but you
cannot remove Romania to Africa,'' the six wrote in the letter,
alluding to Romania's increasing isolation.
   ``How are you going to improve Romania's external relations when
all the leaders of the non-Communist nations of Europe refuse to
meet you?'' the six wrote.
   The letter was signed by former Politburo members Gheorghe
Apostol and Alexan ru Birladeanu, former Foreign Minister Corneliu
Manescu, former ambassador to the United States and editor of the
party daily Silviu Brucan and party veterans Constantin Parvulescu
and Raceanu's father.
   Before his arrest, Raceanu said he had spent 30 years in the
Romanian diplomatic service. He was in Romania's embassy in
Washington from 1969 to 1978.
   ``I opposed Ceausescu and Ceausescu's policies and, as the
former dictator said to a distinguished American public figure who
intervened on my behalf, I betrayed him personally,'' said Raceanu,
who added he could not identify the American.
   Raceanu was saved by the revolution that ousted Ceausescu on
Dec. 22 and freed political prisoners the next day.
   Another military tribunal tried Ceausescu and his wife, Elena,
his second in command. They were executed Christmas Day. The
provisional government said they will be the last people executed
in Romania.
   ``It is because of the young generation, who paid with their own
lives, that we came to the point were we could get rid of this
terrible, cruel, horrifying dictator and his group,'' Raceanu said.
   ``By their action, the young generation showed not only their
courage and dignity, but proved once again the vitality of the
Romanian people in a historic moment.
   ``Romanians from all generations should pay tribute to these
young people and they should do everything to ensure that their
sacrifice is never forgotten. As a man who was on death row, I
personally would like to pay respect to this young generation,
among them my daughter of 20 years. I am proud of them.''
   Raceanu said life in Romania went from bad to worse under
Ceausescu. Conditions were harsh and food was scarce.
   ``There was a unique concentration of power in the hands of one
family supported by a group of people who had transformed Romania
into their own house and garden, neglecting the interest of the
people and Romania as a country,'' he said.
   ``Internally, it was a hell for the people. There was no hope
for anybody, especially for the younger generation. On the
international scene, Romania became an isolated country pointed to
by almost everybody as a model which should never be followed by
any civilized member of the international community.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0028 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 1132EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--ArtTheft     01-07 0169</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Art Theft,0173</SECOND>
<HEAD>Painting by Theodore Rousseau Stolen From Soviet Museum</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Thieves stole a painting by 19th century French
artist Theodore Rousseau from a museum in central Russia, Pravda
reported Sunday.
   The thieves broke in through a window, cut the canvas from its
frame, and fled even though they set off an alarm, the Communist
Party daily said. The painting is a landscape whose Russian title
translates as ``Before the Thunder.''
   The report didn't say when the robbery occurred.
   V. Sazonov, director of the museum in Penza, told Pravda the
work was considered one of Rousseau's best, and the thieves might
try to sell it abroad.
   Rousseau, who died in 1867, was a landscape painter and leader
of the Barbizon School. Prices for his paintings in recent years
have ranged from $1,000 to $100,000.
   The Barbizon School, named after a French village, refers to a
group of artists known for their romantic landscape paintings.
Other members included Jean Baptist Camille Corot and Jean Francois
Millet.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0029 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 1142EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SouthAfrica     01-07 0535</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-South Africa,0548</SECOND>
<HEAD>Parents, Students Confront Government On School Crisis</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVID CRARY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SOWETO, South Africa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Black students and their parents
Sunday demanded nullification of high school exams that 58 percent
of black students failed, and they urged the failing youths to
re-enroll in defiance of government rules.
   These were two of the major steps endorsed at an unprecedented
community meeting attended by more than 1,000 people in Soweto, the
country's largest black township and one of the hardest hit by the
crisis in black education.
   Nationally, only 42 percent of more than 190,000 black high
school seniors passed standardized exams late last year, compared
to more than 95 percent of white students. At high schools in
Soweto, home to 2.5 million blacks, the passing rate was less than
30 percent.
   A student who passes the exams gets a certificate comparable to
a high school diploma in the United States. Those who fail have
little chance of getting any sort of job beyond the equivalent of
manual labor.
   The exams also are used for university admissions purposes _
only 17,533 of the more than 190,000 black students who took the
recent exams did well enough to qualify for universities.
   The meeting Sunday was organized by anti-apartheid activists
specializing in education issues, some of whom have spent long
periods in detention. The chairman, Vusi Khanilye, was one of three
activists who won his freedom by escaping to refuge at the U.S.
Consulate in Johannesburg in 1988.
   Most speakers in the crowded auditorium blamed the
white-controlled Department of Education and Training for causing
the school crisis through overcrowding, underfunding and lack of
commitment to black progress. The government spends five times as
much to educate a white pupil as a black pupil.
   However, some participants said black students and political
activists shared the blame. One teacher said students could have
studied harder, and a parent said anti-apartheid groups were wrong
to have encouraged students to join politically oriented general
strikes and boycotts that frequently disrupted schooling over the
past five years.
   One youth representing a militant student organization said:
``We charge the whole community to take the responsibility of
getting involved and to take control of our schools.'' Addressing
students, the youth said: ``Go back to your battle trenches, which
are the schools themselves.''
   Black schools reopen this week for the new academic year, and
people at the meeting agreed that students who failed the exams
should present themselves for enrollment.
   The government says there is not enough room to accommodate the
failed students and has advised them to attend part-time
``finishing schools.''
   ``You say `No' to one child and you say `No' to a nation,'' said
David Maepa, a parent who helped conduct the meeting. ``We will
meet the government's challenge and take all our children back to
school, even if they sit on top of each other.''
   The country's largest-circulation black newspaper, City Press,
said in an editorial Sunday that the education meeting was one of
the most important for Soweto in several years.
   ``We are glad some of our leaders have finally come of age,'' it
said. ``They realize education is the only real weapon at our
disposal.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0030 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 1152EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a BC-Quake 1stLd-Writethru a0626 01-07 0207</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Quake, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0626,0207</SECOND>
<HEAD>Quake Felt Widely Around Fairbanks, Alaska; No Reports Of Damage</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 4 grafs to UPDATE with later Richter estimate put
at 5, sted 5.5; quake felt 80 miles away. Picks up penultimate
graf.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>FAIRBANKS, Alaska (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A moderate earthquake was felt widely
around Fairbanks early Sunday morning but no damage or injuries
were reported.
   Alex Medberry at the Tsunami Warning Center in Palmer said the 2
a.m. quake was centered 40 miles northwest of here.
   Charlotte Row of the Alaska Earthquake Information Center placed
the Richter scale reading at 5 and said said several small
aftershocks followed. An earlier estimate put the Richter scale
reading at 5.5.
   The quake was felt in the small towns surrounding Fairbanks and
as far away as Clear, 80 miles south, she said.
   The Richter scale is a measure of ground motion as recorded on
seismographs. Every increase of one number means a tenfold increase
in magnitude. Thus a reading of 7.5 reflects an earthquake 10 times
stronger than one of 6.5.
   An earthquake of 3.5 on the Richter scale can cause slight
damage in a local area, 4 can cause moderate damage, 5 considerable
damage, and 6 can be severe.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0031 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 1154EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-TridentBattle Bjt   01-07 0765</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Trident Battle, Bjt,710</SECOND>
<HEAD>Venerable Trident Program Faces Congressional, Administration
Opposition</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN DIAMOND</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Trident submarine program is sailing into
rough seas in 1990 with the Pentagon considering halving the
production rate, and congressional critics poised to divert its
funding into a peace dividend.
   A key element in the nation's three-pronged nuclear defense
system, each submarine, armed with 192 nuclear warheads, costs $1.2
billion _ money that critics contend could be spent on domestic
programs or on reducing the federal deficit.
   Opponents argue that the 17 Tridents already in the water or
under construction are enough to hold up the seagoing leg of the
nuclear triad of missiles, bombers and submarines. Those arguments
are expected to return to Congress with renewed energy at the end
of January when the debate on next year's federal budget begins.
   ``I would say that the battle lines are going to be drawn very
quickly among some of the liberals who are trying to cut the
defense budget,'' said Rep. John Rowland, R-Conn.
   No liberal himself, Rowland is concerned about the fate of the
Trident, which is built in his home state.
   Two Defense Department sources, speaking only on condition of
anonymity, said the 1991 Pentagon budget may propose building a
Trident every other year instead of the current annual construction
schedule. General Dynamics' Electric Boat Division in Groton,
Conn., which has built all the Tridents and which has only one
other competitor, would bear the brunt of such a slowdown.
   ``I would expect that if in fact the administration does
recommend an alternate-year program _ which is not a cataclysm but
a step back from full support _ there will be a major argument on
the floor,'' said Sen. Joseph Lieberman, D-Conn.
   Sen. Dale Bumpers, D-Ark., for the past year has been pushing
for a construction slowdown based on commitments the Reagan
administration made in strategic arms talks with the Soviet Union.
   Tentative START agreements reached in Geneva in 1987 would limit
the number of ballistic missile warheads to 4,900. Under the
current Trident program, the number of warheads aboard the subs
alone would approach that figure within a few years.
   ``I'm just trying to save a little money,'' said Bumpers. ``My
objection is we are continuing to produce Tridents on the old
schedule and in light of the tentative agreement in the START
talks, that just doesn't make sense.''
   When the Senate returns Jan. 23, Bumpers said he will be ready
with his proposal again, regardless of whether the Bush
administration endorses the slowdown idea.
   The Arkansas Democrat said the warming of relations between the
United States and the Soviet Union would add momentum to his
proposal.
   On the House side, Rep. Thomas Foglietta, D-Pa., is leading a
similar campaign. In a letter last spring to President Bush signed
by, among others, Rep. Les Aspin, D-Wis., chairman of the House
Armed Services Committee, Foglietta warned of the consequences of
overbuilding.
   ``We may end up buying Tridents in excess of those we would
deploy under START,'' Foglietta wrote. ``This may force premature
retirements of one or more Tridents _ forfeiting a
multibillion-dollar expenditure.''
   Also on Foglietta's agenda is saving the V-22 Osprey, a vertical
take-off airplane, from the budget knife. Part of the Osprey
project would be handled by a Boeing plant near Foglietta's
Philadelphia district.
   An Armed Services Committee aide who asked to remain anonymous
predicted that proposals to slow down Trident production ``will be
looked at with great favor'' in the House.
   Electric Boat began building Tridents 16 years ago. Nearly two
football fields long and 42 feet in diameter, the Tridents carry 24
ballistic missiles each with eight warheads. They have a cruising
speed of 20 knots.
   Although Trident has been one of the most popular defense
programs on Capitol Hill, there have been pockets of opposition. In
1986 the administration budget contained no start-up money for a
future Trident and it took Senate action to restore the funds after
the House failed to act.
   In 1988 the House seapower subcommittee led by Rep. Charles
Bennett, D-Fla., cut out funding for Trident but the full Armed
Services Committee restored the money. Bennett wanted to build more
destroyers instead of the Trident.
   General Dynamics has plenty of submarine work to keep it busy
into the 1990s even if Trident is switched to an every-other-year
schedule. But a slowdown would begin a cycle of layoffs and
rehiring which would destabilize the workforce and increase the
cost of a Trident by some $200 million, according to Electric Boat
spokesman Neil Ruenzel.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0032 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 1155EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-EasternEurope-Economic     01-07 0714</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Eastern Europe-Economic,730</SECOND>
<HEAD>World Bank and IMF Guide Shift from Communist Economies</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CARL HARTMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Nobody has much experience in moving a country
from communism to a system with a big role for private business, so
East European governments have turned for guidance to a pair of
worldwide bodies based in Washington.
   They are the World Bank and the International Monetary Fund,
both owned by 152 countries which have many different mixes of
public and private ownership. The United States takes a leading
role in both organizations.
   Their headquarters face one another in Washington, three blocks
from the White House. The bank is headed by President Barber B.
Conable, a former Republican Congressman from New York state and a
friend of President Bush. At the fund, the top official is
traditionally a European, now Managing Director Michel Camdessus of
France.
   A senior IMF official said last week that the fund is now in
contact with all the major East European countries.
   The Soviet Union has said it wants to join, but the United
States has opposed that on the ground that the country is far from
a market economy. Poland and Hungary are already members. The new
Czechoslovak government says it would like to be.
   Camdessus himself put the final touches to an accord with Poland
that has brought decontrol of prices, a convertible currency and
other measures that the fund traditionally advises.
   ``We believe that the program the Polish authorities have
adopted is a very strong one,'' said the official, who spoke on
condition he not be identified. ``They are trying to tackle in a
very determined fashiom the key problem in the country, which is
skyrocketing inflation.''
   The fund and bank influence governments mostly through loans and
the conditions attached to them. They promote conservative
policies: sale of state-owned industry, reduced government
deficits, abolition of price controls, holddowns of wages,
promotion of exports, cuts in subsidies.
   Poland has promised such policies, and in return is expected to
get a loan of $710 million from the fund. Billions in other loans
are expected to follow, on top of the $42 billion Poland already
owes.
   The fund has been making similar arrangements for years with
Third World countries. The borrowing government's promises
generally result in a time of austerity: higher prices for food and
other basic goods as government subsidies are cut; higher
unemployment as unprofitable enterprises are shut down. The fund
says the austerity will be worse if the measures are delayed.
   Sometimes the belt-tightening programs have resulted in bloody
rioting, as occurred last year in Venezuela and Jordan.
   In Poland, bus fares and gasoline prices were doubled at the
start of the new year. Food prices are also rising. Higher food
prices previously have brought unrest when they were imposed by the
Warsaw government.
   Because of the IMF's stiff requirements, other lenders usually
wait for the fund to act before making new loans themselves. The
agreement between the fund and the borrowing country has teeth. If
the fund decides that the brrower has not kept its promises,
disbursements are cut off.
   That occurred last year with Yugoslavia, which has had 11
successive agreements with the fund, eight of them completed to the
fund's satisfaction. Now Yugoslavia has another crisis and a new
accord is being negotiated.
   China has had billions of dollars of help from both the fund and
bank, to meet its general obligations and for specific projects
such as building schools and roads.
   ``We're setting up a unit to deal with socialist economies and
to see how much cross-fertilization there can be with Europe and
Asia,'' said Shahid Yusuf, a Pakistani who has been handling the
World Bank's relations with China.
   He added in an interview that there will be important
differences from country to country in Eastern Europe.
   In China, 90 percent of farm households now work independently,
though they are still obliged to sell some of their production to
the state. But Yusuf predicted that in the Soviet Union it will be
much harder to break up the big collectives and state farms. In
Poland, on the other hand, the communist government never
interfered much with private farmers _ but it gave them much less
help then they thought they needed.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0033 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 1156EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-GunControl-Washington Bjt   01-07 1111</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gun Control-Washington, Bjt,950</SECOND>
<HEAD>Murder Rate Soars in D.C. Despite Stiff Gun Control</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CAROLYN SKORNECK</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   For the past half-year, as the District of
Columbia's murder rate grew ever higher, actor Charlton Heston has
noted ironically in a National Rifle Association television ad:
``They banned guns in this city a decade ago.''
   ``And the criminals just laugh at their laws,'' he intones,
sirens wailing in the background. ``That tells me guns aren't the
problem. Criminals are.''
   The District of Columbia has one of the nation's toughest gun
laws, yet armed violence persists. Of the record 438 murders in the
nation's capital in 1989, about 78 percent were committed with
firearms, says Metropolitan Police Officer Quintin Peterson.
   In addition, he said, more than 1,300 people were shot and
wounded. Police estimate that about 60 percent of the killings were
drug-related.
   The District of Columbia's Firearms Control Act of 1975,
implemented in February 1977, banned the sale of handguns with a
few exceptions for law enforcement and security personnel and
required registration of all firearms previously purchased. Those
seeking to register the weapons also had to submit to a thorough
background check.
   So where are these guns coming from?
   The federal Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco and Firearms, which
compiles an annual report on guns retrieved in crimes in
Washington, found 52 percent of those collected in 1989 came from
Virginia, a slight increase over 1988, and 18 percent came from
Maryland, up from 15 percent from the previous year, said Dick
Pedersen of the ATF office covering Washington, Maryland and
Virginia.
   ``If you put them together, you have 70 percent'' of the guns,
he said. ``You can basically disregard the rest of the country.
We're looking at ones and twos from rest of the union, people
moving in and losing their gun, having it stolen.''
   The study is based on traces of several hundred guns each year
which are randomly selected, he said. A total of 2,333 firearms
were picked up in Washington last year, he said.
   While some of the weapons are rifles, ``This is really a handgun
city and a handgun area,'' Pedersen said. ``We're finding more than
half the guns picked up in crime now are semiautomatic handguns,
and that appears to be growing, based on the last couple of years.''
   In many cases, these are not the now-infamous Saturday Night
Specials, cheap handguns bought on the spur of the moment.
   ``We find a lot of high-quality firearms, a direct result of the
drug trade,'' Pedersen said. ``They can afford high quality, and
they buy them.''
   Some are the same weapons used by police forces around the
country, 9mm semiautomatic handguns that cost $500 to $700 apiece,
he said. At the same time, many of the guns are small and
concealable .25-caliber semiautomatic pistols that cost about $200,
he said.
   The NRA contends that Washington's murder rate _ the highest in
the nation _ demonstrates that gun control doesn't work.
   Gun control laws vary widely in the major cities with some of
the highest murder rates in 1988. The top 12 among the 35 U.S.
cities with 400,000 or more people included four cities with no gun
control measures, including Detroit, which has the second highest
murder rate.
   Seven more of the 12 had relatively strong gun control laws,
while one, Miami, had a three-day cooling off period for a gun
purchase, but no background check on the buyer.
   At the same time, Honolulu, covered by a strong state gun
control measure, showed the lowest murder rate among the 35 largest
cities.
   Law enforcement officials and gun control advocates say there's
more to the issue than whether an individual city has strong
controls.
   They say Washington's location _ carved out of Maryland and
Virginia with virtually no natural boundaries other than the easily
crossed Potomac River _ makes its handgun ban virtually
unenforceable.
   ``In Washington, you can drive across the river and purchase
handguns,'' said Susan Whitmore of Handgun Control Inc. ``Until
this last year, Virginia had one of the weakest gun laws in the
country.''
   New York City has the same problem, she said.
   ``More than 90 percent (of the guns used in New York crimes)
come from other states with very weak laws,'' Whitmore said.
``That's why we believe we need a national law.''
   A new law in Virginia that took effect Nov. 1, 1989, requires an
immediate background check prior to the purchase of assault-style
weapons and most handguns. A person wishing to buy a gun must
complete an application and the gun dealer must call the Virginia
State Police to get approval for the sale.
   As of Dec. 31, 1989, Virginia officials had approved 9,834 sales
_ each of which could involve numerous guns _ and rejected 109
applications, said state police Lt. R. Lewis Vass, who runs the
program.
   The program has produced an unexpected dividend: the capture of
three fugitives, one from Florida and two from New Jersey. By state
law, police have until the close of business the day after a
gun-purchase application has been rejected to tell the gun dealer
the rejection is confirmed or a search of records found the sale
could be made. As a result, some people rejected initially have
returned to gun stores the next day to get the final decision. In
three cases, police were waiting when the fugitives returned, Vass
said.
   Officials also are hoping prosecution of certain gun dealers
will curb illicit sales. Donald P. Percival, a former U.S. Park
Police officer who owned gun stores in Virginia, and James S.
Chapman, a former D.C. police officer and retired Secret Service
uniformed agent, were convicted in November of illegally selling
semiautomatic handguns to an 18-year-old drug dealer who resold or
traded the weapons for drugs in Washington.
   While Whitmore said she was encouraged by Virginia's new law,
Pedersen said it's still too early to tell what impact it will have
on gunfire in Washington, saying the problem occurs when legitimate
purchasers in Virginia provide weapons to people who would be
ineligible to purchase them legally.
   Gun control groups want national laws, but one law enforcement
official says regional controls might be sufficient.
   ``If you were in a town that had mountains or deserts around it
and people had to travel four hours and take two interstates to get
to the area, I can see how you might control a problem like this,''
the officer said. But in Washington, ``It's like walking across the
street to get a hamburger. We're one large urban area here. It's
hard to keep guns out of D.C. when there are no natural borders.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0034 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 1159EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Obit-Kelly 1stLd-Writethru a0637 01-07 0314</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Kelly, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0637,0319</SECOND>
<HEAD>Margaret Kelly, Mother of Princess Grace, Dies at 91</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 8th graf, `Mrs. Kelly, to CORRECT name of surviving
daughter to Conlan sted Conland; SUBS last graf to add location of
funeral.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>LINWOOD, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Margaret Kelly, mother of the late Princess
Grace of Monaco and matriarch of the famed Kelly clan of
Philadelphia, died at a convalescent home here. She was 91.
   Mrs. Kelly died at 8:45 a.m. Saturday of pneumonia, a spokesman
for the Linwood Convalescent Center said. She had been a resident
of the nursing home since 1982 and had suffered several strokes in
recent years.
   A former beauty queen and magazine cover girl, she was known
both for her own accomplishments and those of her husband and
children, particularly her daughter, actress Grace Kelly, who later
married Prince Ranier of Monaco. Princess Grace died of injuries
suffered in an automobile accident in September 1982.
   Mrs. Kelly's husband, John B. Kelly Sr., was an Olympic rowing
champion who parlayed his skills as a bricklayer into a
construction empire. He died in 1960.
   Born on Dec. 13, 1898, the former Margaret Majer met her future
husband at a Philadelphia swimming pool when she was just a
teen-ager. They married in 1924.
   Earlier, in her early 20s, she appeared on the covers of several
national and Philadelphia magazines.
   An accomplished swimmer and athlete, Mrs. Kelly was the first
director of women's athletics at the University of Pennsylvania.
   Mrs. Kelly is survived by two daughters, Margaret R. Conlan of
Philadelphia and Lizanne K. LeVine of Gladwyne, Pa.; 13
grandchildren; and 17 great-grandchildren.
   The couple's only son, John B. Kelly Jr., also rowed in the
Olympics, was at one time president of the U.S. Olympic Committee
and served on the Philadelphia City Council. He died in 1985.
   Funeral services were planned for Tuesday in Philadelphia.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0035 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 1209EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Dog'sLife Bjt   01-07 0537</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Dog's Life, Bjt,510</SECOND>
<HEAD>This Doghouse Has Tails Wagging</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto WX6</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT M. ANDREWS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>GREAT FALLS, Va. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In the heart of this fashionable
Washington suburb, there's a yuppie dream house that's gone to the
dogs.
   The luxurious amenities of the doghouse that Richard T. Ziegler
built for Crissy, his white German shepherd, and J.R., his Doberman
pinscher, would strain the hyperbolic lyricism of a real estate ad
writer.
   Their doggie digs feature a redwood cathedral ceiling, Italian
porcelain tile flooring, solid brass fixtures, a terra cotta
chimney for the fake flagstone fireplace, cedar-shake roof and
double-paned windows with space heater to keep it toasty warm on
winter nights.
   Outside, there's a kidney-shaped pool surrounded by a patio deck
and rock garden.
   And all for only $15,000 plus.
   Ziegler had the doghouse designed as a miniature, 8-foot version
of the $3.5 million ``contemporary Victorian'' mansion that Ziegler
built for himself on 25 acres of rolling woodland in the Virginia
countryside west of Washington.
   He says he plans to build an equally lavish ``guest cottage''
below the doggie pool to house Crissy and J.R.'s overnight visitors.
   It's a doggone shame, but the two dogs hardly ever use their
posh living quarters, except to flop down on the cool tile floor
for relief on hot summer days, Ziegler says. Unlike the doghouse
that Jim and Tammy Bakker built, this one isn't airconditioned.
   So far, Crissy and J.R. have only dipped their paws in the pool,
Ziegler says, although they enjoy sprawling on the deck to spy on
squirrels and other wildlife scampering in the woods.
   ``They spend most of the time in my house,'' he said. ``They
sleep on their own bed right in the master bedroom. You don't tell
a Doberman where he's going to sleep.''
   Ziegler, 53, a developer whose companies have built two dozen
shopping centers in metropolitan Washington, North Carolina and the
San Francisco Bay area, isn't the sort of man who'd nail a few
pieces of plywood together to make a doghouse, like most folks.
   Ziegler believes in going first class.
   His own backyard has a gigantic, heated swimming pool with three
waterfalls gurgling past rock gardens and a bubbling whirlpool
bath. The main house, with its vaulted ceilings and wide glass
windows, is covered with 4{ miles of redwood siding and 320 tons of
flagstone from the Blue Ridge mountains.
   His five-car garage is full. It's currently occupied by a white
Lincoln stretch limo with telephones, bar, TV set and curving white
leather sofa; a white Jaguar convertible; a couple of neo-classic
Excalibur and Zimmer touring cars; and a four-wheel drive vehicle
``that belongs to my dogs.'' Ziegler also keeps a 53-foot Italian
motor yacht berthed in Miami.
   Not bad for a bread truck driver's son from Suitland, Md., who
couldn't afford to attend college, but took night classes, raised a
family and worked 90-hour weeks for two decades to build a booming
construction business.
   Does Ziegler have any qualms about spending more than $15,000
for a doghouse while homeless people are sleeping in the streets of
Washington?
   ``Not at all,'' he says. ``That's why I worked all my life, so I
could do things like that.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0036 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 1210EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Argentina-Menem     01-07 0877</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Argentina-Menem,0901</SECOND>
<HEAD>President in First 6 Months Acts Boldly, Though With Little
Success</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP Extra</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ED McCULLOUGH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUENOS AIRES, Argentina (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In the six months he has been
president, Carlos Menem has boldly addressed Argentina's biggest
problems, so far with little success.
   To overcome inflation and recession that forced his predecessor
to leave office 22 weeks early, Menem put up for sale state
companies his Peronist Party nationalized or created four decades
ago.
   To reduce tensions in the armed forces, he called off the trials
of officers accused of kidnapping, torture and murder during the
1976-83 dictatorship, pardoning several hundred soldiers along with
a handful of one-time, left-wing terrorists.
   To restore ties with Great Britain severed during the 1982
Falkland Islands war, Menem set aside the thorny issue of
sovereignty over the South Atlantic archipelago. Consulates
reopened in Buenos Aires and London last month; full diplomatic
relations are pending.
   ``He said nothing about any of this during his campaign, which
focused on charisma and nationalism,'' historian Felix Luna said in
an interview. ``The change has been night to day.''
   Nevertheless, Menem's willingness to tackle head-on issues his
predecessor, Raul Alfonsin, ignored or tried to finesse has not
moved Argentina from the brink of hyperinflation, social unrest and
military insurrection.
   The cost of living in December soared by at least 50 percent _
eight times the November rate. Inflation for 1989 topped 4,200
percent. Real wages have shrunk to about one-half the level of a
year ago. Underemployment and unemployment total 16 percent.
   Teachers, police officers, bus drivers, unskilled laborers and
many others earn about $100 a month, or less. All have held strikes
since Menem took office.
   ``Wages are absolutely insufficient ... and if prices don't come
down ... people aren't going to have enough even to buy food,''
said Cesar Jaroslavsky, leader of the opposition Radical Civic
Union bloc in the House of Deputies.
   Noting that hundreds of border guards were deployed last month
in Rosario, Argentina's second-biggest city and the site of food
riots in May and June, Jaroslavsky added, ``I think social unrest
is a real risk.''
   The army remains bitterly divided between loyal officers and
rebels who staged three insurrections against Alfonsin, president
from December 1983 through last July.
   ``There is no possibility of a military coup,'' said Rosendo
Fraga, executive director of the Union for the New Majority Studies
Center. ``For that, you would need three things: at least some
international support, at least some public support, and an
efficient military leader. In Argentina, none of those three
factors exists.''
   Only Menem's harshest critics blame his policy ``errors'' for
Argentina's continued economic and political morass. Others note
ills run so deep that a major endeavor in one area fails to resolve
it at one fell swoop, and provokes problems somewhere else.
   The government's confiscation of several billion dollars worth
of certificates of deposit last week stabilized the austral and
lowered interest rates from 600 percent a month. But it also dried
up funds for investment and may worsen the existing recession.
   It also eroded public confidence in the government and the
banking system.
   ``The government is disoriented and Menem doesn't know what to
say,'' said Juan Sanabria, a dentist, as he waited in line outside
a bank. ``Everytime he opens his mouth, he makes things worse.''
   If Menem, a career politician who was jailed nearly five years
during the last dictatorship, has ignored tradition and struck out
in new directions, he also has shown himself to be unpredictable,
volatile, and willful.
   If a plan fails or a minister lets him down, Menem changes to
another. Three of the eight Cabinet ministers he appointed in July
have been replaced. On Dec. 10, a new, official exchange rate was
set. On Dec. 18, controls on foreign exchange were lifted.
   Menem allowed long-time aide Eduardo Curia to draft a plan to
``dollarize'' prices and wages in an effort to stabilize the
austral. At the last minute, Menem changed his mind. Curia resigned
from the Economy Ministry days later.
   ``Menem has correct intuitions, but he has demonstrated he has
little liking for the routine of government,'' said Fraga of the
center-right Studies Center.
   Among the sharpest criticism of Menem is that having pushed
through legislation giving him authority to sell state companies
and cut the budget, he has done neither.
   Also, some accuse him of spending too much time kissing snow
queens at ski resorts, driving in car and boat rallies, playing
soccer and tennis, and playing host to foreign dignitaries.
   Menem tells Argentines his government is on the right track and
has accomplished more in six months than previous governments did
in six years.
   As much as he has wavered in other areas, Menem stands firmly
behind plans to sell the state airline, railroad and other public
companies; to deregulate the oil and other state industries; to
remove government controls of wages, prices, exchange and interest
rates; and to cut state spending and encourage foreign investment.
   ``From my point of view, this is the last serious crisis,'' he
said in an interview published last week by the news magazine
Gente. ``The important thing (for me) is not to lose calm, to be a
good pilot in a storm.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0037 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 1215EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Spain-RailStrike     01-07 0132</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Spain-Rail Strike,0134</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rail Strike Reduces Service in Spain</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MADRID, Spain (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A strike by engineers of the national
railway RENFE reduced service between major cities Sunday as
Spaniards returned home after the Epiphany holiday, management and
union officials said.
   The 24-hour strike, the third since Christmas, forced RENFE to
cancel international service to all cities except Lisbon and Geneva.
   RENFE officials said 53 domestic intercity trains ran, far fewer
than normal, while commuter train service was reduced by 30 percent.
   Management said about 15 percent of the engineers struck, but
union representatives put the figure at 60 percent.
   Management and unions that represent the majority of RENFE's
50,000 employees oppose the strike because the engineers are
seeking to negotiate a pay increase separate from the existing
collective bargaining agreement.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0038 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 1225EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-EastGermany Bjt   01-07 0629</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-East Germany, Bjt,0648</SECOND>
<HEAD>Opposition Coalition Crumbling After Only Three Days</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CAROL J. WILLIAMS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WEST BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A coalition created by six East German reform
movements to challenge the Communists crumbled Sunday just three
days after being formed, underscoring the difficulties
pro-democracy forces face in May elections.
   While Communist Party leader Gregor Gysi kicked off his party's
campaign in Potsdam, one of the pro-democracy groups announced it
was leaving the coalition, and the largest group said it preferred
to run candidates independently.
   The Communist Party has been stripped of its constitutional
mandate to rule and has been tarnished by corruption scandals, but
the lack of a credible alternative has left it in control of the
government and better positioned for the election than the
fractured opposition.
   Massive street demonstrations and the exodus of thousands forced
the Communists to grant historic concessions last year, including
the promise of free elections May 6.
   Dozens of citizens' groups pressing for social, political,
environmental and economic reforms have sprung up since the Oct. 18
removal of Communist leader Erich Honecker and the nation's turn
toward democracy.
   Social Democratic leader Steffen Reiche said Thursday his party
had joined with New Forum, Democratic Awakening, Democracy Now, the
Initiative for Peace and Human Rights, and the United Left to form
Election Alliance 90.
   But the United Left announced Sunday it had withdrawn from the
coalition, telling East Germany's official ADN news agency that the
group had been ``misleadingly presented'' in the announcement
Thursday.
   Bernd Gehrkes of United Left said his group was open to other
alliances ``if suitable common policies can be worked out.''
   New Forum, the largest of the pro-reform groups with more than
200,000 members throughout East Germany, held a strategy congress
in Leipzig over the weekend and announced its union with the other
groups was limited.
   The 150 New Forum delegates said the election of individual,
independent candidates was preferable to voting for political
parties or alliances, and that New Forum candidates would rather
run alone.
   Regulations on campaigning and balloting are to be set out under
a new election law, a draft of which is expected to be published
before Parliament meets Thursday.
   Differences among opposition groups also have become apparent
during the weekly negotiations among the various reform movements,
the Communists and other political parties.
   The confrontation between the fractured opposition groups and
the Communists could result in collapse of the talks and further
destabilization of Premier Hans Modrow's transitional government.
   The talks began Dec. 7 to provide a forum for drafting reforms
and airing the views of citizens' groups that have no
representation in the government.
   Democratic Awakening has threatened to pull out of them Monday
unless Modrow's government shows proof the former state security
force has been disbanded.
   New Forum said it, too, would leave the talks if Parliament acts
to form a secret police force before the elections.
   ADN reported in December that the government had abolished the
once-feared secret police agency. But media reports have since
contended some armed units continue to operate.
   Modrow said in an interview Sunday with Austrian television that
a security force is needed to prevent the spread of right-wing
extremism in East Germany.
   Communists have made the recent rise in neo-Nazi incidents a
major theme of the election campaign and an argument against
reunification with West Germany.
   A ``greater Germany'' would awaken concerns in the rest of
Europe, Modrow told Austrian television.
   Opposition forces consider Modrow's Cabinet to have limited
authority because it was chosen by a Communist-controlled
Parliament that was not democratically elected.
   New Forum also insisted during the meeting in Leipzig that
delegates should be assigned to government ministries and
commissions to give the opposition a voice in national affairs
prior to the elections.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0039 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 1253EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-VideoRebellion     01-07 0442</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Video Rebellion,0454</SECOND>
<HEAD>Would-Be Buyers of Video Recorders Lay 5-Day Siege to Russian
Stores</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CAREY GOLDBERG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hundreds of people clamoring to buy imported VCRs
surrounded stores in a Russian city for five days, and some even
staged a hunger strike and protests demanding the chance to buy the
precious goods, a newspaper said Sunday.
   It was the latest show of discontent among Soviets, who are
deprived of many consumer goods.
   The newspaper Sovietskaya Rossiya described the incident in the
Russian city of Yaroslavl as a ``video uprising.''
   The disturbance began when word went out that imported VCR's for
workers who had earned foreign currency had been delivered to a
store in Yaroslavl, an industrial city about 125 miles northeast of
Moscow.
   About 200 people immediately surrounded the store and sat
through the night, demanding they be given the chance to buy the
VCR's as well. Two other stores that also received shipments were
similarly besieged, the newspaper said.
   At dawn of the fourth day, the angry residents launched a
protest on the central town square. Eventually, city authorities
persuaded the workers who were to receive the VCRs to share some of
their spoils with the public, the newspaper said.
   But when the store at the center of the turmoil did not
immediately begin selling some of its 158 VCRs to all customers the
next day, a group of citizens declared a hunger strike.
   Finally, after five days of turmoil, a happy buyer walked out of
the store with the first VCR, called the local TV station and
declared: ``Victory! The Panasonic is in my hands!''
   Sovietskaya Rossiya said this was the first time in Yaroslavl
history that videocassette recorders were sold freely to the public.
   Traditionally, imported electronic goods have been quietly
distributed only to the party and government elite or sold on the
black market, where a VCR can cost as much as $6,400.
   These days, under the Kremlin's economic reforms, factories that
earn foreign currency are generally allowed to decide for
themselves how to spend it, and they frequently buy Western
consumer goods for their workers.
   Residents of the central Russian city of Sverdlovsk took their
frustration to the streets in similar unrest Dec. 29, when a crowd
upset by the shortage of vodka gathered downtown and halted city
transport.
   Communist Party officials soothed them and flooded the stores
with vodka, and the crowd dispersed when people rushed off to buy
their bottles, the newspaper Rabochaya Tribune, or Worker's
Tribune, reported.
   The Sovietskaya Rossiya story did not specify which days the
``video uprising'' took place but indicated the disturbance had
ended recently.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0040 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 1257EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BerlinWall     01-07 0367</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Berlin Wall,0378</SECOND>
<HEAD>Police Move to Protect Crumbling Berlin Wall</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-East Germany, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TONY CZUCZKA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WEST BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Tourists have chiseled so many souvenirs out
of the Berlin Wall that some sections are in danger of collapsing,
and police have had to cordon off one especially hard-hit area near
the Brandenburg Gate.
   The East German government plans eventually to tear down the
entire wall and replace it with normal border markings, President
Manfred Gerlach disclosed in an interview last week. But free-lance
demolition work has already proceeded on the 100-mile border
barrier, especially on the West Berlin side.
   East German border guards on Sunday welded steel bars over a
gaping hole near the Brandenburg Gate to shore up the reinforced
concrete structure.
   West Berlin police put up crowd control barriers Saturday around
the most damaged sections to keep adults and children from climbing
inside giant holes carved out of a double-walled segment. Police
cited a danger of collapse.
   Once covered by graffiti, the wall has been chipped bare at the
Brandenburg Gate, the 18th-century arch that now symbolizes German
unity.
   The wall has also taken a beating at Checkpoint Charlie, the
famed intra-Berlin crossing, but police said they do not fear a
collapse there.
   On Sunday, onlookers and chippers on the West Berlin side booed
when East German border guards welded steel bars over a 7-foot-high
hole at the Reichstag, the former seat of Germany's parliament near
the Brandenburg Gate.
   Enterprising vendors have been selling pieces of the wall for up
$30 and even rent hammers and chisels for do-it-yourself chipping.
   But each wall chunk removed means lost business for East Germany.
   An East German company said last month it plans to raise Western
currency by selling sections of the wall removed from the
Brandenburg Gate and Potsdamer Platz, a square that was the hub of
1920s Berlin.
   Profits from sales are to go to humanitarian causes.
   Communist East German authorities have punched dozens of
crossings into the wall since their decision Nov. 9 to open borders
to the West, The action was the result of a sudden and peaceful
popular revolution that drummed hard-line Communist leaders out of
power.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0041 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 1258EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-EasternEurope-Debt     01-07 0852</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Eastern Europe-Debt,790</SECOND>
<HEAD>Market Weak on East European Debt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CARL HARTMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Eastern European governments have fallen in
love with free markets, but there's at least one free market that
doesn't love them.
   The more democratic governments that have taken over from the
hard-line communists in Eastern Europe are still liable for the
debts incurred primarily during the 1970s when Western bankers
thought the Soviet bloc was a good credit risk.
   But there is waning hope among Western financial dealers that
the loans will ever be paid in full, even as Western governments
are seeking ways to support the democracy movement so that Western
bankers and businesses will invest in Eastern Europe.
   Western bankers fear the new Eastern European governments will
set their sights more on internal development programs and less on
paying off old debts.
   The old debts of Poland and some other Eastern European
countries are bought on the so-called secondary market by
speculators who want to collect the interest still paid on them by
the borrowers.
   Speculators also hope that they can sell the debt at a higher
price or that some day the debtor government will pay in full.
   Last July Polish debt was selling for as much as 41 cents on the
dollar of the debt's original value. But Friday Polish debt was
selling at just 17.5 cents on the dollar, and the debts of Hungary
and Bulgaria have started to show signs of weakness.
   The debt of Yugoslavia, a communist-ruled country outside the
Soviet bloc, has been sharply devalued.
   Keith Fogarty, managing director of Dillon, Read International
Finance, estimated that Poland owes $6 billion to $7 billion to
private creditors in other countries. For the past few years these
debts have been trading on the secondary market at 35 cents to 45
cents on the dollar.
   ``Then last fall the Poles sent out a telex saying they could
not pay the full interest anymore _ only about 15 percent of it,''
Fogarty said in an interview. The Poles said they pay the remainder
of the interest later, but financial markets are dubious.
   Fogarty said Poland has many other pressing needs for the hard
foreign currency _ yen, dollars or West German marks _ in which the
interest must be paid. But it has few ways to earn that money.
   It needs foreign currency, for example, to buy equipment for
farms that have been much neglected. Partly as a result of that
neglect, it has little food to sell. The United States and Western
Europe are sending relief shipments.
   Other experts point out that the new Polish government, the
first non-communist authority in Eastern Europe in 40 years, is led
by people who were active in the Solidarity trade union. They would
not want to be seen paying out large sums to financiers at a time
when workers are being thrown out of jobs and paying high prices
for necessities.
   For their parts, the new governments in Poland and other
countries are eagerly freeing the prices of goods from traditional
communist controls and letting them find their own level on the
market.
   The new governments hope the inevitable price rises will bring
more supplies. That would ease the equally traditional communist
scarcity of food and other basic products.
   The price of a loaf of bread in Poland, which has taken the lead
in opening up to the market, has just gone up from the equivalent
of 9 cents to 14 cents.
   Most of the Polish and other East European debt being traded was
money lent by private banks in West Germany, France and Japan, with
a small share from American bankers. Many of those bankers believed
the Soviet Union ultimately would be responsible for Polish debt,
but in the early 1980s Moscow made it plain that it would not.
   The Central Intelligence Agency estimated that the Soviet Union
owed $42.3 billion in the West at the end of 1988, about as much as
Poland. But Soviet debts are not much traded.
   Unlike Poland, Yugoslavia and many Third World countries the
Soviet Union has always kept up with its payments _ it has vast
resources of gold and petroleum that produce hard currency.
   Yugoslav debt was selling Friday at 52.5 cents on the dollar,
according to Dillon, Read.
   Paul Masco, a trader at Salomon Brothers, said that Yugoslav
debt had sold for as little as 40 cents on the dollar. It rose to
57 cents last fall, after the Yugoslav government started a program
of buying some of it back in Yugoslav currency at prices
advantageous to creditors. Now Yugoslavia is in trouble and the
price has fallen again.
   Masco said Hungarian debt had been trading at par, but recently
it fell to 98 cents or 99 cents on the dollar because of the
expectation that Hungary will want to borrow a lot more money.
There is some doubt about the country's ability to handle a lot of
new debt, he added.
   According to the World Bank, Hungary already owed private
creditors more than $13 billion at the end of 1988.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0042 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 1336EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Lebanon     01-07 0528</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lebanon,0546</SECOND>
<HEAD>PLO Separates Warring Shiite Factions; Combat Flares Across Green
Line</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By FAROUK NASSAR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BEIRUT, Lebanon (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Christian troops and Moslem militiamen
battled with mortars and tank fire across Beirut's dividing Green
Line for a second day Sunday, while hundreds of PLO guerrillas were
deployed to stop militia battles in south Lebanon.
   No casualties were reported from the fighting in Beirut or the
duels between the Iranian-backed Hezbollah, or Party of God, and
the pro-Syrian Amal militia in south Lebanon.
   The violence in Beirut after a three-month lull raised fears of
renewed carnage in the 14-year-old civil war.
   Thousands of Beirut residents scurried to basements and bomb
shelters as the thunderous blasts of mortar and artillery shells
echoed across the city.
   Moslem militias entrenched in the Ras el-Nabaa neighborhood
accused soldiers of Christian Gen. Michel Aoun of starting the
clash. Aoun's command said in a communique that ``Syria's
surrogates'' were behind the escalation.
   Green Line fighting on Saturday killed two Christian civilians
and wounded two Moslems. The clashes also forced the closing of the
only gateway between the Moslem and Christian sectors of the
capital. Police said it was the gravest violation of a cease-fire
called by the Arab League on Sept. 22.
   That truce halted six months of murderous artillery duels
between Aoun's forces and the Syrian army, which Aoun has vowed to
drive from Lebanon.
   ``The accelerating tempo of the violations is alarming,'' said a
police spokesman, who cannot be named in line with standing rules.
``There is no cohesive mechanism to curb the breaches.''
   The hostilities reflect a deepening political crisis resulting
from Aoun's defiance of the government of President Elias Hrawi,
elected by parliament Nov. 24.
   Hrawi was elected as part of an Arab League peace plan that Aoun
refused to accept. He opposed the plan because it did not include a
deadline for the withdrawal of Syria's 40,000 troops from Lebanon.
   Also at war are Amal and Hezbollah, Shiite Moslem militias who
have been battling two years for domination of Lebanon's 1.2
million Shiites.
   Iran's deputy foreign minister, Mohammad Ali Besharati, arrived
in the Syrian capital Saturday, seeking a settlement to the latest
round of fighting, which has killed at least 77 people and wounded
275 wounded since Dec. 23.
   The PLO sent in 400 guerrillas Sunday to reinforce a 300-strong
force dispatched last week to separate Amal and Hezbollah fighters,
police said.
   The PLO guerrillas fanned out in a two-mile buffer zone between
Hezbollah's front lines in the village of Kfar Milki and Amal's
forces in the adjacent village of Kfar Hatta, police reported.
   The guerrillas, equipped with jeep-mounted anti-aircraft guns
and shoulder-fired armor piercing rockets, ignored warning shots
from Hezbollah fighters and set up checkpoints 20 yards from the
entrance to each village.
   Both sides had been pounding each other with rockets and other
artillery but stopped after the guerrillas moved in.
   Police said the PLO apparently is seeking to prevent either
Shiite faction from capturing territory that would give it direct
access to the Palestinian refugee camps of Ein el-Hilweh and Mieh
Mieh.
   The camps are PLO chairman Yasser Arafat's main strongholds in
Lebanon.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0043 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 1405EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Liberia     01-07 0520</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Liberia,0537</SECOND>
<HEAD>Liberian Refugees Report Troops Attacking Civilians</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MONROVIA, Liberia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Liberians are fleeing across the border
to the Ivory Coast to escape violence resulting from an alleged
coup attempt, and they accuse the military of killing civilians
indiscriminately, it was reported Sunday.
   On Saturday, President Samuel K. Doe warned Liberians to ``be on
the safe side'' and turn in suspected rebels.
   The British Broadcasting Corp. said Sunday that Liberian
refugees who crossed into neighboring Ivory Coast claim soldiers
have opened fire on civilians and killed an unknown number.
   It is difficult to determine the number of Liberians fleeing
because the border area is heavily forested and communications are
poor. Some reports have put the figure as high as 8,000 to 10,000.
   The sparsely populated region 100 miles northeast of Monrovia,
the capital, was placed under a dusk-to-dawn curfew.
   Fighting erupted two weeks ago when Liberia claims about 100
rebels led by a former Liberian civil servant crossed into
northeastern Nimba County from Ivory Coast to overthrow Doe.
   Doe told thousands at a rally in Monrovia on Saturday that
Liberian forces were engaged in a massive search to find remaining
rebels.
   He ordered citizens to inform on the rebels' whereabouts,
``because if we catch them in your home, we will treat you as a
rebel. Therefore, furnish us with information if you want to be on
the safe side.''
   Liberia said the rebels, who call themselves the National
Patriotic Front, killed more than 200 people but that troops were
bringing the situation under control and only a few of the
dissidents remained at large.
   Brig. Gen. Edward Smith, army commander in the embattled Nimba
county, was quoted on the radio as saying that in one border town,
rebels shot to death seven people as they were praying in a mosque.
   Smith also said three identity cards taken from suspected rebels
identified the rebels as being from Ivory Coast.
   Liberia repeatedly has accused Ivory Coast of harboring Doe's
opponents, a charge the Ivorians deny. Ivory Coast President Felix
Houphouet-Boigny reportedly sent a high-level delegation to
Danande, the Ivorian border village from where the dissidents are
said to have crossed into Liberia.
   In Paris, the humanitarian organization Doctors Without Borders
said an evaluation team that flew to the Ivory Coast on Friday
found ``a precarious nutritional situation among the Liberian
refugees,'' most of whom were women, children or elderly people.
   ``The number of wounded people arriving in the Ivory Coast is
not very great for the moment,'' the organization said in a
statement.
   A second three-member team, carrying emergency medical gear, was
being dispatched Sunday night from Paris to Abidjan, the Ivory
Coast capital, the group said.
   The dissidents are led by Charles Taylor, a Liberian government
official from 1980-83. Taylor was accused of embezzling nearly $1
million and fled to the United States, where he was imprisoned
pending extradition. He escaped in 1984.
   His forces appear to have no connection with Liberia's
opposition parties.
   Doe, a former sergeant major, seized power in an April 1980 coup
in which President William Tolbert and most of his political allies
were killed.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0044 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 1432EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-ComputerWorm Bjt   01-07 0813</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Computer Worm, Bjt,0834</SECOND>
<HEAD>Student Charged With Creating Computer Worm Goes on Trial</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By WILLIAM KATES</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SYRACUSE, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A graduate student charged with crippling
a national computer network goes to court this week, and win or
lose, his showcase federal trial will mean more stringent computer
security laws, say industry experts.
   Robert T. Morris Jr., 24, of Arnold, Md., a graduate student
suspended from Cornell University, is the first person to be tried
criminally under the 1986 federal Computer Fraud and Abuse Act.
Jury selection begins Monday.
   Morris is accused of designing and setting loose in November
1988 a rogue program that replicated wildly, immobilizing an
estimated 6,000 computers linked to a research network, including
computers at the National Aeronautics and Space Administration
facility at Moffet Field, Calif., and at the Air Force Logistics
Command at Wright Patterson Air Force Base in Dayton, Ohio.
   The program was originally described as a computer ``virus,''
but experts said it was more properly called a ``worm,'' which
unlike a virus does not need to be in a host program to duplicate
itself.
   Morris, a first-year doctoral student in computer studies, has
never admitted creating the worm or introducing it into the
Internet system. But a Cornell commission concluded Morris created
the program and was guilty of ``reckless disregard'' in doing so.
   Morris, whose father is chief scientist at the government's
National Computer Security Center in Bethesda, Md., faces up to
five years in prison and a $250,000 fine if convicted.
   ``It's a no-lose situation because the trial will showcase the
weaknesses of computer security and current computer security
law,'' said Harold Highland, professor emeritus of computer science
at the State University of New York and editor of Computers &amp;
Security, a trade journal.
   If the government loses, he said, computer security advocates
``will say there is a need for stronger laws. If the government
wins, they'll say he did it because the system is weak and we need
to tighten up the system.''
   Christopher A. Breceda of American Computer Security Industries
Inc., a Nashville, Tenn., maker of security systems, agreed.
   ``Either way it goes, the pure attention is going to fuel the
cry for tougher laws and better security,'' he said. ``Whether
Morris is convicted or not, we win.''
   The 3-year-old federal law makes it a felony to ``intentionally
access a federal interest computer without authorization and alter,
destroy or damage information'' or ``prevent access'' to such
computers.
   The law applies only to U.S. government computers, computers of
financial institutions and networks covering more than one state.
   Joseph B. Tompkins Jr., chairman of the American Bar
Association's Task Force on Computer Crime, is one of numerous
computer crime specialists who have appeared before Congress to
urge passage of an even stronger law.
   In November, Tompkins told a House Judiciary subcommittee the
statute is unclear about whether a hacker can claim he didn't have
malicious intent and that it was an innocent prank or a
demonstration of weaknesses in computer security.
   Morris' attorney, Thomas Guidoboni, raised the question of
intent in a motion seeking dismissal of the indictment. U.S.
District Judge Howard Munson rejected the request.
   It is expected that Guidoboni will focus on intent as Morris'
defense. Several associates have said that Morris created the worm
to call attention to the security shortcomings of the Internet
system but that the program ran amok.
   Eugene Spafford, a professor of computer science at Purdue
University who has written articles on the Morris case and a book
on computer viruses, said that the lack of intent to damage should
not be a defense.
   ``Ten years ago, these kinds of things didn't hurt anybody, but
you have to realize now all the places where computers are used and
the dangers involved in shutting down a system or damaging data,''
said Spafford, who is expected to be a government witness.
   ``There's only a subtle difference between this and a person who
burns down a building and says he didn't mean to do it and says,
`It just got away from me.'''
   Spafford said computer crime losses in the United States total
about $7 billion annually.
   The worm allegedly created by Morris did not destroy any data,
and prosecutors have not put a price tag on the damage. But
Spafford estimated the one-day paralysis cost between $5 million
and $15 million in lost time and in later protective work.
   Spafford also said he believes the case will focus attention on
computer security, but he doesn't think it is going to affect a
public perception that such crimes aren't serious.
   ``There is a kind of sympathy for the hacker. He's seen as a
bored college student or a brillant college student exposing a
weakness or striking a blow against the system,'' said Spafford.
``Nevertheless, all the inconvenience and damage that is caused
fits what I'd call vandalism.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0045 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 1443EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p AM-MassachusettsGovernor     01-07 0778</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Massachusetts Governor,0799</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dukakis The Target In Governor's Race</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DANIEL BEEGAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Gov. Michael S. Dukakis will be the issue in this
year's race for governor even though the unpopular Democrat won't
even be on the ballot.
   Dukakis' popularity took a nosedive after he returned from his
unsuccessful bid for president in 1988 to a state in its worst
financial crisis since the mid-1970s. Its bonds are ranked lowest
in the nation by one rating agency.
   Even former Attorney General Francis Bellotti, a Democrat who
backed Dukakis for the presidency and has been a fixture in state
politics, is running as a self-styled ``outsider.''
   With the party primaries still more than eight months away, the
Democratic race also includes Lt. Gov. Evelyn Murphy and Rep. John
Flood of Canton, a Dukakis critic. Boston University President John
Silber and Boston Mayor Raymond Flynn are considering the
Democratic race. U.S. Rep. Joseph Kennedy has taken himself out of
it.
   The Republican field is led by former federal prosecutor William
Weld and state House Minority Leader Steven Pierce. It also
includes former Rep. Paul Cronin and former Metropolitan District
Commissioner Guy Carbone.
   The fields will probably be narrowed during state political
conventions, in March for Republicans and June for the Democrats.
Both parties require candidates to get the support of at least 15
percent of the convention delegates to win a spot in the Sept. 18
primaries.
   Dukakis took himself out of the governor's race a year ago,
setting the stage for a wide-open election that Republicans say
could be their best chance of recapturing an office they have not
held since 1974.
   That was the year Dukakis defeated Republican incumbent Frank
Sargent. Except for a four-year absence after he was defeated by
Democrat Edward J. King in a primary in 1978, Dukakis has been
governor since.
   Pierce says the state's fiscal mess _ with the budget deficit
still calculated at about $500 million even after a series of sharp
cuts in state spending _ and the failure of Dukakis and the
Democratic-controlled Legislature to solve it will be a focus in
the GOP nomination for governor.
   ``That asbolutely presents us with our best political
opportunity in many years,'' said Pierce, who brought up the issue
of rising state spending and sinking revenues while Dukakis was
running against George Bush.
   Weld announced his bid for the Republican nomination last week.
   ``In 1990, the people of the commonwealth are saying that they
are ready for a change, ready to move beyond the big government
philosophy that has brought us to the brink of fiscal ruin,'' Weld
said.
   Pierce is a veteran legislator, while Weld lost his one bid for
statewide office, an attorney general's race against Bellotti in
1978. He then made a reputation for fighting public corruption as
U.S. attorney for Massachusetts.
   Republicans are not alone in calling for change.
   Bellotti, who served as attorney general for 12 years before
stepping down in 1986, called on voters to ``take back the state''
from ``technocrats and team players'' in his announcement.
   ``I have spent my career threatening the status quo and running
as an outsider,'' Bellotti said, who has run for governor twice
before.
   Flood, House chairman of the Legislature's Taxation Committee,
also sounded an outsider theme when he announced his candidacy in
October.
   ``There are those who say a Democrat cannot win next year's
election for governor of the commonwealth. That will not be the
case if our party embraces new ideas, new directions and, most
important, new leadership for the '90s,'' Flood said.
   Even Murphy, the ``team player'' Bellotti referred to, has
advocated tougher fiscal management than Dukakis.
   Murphy, however, has been the only candidate to join Dukakis in
calling for higher taxes to balance the state's budget and has
campaigned for support among traditional Democratic interest groups
such as public employee unions.
   Before becoming lieutenant governor, Murphy served in Dukakis
administrations as secretary of environmental affairs and as
economic development secretary.
   Silber, a transplanted Texan considered conservative by
Massachusetts Democratic standards, could become the ultimate
outsider candidate, although he is looking for support from some
traditional Democratic powers. They include state Senate President
William Bulger and former Boston Mayor Kevin White, now a BU
faculty member.
   Flynn may be inching closer to seeking the Democratic
nomination, saying recently that he is willing to ``lay it on the
line'' if the Legislature fails to raise taxes to save social
programs and aid to local government. Flynn, while potentially
appealing to liberals on most social issues, opposes abortion, a
position that could give him trouble in a state that polls show is
solidly pro-choice.
 
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0046 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 1452EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Hostages     01-07 0543</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Hostages,0560</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mohtashemi on Hostages, Gulf Relations, Economic Investment</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NICOSIA, Cyprus (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Iranian Parliament member Ali Akbar
Mohtashemi said in an interview released Sunday that Iran does not
want ties with the United States and that the Lebanese have a right
to hold foreign hostages.
   In the interview with the English-language Tehran Times, the
former Iranian foreign minister said Iran is interested in
developing diplomatic relations with all the countries of the world
except the United States, Israel and South Africa.
   Mohtashemi said the holding of foreign hostages in Lebanon was
an internal matter and he believes the Lebanese are within their
rights.
   ``Lebanese Sunnis, Shiites, Druse and Christians are the
hostages of the U.S., Israel and other Western powers,'' Mohtashemi
said. ``So it's their natural right to take hostages to inflict
heavy blows on their enemies.''
   ``No negotiations, but force is the answer to what the enemies
of the Lebanese have done against that deprived nation,'' he said.
   The 18 foreigners held hostage in Lebanon are believed held by
Shiite Moslem groups loyal to Iran. The hostages include eight
Americans, among them Terry Anderson, chief Middle East
correspondent for The Associated Press.
   Anderson was kidnapped March 16, 1985, and is the longest-held
hostage.
   An advance copy of Mothashemi's interview was telexed to The
Associated Press in Nicosia by the newspaper.
   President Hashemi Rafsanjani ousted Mohtashemi as interior
minister after his election last July. Mohtashemi, a leader of a
radical group of clergy, was elected to Parliament in a by-election
last month.
   Before becoming interior minister in 1984, he was ambassador to
Syria and was credited with creating Hezbollah, or Party of God,
the fundamentalist Lebanese Shiite militia believed to be the
umbrella for the groups holding hostages.
   The mothers of two Swiss relief workers who were taken hostage
in Lebanon four months ago arrived in Beirut on Sunday with a
petition signed by 70,000 people urging the men's release.
   Emmanuel Christen and Elio Erriquez worked as orthopedic
technicians at a Red Cross clinic in south Lebanon that provided
artificial limbs to Lebanese and Palestinian war victims.
   No group has claimed responsibility for kidnapping Christen, 32,
and Erriquez, 23. The PLO and Lebanese police contend the pair are
held by the Fatah Revolutionary Council, a breakaway guerrilla
group led by Palestinian terrorist mastermind Abu Nidal. The group
has denied responsibility.
   ``I cannot be pessimistic in thinking of my son's release. I
should always be optimistic,'' Marianne Christen told reporters
upon arrival at Beirut airport. She and Graziella Erriquez planned
to hold a news conference in Beirut on Monday and return to Geneva
on Tuesday.
   On Saudi Arabia, Mohtashemi said that close ties were blocked by
what he called the kingdom's suppression of Iranian-led
demonstrations during the 1987 pilgrimage to Mecca. More than 400
demonstrators, mostly Iranians, died in ensuing violence, and last
year Saudi Arabia executed 16 Kuwaiti Shiites it said confessed to
planting bombs that killed one pilgrim.
   The two events ``bar any Moslem country from having relations
with such a foreign-dependent country,'' Mohtashemi said.
   He said relations with Syria would remain strong and not be
changed by the recent restoration of links between Syria and Egypt.
Syria was Iran's staunchest ally during the Iran-Iraq war, and
Egypt backed Iraq.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0047 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 1503EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Israel-Jordan 1stLd-Writethru a0655 01-07 0542</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel-Jordan, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0655,0556</SECOND>
<HEAD>Troops Kill Gunman on Jordanian Border</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 7 grafs to UPDATE with Jordan comment, official
saying gunman may be responsible for all five attacks; Picks up 5th
graf, `Israel's chief ...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By LOUIS MEIXLER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Soldiers killed an armed infiltrator from
Jordan near an Israeli tourist resort Sunday in the fifth shooting
this year along the countries' border, an army spokesman said.
   Defense Minister Yitzhak Rabin issued a tough statement on
behalf of the government, saying Israel regards Jordan as fully
responsible for any border infiltrations.
   The army spokesman said troops opened fire on a gunman wearing a
Jordanian army uniform near the Hamat Gader sulpher springs park,
five miles east of the Sea of Galilee.
   The spokesman, who under military regulations was not
identified, said the gunman was carrying a U.S.-made M-16 assault
rifle, standard equipment in the Jordanian army. No Israeli
soldiers were reported wounded.
   The gunman carried nine clips of ammunition, four of which were
empty, the spokesman said, adding that he believed it was likely
that the lone gunman was responsible for all five shooting
incidents this year.
   In Jordan, an army official said a conscript from the same area
``was absent since yesterday and had his personal weapon.''
   The official, quoted by the state-run Petra news agency, said
soldiers had searched the area but could not find him.
   Israel's chief of staff, Lt. Gen. Dan Shomron, told army radio
that the infiltration may have been carried out by Palestinian
guerrillas that crossed from a third country into Jordan to attack
Israelis along the border.
   But he also said that the recent spate of attacks could have
been carried out by Jordanian soldiers encouraged by the recent
success of Islamic fundamentalists in Jordan's parliamentary
elections.
   On Friday, Israeli troops patrolling in the same area came under
fire twice. Afterward, the army evacuated dozens of tourists who
had been bathing in the springs or fishing.
   Israel radio reported that radical Palestinians led by Abu Musa,
a Syrian-backed dissident from the PLO, claimed responsibility for
the attack.
   A similar incident occurred in the Hamat Gader area Monday.
   On Thursday, Israeli soldiers opened fire on two men who
appeared to be attempting to infiltrate from Jordan about six miles
south of the Sea of Galilee, and one of the would-be infiltrators
was wounded, the army said.
   In a statement released before the gunman was killed Sunday,
Rabin said: ``Israel views the government of Jordan as responsible
for the prevention of hostile acts against the territory of
Israel.''
   Rabin said the ``army is increasing its activities to prevent
shooting and the infiltration of terrorist squads from the
territory of Jordan into Israel.''
   The statement was released after a Cabinet discussion on the
shooting incidents.
   In Jordan, Foreign Minister Marwan el-Kassem said Israel is
responsible for the shooting incidents and that Jordan has no
desire to increase tensions along the border, Israel's army radio
reported. He spoke prior to the fatal shooting.
   Last year, there were seven incidents along the Jordanian
border, including six infiltrations, the army said.
   Three Israeli soldiers were killed and at least seven soldiers
and civilians wounded in the 1989 incidents, the army said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0048 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 1511EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Nicaragua-US     01-07 0189</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Nicaragua-US,0194</SECOND>
<HEAD>Six Visas Approved For U.S. Diplomats</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MANAGUA, Nicaragua (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The leftist Sandinista government has
approved six entry visas for American diplomats to allow the
minimum number of officers at the U.S. Embassy, an official source
said Sunday.
   Twenty U.S. diplomats were expelled from Nicaragua on Dec. 29 in
retaliation for a raid by U.S. troops on the Nicaraguan
ambassador's residence in Panama City. Nine U.S. diplomats were
left in place, including Charge d'Affaires John Leonard.
   Under international conventions, the minimum number of diplomats
in a foreign mission is 15.
   The Nicaraguan Foreign Ministry source, who insisted on
anonymity, said the six American diplomats were expected to arrive
soon.
   Leonard has been the chief U.S. diplomat in Managua since July
1988, when the Nicaraguan government expelled U.S. Ambassador
Richard Melton and seven other American diplomats, accusing them of
inciting anti-government demonstrations.
   Washington retaliated by expelling the same number of Nicaraguan
diplomats, including Ambassador Carlos Tunnermann.
   In May 1989, Nicaragua expelled two U.S. diplomats, including
one based in Honduras who was on a working visit here, also
accusing them of inciting unrest. Washington again retaliated in
kind.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0049 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 1527EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Noriega-Italy     01-07 0322</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Noriega-Italy,0330</SECOND>
<HEAD>Noriega Was Warned He Risked Same End as Mussolini</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ROME (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Panama's Gen. Manuel Noriega decided to give himself
up after an aide warned he risked the same end as Italy's fascist
dictator, Benito Mussolini, the papal nuncio in Panama was quoted
Sunday as saying.
   Monsignor Jose Sabastian Laboa, the Vatican's representative in
Panama, said Capt. Eliecer Gaitan, Noriega's personal security
chief, helped persuade Noriega to leave the Vatican Embassy,
newspapers reported.
   Gaitan told Noriega they risked the same fate as Mussolini
because Panamanians would one day storm the embassy, Laboa was
quoted as telling Italian journalists in Panama.
   Mussolini was shot and killed and then hanged by his feet in a
public square.
   Laboa has insisted that Noriega left the embassy on his own
accord and previously denied reports he gave Noriega an ultimatum
to leave the mission.
   Laboa said there was never any talk of granting concessions and
that once it was made clear Noriega would not be sent to another
country, it came down to getting him to accept guarantees such as
not facing the death penalty in the United States.
   ``He knows Panamanian prisons, while I told him those in America
have TV and air conditioning,'' the nuncio was quoted as saying in
Turin's La Stampa and other newspapers.
   Laboa said it was his decision to allow Noriega in the embassy
Dec. 24 and that he did not have time to consult with the Vatican.
   ``I asked help from the Lord and understood that the most
important thing was to avoid further combat and that, if Noriega
entered the embassy, the battle was over,'' the nuncio was quoted
as saying.
   Noriega took refuge in the embassy four days after U.S. troops
invaded Panama in an effort to capture him and bring him to the
United States to face drug charges. Noriega left the embassy Jan. 3
and was taken to Miami to face charges.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0050 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 1555EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brite     01-07 0195</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brite,0206</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bright &amp; Brief</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WEWAHITCHKA, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Whoopie-ie-oh! Get along little
crawfish!
   The ranch foreman shaded his eyes from the Florida Panhandle sun
with a rakish cowboy hat, grinned broadly and recounted tales from
the crawfish corral.
   ``Crawfish are easier to round up than cattle are,'' said M-K
Ranch foreman Bryant Copeland, in his native Arkansas drawl.
``Harder to brand, but easier to round up.''
   Copeland allowed how he was only kidding about the branding, but
not the roundups at the M-K ranches. They are done with 40
flat-bottom boats built in Louisiana bayou country where crawfish,
which look like small lobsters, are a staple of the Cajun diet.
   Until five years ago, Copeland had never eaten one of the
freshwater crustaceans. Now, he supervises one of the largest
crawfish-raising operations in the nation.
   Each year, M-K Ranches produce from 850,000 to 1 million pounds
of crawfish, also known as crayfish or ``mud bugs.''
   The switch to aquaculture meant some retraining for hands at the
ranch that had once raised cattle, but Copeland said it's all the
same.
   ``Farming is farming,'' Copeland said. ``It's 24 hours a day,
seven days a week.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0051 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 1557EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Iran-Soviet     01-07 0527</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Iran-Soviet,0545</SECOND>
<HEAD>Iranian Deputy Tells Soviet Demonstrators that Border Protests
Fruitless</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By NEIL MacFARQUHAR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NICOSIA, Cyprus (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An Iranian legislator shouted to
protesters across the Soviet border Sunday that Iran wants closer
relations with them but that border protests are useless, Iran's
official news agency reported.
   About 1,000 demonstraters on the Soviet side of the Araks River,
which forms part of the closed border, chanted Islamic slogans for
two hours Sunday, the Islamic Republic News Agency said.
   The report from the border town of Jolfa said a similar group
gathered on the Iranian bank of the river and ``responded to the
enthusiasm of the Soviet Moslems.''
   Soviet protesters in the republic of Azerbaijan are demanding
freedom to travel to the Iranian region of the same name. Like
Iranians, most residents of Soviet Azerbaijan are Shiite Moslems.
   Soviet officials expressed concern about Islamic fundamentalism
creeping across the border after the Islamic revolution in Iran in
1979.
   The border protests began Dec. 31, and at one point extra Soviet
border guards were deployed to control demonstrators who threatened
to dismantle the border barriers.
   IRNA, monitored in Nicosia, said Karim Shafe'i, representative
from the northwest city of Marand in the national Parliament, used
a loudspeaker to tell Soviets the Iranian people want closer
relations.
   But he called on them to ``safeguard the security of the border
lines,'' the report said.
   It quoted him as saying the protests on the riverbank were
``fruitless and that Soviet Moslems can talk to their officials to
prepare the grounds for visiting Iran.''
   Another IRNA report quoted demonstraters as threatening to build
a bridge across the river with their own hands if their demands for
freer travel were not met.
   It said the demonstraters were demanding the government fulfill
promises made six months ago for freer travel to Iran, especially
to visit religious shrines.
   Tehran radio, also monitored in Nicosia, reported that three
Soviet Moslems crossed into Iran's Azerbaijan over the weekend and
returned home after a daylong visit carrying souvenirs and copies
of the Koran, Islam's holy book.
   The broadcast said the Soviet Azerbaijanis crossed the Araks
River and visited Iranian Moslems in the village of Poldasht on
Saturday.
   It did not say if the men swam the river or used boats.
   Four Soviet youths cut through wire border fences on the river
and swam to the Iranian side a week ago. A fifth companion drowned.
   Tass, the official Soviet news agency, said protesters have
destroyed guard observation towers, electronic alarm equipment and
communications lines along the border since the unrest began.
   It said one person was killed in a clash among protesters but
did not give details.
   The Iranian broadcast coincided with a report on Moscow radio
that the Azerbaijani government has promised to allow more access
to arable land on the banks of the Araks River and take measures to
make it easier to cross the border into Iran.
   Soviet Azerbaijan was acquired by Russia in the 1800s. In 1941,
the Red Army moved into northern Iran and the Soviets set up a
puppet state there. But after an international outcry, the troops
pulled out in 1946.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0052 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 1607EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Soviet-Hermit     01-07 0320</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Hermit,0331</SECOND>
<HEAD>Soviet Soldier Emerges After 42 Years in Woods, Media Say</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY15</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A soldier who claims he went into hiding from
Stalin's secret police 42 years ago has emerged from the woods,
convinced by reports of the Kremlin's reforms that it is finally
safe, Soviet media reported Sunday.
   Ivan Bushilo was a 25-year-old decorated veteran newly returned
home when he ran afoul of Josef Stalin's secret police in 1947,
Soviet TV reported in footage showing the wrinkled but
healthy-looking 68-year-old adjusting to life in his home village
in Byelorussia.
   When his attempts to fight the injustices of the security police
put him in serious danger, Bushilo fled to the Byelorussian woods
and lived off the land in primitive shelters for the next four
decades, Soviet TV said.
   He had almost no human contact except for rare visits from close
relatives, the official news agency Tass reported.
   None of the reports explained how Bushilo could have survived
the cold winters, and they did not say if Soviet officials believed
Bushilo's tale.
   In an interview with the weekly news program Seven Days, Bushilo
said it was reports about President Mikhail S. Gorbachev in
newspapers he was brought that persuaded him to come back.
   Asked why he didn't return earlier, Bushilo said, ``I didn't
come out because I didn't trust anybody. Only now I trust
Gorbachev. And only Gorbachev.''
   Bushilo said he was never sick throughout all those years in the
woods. He survived without a gun, mainly by trapping and fishing
and gathering what the forest would yield.
   Relatives brought him occasional clothes, food and newspapers,
Tass said.
   Bushilo told Soviet TV it was knowing he was right that gave him
the strength to survive.
   ``My truth gave me all the strength I needed,'' the former
peasant said. ``I am not a criminal. I was not hiding from justice,
for some crime, but for the truth.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0053 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 1615EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Noriega-Cuba     01-07 0731</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Noriega-Cuba,0755</SECOND>
<TEXT>
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Noriega Ouster Blow For Castro</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-US-Panama, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAN SEWELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The overthrow of Panamanian Gen. Manuel Antonio
Noriega not only rid the United States of a nettlesome regime in
this hemisphere, but dealt a blow to the nemesis at its back door,
Cuba's Castro government, observers say.
   ``There are many impacts for Castro,'' said Jamie Suchlicki,
director of the Institute of Interamerican Studies at University of
Miami. ``Noriega was an ally of Fidel, so he lost a friend. More
importantly, he lost a place where he could do business.''
   Some ever-hopeful Cuban exiles saw the U.S. invasion and
Noreiga's surrender as a step toward bringing down Castro's
31-year-old government.
   ``The people in Cuba have to be free _ maybe in six months, no
later than one year,'' said Norberto Pino, part of the crowd that
turned out at the federal courthouse Thursday for Noriega's
arraignment on drug charges.
   ``Rent This Ad When Fidel Falls,'' read a banner pulled by a
small plane flying over the courthouse.
   Sen. Bob Graham, D-Fla., noted that the ouster of Noriega
followed the falls of one-party governments in the East bloc,
Castro's cooled relations with reform-minded Moscow, and the rise
of elected governments in Latin America.
   ``With the downfall of yet another dictator, Castro will seem
even more like a relic _ out of step with the times and out of
touch with reality,'' Graham said.
   Panama's new leader, President Guillermo Endara, has said his
government will study the question of Panama's relations with Cuba,
but has other priorities now. But few Cuba-watchers expect Castro
to have keep the advantages he had when Noriega ruled Panama.
   While Suchlicki said Castro is firmly in control of his own
country, he and others identified a variety of likely effects on
Castro of the ouster of Noriega, including:
   _ Loss of a conduit for technology and a range of U.S.-produced
equipment and commodities banned from Cuba because of the U.S.
trade embargo.
   The U.S. Customs Service, indicting three men in 1987 for
violating the U.S. trade embargo with Cuba on selling computer
equipment, said the Cuban Minister of Commerce had set up several
``front companies'' in Panama to get around the embargo.
   Castro has denied Noriega cooperated with Cuba in smuggling
technology. But even common items were getting from the United
States to Cuba via Panama, authorities say.
   _ Potential embarrassment for Castro during Noriega's trial.
   The Miami federal indictment alleges that Castro acted as a
mediator in a 1984 dispute between Noriega and the Medellin Cartel
cocaine traffickers he was supposed to be protecting in Panama.
   There are no details cited in the indictment, and prosecutors
said in 1988 they lacked evidence to indict Castro along with
Noriega. However, some of the government's key witnesses have
claimed first-hand knowledge of Castro's involvement.
   Castro denies that he supports drug trafficking. U.S.
investigators have charged for years, including in a 1982 federal
indictment in Miami of four Cuban officials who were never
prosecuted, that Castro has allowed Cuba to be used for trafficking
to the United States.
   _ Reduced intelligence-gathering.
   ``Castro's embassy in Panama was a major intelligence-gathering
center,'' said Ambler Moss, former U.S. ambassador to Panama.
   _ The loss of another friendly government in this region.
   Since 1979, when pro-Castro governments came to power in
Nicaragua and Grenada, Cuba has seen Jamaica's Michael Manley
government defeated in 1980 elections (Manley at the time blamed
the United States, but won elections last year after promising a
moderate government that will seek cooperation with Washington),
Grenada's Marxist government fall in a 1983 rift capped by the U.S.
invasion, Suriname sever most ties with Cuba in 1983, and general
decreased influence for leftist parties throughout the Caribbean.
   Castro condemned the U.S. invasion of Panama and Moss, now dean
of the Graduate School of International Studies at University of
Miami, said Castro is using the invasion ``as a distracting issue''
at home.
   Cuba's economy is stagnant, and reduced trade with East bloc
countries and, potentially, reduced aid from the Soviet Union will
worsen the economy and could stimulate domestic opposition, the
observers said.
   ``Fidel seems to be still strong and charismatic. Fidel is also
ruthless,'' Suchlicki said.
   ``I don't think the thing is ripe yet,'' he said. ``But after
what we've seen (in Eastern Europe), I hate to be categoric about
anything.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0054 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 1622EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>d a AM-BRF--MissingArt     01-07 0190</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Missing Art,0193</SECOND>
<HEAD>More Indian Art Works Discovered Missing From LA Museum</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Forty-four more pieces of valuable American
Indian art have been reported missing from the Southwest Museum,
bringing the institution's total loss to more than $2 million,
officials said.
   Among the latest items discovered missing are a personally
inscribed Thomas Moran painting that could fetch more than $100,000
at auction and a sacred Zuni wood carving, museum officials said.
Other items include masks, paintings, baskets, carvings and jewelry.
   Museum officials intitially reported 65 items missing. The FBI
has recovered eight of those pieces and has leads on 16 others,
Southwest Museum Executive Director Jerome Selmer said in a recent
interview.
   ``We get the feeling that things are picking up in the
investigation, that more pieces will be recovered soon,'' Selmer
said. ``But we are not working under the illusion that we are going
to get every piece back.''
   Museum officials first became aware art works were missing nine
months ago during an inventory that is continuing of the museum's
200,000 items. They declined to discuss how the artworks might have
left the museum's collection.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0055 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 1618EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Romania-US     01-07 0389</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania-US,0400</SECOND>
<HEAD>Romanian Minister Calls For More U.S. Assistance</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SLOBODAN LEKIC</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUCHAREST, Romania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The foreign minister believes the U.S.
government should be playing a greater role in helping Romania
recover from its pro-democracy revolution, a human rights activist
said Sunday.
   Geri Laber, executive director of the U.S.-based Helsinki Watch
Human Rights organization, also said human rights groups must
ensure that loyalists of former ruler Nicolae Ceausescu receive
fair trials and that laws are drafted to replace the draconian ones
the Communist dictator relied on for 24 years.
   Foreign Minister Sergiu Celac told visiting Helsinki Watch
representatives he was ``very disappointed that the United States
government was so slow in responding to the situation in Romania,''
Laber said.
   Celac indicated that the nation needs a ``counterbalance'' to an
expanded Soviet presence, following a visit Saturday by Soviet
Foreign Minister Eduard Shevardnadze, according to Laber.
   Under Ceausescu, the Soviet bloc maverick who frequently acted
independently of Moscow, the Soviets had fairly little say in
Romanian affairs.
   Shevardnadze said his country supported ``the solidarity of the
Soviet and Romanian peoples'' and pledged ``wide-ranging
assistance,'' including immediate supplies of sorely needed oil and
gas.
   Several senior Western government officials also have visited
Bucharest since Ceausescu's overthrow Dec. 22.
   French Premier Roland Dumas and West German Foreign Minister
Hans Dietrich Genscher are scheduled to arrive this month. But
despite considerable food and medical assistance from the United
States, Rep. Frank Wolf, R-Va., has been the highest-ranking U.S.
official to visit so far.
   Laber said, ``As soon as I get back to the U.S., I intend to
pressure the State Department into moving quickly on indicating
unequivocally its concern for developments in Romania.''
   On another matter, Laber said Helsinki Watch was ``very critical
of the way Ceausescu and his wife Elena were executed. Although we
deplore their crimes, we feel they should have been given a fair
hearing, with the right to bring witnesses and present evidence''
in their defense.
   The two were executed Dec. 25 by firing squad immediately after
being tried in secret by a military court.
   ``Because this happened it is even more incumbent on the
government to ensure that the (arrested secret police officers) are
accorded fair trials,'' and the Helsinki group plans to send
observers to monitor them, Laber said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0056 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 1623EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-People     01-07 0798</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People,0831</SECOND>
<HEAD>People in the News</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY44</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SANTA YNEZ, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Pop superstar Michael Jackson threw a
party for 80 abused or neglected children at his 3,000-acre ranch.
   Jackson greeted the two busloads of children from the Village of
Childhelp in Beaumont and gave them a tour of his well-stocked game
and toy rooms, and served up a barbecue lunch of hamburgers and
hotdogs under sunny blue skies.
   ``I'm so happy you came and glad you can share all these
pleasures with me,'' Jackson told the kids at lunch Saturday,
accompanied by his pet chimpanzees Max and Alexandria dressed in
blue coveralls and striped T-shirts.
   The party was private and the singer's comments to the children
were relayed through publicist Lee Solters.
   The kids also got to play volleyball and bounce on a trampoline.
The toy room offered an enormous accumulation of playthings Jackson
purchased on his recent 17-month world tour.
   After lunch, Jackson and the kids retired to the ranch's theater
to watch the current hit movies ``The Little Mermaid'' and ``Back
to the Future Part II.'' The children autographed a lifesize cutout
of Jackson and presented it to the singer.
   ``He's getting a big kick. He's like the Pied Piper,'' the
singer's spokesman said.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Pat Sajak made his name and his millions as host
of ``Wheel of Fortune,'' but it was another game show that helped
prod him toward his second marriage.
   Sajak was married New Year's Eve to Lesly Brown, a 24-year-old
model from Maryland whose previous claims to fame were a
lingerie-clad pose in Playboy's ``Women of Washington'' and an
appearance on ``The Dating Game.''
   Their friendship turned to romance in June when Brown got her
Dating Game prize: a chaperoned trip to Mexico with a lucky
bachelor, the couple told People magazine.
   ``Frankly, I was a little annoyed at that,'' Sajak said.
   ``There was definitely borderline jealousy,'' Brown said. ``That
was good.''
   Their old-fashioned wedding in Annapolis, Md., included praise
from the officiating priest for a wife who is silent and keeps a
clean house, People reported.
   ``Lesly swore to keep quiet and clean the toilet every day. I
thought he should say a word about Mop &amp; Glo,'' joked Sajak, who
also is host of a late-night talk show.
   Vanna White, the letter-turner on ``Wheel of Fortune'' and one
of 150 guests at the wedding, said, ``It's a storybook love story.
Pat seems to have been reborn.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>PHILADELPHIA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   ``Glory,'' the Civil War movie starring
Matthew Broderick and Morgan Freeman, has passed muster as
authentic in its depiction of a regiment of black soldiers.
   Two Civil War experts who are sticklers for details found only
minuscule breaches in the film.
   Russ Pritchard, a firearms expert at Philadelphia's Civil War
Library and Museum, said he and flag collector Stan Smullen found
``extraordinarily minor'' flaws during a preview Friday.
   History buffs often have complained about the lack of
authenticity in the treatment of the Civil War on television and in
the movies.
   ``It's an absolute incredible movie,'' Pritchard said.
   ``The combat sequences are the best I've seen in a movie about
the 19th century,'' he said. ``All the uniforms, the accouterments,
the tack on the horses, even what I would call the background
props, they're all great.''
   Pritchard said he and Smullen each noticed a flaw.
   In one scene, recruits were issued Enfield rifled muskets, while
someone called out the serial number of each weapon. The regiment
carried Enfields, Pritchard said, but Enfields had no serial
numbers.
   Smullen pointed out that the regiment's American flags seemed to
have had the stars sewn on. During the Civil War, however, stars
would have been painted on the flags, he said.
   ``Glory'' is the saga of the 54th Massachusetts Regiment, the
most famous black unit of the Civil War. It is the story of the
soldiers' struggle and the regiment's triumph amid the lost battle
of Fort Wagner in 1862.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>PHILADELPHIA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Delores M. Andy was grand marshal of the
high strutting Mummers 90th annual New Years Day parade, which not
only stepped off five days late, but had never before been presided
over by a woman.
   Carrying a dozen long-stemmed roses, Ms. Andy led the string
bands up Broad Street on Saturday.
   ``This is wonderful,'' she said. ``It's a beautiful day.''
   At least 40,000 turned out to see the 12-hour parade that had
been canceled Jan. 1 because of high winds.
   In keeping with the traditional theme song, ``Oh Dem Golden
Slippers,'' most of the Mummers wore their gold-painted shoes as
they entertained crowds who shouted ``Happy New Year'' with their
famous march called a cakewalk.
   Andy, city recreation commissioner, was substituting as grand
marshal for Mayor W. Wilson Goode who was on vacation.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0057 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 1654EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ChildPornography     01-07 0768</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Child Pornography,0791</SECOND>
<HEAD>New York State Court of Appeals Hears Child Pornography Case</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOEL STASHENKO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ALBANY, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   It's against the law in New York to produce,
sell or even mail child pornography. The state's highest court
weighs this week whether it's also illegal to possess it.
   The Court of Appeals will consider the legality of the
indictment of William Keyes of Albany on five counts of promoting a
sexual performance by a child. The charge centers on Keyes'
possession of pornographic magazines and videotapes with such as
``Lolita Colour Special 7'' and ``Wonderboy'' and whether such
possession constitutes promoting a sexual performance.
   The items were found in his home during a police raid in August
1986. He had gotten them from undercover police agents.
   At the time of his arrest, Keyes was on five years' probation
after pleading guilty to promoting a sexual performance by a child.
Because of the prior conviction, Keyes could face a maximum of 3{
to 7 years in prison if convicted on each of the new counts.
   Keyes, 41, has argued that he was wrongly charged with
``promoting'' pornography because he contends he did nothing more
than receive the items from an undercover policeman.
   The prosecutor, George Barber, countered that the decade-old
state law under which Keyes was charged defines ``promoting'' as,
among other things, ``procuring'' pornographic items. Prosecutors
argue that the law indicates that in this case Keyes did
``procure'' the pornography which means he is subject to indictment.
   According to court briefs, Albany detectives found Keyes' home
telephone number on the stall of a movie-viewing booth at a Troy
adult bookstore. Next to the number was written ``Young boys
wanted.'' Authorities said that phone number, and statements Keyes
made to undercover policemen about the best places in Albany to
find underage models, will justify the ``promoting a sexual
preformance'' charge, even if the high court throws out their
argument that even possession is illegal.
   So far, state courts have been of two minds about the legality
of the indictments.
   State Supreme Court Joseph Harris ruled in Albany in June 1987
that the Legislature intend to punish the creators and distributors
of child pornographic materials, not the customers, and he threw
out the indictments. In New York, a Supreme Court is a trial court.
   In November 1987, the midlevel Appellate Division of state
Supreme Court ruled unanimously that the indictments were proper.
   The attorneys who will argue the case before the Court of
Appeals, the state's highest court, agree that the question is
bigger than Keyes' own legal fate.
   In his brief before the court, Barber urged the judges to state
in their decision that neither the state nor federal constitutions
protect the possession of child pornographic materials.
   Keyes' attorney, Terence Kindlon, said Albany County prosecutors
are violating his client's constitutional rights by trying to
equate ``promotion'' with ``possession.''
   A study of New York's penal law, Kindlon said, shows that the
word ``procure'' means to ``go out and get something for someone
else.''
   Kindlon called Keyes ``a good guy'' who acknowledged his problem
with child pornography and was undergoing psychiatric therapy when
approached by Albany policemen about receiving pornographic
materials.
   The items were ``crammed into his hands and he was arrested for
having them,'' Kindlon said.
   ``You go to an Alcoholics Anonymous meeting on the hottest day
in August and stand outside passing out free beers, somebody's
going to drink one,'' he said.
   ``Our statute does not make simple possession of this stuff
unlawful, but they're trying to read into it such a prohibition,''
Kindlon said. ``They're saying the word `procure' means that you
can't have it unless you get it _ that the fact you have it proves
you got it.''
   An attorney for the Manhattan-based Institute for Youth Advocacy
filed a friend-of-the-court brief urging the court to uphold Keyes'
indictment. The institute is affiliated with Covenant House, which
estimates that half the homeless or runaway youths it takes in have
been sexually exploited.
   Barber said 13 states, including Ohio, Illinois, Missouri and
Florida, have expressly outlawed the possession of child
pornography in the past eight years. The U.S. Supreme Court
recently heard oral arguments in a case challenging Ohio's
possession law.
   Keyes, an auto body worker, is described in court papers as
about 80 percent disabled as the result of Vietnam War wounds.
   When he was put on probation after his 1984 conviction, Albany
County Court Judge John Clyne told him: ``There is more to this
life than the sickening, perverted books you have been enjoying on
your own. Read a good novel.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0058 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 1654EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Sudan-TribalConflict     01-07 0211</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Sudan-Tribal Conflict,0216</SECOND>
<HEAD>Gov't to Form Committee to Investigate Tribal Clash</HEAD>
<DATELINE>KHARTOUM, Sudan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Sudanese government said Sunday it
would form a committee to investigate a clash between Arab and
African tribes Dec. 28 which it said left 214 people dead.
   A Cabinet statement said an unspecified number of Sudanese from
the two tribes had been arrested.
   Although the rebel Sudan People's Liberation Army claims that
more than 2,000 southerners of African descent were killed by Arab
militias, the statement said only 214 had been killed and 38
wounded.
   The southern rebels have accused the government of complicity in
the massacre. They said 90 southerners were killed in a police
station where they sought refuge.
   The clash took place Dec. 28 in the Jabalain area, south of
Kosti and about 250 miles south of Khartoum.
   The statement said a high-level official delegation had traveled
to Jabalain and met with representatives of the two tribes.
   Zubair Mohamed Salih, deputy chairman of the 15-man ruling
military council, said a committee will be formed to investigate
the tribal clash.
   The southern rebels are mainly Christians and animists of
African descent. They took up arms against the Arab Moslem majority
government in the north in 1983 for more autonomy and economic
reforms.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0059 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 1709EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Romania 1stLd-Writethru   01-07 0846</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0660,0867</SECOND>
<HEAD>Anti-Communists in Emotional March, Students Rally for Reforms</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 7 grafs to UDATE with report elections might be
delayed; pick up 7th pvs, `They are...' Minor editing thereafter to
conform. ADDS 2 grafs with foreign minister disappointed by lack of
U.S. involvement. No pickup.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos BUC1,2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GEORGE JAHN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUCHAREST, Romania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Thousands of anti-Communists marched
and prayed Sunday for the martyrs of Romania's bloody revolution,
and students rallied in several cities for educational reforms and
a greater say in national affairs.
   Marchers carried white cloth banners with letters in blood-red
paint proclaiming, ``The martyrs want liberty and bread.'' They
knelt repeatedly on the ice-covered sidewalks during their slow,
half-mile procession.
   At sites of particularly heavy fighting, they halted to chant
the Lord's Prayer and cross themselves. Many women wore black
scarves, and some demonstrators carried lit funeral tapers.
   The march was called by the Peasant and Christian Democratic
parties to honor those who fell in the battle against loyalist
forces of executed Communist dictator Nicolae Ceausescu.
   The once-banned parties, which have joined forces in preparation
for promised elections in April, have warned against a renaissance
of the Communist Party, which has been in de facto dissolution
since Ceausescu's downfall.
   The opposition groups also have expressed concern that the April
election date is too soon to allow parties other than the
provisional government, the National Salvation Front, sufficient
time to prepare. The Front's chairman and interim president, Ion
Iliescu, said late Saturday they could be postponed, the national
Rompres news agency reported.
   The Peasant and Christian Democratic parties also have accused
the Front, which includes several former Communists, of being a
front for communism. Those fears were in evidence Sunday.
   ``They are calling for a new Communist Party,'' said Constantin
Dimitrescu, alluding to tentative calls by some Communists to
reform as a Democratic Socialist Party. ``We say to that _ the wolf
has changed its fur but not its morals.''
   Less than two miles away, about 2,500 students met for a rally
at the Polytechnical Institute to press for reform of Ceausescu's
heavily indoctrinated education system.
   Students read an 11-point program addressed to Premier Petre
Roman, demanding autonomy for universities, more student say in
determining the curriculum and postponement of examinations
scheduled for Jan. 25.
   ``We believe the prime minister will listen to our opinions
because he, too, is one of us,'' Bogdan Constantinescu, a
mechanical engineering student, told the cheering crowd.
   Roman previously taught hydraulic engineering at a university
before his appointment last month as government head.
   ``We don't want to waste time on subjects such as political
economy...(and) Marxism _ instead we should be able to choose the
subjects we want to take,'' Constantinescu said.
   During Ceausescu's 24-year reign, all students were required to
take political subjects extolling the virtues of ``scientific
socialism.''
   Slogans reading ``Freedom to the Students,'' ``No Politics,''
and ``University Autonomy,'' were draped across the rally hall,
where Constantinescu announced the formation of a free students
trade union. It will press student demands within Romania's newly
established free trade union federation.
   Razvan Rusovici, a 21-year-old aeronautical engineering student,
expressed hope for the future. ``We want to be more like our
Western brothers and study what we really need and not what some
ignorant dictator imagines we need,'' he said.
   Thousands of other students held gatherings in Braila and
Galatia, about 120 miles northeast of the capital, and in
Timisoara, the cradle of the revolution, about 300 miles northwest
of Bucharest.
   Nicolae Costel, an official of the Christian Democratic Party,
described the pro-democracy demonstrations as among the most
widespread since Ceausescu's overthrow Dec. 22 and execution three
days later.
   Costel said in an interview that the rallies outside Bucharest
were called to demand greater student representation on the
National Salvation Front.
   The Front has decided to run on a democratic platform in the
elections, despite initially saying it would not field candidates.
   Sunday's newspapers continued attempts to determine what
happened to the bodies of hundreds of protesters believed killed
Dec. 16-17 by pro-Ceausescu armed units in Timisoara, site of the
first major demonstrations against Ceausescu.
   Romania Libera, in an article headlined ``Where are the dead
people from Timisoara?'' said most of the bodies were missing,
including 70 bodies in the Timisoara Departmental Hospital morgue
it said had disappeared after being loaded onto refrigerated trucks.
   The paper quoted Lorin Fortuna, president of the Timisoara
council of the National Salvation Front, as saying he is convinced
that many bodies were taken to Bucharest and cremated.
   Foreign Minister Sergiu Celac told visiting Helsinki Watch
representatives he was disappointed that the U.S. government was so
slow in responding to Romania's situation, said Gary Laber,
executive director of the U.S.-based human rights organization, on
Sunday.
   Soviet Foreign Minister Eduard Shevardnadze visited Saturday,
and French Premier Roland Dumas and West German Foreign Minister
Hans Dietrich Genscher are scheduled to visit this month. But
despite considerable food and medical assistance from the United
States, the highest-ranking U.S. official to visit so far has been
Rep. Frank Wolf, R-Va..
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0060 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 1718EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-FosterHomeFire 1stLd-Writethru a0646 01-07 0433</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Foster Home Fire, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0646,0439</SECOND>
<HEAD>Six Children, Woman Killed In Alabama Foster Home Fire</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: UPDATES throughout with seventh victim identified, smoke
detectors required but reports conflicting on whether they were
present, other detail. No pickup. Children's names, with two
Kimberlys and two Jessies, boy named Marketta, are all cq as
provided by state official.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto MY2</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CLAYTON, Ala. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Fire swept through a private foster home in
a rural area early Sunday, killing six young children placed there
by state welfare authorities and a 66-year-old woman, officials
said.
   Barbour County Coroner David Childs said the owners of the
house, Robert and Lois Mitchell, escaped the 2 a.m. blaze
uninjured, as did their three children and two other foster
children.
   Alabama Fire Marshal John Robison said the cause of the fire
that destroyed the large one-story house near the Bakerhill
community was not immediately known. An investigation was
continuing, he said.
   Childs said Mrs. Mitchell told him she thought the fire started
in an area around the hot water heater, adding that the home was
not being heated. The victims' bodies were badly burned and would
be sent to a state forensics laboratory, he said.
   The fire was initially reported as a possible explosion, but
Childs said there was none.
   He identified the children killed in the fire _ two girls and
four boys _ as Kimberly Gilbert, 8; her brother Jessie, 10;
Kimberly Walker, 5; and her brothers Larry, 10, Jessie, 7, and
Marketta, 4.
   The seventh victim was Florene Burgess, 66. The Mitchells had
taken her in ``just out of the goodness of their hearts,'' Childs
said.
   The children who died in the fire had been assigned to the home,
one of 4,000 private foster homes in the state, by the state
Department of Human Resources, he said.
   All homes in the state, not just foster homes, are supposed to
have smoke detectors, Robison said.
   He said initial reports from the scene indicated the Mitchell
home may not have had detectors, but Mike Gibson, a spokesman for
the state Department of Human Resources, said he understood there
were detectors there. All private foster homes in the state are
inspected before they are certified, he said.
   ``This is a case of folks who were just trying to help people,''
Childs said. ``There is no indication of foul play. She took all
the children to church on Sunday and kept them in good shape and
all.''
   The surviving children, whose ages were not immediately known,
were identified as Eric Mitchell, Michael Mitchell, Michelle
Mitchell, Kevin Boyer and Brenda Gilbert.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0061 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 1723EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-NursingMurders     01-07 0511</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Nursing Murders,0528</SECOND>
<HEAD>Former Nurse's Aide On Trail For Patient Death</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PALATKA, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A slightly built former nurse's aide goes
on trial Monday for first-degree murder in the death of one of
seven elderly patients he's alternately confessed to and denied
killing.
   Lawyers will begin Monday with jury selection for Jeffery
Feltner's trial. If convicted, Feltner could go to the electric
chair.
   Feltner, 27, stands 5 feet 3 inches tall and weighs barely 100
pounds. When he made anonymous phone calls to officials saying the
seven patients did not die of natural causes but were strangled,
some people didn't believe his tale.
   Although investigators were initially skeptical, authorities now
say they believe Feltner asphyxiated the seven patients over an
18-month period to ease their suffering.
   The trial will look only at the death of Sara Abrams, 75, at New
Life Acres nursing home in Melrose on Feb. 10, 1988. Feltner also
faces a murder charge in Volusia County for the July 11, 1989,
death of Doris Moriarty, 83, at Clyatt Memorial Center in Daytona
Beach.
   Prosecutors say they are continuing their investigation of the
remaining five deaths: four at New Life Acres from Feb. 7 to April
6, 1988; and one at Bowman's Nursing Center in Ormond Beach on July
27, 1989.
   A plea bargain fell apart late last Friday afternoon, when
Circuit Judge E.L. Eastmoore refused to accept a deal that would
have had Feltner plead guilty to second-degree murder in exchange
for no more than 40 years in prison.
   ``He was willing to bite the bullet,'' said defense lawyer
Howard Pearl, who said Feltner insists he didn't kill anyone.
   Feltner's mother, Shirley Hartman, said her son grew up a loner.
She and his father split up three months before he was born, she
said.
   She moved to Melrose in Putnam County in 1979, where Feltner
graduated from Interlachen High School. In 1986, Hartman helped
Feltner get a job at New Life Acres, where she worked as a nursing
assistant.
   In June 1988, Feltner anonymously called a Gainesville
television station and a mental health crisis center and told them
he had killed five patients.
   But when questioned by detectives, Feltner denied it.
   He eventually pleaded guilty to making harassing phone calls,
trespassing and making a false statement. He served a 127-day
sentence and was freed Nov. 19, 1988.
   Feltner followed a similar pattern last summer. He told a
Daytona Beach TV station, a mental health unit and his roommate
about the most recent death.
   This time, when Daytona Beach detectives questioned him, Feltner
told them about all seven killings, explaining that he did it to
relieve the victims' suffering. But now he denies the killings.
   Both of the Daytona victims had been cremated, as were two of
the four Melrose patients.
   Officials received permission from Abrams' daughter to exhume
her remains, and prosecutors said an autopsy gave them the evidence
they needed to back up Feltner's confessions. Abrams had broken
ribs that showed she could have died when someone held her down
while suffocating her, prosecutors said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0062 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 1750EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Cult-Girl     01-07 0541</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Cult-Girl,0559</SECOND>
<HEAD>Former Young Cult Member Tells of Drinking, Abuse</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Cult Deaths</HEAD>
<DATELINE>KANSAS CITY, Mo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A cult leader charged with murder in the
slayings of five followers often beat children in the group and
once planned an armed raid on a historic religious temple, said a
young girl who lived among them.
   ``They would go to, like, rifle ranges and shoot. They had
knives, too. I know they had machetes,'' said Bonnie Olivarez, ho
was 11 when she lived with the group in the spring of 1988.
   ``It was kind of like normal at first and then it got really
weird,'' said Bonnie, who was with her mother in the cult and now
lives with her father in the Kansas City area.
   ``They were all religious and everything, but they didn't love
me,'' she told The Kansas City Star in an interview published
Sunday.
   The girl's mother, Deborah Sue Olivarez, is among 13 members of
the cult charged with murder or conspiracy in the shootings of a
five-member family whose bodies were found in a barn on the
Kirtland, Ohio, farm where the group once lived.
   The group's leader, Jeffrey Lundgren, his wife and their
19-year-old son were arrested Sunday at a motel near San Diego.
Eight other people, including Bonnie's mother, were arrested last
week.
   Two of Lundgren's followers remained at large Sunday.
   The victims, found shot to death last week in a barn on the farm
in Kirtland, are believed to be Dennis Avery, his wife, Cheryl, and
their three young daughters. Authorities believe they died in
April, shortly before the group left Ohio.
   Bonnie recalled that the group drank a lot and prepared for an
assault on the Kirtland Historic Temple Site on May 3, 1988. The
temple belongs to the Reorganized Church of Jesus Christ of Latter
Day Saints, which Lundgren and his followers quit to form their own
group.
   In the days leading up to the planned assault, men in the cult
donned camouflage clothing and took target practice, Bonnie said.
On the morning of the planned attack, Lundgren went into the woods
and came back saying God had told him to call off the operation,
she said.
   Much of Bonnie's story was confirmed by Kirtland Police Chief
Dennis Yarborough, who told the newspaper that he got an anonymous
tip the group planned to seize the temple, which is based in
Independence and shares some beliefs with the Mormon Church based
in Salt Lake City.
   Lundgren kept a sizable and legal arsenal, Yarborough said. The
weapons included bows and arrows, .22-caliber rifles and handguns,
he said. Bonnie said the cult had about 20 rifles and handguns.
   At night and on weekends in 1988, the group donned military
fatigues and army boots and watched violent films, held firing
practice in the barn and practiced how to recognize types of
weapons and load and unload them in the dark, investigators said.
   Bonnie said children in the cult were subject to ``sessions''
with Lundgren if they misbehaved, though she never had such a
session.
   ``In a session he would yell at the top of his lungs,'' she
said. ``He would hit you, and not with just his hands and stuff. He
would use poles, too.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0063 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 1808EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-WitchDoctors     01-07 0268</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Witch Doctors,0274</SECOND>
<HEAD>Witch Doctors, Sorcerers Flock To Oil-Rich Gulf Coast</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ABU DHABI, United Arab Emirates (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Self-proclaimed sorcerers
and witch doctors have flocked to this Persian Gulf country,
promising oil-rich natives that they can cure diseases and solve
other problems for large fees, officials say.
   A police source said Sunday that an Indian sorceress who claimed
the power of healing diseases was arrested. Two African witch
doctors also were arrested in the United Arab Emirates recently
after they claimed powers through their special relations with
demons, the source said.
   ``The three cases discovered were but a few of a host of a new
generation of witch doctors attracted by the money of the oil-rich
Gulf,'' said the source, who could not be named under standing
rules.
   The Indian, who was arrested Saturday, was identified as Faridah
bin Amirjan. She claimed she could cure diseases and solve social
problems merely by reading verses from the Moslem holy book, the
Koran, for a reward to be decided by the patient.
   The two others were identified as Senegalese Mossa Mohammed
Kawaji and Nigerian Dam Abu Bakr Mousa.
   Kawaji, who claimed to heal diseases and find stolen money, was
arrested in Sharjah. He was quoted as telling police he knew ``all
the 25 groups of demons,'' claiming they resembled black cats and
lions.
   In one case, Kawaji was alleged to have charged a person seeking
a cure $10,000 and 222 grams of gold.
   The Nigerian asked a person for $25,000, claiming he would pay
him back with $250 million, the police source said. No money was
returned, he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0064 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 1822EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-DominicanRepublic     01-07 0228</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Dominican Republic,0232</SECOND>
<HEAD>12 Illegal Immigrants Drown When Boat Capzizes</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RUDDY L. GONZALEZ</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SANTO DOMINGO, Dominican Republic (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A boat carrying 50
people hoping to enter the United States illegally capsized in
heavy seas off the Dominican eastern coast. At least 12 people
drowned, a newspaper reported Sunday.
   The daily Listin Diario said another 15 of those aboard were
able to swim to shore in the Higuey province, about 140 miles east
of Santo Domingo, the capital.
   Military planes searched Sunday for the 23 people still missing
following the accident Wednesday night just three miles from shore,
said a Dominican navy news release.
   The release also said another such boat believed to be carrying
25 Dominicans caught fire Friday in waters off San Pedro de
Macoris. The navy said one body was recovered but no survivors were
found.
   The accidents in Higuey and in San Pedro de Macoris, 45 miles
east of Santo Domingo, were the first such reported this year.
   About 200,000 illegal immigrants try to sail from the Dominican
Republic to Puerto Rico each year through the Mona Passage, a
100-mile wide-channel that separates the Dominican Republic from
Puerto Rico. A navy report says 47 people drowned when their boats
capsized last year, and 2,779 people were arrested by Dominican
authorities.
   Thousands more are arrested and deported by U.S. Immigration and
Naturalization officials.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0065 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 1837EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Peru-DrugSummit     01-07 0286</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Peru-Drug Summit,0293</SECOND>
<HEAD>Garcia Says He'll Attend Summit If Bush Withdraws Troops From
Panama</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LIMA, Peru (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Alan Garcia said Sunday he will
attend a drug summit in February with President Bush if the United
States withdraws its troops from Panama by then.
   Following the U.S. intervention in Panama Dec. 20, Garcia cut
off joint U.S.-Peruvian anti-drug patrols in his country and
announced he would not attend the summit, saying he would not meet
with the leader of an ``invading nation.''
   On Dec. 26 Peru resumed the joint patrols.
   Government officials said last week that Peru would send a
delegation to the summit with Bush and Presidents Virgilio Barco of
Colombia and Jaime Paz Zamora of Bolivia, but Sunday's announcement
was the first signal that Garcia may change his mind about
attending.
   The summit is scheduled for Feb. 15 in Cartagena, Colombia.
   ``If the American troops are withdrawn from Panamanian
territory, President Garcia will go to the summit,'' said
presidential minister Rodolfo Beltran.
   Garcia later confirmed the possibility in brief statements to
reporters.
   Peru is the world's principal producer of coca leaf, the raw
material for cocaine. The Bush Administration has proposed spending
$2.2 billion over the next five years in the three Andean nations
to stop the drug trade.
   U.S. troops invaded Panama to oust Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega
and bring him back to the United States to stand trial on drug
trafficking charges. A civilian government led by Guillermo Endara,
who won elections in May that Noriega annuled, has taken power in
the Central American nation.
   About 14,000 troops joined the 12,000 American soldiers already
stationed in Panama for the U.S. action, and Washington has given
no deadline for their withdrawal.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0066 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 1841EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-WeatherpageWeather     01-07 0240</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Weatherpage Weather,0249</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rain Drenches Southeast, Sunny Skies Elsewhere</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Rain drenched parts of the Southeast and West on Sunday, with
sunny skies elsewhere and snow in the mountains of Nevada, Idaho
and Wyoming.
   Rain stretched from the Carolinas to portions of Tennessee,
Georgia, Florida, Alabama, Mississippi and much of Louisiana.
   Montana, Idaho, Wyoming and the northern Pacific Coast also
received rain, which turned to snow in the higher elevations of
Nevada, Idaho and Wyoming.
   Albany, Ga., got nearly 2.2 inches of rain in the six hours
ending at 7 a.m. EST, the National Weather Service said.
   About 50 homes in nearby Sylvester, Ga., were evacuated because
of flooding, the weather service said.
   Crescent City, Calif., received nearly 2.5 inches of rain in the
same six-hour period.
   From 3 to 5 inches of snow fell overnight near Lake Tahoe.
   Wind gusted up to 87 mph in Livingston, Mont., and up to 60 mph
in Cody, Wyo.
   Marquette, Mich., had a record high temperature of 42 degrees,
breaking the date's previous mark of 37 degrees set in 1965. Mason
City, Iowa, also set a new high _ 47 degrees. The previous record
was 44 degrees set in 1963.
   The cold spot in the nation's Lower 48 states was -7 degrees in
Caribou and Houlton, Maine.
   Temperatures around the nation at 3 p.m. EST ranged from 3
degrees in Limestone, Maine, to 84 degrees In Vero Beach, Fla.,
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0067 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 1938EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Dollar-Yen     01-07 0030</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Dollar-Yen,0029</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dollar Opens Higher</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The dollar opened at 144.55 yen on the Tokyo
foreign exchange market Monday, up from last Friday's close of
144.15 yen.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0068 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 2002EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Hungary     01-07 0267</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Hungary,0274</SECOND>
<HEAD>Gov't Announces Price Increases on Milk, Meat, Bread</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BUDAPEST, Hungary (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The government on Sunday tripled water
and sewer rates and raised prices more than 25 percent on milk,
meat and bread as part of efforts to move Hungary's economy toward
capitalism.
   It is the third Eastern European country in a week to announce
broad economic changes to curtail more than 40 years of price
controls and subsidies implemented by Communist leadership.
   Most of the price increases were to take effect Monday, with
some coming into effect Feb. 1, the state news agency MTI reported.
   The government announcement, carried by MTI, said meat prices
will rise by 32 percent, bread by 26 percent and milk and dairy
products at least 42 percent.
   The cost of cigarettes, beer and spirits is to rise by 20-22
percent, while rents will rise by 35 percent as subsidies are
withdrawn, MTI said.
   Water and sewage rates will increase 336 percent because of a
cut in state subsidies and previously ``irrationally low'' prices,
MTI said. To offset the increases, the government will raise state
pensions and family allowances, the news agency said.
   Hungarians would have to pay at least 45 percent more for urban
public transport and 55 percent more in the Budapest area, the news
agency said.
   The price increases will result partly from the state removing
controls on prices as part of an austerity budget adopted by
Parliament last month.
   On Jan. 1, Poland and Yugoslavia announced broad changes
intended to transform those economies to capitalism, cut inflation
and make their currencies convertible for international trade.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0069 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 2035EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-DressCodePriest     01-07 0375</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Dress Code Priest,0384</SECOND>
<HEAD>Priest Ousted Over Dress Code Supported by Parishioners</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JAMES HANNAH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DAYTON, Ohio (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Roman Catholic priest who was fired for
denying Holy Communion to worshipers dressed in mini-skirts and
shorts got support Sunday from a parishioner who said the priest
was only trying to set a standard.
   The Rev. Roger Griese, 73, was placed on retirement from Sacred
Heart Roman Catholic Church last week by Archbishop Daniel
Pilarczyk, who objected to Griese's refusal of communion to those
worshipers wearing clothing Griese deemed inappropriate for church.
   ``What did Father Griese do that deserves his dismissal?'' Debra
O'Laughlin said in a letter she read in the basement after Sunday's
Mass.
   ``He set a standard, tried to tell people the proper dress and
behavior in the proper place, and got fired,'' her letter said.
   Ms. O'Laughlin had asked Griese's successor if she could read
the letter during the service, but the Rev. Francis Pilliod told
her she would have to read it in the basement afterward. Pilliod's
decision was met with shouts of disapproval from the congregation.
   Also Sunday, parishioner Joseph Cleary said he sent Pilarczyk a
letter signed by about 100 people in support of Griese, who plans
to appeal his forced retirement to the Vatican. Cleary said the
signatures accounted for virtually all members of the parish.
   ``It seemed to us that he (Pilarczyk) didn't have any idea that
the parish stood behind father 100 percent,'' Cleary said. ``Father
isn't doing this all on his own. It's the rest of the parishioners
who feel that way.''
   A letter from Pilarczyk was read during Saturday's Mass
explaining his decision to oust Griese.
   ``It is not intended as a penalty, but reflects a judgment on my
part that Father Griese is no longer able to fulfill the office of
pastor,'' wrote Pilarczyk, head of the Cincinnati archdiocese.
``This decision has not been pleasant or easy. I ask that all of us
pray for Father Griese.''
   Griese, who headed Sacred Heart for 21 years, had twice denied
communion to a man who came to church wearing shorts. He also
criticized the man before the congregation.
   Griese remains a priest in good standing and is entitled to
retirement benefits.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0070 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 2108EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--France-GasLeak     01-07 0123</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--France-Gas Leak,0124</SECOND>
<HEAD>Five Die When Hot Water Heater's Flame Goes Out</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MANOSQUE, France (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Natural gas seeped from a malfunctioning
hot water heater through a home near this southwestern town Sunday,
killing a woman and her four children, firefighters said.
   The water heater's flame apparently went out while Fatma Sila,
29, was taking a bath, the fire department reported. She was found
asphyxiated in the bathtub, while her children, aged 3, 4, 6, and
7, died in an adjacent room.
   Their father, Bouchta Sila, a farm worker, was at work at the
time. His nationality and that of the children was not known. Ms.
Sila was a Moroccan.
   Manosque is in the rugged Provence hills, 55 miles north of
Marseille.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0071 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 2056EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-HongKong-Gold     01-07 0032</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Hong Kong-Gold,0030</SECOND>
<HEAD>Gold Opens Lower in Hong Kong</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HONG KONG (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Gold dropped $1.26 an ounce on Hong Kong
markets Monday, opening at $403.65. It closed at $404.91 Saturday.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0072 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 2059EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Israel 1stLd-Writethru   01-07 0802</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0653,0821</SECOND>
<HEAD>Two Palestinians Die, Nine Activists Banned From Traveling</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 15 grafs to UPDATE with identity of other
Palestinians banned, Tel Aviv mayor says he wants to talk peace
with Arafat. Pick up 12th pvs, `In the...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By NICOLAS B. TATRO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two 18-year-old Palestinians died Sunday of
gunshot wounds after clashes with soldiers, and Israeli authorities
banned nine pro-PLO activists from traveling abroad.
   Palestinian leaders charged Sunday that the three-month travel
bans on the nine pro-PLO activists imposed by Interior Minister
Aryeh Deri were an attempt to disrupt U.S.-backed efforts to
arrange a Palestinian-Israeli meeting in Cairo.
   Those targeted included Sari Nusseibeh and Faisal Husseini, the
two most prominent Palestinians involved in behind-the-scenes
diplomatic efforts.
   Husseini complained that Israeli authorities were trying to
nominate their own Palestinian representatives for the proposed
talks and block any role for the Palestine Liberation Organization.
   Also ordered to stay in the country were Nablus businessman
Saeed Kanaan, activist Zuahira Kamal and a delegation of five
Palestinian trade union leaders who were to attend a conference in
Egypt, Palestinian sources said.
   Nusseibeh was reportedly turned back at the Allenby Bridge while
en route to Jordan and others had planned trips to Egypt, which has
been consulting Palestinians about a list of 10 negotiators to meet
with Israel.
   The English-language Jerusalem Post and Hebrew Maariv dailies
said the travel bans appeared aimed at disrupting contacts between
local Palestinian leaders and Yasser Arafat's PLO. Israel considers
the PLO a terrorist group and refuses to negotiate with it.
   Also Sunday, Tel Aviv's mayor said he was prepared to meet with
Arafat and criticized Prime Minister Yitzhak Shamir's position
toward the organization.
   The Interior Ministry issued a statement saying Deri banned the
Palestinians from leaving because ``he was convinced there was a
serious suspicion that their exit abroad could harm state security,
because they could have met with hostile elements.''
   An Israeli official who briefed a reporter Sunday said he did
not know if the travel ban was related to the diplomatic efforts
but added the three-month restriction was likely to expire before
any Israeli-Palestinian meeting was arranged in Cairo.
   The official said ``Israel is not fully satisfied'' with
Washington's response to Israel's demands for U.S. guarantees that
the PLO will be excluded from the negotiating.
   Israeli sources confirmed media reports that U.S. Secretary of
State James A. Baker III sent a letter to Israel refusing to give a
rigid guarantee and backing Arab demands that issues other than
Israel's peace initiative could be raised at the Cairo meeting.
   The sources said unless Israel could get stronger American
guarantees, a Washington meeting that was planned to help set up
the Cairo talks might not be convened. Baker had planned to invite
Israel's and Egypt's foreign ministers to the Washington session
later this month.
   In Tel Aviv, Mayor Shlomo Lahat said Israel will have negotiate
with the PLO and said he is ``ready to talk to Arafat, if it is
permitted by law,'' said city spokesman Benny Cohen.
   Lahat, of Shamir's Likud bloc, criticized Shamir, who has ruled
out any contacts with the PLO. Meetin with PLO members without
government authoritization carries a maximum three-year prison
sentence.
   In the West Bank town of Bethlehem, about 2,000 people attended
a funeral for Fadi Zabakli.
   Zabakli died earlier Sunday of gunshot wounds suffered in
Bethlehem on Dec. 28. The army said the teen-ager was wearing a
mask and fled from soldiers who ordered him to stop for questioning.
   Several hundred soldiers in Bethlehem's Manger Square watched
without intervening as activists marching in the funeral procession
waved outlawed Palestinian flags and broke into rhythmic chants of
``With our soul and our blood we will revenge you, Fadi!''
   Church bells pealed a mourning cadence, and shopkeepers
throughout Bethlehem staged a spontaneous protest strike.
   The second death came in the West Bank village of Attil.
Residents there told Arab reporters that Kamal Abu Khalil, 18, was
fatally wounded in the head Sunday when soldiers raiding the
village opened fire on Palestinians erecting barricades and
throwing stones.
   Israel radio quoted a military source as saying soldiers raided
Attil shortly after masked youths torched an Israeli bus carrying
Arab workers to jobs in Israel.
   The radio said Khalil was among a group of masked assailants.
The army has orders to arrest Palestinians wearing masks.
   The deaths brought to 644 the number of Palestinians killed by
Israelis during the two-year uprising against Israeli rule in the
occupied West Bank and Gaza Strip. At least 166 Palestinians also
have been slain by fellow Arabs, and 43 Israelis have been killed.
   On the Jordanian border, Israeli troops killed an infiltrator
dressed in a Jordanian army uniform, the fifth shooting incident
this year along the Jordan border, an army spokesman said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0073 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 2116EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-StuartShooting 1stLd-Writethru a0686 01-07 0620</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Stuart Shooting, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0686,0634</SECOND>
<HEAD>Another Woman Linked to Stuart Probe</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: INSERTS one graf after 7th, `Stuart, who ...' to CLARIFY no
arrests have been made; ADDS two grafs at bottom to UPDATE with
brother under surveillance, report of another man in car during
drop.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>BY STEPHANIE SCHOROW</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Charles Stuart bought a $250 brooch last week and
was repeatedly called by a woman while he was hospitalized, leading
investigators to suspect a romantic motive for him to kill his
pregnant wife, wound himself and blame the attack on a mugger,
published reports said Sunday.
   Stuart, who received a nationwide outpouring of sympathy after
his cries for help over his car phone led police to his dying wife
Oct. 23, jumped to his death from a Boston Harbor bridge Thursday
after becoming a suspect in her slaying.
   Authorities said he committed suicide after his brother,
Matthew, told investigators Stuart murdered his wife. Carol Stuart
was shot after the couple left a birthing class. Her son, delivered
by Caesarean section, died 17 days later.
   Authorities sought genetic tests to determine if the child was
fathered by Stuart, and they continued to look for insurance
policies for a motive.
   The search for the gun used in the shootings went into a fourth
day Sunday with no results.
   Matthew Stuart, 23, said his brother passed him the gun and his
wife's purse the night of the shootings and that he later threw
them into a river in Revere, a Boston suburb. The bag has been
recovered.
   Stuart, who was shot in the stomach, provided a description of
an assailant, and the crime riveted the nation as a chilling
example of urban violence. The drama was bolstered by transcripts
of Stuart's gripping call for help on his phone.
   No arrests have been made in the case.
   Police have questioned a woman who worked with Stuart at Edward
F. Kakas &amp; Sons, a fur shop where Charles was manager, the Boston
Globe reported Sunday.
   In a search of Stuart's Reading home, police found telephone
bills that indicate she had been using his credit card to call him
at the hospital, said Reading police Detective Dave Saunders.
   The woman was a Brown University graduate now in graduate school
and worked at Kakas for the last two summers, the Globe said,
quoting neighbors and friends. Police would not release the woman's
identity.
   Police also are investigating Stuart's actions on Tuesday, when
he bought a new car and a $250 14-carat gold brooch at Marco
Jewelers in Peabody, the Globe said. Police are trying to determine
if the jewelry was a present for the woman, the newspaper said.
   John White, the jewelry store manager, said he was surprised by
Stuart's demeanor while making the purchase. ``He didn't express
any grief. None at all. That struck everyone as funny,'' White said.
   In October, the woman was questioned by police and had said she
and her boyfriend had socialized with Stuart and his wife.
   The district attorney's office has sent blood samples to a lab
for DNA testing to establish the parentage of the child. Results
will take at least three weeks, said Dr. Gerald Fegin of the state
Medical Examiner's office.
   Police said they are also looking for insurance policies. Stuart
has collected $82,000 on an insurance policy from his wife's
position as a lawyer. A search of the couple's home turned up
another $100,000 policy on her, authorities said.
   John Julian, a spokesman for the district attorney's office,
said Sunday that Matthew Stuart is under surveillance.
   The Boston Herald said another man was in the car with Matthew
when Stuart tossed him the bag. The man has denied any involvement.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0074 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 2132EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r e BC-RussianRockOpera     01-07 0577</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Russian Rock Opera,0594</SECOND>
<HEAD>Soviet Troupe Presents `The Hope,' Soviet Russia's First Rock
Opera</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: No PMs planned.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By MARY CAMPBELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Russia's first rock opera, set in 1806 with an
elaborate avant-garde staging, cast of 60 and a message ``to bridge
the distance between us with love,'' has opened for four weeks at
the City Center.
   ``Junon and Avos _ the Hope'' is interesting. Though it will
occasionally remind New Yorkers of theater from ``South Pacific''
to ``Jesus Christ Superstar,'' ``Hair'' and ``Les Miserables,'' it
isn't really a copycat show.
   The music is fat-chorded guitar rock underlined with
synthesizers, loud but not superloud. However, it isn't all rock.
There's a choir at the back of the stage which sometimes sings
church music. Four deep-voiced naval officers sing what could be a
lovely sad Russian lullaby. Some of the male solos lean toward Yves
Montand's style. One of the forging-ahead songs, sung with serious
intensity by the men, has the catchy, fun beat of ``Honey Bun''
from ``South Pacific.''
   The story, said to be true, is easy to follow. It's written in
the program and Broadway veteran Philip Casnoff explains it from
time to time. ``The Hope'' was first performed in Moscow's Lenin
Komsomol Theater in 1982. Pierre Cardin took that production to his
Paris theater in 1983 and is the producer of these timely
performances.
   The stage is a series of plastic panels, lighted from
underneath, with some give when stepped on. They're steeply raked.
They don't meet in the center, leaving a long, narrow walkway for
center-stage entrances and exits. At the beginning, a ship is
poised center stage. It is hoisted up, still in sight.
   Count Rezanov wants to take two ships, Junon and Avos, to San
Francisco and open trade and relations between the two countries.
He sails. Spain tells the governor that trade can only be with
Spain. Rezanov seduces the governor's daughter Conchita. He returns
to Russia to get permission to marry her, outside his church, but
dies. She waits 35 years, learns he is dead and becomes
California's first nun.
   Finally, the entire cast, some changed into jeans, gather to
sing ``Alleluia,'' with lyrics imploring peace. It starts like an
oratorio. Then the rock group kicks in and, with the younger
players looking happier, they join arms, sway their bodies in
circles and sing it like the tribe from ``Hair.''
   Nikolai Karachentsev was a strong, rugged-faced Count Rezanov, a
Romeo with a hand mike. In America, he'd probably become a TV
private eye or the next Mick Jagger. In Russia, he acts in
contemporary plays and classics and makes movies.
   Yelena Shanina was a delicate Conchita, her small head and
blonde hair making her look like a Russian ballerina. Program notes
say that Alexander Abdulov, the narrator, is popular in the
Komsomol's musicals, in TV and movies.
   Alexis Ribinkov, who wrote the music, studied with Aram
Khachaturian. He composes classical music, scores films and has
written a second contemporary opera. Poet Andrey Voznesensky wrote
the lyrics and book, based on one of his poems. Director Mark
Zakharov is artistic director of Lenin Komsomol Theater. Lucy
Jarvis, the American producer, took ``Duke Ellington's
Sophisticated Ladies'' to the Soviet Union.
   Bolshoi Ballet star Vladimir Vassiliev choreographed the show.
His new pas de deux, ``Elegy,'' will be performed on American
Ballet Theater's 1990 tour, which could be looked on as fulfilling
part of Count Rezanov's dream.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0075 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 2149EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Peru-Drought     01-07 0179</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Peru-Drought,0182</SECOND>
<HEAD>Lima Suffering From Severe Water Shortage</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LIMA, Peru (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hundreds of residents lined up Sunday to get
water from trucks and scores of people filled jugs and bottles from
downtown fountains as Lima suffered through a severe water shortage.
   Lower than normal rainfall in the Andes Mountains has caused the
shortage, and a summer heat wave and electricity rationing caused
by terrorist attacks on power lines are aggravating the problem.
   The minister of energy and mines, Mario Samame, said the
situation is so bad that if the city doesn't take urgent measures
to conserve water, water services could collapse.
   In an interview published Sunday in the Lima newspaper Expreso,
Walter Gomez of the state weather service said the city of 7
million is tapping water reserves in nearby lakes that it will need
in the dry months of June to November.
   He said the Rimac River, Lima's principal source of water which
flows down from the high Andes to the east, is running at less than
half its normal level for this time of year.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0076 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 2200EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-JailUprising     01-07 0168</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Jail Uprising,0174</SECOND>
<HEAD>Inmates Injured in 20-Minute Rampage</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CHULA VISTA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A detention center remained locked
down Sunday following a brief uprising among inmates that left 27
of them injured, authorities said.
   Black and Hispanic inmates at the San Diego County South Bay
Detention Center began fighting Saturday night, the sheriff's
department said.
   No guards or sheriff's deputies were hurt as they quelled the
20-minute outbreak.
   Sheriff's Deputy Jim Cook said inmates ``tore mirrors off of the
wall; light fixtures were torn down; some of the bunks were
disassembled and the parts were used as weapons.''
   The cause of the disturbance remained under investigation. The
cell block was designed for 24 inmates but held 113, authorities
said.
   Cook said inmates used ``a lot of whatever they could get their
hands on to create makeshift weapons, that's what was used. Some of
the inmates were stabbed by crudely made stabbing weapons.''
   None of the inmates was seriously injured, although 18 were
taken to hospitals for treatment.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0077 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 2218EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Obit-Charleson 3rdLd-Writethru   01-07 0574</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Charleson, 3rd Ld-Writethru,a0694,0589</SECOND>
<HEAD>Scottish Actor Ian Charleson Dies After Fight With AIDS</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: LEADS with 9 grafs to UPDATE with reax from Ian McKellen,
trims. Pick up 9th pvs, `Charleson, the...'</NOTE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Actor Ian Charleson, who starred in the film
``Chariots of Fire'' as an Olympic runner whose religious faith
took precedence over his desire to compete, has died of
complicatons from AIDS, his agent said Sunday. He was 40.
   The Scottish actor, who recently played ``Hamlet'' at London's
National Theater, died at his home in London on Saturday evening
``following a courageous struggle with the AIDS virus,'' Michael
Whitehall said. He said the cause of death was septicemia, a
disease caused by microorganisms in the blood.
   Charleson, who received critical praise for a series of stage
roles, achieved international fame in the 1981 film ``Chariots of
Fire'' in which he played Eric Liddell, a Scottish missionary and
runner who refused to compete on a Sunday. The film won the Academy
Award for best picture.
   He also appeared in the 1982 Oscar-winning film ``Gandhi'' as
Charlie Andrews, the priest who was a friend of Indian independence
leader Mohandas K. Gandhi.
   ``He was the most unmannered and unactorish of actors: always
truthful, always honest,'' fellow actor Ian McKellen said Sunday
night.
   Charleson also was a beautiful singer who ``had the most pure
tenor I've ever heard,'' McKellen said in an interview.
   Mark Fisher, an opposition Labor Party spokesman on the arts,
said Charleson's widely acclaimed performance as Hamlet ``indicated
that an enormous career lay ahead of him. This is a terrible
tragedy for the British theater.''
   His last performance came just nine weeks ago.
   ``After nearly four hours on stage he was given a standing
ovation,'' Whitehall said. ``It was clear that he was exhausted but
his courage, not only in being on that stage but giving us the
performance of his life, left our applause and cheers seeming very
inadequate.''
   Charleson, the son of a printer, was born in Edinburgh Aug. 11,
1949. He won a scholarship to the capital's Royal High School and
went on to study architecture at Edinburgh University.
   His interest in acting developed, Charleson once said, when he
discovered he had the ability ``to make people laugh and make them
cry.''
   He studied at the London Academy of Music and Dramatic Art and
began his stage career in London at the Young Vic Theater from 1972
to 1974. His performances with the National Theater included roles
in ``Julius Caesar'' and ``Volpone''in 1977, and ``Guys and Dolls''
in 1984.
   He received particular acclaim for his performances in two
American plays at the National _ Sam Shepard's ``Fool for Love'' in
1985, and a 1988 production of Tennessee Williams' ``Cat on a Hot
Tin Roof,'' in which he played Brick.
   One of his recent television roles was the lead in ``Troubles''
a film version of J.G. Farrell's book about Ireland's fight for
independence.
   There will be a private family funeral in Scotland later this
week and a memorial service in London later in the year, Whitehall
said.
   Acquired immune deficiency syndrome is caused by a virus that
damages the body's immune system, leaving victims susceptible to
infections and cancer.
   It is spread most often through sexual contact, needles or
syringes shared by drug abusers, infected blood or blood products,
and from pregnant women to their offspring.
   The scientific name for the virus is human immunodeficiency
virus, or HIV.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0078 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 2306EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-SpaceShuttle 1stLd-Writethru a0662 01-07 0557</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Space Shuttle, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0662,0566</SECOND>
<HEAD>Shuttle Countdown Continues, But Weather Looks Bad For Monday
Launch</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: INSERTS 1 graf after 3rd, ``There is...' to UPDATE with
fueling of shuttle. Edits 4th graf to conform and picks up 5th graf
pvs, `The intricate...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By HARRY F. ROSENTHAL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CAPE CANAVERAL, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   NASA officials decided Sunday to
continue the countdown toward a Monday launch of space shuttle
Columbia, although forecasters gave only 1-in-5 odds that the
weather will permit it.
   ``There is a chance and we'd like to be ready to take that
chance,'' said William B. Lenoir, the head of NASA's space flight
program. As long there was more than a zero possibility for liftoff
on Monday, he said, the shuttle's huge fuel tanks would be filled
beginning late Sunday.
   ``There is a 20 percent chance we will get off,'' Lenoir told
reporters. ``We've all been here often enough to know that what is
predicted does not always happen, and sometimes good things happen
when bad is predicted.''
   Kennedy Space Center spokesman Carl Kristoferson said fueling of
the shuttle began at 10:53 p.m. EST.
   The space center has been socked in by fog for several days at
8:10 a.m. EST, the earliest the shuttle can be launched Monday. The
launch opportunity lasts until 9:02.
   The intricate timing on this 33rd shuttle flight is dictated by
Columbia's main mission, to retrieve a science laboratory the size
of a small bus that has been in orbit around Earth since its launch
in April 1984 from the shuttle Challenger.
   Columbia must be launched into the same path as the satellite,
which is called LDEF, for Long Duration Exposure Facility.
   The aerial chase will have the shuttle trailing the LDEF in the
same plane, or driving lane. By flying in a lower orbit and thereby
taking less time to go around the Earth, the shuttle eventually
will catch up to the satellite, snag it with its 50-foot crane, and
bring it into the cargo bay. Mission specialist Bonnie Dunbar is
set to be at the space shuttle controls during the retrieval.
   If the shuttle takes off Monday, the retrieval would take place
on Thursday, Saturday or Sunday, depending on the exact minute of
launch.
   The LDEF is a 12-sided frame on which are mounted 57 trays of
experiments including ones with tomato seeds and different metals
and a a mechanism to catch interplanetary dust.
   Experimenters hope to gain valuable information about the
universe and its origins from postflight examinations of cosmic
dust, interstellar gases and previously unobtainable subatomic
radiation particles.
   Students from the fifth grade through college will try to see
which of 12{ million tomato seeds will grow. Engineers will learn
how materials, coatings, electronic parts and thermal control
systems are affected by long exposure to space.
   Commander Dan Brandenstein and his crew of four also will launch
the fift of a series of Navy communications satellites and conduct
eight scientific experiments. Others on the mission are pilot Jim
Wetherbee and mission specialists Marsha Ivins and David Low.
   The flight is to last 10 days, matching the previous shuttle
record, to test equipment for longer shuttle missions. Flights of
16 and 28 days also are planned as NASA prepares to the day when
astronauts will be aboard a space station for up to six months.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0079 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 2323EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Salvador-Priests 2ndLd-Writethru a0726 01-07 0628</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Salvador-Priests, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0726,0644</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<HEAD>President Says Military Men Killed Priests</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS thruout to reorganize, ADD background. No pickup.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By DOUGLAS GRANT MINE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN SALVADOR, El Salvador (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Military men committed the Nov.
16 massacre of six Jesuit priests, their housekeeper and her
daughter, President Alfredo Cristiani said Sunday night.
   ``It has been determined that there was involvement of some
elements of the armed forces,'' Cristiani said in a five-minute
nationally broadcast address. He termed the massacre ``abominable.''
   The president did not specify who was implicated in the crime,
nor did he indicate the rank or number of those responsible.
   Earlier, Col. Rene Emilio Ponce, head of El Salvador's joint
chiefs of staff, told The Associated Press that members of an elite
battalion have been confined to their base and were being
questioned in connection with the slayings.
   However, he emphasized that the 47 members of the elite Atlacatl
battalion _ including two officers _ are not under arrest.
   It was unclear whether those soldiers and officers were the ones
to whom Cristiani referred.
   Priests and educators Ignacio Ellacuria, Ignacio Martin-Baro,
Segundo Montes, Amado Lopez, Juan Ramon Moreno and Joaquin Lopez
Lopez were taken from their beds in their on-campus residence
before dawn Nov. 16 and killed. The priests' housekeeper, Julia
Ramos, and her 15-year-old daughter Celina, were also slain.
   Ellacuria was the rector of the UCA, and Martin-Baro was its
vice rector.
   Ponce said in a telephone interview that the men being
interrogated were members of the unit that conducted a search of
the Jesuits' residence at the order's Central American University,
or UCA, two days before the priests were slain.
   Asked if the men were implicated by evidence other than the fact
that they conducted the search, Ponce said he could not comment.
   A UCA employee has said she saw men in military uniforms outside
the residence shortly before the shots that killed the priests were
heard. The woman, Lucia Barrera, has been taken for her own safety
to the United States, where she is under the protection of the
Jesuits.
   Cristiani said in his speech Sunday that the work of a
commission investigating the slayings ``has been from the start
professional and exhaustive.'' Agents from the United States, Spain
and Scotland Yard have aided in the probe.
   The president also said a ``Special Commission of Honor,''
including high-ranking military men and respected civilian lawyers,
has been created ``to determine the exact circumstances (of the
slayings) and clarify the truth in its complete magnitude.''
   He said the new commission would work with investigators ``to
deduce responsibilities and make sure justice is done.'' He said
punishment would be meted out ``down to the last person
implicated.''
   Cristiani asked Salvadorans to avoid speculation while the
commissions carry out their work.
   The priests were slain five days after leftist rebels of the
Farabundo Marti National Liberation Front, or FMLN, launched their
biggest offensive of their 10-year-old revolution. The guerrillas
have battled a succession of U.S.-backed governments, which they
allege serve as civilian facades for repressive military rule.
   The far right, which is blamed for the death-squad murders of
several thousand suspected leftists in the early 1980s, had
consistently denounced the left-leaning UCA Jesuits as subversive
ideologues.
   In 1980, El Salvador's Roman Catholic Archbishop Oscar Romero
was murdered, and right-wing death squads were widely believed to
be responsible. The assassins were never brought to justice.
   Cristiani has vowed his administration would find and punish
those responsible for the murder of the Jesuit priests. He offered
a $250,000 reward for information leading to the murderers' arrest
and conviction.
   In the days following the slayings, several high-ranking
military officers, including Col. Francisco Elena Fuentes, 1st army
brigade commander, publicly accused the rebels of the murders.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0080 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 2041EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u o BC-WEA--Temps     01-07 1420</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-WEA--Temps,0561</SECOND>
<BYLINE>The Weather Elsewhere</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Sunday</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Temperatures indicate previous day's high and overnight low to 8
p.m. EST.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
                         
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Hi  Lo Prc Otlk</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Albany,N.Y.            38  16      cdy
Albuquerque            47  17       clr
Amarillo               58  18       clr
Anchorage              19  09 .14   clr
Asheville              44  39 .09   clr
Atlanta                49  45 .30   clr
Atlantic City          41  20      cdy
Austin                 64  44       clr
Baltimore              43  24      cdy
Billings               48  34       clr
Birmingham             50  45 .40   clr
Bismarck               42  21      cdy
Boise                  44  36 .08  cdy
Boston                 37  25      cdy
Brownsville            67  48 .17   clr
Buffalo                40  24      cdy
Burlington,Vt.         34  11      cdy
Casper                 43  28       clr
Charleston,S.C.        52  47 2.17   clr
Charleston,W.Va.       42  25      cdy
Charlotte,N.C.         48  45       clr
Cheyenne               47  26       clr
Chicago                42  28      cdy
Cincinnati             48  24      cdy
Cleveland              46  26      cdy
Columbia,S.C.          49  45 .41   clr
Columbus,Ohio          46  23      cdy
Concord,N.H.           32  09      cdy
Dallas-Ft Worth        60  35       clr
Dayton                 47  26      cdy
Denver                 56  24       clr
Des Moines             40  25      cdy
Detroit                44  22      cdy
Duluth                 43  26      cdy
El Paso                55  20       clr
Evansville             46  24      cdy
Fairbanks             -09 -18 .06  sn
Fargo                  37  23      cdy
Flagstaff              51  02       clr
Grand Rapids           37  26      cdy
Great Falls            51  40       clr
Greensboro,N.C.        47  39       clr
Hartford               41  20      cdy
Helena                 52  40 .05  cdy
Honolulu               84  64       clr
Houston                60  45 .38   clr
Indianapolis           46  25      cdy
Jackson,Miss.          47  44 .76   clr
Jacksonville           64  55       clr
Juneau                 68  30      sn
Kansas City            50  24       clr
Las Vegas              56  27       clr
Little Rock            45  36       clr
Los Angeles            64  47      cdy
Louisville             50  24      cdy
Lubbock                63  19       clr
Memphis                47  37 .08  cdy
Miami Beach            82  76      cdy
Midland-Odessa         63  21       clr
Milwaukee              43  28      cdy
Mpls-St Paul           41  19      cdy
Nashville              46  32      cdy
New Orleans            55  51 .66   clr
New York City          45  29      cdy
Norfolk,Va.            47  33       clr
North Platte           59  17       clr
Oklahoma City          57  25       clr
Omaha                  50  25       clr
Orlando                83  63       clr
Philadelphia           41  23      cdy
Phoenix                62  39       clr
Pittsburgh             44  22      cdy
Portland,Maine         29  18      cdy
Portland,Ore.          54  46 1.18  rn
Providence             39  24      cdy
Raleigh                48  40       clr
Rapid City             53  24      cdy
Reno                   56  37      cdy
Richmond               48  32       clr
Sacramento             54  47 .32  cdy
St Louis               52  30       clr
Salt Lake City         39  17      cdy
San Antonio            64  37       clr
San Diego              65  43      cdy
San Francisco          55  49      cdy
San Juan,P.R.          83  69      cdy
Santa Fe               39  11       clr
St Ste Marie           37  26 .04  cdy
Seattle                52  46 .93  rn
Shreveport             50  40 .07   clr
Sioux Falls            47  18      cdy
Spokane                46  39 .61  cdy
Syracuse               42  15      cdy
Tampa-St Ptrsbg        76  68      cdy
Topeka                 52  19       clr
Tucson                 62  31       clr
Tulsa                  56  24       clr
Washington,D.C.        43  27      cdy
Wichita                49  20       clr
Wilkes-Barre           42  21      cdy
Wilmington,Del.        42  28      cdy
  
National Temperature Extremes for Sunday  
  
High&equals; 85 at Miami (North Dade County), Vero Beach, and West Palm
Beach, Fla. 
 
Low&equals; -14 at Gunnison, Colo.


</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0081 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 2045EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u o BC-WEA--TempsUNJUSTIFIED     01-07 1466</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-WEA--Temps UNJUSTIFIED,1090</SECOND>
<HEAD>The Weather Elsewhere With Tomorrow's Temperature Forecast and
Outlook.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Sunday</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Temperatures on left indicate previous day's high and overnight
low to 8 p.m. EST. Today's forecast temperatures and outlook and
tomorrow's temperatures and outlook are in the right columns.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
                         
</TEXT>
<HEAD> Yesterday   Today   Tomorrow </HEAD>
<TEXT>
                         
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Hi  Lo Prc  Hi  Lo Otlk  Hi  Lo Otlk</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Albany,N.Y.            38  16     39  20  cdy 37 
25  cdy
Albuquerque            47  17     50  20   clr 53  22
  clr
Amarillo               58  18     62  22   clr 66  30
  clr
Anchorage              19  09 .14 15  06  cdy 15  03  
clr
Asheville              44  39 .09 45  38  rn 55  28  
clr
Atlanta                49  45 .30 50  43  cdy 58  34  
clr
Atlantic City          41  20     41  35  rn 45  37
 cdy
Austin                 64  44     69  32   clr 74  39
  clr
Baltimore              43  24     38  33  rn 49  34 
cdy
Billings               48  34     48  37   clr 48  35
  clr
Birmingham             50  45 .40 50  41  cdy 60  33  
clr
Bismarck               42  21     42  28  cdy 41  20
 cdy
Boise                  44  36 .08 47  37  rn 47  35  cdy
Boston                 37  25     43  31  cdy 40  32
 cdy
Brownsville            67  48 .17 75  42   clr 76  51 
 clr
Buffalo                40  24     42  30  cdy 40  29
 cdy
Burlington,Vt.         34  11     32  22  cdy 33  19
 cdy
Casper                 43  28     46  34   clr 48  34
  clr
Charleston,S.C.        52  47 2.17 58  49  rn 59  38  
clr
Charleston,W.Va.       42  25     44  35  rn 52  34 
cdy
Charlotte,N.C.         48  45     46  40  rn 55  35 
 clr
Cheyenne               47  26     53  34   clr 51  34
  clr
Chicago                42  28     45  28   clr 41  31
 cdy
Cincinnati             48  24     45  31  cdy 48  30
 cdy
Cleveland              46  26     46  30   clr 43  30
 cdy
Columbia,S.C.          49  45 .41 52  46  rn 58  34  
clr
Columbus,Ohio          46  23     44  29  cdy 46  31
 cdy
Concord,N.H.           32  09     37  14   clr 35  16
 cdy
Dallas-Ft Worth        60  35     69  32   clr 72  39
  clr
Dayton                 47  26     44  30  cdy 46  30
 cdy
Denver                 56  24     62  34   clr 63  33
  clr
Des Moines             40  25     45  27  cdy 45  31
 cdy
Detroit                44  22     44  27  cdy 39  31
 cdy
Duluth                 43  26     35  27  cdy 34  24
 cdy
El Paso                55  20     62  27   clr 66  29
  clr
Evansville             46  24     50  31  cdy 54  31
 cdy
Fairbanks             -09 -18 .06 10 -15  sn 18 -20  sn
Fargo                  37  23     37  28  cdy 32  22
 cdy
Flagstaff              51  02     51  14  cdy 54  18
  clr
Grand Rapids           37  26     42  28  cdy 40  32
 cdy
Great Falls            51  40     50  38   clr 48  35
  clr
Greensboro,N.C.        47  39     44  38  rn 52  32 
 clr
Hartford               41  20     42  24  cdy 40  27
 cdy
Helena                 52  40 .05 50  32  cdy 48  30  cdy
Honolulu               84  64     84  66  cdy 85  68
  clr
Houston                60  45 .38 67  34   clr 72  43 
 clr
Indianapolis           46  25     47  30   clr 49  31
 cdy
Jackson,Miss.          47  44 .76 53  38  cdy 65  35  
clr
Jacksonville           64  55     65  58  rn 64  39 
 clr
Juneau                 68  30     35  32  rn 32  28 
sn
Kansas City            50  24     53  32   clr 54  35
  clr
Las Vegas              56  27     60  36   clr 64  37
  clr
Little Rock            45  36     55  32   clr 63  35
  clr
Los Angeles            64  47     70  48  cdy 69  47
 cdy
Louisville             50  24     45  32  cdy 55  31
 cdy
Lubbock                63  19     64  24   clr 70  32
  clr
Memphis                47  37 .08 54  38   clr 60  41 
cdy
Miami Beach            82  76     81  68  cdy 77  62
 cdy
Midland-Odessa         63  21     69  26   clr 72  34
  clr
Milwaukee              43  28     43  30  cdy 42  30
 cdy
Mpls-St Paul           41  19     44  25  cdy 42  27
 cdy
Nashville              46  32     50  35  cdy 58  36
 cdy
New Orleans            55  51 .66 65  45   clr 68  46
  clr
New York City          45  29     42  32  cdy 45  34
 cdy
Norfolk,Va.            47  33     47  39  rn 51  39 
 clr
North Platte           59  17     55  20  cdy 58  23
  clr
Oklahoma City          57  25     65  30   clr 69  34
  clr
Omaha                  50  25     51  26  cdy 55  29
  clr
Orlando                83  63     72  64  rn 69  48 
 clr
Philadelphia           41  23     41  35  rn 45  35 
cdy
Phoenix                62  39     68  40   clr 73  44
  clr
Pittsburgh             44  22     42  29  cdy 42  31
 cdy
Portland,Maine         29  18     38  21   clr 35  22
 cdy
Portland,Ore.          54  46 1.18 55  50  rn 51  46  rn
Providence             39  24     43  27  cdy 42  30
 cdy
Raleigh                48  40     45  39  rn 55  34 
 clr
Rapid City             53  24     56  30  cdy 52  30
 cdy
Reno                   56  37     56  34  cdy 56  33
 cdy
Richmond               48  32     43  35  rn 53  35 
 clr
Sacramento             54  47 .32 56  47  cdy 57  46  cdy
St Louis               52  30     55  32   clr 57  34
  clr
Salt Lake City         39  17     45  32  rn 47  33
 cdy
San Antonio            64  37     71  31   clr 75  39
  clr
San Diego              65  43     67  43  cdy 67  44
 cdy
San Francisco          55  49     57  51  cdy 58  50
 cdy
San Juan,P.R.          83  69     84  70   clr 84  71
 cdy
Santa Fe               39  11     44  15   clr 47  17
  clr
St Ste Marie           37  26 .04 33  20  sn 33  28 
cdy
Seattle                52  46 .93 53  46  rn 50  44  rn
Shreveport             50  40 .07 64  34   clr 65  40 
 clr
Sioux Falls            47  18     50  33  cdy 47  25
 cdy
Spokane                46  39 .61 45  37  rn 42  35  cdy
Syracuse               42  15     40  26  cdy 40  25
 cdy
Tampa-St Ptrsbg        76  68     71  65  rn 69  50
 cdy
Topeka                 52  19     56  25   clr 58  29
  clr
Tucson                 62  31     67  33   clr 73  38
  clr
Tulsa                  56  24     63  29   clr 67  33
  clr
Washington,D.C.        43  27     40  35  rn 52  36 
cdy
Wichita                49  20     56  24   clr 60  27
  clr
Wilkes-Barre           42  21     39  32  cdy 40  32
 cdy
Wilmington,Del.        42  28     36  31  rn 47  32 
cdy
  
National Temperature Extremes for Sunday  
  
High&equals; 85 at Miami (North Dade County), Vero Beach, and West Palm
Beach, Fla. 
 
Low&equals; -14 at Gunnison, Colo.


</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0082 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 2047EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u o BC-WEA--TempsEXPANDED     01-07 2235</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-WEA--Temps EXPANDED,0854</SECOND>
<BYLINE>The Weather Elsewhere</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Sunday</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Temperatures indicate previous day's high and overnight low to 8
p.m. EST.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
                         
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Hi  Lo Prc Otlk</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Abilene,Texas          62  27       clr
Akron Canton           45  21      cdy
Albany,N.Y.            38  16      cdy
Albuquerque            47  17       clr
Allentown              43  23      cdy
Amarillo               58  18       clr
Anchorage              19  09 .14   clr
Asheville              44  39 .09   clr
Atlanta                49  45 .30   clr
Atlantic City          41  20      cdy
Austin                 64  44       clr
Baltimore              43  24      cdy
Baton Rouge            51  50 .11   clr
Billings               48  34       clr
Birmingham             50  45 .40   clr
Bismarck               42  21      cdy
Boise                  44  36 .08  cdy
Boston                 37  25      cdy
Bridgeport             40  22      cdy
Brownsville            67  48 .17   clr
Buffalo                40  24      cdy
Burlington,Vt.         34  11      cdy
Caribou                10 -08 .08  cdy
Casper                 43  28       clr
Charleston,S.C.        52  47 2.17   clr
Charleston,W.Va.       42  25      cdy
Charlotte,N.C.         48  45       clr
Chattanooga            44  41 .33   clr
Cheyenne               47  26       clr
Chicago                42  28      cdy
Cincinnati             48  24      cdy
Cleveland              46  26      cdy
Colorado Spgs          45  26      cdy
Columbia,S.C.          49  45 .41   clr
Columbus,Ga.           54  51 .95   clr
Columbus,Ohio          46  23      cdy
Concord,N.H.           32  09      cdy
Corpus Christi         65  44 .24   clr
Dallas-Ft Worth        60  35       clr
Dayton                 47  26      cdy
Daytona Beach          81  59       clr
Denver                 56  24       clr
Des Moines             40  25      cdy
Detroit                44  22      cdy
Duluth                 43  26      cdy
El Paso                55  20       clr
Elkins                 41  16      cdy
Erie                   46  27      cdy
Eugene                 55  51 2.98  rn
Evansville             46  24      cdy
Fairbanks             -09 -18 .06  sn
Fargo                  37  23      cdy
Flagstaff              51  02       clr
Flint                  41  25      cdy
Fort Smith             54  23       clr
Fort Wayne             44  26      cdy
Fresno                 61  38      cdy
Goodland               58  23       clr
Grand Junction         36  04      cdy
Grand Rapids           37  26      cdy
Great Falls            51  40       clr
Green Bay              36  22      cdy
Greensboro,N.C.        47  39       clr
Harrisburg             44  22      cdy
Hartford               41  20      cdy
Helena                 52  40 .05  cdy
Honolulu               84  64       clr
Houston                60  45 .38   clr
Huntsville,Ala.        45  41 .40   clr
Indianapolis           46  25      cdy
Jackson,Miss.          47  44 .76   clr
Jacksonville           64  55       clr
Juneau                 68  30      sn
Kansas City            50  24       clr
Knoxville              45  40 .21   clr
Lake Charles           52  45 1.03   clr
Lansing                39  23      cdy
Las Vegas              56  27       clr
Lexington              44  26      cdy
Lincoln                55  22       clr
Little Rock            45  36       clr
Los Angeles            64  47      cdy
Louisville             50  24      cdy
Lubbock                63  19       clr
Macon                  55  51 1.18   clr
Madison                38  26      cdy
Medford                48  45 1.10  rn
Memphis                47  37 .08  cdy
Miami Beach            82  76      cdy
Midland-Odessa         63  21       clr
Milwaukee              43  28      cdy
Mpls-St Paul           41  19      cdy
Mobile                 56  53 .39   clr
Montgomery             55  50 .58   clr
Nashville              46  32      cdy
New Orleans            55  51 .66   clr
New York City          45  29      cdy
Newark                 44  26      cdy
Norfolk,Va.            47  33       clr
North Platte           59  17       clr
Oklahoma City          57  25       clr
Omaha                  50  25       clr
Orlando                83  63       clr
Paducah                48  22      cdy
Peoria                 48  25      cdy
Philadelphia           41  23      cdy
Phoenix                62  39       clr
Pittsburgh             44  22      cdy
Pocatello              40  14      cdy
Portland,Maine         29  18      cdy
Portland,Ore.          54  46 1.18  rn
Providence             39  24      cdy
Pueblo                 52  18      cdy
Raleigh                48  40       clr
Rapid City             53  24      cdy
Reno                   56  37      cdy
Richmond               48  32       clr
Roanoke                49  31       clr
Rochester,N.Y.         43  15      cdy
Rockford               41  24      cdy
Sacramento             54  47 .32  cdy
St Louis               52  30       clr
St Thomas,V.I.         85  71       clr
Salem,Ore.             54  49 1.26  rn
Salt Lake City         39  17      cdy
San Angelo             64  21       clr
San Antonio            64  37       clr
San Diego              65  43      cdy
San Francisco          55  49      cdy
San Jose               64  50 .01  cdy
San Juan,P.R.          83  69      cdy
Santa Fe               39  11       clr
St Ste Marie           37  26 .04  cdy
Savannah               54  52 1.61   clr
Seattle                52  46 .93  rn
Shreveport             50  40 .07   clr
Sioux City             53  18      cdy
Sioux Falls            47  18      cdy
South Bend             42  26      cdy
Spokane                46  39 .61  cdy
Springfield,Ill.       47  25      cdy
Springfield,Mo.        51  21       clr
Syracuse               42  15      cdy
Tallahassee            68  58 .38   clr
Tampa-St Ptrsbg        76  68      cdy
Toledo                 44  27      cdy
Topeka                 52  19       clr
Tucson                 62  31       clr
Tulsa                  56  24       clr
Tupelo                 45  42 .26   clr
Waco                   63  35       clr
Washington,D.C.        43  27      cdy
W Palm Beach           85  65      cdy
Wichita                49  20       clr
Wichita Falls          60  24       clr
Wilkes-Barre           42  21      cdy
Wilmington,Del.        42  28      cdy
Yakima                 54  42 .12  cdy
Youngstown             45  23      cdy
Yuma                   67  40       clr
  
National Temperature Extremes for Sunday  
  
High&equals; 85 at Miami (North Dade County), Vero Beach, and West Palm
Beach, Fla. 
 
Low&equals; -14 at Gunnison, Colo.


</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0083 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 1408EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-BaldnessDrugs Bjt   01-07 0644</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Baldness Drugs, Bjt,0660</SECOND>
<HEAD>FDA Ban on Bogus Baldness `Remedies' May Boost Rogaine Sales</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LISA PERLMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>GRAND RAPIDS, Mich. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The federal government's ban on
non-prescription anti-baldness drugs, which goes into effect
Monday, is expected to boost the already increasing sales of
Rogaine, the only scientifically proven hair-loss treatment.
   The Food and Drug Administration said in July there is no
evidence to support the hair-growth or anti-baldness claims of
hundreds of over-the-counter creams, lotions, vitamins and food
supplements. American men spend as much as $300 a year on these
so-called baldness remedies.
   The agency said that beginning Monday it will remove such
products from the market on a case-by-case basis if their
distributors continue to make such claims.
   The publicity from the ban as well as more effective advertising
by Upjohn Co. of Kalamazoo have contributed to an increase in the
sales of Upjohn's Rogaine, a prescription baldness drug that
received FDA approval in 1988 but has been slow to catch on,
analysts say.
   Rogaine sales in the fourth quarter of 1989 totaled about $21
million, compared with a disappointing $5 million in the fourth
quarter of 1988, when it first was introduced in the United States,
said Ronald Nordmann, an analyst who follows Rogaine for
PaineWebber Inc. in New York. He attributed the increase to more
forceful advertising.
   Total U.S. sales of Rogaine in 1989 were about $65 million,
Nordmann said. But he said the drug is still unprofitable because
about $50 million was spent on advertising. He estimated 1990 sales
would jump to about $100 million, and even higher if the FDA
approves Upjohn's similar product for female pattern baldness this
year.
   Upjohn applauded the FDA's ban on its would-be competitors, but
spokeswoman Kaye Bennett said Friday it would be difficult to
isolate the ban's effect on Rogaine's improving sales.
   ``Sales have certainly been influenced by the introduction of
the 1-800 number'' in Rogaine ads, Bennett said.
   Since it was introduced in ads in May, the toll-free number has
generated about 200,000 calls from people wanting more information
about the product, Bennett said. Upjohn also has offered financial
incentives of $10 to consumers who see their dermotologists
regarding hair loss _ regardless of whether Rogaine is prescribed _
and $5 in coupons for each of the first four months of Rogaine
treatment.
   The patented drug is a 2 percent solution of the drug minoxidil,
which originally was developed to treat high blood pressure but was
found to have the unintended side effect of promoting hair growth.
   The solution, which is applied externally to the scalp, costs
about $60 for a one-month supply. Once the treatments are stopped,
any new hair will probably fall out, company officials say.
   The drug has been shown in testing to grow hair in about 39
percent of young men who are in the early stages of balding.
   William Gilbertson, director of the FDA's over-the-counter drug
review program, said he expects many of the non-prescription
products now on the market to simply change their labels to promise
``fuller, thicker-looking hair'' rather than hair growth to conform
with the new regulations. Many of these products are sold by mail,
in drug stores and through barbers and beauticians.
   One well-known product, the Helsinki Formula, is in compliance
with the FDA regulations because it does not promise hair growth
but suggests that a cleansing agent it contains ``can relieve the
impediment to hair growing naturally,'' said Hal Z. Lederman,
president of Pantron I of Los Angeles, the product's maker.
   Nordmann, the industry analyst, said he doubts Upjohn will pick
up a substantial amount of consumers who typically buy such
products because of Rogaine's higher price and the long-term
commitment involved in its use.
   ``But even if a portion of a $300 million-a-year market swings
over to Rogaine, that's potential for a significant increase,'' he
said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0084 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 1505EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-Videotel Bjt   01-07 0843</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Videotel, Bjt,0872</SECOND>
<HEAD>Texas Company Models American Videotex on French System</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN A. BOLT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DALLAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Videotex, the delivery of information and services
on a computer screen, has struggled to gain a foothold in U.S.
homes, but a Texas company figures that what works on Rue d'Orme in
France will play on Elm Street, U.S.A.
   U.S. Videotel Inc., based in Houston and financed by a Swiss
backer, is patterned after the French government-owned Minitel
system. Minitel is an in-home computer linkup to services ranging
from information, like sports scores and theater schedules, to
shopping, games and banking services.
   Videotel even uses terminals made by the same company that makes
Minitel's computers, and one service allows connection to the
French system.
   Minitel is the result of a total revamping of the French
communications system, including a $1 billion investment over five
years. In France, the terminals are provided free, but users are
charged to connect to the system.
   Past American videotex efforts have failed. Several companies
have poured millions into development only to be met with
resistance by computer-phobic consumers.
   Videotel believes it has two hooks to land the domestic market:
local information, including restaurant menus and movie schedules,
and its own computer terminal, eliminating the need for the user to
own a personal computer.
   Those two factors distinguish Videotel from the main U.S.
consumer-oriented videotex service, Prodigy, a joint venture of
Sears, Roebuck and Co. and International Business Machines Corp.
Prodigy requires a PC plus a modem for customers to communicate
with the service via a telephone line.
   The same factors helped persuade J.C. Penney Co. Inc. to sign on
with Videotel last week to make its catalog products available to
subscribers beginning Feb. 1, said Art Steinberg, Penney's catalog
business development manager.
   Also, Videotel has had enough success in Houston that Penney's
can see how a market responds, Steinberg said. Penney's, which also
participates in Prodigy, may use Videotel to advertise its store
merchandise, he said.
   For $14.95 a month, Videotel subscribers get a ``dumb'' computer
terminal that provides access to a menu of services. Customers with
PCs and modems can get the programming for $9.95 a month, the same
price as Prodigy.
   The U.S. company takes ``the best parts of the French system,
and combines that with our strategies that have been molded to the
American structure,'' said Craig Spencer, head of Videotel's Dallas
operation.
   Since debuting in April, Videotel has signed up 23,000
subscribers in Houston, and added 2,350 in Dallas-Fort Worth since
becoming available there the first of November.
   Videotel was founded three years ago and is bankrolled by an
anonymous Swiss investor, Spencer said. The company started out in
Texas because it first reached a marketing agreement with
Southwestern Bell Telephone Co. for Houston.
   The company will expand next into Canada, where it also has
agreements with the telephone company, Spencer said. Videotel has a
goal of about 4.5 million homes within five years.
   Despite Videotel's early success, skeptics remain.
   Efrem Sigel, president of Communications Trends Inc. in
Larchmont, N.Y., disputes the perception that videotex has been
successful in France, where he said the public has been ``force
fed'' Minitel because of its government ownership.
   Videotex is even less likely to succeed as a mass medium in the
United States, the analyst said.
   ``Nowhere have I seen it demonstrated that (videotex) is a
cost-efficient way to deliver information into homes,'' he said.
Whereas business success may depend on immediate information,
``consumers don't need information instantaneously,'' he said.
   ``What is it that the consumer is going to use this for that he
can't get on television or in newspapers?'' he asked.
   Sigel relegates Videotel to ``a new generation of companies that
will lose tens of millions of dollars on this stuff.''
   A survey by the Videotex Industry Association said only 28
percent of U.S. households have PCs, and only 6 percent have the
necessary modems. Videotel figures that by providing its own
terminal, it can overcome those limitations.
   ``The network is basically a mall,'' Spencer said. Users can
shop from ``GateWay Square,'' which includes several vendors, or
they can play games, call up news stories, look up information in
an on-line encyclopedia, check menus and prices at area restaurants
and find out what's playing when at local movie houses. Some banks
also allow customers access to their accounts through Videotel.
   Negotiations are under way with vendors to allow customers to
order tickets to events from, or even to order a takeout meal at
their favorite restaurant.
   ``We want this to be a utility,'' Spencer said, as indispensable
as electricity, running water and the telephone.
   The system is analogous to cable television in that many of the
services are included in the basic rate while others, such as
bill-paying or tying into France's Minitel, cost extra.
   But even Spencer concedes that Videotel's success will depend on
the quality of information and services it provides, and that the
future is far from assured.
   ``The market is so virgin to this type of technology,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0085 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 1557EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-CouponClipper     01-07 0701</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Coupon Clipper,0724</SECOND>
<HEAD>Coupon-Clipper Goes to Trial on Fraud, Conspiracy Charges</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto MH1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOAN THOMPSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOCA RATON, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A woman who hoarded thousands of coupons
and raked through the trash to get proofs of purchase for refund
deals faces trial Monday on federal charges of mail fraud and
conspiracy to distribute fake coupons.
   Connie Arvidson, a 34-year-old wife, mother and self-described
``Dumpster lady,'' said she became obsessed over the years in her
quest for special offers through rebates and coupons. But she said
she didn't know the coupons she bought through an advertisement in
a coupon magazine were counterfeit.
   At times, she would pay garbage collectors to retrieve products
that qualified for special offers. At one point, 1,000 liquor
bottles a week soaked in her bathtub to facilitate label-removing
and hundreds of thousands of coupons were jammed into files.
   But it's the coupons, not the refund programs, that have brought
her to the eve of a trial.
   Assistant U.S. Attorney Steve Sucsy, who will prosecute the case
in Dallas, where the case originates, would not comment the case
Friday, with the trial so close. But in the past, he has said:
``There is no way she didn't know what she was doing.''
   Mrs. Arvidson and nine others were indicted in June 1989 in
connection with a $2 million counterfeit coupon scam. According to
the indictment, the coupons for food and other products were
printed and distributed nationwide from Texas.
   Mrs. Arvidson is accused of knowingly buying and distributing
fake coupons.
   ``It's like a nightmare that I have to sit in a courtroom with
some of these people I don't even know and see them try to hurt me
for something I never did,'' Mrs. Arvidson said. ``I've just got to
think I'm going to come home and be with my little girl.''
   The trial of Mrs. Arvidson, along with two San Antonio men named
in the indictment, is expected to last a week. The charges against
David Rees and James Floyd Richards of conspiracy to commit mail
fraud relate to the printing and distribution of the coupons, Sucsy
said.
   The seven others, the man accused of advertising the coupons and
six accused of purchasing them from him through the mail, have made
plea bargains, Sucsy said Friday.
   Mrs. Arvidson said she and other refunders had joked that the
coupons might be stolen. But she believed the ad was legitimate
since it was in magazines.
   ``If I'm guilty of anything, then maybe I'm guilty of accepting
stolen goods,'' she said.
   And by stolen, she says, she thought the coupons might have been
taken from Dumpsters. She plans to bring to court as evidence of
Dumpster ``treasures'' three large rolls, each containing 10,000
bar code strips for light bulbs.
   Mrs. Arvidson said got the bar code strips, which could be used
as proofs of purchase, by trading with a woman who plucked them
from a Dumpster behind the light bulb factory. In return, the woman
got material qualifying the sender for rebates from a diaper
manufacturer.
   ``In refunding, I quit being surprised,'' Mrs. Arvidson said.
``I found anything could happen in refunding.''
   She said her ``little job'' brought her satisfaction and she
became known in the world of refunding. Mrs. Arvidson estimates she
made $200 a week at her rebating peak. On top of that, she paid
little for groceries because of coupons.
   ``I got known as the `diaper, Exxon, Seagram Cooler lady,'''
Mrs. Arvidson said about the proofs of purchase that she
accumulated and then rebated, traded or sold to other refunders.
   ``Everybody loves you if you have something,'' she said.
``Nobody wants to know you if you have nothing. That's what it's
like in refunding.''
   Mrs. Arvidson said she has little left: Her husband has gotten
disability payments after a car wreck but is no longer employed and
she's filed for bankruptcy.
   Mrs. Arvidson said that although others accused in the coupon
scam have made plea bargains, she won't.
   ``They wanted to give me 18 months in jail. I said, `That's
ridiculous, I didn't do anything.'''
   She faces up to 30 years in prison plus $1.5 million in fines,
if convicted on all charges.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0086 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 1724EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-Saudi-OilStrike     01-07 0343</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Saudi-Oil Strike,0354</SECOND>
<HEAD>Saudi Aramco Announces Oil and Gas Find, Third Since July</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DHAHRAN, Saudi Arabia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Saudi Arabian Oil Co. announced
Sunday the discovery of a gas and oil field, the third find in six
months by the world's largest oil exporter.
   The announcement from Saudi Aramco headquarters in Dhahran said
the strike, in the Raghib area about 77 miles southeast of the
Saudi capital of Riyadh, was commercially viable.
   Testing on Jan. 1 showed Raghib-1 well could produce 3,650
barrels per day, while gas could be produced at the rate of 10
million cubic feet per day, it said.
   The announcement, distributed by the official Saudi Press
Agency, said the oil was of the high-quality, sulphur-free crude
found earlier in the year in the Dilam and al-Hawtah discoveries.
   Saudi Oil Minister Hisham Nazer said Friday that the new oil
discoveries south of Riyadh produced oil of the highest quality
that could raise Saudi Arabia's per-barrel oil income by $1 to $2.
   The kingdom already boasts the world's largest single oil
reserves, which it estimates at 252 billion barrels. Saudi Aramco
has recently intensified its search for new oil deposits in the
center of the kingdom, away from the massive producing fields along
the Gulf coast.
   Nazer said in a television interview aired late Friday that the
kingdom will seek a higher oil production quota this year and the
following years from the Organization of Petroleum Exporting
Countries.
   Nazer said the kingdom was confident that world demand for oil
will rise in the 1990's, resulting in satisfactory prices for both
producers and consumers.
   ``Saudi Arabia has been able, through co-operation with its
fellow members of OPEC and through contacts with oil producers, to
restore stability to the world oil markets,'' Nazer said. ``We are
beginning to feel that the situation is improving for the better.''
   Nazer's comments echoed those of King Fahd, who said Dec. 31
that the kingdom will work to increase its current OPEC quota of
5.38 million barrels per day. No new target figure was disclosed.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900107-0087 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-07-90 2120EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>d f PM-Nonferrous     01-07 0130</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Nonferrous,0143</SECOND>
<HEAD>k640-1</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Spot nonferrous metal prices Friday.
   Aluminum .7350 per pound, NY Comex spot month Fri.
   Copper - $1.1880 a pound, U.S. destinations.
   Copper - $1.1000 cents per pound, NY Comex spot month Fri.
   Lead - 38-40 cents a pound.
   Zinc - 73 cents a pound, delivered.
   Tin - $4.0589 (Metals Week composite price per lb.)
   Gold - $405.00 Handy &amp; Harman (only daily quote).
   Gold - $406.30 per troy oz., NY Comex spot month Fri.
   Silver - $5.255 Handy &amp; Harman (only daily quote).
   Silver - $5.318 per troy oz., NY Comex spot month Fri.
   Mercury - $285.00-$300.00 per 76 lb flask, New York.
   Platinum - $503.00-$513.00 troy oz., N.Y. (contract).
   Platinum - $491.80 N.Y. Merc spot per troy oz. Fri.
   n.q.-not quoted.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
</Collection>
