<Collection>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900922-0001 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-22-90 1325EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-S&amp;Ls-HighRollers     09-22 0668</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-S&amp;Ls-High Rollers,0822</SECOND>
<HEAD>Keating Latest High Roller to Face Criminal Charges</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-S&amp;Ls-Starnes, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT DVORCHAK</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP National Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Charles H. Keating Jr., once called ``the Rev. Jim Bakker of
American commerce,'' is the latest of the high rollers to face
criminal charges in the savings and loan fiasco.
   Other S&amp;L officers had fleets of jets and yachts, owned posh
beach mansions, ate in audy European restaurants, threw outrageous
parties and bought million-dollar paintings.
   But it was Keating who symbolized the S&amp;L mess with his carefree
lifestyle while he controlled Lincoln Savings and Loan of Irvine,
Calif.
   Lincoln's 1989 collapse, the most expensive to date, could cost
taxpayers more than $2 billion to cover government-guaranteed
savings.
   With the freewheeling Keating at its helm since 1984, Lincoln
specialized in the sale of junk bonds for its parent company,
American Continental Corp. It also financed such lavish ventures as
a $900-a-night hotel.
   He contributed $1.3 million to five U.S. senators. His salary in
1986 and 1987 totaled $7.25 million, although he now claims to be
broke.
   Earlier this year, U.S. Rep. Jim Leach, R-Iowa, called Keating
``a fianciopath of obscene proportions, the Rev. Jim Bakker of
American commerce,'' referring to the high-profile minister who's
serving a 45-year jail term for bilking $3.7 million from his
followers.
   On Tuesday, Keating was indicted with three associates on 42
counts of criminal fraud relating to the sale of $250 million of
junk bonds. Prosecutors charge he violated California securities
laws in defrauding more than 20,000 investors.
   The criminal charges are not his only legal problem.
   Federal regulators last year filed a $1.1 billion racketeering
suit, the largest bank fraud suit in U.S. history, to try to
recover the money Keating is alleged to have looted from Lincoln.
   Last month, federal officials also took legal action against
Keating and five of Lincoln's top officers in an attempt to recoup
$40.9 million in losses from three sour business deals.
   Keating has denied wrongdoing, saying he is being singled out by
``malicious bureaucrats'' who don't understand the complexities of
the financial deals he attempted.
   The Lincoln failure is part of an S&amp;L debacle that could cost
taxpayers $500 billion with interest over 40 years.
   Leach, a member of the House Banking Committee, called it ``the
biggest bank heist in history - one that goes beyond the bank
vaults to pick the pocket of every American.''
   Others, like Keating, who face charges or investigations:
   - Edwin ``Fast Eddie'' McBirney was indicted in July on 17
counts of bank fraud and other charges for the way he ran Sunbelt
Savings Association, also known as Gunbelt Savings, in Dallas. Its
failure in 1988 could cost the taxpayers $2 billion.
   Federal prosecutors said he spent $1.3 million on Halloween and
Christmas parties in 1984 and 1985. At a 1984 Halloween bash in his
back yard, McBirney dressed up as a king and served his guests
antelope and lion meat.
   The government also said an audience of Sunbelt executives and
borrowers hired Las Vegas prostitutes as striptease dancers who
engaged in sex acts with them.
   - Don Dixon was indicted in June on 38 conspiracy and fraud
counts in the 1987 collapse of the Vernon Savings and Loan in
Vernon, Texas, which will cost taxpayers at least $1.3 billion.
   The government said Dixon used S&amp;L funds to pay for political
contributions, hire prostitutes, take hunting trips and rent a
beach home. The S&amp;L had a luxury yacht and a fleet of five planes
worth $6 million. It also paid the $22,000 tab for Dixon's
gastronomic tour of European restaurants.
   Eight Vernon officers have already been convicted, including
Chairman Woody Lemons, who began serving a 30-year jail term in
June. The sentence is the stiffest to date for an S&amp;L officer.
   - D.L. ``Danny'' Faulkner of the Empire S&amp;L in Mesquite, Texas,
and six other defendants were charged with fraudulently inflating
land values in a $135 million condominium deal north of Dallas.
   Their first trial ended in a hung jury last year. A second trial
is pending.
   Prosecutors said they lavished themselves with jets, expensive
watches and a $4 million mansion. Faulkner reportedly gave mink
coats and Mercedes cars as Christmas gifts. He tipped waitresses
$100.
   In Florida, David Paul has not been charged with breaking the
law. But he was ousted during a federal takeover this year of
CenTrust in Miami, Florida's largest thrift, after the state
alleged he inappropriately spent $45 million of CenTrust's money.
   Paul imported six French chefs for a 1988 dinner of truffle soup
and Beluga caviar, decorated his home with a $13.2 million painting
by Peter Paul Reubens that was paid for with S&amp;L money, entertained
actress Elizabeth Taylor with a party aboard his $7 million yacht,
drove a Mercedes limo and had a boat called Bodacious.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900922-0002 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-22-90 1331EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-Children Bjt   09-22 0622</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Children, Bjt,0788</SECOND>
<HEAD>Jordan's Children Imperiled By Economic Crunch Brought on By
Crisis</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SYDNEY RUBIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BENI HAMIDE, Jordan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   High on a barren mountaintop
overlooking the Dead Sea, Aisha Halifa listens to the evening
newscast on the Persian Gulf crisis on a transistor radio and fears
for her children.
   She knows that no matter what happens next in the confrontation
with Iraq, they are going to suffer the economic consequences of
the crisis.
   Jordan, its economy already in perilous shape and now burdened
with hundreds of thousands of refugees, is staring disaster in the
face.
   Rebecca Salti, Utah-born director of Save the Children in
Jordan, said that even if the crisis does not flare into war,
Jordanian children will be going hungry within a matter of months.
   ``We're just trying to figure out how to get through the
winter,'' she said. ``It's going to be tough ... There will be food
shortages or the inability to buy food by late winter or early
spring.''
   The crisis has devastated Aisha Halifa's family in Beni Hamide,
25 miles southwest of Amman. She and about 600 other women in a
cluster of Bedouin villages in the mountains weave rugs for sale to
tourists. But the visitors aren't coming any more because of the
fear of war.
   Her family raises goats and has a few olive trees. But it was
the income from her weaving that paid for second-hand clothes,
school supplies and medical care for her children.
   Until early August, she received some money from her 23-year-old
son working in Kuwait. But he fled the Iraqi invasion and came
home, along with 120,000 of his countrymen, suddenly poor and
unemployed.
   Before the crisis, unemployment in Jordan was at 15 percent.
Now, there's almost no chance that Aisha's son or husband will find
work.
   ``Families won't have money to take their children to the
doctor, everything will go into food. They won't be able to buy
shoes, erasers or notebooks to keep the kids in school,'' Ms. Salti
said.
   Already, Ms. Halifa can't afford a visit to the clinic for her
son who has a scalp disease. Within weeks there won't be enough
money for school supplies. The girls will be forced to drop out so
their brothers can go on a little while longer. By spring, there
might not even be food.
   ``Even professionals, people who have studied and live in Amman,
are having trouble now,'' she said, tugging at a steel-gray curl
falling from under her brown headscarf. ``If they can't make it,
how can we? I don't know what we're going to do. I'm frightened for
my children.''
   The U.N. International Children's Emergency Fund is worried too.
   ``Children will be the first victims, the hardest hit and the
ones most overlooked by the international community,'' said Nigel
Fischer, UNICEF's deputy regional director in Amman.
   The impact will extend far beyond Jordan. Leila Bisharat,
UNICEF's chief of programs for the Middle East, says similar
hardships will confront children in impoverished nations whose
fathers once sent paychecks home from Kuwait.
   ``Every one of the wage earners who've fled once sent money home
to support an extended family. Kuwait was their one lifeline, and
now that's gone,'' she said.
   Bangladesh, Sri Lanka, India and the Philippines are
ill-prepared to absorb the hundreds of thousands of returning
refugees or help their families.
   For these countries, the months ahead appear bleak. The Persian
Gulf standoff is pushing their already fragile economies closer to
disaster.
   ``We have all over the world four to six million children who'll
now have no source of income,'' Mrs. Bisharat said. ``We're all
holding our breath for what could be a catastrophe.''
   Jordan alone will lose $400 million in workers' pay this year,
the Finance Ministry says. The number of people living below the
World Bank-defined poverty line of $1,600 a year could jump from 25
percent to 40 percent by spring, experts say.
   Half of Jordan's 3.1 million people are under 15 years old. Milk
is already being rationed and UNICEF says it has already seen a
slight increase in malnutrition in the poorest of Amman's
neighborhoods, packed with Palestinian refugees.
   ``These families were managing to feed their kids well, the kids
were looking healthy all across Jordan. We had just sort of made
it,'' said Mrs. Salti.
   ``The children were immunized, they were in school, the girls
were being educated and they were just beginning to bloom. In every
way, Jordan was coming into its own.''
   ``Now,'' she said, ``we'll be lucky if these children can pull
through.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900922-0003 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-22-90 1332EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-GulfRdp 5thLd-Writethru a0490 09-22 0817</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Gulf Rdp, 5th Ld-Writethru, a0490,0986</SECOND>
<HEAD>Saudi Arabia Expels Jordanian, Yemeni Envoys</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 11 grafs to UPDATE with Hussein speech, U.S.
charter taking off for London. Pickup 8th pvs, `Jordan and...
^LaserPhooos NY5,6,7</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By JEFF DONN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Jordan's King Hussein declared today that his country would
never recognize Iraq's occupation of Kuwait as legitimate and urged
the United States to get out of Saudi Arabia ``within the shortest
period of time.''
   His address to the American people, televised by CNN from the
Jordanian capital of Amman, came hours after reports that Saudi
Arabia had ordered ordered nearly all envoys to leave Yemeni and
Jordanian embassies in Saudi Arabia.
   In Washington today, top finance officers from the world's seven
richest industrial democracies met to seek ways to stave off the
specter of world recession as a result of soaring oil prices
sparked by the gulf conflict.
   Another flight of American civilians took off from Iraq today.
The State Department had said it was to be the last U.S. charter
planned from Baghdad and it advised all Americans wanting to leave
to sign up.
   U.S. officials said the Boeing 707 will stop in London and
continue to Raleigh, N.C., arriving Sunday.
   In Beijing, at the opening of the Asian Games, Kuwait's
team-in-exile won cheers today from tens of thousands of
spectators. Iraq, which took over Kuwait on Aug. 2, was barred from
the event.
   In another development, Nigeria announced today it was joining
other nations imposing U.N. sanctions against Iraq. Moslem
fundamentalists in Nigeria have raised angry protests over the U.S.
military presence in the gulf.
   Speaking from his palace, the Jordanian monarch said he played
no role in the planning of the Iraqi invasion of Kuwait on Aug. 2
and said his country ``stands against forcible acquisition of
territory.'' He said Jordan does not recognize Israel's occupation
of the West Bank and the Gaza Strip and would not recognize Iraq's
annexation of Kuwait.
   He also said ``the presence of allied forces'' in Saudi Arabia
``must be terminated within the shortest possible period of time.''
   Earlier Saturday, word of the Saudi expulsion order against 20
Jordanian diplomats came from a senior Jordanian official in Amman.
The diplomatic sources in Saudi Arabia said all nearly all the
staffers from the Jordanian and Yemeni embassies would be expelled.
The sources spoke on condition of anonymity.
   When asked about the report of expulsions, Hussein said it was
``a fabricated story.''
   Jordan and Yemen have been seen as weak links in the embargo
against Iraq, and have failed to support the multinational force
deployed in Saudi Arabia to protect the oil-rich kingdom after
Iraq's invasion of Kuwait. Pro-Iraqi demonstrations have broken out
in both Jordan and Yemen.
   Today's economic gathering in Washington brought together
finance ministers and central bank presidents from the United
States, Japan, West Germany, Britain, France, Canada and Italy.
   The meeting comes as oil prices pushed above $35 per barrel
Friday on the futures market, posting an all-time high. And the
World Bank said a war in the Mideast might push oil prices to $65 a
barrel.
   The price was about $20 a barrel before Iraq invaded oil-rich
Kuwait on Aug. 2 in a dispute over oil, land and money, bringing on
a U.N. embargo against Baghdad.
   The talks, with Treasury Secretary Nicholas Brady and Federal
Reserve Chairman Alan Greenspan as hosts, were being held in
conjunction with the annual meetings of the 152-nation
International Monetary Fund and World Bank.
   Meanwhile, Syrian President Hafez Assad arrived in Iran today
for talks diplomats expected to focus on the standoff in the gulf
and Western hostages in Lebanon, where both countries are
influential. It was his first visit since Iran's 1979 Islamic
revolution.
   Assad is a rival of Iraq's Saddam Hussein. Iran and Iraq have
made recent moves to formally settle their 1980-88 war, but Iran
still opposes the Iraqi invasion of Kuwait.
   Saddam, in an interview published today, blamed the U.S. buildup
for Iraq's decision to annex Kuwait.
   ``Kuwait is now ours,'' the Istanbul daily Milliyet quoted him
as saying. ``We might have refrained from taking such a decision if
the U.S. troops were not massed in the region with the threat of
invading us.''
   Iraq's hostility toward Egypt, which has joined in the
multinational military effort against it, was reflected in an
official Iraqi newspaper today. It warned that Egyptian President
Hosni Mubarak will meet the same fate as his assassinated
predecessor, Anwar Sadat.
   The official Iraqi news agency, monitored in Nicosia, Cyprus,
quoted the Al-Jumhuriya newspaper as branding Mubarak a U.S.
puppet.
   The incident came one day after official Egyptian media reported
that Iraq had ordered the expulsion of several Egyptian diplomats,
including the military attache.
   Cairo Radio and Egypt's Middle East News Agency said Egypt
retaliated by expelling several Iraqi diplomats, including the
Iraqi military attache and an undisclosed number of his staff.
   Iraq today confirmed it has closed down military sections at 10
embassies, ordered the military attaches and their aides expelled
and restricted the movement of the remaining diplomats.
   An Iraqi Foreign Ministry announcement, carried by the official
Iraqi News Agency, listed the countries affected by the Iraqi
decision as the United States, Britain, France, West Germany,
Italy, Spain, the Netherlands, Greece, Saudi Arabia and Egypt.
   The move was the latest in a round of retaliatory expulsions by
Iraq and Western governments. The European nations' expulsions of
Iraqi diplomats were prompted by Iraqi raids on diplomatic premises
in occupied Kuwait; the Iraqi-ordered expulsions were in response
to the European moves.
   Western diplomats in Baghdad had reported Friday that 11
European Community nations were affected. However, today's Iraqi
report indicated five EC countries - Belgium, Denmark, Ireland,
Portugal and Luxembourg - would not be affected by the Iraqi order.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900922-0004 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-22-90 1618EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SAfrica-US     09-22 0336</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-SAfrica-US,0385</SECOND>
<HEAD>De Klerk Says He Won't Plead For End To Sanctions</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-South Africa-De Klerk, Bjt</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto JOH1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BARRY RENFREW</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PRETORIA, South Africa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President F.W. de Klerk said
Saturday he will not plead with President Bush this week to lift
sanctions on his country and seeks only to explain his reform
policies.
   ``I'm not going hat in hand with the particular objective of
getting sanctions lifted,'' de Klerk said before leaving for the
first U.S. visit by a South African leader in 45 years.
   To protest white-minority rule, most Western nations have placed
sanctions on South Africa, including severing air links and
limiting trade.
   De Klerk said he expected sanctions to be lifted as the South
African government moved toward power-sharing.
   ``I think many people (in the United States) are still looking
at South Africa through glasses which they should have discarded by
now,'' said de Klerk, who marked his first anniversary in office on
Thursday.
   De Klerk's three-day visit includes a scheduled meeting Monday
with Bush, whose administration has praised some of de Klerk's
reforms.
   The last South African leader to visit the United States was Jan
Smuts, who attended the formation of the United Nations in 1945. De
Klerk made several visits to the United States before becoming
president.
   De Klerk has been reopening South African ties with Western
nations after years of diplomatic isolation. De Klerk made a tour
of Western Europe earlier this year.
   South African officials hope the visit will convince U.S.
leaders of the complexity of the political situation in South
Africa and generate more international support for de Klerk's
reforms.
   De Klerk has been removing apartheid laws and says he wants the
5 million whites to share power with the 30 million blacks under a
new constitution.
   Although Bush and other U.S. officials have praised de Klerk's
efforts, various groups in the United States remain critical of the
white-led government. Anti-apartheid demonstrations are expected
while de Klerk is in Washington.
   De Klerk also is scheduled to seek U.S. support for proposals
for an 11-nation southern African economic confederation. South
Africa, which has the most powerful economy in the region, believes
it can help improve conditions in neighboring nations.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900922-0005 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-22-90 1643EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-India-Punjab     09-22 0357</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-India-Punjab,0397</SECOND>
<HEAD>Government Postpones Elections in Strife-Torn Punjab</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By VIJAY JOSHI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW DELHI, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The government has decided to postpone
elections in the state of Punjab, where Sikh militants are waging a
separatist war, officials said Saturday.
   The decision, adopted at a late-night Cabinet meeting Friday,
requires a constitutional amendment to extend the federal rule
which has been in effect since May 1987.
   Prime Minister V.P. Singh, who favored an election to reinstate
a local government, failed to reach a consensus among the parties
allied to his National Front government.
   Press Trust of India said the government will convene a special
session of Parliament Oct. 1 to amend the constitution to sanction
a further six-month extension of federal rule, formally known as
President's Rule. The current term expires Nov. 10.
   Under Indian law, the federal government may proclaim a state of
emergency and take over a state's administration for up to three
years by seeking the approval of Parliament every six months.
   Each extension beyond three years requires a constitutional
amendment passed by a two-thirds majority. The first such amendment
was passed last May.
   Friday's decision was taken after prolonged consultations
between Singh's minority National Front government, its leftist and
rightist allies and the argest opposition group, the Congress
Party.
   The Front's allies said the situation in Punjab was not
conducive for the polls. Former Prime Minister Rajiv Gandhi's
Congress Party left its position unclear.
   Congress' support is necessary to push through the amendment. If
the proposed legislation fails, the government will have to
announce a polling date before Oct. 6.
   The local parties in Punjab oppose federal rule, but some
factions have indicated they would boycott any election unless the
federal government grants more autonomy to the Sikh territory.
Underground Sikh militants, who have been fighting since 1982 for a
separate Sikh state, have stayed aloof of the issue.
   The militants' demand for independence grows out of their
complaint that the Sikhs are culturally and politically
discriminated by the Hindu-dominated government.
   Sikhs make up less that 2 percent of India's 880 million people
but form about 55 percent of Punjab population. Nationwide, Hindus
comprise more than 80 percent of the population.
   Sikh militants have been blamed for killing more than 2,000
people this year in Punjab and neighboring states.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900922-0006 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-22-90 1656EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Soviet-Economy     09-22 0327</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Economy,0359</SECOND>
<HEAD>Yeltsin, Gorbachev Clash Again Over Emergency Economic Powers</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ANDREW KATELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Boris Yeltsin, president of the Russian republic,
was back on a collision course with Mikhail S. Gorbachev Saturday
as he challenged the Soviet leader's request for new emergency
powers to rescue the economy.
   Yeltsin and Gorbachev have waged a three-year political feud
that has complicated Gorbachev's efforts to implement urgent
economic reform.
   In a statement read on the nightly television news program
``Vremya,'' the country's most widely watched program, Yeltsin and
other leaders of Russia's legislature called Gorbachev's request
for expanded powers ``unacceptable.''
   The leaders vowed to take ``all necessary measures to defend the
sovereignty and constitutional order of Russia.''
   Gorbachev asked the national legislature Friday to expand his
powers in order to begin an economic rescue plan without having to
go through the tedious process of seeking lawmakers' approval at
each step.
   Gorbachev seeks the authority to issue decrees on property,
management of the economy, prices and law enforcement.
   The national Supreme Soviet would have the power to recommend
Gorbachev revoke or modify the decrees. The Supreme Soviet is
scheduled to vote on the rquest Monday, the same day it is to
choose from among three economic plans.
   Yeltsin fears Gorbachev seeks the power to introduce
presidential rule in sovereign republics and disband their
governments. That request is not contained in Gorbachev's
resolution, but apparently was inferred from his comments to the
Supreme Soviet.
   Gorbachev said he needed the extra authority because the dire
state of the economy requires extreme action. The powers would be
used to implement one of the three plans to switch the Soviet Union
to a market economy.
   Yeltsin's celebrated clashes with Gorbachev date back to
criticism of reforms at a Communist Party meeting in 1987. The
attacks have escalated since Yeltsin was elected president of
Russia in May.
   The two politicians, the most prominent in the country, have
most recently battled over the rights of republics. The Russian
parliament has declared that its laws take priority over those
passed by the Soviet parliament.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900922-0007 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-22-90 1702EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Japan-Blacks     09-22 0568</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Japan-Blacks,0642</SECOND>
<HEAD>Japanese Official Compares Black Americans to Prostitutes</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Japan's justice minister compared prostitutes in
Japan to black Americans who move into white neighborhoods and
``ruin the atmosphere,'' but later said he regretted the remark.
   The comment was the latest in a series of remarks by Japanese
government officials that have offended American minority groups. A
Washington-based civil rights group called the comment by Justice
Minister Seiroku Kaqjiyama racist.
   ``It's a reprehensible and racist statement,'' said Ralph Neas,
executive director of the Leadership Conference on Civil Rights.
   Kajiyama made the commen at a news conference Friday after
observing a nighttime raid on the Shinjuku district of Tokyo, a
notorious red-light district.
   ``It's like in America when neighborhoods become mixed because
blacks move in, and whites are forced out,'' Kajiyama said after
watching police and immigration authorities arrest foreign women
for alleged prostitution.
   Prostitutes ``ruin the atmosphere'' of neighborhoods in the same
way, the 64-year-old minister said. A Justice Ministry spokesman
confirmed the comments Saturday after they appeared in Japanese
news reports.
   Shortly after the news conference, the ministry issued a
statement quoting Kajiyama as saying he meant to convey that people
living in the Shinjuku area feel insecure and have been
complaining.
   ``I intended to say that we must take measures to solve this
problem. I did not mean to talk about racial issues,'' Kajiyama
said in the statement.
   It said the minister's comments contained ``expressions that may
cause misunderstanding,'' but the statement did not contain an
explicit apology.
   In observing the police raid, Kajiyama was carrying out one of
his first official duties as justice minister. He was appointed
last week to replace Shin Hasegawa, who resigned because of
illness.
   Minority groups in the United States have criticized Japan in
recent years for similar statements made by Japanese politicians,
as well as advertising images and allegedly discriminatory hiring
practices by U.S.-based Japanese companies.
   Sensitivity to racial issues ``is a new ballgame for old
(Japanese) politicians, and they still don't know how to play it,''
said Patricia Steinhoff, a University of Hawaii sociologist doing
research in Japan.
   ``There is a very high acceptance of discrimination in Japan,''
she said. ``They don't realize this is out of bounds'' elsewhere.
   The discriminatory comments have sometimes arisen when
politicians and other Japanese praised the ``homogeneity'' of
Japan's population.
   American minority groups protested vigorously in 1986, when
then-Prime Minister Yasuhiro Nakasone said, ``On the average, the
United States is lower because of a considerable number of blacks,
Puerto Ricans and Mexicans.''
   Nakasone said he was referring to literacy rate. He later
apologized and said he realized his comment had ``offended many
Americans.'' But he did not retract his remarks.
   In 1988, Michio Watanabe, policy chief for the governing Liberal
Democratic Party, said American blacks have few qualms about going
bankrupt and implied they walk away from their debts.
   Prime Minister Noboru Takeshita and Watanabe later apologized
for his remark.
   But the furor ignited a debate in the U.S. Congress. The
Congressional Black Caucus accused three Japanese companies of
producing products and mannequins which allegedly show blacks in a
stereotypical and degrading light. The products included wide-eyed
black dolls with red-lipped grins.
   The latest controversy comes at a time when American attitudes
toward Japan have soured because of trade tensions and the belief
that Japan has been slow in providing support in the Persian Gulf
crisis, according to recent polls.
   Despite a law outlawing prostitution in Japan, it is a
flourishing underground industry.
   The numbers of foreign prostitutes have increased along with a
flood of workers entering or staying in Japan illegally to earn
highly valued yen. Mobsters are known to recruit foreign
prostitutes and operate bars and brothels where they work.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900922-0008 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-22-90 1716EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-FakeStudent     09-22 0288</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Fake Student,0344</SECOND>
<HEAD>Administrators Say Student Was Really Army Deserter</HEAD>
<DATELINE>EDWARDSVILLE, Ill. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A young man who administrators thought
was a promising high school football star turned out to be a
25-year-old U.S. Army deserter.
   ``He looked like a 17- or 18-year-old,'' said Edwardsville
Senior High School Principal Lawrence Busch. ``He certainly did not
look like a 25-year-old.''
   Speaking of the 6-foot-4, 210-pound student who called himself
Russ Jackson, Busch said: ``He dressed just like the kids.''
   Police said the young man was really Doyle R. McMahan of
Seviervile, Tenn., and that he'd was being held by the military on
a larceny charge when he escaped Sept. 5.
   For four days starting Sept. 10, McMahan took chorus, honors
English and other classes with the high school's other students,
Busch said.
   ``We had no problems. He was very polite, and we had a lot of
sympathy for his story,'' Busch said. ``He said he lost his mom and
dad in an auto accident, and the will established his brother as
his guardian.''
   Busch said McMahan told the school that he'd moved to the area
with his brother from Venice, Calif., and that he'd already been
recruited to play football at the University of Southern
California.
   Busch said it was the school's eagerness to get the student's
records and establish his eligibility for football that led them to
discover he was really several years older.
   When no one never showed up with a will to prove guardianship,
school officials confronted McMahan. He left quietly.
   Busch said when he learned McMahan was still in Edwardsville, he
alerted police. Police found McMahan Thursday evening as he was
headed out of town in a car reported stolen in Kentucky, police
Capt. David Bopp said.
   He had been living with the family of an Army buddy, Bopp said.
   Busch said McMahan's reason for enrolling at the school is still
a mystery.
   ``We asked him that question, and he said it was just a stupid
idea,'' Busch said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900922-0009 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-22-90 1852EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-Iran-Syria 2ndLd-Writethru a0565 09-22 0725</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Iran-Syria, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0565,0887</SECOND>
<HEAD>Sanctions, Hostages Top Assad's Agenda in Iran</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Leads with 5 grafs to UPDATE with comments from Rafsanjani and
Assad; picks up 3rd graf pvs, `Iran's official...'</NOTE>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf Rdp, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ANWAR FARUQI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NICOSIA, Cyprus (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Hafez Assad of Syria met
Saturday with his Iranian counterpart, Hashemi Rafsanjani, and
reportedly tried to persuade him not to send food and medicine to
Iraq in violation of the U.N. embargo.
   The talks in Tehran also were believed to have focused on the
fate of 13 Western hostages in Lebanon, according to news reports
and diplomats.
   Rafsanjani voiced concern about the presence of U.S. and other
Western military forces in the region, the official Islamic
Republic News Agency reported.
   ``We should not allow foreign forces and those hegemonist powers
who are all geared up to tighten their grip on vital oil resources,
the Persian Gulf, the Red Sea and other sensitive points of the
world to remain in the region,'' Rafsanjani said.
   Assad agreed that security would best be provided by countries
of the region, the news agency reported.
   Iran's official Tehran Radio did not say how long the two
presidents talked in private. It said they later opened their
discussions to their vice presidents and foreign ministers.
   The broadcast said Assad, who was on his first visit to Iran,
earlier visited the tomb of revolutionary leader Ayatollah Ruhollah
Khomeini on the outskirts of the Iranian capital.
   Assad, an archrival of Iraqi President Saddam Hussein, has
allied himself with the Americans and others against Saddam
following the Aug. 2 invasion of Kuwait.
   U.S. officials hope Assad's leverage in Tehran - stemming from
his support of Iran during the 1980-88 war with Iraq - will
persuade Rafsanjani not to help Saddam circumvent the trade
embargo.
   Diplomatic reports have suggested Iran may allow food and
medicine into Iraq, which agreed to formally end its war with Iran
last month. That freed tens of thousands of troops from Iraq's
eastern border for redeployment in southern Iraq and occupied
Kuwait.
   Assad, who met last week with Secretary of State James A. Baker
III, was believed to be carrying a message for Rafsanjani from
Washington, asking what it would take for Tehran to abide by the
sanctions.
   He was also expected to stress to Iran that the U.S.
intervention in the Persian Gulf is aimed solely at forcing Saddam
out of Kuwait and will not be permanent, according to diplomatic
sources who requested anonymity.
   Syria stands to gain Western aid for its ramshackle economy and
political support withheld in the past because of alleged links to
terrorism, they said.
   Arriving at Tehran's Mehrabad airport for his first visit to
Iran, Assad said he was happy to be among his ``dear brethren,''
Tehran Radio reported.
   Tehran Radio, monitored in Cyprus, quoted Assad as saying he was
looking forward to meeting Iran's spiritual leader, Ayatollah Ali
Khamenei.
   Assad said his talks in Tehran will cover bilateral issues, the
gulf crisis and ``ways of confronting Zionism,'' the Islamic
Republic News Agency reported. He made no reference to the Western
hostages held by pro-Iranian militants in Lebanon, where Syria is
the main power broker.
   But the English-language Tehran Times, which reflects government
thinking, said Saturday it was ``coordination between the Islamic
Republic and Syria, as well as the application of their spiritual
influence, which led to the release of some Western hostages in
Lebanon.''
   The statement was an apparent reference to Iran's role in the
release last April of American educators Robert Polhill and Frank
Reed.
   Hours after Assad's visit was announced Tuesday, Javad Mansoori,
Iran's ambassador in Pakistan, said that some of the Western
hostages could be released within days.
   Diplomats in Damascus and Tehran have said the hostages' plight
will be a main topic in Assad's meetings with Rafsanjani.
   Most of the hostages - six Americans, four Britons, two West
Germans and an Italian - are held by Shiite factions linked to the
fundamentalist Hezbollah, or Party of God, Tehran's main ally in
Lebanon.
   The hostages include journalist Terry Anderson, 42, the
longest-held captive. Anderson, chief Middle East correspondent for
The Associated Press, was kidnapped on March 16, 1985.
   Assad discussed the hostage issue with Baker in Damascus last
week.
   Setting aside more than a decade of hostility with the United
States, Assad has sent about 4,000 troops t join the U.S.-led
multinational force in Saudi Arabia. Baker won a pledge from Assad
to send another 15,000 soliders.
   Assad will try to gauge the seriousness of Iranian suggestions
it may dispatch food and other essentials to Iraq.
   Some analysts have seen the Iranian threats as a ploy to secure
Western aid.
   Rafsanjani has sought the return of Iranian assets frozen by
Washington as a condition for improving relations and any
intervention on behalf of the Western hostages.
   On Friday, the United States paid $200 million to Iran for
undelivered American weapons ordered before the ouster of the late
Shah Mohammad Reza Pahlavi in 1979, Western diplomats said.
   Tehran says it has about $11 billion worth of assets in the
United States. But U.S. officials say the figure is considerably
lower.

</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900922-0010 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-22-90 1931EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a BC-DesertTemp     09-22 0050</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Desert Temp,0021</SECOND>
<DATELINE>BAHRAIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Temperature and sky conditions for Saturday.
   Dhahran, Saudi Arabia - Clear, low 75, high 97.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
</Collection>
