<Collection>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0001 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 2338EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-LostCity     07-15 0338</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Lost City,0348</SECOND>
<HEAD>British Explorer To Search For Lost City In Arabia</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MEREDITH CAMPBELL</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MUSCAT, Oman (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A 10-man team of British and American
explorers has begun a search for the lost city of Ubar, which is
believed to have been swallowed by shifting Arabian sands 2,000
years ago.
   The team, headed by Sir Ranulph Fiennes, arrived Sunday and will
explore the southern reaches of the vast Rub al-Khali, or Empty
Quarter, desert.
   Ubar is described in the Koran, Islam's holy book, as ``a
many-columned city ... whose like has never been built in the whole
land.''
   The city is also mentioned in the ``Arabian Nights'' as famous
for its lavish royal court, lush palm groves and fine camels and
horses.
   Other references in ancient texts place it close to the
frankincense groves of southern Arabia and describe it as a great
caravan trade center.
   It is believed to have disappeared during a severe sandstorm in
30 B.C.
   The six-day reconnaissance for the ancient city was to begin
today.
   Fiennes said he first reconnoitered the desert 22 years ago when
he was a British Army captain attached to the Omani Army.
   Researchers have pinpointed eight likely locations for the lost
city. These are based on space technology data supplied by NASA, as
well as on medieval Arabic texts and travelers' tales from the
early 20th century.
   Remote sensing by sand-penetrating radar aboard the U.S. space
shuttle Challenger in 1984 indicated the existence of a buried
roadway stretching for 60 miles in the desert north of Oman's
westernmost Dhofar province.
   Geologists at the U.S. Jet Propulsion Laboratory in Pasadena,
Calif., also observed features they believe may be caused by a
buried site.
   Guided by light aircraft, Fiennes' exploration team will use
desert vehicles to traverse the Rub al-Khali dunes, which rise more
than 600 feet.
   The ruler of Oman, Sultan Qaboos, has ordered his desert-trained
police to assist and if the lost city is located, it will be
excavated under the auspices of Oman's antiquities department.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0002 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 2338EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Lite-CapybaraReturns     07-15 0206</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Lite-Capybara Returns,0213</SECOND>
<HEAD>Giant Rodent Eludes Captors, Returns Home on its Own</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WEST PALM BEACH, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two months of freedom were
apparently all Fatlip the capybara could take.
   On a dark and stormy Friday night, the 130-pound Amazon rodent
slipped back inside the fence around Palm Beach County's Dreher
Park Zoo, using the very hole from which she fled.
   ``It's not surprising,'' general curator Sally Lieb said
Saturday. Capybaras at the zoo are secure and well-fed.
   Fatlip, who resembles an overgrown guinea pig, got the nickname
from an accident that gave it a swollen lip.
   The animal escaped May 10, getting out of the capybara pen by
swimming under a fence in a canal bodering the enclosure, then
finding a hole left by vandals in the park's north fence.
   She was spotted many times while roaming free, but zoo officials
soon stopped trying to capture her, saying a capybara's watery
lifestyle made it difficult.
   Park officials didn't mend the outside fence in hopes Fatlip
would return, and footprints indicate she'd been casing the zoo for
a month.
   And although Fatlip is back in the zoo, she's still not back in
her pen.
   ``It's real hard to sneak up on her,'' Ms. Lieb said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0003 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 0117EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Albania 2ndLd-Writethru a0604 07-15 0806</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Albania, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0604,0827</SECOND>
<HEAD>First Albanian Refugees Reach Heidelberg</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 7 grafs to UPDATE with ALbanians arriving in
Turkey. Pick up 5th graf pvs, `About 4,500...'</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto BRI1</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Albania-Change, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PAUL VERSCHUUR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HEIDELBERG, West Germany (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Thousands of weary but jubilant
Albanian refugees savored freedom Saturday and set about their new
lives.
   Albanians who had sought refugee at the West German Embassy in
the Albanian capital, Tirana, were sent to 14 destinations across
West Germany. About 125 arrived in Heidelberg, a city of 130,000
about 60 miles south of Frankfurt on the Neckar river.
   The refugees, mostly young men and a few women and children,
looked happy but exhausted after the 26-hour trip. They waved their
hands in victory.
   ``We are leaving our country because we don't want the
Communists,'' said Enkeo Halili, a 24-year-old mechanic as he
stepped from the train. ``We are young ... we are poor. We've never
even seen a discotheque.''
   Those sentiments were echoed by Albanians who arrived early
Sunday in Turkey aboard a Turkish Airlines DC-9 sent to Albania by
the Turkish government.
   ``We want to live in a free society. We want to have our
political and legal rights,'' said Arben Shanja, 28, a physics
teacher from Shkoder who fled Albania with his wife and 2-week-old
daughter.
   They were among a group of 76 Albanians who arrived at Ankara's
Esenboga airport, carrying a few belongings in plastic bags. The
refugees looked tired but waved and made victory signs as they
waited to go through passport control.
   About 4,500 Albanians were evacuated in a boatlift across the
Adriatic Sea to Brindisi, Italy, on Friday. Three trains picked up
the 3,000 Albanians who had sought refuge in the West German
Embassy. In Basel, Switzerland, they were sent on smaller trains to
14 different West German cities.
   It was still unclear how many wanted to stay in West Germany and
how many wished eventually to go to third countries. Many have said
they hope to go to the United States.
   Other refugees brought from Albania in the boatlift chose to
remain in Italy, and 544 were shipped on to Marseille, France.
   The French-chartered Yugoslav ferry Orient Star had been
scheduled to dock Saturday. But it was delayed until Sunday because
a 21-year-old pregnant woman had to be evacuated from the ship to
an Italian hospital. Her condition was not immediately known.
   Also Saturday, an Albanian couple was married on board.
Afterward, other refugees joined together to sing an Albanian
wedding song.
   Saturday was Bastille Day, France's national holiday. It was
marked aboard the Orient Star by a member of the French delegation,
which told the Albanians of its meaning and explained the
independence they would have in their new country.
   Also Saturday, the 56 Albanians sheltered in the Polish Embassy
in Tirana were flown to Warsaw. Another 39 who sought refuge in the
Hungarian Embassy were flown to Budapest and on the same plane were
five who took refuge at the Bulgarian Embassy. They traveled on to
the Bulgarian capital of Sofia.
   A Turkish Airlines plane on Saturday was to pick up the 57
refugees at the Turkish Embassy in Tirana, the Anatolia news agency
reported in Ankara.
   ``There was no way to live,'' said Avni Azizi, a 23-year-old
Albanian tailor, of his Communist homeland. ``We all think that at
the most in one year the whole Albanian people will be free.''
   The refugees began crowding into foreign embassies in Tirana two
weeks ago, seeking to flee Albania, which has resisted the kinds of
sweeping democratic reforms that have radically altered other East
European countries.
   The Albanian government has introduced only limited reforms,
including some religious freedom and travel abroad, which Albanians
were not permitted for 45 years.
   One 29-year-old refugee, who asked that only his first name be
used, said Westerners could not understand what life was like in
Albania, Europe's last hard-line Stalinist state.
   ``To understand this regime you have to live there. They want to
systematically destroy spiritual life ... turn us into robots,''
Gijon said.
   He said Albanians began rushing foreign embassies after they
learned a family that had lived for years in the Italian Embassy
had been allowed to leave the country.
   News of the family's May 16 release was broadcast on Italian
television, which many Albanians receive, he said.
   Many other refugees also referred to the Popa family, which
sought refuge in the Italian Embassy in December 1985.
   In Heidelberg, the refugees were given food and clothing. Most
were taken to a former clinic that until recently housed East
German refugees.
   But the German Red Cross said 10 of the 125 were sick and would
be taken to hospitals. Carl Bauer, a Red Cross spokesman in Bonn,
said they were suffering from fever, diarrhea and weakness.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0004 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 0128EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-SubmergedCar     07-15 0254</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Submerged Car,0263</SECOND>
<HEAD>Car Carrying Six People Runs Into Creek; Four Killed</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PEQUEA, Pa. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A car carrying six people veered off a
highway into a rain-swollen creek Saturday night and sank, killing
four young children, officials and witnesses said.
   Witnesses said the station wagon ran into the north side of the
Pequea Creek in this southeastern Pennsylvania town and submerged
about 40 feet out into the water at about 9:40 p.m.
   The driver, Donald Duncan, 27, of Lancaster, suffered critical
injuries, and a 13-year-old girl, Heather Cunrod, who swam to shore
as the car sank, was in serious condition, said officials at
Lancaster General Hospital.
   The children who died were identified as Timothy Cunrod, 3,
Jennifer Cunrod, 7, Donald Duncan, 2, and Jessica Duncan, 6.
   Assistant Fire Chief Brian Sullenberger said rescuers pulled the
occupants out after winching the car to shore.
   The car veered off a highway and crossed a parking lot before
entering the creek near a railroad bridge. Witnesses said they
didn't see brake lights before the car drove out into the water.
   Sullenberger said the driver apparently tried to kick out the
windshield but failed. A fire department vehicle arrived and pulled
the car back to shore.
   The creek, a tributary of the Susquehanna River, was running
high and the water was muddy because of recent rain.
   Kevin Wimer, manager of the Pequea Boat Club, said he watched as
the car drove into the water.
   ``It was like they never knew the creek was there,'' Wimer said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0005 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 0142EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-CampHostage     07-15 0225</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Camp Hostage,0229</SECOND>
<HEAD>Man Kills Camper, Takes Another Hostage Before Being Killed by
Police</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CAMAS VALLEY, Ore. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A police sharpshooter on Saturday shot
to death a gunman who killed a camper and took another hostage for
13 hours at a campground in southern Oregon, authorities said.
   Douglas County District Attorney Jack Banta said an unidentified
man shot and killed Larry Kaun, a 42-year-old fisherman from
Anchorage, Alaska, when Kaun tried to stop him from breaking into a
converted bus at Bear Creek Campground late Friday.
   The man then entered the bus, and held the occupant, Carol
Mensinger, 40, at gunpoint, Banta said.
   The campground, located about 20 miles east of Myrtle Point, was
evacuated as sheriff's deputies and state troopers tried to
negotiate with the hostage-taker.
   Contact between the gunman and authorities ceased about 5:30
a.m. Saturday. At 12:55 p.m., a state police officer felled the
assailant with a single shot from a .308 caliber rifle, Banta said.
   Mensinger escaped injury, and was treated at a hospital and
later released. She had been camping with at least two children,
both of whom had were sleeping outside the bus when the standoff
began, Banta said.
   Kaun had been camping with his 12-year-old son, who witnessed
his father's shooting, police said.
   It was not immediately known whether the gunman knew either
Mensinger or Kaun.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0006 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 0834EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i BC-India-Politics     07-15 0212</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-India-Politics,0219</SECOND>
<HEAD>Indian Prime Minister Withdraws Resignation</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW DELHI, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Prime Minister V.P. Singh withdrew his
offer to resign after conferring Sunday with leaders of his
National Front alliance, the group's chairman announced.
   The announcement, by N.T. Rama Rao, appeared to end a weekend of
crisis for the minority government.
   Rao spoke with reporters after Cabinet ministers and leaders of
the five parties comprising the National Front convened at Singh's
house.
   The crisis was touched off by a power struggle that pitted Singh
and most other alliance leaders against Deputy Prime Minister Devi
Lal who had forged ahead with efforts to advance his son's
political career in Haryana state.
   The son, Om Prakash Chautala, was reappointed chief minister of
Haryana on Thursday, two months after he was forced to resign when
more than a dozen people were slain during a local election in his
constituency.
   Three of Singh's Cabinet ministers resigned Friday in protest of
Chautala's political reincarnation. On Saturday, Singh offered his
own resignation and six more ministers resigned.
   Singh sent his offer of resignation to Sommappa Rayappa Bommai,
president of the Janata Dal, the largest party in the National
Front.
   Bommai rejected it, but Singh declined to withdraw the offer
until the National Front meeting Sunday afternoon.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0007 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 1143EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--Queen'sDemands     07-15 0174</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Queen's Demands,0177</SECOND>
<HEAD>Former Italian Queen Wants Husband's War Pension</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ROME (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The former queen of Italy wants the government to
pay her husband's war pension and interest dating back to 1945,
before the royal family was forced into exile, news reports said
Sunday.
   Maria Jose's husband, the former King Umberto II, died in 1983.
During World War II, he commanded the Italian forces on the
southern front. He reigned for 26 days before the monarchy was
abolished in a 1946 referendum.
   Italian newspapers said the pension claim by Umberto's widow,
who lives in Switzerland, will be evaluated by the Council of
State. Under the Constitution, however, the wealth of former royals
was to be confiscated.
   There was no indication of how much money the claim involved.
   A constitutional ban on Maria Jose's entry into Italy was lifted
in 1987 and she has since visited the country. The couple's son,
Victor Emmanuel, has been campaigning for permission to return to
Italy.
   Kings from the Piedmont-based House of Savoy ruled Italy from
1861-1946.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0008 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 1145EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--MineBlast     07-15 0139</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Mine Blast,0144</SECOND>
<HEAD>Coal Mine Explosion Kills 45</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An explosion at a coal mine in northeast China
killed 45 miners and injured 11, news reports said Sunday.
   The cause of Friday's blast at the mine in Shandong province was
not immediately clear, according to a provincial radio report
carried by the monitoring service of the British Broadcasting Co.
   Rescue workers managed to pull 56 people alive from the mine in
central Shandong's Xinwen county, 90 miles south of the provincial
capital of Jinan. Five of the injured were in serious condition,
the report said.
   Most Chinese coal mines lack modern equipment and safety
provisions. Official data indicates that 1,780 people died in
mining accidents last year.
   In May, the government said an average of 14 miners are killed
for every million tons of coal mined.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0009 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 1147EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--LandMine     07-15 0108</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Land Mine,0109</SECOND>
<HEAD>Report Says Insurgent Landmine Killed 11 People In Burma</HEAD>
<DATELINE>RANGOON, Burma (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A land mine planted by rebels blew up a
passenger vehicle in southern Burma, killing 11 people and wounding
14 others, a state-owned newspaper reported Sunday.
   The vehicle hit the land mine Friday near Thingannyinaung, 160
miles southeast of the national capital, Rangoon, the Working
People's Daily said.
   The newspaper blamed the Karen ethnic minority, which has been
fighting the government for greater autonomy over the past four
decades. The Karens have suffered heavy losses in government
offensives during the past two years.
   The newspaper account could not be independently confirmed.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0010 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 1154EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-S&amp;Ls-SpinControl     07-15 0703</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-S&amp;Ls-Spin Control,680</SECOND>
<HEAD>Critics Say Government Trying To Delay Bad News on S&amp;L Industry</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Presidential Kin Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVE SKIDMORE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Changes in how the government reports on the
health of the savings and loan industry amount to ``spin control''
designed to minimize the frequency with which bad news is delivered
to the public, economists say.
   Office of Thrift Supervision officials say they plan to begin
reporting financial data only for solvent, privately owned savings
institutions. Information on failed but still-operating thrifts
controlled by the government will be reported later by a separate
agency, the Resolution Trust Corp.
   Also, statistics on deposits and withdrawals at thrift
institutions, which previously had been released monthly, will be
put out quarterly. They will be released at the same time as
information on S&amp;L profits and losses, which has always come out
quarterly.
   Economists complain that the changes will make it more difficult
for financial analysts, journalists and the public to interpret the
condition of the industry as a whole in a timely manner.
   ``They're making it more difficult for the markets to get and
disseminate vital information,'' said economist Martin Regalia of
the National Council of Savings Institutions. ``That doesn't make
sense.''
   ``Data is best when it's reported as fully as possible, as
accurately as possible and as timely as possible,'' Regalia said
last week. ``What they're doing here is making information less
timely, and I think there's no excuse for that.''
   Even though the thrift office collects financial information
from both solvent and insolvent S&amp;Ls, it will relay the information
on the failed thrifts to the Resolution Trust Corp., which manages
those institutions until it can sell or close them.
   Financial analysts said it is valid for some purposes to look at
solvent and government-controlled S&amp;Ls separately. However, they
point out that the government-controlled thrifts remain open and
compete against the rest of the industry to attract deposits.
   ``Looking at them together is important because ... they are all
doing the same thing _ they are both making mortgages and taking
deposits,'' said Robert Litan of the Brookings Institution, a
Washington think tank.
   ``By just reporting data on the healthy part of the industry ...
(regulators) can report a number that says the thrift industry is
earning money, when it isn't. It's spin control,'' he said.
   Thrift office Director Timothy Ryan defended the reporting
changes.
   ``It's more appropriate for the RTC to put out information on
conservatorship institutions because they are the conservator,''
Ryan said.
   Thrift office officials also said the switch to quarterly
reporting of deposit flows will save money and reduce errors.
   ``Some of the monthly numbers are subject to so many
restatements ... that they're just not reliable and it's better to
put them out quarterly,'' Ryan said.
   Although the reports will be issued less frequently, the
information will still be available monthly to those who ask, he
said.
   But Bert Ely, a financial institutions analyst in Alexandria,
Va., said ``They're trying to be the good news boys. ... They're
treating the insolvent thrifts as if they had leprosy and pushing
them out of sight.''
   Although regulators did not list worry over deposit runs as a
reason for the new reporting procedures, Litan said he suspects
that is a factor.
   ``Maybe there's an implicit hope that if they don't remind
people constantly, people won't take their money out of thrifts,''
he said. ``They prefer ... to have as little bad news as they can
manage.''
   The policy shift follows a long lapse in reporting by the thrift
office. At this point in past years, the agency normally would have
issued monthly deposit flow reports current through May. And it
would have issued a profit or loss statement for the January-March
quarter.
   However, no information for 1990 has been released, although the
agency plans to issue deposit information for January and February
later this week.
   Thrift office officials said the delay occurred because many
S&amp;Ls were confused by new reporting forms, which were changed to
conform with new capital regulations passed as part of last year's
S&amp;L bailout law.
   Snafus with a new computer program for analyzing the data also
contributed to the delay, they said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0011 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 1154EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-EducatingWorkers     07-15 0708</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Educating Workers,690</SECOND>
<HEAD>Business Not Satisfied With Education Skills of New Workers</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TAMARA HENRY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Education Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Sixty-four percent of major U.S. companies are
not happy with the reading, writing and reasoning abilities of high
school graduates entering the work force, a poll of business
executives said.
   The National Alliance of Business survey found that 72 percent
of executives polled also thought new employees' math skills had
worsened in the last five years. Sixty-five percent said reading
skills decreased over the same period.
   Alliance President William Kolberg said the poll results should
worry everyone _ parents, students, educators and employers.
   ``We are on a collision course with the reality that America is
developing a second-class work force whose best feature in the
future compared with other nations will be low pay,'' Kolberg said
last week in an interview to discuss the survey results. ``Low
skill means low pay.''
   Kolberg said new attitudes and approaches were needed to prepare
Americans for work who do not attend college.
   ``We have abandoned the millions of kids who don't plan to
attend college,'' he said. ``Somewhere along the way, we lost
respect for the skills we now so desperately need in our factories
and on the front lines of our service industries.''
   Kolberg said about 82 million U.S. jobs don't require a college
degree, and filling those jobs may become impossible unless the
educational system is changed.
   ``The entire school enterprise needs to be restructured,
rethought and taken much more seriously,'' he said, pointing to the
national education goals established by President Bush and the
nation's governors.
   Kolberg was an assistant secretary of Labor and administrator of
the Employment and Training Administration from 1973-77.
   The poll, described by the alliance as the first to survey
officers either directly or indirectly responsible for the
recruitment of workers at the 1,200 largest U.S. corporations, said
only 36 percent of the officers were satisfied with the competency
of new employees entering the work force.
   Kolberg defined competency as being able to read beyond the
seventh grade level and compute math at higher than a fifth grade
level.
   The survey indicated companies _ many of which have more
challenging blue collar and secretarial work than in the past _
have to interview seven to eight applicants on average to find just
one acceptable employee.
   Personnel officers also said many of those who are hired require
too much training to become effective in their jobs. Forty-eight
percent were satisfied with the ability of new hires to be
retrained. Only 16 percent were satisfied with the educational
training of new employees.
   Kolberg said the survey documents much of the anecdotal evidence
discussed over the last few years.
   ``Most American companies, particularly smaller companies, have
not been able to adopt new forms of work organization because they
can't afford to spend money upgrading worker skills,'' Kolberg
said. ``Our competitors in Europe and Asia have increased
productivity by using these new methods of work. Our only response
to this competitive situation has been to lower wages.''
   The business alliance predicts that by the year 2000, an
estimated 5 million to 15 million manufacturing jobs will require
skills other than those being used today and that an equal number
of service jobs will be obsolete.
   Kolberg said parents must make sure their children attend school
and are prepared physically and emotionally to learn. Parents and
teachers must raise their expectations of student achievement.
   The weekly wages of high school graduates dropped from $387.24
in 1969 to $335.20 in 1989. The alliance attributes the 12 percent
drop to a loss in productivity by so-called frontline workers. It
compares with a wage gain of about 8 percent for a college graduate.
   The research was conducted in late April by North Coast
Behavioral Research Group of Cleveland, involving 500 of the
largest manufacturing firms in America, the largest 500 service
firms and the largest 200 privately owned companies. The poll had a
margin of error of 6 percentage points.
   The NAB was founded in 1968 under the direction of President
Lyndon Johnson and Henry Ford II to link businesses in a
partnership with education, labor, government and community-based
groups to help build a quality work force for the future.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0012 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 1202EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-WorldPoverty     07-15 0612</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-World Poverty,600</SECOND>
<NOTE>For release at 6:30 p.m. EDT</NOTE>
<HEAD>World Bank Aims to Reduce Ranks of Third World Poor by 300 Million</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CARL HARTMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Third World can reduce the number of its
poor to 800 million from today's 1.1 billion if the right policies
are followed over the next decade, according to World Bank
President Barber Conable.
   About one person in four among Third World countries can be
considered poor. But the ranks of the poor could be cut by nearly a
third by means of strict economic and social reforms, Conable said.
   Developed nations also should increase aid to their poorer
neighbors, he added.
   ``Strategy to reduce poverty should be one of the international
community's fundamental objectives in the 1990s,'' he told
reporters in advance of the release Sunday of the bank's annual
``World Development Report.''
   The 1990 issue is devoted to the problem of easing poverty,
which Conable said is the bank's main purpose. Owned by 151
countries, the bank is the biggest source of aid to the Third
World, lending more than $20 billion a year.
   The World Bank says anyone is poor if he or she earns less than
$370 a year. By that standard the average person in 25 countries is
poor, including Mozambique, where $100 a year is the average
earnings, and Kenya and Togo, where it is $370 yearly.
   Africa contains most of the areas where the average income falls
that low. But average income also is low in the world's two most
populous countries: China, at $330 a year; and India, $340. Figures
are for 1988.
   In the United States, the official poverty level for a single
person was $6,024 a year in 1988, and nearly 32 million people fell
below it.
   Conable said Third World governments should encourage private
business. He also wants them to contain inflation, get rid of
unnecessary public spending and allow realistic prices for farm
products, foreign currency, imports and exports. He wants them to
hold down deficits in their budgets and their balance of
international payments.
   Some Third World leaders are reluctant to follow such policies
on the ground that they make life more difficult for poor people in
the short run.
   Michel Camdessus, head of the International Monetary Fund, the
bank's sister organization, said in a recent speech: ``How do the
poor, who have little or no assets, fare when runaway inflation is
set loose by easy money policies? When factories close down because
of overvalued exchange rates? When there is no incentive to produce
crops because state monopolies pay prices that do not cover the
cost of production?''
   Camdessus said ``the poor are the first hit, the worst hit, the
least able to protect themselves.''
   Both Conable and Camdessus also urge the importance of safety
nets to protect the poorest people from the rising prices that may
result from the new policies.
   Conable proposed a two-pronged strategy against poverty:
emphasis on the use of labor, the Third World's most abundant
asset, to be mobilized by the incentives of the market; and
emphasis on providing health care and education.
   He said parts of the strategy had been tried successfully in
countries as different as Colombia and Indonesia, Chile and
Botswana.
   According to the bank's report, 58 of every 100 Indonesians had
incomes below the poverty line in 1970. By 1987, the number had
dropped to 17.
   Conable said it was inexcusable that rich countries were not
furnishing more aid.
   ``If developed countries cut their military spending by a mere
10 percent they could double their aid,'' he said.
   Conable said Third World nations also could cut military
spending.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0013 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 1203EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Vietnam-Tribe     07-15 0216</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Vietnam-Tribe,0220</SECOND>
<HEAD>Primitive Tribe of 169 People Live in Central Vietnam</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BANGKOK, Thailand (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A primitive tribe of 169 people whose
land was bombed by U.S. planes during the Vietnam War is living
deep in caves in the jungles of central Vietnam, state media said
Sunday.
   Members of the Ruc tribe wear loincloths made of tree bark and
``still retain almost intact the main attibutes of cavemen,'' the
official Vietnam News Agency said. It said the tribe lives in the
central province of Quang Binh.
   The Ruc, it said, have dark complexions and kinky hair _ unlike
the Chinese-looking majority ethnic group _ but their history
remains a mystery.
   The report said the tribe was discovered 30 years ago living in
caves by provincial border guards, who gave them rice, farm tools
and seeds and taught them to build shacks. They began living in
villages.
   ``But (then) came the American bombings against the Truong Son
range which was their natural habitat,'' it said. ``Frightened,
they fled into deep jungles and resumed cave dwelling.'' It said
that the government has been helping the tribe build new villages.
   A 1985 government-published guidebook said Vietnam has 53
nationalities besides the majority Viets, who account for 88
percent of the population. The minorities live mostly in mountain
areas.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0014 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 1204EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-PresidentialKin 1stLd-Writethru   07-15 0815</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Presidential Kin, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0641,790</SECOND>
<HEAD>For Some Presidents, It Is `Oh, Brother!'</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: This subs 9th and 12th grafs pvs to CORRECT that Neil Bush is
President Bush's son, not brother. Picks up 13th graf pvs.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By MIKE FEINSILBER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Maybe the safest thing is for a president to
be an only child, an orphan, unwed and celibate. Then he won't have
a family to get him in trouble.
   Presidential kin _ as George Bush is discovering _ sometimes put
the man in the White House on the spot.
   Ask Richard Nixon, who was taunted for years by Democrats
asking, ``What about the Howard Hughes loan?'' _ a reference to
business mogul Hughes' $205,000 loan to Nixon's kid brother. Donald
Nixon wanted the money to open a chain of restaurants selling
``Nixonburgers.''
   Ask Jimmy Carter, whose good-ol'-boy, beer-swilling brother,
Billy, used to issue profanity-laced observations from his bully
pulpit _ the gas station in Plains, Ga.
   Billy also put his name on a brand of beer that flopped, made
remarks that were denounced as racist or anti-Semitic, accepted
money from Libya and underpaid the Internal Revenue Service.
   It was Billy who, in a quote he admitted having swiped from his
mother, celebrated how a family can embarrass a president:
   ``I've got a mother who joined the Peace Corps at 68; a brother
who wants to be president; a sister who is a holy-roller preacher;
and another sister who rides around on motorcycles. I'm the only
sane one in the family.''
   And, of course, ask Bush.
   Just as the Democrats were despairing of ever finding an issue
to use against Bush, along came son Neil Bush and his links to the
Silverado Banking, Savings and Loan Association of Denver.
   For Democrats, Silverado is El Dorado, a chance to hang the S&amp;L
scandal on a Republican person.
   Neil, 34, was a director of Silverado, which collapsed at a cost
to taxpayers of $1 billion. He has been accused by federal
regulators of failing to disclose adequately his past business
relationship with major Silverado borrowers.
   The subject came up Wednesday. Bush affirmed his confidence his
son's integrity, but added, ``If the system finds he's done
something wrong, he will be the first to step up and do what's
right.''
   The president draws praise from historians for handling the
situation about as well as it can be handled.
   ``Obviously, George Bush isn't trying to cover up; he is a very
honorable man _ and I say that as a Democrat,'' said Frank Freidel,
biographer of Franklin D. Roosevelt.
   ``I think Bush handled it all right,'' added Arthur Schlesinger
Jr., biographer of John F. Kennedy.
   Schlesinger recalls that Jimmy Roosevelt, oldest of FDR's five
children, got in trouble with Joseph Kennedy, father of JFK.
   When Prohibition was repealed, Jimmy accompanied the elder
Kennedy to England where he got distribution rights to Haig &amp; Haig
Scotch. It looked fishy. ``It was thought,'' said Schlesinger,
``that Kennedy used Jimmy as an entree.''
   ``In the early days of the Republic, people didn't pay much
attention to president's families,'' Schlesinger added. ``John
Quincy Adams had a son who was an alcoholic. But I don't think the
press made much of those things then.''
   Nixon biographer Stephen E. Ambrose said the Democrats used the
Hughes loan effectively in the presidential election of 1960 and
again in the California gubernatorial race in 1962.
   Donald Nixon, thinking he had cost his brother the presidency in
1960, ``was in tears on election night,'' Ambrose said.
   Of the Hughes loan, he said: ``We still don't know what the
truth of the matter is.''
   Sam Houston Johnson, Lyndon's brother, had a drinking problem.
``He would go on a toot,'' recalled LBJ confidant Horace Busby.
``They might last days or months or years.''
   But basically, said Busby, Sam and his three sisters strove
mightily to avoid embarrassing their brother.
   Sam, he said, ``was a sweet guy. He was shy, extremely so.''
   He recalls that during the 1948 campaign, a restaurant hostess,
seeking to tell Sam there was a phone call for him, came up and
said: ``Mr. Johnson?''
   ``No,'' interrupted Sam. ``I'm his brother.''
   Freidel said most presidential relatives have been circumspect.
He thinks it is remarkable how few cause embarrassment considering
that ``children, brothers, in-laws are always being sought after
because they have the White House aura.''
   What's a president to do when a relative transgresses?
   ``Grin and bear it and not condone it if it involves serious
betrayal of the public trust,'' said Freidel.
   ``There's nothing you can do,'' said Ambrose. ``Hope for the
best. Pray. You surely can't interfere in any investigation. That's
the kiss of death, especially for a Republican president when so
many civil servants (who will be conducting the investigation) are
Democrats.''
   ``It is hard for any president to cover up, damn near impossible
if he is a Republican.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0015 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 1210EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--PLO-US     07-15 0164</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--PLO-US,0168</SECOND>
<HEAD>Central Council Meeting Postponed</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BAGHDAD, Iraq (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Palestine Liberation Organization has
postponed indefinitely a meeting of its Central Council that was
scheduled for July 18 in the Iraqi capital, a Palestinian official
said Sunday.
   Azzam Ahmed, the PLO's representative to Iraq, said the meeting
was called off ``to allow for more consultations.''
   He said no new date has been fixed for the meeting, which was
called to discuss President Bush's decision last month to suspend
an 18-month dialogue with PLO.
   Bush severed the dialogue in the wake of a failed seaborne
attack against Israel by the Palestine Liberation Front, one of
nine factions under the umbrella of the PLO. The United States said
PLO chief Yasser Arafat failed to sufficiently condemn the May 30
attack, in which four guerrillas were killed.
   The 80-seat Central Council serves as a go-between for the PLO's
ruling Executive Committee and the policy-making Palestine National
Council.
   The 450-seat PNC normally meets once a year.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0016 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 1220EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--LostPlane     07-15 0177</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Lost Plane,0180</SECOND>
<HEAD>Military Searching For Pilot Who Took Off Without Permission</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An air force pilot took off in a two-seater
patrol craft without permission and neither plane nor pilot could
be located after two days, the military said Sunday.
   Israeli newspapers said the army believed the pilot, a reserve
captain, crashed either on land or at sea after commandeering the
plane on Friday. The army first publicized the flight late Saturday
night.
   Military sources said it was the first time an Israeli air force
pilot had disappeared on an unauthorized flight.
   The army declined to speculate on the pilot's whereabouts or
motive. It said only that a search for the twin-engine West
German-made Dornier-28 aircraft was under way.
   ``The 33-year-old reservist pilot ... was awaiting orders to
leave on a reconnaisance mission when he took off without
permission Friday,'' an army statement said. ``Since then the army
has carried out widespread searches on land and sea.'' The pilot
was not identified.
   The missing aircraft is of a type often used for reconnaisance.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0017 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 1224EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BachelorRabbi     07-15 0301</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bachelor Rabbi,0309</SECOND>
<HEAD>Young Rabbi Told To Marry If He Wants His Job</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Israel's chief Sephardic rabbi has taken away
the job of one of the country's youngest rabbis, saying the
20-year-old bachelor must gain the ``experience of marital
relations'' before taking up his post.
   Chief Rabbi Mordechai Eliahu ``froze'' the credentials of Rabbi
Yaacov Avitan, who recently was chosen spiritual leader of Beit
Shikma, a farming community of about 1,000 in southern Israel,
rabbinate spokesman Shmuel Zaafrani said Sunday.
   Avitan's ``lack of experience with marital relations'' was a
main factor in the decision, said Zaafrani. He explained that
giving married couples advice about sexual matters was one of a
rabbi's duties.
   ``To do this, he has to know these matters from up close. A
doctor who hasn't done an internship would never be allowed to
treat any patients,'' Zaafrani said.
   He added that the ruling was more a matter of custom than Jewish
law. ``It is simply desirable for a rabbi to be married,'' he said.
   Avitan is one of the youngest men approved as a rabbi in Israel
and believed to be the youngest appointed to the post of community
rabbi. A community rabbi customarily has to be older than 24 and
married.
   Avitan said he agreed with the chief rabbi's decision.
   ``He's right. There has to be a certain order to things. It's
like a fresh recruit in the army doesn't become chief of staff in a
day,'' Avitan said in an interview.
   ``I will wait patiently until my match comes from heaven,'' he
said.
   Eliahu is chief rabbi to Israel's Sephardic community, Jews of
North African and Middle Eastern origin.
   Sephardic Jews make up about 60 percent of Israel's 3.5 million
Jews. Beit Shikma's residents are mainly Jews of Moroccan and
Libyan origin.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0018 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 1232EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Record-Suicide Bjt   07-15 0737</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Record-Suicide, Bjt,0757</SECOND>
<HEAD>Trial To Begin in Suit Alleging Record Album Led To Suicide</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SANDRA CHEREB</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>RENO, Nev. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A suit against a British rock band goes to
trial Monday alleging that a record contained subliminal messages
to ``do it'' and caused two troubled young fans to shoot themselves
in a deserted playground.
   Raymond Belknap, 18, held a sawed-off shotgun to his chin and
died instantly from a single blast that afternoon two days before
Christmas 1985.
   James Vance, 20, managed only to blow away the lower portion of
his face. Horribly mutilated, he lived three more years, underwent
repeated operations and fathered a child before his death on
Thanksgiving Day 1988 of complications from his injuries and a
reaction to medication.
   In one song by the popular heavy metal rock band, ``Beyond the
Realms of Death,'' the band sings: ``Yeah, I have left the world
behind. I am safe now in my mind. I'm free to speak with my own
mind. This is my life, this is my life, and I'll decide, not you.''
   But the trial beginning this week will focus not on what such
lyrics may have suggested, but whether there was a second,
all-but-inaudible set of lyrics whispered in the background as a
``subliminal message.''
   Attorneys for the Vance and Belknap's families say the two
formed a suicide pact after drinking beer, smoking marijuana and
listening to the ``Stained Class'' album over and over again.
   They will try to convince Washoe District Judge Jerry Carr
Whitehead that subliminal messages on the album, touting the devil
and encouraging listeners to ``do it, do it,'' convinced the two
friends that, as Vance allegedly told an investigator, ``the answer
to life is death.''
   Lawyers for Judas Priest and CBS Records will argue it was the
young men's troubled lives, including a history of drug and alcohol
abuse, psychiatric disorders and physical abuse, that pushed them
over the edge. They deny any subliminal messages exist or that the
band promotes Satan and suicide.
   ``I don't believe that we'd have had the support and following
that we've had for the past 17 years had we deliberately attempted
to contrive to create songs where people did harm to themselves,''
lead singer Robert Halford said in a 1988 deposition.
   Whitehead has already denied a defense motion to dismiss the
case on grounds the record was protected by the First Amendment,
saying that such protection exists for regular music and lyrics but
not ``secret hidden messages that the recipient does not know
exist.''
   The judge stressed that he has no knowledge of whether such
subliminal messages exist on ``Stained Class,'' but ruled attorneys
should be allowed to present their case to the court.
   The lawsuit is proceeding as a products liability case, accusing
the band and CBS Records of negligence and intentional and reckless
misconduct. It seeks unspecified punitive and compensatory damages.
   More than 100 witnesses are expected to testify during the
non-jury trial, which is expected to last four weeks.
   Band members will attend the trial, but attorneys said they have
been unable to locate the original, multitrack recording of the
album that could have made it easier to determine whether there
were subliminal messages.
   Attorneys for the families do not dispute that the two young men
were troubled. But they argue in court filings that because of
their faults, the two were ``susceptible, influenced and vulnerable
to the ideas, suggestions and emotions'' allegedly hidden in the
music.
   Voluminous court documents paint the youths' lives as
troublesome from early adolescence.
   In 1978, a school psychologist from Livermore Valley Unified
School District in California visited Vance's mother, Phyllis
Vance, to discuss concerns about his behavior.
   The psychologist's report concluded that a ``high possibility
existed for James to respond violently to stressful situations and
that this probability might increase as James is subjected to the
additional stresses of adolescence.''
   Vance was in the fifth grade at the time.
   Both he and Belknap dropped out of school in the 10th grade.
Records indicate they drifted between menial jobs, had several
brushes with the law, carried guns and dreamed of becoming
mercenaries.
   In 1984, Vance allegedly made phone calls threatening to kill
the mother and younger sister of his former girlfriend.
   And a week before his suicide, a complaint was filed against
Belknap charging him with animal torture for shooting a neighbor's
cat with darts from a blowgun.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0019 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 1248EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Poland-Analysis Bjt   07-15 0745</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Poland-Analysis, Bjt,0772</SECOND>
<HEAD>Privatization: Poles' Latest Step on the Road to Capitalism</HEAD>
<HEAD>AP News Analysis</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN DANISZEWSKI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WARSAW, Poland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Poland once again is at the vanguard of
reform in Eastern Europe, this time on the economic front.
   Last week's passage of a law to privatize all state-owned
businesses and industries may mean more dislocation for workers.
But it was being hailed as a key step on the road to capitalism.
   ``This is a historic event, equal to taking power away from the
Communists last year,'' said the pro-government Gazeta Wyborcza
newspaper. ``No neighboring country has reached this stage of
dismantling communism.''
   The 328-2 vote Friday showed parliament's conviction that most
people still want to move toward a market system, even though the
road has been bumpy.
   Farmers and workers have called on the Solidarity-led government
to soften its economic program. Solidarity leader Lech Walesa has
been pressing for speedier reforms. Consumers have been grumbling
about high prices, and workers have been laid off by the thousands.
   The surprisingly lopsided approval of the privatization measure
should bolster the embattled government of Prime Minister Tadeusz
Mazowiecki. It also marks a turning point in the radical economic
reform program begun Jan. 1.
   The plan's first phase focused on fighting inflation,
strengthening the currency and stabilizing the market by getting
goods back into stores.
   Like home builders, Poland's economic planners reasoned it was
necessary first to clear the ground. No one would open a business
in conditions of hyperinflation, shortages and worthless money.
   Using tight fiscal and monetary policies, the program got
results _ at a high social cost.
   Real average incomes fell nearly 40 percent, industrial output
fell by 30 percent and unemployment zoomed from virtually zero to
4.2 percent _ more than half a million workers.
   Now, with inflation tamped down to a manageable level, the
Polish zloty stable and empty shelves a fading memory, construction
of the new economic system begins.
   Mazowiecki and his economic chief, Deputy Prime Minister Leszek
Balcerowicz, spelled out their commitment to privatization from the
moment the Solidarity-led government was created in September.
   Rejecting a ``third path'' between capitalism and communism,
Mazowiecki said he would seek an economy based on ``tried and
proven'' Western methods.
   Under the old Communist government, Polish industry in theory
was owned by the state. In practice, there were no owners _ no one
to fire idlers, no one to invest for greater efficiency, no one
impassioned to make profits.
   Restoring ownership was seen as the key to economic renaissance.
   ``Common interests and mutual care for businesses taken over by
citizens will favor democracy,'' Balcerowicz told a television
audience Saturday.
   Finding a palatable privatization plan took some doing.
   Opinion surveys showed the average citizen feared foreign
capitalists would snap up factories and land at bargain prices and
Poles would be second-class citizens in their own country.
   In the parts of Poland that used to be Germany, Poles were
worried that Germans would buy in and resettle.
   Even if the investors were Polish, it was assumed that only
those who lined their pockets as supporters of the old system could
afford to buy. So honest Poles would be toiling for the same old
Communist overlords.
   Finally, workers expected longer hours, more unemployment, and
less of a say in how their workplaces were run.
   The law hammered out by the government and parliament during
three months of committee work addressed all those concerns.
   Workers were promised the right to buy up to 20 percent of their
factories at discount prices. The general public is to be issued
privatization bonds which can be used to buy shares, and can also
buy on installment.
   The government retains an option to limit foreign investments of
more than 10 percent in a company. Officials say they will use that
option sparingly.
   Each of more than 7,600 state enterprises, in every sector of
the Polish economy, is to be privatized as quickly as possible,
starting with a dozen or so companies this year.
   The process will take years because each must be evaluated
before sale, with the healthiest ones up for sale first.
Money-losers will be dissolved and sold for their assets.
   Balcerowicz told Poles the task is a huge one, but it can be
accomplished.
   ``To a large extent,'' he said, ``the future of every one of us
depends on it.''
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   EDITOR'S NOTE: John Daniszewski, Warsaw correspondent of The
Associated Press, has covered Poland since 1987.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0020 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 1315EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Israel-NewExodus Bjt   07-15 0913</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel-New Exodus, Bjt,0941</SECOND>
<HEAD>Immigration of Soviet Jews Accelerates Exodus of Israelis</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KARIN LAUB</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   While Israel welcomes tens of thousands of
immigrants from the Soviet Union with hope and fanfare, thousands
of Jews are leaving, their Zionist dreams faded or gone.
   Officials expect more than 150,000 Soviet Jews this year, but
about 40,000 Israelis will emigrate _ roughly 1 percent of the
Jewish population of 3.8 million.
   About 14,000 Israelis left last year. The increase in emigration
can be blamed in part on the Soviets' entry into already tight
housing and job markets.
   But emigration, especially to the United States, is a
long-standing problem.
   By conservative estimates, 400,000 Jews have left in the four
decades since Israel was founded. Population experts say the number
could be 800,000 if it included Israelis who say they are leaving
temporarily but never return.
   The exodus is a serious blow to a country that was founded to
gather Jewish exiles and worries about a burgeoning Arab population
in Israel and the occupied territories.
   Many of the emigrants are young and educated. Some are offspring
of pioneer Zionist families.
   Most head for America. New York and Los Angeles are estimated to
have attracted 200,000 Israelis each.
   ``When you walk around New York City, you rarely pass one or two
blocks without hearing Hebrew,'' said Mordechai Heiblum, a
physicist who has spent 17 years in the United States and works for
IBM Research Laboratories.
   ``I left because the possibilities in Israel were
non-existent,'' Heiblum said. He plans to return, but said that was
because he had a job directing a new program to encourage the
return of Israeli scientists.
   Michael Kleiner, head of the Immigrant Absorption Committee in
Parliament, said the government must act quickly to create jobs and
housing.
   ``The immigration from the Soviet Union has sharpened the
problems for young Israelis,'' said Kleiner, a senior legislator of
Prime Minister Yitzhak Shamir's right-wing Likud bloc.
   The warnings of growing emigration are echoed in the tent cities
set up by homeless protesters outside the parliament building in
Jerusalem and at city halls across the country.
   One protester, Tal Yakov, said her brother plans to leave when
he is discharged from the army because he has no hope of finding an
apartment.
   ``There are many people today who are leaving: the best and the
brightest, who gave their souls to this country,'' she told Israel
television.
   Some accuse the government of indifference.
   ``The whole country is excited that in the next few years,
300,000 Soviet Jews will arrive, but when you say at least that
many people have left, this does not shock anyone,'' said Boaz
Shviger of the Jewish Agency, which helps settle arriving Jews.
   Avi Pazner, an aide to Shamir, said: ``If we have 100,000
immigrants and 10,000 who leave, we are still ahead by 90 percent.
It disturbs us, but it's not something vital. There is not much we
can do.''
   Increasing emigration also has changed the attitude that
emigrants are deserters who betray the Zionist dream. People now
talk freely about plans to leave and those with U.S. residency
permits are envied, not criticized.
   Half the respondents in a recent survey said emigration was an
acceptable option for people who could not find housing or jobs, up
from about 30 percent five years ago, said pollster Hanoch Smith.
   Shviger said the new attitude resulted from a ``deep ideological
crisis'' among young Israelis who no longer see the Jewish state as
the center of their lives. ``The young generation is running away
from politics and ideology,'' he said.
   This alienation is apparent from the growing number of emigrants
among kibbutzniks, members of the communal farms that were the core
of early Zionism.
   The daily Yediot Ahronot said about 8,000 former kibbutzniks
were among the 200,000 Israelis living in Los Angeles.
   One is 36-year-old Shraga Agam, who left Kibbutz Haogen in
northern Israel 11 years ago and owns a successful home improvement
company.
   ``I believe everyone has to do what's good for him,'' Agam told
the newspaper. ``For me, it's business, success and money.''
   Another category of emigrants is Westerners who came with bright
dreams, but found life difficult in Israel. Heavily taxed salaries
often barely cover rent and other necessities, and men face one
month a year of army reserve duty.
   Of about 2,000 North Americans who arrive each year, 35 to 40
percent return home, said Yoav Peg, director of the Association of
Americans and Canadians in Israel.
   ``More often than not, it's economics,'' he said. ``People are
just not used to living in the red and find it too hard to make
ends meet.''
   Emigrants include a disproportionate number of the young and
highly educated. According to Kleiner, two-thirds of the 14,000
emigrants last year were 21 to 34 years old and 17 percent held
university degrees.
   Each year, 60 to 70 students from the Weizmann Institute of
Science go to the United States for post-doctoral studies.
Institute spokesman Nechemia Meyers said many do not return because
there are no jobs for them in Israel.
   He noted that the influx of Soviet Jews, 60 percent of whom have
university degrees, was making the scientific and professional job
markets even tighter.
   ``There are 200 doctors a month coming from the Soviet Union,
about the same as the number of graduates from Israel medical
schools every year,'' Meyers said, ``and there isn't exactly a
shortage of doctors in Israel.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0021 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 1317EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brite-BucketPassing     07-15 0188</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brite-Bucket Passing,0191</SECOND>
<HEAD>Firefighters Pass the Bucket But There's No Fire</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HUDSON, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   More than a thousand firefighters and
firefighting enthusiasts made a passing attempt at a world record
and a little nostalgia.
   They set up a bucket brigade with an estimated 1,150 people
during New York Firefighters Field Day on Saturday in this town 40
miles south of Albany, said Mellenville Volunteer Firefighter Bill
Richards.
   The event, which called for participants to pass 100 buckets
filled with water from person to person, mimicked firefighting
practices before the advent of modern equipment.
   ``Everyone, even the people out of the crowd _ both young and
old _ did it,'' Richards said. ``I was standing next to a baby no
more than a year and a half. I would pass the bucket to her mother
and she would bend over and let the little girl touch it. It was
really cute. We had a lot of fun.''
   Signatures of the participants were being collected to document
the event. It'll be submitted to the Guinness Book of World
Records, which so far doesn't have a water bucket-passing category.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0022 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 1328EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--Congo-Politics     07-15 0170</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Congo-Politics,0175</SECOND>
<HEAD>Government Charges Journalist, Politician With Conspiracy</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BRAZZAVILLE, Congo (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A former journalist and an
ex-politician have been arrested and charged with conspiring to
overthrow the government, the government said.
   Police arrested Celestin Nkoua, a journalist, and Clement
Mierassa, a former politician, last week after a four-year
investigation, the government said late Saturday.
   In a communique, the government cited ``evidence of seditious
documents and other tracts'' that were found after a police search
of Nkoua's home.
   That seemed to indicate the possibility of other arrests. The
announcement came days after 150 intellectuals and military
officers signed a petition calling for a multiparty system.
   Nkoua was one of the signatories. After his arrest, the
government seized a printing plant he operates.
   Police Lt. Col. Pierre Oba said on national television that the
seditious documents included outlines for a new opposition party, a
provisional government and a new Constitution.
   This central African country of 1.9 million has been ruled since
1979 by President Denis Sassou Nguesso, a former general.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0023 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 1358EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Soviet-Yeltsin     07-15 0493</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Yeltsin,0508</SECOND>
<HEAD>Soviet Miners Place Hope in Yeltsin, the Hero of the Working Class</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Soviet-Protest, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ANDREW KATELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DONETSK, U.S.S.R. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Far from the Russian republic that he
governs, Boris Yeltsin is a favorite among coal miners in the
Ukraine, who hope his anti-establishment crusade will help improve
their lives.
   ``Boris Nikolayevich Yeltsin is the most decent person in the
country,'' said Nikolai Timoshenko, a 55-year-old veteran of the
Gorky mine in Donetsk, the heart of the Ukraine's coal country. ``I
support him because he fights for true democracy, speaks honestly
and openly.''
   The reform-minded president of the Russian republic, who quit
the Communist Party last Thursday during its congress in Moscow,
has nationwide support, even though he is an ethnic Russian and
holds no national office.
   Railing against Kremlin policy and privilege, Yeltsin wins
points from the working class the Communist Party has alienated.
   Miners, tired of promises that their living and working
conditions will improve, are an especially receptive audience.
   At a miner's rally during a one-day strike last week, little was
said about Yeltsin at the rostrum. But the men who spend their
workdays 1,000 yards underground were more than eager to talk when
asked about him.
   Timoshenko said he sees a potential spillover of Yeltsin's
policies from Russia, the Soviet Union's largest republic, to the
Ukraine, the second largest, if a reformer is elected Ukrainian
president.
   Vladimir Ivashko resigned as president of the Ukraine last week
to be Mikhail S. Gorbachev's deputy in the Communist Party, and the
post has not yet been filled.
   Many Donetsk miners feel left out of the political process.
``They didn't ask us who to nominate for president,'' Timoshenko
said.
   Miners, other members of the Soviet working class and
intellectuals who followed Yeltsin out of the Communist Party are
uniting around him into a formal opposition.
   Leaders of Democratic Platform, a coalition of radical reformers
who are mainly intellectuals and skilled workers, quit the party
with Yeltsin but do not expect him to join them in forming a new
opposition party this fall.
   ``Boris Yeltsin remains the leader of the entire democratic
movement,'' said Stepan Sulakhin of the Siberian city Tomsk.
   The miners have adopted an anti-Communist tone in line with
Yeltsin's harsh criticism of the party. They have boldly thrown
Communists out of the mines and plan to organize a government- and
party-free trade union next month.
   Both Yeltsin and Gorbachev had pleaded with the miners not to
strike, but have parted views there. Gorbachev rejected the miners'
demands for the government to resign and end party cells in the KGB
and army. Yeltsin supported them.
   That was not lost on some miners, who say Yeltsin is better
qualified than Gorbachev to lead the country.
   ``He's more flexible than Gorbachev and more decisive in
achieving his goals,'' said Vladislav Lushakov, 30, as he waited
for an elevator to take him into the Zasyadko mine in Donetsk.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0024 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 1407EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-EastTrial 1stLd-Writethru a0660 07-15 0696</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-East Trial, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0660,0709</SECOND>
<HEAD>Senator's Suicide Suit Trial Nearing End</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 16th graf, `In his...', with 2 grafs to explain
reference to Dr. Cary, add that he not a defendant. Picks up
penultimate graf.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By MARTHA WAGGONER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>RALEIGH, N.C. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The trial of a $3.5 million wrongful death
suit filed after the 1986 suicide of Sen. John East is winding down
with closing arguments set to begin this week.
   The 55-year-old first-term Republican killed himself by filling
his garage in Greenville with carbon monixide, 11 months after he
was cured of a thyroid disorder.
   His widow, Priscilla East, contends in the wrongful death
lawsuit that Navy doctors, who provide medical care for members of
Congress, were slow to detect her husband's thyroid condition. She
charges that the delay triggered a severe depression that led to
the senator's suicide.
   He left a suicide note blaming the doctors, saying they ``ruined
my health.''
   Government lawyers argued in the non-jury trial in U.S. District
Court in Baltimore that East was fully capable of making important
decisions _ including the one to kill himself. Closing arguments
are set to begin Tuesday.
   ``Not every death is someone else's responsibility,'' said
Assistant U.S. Attorney Susan Ringler in her opening statement in
March.
   While the suit against the government has attracted attention
because of the victim's prominence, experts say Mrs. East's claim
won't set any legal precedent.
   ``I think the case is more likely to obtain notoriety because of
the identity of the plaintiff as opposed to the substance of her
claim ... it doesn't present any major legal precedental issues,''
Michael Roth, a health care attorney in Los Angeles, said Thursday.
   East, a onetime college professor, ran for the Senate in 1980
under the wing of the National Congressional Club, the political
organization of Sen. Jesse Helms, R-N.C. He defeated Democratic
incumbent Robert Morgan.
   He had decided not to run for re-election in 1986 and planned to
return to East Carolina University, where he had taught political
science.
   Court papers filed by Mrs. East paint a picture of a man who
during his years in the Senate changed from someone known for his
quick wit to one who tried on six suits each morning before
deciding what to wear.
   And when she testified in March, Mrs. East spoke of an
intelligent, vigorous man, a former Marine who relentlessly pursued
his professional and political goals even though he used a
wheelchair since a bout with polio in the 1950s. That changed after
he fell ill in 1983, she said.
   Mrs. East claims in the civil suit that the Navy doctors could
have diagnosed the thyroid disease _ hypothyroidism _ much earlier
with a simple blood test. The disorder occurs when the thyroid
gland fails to produce the hormones needed to maintain the body's
metabolism.
   She testified that Navy doctors insisted her husband's problem
was pyschological and referred him to a psychiatrist. It wasn't
until 1985 that the thyroid disorder was diagnosed after he
collapsed into a near-fatal coma.
   Not long after he regained consciousness, East tried to kill
himself by ramming a chair leg down his throat, according to the
court papers. His hypothyroidism was cured with a synthetic
hormone, but he became convinced that his intelligence and powers
of reason had been permanently damaged, Mrs. East's attorneys say.
   In his suicide note, East wrote: ``By failing to diagnose the
hypothyroidism condition (as they should have) the attending
physician, Dr. Cary, and the Bethesda physicians ruined my health.
I can't go on.''
   He referred to a Navy doctor, Rear Adm. Freeman Cary, who had
treated him at the Capitol and referred him to a psychiatrist. Cary
is not a target of the lawsuit because survivors in such cases can
file claims against the government, but cannot sue individual
doctors.
   Government attorneys blamed East's suicide on the internal
conflict he felt about his unhappiness with the Senate and the
prospect of running again.
   ``He delineated that staying another term and leaving, both
those options, made him depressed,'' his psychiatrist, Ralph
Gemelli, testified in April. ``He thought people would think he
failed in some ways.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0025 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 1438EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-NASA-Congress 1stLd-Writethru a0645 07-15 0921</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-NASA-Congress, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0645,870</SECOND>
<HEAD>Space Program Troubles Shake Congressional Confidence</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: UPDATES throughout with confirmation of White House review,
names of council members, CORRECTS quote in 12th graf pvs, bgng:
``The worse. Makes minor edits throughout and trims from bottom to
shorten</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By STEVEN KOMAROW</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The failure of the Hubble Space Telescope and
grounding of the space shuttle fleet are shaking Congressional
confidence in the space program just as lawmakers search for ways
to redirect defense spending to civilian science.
   The Hubble and shuttle troubles also have prompted top Bush
administration officials to begin searching for ways to
reinvigorate the U.S. space program, an administration source said
Sunday.
   The White House may enlist a team of space experts from outside
government to aid that review, said the official, who spoke only on
condition of anonymity.
   There's still widespread support for space exploration in
Congress, and until its recent problems the National Aeronautics
and Space Administration seemed to be recovering from the black eye
it received from the 1986 Challenger explosion that killed seven
astronauts.
   Rep. Mike Andrews, D-Texas, whose congressional district is home
to thousands of NASA workers, said ``We were right on the edge of
what all of us thought would be a new chapter at NASA.''
   Now, Andrews said last week, cost overruns and defects in the
Hubble and shuttle programs make the space agency look like ``just
one more big bureaucracy.''
   And it's the butt of jokes.
   Sen. Al Gore, D-Tenn., who conducted hearings on the Hubble
earlier this month, quipped ``You know there's new information
about the Hubble. Jay Leno has disclosed that it is actually
working perfectly but the universe is all blurry.''
   Leno is a popular comedian who substitutes for Johnny Carson as
host of ``The Tonight Show'' on NBC-TV.
   The administration source Sunday said Vice President Dan Quayle,
as chairman of the National Space Council, and Admiral Richard
Truly, the former astronaut who heads NASA, are leading the
internal effort to find ways to get the space program back on track.
   The decision has not yet been made to convene a blue-ribbon
panel of experts, the source said, but ``if something is done, it
will be done with a combination of outside and inside advice.''
   CBS News reported Saturday that the administration likely will
name a panel of outside experts this week.
   From the White House perspective, the problems go beyond the
Hubble and shuttle leaks to broader difficulties with diminished
public support for the space program and Congress' refusal to fund
the full 25 percent NASA budget increase that Bush asked for.
   But two days after NASA revealed that the Hubble was crippled by
a defective mirror, the House approved $14.3 billion for the agency
in fiscal 1991, $2 billion more than the current fiscal year.
There's little talk of any immediate cutbacks.
   However, the agency's big projects for the future are being
looked at with much more skepticism than before. Those include a
$50 billion system of weather satellites, the $37 billion permanent
space station and Bush's proposal to land a man on Mars within 30
years.
   ``The worst kept secret in Washington is that defense
contractors who are out of work are now pushing space spending as a
national priority,'' said Rep. Richard Durbin, D-Ill., a member of
the House Budget Committee. ``Where else can they spend billions of
taxpayers' dollars on theory and dreams?''
   More than $300 billion in new space projects have been proposed
for the next three decades. But among ardent supporters in
Congress, there is widespread reluctance to expand NASA's role
before an accounting is made for the problems in the current
programs.
   ``Their plate is quite full, and it's a very stressful time for
NASA. Whatever can go wrong is going wrong,'' said Rep. Bob
Traxler, D-Mich., chairman of the subcommittee that oversees the
space and science budget.
   Rep. Bill Green of New York, the senior Republican on that
panel, said a decision on pulling the plug on the space station
project must be made soon or it could be too far along to kill.
   Traxler says it's too early to tell whether the program, already
far over budget and under-capable, should be scrapped for something
more simple. But he said Congress is increasingly skeptical of big
science projects and especially of the promises made by their
backers.
   The usual gambit for getting a big project approved is to come
in with a low estimate, get Congress to sink money into it, and
then expect Congress to keep spending as the estimates go up
because so much money already is invested.
   ``Those days are gone,'' Traxler said.
   Andrews says NASA's problems run too deeply for Congress to
solve without presidential leadership, and he's critical of Quayle
for not doing more to straighten out NASA from his post as chairman
of the National Space Council.
   ``I hope George Bush doesn't just leave it up to Dan Quayle to
lead us through this difficult time,'' he said.
   In addition to Quayle and Truly, the National Space Council
includes White House chief of staff John Sununu, budget director
Richard Darman, Commerce Secretary Robert Mosbacher and other
officials.
   Quayle, Sununu and Truly talked with several NASA critics in a
meeting held aboard Air Force Two on the flight home Wednesday from
the economic summit in Houston. Participants included former
astronaut Eugene Cernan, former NASA Administrator Thomas Paine,
Cal Tech scientist Bruce Murray and Hans Mark, chancellor of the
University of Texas system.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0026 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 1443EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Soviet-Germany 1stLd-Writethru a0659 07-15 0733</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Germany, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0659,0751</SECOND>
<HEAD>Kohl and Gorbachev Make Progress in Treaty Discussions</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: New thruout to UPDATE with comments on Germany and NATO. No
pickup.</NOTE>
<HEAD>With AM-Soviet-Protest, Bjt</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto MOSB5</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DEBORAH G. SEWARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Mikhail S. Gorbachev said he and West
German Chancellor Helmut Kohl drew a little bit closer Sunday on
the key issue of a united Germany's membership in NATO.
   Moscow's refusal to accept a united German presence in the
Western alliance has become a major obstacle to the swift merger of
the two German states.
   Kohl arrived in Moscow late Saturday on a two-day visit seeking
to remove Soviet obstacles to German unification. Other issues
discussed were the size of a united German army and West German
economic aid to the Soviet Union.
   Late Sunday, Gorbachev and Kohl traveled 1,000 miles south of
Moscow to Stavropol, Gorbachev's native region and the place where
he was Communist Party leader before coming to Moscow. Gorbachev
said he thought the ``fresh air'' of the northern Caucasus would
help both leaders formulate their thoughts clearly, the Tass news
agency reported.
   Asked whether the two sides had managed to come ``a little bit''
closer on the issue of NATO membership, the Tass news agency quoted
Gorbachev as saying:
   ``In the last month or two many important changes have occurred.
And the new context opens possibilities for the way to a new
understanding. In other words, that very `little bit' is
appearing.''
   It is Kohl's second visit to Moscow since February. He told
reporters he was ``optimistic'' that the foreign and security
aspects of German unity could be solved this year.
   Gorbachev said he and Kohl also discussed a comprehensive new
treaty to govern relations between the Soviet Union and a united
Germany. ``We have come quite close on very big questions,'' he
said without elaborating.
   Kohl said both he and Gorbachev were aware of ``the historic
hour'' at hand, but were ``looking forward without forgetting
history.''
   The accord would replace the Moscow Treaty, a non-aggression
pact ratified by the West German and Soviet parliaments in 1972.
The pact has formed the basis of relations between the two
countries.
   The new treaty would cover security issues as well as economic,
financial and cultural cooperation. It would bind both sides to
mutual renunciation of force.
   Fighting between Nazi Germany and the Red Army in World War II
cost at least 20 million Soviet lives. Many Soviet families still
bear the scars of the war.
   For decades, the German threat was a favorite subject of Soviet
propaganda. War movies are still popular on Soviet television _
this weekend prime-time television featured two films on the Nazi
SS forces.
   Moscow stands to lose East Germany, its most important partner
in the Warsaw Pact alliance, once the two Germanys merge sometime
after all-German elections in December.
   The Soviet Union has objected to allowing a united Germany
immediately to become a NATO member and instead has suggested a
transitional membership in both alliances. Western nations want
Germany immediately to join NATO.
   But Soviet Foreign Minister Eduard A. Shevardnadze has indicated
at talks among the two Germanys and the four victorious World War
II Allies _ France, Great Britain, the United States and the Soviet
Union _ that there is room for compromise.
   NATO Secretary General Manfred Woerner, Kohl's defense minister
from 1982-1988 who is also visiting the Soviet Union, said Saturday
the inclusion of a united Germany in NATO would contribute to
stability in Europe.
   On the size of a United German army, the Soviets have suggested
the force number less than 400,000. They have also argued that
their troops should stay in what is now East German territory, and
Bonn has pledged $780 million for the upkeep of Soviet soldiers in
the second half of this year.
   West German economic aid to the Soviet Union is also an issue
between the leaders. The West German government has backed a $3.1
billion loan to support the Kremlin's efforts to lead the Soviet
Union's centralized economy to a market-oriented system.
   But Western leaders rejected a proposal strongly supported by
West Germany and France for a $15 billion aid plan to shore up the
Soviet economy and demonstrate Western support for Gorbachev.
   The Soviet Union is already suffering from the drop in imports
from East Germany, its largest trading partner in the East bloc.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0027 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 1445EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-NuclearWeapons     07-15 0293</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Nuclear Weapons,280</SECOND>
<HEAD>Newspaper: Agency Plans Long-Range Nuclear Weapons Production</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A federal plan recommends continued production
of nuclear weapons at a revitalized complex of factories and
reactors despite the appearance of a reduced Soviet military
threat, according to a published report Sunday.
   The Washington Post said the Department of Energy wants the
military to be able to make new bombs through at least the middle
of the next century. The newspaper quoted an unidentified Energy
Department official as saying the department's research and
spending plans were based on ``a requirement for nuclear weapons as
far a we can see.''
   Energy Department officials say they foresee a continued need to
manufacture new varieties of nuclear weapons to replace those being
retired or withdrawn as obsolete even though the size of the U.S.
nuclear arms cache is expected to decline from 21,000 weapons over
the next 60 years, the Post said.
   The newspaper said Energy Secretary James D. Watkins told the
Senate Armed Services Committee in a letter that under one option
being considered _ Complex 21 _ nuclear weapons construction
activities now spread across 12 states would be consolidated at one
or two sites.
   ``Complex 21, my vision of a fully modernized (nuclear weapons)
complex, is planned to be in operation about 2015 and to support
the nation's strategic deterrent until the middle of the century,''
Watkins wrote.
   The letter provided the most detailed explanation yet of the
department's long-term goal, the Post said.
   Some officials have suggested that such a complex, which
anti-nuclear activists have dubbed a ``nuclear weapons theme
park,'' could be operated in a state such as South Carolina, where
public support remains high for such a bomb building enterprise and
the federal dollars it would bring.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0028 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 1452EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-ForeignAid 1stLd-Writethru a0665 07-15 0830</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Foreign Aid, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0665,790</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.S. Experts Share American Knowledge Around the Globe</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 5th graf pvs, bgng: `A lot, to CORRECT bombs to bomb</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By KAREN BALL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Developing a fly-resistant wheat in Morocco,
teaching Tunisia about banking and bringing down Bangladesh's
fertility rate are among the tasks U.S. experts have taken on as
part of America's global effort to help needy nation's help
themselves.
   Since the aid program was started in the wake of World War II,
the United States has spent more than $212 billion helping about
half the world's countries.
   Now the program is being extended _ on a limited basis _ to the
Soviet Union.
   So-called ``technical assistant'' advisers who have been sharing
American know-how with less fortunate countries for years now will
be available to help the Soviets' reeling economy.
   ``A lot of people think they're going to pass atom bomb secrets,
but it's really rather mundane things like how to dry wheat before
you store it so it doesn't rot,'' Curtis Jackson of the Agency for
International Development said in an interview last week.
   The Soviet Union, which has not received U.S. foreign aid since
America gave it a small sum of post-war relief in the 1940s, is the
latest country to be added to the list of more than 80 nations that
receive American help.
   The Bush administration, while balking at providing the Soviet
Union with cash grants or loans, agreed at the economic summit of
industrial nations in Houston this past week to provide the
technical assistance. The International Monetary Fund also will
study the Soviet economy.
   Under the U.S. aid program, experts _ oftentimes college
professors or consultants from private industry _ travel to
developing and middle-income countries to help with problems
ranging from farming to family planning to nutrition and health.
   American endeavors have included helping Panama set up a new
police force, assisting El Salvador on upgrading its deficient
judicial system and instructing Afghanistan on overhauling its
irrigation system.
   The U.S. program includes both technical assistance _ the
limited type of help the Soviet Union will get _ and also direct
economic aid for housing, agriculture and health projects. This
year's budget is $7 billion.
   The only aid the Soviet Union has received since the program
started _ except for earthquake relief to Soviet Armenia _ was the
$186 million it was handed from 1946-48 for post-war relief.
   ``Some emergency aid has gone to Red Bloc countries, but not
long-term development aid'' like the technical assistants that will
now go to the Soviet Union, said John Matelsky, a spokesman for AID.
   As evolving democracies in Eastern Europe such as Poland and
Hungary try to transfer state-owned industries to private hands,
U.S. experts are helping them cope with questions Americans find
basic but which newcomers to a free market find mind-boggling.
   ``They are used to being told how many units to deliver, where
to deliver them and what time to deliver them,'' said Dean Jansma,
associate dean for international programs in agriculture at
Pennsylvania State University, who recently returned from Poland.
   ``How do you handle employees in a free enterprise system? Can
you fire someone? ... Those kind of questions are second nature to
us, but they've never done them there,'' Jansma said.
   As in Africa and southeast Asia, U.S. experts are trying to help
European countries improve harvesting and storage methods so more
of what the country produces eventually end up on the dinner table.
   ``Sometimes a third of what's grown deteriorates before anyone
eats it,'' Jackson said.
   John Nicholaides, director of international agriculture at the
University of Illinois, was heading to Poland this weekend as part
of an Illinois state trade mission.
   Nicholaides has developed a model small farm for groups of
Polish families to help them get their products to market and so
they will ``have more leverage to obtain a better price'' for their
products, he said.
   U.S. officials can help Poland most by teaching them how to
improve their food processing, such as turning corn into vegetable
oil or snacks rather than just selling the raw product, Nicholaides
said.
   ``They're importing a lot of things they used to export. That's
the big area where Poland really feels like they need input from
the United states,'' he said.
   That country also is seeking assistance for telecommunications
and education, he said.
   Vernon Larson, assistant provost for international programs at
Kansas State University, in the past has worked in Nigeria and
India helping those countries develop agriculture schools.
   Improving a country's agriculture base is the key to improving
the rest of its economy because it frees up more people to work in
industrial sectors, Larson said.
   Kansas State has taken an active part ``because a wheat state
like we are ... our future market is in the underdeveloped
countries.''
   ``It's a humanitarian thing, it's the right thing to do and it
helps us. ... The world needs these crops.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0029 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 1502EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People     07-15 0802</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People,0835</SECOND>
<HEAD>People in the News</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY44</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   To comedian Joan Rivers, getting a pistol permit
apparently isn't a laughing matter.
   The talk show host didn't want to talk about the permit when she
went to police headquarters to pick it up on Friday.
   ``I was waiting for something to make me laugh, but she was
serious,'' said Capt. Allan Shulman of the License Bureau. ``It
shows she understands the seriousness of a license.''
   While at Police Plaza, Rivers toured the 911 offices, hoping to
pick up good stories to pass on to her daughter, Melissa, who is
working for the television program, ``Rescue, 911.''
   Rivers last month won her first Emmy Award for best daytime talk
show host for her syndicated ``The Joan Rivers Show.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>NASHVILLE, Tenn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A wistful hillbilly classic made popular
in the 1940s by country singer Hank Snow is making a comeback on an
all-star album recorded by the Traveling Wilburys.
   ``Nobody's Child,'' co-written by Mel Foree and Cy Coben,
provided the backdrop and title track for an album recorded to
raise funds for Romanian orphans.
   The Traveling Wilburys _ George Harrison, Bob Dylan, Jeff Lynne
and Tom Petty _ get help on their acoustic version of the song by
Eric Clapton, Elton John, Stevie Wonder, Ringo Starr and Guns N'
Roses.
   Foree, 73, said doubts he had about the new recording have
disappeared.
   ``They are the biggest _ Bob Dylan and those boys,'' Foree told
The Tennessean.
   ``But I have to tell you honestly _ I guess I'm one of the old
fogies _ I wouldn't have thought it (the Wilburys' version) would
have been anything at all,'' Foree said. ``But with this new age,
you can't ever tell.''
   The song, which originally was written about the plight of
orphans, now is aimed at a relief effort to help thousands of
neglected children discovered in Romanian orphanages after the fall
of the Ceausescu regime.
   The album, to be released this month, features contributions
from Billy Idol, Dave Stewart and the Spiritual Cowboys, Van
Morrison, the Bee Gees, Edie Brickell and the New Bohemians, and
Mike and the Mechanics.
   A portion of the royalties will go to the Romanian Angel Appeal
Fund.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>SEMINOLE, Okla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Sen. David Boren and his cousin,
entertainer Hoyt Axton, teamed up for a little musical
entertainment at a re-election rally for the Oklahoma Democrat.
   Axton has written songs such as ``I've Never Been To Spain'' and
``Joy To The World,'' and appeared in numerous movies including
``Gremlins'' and ``Endangered Species.''
   Boren and Axton sang ``God Bless America,'' and Axton also sang
``Amazing Grace'' during an old-fashioned ice cream social Saturday.
   Boren, chairman of the Senate Intelligence Committee, is seeking
a third six-year term in the Senate.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>PITTSBURGH (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Stuffed animals, T-shirts and flowers meant
for members of the New Kids on the Block were sent to a
home-away-from-home for families of seriously ill children in
Pittsburgh hospitals.
   The carload of presents intended for the teen-age singing group,
who played concerts over the weekend near Pittsburgh, were left by
fans at the Star Lake Amphitheatre in Washington County.
   Parents of the singers donated the gifts to the Ronald McDonald
House, a home for the families of seriously ill children.
   Before Friday's concert, members of the group met with some of
the children, including the world's first heart-liver transplant
recipient, Stormie Jones of Texas, who is under treatment at
Children's Hospital of Pittsburgh.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>ESSEX, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   TV reporter Charles Kuralt has turned down a
request by a group of archaeologists to dig up the front lawn of
his vacation house.
   In a letter to Wesleyan University archaeology professor John
Pfeiffer, the television newsman told the scholars he is not
interested in what might lie beneath the lush, green turf, Pfeiffer
said Saturday.
   Pfeiffer is leading a crew of Wesleyan University graduate
students who are excavating sections of an 18th- and 19th-century
industrial complex at the mouth of Falls River in Essex. They
believe Kuralt's lawn, several hundred yards upstream from the
site, could hold clues to the development of the area as a
19th-century ivory processing center.
   The professor said Kuralt believed his property had held nothing
more than a bicycle factory.
   ``He felt that archaeology wouldn't tell him anything that he
didn't already know,'' Pfeiffer said.
   A woman who answered the phone Sunday at CBS news in New York
said Kuralt had left for the day, and there was no answer Sunday
afternoon at Kuralt's home telephone in Essex.
   The archaeologists had written Kuralt in May asking for
permission to dig a few small ``test pits'' in the lawn, which they
believe could conceal a trove of ivory notions such as eyelets,
combs and perhaps even fragments of billiard balls.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0030 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 1505EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SouthAfrica     07-15 0418</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-South Africa,0432</SECOND>
<HEAD>Seven Killed, 21 Injured in Unrest, Bombings</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GREG MYRE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JOHANNESBURG, South Africa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Three explosions in
Johannesburg and scattered violence in the eastern province of
Natal have claimed the lives of seven blacks and resulted in 21
injuries, police said Sunday.
   The most serious attack was at a hotel bar frequented by blacks
in the Johannesburg suburb of Roodepoort, where a grenade exploded
late Saturday night, killing one and injuring 21, police said.
   A chef at the Roodepoort Hotel, Violet Cheki, said she saw a
white man open the door to the bar and roll an object into a crowd
of about 100 people just before the blast.
   In the same area, a hotel bar where all the patrons were white
was bombed with explosives before dawn Saturday, killing a black
waiter.
   Police said there also was an explosion Saturday at the suburban
Johannesburg home of a right-wing white, Hans Binneman. No one was
injured.
   No one claimed responsibility for any of the weekend attacks.
   However, white extremists have issued statements claiming
responsibility for a recent spate of bombings in Johannesburg aimed
at blacks and whites who oppose apartheid. Police have detained
nine whites for questioning, but no one has been charged.
   Pro-apartheid whites have vowed to resist President F.W. de
Klerk's plans to dismantle the apartheid system of racial
segregation and share power with the 30-million black majority.
   Robert van Tonder, leader of the right-wing Boer State Party,
said: ``All these blasts, unrest and violence are due to the
government reforms.''
   ``They (the government) created a climate of suspicion, lack of
confidence and anarchy,'' van Tonder told the independent South
African Press Association.
   The African National Congress, the leading black opposition
group, has accused the government of not taking firm action against
right-wingers suspected of violence.
   In Natal, two policemen were among five blacks killed, according
to the police unrest report, which covers incidents from the
previous 24 hours.
   One policeman was stabbed to death near Pietermaritzburg and the
other was fatally shot in Umlazi outside Durban.
   Two men were shot to death and the body of another man was found
in three separate incidents, the report added.
   More than 4,000 blacks have been killed in factional violence in
Natal since 1986. The main combatants are supporters of the ANC and
Inkatha, a relatively conservative Zulu poltical party headed by
Mangosuthu Buthelezi.
   Both sides oppose apartheid, but disagree on tactics and have
many youthful supporters they cannot control.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0031 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 1508EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Britain-Germans     07-15 0647</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Britain-Germans,0669</SECOND>
<HEAD>Thatcher and Academics Analyze Germany's Character</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARCUS ELIASON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher secretly gathered
leading academics to discuss the Germans and explore traits
traditionally attributed to them such as ``angst, aggressive
bullying (and) egotism,'' it was revealed Sunday.
   Mrs. Thatcher's think tank concluded that while the Germans have
changed, the future was uncertain. Meanwhile, they decided, ``we
should be nice to the Germans.''
   A summary of the March 24 meeting at Mrs. Thatcher's country
house, Chequers, was written by her private secretary, Charles
Powell. It was published in full in The Independent on Sunday.
   It was not clear how the paper obtained a copy of the report.
But Foreign Secretary Douglas Hurd, who attended the meeting,
confirmed the text's accuracy.
   ``We started by talking about the Germans and their
characteristics,'' Powell wrote, listing ``angst, aggressiveness
bullying, egotism, inferiority complex, sentimentality.''
   ``But there was a strong school of thought among those present
that today's Germans were very different,'' and that after World
War II, militarism and thirst for conquests disappeared.
   ``Education and the writing of history had changed ... We should
have no real worries about them,'' he reportedly wrote.
   Not everyone agreed, however.
   ``It still had to be asked how a cultured and cultivated nation
had allowed itself to be brainwashed into barbarism. If it had
happened once, could it not happen again?'' the summary said.
   Even today, it said, ``The way the Germans threw their weight
about in the European Community suggested that a lot had still not
changed ... German behavior in the EC _ `we pay so we must have our
way' _ was seen by some as a harbinger of Germany's economic
dominance over Western Europe.''
   The new Germany has never been tested by calamity, the document
said. ``No one (at the meeting) had serious misgivings about the
present leaders or political elite of Germany. But what about 10,
15 or 20 years from now?''
   ``No formal conclusions were drawn,'' the summary said, but
``the weight of the evidence and the argument favored those who
were optimistic about life in a united Germany. ... When it came to
failings and unhelpful characteristics, the Germans had their share
and perhaps more, but in contrast to the past, they were much
readier to recognize and admit this themselves.''
   ``The overall message was unmistakable; we should be nice to the
Germans. But even the optimists had some unease, not for the
present and the immediate future, but for what might lie further
down the road than we can yet see.''
   The participants, according to the newspaper, included Mrs.
Thatcher, historian Hugh Trevor-Roper, Oxford University's Norman
Stone, American Professors Fritz Stern of Columbia University and
Gordon Craig of Harvard, journalist Timothy Garton Ash, and George
Urban, former research director at Radio Free Europe.
   The summary was published amid political upheaval over the
resignation of Trade Secretary Nicholas Ridley for comments made
about Germany, and opposition politicians were quick to accuse Mrs.
Thatcher of insulting a friendly ally.
   The Labor Party's Gerald Kaufman said it was an ``offensive
farce'' for senior Cabinet ministers to ``sit around pulling the
Germans to pieces.''
   But Hurd saw nothing wrong with a brainstorming session about
the implications of a momentous event such as the unification of
Germany.
   The first step toward unification came with economic union of
the German states on July 1 and a full merger will come after
all-German elections, expected in December.
   What mattered, Hurd told BBC-TV, was that the experts' verdict
on Germany was positive.
   It was virtually ``a fantasy to suppose that we're going to be
faced with a new Hitler, or a new Gestapo,'' he said. ``We can
really dismiss that as a possibility.''
   Mrs. Thatcher's views did not appear in the summary, but she has
voiced misgivings about the economic might of a united Germany.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0032 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 1521EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SouthAfrica-Boesak     07-15 0421</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-South Africa-Boesak,0432</SECOND>
<HEAD>Boesak to Reconsider Resignation During 3-Week Leave</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ADIL BRADLOW</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CAPE TOWN, South Africa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Rev. Allan Boesak, a prominent
activist who resigned his church posts after reports he had an
affair with a married woman, is reconsidering his decision to quit,
his lawyer said Sunday.
   Church leaders at the mixed-race branch of the Dutch Reformed
Church in Bellville outside Cape Town said at a service Sunday they
``would be grateful'' if Boesak decides to return after his
three-week leave of absence.
   Boesak is ``much loved by all of us,'' said Johan Retief, a
co-minister at the church. Many congregants wept during the service
and expressed support for Boesak.
   However, graffiti on Boesak's office next to the church made
sexually explicit references to the alleged affair between the
minister and Elna Botha, a producer for government-run television.
   Boesak was not at church Sunday. But his lawyer, Essa Moosa,
said Boesak will ``reflect seriously on his position over the next
few weeks and come to a considered decision with regard to his
resignation.''
   Boesak, one of South Africa's best known anti-apartheid leaders,
is a powerful speaker who is often at the front of anti-government
marches and demonstrations. He has strong ties to the African
National Congress, the country's leading opposition group, and many
observers believe he has political ambitions.
   He tearfully resigned his post in a July 8 sermon following
newspaper reports of the alleged affair. The newspapers said
Boesak's wife, Dorothy, had tipped them off, and that reporters
confronted Boesak at a Cape Town hotel.
   Boesak made no reference to Mrs. Botha in his resignation
speech, but said: ``This is one of the darkest days of my life.''
   ``I am deeply sorry for the the pain I have caused,'' he said.
   Boesak also serves as president of the World Alliance of
Reformed Churches, an international body of Protestant churches.
Retief said he did not know if Boesak had given up that post.
   Boesak, married for more than 20 years, was temporarily
suspended from his church posts in 1985 after he was romantically
linked to a church secretary. He was reinstated and acknowledged a
``special relationship'' with the woman.
   The Sunday Times of Johannesburg reported that Mrs. Botha had
left her husband and gone to Atlanta and that Boesak would join her
shortly.
   Mrs. Botha's husband, television newscaster Colin Fluxman, was
taken off the air last week after breaking down as he read an item
about the alleged relationship between his wife and Boesak.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0033 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 1523EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r e BC-Dance     07-15 0465</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Dance,0487</SECOND>
<NOTE>Eds: No PMs Planned</NOTE>
<HEAD>Bolshoi Dances `Romeo'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARY CAMPBELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Bolshoi Ballet proves that sets and props
aren't needed to tell the story of ``Romeo and Juliet''
dramatically and beautifully in dance.
   The company, dancing at the New York State Theater, presented
its second full-evening ballet here, the first stop on a seven-city
U.S. tour. On Saturday night, Yuri Posokhov and Lyudmila Semenyaka
danced Romeo and Juliet with youthful passion.
   Posokhov enters, dances a solo. Then Mikhail Sharkov as Mercutio
enters and dances. Sharkov is dressed in white and has the build
and dash of a hero. One wonders for a moment whether he's Romeo.
   But Posokhov's slim build and darting intensity make him look,
appropriately, very young. Semenyaka dances a slightly more mature
Juliet. When she runs to her nurse after she has fallen in love at
first sight with Romeo, she doesn't throw herself into the nurse's
arms like a confused child but grabs her arms. One woman is telling
another the news.
   Semenyaka's dancing looks very young and fresh. She danced with
the Bolshoi here in 1979 and 1987.
   Each duet is different in mood. The balcony scene young
passionate love, the wedding scene chaste, the wedding morning
scene tender, the reunion in the tomb scene joyful on her part,
physical exertion after taking poison on his part.
   Yuri Grigorovich, artistic director of the Bolshoi,
choreographed ``Romeo and Juliet'' to Prokofiev's music for the
Paris Opera Ballet in 1978. That version transferred to the Bolshoi
a year later. It changes a few plot details from the ballet
versions usually seen. The newly married Romeo doesn't hold back
Mercutio in his duel with Juliet's brother, Tybalt. Here he grabs
Tybalt's shoulder but Tybalt is able to stab Mercutio in the back,
a nicer touch.
   There's more than the usual amount of dancing by corps de ballet
in this version. The Bolshoi's male dancers are strong and virile.
   Grigorovich's ballet steps and patterns aren't as varied and
nuanced as some choreographers. One gets more of a sense of
repetition with him. But the overall architecture of the ballet is
admirable and he is excellent at choreographing for many couples
who fill the stage.
   The backdrop has sweeps of draped cloth, with different
lighting. A projection of a doorway indicates Friar Laurence's
premises. Yuri Vetrov danced the friar, who lifts and carries
Juliet in this production.
   There's no balcony and no bed in Juliet's bedroom. Oddly, they
aren't needed. Dancers get up from their knees or lie on the floor.
Juliet changes costumes but wears her Juliet cap all the time, even
in bed.
   Aleksei Dovgopoly danced Paris with flair, not making him a
wimp. Aleksandr Vetrov was excellently haughty and audacious as
Tybalt.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0034 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 1529EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BaptistEditors     07-15 0767</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Baptist Editors,0796</SECOND>
<HEAD>Baptist Newsmen's Ouster Attempt Ends Hopes for Bloodless
Conservative Coup</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARY CULPEPPER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NASHVILLE, Tenn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Conservative Baptists who established
control over the nation's largest Protestant denomination began
flexing their authority and promptly sparked a clash over press
freedom.
   The fundamentalist-moderate power struggle over the past decade
for control of the Southern Baptist Convention reached a watershed
last month when moderates failed in what was viewed as a last-ditch
effort to balance leadership.
   And only about 24 hours after a fundamentalist Texas minister
was installed as convention president, two editors of the Baptist
Press were asked to resign.
   They refused, setting up a meeting Tuesday at Baptist
headquarters here that some ministers say will tell a lot about how
conservatives plan to lead the denomination's flock of nearly 15
million members.
   ``We all are waiting to see who's next,'' said the Rev. Roy
Honeycutt, president of Southern Baptist Theological Seminary in
Louisville, Ky. ``For all practical purposes, I assume they've now
won the battle they've set out to win in 1979.''
   Ordered to quit were editors Alvin C. Shackleford, 58, and Dan
Martin, 51. Critics say that under them, the news service has
become biased in favor of moderates. Both have asked for time to be
heard at Tuesday's hearing of the 77-member executive committee.
   Martin said his refusal to quit has put Southern Baptist
conservatives in a tough spot: Their coup can't be bloodless.
   ``They don't want to fire anybody. That leaves this situation a
little ambivalent,'' he said.
   Executive Committee President Harold C. Bennett, who called the
meeting, was at a conference in North Carolina and couldn't be
reached for comment, a secretary in his office said Friday. He did
not return a phone message left at his Nashville home Sunday.
   Newly elected Southern Baptist Convention President Morris
Chapman of Wichita Falls, Texas, also was out of town, a staff
member said.
   In the past, Baptist debate has centered on religious subjects
like whether the Bible should be considered to be literally true in
all respects. But lately is has fallen on secular topics, such as
the amount of coverge Baptist Press has given moderate ministers
vs. conservatives.
   Television journalist Bill Moyers, a lifelong Southern Baptist,
has leaped to the aid of the editors.
   In a letter to state Baptist news editors, Moyers attacked
Houston judge Paul Pressler, a fundamentalist leader who has
spearheaded the fight against the two editors.
   Moyers described Pressler, vice chairman of the 77-member
executive committee, as a ``petty tyrant.''
   ``He rules the Southern Baptist Convention like a swaggering
Caesar, breaking good men when it pleases him,'' said Moyers, who
defended the editors as unwilling to slant their reporting.
   Pressler was out of the country and unavailable for comment
before the meeting.
   The Rev. Fred Wolfe, a pastor at Cottage Hill Baptist Church in
Mobile, Ala., and executive committee treasurer, said he and five
others suggested to Bennett that the editors be ousted.
   ``Real or perceived, there's strong feeling among conservatives
that Baptist Press has been pro-moderate in the last 12 years,''
Wolfe said. ``I can assure you that Mr. Shackleford and Mr. Martin
knew there was a real problem with Baptist Press for a long period
of time.''
   Moderates say the problem is that Southern Baptists are being
required to share a single viewpoint of their faith.
   It's ``like you used to have in factories that stamped out
records _ same speeds, same size, same song,'' Honeycutt said.
   The 44-year-old news service, considered one of the nation's
most open and objective denominational news agencies, serves 400
outlets, including 38 independent Baptist state weeklies. It
maintains bureaus in Dallas; Washington, D.C.; Atlanta; and
Richmond, Va.
   The Rev. Rick Cagle, an executive committee member from Gadsden,
Ala., said the resignation order came because some Baptist
journalists were letting their politics show.
   ``You've got a lot of churches who don't even send the Baptist
publications out to their members because they feel they're so
biased,'' Cagle said.
   The Rev. J.B. Fowler, who heads the Southern Baptist Press
Association, disagreed. He accused conservatives of trying to
neutralize ideological opponents.
   ``In any takeover attempt, regardless of what it is or who it
is, one of the things taken over is the press, that it might be
silenced,'' said Fowler, editor of the Baptist New Mexican, one of
the 38 state Baptist papers.
   Shackleford said the struggle is as simple, and important, as
free speech.
   ``We are basically asking for a right to focus on the real
issue, and that is the Baptist right to know,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0035 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 1532EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-EastGermany-Terrorist     07-15 0395</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-East Germany-Terrorist,0404</SECOND>
<HEAD>Newspaper Says Palestinian Terrorist Living in East Germany</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WEST BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A West Berlin newspaper said Sunday that a
terrorist suspected of involvement in the 1972 Munich Olympics
massacre of Israeli athletes is living in East Germany.
   The Berliner Morgenpost said the internationally sought
terrorist, known as Abu Daoud, had lived in the East Berlin Palast
Hotel for several years until mid-1988. The report said he is still
believed to be somewhere in East Berlin.
   An East German Interior Ministry spokesman said Sunday his
office was investigating the report, but had no other comment.
   East German Interior Minister Peter-Michael Diestel has been
quoted as saying the former secret police, known as Stasi,
sheltered the international terrorist Carlos as well as one of the
men believed responsible for the Sept. 5, 1972, attack at the
Munich Olympics that left 11 Israeli athletes dead.
   The now-disbanded Stasi has also been accused of harboring West
German Red Army Faction terrorists and having contacts with Libyan,
Basque separatist and Irish Republican Army terrorists.
   Abu Daoud, whose real name is Mahmoud Daoud, was a senior
officer of Fatah, the faction of the Palestine Liberation
Organization led by PLO chief Yasser Arafat. Daoud was among the
Fatah personalities believed to have had a hand in the Black
September terrorist group that carried out some of the most
notorious attacks of the 1970s, including the massacre at the
Munich Olympics.
   Daoud reportedly survived an assassination attempt in Warsaw in
1981.
   The newspaper said two of its reporters had ``followed Abu
Daoud's trail in the Palast Hotel.'' The paper said he stayed there
under the name ``Tarek'' four to five times a year in a two-room
apartment on the eighth floor that was equipped with a large bed,
color television and a bar. The room cost $175 a night and the
newspaper said he was treated as a VIP guest of the hotel.
   The newspaper based its information on interviews with several
hotel workers and said many had recognized a photograph of the
suspected terrorist which the reporters had brought with them.
   Employees learned of the man's real identity in 1986 from the
hotel management and were ordered to keep silent, the newspaper
added.
   One hotel chambermaid, who was not named, said the man in
question slept with ``a big caliber revolver'' under his pillow,
the newspaper said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0036 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 1614EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-PanAmThreat     07-15 0383</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Pan Am Threat,0394</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.S. Said to Warn of Bomb Threat Against Pan Am</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A London newspaper reported Sunday that U.S.
authorities have warned U.S. airlines of a threat to blow up a Pan
Am jet on a flight from West Germany in the next 10 days.
   In Washington, FAA spokesman Fred Farrar refused to comment
Sunday. In New York, Pan Am spokesman Jeff Kreindler also declined
comment and referred all queries to the FAA.
   The Sunday Correspondent quoted a confidential Federal Aviation
Adminstration bulletin as saying: ``A female student with a
Canadian passport may be duped into carrying a suitcase containing
a bomb on to a Pan Am flight from either Frankfurt or Berlin.''
   The FAA issues hundreds of bomb threat warnings to airlines each
year, and the newspaper quoted the bulletin as saying ``there are
doubts about the reliability of the individual that originated the
threat information.''
   It said the bulletin was issued Tuesday to all U.S. airlines and
selected airports.
   It quoted the bulletin as saying the student was reportedly
studying at the Sorbonne in Paris and is now touring Europe. Her
destination and date of departure are unknown, it said.
   The student ``allegedly has a Middle Eastern boyfriend'' who
will give her a suitcase containing a bomb made of the Semtex
plastic explosive, the newspaper was quoted as saying.
   It did not say how it obtained its information.
   A bomb concealed in a radio-cassette recorder blew up a Pan Am
jet over Lockerbie, Scotland in December 1988, killing all 259
people on board and 11 on the ground. The New York-bound flight
originated in Frankfurt and changed aircraft in London.
   After the crash, it emerged that the FAA had issued a bomb
warning to airlines and diplomats.
   The Sunday Correspondent said American intelligence experts
believe the source of the latest warning could have been the
Israeli intelligence agency, the Mossad. It said they suspect the
Mossad is attempting to disrupt the release of Irish teacher Brian
Keenan, who has been a captive in Lebanon since April 1986.
   The paper said the Mossad was also the source of a warning that
preceded the Lockerbie bomb plot. It said that warning was
dismissed as an Israeli attempt to interfere with PLO leader Yasser
Arafat's overtures to Washington.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0037 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 1635EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-India-Politics     07-15 0599</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-India-Politics,0620</SECOND>
<HEAD>Indian Prime Minister Withdraws His Resignation</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto DEL6</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By VIJAY JOSHI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW DELHI, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Prime Minister V.P. Singh withdrew his
resignation offer Sunday, but the dispute within the coalition
government that caused the crisis remained unresolved and four more
ministers reportedly quit.
   ``For the sake of the nation, its unity and sovereignty, we
asked (Singh) to withdraw his resignation, which he agreed to do,''
said N.T. Rama Rao, the chairman of the governing National Front
alliance.
   Meanwhile, Foreign Minister Inder Kumar Gujral and three other
ministers resigned Sunday, United News of India said. The latest
resignations brought to 13 the number of ministers who have quit
the government in the dispute.
   Rao made the announcement about Singh after a 90-minute meeting
between National Front leaders and the prime minister.
   The front is composed of Singh's Janata Dal Party and four
smaller groups. However, Janata Dal President Somappa Rayappa
Bommai said the two-day-old crisis gripping the minority government
continues.
   ``The crisis is not over yet. I am in the process of getting to
a solution,'' Bommai told a news conference. He refused to
elaborate.
   Singh's offer of resignation was prompted by a power struggle
with Deputy Prime Minister Devi Lal, who has been promoting his
son's political career despite growing protests and outrage from
senior Janata Dal members.
   Rao said Singh was persuaded to remain in office because ``the
prime minister does not belong to one party, he belongs to the
National Front. He has a commitment to the National Front and to
the nation.''
   Rao and other national leaders of the front arrived in New Delhi
Sunday after local leaders failed a day earlier to force Singh to
retract his resignation.
   Singh submitted his resignation Saturday to Bommai. Bommai
rejected the offer, but Singh had remained adamant until the front
leaders met with him.
   The 7-month-old government was pushed into disarray Friday when
three Cabinet ministers resigned to protest the restoration of Devi
Lal's son to the top government job in Haryana state. Six more
ministers resigned Saturday.
   Bommai said the nine ministers' resignations were still in
effect and the issue was not discussed at Sunday's meeting with
Singh.
   The party's efforts to retain Singh as prime minister reinforced
the view that the prime minister was not serious about resigning
and was trying to force a showdown with Devi Lal, the biggest
irritant in Singh's control of the government. The government had
bogged down while Singh tried to cope with Devi Lal's pressure
tactics and tackle the business of running the country.
   The crisis was precipitated when Devi Lal, the 75-year-old
political patriarch of Haryana state, reinstated his son, Om
Prakash Chautala, as head of the state government. Chautala was
forced from the chief minister's office in May after 12 people died
in repeated election violence in his constituency.
   Chautala took his oath of office Thursday, and the next day
three members of the national Cabinet resigned in protest. On
Saturday, Singh himself offered to resign and six more junior
ministers followed suit.
   Bommai and Rao evaded questions about Chautala's fate. Rao,
leader of the Telegu Desam party, said it was up to the Janata Dal
to resolve the crisis.
   Singh led his party in ousting Rajiv Gandhi's Congress Party in
last November's national elections.
   Neither party got a majority of the seats in Parliament, but the
National Front formed the government on the strength of outside
support by a right-wing Hindu fundamentalist party and left-wing
parties. The common ground of the three groups was their antipathy
to the Congress Party.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0038 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 1641EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-GrayWhales     07-15 0454</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gray Whales,0468</SECOND>
<HEAD>Deaths of Gray Whales Stump Scientists</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ANCHORAGE, Alaska (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Twenty-three gray whale carcasses have
washed up on two remote islands south of Kodiak, and scientists
planned a study to determine why the mammals died.
   ``The concern is that we have a bunch of dead whales and we
don't know the cause,'' said Steve Zimmerman, chief of the
protected resources management division of the National Marine
Fisheries Service in Juneau.
   National Marine Fisheries Service officials in a U.S. Coast
Guard helicopter flew to the beaches in the Gulf of Alaska on
Saturday and planned to examine the dead whales for two days.
   They circled Tugidak and Sitkinak islands in the air to
determine how many carcasses were there and spotted 14 whales on
Tugidak and nine on Sitkinak.
   The 23 are the largest number of dead grays ever discovered in
the gulf, said Zimmerman, whose agency is mandated by Congress to
protect the whales and monitor their population.
   Effects of last year's Exxon Valdez oil spill in Prince William
Sound were among possible reasons for the deaths, but Zimmerman
said that was unlikely.
   The gulf is on the migration path of the whales, which travel
from Baja California to the Bering Sea every March.
   The gray whale population is booming. More than 20,000 of the
mammals were estimated to have migrated this year from their warm
Mexican lagoons to feeding grounds in icy Alaska waters.
   Twenty-three carcasses is ``a large number of dead whales,
certainly,'' said Don Calkins, a wildlife biologist with the Alaska
Department of Fish and Game. ``But the way the gray whale
population is going, it may not be that significant.''
   In fact, the burgeoning population may play a part in the
deaths, authorities said.
   ``It appears to be an indication of population stress,'' said
Jim Brooks, a fisheries service deputy director in Juneau.
   Brooks said the whales' behavior lately has been odd. For
instance, they've been seen in places far off their migration path
_ including in the waters near Juneau, hundreds of miles east.
   ``If you get enough people or animals of any sorts, you're going
to get misfits,'' Brooks said.
   The gray whales range from 36 to 50 feet long and are relatively
thin when they arrive at Alaska waters.
   They are known to eat very little for the six months they remain
at Baja California. The Bering Sea, the vast body of water
separating Alaska's west coast from the Soviet Union, provides the
whales with an ocean-bottom food supply of crustaceans.
   Authorities said carcasses found near Kodiak may be the remains
of weak animals unable to continue the journey north. Strong
currents in the region could have washed the whales ashore,
scientist speculated.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0039 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 1706EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Algeria-Fundamentalists     07-15 0270</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Algeria-Fundamentalists,0278</SECOND>
<HEAD>Islamic Councils Ban Popular Music, Segregate Schools</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ALGIERS, Algeria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Local Islamic fundamentalist councils
have banned a form of popular music and forbidden girls and boys
from sharing the same schoolrooms, the Algerian media reported.
   Along the Mediterranean coast west of the capital, where
fundamentalists won stunning victories in local and regional
elections last month, ``rai'' music is now banned.
   The music, a sort of Arabic rock celebrating love, sex and
youthful revolt, fails to ``correspond to the morals and precepts
of Islam,'' local media reported Saturday.
   Authorities are apparently searching for another form of
entertainment. They organized a three-day festival last week in
Oran dedicated to ``Islamic patriotic songs.''
   The provincial council of Constantine, in eastern Algeria,
meanwhile has ruled out mixed classrooms in schools and
universities.
   The An Nasr newspaper said the council, under the control of the
Islamic Salvation Front, has also banned the sale of all alcoholic
beverages in the province.
   Bars will be shut down and the distribution of non-alcholic
beverages reorganized in an unspecified manner, An Nasr said.
   Similar measures have already been taken in several of the
constituencies won by the front in Algeria's first contested
elections since independence from France in 1962.
   The fundamentalists trounced the ruling National Liberation
Front in the balloting, winning 835 of 1,539 municipalities and 32
of the 48 provincial councils.
   Islamic Salvation Front officials in the seaside resort of
Tipaza last week banned nudity and modern bathing suits on local
beaches. Short pants can be no shorter than the top of the knee for
men and the botton of the knee for women.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0040 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 1707EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Israel-Unrest     07-15 0282</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel-Unrest,0293</SECOND>
<HEAD>Politician Suggests Arming Palestinians Who Support Israel</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An extreme right-wing member of the governing
coalition said Sunday that Palestinians who support Israel should
be armed and organized to patrol the occupied West Bank and Gaza
Strip.
   Also Sunday, a Palestinian suspected of cooperating with Israeli
authorities was found hanged to death in the West Bank town of
Nablus, Arab reports said. Police said they were investigating the
death.
   The death raises to 236 the number of Palestinians killed by
fellow Arabs during the 31-month-old uprising against Israeli rule.
Most were suspected of cooperating with Israeli authorities.
   A total of 723 Palestinians have died of Israeli gunfire during
the rebellion, and 45 Israelis have been slain in the violence.
   Eliakim Haetzni of the nationalist Tehiya party said in an
interview Sunday that Palestinians should be organized into units
whose duty would be to ``enforce order'' in Palestinian villages in
the occupied lands.
   ``We should give them automatic weapons, police uniforms and
radios and let them institute the law,'' said Haetzni, a Jewish
settler who lives in the West Bank.
   Israel has issued weapons to some Palestinians who work with the
authorities, but only for the purposes of self-defense.
   Haetzni said his proposal was submitted to the Defense Ministry
in the past weeks.
   Defense Ministry spokeman Dan Naveh said he had not yet seen the
proposal, ``but we take any proposals by a member of the ruling
coalition seriously,'' he added.
   Senior security officials, however, dismissed the idea and said
it was not being discussed in the Defense Ministry.
   Yossi Sarid, of the left-wing opposition Citizens Rights
Movement, termed the plan ``lunatic, the work of a fringe
character.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0041 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 1717EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-China-Soviet     07-15 0230</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-China-Soviet,0236</SECOND>
<HEAD>China, Soviet Union to Set Up Their First Joint Venture in China</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An agreement to set up the first Sino-Soviet
joint venture in China is expected to be signed within two months,
an official report said Sunday.
   The two countries already have about 20 joint ventures, mostly
restaurants, in the Soviet Union. But the planned flax textile firm
in Inner Mongolia would be the first in China, the English-language
Business Weekly said.
   The flax mill in Baotou, 155 miles south of the Soviet border,
is expected to be completed in 1992, according to Ji Jun of the
Textile Ministry.
   Ji said construction had already begun. The Chinese side will
handle capital construction while four Soviet firms are to supply
spinning machines and materials.
   The report did not say how much each side would invest or how
the ownership will be divided.
   In the 1950s, the Soviet Union sent thousands of technical
advisers to help develop China. That cooperation ended when the two
Communist powers split over ideological and other differences at
the end of the decade.
   Relations have warmed in recent years, and diplomatic ties were
normalized last year when Soviet leader Mikhail Gorbachev visited
Beijing for the first summit in 30 years.
   Trade has developed correspondingly. Last year's trade volume
was estimated at $3.2 billion, or more than 14 times that of 1981.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0042 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 1718EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Salvador-Church     07-15 0335</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Salvador-Church,0350</SECOND>
<HEAD>Church Denounces Government Coverup of Jesuit Massacre</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DOUGLAS GRANT MINE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN SALVADOR, El Salvador (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Declaring the country ``a
kingdom of lies,'' a leading Roman Catholic clergyman Sunday
accused the military of hindering an inquiry into the massacre of
six Jesuit priests.
   ``We hope all those involved will be prosecuted,'' said
Monsignor Ricardo Urioste. ``The sad thing is that in this case, it
seems there is a truth we already know, but there are those who
have an interest in preventing that truth from being demonstrated.
...''
   ``We live in a kingdom of lies, and such a kingdom will destroy
itself,'' Urioste said in remarks to journalists.
   Earlier, Urioste delivered the nationally broadcast weekly
sermon in place of Archbishop Arturo Rivera Damas, who is out of
the country. Urioste is vicar of the capital's archdiocese.
   He told journalists he believed military officers questioned in
connection with last year's massacre had lied to Judge Ricardo
Zamora.
   Army troops killed the priests, their housekeeper and her
daughter before dawn on Nov. 16. A colonel, three lieutenants and
five other soldiers have been charged with the murders.
   The far-right had long considered the priests to be subversives.
It accused them of sympathizing with leftist guerrillas waging a
decade-old insurgency.
   At least 70,000 people, mostly civilians have died in that civil
war.
   The military has repeatedly pledged complete cooperation with
the investigation. But despite the promises, military authorities
have not handed over to Zamora a lieutenant colonel accused of
ordering the destruction of possibly key evidence.
   On June 26, Zamora ordered the arrest of Lt. Col. Camilo
Hernandez on charges of covering up the murder.
   The joint chiefs of staff said Hernandez was placed under arrest
July 5. However, he has yet to be taken before a judge.
   ``This is another demonstration that there are those who seem to
be above the law,'' Urioste said.
   The massacre had prompted calls in the U.S. Congress for cuts in
aid to El Salvador.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0043 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 1740EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-WeatherpageWeather     07-15 0395</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Weatherpage Weather,0410</SECOND>
<HEAD>Much of Nation Cool From Florida to Nebraska; Flooding in
Southeast</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Unseasonably cool weather speckled the nation from Florida to
Nebraska on Sunday, and heavy rains and flooding pounded parts of
Pennsylvania, West Virginia, Ohio, and sections of the Southeast.
   Parts of Crawford and Venengo counties in northwest Pennsylvania
were flooded, including two feet of water in streets in Titusville.
   Flooding extended into the West Virginia Panhandle, where a
mudslides were reported in Brooke County and Route 2 was flooded
near Wellsburg. Many creeks were out of their banks and roadway
flooding was reported in Hancock County.
   Evacuations were prompted in Ohio, but those orders were later
lifted.
   Still, an offramp from Interstate 80 was closed by high water
near Hubbard, Ohio, and a bridge at the town was washed out. State
roads also were closed by flooding at Boardman and Lowellville.
   There was local flooding in Illinois from heavy rain at La
Salle, Marseilles and Ottawa.
   San Angelo, Texas, also reported extensive street flooding
Sunday.
   Heavier rainfalls during the 6 hours ending at 2 p.m. EDT
included two inches at San Angelo, Texas and an inch at Tucson,
Ariz.
   Flooding in Arizona was reported at Tucson, Maricopa, Casa
Grande and Coolidge.More than two inches of rain caused extensive
flooding in the business district of Florence.
   On Sunday, showers and thunderstorms extended from western New
York state across much of Pennsylvania, New Jersey, Maryland,
Delaware, Virginia, West Virginia, eastern Ohio and southeast lower
Michigan.
   Showers and storms also reached from eastern North Carolina
across the South Carolina coast, over much of the Florida
peninsula, across a large part of Texas and western Oklahoma; from
northern Illinois across Wisconsin into western Upper Michigan; in
southeast Iowa, northwest Minnesota, southwestern South Dakota, and
central and southern Arizona; and central California.
   Several cities set record lows for the date on Sunday.
   Among them were Evansville, Ind., 52; Goodland, Kan., 52; Grand
Island, Neb., 52; Hot Springs, Ark., 52; Lincoln, Neb., 51; Paducah
Ky., 55; and Wichita, Kan., 55.
   Hollywood, Fla., tied its record low for the date, 69 degrees,
set in 1980.
   Low temperature for the nation Sunday morning was 39 degrees at
Gunnison, Colo.
   The nation's temperatures at 3 p.m. EDT ranged from 58 degrees
at Crescent City, Calif., to 98 at Palm Springs and Redding, both
in California.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0044 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 1752EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Albania 1stLd-Writethru a0670 07-15 0923</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Albania, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0670,0951</SECOND>
<HEAD>Albanian Refugee Ferry Arrives in French Harbor</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS thruout with details, color from arrival; quotes from
refugees; report of demonstration by refugees arriving in Turkey.
No pickup.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By PHILIPPE LARUE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MARSEILLE, France (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hundreds of Albanian refugees sang the
French national anthem to celebrate their newfound freedom as they
arrived at this port city Sunday after a three-day journey from
their Communist homeland.
   ``Long live France! Long live the Albanian people!'' the
refugees chanted as they left the ferry Orient Star on Marseille's
docks.
   The new arrivals are the last of thousands who boarded five
ferries last week for Western Europe. The Albanians had sought
refuge from the hard-line Communist regime in their homeland by
fleeing to Western embassies in Tirana, the Albanian capital.
   President Ramiz Alia's regime, the last bastion of orthodox
Communism in Eastern Europe, allowed the refugees to leave.
   Hundreds of ethnic Albanians living in France and Belgium lined
the docks of Marseille Sunday to welcome the refugees, singing the
traditional Albanian national anthem, ``Around the Flag,'' as the
ferry pulled into port.
   ``For me, this is a new birth,'' said Albert Aziri, an ethnic
Albanian from Yugoslavia who came to France in 1953. ``I'm going to
see my people, people who have the same blood as me.''
   About 100 Red Cross doctors, nurses and other workers took
charge of the 544 refugees, including 63 children, after they left
the ferry to begin a new life.
   Asked what was wrong with his homeland, one of the refugees,
Arian Cipa, replied simply: ``No freedom. No money. No future.''
   ``I know it won't be easy for me in France, but I hope to
succeed. I won't go back to Albania until the Communists are
gone,'' said Cipa, a geological engineer.
   Cipa was among those who took refuge in the French Embassy in
Tirana, the Albanian capital, for eight days before a U.N.-mediated
settlement allowed thousands of Albanians in foreign embassies to
leave for the West.
   Few of the refugees carried substantial luggage. Many wore only
plain T-shirts, poorly fitting trousers and sandals.
   Bernard Kouchner, secretary of state for humanitarian action,
escorted the Albanians to special trains bound for three reception
centers near Paris and one in southwestern France. At the centers,
fresh clothes, soap and toothpaste await the refugees.
   They will be given medical examinations, French lessons and
instruction in the basics of the French social security system.
   The refugees also will be given temporary residence permits and
have the right to apply for political asylum.
   A 25-year-old refugee who identified himself only as Afrim said
Albanian authorities had prevented his wife and young son from
boarding the Orient Star.
   ``I hope there won't be any reprisals against them,'' he said,
expressing hope they would be allowed to join him in France.
   The ferry had originally been scheduled to arrive on Saturday,
coinciding with celebrations of Bastille Day, the national holiday
marking the start of the French revolution against tyranny.
   The arrival was delayed after a 21-year-old pregnant woman had
to be taken off the ship in Italy with an unspecified ailment.
   Many of the expatriate Albanians on the docks Sunday back the
pretender to Albania's throne, Leka I. Red flags bearing the
double-headed eagle of the monarchy, deposed in 1939 by an Italian
invasion, fluttered under blazing summer skies until a French
official ordered them taken down.
   Francois Filliatre, the port's assistant prefect, told the
monarchists to take down the flags half an hour before the ship
arrived. His assistants distributed French flags.
   ``It's France who welcomes them and only the French flag should
be present,'' Filliatre told an aide to Leka, Hylle Spahija.
   The monarchists grumbled but complied.
   Riot police prevented the ethnic Albanians from embracing the
new arrivals. Only a few expatriates who spoke good French were
able to talk their way past the police cordon to greet the refugees.
   Earlier Sunday, another 76 Albanians flashed the ``V'' for
victory sign when they arrived in Turkey on a government-sponsored
flight from Tirana.
   Some of the refugees arriving in Turkey said they had heard
reports that about 6,000 people staged a pro-democracy
demonstration in the northern Albanian city of Shkoder on Friday,
and seven protesters were killed in a clash with soldiers. The
report could not be independently confirmed.
   About 4,500 Albanians were evacuated in a boatlift across the
Adriatic Sea to Brindisi, Italy, on Friday. Some remained in Italy,
and 544 traveled on the French-chartered Yugoslav ferry Orient Star
to Marseille.
   More than 3,000 of the Albanians who had sought refuge in the
West German Embassy traveled by train to West Germany. It was
unclear how many wanted to stay in West Germany or eventually go to
the United States or other countries.
   Also Saturday, 56 Albanians from the Polish Embassy in Tirana
were flown to Warsaw. Another 39 who sought refuge in the Hungarian
Embassy were flown to Budapest. Five others from the Bulgarian
Embassy traveled to Sofia.
   On Saturday night, two Albanians fled to Yugoslavia, raising to
15 the number of Albanians who have illegally crossed the Yugoslav
border in the past week, the state Tanjug news agency reported.
   The refugees began crowding into the embassies in Tirana two
weeks ago, seeking to flee Albania, which has resisted the kinds of
sweeping democratic reforms that have radically altered other East
European countries.
   Refugees said Albanians rushed the embassies after hearing that
a family that had been in the Italian Embassy since 1985 was
leaving the country.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0045 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 1832EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Marcos-Party     07-15 0328</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Marcos-Party,0339</SECOND>
<HEAD>Imelda Throws a Party for Jurors who Acquitted Her</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Marcos</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RICHARD PYLE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   After weeks of testimony about how she and her
late husband stole millions to buy skyscrapers and jewelry, Imelda
Marcos thought the jurors who acquitted her deserved to be shown
some appreciation.
   Drawing on her experience as the first lady in Manila, she threw
a party.
   It featured Filipino food and entertainment, including Mrs.
Marcos' own soprano rendering of ``God Bless America.''
   Ten of the 12 jurors who on July 2 acquitted Mrs. Marcos and her
co-defendant, Saudi Arabian financier Adnan Khashoggi, attended the
Saturday afternoon affair at Mrs. Marcos' penthouse on Manhattan's
East Side.
   The 100-plus guests also included court personnel, and friends
and relatives who had sat every day in the courtroom, lending moral
support to Mrs. Marcos as the government tried to prove her and
Khashoggi guilty of fraud and obstructing justice.
   Khashoggi stayed only briefly. He said he was flying later to
Saudi Arabia to make a long delayed visit to Islam's holy shrines
in Mecca.
   Since the trial, several jurors have said they felt the
government's case was confused and failed to show that Mrs. Marcos
had direct knowledge of the financial dealings of her late husband,
former President Ferdinand Marcos.
   They also have said they doubted some key witnesses who claimed
Khashoggi had falsified documents to help the Marcoses conceal
their ownership of four New York buildings and artwork bought with
the allegedly stolen money.
   Some of the jurors brought family members to the party.
   ``It's just a gathering of friends,'' said ex-juror Luellen
White, a subway worker who left carrying a decorated cake.
   Others departed with bouquets of flowers.
   Mrs. Marcos said during the party that she has been ordered by
the U.S. Justice Department to face grand jury questioning in
another criminal proceeding, one involving a lawsuit by the current
Philippines government against Westinghouse Electric Corp.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0046 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 1834EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Pakistan-Bombings     07-15 0506</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Pakistan-Bombings,0523</SECOND>
<HEAD>Explosions Rock Pakistani City, Killing 43</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HYDERABAD, Pakistan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Seven bombs exploded in this
ethnically troubled city Sunday, killing at least 43 people and
injuring scores, officials said.
   Six of the blasts occurred within 10 minutes of each other in
different areas of the city, police said. Those bombs killed 33
people and injured 110, hospital officials said.
   The explosives were placed at residential areas, a market and a
bus stop. Hospital officials said they feared the death toll would
rise. Pakistan's state-run news agency, however, said only 12
people died in the six bombings.
   The discrepancy in the casualties was not immediately explained,
but the state-run news agency, Associated Press of Pakistan,
usually reports a lower death toll than hospital and police sources.
   Meanwhile, about an hour later, a seventh bomb ripped through
the second-class coach of a southbound train minutes after it left
Hyderabad, the news agency said. It reported 10 dead and 15 injured
in that bombing.
   No one claimed responsibility for the bombings, but police said
they suspected Sindh nationalists demanding greater autonomy from
Pakistan.
   The Sindh nationalists, who control most of the countryside,
regularly clash with members of the Mohajir Qami Movement, which
represents Indian immigrants who came to Pakistan following
partition of the subcontinent in 1947.
   The Mohajirs want to be recognized as a fifth ethnic nationality.
   Sindh nationalists had called a one-day strike Sunday to protest
the arrest several weeks ago of Qada Magsi, a Sindhi activist,
charged with inciting violence.
   Most rival Mohajirs, who control Hyderabad, a bitterly divided
city of 3 million, refused to honor the strike call. Police
speculated the refusal prompted the bombings.
   Meanwhile, witnesses in Hyderabad said troops opened fire on
mourners who had gathered outside a local hospital, where many of
the dead were taken.
   Three people were killed in the firing, according to several
witness accounts. Other witnesses reported snipers in vehicles
opened fire on panicked crowds fleeing the bomb sites.
   In the past two months, hundreds of people have been killed in
Hyderabad and Pakistan's southern port city of Karachi, 100 miles
south. The deaths have been blamed on bitter ethnic rivalry between
Sindh nationalists and the Indian immigrants.
   Prime Minister Benazir Bhutto earlier acknowledged the Sindh
state government headed by her Pakistan's People's Party has not
done enough to stop the rising violence in her home province.
   The Mohajir Movement broke ranks with Ms. Bhutto in November,
claiming her populist Pakistan People's Party backed off promises.
   The movement, which controls 14 seats in the National Assembly,
aligned itself with Ms. Bhutto's opposition. The move prompted a
no-confidence vote, which she narrowly survived.
   On May 27 after weeks of killings, Ms. Bhutto deployed the army
in both Hyderabad and Karachi. Thousands of police and soldiers now
patrol the cities.
   But the army has also become openly critical of Ms. Bhutto,
claiming she has done little to defuse tensions and open talks.
Some quarters of the military reportedly want greater powers in
Sindh, something Ms. Bhutto has resisted.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0047 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 1835EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Israel-Housing     07-15 0253</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel-Housing,0262</SECOND>
<HEAD>Israel Approves New Housing Plan For Immigrants</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The government Sunday approved an emergency
plan to house thousands of Soviet immigrants in hotels, youth
hostels and sanitariums.
   Housing Minister Ariel Sharon, chairman of the government's
immigration committee, said the new plan would ease Israel's
housing crisis.
   ``I brought this proposal ... in order to block the skyrocketing
housing prices and to stop the young couples, Israelis, from being
thrown out of the apartments they live in,'' Sharon said on army
radio.
   The plan was approved Sunday by the immigration committee, which
is composed of representatives from different ministries dealing
with immigration.
   Rents have doubled and in some cases tripled with the arrival of
a huge wave of Soviet immigrants. Since 1986, about 63,000 Soviet
Jews have arrived in Israel. That figure is expected to hit 150,000
by the end of this year.
   Many Israelis have been forced out of homes or apartments they
rent by inflated housing prices. Some have taken to living in tents
to dramatize their plight.
   According to government figures, the country's 20,000 available
rental apartments will be filled by the end of September.
   Absorption Ministry spokeswoman Ida Ben-Shitrit said under the
new plan immigrants will be offered a choice of living in
apartments, low-rate hotels or youth hostels.
   ``This emergency plan will be implemented as an alternative
route, according to the choice of the immigrant,'' she said.
   She said low-rate hotels and youth hostels had the potential of
housing a maximum of 60,000 immigrants.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0048 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 1835EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SovietTrawler     07-15 0166</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet Trawler,0171</SECOND>
<HEAD>Chilean Navy Fires On Soviet Trawler</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SANTIAGO, Chile (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A navy patrol boat fired on a Soviet
trawler after it entered territorial waters and ignored orders to
halt, a navy communique said.
   There was no word on injuries or damage to the vessel, which
fled.
   According to the communique, the incident occurred early
Saturday in the Pacific Ocean about 180 miles off the southern
coast.
   The text of the communique, issued later Saturday, was carried
by Santiago newspapers on Sunday.
   It said a navy patrol boat spotted the trawler, identified as
the Odishi, at 3 a.m. and ordered it by radio and lantern to stop
and let authorities board.
   ``As it didn't obey the patrol's orders, we proceeded to fire
successive warning shots,'' the communique said. ``It still didn't
halt, so we fired on its superstructure.''
   The government secretary-general, Enrique Correa, said the navy
kept the government informed during the incident. He said the navy
acted in accordance with international law.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0049 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 1841EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--BastilleDay     07-15 0173</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Bastille Day,0177</SECOND>
<HEAD>More Than 1,200 Need Medical Help During Bastille Event</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   More than 1,200 people needed treatment for
injuries and other medical problems after taking to the streets for
a sound-and-light extravaganza capping Bastille Day, the Red Cross
said Sunday.
   About 2 million participants packed the banks of the Seine River
and avenues leading to the financial-district suburb of La Defense
to watch the mammoth concent by Jean-Michel Jarre on Saturday night.
   The Red Cross said Sunday that 22 of the revelers were
hospitalized for injuries. It gave no details of their injuries.
   Another 1,200 spectators sought relief at first-aid stations,
the agency said in a communique. It said most of those seeking
first aid were in need of water, sugar or rest.
   The show capped daylong festivities featuring a military parade
and a pledge by President Francois Mitterrand to keep French
nuclear and conventional forces independent and strong.
   The holiday celebrates the fall of the Bastille prison in 1789
that marked the beginning of the French Revolution.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0050 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 1838EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-PanamaRe-enactment     07-15 0412</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama Re-enactment,0425</SECOND>
<HEAD>Military Brass Downplay Panama Invasion Re-enactment in Air Show</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto SE2</HEAD>
<DATELINE>McCHORD AIR FORCE BASE, Wash. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   About 125,000 people
attended an air show billed as a re-enactment of the invasion of
Panama, but the military, stung by criticism of insensitivity,
downplayed the event.
   The early press release for the base's 50th anniversary
celebration promised a ``re-enactment of the invasion of Panama,
with the actual aircraft, air crews and soldiers who were there
participating!''
   But Capt. John Litton denied Saturday's event was a
re-enactment. ``That was just something that got overemphasized in
a news release,'' he said.
   Still, many of those who oohed and aahed the air show aerobatics
at the oldest Air Force base in the Pacific Northwest said they
were drawn by word they would get some of the sound and fury of the
Dec. 20 invasion.
   ``I think it's appropriate for them to re-create the Panama
invasion,'' said Jean Smith, a Tacoma grandmother joined by three
of her 18 grandchildren. ``This way you get a chance to find out
exactly what goes on, to see it for yourself.''
   ``War is war, and that's a fact of life,'' said Henry Stahl, who
brought his son, a member of the Air Force ROTC, to the show. ``If
the military does a good job, I think they should let the people
see.''
   Fighter planes roared overhead at 600 mph, and bombers and
helicopters swooped low on mock strafing runs. Paratroopers bailed
out of a C-141.
   The show did include some troops who participated in the Panama
invasion, said Bob Rosenburgh, a civilian Fort Lewis spokesman.
   Officials said they received some criticism and accusations of
an insensitivity to the loss of life in the invasion and overthrow
of Gen. Manuel Noriega.
   ``Somebody on base overhyped the event,'' insisted Col. Mike
McCarthy, base commander. ``As soon as I heard about it, I said,
`It's a mistake. We're not doing Panama II.'''
   ``We got a lot of flak about it,'' said Sgt. Randy Mitchell.
``It doesn't make sense to me. The public was overwhelmingly behind
the (Panama) operation, but now it's a sensitive subject, like
Vietnam.''
   Thousands of U.S. combat troops raided Panama in December to
oust and arrest Noriega and install as president Guillermo Endara,
who had lost May elections that were widely described as fraudulent.
   The invasion ultimately cost the lives of 220 civilians and at
least 300 soldiers, 23 of whom were American, according to the
Pentagon.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0051 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 1845EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Soviet-Protest 2ndLd-Writethru a0700 07-15 0794</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Protest, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0700,0816</SECOND>
<HEAD>Thousands Gather to Protest Communist Party Power</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 7th graf `A police...' to fix typos in crowd estimates
to read 50,000 and 400,000. Pickup 8th graf pvs `The rain ...'</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto MOSB9</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ANN IMSE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Tens of thousands of people marched to the Kremlin
walls on Sunday to protest Communist Party control of the
government, the army and the KGB and to demand greater democracy in
the Soviet Union.
   The protest came just two days after the party concluded a
historic congress in which President Mikhail S. Gorbachev
consolidated his control of the center but lost some of the party's
best-known radical reformers, who quit.
   The march took place despite a nearly constant rain. The slogans
were graphic: ``Communist worms _ this corpse won't feed you
anymore,'' said one poster. A woman hoisted a pair of shoes worn
into tatters and labeled, ``Slave of the Party.'' Another banner
said: ``Communist Party Onto the Trash Heap of History.''
   ``Every Communist to his own mausoleum!'' read one poster, a
reference to the mausoleum of Soviet founder Vladimir Lenin just a
few hundred yards away. Many Soviet citizens still treat Lenin as a
veritable God, and thousands file through his crypt every day to
pay homage to his mummified body.
   The protesters, huddled under a sea of umbrellas, hoisted sodden
red-white-and-blue flags of pre-revolutionary Russia and the black
flag of anarchist groups.
   Police used trucks to block entrances to Red Square, and the
protesters ended their march in adjacent Manezh square along one
wall of the Kremlin fortress.
   A police officer and local television station estimated the
crowd at 50,000, while an organizer announced that 400,000 people
marched. Western correspondents estimated the crowd at between
40,000 and 100,000.
   The rain apparently kept the size of the crowd down, although
the rally had been advertised in Moscow newspapers and on radio
stations.
   In an announcement Saturday, the Evening Moscow newspaper said
the rally ``was expected to be the largest joint action of
democratic forces of Moscow since Feb. 25.''
   On that date, a crowd estimated at between 100,000 and 500,000
marched to demand democratic reform. On Feb. 4, about 200,000
demonstrators demanded an end to the Communist Party's monopoly on
power.
   But Sunday's protest marked the first time a large crowd had
demonstrated such clear sentiments denouncing the entire Communist
system.
   The crowd cheered and waved their banners when a speaker
mentioned the names of reformers who quit the party last week:
Russian Federation President Boris Yeltsin, Moscow Mayor Gavriil
Popov and Leningrad Mayor Anatoly Sobchak.
   The protesters raised their hands at the end of the rally to
show their approval of a resolution calling for all ``aware''
Communists to quit the party, which now claims 19 million members.
   People poured in from side streets as the marchers passed along
the rain-swept Krimsky Bridge over the Moscow River and through the
Garden Ring Road, closed to traffic by police.
   One woman wore a wooden toilet seat around her neck, and labeled
it ``Polozkov'' after Ivan Polozkov, the hard-line leader of the
Communist Party in the Russian republic.
   Organizers of the march included the Moscow Voters' Club, the
radical reform groups Democratic Platform and Democratic Russia,
and an organization of reform-minded police and military officers
named Shield.
   In leaflets announcing the rally, they had called for the
Communists to disband their party cells in the army and KGB, and to
accept a coalition government.
   That echoes the calls of reformers who Thursday announced at the
congress they were quitting the Communist Party. Yeltsin has wide
support among the nation's working class, especially the restive
miners.
   Democratic Platform leader Vladimir Lysenko said Soviet coal
miners, who staged a one-day strike last week to demand the
resignation of Prime Minister Nikolai Ryzhkov, called for a second
strike in September. That strike would continue until the prime
minister steps down, he said.
   The crowd broke into shouts of ``Resign! Resign!'' and shook
their fists.
   At the end of the congress, the party announced a new structure
for its ruling Politburo that will no longer include such
government officials as the prime minister, the foreign minister,
the KGB chief and the defense minister.
   But radical reformers say that does not touch the foundation of
Communist Party power in the Soviet Union.
   Several pro-Yeltsin banners were visible in the crowd.
   One marcher advised Gorbachev to give up on his comrades in the
party, and expressed her support for Yeltsin.
   Gorbachev ``has done all he could do with the party,'' said Anna
Balykova, a woman in her 40s who came to the protest with her son.
``He has no more possibilities.''
   Of Yeltsin, she said, ``I pin all my hopes on him.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0052 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 1900EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Britain-Politics     07-15 0456</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Britain-Politics,0475</SECOND>
<HEAD>Some Members of British Party Try to Resurrect Dissolved Group</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A faction of the Social Democratic Party, a
centrist group whose dissolution was announced last month, said
Sunday they won't let their party die.
   Members who are seeking to keep the 9-year-old party alive said
they had overturned last month's decision by founder David Owen and
other party leaders to dissolve the Social Democrats.
   Members of the party's national committee who refused to accept
the dissolution said they took legal advice and decided that the
disbandment violated the party's constitution.
   ``We have formally rescinded the decision, and the party again
exists,'' said John Martin, a member of the national committee.
   However, it was not clear how much support his faction could
muster to keep the party alive.
   The party's national committee had voted 17-5 on June 3 to
suspend its constitution and disband.
   At the time, Owen cited the party's declining membership, which
had collapsed to 6,200 from a peak of 68,000 soon after the Social
Democrats were founded in January 1981.
   Owen is one of only three legislators the party has in the
650-member House of Commons. The three will continue to hold their
seats as independent Social Democrats.
   Owen's decision to pull out was seen as the end of the party.
But Martin said he would ask the party's parliamentary candidates
to remain on board to prepare for the next election, which must be
held by mid-1992.
   Owen and three other former Cabinet ministers broke with the
Labor Party in 1981 to offer voters a centrist alternative to the
Conservative Party and then-increasingly leftist Laborites.
   The Social Democrats had hoped to supplant Labor as the main
challenger to the Conservatives, who are led by Prime Minister
Margaret Thatcher.
   But Labor, led by Neil Kinnock, has abandoned its support for
unilateral nuclear disarmament and unveiled a more centrist
platform this year. Recent polls show it leads the Conservatives.
   
   The Social Democrats enjoyed their biggest electoral success
when they joined with the longer-established Liberals under the
name Alliance. That group polled 26 percent of the national vote in
the 1983 general election and 22.6 percent in 1987.
   But because of Britain's winner-take-all electoral system, it
never won more than a handful of parliamentary seats.
   After winning only 22 of the 650 parliamentary districts in
1987, a majority of the membership of the two parties agreed to
merge as the Social and Liberal Democrats.
   Owen and loyal supporters opposed to the merger, remaining
Social Democrats.
   Last month, Owen said he had no plans for now to rejoin the
Labor Party. He served as foreign minister from 1977-79 under a
Labor government and was once seen as a potential prime minister.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0053 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 1901EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-HospitalDrowning     07-15 0423</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Hospital Drowning,0437</SECOND>
<HEAD>Child Waiting with Family Drowns Outside Hospital</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TAMPA, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A 9-year-old who strayed from his father
drowned in a pond 50 feet from a hospital where his mother was
comforting a sick baby sister, police said.
   The body of Darren Shiwcharan was pulled from the pond in front
of Centurion Hospitals of Carrollwood by Hillsborough County
sheriff's divers Saturday morning, said sheriff's spokesman Jack
Espinosa.
   The boy apparently drowned in the 5-foot-deep pond while his
father and another sister dozed inside the family's station wagon
in a parking lot, Espinosa said.
   ``My eyes just closed a second, and the next thing I know he was
gone,'' said the father, Sewdat Shiwcharan, 39. ``I thought he had
fallen asleep. I ran to the emergency room, but he wasn't there.''
   The Shiwcharans brought their 6-month-old daughter to the
hospital Friday night because she had a high fever.
   ``We had to wait for 45 minutes, and there wasn't anybody else
there they were working on,'' he said. ``Finally they took her and
my wife into the emergency room.
   ``(Darren) was crying because he wanted to be with his mother. I
told them that. They got a security guard and ... kicked us out.''
   But hospital officials said the father was asked to stay in a
waiting room only after he verbally abused the emergency staff. A
security guard was called to the waiting room to watch the father,
who then went to his car with his son and 8-year-old daughter, said
hospital administrator Bill Chambers.
   Chambers said Shiwcharan was ``very upset about something. Foul
language was being used by him in the emergency room.''
   The three went to the car about 1 a.m. Darren apparently got out
at about about 20 minutes later, Chambers said. A couple leaving
the hospital at the time said later that they saw the boy heading
toward nearby Dale Mabry Highway.
   A search of the hospital and its grounds began when the father
discovered the boy missing. It ended just before daybreak when
divers found the boy's body.
   The parents are natives of Guyana and moved to Tampa two years
ago so the husband could take a job as a mechanic.
   ``If they had allowed the kids to go in the hospital and stay
with me, this would not have happened,'' said the mother, Sabitree
Shiwcharan, 29.
   Chambers disagreed.
   ``We were taking care of who we were supposed to be taking care
of _ the baby girl,'' he said.
   The infant was treated and released.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0054 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 1907EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-CircusParade     07-15 0250</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Circus Parade,0256</SECOND>
<HEAD>Parade Threatened with Violence Goes off Without a Hitch</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ANTHONY SHADID</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MILWAUKEE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Thousands of people flocked to downtown
Milwaukee Sunday to enjoy the annual Great Circus Parade despite
threats by a radical alderman who had planned a demonstration to
protest inner-city problems.
   Alderman Michael McGee, who has organized a black militia and
threatened violence in coming years if better jobs and housing are
not provided for his constitutents, told parade sponsors last week
that children should stay away from the parade because matters
``could get ugly.''
   But faced with a court restraining order, McGee called off the
threat and there were no protests at the parade, which took place
under overcast skies and occasional drizzle.
   Still, ``you couldn't help but be nervous and think about it,''
said Jeff Evans, of Waukesha. ``It's too bad that people were
stirring up all this trouble.''
   The parade included elephants and other circus animals. Actor
Ernest Borgnine was one of the costumed clowns. It also featured
about 75 brightly painted, carved wooden wagons from the State
Historical Society's museum collection.
   The wagons are hauled annually by train to Milwaukee from the
society's Circus World Museum in Baraboo, where the Ringling
brothers organized their original road show at the family farm in
the 19th century.
   Police traditionally say 500,000 watch the parade, but
acknowledge it is mathematically unlikely that many people could be
accommodated along a four-mile route. No other attendance figure is
officially issued.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0055 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 1952EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-HubbleTrouble     07-15 0427</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Hubble Trouble,0440</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hubble Trouble Not a Total Loss, Scientist Says</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TONY ROGERS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The $1.5 billion Hubble Space Telescope is not a
total loss despite the blurring of its giant eye by a misshapen
mirror, a scientist told a convention of astronomers on Sunday.
   Eric Chaisson, an adjunct professor of physics at Johns Hopkins
University, said the troubled telescope still can provide
scientists with information.
   ``We can view bright objects with decent resolution, but we
won't be able to see the faintest objects in the universe,''
Chaisson said. ``That, frankly, is what the Hubble had made its
name on. That is compromised.''
   Hubble's biggest mission was to peer into the universe's distant
corners.
   The telescope, launched April 25, has a focusing flaw that has
sharply reduced its usefulness. Because of an error in the grinding
and polishing of the Hubble's main mirrors, it cannot capture
crisp, clean pictures of distant stars.
   An investigation into the problem is continuing. The head of the
NASA probe, Dr. Lew Allen, told Congress last week that it may take
more than six months to pinpoint the error in the telescope
production.
   Chaisson is a senior scientist at the Space Telescope Science
Institute in Baltimore, the group charged with overseeing Hubble's
scientific explorations.
   When the convention of the Astronomical Society of the Pacific
was organized, Chaisson was slated to speak about Hubble's early
findings. Instead, he found himself focusing on the Hubble's woes
in his presentation before several hundred astronomers.
   ``You're going to have to stretch your imagination a little
bit,'' Chaisson said. ``There is a problem, clearly, we can't get
around that. But Hubble is not broken. There is still a lot of
exciting science to come out of it.''
   Chaisson showed a slide of the constellation Orion taken by
Hubble that had slightly greater clarity than one taken from
groud-based telescope.
   ``Hubble already shows starfields better than any ground-based
telescope,'' he said.
   Hubble had been expected to far surpass the capabilities of
observatory telescopes, which must peer up at the stars through
Earth's atmosphere.
   With its focusing problem, Hubble will be unable to pick out
distant stars to determine the size of the universe, Chaisson said.
   Nor will it be able to search the heavens for objects invisible
to ground-based telescopes, like planets in other solar systems or
extremely distant stellar objects, he said.
   Chaisson held out hope that when replacement instruments are
finally installed in 1993, Hubble will be able to complete much of
its mission over its planned 15-year lifetime.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0056 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 1953EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Canada-Mohawks     07-15 0676</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Canada-Mohawks,0701</SECOND>
<HEAD>Indians Keep Bridge Blocked in Canadian Land Dispute</HEAD>
<DATELINE>OKA, Quebec (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Indians locked in a land dispute with
authorities reversed themselves Sunday and kept up their blockade
of a bridge into Montreal.
   The Mohawks said they decided not to lift the blockade, as
promised, because authorities had reneged on a promise to reduce a
police contingent in Oka, about 20 miles west of Montreal.
   The town was the scene of a shootout Wednesday between
authorities and Mohawks manning barricades to block the expansion
of a golf course. The Indians say the expansion would occur on
their ancestral land.
   One police officer was killed in the confrontation, but it is
not clear if he was shot by Mohawks or fellow officers.
   Talks aimed at ending the Oka standoff between armed Mohawks and
police continued Sunday. Quebec province was represented by Native
Affairs Minister John Ciaccia.
   He said Sunday he believed that the two sides were close to
patching up their agreement of the night before.
   ``We have obtained the cooperation of Quebec police,'' said
Ciaccia.
   ``They have reduced the number of personnel _ however, not in
such a way as to affect our own security,'' he said. He refused to
say how many of the estimated 1,000 police officers at Oka have
pulled out.
   The Mohawks of the Kahnawake reserve blocked the Mercier bridge
on Wednesday in sympathy with the Oka Indians. The bridge blockade
enraged some residents, who faced massive traffic jams trying to
get into Montreal from the south shore of the St. Lawrence River by
alternate routes.
   On Saturday evening, a mob of about 2,000 residents gathered at
the boundary of the Kahnawake reserve and shouted racist slurs at
the natives. At one point, they burned a dummy bearing the words
``Non aux Warriors,'' or ``no to the Warriors.'' They also chanted
war whoops, danced and waved Quebec flags.
   The crowd dispersed only after Ciaccia emerged from six hours of
talks with native negotiators in Oka and promised the bridge
blockage would be lifted. He said provincial authorities would make
a ``significant reduction'' in their Oka police contingent in
exchange.
   But in a statement released Sunday, the Mohawk council of
Kahnawake said the deal was off because police forces had been
boosted both at Oka and near the Mercier bridge.
   On Sunday, a crowd of about 500 people gathered again at the
bridge. The afternoon started quietly as people carrying binoculars
and potato chips installed their folding lawn chairs near police
barricades to watch developments.
   Later, the crowd became restive and cheered as an effigy of a
Mohawk carrying a bow and arrow was hung from a lamppost.
   One nearby resident, Irene O'Brien-Neil, was scratched and
punched by two women when she arrived wearing an Indian beadwork
collar.
   ``I'm all for the Indians,'' she said, clutching a tuft of hair
she pulled from one of her attackers. ``It's their land. I'm
inconvenienced like everybody else at this barricade, but they have
rights.''
   Alain Lauzier, a truck driver, had other views. ``What I want to
know is: what happens the day after the bridge is opened and we
drive through Kahnawake? Are my wife and kids going to be faced
with guns from these guys?''
   Meanwhile, in Oka, a town of 3,000, police and the Indians from
the reservation there stared at each other across their own sets of
barricades.
   About 1,000 police officers blocked access to the town. Police
also prevented anyone from taking food into the Mohawk-occupied
area.
   Also Sunday, Gilles Landreville, acting mayor of Oka, said, ``We
don't think it's normal that a minister goes over there and
negotiates with people who have committed criminal acts,'' he said.
He was referring to the negotiations between Ciaccia and Mohawk
representatives.
   ``We are asking that they give up their arms, and then we can
start negotiating.''
   In Calgary on Saturday, Don Mazankowski, the national
government's deputy prime minister, said Ottawa is ready to
establish a committee to try to settle the dispute if blockades are
lifted and guns laid down.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0057 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 2019EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Cuba-Asylum     07-15 0473</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Cuba-Asylum,0488</SECOND>
<HEAD>Cuban Police Chase Asylum-seeker Into Spain's Embassy</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MADRID, Spain (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Cuban police violated the grounds of
Spain's embassy in Havana by chasing an asylum-seeker into the
compound and hauling him away, the Foreign Ministry said Sunday.
   Also Sunday, the official Mexican news agency reported that a
group of 30 Czechoslovak diplomats and dependents had left Havana,
apparently as a result of tensions over Cuban refugees at the
Czechoslovak embassy.
   Three other Cubans have taken refuge in the Spain's embassy and
12 Cubans are at the Czechoslovak embassy.
   The Spanish ambassador to Havana, Antonio Serrano, lodged a
protest with Cuban Foreign Minister Isidoro Malmierca after Cuban
police jumped over the iron gate to the Spanish embassy on Friday
while pursuing a young Cuban. The police detained the man.
   In his reply, Malmierca said there had been no intention of
violating the embassy and offered assurances that there would be no
repeat of such actions, said the Spanish Foreign Ministry
spokesman, Juan Lena.
   Malmierca said the chase had begun outside the embassy grounds.
   Lena said the Spanish government had asked Cuban authorities not
to take reprisals against the young man detained on the embassy
grounds.
   He said an undetermined number of Spanish policemen would be
sent to Havana to protect the embassy.
   Lena reiterated that Spain would not hand over the three Cubans
who sought refuge at the Spanish embassy last week. He said his
country was seeking to arrange their departure for Spain or a third
country.
   The Spanish news agency EFE said Cuba's Communist leader, Fidel
Castro, had guaranteed the security of foreign embassies in Cuba
during a talk with foreign reporters at a Bastille Day reception
Saturday at the French embassy.
   However, Castro was quoted by EFE as saying the refugees in the
Spanish and Czechoslovak embassies were ``anti-social elements
without any patriotic motivation.''
   On Saturday, the Czechoslovak Foreign Ministry in Prague said
two of the 14 Cubans who sought refuge at its embassy in Havana had
left the mission. One Cuban left without notifying the embassy
staff, and the other asked to leave without giving any explanation.
   The influx of asylum-seekers has heightened tensions between
Cuba and Czechoslovakia, which were close allies before last fall's
democratic upheaval toppled Prague's hard-line Communist leaders.
   Castro has resisted the reforms sweeping Eastern Europe and the
Soviet Union, sticking to his orthodox Marxist policies.
   The Mexican news agency, Notimex, did not say when the 30
Czechoslovak diplomats and dependents left the country. It quoted
unidentified European diplomatic sources as saying they were among
a group of about 70 Czechoslovak embassy personnel and family
members who had been warned to leave the country.
   The Notimex dispatch from Havana, monitored in Mexico, did not
give details about the warning other than to say the Czechoslovaks
``had received a recommendation to leave the country.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0058 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 2033EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-RoseKennedy 4thLd-Writethru a0719 07-15 0761</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Rose Kennedy, 4th Ld - Writethru, a0719,0773</SECOND>
<HEAD>Kennedy Clan Gather To Honor Matriarch</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Leads with 4 grafs to RECAST lead, CLARIFY that most of party
was over when Rose wheeled onto porch; picks up 5th graf pvs, ```As
she...</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto HYS1, HYS4</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DANA KENNEDY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HYANNIS PORT, Mass. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A glittering assembly of Kennedys and
other dignitaries saluted Rose Kennedy on her 100th birthday,
although the honored matriarch was in poor health and absent during
most of the celebration.
   The 370 guests attended the party in a large tent on Mrs.
Kennedy's lawn a few yards from Nantucket Sound. Four of her five
surviving children were present, as were most of her 28
grandchildren and 22 great-grandchildren.
   Around 5 p.m., after the lunch and speeches were over, a nurse
briefly wheeled Mrs. Kennedy, flanked by a few members of her clan,
out on the porch of her home.
   Earlier, Sen. Edward M. Kennedy had given a testimonial to his
mother but said he didn't expect her at the festivities because of
her frail health.
   ``As she told me just a few days ago,'' he said, ```I'm like old
wine _ they don't bring me out very often, but I'm well
preserved.'''
   The Massachusetts Democrat was joined by his ex-wife Joan
Kennedy; by Ethel Kennedy, the widow of his brother Robert Kennedy;
and by Kennedy sisters Patricia Kennedy Lawford, Jean Kennedy Smith
and Eunice Shriver. Their mentally retarded sister, Rosemary,
remained in a Wisconsin nursing home.
   ``In the chaos of our household, she was the quiet at the center
of the storm, the anchor of our family, the safe harbor to which we
always came,'' said the 58-year-old Edward Kennedy, the youngest of
nine children of Rose and the late Joseph P. Kennedy.
   ``She always stressed the importance of family loyalty and
family strength,'' said Mrs. Shriver, standing before a
photographic exhibit of her mother's life. ``She taught us we were
much stronger as a family than as individuals.''
   The birthday celebration was held a week before Mrs. Kennedy's
July 22 birthday. A smaller group will visit with her next Sunday.
   The guests were seated in a large tent at small tables under a
huge portrait taken of Mrs. Kennedy in 1980, her chin up and
wearing a red hat.
   The family and their guests ate from a buffet of poached salmon,
turkey, lobster and scallop salad and pasta primavera. Each table
held a bouquet of pink roses and a tiny framed portrait of Mrs.
Kennedy in a floral frame.
   Many of the guests wept during the showing of a film of Mrs.
Kennedy's life, narrated by her son. Singer Maureen McGovern
performed a medley of Mrs. Kennedy's favorite Irish songs,
including ``Rose of Tralee'' before the gathering sang ``Happy
Birthday.''
   President John F. Kennedy's daughter, Caroline Kennedy
Schlossberg, attended but her mother, Jacqueline Kennedy Onassis,
and her brother, John Jr., did not. TV reporter Maria Shriver, 34,
and her husband, Arnold Schwarzenegger, arrived with their baby
daughter, Katherine, dressed in a red polka dot playsuit and red
shoes. Maria Shriver is the daughter of Eunice and Sargent Shriver.
   Members of the Kennedy family spoke prior to the luncheon
ceremony about their contributions to the field of mental
retardation.
   Robert Kennedy Jr., 36, with his son clinging to his side, spoke
of his involvement in an inter-generational home for teen-age
mothers and elderly people in New York's inner city.
   Robert's brother Chris Kennedy, 26, said he has been directing a
model preschool program in Chicago, which mixes mentally retarded
children with average kids.
   ``One of the things that has made the greatest difference to our
mother is the work in which the current generation (of Kennedys) is
involved,'' Sen. Kennedy said. ``Mother told them and us that that
is her greatest birthday present.''
   Many of the guests were specialists in the field of mental
retardation. Also attending were humorist Art Buchwald; Kennedy
historian Arthur Schlesinger Jr.; Gov. Michael S. Dukakis and his
wife, Kitty; Secretary of Education Lauro Cavazos; actor Tom Hulce;
and champion skier Billy Kidd, who is involved with the Special
Olympics for mentally retarded children. The master of ceremonies
was Robert MacNeil of ``The MacNeil-Lehrer News Hour.''
   Four of Rose's children died in tragic circumstances. Her eldest
son, Joe Jr., was killed flying a secret Navy mission in 1944;
daughter Kathleen died in a plane crash in France. President
Kennedy was assassinated in 1963, and in 1968 Robert Kennedy was
shot to death in Los Angeles while he campaigned for the presidency.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0059 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 2045EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Obit-Lockwood     07-15 0376</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Lockwood,0390</SECOND>
<HEAD>Margaret Lockwood, British Film Star, Dies At 73</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Actress Margaret Lockwood, the beautiful brunette
who starred in Alfred Hitchcock's 1938 classic ``The Lady
Vanishes'' and reigned over Britain's film industry in the 1940s,
died Sunday. She was 73.
   A Cromwell Hospital statement said the family had asked for no
other details to be released.
   Born in Karachi, Pakistan, on Sept. 15, 1916, she had her first
stage role at age 12 as a fairy in Shakespeare's ``A Midsummer
Night's Dream.''
   She trained at the Royal Academy of Dramatic Art and made her
first film, ``Lorna Doone,'' when she was 19.
   Other notable films included ``Night Train to Munich,'' ``The
Man in Gray,'' and the 1945 hit ``The Wicked Lady.'' Parts of ``The
Wicked Lady'' had to be reshot before it could be screened in the
United States because her neckline was considered too daring.
   In ``The Wicked Lady,'' with James Mason, she played an
aristocratic lady who joins a highwayman in his life of crime.
   ``Once there was a period when no British film seemed complete
without her getting severely bruised in period costume by James
Mason,'' the critic Sheridan Morley wrote last year.
   By 1957, she had acted in more than 40 films. Her last film
appearance was in 1976 in a cameo role in ``The Slipper and the
Rose.''
   She was featured in the popular 1960s British Broadcasting Corp.
series ``The Flying Swan,'' co-starring her daughter Julia, and in
a series called ``Justice'' in the 1970s.
   In the 1940s, she was twice named biggest money-earner of
British cinema.
   She also enjoyed a rich stage career that continued until 1980
as Queen Alexandra in a short-lived production of ``Motherdear.''
   Her father, a railway clerk in the British colonial service in
India, had little contact with her. Her mother disapproved of her
first love, Rupert Leon, a London commodities clerk, and they
married in secret.
   He disliked her film career. He followed her to Hollywood where
she worked briefly, and they were divorced during World War II.
   Later, she had to fight a bitter court battle to win custody of
Julia, her only child.
   She never remarried, and in her last years lived a modest,
reclusive life in suburban London.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0060 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 2054EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Obit-Galido 1stLd-Writethru a0722 07-15 0364</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Galido, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0722,0372</SECOND>
<HEAD>General Who Implicated Imelda Marcos in Coup Plot Dies</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS four grafs for 5-7 bgng `Mrs. Marcos...' to ADD that
Mrs. Marcos had not said she was involved in attempted coup;
CORRECT name of Wrightwood, dropping ``City'' from name; pickup
graf 8 `U.S. officials...'</NOTE>
<DATELINE>MANILA, Philippines (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Brig. Gen. Alejandro Galido, who
implicated Imelda Marcos and an American in a failed December coup,
died early Sunday of liver cancer, officials said. He was 54.
   Galido gave up his post as chief of the military's southern
Luzon command in December after he was himself linked to the bloody
nine-day coup attempt. It killed 113 people and nearly toppled
President Corazon Aquino.
   Later, Chief of Staff Renato de Villa said Galido had
infiltrated ranks of military dissidents to spy on them for the
government.
   In a statement given in February, Galido said he telephoned Mrs.
Marcos in Hawaii last year to ask for financial backing for a coup
attempt, but she refused because of money problems.
   However, she has never said she was involved in the coup attempt.
   Mrs. Marcos, wife of the late Philippine leader Ferdinand
Marcos, was acquitted July 2 after a 10-week trial in U.S. District
Court in New York. The government had alleged that she helped her
husband loot the Philippines' treasury of more than $220 million,
using the money to buy four New York buildings, artworks and
jewelry.
   Mrs. Aquino was swept into power when a military-civilian
uprising ousted President Marcos in February 1986.
   Galido also said an American, Harold Maglio of Wrightwood,
Calif., offered to sell him $20 million worth of weapons for the
attempted coup. Galido said Maglio introduced himself as an Air
Force colonel working for the Defense Intelligence Agency.
   U.S. officials said Maglio worked at Norton Air Force Base in
southern California but had no links to the Defense Intelligence
Agency.
   Galido was born July 12, 1936, in Antique province. He graduated
from the Philippine Military Academy in 1958 and served primarily
in intelligence positions.
   He also served with the Philippine contingent in Vietnam during
the 1960s.
   He is survived by his widow, Consalacion, six sons and two
daughters.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0061 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 2109EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Nixon     07-15 0331</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Nixon,0341</SECOND>
<HEAD>Nixon Hopes Museum will Help Render Kinder Judgment of His Career</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Richard Nixon doesn't expect the news media
ever to love him, but the man who resigned the presidency in
disgrace thinks the public will judge him more kindly once people
tour his new library.
   The Richard M. Nixon Presidential Library and Birthplace will be
dedicated Thursday in Yorba Linda, in a ceremony to be attended by
President Bush and former Presidents Reagan, Ford and Nixon himself.
   The gathering is also expected to include the largest reunion of
Nixon administration officials since the ex-president's second
inauguration in 1972.
   On the eve of the celebration, Nixon told the Los Angeles Times
he believes the library will help remove much of the taint of the
Watergate scancal that resulted in his resigning in disgrace.
   ``Over time, as their interest fades, and if the public
continues to visit the Nixon museum, I would think that all the
events covered will be seen in a more objective perspective,''
Nixon commented.
   The president's written remarks, in answer to questions
submitted by the Times, were published Sunday.
   Nixon said the news media area are still obsessed with finding a
sinister purpose in his activities. Historians are too liberal ever
to be sympathetic to his cause, he said.
   But he doesn't ``waste time worrying'' about his political
legacy, Nixon said; nor does he give any thought to ``my so-called
political rehabilitation.''
   Nixon, 77, resigned office in 1974 amid allegations he helped
cover up a botched political burglary of Democratic Party
headquarters in the Watergate apartment complex in Washington. A
pardon from Ford kept Nixon from facing any possible charges.
   Library officials say the $21 million complex will have an
extensive Watergate section, along with many other exhibits showing
the more positive aspects of Nixon's career.
   The exhibits will showcase Nixon's foreign policy triumphs and
the adoption of the Clean Air Act and creation of the Environmental
Protection Agency during his administration.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0062 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 2112EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-LightningDeath 1stLd-Writethru a0710 07-15 0431</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lightning Death, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0710,0437</SECOND>
<HEAD>Authorities Rescue Hikers Trapped on Mount Whitney By Storm</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Subs 2nd graf to UPDATE with identification of victim.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>LONE PINE, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Rescuers brought more stranded climbers
down from towering Mount Whitney on Sunday, a day after lightning
struck a stone hut and killed one of the 13 hikers seeking shelter
there from a thunderstorm.
   The body of Matthew Nordbrock, 26, of Orange was flown Saturday
from the summit of 14,495-foot Whitney, the tallest mountain in the
contiguous United States, said Ann Melle, Inyo County sheriff's
spokeswoman.
   Four other people who suffered minor injuries, exposure and
burns also were rescued from the mountain Saturday. Three were
treated and released, while the fourth was admitted to Southern
Inyo Hospital in Lone Pine, Ms. Melle said.
   Eight more mountain enthusiasts who had crowded into the 12
feet-by-12 feet cabin were plucked from the mountain by cargo
helicopter about 6 a.m. Sunday. They and two other climbers, who
had made camp at a lower elevation, also were flown to the hospital
for treatment.
   The deadly lightning bolt struck about 3:30 p.m. Saturday in the
middle of a raging thunderstorm. Several hikers raced down from the
summit for help and met someone with a two-way radio, said
sheriff's Lt. Jack Goodrich.
   The frantic radio SOS was intercepted by a jetliner passing
overhead. Pilots notified air traffic controllers at Los Angeles
International Airport and the controllers passed the emergency call
on to Inyo County authorities.
   Rescue efforts began shortly before nightfall. The victim was
pronounced dead at the hospital about an hour after he was brought
in.
   The stone structure the hikers packed into was built in 1909 for
astronomers. It is not recommended as a shelter.
   ``The hut at the top is not there for hikers,'' Ms. Melle said.
``It's just an old, old structure. This is back country area.
Anyone who is up here is expected to be prepared. Mountain tops are
dangerous places to be.''
   Authorities had no plans to close the trail, Ms. Melle said.
   ``Mount Whitney is known for unusual storms,'' she said. ``It's
a very severe peak. Bad weather conditions are expected and weather
forecasts had predicted bad conditions.''
   Ms. Melle said up to 300 people attempt to scale the mountain
each day during the busy summer climbing season. Experienced
mountaineers usually take two days to hike the roughly 16 miles to
Mount Whitney's summit from the trailhead at 9,000 feet, near Lone
Pine.
   The mountain's majestic peak can be seen for miles along the
eastern Sierra Nevada range.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0063 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 2122EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-HomelessActivistShot     07-15 0204</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Homeless Activist Shot,0209</SECOND>
<HEAD>Seattle Homeless Activist Shot</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SEATTLE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A leading Seattle advocate for the homeless was
shot and critically wounded at his shelter after a fight with
another tenant, who apparently fired in self-defense, police said.
   Robert Willmott, 60, underwent surgery after being shot in the
neck and chest late Saturday night, said nursing supervisor Rosie
Davis, at Harborview Medical Center.
   Mitchell Washington, 36, told police that he shot Willmott with
a .22-caliber rifle after Willmott, brandishing a rifle of his own,
burst into the room at the Strand Helpers shelter where
Washington's family was sleeping.
   Washington also said Willmott had threatened him with a pistol
about 10 hours before the shooting took place.
   The only witnesses to the shooting were Washington's wife and
four children, but the evidence at the scene corroborated
Washington's statement, and he was released after questioning, said
police spokeswoman Tina Drain.
   Wilmott founded Strand Helpers, a private group relying on
donations and volunteer work, in 1982. A brochure from the group
said it had served more than 1.3 million meals and provided 280,000
people with free nights of housing.
   Willmott, who ran unsuccessfully for mayor last year, often
clashed with city authorities over housing policy.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0064 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 2125EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Poland-Priest     07-15 0485</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Poland-Priest,0497</SECOND>
<HEAD>Police Captain Hints at Involvement of Superiors in Priest Slaying</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WARSAW, Poland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A letter from a secret police captain
convicted in the 1984 murder of a pro-Solidarity priest has hinted
that the slaying was not a renegade act, but officially sanctioned
by senior government officials.
   The former secret police officer, Grzegorz Piotrowski, is
serving a lengthy prison sentence for his role in the October 1984
murder of the Rev. Jerzy Popieluszko. The priest was an outspoken
supporter of the then-outlawed Solidarity labor union, and his
slaying shocked the country.
   The text of a letter from Piotrowski to former Interior Minister
Gen. Czeslaw Kiszczak was published Friday in the pro-Solidarity
newspaper Gazeta Wyborcza. It bore no date, but was apparently
written several years ago.
   Piotrowski and three other secret police officers were quickly
arrested, tried and sentenced for the killing, but many Poles
viewed the proceedings as a coverup to prevent the implication of
more senior officials. In his letter, Piotrowski implicates senior
officials in the Interior Ministry.
   Gazeta Wyborcza cautioned its readers that Piotrowski's
allegations had not been independently verified and should be
treated with caution because Piotrowski might not be credible.
   Piotrowski was quoted as saying he was not sure if his letter
ever reached Kiszczak, who headed the interior ministry at the time
of the slaying. Kiszczak played a major role in the 1989
negotiations that led to the establishment of a Solidarity-led
government. He was dismissed as interior minister earlier this
month.
   During his trial, prosecutors maintained that Piotrowski was the
ringleader in the priest's killing and had committed the crime at
the instigation of his direct superior officer, Interior Ministry
Col. Adam Pietruszka.
   In his letter, Piotrowski wrote: ``General, our actions were not
an act of lawlessness but an act of devotion and subordination to
the Service, and you know this.''
   In the letter, in which he appears to be pleading for better
treatment in prison, Piotrowski added that he kept silent during
his trial out of a feeling of loyalty to the security service, and
not because of ``persuasion and promises'' made by a deputy to
Kiszczak.
   Piotrowski was originally sentenced in February 1985 to 25 years
in prison, but his sentence was reduced to 15 years in December
1987.
   Convicted with Piotrowski were his subordinates, two secret
police lieutenants, and his supervisor, Pietruszka, who did not
take part in the actual killing but was convicted of instigating
the crime.
   In his letter, Piotrowski wrote: ``Before the court I took on
myself the entire weight _ a silence which could have cost me my
life.''
   He wrote that the court was not informed that the security
service had routinely violated the law and constitution by
harassing and eavesdropping on church figures.
   ``The force carried out similar tasks very often, getting awards
and praise for them, even from the leadership of the interior
ministry,'' Piotrowski said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0065 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 2146EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Anti-SemiticStabbings     07-15 0358</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Anti-Semitic Stabbings,0371</SECOND>
<HEAD>Psychiatric Patients Stabs Four Jewish Children</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WELLINGTON, New Zealand (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A psychiatric patient screaming
anti-Semitic slogans stabbed four children in the playground of a
Jewish school Monday morning, police said.
   The children, ranging in age from 6 to 8, were hospitalized
after the attack. It occurred before classes started at the Hebrew
Congregation's Kadimah College and Kindergarten school.
   Witnesses said the woman was shouting anti-Semitic slogans as
she rushed into the playground and began stabbing the screaming
children. She was disarmed by a male teacher on duty at the
playground.
   Staff members and parents rushed to help the injured chilren as
schoolmates watched in horror. Parents bringing their children to
the morning assembly rushed them inside, where there were tearful
scenes as students tried to come to terms with what had happened.
   The hospitalized children were identified as 6-year-old twins
Nicholas and Samuel Henderson; Damon Bree, 8; and Simon Clark, 6.
   Their conditions were not immediately available. One suffered a
stomach wound, another sustained a punctured lung, and a third was
stabbed in the shoulder. The fourth was undergoing surgery for
unspecified wounds.
   The school, which has 200 students, offers programs for children
from pre-school age to 12 years old.
   Police Detective Inspector Mike Crawford said the woman would
face four charges of attempted murder in a court appearance later
Monday.
   He did not identify her but said she was an outpatient of
Carrington psychiatric hospital in Auckland.
   Police recovered a kitchen knife with a 4-inch-long blade after
the attack.
   Jewish leaders said the woman was not connected with the school.
   A Jewish student outside the school said the suspect in the
attack had been there Saturday to see an art exhibition. The
student said she had been turned away when she threatened a woman
attendant and made a nuisance of herself.
   Auckland Hebrew Congregation president Michael Kutner said
school security would be reviewed at a meeting Monday night.
   ``It appears to be one crazed person _ an isolated incident _
not part of a wave of violence,'' he said.
   Jewish leaders said they hoped the incident will not spark
copycat anti-Semitic incidents.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0066 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 2209EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-PLO-US 1stLd-Writethru a0653 07-15 0522</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-PLO-US, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0653,0533</SECOND>
<HEAD>Precede BAGHDAD</HEAD>
<HEAD>Arafat Rejects U.S. Conditions for Resuming Dialogue</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS thruout to UPDATE with Arafat rejecting U.S. condition
for dialogue; PRECEDE to Tunis; no pickup</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By HABIB FAKHRI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TUNIS, Tunisia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   PLO chairman Yasser Arafat on Sunday
rejected U.S. demands to discipline a guerrilla leader responsible
for an attempted seaborne raid on Isrel.
   Arafat made his remarks during a meeting at the Arab League's
Tunis headquarters of foreign ministers and delegates from the 21
member countries. The meeting was called to consider the fallout
from the recent break in the dialogue between the United States and
the Palestine Liberation Organization.
   Washington said it would not resume the dialogue with the PLO
unless the organization renounced the seaborne raid and took action
against Abul Abbas. His Palestinian guerrilla group, a PLO faction,
claimed responsibility for the May 30 assault foiled by Israeli
forces.
   ``It's out of the question for the PLO to bend itself to these
conditions,'' Arafat told the closed-door session, according to
participants in the meeting.
   The PLO chairman also accused the United States of ``supporting
Israel without limit,'' participants said.
   Arafat spoke after the PLO's chief delegate to the Arab League,
Mahmoud Abbas, urged ``concrete and efficient measures'' to protect
Arab interests following the suspension of the dialogue. Mahmoud
Abbas is not related to Abul Abbas.
   The delegate did not define what form such measures to protect
Arab interests would take, but he urged Arab countries to prepare a
response if Israel attacks either Iraq or Libya.
   The meeting started late Sunday and was likely to stretch into
Monday, observers said. The Arab League representatives were also
considering problems caused by the massive immigration of Soviet
Jews to Israel.
   League sources said the PLO wants the Arab countries to condemn
President Bush's decision to break off the U.S. dialogue with the
PLO.
   The PLO wants the United States to resume the dialogue, begun in
December 1988 after Arafat renounced terrorism and backed the right
of Israel to exist.
   Earlier Sunday, the PLO indefinitely postponed a meeting of its
Central Council scheduled for Wednesday in Baghdad, Iraq. The
meeting had been called to discuss the suspended dialogue with the
United States.
   The meeting would also have discussed how to respond to the new
right-wing Israeli government headed by Prime Minister Yitzhak
Shamir.
   The PLO's representative to Iraq, Azzam Ahmed, said the meeting
was called off ``to allow for more consultations.'' He said no new
date had been set for the meeting.
   Bush severed the dialogue with the PLO following the foiled
seaborne raid on a civilian-filled beach that was carried out by
Abul Abbas' Palestine Liberation Front, one of nine factions under
the umbrella of the PLO.
   In the raid, four guerrillas were killed and 12 captured. There
were no Israeli casualties.
   Washington has demanded that Abul Abbas be dismissed from the
PLO's Executive Committee for his role in the attack.
   The PLO serves as an umbrella organization for guerrilla
factions that sometimes fight among themselves and launch
independent attacks on Israeli targets. The largest group is
Arafat's mainstream Fatah.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0067 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 2222EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Cambodia 2ndLd-Writethru a0693 07-15 1044</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Cambodia, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0693,1078</SECOND>
<HEAD>Guerrillas Besiege Provincial Capitals, Make Major Military Gains</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS final graf to CORRECT typo in name of Savoeun</NOTE>
<HEAD>An AP Extra</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos NY5,6</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Associated Press correspondent Nate Thayer spent
five weeks with Cambodian guerrillas deep inside Cambodia, the
first Western journalist to make such a trip during the 11-year-old
war. This is his report.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By NATE THAYER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   NATIONAL HIGHWAY 6, Cambodia (AP) _ Guerrillas have seized
hundreds of villages and military positions in northern Cambodia,
forcing the army to fall back and defend besieged provincial
capitals.
   Evidence of the most significant guerrilla gains in more than 11
years of fighting was clear during a five-week trip with the
insurgents that covered 450 miles.
   The three-party guerrilla coalition, which includes the
Communist Khmer Rouge, controls large areas of the north and
northwest. The insurgents are shelling and launching commando raids
on key provincial capitals.
   Senior guerrilla commanders say the attacks are in preparation
for full-scale assaults on the cities of Kompong Thom and Siem
Reap, and the ancient temples of Angkor near Siem Reap.
   During the trip, hundreds of government artillery shells and
rockets landed daily, shaking the paddies of a beautiful
rice-growing region engulfed by war.
   Debris from bridges blown up by guerrillas littered highways.
The jungle fighters set up ambushes to attack convoys trying to
resupply forward government outposts defending the major urban
areas.
   Guerrilla medics trained in China ran field hospitals, dressing
wounds and amputating limbs.
   As the guerrillas advance, the world seeks a political solution
and worries that the Khmer Rouge, whose bloody regime was
overthrown by a Vietnamese invasion in December 1978, may regain
power. More than a million Cambodians were killed or died of
starvation during 3{ years of Khmer Rouge rule.
   Khmer Rouge commanders expressed confidence they would capture
Phnom Penh, the Cambodian capital. They used maps to illustrate
encirclement from the north, south and west _ similar to the
strategy in 1975, when the Khmer Rouge defeated the U.S.-backed
government of President Lon Nol.
   The trip, with an escort of guerrillas loyal to Prince Norodom
Sihanouk, leader of the coalition, began on the Thai border and
covered three northern provinces. Included was a 30-mile stretch of
National Highway 6, a government lifeline to outlying provinces,
now in guerrilla hands.
   It provided the first independent confirmation of the guerillas'
claims that they have advanced deep inside the country.
   Thousands of Sihanouk's guerrillas were seen lounging in
villages, shopping in bustling markets and manning lines around
Kompong Thom, which they said was their next target.
   Kompong Thom, a strategic crossroads city, is 90 miles north of
Phnom Penh.
   In separate attacks, the Khmer Rouge was advancing toward Siem
Reap, 200 miles northwest of Phnom Penh, and was within reach of
the Angkor temples.
   ``We have taken all the positions around Siem Reap, isolating
the town,'' said Ta Pok, a Khmer Rouge brigade commander
interviewed at his jungle base north of the city.
   ``We are winning everywhere we are fighting,'' said Col. Khan
Savoeun, a commander of forces loyal to Sihanouk, Cambodia's former
ruler, at headquarters in Stoeung, the de facto capital of what the
Sihanoukists call their liberated zone.
   In the war's early stages, most guerrillas were in bases along
the Thai border and obtaining weapons from China was easy, given
Thailand's support for the insurgents.
   Now the lines have shifted far from the frontier. The Sihanouk
forces and the Khmer Rouge have forged a network of thousands of
miles of secret roads and trails into the interior.
   Convoys of trucks, oxcarts and thousands of civilian supporters
were seen daily moving supplies from jungle caches to forward areas.
   Convoys of Chinese-supplied trucks and captured government
vehicles moved freely along sections of provincial highways that
were under government control less than a year ago.
   More than 50,000 insurgents are fighting an army that has
superior firepower, but is mostly conscripts reported to be poorly
trained. The guerrilla groups led by Sihanouk and Son Sann are
non-Communist, but the Khmer Rouge is by far the strongest.
   The war took a favorable turn for the guerrillas last fall, when
Vietnam withdrew most of its soldiers, leaving the forces of
Premier Hun Sen to face the battle-tested guerrillas alone.
   ``Sometimes I think Hun Sen is stupid; you know we don't need to
negotiate with him now,'' said Mit Lot, Khmer Rouge deputy division
commander at a base 12 miles from the Angkor Wat ruins.
   ``If they don't compromise, they will lose everything. At this
rate the war will be over by the end of the year.''
   Although the Khmer Rouge is the most powerful force in the
coalition, it seemed clear during the trip that the non-Communists
had gained considerable support and scored significant military
victories.
   The Khmer Rouge has little public support because of its
history, and that hampers its effectiveness in more heavily
populated areas.
   Sihanouk's commanders described a raid by 400 commandos who
briefly seized Kompong Thom in late June. They destroyed military
positions and tested the waters for what guerrilla field commanders
said would be a full-scale attack on the provincial capital.
   Heavy weapons could be seen in place less than five miles from
the city and rockets were being fired at Kompong Thom.
   The Sihanouk forces claim to control more than 700 towns and
villages. A major source of their strength appears to be wide
public support for Sihanouk, revered by many as a god-king during
his reign.
   Around Stoeng, on Highway 6 less than a 30-minute drive from
Kompong Thom, non-Communists control the largest area of Indochina
since the Americans left 15 years ago.
   Followers of Sihanouk have trained hundreds of civilian
administrators, teachers and medical personnel and begun an
aggressive effort to re-establish Buddhism.
   Thousands of children were seen attending primary schools.
Dozens of Buddhist temples were being refurbished and others built.
   While the Sihanoukists and Khmer Rouge are in a loose coalition,
tension between the groups was evident.
   ``For the time being, we share common military goals with the
Khmer Rouge, but we are in full control here,'' said Col. Khan
Savoeun, commander of the Kompong Thom area. ``The Khmer Rouge
understand strength, and we are very strong in Kompong Thom.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0068 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 2225EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-PrairieDogs     07-15 0613</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Prairie Dogs,0635</SECOND>
<HEAD>Shoot Ends with No Protest, Nearly 3,000 Rodents Dispatched</HEAD>
<HEAD>Laserphotos NATX1,2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ELLEN MILLER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NUCLA, Colo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hunters bagged nearly 3,000 prairie dogs in
a weekend shootout and the gleeful organizers of the event said
howls of protest from animal rights activists had done nothing but
attract more business.
   When the shoot was announced in April it drew criticism from
Gov. Roy Romer and Democratic Rep. Ben Nighthorse Campbell, but
Mayor John Vanderpool and shoot organizer Mike Mehew told the pols
to ``buzz off.''
   On Sunday, Mehew said he was grateful for their attentions,
which drew additional hunters and news media to the event. He said
he planned to write thank-you notes to Romer, Campbell and Robin
Duxbury of the Rocky Mountain Humane Society.
   Shoot participants weren't put off by the smattering of protest
either.
   ``All their noise does is bring the prairie dogs out of their
holes to see what's doing on,'' said Terrye Logan, 32, of Clyde,
Texas, one of three women competing in the event. ``My brothers
yesterday ended up laughing so hard they had to put their guns
down.''
   The 106 shooters at the first Top Dog World Championship Prairie
Dog Shoot slew a total of 2,956 prairie dogs in the two-day event.
   The top killers were local rancher Earl Reams and his partner,
Randy Calhoun, who dispatched 112 prairie dogs to win two
top-of-the line Kimber rifles.
   More important to local merchants, the event brought an economic
boost to the neighboring western Colorado towns of Nucla and
Naturita, which have been devastated by range droughts and a bust
in uranium mining.
   ``We did enough in four days to double what we do in an entire
(big game) hunting season,'' said Beulah Colcord, owner of the
Yellow Rock Cafe in Naturita. ``And we couldn't be happier with the
protesters. They made the publicity that brought all these people
in here.''
   Among the popular kitschy items on sale were ``critter
coffins,'' sold at $20-$35 each by Joe Hale and Rod Gerken of Hale
&amp; Gerken Funeral Home in Naturita.
   ``I've got this little office just fill of prairie dog caskets
and we have about 150 orders,'' Hale said. Proceeds were going to
needy families, he said.
   The hunters, resting their rifles on car hoods or shooting from
benches, popped their shots off into a desolate plain scarred by
the six-inch mounds and burrows of the prairie dogs.
   More than $7,000 in prizes was taken home by hunters who came
from North Carolina to California for the competition.
   It was billed as a way of reducing the population of the
foot-tall, grayish brown rodents, relatives of the squirrel.
Ranchers say the prairie dogs carry bubonic plague and ruin fields
that might be planted in oats. Cattle break their legs stumbling
into the holes.
   Only about two dozen protesters were on hand Saturday morning,
and the number dwindled over the weekend. Not surpisingly, none of
the picketers stuck around for the celebratory picnic Sunday
evening.
   Three protesters in their early 20s appeared Sunday morning,
blowing whistles and holding signs.
   ``If nothing else, we're bothering the mighty hunters,'' said
Jon Ellenbogen, 24. ``I don't take their arguments about damage
from prairie dogs. If the prairie dogs are ruining it for the cows,
don't raise cows. Shooting them is not much of a philosophy.''
   Shoot winner Reams, president of the West End Cattlemen's
Association, said the contest had boosted local pride.
   ``This is a rural community where we have guns and do a lot of
shooting. Some places have theaters, we have turkey shoots. This is
good for the town and now we're on the map.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0069 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 2227EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-FallsStuntman 1stLd-Writethru a0689 07-15 0596</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Falls Stuntman, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0689,0606</SECOND>
<HEAD>Man Tries to Go Over Falls in Barrel for Second Time</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Leads with 12 grafs to UPDATE with quotes from Munday; and to
DELETE outdated grafs. Picks up 12th graf pvs: `Two park ...</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto BF1</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NIAGARA FALLS, Ontario (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A daredevil who went over Niagara
Falls in a barrel in 1985 tried again Sunday but low water stranded
his barrel at the brink of the falls, police said.
   The barrel carrying Dave Munday, 53, stopped a foot before the
brink of the 176-foot Horseshoe Falls on the Canadian side of the
Niagara River. Police used a crane to fish the daredevil and his
barrel out of the river rapids.
   Niagara Parks Police, who patrol the park along the Canadian
side of the twin waterfalls, said Munday's barrel was dropped into
the river about 660 feet upstream of the Horseshoe Falls about 4:40
a.m.
   The Ontario Hydro electric utility had been diverting half the
river's flow overnight to power its hydroelectric plant, said
police spokesman George Bailey. The low river level helped snag the
barrel on the falls' rocky ledge, he said.
   Munday ``really doesn't know the river like a lot of people
thought he did,'' Bailey said. ``There was very little water going
over the falls, and he probably could have guessed that he would
get stuck.''
   ``I've never been a religious man, but something stopped it,''
Munday told The Associated Press Sunday night from his home in
Caistor Center, Ontario. ``Probably I would have been dead if it
went over.''
   Mundy said he was lying on his side inside the 650-pound,
7-foot-long barrel when it became stuck. He said part of the barrel
actually hung over the edge of the falls.
   ``If you tried it a thousand times you wouldn't be able to get
it to do that again,'' he said.
   Munday was the seventh person to successfully go over the falls
in a vessel. Three others before him died.
   After his 1985 trip, Munday told reporters, ``Anyone who would
go over the falls twice would have to be crazy.'' But since then,
he had boasted that he would do it again one day.
   Had he been successful Sunday, Munday would have become the
first person to survive two trips over the falls.
   During Sunday's attempt, the steel and foam barrel lodged on the
riverbed a foot from the Table Rock tourist area at the brink of
the falls, police said.
   Two park constables were able to bring the barrel to a wall at
the edge of the falls and secure it there while a crane was brought
to the site. The constables fashioned a sling and, using long
poles, positioned the barrel so it could be lifted up and away from
the brink.
   The rescue took two hours and ``put two people's lives in
jeopardy,'' Bailey said.
   When the barrel was lowered into the tourist area, Munday
emerged and was charged with violating laws that prohibit river
stunts. He faces a fine of up to $10,000 _ about $8,500 in U.S.
dollars. Police kept Munday's barrel.
   After his first ride, Munday was fined the maximum $1,000 for
trespassing and $500 for the stunt itself. In March, the maximum
fine was raised to $10,000 to discourage such stunts, Bailey said.
   Last month, a man who attempted to go over the falls in a kayak
apparently lost his life in the stunt. The battered kayak belonging
to Jessie Sharp, of Ocoee, Tenn., was found below the falls, but
his body has not been recovered.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0070 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 2233EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BRF--Drive-ByShooting     07-15 0168</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Drive-By Shooting,0173</SECOND>
<HEAD>Two Dead, Seven Hospitalized in Stockton, Calif., Shooting</HEAD>
<DATELINE>STOCKTON, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Gunmen opened fire from their cars into
a liquor store parking lot early Sunday, killing two people and
leaving seven others hospitalized, police said.
   Witnesses said the assailants drove by in three cars and opened
fire on the crowd of people, many of them customers of a taco wagon
parked outside the liquor store.
   Sgt. Edward Williams said a fight over a woman had occurred,
adding:
   ``Some of the fellows left and then subsequently returned with
additional people, armed with what we believe at this time was a
shotgun and a couple of rifles, and started firing on the people in
the parking lot.''
   Two men were arrested several hours after the 1:30 a.m.
shooting, but their names weren't immediately available.
   Two teen-age men were killed, and of the seven people
hospitalized in six area hospitals, three were listed in serious
condition and four in stable condition, said police spokeswoman
Dianne Cortez,
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0071 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 2253EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-EskimoVisit     07-15 0220</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Eskimo Visit,0225</SECOND>
<HEAD>Soviet Eskimo Dancers Arrive in Nome under Visa-Free Agreement</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NOME, Alaska (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two Soviet Eskimo dancers are visiting
northwest Alaska in the first instance such travel has been
permitted without visas since 1948, authorities said Sunday.
   Misha Ankarin and Yakov Tagiok arrived in Nome Saturday on a
special waiver granted by the U.S. State Department. The men were
invited by the Nana Native Corp. in Kotzebue to spend the summer
performing with that city's Northern Lights dancers.
   Tagiok, told reporters he hoped the first visa-free connection
between U.S. and Soviet Eskimos would make future visits easier.
   The agreement for visa-free travel among Eskimos from the two
nations was signed last year by Secretary of State James A. Baker
III and Eduard Shevardnadze, the Soviet foreign minister. The
accord is still being finalized, and the visit by the Eskimo
dancers was made as a goodwill gesture.
   Alaskan Eskimos have yet to be allowed to visit the Soviet Far
East without visas.
   The agreement affects natives of the Bering Strait area of the
Soviet Far East coast and from the Kobuk and Nome areas in Alaska.
   Ankarin and Tagiok are visiting friends and relatives in Nome
and plan to stay in Alaska two to three months. They said they also
may take trips to Anchorage and Fairbanks.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0072 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 2304EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-FireRdp     07-15 0330</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Fire Rdp,0340</SECOND>
<HEAD>2,075-Acre Fire Nearly Contained in Oregon; Other Blazes Battled</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Firefighters had nearly contained a 2,075-acre fire in central
Oregon Sunday just as the battle began to intensify against a blaze
in the eastern part of the state.
   The second fire _ 20 miles southeast of John Day in eastern
Oregon _ had consumed 300 acres by Sunday, said Jim Payne, fire
staff officer for the Malheur National Forest. He said it was
burning in subalpine fir and lodgepole pine.
   Temperatures in the 90s, low humidity and light winds were
aiding growth of the blaze, which was consuming commercial timber
and part of the Strawberry Mountain Wilderness. The fire's cause
remained unknown.
   Some 500 firefighters were using two water-dropping helicopters,
three bulldozers and several fire engines.
   ``The conditions are not real good,'' Payne said. ``Everything
depends on the winds. If the winds don't push it around, we'll
contain it. We'll have to wait and see.''
   Meanwhile, the fire burning six miles southeast of Sisters in
central Oregon was 90 percent contained Sunday and it was expected
to be under control by 6 p.m. Tuesday, said Oregon Department of
Forestry spokesman David Morman.
   In northern California's rural Santa Clara County, firefighters
battled rugged terrain, dry winds and high temperatures Sunday
while trying to contain a stubborn fire that burned 800 to 1,000
acres of grass and brush.
   Officials who earlier hoped to fully contain the fire 6{ miles
northeast of Mount Hamilton reported 65 percent containment Sunday
afternoon. Full containment was not expected until midnight Monday,
the California Department of Forestry said.
   ``We're having problems with containment because of the
steepness, wind and weather,'' said state forestry spokesman Chris
Morgan.
   Temperatures were 85 to 90 with 10-12 mph winds, he said.
   Firefighters were using four air tankers. The cause still was
under investigation.
   Only one building, an uninhabited log cabin, was burned.
Although there are ranches in the area, no homes were in danger.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0073 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 2319EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Congress-NASA 1stLd-Writethru a0640 07-15 0818</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Congress-NASA, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0640,750</SECOND>
<HEAD>Space Program Troubles Shake Congressional Confidence</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: Subs 8th graf ``Walsh added xxx to include NY Times report
that reports of outside White House panel are premature</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By STEVEN KOMAROW</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The failure of the Hubble Space Telescope and
grounding of the space shuttle fleet are shaking Congressional
confidence in the space program just as lawmakers search for ways
to redirect defense spending to civilian science.
   ``We were right on the edge of what all of us thought would be a
new chapter at NASA,'' said Rep. Mike Andrews, D-Texas. Now, he
says, cost overruns and defects in the Hubble telescope and shuttle
program make the space agency look like ``just one more big
bureaucracy.''
   ``And now the Hubble. You know there's new information about the
Hubble. Jay Leno has disclosed that it is actually working
perfectly but the universe is all blurry,'' quipped Sen. Al Gore,
D-Tenn., who conducted hearings on the telescope.
   Leno is a popular comedian who substitutes for Johnny Carson as
host of ``The Tonight Show'' on NBC-TV.
   Reports indicate that the White House is preparing to name a
panel of experts to review NASA operations in the wake of the
embarrassing problems with the Hubble and the shuttle program.
   White House spokesman Sean Walsh said the Bush administration is
conducting a ``broad review'' of the space program.
   ``Many ideas are being tossed around,'' he said in response to a
Saturday CBS News report that the panel of experts probably will be
named this week.
   Walsh added, however, that the administration will probably
``steer away from a major shakeup'' at NASA and The New York Times
quoted unidentified administration officials in Monday's editions
as saying no decision has been made on naming an outside review
panel and that such reports were ``premature and overblown.''
   Andrews, whose congressional district is home to thousands of
NASA workers, and other boosters say there's still widespread
support in Congress for space exploration.
   Two days after NASA revealed that the Hubble was crippled by a
defective mirror, the House approved $14.3 billion for the agency
in fiscal 1991, $2 billion more than the current fiscal year.
There's little talk of any immediate cutbacks.
   But the agency's big projects for the future are being looked at
with much more skepticism than before. Those include a $50 billion
system of weather satellites, the $37 billion permanent space
station, and President Bush's proposal to land a man on Mars within
30 years.
   ``The worse kept secret in Washington is that defense
contractors who are out of work are now pushing space spending as a
national priority,'' said Rep. Richard Durbin, D-Ill., a member of
the House Budget Committee. ``Where else can they spend billions of
taxpayers' dollars on theory and dreams?''
   More than $300 billion in new space projects have been proposed
for the next three decades. But among ardent supporters in
Congress, there is widespread reluctance to expand NASA's role
before an accounting is made for the problems in the current
programs.
   ``Their plate is quite full, and it's a very stressful time for
NASA. Whatever can go wrong is going wrong,'' said Rep. Bob
Traxler, D-Mich., chairman of the subcommittee that oversees the
space and science budget.
   Rep. Bill Green of New York, the senior Republican on that
panel, said a decision on pulling the plug on the space station
project must be made soon or it could be too far along to kill.
   Traxler says it's too early to tell whether the program, already
far over budget and under-capable, should be scrapped for something
more simple. But he said Congress is increasingly skeptical of big
science projects and especially of the promises made by their
backers.
   The usual gambit for getting a big project approved is to come
in with a low estimate, get Congress to sink money into it, and
then expect Congress to keep spending as the estimates go up
because so much money already is invested.
   ``Those days are gone,'' Traxler said.
   Andrews says NASA's problems run too deeply for Congress to
solve without presidential leadership, and he's critical of Vice
President Quayle for not doing more to straighten out NASA from his
post as chairman of the National Space Council.
   ``I hope George Bush doesn't just leave it up to Dan Quayle to
lead us through this difficult time,'' he said.
   For supporters of the defense establishment, one answer to
NASA's problems can be found by leaving a little of the ``peace
dividend'' under Pentagon control.
   ``You're already getting a huge amount of that,'' said Sen. Sam
Nunn, chairman of the Senate Armed Services Committee.
   Rep. Durbin, in a speech Friday, seemed to be skeptical either
way.
   ``If the American taxpayers thought peace in the world meant an
end to budgetary excesses of Pentagon contractors, the had their
head in the clouds,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0074 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 1350EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-TaxingServices Bjt   07-15 0813</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Taxing Services, Bjt,0841</SECOND>
<HEAD>States Looking More to Tax the Services Sector</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JONATHAN YENKIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   For decades, the sales tax in most states simply
meant consumers had to pay a bit more money when they bought a car
or a couch.
   But the shift toward a service-based economy has also brought
changes in tax policy. Now when states are in a financial crunch
they increasingly look to collect money each time a janitor mops a
floor or even when an executive phones a lawyer for advice.
   In Massachusetts, the state Legislature recently passed a tax
package that extends the sales tax to a broad range of services,
including accounting fees for businesses and athletic club
memberships.
   The move was a response to fiscal woes that over the last fiscal
saw the state run up a deficit over $1 billion as its bond rating
plummeted to the lowest ranking in the country.
   While Massachusetts is the latest state to consider taxing
services, some experts do not expect a rush to follow. Although a
services tax may be tempting it also can be fraught with
administrative headaches. That means states probably will not take
the step unless pushed by financial necessity.
   ``Talking about it is easier than implementing it,'' said Elaine
Leon, director of taxpayer services for the Department of Revenue
Services in Connecticut, which last year widely expanded its
services tax.
   A handful of states tax some level of services, but many others
have attempted the move and failed.
   Florida enacted a wide range of service taxes in 1987 but
repealed them before the end of the year. Observers, however, blame
the repeal on a political firestorm that accompanied the tax
package rather than administrative difficulties.
   The sales tax generally dates to the Great Depression, when many
states looking for money applied a levy on the purchase of tangible
property.
   ``For most states, the sales tax was set up at a time when the
country was more of a (manufacturing-based) economy,'' said Stephen
Kidder, the Massachusetts commissioner of revenue. ``That's what
has shifted over time.''
   In fact, some tax experts argue that many of the economic forces
that prompted growth in the sales tax in the 1930s also exist in
the 1990s, making the taxation of services a stronger possibility.
   Nonetheless, most states have been hesitant to move into the
services tax. Reasons often cited include a fear that the tax will
add costs to businesses, which then will pass them along to
consumers. Also, critics say the tax can hurt competitiveness in
individual states, prompting some firms to locate elsewhere.
   Unlike cars or washing machines, which are defined easily by
their physical presence, services have fuzzy boundaries and can be
far less tangible.
   For example, Connecticut taxes computer services _ a potentially
broad sector _ and thus tried to tax hotel reservations, since they
rely on computers. But the state's supreme court decided last year
that the tax should not apply, because customers were paying for
the reservations, not the computer service, Leon said.
   When asked how the state defines computer service, Leon said:
``We're still grasping with that.''
   Also, administering the tax becomes highly complex when levying
transactions a multi-state business has with another multi-state
firm.
   Roger Feldman, chairman of Gaston &amp; Snow, a major Boston law
firm with offices around the country, predicted Massachusetts
businesses would take their legal work outside the state to skirt
the sales tax. Firms are likely to shift some of tasks to
out-of-state offices.
   ``We'll try every legal means to avoid paying the tax,'' Feldman
said.
   Tax experts say political inertia is a major factor working
against service taxes.
   ``For most politicians and taxpayers, an old tax is a good
tax,'' said a report delivered last month to the Federation of Tax
Administrators, a national group of state tax officials.
   ``In substance, this position argues that known evils are better
than unknown evils,'' the report said.
   New Mexico is one state without such worries. Its original sales
tax from the Depression included a tax on services, said Carolyn
Lindberg, economic analyst with the New Mexico Taxation and Revenue
Department.
   As a result, New Mexico taxes most services, excluding sales
made by non-profit institutions. ``It's accepted,'' Lindberg said,
though she added, ``it comes as a shock to newcomers.''
   States that have tried more recently to adopt service taxes have
used more of a laundry list approach, identifying various services
to be included but omitting others. For example, Massachusetts'
plan exempts management consulting services, even though accounting
is included.
   Business and tax experts criticize this process, saying it may
meet political expediency but does not make economic sense.
   ``Everyone believes the future will have a different combination
of taxes,'' said James Howell, former chief economist at Bank of
Boston. ``But you can't draw it up in an arbitrary and pernicious
way.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0075 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 1406EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-LayingOff Bjt   07-15 0660</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Laying Off, Bjt,0682</SECOND>
<HEAD>As Layoffs Increase, Companies Seek Legal Advice</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DENISE LAVOIE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HARTFORD, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An employee signs a waiver promising not
to sue for age discrimination in return for a better severance
package, then turns around and sues anyway.
   A sinking retailer tells a federal bankruptcy judge it needs to
close a third of its stores and lay off 18,000 employees to
survive. The judge rules that the retailer must negotiate with the
workers on a severance package.
   Faced with increasingly complex labor laws and the need to trim
work forces in a souring economy, many companies are seeking legal
advice on how to lay off workers, lawyers say.
   ``The advice is simple _ be careful,'' said Felix Springer, an
attorney at Day, Berry &amp; Howard, a Hartford law firm that developed
a seminar on how to lay off employees to satisfy a flood of
corporate inquiries on the subject.
   More than 120 corporate executives attended the seminar this
spring in Hartford and Boston. Citing attorney-client
confidentiality, the law firm wouldn't disclose the names of
companies that sent representatives.
   Other law firms say they too are spending more time counseling
corporate clients on steps they can take to reduce their work
forces without opening themselves to wrongful termination or
discrimination lawsuits.
   ``It's a big issue. As the economy has turned sour, it's getting
to be more and more of our practice,'' said Henry Stewart, a labor
and employment lawyer at the Boston firm Palmer &amp; Dodge.
   New England is a focus of the trend because of its sagging
economic fortunes, and Connecicut is a prime example. Its
unemployment rate rose to 5.7 percent in April, surpassing the
national rate for the first time in 13 years.
   Nearly 30 percent of 480 companies that answered a recent survey
by the Connecticut Business and Industry Association said they
expect to reduce their work forces within the next three months.
   Springer said his firm advises managers to choose workers to be
laid off based on objective criteria including job performance, the
value of their work to the company, length of service and education
level.
   Companies also are urged to offer employees assistance in
finding new jobs, as well as generous severance packages when
possible, he said.
   Workers who feel they've been treated unfairly most commonly
invoke two laws: The federal Age Discrimination in Employment Act,
which covers those 40 and older, and Title 7 of the Civil Rights
Act of 1964, which prohibits employers from discriminating because
of race, religion, sex or national origin.
   But workers also are finding new and innovative ways to protect
themselves.
   More and more companies are asking employees to sign waivers
promising not to sue for age discrimination in exchange for extra
benefits, usually an enhanced severance package.
   That didn't stop two former employees from suing the Coca-Cola
Bottling Co. of New York for age discrimination. They claimed they
were told they wouldn't receive an enhanced severance package after
being let go unless they waived their right to sue under the age
discrimination act.
   The federal Equal Employment Opportunity Commission, already
concerned about such waivers, joined the suit, filed in U.S.
District Court in Bridgeport last year.
   Congress is considering legislation that would limit employers'
ability to offer extra benefits in exchange for an employee signing
a waiver, said Paul Brenner, an EEOC attorney who specializes in
age discrimination cases.
   ``It has become a very serious problem _ that is, that it's
cheaper to buy someone out with a waiver and then not have to worry
about a lawsuit,'' Brenner said.
   An estimated 18,000 employees expected to lose their jobs when
Ames Department Stores Inc. closes 221 stores this summer recently
won the right from a federal bankruptcy judge to negotiate with
Ames management on a severance package.
   The move could have lasting impact. Analysts said bankruptcy
proceedings could change dramatically if employees are made a party
to such negotiations.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0076 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 1448EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-AutoTalks Bjt   07-15 0786</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Auto Talks, Bjt,0808</SECOND>
<HEAD>Contract Talks Open This Week For Big Three Automakers</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By FREDERICK STANDISH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Auto Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DETROIT (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The nation's Big Three automakers open labor
contract talks this week, with the companies worried about
declining profits and Japanese competition and the union stressing
job security.
   The United Auto Workers union begins talks Wednesday at General
Motors Corp., Thursday at Ford Motor Co. and Friday at Chrysler
Corp. The three national contracts covering more than 450,000 auto
workers expire at midnight, Sept. 14, the first time in 11 years
that all three expire at the same time.
   Each of the Big Three is cutting costs, and it's likely the
union will be asked to pay a greater share of rising health and
retirement benefits. Before benefits, an average UAW assembler is
paid nearly $15 an hour.
   Anthony St. John, Chrysler's chief negotiator, has said that
just maintaining the benefits in the current contract would boost
Chrysler's labor costs 16 percent. Chrysler is in the worst
financial shape of the Big Three.
   The union will tell management that protecting existing jobs is
its top priority. Health and safety on the job, wages, time off and
pension improvements also are on the list.
   The union has not had a strike since 1985, but the prospect this
year has union members edgy. Families are paying off debts, holding
off on big-ticket purchases and socking away whatever money they
can.
   ``I try to expect the worst and hope for the best,'' said Gary
Sorrell, president of UAW Local 977 at General Motors Corp.'s
Marion, Ind., metal fabricating plant. He said he and his wife,
Joyce, canceled this year's vacation.
   The UAW left the signing ceremonies of the last contracts
bragging it had won job security because the companies were allowed
to close plants only when sales of the product made there fell.
   Since 1988, however, GM and Chrysler have used that clause to
close six assembly plants, putting 17,000 workers on the street.
The Japanese in the same period have opened three U.S. assembly
plants and announced plans for expansion of another.
   In June 1988, the Big Three's combined share of the nation's car
and truck market was 74.4 percent. The Japanese companies held 19.2
percent. During the next two years, the Big Three lost nearly 3
percentage points. The Japanese gained almost 5 points.
   ``You have to treat plant closings as you do a national
disaster,'' said Franklin Sherman of UAW Local 1005 in Parma, Ohio.
``You're talking about 3,000 or 4,000 people losing their jobs.''
   The UAW set its bargaining agenda at a convention in May;
President Owen Bieber pleaded with delegates to give bargaining
committees broad flexibility.
   Yet, there was militant talk at the convention. It's widely
believed GM will be targeted for a strike this year.
   Auto analyst Ron Glantz of Dean Witter Reynolds Inc. in San
Francisco calls a strike against GM likely. John Kirnan, an analyst
with Kidder, Peabody &amp; Co. of New York, said chances for a
widespread strike are better this year than in the past 20 years.
   The last nationwide strike by the UAW against an automaker was
in 1985 when about 70,000 Chrysler workers walked out for 12 days.
   Negotiations usually start slowly. Bargainers meet through July
and August in subcommittees focusing on contract clauses dealing
with specific issues.
   Sometime around Labor Day, the UAW chooses one of the companies
as a target. Talks at the other two companies are suspended until
settlement with the target is reached. That contract then is taken
to the others, modified slightly and brought to the rank-and-file
for a vote.
   But so-called pattern bargaining may disappear this year.
Chrysler, which reported an 80 percent decline in first-quarter
earnings, is seen as most likely to break the pattern. During its
financial crisis in the early 1980s, Chrysler extracted concession
contracts from the UAW.
   Finances are better at GM and Ford, but GM's first-quarter
profits this year were 54 percent below last year. Ford's were down
69 percent.
   Another factor in this year's talks is the aging work force and
the increasing number of retirees. The average age of the Big Three
auto workers is 42, compared with under 30 in the Japanese plants.
   Demands for retiree cost-of-living protection has led to
numerous protests by older union members; another such
demonstration is planned for Wednesday morning outside GM
headquarters.
   Wally Kijek, a member of Local 1005 in Parma, said that cost of
living adjustments, or COLAs, for retirees ``could be the ultimate
end to that job security issue. The guy who is growing into
retirement right now can rest assured that he will have an
equitable wage when he gets out there.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0077 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 1836EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-AlleghenyInternational     07-15 0293</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Allegheny International,0304</SECOND>
<HEAD>Allegheny International Lawsuit Settled</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PITTSBURGH (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Allegheny International Inc. has taken a major
step toward emerging from Chapter 11 bankruptcy protection as a
judge approved a $50 million settlement of a creditor lawsuit.
   The $1.3 billion suit was filed against Allegheny
International's bank lenders by the company's unsecured creditors.
   U.S. Bankruptcy Judge Joseph L. Cosetti late last week called
the proposed settlement fair, reasonable and essential to the
small-appliance manufacturer's chances of emerging from bankruptcy.
   The banks will make no cash payments. But they agreed to give up
their right to receive $39 million of the $57 million in interest
their loans to Allegheny International accrued from the company's
Feb. 20, 1988, bankruptcy filing through Feb. 29 of this year, plus
all interest accrued after that date.
   Interest has accrued at the rate of about $2 million a month.
   Allegheny International, which makes Sunbeam and Oster
appliances, has paid no interest, because such payments are not
permitted while under bankruptcy protection. It is to make the
payments once it emerges from bankruptcy.
   The interest being forfeited by the banks will be given to
unsecured creditors and shareholders in the forms of stock and
warrants. The banks also agreed to absorb their legal fees, for
which they usually could receive reimbursement from Allegheny
International.
   Allegheny International, meanwhile, agreed to provide legal
indemnity of up to $3 million to the banks arising out of other
claims that could arise from deals that prompted the suit.
   The creditors, who later were joined by shareholders, claimed in
their May 1988 complaint that institutions led by Mellon Bank
doomed the company to bankruptcy, at the expense of other
creditors, when they forced the company in 1986 to accept a harsh
new loan agreement.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900715-0078 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-90 2016EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-S&amp;LCrisis 1stLd-Writethru   07-15 0766</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-S&amp;L Crisis, 1st Ld-Writethru,0788</SECOND>
<HEAD>Thornburgh: No Criminal Evidence Against Neil Bush</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: SUBS 6th graf pvs, bgng: ``We need ...'' to CORRECT name of
TV program; picks up 7th graf pvs, bgng: ``Following the...'' A
version moving on general news wires.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By JOAN MOWER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Attorney General Dick Thornburgh said Sunday
he has no information that Neil Bush, President Bush's son,
participated in criminal activity in his role as director of a
failed savings and loan in Colorado.
   But Thornburgh insisted the Justice Department would pursue any
case against the 34-year-old Bush if it receives credible
allegations of criminal misconduct.
   In the meantime, the attorney general added, it would be unfair
to appoint an independent counsel to investigate Bush, as some
House Democrats have suggested.
   ``I don't think it would be fair to anyone, any citizen of the
United States to appoint an independent counsel ... where there is
not allegations of criminal misconduct,'' he said on ABC-TV's
``This Week With David Brinkley'' program.
   Ron Brown, chairman of the Democratic National Committee, said
there wouldn't be any talk of independent counsels if Thornburgh
and Justice Department officials were doing their jobs on the S&amp;L
debacle.
   ``We need presidential leadership. We need leadership from the
do-nothing Justice Department. ... We've got to clean up this
mess,'' he said on NBC-TV's ``Meet the Press.''
   Following the NBC broadcast, Thornburgh retaliated in a
statement issued by his office.
   ``Mr. Brown is either sadly misinformed or purposefully
distorting the record,'' Thornburgh said. The Bush administration,
he said, has more than doubled the number of investigators or
prosecutors, set up 27 task forces and, in the last 21 months,
indicted 329 people in the S&amp;L crisis.
   Elsewhere Sunday, Republicans and Democrats traded charges over
who's to blame for the S&amp;L cleanup, which may cost taxpayers as
much as $500 billion.
   While attention has focused on Neil Bush because of his father,
leaders of both political parties said he is simply a symbol of a
greater systemic failure.
   In general, Republicans have accused the Democratic-controlled
Congress of thwarting previous efforts to clean up the S&amp;Ls.
Democrats have accused the Republican presidential administrations
of lax supervision.
   ``Neil Bush is really not the issue,'' Brown said on NBC.
   Ed Rollins, co-chairman of the National Republican Congressional
Committee, agreed.
   ``Neil Bush was a passenger on the Titanic when it went down,''
Rollins said on the NBC program, adding: ``I think he was a little
naive, obviously, but he didn't cause the savings and loan
(crisis).''
   But Thornburgh said information turned up in other
investigations of Neil Bush's role as a director of the
Denver-based Silverado Banking, Savings and Loan Association might
be turned over to the Justice Department.
   So far, ``Nothing has been brought to our attention that
indicates criminal activity,'' he said. ``Let me assure you,
however, that in this case as in any other that if there are
credible allegations of criminal wrongdoing, we will pursue them.''
   Bush has been charged by thrift regulators with violating
conflict-of-interest rules for, in one case, accepting a loan from
a businessmen who later received a $900,000 line of credit from
Silverado. Bush has denied doing anything wrong and will appear at
an administrative hearing in September to defend himself.
   In addition, the Federal Deposit Insurance Corp. is
investigating the $1 billion failure of Silverado to determine
whether Neil Bush and other directors acted in a diligent manner.
Charges could be filed against Bush if the FDIC determines there
was negligence.
   Rep. Patricia Schroeder, D-Colo., said she will not abandon her
push to force Thornburgh to appoint an independent counsel to
investigate Silverado. However, she is one person short of the 12
members of the House Judiciary Committee needed to request an
attorney general to appoint a special counsel.
   But Rep. Newt Gingrich, R-Ga., said if an independent counsel
were assigned to the Silverado case, there would be a need for
similar investigations into, for instance, Democratic Sen. Alan
Cranston's acceptance of hundreds of thousands of dollars from
Charles Keating, head of a failed S&amp;L in California.
   William Seidman, chairman of the FDIC, said on CBS the Silverado
case was being handled ``like every other case'' of a failed
institution.
   The FDIC, which insures the commercial banking system, is
``under stress,'' Seidman warned.
   ``It's at a low point in history as a percentage of what it's
insuring,'' he said. ``And we can handle anything we can foresee
right now, but if things come along, major failures that we're not
able to foresee at this time, that would be another story.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
</Collection>
