<Collection>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901201-0001 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-01-90 0105EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Trucker'sChaplain     12-01 0372</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Trucker's Chaplain,0449</SECOND>
<HEAD>CB Minister Preaches From Truck Stop</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ALEX DOMINGUEZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BALTIMORE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Yo, good buddy. Yeah, you with the Bible.
What's you're handle?
   Truckers are calling the Rev. S. Anthony Battaglia, who
broadcasts from a citizen's band pulpit, ``Chaplain Man.''
   The barber-turned-preacher dispenses guidance for the soul and
directions for the road to his congregation of truckers drivers.
   Battaglia, 60, found a new calling when the Baltimore Port Truck
Plaza wanted to hire a CB radio buff to guide tired, hungry and
lost drivers on the busy Interstate 95 corridor.
   ``He's a right responsible fellow. He's kind of a caretaker
around here. He helps guys who get into a bind,'' said Steve
Newton, a former driver who is now a trucking agent in Baltimore.
   Sandwiched between a gift shop - complete with mud flap
ornaments including the popular chrome reclining nude - and a
coin-operated laundry, Battaglia mans his radio pulpit in the
security office of the truck stop's motel.
   Every weekday from 7 a.m. to 3 p.m., Battaglia sits with his
imitation leather Bible at a desk piled with a 40-channel CB radio,
police scanners, atlases and phone books.
   Battaglia, an ordained Baptist minister, is a chaplain at a
suburban Baltimore church and a volunteer chaplain for the
Baltimore County police and fire departments. He wears his fire
department uniform to the truck stop in case he gets a call.
   He spent 30 years as a barber, then switched directions and
worked as a real estate agent.
   Now, his congregation includes drivers with handles such as
``The Rubber Duck,'' ``Low Rider,'' and ``The Destroyer.''
   ``How 'bout that Chaplain Man?,'' one driver calls out. ``We got
an abandoned trailer. It's an Evergreen.''
   Another driver leaving the Fort McHenry Tunnel wants directions
to Eastern Avenue.
   ``That driver coming out of the hole, that exit is 5-9,''
Battaglia replies. ``This is the Baltimore Port Truck Plaza
welcoming you to Baltimore.''
   That greeting is about as much as he is allowed to say on the
air waves about the truck stop, because Federal Communications
Commission regulations forbid advertisements over the radio.
   ``Basically we're here to help the drivers. When they come into
Baltimore its one big maze of streets,'' Battaglia said.
   ``Truckers are lonely, too. They have marital problems. They can
feel free to come in for counsel,'' he said.
   ``I tell them, `Sometimes you just have to make a decision to go
out on your own with your own truck.' Or if things are slow, they
need someone to encourage them, to tell them to just hang on.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901201-0002 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-01-90 1816EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-HousingAbuses     12-01 0526</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Housing Abuses,0622</SECOND>
<HEAD>Report: Homeless Housing Guidelines Abused</HEAD>
<DATELINE>FORT WORTH, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Texas businessmen and church leaders
are living in fashionable homes with government subsidized rents
because of loopholes in federal homeless housing guidelines, a
newspaper reported.
   The Fort Worth Star-Telegram, in a story for Sunday editions,
said people who have too much money to qualify for welfare, food
stamps or other housing assistance qualified as homeless under a
program intended for the poor.
   ``Obviously, these kinds of abuses are unacceptable,'' said Walt
Sevier, a regional deputy administrator for the U.S. Department of
Housing and Urban Development. ``I don't want to overreact, but
that is simply obscene.''
   The Star-Telegram found that the vaguely defined HUD program
aimed at providing temporary shelter to the nation's homeless poor
has helped some of them, but also has resulted in abuses.
   HUD Secretary Jack Kemp launched the program after he took
office in February 1989. It makes available up to 10 percent of
50,000 foreclosed homes the federal government owns nationwide.
   Under the program, HUD-approved sponsors lease the homes for one
year to those who qualify for the assistance. The sponsors are
given additional two-year options to buy the homes at a price 10
percent below market value.
   After purchasing the homes, the sponsors can resell them at
market rates.
   Among examples of abuse cited by the newspaper:
   -Businessman and part-time street minister Roy Gray of Keller
rents a $92,500 home in the upscale Dallas suburb of Rowlett for $1
a year.
   -The net worth of Bill Robinson's non-profit company will soon
exceed $1 million, but the businessman and Baptist minister has
moved into a two-story home in Arlington appraised at $92,000, the
newspaper said.
   -Robert Holton, a construction contractor, pays $348 in monthly
rent for a four-bedroom, $85,500 home that he ``thought would be
adequate to house our furniture.''
   HUD regulations define a homeless person as virtually anyone
without a permanent home, regardless of income, and agency failed
to set limits on size and value of homes, the newspaper said.
   Agency officials said they are investigating whether Gray and
Robinson violated federal conflict-of-interest rules by using their
positions as church-affiliated HUD sponsors to lease the government
homes for themselves.
   The two are key officials in a small circle of area churches and
non-profit organizations linked with HUD to provide housing for the
homeless.
   Gray and Robinson have said they had no profit motive in
deciding who would benefit from the program. Gray said he had ``no
apologies'' for his housing placements and said all met HUD
regulations.
   ``We've got people in houses anywhere from zero income - you
know, people who didn't even have a job - to, I think the highest
one is about $2,000 a month,'' Gray said.
   A small charismatic church near Keller, Calvary Christian
Center, become the nation's largest sponsor for HUD's
homeless-housing program almost overnight, the newspaper said.
   The center holds the leases to 97 government homes. Gray, as
program coordinator for the church, has placed friends and family
members in HUD homes, the newspaper reported.
   The Star-Telegram said at least four Dallas-Fort Worth area
pastors or members of their families are living in HUD homes meant
for the homeless.
   All the pastors said they or their family members qualified for
a HUD home under the government's guidelines because they were
either strapped for cash or facing eviction from previous homes.
   ``It could be such an incredible, wonderful program,'' said Jan
Johnson, director of Community Enrichment Center, a homeless
sponsor affiliated with the Richland Hills Church of Christ.
   ``It's really sad if it's been abused,'' she said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901201-0003 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-01-90 1820EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Germany-Honecker 4thLd-Writethru a0556 12-01 0534</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Germany-Honecker, 4th Ld-Writethru, a0556,0636</SECOND>
<HEAD>German Authorities Issue Arrest Warrant for Honecker</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS thruout to UPDATE with officials seeking to take
Honecker in custody, lawyer saying Soviets have not made decision</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By DEBORAH SEWARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Authorities have issued an arrest warrant for
former East German leader Erich Honecker on charges he personally
gave shoot-to-kill orders at the Berlin Wall, justice officials
said Saturday.
   German police traveled to a Soviet military hospital south of
Berlin where Honecker is staying to take the former Communist Party
chief into custody. An official said the charge is manslaughter.
   But Cornel Christoffel, a spokesman for Berlin's justice
authorities, later told the ADN news agency that Honecker would not
be taken into custody Saturday night.
   News of the arrest warrant came on the eve of Sunday's first
all-German elections since 1932. Honecker was overthrown in October
1989 by a peaceful revolution that eventually led to German
unification Oct. 3.
   Honecker was ``very composed'' when he received the news of the
arrest warrant, said one of his lawyers, Wolfgang Ziegler.
   Ziegler said a Soviet doctor maintains Honecker is too ill to be
jailed, and he did not know when the Soviets would make a decision
on whether to turn over Honecker to German authorities.
   Christoffel, a spokesman for Berlin's justice department, said
the warrant links Honecker, 78, directly to the deaths of several
people who tried to escape East Germany during his rule.
   He said new documents have been uncovered that show Honecker's
signature on an order for border guards to shoot East Germans
trying flee across the Berlin Wall and the inner German border.
   A Justice Ministry official in Bonn, Ludwig Kirst, confirmed the
charge against Honecker is manslaughter. He said the warrant was
issued by a Berlin court late Friday and that German and Soviet
representatives were trying to arrange the necessary papers for
Honecker's release to German authorities.
   Another Berlin justice official, Jutta Limbach, said officials
would have to speak with the head of the Soviet military forces in
the former East Germany. The commanding officer, Gen. Boris
Vasilievich Snetkov, was on a business trip Saturday night.
   If convicted of manslaughter, Honecker could face a sentence of
five years to life in prison, depending on whether the court
considers extenuating circumstances.
   Honecker has been living at the Soviet hospital in Beelitz with
his wife, Margot.
   Honecker is also being investigated for obstruction of justice
on allegations his regime harbored West German leftist terrorists.
   The former East German government that took over last year has
also threatened to indict Honecker for corruption and treason, but
formal charges have not been filed.
   In a November interview with The European newspaper, the former
Communist leader was quoted as saying: ``In the end I will be seen
to have been right.''
   He also rejected personal responsibility for those killed while
trying to flee across East Germany's borders.
   ``I am not afraid of a show trial. I consider all the charges so
far brought by the prosecutor's office untenable,'' Honecker was
quoted as saying.
   News reports earlier this year had said Honecker was suffering
from cancer. However, recent pictures and television footage of him
have shown a fit-looking man walking on hospital grounds.
   Honecker ruled East Germany for 18 years until he was swept from
power in October 1989. As a Communist Party official, he oversaw
the construction of the Berlin Wall in 1961.
   More than 200 people died trying to escape from East Germany
during the 28 years that the wall stood as the Cold War's most
notorious symbol.
   The opening of the wall by East German authorities on Nov. 9,
1989, marked the beginning of the rush to German unity.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901201-0004 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-01-90 1905EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Poland     12-01 0589</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Poland,0698</SECOND>
<HEAD>Poland's Presidential Candidates Clash On Television</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN DANISZEWSKI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WARSAW, Poland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Surprise presidential challenger Stanislaw
Tyminski claimed Saturday on national television that he has
damaging ``personal materials'' about Lech Walesa.
   But the Solidarity leader claimed no such documents exist and
accused his opponent of a smear campaign.
   Tyminski refused to release the documents, saying he wanted ``to
maintain the noble tone of this campaign.''
   The two will meet in a runoff election on Sunday, Dec. 9.
   There were 160 journalists at the news conference, which was
broadcast live.
   ``I have a lot of material in my attache case,'' Tyminski said.
``Some of them are personal materials. Some are so serious that I
believe it needs private discussion with the candidate.''
   ``I expect that the SB (former secret police) is preparing
something I won't be able to answer. I think that is Tyminski's
tactic,'' Walesa said.
   ``This is a very serious accusation and I demand that those
documents be revealed,'' he said. ``Reveal it immediately. If I
win, I won't let you leave the country until you prove it all.''
   Walesa claimed if such documents existed, the Communist regime
would have used them during its battles with the Solidarity labor
leader during the 1980s.
   Tyminski requested to postpone a scheduled Sunday debate until
Thursday night, but Walesa said he will ``be waiting'' Sunday. By
law, campaigning must end at noon Friday.
   Although Saturday's two-hour session was not a debate, the
candidates, moderators and journalists clashed frequently.
   The questioning was supposed to alternate between the
candidates, but the number of inquiries for Tyminski far
outnumbered those for Walesa.
   Neither candidate was very specific about his programs. Walesa
said his positions were well known. Tyminski often clashed with
journalists who accused him of not answering their questions.
   Tyminski came from obscurity to defeat Prime Minister Tadeusz
Mazowiecki for a runoff spot in the first round of elections a week
ago.
   Tyminski, a self-proclaimed millionaire, says he can bring his
business skill to Poland and produce economic improvements within a
month.
   He has appealed to Poles struggling through the harsh economic
reforms carried out by the post-Communist government and has picked
up support among rural, small-town and young voters.
   The first opinion poll published after the first round of voting
showed Walesa leading Tyminski 58 percent to 30 percent.
   But Walesa has expressed concern about the Tyminski challenge,
and he repeated Saturday night that the challenger represents a
``counter-revolution'' and ``an accident on the road of accelerated
democracy.''
   ``We need those accidents, but they should not win,'' Walesa
said.
   Tyminski's candidacy has been clouded by some problems over the
past week. He has rejected an Interior Ministry report that the
emigre businessman's passport file shows he was in Libya seven
times during the 1980s, where he received visas to return to his
homeland.
   Repeatedly questioned about whether former Communist Party
members or discharged secret policemen were helping his campaign,
Tyminski said the background of his aides did not concern him but
that he would publish a list of their names Sunday.
   Tyminski said he was prepared to renounce his Peruvian and
Canadian citizenships if elected president.
   The candidate was vague about whether he still believes that
Poland should have nuclear weapons, as he wrote in a self-published
book issued in September when he returned to Poland after 21 years
and decided to run for president.
   Tyminski said the ``country is sinking'' because of the
government's economic reforms, which seek to create a capitalist
system from the socialist economy. He said the economic situation
is worse now then under the Communists.
   ``I think quick changes are possible,'' Tyminski said. ``First
we have to open government books and find out truth because those
books have been closed.''
   Walesa acknowledged ``many hopes were not realized'' but said
quick results are not possible.
   ``I am convinced that I can lead Polish reforms to achieve what
other candidates propose, but in a realistic way and not a dreaming
way,'' Walesa said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901201-0005 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-01-90 1917EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Chad 3rdLd-Writethru a0588 12-01 0818</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Chad, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0588,0990</SECOND>
<HEAD>President, Troops Flee Chad; Rebels March Into Capital</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 2 grafs for 23rd `A U.S....' to UPDATE wih Washington
announcing some Americans to leave; pickup graf 24 pvs ```We
are...'</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto PAR3</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By HISSENE MAHAMAT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>N'DJAMENA, Chad (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Hissene Habre fled the country
Saturday following a string of rebel victories, and the
Libyan-armed guerrilla fighters later marched into the capital,
Western diplomats said.
   Habre and much of his government sought refuge in neighboring
Cameroon, the diplomats said.
   As the rebels closed in, soldiers threw away their guns and
uniforms, leaving the city practically undefended. There was wild
looting in the capital, N'Djamena, by civilians and renegades from
the Chadian army.
   France began organizing the evacuation of French and other
foreign nationals living in this north-central African nation, a
former French colony.
   It was not immediately known how many rebels marched into the
city, but it appeared they were mainly advance patrols. Most
guerrillas seemed to have remained in eastern Chad, where they have
made significant incursions.
   The rebels' biggest victory has been the capture Thursday of
Abeche, an eastern town of about 30,000 people 500 miles from
N'Djamena.
   The rebels, led by former armed forces chief Idriss Deby, are
armed by Libya, but there was no indication the North African
nation was involved in the latest fighting.
   Libya, which has made historical claims to parts of Chad, denies
involvement in the rebel offensive, which began Nov. 10.
   Deby helped Habre, 48, oust former President Goukouni Oueddei
from power in 1982.
   The French news agency Agence France-Presse cited sources in
N'Djamena as saying Deby would march into the capital Sunday at the
head of an army of guerrillas and government deserters.
   Alingue Bawayeu, president of Chad's National Assembly and
apparently the highest-ranking government official left in
N'Djamena, appealed for calm in an address on Radio Chad. He said
negotiations were under way with Deby.
   Bawayeu, who is under the protection of French troops, said he
was leading an interim government comprised of National Assembly
members and urged soldiers to lay down their weapons.
   Western diplomats in N'Djamena and high-ranking sources in
Paris, all speaking on condition of anonymity, said Habre and his
family fled to neighboring Cameroon in a military transport plane
before dawn Saturday.
   They said government ministers and their entourages escaped
across a bridge into Cameroon, just west across the Chari River
from N'Djamena.
   Some officials remaining in the capital said Habre had left
N'Djamena to direct attacks against rebel forces.
   Troops deserted en masse after rumors spread of Habre's flight.
Angry citizens attacked government buildings or fled to Cameroon.
   Military boots and uniforms littered the roadsides, apparently
left behind by deserters hoping to avoid reprisals from the rebels.
   Many soldiers turned their rifles on motorists and commandeered
cars for the trip to Cameroon or Nigeria, which lies further west
across the northern tip of Cameroon.
   Others threw away their weapons, which were quickly picked up by
looters, who fired them into the air and went on rampages. Renegade
troops and civilians ransacked shops and houses setting fire to
them or stealing belongings.
   Political detainees and common criminals broke out of the city's
central jail, with little opposition from jailers.
   Less than three years ago, the capital city of 400,000 was
re-built after suffering heavy damage from fighting in 1978, 1979
and 1982.
   About 1,000 foreigners, mostly French, assembled at the
N'Djamena airport to be evacuated. A Boeing 747 was to arrive with
the first 500 or so in Paris on Sunday morning, with another to
follow shortly.
   In Washington, State Department spokeswoman Anita Stockman said
an unspecified number of Americans will be leaving N'Djamena on the
French-chartered planes and commercial flights bound for Paris on
Sunday and Monday.
   However, a U.S. Embassy spokesman said that no orders to leave
had been given for the 300 Americans living in Chad. French
officials did not expect many to be aboard.
   ``We are suggesting it is probably a good idea to leave now, but
it would only be voluntary,'' said the U.S. Embassy spokesman.
``There are lootings and firings, but I'm not aware of anybody
being hurt.''
   The Libyan news agency JANA, monitored in Rome, carried a
communique by Deby's Popular Salvation Front that promised no
reprisals against his opponents and urged foreigners not to leave.
   ``We reassure foreign nationals not to worry for their lives and
property,'' the JANA dispatch cited the communique as saying.
   France said Saturday it was sending 150 more Foreign
Legionnaires to bolster Operation Sparrowhawk, a permanent French
force first sent in 1986 when Libya threatened to capture
N'Djamena. At one point, French troops in Chad numbered 2,700.
   About 1,000 French troops are now stationed here under a defense
agreement.
   Paris has said that the current fighting is among Chadians, and
it will not interfere.
   Chad contends the rebels, based in neighboring Sudan, are backed
by Libya, which occupied two-thirds of Chad in 1980 after Habre was
defeated by Goukouni in another power struggle.
   The Libyans withdrew in November 1981 but made incursions from
the north in August 1983. In 1986, Libya moved further into
northern Chad, occupying much of the region known as the BET - the
initials of its three departments.
   Despite a peace treaty signed in 1989, Chad and Libya continue
to dispute a Libyan-occupied strip of land on the northern frontier
of this nation of 5.2 milion people.
   Deby, a highly regarded military strategist, was the mastermind
of a series of lightning attacks the following year that drove the
Libyans from the area.
   He and several other high-ranking officials were charged by
Habre with attempting a coup in April 1989. Deby escaped and
established a base in eastern Sudan.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901201-0006 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-01-90 1934EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-JetCrash 1stLd-Writethru a0584 12-01 0230</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Jet Crash, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0584,0258</SECOND>
<HEAD>Air Force F-16 Crashes, Pilot Survives</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: UDPATES throughout with pilot's ejecting to safety, his
identity, details. No pick up.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>PALMDALE, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An Air Force F-16 fighter on a
cross-country flight crashed Saturday at a military airfield,
officials said. The pilot ejected and parachuted to safety.
   The jet went down about 9:50 a.m. while flying from Luke Air
Force Base, Ariz., to Miramar Naval Air Station at San Diego on a
routine mission, said Lorraine Sadler, a spokesman for Air Force
Plant 42, where the jet went down.
   Plant 42 is a highly secure Air Force installation in the
Antelope Valley, where Northrop Corp. builds the B-2 stealth
bomber. Palmdale is about 50 miles north of downtown Los Angeles.
   ``The crash occurred on Air Force plant facilities,'' said Los
Angeles County sheriff's Sgt. Kennedy Westfall. ``The pilot ejected
and parachuted out. He landed on Air Force property.''
   The F-16 was from the 58th Tactical Training Wing of the 310th
Tactical Training Squadron at Luke.
   The pilot, Capt. Craig Fisher, was the only person aboard. He
was in good condition, Ms. Sadler said.
   A board of officers will investigate the crash. Authorities
provided no information about what kind of trouble the plane
developed or whether the pilot was attempting to make an emergency
landing.
   ``It's way to early to speculate about a cause,'' said Sgt. Rob
Sexton at Luke Air Force Base. ``It may take several weeks to a
couple of months to find out what happened.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901201-0007 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-01-90 1937EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Anti-SemiticVandalism     12-01 0213</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Anti-Semitic Vandalism,0240</SECOND>
<HEAD>Three Arrested In Anti-Semitic Vandalism At College Apologize</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ST. PAUL, Minn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Three men arrested in an investigation of
anti-Semitic vandalism in which a college dormitory was defiled by
human waste apologized moments after they were released from jail.
   They were released Friday because authorities were not ready to
file formal charges, but charges were expected.
   John Wodele, a spokesman for the Ramsey County attorney's
office, said authorities had 36 hours after the men's arrests
Wednesday to either charge them or let them go.
   Wodele said new information surfaced Friday afternoon and
charges against the men, who are not students at the school,
Macalester College, were likely Monday.
   The charges were likely to include ``burglary and the
destruction of property with the bias crime element,'' he said.
   Nov. 23, someone left an anti-Semitic letter and human waste in
the kosher kitchen at Hebrew House, a section of Macalester's Kirk
Hall. A rabbi later performed a ceremony to make the kitchen kosher
again.
   ``It was a practical joke that got a little out of hand,'' said
one of the men, who had been jailed since Thursday with the other
two. ``We didn't know it would affect them that way. We didn't mean
any harm. We're sorry.''
   The three, all in their 20s, said they entered the building only
in search of a warm place to have a party.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901201-0008 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-01-90 1938EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>d a AM-AxMurdersRuling     12-01 0181</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Ax Murders Ruling,0193</SECOND>
<HEAD>Supreme Court Upholds Ax Muderers' Conviction</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Ancy in 5th graf is cq</NOTE>
<DATELINE>ST. PAUL, Minn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Minnesota Supreme Court has upheld
the murder conviction and sentence of David Brom, who was found
guilty in the ax slayings of four members of his family.
   Brom was convicted of four counts of first-degree murder in the
February 1988 deaths in Rochester of his parents, Bernard and
Paulette, his sister, Diane, and his younger brother, Ricky.
   A public defender, Susan Maki, had appealed to the Supreme
Court, arguing Brom's rights were violated when a change of venue
request was denied and when psychiatric testimony was barred from
the trial's first phase.
   Maki said evidence showed that Brom, who had pleaded innocent by
reason of mental illness, was indeed mentally ill.
   Brom was sentenced in October 1989 to three life sentences and
Maki also had argued Olmsted County District Judge Ancy Morse
abused the court's discretion in imposing the sentence.
   The court rejected Maki's arguments in its decision disclosed
Friday by the Olmsted County attorney's office, which received an
early copy of the ruling.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901201-0009 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-01-90 1943EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Lebanon-Israel     12-01 0456</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lebanon-Israel,0525</SECOND>
<HEAD>Lebanon Protesting to United Nations Over Israeli Air Raids</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MOHAMMED SALAM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BEIRUT, Lebanon (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Lebanese officials said Saturday they
will file a U.N. complaint against Israel for repeated air raids on
Palestinian guerrilla bases.
   Israeli fighter jets Saturday staged the second attack in a week
north of its self-designated security zone in southern Lebanon.
Five guerrillas were wounded, police said.
   Lebanon's foreign ministry said it instructed its delegates at
the United Nations to lodge a complaint with the Security Council
about Israel's ``repeated violation of Lebanon's sovereignty.'' It
was not certain when the complaint would be lodged.
   Police said two Israeli jets fired four rockets Saturday into a
base used by the Libyan-backed Palestine Popular Struggle Front in
the Syrian-policed Bekaa Valley.
   A police spokesman, who cannot be identified under standing
regulations, said the guerrillas fired anti-aircraft guns, but no
hits were reported.
   The estimated 20,000 Syrian soldiers deployed in the Bekaa were
not involved in the action, police said.
   The spokesman said the Israeli rockets scored direct hits on a
one-story building used by the Struggle Front as its local
headquarters in the Bekaa town of Taalabaya, about 43 miles north
of the Israeli border.
   The Israeli military said the raid was in retaliation for an
attempted infiltration Nov. 20 by Struggle Front guerrillas in
south Lebanon. An Israeli lieutenant was killed along with four
guerrillas in a firefight.
   A Struggle Front spokesman in Beirut said, ``We lost contact
with the base immediately after it was attacked.''
   The spokesman, who refused to be identified, said the guerrillas
were expecting the attack and evacuated most of their positions in
Lebanon. The front, headed by Samir Ghosheh, is a hard-line faction
within the Palestine Liberation Organization.
   The raid was Israel's 20th air strike in Lebanon this year. By
police count, 20 people have been killed and 67 wounded in the air
raids.
   On Tuesday, Israeli warplanes blasted a base used by Palestinian
terrorist mastermind Abu Nidal's Fatah-Revolutionary Council
faction near the southern port city of Sidon. The planes also hit a
nearby base manned by the Marxist Democratic Front for the
Liberation of Palestine. Five guerrillas were killed.
   Earlier Tuesday, guerrillas of the Popular Front for the
Liberation of Palestine clashed with an Israeli patrol in south
Lebanon, killing five Israeli soldiers and eight guerrillas.
   There have been growing attempts by Palestinian guerrillas to
attack Israel's security zone, which was established after Israel
invasion troops withdrew from most of Lebanon in 1985. The zone
ranges from two to 10 miles wide.
   Palestinian guerrillas have agreed to withdraw from the Apple
Province in southern Lebanon to allow the Lebanese army to deploy
in the area, the government announced Friday.
   Palestinians deployed in the province earlier this year in an
effort to halt a feud between rival Lebanese Shiite Moslem
factions, the pro-Syrian Amal and the Iranian-backed Hezbollah, or
Party of God.
   The two sides, whose power struggle has left 1,100 people
killed, agreed last month to a truce brokered by Iran and Syria.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901201-0010 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-01-90 1949EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-CattleLoose     12-01 0199</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Cattle Loose,0225</SECOND>
<HEAD>Cattle Truck Accident Lets Wichita Relive Its Cowboy Days</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WICHITA, Kan. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The dusty Chisholm trail came to life
Saturday, when about 40 cattle that escaped from an overturned
trailer were rustled up from back yards and garages.
   ``It would not be the first time that cattle ran around down
there,'' said Craig Minor, a history professor at Wichita State
University. ``Of course, today it's not the same as it was then.''
   Dozens of police officers and firefighters rounded up the cattle
from back yards and garages and from between fire trucks, using
string and plywood to create makeshift corrals.
   ``We've got a bunch of good cowboys out here,'' said police Lt.
Jackie Arnold, who supervised the five-hour cattle drive over four
city blocks.
   The double-decker, semi-tractor trailer carrying 97 head of
cattle swerved to avoid a car and overturned. About 40 head
escaped, but the rest remained trapped inside, Arnold said.
   The driver was not hurt. Three of the animals died on impact and
two had to be killed.
   The same blocks in the early 1870s marked the end of the
Chisholm trail for Texas longhorns, which were then driven up to
the town's stockyards, said Minor, who wrote a book on the era.
   Cattle drives were barred within city limits in 1875.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901201-0011 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-01-90 1955EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-SatelliteLaunch     12-01 0200</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Satellite Launch,0216</SECOND>
<HEAD>Air Force Puts Military Weather Satellite in Orbit</HEAD>
<DATELINE>VANDENBERG AIR FORCE BASE, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A weather satellite
that will help the military plan air, sea and ground operatios was
launched Saturday into a near-polar orbit, the Air Force said.
   An Atlas E booster blasted off with a payload for the Defense
Meteorological Satellite Program. The satellite went into orbit
about five minutes later about 500 hundred miles above Earth.
   ``It's going to take 20 days or so to fully check out the
satellite and make sure it's working properly,'' said Staff Sgt.
Tom Clements. ``From what we can see, everything looks picture
perfect.''
   Meteorology information gathered by optical scanners on the
satellite will be used by all branches of the military to aid
commanders planning air, sea and ground operations, the Air Force
said.
   The satellite cost about $40 million to build in 1981, Clements
said. By today's dollars, the price tag is closer to $60 million.
   The Atlas E program costs $30 million to $40 million per year to
launch two payloads, he said.
   The satellite will allow forecasters to track existing and
developing weather patterns over remote areas. It will also be used
by the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration and similar
civilian agencies.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901201-0012 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-01-90 1958EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Poland-Anti-Semitism     12-01 0366</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Poland-Anti-Semitism,0404</SECOND>
<HEAD>Poland's Bishops Concerned About Anti-Semitism</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DRUSILLA MENAKER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WARSAW, Poland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The nation's Roman Catholic bishops said
Saturday they are worried by indications of growing anti-Semitism,
especially during the current presidential campaign.
   They said they plan to condemn hatred toward Jews and voice
regret for anti-Semitic acts committed onPPolish soil in a
long-awaited pastoral letter early next year.
   The text of the letter, to be read at Masses on Jan. 20, was not
disclosed Saturday, but the episcopate said it responds to ``signs
of anti-Semitism which are growing stronger,'' especially during
the presidential campaign.
   The document, which will deal with the centuries-old tradition
of anti-Semitism in Poland, was drafted after two year's work by
the Episcopate Commission for Dialogue with Judaism.
   It was long awaited by international Jewish groups and expected
to have enormous influence in Poland, where 93 percent of the 38
million people consider themselves Catholics.
   ``The commission felt obliged to repeat the words of the Holy
Father (Polish-born Pope John Paul II) who said during ceremonies
to mark the 50th anniversary of World War II that hostility and
hatred toward Judaism is in contradiction to Christian values of
human dignity,'' the epsicopate said in a statement to the official
PAP news agency.
   The Rev. Stanislaw Musial, the commission secretary, recently
said Poles should ask forgiveness for doing too little to save Jews
during World War II and wipe out anti-Semitism.
   His statement was the first by a ranking church official to
address Polish-Catholic culpability in the Nazi extermination of 3
million Polish Jews during World War II and discrimination suffered
by Jews in Poland before and after the war. Only a few thousand
Jews remain in Poland.
   The American Jewish Congress published an open letter in
mid-November expressing distress that the bishops had not yet
issued their letter and that ``the current resurgence of
anti-Semitism in Poland has not been sufficently addressed by the
church.''
   Anti-Semitism has tainted Poland's first democratic presidential
election, and hate grafitti can be seen throughout the country.
   Rumors circulated that the devoutly Catholic Prime Minister
Tadeusz Mazowiecki was Jewish or that his government was dominated
by Jews, and questioners consistently raised the issue at campaign
events. Mazowiecki was defeated in the election's first round a
week ago, but analysts attributed the loss mainly to discontent
with economic reforms.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901201-0013 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-01-90 2009EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-LoungeExplosion 1stLd-Writethru a0567 12-01 0413</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lounge Explosion, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0567,0523</SECOND>
<HEAD>24 People Injured by Rock Band's Exploding Flash Pot at Hotel</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: INSERTS one graf after 10th graf, `Bob David ...' to ADD that
band could not be located after explosion. Pick up 11th graf, `The
device ...'</NOTE>
<DATELINE>PUNTA GORDA, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A special effects ``flash pot,'' used
by a rock band to provide a quick burst of light, injured 24
people, one critically, when it exploded Saturday on a hotel dance
floor, authorities said.
   The band In and Out was using the electronically detonated
device for pyrotechnical effects during a show at a Holiday Inn.
   ``People said it sounded like a cannon going off - a loud bang,
then shrapnel started flying,'' said police detective Gary Depaulo.
   Seven people were admitted to hospitals, including a man listed
in critical condition following surgery for leg injuries. Three of
the injured were reported in serious condition.
   Depaulo said the band's homemade device, set in the middle of
the dance floor, sent debris flying into the crowd when it
exploded.
   ``It was unreal,'' said a witness, Tracey Catania. ``I was
pulling pieces of floor tile out of my hair. My ears are still
ringing.''
   The device consisted of a pipe, about 1{ inches around, screwed
into a piece of wood, Depaulo said. Smokeless powder was packed
into the cylinder.
   ``We don't know if it blew apart due to stress cracks on the
pipe, whether there was some foreign matter in it or whether there
was foul play,'' Depaulo said. ``We still have a lot of
investigating left.''
   The explosion did not cause a fire, but it damaged part of the
stage and some floor and ceiling tiles, Depaulo said.
   Bob David, general manager of the Holiday Inn, said the motel
was open and planned a show in the lounge Saturday night - with a
different band.
   The band left the motel soon after the explosion and could not
be located for comment.
   The device was being sent to the Florida Department of Law
Enforcement for evaluation, said police Cpl. Naomi Patterson.
Officals want to determine whether using explosive materials in the
building was legal, she said.
   Twenty-four people, including one band member, were taken to
three Charlotte County hospitals. All but seven were treated and
released, hospital officials said.
   Punta Gorda is a town of 7,000 about 160 miles south of Tampa.
   David said the Holiday Inn was aware of the injured patrons and
was ``doing everything we can for them. We're trying to console
those injured and see what happened.''
   Audrey Powell said she was with friends at the lounge about 10
feet from the explosion. ``We were very lucky,'' she said.
   Ms. Catania said she saw a man lying near the corner of the
dance floor in white pants soaked with blood.
   ``He was trying to get up, but he couldn't,'' she said.
   Depaulo said the band had been using the device for two years
and had not had any problems with it during its two-week stint at
the Holiday Inn.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901201-0014 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-01-90 2034EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Newspage-Heisman     12-01 0184</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Newspage-Heisman,0191</SECOND>
<HEAD>BYU Quarterback Detmer Wins Heisman Trophy</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Ty Detmer, the latest in a long line of great
Brigham Young quarterbacks, won the Heisman Trophy on Saturday,
becoming the first BYU player to win college football's most
important award.
   Detmer, a 6-foot, 175-pound native of San Antonio, is the 10th
underclassman to win the award. He has set or tied 25 collegiate
passing and total offense records.
   The ceremony was televised live by CBS from New York's Downtown
Athletic Club, which gives the award. In Honolulu for BYU's
regular-season finale against Hawaii, Detmer broke into a wide grin
when the word came.
   ``We've had great quarterbacks in the past and none of them won
it. It's about time we won one,'' he said via satellite hook-up.
   BYU's rich quarterback tradition began with Virgil Carter in the
mid-1960s and continued with stars such as Gifford Nielsen, Marc
Wilson, Jim McMahon, Steve Young and Robbie Bosco.
   Raghib ``Rocket'' Ismail, Notre Dame's all-purpose star,
finished second. Colorado running back Eric Bieniemy was third,
followed by Virginia quarterback Shawn Moore and Houston
quarterback David Klingler.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901201-0015 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-01-90 2037EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-WeatherpageWeather     12-01 0175</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Weatherpage Weather,0193</SECOND>
<HEAD>Snow in West, Rain in Midwest, Southeast</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Snow fell Saturday in the mountains of Washington state and
Oregon and rain was scattered in the Midwest and Southeast.
   In southeast Alaska, winds gusted up to 65 mph and produced wind
chills of 40 to 55 degrees below zero.
   Rain, changing to snow in higher elevations, stretched from the
northern Olympics and the Cascades of Washington state to the
northern Cascades of Oregon and across northern Idaho into
northwest Montana.
   Rain was scattered over Ohio, Indiana, Missouri, Arkansas and
Florida.
   The morning low in the Lower 48 states was zero in West
Yellowstone, Mont.
   A low temperature record for the date was broken in Fairbanks,
Alaska, with a reading of 47 degrees below zero. The record of 46
degrees below zero was set in 1906.
   Redding, Calif., dipped to 27 degrees and broke its low
temperature record for the date - 29 degrees set in 1980.
   Temperatures around the nation at 3 p.m. EST ranged from 8
degrees at Minot, N.D., to 84 degrees at Harlingen and McAllen,
both in Texas.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901201-0016 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-01-90 2059EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Tchaikovsky     12-01 0458</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Tchaikovsky,0531</SECOND>
<HEAD>Cannons Fire, Churchbells Ring for Tchaikovsky Memorial</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LENINGRAD (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Nearly 3,000 people packed a concert hall and
hundreds stood outside in freezing weather Saturday for a
Tchaikovsky anniversary concert featuring American violinist Itzhak
Perlman, cellist Yo Yo Ma and soprano Jessye Norman.
   Loudspeakers projected the 1812 Overture and other works by the
Russian composer onto Leningrad's snow-covered Artists Square on
the 150th anniversary of his birth.
   ``You know, my dear, I am so tired of living in this mess - all
these congresses, demonstrations, decrees and rationing. Here, for
an hour or so, you can forget about all that,'' said 89-year-old
Anna Smolina, who stood outside in minus 14 degree temperatures to
hear the two-hour concert.
   In keeping with Pyotr Ilyich Tchaikovsky's original score for
the 1812 Overture, churchbells rang and 16 cannons that had been
sent for the occasion. The cannons, from South Bend, Ind., were
fired to accompany the piece played by the Leningrad orchestra
under the baton of its music director, Yuri Temirkanov.
   American concert impresario Peter Gelb, a former assistant
manager of the Boston Symphony Orchestra, organized the concert at
the Leningrad Philharmonic's Great Hall. He previously arranged the
return appearances in the Soviet Union of emigre pianist Vladimir
Horowitz and cellist-conductor Mstislav Rostropovich.
   The concert was broadcast on television across the Soviet Union
and to an estimated audience of 25 million people in more than two
dozen other countries. It is scheduled to be shown later this year
in the United States on PBS, according to Kim Smedvig, an assistant
to Gelb.
   Western television companies flooded Artists Square with light,
making a statue of the Russian poet Alexander Pushkin and a small
grove of barren trees stand out starkly against the snow.
   ``It was a fairy tale setting. The tree branches were black
against the snow, and then the music poured out and took my breath
away,'' Maxim Korzhov, a Leningrad journalist, said afterward.
   Sergei Kondratiev, 19, a French horn student, stood with four of
his classmates from the Leningrad Conservatory behind a police
barrier on the cobblestone square, ringed by pre-revolutionary
buildings, including the Russian Museum and Maly Theater.
   ``You know, we couldn't stay away from a concert in which such
masters were playing. But we also couldn't get tickets to sit
inside,'' Kondratiev explained. ``Now, we're not sorry that we
didn't get in. It's more beautiful here.''
   The concert began with the orchestra playing Tchaikovsky's
Polonaise. Perlman then played the Serenade for Strings, followed
by the Waltz-Scherzo.
   Soviet pianist Boris Berezovsky, winner of the 1990 Tchaikovsky
Piano Compeition, played the 3rd movement from the 2nd Piano
Concerto; Ms. Norman sang three songs for voice and piano; the
orchestra played a movement from Tchaikovsky's Symphony No. 6, the
Pathetique; and Ma played the Rococco Variations for Cello.
   The concert concluded with the 1812 Overture and a fireworks
display that set some of the tree branches on fire. Firemen and
militia officers who were standing by quickly extinguished them,
much to the entertainment of the crowd.
   Tchaikovsky died in 1893 in Leningrad, where he spent most of
his life.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901201-0017 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-01-90 2133EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-LeagueofCities 2ndLd-Writethru a0609 12-01 0442</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-League of Cities, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0609,0535</SECOND>
<HEAD>League Postpones Phoenix Visit Because of King Holiday Controversy</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 12th graf, `Daniel Tabor ...' to CORRECT spelling of
Inglewood, sted Englewood.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By SUSAN FAHLGREN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HOUSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The National League of Cities on Saturday
canceled its 1991 convention in Phoenix because Arizona doesn't
recognize Martin Luther King Jr.'s birthday as a state holiday.
   The group, which has 9,000 members, said it would take its
annual convention to Phoenix in 1995, provided the state adopt the
holiday to honor the slain civil rights leader.
   Next year's League gathering was expected to draw at least
10,000 visitors and generate $6.9 million, Phoenix officials said.
   ``Racism is not a problem that can be localized to Arizona by
any stretch of the imagination. It's a problem that exists all over
the nation today,'' said Phoenix Mayor Paul Johnson.
   ``Our city has a Martin Luther King holiday,'' Johnson said.
``We're the only city in the nation today and the only city that
sits on that board that has a holiday that was passed by a vote of
the people.''
   Johnson said he was disappointed with League's decision to pull
the convention but pleased the organization appeared to be open to
visiting the city in 1995.
   ``It's better than I expected,'' Johnson said.
   The League's decision to give Phoenix a second chance in 1995
was suggested by Tucson Mayor Tom Volgy. Montana and New Hampshire
also do not recognize King's birthday as a legal holiday.
   ``This organization is an organization that has been built on
diversity and mutual respect and wherever this organization goes,
it deserves to go only to the cities that do display that same
mutual respect,'' Volgy said.
   He said cities like Phoenix and Tucson should not be penalized
for their state's inaction.
   ``We need this organization to say the right thing to Phoenix
because Phoenix did the right thing,'' Volgy said.
   Daniel Tabor, president-elect of the National Black Caucus of
Local Elected Officials and a councilman from Inglewood, Calif.,
said his group met Friday night with Johnson and other Phoenix
representatives, but were not convinced to back holding the League
convention in Arizona.
   The caucus serves as an advisory committee for the League, which
consists of elected municipal leaders who represent more than 1,300
cities in 49 states. ``While we understood both the economic and
other issues related to a convention of this size going to their
city, we thought a higher precedent was one that made a statement
that NBC/LEO and its membership would not, could not go to Phoenix
because we cannot separate Phoenix from the state of Arizona,''
Tabor said.
   Members agreed that regardless of costs and the ability to find
a new location for the December 1991 convention, it would be worth
because they would not go against a previously stated position by
the League.
   ``I want to send a negative message to the voters of Arizona who
put us in this position,'' said George D. Goodman, executive
director of the Michigan Municipal League. ``And the only way we
can do that is to postpone our convention in their state.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901201-0018 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-01-90 2144EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-PipelineCorrosion     12-01 0215</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Pipeline Corrosion,0221</SECOND>
<HEAD>State Official Declares Pipeline Safe After Company's Rust Check</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ANCHORAGE, Alaska (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The company that oversees the
trans-Alaska pipeline said it completed an investigation of
reported corrosion along the 800-mile link and found the line to be
sound.
   State and federal regulators who supervised the monthlong probe
by Alyeska Pipeline Service Co. said they had not decided whether
to allow the company to increase pressure in the line.
   Oil producers want to increase the amount of crude pumped
through the line linking North Slope with Valdez from 2.06 million
barrels to about 2.1 million barrels daily.
   The investigation, completed Friday, began after a pipeline
inspector accused his former employer, Thorpe Technical Services
Inc., of doing shoddy inspections of reported corrosion problems
over the past year.
   The pipeline carries about 25 percent all crude oil produced in
the United States. Alyeska operates the line for seven oil
companies and Thorpe Technical was hired to perform inspections.
   The investigation consisted of checking and rechecking 19 sites,
which where agreed to by Alyeska Pipeline and government
regulators, for possible corrosion and subsequent weakening.
   In a separate probe, state and federal officials are
investigating allegations that Thorpe Technical workers abused
drugs and alcohol on the job and that worker training was
insufficient.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901201-0019 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-01-90 2150EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-AirplaneRobbery 1stLd-Writethru a0602 12-01 0451</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Airplane Robbery, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0602,0547</SECOND>
<HEAD>Airplane Thieves Flee With $13.7 Million in Gold, Valuables</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 16 grafs to UPDATE with other comments from police,
details on robbery. Picks up 11th graf pvs, `In 1984 ...'</NOTE>
<DATELINE>MONTREAL (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Armed thieves ambushed a private plane as it
taxied down the tarmac Saturday and fled with nearly $13.7 million
in gold ingots and other valuables in one of Canada's largest
robberies, police said.
   The pre-dawn heist at Dorval International Airport outside
Montreal was carried out with commando-style precision by at least
four men, including one armed with a Soviet-made AK47 assault
rifle.
   They used a stolen garbage truck to smash through a fence, then
drove off with the loot in stolen vans, police said. A pipe bomb
exploded three miles away under an airport construction trailer,
and police called it a ``diversion tactic.''
   The vans and the weapon were later found about 3{ miles from the
airport.
   ``It was well executed,'' said Detective Lt. Allen Trepanier, a
Montreal police spokesman. ``For sure, this was done by an
organized group.''
   The twin-engined turbojet, owned by Sky Services Inc. of
Montreal, had been chartered by Brink's Canada Ltd. and was
returning from a regular overnight run from New York via Ottawa and
Toronto. It landed shortly before 4 a.m. EST and ran straight into
the ambush.
   ``As it was taxiing up to the hangar, a heavy garbage truck
broke through a fence followed by two Econoline vans that moved
into position to block the front and rear of the craft,'' said
police spokesman Lt. Andrew Theodosis.
   A masked thief carrying the AK47 stayed on the ground while
three others went inside the plane, Theodosis said.
   ``They told the three people aboard - a Brink's guard, the pilot
and the co-pilot - to keep looking straight ahead, not to turn
back. Then they started unloading the cargo area,'' he said.
   The crew or guard could not give police a detailed description
of the robbers. The robbers were heard speaking English and French.
   Theodosis said the men drove away with gold and silver ingots,
bonds, securities and jewelry. However, they left behind sacks
containing an unspecified amount of cash.
   Police said no one was injured and no shots fired.
   ``Prints were found,'' Trepanier said. ``That's all we can say
at this point.''
   A Brink's official in Montreal refused to comment on the case
and said all information will be released by the firm's
headquarters in Darien, Conn. No one answered the phone there late
Saturday.
   Officials at Sky Services also refused to speak about the
incident.
   In 1984, about $34.7 million in negotiable securities and $24.2
million in non-negotiable securities were stolen in the holdup of
two Merrill Lynch Canada messengers in Montreal.
   In 1983, an armed gang raided a warehouse at London's Heathrow
airport, stealing more than $37.5 million.
   The biggest robbery of all time reportedly occurred at the
Reichsbank following Nazi Germany's collapse in the spring of 1945.
Negotiable securities worth $400 million were stolen at that time.
   U.S. officials have labeled that an ``unverified allegation,''
and it has been dropped from the U.S. edition of the Guinness Book
of World Records.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901201-0020 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-01-90 2200EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Obit-DeTreaux 1stLd-Writethru a0608 12-01 0154</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-De Treaux, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0608,0157</SECOND>
<HEAD>`E.T.' Actress Tamara De Treaux Dead at 31</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: EDITS throughout to tighten.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Tamara De Treaux, a 31-inch-tall actress who
played the lovable alien in the Oscar-winning ``E.T., the
Extra-Terrestrial,'' has died, a friend said. She was 31.
   She died Wednesday of respiratory and heart problems at Medical
Center of North Hollywood, said the friend, Ken Maley.
   Her theater career began in San Francisco, and she joined a
singing group called The Medflies in 1980.
   Director Steven Spielberg spotted her during a Medflies
performance at the Roxy club in Los Angeles. He hired her to take
on the role of the Earth-stuck alien in ``E.T.'' after the original
actor was injured.
   Miss De Treaux played the lovable but ugly E.T. in scenes that
required movement, while a robot was used in close-ups.
   She is survived by her mother, Barbara Detro, a brother and a
sister.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901201-0021 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-01-90 2202EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Obit-Cousins 1stLd-Writethru a0577 12-01 0551</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Cousins, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0577,0667</SECOND>
<HEAD>Author, Editor Norman Cousins Dead at 75</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: ADDS one graf at bottom to UPDATE with funeral plans.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By WENDY E. LANE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Norman Cousins, the emissary and author who
helped inspire the holistic health movement with a strategy of
humor and positive thinking, died of a heart attack. He was 75.
   Cousins died Friday after falling ill at a hotel, where he had
gone to visit a friend.
   The editor of the Saturday Review for more than 30 years found a
new calling in 1979 with publication of the bestseller ``Anatomy of
an Illness as Perceived by the Patient.''
   The book details Cousins' recovery from a life-threatening form
of arthritis through a self-prescribed regimen of positive thinking
and vitamin C. ``He had a terrible illness and after the doctors
gave up hope he took charge of himself,'' said a colleague, Dr.
L.J. West, who is a professor and past director of psychiatry and
biobehavioral sciences at the University of California, Los
Angeles.
   ``He got interested in how attitudes and feelings could
influence a person's ability to cope with illness,'' West said.
   Cousins' 1983 book ``The Healing Heart'' detailed his recovery
from earlier heart trouble.
   He became editor of the Saturday Review at age 25, expanding the
magazine's scope to include book reviews, political coverage and
arts reviews. Two years later, he was named editor in chief.
Cousins left the Review in 1978 to join UCLA and was named editor
emeritus in 1980.
   Cousins undertook numerous diplomatic missions on behalf of Pope
John XXIII and Presidents Eisenhower, Kennedy and Johnson. His
negotiations with Soviet Premier Nikita Khrushchev eventually led
to a limited nuclear test ban treaty approved during Kennedy's
administration.
   Cousins, who died at UCLA Medical Center, taught at UCLA's
School of Medicine as an adjunct professor in the department of
psychiatry and biobehavioral sciences.
   ``Cousins was an inspirational leader in trying to understand
the grandeur of the human spirit and its promotion of health and
resistance to illness,'' said Dr. Sherman Mellinkoff, professor
emeritus and former dean of the UCLA School of Medicine.
   His studies found that a cancer patient's sense of well-being
could positively affect the function of the immune system and
production of cancer-fighting T-cells.
   ``He would talk to them and listen to them and help them
understand that a diagnosis of cancer doesn't have to be a death
sentence,'' West said.
   ``We've been educated to be timid and fearful,'' Cousins told
Los Angeles magazine in an interview last year. ``We don't
understand how beautifully robust the human body is.''
   A lifelong advocate for global peace, Cousins was awarded the
1990 Albert Schweitzer Prize for Humanitarianism. He was a close
friend of Schweitzer and wrote two books about the philosopher.
   ``If you had to put one word to him as an epitaph, it would have
to be, `Norman Cousins, humanitarian,''' West said. ``All people
were important to him.''
   Born in Union Hill, N.J., in 1915, Cousins briefly attended
Columbia University. He joined the New York Evening Post as an
education writer in 1934 and worked for the monthly magazine
Current History.
   Cousins was named honorary president of the United World
Federalists and co-chairman of the National Committee for a Sane
Nuclear Policy. He helped arrange medical treatment in the United
States for the ``Hiroshima Maidens,'' 25 young women victims of the
1945 atomic bomb blast.
   Among his 25 books were ``Modern Man is Obsolete,'' ``Talks with
Nehru,'' ``Head First: The Biology of Hope'' and ``The Celebration
of Life.''
   Cousins is survived by his wife of 51 years, Ellen, the couple's
four daughters and an adopted daughter.
   A private funeral was scheduled for Sunday at Cousins' Beverly
Hills home. A second funeral, also private, was set for early this
week in New Jersey, where Cousins will be buried in the family plot
in Union Hill, West said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901201-0022 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-01-90 2237EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-DailyNews     12-01 0331</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Daily News,0397</SECOND>
<HEAD>Publisher Warns Transit Chief To Seek Injunction in Case of Transit
Strike</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DANA KENNEDY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The publisher of the strikebound Daily News
urged the Metropolitan Transit Authority on Saturday to seek an
injunction if transit workers strike because of newspaper sales in
subways.
   Publisher James Hoge sent MTA chief Robert Kiley a letter
telling him it is illegal for transit workers to strike and he is
``required'' to seek an injunction if a strike is threatened.
   ``The MTA has a choice,'' Hoge wrote. ``It can uphold the rule
of law or it can capitulate to the rule of force. We think that the
choice is clear.''
   Hoge's letter resulted from furor over a temporary court order
issued Friday that allows hawkers to sell the Daily News in train
stations as long as they stay within 10 feet of newsstands or news
vending boxes that don't carry the News.
   Unions striking the newspaper said they would picket alongside
hawkers in train stations and transit union leaders said they would
honor such picket lines. A transit strike would be devastating to
commuters.
   John Cunningham, a spokesman for the MTA, would not comment
Saturday on Hoge's letter.
   The newspaper filed a lawsuit Friday challenging a decision by
the MTA to bar the hawkers from subways and commuter railroads,
which are run by the MTA, out of fear over a transit strike.
   The court order temporarily restoring the hawkers' right to sell
the tabloid was issued by U.S. District Judge Miriam G. Cedarbaum.
   Cedarbaum's temporary restraining order expires in 10 days. She
scheduled a hearing for Friday to hear arguments before deciding
whether to issue a preliminary injunction, which would stay in
effect until the case is decided.
   The newspaper has printed every day since the strike began but
distribution has been a major problem. The hawkers were taken on by
the News after many newsstands refused to carry the newspaper.
   During the strike, circulation has dropped from 1.06 million per
weekday to just over 500,000 daily, the News said.
   The News said it depended on hawkers as the ``only viable
means'' of distributing the newspaper in the transit system because
hardly any newsstands haved carried it since the strike by about
2,100 Daily News workers began Oct. 25.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901201-0023 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-01-90 2238EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Israel-Religion     12-01 0195</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel-Religion,0193</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tens of Thousands Protest Ultra-Orthodox Proposals</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TEL AVIV, Israel (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Tens of thousands of Israelis
demonstrated Saturday against limiting abortion, banning ``indecent
advertising,'' and other proposals that the government has
championed to gain Orthodox backing.
   The legislation is demanded by the ultra-Orthodox Agudat Israel
Party in exchange for backing the right-wing government of Prime
Minister Yitzhak Shamir.
   The proposals would also restrict public transportation on the
Jewish sabbath and restrict the sale of pork, which Judaism forbids
to be eaten.
   About 70 percent of Israel's 3.5 million Jews are non-observant.
   Shamir's Likud bloc has promised to push the bill through
Parliament. Agudat Israel's four seats would give Shamir control of
64 of the 120 Parliament seats.
   Organizers of the demonstration estimated that 60,000 people
marched through the streets of Tel Aviv, many carrying signs
denouncing alleged religious coercion.
   A leading Israeli rabbi, Avidor Hacohen, spoke out against the
legislation Saturday.
   ``What is happening today is a shame and blasphemy. It is
forbidden to leave Judaism and its values in the hands of
merchants,'' Hacohen said, in an apparent reference to Agudat
Israel.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901201-0024 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-01-90 2238EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Philippines-Exile     12-01 0213</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Philippines-Exile,0220</SECOND>
<HEAD>Court Upholds Right Of Aquino Foe To Bring Family Home</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MANILA, Philippines (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The family of a leading opponent of
President Corazon Aquino may return from self-imposed exile in
California, a court ruled in a decision announced Saturday.
   The Court of Appeals validated passports of the wife and
children of Eduardo ``Danding'' Cojuangco, a close ally of the late
President Ferdinand Marcos.
   Cojuangco, a first cousin of Mrs. Aquino, fled the Philippines
in 1986 when the so-called ``people power revolution'' toppled
Marcos' 20-year rule.
   Cojuangco, considered a leading presidential aspirant, slipped
back into the country in November 1989. His wife, Soledad, sons
Marcos and Carlos and their families, remained in the Los Angeles
area because their passports were revoked.
   The appellate court overruled a decision by the Aquino
government revoking the passports, saying the right of return was
guaranteed to any Filipino under the constitution.
   In a statement Saturday, Cojuangco expressed hope the decision
``will be the final step in a reunion with my family.''
   Cojuangco's supporters maintain that Mrs. Aquino refused to
allow her relatives to return because of a personal vendetta.
   Cojuangco's supporters have been organizing a political movement
to promote his candidacy for president in the 1992 elections. Mrs.
Aquino has ruled out a second term.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901201-0025 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-01-90 2240EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-GulfProtests     12-01 0223</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf Protests,0236</SECOND>
<HEAD>Thousands Protest Persian Gulf, Arrests Made At Westover Base</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   About 8,000 people marched Saturday through the
Boston Common to protest U.S. involvement in the Persian Gulf and
39 people were arrested at another demonstration outside a military
base in western Massachussetts.
   ``Hell no, we won't go, we won't die for Texaco,'' protesters
chanted as they marched in the downtown area. They carried signs
reading: ``Build homes, not bombs,'' and ``Yankees Come Home.''
   Some holiday shoppers and other passers-by cheered the
demonstrators.
   Police and organizers estimated the crowd at 8,000.
   The demonstrators included peace activist and nutrition guru
Dick Gregory, who has been fasting since Thanksgiving to protest
deployment of U.S. troops in the Middle East after Iraq's Aug. 2
invasion of neighboring Kuwait.
   ``Mr. Bush, you send your children,'' Gregory said.
   About 900 people gathered outside the Westover Air Force Base in
Chicopee, police said. Thirty nine demonstrators were arrested for
blocking the base's gates. Westover i a staging area for the
Persian Gulf deployment dubbed Operation Desert Shield.
   ``There is something people can do to let the government know
how we feel,'' said Don Phillips, a University of Massachusetts
student who was arrested.
   In Washington, about 250 people gathered in Lafayette Square
across from the White House to protest the U.S. buildup,
authorities said. No arrests were made.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901201-0026 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-01-90 2310EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Chess-Championship 2ndLd-Writethru a0593 12-01 0216</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Chess-Championship, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0593,0250</SECOND>
<HEAD>Kasparov Holds Advantage as 16th Game Adjourns</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 4 grafs for 5-8th pvs bgng `This allowed ...' to CORRECT
that checks were by Karpov, on Kasparov, sted the opposite</NOTE>
<DATELINE>LYON, France (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Garry Kasparov, playing white, held the
advantage Saturday as the 16th game in his struggle with Anatoly
Karpov for the World Chess Championship adjourned.
   The two Soviet grandmasters resume play Sunday, with each
holding 7.5 points after 15 completed matches in the marathon
competition.
   They have had three draws in the French portion of the
championship. They had 10 draws in the 12 games played at New York
between Oct. 8 and Nov. 7.
   Kasparov opened Saturday's match with a Scottish defense, a move
he normally does not favor but also used in the 14th match. After
an exchange of pawns, Karpov tried and failed to free up his
center.
   This allowed Kasparov to pressure column C, with his bishops and
majority of pawns on the king's wing giving him advantage.
   Karpov put Kasparov in check in the 12th move.
   Karpov was forced to sacrifice a pawn in the 16th move to free
his pieces, but in the event allowed Kasparov to develop a queen
attack.
   Karpov tried shoring his pawn defense, but was left in a weaker
position.
   The players made their last 17 moves in 25 minutes before
adjourning, with Karpov putting his opponent in check in the 38th
and 39th moves.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901201-0027 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-01-90 2344EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Honduras     12-01 0277</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Honduras,0290</SECOND>
<HEAD>Armed Forces Chief Resigns</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By FREDDY CUEVAS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TEGUCIGALPA, Honduras (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The country's armed forces chief
Gen. Arnulfo Cantarero Lopez resigned Saturday, apparently due to a
power struggle within the military.
   President Rafael Leonardo Callejas made a nationally broadcast
statement to deny radio reports the general had been arrested.
   The armed forces' official announcement cited unspecified
``overriding personal reasons'' for the resignation. But it
appeared to be linked to a long-running battle over promotions
within the military.
   Cantarero, 45, served 10 months of his three-year command in the
politically powerful post. He was previously head of the navy.
   The military's High Council, which includes 50 key military
officers, said it would propose successors for Cantarero. Infantry
Col. Jose de Jesus Banegas, chief of the armed forces joint
command, will temporarily fill the post.
   Some local radio stations reported Cantarero had been detained
at an air force base outside the capital. Such detentions have
occurred during some top-level armed forces shakeups in the past.
   But Callejas said Cantarero was at his home in Tegucigalpa,
``enjoying all of the rights and privileges conferred by the
constitution, the armed forces law and other legal rules.''
   The resignation appears to signal resurgence of a simmering
struggle between different classes of graduates from the military
academy. Younger officers have often backed efforts to change
leadership, which open opportunities for advancement.
   The disputes led to several changes in national leadership when
the military ruled Honduras from 1963 to 1981. The military remains
a powerful force in local politics.
   According to the Honduran constitution, the legislature will
name a replacement for Cantarero by choosing from three officers
submitted by the High Council.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901201-0028 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-01-90 2346EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-DayWithoutArt 2ndLd-Writethru a0606 12-01 0646</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Day Without Art, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0606,0784</SECOND>
<HEAD>Shrouded Art, Blank Walls And Closed Museums Mark Day Without Art</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS lead and SUBS 12th graf, `The San...' to UPDATE with San
Francisco lights dimmed. Pick up 13 graf pvs, `U.S. cable ...'</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY24</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CATHERINE CROCKER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The New York and San Francisco skylines dimmed
Saturday and museum visitors gazed silently at shrouded sculptures
in a coast-to-coast observance for the victims of AIDS in the art
world.
   At least 3,000 arts organizations in the United States,
including New York's Metropolitan Museum of Art and Washington's
Smithsonian Institution, participated in the second annual Day
Without Art.
   ``You take it for granted - art. It's all around and people
don't realize it,'' Michelle Liebowitz said, looking up at a
sculpture of the goddess Diana that was covered by a black cloth at
the National Academy of Design in New York.
   ``Now that you can't see it here, you take note of it,'' she
said.
   A posted notice told visitors to the academy that Anna Hyatt
Huntington's Diana sculpture was obscured ``as a gesture of
mourning for all those who have suffered from and fallen victim to
AIDS.''
   Day Without Art events were coordinated nationwide in observance
of the World Health Organization's third annual AIDS Awareness Day,
also known as World AIDS Day.
   Many galleries closed in observance of Day Without Art while
others withdrew art works from display. Some held memorial
exhibits. A few handed out leaflets or displayed lists of artists
and others who have died of acquired immune deficiency syndrome.
   At the San Francisco Museum of Art, photographs by Robert
Mapplethrope, who died of AIDS in 1989, went on display. An exhibit
of Mapplethorpe's erotic images launched national debate last year
over restrictions in federal art grants.
   The decorative floodlighting at the Empire State Building and
lights on the Chrysler Building and other major structures in New
York went out for 15 minutes. Marquee lights along Broadway's Great
White Way darkenened for one minute.
   ``To see the skyline, which has always been so important to New
Yorkers, to see it dim, is truly symbolic and truly powerful,''
said Patrick O'Connell, an organizer of the New York observance.
   ``Right now I'm filled with happiness but I also feel sorrow and
rage,'' he said.
   The San Francisco skyline also dimmed for 15 minutes Saturday
night, when the Golden Gate Bridge lights - except for the roadway
lights - were turned off. Lights on City Hall, the Coit Tower and
the tip of the Transamerica building also were dimmed.
   U.S. able TV networks and broadcasters in England, Canada and
Australia planned to interrupt programming with a 60-second
observance, including a blank screen and the sound of a ticking
clock.
   ``The Museum of Modern Art and other cultural institutions want
to use their power and prestige to try and remind people of
something they are not hearing often enough,'' said Philip
Yenawine, director of the museum's education department.
   ``That AIDS is a disease that we believe science can find a way
to cure and halt and that people struggling with the disease need
more care than they are getting,'' Yenawine said.
   Display cases at the Museum of Modern Art held white letters on
a black background spelling ``Remember.'' The Cooper-Hewitt Museum
displayed a dozen panels from the AIDS memorial quilt.
   At the Metropolitan Museum of Art, several great works were
removed, including a Rembrandt self-portrait, Renoir's ``Two Girls
at the Piano,'' and Matisse's ``Nasturtiums and Dance.'' Some
sculptures in the Asian art department were covered.
   In Washington, the Corcoran Gallery of Art darkened three
contemporary art galleries and planned to donate admission fees to
AIDS charities. The Smithsonian Institution's National Portrait
Gallery displayed a list of people in the arts who have died of
AIDS.
   In Los Angeles, the J. Paul Getty Museum gave visitors fliers
listing members of the arts community who have died of AIDS. The
museum planned to give profits from Saturday's sale of the book,
``The Indomitable Spirit: Photographers and Artists Respond to Time
of AIDS,'' to the American Foundation for AIDS Research.
   The Detroit Institute of Art displayed four benches by
Alabama-born artist Scott Burton, who died of AIDS in 1989. In
Atlanta, the High Museum of Art exhibited glass panels depicting
the AIDS virus and mirrors in which museum visitors saw themselves
reflected through the virus' image.
   At the University of Pennsylvania in Philadelphia, pop artist
Claes Oldenburg's statue ``Split Button'' was shrouded in black. At
the Art Institute of Chicago, Edward Hopper's ``Nighthawks'' was
removed for the weekend.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901201-0029 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-01-90 2349EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Soviets-Gulf     12-01 0174</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviets-Gulf,170</SECOND>
<HEAD>Soviet Official Says His Country Can't Fight Persian Gulf War</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Soviet Union is still suffering too much
from the war in Afghanistan to be able to send troops to a Persian
Gulf war, a top aide to Soviet President Mikhail Gorbachev said in
an interview published Sunday.
   ``It would be unjust and unwise to expect direct involvement in
a war,'' Georgi Shakhnazarov told The Washington Post. He referred
to his country's nine-year involvement in Afghanistan that left
nearly 15,000 Soviet soldiers dead. The Soviets withdrew in
February 1989.
   ``It's the same situation as when the United States just
finished the war in Vietnam,'' the 66-year-old foreign policy
adviser said in an interview in Moscow.
   Shakhnazarov said he was speaking personally, but the newspaper
noted that such senior officials rarely contradict policy when
giving interviews for publication.
   On Thursday, Foreign Minister Eduard A. Shevardnadze said in the
United Nations that ``everyone should know that we will not
hesitate to use force'' to protect Soviet citizens still in Iraq.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901201-0030 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-01-90 0019EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-BRF--Poland-Stocks     12-01 0182</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-BRF--Poland-Stocks,0181</SECOND>
<HEAD>Polish Investors Take Stock in New System</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WARSAW, Poland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Advertisements telling Poles to ``learn
the power of money'' greeted investors seeking shares in the first
state-run companies to go private after more than 40 years of
Communism.
   A Western-style campaign tried to educate potential buyers on
how the stock system works, where to purchase shares and what risks
to consider.
   Five companies were selected for the stock program as the
non-communist government that came to power last year dismantles
the communist system.
   The companies include the well-known Krosno glas works, the
Kielce construction company Exbud, the Lodz textile company
Prochnik, the Silesian cable factory and Tonsil, an audio equipment
company.
   Share prices ranged from about $5 to about $12. The minimum
purchase was five shares.
   About 7,000 companies, accounting for more than 80 percent of
the Polish economy, are to be transferred from state to private
ownership or liquidated.
   In two Warsaw banks, 1,500 applications were received by
mid-afternoon Friday, with the average purchase put at $1,050,
state television reported.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901201-0031 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-01-90 0020EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p PM-Bennett-GOP Bjt   12-01 0710</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Bennett-GOP, Bjt,800</SECOND>
<HEAD>Civil Rights Group Blasts Bennett Choice as Republican Chairman</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DONALD M. ROTHBERG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Political Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush's selection of William J.
Bennett to head the Republican Party is drawing fire from a civil
rights group citing the former Education secretary's opposition to
affirmative action.
   ``His department had a woeful record of enforcing the civil
rights laws when he was secretary of education,'' said Ralph G.
Neas, executive director of the Leadership Conference on Civil
Rights.
   Bush announced Friday that he would ask the Republican National
Committee to elect Bennett its chairman when it convenes in
January.
   He also announced he was nominating outgoing Florida Gov. Bob
Martinez to succeed Bennett in the position of director of the
Office of National Drug Control Policy, the nation's so-called drug
czar.
   Bush described Bennett as ``a man of proven leadership,
intellect and commitment whose drive and determination will be a
tremendous asset to the Republican Party organizations and
operations.''
   Neas, however, was sharply critical of Bennett's opposition to
affirmative action as education secretary from 1985 until the final
year of Ronald Reagan's presidency. He linked Bennett to Sen. Jesse
Helms, R-N.C., and Edwin Meese III, who served as attorney general
in the Reagan administration.
   Bennett campaigned this fall for Helms in his race for
re-election to the Senate from North Carolina. In a close contest
with Democrat Harvey Gantt, who is black, Helms appeared to pull
away after running a commercial that said the Democrat supported
racial quotas that would give jobs to blacks in preference to
better qualified whites.
   ``Mr. Bennett is from the Ed Meese-Jesse Helms wing of the
Republican Party,'' Neas declared.
   Bennett would succeed Lee Atwater who has been sidelined by a
brain tumor.
   Bush said Atwater would assume the role of general chairman, a
post that doesn't currently exist.
   ``I'm delighted that Lee Atwater will continue to provide valued
counsel as general chairman of the party,'' said the president.
``He has been, as you all know, a close adviser and political
strategist - chief political strategist - and a good friend.''
   Atwater was manager of Bush's 1988 presidential campaign and is
regarded as a master political tactician.
   Bennett has no hands-on political experience but is viewed as an
articulate spokesman for conservative views. Friday was Bennett's
last day as head of the government office of drug policy, a post he
held for the first 19 months of the Bush administration.
   Republican operatives generally praised the choice of Bennett,
particularly his ability to appeal to social and ideological
conservatives.
   ``If there's anything the Republican Party has lacked over the
past year, it's been a voice,'' said Michele Davis, executive
director of the GOP Governors' Association. ``The base needs to be
talked to in pretty plain terms and if there's anything that's a
specialty of Bill Bennett, it's plain speaking.''
   The fact that the 47-year-old Bennett was a Democrat until four
years ago was viewed by some Republicans as a plus.
   ``Bill can reinforce the conservative base of the party,'' said
Edward J. Rollins, co-chairman of the House Republican Campaign
committee. ``He's a convert to Republicanism, so I think it's a
great statement to make to Reagan Democrats.''
   Republicans also saw Bennett as a spokesman able to hold his own
in debates with Democratic Party Chairman Ronald H. Brown.
   Brown said he welcomed the appointment of Bennett.
   ``If Bennett accomplishes as much for the Republican Party as he
achieved at the Education Department and in ridding us of drugs and
violence, Americans will have to begin worrying about the future of
the two-party system,'' the Democrat said.
   Bush said that in replacing Bennett, he was giving Martinez ``a
battlefield promotion for a leader who has earned his stripes on
the front lines of the drug war.''
   In his four years as governor, Martinez stressed tough
penalties, law enforcement and prison construction over drug
treatment and prevention. But drug crimes escalated significantly
during his tenure.
   ``He stiffened the Florida code and then added the prison space
to enforce it.... As a governor who signed more than 130 death
warrants, he understands tough choices,'' Bush said.
   But Martinez' nomination brought criticism from some on Capitol
Hill that he was not well qualified. Sen. Joseph Biden, D-Del.,
chairman of the Senate Judiciary Committee, said Martinez ``lacks
the background and record'' for the post.
   As for Bennett's lack of experience as a political technician,
Roger Stone, a Republican consultant, said the new party chairman
``is not Lee Atwater.''
   ``He can't be Lee Atwater,'' Stone said. ``But if Ron Brown
wants to debate affirmative action, I'd have a lot of confidence
sending Bill Bennett into that debate.''
   As an academic, Bennett wrote extensively in opposition to
affirmative action.
   ``Bennett is an intellectual who believes that ideas move the
world,'' said GOP consultant David Keene. ``A lot of politicians
make the opposite mistake and assume that ideas don't have any
consequence when in fact they do.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901201-0032 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-01-90 0021EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-Keating-Senators Bjt   12-01 0475</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Keating-Senators, Bjt,530</SECOND>
<HEAD>Regulator Tells of Cranston Phone Calls on Keating's Behalf</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By WILLIAM M. WELCH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A former regulator says Sen. Alan Cranston
waged a telephone campaign to aid Charles H. Keating's savings and
loan association while Keating was funneling large sums of money to
groups formed by the lawmaker.
   ``It was unusual for a senator to place so many telephone calls
to me with regard to a single savings and loan institution,'' M.
Danny Wall said in a deposition released Friday by the Senate
Ethics Committee.
   ``Had I known at the time that the communications to me from
Senator Cranston were contemporaneous with these substantial
contributions from Mr. Keating, I would have been very disturbed,''
he said.
   Wall, former head of the Federal Home Loan Bank Board, will
undergo public questioning next week at hearings on the ``Keating
Five'' senators.
   The five are accused of improperly intervening in the regulatory
process on behalf of Keating and his Lincoln Savings and Loan
Association of Irvine, Calif., while receiving hefty political
contributions from him.
   Lincoln's $2 billion collapse has been perhaps the most
spectacular of the savings and loan crisis and Keating is now under
indictment in California.
   Besides Cranston, a California Democrat, the five senators are
Republican John McCain of Arizona and Democrats Dennis DeConcini of
Arizona, Donald Riegle of Michigan and John Glenn of Ohio.
   All five lawmakers have denied any impropriety and said
contributions from Keating were unrelated to efforts on behalf of
Lincoln.
   Cranston received the bulk of the $1.3 million Keating and his
associates gave to the campaigns and causes of the lawmakers.
Keating gave $850,000 to three voter-registration groups associated
with Cranston and $39,000 to the California senator's campaigns.
   Another regulator, Michael Patriarca, testified Friday that an
April 9, 1987, meeting in DeConcini's office with the five senators
made him and several of his colleagues feel as if they had been
called on the carpet over their examination of Lincoln Savings.
   He said the mood changed when they told the senators there was
evidence of criminal violations and that they were recommending a
Justice Department investigation.
   ``At first I think it was hostile,'' the San Francisco-based
thrift examiner said.
   ``I felt we were being dressed down by the senators for
inappropriate behavior and the conduct and length'' of the
examination, he said.
   Supporting testimony from his former boss, Edwin J. Gray,
Patriarca said Deconcini was the leader of the senators' efforts to
help Keating.
   He said DeConcini offered a deal - that Lincoln would make more
home mortgage loans if regulators would back off a regulation
limiting its ability to make speculative investments.
   Patriarca said the senators seemed to have made up their minds
that the regulators were dragging their feet and harassing Lincoln.
   Patriarca said it was wrong for a senator to attempt to
``influence, to change the outcome'' of an examination.
   ``My personal view is Senator DeConcini did that,'' he said.
``It's not clear to me that any of the others did.''
   But Patriarca also said he would fault the senators generally,
because they ``appeared to have made up their minds in advance''
that Keating was right and the regulators were wrong in finding
serious problems at Lincoln.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901201-0033 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-01-90 0023EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-BRF--JapaneseTraveler     12-01 0162</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-BRF--Japanese Travelers,0157</SECOND>
<HEAD>Japan's Overseas Travelers Exceed 10 Million</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The number of Japanese traveling abroad this year
exceeded 10 million, more than double the number five years ago,
the Transportation Ministry said.
   It was also a milestone for the government, which set 10 million
travelers as the 1990 goal under a three-year program encouraging
travel abroad to help offset the country's huge trade surplus that
has become politically sensitive.
   Tsuneaki Iki, executive vice president of the ministry's Japan
National Tourist Organization, said there should be close to 11
million Japanese international travelers by the end of the year.
   The travelers are expected to spend about $32 billion. Japan's
trade surplus worldwide totaled $77 billion last year.
   The United States is the most popular destination for the
Japanese, with 3.3 million Japanese visitors expected this year,
Iki said.
   Other hot spots include South Korea, Hong Kong, Taiwan,
Singapore and France.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901201-0034 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-01-90 0025EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-BRF--Yugoslavia-CIA     12-01 0156</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-BRF--Yugoslavia-CIA,0145</SECOND>
<HEAD>Yugoslav Foreign Minister Rejects CIA Predicition of Civil War</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ROME (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Yugoslavia's foreign minister says reports of his
country's impending demise are unfounded.
   Budimir Loncar said Friday he's confident of peaceful
resolutions to the nation's ethnic and politicial problems, despite
published reports the CIA predicted Yugoslavia could be torn apart
within 18 months or fall into civil war.
   Yugoslavia, a federation of six republics founded at the end of
World War II, has seen separatist sentiments and ethnic violence
increase dramatically with the collapse of Communism in Eastern
Europe.
   ``The CIA is one of the biggest information services, but that
doesn't mean it's always the most efficient,'' Loncar said.
   Loncar was in Rome for a meeting of foreign ministers of the
Pentagonal organization for cooperation in Central Europe.
Pentagonal members include Italy, Hungary, Austria, Czechoslovakia
and Yugoslavia.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901201-0035 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-01-90 0037EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-BRF--HongKong-Smoking     12-01 0153</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-BRF--Hong Kong-Smoking,0153</SECOND>
<HEAD>Government Ban On Smoking Ads Begins In Hong Kong</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HONG KONG (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Marlboro man has corralled his last horse
and Salem's ``springtime'' has ended on Hong Kong TV following a
cigarette ad ban that began today in this British colony.
   The ban is part of a growing campaign in Asia against tobacco
companies, which have been accused of targeting Asia's women and
children.
   In a related development, Hong Kong's legislature has urged the
government to ban children under the age of 15 from smoking in
restaurants.
   ``Smoking parties'' where a group of young people lounge around
a table and chain-smoke cigarettes is a popular pastime in Hong
Kong.
   Hong Kong is also readying legislation to ban smoking in
ferries, buses, taxis, government buildings, cinemas and theaters.
   In other Asian countries, Indonesia has banned smoking in most
schools and Singapore has moved to limit advertising.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
</Collection>
