<Collection>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900909-0001 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-09-90 0039EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>d a AM-BRF--CovenantHouse     09-09 0175</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Covenant House,0179</SECOND>
<HEAD>New Covenant House Leader Says Shelter Deserves Second Chance</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The new leader of the troubled Covenant House
says the youth shelter deserves a second chance.
   ``The need is still there,'' Sister Mary Rose McGeady said in
Sunday's editions of the Daily News.
   She told the newspaper that it will be difficult to persuade
donors to give money to the charity that has been rocked by sexual
and financial scandals, resulting in a loss of $12 million in
donations this year.
   Despite the scandals, kids keep showing up a the shelter. ``We
are still seeing between 30 to 60 new kids every day,'' she said.
   To help restore confidence in the charity, she plans to invite
potential donors to Covenant House. She also has sent donors a copy
of an internal report about the improprieties.
   The Rev. Bruce Ritter, the charity's founder and main
fund-raiser, resigned earlier this year amid allegations of
financial misdeeds and that he had sexual relationships with
several male youths staying at the shelter.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900909-0002 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-09-90 0008EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Peru-Violence     09-09 0242</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Peru-Violence,0251</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rebels Attack House of Vice President's Mother, Kill Policeman</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LIMA, Peru (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Maoist Shining Path guerrillas attacked the
house of the mother of Vice President Maximo San Roman, killing a
policeman, authorities said Saturday.
   Three other policemen were shot and wounded in the attack Friday
night in the Andean city of Cuzco, 350 miles southeast of the
capital. The vice president's mother, Rebecca de San Roman, was
unhurt.
   Police said about six rebels tossed sticks of dynamite at the
doorway of the house and opened fire on the stunned policemen.
   San Roman, one of Peru's two vice presidents, took office July
28 along with President Alberto Fujimori.
   In other violence, two rebels were killed in a shootout between
an army patrol and a guerrilla column south of Huancayo, a mountain
city 120 miles east of Lima.
   Police said an unknown number of rebels were wounded in the
firefight, in the Pasos district 15 miles south of Huancayo. No
soldiers were wounded, police said.
   The 30-minute gun battle began when the army patrol came upon
about 15 rebels trying to blow up an electrical substation, police
said.
   In Ayacucho, a rebel stronghold 230 miles southeast of Lima, two
rebels shot and killed a maid on Friday.
   A note found on the maid's body said ``This is how squeelers
die.''
   Almost 20,000 Peruvians have died in political violence in the
10 years since the Shining Path first took up arms.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900909-0003 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-09-90 0010EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p AM-NortonTaxes     09-09 0255</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Norton Taxes,260</SECOND>
<HEAD>Former Federal EOC Chief Discloses Local Income Tax Irregularity</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Eleanor Holmes Norton, a former Carter
administration official and the front-runner in a campaign for the
District of Columbia's non-voting congressional seat, disclosed
Saturday that she and her husband failed to file local income tax
returns for eight years.
   The Georgetown University law professor said in a written
statement that she learned Saturday ``for the first time'' that the
1982 through 1989 tax returns she signed were never mailed by her
husband.
   She blamed the failure on ``procrastination'' and a dispute with
the city over the amount of the tax.
   ``I love and trust him and realize that his lack candor resulted
from understandable reluctance to admit to his procrastination,''
she said in a statement. ``The situation is all the more tragic
because our income has at all times been more than ample to pay any
taxes due.''
   Norton's husband, Edward Norton, is a lawyer and former chairman
of the D.C. board of Elections and Ethics.
   The candidate herself was chief of the U.S. Employment
Opportunity Commission under President Carter.
   The disclosure about the unfiled returns follows Norton's
admission Friday that she owes about $25,000 in city taxes.
   She said she and her husband would pay the city $25,381.90 they
owed as of Jan. 18 1990. The sum stems from a protracted dispute
between the Nortons and the city over $10,755 in income taxes the
couple failed to pay in 1982. The additional amount comes from
interest and penalties.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900909-0004 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-09-90 0045EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-MissAmerica-Parks     09-09 0255</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Miss America-Parks,0263</SECOND>
<HEAD>Parks Returns to Miss America Pageant, Croons ``There She Is''</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Miss America</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ATLANTIC CITY, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Bert Parks returned to the Miss
America Pageant Saturday night after a 10-year break to serenade 29
former Miss Americas with a lip-synched ``There She Is.''
   But Parks, 75, neglected to mention at least a dozen of the
former winners he was supposed to introduce. Mouthing his trademark
song over a recording of his own voice, he appeared to get out of
synch.
   He returned to the stage at the end to congratulate the winner,
Miss Illinois Marjorie Judith Vincent.
   Parks, who was fired in 1980 as pageant emcee by pageant
officials who felt he was too old, received a standing ovation of
15 seconds when he first walked onstage.
   Former pageant director Al Marks, who died last year, fired
Parks before the 1980 pageant, saying he was too old at age 65 to
continue performing.
   Parks went on to emcee other pageants ranging from a tugboat
competition to contests judging small dogs. His firing generated
nationwide sympathy and a letter-writing campaign organized by
Johnny Carson.
   Parks' return to the Miss America stage Saturday night began
with an on-stage invitation from actor Gary Collins, who is the
pageant's co-host along with Miss America 1971 Phyllis George.
   ``I thought you would never ask,'' Parks boomed in an offstage
voice as he rose from a front row seat in the audience and bounced
onto the stage to applause.
   ``I never thought you'd answer,'' said Collins.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900909-0005 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-09-90 0118EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-BRF--RocketBlast 1stLd-Writethru a0636 09-09 0265</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Rocket Blast, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0636,0268</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rocket Blaze Victim Identified as Safety Worker Crushed by Crane</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 4 grafs to UPDATE with details of accident,
victim's job description, cause unknown, fresh quote. EDITS. Picks
up 4th graf pvs, `A section...' Rainney in 2nd graf is cq.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>EDWARDS AIR FORCE BASE, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The man killed when part
of Titan 4 rocket erupted in flames after falling from a 400-foot
crane was a safety worker crushed under the collapsing crane,
officials said Saturday.
   Alan M. Quimby, 27, of Lancaster was one of the workers
overseeing the movement of the solid fuel rocket motor Friday when
the crane fell 70 feet and slid another 70 down a concrete-covered
hill, said Rainney Adams, spokesman for the Air Force Astronautics
Laboratory.
   Quimby was crushed by falling boxes of sand and gravel used as
counter weights to balance the crane, Adams said. Nine other people
were injured. The cause of the collapse was unknown.
   ``It could be a very long-term investigation. We'd be remiss in
speculating until we found the cause,'' Adams said.
   A section of the 112-foot rocket booster ignited on impact when
it fell while being maneuvered toward an outdoor test stand, Maj.
Dick Cole said.
   Titan 4s, built by Martin Marietta Corp., are considered the Air
Force's primary booster for launching heavy payloads, particularly
intelligence satellites. It is the nation's most powerful unmanned
rocket.
   The fire sent a cloud billowing over the base, but toxic
hydrogen chloride was released in amounts too small to endanger
anyone in the sparsely populated area, officials said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900909-0006 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-09-90 0145EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Plane-FallingPart     09-09 0201</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Plane-Falling Part,0209</SECOND>
<HEAD>Plane Lands Safely in Guam After Part of Engine Covering Falls Off</HEAD>
<DATELINE>AGANA, Guam (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Continental Air Micronesia DC-10 raining
debris after liftoff turned back and landed safely Saturday.
   Flight 1967, bound for Saipan and Tokyo, was carrying 133
passengers when a witness called the airline to report pieces
falling from the jetliner, Contintal Air Micronesia spokesman Guy
Schroeder said.
   ``We discovered a piece missing from the left-hand No. 2 engine
fan cawl _ it's a curved piece of metal that covers the rear
engine,'' Schroeder said. ``It is substantially gone.''
   Schroeder said the missing piece measured about 4 feet by 8
feet. The airline learned of the problem about six minutes after
takeoff and landed safely less than an hour later.
   The engine continued to function without the cover and there
were no reports of injuries from falling debris.
   Ed Guzman said he recovered a 3-foot-by-1-foot piece of metal
and took it to the Continental desk at Guam International Airport.
   ``We put the piece on the counter and said, `This came off one
of your planes,' and the lady didn't believe me,'' Guzman said.
   Schroeder said the cause of the problem was under investigation.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900909-0007 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-09-90 0149EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-MissAmerica 5thLd-Writethru a0662 09-09 0978</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Miss America, 5th Ld-Writethru, a0662,1008</SECOND>
<HEAD>Miss Illinois Crowned Miss America 1991</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS grafs 15-16 with history of black pageant winners. Minor
editing in 17th graf. Picks up 17th graf pvs, `The other...</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By HENRY STERN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ATLANTIC CITY, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Miss Illinois Marjorie Judith
Vincent, a pianist of Haitian descent who wants to practice
international law, was crowned Miss America 1991 early Sunday.
   Miss Vincent broke into tears and smiled brightly as she given a
suprise serenade of ``There She Is'' by Bert Parks, who returned to
the pageant 10 years after he was fired as emcee.
   ``I couldn't believe it,'' she said afterward. ``I was just so
happy that I was in the Top 10. I still don't believe it.''
   Asked what she would do next, Miss Vincent said, ``I have no
idea. I just want to see my family.''
   First runner-up was Miss South Carolina Mary Waddell Gainey, 24,
of Hartsville.
   Following her as second runner-up was Miss Tennessee Dana Brown,
25, of Memphis. Miss Texas Suzanne Lawrence, 21, of Humble was
third runner-up. And Miss Louisiana Linnea Marie Fayard, 22, of
Shreveport took fifth place.
   Earlier in the pageant, the 75-year-old Parks serenaded 29
former Miss Americas with a lip-synched ``There She Is'' that
wasn't quite synched. A standing ovation greeted Parks, who
neglected to mention at least a dozen of the former beauty queens
he was to introduce.
   Miss Vincent, 25, of Oak Park, is a third-year law student at
Duke University who graduated from DePaul University in 1988 with a
degree in music.
   She played Chopin's ``Fantasy Impromptu _ Opus 66'' with
dramatic flourishes and a light touch during the talent portion of
the competition.
   The 5-foot-6, 110-pound Miss Vincent performed in a rust satin
embroidered coat detailed in gold cracked ice over a black sheath
petticoat dress.
   She wore a turquoise chiffon silk gown that was beaded with
silver, white and varying shades of turquoise bugle beads, sequins
and rhinestones. The gown also featured a sweetheart neckline with
a keyhole opening in the back.
   Miss Vincent, who came to the United States from Haiti when she
was 3 years old, has said she wants to study international law and
help in the economic development of the impoverished Caribbean
nation. She speaks French and creole.
   Miss Vincent comes from a modest family. Her father is a doorman
and a check cashier and her mother is a seamstress.
   She said in a pre-pageant interview that she wants to speak out
on the plight of battered women.
   Miss Vincent was the only black contestant among the 50 this
year. Last year's Miss America, Debbye Turner, also is black. Miss
Vincent is the fourth black woman to hold the title.
   Vanessa Williams, then Miss New York, was the first in 1983. She
lost the crown because nude photos taken years earlier appeared in
Penthouse magazine. She was replaced by first runner-up Suzette
Charles, Miss New Jersey, who also is black.
   Among her interests, Miss Vincent lists listening to chamber
music and jazz, collecting mugs, cooking, reading mysteries and
romance novels.
   The other semifinalists were Miss Colorado Karrie Mitchell, 24;
Miss Iowa Kerri Lynne Rosenberg, 26; Miss Oklahoma Cynthia Lynne
White, 24; Miss Pennsylvania Marla Wynne, 23, and Miss Virginia
Shannon Noelle DePuy, 19.
   They scored the highest after three nights of preliminary
competitions in swimsuit, talent, evening gown and interviews with
judges.
   Miss South Carolina, like Miss Turner, played the marimba. Miss
Pennsylvania performed a ventriloquist act with a green cockatoo
puppet named Oscar.
   Several of the contestants overcame personal tragedies and
disabilities to make it to the Boardwalk.
   Miss Texas recovered from cervical cancer last year and also
controversy this year surrounding the head of the state pageant,
who has faced allegations he made sexist remarks to contestants.
Miss Pensylvania has lost 11 family members to cancer.
   Miss South Carolina went through six operations to correct four
birth defects, including a collapsible urethra and a lack of a hip
socket.
   The pageant axed Parks in 1980 as master of ceremonies, saying
he was too old for the program at age 65.
   Gary Collins and Miss America 1971 Phyllis George served as
co-hosts of the show.
   Despite the nostalgic appeal of Parks and the former Miss
Americas, the pageant has continued taking small steps away from
its image as a beauty contest.
   Pageant director Leonard Horn banned pre-pageant week photos of
contestants in swimsuits, but the swimsuit competition remains in
the contest because the ratings-conscious pageant believes viewers
would rebel if it were eliminated.
   For a second straight year, contestants selected platforms they
would like to emphasize during their reign. Most chose safe issues
such as illiteracy, education and elderly care.
   Miss Turner, 24, of Mexico, Mo., plans to return to the
University of Missouri-Columbia School of Veterinary Medicine where
she is six months short of her degree.
   The pageant generates more than $5 million in scholarship money
for the estimated 80,000 women between the ages of 18 and 26 who
compete at the local, state and national level.
   The new Miss America receives a $35,000 scholarship and makes
appearances throughout the year that Miss Turner guesses netted her
more than $200,000.
   The first runner-up receives $20,000; the second runner-up
$14,000; the third runner-up $11,000; and the fourth runner-up
$8,000. The other five semifinalists receive $6,000 and the other
40 contestants get $2,500 apiece.
   In determining the winner, interviews conducted during the week
count for 30 percent; the Saturday evening talent competition
counts for 40 percent; and the Saturday night swimsuit and evening
gown competitions were each 15 percent.
   Chosen for the celebrity panel were actresses Delta Burke,
Shirley Jones, Nell Carter and Cynthia Sikes; talk show host Larry
King; actor John Forsythe; and author Sidney Sheldon.
   Ms. Burke was Miss Florida 1974 and Ms. Sikes was Miss Kansas
1972.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900909-0008 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-09-90 0241EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-GulfRdp 6hLd-Writethru a0642 09-09 1125</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf Rdp, 6h Ld-Writethru, a0642,1158</SECOND>
<HEAD>Saddam Says Iraq `Loves Peace;' More Americans Arrive in Jordan</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 2 grafs to UPDATE with plane arriving in
Frankfurt; Pickup 4th, `Saddam in...'; SUBS 23-25 pvs, `A
U.S....would arrive' to conform; Pickup 26th, `Future charter...'</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos DOD1, DOD2, DHA1, NY23, NY28</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LAURA KING</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Iraq's Saddam Hussein on Saturday urged Presidents Bush and
Gorbachev on the eve of their summit to get out of the Persian Gulf
crisis and let the Arab world settle the matter.
   A U.S.-chartered flight carrying about 300 Americans from Kuwait
and Iraq meanwhile, landed in Frankfurt, West Germany early Sunday
and, after refueling, was to continue on to Charleston, S.C. The
plane arrived from Amman, Jordan.
   Saddam, in a statement read by an announcer on Iraqi television
and billed as an open message to the U.S. and Soviet leaders, told
them: ``I am not saying to either of you ... what your decision
should be.''
   But he said Bush and Mikhail S. Gorbachev should bear in mind
that ``Iraq's army did not invade either of your countries.''
   Saddam, whose Aug. 2 takeover of Kuwait set off the chain of
events leading to the summit in Helsinki, Finland, described Iraq
as a peace-loving nation and warned of dangers of the huge U.S.-led
buildup of forces in the gulf region.
   ``God and history are witness ... that the foreign intervention
is complicating matters and will not provide a settlement,'' he
said.
   In Helsinki, Bush and Gorbachev expressed hopes for a settlement
to the Persian Gulf crisis, now in its sixth week.
   Bush told reporters on arrival he hoped the summit would
``strengthen our common approach to this unjustifiable act of
aggression.''
   The Soviet president, arriving later, cited the ``acute crisis''
in the gulf. ``I hope this meeting will be successful,'' he said.
   Bush's National Security Adviser Brent Scowcroft suggested that
the prospect of U.S.-Soviet unity on the Persian Gulf has Saddam on
the run.
   ``We hope it causes him to lose some sleep,'' Scowcroft told
reporters after a Saturday evening working dinner in Bush's hotel
suite.
   ``We've put together a strategy that has a good chance of
success without the use of military force,'' Scowcroft said,
referring to the trade embargo against Iraq.
   Asked whether Saddam was backing off, Scowcroft said, ``I think
he's maneuvering at present ... looking for a way out of his
dilemma.''
   Iraq, meanwhile, sought to solidify its new rapprochement with
Iran in an effort to get around U.N. economic sanctions.
   Iraqi Foreign Minister Tariq Aziz is due in Tehran on Sunday for
the first high-level visit in a decade. Tehran's Jomhuri Islami
newspaper said in an editorial that Aziz would return to Iraq
``with his hands full'' if Iraq continues its conciliatory policy
toward Iran.
   This policy has included Iraq's withdrawal of troops from
Iranian territory, its exchange of war prisoners, and its dropping
of a long-standing demand for full control of a strategic waterway.
   In Kuwait, two more embassies bowed to the pressure brought to
bear by the Iraqi occupiers. Sweden and Norway evacuated their
diplomatic staffs but insisted their missions technically remained
open.
   The Iraqis, who ordered embassies in the conquered emirate to
close two weeks ago, have been backing up that demand with a cutoff
of food, water, power and telephone service to the missions.
   About 20 embassies, including the U.S. mission, remain open with
skeleton staffs to symbolize their refusal to accept Iraq's
annexation of Kuwait, and to try to provide some protection for
their citizens trapped by the invasion.
   About 2,200 Americans remain in Iraq and Kuwait, U.S. officials
estimate, and some men among them have been placed at important
installations to deter possible Western attacks.
   Women and children are being allowed to leave.
   A U.S.-chartered Iraqi Airways flight from Kuwait to Amman on
Friday carried 165 Americans, most of them women and children, and
a few other foreigners. A second flight, carrying 130 Americans,
left Kuwait on Saturday, with a stopover in Baghdad, U.S. Embassy
sources in Amman said.
   The entire group was flown to Frankfurt early Sunday aboard a
Northwest Airlines plane and after a brief stopover was to fly on
to Charleston, S.C.
   Future charter flights were unlikely to be routed through the
Jordanian capital. Iraq said Saturday that charters would no longer
fly to Amman, although they could travel to other points.
   That appeared to be acceptable to U.S. officials. A State
Department spokesman said on condition of anonymity a
U.S.-chartered flight would leave Baghdad on Sunday for London.
   Friday's flight was the first U.S.-chartered airlift out of
Kuwait. Other departing Americans have had to make their way out in
desert convoys.
   The Norwegian and Swedish diplomats who left their embassies in
Kuwait on Saturday were traveling overland to Baghdad, where an
uncertain fate awaited them. It was not clear whether the Iraqi
government would let them leave.
   Male diplomats and dependents who left the U.S. Embassy in
Kuwait have been prevented from leaving.
   In Cairo, Egyptian President Hosni Mubarak met with Secretary of
State James A. Baker III and urged the United States and Soviet
Union to coordinate their actions in the gulf crisis.
   ``I hope that Gorbachev and Bush have one line for dealing with
this problem,'' said the normally circumspect Mubarak, ``because it
will be a hell of a problem in this area if there are differences.''
   Baker said Washington and Cairo agree that the crisis cannot be
solved without total Iraqi withdrawal from Kuwait and restoration
of the Kuwaiti government deposed in the invasion.
   About 100,000 U.S. troops are dug into the Saudi desert and
aboard ships in the gulf region, facing an estimated 260,000 Iraqi
soldiers in and around Kuwait.
   Mubarak indicated more Egyptian troops would be deployed in the
gulf region but gave no details.
   In other developments:
   _ A Columbus, Ga., woman identified her son as the American
wounded by Iraqi troops while trying to avoid capture in Kuwait.
The State Department had refused to identify the American shot
Thursday. Mrs. Cullen Hoffman, who would not give her first name,
identified the American as her son, 33-year-old Miles Hoffman, a
financial analyst and investor for the Kuwaiti government. She said
she did not know her son's condition.
   _ One pilot was hospitalized and a second escaped unhurt when a
U.S. army helicopter crashed during a night training mission, U.S.
military spokesmen said Saturday. It was the second such crash in
two days.
   _ In London, Britain's Department of Trade and Industry
announced it will allow the export of medicine to Iraq and Kuwait.
A department spokesman said such exports were permitted on
humanitarian grounds under the U.N. Security Council resolution
imposing a trade embargo on Iraq and Kuwait.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900909-0009 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-09-90 0626EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i BC-SummitRdp 4thLd-Writethru a0669 09-09 0922</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Summit Rdp, 4th Ld-Writethru, a0669,850</SECOND>
<NOTE>Eds: Leads with 6 grafs with Gorbachev comment after first
meeting, picks up 3rd graf pvs, 'When Gorbachev</NOTE>
<HEAD>Saddam Tops Summit Agenda for Bush and Gorbachev</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TOM RAUM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HELSINKI, Finland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush and Soviet President
Mikhail Gorbachev held their hastily scheduled summit today,
searching for ways to forge an even closer alliance in the
international effort to isolate Iraq's Saddam Hussein.
   At a break midway through the scheduled five hours of talks,
Gorbachev told reporters, ``It was a good conversation.''
   But the Soviet leader refused to divulge details, saying they
would answer questions later at a joint news conference wrapping up
the one-day summit.
   Bush, too, waved off questions as they posed for photos with
Finnish President Mauno Koivisto and their wives.
   ``You heard what the man said,'' said Bush, before heading off
to lunch with their host and his wife.
   Bush arrived first for the talks at Finland's Presidential
Palace, arranged just eight days ago against the backdrop of the
gulf crisis. It was the third Bush-Gorbachev summit in the past
nine months.
   When Gorbachev stepped into the palace's yellow salon, Bush
greeted him with a handshake and said, ``How are you, sir? I look
forward to the meeting.''
   Gorbachev gave Bush a large, framed cartoon depicting the two
leaders as champion boxers, with a fallen figure representing the
Cold War at their feet. The referee's head was a globe. The Russian
caption read, ``Knockout punch!''
   Bush laughed and said, ``That's wonderful.''
   A reporter asked the Soviet leader in Russian if he was
optimistic. ``Yes, and tomorrow, too,'' replied Gorbachev.
   The two leaders briefly stepped out onto a balcony behind a
bulletproof shield, drawing applause from a crowd of 300 people
gathered in Market Square in front of the palace.
   As a light rain fall on the misty morning, a woman in the crowd
sang ``We Shall Overcome'' in English.
   ``Much is at stake'' at Sunday's hastily arranged summit, Bush
said before his third meeting as president with the Soviet leader.
   Iraq's five-week occupation of Kuwait and its treatment of
foreign hostages dominated the agenda as the two leaders prepared
for five hours of face-to-face meetings, a lunch and a joint news
conference.
   And, while neither side gave any indication that a major new
initiative would emerge, both leaders seemed ready to renew
pressure on Saddam to withdraw from Kuwait.
   White House officials hinted late Saturday that the two leaders
may decide to issue a joint statement on the Persian Gulf crisis.
   Several other subjects are likely to be discussed, including a
possible swap of U.S. oil-delivery technology for more Soviet oil
and a more sympathetic U.S. ear for Western economic aid for Moscow.
   In Saudi Arabia, a diplomatic source said Gorbachev came to
Helsinki prepared to offer the Soviet maritime fleet to the United
States to transport equipment to the Gulf and to withdraw Soviet
advisers from Iraq.
   The month-old U.S. military deployment has been handicapped by
the lack of sealift for materiel. And while the Bush administration
would like to see the Soviet advisers pulled out, it has been
low-key on the issue.
   Both leaders were upbeat about the session, which puts the two
superpowers on the same side of a major international issue for the
first time since World War II.
   ``We'll be speaking, not to some adversary, but to the leader of
a country with whom I think we're going to have increasingly
productive relations,'' Bush said on Saturday.
   Gorbachev, arriving in the Finnish capital Saturday evening,
said it was necessary ``to discuss the acute crisis in the Persian
Gulf and a number of other issues.''
   For Gorbachev, joining the United States' condemnation of Iraq's
Aug. 2 invasion of Kuwait and supporting the full naval blockade
sanction by the United Nations is a sensitive matter.
   Moscow has long been Baghdad's principal arms supplier and has
enjoyed a special relationship with the Iraqi government. Gorbachev
must also be careful not to offend the already restive Moslem
population in Central Asia.
   En route to the summit, Bush said he did not plan to ask
Gorbachev to contribute ground forces to the U.S.-led military
buildup along Iraq's border with Saudi Arabia _ even though
high-ranking U.S. officials have said such assistance would be
helpful.
   Both leaders arrived under overcast skies and received matching
red-carpet greetings from Finnish President Mauno Koivisto, who had
lunch with Bush and dinner with Gorbachev.
   It was a working summit for both leaders and they did little in
the way of recreation or sightseeing. Security was extremely tight,
as always, and Soviet, American and Finnish flags were flown
together. Crowds lined the streets as the U.S. and Soviet
motorcades passed by and people forked over $20 for T-shirts with
the faces of Bush and Gorbachev superimposed on that of Saddam.
   Except for a brief stop to shake hands in a downtown Helsinki
market district and a short visit to the U.S. embassy, Bush spent
much of his time in his hotel suite meeting with advisers.
   White House officials said the administration would have no
reaction to Saddam's six-point message to both leaders. It was not
clear whether Bush watched the address, broadcast on Cable News
Network and available to him in his hotel suite.
   Bush was also to meet on Sunday with a trade mission of U.S.
business executives here on their way to Moscow.
   The two leaders last met in Washington in early June. Their
first summit was at Malta last December.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900909-0010 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-09-90 1048EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i BC-Gulf-DesertTemps     09-09 0072</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Gulf-Desert Temps,0079</SECOND>
<HEAD>With Gulf Rdp, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   
   Here are the weather conditions and temperatures for the 24-hour
period ending midnight (local time) Sunday:
   
   Dhahran, Saudi Arabia: Clear, Low 79, High 106
   Jiddah, Saudi Arabia: Partly Cloudy, Low 77, High 99
   Mecca, Saudi Arabia: Partly Cloudy, Low 82, High 112
   Riyadh, Saudi Arabia: Clear, Low 75, High 108
   Manama, Bahrain - Clear, Low 82, High 99
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900909-0011 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-09-90 1156EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-911Call     09-09 0215</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-911 Call,0223</SECOND>
<HEAD>Woman Dials 911 With Nose, Rescued from Gas-filled Home</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DENVER (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A woman saved herself by dialing for help with her
nose after an intruder tied her up, turned on the gas in her stove
and left a candle burning, apparently in hope of triggering an
explosion, authorities said.
   Police said they were hunting for the person who attacked the
37-year-old woman early Thursday and seemed to want to make certain
she died.
   ``He shut the windows when he left, and he shut the door behind
him when he left. And he did light a candle in the living room,
where the victim was,'' said Detective Alan Keiser.
   Police did not release the victim's name.
   After breaking into the woman's home, the man tied her hands in
back of her and fastened to a chair, police said. He then ransacked
the house, turned on the gas in the oven without lighting it,
closed the windows, lit the candle and left.
   But the victim was able to tip her chair over to the floor, grab
the telephone with her teeth and dial 911 with her nose, police
said.
   The victim was taken to Denver General Hospital for treatment of
exposure to natural gas.
   There were no arrests as of early Sunday.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900909-0012 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-09-90 1204EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Gulf-The265th     09-09 0654</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-The 265th,0675</SECOND>
<HEAD>Training Before Dawn, By The Light of the Moon</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf Rdp, Bjt</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   The 265th Quartermaster Detachment of the South
Carolina National Guard is one of the reserve units called up for
possible duty in Saudi Arabia. National Writer Fred Bayles is
following the 14 Guardsmen as they prepare for deployment overseas.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>___</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>By FRED BAYLES</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP National Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>FORT STEWART, Ga. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The waning moon is still the brightest
object in the morning sky as the men from the 265th Quartermaster
Detachment turn into the homestretch of their daily run.
   The rest of this huge Army post just now is shrugging awake.
Diesels crank over at the motor pool. Shouts of other groups doing
calisthenics come from different directions.
   But the 265th, a South Carolina National Guard unit training for
the Mideast, is finishing its hour of PT _ physicial training. The
men have chanted cadence about whiskey, women and dying in the drop
zone. Now something else is needed to get them back to the barracks.
   ``TWO-SIX-FIVE,'' calls the captain leading the heavy breathing
troop.
   ``TWO-SIX-FIVE,'' they answer in unison.
   The pace picks up; the barracks is a quarter mile away. But the
captain orders a turn and, with a chorus of groans, the group
doubles around to pick up stragglers.
   ``More PT,'' some of the men gasp. ``Please sir, more PT!''
   Like many facets of military training, the 6 a.m. run has
multiple purposes. It conditions civilian bodies and minds. It
acclimates men for the desert. And it reinforces the idea of unity.
   The 265th is a tiny National Guard unit from Allendale, S.C.,
that specializes in water purification. Yet over 11 days, the group
has trained for everything but that.
   The men, whose civilian jobs range from prison guard to college
student, have drilled over and over on radio communications,
weapons, chemical warfare and field operations.
   ``These guys are probably going to be far back behind the lines,
but water is one of the most important things over there,'' said
Capt. Robert Appiah, the regular Army officer supervising the
265th's training.
   ``That makes them a target and we have to prepare them for
that,'' he said.
   But the constant training and the debilitating heat and humidity
of southern Georgia have taken a toll in the group, which has an
average age of 35. Several of the men hobble around with bad knees
and pulled muscles. One went to sick call suffering from mild
dehydration.
   Sgt. Earnest Deloach was excused from PT for two weeks to give a
damaged hamstring time to heal. But he was out on the road the next
morning trying to keep up. When he began to fall behind, he was
ordered to drop out.
   ``I'll finish it, Sarge,'' he called. He did finish, limping
into the barracks area as the other men were finishing their
showers.
   Deloach, who has spent 18 of his 38 years in the Guard, is a
big, jolly man whose tight-fitting helmet looks like it was screwed
onto his head. When he laughs, which is often, his big body shakes
with mirth. When he gets excited or angry, his voice climbs several
octaves.
   Now a supervisor at the Allendale Correctional Institution,
Deloach used to travel the country as a lineman, stringing wire for
power and cable systems.
   ``I quit because I was away from home too much. I got tired of
all that traveling,'' he said. ``Now look at me, here I go again,
10,000 miles.''
   Like the other men, Deloach tries to balance his duty with the
problems it causes his personal life, like missing his son's 16th
birthday last week.
   During a briefing about conduct for troops in Saudi Arabia,
someone asks what they can bring back with them from overseas duty.
   ``There's only one damned thing I want to bring home,'' Deloach
said with annoyance. ``That's the head of Saddam Hussein.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900909-0013 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-09-90 1248EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-EducationGoals     09-09 0743</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Education Goals,750</SECOND>
<HEAD>Education Goals Set, Now for the Hard Part</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TAMARA HENRY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Education Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Gov. Terry Branstad of Iowa was asked whether
President Bush and the nation's governors had set education goals
that were impossible to achieve. His response: a chuckle.
   ``Look,'' Branstad said. ``What did you want us to say _ that
`U.S. students will be third, fourth or fifth in the world in
mathematics and science achievement by the year 2000?'''
   The exchange at a recent CBS News education conference reflects
a growing concern that the goals approved in February after an
education summit between the president and governors may be a bit
too lofty.
   The goals say that beginning in the year 2000:
   _All children will start school ready to learn.
   _High school graduations will increase to at least 90 percent.
   _Students will demonstrate competency over challenging subject
matter.
   _Students will be first in the world in math and science.
   _Every adult American will be literate.
   _Every school will be free of violence and drugs.
   The goals are set against a backdrop of dismal statistics. The
Children's Defense Fund notes that every eight seconds a student
drops out, every 67 seconds a teenager has a baby, every 7 minutes
a child is arrested for drugs and every year 700,000 students
graduate who cannot read their diplomas.
   ``The issue of having all children come to school ready to learn
is almost breathtaking in its implications,'' said Ernest Boyer,
president of the Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of
Teaching.
   He said the concept includes making sure pregnant women receive
adequate prenatal care and children get good nutrition and health
care.
   ``If we would deliver on that, I am confident all the others
would fall into place much more completely,'' Boyer said. He said
the pledge ``really brings the issue of commitment to children
front and center.''
   Asked about the chances of attaining the math goal, educator
Marilyn Burns of Sausalito, Calif., quipped: ``Is this a
probability question? What, did Jimmy the Greek give this one?''
   ``I do believe this is a window of opportunity,'' said Burns,
who has created special math training courses.
   ``I have to believe that futility is better than apathy. It's
only going to happen if we make it happen,'' she said. ``It takes
all of us to save the system.''
   The Education Department said 19 percent of all eighth graders
and 30 percent of Hispanics, blacks, and American Indians were not
proficient in the basic math skills considered necessary to perform
everyday tasks.
   About 12 percent of the 29.5 million students entering the
57,000 public elementary schools this fall will attend remedial
reading programs and 6 percent will go to similar programs for
extra help in math, said the National Association of Elementary
School Principals.
   Congressional statistics show that four-fifths of elementary
school mathematics teachers are not fully qualified to teach math
and two-thirds of elementary school science teachers are not fully
qualified.
   A third of American high schools offer no physics course, and
many others offer no chemistry course. U.S. high school seniors
ranked ninth in advanced physics in a survey of 13 countries and
11th in advanced chemistry. American students were last in advanced
biology.
   The science goal ``was the president's and governors'
statement,'' said Timothy Goldsmith, biology professor at Yale
University. He sought to separate himself from that view but said
the statement raises questions about the objective of science
education.
   ``If the task seems gargantuan, consider recent history,'' said
AT&amp;T Chairman Robert E. Allen. ``A curtain of iron and a wall of
stone crumbled in the face of an ideal. Let us keep that picture
before us. For if freedom can topple walls, surely a belief in
children can build effective classrooms.''
   Edward Ahnert, incoming head of the Exxon Education Foundation,
added that the goal will serve a useful purpose by ``mobilizing the
hundreds of thousands of people that it's going to require to do
what we want to do.''
   ``If by the year 2000, we have moved from (a low ranking) up to
second or third _ we're not No. 1 _ have we failed?'' asked Ahnert.
``It's not getting to be No. 1 that's nearly so important as
getting to be much better than we are.
   ``So if Japan or whoever it is is still No. 1 and we're No. 2 _
it's still a hell of a lot better than being 14th or 15th.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900909-0014 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-09-90 1252EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--Corsica-Attack     09-09 0142</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Corsica-Attack,0144</SECOND>
<HEAD>Gunmen Stage Another Attack In Corsica</HEAD>
<DATELINE>AJACCIO, Corsica (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Five masked gunmen blew up a villa at a
southern housing development Sunday after tying up 14 residents,
police said. It was the second such bombing in two days.
   No one was injured, and there was no immediate claim of
responsibility in either incident. But previous attacks have been
launched by separatist guerrillas who oppose tourist development on
this French Mediterranean island.
   In the latest incident, the gunmen tied up occupants of two
homes and placed explosives in each building late Saturday, police
said. One of the charges did not go off, and the other exploded
after midnight, causing severe damage, according to police.
   On Friday, gunmen tied up 29 Italian vacationers and workmen at
a partially built tourist complex, then blew up two bungalows and a
construction crane.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900909-0015 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-09-90 1252EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--France-Champagne     09-09 0117</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--France-Champagne,0120</SECOND>
<HEAD>Price Of Champagne Grapes Up 20 Percent</HEAD>
<DATELINE>REIMS, France (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   High prices for champagne lie ahead as
farmers prepare to launch the annual grape harvest Tuesday.
   A dispute between growers and champagne producers ended in April
with the collapse of a 30-year system that fixed an overall price
for grapes each season. The price has since risen by 20 percent, to
about $3 a pound.
   There is usually a two-year gap between the grapes' harvest and
their sale for champagne production, but producers say the price of
a bottle of champagne could rise by 10 percent or more as early as
January 1991.
   Last year, 249 million bottles of champagne were sold worldwide.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900909-0016 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-09-90 1253EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-MotherTeresa     09-09 0424</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mother Teresa,0439</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mother Teresa Calls Her Re-Election God's Plan</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ARTHUR MAX</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CALCUTTA, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Mother Teresa, whose wish to retire was
rejected by nuns from around the world, said Sunday her re-election
as head of her charity was part of God's ``own plans.''
   The balloting was to have been a vote to choose a successor to
the frail, 80-year-old nun who is known as the ``saint of the
gutters'' for her work with the destitute and the poor.
   ``I was expecting to be free, but God has his own plans,''
Mother Teresa said when she met reporters for the first time after
Saturday's election.
   The Nobel Peace Prize laureate withdrew her decision to step
down as superior general of the Missionaries of Charity after
ballots were cast by 103 delegates summoned from missions around
the globe.
   Calcutta's Vicar General Monsignor Francis Gomes, who presided
over the secret balloting, said Mother Teresa had little choice but
to accept the unanimous vote.
   Mother Teresa said she had been firm on stepping down _ until
the balloting forced her to change her decision. ``These things
cannot be decided beforehand,'' she said.
   In March, Pope John Paul II said he was bowing to Mother
Teresa's wish to retire from the top post of the order she founded.
He had rejected her earlier requests to step aside.
   Mother Teresa suffered a nearly fatal heart attack a year ago.
She returned to work but asked for retirement within a few months.
   Asked if she would slow down her pace of work, Mother Teresa
replied: ``We have sisters who are capable of helping.''
   But she said she would continue to travel according to the needs
of her group.
   Along with Mother Teresa, four aides were elected. Sister
Fredrick, a Maltese nun who previously was head of the charity's
U.S. chapter based in Washington, was elected as Mother Teresa's
deputy.
   Mother Teresa was elected to a further six-year term.
   The Yugoslav-born Roman Catholic nun began her work in earnest
for the poor and helpless 43 years ago in the gutters of Calcutta,
India's most densely populated city in the eastern state of West
Bengal.
   Mother Teresa gave up a comfortable teaching job at a Catholic
school to set up a series of homes for the dying in Calcutta and
eventually throughout the world.
   Today, the Missionaries of Charity operate 430 homes in 95
countries for lepers, cripples, abandoned babies and others with no
place to turn.
   Mother Teresa was awarded the Nobel Prize in 1979.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900909-0017 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-09-90 1254EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-FuelEconomy     09-09 0700</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Fuel Economy,690</SECOND>
<HEAD>Gulf Crisis Improves Chances for Tougher Standards, Supporters Say</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN FLESHER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Proponents of legislation to require the U.S.
auto fleet to average 40 miles per gallon insist they are gaining
momentum as the Persian Gulf crisis focuses new attention on the
nation's dependence on foreign oil.
   The Senate bill, which opponents claim could force Americans to
give up the convenience of big cars and minivans, is expected to
reach the Senate floor this week. It cleared the Commerce Committee
on a 14-4 vote in April.
   An environmental lobbyist said supporters are within two or
three votes of the 60 needed to thwart an expected filibuster. He
said the bill is a weapon to use against Iraqi President Saddam
Hussein, whose invasion of Kuwait and threat to Saudi oil fields
precipitated the latest Middle East crisis.
   ``It's the single biggest step we can take to curb Saddam
Hussein's power,'' said Dan Becker of the Sierra Club. ``If we
don't need his oil, it lowers our stakes in the Middle East.''
   Prior to the Iraqi invasion, the bill's primary selling point
was supporters' contention that it would curb carbon dioxide
emissions, which are believed to be a major contributor to global
warming.
   The automobile industry is mounting a full-scale lobbying effort
against the measure, which is sponsored by Sen. Richard Bryan,
D-Nev.
   The Motor Vehicle Manufacturers Association, which represents
the Big Three U.S. automakers, is purchasing full-page
advertisements in major newspapers to argue its case.
   An industry spokesman acknowledged that the job of defeating the
bill in the Senate, already difficult, had become tougher since
Iraq invaded Kuwait last month, prompting a United Nations economic
boycott and deployment of U.S. troops to Saudi Arabia.
   ``It's going to be tough because there is an effort to portray
the Bryan bill as a positive reaction to the Middle East
situation,'' said Tim McCarthy of the manufacturers group.
   But he said prospects of the bill getting through the House are
slim even if it passes the Senate and he noted that the Bush
administration strongly opposes the measure. The administration has
urged motorists to drive the speed limit and keep their tires
properly inflated to save fuel.
   Congress established fuel economy standards in 1975 in response
to the 1973 Arab oil embargo. At that time, the average U.S.-made
car got 12 mpg.
   Under current law, new car fleets _ all the cars a company
manufactures in a given year _ must get an overall average of at
least 27.5 miles per gallon.
   The Bryan bill would require each manufacturer to improve its
corporate average fuel economy, or CAFE, 20 percent by 1995 and 40
percent by 2001. The overall fleet average would be about 34.4 mpg
in 1995 and 40.2 mpg by 2001, Bryan says.
   ``This higher CAFE can save us 2.8 million barrels of oil a
day,'' Bryan said Friday.
   Half of the nation's oil consumption _ 16.9 million barrels a
day _ is imported. About 63 percent of the nation's oil goes to
transportation, mainly the 180 million cars, trucks and buses on
U.S. highways.
   Automakers say the Bryan bill would have no impact on the
current crisis because the fuel savings would not materialize for
10 years to 15 years.
   Fuel efficiency has doubled since the 1970s, partly because the
average car's weight fell from 4,000 pounds to 3,000 pounds,
McCarthy said. The Bryan bill's standards are not technologically
feasible without another round of ``downsizing,'' which would
eliminate many larger models, he said.
   ``You're talking about an absolutely drastic change in the
models available to the public,'' McCarthy said. Station wagons and
minivans popular with families could disappear from showrooms, he
said.
   Bryan said automakers had equally dire warnings in the 1970s,
but managed to meet the standards.
   Sens. Donald Riegle, D-Mich., and Don Nickles, R-Okla., will
lead the opposition during debate, which could begin this week.
Congressional sources said the bill was among several that Majority
Leader George Mitchell, D-Maine, hoped to bring to the floor.
   Riegle served notice of a likely filibuster Friday by filing an
objection to waiving the customary two-day waiting period before
voting to halt debate.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900909-0018 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-09-90 1307EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-DefenseBudget     09-09 0756</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Defense Budget,710</SECOND>
<HEAD>Lawmakers Leaning Toward Old-Fashioned Conventional Weapons</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DONNA CASSATA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   America's buildup in the Persian Gulf has
given added impetus to proponents of a post-Cold War defense budget
that favors old-fashioned conventional weapons over sophisticated
strategic hardware.
   The House of Representatives takes up the fiscal 1991 defense
bill Monday, working from a $283 billion blueprint drawn up prior
to Iraq's Aug. 3 invasion of Kuwait.
   Deterring Iraqi aggression and its cost were not a direct
consideration when the House Armed Services Committee drew up the
plan.
   But some lawmakers say all the same that the measure is geared
to equipping U.S. forces for a desert conflict rather than a
European showdown.
   ``The bill better addresses these types of contingencies,'' said
Rep. Dave McCurdy, D-Okla., a senior member of the House Armed
Services Committee.
   The summit meeting between President Bush and Soviet President
Mikhail Gorbachev drove home what had already been seen as a
diminished Soviet threat. Both leaders expressed confidence that
the two superpowers could agree on a treaty to slash nuclear arms
by the end of the year.
   Responding to improved climate before the Helsinki summit, the
Armed Services bill slashed $24 billion from President Bush's
original request of $307 billion for fiscal 1991.
   Among the budget targets were the B-2 stealth bomber, the
Strategic Defense Initiative and two land-based nuclear missiles.
Among the programs given a second chance were the M-1 tank, F-15
jet fighter and V-22 Osprey helicopter.
   The estimated $1 billion a month cost of Operation Desert Shield
could change the amount eventually approved by the House. And any
deficit reduction agreement between congressional and White House
negotiators could do the same.
   A package covering some of the cost of Desert Shield will be
presented to the Armed Services Committee on Wednesday and taken up
by the full House the same day.
   Even if a so-called ``Iraqi add-on'' is adopted, the House bill
will differ in detail from the legislation approved by the Senate
last month.
   The Senate measure calls for $289 billion in defense spending
and leaves intact Bush's request for the B-2 bomber. But it slashes
$1 billion from his proposal for SDI.
   The ranking Republican on the Senate Armed Services Committee,
Sen. John Warner of Virginia, said in an interview last week that
$289 billion is the lowest the defense budget can go.
   ``Senator Nunn and I are firmly together. The Senate numbers on
defense are the bare minimum,'' Warner said referring to the
committee's chairman, Sam Nunn, D-Ga.
   The Senate adopted its defense bill shortly after Iraqi troops
invaded Kuwait and many lawmakers cautioned against deep cuts in
light of the events in the Middle East.
   Senate Minority Leader Bob Dole of Kansas summed up the
argument, saying Iraqi President Saddam Hussein has provided a
``wake-up call.''
   The Senate reaction was duly noted by a liberal Democrat on the
House Armed Services Committee, Rep. Patricia Schroeder of Colorado.
   ``I'm hoping that time and reflection won't allow that same
stampede here,'' Schroeder said in an interview last week.
   Sen. William Cohen, R-Maine, says the Iraqi aggression will
temper the widespread calls for significant cuts in the defense
budget but not prevent military reductions.
   ``I think it will slow it down somewhat but there will be cuts
and we'll still look at the kind of strategic systems like the B-2,
MX rail-garrison that we have proposed eliminating,'' Cohen said on
returning from a congressional trip to the Middle East.
   The House Armed Services legislation would limit production of
the B-2 stealth bomber to the 15 planes already under construction.
   The Air Force believes the radar-evading plane is ideal for
locating targets in the Soviet Union, but lawmakers have winced at
the bomber's cost of nearly $865 million per plane.
   The committee also stripped nearly $2 billion from Bush's
request of $4.7 billion for the Strategic Defense Initiative, cut
military personnel by 129,500 and scaled back on two nuclear
missile programs.
   It also rejected Defense Secretary Dick Cheney's second attempt
in two years to kill the V-22 Osprey, the tilt-rotor aircraft the
Marine Corps envisions as a futuristic transport vehicle.
   The panel also added money for programs that the Defense
Department and Bush did not want, coming under attack from some
Republicans for pork-barrel spending.
   Among the additions are $150 million for M-1 tank modifications
and $100 million for F-15 fighters.
   Some Democrats perceive those additions as necessary for a
military that is more likely to face Iraq than the Soviet Union.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900909-0019 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-09-90 1315EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Summit-Soviet-Iraq     09-09 0785</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Summit-Soviet-Iraq,780</SECOND>
<HEAD>Iraqi Link to Moscow Has Weakened in Recent Years</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT BURNS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Soviet Union has been Iraq's main arms
supplier for more than two decades, but Middle East experts say
relations between Moscow and its Persian Gulf client cooled in
recent years as Iraq looked to the West for technology.
   Moscow's decision to condemn the Iraqi occupation of Kuwait, and
its support for United Nations economic sanctions against Baghdad,
is a major blow to Saddam Hussein. But it's not the first sign of
change in Iraqi-Soviet relations.
   ``It already was changing,'' said Robert Neumann, a former U.S.
ambassador to Saudi Arabia and other Middle Eastern nations.
   Neumann said Iraq began turning toward the West, especially
France, in the early 1980s. This followed Iraq's condemnation of
the December 1979 Soviet invasion of predominantly Muslim
Afghanistan and the start of Iraq's eight-year war with Iran.
   Iraq also has been irritated by Soviet support for Syria, an
arch enemy of Iraq.
   Signs of the strained relationship were evident Sunday when
Soviet President Mikhail S. Gorbachev said Iraq was asking for
trouble by refusing to withdraw from Kuwait.
   ``What the present Iraqi leadership is doing is driving it into
a dead end, and I hope President Saddam Hussein will heed this
appeal to him,'' Gorbachev told a news conference at the conclusion
of his summit with President Bush in Helsinki, Finland.
   Moscow halted arms sales to Iraq after the invasion of Kuwait on
Aug. 2. Up to then it ranked as Baghdad's main arms supplier.
Moscow sold Iraq $23 billion in weapons between 1982 and 1989, or
about 55 percent of total Iraqi arms purchases in that period,
according to the Congressional Research Service.
   Last year Iraq began building Soviet-designed T-72 main battle
tanks which it previously had purchased directly from Moscow. The
Soviets sold hundreds of the tanks to Iraq during the gulf war, and
they were a key factor in a string of Iraqi military victories that
forced Iran to accept a cease-fire that took effect in August 1988.
   Also in Iraq's arsenal are Soviet-made MiG-29 fighter jets,
Sukhoi Su-24 and Su-25 fighter-bombers, and Tu-22 Blinder bombers.
Iraq also has an undetermined number of Soviet-made SS-12
Scaleboard mobile ballistic missiles as well as shorter-range
Scud-B missiles.
   Some American analysts believe Moscow is playing a ``double
game'' of giving the appearance of cooperating with the West in
trying to push Saddam out of Kuwait while at the same time
preserving its relations with its longtime ally.
   ``The Soviet Union has provided Iraq with tangible and
invaluable diplomatic support even as it seeks to promote the
perception that Moscow is sorely chagrined with Saddam Hussein,''
said Frank J. Gaffney Jr., director of the Center for Security
Policy, a Washington think tank.
   Gaffney said cooperation between Moscow and Baghdad also extends
to intelligence gathering.
   ``It is only reasonable to presume that this cooperation now
involves the provision to Baghdad of vital strategic warning and
tactical information about the multinational force arrayed against
Iraq _ a capability which Iraq basically lacks,'' he said Friday.
   On Thursday the Iraqi foreign minister, Tariq Aziz, said in
Moscow after meeting with Gorbachev that he appreciated the
Soviets' willingness to listen to his country's grievances even
though Gorbachev still insisted Iraq withdraw from Kuwait.
   ``I without hesitation can still call the Soviets our friends
despite the differences between us,'' Aziz told reporters.
   Saddam took a tougher tone on Saturday in a public message to
Gorbachev and Bush on the eve of their Helsinki meeting. The Iraqi
leader suggested the outcome of the meeting would determine whether
Moscow was finished as a superpower.
   ``He who represents the Soviet Union should remember that doubts
about the place of the Soviet Union as a superpower have gotten
into the mind of every politician for some time, especially as the
U.S. began to assume to be the sole power in the world,'' Saddam
said.
   Soviet advisers in Iraq, estimated to number about 1,000, are
believed to have helped train soldiers in the use and maintenance
of Soviet-made weaponry.
   Gorbachev said Sunday that only 196 of those advisers were
involved in military matters. He said their number had dropped to
150 and that all eventually would leave Iraq.
   Iraq began building relations with the Soviet Union after a 1958
coup that toppled the Iraqi monarchy and established a modern
republic. In April 1972, Iraq signed a 20-year treaty of friendship
and cooperation with Moscow. The pact called for cooperation in
military, political, economic and social matters and was similar to
a treaty the Soviets had with Egypt before President Anwar Sadat
expelled thousands of Soviet advisers and repudiated the pact.

</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900909-0020 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-09-90 1324EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>d a AM-BRF--SharkAttack     09-09 0164</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Shark Attack,0171</SECOND>
<HEAD>Diver Attacked By Shark</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JENNER, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A shark grabbed a diver by his head but
was driven off when the man smacked it several times with his spear
gun, according to deputies.
   ``It picked him up, then just let go and sank back down,'' Bill
Davenport said after his diving partner, Rodney Orr was attacked
Saturday.
   Orr, 49, of Santa Rosa was able to reach his dive board and
paddle for 20 minutes back to shore. He was treated for cuts on his
nose, cheek and neck.
   The two were diving for abalone in about 40 feet of water in the
ocean north of here.
   Orr told Sonoma County deputies he was on the surface when he
was struck from behind.
   ``He was lucky,'' said Davenport. ``It was most likely a great
white, from the size of it, from the size of the teeth marks.''
   Orr said the shark's head measured between 18 inches and two
feet across.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900909-0021 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-09-90 1325EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Summit-High-TechFinland Bjt   09-09 0603</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Summit-High-Tech Finland, Bjt,600</SECOND>
<HEAD>Modern Arctic Country Stages Summit in a Week</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LAURINDA KEYS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HELSINKI, Finland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   High-tech Finland, a model of
efficiency and electronic knowhow, was an ideal choice to stage a
complicated superpower summit on a week's notice.
   ``There wasn't much time ... but we can handle it,'' President
Mauno Koivisto said calmly a few days before the sudden summit
meeting between Presidents Bush and Mikhail Gorbachev.
   And he was right, though Bush and Gorbachev struggled at times
with the sound system at their end-of-summit news conference.
   ``We have had a lot of big events _ not as big as this of course
_ so we were confident we would be able to build this in such a
short time,'' said Christer Hagglund, who supervised installation
of telephones, electric typewriters, computer terminals and
transmission facilities for 2,160 journalists from all over the
world.
   ``Our telephone network is very efficient,'' he said.
   One radio journalist from Washington agreed. ``Is this a
cellular phone? This town has the greatest toys,'' he exclaimed,
holding a tiny, lightweight mobile telephone that isn't available
in the United States yet.
   The Finnish company Nokia produces 14 per cent of the world's
cellular phones, the largest share of any company in the world.
   Gorbachev was astounded by a Nokia product during his state
visit to Helsinki last October. He was handed one of the
six-inch-long phones with a short aerial and told to listen.
Someone he knew in Moscow spoke to him through the phone and
photographers registered Gorbachev's disbelief.
   Finnish technology has also produced thermal suits which protect
humans at sub-zero temperatures; the artificial sweetener, Xylitol;
the antiviral protein, interferon, and a five-year contraceptive
coil without the adverse side effects of other intrauterine devices.
   While a few Lapps in the north still live a nomadic life, using
reindeer for meat, for clothing and for bearing their belongings,
most Finns are city dwellers in the south and the nation boasts one
of the world's highest standards of living.
   The national school system reaches the Lapps, too, and Finland
claims nearly 100 per cent of its population can read and write.
   At least 17 percent of the government's budget is allocated to
education, science research and culture. Including funds from
private industry, more than half of all Finnish research money goes
to technology.
   Sixty percent of all working icebreakers were made in Finland,
where one-third of the land mass is above the Arctic Circle. The
country has over 100,000 lakes and its Finnish name, ``Suomi,'' is
believed to be based on the word for ``swamp.''
   Finland is a particular leader in forestry and agricultural
developments. More than half its 135,200 square miles are covered
with forest.
   Metal and forest products are Finland's main exports, and it is
the world's second largest exporter of paper.
   Although Finns have all the modern conveniences, the latest
technology and styles, they pay a lot for it.
   The modern railroad, highway and telephone networks are
expensive to maintain because of the great distances involved, even
though 60 per cent of the 5 million people live in urban areas. The
low population, representing a small market for mass-produced
products, makes prices higher.
   Cars are taxed at 130 per cent of their value to justify the
cost in foreign currency of getting them and their parts to
consumers. A radio priced at the equivalent of $600 in Helsinki
could be bought for $100 at a discount warehouse in New York.
   Finns also pay high taxes, from 30 percent to 60 percent of
their income, and 17 percent in sales taxes.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900909-0022 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-09-90 1343EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-HeartlandHaute     09-09 0480</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Heartland Haute,0495</SECOND>
<HEAD>Midwest Market Basket Holds More Than Corn and Soybeans</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SARAH NORDGREN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CHICAGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   California cuisine leave you longing? Your taste
for Cajun cooking on the wane? An ambitious band of gourmet farmers
and restaurateurs may have the answer for your tired taste buds:
``heartland haute cuisine.''
   The nation's breadbasket is out to prove at the grocery and in
the best restaurants that Midwest means a whole lot more than corn
and soybeans.
   At the second annual ``Best of the Midwest Market'' on Sunday,
more than 60 of gourmet food purveyors from 10 states strutted
their stuff: wild forest gypsy mushrooms from Michigan, Illinois
buffalo summer sausage, Nebraska blue corn, wine from Michigan,
Illinois caviar and local blue-veined goat cheese.
   ``We don't have to borrow it from the West Coast, the East Coast
or Europe,'' says Jim Eschner, who produces about 1,000 cases of
Reisling, Chardonnay and Gewurztraminer wine each year at Winegrow
Inc. in Buchanan, Mich. ``It's kind of neat _ Midwesterners have
got their own identity.''
   Winegrow's wine is served at Chicago's Printer's Row restaurant,
where chef Michael Foley was among the first to tout Midwestern
cuisine.
   ``We have all sorts of local fish, great games, unbelievable
fruits and berries,'' said Foley. ``We are the stable breadbasket
of the nation.''
   ``Nobody's apologizing anymore for being Midwest,'' Linda
Griffith, co-author of the newly published ``The Best of the
Midwest'' cookbook, said in an interview Friday.
   Organizers of the Best of the Midwest Market say interest in
heartland haute is growing. But it may still take some time for
regional specialties to reach supermarket shelves.
   ``The majority of the market's foods cannot be found anywhere in
Chicago,'' said Jill Van Cleave, co-chairman of the event sponsored
by the Chicago chapter of the American Institute of Wine and Food.
   ``This is a major concern of ours _ to get the marketplace up to
a better level,'' she said.
   Many of the participants run small cottage industries that do
their own growing and marketing, cutting out the middleman. The
farmer's market, they say, gives them a chance to showcase their
products to a broader audience.
   ``It's a network,'' said Mary Galle, sales director of American
Spoon Foods of Petoskey, Mich. ``The real important thing is ...
the quality of both the product that we have and the service that
we give.''
   American Spoon Foods expects this year to sell 300,000 jars of
its gourmet preserves, made from Michigan blueberries,
thimbleberries and other fruits.
   Most sales are to restaurants and gourmet food shops, said Galle.
   Restaurants like Cousins Heritage Inn in Dexter, Mich., and
River Wildlife, a private dinner club in Kohler, Wis., say they buy
nearly all of their food from within the region.
   ``We don't go out of Wisconsin to get anything _ unless it's
Norwegian salmon,'' said River Wildlife chef Sandy Wassink.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900909-0023 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-09-90 1343EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i Summit-FirstLadies     09-09 0546</FIRST>
<SECOND>Summit-First Ladies,540</SECOND>
<HEAD>Barbara Bush, Raisa Gorbachev Leaf Through History Books</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LESLIE SHEPHERD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HELSINKI, Finland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Barbara Bush and Raisa Gorbachev leafed
through the pages of history in Finland's national library on
Sunday, and said they were optimistic their husbands would find a
peaceful solution to the Persian Gulf crisis.
   The U.S. and Soviet first ladies, touring the Helsinki
University Library, pored over ancient books, manuscripts, and
maps, including the oldest known Moscow city map and an early
American map showing California as an island.
   Mrs. Bush wore a royal blue dress, while Mrs. Gorbachev was
wearing a severe gray suit and a violet blouse, appearing less
stylish than she has on previous visits to the West. She has drawn
criticism in the Soviet Union for her fashionable attire.
   Librarian Esko Hakli escorted the women through the domed,
neoclassical library, pointing out the rarest of its 3 million
books and 2 million other documents.
   Mrs. Gorbachev, a former university professor, repeatedly
prodded him for historical tidbits as they strolled past stack upon
stack of books, including the most complete collection of Russian
works in Western Europe.
   She urged Mrs. Bush to prepare for a visit to Moscow by studying
the 1538 map, although Hakli told reporters it shows only the
Moscow River and a few other details ``and you wouldn't find your
way with the help of that map.''
   Mrs. Gorbachev corrected Halki when he pointed to ``Asiatic
Russia'' on a map, saying of her ethnically diverse homeland, ``We
are one Russia, not Asian Russia and European Russia.''
   Helsinki University Library, as Finland's national library,
receives copies of all books published in the country, including
one of the first Finnish language books, a religious primer printed
in the mid-1500s.
   ``Is it a Bible?'' Mrs. Gorbachev asked in English.
   From 1820 to 1917, when Finland was a province of Czarist
Russia, the library also had the right to a copy of all books
published by Russian printers, and now has more than 400,000 works
in Russian.
   The buff and white building also houses manuscripts of Finnish
composers, including the first draft of Jean Sibelius' violin
concerto and the score of his 5th symphony.
   The university was founded in 1640 in Turku, the former capital
of Finland, but a fire destroyed the entire city in 1827 and the
university was moved to Helsinki. Only 800 of the library's 40,000
volumes were rescued.
   Russian Czar Nicholas I took a personal interest in rebuilding
the library, and the floor plan is arranged in the shape of his
monogram.
   Mrs. Gorbachev and Mrs. Bush, looking relaxed after morning tea
with Finnish President Mauno Koivisto's wife Tellervo, told
reporters they expected their husbands would have a successful
summit.
   ``Yes, there is a peaceful solution,'' to the Persian Gulf
crisis, Mrs. Bush said. ``Otherwise we wouldn't be here.''
   ``I hope our husbands, along with the rest of the free world,
will work hard to make peace,'' she said.
   Mrs. Gorbachev added that ``as people, as citizens of our
countries,'' the first ladies wanted ``a political, peaceful
solution to be found.''
   Asked whether she was worried about American soldiers sent to
Saudi Arabia, Mrs. Bush said: ``Of course we worry about the men
and the women. We worry.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900909-0024 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-09-90 1353EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People     09-09 0737</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People,0763</SECOND>
<NOTE>Eds: Retransmitting a0721 to fix hyphen in slugline.</NOTE>
<HEAD>People in the News</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY44</HEAD>
<DATELINE>GRAND RAPIDS, Mich. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Former President Gerald R. Ford's
boyhood home that has stood empty for nearly 20 years will be sold
because efforts failed to turn it into a museum.
   ``It's almost a lost cause,'' said Steele Taylor, chairman of
the Grand Rapids Arts and Museum Commission. ``We can't get anybody
interested in fixing it up.''
   The federal Veterans Administration acquired the four-bedroom
house in 1972 when the owner defaulted. Three years later, after
Ford became president, the VA donated it to the city.
   The commission had trouble raising the estimated $51,000 to
renovate the home into a museum because Ford lived in at least
eight homes in Grand Rapids, said Jim Kratsas, curator of the
Gerald R. Ford Museum.
   City records show Ford lived in the white two-story house from
1923 to 1930, from the time he was 10 years old through his junior
year at the Grand Rapids South High School.
   In a 1989 letter to museum director Timothy Chester, Ford wrote:
``I have no objection to _ in fact, I endorse the sale.''
   Museum officials have asked the city's Historic Preservation
Commission to designate the house as a historic landmark to protect
it from demolition.
   Helena Jones, 86, who has lived next door to the Ford house for
20 years, said sentimentality aside, she hopes the house gets sold.
   ``He wasn't president that long,'' Jones said. ``We've got
enough things named after Ford.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>BYNUM, Mont. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Former CBS anchorman Walter Cronkite says he
has something in common with every ``red-blooded human being'' _ a
fascination with dinosaurs.
   Cronkite was doing his part last week to publicize the great
beasts of the past, spending time in Montana to film a documentary
series on dinosaurs.
   ``It's a fascinating project,'' he said Friday as an
international crew filmed a segment northwest of Great Falls, Mont.
``It's something that I think will make an impact in America.''
   The four-hour series produced by Canadian, British and German
television will be shown in the United States on the Arts and
Entertainment cable channel about a year from now.
   Cronkite, 73, spoke with owners of the Bynum Rock Shop, who
found the bones of baby dinosaurs that led to discovery of a key
fossil site. The crew also has filmed a fossil dig near Circle,
Mont., where the most complete skeleton of a Tyrannosaurus rex was
discovered two years ago.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>COLUMBUS, Ohio (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Actor Tony Randall will be the master of
ceremonies and violinists Itzhak Perlman and Pinchas Zukerman will
perform duets at an concert to wrap up a campaign to raise money
for the arts.
   The Oct. 31 performance is to celebrate the official end of
``Trilogy: A Campaign for the Arts,'' a $25 million campaign to
support Columbus' three major arts institutions.
   The Columbus Symphony Orchestra will receive $12.5 million of
the money raised; the Columbus Museum of Art will receive $6
million. The Columbus Association for the Performing Arts, which
owns and operates the Ohio and the Palace theaters, will receive $6
million to pay off the Ohio Theatre expansion.
   ``The concert will be a celebration and a fund-raising campaign
at the same time,'' said Doug Kridler, president of the Columbus
Association for the Performing Arts. ``Obviously, we already have a
lot to celebrate by having gotten this far, and we have a lot of
people to thank for helping get it there.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Lou Diamond Phillips' latest role is causing
controversy among Navajos, but South Dakota Sioux are honoring the
multiracial actor for his portrayals of American Indians.
   The Sioux have given Phillips, 28, star of the 1987 film ``La
Bamba,'' the honorary name ``Starkeeper,'' publicist Eddie Michaels
said Friday.
   The tribe will officially confer the name on Phillips at a
ceremony later this year in the Black Hills of South Dakota,
Michaels said.
   The watchdog group the American Indian Registry for the
Performing Arts has challenged the casting of Phillips as a Navajo
policeman in a film based on author Tony Hillerman's novel ``The
Dark Wind.''
   Phillips, who played a Mexican-Indian in ``Young Guns'' and
``Young Guns II,'' has said he is part Cherokee, Filipino,
Scottish-Irish, Hawaiian and Hispanic.
   Bonnie Paradise, director of the American Indian Registry, said
last week that Phillips had not provided documentation of his
lineage.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900909-0025 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-09-90 1427EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Cambodia     09-09 0571</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Cambodia,0586</SECOND>
<HEAD>Warring Cambodian Factions Said Ready To Accept U.N. Peace Plan</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto JAK2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KENNETH L. WHITING</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JAKARTA, Indonesia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The four warring factions in Cambodia
appear ready to accept a U.N. peace plan to end their 11-year-old
war, Indonesian Foreign Minister Ali Alatas said Sunday.
   ``We are encouraged by the fact that the four factions have
indicated they can accept the document as the basis for settling
the Cambodian conflict,'' the foreign minister said after the
opening session of peace talks in the Indonesian capital.
   Alatas said ``the circumstances for achieving a comprehensive
settlement are unlikely ever again to be as favorable as they are
now.''
   The guerrillas and Cambodia's Vietnam-backed government had no
immediate comment.
   The talks, originally scheduled to open Wednesday, were delayed
because key leaders threatened to stay away unless their
counterparts attended.
   The talks were focusing on a plan backed by the five permanent
members of the U.N. Security Council _ the United States, Soviet
Union, China, Britain and France _ to end Cambodia's civil war.
   The plan envisions the formation of a transitional council on
which each of the four Cambodian factions would be represented.
   The so-called Supreme National Council would cede much of its
authority to the United Nations, whose representatives would
administer the country until free elections could be held. The plan
also calls for disarming and regrouping the four armies.
   Earlier meetings in Indonesia and elsewhere since July 1988
ended inconclusively when the four factions disagreed on how to
share power in the period before elections.
   Premier Hun Sen of the Vietnam-installed government in Phnom
Penh has accepted the U.N. plan ``not only as the agenda of the
meeting, but also as the framework of the solution.''
   The three-party guerrilla resistance coalition also accepts the
U.N. proposal. It was represented Sunday by Khieu Samphan, nominal
leader of the communist Khmer Rouge; former Cambodian Premier Son
Sann, who heads the anti-communist Khmer People's National
Liberation Front; and Prince Norodom Ranariddh, who represents the
faction of his father, Prince Norodom Sihanouk. He said he was ill
and could not attend.
   The Indonesian foreign minister and a French Foreign Ministry
official, Edwige Avice, were leading the talks.
   ``The main idea for us, for the permanent five, is an enhanced
intervention of the United Nations in order to create a neutral
political environment allowing the Cambodian people to decide
freely on its future by free and fair elections,'' Ms. Avice said.
   Sihanouk has said the guerrilla coalition would allow the Phnom
Penh government half the seats on the proposed 12-member council,
with the other six seats to be divided equally among the three
guerrilla groups. However, he said the council's decisions should
be made by consensus rather than majority vote.
   He also said the council should be formed before the start of
the U.N. General Assembly session later this month so its
representative could take Cambodia's seat in the world body, which
is now held by the guerrilla coalition. He said China supported his
proposals.
   The guerrilla coalition's non-Communist resistance forces are
backed by Washington. China backs the Khmer Rouge.
   The guerrilla coalition is battling the government Vietnam
installed in Phnom Penh after it invaded in late 1978 and toppled
the Khmer Rouge, who had during their nearly four-year rule tried
to transform Cambodia into a radical agrarian society. Their
program resulted in the deaths of nearly 1 million people.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900909-0026 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-09-90 1439EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-SmothersShooting     09-09 0223</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Smothers Shooting,0229</SECOND>
<HEAD>Woman Shot to Death at Comedian Tom Smothers' Ranch While He Was
Away</HEAD>
<DATELINE>KENWOOD, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A man killed his sister and wounded a
cousin in a shooting at a vineyard-girded estate owned by comedian
Tom Smothers, who was away at the time, deputies said.
   Less than an hour after Saturday's shooting, a man identified as
Gustavo Pureco, 25, of Santa Rosa surrendered at the Sonoma County
jail and was booked on suspicion of murder and attempted murder.
   Sheriff's authorities said Pureco apparently was angry because
his sister, 18-year-old Eva Pureco, had recently moved out of his
house and had gone to live with other relatives at Smothers'
25-acre hilltop Remick Ridge estate.
   The woman was shot twice in the chest with a .45-caliber pistol,
said sheriff's Sgt. Chuck Laver.
   The cousin, Ismael Calderon, was in critical condition Sunday at
Sonoma County Community Hospital, said nursing supervisor Kathy
Kuhne.
   Smothers said Miss Pureco was not one of his employees, but he
has known Calderon for many years.
   ``This was one of our loyal workers,'' he said. ``I've had this
ranch 18 years and he's been here 15 or 16.''
   Smothers planted the vineyard in the 1970s to supply grapes for
his brother Dick's former winery in Santa Cruz. Dick Smothers has
since gotten out of the winery business.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900909-0027 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-09-90 1449EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Lebanon-Palestinians     09-09 0504</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lebanon-Palestinians,0523</SECOND>
<HEAD>PLO Guerrillas Battle Abu Nidal Fighters In Tunnels</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By AHMED MANTASH</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SIDON, Lebanon (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   PLO forces claimed victory Sunday in their
battle for control of refugee camps in south Lebanon after storming
fortified tunnels holding the remnants of troops loyal to terrorist
leader Abu Nidal.
   Police report at least 75 people killed and more than 200
wounded during the Palestine Liberation Organization's three-day
offensive to oust Abu Nidal guerrillas from Sidon and nearby
refugee camps.
   ``We have established undisputed control over all the refugee
camps in Sidon and the rest of south Lebanon,'' Younis Awad, a
senior aide to PLO chairman Yasser Arafat, said in the Ein
el-Hilweh shantytown, site of the 12-hour battle in the tunnels.
   Awad said most of the 300 fighters from Abu Nidal's
Fatah-Revolutionary Council were either killed or captured in the
camp on the outskirts of Sidon, a port city about 25 miles south of
Beirut. The two sides fought in hand-to-hand combat in the refugee
camp, Lebanon's largest with an estimated 32,000 people.
   ``They're finished,'' Awad said. ``It's a final victory.''
   During the fighting, Abu Nidal forces in the nearby hilltop
village od Majdalyoun unleashed a 30-minute artillery barrage on
Ein el-Hilweh. Thousands of refugees fled the camp at the height of
the fighting. Many of those killed in the latest battles were
civilians.
   Police reported about 100 Abu Nidal fighters remained holed up
in Majdalyoun, a main training base and weapons depot for Abu
Nidal's group. The village is about five miles east of Sidon.
   ``It's a fortress up there. It will take the PLO quite a while
to get them out,'' said a police spokesman who cannot be identified
under briefing regulations.
   Abu Nidal, whose real name is Sabri al-Banna, broke away from
the PLO in 1973 and was sentenced to death in absentia by a PLO
tribunal for killing Arafat aides.
   Abu Nidal's group has been torn by internal feuds in recent
months. Scores of men have been killed and some of Abu Nidal's top
aides defected with their followers.
   Abu Nidal is sought by the United States and some Western
European nations for terrorist attacks over the last 15 years,
including massacres at the Rome and Vienna airports in December
1985 that killed a total of 20 people.
   He is also wanted in connection with the hijacking of a Pan
American World Airways jet in Karachi, Pakistan, in September 1986.
Twenty passengers were killed and 120 wounded.
   Security sources say Abu Nidal's faction has increasingly been
allied with the Syrians, who have about 40,000 troops in Lebanon.
   Police officials, speaking on condition of anonymity, predict
that the PLO victory in south Lebanon could trigger retaliation by
Abu Nidal loyalists.
   ``We're going to see a wave of assassinations, bombings and
kidnappings against Arafat's men,'' one official commented.
   Arafat reportedly has about 5,000 guerrillas in south Lebanon.
   In Sidon, a general strike was called Sunday to protest the
violence. The city of 350,000 people has been ravaged by fires
following heavy shelling.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900909-0028 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-09-90 1456EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Summit-Gorbachev     09-09 0732</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Summit-Gorbachev,720</SECOND>
<HEAD>Gorbachev Wins Hints of Aid, Says Soviets Can't Be Bought</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BRYAN BRUMLEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HELSINKI, Finland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Mikhail Gorbachev won hints of more
economic aid from President Bush on Sunday but rebuffed suggestions
that Moscow would play a global second fiddle to Washington.
   ``It would be very oversimplified and very superficial to judge
that the Soviet Union could be bought for dollars,'' Gorbachev told
a joint news conference with the U.S. president at the close of
their one-day summit.
   The Soviet and U.S. leaders pledged to work closely in using
commercial and diplomatic pressure to force Iraq to withdraw from
Kuwait, but Gorbachev stressed he was not following the U.S. lead
in order to win American aid.
   ``We do not want to get caught up in a debate about prestige,''
he said when asked to respond to Iraq leader Saddam Hussein's
challenge for Moscow to defy U.S. will in the Middle East in order
to prove that it was still a superpower.
   ``No single country, however powerful, will be able to provide
the leadership which individual countries formerly tried to
provide, including some countries which are represented here,'' he
said.
   Gorbachev and his entourage departed for Moscow Sunday night.
   During the seven hours of summit talks, the Soviet leader again
balked at sending troops or warships to bolster U.S. forces
implementing a United Nations embargo against Iraq.
   Gorbachev won a pledge from Bush that U.S. troops would withdraw
from the Arabian peninsula at the close of the crisis. And the
Soviet leader announced that about 150 Soviet military experts
remained in Iraq, down from 196 at the beginning of the crisis.
   ``They are leaving Iraq and the process is moving forward, so I
don't think it's a problem,'' he said. There had been speculation
he might agree to withdraw all the experts.
   Bush said the presence of the advisers was ``not a major
irritant,'' but that there removal would ``facilitate''
understanding in the United States of the Soviet position.
   Bush said that he had asked Gorbachev neither to send a special
message to Hussein _ a former Soviet client _ nor to dispatch
troops or naval vessels to join U.S. forces implementing U.S.
sanctions against Iraq.
   ``I did not ask him to send troops in,'' Bush said. ``If the
Soviet Union wants to send troops in at the invitation of the
Saudis, that would be fine with me.''
   Gorbachev stressed his desire for a political rather than a
military solution to the crisis, and Bush acknowledged that ``some
differences remain'' in the advisability of using force.
   Bush did not spell out any concrete steps the U.S. government
might take to prop up the failing economy of the Soviet Union,
where shortages of bread and other staples were spreading.
   But the U.S. president did he say he wanted to bolster radical
reform policies that are now under debate in the Soviet Union.
   ``We, for course, want perestroika to succeed,'' Bush said. ``I
think that this remarkable cooperation that has been demonstrated
by the Soviet Union at the United Nations gets me inclined to
recommend as close cooperation in the economic field as possible,
and I will be saying this to the Congress when I get back,'' he
said.
   Bush and key members of the Senate say they will push for
ratification of a bilateral trade agreement and favorable tariffs
for the Soviet Union once that nation's parliament codifies recent
liberalizations in emigration policy.
   Bush also noted that he was sending Commerce Secretary Robert
Mosbacher to Moscow this week with a team of U.S. businessmen to
``encourage economic cooperation in as many ways as possible.''
   White House chief of staff John Sununu told reporters that the
two leaders discussed cooperation in developing energy resources,
but he did not go as far as Bush did on Saturday, saying he might
be willing to trade U.S. technology for Soviet oil. The Soviet
Union is the world's largest oil producer.
   Gorbachev won from Bush a renewed pledge that the United States
does not intend to maintain a permanent military base in Saudi
Arabia, 1,000 miles from southern Soviet borders.
   Bush said U.S. forces would stay in the region as long as
needed, but ``the sooner they are out of there as far as I'm
concerned, the better. ... We have no intention of keeping them
there a day longer than required.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900909-0029 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-09-90 1500EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-ColemanExecution     09-09 0180</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Coleman Execution,160</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<HEAD>Court Denies Stay of Execution for Oklahoma Killer</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Supreme Court on Sunday denied a stay of
execution for convicted killer Charles Troy Coleman, setting up the
first execution in Oklahoma in 24 years.
   Court spokesman Ed Turner said both a stay request and a
petition of certiorari (review) were denied. Justice Thurgood
Marshall dissented and Justice Harry Blackmun did not participate,
Turner said.
   Coleman was scheduled to die by drug injection at 12:02 a.m. CDT
Monday for the 1979 shotgun slaying of John Seward in Muskogee.
Execution was to take place at the Oklahoma State Penitentiary in
McAlester.
   Seward and his wife, Roxie, were killed when they surprised a
burglar at the residence of a relative. Seward was 68 and his wife
was 62.
   The high court previously had turned down Coleman's appeals five
times.
   Coleman, 43, came within 36 hours of execution three years ago,
before receiving a stay.
   The last person to be executed in Oklahoma was James D. French,
who was electrocuted in 1966 for killing his cellmate.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900909-0030 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-09-90 1519EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SouthAfrica     09-09 0446</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-South Africa,0459</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ten Die in Attack on Squatters; Police Open Fire To Disperse
Protesters</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TOM COHEN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JOHANNESBURG, South Africa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Police opened fire Sunday to
disperse crowds of blacks in Soweto angered by an overnight attack
on a squatter camp that killed at least 10 people.
   At least three people were wounded during Sunday's
confrontations, according to a witness.
   A total of 32 people had died in black factional fighting since
Saturday, reports said. Hundreds have died since the violence in
black townships near Johannesburg began less than one month ago.
   Residents accused Zulu supporters of the conservative Inkatha
movement of launching the nighttime attack with police help. They
also said masked white men took part in the assault on Soweto's
Tladi squatter camp.
   The head of the South African Council of Churches, the Rev.
Frank Chikane, visited the camp and said he had seen enough to know
that ``police are involved in killing us.''
   Police fought running battles with residents hurling rocks and
firebombs throughout the morning near the camp in the sprawling
township southwest of Johannesburg.
   At least three blacks were wounded when police opened fire with
birdshot and live ammunition, a witness said. Earlier, police had
fired tear gas and rubber bullets at the residents.
   The Independent South African Press Association reported a crowd
of about 100 people attacked the camp on Saturday night, assaulting
occupants and smashing dwellings.
   A total of 26 people were killed in Soweto over the weekend,
police said Sunday. Residents and witnesses said 13 died at the
Tladi squatter camp, but police could not confirm that figure.
   Six other deaths were reported Sunday in other Johannesburg-area
townships, including four men found stabbed in a van at a squatter
camp near Vosloorus, south of the city.
   Fighting between Zulu Inkatha backers and Xhosas and other
blacks loyal to the African National Congress has killed nearly 600
people in black townships near Johannesburg since Aug. 12.
   Black leaders and others have accused police of fueling the
violence by siding with the Inkatha fighters. Police and government
officials have denied the charge, saying some officers may have
acted improperly but that the force as a whole was impartial.
   Police confirmed Saturday they would investigate the
allegations. A police spokesman told the government-operated South
African Broadcasting Co. that witnesses would be interviewed.
   The leftist ANC and more conservative Inkatha blame each other
for the factional fighting. Both groups oppose apartheid but differ
over tactics and plans for a future South Africa.
   The two sides have been fighting for supremacy since 1986 in the
eastern province of Natal. Those battles have resulted in about
5,000 deaths.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900909-0031 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-09-90 1521EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p AM-PrimariesRdp Bjt   09-09 0941</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Primaries Rdp, Bjt,890</SECOND>
<HEAD>Undecided Voters Could Aid Mecham Bid To Return in Arizona</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LARRY LOPEZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PHOENIX (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A large bloc of undecided voters and the
prospects of a low turnout raised Evan Mecham's hopes for an upset
in Arizona's Republican gubernatorial contest, one of 11 primaries
Tuesday that will complete the general election lineups for all but
a handful of states.
   Candidates spent heavily to get their messages on television,
but they were competing for attention with a U.S.-Soviet summit and
the military crisis in the Persian Gulf.
   An election official in Arizona predicted that fewer than 40
percent of the state's Republican voters would cast ballots in the
hotly contested primary between Mecham, whose tumultuous service as
governor ended in 1988 with his impeachment, developer Fife
Symington and three other contenders.
   Former Phoenix Mayor Terry Goddard was heavily favored in the
Democratic gubernatorial primary and was expected to enter the
general election as the front-runner to succeed Gov. Rose Mofford,
a Democrat who is retiring.
   A low turnout also was forecast in Minnesota where Democratic
Gov. Rudy Perpich was battling a strong primary challenge from
former state commerce commissioner Mike Hatch.
   There was a hotly contested GOP primary in Minnesota as well.
State auditor Arne Carlson, businessman Jon Grunseth and former
prosecutor Doug Kelley were competing for the GOP nod. Carlson
surprised party leaders by jumping to a healthy lead in the polls
over Grunseth, who had the organization endorsement.
   The other states holding primaries on Tuesday were Connecticut,
Maryland, New Hampshire, New York, Rhode Island, Utah, Vermont and
Wisconsin. After Tuesday's round of primaries, the only states left
to choose nominees will be Massachusetts, Washington, Oklahoma,
Florida, and Louisiana.
   In the District of Columbia, voters were choosing nominees to
succeed Mayor Marion Barry, whose plans to seek re-election were
sidetracked after his indictment on cocaine possession charges.
   Also on the ballot in the nation's capital was Jesse Jackson.
The two-time candidate for the Democratic presidential nomination
was expected to win nomination easily for the symbolic office of
``shadow senator,'' a position created to press the city's campaign
for statehood.
   Mecham wasn't the only politician seeking to regain an office he
once held.
   Richard Snelling had only minor opposition to his bid for the
GOP nomination for governor of Vermont, an office he gave up in
1984, after serving four two-year terms. His successor, Democrat
Madeleine Kunin, is retiring.
   Former Sen. John Durkin, defeated for re-election in 1980, is
competing with Nashua Mayor James Donchess and businessman John
Rauh in the New Hampshire Democratic Senate primary. Republican
Rep. Bob Smith was heavily favored in the GOP primary for the seat
now held by Republican Sen. Gordon Humphrey, who is retiring.
   Another 1980 Democratic casualty, former Rep. Edward Beard of
Rhode Island, is trying to regain his old House seat, but is locked
in a tough primary with state Sen. John F. Reed.
   One House member in serious danger of being denied renomination
was Rep. Roy Dyson, D-Md. State legislator Barbara Kreamer was
benefiting from the disclosure that the hawkish Dyson was a
conscientious objector during the Vietnam War.
   Several House members also faced primary challenges on Tuesday,
but none was seen as in serious danger.
   Other contests being settled include a three-way race for the
Democratic nomination to challenge Republican Gov. Edward DiPrete
of Rhode Island and a two-way fight for the Democratic nomination
for governor Connecticut.
   The Democratic and GOP nominees for governor of Connecticut
enter the general election race as underdogs to former Republican
Sen. Lowell Weicker, who is running as an independent.
   In Arizona, pre-election polls found more than 40 percent of
potential GOP primary voters saying they remain undecided in the
race for governor.
   Observers speculate that Mecham's supporters tend to be the most
likely to refuse to state their preference when questioned by
pollsters. The prospects for a low turnout also was considered a
plus for the former governor.
   ``If the turnout is under 35 percent, Mecham could win it,''
said Bruce Merrill, director of the Media Research Center at
Arizona State University.
   Voters ``may be confused,'' Mecham said Friday after the last
public debate in the five-way GOP primary for governor. ``They've
listened and been disappointed so very often by politicians.''
   Secretary of State Jim Shumway, a Democrat whose office handles
state elections, predicts a 38 percent GOP turnout but admits ``I'm
being optimistic.''
   The turnout is likely to be much higher _ perhaps as much as 60
percent _ in rural areas where Mecham has fared well in five
previous tries for governor but where there are relatively few
voters.
   Mecham himself has been the hottest issues in the GOP primary.
He was removed from office in April 1988 after his conviction in an
impeachment trial on charges he misused money from supporters and
also interfered with a police investigation of an alleged death
threat by one of his aides.
   During the current campaign, Symington has referred to Mecham's
tenure as a period in which the state was ``the object of national
derision.''
   Equally controversial were Mecham's positions on such issues as
gay rights and a state holiday commemorating slain civil rights
leader Martin Luther King.
   Mecham's hard-core support shrank to about 15 percent or 20
percent of the GOP after his impeachment, but his supporters are
fiercely loyal, vote in large numbers and could triumph if the
anti-Mecham vote is split between the other four candidates.
   Three other GOP candidates, Sam Steiger, Fred Koory and Bob
Barnes, contend that nomination of either Mecham or Symington would
split the party and assure the election of Goddard.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900909-0032 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-09-90 1654EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-WalkingHorses     09-09 0675</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Walking Horses,0695</SECOND>
<HEAD>Court Ruling Could Stop High-Stepping Walking Horses</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By VICKI BROWN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NASHVILLE, Tenn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An appellate court could stop the
high-stepping Tennessee walking horses in their tracks if it
upholds a ban on the bracelet-like chains that trainers use to
produce the animals' distinctive gait.
   The American Horse Protection Association argues the use of the
chains causes pain and swelling in the horses' forelegs and should
be banned.
   Lawyers for the walking horse industry and the U.S. Department
of Agriculture on Tuesday will ask the U.S. Court of Appeals for
the District of Columbia to overrule a lower court ruling that
overturned USDA rules and banned use of the chains.
   ``The AHPA's position is that it's no coincidence `soring' is a
particular problem in the walking horse industry and the walking
horse industry is the only breed which allows chains in the show
ring,'' Russell Gaspar, general counsel for the association, said
last week.
   Trainers say the exaggerated gait is what thrills people, like
the nearly 250,000 spectators who came to Shelbyville, Tenn., last
month during the 10-day Tennessee Walking Horse National
Celebration, the crown jewel of walking horse shows.
   They argue the exaggerated ``Big Lick'' gait can't be achieved
without the 6-ounce chains, which trainers say don't hurt the horse.
   ``I love these horses. They are my whole life,'' said trainer
Gary Edwards of Dawson, Ga. ``I'd love to think half of the kids in
the U.S. get the treatment our horses get.''
   The chains just make the horse want to ``step out of them,''
which produces the high-step, head-shaking walk which makes the
horses so distinctive, Edwards said.
   P.H. ``Buddy'' Payne, executive director of the Walking Horse
Breeders and Exhibitors Association, said the AHPA itself admits
that chains alone don't cause sores. And he said the breeder's
association will argue that U.S. District Judge Oliver Gausch had
no authority to order the ban.
   The USDA adminsters the Horse Protection Act of 1970, which
prohibits the practice of ``soring'' horses by using cruel methods,
devices or chemicals to cause horses pain while walking. An issue
in the lawsuit is whether the use of chains is in itself cruel.
   At present, the USDA allows chains, on the theory that if the
chains are used on sore horses in the show ring, or if chemicals
are placed on the chains to irritate the horses' skin, federal
inspectors will catch the violation and fine the offender.
   Payne said those rules are ``fair and equitable to everyone''
and were written after USDA officials considered hundreds of
written comments and evidence on chains.
   But Gaspar said Gausch was correct in ruling that the USDA never
resolved the issue of soring practices.
   ``There is a substantial body of evidence that USDA inspectors
are not catching all the sore horses,'' Gaspar said. He said chains
combined with chemical irritants create the exaggerated gait by
hurting the horse.
   Gaspar said some believe horses can be taught the gait without
the chains, although Edwards disagreed.
   ``The key is it has to be a talented horse,'' Gaspar said.
``It's been shown that the reason that soring is practiced is to
take a horse of modest talents and make them perform better, as
well as to train a horse to do the Big Lick show gait faster.''
   Edwards said an outright ban on chains would destroy the
industry.
   ``We're not selling horses like we've been selling them, not
getting new people into showing,'' he said. ``Who wants to invest
their savings in something that six months from now might not be
worth a tenth what you paid for it?''
   A spokeswoman for the International Arabian Horse Association in
Denver says the whole horse industry is shifting to the amateur
rider.
   ``The entire industry is experiencing an economic slump, because
horses are a luxury item,'' said Jane Greer, public relations
director for the Arabian association. ``I don't know whether the
chains hurt the horse or not, but I don't think it would be the
death knell for the industry.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900909-0033 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-09-90 1557EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-EllisIsland Bjt   09-09 0656</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Ellis Island, Bjt,0670</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ellis Island: The Immigrants Return</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto staffing</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JUDIE GLAVE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The ``Isle of Tears'' cracked a smile Sunday as
immigrants old and new celebrated the reopening of Ellis Island,
gateway to the New World for the ancestors of two out of five
Americans.
   ``There are thousands of different names, thousands of different
stories, but you stitch all of them together and you have one huge
saga, and it's our saga,'' said Chrysler Chairman Lee Iacocca, who
spearheaded the campaign that raised $156 million to restore the
90-year-old immigration station.
   Before snipping a white ribbon, Vice President Dan Quayle linked
the nation's immigrant history to the crisis in the Persian Gulf.
There, he said, ``children of Mexicans or Kenyans stand shoulder to
shoulder with the grandchildren of Japanese or French, next to the
great-grandchildren of Poles or Dutch _ now Americans all.''
   ``What we celebrate in Ellis Island is nothing less than the
triumph of the American spirit,'' Quayle said. ``We may all know in
our minds that time and time again, it has been the immigrant who
has renewed and rekindled the American spirit. But here in Ellis
Island, we feel it in our hearts.''
   About 2,500 guests gathered outside the huge, four-towered brick
building that reopens to the public Monday as a museum and memorial
following six years of work.
   The restoration project, the most expensive of its kind in
American history, was entirely financed by private contributions to
the Statue of Liberty-Ellis Island Foundation.
   Forty-nine new citizens, including three children, were sworn in
by Supreme Court Justice Antonin Scalia, and six people who entered
the nation through Ellis in the first quarter of the century were
singled out to represent the millions of immigrants who passed
through the island.
   They included Johanna Flaherty, 84, who said she left her native
Ireland in 1923 because she ``didn't want to wake up and stare a
cow in the face every morning.'' Another was Clara Larsen, who came
from Russia in 1913 because she wanted to get an education.
   ``In Russia, the Jewish kids didn't stand a chance,'' she
recalled. ``They didn't accept them in the public schools.'' She
went on to become an early leader of the International Ladies
Garment Workers Union.
   Immigrants' contributions were celebrated throughout the
program, down to the music; the U.S. Army Band played selections by
Irving Berlin, who came through Ellis as a child.
   Iacocca dedicated the American Immigrant Wall of Honor, which
bears the names of about 2,000 immigrants whose descendants donated
$100 or more to the renovation effort. The names are inscribed on a
long copper strip on the island's seawall, about 400 yards from the
Statue of Liberty.
   One of the names was that of Antonio Macchiarola, 80, of
Johnston, R.I., who arrived at age 11.
   In retrospect, Macchiarola said, it all seems ``like a
pilgrimage. ... I was just a little bit of a kid and I had to go
through these lines to be examined. Everybody was afraid they
wouldn't make it.''
   Macchiarola did, like 98 percent of those who landed at Ellis.
But for those who were turned back _ including a little girl who
traveled with his family and was rejected because of eye disease _
Ellis was called the Isle of Tears.
   The federal government bought the 27.5-acre island in the late
1800s for about $10,000 from the descendants of a man named Samuel
Ellis. It opened the first immigration station on the island in
1892, but the building burned down five years later.
   Its replacement was finished in 1900, a building designed to
impress immigrants with its ornate copper domes, vast windows and
vaulted ceilings.
   Between 1892 and 1924, when Ellis was the nation's busiest port
of entry, an average of 5,000 people a day passed through. On the
busiest day _ April 17, 1907 _ 11,747 immigrants were processed.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900909-0034 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-09-90 1601EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Liberia 1stAdd a0745 09-09 0147</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Liberia, 1st Add, a0745,0149</SECOND>
<HEAD>MONROVIA: civil war.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Liberia now has three people who claim to be its president: Doe,
Johnson and Charles Taylor, leader of the mainstream rebel National
Patriotic Front.
   Liberia's 8-month-old civil war began Dec. 24 when Johnson
helped lead rebels loyal to Taylor in an invasion from Ivory Coast.
In March, Johnson broke away to form his own faction.
   Sunday's capture of Doe came amid confusion after Taylor's
rebels had attacked West African troops in the port Saturday with
shells and gunfire.
   Some of the 3,000 soldiers in the five-nation West African army
sent to enforce a cease-fire held off the rebels. The West African
task force on Friday had called for aid agencies to return to
Monrovia and promised to assure their safety.
   American government and European disaster relief workers were
flown into the besieged city Saturday by U.S. Marines.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900909-0035 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-09-90 1615EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Summit-ArmsControl     09-09 0840</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Summit-Arms Control,820</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush, Gorbachev Pledge to Push Arms Control Negotiators</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SALLY JACOBSEN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HELSINKI, Finland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush and Soviet leader
Mikhail Gorbachev pledged Sunday to speed up arms control
negotiations, hoping for agreement by year's end to slash both
nuclear and non-nuclear weapons.
   But the leaders, wrapping up their one-day summit, gave no clues
on whether either side had put forth fresh proposals that would
advance the twin sets of talks.
   Secretary of State James A. Baker III later raised the
possibility that negotiators might drop the contentious issue of
placing limits on combat aircraft to win early agreement on cutting
conventional weapons in Europe.
   ``There's quite a bit of difference between us still on
aircraft, and it may be that ... we'll have to proceed with
everything we can do ... and save aircraft for a later time,''
Baker said in an interview on Cable News Network's Newsmaker Sunday
program.
   But he said no final decision has yet been made.
   The issue of aircraft ceilings is the most difficult for
East-West negotiators bargaining on a treaty to slash troops, tanks
and other conventional, or non-nuclear, arms in Europe.
   At a joint news conference, Bush said he and Gorbachev ``vowed
that we would encourage our negotiators to move forward more
rapidly on both the strategic arms treaty and the conventional
force agreement.''
   Gorbachev added that the officials agreed they would ``make
fresh efforts to give further instructions'' to their bargainers.
   Both said they were hopeful agreement could be reached by the
end of the year. But others have said the slow pace of the
negotiations has raised concern the deadline could be missed.
   Baker said the leaders stressed the importance of gaining a
conventional arms treaty before the opening of a 35-nation summit
of the Conference on Security and Cooperation in Europe. French
officials already have begun plans to hold the gathering Nov. 19-21
in Paris.
   Bush has said he will not attend the summit unless the treaty is
wrapped up by then.
   The second set of negotiations, designed to win a Strategic Arms
Reduction Treaty, would slash the superpowers' holdings of
long-range nuclear weapons by about 30 percent. It would be the
first-ever negotiated cut in this category of weapons.
   The Conventional Forces in Europe talks have been on a fast
track since they opened in March 1989 between negotiators for the
16 nations of the North Atlantic Treaty Organization and the seven
of the Soviet-led Warsaw Pact.
   They were designed to bring both sides to equal ceilings in main
battle tanks, armored combat vehicles, artillery, troops, combat
aircraft and attack helicopters. The West's aim is to cripple the
Soviets' ability to mount a lightning attack on European countries.
   Negotiators for the 23 nations have reached agreement on
numerical ceilings and definitions for equipment covered in only
two areas _ main battle tanks and armored combat vehicles. They are
considered close on artillery and not too far apart on attack
helicopters.
   But they have made little headway in their talks on reducing
combat aircraft because of sharp differences over what should be
covered in that category.
   The United States wants to include in the count planes that are
based on land but are used in naval operations. The Kremlin has
said no. It has offered proposals that would exempt large numbers
of land-based naval planes from the accord.
   Baker said the United States was not willing to put off the
aircraft issue unless its NATO allies agreed.
   ``If they would join in, we would have to give some
consideration to that, because we think it's important to lock in
the other elements of the treaty,'' he told the CNN interviewers.
   The arms bargaining also has snagged over reductions in troops
in Europe.
   Moscow and Washington settled on a plan earlier this year to
trim their forces to 195,000 for each side in central Europe, with
the United States retaining an additional 30,000 in Britain and
southern Europe.
   But it is unclear whether that accord still holds.
   A NATO official, speaking in advance of the weekend summit, said
the Soviets have said the upheavals in Eastern Europe have made the
troop caps outdated. With the diminished military threat, the
number of soldiers stationed in central Europe by the superpowers
might well be below those limits.
   During the summer, the Soviets mentioned a possible ceiling of
70,000 to 80,000 soldiers for each superpower in Europe, said the
official, who demanded anonymity. But they recently renewed their
interest in the earlier cap of 195,000 troops.
   ``They have put up so many proposals now that we're uncertain
what one they really want,'' said a Western diplomat in Vienna,
where the negotiations are being held.
   The two sides so far have agreed to limit main battle tanks to
20,000 for each side, a cap that will require the Soviet Union to
get rid of tens of thousands of the heavy giants in Europe.
   They also have decided to cap armored combat vehicles at 30,000
on each side.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900909-0036 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-09-90 2022EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Brazil-MassGrave     09-09 0596</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brazil-Mass Grave,0614</SECOND>
<HEAD>Discovery of Mass Grave Renews Questions About Amnesty for Killers</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP Extra</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KEN SILVERSTEIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>RIO DE JANEIRO, Brazil (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The discovery of a clandestine
mass grave containing more than 1,700 bodies, some apparently of
political opponents of Brazil's former military rulers, has stirred
many painful memories.
   Although an amnesty passed by the former military dictatorship
bars trying anyone for involvment in the deaths, activists are
demanding a full investigation.
   ``The construction of a state of law and democracy demands the
truth ... is fully told,'' said a statement issued last week by two
human rights groups.
   ``This necessity is even greater in Brazil because the amnesty
eliminated the possibility that those responsible for torture and
assassinations would be held accountable for their actions,'' the
statement said.
   The grave, discovered Tuesday in Perus on the outskirts of Sao
Paulo, contained mostly the remains of paupers. But an estimated 50
of the dead are believed to be former enemies of the military
government that ruled from 1964 to 1985.
   Some of the skeletons unearthed had damaged skulls from gunshot
wounds to the head, and human rights officials say the people were
summarily executed. A pacemaker and platinum dental work also
indicated that not all the remains were those of paupers.
   Sao Paulo Mayor Luiza Erundina said records at three other city
graveyards would be checked this week to see if other military
``enemies'' were buried there.
   Unlike some South American countries, Brazil never fully
investigated human rights abuses that occurred under military rule.
   In Argentina, a full public accounting of the crimes of the
1976-1982 dictatorship took place. Five former junta members later
were found guilty of murder and human rights violations.
   Uruguay returned to civilian rule in 1985 after nine years of
military dictatorship. A nationwide referendum was held there on
revoking the military's self-approved amnesty, and after much
public debate the amnesty was narrowly upheld.
   Brazil's dictatorship was not as brutal as some in the region,
but it systematically violated human rights. Rights groups say
about 200 people were killed in Brazil, 150 disappeared and
thousands were tortured.
   Many people with leftist sympathies were exiled.
   However, a key to the 1985 return of civilian rule, which was
negotiated among the generals and civilian politicians, was the
understanding there would be no investigations or trials of former
military officials.
   ``That agreement allowed the civilians to take charge and
provided them with some stability,'' said political science
professor David Fleischer, who worked in Brazil's Senate during the
transition period.
   ``But it also had a negative side: The military maintained great
influence, and there was no definitive rupture with the past,'' he
said.
   One direct result was that hundreds of those directly involved
in torture and human rights violations retained their positions in
the police and armed forces.
   President Fernando Collor de Mello, who took office in March as
Brazil's first directly elected president since 1960, promised to
abolish the National Intelligence Service, the former
dictatorship's secret police force, which was involved in
repression of civilians.
   Instead, he renamed the agency and put a civilian in charge, but
it continues to spy on the population.
   Some people hope the discovery of the mass grave leads to a
renewed interest in fully airing abuses committed during the
military rule.
   ``The truth is a moral sanction,'' wrote prominent political
columnist Clovis Rossi in the Folha de Sao Paulo newspaper. ``The
widows, the orphans and the brothers and sisters of the victims
have the right to know who killed their loved ones.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900909-0037 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-09-90 1642EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Gulf-SaudiVolunteers     09-09 0409</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Saudi Volunteers,0429</SECOND>
<HEAD>Saudis Volunteer To Beef Up Military Reserves</HEAD>
<HEAD>With Gulf Rdp, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOAN MOWER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DHAHRAN, Saudi Arabia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Thousands of volunteers, from
fresh-faced teens to white-haired seniors, have stepped forward for
military training as Saudi Arabia seeks to beef up its army
reserves, officials said Sunday.
   With many of the regular Saudi Army troops deployed to the
nation's northern border following Iraq's Aug. 2 invasion of
Kuwait, military officials are looking to boost backup forces.
   The all-male Saudi volunteer units function like U.S.
reservists, some of whom were called to Saudi Arabia along with
regular American troops.
   The Saudi volunteers train for two hours a day over four weeks,
primarily drilling and training with weapons. Regular Saudi Army
recruits undergo six months of training.
   The volunteers hold down regular jobs, live at home and will be
called up only if needed.
   Because of their brief training program, Saudi military
officials said it is unlikely the volunteers will ever see combat.
   But a captain, who spoke on condition of anonymity, said he
would have no qualms about putting the men into battle.
   ``They have to be deployed when the need is there,'' he said.
   The Saudi Army has about 37,000 troops, but King Fahd has
pledged to build up the nation's fighting force.
   At one military training base, new volunteers clad in fresh
khakis practiced basic drill steps as sergeants yelled out commands.
   Most of the men had boots, but some wore their sneakers. They
often made missteps.
   Although the Saudis have age limits for volunteers, from 16 to
40, officials made exceptions for those who were particularly keen.
They stressed, however, the younger and older men would not go to
battle.
   ``I joined yesterday,'' said 14-year-old Mohammed Al-Akassa, an
eighth-grader spending his first day on the drill field.
   ``I've never had a uniform like this before,'' he said.
   The boy said he wanted to learn to use a gun, even though that
was not the reason he joined the volunteers.
   ``It's my duty to my country,'' he said.
   Mohammed Abdullah Al-Mubarak, who said he's more than 70 years
old, joined for similiar reasons.
   ``I want to protect myself and my country,'' the white-bearded
man said through an interpreter.
   A former seaman, Al-Mubarak insisted he could keep up with the
younger men, and he said he wanted to learn to shoot.
   ``I don't want to be in the back line,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900909-0038 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-09-90 2009EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-WestwoodWoes     09-09 0665</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Westwood Woes,0686</SECOND>
<HEAD>Street Violence Sparks Swift Response in Popular Westwood</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Summer of Crime, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MICHAEL FLEEMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Shish kebobs used to sell like hot cakes on
Friday and Saturday nights at Emad Ahmadie's Shish Kabob Grill in
trendy Westwood Village.
   But not anymore.
   The city has barricaded major streets on those nights to cut
traffic and prevent the gathering of unruly crowds, cooling down
what has long been one of the city's hottest destinations for a
night out.
   ``Last night, we had to eat all the food ourselves so it
wouldn't go bad,'' Ahmadie said on the Tuesday after Labor Day
Weekend. ``I wish things would go back to how they were.''
   The village, a neighborhood of Los Angeles, is a compact cluster
of movie theaters, restaurants, bars, bookstores, boutiques and
other shops outside the main entrance to the University of
California, Los Angeles.
   Surrounded by the pricey districts of Brentwood, Bel-Air,
Century City and just west of the posh Los Angeles Country Club and
Beverly Hills, the village seems far from the city's troubled areas.
   So when trouble happens, the city takes notice. And that brings
charges from poorer parts of the city of favoritism, possibly
racially motivated.
   It happened in 1988 when a gang fight erupted and a bystander
was killed by a stray bullet. The killing triggered an outcry for
police action.
   And trouble's happened again this summer. A scuffle Aug. 3 by
about 60 youths, many of whom had come to see the opening of Spike
Lee's ``Mo' Better Blues,'' ended in three injuries and nine
arrests.
   Though the injuries were not serious _ and on the same weekend
murders and other violent crimes were committed elsewhere in the
city _ the ``Westwood melee,'' as the media called it, got lots of
attention.
   Councilman Zev Yaroslavsky called for the city to put up
barricades on major streets. Barriers had been used on a limited
scale before, and expanding their use had been considered for some
time.
   The barricades went up Aug. 24 and are expected to remain on
Friday and Saturday nights indefinitely.
   ``When more people are on the sidewalk, they start jostling one
another,'' Yaroslavsky said. ``People's attitudes change. They get
more defensive. They get more edgy. The atmosphere all over gets
more negative in what should be a more positive place.''
   For many merchants, the traffic blockades spelled disaster.
Restaurants reported that receipts were down as much as fivefold.
   Yaroslavsky said that in the long run the barriers will make
Westwood a better community, but some say he's fighting a losing
battle.
   ``There could be other ways of controlling what they're trying
to control,'' said Steve Fulton, a manager of Westwood Drugs. ``But
maybe they shouldn't try. Westwood is changing. Instead of getting
the Bel-Air, Beverly Hills, Brentwood crowd, you're getting more of
the kids running around.''
   The city's response to trouble in Westwood has a history of
controversy.
   The 1988 killing brought widespread attention to gang violence
and prompted the city to put more officers on patrol in Westwood.
Yaroslavsky called for the city to post a $25,000 reward, police
were flooded with calls, and a reputed gang member was convicted of
murder.
   But all that activity raised the ire of leaders in the eastside
and south-central areas where gangs have been rampant for years.
They accused police, the media and other politicians of white
favoritism by giving more attention to a crime in an upscale white
area than in a poor, minority neighborhood.
   Yaroslavsky and other officials contended that similar
anti-crime efforts have been made in poorer areas.
   Mark Ridley-Thomas, head of the Southern Christian Leadership
Conference office in Los Angeles, said complicated forces were at
work in the responses to the gang shooting and barricade cases.
   ``But what it always seems is that one part of the city is more
valuable than another, as subtle or as overt as some of that may
be,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900909-0039 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-09-90 1702EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Gulf-Iran-Iraq 1stLd-Writethru a0726 09-09 0768</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Iran-Iraq, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0726,0791</SECOND>
<HEAD>First Iraqi Trip To Iran Since War In Effort To Mend Ties</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf Rdp, Bjt</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 11 grafs to ADD remarks by Iranian parliament
speaker warning of possible terrorist attacks if U.S. forces remain
in gulf; pickup 7th graf pvs. `The two...'
^LaserPhoto TEH1</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By SLOBODAN LEKIC</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TEHRAN, Iran (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Iraq's foreign minister Sunday reportedly
sought to break the U.N. trade embargo over his nation's occupation
of Kuwait during Iraq's first official visit to Iran in a decade.
   Iraqi Foreign Minister Tariq Aziz met with his Iranian
counterpart, Ali Akbar Velayati, amid unconfirmed reports that rice
and flour shipments already were passing over Iraq's northeastern
border from Iran.
   Aziz told reporters the 2{-hour meeting was ``constructive.''
The eight-year Iran-Iraq war was halted in 1988 by a cease-fire but
the countries have never reached a peace settlement.
   Velayati repeated Iran's condemnation of Iraq's seizure of
Kuwait last month, but he also criticized the presence of U.S. and
other foreign forces building up in the Persian Gulf, according to
Iran's official Islamic Republic News Agency.
   It was not known whether Aziz would hold further talks before
his departure Monday.
   In a related development, Iran's radical Parliament speaker,
Mehdi Karrubi, warned of possible attacks by Moslem terrorists if
U.S. troops remain in the gulf region, IRNA said.
   The news agency quoted Karrubi as saying ``the United States ...
would be driven out of the region, humiliated by Moslems, if it
intended to remain there.''
   ``The United States should know that it will never enjoy
security in the Persian Gulf,'' he said.
   Pro-Iranian Shiite Moslem groups have been linked to hijackings,
bombings of U.S. Marines in Lebanon and the holding of 13 Western
hostages, including six Americans, in Lebanon.
   Karrubi said he was concerned the United States intends to keep
troops in the region even if the Iraqis withdrew from Kuwait.
   Aziz's visit, the first such contact between Iran and Iraq since
before the Iran-Iraq war, has been publicized as groundwork for a
meeting between Iraqi President Saddam Hussein and Iranian
President Hashemi Rafsanjani.
   The two are expected to meet for a peace treaty officially
ending the hostilities between the two nations.
   The overtures could free up hundreds of thousands of Iraqi
troops stationed along the 750-mile Iranian border. They could
presumably be used to confront U.S. forces in Saudi Arabia.
   Talks on a formal treaty after the 1988 cease-fire were mired in
dispute. But after Iraq's Aug. 2 invasion of Kuwait prompted U.S.
and other forces to rush to the region, Saddam began withdrawing
troops from Iranian territory and exchanging prisoners with Iran.
   Saddam agreed to respect a 1975 treaty splitting the waters of
the vital Shatt-al-Arab waterway, a key outlet to the sea for Iraq
and a major sticking point in the peace talks.
   Tehran sources said Aziz was expected to ask Iranian officials
to allow shipment of food and medicine to Iraq.
   ``The aid in food and medicines that Iran could provide could be
of crucial important at this stage,'' said a diplomat, speaking on
condition of anonymity.
   But U.N. sanctions imposed on Iraq permit only humanitarian
shipments of food and medicine.
   ``There is no reason to believe that Iran would agree to supply
Iraq with anything more than that because that would constitute
sanctions busting,'' the diplomat said.
   Aziz was accompanied by Iraqi Oil Minister Issam Abdul-Rahim
Al-Shalabi, and Iranian Oil Minister Gholamreza Aqazadeh was part
of the welcoming committee at Mehrabad Airport.
   The presence of the two oil ministers could signify an Iranian
solution to Iraq's inability to export its oil, the country's
primary source of income.
   Iran' pipeline running to the Kharg Island Terminal at the
northern end of the Persian Gulf could be refitted to carry Iraqi
oil from over the nearby border, sources said.
   But the diplomat in Tehran doubted whether Iran would risk
international condemnation by doing such a valuable service for its
former enemy.
   ``What could Aziz possibly offer them in return for that?'' said
the diplomat.
   Iraq has been seeking governments that would be willing to help
it get around the U.N. sanctions. Its tiny coastline is effectively
blocked by the multinational fleet in the gulf.
   Middle East observers say that in advance of Aziz's trip, envoys
from Yemen, Jordan and the Palestine Liberation Organization
visited Tehran to seek Iranian assistance in breaking Iraq's
economic isolation.
   Aziz was surrounded by tight security on his visit. A Christian
in an overwhelmingly Moslem region, Aziz survived an assassination
attempt in 1980 by Shiite Moslem Iraqis who sided with Shiite Iran.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900909-0040 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-09-90 2041EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Gulf-Congressmen     09-09 0301</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Congressmen,300</SECOND>
<HEAD>Returning Congressmen Say Embargoes Could Topple Saddam</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ALAN FRAM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ANDREWS AIR FORCE BASE, Md. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The economic and military
embargoes in place against Iraq could topple Saddam Hussein,
perhaps in two months, congressmen returning from the Middle East
said Sunday.
   ``The officials we spoke with all felt that he had been weakened
by the long, costly Iran-Iraq war, the subsequent settlement with
Iran ... and his miscalculation in invading Kuwait,'' said Rep.
John Murtha, D-Pa., chairman of the House Appropriations defense
subcommittee.
   Murtha and nine other lawmakers visited Saudi Arabian King Fahd,
Egyptian President Hosni Mubarak, some exiled Kuwaiti officials,
and U.S. military commanders and troops in the field during their
five-day trip.
   The consensus among the rulers they met with was that Saddam,
the Iraqi ruler, would remain in power for two more months, Murtha
said.
   ``In that part of the world, the insinuations were there are
other methods of removing dictators from their positions of power,
other than caving in,'' said Murtha, who would not elaborate.
   Murtha, whose subcommittee oversees military spending, said he
could not estimate how much the U.S. deployment in the gulf will
cost.
   He also said that military equipment was working surprisingly
well in the hot, sandy Saudi desert.
   ``You can't see 25 or 30 yards in front of you,'' Murtha said of
the dusty conditions at the front lines. ``Equipment has to be
maintained constantly. They sleep in the sand beside their
equipment. Yet even with those difficulties, morale is very high.''
   The congressman said that he and his colleagues wore military
uniforms one day to test their comfort and found them acceptable.
   He did say, however, that a lot of sand penetrated the boots and
that officials have discussed sending different ones to the troops.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900909-0041 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-09-90 2041EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Britain-Thatcher     09-09 0205</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Britain-Thatcher,0212</SECOND>
<HEAD>Thatcher May Stay in Office Another Five Years</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher said Sunday she
may stay in office another five years and would not rule out being
prime minister at the age of 70.
   ``I am not immortal, but I've got a lot left in me yet,'' said
Mrs. Thatcher, who will be 65 next month.
   ``Some people started their administration at the age of 70,''
she said in an Independent Television interview.
   Mrs. Thatcher said she wanted to lead the party into the next
election, which must be called in 1991 or 1992.
   But, the prime minister told interviewer David Frost, ``I am not
going to give you the chance to say that she is going to go on and
on and on.''
   She was first elected Conservative Party leader in 1975 and came
to power when her Conservative Party won in the 1979 general
election. She since has led the party to two general election
victories.
   But this summer the Conservatives have trailed the left-leaning
Labor Party in the polls after an unpopular per-capita tax was
instituted in April. The tax sparked violence in London and other
cities. Homeowners have been hurt by high interest rates.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900909-0042 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-09-90 1742EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Israel-Uprising 1stLd-Writethru   09-09 0431</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel-Uprising, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0703,0440</SECOND>
<HEAD>Soldiers Kill Palestinian Youth, First Killing in Weeks</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS thruout to UPDATE with Palestinian youth reported slain
by troops; DROPS pvs grafs 5-17 bgng `Meanwhile authorities....' to
TRIM. No pickup.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Israeli soldiers shot and killed a Palestinian
youth Sunday in the first lethal clash between troops and
stone-throwing activists in three weeks, Arab reports said.
   The clash in the West Bank village of Beita came as Palestinians
throughout the occupied lands observed a general strike marking 33
months since the start of their uprising against Israel.
   The military command confirmed that an 18-year-old Arab had been
killed in Beita but said the army was checking the cause of death.
``He was killed by gunfire of unknown origin in the back,'' a
command spokesman said.
   The spokesman added that soldiers had opened fire with rubber
bullets to disperse stone-throwing youths in Beita, six miles from
the West Bank's largest city of Nablus. It was unclear whether the
victim was killed in that clash, the spokesman said.
   Palestinian reporters identified the victim as 17-year-old Ahmad
Abu Seif, saying he died after soldiers shot him in the chest while
chasing a group of stone-throwers into a field in Beita.
   About 2,000 villagers later buried the teen-ager in a nighttime
funeral, his body draped in a black-green-red and white Palestinian
flag, the reporters added.
   Abu Seif was the 729th Palestinian killed by Israelis during the
revolt that began Dec. 8, 1987. The Palestinians are fighting
Israel's occupation of the West Bank and Gaza Strip since 1967.
   Sunday's death was also the first uprising fatality caused by
Israelis since Aug. 19. During the summer months, most uprising
victims were slain by fellow Palestinians as alleged collaborators
with Israel.
   In all, 258 Palestinians have been killed by fellow Arabs on
such charges during the uprising. Fifty-one Israelis and foreigners
have been slain by Palestinians during the unrest.
   In another development in Jerusalem, a police investigating team
has recommended putting nine policemen on trial for allegedly
torturing Palestinian inmates in Jerusalem's main jail, Israeli
newspapers reported.
   National Police spokesman Ron Yishayahu confirmed an inquiry was
under way into charges of abuse at Jerusalem's main jail, but he
declined to provide additional details.
   Three Israeli newspapers reported that top officials ordered
further examination of physical evidence of torture following the
panel's recommendation in favor of charges.
   The internal police investigation was started after the Israeli
human rights group Betselem claimed Palestinians were being
tortured and one inmate testified he falsely confessed to murder
after being severely beaten, the newspapers reported.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900909-0043 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-09-90 2254EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>d a AM-BRF--SwampFire     09-09 0193</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Swamp Fire,0198</SECOND>
<HEAD>Calm Winds Slow Progress of Okefenokee Fire</HEAD>
<DATELINE>FARGO, Ga. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A fire sparked by lightning more than a week
ago has consumed 2,300 acres of the Okefenokee National Wildlife
Refuge, but calm weather kept it from spreading Sunday, a spokesman
said.
   ``The fire is just creeping along right now because winds are so
light and variable,'' said Jim Burkhart, fire information officer
for the 400,000-acre swamp refuge in southeast Georgia.
   More than 180 firefighters battled the blaze.
   The fire began in the swamp's west end and spread east toward
Honey Island and Billy's Island, he said.
   Billy's Island is a habitat for the endangered red cockaded
woodpecker. Firefighters dug breaks in an effort to protect the
birds, he said.
   Three fires since May have burned a total of 9,500 acres in the
refuge, and the typically driest months of the year _ October and
November _ are still ahead.
   Researchers say fires keep the swamp from turning into a bog.
The swamp fills with vegetation that turns into peat, which the
fire helps clear. But too much uncontrolled burning could destroy
the swamp and its inhabitants, they say.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900909-0044 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-09-90 2100EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brite-FirstCoupleBikers     09-09 0213</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brite-First Couple Bikers,0218</SECOND>
<HEAD>Maine's First Couple Lead Thousands of Bikers Through Capital</HEAD>
<DATELINE>AUGUSTA, Maine (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   It took some prodding from his
congresswoman wife, but Maine's governor hopped on the back of a
thundering motorcycle Sunday to lead thousands of leather-clad
bikers in an annual charity run.
   Gov. John R. McKernan, known for his annual tea parties that
draw scores of motorcyclists to the executive mansion, had shied
away from riding one of the big machines in past ``toys for tots''
runs through the state capital.
   But some gentle persuasion by his wife, U.S. Rep. Olympia J.
Snowe, R-Maine, who once had a motorcycle learner's permit, changed
that.
   ``I had to marry the governor to get him to ride a bike,'' Snowe
told the crowd at the Capitol Complex after she and her husband
finished their two-mile jaunt.
   McKernan rode on the back of a motorcycle driven by Carlie
Snowe, the congresswoman's former father-in-law, and she rode on
one driven by Ken Monroe.
   The estimated 10,000 motorcyclists filled two trucks with
Christmas presents for needy children.
   Jim Paterson, the Harley-Davidson motorcycle company president
who attends similar events all over the country, was impressed by
McKernan's presence.
   ``It's the only one where I've ridden behind a governor on a
Harley,'' said Paterson.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900909-0045 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-09-90 2105EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-NortonTaxes 2ndLd-Writethru a0747 09-09 0350</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Norton Taxes, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0747,320</SECOND>
<HEAD>House Delegate Nominee Won't Quit Race Despite Tax Problems</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: New throughout with comments from Norton's opponent,
endorsements, ADDS byline.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By RICHARD KEIL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Eleanor Holmes Norton, the leading candidate
for Washington's non-voting congressional seat, has no plans to
drop out of the race despite disclosures she and her husband filed
no local income tax returns from 1982 to 1989, an aide said Sunday.
   The former Carter administration official has said she did not
realize her husband did not mail the returns.
   Withdrawal is ``absolutely out of the question,'' Norton
spokeswoman Gwen McKinney said Sunday. ``I'm not going to say it
won't affect the undecided voters, but we have found that the
support we have received is phenomenal.''
   But an influential city councilman who had remained neutral on
the race endorsed one of Norton's opponents Sunday and called on
Norton to withdraw.
   ``The message I am receiving, from my constituents, is that we
cannot elect someone who has a cloud over them,'' said councilman
James Nathanson, who endorsed Betty Ann Kane.
   Norton, who headed the U.S. Equal Employment Opportunity
Commission during the Carter administration, said she signed the
District of Columbia tax returns for the years in question and did
not realize until Saturday that her husband had not mailed them.
   ``I hope that the people of the district, who have been
exceedingly generous to me during this campaign ... will understand
the matter for what it is _ a human failing and not a deliberate
attempt to circumvent responsibility,'' she said, blaming the lapse
on ``procrastination'' and a dispute with the city over the amount
of taxes owed in 1982.
   Her husband, Edward Norton, is a lawyer and former chairman of
the D.C. board of Elections and Ethics.
   The candidate's spokeswoman said an accountant working on
Norton's taxes concluded that $49,593.63 in city taxes withheld by
the city from 1982 until 1989 will satisfy Norton's actual tax
obligation.
   ``The problem now is with interest and penalties,'' McKinney
said. She declined to say how much more Norton owes.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900909-0046 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-09-90 1820EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-WeatherpageWeather     09-09 0323</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Weatherpage Weather,0333</SECOND>
<HEAD>Thunderstorms Most Numerous Over Texas</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Thunderstorms produced locally heavy rain over parts of Texas on
Sunday, and rain was broadly scattered over much of the rest of the
eastern two-thirds of the nation.
   Showers and thunderstorms developed in response to several weak
upper level weather disturbances over much of central and eastern
Texas. Thunderstorms in central Texas produced more than 2 inches
of rain in Bell County and Falls County, the National Weather
Service said.
   Thunderstorms also produced locally heavy rain in Ohio early in
the morning, with heavier rainfall totals during the six hours up
to 8 a.m. EDT including 1.16 inches at Findlay and 1.03 inches at
Cleveland.
   A few showers and thunderstorms developed along a cold front
over eastern Minnesota and northern Wisconsin, and more were
scattered from Kentucky to New York state.
   Showers and thunderstorms also extended across parts of
Louisiana and Mississippi.
   Isolated showers and thunderstorms spread over southern Missouri
and northern Arkansas, over the central Plains, and were scattered
over the Southeast.
   Heavier rainfall totals during the six hours up to 2 p.m. EDT
were 1.01 inches at Columbus, Ohio, and an even 1.00 inch at
Killeen, Texas.
   Temperatures warmed into the 90s in much of the Southeast and
climbed above 90 in Oklahoma and the central Plains. Miami Beach,
Fla., cooled only to an overnight low of 82.
   In the desert Southwest, Palm Springs, Calif., had already hit
110 by noon local time.
   Overnight temperatures dropped into the 40s across parts of
North Dakota, New York state, New Jersey, eastern Pennsylvania and
southern New England, and into the 30s over parts of northern New
England.
   In Alaska, Kotzebue dipped to 32, a record for the date. It was
the first time the town, off the Bering Strait just above the
Arctic Circle, hit freezing since June 3.
   Sunday's low for the Lower 48 was 32 at Gunnison, Colo.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900909-0047 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-09-90 2114EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ImmigrantItems     09-09 0401</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Immigrant Items,0411</SECOND>
<HEAD>Immigrant Museum: Elevating the Ordinary</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Ellis Island, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JUDIE GLAVE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A show at once ordinary and extraordinary opened
Sunday on Ellis Island, where the ``Treasures from Home'' exhibit
elevated the most mundane of immigrants' possessions to museum
pieces.
   The exhibit comprises scores of objects on loan from the
families of immigrants who passed through Ellis between 1892 and
1954. They reflect the desire to make the Ellis Island Immigration
Museum what chief curator Diana Pardue calls ``everyman's museum.''
   The first day's visitors, many of whom had donated objects to
the collection, cried and cheered as they spotted their family
heirlooms, newly enshrined behind glass.
   Items ranged from the relatively exotic, such as a formal
Aragonese dress fan from end-of-the-century Spain, to passports and
other travel documents.
   The tone of the exhibit is set by a poster-sized excerpt from a
letter written by Sam Auspitz, a Jew who emigrated from eastern
Europe in 1920: ``My mother brought her candles, the ones you use
on Friday night. She brought the things that were near and dear to
us, which were not very important to anybody but us.''
   Among the donors was Herman Gold, 82, of Chester, Pa., who
arrived from the Ukraine in 1924. He stared at his father's old
passport and recalled spending three long weeks on the island when
he was 16.
   Doctors had detained the whole family after they discovered a
suspicious looking fungus on his father's fingernail.
   ``I remember it was cold as hell at night,'' he said. ``They
gave us a blanket, but at night someone would always come and sneak
and pull it out from under you. That's what I remember best _
freezing to death.''
   A pair of elderly sisters, Anne and Mary Lipozac, stood talking
excitedly next to a display case filled with objects their mother
brought from Croatia in her hope chest.
   Its contents included china, christening bonnets, linens,
hand-crocheted socks and a tiny loop of beads that was thought to
cure sore throats.
   The sisters said they regretted that their sister Amy, who
helped assemble the collection, died before she could see it
encased on Ellis Island.
   ``I look at this and I can only hope and pray that Amy and Mama
and Papa know how valuable this has become,'' said Mary Lipozac,
her eyes brimming. ``Mama would be overwhelmed.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900909-0048 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-09-90 2115EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-NYCPoll     09-09 0220</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-NYC Poll,0225</SECOND>
<HEAD>Most New Yorkers Say You Have to Be a Little Crazy</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Summer of Crime, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Six out of 10 New Yorkers say they would live
elsewhere if they could, and three-quarters describe the city as
dangerous and dirty, according to a poll published Sunday.
   The Time magazine-Cable News Network poll asked 1,009 residents:
``If you could choose where you live, would you stay in New York
City or move somewhere else?'' According to the results, 59 percent
would be ex-New Yorkers, and 37 percent would stay.
   The poll, conducted Aug. 2-5, has a margin of error of plus or
minus 3 percent.
   Asked if the quality of life had become better in the past few
years, 7 percent said yes. Sixty-eight percent said things were
worse.
   Twice as many New Yorkers said things would get still worse as
said things would get better _ 45 percent to 23 percent.
   Asked if New York was dirty, 78 percent said yes. Dangerous?
Yes, said 73 percent. On the other hand, 54 percent described New
York as a city they like to live in.
   That may be explained by the response to the statement: ``To
live in New York City, people must be a little crazy.'' More than
half _ 52 percent _ agreed.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900909-0049 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-09-90 1945EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Pope     09-09 0720</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Pope,0744</SECOND>
<HEAD>Pope Arrives in Ivory Coast to Consecrate World's Largest Church</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT WELLER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>YAMOUSSOUKRO, Ivory Coast (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Pope John Paul II arrived
Sunday to consecrate the biggest Christian church in the world, a
basilica that rivals the grandeur of St. Peter's. Oppponents say
the country can't afford it.
   Heavy security was in place around Yamoussoukro, the native town
of President Felix Houphouet-Boigny, to prevent anti-government
demonstrations by recently legalized opposition parties.
   Architect Pierre Fakhoury defended construction of the church in
a country where Roman Catholics are estimated to make up less than
15 percent of the 10 million people. Most of the people are
animists and Moslems.
   ``The president swore he would give God the biggest and most
beautiful church he could,'' he told reporters.
   On Thursday, police fired tear gas and used truncheons to break
up an attempt by opposition leaders to stage a peaceful march in
Abidjan, 150 miles south of here. A British Broadcasting Corp.
television team that tried to meet with opposition leaders was
briefly detained Sunday.
   Houphouet-Boigny has ruled this nation as a one-party state
since independence from France in 1960.
   The pope met with the president at his residence Sunday evening.
   Among the dignitaries who were to attend the Monday morning
consecration were South African Foreign Minister Pik Botha, French
Cooperation Minister Jacques Pelletier and Jean-Christophe
Mitterrand, the son and counselor of President Francois Mitterrand.
   Cardinals and bishops from 18 African nations and about 350,000
people also were to attend the consecration of the Basilica of Our
Lady of Peace, which towers over this small town 150 miles north of
Abidjan.
   The Ivorian League of Human Rights charged Sunday that
authorities had forced thousands of villagers to come to
Yamoussoukro for the service.
   The consecration ceremony will end a 10-day papal tour of four
African nations, during which the pope has called for a narrowing
of the economic gap between the continent's urban elite and rural
poor.
   Earlier Sunday, in Kigali, the capital of Rwanda, the
Polish-born pope prayed to ``the Virgin Mary, queen of peace,''
appealing for her intercession to bring peace to the world,
particularly in the Persian Gulf.
   A Rwandan government official publicly challenged the pontiff on
the church's attitude to AIDS, celibacy and sainthood of Africans.
   Christophe Mfizi, Rwanda's state information director, said
doctors were hard pressed to defend Catholic bans on birth control
in nations facing a population problem and the use of condoms to
prevent the spread of acquired immune deficiency syndrome.
   John Paul initially declined to visit the basilica in
Yamoussoukro, but accepted the invitation after Houphouet-Boigny
agreed to build a hospital nearby and grant the Catholic Church
permission to open a radio station.
   Houphouet-Boigny, a Catholic, has said he paid for the
construction of the basilica with his own money.
   But opposition leader Laurent Gbagbo has questioned how the
president, a former cocoa farmer, could afford to pay for a
basilica on the scale of St. Peter's in Vatican City. Government
opponents have accused Houphouet-Boigny of stealing state funds.
   The government says the basilica cost $140 million, but other
estimates have put its cost as high as $250 million.
   Gbagbo, a Catholic, has promised not to organize demonstrations.
``We will not disturb this visit, but the pope should know that the
visit disturbs our faith,'' he said.
   Bishops have told other priests that they are not obliged to
attend the consecration, according to church sources.
   The basilica was built between 1985 and 1989, years of hardship
for Ivorians as the country's economy nearly collapsed because of
slumping world prices for cocoa, the main export.
   Fakhoury, an Ivorian of Lebanese descent, said the church is
bigger than St. Peter's, on which it is modeled. St. Peter's had
been considered the largest church in the Christian world.
   The basilica looms up from a 320-acre site carved out of a
former cocoa plantation owned by Houphouet-Boigny. At its tip it is
525 feet high, compared with 452 feet at the top of the cross on
the dome of St. Peter's.
   Sixty artisans, painters and cutters from 14 countries worked on
the 15,000 panels of stained glass _ more than exist in all of
France.
   The basilica seats 7,000 people and another 11,000 standing. The
entire grounds can accommodate more than 350,000 worshipers.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900909-0050 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-09-90 2010EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Homosexuals-Wristbands     09-09 0302</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Homosexuals-Wristbands,0312</SECOND>
<HEAD>Wristbands on Jailed Homosexuals Under Fire</HEAD>
<DATELINE>FORT WORTH, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Fort Worth jail has promised to
reconsider its system of marking homosexual inmates with colored
wristbands, a policy one gay activist said was ``like throwing meat
to the dogs.''
   All prisoners at Tarrant County Jail wear colored wristbands:
red for felons, blue for misdemeanor offenders, orange for those
awaiting transfer to federal prisons, yellow for prisoners with
medical problems and gray for homosexuals.
   New inmates are questioned as they enter the jail, which houses
both men and women. Those who say they are homosexual or bisexual
are allowed protective custody because homosexuals are common
targets of abuse by other inmates, jail officials said Saturday.
   Homosexual inmates who choose protective custody are given gray
wristbands and housed in isolated groups, although they mingle with
the rest of the prisoners during meals and exercise breaks,
officials said.
   ``We need to make sure one prisoner is not abusing another
prisoner for any reason, and this is an aid to us,'' said John
Pempsell, the chief deputy sheriff who oversees the jail.
   Many homosexual activists and civil libertarians said the
wristbands invite abuse, rather than deter it.
   ``You're putting a sign around their neck like, `Come and Beat
on Me,' '' said Ed Koren, a Washington attorney for the National
Prison Project of the American Civil Liberties Union.
   Tarrant County Gay Alliance member Thomas Bruner said the policy
is ``like throwing meat to the dogs.''
   Jail administrator Bill Broome met Thursday with two members of
the gay alliance and said the policy, which has been in effect for
years, would be reconsidered.
   ``No policy is set in concrete,'' Broome said. ``But the
question has never before been brought to my attention.''
   Broome did not say when the policy might be changed.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900909-0051 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-09-90 2225EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-TrainDerailment     09-09 0209</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Train Derailment,0214</SECOND>
<HEAD>Homes Evacuated After Runaway Cars Collide With Locomotive, Derail</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PICO RIVERA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Fourteen runaway railroad cars
collided with a locomotive Sunday, knocking down power lines and
causing a small fire, authorities said. Nine of the cars derailed,
one inches from a home here.
   No one was injured, and none of the Southern Pacific cars
carried hazardous materials, said Andy Anderson, a spokesman for
Southern Pacific in San Francisco.
   One of the derailed cars came to rest inches from a home and ten
houses were evacuated while workers determined that the derailed
cars were stable, said Los Angeles County sheriff's Sgt. Pat Fallis.
   The Union Pacific locomotive crew was warned of the impending
collision and fled the locomotive before the crash, Anderson said.
   One car carrying fiber board caught fire, but the blaze was
quickly controlled, he said.
   The runaway cars apparently were improperly connected to a
locomotive in a switching yard about 15 miles northeast of Pico
Rivera, Anderson said.
   They reached speeds of up to 30 mph before crashing into the
locomotive here, about 25 miles east of Los Angeles.
   Although some lines were downed, no power outages were reported.
There was no estimate on damage caused by the crash, authorities
said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900909-0052 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-09-90 2018EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-MissAmerica     09-09 0660</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Miss America,0682</SECOND>
<HEAD>Retransmitting for all needing.</HEAD>
<HEAD>New Miss America A Romantic Who Wants It All</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos XACC1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By HENRY STERN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ATLANTIC CITY, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Miss America 1991 Marjorie Judith
Vincent said Sunday she's a romantic who wants it all and plans to
use her reign to help battered women.
   Miss Vincent, a 25-year-old Miss Illinois from Oak Park, said
she didn't get to sleep until 4 a.m. Sunday, about four hours after
she was crowned. She said she wants to celebrate with cheesecake
her pageant director denied her.
   ``I got so excited and when I get going, my adrenaline starts
going,'' said Miss Vincent, wearing the pageant's rhinestone tiara.
   Miss Vincent said she has a tendency to put on weight and had
slimmed down about 15 pounds to 110 pounds on her 5-foot-6 frame.
   First runner-up was Miss South Carolina Mary Waddell Gainey, 24,
followed by Miss Tennessee Dana Brown, 25; Miss Texas Suzanne
Lawrence, 21; and Miss Louisiana Linnea Marie Fayard, 22.
   Miss Vincent credited her victory to determination and a
lifelong ambition to participate in the pageant.
   ``I want it all,'' said Miss Vincent, who was on the Boardwalk
shortly after 7 a.m. for the traditional ``frolicking in the surf''
picture.
   Her victory came the same night as the return of once-fired
master of ceremonies Bert Parks. Pageant director Leonard Horn said
he has made no decision if the 75-year-old crooner would be invited
back next year.
   Parks, who was fired 10 years ago by pageant officials who said
he was too old, skipped over introductions for at least a dozen
former Miss Americas during a segment celebrating the pageant's
70th anniversary.
   Horn said two pages in Park's script stuck together.
   ``It's a shame for Bert because he was so excited ... It's one
of the chances you take with live TV,'' Horn said.
   Parks was returning to his Connecticut home and unavailable for
comment.
   During one segment of Saturday's show, Parks rambled about
raunchy comedians and a good place to eat on the Boardwalk, and he
asked America to refer to women as ``ladies'' rather than
``chicks.''
   Master of ceremonies Gary Collins interrupted Parks, took him by
the arm, and said it was time to let the contestants speak. Horn
said Parks did not ad-lib too long.
   ``It's very unfair of the press to think he was dragged off,''
Horn said.
   Miss Vincent, who graduated from DePaul University in 1988 with
a degree in music, performed Chopin's ``Fantasy Impromptu _ Opus
66'' during the talent part of the competition.
   A third-year law student at Duke University, she chose the
plight of battered women as the platform she would like to
emphasize during her reign.
   ``We need to focus on this kind of abuse,'' Miss Vincent said.
``I may be in a situation where I may be battered ... and I want a
way to get out of that situation.
   Her father, Lucien, is a doorman and a check cashier, and her
mother, Florence, is a seamstress. They came to the United States
from Haiti.
   During Sunday's news conference, Miss Vincent broke into French
to tell the people of Haiti, that ``If you want to achieve a goal
and work for it very hard, you can achieve it.'' Miss Vincent also
speaks Creole.
   With her crown, Miss Vincent receives a $35,000 scholarship, a
$40,000 white Chevrolet Corvette convertible and personal
appearance fees that will likely net about $200,000.
   She said she has registered as a Democrat but does not know if
her registration is still valid. She supports abortion rights
although she was raised in the Catholic church, which opposes
abortion.
   She became the second consecutive black to win the crown,
following Miss America 1990 Debbye Turner. She's the fourth black
to hold the title.
   ``My race never played a role,'' Miss Vincent said. ``I came
here and filled out an application for Miss America ... and they
didn't ask my race.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900909-0053 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-09-90 2033EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Dollar-Yen     09-09 0031</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Dollar-Yen,0032</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dollar Opens Down</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The dollar opened at 139.50 yen on the Tokyo
foreign exchange market Monday, down 0.75 yen from Friday's close
of 140.25.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900909-0054 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-09-90 2049EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Liberia 3rdLd-Writethru a0780 09-09 0756</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Liberia, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0780,0778</SECOND>
<HEAD>President Doe Reported Wounded, Captured in Liberia</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 3 grafs to UPDATE with State Department confirming
Doe's capture; pickup 4th graf pvs, `Doe had...'</NOTE>
<DATELINE>ABIDJAN, Ivory Coast (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A rebel faction shot Liberian
President Samuel Doe in both legs and captured him Sunday during a
battle in that nation's capital, the British Broadcasting Corp.
reported.
   The U.S. State Department confirmed that Doe had been captured
by rebels led by Prince Johnson but would not comment further.
   More than 60 people, including dozens of Doe's bodyguards, were
killed in the fighting between Doe loyalists and Johnson's
fighters, the BBC said. It said the battle took place outside the
headquarters of a West African task force in Monrovia, Liberia.
   Doe had left his fortified seaside mansion to pay an unscheduled
visit to the commander of the West African task force, Lt. Gen
Arnold Quainoo of Ghana, the BBC's correspondent in Monrovia
reported.
   Johnson and some of his fighters followed Doe, and a quarrel
erupted, the BBC report said. The two sides then started battling
with rifles, machine guns and grenades.
   Johnson's rebels wounded Doe in both legs and carried him off to
their base camp, the report said.
   Johnson called the BBC and declared himself president of Liberia
until an interim government could be installed. Rival rebel leader
Charles Taylor of the National Patriotic Front previously claimed
the presidency.
   The BBC said Johnson pledged to court-martial Doe.
   Earlier, Doe and Johnson had agreed to an informal cease-fire
between their forces when the West African task force sailed into
Monrovia two weeks ago. Taylor's forces opposed the West African
intervention and continued fighting.
   Rebels in the 8-month-old civil war have accused Doe of nepotism
and stealing millions of dollars of state money. They also hold him
responsible for the deaths of thousands of civilians killed during
the civil war.
   Liberia's civil war began Dec. 24, when Johnson helped lead
rebels loyal to Taylor in an invasion from Ivory Coast. In March,
Johnson broke away to form his own faction.
   Doe had been holed up in his fortified seaside mansion in
Monrovia.
   Taylor's rebels Saturday launched their own attack at the port
against some of the 3,000 soldiers in the West African force.
   The task force had called for relief agencies to return to
Monrovia and promised to assure their safety. U.S. Marine
helicopters Saturday flew in four workers from the U.S. Agency for
International Development and officials of the Belgium-based
Doctors Without Borders and the Feed the Hungry programs.
   The war has left Monrovia without running water and telephone
communications. Very little food has made it to the capital, a city
of 400,000 people, for about two months.
   U.S. Ambassador Peter de Vos to Liberia said food shipments now
in neighboring Ivory Coast would remain there until the conflict
eases.
   A Nigerian military official also said a case of cholera was
reported in a refugee camp near the port.
   Meanwhile, Nigeria accused France of supporting the rebels
because they have French-made weapons. But a French Embassy
spokesman in Lagos, Nigeria, said France was not involved and the
arms possibly were supplied by Burkina Faso or Ivory Coast.
   The Nigerian External Affairs Ministry said French Ambassador
Jacques Lanreau was called in Friday to discuss the alleged arms
shipments, the Lagos Guardian newspaper reported Sunday.
   Nigeria is a member of the the five-nation force assembled to
end the Liberian strife. The other nations are Ghana, Sierra Leone,
Gambia and Guinea.
   Johnson's forces control Monrovia's port. Taylor's 10,000
fighters have overrun most of Liberia but have been bogged down on
Monrovia's outskirts for more than two months.
   Taylor accuses the West African nations in the task force of
supporting Doe.
   About 2,100 U.S. Marines are based on ships off Monrovia and
assigned to guard the U.S. Embassy and residential compound in the
capital. They have evacuated hundreds of foreigners from the city
but have orders not to intervene in the war.
   Doe, who claims to have survived more than 30 coup attempts,
seized power in a 1980 coup that ousted descendants of American
slaves who founded Liberia in 1847.
   Liberia, a nation of about 2 million people, has strategic
importance for the United States. It is the base for all diplomatic
messages to and from U.S. missions in Africa.
   In addition, there is a huge Voice of America transmission
station a few miles from Monrovia, and the country has a powerful
marine transmitter responsible for guiding all U.S. shipping in the
Atlantic Ocean.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900909-0055 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-09-90 2107EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Gulf-Evacuees 3rdLd-Writethru a0789 09-09 0632</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Evacuees, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0789,0649</SECOND>
<HEAD>Gulf Crisis Evacuees Arrive in London</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS grafs 7-11 pvs with 3 to UPDATE with further details
about evacuees and Americans' departure; pickup 12th graf pvs,
`Embassy officials...'</NOTE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hundreds of American and other evacuees from the
Persian Gulf crisis headed home to safety Sunday in
government-chartered jets flying out of Jordan and Iraq.
   An Iraqi Airways jumbo jet carrying more than 400 women and
children arrived in London from Baghdad, said officials at Gatwick
airport near London, and a squadron of Indian air force planes flew
home hundreds of Indians stranded in makeshift Jordanian refugee
camps.
   Since the Iraqi invasion of Kuwait on Aug. 2, thousands of
foreign workers have been trying to flee the country and are
waiting in the squalid camps for transportation home.
   A U.S.-chartered Northwest Airlines jumbo jet carrying about 300
American evacuees arrived Sunday night at Charleston International
Airport in South Carolina.
   The flight took off from Amman, Jordan, early Sunday, refueled
in Frankfurt, West Germany, and made an unexpected stop in Halifax,
Nova Scotia, to let off several ill passengers.
   One woman was suffering chest pains and three children from
another family were feeling ill. All four, plus the children's
mother, got off the plane in Halifax and were taken to a hospital
for care, said a State Department official.
   A chartered Iraqi Airways jumbo jet, with an almost full
passenger load of women and children, arrived at London's Gatwick
Airport Sunday night after a 6{-hour flight from Baghdad.
   British Airways, the handling agent, said there were 438 people
on board, including 176 Britons, 163 Americans and 32 Irish. Also
on the flight were people from Indonesia, the Philippines, Jordan,
Kenya, Taiwan, Lebanon, Trinidad, Singapore, Jamaica, the
Seychelles, Sri Lanka, Nigeria and South Africa. All were evacuated
from Kuwait and Iraq.
   British Airways Tony Cocklin said the Americans were scheduled
to depart Monday afternoon for Baltimore on a Lockheed 1011 Tristar.
   Embassy officials representing each nationality on the flight
were at the airport to meet the hostages.
   Among the British evacuees, Bhavna Trivedi, 32, holding her baby
son Adarsh, sobbed as she said: ``My poor husband is still there.''
   ``The last time I saw him was 10 days ago. He is in Kuwait
hiding. Then I came to Baghdad.''
   ``Everyone is tense,'' Mrs. Trivedi said. ``There is a lot of
resistance. They are trying to blow up ammunition trucks. There is
a lot of shooting on the street.''
   Suzanne Turvey, 18, said she was interrogated by the Iraqi
forces until she finally gave them the address where her father was
in hiding and he was taken to Baghdad.
   She said she was visiting her father, John Turvey, an oil
company worker who had been in Iraq for eight years.
   The freed Americans spent the night at a hotel near Gatwick,
about 25 miles south of London. They were to catch a chartered
flight to Baltimore on Monday, Press Association said.
   The British Foreign Office said it chartered the Iraqi Airways
Boeing 747 for the flight. The plane was expected to return
immediately to Baghdad with no passengers, the Gatwick spokesman
said.
   An Indian consular offical said 1,600 refugees had been
repatriated by that nation's airlift, which began Saturday.
   Air India charters picked up hundreds of Indian refugees at
Amman airport on Sunday and flew them to Dubai, where they were
flown home by a squadron of air force jets.
   About 10,000 Westerners were believed to remain in Kuwait and
Iraq, including about 2,200 Americans. While Iraq has allowed women
and children to leave, it has moved more Western men to army
installations, factories and other potential military targets.
   Male diplomats and dependents who left the U.S. Embassy in
Kuwait also have been prevented from going home.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900909-0056 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-09-90 2136EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Gulf-Syria-Iraq 1stLd-Writethru a0793 09-09 0305</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Syria-Iraq, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0793,0312</SECOND>
<HEAD>Explosions Reported in Iraqi Border Town</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf Rdp, Bjt</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS throughout to ADD earlier report that Americans were
brought to chemical plant last month; no pickup.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>DAMASCUS, Syria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A series of 46 explosions rocked an Iraqi
town near the Syrian border Sunday, and there were an undetermined
number of casualties, Syria's official news agency reported. Iraq
denied the report.
   Its correspondent in the Syrian town of Boukamal, three miles
west of al-Qaim, reported that ``minutes after the wave of
explosions'' appeals for urgent blood donations ``to save the lives
of the victims'' were made over loudspeakers in the Iraqi town's
mosques.
   The Syrian Arab News Agency said no further details were
available.
   The American network ABC identified the site of the blasts as
the al-Qaim chemical plant.
   Last month, Polish workers returning home from Iraq said that
about 35 Americans were brought to the chemical plant in al-Qaim on
Aug. 17 under guard. Iraq has allowed foreign women and children to
leave Kuwait and Iraq since its standoff with the West began over
its invasion of Kuwait on Aug. 2, but it has moved Western men to
army installations, factories and other potential military targets.
   It was not known whether any Westerners were still being held as
human shields at the al-Qaim plant.
   Iraq denied there were any explosions in the town. Quoting an
unidentified source, the government-run Iraqi News Agency called
the Syrian report ``sheer fabrication.''
   Syria and Iraq have been locked in an ideological feud for more
than a decade. They are ruled by rival wings of the Baath Arab
Socialist Party.
   Syrian President Hafez Assad has sent troops to join the Arab
component of a multinational forces in Saudi Arabia confronting the
Iraqis following their invasion of Kuwait on Aug. 2.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900909-0057 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-09-90 2138EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Gulf-HostagesReturn 1stLd-Writethru a0782 09-09 0841</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Hostages Return, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0782,0863</SECOND>
<HEAD>Chartered Jet Arrives in U.S. Carrying 300 Evacuees from Kuwait</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: UPDATES throughout with details of landing, quotes from
evacuees, other details. DELETES outdated grafs about people
waiting for relatives. No pickup.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto Staffing</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BRUCE SMITH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CHARLESTON, S.C. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   More than 300 weary U.S. evacuees from
war-torn Kuwait sang ``God Bless America'' Sunday when their
chartered jet landed after a flight from Jordan.
   The 747 aircraft, which left Amman early Sunday, arrived at the
Charleston International Airport 6:10 p.m. with 305 evacuees _
mostly women and children, and a handful of men.
   The plane was delayed several hours because of an unexpected
stop in Halifax, Nova Scotia, to let off several people for health
reasons, Mike Brennan of the State Department said.
   One woman was suffering chest pains and three children from
another family were feeling ill. All four, plus the children's
mother, got off the plane in Halifax and were taken to a hospital,
he said.
   The passengers told harrowing tales of escape from Kuwait. They
said they went into seclusion after Iraq's invasion Aug. 2 because
Westerners were at risk if they moved freely. They also spoke of
the brave but outmanned resistance fighters trying to battle Iraqi
invasion forces.
   ``I was lucky enough and smart enough to get away,'' said Jimmy
Hawkins of Dallas, who worked as an engineer in Kuwait. ``Americans
can't go out. No way. If you don't have Arab friends, you're
stuck.''
   Oriole Hart of Denver, a computer analyst for a bank in Kuwait,
described how she hid out for the last month before she could
contact officials and get on the first evacuation flights.
   Kuwait is devastated, she said, adding, ``It's really a shame.''
   ``Westerners are not safe there,'' she said. ``We don't know
what they (Iraqis) are going to do next.''
   Social workers, customs agents and other officials greeted the
evacuees, many of whom were to spend the night in Charleston
because they could not get connecting flights to other destinations.
   ``This is the same crowd that was gathered to handle the
aftermath of Hurricane Hugo,'' which struck Charleston and much of
the South Carolina coast in September 1989, Gov. Carroll Campbell
said. ``This is a much more pleasant assignment.''
   As the evacuees left the concourse and entered the main
terminal, they could choose from an array of social service
agencies.
   The passengers were greeted with applause by those waiting at
the airport. Children carried teddy bears, gifts from volunteer
workers who met the plane.
   Maria Al-Rizaiqi, an American whose husband, Musallam, is a
citizen of the United Arab Emirates, had gone to Kuwait on the
night before the Iraqi invasion to visit friends. They were unable
to leave until the flights this weekend.
   ``I was very scared,'' she said. ``They were taking foreigners.
They said any person harboring foreigners in their house, the whole
family would be executed.''
   Musallam Al-Rizaiqi said one of his friends was killed last week.
   ``They took him last Sunday. Then I saw him the next Monday. He
was shot dead in the street. Then they buried him, his friends,''
he said.
   The couple planned to head to Miami, where Mrs. Al-Rizaiqi has
relatives.
   Hawkins described how he escaped from Kuwait in a car owned by a
Jordanian friend. They went to Baghdad but were arrested.
   Hawkins said he bribed police in Iraq's capital, disguised
himself as an Iranian and fled for the Jordanian border before he
was turned back. Later, he said, he crossed the desert at night and
made his way to Amman.
   In the days after the invasion, Hawkins said: ``There was
resistance. There's fighting nightly. There were bullets flying and
bombs going off every day. ... (The resistance) is very brave and
well organized but they're low on equipment and badly outnumbered.''
   Added Al-Rizaiqi: ``The resistance is very strong. One of my
friends said, `No matter what, they will never get us.'''
   Hawkins said there is food, bread, eggs and potatoes in Kuwait.
``Most everything you can buy in Iraq has been stolen from
Kuwait,'' he said.
   State and local politicians turned out to welcome the evacuees
home.
   Campbell, wore a yellow ribbon on the lapel of his blue suit,
and U.S. Rep. Arthur Ravenel, whose congressional district includes
Charleston, were on hand, as was U.S. Sen. Ernest Hollings, D-S.C.
   ``I'm just here to welcome them home. You can imagine how they
feel,'' Ravenel said.
   U.S. officials estimate about 2,200 Americans remain in Iraq and
Kuwait. Some of the men in that group have been sent to military
installations to discourage possible Western attacks.
   Earlier this year, Americans evacuated from the civil war in
Liberia were brought back to the United States through Charleston.
Last year, American military dependents were evacuated from Panama
to Charleston prior to the U.S. invasion.
   When the United States invaded the island of Grenada in 1983, a
total of 698 evacuees, many of them U.S. medical students, were
returned to the United States through Charleston.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900909-0058 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-09-90 2146EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-GainesvilleSlayings 1stLd-Writethru a0771 09-09 0800</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gainesville Slayings, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0771,0815</SECOND>
<HEAD>Knife Reportedly Found in Milk Carton In Suspect's Home</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: INSERTS 5 grafs after 8th graf pvs, `Gainesville police...'
to UPDATE with defense lawyer saying knife in milk carton not
unusual, grandmother defending Humphrey; SUBS 9th graf pvs,
`Meanwhile, police...' to DELETE incorrect reference to University
of Florida, SUBS penultimate graf pvs to CORRECT victims' schools.
Picks up last graf pvs, `Mike Floyd...'
^By RON WORD</NOTE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>GAINESVILLE, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   State agents who searched a suspect's
home in the killing of five college students found a knife hidden
in a milk carton, a newspaper reported Sunday.
   The Gainesville Sun quoted two sources close to the
investigation as saying that the knife was found Thursday as agents
searched the Indialantic home of Edward Lewis Humphrey, his
Gainesville apartment and his car.
   Police in Colby, Kan., said Sunday that Humphrey was told to
leave the town in western Kansas last month, about two weeks before
the killings in Gainesville, because of his suspicious behavior,
including arguing with a hitchhiker and later driving slowly
through residential areas.
   Humphrey, 18, hasn't been charged in the slayings but has been
identified by police as one of eight suspects. They have refused to
call him the prime suspect.
   The Sun reported that the knife was found where Humphrey told
investigators earlier this month it would be. Lab tests will be
performed to determine if the knife is linked to the killings.
   All of the victims died from multiple stab wounds, police said.
   Also confiscated from the home, owned by Humphrey's 79-year-old
grandmother, Elna Hlavaty, were books, videotapes, and clothing.
Humphrey lived there with his mother and grandmother.
   Gainesville police Lt. Sadie Darnell said Friday that
``promising evidence'' was found in the searches, but she refused
to elaborate.
   Humphrey's attorney, J.R. Russo, said Sunday he could not
confirm the seizure of the knife, but said it would not be unusual
for Humphrey to keep things in strange places.
   ``An emotionally disturbed individual might keep his toothbrush
under the pillow and his shoes in the oven,'' he said.
   Humphrey is being in lieu of $1 million bond in the Brevard
County jail in Sharpes for allegedly assaulting his grandmother the
night of his return from summer school at the University of Florida
here, where he is a freshman. His grandmother has said she wants to
drop the charges and defended him on Sunday.
   ``They are drumming up a case,'' Ms. Hlavaty said. ``He will do
anything to sleep when he needs his medication. He will say
anything.''
   Humphrey suffers from psychiatric problems and takes Lithium to
control his mood swings.
   Meanwhile, police said Sunday that the three apartments where
the students were murdered have been released to their landlords.
   ``We feel at this point that nothing more is going to be gained.
We have recovered all we are going to recover,'' said Alachua
County Sheriff's Lt. Spencer Mann.
   In Colby, Kan., an officer intervened in an argument between
Humphrey and a hitchhiker he had picked up Aug. 10, said Police
Chief Randy Jones. Humphrey then asked the officer where he could
use a certain gasoline credit card and the officer pointed out a
station about three blocks away, Jones said.
   ``But he drove right past it and he was then seen driving slowly
through some residential areas,'' Jones said. ``The officer stopped
him, asked him if he needed some assistance and they came to the
mutual agreement that Humphrey would leave town.''
   Hours after Humphrey left Colby, he was arrested in Colorado's
Crowley County, about 90 miles west of the Kansas border, after he
allegedly failed to pay for $12 worth of gasoline at a convenience
store, Sheriff's Sgt. Allan Turner said Thursday. His grandmother
flew to Denver to return him to Florida, and the charges were
dropped.
   The only other suspect publicly identified is Stephen Michael
Bates, 30, a Lakeland short-order cook also jailed on an unrelated
assault charge.
   Published reports have said Humphrey may have a multiple
personality and has referred to himself as ``John'' and other
names, including ``Henry.'' The Sun also reported he sometimes
refers to a female personality.
   Experts said the slayings were committed by a meticulous,
calculating killer who left subtle messages for police. The killer
also may be a sexual sadist because of the way three bodies were
mutilated.
   Before the University of Florida's first football game of the
season Saturday, school President John Lombardi asked the 72,000
fans to observe a moment of silence for the victims, who attended
the university or nearby Santa Fe Community College.
   Mike Floyd, owner of a sports shop across the street from the
university, observed: ``The mood is changing, but this will always
be with the students the rest of their lives.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900909-0059 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-09-90 2241EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Gulf-PeaceProtest     09-09 0271</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Peace Protest,0280</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.S. Buildup in Mideast Prompts Protests</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SEATTLE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   About 700 marchers protested U.S. military
involvement in the Persian Gulf over the weekend, chanting ``Hell,
no, we won't go, we won't fight for Texaco,'' and ``Money for
school, not for war.''
   The crowd listened to speeches Saturday at Seattle Center before
marching peacefully downtown. The rally was organized by the
Northwest Coalition Against U.S. Military Intervention in the
Mideast.
   Among the protesters, which police estimated at 700, was Korean
War veteran Don Alexander. A hand-lettered sign taped to his
wheelchair said: ``No blood for oil.''
   ``Can you believe that our young men, mostly poor and of color,
are going to die for the rights of profit and oil machinery?'' he
asked.
   The United States massed thousands of troops in Saudi Arabia
after Iraq invaded neighboring Kuwait on Aug. 2.
   Hamid Mobarez, a bus driver who came from Iran 12 years ago,
joined 20 Iranian friends at the march.
   ``We certainly don't support Saddam Hussein,'' Mobarez said,
referring to to the Iraqi president. ``But we don't agree with the
U.S. imperialist policy of doing police work around the world. It's
like old colonial rule.''
   Meanwhile, a peace vigil entered its third week at Seattle's
Gasworks Park with a picnic and speakers Sunday.
   Activists opposed to the U.S. buildup have been at the park
since Aug. 26, with participants replacing each other in shifts,
said ``Peaceworks Park'' member Joseph Mabel.
   As many as 100 and as few as three people at a time have
maintained the vigil.
   Mabel said the vigil would continue until the crisis was settled
peacefully.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900909-0060 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-09-90 2215EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-SummitRdp 3rdLdWritethru a0764 09-09 0880</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Summit Rdp, 3rd Ld Writethru, a0764,910-1,530</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush, Gorbachev Conclude Summit With Joint Condemnation of Iraq</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: UPDATES graf 13 with Bush returning to Washington, INSERTS 3
grafs on Soviet advisers after 17th, picks up 18th graf, ``There
was xxx</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By DAVID ESPO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HELSINKI, Finland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush and Soviet leader
Mikhail S. Gorbachev joined Sunday in an extraordinary condemnation
of Iraq's invasion of Kuwait, and said they agreed in seven hours
of summit talks that ``aggression cannot and will not pay.''
   Gorbachev emphasized the need for a ``political'' solution,
insisting that his former ally, Saddam Hussein, is headed ``into a
dead end'' by struggling to hold Kuwait against stiff international
sanctions.
   Bush held out the possibility of using force if the embargo is
not effective, but Gorbachev pointedly refrained from saying the
Soviet Union would support a military move against Iraq.
   Yet the Soviet president said he hoped to make it ``quite clear
to Saddam Hussein that if Iraq were to provoke military action,
then the result would be a tragedy first and foremost for the Iraqi
people themselves, for the whole of the region and for the whole of
the world.''
   The leaders spoke with reporters following the release of their
joint summit declaration that said: ``We are united in the belief
that Iraq's aggression must not be tolerated. No peaceful
international order is possible if larger states can devour their
smaller neighbors ...
   ``Our preference is to resolve the (Persian Gulf) crisis
peacefully, and we will be united against Iraq's aggression as long
as the crisis exists,'' they declared.
   The statement stood in unprecedented contrast to Cold War
bickering that accompanied crises during the past four decades.
   The statement also said that once Iraq withdraws from Kuwait,
the two countries will work with nations in the region to develop
regional security structures and measures to promote peace and
stability.
   Afterward, as he headed home aboard Air Force One, Bush said he
``couldn't be more pleased'' by his talks with Gorbachev and the
``clear signal'' they sent to Saddam Hussein.
   Asked how the summit had changed things, Bush told reporters:
``I think he (Saddam) has been hopeful that he could divide and
peel the Soviet Union away from the United States and from the rest
of the world.'
   Bush, who returned to Washington late Sunday night, said he
hoped to meet again with Gorbachev late this year or early next
year.
   The official Iraqi news agency INA said in a commentary that the
summit showed Bush's ``evil tendencies and his spite for the Arab
nation and its central issues, primarily the tragedy of the
Palestinian people, who are suffering under the Zionist occupation
enforced by U.S. support.''
   At the summit-concluding news conference with Gorbachev, Bush
said Soviet support for anti-Iraq sanctions ``gets me inclined to
recommend as close cooperation in the economic field as possible.''
He said there had been a ``good long discussion'' on Soviet
requests for economic assistance, and that he would address the
topic when he makes a nationally televised speech to Congress
Tuesday night.
   The possibility that sanctions will not succeed against Iraq
prompted the most significant differences between Bush and
Gorbachev.
   Without elaboration, their joint statement said, ``if the
current steps fail to end it, we are prepared to consider
additional ones'' consistent with the United Nations charter.
   ``I did not say that if Iraq does not withdraw peacefully, we're
going to have recourse to military methods. ... I do not state
that,'' said the Soviet president.
   ``We may have a difference on that,'' Bush acknowledged. He said
again that he will not discuss U.S. options if Iraq continues to
defy the U.N. resolution.
   One other area of disagreement emerged: the presence of nearly
200 Soviet military advisers in Iraq, once a major military client
of the Soviet Union.
   Gorbachev said the number of advisers had been reduced from 196
to about 150. ``They are leaving Iraq and the process is moving
forward, so I don't think it's a problem,'' he said.
   Said Bush: ``I think it would facilitate things'' if all the
advisers were withdrawn,'' he said, but added it was not a ``major
irritant.''
   There was no attempt to claim agreement on all elements of Gulf
policy.
   Said Gorbachev: ``Differences, nuances in the differences of
view, arguments, these can be _ these are natural. It's natural
those should arise. But what we have seen today is that we have
confirmed the most important progress of recent time.''
   Said Bush: ``Neither of us try to indicate that we look at
exactly every problem exactly the same way.''
   While the Persian Gulf crisis was the dominant topic, the two
presidents said they had agreed to press their arms control
negotiators to seek terms on limiting both strategic arms and
conventional weapons in Europe.
   ``We really have agreed to make fresh efforts,'' Gorbachev said,
because there is a possibility negotiations could be concluded by
year's end.
   One U.S. official, speaking on condition of anonymity, said the
two leaders had not settled any of the issues blocking agreement on
either accord. A fresh push for agreement could come as early as
this week when Secretary of State James Baker meets in Moscow with
Soviet Foreign Minister Eduard A. Shevardnadze.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900909-0061 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-09-90 2249EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Gulf-GasolinePrices     09-09 0253</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Gasoline Prices,0259</SECOND>
<HEAD>Retail Gas Prices Continue To Rise, But More Slowly</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Gasoline prices across the nation continued
to climb last week, but at a slower rate than immediately after
Iraq's invasion of Kuwait, an oil industry analyst said Sunday.
   The average price for all grades of gasoline at full- and
self-serve stations was $1.35 a gallon Friday, an increase of 2.28
cents a gallon from Aug. 24, according to Trilby Lundberg's survey
of 13,600 gasoline stations.
   ``The Middle East crisis is still driving these moves because of
the impact of the highly sensitive international market,'' said
Lundberg, publisher of the biweekly Lundberg Letter.
   Prices jumped an average of 10.2 cents a gallon between July 20
and Aug. 10 and another 5.2 cents a gallon between Aug. 10 and Aug.
24, Lundberg said.
   ``So you can see the rate has slowed down, but a 2.28 increase
is still very strong for this time of year,'' she said.
   The average price of regular leaded gasoline at self-serve
stations last week was $1.23 a gallon, while regular unleaded sold
for $1.24 a gallon and premium unleaded was just shy of $1.41 a
gallon, Lundberg's survey showed.
   At full-service stations, regular leaded retailed for $1.46 a
gallon, regular unleaded averaged nearly $1.47 a gallon and premium
unleaded sold for $1.60 a gallon.
   ``Whether gasoline prices soften as they often do in colder
months after peak summer driving depends on the unknown of crude
oil supplies and the Mideast crisis,'' said Lundberg.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900909-0062 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-09-90 2222EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-GulfRdp 4thLd-Writethru a0801 09-09 1058</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf Rdp, 4th Ld-Writethru, a0801,1084</SECOND>
<HEAD>Iraq Seeks Closer Ties With Ex-Foe Iran; Superpowers Discuss
Crisis</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 24th graf to CORRECT to South Carolina sted North
Carolina; pickup 25th graf pvs, `About 10,000...'
^With LaserPhoto AMM1, DXB2</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By CHRISTOPHER BURNS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Iraq's foreign minister Sunday sought help from Iran in cracking
the U.N.-imposed embargo on Baghdad, but the United States and
Soviet Union renewed their commitment to the sanctions.
   Syria's official news agency reported that a series of 46
explosions were heard in the Iraqi town of Al-Qaim near the border,
resulting in an undetermined number of casualties. ABC News
identified the site of the blasts as the al-Qaim chemical plant.
   The official Iraqi News Agency denied the reports.
   Polish workers returning home from Iraq reported that about 35
Americans were brought to the chemical plant in Al-Qaim on Aug. 17
under guard. It was not known whether any Westerners were still
being held as human shields at the plant.
   Meanwhile, more Americans flew to freedom after being held in
Iraq and Kuwait following Iraq's invasion of its neighbor on Aug.
2. Hundreds are still held as human shields against U.S. and other
forces building up in the Persian Gulf region.
   Iraqi Foreign Minister Tariq Aziz met with Iranian officials in
Tehran, Iran's capital, in the first official Iraqi visit since the
two countries went to war in 1980. The fighting ended in a
cease-fire in August 1988.
   Sources in Tehran, speaking on condition of anonymity, said Aziz
was likely to ask Iranian officials to allow shipments of food and
medicine into his country. The U.N. embargo permits only
humanitarian shipments of such supplies.
   The trip by Aziz paves the way for a meeting between Iraqi
President Saddam Hussein and Iranian President Hashemi Rafsanjani
to sign a peace treaty officially ending hostilities.
   In Sunday's talks, Iranian Foreign Minister Ali Akbar Velayati
reiterated his country's condemnation of the invasion of Kuwait.
But he also criticized the presence of U.S. and other foreign
forces building up in the Persian Gulf, according to Iran's
official Islamic Republic News Agency.
   Iran's radical parliament speaker, Mehdi Karribui, warned of
Moslem terrorist acts against U.S. interests unless Washington
withdraws its forces from the gulf, IRNA reported.
   Another warning of terrorist attacks came from the leader of a
faction of the Palestine Liberation Organization. Abul Abbas, head
of the Palestine Liberation Front, told the American television
network CNN that his group could strike ``if the United States
initiates the attack on the Arab people and on us.''
   In another indication Iraq was hurting from U.N.-imposed
sanctions, the Baghdad government is cracking down on black
marketeers.
   Iraqi newspapers on Sunday published a government decree saying
anyone hoarding food or gouging prices on scarce food will face
jail terms of up to 15 years. Food already is being rationed.
   The Syrian news agency, in its dispatch on explosions in Iraq,
said its correspondent in the town of Boukamal, three miles west of
the Iraqi town of al-Qaim, reported a ``wave'' of blasts. It said
appeals for urgent blood donations ``to save the lives of the
victims'' were made minutes later over loudspeakers in al-Qaim's
mosques.
   The news agency said no further details were available. Syria is
a bitter rival of Iraq within the Arab world and has sent troops to
Saudi Arabia as part of a multinational Arab force.
   The government-run Iraqi News Agency, quoting an unidentified
source, dismissed the Syrian report of explosions as ``sheer
fabrication.''
   In Helsinki, Finland, President Bush and Soviet President
Mikhail Gorbachev agreed anew Sunday on ``the path that the U.N.
has set'' in forcing Iraq to pull its troops out of Kuwait.
   But the superpower leaders stopped short of asking each other to
take any immediate specific measures to force Iraq from Kuwait.
   Saudi Arabia, an orthodox Moslem kingdom, has resisted relations
with Moscow over the years because of its aversion to atheistic
communism. But Prince Saud al-Faisal, the Saudi foreign minister,
said Sunday there have been ``serious contacts'' with Moscow about
establishing diplomatic relations between the two countries.
   Iraq's 1 million-member army has deployed an estimated 260,000
troops along with hundreds of tanks in and around Kuwait since
seizing its oil-rich southern neighbor in a dispute over oil, land
and money.
   About 100,000 U.S. troops have been deployed in the Gulf region
as part of a multinational buildup to defend Saudi Arabia and
enforce the U.N.-sanctioned embargo on trade with Iraq.
   Navy officers from the United States and nine other countries
met Sunday in Manama, Bahrain, to coordinate the sea blockade.
   Meanwhile, the flow of refugees from Iraq and Kuwait continued
Sunday. Thousands more Asians and Arabs crossed into Turkey and
Jordan, and more American and British women and children were
headed home.
   A U.S.-chartered flight carrying about 300 Americans flew from
Amman, Jordan, to Charleston, S.C., and a British-chartered Iraqi
Airways jumbo jet carrying 438 evacuees _ including 163 Americans _
flew from Baghdad to London.
   About 10,000 Westerners were believed to remain in Kuwait and
Iraq, including about 1,000 Americans in Kuwait. While Iraq has
allowed women and children to leave, it has moved more Western men
to army installations, factories and other potential military
targets.
   More than 110,000 mostly penniless men, women and children from
Bangladesh, India, Pakistan, Philippines, Sri Lanka, Thailand and
other Third World nations have been stuck in Jordan since fleeing
Kuwait and Iraq.
   A squadron of Indian air force planes and chartered airliners
flew home hundreds of Indians on Sunday.
   Another airlift, by the International Migration Organization,
started Thursday and continued over the weekend to fly Sri Lankans
home.
   But a senior Jordanian official said the number of repatriations
``hardly keeps up with the continuing influx of new arrivals.''
   The U.S. and other embassies in Kuwait were defying a siege by
Iraqi troops trying to shut them down, but many ran low on supplies
after the Iraqis cut off their water and power nearly two weeks ago.
   On Sunday, Danish Ambassador Birger Dan Nielsen left his
compound and arrived in Baghdad on orders from his government to
temporarily close the embassy.
   Belgian Foreign Minister Mark Eyskens said the remaining
European Community embassies in Kuwait could hold out for two more
weeks. After that, he said they will seek to accredit their
diplomats with the Kuwaiti government-in-exile in Saudi Arabia.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900909-0063 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-09-90 2253EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-StoicGrandmother     09-09 0365</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Stoic Grandmother,0377</SECOND>
<HEAD>Grandmother Faces Jail Unless She Reveals Granddaughters'
Whereabouts</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KAREN SCHWARTZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PROVIDENCE, R.I. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A 77-year-old grandmother faces jail on
contempt charges Monday if she refuses to say where her daughter
has taken her two young granddaughters.
   Superior Court Judge Mark A. Pfeiffer ruled last year that Mary
Pigeon helped her daughter, Elaine Yates, flee Warwick with the
children five years ago and conspired to keep them from their
father, Russell M. Yates Jr.
   Yates had sued his mother-in-law to find out what she knows.
   Mrs. Pigeon has testified that she does not know the whereabouts
of her grandaughters, Kimberly and Kelly. But Pfeiffer found her in
contempt of court and gave her until a hearing Monday to say where
the girls are or face prison.
   Mrs. Pigeon could not be reached at her home or summer residence
on Sunday. Her lawyer, Daniel Schrock, was not at the office and
his home number was not listed.
   Yates said he was optimistic Mrs. Pigeon would break her silence.
   ``I've got to keep the faith and be hopeful,'' he said Sunday.
   Kimberly was 3 years old and Kelly was 10 months when they
disappeared with their mother a few weeks after Mrs. Yates found
her husband in bed with another woman. Yates has said he hit his
wife and cut her forehead during an argument over the infidelity.
   The couple has not divorced, but Yates has legal custody of the
children.
   ``I won't divorce her because I won't let it be easy for her to
change her name or the children's,'' he said.
   In May, Pfeiffer ordered Mrs. Pigeon to work 60 hours at an
agency in Newport that searches for missing children, and she ended
up serving twice that much.
   Her lawyer said last month that she was ``very scared'' about
going to jail. Schrock said he hoped Mrs. Yates would hear of the
order and bring the children home.
   Yates said he did not care if his mother-in-law went to jail.
   ``It wouldn't disturb me at all because she's the one, she and
her daughter, who have let things go as far as they have,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900909-0064 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-09-90 2253EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Deaths Advisory   09-09 0014</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Deaths, Advisory,0013</SECOND>
<TEXT>
   Editors: No AM-Deaths will move this cycle.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>The AP</HEAD>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900909-0065 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-09-90 2256EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-DoeProfile     09-09 0517</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Doe Profile,0533</SECOND>
<HEAD>Captured Liberian Leader Survived Many Coup Attempts</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Liberia</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Liberian President Samuel K. Doe sometimes boasted that he had
survived more than 30 coup attempts, but on Sunday his many lives
may have run out.
   A rebel faction led by Prince Johnson shot Doe in both legs and
captured him Sunday in a battle outside the headquarters of the
West African task force sent to Monrovia to end the country's
8-month-old civil war.
   Doe had ventured out of his fortified seaside mansion to make an
unscheduled visit to Lt. Gen. Arnold Quainoo of Ghana, the task
force's commander.
   Johnson declared himself president and pledged to court-martial
Doe. Charles Taylor, the leader of the rival rebel National
Patriotic Front _ which controls most of the country outside
Monrovia _ has also named himself president.
   Doe had been holed up in his mansion since July as street
fighting raged in the capital. His troops _ many of them members of
his Krahn tribe _ reportedly refused to let him flee without
obtaining assurances for their own safety.
   As the rebels advanced, the Liberian leader sent out conflicting
signals about whether he would resign. He rejected an offer by the
U.S. ambassador to help him leave the country.
   Liberia's civil war began Dec. 24, when Taylor led a small rebel
force in an invasion from Ivory Coast. In March, Johnson broke away
to form his own faction.
   Despite the split, the rebels continued to gain recruits and
take control of nearly all the country except for part of Monrovia.
   The rebels have accused Doe of nepotism and stealing millions of
dollars of state money. They also hold him responsible for the
deaths of thousands of civilians killed during the civil war.
   As a master sergeant, Doe seized power in a bloody coup on April
12, 1980, that ousted descendants of American slaves who founded
Liberia in 1847. The coup ended the rule of President William
Tolbert, who was killed.
   Doe came to power by playing on the resentment felt by the
majority of the population _ members of indigenous African tribes _
toward the Americo-Liberians who had dominated the country for more
than 100 years.
   Doe was born on May 6, 1950, in Tuzon, Grand Gedeh County.
   He attended R.E.B. Richardson Baptist Junior High School and the
Ministry of National Defense Radio and Communication School in
Monrovia.
   Since taking power, his presidency has been characterized by
numerous coup attempts, murders and detentions of opposition
leaders and suppression of the country's press.
   He permitted elections in October 1985. When opposition parties
appeared to have won the voting, Doe's men burned and destroyed
ballots. The election commission Doe had appointed declared him the
winner.
   The election rigging triggered the worst violence under Doe's
rule prior to the civil war. At least 1,500 people were estimated
to have died, including Brig. Gen. Thomas Quiwonkpa, who led a coup
attempt.
   Quiwonkpa had been a popular commander from Nimba County and his
killing made his home area a fertile base for Taylor's rebels when
they invaded Liberia.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900909-0066 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-09-90 1441EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-BRF--Japan-USRice     09-09 0161</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Japan-US Rice,0167</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tokyo Says U.S. Rice Inferior to Japanese</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Laboratory tests show American rice provided by
Agriculture Secretary Clayton Yeutter is inferior to Japanese rice,
Japan's agriculture minister was quoted as saying Sunday.
   Yeutter gave several bags of American rice to Japanese Cabinet
members during a visit last month in which he called for Japan's
rice market to be opened.
   ``I thought if I ate all the rice myself it would be a waste, so
I had some tested,'' Kyodo News Service quoted the minister of
Agriculture, Forestry and Fisheries, Tomio Yamamoto, as telling a
meeting of members of the governing Liberal Democratic Party.
   ``I can't tell you what the results were, but we found that
Japanese rice is far superior in quality,'' it quoted him as
telling the meeting in Ito, southwest of Tokyo.
   Yamamoto said he believed Japan will continue restrictions on
rice imports, despite calls for liberalization during international
trade negotiations, Kyodo said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
</Collection>
