<Collection>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0001 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 2330EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Panama-Complaint     01-14 0510</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama-Complaint,0524</SECOND>
<HEAD>Female Soldier Blames Policy for Panama Exclusion</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Women-Combat</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>FORT BRAGG, N.C. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A female Army intelligence officer whose
specialty is Panama filed a complaint over her exclusion from the
U.S. invasion there, but said Sunday her problem stems from
``confused'' policy rather than sexism.
   ``I think that it was not deliberate,'' Sgt. Rhonda Maskus said
on CBS-TV's ``Face the Nation'' in an interview from the Army's
Fort Bragg.
   Ma. Maskus filed the complaint Jan. 3 with the Army's Office of
Inspector General in Washington. Army officials have declined to
comment on the complaint.
   Ms. Maskus, a Spanish linguist and intelligence analyst who is
an expert on Panama, described herself as ``a major factor in the
contingency planning for Panama.''
   But Ms. Maskus, who belongs to the 82nd Airborne Division, did
not go to that Latin American country when U.S. forces invaded Dec.
20. Instead, a male soldier she said was not an expert on Panama
was sent to a secure U.S. base, Ms. Maskus said.
   ``Now if I had been a male soldier, without doubt, without
question, without hesitation, I would have been the one deployed to
Panama,'' she said.
   Also appearing on ``Face the Nation'' were Christopher Jehn,
assistant secretary of defense for personnel; Brian Mitchell,
author of ``The Weak Link,'' a book against women in the military;
and Rep. Patricia Schroeder, D-Colo., who supports women serving in
combat positions.
   ``It has been my contention all along that it is because of a
confused policy that the Army, especially 82nd Airborne Division,
is just not quite sure where to put its females in when comes to
actual operational roles, especially considering the mission the
82nd has as a quick deployment force,'' Ms. Maskus said.
   Jehn acknowledged the Army policy that bans women in combat
units but allows them in groups such as supply battalions and
military police who can be fired upon may seem inconsistent.
   ``It seems inconsistent to many, I know,'' he said. ``It is very
difficult to defend putting women at risk in one situation and not
in others except on the basis of some of the arguments we've heard
earlier that the presence of wommen in combat units would in some
way or another adversely affect the effectiveness of those units.''
   Ms. Maskus said she does not look forward to facing fire but
hopes her complaint paves the way for other women who want to serve
in the armed forces.
   ``I'll take it as far I have to take it, which can be all the
way up to the Department of the Army, Congress, the president if
need be, just to be sure that females that come into the 82nd
Airborne Division behind me do not face the same problem,'' she
said.
   The invasion resulted in the surrender of ousted Panamanian
dictator Manuel Antonio Noriega, who was brought to the United
States to face drug charges.
   Twenty-three U.S. servicemen died in the invasion.
   About 600 of the 24,500 U.S. soldiers who participated in the
invasion were women.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0002 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 2332EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Panama 1stLd-Writethru   01-14 0550</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0731,0563</SECOND>
<HEAD>Cuban Ambassador Held By U.S. Soldiers In Panama</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 7 grafs to UPDATE with Cuban ambassador detained
for more than two hours. Pick up 7th pvs, `The Cuban....'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By MARIA VICTORIA GONZALEZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   U.S. soldiers briefly detained the
Cuban ambassador Sunday, officials said. It was the second time he
was stopped and searched since the invasion to oust Gen. Manuel
Antonio Noriega.
   Also Sunday, Manuel Solis Palma, a former president under
Noriega, was reportedly in the Venezuelan Embassy waiting for word
on his petition for asylum.
   At a roadblock outside the Cuban Embassy, U.S. troops stopped
Ambassador Lazaro Mora Secada and two other embassy officials, the
Cuban consul said.
   ``The ambassador was going home in a vehicle with diplomatic
plates,'' said the consul, Jose Luis Mendez. ``They took his
passport and would not let him leave if he didn't let them check
(the group).''
   Mendez said he was detained at 1:45 p.m.
   A U.S. Embassy official confirmed the report, and added that the
ambassador had been released by 4 p.m. ``It's been resolved,'' said
the official, who was reached by telephone. He did not elaborate.
   On Dec. 28, Mora was stopped by U.S. forces and had to go with
them to obtain documents for another embassy employee traveling
with him.
   The Cuban Embassy has given refuge to Noriega's family. The
Panamanian government of Guillermo Endara, which replaced Noriega
after the Dec. 20 invasion, has refused to allow the Noriega family
to leave for exile in the Dominican Republic.
   Noriega sought refuge in the Vatican Embassy on Christmas Eve
and surrendered to U.S. forces 10 days later. He awaits trial on
drug charges in Miami.
   About 500 Cubans in Panama staged a rally Sunday to publicize
their efforts to seek asylum in the United States.
   Hector Higueras, vice president of the Cuban Refugees Commission
of Panama, said the refugees are asking the U.S. and Panamanian
governments ``that they give their technical and material support
... for the United States to urgently accept their immigration.''
   Higueras said the Cuban refugees do not have permission to work
and have no rights in Panama. He said that under a deal between
Cuba and the deposed Noriega government, the Cubans paid $8,000 to
$20,000 to come to Panama as a transit point to the United States.
   Solis Palma's wife said Saturday that she believed her husband
had taken refuge in the Venezuelan Embassy. Solis Palma was
appointed president on Feb. 26 when Arturo Delvalle was removed for
trying to fire Noriega. He held the post until Sept. 1, 1989.
   In Caracas, President Carlos Andres Perez said that his
government was studying Solis Palma's petition for asylum.
   ``This is possible, because we are devoted to the right of
asylum and we cannot deny asylum to anyone without an evaluation,''
Perez told reporters.
   Troops continue to surround several foreign embassies, including
those of Cuba and Nicaragua, where an undetermined number of
Noriega's officers and cronies are believed to have sought asylum.
   Noriega's wife, Felicidad, and the couple's three daughters have
been inside the Cuban Embassy residence since the night of the
invasion and U.S. soldiers have blocked off most traffic in that
neighborhood, located in the plush San Francisco district of the
capital.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0003 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 2332EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a BC-AceAwards-List 2Takes   01-14 0612</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Ace Awards-List, 2 Takes,0651</SECOND>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here is a complete list of the 11th annual
ACE Awards announced Friday and Sunday night, honoring outstanding
achievement in cable television programming:
   1. DRAMATIC SERIES: ``The Ray Bradbury Theater,'' USA Network.
   2. ACTOR IN A DRAMATIC SERIES: Harold Gould, ``The Ray Bradbury
Theater: To the Chicago Abyss,'' USA Network.
   3. ACTRESS IN A DRAMATIC SERIES: Sydney Walsh, ``Vietnam War
Story: Dirty Work,'' Home Box Office.
   4. DIRECTING IN A DRAMATIC SERIES: David Burton Morris,
``Vietnam War Story: Dirty Work,'' Home Box Office.
   5. WRITING A DRAMATIC SERIES: Terry Black, ``Tales From the
Crypt: Dig That Cat ... He's Real Gone,'' Home Box Office.
   6. COMEDY SERIES: ``It's Garry Shandling's Show,'' Showtime.
   7. ACTOR IN A COMEDY SERIES: Mark McKinney, ``The Kids in the
Hall,'' Home Box Office.
   8. ACTRESS IN A COMEDY SERIES: Lucy Webb, ``Not Necessarily the
News,'' Home Box Office.
   9. DIRECTING A COMEDY SERIES: Alan Rafkin, ``It's Garry
Shandling's Show: The Natural,'' Showtime.
   10. WRITING A COMEDY SERIES: Tom Gammill, Max Pross, Alan
Zweibel, Garry Shandling, ``It's Garry Shandling's Show: What's
Happening to Me?'' Showtime.
   11. MOVIE OR MINISERIES: ``Murderers Among Us: The Simon
Wiesenthal Story,'' Home Box Office.
   12. ACTOR IN A MOVIE OR MINISERIES: Ruben Blades, ``HBO
Showcase: Dead Man Out,'' Home Box Office.
   13. ACTRESS IN A MOVIE OR MINISERIES: Vanessa Redgrave, ``A Man
for All Seasons,'' TNT.
   14. SUPPORTING ACTOR IN A MOVIE OR MINISERIES: James Whitmore,
``Glory! Glory!'' Home Box Office.
   15. SUPPORTING ACTRESS IN A MOVIE OR MINISERIES: Mimi Maynard,
``The Forgotten,'' USA Network.
   16. DIRECTING A MOVIE OR MINISERIES: Brian Gibson, ``Murderers
Among Us: The Simon Wiesenthal Story,'' Home Box Office.
   17. WRITING A MOVIE OR MINISERIES: Ron Hutchinson, J.D. Maria
and Lorna Soroko, ``HBO Showcase: Dead Man Out,'' Home Box Office.
   18. DRAMATIC OR THEATRICAL SPECIAL: ``HBO Showcase: Lip
Service,'' Home Box Office.
   19. VARIETY SPECIAL OR SERIES: ``The Magic Circus: Cirque Du
Soleil,'' Home Box Office.
   20. COMEDY SPECIAL: ``One Night Stand: Dom Irrera,'' Home Box
Office.
   21. PERFORMANCE IN A COMEDY SPECIAL: Bill Maher, ``One Night
Stand: Bill Maher,'' Home Box Office.
   22. DIRECTING A COMEDY SPECIAL: Dean Parisot, ``Steven Wright in
`The Appointments, of Dennis Jennings,''' Home Box Office.
   23. ENTERTAINMENT HOST: Billy Crystal, Whoopi Goldberg and Robin
Williams, ``Comic Relief III,'' Home Box Office.
   24. WRITING AN ENTERTAINMENT SPECIAL: Dick Blasucci and Martin
Short, ``HBO Comedy Hour: I, Martin Short Goes Hollywood,'' Home
Box Office.
   25. MUSIC SERIES: ``New Visions,'' MTV Networks.
   26. PERFORMANCE IN A MUSIC SPECIAL OR SERIES: Bruce Springsteen,
``HBO World Stage: The Human Rights Now Tour,'' Home Box Office.
   27. MUSIC SPECIAL: ``Gloria Estefan &amp; Miami Sound Machine,''
Showtime.
   28. DIRECTING A MUSIC SPECIAL OR SERIES: Jim Yukich, ``Gloria
Estefan &amp; Miami Sound Machine,'' Showtime.
   29. SPORTS EVENTS COVERAGE SERIES: ``Speedworld '89,'' ESPN.
   30. SPORTS EVENTS COVERAGE SPECIAL: ``World Championship Boxing:
Mike Tyson vs. Bruno,'' Home Box Office.
   31. SPORTS INFORMATION SPECIAL: ``The Golden Age of Sport,''
Home Box Office.
   32. SPORTS INFORMATION SERIES: ``Inside the NFL,'' Home Box
Office.
   33. SPORTS NEWS SERIES: ``NFL GameDay,'' ESPN.
   34. SPORTS HOST: Paul Ryden, ``NBA Halftime Show,'' TBS
SuperStation.
   35. SPORTS PLAY-BY-PLAY ANNOUNCER: Marv Albert, ``NY Knicks
Basketball,'' Madison Square Garden Network.
   36. SPORTS COMMENTATOR OR ANALYST: Benny Parsons,
``SpeedWorld,'' ESPN.
   37. DIRECTING LIVE SPORTS EVENTS COVERAGE SPECIAL OR SERIES:
Marc Payton, ``ESPN Sunday Night NFL,'' ESPN.
   38. DOCUMENTARY SERIES: ``Rockumentary,'' MTV Networks.
   39. DOCUMENTARY SPECIAL: ``You Don't Have to Die,'' Home Box
Office.
   40. INFORMATION OR DOCUMENTARY HOST: Larry King ``Larry King's
Night of Soviet Television,'' TBS SuperStation.
   41. DIRECTING A DOCUMENTARY: Malcolm Clarke, ``You Don't Have To
Die,'' Home Box Office.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0004 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 2334EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a BC-AceAwards-List 1stAdd   01-14 0672</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Ace Awards-List, 1st Add,0710</SECOND>
<HEAD>LOS ANGELES: Box Office.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   42. NEWS SPECIAL OR SERIES: ``The Big Story: The Big Spill,''
CNN.
   43. NEWSCASTER: Bernard Shaw, ``Bernard Shaw's Coverage of
China.''
   44. EXTENDED NEWS OR PUBLIC AFFAIRS COVERAGE: ``China
Coverage,'' CNN.
   45. PUBLIC AFFAIRS SPECIAL OR SERIES: ``Smoking: Everything You
and Your Family Need to Know,'' Home Box Office.
   46. TALK SHOW SPECIAL OR SERIES: ``The Capital Gain,'' CNN.
   47. PROGRAM INTERVIEWER: Larry King, ``Larry King Live,'' CNN.
   48. MAGAZINE SHOW SPECIAL OR SERIES: ``National Geographic
EXPLORER,'' TBS SuperStation.
   49. GAME SHOW SPECIAL OR SERIES: ``Top Card,'' The Nashville
Network.
   50. INTERNATIONAL DOCUMENTARY SPECIAL: ``Shattered Dreams:
Picking Up the Pieces,'' The Discovery Channel.
   51. INTERNATIONAL DOCUMENTARY SERIES: ``AIDS Now,'' BRAVO Cable
Network.
   52. INTERNATIONAL COMEDY SPECIAL OR SERIES OR DRAMATIC SERIES OR
MINISERIES: ``The Rainbow,'' A&amp;E Network.
   53. INTERNATIONAL DRAMATIC SPECIAL OR MOVIE: ``Sweet As You
Are,'' A&amp;E Network.
   54. INTERNATIONAL MUSIC SPECIAL OR SERIES: ``Stage: Jacques
Loussier: Bach to Bach,'' A&amp;E Network.
   55. INTERNATIONAL CULTURAL OR PERFORMING ARTS SPECIAL OR SERIES:
``The Modern World: Ten Great Writers,'' BRAVO Cable Network.
   56. INTERNATIONAL THEATRICAL SPECIAL OR SERIES: ``Stage: The
Rivals,'' A&amp;E Network.
   57. INTERNATIONAL EDUCATIONAL OR INSTRUCTIONAL SPECIAL OR
SERIES: ``The Wolf In Your Living Room,'' The Discovery Channel.
   58. INTERNATIONAL NEWS, PUBLIC AFFAIRS, MAGAZINE, TALK SPECIAL
OR SERIES: ``Coup d'Etat _ The Philippines Revolt,'' The Discovery
Channel.
   59. INTERNATIONAL CHILDREN'S PROGRAMMING SPECIAL OR SERIES:
``Babar,'' Home Box Office.
   60. CULTURAL OR PERFORMING ARTS SPECIAL OR SERIES: ``Stage:
Irving Berlin: Voice of the City,'' A&amp;E Network.
   61. EDUCATIONAL OR INSTRUCTIONAL SPECIAL: ``How to Raise a Drug
Free Child,'' Home Box Office.
   62. EDUCATIONAL OR INSTRUCTIONAL SERIES: ``What Every Baby
Knows: the First Three Years,'' Lifetime.
   63. RECREATION AND LEISURE SPECIAL OR SERIES: ``Living
Dangerously: In Clippers Wake,'' A&amp;E Network.
   64. CHILDREN'S PROGRAMMING _ 8 AND YOUNGER: ``Eureeka's
Castle,'' Nickelodeon.
   65. CHILDREN'S PROGRAMMING _ 9 AND OLDER: ``Roald Dahl's Danny
The Champion of the World,'' The Disney Channel.
   66. ANIMATED PROGRAMMING SPECIAL OR SERIES: ``The Railway
Dragon,'' The Disney Channel.
   67. SHORT-FORM PROGRAMMING SPECIAL: ``Not in My Backyard,'' CNN.
   68. SHORT-FORM PROGRAMMING SERIES: ``Global Village News,''
Nickelodeon.
   69. DIRECTION OF PHOTOGRAPHY AND-OR LIGHTING DIRECTION FOR A
COMEDY OR MUSIC SPECIAL: David Agress, Bob Dickinson, Dino
Meminger, Brian Monahan, ``Frank, Liza, and Sammy: The Ultimate
Event,'' Showtime Event Television.
   70. DIRECTION OF PHOTOGRAPHY AND-OR LIGHTING DIRECTION FOR A
COMEDY OR DRAMATIC SERIES: Dean Cundey, ``Tales From The Crypt: And
All Through The House,'' Home Box Office.
   71. DIRECTION OF PHOTOGRAPHY AND-OR LIGHTING DIRECTION FOR A
DRAMATIC OR THEATRICAL SPECIAL, MOVIE OR MINISERIES _ Don Burgess,
``Breaking Point,'' TNT.
   72. ART DIRECTION FOR A COMEDY OR MUSIC SPECIAL: Bruce Ryan and
Mitch Gill, ``5th Annual MTV Video Music Awards,'' MTV Networks.
   73. ART DIRECTION FOR A COMEDY OR DRAMATIC SERIES: John Blackie,
``The Ray Bradbury Theater: To The Chicago Abyss,'' USA Network.
   74. ART DIRECTION FOR A DRAMATIC OR THEATRICAL SPECIAL, MOVIE OR
MINISERIES: Jozsef Rombari, ``Murderers Among Us: The Simon
Wiesenthal Story,'' Home Box Office.
   75. COSTUME DESIGN FOR A COMEDY OR DRAMATIC SERIES: Jill
Blackie, ``The Ray Bradbury Theater: To The Chicago Abyss,'' USA
Network.
   76. COSTUME DESIGN FOR AN ENTERTAINMENT SPECIAL, MOVIE OR
MINISERIES: Tiny Nichols and Joyce Stoneman, ``Great
Expectations,'' The Disney Channel.
   77. EDITING A COMEDY SPECIAL OR SERIES OR MUSIC SPECIAL: Jerry
Behrens, ``Gloria Estefan &amp; Miami Sound Machine,'' Showtime.
   78. EDITING A DRAMATIC SPECIAL OR SERIES OR THEATRICAL SPECIAL,
MOVIE OR MINISERIES: Eva Gardos and Chris Wimble, ``Murderers Among
Us: The Simon Wiesenthal Story,'' Home Box Office.
   79. EDITING A DOCUMENTARY SPECIAL OR SERIES: Bobby Jones, ``The
Making of a Legend: Gone with the Wind,'' TNT.
   80. ORIGINAL SONG: John Lewis Parker and Stephanie Tyrell, ``How
Can I Be Sure,'' from ``Glory! Glory!,'' Home Box Office.
   81. ORIGINAL SCORE: Alan Silvestri, ``Tales From The Crypt: And
All Through The House,'' Home Box Office.
   82. MAKE-UP: Tom Brumberger, ``Fred Travalena's Great Debate of
'88,'' The Family Channel.
   SPECIAL GOLDEN ACE AWARD: CNN for its coverage of the Beijing
uprising.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0005 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 2351EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-StormKoryn 1stLd-Writethru a0728 01-14 0328</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Storm Koryn, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0728,0334</SECOND>
<HEAD>Typhoon Heads North of Island Territory</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 8 grafs to UPDATE with typhoon headed north of
Saipan, storm's position, storm believed to have reached peak,
water service partly restored on Guam, residents leaving Guam
shelters; picks up 10th graf, `The Guam ...' Monday is cq.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>SAIPAN, Northern Marianas Islands (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Typhoon Koryn headed
north of this U.S. island commonwealth in the Pacific Ocean on
Monday with winds gusting to 110 mph, and forecasters believed the
storm had hit its peak, officials said.
   On Guam, crews worked to clear damage and restore water and
power service cut when the storm hit Sunday night.
   By noon Monday (9 p.m. Sunday EST), Koryn's center was 40 miles
north of Saipan, and the storm was moving north-northeast at 8 mph,
said Navy Lt. Diane Crittenden of the Joint Typhoon Warning Center
on Guam.
   The typhoon, with maximum sustained winds of 85 mph and gusts
reaching 110 mph, was believed to have reached its peak, she said.
   If the storm kept to its course, it would not hit any other
islands in the Northern Marianas, but might hit the Japanese island
of Minami-Tori, according to Ms. Crittendon.
   Residents on Saipan boarded up houses, put boats to sea and
moved to community shelters, said Civil Defense coordinator Felix
Sasamopo. The airport was closed.
   On Guam, water service was restored to about 40 percent of the
island's population of 130,000, and 40 percent remained without
electricity, said Ben Reyes, a staff officer with Guam Civil
Defense.
   Winds tore tin roofs off two houses in Guam and forced more than
500 people into emergency shelters Sunday, but only a few remained
in shelters after the storm passed, said Reyes. Two minor injuries
were reported.
   The Guam airport was reopened after the typhoon passed. Guam is
also home to Andersen Air Force Base.
   Both Guam and the Northern Marianas are located west of the
International Date Line.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0006 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 0051EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p AM-Cranston-Poll     01-14 0400</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Cranston-Poll,0414</SECOND>
<HEAD>Poll Finds Cranston Out Of Favor With San Francisco Voters</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SAN FRANCISCO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   San Franciscans, who have strongly
supported U.S. Sen. Alan Cranston, said by more than a 2-1 margin
that he should not seek re-election and they would not vote for
him, according to a newspaper poll.
   City residents surveyed in the poll published in Sunday's
editions of the San Francisco Examiner said by a 4-1 margin that
Cranston'sconduct on behalf of a troubled savings and loan was
improper.
   But four out of five said the state's senior senator, who has
promised to run for a fifth term in 1992, should be allowed to
serve out his term.
   ``If you see these numbers in San Francisco, you can only assume
the numbers are worse elsewhere,'' said Bruce Cain, a political
scientist who is associate director of the Institute of
Governmental Studies at the University of California, Berkeley.
   In the poll conducted from Dec. 26 to Dec. 30 by Richard Hertz
Consulting of Bodega Bay, 401 city residents were interviewed by
telephone.
   Cranston, the Democratic majority whip, is one of five senators
under fire for interceding with regulators on behalf of Charles
Keating Jr., president of Lincoln Savings &amp; Loan. Cranston's
re-election committee and voter registration efforts received a
total of more than $1.2 million in contributions from Keating.
   The institution went bankrupt, and regulators estimate taxpayers
will have to pay up to $2 billion to cover its loss of federally
insured deposits through sham land transactions, fraud and
racketeering.
   Cranston called his backing of Keating a ``political mistake,''
but denied it was improper or illegal.
   Asked whether Cranston acted properly, 53.1 percent of
respondents said no, 10 percent said yes, and 36.9 percent said
they did not know.
   To the question of whether the senator should run again, 56.4
percent said no, 27.7 percent said yes and 16 percent said they did
not know.
   Asked whether they would vote for Cranston again, 53.4 percent
said no, 23.4 percent said yes and 23.2 percent said they did not
know.
   The poll had a margin of error of plus or minus 5 percent.
   When Cranston first took office in 1968, San Franciscans gave
him 80 percent of their vote. He received 78 percent in 1974, 80
percent in 1980 and 74 percent in 1986, his closest election in
which he won by less than 1 percent statewide.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0007 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 0044EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-MotherTeresa-Accident 3rdLd-Writethru   01-14 0296</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mother Teresa-Accident, 3rd Ld-Writethru,a0617,a0618,0301</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ambulance From Mother Teresa's Hospital Kills 2 When Brakes Fail</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Leads with 7 grafs to UPDATE with details, quote. Pickup 6th
graf `Mother Teresa won...'</NOTE>
<DATELINE>CALCUTTA, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An ambulance operated by Mother Teresa's
hospital veered onto a sidewalk when its brakes failed, killing two
pedestrians and seriously injuring two others, police said Sunday.
   Police initially reported the 79-year-old Nobel Peace Prize
winner was in the ambulance when the accident happened Saturday.
But police and Mother Teresa's fellow Roman Catholic nuns said
Sunday she was not in the vehicle.
   ``There was confusion because she reached the scene within
minutes,'' a police duty officer said Sunday, speaking on condition
of anonymity.
   The accident occurred near the Missionaries of Charity building
where Mother Teresa resides. Several nuns, wearing blue and white
saris identical to Mother Teresa's attire, were in the ambulance,
adding to the confusion.
   The ambulance was carrying medical supplies but no patients when
the accident happened.
   The ambulance struck two pedestrians who had just stepped off
the sidewalk into the street, police said. The vehicle, running out
of control after its brakes failed, then veered onto the sidewalk
and struck two more people, according to the police reports.
   Mother Teresa accompanied the four seriously injured people to a
nearby hospital, where two of them later died, the police report
said.
   Mother Teresa won the 1979 Nobel Peace Prize for her work among
the poor. She suffered a heart attack Sept. 5 but resumed work last
week.
   The Yugoslav-born nun founded the Missionaries of Charity in
October 1959 in an abandoned hostel donated by the city of
Calcutta. The order, which was formally recognized by the Vatican
in 1965, expanded and now has 3,000 nuns working in 87 countries.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0008 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 0117EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-GiantFrogs Disregard   01-14 0028</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Giant Frogs, Disregard,0028</SECOND>
<TEXT>
   
   Eds: Please disregard a0411, PM-Giant Frogs, a story from last
week that moved on these circuits because of computer error.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>The AP</HEAD>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0009 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 0149EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-SiameseTwins     01-14 0132</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Siamese Twins,0135</SECOND>
<HEAD>Siamese Twins Separated In Australia, Doing Well</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MELBOURNE, Australia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Siamese twin girls were reported in
stable condition Sunday after being separated in a 7{-hour
operation at Royal Children's Hospital.
   Hospital spokesman Don Kinsey said the girls were progressing
well after the operation to separate them on Thursday.
   Kinsey said a 25-member surgical team led by Dr. Keith Stokes
separated the girls, who were 11 days old on the day of the
operation. The operation involved separating two livers and two
digestive tracts.
   Kinsey said the operation was the fourth successful separation
of Siamese twins carried out at the hospital and the 33rd
successful operation of its kind since 1690 when international
records for the operation were first kept.
   The name of the family was not revealed.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0010 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 0223EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Koryn 1stLd-Writethru   01-14 0304</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Koryn, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0616,0312</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<HEAD>Tropical Storm Off Guam Upgraded To Typhoon</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Leads with 8 grafs to UPDATE with storm upgraded to typhoon,
details. Pickup 7th graf `All Navy...'</NOTE>
<DATELINE>AGANA, Guam (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Tropical storm Koryn became a full-fledged
typhoon Sunday, lashing this U.S. Pacific territory with strong
winds and heavy rains, toppling trees and flooding low-lying areas,
authorities said.
   There were no immediate reports of injuries or damage to
structures.
   As of 5 p.m. (2 a.m. EST), Koryn had sustained winds of 75 mph,
with gusts to 90 mph, according to Navy Lt. Joe Atangan of the
Joint Typhoon Warning Center Rapid Response Team.
   The storm's center was located 45 miles east of the northern tip
of the island, where Andersen Air Force Base is located, Atangan
said.
   The typhoon was ``quasi stationary'' but was expected to move
off to the north-northwest, skirting the northern coast, he said.
   Guam and the Northern Mariana Islands remained under a typhoon
alert, although the projected path of the storm would take it south
of the Marianas and away from any other islands, Atangan said.
   There were reports on Guam of intermittent power outages because
of downed lines, and flooding was reported in many areas, the
Pacific Daily News said.
   ``There's lots of coconuts on the roads,'' Atangan said.
   All Navy aircraft were placed in hangers for protection against
the strong winds, and the USS Haleakala was sent out to sea to
weather the storm, said Lt. Dave Lee. Three other warships were
allowed to remain in port, he said.
   The 12 planes at Andersen, including 11 B-52s, were parked
behind fortifications as the storm approached, said base spokesman
Capt. Wayne Perry.
   A tropical storm has sustained winds ranging from 39 to 73 mph.
A typhoon has a minimum sustained surface wind of 74 mph.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0011 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 0238EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-RadioactiveWreck 1stLd-Writethru a0602 01-14 0332</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Radioactive Wreck, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0602,0337</SECOND>
<HEAD>Truck Carrying Radioactive Material Crashes, Killing 1, Forcing
Evacuation</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 7th graf, `They were...,' to CORRECT spelling of
material to Americium, sted Amercurian. Dayne in 9th graf is cq.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>CHINA GROVE, N.C. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A car crashed into a tractor-trailer
carrying low-level radioactive material on Interstate 85, killing
one person and prompting the evacuation of about 225 people,
officials said.
   Lynne Denise Beatty, 29, of Charlotte was killed in the accident
at 9:05 p.m. Friday, the state highway patrol said. Ms. Beatty
suffered a seizure while driving south on I-85 and her car crossed
the median and struck the tractor-trailer head on, police said.
   The truck, owned by Consolidated Freightways, continued about
three-tenths of a mile before it stopped and the cab burst into
flames, according to the report filed by Highway Patrol Trooper
W.D. Greene.
   James Nelson Brown of Charlotte, the driver, was treated for
minor injuries.
   As a precaution against radioactive contamination, authorities
evacuated 75 homes in a quarter-mile area around the accident scene
at the exit ramp of U.S. 29 onto I-85, said Frank Thomason,
communications supervisor with the Rowan County Emergency
Operations Center.
   About 225 residents left their homes; 52 went to a shelter set
up by the county, authorities said.
   They were allowed to return home about 2 a.m. Saturday after
emergency personnel learned that the radioactive material consisted
of Cesium 137 and Americium 241, both used for soil testing,
authorities said. The cargo was bound for Durham.
   ``It has a very low radioactivity,'' Greene said.
   The radioactive material did not pose a significant threat to
people in the area, said Dayne Brown, director of the N.C. Division
of Radiation Protection.
   A hazardous materials team went to the scene and inspected for
any radioactive leaks, Thomason said.
   ``If there was any leak it was very minimal,'' he said.
   Southbound lanes of the interstate were reopened at about 3
a.m., and northbound lanes were reopened about 6 a.m.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0012 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 0252EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Spain-Fire 1stLd-Writethru   01-14 0204</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Spain-Fire, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0623,0209</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<HEAD>At Least 43 Killed in Disco Fire</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: UPDATES with report that 44 bodies recovered, CORRECTS
governor's middle name to Perez, short circuit suspected as cause</NOTE>
<DATELINE>ZARAGOZA, Spain (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Fire broke out in a basement discotheque
early Sunday, and at least 43 people died of smoke inhalation, said
officials in this northern city.
   Firefighters extinguished the blaze which erupted about 3:45
a.m. (9:45 p.m. EST Saturday) in the Flying disco. About 130 people
were inside when the fire broke out, said Civil Gov. Carlos Perez
Anadon.
   Forty-three people died and three others were hospitalized for
smoke inhalation, said the civil governor in this city about 160
miles northeast of the capital Madrid.
   EFE, the official Spanish news agency, said 44 bodies were
recovered.
   The civil governor was quoted by EFE as saying the dead ranged
in age from 35 to 50 years old.
   The news agency quoted an unidentified government spokesman as
saying an electrical short circuit was suspected of sparking the
blaze after first causing a power blackout.
   Six years ago, more than 90 people died in a basement disco fire
in the Alcala 20 discotheque in Madrid, also from inhalation of
toxic fumes and smoke.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0013 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 0513EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i BC-China-Quake     01-14 0106</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-China-Quake,0109</SECOND>
<HEAD>Strong Quake Hits Remote Northwest</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A strong earthquake cracked buildings in
northwest China's Qinghai province Sunday, but there were no
reports of casualties, the official Xinhua News Agency said.
   It said the quake measuring 6.7 on the Richter scale hit
Mangnai, a small outpost 1,300 miles west of the capital Beijing.
People at a nearby oilfield felt the temblor and found cracks in
their buildings.
   The Richter scale is a gauge of the energy released by an
earthquake, as measured by the ground motion recorded on a
seismograph. A quake meauring 6 can cause severe damage in a
populated area.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0014 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 0531EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i BC-Koryn     01-14 0325</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Koryn,0336</SECOND>
<HEAD>Typhoon Sweeps by Guam, Heads for Marianas</HEAD>
<DATELINE>AGANA, Guam (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Typhoon Koryn, packing sustained winds of 75
mph and gusts to 90 mph, swept past this U.S. Pacific territory
Sunday night before heading toward the Northern Mariana Islands,
authorities said.
   High winds and heavy rains knocked out electricity over 30
percent of Guam, cutting power to 56 of the island's 90 water
wells, officials said.
   Winds ranging from 35 to 55 mph ripped tin roofs off two houses
and forced 21 people into emergcy shelters, the officials said.
   There were two reports of minor injuries. A 50-year-old man
suffered a cut ear while trying to put up shutters and a
46-year-old woman was injured when she was blown into a pole. Both
were treated and released from Guam Memorial Hospital, a hospital
spokesman said.
   As of 7 p.m. (4 a.m. EST), Koryn was 44 miles northeast of Guam,
moving to the northwest at 8 mph, according to Navy Lt.j.g. Ken
Minogue of the Joint Typhoon Warning Center Rapid Response Team.
   The typhoon was forecast to pass to the north of Rota, the most
southern of the Northern Marianas, a U.S. commonwealth, some 40
miles north of Guam, Minogue said.
   Rota was getting heavy rains and winds up to 50 mph, the same
conditions the Mariana islands of Tinian and Saipan could expect
Monday, he said.
   On Guam, all Navy aircraft were placed in hangers for protection
against the strong winds, and the USS Haleakala was sent out to sea
to weather the storm, said Lt. Dave Lee. Three other warships were
allowed to remain in port, he said.
   Twelve planes, including 11 B-52s, at Andersen Air Force Base on
the north coast of Guam, were parked behind fortifications as the
storm approached, said base spokesman Capt. Wayne Perry.
   A tropical storm has sustained winds ranging from 39 to 73 mph.
A typhoon has a minimum sustained surface wind of 74 mph.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0015 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 0608EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i BC-Spain-Fire     01-14 0514</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Spain-Fire,0531</SECOND>
<HEAD>Disco Blaze Kills 43, Electrical Malfunction Blamed</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ZARAGOZA, Spain (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An electrical fire broke out in a
discotheque early Sunday, giving off poisonous smoke that killed 43
people and injured three others, said officials in this northern
city.
   The victims were in the basement of the club where a local band
was playing when the fire broke out, and many of the dead ``were
still sitting in their chairs'' when they were found, said Deputy
Mayor Luis Garcia Nieto.
   The blaze began shortly before 2:40 a.m. near the front door of
the Flying discotheque, filled with about 130 people, government
spokesman Ignacio Bruna said in this city about 160 miles northeast
of the capital Madrid.
   The smoke funneled through air conditioning ducts down to the
basement, where the dance floor, bar and lounge are located, said
the central government representative in Zaragoza, Carlos Perez
Anadon.
   Firefighters arrived eight minutes after the blaze broke out and
quickly extinguished the flames, but rescue workers could do little
to save the victims, said Garcia Nieto, speaking to Spanish
National Radio (RNE).
   The speed with which people died may have been due to the
presence of hydrocyanic acid in the smoke, the national news
service EFE quoted civil protection head Antonio Herrera as saying.
Hydrocyanic acid is used to produce acryclics.
   Bruna said a woman was being treated for smoke inhalation in the
intensive care unit of Miguel Servet hospital, which reported her
condition as serious. Two others had been treated for minor
injuries, he added.
   He said preliminary information indicated the fire was caused by
an electrical overload.
   ``It began on the ground floor, near the door,'' he said, adding
all 43 killed had been in the discotheque's basement and died of
smoke inhalation.
   At the municipal morgue, several dozen anxious people waited to
find out whether family members were among the dead.
   Bruna said 25 victims had been identified as area residents.
Their ages ranged from 21 to 52, but most were between 25 and 35
years old.
   Garcia Nieto said the discotheque had been licensed Oct. 3,
1984, a year after authorities passed a new series of tough fire
regulations after a Dec. 17, 1983 fire killed more than 90 people
in the Alcala 20 discotheque in Madrid.
   He said the discotheque had been routinely investigated since
then to ensure it complied with the regulations.
   ``It would appear (the discotheque) was in compliance with all
the regulations,'' Bruna said.
   The national news agency EFE quoted a waitress who said the fire
blocked one of the two stairways leading from the basement to the
street.
   ``I smelled something burning, and in seconds nobody could get
out,'' said the waitress, who added she escaped up the main
stairway after seeing the emergency steps were blocked by flames.
   ``While I was going up towards the main door, a group of
customers, probably blinded by the smoke, were trying to get up the
emergency steps. But I'm sure they couldn't get out, because the
fire was there,'' said the waitress, who was not identified.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0016 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 0729EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i BC-Soviet-Unrest     01-14 0236</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Soviet-Unrest,0251</SECOND>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Calls to drive Armenians from the capital of
Soviet Azerbaijan touched off a riot in which 22 people were
killed, mostly Armenians, Soviet radio reported Sunday.
   The Saturday night rampage in the southern republic was only the
latest violence between Armenians and Azerbaijanis, who have been
locked in a nearly two-year feud over who should govern
Nagorno-Karabakh, a mostly Armenian enclave.
   Radio Moscow said news that an Azerbaijani had been killed and
another wounded by an axe-wielding Armenian family in Baku,
Azerbaijan's capital, was announced at a Saturday night rally in
the city's central square attended by 150,000 people.
   The two Azerbaijanis earlier Saturday had demanded that the
Armenian family leave Baku and a struggle ensued, the radio said.
   The riot broke out after ``calls were made at the rally to drive
the Armenians out of the city,'' the radio correspondent reported
from the Caspian Sea port city.
   Twenty-two people were killed and 26 wounded, the radio
reported. It quoted local Interior Ministry officials as saying
most of the casualties were Armenians.
   Nagorno-Karabakh, an enclave of 160,000 people, has been under
control of mainly Shiite Moslem Azerbaijan since 1923. Attempts to
annex it to predominantly Christian Armenia spurred unrest that has
left about 200 people dead over the last two years.
   Azerbaijan last week renewed a railroad blockade of Armenia,
which gets most of its supplies through the neighboring republic.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0017 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 0931EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a BC-SpaceShuttle 2ndLd-Writethru a0630 01-14 0655</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Space Shuttle, 2nd Ld - Writethru, a0630,0669</SECOND>
<HEAD>Astronauts Pass Halfway Point of Long Space Mission</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 16 grafs to UPDATE with flight director's comments
on first half of flight, broken experiment being fixed; picks up
14th graf, `The astronauts...'</NOTE>
<DATELINE>SPACE CENTER, Houston (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Columbia's astronauts were busy
with medical and science experiments Sunday as they soared past the
halfway point of what a flight director called a ``flawless
flight.''
   Near the midpoint, the crew was beaming to Earth a television
shot of mission specialist Marsha Ivins checking David Low with an
echocardiograph, a device which generates a two-dimensional,
cross-section image of the heart.
   It is one of many experiments the astronauts are conducting to
determine how well the human body adapts to weightlessness in space.
   Columbia, launched Tuesday, is scheduled to land at 2:59 a.m.
PST Friday at Edwards Air Force Base, Calif.
   Assessing the first half of the trip, flight director Al
Pennington said ``it has been a flawless flight. We have a
beautifully running orbiter.
   ``We have achieved our main objectives of releasing the Syncom
satellite and retrieving the Long Duration Exposure Facility,'' he
said. ``For the rest of the time we will do the secondary
experiments and work on the EDO objectives.''
   EDO means extended duration orbiter. The 10-day flight is the
second longest shuttle mission yet and is intended as a stepping
stone toward even longer shuttle flights and months-long trips
aboard space station Freedom.
   The sixth day of the 10-day mission began when fellow Notre Dame
alumni serenaded Columbia pilot Jim Wetherbee with a rousing wakeup
song.
   The strains of ``Notre Dame Victory March,'' sung by an ad hoc
Mission Control choir, were beamed to the shuttle at 12:30 a.m.
   ``That was provided by local alumni of a school you know pretty
well,'' said Mission Control's Ken Bowersox.
   ``Yeah, there's a lot of Damers down there,'' said Wetherbee, a
1974 graduate of the school in aerospace engineering.
   Commander Dan Brandenstein, Wetherbee and mission specialists
Bonnie Dunbar, Ivins and Low were continuing experiments begun the
day of launch, including IMAX movie camera observations of selected
locations on earth.
   ``This is the second-longest shuttle mission that we've had so
far, so we can do some good materials science experiments up here
and we can also get some very good medical data,'' Low said
Saturday.
   One experiment, involving melting and resolidifying a metal,
broke down Friday when a crack developed in a glass container,
probably because of overheating. But Pennington said Sunday that
experts on the ground had worked out a solution to the problem and
the astronauts were working to resume operation of the experiment.
   The glass container, called an ampul, contains the element
indium, a metal that melts at a relatively low temperature. It had
been feared that the cracked glass could shatter, sending shards of
glass floating around the cabin.
   Pennington said one of the astronauts, wearing a mask and
gloves, removed the cracked container and carefully vacuumed the
machine. There was no sign of any loose glass shards, Pennington
said. A new glass ampul will be installed later Sunday, he said.
   The astronauts on Friday captured the 11-ton Long Duration
Exposure Facility, a space laboratory, and tucked it into the
shuttle's cargo bay in time to save it and 57 experiments on board
from burning up in an expected March 9 plunge into Earth's
atmosphere.
   The astronauts took time out for a little fun Saturday
afternoon, playing the song ``Attack of the Killer Tomatoes'' from
a movie by the same name as they showed Mission Control a drawing
of LDEF wildly entwined in tomato vines.
   It was a joking reference to an LDEF experiment that consists of
12.5 million tomato seeds for student experiments and research.
Brandenstein's 22-year-old daughter, Adelle, had sent a greeting to
the crew asking, ``Have the killer tomatoes attacked yet?''
   ``I guess that answers Adelle's question earlier,'' the
commander said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0018 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 1119EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Malaysia-BoatPeople     01-14 0168</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Malaysia-Boat People,0173</SECOND>
<HEAD>Nine More Boat People Bodies Found</HEAD>
<DATELINE>KUALA LUMPUR, Malaysia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Nine more decomposed bodies of
Vietnamese boat people were found off the coast of Malaysia on
Sunday, bringing the total found in the past two days to 23, police
said.
   They were believed to have drowned after their boat sank in
rough waters off the Trengganu coast, the National News Agency
Bernama reported from Kuala Trengganu, the capital of Trengganu
state. It quoted police and hospital sources.
   Fourteen bodies were found Saturday along the coast, 180 miles
northeast of Kuala Lumpur.
   The bodies have been buried at the Vietnamese refugee cemetery
in Kuala Trengganu.
   Early last month, 15 bodies believed to be those of Vietnamese
boat people were spotted along the Marang coast.
   Waters in the South China Sea off Trengganu are rough this time
of year because it is the monsoon season.
   Malaysia accepts Vietnamese boat people for temporary asylum
pending permanent settlement in the United States, Australia,
Canada and other countries.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0019 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 1120EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SouthKorea     01-14 0349</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-South Korea,0359</SECOND>
<HEAD>Police Fire Tear Gas to Break Up Anti-Government Protests in
Downtown Seoul</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KELLY TUNNEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SEOUL, South Korea (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Riot police fired tear gas and punched
protesters Sunday to break up hundreds of radical students who
surged through the streets of a fashionable downtown shopping area
yelling anti-government slogans.
   More than 100 students were arrested in the two-hour clash and
there were some injuries, but a number was not immediately
available.
   Police hit some protesters with their fists and shields, and
students fought back, kicking and screaming. The clashes broke out
after 700 radicals were blocked from holding a commemorative rally
for a student tortured to death by police three years ago.
   ``Drive out yankees!'' students yelled, ``Overthrow (President)
Roh Tae-woo!''
   At one point students attacked about 40 riot police surrounding
about 20 other students, who had been detained and forced to kneel
on the street. ``Pig!'' one student yelled, grabbing a policeman's
helmet.
   Riot police fired tear gas grenades into the narrow streets,
where hundreds of citizens were browsing in boutiques. Stores
closed and shoppers fled, coughing and choking on the gas.
   One plainclothes policeman who chased a protester into a fried
chicken restaurant was chased out by screaming customers who tried
to grab the policeman by his coat.
   ``Chun Doo-hwan must be punished and his successor Roh Tae-woo
must resign to pave the way for democracy!'' students shouted. They
also demanded the withdrawal of 43,000 U.S. troops stationed in
South Korea under a mutual defense pact.
   Radical students, a small but vocal minority on campuses, have
called for the punishment of Roh and his predecessor, Chun
Doo-hwan. They hold both men responsible for a government crackdown
on a civil uprising in Kwangju in 1980 that left at least 200
people dead and 1,500 wounded.
   Violent radical student protests were staged Saturday in
Kwangju, a provincial city south of the capital.
   Sunday's rally in Seoul was in honor of Park Chong-chol, a
university student whose death by torture in 1987 touched off
nationwide protests.
   Police banned the rally in advance.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0020 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 1122EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--BritishCommunists     01-14 0156</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--British Communists,0160</SECOND>
<HEAD>Communist Party Elects First Woman Leader</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Communist Party of Great Britain on Sunday
elected its first woman general secretary, Nina Temple, who is the
party's news media and publicity officer.
   The party's executive committee voted 34 to 1, with three
abstaining.
   Miss Temple, 33, succeeds Gordon McLennan, 62, who retired as
leader of the 7,500-member party after 14 years.
   She said the party ``has become completely marginalized in
British society _partly because of its association with those huge
edifices in Eastern Europe which were so undemocratic, and partly
because of our own self-imposed limitations.''
   Miss Temple joined the Communist Party at age 13 and became
general secretary of the Young Communist League. Her father, Landon
Temple, runs Progressive Tours, which promotes visits to the Soviet
Union.
   Hard-liners broke away from the Communist Party of Great Britain
in 1984, following McLennan's attempts at moderation, and formed a
splinter party.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0021 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 1145EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-HongKong     01-14 0423</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Hong Kong,0435</SECOND>
<HEAD>Pro-Democracy Activists Call for More Democracy</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-China-Flight, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CINTY LI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HONG KONG (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   About 100 activists marched to the governor's
residence on Sunday to plea for more democracy before Britain hands
this colony back to China in 1997.
   They presented a petition addressed to British Foreign Minister
Douglas Hurd, who is in Hong Kong on a four-day visit.
   The protesters want to double the number of directly elected
legislators to 20 of the governing body's 56 seats next year.
   Marching from a downtown park to Governor's House _ the official
residence and office of Gov. Sir David Wilson _ the demonstrators
chanted ``We want democracy, we want human rights'' and ``Full
democracy to people of Hong Kong.''
   ``We are not asking for sympathy from Britain, we are asking for
the rights we deserve,'' said Yeung Sum, a spokesman for the march.
``We hope Hurd would respect Hong Kong people's wishes to set up a
democratic political system in 1991.''
   The demonstration was organized by the Joint Committee on the
Promotion of Democratic Government, which says it includes 150
trade unions, student groups and other organizations.
   In the letter to Hurd, the committee said Hong Kong is a
political orphan because ``China suppresses pro-democracy movements
in Hong Kong and Britain betrays Hong Kong people's rights.''
   ``We who cannot emigrate have to face this problem ... and set
up a real democratic political system,'' the letter said.
   Under a 1984 agreement, Hong Kong is to retain its free-wheeling
capitalist system and a high degree of autonomy for 50 years after
1997. But since the June 4 crackdown on pro-democracy demonstrators
in China, confidence in Beijing's promise has evaporated.
   Since June 4, the government has been pushing a plan to speed up
the pace and extent of democratization in the colony. The
government currently is calling for 18 of the 56 legislature's
seats to be contested in 1991, about 50 percent in 1997 and 100
percent in 2003.
   Currently 24 of the 56 members in the Legislative Council are
elected by bodies representing labor, business and districts. Aside
from the 10 popularly elected, the rest are appointed by the
government.
   When he arrived in Hong Kong on Saturday, Hurd said the ground
rules would be ready for the direct elections in ``a few weeks.''
   Last month, the Chinese-appointed committee writing the Basic
Law, the blueprint to run the territory after 1997, decided that
fewer than 18 seats would be directly elected in the legislature
after 1997.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0022 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 1250EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Video-TobaccoAds     01-14 0783</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Video-Tobacco Ads,0808</SECOND>
<HEAD>Cigarette, Alcohol Ads Appear in Children's Video Games</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PAUL RAEBURN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Editor</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Signs advertising cigarette and alcohol are
appearing in children's video arcade games, with video motorcycles
racing past Budweiser billboards and race cars speeding underneath
Marlboro banners.
   One game, Super Monaco GP, manufactured by Sega of America,
includes Marlboro race cars, billboards, banners and Marlboro signs
in the crowd. Occasionally the cars race past a building in which
all of the windows have been replaced by Marlboro logos.
   In Sega's arcade game Power Drift, race cars pass Budweiser
billboards.
   Philip Morris, the maker of Marlboro, and Anheuser Busch, which
makes Budweiser, said Friday that they had not authorized the use
of their brand names or logos. Philip Morris said it had asked Sega
to recall the games.
   Sega said in a statement that the inclusion of the logos was
``simply a game designer's innocent attempt to mimic real-life
locations.'' It said it was in the process of removing them. The
statement did not indicate how many games were manufactured or how
long they have been in use.
   ``Super Monaco GP is essentially one big Marlboro ad,'' says Dr.
John W. Richards of the Medical College of Georgia, who has
investigated the video game cigarette ads.
   ``A child playing Super Monaco GP is exposed to literally
hundreds of Marlboro ads during the game, if he's good,'' Richards
wrote last month in a letter of complaint to the Federal Trade
Commission. Richards is president of Doctors Ought to Care, or DOC,
an anti-smoking group.
   ``If he's not good and doesn't reach `extended play,' then he'll
see only 50 or so Marlboro ads,'' Richards wrote. A copy of the
letter was obtained by The Associated Press.
   ``I think it's regrettable at best, and scandalous at worst,
that this is happening,'' said Dr. Ronald M. Davis, director of the
Office on Smoking and Health of the U.S. Centers for Disease
Control.
   ``It's a strong indication that the cigarette industry is
interested in luring children to begin to smoke. Certainly with all
the resources available to the cigarette companies, they'd prevent
this obvious copyright infringement if they weren't interested in
kids,'' he said.
   Smoking kills 390,000 Americans each year, and 90 percent of
smokers take up the habit as teen-agers, Davis said.
   Steven Weiss, manager of media relations for Philip Morris USA
in New York, said the company only recently found out about the
video game advertisements.
   ``Sega has not asked permission to use our logo, and, moreover,
we would not grant such permission to use any of our cigarette
logos in any video game, especially those played by minors,'' Weiss
said in an interview Friday.
   ``All our cigarette advertising and promotions are directed at
informed adult smokers only,'' he said.
   Weiss said Philip Morris wrote to Sega on Nov. 20 asking the
company to stop using the Marlboro logo and recall all games that
include it.
   The letter was sent seven days after Rep. Thomas Luken of Ohio
wrote Philip Morris to say his subcommittee wanted to hold hearings
on the video game advertisements.
   A video game in Australia called Pole Position contained the
Marlboro logo in 1983, according to the March 5, 1983, issue of the
Medical Journal of Australia. The journal said that a Philip Morris
official in Australia had been informed then of the existence of
the logos in the games.
   Scott Murdock, director of sales promotion and merchandising for
Anheuser Busch Inc., which makes Budweiser, said in a statement
that the company had not authorized the use of its brand name or
logo. ``Based on the information you have provided to us, we will
ask our legal department to investigate the matter,'' he said.
   Dave Rosen, co-chairman of the board of Sega of America, said in
a statement that ``there is absolutely no form of paid or
intentional advertising displayed in any of Sega's arcade or
consumer video games.''
   ``We're already in the process of removing any graphics that
could unintentionally be construed as real-life product in our
games and packaging,'' he said.
   Richards said he has seen the games at video arcades in South
Carolina, Tennessee and Georgia. The Associated Press found the
same games at a video arcade in New York City's Times Square.
   The Federal Trade Commission, which regulates advertising, said
it cannot disclose whether it is investigating the video game
advertisements. But the commission's new chairman, Janet D. Steiger
said at the time of her confirmation last summer that she is
concerned about the issue.
   ``Allegations that tobacco and alcohol products are being
marketed to young people are matters of serious concern that
deserve priority attention,'' she said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0023 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 1314EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Barry-Jackson Bjt   01-14 0645</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Barry-Jackson, Bjt,620</SECOND>
<HEAD>Jackson Campaign Rumors Seen Straining Friendship With Barry</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RICHARD KEIL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   They marched together in the civil rights army
around Martin Luther King Jr. They call themselves friends. But
whatever remains of the relationship between Marion Barry and Jesse
Jackson is severely strained by today's political realities.
   Barry is fighting for political survival as mayor of the
nation's capital and sees his old friend Jackson as a formidable
obstacle.
   Observers of the byzantine local political scene in Washington
speculate that whatever the mayor did or didn't say in a recent
interview with the Los Angeles Times stemmed from his unease over
the fact Jackson established residence in the capital in time to
qualify for a campaign for mayor.
   ``Jesse don't want to run nothing but his mouth,'' Barry was
quoted as telling a Times reporter. The mayor spent much of the
past week trying to extinguish the political fires that his
comments sparked.
   Jackson has said he believes Barry's assertions that he never
made any of the comments attributed to him in the Times profile.
   But Jackson aides and top city officials said Jackson was angry
enough to call the newspaper and ask whether Barry really made the
remarks. He was told that the interview was tape-recorded.
   It is easy to understand why Barry may frequently be thinking
about his former civil rights colleague.
   Barry and Jackson, who have been friends since both worked with
King, have seen their relationship put under the microscope since
Jackson's April relocation to the nation's capital fueled rumors
that he would try to unseat Barry.
   Jackson has said repeatedly he would never run against Barry,
but he left open the possibility he would enter the race if Barry
decided against seeking a fourth term.
   ``Given that Jackson has not eliminated the possibility of
running, his presence has cast a heavy shadow over Barry's
reelection effort,'' says Julius Hobson, a former city official who
is now an advisor to Sen. Charles Robb, D-Va. ``He is not an
announced candidate, but he is doing all the things that a
candidate has always done in this town _ like visiting the
ministers _ and that certainly makes it more difficult for Barry.''
   Barry, despite trailing several rivals in fund-raising, is
nonetheless predicting he can coast to reelection.
   But federal prosecutors continue their investigation of Barry's
ties to a convicted drug dealer, and an indictment of the mayor
would cripple him politically and open the door for a Jackson
candidacy, the thinking goes.
   Top city officials say Jackson has indicated to them he may be
interested in representing the city as a ``shadow'' senator on
Capitol Hill. The non-voting position, which would pay almost
$80,000 per year, is designed to serve as a platform from which to
lobby for statehood.
   Ironically, the latest tensions between the two old friends
flared despite statements over several weeks from Jackson
associates that indicated he was growing less interested in running
for mayor.
   Jackson recently adopted statehood as his new crusade _ calling
it ``the major social justice issue of the day'' _ and is scheduled
to announce a national statehood lobbying effort on Monday.
   In conversations with congressional leaders, Jackson also has
been told that having Barry at the helm of the city makes statehood
a much tougher proposition, according to Jackson aides.
   ``Jesse has reminded them that Maryland wasn't disenfranchised
when Governor (Marvin) Mandel went to jail,'' said one Jackson aide
who spoke only on condition of anonymity. ``But the problems with
Marion on the Hill are obvious to Jesse, and he can't avoid
thinking about them or dealing with them.''
   ``Statehood works for Jesse,'' Hobson says, ``if that's what he
really wants to do.''
   And for now, the rest of Washington _ from Barry on down _ can
only wonder about Jackson's real intentions.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0024 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 1341EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-HitchhikingCommuters Bjt   01-14 0825</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Hitchhiking Commuters, Bjt,770</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hitchhiking Becomes Commuting Mode in Washington Suburb</HEAD>
<NOTE>With LaserPhoto WX6</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By DAVID BRISCOE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BURKE, Va. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A group of well-dressed hitchhikers was there
waiting when Rose McMurray pulled into the Rolling Valley Mall
parking lot in search of the ``warm bodies'' that would enable her
to use the express lanes on the interstate and get to work on time.
   ``It's a win-win situation for everybody,'' McMurray says as she
piles two riders into her car. Drivers get to use the
high-occupancy vehicle, or HOV, lanes, and cut 20 minutes or more
off from their commute through mind-numbing traffic to downtown
Washington, D.C. Passengers get a free trip.
   Without government direction or subsidy, the informal, instant
carpooling system has evolved into a unique commuting mode that
relieves pressure on the subsidized bus system, cuts congestion and
saves commuters money.
   Transportation researchers call it the ``Springfield
underground'' because it started with the opening 15 years ago of
HOV lanes down the center of I-395 to the Washington suburb of
Springfield, Va. The two-lane HOV lanes are restricted to buses and
cars carrying three or more passengers during rush hour.
   Most carpooling involves people from the same office or the same
neighborhood or those matched by formal programs. But in
Springfield and the nearby bedroom community of Burke, it's stand
there and take your chances.
   The only other area where the instant carpooling occurs on a
large scale is at bus stops leading to the east entrance to the Bay
Bridge between Oakland and San Francisco, according to a study by
the Urban Institute.
   Arlee Reno, who heads transportation projects for the Urban
Institute, said he has taken a slide show on Springfield's
hitchhiking commuting system to Houston, Minneapolis, Seattle and
Los Angeles.
   But researchers caution that several conditions have to be met
if such systems are to work. Among them:
   _At least 500 commuters in the given area.
   _HOV lanes that save enough time to give drivers a reason to
pick up passengers.
   _A parallel bus system that gives hitchhiking commuters an
alternative if no cars show up.
   One drawback of the system is the reluctance of people to climb
into a car with a stranger. But riders see little risk with three
people in the car.
   ``A requirement of two persons per vehicle in order to use the
HOV lanes would undoubtedly result in a much higher level of
psychological resistance to instant carpooling,'' Reno said in a
study of the Springfield system.
   The ``Springfield underground'' has been so successful that
nearly all the spaces in park-and-ride lots along the route are
taken up by hitchhikers, ranging from stylishly dressed single
women to uniformed military officers heading for the Pentagon.
   At one lot, surveyors watched 553 people get into cars with
strangers and only 25 board buses that pass by the lot. Drivers
call out their destinations and the next riders in line pile in.
   Ms. McMurray alternates between driving and hitching rides at
the mall, located about 20 miles southwest of downtown Washington.
   ``All we need is warm bodies for the express lane,'' she says.
   Dottie Cousineau, head of commuter programs for Fairfax County,
said the system has freed morning buses for other areas.
   Some riders also hitch rides in Washington to get home, but Ms.
Cousineau said the system doesn't work as well because workers have
to get to limited pickup points, including ones near the Washington
Monument and at the Pentagon.
   Ms. Cousineau said she has never heard of a complaint about the
system from a driver or a rider.
   ``I guess it's because it's entirely voluntary,'' she said.
   Instant carpooling has fostered a new riding culture and
etiquette. The 30-minute rides may feature the unfriendly silences
more common in elevators or, on the other hand, convivial commutes
that cover the gamut of political and social discussion.
   On the morning after the U.S. invasion of Panama, a military
officer on his way to the Pentagon discussed the timing of the
operation. On another day in another car, an Agricultural
Department worker criticized farm subsidies.
   But the most common topics are the weather and the difficulty of
getting to work in the nation's capital.
   For the commuter, a roundtrip between Fairfax County and
Washington can cost as much as $6.80 a day _ $2.40 each way on
buses and the subway and $2.00 to park at a Metro station. With the
ride-sharing program, the trip is free for the passengers.
   One private lot owned by a movie house was selling parking
stickers that included their value in movie tickets.
   Drivers still have to pay for gas and downtown parking, but they
get to work faster.
   Metropolitan transit officials like the system too, although bus
ridership has decreased on the route.
   ``More power to them,'' said Metro spokeswoman Marilyn Dicus.
``We all have the same goal _ to get more than one person in a
vehicle.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0025 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 1354EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Centenarian-Congress     01-14 0808</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Centenarian-Congress,0836</SECOND>
<HEAD>100-Year-Old Congressional Candidate Says He's Running for
Children's Sake</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto RA1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DENNIS PATTERSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>GOLDSBORO, N.C. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Dr. Henry Stenhouse says he started
thinking about running for Congress when he saw all the young
relatives and friends who turned up for his 100th birthday party
last month.
   ``I got to thinking about the children of this country,''
Stenhouse said Friday as he sat in his small cluttered
ophthalmology office. ``I've been concerned about them for a long
time.
   ``We've been doing a lot of bad planning in this country,'' he
said. ``And it's not us that's going to catch it, it's the
children.''
   Last week Stenhouse, who has never held public office, hitched a
ride with a visiting son for the 60-mile trip to Raleigh to file as
a Republican candidate for the 3rd Congressional District.
   His life has not been the same since.
   ``I've never been under such a siege in my life,'' he said, as
he answered the third phone call in less than 30 minutes. ``I've
had calls from everywhere, people stopping by wanting to help with
the campaign. It's been just wonderful.''
   Stenhouse said he hasn't worked much on a campaign plan yet, but
expects to use a lot of word-of-mouth advertising and speaking to
groups whenever he gets the chance.
   ``I haven't had much experience with public speaking, but I know
I've got the capacity,'' he said. ``My father could hold an
audience spellbound, so quiet you could hear a pin drop, so I know
I've got it in me.''
   He acknowledged, however, ``It might be hard for me to speak
without making some people mad.''
   Stenhouse opposes welfare programs, believes mandatory seat belt
laws should be repealed and thinks women who have children should
stay home to raise them.
   ``I'm going to get some opposition on that one, loads of it,''
Stenhouse said. ``But when a woman has children, she has a
responsibility to raise them, to care for them, not shuttle them
off to some day-care place. You can't have it all and children,
too.''
   Welfare, he said, is the responsibility of churches, not
government.
   ``I think we've got sidetracked somehow,'' he said. ``The
government should have never got into it. I think it's the duty of
churches to look after the needy in their community, but they
aren't doing it.''
   Mandatory seat belt laws, he said, are just an example of big,
intrusive government.
   The three small rooms in Stenhouse's office, where he walks from
home three days a week to see some of his old patients, are crowded
with files, stacks of correspondence, books and pamphlets. The
walls and shelves are covered with photographs and remembrances of
a Navy career that took him to China, the Philippines and the
Virgin Islands.
   The office door has a brass nameplate that was his father's,
also a doctor. Near it is a color photograph of President and Mrs.
Bush, sent to him when he turned 100.
   ``The first vote I ever cast was for William Howard Taft against
Theodore Roosevelt and Woodrow Wilson,'' in 1912, Stenhouse said.
``I've been involved with Republican politics for a long time.''
   Stenhouse was born in Colorado on Dec. 7, 1889, when much of the
West ``was real frontier country still. Indians _ the works.''
   He followed his father into medicine. While interning at a
Denver hospital, Stenhouse joined the Navy as a physician. He was
in the Philippines when World War I began. The enemy he mainly
fought was the influenza epidemic that wiped out thousands of
servicemen.
   When he retired from the Navy in 1937, he wound up in North
Carolina, where his recently widowed father-in-law lived. Stenhouse
himself was widowed in 1983. He and his wife had five children.
   Stenhouse said he now spends a lot of time reading, particularly
the National Review.
   ``That Bill Buckley, now that's a smart fellow,'' he said. ``He
has had a lot of influence on my thinking. Of course, I keep a
dictionary right there with me so I can look up some of the words
he uses.''
   Stenhouse said he never expected the attention his candidacy has
drawn _ interviews, invitations to speak, even a request to appear
on ``The Tonight Show'' with Johnny Carson. But he said it has
energized him.
   ``I can't help thinking that a lot of people must think like I
do,'' he said. ``There is a lot of latent patriotism and common
sense in this country, but it's going to take something to break it
open. Maybe this can help do that.''
   Thus far, the only other candidate to file for the congressional
seat is the incumbent, Martin Lancaster, a Democrat.
   Stenhouse said if he wins, he promises not to serve more than
two terms. That would have him retiring shortly after his 105th
birthday.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0026 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 1349EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-FerryAccident     01-14 0187</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Ferry Accident,0192</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<HEAD>Ferry Sinks Near Dhaka, 100 Feared Lost</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DHAKA, Bangladesh (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A ferry carrying about 150 people sank
Sunday night in a river outside Dhaka, and only about 50 passengers
were reported to have swum to shore, police said.
   Darkness prevented any rescue efforts, and by midnight no bodies
had been recovered, police said.
   The ferry went down in the Dhaleswari River near Mushiganj town,
20 miles southeast of the Bangladesh capital, Dhaka, around 7 p.m.
   A police official, contacted by telephone and speaking on
condition of anonymity, said there were about 150 people aboard the
ferry.
   ``We have reports of 50 people swimming ashore,'' he said. ``We
don't yet know what had happened to the others.''
   With the winter temperature dropping to 50 degrees during the
night, most passengers were in the hull of the ferry, the police
said.
   They said a clear picture about fatalities was unlikely to
emerge before Monday morning, when divers would be sent to the
scene. The ferry, which police said might have sunk because of
overloading, was on a short run from Munshiganj to Dhaka.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0027 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 1356EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Blacks-Military     01-14 0359</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Blacks-Military,330</SECOND>
<HEAD>Powell Says Military Offers Great Opportunities for Blacks</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Gen. Colin L. Powell, chairman of the Joint
Chiefs of Staff, said Sunday the armed forces offer black Americans
equal opportunity ``more so than any other form of endeavor in our
society.''
   Powell, the first black to be named the nation's highest-ranking
uniformed officer, also said he does not believe the all-volunteer
U.S. military has become disproportionately black.
   ``I don't think it's out of proportion,'' he said, adding that
``anybody who is willing to serve, qualified to serve, proud to
serve should be allowed to serve.''
   Blacks currently comprise about 21 percent of the armed forces,
compared with about 12 percent of the overall U.S. population.
   Powell was interviewed on ABC-TV's ``This Week With David
Brinkley'' on the eve of the holiday marking the birthday of the
late Martin Luther King Jr.
   He was asked whether he considers the U.S. military a
``meritocracy'' and equal-opportunity employer.
   Powell replied: ``More so than any other form of endeavor in our
society. I've very proud of what we have done in the military over
the years, and I think for the most part it is a meritocracy. You
are not limited by anything but your own ability.''
   In another development, the Washington-based American Council on
Education said in a report for release Monday that because of
increased selectivity and benefits within the armed forces, the
military is becoming more competitive with colleges in recruiting
high-ability, college-eligible blacks.
   It cited a Congressional Budget Office study finding that in
1987, ``Black and white recruits tended to come from different
socioeconomic strata within their respective populations, with
black recruits coming disproportionately from areas with
above-average black incomes and better-educated black adults.''
   ``Only 44 percent of black, male, active-duty recruits in 1987
came from areas in the bottom half of the income distribution for
black families, compared with almost 55 percent of white
recruits,'' the report said.
   ``This recruitment pattern of African Americans represented a
marked change from 1980, when black recruits were drawn much more
heavily from lower income levels,'' the council said in a report on
minorities in higher education.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0028 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 1405EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-NudistBombing 1stLd-Writethru a0635 01-14 0279</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Nudist Bombing, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0635,0282</SECOND>
<HEAD>Masked Nationalists Blow Up Cabins At Nudist Colony</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 4 grafs to UPDATE number of cabins destroyed to
60, correct that nudists weren't only ones held; Picks up 5th graf,
`Police speculated ...'</NOTE>
<DATELINE>BASTIA, Corsica (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Masked gunmen advocating independence for
Corsica rounded up nudists and other residents of a holiday complex
Sunday and blew up about 60 vacation cabins, police said. There
were no injuries or arrests.
   The letters FNLC, for the Corsican National Liberation Front,
were scratched into the hood of a car parked at entrance of the
complex.
   About 60 masked men entered the Corsicana Foret and Corsicana
Village camps on the eastern side of the Mediterranean island about
8 a.m., police said. The Corsicana Village camp caters to nudists.
   They removed about 50 people from the cabins and beaches, bound
their hands and held them at a restaurant closed for the winter.
Bombers placed explosives in about 60 of the complex's 108 cabins
and blew them up four hours later.
   Police speculated that 50 bottles of gas stolen from a
distributor last week were used in the blast, and they cordoned off
the area to search for clues.
   The bombing marks the fourth attack claimed by the nationalist
movement since November. The FNLC's aims are to win independence
for Corsica and prevent the island from being ``colonized'' by
tourists and other outsiders.
   Tourism and fishing are the main industries on the poor, rugged
island of 250,000 people, most of whom are immigrants from mainland
France 100 miles away.
   The native islanders have their own language and customs and
have long resisted cultural domination by France.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0029 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 1405EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SouthAfrica     01-14 0281</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-South Africa,0286</SECOND>
<HEAD>White Police Kill Black Constable, Newspapers Report</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JOHANNESBURG, South Africa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Three white policemen severely
beat a black colleague, then left him bleeding outside the station
gates, and he later died at a hospital, newspapers reported Sunday.
   Police have said the Dec. 29 death of Constable Mthakazeli
Sangweni has been investigated and the attorney-general would
decide whether to bring murder charges. The three officers had not
been suspended and police had not reported the case.
   Police spokesmen said, in response to the newspaper reports,
that Sangweni pointed his firearm at an officer when three
superiors were speaking to him about an unspecified ``disciplinary
matter.'' Police said the constable ``was tackled and overpowered.
He later died in hospital, apparently from a head injury sustained
in the incident.''
   Police refused to comment on reports from the Lawyers for Human
Rights group that Sangweni was dumped, bleeding from the nose and
mouth, outside the police station, where he lay until fellow black
officers called an ambulance to take him to the hospital where he
died.
   Newspapers said the case came to light when black policemen
approached the lawyers' group, which has demanded the suspension of
the white officers. One newspaper, City Press, said one of the
officers is the commander of the police station.
   The newspapers gave differing accounts, but said the argument
involved whether Sangweni had properly performed his job of keeping
the police station gate locked.
   The Sunday Star, quoting Brian Currin of Lawyers for Human
Rights, said black officers on the scene reported that Sangweni
refused to turn over his firearm to the three white officers, but
denied he had aimed it at any of them.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0030 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 1444EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Israel     01-14 0545</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel,0566</SECOND>
<HEAD>Border Policemen Suspended in Death of Palestinian</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ARIEH O'SULLIVAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two border policemen were suspended Sunday and
ordered to stand trial for fatally shooting a Palestinian teen-ager
without first firing warning shots and then allegedly lying about
the incident.
   They were accused of giving a false account after military
officers viewed ABC-TV videotape of the shooting, said an army
spokesman who spoke on condition of anonymity.
   Also Sunday, a Palestinian man died of gunshot wounds suffered
in a clash between masked Arabs and Israeli soldiers three weeks
ago in the Gaza Strip, the army said.
   The victim was identified as Abdulla al-Rekhawi, 42, of the
Rafah refugee camp. Two other Palestinians were killed in the clash.
   After al-Rekhawi's funeral, Palestinians blocked roads with
stone barricades and burned tires, Arab reports said.
   His death raised to 647 the number of Palestinians killed by
Israelis in the 25-month-old Palestinian uprising against Israeli
rule in the occupied West Bank and Gaza Strip.
   At least 170 Palestinians have been killed by fellow Arabs, most
on suspicion of collaborating with Israel, and 43 Israelis have
died.
   The border policemen, members of a paramilitary unit that works
with army troops in the territories, were suspended by Maj. Gen.
Yitzhak Mordechai, head of the army's Central Command, and
Inspector Gen. Meshulam Amit, the border police commander.
   The victim, 18-year-old Fadi Zabakli of Bethlehem, was shot in
the head during a demonstration Dec. 28 and died Jan. 7.
   The army initially said Zabakli and fellow Palestinians carried
axes and ignored warning shots and orders to halt.
   Troops are required to shout a warning and fire in the air
before aiming at a suspect's legs.
   Mordechai ordered a probe after ABC-TV reported that the youths
were not armed and that no warning shots were fired. The videotape
was aired Saturday on Israel television.
   The names of the two men charged were not made public.
   Meanwhile, a military court demoted Israeli Lt. David Lior to
the rank of sergeant and sentenced him to 45 days in jail for
mistreating a Palestinian prisoner, army radio said.
   According to the radio, Lior kicked and beat a Palestinian after
the suspect cursed him in a jeep en route to the lockup. The
Palestinian was apprehended for throwing stones.
   Also Sunday, Italy's ambassador to Israel, Alberto Bartoli,
filed a protest on behalf of the European Community with the
Israeli Foreign Ministry over police handling of peace rallies in
Jerusalem last month.
   More than 50 people were injured Dec. 30 when police charged a
section of the crowd that had gathered to form a ``human chain''
for peace around Jerusalem's Old City. Many were Italian and other
European activists.
   Police said stones and bottles were thrown, but reporters saw no
stone throwing before the police moved in.
   A day earlier, police fired tear gas and used night sticks to
break up a women's peace march after an outlawed Palestinian flag
was raised.
   Bartoli's statement criticized ``unjustified use of generalized
violence against hundreds of people during authorized, peaceful
demonstrations.''
   The statement also criticized Israel's decision last week to ban
foreign travel by nine Palestinian activists. It said the action
was ``not conducive to the climate of confidence necessary for any
(peace) negotiation.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0031 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 1452EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-PreschoolMolest     01-14 0652</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Preschool Molest,0672</SECOND>
<HEAD>Final Verdicts Near in Nation's Longest, Costliest Trial</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Pre-School with hyphen is cq for name of school.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By LINDA DEUTSCH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Thirty-three months after the first jurors
were summoned to weigh the McMartin Pre-School case, verdicts are
nearly complete in the longest, costliest criminal trial ever held
in the United States.
   The molestation trial of Raymond Buckey and his mother, Peggy
McMartin Buckey, has become a crucible for the justice system and a
soul-wrenching ordeal for participants.
   Buckey, 31, and his 63-year-old mother await the jury's word _
which could come this week _ on whether they will be found guilty
or innocent of 65 counts of child molestation and conspiracy.
   Parents and their youngsters who once attended the McMartin
Pre-School in Manhattan Beach also wait anxiously for the outcome.
   When the 12 jurors retired for the weekend after eight weeks of
deliberation, they had delivered 52 sealed verdicts to Superior
Court Judge William Pounders and sent him a question that suggested
their verdicts may be as complex as the entire McMartin case.
   Considering the single count of conspiracy, which names both
Buckey and his mother, the jury asked: ``Can we find one defendant
guilty and one not guilty?''
   Pounders is expected to tell the jury that the answer is yes.
They can convict one alleged conspirator without the other because
there are a number of unnamed co-conspirators alleged in the
charges.
   The jurors, who have the day off Monday for Martin Luther King
Jr.'s birthday, were to resume deliberations Tuesday. Thirteen
verdicts remain to be delivered.
   Pounders, anxious to learn the results and have the verdicts
recorded while 12 jurors remain seated, considered opening the
sealed envelopes and disclosing them to the public.
   But lawyers on both sides persuaded him to wait until the jury's
task is concluded. Jurors themselves have expressed fears that
disclosure of partial verdicts would subject them to community
pressure if any of their decisions proved unpopular.
   ``I don't mean to betray them,'' said the judge. ``They've done
such a great job. But I'm concerned with having 12 jurors here at
the end.''
   The trial's length forced the judge to use all six alternates to
maintain 12 jurors on the panel. There are no alternates left if a
juror should fall ill, and a mistrial would have to be called. The
52 verdicts already reached are not official until they are
announced in court and affirmed by each juror.
   ``We have 78 percent of the verdicts in,'' Pounders said. But if
I lose one juror I lose all 52 verdicts, which is why I'm on the
razor's edge.''
   Those familiar with the case don't believe the verdicts will end
the bizarre saga that has spread itself over nearly seven years,
leaving wrecked lives in its wake.
   Seven people were originally arrested in 1984, but after a
two-year preliminary hearing, charges against the other five were
dropped.
   Appeals could follow any convictions. At least one book is
planned on the case no matter what the outcome.
   ``This case, in my view, has poisoned everyone who had contact
with it,'' Pounders said some months ago. Two witnesses had died.
Some of the children involved in the proceedings are now
adolescents.
   More than 1,000 items have been entered in evidence and 124
witnesses have testified during the nearly three-year trial. The
cost has soared past $15 million.
   Deputy District Attorney Lael Rubin has said she believes the
cost is worthwhile because it has alerted the public to the problem
of child molestation.
   Buckey's attorney, Danny Davis, called the McMartin trial ``a
cottage industry'' that provided a showcase for experts to build
reputations, for lawyers to build careers and for TV news shows to
outrate one another.
   ``My heartfelt feeling is that the truth never had a chance,''
Davis said. ``We rushed into the glitz of a fantastic media event.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0032 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 1456EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-EastGermany     01-14 0455</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-East Germany,0468</SECOND>
<HEAD>Major Opposition Force Favors Talks on German Unity</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Edzard for first name of Daimler-Benz chief is correct.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By KEVIN COSTELLOE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>EAST BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   East Germany's largest opposition political
party said Sunday that it will open talks on unification with West
Germany if it wins national elections in May.
   Tens of thousands of East Germans demonstrated Sunday against
the Communists in at least four cities to keep up the pressure on
Communist Premier Hans Modrow's shaky coalition government.
   ``Forty years of Communist Rule are Enough'' and ``Lies,
Corruption and Treason Marked the Communist State,'' read two of
the banners at a rally in East Berlin. Several people waved West
German flags.
   Protesters also rallied in Magdeburg, Karl-Marx-Stadt and Suhl,
according to East German television.
   The leading opposition party, Social Democrats, originally
organized the East Berlin demonstration to pay tribute to two
German Communists murdered 71 years ago. The two, Rosa Luxemburg
and Karl Liebknecht, have become martyrs for German leftists.
   Several hundred thousand people across East Germany took part in
various ceremonies marking their deaths Jan. 15, 1919. For the
first time, the events were not controlled by the Communist Party.
   In a party platform statement released after a meeting, the
Social Democrats said Sunday that if they lead the government after
elections on May 6, they will open talks with Bonn on ``the
necessary steps'' for German unity.
   The statement said: ``Our political goal is a united Germany.''
   ``Whatever is possible immediately, should happen immediately,''
the Social Democrats said.
   The 500 delegates said German unity must come as part of an
overall process of European integration, and it must have the
consent of neighboring countries.
   On Saturday, the West German Social Democrats promised campaign
support for their sister party in East Germany, which has 32,000
members and has emerged as a top contender to win East Germany's
first open elections.
   The far larger New Forum opposition group, with an estimated
200,000 members, remains a diffuse organization with little
interest in becoming a formal political party.
   The Communist Party still has 1.4 million members, despite a
wave of resignations, and has a grip on businesses, bureaucracy and
the news media.
   Even before Sunday's announcement by the Social Democrats, the
two German states were well on their way toward unification.
   Political, cultural and business ties are growing daily, in a
spirit of cooperation unthinkable before the ouster of hard-line
Communist leader Erich Honecker on Oct. 18, the opening of the
Berlin Wall in November, and a series of democratic reforms.
   Daimler-Benz chief Edzard Reuter, whose conglomerate makes
trucks, Mercedes-Benz cars, aerospace products and electronics
equipment, said he will start working with East German leaders even
before the elections.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0033 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 1457EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Keating     01-14 0512</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Keating,500</SECOND>
<HEAD>Keating Blames Regulators for S&amp;L Crisis</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MATT YANCEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Lincoln Savings and Loan executive Charles H.
Keating Jr. said Sunday that taxpayers could have been saved half a
trillion dollars in savings and loan losses if regulators had
listened to the five senators for whom he raised campaign money.
   Keating, who is a central figure in the S&amp;L crisis and an
accompanying congressional ethics scandal involving the five
senators, blamed regulators for the collapse of Lincoln and
hundreds of other thrifts.
   ``Had they listened to the senators and had they listened to me,
there wouldn't be mess today,'' he said on NBC-TV's ``Meet the
Press'' show. ``I'm convinced that the cost of this debacle is
going to exceed $500 billion. ... Never ... has so much misery and
economic disaster been caused by so few men.''
   Keating defended raising $1.3 million from associates for
political campaigns and related causes of Sens. Dennis DeConcini,
D-Ariz.; John McCain, R-Ariz.; Alan Cranston, D-Calif.; Donald W.
Riegle Jr., D-Mich., and John Glenn, D-Ohio.
   Edwin Gray, a former chairman of the Federal Home Loan Bank
Board, and federal S&amp;L examiners told a House committee last fall
they were pressured by the senators in a pair of meetings in
DeConcini's office in 1987 to ease their regulation of Lincoln.
   ``I wanted to be involved in the process,'' Keating said Sunday.
``It was particularly important how the savings and loan industry
went. It you want to support the system, you have to, in my case,
it seems to me, raise funds and support the people.''
   Since the disclosures of the campaign gifts and the meeting with
regulators, the five senators have tried to disassociate themselves
from Keating, saying they didn't know at the time the nature of
Lincoln's loans and investments. All five are now the subject of a
Senate Ethics Committee inquiry.
   Asked Sunday if the meetings between the senators and bank board
officials over Lincoln was unusual, Keating said his problem with
the regulators were more than ordinary.
   ``It was a problem of taking down a savings and loan which was
critical to the economy and employment in those areas in which the
senators served,'' he said.
   Claiming that the Irvine, Calif.-based Lincoln was being
operated in an ``unsafe and unsound manner,'' the bank board seized
control of it last April, two years after examiners first
recommended shutting it down.
   Regulators now estimate that its loss of federally insured taxes
through what the government claims in a suit were fraudulent loans
and racketeering investment practices will cost taxpayers up to $2
billion.
   Keating, in turn, has sued the government, claiming its takeover
of Lincoln was part of a vendetta that regulators waged against him
because he was operating Lincoln as an investment bank rather than
as a traditional home mortgage lender.
   ``It operated profitably until the government confiscated it,''
he said Sunday. ``It seems to me that something's wrong for the
government that takes away a profitable property. There's no loss
that's ascertainable at this point in Lincoln.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0034 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 1504EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Euphrates     01-14 0207</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Euphrates,0212</SECOND>
<HEAD>Oil Minister Arrives With Hussein Message After River Cutback</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ANKARA, Turkey (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Iraq's oil minister arrived Sunday for
talks on Turkey's reduction of the Euphrates River flow toward Iraq
and Syria.
   The newspaper of Iraq's ruling Baath Socialist Party said
relations between Turkey and its neighbors could suffer if Turkey
does not let the water flow freely again.
   The Iraqi minister, Issam Abdul Rahim Al-Chalabi, arried with
him a message from Iraqi President Saddam Hussein for Turkey's
president, Turgut Ozal. He refused to tell reporters what the
letter said.
   On Saturday, Ozal cut the flow of the Euphrates with the push of
a button, diverting its waters to a reservoir that is part of a
huge dam and hydroelectric project in southeastern Turkey.
   During the one-month stoppage, Syria and Iraq will get 75
percent less water from the tributaries of the Euphrates.
   Iraq sent its deputy foreign minister, Nizar Hamdoun, to Turkey
last month to try to get the reduction in flow shortened from one
month to two weeks. Turkey refused, saying a month was necessary to
fill the reservoir.
   Turks maintain that since November they have released extra
water to Syria and Iraq to store in reservoirs in preparation for
the shortfall.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0035 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 1507EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Leland-Twins     01-14 0208</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Leland-Twins,0214</SECOND>
<HEAD>Congressman's Widow Has Twins In Atlanta</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ATLANTA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The widow of Texas Congressman Mickey Leland, who
was expecting at the time of his death in a plane crash last
summer, gave birth Sunday to twin boys at an Atlanta hospital, a
spokesman said.
   Alison Leland, 31, was in town for festivities surrounding
Monday's Martin Luther King Jr. national holiday.
   Mrs. Leland came to Grady Memorial Hospital about 5 a.m. Sunday,
and gave birth to the boys around noon, according to Grady
spokesman Jim Driscoll.
   She and the boys _ one 3 pounds, the other 2 pounds, 11 ounces _
are doing well, Driscoll said. But the infants, several weeks
premature, are in Grady's special care nursery.
   Mrs. Leland was about six weeks pregnant when Leland, 44, was
killed Aug. 7 in a plane crash in Ethiopia while on a hunger relief
mission. He was first elected to Congress from Houston's 18th
District in 1978.
   On Leland's behalf, his widow accepted a ``Salute to Greatness''
award from the King Center on Saturday night.
   In late August, Mrs. Leland declined to run for his seat in
Congress, saying her top priorities were her son _ Jarrett, now 4 _
and the ``new baby on the way.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0036 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 1510EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Cambodia     01-14 0640</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Cambodia,0666</SECOND>
<HEAD>As The Khmer Rouge Advance, Nations Speed Up Efforts to Settle
Conflict</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP Extra</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PETER ENG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BANGKOK, Thailand (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The search for a negotiated settlement
of the Cambodian war has quickened amid reports of Khmer Rouge
guerrilla advances from the jungles.
   Deputy Foreign Minister Igor Rogachev of the Soviet Union on
Friday announced after talks in Beijing that the Soviet Union and
China have agreed the United Nations should play ``a very major
role'' in a Cambodian settlement.
   The Soviet Union has been arming the Vietnamese-installed
Cambodian government, and China arms the guerrillas.
   The Soviet announcement increased hopes that are centered on
Australia's proposal for a U.N. interim authority in Cambodia,
which diplomats call the most promising peace plan in years.
   The Soviet Union, China and the three other permanent members of
the U.N. Security Council will discuss that and other Cambodian
peace initiatives at a meeting in Paris on Monday and Tuesday. The
plan would require approval by the members, which also include the
United States, Britain, and France.
   Fears of a Khmer Rouge return have intensified since September,
when Vietnam said it withdrew the last of its troops aiding the
Hanoi-installed government.
   The Khmer Rouge claimed last week that its forces hit the two
largest cities, Phnom Penh and Battambang. Phnom Penh sources said
minor explosons went off in the capital on Jan. 5 and 6.
   The government said the guerrillas also struck near Battambang,
the provincial capital in the northwest. The guerrillas said they
set parts of the city ablaze, but the reports could not be verified.
   Western diplomats said the effect of the attacks was ``more
psychological than strategic'' and involved little actual fighting.
They predicted more strikes in coming weeks, designed not to
overthrow the government but to bolster bargaining power at peace
talks.
   After toppling the U.S.-backed Lon Nol government in April 1975,
the Khmer Rouge emptied the cities and banished residents to labor
camps in the countryside.
   Hundreds of thousands were executed, died of torture or disease
in labor camps during the 3{-year rule of Pol Pot's black-clad
fanatics.
   Vietnam's invasion of December 1978 drove the Khmer Rouge to the
Thai border. But aid from Thailand and China revived the guerrillas
and they formed a coalition that includes the non-Comunist forces
of Prince Norodom Sihanouk and Son Sann.
   ``If we let the situation persist and the Khmer Rouge gain more
ground, they might harden their stance at the negotiating table,''
said Ek Sereywath, a spokesman in Sihanouk's office in Bangkok.
   The Australian proposal says a U.N. authority should govern
Cambodia until a free election can be held.
   Foreign Minister Ali Alatas of Indonesia on Thursday praised the
proposal because among the many issues unsettled at the
international conference on Cambodia last summer, ``one of the most
difficult to overcome was the question of an interim administering
authority.''
   In that conference, Premier Hun Sen of Cambodia rejected
guerrilla demands for a transitional coalition government because
of the inclusion of the Khmer Rouge.
   Other unresolved issues, Alatas said, include verification of
Vietnam's claimed troop pullout, a truce and a halt to outside
military aid to the combatants, and measures to prevent a return of
the Khmer Rouge terror.
   Deputy Foreign Secretary Michael Costello of Australia will try
to gather support for the plan in visits to France, the United
Nations and the United States.
   The main antagonists at any talks will be Hun Sen and Khmer
Rouge leader Khieu Samphan.
   Their will to fight has not weakened.
   In a speech Jan. 6, Hun Sen urged authorities to step up
recruitment ``at all costs. We must strengthen the armed forces.
Without the armed forces we cannot survive.''
   The Khmer Rouge radio said the government surely will fall and
told citizens to flee immediately ``in order to live.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0037 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 1514EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People Sub a0667 01-14 0150</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People, Sub, a0667,0150</SECOND>
<HEAD>People in the News</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS lead of NEW YORK-dated 4th item in rdp to CORRECT
spelling of turfdom.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Actor Tim Conway, a mainstay on the long-running
``The Carol Burnett Show'' and the bumbling Ensign Parker on
``McHale's Navy,'' was elected 1989 Big Sport of Turfdom for his
part in founding the Don MacBeth Memorial Jockey Fund.
   The MacBeth fund was started in 1987 and named for the late
jockey, who died of cancer. Since that time, it has funded physical
therapy and medical treatment and provided financial assistance to
jockeys in need.
   Conway, 54, who got into racing as an exercise rider for his
father at old Randall Park in Cleveland, is one of several
celebrities who have been honored by the Turf Publicists of
America. Others include composer Burt Bacharach and actors Telly
Savalas, Jack Klugman and John Forsythe.
  
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0038 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 1549EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Soviet-Unrest 1stLd-Writethru   01-14 1074</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Unrest, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0647,1110</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<HEAD>Dozens Reported Killed in Azerbaijani-Armenian Violence</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: New thruout to UPDATE with reports of violence spreading,
deaths elsewhere in republic, extra troops deployed, armed
Armenians and Azerbaijanis massing. No pickup.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By JOHN-THOR DAHLBURG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   At least 25 people died in the capital of the
Azerbaijan republic after ethnic rioting broke out overnight, and
dozens more people were killed as the unrest spread across the
republic, official media said Sunday.
   Extra internal security troops were flown to the southern
republic to try to quell the violence, and a military commander of
one besieged area called for a state of emergency, the television
news program ``Seven Days'' reported.
   A witness in the city of Baku, where the violence began,
described a street awash in blood and said victims there included
two women tossed from balconies.
   It was the bloodiest clash in nearly two years between
Azerbaijanis and Armenians, who are locked in a feud over
Nagorno-Karabakh, an enclave populated mainly by Armenians but
which is controlled by Azerbaijan.
   Most Armenians are Christians; most Azerbaijanis are Shiite
Moslems.
   The violence was set off by news that an Azerbaijani had been
killed and another wounded by Armenians in Azerbaijan's capital,
Baku.
   Radio Moscow said the incidents were announced at a rally
Saturday night in Baku's central square that was attended by about
150,000 people.
   ``Calls were made at the rally to drive the Armenians out of the
city,'' the Radio Moscow correspondent reported from the Caspian
Sea port of 1.7 million people. ``Among the crowd, anti-Armenian
slogans were shouted, and then the most terrible thing of all began
_ the pogroms.''
   The official Tass news agency said 25 people were killed in
Baku. Radio Moscow quoted local Interior Ministry officials as
saying most victims were Armenians.
   Late Sunday, Tass said the violence had spread to the
Shaumyanovsk and Khanlar regions of Azerbaijan, near
Nagorno-Karabakh, and that there were ``tens of dead and wounded
from both nationalities.''
   ``Seven Days'' said thousands of armed Azerbaijani militants
were massing in the two districts and that Armenians also bearing
arms were being transported there.
   The military commander in Shaumyanovsk, Maj. Gen. Yu. A.
Kosolapov, called for the introduction of a state of emergency,
``Seven Days'' said.
   Two helicopters were shot at with artillery guns, and a
lieutenant aboard one was wounded. Highways and railroads to
Nagorno-Karabakh were blocked and shipments of food and fuel were
not reaching the district, according to Soviet TV.
   It said four soldiers of the Interior Ministry, who are
responsible for internal security, have disappeared since Saturday
and that a fifth was killed.
   The fate of Armenians taken hostage by Azerbaijanis, including
the entire Communist Party and government leadership in
Shaumyanovsk, was unknown, according to the reports.
   A Russian resident of Baku told The Associated Press by
telephone she saw at least two Armenian women in torn,
blood-spattered clothes hurled from the balconies of upper floors
of apartment houses on Lenin Street.
   In front of the office, she said, an old woman who looked like
an Armenian was shot point-blank in the head and chest by a mob
armed with shotguns and pistols.
   ``You can't imagine, I've just seen death for the first time in
my life,'' said the woman, who asked not to be identified by name
for fear she would become the target of reprisals. She said Lenin
Street was covered with blood.
   About 20,000 ethnic Armenians, mainly elderly people, live in
Baku, although ethnic violence in the last two years has caused an
exodus of Azerbaijans and Armenians back to their home republics.
   Alexander Argumanyan, a press officer for the Armenian National
Movement, said at least 250,000 people gathered in Yerevan, the
Armenian capital, Sunday after hearing of the violence.
   He said Vano Syragedlyan, a member of the movement's
directorate, urged Armenians who own firearms to volunteer to be
flown by helicopter to two districts of Azerbaijan near the
disputed region of Nagorno-Karabakh.
   Radio Moscow said the strife was kindled in Baku, a major
petroleum-producing center, when two Azerbaijanis visited an
Armenian family at midday and demanded they leave town. The
Armenians had an ax, and the Azerbaijanis were hurt in a struggle
and taken to a hospital.
   One died and the other was in serious condition, the radio said.
   The news enraged the crowd that gathered later in Baku.
   Alesker Siyabov, a spokesman for the Azerbaijani People's Front,
said the rally voted to establish a ``council for national
security'' designed to protect Azerbaijanis.
   Radio Moscow said police had 1,500 men on patrol.
   ``It was not possible to avert so many sad and tragic cases. But
in dozens of cases, the militia (police) saved people,'' the Baku
correspondent said. In other cases, he said, Azerbaijanis saved
Armenian neighbors by sheltering them.
   Radio Moscow said 53 apartments, presumably those of Armenians,
were wrecked in the violence and that the situation in the city,
1,240 miles southeast of Moscow, remained tense.
   ``The republic is on the boil. Hearts are bleeding and the
militia is trying to do everything it can,'' the correspondent said.
   He said he had been told that reinforcements were on the way.
``But what guarantee is there that the frightful thing which took
place yesterday evening and last night will not be repeated?''
   A duty officer at the Azerbaijani Communist Party's Central
Committee, Kamal Abdulayev, said the number of victims was unclear.
   The duty officer at the republic's Interior Ministry, which is
responsible for law enforcement, said Baku ``was and is normal.''
He hung up before he could be asked his name.
   Azerbaijani People's Front spokesman Khalid Mukhtarov denied
knowing of any rioting. When told that Pravda, the Communist Party
daily, had printed the Tass dispatch about the hooligan rampages,
he charged that the newspaper always printed lies about Azerbaijan.
   The Armenian-Azerbaijani dispute is the bloodiest of the many
ethnic conflicts facing Soviet President Mikhail S. Gorbachev.
   The last major rioting occurred in February 1988, when
Azerbaijanis attacked Armenians in the city of Sumgait, near Baku.
Thirty-two people died, most of them Armenians.
   Nagorno-Karabakh, a territory of about 160,000 people, has been
controlled by Azerbaijan since 1923.
   In addition to Nagorno-Karabakh, Azerbaijanis also have rioted
over demands they be united with their Shiite Moslem breathren in
the neighboring Iranian Azerbaijani region. Over the New Year's
holiday weekend, Azerbaijani rioters tore down border fences and
put guard towers and communications lines out of commission.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0039 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 1606EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Colombia     01-14 0575</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Colombia,0593</SECOND>
<HEAD>Gov't Orders Arrest for Extradition of Chief of Cali Cartel</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TOM WELLS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOGOTA, Colombia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Colombia on Sunday ordered the arrest of
the leader of the Cali cocaine cartel to face U.S. charges, and the
army reportedly arrested hundreds of people to try to dismantle a
drug traffickers' private army.
   The Justice Ministry said the attempt to extradite Gilberto
Rodriguez Orejuela, the chief of the Cali cartel, is based upon
charges of laundering money from cocaine sales in the United States.
   A U.S. attempt to extradite Rodriguez two years ago collapsed
when a judge ruled there was no merit to the U.S. charges that he
smuggled 20 tons of cocaine into the United States.
   The Cali and Medellin cartels are believed responsible for most
of the cocaine that is smuggled into the United States.
   The army operation against the head of the Medellin cartel,
Pablo Escobar, began Friday in lower class areas of Medellin known
to be the source for Escobar's army of hired killers, said the
Bogota daily El Tiempo.
   El Tiempo, quoting army Gen. Harold Bedoya Pizarro, said the
army has arrested 2,500 people from the northwestern city of
Medellin belonging to 150 gangs working for Escobar. The newspaper,
Colombia's largest, has good sources within the Colombian military.
   The Colombian radio network RCN said Sunday, quoting army
sources, that the operation has resulted in the arrest of 1,800
people.
   The Defense Ministry was closed Sunday, and the RCN and El
Tiempo reports could not be confirmed.
   Four soldiers have been killed by Medellin cartel gunmen in
Medellin since Jan. 4, El Tiempo said.
   Twenty-eight persons have been kidnapped in the last two months
in Medellin, where a communique signed by a traffickers' group
known as the Extraditables encouraged people in poor class
neighborhoods to fight on the side of the Medellin cartel.
   The communique urged people in slum areas to kidnap wealthy
Colombians and hold them for ransom. Half the money would go for
decent housing for the poor, and half for the Medellin cartel's war
on the government, the communique said.
   There have been no ransom demands and it is not known that the
28 were kidnapped on behalf of the Medellin cartel since there have
been no communiques from the kidnappers.
   Escobar has built hundreds of brick and cinderblock houses for
the poor in Medellin slums, replacing shanties of scrap wood and
tar paper. People there have said Escobar is a hero to them.
   The communique appealing for ransom money to help finance the
Medellin cartel's war on the government left government officials
puzzled because Escobar is known to be a billionaire as a result of
his cocaine smuggling.
   On Dec. 20, the Extraditables kidnapped Diego Montoya, the son
of President Virgilio Barco's top aide.
   A Jan. 6 communique signed by the Extraditables said Montoya
would be executed in seven days if five persons allegedly arrested
by Colombia's secret police were not released.
   The deadline passed Saturday with no news of Montoya's fate.
   The secret police have denied arresting the five people
mentioned in the communique. The five have not been heard of before.
   The government declared war on drugs Aug. 18, after traffickers
assassinated a leading presidential candidate, Sen. Luis Carlos
Galan.
   On Dec. 15, the army tracked down the second highest ranking
member of the Medellin cartel, Gonzalo Rodriguez Gacha, and killed
him in a gun battle on Colombia's northern coast.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0040 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 1607EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brite     01-14 0384</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brite,0396</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bright &amp; Brief</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DURHAM, N.C. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A firefighter who used mouth-to-mouth
resuscitation to revive two palm-sized kittens overcome by smoke
says he draws the line at reptiles.
   ``If somebody has a pet snake and it quits breathing they can
hang it up. I'm not kissing a snake,'' said A.J. Green, who
received letters from far and wide after his Nov. 13 feat was
publicized.
   Green used mouth-to-mouth resuscitation followed by oxygen to
save the 2-week-old kittens at a house fire. Since then, Green has
received letters from animal lovers from California to
Massachusetts.
   On Jan. 10, he received one with $2 inside from a woman in
Marietta, Ga.
   ``You are a very kind man,'' she wrote, signing the letter,
``From an old lady who loves animals.''
   Green, a Durham police and fire veteran of 21 years, answers all
the letters he receives and sends money he gets to the Animal
Protection Society.
   Green said he saw the two white and gray kittens lying on the
ground outside the burning house, where they had been brought by
other firefighters. Neither animal appeared to be breathing. Their
13-year-old owner, Jennifer Pruitt, was screaming nearby. That's
when Green said he sprung into action on one of the pets.
   ``I held it in my hand and blew into the mouth of the kitten. It
wasn't close contact. When the kitten started responding to that I
hooked up oxygen and gave them oxygen,'' he said.
   ``I wasn't sure how much oxygen to give a kitten so I pretended
it was an infant and set the oxygen for that amount. I rotated the
kittens for about 20 minutes,'' Green said.
   ``I saw the girl there and she had apparently lost everything.
She was so distraught that I felt like I had to try to do something
for her,'' he said.
   The kittens are alive and healthy today, Green said.
   Green, whose own household includes a cat, three dogs, a parrot
and two parakeets, said he is amazed by the attention his rescue
has received.
   ``This has been overwhelming to me. I never expected to see a
thank-you card or letter or anything,'' he said. ``It makes you
more conscientious of your job. Something like this is like icing
on the cake. It makes you feel good.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0041 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 1613EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Women-Combat     01-14 0405</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Women-Combat,360</SECOND>
<HEAD>Schroeder Doubts Chances for Bill Allowing Women in Combat</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MATT YANCEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Rep. Patricia Schroeder said Sunday she doubts
her bill to allow female U.S. military personnel into combat will
get very far in Congress with most members up for re-election next
November.
   ``They want to duck, waffle, tap dance and everything else,''
Schroeder, D-Colo., said of her colleagues on CBS-TV's ``Face the
Nation'' show. ``I think they're terrified to take the next step
because of the emotionalism and irrationality surrounding the
issue.''
   Most members of Congress, she said, fear that if they voted to
allow women in combat, opponents would campaign against them as
``the congressman who voted to put your daughter in combat boots.''
   A member of the House Armed Services Committee, Schroeder
announced after the U.S. invasion of Panama last month she would
introduce the bill when Congress reconvenes Jan. 23.
   Sen. Sam Nunn, D-Ga., chairman of the same committee in the
Senate, has said he opposes changing the current law, which
prohibits the Navy and Air Force from assigning women to combat
ships or planes.
   While the law does not explicitly include the Army, Assistant
Secretary of Defense Christopher Jehn said on the same program
Sunday that the Army takes its ``cue'' from the statute that
Congress doesn't want women in combat.
   Jehn said there are senior military officials on both sides of
the question but that the Pentagon, itself, has no official view.
   ``It's really an emotional, political issue that we think needs
to be resolved in the Congress, not by policy edict in the Defense
Department,'' he said.
   Controversy flared over the role of U.S. women in combat during
the Panama invasion when presidential spokesman Marlin Fitzwater
praised the commander of a military police unit, Capt. Linda Bray,
for her role in a battle at a Panamanian Defense Forces kennel.
   Fitzwater implied she had led the military action, but military
officials said later she had directed the operation by radio from a
command post a half-mile away and then rushed to the scene when
fighting broke out.
   Schroeder said the Panama invasion proved that men and women
``could go into combat together and bond'' and that men had no
problems taking orders from women senior to them in rank or command.
   ``This is a generation that grew up playing soccer together,''
she said. ``They really do see women as teammates.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0042 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 1628EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-GM-Hungary 1stLd-Writethru a0681 01-14 0561</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-GM-Hungary, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0681,0570</SECOND>
<HEAD>GM is First U.S. Automaker Behind Toppled Iron Curtain</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 1st two grafs to recast. Picks up 3rd graf pvs, `The
agreement...'. A version moving on the financial wire.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By JOSE MARTINEZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DETROIT (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   General Motors Corp. announced Sunday it had
reached a tentative agreement with a Hungarian government-owned
automaker to jointly build cars and engines at a plant under
construction in the Eastern European nation.
   The deal makes GM the first U.S. automaker to invest in Eastern
Europe, which has undergone tremendous political and economic
liberalization in recent months, said R.L. Theis, GM's
Detroit-based international spokesman. The company is to invest
$150 million in the dea.
   The agreement between General Motors Europe and RABA, Hungary's
state-owned manufacturer of trucks, diesel engines and axles, could
lead to a joint venture to build engines and cars at a plant in
Szentgotthard, near the Austrian border, beginning in 1992, Theis
said.
   ``The tentative agreement spells out the full intent of the
joint venture. Now, both parties have to finalize all the details
and actually form the joint venture,'' Theis said.
   Although GM is the first U.S. automaker to announce an
agreement, Japan's Suzuki Motor Co. announced Tuesday it would
build a $138.9 million assembly plant near Budapest, Hungary's
capital, to make Suzuki Swift subcompact cars beginning in 1992.
   GM Europe President Robert J. Eaton and RABA Managing Director
Ferenc Romvari signed the protocol Saturday in Budapest before
Hungarian Deputy Prime Minister Peter Medgyessy.
   ``As these markets continue to open up, investing in plants
there is becoming a more attractive business proposition,'' Eaton
said in a statement. ``This new strategic partnership would provide
us with better access to the growing car market in Hungary and
elsewhere in Eastern Europe.''
   Under the tentative agreement, GM would have a 67 percent
interest in the Szentgotthard plant and would be allowed to appoint
management staff. The plant would create about 880 jobs in the
western Hungarian town, Theis said.
   The world's largest automaker said about 200,000 engines would
be turned out yearly, most of which would be exported for use in
GM's Opel and Vauxhall cars. The rest would go into the Opel Kadett
model to be built at the Hungarian plant.
   Theis said current plans call for only one car-assembly shift
and an annual production of 15,000 vehicles for sale in Hungary and
other Eastern European markets.
   ``Market conditions will dictate whether an additional shift is
required,'' he said. Last year, Opel sold 6,600 cars in Hungary.
   The profitable European branches of both GM and Ford Motor Co.
have been bolstering sagging U.S. operations recently. Chrysler
Corp. also sells cars in Europe but does not run independent
manufacturing plants there.
   Last month, GM agreed to acquire half of the car business of
Sweden's Saab-Scania AB for about $600 million. That announcement
came on the heels of rival Ford's acquisition of Great Britain's
Jaguar PLC for $2.5 billion. Of the Big Three, Ford has the largest
presence in Europe.
   On Thursday, Ford spokeswoman Lin Cummins said the world's
second-largest automaker had no negotiations in the works involving
Eastern Europe, but was watching the market carefully.
   ``There would seem to be a good chance that multinational
companies will find opportunities for major business deals there in
the course of the next several years,'' Cummins said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0043 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 1709EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-King-Stallings     01-14 0246</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-King-Stallings,240</SECOND>
<HEAD>Black Priest Canonizes King</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: RETRANSMITTING a0699 to delete byline.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A renegade black Catholic priest on Sunday
declared Martin Luther King Jr. a saint but Vatican officials said
the slain civil rights leader was ineligible for canonization.
   The Rev. George A. Stallings told a congregation of nearly 900
people that to canonize King was to ``ratify what God had already
done.''
   ``Martin Luther King, Jr. is a saint by virtue of his life work,
his communion with God and his sharing in the joys of everlasting
life,'' said Stallings.
   In a lavish three-hour service Stallings said King was ``a
doctor and martyr'' and exhorted the worshippers to follow King's
example by dedicating their lives to a cause.
   Stallings is prohibited from giving communion and performing
other duties as a priest since breaking from the Catholic church in
July to form the Imani Temple African American Catholic
Congregation.
   Vatican officials in Rome said King would not be eligible for
sainthood even if the ceremony was performed by a sanctioned priest.
   ``Reverend King may have been a great man, but because he was
not a Catholic, that judgment must be left to others outside the
church,'' said a Vatican official.
   ``They say King wasn't a Catholic, but there are saints who
aren't Catholic,'' said Imani Temple spokesman William Marshall.
   Catholic Information Center researchers say Pope John Paul II
has named 250 saints and as many as 1,500 candidates are being
considered.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0044 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 1714EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Salvador-Jesuits     01-14 0767</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Salvador-Jesuits,0791</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bishop Praises President, But Says More Must Be Done</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARCOS ALEMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN SALVADOR, El Salvador (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Roman Catholic leader on
Sunday praised President Alfredo Cristiani's efforts to bring to
justice those responsible for killing six Jesuit priests.
   But Monsignor Gregorio Rosa Chavez, San Salvador's auxiliary
bishop, said much more needs to be done to end the cycle of
violence in the country.
   ``Now that Mr. Cristiani has made public the names of those
implicated, the possibility that El Salvador will regain confidence
in its institutions has grown,'' the Roman Catholic leader said in
his homily.
   However, ``It's not enough to punish some. It is necessary to
completely revise the criteria to define who are really enemies of
the people and enemies of the nation,'' he said. ``This seems like
a good start, but it's not the end.''
   Cristiani announced Saturday that an army colonel, three
lieutenants and five enlisted men are the prime suspects in the
November massacre.
   Eight of the suspects, he said, ``have been placed at the
disposition of the Special Investigative Commission.'' A ninth
suspect, a private, deserted from the armed forces last month and
was a fugitive, he said.
   Cristiani did not say specifically that the eight suspects had
been arrested, but sources close to the investigation said the men
were indeed under arrest. They have not yet been charged.
   The colonel was identified as Guillermo Alfredo Benavides
Moreno. He is the highest-ranking military officer to be officially
accused of a human rights abuse crime in El Salvador's 10-year-old
civil war.
   Rosa Chavez said the government ``has insisted that this be
treated simply as a group of members of the army who have blemished
the honor of the military.'' He added, ``It is difficult for us to
accept this conclusion.''
   ``We realize that the mission of the church, especially in the
countryside promoting human rights, is misunderstood by the
military world,'' the bishop said.
   The New York Times reported Sunday that an American officer was
being questioned about the case. The newspaper, quoting
unidentified officials, said the officer may have had advance
knowledge of plans to kill the priests.
   Military men implicated in serious crimes have often gone
unpunished in El Salvador. Many observers contended the Jesuit
massacre was only being prosecuted because of international
pressure, especially from the United States.
   Cristiani was to visit Washington this week but postponed the
trip, a government spokesman said Sunday. Cristiani changed his
plans because U.N. Secretary General Javier Perez de Cuellar was
not able to meet with him as scheduled, the spokesman said.
   No military officer has been convicted of a human rights abuse
crime in the civil war, although rightist death squads sponsored or
tolerated by the armed forces killed thousands of suspected
leftists in the early 1980s.
   In 1980, four churchwomen were killed in El Salvador. Five
national guardsmen were convicted for their murder.
   The leftist Farabundo Marti National Liberation Front has waged
a 10-year civil war against a succession of U.S.-backed
governments. The government frequently blames the rebels for
atrocities and initially said the Jesuits may have been killed by
the rebels.
   ``Many voices have demanded that other equally condemnable acts
that have been attributed to the (guerrillas) be clarified with the
same zeal as the deaths of the Jesuits,'' Rosa Chavez said.
   The bishop cited the resurgence of death squads who are believed
to have killed many union activists and left-of-center politicians.
   He said ``it is urgent to investigate completely the delicate
question of the criminal death squads, whose resurgence does not
favor the forces of peace.''
   On Nov. 16, armed men broke into the Central American University
campus residence of Jesuit priests and educators Ignacio Ellacuria,
Ignacio Martin-Baro, Segundo Montes, Amado Lopez, Juan Ramon Moreno
and Joaquin Lopez Lopez.
   The six were taken to the yard behind the building and shot to
death with assault rifles.
   The assailants also killed the Jesuits' housekeeper, Julia
Ramos, and her 15-year-old daughter, Celina.
   Ellacuria was rector of the Central American University, one of
the region's most respected institutions of higher learning.
Martin-Baro was its vice-rector.
   Rosa Chavez also condemned the killings of Hector Oqueli
Colindres, deputy secretary-general of the leftist National
Revolutionary Movement. Oqueli was reportedly kidnapped in
Guatemala, and his body was found Friday night with a gunshot wound
in the head.
   The government of Guatemala has promised to investigate, but has
said anything about what organizations or individuals it might
suspect.
   Some leftist politicians said they believe the Oqueli killing to
be the work of Salvadoran and Guatemalan death squads working
together.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0045 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 1730EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Czech-Soviet     01-14 0265</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Czech-Soviet,0272</SECOND>
<HEAD>Thousands Call For Early Pullout of Soviet Troops</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PRAGUE, Czechoslovakia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   About 6,000 people calling for the
earliest possible pullout of Soviet troops from Czechoslovakia
rallied Sunday on the eve of Soviet-Czechoslovak talks on the
topic, the state news agency CTK reported.
   The protesters in the town of Pohorany reportedly demanded the
estimated 70,000 Soviet troops in Czechoslovakia leave by Aug. 21 _
the 22nd anniversary of the Soviet-led invasion that crushed the
Prague Spring reforms of then-Communist Party chief Alexander
Dubcek.
   They protested the deployment of any foreign troops on
Czechoslovak soil and supported the government's efforts to seek an
early withdrawal, CTK said.
   Local chapters of the Civic Forum political movement organized
the rally in Pohorany, about 150 miles east of Prague, the capital.
   Negotiations between Czechoslovakia and the Soviet Union on the
withdrawal of the Red Army troops will start Monday. No other
details were known.
   The government has proposed that the Soviet soldiers be removed
by the end of the year.
   Also Sunday,the new Party of Democratic Socialism asked the
government to appeal to the Soviet Union for disclosure of names of
those officials who asked the Soviet Union for military
intervention in 1968.
   Former Communist Party ideologist Vasil Bilak, who since has
been expelled from the party, and former Parliament president Alois
Indra have long been named as among Czechoslovak leaders calling
for the Kremlin's help to ``save socialism'' in Czechoslovakia.
   A peaceful revolution in November and December toppled the
hard-line Communist government. Dissident playywright Vaclav Havel
is now president and Dubcek is head of Parliament.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0046 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 1755EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Iran-Soviet     01-14 0429</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Iran-Soviet,0441</SECOND>
<HEAD>Soviet Moslems Swim To Iran, Hundreds Gather On Border</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Soviet-Unrest, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NICOSIA, Cyprus (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A number of Soviet Moslems escaped into
Iran by using inflated tire tubes to float across the Araks River
that separates the two countries, Iran's official Islamic Republic
News Agency reported Sunday.
   IRNA, monitored in Nicosia, did not say how many Soviet Moslems
entered Iran during the crossing in sub-zero temperatures Saturday.
It reported earlier that 12 such crossings have occurred since
riots involving Shiite Moslems in Soviet Azerbaijan broke out Dec.
31.
   The report of the escapes came as official Soviet media said at
least 25 people died in Baku, the Azerbaijani capital, after
rioting between Azerbaijanis and the mainly Christian Armenian
minority broke out overnight. Reports said the unrest spread across
the republic Sunday.
   Shiites in the Soviet province are demanding closer links with
their fellow Moslems in northwest Iran amid the wave of reform that
has been sweeping Eastern Europe. Some militants want total union.
   IRNA said that about 1,000 Soviet Moslems congregated on the
Soviet bank of the Araks Saturday, shouting greetings and religious
slogans to a similar number or Iranian Azerbaijanis gathered on the
other side.
   Such gatherings are reported frequently in the Iranian media.
Tehran television, also monitored in Nicosia, earlier showed a
gathering of about 1,000 Soviet Moslems across the river Friday.
   The Soviet Azerbaijanis share a common culture, language and
religion with their Iranian cousins, who constitute about one-third
of Iran's 55 million population.
   The other conflict in the southern republic between militant
Soviet Azerbaijanis and Soviet Armenians is over who should govern
the mostly Armenian enclave of Nagorno-Karabakh in Azerbaijan.
   Iran's official media has made no mention of the bloodshed
reported in Nagorno-Karabakh and Baku, Soviet Azerbaijan's capital.
   The Soviets have long been fearful of Moslem unrest along the
southern border with Iran. But President Hashemi Rafsanjani's
government in Tehran, which has good links with Moscow, apparently
does not want to stir up Islamic fervor in the region.
   Iranian Foreign Minister Ali Akbar Velayati said Saturday his
country would welcome Soviet Moslems who wish to visit Iran, IRNA
reported.
   Earlier this month, Soviet demonstrators calling for the
reunification of the Soviet and Iranian Azerbaijans went on a
rampage for several days, tearing down border fences, guard towers
and communication lines.
   Azerbaijan was once completely ruled by Iran and was divided in
1828.
   In 1941, the Red Army invaded northern Iran and set up a
short-lived puppet republic after World War II. But the Soviets
pulled out in 1946 under international pressure.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0047 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 1759EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Chile-Crash     01-14 0201</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Chile-Crash,0205</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bodies Recovered From Plane Crash That Killed Two Americans</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SANTIAGO, Chile (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Police on Sunday recovered five bodies,
including those of two U.S. government officials, from the wreckage
of a plane crash in the Andes in northern Chile.
   The air force said the bodies were taken to Copiapo, a city in
the Atacama desert 500 miles to the north, and flown to Santiago
later in the day.
   The twin-engine Cessna 206 crashed Wednesday night, shortly
after taking off from the Copiapo Chamanate airport. It was found
Saturday near Copiapo, according to Cmdr. Rodolfo Acunna, head of
the air force Rescue Service.
   The Americans killed were John Harty, Jr. and Patrick Pouzar,
officials of the Food and Drug Administration who arrived in Chile
a week ago to check security procedures in the export of fruit to
the United States.
   The security checks were part of an agreement reached with Chile
after two grapes laced with cyanide were found in Philadelphia last
year. The finding prompted the temporary suspension of the sale of
all Chilean fruit in the United States.
   The Chilean victims were the pilot, a Chilean agricultural
official and an executive for the Chilean Fruit Exporters
Association.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0048 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 1918EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Sudan     01-14 0162</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Sudan,0166</SECOND>
<HEAD>Government Claims Killing 21 Rebels in Fighting</HEAD>
<DATELINE>KHARTOUM, Sudan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Army troops killed 21 rebels and
destroyed at least four of the insurgents' camps in southwestern
Sudan, the armed forces newspaper reported Sunday.
   The daily al-Kuwat al-Musalaha said the operation took place
Wednesday. There was no way to independently confirm the claims.
   The newspaper said an army unit destroyed the rebel camps of
Bekka, Kamouda, Gardoud and Gadham Kajar in the southern part of
the Kordofan region. Kordofan is in western Sudan.
   It said the 21 soldiers of the rebel Sudan People's Liberation
Army were killed during an attack on Karareikh camp. Army troops
seized a number of rifles, ammunition and cattle that the rebels
had looted from neighboring villages, it said..
   Five army troops were slightly wounded during the fighting, the
report said.
   The rebels, who are mainly Christian and animist, took up arms
against the Moslem-dominated government in 1983. They want more
autonomy and economic reforms.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0049 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 1941EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-StockMarkets     01-14 0518</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Stock Markets,0533</SECOND>
<HEAD>Analysts: Stock Market News Not Likely to Improve</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TOM BUERKLE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Friday's big drop on world stock markets and increasing worries
about inflation and interest rates gave investors a jolt, and
analysts say the news isn't likely to improve soon.
   In Tokyo, a weak yen and soaring interest rates caused the
Nikkei average of 225 stocks to slide 653.36 points to 37,516.77 on
Friday, the biggest one-day point decline in the index since
November 1987.
   Japanese markets could remain weak at least until elections for
the lower house of Parliament next month, experts said.
   News later Friday on Wall Street that U.S. wholesale price
inflation hit an eight-year high of 4.8 percent in 1989 exacerbated
the decline. The Dow Jones industrial average plunged 71.46 points,
or 2.59 percent, the biggest one-day point drop since October's
190-point plunge.
   Inflation fears also depressed stocks in London. Frankfurt's
stock exchange avoided a selloff, but inflation worries have been
pushing up interest rates in West Germany.
   The global trend toward higher interest rates threatens to
weaken a U.S. economy many analysts already believe is bordering on
recession. High interest rates and a weak economy don't bode well
for the stock market.
   ``It's a very good time to be cautious,'' said Robert Brusca,
chief financial economist at Nikko Securities Co. International
Inc. in New York.
   Investors should get a respite Monday because Japan's markets
are closed for a national holiday and the U.S. government bond
market is closed for Martin Luther King Jr. Day.
   That could limit selling in stocks because investors usually
look to put their money in bonds when they unload stocks, said
Kathleen Stephansen, senior economist at the brokerage Donaldson,
Lufkin &amp; Jenrette Securities Corp.
   U.S. investors may have to wait several weeks for positive news,
Stephansen said Sunday. The economy remains very weak, hurting the
outlook for corporate profits. But the Federal Reserve can't lower
interest rates to stimulate the economy because inflation remains
stubbornly high, she said.
   ``That's the worst kind of situation for the stock market,''
Stephansen said.
   Strength in the Tokyo market helped stabilize world markets in
the aftermath of the 1987 crash and last October's mini-crash, but
the news from Japan lately has been negative. The Nikkei average
has fallen almost 1,400 points, or 3.7 percent, in the first seven
sessions of the new year.
   The yen has weakened because of concerns that the ruling,
pro-business Liberal Democratic Party might lose its majority in
the lower house of Parliament next month. The currency's weakness
forces Japan to pay more for imports of fuel and raw materials,
putting pressure on inflation and interest rates.
   The United States is particularly vulnerable to higher interest
rates abroad because the country needs big inflows of foreign
capital to finance its trade deficit. But over the past year, U.S.
interest rates have declined while rates overseas have risen,
making investments abroad more attractive.
   ``There really isn't that much of an incentive to continue
flowing their moneys into the U.S. economy,'' said Samuel D. Kahan,
chief financial economist at Kleinwort Benson Government Securities
Inc.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0050 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 1949EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Romania-SwissBanks     01-14 0237</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania-Swiss Banks,0243</SECOND>
<HEAD>Swiss Lawmakers Pledge Help in Tracing Ceausescu Millions</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Romania</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BUCHAREST, Romania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Several Swiss lawmakers pledged help
Sunday in tracing money that Nicolae Ceausescu reportedly hid in
Swiss banks, but they said there was not yet proof any money had
been transferred to Switzerland.
   Heinrich Ott, one of seven Swiss parliamentarians meeting with
Romanian officials, said there were reports that the Communist
dictator deposited $400 million in gold in Swiss banks before his
ouster Dec. 22.
   Other reports suggested assets totaling up to $1 billion may
have been smuggled to Switzerland or other foreign countries, Ott
said.
   Henrich Rittmeyer, another lawmaker, said the process of finding
Ceausescu's missing millions could take years.
   ``The Romanian government and Romanian bank representatives
don't know yet how much money is missing,'' Rittmeyer said.
   Ott said a Swiss inquiry into possible Ceausescu bank accounts
included asking central banks in other countries to try to trace
Romanian funds transferred to Switzerland.
   ``We are all convinced that if it can be verified that there is
a fortune of the Ceausescu family, it must be returned,'' Ott said.
``We have a moral responsibility.''
   The delegation, which included lawyers and doctors, also
discussed Swiss aid to Romania, Ott said.
   Ceausescu ruled Romania for 24 years before his ouster in a
popular revolution backed by the army. He and his wife, Elena, were
convicted of ``grave crimes'' and executed Dec. 25.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0051 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 2014EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Mexico-TrainCrash     01-14 0200</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mexico-Train Crash,0205</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bus-Train Collision Kills 33</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LEON, Mexico (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A freight train struck a bus on the
outskirts of the northern city of Leon, killing at least 33 people
and injuring 26, a Red Cross official said.
   ``The bus tried to outrun the train, but it was overloaded,''
said Jose Luis Quintero, head of the Red Cross in Leon, 170 miles
northwest of Mexico City. He quoted witnesses.
   All the casualties were from the bus, Quintero said. He said at
least two of the injured were in critical condition.
   The accident occurred at a railroad crossing on the edge of the
city less than a mile from the Leon train station, the official
news agency Notimex said.
   Quintero said the bus was from a line that runs from the
countryside into town. Fifty-nine people were aboard the bus, which
has a passenger capacity of 45, he said.
   The 18-car freight train was on a run from Mexico City to the
northern city of Ciudad Juarez on the Texas-Mexico border.
   Quintero said the injured were taken to hospitals in Leon, a
city of about 2 million in Guanajuato state.
   Notimex said the bus driver was among those killed.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0052 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 2022EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-WeatherpageWeather     01-14 0241</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Weatherpage Weather,0249</SECOND>
<HEAD>Winter Storm Brings Rain and Snow to West</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   A winter storm dropped rain and snow in several Western states
Sunday, and officials in San Francisco asked people attending a
professional football playoff to leave their cars at home because
of parking lots turned muddy.
   Freezing rain coated portions of Montana, with drizzle in
Oregon, Washington and Idaho.
   Lower elevations of northern and central California received
heavier rain. Skiers in the Sierras and other mountain ranges got
snow.
   In San Francisco, Candlestick Park officials pleaded with people
coming to the National Football Conference championship between the
49ers and the Los Angeles Rams to take buses or commuter trains
rather than risk being marooned in perimeter parking lots turned to
mush.
   Mount Wilson, Calif., received 2.5 inches of rain and Sacramento
got about 2 inches during the 24 hours ending at 7 a.m. EST.
   A warm front extended from Wisconsin to Ohio, producing
scattered rain and snow in the Ohio Valley and the Great Lakes
region.
   In the central United States, sunshine and strong winds helped
raise temperatures into the 50s, 60s and low 70s, but readings in
the Mississippi Valley were in the 20s and 30s. Temperatures in
northern New England and New York state were in the teens.
   Temperatures in the Florida Peninsula were in the 60s and 70s.
   The cold spot in the Lower 48 states was Massena, N.Y., at -6
degrees.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0053 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 2109EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-KingHoliday 3rdLd-Writethru a0720 01-14 1205</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-King Holiday, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0720,1236</SECOND>
<HEAD>Coretta Scott King Calls on Bush to Help Unify America</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 11 grafs to UPDATE with new quote from Coretta
Scott King, quote from Kemp; PICK UP 8th graf, `Let's be ...';
DELETES redundant 26th graf.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos NY4, AX7</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DEBRA ELLIOTT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Martin Luther King Jr. was remembered in church services
nationwide Sunday on the eve of what would have been his 61st
birthday, and the slain civil rights leader's widow called on
President Bush to help unify America.
   Coretta Scott King delivered her annual ``state of the dream''
address at Ebenezer Baptist Church, where her husband was pastor,
before about 1,000 people, including such civil rights leaders as
the Revs. Jesse Jackson and Joseph Lowery.
   Mrs. King reflected on the dramatic social changes of 1989 in
other parts of the world and her husband's philosophy of civil
disobedience.
   ``The cataclysmic changes we have seen in Eastern Europe, in
China and in South Africa since last year have deep roots in this
very pulpit,'' she said.
   Mrs. King, noting that Bush is to deliver his State of the Union
address in a few days, recalled a State of the Union speech in the
1960s by then-President Johnson.
   Johnson ``captured the imagination of the American people just
by saying three little words, `We shall overcome,''' Mrs. King said.
   ``A quarter of a century later, President Bush has the same
opportunity,'' she said. ``He can help unify America if he will
break with the past by ending the arms race and working for
programs to provide jobs and educational opportunities for all
Americans.
   ``If he will avoid the kind of military entanglements that
destroyed (Johnson's) war on poverty, he can unify America and lead
the world to a higher destiny,'' Mrs. King said.
   Jack Kemp, U.S. secretary of housing and urban development,
presented Mrs. King with a large photograph of a Chinese student
standing in Beijing's Tiananmen Square holding a sign reading, ``We
Shall Overcome.''
   ``The dream lives on not only here, but throughout the world,''
Kemp said.
   Mrs. King called on King supporters to carry on her husband's
dream.
   ``Let's be clear that the future depends on us and our
determination to do God's will,'' she said. ``If you take nothing
else away from here today, let it be a conviction that you can make
a difference.''
   Earlier, Jackson, a former Democratic presidential contender and
former King aide, spoke to textile workers in Louisville in central
Georgia from the steps of the Jefferson County Courthouse within
sight of an old slave auction block.
   He urged all workers to stand up against their bosses for a
living wage and decent working conditions.
   ``As long as the plug is pulled and the lights are out, we're
all the same in the dark,'' Jackson said. ``Regardless of color,
hunger hurts.''
   In New York City, Mayor David Dinkins, the first black to hold
that office, told about 400 people at Judson Memorial Church about
King's struggle for equality and the need to continue.
   ``Dr. King took us to the dawn of a new era,'' Dinkins said.
``It is up to us to push on into the bright light of day.
   ``Dr. King dreamed of an inclusive society, where people would
be judged by their good will and their good deeds,'' he said.
``That is my dream for our city.''
   In Cleveland, Roman Catholic Bishop Anthony M. Pilla presided at
an afternoon prayer service at St. John's Cathedral.
   The Rev. Howard Moody, senior minister at Judson Memorial,
expressed concern at Sunday's service that King's dream had not
been fulfilled.
   Racial strife shows that the ``dream has been deferred and we
haven't lived up to the promise,'' said Moody, who is white.
   ``Racism and prejudice is still alive and well in this country
despite everything he did,'' Moody said. ``I don't think white
people have lived up to what he hoped we would. He was betting
everything on us. He bet his life, finally, that we would change.''
   King, the son of an Atlanta Baptist minister, led non-violent
marches in the South in the 1950s and 1960s in a quest to end
discrimination against blacks and other minorities. He was
assassinated on April 4, 1968, in Memphis, Tenn.
   King's teachings were honored Sunday in Miami as about 100 to
150 Haitian exiles staged a peaceful demonstration for democracy in
their Caribbean island nation. Demonstrators called for a halt in
U.S. aid to Gen. Prosper Avril's government and that Avril, on a
trade mission to Taiwan, be kept from returning home.
   For the first time, the holiday falls this year on King's actual
birthday, Jan. 15. There were plans in all 50 states and 144 other
countries for bells to ring and for a moment of silence in honor of
King at 12:30 p.m. EST. The New York Stock Exchange also planned to
pause, and the Liberty Bell was to ring in Philadelphia.
   In Los Angeles on Saturday, hundreds of volunteers, including
Mayor Tom Bradley, planted nearly 400 Canary Island Pine trees
along a seven-mile stretch of Martin Luther King Boulevard.
   At a banquet in King's honor at the University of Kansas in
Lawrence on Saturday, Martin Luther King III said his father's
dream is a long way from reality.
   ``The reality is that time has not arrived,'' King said. ``We
still have a long way to go ... to try to achieve his unfinished
work, to create a world where freedom, justice and equality becomes
reality to all mankind.''
   King said black enrollment in colleges has been declining, and
that black people are still denied advancement in business.
   King's birthday became the 10th national holiday in 1986.
   Forty-six states and the federal government mark the holiday.
The four states that do not recognize the federal holiday are
Arizona, Montana, Idaho and New Hampshire. Wyoming is observing the
holiday this year only.
   Arizona's holiday is on hold, and the state faces more months of
debate before voters settle the controversy in November. It began
when former Democratic Gov. Bruce Babbitt declared a King holiday
by executive order in 1986 only to have it rescinded by his
successor, Republican Evan Mecham.
   According to a poll published by the Arizona Republic newspaper
Sunday, 71 percent of those surveyed would vote to repeal a law
passed by the Legislature that would set a holiday for King and do
away with Columbus Day.
   But when Columbus Day was eliminated as an issue, 49 percent of
the 808 respondents said they supported a King holiday in
principle, 40 percent opposed it and 11 percent said they did not
know.
   In Phoenix on Sunday, a supporter of the King holiday there said
efforts to stop the referendum went against what King stood for.
   ``You have to remember Dr. King's part of his movement was to
get people the right to vote so now that the `people' have said
`put it on the ballot' to circumvent them from voting would almost
go against some of the principles,'' said the Rev. Warren Stewart
Sr. ``So what we have to do is the more difficult task, and educate
people on why Martin King ought to have a holiday in Arizona.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0054 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 2139EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Rushdie     01-14 0359</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Rushdie,0369</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rushdie Defends Himself Against Book's Protesters</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Author Salman Rushdie pressed his publishers to
bring out a paperback edition of ``The Satanic Verses,'' arguing in
an interview published Monday that Moslem hostility toward the book
``is totally misplaced.''
   Rushdie, who has been in hiding under police guard since Iran's
leaders ordered his death 11 months ago, was quoted by the Guardian
newspaper as saying he anticipated his plight would continue.
   ``One would wish the thing to come to an end,'' he was quoted as
telling the London daily. ``But I'm not the maker of the problem.
   ``I think if some of the people who protested about the book
took the trouble to read it, they would see that it is not
unsympathetic to them,'' he was quoted as saying.
   More than 1.2 million hardcover copies of the novel have been
sold since September 1988, but Viking Penguin has yet to bring out
a paperback edition.
   ``The paperback should be published,'' Rushdie was quoted as
saying. ``As for my own feelings, you can draw your own
conclusions.''
   Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini declared the book to be blasphemous
to Islam, and on Feb. 15 urged Moslems to kill the Indian-born
British author. The Iranian leadership also offered a $5.2 million
bounty.
   Iranian leaders who succeeded Khomeini after his death in June
have not withdrawn the death threat.
   ``It would be impossible not to be affected by this degree of
hostility, which is totally misplaced,'' Rushdie, born a Moslem in
India, was quoted as saying. ``I am not the enemy of my own people.
I do not feel like the enemy of my people.''
   Rushdie declined to discuss his security arrangements, but was
quoted as saying, ``You shouldn't assume I have very much freedom
at all.''
   Rushdie, 42, said he is writing a children's novel that he hopes
to finish in March, and said he is buoyed by support from friends
and readers.
   ``It's nice to know there is something other than anger aimed at
me,'' he was quoted as saying. ``I do get a great many letters of
support, including some from Moslems who've read the book.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0055 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 2140EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Newspage-SuperBowl     01-14 0252</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Newspage-Super Bowl,0256</SECOND>
<HEAD>San Francisco, Denver to Meet in Super Bowl</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   The Denver Broncos and the San Francisco 49ers earned a trip to
the Super Bowl on Sunday behind superb passing performances by
quarterbacks John Elway and Joe Montana, who wrote his name in the
all-time NFL record book.
   Behind an almost-flawless Montana, the 49ers beat their NFC
West-rival Los Angeles Rams 30-3 for the NFC championship in San
Francisco and a chance at becoming the first repeat Super Bowl
winner in a decade.
   Montana, who passed for 156 yards in a 21-point second quarter
that broke the game open, had a 20-yard TD pass to Brent Jones and
an 18-yarder to John Taylor, his 30th and 31st in postseason.
   That broke the record of 30 by Pittsburgh's Terry Bradshaw and
sent the Niners on to New Orleans, where in two weeks they will be
trying to match another standard set by Bradshaw and the Steelers
with their fourth Super Bowl victory. Pittsburgh was the last team
to win two straight Super Bowls, in 1979 and 1980.
   In Denver, the Broncos earned their fourth shot at the Super
Bowl with a 37-21 victory over the Cleveland Browns, whom they've
beaten three times in the AFC championship since 1987.
   Elway enjoyed his best game of the season and his best ever in
the playoffs, completing 20 of 36 passes for 385 yards and three
touchdowns. He took Denver on scoring drives of 82, 80, 80 and 60
yards.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0056 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 2214EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Duarte     01-14 0193</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Duarte,0199</SECOND>
<HEAD>Former Salvadoran President Returns Home</HEAD>
<DATELINE>GUATEMALA CITY (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Former Salvadoran President Jose Napoleon
Duarte, who has incurable cancer, left Guatemala for home Sunday on
board a special Guatemalan air force jet loaned by President
Vinicio Cerezo.
   His personal physician said Duarte does not have long to live.
   Carlos Armando Soto Gomez, Duarte's doctor, said Friday that the
64-year-old Duarte would travel Jan. 23 to Washington for cancer
treatment at the Walter Reed Medical Center.
   He also said that in recent days Duarte has needed blood
transfusions but has stabilized since then.
   Duarte was diagnosed as having incurable liver cancer in June
1988. At that time, doctors said he had six to 18 months to live.
   He left the Walter Reed center in November and went to Guatemala
instead of El Salvador because of an offensive launched by the
leftist Farabundo Marti National Liberation Front, the rebel
group's biggest offensive in El Salvador's decade-long civil war.
   Duarte won the presidency in 1984 but his centrist Christian
Democrats were defeated in March elections by the rightist Arena
party. He turned over the presidency to Arena leader Alfredo
Cristiani on June 1.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0057 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 2236EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Poland-Japan 1stLd-Writethru   01-14 0550</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Poland-Japan, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0666,0563</SECOND>
<HEAD>Japan and Poland Sign Economic Accord and Discuss Further Aid</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 7 grafs to UPDATE with agreements signed, Walesa
comment, details. Pick up 3rd pvs, `His visit...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By DEBORAH G. SEWARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WARSAW, Poland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Prime Minister Toshiki Kaifu of Japan told
the Solidarity-led government Sunday that Japan is considering
giving credit guarantees of up to $850 million to aid Poland's
transition to a market economy.
   Japan and Poland also signed a previously announced agreement
under which Japan will provide a $150 million credit to a
stabilization fund to back the Polish currency, the zloty, as it
becomes a convertible currency.
   Japan also pledged to provide Poland with $25 million in food
aid as well as $15 million that will be used to train Polish
managers.
   Foreign Ministry spokesman Wladyslaw Klaczynski told reporters
that the two sides on Sunday discussed a possibile $350 million
guarantee for government investments as well as a $500 million
guarantee by the Japanese Export-Import Bank for Japanese
investments in Poland.
   The signing ceremonies came on the first day of Kaifu's two-day
visit, which included a meeting and dinner with Solidarity leader
Lech Walesa.
   ``Poland's economic structures are 50 years behind the times. It
is hard to imagine rebuilding them without Japan,'' Walesa said as
he arrived for the meeting with Kaifu at the residence of the
Japanese ambassador to Poland.
   Kaifu was met at Okecie airport by Prime Minister Tadeusz
Mazowiecki and other leading Cabinet members. The Japanese leader
is on a 10-day tour of Europe which will take him to seven
countries.
   His visit comes as Poland is pursuing financial and technical
support from developed countries to implement a radical economic
reform aimed at developing a market-oriented economic system.
   Economic powerhouses like West Germany and the United States
have led the way in pledging aid to the newly elected
Solidarity-led government, but Japan has remained cautious.
   ``The Japanese always showed interest in our market, but
financial cooperation was always limited. They were skeptical in
the past, but this visit may be the beginning of a change,'' said a
senior Polish Finance Ministry official who declined to be named.
   But the official said the $150 million that Japan has pledged to
a stabilization fund to support the transformation of the zloty
into a convertible currency was a promising sign.
   The aid is in the form of a long-term credit at a preferential
interest rate of 2.9 percent.
   ``It's an important signal,'' the finance minsistry official
said in reference to to the stabilization fund assistance. ``The
Japanese are beginning to show some flexibility.''
   Poland is hoping for Japanese support at Paris Club negotiations
for Warsaw's request for restructuring its $38 billion debt. Poland
owes $1.3 billion to Japan.
   In addition to assistance for the stabilization fund, Tokyo has
pledged to bring several hundred Poles to Japan for training,
particularly in the banking field and quality control sector.
   Poland also is hoping to establish joint ventures with Japan. A
list of about 10 potential projects will be presented to the
Japanese during Kaifu's visit, but no agreements are expected to be
signed.
   The two sides also are expected to discuss the creation of an
investment fund to guarantee Japanese investments in Poland, the
finance ministry official said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0058 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 2251EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-PoliceSearches 1stLd-Writethru a0709 01-14 0573</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Police Searches, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0709,0585</SECOND>
<HEAD>Survey Points Up Pre-Stuart Police Sweeps</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 14 grafs to RECAST. Picks up 15th graf, `Stuart
committed ...</NOTE>
<HEAD>With AM-Stuart-Image, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Police made a practice of searching young blacks
and Hispanics in sweeps of their working-class neighborhoods even
before Charles and Carol Stuart were shot, more than 50 people said
in accounts published Sunday.
   Fifteen of those surveyed by The Boston Sunday Globe said they
were strip- searched by police officers without being arrested, a
practice residents of the city's Mission Hill section say was also
widespread after the Oct. 23 Stuart shootings.
   Young people told the newspaper that searches occurred prior to
the shootings in a variety of situations throughout working-class
sections of the Mattapan, Roxbury and Dorchester neighborhoods.
   Questions about the legality of police searches were first
raised last summer, but have become more prevalent amid allegations
that police violated privacy rights during their dragnet in Mission
Hill in the Stuart case.
   Johnny Saldana, 16, of Roxbury said that before police searched
him in front of a high school in early November they asked the
names of his family members and whether he had ever been convicted
of a crime.
   ``They stripped me,'' Saldana said. ``They pulled off my jacket.
They made me take off my pants. They checked my pants. It was
awful, like I was a criminal, which I'm not. I'm a B student. ... I
should be treated as an adult.''
   Raymond Bowder, 14, also of Roxbury, said he was walking from
his aunt's house with two friends in late October when a police
cruiser screeched to a halt in front of them.
   ``They were searching us and one of my friends said, `What are
you doing?' '' Bowder said.
   ``They said, `Shut up and pull your pants down.' I said, `What?'
They made me pull my underwear down, too. There were like four to
six people watching,'' Bowder said.
   Charles Ogletree, a professor at Harvard Law School, said such
searches clearly violated the U.S. Constitution.
   ``I haven't heard any case where it sounds like police have
followed the letter or the spirit of the law,'' Ogletree said.
``They seem to think that the mere presence of a person on the
street, or mere fear, is justification for stopping, searching,
removing clothing, taking items from people.''
   Police Commissioner Francis Roache said he would personally
oversee the investigation of any complaints arising from the
searches.
   ``There are going to be occasions when (officers) can't go back
to textbooks when making stops,'' Roache said. ``I'd like to use
these cases to get back on track if we're off track. If even one
person had their trousers lowered and there was no reason for
suspicion, that would really concern me.''
   Extensive searches were also conducted after Stuart told
authorities a black gunman forced his way into the white couple's
car as they left a hospital birthing class, then robbed and shot
them.
   Stuart committed suicide on Jan. 4, and black man police sources
had said was a prime suspect in Carol Stuart's death and Stuart's
wounding was cleared.
   Ogletree said searches as part of police sweeps are illegal
unless police have a detailed description of a suspect and frisk
only the person whom they reasonably suspect committed the crime.
   ``You have to enforce the law in Roxbury the same way you would
in Brookline,'' an upper-income suburb, Ogletree said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0059 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 1503EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-LastMine Bjt   01-14 0676</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Last Mine, Bjt,0700</SECOND>
<HEAD>New Mexico's Last Uranium Mine Ceases Operations</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MATT MYGATT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ALBUQUERQUE, N.M. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   New Mexico had 55 bustling uranium
mines in 1978, the most in the nation. Now it has none.
   The state's last active uranium mine, Chevron Resources Co.'s
Mount Taylor Mine near Grants, ceased mining and production Friday
because of low uranium prices, a spokesman said.
   ``We are putting the mine on standby,'' Santana Gonzalez said.
``The ventilation, pump systems and hoisting facilities will be
maintained.''
   The underground Mount Taylor Mine had employed 180 people, he
said. Of those, 97 will be laid off, 15 found jobs elsewhere and
the remainder will be retained, Gonzalez said.
   ``Employees will come back to the mine on Monday for a briefing
on benefits,'' he said from his Chevron Corp. office in Santa Fe.
   Jean Fisher, executive vice president of the Grants Chamber of
Commerce, said her community was saddened by the layoffs.
   ``It's hard to stay upbeat when things like this happen,'' she
said. ``It just trickles down to all of us in the community.
   ``Hopefully, we'll get something else in. That's what we need
and we're working on it. Maybe we'll advertise as a retirement
community,'' Ms. Fisher said.
   Frank Kottlowski, director of the New Mexico Bureau of Mines and
Mineral Resources in Socorro, said New Mexico's employment in the
uranium mining industry peaked at 7,000 in 1979.
   But the mines started closing as uranium prices tumbled.
   Bob Daniel, president of Chevron Resources, the mining and
geothermal subsidiary of Chevron Corp., said the U.S.-Canada Free
Trade Agreement and the entrance of China and the Soviet Union into
the uranium marketplace have forced uranium spot market prices down
to less than $10 a pound, the lowest in history.
   A pound of uranium sold for $43.70 in 1978.
   Uranium would have to sell in the $20-a-pound range for the
Mount Taylor Mine to remain open, Gonzalez said.
   Kottlowski said these indeed are dark days for the U.S. uranium
industry.
   ``With the present conditions and the federal government not
being very helpful _ not passing restrictions on imports _ I don't
see how it could come back for quite a while,'' he said. ``There
are so many vast resources in other parts of the world.''
   Chevron Resources, which announced last August it would close
the Mount Taylor Mine unless a buyer or partner were found, is
continuing to discuss the sale of the mine with potential buyers,
Gonzalez said.
   Sen. Jeff Bingaman, D-N.M., said the pumping at the mine will
prevent the mine from being flooded by underground water in the
area.
   ``This will ensure that a precious resource is not lost
completely,'' he said in a statement from Washington, D.C. ``I am
hopeful that Chevron can find a buyer so that the mine can resume
operations.''
   Sen. Pete Domenici, R-N.M., said in a telephone interview from
Santa Fe that there were talks with the Japanese about possible
purchase of the mine and more U.S. uranium, but ``their interest
appeared to be minimum.''
   In October 1988, New Mexico's ailing uranium industry received a
boost when four Japanese utility companies agreed to buy 3 million
pounds of uranium from the Mount Taylor Mine.
   The mine, near San Mateo on the western slope of Mount Taylor in
Cibola County, has 35 percent to 45 percent of the recoverable
uranium reserves in the United States, Domenici said.
   If the mine were flooded, then ``it is at least highly possible
that it would be lost forever and that is more than a trivial
incident in the uranium situation in the United States,'' he said.
   The U.S. Department of Energy, at the direction of the White
House, is trying to evaluate the impact of the mine's closure on
the national interest, Domenici said.
   ``We have asked the federal government to think of any and all
ways and means of logically preserving this asset and that's what
they're looking at,'' he said. ``Many of us believe we should not
become totally dependent on foreign countries.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0060 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 1502EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-StockMarkets Advisory   01-14 0040</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Stock Markets, Advisory,0045</SECOND>
<TEXT>
   Editors:
   Japanese markets are closed Monday due to a national holiday.
Therefore, AM-Stock Markets, Bjt, will not be led with Japanese
market activity, as promised on the AM-Business News Digest.
   
   AP Business News
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0061 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 1819EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f BC-AutoIncentives     01-14 0162</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Auto Incentives,0169</SECOND>
<HEAD>GM Workers Get Incentives To Help Sell Cars</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DAYTON, Ohio (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   General Motors Corp. workers in the Dayton
area, stung by layoffs, can win prizes by bringing customers to GM
dealerships under a program to fight weak auto sales.
   GM told its Dayton-area employees about the voluntary program in
a letter Friday. The plan starts Jan. 22.
   The program is modeled after one launched two years ago at a GM
truck and car engine plant in Tonawanda, N.Y., near Buffalo.
   GM spokeswoman Kathy Tanner said the Tonawanda employees helped
sell 1,140 vehicles last year.
   ``We have a whole lot of energy out there,'' GM spokesman Thomas
Tatham said. ``We think it will have a whale of an impact.''
   Employees who bring in a customer who buys a vehicle will
receive a shirt or jacket. Employees who bring in more than one
buyer earn chances at a prize drawing that includes gift
certificates and a vacation, Tatham said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0062 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 1827EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f BC-GMWagon-Move     01-14 0200</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-GM Wagon-Move,0208</SECOND>
<HEAD>GM To Move Wagon Model From Arlington Plant</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ARLINGTON, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   General Motors Corp. will stop
assembling the Oldsmobile Custom Cruiser Wagon at its Arlington
plant once the redesigned Chevrolet Caprice goes on line there in
June, officials said.
   The low-volume wagon is one of three car models now being
assembled at the plant. The Caprice and the Cadillac Brougham are
the others.
   GM officials said assembly of the Custom Cruiser will be moved
to its Willow Run, Mich., plant, where the automaker is
consolidating production of station wagons for the Chevrolet, Buick
and Pontiac lines.
   The move won't affect employment at the plant, a union official
said.
   Elimination of the Custom Cruiser not only leaves more room for
Caprice and Brougham production but also could clear the way for
building the new Buick Roadmaster in Arlington in 1991 as a
1992-model car, the Fort Worth Star-Telegram reported.
   The Roadmaster and a new Cadillac model are scheduled for
production as derivatives of the Caprice's GM300 platform. The new
Caprice is an aeordynamic version of the large, rear-wheel-drive
car it replaces.
   The Arlington plant is being considered for production of the
two models, the Star-Telegram reported.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0063 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 1837EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f BC-Chevron-Pennzoil     01-14 0176</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Chevron-Pennzoil,0183</SECOND>
<HEAD>Judge Allows Chevron To Sue Pennzoil</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SAN FRANCISCO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A federal judge has allowed Chevron Corp.
to sue Pennzoil Co. for allegedly concealing a takeover attempt,
but he refused to let Chevron use the case to validate its
anti-takeover maneuvers.
   U.S. Distrcit Judge Thelton Henderson said Chevron, despite a
``unquestionably weak .... factual support,'' could try to prove
its claim that Pennzoil was plotting a takeover or a forced
restructuring when it secretly bought 8.8 percent of Chevron's
common stock.
   Henderson, in the ruling Friday, dismissed the rest of Chevron's
suit, including the oil company's request for an order that its
management acted legally in changing company bylaws to make hostile
takeovers more difficult.
   The judge said Pennzoil was not challenging that action, and
also noted that several other suits against Chevron management had
been filed by other groups of stockholders in Delaware state courts.
   The rulings narrowed the scope of the suit San Francisco-based
Chevron filed Dec. 7 after Pennzoil disclosed it had bought $2.1
billion worth of Chevron stock.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0064 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 1848EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f BC-GE-Engine     01-14 0252</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-GE-Engine,0262</SECOND>
<HEAD>GE Reportedly Planning Biggest Civilian Jet Engine</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HARTFORD, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   General Electric Co. will unveil plans to
develop what it claims will be the world's most powerful commercial
jet engine, a newspaper reported.
   GE's planned turbofan, called GE90, is intended to be ready by
1994 and would offer up to 95,000 pounds of thrust for a new
generation of jumbo jets, The Hartford Courant reported Saturday.
   The greater thrust would enable jets to carry more passengers
over longer distances, officials said. It also would enable
twin-engine jets to replace existing jumbo jets that use three or
four engines providing around 60,000 pounds of thrust each, they
said.
   Rick Kennedy, a spokesman at GE's jet-engine group in Evendale,
Ohio, said the company will announce a major engine development
program Tuesday, The Courant reported.
   GE officials declined to say how much it would invest in the new
GE90s, which would be capable of powering larger versions of the
four-engine Boeing 747s and the three-engine MD11, as well as the
twin-engine Boeing 777, planned for the mid 1990s.
   GE will own a majority of the engine, The Courant reported.
Snecma of France, which already makes engines in a joint venture
with GE, and MTU of West Germany have agreed to help develop the
engine, the newspaper said.
   Officials at GE's main rivals, Pratt &amp; Whitney of East Hartford
and Rolls-Royce of Great Britain, said their existing wide-body
engines could be modified to provide as much thrust as the planned
GE engine.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0065 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 1917EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f BC-GM-MissouriPlant     01-14 0271</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-GM-Missouri Plant,0283</SECOND>
<HEAD>GM Leeds Plant Will Not Reopen</HEAD>
<DATELINE>KANSAS CITY, Mo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   United Auto Workers officials told
several thousand idled workers at General Motors Corp.'s Leeds
assembly plant that their indefinite layoff was likely to be
permanent.
   Plant and union officials told the workers Saturday that the
company had eliminated the plant from consideration as a site to
build a new line of light trucks.
   ``We told them we thought this meant the end,'' said Dennis
Stanley, bargaining unit chairman for UAW Local 93. ``There is
nothing else out there.''
   The plant has been shut since April 1988, when 1,600 autoworkers
were laid off because of slow car sales.
   Officials have been trying to find a new product for the Leeds
plant for the past 18 months, but union leaders learned Wednesday
that the company had ruled out the plant.
   GM officials have not determined where it will build the new
truck line but they indicated no other products are being
considered for the Leeds plant.
   A UAW agreement with GM prohibits the closing of any plants
until December.
   ``Nothing will be said until September,'' Stanley said. ``Then
we'll probably be told we'll be closed.''
   Leeds at one time employed more than 4,000 people to produce
GM's ``J-cars,'' or front-wheel-drive subcompacts. As sales
declined and inventory accumulated in 1987, GM laid off 2,700
workers. The company idled the plant and laid off the remaining
1,600 workers in 1988.
   Earlier this month, GM announced it was laying off 700 employees
at its Fairfax plant in Kansas City, Kan. That plant is the sole
maker of the Pontiac Grand Prix.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0066 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 1925EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f BC-MellonBank     01-14 0138</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Mellon Bank,0145</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mellon Chairman Takes President's Title</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PITTSBURGH (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Mellon Bank Corp. Chairman Frank Cahouet has
taken the additional title of president following the departure of
President Anthony Terracciano.
   Cahouet also named four new vice chairmen and a new chief
financial officer in a reorganization of Mellon's office of the
chairman.
   The appointments were announced in a memorandum to employees
Friday.
   Cahouet said his new duties will include direct responsibility
for the bank holding company's human resource and auditing
departments.
   Terracciano announced recently that he was leaving to become
chairman of New Jersey-based First Fidelity Bancorp. next month.
   Mellon recruited Terracciano two years ago from Chase Manhattan
Bank, where he was vice chairman. Under his tenure, the
Pittsburgh-based Mellon restructured its retail operations,
increased its presence in Philadelphia and did more business with
mid-sized corporations.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0067 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 1927EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-Romania-EEC     01-14 0428</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania-EEC,0443</SECOND>
<HEAD>Common Market Considering Economic Cooperation With Romania</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By G.G. LABELLE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUCHAREST, Romania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The vice president of the European
Economic Community's governing commission said Sunday that the EEC
is examining the possibility of trade and economic cooperation
agreements with Romania.
   Frans Andriessen announced the EEC position at a news conference
after a day of meetings with the provisional Romanian leadership
and representatives of five opposition parties.
   Romanian Foreign Minister Sergiu Celac told the news conference
that his country's economy is in ``almost complete ruin'' and needs
massive imports of food to feed its 23 million people.
   Andriessen, who is Dutch, said he discussed short-term aid with
interim President Ion Iliescu, Prime Minister Petre Roman, Celac
and other officials. But he added there was not time on the one-day
visit to talk about longer-term projects.
   ``We are ready to review negotiations on a trade agreement and
an agreement of economic cooperation,'' Andriessen said.
   He said technical experts who accompanied him would stay on to
study short-term aid needs. A statement distributed at the news
conference said that ``as soon as possible'' a meeting would be
arranged on a trade and economic agreement.
   The EEC cancelled a 1980 trade agreement with Romania last year
because of human rights abuses during the regime of dictator
Nicolae Ceausescu, who was overthrown and executed in late December.
   Asked if a revived agreement would have to be put off until
after elections for a permanent government, Andriessen said no
``substantial package'' could probably be worked out until after
such a vote. But he added he was not listing an election as a
condition for aid.
   Andriessen said the only conditions were ``the state of play of
democracy'' in Romania and certain economic and monetary conditions
in line with EEC philosophy.
   Celac was asked why Romania needed an infusion of aid when
Ceausescu's stringent economic policies succeeded in paying off a
foreign debt of more than $10 billion between 1982 and last year.
   ``The repayment of the huge foreign debt was made at a cost of
great suffering to the people and the almost complete ruin of the
economy,'' he replied. ``We are none the better for having paid the
foreign debt. We have a lot to rebuild.
   ``We are now impelled to import food massively,'' he said,
adding it was needed both to feed the population and to save
livestock.
   Andriessen was asked if there was a time frame for Romania
joining the EEC. He responded that the EEC was not accepting new
members at this point.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0068 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 1931EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f BC-CigaretteProtest     01-14 0324</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Cigarette Protest,0336</SECOND>
<HEAD>Groups Protest Black Cigarette Campaign</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PHILADELPHIA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Black leaders and health organizations plan
to protest the R.J. Reynolds Tobacco Co.'s launch here of a new
menthol cigarette targeted at blacks. The company says it's a
victim of discrimination.
   Reynolds plans to introduce Uptown cigarettes in Philadelphia on
Feb. 5 as a test before marketing the brand nationally.
   ``They're taking their own brand of death and trying to market
it to the black community,'' said Pastor Jesse Brown of the Christ
Evangelical Lutheran Church and president of the Committee to
Prevent Cancer Among Blacks.
   But Reynolds spokeswoman Maura Payne said the company was merely
trying to compete with other existing brands.
   ``There seems to be a bit of bigotry here,'' Payne said.
``People are arguing that black consumers don't have a right to buy
a product for which they have expressed a desire. We believe black
smokers have a right to choose between Newport, Salem, Kools and
Uptown.''
   Representatives from 30 groups including the American Cancer
Society, local black religious groups and the city Health
Department, met Thursday and will meet again soon to plan protest
strategies, said Robert Robinson, president of the National Black
Leadership Initiative on Cancer in Philadelphia.
   ``I'm very opposed to the idea of a cigarette being developed
and targeted to the African-American community,'' Robinson said.
``The African-American community is already suffering the highest
rate of cancer in the country.''
   Uptown is being marketed partly because Reynolds' other menthol
cigarette _ Salem _ has declined in popularity, Ms. Payne said.
About 62 percent of all black smokers prefer menthol cigarettes,
she said, but studies showed Salem had too much menthol for many
black smokers.
   Reynolds chose Philadelphia as a test market because of its
sizable black population, Ms. Payne said.
   According to the U.S. Office of Smoking and Health, 34 percent
of blacks and 29 percent of whites smoked cigarettes in 1985, the
latest figures available.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0069 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 2017EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f BC-UAL     01-14 0255</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-UAL,0264</SECOND>
<HEAD>Pilots To Try For Buyout Plan Next Week</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CHICAGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Officials of United Airlines' pilots union say
they'll try to come up with a new buyout proposal for parent UAL
Corp. by the middle of next week to prevent a costly
recapitalization by the board.
   The union's governing council will meet Jan. 24 ``to determine
if we can develop a viable proposal for employee ownership to
submit to the board the next day,'' three top officials of the
United branch of the Air Line Pilots Association said in a letter
to the 7,000 members Saturday.
   Last week, the board of suburban Elk Grove Village-based UAL
said its advisers would try to submit a recapitalization plan by
Jan. 25 because no leveraged buyout proposal from employees was in
sight.
   Such a recapitalization, intended to boost the company's stock
price, would be likely to reduce UAL's equity and increase its debt.
   The pilots and UAL Chairman Stephen Wolf led a $300-a-share, or
$6.8 billion, buyout attempt for the carrier's parent last year.
The offer collapsed when they failed to obtain financing, though,
and talks to come up with a revised plan have gone slowly.
   The letter to union members said traditional labor tactics, even
calling for a strike, are of ``questionable and limited value'' in
blocking a recapitalization. It was signed by union chairman
Frederick Dubinsky, vice chairman Stephen Smith and treasurer Felix
Isherwood.
   They said the only course was to submit a proposal for employee
ownership at the Jan. 25 board meeting.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900114-0070 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-14-90 2103EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>d f PM-Disney'sDecade     01-14 0747</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Disney's Decade,0772</SECOND>
<HEAD>Major Expansion To Include New Theme Park, Soviet Pavilion</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By IKE FLORES</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LAKE BUENA VISTA, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A fourth theme park, a Soviet
pavilion and seven new hotels will be among major projects to be
built during a decade of rapid expansion at Florida's Disney World,
Disney Chairman Michael Eisner announced.
   The 1990s also will feature the entertainment conglomerate's
venture into time-share vacation units, and it plans to open 29 new
attractions at its three existing Florida parks: the Magic Kingdom,
Epcot Center and Disney-MGM Studios.
   Walt Disney Co. already has plans to open Euro Disneyland near
Paris and to build studio attractions at its Japanese and
California parks during the next few years, among other additions,
Eisner said. On Friday, Disney said it is studying the possibility
of opening another Southern Califoria theme park.
   ``But this is the place where the `Disney Decade' will have the
most impact,'' he said Sunday.
   Eisner would not put a price tag on any of the new projects but
said each ``must give the Walt Disney Co. the required return on
investment.''
   The company's objectives are to grow about 20 percent a year
``and have a return on equity of 20 percent for the next decade ...
so we can stay healthy.''
   Disney expects total attendance at all its parks to approach 100
million visits a year by the end of the century, said company
President Frank Wells. Though Disney does not provide annual
attendance figures, published reports have said that Disney
attractions worldwide drew about 30 million people last year.
   Eisner, Disney's chairman and chief executive officer, said at a
news conference at the newly opened 758-room Swan Hotel that the
company anticipates a strong national economy over the decade but
that some of Disney's plans could be modified if there is a drastic
downturn.
   Otherwise, he said, ``Everything we have announced will
definitely be built.''
   Disney officials would not disclose any details about the fourth
Florida park or say when construction would begin.
   Negotiations with Soviet officials have been taking place for
years, and an agreement on a Soviet pavilion at Epcot Center is
near, Eisner said. Also to be announced soon, he said, are plans
for a Swiss pavilion featuring a Matterhorn ride.
   Most of the focus at the start of the decade will be on new
hotels and expansion of the newest Central Florida park, Disney-MGM
Studios, because ``its overwhelming success caught us off guard.''
   Sixteen new shows will result in doubling the capacity of the
studios' exhibits in the next five years, Eisner said.
   These include the newly opened Star Tours thrill ride, several
shows featuring the Muppets, a Dick Tracy musical revenue based on
a Dick Tracy movie and the revival of the television game show
``Let's Make A Deal.''
   Seven new or completely transformed attractions will be
introduced at the Magic Kingdom and five at Epcot Center, he said.
   The $375 million Swan, formally opened Saturday, is the first of
the hotels being built with entertainment as the main architectural
theme. They will have 5,500 guest rooms in total and are in
addition to two others under construction.
   Eisner said Walt Disney World did not intend to be ``completely
self-contained'' in guest accommodations and activities. ``But
we're not meeting the demand of those who want to stay on-site,''
he said.
   The Swan is part of a convention center complex with a
1,509-room hotel called the Dolphin that is scheduled to open July
4.
   Miami Dolphins quarterback Dan Marino assisted Sunday in
ceremonies at which the first of two 30-ton dolphin statues was
hoisted to the roof of the partially completed hotel.
   Among its other expansion plans, Disney says it will build 500
time-share units near its theme parks. Replying to a question about
the bad reputation many of these developments have acquired, Eisner
said the company believed ``we can do it in an attractive, honest
way.''
   A long-discussed commercial shopping mall is still planned on
property Disney owns in neighboring Osceola County, and Eisner said
details of the project are to be announced within 60 days.
   Disney owns 27,400 acres straddling Orange and Osceola counties.
   A 30-acre ``Disney Boardwalk,'' in the tradition of the Atlantic
City and Coney Island amusement areas, is scheduled to open late
next year.
   There was speculation in the past week that Disney also planned
a zoo or live-animal attraction, but Eisner said there were no such
projects in the works.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
</Collection>
