<Collection>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0001 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 2325EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Obit-Bernstein -URGENT- a0400 10-14 0811</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Bernstein, 4th Ld, a0400,1017</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<HEAD>Leonard Bernstein, Composer and Conductor, Dies</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: INSERTS one graf after 2nd with Solti quote. Georg is cq. SUBS
8th graf, ``It's really...' with 2 grafs to UPDATE with Isaac Stern
comment. Picks up 9th graf pvs, `The loss...'</NOTE>
<HEAD>With AM-Bernstein-Works</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos NY31, NY32, NY38, LaserColor NY34</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BETH J. HARPAZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Leonard Bernstein, the impassioned American
maestro who thrilled an international multitude with his spirited
shows ``On the Town'' and ``West Side Story,'' his podium
pirouettes and his hundreds of recordings, died Sunday. He was 72.
   Bernstein was a conductor, pianist, educator, author and
composer. His compositions included the theatrical, chamber music,
symphonies, ballet and even a Mass.
   ``He was the most versatile musician and he did more than any
other person in this century for the appreciation of American music
and music culture,'' said Sir Georg Solti, music director of
Chicago Symphony Orchestra.
   The son of Russian-Jewish immigrants, he led an orchestra
performance at a liberated concentration camp, raised money for the
Black Panthers and on Christmas 1989 celebrated the demise of the
Berlin Wall by conducting Beethoven's ``Ninth Symphony,''
substituting the word ``freedom'' for ``joy'' in its last movement,
the ``Ode to Joy.''
   He won Grammys, Emmys and a Tony, but in November 1989 refused
to accept the National Medal of Arts to protest cancellation of a
$10,000 National Endowment for the Arts grant for a New York art
exhibit about AIDS.
   Bernstein died in his Manhattan apartment, his spokeswoman
Margaret Carson said. Dr. Kevin M. Cahill, who was present, said
the cause of death was progressive lung failure.
   On Cahill's advice, Bernstein announced through Carson last week
that he would retire from conducting. Cahill said emphysema and
lung infections left Bernstein too weak.
   Bernstein, who was once a heavy smoker, canceled performances
with increasing frequency in recent months. His last conducting
appearance was at Tanglewood, Mass., on Aug. 19.
   Violist Isaac Stern paused after his 70th birthday tribute at
the Academy of Music in Philadelphia Sunday night to remember his
friend of 47 years.
   ``We knew he was critically ill,'' Stern said. ``He hoped
against hope he would be given a little more time for himself and
his activity. With him goes a spectacular, special era in American
music making. He was in a way the epitome of this burgeoning,
exultant young powerful giant called music making in this
country.''
   ``The loss is too great to consider,'' said choreographer Jerome
Robbins, his voice breaking. ``I've lost a very good personal
friend and collaborator from early on.''
   Morton Gould, a composer, conductor and president of the
America  Society of Composers, Authors and Publishers, said:
``Lenny had the magic touch. Almost anybody he conducted, he
popularized. Whatever he did, he had such involvement and such
dedication. When Lenny did Mahler, he was Mahler. He put Mahler
symphonies on the map.''
   John Williams, conductor of Boston Pops, said, ``His departure
creates an unfillable gap in our artistic and spiritual life. He
leaves us at a moment when we seem to need him the most.''
   Pianist Jerome Lowenthal, who had played Bernstein's ``Age of
Anxiety'' with Bernstein conducting, said: ``Bernstein related to
this music. He was a very tortured man and you just had to have a
word with him to know that, and at the same time he managed to be
embarrassingly charming. ... His success just exacerbated the
torture. He suffered from the pressures of superstardom.''
   Bernstein was a wiry young man of 25, with high cheekbones and
dark wavy hair, when he got his first major break. On Nov. 14,
1943, he filled in at the last minute for an ailing Bruno Walter to
conduct the New York Philharmonic in a concert broadcast on
national radio.
   The triumph of the orchestra's newly appointed assistant
conductor was was big enough to join the World War II headlines on
The New York Times' front page.
   His surprise appearance seemed to fulfill the prophecy of one of
his friends, who said: ``Lenny is doomed to success.''
   ``I walked on with an awful hangover and don't remember another
thing until I heard a thunderous ovation,'' Bernstein recalled
years later.
   On the podium, his jabs, contortions and leaps occasionally
caused him to fall. ``He shagged, shimmied and, believe it or not,
bumped,'' the late composer-critic Virgil Thomson once said.
   ``Bernstein rose vertically, a la Nijinsky, and hovered there a
good 15 seconds,'' New York Times' critic Harold Schonberg wrote.
   But later, on the occasion of Bernstein's 1,000th performance
with the Philharmonic, on Dec. 15, 1971, Schonberg wrote: ``At this
time it is only right to put reservations aside and salute
Bernstein for what he did and even for what he tried to do.
Bernstein was a figure that no conductor in history has matched.''
   Bernstein maintained that conductors should be actors.
   ``I don't mean that when the music is tragic you've got to act
like Barrymore in `Hamlet,' '' he once said. ``But you have to
indicate to the orchestra by your body and your face, which is all
you've got, what the shape of the phrase is.''
   Born in Lawrence, Mass., Bernstein got a relatively late start
in music. The boy genius was 10 when his Aunt Clara gave the family
an upright piano. But he always had an ear for music, recalled his
mother, Jennie.
   ``When he was 4 or 5, he would play an imaginary piano on his
windowsill,'' Mrs. Bernstein said in Joan Peyser's 1987 biography
``Bernstein: A Biography.'' ``When we finally got a piano, he did
what he now says he did: made love to it all the time.''
   His father, Sam, however, hoped Lenny would join his beauty
supply business. Lenny persisted with piano. He went on to study
under Walter Piston at Harvard, Fritz Reiner at Curtis Institute,
and Serge Koussevitzky at the Boston Symphony's summer Tanglewood
retreat.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick up 1st Add, a0402</HEAD>
<TEXT>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0002 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 2327EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--Salvador-Explosi     10-14 0137</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Salvador-Explosion,0137</SECOND>
<HEAD>Death Toll Rises to 18 From Hot Spring Explosion</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SAN SALVADOR, El Salvador (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The death toll rose to 18
Sunday from a geyser-like eruption that spewed boiling water and
red-hot rocks over a village in western El Salvador, officials
said.
   At least six of the victims died at a hospital in the city of
Ahuachapan, 60 miles west of San Salvador.
   The pre-dawn eruption Saturday in the village on Ahuachapan's
outskirts also destroyed 14 homes and damaged six others, officials
said. Among the dead were 13 children.
   A resident, Miguel Antonio Melgar, said seven members of his
family died and seven others were injured. The 56-year-old farmer
said he lived about 200 yards from the spring, which was a tourist
attraction before pressure built underneath it and it exploded.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0003 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 2358EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Hungary-Holocaust     10-14 0191</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Hungary-Holocaust,0194</SECOND>
<HEAD>Memorial For Holocaust Victims Unveiled</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BUDAPEST, Hungary (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The first memorial dedicated to
remembering the more than 85,000 Jews killed by the Nazi-affiliated
Arrow-Cross is an abstract angel in flight, imbedded in a sidewalk
on a bank of the Danube river.
   The mosaic, unveiled Sunday, was created in Budapest on the
river embankment where the Jews and opponents of the Arrow-Cross
government of Nazi-occupied Hungary were killed.
   Marched to the enbankment by storm troopers, the victims were
shot into the Danube's icy waters.
   The memorial, by Hungarian-born, Paris-based artist Anna Stein,
bears the inscription: ``Cry to the Heavens ... In memory of those
Hungarians who fell victim to the Arrow-Cross reign of terror in
the winter of 1944-45.''
   An estimated 80,000 Jews live in Hungary - the largest Jewish
community in central Europe. Before World War II, the country's
Jews numbered some 600,000.
   The memorial was sponsored by a non-partisan committee.
   A statement issued by the committee said the unveiling marked
``an important step toward national reconciliation'' and condemned
the ``ostracizing of the Jews from the nation and their
humiliation, deportment and murder.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0004 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 0734EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i BC-Israel-UN -URGENT-   10-14 0254</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Israel-UN,0279</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<HEAD>Israel Rejects U.N. Mission</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Israel on Sunday rejected a U.N. investigation
into the shooting of 19 Palestinians on the Temple Mount.
   The decision came after a four-hour meeting of Israel's Cabinet
and was announced by Foreign Minister David Levy.
   On Friday, the U.N. Security Council condemned Israel and
decided to send a team under Secretary-General Javier Perez de
Cuellar to investigate the slayings Monday.
   Israeli troops fired live ammunition at Palestinian protesters
on the mount, known in Arabic as Haram al-Sharif, or Noble
Enclosure. Haram al-Sharif is considered Islam's third holiest
shrine.
   Israel maintains its police were provoked by Palestinian rioters
who threw rocks from the Moslem compound on the Temple Mount at
Jews worshiping at the adjacent Western Wall, also known as the
Wailing Wall.
   It has mounted its own investigation by a panel of three senior
public figures: former Mossad secret service chief Zvi Zamir,
leading lawyer Yaacov Neeman and retired civil servant Haim
Kubersky.
   Before the Cabinet meeting, Justice Minister Dan Meridor said
the U.N. investigation would violate Israel's sovereignty over
Jerusalem. The Mount, holy to both Moslems and Jews, is in Arab
east Jerusalem, which Israel captured in the 1967 Middle East War
and later annexed.
   The U.N. resolution did not specifically mention a U.N. mission
to Jerusalem, but referred only to a visit to ``the region.''
   It was the bloodiest incident in Jerusalem since Israel captured
the city's Arab sector from Jordan in 1967, and the worst loss of
life in a single day of the 34-month-old Palestinian uprising
against Israel occupation in the West Bank and Gaza Strip.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0005 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 1137EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Gulf-SchoolBuses     10-14 0640</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-School Buses,800</SECOND>
<HEAD>Higher Fuel Prices Could Mean Cuts in School Bus Service</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf-US Coalition, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TAMARA HENRY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Education Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Persian Gulf crisis is expected to cost
the nation's school districts nearly $250 million in additional
fuel charges this year, and some officials say that could mean a
cut in service.
   The National School Transportation Association said it found in
a September survey that fuel prices for the 370,000 buses used by
U.S. schools had increased an average of 25.3 cents a gallon since
the Aug. 2 Iraqi invasion of Kuwait.
   ``The nation's yellow school buses drive a total of some 3.5
billion miles a year, transporting about half of all U.S.
students,'' said Karen Finkel, executive director of the
association.
   ``No one wants to cut service to schoolchildren,'' she said, but
added that school officials have begun looking at ways to cut fuel
costs.
   Short-term solutions include teaching drivers methods to improve
fuel economy, such as reducing time spent idling and parking buses
at the schools to eliminate the drive back to the bus lot.
   More drastic long-term solutions include reducing the number of
routes by making children walk longer distances or serving more
than one school with the same bus.
   According to the association's survey, the Southeast and West
have suffered the most, with average increases of 36.9 cents and
34.2 cents per gallon, respectively.
   In the Northeast, the average price was up 28.1 cents, while
fuel prices were up an average of 26.9 and 23.1 cents in the
Midwest and Southwest respectively.
   But Carl Janssens, executive vice president of National School
Bus Service Inc., says the increased price ``is obviously one
that's built on speculation.''
   ``We've not had any problem with supply. There's no shortage,''
said Janssens, whose Barrington, Ill.-based company operates 3,000
buses in New York, Massachusetts, Maine, New Hampshire, New Jersey,
Pennsylvania, Michigan, Illinois, Wisconsin and Minnesota.
   The Los Angeles Unified School District has had experience
dealing with such a crisis. About 20,000 school students were put
off school buses 10 years ago because of budget cuts, said Bud
Dunevant, director of transportation.
   And the Persian Gulf crisis is only increasing the problem,
Dunevant said.
   The district uses about 9 million gallons of gasoline and diesel
fuel a year, and Dunevant said last year's bill was $4.2 million.
   However, he estimated that by the end of this school year the
cost will reach $6.2 million.
   ``We're dealing with it because we have to,'' said Dunevant,
noting the busing done now is required by the court to eliminate
discrimination or by law to transport special education students or
to relieve overcrowding.
   About 2,900 school buses are used daily to transport 82,000
students. The school district's total enrollment is 625,000.
   Dunevant estimates an additional 6,000 students will be riding
the bus by the end of the year with the bus fleet increasing to
well over 3,000 by the end of the year.
   ``We can make some changes in the way we do transportation,'' he
said. ``It's possible that we might make some changes that we don't
like to have to do that would save some money, but we'd only do
that if it appears necessary and if the board authorizes us to do
it.''
   William Westcoat, supervisor of automotive maintenance for
Maryland's Montgomery County Public Schools, said it was a ``remote
possibility'' that more schoolchildren would be forced to walk
longer distances to school because of the fuel crisis.
   In Montgomery County, 63,000 of the 103,000 youngsters enrolled
ride school buses each day.
   The district is not required to provide bus service to
elementary schoolchildren who live with a mile of school, middle
school youngsters who live within 1{ miles and high school students
who live with 1} miles.
   Westcoat said increasing those distances to cut down on service
and save money could put children at risk because they would have
to walk farther to school.
   ``It's a remote possibility at this time,'' he said. ``I'd say
it would have to be very critical before we would go to that
extent.''
   The district's budget calls for paying 75 cents a gallon for
fuel, but the cost now is an average of $1.15 a gallon, Westcoat
said. About 2 million gallons of gasoline and diesel are used each
year.
   Although the problem hasn't been considered formally, Westcoat
said school officials could cancel field trips and athletic trips
rather than cut daily bus service.
   Other options for urban areas, Westcoat said, are ``enticing
high school students to use mass transit as opposed to providing
the yellow school bus.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0006 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 1139EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--Algeria-Protest     10-14 0181</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Algeria-Protest,0177</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tens of Thousands March Against Rising Prices</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ALGIERS, Algeria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Tens of thousands of people on Sunday
protested the skyrocketing cost of living that they blame on
government reforms to liberalize the economy.
   The protest by trade unionists in Constantine, this North
African country's third-largest city, came two years after economic
riots swept the nation.
   ``That's enough, the poor are dying,'' the protesters cried,
brandishing empty food baskets, as they marched through the streets
of Constantine, 300 miles east of the capital.
   The crowd presented a list of its grievances at regional
government offices and in a letter to President Chadli Bendjedid,
Algerian TV reported.
   They demanded lower food prices and job protection.
   Bendjedid introduced sweeping economic and political reforms in
Algeria after the riots in October 1988, where army troops gunned
down scores of Algerians protesting declining living standards.
   But market reforms are coming slowly and sales of Algeria's
principal export, oil, have been unable to revitalize a stagnant
economy marked by official unemployment of 25 percent.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0007 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 1139EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--Beethoven'sAilme     10-14 0184</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Beethoven's Ailment,0188</SECOND>
<HEAD>Beethoven Reportedly Suffered From Rare Rheumatic Disorder</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Ludwig van Beethoven, the composer who gradually
went deaf, lost his hearing and died from a rare rheumatic disorder
that is easily treated by modern medicine, a doctor was quoted
Sunday as saying.
   The theory challenges previous claims that the German composer's
deafness was caused by syphilis and that he died from liver failure
brought on by alcoholism, the Sunday Times said in reporting the
findings.
   The newspaper said Dr. Tom Palferman, a rheumatologist and
amateur cellist, has spent 10 years sifting through Beethoven's
private letters and autopsy reports to arrive at his diagnosis. It
said his findings will be published in the Royal Journal of
Medicine this month.
   ``I approached the problem as if Beethoven was one of my own
patients,'' Palferman told the newspaper.
   His theory is that Beethoven died of sarcoidosis, which affects
hearing and eventually destroys the liver, the newspaper said. The
doctor believes Beethoven could have been treated with modern
steroids and his life saved by a liver transplant.
   The composer lived from 1770 to 1827.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0008 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 1139EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Rembrandt     10-14 0233</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Rembrandt,0249</SECOND>
<HEAD>British Museum Doubts Authenticity Of Some Of Its Rembrandts</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The British Museum says 24 drawings from its
celebrated Rembrandt collection may not have been done by the
master, a newspaper reported Sunday.
   The conclusion by the museum, which has the world's largest
collection of Rembrandt drawings, is expected to touch off a major
dispute among art scholars, The Observer said in its report.
   The British Museum has the world's largest collection of
drawings by the 17th century Dutch painter and etcher.
   The suspect drawings, nearly a quarter of the museum's
collection, are now being attributed to Rembrandt's pupils or
followers. They include three of the museum's best-loved drawings
credited to Rembrandt: a picture of his sleeping son, one of his
wife and a nude study of his mistress, the newspaper said.
   The museum decided to reevaluate the drawings as it prepares for
a major 1992 exhibition of Rembrandt drawings.
   ``The downgraded works were probably not made as fakes, although
some of them may have been fraudulently passed off as Rembrandts at
some point in their history,'' said Martin Royalton-Kisch, the
British Museum's curator and organizer of the exhibition.
   Christopher White, Royalton-Kisch's predecessor at the British
Museum, opposes insists several of the downgraded drawings are
genuine.
   The questions mirror a similar debate over Rembrandt's
paintings. Earlier this century, about 1,000 paintings were
recognized as Rembrandts. But scholars now believe the number could
be as low as 300.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0009 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 1148EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p AM-HelmsCampaign Bjt   10-14 0676</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Helms Campaign, Bjt,820</SECOND>
<HEAD>RETRANSMITTING to include Bjt designation</HEAD>
<HEAD>Helms Campaign Using Fax Machine to Hold Press at Bay</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DENNIS PATTERSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>RALEIGH, N.C. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Democrat Harvey Gantt found a bright spot
in President Bush's recent campaign appearance on behalf of his GOP
rival, Sen. Jesse Helms. It brought Helms out in public.
   ``I was delighted to be in the same town with Sen. Helms
today,'' Gantt said. ``That's about as close as we've ever gotten
to being with him.''
   Helms refuses to debate Gantt and the conservative GOP senator
has been limiting his public appearances this year.
   His distrust of the news media runs so deep that his campaign
takes reporters' questions only by fax machine. The answers are
sent back the same way.
   ``The major papers in this state are biased and they misquote
and take out of context what our campaign says,'' said Beth Burrus,
the spokeswoman for Helms' re-election effort. ``This is a way to
keep them accountable.''
   The conservative Helms criticizes ``liberal media'' in virtually
every stump speech he makes.
   As in previous campaigns, Helms has flooded the airwaves with
television advertising, telling supporters in a recent fund-raising
letter that he needed another $1 million to buy television ads.
   ``I guess his campaign has learned time and time again that you
can't trust the `unpaid' media,'' said Thad Beyle, a political
science professor at the University of North Carolina. ``Reporters
may not tell it exactly like you want it told.
   ``With paid media (advertising), you can tell it the way you
want to tell it and nobody's there to question it.''
   During the August congressional recess, the Helms campaign
announced only a few public appearances, although Helms insisted he
had been campaigning around the state without telling reporters.
   Since then, the fax machine has been almost the only way for the
news media to communicate with the Helms camp.
   Helms himself has held only a few brief sessions with reporters
and no campaign officials will talk with the press on the
telephone.
   In one fax exchange, The Charlotte Observer inquired about a
Helms ad. In it, an unidentified woman accuses Democrat Gantt of
supporting sex-selection abortions and abortions in the last few
weeks of pregnancy. Gantt says the ad is untrue.
   ``Who is the woman in the Helms for Senate abortion ad?'' The
Observer asked in a question sent to the Helms campaign.
   The reply: ``Why do you want it?''
   The Helms campaign only began releasing a schedule of public
appearances in September after Helms had returned to Washington.
His campaigning since then has been limited to weekend rallies
before select crowds of supporters and quick fly-ins, such as the
fund-raising breakfast with Bush last week.
   Gantt has tried to make an issue of Helms' reclusive campaign
style.
   It represents a ``double standard'' in coverage of the Senate
campaign, said Gantt press secretary Susan Jetton.
   ``We go out of our way to have Harvey out there every day,
answering questions, talking to reporters. We make sure reporters
have a schedule days in advance of where Harvey will be,'' she
said.
   The widespread use of fax machines has given Helms just one more
way to hold reporters at arm's length, Beyle said.
   ``I've always found his relationship with the media curious,
given his background,'' Beyle said, referring to Helms' stints as a
newspaper city editor and broadcaster. ``You would think with his
background he would be able to play the media like a violin.''
   After Bush's visit last week, Gantt said ``it was interesting to
note that Mr. Helms still needs to bring the president in to speak
on behalf and to defend his record.''
   ``Why doesn't he simply come on out now and speak for himself?''
Gantt asked. ``He's got 18 years in the Senate. He seems to lack
the courage to want to come out and speak to the people of North
Carolina and let them talk back to him.''
   In his three terms in the Senate, Helms has fostered an image in
North Carolina as a down-home boy fighting the ``city slickers'' in
Washington.
   But his political organization, the Congressional Club, has
always been on the cutting edge of technology. It raises funds 365
days a year with sophisticated computerized mail techniques and
over the years has fine-tuned the 30-second attack ads it
developed.
   In 1980, Beyle said, the Congressional Club ``showed you could
win an election with a candidate that wasn't seen by anybody - John
East.''
   East, a political science professor and political unknown,
unseated U.S. Sen. Robert Morgan with a hard-hitting television
campaign. East, a polio victim who used a wheelchair, made few
public appearances and his television commercials showed East from
the shoulders up talking into the camera.
   Television ad campaigning reached new heights in 1984, when
Helms and Gov. Jim Hunt blitzed the airwaves in a $25 million
campaign that was the most expensive Senate race in history.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0010 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 1155EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--BombThreat     10-14 0135</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Bomb Threat,0135</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bomb Hoax Delays Play at Tournament Watched by U.S. Ambassador</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A bomb warning was telephoned Sunday to a Tokyo
gymnasium where the U.S. ambassador was about to arrive, but police
said they found no bomb in a search that delayed a tennis
tournament for one hour.
   Ambassador Michael Armacost arrived as scheduled, and saw Ivan
Lendl beat Boris Becker in the finals of the Seiko Super Tennis
Tournament.
   Isao Abe of the Harajuku police station said there was no
confusion, although the gymnasium was filled with 7,000 spectators.
Organizers announced that the match was being delayed for technical
reasons.
   Abe described the bomb threat as a mischief call.
   More than 30 policemen and guards searched the gym for one hour,
but found no bomb, he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0011 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 1156EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SAfrica-Crash     10-14 0106</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-SAfrica-Crash,0089</SECOND>
<HEAD>24 Killed When Truck, Van Collide</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JOHANNESBURG, South Africa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Twenty-four blacks were killed
and more than 30 injured when a truck loaded with laborers collided
with a taxi van on a narrow bridge, the government-run South
African Broadcasting Corp. reported Sunday.
   The truck, which was packed with more than 60 people, fell off
the bridge into the Mutshindudi River that runs through the Venda
homeland in the country's northeastern corner.
   Many of those injured in Saturday's accident remained
hospitalized Sunday, the SABC reported.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0012 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 1205EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-NewHavenChief     10-14 0631</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-New Haven Chief, </SECOND>
<HEAD>For New Haven Police Chief, It's Not Business As Usual</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LARRY ROSENTHAL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW HAVEN, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Police Chief Nicholas Pastore is trading
in his force of drug-busting, doughnut-eating militiamen for what
he calls social engineers.
   The new chief has banned leather driving gloves on police
officers as too intimidating and has told the members of his force
to steer drug users to treatment programs instead of jails.
   He's also told his officers to knock off the frequent
coffee-and-doughnut runs during their breaks because it gives them
a bad image with the public.
   ``I want the police to be perceived as a helping-hand agency,''
said Pastore, who has been on the job for seven months.
   That perception can be bolstered if officers, among other
things, help drug users rather than just arrest them, the new chief
said.
   ``We've tried the tanks, the helicopters, the big guns for many
years. It doesn't work,'' Pastore, 52, said in a recent interview.
``I don't subscribe to the philosophy that the more arrests you
make, it's going to solve the crime problem.''
   Arrests in New Haven, a city of 125,000, dropped sharply when
Pastore discontinued sting operations to round up drug buyers. He
has also stopped dispatching teams of officers into high-crime
neighborhoods for round-the-clock arrests and disbanded the
department's canine unit.
   Instead, he ordered about 20 more officers to walk beats, placed
officers at high-visibility posts throughout downtown and made
extensive community outreach efforts to end what he calls the
``we-they mentality'' in drug-infested neighborhoods.
   He also walks the streets of crime-plagued neighborhoods
himself, frequently striking up conversations with known drug
dealers.
   ``When I'm seen in these neighborhoods, people realize this man
cares,'' he said.
   His actions have brought praise from various members of the
public and business community, but have put him at odds with the
police department's union.
   A group of downtown merchants recently presented Pastore with a
a plaque for his efforts to increase police visibility. But Sgt.
Louis G. Cavalier, the head of the police officers union,
complained that the stepped-up presence has merely provided the
community with a ``false sense of security.''
   Pastore has also won the confidence of at least one drug user's
mother, who called him recently to say she needed to talk to
someone she could trust.
   The chief believes marijuana use should be decriminalized, and
he said his efforts to encourage addicts to seek treatment reflects
his belief that the drug problem should be resolved by physicians,
not lawyers.
   Such views earned him a prominent profile in the August issue of
``High Times,'' a magazine devoted to marijuana smoking.
   Pastore said he didn't know the free-lance writer who spoke with
him was doing the interview for High Times. But he added that he
was accurately quoted and had no problems with the story.
   His comments in a newspaper interview that there would be fewer
coffee-and-doughnut runs now that he was police chief ruffled some
feathers in the department. Union officials accuse him of
frequently entering restaurants and asking officers what they are
doing.
   ``There is the sense that the chief is on their backs
constantly,'' Cavalier said.
   Pastore said he recalls only one such restaurant incident. He
added that his doughnut policy is not an attack on his officers'
work ethic but on the traditional concept of police work.
   ``Police work should not be just doing what the dispatcher says,
then in between going to Dunkin' Donuts,'' he said.
   He praises his officers, but dismisses the union's criticism.
   ``The union doesn't care about the public,'' he said. ``All they
care about is what's good for them. ``They have become a group of
militant mercenaries.''
   Pastore came into office with a mandate to shake up the
department and move to a concept of community-based policing, in
which officers are assigned to individual neighborhoods. Because of
a tight city budget, the new program has gotten off to a slow
start.
   First-term Mayor John Daniels, a friend since high school,
bypassed nearly 20 internal candidates in hiring Pastore, who had
spent 18 years with the department before retiring in 1981 because
of a congenital kidney defect. The ailment has since been
corrected.
   ``His style is perhaps a little different from your typical
police chief, but if it serves a successful effort, I'm all for
it,'' said Michael Dearington, the chief state prosecutor in New
Haven. ``Some innovation is due in the area of law enforcement.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0013 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 1208EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Vietnam-Resistance     10-14 0329</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Vietnam-Resistance,0389</SECOND>
<HEAD>Vietnam's Supreme Court Imposes Prison Term on Infiltrators</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BANGKOK, Thailand (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Vietnam's Supreme Court has imposed
long prison terms on some of 38 men accused of trying to infiltrate
the country to topple the Communist government, the state news
agency said Sunday.
   The court sentenced the guerrillas' top commander, Tran Quang
Do, to life in prison and two other commanders to terms of 20 years
and 16 years, the Vietnam News Agency said.
   The others received terms ranging from three to 15 years, it
said.
   The People's Supreme Court sentenced the men Saturday after a
three-day trial, according to said report seen in Bangkok Sunday.
   ``The indictment said this was a case of special danger to
national security,'' the report said.
   It said the men confessed to ``collaborating with foreign
reactionary forces in an attempt to undermine and overthrow the
Socialist Republic of Vietnam.''
   Previous official media dispatches said the infiltrators
received help from the United States and Thailand. Both the U.S.
and Thai governments have denied the accusations.
   Saturday's report said the guerrillas were members of the
Vietnam National Liberation and Unity Front and of another group
led by Hoang Co Minh. He was a Navy vice admiral of the U.S.-backed
South Vietnam government that the Communists toppled in April 1975.
   Vietnamese authorities have said Minh was killed during an
infiltration attempt in 1987. Minh had been based in the United
States, where hundreds of thousands of Vietnamese who fled the
Communists have resettled.
   The report said Do, the top commander, led two groups of 68 men
who entered Laos from bases in Thailand on their way to infiltrate
Vietnam.
   It quoted Do, who is about 38 years old, as saying he had failed
in previous infiltration attempts in 1986 and 1987.
   The report said that from Aug. 26 to Oct. 2, 1989, the Laotian
armed forces, which are closely allied with Vietnam, captured 38 of
the guerrillas and killed the rest.
   An earlier Vietnam News Agency report said the guerrillas had
set up a base near the Vietnamese border and tried to persuade
people to join them in sabotage against key economic targets in
Vietnam.
   That report said the 38 were tried by Laos's Supreme Court, then
deported to Vietnam.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0014 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 1214EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Colombia     10-14 0168</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Colombia,0163</SECOND>
<HEAD>Seven Killed, Seven Others Wounded in Medellin</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BOGOTA, Colombia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Assailants dressed in military fatigues
fired on a crowd in the cocaine trafficking center of Medellin,
killing seven people and wounding seven others, police said Sunday.
   The assailants fired at pedestrians from two passing vehicles in
a working class neighborhood on Saturday night, a Medellin police
spokesman said in a telephone interview. He spoke on condition of
anonymity.
   Among those killed was a former policeman, the official said.
   The Medellin cocaine cartel has claimed responsibility for the
killings of hundreds of Medellin police officers earlier this year.
   A series of civilian massacres, allegedly in retaliation for the
assassinations of police, prompted officials to declare that
Medellin was falling into anarchy.
   The violence diminished in July, after drug traffickers called a
cease-fire in their yearlong terrorist campaign.
   ``This massacre is so frightening because it broke the calm in
the city,'' the police spokesman said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0015 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 1220EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SAfrica-FriendsAndRiv Bjt   10-14 0671</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-SAfrica-Friends And Rivals, Bjt,0796</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mandela and Buthelezi: Old Friends, Political Rivals</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY16</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GREG MYRE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JOHANNESBURG, South Africa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Nelson Mandela and Mangosuthu
Buthelezi are old friends who find themselves in a power struggle,
propelled by violence, that could delay the opportunity for blacks
to govern South Africa.
   The nation's two most powerful black leaders have known each
other since the 1940s. Both want black majority rule, but they have
different visions of the future. And neither appears ready for
concessions that might stop the bloodshed between their supporters.
   ``If the violence becomes endemic, this country could be worse
off after liberation than before,'' City Press, the largest
black-oriented weekly, said recently.
   Mandela, who leads the African National Congress, and Buthelezi,
conservative head of the Zulu-based Inkatha Freedom Party,
repeatedly call for peace, but each blames the other for the
fighting.
   ``People are actually dying because the ANC will not talk with
Inkatha and Mandela will not talk with me,'' Buthelezi said.
   But then Buthelezi, who also leads the KwaZulu homeland,
rejected an invitation to join other homeland leaders in talking
with Mandela.
   Buthelezi insists on a face-to-face meeting with Mandela.
Mandela, who is even willing to meet right-wing whites, has
refused.
   ANC leaders say Buthelezi has orchestrated the factional
fighting as a way to obtain such a meeting and enhance his stature.
Buthelezi, a quick-tempered man, bristles at the suggestion and
accuses the ANC of trying to crush its black rivals.
   Violence between followers of the ANC and Inkatha in black
townships around Johannesburg has claimed about 800 lives since
early August, but has eased somewhat in recent weeks. In the
eastern province of Natal, the ANC-Inkatha conflict has left about
5,000 dead since 1986.
   President F.W. de Klerk says he wants to negotiate the end of
the apartheid race policy that denies political power to blacks,
but that no progress is possible until the factional fighting is
under control.
   Mandela also wants to negotiate. But his militant young
supporters in the black townships demand arms and want results.
   Buthelezi, at 62 a decade younger than Mandela, insists Inkatha
be represented at black-white peace talks and claims the ANC wants
to exclude him.
   His Zulu supporters often are blamed for initiating attacks.
There are strong suspicions, unproven, that some Inkatha supporters
have acted with at least tacit approval from some sectors of the
police.
   The ANC, the largest black opposition group, is
socialist-oriented and has fought the government with boycotts,
protests, calls for sanctions and a guerrilla campaign that was
suspended in August. Inkatha rejects those tactics and favors
capitalism.
   Power, more than ideology, is the focus of their conflict.
   Thousands of young men beyond the leadership's control are
waging what amounts to gang warfare.
   In many neighborhoods, a road becomes the dividing line between
ANC and Inkatha followers. Young men fight in the name of
``Mandela'' or ``Buthelezi,'' but know little about the groups the
men lead.
   Buthelezi's well-tailored suits, capitalist economics and
opposition to violence against the government make him appear less
threatening to whites than other black leaders. The government has
hinted at seeking an alliance with him.
   When clad in his leopard skins at Zulu ceremonies, Buthelezi
also is the politician who appeals most strongly to tribal
loyalties and the Zulu warrior tradition.
   He sees tribalism as a fact that must be addressed in any
political settlement.
   Zulus, although divided politically, are the country's largest
tribe, numbering about 7 million.
   Inkatha claims 1.8 million members, virtually all Zulus. While
Inkatha is strong among the rural poor, the ANC gets much of its
support from urban, educated, middle-class blacks.
   The ANC plays down ethnic differences and has national support
that cuts across tribal lines. Most observers believe it would get
the most votes if the country's 30 million blacks were allowed to
cast ballots.
   Mandela and Buthelezi both joined the ANC in the 1940s, and
exchanged warm letters during Mandela's 27 years in prison.
   ``I remain indebted to him because of our friendship and the
support that he has given to me,'' Mandela has said.
   Exiled ANC leaders gave their blessing to Inkatha's formation in
1975, but were against Buthelezi becoming leader of the KwaZulu
homeland. The ANC sees the 10 black homelands as part of the
apartheid system, while Buthelezi considers them a step toward
majority rule.
   Since de Klerk began his reforms, black groups have battled each
other more than the government.
   ``The trouble with our country is that we do not have a
tradition of dissent, of allowing different points of view,'' said
Desmond Tutu, the black Anglican archbishop.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0016 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 1239EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SovietAlcoholism Bjt   10-14 0747</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet Alcoholism, Bjt,0901</SECOND>
<HEAD>Anti-Drinking Campaign Fails, Alcoholism Grows</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto MOSB1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BRIAN FRIEDMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   ``There is a saying: `Have a glass of vodka in the
morning, and you'll be free all day long,''' said Viktor, who led a
recent meeting of Alcoholics Anonymous in Moscow.
   More than 20 million Soviet citizens regularly take that advice,
and the problem seems to be growing worse.
   Prosecutors say alcohol contributed to 70 percent of the city's
violent crimes last year.
   While Viktor told two dozen recovering alcoholics of the motto
that sustained his 26 years of drinking, Sasha swayed in his chair,
obviously drunk. It was Sasha's first meeting, and no one was sure
whether he would return.
   At the meeting's tearful conclusion, speakers told of broken
marriages, lost jobs and the struggle to stay sober.
   Alcoholics Anonymous, an American program, enjoys some success
after three years in Moscow and has the grudging respect of
authorities, but the overall war on alcoholism in the Soviet Union
is going badly.
   ``There's enough work here to last three lifetimes,'' said Jeb
Byrd, a psychotherapist with the Caron Foundation of Pennsylvania.
His non-profit organization has a clinic in Moscow that combines AA
methods with outpatient counseling.
   Alcohol abuse is increasing; the number of heavy drinkers is
estimated at 20 to 25 million in a total population of about 290
million.
   At Truck Garage No. 21 in southeastern Moscow, supervisor Sergei
Borisov said he had to fire 120 people for drunkenness between 1985
and 1988, or 20 percent of his workers. The garage is a dispatching
point for bread trucks.
   Drunks stagger across Moscow's broad streets at night or
panhandle in parks during the day. Some pool resources for a bottle
and drink it on a street bench or in a ``stolovaya,'' a sort of
stand-up cafeteria.
   Many end up in drunk tanks or overcrowded, ineffective treatment
clinics.
   In March, President Mikhail S. Gorbachev admitted the
anti-drinking campaign he started five years ago, under which
alcohol production was drastically reduced, had not worked.
Treatment and rehabilitation programs are acknowledged failures.
   Nikolai S. Chernyk of the All-Union Voluntary Temperance
Promotion Society asked Parliament this month to revive the
Gorbachev program, but some lawmakers oppose a return to coerced
sobriety.
   When the program was implemented shortly after Gorbachev took
power in 1985, long lines formed at liquor stores and public anger
grew. Some alcoholics drank perfume, cleaning fluids or glue;
others made moonshine, which cut seriously into the sugar supply
and angered more temperate citizens.
   The government lost 47 billion rubles in alcohol sales during
the three years that supplies were severly curtailed, Chernyk said
in an interview.
   Production of alcohol has been increased again. Although it is
not plentiful in stores, the long lines are gone.
   ``Taking into account what is happening to our economy nowadays,
the government had to return to the old ways, and so we again began
increasing the sales,'' Chernyk said. ``And as soon as we started
increasing the sales, we began to have the negative effects of
alcoholism.''
   Vladimir Treml, a Duke University professor who has written
extensively on drinking in the Soviet Union, said statistics on
crime, life expectancy, accidents and causes of death all point to
increased alcohol abuse.
   According to official figures and his own estimates, Treml said,
per capita consumption of pure alcohol and moonshine by Soviets
aged 15 and older amounted to 9.5 quarts in 1989. That did not
include beer and wine.
   A complaint from a spouse, relative, neighbor, employer or
police can land an alcohol abuser in one of the occupational
therapy institutions known as LTPs, for their initials in Russian.
   They are barrack-like camps run by the Interior Ministry and
surrounded by fences topped with barbed wire.
   In the LTPs, alcoholics are treated more like prisoners than
patients. Treml said they receive no medical attention and are used
as cheap labor, receiving only one-third of their regular pay.
   An estimated 200,000-300,000 people are in the LTPs, and many
have been drafted to pick potatoes in the current harvest crisis.
   Some reports say alcoholics have even been sent from the camps
to work in distilleries.
   Inmates have gone on strike in recent months, demanding an end
to guards and punishment cells, and such privileges as family
visits and packages.
   Parliament is considering measures to reform LTPs and put them
under the Ministry of Health rather than the Interior Ministry,
which runs the national police.
   Chernyk said his temperance society had cured 8,000 alcoholics
in the past year, but recovering alcoholics and such experts as
Treml say the organization is ineffective.
   Treml said the group advocates prohibition, not temperance, and
tries to destroy the reputations of medical specialists who promote
moderation.
   Chernyk said his group is ready to cooperate with such groups as
Alcoholics Anonymous, which has 12 chapters in Moscow and 13 more
in various Soviet republics.
   A recent dinner in Moscow attracted about 450 recovering
alcoholics who were using the AA method, said J.W. Canty, chairman
of the Soviet-U.S. Joint Conference on Alcoholism and Drug
Addiction.
   Soviet programs employ some of those methods, like having
alcoholics keep journals and embrace some form of spirituality or
religion, including the Russian Orthodox Church.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0017 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 1304EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ArsenicPoisoning Bjt   10-14 0541</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Arsenic Poisoning, Bjt,0690</SECOND>
<HEAD>Trial Set To Begin For Woman Charged in Arsenic Poisonings</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto RA1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PAUL NOWELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   WINSTON-SALEM, N.C. (AP) - A 58-year-old former grocery store
clerk accused of using arsenic to poison two husbands and a
boyfriend over 16 years goes on trial Monday and could get the
death penalty if convicted.
   Blanche Taylor Moore, once described by a police official as
``an average, ordinary neighborhood lady,'' is charged with
first-degree murder in the Oct. 7, 1986, poisoning death of Raymond
Reid, who was her boss and later became her boyfriend.
   Although several women are on death row, only one woman has been
executed in this country since the 1976 U.S. Supreme Court ruling
allowing states to resume the death penalty. Velma Barfield, also
of North Carolina, was put to death in 1984 at age 52 for poisoning
a boyfriend.
   Prosecutors say Mrs. Moore systematically poisoned Reid; James
N. Taylor, her first husband, who died in 1973; and the Rev. Dwight
Moore, her second husband, who survived.
   Non-fatal amounts of arsenic also were found in the bodies of
her father, who died in 1966, and mother-in-law from her first
marriage, who died in 1970. No charges were filed in those cases.
   Moore was hospitalized in May 1989 shortly after returning home
from his honeymoon. Doctors were perplexed by his severe nausea and
vomiting. Tests showed the Burlington minister had ingested a near
fatal dose of arsenic; he remains disabled from it.
   Hospital officials notified police, who began checking into the
past of Moore's bride.
   They discovered that Reid, 50, had died three years earlier
after a long hospital stay. His body was exhumed and an autopsy
showed he died from arsenic poisoning.
   A subsequent autopsy also found a fatal level of arsenic in the
exhumed body of Taylor, who died at age 45 in 1973. At the time,
his death was attributed to a heart attack.
   Mrs. Moore will be tried later on the second murder charge in
Taylor's death and assault charges in the poisoning of Moore.
   Since her arrest July 18, 1989, Mrs. Moore has been held without
bail in the Alamance County Jail in Graham, just a few miles from
Burlington, where she had once lived and worked at the local
Kroger's grocery store.
   Mrs. Moore has steadfastly maintained her innocence.
   ``She's been stuck in a cell in the county jail, and it has
taken its toll,'' one of her attorneys, Mitchell McEntire, said
last week. ``But she has a spirit about her that remains very
strong.
   ``Her innocence has given her the strength to overcome it all.''
   While prosecutors declined to discuss the case, McEntire said he
expects the trial to last from six to eight weeks, including jury
selection. He said dozens of witnesses will be called by both
sides.
   ``I think it will be difficult to pick a jury,'' he said, adding
that the judge denied a defense motion for a different location for
the trial because of extensive pretrial publicity.
   After Mrs. Moore was charged in the three poisonings, police
also investigated the deaths of several of her relatives and
friends.
   Medical examiners subsequently found abnormally high, but not
fatal, levels of arsenic in the bodies of her father, Parker Kiser
Sr., who died at age 62 in 1966 after suffering his eighth heart
attack, and Isla Taylor, Mrs. Moore's mother-in-law, who died in
1970 at 83.
   No charges were filed in those deaths.
   Last spring, there was a new spin in the case.
   A five-page, handwritten letter was delivered May 25 to Mrs.
Moore at the jail. The letter, dated May 19, was signed by Garvin
Thomas, 59, of Burlington, who had died of natural causes May 22.
It letter said Thomas was obsessed with Mrs. Moore and that he
confessed to the poisonings.
   Prosecutors have since claimed Mrs. Moore wrote the letter
herself. But defense lawyers claim they have evidence to prove that
Thomas wrote the letter shortly before he died.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0018 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 1317EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ABCApology     10-14 0238</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-ABC Apology,0278</SECOND>
<HEAD>ABC To Make Amends To Cleveland</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CLEVELAND (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   ABC television will try to soothe bruised
feelings in Cleveland stemming from a joke in a promotion for the
situation comedy ``Coach,'' the mayor's office says.
   Robert A. Iger, president of ABC Entertainment, promised to air
an apology the night of Oct. 22, when ABC broadcasts the Cleveland
Browns' home game against the Cincinnati Bengals, a statement by
Mayor Michael R. White's office said Saturday.
   When the Browns played in Denver against the Broncos on Oct. 8,
the network broadcast a brief promotion for ``Coach.''
   Actor Jerry Van Dyke, who plays an assistant college football
coach on the series, commented that even if the Browns beat Denver,
they would still lose ``because they have to go back to
Cleveland.''
   White sent a letter to ABC, calling the remark insensitive and
disrespectful to the city.
   ``Any comedian or comedy show that uses Cleveland as the punch
line for a joke has never visited our city and is relying on what
has been for years the crutch of feeble comedians,'' White said in
his letter to ABC.
   Iger's letter explained that Van Dyke's joke was done ``in
character'' and that no malice was intended. Iger noted that two
weeks earlier, during a Monday Night Football broadcast, Van Dyke
made the same comment about Buffalo, N.Y.
   ``We firmly believe this incident should be kept in the proper
perspective, and given the problems existing in the world today, we
urge you and the citizens of your fine city to take this in the
lighthearted spirit in which it was meant,'' Iger wrote.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0019 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 1328EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Soviet-Chernobyl 1stLd-Writethru a0657 10-14 0305</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Chernobyl, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0657,0337</SECOND>
<HEAD>New International Medical Service Planned For Chernobyl Victims</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 7th pvs, `The medical...' with 1 graf to CORRECT
operation mentioned to bone marrow transplants. Pickup 8th pvs,
`The countries...'</NOTE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The United States, Italy, Belgium and Spain have
agreed to help set up a medical center in the region hit hardest by
the 1986 Chernobyl nuclear accident, Tass reported Sunday.
   The center will be built in Gomel, in the region of the
Byelorussian republic hit by 70 percent of the radioactive fallout
from the power plant accident, the news agency reported.
   Officials hope to build similar centers in other regions as
well.
   Soviet media have said more than 2 million Byelorussians are
living on contaminated land. The Byelorussian legislature has
declared the republic a ``national ecological disaster zone'' and
has halted shipments of food and vehicles to other regions because
they are contaminated.
   Workers in Gomel have held protest strikes demanding more aid
and better handling of the cleanup.
   Many Chernobyl-area residents have complained of inadequate
medical care. Cases of anemia, leukemia and cancers have been
reported rising among people living on contaminated land. Many
residents still eat food from that land because alternatives are
not available.
   The medical center will allow physicians to give residents
``continuous medical observation and ... highly skilled medical aid
on an international level,'' Tass reported. Complex operations will
be performed at the center, including bone marrow transplants, it
said.
   The countries will sign a final agreement on the center ``soon''
and construction should be completed in 1992, Tass said. It said
the Soviet Union will contribute $50,000 to the project, but did
not say what the other countries would contribute and gave no other
details about the agreement.
   Official reports say 31 people were killed in the April 26, 1986
accident at the nuclear power plant in the Urkaine, but others say
the number is much higher. Tass gave no new details about the
number of victims.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0020 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 1332EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brite-UnderwearFestiv     10-14 0236</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brite-Underwear Festival,0270</SECOND>
<HEAD>Townsfolk Strut Their Unmentionables in Annual Underwear Fest</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PIQUA, Ohio (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Wearing underwear - and nothing else - in
public is becoming a proud tradition in this western Ohio town's
annual ``Made in Piqua'' parade.
   This weekend's two-day Great Outdoor Underwear Festival was the
community's third.
   Patricia Cunningham Flesh, grand marshal of Sunday's festival
parade, said underwear has been good to her family and the
community. She is the widow of Alfred Flesh, whose father, Leo,
founded the Atlas Underwear Co.
   Mrs. Flesh, 83, considers it a duty to her community and the
family name to take part in the parade.
   ``Where else would you put underwear but on flesh?'' she said.
   The hour-long parade each year includes about 100 units - at
least one of which touts the virtues of underwear.
   Organizers cautioned that the parade is a family affair. Risque
lingerie is not welcome.
   ``It gets bigger and better each year. And it's an idea crazy
enough to work,'' said Doug Stilwell, a downtown merchant and
president of the Piqua Downtown Association.
   Items and antiques relating to Piqua's industrial past - which
includes having been home to 14 underwear makers since 1886 - were
on display at the Piqua Historical Museum.
   ``This was once quite an industrial town, and it's nice for the
townfolk of Piqua to get together and see what Piqua is about, how
interesting it is,'' said Carolyn Sullivan of the Half-Way There
Antiques shop. ``And te festival is just fun.
   ``I don't know if it's important, but it's fun.'
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0021 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 1359EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-US-GulfCoalition 1stLd-Writethru   10-14 0810</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-US-Gulf Coalition, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0660,900</SECOND>
<HEAD>Can the Fragile Group of Anti-Iraq Nations Stand Up for Long?</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: INSERTS 3 grafs after 7th graf pvs `It's terribly ...' to
UPDATE with Sununu comment on possible additional U.N. sanctions
against Iraq. INSERTS 2 grafs after 11th graf pvs `I don't ...' to
UPDATE with comment from Quayle. CORRECTS style to U.N., sted UN,
throughout. Edits throughout to tighten</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By RUTH SINAI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two months after the United States recruited
some unlikely partners to stand against Iraq, experts are asking
whether the group can withstand the diverse views of its members.
   The clash between the United States and its allies over a United
Nations' resolution condemning Israel and Friday's assassination of
an Egyptian leader highlight the possible risks to the
international coalition.
   From its largest shareholders, the United States and Britain, to
its smallest participants, Norway and Denmark, the anti-Iraq
grouping has achieved an unparalleled degree of unanimity.
   Its stated goal, in defense of which members have deployed
military forces and stopped trade with Iraq, is to oust President
Saddam Hussein from Kuwait and stop him from attacking other
oil-rich neighbors.
   The first major test of the cohesion came last week when Yemen,
an Iraqi ally, introduced a resolution condemning Israel for
killing 19 Palestinians after Jewish worshipers were attacked in
Jerusalem.
   In an attempt to placate its Arab coalition allies, the United
States broke with precedent and agreed to condemn Israel. But it
also wanted the U.N. resolution to criticize the Palestinian
violence, and rejected language calling for U.N. measures to
protect Palestinians under Israeli occupation.
   That put President Bush at odds with Egypt, Syria and other Arab
members of the anti-Iraq coalition, as well as with his European
partners, including France.
   ``It's terribly important for Bush to succeed on this if he's
going to retain credibility as the head of the coalition,'' said
Robert Hunter, a former presidential aide who's now an analyst at
the private Center for Strategic and International Studies.
   White House Chief of Staff John Sununu said Sunday that there
had been discussions about seeking further U.N. sanctions against
Iraq.
   ``There are some concerns ... about the terrible things that
have been done in Kuwait - the dismantling of a population, the
atrocities that have taken place there,'' Sununu said on NBC's
``Meet the Press.''
   Bush, he said, ``feels strongly that (Iraq) ought to receive
international condemnation'' on those matters.
   Saddam has from the start tried to drive a wedge between the
United States and the Arabs by portraying himself as the protector
of Palestinians and other downtrodden Arabs in a class struggle
against wealthy Americans and their ``expansionist'' ally, Israel.
   He has hit a responsive chord among Egyptians, Syrians and other
Arabs, splitting them from their governments, which are lined up
against him in the sands of Saudi Arabia. Thus, the U.S. refusal to
strongly condemn Israel has embarrassed those Arab leaders who are
called upon to defend their positions at home.
   ``I don't think the coalition can withstand this sort of double
standard by the United States,'' said Rashid Khalidi, associate
director of the Center for Middle East Studies at the University of
Chicago. ``It's a weak link.''
   But Vice President Dan Quayle said Sunday that there was no
connection between the Palestinian question and Saddam.
   ``The problem in the Middle East is not Israel,'' Quayle said on
CBS' ``Face the Nation.'' ``We still have a special relationship
with Israel; we always will. The problem is Saddam Hussein.''
   The resolve of the Arab leaders could also be threatened by more
concrete forms of Iraqi intimidation.
   On Friday, gunmen killed Egypt's parliament speaker and four
security men outside a luxury Cairo hotel. The shootings came days
after the government warned that terrorists might punish Egypt for
opposing Iraq.
   There was no claim of responsibility in the slayings.
   Experts predicted the resolve of Egypt and other Arab nations
that have traditionally struck a united front against the West no
matter what disagreements they had could be systematically weakened
if Iraqi proxies start a campaign of terror.
   Other experts believe that time and an erosion of domestic
support are the greatest enemies.
   ``As time goes on, each party discovers that its own interests
aren't necessarily compatible with those of the others,'' said
Judith Kipper, a scholar at the Brookings Institution, a
Washington-based research group.
   If the confrontation with Saddam drags on without resolution,
Americans might start demanding that President Bush bring home the
165,000 troops he has sent to the region, 31 of whom have been
killed in accidents.
   Japan, which has contributed funds to the coalition, also has
problems at home.
   The government, under pressure from Washington to increase its
role in the gulf, has proposed sending troops to the region. But
the legislation faces an uncertain future in parliament because
lawmakers say an overseas force violates Japan's constitution.
   Another scenario for trouble envisions Iraq trying to split the
coalition by agreeing to negotiate on formulas that fall short of
the U.S. demand for an unconditional withdrawal from Kuwait.
   Peace feelers from U.S. allies France and the Soviet Union have
fizzled, but Jordan and Yemen are putting forth various proposals
for resolving the crisis without war.
   ``If Saddam made a genuine offer to negotiate, or began
withdrawing his forces, it is likely that some European and Arab
allies would press for face-saving concessions to Saddam,'' said
Marvin Feuerwerger, a fellow at the Washington Institute for Near
East Studies.
   Negotiations could drag out, allowing Saddam to strengthen his
hold on Kuwait and to ``exploit differences in the international
coalition and within the United States,'' Feuerwerger said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0022 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 1402EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People     10-14 0536</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People,0654</SECOND>
<HEAD>People in the News</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY44</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SEATTLE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Allen Ginsberg, the Beat Generation
poet-activist, visited with about a dozen people camping at a city
park to protest U.S. military involvement in the Middle East.
   Ginsberg led the group in a minute-long meditative chant Friday
evening. He said meditation or ``centering'' helps one deal with
the anxiety of crisis and conflict.
   The protesters have camped since Aug. 26 at Gas Works Park,
renaming it Peace Works Park. Ginsberg, who teaches in Boulder,
Colo., heard about the vigil at a Seattle poetry reading.
   ``Such a vigil as this depends, for its long-range success, on
being user-friendly and friendly to the outside world,'' he said.
``But how do you cultivate that friendliness and maintain a lonely
vigil?''
   Vigil organizers have said they will stay at the park until the
departure from the Middle East of U.S. troops deployed in the Iraqi
crisis.
   ---
   COSTA MESA, Calif. (AP) - The tale would have been perfect if
she had kissed Kermit the Frog, but it was Mickey Mouse who
welcomed Princess Alexandra to a storybook day.
   The first cousin of Queen Elizabeth II on Saturday opened the
Festival of Britain, two weeks of cultural exchange in Orange
County.
   The princess reviewed processions of Rolls-Royces and bagpipers
in kilts, then visited food booths selling British delicacies from
the curries learned in the colonies to the good old fish and chips
of home.
   Actress Julie Andrews was on hand to kick off nine days of
screenings of films for which British actors were nominated or
received Academy Awards. She was hostess at a ``Mary Poppins tea
party'' before a screening of the film that won her an Oscar for
best actress in 1964.
   ---
   LOS ANGELES (AP) - A sequel to ``The Terminator'' will see the
return of Arnold Schwarzenegger in his role as a murderous cyborg
and of ``Beauty and the Beast'' TV star Linda Hamilton as a woman
out to save the future.
   ``Terminator 2: Judgment Day'' began production last week and is
scheduled for release in summer 1991. It depicts a nuclear
holocaust on Aug. 29, 1997, in which 3 billion humans perish.
   Miss Hamilton, repeating her role as Sarah Connor from the 1984
``Terminator,'' and other humans will have to face a nightmare war
against machines.
   Schwarzenegger returns as an unstoppable cyborg from the future
sent to kill Connor's son, John, destined to lead the human
resistance against the machines.
   Director James Cameron, who directed and co-wrote ``The
Terminator,'' will film ``Terminator 2'' for Carolco Pictures.
   ---
   BUTTE, Mont. (AP) - A judge says he'll write to Sports
Illustrated to clarify what he meant when he barred Evel Knievel
from testifying as an expert witness in a lawsuit over a motorcycle
crash.
   The former motorcycle stuntman, battered survivor of innumerable
motorcycle crashes, is less than happy about newspaper headlines
around the country with some variation of ``Evel No Expert.''
   Sports Illustrated noted the ruling briefly under the headline,
``We're Not Making This Up.'' Knievel was not amused.
   Attorneys wanted Knievel, 52, to testify on behalf of a friend,
J. Robert Riley, who was paralyzed after a 1980 motorcycle
accident. Riley sued the American Honda Motor Co., claiming
defective design of a motorcycle caused his accident.
   In court, Riley's lawyer asked Knievel his opinion about the
cause of Riley's accident, rather than asking him to testify about
motorcycle design.
   Honda's attorney objected and State District Judge Ted Mizner
sustained the objection, saying Riley's attorneys had not shown
that Knievel's knowledge of motorcycles qualified him as an
``accident reconstruction'' expert.
   The plaintiffs withdrew Knievel as a witness.
   The jury eventually ruled for Honda, and Mizner said Thursday he
plans to write a humorous letter to Sports Illustrated to clarify
his ruling.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0023 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 1408EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Red-HotBand     10-14 0285</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Red-Hot Band,0329</SECOND>
<HEAD>Grand Junction Band Cancels March Across Burning Coals</HEAD>
<DATELINE>GRAND JUNCTION, Colo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The marching band at Grand Junction
Central High School has gotten cold feet over doffing their
footwear and hot-footing it across a bed of burning coals this
month.
   Band members had planned to attend a motivational seminar called
``The Firewalk Experience.'' It concludes with a barefoot walk
across burning coals reputed to be 1,200 degrees.
   Fire-walking counselor Michael Douglas said the feat would be
painless and will show people that ``they can shatter self-imposed
limitations.''
   ``It motivates people to reach their peak performance,'' said
Douglas, who has used the technique in his work as a drug and
alcohol counselor.
   However, parents got concerned over safety and liability, and
band leader Gary Ambrosier said Central High School principal Bill
Lange decided if a student got hurt, the school could get in real
trouble.
   ``The last thing I want is a lawsuit brought against me and the
school,'' he said.
   Ambrosier said he had hoped the experience would improve the
band members' marching and music, and also their grades and their
self-confidence.
   Ambrosier came up with the idea after seeing a video of the Mesa
State College football tam and coaching staff performing a similar
feat last week after listening to Douglas' two-hour presentation.
   ``If those clunkheads can go across I can, too,'' Ambrosier
said.
   John Taylor, a University of Colorado physics professor known as
``Mr. Wizard'' for his ``Physics for Fun'' television show, has
walked on red-hot coals numerous times.
   ``I think the main point is that these coals are poor conductors
of heat. As you stand on them briefly, there isn't enough time for
the heat to transfer into your feet,'' said Taylor.
   He said the key is to walk deliberately and not dawdle. ``You
don't have to run, but I've never heard of anyone standing on the
coals,'' Taylor said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0024 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 1420EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Afghanistan     10-14 0296</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Afghanistan,0318</SECOND>
<HEAD>Guerrillas Claim Outposts Captured, Hundreds Dead</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PESHAWAR, Pakistan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Moslem guerrillas claimed on Sunday
they had captured strategic security outposts and killed more than
200 Afghan troops in the latest attempt to capture the capital,
Kabul.
   The Afghan government, in a broadcast on state radio, said its
soldiers killed 177 guerrillas trying to overrun the city and
destroyed a huge cache of weapons and ammunition.
   Claims by both the guerrillas and the Kabul government are often
exaggerated and impossible to verify independently.
   Midia, the news agency of the guerrillas' government-in-exile in
Pakistan, said guerrilla fighters had captured 16 outposts in
intense fighting south and east of Kabul and chipped away at the
security belt surrounding the city.
   The agency said 16 guerrillas were killed in the latest battle
to unseat the Soviet-backed government of Afghanistan.
   But official Kabul Radio, monitored in the Pakistani capital of
Islamabad, said the guerrillas had suffered heavily losses in the
two-pronged attack.
   The radio said sporadic fighting, including hand-to-hand combat,
continued in several places near the city, but that the worst
fighting was over.
   Fighting between the resistance and government troops usually
intensifies from late September to early November, before winter
storms blanket the mountains that ring the capital.
   Diplomatic and guerrilla sources said fundamentalist guerrillas
stepped up their attacks in early October and were preparing to
launch a major offensive on the heavily fortified capital.
   More moderate guerrilla commanders have opposed the plan and
were drawing up a strategy to counter the fundamentalists.
   The guerrillas, financed by the United States, Saudi Arabia and
other Arab states, have been fighting for more than 12 years to
topple the Communist government that seized power in an April 1978
coup.
   Soviet troops intervened in December 1979 to back the Kabul
government and withdrew in February 1989 under a U.N.-mediated
agreement.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0025 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 1434EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ArchaeologyArgument     10-14 0640</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Archaeology Argument,0825</SECOND>
<HEAD>Proposed Excavation of 11,000-Year-Old Site Sparks Controversy</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By NICHOLAS K. GERANIOS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>EAST WENATCHEE, Wash. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A scientist planning to dig up a
collection of ancient spear points says archaeology must be served,
but one critic dismisses the effort as a treasure hunt, and Indians
say it may disturb a burial ground.
   At the center of the controversy is a cache of 11,000-year-old
stone spear points and other tools that may have belonged to people
who crossed the land bridge from Asia to North America at the end
of the last ice age.
   The excavation is to take place starting next week under the
direction of Michael Gramly of the Museum of Science in Buffalo,
N.Y.
   Local Indians fear that graves will be disturbed. And Washington
State University archaeologist Peter Mehringer charges that Gramly
is rushing into the dig needlessly.
   Mehringer was especially critical of Gramly's tentative proposal
to place artifacts from the site on display in museums across the
country.
   ``A traveling roadshow is no excuse for an awful desecration,''
said Mehringer, who headed a preliminary dig at the site in 1988.
``It's not archaeology. It's a treasure hunt.''
   Members of the Colville Confederated Indian Tribes say their
concerns have been ignored. They are planning a sit-in when the
month-long excavation begins next Sunday or Monday.
   ``They are digging up the remains of some of our ancestors,''
said Matthew Dick Jr., cultural resources director for the tribe.
   Mehringer agreed the area may be a burial site. But Gramly said
there is no evidence of human remains, and that he has a state
permit to dig. He said the museum also intends to return whatever
is found, once it has been studied and displayed.
   ``Frankly, what I see here is we are looking at the future of
North American archaeology,'' Gramly said. ``If I can't explore an
archaeological site and make a decision on what is there, we will
have no archaeology in this country.''
   If human remains were found, scientists would want to compare
them with living people to see if there was a relationship with a
specific group such as an Indian tribe, Gramly said.
   The site was unearthed in Ma 1987 by two employees installing
water sprinklers at an apple orchard in this small central
Washington city.
   The orchard and the artifacts are owned by Mack Richey, a Renton
doctor. Richey did not return a telephone call seeking comment on
why he prefers to have Gramly excavate the site.
   Mehringer's preliminary excavation in 1988 revealed a cache of
distinctive fluted stone points, some up to 9 inches long. Also
found were four tools made from the bones of extinct animals.
   The items were taken to the Buffalo museum, and huge concrete
slabs were placed over the site to protect the remaining artifacts.
   The stone points, known as Clovis points, were used during a
500-year period ending about 11,000 years ago.
   Clovis points are named for a site near Clovis, N.M., where they
were first found in the 1930s. The base of each point was notched
or grooved to make it easier to fasten to a spear shaft.
   Other Clovis sites that have been uncovered were heavily damaged
by the time they were found, but this one was intact.
   The items found at this site may have been set in their present
positions by some of the earliest dwellers of North America,
Mehringer said. Scientists want to learn the signficance of the
placement.
   Jake Thomas, the state historic preservation officer who issued
Gramly his permit, said there were no signs of human remains at the
site. Because the site is privately owned and because Gramly is a
qualified scientist, the state had little choice but to issue a
permit, Thomas said.
   Mehringer suggested a one-year delay until all the issues are
resolved.
   ``There is no reason to dig the site,'' he said. ``It's not
threatened.''
   But Gramly said the site could be damaged by looters and farming
activity.
   He added that Richey, who owns the land, has indicated he wants
the artifacts to eventually go to a public institution in the state
of Washington.
   George Frison of the University of Wyoming, a highly-regarded
Clovis archaeologist, knows both men and considers them both good
scientists, but says he's heard too many stories about the
controversy to know what to believe.
   He said he does not hold it against Gramly that he has sold
artifacts - something Gramly says he has never done for personal
profit.
   ``He's in the museum business, and museums buy and sell
artifacts all the time,'' Frison said. He said his only problem
with Gramly is that he doesn't understand why he's in such a hurry
to excavate the East Wenatchee site.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0026 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 1454EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p AM-Candidate`Papered'     10-14 0240</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Candidate `Papered',0279</SECOND>
<HEAD>Black Mayoral Candidate Thinks `TP' Vandalism May Be Racially
Motivated</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SHREVEPORT, La. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The first black ever to make a runoff for
mayor in Shreveport says he thinks racial hatred may have been the
motive of whomever festooned his front yard with toilet paper.
   ``This makes me more determined to be mayor of this town,'' said
C.O. Simpkins, looking at the yards of toilet paper draped through
trees and bushes Saturday.
   ``I think that this speaks for just a small number of people in
Shreveport,'' said Simpkins, a Democrat. ``In my talking to people,
especially white people, I feel that they would be appalled by
this.''
   Simpkins said anonymous callers have threatened to kill him or
his wife, Elaine, unless he dropped out of the race for mayor. Some
have identified themselves as Ku Klux Klan members, he said.
   An anonymous woman caller woke the couple Saturday, telling them
to look at their yard, then called again a few momemts later,
spewing obscenities, said Mrs. Simpkins, who has fielded most of
the threatening calls.
   Simpkins, a dentist, led the civil rights movement in Shreveport
in the 1950s and early 1960s.
   He led the Oct. 6 primary, in which all candidates competed
regardless of party, with 32 percent of the vote, and faces
Republican City Council member Hazel Beard in the Nov. 6 runoff.
   Beard said she was worried the incident would foment racial
tension in the city. Her family also has received threatening phone
calls and letters during the campaign, she said, adding, ``It's no
secret that I've long ago disavowed hatred in any form.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0027 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 1501EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-FugitiveArrested     10-14 0228</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Fugitive Arrested,0250</SECOND>
<HEAD>Man Wanted for 1985 Wisconsin Murders Arrested in Florida</HEAD>
<DATELINE>RAIFORD, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A suspect in the 1985 slayings of a
Wisconsin couple lived quietly under his dead brother's name until
he was unmasked by a television show, authorities said.
   Charles Anthony Hoffman, 37, refused to waive extradition and
return voluntarily to Wisconsin during an arraignment Saturday.
Union County Judge David Reiman ordered him held on $500,000 bond
and appointed a public defender to handle his case.
   Sheriff's Lt. Larry Cochran said Hoffman is wanted by the FBI
and Wisconsin authorities in connection with the June 1985
shootings of Sherrie Piater, 21, of Sussex, Wis., and Michael A.
Heier, 22, of Medford, Wis. Their bodies were found in the
Chequamegon National Forest in northern Wisconsin.
   Hoffman was arrested Friday after Union County sheriff's
officials said several people saw him profiled on the ``America's
Most Wanted'' television show and contacted them.
   ``We arrested him without incident,'' Cochran said. ``We knocked
on his door and asked him to come outside and we surprised him.''
   Authorities said Hoffman lived quietly in the area under the
name of his late brother, Joseph Paul Hoffman, for at least 18
months.
   During that time, police said, he worked as a supervisor at
several restaurants in nearby Gainesville and married a
schoolteacher.
   Hoffman's wife, Jan, was unaware he was a fugitive and was ``in
a state of traumatized shock'' following his arrest, Cochran said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0028 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 1502EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-AlaskaOilRevenue     10-14 0236</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Alaska Oil Revenue,0258</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rising Oil Prices Coudd Double Alaska's 1990 Revenues</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ANCHORAGE, Alaska (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The increase in world oil prices could
nearly double Alaska's annual revenue this fiscal year, state
officials say.
   That estimate is the most optimistic of the oil price forecasts
state Department of Revenue officials came up with during their
semiannual oil price review last week.
   Should the projection come true, the state's fiscal 1991 revenue
could nearly double original estimates and hit $4.5 billion by June
30, officials said Friday. That rosy picture, however, is based on
the darkest scenario for the Middle East - a major war.
   Prices have fluctuated since Iraq's Aug. 2 invasion of Kuwait
but are still nearly double July prices. Alaska North Slope crude
closed at $35.32 per barrel on the U.S. Gulf Coast spot market
Friday.
   About 85 percent of Alaska's revenue comes from oil taxes and
royalties.
   Even the most pessimistic projection of $2.6 billion exceeds
estimates previously used to gauge the state's budget.
   Gov. Steve Cowper relied on a $2.1 billion estimate in July when
he culled $325 million from the state's $2.9 billion budget. The
projection he used is $500 million shy of most recent projections.
   While revenue officials haven't finalized per-barrel prices in
their new estimates, they expect to come up with projections based
on $20-per-barrel to $35-per-barrel oil prices, said Chuck Logsdon,
the department's chief petroleum economist.
   ``What's bad news for the rest of the country is good news for
Alaskans,'' Logsdon said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0029 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 1503EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Students-Vaccinations     10-14 0478</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Students-Vaccinations,0537</SECOND>
<HEAD>Medical Students Often Unprotected Against Preventable Diseases</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: For release 6:30 p.m. EDT</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By A.J. HOSTETLER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PHILADELPHIA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   One of every four medical schools does not
require students to be immunized, contributing to outbreaks of
rubella and measles in hospitals and schools, according to a newly
reported survey.
   Not one medical school surveyed followed all federal vaccination
recommendations against preventable, infectious diseases,
researchers reported in an article in Monday's Annals of Internal
Medicine.
   The findings come as public health officials worry about a major
outbreak of more than 19,000 measles cases in this country in the
first 35 weeks of this year. The majority of the cases were
attributed to failure to vaccinate.
   Researchers from the Mayo Clinic in Rochester, Minn., and the
Veterans Affairs Medical Center in Minneapolis surveyed 144 medical
schools in the United States and Canada; 115 responded. Their
report did not name any participating schools.
   The failure to require immunization has left students and
patients unprotected against preventable diseases, the researchers
said.
   ``When a medical student or doctor gets rubella, and sees a
pregnant woman, or child, or elderly patient, the outcome could be
deadly,'' warned the study's lead author, Dr. Gregory Poland of the
Mayo Clinic.
   The survey, completed in 1988, found that 28 percent of the
schools responding to the survey had no immunization requirements
of entering medical students, which number about 15,000 a year.
   Thirty-one percent of the schools had no rubella immunity
requirement, 40 percent lacked a measles immunity requirement and
44 percent did not require proof of polio vaccination.
   The researchers noted that 97 percent of all the schools
required at least one immunization before students began their
clerkships, a training period in which they help treat patients.
   Poland said he was shocked at the report's findings, calling
them ``unacceptable.''
   ``We're exposed to so much more than the general population,''
he said, adding that previous studies have found that medical
students in clerkships or residency are 13 times more likely to
contract measles than the public.
   Poland said hospitals and medical schools were ``lulled into
thinking these diseases weren't a problem anymore,'' because they
saw fewer cases each year. That lessened the perceived need for
vaccinations, he said.
   ``But these viruses are there all the time, waiting to come
back,'' he said.
   Since the survey was completed in 1988, Poland pointed out, the
country has seen an outbreak of measles and mumps, with cases
nearing pre-vaccination levels.
   Poland said the study was sparked by the researchers' earlier
findings, published in January, that identified medical students as
the source of 13 percent of reported measles and rubella outbreaks
from 1980-88.
   Poland said not one of the schools surveyed followed all the CDC
recommendations for vaccinations against measles, rubella, mumps,
tetanus-diphtheria, hepatitis B and polio. The CDC also urges
medical students to receive annual flu shots.
   Even when state laws required vaccinations, not all schools
complied, he said.
   The authors urged schools to establishimmunization policies
that include subsidized or free vaccines, methods for monitoring
student compliance, and required proof of vaccination from a
physician.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0030 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 1511EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Boston-Police     10-14 0630</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Boston-Police,0770</SECOND>
<HEAD>Allegations of Police Misconduct Shadow Murder Trial</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MICHELLE LOCKE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>GREENFIELD, Mass. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The trial of a Jamaican immigrant on
charges he killed a Boston policeman during a drug raid has focused
on allegations that the slain officer's partners lied to get the
warrant that set up the raid.
   The case has prompted questions about the validity of other
warrants obtained by the drug squad and the general integrity of
police investigations.
   The allegations against the officers also have been raised by
some who question the quality of recent Boston murder
investigations, including the Charles Stuart murder case.
   Police now believe Stuart killed his pregnant wife and then
wounded himself in October 1989, then later committed suicide when
the story began unraveling. But they initially accepted Stuart's
account that he and his wife were attacked by a black man and named
a man as a suspect.
   Arguments and testimony in the murder trial of Albert Lewin
began in this northwestern Massachusetts city Oct. 4, after the
case was moved from Boston because of extensive media coverage.
   The case against Lewin, 34, stems from a drug raid Feb. 17,
1988, when Detective Sherman Griffiths was killed by shots fired
through an apartment door.
   Suffolk County prosecutors claim Lewin, later found sitting in
the living room of another apartment, was the unseen gunman.
   Three other people in the apartment where he was arrested have
testified against Lewin, and in exchange, prosecutors have dropped
charges pending against them.
   Police have admitted making up an informant whose information
supposedly was the basis of the search warrant used for the drug
raid. And Lewin doesn't match the description of the drug dealer
described in the warrant.
   The case has prompted questions about the validity of other
warrants obtained by the drug squad and the general integrity of
police investigations.
   ``The problem is that the law presumes that police officers are
going to tell the truth. The conditions of the job create pressures
to not tell the truth and offers temptations to get away with it,''
said David Rossman, director of Boston University's Criminal
Clinical Project.
   ``It brings up the whole issue of the enormous discretion that
police and prosecutors have in the criminal justice system,'' said
Martin Rosenthal, managing attorney for Harvard Law School's
Criminal Justice Project.
   Following the admission that police officers had lied, a
commission was appointed to investigate the department. Changes
implemented included tightening up monitoring and a special class
on constitutional rights, said spokeswoman Jill Reilly.
   Defense attorney Max Stern maintains Lewin is the victim of a
``desperate effort'' by police to cover up a botched investigation.
   The state's case rests in part on the testimony of the three
people, all related, in the apartment where Lewin was found. They
identify Lewin as the suspected drug dealer sought in the raid.
   One of the three was initially charged with murder in Griffiths'
death.
   Controversy also developed over a fingerprint on the ammunition
clip of the murder weapon. Originally deemed useless by Boston
police, it was re-examined by the FBI this summer, using techniques
unavailable in 1988, and was identified as Lewin's.
   The print was photographed and then destroyed in a subsequent
chemical test. The defense challenged use of the print as evidence,
because it couldn't be re-examined, but a judge ruled the
photograph could be used.
   Detective Carlos A. Luna and Sgt. Hugo R. Amate are awaiting
trial on charges they lied under oath about an informant and filed
false police reports in a cover-up attempt.
   The affidavit filed by detectives to obtain the search warrant
quoted an informant named John who said a 5-foot, 6-inch Hispanic
drug dealer was dealing cocaine from the apartment where Griffiths
was killed. Lewin is 6-foot-2 and Jamaican.
   The informant was never produced and Luna is accused of
attempting to concoct a story that the man died or couldn't be
found. Amate is charged with being an accessory after the fact in
the alleged perjury.
   The case against Lewin was thrown out by a Superior Court judge,
but it was later reinstated by the Supreme Judicial Court,
Massachusetts' highest court.
   The justices called police conduct in the case ``contemptible
and disgusting,'' but added:
   ``In order to express its outrage at the reprehensible police
conduct in this case, society need not punish itself by freeing a
man who may be guilty of murder in the first degree and other
serious crimes.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0031 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 1522EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-StolenExplosives     10-14 0495</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Stolen Explosives,0588</SECOND>
<HEAD>Report: Stolen Military Weapons Show Up Nationwide</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HARRISBURG, Pa. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Army has hushed up the theft of
military guns, explosives and even anti-tank rockets that have been
found in the hands of criminals around the country, a newspaper
reported Sunday.
   Since 1984, stolen military weapons worth tens of millions of
dollars have been used in 349 bombings that killing 13 people,
injuring 165 and causing $1.6 million in damage, the Sunday
Patriot-News reported. The Harrisburg newspaper cited government
documents obtained under the Freedom of Information Act and
interviews with officials.
   Military guns, grenades, mines, plastic explosives and rockets
have been sold to drug dealers, hate groups, motorcycle gangs, hit
men and mercenaries, the newspaper reported. Other weapons have
been stopped by Customs agents as they were being smuggled out of
the country.
   Anti-tank rockets - capable of piercing armor and blowing up
tanks, buildings, police cruisers, helicopters and boats - have
been discovered in Philadelphia, New York City and the Detroit
suburbs, the paper said. Some were in the hands of drug dealers.
   In some cases, the thieves are soldiers, the newspaper reported.
The stolen goods can be sold on the international black market and
wind up in the hands of terrorists abroad.
   The Pentagon's latest report to Congress on theft of government
property doesn't mention of weapons and explosives, despite
instances across the country of such thefts, the Patriot-News
reported.
   Army officials agreed only last month to abide by a 1987 law
that mandates they report thefts of weaponry to the U.S. Bureau of
Alcohol, Tobacco and Firearms within 72 hours, the paper said.
   ``This has been a long-term problem with the military,'' said
Dick Helmer, a deputy associate director for national security and
international affairs at the General Accounting Office, the
accounting arm of Congress. ``We are very fortunate there has not
been a major catastrophe or a lot of deaths.''
   Among the munitions reportedly recovered have been more than 85
rockets, 400 grenades, a dozen lad mines, anti-aircraft shells,
howitzer rounds, cluster bombs, 25-pound fragmentation bombs, 200
pounds of plastic explosives, 45 pounds of military TNT and 18,000
bullets.
   The Army doesn't say the recovered items are stolen. Reports say
they come from ``unexplained origins,'' although many have serial
numbers that can be traced to any of a variety of bases, the paper
said.
   The newspaper said it obtained documents that showed:
   -The Pentagon doesn't know how many weapons or explosives have
been stolen, or what the losses cost the taxpayer.
   -In the 1980s, government agents recovered more than five tons
of stolen military TNT and C4 plastic explosives. A quarter-pound
of C4, which costs the Army $1.20, is enough to blow up an
airliner.
   -Customs agents confiscated $433 million in weapons and
explosives that were to be illegally shipped overseas from 1981
through March of this year.
   -Security is loose at many bases, especially where reservists
train. Officials are often unable to tell if explosives used in
training were actually detonated or pocketed for sale on the black
market.
   -Accounting and supply systems are in such disarray that the
Pentagon often doesn't know if something disappears from inventory
unless it somehow is found later.
   Profits are good on the black market. A grenade costs the Army
$7.43 but sells on the black market for $50, experts told the
paper. Anti-tank LAW rockets sell for more than $1,000 each on the
street.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0032 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 1524EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-GasDeaths     10-14 0250</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gas Deaths,0290</SECOND>
<HEAD>Three Die in Fume-Filled Apartment; Friend Suffers Fatal Heart
Attack</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HAMMOND, Ind. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The bodies of a man, a woman and her
17-year-old son were found in a fume-filled apartment, and a friend
who turned up at the scene collapsed and died, apparently of a
heart attack, police said Sunday.
   Police said they suspected that Douglas Willie Hemphill, 64, his
girlfriend, Bernice Johnson, 40, and her son, Trent, were overcome
by carbon monoxide leaking from a faulty furnace.
   A coroner refused to rule out foul play.
   Hemphill's son, Douglas, discovered the bodies Saturday
afternoon, said Sgt. John Pohl. He went there because other family
members hadn't seen or heard from them for several days, Pohl said.
   Richard Knight, 64, a friend of Hemphill's who showed at the
duplex apartment when emergency crews arrived, apparently suffered
a heart attack ouside on learning of the deaths, police said. He
died several hours later at St. Margaret Hospital.
   Coroner Daniel Thomas said he was performing autopsies on the
bodies but did not expect to determine the cause of death until
Monday.
   ``It certainly is suspicious,'' Thomas said. ``We were told they
did have some problems with the furnace about a week ago. There's
other circumstances that we can't reveal at this time.''
   Pohl said police had no immediate evidence to suggest foul play.
   Gas levels inside the house were so high that firefighters had
to ventilate the home before they could enter it, a fire department
spokesman said.
   The building's owner, Norman Karr, said he was unaware of any
problems with the gas furnace.
   The woman who lives in the other half of the duplex was unhurt.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0033 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 1531EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-Iran-Iraq     10-14 0263</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Iran-Iraq,0283</SECOND>
<HEAD>Former Gulf Foes Reopen Embassies</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf-US Coalition, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NICOSIA, Cyprus (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Iran and Iraq reopened embassies in each
other's capitals Sunday, resuming full diplomatic ties and ending a
decade of enmity, Iran's Islamic Republic News Agency reported.
   The exchange of diplomats came only two years after a
U.N.-brokered cease-fire halted hostilities in the eight-year
Iran-Iraq war.
   The Iraqi charge d'affaires took up his post Sunday and his
Iranian counterpart was to leave for Baghdad shortly, said IRNA,
monitored in Cyprus.
   Neither was named, but the Tehran Times quoted Iranian political
circles as saying the likely Iranian envoy would be Javad
Turkabadi, Iran's former charge d'affaires in Kuwait.
   Turkabadi now heads the Persian Gulf Affairs desk at the Iranian
Foreign Ministry.
   Iraqi President Saddam Hussein is believed to be seeking Iranian
assistance in circumventing the U.N. economic embargo imposed to
force him out of Kuwait, which he invaded Aug. 2. There have been
reports of food shipments crossing from Iran into Iraq along their
730-mile border.
   Tehran has officially condemned Saddam's invasion of Kuwait and
called for his withdrawal. But at the same time, Iran has condemned
the presence of Western forces in Saudi Arabia, home of Islam's
holiest shrines.
   The decision to re-establish full diplomatic ties came during a
September visit to Tehran by Iraqi Foreign Minister Tariq Aziz. The
opening of embassies coincided with the end of a four-day visit to
Tehran by an Iraqi Foreign Ministry undersecretary, Wisam
al-Zahawi.
   Diplomatic ties were never officially severed even though the
two nations were at war from 1980-88.
   The two nations closed their embassies in 1987 and their
diplomats returned home.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0034 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 1551EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Lebanon 1stLd-Writethru a0672 10-14 0684</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lebanon, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0672,0817</SECOND>
<HEAD>Diplomatic Quarrel Over Asylum For Aoun</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS thruout to UPDATE with justice minister saying they will
take Aoun if he tries to leave embassy. Moves up background on Aoun
and adds details. No pickup.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos BEI1-4,PAR1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RODEINA KENAAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BEIRUT, Lebanon (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Lebanon and France quarreled Sunday over
the fate of Gen. Michel Aoun, whose 11-month mutiny in the
Christian heartland was crushed by a Syrian-led military blitz.
   Aoun remained inside the French Embassy, where he fled during
Saturday's attack and was granted asylum.
   Lebanese officials were insisting the 55-year-old general remain
in the country for possible trial on charges including the alleged
theft of $75 million from the state treasury.
   ``We shall not violate international law and go get Aoun out of
the French Embassy,'' Justice Minister Edmond Rizk said in a
statement. ``But we shall exercise our judicial rights if the
embassy decides to take him out of Lebanon because he is wanted for
trial.''
   Staccato bursts of machine-gun fire echoed across the pine woods
surrounding the shell-shattered presidential palace in the
Christian suburb of Baabda. Helmeted Syrian troops searched the
hills for supporters of the defeated general.
   Aoun was forced into surrender Saturday after 11 months of
resisting the Syrian-backed government. His defeat moved Lebanon
closer to an end of its 15-year-old civil war.
   The Christian general had opposed the government's peace plan,
which gives the Moslem majority an equal share of power but gives
no timetable for withdrawing the 40,000 Syrian troops in the
country.
   After fighting battles with the Syrians, Moslems and a rival
Christian militia, Aoun's territory had been reduced to an
80-square-mile enclave north and east of Beirut.
   He escaped an assassination attempt Friday night and had pledged
to ``die fighting.'' But he fled his headquarters during the
onslaught by Syrian troops.
   The casualty toll from the eight-hour crackdown on Aoun's
enclave stood at 160 dead and 800 wounded, by police count.
   The casualties included 32 Syrian soldiers killed and 85
wounded. Their bodies were flown to Damascus by two Syrian army
helicopters, police said.
   Syrian and Lebanese troops set up checkpoints on roads leading
to the French Embassy in Beirut's Christian suburb of Hazmiyeh.
Embassy guards mined the walls.
   Syrian soldiers and troops of Hrawi's army besieged the embassy
Saturday night, hours after Aoun and three senior aides took refuge
there. The embassy compound also houses Ambassador Rene Ala's
residence.
   There were no soldiers in the embassy's immediate vicinity later
Sunday.
   A Lebanese neighbor of the compound, who identified himself only
by his first name, Antoine, said the soldiers ``left this
morning.''
   Antoine said Aoun arrived at the embassy entrance in an armored
personnel carrier early Saturday, 45 minutes after Syrian warplanes
and artillery started bombing the presidential palace.
   ``He was met at the entrance by (Ambasador) Ala. As they ran on
foot toward Ala's residence, shells started falling on the embassy
compound. They nearly got killed,'' Antoine said.
   The embassy's swimming pool was hit by shells, as was the main
lobby. A carpet of glass shards and debris blanketed the main
entrance.
   France, the traditional protector of Lebanon's Christians,
promptly granted Aoun asylum Saturday.
   Ala met with Hrawi in Moslem west Beirut on Sunday to try to
resolve the issue, presidential spokesman May Kahhaleh said. Ala
left after two hours without making a statement.
   ``France must pardon us for not swallowing its hasty decision to
grant asylum to Aoun,'' said Cabinet Minister Nabih Berri. ``He
should stand trial as a plain criminal, not a politician.''
   Christian warlord Samir Geagea, whose Lebanese Forces militia
fought a four-month power struggle with Aoun's men early this year,
also said the defeated general ``should be brought to justice and
tried as a criminal.''
   Aoun's fall tightened Syria's hold on Lebanon, which the Syrians
consider their strategic backyard. Syria, the main power broker in
Lebanon, sent its troops to Lebanon under a 1976 peacekeeping
mandate.
   Sources close to Hrawi said his next step would be to move to
the presidential palace. They said a new government would be formed
under Prime Minister Salim Hoss, a Sunni Moslem, to supervise the
unification of Beirut.
   The capital has been divided into Christian and Moslem sectors
since outbreak of the civil war in 1975.
   Aoun had tried to establish himself as the legitimate authority
in Lebanon since September 1988, when he was appointed caretaker
prime minister by President Amin Gemayel.
   Hrawi was elected president Nov. 24, 1989, with a mandate to
enforce the peace plan brokered by the Arab League.
   After his election, Hrawi promptly dismissed Aoun as army
commander and interim prime minister, but the general denounced
Hrawi as a ``Syrian puppet'' and refused to leave the presidential
palace.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0035 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 1552EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Soviet-Iraq     10-14 0485</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Iraq,0579</SECOND>
<HEAD>Soviet News Agency Says Saddam May Pull Out of Kuwait</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By THOMAS GINSBERG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Iraqi leader Saddam Hussein indicated to a
visiting Soviet official last week he might remove his troops from
Kuwait in return for some Kuwaiti territory along the Persian Gulf,
a Soviet news agency reported.
   The government-run Novosti Press Agency said the shift in Iraq's
position raised the Kremlin's hopes for a diplomatic solution to
the standoff. But an editor at the official Iraqi News Agency
denied Iraq had made any offer of a partial withdrawal.
   Novosti, in a dispatch published Sunday by the labor newspaper
Rabochaya Tribuna, said Saddam made the comments in talks with
Yevgeny Primakov, a top Kremlin aide whom President Mikhail
Gorbachev sent to Baghdad last week to discuss the gulf crisis.
   ``In talks with Saddam Hussein, not once did (Saddam) mention
the `historical rights' of Iraq to the territory of Kuwait,
amounting to a definite softening of the Iraqi president's
position,'' Novosti reported.
   ``From these remarks, it follows that Iraq might withdraw its
army from Kuwait, retaining for itself southern Rumaillah and the
islands Warba and Bubiyan, opening up exits to the sea,'' the news
agency said.
   Soviet presidential spokesman Vitaly Ignatenko had said last
week that Soviet officials were optimistic after the
Saddam-Primakov meetings, but gave no details.
   ``I can only tell you that we are today more able to look more
optimistically at the prospect of a political settlement in that
region,'' Ignatenko had said.
   But the Iraqi News Agency, in a dispatch Sunday, quoted an
unidentified editor as denying any concessions. The editor said the
reports were ``sheer lies and baseless, and those propagating them
were known and their objectives known too.''
   Historical claims to Kuwaiti territory have been among Saddam's
official justifications for Iraq's Aug. 2 invasion of the oil-rich
kingdom. He also claimed the Kuwait government was taking oil that
belonged to Baghdad, and that the rule of Kuwaiti's monarchy was
illegitimate.
   The islands of Bubiyan and Warba are off the Kuwaiti coast near
the border with Iraq. Rumaillah is one of Kuwait's major oil fields
along the Kuwaiti-Iraqi border near the coast.
   By acquiring the three additional sites, Saddam could vastly
expand his oil production capacity and open new ports. Iraq
currently has only a small coastline from which to export most of
its oil, its main source of revenue.
   A U.S.-led international economic embargo against Iraq, enforced
by a U.N.-sanctioned air and sea blockade, has cut off Iraq's major
oil markets.
   U.S. Defense Secretary Dick Cheney is visiting Moscow Wednesday,
and an official at the Pentagon said Cheney would ask for
intelligence on Iraq. The official complained Moscow had failed to
provide Washington with data on the Iraqi military, which the
Soviet Union has been arming for a decade.
   The Soviet Union has backed U.N. sanctions against Iraq and has
two ships in the gulf, but Gorbachev has declined to send in more,
saying the conflict should be settled peacefully.
   The weekly Moscow News on Sunday published an article by an
international security expert who called for the Soviet Union to
send a volunteer military contingent to the gulf.
   ``Such action could strengthen the army's prestige and its role
... as guarantor of stability, law and order,'' wrote Alexei
Arbatov of the Institute of World Economy and International
Relations.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0036 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 1558EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-NewHavenPolice     10-14 0636</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-New Haven Police,0775</SECOND>
<HEAD>For New Haven Police Chief, It's Not Business As Usual</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Retransmitting a0661 to fix slug.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By LARRY ROSENTHAL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW HAVEN, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Police Chief Nicholas Pastore is trading
in his force of drug-busting, doughnut-eating militiamen for what
he calls social engineers.
   The new chief has banned leather driving gloves on police
officers as too intimidating and has told the members of his force
to steer drug users to treatment programs instead of jails.
   He's also told his officers to knock off the frequent
coffee-and-doughnut runs during their breaks because it gives them
a bad image with the public.
   ``I want the police to be perceived as a helping-hand agency,''
said Pastore, who has been on the job for seven months.
   That perception can be bolstered if officers, among other
things, help drug users rather than just arrest them, the new chief
said.
   ``We've tried the tanks, the helicopters, the big guns for many
years. It doesn't work,'' Pastore, 52, said in a recent interview.
``I don't subscribe to the philosophy that the more arrests you
make, it's going to solve the crime problem.''
   Arrests in New Haven, a city of 125,000, dropped sharply when
Pastore discontinued sting operations to round up drug buyers. He
has also stopped dispatching teams of officers into high-crime
neighborhoods for round-the-clock arrests and disbanded the
department's canine unit.
   Instead, he ordered about 20 more officers to walk beats, placed
officers at high-visibility posts throughout downtown and made
extensive community outreach efforts to end what he calls the
``we-they mentality'' in drug-infested neighborhoods.
   He also walks the streets of crime-plagued neighborhoods
himself, frequently striking up conversations with known drug
dealers.
   ``When I'm seen in these neighborhoods, people realize this man
cares,'' he said.
   His actions have brought praise from various members of the
public and business community, but have put him at odds with the
police department's union.
   A group of downtown merchants recently presented Pastore with a
a plaque for his efforts to increase police visibility. But Sgt.
Louis G. Cavalier, the head of the police officers union,
complained that the stepped-up presence has merely provided the
community with a ``false sense of security.''
   Pastore has also won the confidence of at least one drug user's
mother, who called him recently to say she needed to talk to
someone she could trust.
   The chief believes marijuana use should be decriminalized, and
he said his efforts to encourage addicts to seek treatment reflects
his belief that the drug problem should be resolved by physicians,
not lawyers.
   Such views earned him a prominent profile in the August issue of
``High Times,'' a magazine devoted to marijuana smoking.
   Pastore said he didn't know the free-lance writer who spoke with
him was doing the interview for High Times. But he added that he
was accurately quoted and had no problems with the story.
   His comments in a newspaper interview that there would be fewer
coffee-and-doughnut runs now that he was police chief ruffled some
feathers in the department. Union officials accuse him of
frequently entering restaurants and asking officers what they are
doing.
   ``There is the sense that the chief is on their backs
constantly,'' Cavalier said.
   Pastore said he recalls only one such restaurant incident. He
added that his doughnut policy is not an attack on his officers'
work ethic but on the traditional concept of police work.
   ``Police work should not be just doing what the dispatcher says,
then in between going to Dunkin' Donuts,'' he said.
   He praises his officers, but dismisses the union's criticism.
   ``The union doesn't care about the public,'' he said. ``All they
care about is what's good for them. ``They have become a group of
militant mercenaries.''
   Pastore came into office with a mandate to shake up the
department and move to a concept of community-based policing, in
which officers are assigned to individual neighborhoods. Because of
a tight city budget, the new program has gotten off to a slow
start.
   First-term Mayor John Daniels, a friend since high school,
bypassed nearly 20 internal candidates in hiring Pastore, who had
spent 18 years with the department before retiring in 1981 because
of a congenital kidney defect. The ailment has since been
corrected.
   ``His style is perhaps a little different from your typical
police chief, but if it serves a successful effort, I'm all for
it,'' said Michael Dearington, the chief state prosecutor in New
Haven. ``Some innovation is due in the area of law enforcement.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0037 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 1612EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r e AM-Opera     10-14 0426</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Opera,0556</SECOND>
<HEAD>`Martha' Is Sung at NY City Opera</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: No PMs Planned</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By MARY CAMPBELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The New York City Opera performed ``Martha'' in
its first season in February 1944. On Saturday night, it performed
the Friedrich von Flotow opera for the first time since then, with
serious singing and charming decor.
   ``Martha'' is almost an operetta. When Plunkett, sung by Dean
Peterson, says early on that his brother Lionel, sung by Martin
Thompson, is a foster brother, it sounds like Gilbert and Sullivan.
Lionel is surely going to turn out to be noble.
   All four leading singers in the New York State Theater were
excellent. All sang as though in the most serious of operas, which
``Martha'' needs.
   The production maximizes charm and fun. The first performance of
``Martha'' was in Vienna in 1847. This one is set in the 1920s in
England and sung in English, with subtitles.
   In the first scene, chorus women are in attractive pastel
flapper dresses. Later, they wear them again, with different color
coordination.
   Comic cops enter, bumping into each other. Cars are used
cleverly but not too much. In the second scene, at a rural fair,
one tiny car careens along a background roller coaster. When the
two women are being rescued, car lights are seen approaching in the
distance and, later, going away, much faster.
   Sheryl Woods had a lovely tone and light, unforced coloratura as
Martha. Lucille Beer, as her servant, Nancy, has a Marilyn Horne
kind of mezzo-soprano voice, strong on its deep side.
   The music is pleasant. One problem is that the story doesn't,
today, seem very nice. Operas of villainous revenge somehow are
easier to take.
   Lady Harriet, maid of honor to the queen, is bored. So she
decides that she, her servant and her cousin, sung by Joseph McKee,
should go to a fair dressed as peasants. She calls herself Martha.
Plunkett and Lionel, farmers, offer to hire the two women as
servants for a year and they accept.
   There's a funny scene with a crank-turned washer and wringer
which the men show the ``servants'' how to operate. The two men
have fallen in love. Lionel asks Martha to sing to him and she
sweetly sings ``The Last Rose of Summer.'' She's in love, too, but
wouldn't consider somebody so far beneath her.
   That night, the women climb out a window into her cousin's car.
   When plot turns get Lionel's ring to the king, it's discovered
that he's really the Earl of Derby. Martha now tells him she loves
him. He says that she's just interested in the Earl of Derby.
Program notes say that ``having lost his reason, he rebuffs her.''
It sounds like he had a point.
   The two couples wind up together.
   The Metropolitan Opera has performed ``Martha'' since it moved
to Lincoln Center in 1966 but did not make of it such a jolly romp.
   John Lehmeyer directed and costumes were created from his
designs. John Michael Deegan, who did the warm, bright lighting,
and Sarah G. Conly designed sets. Mary Corsaro choreographed. All
were debuts with the company. Arthur Fagen conducted.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0038 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 1614EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Pakistan     10-14 0354</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Pakistan,0397</SECOND>
<HEAD>Court Upholds Dismissal Of Bhutto Government</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MAHMOOD ZAMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LAHORE, Pakistan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A court on Sunday upheld the dismissal
of Prime Minister Benazir Bhutto, ruling that corruption and
mismanagement had stalled her government after 20 months in office.
   The Lahore High Court's decision will likely be challenged in
the Supreme Court. In any case, national elections are set for Oct.
24, so a victory for either side would be merely a moral one.
   Four lawsuits filed by supporters of Ms. Bhutto's Pakistan
People's Party argued that President Ghulam Ishaq Khan had
overstepped his constitutional authority by abruptly dismissing Ms.
Bhutto's government Aug. 6.
   Khan fired Ms. Bhutto on charges of corruption, nepotism and
abuse of power and installed a military-backed caretaker
government. The former prime minister has denied the charges and
called her dismissal a political move.
   Meanwhile, a poll released Sunday showed Ms. Bhutto's opponents
would likely win the October elections, but that the ousted prime
minister would command a formidable political force after the
balloting.
   The poll by Gallup Pakistan indicated Ms. Bhutto and her
Pakistan People's Party would take 30 percent of the vote. The
largely right-wing coalition, the Islamic Democratic Alliance,
would win 40 to 45 percent, it said. The poll gave no margin of
error.
   The six-judge panel on Sunday rejected the contentions of the
People's Party and cited eight grounds for Ms. Bhutto's ouster and
the appointment of a caretaker government.
   ``We find that the president was justified in the opinion that
the government could not be carried on in accordance with the
constitution and an appeal to the electorate was necessary,'' the
court said in its ruling.
   Ms. Bhutto is being tried on the corruption and other charges by
special one-judge tribunals in Lahore and her hometown of Karachi.
   The high court noted that Ms. Bhutto's government had offered no
substantial legislation while in power, faile to resolve disputes
with the provincial governments and deprived them of vital revenue.
   It alleged Ms. Bhutto's government violated individual human
rights ``by tapping the telephones of highly respectable people,''
including supporters, and was discriminatory in civil service
appointments.
   The court accused Ms. Bhutto of publically ridiculing the Senate
and the judiciary and alleged she misused millions of dollars in
government funds to buy political favors.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0039 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 1625EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Poland     10-14 0485</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Poland,0548</SECOND>
<HEAD>Prime Minister Kicks Off Presidential Campaign</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN DANISZEWSKI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>KRAKOW, Poland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Prime Minister Tadeusz Mazowiecki began
his campaign for president Sunday, saying the nation must stick
with the government's economic policy and reject ``amateurish
experiments.''
   While not mentioning rival Lech Walesa by name, Mazowiecki
portrayed himself as the candidate of law, stability and pragmatic
change. He warned against demagoguery, unpredictability and ad hoc
solutions on the other side.
   Poles vote Nov. 25 to decide the successor to President Wojciech
Jaruzelski, who is stepping down 4{ years before the end of his
term.
   The nation's first popular presidential race in more than 50
years has split the Solidarity movement, pitting the publicity-shy
Mazowiecki against Walesa, 47, the Solidarity chairman and
Mazowiecki's former ally and political sponsor.
   Jaruzelski, the former Communist Party leader, asked Parliament
Sept. 19 to shorten his term because of increasing demands for him
to step down as an unwanted symbol of Poland's old order.
   Mazowiecki, the East bloc's first non-Communist prime minister,
proclaimed his candidacy Oct. 4. He spent Sunday in Krakow, a
center of his support about 150 miles south of Warsaw.
   
   Thousands chanted ``Mazowiecki! Mazowiecki!'' and surrounded the
prime minister as he walked through the city's huge Old Market and
laid a wreath in honor of Polish patriot Tadeusz Kosciuszko.
   In the day's keynote speech at the Krakow Philharmonic Hall,
Mazowiecki, 63, told 1,000 invited guests that the choice facing
voters was between himself and ``some demagogues'' who promise
``magical solutions'' to economic problems.
   ``Our policy is going through a steep and thorny path, but this
is the only possible way leading to improving the republic and
creating better, more decent conditions,'' he said of the country's
plans to move toard a more market-oriented system.
   The 10-month-old program is expected to raise the number of
unemployed to 1.3 million by the end of the year.
   ``We cannot go back. We cannot change the route halfway,''
Mazowiecki said.
   ``Our policy has got to be flexible, but expert and consistent.
We can no longer afford new amateurish experiments,'' he said.
   Walesa has criticized the government's economic reform timetable
as too slow.
   In a question-and-answer session after the speech, Mazowiecki
said he declared his candidacy after Walesa rejected a proposal for
a compromise third candidate.
   Mazowiecki also said he would not accept Walesa's
counterproposal to join forces behind a Walesa candidacy, with
Mazowiecki continuing as prime minister.
   Krakow, the medieval royal capital and home of the country's
most prestigious university, has long provided a base of political
support for Mazowiecki, whose campaign appeals to intellectuals and
modern-thinking business people.
   The editor of the influential Krakow-based Roman Catholic weekly
Tygodnik Powszechny founded the pro-Mazowiecki group Alliance for
Democracy in May.
   The city was decorated with banners saying ``Tadeusz Mazowiecki
is the candidate of the royal city'' and ``It's safer with
Mazowiecki.''
   But volunteers for Walesa continued to collect nominating
signatures for his candidacy not far from where Mazowiecki was
speaking.
   Campaign worker Adam Rakszanski said they had collected 200
signatures in three hours.
   Each candidate needs 100,000 signatures by Oct. 25 to get on the
ballot.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0040 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 1626EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-WeatherpageWeather     10-14 0243</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Weatherpage Weather,0269</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rain In Northwest, Around Great Lakes</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Rain was scattered around the Great Lakes and the Northwest on
Sunday, and tropical storm Lili sped out to sea after drenching
parts of New England.
   Afternoon showers with occasional thunderstorms reached across
eastern Upper Michigan, northwestern Lower Michigan, southeastern
Wisconsin and northern Illinois.
   The heaviest rainfall during the six hours up to 2 p.m. EDT was
0.54 of an inch at Sault Ste. Marie, Mich., the National Weather
Service said.
   Showers extended over the Washington state coast, southern
Washington, northern Oregon and the Idaho Panhandle. Rain was mixed
with snow at higher elevations of the Northwest.
   In Alaska, snow fell at Kodiak with an accumulation of 2.3
inches during the morning.
   Lili was about 250 miles east of Massachusetts' Nantucket Island
at midday, moving toward the northeast at about 32 mph.
   Lili and the remnants of tropical storm Marco dumped 3 to 6
inches of rain on southern New England from Saturday afternoon to
early Sunday, the weather service reported. Many areas, including
Woonsocket, R.I., received more than 3 inches of rain in an hour.
   By Sunday afternoon, the Northeast had only showers over
northern Maine.
   Elsewhere, showers were scattered over east-central Minnesota
and east-central South Dakota.
   Atlantic City, N.J., warmed to a record high of 83 degrees
Sunday.
   Sunday's low for the Lower 48 states was 19 at Truckee, Calif.
   Temperatures around the nation at 3 p.m. EDT ranged from 34 at
McCall, Idaho, to 93 at Harlingen and McAllen, Texas.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0041 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 1628EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-India-Hindus     10-14 0445</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-India-Hindus,0535</SECOND>
<HEAD>Procession to Support Building of Temple Reaches Delhi</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ARTHUR MAX</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW DELHI, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A procession of Hindu conservatives
arrived in the capital Sunday on a 6,000-mile pilgrimage to promote
the building of a temple on a site claimed by Moslems and now
occupied by a mosque.
   Tens of thousands of supporters cheered the two-mile-long
procession as it reached the capital 20 days after setting out from
the western city of Somnath.
   The procession was led by Lal Krishna Advani, leader of the
Indian People's Party, who rode in a Toyota pick-up converted to
look like a chariot used in festivals to carry Hindu idols.
   The pilgrimage was on a roundabout route to the holy town of
Ayodhya, 300 miles southeast of New Delhi and home to the disputed
site. Hindus revere Ayodhya as the birthplace of Lord Rama, an
important Hindu god.
   Hindu fundamentalists want to tear down the mosque they claim
replaced a temple destroyed in the 16th century by Moghul
conquerers. Moslem leaders dispute the claim and refuse to vacate
the site. Neither side will compromise.
   ``Never in the 40 years of my political life have I seen such
vast popular support for an issue,'' Advani told Press Trust of
India.
   News agencies said police put dozens of Advani's supporters
under preventative detention in towns along the route, apparently
fearing Moslem-Hindu clashes.
   Earlier, police used truncheons to clear a path for the
procession through a crowd of 200 people protesting a new
government policy that would reserve half of federal jobs for
lower-caste Hindus, suppressed for centuries.
   There are 17 million unemployed educated youths, many of them
from the upper castes. The new policy, over which more than 60
students have committed suicide, has overshadowed the deeper
problem between the two religious communities.
   While Advani prepared for a rally, expected to draw more than
100,000 supporters, People's Party activists drove through the city
on trucks garlanded with marigolds, blaring a message that ``the
temple will be built.''
   The dispute is also laced with politics, piting not only Hindus
against Moslems, but Prime Minister V.P. Singh against Advani's
People's Party, which provides crucial support to keep the minority
government in power.
   The fundamentalists say they will tear down the mosque and begin
building the new Ram temple on Oct. 30, with or without permission.
The Uttar Pradesh local government has said it will not allow
Advani's procession into the state.
   Singh has urged restraint until a court rules on petitions
submitted by both sides. Advani has said, however, it was not a
matter for the courts to settle.
   Advani has said the People's Party will decide in November
whether it will continue to support Singh's coalition, implying the
temple issue may determine its stand. A withdrawal of support could
lead to an election next year.
   Hindus comprise 82 percent of India's 880 million people.
   Critics say mounting tensions fueled by the procession through
eight Indian states were responsible for two outbursts of violence
between Hindus and Moslems over the last two weeks in which at
least 80 people died.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0042 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 1633EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Budget     10-14 0577</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Budget,680</SECOND>
<HEAD>Administration `Violently Opposed' to Democratic Tax Plan</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Budget-Deficit Plans</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Vice President Dan Quayle said Sunday the Bush
administration is ``violently opposed'' to a Democratic plan for a
large increase in the top tax rates paid by the wealthiest
Americans.
   But a principal supporter of the increase, Rep. Dan
Rostenkowski, chairman of House Ways and Means Committee, said he
would seek its approval this week as part of a deficit reduction
plan in an election campaign test of strength.
   ``I'm not going to deny that we're trying to make a political
statement, and there certainly is evidence that there's now a
division between Democrats and Republicans,'' said Rostenkowski,
D-Ill.
   Quayle and Rostenkowski made their comments on Sunday television
news programs, setting the stage for this week's attempt in
Congress to fashion a $500 billion five-year package of spending
cuts and tax increases to rein in the federal deficit.
   If Congress fails to approve an acceptable deficit reduction
plan before midnight Friday, White House Chief of Staff John Sununu
said chances were ``relatively high'' the federal government would
shut down for a second time this month.
   When Congress refused to pass the first deficit plan that
administration officials and congressional leaders had labored over
for months, Bush closed the government for the three-day Columbus
Day weekend. The impact was tempered by the holiday and Bush later
agreed to a temporary spending measure.
   Aside from the deficit reduction plan, Congress hopes to
complete work on comprehensive clean air legislation, a civil
rights bill, a new farm bill and several other major pieces of
legislation before it adjourns forthe year sometime in the next
two weeks.
   There are several hundred billion dollars in spending cuts in
the package, including more than $13 billion in agriculture
spending.
   Any deficit reduction plan also is expected to curb the defense
buildup, cut Medicare, and restrain spending in hundreds of federal
programs. But most of the debate in recent days has centered around
whose taxes should be raised and by how much.
   Rostenkowski's House Ways and Means Committee approved a
proposal that would raise the top tax bracket from 28 percent to 33
percent.
   ``We want to protect middle income and poor America, and we want
everybody to share in the pain of governing,'' Rostenkowski said on
CNN's ``Newsmaker Sunday.''
   He said he would be willing to compromise if need be, but that
he believes the 33 percent tax rate is necessary.
   But Sununu said on NBC's ``Meet the Press'' that the
administration was ``opposed to playing around with the income tax
rate for Americans across the board.''
   An alternative plan was approved by the Senate Finance Committee
early Saturday without the increase in the upper tax bracket. That
plan relies on limiting deductions taken by the wealthy to increase
tax collections.
   In addition, both plans would raise the taxes on gasoline,
alcohol, tobacco and such luxury items as furs, jewelry and
expensive cars.
   ``I had tried to get a 33 percent rate, and the president could
not accept it at all,'' said Sen. Lloyd Bentsen, D-Texas, chairman
of the Senate Finance Committee.
   So, he said, his committee ``came through the back door'' by
limiting deductions on wealthy Americans.
   ``And that means that we have a progressive table, that those
making the highest income will pay the highest increase in the
taxes,'' he said on ABC's ``This Week With David Brinkley.''
   Bentsen said he would defend his plan on the Senate floor, but
noted that some compromise is likely before a final bill emerges
from Congress.
   Quayle, on CBS' ``Face the Nation,'' said Bush was prepared to
reject any deficit-reduction plan he dislikes, regardless of how
long the process takes.
   ``They are going to have to stay in town and pass a budget,''
Quayle said, referring to members of Congress. ``The president is
simply not going to let the Congress go home until they pass a good
deficit-reduction plan that is going to avoid a recession.''
   The original package, which included the budget for the 1991
fiscal year that began Oct. 1, was killed by the House.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0043 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 1634EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Budget-DeficitPlans     10-14 0491</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Budget-Deficit Plans,550</SECOND>
<HEAD>With AM-Budget</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here is a comparison of key parts of rival
deficit-reduction plans backed by House Democrats and the Senate
Finance Committee:
   GASOLINE: No change in the House bill. The Senate would raise
the 9-cent tax to 18{ cents a gallon by 1992. Neither bill would
affect heating oil.
   INDEXING: The House would forgo for one year the annual
adjustments to income tax brackets and personal exemptions, which
are designed to protect against inflation-caused bracket creep.
That would mean higher income taxes for everybody in 1991. The
Senate has no such provision.
   ALCOHOL: House - Raise the $12.50-a-gallon tax on 100-proof
liquor by $1; double the beer tax to 32 cents a six-pack; raise
taxes on most wines, including table wine, which would go from 3
cents a 750-milliliter bottle to 25 cents. Senate - Raise liquor
tax by $1.20; double beer tax; raise wine tax to 21 cents.
   TOBACCO: Either would raise the 16-cent cigarette tax by 4 cents
in 1991 and another 4 cents in 1993. Snuff, cigars and other
tobacco would face 25 percent tax increases each year.
   FLYING: Either would raise the 8 percent tax on airline tickets
to 10 percent.
   LUXURIES: Either would impose a 10 percent tax on the portion of
the price of cars above $30,000; boats above $100,000; jewelry
above $5,000; furs above $10,000 (House) or $5,000 (Senate), and
private planes $100,000 (House) or $250,000 (Senate).
   TAX RATES: The House bill would raise the top rate paid by the
wealthiest people, now 28 percent, to 33 percent. It would impose a
10 percent surtax on those with taxable incomes over $1 million.
The Senate bill would do neither.
   ITEMIZED DEDUCTIONS: The Senate would limit itemized deductions
(except those for medical expenses and investment interest) of
people with adjusted gross income over $100,000. Only 95 percent of
deductions would be allowed against the portion of income above
$100,000.
   CAPITAL GAINS: The House bill would allow a person to avoid tax
on half of up to $200,000 of capital gains earned in a lifetime;
the gains could come from most investments but not from stocks. A
person with annual income under $100,000 could avoid tax on another
$1,000 a year of gains, including those on the sale of stock. No
capital gain would be taxed at a rate above 28 percent. The Senate
bill has no capital-gains provisions.
   LOW-INCOME: Both bills would increase the earned-income tax
credit, which benefits low-income families with children, as a way
of offsetting some of the increased excise taxes. The House plan
included an $11 billion, five-year expansion of the credit; the
Senate, $16.8 billion.
   MEDICARE TAXES: House would increase to $100,000 the maximum
annual wage to which the 1.45 percent Medicare tax applies. The tax
is withheld as part of the Social Security tax. The Senate would
raise the limit to $89,000. The Senate would require all state and
local government workers and their employers to pay the tax; the
House would continue exempting workers hired before 1986.
   MEDICARE PREMIUMS: House would raise the $28.60 monthly premium
for Medicare Part B insurance to $29.90 next year and $46.20 by
1995. Senate: $29.90 next year and $47 by 1995.
   MEDICARE DEDUCTIBLE: House would raise to $100 through 1995 the
present $75 deductible, which beneficiaries must pay before
Medicare starts paying for doctor bills. Senate: $150 each year.
   SOCIAL SECURITY: Either would require all state and local
government workers not covered by a public retirement plan to pay
Social Security taxes.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0044 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 1650EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Israel-ArmyTrial     10-14 0400</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel-Army Trial,0480</SECOND>
<HEAD>Senior Officer on Beatings: ``It is Hard to Believe I Did That''</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Israeli soldiers received ``incredible'' orders
to beat up Arabs while quelling riots at the start of the
Palestinian uprising, a senior officer was quoted as saying Sunday.
   The testimony by Col. Yoni Shimshoni coincided with growing
world criticism of use of force by Israeli security forces
following the Temple Mount killings by police of at least 19 Arabs
during a riot last Monday.
   Shimshoni spoke at the trial of Col. Yehuda Meir - the highest
ranking Israeli officer tried during the 34-month uprising - who is
charged with sanctioning excessive use of force.
   Meir is accused of ordering soldiers to break the bones of
Palestinian rioters in two West Bank villages in January 1988,
while serving as commander of the Nablus area.
   He was charged March 29 on seven felony counts. The most severe
was causing bodily harm with malicious intent, which carries a
maximum 20-year jail sentence.
   According to the charges, soldiers under Meir's orders detained
21 Palestinians in two West Bank villages, bound and gagged and
then beat them with rifles and clubs.
   Meir has admitted giving the orders, claiming they were in
keeping with instructions from former Defense Minister Yitzhak
Rabin to beat rioters as a deterrent measure.
   Rabin has repeatedly said beatings were allowed to control a
riot, but that troops were told detainees could not be struck
unless they resisted arrest.
   The beatings were intended to reduce the number of deaths from
gunshot wounds in the uprising, which began Dec. 8, 1987.
   Some beatings have resulted in deaths. Four officers were
convicted on Oct. 1 of aggravated assault for a beating in which a
21-year-old Palestinian died in February 1988.
   Testifying Sunday, Shimshoni, who served two years ago in the
nearby Tulkarem area, suggested he also had given troopers orders
to beat Palestinians, with backing from superiors.
   Shimshoni said Meir and other commanders ``would voice despair
over the instructions about which it wasn't clear how they should
be carried out.''
   ``When I think about it now,'' Shimshoni reportedly told the
radio, ``it is hard to believe that I did that, that I gave such
orders.''
   ``Today I understand that some incredible things were done
there, under the perception that we are in a state of war, with no
time to stop and think,'' Shimshoni was quoted as saying.
   Another officer, Brig. Gen. David Yaacov, a former operations
officer in the West Bank, was quoted as saying: ``The orders were
clear that rioters should be beaten with force, to deter them from
repeating their actions.''
   Yaacov said ``many detainees reached detention centers with
broken limbs or fractured skulls after being hit with clubs. The
top commanders knew well what was happening.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0045 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 1700EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-SaudiCalls     10-14 0180</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Saudi Calls,0196</SECOND>
<HEAD>AT&amp;T Ends U.S. Soldiers' Free Calls Home</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEWARK, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   American Telephone &amp; Telegraph Co. has cut
short its offer for U.S. troops in Saudi Arabia to call home for
free.
   The troops racked up so many calls in one week that Saudi
communications officials complained their long-distance lines were
being clogged.
   After just one week, and an estimated 100,000 calls at a cost of
$1 million, AT&amp;T on Wednesday notified the military it was
scrubbing its complimentary, direct-dial service, spokesman David
Bikle said Sunday.
   AT&amp;T had planned to offer USADirect Service to troops for two
weeks.
   Soldiers are now charged $16.04 for a 10-minute call home. The
charge is $18.29 for a 10-minute collect call, said AT&amp;T spokesman
Rick Wallerstein.
   The volume of calls had peaked at 1,500 an hour. ``With 100,000
calls, we gave most people a chance for one call home,''
Wallerstein said.
   AT&amp;T, based in Basking Ridge, has yet to calculate the exact
number of calls made since the service was discontinued, he said.
   U.S. troops have been deployed in Saudi Arabia since Iraq
invaded neighboring Kuwait on Aug. 2.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0046 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 1712EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-Libya-Iraq     10-14 0324</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Libya-Iraq,0364</SECOND>
<HEAD>Report: Libya Negotiating Iraqi Purchase of Bomb</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Libya is negotiating with an arms maker to obtain
high-explosive bombs for Iraq that could radically alter the
strategic balance in the Persian Gulf, according to a newspaper
report Sunday.
   The Independent on Sunday reported that Libya was negotiating on
Baghdad's behalf with Chilean arms manufacturer Industrias Cardoen
to buy fuel air explosives, known as FAE, among the most lethal
devices in the conventional armory.
   The bombs unleash a huge fireball and powerful shockwave over a
concentrated area, it said. They work by releasing fuel that seeps
into confined spaces before igniting, the newspaper said.
   ``They are a poor man's nuclear bomb,'' Paul Beaver, editor of
Jane's Defense Weekly magazine, told The Independent on Sunday.
   An Industrias Cardoen official, who wished to remain anonymous,
confirmed the negotiations were under way, the newspaper said.
   It reported that Explosivos Alaveses SA, a Spanish arms company,
developed the explosives for the Spanish air force in 1984 and
1985. Technology for the weapons was manufactured by M.S. Systems
in Madrid, it said.
   Spanish prohibitions against arms sales to Libya or Iraq would
have forced any Spanish company to export through a third country,
the newspaper said.
   ``In this case it was a triangular arrangement,'' the Cardoen
source is reported to have said.
   Cardoen developed fuses for the bombs, the newspaper said. The
company is building a $60 million high-technology fuse factory near
Baghdad, it said. It wasn't clear whether the factory's status had
been altered by the U.N.-ordered sanctions on doing business with
Iraq.
   ``Shortly after the U.N. embargo was imposed (on Iraq), Cardoen
tested FAE about 50 miles north of Iquique in Chile's Atacama
desert,'' the newspaper said. The test, attended by Cardoen
scientists and five Spanish engineers, was not reported to the
Chilean authorities, it said.
   Beaver said the the British army was very concerned when it
learned the Soviets possessed the explosives, which they reportedly
used in Afghanistan.
   ``They would have wreaked havoc with tanks in Europe. So imagine
the anxiety felt over Iraq getting their hands on them,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0047 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 1717EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Gulf-PLO-France     10-14 0366</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-PLO-France,0411</SECOND>
<HEAD>Arafat: Saddam Showing Flexibility on Kuwait</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SAFIA ALLAG-MORRIS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TUNIS, Tunisia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   PLO Chairman Yasser Arafat said Sunday
that Iraqi President Saddam Hussein was showing a ``certain
flexibility'' regarding Kuwait and urged all countries involved in
the gulf crisis to follow suit.
   The Palestine Liberation Organization leader spoke at a joint
press conference with French Foreign Minister Roland Dumas
following meetings on the Persian Gulf and the deaths of 19
Palestinians last week in Jerusalem.
   Arafat spoke with Dumas upon the Palestinian leader's return
from Baghdad, where he met Saddam. Dumas is on the first leg of a
two-day Middle East trip.
   Arafat said Saddam had softened his stance on pulling out of
Kuwait, which Iraqi forces invaded on Aug. 2 and later annexed. He
did not elaborate.
   ``I'm optimisitic on the chances to reach a poltical
settlement,'' Arafat said. ``There's no other alternative; the only
alternative is war. Everybody has to give.''
   The Soviet government-run Novosti Press Agency said in a report
published Sunday that Saddam had given similar indications of a
softened stance to Yevgeny Primakov, an aide to President Mikhail
Gorbachev who was in Baghdad last week.
   Dumas' visit to Tunis came a day after the U.N. Security Council
condemned Israeli police for killing 19 Palestinans at Jerusalem's
Temple Mount, holy to both Jews and Moslems, and voted to
investigate the incident.
   Arafat thanked France for supporting the condemnation. Although
the PLO has criticized the resolution as weak, Arafat on Sunday
called it ``progress.''
   The PLO also seeks United Nations protection for Palestinians
living in the Israeli-occupied West Bank and Gaza Strip and an
international conference on the Middle East.
   Dumas warned against making hasty judgments regarding Arafat's
declarations on Saddam's flexibility.
   ``I believe we must explore all the chances of reaching a
peaceful solution,'' he said. ``If there's one point I have in
common with Mr. Arafat, it's this one.''
   French Foreign Ministry spokesman Daniel Bernard said earlier
Sunday that Dumas wanted to express French solidarity with Arafat
over the Temple Mount killings, which occurred after Palestinians
stoned Jewish worshipers.
   Dumas met with President Zine el-Abidine Ben Ali before holding
talks with Arafat at the PLO's headquarters in suburban Gammarth.
   Dumas will also visit Qatar, Bahrain and Oman on his two-day
visit. French President Francois Mitterrand recently traveled to
Saudi Arabia and Abu Dhabi.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0048 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 1724EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-SnakeAlert     10-14 0281</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Snake Alert,0333</SECOND>
<HEAD>Latest NYC Hazard - Poisonous Snakes in Pet Shops</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   About 50 supposedly harmless snakes sold to a
chain of pet stores by a wholesaler turned out to be poisonous, but
the mistake wasn't noticed until some had been sold to the public.
   Venomous Asian water snakes known as Redneck Keelbacks were
mistakenly labeled as harmless garter snakes. Some of the snakes
bought by Petland Discounts were distributed among the company's 50
stores in the metropolitan area.
   The Health Department issued a public warning Friday.
   Afterward, the ASPCA picked up five snakes from pet owners who
called for help. Two of them turned out to be Keelbacks.
   In addition, 14 venomous snakes were removed from stores and
taken to the zoo.
   Redneck Keelbacks are not usually aggressive. But a bite can be
fatal if not treated, said Peter Lynn, a Health Department
spokesman.
   The snakes are about 18 inches long and about as big around ``as
your pinky,'' said Marilynn LeVine, spokeswoman for the Bronx Zoo.
They are orange but look like common North American garter snakes.
   A self-taught snake handler whose discovery of the mistake led
to a tri-state snake alarm said he tried to tell people but
initially no one would listen, Newsday reported Sunday.
   ``But they believe me now,'' said Tom Robertson Jr.
   Robertson was in a Petland Discount store in Manhattan when he
noticed the Keelbacks.
   ``I told the police, the federal wildlife service - I called a
lot of places'' to no avail, Robertson told Newsday.
   ``The guys in the store didn't believe me and got nasty about
it,'' said Robertson. ``I brought back a book, but they still
didn't believe me.''
   It was the city Health Department that took him seriously. Its
inspectors called a New York University biologist who confirmed
Robertson's suspicions.
   A person who answered the phone Friday at the pet store
headquarters refused to comment.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0049 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 1738EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-JebBush-Loan 1stLd-Writethru a0705 10-14 0417</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Jeb Bush-Loan, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0705,0503</SECOND>
<HEAD>Savings and Loan Bailout Helped Pay Off Loan to Bush's Son Jeb</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 5th graf to restore missing word, `million,' after $4.565
figure.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A savings and loan became insolvent after
lending President Bush's son Jeb and a partner about half the money
toward purchase of a $9 million office building, and the federal
government ended up repaying most of the loan, a newspaper reported
Sunday.
   The New York Times reported that the loan arrangement involved
no criminal behavior, but stood as an example of some savings
institutions' poor lending practices that led to the industry's
troubles.
   The transaction was unrelated to civil charges in Denver that
the president's youngest son, Neil, 35, acted improperly in his
role as a director of Silverado Banking, Savings and Loan
Association. That S&amp;L failed in 1988 after making questionable
loans.
   The Miami deal involves Jeb Bush, 37, and his partner, Armando
Codina, who own a partnership called 1390 Brickell.
   In 1985, the two men bought a Miami office building at that
address for $9 million. They used a $7 million mortgage from an
insurance company and a $4.565 million loan from Broward Federal
Savings and Loan of Sunrise, Fla. The surplus money was to be used
for improvements and a reserve account.
   The loan from Broward Federal was obtained through J.E. Houston
Financial Group, headed by J. Edward Houston, a former Fort
Lauderdale banker and associate of Bush's and Codina's.
   Broward Federal became insolvent in 1988, and the federal
government paid more than $4 million to make good the loan on the
Miami property as part of the bailout of the S&amp;L industry.
   Bush and Codina negotiated a settlement with regulators in which
they repaid $505,000 and retained control of the building, the
Times said.
   The Times said that Bush and Codina expressed surprise that the
settlement could be interpreted as the use of taxpayers' money to
bail out the loan. Asked if they were aware the money for the
repayment of the Broward Federal loan came from the taxpayers, both
men said no.
   Federal officials defended the agreement, the newspaper said,
saying it was the best settlement available because of the weakened
commercial real estate market in Miami and because the loan was
secured by a risky second mortgage.
   They said Jeb Bush received no preferential treatment, the Times
said.
   A lawsuit between the 1390 Brickell partnership and Houston over
who should pay back the $4.565 million was settled out of court
under the auspices of federal regulators.
   They were authorized to step in because of a Dec. 31, 1988,
agreement under which the assets and liabilities of Broward Federal
were sold to California Federal Bank, a Los Angeles-based S&amp;L.
   The agreement called for the government to guarantee any loss
experienced by Cal Fed in taking over Broward's affairs and to pay
Cal Fed's costs in managing the loans and any litigation to resolve
them.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0050 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 1746EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Obit-Brownell     10-14 0238</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Brownell,0259</SECOND>
<HEAD>Former Education Commissioner Samuel Brownell Dead at 90</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW HAVEN, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Samuel Brownell, a one-time Nebraska
high school teacher who served as U.S. Commissioner of Education in
the Eisenhower administration, has died of heart failure at age 90.
   Brownell died Friday at Yale-New Haven Hospital after a short
illness, said his son, Richard Brownell.
   Brownell was a Yale professor and president of the New Haven
State Teachers College in 1953 when President Dwight D. Eisenhower
named him Commissioner of Education.
   At the time, school enrollments were soaring as the ``baby
boom'' generation entered public schools across the nation.
Brownell urged a rapid expansion of the American education system
at all levels, warning that tens of thousands of new schools would
be needed.
   He also began programs to fight illiteracy and rising dropout
rates, pushed for higher salaries and better working conditions for
teachers, and prodded Congress to provide more money for education.
   He resigned in 1956 to become superintendent of schools in
Detroit, taking on the problems of a school system troubled by a
high dropout rate, demoralized teachers and racial divisions.
   In 10 years in Detroit, Brownell introduced new systems of
hiring and promotion that opened top administrative jobs to blacks,
and began a $100 million construction program that put up 53 new
schools.
   He left Detroit in 1966 to return to Yale and part-time
teaching.
   The one-time Nebraska teacher is survived by his wife, Esther
Delzell Brownell, a son, three daughters, and two brothers.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0051 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 1748EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-Foreigners     10-14 0392</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Foreigners,0456</SECOND>
<HEAD>120 Soviets To Leave Baghdad; Four Britons Arrive in Amman</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ABNER KATZMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NICOSIA, Cyprus (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Iraq has said it will allow more than a
hundred Soviet military advisors and oil technicians to leave
Baghdad for Moscow on Sunday, according to Soviet diplomats in the
Iraqi capital.
   Four Britons, meanwhile, arrived in Amman, Jordan on Sunday from
Baghdad with Youssef Islam, a former singer known previously as Cat
Stevens. He said British nationals held in Iraq and Kuwait have
suffered more than others because of Prime Minister Margaret
Thatcher's ``intransgent'' attitude toward Iraq.
   A Soviet Tupolev 154 arrived in Baghdad to pick up the 120
Soviet nationals, who were to leave late Sunday, the diplomats said
on condition of anonymity.
   Their departure would leave another 180 military advisors still
in Iraq, which before its Aug. 2 invasion of Kuwait depended on
Moscow for the bulk of its advanced weaponry.
   The diplomats said that when their contracts expired, the
remaining advisors would leave, but that they could also choose to
leave before then.
   Iraq threatened last week to ``restrict the travel'' of Soviet
military advisors if Moscow disclosed any Iraqi military secrets to
the United States.
   U.S. Defense Secretary Dick Cheney will ask Soviet officials for
intelligence on Iraqi weaponry when he visits Moscow this week, a
senior Defense Department official has said in Washington.
   Islam arrived in Amman aboard a commercial Iraqi Airways flight
along with the four Britons, Shiite Moslems stranded in Iraq after
the invasion. The British Embassy said the five would leave for the
United Kingdom early Monday.
   The men were identified as Mohammad Gulamhossein, Mohammad S.H.
Rahim, Said Hassan Askari, and Anwar Haj Abdullah. A British
embassy official said Islam secured their release after a month of
negotiations.
   The four, all of Indian or Pakistani origin, were making
pilgrimages to the Moslem shrines of Najaf and Kerbela in Iraq when
the invasion occurred.
   Islam called their release a ``symbolic gesture'' by Iraq.
   He accused Mrs. Thatcher of adopting a stubborn attitude toward
Iraq during the 2-month-old standoff. He did not, however, specify
how the Britons had suffered more than the hundreds of other
Westerners detained by Saddam Hussein.
   More than 1,000 U.S. nationals and 1,500 Britons are still held
in Iraq and Kuwait. Iraq has sent about 700 Westerners to strategic
sites to deter against attack by the U.S.-led multinational forces
in the Persian Gulf.
   Rahim said he and his fellow detainees were held at a Baghdad
hotel, which they were free to leave. He said they were ``overfed''
by the Iraqis, reportedly suffering food shortages because of the
U.N.-imposed trade embargo.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0052 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 1821EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-KuwaitConference 1stLd-Writethru   10-14 0611</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Kuwait Conference, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0681,0702</SECOND>
<HEAD>Kuwaiti Exiles Want Guarantees of Democracy</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Leaqds with 10 grafs with new quotes from Kuwaiti opposition,
picks up 8th graf pvs, `Parliament was ...</NOTE>
<HEAD>With AM-US-Gulf Coalition, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ALY MAHMOUD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JIDDAH, Saudi Arabia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Kuwaiti opposition figures meeting
with their government-in-exile said Sunday they want guarantees of
democratic reform in a future liberated Kuwait.
   One prominent Arab nationalist blamed the Aug. 2 Iraqi invasion
on the lack of democracy throughout the Arab world.
   ``When we are liberated we have to go down to the roots and see
what went wrong in Kuwait and elsewhere in the Arab world,'' said
Ahmed al-Khatib.
   ``We live in an Arab world where no government is really
representative of its people,'' he said. ``No government came
through elections.''
   His views - unsually frank by Kuwaiti standards - were expressed
as 750 Kuwaiti businessmen, economists and politicians gathered
over the weekend to explore ways of ending the Iraqi occupation of
Kuwait and charting out a ``democratic path'' for its future.
   The Kuwaitis here were impatient, saying that the U.N. trade
embargo on Baghdad will not work and expressing hope that the
U.S.-led multinational force would launch military action against
Iraq.
   ``International unanimity could be adversely affected, in
Saddam's favor of course, unless the Americans act without delay,''
said former parliamentarian Mubarak Duweileh, who fled Kuwait to
Saudi Arabia after the invasion.
   Those attending the conference were agreed on seeking national
unity under the leadership of the emir, Sheik Jaber al-Ahmed
al-Sabah. But they said greater democracy would be necessary if
Kuwait were regained.
   ``If we are liberated,'' Khatib said, ``We have to present
ourselves to the world ... and underscore our respect for free
speech and human rights, our demand for democracy at large.''
   The emir received strong support at the opening session
Saturday. His crown prince and prime minister, Sheik Saad
al-Abdullah al-Sabah, promised that Kuwait would enjoy a
``democratic'' system of government based on the 1962 constitution,
which provided for Western-style parliamentary rule.
   Parliament was suspended in 1986 because of pressure from
opposition deputies at a time when the country was the target of a
terrorist campaign meant to break Kuwait's support for Iraq in the
Iran-Iraq war.
   Opposition figures at the conference welcomed Saad's assurances,
but said Sunday that they need guarantees.
   ``We are optimistic about the promise the rulers made to return
to the constitution of 1962 but there are not enough assurances,''
said former Parliament Speaker Ahmed al-Saadoun, who leads 30
former parliamentarians who oppose the government-in-exile.
   ``Kuwait's ordeal has amply demonstrated that politically free
people can be more instrumental in safeguarding their government,''
Saadoun told reporters. ``Free people stick to legitimacy and
promote it.''
   In the past, Saadoun has accused the emir of violating the
constitution because he dissolved Parliament without holding
elections within 60 days.
   But Saadoun insisted that the opposition strongly backs the
exiled government in its efforts to achieve liberation, and he
denied Iraqi claims that the opposition sought to get rid of the
ruling al-Sabah family.
   ``Article 4 of the constitution states that Kuwait is a
hereditary emirate to be ruled by the al-Sabah family,'' he said.
``This article cannot be amended.''
   But he demanded the desired national unity be based on ``the
basic freedom and participation of the people in shaping the policy
of state.''
   Saadoun rejected as ``absurd'' an Iraqi call for a referendum in
Kuwait to determine whether the al-Sabah family are the legitimate
rulers of Kuwait.
   ``The question of legitimacy has never been at issue,'' Saadoun
said. ``The whole country stands united behind the al-Sabah family.
   ``We all stand with Sheik Jaber until Kuwait is fully liberated.
Afterward, we would sit down and discuss whatever shape of
government is deemed best for the situation.''
   A conference spokesman, Mohammed al-Rumaihi, announced that the
Kuwaiti representatives at Sunday's meeting decided to provide
military training for all capable Kuwaiti youth.
   He said they discussed methods of liberation ``in depth'' but
did not elaborate. A final communique will be issued Monday when
the conference ends, he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0053 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 1846EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Egypt-Shooting 1stLd-Writethru a0720 10-14 0434</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Egypt-Shooting, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0720,0483</SECOND>
<HEAD>Iraqis Deny Role in Shooting; 25 Arrests Made</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Updates throughout with new arrests, details; no pickup</NOTE>
<DATELINE>CAIRO, Egypt (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Police have rounded up dozens of Moslem
extremists and foreigners suspected of involvement in the
assassination of the parliament speaker, including 25 Palestinians
and Iraqis, newspapers reported Monday.
   But Iraq denied any involvement in the killing of Speaker Rifaat
el-Mahgoub, his driver and four security men Friday in Cairo.
   The official Iraqi News Agency said the reports linking Iraq to
the slayings were ``based on the promotion of lies'' and meant to
``cover up popular indignation'' against Egypt's support of the
U.S.-led forces in the Persian Gulf region.
   The state-owned newspaper Al-Ahram said in its early edition
that the suspects also included two Pakistanis detained while
trying to leave Egypt. It gave no breakdown on how many of the 25
were Palestinians or Iraqis.
   Security authorities have firm evidence the killers were Arabs
who infiltrated Egypt to carry out the assassination, Al-Ahram said
without elaboration.
   Another state-owned newspaper, Al-Akhbar, said Sunday that two
men carrying forged Syrian and Iraqi passports were arrested at
Cairo International Airport as they were leaving the country.
   Airport security officials said later that three Arabs carrying
Australian, American and Syrian passports were arrested Sunday.
   All the arrested suspects resembled composite sketches of five
gunmen compiled from witnesses.
   A spokesman at the Interior Minister, which is in charge of
internal security and police, declined Sunday to comment on the
newspaper reports.
   In additon to the Arabs, Al-Ahram said an unspecified number of
local Moslem extremists were arrested for questioning. It also said
police were interrogating Palestinians and Iraqis who were arrested
before the assassination.
   Interior Minister Abdel-Halim Moussa last week announced the
arrests of 35 alleged saboteurs and warned of possible terror
attacks by Iraqi agents.
   Among the previously arrested Palestinians were men suspected of
belonging to Abu Nidal's terrorist group. Recent reports said Abu
Nidal, who split years ago with the Palestine Liberation
Organization, has moved his headquarters to Iraq from Libya.
   But the Iraqi News Agency, monitored in Nicosia, Cyprus, said
Egyptian news reports ``accusing Iraq one way or another'' were
published ``in accordance with Egyptian media policy, based on the
promotion of lies and the misrepresentation of facts.''
   ``In the final analysis, the fate of he who betrayed Egypt, and
the Arab nation, and failed to keep their pledges will receive
further blows until he returns to his senses,'' it said, in an
apparent reference to Egyptian President Hosni Mubarak.
   A little known Palestinian group called the World Islamic
Liberation Front claimed responsibility for el-Mahgoub's
assassination in a telephone call to a Western news agency in the
Jordanian capital, Amman. Sources in Amman said the group was made
up of publicity-seekers who had a record of false claims.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0054 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 1901EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-GalleryDirector-Award     10-14 0252</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gallery Director-Award,0261</SECOND>
<HEAD>Society of Professional Journalists Honors Cincinnati Gallery
Director</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOUISVILLE, Ky. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Directors of the Society of Professional
Journalists on Sunday voted to give a First Amendment Award to
Cincinnati art gallery director Dennis Barrie for his stand on
artistic freedom.
   Barrie was acquitted Oct. 5 of pandering obscenity for
exhibiting photos by the late Robert Mapplethorpe at the
Contemporary Arts Center in Cincinnati.
   ``When other museums were bowing to community pressure in
canceling the exhibit, Dennis Barrie chose to stand firm for the
artist's right to express himself, and the public's right to see
that expression,'' said SPJ President Frank Gibson, metro editor
for The Tennessean in Nashville.
   ``His battle to uphold the principles of the First Amendment
came at considerable expense and the threat of jail.''
   The SPJ First Amendment Award recognizes exceptional efforts by
individuals and institutions to preserve the American public's
right to free speech or free press.
   The board acted during a meeting following the national SPJ
convention. The award will be presented to Barrie later.
   The nation's largest organization for journalists presented two
First Amendment awards Friday at its convention. The recipients
were:
   - Texas Supreme Court Justice Lloyd Doggett, for longstanding
efforts on behalf of governments having open meetings and records.
   - Peter Sussman, editor of the San Francisco Chronicle's Sunday
``Punch'' section, for publishing the bylined essays of Dannie
Martin, a convicted bank robber. The inmate and the newspaper have
sued in federal court to keep prison officials from restricting
Martin's reporting.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0055 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 1903EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Germany-Elections 2ndLd-Writethru a0706 10-14 0671</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Germany-Elections, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0706,0771</SECOND>
<HEAD>Christian Democrats Dominant in Former East German States</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: UPDATES throughout with firmer projections, Social Democrats
losing majority in lower Parliament, Republicans apparently not
winning seats in Bavaria; no pickup</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto BER2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARK FRITZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Chancellor Helmut Kohl's party strengthened its
dominant national position Sunday with a near sweep in elections
across former East German territory, projections showed.
   Kohl's conservative Christian Democrats took four out of the
five eastern states, adding momentum for national elections Dec. 2
and giving the party control of both houses of Parliament,
preliminary returns indicated.
   ``The Dec. 2 elections have not been won, the results will come
on Dec. 2,'' Kohl said. ``But we are in a good starting position.''
   According to preliminary returns, the main opposition Social
Democrats will lose their slim majority in the Bundesrat, the upper
house of Parliament, which bases seats on how parties did in state
elections. The Christian Democrats already control the lower house.
   The former Communists who ruled East Germany for 40 years
apparently won seats in state legislatures, indicating they may
have enough support to grab a place in the united German
Parliament.
   Kohl's party easily won in the four eastern states of Thuringia,
Saxony, Saxony-Anhalt and Mecklenburg-Lower Pomerania, according to
projections by the German television networks, ARD and ZDF.
   The Christian Democrats were losing the state of Brandenburg to
the left-leaning Social Democrats. In the March national elections,
the Christian Democrats won that state.
   The state elections were important because they finally gave
those in the former East Germany the governors and state
legislatures who will have to assume a major responsibility for
removing much of the entrenched Communist system.
   The December elections will be the first united German elections
in 60 years. Kohl, the politician most responsible for uniting the
German states on Oct. 3, is widely favored to win.
   Wolfgang Thierse, a top Social Democrat in eastern Germany, said
the Christian Democrats dominated because they promised quick
prosperity to the downtrodden eastern Germans.
   ``We can't present ourselves, and don't want to present
ourselves, as the party of big money,'' he said. ``We also can't
present ourselves as miracle workers.''
   Across eastern Germany, the television projections had the
Christian Democrats with 44 percent of the vote, the Social
Democrats with 25, and the former Communists with 11 percent.
   If they clear 5 percent of the vote, the former Communists are
guaranteed seats in the state legislatures.
   The reformed Communists, now called the Party of Democratic
Socialism, have been the third-strongest party in the nation since
they were ousted from power.
   Party leader Gregor Gysi predicted the party would retain enough
support to win Parliament seats in the national elections.
   ``We have good chances to enter Parliament on Dec. 2,'' he said.
   Elections also were held in wealthy Bavaria, the largest of the
states in former West Germany. The arch-conservative Christian
Social Union was again dominant, according to the television
projections.
   The projections showed the ultra-right Republican Party at just
under the 5 percent hurdle needed to get into the Bavarian
legislature. Earlier, they appeared over the amount needed to win
seats.
   The extremist Republicans, led by a former Nazi SS soldier,
favor tougher restrictions on allowing foreigners to live in
Germany. They garnered miniscule support in what was East Germany,
according to the projections.
   After 40 years without free elections, voters in the former East
Germany have now held three in six months and face a fourth in
December.
   In March, they chose their first democratic government to
replace the ousted Communist regime toppled by the peaceful revolt
last year.
   The Christian Democrat-led government quickly led the nation to
German unification. In May, voters elected local governments.
   The Christian Democrats have dominated all the elections by
promising an unhindered free market economy and fast unification
with West Germany.
   However, the projections showed them winning by a margin that
was substantially lower than the margin in the March balloting, the
first free elections in East German history.
   The Social Democrats have tried to capitalize on the terrible
economic problems in the East German territory since the former
nation converted to a free market economy.
   The five eastern German state governments face the monumental
task of forming separate adminstrations from the vestiges of the
old centralized Communist system, where all power emanated from the
national party bosses.
   The states will have to quickly assume responsibility for
police, education, transportation and some social services.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0056 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 1913EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-GulfRdp     10-14 0673</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf Rdp,0792</SECOND>
<HEAD>PLO Head Hints at Iraqi `Flexibilty' on Gulf Crisis</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CARRIE FIGDOR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   PLO Chairman Yasser Arafat said Sunday that Saddam Hussein was
showing a ``certain flexibility'' regarding his claims to Kuwait
and urged all countries involved in the gulf crisis to follow suit.
   The Palestine Liberation Organization leader held a news
conference in Tunis, Tunisia, with French Foreign Minister Roland
Dumas, after discussing the gulf and the deaths of 19 Palestinians
last week in Jerusalem.
   Arafat, who recently returned from meetings in Baghdad with
Saddam, said the Iraqi president had softened his stance on
withdrawing from Kuwait, which Iraqi forces invaded on Aug. 2.
Arafat did not elaborate. Later Sunday, Arafat flew to Baghdad for
further talks with Saddam, the Iraqi News Agency said.
   Saddam has previously linked a gulf settlement to Israeli
withdrawal from territories claimed by the Palestinians.
   Moscow's government-run Novosti Press Agency said in a published
report Sunday that Saddam gave similar indications of flexibility
on Kuwait to Soviet President Mikhail Gorbachev's envoy in Baghdad
last week.
   In other developments, Iran and Iraq reopened embassies in each
other's capitals, resuming full diplomatic ties after a decade of
hostility, Iran's Islamic Republic News Agency reported Sunday.
   The exchange of diplomats came two years after a U.N.-brokered
cease-fire halted hostilities in the eight-year Iran-Iraq war.
   The Iraqi charge d'affaires took up his post Sunday and his
Iranian counterpart was to leave for Baghdad shortly, said IRNA,
monitored in Nicosia, Cyprus.
   Neither was named, but the Tehran Times quoted Iranian sources
as saying the likely Iranian envoy would be Javad Turkabadi, Iran's
former charge d'affaires in Kuwait.
   Saddam is believed to be seeking Iranian help in circumventing
the U.N. embargo imposed to force him out of Kuwait. Reports have
said food shipments reached Iraq from Iran across their 730-mile
border.
   Also Sunday, Kuwaiti opposition figures continued meetings in
Jiddah, Saudia Arabia, with their government-in-exile and said they
wanted guarantees of democratic reform in a future liberated
Kuwait.
   The Iraqi invasion caught a group of Kuwaiti activists in the
midst of a pro-democracy struggle over demands for a Western-style
parliament.
   Kuwait's parliament was suspended in 1986 because of pressure
from opposition deputies at a time when the country was the target
of a terrorist campaign meant to break Kuwait's support for Iraq in
the Iran-Iraq war.
   An estimated 750 Kuwaiti politicians, businessmen and economists
met behind closed doors at the conference palace to discuss ways of
achieving national unity under the leadership of the emir, Sheik
Jaber al-Ahmed al-Sabah.
   Many said they were doubtful the trade embargo would work and
that they hoped the U.S.-led multinational force in the Gulf would
launch military action against Iraq.
   On Sunday night, a special flight arrived in Baghdad on Sunday
to collect more than 100 Soviet military advisers and oil workers
for the return trip to Moscow, diplomats said from the Iraqi
capital.
   A Soviet diplomat in the Iraqi capital said its departure later
that night would leave 180 military advisers still in Iraq.
   Prior to the invasion, Baghdad relied on Moscow for the bulk of
its advanced weaponry. The Soviet diplomats said remaining advisers
could leave when their contracts expire unless they opt to depart
sooner.
   Iraq threatened last week to restrict the travel of Soviet
military advisors if their government disclosed any of its military
secrets to the United States.
   Four British nationals arrived on a flight from Baghadad to
Amman, Jordan, in the company of former pop singer Cat Stevens, who
now uses the name Youssef Islam. He had appealed for their release.
   Islam said British citizens in Iraq and Kuwait have suffered
more than others because of Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher's
``intransigent'' attitude toward Iraq.
   In other developments:
   -Newspapers in Cairo reported Sunday that police had arrested
dozens of Arabs and Egyptian Moslem extremists suspected of
involvement in the assassination of Parliament Speaker Rifaat
el-Mahgoub last Friday. They said they included at least 25
Palestians and Iraqis.
   The Iraqi News Agency said the reports ``accusing Iraq one way
or another'' of the killing were ``lies'' and a ``misrepresentation
of facts.''
   -In London, the Independent on Sunday reported that Libya was
negotiating for Iraq to purchase a highly explosive bomb from
Chilean arms manufacturer Industrias Cardoen. A company official
confirmed the report.
   The ``Fuel Air Explosives'' weapon has been described by a
weapons expert at Jane's Defense Weekly, a leading military
industry publication, as ``the poor man's nuclear bomb.''
   -U.S. Secretary of Defense Dick Cheney arrived in London on
Sunday for high-level talks to be dominated by the crisis.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0057 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 1920EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Gulf-SaudiCalls 1stLd-Writethru a0708 10-14 0355</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Saudi Calls, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0708,0433</SECOND>
<HEAD>AT&amp;T Ends U.S. Soldiers' Free Calls Home</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: UPDATES throughout with reaction from soldiers, other details.
Stands as a 1st Ld-Writethru to AM-Saudi Calls.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>NEWARK, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   American Telephone &amp; Telegraph Co. has cut
short its offer for U.S. troops in Saudi Arabia to call home for
free, disappointing soldiers who said the calls boosted morale.
   The troops racked up so many calls that Saudi communications
officials complained their long-distance lines were being clogged.
   After just one week, and an estimated 100,000 calls at a cost of
$1 million, AT&amp;T on Wednesday notified the military it was
scrubbing its free, direct-dial service, spokesman David Bikle said
Sunday.
   AT&amp;T had planned to offer USADirect Service to troops for two
weeks.
   Soldiers are now charged $16.04 for a 10-minute call home. The
charge is $18.29 for a 10-minute collect call, said AT&amp;T spokesman
Rick Wallerstein.
   The volume of calls had peaked at 1,500 an hour. ``With 100,000
calls, we gave most people a chance for one call home,''
Wallerstein said.
   U.S. troops have been deployed in Saudi Arabia since Iraq
invaded neighboring Kuwait on Aug. 2.
   In the eastern Saudi city of Dhahran, soldiers formed long lines
to use phones at the Dhahran International Hotel when the free
service was in effect.
   ``I wish they would keep it up,'' Sgt. John Tackitt, 27, of
Concord, Calif., told an Associated Press reporter Thursday. ``It's
a good morale booster knowing that you don't have to pay for
something that you look forward to using.''
   ``Talking to people at home picks you up a little bit,'' echoed
Spc. Richard Cloud, 24, of Atlanta. ``You get tired of talking to
people here because you hear the same stories. ... I wish it was
free. I sure do. I don't know how much it is going to cost. But I'm
calling anyway.''
   Sgt. Moses Clerk, of St. Louis, said phone calls made life more
bearable. ``You can call home and talk to your family and find out
what is going on at home because sometimes the news does not get
here on time,'' he said.
   Saudi officials said several factors helped to overload the
circuits, including the U.S. military reserving 40 lines for its
own use and a satellite station in Riyadh having to shut down for
repairs.
   All that was left were 400 lines, and the Saudi government
suggested AT&amp;T open up more circuits on the satellite between the
United States and Saudi Arabia, said the officials, speaking on
condition of anonymity.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0058 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 1922EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Summit-Liberia     10-14 0236</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Summit-Liberia,0252</SECOND>
<HEAD>Summit Meeting on Liberia Canceled</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ABIDJAN, Ivory Coast (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An emergency summit of West African
leaders to discuss Liberia's civil war has been canceled, the
Ivorian government said Sunday.
   No reason was given, but some officials feared the meeting could
have widened the dispute over a five-nation military force sent to
Liberia to end the fighting.
   The summit, which had been scheduled for Monday in President
Felix Houphouet-Boigny's hometown of Yamoussoukro, was opposed by
some members of the 16-nation Economic Community of West African
States, including Nigeria and the four other countries
participating in the task force.
   Ivory Coast, Burkina Faso and some other French-speaking
countries have opposed the intervention. These countries also have
supported rebel leader Charles Taylor's claim as the legitimate
president of Liberia.
   All the nations in the task force are English-speaking except
Guinea, a former French protectorate.
   Taylor and his supporters had been pressing for a summit to push
for a withdrawal of the task force, which has taken control of the
capital city of Monrovia and moved into suburbs.
   Taylor's forces, which invaded from Ivory Coast on Dec. 24, have
overrun most of the country except the capital.
   Troops loyal to slain President Samuel Doe and a second rebel
leader, Prince Johnson, have been cooperating with the task force
and are concentrated in Monrovia.
   Liberia's 10-month-old civil war has left at least 5,000
civilians dead and forced about 250,000 refugees to flee to
neighboring countries.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0059 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 1927EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-NortheastStorm 2ndLd-Writethru a0717 10-14 0444</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Northeast Storm, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0717,0530</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dwindling Storms Pour Heavy Rain on New England</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 5 grafs to UPDATE with 6 p.m. advisory, comment
from Hurricane Center. Picks up 4th graf, `Flooding hampered ...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   The remnants of tropical storms Lili and Marco combined to dump
a month's worth of rain in less than a day in parts of southern New
England, flooding roads and washing out football games.
   Before moving northward, Marco and the remnants of tropical
storm Klaus caused extensive flooding last week in Georgia and the
Carolinas. At least 12 people were killed.
   At 6 p.m. EDT Sunday, Lili was centered near latitude 44 north
and longitude 63 west, or about 50 miles southeast of Halifax, Nova
Scotia, moving toward the northeast at about 37 mph. Its maximum
sustained wind speed was down to 65 mph.
   Max Mayfield of the National Hurricane Center in Coral Gables,
Fla., said Lili, downgraded from a hurricane on Saturday, had lost
its tropical character because its highest winds are no longer
concentrated at its center and because of its northerly location.
   ``We'll get three or five of these a year that hold together as
they get far up north,'' he said. ``It's technically an
extratropical low pressure system.''
   Flooding hampered travel in many parts of New England on
Saturday night and power outages were reported as the storms
brushed past.
   Power outages affecting about 1,400 electricity customers were
reported in the Acton-Maynard and Waltham areas of Massachusetts,
said Boston Edison spokesman Mike Monahan.
   On New York's Long Island, floodwaters washed beneath commuter
train tracks.
   ``You can now walk underneath the tracks,'' said Suffolk County
police spokesman Sgt. Donald Yourie.
   The storms dumped 3 to 6 inches of rain on southern New England
from Saturday afternoon to early Sunday, said Tom DeGregorio of the
National Weather Service.
   Many areas received more than 3 inches of rain in an hour,
including Woonsocket, R.I., he said.
   ``That's the normal monthly average for this time of year,''
DeGregorio said.
   In New Haven, Conn., 2 inches of rain fell in just six hours,
flooding roads, snarling traffic, and wiping out most high school
football games. Some people were even marooned at their homes.
   ``We can't get out unless we walk out and tread through
knee-deep water,'' said Lucia Smith of East Haven, Conn.
   A Connecticut man was reported struck by lightning but was not
seriously injured, said a spokeswoman at Day Kimball Hospital in
Putnam, Conn.
   The downpours also washed some bright red and yellow leaves off
trees before the fall foliage reached its peak colors.
   ``It'll make for a less brilliant season,'' said Mel Goldstein,
director of the Weather Center at Western Connecticut State
University in Danbury.
   In Georgia, state and federal emergency management teams worked
Sunday to complete reports on an estimated $34 million in damage
caused by Marco.
   If a request for federal aid is approved, 75 percent of the
damage to public property could be paid with federal money, and
reconstruction funds would be available soon to residents without
insurance, officials said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0060 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 1953EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Brazil-CabinetAffair     10-14 0434</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brazil-Cabinet Affair,0500</SECOND>
<HEAD>Cabinet Resignation Caused by Romantic Scandal Shocks Brazil</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KEN SILVERSTEIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>RIO DE JANEIRO, Brazil (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The romance between Justice
Minister Bernardo Cabral and Economy Minister Zelia Cardoso de
Mello was the stuff of scandal sheets for weeks. But it was a
steamy bolero that blew the lid off the affair.
   On Saturday, Cabral resigned, citing ``intimate personal
reasons'' in his letter to President Fernando Collor de Mello.
   Neither he nor his alleged mistress have seen fit to comment on
the relationship that Veja newsmagazine, the country's largest,
descriped on its cover Sunday as ``The Romance That Brought Down
Cabral.''
   But fully detailed reports on the extra-Cabinet relations of two
of the more important government ministers had been circulating for
weeks.
   Even before the rumors started, Cabral was in hot water with
Collor over his job performance. Collor was reportedly angry that
Cabral had given him bad advice on the constitutionality of various
bills.
   But for the president, who has promised to ``moralize''
Brazilian politics, the scandalous evidences of the tryst between
the 58-year-old, married Cabral and Cardoso de Mello, 37 and
single, were apparently the last straw.
   At a Sept. 19 birthday party for the economics minister, she
danced cheek-to-cheek with her tipsy colleague at a posh Brasilia
club before hundreds of gawking journalists and dignataries.
   The guests' eyes bulged as Cabral whispered in the ear of the
former economics professor, using the intimate diminutive
``Baixinha,'' or ``Shorty.'' The romantic ballad they danced to was
entitled ``Besame Mucho,'' which contains the line ``Kiss me a lot/
Like tonight was the last time.'' And indeed it turned out to be
Cabral's swan song.
   Collor, outraged, only waited to demand Cabral's resignation
because he needed extra time to find a replacement, according to
news reports.
   Sen. Jarbas Passarinho, a widely-respected conservative, was
named over the weekend to replace Cabral.
   Even before the party, the government had commissioned the Vox
Populi polling institute to conduct a survey about the potential
public fallout from the affair. Eighty percent of those interviewed
said they were ``uncomfortable'' about the reported romance.
   Leading political commentator Gilberto Dimenstein, noting that
many gossip columnists were invited to the party where the
ministers rubbed their noses, said Cabral had ``transformed
adultery into governmental marketing.''
   The newsweekly Isto E/Senhor published a caricature showing the
two dancing closely, as Cabral sighed, ``My God, what cheeks!''
   Cardoso de Mello's job - arguably the most important Cabinet
post in a country whose economy is reeling - is the subject of much
speculation.
   Local press accounts published Sunday said Collor had recently
promised Cardoso de Mello - who is no relation to the president -
she would stay. Others said she eventually would resign.
   ``In any country of the First World, a case like this would end
with the dismissal of the two,'' an unnamed minister told Veja.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0061 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 2019EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Israel 2ndLd-Writethru a0721 10-14 0973</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel, 2nd Ld - Writethru, a0721,1180</SECOND>
<HEAD>Government Won't Cooperate With U.N. Team On Temple Mount Slayings</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Leads with 18 grafs to UPDATE with housing construction plan,
picks up 13th graf pvs, `Haim Ramon ...; FIXES age of Nimer in
penultimate graf</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto JRL2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GWEN ACKERMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The government decided Sunday against
cooperating with a U.N. team investigating the shooting deaths of
19 Palestinians by Israeli police, and said the delegation should
stay away from Israel.
   The ministers also delivered a slap to the United States by
announcing plans to build apartments for immigrants in the occupied
eastern sector of Jerusalem. The U.S. government has linked a $400
million loan guarantee to Israel's agreement to avoid settling
immigrants there.
   ``We have read the Security Council's decision ...and it is
completely unacceptable,'' a Cabinet communique said. ``As a result
Israel will not receive the delegation of the U.N.
Secretary-General.''
   Israel television said the Cabinet decision came despite a
personal appeal to Foreign Minister David Levy from U.S. Secretary
of State James A. Baker III, who said the U.N. visit would make it
easier to direct world attention ``to the struggle against Saddam
Hussein.''
   Radio stations said right-wing Housing Minister Ariel Sharon
proposed that the investigators be barred from Israel, but Sharon's
spokesman, Nimrod Granit, denied that.
   Israeli officials, however, made it clear that they expect the
three-man mission to stay away.
   ``This is not an invitation to come; it's an invitation not to
come,'' said Deputy Foreign Minister Benyamin Netanyahu.
   ``There is a limit to absurdity.... It isn't customary to break
down the door,'' Netanyahu said on Israel television. ``It is not
acceptable between countries and not between international
organizations.''
   Police opened fire last Monday on Palestinians during a riot on
the hallowed Temple Mount, sacred to both Moslems and Jews. The
Moslems call it Haram-es-Sharif.
   The riot began when Palestinians threw rocks onto worshipers
praying below at the Western Wall, Judaism's holiest site. Police
first used tear gas and rubber bullets, then live ammunition.
   The U.N. Security Council voted Friday to condemn Israel, and to
send a delegation to investigate. In a rare gesture, the United
States joined in the censure of its ally.
   Israel's Cabinet, at its regular weekly session Sunday, said it
saw no reason for the United Nations to intervene when it had
ignored worse incidents in other countries.
   Netanyahu said: ``When hundreds of worshipers were massacred in
Mecca they did nothing. When hundreds of worshipers were massacred
at the Golden Temple in India they did nothing.''
   In a later meeting of a committee on immigration, Sharon
announced plans to build 5,000 apartments a year in eight
neighborhoods, six of them in east Jerusalem, said Ida
Ben-Shitreet, spokeswoman for the Immigrant Absorption Ministry.
   She insisted the housing decision had been planned before the
U.N. resolution.
   ``This wasn't done to flex muscles. There is no doubt we must
increase immigration to Jerusalem,'' Mrs. Ben-Shitreet said.
   But the radio said Sharon told reporters after the meeting:
``Jerusalem as the capital of the Jewish people is stronger than
any security council decision.''
   Opposition politicians, meanwhile, questioned the Cabinet
boycott of the United Nations.
   Haim Ramon, head of the opposition Labor Party's parliament
faction, said the U.N. mission could not be prevented from coming
and should be allowed into Israel at a non-diplomatic level.
   ``I wouldn't play angry with the whole world. I would accept the
delegation at a low level, to meet with police officers,'' Ramon
told Israel television.
   Levy said the U.N. investigation would violate Israel's
sovereignty over Jerusalem and pave the way for stationing U.N.
forces in the city.
   The Temple Mount is in Arab east Jerusalem, which Israel
captured in the 1967 Middle East War and later annexed.
   Israel maintains its police were provoked by the barrage of
stones onto Jews at the Western Wall, also known as the Wailing
Wall.
   An Israeli human rights group on Sunday accused police of
indiscriminate shooting and ``criminal negligence'' in the
bloodshed. The group, Betselem, said the government has attempted
to ``hide the facts, mislead the public... and evade
responsibility'' in the shootings.
   The Arab League has called a meeting in Tunis to discuss the
killings, and Egypt announced Sunday it would attend, the Middle
East News Agency said. That could be significant becaause the Arab
League has been split between countries that support Iraqi
President Saddam Hussein and those who oppose him.
   Egypt has led Arab opposition to Iraq, while the PLO has
supported Baghdad.
   Arab diplomatic sources in Tunis said the other Arab League
members who would attend the meeting included Iraq, Jordan, Sudan,
Yemen, Algeria, Tunisia, Mauritania and Morocco.
   Israeli officials first said Palestinians planned the stoning of
Jewish worshipers in advance, hoping to provoke an incident that
would divert world attention from the Persian Gulf crisis.
   But Police Commissioner Yaacov Terner later said he believed the
riot was spontaneous.
   It was the bloodiest incident in Jerusalem since the 1967 war,
and the worst loss of life in a single day of the 34-month-old
Palestinian uprising against Israel occupation in the West Bank and
Gaza Strip.
   Levy said he hoped to avoid a collision with the United States.
   ``Our relations with the United States are very important, but
we should not accept, and we should not ignore, the sorry fact that
the U.S. administration has made a mistake,'' Levy said.
   He added that the United States had ``followed this coalition it
formed against (Iraqi President) Saddam Hussein'' - a reference to
pressure on Washington from moderate Arab states to condemn Israel.
The Arabs have formed a coalition with the United States against
Iraq following its Aug. 2 invasion of Kuwait.
   Even before the Temple Mount killings, Jerusalem was a sensitive
issue between Israel and the United States. Washington has insisted
that Israel not spend U.S. aid on settling Soviet immigrants in
Arab Jerusalem.
   The government has appointed its own comittee to investigate the
killings. The three-man panel consists of former Mossad secret
service chief Zvi Zamir, leading lawyer Yaacov Neeman and retired
civil servant Haim Kubersky.
   It held its first session behind closed doors Sunday and
appealed to witnesses to come forward by noon Wednesday.
   In the occupied territories Sunday, one Arab was shot and killed
in clashes with Israeli soldiers and ten others were injured, one
seriously.
   Abdel Abu El-Nimer, 73, from Khan Yunis refugee camp in the Gaza
Strip, was shot in the chest and arrived dead at Nasser Hospital,
Arab reports said.
   The army said it was checking the reports.
   El-Nimer's death brought to 761 the number of Palestinians
killed by Israeli soldiers or civilians since the revolt against
Israeli occupation began in December 1987. About 279 Palestinians
have been killed by fellow Arabs, most on suspicion of
collaborating with Israel.
   Forty-eight Israelis have also died in the violence.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0062 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 2031EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Britain-KGB 1stLd-Writethru a0731 10-14 0517</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Britain-KGB, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0731,0625</SECOND>
<HEAD>Book Alleges `Fifth Man' Was John Cairncross</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 7th graf, `Harold ``Kim ...' to RESTORE first reference
to Guy Burgess; picks up 8th graf pvs, `Some scholars ...</NOTE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The long-secret ``Fifth Man'' of Kim Philby's spy
ring was John Cairncross, a former high-ranking British
intelligence officer, according to a book by a former KGB double
agent who fled to the West.
   Oleg Gordievsky, the Soviet agent who came to Britain in 1985,
makes the claim in a book, ``KGB: The Inside Story of its Foreign
Operations from Lenin to Gorbachev.'' It was written with
Christopher Andrew, a Cambridge University intelligence historian.
   Serialization of extracts from the book began Saturday in
London's Times newspaper. The book was to be released in Britain
and the United States on Friday.
   In Monday's extract, Gordievsky and Andrews say Cairncross was a
spy before and during World War II. He worked during his spy years
in the Foreign Office, the Treasury, for a government minister, for
Britain's electronic eavesdropping center and for the MI6 foreign
intelligence service, the book claims.
   The Times said the Scottish-born Cairncross confessed to the MI5
counterintelligence service in 1964 after interrogation and that he
lives in the south of France.
   ``This is not a new discovery,'' said Labor party legislator Ted
Leadbitter. ``This has been known for an awfully long time.''
   Harold ``Kim'' Philby, said to be the most damaging double agent
in British history, spied for the Soviets for 26 years until he
defected to Moscow in 1963. He and three fellow agents, Guy
Burgess, Donald MacLean and Anthony Blunt, all now dead, turned
Britain's secrets over to the Soviets.
   Some scholars of espionage have long suspected that Soviet
penetration of the British secret service did not end with the
unmasking of the four and that there was probably a ``Fifth Man.''
Others have maintained that the KGB fostered the theory to keep
Western intelligence in doubt.
   It was at Cambridge University, where all five of the men
studied, that Blunt ``talent-spotted'' Cairncross and Burgess
recruited him, the excerpt says.
   Philby, who rose to become head of the MI6 anti-Soviet section,
responsible for the study of communism and the Soviet intelligence
services, was on his way to becoming head of MI6 when he first came
under suspicion in 1951, when Maclean and Burgess fled to Moscow.
   The Times said Cairncross's involvement with Soviet intelligence
has been well documented, but he had never been placed in the same
category as the other four. ``Cairncross always claimed he was just
`a small fish'.'' the Times said.
   On the contrary, ``Cairncross's achievements were the equal of
any of the five except Philby,'' the excerpt quotes KGB officer
Dmitri Svetanko as saying.
   ``Until the end of World War II, when Philby's career began to
take off, I think he provided more important intelligence than any
of the others,'' co-author Andrews told The Associated Press.
   Writer Chapman Pincher and former MI5 officer Peter Wright,
whose book ``Spycatcher'' the British government failed to suppress
in a long court battle, both alleged that former MI5 head Sir Roger
Hollis was a Soviet spy.
   Earlier this year Gordievsky said in a BBC television interview
that Hollis, who ran the counterespionage service from 1956 to
1965, was not a Soviet agent.
   Gordievsky began working for the British while posted in
Copenhagen in the early 1970s.
   The KGB Soviet intelligence service sent him to London but he
was recalled to Moscow. He eluded his KGB tail and escaped to the
West in 1985. His defection led to the retaliatory expulsion of 31
Soviet and 31 British diplomats, trade representatives and
journalists.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0063 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 2140EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Greece-Elections     10-14 0375</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Greece-Elections,0414</SECOND>
<HEAD>Conservative-Backed Candidate Elected In Athens</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PHILIP DOPOULOS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ATHENS, Greece (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The government-backed mayoral candidate in
Athens narrowly defeated a former actress Sunday in municipal
elections widely seen as a referendum on the government's economic
austerity measures.
   In Salonica, Greece's second-largest city, the candidate backed
by the ruling New Democracy party was winning slightly less than
the 50 percent needed to avoid a runoff election.
   In Athens, Antonis Tritsis received 50.1 percent of the vote to
defeat Melina Mercouri, former star of ``Never on Sunday,'' who is
a Parliament member for the Panhellenic Socialist Movement, known
as PASOK.
   The nationwide municipal elections were held to elect 361 mayors
and thousands of local officials. Runoff elections are scheduled
for Sunday in communities with more than 5,000 inhabitants where no
candidate won an absolute majority.
   In the weeks before the vote, the PASOK-led opposition said the
election would gauge public support for the government's efforts to
reduce the nation's $10 million debt and control inflation running
as high as 25 percent.
   Widespread protests and strikes have greeted Premier Constantine
Mitsotakis' plans to raise the retirement age, sell off or close
some state-controlled industries and streamline the social security
system.
   Mitsotakis early Monday said the overall vote was ``positive for
the government ... despite the tough measures taken since it was
elected six months ago.''
   Tritsis, a planning minister from 1981-85 under a PASOK
government, ran as an independent, but was supported by New
Democracy, a conservative party.
   Ms. Mercouri, a former PASOK culture minister, also was backed
by the communist-led Coalition of the Left and Progress. Three
other candidates, including an environmentalist, failed to make a
significant showing in Athens.
   Tritsis, who twice was a Fulbright scholar at the Illinois
Institute of Technology in Chicago, said he would seek assistance
and cooperation from the European Community to help fund
modernization projects in Athens.
   In the port city of Piraeus, adjacent to Athens, a candidate
supported by the socialists and the left coalition defeated the New
Democracy-supported candidate.
   About two-thirds of Greece's 10 million people live in Athens,
Piraeus and Salonica, about 100 miles north of Athens.
   The Ministry of Interior said voter turnout was low, but no
figures were immediately available. Voting is obligatory for all
Greeks between the ages of 18 and 70 except those who live 125
miles from the place where they are registered.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0064 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 2144EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p AM-Illinois-USSenate     10-14 0361</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Illinois-US Senate,0412</SECOND>
<HEAD>Martin and Simon Focus on Taxes, Education in First Debate</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By COLLEEN DISKIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CHICAGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Rep. Lynn Martin assailed Sen. Paul Simon in
their first Senate campaign debate Sunday for supporting more taxes
and foreign aid, while Simon belittled her record on education and
military spending.
   On topics ranging from foreign relations to domestic spending,
the Republican congresswoman repeatedly tried to paint Democrat
Simon as a tax-and-spend liberal whose solution to the nation's
problems was to throw money at them.
   ``My opponent will talk again and again about needing more
money,'' Martin said in the televised debate. ``I don't believe
it's just more money we need.''
   Martin said she supports limiting government spending to natural
revenue growth levels and discontinuing federal programs that prove
ineffective.
   In response, Simon said he supports modest increases in
cigarette and alcohol taxes and higher taxes on the wealthy.
   ``I don't believe it's just more money, but you just can't do
what you need to do without more resources,'' he said.
   ``I've led, my opponent has not,'' said Simon, a member of the
Senate's higher education subcommittee. ``What we need is
leadership in education and I have provided it.''
   But Martin criticized Simon's support of additional aid to
foreign countries when she said Illinois ranks second to last among
states in getting a return on residents' tax dollars.
   ``I think it might sadden you to know that Guatemala gets more
of our money than Chicago's schools,'' Martin said. ``That's under
my opponent's leadership.''
   Simon said more of Illinois' tax dollars could go towards
improving education and human services if the country spent less on
defense and weapons research.
   He criticized Martin for opposing cuts in defense spending, and
especially in the federal government's proposed ``Star Wars''
space-based, ballistic missile system.
   ``We spend three times more per capita for defense of Western
Europe than Western Europeans do,'' Simon said. ``What good does
Star Wars do us anymore when there's no real Russian threat
anymore.''
   Martin took occasional jabs at Simon's unsuccessful run for the
presidency in 1988, saying he still had aspirations for higher
office while she only wanted to be senator.
   But after the debate Simon dismissed the notion, saying, ``The
only person in America whose talking about Paul Simon running for
the presidency is Lynn Martin.''
   They are scheduled to debate again on Oct. 25.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0065 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 2148EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-TrooperKilled 2ndLd-Writethru a0711 10-14 0263</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Trooper Killed, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0711-10,0300</SECOND>
<HEAD>Iowa State Trooper Killed in Plane Crash</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: UPDATES throughout with details. ADDS byline. No pickup.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By GREG SMITH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>IOWA CITY, Iowa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A state trooper tracking a robbery
suspect's car in a light plane was killed Sunday when the craft
plunged into a field in eastern Iowa and burst into flames,
authorities said.
   Trooper Al Neiland took off from Cedar Rapids in a Cessna 172 at
about 7:20 a.m. and crashed 10 minutes later near Interstate 80
about 5 miles east of Williamsburg, the Iowa State Patrol office in
Cedar Rapids said.
   Neiland was helping to pursue a vehicle stolen in Reno, Nev.,
that had been involved in a robbery in Poweshiek County, near where
the plane went down. The driver, Walter Wayne Garris, was arrested
about 20 miles away 3{ hours after the crash, said Iowa County
Sheriff James Slockett.
   Garris, 29, was charged with homicide by vehicle, which carries
a 10-year prison term, Iowa County Attorney Kenneth Martens said.
He was being held Sunday on $600,000 bond, and charges of theft
were being prepared by Poweshiek County authorities, Slockett said.
   Details of the robbery were not immediately disclosed.
   Sandra Campbell, a spokeswoman for the Federal Aviation
Administration at Kansas City, Mo., said the cause of the crash is
under investigation. Neiland was flying solo, she said.
   Neiland, who lived in Iowa City, was married with two sons.
   It was the second fatal accident involving an Iowa State Patrol
plane in two years. A single-engine plane crashed during a search
for a missing man near Atlantic on June 30, 1989, killing two
troopers.
   The National Transportation Safety Board ruled last month that
pilot error was a contributing factor in that crash.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0066 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 2158EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-KoreaVisits     10-14 0308</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Korea Visits,0361</SECOND>
<HEAD>South Korean Musicians Visit North</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   North Korean youths showered a visiting South
Korean musical delegation with confetti and hoisted the visitors on
their shoulders in a welcome to Pyongyang Sunday, North Korean
media reported.
   The 17-member group arrived by train in the North Korean capital
to begin a 10-day concert series. The two countries have begun
taking steps they hope will lead eventually to reunification.
   South Korean Premier Kang Young-hoon was to meet with North
Korean leader Kim Il Sung during a visit to Pyongyang to begin
Tuesday.
   The Korean Central News Agency, monitored in Tokyo, said
thousands of ``working people, men of culture and art, youth and
students'' greeted the artists when they arrived at the railway
station.
   ``Young men rushed to give them a ride on their shoulders,'' it
said.
   The welcomers held up banners with such slogans as ``Let us
loudly sing of reunification'' and ``Korea is one,'' the agency
said.
   Earlier, the 14 musicians and musical writers and three
reporters were met by 500 North Korean officials and villagers at
the border village of Panmunjom.
   ``Your visit has marked a breakthrough in self-reliant cultural
exchanges between the North and the South, and it is an epochal
event in the history of the divided peninsula,'' said Kim Won-kun,
chairman of North Korean League of Musicians.
   Professor Hwang Byung-ki, leader of the South Korean delegation,
said he hoped the trip would ``bring harmony.''
   It was the third private visit by a South Korean delegation in a
series arranged by the two nations' leaders. On Saturday, a South
Korean soccer team returned home after a friendly match in the
north.
   North Korean Prime Minister Yon Hyong Muk visited Seoul early
last month and spoke with South Korean President Roh Tae-woo in the
highest-level talks ever between the two Koreas.
   The two Korean nations have been bitter rivals since the
division of their peninsula in 1945. The border between the two
countries has been shut since the Korean war ended in 1953, and
there is no mail or other direct communication between them.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0067 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 2208EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Obit-Larsen 1stLd-Writethru a0744 10-14 0238</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Larsen, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0744,0273</SECOND>
<HEAD>Famed Norwegian WW II Hero Dies of Stroke</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Fixes date in penultimate graf to 1906 sted 1909</NOTE>
<DATELINE>OSLO, Norway (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Leif Andreas Larsen, the country's
best-known World War II resistance fighter and one of the war's
most highly decorated naval heroes, died from a stroke at age 84,
news reports said Sunday.
   He died Friday at a hospital in Bergen.
   Larsen, a sea captain, made 52 daring voyages across the North
Sea using his fishing boats to slip allied agents, arms and
supplies past Nazi warships into occupied Norway.
   His volunteer crews sailed for the allied Special Operations
Executive, based in the Shetland Islands, north of Britain, from
1941 to 1945. The nickname, ``Shetlands Larsen,'' stuck for life.
   Larsen survived two shipwrecks off Norway's rough coast to
return to England to rejoin the war effort. He scuttled a third
fishing boat in a Norwegian fjord during a failed 1942 attempt to
sink the German warship Tirpitz with torpedoes.
   He got his crew back to England through neutral Sweden, and went
on to lead secret missions supplying the Norwegian underground from
a U.S. submarine that was made available to him in 1943.
   Larsen's exploits have been recounted in numerous Norwegian
films and books, and his 11 bravery medals ranked him among the
war's most decorated naval officers.
   He was born Jan. 9, 1906 in Bergen, and went to sea at age 16.
After the war, he ran a small factory.
   Larsen in 1947 married Anna Justad, daughter of American builder
Marius Justad. He is survived by his wife and three daughters.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0068 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 2216EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Hungary-Elections     10-14 0195</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Hungary-Elections,0204</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hungary Municipal Runoff Elections Held</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BUDAPEST, Hungary (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Light voter turnout was reported Sunday
in municipal runoff elections, the sixth time Hungarians went to
the polls in less than a year.
   In Budapest, the opposition Alliance of Free Democrats won a
plurality of votes in the first round of municipal elections Sept.
30 and was leading in Sunday's second round.
   The liberal Free Democrats led with 36 percent of the vote in
Budapest, with about 17 percent of the ballots counted, state-run
television reported. The Hungarian Democratic Forum, the strongest
force in Parliament, had about 25 percent.
   The results in Budapest and other urban centers are seen as a
test for the center-right coalition government of Jozsef Antall,
six months after national elections.
   Runoffs were held in communities with below 40 percent turnout
in the first round of municipal elections. The first-round turnout
was 34 percent in Budapest.
   In the runoffs, a simple majority will decide the vote. Complete
results in Budapests and results elsewhere were not expected until
Monday.
   According to state radio, turnout Sunday ranged from 20 percent
in some rural areas to about 32 percent of Budapest's 1.5 million
eligible voters.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0069 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 2239EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-PrisonPoisoning     10-14 0230</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Prison Poisoning,0240</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bad Spaghetti Strikes 200 Inmates at Florida Prison</HEAD>
<DATELINE>INDIANTOWN, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   About 200 inmates suffered food
poisoning symptoms after eating a spaghetti dinner, and 21 of them
were escorted to the hospital in chains or handcuffs, the prison
said Sunday.
   Two prison employees also stricken with food poisoning after
Saturday night's meal at Martin Correctional Institution remained
in Martin Memorial Hospital Sunday, one of them in intensive care,
said prison Superintendent David Farcas. All but three of the
inmates were treated and released.
   State health officials planned to visit the prison near
Indiantown, about 25 miles northwest of West Palm Beach, on Monday
to determine the exact source of the outbreak, said Florida
Department of Corrections spokesman Bob MacMaster.
   ``The spaghetti, the old-fashioned, all-American spaghetti was
contaminated with food poisoning,'' Farcas said. ``We don't know
how or when it became contaminated,'' Farcas said.
   Inmates began complaining of diarrhea, vomiting and stomach
cramps at about 6 p.m., and about two hours later ``the staff
realized very clearly that we had a serious matter here,'' Farcas
said. ``Then by 9:30 all heck had broken loose.''
   Sheriff's deputies supplied a bus and escorted the worst cases
to the hospital in handcuffs or chains, he said.
   ``I just can't praise them all enough for their marvelous job of
responding,'' Farcas said. ``Their response circumvented further
incidents... you know, disturbances, riots, things like that.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0070 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 2243EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p AM-PoliticalBriefs     10-14 0367</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Political Briefs,0411</SECOND>
<HEAD>Political Briefs</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Former Sen. Lawton Chiles won the endorsement
Sunday of Florida's largest newspaper, The Miami Herald, over
Republican Gov. Bob Martinez, in the governor's race.
   The Herald said it endorsed Martinez four years ago because he
was prepared to provide mature leadership. The former Tampa mayor
became the first Republican to govern the state since
Reconstruction.
   ``The ensuing four years have proved the inadequacy of that
preparation and the tenuousness of that leadership,'' the newspaper
said. Instead of leading, Martinez settled for ``anti-tax
expediency interspersed with divisive appeals to various
narrow-interest constituencies.''
   The Herald said Chiles is the better choice on Nov. 6 because of
his ``outstanding record and positive campaign promise to banish
the state's deepening political cynicism'' and because Martinez
``has been a serious disappointment.''
   Chiles decided in 1987 against seeking a fourth term, saying
big-money politics left him burned out after 18 years in the U.S.
Senate.
   ---
   PORTLAND, Maine (AP) - U.S. Rep. Olympia Snowe, concerned about
an anti-incumbent sentiment among voters, went on the attack Sunday
against Democratic challenger Patrick McGowan in their first
debate.
   The six-term congresswoman accused McGowan of being ``a
political opportunist'' who would be tied to the Democratic
leadership that she blames for the country's budget crisis.
   McGowan, a five-term state representative, contended that Snowe,
as a member of Congress, was responsible for the nation's fiscal
crisis and that Maine voters are seeking ``fresh blood'' in
Congress.
   ``I think this country is falling apart economically and I think
it's because of people like you,'' McGowan contended. ``We are
leaving my children and your children the largest sea of red ink in
the history of the world and I think it's time to make some
changes.''
   Snowe countered that Senate Majority Leader George Mitchell of
Maine and the Democratic leadership were largely to blame for the
budget problems, and that McGowan would be beholden to his party's
leadership.
   ``Pat, you're going to be more of the same. You're an appendage
of Sen. Mitchell, she said.
   The debate was taped for broadcast Monday.
   ---
   SALEM, Ore. (AP) - Secretary of State Barbara Roberts suspended
her campaign for governor when her father, Bob Hughey, died Sunday.
   Roberts, a Democrat, is locked in a tight race with Republican
Dave Frohnmayer. Neil Goldschmidt, a Democrat, decided against
seeking a second term.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0071 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 2249EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-France-Lebanon     10-14 0155</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-France-Lebanon,0150</SECOND>
<HEAD>Lebanese Embassy Occupied by Aoun Supporters</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Lebanon, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   About 50 people who occupied the Lebanese Embassy
vowed to remain until the Lebanese government allows rebel Gen.
Michel Aoun to leave Beirut for asylum in France.
   The occupation, which began Saturday during a demonstration by
hundreds of Aoun supporters, is backed by Lebanon's Christian
ambassador to France, Johnny Abdo, an embassy spokesman said.
   Aoun took refuge in the French Embassy in Beirut on Saturday
after Syrian warplanes bombed his headquarters and troops loyal to
Lebanese President Elias Hrawi attacked his stronghold in East
Beirut.
   The French and Lebanese governments have been negotiating the
mutinous general's departure from Lebanon.
   Moslem leaders are said to be happy to let him go, but Aoun's
Christian rivals want him to be tried for insurrection and for
allegedly taking $75 million from the state treasury.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901014-0072 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-14-90 2300EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Haiti-Politics     10-14 0356</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Haiti-Politics,0406</SECOND>
<HEAD>Former Head of Tonton Macoutes Named Party Chief in Haiti</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MICHAEL NORTON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   PORT-AU-PRINCE, Haiti (AP) - The former chief of the fearsome
Tonton Macoutes paramilitary squads was named to head a new party
linked to supporters of the Duvalier family dictatorship.
   Roger Lafontant said he would file as the presidential candidate
of the Union for National Reconciliation Party before the Friday
deadline, but it was not certain if he would be allowed to run.
   The 1987 constitution gives the Electoral Council discretionary
power to bar candidates who were criminal supporters of past
dictatorships.
   ``I am the candidate,'' Lafontant said following a two-day party
convention that ended Sunday night.
   A former Interior and Defense Minister under ousted dictator
Jean-Claude Duvalier, Lafontant headed the dreaded Tonton Macoutes,
blamed for numerous murders and other human-rights violations.
   In a communique Friday, government prosecutor Bayard Vincent
said an arrest warrant charging Lafontant with plotting against
national security was issued July 10. But Lafontant said the
warrant, which has never been served, was illegal and had been
quashed in another judicial decision.
   ``I challenge anyone to prove I am guilty,'' Lafontant said.
   If the Electoral Council rejects Lafontant, he said the party
would decide on what steps to take.
   ``We believe in respect for the laws of the country to the
extent they apply to everyone. We will be violent towards no one,
on condition everyone is respected,'' Lafontant said to a cheering
crowd of about 1,000 at a night club outside the capital of
Port-au-Prince.
   Electoral Council secretary general Jean Casimir said he does
not have ``any special problem with Lafontant.''
   ``He will submit his file, and we will consider it on its
merits,'' said Casimir.
   There are about 20 presidential hopefuls for elections set for
Dec. 16. The voting is expected to be monitored by observers from
the Organization of American States, Caribbean nations and the
United Nations.
   The last attempt to hold elections, on Nov. 29, 1987, was
aborted when army-backed bands attacked and killed voters at the
poll.
   The president-elect will take office Feb. 7, 1991, on the fifth
anniversary of the overthrow of dictator Jean-Claude ``Baby Doc''
Duvalier. Duvalier fled to exile in France in 1986, ending 29 years
of rule by the Duvalier family.
   Ertha Pascal-Trouillot has led a provisional government since
March.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
</Collection>
