<Collection>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0001 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 0155EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-TyphoonOfelia 1stLd-Writethru a0535 06-24 0420</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Typhoon Ofelia, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0535,0432</SECOND>
<HEAD>Storm Slams Taiwan, Killing Seven; Heads for China</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: New throughout to UPDATE death toll to seven in Taiwan, 35
missing; Ofelia downgraded to tropical storm, heading for China. No
pickup.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>TAIPEI, Taiwan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Typhoon Ofelia was downgraded to a
tropical storm on Sunday, a day after it slammed into eastern
Taiwan with 85 mph winds, killing seven people and leaving 35
others missing.
   The storm also left 30 people dead in the Philippines.
   On Sunday, Ofelia was bearing down on the Chinese province of
Zhejiang, but its winds had weakened to 50 mph, forecasters said.
   Taiwan police said seven people drowned or died in landslides
and 35 others were missing in and around the eastern coastal city
of Hualien, 124 miles southeast of Taipei.
   Most of the missing were swept away by floods that inundated
more than 200 homes in villages, police said. Some villages were
under three feet of water, and authorities estimated property and
crop damage at more than $3.6 million.
   Two Panamanian ships were pounded by Ofelia off Hualien on
Saturday.
   The 10,890-ton freighter Cahaya broke up into three sections in
heavy seas, police reported. Its 24-member Indonesian crew was
rescued, they said.
   Another 28 crewmen from the Panamanian freighter Juliana were
rescued when their 7,000-ton vessel broke loose from its moorning
and ran aground, the officials said.
   Taiwan police said air and road links in the county were
disrupted by landslides and flooding from the storm. They reported
that 18 inches of rain was recorded in one area in a 24-hour span.
   Authorities canceled all domestic flights.
   Ofelia also buffeted the island's north and south with strong
winds, but no damage or casualties were reported.
   The storm forced 84,600 people to flee their homes in the
Philippines as it swept through Luzon island with rain and strong
winds, according to the Red Cross and other relief agencies.
   The hardest-hit community in the Philippines was La Union, 150
miles northwest of Manila, where at least 22 people drowned or were
crushed to death in landslides, relief officials said.
   In Pangasinan, west of La Union, two people were electrocuted.
In the Manila suburb of Pasig, three children died when a concrete
wall collapsed on their shanty, officials said. A 4-year-old girl
died in a landslide in the mountain resort city of Baguio.
   Two other people were killed by lightning during a thunderstorm
unleashed by Ofelia in Lanao del Sur province on Mindanao island,
about 520 miles south of Manila.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0002 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 0543EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i BC-Finland-Hijack 2ndLd-Writethru a0651 06-24 0383</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Finland-Hijack, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0651,0389</SECOND>
<HEAD>Soviet Airliner Hijacked to Finland; Hijacker Surrenders</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 6 grafs to UPDATE with asylum request, hijacker's
age, bomb threat, CORRECTS destination of plane, adds byline. Pick
up 6th graf pvs, `Last Tuesday...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By MATTI HUUHTANEN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HELSINKI, Finland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A young hijacker surrendered to police
Sunday after forcing a Soviet airliner on a domestic flight to land
in Finland, authorities said. The 72 passengers and six crew
members were released unharmed.
   Police Commissioner Pentti Luntiala, speaking to reporters,
quoted the 21-year-old man as saying he wanted to seek political
asylum and go to the United States.
   It was the second Soviet hijack incident in Finland in a week
and the third in a Scandinavian country in two weeks. There was
also a fourth incident involving the commandeering of a Soviet
aircraft with no passengers aboard.
   The hijacker commandeered the twin-engine Tupolev 134, bound
from the Estonian capital of Tallinn to Lvov in the Ukraine, by
saying he carried a bomb in his luggage, an official at Helsinki's
international airport said.
   The official, terminal duty officer Pirjo Lahteela, said police
were searching the plane for explosives and the hijacker was being
interrogated.
   The Aeroflot airliner landed at Helsinki's international airport
at about 8:30 a.m. (1:30 a.m. EDT) time, authorities said.
   Last Tuesday, a 20-year-old hijacker forced a Soviet airliner
with 60 people aboard to land in Finland and asked for political
asylum. No one was injured in that incident. Moscow asked Helsinki
to extradite the hijacker, identified as Oleg Kozlov.
   A day earlier, a 29-year-old pilot, Valeri Yuricevic,
commandeered a 12-seat Antonov-2 aircraft in Izmail, near the
Ukrainian port of Odessa, and flew to Turkey, where he asked for
asylum. There was no one else on board.
   On June 9, Dimitry Semionov, a 17-year-old Soviet youth, used a
fake hand grenade to hijack a plane carrying 121 passengers during
a flight from Minsk to Murmansk. That plane was forced to fly to
Stockholm, where Semionov surrendered.
   The youth said later through a lawyer he had acted on impulse
after a family quarrel and wanted to go to a ``free country.''
Semionov was arraigned in a Stockholm court and could face up to
four years in prison, depending on the results of psychiatric tests.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0003 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 0630EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i BC-PacificTyphoon     06-24 0219</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Pacific Typhoon,0225</SECOND>
<HEAD>High Wind, Heavy Rain Leave Boy Dead, Palau Battered</HEAD>
<DATELINE>AGANA, Guam (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   High wind and heavy rain from Typhoon Percy
battered Palau on Sunday night, leaving a child dead and knocking
out utility service, a newspaper reported.
   A young boy died Saturday night when he was swept by rain into
mangrove trees near his home in the cluster of islands that
comprise Palau, the Pacific Daily News said.
   The storm passed 90 miles north of Palau, which is 800 miles
south of Agana, said Navy Ensign Richard Jeffries of the Joint
Typhoon Warning Center.
   The typhoon moved west-northwest at 16 mph on a path that could
take it between Taiwan and the Philippines in four or five days,
Jeffries said.
   Wind gusts of up to 103 mph blew off tin roofs of many buildings
and knocked radio and television stations off the air, the Pacific
Daily News said.
   Airline flights into the republic were canceled, the newspaper
said.
   Earlier Sunday, the typhoon's winds battered Yap Island in the
neighboring Federated States of Micronesia, collapsing about 30
houses and damaging banana and coconut plantations, police said.
   There were no reports of injuries on Yap, and the winds and
accompanying heavy rains posed no problems for the island's
electric and water systems, Officer Kenneth Chugrad said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0004 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 0646EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i BC-UN-IranQuake     06-24 0428</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-UN-Iran Quake,0445</SECOND>
<HEAD>UN: Iranian Authorities Fear Death Toll May Reach 50,000</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By HANNS NEUERBOURG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>GENEVA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Iranian authorities fear that the death toll in
Thursday's devastating earthquake may reach 50,000, a senior U.N.
relief official said Sunday.
   Previous figures on the number of deaths had varied, but
officials had said earlier an estimated 40,000 were feared dead.
   M'Hamed Essaafi also said parts of the stricken area were still
inaccessible because roads in the Caspian Sea region were blocked
by landslides and rain.
   Essaafi spoke at a press briefing after meeting with the head of
the Iranian mission to the U.N. office in Geneva, Ambassador Sirous
Nasseri. He said Nasseri again stressed that Iran was more urgently
in need of relief supplies than in rescue personnel.
   He said the number of injured was still believed to be about
100,000, but there was no confirmed figure yet. He said the
homeless numbered about half a million.
   About 6,000 injured people are being treated in Tehran
hospitals, according to the Iranian authorities. Hospitals in the
affected provinces are filled to capacity, Essaafi added, quoting
official Iranian reports.
   Essaafi, named by U.N. Secretary General Javier Perez de Cuellar
to oversee the international earthquake relief effort, said he did
not think there was any effort by the Iranians to underreport the
casualty figure.
   An Iranian resistance movement, Mujahedeen Khalq, had made such
an accusation.
   Essaafi said that during the next two days at least 32 relief
flights from nine countries were scheduled to land at Tehran
airport.
   He said they included 11 planes from West Germany carrying 145
tons of supplies, plus a field hospital with two medial teams, and
nine flights from Turkey.
   Other flights announced to the office of the U.N. Disaster
Relief Coordinator, UNDRO, were to arrive from Bangladesh, Japan,
Canada, Cuba, Czechoslovakia Pakistan, Switzerland and Britain, he
said..
   Iran also asked for help from U.N. experts in improving
communications, which continued to pose problems in the quake zone.
   The International Red Cross said Friday Iran expressly stated it
did not want satellite communications equipment to be included in
the relief supplies.
   The U.N. official, who will leave for Tehran on Monday, said
that the situation was being ``handed rather well by Iran.''
   Since the predawn quake on Thursday, more than 200 aftershocks
have hit the region, the biggest registering 4.2 on the Richter
scale and rocking the Tarom-e Olia region about 125 miles northwest
of Tehran, the official Islamic Republic News Agency said.
   Thursday's quake was at least 7.3 on the Richter scale.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0005 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 1006EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i BC-Iran-Quake 1stLd-Writethru a0656 06-24 0477</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Iran-Quake, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0656,0487</SECOND>
<HEAD>Aftershock Hits Devastated Area</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 7th graf, `The aftershock...' with 1 graf to ADD details
on aftershock. Pick up 8th pvs, `Rasht is...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By SLOBODAN LEKIC</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>RUDBAR, Iran (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The strongest aftershock in three days hit a
quake-devastated northern province Sunday, and a moderate
earthquake was reported in southern Iran.
   The stench of decomposing bodies hung over Gilan and Zanjan
provinces, the two hardest hit in Thursday's earthquake, as
rescuers aided by police dogs pulled corpses from the rubble and
quickly buried them in mass graves to stem the outbreak of disease.
   A senior U.N. relief official said Sunday in Geneva that
authorities fear the death toll may reach 50,000. Some official
Iranian reports have set the toll at 40,000.
   Tehran Times, the nation's leading English-language newspaper,
quoted an unnamed official as saying 50,000 people died and 200,000
were injured in the quake. He said even that was a conservative
estimate because ``the figures are quoted taking account only of
those who have been registered officially as dead or wounded.''
   ``There are areas where bodies were buried without counting
them,'' he was quoted as saying.
   Tehran University's Geophysics Center reported 60 aftershocks in
the northern provinces, the strongest of which jolted Rasht,
capital of Gilan province, at 1:16 p.m. (5:46 a.m. EDT) Sunday. It
measured 5.7 on the Richter scale.
   The aftershock was the worst since several Thursday shortly
following the quake. IRNA said details of casualties or damage from
the aftershock were not immediately available, but ``the
Rasht-Rudbar road, which had just been reopened, was once again
blocked by the latest tremor which caused a mountain slide.''
   Rasht is 35 miles north of Rudbar, which is on the border
between Gilan and Zanjan provinces.
   The Geophysics Center also reported a moderate earthquake
measuring 4.9 on the Richter scale in southern Iran at 8.39 a.m.
(1:09 p.m.). It caused no casualties or damage. No further details
were available.
   The center, in a statement carried by the official Islamic
Republic News Agency, said 360 tremors have struck northern Iran
since the quake.
   The aftershocks have caused massive landslides, blocking many
roads leading to demolished villages on the northern edge of Gilan,
on the Caspian Sea.
   IRNA, monitored in Cyprus, said: ``More than 72 hours after the
horrifying earthquake, many villages in the mountainous region
which have been leveled remain inaccessible.''
   The agency quoted a survivor from Ab-bor village in Zanjan as
saying: ``So many bodies have perished under the rubble. They have
not been retrieved or buried.
   ``The whole area is stinking because of the decaying corpses
which make rescue operations even more difficult,'' the survivor,
identified as Ahmad Ali, was quoted as saying.
   The Richter scale is a gauge of the energy released by an
earthquake, as measured by the ground motion recorded on a
seismograph.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0006 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 1139EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--PenguinStampede     06-24 0176</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Penguin Stampede,0180</SECOND>
<HEAD>7,000 Penguins Die in Mystery Stampede</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HOBART, Tasmania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   King penguins at a rookery on a nearby
island stampeded, killing 7,000 of the birds, and officials said
Sunday they were investigating the mysterious occurrence.
   ``We don't know at this stage why they stampeded _ we have not
observed this type of behavior before,'' a spokesman for the
Australian State Parks Wildlife and Heritage Ministry said on
condition of anonymity.
   The stampede occurred on Macquarie Island, which is midway
between Australia and Antarctica and part of Tasmania, an
Australian state.
   The parks spokesman said about 6,000 chicks and 800 to 1,000
adults were found dead about three weeks ago on the island.
   ``There was no one in the area at the time, and we have ruled
out earthquakes,'' he said. ``There is a lot of seismic activity on
Macquarie Island, but there was no activity on that day.''
   Macquarie Island's Lusitiana Bay is home to hundreds of
thousands of birds and the site of one of the world's biggest king
penguin rookeries.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0007 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 1139EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--Jordan-Libya     06-24 0108</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Jordan-Libya,0111</SECOND>
<HEAD>Jordan Restores Diplomatic Ties With Libya, Names Ambassador</HEAD>
<DATELINE>AMMAN, Jordan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Jordan on Sunday announced the appointment
of an ambassador to Libya, formally ending a six-year diplomatic
rift with the northern African Arab country.
   The official Jordanian news agency Petra said Prime Minister
Mudar Badran named Hisham Muheisen as ambassador.
   Muheisen had led a senior Jordanian delegation to Tripoli in
April to reopen the Jordanian Embassy there for the first time
since the Arab nations severed diplomatic relations in 1984.
   Jordan closed its embassy that year after Libyan students
attacked the building during demonstrations protesting reported
efforts by Jordan to negotiate peace with Israel.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0008 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 1140EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--LoserDog     06-24 0139</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Loser Dog,0142</SECOND>
<HEAD>Prince Edward Sees His Greyhound Run Second</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A touted greyhound part-owned by Prince Edward
finished second in the Greyhound Derby, dog racing's richest prize.
   Queen Elizabeth's youngest son was at Wimbledon Stadium Saturday
night to see his dog, Druids Johno, the 4-7 favorite, beaten by 8-1
shot Slippy Blue.
   Slippy Blue lost two heats to Druids Johno but ran the final
525-yard circuit in 28.7 seconds for the $69,200 first prize.
   Edward, 26, said he would donate his share of the $13,800
second-place winnings to a fund for injured victims of an Irish
Republican Army bombing of the military music school. Ten people
died in the 1989 attack.
   Edward dropped out of military training to take a backstage job
in the London theater. He owns the dog with Irish trainer Patsy
Byrne.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0009 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 1144EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Germany-Europe Bjt   06-24 0760</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Germany-Europe, Bjt,0786</SECOND>
<HEAD>German Economic Merger a Double-Edged Sword For Europe</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By COTTEN TIMBERLAKE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The economic merger of the Germanys on July 1
probably will be a double-edged sword for the rest of Europe.
   Experts feel it will spur general economic growth and speed the
march toward a single European market, but also may give West
Germany, already the strongest economy by far, even more influence
over the continent's economic affairs.
   The Germans believe they have a strategy that will merge the two
economies with minimum shock to the rest of Europe, but there are
unknowns.
   If the union increases inflation, German interest rates may rise
and the other Western European economies, linked in an
exchange-rate system, may have to follow.
   The economic merger is the first major step toward reunification
of East and West Germany.
   On July 1, the West German mark becomes the currency of East
Germany and the Germanys will merge their economic machinery to
create what their treaty calls ``identical social market systems.''
   That means East Germany's communist economic regulations will be
replaced by West Germany's corporate, union and welfare practices.
   ``Overall, it should provide a bit of a spur of growth around
Europe over the longer term,'' said Stephen King, international
economist with the London investment firm James Capel and Co. ``It
should be good for the other European export sectors.''
   Britain's National Institute of Economic and Social Research
said in a report: ``The rest of Europe is expected to benefit both
from higher demand in Germany and also marginally because of
increased centrally planned economies' imports.''
   Neighboring Holland, which sells one-fourth of its exports to
Germany, expects to benefit even if unification proves bumpy.
   ``In the long run, it will be a boon for the Dutch,'' said Chen
Ie Lie, an analyst for Banque Paribas Amsterdam. ``People can't do
without things like cheese, poultry and pork.''
   More truck drivers could be employed in hauling foreign goods
from the Dutch port of Rotterdam, Europe's busiest, to Germany.
   There also are worries.
   Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher of Britain said in mid-June
that a unified Germany within a federal Europe ``would be dominant
both in numbers and political and economic power.''
   Asked whether that worried her, Mrs. Thatcher said, ``Yes ...
and I think many people in Europe are a little bit apprehensive
about a unified Germany.''
   King said: ``Quite clearly, the other Europeans are worried
about having such a large Germany in the center of Europe.
   ``There is of course the fear that Germany's economy makes it
much more politically powerful as a whole and raises its prestige
and raises its power in the European Community.''
   A united Germany will have a population of nearly 80 million.
West Germany's gross national product last year was $1.2 trillion,
more than 25 percent greater than second-place France.
   The central Bundesbank, with its traditionally tight,
inflation-fighting monetary policy, already dominates European
monetary affairs.
   Unification of Germany within the context of Western European
integration greatly complicates the economic and political issues.
   In 1992, the 12 European Community nations are to scrap trade
barriers and become a single market.
   Germany and France want a single European currency and a single
central bank. Britain is opposed, but the National Institute report
said monetary integration appeared to have gained support in recent
months.
   Peter Pietsch, an economist with Commerzbank in Frankfurt, said:
``Of course Germany has a big economic importance and the
importance will grow. I don't see how this would be a bad
influence.''
   ``We want to be a group of countries with the same target and
the same goal'' of low inflation, he said in an interview. ``We are
European, we feel European. I think that is much more important
than the isolated importance of one country.''
   King said France and the Netherlands hope an integrated Europe
will spread power more evenly, but Germany ``would like to impose
more strongly a Bundesbank on the whole of Europe and essentially
make a deutsche mark bloc.'' Hans Jaeckel, senior German economist
for the private forecasting firm DRI Europe in Frankfurt, said
European integration should be hastened to create a ``less
German-dominated'' Europe.
   John Major, Britain's chancellor of the exchequer, takes the
opposite view.
   ``There are those who see in the hectic pace of change in the
East a reason for urging similarly hectic change within the
Community,'' he told the German Chamber of Industry and Commerce in
London. ``Speed is of no advantage if you go in the wrong
direction. Better to build slowly and well.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0010 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 1144EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u p AM-MichiganGovernor Bjt   06-24 0749</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Michigan Governor, Bjt,750</SECOND>
<HEAD>Democrats Nervous About Book by Governor's Ex-Wife</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JEFF HOLYFIELD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LANSING, Mich. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Republicans can't wait to get their hands
on an upcoming book by the ex-wife of Democratic Gov. James
Blanchard. Nervous Democrats wish they could put it on hold until
after the November elections.
   Paula Blanchard says both sides are overreacting. Her book
covering the 1987 breakup of her 21-year marriage to Blanchard is
due out in July.
   Blanchard, who last year married Janet Fox, his former
secretary, is favored for re-election this fall over likely GOP
opponent John Engler, the state Senate majority leader.
   Paula Blanchard's book _ ``'Til Politics Do Us Part'' _ is a
question mark in the campaign, but Michigan's former first lady
predicts it won't affect the election.
   ``This book is not a kiss-and-tell book,'' she said. ``This book
is not an exercise in vengefulness or anything like that. It's the
story of my life as a political spouse and the choices I made and
why I made the choices.''
   Paula Blanchard supports her ex-husbands's re-election bid and
predicts he will win ``based on his solid record of performance.''
   Engler offers a different assessment.
   He describes Michigan as overtaxed, sputtering economically, and
in need of a new leader. He contends Blanchard masks an average
record with a high-powered public relations machine.
   ``Just think what the right man could do,'' is the theme of his
campaign.
   Engler himself is divorced, and his ex-wife, Colleen, also has
written a book that touches on the breakup of their marriage.
   Colleen Engler, a former state legislator and onetime
gubernatorial candidate who works for the Commerce Department in
Washington, said she doesn't have a publisher yet.
   ``It hasn't even been edited yet. An editor might say, `You
don't want any of this stuff about John Engler in there,''' she
said. ``My book is about running for governor in 1986 and then
running for lieutenant governor.''
   Blanchard's divorce made front-page news, as did his remarriage,
but there has been no backlash from voters. In fact, the newlyweds
got a warm welcome earlier this month on a two-day tour to announce
his bid for a third four-year term.
   Paula Blanchard said the governor and a number of his associates
asked her to hold up her book until after the election.
   ``The curious thing is none of them have read it,'' she said.
``They were asking me to hold it based on speculation and
assumptions.''
   ``I've encouraged Jim to read the book. After he does that, his
concerns about it will be minimized. He will be able to see it's a
book that puts a lot into perspective,'' she said. ``It goes
directly from my heart to the page.''
   Blanchard is unopposed in Michigan's Aug. 7 primary, while
Engler is expected to easily defeat tax fighter John Lauve. A March
poll found Blanchard leading Engler 51 percent to 31 percent, but
the lesser-known Engler said that was to be expected early in the
campaign.
   Engler launched his campaign in February and immediately began
airing television ads aimed at boosting his name identification.
   Democrats say Engler's leadership is untested and focus on
Blanchard's record in erasing a $1.7 billion debt, his efforts to
diversify the state's economy, improve education, and fight crime
while keeping the state budget balanced.
   The governor's first TV ad, unveiled last month, touted
Blanchard as tough on crime and set out his campaign theme,
``Tough. Tested. Trusted.''
   The ad closed with a white guard yelling at a black inmate at
Michigan's boot camp prison for non-violent young offenders, who
volunteer for its military-style discipline.
   The ad was aired everywhere in the state except Detroit, which
is two-thirds black. Engler's campaign director, Dan Pero,
denounced it as racist, and some black leaders and lawmakers agreed.
   The ad later aired in Detroit. Blanchard defended it as showing
a real answer to a tough problem and dismissed the whole
controversy as being manufactured by Republicans.
   The flap ended quickly and Michigan Democratic Party Chairman
Tom Lewand said it was ``well behind us and not something to be
concerned about.''
   But Engler sees cracks in Blanchard's public image, and cites
the boot camp ad, tight budgets ahead and 78-year-old Lt. Gov.
Martha Griffiths' decision not to retire _ which came as a surprise
to the governor.
   ``The carefully constructed facade is in tatters,'' Engler said.
``This is a very isolated administration that isn't as finely tuned
and well-oiled as people would believe.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0011 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 1145EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Iran-US     06-24 0292</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Iran-US,0301</SECOND>
<HEAD>Radical Paper Blames U.S., In Part, For Quake Damage</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Iran-Quake, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TEHRAN, Iran (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An anti-American newspaper in Iran said
Sunday the United States is partly to blame for the death of tens
of thousands of people in last week's earthquake.
   The ``criminal role of America in Iran's past became evident
once again in the recent earthquake,'' the Jomhuri Islami said in
an editorial reported by the official Islamic Republic News Agency.
   ``Our people, even under the rubble, chant `Death to America'
and pray to God to cut off the hands of the United States ... even
those hands stretched out to help,'' it said.
   It argued that by ``plundering Iran's oil and other resources''
for 25 years, the United States had prevented the use of even a
small part of the national wealth for urban development projects
and ``advanced (anti-seismic) building construction systems.''
   ``Even after its expulsion from Iran, the U.S. government by
imposing economic sanctions and launching several other plots,
halted the renovation of the country,'' the editorial added.
   The newspaper was implying that with these actions the United
States had blocked the diversion of funds to earthquake safety
measures.
   ``If the United States has real humanitarian objectives and
intended to help the Iranian nation, it should do only one thing,
stop hatching plots,'' the newspaper said.
   It called on Iranians to reject relief offers by the United
States and ``other governments whose hands are stained with the
blood of the Iranian people.''
   Iran, at odds with the United States since the 1979 seizure of
hostages at the U.S. Embassy in Tehran, has said it would welcome
relief from the American Red Cross and other U.S. humanitarian
groups. The two nations have no diplomatic ties.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0012 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 1146EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AMs-DrugTenants     06-24 0574</FIRST>
<SECOND>AMs-Drug Tenants,540</SECOND>
<HEAD>Nationwide Raids To Hit Public-Housing Drug Dealers This Week</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JAMES ROWLEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Public housing tenants known to deal drugs
will be kicked out of their apartments during nationwide raids set
to begin this week even if they haven't been convicted of a crime,
officials say.
   Federal marshals are scheduled Monday to begin raiding
apartments in housing projects located in as many as 22 cities
where the holder of the lease is a known drug dealer and could be
prosecuted for two felonies, officials said.
   The tenant and his or her family may be kicked out of the
apartment even if the person has not yet been convicted of a drug
crime under the program first announced last month by Housing
Secretary Jack Kemp, officials said.
   The government calls the actions ``leasehold forfeitures'' _ not
evictions. The plan already has stirred up a legal challenge in one
city.
   The forfeiture of public-housing leases by known drug dealers is
specifically authorized by asset-forfeiture provisions of the 1988
Anti-Drug Abuse Act, government officials say. The same provisions
enable federal prosecutors to seize boats, cars and cash of drug
dealers awaiting trial.
   In this case, the lease is the asset to be seized.
   The raids are scheduled to be conducted in cities where
authorities have identified drug dealing in housing projects as a
significant problem.
   The targeted housing projects are in some of the nation's
largest cities _ New York, Los Angeles, Chicago _ as well as
smaller municipalities such as Chandler, Ariz., Tacoma, Wash., and
Frederick, Md., according to a list obtained by The Associated
Press.
   Bob Nipp, a spokesman for the Department of Housing and Urban
Development, declined to comment on the planned raids. When Kemp
first announced the plan, he declined to identify the cities where
housing projects would be raided.
   Civil libertarians have criticized the planned raids, saying
they will violate the principle that a person is innocent of
criminal wrongdoing until proven guilty.
   Legal aid lawyers in Richmond, Va., _ one of the targeted cities
_ last week obtained a temporary restraining order from a federal
judge barring the government from removing tenants without giving
them advance notice and an opportunity to be heard.
   The order by U.S. District Judge Richard L. Williams, in effect,
affords tenants some of the due process of eviction proceedings. It
only applies to the Richmond area but legal aid lawyers are
expected to seek similar court rulings in other cities.
   Under guidelines adopted by the Department of Housing and Urban
Development and the Justice Department, only apartments that are
notorious and open sites of drug distribution and leased by known
drug dealers will be raided, officials said.
   The guidelines also state that authorities should have ``proof
beyond a reasonable doubt'' that the leaseholder committed at least
two felony drug crimes and will face prosecution, said the
officials, who spoke on condition of anonymity.
   It was not known if authorities also planned to serve search
warrants to seek possible evidence of drug activity.
   The plan calls for using local social service agencies to
relocate children and elderly people who will be displaced from
their homes by the raids, officials said.
   Public housing projects in the following cities also have been
targeted: Washington; Atlanta; Dallas; Baltimore; Hartford, Conn.;
Newark, N.J.; Indianapolis; Flint, Mich.; Charleston, S.C.; Macon,
Ga.; El Paso, Texas; Kansas City; Omaha; Portland, Ore.; and St.
Louis, Mo.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0013 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 1146EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-BlackbirdDispute     06-24 0735</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Blackbird Dispute,740</SECOND>
<HEAD>You Thought the Blackbird Was Retired? Think Again</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DONNA CASSATA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   When last seen, the SR-71 Blackbird spy plane
was slicing through a dreary March sky for a record-setting, final,
coast-to-coast flight that touched off regrets and doubts over its
retirement.
   The Air Force and Congress had decided several months earlier
that the reconnaissance aircraft which provided unsurpassed
snooping during the Cold War had become too costly and that
satellites could do the job easily.
   Shortly after its 68-minute, 17-second trip from Los Angeles to
Washington, Blackbird No. 17972 was shipped off to the Smithsonian
Institution.
   But the Blackbird wasn't quite dead yet.
   Tucked away in the report accompanying a $4 billion spending
bill that President Bush signed last month was a provision telling
the Pentagon to maintain at least six of the spy planes for use in
the event of a national crisis.
   ``The above outlined program should not be considered a charter
for re-establishment of SR-71 flight operations which were
terminated as a part of the fiscal 1990 budget deliberations,'' the
report said.
   Rather, the intent of the lawmakers' action was to ensure that
the National Aeronautics and Space Administration, which will
receive three of the planes, has enough funds to conduct
aeronautics research and that the Air Force could begin flight
operations within 90 days of an emergency.
   The report even designated the aircraft by tail numbers for the
contingency program.
   Although the report provision is non-binding, Pentagon refusal
to adhere to the language would be too costly in the tenuous
relationship between Congress and the Bush administration.
   Thus, behind-the-scenes negotiations have been going on between
the Air Force and several congressional committees over the report
language. And the cost to maintain the black, dagger-shaped planes
is a major issue.
   Lawmakers and congressional sources, who requested anonymity,
said Air Force Gen. Michael J. Dugan told members of Congress that
the cost of maintenance would total $30 million.
   Dugan is commander of the Air Force in Europe and President
Bush's nominee for chief of staff, a selection the Senate Armed
Services Committee approved last week.
   The report said the Air Force should use $6 million of money it
already has for upkeep of the aircraft.
   Shortly before Pentagon and congressional negotiators sought a
common ground on the issue, Defense Secretary Dick Cheney staked
out his position in testimony before the Senate Appropriations
defense subcommittee.
   ``We can park them,'' Cheney told the panel earlier this month.
``We can't bring them back within 90 days without going back and
spending a lot of money to reconstitute at least a portion of
manpower and maintenance and so forth and recertify pilots.''
   Dugan, in his Senate confirmation hearing, complained of the
``conflicting guidance from the Congress'' on the issue.
   ``The resources to get the five or six airplanes ... operational
within a 90-day period _ those resources are considerably more than
made available,'' Dugan told the Armed Services panel.
   Rep. Joseph McDade of Pennsylvania, ranking Republican on the
House Appropriations subcommittee on defense, said lawmakers did
not believe the report provision was ``an unreasonable
disposition'' for the spy plane.
   The Blackbird regularly flew missions over heavily defended
North Vietnam and provided intelligence in many other regions,
including the Middle East, China and the Persian Gulf.
   The plane can outrun the fastest fighters and has never been
shot down. Built to withstand temperatures of more than 800 degrees
Fahrenheit, its skin is a titanium alloy instead of the aluminum
used on most airplanes. It can sustain a speed of Mach 3, or three
times the speed of sound, but its maximum speed is classified.
   McDade noted that Cheney, during his tenure as a Wyoming
congressman on the House Intelligence Committee, had opposed the
Blackbird.
   ``Cheney always felt the system was not a cost-effective system.
He didn't think it justified the expenditures,'' McDade said in an
interview last week.
   Congressional sources said the provision in the spending bill
report was perceived by the Armed Services, Intelligence and
Appropriations committees as the best opportunity to resolve the
issue and negotiations were going well.
   If they fail, however, the question of the highflying Blackbird
is certain to surface in next year's defense bills, which Congress
will begin crafting later this summer.
   ``They're not going to re-create the SR-71, but it's not going
away lock, stock and barrel,'' one congressional source said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0014 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 1149EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SouthAfrica     06-24 0474</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-South Africa,0489</SECOND>
<HEAD>Right-Wing Groups Join Forces, Pledge Support For Extremist</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GREG MYRE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JOHANNESBURG, South Africa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two extreme right-wing groups
signed a cooperation agreement Sunday in the latest effort by
pro-apartheid whites to build opposition to reforms instituted by
President F.W. de Klerk.
   The groups also pledged support for a white fugitive who has
declared war on the government.
   Both de Klerk and African National Congress leader Nelson
Mandela have warned that heavily armed right-wing extremists could
undermine efforts to launch black-white negotiations on a new
constitution and ending apartheid.
   The Boer Resistance Movement and the Boer State Party announced
Sunday they would work together to establish a homeland for the
Boers, or Afrikaners, the country's Dutch-descended settlers who
account for 3 million of the 5 million whites.
   The two groups, which are believed to have several thousand
followers among them, are among several right-wing organizations
that favor strict segregation and oppose all concessions to South
Africa's 28 million blacks.
   The organizations consider the ANC, the country's largest black
opposition group, a communist-led terrorist movement.
   The right-wing groups ``promised all possible legal support''
for Piet Rudolph, a member of the Boer State Party who declared war
on de Klerk's government last week.
   Rudolph has been in hiding since he allegedly stole arms and
ammunition from an air force base in April. He made his declaration
of war in a videotape sent to a newspaper. The government has
offered a $19,000 reward for information leading to Rudolph's
arrest.
   The two Afrikaner groups said they had established a fund to
help ``all the other unknown Piet Rudolphs ... who have to flee
from the de Klerk-Mandela Communists.''
   Right-wingers have been threatening the government for months.
Events of the past week provided the strongest indications yet that
such groups are ready to act.
   Among them:
   _Two offices belonging to de Klerk's National Party were bombed
Friday night, causing extensive damage but no injuries. No one has
claimed responsibility, but government officials say right-wing
whites are the most likely suspects.
   _An Afrikaans-language newspaper reported Friday that white
extremists were planning to assassinate Mandela and de Klerk and
poison drinking water in Soweto, the huge black township outside
Johannesburg. Police arrested 11 whites for questioning, but all
were released Friday and no charges have been filed.
   Most political analysts believe that an increasing number of
whites are joining right-wing groups in response to de Klerk's
reforms. The pro-apartheid Conservative Party captured 31 percent
of the vote in white elections last September and would probably
improve on that figure if polls were held at present, analysts say.
   De Klerk says he wants to end racial discrimination in South
Africa and negotiate a constitution that allows blacks and whites
to share power. Under the current apartheid system, whites control
the government and the economy.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0015 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 1155EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SriLanka     06-24 0487</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Sri Lanka,0500</SECOND>
<HEAD>27 Killed As Gov't Troops Advance Toward Town `Waiting to Die'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PATRICK CRUEZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>COLOMBO, Sri Lanka (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Government troops hunting for Tamil
rebels crept forward Sunday from two sides towards war-ravaged
Batticaloa, and residents said the city was ``waiting to die.''
   A Defense Ministry statement said 16 soldiers and 11 separatists
were killed in fighting that has already left more than 1,400
combatants and an unknown number of civilians dead.
   Residents of Batticaloa, on the eastern coast, said they feared
reprisals by government troops, who are mostly Sinhalese, because
the rebels burned police stations and Sinhalese shops before
fleeing into the jungles.
   ``We are like a drum, beaten on both sides. First the Tigers
threatened and killed many of us, and now government soldiers are
coming. We can only pray,'' said a hotel owner on condition of
anonymity.
   The city has been without electricity and transport since the
fighting began.
   Military officials, speaking on condition of anonymity, said the
troops were approaching Batticaloa from Chenkaladi in the north and
Kalmunai in the south, and were expected to reach the town early
Monday.
   The troops are mainly Sinhalese, who make up about 75 percent of
Sri Lanka's 16 million people. Tamil rebels say the Sinhalese
discriminate in hiring and education against mainly Hindu Tamils,
who make up 18 percent of the population.
   Batticaloa, 135 miles northeast of Colombo, was the first
flashpoint of the fighting that erupted two weeks ago, ending a
13-month cease-fire between the government and the militants of the
Liberation Tigers of Tamil Eelam.
   According to the Defense Ministry statement, nine soldiers died
Saturday when Tamil rebels blew up a motorized military patrol near
Weli Oya village in the north. Another seven soldiers and 11 rebels
died when government troops attempted, but failed, to reach the
besieged Kankesanthurai naval base on Jaffna peninsula.
   On Saturday, troops destroyed five rebel bunkers and cleared
land mines as they moved towards Batticaloa, the military officials
said.
   A Tamil reporter in the city described Batticaloa's 200,000
people _ 85 percent Tamil and the rest Moslem _ as ``populating a
city waiting to die.''
   ``Batticaloa has a whole lot of scars, a burnt Buddhist temple
and a police station, and the gutted remains of eight Sinhalese
shops. The Sinhalese soldiers are going to be pretty mad when they
get here,'' said the reporter, speaking on the condition he was not
identified further.
   On Saturday, President Ranasinghe Premadasa, the architect of
the cease-fire forged in May 1989 with the rebels, said he still
hoped for a negotiated settlement.
   Several Tamil militant groups had been fighting for a separate
homeland in the northeast since 1983, but most gave up their
weapons after a 1987 peace accord. The Tamil Tigers, after a brief
acceptance, reneged on the pact and began attacking Indian soldiers.
   More than 11,000 people have been killed in the seven-year
revolt.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0016 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 1158EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Lebanon-Bomb     06-24 0141</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lebanon-Bomb,0145</SECOND>
<HEAD>Car Bomb Kills Amal Official</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SIDON, Lebanon (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A booby-trapped car exploded Sunday near
this southern port city, killing the regional security commander of
the Syrian-backed Shiite Moslem Amal militia, police said.
   Three aides of the slain leader were wounded in the blast and
rushed to a hospital in Sidon, 25 miles south of Beirut, the police
said.
   The car blew up when the commander, Hussein Hijazi, started the
ignition, a police spokesman said. The car was parked outside
Hijazi's base in Ghaziyeh, three miles south of Sidon, provincial
capital of southern Lebanon.
   No one claimed responsibility for the attack.
   Amal has been engaged in a three-year power struggle with the
pro-Iranian fundamentalist Hezbollah, or Party of God. More than
1,000 people have been killed in intermittent clashes between the
two factions in Beirut and southern Lebanon.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0017 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 1206EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Colombia     06-24 0316</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Colombia,0327</SECOND>
<HEAD>Gunmen Storm Tavern, Killing 19</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By STEVEN GUTKIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOGOTA, Colombia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Asssailants toting automatic machine
guns stormed a tavern near the cocaine trafficking center of
Medellin, killing 19 people and wounding at least four, police said
Sunday.
   The massacre occurred Saturday night in Envigado, a Medellin
suburb long considered the headquarters of the powerful Medellin
cocaine cartel.
   Twenty armed men entered the tavern, shooting indiscriminately
at customers drinking and listening to music, a Medellin police
spokesman said in a telephone interview.
   He said police did not know the motives for the murders, nor who
was responsible. All 20 assailants escaped without being caught,
the spokesmen said on condition of anonymity.
   In the past, similar violence in Medellin has been attributed to
fighting between rival gangs working for the cocaine barons.
   In another development, two more policemen were assassinated
Saturday in Medellin, bringing to 127 the number of law officers
slain in the city so far this year, the police spokesman said.
   The Medellin drug cartel has commissioned young killers, often
riding motorcycles, to shoot policemen throughout the city. It
reportedly pays $4,300 for each killing.
   Medellin, a city of about 3 million, has been placed under
virtual army occupation because of bombings and assassinations by
drug traffickers.
   In the past two months, authorities have sent 1,500 new soldiers
and policemen to reinforce Medellin's security force. More than
4,000 policemen are patrolling the streets.
   In August, the government declared war on traffickers following
the assassination of anti-drug crusader Luis Carlos Galan.
   Since then, more than 15 people have been extradited to the
United States to face drug charges.
   In December, police killed the No. 2 leader of the Medellin
cartel, Gonzalo Rodriguez Gacha, in a shootout.
   U.S. officials say cartels in Medellin and the city of Cali are
responsible for more than half the cocaine smuggled into the United
States.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0018 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 1209EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Lebanon-Israel     06-24 0447</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lebanon-Israel,0463</SECOND>
<HEAD>Guerrilla Group Claims Responsibility For Sea Attack</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SIDON, Lebanon (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Sunni Moslem fundamentalist group on
Sunday claimed responsibility for a failed seaborne raid and said
its guerrillas had been headed for ``occupied Palestine.''
   Police in Tyre, 50 miles south of Beirut, said Israeli warplanes
flew over the ancient port city all night, dropping parachute
flares that started several fires. A 50-year-old woman was injured
and three cars were set ablaze, they said.
   In apparent retaliation for the aborted raid Saturday night, the
Israelis also shelled Tyre. No casualties were reported, but
several houses were damaged, a police spokesman said.
   There were conflicting reports about how many guerrillas and how
many boats were involved in the failed raid.
   Lebanese police said an Israeli patrol vessel spotted two rubber
dinghies with outboard motors, each carrying four guerrillas, as
they sailed south of Tyre toward Israel.
   The Israelis opened fire with cannons and machine guns, sinking
one of the dinghies and killing three of the guerrillas on board,
said a police spokesman in Tyre. The fourth man was reported
missing.
   Israel said only one guerrilla boat was involved with two
guerrillas killed.
   The Islamic Grouping, a Sunni Moslem group based in this
provincial capital 25 miles south of Beirut, also said two
guerrillas were killed.
   ``A squad of fighters clashed for more than an hour with the
Israeli navy as it was on its way to occupied Palestine,'' the
group said in a statement distributed to news organizations in
Lebanon. It did not say whether there were others aboard the craft
who survived.
   ``Our fighters shelled one of the enemy's navy boats with
rocket-propelled grenades and automatic weapons, causing severe
damage and many casualties,'' it added.
   The Israeli military mentioned no casualties on its side. It
said in a statement that the clash at sea occurred off Ras
al-Bayada, two miles north of the border and near the headquarters
of the U.N peacekeepng force in southern Lebanon.
   A military spokesman said the attackers were ``headed to destroy
targets in Israel.'' It said at least two guerrillas were sighted
before troops opened fire, sinking the boat.
   The army did not identify the guerrillas or say if they belonged
to Palestinian or Lebanese groups.
   On May 30, guerrillas belonging to the Palestine Liberation
Front faction of the PLO attempted to attack an Israeli beach south
of Tel Aviv.
   Israeli forces foiled the raid, killing four guerrillas and
capturing 12.
   The attack prompted the United States to suspend its dialogue
with the Palestine Liberation Organization until PLO chief Yasser
Arafat condemns the attack and disciplines the leader of the
faction, Mohammed Abul Abbas, also known as Abul Abbas.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0019 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 1226EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-DeadlineGang Bjt   06-24 0716</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Deadline Gang, Bjt,0736</SECOND>
<HEAD>1920s Gang Recalls Hard Times, Good Times</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto BX4</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MICHELLE LOCKE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WEST SPRINGFIELD, Mass. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   They came from the across the
tracks, and the more they were snubbed, the closer they became. The
immigrant kids are retired now, but they still celebrate their
exploits as members of the ``Deadline Gang.''
   The youthful alliances forged during the 1920s and 1930s will be
renewed this Saturday when the gang _ children of immigrants who
moved to western Massachusetts in the 1900s _ gets together for a
sixth time.
   The memories come tumbling out when members of the ``Deadline
Gang,'' recall growing up in a gritty railroad town when the
century was young.
   For Lester Lamothe, it was picking nuggets of reusable coal from
the piles dumped at the railroad yards. For Cy Conner, it was
playing ``the whip,'' hanging on to the back of a Model T spinning
across a frozen river. For John DeChaine, it was swiping ears of
corn to roast on summer bonfires.
   ``That's all we had. We didn't have anything big, but this was
ours,'' said Sam Pompei, balding, 72 years old, but with the
mischief of youth glinting behind his thick glasses. ``This goes
back to the 1920s and the same feeling toward each other has
existed ever since.''
   ``Let's be honest, everyone looks at everyone else and sees how
old they are,'' Lamothe said. ``Of course, I don't get old.''
   Just how the gang got started is hard to determine, members say.
   ``They never had a meeting, a formal meeting. It just sort of
grew out of nothing,'' Pompei recalled. ``When you came through
this area, we never bothered anybody, but (we said) `Don't bother
our property. Just behave yourselves.'''
   ``Deadline territory,'' was just a few blocks bounded by a
river, railroad tracks, industrial yards and a street.
   ``This was our back yard. This is where we played and this is
where we fought. We've always stuck together,'' said Lamothe, the
68-year-old chairman of the gang's reunions, held sporadically at
first, but biennial since 1986.
   ``Everyone looked at us as `you come from across the tracks,'''
he said. ``The more they looked down on us, the more we stayed
together.''
   Nowadays, shopping strips and fast-food joints have swallowed up
the fields where the children used to play. And, somehow, World War
II was the time the last of the deadliners grew up.
   But even as adults living in a world that no longer revolved
around the railroad and the local ice rink, the group held onto its
past.
   Now that retirement has freed their afternoons, deadliners still
living in their hometown can often be found at the Dante Club, a
social club housed in what used to be the neighborhood elementary
school.
   Out come the scrapbooks and the faded black-and-white
photographs as new life is breathed into the decades-old memories.
   ``That one's me,'' a white-haired Flora Senk says, pointing to a
1927 picture of children lined up against the wall, shirts stiff
with starch.
   ``Look at those long stockings,'' she says with a laugh,
pointing to the cloth-swathed legs of the dark-eyed girl she once
was.
   Other photographs celebrate the exploits of the grown-up gang.
   Pete Bessone played hockey with the Detroit Red Wings. The
Zucchini brothers, Mario and Babe, played for the pre-World War II
Italian Olympic ice hockey team. And there is 1943 Heisman Trophy
winner Angelo Bertelli, who now lives in Clifton, N.J., but plans
to be on hand for the reunion.
   ``There was a closeness,'' Bertelli recalled. ``We were all
first-generation Italians, or most of us. Our parents, not too many
of them spoke good English. (But) it was a beautiful existence.
None of us was hungry.''
   The reunions started in 1939, when gang members decided to get
together one last time as war threatened. That session and two more
reunions didn't include women. But in 1986, the women insisted on
inclusion. Two years ago, about 500 people showed up and this year
the rules have been amended to allow the children of members to
attend.
   Bertelli said he wouldn't miss the chance to see his old
friends. For the Heisman Trophy winner, the Deadline Gang comes
down to one thing.
   ``I think of my youth,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0020 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 1227EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-BlackWashington     06-24 0410</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Black Washington,390</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mandela Might Find Some Familiar Problems in Washington</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Mandela Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LAURIE ASSEO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Rampant unemployment. Racial division.
Poverty. Nelson Mandela needn't look far in Washington to find some
of the same troubles that afflict his homeland.
   Tourists stroll the manicured Mall and the pristine Capitol
grounds. But just a stone's throw away, the city's black community
struggles.
   Many of Washington's problems can be laid at the altar of a
flourishing drug trade.
   ``A Nelson Mandela, a Jesse Jackson or any other leader is not
going to change it,'' says Gary Burke, a street vendor in the
predominantly black southeast section of the city. ``Talk alone is
not going to do it. ... It's around me every day and it affects us
deeply.''
   More than 400 people were murdered in the nation's capital in
1989, and another 200 were slain in the first half of 1990 _ more
than half of the deaths blamed on drugs.
   During Mandela's visit, Mayor Marion Barry will be spending his
days in court _ standing trial on drug and perjury charges.
   The city's infant mortality rate rose to an alarming 23.2 deaths
per 1,000 live births in 1988, more than double the national
average.
   ``We've been hit by a hurricane that government can't control,''
Patricia Tompkins, chief of the Office of Maternal and Child
Health, said. ``There's a tremendous amount of drug abuse among
women of childbearing age.''
   Many of those babies were born to teen-agers. Of the 10,514
births recorded in 1988, 1,765 were born to girls ages 15-19.
   Local youth employment programs have helped slash the teen
jobless rate by half in recent years, but it still stood at 20
percent in 1988.
   Mandela is not scheduled to see Washington's disadvantaged side
during his three-day visit. Nonetheless, many Washington blacks
share the excitement Mandela has generated since his release from
27 years in South African prisons.
   ``I think it's wonderful,'' said Von McMeekin, a graphics
worker. ``I think he's going to bring more of an understanding of
black people toward each other.''
   ``Nelson Mandela is a symbol to black Americans of great
courage, principle, integrity and sacrifice,'' said Randall
Robinson, executive director of the anti-apartheid lobby,
TransAfrica. ``This is the most sought-after person of our time.''
   Robinson and others said Mandela is an inspiration to Washington
blacks, who outnumber whites by more than 2-to-1 but share little
in the city's overall affluence.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0021 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 1247EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-ECSummit     06-24 0550</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-EC Summit,0563</SECOND>
<HEAD>West European Leaders Meet To Press Ahead With Unity Plan</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MAUREEN JOHNSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DUBLIN, Ireland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Leaders of the European Community begin a
summit meeting Monday divided over Soviet aid and South African
sanctions but set to press ahead with plans to achieve political
and monetary union by 1993.
   ``The whole trend is toward unity and coherence and integration,
and not the other way about,'' Irish Prime Minister Charles Haughey
said. He spoke in a radio interview on the eve of the two-day
summit in the medieval Dublin Castle.
   For the first time an East bloc leader, East German Prime
Minister Lothar de Maziere, will join the summit as a guest. East
Germany is due to become part of the 12-nation trade bloc after
German unificiation, expected by the end of the year.
   Despite reservations by Britain's Margaret Thatcher, the summit
appeared certain to agree to begin a conference on political union
in December. It would run alongside one on economic and monetary
union, with a December 1992 deadline for final conclusions.
   Mrs. Thatcher is confident that political union will amount to
what she terms ``much closer cooperation'' among the 12 nations,
rather than grandiose plans for some kind of federal Europe.
   At an emergency summit in April, the community leaders agreed to
strive toward an undefined form of political union, spurred by what
they see as the need for stability in the rapidly changing
continent.
   Britain, threatened with being sidelined while the other 11
nations move toward economic union, last week suggested that the
community create a new currency, primarily for tourists and
businessmen. The banknotes of the European Currency Unit would
circulate with the 12 exisiting currencies.
   The plan is expected to be discussed in Dublin, but it has
received a lukewarm response and been dismissed by critics as the
creation of a glorified traveler's check.
   The issue of aid to the Soviet Union was a last-minute addition
to the loose agenda after West Germany and France last week called
for the swift organization of a major Western aid program to help
President Mikhail S. Gorbachev's crumbling economy.
   West German and French officials will also seek to get the
United States and Japan to agree to an aid package at a meeting
next month in Houston of the world's leading industrialized nations.
   Community officials said there was little prospect of any
agreement on Soviet aid being reached at the Dublin meeting.
   Britain, in particular, endorses the U.S. view that the right
course is to give technical and other assistance rather than
pouring in money to an economy that is potentially rich but grossly
mismanaged.
   On South African sanctions, the summit appeared likely also to
refuse to lift measures and agree only on a general experession of
support for President F.W. de Klerk's reform measures.
   Britain has already lifted so-called ``voluntary'' measures,
such as discouraging academic contact and trade missions to South
Africa. But the community approval is required to end a ban on
imports of South African iron, steel and gold coins and new
investment agreed in 1986.
   After the summit, the community's six-month rotating presidency
will pass to Italy. The other members of the bloc are West Germany,
Britain, France, Denmark, The Netherlands, Spain, Portugal, Greece,
Belgium and Luxembourg.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0022 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 1319EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-TuitionTax     06-24 0740</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Tuition Tax,0765</SECOND>
<HEAD>Alderman Pushing For Precedent-Setting Tax on College Tuition</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BERNARD SCHOENBURG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>EVANSTON, Ill. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   If Alderman Jack Korshak has his way,
students at Northwestern University will be first in the nation to
pay a tax on tuition.
   Administrators at Northwestern and other schools nationwide,
students and the American Council on Education say such a tax would
hurt students and take a swipe at the value of education.
   The City Council in this Chicago suburb of 75,000 residents has
tried before and failed to implement such a tax. Korshak, a 12-year
member of the council and a Northwestern graduate, says the move to
tax is back because in his view, his alma mater wants something for
nothing.
   ``The stated public attitude of Northwestern is `We don't give
you a dime,''' said Korshak. ``If you treat people in a rotten way,
sooner or later people are going to react.''
   The reaction came in the form of a proposed 0.5 percent tax on
tuition, levied against students at Northwestern and three smaller
colleges in Evanston _ including two seminaries.
   Most of Northwestern's nearly 10,500 students are undergraduates
who would pay about $68 a year based on next year's annual tuition
of $13,725. The tax would raise more than $700,000 a year, said
Alderman Marjorie Collens, head of the city council's Budget Policy
Committee.
   The committee passed the tax proposal May 31. Collens, who
opposes the plan, said it likely will be introduced to the full
council Monday and could be decided on July 9.
   No other city in the United States has such a tax, according to
Sheldon E. Steinbach, vice president and general counsel of the
Washington, D.C.-based American Council on Education. The council
represents 1,500 colleges and universities nationwide.
   A tuition tax would be ``very poor public policy,'' he said.
Tuition already is high and ``to impose an additional burden on
parents is somewhat unconscionable.''
   Some other large universities make donations to their host
cities, but usually because city property they have had to buy,
said Michael Weston, vice president and general counsel at
Northwestern.
   Cornell University pays its host city of Ithaca, N.Y., more than
$2 million in contributions, user fees and property taxes on
university-owned land not used for educational purposes, said David
I. Stewart, Cornell's director of community relations. Yale and
Harvard also make lump-sum payments to their host cities.
   Some University of California campuses reimburse their host
cities for services like fire protection and city planning, said
Ron Kolb, spokesman for the UC system.
   ``But it's always been our position that students shouldn't have
to shoulder that burden,'' Kolb said.
   ``We have always felt it's important to keep fees as low as
possible, and I think the university would resist a taxation
structure,'' he said.
   Korshak says Northwestern consistently has avoided paying for
police and fire protection. But Weston says the university is a
good neighbor, bringing an estimated half million visitors a year
to the city, adding millions of dollars to the Evanston economy,
and providing cultural advantages often used by city residents.
   The university also has its own police force, handling most
campus calls, he said.
   ``What this tells the nation and the world about Evanston is
really unhealthy _ the notion that education should somehow be
subject to tax'' like liquor or cigarettes, Weston said.
``Education may be addictive, but it's clearly a beneficial
addiction.''
   Lee Ellis, another Northwestern vice president, testified at the
committee's hearing that the school pays nearly $1 million a year
in utility taxes, permit costs and fees, while students spend $10
million a year and the university spends $7 million a year in the
city.
   But Korshak calls the campus a money machine because he says its
annual budget dwarfs the city budget of $77.6 million.
   Northwestern's operating budget this year is $610 million, said
Ken Wildes, director of university relations.
   ``There's no question that Northwestern is a bigger operation
than the city of Evanston,'' Wildes said. ``It doesn't mean we're
flush with funds as he implies.''
   Some students also object.
   ``I really think it's absurd that they're trying to tax the
students,'' said Paul Murphy, 20, a junior from Syosset, N.Y.
   Dave Hursey, 23, manager of a Chess-King men's clothing store
near campus, said the campus contributes enough.
   ``If it wasn't for the college, I don't know if Evanston would
have much to put it on the map,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0023 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 1351EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SAfrica-Apartheid     06-24 0337</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-SAfrica-Apartheid,0347</SECOND>
<HEAD>More Blacks Receiving Permission To Live In White Neighborhoods</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Mandela, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JOHANNESBURG, South Africa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The government has begun to
routinely issue permits to non-whites applying to live in
``whites-only'' neighborhoods, a leading newspaper reported Sunday.
   President F.W. de Klerk has said that in 1991 the government
will amend the law segregating residential areas by race. But a
growing number of blacks, Indians and people of mixed-race are
seeking and receiving official permission to move to white
neighborhoods even before Parliament changes the law, The Sunday
Star of Johannesburg said.
   The newspaper said that when the government received an
individual request by a non-white to live in white area, approval
often was sent in less than 24 hours.
   ``As yet I have not had a permit refused,'' one unidentified
real estate agent told The Sunday Star.
   The report gave no indication of how many applications have been
approved in recent weeks or months. Government offices were closed
Sunday and officials could not be reached for comment.
   The Group Areas Act, passed in 1950, segregates South African
residential areas by race and is considered one of the pillars of
apartheid.
   However, tens of thousands of blacks in recent years have moved
illegally into inner-city neighborhoods officially reserved for
whites. A far smaller number has applied for and received
permission.
   The government has largely stopped prosecuting alleged
violations of the Group Areas Act, although dozens of bureaucrats
are assigned to enforce the measure. Last week prosecutors dropped
11 cases against 30 people.
   The government also has opened four small neighborhoods to all
races.
   De Klerk wants to amend the Group Areas Act but has said he
opposes its repeal. He has not spelled out a new plan, but has said
the new law must be supported by a majority of South Africans.
   There is a surplus of housing for the 5 million whites in South
Africa, but blacks face a critical shortage. Several million of the
country's 28 million blacks live in squatter shacks.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0024 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 1352EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-CaveRescue Bjt   06-24 0643</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Cave Rescue, Bjt,0667</SECOND>
<HEAD>Family Saved Energy, Recited Bible Verses During 5 Days in Cave</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HARRISONBURG, Va. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A man and his two sons lost in a cave
for five days without food or water survived by sitting quietly to
save energy and reciting Bible scriptures to remain hopeful, the
father said Sunday.
   ``Toward the end, we figured we were going to die,'' Gary Lutes
said. ``We were happy it would be all three of us together and not
just one. We figured that was better than continuing on like that.''
   Lutes, 37, a Tampa, Fla., land surveyor, and sons Gary Jr., 13,
and Timothy, 9, were rescued from a West Virginia cave Saturday,
state police said. They had been lost since Monday.
   They were taken to Rockingham Memorial Hospital in Harrisonburg,
Va., where they were listed in stable condition Sunday.
   The search did not begin until Friday. Father and sons endured
bats, dehydration and hallucinations during the wait for rescuers
that began soon after their lamps went out while they explored a
side trail, Lutes said.
   ``If it had gone on another day, it would've been a different
outcome,'' Lutes said in a telephone interview with The Associated
Press from his hospital bed.
   ``For the first few days, I thought we would be rescued,'' he
said. ``After the fifth day, I was really beginning to wonder.''
   Lutes, a member of the National Speleological Society, said it
was the first time he had gotten lost in 20 years of cave
adventuring.
   He and his sons were exploring New Trout Cave in Pendleton
County in eastern West Virginia, about 200 miles west of
Washington, D.C.
   The trouble began when Lutes put down his pack to squeeze
through a small opening, intending to retrieve the pack on his way
out. When their lamps later went out, he and his sons couldn't find
the opening or the pack, which held food, water and extra
flashlights.
   ``When the light started going out, I knew there was a serious
problem. (The boys) got upset because they saw the look in my face,
but it was basically calm from then on,'' Lutes said.
   ``I knew if there was panic or terror we'd be nowhere. We
wouldn't have made it unless we were sitting and being calm,'' he
said.
   They took turns keeping watch. They recited psalms and prayed
they would be rescued, Lutes said.
   The search began after relatives in Powhatan, Va., contacted
police when the Luteses missed a meeting, police said. About 25
experienced cave rescuers from Virginia, West Virginia and Maryland
helped police search.
   Using Lutes' parked car as a starting point, they began combing
three sets of caves Friday morning.
   They found the pack shortly after 12:30 a.m. Saturday and
reached the Luteses about 90 minutes later, about a half-mile into
a cave, said state Trooper R.D. Gillespie in Franklin.
   The three were caked in dirt and parched, but otherwise were in
remarkably good condition, he said.
   ``They were thirsty and just jubilant to see the light of day,
even though it was night,'' Gillespie said.
   Barry Chute, a National Speleological Society member from
Burtonsville, Md., who led the rescue effort, said the Luteses
behaved smartly.
   ``If you get lost and lose your light sources, you can't go
anywhere in a cave,'' he said. ``You can't grope your way out.
You'd just go in circles.
   Lutes, who with his sons was being treated for dehydration and
exhaustion, said he plans to give up caves.
   ``When I was down in there, it sure made things seem
insignificant, things I thought were important before. I thought to
myself if I ever get out of this, what do those things mean? Job,
pressure, whether I get the lawn mowed ... things like that.
   ``I prayed so hard I'd be given a second chance, and it came
through.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0025 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 1356EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-NavyCrash     06-24 0263</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Navy Crash,0270</SECOND>
<HEAD>Navy Finds Last Two Missing Crewmen From Helicopter Crash</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NORFOLK, Va. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Searchers have found the bodies of all four
victims of last week's Navy helicopter crash off the Virginia
coast, a Navy spokesman said.
   The bodies of Lt. Jane T. Paradeis, 26, of Rice, Minn. and Lt.
j.g. Jason K. Skubi, 24, of Sandpoint, Idaho, were found Saturday
night, said Lt. Russ Greer, a spokesman for the Atlantic Fleet
Naval Air Force.
   Searchers also found additional pieces of the CH-46 Sea Knight
helicopter, which went down at 12:50 p.m. Friday about 6{ miles off
Virginia Beach, said Lt. Russ Greer, a spokesman for the Atlantic
Fleet Naval Air Force.
   The bodies of Petty Officer 1st Class Norman H. Geisel, 29, of
Saint Mary's, Md., and Airman John W. Burkhardt Jr., 21, of
Boylston, Mass., were found earlier Saturday, Greer said.
   The Norfolk-based helicopter was flying from the Norfolk Naval
Air Station to the USS Detroit, a combat support ship, when it went
down within sight of the ship.
   The 89-foot-long, twin-engine Sea Knight is used by the Navy to
resupply ships at sea. It can carry loads of 6,000 pounds at speeds
of 165 mph.
   The Navy and Marine Corps fleet of 340 Sea Knights was grounded
twice in May because of mechanical problems in the helicopter's
rear transmission and forward rotor.
   The suspect parts were replaced before the helicopters were put
back in service. There is no indication the crash was related to
those problems, Greer said, and the cause of the crash is under
investigation.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0026 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 1432EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-JoggerAttack     06-24 0353</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Jogger Attack,0362</SECOND>
<HEAD>First Three `Wilding' Defendants in Jogger Rape Go On Trial</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SAMUEL MAULL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The victim is known only as the ``Central Park
jogger'' and she cannot remember the crime. But her gang rape and
beating will be relived when three teen-agers go on trial Monday
for the so-called ``wilding'' attack.
   Antron McCray, 15, and Raymond Santana and Yusef Salaam, both
16, are charged with attempted murder, rape, sexual abuse, assault,
robbery and riot in the April 19, 1989, attack.
   They are being tried as adults.
   Three other youths face trial later for their alleged roles in
the crime that prosecutors say was committed by a gang out for a
night of violence in Central Park. The teens allegedly told police
they were out ``wilding'' _ a slang term for attacking anyone who
wandered across their path.
   The victim, a Wall Street investment banker, was raped, beaten
and smashed in the head with a rock. She nearly bled to death.
   She suffered brain damage in the assault, cannot remember the
attack or identify her assailants and is considered unlikely to
testify. Her identity has not been publicized because of the nature
of the crime.
   But despite her injuries, she has recovered. After emerging from
a coma and undergoing treatment at a Connecticut rehabilitation
hospital, she returned to work at Salomon Brothers Inc., where she
recently was named a vice president. Doctors have called her
recovery little short of miraculous.
   The woman, now 29, was out for her nightly jog in the park when
she was attacked shortly before 10 p.m. Several other people were
attacked earlier in the park by the roving gang.
   Lawyers for both sides maintain that race has nothing to do with
the case, but because the victim is a successful young white woman
and her alleged attackers are inner-city blacks, attention has been
focused on the race and class of the prospective jurors.
   Jury selection began June 13. The jurors ultimately selected to
hear an estimated six to eight weeks of testimony include blacks,
whites, Hispanics and one Asian.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0027 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 1454EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Finland-Hijack 1stLd-Writethru a0673 06-24 0606</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Finland-Hijack, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0673,0622</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hijacker Forces Soviet Airliner to Finland, Surrenders</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto HEL1</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 14th graf, `The aircraft...' with 1 graf to UPDATE with
plane returning to Soviet Union. Pick up 15th pvs, `On Tuesday...'
^By MATTI HUUHTANEN</NOTE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HELSINKI, Finland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A young Soviet hijacker claiming to
have a bomb in his briefcase forced a Soviet domestic airliner to
land in Finland on Sunday, then surrendered to police, airport
officials said.
   The 71 other passengers and six crew were released unharmed, and
police found no explosives or arms aboard the airliner, said Erkki
Lepola, head of air traffic controllers at Helsinki airport.
   It was the second hijacking of a Soviet aircraft to Finland in
less than a week, and the third to Scandinavia in two weeks.
Finnish authorities said they were concerned and would raise the
issue with Moscow.
   The plane, a Tupolev 134, was on an internal flight from
Tallinn, Estonia's capital, to Lvov in the Ukraine.
   The hijacker, a 21-year-old Russian, asked for political asylum
in Finland. He refused to explain his motive before speaking to a
lawyer.
   Police earlier said the hijacker had asked for political asylum
in the United States.
   A Soviet civil aviation official in Moscow identified the
hijacker as M. Varfolomeyev. Finnish authorities refused to confirm
his identity because of his asylum request. Soviet authorities have
asked for his extradition.
   Witnesses said Varfolomeyev took control of the plane five
minutes after takeoff from Tallinn, and demanded that the crew
divert the flight to Stockholm, Sweden.
   ``About five minutes after takeoff he went to the toilet with
his briefcase, then to an air hostess, so I thought he was sick,''
said Vladimir Vager, a passenger who sat next to the hijacker.
   ``When he came back to his seat he said to us, `All of you
remain seated and obey me,' and he said he had a bomb in his
briefcase,'' Vager told The Associated Press. He said everyone on
the plane remained calm.
   After conferring with the rest of the crew, the copilot told the
hijacker the plane did not have enough fuel to reach Stockholm.
Varfolomeyev agreed to fly to Helsinki, where the plane landed
Sunday morning.
   ``When we had landed police came on board with an interpreter
and took the hijacker off the plane,'' said Vager.
   The briefcase and hand luggage were put on the runway and
examined with the help of dogs, while the plane was searched for
explosives. None was found.
   The aircraft left later for the Soviet Union, TV news in
Helsinki reported.
   On Tuesday, another Soviet airplane was diverted to Helsinki but
had difficulty communicating with the Finns. Tass, the Soviet news
agency, reported that the crew needed the help of the pilot of a
West German light plane bound for Helsinki.
   The 20-year-old hijacker of Tuesday's flight, who was identified
as Oleg Kozlov, is in police custody in Helsinki.
   Kozlov also asked for political asylum after surrendering to
Finnish authorities. He told police his intention was to reach the
United States.
   Finland, which has traditionally close ties with the Soviet
Union, has granted asylum to a Soviet citizen only once before
since World War II, in 1973. Officials refuse to discuss that case.
   On June 9, 17-year-old Dimitry Semionov forced a domestic Soviet
plane to land in Sweden by threatening the pilot with a dummy hand
grenade. All 114 passengers and seven crew were unharmed and
Semionov surrendered.
   Semionov has been arraigned in court but has not asked for
political asylum. He said he wanted to leave his home in
Byelorussia after a quarrel with his father.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0028 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 1512EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Cameroon-WorldCup     06-24 0199</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Cameroon-World Cup,0203</SECOND>
<HEAD>Cameroon Fans Celebrate Soccer Victory</HEAD>
<DATELINE>YAOUNDE, Cameroon (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Soccer fans danced until dawn Sunday
after Cameroon's historic advance into the World Cup quarterfinals,
and support swelled for a campaign to erect a monument to the
team's star player.
   Police said 21 people were hurt in various incidents during the
celebrations, and an entire neighborhood was blacked out by a fire
that wrecked three houses.
   But nothing could dampen the joy that swept Yaounde, the
capital, after the 2-1 overtime victory over Colombia on Saturday
night. The victory made Cameroon the first African team ever to
reach the quarterfinals.
   ``Euphoria was total,'' said one journalist, describing the
throngs that flooded sidewalks and cafes for all-night merrymaking.
   Roger Milla, whose two goals against Colombia raised his
tournament total to four, told national TV he dedicated his goals
to his two children and to President Paul Biya.
   Many of the celebrating fans supported a proposal by the
state-owned Cameroon Tribune to construct a monument in honor of
Milla, 38, who came out of retirement at age 38 to compete in the
World Cup. Citizens were urged to contribute even small sums to
help raise the needed funds.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0029 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 1514EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p AM-NebraskaElection     06-24 0667</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Nebraska Election,0690</SECOND>
<HEAD>Democrats Say Protracted Primary Hasn't Hurt</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Michigan Governor, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By J.L. SCHMIDT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LINCOLN, Neb. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Democrats' campaign to unseat
Republican Gov. Kay Orr has taken a detour _ by way of the
courtroom to decide a primary election cliffhanger.
   Unofficial tallies from a recount in May 15's closest-ever
Democratic primary election showed Ben Nelson with a 32-vote lead
over Bill Hoppner, but the State Board of Canvassers has not
certified the results.
   Last week, the board ordered 23 of the state's 93 counties to
count by hand some ballots that machines had read as having no vote
in the race. The additional counting was expected to begin this
week.
   But Nelson, an Omaha lawyer, has asked the Nebraska Supreme
Court to order the board to certify the results and declare him the
primary winner. Hoppner, a former aide to Sen. Bob Kerrey, D-Neb.,
faced a Monday deadline for filing a challenge to the election.
   The situation has left Mrs. Orr, who has received high
disapproval ratings in recent polls, wondering against whom she
should campaign.
   ``Research is difficult,'' acknowledged Scott Matter, Mrs. Orr's
campaign manager. ``What do you do, spend your mornings on Hoppner
and afternoons on Nelson?''
   Recent floods and tornadoes have given Mrs. Orr a chance to be
visible in an official capacity statewide.
   During a flight to view flood-ravaged northeastern Nebraska,
Mrs. Orr said Thursday that she was anxiously awaiting the
selection of a challenger, but her campaign goes on _ with or
without a known opponent.
   Mrs. Orr's unpopularity is based largely on the perception that
she raised taxes. The governor said that taxes were raised
inadvertently when Nebraska's income tax structure was adjusted to
match federal guidelines.
   She admitted the mistake nearly a year after it was made and
attempted to soothe ruffled property owners by returning $118
million to them through legislation last year.
   ``She's clearly in a nasty situation,'' said Larry Grisolano,
Hoppner campaign manager. ``With her negative (approval) numbers,
she's got to be anxious to go on the attack. The time lag is to her
detriment,'' he said.
   The situation has put Mrs. Orr in a difficult position in other
ways. To avoid a potential conflict of interest, she excused
herself from Wednesday's meeting of the five-member canvass board
which she normally chairs.
   But it has also posed problems for the Democrats.
   State Democratic Party Chairman Mike Dugan said it has ``slowed
fund-raising, but the money hasn't gone anyplace else. It's still
there, a gold mine just waiting to be tapped.''
   Grisolano said the ``eventual Democratic nominee will have to
play a quick catch-up in fund-raising, but a lot of people are
ready to give to the candidate.''
   Nelson said he hasn't changed his campaign strategy, but ``I'm
eager to get it rolling.''
   Democrats have viewed 1990 as an opportunity to recapture the
governorship.
   A mid-April poll of 900 Nebraskans by the Omaha World-Herald
showed Mrs. Orr's approval rating was 39 percent while her
disapproval rating was 51 percent.
   And in the GOP primary, Omaha businessman Mort Sullivan, who did
little campaigning, received 30 percent of the vote. Matter said
Sullivan's showing was ``a concern.''
   ``But look at Hoppner and Nelson. Each of them only got 27
percent of the vote'' in the seven-man Democratic primary, Matter
said.
   Dugan said that low percentage is not a concern.
   ``I am very confident that either one of these candidates have
the ability to beat Kay Orr,'' he said.
   Dugan said the primary ``has drawn a lot of attention to the
party, but it hasn't harmed us any. It has the governor concerned
and the Republicans don't really know which set of advertisements
to use.''
   The Republicans can draw on the party for campaign support.
President Bush has been in Nebraska twice in four months. Vice
President Quayle visited once and the past few weeks brought Senate
Minority Leader Bob Dole, R-Kan., and Bush's Chief of Staff John
Sununu to Orr fund-raisers.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0030 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 1521EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brite--ConcreteCanoes     06-24 0208</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brite--Concrete Canoes,0213</SECOND>
<HEAD>Michigan State Team Wins National Concrete Canoe Competition</HEAD>
<DATELINE>AMHERST, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The ``Rowing Stone,'' entered by Michigan
State University, swamped the competition to win the American
Society of Civil Engineers' third annual National Concrete Canoe
Competition this weekend.
   The winners beat 19 other schools to win a $5,000 scholarship
for the civil engineering department from contest sponsor Master
Builders Inc. of Cleveland.
   The champions took the title Saturday night after the second
phase of the competition, which involved races of 100 meters and
200 meters on St. Rita's Lake at the state University of New York,
Buffalo.
   The first phase _ oral and written presentations of the canoe
designs _ was held Friday and counted for 60 percent of team points.
   The University of Maryland finished second to earn a $2,500
scholarship while the University of California, Berkeley, took
third and a $1,500 scholarship.
   The fourth-place finisher, the University of Texas, Austin, and
fifth-place finisher, the University of Wisconsin, Milwaukee, will
receive commemorative plaques.
   The canoes are judged on design, construction, speed and
maneuverability. The contest is designed both to give student
engineers a chance to put classroom theories into practice and
demonstrate how concrete can be used to construct a floating vessel.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0031 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 1523EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People SUB a0703 06-24 0261</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People, SUB, a0703,0267</SECOND>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS Seattle-dated item on Michael Jackson to UPDATE with
attempt to reach Jackson for comment in new 4th graf.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>SEATTLE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Neither rain, nor sleet, nor snow, nor dark of
night, nor Michael Jackson shall keep the U.S. Postal Service from
its appointed rounds.
   That's what lawyer Thomas Wampold reasoned after trying to serve
a summons and other court papers to Jackson.
   Wampold filed a class-action suit that alleges Jackson was not
sick, as he said he was, when he canceled three concerts in Tacoma,
and that he therefore committed a breach of contract with 72,000
fans.
   A telephone call seeking comment from Jackson's publicist Lee
Solters in Los Angeles on Sunday was not immediately returned.
   The suit also names Ticketmaster Corp., which withheld service
fees from refunds on tickets sold to the canceled October and
November 1988 concerts.
   Wampold had no luck trying to reach Jackson's attorney in Los
Angeles by telephone. So he decided to have a process server go to
Jackson's residence.
   But process server Mark Hamilton was turned away repeatedly by
guards at Jackson's Encino and Malibu homes. At Encino, Hamilton
was first told Jackson didn't live there, and then was told he was
out of town and wouldn't be back for several weeks.
   Wampold finally asked King County judge Marsha Pechman for an
order allowing him to give Jackson legal notice of the case by
first-class and certified mail. The judge granted the request.
   Wampold figures guards may turn away process servers, but
nothing stops the U.S. Postal Service.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0032 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 1532EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ReverseArchaeologists     06-24 0818</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Reverse Archaeologists,0850</SECOND>
<HEAD>`Reverse Archaeologists' Wants Return Of Relics Looted From Ruins</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ELLEN MILLER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CORTEZ, Colo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Thousands of relics left by a lost Indian
tribe in the ruins of their famed cliff houses were methodically
looted before the turn of the century. Now a band of ``reverse
archaeologists'' wants to bring them home.
   Before Congress outlawed the practice in 1905, collecting
baskets, pots, tools and other everyday household items from
Anasazi Indian ruins was a thrilling romp through history for
explorers hired by East Coast collectors.
   Like the swashbuckling treasure hunter in the ``Indiana Jones''
movies, they took the ancient ruins of a culture that vanished
before Europeans reached the New World.
   Most of the loot eventually found its way into museum display
cases. Large collections are housed at the American Museum of
Natural History in New York and the Museum of the American Indian
in New York, among others.
   But a group of volunteer researchers is eager to bring them home
to the Four Corners area of the Southwest where the Anasazi
pioneered farming and built dense communities hundreds of feet high
in scenic cliffsides.
   Julia Johnson, the director of the volunteer Wetherill-Grand
Gulch researchers, decried the looting at a recent symposium on the
early Anasazis, known as the Basketmakers, in Blanding, Utah.
   The group wants to reverse the actions of 1890s explorers and
return the artifacts to museums as close to the ruins from which
they were taken as possible.
   To help achieve that and to help scientists study the Anasazi,
5,000 pages of documents and 500 photographs have been compiled on
the museum artifacts to trace their origins.
   Since many of the early-day explorers kept meticulous diaries,
``it's possible in some cases to identify exactly which hole
something came out of,'' said Fred Blackburn, a biologist who
joined the ``reverse archaeologists.''
   Blackburn, 40, and his colleagues crawl through Grand Gulch in
Utah, about 100 miles west of Cortez, searching for signatures the
explorers carved into cliff walls.
   By matching the individual artifacts on display in Eastern
museums with the diaries, Blackburn's group can supply a research
base for scientists studying the Basketmaker era of the Anasazi, he
said.
   The ruins were virtually cleared out and their treasures carted
off by the time Congress forbade the practice in 1905, Blackburn
said.
   ``And the expeditions weren't real researchers,'' said
Blackburn, whose wife, Victoria Atkins, is an archaeologist.
``There's so much we don't know about the Basketmakers.''
   The Basketmaker Anasazis lived in the area from about the time
of Christ until the year 700, Blackburn said.
   They are believed to be the farming pioneers of the tribe that
built a thriving civiliation in the famous cliff houses of Mesa
Verde National Park. Their Pueblo Anasazi descendants disappeared
from the area, apparently driven by a long drought, in about 1300.
   ``We're putting this together so researchers can go back and
find out what the origins of these people were, their customs,
where they came from and where they went,'' Blackburn said.
   He started with the diary of Charles Cary Graham, who with
Charles McLoyd began excavating Grand Gulch in 1890. The pair met
Richard Wetherill and Charlie Mason just as the latter two were
riding out after discovering the landmark Balcony House at Mesa
Verde.
   Wetherill, a nearby rancher and amateur archaeologist, hired
Graham and McLoyd to bring artifacts from Grand Gulch to the local
historical society. The collection later ended up at the Field
Museum in Chicago.
   As news of the rich ruins spread, other expeditions followed,
explorers erasing clues to the mysterious Anasazi's past in their
diligence to gather prized artifacts.
   One likely site for any relics returned to the region would be
the Anasazi Heritage Center in Dolores, a town north of Cortez.
Initial efforts will try to arrange artifact loans, with the
eventual goal of establishing permanent exhibits, volunteers said.
   Fund-raising is under way to pay for lobbying visits to museums
that house large Anasazi collections.
   Blackburn, who specializes in studies of Bighorn sheep, says his
strong ties to the Four Corners area prompted his ``reverse
archaeology'' work. He's especially fascinated with evidence of the
Anasazis ability to co-exist with the sheep that used to roam the
area in large numbers.
   The fledgling ``reverse archaeolgist'' movement _ looking for
artifacts in museums to bring them back to historic sites, rather
than the other way around _could provide clues to true
archaeologists enabling them to unravel the mystery surrounding the
demise of the Anasazi, he said.
   ``Archaeology is really pretty new here in southwest Colorado,''
he said. ``And there hasn't been much done on the Basketmakers.
   ``There are a lot of parallels between the Anasazi and what we
have today. Overpopulation and drought were a major problem for
them and many archaeologists think that's what drove them out of
here. Overpopulation and drought are big problems for us, too.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0033 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 1533EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Obit-Frank     06-24 0218</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Frank,0225</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ilya Frank, Soviet Scientist and Nobel Laureate, Dead at 81</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Ilya M. Frank, a scientist who won the Nobel
Physics Prize in 1958 for his work in neutron physics, has died,
Soviet television reported Sunday. He was 81.
   The evening newscast ``Vremya'' said Frank died Friday. It did
not report the cause of death or give funeral arrangements or a
list of survivors.
   Frank was praised as an ``outstanding Soviet physicist'' who
made ``substantial contribution to nuclear physics.''
   ``Soviet science suffered a great loss,'' the announcer said as
a photograph of Frank appeared on the TV screen.
   The obituary was signed by Communist Party and government
officials, as well as fellow scientists.
   Frank was born on Oct. 23, 1908 in Leningrad and graduated from
Moscow University in 1928. He worked at the Leningrad Optical
Institute, the Lebedev Institute of Physics. In 1944, he became a
professor at Moscow University and in 1957, was put in charge of
the university lab.
   Frank shared the Nobel Physics Prize in 1958 with two other
Soviets, Pavel Cherenkov and Igor Y. Tamm. He also received the
Soviet Union's Lenin Prize.
   The scientist was a specialist in physical optics and nuclear
physics who, along with Tamm, explained the nature of and developed
a theory on neutron physics.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0034 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 1540EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-ParisHarvest     06-24 0167</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Paris Harvest,0171</SECOND>
<HEAD>Champs-Elysees Turned Into Wheat Field</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto PAR2,4</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Champs-Elysees, the most famous street in
Paris, was transformed into a giant field of golden wheat Sunday
during an eye-catching promotion for French agriculture.
   An army of 1,500 farmers laid sections of turf holding 3,600
tons of wheat across a large stretch of the avenue starting at the
Arc de Triomphe, then mobilized a fleet of tractors to harvest it.
   Police estimated that more than 300,000 Parisians and tourists
gathered behind barricades along the avenue to glimpse and
photograph the unique spectacle. Many clasped shocks of wheat in
their hands, others purchased small plastic periscopes for $5.40 in
order to see over the throng.
   The field covered almost five acres.
   ``The Big Harvest'' was sponsored by the National Center For
Young Farmers, at the cost of $3.6 million to focus public
attention on the positive aspects of farming.
   Farmers from all member countries of the European Economic
Community participated in the celebrations.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0035 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 1607EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-SouthAfrican-Exiles 1stLd-Writethru a0706 06-24 0572</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-South African-Exiles, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0706,550</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mandela Gives Exiles Some Hope of Returning Home</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Mandela Bjt</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: SUBS 4th graf to CORRECT that ANC officials trying to arrange
Mandela meeting with exiles. Top prospects uncertain</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By TAMARA HENRY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Nomonde Ngudo and Dr. Naomi Baumslag share a
dream that might have been impossible to have only a few months ago.
   Ngudo, a black labor relations expert, and Baumslag, a white
pediatrician, want to return to their native South Africa in the
near future and maintain the friendship that has developed since
they've been living in the nation's capital.
   For both women, Nelson Mandela's trip to the United States has
rekindled hopes that began when South African President F.W. de
Klerk agreed that reforms are needed and released the black
nationalist leader from prison after 27 years.
   African National Congress officials were trying to arrange a
meeting between some of the area's South African exiles and Mandela
following his arrival in Washington on Sunday.
   ``I am hoping with this Mandela visit, new channels will be
opened up to go back home,'' Ngudo said in an interview. ``I am
really excited. He (Mandela) embodies all of our anticipations
totally.''
   Baumslag also bubbled with excitement in a separate interview.
   ``My heart cries for the country, although my feet are here,''
she said. ``I'm glad it (movement towards change) happened in my
lifetime so I could see it.''
   The women say their feelings echo the sentiments of nearly all
of the estimated 500 to 750 South Africans living in the Washington
area.
   ``My main concern is if we're all going to be absorbed,''
Baumslag said of the desire of many to return home. She pointed to
the slow efforts of the white-ruled government to make room for the
many South Africans who want to return to their homeland to help
put into place the many needed reforms.
   Baumslag said she also is ``very nervous'' about the reluctance
of the United States to provide South Africa with needed resources
that are absolutely necessary for changes.
   Ngudo, who lived in Queenstown, South Africa, said she came to
America in 1983 to attend Indiana University of Pennsylvania. After
completing the two-year labor relations program, she worked with
the United Mine Workers Union.
   For political reasons, Ngudo refused to discuss her family back
in South Africa and why she had not been able to return home. But
she stressed her work with the union here has had positive impact
in South Africa, where many blacks work in the gold mines.
   Baumslag and her husband, Dr. Ralph E. Yodaiken, also a South
African native, left the country because they could no longer
tolerate the poor treatment of the blacks. As physicians working in
many of the segregated black townships, they said they constantly
were faced with conditions they felt compelled to reveal to the
public.
   ``We were treating preventable conditions that only the blacks
were exposed to, such as diarrhea, malnutrition, polio and
rheumatic fever,'' said Baumslag. ``We had to choose either to stay
there and risk going to jail'' because of the compulsion to buck
the apartheid system ``or leave and try to do things from the
outside.''
   Since coming to America, Baumslag said she and her husband
``have been able to work with others, help with meetings, make
ourselves available as resources and help with students. It's
almost like a little family.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0036 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 1612EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Floods-StartingOver     06-24 0678</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Floods-Starting Over,0697</SECOND>
<HEAD>When Times Get Tough, Shadyside Looks After its Own</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BOB LEWIS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SHADYSIDE, Ohio (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   People in this once-thriving mining town
say they've never turned to strangers when times got tough, and
they're not going to start now.
   Residents who lost homes and loved ones when a heavy storm sent
a wall of water crashing down from the Appalachian foothills are
skeptical about help from the government and outside charities,
said Mead Township Trustee Gregg Warren.
   ``People in this town take care of their own. They've always
been leery of outsiders,'' said Warren, whose village of 4,300 has
lost at least 23 lives and scores of homes and businesses from a
flash flood June 14. Ten people are missing.
   ``There was plenty of food, clothing and volunteerism here
before any of these outside organizations came in,'' he said. ``The
local TV stations have raised a quarter of a million dollars around
here, banks have put up thousands of dollars, contractors have
donated the equipment and labor.''
   Adversity is no stranger to Shadyside, where the slumping steel
and coal industries idled many residents who once earned good
wages, and forced others to leave in search of work.
   ``When the coal industry left, that was the roughest thing that
happened to this valley. These people have been beaten down, and
now this flood just beats them down even further,'' Warren said.
   The area's 6.8 percent unemployment figure is misleading because
it does not account for people who have been unemployed so long
they've exhausted their unemployment benefits, Warren said.
   Residents know that sooner or later, the government disaster
relief agencies, the American Red Cross and others will go home and
they will again be alone to deal with their grief and hardship.
   ``If people in this valley get their lives put back together,
it's other people right here who are going to help them get it
done, not nobody from Columbus, not nobody from Washington or
nowhere else,'' said Ben Otto, whose house along Pipe Creek was
severely damaged by the flooding.
   Robert Henry, the Shadyside Local School District
superintendent, said the community would unite to rebuild just as
it does to grieve.
   ``It's a chance for people to pull even closer together,'' Henry
said as about 900 people gathered last week at the high school
football field for a memorial service for the dead and missing.
   ``We've got to go from where we are and start to rebuild in our
community. The people of Shadyside have always responded that way.''
   Residents have not refused government help. A Federal Emergency
Management Agency disaster aid center here has received about 350
applications from people who sustained flood damage, said Gene
Neiditch, who manages the center.
   Outsiders also have come in large numbers to volunteer their
services, many from hundreds of miles away. Tommy Hause said he and
his cousin, Chris Hause, drove in from Mobile, Ala., after reading
about the flood.
   ``Ten years ago, we had a hurricane _ Hurricane Frederick _ hit
our state. We had an 11-acre farm, and it was wiped completely out.
People from Ohio were the first to volunteer to help us. A group
came in from Springfield, Ohio, and stayed at our place 2{ weeks,
doing whatever they could.
   ``I was on vacation, and I said `Well, maybe I ought to be up
there,''' said Tommy Hause, 30, who owns an auto parts store in
Mobile.
   People are tired of the reporters and the Ohio National Guard
troops who have swarmed into town, said Raymond Ponzo, the school
band director.
   ``People are feeling overwhelmed. We're such a small town. Kids
around here are thrilled when the man from the local paper aims a
camera at them. Now, they're seeing themselves on evening network
news,'' Ponzo said.
   Warren said townspeople need to be left alone now to deal with
their emotions. ``I realized after I went to the first of these
funerals that it's more important to be with our own than showing
some reporter around,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0037 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 1620EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-AIDS-Doctors     06-24 0589</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-AIDS-Doctors,0603</SECOND>
<HEAD>Distaste For AIDS Patients Turns Doctors Away From HIV Treatment</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-AIDS Meeting, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LISA LEVITT RYCKMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP National Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN FRANCISCO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Molly Cooke happened to be a physician at
San Francisco General Hospital in the eye of the AIDS storm when
the epidemic blew in a decade ago. And if she had it to do over
again, she would.
   But some of the 1,045 residents she and other researchers
interviewed at 41 internal medicine programs across the nation are
so fearful of contracting the deadly virus and so prejudiced
against the groups of people primarily infected that they want
nothing to do with AIDS treatment.
   ``The residents' intention to care for HIV-infected people was
low by all measures,'' Cooke said. ``Some residents would not treat
to save a life in the face of any seroconversion risk, and only 17
percent of the residents (indicated) a strong intent to accommodate
HIV-infected people in practice.''
   Distaste for the groups of people disproportionately affected by
the disease was the one factor that distinguished doctors who had
no plans to treat HIV and those who did, Cooke said on Saturday in
her report to the Sixth International Conference on AIDS.
   Some 65 percent of those surveyed agreed with the statement,
``Most IV drug-using patients with AIDS have brought the disease on
themselves.'' Forty-six percent agreed with the same statement when
the phrase ``gay patients'' was substituted, and 35 percent agreed
when ``minority patients'' filled the blank.
   Eighty percent of the residents thought that treating AIDS was
difficult, and more than half were insecure about their ability to
offer proper social support. One-quarter believed caring for AIDS
patients was unpleasant because they always die.
   ``What's happening is everybody's scared, and there are some
people who have, say, a high sense of professional duty. They say,
`I may be scared, but this is what doctors do,''' Cooke said.
   ``Other people have a low sense of professional duty or are very
prejudiced. They say, `These people are not worth me dealing with
all this fear about. So I'm going to take myself somewhere else
where I don't have to feel this anxiety all the time.'''
   Cooke said more than half the residents believed that HIV will
prove to be transmissible in ways now believed to be safe, and
two-thirds said they were afraid of being infected on the job.
Thirty-six percent said their practices wouldn't be set up to
accommodate HIV-infected patients.
   ``There's a myth that I ran into all the time in the mid-'80s
when I would go out and talk to doctors in other hospitals about
what we were doing,'' she said. ``And what people would say was,
`You can do that because somehow at San Francisco General, you're
different. But it scares us too much.'''
   For years, she would reply, ``You shouldn't be scared. There's
nothing to be scared about.'' She finally decided that wasn't true.
   ``I learned to say, `It's very scary,''' Cooke said. ``The point
is not whether you're scared. The point is what you do next.''
   Cooke said the researchers plan to follow the residents and find
out what they actually do when their training is done.
   ``People who are HIV-infected already have to deal with a number
of obstacles to getting care,'' Cooke said. ``There's
discrimination. The treatments are expensive. The HIV-infected
patients in the second wave have enormous social problems in their
lives that are impediments to care.
   ``And I think the unwillingness of physicians may be added to
that list.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0038 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 1630EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brite-Corvette     06-24 0243</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brite-Corvette,0251</SECOND>
<HEAD>Road Tour Kicks Off Corvette Convention</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BLOOMINGTON, Ill. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   From the 700 Corvettes in the 20-mile
road tour to the 200 radio-controlled models in their own road
race, there was something for every Corvette fan at the Bloomington
Gold-Corvettes USA show.
   There's also the coveted Bloomington Gold certificate for the
Chevrolet two-seaters preserved in or restored to 95 percent of the
showroom condition.
   And there's a classification for ``Survivors,'' Corvettes at
least 20 years old that have been largely unrestored but preserved
well enough to serve as models for those doing restoration.
   In excellent condition, a Corvette built between 1963 and 1967
could fetch up to $100,000, says David Burroughs, president of the
show.
   Some custom-built racing models go even higher. Five Grand Sport
Corvettes produced in 1963 exclusively for racing are worth up to
$1 million, Burroughs says.
   Next on the most-valuable list would be the L88 Corvette, says
Burroughs. Produced from 1967 to 1969, and also built for racing,
L88s sell for $100,000 to $500,000. Only about 200 of the cars were
built.
   The demand for Corvettes is changing, though, Burroughs says.
The 'Vettes of the 1950s are popular with people who grew up then,
but as baby boomers become able to invest in the cars, the 1963-67
models are becoming more popular.
   About 35,000 people and as many as 5,000 Corvettes were expected
for this year's show, which concluded Sunday with judging and the
radio-controlled finals.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0039 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 1632EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Children'sRally     06-24 0312</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Children's Rally,300</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hundreds Rally at White House for Child Care Legislation</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By H. JOSEF HEBERT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Several hundred adults and children rallied in
a park across the street from the White House on Sunday to protest
the slow progress in getting federal child care assistance
legislation enacted.
   ``Working families are weary of campaign promises that vow to
help America's families only to see those promises go
unfulfilled,'' Marian Wright Edelman, president of the Children's
Defense Fund, told the gathering.
   The rally took on a festive atmosphere as red, green and yellow
balloons were distributed to youngsters, many of whom munched on
ice cream bars donated for the event. Several clowns and a juggler
performed for the youngsters, along with volunteer who told
children's stories and sang children's songs.
   Ms. Edelman said the rally was intended for families to ``have
some fun together on a Sunday afternoon,'' but she also focused on
the more serious concerns many parents have about inadequate child
care.
   More than half the mothers of children under 2 work outside the
home and millions of parents have a hard time getting proper
daycare for their children ``yet the men in Congress and in the
White House are still dickering about technicalities'' on a child
care assistance bill, she said.
   The House and Senate have agreed on parts of a $1.75 billion
child care assistance bill, but differences remain on some elements
dealing with tax credits.
   The rally featured thousands of paper ``chain links'' that had
been collected in more than 130 cities in 30 states to dramatize
support for child care legislation. Organizers of the rally said
they planned in coming weeks to encircle the White House with the
paper chain.
   President Bush was at Camp David in Maryland during the rally in
Lafayette Park across Pennsylvania Avenue from the White House.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0040 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 1640EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-AlaskaSubsistence 1stLd-Writethru a0695 06-24 0820</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Alaska Subsistence, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0695,0837</SECOND>
<HEAD>Right to Live off the Land in Alaska at Center of State-Federal
Dispute</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 15th graf, `Federal land...', to restore dropped word
`for.'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By BRIAN S. AKRE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JUNEAU, Alaska (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   For thousands of Alaskans, venturing into
the wild to hunt, fish and gather plants for food is as much a
routine part of their daily lives as a trip to the supermarket is
for most Americans.
   The right to live off nature's bounty in this wildlife-rich
state is at the center of a dispute that has the federal government
poised for an unprecedented takeover of game management in most of
Alaska next week.
   The takeover is the result of an Alaska Supreme Court ruling
that put state and federal laws governing subsistence hunting and
fishing at odds.
   On Monday, the Alaska Legislature convenes in special session to
consider an amendment to the state constitution that would
guarantee that rural Alaskans continue to have first crack at fish
and game for subsistence uses.
   Gov. Steve Cowper says the amendment is the only way to avert a
permanent federal takeover of game management on the two-thirds of
Alaska that is federally owned.
   In Alaska, subsistence hunting, fishing and gathering is a
traditional way of life central to the state's Indian, Aleut and
Eskimo cultures.
   ``It is the means for them to provide food to feed their
extended families and their communities,'' said Julie Kitka,
president of the Alaska Federation of Natives. ``It's the core of
their existence.''
   But Indians, Aleuts and Eskimos comprise fewer than half of the
estimated 110,000 Alaskans who take part in subsistence activities.
In much of Alaska, the absence of stores and roads to the cities
makes subsistence hunting and fishing a necessity.
   Subsistence is defined and protected for Alaskans in state and
federal law. In fact, Alaska is the only state that gives
subsistence use of fish and game the highest priority when
decisions are made about catch limits and seasons. Sport and
commercial hunters and fishermen take a back seat.
   Subsistence and the way it's regulated has been an issue in
Alaska since statehood 31 year ago. The state's first subsistence
law was enacted in 1978, and there have been repeated legal
challenges.
   Public support for subsistence rights has remained strong,
however. An initiative to repeal the subsistence law failed by a
wide margin in 1982, and a statewide poll in March showed solid
support for the constitutional amendment.
   The latest dispute began in December when the Alaska Supreme
Court ruled that part of a state law that limits subsistence
activities to rural residents unconstitutionally discriminates
against urbanites.
   But a federal law, the Alaska National Interest Lands
Conservation Act of 1980, requires a rural preference. As a result,
five federal land agencies plan to assume game management of
Alaska's federal land _ about 180 million acres _ on July 1 to
protect the rural subsistence right.
   The takeover, which doesn't affect management of the state's
fisheries, is expected to lead to considerable confusion among
hunters as they are faced with differing regulations on Alaska's
patchwork of public lands.
   Federal land mangers said they were taking over control of the
wildlife because of the federal requirement for the rural
preference. But they said they were doing so only reluctantly
because of the complexity of setting hunting seasons, bag limits
and the like over such a wide area.
   ``It's the worst jigsaw you can imagine,'' said Bruce Batten, a
spokesman for the federal Fish and Wildlife Service.
   The court had stayed the ruling's effective date until July 1 to
give the state time to find an alternative solution. But thus far,
lawmakers have failed to pass a constitutional amendment bill.
   Some advocate a permit system that would provide subsistence
rights only to those who meet certain requirements based on
traditional use and need, regardless of where they live.
   ``It seems to me you lose some people out in the bush and gain
some people in the urban areas,'' said Rep. Robin Taylor,
R-Wrangell and House minority leader. ``I think it would be kind of
wash.''
   A group of environmental and sportsmen's groups and individual
plaintiffs in the lawsuit that led to the Supreme Court ruling
filed another lawsuit Friday, seeking to overturn the federal rural
preference.
   If an amendment is not put to voters in November, it would be
two years before the Legislature could get another amendment on the
ballot.
   Cowper fears that if federal game management is allowed to
continue past this year, it could expand and become more
restrictive.
   By the weekend, legislative support for a constitutional
amendment appeared to be increasing. Cowper, a Democrat, got help
from the state's all-Republican congressional delegation when it
endorsed his plan Friday.
   U.S. Sen. Ted Stevens was scheduled to address a joint session
of the Legislature on Monday and urge passage of the amendment.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0041 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 1641EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-AttorneyWar     06-24 0411</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Attorney War,0425</SECOND>
<HEAD>Two Lawyers Trade Lawsuits in Backyard Basketball Dispute</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A neighbors' dispute between a pair of
lawyers has escalated into a multimillion-dollar war of lawsuits.
   It began on an afternoon in March 1989. Michael Rubin, 36, a
personal injury lawyer, wanted to take a nap. His neighbor Kenneth
Schild, 47, a tax lawyer, wanted to play a little basketball with
his son before dinner.
   Schild sayd Rubin sprayed him and his son with a hose when they
wouldn't stop playing basketball. Rubin doesn't deny that, but says
his nights have become ``haunted by the fear of being suddenly
awakened by the obnoxious sounds'' emanating from his neighbor's
basketball court.
   Schild sued after Rubin allegedly warned that he would enter
Schild's property if necessary to prevent future basketball games.
And Rubin has sued not only Schild and his wife, Gail, but the
couple's son and daughter, ages 13 and 11, their psychologists and
attorneys.
   ``It's very unfortunate, but you have someone attacking your
kids in the back yard,'' said Schild. He said his lawsuit, which
seeks general damages, is to protect his children's right to play
safely in their own back yard.
   Rubin's lawsuit against the Schilds seeks more than $2 million
in assorted damages, claiming injury ``in his health, strength, and
activity.''
   A Superior Court dismissed the lawsuit against the psychologists
and attorneys last week and ordered Rubin to pay $1,500 in damages
to the lawyers, but Rubin said he'll appeal.
   Rubin also has filed a product liability lawsuit against the
manufacturer of Schild's backyard basketball hoop and has conducted
sound tests to determine the noise level of bouncing basketballs.
   Rubin has obtained a restraining order limiting the Schilds'
basketball playing. Schild got one forbidding the Rubins from
coming into contact with them or their guests.
   The Rubins have videotaped the Schilds shooting hoops, court
records show. The Schilds have videotaped the Rubins videotaping
them.
   Schild claims in court papers that he has also videotaped Rubin
spraying his son with a hose a second time on April 1 this year.
Schild says Rubin told his son, ``You play and I'll spray _ you got
that?''
   Rubin agrees that's what he said.
   The two have been unable to settle their dispute out of court,
although both say they don't need the hassle of the embarrassing
legal battle.
   ``I guess if nothing else, it's a great opportunity for
newspapers to make lawyers look silly,'' Rubin said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0042 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 1652EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ExxonTrial     06-24 0380</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Exxon Trial,0389</SECOND>
<HEAD>Complex Issues Delay Exxon Trial Until April</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ANCHORAGE, Alaska (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The criminal trial of Exxon Corp. over
the Exxon Valdez oil spill has been scheduled for April 1991, more
than a year after the case was filed and more than two years after
the tanker ran aground.
   U.S. District Court Judge Russel Holland said the case is so
complicated both sides will need an unusual amount of time to
prepare.
   ``The underlying factual situation is extremely complex, and it
is understood by the court to involve massive quantities of
documents as well as review of an extensive transcript of a
related, earlier trial,'' Holland wrote in an order signed Thursday.
   Holland was referring to the state trial of Joseph Hazelwood,
the captain who was accused, and acquitted, of operating the tanker
under the influence of alcohol when it struck Bligh Reef on March
24, 1989.
   The crippled tanker spilled nearly 11 million gallons of crude
oil in Prince William Sound, fouling miles of shoreline and killing
many birds, otters and other sea animals.
   Hazelwood was acquitted of the alcohol charge and a felony
criminal mischief count in March following a two-month trial.
Jurors found Hazelwood guilty of a single misdemeanor charge,
reckless discharge of oil.
   In the federal indictment against Exxon and Exxon Shipping Co.,
the government charged the companies with violations of the Clean
Water Act, the Refuse Act and the Migratory Bird Act.
   In addition, the companies are accused of violating the Ports
and Waterways Safety Act and the Dangerous Cargo Act by failing to
make sure that competent people were in charge of the vessel and by
allowing physically and mentally incompetent people to operate the
tanker.
   In other court papers, the government has said the latter
charges are connected to Hazelwood's history of alcohol abuse and
the limited abilities of seaman Robert Kagan, who was at the helm
when the tanker failed to complete a maneuver and struck the reef.
   Exxon attorneys say the charges against the oil company for the
actions of employees of a subsidiary company are unprecedented.
   In his trial-setting order, Holland agreed, at least in part,
saying the case is ``likely to present novel questions of fact and
law'' that will demand more time for trial preparations.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0043 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 1701EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Iran-QuakeScene     06-24 0345</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Iran-Quake Scene,0355</SECOND>
<HEAD>Quake Reduced Farming Town To Pile Of Rocks</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Iran-Quake, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>LaserPhotos TOK1,2,3,4,5,6 TEH1,5
^By SRDJAN ILIC</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MANJIL, Iran (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   From a distance, this village on Sunday
looked like just another pile of rocks found on any hillside in
northern Iran.
   Thursday's devastating earthquake left hardly a building
standing in the town and killed many of its 2,000 residents.
   In a nearby field, army bulldozers dug communal graves, which
soldiers filled with hundreds of bodies and, amid an overpowering
stench, hurriedly covered them with soil.
   The graves were shallow ``because we did not expect so many
bodies,'' said one army sergeant on condition of anonymity.
   A few survivors gathered around the graves and many wailed in
grief for relatives and friends.
   The scene in Manjil, a farming and fishing community on the
banks of an artificial lake, 125 miles northwest of Tehran, was
reminiscent of old photographs of devastation during World War II.
   Only occasional telephone poles and parts of some buildings were
left standing. A large mural portrait of late revolutionary
patriarch Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini, half his face reduced to
rubble, loomed above the remains of a house.
   Similar scenes of devastation and tales of grief were reported
throughout the afflicted region after the quake, which by some
accounts killed 50,000 people.
   The Islamic Republic News Agency quoted a survivor from Ab-bor
village in Zanjan province as saying: ``So many people perished
under the rubble. The bodies have not been retrieved or buried.''
   ``The whole area is stinking because of the decaying corpses
which make rescue operations even more difficult,'' the survivor,
identified as Ahmad Ali, said.
   Another survivor, identified only as Soleyman from Kopteh,
another village in Zanjan, said: ``Don't ask me how many are dead.
Ask how many survived. Only me, my son and a woman from my village.
   ``My survival was a miracle, because tons and tons of rocks slid
from mountain peaks and buried the village and all the villagers,
livestock and orchards are under mountains of rock and rubble,'' he
said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0044 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 1750EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-AcademyLetter 1stLd-Writethru a0725 06-24 0383</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Academy Letter, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0725,0389</SECOND>
<HEAD>Superintendent Sends Reassuring Letter to Incoming Female Mids</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 2nd graf: Rear Adm. ..., to add time element.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>ANNAPOLIS, Md. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The head of the U.S. Naval Academy wants
new female students to know the institution will not tolerate
incidents like the recent handcuffing of a woman to a urinal.
   Rear Adm. Virgil L. Hill Jr. wrote to incoming female midshipmen
``to extend his personal commitment to the protection of their
civil rights here,'' Lt. Cmdr. Mark Van Dyke, academy spokesman,
said late last week.
   The letters, dated June 1, were mailed to the women who on July
3 will begin their military careers at the academy. Van Dyke said
the academy this year accepted 136 of 170 female applicants.
   Male candidates for the Class of 1994 were not sent letters, Van
Dyke said. About 1,000 students are in each class.
   Van Dyke said Hill was concerned about the adverse publicity the
academy received with reports of the handcuffing of former
second-year Midshipman 2nd Class Gwen Marie Dreyer.
   Dreyer, 19, resigned in April to protest the punishment meted
out to male classmates who dragged her from her room, handcuffed
her to the urinal and snapped photos. Two male midshipmen were
penalized with loss of leave time and demerits and six others were
issued written reprimands.
   Van Dyke said Hill's letters congratulated the incoming women on
being accepted to the academy and explained the circumstances of
the Dreyer case, noting that the male midshipmen responsible were
``severely punished.''
   ``Hill also indicates in his letter that he did not feel the
news coverage accurately conveyed his disgust over what happened,
and that the academy will not condone this behavior,'' Van Dyke
said.
   The case triggered national media coverage and Congressional and
Navy inquiries into student hazing and sexual harrassment at the
academy.
   Last month the academy toughened its rules so any midshipman
found guilty of physical abuse of a plebe will be expelled.
Previously midshipmen were expelled for the more narrowly defined
hazing.
   In the Dreyer case, a hearing panel found the male midshipmen
had not planned the action they took and it therefore was not
hazing. The new rules also call for increased demerits and
restrictions for forcing a fellow middie to engage in horseplay.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0045 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 1718EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Romania-Moldavia     06-24 0407</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania-Moldavia,0427</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tens of Thousands Rush Across Romanian-Soviet Border</HEAD>
<HEAD>With XBUC1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CHRISTINA PIRVULESCU</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ALBITA, Romania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   About 10,000 Romanians, many waving flags
and chanting ``Unite, Unite with the Country,'' poured across a
bridge into Soviet Moldavia to mark the 50th anniversary of
Moscow's annexation of the republic.
   Smaller groups from Kishinev, the capital of Soviet Moldavia,
and other areas crossed into Romania to visit relatives.
   The Romanians surged across a bridge at Albita into the Soviet
republic, despite attempts by border guards to stop them.
   Several Romanian army helicopters flew over the frontier
surveying the tens of thousands of people who crossed at Albita and
at other points along the border.
   Romanian and Soviet border patrols watched the exuberant
Romanians, who crossed without passports or visas. No incidents
were reported before the crowds returned home.
   The Soviet Union occupied Bessarabia, then a part of Romania in
June, 1940, and annexed it as the Soviet Republic of Moldavia.
   ``You cannot stop these people. They have the same blood in
their veins,'' said a Soviet border official. He was pushed aside
by hundreds of Romanians who stormed passed a red line marking the
border in the middle of the bridge.
   Romanians and Moldavians were seen swapping addresses, books and
records and heatedly discussing the possiblity of reunification.
   ``This celebration does not do any good for the USSR, but it
does to us because we want to live with our families from the other
side in democracy,'' said 24-year old Elena Matarkova.
   The Popular Front of Moldavia and other official and independent
cultural organizations have been growing on both sides of the
frontier.
   On May 6, tens of thousands of Romanians streamed across eight
bridges on the Prut River into Soviet Moldavia for their first
visit to the republic in more than half a century.
   Last year, Moldavia restored their language's Latin script,
which is virtually identical with the Romanian script. The Soviet
Union had imposed the use of the Russian Cyrillic alphabet in
Soviet Moldavia.
   On Saturday, Moldavia's Parliament followed the Baltic states
and Russia in approving a declaration of sovereignty, declaring
that its laws supersede those of the Soviet Union.
   Addressing the crowd on the bridge, Ion Hadarcan, president of
the Popular Front of Moldavia, said the declaration of sovereignty
turned Moldavia ``into a free nation again.''
   After several hours the crowds peacefully returned home to their
respective sides of the border.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0046 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 1803EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Turner-Castro     06-24 0218</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Turner-Castro,0226</SECOND>
<HEAD>Castro Committed to Socialism Despite Changes Elsewhere</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ATLANTA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Cuban President Fidel Castro says he remains
committed to socialism, despite the political changes in the Soviet
Union and the wave of democracy that has swept Eastern Europe.
   Castro also said in an interview with media tycoon Ted Turner
that the changes in the Soviet Union would not affect its political
ties with Cuba.
   Soviet reforms, said Castro, ``may affect our economic
relations, not political relations. If the Soviet Union wants to
adopt the U.S. Constitution, we will respect that.''
   But capitalist-style reforms will not be coming to Cuba, Castro
said.
   ``As a socialist and as a man that is fully convinced of what
socialism means, of what socialism has meant for our country, I
cannot agree with that movement in the socialist countries toward
capitalism,'' he said.
   ``We have not renounced any of these possibilities of
socialism.''
   Castro said the changes in Eastern Europe resulted from complex
situations unique to each nation and rejected the idea that the
changes were sudden.
   The interview, taped during Turner's visit to Cuba June 8-10, is
to be shown Monday night on his Cable News Network.
   Turner and Castro have been friends for several years, and in
1982 the Cuban leader appeared in a promotional spot for CNN.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0047 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 1731EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-EastGermany 1stLd-Writethru a0679 06-24 0711</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-East Germany, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0679,0729</SECOND>
<HEAD>East Germans Riot, Wait in Line as Unification Moves Closer</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: To UPDATE with comment by East German prime minister, SUB 5th
graf pvs, `Despite recent...' with 2 grafs of comment by East
German prime minister; pickup 6th pvs, `East Germany's...'</NOTE>
<HEAD>With AM-Germany-Europe, Bjt</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto BER1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARK FRITZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>EAST BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   East Germans lined up in front of banks on
Sunday as they spent an anxious weekend on the threshold of
enormous change.
   Next Sunday, the former Communist country will merge its economy
with West Germany, a momentous event that will have an immediate
effect on the lives of the nation's 16 million people.
   Left-wing radicals tried to attack the East Berlin headquarters
of a neo-Nazi group Saturday, the latest in a series of extremist
clashes in recent months that some officials call a byproduct of
the social upheaval under way.
   Authorities said 21 police officers were badly injured in the
rioting, and East German Interior Minister Peter-Michael Diestel
called for tougher laws against extremist acts.
   Prime Minister Lothar de Maiziere urged the nation to stay calm
and condemned extremist violence as an affront to the peaceful
revolt that toppled the former Communist government last fall.
   ``Right extremist power must not be combated through violent
left extremism,'' he said in a statement. ``The basis for the
democratization of our land was the peaceful protest of the people.
So must it remain.''
   East Germany's currency will be changed to West German marks
Sunday, which marks the former Socialist nation's official
immersion into the free market and a major step toward full
unification with West Germany.
   Banks stayed open all weekend to allow customers to fill out
applications to change their savings to West German marks, and
thousands of people stood in lines.
   To keep the powerful West German mark from being weakened by the
abrupt expansion of the money supply, East Germans will only be
able to convert 2,000 marks _ $1,210 _ of their savings to West
marks during the first month of economic union.
   Some already were receiving checks for that money, which they
will be able to cash Sunday.
   ``We're going to buy a car,'' said Margit Schollain, 32, as she
waited with more than a thousand other people in lines that snaked
from a bank on East Berlin's Leipziger Street.
   The mood was a mixture of apprehension and excitement over the
economic experiment about to unfold.
   ``I think it will bring many social problems, and not just
unemployment,'' said Jan Falkenstern, 24, as he waited. ``I think
the unrest that happened yesterday is part of it.''
   The riot in the city's Lichtenberg district followed a
demonstration by about 4,000 leftists who were protesting recent
attacks by radical rightists on foreigners.
   The group tried to march on an apartment house where members of
the radical right-wing group, National Alternative, lived.
   However, thousands of police blocked intersections and the
protest broke up without incident.
   Later, police said 400 leftists rampaged through the streets and
battled police, who used tear gas, truncheons and water cannons.
Four police vans were burned and a small kiosk was plundered. Four
people were arrested.
   Lichtenberg, a working class district where many Vietnamese,
Mozambicans and other foreigners live, has become a flashpoint for
extremist violence.
   Diestel said in a statement Sunday the government should ban
such radical groups and give the police broader powers to battle
extremists.
   Resentment of foreign workers in East Germany has been growing.
The country is expected to face massive unemployment as its former
state enterprises compete with more efficient Western companies
that already are flooding the country.
   On Leipziger Street, West Germany's Mayer food chain already has
renovated a building just 50 yards from a dowdier looking East
German store. The new store is to open its doors next week.
   ``It is too expensive,'' said Martin Ibold, 31, as he waited in
line at the bank across the street. ``I know a lot of these people
will take their (West German) marks and buy a lot of things.
   ``But I have two children and another coming probably this
week,'' he said, gesturing to his pregnant wife. ``I just need the
money to live and keep up with the prices.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0048 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 1805EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ChildSearch     06-24 0255</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Child Search,0262</SECOND>
<HEAD>Search Still On for 9-Year-Old Missing Since Autumn</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CHEMULT, Ore. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   More than 120 people searched a wilderness
area this weekend for the body of a 9-year-old boy who disappeared
during a cattle drive last autumn, leaving behind only his
wandering horse.
   Nathan Madsen was last seen heading back toward camp on Oct. 22,
1989. A month later, his horse was found wandering on a rocky crest.
   More than 120 people from eight counties trudged through Mount
Thielsen Wilderness this weekend, but found no sign of the boy.
   ``We can't do anything for Nathan,'' said Klamath County search
and rescue chief Del Sparks. ``But the family needs to know
something so they can get their lives organized again.''
   The boy's father, Jerry Madsen, said the family would not
abandon the search effort even if nothing turned up this weekend.
   Nathan was the subject of one of the most extensive searches
ever conducted in Oregon. Hundreds of searchers culled through the
forest and clawed their way up stony slopes until mid-December
snows drove them out of the mountains.
   This weekend's efforts were the first since the spring thaw.
   Nathan's pony was the only clue. The animal was found a short
distance below the 6,400-foot summit of Six Horse Springs Ridge,
where tracks and manure indicated he had been in the area, five
miles from the nearest road, for two weeks.
   The tackle was removed, suggesting Nathan might have taken them
and huddled somewhere nearby, using his pony's saddle blanket for
warmth.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0049 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 1755EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Durenberger-Condo 1stLd-Writethru a0661 06-24 0901</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Durenberger-Condo, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0661,850</SECOND>
<HEAD>Attorney Warned Durenberger in 1986 About Condominium Deal</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: Subs 7th graf, ``It wasn't xxx to change phrasing in
reference to newspaper</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   By LARRY MARGASAK&equals;
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Sen. Dave Durenberger was cautioned by his
attorney in 1986 about accepting government reimbursement for stays
in a Minneapolis condominium, according to documents, despite his
contention this month that he had no reason to doubt the propriety
of the plan.
   Durenberger, R-Minn., collected $40,055 in per diem payments
from the Senate from 1983 to 1989 for staying in the condominium.
He was part owner from 1983 to 1987, and says he sold the facility
in April 1987 _ a deal called a sham by the special counsel for the
Senate Ethics Committee.
   The propriety of Durenberger accepting reimbursement for staying
in the condominium _ with a bedroom, bathroom, kitchen and sitting
area _ is one of the principal areas of investigation for the
Senate panel.
   After a 15-month investigation of alleged financial
irregularities by the 55-year-old Republican, the committee soon
will decide whether he willfully violated the rules and deserves
punishment.
   The committee's special counsel, Robert S. Bennett, argued in
trial-like hearings June 12 and June 13 that Durenberger misled the
Senate. First, Bennett said, Durenberger hid his part ownership of
the condominium as he collected reimbursements from 1983-87; and
then he engineered a phony sale to the company owned by his former
campaign manager to keep the reimbursement money flowing from 1987
to 1989.
   It wasn't until December 1989 that Durenberger formally sought
the Senate's advice on the propriety of the reimbursements, after a
story in the Star Tribune newspaper in Minneapolis raised
questions. The Rules panel said $11,005 of the reimbursements were
improper, and Durenberger repaid the money. The Ethics Committee
will determine the legality of the remaining $29,050.
   Three years before Durenberger asked for a Senate ruling, his
personal attorney, Michael C. Mahoney, advised the senator in late
1986 that he ``couldn't find any support'' for the reimbursements
the lawmaker had been receiving since 1983. Mahoney recalled the
advice in statements to the Ethics Committee, now part of its
official record.
   The documents made public in the Ethics Committee probe also
show that seven months after lawyer Mahoney issued his caution, in
June 1987, Durenberger confided to friends in a personal letter
that he believed he had relied on ``shaky or misleading'' legal
advice when he set up the condominium partnership in 1983.
   In his appearance before the committee June 13, the senator
conceded that rules had been broken, but insisted he never intended
to commit violations.
   Durenberger said the ``strains and vulnerabilities'' in his
personal life affected his decisions, including heavy education and
medical expenses, the loss of his first wife to cancer and the
burdens of his current wife, Penny, whose first husband was killed
in Vietnam.
   The senator told the committee that ``all the key decisions'' on
the condominium were made by his lawyers. Defense attorney Jim
Hamilton argued, ``there was no warning for six years'' that
anything was improper.
   Durenberger spokeswoman Lois West, asked to comment on the
documents, responded, ``We aren't going to try to argue our case in
the press.''
   Durenberger's June 1987 letter was written to a former campaign
chairman, Gene Holderness, and former law partner Paul Magnuson,
now a U.S. district judge.
   He wrote: ``For the last five years I have had the benefit of
renting my former condominium at 1225 LaSalle from a partnership
with (businessman) Roger Scherer. I now discover that my legal
advice was either shaky or misleading.''
   Bennett, the Ethics Committee lawyer, said Durenberger misled
the Senate when he and Scherer each placed a condominium into their
joint venture and named it the 703-603 association _ not using the
senator's name. Durenberger rented the condominium from the
association.
   Bennett further said that the 1987 sale to the firm headed by
Durenberger's ex-campaign manager, Paul Overgaard, was engineered
solely to continue the reimbursements. The transaction, documents
show, was an oral agreement, and final papers were not signed until
October 1989 _ after Overgaard threatened to cancel the deal due to
the delays.
   Durenberger said he bought the condominium in 1979, but when it
became too costly in 1983, he placed it in the partnership with
Scherer, a former Minnesota state legislator and a businessman. He
said he made the deal with Overgaard after Scherer said he was
backing out of the partnership.
   Durenberger said he made the 1983 ownership change because a
political adviser told him he could qualify for Senate
reimbursements by renting the condominium or staying in a hotel,
but not if he owned the residence.
   In fact, Senate rules are unclear on how ownership affects
reimbursements when a senator stays in his home state.
   In an interview with Ethics Committee lawyers in April 1989,
Mahoney stated, ``our advice was we can't confirm nor could we
deny'' that Durenberger was correct in his interpretation that the
rules allowed the reimbursements. ``We simply couldn't find any
support for it.''
   In his defense, Durenberger pointed to a legal opinion he was
given June 28, 1983, by another lawyer, Randall E. Johnson.
Johnson's sworn statement to the committee on June 7 said he
advised Durenberger seven years ago that ``under Senate rules, I
believed he could claim reimbursement for official business stays
at the condominium that he rented from the partnership.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0050 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 1823EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Benson     06-24 0115</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Benson,0121</SECOND>
<HEAD>Church President Released From Hospital</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SALT LAKE CITY (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Mormon Church President Ezra Taft Benson
was released from a hospital here Sunday after being treated for a
bacterial infection.
   No further information was available on the condition of the
90-year-old church leader, said Don LeFevre, spokesman for the 7.5
million-member church.
   Benson was admitted to LDS Hospital in serious condition on
Wednesday. He was moved out of the intensive care unit Friday and
his condition upgraded to fair.
   Benson, who received an electronic heart pacemaker in 1986, was
U.S. agriculture secretary under President Dwight D. Eisenhower.
   He was named president of The Church of Jesus Christ of
Latter-day Saints in 1985.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0051 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 1903EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-WeatherpageWeather     06-24 0299</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Weatherpage Weather,0308</SECOND>
<HEAD>Thunderstorms and Record Low Temperatures Mark Summer's First
Weekend</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Unseasonably cool weather Sunday chilled out a week's worth of
high heat in the Deep South, but the Southwest sizzled for the
first weekend of summer.
   Weatherford, Texas, west of Dallas, got hail as large as tennis
balls during the morning, but much of the region got afternoon
rainshowers and thunderstorms ranged from central and northeast
Texas across eastern Oklahoma.
   Showers and thunderstorms were scattered from south-central
through northeast Kansas, northeast Nebraska, the upper Texas Gulf
Coast, southwest Louisiana and parts of Florida.
   Showers and thunderstorms also extended from eastern Kentucky
across Ohio, western and northern Pennsylvania, eastern New York
and central New England.
   Heavier rainfall during the six hours ending at 2 p.m. EDT
included almost two-thirds of an inch at McAlester, Okla.
   Cool early morning temperatures snapped a weeklong string of hot
days in the lower Mississippi Valley. Low temperature records for
the date were: 61 degrees in Little Rock, Ark. (the previous low
was 63 in 1926); 64 in Mobile, Ala. (65 in 1893), and 65 in New
Orleans (66 in 1965).
   It was a hot day for eastern New Mexico, western Texas, the
Texas Panhandle and southeast Colorado, with temperatures reaching
106 degrees by early afternoon at Roswell, Carlsbad and Tucumcari,
New Mexico.
   Lubbock, Texas, reached 105 degrees, but the state's record
highs were 98 degrees in Corpus Christi (97 in 1964), and 105 in
Midland and Odessa (104 in 1980). Pueblo, Colo., tied its 1971
record of 104 degrees.
   Temperatures around the nation at 3 p.m. EDT ranged from 53
degrees at Mansfield, Ohio, to 109 degrees at Palm Springs, Calif.
   The low temperature for the Lower 48 states Sunday morning was
36 degrees at Truckee, Calif.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0052 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 1914EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Obit-Johnson     06-24 0222</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Johnson,0231</SECOND>
<HEAD>Del-Vikings Founder Dies at 57</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PONTIAC, Mich. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Corinthian ``Kripp'' Johnson, the founder
of the 1950s doo-wop quartet the Del-Vikings, has died of cancer.
He was 57.
   Johnson died Friday at his home, said band member Ritzy Lee.
   Johnson founded the Del-Vikings in 1955 _ the first racially
integrated rock 'n' roll group. The four were best known for the
hits ``Come Go With Me'' and ``Whispering Bells.''
   Lee said the cancer hit Johnson hard in the last few months.
   ``He knew it was coming because he was very weak,'' Lee said.
``I was lucky to have known him. I owe being in show business to
him.''
   ``He was a spiritual and religious man,'' said Mili Lilley,
manager of the group since 1985. ``He was the heart and soul of the
group. He was loved by a lot of people and is certainly going to be
missed.''
   Elmer Hopper, lead vocalist with the Platters, visited Johnson
at a Detroit area hospital earlier this month. ``So sad, so fast,''
Hopper said.
   ``We worked so many shows with him,'' Hopper said, adding that
Johnson told him, ``God was good to me. I had a wonderful life.''
   Johnson last performed with the band April 26 in Hollywood, Fla.
   He is survived by his wife, Johnnie Mae, four sons and four
daughters.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0053 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 1939EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-NIreland-WomenPriests     06-24 0376</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-NIreland-Women Priests,0387</SECOND>
<HEAD>Anglican Church of Ireland Ordains First Two Women Priests</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BELFAST, Northern Ireland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Church of Ireland ordained
two women as priests Sunday, joining Anglicans in seven other
countries in taking a step resisted by the mother Church of England.
   The Rt. Rev. Samuel Poyntz, bishop of Down and Connor, ordained
Irene Templeton and Kathleen Young in an afternoon ceremony in St.
Anne's Cathedral. They became the first women priests in the United
Kingdom.
   Mrs. Templeton, 49, of the Belfast suburb of Dunmurray, is
married and has a 5-year-old son. Mrs. Young, 50, of Carrickfergus,
is widowed.
   Four men also were ordained.
   Both women had previously been ordained deacons, which is the
highest post women may hold in the Church of England. Mrs. Young
had been a paid curate in Carrickfergus while Mrs. Templeton was
unsalaried.
   The Church of Ireland's General Synod decided May 17 to admit
women to the ranks of priests and bishops.
   It became the seventh Anglican province to ordain women,
following the United States, Canada, New Zealand, Brazil, Kenya,
and Uganda.
   The ordinations in Ireland may have a greater impact on the
Church of England because priests ordained by the Church of
Ireland, like those of the Scottish Episcopal Church and the Church
in Wales, are not classified as overseas clergy by the Church of
England.
   At the time of the synod vote, The Irish Times of Dublin said in
an editorial that the ordination of women as Anglican priests ``may
come to be remembered as one of the landmarks in the liberation of
women in Ireland. ... This was a brave vote, which places the
Church of Ireland not only at the forefront of liberal thinking in
Ireland but at the forefront of liberal thinking in the Anglican
Community.''
   Earlier this month, the spiritual heead of the Anglican church,
Archbishop of Canterbury Robert Runcie, said he expected to see
women ordained by the Church of England within a decade.
   Ecclesia, a newsletter published by a conservative
Anglo-Catholic organization in Hull, England, denounced the Church
of Ireland as ``a Protestant sect that can no longer claim the
allegiance of Catholics.''
   According to the Church of England Newspaper, Ecclesia contended
that future Irish Anglican ordinations will be invalid.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0054 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 1939EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BRF--SoCalWildfire     06-24 0183</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--SoCal Wildfire,0188</SECOND>
<HEAD>Children Playing With Lighters Blamed for 280-Acre Brush Fire</HEAD>
<DATELINE>FILLMORE, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A fire that burned more than 280 acres
of parched brush near here was started by two children playing with
cigarette lighters, officials said Sunday.
   The fire in Pole Canyon, a dry mountainous area about 50 miles
northwest of Los Angeles, was virtually contained and almost under
control Sunday afternoon, said Cece Grives, a spokeswoman for the
Ventura County Fire Department.
   No injuries were reported and no structures were threatened by
the fire that began Saturday afternoon, she said. Winds in the area
were calm Sunday.
   About 150 firefighters and one water-dropping helicopter
remained on the scene Sunday.
   Witnesses told authorities about the children playing with
lighters, said Ms. Grives, who added that no arrests had been made.
   In Los Angeles, firefighters moved quickly Sunday to douse a
two-acre blaze in the Mount Washington area and a small fire in
Highland Park.
   Fire danger throughout California is considered extreme this
summer after a four-year drought turned millions of acres of trees
and brush into brittle fuel.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0055 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 1905EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-WeddingRiot 1stLd-Writethru a0658 06-24 0383</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Wedding Riot, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0658,0390</SECOND>
<HEAD>At Least Five Killed In Riot Over Marriage Procession</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: New thruout to recast lead, clarifies that wedding procession
was near Agra; UPDATES with details on Sunday's clashes, raises
death toll, ADDS other details; No pickup.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>NEW DELHI, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Members of Hindu castes clashed for a
third day Sunday in a dispute that began over a noisy wedding
procession near Agra, site of the world's greatest monument to
love. At least five people have died in the fighting, news reports
said.
   Police opened fire several times to control the rioting, which
began late Friday, the reports said.
   One woman was killed and 50 people were injured Sunday in
clashes in Akola village near Agra, United News of India said. The
news agency said sporadic fighting continued in other nearby
villages.
   The Hindustan Times said four people were killed Friday and
Saturday in the fighting and police fire, but the Times of India,
quoting witnesses, said six people died during the same period.
   The reports said about 60 people were injured in the first two
days of clashes and that dozens of shops and buses were burned.
   On Saturday, mobs armed with guns and sticks prevented tourists
in Agra from visiting the Taj Mahal, the 17th century white marble
mausoleum built by the Mogul emperor Shah Jehan as a tribute to his
beloved wife Mumtaz Mahal.
   Police slapped an indefinite curfew on the city, 110 miles south
of New Delhi. Authorities extended the area of the curfew on Sunday
and said the situation was ``tense.''
   The trouble began late Friday in Panwari village outside Agra.
Residents objected when thousands of people who were to take part
in the wedding tried to walk through their town.
   The villagers said they didn't want the celebrants in Panwari
because the wedding participants were noisy and belonged to a low
Hindu caste while the villagers belonged to the relatively high
Jat, or farmer, caste.
   When the revelers shouted insults, villagers who were perched on
the walls of their houses hurled stones, the Hindustan Times
newspaper said.
   Fighting spread to at least 10 other nearby villages and some
parts of Agra, the Times said.
   Clashes between various Hindu castes are common in India and
claim dozens of lives every year.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0056 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 1948EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r e AM-JVCJazz-Saxophones     06-24 0360</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-JVC Jazz-Saxophones,0371</SECOND>
<HEAD>World Saxophone Quartet Dazzles Carnegie Hall Crowd</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By WILLIAM GILLEN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Sometimes programming is the worst enemy of jazz
festivals.
   Take Saturday night's lineup at one concert of the JVC Jazz
Festival. The World Saxophone Quartet, a powerhouse jazz outfit,
was paired with Steve Reich and his disciples, followers of
minimalist music.
   Talk of an odd couple.
   In the old days at Newport, the Rhode Island forebear of this
annual Big Apple festival, such a pairing would have been laughed
off Aquidneck Island.
   Maybe those in charge thought this kind of eclectic bill would
attract a large New York audience. If so, they were wrong. But
adding a solid jazz group and deleting the minimalists might have
filled the place and created a night worth remembering.
   Although the program indicated the saxophonists would play the
second half, they came on first. They were wise; they didn't have
to hang around backstage listening to Reich's futuristic but
joyless stuff.
   The quartet _ Arthur Blythe, Oliver Lake, David Murray, Hamiet
Bluiett _ impressed the Carnegie Hall crowd with their skillful
playing, their feeling for their music, much of which they've
composed themselves.
   This is no kind of ersatz all-star group, in which each player
has a starring role but the group as a whole is only passable.The
four saxophonists clearly respect each other and enjoy their
collaboration.
   In solos and together, they explored the saxophone's full range,
its hotness and coolness, its chaos and simplicity.
   And what a pleasure to hear jazz without all the electronics.
This is the way jazz should be played, whether in Preservation Hall
in New Orleans or in a New York concert hall.
   Unfortunately, for some in the audience, the World Saxophone
Quartet's set lasted only 45 minutes. Steve Reich and his musicians
played only two pieces, one of which ran an hour by itself. At the
end the listener wondered, what did this New Age music have to do
with a jazz festival?
   The JVC Jazz Festival, sponsored by the Japanese electronics
firm, runs in New York through Saturday and then goes to Saratoga
Springs, N.Y.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0057 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 1948EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-India-DerailedFestival     06-24 0405</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-India-Derailed Festival,0419</SECOND>
<HEAD>600,000 Watch Hindu God's Chariot Derail During Festival</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PURI, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A four-story chariot carrying a wooden image
of a Hindu god crashed onto a building Sunday, but it didn't dampen
the spirits of 600,000 celebrants marking the Lord Jagannath
festival, one of Hinduism's biggest.
   Nobody was injured when the chariot carrying the wooden image
slipped off its tracks and crashed into a building.
   During the observances, Hindus bedecked in flowers chanted and
sang, while many surged to touch images of Hindu gods.
   The festival at Puri, an ancient town on India's east coast
about 1,550 miles southeast of New Delhi, has been celebrated for
almost 1,000 years. The festival introduces Lord Jagannath,
Hinduism's god of the universe, to non-Hindus. But few non-Hindus
were on hand Sunday.
   During the rest of the year, nonbelievers are prohibited from
entering Puri's 11th-century Lord Jagannath Temple. It houses the
images of the Hindu god, his elder brother Balabhadra and sister
Subhadra.
   These images _ 6{-foot-high wooden statues _ are taken out of
the temple during the festival, placed on chariots and rolled
around Puri until they reach another temple, where they remain for
nine days.
   Hundreds of devotees had enormous difficulty lifting the statue
of Lord Jagannath onto his chariot. Made of solid wood, it weighs
several tons.
   Some said that Jagannath, who legend describes as a willful god,
``didn't want to leave his temple this year.''
   The wooden images were placed on the chariots, which stand four
stories high atop 14 wheels about eight feet in diameter.
   The king of Puri, part of India's hereditary aristocracy,
arrived on a silver litter led by an elephant. He blessed the
chariots and swept the floors with a golden broom. Then the
procession started.
   Thousands of devotees pulled ropes attached to the chariots on
the two-mile journey along Puri's Grand Avenue to the other temple.
Hindu legend says that pulling a chariot guarantees salvation.
   After about 100 yards, the chariot of Lord Balabhadra fell off
its tracks and crashed into nearby buildings. Eleven of the
chariot's wheels were damaged.
   As night fell, furious efforts were made to repair the wheels of
Lord Balabhadra's chariot so it could finish the journey Monday.
   News reports said that ``every available'' lodging in the city
had been filled by pilgrims from all over India. Tourists and
worshippers from the United States, Japan and Europe also flocked
to the festival.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0058 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 1949EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-WuxtryAward     06-24 0212</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Wuxtry Award,0216</SECOND>
<HEAD>`Tiara Boom Today' For Princess Di Story Wins Headline Award</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SAN FRANCISCO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A New York Daily News copy editor who
crowned a story about the Princess of Wales with ``Tiara Boom
Today'' has won the Wuxtry Headlines Award.
   ``I love what I do. It's hard to find a job where they pay you
to write puns,'' said winner Wayman Wong, 31.
   The award, named for newsboys' garbled cry of ``Extra!'', was
announced Saturday at a San Francisco Press Club luncheon sponsored
by the International Society for General Semantics. Headlines were
judged by a panel of 19 newspaper editors, writers, semanticists
and teachers.
   The Wuxtry for outstanding performance in handling major news
went to the Daily News. Last year the paper shared the award with
The Houston Post.
   Ned Crabb, The Wall Street Journal copy editor who puts brief
headings atop letters to the editor, received a Wuxtry special
recognition award. Another went to Dewey Webb, a writer and editor
at the weekly New Times in Phoenix.
   The Sacramento Bee, San Francisco Chronicle, Seattle
Post-Intelligencer and Oregonian received commendations for
outstanding copy desk performance. The Standard Times of New
Bedford, Mass., received a commendation for outstanding copy desk
performance for a newspaper with less than 50,000 circulation.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0059 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 1943EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Japan-US-ForeignAid     06-24 0447</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Japan-US-Foreign Aid,0460</SECOND>
<HEAD>Japan Overtakes U.S. As World's Biggest Aid Donor</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Japan surpassed the United States to become the
biggest donor of government aid to the Third World in 1989, the
Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development said Monday.
   The achievement could soften criticism that Japan, with its
immense financial strength, has not done its share to help
developing countries.
   Japan's total aid effort in 1989 was $9 billion, compared with
$7.7 billion for the U.S., the Paris-based organization of
industrial democracies said in a report.
   The U.S. figure represented a decline of 27 percent from 1988,
after adjusting for inflation.
   The decline meant that U.S. aid as a share of gross national
product declined from 0.21 percent in 1988 to 0.15 percent last
year _ the worst performance among the organization's main aid
donor countries.
   Joseph Wheeler, chairman of the group's Development Assistance
Committee, told a news conference Sunday that U.S. aid to the Third
World has fallen steadily in recent years.
   But Wheeler said he expects the U.S. will lift its aid effort to
at least $9 billion this year. He said U.S. contributions to
multilateral aid institutions should return to normal levels in
1990, and substantial new aid programs in Central America are
likely.
   But this probably won't be enough to enable the U.S. to regain
its number one slot, Wheeler said, since Japan plans to spend at
least $31 billion on aid over the next three years.
   Wheeler said government assistance to developing countries from
all sources in 1989 totalled $51.3 billion, scarecely changed from
the year-earlier figure of $51.7 billion. The total flow, including
private funds and export credits, to these countries is estimated
at $109 billion, up 4.5 percent from 1988.
   Wheeler said the aid effort of the international group's 18
richest countries has increased in real terms at an average rate of
2.9 percent a year, or a total of about 33 percent in the past
decade.
   Wheeler said the aid effort of Western industrialized nations in
1989 wasn't affected by assistance to Eastern Europe. Most donor
countries have indicated future aid to Eastern Europe won't be
diverted from traditional aid recipients, he said.
   The group said Scandinavian countries continued to provide the
most official aid last year as a percentage of GNP, led by Norway
with 1.02 percent.
   The member nations are: Australia, Austria, Belgium, Britain,
Canada, Denmark, Finland, France, Greece, Iceland, Ireland, Italy,
Japan, Luxembourg, the Netherlands, New Zealand, Norway, Portugal,
Spain, Sweden, Switzerland, Turkey, the United States and West
Germany.
   The third biggest donor in dollars, after Japan and the U.S.,
was France with $5.14 billion followed by West Germany with $4.95
billion.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0060 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 2020EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People-Darryl     06-24 0189</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People-Darryl,0196</SECOND>
<HEAD>A `Darryl' From `Newhart' Weds</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   For years on TV's ``Newhart,'' John Voldstad
only grinned when introduced by brother Larry as one of the silent
Darryls.
   But he managed recently to get out the words ``I do'' and wed
20-year-old Kellye Fowler in Gadsden, Ala.
   Voldstad, 39, who played the chubby, blond Darryl, met Kellye in
August when he was playing tennis in a celebrity tournament in
Macon, Ga., and she asked him for an autograph.
   ``She was spelling Kellye with a ye, and I thought, 'Umm, that's
very pretty,''' Voldstad says in the July 2 issue of People
magazine.
   Kellye's mom wasn't too keen about the romance and _ not
trusting those Hollywood types _ went along on most of the couple's
dates.
   Kellye, who wants to act, appeared on ``Newhart'' as an extra
before the show went off the air.
   But it's love, not a career, she wanted from Voldstad, she says:
``I love John and he loves me, and if you can't see that you must
be blind.''
   As for their 19-year age difference: ``John's 25 mentally
anyway,'' she shrugs.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0061 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 2108EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Iran-Quake 3rdLd-Writethru a0726 06-24 0777</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Iran-Quake, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0726,0801</SECOND>
<HEAD>Strong Aftershock Triggers Landslide in Devastated Area</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS grafs 4-5, A plane ..., with 3 grafs to ADD details
about U.S. relief shipment, UPDATE with 2nd U.S. relief flight;
Pickup 6th pvs, `It was ...'</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos TEH1,9 TOK2,3,4,5,6</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SLOBODAN LEKIC</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>RUDBAR, Iran (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The most powerful aftershock in three days
rocked earthquake-devastated northern Iran on Sunday, triggering a
landslide that blocked the road linking this shattered town to the
Caspian Sea coast.
   The casualty toll climbed to 50,000 dead and 200,000 wounded,
according to a newspaper close to President Hashemi Rafsanjani.
Official radio put the death toll at 48,000.
   Army mountaineers climbed peaks in the rugged region in an
effort to rescue villagers trapped in remote hamlets following
Thursday's earthquake, the official Islamic Republic News Agency
reported.
   Tehran radio said 68 relief aircraft had landed at the capital's
Mehrabad airport during a 24-hour period.
   Among them was a cargo jet carrying 84,000 pounds of U.S. aid _
including bandages, antiseptic burn cream, tents and orange slices
in syrup _ collected by Americares, a private relief organization
based in New Canaan, Conn.
   It was the first overt U.S. shipment of its kind to be accepted
by Iran since the hostage crisis of 1980, when 52 American hostages
were held at the U.S. Embassy in Tehran for 444 days. The two
nations have no diplomatic ties.
   In Washington, the State Department said a Red Cross charter
flight carrying supplies donated by the U.S. government was
scheduled to arrive in Tehran late Sunday.
   Earlier, the radical newspaper Jomhuri Islami urged that no help
be accepted from the United States and other countries whose hands
``are stained with the blood of the Iranian people.''
   The Foreign Ministry, however, said that ``due to the magnitude
of the disaster'' Iran would accept all such aid.
   ``Iran accepts the assistance of all foreign countries except
Israel and South Africa,'' Tehran radio quoted Deputy Foreign
Minister Ali Mohammad Besharati as saying.
   There were conflicting death tolls. The Tehran Times, the
nation's leading English-language newspaper, quoted an unidentified
senior relief official as saying 50,000 people died and 200,000
were injured in the quake.
   He said even that was a conservative estimate because ``the
figures are quoted taking account only of those who have been
registered officially as dead or wounded.'' Many victims were not
counted, he said.
   In Geneva, senior U.N. relief official M'hamed Essaafi also
estimated the toll would reach 50,000 dead and 200,000 wounded.
   Tehran radio put the toll late Sunday at 48,000 killed and
100,000 injured.
   The stench of decomposing bodies hung over Rudbar, a town of
100,000 people. Rescuers aided by police dogs pulled bodies from
the rubble. A team of 205 French rescue workers arrived in the
region with 18 search dogs and 35 tons of equipment, state
television reported.
   Officials said the quake killed 150,000 head of cattle, and
health officials were trying to dispose of the rotting carcasses,
fearing contamination of water supplies and the spread of
infectious diseases.
   The geophysics center at Tehran University reported 60
aftershocks Sunday. It said the strongest jolted Rasht on the
Caspian Sea and measured 5.7 on the Richter scale.
   Television reports said the jolt touched off a landslide that
blocked the 35-mile road between Rasht and Rudbar, a critical route
for relief supplies. It gave no further details. There were no
reports of casualties.
   A quake of magnitude 5 can cause considerable damage, while one
of magnitude 6 can cause severe damage. Thursday's quake registered
between 7.3 and 7.7 on the scale, which measures energy released by
an earthquake.
   The geophysics center also reported a moderate earthquake
measuring 4.9 in southern Iran Sunday morning. No casualties or
damage were reported.
   Iran's news agency said the quake ``buried villages on
mountaintops and in inacessible valleys under tons of rocks,
cutting off the routes with the outside world.''
   In Rudbar, dozens of Iranian military helicopters flew relief
supplies into makeshift airstrips on a small island in a river that
flows through the agricultural city.
   Yawning cracks in the earth, measuring up to a foot wide,
testified to the quake's ferocity.
   Thousands of tents have been set up by the Red Crescent to house
people in Rudbar, where an estimated 95 percent of the buildings
were destroyed or damaged.
   The death toll from Thursday's quake surpassed a temblor that
killed 25,000 people in nearby Soviet Armenia in December 1988, and
a quake in Iran in 1978 that also killed 25,000.
   The quake's toll was the highest anywhere since July 28, 1976,
when an estimated 200,000 people were killed in China by a quake.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0062 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 2122EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Iran-USAid 1stLd-Writethru a0768 06-24 0687</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Iran-US Aid, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0768,0705</SECOND>
<HEAD>First U.S. Aid Shipment Arrives for Iran Quake Victims</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Iran-Quake, Bjt</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 6 grafs to delete reference to weight in lead,
UPDATE with 2nd U.S. plane to arrive late Sunday EST; Pickup 5th,
`The quake...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By NEIL MacFARQUHAR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TEHRAN, Iran (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A cargo jet carrying U.S. aid for Iranian
earthquake victims arrived Sunday, becoming the first private
American relief mission to this country after more than a decade of
bitter relations.
   ``To be on the ground here in Tehran is a very special feeeling
for us,'' said Stephen M. Johnson, president of Americares, a
private U.S. relief organization based in New Canaan, Conn.
   ``We are trying to fulfill the needs of the Iranian government.''
   Americares flew in 84,000 pounds of supplies to Tehran after the
Iranian government said it would accept humanitarian assistance
from the United States for victims of Thursday's devastating
earthquake in northwestern Iran.
   In Washington, Renee Bafalis, a spokeswoman for the U.S. Agency
for International Development, said a Red Cross charter flight
carrying supplies donated by the U.S. government was scheduled to
arrive in Tehran late Sunday.
   The quake killed 50,000 people and wounded 200,000, according to
a senior Iranian official quoted in the English-language Tehran
Times. Official radio put the death toll at 48,000.
   The U.S. relief shipment included everything from bandages and
antiseptic burn cream to orange slices in syrup and tents with
built-in fiberglass frames.
   The cargo palletes heaped with supplies each bore an American
flag and a hand-lettered sign in Farsi reading: ``From the American
people to the Iranian people with very great affection and love, we
offer you these things.''
   Americares officials said they received scores of telephone
calls both opposing and supporting the relief effort even before
the shipment left Connecticut on Saturday.
   Some callers criticized the group for helping Iran, saying the
Islamic government would not return the favor if the situation was
reversed and Americans were suffering.
   The U.S. relief shipment also had critics in Iran. The radical
newspaper Jomhuri Islami urged Sunday that no help be accepted from
the United States and other countries whose hands ``are stained
with the blood of the Iranian people.''
   But the Foreign Ministry said Sunday Iran would accept all aid
``due to the magnitude of the disaster.''
   The U.S. shipment was the first of its kind to be accepted by
Iran since the hostage crisis of 1979-80, when 52 Americans were
held at the U.S. Embassy in Tehran for 444 days.
   Iran is also believed to have influence with the Shiite Moslem
extremists holding 16 Western hostages, including six Americans, in
Lebanon. The longest-held is Terry Anderson, chief Middle East
correspondent of The Associated Press. He was kidnapped March 16,
1985.
   But Americares officials said the scope of the human disaster in
northwestern Iran meant that political differences had to be put
aside.
   ``It's a disaster we haven't seen the likes of, even in
Armenia,'' said Johnson, referring to the December 1988 quake in
the Soviet republic of Armenia that killed an estimated 25,000
people.
   ``When you have a disaster of this magnitude you have to set
aside differences and come on over and help,'' said Doyt L. Conn, a
project director for Americares.
   The Iranian air force ground staff at the miltary field in
Tehran where the supplies were unloaded seemed slightly taken aback
at the amount of aid.
   Ducking into the plane's cargo deck to confirm that the
Americans had indeed brought emergency supplies, they emerged
grinning.
   ``Thank you,'' said one officer on condition of anonymity. ``The
quake area is like a leveled graveyard. It's terrible.''
   The Americares group praised the speed with which the plane was
unloaded but was not told how the supplies would be distributed.
   The Americans waited on the ground for about four hours, hoping
that someone from the Iranian Red Crescent Society, the equivalent
of the Red Cross, would come to greet them.
   But nobody showed up. After a slight delay in collecting their
passports, the Americans departed, expecting to return to the
United States by early Monday.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0063 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 2135EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-ZodiacGunman 2ndLd-Writethru a0749 06-24 0744</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Zodiac Gunman, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0749,0761</SECOND>
<HEAD>Zodiac Victim Dies, Serial Shooter Stalks City's Defenseless</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 5th graf, `Police believe ...,' to CORRECT Proce's
birthdate to May 20 sted May 12. Quote in 4th graf from note is CQ.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By VIRGINIA BYRNE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The city's ``Zodiac'' gunman became a killer
Sunday when a 78-year-old man died, 3{ weeks after he was shot in
the back by the letter-writing attacker, a hospital administrator
said.
   Joseph Proce, the third of four people the gunman shot, went
into cardiac arrest at Jamaica General Hospital at 10:25 a.m. and
died about 40 minutes later, said administrator Ole Pedersen.
   Proce, who walked with a cane, was shot in the back as he walked
near his Queens home on May 31. He lost a kidney and never left the
hospital's surgical intensive care unit, Pedersen said.
   A note was discovered near the street where Proce was shot. It
read simply, ``Zodiac _ Time to Die.'' The gunman also wrote
police, ``The third sign is dead on May 31 1990 2:04 a.m. white old
man with a cane shoot in front of house.''
   Police believe the victims have been chosen because of their
birthdates; Proce was a Taurus born May 20, 1912.
   The Zodiac victims also are vulnerable. Besides Proce, they have
been a 50-year-old man who used a cane to steady a childhood limp;
a 33-year-old man who was drunk, and a sleeping homeless man.
   The Zodiac gunman has written letters to news media and police
detailing the shootings, which began in March. In a November letter
to police, Zodiac threatened to kill 12 people, one for each
astrological sign.
   The latest shooting was before dawn Thursday, when Larry
Parnham, a 30-year-old homeless man, was wounded as he slept on a
Central Park bench.
   The police Zodiac Task Force was doubled to nearly 50 officers,
chief of detectives Joseph Borrelli said Friday.
   The latest victim apparently was chosen and stalked because of
his astrological sign, police said. The other three each had
different signs, but authorities didn't know whether the attacker
knew that before they were shot.
   Parnham told detectives that days before the shooting, he was
befriended by a stranger who asked him his birth date, Borrelli
said.
   Detectives fear the gunman may stalk future victims the same
way, and urged New Yorkers to beware of strangers asking their
birth dates.
   A note claiming responsibility for the Central Park shooting was
received Friday by the New York Post. The gunman also has claimed
responsibility for the other shootings, which took place in March
and May in an eight-block working-class section straddling the
Brooklyn-Queens borough line.
   The latest note appeared identical to an earlier one sent to the
paper by the gunman, said Post editor Jerry Nachman. Four similar
notes have been found: one sent to police, one to the CBS show ``60
Minutes,'' and two left with shooting victims.
   All but one of the notes start with the words ``This is the
Zodiac,'' and three contain the phrase ``the twelve sign will die
when the belts in the heaven are seen.''
   The birth dates of the other three victims correspond to
astrological signs scrawled in the gunman's notes, Borrelli said.
   The notes recalled David Berkowitz, who killed six young men and
women and wounded seven others in New York City in 1976 and 1977.
He wrote letters to newspapers about the killing signed ``Son of
Sam.''
   The case also recalls the San Francisco ``Zodiac'' killer who,
in a series of letters, took responsibility for 40 murders since
the 1960s. Unlike Berkowitz, he was never captured.
   In the latest letter to the Post, the gunman claimed to be the
same man who terrorized California. Police do not believe that.
   Astrologers had warned police that the first day of summer, when
the Central Park shooting occurred, was considered a significant
day because the zodiac changed from the sign of Gemini to the sign
of Cancer.
   A note sent to police and dated Nov. 19, 1989, written by the
gunman, threatened to kill 12 people and warned, ``When the
Zodiacal light is seen Zodiac will spread fear.''
   The zodiacal light is the diffuse glow seen in the west after
twilight and in the east before dawn. Since March 8, the gunman has
struck during the predawn hours on Thursdays, at 21-day intervals,
except for a gap of 63 days between his second and third victims.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0064 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 2156EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-PlaneSearch 1stLd-Writethru a0722 06-24 0406</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Plane Search, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0722,0413</SECOND>
<HEAD>Wreckage of Missing Plane Found; Bodies of FBI Agent and Trooper
Found</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: UPDATES throughout with investigators saying pilot had
trouble with runway lights, wreckage found where radar signal
disappeared.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>GREENVILLE, Maine (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The bodies of an FBI agent and a
Massachusetts state trooper were found Sunday in the wreckage of a
small plane atop a mountain ridge in western Maine, a search and
rescue official said.
   The missing Piper Cherokee vanished in rough weather late
Monday, but FBI Agent Paul Cavanagh and Trooper Joseph Moynihan
were not declared missing until Friday, said Paul Fournier, a
spokesman for the Maine Warden Service.
   The wreckage was spotted on 1,400-foot-high Oak Ridge near
Elliotsville, about three miles southwest of Greenville, by a
helicopter pilot searching for the downed aircraft, Fournier said.
   Ground searchers reached the site by afternoon, Fournier said,
and federal aviation officials would investigate the crash.
   The plane disappeared from radar screens around midnight Monday
heading into the Greenville area near Moosehead Lake. The
disappearance did not prompt a search because it happens frequently
in the mountainous area, officials said.
   Fournier said Moynihan had indicated to air traffic control that
he was having trouble activating the runway lights. At many small
airstrips, an approaching pilot activates the runway lights by
radio.
   A controller asked the pilot at least twice if he could see the
runway lights and he answered ``no,'' Fournier said, adding that
the pilot might have been too far from the runway or his view
impaired by the dense forest.
   Lt. Carter Smith of the warden service said investigators
believe the pilot ``was preoccupied with the landing lights and
trying to focus on two or three different things'' while flying
``at a considerable speed.''
   ``The plane was exactly where the radar showed it dropping off
the scope,'' Smith said of the wreckage. ``They definitely were too
low. ... It would appear that the left wing caught on a tree.''
   In Boston, FBI Agent Stephen Morrill said Cavanagh was traveling
to a training mission; State Police Maj. Robert Morse said the two
men may have combined plans for a training session with a rafting
excursion.
   FAA spokesman Mike Ciccarelli said Moynihan received a weather
briefing Monday night for a flight from Worcester, Mass., to
Greenville.
   When the pair did not arrive in Greenville, those they were to
meet assumed they canceled travel plans because of stormy weather.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0065 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 2218EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-CivilRights 1stLd-Writethru a0689 06-24 0488</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Civil Rights, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0689,410</SECOND>
<HEAD>Fletcher Says He Can't Persuade Bush To Accept Civil Rights Bill</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: Subs 5th graf to insert that bill awaiting House committee
action before reaching floor</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT NAYLOR JR.</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The head of the U.S. Civil Rights Commission
said Sunday he had been unable to convince President Bush that a
proposed civil rights bill would not lead to racial hiring quotas.
   But Arthur Fletcher said he hoped Bush would back away from a
threat to veto the Civil Rights Act of 1990 unless it is modified.
   Fletcher, who appeared on NBC-TV's ``Meet the Press'' program
with Jesse Jackson, was asked whether he believed Bush would veto
the legislation, Fletcher responded, ``I hope not.'' But he added
``I can't tell you what the president is going to do.''
   The bill is designed to overcome a series of Supreme Court
decisions last year that made it more difficult for workers to sue
employers for alleged job discrimination.
   But the Bush administration has sought changes in the measure,
co-sponsored by Sen. Edward M. Kennedy, D-Mass., and Rep. Augustus
F. Hawkins, D-Calif. The bill may be brought up for Senate
consideration this week. A similar version still awaits Judiciary
Committee approval before being cleared for debate in the House.
   The administration has claimed that the bill, as drafted, would
in effect force businesses to resort to hiring quotas to reduce
their exposure to lawsuits. Backers deny that the bill requires
quotas, either directly or indirectly.
   The White House has said it is willing to compromise, although
some Republican leaders have expressed doubts that an accord can be
reached.
   White House spokesman Marlin Fitzwater said last week that Bush
``wants a bill he can sign.''
   But Fletcher, appointed by Bush in February, said the commission
voted 7-1 last week to support the legislation. However, the
commission wants included a statement that there is no intention to
force quotas.
   Fletcher said he had tried to convince administration officials
that the bill as drafted would not do so.
   ``I obviously haven't convinced them yet, but ... we don't know
the language in the bill yet. When we finally see what that says,
we'll know whether there is a propensity for quotas or not,'' he
said.
   GOP leaders have urged top congressional Democrats not to bring
the bill to the Senate floor during the U.S. visit of South African
anti-apartheid leader Nelson Mandela. The African National Congress
official arrived last week and was scheduled to be in Washington
from Sunday through Tuesday. He has other U.S. appearances
scheduled through Saturday.
   On another matter, Jackson was asked if he would run for
president in 1992.
   ``It's a matter that is worthy of serious consideration given
the favor that we've gained among the public,'' said Jackson, who
unsuccessfully sought the democratic presidential nomination in
1984 and 1988. ``But it's too early to make that decision.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0066 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 2228EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Japan-USTrade     06-24 0457</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Japan-US Trade,0472</SECOND>
<HEAD>Japan's Public Spending to Overshadow Trade Talks</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ELAINE KURTENBACH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Japanese and U.S. trade officials met Monday for
talks on barriers to trade and investment that were expected to
center on Tokyo's public works spending, officials said.
   Negotiators tackled Japan's land use policies, the Foreign
Ministry said in a statement. U.S. officials say the policies have
contributed to higher real estate prices that prevent foreign firms
from setting up business here.
   Before the talks began, Japanese officials indicated they would
push the United States to cut its federal budget deficit. U.S.
officials, meanwhile, said they hoped Japan would agree to increase
public works spending.
   Both nations agree the government should do more to improve the
quality of life in Japan, and in turn encourage more imports, but
they differ widely over exactly how much more spending Tokyo should
promise in the talks.
   Prime Minister Toshiki Kaifu has endorsed a $2.68 trillion
10-year public works package.
   But Deputy U.S. Trade Representative Linn Williams and other
U.S. officials say that figure would not result in a sizable fall
in Japan's current account surplus. They say Japan should spend
one-tenth of its gross national product each year on public
investment instead of the current 6 percent to 7 percent.
   Williams, in an interview with Kyodo News Service here, said he
would be satisfied if Japan committed itself to spending at least
$3.23 trillion over 10 years.
   Japanese officials acknowledge the need here for better
airports, roads, sewers and parks. But they oppose committing a set
percentage of GNP to such projects because it would limit the
government's flexibility.
   Economists say Japan's booming economy has a limited capacity to
absorb a significant increase in public spending without
stimulating inflation.
   U.S. officials, speaking on condition of anonymity, said the
talks, which began Monday, were to fine-tune the wording of a final
report. Media reports said disagreements remained over details of
measures to be adopted.
   Both sides hope to complete the final report before the summit
of seven major industrialized nations begins in Houston on July 9.
   President Bush proposed the talks, dubbed the Structural
Impediments Initiative, last July, to help cut Japan's massive
trade imbalance with the United States.
   The talks are aimed at reforming business practices and policies
that are believed to act as structural trade and investment
barriers.
   In an interim report in April, Washington committed itself to
cutting the federal budget deficit, encouraging savings, curbing
excessive consumption and improving worker training and education.
   Japan said it would ease rules on opening retail stores, crack
down on allegedly unfair business practices by corporate groups,
consider revising land use policies to help reduce inflated real
estate prices, and increase public works.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0067 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 2234EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-MarriedPriests     06-24 0354</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Married Priests,0363</SECOND>
<HEAD>Four Roman Catholic Bishops Meet With Married, Former Priests</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SANTA CLARA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Four Roman Catholic bishops held a
cordial but noncommittal meeting with a delegation of former
priests who were stripped of their duties because they married and
who want to return to work.
   The hour-long exchange came Saturday during a retreat for about
200 members of the National Conference of Catholic Bishops.
   ``They listened and took notes,'' said Terry Dosh, one of five
former priests at the meeting. ``None of us got our hopes up that
anything could happen immediately. We're realists.''
   The four bishops, including Pierre Dumaine of the San Jose
Diocese, agreed to take the request to their national committees
for further discussion. At least one bishop appeared to support the
former priests' cause.
   ``Within the framework of the discipline of the church, which
has served the church well over the centuries, these men should be
encouraged to put their life experience at the church's service,''
Bishop Donald Wuerl of Pittsburgh said in a prepared statement.
   The former priests are members of a Minneapolis-based group
called CORPUS, or the Corps of Reserve Priests United for Service,
which held an annual meeting over the weekend at San Jose State
University.
   The group claims about 10,000 members, about half of them
priests who married and are no longer allowed to serve.
   The meeting with the bishops was the first since the 1978
election of Pope John Paul II, who opposes letting married priests
or women celebrate Mass or perform other priestly duties.
   CORPUS President Anthony Padovano said the group tried before to
meet with bishops without success. CORPUS hopes the church will
reconsider the ban on married priests this fall at an international
meeting of bishops in Rome.
   Despite its insistence on a celibate clergy, the church in
recent years has allowed married Episcopal priests to convert to
Roman Catholicism, remain married and celebrate Mass, hear
confessions and perform other priestly duties.
   ``That's a double standard,'' said Guy Murning, who was ordained
as a Roman Catholic priest in 1970 but left eight years later to
get married.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0068 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 2237EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Philippines-Typhoon 1stLd-Writethru a0682 06-24 0369</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Philippines-Typhoon, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0682,0378</SECOND>
<HEAD>Typhoon Percy Heads For Philippines, Gains Speed After Striking
Palau</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 4 grafs to UPDATE with typhoon picking up speed,
moving closer to Philippines. Pickup pvs 5th graf, `Storm
signals...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT H. REID</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MANILA, Philippines (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Typhoon Percy battered the Pacific
island of Palau and then roared Sunday toward the Philippines,
where 30 people were killed in a tropical storm last week.
   One child was killed on Palau, a newspaper said.
   The Manila weather bureau reported at 5 a.m. Monday that Percy,
packing 93 mph winds, was centered about 465 miles east of the
Philippine island of Samar.
   Percy was moving west-northwest at about 19 mph toward the
islands of Catanduanes and southeastern Luzon island, which were
expected to feel the effects of the storm late Monday, the weather
bureau said.
   Storm signals were raised over southeastern Luzon and the
central Visayas island chain, which includes Samar.
   In Palau, a young boy died Saturday night when he was swept by
rain into mangrove trees near his home in the cluster of islands
that comprise Palau, the Pacific Daily News of Guam reported.
   The storm passed 90 miles north of Palau, which is 800 miles
south of Guam, according to the Joint Typhoon Warning Center.
   Wind gusts of up to 103 mph blew off tin roofs of many buildings
and knocked radio and television stations off the air, the Pacific
Daily News said.
   Airline flights into the republic were canceled, the newspaper
said.
   Earlier Sunday, the typhoon's winds battered Yap Island in the
neighboring Federated States of Micronesia, collapsing about 30
houses and damaging banana and coconut plantations, police said.
There were no reports of injuries on Yap.
   On Friday, Typhoon Ofelia swept over the eastern coast of Luzon,
the main Philippine island, then struck Taiwan. Officials said at
least 30 people were killed in the Philippines and at least seven
in Taiwan.
   More than 84,000 people in the Philippines were forced to flee
their homes because of flooding and landslides touched off by
Ofelia, officials said. Officials were still assessing damage to
crops and infrastructure.
   About 20 typhoons and tropical storms strike the Philippines
each year.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0069 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 2315EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Mandela 7thLd-Writethru a0790 06-24 1240</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mandela, 7th Ld-Writethru, a0790,1,100</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mandela Criticizes Aid to Savimbi</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: 1st and 4th grafs to CORRECT spelling of guerrillas and
guerrilla</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By JOAN MOWER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Nelson Mandela criticized U.S. aid to
non-communist guerrillas in Angola on Sunday shortly after he
arrived in Washington for meetings with President Bush and
congressional leaders.
   The pointed remarks were a sure sign that the African leader's
three-day visit to the U.S. capital will have a decidedly more
business-like flavor than his first four days in the United States,
which were marked by a round of enthusiastic rallies and
appearances that drew hundreds of thousands of supporters in New
York and Boston.
   It is here where Mandela must make his case for continued U.S.
economic sanctions against South Africa's government and press
other items on his political agenda.
   During an unusual 20-minute question-and-answer session with
reporters and editors from black-owned media concerns, Mandela said
the United States should not be providing assistance to Jonas
Savimbi, a guerrilla fighter seeking to overthrow the Angolan
government.
   ``The United States and South Africa are the main countries that
support Savimbi,'' he said. ``We strongly condemn that because ...
independent countries should respect the political sovereignty and
territorial integrity of Angola and no assistance should be
rendered to Savimbi.''
   Although questions were limited to representatives of
black-owned media, other reporters were allowed to monitor the
event.
   Mandela said he had not broached the subject of Angola with
South Africa's white government and he refused to divulge what he
is going to tell Bush when they meet Monday.
   Nevertheless, Mandela was explicit in saying ``no assistance''
should be given Savimbi's rebels, who have waged war for nearly 20
years against the Soviet and Cuban-backed Angolan government.
   Several of the reporters who were allowed to ask questions
praised Mandela and asked what they could do to help the
anti-apartheid struggle.
   ``Apartheid is still there,'' Mandela said. ``It is therefore
necessary for you to continue to put pressure on your government
and Congress'' to continue sanctions.
   Moreover, he said the African National Congress, with 20,000
exiles and enormous financial needs for new programs, must have
money. ``Take part in the campaign to raise funds for the ANC,''
Mandela said.
   In a lighter vein, when one reporter asked about his health the
71-year-old leader said ``why don't you arrange a ball (a dance)
and take me on.''
   Asked whether he could control militant ANC youth in South
Africa, Mandela acknowledged they are militant but that they also
``are highly disciplined'' and take orders from their leaders.
   He showed no bitterness about having spent 27 years in jail,
saying he didn't want to dwell on the past. ``Let bygones, be
bygones,'' he said when asked specifically about reports that the
CIA had helped arrange his arrest in the early 1960s.
   When one of the reporters asked Mandela whether he would help
end vestiges of racism in the United States, the South African
responded, ``We are prepared to be guided by the black leadership.''
   At a brief airport arrival ceremony earlier, Mandela had said he
was ``greatly encouraged'' by his rousing reception in the United
States.
   ``I come here to put the message out that sanctions must be
intensified, and to ask for resources so we could be able to
address the problems that are facing our country today,'' said the
ANC deputy president.
   ``We have been greatly encouraged by the rousing reception which
the American people in New York and Boston have given us. They have
left us with the distinct impression that in this country we have
our brothers and sisters who are committed to the fight against
racial oppression in our country,'' Mandela said.
   Mandela noted that recent concessions by South African President
F.W. de Klerk ``have raised the hope for peace.'' But he said the
government yielded ``not because of a change of heart but because
of the pressure put on the government inside the country and of the
international community generally.''
   Before getting down to business, the Mandela motorcade took the
scenic route into town from National Airport, winding across the
Potomac River and past the Lincoln Memorial and the Washington
Monument. There was little traffic on the streets and no crowds
lining the way.
   Once he reached the Madison Hotel, however, Manela was greeted
by hundreds of people lined up behind ropes on the sidewalk across
the street from the hotel. Some danced and waved banners. Security
was tight.
   His only other announced events Sunday were a reception for
African diplomats and a visit to a meeting between ANC members and
South African exiles living in the Washington area. Both were
closed to reporters.
   Mandela's wife, Winnie, attended a church service Sunday
afternoon to honor South African women.
   Washington Mayor Marion Barry, on trial on drug and perjury
charges, was not present at airport welcoming ceremonies, but Leila
McDowell of the communications company helping with the Mandela
arrangements said the mayor was invited. She said the mayor said he
would not be able to attend because of his trial. Barry's wife and
son were among those greeting Mandela.
   On Monday, Mandela meets with Bush and Secretary of State James
A. Baker III. On Tuesday, he becomes one of only a handful of
private citizens who have addressed a joint session of Congress.
   ``Mr. Mandela is a working statesman,'' said Roger Wilkins,
national coordinator of Mandela's visit. ``This is a visit to
official Washington, really.''
   During his three-day stay, he also will speak to 19,000 people
at a sold-out rally at the Washington Convention Center and visit
labor leaders.
   In advance of Mandela's arrival, Assistant Secretary of State
Herman Cohen told reporters that Bush and other U.S. officials are
eager to hear Mandela's view on how he envisions a post-apartheid
society in South Africa.
   ``The main emphasis of the meeting (with Bush) is negotiations
and how to we help promote negotiations,'' Cohen said.
   The ANC and the de Klerk government held their first talks last
month over obstacles to negotiations for a new constitution.
Mandela has said the next problem to resolve is who sits at the
negotiating table.
   Cohen said that among the questions U.S. officials have for
Mandela is what would be the format for negotiations, what are his
constitutional ambitions for South Africa and what are his economic
models.
   The United States also disagrees with Mandela's unbridled
support for Cuban leader Fidel Castro, Libyan leader Moammar
Gadhafi and Palestine Liberation Organization chief Yasser Arafat.
Mandela says he won't criticize their human rights records because
they've been strong backers of the anti-apartheid movement.
   Jesse Jackson, who is promoting Mandela's visit, said Sunday on
NBC-TV's ``Meet the Press'' program that Mandela's support for
Castro must be put in an African context. Castro sent Cuban troops
to help drive South Africans out of Angola, Jackson noted.
   Cohen said the United States can't relax sanctions, which
include a ban on new U.S. investment in South Africa and a trade
embargo on items such as oil and agricultural products, until the
white government meets a list of conditions set out in the 1986
Comprehensive Anti-Apartheid Act.
   De Klerk has satisfied all of those conditions with the
exception of two: releasing all political prisoners and lifting a
state of emergency in the Natal province, where ANC members are
waging a bloody political battle with the supporters of Chief
Mangosuthu Buthelezi, who heads the Zulu-dominated Inkatha movement.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0070 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 2323EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-LULAC-Campaign     06-24 0399</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-LULAC-Campaign,0415</SECOND>
<HEAD>LULAC Rejects Old Guard; Incumbent Concedes Before Vote</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ALBUQUERQUE, N.M. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A new slate of officers for the
nation's oldest Hispanic advocacy group was elected by acclamation
Sunday during a raucous convention that ended with a pledge of
unity.
   ``We will work together,'' said Jose Velez after he was sworn in
as president.
   The League of United Latin American Citizens, which has 110,000
members, is the nation's oldest and largest Hispanic advocacy
organization.
   Its 61st annual convention, held here this week, was rife with
accusations of vote-buying and election fraud.
   Proceedings were stopped often during Sunday's general assembly
as delegates tried to shout each other down over parliamentary
procedure.
   Disgruntled supporters of outgoing two-term president Jose
Garcia De Lara accused Velez, a Las Vegas entrepreneur, of buying
the presidency.
   Velez supporters said De Lara, a San Antonio, Texas, architect,
used heavy-handed tactics to maintain power like suspending and
expelling members.
   But both camps called the convention atmosphere standard LULAC
operating procedure and a healthy expression of the democratic
process.
   ``Sometimes Latinos are so Americanized that they do the same
things Democrats and Republicans do,'' Arnold Torres, LULAC
national political adviser, said Friday.
   Sunday's real battle centered on whether 43 recently formed
local councils, made up primarily of Velez supporters, would be
able to vote.
   Most of the local councils are made up of Filipino-Americans
from California, and the De Lara supporters argued that LULAC's
constitution says the bodies must be at least two-thirds Hispanic.
   They said Velez's effort to bring in the Filipino-American
contingent amounted to vote-buying.
   Velez supporters countered that De Lara was trying to limit his
opponent's backing by keeping the councils out.
   After hours of unruly debate, a roll call vote was ordered
Sunday afternoon to decide the council question.
   About 40 votes before the tally would have been final, De Lara
suddenly appeared on stage and withdrew his candidacy, saying,
``The people have spoken.''
   With a graciousness rarely seen during the four-day convention,
De Lara pledged his full support to Velez as the two men stood
arm-in-arm.
   One by one, all other incumbents then withdrew.
   At a news conference later, Velez said an early order of
business would be returning LULAC's national headquarters to
Washington, D.C., from San Antonio.
   Velez also said he would investigate all suspensions and
expulsions under De Lara and review all lawsuits in which LULAC is
involved.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0071 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 2328EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ComatoseBoy 2ndLd-Writethru a0784 06-24 0486</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Comatose Boy, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0784,0496</SECOND>
<HEAD>2-Year-Old Battered Boy Dies in Coma After Life Support Removed</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 6th graf, `An autopsy ...,' to CORRECT that coroner from
Allegheny County sted Warren and clarify that he ruled death
homicide. Picks up 7th graf pvs: `Warren County ...'</NOTE>
<DATELINE>PITTSBURGH (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A 2{-year-old boy who spent all but seven
weeks of his life in a coma after a severe beating by his mother
has died after his father allowed the hospital to turn off life
support machinery.
   A coroner said Sunday that the boy's death was a homicide that
resulted from the December 1987 beating.
   ``This was the most difficult decision of my life,'' David M.
Crane said in a statement. His son, Leslie Michael Crane, died
Saturday.
   Hospital officials had urged Crane for a year to permit them to
turn off Leslie's respirator, but Crane would not because he feared
his wife could then face murder charges.
   Tracey Jean Crane, 26, of Warren County was convicted in 1988 of
assault for beating her son repeatedly after his birth on Oct. 16,
1987.
   An autopsy showed Leslie died Saturday of brain injuries
suffered in a December 1987 beating, said Allegheny County Coroner
Joshua Perper, who ruled the death a homicide.
   Warren County District Attorney Joseph A. Massa Jr. said he
expected to announce Monday whether he will file any new charges
against Mrs. Crane, who is serving a six- to 20-year prison
sentence.
   The child was 7 weeks old when he was admitted to Children's
Hospital of Pittsburgh with a severe brain injury he suffered in a
beating by Mrs. Crane. His leg had been broken and his skull
fractured in two earlier beatings.
   Leslie remained in a vegetative state for the rest of his life,
connected to the respirator. The baby grew teeth and gained weight,
but showed no other signs of improving.
   ``It was apparent the first hour he was here that he was a
profoundly injured child and it was unlikely we could make any kind
of a difference,'' said Dr. Ann Thompson, director of critical care
medicine at Children's Hospital.
   The boy died at 2:29 a.m. Saturday. Hospital officials declined
to say when they shut off the respirator.
   ``I became convinced that morally, ethically and practically, it
was time to commit Leslie to the mercy of God,'' said Crane, of
Turtle Creek. His statement was issued by his attorney, George C.
Entenmann.
   Children's Hospital president Edwin K. Zechman Jr. said the
hospital had planned to ask the court to appoint a new guardian for
the child.
   Costs in the hospital's respiratory care unit run about $1,000 a
day. Hospital spokeswoman Lynn McMahon would not say how the bills
were being paid.
   Entenmann would not comment on whether Crane had agreed to allow
the life-support removal in exchange for leniency for his wife.
   The lawyer said the boy's burial arrangements would be private.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0072 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 1557EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-DigestBriefs 1stLd-Writethru a0709 06-24 0691</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Digest Briefs, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0709,0714</SECOND>
<NOTE>EDS: Retransmitting a0709 to fix number. DELETES reference to 1st
add; no add will move.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The economic merger of the Germanys on July 1
probably will be a double-edged sword for the rest of Europe.
   Experts feel it will spur general economic growth and speed the
march toward a single European market, but also may give West
Germany, already the strongest economy by far, even more influence
over the continent's economic affairs.
   The Germans believe they have a strategy that will merge the two
economies with minimum shock to the rest of Europe, but there are
unknowns.
   If the union increases inflation, German interest rates may rise
and the other Western European economies, linked in an
exchange-rate system, may have to follow.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>HARRISONBURG, Va. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A man and his two sons lost in a cave
for five days without food or water survived by sitting quietly to
save energy and reciting Bible scriptures to remain hopeful, the
father said Sunday.
   ``Toward the end, we figured we were going to die,'' Gary Lutes
said. ``We were happy it would be all three of us together and not
just one. We figured that was better than continuing on like that.''
   Lutes, 37, a Tampa, Fla., land surveyor, and sons Gary Jr., 13,
and Timothy, 9, were rescued from a West Virginia cave Saturday,
state police said. They had been lost since Monday.
   They were taken to Rockingham Memorial Hospital in Harrisonburg,
Va., where they were listed in stable condition Sunday.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Sen. Dave Durenberger was cautioned by his
attorney in 1986 about accepting government reimbursement for stays
in a Minneapolis condominium, according to documents, despite his
contention this month that he had no reason to doubt the propriety
of the plan.
   Durenberger, R-Minn., collected $40,055 in per diem payments
from the Senate from 1983 to 1989 for staying in the condominium.
He was part owner from 1983 to 1987, and says he sold the facility
in April 1987 _ a deal called a sham by the special counsel for the
Senate Ethics Committee.
   The propriety of Durenberger accepting reimbursement for staying
in the condominium _ with a bedroom, bathroom, kitchen and sitting
area _ is one of the principal areas of investigation for the
Senate panel.
   After a 15-month investigation of alleged financial
irregularities by the 55-year-old Republican, the committee soon
will decide whether he willfully violated the rules and deserves
punishment.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>LANSING, Mich. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Republicans can't wait to get their hands
on an upcoming book by the ex-wife of Democratic Gov. James
Blanchard. Nervous Democrats wish they could put it on hold until
after the November elections.
   Paula Blanchard says both sides are overreacting. Her book
covering the 1987 breakup of her 21-year marriage to Blanchard is
due out in July.
   Blanchard, who last year married Janet Fox, his former
secretary, is favored for re-election this fall over likely GOP
opponent John Engler, the state Senate majority leader.
   Paula Blanchard's book _ ``'Til Politics Do Us Part'' _ is a
question mark in the campaign, but Michigan's former first lady
predicts it won't affect the election.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WEST SPRINGFIELD, Mass. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   They came from the across the
tracks, and the more they were snubbed, the closer they became. The
immigrant kids are retired now, but they still celebrate their
exploits as members of the ``Deadline Gang.''
   The youthful alliances forged during the 1920s and 1930s will be
renewed this Saturday when the gang _ children of immigrants who
moved to western Massachusetts in the 1900s _ gets together for a
sixth time.
   The memories come tumbling out when members of the ``Deadline
Gang,'' recall growing up in a gritty railroad town when the
century was young.
   For Lester Lamothe, it was picking nuggets of reusable coal from
the piles dumped at the railroad yards. For Cy Conner, it was
playing ``the whip,'' hanging on to the back of a Model T spinning
across a frozen river. For John DeChaine, it was swiping ears of
corn to roast on summer bonfires.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0073 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 1355EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-CurrencyMarkets     06-24 0311</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Currency Markets,0322</SECOND>
<HEAD>The West German Mark's Future is Anybody's Guess</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Germany-Europe, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Foreign exchange dealers agree the first trading
day after the powerful West German mark becomes East Germany's
currency should be calm, but what happens next is a matter of
argument.
   July 1, when the merger takes place, is ``a special day of
course ... in particular for the history of this country, but in
economic terms, the world will not be so different from June 30,''
said Peter Pietsch, an economist with Commerzbank in Frankfurt.
   West Germany will convert East German marks at the generous 1-1
rate for the first 4,000 and 2-1 above that total.
   The government is printing 120 billion marks _ $70 billion _ for
the conversion, which will increase West Germany's money supply by
10 percent.
   Recently, the mark has been strong in relation to the dollar and
Japanese yen, against which it floats freely, but weaker within the
nine-currency European Monetary System, which limits its movements.
   Bulls believe the mark will be pushed higher by Germany's
expected economic expansion and possible increases in interest
rates to check inflation. Bears worry about political uncertainty
and inflation.
   Robin Aspinall, director of currency economics at the London
investment firm Hoare Govett Ltd., sees a rise in value to 1.40
marks to the dollar from the current 1.68, and perhaps even to
parity in three or four years.
   ``You have the perfect conditions for a strong currency,'' he
said. ``It's right out of the textbook. Of the major currencies, I
would back the deutsche mark against all comers.''
   Pietsch expects an increase to 1.60 to the dollar within a year,
but no more.
   Stephen King, international economist with the London investment
firm James Capel and Co., feels the mark will weaken against the
dollar and yen, but rise against other European currencies.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0074 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 1522EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-Germany-UnityCosts     06-24 0283</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Germany-Unity Costs,0292</SECOND>
<HEAD>Sources Say First Unified Budget Will Have 45 Billion Mark Debt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BONN, West Germany (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The first federal budget of a unified
Germany in 1991 will be in deficit by more than 45 billion marks,
or $28 billion, West German government financial sources say.
   According to a draft report from the West German finance
ministry, a copy of which was obtained Sunday by The Associated
Press, 14 billion marks, or $8.75 billion, of the 1991 deficit will
be the result of absorbing the East German budget after unification.
   The report also estimated East Germany would receive about 22
billion marks ($14 billion) in the second half of 1990 and 35
billion marks ($22 billion) in 1991 to help cover unification costs.
   The money would come from the German Unity Fund, a venture set
up by the West German government to raise money on the bond market
to help finance unification, the report said.
   On July 1, East Germany will merge its economy with West
Germany, ruled by the powerful West German mark, and shed 40 years
of rigid socialist economic policy for free-market rule.
   West Germany's portion of the 1991 estimated deficit, 31.46
billion marks or $19.7 billion, compares with an actual 1989
deficit of 19 billion marks, or $12 billion.
   The draft report says total German government expenditures in
1991 are expected to be 324 billion marks ($202 billion). Revenues
are expected to total 292.5 billion marks ($183 billion).
   West Germans are worried how much unification may cost them in
terms of either higher taxes or inflation, but Chancellor Helmut
Kohl's government has promised no new taxes. The report also said
higher taxes would not be necessary.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0075 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 1702EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-S&amp;Ls     06-24 0615</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-S&amp;Ls,0640</SECOND>
<HEAD>Thornburgh Defends Administration's Attack on S&amp;L Fraud</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also on general news wires.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT NAYLOR JR.</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Attorney General Dick Thornburgh on Sunday
fired back at critics who say the Bush administration is not moving
aggressively to ferret out savings and loan fraud.
   ``We're going after savings and loans crooks, whether they're
Republicans or Democrats, North, South, East and West. And we've
compiled ... a very impressive record on that score,'' Thornburgh
said during an appearance on the CBS-TV program ``Face the Nation.''
   His comments came as Treasury Secretary Nicholas Brady said it
was time for Democrats and Republicans to stop trying to affix
blame for the S&amp;L scandal and concentrate on catching culprits.
   Brady, appearing on ABC-TV's ``This Week With David Brinkley''
program, agreed with members of Congress who have said the focus
should shift from fingerpointing to prosecuting S&amp;L industry
officials who violated the laws.
   ``What the American people want is a dedicated, organized, calm
approach to cleaning up the problem (and) ... make sure to
prosecute the criminals involved,'' Brady said.
   Brady recently revised the Bush administration's estimate on the
cost of the savings and loan bailout to as high as $130 billion.
   Thornburgh denied that prosecutors have targeted lower-level
employees of failed institutions rather than top officials.
   ``I think the record clearly indicates the contrary. You've seen
executive after executive convicted, sentenced to jail,'' he said.
   But Thornburgh couldn't say how many new indictments have been
obtained since Bush took office in January 1989.
   ``There's a continuum there of activity on (the part of) the
Department of Justice,'' he said. ``We don't keep score by who's
the president at the time.''
   Members of Congress have criticized the slow pace of
prosecutions in the saving and loans scandal. But administration
officials have said the investigations of financial mismanagement
and fraud are extremely complicated and will take time to resolve.
   Thornburgh said Sunday that something ``more important than the
numbers'' should be addressed, ``and that's the commitment.''
   Administration officials said last week there were 791 fraud
convictions in 1989 and $100 million in stolen funds was recovered.
   Sen. Pete Domenici, R-N.M., urged against focusing on which
political party is more to blame for the savings and loan debacle,
saying ``that's history. We ought to go after the crooks.''
   Rep. Leon Panetta, D-Calif., chairman of the House Budget
Committee, said that while a Republican administration failed to
adequately regulate the savings and loan industry, Congress also
should bear some of the blame. ``The issue is, do we go after those
involved?'' said Panetta.
   In recent days members of the Bush administration have said the
Democratic-controlled Congress should accept part of the blame for
the S&amp;L mess.
   Likewise, Democrats have been quick to claim that the crisis
emerged largely because of lax regulation of the savings and loans
by the Republican Reagan administration.
   Brady, meanwhile, said Sunday that the government should dispose
of real estate holdings acquired as part of the growing savings and
loan scandal even if it has to offer more favorable discounts.
   ``The government shouldn't be in the real estate business,'' he
said on the ABC program.
   As part of the bailout of the ailing savings and loan industry,
the Resolution Trust Corp. is selling about 36,000 properties,
originally valued at $14.9 billion, often at discount.
   Most of the properties are in Texas, although they are scattered
through 45 states.
   Brady said Sunday that part of the increased cost estimate of
the S&amp;L cleanup was sagging real estate industry which has affected
the sale of the distressed properties held by the RTC.
   The RTC was created to administer the savings and loan cleanup.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0076 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 1855EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f BC-OECD-ForeignAid     06-24 0517</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-OECD-Foreign Aid,0533</SECOND>
<HEAD>Japan Overtakes U.S. As World's Biggest Aid Donor</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Japan surpassed the United States to become the
biggest donor of government aid to the Third World in 1989, the
Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development said.
   The achievement could soften criticism that Japan, with its
immense financial strength, has not done its share to help
developing countries.
   Japan's total aid effort in 1989 was $9 billion, compared with
$7.7 billion for the U.S., the Paris-based organization of
industrial democracies said in a report.
   The U.S. figure represented a decline of 27 percent from 1988,
after adjusting for inflation. The decline meant that U.S. aid as a
share of gross national product declined from 0.21 percent in 1988
to 0.15 percent last year _ the worst performance among the OECD's
main aid donor countries.
   Joseph Wheeler, chairman of the OECD's Development Assistance
Committee, told a news conference Sunday the U.S. aid figure for
1989 understates the U.S. effort in the same way the 1988 total
overstated aid disbursements.
   If U.S. contributions to multilateral aid institutions were
spread evenly over the two years instead of bunched more heavily in
1988, Wheeler said, the level each year would have been $8.9
billion, equivalent to 0.18 percent of GNP in 1988 and 0.17 percent
in 1989.
   But the OECD said U.S. bilateral aid to the Third World has
fallen steadily in recent years.
   Wheeler said he expects the U.S. will lift its aid effort to at
least $9 billion this year. He said U.S. contributions to
multilateral aid institutions should return to normal levels in
1990, and substantial new aid programs in Central America are
likely.
   But this probably won't be enough to enable the U.S. to regain
its number one slot, Wheeler said, since Japan plans to spend at
least $31 billion on aid over the next three years.
   Wheeler said government assistance to developing countries from
all sources in 1989 totalled $51.3 billion, scarecely changed from
the year-earlier figure of $51.7 billion. The total resource flow _
including private funds and export credits _ to these countries is
estimated at $109 billion, up 4.5 percent from 1988.
   Wheeler said the aid effort of the OECD's 18 richest countries
has increased in real terms at an average rate of 2.9 percent a
year, or a total of about 33 percent in the past decade.
   Wheeler said the aid effort of Western industrialized nations in
1989 wasn't affected by assistance to Eastern Europe. Most donor
countries have indicated future aid to Eastern Europe won't be
diverted from traditional aid recipients, he said.
   The OECD said Scandinavian countries continued to provide the
most official aid last year as a percentage of GNP, led by Norway
with 1.02 percent.
   The OECD's member nations are: Australia, Austria, Belgium,
Britain, Canada, Denmark, Finland, France, Greece, Iceland,
Ireland, Italy, Japan, Luxembourg, the Netherlands, New Zealand,
Norway, Portugal, Spain, Sweden, Switzerland, Turkey, the United
States and West Germany.
   The third biggest donor by dollars, after Japan and the U.S.,
was France with $5.14 billion followed by West Germany with $4.95
billion.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900624-0077 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-24-90 2028EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f BC-GasPrices     06-24 0166</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Gas Prices,0172</SECOND>
<HEAD>Survey Says Gas Prices Down Four-Tenths of a Cent</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Gasoline prices dropped slightly over the
past two weeks as retailers passed along a decline in wholesale gas
prices, according to a nationwide survey of retailers.
   The average price for a gallon of gas, including all taxes, was
117.68 cents a gallon on June 22, down 0.42 cents from June 8, the
Lundberg Survey said Sunday.
   Retailers passed through lower wholesale prices in most places,
but not on the West Coast, said survey manager Trilby Lundberg.
Refinery output there was affected by summer pollution control laws
and retail demand continued strong, Lundberg said.
   The average prices at self-service stations, which now account
for about 83 percent of all retail sales: regular unleaded, 105.83
cents a gallon; premium unleaded, 123.08 cents a gallon, regular
leaded, 106.44 cents a gallon.
   At full-service stations: regular unleaded, 132.31 cents a
gallon; premium unleaded, 145.97 cents a gallon; regular leaded,
129.31 cents a gallon.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
</Collection>
