<Collection>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0001 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-PX-08-19-90 2322EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-IndianUprising 1stLd-Writethru a0723 08-19 0860</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Indian Uprising, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0723,0884</SECOND>
<HEAD>War Not Over, But Important Battle Won</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS one graf for 12th `Ojibwa Indians...' to UPDATE with
agreement reached to lift one Indian blockade; pickup graf 13
`There are...'</NOTE>
<HEAD>An AP News Analysis</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JEFFREY ULBRICH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>OKA, Quebec (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   For perhaps the first time in a century,
North American Indians have taken up arms against the white man and
won an important battle.
   The war is far from over, but the lesson from the six-week
confrontation between Mohawks and the forces of law and order seems
to be that violence and militancy get public attention _ and public
attention leads to action.
   The situation has evolved considerably since July 11, when the
provincial police launched an ill-advised attack on a small group
of Mohawk militants blocking a road through Kanesatake reserve at
Oka, just west of Montreal on the St. Lawrence River.
   The police were repulsed and an officer was killed, though it is
still unclear by whom.
   To the south of Montreal, in the bedroom community of
Chateauguay, Mohawks from the Kahnawake reserve set up a sympathy
blockade, shutting down the Mercier bridge vital to commuters who
work in the city.
   Since then there has been a steady war of nerves, growing anger
on the part of frustrated south shore residents, three nights of
rioting last week and on-again, off-again talks.
   On Thursday, serious negotiations finally got under way and the
army began preparations over the weekend to replace the weary
police on the barricades.
   Ostensibly, the fuss was over the village of Oka's plan to
expand its nine-hole golf course on land the Indians claim is
theirs, including a sacred burial ground. The golf course question
was resolved when the federal government agreed to purchase the
land and turn it over to the Mohawks.
   But the land claim issue is much wider and much more complicated
here, and it goes far beyond the Mohawks at Kanesatake and
Kahnawake.
   ``Any outcome at Oka short of a bloodbath will send a powerful
message to native people across Canada whose grievances far
outweigh those of Kanesatake,'' wrote University of Toronto
historian Desmond Morton.
   ``Even the massive land claims settlement in the western Arctic,
proudly announced last spring, is now in a state of collapse while
native leaders wait to see whether Oka tactics produce better
terms.''
   Ojibwa Indians in Ontario jumped on the bandwagon and cut all
east-west rail traffic to support their land claims. One band set
up a blockade at Longlac and another group cut rail traffic east of
White River, north of Lake Superior. However, authorities said
Sunday that the Longlac group had agreed to end their blockade.
   There are thousands of Indian land claims pending before the
federal government, covering about two-thirds of Canada's
territory. The government actively processes only six at a time and
typically settlements take 20 years or more.
   Quebec Premier Robert Bourassa, who called on the army for help,
seems to have only two options, neither of them good.
   He can again try to dislodge the Indians by force, in front of a
worldwide television audience and international observers. Or he
can surrender to the pressure and negotiate with gun-toting
militants who clearly have broken the law. He has opted for the
second.
   The situation on the ground now is being watched by 24 observers
from the Paris-based International Federation of Human rights. The
negotiation process has been sealed off.
   The Quebec public was horrified last week when it saw a federal
minister, a provincial minister and a judge sit down with armed,
masked Indians to sign a document on a format for talks.
   The image remains indelible.
   ``Did you see that scene here with the ministers?'' lamented
Yvan Patry, mayor of Oka Parish, which surrounds both the village
of Oka and the Kanesatake reserve.
   Both sides in the conflict have clammed up since the beginning
of talks. They say they have agreed not to speak about the
negotiations, not even what is on the agenda.
   Tom Siddon, the federal minister of Indian affairs, claims that
promises to reopen land claim talks with the Mohawks have nothing
to do with the blockades in Oka and Chateauguay.
   ``I don't in any way agree with any suggestion that we have
agreed to negotiate in the face of guns,'' said Siddon. ``We will
not.''
   Appearances, however, are to the contrary.
   The Kanesatake reserve is a patchwork of Indian territory with
pieces separated by privately owned land. There had been earlier
talks about finding a way to join up the various patches of Mohawk
land.
   What the federal and provincial governments clearly fear is
setting a dangerous precedent.
   ``Blockades will not result in any band being allowed to jump
the queue in the claims process,'' the minister vowed.
   One thing is certain. The barricades will come down one day
soon, and it appears likely that the band of Mohawk warriors who
held off the forces of the white man will walk away with their
heads held high and an inspiration for their brothers elsewhere.
   And that is, perhaps, the biggest concern of the Canadian
authorities.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0002 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-PX-08-19-90 2348EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Obit-Skinner-Books     08-19 0110</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Obit-Skinner-Books,0128</SECOND>
<HEAD>With PM-Obit-Skinner, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Here is a list of psychologist B.F. Skinner's books:
   ``The Behavior of Organisms'' 1938
   ``Walden Two'' 1948
   ``Science and Human Behavior'' 1953
   ``Verbal Behavior'' 1957
   ``Schedules of Reinforcement (with Charles B. Ferster) 1957
   ``Cumulative Record'' 1959, revised 1961, 1972
   ``The Analysis of Behavior'' (with James G. Holland) 1961
   ``The Technology of Teaching'' 1968
   ``Contingencies of Reinforcement: A Theoretical Analysis'' 1969
   ``Beyond Freedom and Dignity'' 1971
   ``About Behavorism'' 1974
   ``Particulars of My Life'' 1976
   ``Reflections on Behavorism and Society'' 1978
   ``The Shaping of a Behavorist'' 1979
   ``Notebooks'' 1980
   ``A Matter of Consequences'' 1983
   ``Enjoy Old Age'' 1983
   ``Upon Further Reflection'' 1986
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0003 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-PX-08-19-90 2346EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w PM-BicycleRecall CORRECTIVE   08-19 0110</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Bicycle Recall, CORRECTIVE,0110</SECOND>
<HEAD>Members who used the first item about a bicycle recall in a0436,
PM-Washington in Brief, sent Aug. 16 under a Washington dateline,
are asked to use the following story.</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An Associated Press story Friday concerning
the recall of 1,600 ``Randonneur'' bicycles which may have
defective front forks contained erroneous information about how to
identify the model years involved and an incorrect telephone number
for consumers to call.
   Only those bicycles that do not have a letter ``B'' on the fork
crown are subject to the recall. The correct number for owners to
call to check whether their bicycles are involved is 1-800-669-6400.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0004 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-PX-08-19-90 2348EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Lite-SpaceTrip     08-19 0229</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Lite-Space Trip,0235</SECOND>
<HEAD>`Space Baby' Wants to Trade Moon Trip for Earth Orbit</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HUNTSVILLE, Ala. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winner of a 1953 Space Baby contest
has a deal for NASA: Instead of honoring her ``official'' ticket
for a ride to the moon, let her orbit Earth aboard a space shuttle.
   Nancy Cavanagh, a fourth-grade teacher in Buckeye, Ariz., won
the ticket seven years before the creation of NASA. She was judged
the cutest baby at Redstone Arsenal Army Missile Command in
Huntsville, now known as Redstone Arsenal.
   Her father, Bruce Carpenter, was an electrical engineer for
Philco, an Army missile subcontractor. Today, NASA's Marshall Space
Flight Center is on the base.
   ``I think it would be wonderful ... and NASA wouldn't have to
take me as far as the ticket promises,'' Cavanagh said recently
while in Huntsville to attend U.S. Space Camp, an educational
program on space.
   ``I'd really like to go to the moon, but I'll settle for Earth
orbit.''
   ``NASA's not in the business of making trades like that,'' said
flight center spokesman Don Amatore. ``But if she wants to apply
for the Teacher-in-Space Program, I'm sure the agency would be glad
to look at her application.''
   The program was suspended after Challenger exploded in 1986. Its
first participant, Christa McAuliffe, died with the rest of the
shuttle's crew.
   Amatore said the program may someday resume.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0005 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-PX-08-19-90 2354EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a BC-LOT--SaturdayLotteries     08-19 0608</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-LOT--Saturday Lotteries,0729</SECOND>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<HEAD>ARIZONA</HEAD>
<HEAD>Pick</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PHOENIX (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers in Saturday-OR-Wednesday
night's drawing ottery's Pick game were 15, 16, 17,
21, 36 and 4f the Arizona Lo0 with a bonus number of 10.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>CALIFORNIA</HEAD>
<HEAD>Decco</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning playing card numbers picked Saturday night
for the California Lottery's daily ``Decco'' game:
   Hearts: Queen.
   Clubs: Two.
   Diamonds: Seven.
   Spades: Queen.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>DELAWARE</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DOVER, Del. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   These Delaware lotteries were drawn Saturday
night:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   3-7-3
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Play Four</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   1-5-5-8
</TEXT>
<HEAD>FLORIDA</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the wiRAINTREE, Mass. (AP) _ The winning numbers drawn Saturday
night
in the ``Massachusetts Daily Lottery'' were:
   5-4-3-0
</TEXT>
<HEAD>MICHIGAN</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DETROIT (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected Saturday in
the Michigan State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   2-3-7
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily-4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   9-8-1-3
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto 47</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   9, 15, 21, 33, 39, 40
</TEXT>
<HEAD>MINNESOTA</HEAD>
<HEAD>Daily 3</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MINNEAPOLIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers drawn Saturday night in
the Minnesota Daily 3 lottery game are:
   6-3-7
</TEXT>
<HEAD>MISSOURI</HEAD>
<HEAD>Pick 3</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ST. LOUIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers in Saturday's Missouri
Lottery Daily Pick 3 game:
   2-7-8
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ST. LOUIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers in Missouri's Lotto drawing
Saturday night:
   4-14-18-19-24-37
</TEXT>
<HEAD>NEW JERSEY</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TRENTON, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday night in the New Jersey State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 3</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   3-6-3
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   7-1-4-1
</TEXT>
<HEAD>NORTHERN NEW ENGLAND</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CONCORD, N.H. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the daily New Hampshire, Vermont and Maine lotteries:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 3</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   3-4-0
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   1-6-5-1
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Tri-State Megabucks</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CONCORD, N.H. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers in the
``Tri-State Megabucks'' game for New Hampshire, Vermont and Maine:
   11-13-16-21-25-38
</TEXT>
<HEAD>OREGON</HEAD>
<HEAD>Daily 4</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PORTLAND, Ore. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are Saturday's winning numbers in the
``Oregon Daily 4'' lottery game:
   6-1-9-6
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Megabucks</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PORTLAND, Ore. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are Saturday's winning numbers in the
``Oregon Megabucks'' lottery game:
   2-12-24-28-36-39
</TEXT>
<HEAD>PENNSYLVANIA</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HARRISBURG (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected Saturday
in the Pennsylvania State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Number</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   5-9-4
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Big 4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   4-5-8-4
</TEXT>
<HEAD>RHODE ISLAND</HEAD>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CRANSTON, R.I. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers in the Rhode Island
daily lottery drawing for Saturday were:
   3-5-1-7
</TEXT>
<HEAD>VIRGINIA</HEAD>
<HEAD>Pick 3</HEAD>
<DATELINE>RICHMOND (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   These numbers were drawn Saturday in the
Virginia Lotto Game:
   20-23-25-37-42-43
</TEXT>
<HEAD>WASHINGTON</HEAD>
<DATELINE>OLYMPIA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are winning numbers selected Saturday in the
Washington State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   0-3-1
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   14-17-18-26-29-33
</TEXT>
<HEAD>WASHINGTON, DC</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The following results were drawn Saturday in
the District of Columbia Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lucky Numbers Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   0-3-0
</TEXT>
<HEAD>D.C. Four Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   6-1-6-2
</TEXT>
<HEAD>D.C. Daily Double Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   6, 27
</TEXT>
<HEAD>D.C. Quick Cash Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   33-12-14-9-3-19
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0006 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-PX-08-19-90 2355EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Japan-Markets 1stLd-Writethru a0787 08-19 0253</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Japan-Markets, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0787,0259</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dollar Opens Higher, Share Prices Fall</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: UPDATES with morning Nikkei, dollar closing. No pickup.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Stock priced bounced higher Monday morning despite
deepening tension in the Middle East, while the dollar inched up
against the yen.
   The dollar closed the morning session at 147.52 yen, up 0.17 yen
from Friday's finish. It opened at 147.75 yen and fluctuated
between 147.35 and 147.77.
   The benchmark Nikkei Stock Average of 225 selected issues opened
lower but rebounded in late morning trading to 26,920.77, up 134.05
points or 0.50 percent from Friday's close. The index had lost
762.72 points on Friday.
   On the bond market, the No. 119 10-year Japanese government bond
was quoted at 83.25 points at 11:15 a.m. (10:15 p.m. Sunday EDT),
up from Friday's close of 83.21. The yield was 8.05 percent, down
from 8.06 percent.
   The dollar, which normally firms in times of international
crisis, has now gained 0.87 yen since Iraq invaded Kuwait on Aug. 2.
   Traders said the dollar would remain stronger with the Mideast
tension ongoing.
   Share prices bounced in thin trading late morning, fully
recovering losses made early in the session. Index-linked buying
helped lift the prices, dealers said.
   In the first section, an estimated 110 million shares changed
hands, down from 170 million shares Friday morning.
   Losing issues outnumbered winning issues 532 to 302, while 208
issues remained unchanged.
   Meanwhile, North Sea Brent crude oil for October delivery was
valued at $27-$27.20 a barrel, up from Friday's $26.10-$26.20.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0007 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-19-90 0028EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-GulfRdp 7thLd-Writethru   08-19 1025</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf Rdp, 7th Ld-Writethru,a0647,1057</SECOND>
<HEAD>First U.S. Shots Fired, Foreigners Become Iraqi Trump Card</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with three grafs to UPDATE with U.N. Security Council
resolution; Pickup 3rd pvs, `Iraq's statement...'</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto AMM7</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By THOMAS WAGNER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   U.S. warships fired the first shots by American forces in the
Persian Gulf crisis in an unsuccessful effort to halt two Iraqi
tankers, and Iraq said thousands of foreign captives will suffer
first if a U.S. ``blockade'' curtails food.
   Iraq's threat, which singled out foreign babies and elderly
people, was immediately denounced by the White House as an illegal
``use of innocent civilians as pawns'' in the Middle East standoff.
   The U.N. Security Council late Saturday unanimously demanded
that Iraq let all foreigners leave and that Baghdad ``take no
action to jeopardize the safety, security or health of such
nationals.''
   
   Iraq's statement, coupled with an earlier threat to use
Americans and other foreigners as a defensive shield for Iraqi
military installations, made it clear the foreigners have become a
central part of Iraq's anti-U.S. strategy.
   Iraq said Saturday it had begun moving some of the foreigners to
``strategic'' locations around the country.
   In Washington, the Pentagon said the USS Reid fired six warning
shots across the bow of the Iraqi ship Khanaqin in the Gulf of Oman
after it ``refused repeated requests to halt.''
   The shots were the first fired in the 2-day-old interdiction
effort ordered by President Bush to halt goods leaving and entering
Iraq.
   Also, the USS Bradley fired three warning shots across the bow
of another Iraqi tanker to the north in the Persian Gulf and headed
toward the Gulf of Oman, the Pentagon said.
   The Persian Gulf, which connects with the Gulf of Oman, is
Iraq's outlet to the sea.
   ``Both tankers are currently under way, but are under close U.S.
Navy surveillance,'' the Pentagon said. A Pentagon source who spoke
on condition of anonymity said Navy ships were unlikely to take
further action against the ships during nighttime hours.
   The Pentagon said the Iraqi vessels, which were heading out of
the Persian Gulf area, were believed carrying Iraqi oil.
   Baghdad said the tankers were not hit and continued on their
way, but that a similar act in the future will have ``grave
consequences.''
   Iraq's foreign minister, Tariq Aziz, said he did not consider
the Iraqi treatment of foreigners an act of war, merely an attempt
to prevent U.S. forces massing in Saudi Arabia from attacking Iraq
or Kuwait.
   ``Foreigners would live with the Iraqis in some places that are
the target of probable American aggression,'' Aziz told CBS News.
``That might deter the American government from committing the
crime that the Iraqi people would like to avoid.''
   In an interview Saturday with Britain's Independent Television
News, Iraqi Ambassador to France Abdul Razzak al-Hachimi said in
Paris: ``Some of them (the foreigners) ... have been distributed in
strategic installations in Iraq starting all the way from north of
Iraq to the south.''
   Thomas R. Pickering, the U.S. ambassador to the United Nations,
said later Saturday that Iraq's actions over the past 24 hours make
it clear that Iraqi President Saddam Hussein is ``going to hold
hostage all foreigners.''
   U.S. officials had previously avoided using the word ``hostage''
to refer to the Americans and other foreigners trapped in Iraq and
Kuwait.
   The British Foreign Office said 40 Britons, five Americans, four
Germans and one French citizen were moved from Kuwaiti hotels to
undisclosed locations. Aziz told CBS that Iraq will not use
chemicals weapons unless the United States uses nuclear weapons in
the conflict.
   However, Iraq's army newspaper on Saturday reiterated a threat
to use weapons of ``mass destruction'' against any attacker, an
apparent reference to Iraq's arsenal of long-range missiles, nerve
gas and mustard gas.
   The United States, meanwhile, continued to pour thousands of
troops into Saudi Arabia in an effort to build up a force that
could withstand an invasion by tens of thousands of Iraqi soldiers
massed on the Saudi-Kuwait border.
   For the first time since Iraq invaded Kuwait on Aug. 2 and later
annexed the emirate, U.S. troops stationed in the Saudi desert
conducted maneuvers at night in temperatures that still hovered
around 95 degrees.
   ``We're here sweating because our lives may depend on it,'' said
one private who carried a 50-pound pack Friday night. ``But it's
really not up to us. Our lives are in the politicians' hands.''
   ``Finding the courage is tough,'' said a medic traveling with
the soldiers. ``It's scary out here. But you've got to swallow that
and go out and do it.''
   In other developments:
   _President Bush prepared to call up military reserves to fill in
the ranks of military doctors, cargo handlers and other
specialists. An Army source said as many as 80,000 reservists and
National Guardsmen could be activated.
   _The Pentagon launched an unprecedented diversion of civilian
aircraft to bolster the U.S. military presence in the Middle East.
   _Defense Secretary Dick Cheney said the U.S. military commitment
to Saudi Arabia's defense is ``long-term.'' ``Where we'll be a year
or two from now, I wouldn't want to speculate,'' he said while en
route to Saudi Arabia.
   _Iraq, which made peace overtures to Iran in order to devote its
full attention to the standoff with the United States, withdrew
thousands of troops from its Iranian border and said they would be
deployed near Saudi Arabia.
   _Saudi Arabia said it is ready to increase its oil output by up
to 2 million barrels a day to help offset the shortfall caused by
the Iraqi invasion. But a Saudi minister said that would leave
world markets 2 million barrels short of pre-invasion levels, and
it may not halt soaring gas and oil prices.
   _Thousands of Arabs continued to reach Jordan after fleeing from
Iraq and Iraq-occupied Kuwait. The only Westerners to get out were
the few brave enough to dash for the border in private cars.
   The Baghdad government holds 3,000 Americans, 4,000 Britons and
about 14,000 other Westerners among the more than 2 million
foreigners caught in Iraq and Kuwait when Iraqi troops invaded
Kuwait on Aug. 2.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>In its, 1st graf, a0619</HEAD>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0008 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-19-90 0052EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Gulf-ChemicalWeapons 1stLd-Writethru a0653 08-19 0280</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Chemical Weapons, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0653,0284</SECOND>
<HEAD>Serviceman Says Some Military Don't Have Chemical Warfare Gear</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 6th graf to CLARIFY composition of unit and source's US
base.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By MICHELLE MITTELSTADT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DALLAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   About 120 troops stationed in Saudi Arabia are
sitting in the ``front seat of Armageddon'' without weapons or
equipment for chemical warfare, an non-commissioned officer said
Saturday.
   ``I want to have a fighting chance. I don't have that,'' said
Air Force Master Sgt. Johnnie Bratton in a phone interview from
Dhahran on Saturday night. ``I'm ready to go out and do whatever I
have to do but I don't have the minimum protection that is
required.''
   The thousands of American servicemen recently deployed to Saudi
Arabia are equipped for chemical warfare, but those who have been
there for months are not, he said.
   Bratton, a Vietnam veteran who has been in the military for 19{
years, said the Persian Gulf situation could evolve into another
long conflict, and troops should be protected every way possible.
   ``We're in the front seat of Armaggedon,'' he said.
   Bratton, of San Marcos, said he and 120 other troops have been
based at Dhahran, about 165 miles south of Kuwait, for up to two
years on training missions. He said his unit was composed of Air
Force, Army and Navy personnel and that he was based in Grand
Forks, N.D., declining to disclose further details.
   Bratton said he decided to speak to the news media after pleas
to his superiors, congressional leaders and others failed.
   The Pentagon had no immediate comment Saturday night.
   ``I don't have any knowledge of that,'' said Pentagon spokesman
Lt. Col. Stuart Wagner.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0009 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-19-90 0108EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Gulf-TankerIncident 4thLd-Writethru a0651 08-19 1039</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Tanker Incident, 4th Ld-Writethru, a0651,1069</SECOND>
<HEAD>Iraqi Tankers Continue After U.S. Ships Fire Warnings</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: SUBS grafs 26-31 pvs, `The captain...early Wednesday' to
CORRECT name of Sudan port, Saudi Arabian city; No pickup.</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   EDITORS: The following story is partly based on a pool dispatch
from journalists aboard the USS Eisenhower, with added detail from
Washington.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By SUSANNE SCHAFER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Military Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ABOARD THE USS EISENHOWER (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   U.S. Navy ships closely watched
two Iraqi tankers late Saturday after the oil-carrying vessels
ignored U.S. warning shots and headed out of the Persian Gulf area,
U.S. military officials said.
   A Navy officer told reporters with Defense Secretary Dick Cheney
aboard the USS Eisenhower in the Red Sea that the guided-missile
frigate USS Reid fired the first shots of the two-day-old
interdiction effort ordered by President Bush.
   The Pentagon later confirmed two Iraqi ships were warned with
gunfire in separate incidents and that both continued under the
watch of U.S. vessels. The Pentagon statement said both tankers
were believed carrying Iraqi oil.
   Officials aboard the ships said U.S. forces briefly went to
battle stations over the incidents. The U.S. operation is intended
to halt goods leaving and entering Iraq in the Persian Gulf crisis.
   ``Both tankers are currently under way, but are under close U.S.
Navy surveillance,'' according to a Pentagon statement issued late
Saturday, when it was already past midnight in the gulf.
   A Pentagon official in Washington, speaking on condition of
anonymity, said the Navy warships were unlikely to use any force
against the tankers during nighttime hours.
   The USS Reid fired six warning shots across the bow of an Iraqi
tanker that it intercepted in the Gulf of Oman, the Pentagon said.
   ``Initial reports indicate the Iraqi-flagged vessel Khanaqin
refused repeated requests to halt,'' and the Reid then fired the
warning shots, the Pentagon said.
   Also, the USS Bradley fired three warning shots across the bow
of another Iraqi tanker after it refused U.S. requests to halt, the
Pentagon said. The unidentified tanker was in the Persian Gulf,
heading toward the Gulf of Oman.
   The only Iraqi port from which oil could be shipped is at the
northern tip of the Persian Gulf, connected to the Gulf of Oman
through the Strait of Hormuz. The gulf opens up into the Arabian
Sea where oil-laden ships fan out to world ports. The Eisenhower is
on the other side of Saudi Arabia in the Red Sea.
   In Baghdad, Iraq reported that the United States had fired on
two Iraqi oil tankers that refused to be searched, and said a
similar act in the future would have ``grave consequences.''
   In the Red Sea, Capt. Morris Foote of the guided missile cruiser
Ticonderoga said, ``One of our frigates, out in the Gulf of Oman,
has fired a warning shot at an Iraqi tanker, in fact, fired six of
them.''
   The Ticonderoga was operating with the carrier Eisenhower in the
Red Sea on the opposite side of the Saudi Arabian peninsula from
the shooting incident.
   Foote later clarified that statement to say the shots were fired
across the bow of the tanker.
   Foote said the Persian Gulf forces initially went to battle
stations. The Eisenhower battle group, however, did not go on high
alert status during the shooting incident, and he said the Iraqi
tanker posed no apparent danger to U.S. forces.
   The Reid incident occurred about 4 p.m. local time (9 a.m. EDT),
south of the narrow entrance to the Persian Gulf from the Gulf of
Oman.
   Foote did not have details but other officers said they believed
the Iraqi ship had not stopped when ordered. Foote said warning
shots were fired by the Reid's 76 millimeter gun after the
frigate's commander received permission to do so from Rear Adm.
William Fogarty, commander of the Middle East task force in the
Persian Gulf.
   Iraqi Oil Minister Issam Chalabi said in Baghdad that U.S.
warships had fired on the Iraqi oil tanker Baba Karkar in the
Persian Gulf and the oil tanker Khanaqin in the Gulf of Oman.
   Chalabi said the shots fell in front and behind the ships and
they proceeded without stopping.
   Foote said there was apparently no threat from the Iraqi tanker
in the Gulf of Oman, which like all other commercial vessels should
not be armed.
   ``I don't think that there was any other provocation. I don't
think there was anything, in fact, threatening from the Iraqis or
from any other source,'' he said.
   ``But as a general course, when we start getting into the
business of firing shots, you're never sure of the reaction,'' he
said.
   On Thursday evening, President Bush authorized American warships
to use force if necessary to stop commerce headed to and from Iraq
and Kuwait, which is occupied by an estimated 160,000 Iraqi troops.
   Defense Department spokesman Pete Williams, accompanying Cheney
aboard the Eisenhower at the beginning of a four-day trip to the
region, refused to comment on the situation. Cheney was not
available for comment.
   While on board the destroyer USS Scott, Cheney was told that the
Scott had just returned from its interdiction duty at the mouth of
the Gulf of Aqaba and had turned back a Cypriot bulk freighter
headed for the port.
   The captain of the Scott said the Cypriot freighter was headed
for the port of Aqaba and had departed from Port Sudan, Sudan's
main Red Sea port.
   Scott Commander Tom Corcoran said he had a ``very polite
conversation'' with the master of the Cypriot ship and the
freighter turned around after reporting that it was carrying a
cargo of aluminum chromate and other chemicals.
   ``We didn't want to take the chance. We maneuvered at a safe but
fairly close distance and spoke on the radio,'' Corcoran told pool
reporters.
   He said the ship turned around and headed for an unknown
destination.
   Cheney was to remain on the Eisenhower until Sunday morning when
he was to travel to northern Saudi Arabia and visit American troops
deployed on land in the defense of the desert kingdoms' vital oil
fields.
   He was to travel on to Bahrain, and several other Persian Gulf
nations before visiting in Jiddah on Monday and stopping in Cairo
before arriving back in Washington early Wednesday.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0010 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-19-90 0129EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Gulf-UN 3rdLd-Writethru a0654 08-19 0769</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-UN, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0654,0812</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.N. Security Council Demands That Iraq Release Foreigners</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: INSERTS two grafs after 14th pvs, `Iraqi Ambassador...' to
UPDATE with comment from Iraqi, Kuwaiti ambassadors; Pickup 15th,
`Saturday's resolution...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By PETER JAMES SPIELMANN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>UNITED NATIONS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The U.N. Security Council on Saturday
unanimously demanded that Iraq let all foreigners leave, and the
U.S. ambassador accused Baghdad of holding them ``hostage.''
   Concern about thousands of Americans, West Europeans and
Japanese trapped in Iraq and Kuwait heightened after Iraq said
Friday foreigners from ``aggressive nations'' would be used as
defensive shields for Iraqi military installations.
   On Saturday, Iraq said some foreigners were moved to ``strategic
installations'' around the country.
   It also said the foreigners, including babies and the elderly,
would be among the first to suffer the privations of the
U.N.-ordered embargo on Iraq.
   In its resolution Saturday, the Security Council ``demands that
Iraq permit and facilitate the immediate departure from Kuwait and
Iraq of the nationals of third countries and grant immediate and
continuing access of consular officials to such nationals.''
   The resolution also demands that ``Iraq take no action to
jeopardize the safety, security or health of such nationals.''
   All 15 members of the council voted for the resolution. Yemen,
the only Arab nation on the council, voted for the resolution, but
its ambassador, Mohamed A. Sallam, said food should be allowed into
Iraq.
   The U.N. sanctions allow food and medicine shipments to Iraq for
humanitarian purposes.
   Meanwhile, U.N. Secretary-General Javier Perez de Cuellar
dispatched two senior U.N. officials to Baghdad to urge Iraqi
officials to safeguard the foreigners and let them leave.
   Earlier Saturday, U.S. Ambassador Thomas R. Pickering denounced
the latest moves by Iraqi President Saddam Hussein.
   ``We are now responding to the three steps which Saddam Hussein
has taken in the last 24 hours, including beginning a process of
sequestering foreign nationals, the announcement that he was going
to use them as military shields, and finally the statement this
morning in which it was clear he was going to hold hostage all
foreigners.''
   U.S. officials had previously avoided using the word ``hostage''
to describe the Americans and other foreigners trapped since the
Aug. 2 Iraqi invasion of Kuwait.
   Asked if he was aware of anyone being harmed or in danger in
Iraq or occupied Kuwait, Pickering said the United States was
concerned about people who might need routine medical treatment.
   Iraqi Ambassador Abdul Amir al-Anbari, speaking before the
Security Council, said the economic embargo of his country is
``unjust'' and called the U.S. ``blockade'' of food and medicines
to Iraqis a ``terrorist act.''
   ``Iraq will not prevent foreign nationals from obtaining
foodstuffs and medicines; it will share with foreign nationals what
comes in,'' al-Anbari said.
   The representative of the ousted Kuwaiti government, Mohammad
Saad Al Sallal, told the council the resolution addresses a
situation ``unprecedented in the whole history of the international
community ... the taking thousands, rather millions of citzens of
many countries as ransom.''
   Saturday's resolution was the fourth passed by the council
condemning Iraq since the invasion. The council previously
denounced the Iraqi invasion, imposed the trade embargo and
rejected the annexation of Kuwait.
   In the resolution, the council again declared the annexation of
Kuwait ``null and void, and therefore demands that the government
of Iraq rescind its orders for the closure of diplomatic and
consular missions in Kuwait and the withdrawal of the immunity of
their personnel. ...''
   Iraq has ordered all embassies in Kuwait to close, claiming the
country is now part of Iraq and diplomats should only be accredited
in Baghdad.
   U.N. spokesman Fred Eckhard said Perez de Cuellar is sending two
undersecretary-generals to Baghdad to discuss freedom of movement
for the foreigners in Iraq and Kuwait.
   The two U.N. officials, whom he did not name, are expected to
arrive in Baghdad early Monday.
   The Baghdad government holds 3,000 Americans, 4,000 Britons and
about 14,000 other Westerners among the more than 2 million
foreigners caught in Iraq and Kuwait when Iraq invaded Kuwait.
Thousands of Arabs, East Europeans and Soviets and Asians have been
allowed to cross into Jordan.
   A U.S.-led multinational force and an Arab force have been
deployed to keep Iraq from attacking Saudi Arabia and to impose the
trade embargo on Iraq.
   A statement read over Iraqi television and radio Saturday
referred to the U.S.-led quarantine as ``an act of war,'' and said
that as food and medicine become scarce, supplies will be set aside
for the military.
   ``We're outraged,'' Ambassador Sir Crispin Tickell of Britain
said earlier Saturday. ``It's almost incredible something like that
could happen.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0011 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-19-90 0426EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a BC-CentralParkJogger     08-19 0841</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Central Park Jogger,0863</SECOND>
<HEAD>Three Youths Convicted in Jogger Trial</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: STANDS as 7th Ld-Writethru to AM-Central Park Jogger, a0657.
SUBS 10th graf to CORRECT that only two of remaining three
defendants are free on bond.
^LaserPhoto NY28</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By SAMUEL MAULL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Three teen-agers were convicted Saturday of
raping and assaulting a woman jogger who was brutalized and left
for dead in Central Park by a marauding gang of youths.
   The defendants _ Antron McCray, 16, Yusef Salaam, 16 and Raymond
Santana, 15 _ were found innocent of sodomy and of attempted
murder, the most serious charge in the much-publicized case. They
also were convicted of riot.
   The three were jailed without bail. As juveniles, they faced a
maximum of 10 years in prison at sentencing Sept. 11.
   The 30-year-old jogger was found lying senseless in a pool of
blood after the April 19, 1989, attack. In a coma for two weeks,
she recovered enough to return to her investment banking job and
give dramatic testimony at the trial.
   The jury spent 10 days in deliberations, the last three
convincing one holdout who believed McCray was innocent. It also
took three days to consider the attempted murder charges, said
juror Charles Nestorick. The jury finally decided to acquit because
they believed the teen-agers didn't intend to kill.
   ``Youths that age are not well versed in how many blows it takes
to kill someone,'' Nestorick said.
   The case created enormous sympathy for the victim, whose name
was not printed by most newspapers. The defendants also had
supporters, who demonstrated outside the courthouse regularly,
charging racism because the victim was white and wealthy, the
youths black or Hispanic.
   Defense attorneys claimed police lied and threatened Santana and
McCray into making videotaped confessions. Salaam did not sign a
written statement or make a videotaped statement.
   Prosecutors said the three defendants were part of a gang of as
many as 30 youths who rampaged through the park, harassing at least
nine people. Three other teen-agers charged in the assault on the
woman await trial. Two are free on bond.
   Salaam, McCray and Santana also were convicted of assault and
robbery for attacks on two male joggers, John Loughlin and David
Lewis.
   The woman was jogging through the northern end of the park when
she was attacked. She was dragged about 70 feet into the woods,
gang-raped and bashed repeatedly with a brick and pipe.
   She recovered enough to resume work _ and jogging _ within eight
months of the attack. She is a vice president for Salomon Brothers,
a Wall Street firm.
   In a statement after the verdict, Mayor David Dinkins said the
attack ``seared the soul of every decent New Yorker.''
   ``We should recommit ourselves to building a city and forging a
society in which such heinous crimes do not occur,'' he said.
   While the woman's recovery was inspirational to many New
Yorkers, a few activists, including the Rev. Al Sharpton, claimed
police arrested the youths because most were black.
   Earlier Saturday, the jurors had asked for the fourth time to
see McCray's videotaped statement, in which he told police he
kicked the jogger and feigned sex with her to impress his friends.
   McCray's father, Bobby McCray, testified he encouraged his son
to lie to police because he was led to believe there was an
agreement that would allow his son to go free. The detective who
took the statement said no deal was offered.
   Another detective testified that Santana told him he counted 33
youths who entered the park shortly after 9 p.m. on the night of
the attack to ``beat up and rip off joggers and cyclists.''
   When the group saw the female jogger on her nightly six-mile
run, ``We all charged her,'' McCray said on the videotape. She
struggled and screamed as several teen-agers dragged her from the
paved drive down a wooded slope into the darkness, he said.
   The defendants told detectives the naked woman was struck with a
metal pipe, bashed in the head and face with a brick, cut on the
legs with a knife and sexually attacked in a frenzy of violence,
assistant District Attorney Elizabeth Lederer said.
   The trial's most riveting moment came when the jogger took the
witness stand. She walked unsteadily before describing the lasting
effects of the attack: trouble with balance and sight, no sense of
smell, a six-week stretch of amnesia.
   The rampaging youths went on to attack several other people _
Loughlin, a teacher, hospitalized for two days with his injuries;
Lewis, a banker, who escaped serious injury because of his speed;
and John Goode, a British Airways employee who was punched.
   Medical workers testified the woman had lost about
three-quarters of her blood and was near death when she arrived at
a hospital. She later was transferred to a Connecticut
rehabilitation center.
   The jurors criticized Salaam's attorney, Robert Burns, for
putting his client on the stand.
   ``It shot down everything he had going for him because his story
was so far-fetched,'' Nestorick said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0012 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-19-90 0428EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-US-Gulf 4thLd-Writethru a0655 08-19 1128</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-US-Gulf, 4th Ld-Writethru, a0655,1000</SECOND>
<HEAD>Pentagon Readies for Reserves Call-Up As First Shots Fired</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: INSERTS 2 grafs after 6th graf bgng The Pentagon xxx to
UPDATE with Iraqi report of third firing; picks up 7th graf pvs
bgng In a statement.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT BURNS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Pentagon geared up for expected activation
of thousands of reserves as U.S. warships began attempting to
enforce an embargo against Iraq on Saturday, firing warning shots
at two Iraqi oil tankers and shadowing them as they sailed away
under cover of darkness.
   President Bush could activate as many as 80,000 members of the
Army Reserve and the Army National Guard to bolster the U.S.
military buildup in the Middle East, which Defense Secretary Dick
Cheney said could last for years.
   But the actual number was likely to be much less, said an Army
source, speaking on the condition of anonymity. The source said
80,000 was a ``tentative upper limit planning figure.''
   The shots were the first fired by American forces in the Persian
Gulf crisis following Bush's order Thursday to interdict shipments
in and out of Iraq, using ``the minimum force necessary.''
   Iraqi Oil Minister Issam Chalabi said the shots fell in front of
and behind the two tankers, the Baba Karkar in the Persian Gulf and
the Khanaqin in the Gulf of Oman, and they proceeded without
stopping.
   The Pentagon said Navy ships were closely monitoring the two
Iraqi tankers heading out of the Persian Gulf area and believed to
be carrying Iraqi oil. Military sources said it was unlikely the
Navy would take any further action against the ships during the
night, which settled over the region a few hours after the initial
incidents.
   But the Iraqi News Agency said a third Iraqi tanker was fired
upon Sunday as it sailed in the central part of the Gulf. It did
not say in which direction the ship was heading, or name the U.S.
warship that allegedly fired the shots Sunday.
   The report could not be immediately confirmed independently, and
a Pentagon spokesman, Marine Lt. Col. Stuart Wagner, said,
``Nothing has been called into the Pentagon about it. We have not
been notified of any such incident.''
   In a statement, the Pentagon said the USS Reid fired six warning
shots across the bow of an Khanaqin in the Gulf of Oman after it
``refused repeated requests to halt.''
   Also, the USS Bradley fired three warning shots across the bow
of another Iraqi tanker in the Persian Gulf and headed toward the
Gulf of Oman, the Pentagon said.
   ``Both tankers are currently under way, but are under close U.S.
Navy surveillance,'' the Pentagon said.
   Iraq's only port is nestled at the northernmost tip of the
Persian Gulf, which connects with the Gulf of Oman through the
Strait of Hormuz. Beyond the Gulf of Oman is the Arabian Sea and,
beyond that, the open waters of the Indian Ocean.
   Meanwhile, fears mounted that Iraqi President Saddam Hussein was
using U.S. citizens and other foreign nationals in Iraq and
occupied Kuwait as weapons in his battle to defeat UN-sponsored
economic sanctions.
   The Iraqi government announced that the sanctions were causing
shortages of food, including milk for babies. It said ``the same
calamity'' would befall the thousands of foreign nationals,
including babies, under Iraqi control because the government
considered the sanctions ``an act of war.''
   The White House said it was deeply concerned by Iraq's latest
moves.
   ``The use of innocent civilians as pawns to promote what Iraq
sees to be its self-interest is contrary to international law and
indeed to all accepted norms of international conduct,''
presidential spokesman Marlin Fitzwater said from Kennebunkport,
Maine.
   An estimated 3,000 Americans are in Iraq and Kuwait.
   Bush, vacationing in Kennebunkport, was preparing to sign an
executive order to authorize the call-up of thousands of Army, Navy
and Air Force reserves. Officials said he had decided a call-up was
necessary, but details of how many and from which reserve units
were still being worked out.
   A wide variety of tasks are assigned to reserve forces, from
cargo handling and medical support to aerial refueling and infantry
operations. The Army, Navy and Air Force are heavily dependent on
the reserves during a large-scale mobilization.
   A reserve call-up shows the magnitude of the U.S. military
commitment in Saudi Arabia, which Cheney described as ``long term''
and said might last for years.
   ``Where we'll be a year or two from now, I wouldn't want to
speculate,'' Cheney told reporters Friday en route to the desert
kingdom. Cheney was on a four-day swing through several gulf
nations to visit U.S. soldiers, sailors and airmen and to talk with
government officials.
   A decision to activate reserves is fraught with domestic
political risk because of a public perception that it is tantamount
to putting the nation on a war footing.
   Cheney had recommended to Bush that he use his authority to call
as many as 200,000 armed services reserves to active duty. It would
be the first reserve call-up for military action since President
Johnson activated 35,000 reserves in 1968 following the Tet
offensive in Vietnam and the seizure by North Korea of the U.S.
surveillance ship Pueblo.
   Some reservists would be deployed to U.S. military installations
and ports to help with the transportation of troops and equipment
to Saudi Arabia. Others may make the trip to the Arabian desert as
part of the U.S. combat force.
   Reserves provide more than two-thirds of wartime medical
personnel support, three-quarters of medical evacuation crews and
nearly all of the Navy's search and rescue operations.
   In a further indication of the enormous scale of the U.S.
military deployment, the Pentagon on Friday night announced it was
commandeering up to 38 airplanes from 29 commercial carriers to
help ferry troops and cargo to the Middle East. It was the first
time the Pentagon has exercised its contractual right to use the
Civil Reserve Air Fleet in the 38 year that the program has existed.
   And on Saturday, the Navy issued a formal statement confirming
earlier acknowledgment from Pentagon sources that the aircraft
carrier USS Kennedy was being dispatched to the Middle East.
   Also, the head of the Military Sealift Command said the Navy,
which runs the sea-transport system, chartered four commercial
merchant ships to bolster its fleet of vessels ferrying supplies,
weapons and equipment to Saudi Arabia.
   Admiral Francis Donovan said in an interview that more
commercial ships would be needed in the days ahead. He said the
overall sealift was operating satisfactorily.
   He declined to provide exact details of the sealift, but said
nine ships prepositioned near Guam and the Indian Ocean island of
Diego Garcia were carrying enough supplies to Saudi Arabia to
sustain 33,000 Marines for 30 days.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0013 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-19-90 0445EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i BC-Gulf-Shooting 2ndld-Writethru a0666 08-19 0493</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Gulf-Shooting, 2nd ld-Writethru, a0666,0503</SECOND>
<HEAD>PRECEDE Manama</HEAD>
<HEAD>Iraq Calls U.S. Actions `Piracy'; Pentagon: No Reports of New
Shots</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: New thruout to UPDATE with no confirmation of shots fired
Sunday from Pentagon; No pickup.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>NICOSIA, Cyprus (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Iraqi Foreign Minister Tariq Aziz on
Sunday called U.S. shipping inderdiction efforts ``piracy and armed
aggression'' and called on the international community to condemn
it, the Iraqi News Agency said.
   Aziz sent a letter to U.N. Secretary-General Javier Perez de
Cuellar complaining about U.S. warships firing shots toward Iraqi
oil tankers that refused to stop, according to the news agency,
monitored in Nicosia.
   ``American warships intercepted and inspected and fired shots
against our tankers Saturday and Sunday,'' Aziz said. ``Such acts
are clear proofs that America is permitting itself to commit piracy
and armed aggression on high seas against Iraq.''
   U.S. warships on Saturday fired on two Iraqi oil-bearing
tankers, but shipping sources and the Pentagon were unable to
confirm a third incident Sunday.
   Pentagon spokesman, Marine Lt. Col. Stuart Wagner, said:
``Nothing has been called into the Pentagon about it. We have not
been notified of any such incident.''
   Shipping sources said they had not monitored gunshots but that
they were checking with other points along the Gulf. ``It must be
just too far from our monitoring radios,'' said one executive in
the southern Gulf.
   The Iraqi News Agency said the third Iraqi tanker was fired upon
Sunday as it sailed in the central part of the Gulf, but did not
say in which direction the ship was heading, or name the U.S.
warship that allegedly fired the shots.
   According to the Iraqi News Agency, Aziz said his government
wanted the U.N. to guarantee ``measures that prevent America from
exercising the police role in international waters.''
   American warships were monitoring the movements of two Iraqi oil
tankers early Sunday after the vessels ignored U.S. warning shots
and headed out of the Gulf region.
   A U.S. Navy officer told reporters with Defense Secretary Dick
Cheney aboard the USS Eisenhower in the Red Sea that the
guided-missile frigate USS Reid fired the first shots Saturday of a
two-day-old interdiction effort ordered by President George Bush.
   In Washington, the U.S. Defense Department later confirmed that
two Iraqi ships had been warned with gunfire in separate incidents
and that both continued sailing under the watch of the naval
vessels.
   On Saturday, The USS Reid fired six warning shots across the bow
of an Iraqi tanker that it intercepted in the Gulf of Oman, the
Pentagon said.
   Later, the USS Bradley fired three warning shots across the bow
of another Iraqi tanker that refused U.S. requests to halt, the
Pentagon said. The unidentified tanker was in the Persian Gulf,
heading toward the Gulf of Oman.
   U.S. forces are in the Persian Gulf region to enforce
U.N.-imposed economic sanctions against Iraq designed to force that
country to withdraw from Kuwait, which it invaded on Aug. 2 and
later annexed.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0014 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-19-90 1136EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--Neo-Nazis     08-19 0160</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Neo-Nazis,0164</SECOND>
<HEAD>Leftists, Neo-Nazis Brawl on Anniversary of Hess' Death</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WUNSIEDEL, West Germany (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hundreds of neo-Nazis marking the
death of Rudolf Hess brawled with a group of leftists in the
southern West German town where the former Hitler deputy is buried.
   Police said they arrested 46 people for assault, property
damage, and other incidents.
   About 1,000 right-wing extremists gathered in Wunsiedel on
Saturday to mark the third anniversary of Hess' death.
   About 4,000 leftists took part in a counterdemonstration, and
clashes broke out between the two groups, police said.
   Hess, a native of Wunseidel, is buried in a cemetery in town.
Police blocked off the graveyard on the anniversary of his death.
   Hess was deputy leader of the Nazis when he flew to Scotland in
1941 to negotiate a separate peace with Britain. He was jailed
until 1946, when he was convicted at the Nuremberg war crimes
trials and sent to Berlin's Spandau prison until his death.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0015 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-19-90 1138EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--EastGermany-PLO     08-19 0144</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--East Germany-PLO,0147</SECOND>
<HEAD>Defense Minster to Halt Army Training of PLO Members</HEAD>
<DATELINE>EAST BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Under heavy criticism from Jewish groups,
East Germany's defense minister said Sunday he will halt army
training of members of the Palestine Liberation Organization.
   Defense Minister Rainer Eppelmann said he was stopping the
training on Monday but that the government still must make a
declaration of principle to end the training permanently.
   He said the East German army currently provides training to 31
PLO members, 29 Libyans and 130 Yemenis.
   He said none of the trainees were involved in training for
terror acts.
   On Friday, West Berlin's Jewish community sharply criticized the
training program and demanded it be stopped.
   Community leader Heinz Galiniski said it was unbelievable that
the practice of training the PLO had not been discontinued after
the former Communist government was toppled last year.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0016 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-19-90 1142EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--Soviet-Communists     08-19 0176</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Soviet-Communists,0180</SECOND>
<HEAD>162,750 Quit Russian Communist Party in July</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The head of the Russian branch of the Communist
Party was quoted Sunday as saying 162,750 members quit in July,
about 1.5 percent of the 11 million Communist Party members in the
republic.
   The figures were announced by Ivan Polozkov, a hard-liner who
was elected in June to lead the Russian branch. Polozkov was quoted
by the Sovietskaya Rossiya (Soviet Russia) newspaper.
   He said he was concerned by the number of drop-outs,
particularly since 90,000 of them were the very factory workers
that the Communist Party claims to represent.
   Many had predicted mass defections after the Russian party
congress in June, which was dominated by hard-liners opposed to
many of the democratic and market-oriented reforms favored by
Mikhail S. Gorbachev.
   Gorbachev is both president of the country and head of the
national Communist Party.
   Some reformers are planning to quit the party in autumn when
they form an alternative party and make a bid for a share of the
Communists' vast financial resources.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0017 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-19-90 1144EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--TrainProtest     08-19 0188</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Train Protest,0194</SECOND>
<HEAD>About 20,000 Passengers Stranded by Train Protests</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MARSEILLE, France (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hundreds of demonstrators protesting
plans to bring high-speed trains to the scenic Provence region
occupied stations and barricaded tracks, stranding about 20,000
passengers, officials said Sunday.
   The demonstrators disrupted rail service for several hours in
the Saturday evening protest.
   Police cleared the last occupied stations at Miramas, Senas and
Sain-Martin-de-Crau shortly after midnight, but rail officials said
service would probably not return to normal before midday Sunday.
   The protest was the largest in a series of demonstrations to
prevent the expansion of the high-speed trains into Provence.
   Protesters fear a new high-speed line through Provence to
Marseille would destroy the region's scenic beauty and its
important wine industry.
   On Saturday, Transportation Minister Michel Delebarre promised
new studies to find the route least damaging to the environment.
But he stopped short of saying the $180 million project would be
canceled.
   Railroad officials say the new line, if completed, would cut
travel time between Paris and Marseille to three hours, a reduction
of 1 hour, 40 minutes.
   The high-speed locomotives travel at about 200 mph.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0018 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-19-90 1145EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Israel-Begin     08-19 0226</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel-Begin,0232</SECOND>
<HEAD>Begin Leaving Jerusalem, Moving to Tel Aviv Hospital</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Former Prime Minister Menachem Begin was
discharged from a Jerusalem hospital Sunday and was moving to Tel
Aviv at the request of his family, hospital officials said.
   Begin, who turned 77 two weeks ago, has been recovering from a
broken right hip at Jerusalem's Sharei Zedek Hospital since he fell
in his living room July 3.
   Dr. Arnold Rosen, head of the hospital's geriatric department,
described Begin's condition as ``good, very good even.''
   Hospital Spokeswoman Orna Cohen said Begin's family had
suggested he move to Tel Aviv, where he could be visited daily by
his daughters, one of whom lives in the coastal city.
   Begin was moved to Tel Aviv's Ichilov Hospital and was expected
to move later into an apartment, Ms. Cohen said.
   Begin maintained a residence in Tel Aviv until his election as
prime minister in 1977. He had been living in virtual seclusion in
a Jerusalem apartment since resigning as prime minister on Sept.
14, 1983.
   At the time of his sudden resignation, he was believed to be
depressed over Israel's military involvement in Lebanon and the
death of his wife, Aliza, in November 1982.
   Begin has two daughters, Leah and Hassia, and a son, Binyamin,
who is a leading member of Prime Minister Yitzhak Shamir's
right-wing Likud bloc.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0019 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-19-90 1146EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Israel-BorderClash     08-19 0222</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel-Border Clash,0228</SECOND>
<HEAD>Israeli Troops Clash with Jordanian Soldiers, One Killed</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Israeli soldiers killed one Jordanian soldier
and wounded another Sunday after the Jordanians infiltrated into
the occupied West Bank, the military command said.
   No Israeli troops were injured in the clash, the command said.
   The incident occurred when a routine army patrol in the West
Bank found footprints south of the Adam Bridge over the Jordan
river, the army said.
   The area is about 15 miles north of Jericho.
   An army statement said the Israeli patrol ``identified two armed
people in Jordanian army uniforms. The two were ordered to halt but
did not, and opened fire at the Israeli troops.''
   ``The soldeirs returned fire and in the exchange of gunfire one
of the Jordanian soldiers was killed and the other slightly
wounded,'' the statement said. The wounded soldier was captured and
was being interrogated.
   The army statement did not link the infiltration to the current
tensions involving Iraq. Attempted infiltrations often occur on the
Jordanian-Israeli frontier, and several times the infiltrators have
been Jordanian soldiers acting on their own.
   The army said it was the second infiltration of Jordanian
soldiers into Israel this year. There have also been three shooting
incidents from Jordanian territory, the army said.
   No Israeli soldiers were injured in any of these incidents.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0020 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-19-90 1154EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i BC-GulfRdp 6thLd-Writethru   08-19 1087</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Gulf Rdp, 6th Ld-Writethru,a0678,1113</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<HEAD>Saddam to Use Foreigners as Shield, Offers Trade to Bush</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Leads with 5 grafs to UPDATE with Saddam offering to let
foreigners go if Bush pulls out troops and backs off on embargo.
Pickup 5th, `U.S. warships...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   President Saddam Hussein of Iraq said on Sunday that he will
hold Westerners who have been detained since the Kuwaiti invasion
at vital targets in Iraq to avert a ``catastrophe'' that might
result from a U.S.-led attack.
   But he offered to let the foreigners leave if President Bush
offers written guarantees that American forces will be withdrawn
from Saudi Arabia and that the embargo imposed on Iraq after it
invaded Kuwait will be lifted.
   Earlier Iraqi government statements had said the foreigners
would be used as a shield for Iraqi military installations, and
that they would suffer first if an international embargo on Iraq
causes shortages of food and medicine.
   Sunday's statement, broadcast on Iraqi television and translated
by The Associated Press, was described as an open letter to the
families of the thousands of foreigners, including 3,000 Americans,
trapped in Iraq and Kuwait.
   Saddam also defended detaining the foreigners, blamed Western
powers for causing the Persian Gulf crisis, and reiterated Iraq's
longstanding historical claims to Kuwait, which it annexed six days
after its invasion three weeks ago.
   U.S. warships on Saturday fired warning shots at two Iraqi oil
tankers, one in the Persian Gulf and one further south in the Gulf
of Oman.
   The official Iraqi News Agency claimed that U.S. warships fired
on another Iraqi tanker Sunday as it sailed in the central Persian
Gulf, but the Pentagon and shipping sources in the region could not
confirm the report.
   Elsewhere in the gulf, an official in the Jordanian port of
Aqaba said U.S. warships prevented a Sudanese ferry from entering
the port Sunday to pick up 550 Sudanese who had escaped from Iraq
and Iraqi-occupied Kuwait.
   The official, who spoke on condition of anonymity, said U.S.
warships also searched a Chinese freighter Sunday before allowing
it to enter the port.
   Although Jordan has said it will enforce an international
embargo on Iraqi goods, heavy trucks with Iraqi license plates
continue to load goods from docked ships and warehouses in the port
area and drive them back to Iraq. The embargo was imposed after
Iraq invaded Kuwait on Aug. 2.
   Since overrunning Kuwait, Iraq has mined Kuwait's oil ports and
placed explosives in Kuwait City's electric and water plants,
according to a report from official Radio France International that
quoted Egyptian engineers.
   Refugees fleeing occupied Kuwait said on Sunday that a Kuwaiti
resistance fighter carried out a suicide car bomb attack Friday on
Iraqi forces near a hospital in a suburb of Kuwait City. A
clandestine Kuwait radio station said an unspecified number of
Iraqi soldiers died or were wounded in the attack.
   Defense Secretary Dick Cheney said Sunday that Iraq has massed
200,000 troops and more than 1,000 tanks on the Saudi border and
that U.S. forces in the region are there to defend the oil-rich
nation from a possible Iraqi attack. Cheney spoke to servicemen
aboard the USS Eisenhower in the Red Sea.
   At another stop at a military base in Saudi Arabia, Cheney
refused to say how many U.S. troops have been rushed to the
kingdom, but he said they should be able to repulse an attack
ordered by Saddam.
   ``Should Saddam Hussein be foolish enough to launch an attack on
Saudi Arabia, we would be able to do a very effective job of making
him pay a bit of a price for that,'' Cheney said. But he added,
``Obviously, I'll be more comfortable once we've got more forces in
the country.''
   Also Sunday, the Gulf Cooperation Council alliance was to meet
in Jiddah, Saudi Arabia, sources said, to consider sending troops
to help defend member nations, who include Saudi Arabia, Bahrain
and the United Arab Emirates.
   The latest Iraqi statements, carried by the Iraqi News Agency,
came amid growing international anxiety over the fate of an
estimated 21,000 Westerners, including 3,000 Americans, who were
trapped in Iraq and Kuwait by the invasion.
   The statements also came just hours after the U.N. Security
Council unanimously demanded that Iraq let all foreigners leave and
``take no action to jeopardize the safety, security or health of
such nationals.''
   In one statement carried by the news agency, Iraq singled out
``Western foreigners and Australians'' living in three cities in
Kuwait for assembly at three hotels in the capital, Kuwait City.
   It said the measure was to secure their safety and ``Anyone who
does not comply will, together with his government, bear full
responsibility for any undesirable action that might be targeted
against them by hostile elements.''
   Westerners in Kuwait City, Al-Nidaa and Al-Jahrah were ordered
to assemble at the Hyatt Regency, the Meridian and the
International, according to the statement, monitored in Nicosia,
Cyprus.
   Al-Jahrah is the site of a former Kuwaiti military air base west
of Kuwait City, but the location of Al-Nidaa could not immediately
be determined.
   Radio France International also reported Sunday that Iraq has
moved some Westerners to Kuwaiti oil installations to prevent them
from being attacked.
   The Iraqi statement was the second such asssembly order in four
days. On Thursday, American and British nationals in Kuwait were
ordered to report to hotels, but no Iraqi officials were there to
meet the few who showed up.
   On Saturday, Iraq said foreigners would be the first to suffer
if the embargo results in shortages of food and medicine in Iraq.
On Friday, Iraq said foreigners may be placed around Iraqi military
installaions to prevent U.S. forces in the region from attacking
them.
   On Sunday, the Iraqi Foreign Minister Tariq Aziz called U.S.
shipping interdiction efforts ``piracy and armed aggression'' and
demanded the international community condemn them, the Iraqi News
Agency said.
   In a letter to U.N. Secretary-General Javier Perez de Cuellar on
Sunday, Aziz protested the warning shots fired at Iraqi tankers,
the news agency said.
   ``Such acts are clear proofs that America is permitting itself
to commit piracy and armed aggression on high seas against Iraq,''
the letter said.
   Two U.S. destroyers, meanwhile, steamed through the Suez Canal
on Sunday on their way to the Red Sea, a canal official said.
   The official, who spoke on condition of anonymity, said the John
Rodgers, a destroyer, and the Tattnall, a guided missile destroyer,
had entered the waterway and would exit the canal later Sunday.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0021 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-19-90 1215EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-Israel     08-19 0696</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Israel,0720</SECOND>
<HEAD>Israel Tense Over Reported Jordanian Military Alert, Hussein's
Stand</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf Rdp, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SERGEI SHARGORODSKY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Israel officials said Sunday that Jordan has
declared a top-level military alert and is recruiting more than
80,000 volunteers for the Iraqi army _ moves that have confused
Israel and heightened tension in the region.
   A senior government official said the Jordanian actions follow
repeated signals from Israel that it has no intention of attacking
the neighboring country.
   The official, speaking on condition of anonymity, told The
Associated Press Israeli intelligence analysts have concluded that
a U.S.-Iraqi military conflict is imminent.
   He said analysts also believe that Iraq is likely to use
Palestinian terror groups for attacks on U.S. targets in the Middle
East.
   Speaking of Jordan, the official said ``the army has been placed
on the highest possible level of alert and is ready for war. What
war, we don't understand.''
   The official declined to specify what steps have been taken by
Jordan's military. But a reporter who arrived from Jordan last week
said police and army leaves were cancelled and civil defense was
being organized in the Jordan Valley, along the 225-mile border
with Israel.
   In Jordan's capital of Amman, rumors of impending mobilization
of reserves circulated among the population, the reporter added.
   The Israeli official said Israel was unable to comprehend the
Jordanian moves and was worried that Jordan's King Hussein may be
losing control.
   ``After knowing this guy for 37 years we suddenly come to a
point when we don't understand what he does,'' he said. ``But maybe
it does not matter what the king says or does anymore, because he
may not be in control.''
   Hussein has remained Iraq's closest ally throughout the Persian
Gulf crisis. Israel is concerned that Iraq may eventually use
Jordan as a platform from which to attack the Jewish state and has
warned that the entrance of Iraqi troops into the kingdom would
mean war.
   The official expressed concern that King Hussein, known as a
moderate, may now be swept up in the wave of pro-Iraqi enthusiasm
in Jordan.
   He cited mass rallies in support of Iraq's President Saddam
Hussein, persistent pro-Iraqi propaganda by the Jordanian media,
and the registration of some 80,000 Jordanians who have volunteered
to serve in the army of Iraq.
   The official said King Hussein ``is definitely in alliance with
Saddam. He is agitating pro-Iraqi sentiments and definitely did not
agree to fully blockade Aqaba,'' Jordan's Red Sea port and a
principle supply route for Iraq.
   As one sign of increasing tension, the official noted Sunday's
firefight between an Israeli military patrol and two Jordanian
soldiers who infiltrated into Israel. One Jordanian was shot to
death and another wounded and captured.
   ``We expect more such clashes,'' the official said.
   Some Israeli military analysts said Jordan's military actions
could be explained by fear of an Israeli preemptive strike.
   ``The Jordanian action is a prudent one. They are worried about
a possible Israeli preemptive strike. I would do the same thing in
their place,'' said Ron Ben-Ishai, military commentator for the
daily Yediot Ahronot.
   But the government official said Israel had repeatedly assured
King Hussein that it had no aggressive intentions. ``We have sent
all kinds of signals to calm him,'' the official said.
   As part of its effort to reassure Jordan, the government has
requested officials to avoid alarming statements, such as claims by
right-wing politicians that a Palestinian state should be created
in Jordan, the government official said.
   ``We are definitely not saying anything that we know can provoke
more worry on the part of King Hussein,'' he said.
   Turning to the gulf, the official said Israeli intelligence has
concluded that ``the Americans are preparing for a military strike,
and we believe Saddam will resist.'' He said it was still unclear
who will start a shooting war.
   But Saddam was prepared to use Palestinian terrorist groups for
attacks on American targets, ``including those in Saudi Arabia,''
the official said.
   He said the organizations likely to be used include the radical
Abu Nidal group, Abul Abbas' Palestine Liberation Front and perhaps
other factions of the Palestine Liberation Organization.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0022 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-19-90 1225EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Portugal-Fire Bjt   08-19 0757</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Portugal-Fire, Bjt,0778</SECOND>
<HEAD>Work to Begin on Razed Historic District Two Years After Fire</HEAD>
<HEAD>Am AP Extra</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TONY SMITH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LISBON, Portugal (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Many people wept when fire razed
historic Chiado, where the shop windows were full of dreams and
cafes echoed with endless debate of art and politics. Two years
later, rebuilding is about to begin.
   Lisbon received messages of sympathy from cities and national
governments after the fire. It was showered with offers of help in
recovering from a ``cultural disaster.''
   Gone were the Cafe Ferrari, scene of much good conversation and
passionate argument; window shopping on the Rua do Carmo; the smell
of roasting chestnuts in the old streets.
   Now, the man who will direct the reconstruction says it may have
been a blessing in disguise.
   ``When the Chiado burned, the first news that went around the
world was `disaster. . . . In fact, it was bad, but not that bad,''
Alvaro Siza Vieira, Portugal's leading architect, said in an
interview.
   Siza is ready to begin a $74 million rebuilding project in the
10-block downtown area that is expected to take three years.
   The goal is ``regeneration of an area that before the fire was a
bit ill and dilapidated,'' he said, strolling through the ruins of
the Grandela department store, where the fire started Aug. 25, 1988.
   It raged for more than a day, killing two people, injuring 40,
leaving 300 homeless and 6,000 temporarily out of work.
   Only charred ruins remained of such landmarks as the Ferrari
cafe, specialty grocers Costa e Martins and the 350-year-old Casa
Batalha button shop on Rua Garrett.
   The disaster inspired a debate worthy of the Ferrari on topics
ranging from city planning to safety standards.
   Most of the wood-frame buildings had no fire sprinklers. Stone
terraces in a new pedestrian mall kept fire trucks away from the
heart of the blaze.
   Many Lisbon residents, proud of the beauty of a city stretching
over seven hills along the shimmering Tagus estuary, worried that
modern office blocks might be built in the old Baixa, or lower town.
   In 1985, controversial architect Tomas Taveira shocked the city
by building the Amoreiras, a massive, pastel-colored shopping,
apartment and office complex, atop one of the city's hills. The
Amoreiras is a commercial success, but few Lisbon inhabitants say
they like its style.
   Faced with this traditional-modern rivalry, Siza departed from
the contemporary, ascetic style that won him the Alvar Aalto
international architecture award in 1988.
   ``It would have been wrong to use an accident to make an island
of modern architecture in the historic center'' of Lisbon, he said.
   Chiado will look much the same as before, he said, because 18 of
the 20 charred facades now propped by scaffolding can be saved, but
there will be ``new, hidden improvements'' and the district ``won't
be a museum.''
   The project, approved by Mayor Jorge Sampaio last month,
includes a luxury hotel and small-scale shopping malls behind the
facades.
   Up to 40 percent of space on upper floors of reconstructed
buildings will be devoted to apartments, ``to keep people in the
Chiado, not offices,'' the architect said.
   A new subway station will link the district with the Baixa,
which was rebuilt on a grid system by the Marquis of Pombal after
an earthquake destroyed most of Lisbon in 1755.
   One victim of the quake was the Carmo convent. Siza plans a
pedestrian ramp leading up to the convent ruins, which have become
part of Lisbon's skyline, and to the labyrinth of trendy bars and
restaurants in the narrow cobbled streets of the Bairro Alto, or
upper town.
   The stone terraces on the Rua do Carmo that stopped the fire
trucks will be ripped up and the street reopened to limited traffic.
   Mayor Sampaio said the Chiado project would set a precedent for
restoring other parts of the city, some of which date to the 11th
century.
   Two areas that need renovation are Alfama and Mouraria, where
the rose-pink and ocher houses usually are in bad repair because
regulated low rents do not leave the owners enough money to fix
them.
   City housing expert Vasco Franco said 15 neglected houses
collapsed in last winter's heavy rains and he hoped foreign
financing could be obtained, perhaps from the European Community.
   Repairing the old houses is cheaper than building new ones, he
said.
   Last year, the EC gave $135,000 toward the renovation of
Mouraria, the old Arab quarter. ``Symbolic, but a good start,''
said Joao Geraldes, another city project coordinator.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0023 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-19-90 1230EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-JoggerHistory     08-19 0750</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Jogger History,0769</SECOND>
<HEAD>Witness, Victim, Symbol: The Jogger Survives</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Central Park Jogger, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LARRY McSHANE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   She arrived in Central Park just another
anonymous New York runner. She came out of a coma 15 days later as
a tabloid headline, a victim of unspeakable crime, and a symbol of
hope in a city choked by violence.
   She's known to millions now, but still maintains her anonymity;
to all but a handful, she is as nameless and faceless as she was on
April 19, 1989. Her remarkable recovery inspired the city, just as
the brutality of her assault had horrified it.
   The Central Park jogger.
   She was found lying in a puddle of mud and blood early on April
20, unconscious. She arrived at Metropolitan Hospital a short time
later, an unlikely candidate for survival, much less recovery. She
seemed destined to become another fatality in a record year for
homicides.
   Her skull had been fractured. Three-quarters of her blood was
gone, splattered around the roadway crossing the park. Her body
temperature had dipped into the 80s.
   She needed a machine to breathe. Her body was bruised literally
from head to toe, with severe head lacerations, brain contusions
and fractured facial bones.
   Photos of her injuries produced looks of dismay and disbelief
from a jury which sat poker-faced through six weeks of graphic
testimony about her injuries.
   On a scale of 3 to 15 used by neurologists to measure brain
function, the woman was rated a 4. Even as she began to emerge from
the coma, attending physician Dr. Howard S. Kurtz put her chances
for full recovery at slim.
   Slowly, steadily, she came back. New Yorkers were cheered by
reports of her high-fiving a nurse, of a soft ``hello'' to her
brother.
   She had no recollection of the events that changed her life; her
last memory before the attack was canceling dinner with a friend,
her next was waking up in the hospital for the Memorial Day weekend.
   Her progress could be charted by the holidays: rapid improvement
in a Connecticut rehabilitation center by Labor Day. Back home _
and out jogging again _ for Thanksgiving. Back at work by
Christmas. And ringing in the new year with a promotion to vice
president at Salomon Brothers.
   While it appeared on the surface that her life was returning to
normal, the jogger _ in a dramatic, 12-minute appearance in a
Manhattan courtroom _ demonstrated that things were forever altered
in her life.
   It was 15 months after the attack when a bailiff in state
Supreme Court summoned the woman, now 30, to the witness stand. By
now, everyone knew who she was. There was silence for 2{ minutes as
spectators and reporters waited, tension building, for the arrival
of the Central Park jogger.
   She took her seat slowly, assisted by a court officer. A jagged
scar ran along her face, mute testimony to the viciousness of her
attackers. In a steady voice, she detailed the lasting effects of
the beating she can't remember.
   ``I have problems with balance when I'm walking, and
coordination. At times, I'll veer off to the right or the left,''
she testified. ``I have trouble walking down steps. I also lost my
sense of smell completely. That has not come back.
   ``I have double vision. When I'm reading, I hold newspapers over
to the left to compensate. It takes a fair amount of concentration
to make the image one.''
   She left the courtroom and slipped quietly back into her
day-to-day existence, her anonymity respected by almost all news
media.
   Yet everyone reported intimate details of the woman's life after
her testimony: her method of birth control, the last time she made
love with her boyfriend. A defense lawyer, in his closing argument,
suggested she stopped for a tryst on her way to the park and had
never been raped.
   Much of her background is well known: a Pennsylvania native,
holder of graduate degrees from Yale, a Wall Street investment
banker, a hard worker, a dedicated runner. Family members say she
holds no grudges, and remains determined in her recovery.
   But no one can say what the future holds for the Central Park
jogger, other than to say it can't be like the past.
   ``The fact that she could even come to this courtroom is a
miracle,'' Assistant District Attorney Elizabeth Lederer told the
jury in her closing argument. ``(The jogger) will never be the same
as she was.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0024 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-19-90 1232EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-LegionConvention     08-19 0228</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Legion Convention,0233</SECOND>
<HEAD>American Legion to Meet in Indianapolis</HEAD>
<DATELINE>INDIANAPOLIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Up to 25,000 old warriors will gather this
week for the 72nd American Legion national convention, while their
active-duty counterparts prepare for the possibility of combat in
the Middle East.
   Beginning Friday, members of the nation's largest and most vocal
war veterans organization gather in the city of their national
headquarters. It is the first time that the 3 million-member
Legion, founded in 1919, has held its annual meeting here.
   ``We call this our homecoming,'' said Lew Wood, the Legion's
national director of public relations. ``We plan to have an
old-fashioned, patriotic celebration, and most events will be held
on our own front lawn.''
   Unless events in the Middle East disrupt speakers' schedules,
the week-long program is to include addresses by Army Gen. Colin L.
Powell, chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff; retired Adm. Elmo R.
Zumwalt, former chief of naval operations; and retired Air Force
Brig. Gen. Chuck Yeager, the famed test pilot.
   The 3,400 delegates will vote on resolutions asking Congress to
amend the American Legion's charter to permit veterans who served
during recent actions in Grenada, Panama and Lebanon to join the
organization.
   Under current rules, only those who served during World War I,
World War II and the Korean and Vietnam wars may join.
   The convention will end Aug. 30.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0025 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-19-90 1239EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Gulf-PolicyFailure Bjt   08-19 0635</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Policy Failure, Bjt,630</SECOND>
<HEAD>US Misread the Iraqis for Years</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP News Analysis</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GEORGE GEDDA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   As military tensions in the Persian Gulf
increase, the six-year American effort to moderate Iraqi policies
seems in retrospect like perhaps the most ineffectual U.S.
diplomatic venture in more than a decade.
   The Reagan administration's attempts to tame President Saddam
Hussein evoke memories of the 1970s, when the United States tried
to encourage peaceful behavior in the Soviet Union by promoting
expanded trade and financial ties.
   Over the short term, the ``detente'' policy toward the Soviets
was a disappointment. By contrast, it was a glittering success next
to the outcome of the U.S. effort in Iraq.
   An overture to Iraq seemed to some an obvious option for the
Reagan administration in the early 1980s. At the time, the big
concern was Iran and its goal of spreading its Shiite
fundamentalist orthodoxy elsewhere in the gulf region and beyond.
   By the fall of 1984, the United States had removed Iraq from the
list of countries engaged in state-sponsored terrorism and had
restored full diplomatic relations with Baghdad.
   American rice and wheat farmers began doing a flourishing
business with Baghdad, and Iraq also made use of the U.S.
Export-Import Bank to buy American products on credit. Overall
transactions between the two countries were measured in the
billions of dollars.
   The New York Times reported last week that the CIA provided the
Iraqis with valuable military information on their Iranian foes the
long and bloody Iran-Iraq war of the 1980s. The United States also
helped finance Iraq's war effort through oil purchases.
   Part of the reason for helping the Iraqis was concern that they
might otherwise be routed by Iran. Since the end of the war in
1988, the rationale for maintaining ties with Iraq changed: it was
thought that Saddam would be eager to preserve the benefits of his
economic ties with the United States and shape his foreign policy
accordingly.
   Thus, the administration resisted congressional attempts this
year to impose economic sanctions against Iraq, arguing that the
dissolution of the relationship would rob the United States of all
leverage with Saddam.
   So appalling was Iraq's behavior even before the Kuwaiti
invasion that at least one farm state senator, Kansas Republican
Nancy Kassebaum, lobbied hard for economic sanctions even though
many of her own constituents have benefitted from Iraqi wheat
purchases.
   The Iraqi conquest of Kuwait on Aug. 2 dramatized just how much
the administration overestimated its sway with the Iraqis.
   To many members of Congress, the warning signs have been there
to see for years. Iraq has a record of using chemical weapons
dating back to 1984 and used them against Iraqi Kurds just two
years ago.
   Since Iraq's war with Iran ended, there has been no appreciable
reduction in Iraqi military spending. Iraq has a million-man
military and missiles capable of reaching Israel. It is believed to
be the world's largest manufacturer of chemical weapons. It may
also be developing biological weapons and it is harboring some of
the most radical Palestinian leaders.
   Secretary of State James A. Baker III spoke for many current and
past government officials last week when, alluding to Iraq's
behavior dating back to the 1980s, he said the United States
``should have been concerned about all of this'' years ago. Other
officials conceded that the United States should have been far more
outspoken in calling attention to Iraqi behavior.
   Perhaps Kuwait should have been more wary as well. The Kuwaitis
lent the Iraqis more than $10 billion to help the finance Saddam's
war effort against Iran.
   Now Saddam has contrived a way not to have to pay the Kuwaitis
back.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   George Gedda has covered foreign affairs for the
Associated Press since 1968.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0026 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-19-90 1243EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Yugoslavia     08-19 0508</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Yugoslavia,0522</SECOND>
<HEAD>Serbs Vote On Autonomy in Croatia</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SLOBODAN LEKIC</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>KNIN, Yugoslavia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Armed Serbs patrolled streets in the
republic of Croatia Sunday to stop police from intervening as the
Serb minority voted on autonomy in open defiance of a government
ban.
   Voters formed long lines in front of polling booths in this
Serbian center in southwestern Croatia for the referendum,
organized by the Serbian Democratic Party. The party favors a
degree of self-government for Serbs.
   Croatians, who are Roman Catholic, dominate the western half of
Yugoslavia, while Orthodox Serbs form the majority in the south of
the country. The two ethnic groups have been traditional rivals
ever since they were united within Yugoslavia in 1918.
   According to official statistics, Serbs make up 11 percent of
Croatia's 5 million people. The two ethnic groups are intermingled
in a patchwork of small communities in southwestern Croatia.
   If the referendum is passed it is likely to worsen tensions
between the two groups. Voting was to continue for the next two
weeks in ethnic Serbian areas of Croatia.
   The vote was declared illegal by Croatia's government, which
says it is part of a scenario to destabilize the newly elected
administration.
   Organizers of the referendum said that all ethnic Serbs born in
the area were being allowed to vote, and that the referendum is
expected to be passed by a near unanimous vote.
   Nikola Ozegovic, the official in charge of one polling station,
claimed that about 90 percent of the eligible voters among Knin's
10,000 Serbs had cast ballots by early afternoon. The town has a
total population of about 11,000.
   He said that Croatians who expressed a desire to vote for
autonomy were being allowed to participate in the ballot. He said
two such Croatian women were permitted to vote at his polling
station.
   Serbs armed with automatic rifles patrolled streets and stood
guard at government buildings and the radio station to prevent
police from intervening in the vote.
   On Friday and Saturday, armed villagers blocked highways leading
to the Adriatic coast. On Sunday, traffic was reported to be
flowing through the roadbocks, which were manned by Serbs with
walkie-talkies.
   ``We can't believe the Serbs are suddenly so full of hatred for
us,'' said Nikola Pozar, a local Croatian political leader. ``But
we've been advised by the Croatian government not to respond to
their provocations,'' he added.
   Authorities in Croatia, where a center-right party swept into
power last spring in the first multiparty elections in the area in
more than 50 years, claimed the plebiscite was being directed by
the Communist leadership of Serbia, Yugoslavia's largest state.
They said the effort was an attempt to divert public attention from
the lack of democratic reforms in Serbia.
   Polling stations were decorated with posters showing the red,
blue and white Serbian flag and a large ``Yes'' printed in the
middle. There were no voting booths and ballots were marked openly
in front of polling officials.
   Yugoslavia is a loose federation of six republics and two
autonomous provinces.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0027 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-19-90 1315EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Mosbacher-Exports     08-19 0597</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mosbacher-Exports,580</SECOND>
<HEAD>Commerce Secretary Says Growing Export Base Will Stem Recession</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN D. McCLAIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Commerce Secretary Robert A. Mosbacher expects
growing exports to keep the U.S. economy out of a recession this
year.
   Reacting ecstatically to the record export posting in the latest
merchandise trade report, Mosbacher said in an interview in his
fifth floor office late last week:
   ``I feel that the export side ... not only will keep us out of
recession but it's going to bring back a continuing higher growth.''
   The record $34.3 billion in exports, combined with a reduced
$39.37 billion in imports, resulted in a $5.07 billion trade
deficit in June, the lowest since a $3.96 billion imbalance in June
1983.
   Asked if he were satisfied with the report, Mosbacher replied:
``Satisfied might be an understatement. I'm very pleased with it,''
he said, emphasizing the word ``very.''
   So far this year, he said of the export gain, ``It's very much
across the board _ it's capital goods, it's high-tech goods, and
it's agriculture.''
   The secretary repeated his belief that the nation's merchandise
trade deficit would drop below $100 billion this year for the first
time since 1983. Already, he said, the deficit has tumbled to $45.8
billion _ the lowest six-month imbalance since the second half of
1983.
   But like most other observers, he had a caveat _ the rising cost
of oil following the Iraqi invasion of Kuwait.
   ``Now you tell me how long the crisis will last and the prices
will stay up? If the price of oil doesn't stay up very long, we'll
still make it,'' he said.
   Many analysts have said they believe skyrocketing oil prices
will cause America's oil bill to shoot up in the second half of the
year, offsetting any growth in exports.
   Mosbacher said the United States has been running an oil deficit
of between $47 billion and $48 billion a year _ ``That's $18 (a
barrel) oil, plus or minus. If you've got $27 oil, you got about a
50 percent increase.''
   On Friday, oil was costing nearly twice the $14.64 a barrel it
averaged during June.
   Nevertheless, assuming oil prices do decline soon, he said,
``we're headed at close to a $90 billion trade deficit this year _
it could be $95 billion, under $100 billion is what I've been
saying.''
   That would be more than a one-third cut from the 1987 peak
deficit of $152.12 billion. The trade imbalance has declined each
year since then, falling to $109 billion last year.
   The commerce secretary attributed the export progress to the
decline in the dollar, improved quality of U.S. goods and greater
export expertise.
   ``U.S. goods are a lot cheaper overseas now for these
customers,'' he said. `` Plus, our quality keeps improving and our
knowledge of how to export ... keeps improving. And finally, the
government's working with exporters....''
   ``This is just what we need to accomplish to keep our
competitive edge in this world _ export buildup,'' he said. ``You
know, instead of talking about what we can do to limit imports, we
need to keep working on building exports.''
   Thus far, he said, the growing export base ``shows American
business is competitive around the world, it shows American
business is beginning to realize it's a global marketplace, with
the biggest potential area of growth and unsatisfied demand is
outside the U.S.
   ``And it does create jobs and business opportunities for
everyone,'' he said. ``It can keep the economy on the positive
side. I mean, keep us from ... a recession.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0028 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-19-90 1348EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Bush-Gulf     08-19 0389</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bush-Gulf,390</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush Returns To Washington For Persian Gulf Briefing</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Bush scheduled to depart Kennebunkport at 3:30 p.m. EDT and
arrive White House at 5:30 p.m. EDT</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By TERENCE HUNT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP White House Correspondent</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>KENNEBUNKPORT, Maine (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A grim-faced President Bush headed
back to Washington to review the Persian Gulf crisis with national
security advisers Sunday as the administration for the first time
called foreigners trapped in Iraq and Kuwait hostages.
   Bush scheduled a dinner meeting with senior officials and
planned to remain at the White House overnight. On Monday, he will
deliver a major speech in Baltimore before the annual Veterans of
Foreign Wars convention, focusing on the showdown with Iraq and the
high stakes it holds for the United States.
   The president is to return to his vacation home later Monday
after stopping at a Republican fund-raising reception at a Rhode
Island country club.
   Bush's mood has noticeably darkened over the past week as
Baghdad has issued increasingly bellicose statements and has warned
that it will use foreigners as a shield against Western attack.
There are an estimated 3,000 Americans in Iraq and Iraqi-occupied
Kuwait.
   Thomas R. Pickering, the U.S. ambassador to the United Nations,
said Saturday that Iraqi President Saddam Hussein had made clear
that ``he was going to hold hostage all foreigners.'' U.S.
officials previously had avoided using the word ``hostage'' to
describe the foreigners trapped since Iraq invaded Kuwait on Aug. 2.
   Bush, emerging from services at St. Ann's Episcopal Church with
his family, ignored a reporter's shouted question about whether he
agreed with Pickering's characterization. He walked directly to his
limousine instead of stopping to greet fellow worshippers, as he
usually does.
   A day earlier, a visibly irritated Bush announced that he was
going to stop answering questions from reporters on the golf course.
   During Sunday's service, the rector, the Rev. Laman H. Bruner
Jr., offered a poignant prayer for the president, the captive
foreigners in Iraq and Kuwait and the success of the U.S. military
mission.
   ``O, Almighty God, uphold the hand of our president in our
resolve in the Middle East. Support with Thy might our people in
their proving; that they fear not the threatenings and strokes of
their enemy,'' Bruner said.
   ``Protect those who are interned and restore them to their homes
in safety,'' he added.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0029 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-19-90 1350EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-Reporters     08-19 0564</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Reporters,560</SECOND>
<HEAD>Closed Society, Heat Make Reporting Difficult in Saudi Arabia</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOAN MOWER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DHAHRAN, Saudi Arabia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Western reporters are finding that
the challenge of reporting in a society that has been virtually
closed to foreigners until now is as stiff as working in heat that
often soars above 100 degrees.
   Although the Saudi government allowed the Defense Department to
chaperone a small pool of reporters in the country more than a week
ago, it was not until the last few days that the kingdom agreed to
grant visas for open coverage to more than a dozen journalists.
   When the thumbs-up came on visas, the networks were ready.
   ``We are hitting the ground running,'' NBC-TV's ``Today'' show
co-host Bryant Gumbel said as he plotted the day's work Sunday with
two producers in the coffee shop of the Dhahran International Hotel.
   Gumbel and at least a score of other foreign television and news
reporters have arrived in Saudi Arabia, more than two weeks after
Iraqi troops invaded Kuwait.
   The thousands of American troops President Bush dispatched to
defend this desert kingdom have turned Saudi Arabia into the
hottest news story around _ literally.
   Habib Shaheen, a spokesman for the Saudi government, said the
number of reporters in the country was unprecedented. The last time
he dealt with all four television networks here was three years ago
when Iranians attacked Mecca, he said.
   On Saturday, the Saudi government flew reporters _ including
some of the biggest names in television _ to Jiddah, 1,000 miles
away, for interviews with top officials.
   Ever sensitive to the draw of television, the government
arranged for NBC's Tom Brokaw, ABC's Sam Donaldson and CBS' Bob
Simon to have individual interviews with the Saudi oil minister and
the foreign minister.
   ``Very smooth,'' Donaldson pronounced after his 10 minutes with
Prince Saud al-Faisal, the foreign minister. Al-Faisal, clad in his
traditional flowing robe and red headdress, spoke in flawless
English as he recounted Saudi Arabia's insistence that Iraqi troops
leave Kuwait.
   The Saudis' decision to open their borders awed some reporters
who until now have spent years trying to penetrate the kingdom.
   ``We would wait forever just to get one interview and now we
have three top officials in one day,'' said Barnie Mason of BBC
radio.
   Although the Saudis appear to be amenable to open coverage,
Gumbel said he thought it might be difficult to really find out
what is happening in the country, where some citizens are not keen
on opening their society.
   ``We have a different culture; please be kind to us,'' said
Ahmad Al-Otiri, an F-15 pilot.
   He said he hated television reports that seemed to be critical
of Saudi Arabia, such as one that focused on Saudi displeasure at
American soldiers wearing tee-shirts.
   And a high-ranking Saudi official said the reluctance for
publicity ``has not been forgotten.''
   Whatever the news, the logistics for covering it are formidable.
   CNN's Carl Rochelle was the pool reporter who flew to Saudi
Arabia with the Defense Department. Once in the country, he and his
technicians had to set up a portable satellite Earth station at the
Dhahran Air Base.
   The heat was so intense that one technician was overcome and
military officials were forced to install an air conditioner in a
tent.
   ``We've learned to drink a lot of water,'' said Tom Mote, a CNN
cameraman.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0030 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-19-90 1351EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-DrivingPoll-List     08-19 0261</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Driving Poll-List,0283</SECOND>
<HEAD>Answers To True-And-False Questions In Driver Safety Poll</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Driving Poll</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOUISVILLE, Ky. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the 10 auto safety
true-and-false questions included in this year's poll of drivers
sponsored by a subsidiary of Ashland Oil Co.
   Not included on the list are sections of the poll dealing with
motorists' opinions on issues related to driving, and questions on
individual motorists' driving habits.
   The judgment on whether a statement is true or false is provided
by the National Safety Council, the poll sponsors said.
   1. If a traffic light changes from green to yellow, you should
hurry through the intersection.
   2. If a car approaches you with its high beams on, it is
recommended that you flash your high beams.
   3. When you turn on your windshield wipers, you should also turn
on your headlights.
   4. If your brakes fail to work, the first thing you should do is
use your car's emergency brake.
   5. If your accelerator is stuck, you should immediately turn off
the car's ignition.
   6. Traffic accidents are primarily due to mechanical failures in
cars.
   7. Most deaths due to traffic accidents occur at night.
   8. Most deaths due to traffic accidents occur in rural areas.
   9. Wearing a seat belt gives you a better chance of escaping a
burning or submerged vehicle.
   10. There is no nead to wear seat belts in a car that has air
bags.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   The answers:
   1. False; 2. False; 3. True; 4. False; 5. False; 6. False; 7.
True; 8. True; 9. True; 10 False.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0031 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-19-90 1456EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-CentralParkJogger Bjt   08-19 0699</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Central Park Jogger, Bjt,0721</SECOND>
<HEAD>Defendants Guilty of Rape, Assault In Jogger Trial</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SAMUEL MAULL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Jurors say they decided to acquit three
teen-agers of attempted murder in the Central Park jogger case
because they did not think the youths intended to kill the young
woman, who suffered brain damage.
   Juror Rafael Miranda said the mood in the jury room was often
tense, with ``a lot of screaming, and a lot of names called,''
before the teen-agers were convicted Saturday night of raping and
assaulting the jogger.
   The anonymous victim, now 30, became a national figure as she
recovered from the savage assault by a youth gang during her
nightly run on April 19, 1989.
   The savage attack on the woman taking her nightly run horrified
New Yorkers because of its randomness and brutality.
   After therapy, she returned to work and to jogging within eight
months. But she doesn't remember the attack, has lost her sense of
smell and sometimes has difficulty in walking and in focusing her
vision.
   Like some other recent high-profile trials in New York City,
this case involved victims and attackers of different races _ the
three on trial were black or Hispanic and the victim was a white
Wall Street executive.
   Supporters of the youths charged that the police were satisfied
with the arrest of any minority suspect. Defense lawyers charged
the defendants' incriminating statements were the product of police
lies and intimidation.
   But Miranda said the jury of four blacks, four whites, three
Hispanics and one Asian never was split along racial lines during
10 days of deliberations.
   The defendants _ Yusef Salaam, Antron McCray and Raymond Santana
_ were acquitted of the top count of attempted murder and a lesser
count of sodomy.
   Salaam, 16, McCray, 16, and Santana, 15, were tried as adults
but will be sentenced as juvenile offenders on Sept. 11. They face
up to five to 10 years in prison on the top count of rape. All
three defense attorneys promised to appeal.
   Justice Thomas Galligan ordered them all jailed without bail.
   Three other defendants have yet to stand trial.
   The defendants' supporters demonstrated frequently outside the
courthouse, accusing the victim of promiscuity and questioning her
reasons for being in the park late at night.
   When prosecutor Elizabeth Lederer left the courthouse, a group
shouted: ``The devil herself. The devil, she's going to pay for
it.''
   Lederer's boss, Manhattan District Attorney Robert Morgenthau,
denied any racial element in the case. ``This city is ill-served by
those who have sought to exploit it ... and advance their own
private agendas,'' he said.
   ``The brutal events which occurred at Central Park late one
April night in 1989 seared the soul of every decent New Yorker,''
Mayor David Dinkins said in a statement. ``We should recommit
ourselves to building a city and forging a society in which such
heinous crimes do not occur.''
   Charles Nestorick, one of two jurors who agreed to talk with
reporters after the verdict was read, said the attempted murder
charges ``gave us a lot of difficulty because she had really been
beaten.''
   But he said the jurors felt the teens didn't realize how badly
they had hurt her. ``Youths that age are not well versed in how
many blows it takes to kill someone,'' he said.
   After three days of deliberating on nothing but the attempted
murder charges, ``we saw that we couldn't prove intent,'' he said.
   Asked why it took 10 days for a verdict, Nestorick said one
person held out to acquit McCray on rape and assault.
   The defendants' statements to police were the heart of the
prosecution's case. A detective testified that Santana told him he
counted 33 youths who entered the park to ``wild some joggers ...
beat up and rip off joggers and cyclists.''
   The defendants told detectives the naked woman was struck with a
metal pipe, bashed in the head and face with a brick, cut on the
legs with a knife and sexually attacked, Lederer said.
   The defendants also were convicted of first-degree riot; of
assault and robbery in an attack on one male jogger and of
assaulting a second man.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0032 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-19-90 1514EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p AM-FloridaGovernor Bjt   08-19 0760</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Florida Governor, Bjt,0785</SECOND>
<HEAD>Chiles' Renewed Use of Anti-depressant Dogs Gubernatorial Campaign</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY7</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAN SEWELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Former three-term Sen. Lawton Chiles is being
chased by questions about his health, particularly his resumed use
of the anti-depressant drug Prozac, as he heads into the stretch of
the Democratic gubernatorial race.
   Since his surprise entry into the race in April, Chiles has been
the front-runner both to win the Sept. 4 primary and to unseat
Republican Gov. Bob Martinez in November. But an initial lead of 30
to 40 points over six-term U.S. Rep. Bill Nelson was down to 12
points in polls last month.
   And last month, Chiles disclosed that he had resumed taking
Prozac. His use of the anti-depressant was leaked to the news media
as he entered the race, but Chiles had stopped taking it until
recently.
   ``I started experiencing some of the symptoms I'd seen before,
so I resumed the taking of it,'' Chiles said Friday, citing loss of
appetite and sleeplessness.
   ``They're doing much better now,'' he added.
   Nelson's running mate, state House Speaker Tom Gustafson,
suggested two weeks ago Chiles could be a suicide risk in the
governor's mansion. Nelson distanced himself from the remark and
Gustafson eventually apologized.
   Questions about Chiles' use of Prozac come as the
anti-depressant is the subject of lawsuits filed against its maker,
Eli Lilly &amp; Co. of Indianapolis, by users or their survivors
linking the drug to violence and suicide.
   Eli Lilly says the drug has been prescribed to more than 2
million people and that extensive testing has shown no link to
suicidal impulses.
   During the campaign's first live television debate Thursday,
Nelson, 47, renewed his call for Chiles to release his medical
records. Chiles agreed and said Friday he has told his physician to
assemble his medical files.
   The 60-year-old Chiles, who underwent quadruple-bypass heart
surgery in 1985, had balked at releasing records. But he decided to
release them in hopes of quieting any concerns about his health.
   Chiles said voters don't query him about his health while he is
out campaigning. ``I think they sort of look at me, see the
schedule I'm keeping, and see how I'm doing,'' he said.
   With former U.S. Rep. Kenneth ``Buddy'' MacKay as his running
mate, Chiles has sought to make big-money politics the issue. He
and MacKay have long been among the state's most respected
politicians for integrity. They have raised nearly $2 million while
imposing a $100 limit on contributions.
   Nelson has raised $5.8 million, and Martinez has been running
ahead of the Democrats in funds.
   The Democratic campaign has gotten more heated in its final
month, with Nelson raising ethics charges against Chiles, and
Chiles criticizing Nelson for the politics of negativism and big
money.
   While Chiles hopes voters will back him against what one of his
ads terms ``the politics of the sewer,'' Nelson is pushing the
health issue.
   He wrote Chiles on Friday asking a timetable for the release of
Chiles' medical records, and campaign manager Jay Hakes said Nelson
will bring the disclosure issue up in their next televised debate
Friday, if Chiles still hasn't responded.
   Nelson and Martinez, both joggers, made their medical records
public months ago.
   Hakes said Chiles' health is a legitimate, but ``delicate,''
issue.
   ``I don't think it's really going to be appropriate to discuss
Prozac,' Hakes said, calling it too personal.
   But the Nelson campaign cites Chiles' own statement in December
1987 that he was retiring from the Senate because he was burned out.
   Nelson repeatedly talks about ``energy and vitality.''
   Chiles said he didn't recognize his depression until after he
left the Senate. He decided to retire when, as Senate budget
chairman, he became frustrated because Senate politics were making
it impossible to make headway toward reducing the federal deficit.
   J.M. ``Mac'' Stipanovich, Martinez's sharp-tongued politic guru,
said he would have no reticence in highlighting Chiles' mental
health.
   ``Lawton Chiles by his own admission was incapable of continuing
in public office,'' he said. ``By his own admission, he suffered
from clinical depression. By his own admission, while campaigning
without the medication, he couldn't sleep or function.''
   Stipanovich said those admissions raise questions about how
depressed Chiles is.
   ``They're all fair questions, and that has nothing to do with
the morality of Prozac or depression,'' said Stipanovich, who said
his own mother takes Prozac. ``That doesn't make him a bad person.''
   Chiles insisted he's not worried, that he is proving he's fit.
   ``I'm sure they'll use anything against me,'' he said, chuckling.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0033 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-19-90 1514EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-NAACP-Coalition     08-19 0311</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-NAACP-Coalition,310</SECOND>
<HEAD>NAACP, Other Groups To Fight Social Problems</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The NAACP and more than 100 other
organizations ranging from law enforcement to religious groups have
formed a coalition to battle nagging social ills in black
communities.
   The group, calling itself the National Association of Black
Organizations, grew out of a three-day ``Summit Conference of Black
Organizations'' in Washington assembled by the National Association
for the Advancement of Colored People.
   Coalition members, which include groups as varied as the
National Organization of Black Law Enforcement Executives and the
Progressive National Baptist Convention, will focus their efforts
on such problems as teen-age pregnancy, school dropouts and other
social problems.
   NAACP Executive Director Benjamin Hooks said the coalition is
designed to enhance the ``continuing struggle of African Americans
to gain a fair share of the American dream.''
   The organization's plans call for establishment of a
communications network to share information, development of a brain
trust to research and make recommendations on social and economic
concerns affecting blacks, spreading of effective self-help
initiatives, and development of strategies to strengthen support
for black institutions.
   The NAACP moves in a new direction with the formation of the
coalition. The nation's preeminent civil rights organization has
traditionally focused on legislation and litigation.
   ``What we have accomplished here is but a beginning,'' Hooks
said. ``It marks the start of a new approach, where the visible
payoff is farther down the road.''
   Hooks said the NAACP does not intend to turn from its historical
focus. But he said the 81-year-old group also realizes the need for
black organizations to address problems facing blacks.
   ``We as black people are stepping up to the bat and saying we
are taking responsibility for our own destiny,'' Hooks said.
   He said the coalition's nine-member executive committee would
meet within two weeks to work out further details.
   The conference concluded Saturday.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0034 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-19-90 1520EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People     08-19 0666</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People,0693</SECOND>
<HEAD>People in the News</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY44</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ITASCA, Ill. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The award-winning rhythm and blues group
Soul II Soul canceled its North America tour after becoming
involved in a seven-car pileup over the weekend.
   Jazzie B. _ the 27-year-old lead singer and songwriter whose
real name is Beresford Romeo _ suffered back injuries, and doctors
advisde him against performing for about a week, said the group's
manager, Don Taylor.
   Four other band members were treated for minor injuries and
released, Taylor said.
   He said the group canceled the rest of the shows on its
itinerary, including performances in the west Chicago suburb of
Hoffman Estates; Columbus, Ohio; Montreal; Toronto; Bristol, Conn.;
and Boston.
   The group's two tour buses were involved in a chain-reaction
accident Saturday that sent 31 people to three hospitals, Illinois
State Trooper Bruce Shimizu said.
   In February, the band won a Grammy award in the rhythm and blues
category for the ``Back to Life'' single. Their song ``African
Dance'' was named best instrumental.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Comedian Yakov Smirnoff's success brought him
from a one-room apartment in Moscow to a five-bedroom house near
the glittering Sunset Strip.
   But with the birth of his first child approaching, he's giving
up his trendy address for a quieter, family oriented neighborhood
   ``We want a better place for Linda to push the baby cart,''
Smirnoff said in a recent interview after returning Los Angeles
following appearances in Las Vegas and Atlantic City, N.J.
   The former Soviet citizen and his wife, Linda, are purchasing
the 3,500-square-foot home on the 18th hole of the Riviera Country
Club for $2.4 million and listing their old one for about $1.8
million.
   The new home, in the Pacific Palisades area of Los Angeles, has
three bedrooms and a maid's quarters.
   ``It's something like a Mr. and Mrs. Cleaver house. And it's
one-story, which will be better for our child,'' said Smirnoff, who
moved to the United States 13 years ago and became a citizen in
1986.
   Goldie Hawn and Tom Hanks will be among the Smirnoffs' new
neighbors. Smirnoff appeared with Hanks in the movie ``The Money
Pit'' and with fellow comedian Robin Williams in ``Moscow on the
Hudson.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>SANTA BARBARA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Pop superstar Michael Jackson
invited 130 children to his ranch, where the YMCA day campers from
Santa Barbara and Los Angeles visited his zoo, video arcade and
custom theater.
   At first, the children, age 7 to 13, were in awe of Michael
Jackson, but that quickly changed.
   ``He was so much more than I expected. I thought he was going to
say `hi' and `bye.' But he played with us the whole time,'' said
12-year-old Monique Jackson of Los Angeles.
   During Saturday's visit, the kids presented the star with a
banner that said ``We love you Michael,'' and made him an honorary
member of the 28th Street YMCA in Los Angeles, said Lee Solters, a
Jackson spokesman.
   Jackson has invited groups of children to his mountain estate
before. Last month, he spontaneously asked a group of terminally
ill children who were camping nearby to come for a barbecue and
movie.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>DENVER (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Former Colorado Sen. Gary Hart is using his
experience in politics to capitalize on the newly democratizing
East bloc.
   Three years after dropping out of the presidential race, the
53-year-old Democrat is helping a newly incorporated consulting
practice at a Denver law firm to assist U.S. companies expand into
foreign markets.
   Hart says he's not from the same mold as former Secretary of
State Henry Kissinger.
   ``I'm not a jet-setter or a Kissinger,'' he said. ``I never
thought of public service as a career and always knew I'd come back
to the private sector. My activities aren't just based on old
friends.''
   Hart also has expanded outside the East bloc, helping the
Italian state energy company ENI explore oil and gas acquisitions
in the United States. He also represented a Taiwanese group of 27
companies looking for hotels.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0035 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-19-90 1553EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Jogger-Chronology     08-19 0529</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Jogger-Chronology,0562</SECOND>
<HEAD>Key Dates In Case of Central Park Jogger</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Central Park Jogger Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A chronology of key dates in the Central Park
jogger case:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>1989</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   April 19 _ The female jogger, out for an evening run, is
brutally attacked, raped and left for dead in Central Park.
   April 20 _ The badly battered woman, comatose and suffering from
hypothermia, is discovered and rushed to Metropolitan Hospital. Her
prognosis for recovery is pessimistic. Police say a gang of
teen-agers out for a night of ``wilding'' was responsible.
   April 23 _ Suspects are arraigned. A prosecutor says seven of
eight suspects made incriminating statements to police about the
attack.
   April 26 _ Yusef Salaam and Raymond Santana are indicted on
charges of rape and attempted murder.
   April 27 _ Kharey Wise, Antron McCray and Steven Lopez are
indicted on charges of rape and attempted murder. Jermaine Robinson
is indicted for attack on a male jogger in the park. Clarence
Thomas, 14, released with no charges brought.
   April 28 _ Kevin Richardson is indicted on charges of rape and
attempted murder. Parks Commissioner Henry Stern announces
wide-ranging plans to improve Central Park security.
   May 1 _ Jogger's condition improves enough to give a nurse a
``high five.''
   May 3 _ Jogger emerges from coma, whispers ``Hello'' to her
brother.
   May 17 _ The jogger undergoes surgery to repair her shattered
face.
   June 7 _ She is transferred to Gaylord Hospital in Wallingford,
Conn., for physical and mental rehabilitation.
   Oct. 5 _ Jermaine Robinson, 15, pleads guilty to robbery in
attack on a male jogger the same night of the rape-assault.
   Oct. 9 _ Genetic evidence tested by the FBI turns up no link to
the half-dozen rape suspects.
   Nov. 14 _ The jogger is released from Gaylord Hospital after a
``miraculous'' recovery.
   Nov. 27 _ She returns to her job at Salomon Brothers on Wall
Street.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>1990</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Jan. 1 _ The jogger is promoted to a vice president at Salomon
Brothers.
   Feb. 23 _ State Supreme Court Justice Thomas Galligan rules the
suspects' statements to police the day of their arrests are
admissible at trial.
   March 16 _ The case is split into two trials, with Antron
McCray, Yusef Salaam and Raymond Santana the first three defendants
to be tried.
   May 30 _ Michael Briscoe pleads guilty to separate attack on the
night of the jogger rape.
   June 13 _ Jury selection begins.
   June 25 _ Opening arguments in the trial.
   July 16 _ The jogger, in a 12-minute appearance on the witness
stand, details the lasting injuries of the attack: amnesia, lack of
balance, no sense of smell.
   Aug. 1 _ Defendant Yusef Salaam, over the objection of two
defense lawyers, takes the stand and declares his innocence.
   Aug. 6 _ Salaam's mother, Sharonne, is ejected from the
courtroom after an outburst in which she calls one prosecutor a
liar in the presence of the jury.
   Aug. 7 _ Defense closing arguments.
   Aug. 8 _ Prosecution closing.
   Aug. 9 _ Jury begins deliberating.
   Aug. 18 _ The three defendants are convicted of rape and assault
and acquitted of the top count of attempted murder.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0036 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-19-90 1558EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p AM-LeeAtwater     08-19 0184</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lee Atwater,180</SECOND>
<HEAD>Spokeswoman: No Release Date Discussed for Atwater</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Physicians treating Lee Atwater have not
decided when to release the Republican National Committee chairman
from the hospital, a spokeswoman said Sunday.
   ``There is no release date and ... I have heard no discussion of
that,'' said Leslie Goodman, the RNC spokeswoman.
   Atwater has been undergoing radiation therapy at a Washington
hospital since Wednesday for brain tumor ``progression.''
   Published reports had indicated that physicians found a new
tumor in the brain of the 39-year-old South Carolinian. But Goodman
has said doctors were not specific about whether Atwater was
afflicted with a new tumor or the recurrence of a previous one.
   Atwater, who gained prominence in national political circles
when he directed President Bush's 1988 campaign, underwent brain
tumor surgery on April 3. He has since been in and out of the
hospital repeatedly for treatment of ailments ranging from a blood
clot in his leg to a nagging fever.
   Atwater was described as alert and said to be receiving visitors
following therapy. Goodman said Sunday that his condition was
``unchanged.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0037 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-19-90 1614EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-MilitaryCuts     08-19 0663</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Military Cuts,0685</SECOND>
<HEAD>Future of Defense Personnel Cuts Clouded by Crisis in Persian Gulf</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NR1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By AMY TEIBEL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>EATONTOWN, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   May of the civilian workers from Fort
Monmouth crowding into Hannah's restaurant after work recently have
been crying in their beer as well as quaffing it.
   The 292 employees laid off from the Army post were among some
5,400 at installations nationwide to receive pink slips in a
continuing congressional effort to trim President Bush's proposed
$307 billion defense budget.
   Fort Monmouth, with 8,200 civilian and 2,800 military workers,
provides high-tech logistic support for military operations and has
a research and development center for military electronics.
   The Army called the layoffs RIF terminations, for Reduction in
Force.
   No matter what they're called, Carol Locklin, a Fort Monmouth
secretary, will be out of work effective Oct. 15 unless the ``RIF''
is reversed.
   ``We don't really have savings, so to speak,'' said the
42-year-old Bricktown resident. ``It's going to really affect us if
I don't find a job that pays as much money.''
   Some members of the House and Senate Armed Services Committees
have lobbied to shrink the defense forces, citing the budget
deficit and democratization of Eastern Europe.
   The Senate Armed Services Committee wants to reduce the military
force by 100,000, and the House Armed Services Committee wants it
cut by 129,500, the Defense Department said.
   Some fort employees hope the invasion of Kuwait by Iraq and the
projected deployment of as many as 250,000 military personnel to
the Middle East will give both houses of Congress reason to
reconsider proposed cutbacks.
   Bill Eastburn, a section chief in the fort's Computer Controlled
Systems-Automatic Data Processing division, said an RIF notice he
received in 1970 was retracted.
   ``I keep telling other people my experience,'' Eastburn said.
``I tell them, don't jump off a bridge. Just hang in there. Now,
with the Iraqi situation, this may all be wiped out with a phone
call or the stroke of a pen.''
   Eastburn's optimism finds some echo in Congress.
   ``I think what's going on now will bring some appreciation to
members of keeping a ready reserve and a ready capability,'' said
Alabama Rep. William Dickinson, the ranking Republican on the House
Armed Services Committee. ``We can't just slash defense spending
and think everything will be OK. The world's just not like that.''
   President Bush _ who had proposed cutting 37,605 troops in his
1991 budget request _ has cited the dispatch of U.S. forces and
materiel to the Middle East in arguing against large-scale defense
cuts.
   Because Congress has not decided how large the reduction in
armed forces should be, no termination notices have been given to
enlisted staff, said Maj. Doug Hart, a Pentagon public affairs
officer.
   Through attrition, retirement and a cutback in recruitment, the
number of troops in all branches of the service has fallen from
2.12 million to 2.05 million in the 12 months ending June 30.
   A hiring freeze mandated by Secretary of Defense Dick Cheney on
Jan. 11 has helped shrink the civilian work force from 1.15 million
at the end of 1989 to 1.13 million as of June 30, Hart said.
   Layoffs for the military's 1991 fiscal year, which begins Oct.
1, so far have exclusively affected Army civilians, he said.
   At Fort Monmouth, there had been talk of layoffs for weeks. But
when the division chief called Mrs. Locklin to his office this
month to say she would lose her $16,000-a-year job, she was
shocked. The notification was dated Aug. 9.
   ``The worst I thought they would do is move me or downgrade
me,'' Mrs. Locklin said.
   People at Fort Monmouth are running scared, Mrs. Locklin said.
   ``They're wondering, `Am I next?' '' she said.
   At Hannah's, manager Chuck Armstrong said the layoffs haven't
translated into reduced business.
   ``Everyone comes over to party after they get their pink
slips,'' said Armstrong, who keeps petitions to save Fort Monmouth
jobs in the restaurant entrance.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0038 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-19-90 1614EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People-Bakker     08-19 0238</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People-Bakker,0245</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tammy Bakker Appeals for Funds, Hopes for Flock From Disney</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ORLANDO, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Evangelist Tammy Faye Bakker held her first
service in a converted warehouse near Disney World on Sunday after
winning a zoning appeal to allow a religious congregation on the
site.
   Mrs. Bakker told about 60 followers that she had the support of
her imprisoned husband, Jim Bakker, and may consider moving
services to Friday evening in order to draw additional people from
the nearby theme park.
   The Orange County Commission last week reversed a zoning board
decision that prohibited Mrs. Bakker from holding services in the
industrial park where her ministry has its television recording
studios.
   Attorneys for the American Civil Liberties Union representing
Mrs. Bakker before the commission argued the ban was
unconstitutional.
   ``I was in shock when we finally won it,'' she told worshippers
Sunday. ``I guess I've kind of gotten used to accepting defeat.''
   She pleaded for donations to meet the rent and other expenses.
   Her husband is in a federal prison in Minnesota, serving a
45-year term for bilking $3.7 million from followers of his former
Praise the Lord ministry in South Carolina.
   The Bakkers set up an Orlando-based cable-television ministry
before his conviction last year on fraud and conspiracy charges.
Since then the ministry has been located in a shopping center, a
former piano sales store and a hotel before moving to the
International Corporate Park.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0039 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-19-90 1616EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Gulf-Commander     08-19 0163</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Commander,160</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mauz To Head U.S. Forces In Middle East</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Pentagon officials on Sunday said Vice Adm.
Henry H. Mauz Jr., commander of the Navy's 7th Fleet, has assumed
duties as commander of U.S. Naval Forces, Central Command, in the
Middle East.
   In the new post Mauz will direct the ``maritime intercept
force'' poised to enforce United Nations sanctions against Iraq,
the Pentagon said in a statement issued in the name of Secretary of
Defense Dick Cheney, who was traveling in the Persian Gulf area.
   The United States is pouring thousands of soldiers into Saudi
Arabia to protect its largest source of foreign oil from a possible
Iraqi attack. Iraq overran Kuwait Aug. 2 and annexed the emirate
six days later. U.S. officials have said the troop deployment could
reach 200,000 men and women.
   The Pentagon said Mauz will retain his responsibilities as
commander of the 7th Fleet, based in Japan. He has held that post
since October 1988.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0040 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-19-90 1620EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-Jordan     08-19 0423</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Jordan,0437</SECOND>
<HEAD>Sudanese Ferry Turned Back, Chinese Freighter Searched</HEAD>
<DATELINE>AQABA, Jordan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   U.S. warships forced an empty Sudanese
ferry to turn back and searched a Chinese freighter Sunday before
allowing it to proceed to this Jordanian port, a port official said.
   At the Pentagon, Defense Department officials confirmed that the
USS Scott, a destroyer, turned back a Cypriot ferry flying the flag
of Sudan as it attempted to enter Aqaba.
   The Jordanian official said the ferry, identified the Dongola,
was on its way to Aqaba to pick up 550 Sudanese waiting to be
ferried home after crossing into Jordan from Iraq and Kuwait late
last week. He could not be named under regulations.
   But a Pentagon offical, who also could not be identified by
name, said the commander of the Scott had determined that the
Dongola also carried cargo banned under the U.N. sanctions against
Iraq.
   The Pentagon official described the incident as ``amicable,''
and said that no shots were fired.
   In Khartoum, Sudanese Foreign Minister Ali Sahloul said he has
ordered his ambassador in Washington to lodge a protest. He also
said Sudan plans to protest to the United Nations.
   Sahloul said the Dongola had 200 tons of cargo, mainly steel,
aboard. He said it was unloading at Port Sudan Thursday when it was
urgently requested to go to Aqaba to pick up the Sudanese.
   He said the vessel was now anchored 110 miles off of Aqaba.
   Sudan's Justice Minister Ahmed Mahmoud Hassan called the U.S.
interception ``illegal and a violation of human rights.''
   ``The ship was on its way to evacuate civilians escaping a
battle area,'' he said.
   The Jordanian port official said a Chinese-flagged freighter
identified as the Chan Chin was also stopped and searched, but was
allowed to proceed. He said the ship was on its way to Aqaba from
the Saudi port of Jiddah.
   Aqaba, Jordan's only port, is used extensively as a transit
point for Iraqi-bound cargo, which is unloaded there and
transported overland by truck.
   Though Jordan has said it will abide by the U.N. sanctions
against Iraq, it has yet to start implementing the resolution and
Iraqi-bound shipments continue to be channeled through Aqaba.
   King Hussein has said Jordan wants to discuss the sanctions
after consultations with the United Nations in view of Jordan's
heavy dependence on trade with Iraq.
   The United States has said it will enforce the embargo against
Baghdad by tightly controlling shipping to Iraq. The embargo was
called by the United Nations following Iraq's Aug. 2 invasion of
Kuwait.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0041 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-19-90 1627EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Soviet-KGBCandidate     08-19 0468</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-KGB Candidate,0477</SECOND>
<HEAD>Soviets Vote On Whether to Put KGB Renegade into Parliament</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ANDREW KATELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Voters considered Sunday whether to give a seat in
the national parliament to a KGB renegade who says the Soviet
secret police still play dirty tricks and cling to Stalinist
repression.
   A total of 20 candidates were running against former KGB agent
Oleg Kalugin for a seat in the Congress of People's Deputies from
the southern Russian province of Krasnodar. Among them were
cosmonaut Anatoly Berezovoi, a veteran of a 211-day space flight in
1982; and Gen. Vladimir Sein, political chief of the Transcaucasian
Military District.
   Election commission officials in Krasnodar said nearly 60
percent of the 3.5 million eligible voters turned out to vote. The
winner was expected to be announced Monday, although a runoff may
be necessary.
   The KGB and its supporters tried hard to discredit Kalugin
before the election. One resident of the region about 740 miles
south of Moscow on the Black Sea wrote to the Arguments and Facts
weekly that rumors were circulating that people who voted for
Kalugin would be imprisoned.
   Kalugin worked as an operative in the United States from
1958-1970, first under the cover of a Radio Moscow correspondent
and later as a first secretary in the Soviet Embassy in Washington.
   Kalugin's recent charges of wiretapping, smear campaigns and
other dirty tricks have been a major thorn in the KGB's side while
it is trying to improve its image. Many Soviets associate the KGB
and its predecessor agencies with the deaths of millions of people
under dictator Josef Stalin in the 1930s and 1940s and exile,
beatings and imprisonment of dissidents through the early 1980s.
   Kalugin, 55, focused renewed attention on the KGB's tarnished
past _ and he claims its present _ when he went public in June. He
told foreign and Soviet journalists that KGB agents are still
tapping telephones, infiltrating the Russian Orthodox Church and
labor unions, and carrying out dirty tricks at the behest of their
superiors. He said the agency should be abolished.
   At first, the KGB rejected his charges as hostile and distorted
and accused him of making them to further his own political
ambitions. Later, President Mikhail S. Gorbachev stripped his
military rank and decorations for ``compromising the honor and
dignity of the state security organs.''
   The Soviet prosecutor then began investigating Kalugin under a
law against divulging state secrets. Kalugin is fighting back with
a lawsuit against Gorbachev, Premier Nikolai Ryzhkov and KGB chief
Vladimir Kryuchkov.
   A member of the Democratic Platform reform movement, Kalugin is
trying to gain a seat in the the national parliament that meets
twice yearly. The seat became vacant in June when Ivan Polozov left
to become the Communist Party chief of the Russian federation.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0042 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-19-90 1629EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r r AM-Gulf-BorderTown     08-19 0476</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Border Town,0492</SECOND>
<HEAD>All Quiet in Saudi Border Town, But Some Are Fearful</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf Rdp, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOAN MOWER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>KHAFJI, Saudi Arabia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hundreds of people who had fled this
desert city near the Saudi-Kuwait border are returning because they
believe the threat of attack by Iraq has eased. But some are still
jittery.
   Khalid Al Otaishan, the administrative head of the area, said he
had drawn up an evacuation plan that calls for 50,000 people to
move to a tent city should Iraqi troops cross the border from
Kuwait.
   ``We have warned the people,'' Al Otaishan said in an interview
outside the city government building that overlooks the Persian
Gulf. Six Saudi tanks could be seen parked in the desert several
hundred yards away.
   The governor said more Saudi troops were stationed nearby, but
few could be seen in the city, which resembled a ghost town in the
midday sun.
   Handfuls of Saudi soldiers prayed along the side of the road
during regular Moslem prayer times.
   Only one batch of American soldiers was spotted in the course of
a day: seven Army men sat in a parked station wagon at the border
checkpoint. One studied a detailed map of the area.
   ``I am sorry we can't talk to you,'' the colonel in charge told
an American reporter.
   The Americans were among a force of tens of thousands of troops
deployed to the Persian Gulf region, backed up by an array of
planes and warships.
   Mursi Abu Bakr, whose family owns the Al Khafji Hotel, was asked
if he was worried about an invasion.
   ``The first week we were. Now things are getting better and we
work the best we can,'' he said. The arrival of American and other
troops in the region provided somewhat of a sense of security, he
said.
   But Scott Scheid of Newport Beach, Calif., said the town, only
six miles from the border checkpoint, was too close for comfort to
occupied Kuwait, with its huge Iraqi military contingent.
   ``I don't think you want to be here if something starts up,''
said Scheid, who works for an American oil company is based in
Khobar, more than 180 miles to the south. His company has evacuated
its 19 local employees from Khafji.
   ``There is a lot of tension in the air,'' said Scheid's
co-worker, Albert Skiba of Tuscon, Ariz.
   Khafji was flooded with Kuwaiti refugees after the invasion.
   ``For the first week, it was terrible,'' Al Otaishan said.
``They needed too much food, water.''
   The small oil town continues to serve as a magnet for those who
flee across the desert from Kuwait, as well as for those awaiting
word from relatives and friends still in Kuwait.
   Iraq annexed the emirate six days after the invasion, and
Baghdad has said Kuwait is now irrevocably part of Iraq.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0043 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-19-90 1636EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brite-BigYardSale     08-19 0336</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brite-Big Yard Sale,0347</SECOND>
<HEAD>Huge Roadside Yard Sale Provides Miles of Bargains</HEAD>
<DATELINE>OWENTON, Ky. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   For anyone into yard sales, it was
hand-me-down heaven _ the U.S. 127 Corridor 450-Mile Outdoor Sale
Festival.
   Sunday marked the end of the fourth annual, four-day, four-state
roadside extravaganza, which started Thursday. It stretched from
Covington, Ky., and ended around Gadsden, Ala., passing through
Tennessee and Georgia.
   Although there wasn't a continuous line of stalls along the
entire route, there was no shortage of tables and truckbeds to pick
over and racks to browse through.
   The festival is meant to help the economies of small towns and
counties along U.S. 127 by luring tourists off the interstates.
   ``We've got beautiful scenery along 127 and it's worth the drive
_ even if you don't find any bargains,'' said Judy Roysden of
Jamestown, Tenn.
   She said the sale was promoted in tourist magazines and by
tourism departments in Kentucky and Tennessee.
   Business slowed down toward the end the weekend after a brisk
start on Thursday and Friday. Several dealers attributed the slump
to travelers from northern states already having passed through.
   George and June Minor of Louisville, Ky., who were en route to
the annual Pioneer Days Festival in Kentucky's Mercer County, said
they didn't know about the yard sale event but were stopping at
many of the stands.
   ``George is crazy about yard sales,'' June Minor said.
   By Saturday afternoon, some dealers were beginning to see
travelers returning from the south, their vans and cars loaded and
their pockets empty.
   Rebekka Seigel of Owenton, Ky., about 25 miles north of
Frankfort, said a Pennsylvania man had stopped to buy some marbles
but lacked the money to pay for them.
   ``His van was completely full,'' she said.
   The man pulled out a piece of pottery made in North Carolina and
asked if the Seigels would trade. They did and the man added 100
marbles to his load.
   ``His van would have been a real treat to go through,'' she said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0044 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-19-90 1651EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-Iran-Iraq     08-19 0501</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Iran-Iraq,0516</SECOND>
<HEAD>Iran Prepared to Ease Tensions With Iraq, Won't Violate Embargo</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf Rdp, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ED BLANCHE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NICOSIA, Cyprus (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An Iranian newspaper close to the
government said Sunday that Tehran is prepared to ease tensions
with Iraq, but will not help Baghdad circumvent a multinational
embargo.
   Iranian media also reported Sunday that the withdrawal of
thousands of Iraqi troops from the Iraqi-Iranian border will be
completed by Tuesday. Many of those troops are expected to be
shifted to the Iraqi-Kuwait border, where they will face U.S.
forces.
   The English-language Tehran Times, which is close to Iranian
President Hashemi Rafsanjani, said Iraq demonstrated good will by
offering Wednesday to bring a formal end to the 1980-1988 Iran-Iraq
war. A cease-fire halted the fighting two years ago.
   The English-language daily said Tehran was ``well prepared to
reciprocate any Iraqi goodwill gesture.'' But it denied suggestions
that Iran would help Baghdad violate the economic sanctions imposed
by the United Nations. The measures were enacted after Iraq invaded
Kuwait on Aug. 2. Iran has condemned the invasion.
   The daily said ``Western circles and U.S. congressional
quarters'' were voicing such concerns ``to drag Iran into the
current crisis.''
   It also stressed that ``Iran will in no way pit itself in a war
against Iraq in order for the Kuwaiti sheiks to return, or for the
sake of Western interests in this part of the world.''
   Iran's official Islamic Republic News Agency said Sunday the
Iraqi troops blew up fortifications and laid minefields along the
border as they withdrew.
   As the three-day-old pullout continued, the biggest
prisoner-of-war exchange since World War II gathered momentum after
Iraq began the long-delayed swap of soldiers captured in the
Persian Gulf war.
   Iraq's army daily, al-Qaddisiyah, has reported that an
unspecified number of the 30 divisions it said were deployed along
the 730-mile frontier with Iran following the cease-fire will be
sent south to confront U.S. forces in Saudi Arabia.
   The divisions contain an estimated total of about 300,000 troops.
   Iran's news agency quoted an unidentified Iranian officer as
saying that since the pullback of forces began Friday, Iraq has
withdrawn 90 percent of the forces that it had occupying an
estimated 700 square miles of captured Iranian territory. The
number of troops in that territory is unclear.
   The withdrawal is part of the peace initiative with Iran
launched by Iraqi President Saddam Hussein last week, primarily
aimed at securing his eastern flank in the confrontation with the
United States.
   In the POW exchanges, IRNA said 3,000 men were repatriated by
Iraq and 2,000 by Iran.
   The agency quoted an unidentified Foreign Ministry spokesman in
Tehran as saying that the two countries have agreed to speed up the
exchange from 2,000 men a day to 8,000.
   The Red Cross has registered some 50,000 POWs held by Iran and
30,000 held by Iraq. But United Nations officials and diplomats in
the region estimate there are as many as 100,000 men held by both
sides.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0045 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-19-90 1658EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Liberia 1stLd-Writethru a0705 08-19 0412</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Liberia, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0705,0425</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.S. Marines Bring Hundreds of Foreigners Out of Liberia</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 6 grafs to UPDATE with 800 people evacuated. Pick
up 7th graf pvs, `The Rev...'</NOTE>
<DATELINE>FREETOWN, Sierra Leone (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   About 800 people, most of them
Lebanese, were plucked from Liberia's war-ravaged capital Sunday by
U.S. Marines and flown by helicopter to neighboring Sierra Leone.
   The helicopters were arriving so quickly at a heliport on the
outskirts of Sierra Leone's capital of Freetown that there was
chaos in the waiting room.
   The evacuees were first flown from Monrovia to U.S. warships off
the West African coast and then ferried to Sierra Leone.
   More than 600 of the evacuees were Lebanese. The Lebanese
Embassy had said earlier that about 670 of its nationals were
expected to arrive in Sierra Leone on Sunday, and that two jets
have been chartered to take them to Beirut on Tuesday and Wednesday.
   The three arms of the Red Cross movement in Sierra Leone _ the
League of Red Cross, the Sierra Leone Red Cross Organization and
the International Red Cross _ were helping care for the evacuees,
who included Haitians, Togolese, Zaireans and Columbians.
   Others who had been expected to arrive Sunday included a few
Americans, some Germans, French, Indians, Chinese and a Ghanaian
priest.
   The Rev. Francis Johnson, whose Roman Catholic church was
located on Monrovia's Bushrod Island, said the fighters of rebel
leader Prince Johnson escorted him to the U.S. Embassy for the
evacuation.
   The priest described the situation in Monrovia as ``horrible.''
   ``Monrovia is dead, no activities, dead bodies lie all over the
place, houses are burned down and warehouses are looted,'' he said.
   The priest appealed to all embassies, particularly those of
Sierra Leone, Nigeria and Ghana, to evacuate their citizens from
Liberia.
   ``These countries should do away with politics and diplomacy and
see to the lives of their nationals,'' he said.
   It has been confirmed here that 1,300 Sierra Leoneans remain
trapped in their country's embassy.
   Johnson said foreigners still trapped in Liberia were hoping
that West African peacekeeping troops will arrive and halt the
fighting.
   ``But the troops are too slow in coming,'' he said.
   Sources in Sierra Leone said there was still no indication when
the peackeeping force would leave.
   Its deployment has been delayed while negotiators try to
persuade rebel leader Charles Taylor to accept a cease-fire and
cooperate with the force. President Samuel Doe and Taylor's rival,
Johnson, have accepted.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0046 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-19-90 1659EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-WeatherpageWeather     08-19 0578</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Weatherpage Weather,0597</SECOND>
<HEAD>Strong Thunderstorms Develop In Upper Ohio Valley</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Locally heavy rain caused flooding Sunday in West Virginia and
flooding caused by earlier rain threatened a dam in Indiana,
forcing evacuations.
   Thunderstorms developed overnight along and south of a
stationary front and produced heavy rain in the upper Ohio Valley,
and developed over some of the same areas again Sunday afternoon,
including eastern Kentucky, southern Ohio and southwestern West
Virginia.
   Thunderstorms dumped more than 5 inches of rain on parts of
northwestern West Virginia early Sunday, forcing people from their
homes and leaving a couple clinging to a clump of trees after their
pickup was washed away, authorities said.
   ``We got a call when a neighbor saw the truck floating away,''
said Wood County Sheriff's Sgt. Mark King. ``By the time our
deputies got there, the water was over the truck.''
   King said a number of homes along a creek were evacuated, many
county roads were inaccessible because of downed trees, minor mud
slides and high water, and there were power outages.
   Parkersburg received 3.4 inches of rain, while Clarksburg in
nearby Harrison County received 2.6 inches. In northeastern Wood
County, 5.1 inches of rain was measured in 3{ hours early Sunday.
   At Rochester, Ind., a hospital and apartments for elderly people
were evacuated as a precaution Sunday when high water threatened to
break a dam on Lake Manitou, police said.
   Six inches of rain Saturday pushed the lake about 2 feet above
flood stage and leaks appeared in the dam. Officials said between
50 and 75 people were evacuated from the Waterhaven Apartments and
another 28 were moved from the hospital.
   Volunteers, fire crews and civil defense officials laid about
13,000 sand bags along the dam early Sunday, Fulton County chief
jailer Robert Bryant said.
   Showers and a few thunderstorms also extended from eastern South
Dakota to Wisconsin during Sunday afternoon.
   Showers and thunderstorms also were scattered across Florida and
the central Gulf Coast region, along the middle Atlantic Coast and
southern New England, and over the lower Great Lakes.
   Elsewhere, isolated showers and thunderstorms were over central
Arkansas, central Oklahoma and eastern Kansas. Isolated showers
spread along and west of the central Rockies.
   During the night and early Sunday, showers and thunderstorms
produced locally heavy rain in the southern Plains, the North
Central states, the Great Lakes, the upper Ohio Valley and Florida.
   Heavier rainfall totals for the six hours up ,to 2 a.m. EDT
included 1.9 inches at Grand Rapids, Mich., and 1.7 inches at Key
West, Fla.
   Heavier rainfall for the six hours up to 8 a.m. EDT included 4.9
inches at Altus, Okla.; 2.8 inches at Rockford, Ill.; And 1.9
inches at Akron, Ohio.
   For the six hours up to 2 p.m. EDT, heavier rainfall included
3.1 inches at Islip, N.Y., and 1.8 inches at Rochester, Minn.
   Blustery north wind ushered cool air into New England during the
afternoon.
   Afternoon readings were only in the 60s across much of the area
from the northern Plains to New England, with temperatures in the
50s in some areas.
   Morning lows dipped into the upper 40s and 50s across parts of
the northern Plains, the upper Mississippi Valley, the Great Lakes
and the northern Atlantic Coast.
   Lows also were in the 40s and 50s in the Rocky mountain region
and the Great Basin covering Nevada and western Utah.
   Sunday's low for the Lower 48 states was 35 at Gunnison, Colo.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0047 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-19-90 1713EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Gulf-Foreigners 1stLd-Writethru a0725 08-19 0858</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Foreigners, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0725,0884</SECOND>
<HEAD>Saddam Demands U.S. Pullout, Embargo Halt, in Exchange For
Detainees</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: New thruout to UPDATE with French, Spanish reaction,
reorganizes. No pickup.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By MONA ZIADE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NICOSIA, Cyprus (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Iraq promised on Sunday to free citizens
of nations that are neutral in the Persian Gulf crisis, but renewed
threats to punish ``aggressive'' countries by using their nationals
as a shield against attacks.
   Three thousand Americans are among about 21,000 Westerners who
were trapped by Iraq's Aug. 2 invasion of Kuwait.
   In a series of statements on Sunday, Baghdad promised to allow
the nationals of five European countries to leave Iraq and occupied
Kuwait, but said it would use the other trapped foreigners _
including Americans _ as protection against attacks on vital
installations.
   ``Our people are seeking to avert a catastrophe,'' President
Saddam Hussein said in comments read by an announcer on Iraqi
television. ``The presence of the foreigners with Iraqi families at
vital targets might prevent an attack.''
   Saddam demanded the withdrawal of U.S. and other forces deployed
to protect Saudi Arabia, and called for an end to the international
embargo against Iraq.
   When those conditions were met, he said, all foreigners would be
free to go.
   Iraq's treatment of the foreigners was denounced by Western
governments.
   France said Sunday it had been informed by the Iraqis that 27 of
its nationals in Iraq and Kuwait had been taken from their hotels
to undisclosed locations. It protested the move and ordered its
naval commanders in the Persian Gulf to firmly enforce the United
Nations embargo.
   Spain's foreign minister, Francisco Fernandez Ordonez, called
Saddam's threats ``absolutely unacceptable.'' There are 184
Spaniards in Iraq and Kuwait.
   Britain, which has about 4,000 citizens in Iraq and Kuwait, has
accused Baghdad of using ``outlaw tactics'' in its treatment of
foreigners.
   The White House on Saturday said Iraq's holding American and
other foreign citizens is ``totally unacceptable,'' and denounced
the use of ``innocent civilians as pawns.''
   Late Saturday, the U.N. Security Council unanimously demanded
that Iraq let all foreigners leave.
   Baghdad said Sunday it would allow citizens from five countries
to leave Iraq and occupied Kuwait as a ``goodwill gesture'' _
because their governments had not sent ``aggressive forces'' to the
region.
   The official Iraqi News Agency quoted Sadi Mehdi Saleh, the
speaker of the Iraqi parliament, as saying Austrian, Swiss,
Swedish, Finnish and Portuguese would be allowed to leave Iraq.
   Those nationals account for fewer than 600 of the stranded
Westerners. They included 160 Swedes, 48 Finns, 140 Swiss, 140
Austrians and 100 Portugese.
   The news agency quoted Saleh as saying the National Council, or
parliament, would consider allowing citizens of other countries
neutral in the crisis to leave as well.
   Saddam, whose broadcast message was monitored in Nicosia, called
on the U.N. Security Council to guarantee a withdrawal of U.S. and
other Western forces from the region.
   He suggested Saudi Arabia be given assurances the Security
Council would coordinate ``collective military action'' against
Iraq if it attacked the kingdom.
   Under what the Iraqi agency described as Saddam's ``peace
initiative,'' the Security Council also was to guarantee regional
security ``on the basis...of our previous initiative.''
   That was a reference to an earlier offer from Saddam, linking a
possible withdrawal from Kuwait to Israel's withdrawal from
occupied Arab territories and a Syrian withdrawal from Lebanon.
   Saddam said the Kuwait crisis ``should be left for Arabs to
tackle as an Arab issue,'' and denounced the United States and
Britain as the chief obstacles to peace.
   ``Let us cooperate to prevent these governments from committing
major crimes ... which will result in an inferno and an
insurmountable flood of fire,'' he said.
   He said the detention of foreigners was meant to prevent
``death, murder and starvation'' that he said would result from
American policy. Thus, he said, holding the foreigners was ``a
service to humanity.''
   Earlier Sunday, Iraq ordered Westerners in three cities in
occupied Kuwait to report to hotels in the Kuwaiti capital. He
issued veiled threats against anyone who disobeyed.
   ``Anyone who does not comply will, together with his government,
bear full responsibility for any undesirable action that might be
targeted against them by hostile elements,'' said the news agency,
monitored in Nicosia.
   It was the second such asssembly order in four days. On
Thursday, American and British nationals in Kuwait were ordered to
report to hotels, but no Iraqi officials were there to meet the few
who showed up.
   Britain's Foreign Office said it was told by the Iraqis that
those who report to the hotels would be taken to ``key
installations in Kuwait and Iraq'' while those who did not report
to the hotels would be rounded up and taken straight to the sites.
   It repeated its advice to Britons to stay home, and not to
resist if confronted by Iraqi troops.
   Iraq said Friday it was detaining citizens of ``aggressive
countries'' and placing them in areas that would be likely targets
in the event of a U.S. attack such as Iraqi oil installations. On
Saturday, Iraq said foreigners, along with Iraqis, would suffer any
shortages provoked by U.N.-imposed economic sanctions.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0048 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-19-90 1723EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-OregonRationing     08-19 0662</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Oregon Rationing,0683</SECOND>
<HEAD>Oregon's Efforts to Reform Medicaid A Year Behind Schedule</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARILYNN WHEELER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PORTLAND, Ore. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A plan to ration services provided by
Oregon's Medicaid program to ensure that basic health care is
available to the largest number of people has fallen more than a
year behind schedule.
   Approved by the Legislature in 1989, the program is the nation's
first to consider eliminating expensive or ineffective treatments
for Medicaid patients instead of providing total care, as most
states do.
   A key to the program is an effort to establish a priority
ranking of medical procedures that will be used to draw the line on
Medicaid spending.
   But that effort encountered criticism when an initial ranking
put crooked teeth near the top of its list and AIDS treatment near
the bottom.
   Moreover, critics say any reduction in Medicaid coverage sets a
dangerous precedent.
   But state Medicaid director Jean Thorne says health care costs
are increasing at an alarming rate and she would far prefer to
ration services than reduce the number of people who qualify for
Medicaid.
   ``We constantly hear we've got to do something. ... Well,
there's no way we can attack this problem without being
controversial,'' she said. ``If the critics don't have anything
better to offer, why not let us try this?''
   Major health coverage celebrated its silver anniversary just
last month. On July 30, 1965, President Lyndon Johnson signed into
law Medicare and Medicaid, its companion health plan for the poor.
   Medical spending increased from $38 billion in 1965 to $70
billion in 1970. By 1980, health care costs had reached $236
billion.
   In 1983, the program was retooled. Payments to doctors and
hospitals decreased, and what constitutes the poor was redefined.
   In Oregon, that meant a 6-year-old whose parents earn $575 a
month was entitled to a heart transplant. But if the family's
income totaled $576 a month, that child could not get so much as a
booster shot.
   Even so, the state's Medicaid budget increased from $250 million
during the 1985-87 biennium to $520 million during the current
two-year budget period, according to Thorne.
   ``That's a 106 percent increase in funding, but the number of
people covered has increased by only 33 percent,'' Thorne said.
``If we're going to increase spending, let's spread the money
around more equitably.''
   The Medicaid rationing program, approved by the 1989
Legislature, originally was to have begun on July 1. But state
officials now concede there is little chance it will be ready by
July 1, 1991.
   An 11-member panel of doctors, health care administrators and
consumers has been poring over the priority list since September.
They spent months devising a mathematical formula that would weigh
the cost of a medical procedure against the severity of an illness
and the benefit of treatment.
   Detection and prevention of AIDS was high on the list, but
treatment for AIDS when a patient is close to death is near the
bottom. So are liver and bone marrow transplants, which can run
into the hundreds of thousands of dollars.
   
   Thumb sucking was 37th, ahead of croup and congenital syphilis.
That's because common ailments like thumb sucking are easily
treated at a relatively low cost.
   ``The first draft was a data dump,'' said Paige Sipes-Metzler,
executive director of the Oregon Health Services Commission.
``There will be another draft, possibly more than one. But, for the
time being, we have something to work with.''
   In June, the panel split into two subcommittees, each taking a
different approach to the priority list.
   The panel has postponed until September any further decision on
a ranking method. Meanwhile, no deadline has been set for the next
draft of the priority list.
   ``We felt it was more important to get an extension of the
deadline than to produce a list that doesn't work,'' said
Sipes-Metzler, adding: ``It's never going to be a perfect list or
satisfy everybody, but at least people will understand it.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0049 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-19-90 1722EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Gulf-UAE     08-19 0492</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-UAE,0508</SECOND>
<HEAD>United Arab Emirates Agrees To Deployment of Foreign Troops</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ABU DHABI, United Arab Emirates (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The United Arab Emirates
announced Sunday it has agreed to the deployment of Arab and
``friendly'' forces on its territory to help defend the Persian
Gulf region.
   Diplomatic sources said the statement gave the greenlight to
deploy U.S., Egyptian and Pakistani troops here, but it was not
immediately known if those nations plan to send any forces.
   The announcement by the United Arab Emirates' Foreign Ministry
came on the eve of a scheduled visit by U.S. Defense Secretary Dick
Cheney. On Sunday, Cheney was in Bahrain and Saudi Arabia, where he
inspected U.S. troops at a desert air base.
   The Foreign Ministry said this oil-rich state supports the
multinational force deployed in neighboring Saudi Arabia. The
United States and Arab countries have sent troops to Saudi Arabia
to defend the kingdom from possible attack by Iraq, which invaded
neighboring Kuwait on Aug. 2.
   ``The United Arab Emirates has agreed to receive some Arab and
friendly forces as a contribution to the Arab and international
efforts being exerted to defend the region,'' said the Foreign
Ministry statement released by the United Arab Emirates' official
news agency.
   It did not specifically name any countries or say how many
forces would be involved.
   Diplomatic sources said the statement gave approval to deploy
U.S., Egyptian and Pakistani troops in the United Arab Emirates.
   ``We are not expecting more than 5,000 soldiers from each of the
three states to be deployed in the U.A.E,'' said a Western
diplomat, who could not be identified under his embassy's rules.
   The brief Foreign Ministry statement said the deployment of
foreign troops in the country was in line with various
international agreements, including the charters of the United
Nations and the Arab League.
   The statement also said the deployment was in keeping with U.N.
Security Council resolutions denouncing the Iraqi invasion of
Kuwait and the decision taken at the Arab League summit in Cairo,
Egypt, to send a multinational Arab force to defend threatened
Persian Gulf states.
   The United States has undertaken a massive buildup of air, naval
and ground troops in the gulf region after Iraqi troops were
reported massing on Kuwait's border with Saudi Arabia.
   So far, foreign troops have been deployed only in Saudi Arabia,
where U.S. forces have been joined by troops from Egypt, Morocco
and Syria. Pakistan and Bangladesh have also agreed to send forces
to Saudi Arabia.
   The six-nation Gulf Cooperation Council, which includes the
United Arab Emirates, has also sent some troops to Saudi Arabia.
   Bahrain, which provides naval facilities to the United States,
has reached agreement with Britain to open its air space and air
bases to Royal Air Force squadrons of Jaguar and Tornado warplanes.
   The United Arab Emirates is located at the southern rim of the
Persian Gulf, near the strategic Strait of Hormuz. The gulf is
Iraq's outlet to the sea.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0050 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-19-90 1724EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BRF--WisconsinCrash     08-19 0131</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Wisconsin Crash,0134</SECOND>
<HEAD>Seven Die Moments After Takeoff</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WATERTOWN, Wis. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The wreckage of a single-engine plane
that apparently crashed just after takeoff was found Sunday with
the bodies of seven victims, including four children.
   The plane left the Watertown airport Saturday night, and there
was no hint of a problem until the pilot's wife reported Sunday
morning that it was missing, Jefferson County sheriff Keith Mueller
said.
   Authorities said searchers found the aircraft in a field about a
half mile south of the airport.
   Mueller said authorities assumed the plane crashed on takeoff,
not while coming back for a landing.
   There was no immediate indication of the cause. There were
occasional thundershowers during the night, and the cornfield was
shrouded in a thin haze during the morning search.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0051 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-PX-08-19-90 1953EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-FatalVision 1stLd-Writethru a0727 08-19 0822</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Fatal Vision, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0727,0837</SECOND>
<HEAD>`Fatal Vision' Again: New Evidence Promised in Jeffrey MacDonald
Case</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: ADDS 1 graf with background on von Bulow case; no pickup</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By DANA KENNEDY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Pruss wkuer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   the defense attorneys who won an acquittal for
Claus von Bulow say they have new evidense`in the Jeffrey MacDonald
case, the subject of the best-selling book ``Fatal Vision.''
   Boston attorneys Harvey Silverglate and Alan Dershowitz plan to
file a writ of habeas corpus to overturn the conviction of
MacDonald, a Green Beret found guilty of murdering his wife and two
daughters 22 years ago. The motion is due to be filed in U.S.
District Court in Raleigh, N.C., sometime late next month or early
October.
   Silverglate said last week that his team has uncovered forensic
evidence in the highly publicized case that he says was hidden by
the government during MacDonald's trial and subsequent appeal. He
did not describe the evidence but said it corroborates a claim by a
woman, now dead, who allegedly had told others she participated in
the killings.
   ``Had it been available to Jeffrey MacDonald prior to the trial
he would have been acquitted,'' said Silverglate. ``It will
demonstrate that the story he told on the night of the murders was
true.''
   MacDonald, a Princeton-educated Army doctor, was convicted in
1979 of the bludgeoning and stabbing deaths of his pregnant wife,
Colette, and two small daughters, Kimberly and Kristen, at their
Fort Bragg, N.C., apartment in February 1970.
   MacDonald has maintained from the beginning that he and his
family were attacked in their home by three men accompanied by a
woman with ... hat, blond hair and boots. He said the woman
chanted, ``Acid is groovy, kill the pigs.''
   James Blackburn, who prosecuted the 1979 case, said Sunday he
has been hearing the writ would be filed for more than a year.
   ``They have made that claim for a long time that they were going
to file those motions,'' he said in a telephone interview from his
home in Raleigh, where he is now an attorney. ``Once they are
filed, I or the appropriate authorities will file a response.
   ``During the trial certainly absolutely no evidence was hidden
from the defense that they were entitled to,'' he added.
   MacDonald, 46, is currently serving three consecutive life
sentences at the Terminal Island federal penitentiary in San Pedro,
Calif. He was transferred there from a Phoenix prison three years
ago to be near his mother, Dorothy MacDonald, who is in poor health.
   ``I shouldn't be in prison,'' said MacDonald in a telephone
interview from prison Friday. ``I'm going to keep fighting. ... I
would never give up and just remain quietly in prison. I need to be
vindicated.''
   MacDonald asked Silverglate to take his case in 1983 and called
him again last year with the new evidence. MacDonald, working from
prison with a network of outside investigators and supporters,
uncovered the new evidence, said attorney Phil Cormier, part of the
defense team.
   MacDonald's case has followed a surreal, zigzag course through
the years. Though he was originally a suspect in the case, the Army
cleared him of charges after the longest pre-trial hearing in
military history. He moved to Huntington Beach, Calif., and took a
job as an emergency physician at a Long Beach hospital.
   His father-in-law, Freddy Kassab, initially his staunchest
supporter, turned bitterly against him and conducted a virtual
crusade against him. Kassab's persistence led in part to
MacDonald's eventual indictment in 1975. MacDonald was tried and
convicted of the crimes in 1979.
   A one-time suspect in the case, Helena Stoeckley, a chronic drug
abuser, allegedly confessed to the crimes to various people on
several occasions. The testimony of those people to whom Stoeckley
allegedly confessed was not allowed during the trial. Stoeckley
died in 1983.
   Silverglate said the new evidence links both Stoeckley and
others to the crime scene and corroborates the testimony she gave
witnesses for the first time.
   Author Joe McGinniss wrote the best-selling 1983 book ``Fatal
Vision,'' in which he concluded MacDonald was guilty of the
murders. The book was made into a highly rated television movie.
   MacDonald later sued McGinniss, claiming the author lied to gain
his confidence and write the book. MacDonald won a $325,000
out-of-court settlement but was allowed to keep just $50,000.
   MacDonald said he is convinced he will finally be vindicated
once the new evidence is made public.
   ``Then I can home and rebuild my life,'' he said.
   Blackburn characterized the legal maneuvering as ``another in a
long series of attempts by MacDonald to deny that he was in fact
involved, when a trial jury found he was guilty.''
   Dershowitz and Silvergate made the celebrated defense of Claus
von Bulow, who in 1985 was acquitted in Rhode Island of trying to
murder his heiress wife, Martha ``Sunny'' von Bulow. Von Bulow had
been convicted three years earlier.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0052 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-PX-08-19-90 1945EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-SouthAfrica 1stLd-Writethru a0692 08-19 0694</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-South Africa, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0692,0712</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tribal Fighting Claims 49 More Lives</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 17 grafs to UPDATE with death toll rising to 49;
ADD comments by ANC and Inkatha leaders; pickup 16th graf pvs `But
the ...'</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto JOH2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GREG MYRE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JOHANNESBURG, South Africa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Police said Sunday that 49
blacks were killed in weekend tribal fighting waged with clubs,
machetes and spears, bringing the death toll in a week of violence
to 291.
   Soldiers were sent in to assist police in Tokoza and other
townships east of Johannesburg, where battles broke out a week ago
between Xhosas and Zulus, the country's two largest black tribes.
   Despite the increased security presence, 49 blacks were killed
in Tokoza and five neighboring townships from Saturday morning
through Sunday night, said police spokeswoman Lt. Ida van Zweel.
   Some victims were ritually castrated and had their hands cut
off. Corpses were burned so badly police could not determine if the
deceased were men or women.
   At least 213 blacks have died in Tokoza and neighboring
townships since Aug. 12. Another 78 blacks have been killed in
Soweto township southwest of Johannesburg during the same period.
   Xhosas on Sunday looted a deserted migrant workers hostel in
Tokoza that had been occupied by thousands of Zulus a week earlier.
Smoke rose from one hostel building that had been set alight.
   Police fired tear gas and shotguns to drive off looters. But
when the police left, the looters returned, piling refrigerators,
stoves and other items into cars and pickup trucks.
   There were scattered clashes and at least one Zulu was killed
Sunday morning, witnesses said. Some Zulus returned to the hostel
to pick up their possessions.
   ``They are trying to kill me,'' one Zulu man said of the Xhosas.
``It is a war.''
   More than 6,000 armed Zulus remained at hostels in other parts
of Tokoza, police said.
   ``Has the descent into a Beirut-style apocalypse begun?'' asked
the Sunday Times, the country's largest-circulation newspapaper.
   ``In countless white homes, families watched the carnage and
wondered if it would ever be possible to share power with people
who regard the panga (machete) and the knobkerrie (club) as tools
of political expression,'' the newspaper said in a front-page
editorial.
   The fighting appears to be mostly a tribal conflict with a long
history, but it also has political overtones.
   Nelson Mandela and many other leaders of the African National
Congress, the largest opposition movement, are Xhosas. The rival
Inkatha movement is a Zulu-based organization headed by Mangosuthu
Buthelezi.
   According to local media reports Sunday, an ANC leader, Walter
Sisulu, blamed Inkatha for the violence. But Buthelezi denied the
allegation.
   ``It only stokes the violence when he (Sisulu) indulges in war
talk,'' Buthelezi said. ``It's nonsense to say that Inkatha ... has
imported the violence.''
   Mandela and Buthelezi are old friends, and both have repeatedly
called for an end to black faction fighting that has plagued the
eastern province of Natal for five years and now is spreading to
the Johannesburg area.
   But the two men have not met since Mandela was released from
prison in February after serving 27 years for plotting to overthrow
the white-led government.
   City Press, the country's largest black-oriented weekly, printed
an open letter to Mandela and Buthelezi, urging them to hold
immediate peace talks.
   ``Like millions of other black people, I cannot understand why
you (Mandela) refuse to talk to Dr. Buthelezi, when at the drop of
a hat you meet and talk to (President) F.W. de Klerk,'' wrote the
paper's editor, Khulu Sibiya.
   ``I also fail to understand why in this century you (Buthelezi)
still encourage tribalism among your people,'' Sibiya added.
   Both the ANC and Inkatha oppose apartheid, the system of racial
segregation that allows the 5 million whites to maintain political
and economic control over the 30 million blacks.
   However, the two black-led groups differ over tactics. The ANC
has favored confrontational tactics such as boycotts and strikes,
but recently agreed to suspend its ineffective armed struggle
against the government.
   The relatively conservative Inkatha movement has never endorsed
those methods, and favors capitalism as opposed to the
socialist-oriented ANC.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0053 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-PX-08-19-90 1948EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Gulf-AtSea 1stLd-Writethru a0700 08-19 0664</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-At Sea, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0700,650</SECOND>
<HEAD>Sailors At Sea: Life-and-Death Video Games, Cigarette Smoke,
Shotguns</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: Subs grafs 17-19, ``Posted where xxx to CORRECT spelling of
Aqaba</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By SUSANNE M. SCHAFER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Military Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ABOARD THE USS SCOTT (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The sailors aboard this guided
missile destroyer control what their captain calls life-or-death
``video games'' in their mission to help tie the noose around Iraqi
commerce.
   Young sailors closely studying an array of video screens puff on
cigarettes. Swirls of smoke fill the air.
   Nearby, a specially trained boarding party stands ready with
hand-held radios and shotguns.
   The USS Scott is on duty in the northern Red Sea.
   Hours after ships in the USS Eisenhower battle group confronted
their first Iraqi vessels Saturday with shots across the bows of
two tankers, Cmdr. Tom Corcoran is giving Defense Secretary Dick
Cheney and a pool of Pentagon reporters a glimpse of the work
aboard his ship.
   In the darkened, high-tech Combat Intelligence Center that is
the warship's nerve center, sailors peer at giant circular screens,
marked with neon symbols. They keep track of any air, sea or
underwater threat to them or their lead ship.
   ``It's a little like being an air traffic controller in New York
City or Chicago,'' Corcoran says. ``These guys are playing an
enormous video game with life or death consequences.''
   The threat of missiles, mines or enemy aircraft could bring
death to those aboard the battle group as it spreads across this
vital shipping lane on the Eastern Coast of Saudi Arabia.
   Corcoran shows Cheney the room's wide array of computers and
weaponry guidance systems as he introduces young sailors who man
some of the world's most potent weapons.
   Memories of past tragedies are in everyone's mind as Cheney
views the Close-in Weapons System control panel, which directs a
high-speed cannon.
   ``It's a last-ditch weapon, but it's so fast it can shoot the
missiles right out of the sky,'' Lt.j.g. Daryl Hancock tells the
defense secretary.
   ``They didn't use it on the Stark,'' he said, recalling the May
1987 incident in which an Iraqi Exocet missile inadvertently hit
the USS Stark, killing 32 American sailors.
   At other screens that glow brilliant orange in the darkened
room, sailors operate equipment to differentiate between friends
and foes.
   Murmuring into headsets and drawing nervously on cigarettes,
sailors follow aircraft along the commercial routes in the region,
looking for any that stray from the known pathways.
   They look for any threat to the aircraft carrier USS Eisenhower,
its crew of 5,200, or other U.S. ships and their crews.
   Corcoran's ship and the Eisenhower battle group have been at sea
since March. Once the alert was sounded after Iraq's Aug. 2
invasion of Kuwait, the battle group went into an 18-hour frenzy to
arm and supply itself for passage through the Suez Canal and into
the Persian Gulf.
   Posted where it can stop ships entering or leaving the crucial
Jordanian port of Aqaba, the Scott became one of the first ships to
play an active role in President Bush's interception of Iraqi
shipping.
   Aqaba has been the one loophole through which Iraq has
transported goods since a United Nations-mandated trade embargo
began.
   Most ships encountered by the Scott have been empty or posed no
problem, Corcoran says, but a Cypriot freighter carrying aluminum
chromate and other chemicals bound for Aqaba was told not to
continue and turned back after an hour of radio communications, the
captain says.
   Corcoran describes his crew as ``very, very alert, but very
confident and relaxed about what they're doing.''
   Aboard the Eisenhower, Cheney tells sailors and marines that
they are involved in an international struggle for control of the
world's oil reserves.
   Speaking of Iraqi leader Saddam Hussein, Cheney says, ``If he
succeeds, he'll control the world economy.''
   ``It`s tough, hard, dirty duty,'' Cheney says. ``But it is an
enormously important deployment. This may be one of the most
important moments for this nation for the rest of this century.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0054 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-PX-08-19-90 1954EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Honduras-Guerrillas     08-19 0453</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Honduras-Guerrillas,0468</SECOND>
<HEAD>Honduras Armed Forces Chief Warns Of Crackdown on Left</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By FREDDY CUEVAS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>OMOA, Honduras (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The armed forces chief Sunday warned of a
renewed crackdown on leftists, saying guerrillas have infiltrated
the military and planned a wave of attacks.
   ``Subversion is a reality in Honduras,'' said armed forces chief
Arnulfo Cantarero Lopez in an interview with The Associated Press.
``And to counteract this, the country could return to the era of
the doctrine of national security,''
   Cantarero Lopez was referring to the period from 1982-1984 when
the armed forces, then led by Gen. Gustavo Alvarez Martinez,
followed a policy of detaining leftists in advance of attacks.
   Human rights organizations have accused the armed forces of
killing about 300 people and causing the disappearance of 150
others during that period.
   Alvarez Martinez was shot to death in 1988 by the Cinchonero
Popular Liberation Movement. Cantarero Lopez, 44, took over the
post in January.
   In the interview, he said, ``The armed forces have been
infiltrated by leftist guerrillas who are now trying to obtain
resources to finance a wave of terrorism in Honduras.''
   The general, interviewed in the city of Omoa 180 miles north of
Tegucigalpa, suggested the leftists ``could be financed by
international drug trafficking.''
   ``This is logical because traditionally Honduras has been used
as a trampoline for drug traffic between Colombia and the United
States,'' he said.
   He did not specify what national security measures the
22,000-member army might take.
   But he said, ``The armed forces will do everything possible to
block the communists from taking power in our nation ... and in
this fight we hope to count on the aid of our people.''
   ``The armed forces are vulnerable ... and have been infiltrated
by subversion,'' said Cantarero Lopez. ``Military intelligence has
detected numerous cases of guerrilla infiltration. ...''
   He said a foiled bank robbery on Aug. 15 in El Zamorano, 18
miles east of Tegucigalpa, ``was the work of the Cinchoneros.''
   No group has admitted attempting that robbery, which resulted in
the deaths of six alleged guerrillas, three policemen, a bank guard
and two other people. Six security agents were injured.
   ``The native guerrillas have been strengthened by the return of
numerous Honduran leftists who for the past decade were in exile in
Nicaragua,'' Cantarero Lopez said. ``The local insurgents have been
trained for the past 10 years in the Soviet Union, Cuba and Libya.
Because of that, they are well consolidated.''
   ``We don't want to frighten the people, but the genesis of
leftist violence has already been introduced in Honduras,'' he said.
   The Cinchoneros rose in Honduras in 1979 as an armed wing of the
Communist Party, which has operated clandestinely since 1920.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0055 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-PX-08-19-90 1957EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Magellan-Venus     08-19 0392</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Magellan-Venus,0405</SECOND>
<HEAD>NASA Unloads Magellan Memory Banks to Diagnose Venus Orbiter's
Woes</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PASADENA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Engineers continued to read data from
Magellan's memory banks Sunday, looking for clues as to why the
unmanned space probe temporarily lost contact with Earth during its
mission around Venus.
   Franklin O'Donnell, a spokesman for the Jet Propulsion
Laboratory in Pasadena, said the process of reading the craft's
computer memory would take another four or five days.
   ``We're only getting data at 40 bits per second,'' O'Donnell
said. ``Usually we read it at some thousand bits per second.''
   In order to regain solid communication with Magellan, ground
engineers commanded the craft to point a secondary antenna at
Earth, O'Donnell said.
   Magellan's secondary antenna sends a much broader radio beam
than the main antenna. But it sends data at a slower 40 bits per
second, so unloading Magellan's memory banks proceeded at a crawl.
   But the contact with Magellan was ``quite solid,'' O'Donnell
said.
   The engineers lost contact with Magellan Thursday night just
after it bounced radar waves off Venus for a test and sent the
information to Earth.
   They already know the malfunction made one of Magellan's
computers stop sending signals called ``heartbeats'' to another
computer, said David Okerson, a Magellan engineer assigned to JPL.
   That spurred Magellan to put itself into a series of protective
safety modes that cut off contact with Earth, then sent radio
signals across the heavens in a long effort to restore its radio
link with controllers.
   A steady hookup was re-established Friday night after nearly 15
hours of no radio contact followed by eight hours of intermittent
contact.
   ``The spacecraft administered CPR to itself,'' Okerson said.
``These protection mechanisms just saved our bacon.''
   Jet Propulsion Laboratory spokeswoman Mary Beth Murrill said the
time needed to diagnose and fix the problem likely would delay the
planned Aug. 29 start of Magellan's mission to use radar to map
Venus' cloud-covered surface.
   Normal contact with Magellan would be restored after it is
ordered to leave the safety mode, point its main antenna at Earth
and send data at a higher speed. Scientists hope to do that this
week.
   Magellan was launched from the shuttle Atlantis on its $744
million Venus exploration mission on May 4, 1989. It went into
orbit around Venus Aug. 10 after a circuitous trip of 948 million
miles.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0056 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-PX-08-19-90 2058EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-GasolineSpill 2ndLd-Writethru a0715 08-19 0326</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gasoline Spill, 2nd Ld - Writethru, a0715,0328</SECOND>
<HEAD>150,000 Gallons Of Gasoline Spills Into Delaware After
Barge-Tanker Crash</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: UPDATES throughout with no fish kills reported, tanker
carrying cat feed stock, damaged tank emptied; no pickup</NOTE>
<DATELINE>LEWES, Del. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A fuel barge and an oil tanker collided in
the Delaware River early Sunday, spilling about 150,000 gallons of
gasoline from the barge, the Coast Guard said. Environmental damage
was expected to be minor.
   The tanker had hull damage in the bow area, but did not spill
any of its cargo. No one was injured in the 12:45 a.m. accident 4
miles off Lewes at the mouth of Delaware Bay, Coast Guard officials
said.
   The gasoline was not expected to hit the Delaware or New Jersey
shorelines and did not pose an environmental threat, said Coast
Guard Cmdr. Steve Gilbert in Philadelphia. No fish kills were
reported by late Sunday.
   The Coast Guard said it did not plan to try a cleanup because
the gas would evaporate.
   The Panamanian-registered tanker, the Faith I, was carrying cat
feed stock, a substance used in refining overseas. It was loaded
overseas and headed to Coast Eagle Point in New Jersey. The tugboat
independence was pushing the barge Ocean 192 and was en route from
Marcus Hook, Pa., to Boston, Gilbert said.
   Both were taken to Big Stone Anchorage where the barge was being
unloaded. The anchorage is an area in the middle of Delaware Bay
used as a parking lot for tankers which draw too much water to
proceed farther up the river toward Wilmington and Philadelphia.
   The barge's seven tanks were loaded with 7.1 million gallons of
gasoline and No. 2 fuel oil. The tank that spilled the fuel held
600,000 gallons of gasoline, Gilbert said.
   The remaining gas from the damaged tank was emptied onto another
barge Sunday evening, Gilbert said.
   Further details of the accident were not released pending an
investigation, Coast Guard officials said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0057 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-PX-08-19-90 2103EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-DrivingPoll 2ndLd-Writethru a0729 08-19 0520</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Driving Poll, 2nd Ld - Writethru, a0729,0527</SECOND>
<HEAD>Poll: People Like to Drive, But That Doesn't Mean They're Good at
It</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS grafs 2, 6 and 8 to add percentage of respondents in
`didn't know' category to make percents add up to 100. </NOTE>
<HEAD>With AM-Driving Poll-List</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOUISVILLE, Ky. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Most Americans like to drive, but they
don't know as much about it as they might think.
   An oil company's second annual poll of American motorists found
that 81 percent of American drivers love or like to drive, while
only 16 percent said they dislike driving and 3 percent didn't know.
   But when asked 10 questions about causes of accidents, how to
avoid them and how to survive them, not one of the 500 licensed
drivers participating in the poll answered all of them correctly.
   Among other findings in the poll, being issued Monday by
Valvoline, automotive products subsidiary of Ashland Oil Inc. of
Ashland:
   _Thirty percent of those surveyed rated New York City drivers
the worst. Los Angeles was second, with 10 percent.
   _Fifty-four percent said they were better than other drivers,
while 43 percent said their driving habits were about the same as
others in their cities and towns. Two percent said they were worse
drivers and 1 percent didn't know. _Nineteen percent said they
always observed speed limits, while 58 percent said they did so
most of the time. Seventeen percent said they sometimes obeyed
speed signs, but 5 percent said they hardly ever did and 1 percent
said they always ignored posted speed limits.
   _Thirty-two percent said gender was not a factor in driving
skills, 36 percent said men were better drivers, 28 percent
responded that women were better and 4 percent didn't know.
Fifty-five percent of those surveyed were women and 45 percent were
men.
   The nationwide poll was conducted through random telephone calls
during June by Fleishman-Hillard Research Inc. of St. Louis. Its
reported margin of error was 4 to 6 percentage points.
   The 10 true-or-false questions on driving safety and accident
avoidance included ones on where and when most traffic deaths occur
(rural, and at night); whether accidents are primarily due to
mechanical failures (no); and whether seat belts give you a better
chance in getting out of burning or submerged vehicle (yes _ just
28 percent got this right).
   Drivers also had the chance in the poll to sound off about what
irks them the most about other drivers. At the top of the list was
failure to use turn signals, cited by 24 percent of the
participants.
   Other bad habits cited included cutting off or pulling in front
of other drivers, driving too slowly and tailgating.
   On driving issues, 90 percent said motorcyclists should be
required by law to wear helmets and 79 percent said air bags should
be standard equipment in passenger cars and trucks.
   Only 30 percent said they don't want permissible blood-alcohol
levels lowered to make drunk-driving laws more strict. Sixty-eight
percent said they want tougher laws.
   And 57 percent agreed that alternative fuels, such as methanol
and natural gas, are practical alternatives to gasoline.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0058 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-PX-08-19-90 2105EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Gulf-AirGuard     08-19 0516</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Air Guard,0530</SECOND>
<HEAD>Air Guard's Deployment Changes Nature of a Town</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RAY FORMANEK Jr.</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MARTINSBURG, W.Va. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   It's a lot easier to get a window
booth these days at Joann's Pantry, a lunch time favorite of the
West Virginia Air National Guard's 167th Tactical Airlift Group.
   ``A lot of our regulars are over in the Middle East,'' said Bob
Garza, who manages the restaurant. ``I would say our lunch business
has been down 50 percent since they pulled out last week.''
   The 1,200-member group drops men and equipment from C-130
turboprop aircraft into battle zones. It has shipped at least 194
volunteers to various locations, including the Middle East, since
Aug. 8.
   Thirty unit members were sent to Saudi Arabia, said Adj. Gen.
Joseph Skaff, state secretary for public safety.
   Skaff, who commands the air guard and the state's Army National
Guard, said most of the rest were filling in at U.S. bases for
regular troops deployed to the Middle East.
   The group, based in this northeastern West Virginia town, is
comprised mainly of West Virginians but includes members from
nearby Maryland, Pennsylvania and Virginia.
   ``No one around here is saying anything,'' said Garza, 42, as he
served food on a slower-than-usual Friday. ``I haven't really heard
much about it and we're familiar and close to a lot of them.''
   Air guard members quickly volunteered for duty after Iraq
invaded Kuwait and the United States began moving troops to the
region. Their response carried on a patriotic tradition, said Jack
Koch, a retired Air National Guard colonel and former air commander
of the 167th.
   West Virginia has, on a per capita basis, more Medal of Honor
winners than any other state, Koch said. It also has the greatest
number of war volunteers and the highest number of war casualties,
on a per capita basis.
   There are few outward signs of the mobilization around this
prosperous town of 14,000, where many residents commute to work in
Washington. Residents are as likely to shrug as to answer when
asked about the call-up.
   ``Before it was communism, now it's oil,'' said Jim Mahares, 40,
as he tended his hot dog stand on the town's main street.
   ``No one has said a single thing to me about this,'' said F.
Page Burdette, editor of The Morning Journal. ``We have received no
letters to the editor, no phone calls, nothing.
   ``Now, if you ask them `What do you think about gas prices going
up?' that's different,'' Burdette said. ``They're thinking about
their pocketbooks.''
   National Guard members from at least 21 states are part of the
U.S. mobilization.
   The Pentagon has refused to say how many guardsmen were
deployed. But information from state capitals indicates that more
than 1,000 air crew members, technicians, communications experts
and medical personnel have volunteered for duty.
   Skaff said West Virginia guardsmen and their aircraft could be
close to the fighting if a shooting war breaks out.
   ``These aircraft would be in country, moving troops from a port
to an operational base,'' Skaff said. ``We're the local commuters
if you will.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0059 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-PX-08-19-90 2114EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-US-Gulf 4thLd-Writethru a0766 08-19 0765</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-US-Gulf, 4th Ld-Writethru, a0766,690</SECOND>
<HEAD>Congressmen Advocate Firing on Iraqi Vessels</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: Subs 14th graf, ``CBS News xxx to delete reference to the 35
Americans being same ones who previously in hotel</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By JIM ABRAMS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two influential Democratic congressmen said
Sunday that U.S. warships should fire on Iraqi vessels that ignore
orders to stop, even if that meant an act of war against Iraq.
   Rep. Les Aspin, D-Wis., chairman of the House Armed Services
Committee, said U.S. warships should be prepared to fire on ships
that try to break the embargo against Iraq.
   ``I think that's what a blockade is all about,'' Aspin said on
NBC-TV's ``Meet the Press'' program. ``You give people ample
warning to stop and to be searched and to be checked out, and then
if they don't, then of course you proceed to try and disable the
ship.''
   U.S. Navy vessels in the Persian Gulf region fired warning shots
at two Iraqi oil tankers Saturday, following President Bush's
orders Thursday to interdict shipments in and out of Iraq using
``the minimum force necessary.''
   The oil tankers proceeded without stopping and were being
monitored by U.S. warships. The Pentagon said it knew nothing about
a claim by the official Iraqi news agency's of a third firing
Sunday.
   Rep. Lee Hamilton, D-Ind., chairman of the House Middle East
subcommittee, said any firing on an Iraqi vessel ``would be an act
of war'' under international law.
   Hamilton said that if Bush orders ships to open fire, ``I
believe that the Congress will support the president.''
   The White House dismissed an offer by Iraqi President Saddam
Hussein to release Westerners held since the Aug. 2 invasion of
Kuwait if Bush offers written guarantees that U.S. forces will be
withdrawn from Saudi Arabia and the economic boycott against Iraq
is ended.
   ``It seems we're getting a daily seminar of Iraqi ridicule these
days,'' said White House spokesman Marlin Fitzwater. He said the
latest Iraqi proposal ``doesn't have much relationship to our
objective and contains no new relevant proposals and makes no
reference to the United Nations and Arab League calls for them to
leave Kuwait.''
   Washington has insisted that U.S. military action in the Middle
East will end only after Saddam removes his troops from Kuwait and
the ousted Kuwaiti government is restored to power.
   Fitzwater commented on Air Force One as Bush was returning to
Washington from his Maine vacation home Sunday afternoon for a
meeting with national security adviser Brent Scowcroft.
   In related news Sunday:
   _Undersecretary of State for Political Affairs Robert Kimmitt
said on the NBC program that there was no confirmation yet the
Iraqis were carrying through on threats to move Americans and other
foreigners to vital targets to deter a U.S. attack. He said the
State Department was urging the estimated 3,000 Americans trapped
in Iraq and occupied Kuwait to stay in their homes but not to
resist if Iraqi authorities try to move them.
   _CBS News, quoting a U.S. consular official in Baghdad, reported
that 35 Americans have been taken to U.S. diplomatic quarters in
the Iraqi capital. A State Department official, asked about the
report, said ``We can't comment on that at this time.''
   _Iraqi Ambassador to the United States Mohammed Sadiq al-Mashat,
interviewed on ABC-TV's ``This Week With David Brinkley'' program,
rejected suggestions that Iraq was violating international norms by
refusing to allow Americans and other Westerners to leave Iraq and
Kuwait.
   ``When you deny our children food and milk, what do you
expect?'' he said, adding that the United States should work for
peace rather than ``beating the drums of war'' because ``we are on
the brink of a catastrophe for everybody.''
   _Sen. Ted Stevens, R-Alaska, said Defense Secretary Dick Cheney
has asked Transportation Secretary Samuel Skinner to authorize the
use of armed Coast Guard personnel for boarding ships in the
Persian Gulf region. But a Coast Guard spokesman, Lt. Cmdr. Kim
Krzywicki, said the agency had heard nothing about such an
assignment.
   The White House has shied away from referring to U.S. Navy
action in the Middle East as a blockade, but Hamilton, also
speaking on NBC, said ``I think the lawyers may quibble about these
words, but I don't think the public does.''
   Hamilton and Aspin cautioned, however, that Bush will not have
support for use of military force against Iraq unless Iraqi
President Saddam Hussein escalates the current war of nerves.
   ``The key is that the president and the Congress must not move
too far out in front of the consensus,'' both domestic and
international, Hamilton said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0060 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-PX-08-19-90 2133EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Stealth-Gulf     08-19 0563</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Stealth-Gulf,0584</SECOND>
<HEAD>Stealth Fighters En Route to Middle East</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By D.W. PAGE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HAMPTON, Va. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Air Force showed off its once-secret
Stealth fighter Sunday as 22 of the attack planes headed toward the
Mideast in a show of force intended to warn Iraq of U.S. air
superiority.
   Reporters were invited to Langley Air Force Base to view the
F-117A planes as they landed here en route to joining the military
buildup in the Persian Gulf.
   The United States has said the buildup is defensive and intended
to assure that the Iraqis, who invaded Kuwait on Aug. 2, don't
attempt further military adventures.
   Col. Anthony Tolin, until recently a wing commander of the
Stealth fighters, which are based at Nellis Air Fore Base in
Nevada, acknowledged the F-117A is not a defensive weapon.
   ``I guess it would be tough to classify the F-117A as a purely
defensive weapon. It's defensive nature is its ability to penetrate
enemy radar without detection,'' Tolin said.
   He said the presence of the planes in the gulf could be an
important psychological weapon.
   ``They give us an ability, should we need it, to get in with the
least amount of casualties and attack those important targets if
necessary,'' Tolin said.
   The planes are scheduled to leave for the gulf Monday afternoon.
   The Air Force has already sent F-15 fighter planes and A-10s
since Iraq moved on Kuwait and massed troops on Kuwait's border
with Saudi Arabia. The A-10 is a ground support aircraft designed
to take out tanks and other armored vehicles.
   Tolin said the Stealth fighter was designed ``to penetrate enemy
defenses, to locate high priority targets and to deliver
ordinance.''
   The plane was once considered so secret the Air Force flew it
only at night on test missions high above the Nevada desert. The
plane was designed and built by Lockheed Co.'s super-secret ``Skunk
Works'' in Burbank, Ca. The Air Force says it has 56 of the planes.
   The F117A and the newer B2 Stealth bomber got their ``stealth''
nickname because they are designed to be nearly invisible to radar.
The F117A has seen combat only once, when they bombed a target
using laser-guided bombs during the December 1989 Panama invasion.
   Tolin left his job as commander of the 37th Tactical Fighter
Wing at Nellis two days ago. He is now assistant deputy chief of
staff of the Tactical Air Command at Langley.
   The planes began landing shortly after 3:30 p.m. About the size
of an F-15, the ungainly matte black jets gently settled onto the
runway and slowed with the help of a drogue chute.
   At $42.6 million per plane, not including the research and
development costs, the fighters are one of the world's most
expensive planes.
   Tolin said the planes are remarkably easy to fly, but was
closemouthed about the plane's capabilities and armament.
   He was more talkative about the plane's odd appearance.
   ``I'm often asked how I can love something this ugly,'' he said
as another F-117A landed. ``Tom Clancy, the author, gave me a good
story that can explain it.
   ``The Scottish wolfhound is considered the ugliest dog in all of
Scotland. But the owners of Scottish wolfhounds are always quick to
point out that there are no wolves in Scotland.''
   Clancy is the author of ``The Hunt for Red October'' and other
thrillers with military themes.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0061 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-PX-08-19-90 2143EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-PlanesCollide     08-19 0182</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Planes Collide,0189</SECOND>
<HEAD>Two Planes Crash Into Long Beach Harbor</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONG BEACH, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two small planes collided over Long
Beach Harbor and crashed into the water Sunday afternoon,
authorities said. Scuba divers were searching for the pilots and
any others on board.
   After the collision, one plane crashed just outside the
breakwater and the other plunged into the water near the entrance
to the Southern California harbor, said lifeguard Tim Murphy.
   It was not immediately known what type of aircraft were involved
or how many people were on board. Authorities described the planes
as small, private aircraft.
   No injuries or damage were reported to people or boats in the
harbor, authorities said.
   Scuba divers were searching for passengers and debris from the
planes.
   ``The area has been marked by buoys where some floating debris
and an oil slick is, but it's pretty deep and it going to be a
pretty difficult task,'' Murphy said.
   The Federal Aviation Administration said the planes were not in
contact with air traffic controllers when they collided.
   The National Transportation Safety Board was investigating.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0062 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-PX-08-19-90 2146EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Obit-Smith     08-19 0192</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Smith,0198</SECOND>
<HEAD>Kennedy Brother-in-Law Stephen E. Smith Dies</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Stephen E. Smith, who managed brother-in-law
John F. Kennedy's presidential campaign, died Sunday in his
Manhattan home after a long illness. He was 62.
   Smith, who was married to the former Jean Kennedy, also ran
several family businesses and advised the family on financial
matters and political campaigns, said Eddie Martin, a spokesman for
Sen. Edward Kennedy, D-Mass.
   ``For 34 years, from the day he married Jean, Steve was like a
brother in our family. He was the wisest adviser, the most skillful
campaign manager, and the best friend that any of us ever had,''
the senator said through his spokesman. ``There wouldn't have been
a Camelot without Steve Smith.''
   The spokesman who released news of the death did not give a
cause.
   Smith's survivors include his wife and his four children,
William, Stephen Jr., Amanda and Kym, all of whom were with him
when he died, Martin said.
   A funeral Mass is scheduled for 10 a.m. Tuesday at St. Thomas
More's Church.
   Viewing will be from 5 p.m. to 7:30 p.m. at the Frank E.
Campbell Funeral Chapel.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0063 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-PX-08-19-90 2154EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SriLanka     08-19 0298</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Sri Lanka,0307</SECOND>
<HEAD>Sri Lankan Rebels, Government Clash; At Least 22 Dead</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PATRICK CRUEZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>COLOMBO, Sri Lanka (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Tamil rebels killed nine soldiers in
an ambush on the west coast, and government forces killed at least
13 Tamil guerrillas in the east, military officials said Sunday.
   The soldiers were ambushed while patrolling near Karadipuval,
about 85 miles north of Colombo, on Saturday, according to the
officials, who cannot be identified under briefing rules. They gave
no other details on that clash.
   In the east, a helicopter gunship Saturday strafed about 30
Tamil Tiger guerrillas who were closing in on Colony 11, a Moslem
village in the Ampara district, the officials said. They said 10 to
12 of the guerrillas were killed.
   The government says the Tigers have massacred nearly 400 Moslems
this month, but the Tigers claim the killings were the work of
pro-government Tamils who are trying to discredit the Tigers.
   Three other Tigers were killed Saturday by police commandos
during search operations near Akkaraipattu, and a Moslem civilian
was killed in a cross-fire between the police and Tigers near
Colony 13, the officials said.
   Both those villages are in the Ampara district, about 120 miles
east of Colombo.
   The Tigers have been fighting the Sinhalese-controlled
government since 1983 in the quest for a separate homeland for
their ethnic minority. In the past two years, they also have
accused Moslems of supporting the government and attacked them too.
At least 14,000 people have died in the insurrection.
   Tamils comprise 18 percent of Sri Lanka's 16 million people and
say the Sinhalese discriminate against them in jobs and education.
   Sinhalese make up 75 percent of the population of this island
nation off the southern tip of India. Moslems account for 7 percent.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0064 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-PX-08-19-90 2219EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Canada-Indians     08-19 0433</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Canada-Indians,0446</SECOND>
<HEAD>Indians Agree to End Rail Blockade in Ontario</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONGLAC, Ontario (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Indian leaders on Sunday agreed to end a
blockade of CN Rail trains in northern Ontario, but other rail
lines remained blocked by Indian bands pressing land claims, police
said.
   After meeting with police, Indians from the Long Lake band
dismantled their blockade about 180 miles northeast of Thunder Bay
on Lake Superior. The four-day protest had blocked east-west trains
on Canadian National Rail lines, the nation's main transcontinental
rail link, for almost a week.
   But Indians from the Pic Mobert band continued to block Canadian
Pacific rail tracks near White River, Ontario.
   The Indian bands have been blocking the rail lines to call
attention to their land claims and demands for meetings with
federal Indian Affairs Minister Tom Siddon. They are also
expressing support for Mohawk Indians in Quebec who have been
engaged in an armed standoff with army troops and authorities in
another land dispute.
   Meanwhile, in British Columbia, the Seton-Portage Indian band
continued to block the BC Rail link between Vancouver and Prince
George, defying a court injunction to clear the tracks.
   Those Indians set up the blockade Friday because they were upset
with the response by British Columbia officials to their land claim
proposals.
   Details of the agreement to end the blockade of the CN Rail line
were not immediately available.
   ``We'll be moving quickly to restore normal traffic,'' CN Rail
spokesman Roger Cameron said late Sunday from Montreal. He said the
railway would rescind layoff notices sent to about 300 employees
because of slowdowns caused by the blockade.
   Sunday's meeting between police and the Indians was held in a
grassy field near the blocked CN Rail line.
   On Saturday, the railway obtained a court injunction Saturday
ordering the Long Lake Indians to clear tracks running through
their reservation, said a statement by the provincial police.
   CN service between Winnipeg and Toronto had been severely
disrupted since the blockade started Monday. Several trains a day
were canceled and hundreds of carloads of freight were delayed,
Cameron said.
   Talks between Pic Mobert leaders and mediator George Broeffle on
Saturday failed to settle the dispute after the Indians rejected
the latest government offer.
   British Columbia Rail obtained an injunction from the British
Columbia Supreme Court on Saturday night ordering the Seton-Portage
band to stop halting traffic of the line south of Lillooet, about
110 miles northeast of Vancouver.
   But the 70 Indians blocking the tracks refused to move Sunday
when railway officials arrived with three Royal Canadian Mounted
Police officers, said BC Rail spokesman Barrie Wall.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0065 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-PX-08-19-90 2233EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Deaths SUB   08-19 0201</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Deaths, SUB,0207</SECOND>
<NOTE>Eds: CORRECTS name of hospital in Skinner item to Mount Auburn
Hospital sted Auburn Hospital.
^By The Associated Press</NOTE>
<BYLINE>B.F. Skinner</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CAMBRIDGE, Mass. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   B.F. Skinner, one of the century's
leading psychologists who believed human behavior could be
engineered to build a better world, died Saturday of leukemia at
age 86.
   He was the patriarch of the school of thought known as
behaviorism and the inventor of the ``Skinner box,'' a tool he used
to demonstrate his theory that rewarded behavior is repeated.
   While remembered by many _ and sometimes scorned _ for teaching
pigeons to play pingpong and guide missiles, his book ``Walden
Two'' was required reading for a generation of college students in
the 1960s and 1970s.
   Burrhus Frederic Skinner views were based on his principle of
``operant behavior,'' the idea that seemingly spontaneous action is
regulated through rewards and punishment.
   Many psychologists disagreed with his theories.
   But his application of the ideas of the Russian physiologist
Ivan Pavlov left an indelible stamp on American society. Parents
use his ``operant conditioning'' each time they praise a behavior
they want and punish one they don't want.
   He died at Mount Auburn Hospital in Cambridge.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0066 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-PX-08-19-90 2243EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-GulfRdp 4thLd-Writethru a0770 08-19 0940</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf Rdp, 4th Ld-Writethru, a0770,0965</SECOND>
<HEAD>Saddam Offers to Free Foreigners if U.S. Pulls Out, Ends Embargo</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: INSERTS two grafs after 22nd `U.N. Secretary-General...' to
ADD U.N. meeting to discuss military action; pickup graf 23 pvs
`The United...'</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos DOD1,NY50,51,52,53</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By THOMAS WAGNER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Saddam Hussein offered on Sunday to free all foreigners in Iraq
and Kuwait if the United States promises to withdraw its forces
from Saudi Arabia and guarantees that an international economic
embargo will be lifted.
   U.S. and British officials dismissed the initiative.
   As a goodwill gesture, Iraq said it will immediately free all
detainees from Austria, Switzerland, Sweden, Finland and Portugal.
Those countries account for fewer than 600 of the 21,000 Westerners
who have been trapped in Kuwait and Iraq for the last three weeks.
   ``When the above-mentioned items are met, we will use our
constitutional powers to allow all the foreigners to travel out of
Iraq, each according to his wish,'' the official Iraqi News Agency
quoted the Iraqi president as saying.
   In the meantime, Saddam said, the remaining foreign captives,
including 3,000 Americans, will be held at vital Iraqi targets to
avoid the ``flood of fire'' that will result if U.S.-led forces
attack Iraq.
   CBS News reported from Baghdad on Sunday that 35 Americans,
including four women and three children, have taken refuge at U.S.
diplomatic ``quarters'' in the Iraqi capital. It did not specify
what it meant by quarters.
   The report quoted the officer in charge of the U.S. Embassy in
Baghdad, Joseph Wilson, as saying he and his staff were doing
everything possible to prevent Americans from being rounded up by
Iraqi authorities.
   Asked about the report, a spokesman at the State Department
said: ``We can't make a comment on that at this time.''
   One of the refuge-seeking Americans, Vivian Hill, of Orlando,
Fla., told CBS that her biggest concern was ``that it could get
worse. We could be taken from here. I wouldn't be surprised. We've
contemplated that happening.''
   CBS also reported that some other Americans had been taken from
a Baghdad hotel and dispersed as human shields at strategic
locations, including a sulphuric acid plant at Al Qaim, munitions
and chemical sites in Baiji and Taji, and a chemical and artillery
production facility at Al Iskandariyah.
   Saddam's statement, also carried on Iraqi television, was
described as an open letter to the families of the detained
foreigners.
   It was Saddam's second attempt to negotiate an end to the
Persian Gulf crisis since Iraq invaded Kuwait on Aug. 2 in a
dispute over oil, money and territory. He later annexed the
oil-rich nation.
   Earlier, Saddam had linked an Iraqi withdrawal from Kuwait with
an Israeli pullout from its occupied territories and a Syrian
withdrawal from Lebanon.
   White House spokesman Marlin Fitzwater dismissed the latest
Iraqi proposal.
   ``It seems we're getting a daily seminar of Iraqi ridicule these
days,'' said Fitzwater, who was traveling on Air Force One en route
from Kennebunkport, Maine to Washington.
   He said the Iraqi proposal ``doesn't have much relationship to
our objective and contains no new relevant proposals and makes no
reference to the United Nations and Arab League calls for them to
leave Kuwait.''
   When President Bush sent thousands of troops to defend Saudi
Arabia against a possible Iraqi attack, he also demanded that Iraqi
troops unconditionally withdraw from Kuwait and restore its
monarchy to power.
   In London, a British Foreign Office spokesman also dismissed
Saddam's latest initiative, saying, ``It doesn't represent any real
progress at all.''
   Saddam gave a lengthy justification Sunday for the invasion and
reiterated Iraq's longstanding claims to Kuwait.
   Earlier Iraqi announcements have ordered Westerners living in
Iraq and Kuwait to report to specific hotels, prompting fears they
will be interned. Iraq also has said that foreign babies and
elderly people will be the first to suffer if the embargo results
in food and medicine shortages in Iraq.
   Thomas R. Pickering, the U.S. ambassador to the United Nations,
said on Saturday that Saddam has made it clear he intends ``to hold
hostage all foreigners.'' U.S. officials previously had avoided
using the word hostage.
   U.N. Secretary-General Javier Perez de Cuellar, meanwhile,
dispatched two senior U.N. officials to Baghdad to urge Iraqi
officials to free its detainees. Perez de Cuellar said Saddam had
sent a letter requesting that the envoys be sent, but he did not
elaborate.
   The United States and the other four permanent members of the
U.N. Security Council met Sunday at the French Mission in New York
and explored the possibility of joint military action under the
U.N. charter, Western diplomats said.
   The meeting was inconclusive, but some members felt the council
should move toward some kind of military action, said a diplomat
who spoke on condition of anonymity. Informal private consultations
of the council were likely Monday.
   The United States is pouring thousands of soldiers into Saudi
Arabia, and U.S. officials have said the deployment could reach
200,000 men and women.
   Other Western and Arab countries have contributed troops to the
growing multinational force, but it is still made up of mostly U.S.
soldiers.
   Defense Secretary Dick Cheney said on Sunday that Iraq has
massed 200,000 troops and more than 1,000 tanks on the Saudi border.
   ``Should Saddam Hussein be foolish enough to launch an attack on
Saudi Arabia, we would be able to do a very effective job of making
him pay a bit of a price for that,'' said Cheney, who visited U.S.
soldiers in Saudi Arabia and seamen on the USS Eisenhower in the
Red Sea. ``Obviously, I'll be more comfortable once we've got more
forces in the country.''
   U.S. ships, 1st graf, a0771
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0067 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-PX-08-19-90 2248EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Obit-Skinner 2ndLd-Writethru a0798 08-19 1355</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Skinner, 2nd Ld - Writethru, a0798,1387</SECOND>
<HEAD>Psychologist B.F. Skinner Dead at 86</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: INSERTS 1 graf after 4th graf, `While remembered...' with
reaction from friend, picks up 5th graf, `Burrhus Frederic...;
INSERTS 2 grafs after 11th graf pvs, `But his...' with contrast to
cognitive psyhology, reaction from psychologist; picks up 12th graf
pvs, `Skinner, in...'; SUBS last graf with 2 grafs to include
mention of honors; no pickup</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY21, BX8</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DANIEL Q. HANEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CAMBRIDGE, Mass. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   B.F. Skinner, one of the century's
leading psychologists who believed human behavior could be
engineered to build a better world, died of leukemia. He was 86.
   Skinner died Saturday at Mount Auburn Hospital in this
university city, a hospital administrator said.
   He was the patriarch of the school of thought known as
behaviorism and the inventor of the ``Skinner box,'' a tool he used
to demonstrate his theory that rewarded behavior is repeated.
   While remembered by many _ and sometimes scorned _ for teaching
pigeons to play pingpong and guide missiles, his novel ``Walden
Two'' was required reading for a generation of college students in
the 1960s and 1970s.
   ``He was certainly the leading psychologist of his time,'' said
Richard Herrnstein, a psychology professor at Harvard who knew
Skinner for 38 years.
   Burrhus Frederic Skinner _ B.F. to the world, Fred to his
friends _ spent most of his career at Harvard, where he applied his
observations of animals to the motives and manipulation of human
conduct.
   Skinner's views were based on his principle of ``operant
behavior,'' the idea that seemingly spontaneous action is regulated
through rewards and punishment. People don't shape the world, he
said, the world shapes them.
   In the months leading up to his death, Skinner remained active,
preparing a defense of his research that explored the uses of
positive and negative reinforcement to improve human behavior.
   ``I will be dead in a few months,'' he said in an interview last
month. ``But it hasn't given me the slightest anxiety or worry or
anything; I always knew I was going to die.''
   Skinner believed that human behavior is predictable, just like a
chemical reaction. Since people were run through their paces by
their environment, ``behavioral technology'' could put them to work
to create a happy and safe world, free of overpopulation, war and
pollution.
   Many psychologists disagreed with his theories. Of his
contemporaries, Skinner once said, ``I can mention only one or two
who really very seriously changed their attitudes toward the study
of behavior as a result of anything I have ever done or said.''
   But his application of the ideas of the Russian physiologist
Ivan Pavlov left an indelible stamp on American society. Parents
use his ``operant conditioning'' each time they praise a behavior
they want and punish one they don't want.
   Skinner's work was opposed to that of the cognitive
psychologists, who emphasize the unconscious structures of the
human mind that are unaffected by conditioning. Skinner saw no
difference between brain and mind.
   ``What he did was decry psychological theory and place the
emphasis on what behavior could be observed,'' said Albert Ullman,
a retired professor of sociology at Tufts University in Medford.
   Skinner, in his later years a lean man with a fine-featured,
patrician face beneath a broad expanse of forehead, was born March
20, 1904, in Susquehanna, Pa., the elder son of Grace Burrhus, an
amateur musician, and William Skinner, a lawyer.
   After majoring in English at Hamilton College in Clinton, N.Y.,
Skinner decided he wanted to be a writer. He sent some short
stories to the poet Robert Frost, who wrote back: ``You are worth
twice anyone else I have seen in prose this year.''
   Skinner went to Manhattan's Greenwich Village to work on his
craft but after a year or so gave it up. ``I discovered the unhappy
fact that I had nothing to say,'' he recalled, ``and went on to
graduate study in psychology, hoping to remedy that shortcoming.''
   He was attracted to the work of John B. Watson, the founder of
behaviorism, and earned his doctorate from Harvard in 1931. He
taught at the University of Minnesota and Indiana University before
joining the Harvard faculty in 1947.
   It was at Harvard that the life-long tinkerer devised the
Skinner box, a soundproof enclosure with buttons or levers that
animals press to receive food in return for doing whatever the
experimentor wants them to do.
   The box provides a precise way to observe, record and measure
behavior. It is widely used by psychologists, many of whom are not
Skinnerians, as well as by drug researchers, who watch the way
animals react to new medicines.
   Skinner preferred to call his invention an ``operant
conditioning apparatus.'' He employed it to teach rats, and later
pigeons, to perform amazing tricks. Birds learned to play the
piano, walk in figure eights and dance.
   Table tennis, though, might have carried things too far. Asked
once what he would do differently if given the chance, he replied:
   ``Just one thing. I performed one experiment that has never
ceased to reverberate. I've been laughed at by enemies and kidded
by friends. If I could do it all over again, I'd never teach those
pigeons to play pingpong.''
   During World War II, he rigged up a way for a pigeon to guide a
missile to its goal by pecking on an image of the target when it
appeared on a screen. The government never adopted the method.
   In the 1940s, Skinner also invented something he thought could
revolutionize child rearing _ his air crib, known less reverently
as the baby box.
   The crib was a roomy, insulated, temperature-controlled box with
a window. Inside, the baby could sleep and play comfortably without
blankets or clothes. Skinner's younger daughter, Deborah, was
raised in an air crib for 2{ years. But like the pigeon-run
missiles, it never caught on.
   Many people's understanding of Skinner's vision for society came
from his novel ``Walden Two,'' which was published in 1948. In it,
he described a tightly controlled utopia in which people were
motivated by positive and negative reinforcements _ rewards and
punishment.
   During the 1960s and beyond, the book attracted a kind of cult
following. Hundreds of thousands of copies were sold, many to young
people intrigued by Skinner's image of a better world.
   In the society he drew, everyone is happy. People don't know the
meaning of envy and jealousy. Buildings are communally owned, and
everyone helps out with chores. There's time for reading and
painting, song and friendship.
   The key to this community's success is child rearing. Youngsters
are raised together. Discipline is strict, and children are taught
to rein in their desires though self-control exercises.
   Some critics decried his model society as tyrannical. Others
thought that a world populated by such happy and well-behaved
people would be bland indeed.
   Said psychologist Carl Rogers: ``I can only feel that he was
choosing these goals for others, not himself. I would hate to see
Skinner become well-behaved, as that term would be defined for him
by behavioral scientists. And the most awful fate I can imagine for
him would be to have him constantly happy. It is the fact that he
is very unhappy about many things which makes me prize him.''
   Skinner recorded his work in a series of scholarly books,
including ``The Behavior of Organisms,'' ``Verbal Behavior'' and
``Science and Human Behavior.'' He wrote a three-volume
autobiography, and as he turned 80 reflected on aging in ``Enjoy
Old Age.''
   After his retirement in 1974, Skinner maintained an office at
Harvard, walking the 2{ miles each day from his Cambridge home. He
also spoke occasionally at scientific societies, and in 1982 gave
the American Psychological Association a report on how to cope with
the frailties of age: Build a stimulating environment, create
memory tricks, work less and rest the mind between intellectual
workouts.
   His honors included the National Medal of Science, which he won
in 1968, and the gold medal of the American Psychological
Association, in 1971.
   Skinner is survived by his daughters, Deborah Buzan and Julie
Vargas, and his wife, Yvonne.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0068 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-PX-08-19-90 2332EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-DamThreatened 2ndLd-Writethru a0769 08-19 0516</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Dam Threatened, 2nd Ld - Writethru, a0769,0526</SECOND>
<NOTE>Eds: RETRANSMITTING to fix cycle designation</NOTE>
<HEAD>Precautionary Evacuations Begun After High Water Threatens Indiana
Dam</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Leads with 4 grafs with dam leaking, more rain forecast;
picks up 3rd graf pvs, `Other residents...</NOTE>
<DATELINE>ROCHESTER, Ind. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A A leaky dam forced the evacuation of a
hospital and apartments for the elderly Sunday after high water
threatened to break a dam on Lake Manitou, police said.
   ``If we don't get any more rain, we'll be all right,'' said
Mayor Philip Thompson, who was supervising the sandbagging efforts
of volunteers, police and civil defense officials.
   Forecasters predicted thunderstorms could bring two more inches
of rain early Monday, and the National Weather Service issued a
flash flood watch.
   Leaks appeared in the dam on Saturday, after six inches of rain
pushed the lake about two feet above flood stage. The lake rose at
about one inch per hour until cresting at 1 p.m. Sunday, Fulton
County Conservation Officer Dick Eurit said.
   At least 100 people were evacuated from the area immediately
below the dam, officials said.
   Other residents of the lightly populated area below the dam were
advised to leave their homes or prepare to evacuate if the dam were
to break, said Fulton County chief jailer Robert Bryant.
   Twenty-eight patients at Woodlawn Hospital were dismissed, taken
to other hospitals, nursing homes or the local high school
gymnasium shortly after midnight, officials said.
   Volunteers, fire crews and civil defense officials laid about
13,000 sand bags along the dam early Sunday, Bryant said.
   ``It's holding at this point. Our main problem is now we're
expecting another 2 to 3 inches of rainfall tonight,'' he said
Sunday afternoon.
   The U.S. Army Corps of Engineers brought large pumps to attempt
to lower the lake, the National Weather Service said.
   Lake Manitou is about 12 feet above Mill Creek, which flows
along the eastern edge of Rochester, a town of 5,000 in
north-central Indiana, and empties into the Tippecanoe River.
   A complete failure of the dam could raise Mill Creek by 6 feet,
the weather service said. It would crest in Rochester within a half
hour of a dam failure.
   ``The biggest problem it would affect would be our hospital. If
the dam was to go out, a large quantity of water would hit it,'' he
said.
   A similar threat faced the west-central Wisconsin town of Tomah
on Saturday. About 1,500 people evacuated when high water
threatened to rupture the Lake Tomah Dam on the Lemonweir River.
About 700 people stayed out of their homes during the night but
began returning Sunday.
   But flowing though the gates of the dam raised the level of the
Lemonweir River and caused alarm downriver in Mauston and New
Lisbon. The Juneau County sheriff's office said late Sunday the
Lemonweir was within a foot of flood stage.
   Tomah got about 8 inches of rain in three hours late Friday.
   The dam was reinforced with about 20,000 sandbags and its
reservoir dropped eight inches by Saturday night after the
floodgates were opened, said Tomah Fire Chief Tom Flock.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0069 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-PX-08-19-90 2333EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-High-TechAgriculture     08-19 0410</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-High-Tech Agriculture,0421</SECOND>
<HEAD>Thousands of Scientists Participate in Televised Plant Biotech
Symposium</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   PULLMAN, Wash. (A) _ A scientist in Egypt asked a question about
wheat, which was answered by an expert in West Germany. Observers
in Pullman and 80 other sites around the world listened in on the
exchange.
   The question from Cairo was one of more than 100 raised Saturday
during the first plant biotechnology symposium to be conducted via
worldwide telecommunications.
   Eight satellites carried the discussions _ between international
panels of scientists at the Max Planck Institute for Genetics
Research in West Germany and at Washington State University _ to 80
viewing stations around the world.
   Viewers' questions, relayed by facsimile machines, were passed
on to the panels, which had experts from Mexico, Australia, the
United States, Germany, India and the Soviet Union.
   C.A. ``Bud'' Ryan, director of Washington State's Institute of
Biological Chemistry, began planning the teleconference two years
ago. Afterward, he said he was ``thrilled beyond my wildest
expectations.''
   ``We didn't try to do this as a symposium that is going to bring
in new science. It was an experiment in the spirit of Ed Murrow,''
Ryan said. ``The news is happening so fast that you want to sit
back with the people that are making it and analyze what it means.''
   The question from Cairo _ about wheat's tolerance to drought and
salinity _ was answered in Germany by Jozef St. Schell, who said it
was too early to say when strains of wheat more capable of
surviving salty water and dry spells would be developed.
   Most of the questions came from developing nations, said James
Cook, a WSU biotechnolgy researcher who monitored the facsimile
machines.
   Biotechnology, which include genetic modification of plants and
animals so they can resist disease or be more productive, affects
everything from the color of flowers to plants' defense against
insects.
   Advances in communications technology, meanwhile, should allow
more scientific teleconferences to help spread new information,
said Donald E. Hanna, program coordinator and associate vice
provost for extended university services at Washington State
University.
   The broadcast ``really represents a first for this kind of
program,'' Hanna said.
   The teleconference, which cost $115,000, was sponsored by
Washington State, the Planck Institute, the U.S. Department of
Agriculture, the West German government, and private communications
companies.
   It was relayed to 60 U.S. universities and research centers, as
well as to Germany, Egypt, Pakistan, India, Thailand, Morocco,
Malawi, Mexico and Barbados, Hanna said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0070 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-19-90 1455EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f BC-BusinessHighlights     08-19 0884</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Business Highlights,0929</SECOND>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Investors dumped stocks and dollars as oil and
gasoline prices shot higher and uncertainty intensified about the
desert standoff against Iraq and its effect on the weak U.S.
economy.
   Friday, on Wall Street, sellers took the offensive for most of
the day amid speculation that the economy _ already in a recession
by some accounts _ would suffer further from expensive oil
resulting from Iraq's seizure of Kuwait and its threat to other key
Persian Gulf oil states.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Unleaded gasoline hit a record high on the New
York Mercantile Exchange, as crude oil prices shot up and
speculators kept betting that the Middle East standoff would
curtail supplies.
   September wholesale unleaded gas futures soared Friday to as
high as 96.25 cents before settling at 95.97 cents per gallon, up
8.5 cents from Thursday's record close.
   West Texas Intermediate, the benchmark U.S. crude, finished up
$1.27 at $26.83 per barrel.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Record exports and shrinking oil imports
helped push the nation's merchandise trade deficit to a seven-year
low in June, the government reported. Analysts saw oil as a problem
in coming months because of the Mideast crisis.
   The Commerce Department said Friday that the deficit dropped to
$5.07 billion, a 34.7 percent decline from $7.77 billion in May and
the lowest since a $3.96 billion imbalance was posted in June 1983.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   _
   JIDDAH, Saudi Arabia (AP) _ Saudi Arabia is ready to increase
its oil output by up to 2 million barrels a day to help offset the
world shortfall caused by the Iraqi invasion of Kuwait, the oil
minister indicated.
   Oil Minister Hisham Nazer told a news conference in Jiddah
Saturday that his country would have ``no alternative'' but to
increase oil production unilaterally if OPEC does not convene an
emergency meeting requested by Saudi Arabia.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   _
   ATLANTIC CITY, N.J. (AP) _ Developer Donald Trump's financial
footing became more precarious when the state Casino Control
Commission said it would not rule on his complex financial bailout
until Tuesday.
   Acting Chairwoman Valerie Armstrong said Friday the commission
needed more time to review more than 1,000 pages of documents.
   Trump attorneys had argued that any delay beyond Friday could
jeopardize Trump's $65 million bailout and trigger a chain of
bankruptcies in his debt-riddled Atlantic City casino and Manhattan
real estate empire.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>ATLANTIC CITY, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Casino Control Commission
unanimously approved a restructuring plan for Resorts International
that leaves owner Merv Griffin with just 21.5 percent of the
company and includes a $5 million fund to possibly sue Donald Trump.
   The commission voted 5-0 Friday for the plan approved early
Friday morning by U.S. Bankruptcy Judge Rosemary Gambardella. It
still must be approved by the Bahamian government, where Resorts
also runs a casino.
   The plan, filed under Chapter 11 of the U.S. Bankruptcy Code,
gives bondholders holding $911 million in bonds 78.5 percent of the
company and $434 million in new notes.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>DETROIT (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Chrysler Corp., which is trying to reduce its
salaried work force as a cost-cutting move, is offering nearly all
of its 60,000 or so unionized employees money to leave the company.
   Chrysler spokesman Lee Sechler said Friday that 400 to 450 of
the eligible workers had chosen the buyout so far. Another week is
left for workers to sign up. The last day of work for anyone
choosing to leave will be Aug. 31.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Consumer food prices are going up 5 percent to
7 percent this year, sharply more than had been predicted, the
Agriculture Department said.
   The new forecast Friday compared with the 3 percent to 5 percent
price hike the department has been predicting for 1990 since
December.
   Double-digit price gains in the first half of this year for
fresh fruits, pork, eggs and dairy products, along with
uncertainties about future energy prices, are mostly to blame for
the upward revision, the department said.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Foster Grant Corp., whose ads asking which star
was behind its sunglasses produced sales and advertising
prominence, has sought Chapter 11 bankruptcy court protection from
creditors.
   In papers filed Thursday in U.S. Bankruptcy Court in Tucson,
Ariz., the sunglass maker that became popular in the 1960s and '70s
reported total assets of about $25 million and liabilities of about
$36 million, including nearly $19.3 million in unsecured debt.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   FundAmerica Inc., a buying club with 100,000
members, filed for bankruptcy protection from its creditors and
asked the court to appoint an independent examiner to investigate
various allegations against it.
   The Irvine, Calif.-based firm is facing scrutiny from regulators
in Florida and other states and is the subject of a $150 million
class-action suit in San Francisco.
   Its federal bankruptcy filing Friday in Santa Ana, which had
been expected, listed assets of $17.5 million and liabilities of
$14.5 million.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Stock prices fell broadly Friday in heavy trading, echoing
losses overseas amid continued concern about the Mideast. The Dow
Jones industrial average fell 36.64 to 2,644.80, its lowest close
since March 1.
   The dollar sank to another all-time low against the German mark.
   Bond prices were mixed.
   Pork futures were mixed, precious metals rose, and grains and
soybeans were mixed.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0071 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-19-90 1502EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-Gulf-Japan-Markets Bjt   08-19 0717</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Japan-Markets, Bjt,0742</SECOND>
<HEAD>Gulf Crisis Sends Tokyo Markets Reeling</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By S.L. BACHMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Iraq's invasion of Kuwait sent the already bearish
Tokyo stock market plummeting, and traders said the trend is likely
to continue.
   The dollar-yen exchange rate, meanwhile, settled into a range of
around 147 to 148 yen to the dollar after major fluctuations early
in the crisis.
   Analysts predicted that the strength of the Japanese economy,
and the relative weakness of the U.S. economy, would keep the
exchange rate hovering around the same level until the Middle East
stalemate breaks.
   Tokyo's stock traders were already seven months into a bear
market by Aug. 2, when Iraqi troops overtook Kuwait. The market,
which had been near the 31,000-point level, immediately plunged
nearly 600 points.
   The next two weeks brought new shocks.
   The first was Japan's decision a few days after the invasion to
impose unpredented strict sanctions on Iraq, followed by the United
Nations' decision to impose sanctions.
   The second was Prime Minister Toshiki Kaifu's decision the
following Monday to cancel his long-planned tour of five Middle
Eastern countries, scheduled to begin Aug. 15.
   Also during the second full week of August, the traditional
``O-bon'' holiday, beautiful weather and the distraction of the
national high school baseball tournament, combined to weaken
interest in all markets, traders said.
   On Friday, the 225-issue Nikkei Stock Average closed at
26,786.72 points, down 13 percent from its Aug. 1 close.
   Traders said the market would continue to slide.
   ``The most likely scenario for the stock market right now is to
weaken further,'' said Pelham Smithers, an analyst for Shearson,
Lehman, Hutton Asia, Ltd., citing weakness in the bond market along
with uncertainty about the Iraq-Kuwait situation as influences.
   Low yields on the stock market, he said, ``have made other
instruments, such as holding cash, more attractive.''
   Long-term interest rates on bonds, for instance, started going
up in June, when Japan agreed to spend some $2.72 billion on public
works over the next 10 years, he said. The yield of the benchmark
10-year Japanese government bond closed Friday at 8.050 percent, up
from 7.505 percent on Aug. 1.
   The market has been on a long-term downswing since Dec. 29, when
the latest postwar ``Superbowl'' market peaked at 38,916 points,
said Darrel Whitten, director of research at the Tokyo office of
Prudential Bache Securities.
   Superbowl markets, when markets typically expanded by about 5.5
percent, have been followed by corrections averaging 80 to 90
months, he said. ``The question is how long the adjustment will
last.''
   Another indicator, the five-year moving average, suggests the
market will bottom out at 25,000-21,000 points, he said.
   With higher oil prices killing any chance of bringing interest
rates down, and corporate profits unlikely to go up, ``The blow-off
comes in the market,'' he said.
   Early in the crisis, Japan's near total dependence on imported
oil buoyed the dollar.
   Brent Crude for October delivery closed Friday at about $26.10
to $26.20 a barrel in Tokyo, compared with $19.90 to $21.00 a
barrel in New York on Aug. 1.
   But eventually the markets valued the yen higher because of
Japan's economic strength. Although the dollar normally gains
strength in times of crisis, the structural weaknesses of the U.S.
economy has overwhelmed its traditional strength in times of
crisis, many traders said.
   Japan has been working since the first oil shocks of the early
1970s to broaden its list of suppliers and lessen its dependence on
oil imports through efficiency and use of other energy sources,
notably nuclear, they said.
   ``The yen appears to have settled temporarily into a trading
range against the U.S. dollar and the Deutschemark, and the earlier
pattern of dollar weakness is not expected to re-emerge until the
Middle East situation is clarified,'' said analysts at Salomon
Brothers Asia, Ltd., in a newsletter prepared for the week of Aug.
13.
   The dollar closed at 147.35 yen to the U.S. dollar Friday. On
Aug. 2, the currency jumped 2.25 yen to 147.13 yen. Closing figures
bounced between 149 yen and 150 yen but no higher than 150.65 yen
in subsequent days.
   With energy prices already high, oil and utility company profits
would cushion the Japanese economy, while the United States economy
is struggling under numerous burdens, added analyst Robert A
Feldman.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0072 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-PX-08-19-90 2000EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>d f PM-VideoFlackery     08-19 0919</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Video Flackery,0952</SECOND>
<HEAD>Press Releases Enter the Age of Video</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto HF1 of Aug. 20.</HEAD>
<HEAD>Also in Monday AMs report.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DENISE LAVOIE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BLOOMFIELD, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   When Spalding Sports Worldwide wanted
to entice television journalists into doing stories on its new
Top-Flite golf ball, the company knew sending out a few typed pages
and a photograph or two wouldn't be enough.
   So Spalding put out a video, joining the growing number of
companies that are turning to ``video news releases'' to promote
their products.
   Known as ``VNRs,'' the 90-second spots have become an electronic
alternative to standard news releases.
   Spalding's VNR cost just $10,000 to make _ compared to the
hundreds of thousands of dollars a commercial can cost _ but ended
up reaching more than six million viewers, according to Steven
Shaw, president of Visual Concepts Media Inc., a Bloomfield company
that produced and distributed the video.
   First, the video was distributed to local television stations
across the country. Then Spalding's new golf ball made the national
airwaves when, after seeing the video, the ``Today'' show did its
own story on game-improvement equipment.
   ``It was an opportunity for us to be associated with a
tremendous growth in the game of golf without being blatantly
commercial,'' said J. Greg Sherry, a spokesman for Spalding, based
in Chicopee, Mass.
   Publicity-hungry corporations have been sending public relations
film to local stations since the advent of television in the 1940s.
   But VNRs only began to enjoy a boom in popularity in the
mid-1980s, when the proliferation of satellite dishes made them
easier to distribute and local news shows needed more material to
fill longer, one-hour formats.
   Most VNRs closely resemble news stories, complete with
interviews and narration. The product being hawked is presented,
but only as part of what appears as a larger news story.
   The Spalding video is presented as a story about how high-tech
sporting equipment can improve the performance of weekend athletes.
   Professional and weekend golfers were interviewed about what
they look for in a golf ball. Greg Norman, without ever endorsing
or even mentioning the Top-Flite ball, tells the viewer that the
average golfer should simply find a ball he likes and stick with
it. But after his interview, the camera zooms in on one of
Spalding's ``Top-Flite Plus II'' balls.
   For a cost of between $10,000 and $20,000, a VNR _ which
typically runs about 90 seconds _ can be beamed to newsrooms around
the country via satellite.
   The use of VNRs remains a controversial topic in the television
news industry.
   Many news directors question the objectivity of a
corporate-produced video and claim to have rigid policies against
using them.
   ``They're great for the company, but they're terrible for
viewers because they're biased,'' said Paul Frega, news director of
WVIT-TV in New Britain.
   Deborah Johnson, assistant news director at WFSB-TV in Hartford,
added: ``They're not useful to us because they are no different
than a press release.''
   Johnson and Frega acknowledge that their stations sometimes use
a small film clip from a VNR for background footage that might be
difficult to get on their own. Both news directors cringe, however,
when asked if they ever use unedited versions.
   ``We never, ever use those,'' said Frega. ``I think it's kind of
sad that some stations do.''
   Such hostility comes as something of a surprise to those who
produce VNRs, who say many stations use them, despite their
disclaimers.
   ``It's a holier-than-thou attitude,'' said Douglas Brush,
executive vice president of D-J Brush Associates, a New York
consulting firm specializing in corporate communications.
   ``News directors do not like to admit they use prepared
material,'' Brush said. ``But the fact of the matter is there are
cutbacks in the television news industry, and despite what they
tell you, many of them welcome well-prepared video releases.''
   Medialink, a New York-based public relations firm that is the
nation's largest distributor of video news releases, commissioned a
poll in February to find out whether news stations were using VNRs.
   James Gold, Medialink's managing editor, said 78 percent of news
directors and producers who responded to the Nielsen poll said they
used edited material from a video news release an average of once a
week.
   Gold, whose company distributed 1,200 VNRs last year, said most
of the videos provided television stations with story ideas they
later developed themselves. Usually, only a small portion of the
video news release ends up being used in the news broadcasts.
   ``If used responsibly, there's nothing wrong with them,'' said
Gold.
   At Visual Concepts, Shaw and partner Ric Serrenho, both former
staffers for WTNH-TV in New Haven, say they are amazed when local
stations claim they never use VNRs.
   ``I really take offense to that,'' says Serrenho. ``We're not
forcing anybody to take this product. It has to be a legitimate
news story.''
   Industry analysts, however, say most television news stations
still view VNRs with skepticism because of their inherent public
relations slant.
   ``These people are not stupid. They know a commercial when they
see it,'' said James Kaminsky, editor of Corporate Video Decisions,
a magazine that covers the corporate video industry.
   Despite the war of words between news directors and video
producers, VNRs are becoming a lucrative cottage industry within
the corporate video industry.
   Today, VNRs account for anywhere from $60 to $100 million of the
corporate video industry, according to industry estimates.
Medialink's survey showed that last year, approximately 3,500 VNRs
were produced across the country.
   ``It's big and getting bigger,'' Kaminsky said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900819-0073 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-PX-08-19-90 2000EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>d f PM-TrumpFinances     08-19 0674</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Trump Finances,0692</SECOND>
<HEAD>Trump And Gambling Agency Differ Over His Casino Future</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Monday AMs report.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By HENRY STERN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ATLANTIC CITY, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Donald Trump blames troubles at his
three casinos on a faltering economy and believes his latest deal
will give them time to rebound. State officials disagree.
   The Division of Gaming Enforcement says mismanagement and the
opening in April of Trump's Taj Mahal Casino Resort are to blame.
And a report by the gaming division for the state Casino Control
Commission holds out little hope for a long-term turnaround apart
from Trump's request for approval of a plan to put up his casinos
as collateral for an emergency $65 million loan.
   Trump pledged the casinos as security for the loan as part of a
restructuring of the casinos' $1 billion debt. The banks agreed in
June to lend him the $65 million so he could make an overdue $43
million bond payment on Trump Castle Casino Resort By The Bay. A
Trump attorney says the loan is in escrow awaiting the commission's
decision.
   The gaming division reluctantly recommended the commission
approve the plan Tuesday, but it attached 13 reporting conditions.
   And it said the deal, which is part of Trump's scramble to
handle the $3.2 billion in debt he has amassed to build his
fortunes here and in New York, is no guarantee of success.
   ``These agreements, even if approved and strictly adhered to by
the parties, do not and will not bring to a conclusion the
financial difficulties facing the Trump Organization,'' said the
report, released on the first day of commission hearings Thursday.
   The report said mistakes in loading the casinos and Trump's real
estate and airline holdings with so much debt might force the
developer to shed assets and concentrate on rallying a few core
assets.
   ``Excessive debt has acted as a powerful agent for change and,
ironically, has acted as a brake on management mistakes,'' the
report said.
   According to second-quarter casino reports released Wednesday by
the Casino Association, the Taj Mahal lost $14 million in its first
three months ended June 30, Trump Castle lost $8 million last
quarter and Trump Plaza Hotel and Casino recorded an $863,000
profit.
   The division blames the new Taj Mahal, in part, for accelerating
Trump Castle's decline and weakening the previously solid Trump
Plaza. The Taj Mahal has hovered around its break-even point of
$1.3 million a day during the busy summer months, leaving Trump's
remaining casinos and the city's other gaming halls to split the
remaining business.
   Trump conceded Friday that perhaps the Taj Mahal had
``cannibalized'' some of the business directed at his other two
casinos. But he repeated his claim that none of his gaming halls is
for sale, saying the Taj Mahal merely had the misfortune to open in
a stagnant gaming market and a recession striking especially hard
in the Northeast.
   ``Had the Taj Mahal opened in a good economy, the other casinos
would not have been hurt,'' Trump said. ``Atlantic City business is
down. When you have something opening in a bad economy ... you're
looking at a whole different ball game.''
   Ed Tracy, president of Trump's casinos and non-casino hotel
here, said the Taj Mahal has taken some business away from the
city's other gaming halls but that he expected the situation to
turn around within six months.
   The gaming division is unwilling to wait. If the commission
approves the plan Tuesday, the panel wants Trump's chief financial
officer to return within three weeks with details of how a $47
million bond payment due Nov. 15 on the Taj Mahal will be made.
   ``The Taj Mahal will be faced with a crisis similar to that
recently experienced by Trump Castle unless the Trump Organization
directly and expeditiously addresses this matter with the
bondholders,'' the report said.
   Trump acknowledges he has problems but said the latest deal will
allow him to recover.
   ``The whole Northeast has been affected,'' Trump said.
``Unfortunately, I'm the only one everybody writes about.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
</Collection>
