<Collection>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0001 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 2318EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-TropicalWeather 2ndLd-Writethru a0757 08-26 0373</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Tropical Weather, 2nd Ld - Writethru, a0757,0379</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hurricane Gustav, Tropical Storm Hortense Grow on Ocean Crossing</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: UPDATES thoughout with new storm positions, wind speeds</NOTE>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Newly born Hurricane Gustav spun toward the
northeastern Caribbean with 80 mph winds Sunday, tailed by Tropical
Storm Hortense in the mid-Atlantic about a thousand miles to the
east.
   The governments of Guadeloupe, Antigua, Barbuda, Montserrat,
Nevis and St. Kitts issued hurricane warnings Sunday, according to
the National Hurricane Center in suburban Coral Gables.
   A hurricane watch remained in effect for Dominica, Martinique,
St. Martin, Anguilla and surrounding islands, said Bob Sheets,
director of the center.
   At 10:30 p.m. EDT, Gustav, which reached hurricane strength
earlier in the day, was centered near 15.7 degrees north latitude,
57.2 degrees west longitude, or about 280 miles east-southeast of
Guadeloupe. It was moving northwest near 9 mph and was expected to
maintain that course and speed through noon Monday.
   Maximum sustained winds were near 80 mph and some increase in
strength was likely during the forecast period, the center said.
   Meanwhile, Hortense, the eighth named storm of the Atlantic
season, had gathered top sustained winds of 45 mph and was growing
stronger, its course turning to the north.
   At 10:30 p.m. EDT, Hortense was centered near 17.6 degrees north
latitude, 40.5 degrees west longitude, or about 990 miles west of
the westernmost Cape Verde Islands. It was moving north near 5 mph
on a course expected to hold through Monday morning.
   Forecaster Bob Case said the storms were far enough apart not to
affect each other.
   ``We're not seeing interaction between the storms,'' he said.
   Both storms were born as tropical depressions off the Cape Verde
islands on the western tip of Africa. Such storms, typical for this
the busiest time of the Atlantic season, have been among history's
worst, forecasters note.
   Case said a tropical wave, potential forerunner to a depression,
was shaping up over western Africa but wasn't of much concern at
the moment because of Gustav and Hortense.
   ``They're keeping us quite busy,'' he said. ``The two of them
are plenty.''
   Tropical depressions become named storms when their top
sustained winds top 39 mph. They become hurricanes if those winds
hit 74 mph.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0002 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 2350EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-OpryZealot     08-26 0293</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Opry Zealot,0303</SECOND>
<HEAD>He's Attended Country Music Show 503 Times</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOE EDWARDS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NASHVILLE, Tenn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Neither injury nor work can keep Johnny
Shealy from listening to the Grand Ole Opry.
   He's been to the Saturday night country music show 503 times.
When he can't be there in person, he listens on the radio, as he
has done for 25 years.
   He keeps a log of who has performed every Saturday night and
what they sang.
   He even moved to Nashville from Greenwood, S.C., in 1969 to be
closer to the fabled program. He lived in a downtown hotel two
blocks away to be near the singing stars, and when the Opry moved
to the suburbs in 1974, he moved nearby.
   He explains his enthusiasm like a simple country song might: ``I
really love it.''
   In a box in his bedroom are 25 years of logs in notebooks with
red covers.
   If he can't listen on radio, such as in February when he was
hospitalized after a traffic accident, he appeals to friends who
tape the broadcast.
   When he briefly took a job cleaning floors at a supermarket last
winter, his 11 p.m. reporting time didn't get in the way. ``I just
took a radio with me and listened at work, but I had to watch out
for the boss,'' he said.
   ``I'll never quit listening. Only death and taxes will stop me.''
   Shealy, 48, who has never married and has worked a series of
blue-collar jobs, also has his 503 ticket stubs.
   The cost of Opry tickets, now $13 and $11, concerns him. His
pocketbook can't match his enthusiasm these days. But there's
always the broadcast.
   ``They'll have to outlaw radio before I quit listening,'' he
said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0003 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 2350EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-BowieKnife     08-26 0174</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Bowie Knife,0178</SECOND>
<HEAD>Group Scraps Plans to Buy `Bowie' Knife</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HOUSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A $3.5 million offer for a knife believed to have
belonged to James Bowie during the battle of the Alamo was
withdrawn because the dagger's owner refused to have it tested for
authenticity.
   Spirit of the Alamo, a non-profit fund-raising group, dropped
the offer, president John Stokes said Saturday.
   Bartley Dean Moore of Riverside, Calif., said family lore has it
that a young Mexican soldier found the knife after the mission fell
in 1836. In 1890, the soldier gave the knife to Moore's grandfather
in Texas to settle a $5 debt, the story goes.
   Museum curators and other experts discounted the claim.
   The fund-raising group, formed last year, had agreed to pay $3.5
million if the knife proved genuine, but wanted tests to determine
its age and metal content.
   All 187 American defenders, including Bowie and Davy Crockett,
were killed in the 13-day siege of the Alamo. Legend credits Bowie
with inventing what is now known as the bowie knife.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0004 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 2357EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Peru-Violence     08-26 0215</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Peru-Violence,0221</SECOND>
<HEAD>Leftist Rebels Kill Political Activist and Son</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LIMA, Peru (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Rebels killed a well-known political activist
and his eight-year-old son, stopping the activist and his family
with gunfire as they took a Sunday drive just outside Lima, police
said.
   Arturo Pacheco, a a long-time member of the Aprista Party of
former President Alan Garcia, was killed by a dynamite charge
placed on his chest after the rebels stopped the family car, the
police said.
   They said Pacheco had been driving on the main highway east of
the city with his four children, his wife and a male employee early
Sunday afternoon _ probably bound for his hog farm _ when they were
attacked by seven people armed with automatic weapons and pistols.
   Pacheco and his eight-year-old son were wounded by the gunfire,
police said, and the attackers made his wife, children and the
employee step out of the vehicle and placed the dynamite charge on
his chest.
   They said the eight-year-old son who died had been struck by
three bullets.
   Authorities said the style and cruelty of the attack indicate it
was carried out by Maoist-inspired Shining Path rebels.
   More than 18,000 people have died in political violence since
the Shining Path began its war against the government 10 years ago.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0005 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 0004EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Gulf-Americans 2ndLd-Writethru a0566 08-26 0678</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Americans, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0566,570</SECOND>
<HEAD>Iraqi Ambassador Says Dependents of Diplomats in Baghdad Free To
Go</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: Inserts grafs 11-12, ``Meanwhile, The Washington Post xxx to
include report of two Americans detained in Kuwait City</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By BARRY SCHWEID</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Diplomatic Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Iraq's ambassador said Saturday the wives and
children of American diplomats who fled Kuwait to Baghdad are free
to go but that the diplomats will be treated ``just like anybody
else.''
   Summoned to the State Department for another U.S. protest,
Ambassador Mohamed Sadiq al-Mashat said ``we are on the brink of a
catastrophe. ... American lives are being risked for no reason
whatsoever.''
   And yet, the Iraqi diplomat did not register any direct threat
to the diplomats or any of the more than 3,000 U.S. citizens
trapped in Iraq and Kuwait.
   Specifically, al-Mashat said ``we are not going to use force''
against the U.S. Embassy in Kuwait where Ambassador Nathaniel
Howell and a staff of about 10 are defying an order by Iraqi
President Saddam Hussein to shut down.
   ``We haven't touched any embassy there,'' the Iraqi said at an
impromptu news conference after a brief session with David Mack, a
deputy assistant secretary of state who had called him in.
   Iraqi troops appeared outside the U.S. Embassy in Kuwait City on
Thursday night and, according to U.S. officials, have blocked entry
and exit ever since.
   U.S. officials said the embassy's electricity was cut off
Saturday at about 4:15 a.m. EDT and water was shut off sometime
later. Telephone service is sporadic, though embassy contact with
Americans in Kuwait continues.
   ``A small number of Iraqi soldiers remain outside the embassy,''
the State Department said. ``No attempt has been made by them to
enter the embassy compound.''
   Al-Mashat said he had no ``official word'' on whether that was
true.
   Meanwhile, U.S. officials said the embassy was operating on
generator power.
   Meanwhile, The Washington Post reported in Sunday's editions in
a dispatch from Kuwait that two Americans were detained by Iraqi
troops. The paper quoted a spokeswoman at the embassy in Kuwait
City as saying she did not know where the two Americans were
arrested, but that they were detained at a local hotel and are
unharmed.
   In Washington, a State Department spokesman, who asked to remain
anonymous, said of the report, ``We are not prepared to confirm
this now.''
   Saddam had ordered the embassy to close on Friday and to move
its functions to the U.S. Embassy in Baghdad. But Howell and his
staff remained to keep in touch with the Americans trapped in
Kuwait since Iraq invaded the Persian Gulf country Aug. 2.
   Some 100 U.S. diplomats and dependents fled Kuwait for Iraq late
Thursday, arriving in a 33-car caravan after more than 19 hours on
the road.
   According to the Bush administration, their safe passage out of
the area was assured by Iraq.
   But while they were en route, Iraq imposed new regulations
prohibiting the departure of diplomats whose embassies had not shut
down as ordered by Saddam.
   This left the diplomats and their families stranded in the Iraqi
capital.
   Late Friday, the Iraqi news agency said the dependents would be
permitted to leave. But U.S. officials said they had not been
notified.
   ``The dependents are going to be released,'' al-Mashat said
Saturday.
   In fact, he said, ``some of them will be leaving soon.''
   But asked why the diplomats could not join the 60 or so
dependents, about 30 of them children, the diplomat said: ``Because
they don't have diplomatic status. They are considered ordinary
citizens, just like anyone else.''
   He then admonished the four reporters questioning him: ``You
people should be concerned with the major problem: We are on the
brink of catastrophe, unnecessary. Without any reason American
lives are being risked. For no reason whatsoever.''
   A U.S. official, speaking only on condition of anonymity, said
Mack's conversation with al-Mashat focused on the welfare of
Americans and other foreign nationals who are in Iraq and Kuwait,
``including their very basic freedom to leave those countries if
they desire to do so.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0006 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 0016EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BRF--TrainCollision     08-26 0205</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Train Collision,0212</SECOND>
<HEAD>Four Children Killed When Train Hits Car</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DELANO, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Four brothers ranging in age from 1 to 7
were killed Saturday when a freight train going nearly 70 mph
smashed into their stalled car as their frantic mother tried to
flag the engineer and stop the locomotive.
   The mother, Leoninia Lendes, 32, of Delano ``got out of the way
right at the last moment,'' said police Sgt. Don Callahan.
   Trapped inside the wreckage were her children, aged 1, 4, 6 and
7.
   The engineer told police he saw a woman waving and began to
brake one block before impact. The Southern Pacific train,
traveling nearly 70 mph and pulling about 100 cars had no chance to
stop in time, Callahan said.
   The train carried the auto wreckage for eight blocks before
stopping. The railroad crossing arm had dropped behind the 1990
Nissan Sentra, trapping it on the tracks.
   ``We don't know why her car stalled. She could possibly have
panicked,'' Callahan said, adding that the children's mother was
treated for emotional distress, he said.
   Delano, is a small farming community about 30 miles north of
Bakersfield. Trains travel through the center of town about once an
hour, Callahan said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0007 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 0055EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-GulfRdp 4thLd-Writethru a0626 08-26 1117</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf Rdp, 4th Ld-Writethru, a0626,1148</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.N. Approves Force for Iraqi Embargo; Baghdad Harasses Embassies</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos NY11,12,19,20,25,27,29,45; AMM2,7; DOD1,2</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: INSERTS one graf after 16th pvs, `Italy's Foreign...' to
UPDATE with troops retreating from Canadian Embassy; Pickup 17th,
`Iraqi soldiers...'; INSERTS 3 grafs after 27th, `As the...' to ADD
reports two more Americans rounded up in Kuwait; Pickup 28th,
`Waldheim said...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By THOMAS WAGNER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   The United Nations on Saturday gave the world's navies the right
to use force to stop vessels trading with Iraq, and Baghdad cut
supplies to some embassies in Kuwait but did not carry out its
threat to close them by force.
   Iraq's U.S. ambassador, meanwhile, said the families of American
diplomats who fled Kuwait to Baghdad can leave but that the
diplomats will be detained. He also said Iraq will not use force
against the U.S. Embassy in Kuwait.
   In another U.N. initiative, the world body's secretary-general,
Javier Perez de Cuellar, announced on Saturday he has invited the
Iraqi foreign minister to open urgent talks aimed at resolving the
Persian Gulf crisis.
   Perez de Cuellar said the talks could begin this week in New
York or Geneva. But he did not say whether Iraq had accepted the
offer.
   Even as the Security Council took steps to enforce its
sanctions, evidence mounted Saturday that the embargo is already
squeezing Iraq's citizens.
   Reports filtering out of Baghdad described panic buying;
shortages of cooking oil, flour and fruit; the start of a national
rationing program; and house-to-house sweeps by militiamen hunting
food hoarders.
   The official Iraqi News Agency reported that hundreds of Iraqi
children gathered outside the U.S. Embassy in Baghdad on Saturday
carrying signs complaining that the international trade sanctions
are depriving them of milk. The protest was likely to have had
official Iraqi sanction.
   The United States and its allies praised the U.N. Security
Council for voting early Saturday to allow military action to
uphold the embargo aimed at punishing Iraq for invading Kuwait on
Aug. 2.
   ``Iraq has evaded resolutions of the Security Council and
thumbed its nose at all humanity,'' U.S. Ambassador Thomas R.
Pickering said following the unanimous vote at the United Nations.
``This has prompted the council to take one of the most important
decisions in its history.''
   The White House said the vote ``further strengthens the world
resolve to force Iraq out of Kuwait.'' Although U.S. warships have
been shadowing Iraqi vessels in the Persian Gulf, they have not
forced them to stop.
   President Bush's national security adviser, Brent Scowcroft,
said the United Nations has given the Bush administration a free
hand to enforce the economic embargo on Iraq. But he sidestepped a
question of how much force America was willing to use.
   Scowcroft said on Cable News Network that the U.N. action
``means no commerce should go in and out (of Iraq) by sea, and that
means that vessels will be stopped and inspected,'' effective
immediately.
   Iraq's U.N. ambassador, Abdul Amir Al-Anbari, immediately
denounced the Security Council vote and said it could lead to war.
   ``This use of force by the United States or any of its allies or
puppets will lead inevitably to a number of explosions which will
burn all in their path,'' he said at the United Nations in New York.
   Iraq, meanwhile, carried out its threat to cut supplies to
embassies in Kuwait, shutting off power at the Italian, British,
Austrian and French missions; power and water at the U.S., East
German and Norwegian embassies; and power, water and telephone
service at the Japanese mission.
   Italy's Foreign Ministry said that Iraqi soldiers were knocking
down a wall at the French mission in Kuwait in an apparent effort
to cut off the water supply there, but France could not immediately
confirm the report.
   But Iraqi troops stationed outside the Canadian Embassy
retreated Saturday, Canadian Press news agency said.
   Iraqi soldiers, some armed with machine guns and mortars,
remained outside many embassies in Kuwait City but made no effort
to remove diplomats by force, according to reports reaching foreign
ministries in several countries.
   U.S. officials said an electric generator was being used at the
U.S. Embassy and that other supplies remained adequate for
Ambassador Nathaniel Howell and his staff of about 10 diplomats.
   Thousands of American troops and dozens of U.S. warships are
within striking distance of Iraq and Kuwait, but President Bush has
given no indication how he will respond if Iraq attempts to overrun
the U.S. embassy.
   Earlier this week, the United States reduced its staff at the
embassy in Kuwait by sending about 100 U.S. diplomats and
dependents to Baghdad, where they have been stranded. Iraq's U.S.
ambassador said in Washington Saturday that the wives and children
of the American diplomats can leave.
   ``The dependents are going to be released,'' said Mohamed
al-Mashat, who had been summoned to the State Department for
another U.S. protest.
   ``Some of them will be leaving soon.'' However, he said the
diplomats will be treated ``just like anybody else,'' meaning they
will be detained. He said that although Iraq and the United States
``are on the brink of a catastrophe,'' Baghdad is ``not going to
use force'' against the U.S. Embassy in Kuwait.
   Although international law says embassies must remain inviolable
even in times of war, Baghdad ordered all embassies in Kuwait to
close and threatened to detain as hostages any diplomatic personnel
who defy the decree.
   The many other countries that have refused to close their
embassies include Canada, Sweden, Romania, Hungary, Spain, Greece,
Bangladesh, Switzerland, Poland, Czechoslovakia and Yugoslavia.
   Moscow has evacuated its embassy but says it remains technically
open.
   Many governments believe that closing the missions could be
interpreted as the first step toward recognition of Iraq's claim of
sovereignty over Kuwait.
   As the embassy standoff continued, 96 Austrian hostages were
freed in Iraq, an Austrian official said. Austrian President Kurt
Waldheim secured their release in a meeting with Iraqi President
Saddam Hussein in Baghdad Saturday.
   Meanwhile, Japan announced that some of its nationals had been
rounded up.
   And two more Americans were detained by Iraqi troops, the
Washington Post quoted a U.S. Embassy spokeswoman in Kuwait city as
reporting Saturday. It was not clear when they were detained or
where. The spokeswoman said the two were being held at a hotel and
were unharmed.
   A State Department spokesman said of the report: ``We are not
prepared to confirm this now.''
   Waldheim said later in Amman, Jordan, that he had raised the
issue of U.S. and other Western citizens stranded in Iraq and
Kuwait with Saddam, but had received no commitments from the Iraqi
leader.
   About 21,000 Westerners, including 3,000 Americans, are being
held hostage in Iraq and Kuwait.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pickup a0627</HEAD>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0008 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 0126EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BRF--RunawayTrain     08-26 0120</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Runaway Train,0123</SECOND>
<HEAD>Train Travels 15 Miles Without Crew, Warning Lights</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SAN BENITO, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A runaway freight train traveled more
than 15 miles without a crew Saturday and reached speeds of 35 mph
before an engineer hopped aboard and brought the train to a halt,
police said.
   Railroad crossing lights, normally activated by train engineers,
were not working so police from Brownsville and Cameron County
Sheriff's deputies blocked roads along the route with patrol cars.
   No injuries were reported. Authorities were unsure how the Union
Pacific freight train with about 20 cars got loose on the tracks in
Brownsville. Railroad officials refused to comment.
   San Benito is in southern Texas about 250 miles south of San
Antonio.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0009 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 0207EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Taiwan-Yacht 3rdLd-Writethru a0655 08-26 0437</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Taiwan-Yacht, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0655,0448</SECOND>
<HEAD>Yacht Overturns in Central Taiwan, Killing 16</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Leads thruout to ADD British Foreign Office comment, that
unclear how many crew aboard; No pickup.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By SHIRLEY LAI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Assoicated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TAIPEI, Taiwan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A yacht carrying oil company employees on
a moon-gazing excursion overturned on a lake in central Taiwan,
killing 16 people and leaving at least 36 missing and feared dead,
police reported Sunday.
   In London, a spokesman for Shell Oil Co., whose subsidiary Shell
Taiwan Ltd. chartered the yacht, said about 80 employees were
aboard. A list provided by the travel agent for the excursion
showed 91 joined the trip, police said.
   Among the missing were three Britons.
   Police in Nantou, 160 miles southwest of Taipei, said they
arrested yacht owner Hsu Ching-hsin for alleged unintentional
manslaughter in the accident, which occurred Saturday evening.
   They said the boat lacked a commercial licence to run on the
lake and was overcrowded beyond its 60-person capacity. The boat
also violated a ban on yachting after 6:00 p.m.
   The vessel was chartered for a weekend cruise for Shell Taiwan
employees on Sun Moon Lake, a popular resort in Nantou, according
to John Crossman, company general manager.
   Crossman, from Britain, said there were 82 employees and their
families, including 30 children, on board the vessel.
   Alan Jacobs, spokesman for Shell Oil in London said: ``The best
information I have is that there were about 80 of our Shell
employees and their relatives on a pleasure craft.''
   Crossman, who was on the vessel's upper deck, said the boat
suddenly overturned as it was turning left about 165 feet from
shore and he was tossed overboard. There was no immediate
explanation for what caused the boat to tip.
   Crossman said he was rescued by one of several boats that rushed
to the scene.
   Police said about 34 people swam ashore and several were taken
to a hospital, where they were reported in stable condition. It was
not clear how many crew were aboard the vessel.
   The identities of the foreigners aboard were not immediately
available, but officials said they included nine Britons, one
Australian and 10 Malaysians.
   Police said those missing included three Britons, identified as
Sally Aylwin, 56, Julia Crossman, 40, and Bruce Robson, 48. Their
hometowns were not available. It was not immediately clear whether
Julia Crossman was related to the Shell Taiwan general manager.
   The British Foreign Office was unable to confirm that Britons
were among the dead or missing.
   The accident occured on the eve of the Chinese Valentine Day
festival when moon-gazing is a traditional part of the celebrations.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0010 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 0339EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-TVStudioEvacuated 1stLd-Writethru a0653 08-26 0319</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-TVStudio Evacuated, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0653,0326</SECOND>
<HEAD>TV Studio Goes Off the Air As Police Search for Pizza Robber</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: INSERTS 2 grafs after 7th graf pvs, `WLS general...' to
UPDATE with search halted, nobody found. Picks up final graf pvs,
`The television...</NOTE>
<DATELINE>CHICAGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A television station went off the air Saturday
night when police evacuated studios to conduct their third search
of the day for a possible pizza restaurant robber.
   After 25 minutes of dead air, Chicago station WLS-TV resumed
broadcasting at a jury-rigged studio in the Sears Tower. It issued
a special newscast to let viewers know what had happened.
   The station then went off the air again 15 minutes later as
police using scent dogs searched the 13-story studio building.
   A man thought to be armed with a pistol was seen entering the
building Saturday morning not long after a nearby pizza restaurant
was robbed, police said.
   Two daytime searches failed to locate the man, but repeated
sightings by station employees prompted the studio evacuation and
third search at about 8:30 p.m., Lt. Frank Kehoe said.
   ``There's no guarantee that this is the guy involved in the
robbery,'' Kehoe added. ``It could be just a trespasser.''
   WLS general manager Joe Ahearn later said he would not allow
employees to return until police were sure it was safe.
   The station came back on the air at about 1:40 a.m. Sunday
reporting in a 10-minute news update that the search failed to find
the man. After the update, the station went off the air again.
   ``We've gone through every cubbyhole as well as the roof and
around the satellite dishes,'' said Ahearn, who accompanied police
through the building. ``I am absolutely confident that he's not in
the building.''
   The television station is owned and operated by ABC. WLS
broadcasts are seen in eight counties in northern Illinois, two in
northwestern Indiana and two in southern Wisconsin.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0011 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 0513EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i BC-Taiwan-BoatSinking 1stLd-Writethru a0658 08-26 0438</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Taiwan-Boat Sinking, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0658,0448</SECOND>
<HEAD>Overloaded Tourist Boat Overturns, Killing at Least 19</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: RETRANSMITTING to CORRECT overline</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By SHIRLEY LAI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NANTOU, Taiwan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An overloaded tourist boat carrying oil
company employees on a moon-gazing cruise overturned on a lake in
central Taiwan, killing 19 people and leaving at least 33 missing,
police said Sunday.
   In London, a spokesman for Shell Oil Co., whose subsidiary Shell
Taiwan Ltd. chartered the boat, said about 80 employees were
aboard. A list provided by the travel agent for the excursion
showed 91 joined the trip, police said.
   A Shell Taiwan official said four Britons were among those
killed in the accident on Sun Moon Lake late Saturday, eve of the
Chinese Valentine day festival. Moon-gazing is a traditional part
of the celebrations.
   Police said they arrested yacht owner Hsu Ching-hsin for alleged
unintentional manslaughter in the accident. The boat lacked a
license to operate on the lake and was packed beyond its 60-person
capacity, they said.
   The vessel had been chartered for a weekend cruise for employees
on the lake in Nantou, 160 miles southwest of Taipei, according to
Johnathan Crossman, general manager of Shell Taiwan.
   About 200 rescuers, including divers, searched the lake
throughout Saturday night and Sunday, Police said.
   Crossman, 44, from Britain, said there were 82 employees and
their families, including 30 children, aboard the vessel.
   Alan Jacobs, spokesman for Shell Oil Co. in London said: ``The
best information I have is that there were about 80 of our Shell
employees and their relatives on a pleasure craft.''
   Crossman, who was on the vessel's upper deck, said the boat
suddenly capsized as it turned to the left about 50 yards from
shore and he was tossed overboard.
   Newspapers quoted survivors as saying strong winds overturned
the boat.
   Crossman and his 7-year-old daughter, Nicola, were rescued by
boats that rushed to the scene, but his wife, Julia, 40, and a son,
Robert, 6, were missing, Shell official Tseng Tung-shin said.
   Tseng said Sally Aylwin, 46, wife of Shell executive Charles
Aylwin was killed and another Shell executive from Britain, Bruce
Robson, 48, was missing. Aylwin and his two teen-age children were
rescued.
   Crossman _ who was transferred to Taiwan last November _ and
Aylwin were believed from London, but Robson's hometown was not
immediately known, Tseng said.
   Police said about 34 people swam ashore and several were taken
to a hospital, where they were reported in stable condition. It was
not immediately clear how many crew members were aboard the vessel.
   Officials said foreigners aboard included nine Britons, one
Australian and 10 Malaysians.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0012 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 0618EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i BC-Yugoslavia-MineBlast     08-26 0135</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Yugoslavia-Mine Blast,0141</SECOND>
<HEAD>178 Miners Trapped, 8 Bodies Recovered</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BELGRADE, Yugoslavia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An underground explosion killed at
least eight coal miners early Sunday and trapped 178, the Tanjug
news agency reported.
   The blast occurred at the Dobrnja-Jug pit of the Kreka mine,
located 90 miles west of Belgrade.
   Eight bodies were recovered, and two miners were pulled out
alive, Tanjug reported.
   It said 188 miners were in the shaft at the time of the
explosion.
   The blast likely was caused by coal dust, methane gas, or a
combination of the two, Tanjug said. Coal dust is explosive under
certain conditions.
   There was no immediate information on how many of the trapped
miners might have been killed by the blast, or how deep they were
in the shaft.
   No further details were available immediately.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0013 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 0749EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i BC-Gulf-Americans 2ndLd-Writethru a0662 08-26 0453</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Gulf-Americans, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0662,0463</SECOND>
<HEAD>55 U.S. Dependents From U.S. Embassy in Kuwait Leave Baghdad</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Leads withy 5 grafs to UPDATE with embassy saying dependents
have left Baghdad en route to Turkey. Pickup 6th, `Earlier this...'</NOTE>
<DATELINE>ANKARA, Turkey (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   About 55 dependents of American diplomats
who were stranded for several days in Baghdad after fleeing Kuwait
left the Iraqi capital on Sunday for Turkey, the U.S. Embassy here
said.
   Embassy spokeswoman Carole Lee Heileman said the Americans left
Baghdad early Sunday morning in a 13-car convoy for the
Turkey-Iraqi border.
   Ms. Heileman said the group was expected to arrive at Turkey's
Habur border post sometime in the afternoon or evening.
   From there they will be taken by bus to the southern Turkish
city of Diyarbakir and will be flown out of Turkey sometime Monday,
she said.
   She said the 55 were all dependents of U.S. personnel who had
been stationed in the U.S. Embassy in Kuwait. ``An additional 54 or
55 personnel, mostly men, who had been stationed in Kuwait are
still in Baghdad and we have not secured their release,'' Ms.
Heileman said.
   Earlier this week, Iraq gave a Friday deadline for nations to
close their embassies in Kuwait, claiming its oil-rich neighbor as
part of Iraqi territory. Iraq annexed Kuwait six days after its
Aug. 2 invasion of the emirate.
   But the United States, most European nations and many other
countries have refused to close their embassies in Kuwait city,
instead reducing personnel there to a minimum.
   The U.S. Embassy sent about 100 diplomats and their dependents
to Baghdad, where they were stranded when Iraqi President Saddam
Hussein reversed an earlier promise and refused to let them leave.
   But on Saturday, Iraq's U.S. ambassador said in Washington that
the wives and children of the American diplomats would be allowed
to leave.
   ``The dependents are going to be released,'' said Mohamed
al-Mashat, who had been summoned to the State Department for
another U.S. protest.
   ``Some of them will be leaving soon.'' However, he said the
diplomats will be treated ``just like anybody else,'' meaning they
will be detained. He said that although Iraq and the United States
``are on the brink of a catastrophe,'' Baghdad is ``not going to
use force'' against the U.S. Embassy in Kuwait.
   Iraqi troops have surrounded several embassies in Kuwait City,
cutting off water and electricity to many. Iraq had initially said
it would not allow any of the party of 100 leave baghdad until the
U.S. Embassy in Kuwait was closed.
   In all, about 21,000 foreigners have been caught in Iraq and
Kuwait, including 3,000 Americans. Some were distributed among
Iraqi strategic sites for use as human shields to deter any U.S.
attack.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0014 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 0802EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i BC-Gulf-Iran 1stLd-Writethru   08-26 0395</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Gulf-Iran, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0664,0405</SECOND>
<HEAD>Gulf Refugees Can Escape Through Iran, Tehran Radio Says</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: New thruout to UPDATE that Syria promised Saturday to open
its border, more on border crossings in Iran. No pickup.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>NICOSIA, Cyprus (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Iran's foreign minister said Sunday that
foreigners fleeing Iraq and Kuwait can do so through Iran,
according to Tehran radio.
   The report came after Jordan and Turkey complained that they are
overburned by thousands of refugees and said they may have to close
their borders.
   Syria, Iraq's main Arab rival, announced on Saturday that it
will allow foreigners to cross the Syrian border with Iraq.
   Most of the people who have fled Iraq and Kuwait since Baghdad
invaded its oil-rich neighbor on Aug. 2 have entered Jordan,
forcing it to feed and shelter them until they can afford to
continue on to their home countries.
   Iran has condemned the invasion of Kuwait and said it will
enforce an international trade embargo against Iraq.
   But Iran also recently settled disputes over territory and
prisoners of war left unsettled by its long war with Iraq, and that
allowed Iraq to transfer thousands of troops from the Iranian
border and move them to occupied Kuwait.
   The Tehran radio broadcast, monitored in Nicosia, quoted Foreign
Minister Ali Akbar Velayati as saying that for humanitarian reasons
``Iran agrees to foreign evacuees from Iraq and Kuwait transiting
in its territory.''
   Iran shares a 730-mile-long border with Iraq.
   Velayati agreed to let foreigners leave through Iran after
Philippines Foreign Minister Raul Manglapus, who is visiting
Tehran, asked that thousands of his countrymen trapped in Iraq and
Kuwait be allowed to cross into Iran.
   Velayati did not specify if Tehran's offer included only Asians,
or whether thousands of Western hostages in Iraq will be able to
cross the border too.
   Tensions between Iran and Iraq have lessened since Baghdad
settled a border dispute with Tehran last month, pulled out troops
from occupied Iranian territory and initiated an exchange of
prisoners of war.
   However, the border is still heavily fortified on both sides,
and foreigners will likely be allowed to cross only at certain
points.
   About 50,000 Iranians living in Kuwait have returned home
through the Iran-Iraq border, and hundreds more continue to stream
in every day.
   Food, water and a place to sleep are provided for the refugees,
according to the Tehran radio report.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0015 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 0919EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i BC-Gulf-Iraq-UN 1stLd-Writethru   08-26 0398</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Gulf-Iraq-UN, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0663,0409</SECOND>
<HEAD>Iraqi President Invites U.N. Chief to Iraq</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: New thruout to CORRECT that Perez de Cuellar invited the
Iraqi foreign minister, not Saddam, ADD more on news conference. No
pickup.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>NICOSIA, Cyprus (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   U.N. Secretary-General Javier Perez de
Cuellar has invited Iraq to open talks aimed at resolving the
Persian Gulf crisis, and President Saddam Hussein has invited the
U.N. chief to visit Iraq.
   The developments offered the first glimmer of hope that the
crisis caused by Iraq's invasion of Kuwait on Aug. 2 could be
solved by negotiations.
   However, the United States has repeatedly said no peace talks
are possible until Iraq withdraws its troops from Kuwait, which
Baghdad has refused to do.
   On Saturday, Perez de Cuellar invited the Iraqi foreign minister
to open peace talks. Perez de Cuellar, who issued his statement
while traveling in Bogota, Colombia, said the talks could begin
this week in New York or Geneva, but he did not say whether Iraq
had accepted the offer.
   In Baghdad on Saturday, Saddam was asked by reporters traveling
with Austrian President Kurt Waldheim, whether he would agree to
meet with the United Nations secretary-general in Iraq.
   ``Of course,'' Saddam replied, ``the U.N. secretary-general is
always welcome.'' Although Saddam did not mention Perez de Cuellar
by name, it was assumed he was extending the invitation to him.
   Perez de Cuellar called for peace talks hours after the U.N.
Security Council authorized the use of military force to uphold the
trade embargo imposed on Iraq in a bid to force it to withdraw from
Kuwait.
   ``I believe that after the resolutions adopted by the Security
Council, the time has come for the secretary-general to begin
diplomatic efforts to alleviate the present crisis in the gulf in
all aspects, through the process of dialogue,'' Perez de Cuellar
said.
   In Kennebunkport, Maine, White House spokesman Roman Popadiuk
said Saturday he had not heard about Perez de Cuellar's proposal
but that Washington welcomes a ``discussion by all U.N. members in
the context of the complete and immediate and unconditional
withdrawal'' of Iraqi forces from Kuwait.
   The Saddam news conference, which was broadcast by Cable News
Netrowk, came at the end of a one-day visit by Waldheim, who flew
out of Baghdad with 100 Austrian nationals who had been stranded in
the country.
   About 3,000 Americans and 4,500 Britons remain stranded in
Kuwait.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0016 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 1123EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--SikhAttack     08-26 0174</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Sikh Attack,0177</SECOND>
<HEAD>Sikh Gunmen Kill Family of Policeman, Eight Others in Punjab</HEAD>
<DATELINE>AMRITSAR, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Sikh gunmen raided the home of a police
interrogator in Punjab and killed four members of his family,
police said Sunday.
   Elsewhere in the state, eight deaths were blamed on Sikh
militants who are leading a violent campaign for an independent
homeland in the rich farming state, news reports said.
   The killings brought the number of deaths blamed on the
militants in the Punjab this year to 1,795.
   The militants say Sikhs are discriminated against by the
majority Hindus. Sikhs make up two percent of India's 880 million
people, but they are in slight majority in Punjab. Hindus are 82
percent nationwide.
   About half a dozen militants burst into the home of Constable
Dalbir Singh near Tarn Taran late Saturday, said area police chief
Narinder Pal Singh. The gunmen shot and killed the policeman's
50-year-old mother and three daughters.
   The other deaths occurred across the state in separate incidents
on Saturday, United News of India reported.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0017 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 1123EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--SundayNewspaper     08-26 0131</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Sunday Newspaper,0133</SECOND>
<HEAD>Paper Prints Norway's First Major Sunday Edition in 71 Years</HEAD>
<DATELINE>OSLO, Norway (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A newspaper came out with Norway's first
national Sunday edition since 1919, when typographers and other
workers stopped the presses by refusing to work on the Sabbath.
   Dagbladet, one of the country's top three newspapers, kept its
Sunday edition secret until Saturday night, calling it a
``guerrilla attack'' on its rivals, the Oslo newspapers Verdens
Gang and Aftenposten.
   The Oslo tabloid's editorial said changes in labor laws, which
used to severely limit working on Sundays, made it possible to
resume printing seven editions a week after a break of 71 years.
   About 225,000 copies of the 48-page newspaper were distributed
nationwide.
   The state radio network NRK predicted a rush of other Sunday
newspapers.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0018 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 1128EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Gulf-USForces Bjt   08-26 0784</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-US Forces, Bjt,750</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.S. Mideast Force Approaches 60,000 Troops; More Marines Expected</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT BURNS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Roughly 60,000 American soldiers, airmen and
sailors have moved to battle stations in the Persian Gulf since
President Bush ordered U.S. firepower into the area to thwart
Iraq's Saddam Hussein, sources say.
   In addition to the massive troop movement, the Pentagon has
built a virtual armada in the region's seas and rushed in hundreds
of fighter jets and support aircraft.
   The deployment, the largest since the Vietnam War, is far from
complete.
   Within a few weeks, about 45,000 Marines are expected to have
arrived in the area. By then the total U.S. combat force in the
region may number well over 100,000, military sources said last
week.
   The final elements of the 7th Marine Expeditionary Brigade were
arriving in Saudi Arabia over the weekend after a 7,000-mile flight
from their home base at Twentynine Palms, Calif., and the 1st
Marine Expeditionary Brigade was heading for the gulf from its home
base at Kaneohe Bay, Hawaii, one source said.
   A third Marine unit, the 4th Marine Expeditionary Brigade from
Camp Lejeune, N.C., was preparing for deployment but was not
expected to arrive for at least another two weeks.
   Over the past week, the Bush administration added significantly
to not only the U.S. ground forces in Saudi Arabia but also the air
and sea power in the area, including:
   _A squadron of 22 F-117A stealth fighter-bombers. The
radar-evading planes, on their first overseas deployment, are
specially designed to operate at night. They can slip deep behind
enemy lines to lead an offensive strike on vital targets.
   _The aircraft carrier USS Saratoga arrived in the Red Sea by way
of the Suez Canal. It is accompanied by the Aegis missile cruiser
Philippine Sea and the missile cruiser Biddle. It is to be joined
soon by three other members of its battle group, the missile
destroyer Sampson and frigates Elmer Montgomery and Thomas C. Hart.
   The aircraft carrier USS Eisenhower, which had been on patrol in
the Red Sea, headed back into the Mediterranean.
   _The aviation brigade of the 101st Airborne Division, an air
assault unit based at Fort Campbell, Ky., began arriving in the
Saudi desert. It is armed with Apache helicopters, the backbone of
the Army's tank-killing arsenal. The aircraft are equipped with
laser-guided missiles that can hit moving targets at night.
   _The first deployments of U.S. forces from NATO bases in Europe.
Elements of the U.S. Army Europe's 7th Medical Command, based in
West Germany, headed for Saudi Arabia, as did C-130E Hercules
transport airplanes of the 435th Tactical Airlift Wing from West
Germany.
   Also, the Strategic Air Command acknowledged Saturday that B-52
bombers were dispatched overseas two weeks ago from two undisclosed
U.S. air bases.
   Bush last week authorized the Pentagon to call up military
reserves for the first time in 20 years. Defense Secretary Dick
Cheney on Thursday approved plans to activate as many as 46,700
members of the National Guard and armed forces reserves, and the
first call-ups came Friday.
   Cheney said nearly 10,000 reserves would be called to active
duty by the end of August and the total would reach 46,700 by Oct.
1.
   Most of the reserves are to be sent to the Arabian peninsula.
Others will fill vacancies left by U.S. troops deploying to the
Middle East from the United States or Europe.
   One of the least publicized features of the enormous
mobilization of U.S. forces is the Marine Corps operation.
   For years the Marines have organized what they call Marine
Prepositioned Ships at three strategic points on the globe: along
the Atlantic Coast, near Diego Garcia in the Indian Ocean and near
Guam. The idea is that in time of crisis, any or all of these three
units _ each with four or five ships _ could move quickly into an
area of conflict with enough firepower and supplies to last 30 days.
   The Marine Prepositioned Ships from Diego Garcia and Guam were
among the first forces to get the word to head for Saudi Arabia.
The first group took just six days to get there.
   ``It's been a very substantial projection of combat force, and
this is important: both air and ground,'' said Marine Corps Lt.
Col. Stuart Wagner, a Pentagon spokesman.
   Among the weapons each Marine expeditionary brigade brings to
the field are M-1 tanks, F@A-18 attack aircraft, 115mm howitzers
and A-6E ground attack airplanes.
   Some Army airborne units were deployed quickly to Saudi Arabia,
but they were unable to bring as much firepower and supplies with
them as the Marines, which are virtually self-sustaining in food,
water, fuel, trucks, weapons and ammunition.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0019 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 1130EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Gulf-Images     08-26 0844</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Images,840</SECOND>
<HEAD>Public Relations Ploys of Bush, Saddam Backfire</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-US-Gulf, Bjt</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: Rodger in 6th graf is cq</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By ALEXANDER G. HIGGINS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush and Iraqi leader Saddam Hussein
are both learning that cultivating the right image through
television can be a tricky business.
   Saddam's lesson came in his failed attempt to ease international
fears about the safety of Western hostages in Iraq and Kuwait.
Instead, he provoked outrage by releasing a videotape that showed
him patting the heads of cringing British boys.
   The relentlessly vacationing Bush set out to show that the
Persian Gulf crisis wasn't holding him hostage in the White House.
But he has faced criticism that his golf-playing and motorboating
in Kennebunkport, Maine, were inappropriate when U.S. soldiers were
preparing for war along the Kuwaiti-Saudi border.
   ``Saddam Hussein must have figured that these tapes would play
wonderfully all over the world,'' said Philip Robbins, chairman of
the journalism department at George Washington University.
   ``The reaction ... is almost completely contrary to that,''
Robbins said. If it was meant to change world opinion, ``I think
it's failed miserably.''
   ``It's pretty clear that this was total theatrics that they had
put together to win the sympathy of some people somewhere,'' said
Rodger Streitmatter, an American University specialist in
presidential public relations.
   ``But,'' he added, ``it certainly is not going to convince very
many Americans that this is a humanitarian undertaking.''
   White House spokesman Marlin Fitzwater also denounced Saddam's
venture into video.
   ``The Iraqi film of Saddam Hussein posing with British hostages
shows the cynical and inhumane view that he holds for human life,''
Fitzwater said. ``To hold men, women and children up for viewing as
targets for destruction is sick beyond expression.
   ``It only serves to confirm and justify the world condemnation
of Iraq's aggressive ambitions.''
   Bush's problems stem from his determination to avoid appearing
to be a hostage in the White House of the Middle East situation.
President Jimmy Carter was accused of that after the Iranian siege
of the U.S. Embassy in Tehran in 1979 and the taking of American
hostages.
   Bush proceeded with vacation plans even as he ordered the
deployment of U.S. forces to the Gulf region and continued frequent
telephone contact with other world leaders.
   ``Reasonably thinking people would realize that this man
continues to be in touch with what's going on in the world and with
communication the way it is today could react to anything that
happened,'' said Streitmatter.
   ``But ... we tend to remember more what we see than what we
hear, and what we see is him playing golf,'' he said. ``Here we
have these images of these troops preparing to go off to
(potential) combat and leaving their families behind, juxtaposed
against these images of our president playing golf.''
   Robbins said Bush apparently was trying ``to present a picture
of the presidency being able to handle the situation without
anything abnormal taking place, so everybody should stay calm, cool
and collected. But I don't think it's worked that way.''
   ``I think most of the public when they see ... the troops going
to Saudi Arabia and the reservists being called up and the
discomfort, the downright inconvenience and the possible fate that
all of these service people are meeting, I don't think they like it
very much,'' Robbins said. ``I think it's going to turn out to be a
public-relations disaster, not just a mistake.''
   Streitmatter, noting that Bush's golfing had sparked criticism
from women demonstrators in Jordan, said international television
added a further dimension to the problem.
   ``At a time when we're dealing an international crisis and we
need some of these other nations dealing with this crisis with us,
it does make sense for the White House to be more sensitive to
cultural differences,'' he said.
   Stephen Hess of the Brookings Institution, a former adviser to
Democratic and Republican presidents, said, however, that Bush's
public-relations mistake was only ``of the most modest sort.''
   ``It really isn't that troubling out in the hinterlands. That's
what we're finding out,'' Hess said.
   ``George Bush is notably not a frivolous man,'' he said.
``Nobody thinks that he isn't paying proper attention. Sure he
shouldn't have answered reporters' questions while he was on the
golf links and maybe they should have made greater efforts to
pretend that presidents are working night and day while they're on
vacation. But ... George Bush is doing what a president is supposed
to be doing.''
   Streitmatter said long-term damage from Bush's image problems
would occur only if a disaster _ such as a number of soldiers being
killed _ were seen to coincide with his playing golf.
   ``This sort of thing is so ephemeral that there's no way it's
going to stick to the ribs,'' said Hess. ``The president comes back
to Washington in another 10 days and that's the end of this as an
issue.'' What's really hurting him is not so much the fact that
he's on vacation, but all we ever seem to see is him on vacation.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0020 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 1133EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-EastGermany'sEnd Bjt   08-26 0869</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-East Germany's End, Bjt,0900</SECOND>
<HEAD>Impending End of a Nation Creates Mixed Feelings</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TERRENCE PETTY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LEIPZIG, East Germany (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   East Germany is about to disappear,
to be swallowed up by its rich western neighbor, and the universal
enthusiasm of a few months ago has waned.
   Polls say the vast majority of East Germans favor unification,
which is barely a month away. But appearances don't always
reinforce that conclusion.
   The ``We are one people'' banners that hung from trees,
factories and homes during the pro-unity frenzy of early 1990 are
gone.
   There are no cheering crowds and no convoys of motorists
blasting their horns in anticipation of full unification on Oct. 3.
   Reality has set in, especially since the economic merger
officially began in July. The issue foremost in the minds of East
Germans is how to tackle the huge challenges facing them as their
crumbling economy is absorbed by West Germany.
   Some show a decided lack of eagerness for unity, especially in
Leipzig, birthplace of the uprising that ended 40 years of
Stalinist rule less than a year ago.
   ``Maybe the GDR (East Germany) could have survived as a newly
democratized country,'' said Maria Chudoba, who tends bar at the
Cappuccino cafe in Leipzig. ``But now it's too late to turn back.''
   Heinz Weisse, 74, and his 70-year-old wife, Gertrud, loading
bales of hay onto a cart outside Weimar, said they wouldn't have
minded seeing East Germany continue as a democracy.
   ``We're happy about unity, but it was not a necessary
development,'' said Weisse, a retired hairdresser. ``There's a good
side and bad side to everything.''
   He said he and his wife had a relatively good life even under
communism and, as pensioners, had been allowed to travel outside
the country.
   ``We had our little house here, and we were born here, so we
always came back,'' Weisse said.
   Most East Germans seem to see unification as their only
salvation, but have come to realize it will not be an overnight
cure for such problems as the high unemployment brought on by the
July 1 economic union.
   ``We had our celebrations last year when the Berlin Wall came
down,'' said Gisela Oswald, a 63-year-old retired opera singer in
Weimar, an East German cultural center.
   ``We're glad unity is coming, but we've got to get to work now
on some important problems, like putting the economy in order.''
   East German cities are decaying, the bottom has dropped out of
industrial production and unemployment is soaring.
   Most of East Germany's problems require money in huge amounts.
   Leipzig has a desperate housing shortage, crumbling public and
commercial buildings and an antiquated sewerage system that has
become a health hazard.
   Unification and the resulting West German funds undoubtedly will
help solve the economic problems over the next few years, but also
will introduce problems new to East Germany.
   ``Prostitution will come with the joblessness because people
need money,'' said Peter Fernau, chief of detectives in Bitterfeld,
an industrial city. ``We're also worried about heroin and the
possible appearance of criminal gangs. There will be totally new
dimensions to crime.''
   Several aspects of life will change after unity.
   West Germany's legal system will be extended to the East,
bringing in an entirely new code of laws.
   ``My officers are going to have to learn, learn, learn,'' Fernau
said.
   Many East Germans fear West Germans will make all the decisions
about their future.
   A recent poll by the West German magazine Stern indicated 88
percent of East Germans support unification, but 70 percent were
disappointed by how it has been managed. The process has been
largely orchestrated by Helmut Kohl, West Germany's chancellor.
   With the two Germanys united, East Germans will find themselves
in stiff competition with West Germans jobs and business
opportunities. They worry about coping.
   ``We never learned to persist in the face of adversity because,
in the old system, that was of no use,'' said Ms. Oswald, the opera
singer. ``This is something we must learn.
   ``But we also have many good qualities. We tend to be very
close-knit and helpful to each other, and that's something we don't
want to lose,'' she said.
   Peter Heyroth, Lutheran pastor in Bitterfeld, said the way unity
has been managed is demoralizing many people.
   ``They see the trucks rumbling into town at 6 a.m. with goods
from West Germany, while goods made in this country go unsold,'' he
said. ``They see prices climbing, and they feel like their job
training was worthless.''
   In the small city of Saalfeld, on the eastern edge of the
Thuringian forest, a former member of the disbanded Communist
secret police pondered his future.
   He has a new job, but things aren't going well.
   ``People hoot at me behind my back,'' he said. ``It's really
very difficult.''
   ``I was never involved in any heavy intelligence, just checking
passports and that kind of thing, but I'm ashamed of the corrupt
government we supported,'' said the former agent, who asked that
his name not be used.
   Then, seeming to speak for many East Germans, he said: ``Sure,
mistakes were made during the Communist period, but should four
decades of our past really be flushed down the sewer?''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0021 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 1141EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BarefootGuerrillas Bjt   08-26 0767</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Barefoot Guerrillas, Bjt,0793</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ragtag Tamil Rebel Force Challenges Sri Lanka's Army</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ARTHUR MAX</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>KARADIYANARU, Sri Lanka (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The barefoot rifle-toting
guerrillas occupying this eastern village hardly seem a match for
the crisply uniformed government soldiers down the road with
well-oiled machine guns.
   But here and elsewhere in Sri Lanka, the Tamil Tiger rebels _
many of them only teen-agers _ are engaging the army in a long and
savage civil war.
   ``Step by step we will defeat the army,'' said a Tiger commander
who has taken the name Newton. That seems unlikely, in the view of
observers and Western diplomats. But the army also seems incapable
of beating the ragtag guerrillas.
   In the north, the government launched a major offensive last
week to relieve Jaffna Fort, a 300-year-old colonial outpost
besieged by the rebels for 10 weeks.
   After initial gains, the advance bogged down under heavy rebel
mortar fire and machine-gun fusillades from bunkers, the government
said.
   On Sunday, military officials said, troops overran the
guerrillas after a three-hour battle on Mandativu Island, a
stepping stone to the star-shaped fortress.
   But army troops have failed to meet their aim of reaching the
trapped 250-man garrison in the fort, the government's strongest
outpost on the rebel-controlled Jaffna Peninsula.
   On the eastern front, the guerrillas have once again yielded the
main towns and most of the roads to the army. They have faded into
the jungles and the villages from where they have launched
hit-and-run raids and mined roads for the past seven years.
   Newton, asked about his tactical objectives in the east, had a
simple answer. ``We are going to kill a large number of army,'' he
said.
   Newton and two other Tiger commanders, known as Karikalan and
Nithi, spoke in a bare room in the dusty village of Karadiyanaru,
on the main road leading to Batticaloa, 170 miles southeast of
Jaffna.
   Earlier, government officials had earlier claimed all three had
been killed.
   The rebels were contacted by walkie-talkie from a checkpoint
manned by a dozen barefoot teen-agers who wore wore fatigue shirts
and ammunition belts, stuffed with rifle clips, grenades and a
toothbrush _ for cleaning weapons.
   The civil war erupted in 1983 over Tamil complaints that they
were suppressed by the Sinhalese, who comprise 75 percent of the
population and control the government. Tamils make up 18 percent of
Sri Lanka's 16 million people.
   The Tigers, who demand independence for their ethnic minority,
are the only Tamil group continuing the fight. Others gave up their
weapons in 1987 and agreed to negotiate for an autonomous region in
the north and east.
   After a 13-month cease-fire, the Tigers resumed the war on June
11, by storming 30 police and army barracks in the east.
   Villagers in Karadiyanaru appeared unhappy over the presence of
the rebels. Food is scarce, commerce has stopped and the area is
virtually cut off from the rest of the region. Army patrols
occasionally come through, firing into roadside homes.
   ``All the poor people in this area get no help from the
government or from anyone else,'' said one village elder.
   An army officer commanding a checkpoint 12 miles to the west of
the village claimed only about 100 Tigers were scattered in the
bush, and the rest had fled to the north.
   The army checkpoint had four small armored vehicles, and the
troops looked sharp and well-trained.
   Newton, asked whether his forces were retreating, only laughed.
About 15 Tigers were seen in and near the village.
   The Tigers' heaviest weapons are mortars, and most equipment is
stolen or stripped from the corpses of army casualties. Newton
proudly displayed a homemade mortar from a secret armory.
   The Liberation Tigers for Tamil Eelam grew out of a student
movement in the Jaffna area in the 1970s and emerged into the open
as a guerrilla force in 1983.
   The group is led by Veluppillai Prabhakaran, a school dropout
who catapulted to the group's leadership when he assassinated the
mayor of Jaffna in 1975.
   Prabhakaran demands absolute discipline. His forces are
forbidden to smoke or drink. He approves every major operation,
according to a source close to the Tigers.
   Western diplomats believe a political settlement is the only
answer to the war, but it may be a long time in coming.
   ``The government has to knock back the Tigers a bit,
militarily,'' said one diplomat who spoke on condition of anonymity.
   ``They can't defeat the Tigers or wipe them out,'' the diplomat
said. ``There will have to be a stalemate for long enough for the
war fever to wear off.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0022 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 1150EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Gulf-VOAJamming     08-26 0282</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-VOA Jamming,280</SECOND>
<HEAD>VOA Says Iraq Jamming Its Arabic Broadcasts To Persian Gulf</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-US-Gulf, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Iraq has jammed the Voice of America's Arabic
language broadcasts since the Persian Gulf crisis began, but VOA
says the radio programs still can be heard.
   In a message sent to U.S. embassies in the gulf region last
week, the agency said it was possible to overcome the Iraqi jamming
in several ways.
   Embassies were urged to advise listeners who did not hear the
VOA broadcasts on the usual frequency to tune around in the same
shortwave band because the frequency might have been changed to
avoid jamming.
   Also, the message said, the Arabic broadcasts emanate from relay
stations that are west of Iraq and thus are in daylight while the
Iraqi jamming stations are in darkness. Since the stations still in
daylight can use higher frequencies, listeners were advised to tune
to the highest frequency after sunset.
   Voice of America said also that its Arabic language broadcasts
to North Africa generally are not jammed and can be heard in the
Gulf region, although not as well as those directed toward the
Middle East.
   ``Listen in different locations, even within the same house or
apartment,'' the message said. ``Shortwave reception can differ
greatly from within the same room. One location may favor VOA more
than the jamming signal.''
   VOA spokeswoman Judy Jamison said Iraq had not previously jammed
the broadcasts, but began doing so within a few days after its Aug.
2 invasion of Kuwait, utilizing ``a definite warbling sound.''
   Despite the jamming, Ms. Jamison said, ``a determined listener''
can hear the broadcasts.
   VOA's English language broadcasts are not jammed, she said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0023 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 1154EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-AnonymousElmer     08-26 0803</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Anonymous Elmer,750</SECOND>
<HEAD>Who's That Crouching Next to the Pianist? Hey, It's Elmer Booze!</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT M. ANDREWS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Elmer Booze strides onto the concert stage for
another virtuoso performance, but nobody applauds. He shares the
spotlight but never takes a bow. His name doesn't even appear in
the program.
   So what? The guy spends most of the evening staring at the sheet
music and wetting his thumb and forefinger. Big deal.
   Any pianist, though, will say that Elmer Booze really is a big
deal. He is a professional page turner, one of the most
indispensable _ and most anonymous _ figures in the musical world.
   Booze, 57, a small, soft-spoken man who wears gold-rimmed
glasses, has turned the pages of musical scores for Aaron Copland,
Rudolf Serkin, Andre Watts, Leon Fleisher and Bella Davidovich and
hundreds of other musicians for nearly a quarter-century.
   He turned pages for opera singer Leontyne Price's accompanist at
a White House recital for President Carter. He's been a consultant
and resident page turner for the annual summer Newport (R.I.) Music
Festival for the past 14 years.
   He's a regular at concert series at the National Gallery of Art,
the Canadian Embassy, the Kennedy Center and the Library of
Congress in Washington. He has flown to New York and London to sit
at the elbow of concert pianists who insisted that only Elmer Booze
would do.
   An accomplished pianist himself, with music degrees from two
universities, Booze is content to labor in the shadows of the
keyboard giants.
   A colleague at the Library of Congress, where Booze works during
the day as a senior reference librarian in the music division,
proudly calls him ``a world-renowned page turner.'' Booze modestly
dismisses such extravagant praise.
   ``For me, it's a job that anybody can do,'' he said. ``But
apparently that's not entirely true. I've talked to pianists who
say they can't turn pages. It makes them very nervous.''
   By contrast, Booze sits on the edge of his chair with
unflappable ease as the pianist struggles through stormy
fortissimos and crashing arpeggios.
   ``Pianists want someone with them in their greatest moment of
need, when they've gotten to the last note on the page,'' he said.
   That's the moment when Booze shifts into a low crouch and, with
a lightning thrust of the arm, flips to the next page and returns
to his seat. His movements are so unobtrusive that one pianist
calls him ``the ghost.''
   A good page turner must be skilled in reading a musical score,
Booze says, and a rehearsal is helpful to become familiar with the
pianist's eccentricities.
   Does he memorize the score? (Chamber music is rarely played from
memory, Booze says.) Are the pianist's jerks and nods a signal to
turn the page, or is he simply getting carried away with the music?
Are the pages old and brittle? Do they stick together?
   Onstage, he says, a page turner should keep his eyes on the
music and maintain ``a certain decorum'' to put the pianist at ease.
   ``If there's panic in your eyes, you can believe the pianist
will panic, too,'' he said. ``The last thing he needs is a spastic
page turner.''
   Despite the page turner's best efforts, disasters do happen.
Booze recalls the nightmarish evening of the missing paper clip.
   His pianist had promised in the dressing room of the Kennedy
Center Concert Hall to insert a paper clip in the score of a
devilishly complex work by Franz Liszt for two pianos. At the point
when Booze was supposed to turn back 20 pages for a repeat in the
second movement, the paper clip wasn't there.
   ``It was something to behold,'' he said. ``He was going like a
bat out of hell. His arms were in my way and mine were in his,
trying to find the exact page. Both pianists stopped playing, and
the whole thing came to a screeching halt. It was not a good show.''
   Booze has left his tuxedo jacket unbuttoned during concerts ever
since he rose from his chair to turn a page for Aaron Copland and a
button popped onto the keyboard while the composer was performing
at the Library of Congress.
   Booze turned another anxious moment into a tour de force that
garnered the first and only ovation he has ever received from an
audience.
   When he and a pianist took their seats at the Newport festival,
they discovered that the piano's music rack had been removed and
was nowhere to be found. So Booze became a human music rack,
holding up photocopies of each page of the score.
   When the piece was finished, the festival president leaped to
her feet. ``Let's all clap for Elmer,'' she shouted, and the page
turner shyly emerged from the shadows to accept his acclaim.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0024 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 1211EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--ForestFires     08-26 0180</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Forest Fires,0182</SECOND>
<HEAD>Fires Under Control After Five Days</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOULON, France (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Firefighters and soldiers worked Sunday to
extinguish fires that raged for five days near the Mediterranean
cities of Toulon and Nice. One firefighter has died and one was
seriously hurt battling the blazes.
   The fire near Toulon in the southern Var region, which started
Tuesday, was fanned by strong mistral winds. It destroyed up to
34,600 acres of brush and pine forest before being brought under
control, making it one of the area's biggest single fires,
officials said.
   On Sunday, planes and helicopters were dumping water over
pockets of flames and smoldering brush.
   A smaller fire near Nice, at the eastern end of the French
Riviera, also was nearly extinguished Sunday, five days after it
began. Police sources said that fire, which destroyed 1,485 acres
of Mediterranean pine, might have been arson.
   A volunteer firefighter was killed Wednesday fighting the blaze
near Nice when his truck overturned, and on Friday, a fireman was
seriously injured in the Var region when his vehicle plunged into a
ravine.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0025 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 1220EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-PhillyJustice     08-26 0804</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Philly Justice,0827</SECOND>
<HEAD>Glimmers of Hope for Philly Courts, Prisons</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Out of Jails, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TED DUNCOMBE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PHILADELPHIA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The mayor calls courtrooms in this city ``a
bastion of inefficiency,'' but justice no longer will be delayed if
a fast-track program continues to cut into heavy courtroom
backlogs, supporters say.
   Expected to cut a 12,200-case backlog by 41 percent this year,
it's a glimmer of hope for city courts, police and prisons, which a
blue-ribbon task force characterized earlier this year as at ``the
edge of a precipice.''
   Optimism has been buoyed in some quarters by four reports this
year that recommended a new courthouse, more prison cells, a
professional court administrator and other changes.
   ``I see light,'' said A. Leo Levin, a University of Pennsylvania
law professor and chairman of the 16-member Philadelphia Criminal
Justice Task Force that produced one of the reports. ``I refuse to
see the absence of light.''
   Richard F. Moore, projects management coordinator for the city's
Justice Facilities and System Improvement Strategy program, said
that when the reports appeared, ``everybody simply condemned
everybody's report.''
   ``However, it seemed that once everybody got all that out of
their system, everybody started reading these reports,'' he said.
``Things that we wrote started popping up in various proposed
solutions.''
   Skeptics say Philadelphia's justice system is so mired in
politics it can never change.
   ``The fact is that government in Philadelphia, historically and
to some extent today, operates in a culture of nepotism, favoritism
and corruption,'' said Gerald M. Caplan, a law professor at George
Washington University and staff director for a 1987 report on the
Philadelphia Police Department.
   The courts have been engaged in a running battle with city
government over construction of a new courthouse and who should pay
the costs of court staff.
   ``Our courts, which should serve as a bulwark of equity, are
instead a mecca of patronage,'' Mayor W. Wilson Goode said last
week. ``They should stand as a monument of progress, but are
instead a bastion of inefficiency.''
   He has called for sweeping court reforms before the courthouse
is built.
   An audit conducted as part of a judges' lawsuit seeking more
city funds concluded the courts had enough money ``to perform their
constitutional mission,'' but said more money could cut backlogs.
   ``The delays now tolerated ... are excessive by any standard,''
the audit said.
   Common Pleas Court had a 10-month backlog of criminal cases and
a 27-month backlog of civil cases at the time. The audit urged more
accountability for judges and less control by lawyers of the pace
of proceedings.
   Yet a cooperative effort begun Jan. 2 by prosecutors, public
defenders and Common Pleas Court drew praise in the audit and other
reports. It was intended to speed the processing of less serious
felonies such as retail theft, auto theft, forgery and arson.
   The backlog is projected to fall to 7,263 by Dec. 31 from 12,199
at the end of last year, according to the district attorney's
office. At that rate, the backlog would be gone by April 1992.
   The program allows defendants to enter guilty pleas earlier in
the court process than previously, to combine pleas if facing more
than one charge and to reach trial sooner if they plead innocent.
It will be attempted with major felonies come autumn.
   ``This program benefits everyone by eliminating unnecessary
postponements and by providing trial listings only to those cases
which cannot be disposed through appropriate plea arrangements,''
District Attorney Ronald D. Castille said.
   Another bright spot may be found in plans to expand a 125-inmate
holding cell area on the seventh floor of City Hall. An average of
280 prisoners are jammed daily behind Plexiglas panels to await
court hearings.
   ``It looks like a way station to hell when you see the bodies
lined up in there,'' said Allen M. Hornblum, chief of staff since
May for the Sheriff's Department.
   By December, several nearby offices now used for inmate
psychiatric exams will be converted into more holding cells, he
said.
   ``It will benefit the people we put in the cells as well as the
deputies who guard them,'' Hornblum said. ``It's gotten to the
point where something very explosive could happen that would affect
public safety in a very serious way.''
   More crowding exists in the city's four prisons, which have a
federal court cap on population of 3,750 but typically have 5,000
to 5,200 inmates.
   The city was ordered in July to pay $20,000 in fines a day
because of its failure to add more guards, nurses and social
workers and meet other conditions required under a separate lawsuit.
   Prisons Commissioner J. Patrick Gallagher, who was hired in
1989, sees construction of 500 new cells this fall as the beginning
of the rehabilitation and replacement of prison buildings dating
from 1893.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0026 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 1220EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Howell-Wife     08-26 0515</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Howell-Wife,0530</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ambassasor's Wife Says He Has Become Symbol Of Hope</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-US-Gulf, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CHARLOTTESVILLE, Va. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The wife of Ambassador W. Nathaniel
Howell, who is trapped in the U.S. Embassy in Kuwait, says her
husband has become a symbol of peace and hope for Americans and
foreigners held hostage by Saddam Hussein.
   Margie Saunders Howell said in an interview at her
Charlottesville home Saturday that she feared for her husband's
safety. But she said he had no choice but to stay at the American
mission after Saddam ordered embassy personnel to Baghdad and the
mission closed.
   She has faith that Howell can stand up to Iraqi pressure.
   Howell and 10 others remained at the besieged embassy Sunday,
two days after Iraqi troops surrounded it, cutting off electricity
and water. Marine embassy guards were among personnel sent to
Baghdad, the State Department said.
   The United States, Canada, Japan, Bangladesh, Switzerland,
Austria, Poland, Czechoslovakia, Yugoslavia and the 12 European
Community nations were among those who announced they would defy
the Iraqi order to shut down.
   ``He knows that things could go badly, because there's nothing
between him and the Iraqis,'' Mrs. Howell said. ``But his presence
there is not only a sign to Iraq that we don't agree with their
actions, it's a sign to Americans that we care about them.''
   Mrs. Howell, who returned to Charlottesville from Washington on
Saturday, last spoke with her husband around 5 a.m. Friday, noon in
Kuwait, she said. That was Saddam's deadline for the American
embassy to close.
   ``I didn't sleep all night the night before,'' Mrs. Howell said.
Howell reassured her that the embassy was safe, she said. ``He was
eating lunch,'' Mrs. Howell said. ``He was very calm.''
   Mrs. Howell returned to the United States from Kuwait on July 27
to attend her father's 84th birthday celebration. She was aware of
mounting tensions between Iraq and Kuwait, she said, but no one
expected an invasion.
   ``When I left, there were 30,000 Iraqi troops sitting at the
border, but we thought that was Saddam Hussein's way of extorting
money from Kuwait, '' she said.
   Howell, 51, was scheduled to step down as ambassador this month
and join his wife as he resumed duties in Washington. He has served
as ambassador to Kuwait for three years and was in diplomatic
positions in Algiers, Lebanon and Egypt.
   ``This is our third war,'' Mrs. Howell said. Howell worked for
the U.S. Foreign Service in Cairo during the Six-Day War in 1967
and in Beirut when Lebanon's civil war broke out in 1975.
   Howell graduated from the University of Virginia in 1961 and
received his doctorate in government and foreign affairs from the
school in 1965. Mrs. Howell is a graduate of the university's
nursing school.
   University of Virginia Professor R.K. Ramazani describes his
former student as imaginative, systematic, hard-working and
thorough.
   ``He's a very accomplished diplomat,'' said Ramazani, who served
as a consultant to President Jimmy Carter during the American
hostage crisis in Iran.
   The Howells plan on retiring in Charlottesville, where Howell
hopes to teach at the university.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0027 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 1230EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-Israel-Masks     08-26 0389</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Israel-Masks,0399</SECOND>
<HEAD>Schools To Instruct 1 Million Students In Gas Mask Use</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf Rdp, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GWEN ACKERMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   More than a million Israeli schoolchildren will
get an intensive course in the use of gas masks and other ways of
surviving chemical warfare to prepare for a possible Iraqi attack,
officials said Sunday.
   The program, to begin when school starts Sept. 2, follows
threats earlier this year by Iraqi President Saddam Hussein to
attack Israel with chemical weapons if an Israeli nuclear attack is
aimed at Iraq.
   ``The children will be instructed how to put on their gas masks
and walk up to the upper floors of the school, to previously sealed
off classrooms,'' Ran Levine, deputy director general of the
Education Ministry, told Israel radio.
   According to officials, the instruction will be given to all
Israeli students, both Jews and Arabs, between age 5 and 18.
   Some 5,000 teachers will take a course on using the protective
equipment. Two teachers from each school will then complete
instruction for the students by Sept. 20. Each school will receive
a videotape and 25 gas masks for demonstrations, officials said.
   Dr. Avigdor Klingman, the Education Ministry's coordinator for
crisis intervention, said the course also is designed to quiet
children's fears about gas masks.
   ``A child who thinks that he can't wear a mask because it is too
scary, then puts it on with the help of his teacher, paints with
it, or does exercises with it then sees that the devil is not so
bad,'' Klingman said.
   Gas masks will not be handed out at schools, but will be
distributed to families through neighborhood civil defense offices.
   Despite the recent crisis, Israeli authorities have decided not
to distribute the masks to the public now for fear of causing panic
or sending a wrong signal to Iraq.
   Saddam first warned he would use chemical weapons against Israel
last April. During the current crisis, he has threatened to attack
Israel in response to a U.S. military strike, but he has not
specifically mentioned chemical weapons.
   Bomb drills have always been part of Israel's school curriculum.
   In the past four years, instruction on protection against
chemical warfare has been introduced at some 250 middle and high
schools. This year the program is being expanded to all schools.

</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0028 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 1251EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-Pope     08-26 0380</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Pope,0390</SECOND>
<HEAD>Pope Criticizes Iraq, Prays for Those `Unjustly Held'</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf Rdp, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CASTEL GANDOLFO, Italy (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In his first public condemnation
of Iraq, Pope John Paul II on Sunday denounced Saddam Hussein's
detention of foreigners, praying for those ``unjustly kept far from
their homeland.''
   In the first weeks following the Aug. 2 Iraqi invasion of
Kuwait, the pontiff made no public statements about the crisis.
   On Wednesday, speaking to a small group of Japanese Buddhists,
the pope alluded to the crisis for the first time, saying peace was
being threatened. Although he did not mention any geographical
area, the reference to the Persian Gulf was clear.
   On Sunday, the pope specifically cited the crisis, following his
noontime prayer from the balcony of his summer palace in the hills
outside Rome, where pilgrims were gathered for his blessing.
   ``On this day of the Lord, I feel the duty to invite you to pray
for peace in the Persian Gulf, where recently, a truly worrisome
situation has developed,'' the pope said.
   `We have been witnesses to grave violations of international
rights and of the U.N. charter, as well as of ethical principles
that must prevail among all peoples,'' he said.
   ``The mistrust of one side versus another is dramatically
increasing and international order, constructed with so much effort
and at the sacrifice of so many human lives, is gravely
threatened,'' John Paul continued.
   The pontiff prayed for peace in the entire Middle East, asking
God to ``enlighten those who control the fates of peoples so that
they will find fair solutions for the existing problems and make
the star of peace shine strongly on the tried peoples of the
Persian Gulf as on all the peoples of the Middle East, above all
those who suffer in Lebanon and in Palestine.''
   The pontiff ended with a prayer to the Virgin Mary for the
foreigners prevented from leaving Iraq and Kuwait.
   ``Mary, queen of peace, intercede for us and above all for those
who suffer because they are unjustly kept far from their homeland.
Lord, give us peace.''
   Saddam has said foreigners caught in Iraq and Kuwait will be
used as human shields to protect key Iraqi installations. About
21,000 of them are Westerners, including 3,000 Americans and 3,000
Britons.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0029 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 1420EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-RolexRobberies     08-26 0596</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Rolex Robberies,0616</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rash of Robberies Target Expensive Status-Symbol Watches</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Rolex watches, gilded badges of wealth and
luxury, have become an emblem of violence and death as robbers who
covet the expensive timepieces are killing their owners for them,
police say.
   Sam Sabbah was meeting his wife and a painter in his new Beverly
Hills home last June when an intruder fatally shot him and took his
Rolex.
   A few days later, west Los Angeles transmission shop owner
Melvin Thompson broke with his usual routine and wore his Rolex to
work, intending to take it to a jeweler. A robber hit at closing,
taking the watch and cash and shooting Thompson to death.
   This month, nursery owner Donald McKinsey hung on to his $10,000
watch during a robbery and was shot to death by gunmen who had
posed as customers.
   A Rolex watch can range in price from about $1,000 to more than
$20,000. Some of the 18-karat gold timepieces are encrusted with
diamonds. It's not the watch the robbers want, but rather the money
it commands.
   The police division covering Los Angeles' affluent west side
dealt with 49 Rolex robberies from September to July. Beverly Hills
has been averaging one a month, according to police Lt. Robert
Curtis.
   Police say no one individual or group is responsible. There have
been arrests but watch robberies continue.
   Sometimes the victims were followed home from a shopping mall or
other public place where an expensive watch on a wrist could be
spotted, police say.
   In the McKinsey murder, however, the killers came to the nursery
and discussed renting plants, then returned the next day to do the
robbery.
   Nursery office manager Ken Steller said later that McKinsey knew
of the watch robberies but continued to wear the timepiece.
   ``It was his signature,'' Steller said.
   Car salesman Bob Gordon of Santa Monica thinks similarly of his
$17,750 Rolex.
   ``I love that watch. It's a sign of my success,'' he said. ``But
I don't think I can wear it, certainly not to work. It's too
dangerous.''
   Gordon immediately handed the watch over to three robbers who
entered his office Aug. 16. A gun was pointed at his heart but the
trio left him unharmed. A police pursuit ended with three arrests
and the watch was recovered.
   Last week, the district attorney's office charged Eric Jones,
23, his brother Derrick Jones, 20, and Isaac Williams 21, with the
Gordon robbery.
   Williams was also charged with a similar robbery that occurred
the day before in Beverly Hills. A Rolex watch and $140,000 in
jewelry were taken.
   Those were only the latest arrests. Los Angeles County sheriff's
detectives and South Bay police seized two men in May in a probe of
watch robberies in which victims were often approached in parking
structures.
   A Rolex robbery in December led to the arrest of two other men
in Redondo Beach. The investigation encompassed similar holdups in
affluent Rolling Hills Estates and Palos Verdes Estates.
   It's not clear in every case the robber knew he was getting a
Rolex. Los Angeles police Detective Dan Andrews notes there are
other kinds of valuable watches, and that ``it's the money behind
the watch that's the target.''
   Andrews investigated the McKinsey murder as well as the killing
a year ago of restaurateur Andre Coffyn at a westside bistro.
   Coffyn was chatting with customers on a patio when a gunman
barged in and demanded: ``Give me your watches.'' Coffyn handed
over a gold Omega watch and wallet. The bandit shot him to death
and fled.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0030 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 1421EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-PrayerSuit Bjt   08-26 0671</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Prayer Suit, Bjt,0691</SECOND>
<HEAD>Graduation Prayer: No Harm, Says Governor; ACLU Disagrees</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PEG McENTEE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SALT LAKE CITY (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   To Gov. Norm Bangerter, an impending legal
battle over the saying of prayers at public school graduations is a
local issue that scarcely affects predominantly Mormon Utah's image
in the global marketplace.
   Nor does he see the bitterly divisive issue tainting Salt Lake
City's bid to be host of the 1998 Winter Olympics.
   ``I doubt anyone who's going to come to the Olympics worries
whether there's prayer in graduation at high school. I doubt that
it's going to cross many people's minds,'' Bangerter said in an
interview.
   But Michele Parish-Pixler, state director of the American Civil
Liberties Union, is among many non-Mormons who believe the
governor's attitude helps perpetuate the outsider's image of Utah
as a narrow-minded theocracy.
   ``We spend all this money to promote tourism, then we do this
stuff,'' she said.
   Perhaps not since non-Mormon efforts to permit hard liquor to be
served by the drink failed in 1968 has an issue so sharply divided
Utah residents along religious lines. The battle was joined July 30
when the ACLU filed suit in federal court seeking to ban prayer
from public school graduations.
   Bangerter, a Mormon and a Republican, said he may ask the state
Legislature for a special appropriation to help the two school
districts named in the suit defend themselves in court.
   ``I felt local districts were being somewhat intimidated by the
threat of a lawsuit in doing what they desired to do,'' he said.
   The U.S. Supreme Court banned organized, school-sponsored prayer
sessions for students in 1962. Bangerter believes a legal gray area
remains for opening and closing prayers at events such as
commencement.
   Seventy percent of Utah's 1.7 million residents are members of
the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints and most of the
graduation prayers are delivered by Mormons.
   Many defend the practice, saying critics are taking potshots at
a faith defenders say is virtually synonymous with a healthy and
industrious lifestyle.
   Others decry the church's influence on daily life in Utah,
saying Mormons have no conception of the ostracism felt by everyone
else.
   ``It's not just prayers at high school graduation,''
Parish-Pixler said. ``The governor brings this down to kids sitting
through a 30-second prayer once in 12 years. The people who go to
school here deal with it at every activity.
   ``This is a state that's reluctant to give up its church-state
status. That does not play well with people on the outside. They
come, stay a couple of years, and leave.
   ``They say, `My kids were so unhappy we had to leave.' Every
time Utah loses somebody that way, the message goes out to
corporate America that this is a hardship post.''
   To be sure, Utah isn't the only state to confront the issue.
   Last month, the 1st U.S. Circuit Court of Appeals affirmed a
Rhode Island Court's ban on graduation prayers. Iowa courts have
done the same.
   In California, the state Supreme Court has been asked to review
contrary rulings on whether the practice violates the First
Amendment, Parish-Pixler said.
   State Sen. Frances Farley, a non-Mormon Democrat who moved to
Utah two decades ago, is saddened by the dispute.
   During a recent bipartisan Senate caucus in which the subject
was discussed, she said Utah ``should grow up.'' And in what she
now considers an intemperate remark, she added, ``To be crass, it's
not good for business.''
   ``What I said on the floor of the Senate was more or less a plea
of understanding for people who move to Utah, and love it, and make
it their home, but are not accustomed to the pervasiveness of what
seems like the dominant religion,'' she said.
   The Mormon Church has remained silent on the lawsuit.
   But Elder Dallin H. Oaks, a member of the church's Council of
the Twelve Apostles and a former Utah Supreme Court justice,
defended graduation prayers in a May column in The Wall Street
Journal.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0031 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 1426EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-IcedTeaRescue     08-26 0261</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Iced Tea Rescue,0267</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rescuers Use Iced Tea to Douse Car Fire, Save Woman</HEAD>
<DATELINE>GUILFORD, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A woman whose car crashed and burst into
flames was rescued by a quick-thinking couple who used a jug of
iced tea to douse the flames.
   ``Thank God for my wife's iced tea,'' said Michael Rodrigue, a
Sarasota, Fla., firefighter and paramedic who pulled Natalie A.
Corcoran, 60, from her burning car Saturday.
   Police said Corcoran was driving north on Interstate 95 at about
7 p.m. when her car slammed into a highway sign, flipped over and
skidded along the road, bursting into flames.
   Rodrigue and his wife, Kim, a registered nurse, pulled over to
help her, grabbing a plastic jug of iced tea from their car.
   ``I could hear her screaming, `Help me! Help me! I'm burning!'''
Rodrigue said.
   He got down on his knees and began pouring poured iced tea on
the flames while he tried to free Corcoran, who was wearing a seat
belt, from the car.
   ``Her right shoe was burning and her legs were almost on fire,''
he said.
   A second motorist, Judy Volner, called 911 on her car telephone
and had a small knife to cut the seat belt to free Corcoran. And a
truck driver, Armand Brodeur, stopped and brought out a small fire
extinguisher to help.
   Rodrigue finally managed to pull got Corcoran from out the car
and away from the wreckage as fire and rescue trucks arrived.
Corcoran was taken by ambulance to Yale-New Haven Hospital where
she was reported in stable condition.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0032 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 1441EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People     08-26 0715</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People,0742</SECOND>
<HEAD>People in the News</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY44</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PITTSBURGH (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Linda Ronstadt blames arena concerts and radio
programmers for the ``awful'' state of pop music.
   ``What really ruined pop music is the architecture that it's
presented in,'' Ms. Ronstadt told The Pittsburgh Press in Sunday's
editions. ``Any place that's bigger than 11,000 is just not a
suitable environment for music.''
   Describing the sound in such places as ``swimmy and boomy,'' she
said, ``I hate playing in them, and I will never be in an audience
at one of them.''
   Of the current music scene, the singer-songwriter said, ``It's
awful.'' One reason: ``the corporate approach to radio
programming.''
   ``If you're a musician and you come from Memphis or Nashville or
New Orleans, areas that have some of the richest musical heritage
in the country, you have to go to Los Angeles in order to do it,''
Ms. Ronstadt said.
   Twenty-five years ago, regional sounds like Memphis
rhythm-and-blues and Motown found national niches, according to Ms.
Ronstadt.
   Ms. Ronstadt's next pop album probably will include some New
Orleans tunes by Allan Toussaint or Irma Thomas, she said. Her most
recent album is ``Cry Like a Rainstorm, Howl Like the Wind.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>HOLMDEL, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Pop singer-songwriter Sinead O'Connor has
sung her last note at the Garden State Arts Center.
   Ms. O'Connor, known for the hit single ``Nothing Compares 2 U''
and her extremely short haircut, threatened Friday to walk out on a
9,000-member audience if the American national anthem was played at
her concert. Ms. O'Connor is Irish.
   Backstage staff relented out of fear that a last-minute
cancellation would cause a commotion, said Dennis Ingoglia, a
spokesman for the New Jersey Highway Authority, which operates the
center. She gave no reason for the request, Ingoglia said in
Saturday's editions of The Star-Ledger of Newark.
   But George Zilocchi, the authority's acting executive director,
gave his reasons for banning Ms. O'Connor from appearing at the
concert hall.
   ``No performer who does not agree to have the national anthem
played will be allowed to perform,'' Zilocchi said.
   Efforts to reach Ms. O'Connor's spokeswoman, Elaine Schock of
Pelham, N.Y., were not immediately successful Sunday. There was no
telephone listing under Ms. Schock's name there.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>AUGUSTA, Maine (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Former Olympic women's marathon champion
Joan Benoit Samuelson is supporting a campaign aimed at keeping
guns locked away from kids.
   ``Having young children around the house, I see them getting
into everything,'' said Samuelson. ``It drives it home that guns
need to be stored properly and beyond the reach of kids.''
   A proposed referendum would ask whether adults should be held
responsible if children under 16 gain unsupervised access to
firearms. Such a law would require that guns be stored in locked
boxes or protected by trigger locks. Maximum penalties would be
$1,000 in fines and a year in jail.
   Portland Police Chief Michael Chitwood began the campaign after
the Maine Legislature rejected a bill to keep guns out of the hands
of children. He cited the fatal shootings of eight children within
a year and a half.
   The gun-safety campaign is seeking 50,000 signatures on
petitions to put the question on the November 1991 ballot. So far,
about 10,000 signatures have been collected, said Chitwood.
   The Sportsman's Alliance of Maine is opposing the measure and
says that gun-safety programs are more effective than laws in
protecting people.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>Eds: Following item embargoed for release 6 p.m. EDT.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>RADNOR, Pa. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Veteran soap actress Frances Reid says times
have changed for aspiring actors and actresses.
   ``In my day, you could have a career if you stood up straight
and spoke your lines loud and clear,'' the Emmy nominee said in the
Sept. 1 issue of TV Guide. ``Now, being prepared is more important
than ever. To survive today's competition, you have to be able to
act, sing, dance ... and strip.''
   Reid, who once landed a stage role as Roxanne opposite Jose
Ferrer's Cyrano de Bergerac, today plays great-great-grandmother
Alice Horton on NBC's ``Days of Our Lives.''
   She also helps with career-orientation sessions for the
television performers' union, the American Federation of Television
and Radio Artists.
   ``A lot of Hollywood hopefuls still think you can get discovered
in a pink angora sweater at Schwab's drug store,'' she said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0033 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 1444EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Gulf-Kerry 1stLdWritethru a0709 08-26 0434</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Kerry, 1st Ld Writethru, a0709,430</SECOND>
<HEAD>Nebraska Senator Says No Loss Of Life For Cheap Oil</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS pvs lede to CORRECT American's to Americans</NOTE>
<HEAD>With AM-US-Gulf, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By H. JOSEF HEBERT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Declaring that young Americans shouldn't die
in battle just to keep gasoline prices low, Sen. Bob Kerry on
Sunday said the U.S. should abandon the notion of cheap oil.
   The Nebraska Democrat, a Vietnam veteran and Congressional Medal
Of Honor recipient, said he supported President Bush's decision to
send troops to the Persian Gulf, but only as a means of preventing
an Iraqi invasion of Saudi Arabia.
   ``I question the response that says that we're going to go there
and have our young people die so that we can have cheap oil here at
home,'' Kerry said in an appearance on NBC-TV's ``Meet the Press.''
   ``The only justification that I find that is legitimate is that
... we're the only nation that could move quick enough to prevent
an invasion of Saudi Arabia.''
   Congressional Democrats have generally supported Bush during the
Middle East crisis, although there has been some grumbling that the
president should clarify his long-term objectives in the Persian
Gulf region.
   American troops were sent to the area after Iraqi forces easily
conquered Kuwait in an Aug. 2 invasion. Iraq annexed the oil-rich
emirate six days later.
   Congressional leaders have asked for a White House briefing next
Tuesday on the Middle East developments.
   Like most members of Congress, which has been recessed in
August, Kerry has been in his home while the tense situation in the
Persian Gulf has unfolded. He expressed some frustration that Bush
had not provided lawmakers with more details about the
administration's intentions in the gulf region.
   ``We aren't, it seems to me, being provided a sufficient amount
of information to really engage meaningfully in a debate about
whether or not this (U.S. deployment of military forces) is
appropriate,'' said Kerry, who is not among the congressional
leadership and knew nothing of Tuesday's planned briefing.
   ``I know from reading the newspapers that it's hot in the desert
and the chow is bad,'' he added.
   Kerry suggested that American demand for cheap oil contributed
to Iraqi President Saddam Hussein's rise to power in the Middle
East.
   ``We in general have been blinded by money ... and as a
consequence we put into place policy that encouraged Hussein to
become extremely strong,'' he said.
   Kerry said Americans are being ``very tolerant of higher oil
prices' that have resulted from the gulf tensions, ``even though
they are grumbling a bit about it.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0034 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 1454EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Taiwan-Boat     08-26 0385</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Taiwan-Boat,0398</SECOND>
<HEAD>20 Dead In Capsizing Of Crowded Tourist Boat</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SHIRLEY LAI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NANTOU, Taiwan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Rescuers on Sunday pulled more bodies from
a lake where an overloaded tourist boat overturned during a
moon-gazing cruise a night earlier. At least 21 people drowned and
34 were missing and feared dead, police said.
   Shell Taiwan Ltd., which chartered the boat for a weekend tour,
said in a statement that 88 people were on board, including three
British executives and 82 other company staffers and family members.
   About 200 rescuers, including divers, searched the picturesque
Sun Moon Lake in one of Taiwan's most popular tourist districts for
survivors through Saturday night and Sunday, police said. No
Americans were known to be aboard.
   ``We are extremely distressed by this great tragedy,'' said
Jonathan D. Crossman, a survivor of the accident and president of
Shell Taiwan Ltd., a subsidiary of the British company.
   Crossman and his 7-year-old daughter, Nicola, was rescued by
boats that rushed to the scene but his wife, Julia, 40, and a son,
Robert, 6, were missing, Shell official Tseng Tung-shin said.
   Rescuers said a baby was among a handful of people rescued from
a cabin with windows that were fixed shut and could not be opened.
   But Crossman said 10 bodies, including three or four children,
were recovered from the closed cabin.
   Sobbing relatives of the Taiwanese victims and many of the
survivors burned paper money in a traditional offering to the dead
at a tent set up near the dock, where investigators were examining
the recovered bodies.
   Crossman said the vessel was chartered by the oil company for a
weekend cruise for employees on the lake in Nantou, 165 miles
southwest of the capital Taipei.
   He said the boat suddenly overturned as it was making a left
turn about 50 yards from shore and he was tossed overboard from an
upper deck.
   Newspapers quoted survivors as saying strong winds overturned
the boat.
   Police arrested boat owner Hsu Ching-hsin on suspicion of
unintentional manslaughter.
   They said the boat lacked a commercial license to operate on the
lake and carried more than its 60-person capacity when the accident
occurred at 9:30 p.m. Saturday, the eve of the Chinese Valentine
Day festival in which moon-gazing is a traditional part of the
celebrations.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0035 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 1535EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Gulf-Kerrey 2ndLdWritethru a0712 08-26 0435</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Kerrey, 2nd Ld Writethru, a0712,430</SECOND>
<HEAD>Nebraska Senator Says No Loss Of Life For Cheap Oil</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: CORRECTS spelling of Kerrey in slug and throughout copy</NOTE>
<HEAD>With AM-US-Gulf, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By H. JOSEF HEBERT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Declaring that young Americans shouldn't die
in battle just to keep gasoline prices low, Sen. Bob Kerrey on
Sunday said the U.S. should abandon the notion of cheap oil.
   The Nebraska Democrat, a Vietnam veteran and Congressional Medal
Of Honor recipient, said he supported President Bush's decision to
send troops to the Persian Gulf, but only as a means of preventing
an Iraqi invasion of Saudi Arabia.
   ``I question the response that says that we're going to go there
and have our young people die so that we can have cheap oil here at
home,'' Kerrey said in an appearance on NBC-TV's ``Meet the Press.''
   ``The only justification that I find that is legitimate is that
... we're the only nation that could move quick enough to prevent
an invasion of Saudi Arabia.''
   Congressional Democrats have generally supported Bush during the
Middle East crisis, although there has been some grumbling that the
president should clarify his long-term objectives in the Persian
Gulf region.
   American troops were sent to the area after Iraqi forces easily
conquered Kuwait in an Aug. 2 invasion. Iraq annexed the oil-rich
emirate six days later.
   Congressional leaders have asked for a White House briefing next
Tuesday on the Middle East developments.
   Like most members of Congress, which has been recessed in
August, Kerrey has been in his home while the tense situation in
the Persian Gulf has unfolded. He expressed some frustration that
Bush had not provided lawmakers with more details about the
administration's intentions in the gulf region.
   ``We aren't, it seems to me, being provided a sufficient amount
of information to really engage meaningfully in a debate about
whether or not this (U.S. deployment of military forces) is
appropriate,'' said Kerrey, who is not among the congressional
leadership and knew nothing of Tuesday's planned briefing.
   ``I know from reading the newspapers that it's hot in the desert
and the chow is bad,'' he added.
   Kerrey suggested that American demand for cheap oil contributed
to Iraqi President Saddam Hussein's rise to power in the Middle
East.
   ``We in general have been blinded by money ... and as a
consequence we put into place policy that encouraged Hussein to
become extremely strong,'' he said.
   Kerrey said Americans are being ``very tolerant of higher oil
prices' that have resulted from the gulf tensions, ``even though
they are grumbling a bit about it.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0036 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 1554EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>d a AM-EpilepticFatality     08-26 0266</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Epileptic Fatality,0278</SECOND>
<HEAD>Epileptic Charged In Accident That Killed Boy</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WEST MIFFLIN, Pa. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A man whose driver's license was taken
away because he has epilepsy was charged with homicide after he
suffered a seizure while driving and struck and killed a 7-year-old
boy, authorities said.
   James Cheatham, 23, of Hazelwood was ordered Friday to stand
trial in the Aug. 3 death of Ryan Maszle in West Mifflin.
   At a hearing Friday, the arresting officer, Joseph Sotak, said
he initially suspected Cheatham was under the influence of drugs or
alcohol because Cheatham said nothing after the accident and could
barely walk.
   ``I had to practically carry him over to my police car,'' he
said.
   About 15 minutes after the accident, however, Cheatham recovered
from his seizure.
   After the hearing in Allegheny County Court, Cheatham was
charged with involuntary manslaughter and homicide by vehicle.
   Cheatham's attorney argued that because his client was suffering
a seizure at the time, he could not have formed the intent to harm
and therefore the charges were unfounded.
   Ryan was sitting on a fence with his sister and cousin when the
car struck him.
   ``The car came speeding down the road. I happened to look up the
road and said, `My God!' and the next thing I knew, the kids
flew,'' said his grandmother, Ada Sarvor. ``I watched until the car
hit the fence. It happened so fast.''
   Cheatham also was charged with aggravated assault, reckless
endangerment, driving under suspension, reckless driving and
carrying a firearm without a license. Cheatham lost his driver's
license last year because of his condition.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0037 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 1551EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-Waldheim     08-26 0541</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Waldheim,0559</SECOND>
<HEAD>Waldheim Praised at Home, Rebuffed Abroad for Iraq Mission</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf Rdp, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARK PORUBCANSKY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>VIENNA, Austria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Austrian President Kurt Waldheim, who has
spent much of the past four years in the shadow of his World War II
record, won warm praise here Sunday for his mission to Iraq that
freed about 100 countrymen.
   But he was reprimanded outside Austria for breaking the
isolation the Western world imposed on Iraq after it invaded and
annexed Kuwait.
   Waldheim, in an interview Sunday, insisted he did not break with
the West's solidarity against Iraqi President Saddam Hussein.
   Waldheim returned home early Sunday with the Austrians, who were
among the thousands of foreigners stranded in Iraq because of the
Persian Gulf crisis. He was the first Western leader to meet with
Saddam since the Iraqi president sent his army into Kuwait on Aug.
2.
   ``Waldheim took his greatest risk of this job and probably of
his entire career, and he won,'' said the mass daily Kurier.
   He and the Austrian hostages were greeted at the airport by
family and well-wishers, some of whom held signs saying, ``Bravo
Waldheim.''
   Waldheim, a former U.N. secretary-general, has spent the four
years of his presidency as a pariah in world politics and an
embarrassment to many of his countrymen because of his wartime
record.
   He is barred from entering the United States because of charges
that he knew about or participated in war crimes as a German army
intelligence officer in the Balkans during the war.
   Waldheim has acknowledged concealing his past, but denies any
wrongdoing.
   His term in the largely ceremonial Austrian presidency runs
until 1992, and he has not indicated yet whether he intends to run
again.
   Austrian Chancellor Franz Vranitzky, who reportedly was
skeptical when the visit was announced last Thursday, told the
national radio that ``the most important point is that we are
enthusiastic of having all our Austrians out of the region.''
   Outside Austria, however, officials and the media were less
admiring.
   ``I think one can sympathize with the leader of a country
wanting to get his own citizens out,'' U.S. national security
adviser Brent Scowcroft said on ABC-TV's ``This Week With David
Brinkley.''
   However, he added, ``It would have been much more helpful if he
had pleaded for the tens or hundreds of thousands of foreigners who
find themselves trapped inside Kuwait and Iraq.''
   Asked if he wished Waldheim had not gone to Iraq, Scowcroft
responded, ``I think he could have done more.''
   Italian Foreign Minister Gianni De Michelis, speaking to
reporters in Venice, expressed his ``reserve and perplexity'' about
the visit.
   Italy's La Stampa, which comes out in Turin, carried an article
headlined ``A gift to Waldheim: 76 hostages,'' and subheaded ``His
visit breaks Iraqi isolation.''
   Waldheim, in a Sunday interview with British Broadcasting Corp.
said he realized before his trip that some people would criticize
his effort, but ``I do not consider that justified.
   ``I made crystal clear that we stick to Western solidarity, that
we implement all the resolutions which the Security Council has
adopted and that this, my humanitarian mission, does not in any way
mean that we are trying to break out of that Western solidarity,''
Waldheim said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0038 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 1606EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Gulf-PressPool     08-26 0104</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Press Pool,100</SECOND>
<HEAD>`Open' Saudi Coverage Leads to Disbanded Press Pool</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Pentagon disbanded its Persian Gulf news
media pool Sunday, saying it is not needed because open coverage is
now being permitted.
   ``The decision by the government of Saudi Arabia to allow
reporters from the U.S. and other countries to cover the military
operation in the Gulf region makes it unnecessary to continue the
National Media Pool,'' the Defense Department said.
   The 17-member pool left Washington Aug. 12 and has been filing
press and broadcast reports and transmitting still photographs
daily since its arrival in Saudi Arabia Aug. 13.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0039 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 1629EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ScholarsforFreedom     08-26 0348</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Scholars for Freedom,0358</SECOND>
<HEAD>University Initiates Scholarships for Eastern Europeans</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CLIFF EDWARDS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CHICAGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A small liberal arts college is giving two
Eastern Europeans a taste of U.S. capitalism and competition under
its Scholars for Freedom program.
   ``We hope to show them the ways of a market economy and instruct
them in the ways of a democratic and open system,'' said Gilbert
Ghez, a Roosevelt University business professor who runs the
program.
   Peter Leidl, 21, of Czechoslovakia will take undergraduate
business courses at the university, and Laszlo Pribusz, 24, of
Hungary will study graduate computer science, Ghez said.
   Many U.S. universities say they can't offer specific financial
aid to Eastern Europeans, who are taking advantage of freedoms
recently won in their own countries by seeking to study in the
United States.
   But Roosevelt _ working with Scandinavian Airlines,
multinational corporations and private groups _ is offering two
students $20,000 in full tuition, room and board for the 1990-91
school year as well as round-trip air fare.
   Competition for the scholarships was keen. About 500 people
applied before the list was weeded down to 50 students, who were
interviewed by professors at Roosevelt, a school with about 6,000
students.
   The two students chosen are scheduled to arrive at O'Hare
International Airport on Tuesday.
   They will study problems faced by Czechoslovakia, Hungary,
Poland and Romania alike: turning from planned to market economies
and dealing with rampant shortages and inflation.
   The Scholars for Freedom program hopes to train students in
capitalism and return them home to use those skills, Mark
Holtzblatt, a Roosevelt professor of science and international
business.
   While the university so far has been able to offer students just
one free year of study, Ghez said even that experience should prove
valuable to Eastern governments.
   ``I'm not saying they'll be CEOs right away, but they will be
able to take the skills they've learned here in America and use
them over there,'' he said.
   The university hopes to offer scholarships to as many as 20
people for the program's second year, he added.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0040 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 1632EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Ireland-Hostage     08-26 0401</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Ireland-Hostage,0415</SECOND>
<HEAD>Keenan Didn't Want Freedom Without Fellow Hostage, Doctor Says</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By EDITH M. LEDERER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DUBLIN, Ireland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Freed Irish hostage Brian Keenan didn't
want to be released unless fellow prisoner John McCarthy was also
set free by their Lebanese captors, one of Keenan's doctors said
Sunday.
   ``He said `no,' he would not go without John McCarthy,'' Dr.
Sean Blake said a day after Keenan arrived in Dublin. ``But in the
end, he had no option. They just told him, `we want you out.' ''
   Blake is one of the doctors tending Keenan at Mater hospital in
Dublin, where he was taken for a checkup after his flight home from
Syria aboard a government jet. Keenan was freed Friday and turned
over to Irish officials in Syria a day later.
   Keenan, a 39-year-old Belfast teacher, spent his first full day
back in Ireland making phone calls from the hospital to the
families of McCarthy and other hostages he left behind in Lebanon.
   Keenan said Saturday that he saw American hostages Terry
Anderson and Thomas Sutherland during his captivity, and that they
were in good spirits.
   He also said he saw McCarthy, with whom he spent much of his
four years and four months in captivity, on Thursday and that the
33-year-old British journalist was well.
   American former hostage Frank Reed, who spent about three years
in the same room or house as Keenan and McCarthy, greeted the Irish
teacher at Dublin airport Saturday night.
   Reed was released April 30, eight days after fellow U.S. hostage
Robert Polhill was freed. Two Swiss Red Cross workers, Emanuel
Christen and Elio Erriquez, were freed earlier this month.
   Six Americans, four Britons, two West Germans and an Italian are
still believed held by extremist Moslems in Lebanon.
   Anderson, 42, chief Middle East correspondent for The Associated
Press, was kidnapped March 16, 1985 and is the longest-held.
   Blake, a cardiologist, said Keenan was somewhat malnourished and
unfit from lack of physical activity. But otherwise, he appeared
``very well.''
   Sister Gemma Byrne, the hospital's chief executive, said Keenan
had lost 42 pounds in captivity and ``must have a complete rest.''
   ``His first reaction on going into his room was it was the first
bed he had seen in 4{ years,'' she said.
   Dr. Richard Firth, an endocrinologist who examined Keenan, said
his general condition was ``excellent'' though test results were
not in.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0041 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 1637EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Romania     08-26 0290</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Romania,0301</SECOND>
<HEAD>Demonstrators Reoccupy Central Square After Clash</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BUCHAREST, Romania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   About 300 anti-government
demonstrators occupied a central square in the capital for a fifth
day Sunday, a day after 48 people were arrested and two reportedly
hurt in a clash with police.
   The latest arrests brought to 80 the number of people detained
in and around the square in the last week, police said Sunday in a
communique.
   On Saturday night, a clash erupted after police moved in, armed
with clubs and shields. At least two people were reported
hospitalized.
   The police communique called on the public to support the
authorities and ``disassociate themselves from the destabilizing
demonstrations of ill-intentioned elements, which can create
dangerous tensions.''
   On Sunday, demonstrators at the square shouted slogans demanding
the resignation of President Ion Iliescu.
   Critics accuse Iliescu and his associates, who won free
elections earlier this year, of keeping many of the policies of the
authoritarian Communist leader Nicolae Ceausescu. Ceausescu and his
wife Elena were ousted and executed in December's popular uprising.
   The demonstrators at University Square, located at the main
intersection on the capital's fashionable Balcescu Boulevard,
disrupted traffic and forced motorists to use side streets.
   Saturday evening's violence broke out when about 2,000 riot
police, military police and firefighters arrived to clear the area.
They were greeted by showers of rocks, bottles and firebombs from
the hundreds of angry demonstrators.
   The confrontations spread to nearby streets, where windows were
broken and several fires broke out.
   The square was the site of a 53-day anti-government
demonstration and traffic blockade earlier this summer organized by
students and activists.
   This week's rallies appeared to be motivated by the
deteriorating economy and food and energy shortages. It attracted
mostly lower-income workers.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0042 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 1641EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-Embassies 1stLd-Writethru a0702 08-26 0647</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Embassies, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0702,0664</SECOND>
<HEAD>Iraq Keeps Up Pressure On Embassies In Kuwait</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf Rdp, Bjt</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS thruout to UPDATE with State Department saying two more
U.S. citizens detained in Kuwait. No pickup.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By ALEX EFTY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NICOSIA, Cyprus (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Defiant diplomats in Kuwait held out for
a second day Sunday, with some embassies guarded by Iraqi troops
and lacking electricity, water and telephone service.
   There were no reports that the Iraqis, who had ordered all
embassies closed by Friday, were using force against the diplomats.
However, the United States, Britain and France all reported Sunday
that more of their citizens in Kuwait had been rounded up.
   One of the reasons the embassies defied the Iraqi order to close
down was that they wanted to try to help their citizens trapped in
the occupied emirate. According to reports reaching foreign
ministries in Europe and elsewhere, the Iraqis cut off electricity
and other utilities Saturday at some missions, including the U.S.
Embassy, after the diplomats refused to shut down.
   Iraq, which invaded Kuwait Aug. 2 and annexed it six days later,
says Kuwait is now part of Iraq and thus needs no embassies.
   Reports Sunday said the U.S., British, French, Hungarian and
Danish embassies were among those surrounded by troops.
   In other developments:
   _ The British Foreign Office said contact was still possible
with the four diplomats holed up in the British mission. Some other
governments said diplomats at their embassies were free to come and
go.
   _ West Germany's Foreign Ministry said its embassy's water and
electricity were cut off Sunday. The ministry said it still has
contact with the embassy, and West German diplomats were working to
set up radio communication for the French embassy, which has lost
contact with Paris.
   _ The French Embassy in Kuwait is without water and electricity
and telephone communication has been severed, West German officials
said. The East German Embassy also was without water and
electricity.
   _ Water and power to Canada's embassy has also been cut,
Canada's External Affairs department said Sunday, and troops who
had surrounded the embassy Friday moved about 100 yards away. The
department said the mission was making regular telephone contact
with Canadians stranded in Kuwait.
   _ The Japanese Foreign Ministry said Sunday several soldiers
were patrolling near its embassy, and water and electricity
remained cut off.
   _ Denmark said electricity at its embassy was cut Sunday and
shortwave radio contact had been lost. Only the Danish ambassador
remains at the embassy, which has been surrounded by Iraqi troops.
   The United States, the 12 European Community states and many
other countries have refused to close their Kuwait embassies,
saying the closing order violated international law.
   They say going along with the Iraqi order to close could be
construed as recognition of the annexation.
   Meanwhile, the State Department said Sunday it had been informed
that two additional Americans have been taken into custody by Iraqi
troops.
   Department spokeswoman Anita Stockman said the information was
relayed to the U.S. Embassy in Kuwait by telephone. Although
officials had no way of confirming the information, she said
embassy personnel had reason to believe it was accurate. She had no
additional details about those arrested.
   Britain's Foreign Office said Sunday that Iraqi troops rounded
up eight more Britons in Kuwait City. It said the eight adults,
seized Saturday, were being held at a civilian establishment in
Kuwait City, bringing to 147 the number of Britons rounded up since
the invasion.
   And France's Foreign Ministry said Iraqi troops have forced
eight more French, including two women and two children, from their
homes in Kuwait. They were taken to a hotel where other French
citizens rounded up earlier were staying, the ministry said.
   About 60 of the approximately 270 French citiziens who were in
Kuwait at the time of Iraq's Aug. 2 invasion have been detained.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0043 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 1644EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SriLanka     08-26 0544</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Sri Lanka,0559</SECOND>
<HEAD>Goverment Gains Ground in Advance Toward Strategic Fort</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Barefoot Guerrillas, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PATRICK CRUEZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>COLOMBO, Sri Lanka (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The government said Sunday its troops
overran a rebel-held island and killed more than 80 Tamil
guerrillas in an advance toward a strategic northeast fort under
siege by the insurgents.
   Military officials in Colombo say government troops are now
within about two miles of the 17th-century Jaffna Fort, where about
250 policemen and soldiers have been trapped for 10 weeks.
   Vowing to crush the Tamil Tiger rebels once and for all, the
government has staked its prestige on breaking the siege of the
fort, the Sinhalese-controlled government's only outpost in
Tamil-dominated Jaffna town 185 miles northeast of Colombo.
   There was no confirmation of the government claim that its
forces captured Mandativu Island after a fierce three-hour battle
Saturday night.
   Conventional communications to the Jaffna Peninsula were cut
after June 11, when the Tigers broke a 13-month-old cease-fire with
the government. The combatants use radios to communicate with
colleagues outside the peninsula.
   The last word from the Tigers was Friday when a guerrilla
spokesman in Geneva acknowledged government forces were trying to
advance from Kayts Island to Mandativu Island. Government troops
landed on Kayts Island on Wednesday, disloging Tamil fighters.
   The islands are connected by a causeway that continues across
the Jaffna lagoon and ends just beside Jaffna Fort. But the
causeway is heavily mined, the military officials said.
   In the seven years since militants from the Tamil minority
revolted against Sinhalese rule, the Tigers have proved
devastatingly effective at making and planting mines.
   Military officials in Colombo, who under briefing rules cannot
be identified, claimed 84 Tigers and only two government soldiers
were killed in the battle for Mandativu Island.
   They said advancing troops found the bodies of 28 rebels on
Mandativu and killed 16 others who tried to swim to safety. Another
40 Tigers were killed in strafing from a helicopter gunship as they
tried to reach the mainland, the officials said.
   The government says it now expects to reach Jaffna Fort by
Monday.
   Since launching its latest offensive against the Tigers, the
government says it has stepped up aerial attacks on rebel positions
around the star-shaped fort, a legacy of Portuguese, Dutch and
British colonial rule on this island off the southern tip of India.
   The Tigers have not acknowledged any losses but have accused the
government of killing more than 300 Tamil civilians in bombing and
strafing raids and ground fire on the Jaffna Peninsula, where
850,000 people live.
   The government says 5,000 people have been killed since June 11,
when the Tigers broke the cease-fire in northern and eastern Sri
Lanka where most Tamils live. That brings to at least 14,000 the
total number of victims of the 7-year-old Tamil insurrection.
   Tamils make up 18 percent of the Indian Ocean island's 16
million people. They have long complained that the Sinhalese
majority discriminates against them in the jobs, education and use
of the Sinhala language. Militants sought to create a separate
homeland for Tamils in the northeast.
   Sinhalese, who account for 75 percent of the Sri Lankan
population, have dominated politics and the military since this
country gained independence from Britain in 1949.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0044 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 1647EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Colombia     08-26 0472</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Colombia,0487</SECOND>
<HEAD>Europe Reportedly Becoming Drug Mafia's Main Cocaine Market</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By STAN YARBRO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOGOTA, Colombia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Colombian drug cartels and the Mafia are
building a cocaine empire in Western European countries, which have
replaced the United States as the biggest market for the drug, a
Bogota newspaper reported Sunday.
   ``Consumption in Spain, Holland and Italy is leaving the North
American market behind,'' said Bogota's El Tiempo newspaper, citing
a joint report by the international police organization Interpol
and the Colombian intelligence police, known as the DAS.
   The Bogota offices of both Interpol and the DAS were closed
Sunday, and no one could be reached for comment.
   The European market will continue to grow because of the Italian
Mafia's intention to preserve its distribution monopoly and the
Colombian cartel's desire to capture part of the market, according
to the study.
   It said the cartel and the Mafia are likely to form agreements
to flood the market with cocaine.
   El Tiempo quoted the report as saying the dramatic growth of the
cocaine market in Western Europe is fueled by high prices.
   The drug is sold in Europe for between $27,500 and $115,000 a
kilogram, compared to between $10,000 and $20,000 in the United
States, according to the document. A kilogram is 2.2 pounds.
   Profits from the European business are enormous, the report
added, because distributors receive cocaine that is 90 to 94
percent pure and sell a product that is only 45 percent pure.
   The report cited Spain as the principal receiver of cocaine from
Latin America and the main trafficking center for drug destined for
the European markets.
   The report also said cocaine laboratories have been discovered
in Spain as well as in France and Italy. Cocaine processing has
traditionally been confined to Colombia, but the country's war
against the cartels and its crackdown on imports of processing
chemicals have reportedly forced drug bosses to move some of their
operations elsewhere.
   ``Although for some the detection of these (European) processing
centers has not been alarming, the facilities certainly are
providing a supply of hundreds of kilograms,'' the report said.
   The enormous expansion of the cocaine business, combined with
the participation of other criminal organizations, has reduced the
importance of the Colombian drug barons, especially the Medellin
cartel.
   ``The Medellin cartel has begun to lose part of its key members
and along with them part of the power they exercised over world
distribution networks,'' said the police report.
   It estimated that the cartel's share of the world cocaine market
has been reduced from 75 percent to 40 percent.
   In the past eight months, several key cartel figures have been
killed in shootouts with Colombian authorities. The organization's
leader, Pablo Escobar, the target of a manhunt by police, is in
hiding and reportedly unable to run the cartel's day-to-day
operations.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0045 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 1748EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-China     08-26 0442</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-China,0458</SECOND>
<HEAD>Legislative Committee Agenda Includes Proposed Press Law</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HONG KONG (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   China is preparing to enact a law to prevent
``the abuse of press freedom'' and ensure that the media support
the Communist Party, Hong Kong newspapers reported Sunday.
   The standing committee of China's legislature, the National
People's Congress, was to meet starting Tuesday, said two
pro-Beijing papers and one independent daily.
   Zhang Husheng, spokesman for the standing committee, was quoted
as saying no major personnel changes in the leadership were
expected during the 10-day meeting in Beijing.
   The reports said Premier Li Peng would address the standing
committee on ``recent international events,'' possibly the current
crisis in the Middle East. China has generally supported the West
during the crisis.
   Beijing says it opposes the use of military force to enforce the
blockade on Iraq although it endorsed a U.N. Security Council
resolution allowing such force to be used.
   Other reports will concern China's fragile economy and the
status of scientific research in the country, the pro-Beijing
papers, Ta Kung Pao and Wen Wei Po, and the independent Ming Pao
said.
   The newspapers said the standing committee, which controls the
rubber-stamp legislature, will also debate drafts of laws on
copyrights, railroads, the signing of treaties and the export of
labor.
   Spokesman Zhang was quoted by the papers as saying a press law,
a publishing law and a maritime commerce law would be enacted soon.
   China's legislature has been debating a press law since 1984 and
its contents have changed with the political winds.
   Papers quoted Wang Qianghua, who heads a team drafting the law,
as saying the current version mandates that the press uphold the
leadership of the Communist Party, Marxist thought and socialism.
   ``The law also protects against the abuse of press freedom,'' he
said.
   Beijing Mayor Chen Xitong will also report on the status of the
Asian Games, set to begin in September. Lack of money, the crisis
in the Middle East and apparent mismanagement have hurt China's
preparations for the games.
   Many analysts say the games are important to China's attempts to
restore its international image following the bloody June 1989
crackdown on the pro-democracy movement.
   There is speculation in Hong Kong that more changes in China's
government and Communist Party will come starting within the next
few months and extending into the first half of next year.
   Since the June crackdown, China has undergone a large-scale
military and political shake-up as conservative and relatively
reform-minded groups compete for power.
   So far, 11 provinces have lost top officials, such as provincial
party secretaries or provincial chiefs. Six out of the seven
military regions have new commanders.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0046 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 1758EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-IraqiMilitia     08-26 0286</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Iraqi Militia,0292</SECOND>
<HEAD>Iraq Claims 5 Million Join People's Militia</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf Rdp, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MONA ZIADE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NICOSIA, Cyprus (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Iraqi officials claim 5 million people
have volunteered for a militia known as the Popular Army to back up
the army in any Persian Gulf showdown, according to reports from
Baghdad on Sunday.
   Every residential neighborhood in Baghdad now has a recruiting
center for what is billed there as the Arabs' war against ``foreign
invaders.''
   The move was seen as part of an effort by Iraqi President Saddam
Hussein to mobilize Iraq's 17 million people following his Aug. 2
invasion of oil-rich Kuwait.
   It is unlikely that any of the volunteers will be used to fight
the Americans and other countries deploying forces in neighboring
Saudi Arabia. But they could help free regular troops in Iraq's 1
million-member armed forces to man front-line positions.
   Iraq's state-run television has shown film of troops handing out
automatic weapons to men in civilian clothes in Baghdad's streets
in recent days.
   Young men and women line up in the scorching summer heat for
hours to enlist in the Popular Army, sources in the Iraqi capital
reported. They spoke on condition of anonymity.
   ``We now have 5 million people under arms in the Popular Army,''
Information Minister Latif Nassayif Jassim told reporters in
Baghdad on Sunday. One Baghdad volunteer said within days, those
who sign up are sent to training centers, most of them outside the
city, where they receive basic training on light weapons and are
handed AK-47 automatic rifles.
   Those with good credentials, usually members or loyal supporters
of the ruling Baath Party, are also given pistols or assigned to
light Soviet-designed anti-aircraft guns.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0047 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 1759EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Czechoslovakia-Rally     08-26 0364</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Czechoslovakia-Rally,0376</SECOND>
<HEAD>Slovak Rally Ends on Separatist Note</HEAD>
<DATELINE>RUZOMBEROK, Czechoslovakia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Thousands of Slovaks honored
their former leader Sunday in a rally that ended with a strong call
for independence.
   The two-day memorial to Andrej Hlinka included a seminar on his
life, a Mass and the political rally with about 20 speakers.
   Hlinka was the leader of the Slovak National Party, the
strongest political force in Slovakia. He opposed the Czechoslovak
national government and after his death in 1938, his party
collaborated with Hitler within the Slovak puppet state.
   He was accused of both separatism and fascism and his name was
taboo in official history books under Communist rule.
   The newly found freedom that came with Czechoslovakia's peaceful
revolution last year is seen by many Slovaks not only as an
opportunity to reassess the country's history, but also a good time
to demand full independence.
   Slovakia, the country's eastern part, contains roughly one-third
of Czechoslovakia's 15.5 million people. Partly in answer to
Slovaks' reawakening ethnic feelings, Czechoslovakia officially was
renamed the Czech and Slovak Federative Republic on April 20.
   Before independent Czechoslovakia was founded by President Tomas
Garrigue Masaryk in 1918, Slovakia was dominated by Hungarians for
centuries. The Czech lands lived under strong German influence
within the Austro-Hungarian empire.
   ``Hlinka once said the 1,200-year-long marriage with the
Hungarians failed, and I say the 72-year old marriage with the
Czechs failed as well,'' Vitezoslav Moric, leader of the Slovak
National Party told the crowd of several thousand people Sunday.
   The Slovak National Party won 16 seats in the country's 300-seat
Parliament in June elections, making it the fourth-strongest in
Slovakia. But its popularity has been rising since.
   Jan Carnogursky, leader of the Christian Democratic Movement,
the second-strongest political force in Slovakia, called for
keeping Czechoslovakia together. He was booed off the stage.
   Participants in the rally adopted a demand that the Slovak
Parliament and government ``take necessary measures to make
Slovakia a sovereign state.''
   It also called for making the Slovak language the only official
language. Now, both the Czech and Slovak language are official
throughout the country.
   The memorandum also called for a constitutional amendment giving
Slovakia the right to secede.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0048 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 1818EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Bush 1stLd-Writethru a0708 08-26 0582</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bush, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0708,520</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush Confers Via Telephone With Mubarak And Thatcher</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: Top three grafs new with calls to Mubarak and Thatcher;
pickup 2nd prv, ``The president xxx</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By RITA BEAMISH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>KENNEBUNKPORT, Maine (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush telephoned Egyptian
President Hosni Mubarak and British Prime Minister Margaret
Thatcher on Sunday to discuss the Persian Gulf situation, White
House aides said.
   They did not release any information as to the substance of the
conversations.
   In addition to the telephone consultations with foreign leaders
and briefings from aides on developments in the Middle East, Bush
spent a sun-drenched Sunday with family members, attending church
services and playing tennis and golf.
   The president, in the third week of a vacation at his seaside
family home, received a briefing from his national security
adviser, Brent Scowcroft, early in the morning before heading off
to church.
   He attended an annual breakfast for the vestrymen of St. Ann's
Episcopal Church. Bush is an elder in the church and when he is in
town he generally attends St. Ann's, which is just up the road from
his home on Walker's Point.
   Bush was joined by his wife, Barbara; mother, Dorothy Walker
Bush; son, Jeb; and assorted grandchildren for services at St.
Ann's later in the morning.
   Bush waved off reporters' attempts to question him about
developments in the Persian Gulf. He returned to Walker's Point for
some tennis before an afternoon golf game.
   Bush left the policy comments to Scowcroft, who gave an ABC-TV
interview and also took questions from a handful of reporters.
   Scowcroft said the Bush administration is comfortable with its
policy on Iraq, as thousands of U.S. troops dig in to face Iraqi
President Saddam Hussein on land and sea if necessary.
   He said the administration was amenable to talks that appear in
the offing between U.N. Secretary General Javier Perez de Cuellar
and Iraqi officials.
   ``We wouldn't have any problem with that,'' Scowcroft said.
   He also said the United States has no problem entering talks
with the Iraqi leader, but he maintained the same hard-line
position on conditions for such talks: Saddam must withdraw his
forces from Kuwait and allow the emir of Kuwait to return to power.
   ``You have to make a distinction between being willing to talk
to him and changing the conditions under which we're operating,''
Scowcroft said. ``That we're not willing to do.''
   Bush's recreation-filled Sunday launched a week in which he
planned to devote energies to the Middle East, including a
congressional briefing Tuesday in Washington.
   Bush planned to consult Monday with Canadian Prime Minister
Brian Mulroney, who was bringing his family to Walker's Point for
an overnight stay. Canada is among the 22 nations providing forces
to the multinational effort in the Persian Gulf.
   After Mulroney's departure, Bush was to fly to Washington to
fill in key members of Congress on his Persian Gulf strategy.
   While administration officials say they have been in frequent
contact with members of Congress since Iraq's Aug. 2 invasion of
Kuwait, this would be the first time Bush has held such a
face-to-face session with lawmakers on the gulf crisis.
   Bush's press secretary, Marlin Fitzwater, said several members
of Congress had requested the briefing, even though Congress still
is in recess.
   Fitzwater told reporters that Mulroney ``has many contacts in
the Arab world, and discussions he would also like to explore.''
   Mulroney, a frequent confidant of Bush, and his family also
visited the Bushes in Kennebunkport last summer.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0049 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 1819EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Soviet-KGB     08-26 0508</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-KGB,0523</SECOND>
<HEAD>KGB Official Says Spy Agency's Mission is Protecting Perestroika</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ALAN COOPERMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A top KGB official Sunday disclosed the espionage
arrests of some high-ranking Soviet officials in recent years and
paid grudging tribute to the CIA as a crafty and determined
adversary.
   In the interview in the Communist Party newspaper Pravda, the
KGB official, Victor F. Grushko, also said the duty of the
once-feared secret police is to protect perestroika, Mikhail S.
Gorbachev's policy of political and economic reform.
   Interviews with top KGB officials were once extremely rare, but
they have been appearing in print and even on television recently
as part of a campaign to revamp the spy agency's image.
   These days, the KGB emphasizes its role in fighting corruption
and foreign intelligence agencies. It has been playing down its
history of terrorizing Soviet dissidents, tapping telephones and
carrying out the late dictator Josef Stalin's purges.
   Grushko said that since 1985, the KGB had arrested more than 30
``extremely dangerous'' spies. Virtually all were tried and shot,
he said.
   Those arrested included Maj. Gen. Polyakov, a former top officer
in the counterintelligence department of the Soviet General Staff,
he said. Polyakov, whose first name was not given, would have been
one of the highest-ranking Soviet spies in history.
   Grushko _ head of the KGB's second chief directorate, which is
responsible for counterintelligence _ said Polyakov had ``handed
over important information on the activities of our military
intelligence.''
   The KGB official boasted that the Soviet spy agency has stopped
more than 120 attempts to relay secrets to Western intelligence
services in the past five years.
   Other than Polyakov, other alleged spies identified by Grushko
were A.G. Tolkachev, an engineer in the Radio Industry Ministry; a
KGB agent identified only as Vorontsov; and a scientific worker at
the Institute of the U.S.A. and Canada identified only as Potashov.
   The article did not provide any details on their arrests or what
they were alleged to have done.
   Jeffrey T. Richelson, an American who has written about the KGB,
said in a telephone interview from Washington that Tolkachev's
arrest and execution previously have been made public, but that the
other cases may be coming to light for the first time.
   Richelson, author of ``Sword and Shield,'' a 1986 book about
Soviet intelligence operations, said Polyakov may have been a CIA
source previously known by the code name ``Donald.''
   The author also said he believed that Potashov had not
previously been named, although it was known that there had been an
espionage case at the U.S.A. and Canada Institute, a leading
research center in Moscow.
   In the interview, Grushko also discussed the operations of CIA
agents in Moscow, describing the tools of their trade, including
miniature shortwave radio transmitters, tiny cameras, secret
message containers that look like pebbles, invisible ink and an
array of disguises.
   ``For example, an attache of the American Embassy _ a man with a
fairly large build _ went on one operation artfully dressed in
women's clothing,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0050 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 1820EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--Germany-Graves     08-26 0155</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Germany-Graves,0159</SECOND>
<HEAD>Graves in West German Jewish Cemetery Desecrated</HEAD>
<DATELINE>FREIBURG, West Germany (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Vandals overturned gravestones and
painted slogans and swastikas in a Jewish cemetery, a police
spokesman said Sunday.
   The vandalizing of the cemetery in the southwestern town of
Freiburg was the fourth such incident in a month in the West German
state of Baden-Wuerttemberg.
   Werner Erlach, a police spokesman in Freiburg, said the
vandalism occurred overnight Saturday and was discovered by
passersby on Sunday. He said police had no suspects.
   In similar incidents in recent weeks, 177 gravestones were
overturned and damaged in the small town of Ihringen, about 12
miles from Freiburg. Slogans were also painted in Jewish cemeteries
in Tuebingen and Stuttgart, two other towns in Baden-Wuerttemberg,
Erlach said. No one was caught.
   In recent months, an outbreak of such desecrations in Jewish
cemeteries in West Germany, France and other countries has raised
fears of a wave of anti-Semitism.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0051 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 1830EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Cambodia     08-26 0385</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Cambodia,0398</SECOND>
<HEAD>Guerrillas Claim To Repulse Government Offensive in Cambodia</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BANGKOK, Thailand (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Cambodian guerrillas Sunday claimed
they repulsed a large-scale offensive by that country's Communist
government.
   Troops backed by multiple rocket launchers and Soviet-made T54
tanks struck guerrilla defense lines early Saturday morning, said a
statement from Ok Serei Sopheak, a spokesman for the Khmer People's
National Liberation Front.
   ``The front lines remain stable but still tense,'' said the
statement from Ok Serei Sopheak, who had generally proved reliable
in the past.
   The non-communist liberation front, led by former Cambodian
Prime Minister Son Sann, is one of three guerrilla groups fighting
the government Vietnam installed after invading Cambodia in late
1978.
   The statement said the guerrillas repulsed troops who attacked
near Sisophon, a strategic crossroads town in Battambang province
and about 30 miles east of the Thai border.
   ``After two hours, enemy forces retreated back without any
success,'' it said. ``We maintain all our positions in the south.''
   Attacking government troops were also driven off near Svay Chek,
a town about 15 miles north of Sisophon, and Ta Vong, 17 miles
southeast of Thmar Puok, a district capital in western Cambodia.
   Peace talks between the government and the three-party guerrilla
coalition have been stalled by quarrels over who should rule
Cambodia in the period before a general election.
   The other rebel groups are non-communist followers of former
Cambodian head of state Prince Norodom Sihanouk and the Khmer
Rouge, a Communist group that has the most powerful insurgent army.
Under leader Pol Pot, the Khmer Rouge killed hundreds of thousands
of people when it ruled Cambodia from 1975 until Vietnam's invasion
ousted it.
   In an interview carried by the official Radio Hanoi on Saturday,
Vietnam's Foreign Minister Nguyen Co Thach said Cambodia was
capable of holding free elections as Nicaragua did recently.
   He reiterated that dissolution of the Vietnamese-installed
government before an election would only bring chaos and thus
facilitate a Khmer Rouge attempt to restore its brutal regime.
   ``The general elections in Nicaragua, all organized by the
existing administrations under the supervision of the United
Nations and foreign countries, were recognized by the world as
truly free, democratic and fair,'' Thach said. ``Obviously, the
same thing can be done in Cambodia.''
   A text of the Thach interview was seen Sunday in Bangkok.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0052 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 1753EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-WeatherpageWeather     08-26 0264</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Weatherpage Weather,0274</SECOND>
<HEAD>Thunderstorms Across Much of Nation</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Thunderstorms brought high winds and heavy rain to much of the
nation Sunday while especially hot weather continued in parts of
the Midwest and Texas.
   Hail the size of golf balls fell near Minnewaukan, Minn., and
one-inch hail hit Isabel, S.D., the National Weather Service
reported.
   Winds gusted to 100 mph near La Crosse, Wis. and to about 60 mph
at Mobridge, S.D., Rochester, Minn. and Deforest, Wis. There was
some storm damage in those states, the weather service said.
   Afternoon rainshowers and thunderstorms continued over lower
Michigan, southern Wisconsin and northern Illinois as well as
across western Arkansas and from western Montana into northern
Idaho.
   Rain reached over the Florida panhandle and along the coast
across Georgia, South Carolina, North Carolina and central Virginia.
   In Texas, Corpus Christi reached 101 degrees, a record high for
the date.
   It was 100 degrees in Lake Charles, La., also a record.
   Unseasonably hot weather extended over much of Kansas, and was
forecast to continue. The overnight low for Concordia, Kan. was 78
degrees, its warmest low for the date.
   Hot weather prevailed over much of the central and southern
Plains as well as most of the Mississippi Valley.
   In Alaska, a storm moved over the Chukchi Sea and spread rain
across the north part of the state.
   Temperatures around the nation at 3 p.m. EDT ranged from 51
degrees at Mount Shasta, Calif. to 103 degrees at Medicine Lodge,
Kan.
   Low temperature for the nation this morning was 31 degrees at
Gunnison, Colo.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0053 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 1836EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Obit-PintodeAndrade     08-26 0412</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Pinto de Andrade,0423</SECOND>
<HEAD>Angolan Revolution Leader Mario Pinto de Andrade Dies</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LISBON, Portugal (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Angolan writer and politician Mario
Pinto de Andrade, a pioneer in Angola's struggle against Portuguese
colonial rule, died Sunday in London after a long illness. He was
62.
   Although he dropped out of Angolan politics in the mid-1970s,
Pinto de Andrade remained an influential figure in the war-torn
southern African country.
   Pinto de Andrade became the first president of the Popular
Movement for the Liberation of Angola in 1960, just before the
Marxist group launched its 15-year guerrilla war to end Portuguese
colonial rule.
   In 1974, he split with the Popular Movement, which came to power
the following year when Angola became independent.
   Since 1975, Pinto de Andrade lived mainly in Guinea-Bissau. Both
the Popular Movement government and the U.S.-backed UNITA rebels
tried unsuccessfully to win his support in the continuing civil war
that followed Angolan independence.
   Recently, he worked with other Popular Movement veterans in an
effort to mediate the conflict. His brother Joaquim Pinto de
Andrade leads an independent human rights group in Angola.
   The nationalist's death came as delegations from the government
and UNITA, the National Union for the Total Independence of Angola,
arrived in Lisbon for talks aimed at reaching a cease-fire in the
15-year-old civil war.
   Pinto de Andrade was born in 1928 in the northern Angolan town
of Golungo Alto and attended high school in the capital, Luanda. He
studied classical philosophy at Lisbon University.
   In Lisbon in the 1950s, he worked with other African
nationalists from Portuguese-speaking Africa, including the poet
Agostinho Neto, who became Angola's first president, and Amilcar
Cabral, who led Guinea-Bissau's struggle for independence in the
1960s.
   They tried to promote African culture and nationalist ideas in
Portugal's five African colonies _ Angola, Mozambique,
Guinea-Bissau, Cape Verde and Sao Tome e Principe.
   Pinto de Andrade edited an anthology of Portuguese African
poetry that was published in 1969, which helped widen international
awareness of the culture and provided a focus for young African
intellectuals.
   After he split with the Popular Movement and left Angola in
1974, Pinto de Andrade worked for the government of
newly-independent Guinea-Bissau as general secretary of the
National Cultural Council.
   In 1980, he was appointed Guinea-Bissau's representative on the
Executive Council of UNESCO.
   His last book, a history of the nationalist movements in
Portuguese-speaking Africa, is due to be published soon.
   There was no immediate information on his survivors or funeral
arrangements.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0054 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 1837EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Obit-Roberts     08-26 0254</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Roberts,0261</SECOND>
<HEAD>Veteran Oklahoma City Journalist Dies at 67</HEAD>
<DATELINE>OKLAHOMA CITY, Okla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Stella Mae Roberts, a longtime
reporter with The Associated Press and the first woman to be
national secretary-treasurer of the Wire Service Guild, died at age
67 after a lengthy illness.
   An Oklahoma City funeral parlor said she died Saturday but did
not give an exact cause of death.
   Ms. Roberts joined the AP in Oklahoma City in 1945 and worked
there 31 years, much of that time in the Capitol bureau. After
retiring in 1976, she became public information director of the
Oklahoma Employment Security Commission.
   In 1964 Ms. Roberts was elected secretary-treasurer of Wire
Service Guild, Local 222 of The Newspaper Guild, representing 2,300
employees of the AP and United Press International. She held the
position two years.
   In 1970, Ms. Roberts received a double honor from the group
Women in Communications. She was given the Byliners Award from the
Oklahoma City professional chapter and was named Woman of the Year
by the student chapter at the University of Oklahoma.
   Ms. Roberts was inducted into the Oklahoma Journalism Hall of
Fame in 1984.
   Survivors include a niece, Joanna Roberts Chandler of Austin,
Texas, and nephews Jim Roberts of San Antonio and Rob Parr of
Oklahoma City, and several cousins.
   A prayer vigil is scheduled at 7 p.m. Monday at an Oklahoma City
funeral home. A burial Mass will be held 10 a.m. Tuesday at St.
Francis of Assisi Catholic Church with burial in Rose Hill Burial
Park.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0055 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 1843EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Silverado-Regulator     08-26 0470</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Silverado-Regulator,0487</SECOND>
<HEAD>Newspaper Reports Regulator Raised Money for Senator</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DENVER (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The federal regulator who oversaw Silverado
Banking, Savings and Loan solicited campaign money for a
congressman charged with supervision of the S&amp;L industry, a
newspaper reported Sunday.
   The Denver Post said Kermit Mowbray, former president of the
Federal Home Loan Bank of Topeka, Kan., solicited campaign funds
from other regulators for former Sen. David Karnes, R-Neb., then a
member of the U.S. Senate Banking Committee.
   Karnes was chairman of the Topeka bank before being appointed to
the Senate in 1987 when Democrat Ed Zorinsky died. He ran
unsuccessfully for the seat in 1988.
   Karnes said he was unaware of campaign contributions from
Mowbray and other regulators.
   Edwin Gray, former chairman of the Federal Home Loan Bank Board,
which in turn governed the Topeka bank, said Mowbray's fund-raising
``shows very poor judgment. It's dead wrong.''
   ``If there was any kind of coercion, I would say that it is at
the least highly improper and possibly a violation of the law,''
Gray said.
   Federal law prohibits government employees from raising money
for federal campaigns, but does not apply to Home Loan Bank
employees.
   Mowbray gave $2,000 to Karnes' campaign in June 1987 and
suggested to presidents of the Home Loan Bank system's 12 regional
banks that they also contribute.
   ``I didn't see anything wrong with that,'' Mowbray told the Post.
   The bailout of the nationwide savings and loan industry is
expected to cost taxpayers at least $500 billion. The objectivity
of thrift regulators has become an issue in the Silverado case
largely because President Bush's son, Neil, was a director of the
Denver thrift, which failed at a cost of $1 billion to taxpayers.
   Last month, the Treasury Department began investigating
allegations that Mowbray deliberately postponed seizing Silverado
until after the 1988 presidential election to protect Bush from bad
publicity.
   Mowbray told the House Banking Committee in June that he
received a telephone call from Washington in October 1988 ordering
the delay. The thrift was seized in December 1988, after the
November presidential election. He said he did not remember who
made the call.
   Shortly after Silverado failed, Mowbray left his job at the
Topeka bank.
   During his tenure, Karnes was a bank board member along with
Silverado chairman Michael Wise, who donated $2,000 to Karnes'
campaign.
   As a member of the Senate Banking Committee, Karnes proposed the
``Thrift Charter Enhancement Act of 1988,'' which sought to create
incentives for investors to place additional capital in the thrift
industry.
   Federal election records also show that Thurman Connell,
president of the Federal Home Loan Bank of Des Moines and Brian
Dittenhaufer, president of the Federal Home Loan Bank of New York,
each gave $500 to Karnes' campaign.
   Karnes said last week he never discussed Neil Bush or Silverado
with Mowbray.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0056 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 1828EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Gulf-UN 2ndLd-Writethru a0722 08-26 0622</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-UN, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0722,0640</SECOND>
<HEAD>Perez de Cuellar To Meet Iraqi Foreign Minister</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 11 grafs to UPDATE with Aziz comment, Kuwaiti
reax; pickup 6th graf `On Saturday...'</NOTE>
<DATELINE>UNITED NATIONS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Secretary-General Javier Perez de Cuellar
will meet Iraqi Foreign Minister Tariq Aziz this week to discuss
the Persian Gulf crisis, U.N. and Iraqi officials said Sunday.
   The meeting will be the United Nation's first formal attempt to
mediate the international dispute.
   The secretary-general will meet with Aziz on Thursday in the
Jordanian capital, Amman, ``in order to engage in a full exchange
of views on the crisis,'' said U.N. spokeswoman Nadia Younes.
   She said she could not say whether any other leaders would
attend the meeting. ``We're not ruling anything out,'' she said.
   The crisis was set off by Iraq's invasion and annexation of
Kuwait, which has been condemned by the United Nations in a series
of resolutions. The latest came Saturday with support for military
enforcement of the U.N. embargo against Iraq.
   U.S. and other warships have assembled in the Persian Gulf
region since the crisis began. American planes and thousands of
troops have been rushed to Saudi Arabia, which borders Kuwait.
   Aziz said in Baghdad on Sunday that he planned to meet with
Perez de Cuellar this week, but he did not elaborate. He declined
to say whether Iraq was prepared to compromise on Kuwait's status,
but he said his country would listen to any proposal.
   ``We are open to listen to suggestions,'' Aziz said in an
interview with CNN. ``We have not closed the door to any idea. But
this question is complicated by the American threat to Iraq.''
   Aziz called the United Nations ``a pawn'' of the United States
and said other countries voted for U.N. resolutions against Iraq
because they ``were under severe pressure from the United States.''
   Kuwait's U.N. ambassador, Mohammad A. Abulhasan, said he did not
foresee a breakthrough in the planned meeting. In an interview, the
envoy said Perez de Cuellar was only to gather information.
   ``I don't expect him to negotiate with Iraq,'' Abulhasan said.
   On Saturday, Perez de Cuellar said in Bogota, Colombia, that he
had invited the Iraqi minister to meet to discuss the situation.
   Ms. Younes would not comment on Iraqi President Saddam Hussein's
statement Saturday that he would welcome a visit by the U.N. chief.
   Saddam's statement came in Baghdad, where he was was asked by
reporters traveling with Austrian President Kurt Waldheim whether
he would agree to meet with the U.N. secretary-general in Iraq.
   ``Of course,'' Saddam replied, ``The U.N. secretary-general is
always welcome.'' He was quoted by the official Iraqi News Agency.
   The news agency said Saddam was referring to Perez de Cuellar _
not Waldheim, the former secretary-general _ but provided no
further details.
   Saddam's news conference came at the end of a one-day visit by
Waldheim, who flew out of Baghdad with about 100 Austrian nationals
who had been stranded in the country.
   Perez de Cuellar made his offer hours after the U.N. Security
Council authorized the use of military force to enforce the trade
embargo against Iraq to punish Saddam for his Aug. 2 invasion of
Kuwait.
   ``I believe that after the resolutions adopted by the Security
Council, the time has come for the secretary-general to begin
diplomatic efforts to alleviate the present crisis in the gulf in
all aspects, through the process of dialogue,'' the
secretary-general said.
   In Kennebunkport, Maine, White House spokesman Roman Popadiuk
said Saturday that Washington welcomes a ``discussion by all U.N.
members in the context of the complete and immediate and
unconditional withdrawal'' of Iraqi forces from Kuwait.
   Saddam has repeatedly refused to withdraw from Kuwait, which
Iraq annexed six days after the invasion.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0057 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 1845EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Norway-Hate     08-26 0501</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Norway-Hate,0517</SECOND>
<HEAD>Nobel Laurate at Hate Conference Demands Iraq Free Hostages</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DOUG MELLGREN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>OSLO, Norway (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Nobel Peace Prize winner Elie Wiesel,
opening an international conference on ways to counter hate,
appealed to Iraq on Sunday to free thousands of trapped foreigners.
   ``Our thoughts go to the most recent victims and prisoners of
hate _ those who are being used and manipulated in Kuwait and
Iraq,'' Wiesel said in his opening remarks.
   ``In the name of humanity, we appeal for their unconditional and
immediate release,'' said Wiesel, the Romanian-born author and
human rights activist.
   ``A human being is not a shield,'' he said, referring to Iraq's
move to place scores of foreigners at military and industrial sites
as human shields to deter any U.S. air strikes.
   The four-day conference on ``The Anatomy of Hate''has attracted
about 70 participants from 30 countries _ including world
statesmen, Nobel laureates, thinkers and activists.
   Among those scheduled to attend are South African anti-apartheid
activist Nelson Mandela; Czechoslovak President Vaclav Havel, a
former dissident playwright; French President Francois Mitterrand,
and Lithuanian President Vytautas Landsbergis.
   Wiesel, the Nazi death camp survivor who won the 1986 Nobel
Peace Prize for his work exposing the horrors of the Holocaust,
organized the conference with the Oslo-based Nobel Peace Prize
committee to discuss the problem of hate.
   Last fall, when he issued the call to attend the conference,
Wiesel said he feared that the new freedoms won by East bloc
nations would cause smoldering religious, ethnic and regional
hatred to flare.
   Now, he said, he wishes that the conference could have been held
six months ago, when it might have helped relax tensions in such
hotspots of conflict as the Persian Gulf and South Africa.
   ``Hate, as we know, wears many masks,'' said Wiesel, 61, who is
now a U.S. citizen and Boston University professor.
   He asked participants to expose various forms of hatred:
``racial hate, religious hate, ethnic hate, fanaticism, bigotry,
prejudice and discrimination.''
   Wiesel said he hoped the seminar would end with some kind of
joint declaration.
   Yelena Bonner, the Soviet human rights activist and widow of the
1975 Nobel Peace Prize laureate Andrei Sakharov, said the
participants must first admit ``that hate is an emotion given us by
God.''
   ``Our conference is opening at time that is not the best for
calm and clear reason. ... After the August 2 invasion (of Kuwait),
we are living in a very different reality,'' she said, speaking
through an interpreter.
   Ms. Bonner said years of arms sales by the Soviet Union and
France to ``a known assassin'' like Iraqi leader Saddam Hussein
prove that firm international rules, and not just debates about
morals, are needed to protect human rights.
   On Monday, Mandela is scheduled to open a discussion on
apartheid, South Africa's system of racial separation.
   Others attending the conference are Harvard economist John
Kenneth Galbraith, actor Gregory Peck, former President Jimmy
Carter and Chai Ling, a leader of last year's pro-democracy
movement in Beijing.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0058 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 2005EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-SpottedOwl     08-26 0489</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Spotted Owl,0501</SECOND>
<HEAD>Lujan: Timber Job Losses Will Be Minimized Under Spotted-Owl Plan</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARTIN GRIFFITH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>RENO, Nev. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Timber industry job losses will be far less
than originally thought under a plan to protect the spotted owl on
Forest Service land in the Pacific Northwest, Interior Secretary
Manuel Lujan said Sunday.
   Lujan and Agriculture Secretary Clayton Yeutter are facing a
Saturday deadline to report to President Bush with a plan to
protect the owl, as required under the federal Endangered Species
Act.
   ``Environmentalists are not going to like it, but you have to
have balance,'' Lujan told reporters. ``You can't throw 21,000
people out of work and not give it consideration ... I fully expect
one side or the other to sue me over the plan.''
   A recommendation by Forest Service biologist Jack Ward Thomas
would ban logging on 3 million acres of Northwest forests currently
open to timber harvests.
   The government has estimated the move would reduce federal
harvests in the region by nearly 50 percent at a cost of more than
20,000 jobs by the end of the decade.
   Lujan, while declining to say how the plan might be altered in
terms of acreage, said job losses probably would be scaled down.
``That's my aim,'' he said, ``to come out with a substantial
reduction in job loss.''
   Lujan conceded the spotted owl needs plenty of old-growth forest
to survive, but questioned whether it needs as much as
environmentaists think.
   ``I found an owl last week in Oregon and it wasn't in old-growth
timber,'' he said. ``So it showed me that the owls can live outside
of old-growth areas.''
   Lujan was taken by Bureau of Land Management officials on a tour
last week of a forest 10 miles northeast of Eugene, Ore., where he
got a clear look at a male spotted owl. But officials there said
the owl lived in old-growth forest.
   Later, at a Republican fund-raiser here, Lujan renewed his
criticism of the Endangered Species Act, saying it has become a
tool for environmentalists to block economic development and
multiple use of public lands.
   ``In some cases, a particular listing may threaten the jobs of
thousands, throwing entire communities or regions into economic and
social turmoil,'' he said. ``We must work to ensure that a balance
is reached between our desire to preserve species, while also
preserving the livelihoods of our citizens.''
   In June, Lujan wondered in a published interview if endangered
species must be protected in every locale where they exist.
   ``Do we have to save every subspecies?'' Lujan said. His
statement drew the ire of conservationists who insist that the loss
of any genetically distinct subspecies poses a potentially dire
threat to the environment.
   The government gave permission to the University of Arizona last
week to proceed with construction of a $200 million observatory
that some say could threaten the habitat of the endangered Mount
Graham red squirrel.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0059 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 2015EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>d a AM-BRF-TankerAccident     08-26 0114</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF-Tanker Accident,0117</SECOND>
<HEAD>Driver Uninjured in Fiery Tanker Crash</HEAD>
<DATELINE>THE DALLES, Ore. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A tanker truck carrying 8,650 gallons of
gasoline overturned and exploded Sunday on a bridge over the
Deschutes River, but its driver walked away uninjured, police said.
   The accident closed for several hours the Interstate 84 bridge,
about seven miles east of this northern Oregon city. The highway is
the main road link between eastern and western Oregon.
   Burning gasoline dropped into the Deschutes River but it burned
or evaporated quickly and did not pose an environmental hazard,
officials said.
   Police Sgt. Stephen White identified the driver as Christopher
Mark Haberstich, who worked for Russell Oil Co. of Boardman.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0060 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 2020EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-Refugees 1stLd-Writethru a0736 08-26 0813</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Refugees, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0736,0833</SECOND>
<HEAD>Iraq's Neighbors Move to Ease Refugee Passage</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf Rdp, Bjt</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDs: LEADS thruout to UPDATE with Pakistanis crossing into Iran;
new reports of evacuees arriving in Jordan; ADDS quotes from Briton
who escaped into Syria; CORRECTS that Iran borders Iraq to east
sted north; minor editing; no pickup</NOTE>
<DATELINE>NICOSIA, Cyprus (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Iraq's neighbors moved Sunday to ease
passage for refugees of the Persian Gulf conflict, in some cases
setting aside disputes among themselves to do so.
   Israel plans to ease restrictions at its only border crossing
with Jordan _ which borders Iraq _ to assist those fleeing the gulf
region, officials in Jerusalem said Sunday.
   Tehran radio, monitored in Nicosia, quoted Iran's foreign
minister as saying foreigners fleeing Iraq and Kuwait can do so via
Iran, which borders Iraq to the east.
   Later, Tehran radio said more than 3,000 Pakistanis who had been
living in Kuwait had crossed into Iran along its border with Turkey.
   But it was not clear whether the Iranian promise, which came at
the request of the Philippines, applied to Westerners, or was
confined to Asians and Arabs.
   Jordan and Turkey, which have been the prime escape routes for
foreigners so far, have complained they are overburdened by
thousands of refugees and have threatened to close their borders
unless they received international help to cope with the influx.
Such aid has begun to flow.
   Most of the people who have fled since Iraq invaded its oil-rich
neighbor Kuwait on Aug. 2 have gone by way of Jordan, which has
been forced to feed and shelter thousands until they could afford
to continue on to their home countries.
   A Jordanian border official at Ruweishid, 210 miles northeast of
Amman, said 5,000 people, mostly Egyptians, crossed there from Iraq
on Sunday morning. On Saturday, more than 13,000 people entered
Jordan at Ruweishid, he said. Nearly all of these refugees are
Arabs or Asians.
   A group of 31 Westerners _ including French, British and U.S.
citizens _ arrived in Jordan from Iraq on Sunday. All of the
Americans were of Arab extraction, a senior Jordanian official said.
   Syria, Iraq's main Arab rival, announced Saturday it would allow
foreigners to cross its border with Iraq for humanitarian reasons.
The border has been closed since 1981.
   Martin Watts, a Briton who arrived Saturday in Syria after
fleeing across the desert with six other Britons and an Australian,
said the group fled after deciding it was better to face hostile
border guards than remain in Baghdad and risk being detained.
   ``We decided we all preferred risking bullets while escaping to
remaining in Iraq and risking chemical weapons,'' said Watts, an
engineer who like his companions worked for a British company
building a power station near Baghdad.
   ``We told people we were going to Baghdad for a beer, boarded
our trucks, carried a map and our passports and drove west across
the desert'' for 43 hours, Watts said.
   The coordinator of Israel's occupied territories, Shmuel Goren,
said on Israel radio Sunday that the government was easing
restrictions on crossing the Allenby Bridge on the
Israeli-Jordanian frontier. He cited humanitarian reasons.
   Normally, tourists who want to cross between Jordan and the
occupied West Bank via the Allenby bridge must make arrangements
ahead of time.
   Last week, an agreement that would have allowed tens of
thousands of Egyptian refugees passage home through Israel was
scrapped after it was leaked to the press, embarrassing the
Jordanian and Egyptian governments.
   Jordan is officially in a state of war with Israel. Egypt is the
only Arab state to have made peace with Israel and is sensitive to
suggestions it is too close to the Jewish state.
   Most of the refugees crossing into Jordan are Arabs, but some
have been Westerners.
   There are about 840,000 Palestinians working in the Persian Gulf
region, and many of those in Iraq and Kuwait are now fleeing.
Others in oil-rich gulf nations such as Saudi Arabia and the United
Arab Emirates fear a backlash against Palestinians for their
support of Iraqi President Saddam Hussein.
   Normally, Palestinians without Israeli-issued identity cards
seeking to visit the occupied territories must wait for permission
from the Israeli authorities.
   ``It can usually take up to four weeks for their security
clearance to come through, and they can then only stay up to three
months,'' an Israeli government source said.
   ``Now, we are doing everything we can to make the process as
quick as possible, and we will allow them to extend their stay on a
case-by-case basis,'' he said.
   The government also was dropping the requirement that men
between 16 and 35 who leave the territories must stay away for more
than nine months, the source said.
   That rule is designed to allow students to go abroad but prevent
Palestinian activists making frequent trips in which they could
carry messages back and forth.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0061 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 2040EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BRF-Gulf-Videos     08-26 0141</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF-Gulf-Videos,0145</SECOND>
<HEAD>Free Video Time For Gulf Messages</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CHICAGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A cable company is producing free 30-second video
greetings from family and friends of soldiers deployed to the
Middle East, and the military has agreed to broadcast them to U.S.
ships in the Persian Gulf.
   Arrangements are underway to have the ``Cable Grams From Home''
broadcast to troops on land also, said Edward K. Conklin, spokesman
for Jones' Intercable Inc.
   The company will produce the videos this week at its 10 studios
in suburban Chicago, he said.
   ``We know people who have not had the chance to say goodbye to
family and friends,'' Conklin said. ``We had one lady who was
contacted and all she got was a call from a computer that the
private so-and-so had been shipped to the Persian Gulf and no other
information was available.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0062 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 2117EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Germany-Unification     08-26 0435</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Germany-Unification,0450</SECOND>
<HEAD>Abortion Flap Causes German Politicians to Disagree on Unity
Treaty</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WEST BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Sharp differences over abortion regulations
kept West German political leaders from forging a consensus Monday
on a treaty to merge the country's laws with those of East Germany.
   West German Chancellor Helmut Kohl and top members of his
conservative coalition met for four hours until early Monday
morning with leaders of the opposition Social Democrats in an
effort to ensure smooth passage for the treaty in the legislature.
   But Oskar Lafontaine, the Social Democratic candidate who will
oppose Kohl for chancellor in all-German elections scheduled for
December, said after the meeting in Bonn that differences remained
on the abortion issue.
   The left-of-center Social Democrats are incensed at a government
decision that West German women who try to take advantage of East
Germany's more liberal abortion law after unification can be
prosecuted.
   As a result, the Social Democrats have threatened to block
adoption of the unity treaty, which needs a two-thirds vote to pass
in the Parliament.
   The treaty will cover various issues, including distribution of
sales tax revenues among the German states, how to settle claims by
West Germans seeking the return of their former property in East
Germany, and abortion.
   Failure to pass the treaty would not jeopardize the Oct. 3 date
set for the unification of the two German states.
   But it would mean that most West German laws would go into force
in East Germany after unity takes place, a move East German Prime
Minister Lothar de Maiziere has said would not serve the best
interests of his compatriots.
   East Germans are increasingly unsettled by the prospect of
simply being absorbed by their richer neighbor and having to adjust
to an entirely new economic and legal system.
   Politicians in both countries, women's groups and government
officials have been debating for weeks over the best abortion law
for a united Germany.
   While the Social Democrats are pro-choice, Kohl's conservative
Christian Democrats support restrictions on a woman's right to an
abortion.
   East German women have a legal right to an abortion within the
first 12 weeks of pregnancy.
   But the West German law is much more restrictive. West German
women must prove the pregnancy is life-threatening, resulted from
rape or incest, or would create severe social and economic
hardships.
   Participants in the Bonn meeting called by Kohl are to meet
again on Wednesday for further talks on the treaty.
   They did agree that an all-German parliament should adopt rules
governing abortion that would apply throughout the country.
Elections for the all-German legislature are set for Dec. 2.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0063 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 2154EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Obit-Tendzin     08-26 0353</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Tendzin,0367</SECOND>
<HEAD>Buddhist Church Members Confirm First Western Leader Dead From
AIDS</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LAURA MYERS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN FRANCISCO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Vajra Regent Osel Tendzin, the first
Westerner to lead an international Tibetan Buddhist sect, has died
from an AIDS-related illness, members of the religious group said
Sunday. He was 47.
   Tendzin, born Thomas Rich, died Saturday of respiratory failure
at Pacific Presbyterian Medical Center in San Francisco, according
to members of the Boulder, Colo.-based Dharmadatu Buddhist church
called Vajradhatu.
   Julie Murray, spokeswoman for the hospital, could not confirm
his death, saying no one was registered under the Tendzin or Rich
names.
   ``A lot of members had difficulty accepting that he was sick,''
said one of the church members, who refused to give his name.
``It's been quite difficult for a lot of students of our church.
There have been a lot of different versions of reality.''
   Tendzin was reportedly admitted to the hospital in mid-August.
   He was raised in Passaic, N.J. After dropping out of Fordham
University, he met the Venerable Chogyam Trungpa in 1971 and became
the Tibetan Buddhist leader's top student. Trungpa gave him the
name Osel Tendzin, or ``radiant holder of the teachings.''
   Vajradhatu was founded by Trungpa, who had fled the Chinese
invasion of Tibet to settle in Boulder. Trungpa also founded the
Naropa Institute, an accredited liberal arts college combining
Eastern and Western studies.
   In 1976, Trungpa named Tendzin as his successor, the first time
a Westerner had achieved such a position in the Tibetan Buddhist
tradition. Trungpa died in 1987 at the age of 47.
   In December 1988, Tendzin told Vajradhatu members in San
Francisco that he had contracted AIDS. There were reports at the
time he also had acknowledged putting others at risk through his
sexual behavior.
   The revelation tore the organization apart, with supporters
insisting Tendzin should remain as the group's leader and critics
arguing he must resign because he had betrayed the trust of
followers.
   The Buddhist church's board of directors, who wrested leadership
of the group from Tendzin, were meeting this weekend at
Karmecholing, a meditation center in Barnet, Vt.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0064 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 2204EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-US-Gulf 4thLd-Writethru a0776 08-26 1173</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-US-Gulf, 4th Ld-Writethru, a0776,1,100</SECOND>
<HEAD>Three American Dependents Stopped at Iraq-Turkish Border</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: Subs 5th graf prv, ``The spokeswoman xxx to note that all 55
U.S. dependents previously described as women and children; and
inserts grafs 8-9, ``In a telephone xxx with further detail from
telephone interview</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By GEORGE GEDDA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Fifty-two of 55 dependents of U.S. Embassy
personnel from Kuwait crossed from Iraq into Turkey late Sunday,
but three males were detained by Iraqi border authorities, the
State Department said.
   A spokeswoman for the Kuwait task force at State Department
headquarters said, ``The convoy of Kuwait embassy dependents
crossed the border from Iraq into Turkey about 2 a.m. Iraqi time (6
p.m. EDT.). Fifty-two of the group of 55 who earlier had permission
to cross were allowed to leave.
   ``Three young men in the group, male dependents of Kuwait
embassy diplomats, were not allowed by Iraqi officials to transit
the border and are in the company of an American Embassy Bagdad
escort officer.
   ``The 52 were met by a party from the American Embassy in
Ankara. They will rest tonight in Turkey and plans are being made
for their en route journey home.''
   The spokeswoman, who declined to allow her name to be used, said
she had no information on the ages of the three males held back,
nor on what would happen to them. State Department officials
previously have described all 55 of the dependents as ``women and
children.''
   She likewise had no details on the whereabouts of the 52 allowed
to cross other than that they were in safe hands had were moved
some distance away from the border in buses to spend the rest of
the night.
   The announcement from the State Department came a few hours
after an ABC News report that a bus carrying the Americans had been
turned back at the border, leaving U.S. officials waiting in Turkey
uncertain for a time as to what was happening.
   In a telephone interview with AP Broadcast from Diyarbakir,
Turkey, David Kostelancik, vice consul of the U.S. Embassy in
Ankara, Turkey, said the 52 dependents ``were received by the
American consul from Adana, Mr. Harry Cole, and at a later time
transportation was arranged for them from the border to Dyarbakir.''
   ``They were all very, very tired but they were all very
enthusiastic, very happy to be in Turkey,'' said Kostelancik.
``They will be transported sometime today (Monday) to the Interlik
air base near Adana, where they will remain and they will probably
leave sometime tomorrow (Tuesday) for the United States.'' The
crossing occurred, as previously planned, at Habur.
   Meanwhile, national security adviser Brent Scowcroft said Sunday
that Iraqi President Saddam Hussein, faced with increasing global
opposition to his conquest of Kuwait, is now intent on seeking a
way out of the ``box'' he is in.
   Scowcroft and a variety of other experts interviewed Sunday all
indicated there was room for hope that the 24-day-old Persian Gulf
crisis could be resolved short of military conflict.
   ``I can see a peaceful way out of it,'' Scowcroft said on
ABC-TV's ``This Week With David Brinkley'' program. ``Saddam
Hussein must now see he's facing overwhelming world opinion.''
   ``He is casting about for a way out of the box in which he finds
himself,'' Scowcroft said.
   The pressure on Saddam appeared to increase dramatically
Saturday when the U.N. Security Council gave the United States and
other nations the right to use military power in enforcing the
economic embargo against Iraq.
   Scowcroft said Saddam has shown himself in the past to be a
realist, citing his willingness two weeks ago to bow to Iran's
terms for a settlement of their eight-year war. Among other
concessions, Saddam agreed to recognize the prewar boundary of the
two countries.
   Meanwhile, State Department press officer Anita Stockman said
Sunday the U.S. Embassy in Iraqi-occupied Kuwait has been informed
that two additional Americans have been taken into custody by Iraqi
troops.
   She said the information was relayed to the embassy by
telephone. Although officials had no way of confirming the
information, she said embassy personnel had reason to believe it
was accurate. She had no additional details about those arrested.
   Assistant Secretary of State for Near East and South Asian
Affairs John Kelly said little had changed at the U.S. Embassy in
Kuwait City, which, along with a number of other Western diplomatic
missions, was being surrounded by Iraqi troops.
   Appearing on NBC-TV's ``Meet the Press'' program, Kelly said the
embassy is hampered in its efforts to help the estimated 2,500
Americans whom Iraq is refusing permission to leave the country. He
said less than 10 have been picked up by Iraqi troops. Another 50
are in Iraqi troop custody in Baghdad, he said.
   Iraq cut off electricity at the U.S. Embassy in Kuwait on
Saturday and the power remained off Sunday. The embassy was using a
power generator.
   Iraqi troops were preventing anyone from entering or leaving the
embassy but Kelly said the reduced staff there probably had a
couple of weeks worth of supplies remaining.
   At the Pentagon, the Army on Sunday ordered 50 more Army reserve
and National Guard units in 25 states to report for active duty by
Aug. 31. The Defense Department also said elements of the Army's
13th Support Command at Fort Hood, Texas, had begun to deploy to
the Middle East.
   The impetus for a diplomatic solution appeared to increase when
Iraqi Ambassador Mohamed al-Mashat said his government would
welcome a mediation effort by U.N. Secretary General Javier Perez
de Cuellar.
   Perez de Cuellar said Saturday he was seeking an urgent meeting
this week with Iraqi Foreign Minister Tariq Aziz in either New York
or Geneva. After his television appearance, Scowcroft said the
administration ``would have no problem'' with a mediation by Perez
de Cuellar.
   He added that highest U.S. priority was inducing Iraq to
withdraw from Kuwait. After that, he said, ``We're prepared to talk
about anything.''
   Scowcroft was interviewed in Kennebunkport, Maine, where he was
staying with the vacationing President Bush. The president, who
played golf and tennis and received a briefing from Scowcroft,
continued to refuse to answer reporters' questions about the gulf
situation.
   Bush was to return to Washington on Tuesday to brief
congressional leaders on the gulf crisis.
   Al-Mashat, appearing on CBS-TV's ``Face the Nation'' program,
contrasted Iraq's ``desire for peace'' with the American ``design
to have war.'' He said America's aggressive intentions were clearly
demonstrated by the dispatch of offensive weaponry, including
stealth bombers, to Saudi Arabia.
   The notion that the United States and Iraq were moving
inevitably toward war was disputed on ABC by Henry A. Kissinger and
Zbigniew Brzezinski, both former national security advisers.
   ``I believe that Saddam Hussein is looking for some way out,''
Kissinger said. ``If we stay firm ... we will get it.''
   The under secretary of state for political affairs, Robert
Kimmitt, said on CBS that Saddam's hand sooner or later will be
forced by the economic sanctions approved by the U.N. Security
Council.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0065 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 2222EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-MisterEd     08-26 0207</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mister Ed,0211</SECOND>
<HEAD>Monument Erected at Rumored Gravesite of Talking Horse</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TAHLEQUAH, Okla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   About 200 people milled around Sunday
under a wild cherry tree where Mr. Ed, the 1960s television star,
is said to be buried. But there's no record of his death because
Mr. Ed was a horse, of course.
   A 5-foot-tall granite monument, with a picture of the ``talking
horse'' sticking his head out over a barn door as he did in the
show, was unveiled on the farm of Danny and Darlene Snodgrass.
   When the Snodgrasses bought the 17-acre site north of Tahlequah
in 1981, they didn't give much credence to a cousin's recollection
of visiting the place as a youngster to see Mr. Ed.
   But other people around this northeastern Oklahoma town told the
couple the same story. They learned that Clarence Tharp, whose
family sold them the land, brought Mr. Ed to Tahlequah after the
series was canceled.
   There are other versions of Mr. Ed's demise. One person
associated with the show said the horse died in 1973 and was
cremated, with his ashes spread over Hollywood, Mrs. Snodgrass
said. Another said Mr. Ed died in 1968.
   But ``we feel pretty certain that it's Mr. Ed here,'' she said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0066 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 2313EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Guam-Yacht 1stLd-Writethru a0756 08-26 0251</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Guam-Yacht, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0756,0254</SECOND>
<HEAD>Yacht with 17 People Aboard Found Adrift in Pacific</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: UPDATES throughout with yacht found, crew safe</NOTE>
<NOTE>Eds: Monday cq in lead</NOTE>
<DATELINE>AGANA, Guam (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Coast Guard found a yacht that had been
crippled in rough seas southwest of Guam and sent a patrol boat
Monday to tow the boat and its crew to safety, officials said.
   A C-130 search and rescue plane from Hawaii spotted the Royal
Taipan about 120 miles east-northeast of Yap, an island of the
Federated State of Micronesia, said Lt. Kent Youel, a Coast Guard
spokesman in Honolulu.
   Earlier reports had said the 146-foot vessel was lost about 225
miles south-southwest of Guam, but its location Monday was about
500 miles southwest of Guam.
   A 95-foot patrol boat was sent out from Yap to take the boat in
tow, Youel said. Everyone aboard was reported safe, he said.
   The Royal Taipan, a converted Navy minesweeper owned by
Honolulu-based Windjammer Cruises, first radioed for help Saturday
when it ran into the fringes of Tropical Storm Abe.
   Communication was lost Sunday night just after the crew reported
that it was taking on water in 25-foot seas and about 50 mph winds,
and that water had reached the floorboards, said Youel.
   The crew, including 14 Filipinos and two Americans, was sailing
the Royal Taipan from the Philippines to Saipan, where the yacht
was to have been refurbished for cruises, Youel said. The
nationality of the 17th crewmember wasn't known.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0067 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 1840EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-DigestBriefs     08-26 0440</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Digest Briefs,0461</SECOND>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Roughly 60,000 American soldiers, airmen and
sailors have moved to battle stations in the Persian Gulf since
President Bush ordered U.S. firepower into the area to thwart
Iraq's Saddam Hussein, sources say.
   In addition to the massive troop movement, the Pentagon has
built a virtual armada in the region's seas and rushed in hundreds
of fighter jets and support aircraft.
   The deployment, the largest since the Vietnam War, is far from
complete.
   Within a few weeks, about 45,000 Marines are expected to have
arrived in the area. By then the total U.S. combat force in the
region may number well over 100,000, military sources said last
week.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>SAUDI ARABIA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   U.S. forces in Saudi Arabia still lack
ground-based anti-aircraft systems and other equipment considered
vital for extended combat, field commanders say.
   ``We're pretty naked out here right now,'' an Air Force officer
said during a recent visit to his desert base area.
   Commanders and supply officers characterized the equipment
problems as serious but not severe, and attributed them to the
limited transport capabilities of the U.S. military. Officials said
many of the concerns should be addressed over the next week to 10
days, as more ships arrive.
   For the most part, the unprecedented air and sea lift of U.S.
forces has proceeded smoothly.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   National security adviser Brent Scowcroft said
Sunday that Iraqi President Saddam Hussein, faced with increasing
global opposition to his conquest of Kuwait, is now intent on
seeking a way out of the ``box'' he is in.
   Scowcroft and a variety of other experts interviewed Sunday all
indicated there was room for hope that the 24-day-old Persian Gulf
crisis could be resolved short of military conflict.
   ``I can see a peaceful way out of it,'' Scowcroft said on
ABC-TV's ``This Week With David Brinkley'' program. ``Saddam
Hussein must now see he's facing overwhelming world opinion.''
   ``He is casting about for a way out of the box in which he finds
himself,'' Scowcroft said.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>LEIPZIG, East Germany (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   East Germany is about to disappear,
to be swallowed up by its rich western neighbor, and the universal
enthusiasm of a few months ago has waned.
   Polls say the vast majority of East Germans favor unification,
which is barely a month away. But appearances don't always
reinforce that conclusion.
   The ``We are one people'' banners that hung from trees,
factories and homes during the pro-unity frenzy of early 1990 are
gone.
   There are no cheering crowds and no convoys of motorists
blasting their horns in anticipation of full unification on Oct. 3.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0068 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 1425EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-CreditMarkets Bjt   08-26 0554</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Credit Markets, Bjt,0576</SECOND>
<HEAD>Junk Defaults Rising, Outlook for Rest of Year Dim</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAN BLAKE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Junk bond defaults rose in the first half of
1990 and analysts say a weak economy and higher oil prices could
bring the highest default rate in 20 years.
   As the economy slows and higher gasoline and heating oil prices
leave consumers with less money to spend in casinos, department
stores and on new homes, businesses will have less cash to make
interest and principal payments.
   In the first seven months of the year, 32 high-yield bond
issuers defaulted for an annualized rate of 5.8 percent, according
to John Lonski, chief economists at Moody's Investor Service Inc.
   If maintained, the it would be the highest rate since the
collapse of the Penn Central railroad accounted for a 10.9 percent
default rate in 1970, Lonski said.
   ``I don't think we've passed the bottom yet in all likelihood,
especially for the highly-leveraged firms that depend on
descretionary income,'' Lonski said.
   Prices of issues expected to ride up and down with the business
cycle have taken a pounding since oil prices rose after Iraq
overran Kuwait on Aug. 2.
   Numbers compiled by Citicorp show total returns on junk bonds
issued by recession-prone industries suffered the worst in the
first half of August. Casinos dropped 7.8 percent, building
materials fell 7.1 percent and retailers are off 3.6 percent.
   Toilet maker American Standard Inc., which relies heavily on
energy in making ceramics as well as new homes for sales, saw its
12~-percent senior subordinated debentures that mature in the year
2000 skid from 93 to the high 80s last week.
   Junk bonds are debt securities typically issued by companies
that lack investment grade credit. Often used to raise capital for
expansion, they carry high interest rates to compensate for their
risky nature.
   ``The market is reflecting fears of a recession. It was already
worried about corporate profits weakening,'' said Mariel Clemensen,
Citicorp's high-yield research director.
   A recession would hit steeply leveraged companies particularly
hard, which have huge principal and interest payments among their
fixed costs, Lonski said. When looking to cut expenses, capital
spending and employment are likely to be hit harder than if a
company didn't have a high debt obligation.
   Even industries such as food, tobacco and health care, whose
fortunes tend to resist economic downturns, could be hurt as
consumers resist price hikes that heavily indebted companies have
relied upon to boost cash flow, Lonski said.
   Citicorp's numbers show total returns on health-care issues
dropping 0.9 percent and broadcasting issues falling 1.7 percent in
the first half of August.
   ``You might find some that will escape unscathed,'' Lonski said,
particularly utilities that rely heavily on nuclear power to
produce electricity.
   For utilities, junk bonds are usually so-called fallen angels,
once highly rated issues that became viewed as risky the more they
faced trouble with their investments in nuclear power.
   But these utilities' reliance on nuclear power is what may make
some an attractive investment during a prolonged oil-price shock,
Lonski said. Arizona Public Service Co. and Philadelphia Electric
Co., for example, are two utilities with speculative-grade bonds
that have substantial nuclear-power generating capabilities.
   Moreover, public sentiment about nuclear power could improve if
the country once again starts looking to alternative fuel sources.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0069 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 1426EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-SprintTrouble Bjt   08-26 0756</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Sprint Trouble, Bjt,0780</SECOND>
<HEAD>No. 3 Long-Distance Company Dogged by Problems</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SALLY STREFF BUZBEE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>KANSAS CITY, Mo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A month after reporting a shocking
second quarter loss, US Sprint is airing new TV ads and
strengthening its sales staff to grab business from the the
nation's two largest long-distance companies.
   But many think Sprint, with 10 percent of the market, faces an
uphill battle.
   It must compete for residential customers at a time when MCI
Communications Corp. and American Telephone and Telegraph Co. have
established strong telemarketing, sales and ad campaigns targeted
toward the individual buyer. Sprint must cut costs at the same time.
   ``I think things are going to turn around for them,'' said
Audrey Stevoff, vice president and telecommunications analyst for
Duff &amp; Phelps in Chicago. ``But I'm not sure how quickly. They can
cut costs fairly easily. But getting customers onto your network _
that's the challenge.''
   Other analysts think the $42 million loss that caused the stock
of Sprint's parent company to plummet is a sign the fiercely
competitive long-distance industry is stabilizing.
   ``Sprint was late to the dinner table, and it is just never
going to have as large a portion of the pie,'' said Robert B.
Morris III, analyst for Goldman, Sachs &amp; Co. in San Francisco.
``You will have them as a viable third carrier, but they probably
will never reach the levels of market share that MCI will reach.''
   Partly, Morris says, that's because ``the gobs of market share
that AT&amp;T was losing at one point are no longer available.''
   ``You had many investors working on the premise that Sprint was
just MCI two years later,'' Morris said, and would grow just as
big. MCI has about 14 percent of the market. Now that premise has
been shaken, he contends.
   Sprint officials, for their part, say the market, analysts and
the media overreacted to the loss they announced July 17. The loss
caused second quarter earnings of United Telecommunications Inc. to
fall 55 percent. It owns 80 percent of Sprint.
   The loss also delayed United Telecom's buyout of the remaining
20 percent of Sprint owned by the GTE Corp. of Stamford, Conn. The
two companies formed Sprint in mid-1986.
   Sprint officials acknowledge costs were too high and revenue
growth lower than expected. Basically, the company fell behind in
the fight for residential customers, they say. It continues to sell
well to businesses and is getting revenues from its share of a
large government contract.
   ``We've said very clearly that we did not take action as soon as
we could have in that part of the market,'' said Ron LeMay,
Sprint's president and chief operating officer. ``We realize that
we have to become more aggressive, and what you're seeing now in
action is a reflection of that.''
   Those actions include eliminating 1,300 jobs nationwide, mostly
administrative jobs, and putting more people into marketing
efforts, including sales and service jobs targeted toward smaller
customers.
   In addition, new TV ads directly confront a recent AT&amp;T charge
that other long-distance companies won't put their promises in
writing.
   ``It's an attempt to very clearly educate customers that we have
the full range of long-distance possibilities, plus the service to
back it up,'' LeMay said.
   Those are steps in the right direction, say analysts who contend
Sprint simply lost track of what its competitors were doing.
   ``I think they thought their blanket commercial about the pin
would reach all markets,'' Stevoff said.
   But MCI decided last fall to refocus on residential customers
and began an intense telemarketing campaign. And AT&amp;T blanketed
television with commercials designed to attract ``the average Joe
calling Aunt Sophie,'' Stevoff said.
   Morris worries that Sprint still is just reacting to the market
instead of leading the way.
   ``These are things that will help you maintain your share,'' he
said of the new ads. ``But if you're really going to accelerate
things you have to lead the market, rather than follow it.''
   Since the earnings announcement, Sprint officials also have
reacted angrily to charges that the billing problems they struggled
with in the late 1980s have recurred. Morris said he has heard of
no new problems.
   The Federal Communications Commission says 376 written
complaints about billing were filed against Sprint in the first 10
months of this fiscal year, vs. 821 last year.
   But Sprint does lag in development of the sophisticated billing
systems that competitors are offering customers.
   ``Once again, it's just an extremely competitive atmosphere
where they're struggling to keep up,'' Morris said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0070 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 1427EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-TickerTalk Bjt   08-26 0596</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Ticker Talk, Bjt,0615</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bear Sightings on Wall Street</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CHET CURRIER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The steep decline in stock prices this summer
has left investors staring into the jaws of what some say may be
Wall Street's first sustained bear market in nearly a decade.
   Today's generation of stock traders and analysts is by no means
unaccustomed to to the phenomenon of falling markets. Most of them
were around for the Crash of 1987, which provided all the
conditions you could want for a baptimism of fire.
   That debacle produced a 36 percent drop in the Dow Jones
industrial average, enough to rank prominently on any list of
modern-day market declines.
   But almost all the carnage occurred in a span of less than two
months, and stocks began to recover quickly thereafter en route to
new highs.
   Many an investor, it appeared, was still numb from the shock
when the wounds began to heal.
   For an undisputed example of the kind of long, debilitating
slide for which classic bear markets are famous, one has to go back
to 1981-82, before the big boom of the '80s on Wall Street was
ready to start.
   From April 27, 1981 to Aug. 12, 1982, the Dow Jones industrials
tumbled from 1,024.05 to 776.92 as the economy struggled through a
recession exacerbated by rapid inflation and high interest rates.
   Instead of the sudden jolt of a crash, the market in those days
experienced a kind of slow, steady erosion that gave investors
plenty of time to think about how much money they were losing and
how bleak the outlook seemed.
   The question of the moment now, of course, is whether stocks are
in for a similar malaise, or just undergoing one of the periodic
``corrections'' that have punctuated the long bull market since '82.
   Simple to ask, not so easy to answer. Incipient bear markets are
notoriously cunning at disguising themselves as short-term
corrections, and vice versa.
   On the optimistic side, however, analysts point out that
authentic bear markets have seldom begun with a single event that
serves as an ``explanation'' for the decline _ in this case, Iraq's
invasion of Kuwait on Aug. 2.
   Indeed, many veteran market-watchers worry more when declines
set in that have no readily discernible cause.
   ``Past major confrontations such as the Cuban missile crisis or
other military squabbles that were resolved favorably proved to be
just a blip in the stock market's general trend,'' observes Greg
Smith, an analyst at Prudential-Bache Securities.
   ``We could be in one of those blips, or this could be something
much more significant.''
   Norman Fosback, editor of a group of investment advisory letters
published by the Institute for Econometric Research in Fort
Lauderdale, Fla., plants himself squarely on the ``blip'' side of
the argument.
   ``Price weakness touched off by the geopolitical crisis does NOT
constitute a bear market,'' he declared in the firm's Mutual Fund
Forecaster. ``It does appear to be the 10 percent to 15 percent
correction that has been long overdue.
   ``Midstream bull market corrections are nearly always abrupt.
They shake out the market's weak participants by leading them to
believe, falsely, that a bear market has begun.''
   One big risk behind this view is the chance that the market has
looked beyond the Persian Gulf showdown and correctly discerned the
approach of a recession.
   It will take a good while for these overlays of uncertainty to
sort themselves out, observed Morton Silverman, portfolio
strategist at Piper, Jaffray &amp; Hopwood in Minneapolis.
   Silverman concluded, ``it's a time for prudence, not
opportunism.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0071 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 1428EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-StoveSales     08-26 0660</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Stove Sales,0682</SECOND>
<HEAD>Sales Reheating for Wood Stoves</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: also on general news wires.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By JONATHAN YENKIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Sales of wood stoves are heating up again as
people worry about the rising cost of fuel for the winter.
   Wood stoves have been both maligned and romanticized as having a
certain pioneer mystique. While oil price hikes and tensions in the
Middle East fanned sales in the 1970s and early 1980s, wood stoves
also were the target of pollution restrictions and the source of
fatal house fires.
   Industry officials say stoves today have more sophisticated
designs to remedy the old problems. Now wood stove makers and
retailers are hoping to cash in on the Persian Gulf crisis, which
they say demonstrates the risks of depending on oil.
   ``The good news for our industry is that there's been a wake-up
call on the energy front,'' said Jim Hermann, president of the
Earth Stove Inc., a Portland, Ore., company that is one of the
largest wood stove producers in the country. ``We've been living in
this artificial world of cheap oil.''
   Stores that sell wood stoves say they saw surging interest in
their products almost immediately after Iraq invaded Kuwait this
month. In Massachusetts, the average price of home heating oil has
risen 18 cents per gallon since the invasion.
   ``We had twice as many calls right off,'' said Peter Dormitzer,
owner of the Chelmsford Fireplace Center north of Boston.
   One day last week, his store sold five stoves. ``We haven't been
doing five stoves a month until now,'' he said.
   This growing interest comes as a sharp contrast to the
industry's recent performance.
   More than a decade ago, the industry was growing so quickly that
officials had no solid sales numbers. They estimated annual stove
sales exceeded 1 million around the start of the 1980s, as large
and small manufacturers proliferated around the country.
   ``Anybody that had a welding shop was putting together a wood
stove back then,'' Hermann said.
   But for several reasons, the industry shrank quickly. Annual
sales are now estimated around 225,000.
   A big factor was the falling price of oil, which meant people no
longer were looking for another energy source. Instead, wood stoves
increasingly were bought for aesthetic reasons, which meant they
were ``competing with a new sofa or VCR,'' said Jason Densmore, of
Lebanon, N.H., president of Wood Heating Alliance, a national trade
association.
   Wood stoves also had a publicity problem. Mountain towns in
Colorado, where air currents create special pollution problems,
restricted numbers of wood stoves. In 1988, the U.S. Environmental
Protection Agency set new rules for wood stoves, forcing sharp
reductions in smoke emissions.
   Meanwhile, fatal house fires were reported across the country in
which wood stoves were involved.
   Industry officials say, however, these accidents usually were
due to improper installation of the stoves or poor maintenance of
chimneys.
   But these events have prompted the industry to change for the
better, company representatives say. Because of the EPA
restrictions, wood stoves today burn much more cleanly, and they
are also made under tighter safety guidelines, said Jiggs
Blackburn, research and development director for Vermont Castings
Inc., a wood stove maker in Randolph, Vt.
   ``Wood stoves have undergone a remarkable transformation,''
Blackburn said. ``It is now a very sophisticated appliance.''
   While the initial investment in a wood stove can exceed $1,000,
wood stove representatives say the low price of wood compared with
oil translates into savings over the long term.
   That is part of the sales pitch for people who might otherwise
prefer the convenience of turning up their thermostats rather than
gathering wood.
   Another advantage is simply the independence from foreign oil
suppliers or local utilities, said Densmore, who noted he uses a
wood stove to heat his 12-room house in central New Hampshire.
   ``I think we're certainly pleased to see the alternative fuel
issue raised,'' he said. ``Unfortunately it takes something like
this to create the awareness.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0072 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 1648EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-Gulf-OPEC 2ndLd-Writethru   08-26 0579</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-OPEC, 2nd Ld-Writethru,0597</SECOND>
<HEAD>OPEC Ministers Urged to Convene Emergency Meeting</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS thruout to UPDATE with six of seven necessary votes in
favor of emergency conference on increasing oil production, edits
to conform. No pickup; also on general news wires.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By SALLY JACOBSEN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>VIENNA, Austria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   OPEC appeared close Sunday to calling an
emergency meeting to approve an increase in oil production because
of the Persian Gulf crisis.
   A vote of seven nations is needed to call an emergency meeting,
and the Venezuelan oil minister, Celestino Armas, said six
countries already supported the measure.
   Armas, in Vienna for informal talks with other OPEC nations,
said the oil market is suffering from ``an important disruption,
and we have to do something about that.''
   Since Iraq invaded Kuwait on Aug. 2, prompting a U.N. oil emargo
on both nations, crude prices have risen from about $20 a barrel to
more than $30, threatening the global economy.
   Ministers from 11 of the 13 member nations from the Organization
of Petroleum Exporting Countries were in Vienna, site of the
cartel's headquarters, for the talks.
   Those supporting an emergency meeting were Saudi Arabia,
Venezuela, Kuwait, Qatar, Ecuador and the United Arab Emirates,
Armas said.
   Saudi Arabia and Venezuela tried last week to call an emergency
meeting on increasing production, but were rebuffed. Saudi Arabia,
Venezuela, the United Arab Emirates and a few others have the
ability to pump more crude oil.
   Some nations, like Iran, have argued that there is enough oil in
storage to make up for any shortages caused by the gulf crisis.
   Only Iraq and Libya were not represented at Sunday's gathering,
OPEC sources said on condition of anonymity.
   The finance minister of Kuwait's exiled government, Ali Khalifa
al-Sabah, who was the conquered emirate's oil minister until
earlier this summer, said Sunday he would like to see an increase
in oil production.
   Saudi Arabia has said it intends to increase production by up to
2 million barrels a day _ with or without OPEC's blessing _ to make
up some of the loss of crude caused by the Persian Gulf crisis.
   But clearly Saudi Arabia, the world's largest crude exporter,
would like the cartel's approval to exceed its OPEC supply quota of
5.4 million barrels a day.
   Analysts estimate some 4 million barrels of crude a day have
been pulled off the markets because of the international embargo on
Iraqi and Kuwaiti oil. They said four other OPEC nations _ the
United Arab Emirates, Venezuela, Nigeria and Libya _ also have the
ability to pump extra oil.
   Venezuela's Armas said his country will boost output to fill its
stocks because of the possibility that the oil crunch will continue
for some time.
   Analysts say Venezuela could add as much as 500,000 barrels a
day to its OPEC quota of 1.9 million barrels.
   OPEC President Sadek Boussena, the Algerian oil minister, echoed
private analysts in saying that the cartel has had little impact on
prices in recent weeks. The oil-consuming nations, he said, ``are
masters of the prices.''
   Last month, the cartel agreed to restrain production at 22.5
million barrels a day in the last half of the year in an effort to
drive prices up to a new target of $21 a barrel. The benchmark was
surpassed almost immediately because of the gulf crisis.
   OPEC nations are: Algeria, Ecuador, Gabon, Indonesia, Iran,
Iraq, Kuwait, Libya, Nigeria, Qatar, Saudi Arabia, the United Arab
Emirates and Venezuela.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900826-0073 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-90 1757EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-CableIndustry-Unions     08-26 0377</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Cable Industry-Unions,0390</SECOND>
<HEAD>Two Labor Unions Set Sights On Organizing Cable Industry</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DENVER (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two labor unions hope to tap the booming cable
industry for new membership in an effort to stem a decade-long
decline in traditional membership.
   As revenue in the cable industry has mushroomed _ from about
$2.9 billion in 1980 to $17.3 billion this year _ so has
employment. An estimated 101,400 people currently work in the
industry.
   The Communications Workers of America and the International
Brotherhood of Electrical Workers have begun focusing on organizing
those workers, but it isn't easy.
   The CWA failed twice _ most recently in June _ to unionize
United Cablevision, a subsidiary of United Artists Entertainment
Inc. with roughly 130,000 subscribers in metropolitan Denver,
though similar efforts at United's Grand Junction office succeeded.
   ``The difficulty you have is that each franchise has relatively
few employees,'' said Morton Bahr, president of the CWA in
Washington. ``This enables management to divide and conquer.''
   Experts say unions represent workers in no more than 10 percent
of the nearly 10,000 U.S. cable systems. By comparison, 100 percent
of the regional Bell telephone companies are unionized.
   Ray McGuire, a Washington labor attorney, said the industry's
relative youth has helped insulate it from unions.
   ``Cable has not been for a very long time a very profitable
industry,'' he said. ``Cash flow was thin at the beginning.'' That
changed during the 1980s, and now McGuire says the unions see
cable's potential.
   The United Steelworkers of America found a receptive environment
last fall at American Cablevision, which serves about 35,000
subscribers in the Denver area. Tim Richter and several co-workers
drew on employees' dissatisfaction over wages, benefits and working
conditions. Last November, employees voted for the union, and a
second vote last month confirmed the previous election.
   But the cable companies view labor unions warily.
   ``If you have a strike or workplace disruption, you're going to
have real upset customers,'' said Ron Christensen, vice president
of human resources at Englewood-based Jones Intercable Inc. and
chairman of the Cable Television Administration and Marketing's
human resources committee.
   ``Although many unions are good unions, in a few cases you get
an adversarial relationship,'' said Christensen. ``It's hard to say
who's at fault, but it's a very unproductive environment.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
</Collection>
