<Collection>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0001 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 2302EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-TropicalWeather     09-23 0179</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Tropical Weather,0184</SECOND>
<HEAD>Eleventh Depression Disperses While No. 12 Loiters in Open
Atlantic</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The season's 11th tropical depression dissipated in
the mid-Atlantic on Sunday while No. 12 lingered about 1,000 miles
to the west, forecasters said.
   Sunday evening, the season's 11th tropical depression lost its
center at latitude 19.7 north, longitude 52.7 west, about 700 miles
east-northeast of the Leeward Islands.
   By 10:30 p.m., forecasters at the National Hurricane Center in
suburban Coral Cables located tropical depression No. 12 at
latitude 19.3 north, longitude 34.2 west, or about 700 miles
west-northwest of the Cape Verde Islands off the western shoulder
of Africa.
   It was drifting west-northwest near 4 mph with top sustained
winds of 35 mph, and was expected to maintain its speed and
strength while gradually turning to the northwest by Monday night.
   Tropical depressions become tropical storms if their maximum
sustained winds top 39 mph. Storms become hurricanes if the winds
top 74 mph.
   September is usually the most active month for the Atlantic
hurricane season, which lasts from June 1 to Nov. 30.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0002 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 2316EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Mohawks-Jackson     09-23 0217</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mohawks-Jackson,0237</SECOND>
<HEAD>Jesse Jackson Says He Hopes To Mediate Mohawk Standoff</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MONTREAL (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Civil rights activist Jesse Jackson said Sunday
that he hoped to mediate a solution to the standoff between police
and Mohawk Indians in Oka.
   ``Hopefully, through dialogue and through the interviewing
process the tensions will ease and the bloodshed will stop,'' he
told reporters after arriving in Montreal. ``And there will be some
rational resolution to this conflict.''
   Jackson said he's already spoken to Quebec Premier Robert
Bourassa about his efforts to resolve the crisis.
   ``The problem that develops in standoffs is that people harden
their positions,'' he said. ``And when talking becomes impossible,
violence becomes inevitable.''
   Army spokesman Maj. John Paul MacDonald said Jackson will be
denied access to the Kahnesatake treatment center, where about 50
Mohawk women, children and men have been encircled by soldiers for
the last three weeks.
   ``As with everyone else who has requested to come into the
perimeter but really has no business being there, he will be
refused as well,'' MacDonald said.
   The 74-day standoff began over plans to sell property in the
town of Oka that the Mohawks claim is ancestral land. Quebec
provincial police stormed an Indian roadblock in Oka on July 11 and
Cpl. Marcel Lemay was killed in the ensuing gun battle.
   It has not been determined who was responsible for his death.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0003 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 2340EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-BudgetTalks 1stLd-Writethru a0706 09-23 0628</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Budget Talks, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0706,690</SECOND>
<HEAD>Sen. Mitchell Willing to Consider Dole Budget Compromise</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Subs 4th graf, ``His remarks xxx to update with 4-hour session
completed with no indication of progress; STANDS FOR AMS</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By ALAN FRAM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Senate Majority Leader George Mitchell said
Sunday that Democrats are willing to consider a Republican idea for
unsnarling stalled budget talks by placing a capital gains tax cut
into a separate package.
   Mitchell's comment was the first indication that Democrats might
be willing to explore the suggestion, which Senate Minority Leader
Bob Dole, R-Kan., made Thursday. The fight over whether to slash
the capital gains tax rate is perhaps the major hurdle remaining
for the two sides to complete a five-year, $500 billion
deficit-reduction package.
   ``We'd be prepared to consider it, to work, to see precisely
what he has in mind, and to come up with some way to get this thing
done,'' said Mitchell, D-Maine, on CBS's ``Face the Nation.''
   His remarks came before eight budget bargainers from the Bush
administration and Congress held a four-hour, closed-door evening
session in the Capitol. There was no indication what, if any,
progress was made by the group, which has met four other times
since last Tuesday in an effort to end a yearlong budget stalemate.
Another meeting was scheduled for Monday.
   Meanwhile, President Bush was reported to have expressed
optimism about a budget agreement during a conversation with
Maryland Gov. William Donald Schaefer.
   Schaefer, who talked with the president at a Maryland golf
course where he stopped for an 18-hole round en route back to the
White House from Camp David, had told reporters beforehand how
worried he was about the prospects of massive furloughs starting
Oct. 1 if the White House and Congress fail to reach a budget
agreement.
   Thousands of federal workers live in the Maryland suburbs of
Washington and Baltimore, where Social Security's headquarters is
located.
   After speaking with Bush, Schaefer said he told the president,
``I'm very worried.'' He said the president replied ``I think we'll
have a deal.''
   ``He was not pessimistic. He was very optimistic,'' the governor
told reporters.
   Dole has suggested that the negotiators write two measures. One
would contain tax increases and spending cuts.
   The second bill would contain what he on the same program called
``all the goodies.'' These would include the capital gains tax
reduction, which Bush wants; a more expensive child care program,
favored by Democrats; and tax breaks for the poor and for
businesses.
   The measure - which could cost $50 billion or $60 billion -
would have to be paid for by additional taxes or spending
reductions.
   ``We ought to stop dancing around capital gains, face up to it,
get it resolved and get this package put to bed,'' Dole said.
   Dole broke somewhat with his GOP colleagues by emphasizing the
importance the capital gains dispute holds in clearing the way for
a deal. Other Republicans have argued that differences over
spending cuts and the types of taxes to be raised are just as
important in finishing the negotiations.
   ``Right now the big hurdle is capital gains,'' Dole said.
   Dole seemed to express pique at the pace of negotiations favored
by White House budget bargainers.
   ``We shouldn't be in too much of a rush,'' he said White House
officials have told him. ``Well, I don't know what else they've got
to do this year, but I've got a lot of things I'd like to do.''
   The delay, he said, could be strategically costly.
   ``We're losing votes every day, in my view, in the House and the
Senate by not getting it done,'' he said.
   It is unclear whether Dole's suggestion to create two packages
will ever become a formal GOP offer at the budget talks. Some White
House officials, including Chief of Staff John Sununu, have
vehemently opposed the idea. At a news conference Friday, Bush
failed to endorse it, but did not rule it out, either.
   The full impact of the idea is also uncertain because of an
unusual voting procedure Dole has suggested.
   Under his plan, the two measures would be voted on separately.
But if the ``goodies'' package were to be defeated, then the
deficit-reduction measure would be considered rejected as well,
even if it was approved on an earlier vote.
   The proposal raises yet another question: how would the capital
gains tax reduction and other ``goodies'' be paid for? Budget
bargainers have had a hard enough time coming up with $500 billion
worth of savings, let alone having to find another $50 billion or
$60 billion.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0004 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 2352EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Gulf-PainfulGoodbyes     09-23 0590</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Gulf-Painful Goodbyes,0764</SECOND>
<HEAD>Wrenching Goodbyes: Wives Who Fled Middle East Remain Hostages at
Home</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Gulf Rdp, Bjt</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Rande in 8th graf and Anderton in 13th graf are cq.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By LESLIE DREYFOUS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP National Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   As food grew scarce and Iraqi soldiers more entrenched, Ruthie
and her husband made the decision: She and their three young
children could not remain in Kuwait.
   ``I don't like to talk this way in front of the kids, but here
are my thoughts: It feels like I left him there to die,'' said
Ruthie Al-Qallef, a Memphis, Tenn., native. ``l feel like I
deserted him.''
   She and hundreds of other American wives and children who fled
the Middle East remain trapped by visions of loved ones left
behind.
   ``Leaving him was the hardest thing I've ever done,'' said Mrs.
Al-Qallef, whose husband of 10 years is a Kuwaiti military officer.
``His face scared me more than the whole six weeks we spent in
hiding.''
   Her husband's eyes were glazed, his expression frozen. His
silence didn't add to the tension, she said. It was the tension:
``He didn't know how to say goodbye.''
   Separated families were the result of Saddam Hussein's order
that foreign men not be allowed to leave after his invasion of
Kuwait in early August. Many are being used as shields against
attack.
   An estimated 930 Americans remain in Kuwait and 170 in Iraq, the
State Department says. At the time of the invasion, about 3,500
U.S. citizens were in either Iraq or Kuwait.
   Rande Vallekoop said goodbye to her husband, Laurens, soon after
sunrise on Aug. 25. Bolstered by a night of shared whispers and
prayers, the American woman avoided tears when she and the couple's
two young daughters left her husband behind at the U.S. Embassy in
Baghdad.
   ``I cried when I got to Turkey,'' said Mrs. Vallekoop, who
returned home to relatives in Minneapolis. ``The people that met us
at the border just kind of took us into their arms. It was so
difficult knowing he was still in there.''
   Mrs. Vallekoop and her husband, an employee at the U.S. Embassy
in Kuwait, were separated by Iraqi authorities after fleeing
Kuwait.
   ``We were notified that only the women and children would be
allowed to leave,'' Mrs. Vallekoop, 30, said recently. ``It was
totally heart-wrenching.''
   She has been able to speak periodically with her husband, who
remains stranded but able to communicate with her from the U.S.
Embassy in Baghdad.
   Bonnie Anderton hasn't had any word since parting with her
husband, Richard, an engineer. The image of him cooped up at the
besieged embassy in Kuwait is all she has to go on.
   And the picture isn't pretty. By the time Mrs. Anderton and her
10-year-old daughter left in August, embassy staff members had
already begun draining the swimming pool for drinking water.
   ``The food was spoiling ... and the Iraqi troops had completely
surrounded us,'' Mrs. Anderton, 40, said from Larkspur, Colo.
``It's the sort of thing where you make up your mind and you can't
even feel anything until later. Your first responsibility is to
your children.''
   At first, Kristine Knutson wasn't sure what was best for her
children.
   From her kitchen window in Kuwait, the Minnesota native with
four children under the age of 8 could hear bombs and see
helicopters swarming overhead.
   Mrs. Knutson, who asked that her maiden name be used to protect
her husband's identity, waited more than a month before finally
deciding that the only route she could take was out of the Middle
East.
   ``The windows at our house were covered. We couldn't answer the
door or the telephone. The kids had to stay indoors ... and it was
so hot,'' Mrs. Knutson said in a telephone interview last week from
Minneapolis.
   ``You couldn't find chicken, eggs, bread. I heard the medical
supplies were getting low, too,'' she said. ``I just kept thinking:
`I have to get my children out of here.' I knew I had to leave my
husband.''
   Now she, like the other displaced mothers, is thinking about how
to make ends meet. They are looking for jobs, getting their kids
into school, pushing back frightening thoughts of their husbands
for the sake of their kids.
   ``At night we all sleep together, the kids and me. They're
wonderful, but so little. It's not like snuggling up against your
big husband,'' said Mrs. Al-Qallef. ``I want my husband back.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0005 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 2356EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-SiouxJournalist     09-23 0547</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Sioux Journalist,0691</SECOND>
<HEAD>Sioux Publisher Brings Insights, Questions to Harvard</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ARLENE LEVINSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CAMBRIDGE, Mass. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   This is the world according to Tim
Giago:
   -Ellis Island was a gateway for invaders.
   -Tourists who visit Pine Ridge Reservation, his homeland in
South Dakota, are constantly deanding to see ``the real Indians.''
   -At a powwow he witnessed in Oxford, Mass., participants dressed
up in turkey feathers to improvise an Indian ritual they had never
learned.
   ``There are so many misconceptions, it's going to take the rest
of my life to get rid of them,'' said Giago, 55, an Oglala Sioux
who is the founding publisher of the award-winning Lakota Times of
Rapid City, S.D.
   Giago is taking a break from daily reporting on American Indians
to spend a year as a Nieman fellow at Harvard University.
   ``I have only one mission,'' Giago said. ``I started a newspaper
10 years ago because the media in the United States are totally
ignorant of who we are and what we are. If I relied on the
mainstream press to do our story from our perspective, it will
never happen.''
   Since the first Nieman class of journalists in 1938, there have
been 862 Niemans. Giago is the program's first American Indian
print journalist. There was one other American Indian Nieman, in
broadcasting.
   Fellows selected for the prestigious program spend a year at
Harvard studying whatever they wish and meeting in seminars. This
year's class has 22 journalists, half of them American.
   Giago said he hopes to enlighten his fellow scholars and the
Harvard staff on the Indian perspective.
   ``What I see here even, it's almost as if people believe that to
be Indian you're supposed to wear headdresses and live in a
teepee,'' Giago said in a recent interview. ``We're locked in a
certain time in history.''
   As a 17-year-old Navy recruit during the Korean War, Giago was
sent to California and put to work on a Navy newspaper.
   He later studied business and journalism at the University of
Nevada and worked for newspapers in New Mexico and South Dakota. He
became discouraged when editors said they didn't think he should
cover Indian matters because he might be biased.
   Giago said he recognized that before getting the Indian
viewpoint into the mainstream media, it would be necessary to
satisfy the needs of the country's 1.4 million Native Americans.
   His newspaper has a circulation of 11,000 on 24 reservations in
the Dakotas, Montana and Nebraska. ``Mine is a community newspaper
that reports everything important to Indian people,'' he said.
   Indians often bring a different perspective to national events,
he said.
   Take the melting pot that was celebrated recently with the
opening of an immigration museum in New York Harbor at Ellis
Island, where immigrants poured into this country in search of
freedom and opportunity.
   ``Ellis Island doesn't mean a damn thing to the American
Indian,'' Giago said. ``To us, it was another form of invasion.''
   Giago said he wants to establish a network of Indian newspapers
and expand the Lakota Times into a national publication.
   For two years after he founded his newspaper, the building was
firebombed and its windows were shot out. A gunman blasted the
windshield of his car after he wrote editorials critical of
militant Indians.
   Giago said he has been enraged again and again by newspaper or
TV coverage of Pine Ridge. Reporters catalog the problems of
alcoholism, poverty, violence and unemployment but never dig deep
enough to find the causes, he said.
   Giago's columns won him the coveted H.L. Mencken prize in 1985,
but he gave it back when Mencken's bigotry was revealed in the
posthumous publication of his diaries.
   Now he has set himself the challenge of bringing the Indian
point of view to the genteel setting of Harvard Yard.
   ``I don't come here as Tim Giago doing this as myself,'' he
said. ``I'm here as a member of the Oglala Sioux Tribe. What I
bring back will benefit the tribe.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0006 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 2357EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Algeria     09-23 0229</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Algeria,0248</SECOND>
<HEAD>President Dissolves Secret Police</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ALGIERS, Algeria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Chadli Bendjedid has ordered
Algeria's secret police dissolved in a move seen as a sign of his
wish to appease pro-democracy forces in this North African nation.
   The move comes on the eve of the return from exile this week of
former President Ahmed Ben Bella and about six months before
legislative elections that could give Algeria its first multiparty
Parliament in nearly 30 years.
   Ben Bella and other opposition leaders had called for the
dissolution of the secret police unit as a sign of real
democratization.
   In an announcement late Saturday, the government said the
General Delegation for Documentation and Security, known as the
DGDS, would be replaced by an intelligence branch dealing
exclusively with counter-espionnage.
   The existence of the secret police was only made official with
the resignation announcement Sept. 5 of its director, Gen. Mohammed
Betchine. He had been given the post after October 1988 riots.
   Scores of citizens, mainly youths, were killed in the riots,
which set in motion the process that is expected to lead to a
multiparty system.
   The National Liberation Front has ruled Algeria since its
independence from France in 1962. Ben Bella led the struggle but
was overthrown in a coup d'etat, imprisoned and sent into exile in
Switzerland.
   The main opposition group is currently the Islamic Salvation
Front, a Moslem fundamentalist group that won June 12 municipal and
provincial elections.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0007 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 1122EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-VegasIllusionists     09-23 0588</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Vegas Illusionists,0759</SECOND>
<HEAD>Famed Illusionists Mark 10,000th Show in Vegas</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT MACY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LAS VEGAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two decades ago, illusionists Siegfried &amp; Roy
were told to forget their dream of bringing their act to this
entertainment capital because ``magic doesn't work in Vegas.''
   Now, some 10,000 shows and tens of millions of dollars later,
they are the architects of one of America's hottest attractions,
the top draw in a city of stars, and are building on a dream to
save the rare white tiger.
   When Siegfried &amp; Roy take the stage at the Mirage Hotel Monday
night, it will mark the 10,000th live performance in the city they
have adopted as their home. By comparison, the longest running show
on Broadway, ``A Chorus Line,'' closed this year after 6,137
performances.
   Today Siegfried Fishbacher and Roy Horn rank No. 27 on Forbes
magazine's list of highest-paid performers, ahead of the likes of
Frank Sinatra, Tom Cruise and the rock group U2. They're forecast
to earn $28 million in the two-year period ending in December.
   But it was a different story 20 years ago when the two
illusionists, who met and formed their act on a cruise ship, tried
to break into the Las Vegas market.
   ``Don't tell me you're a magician because magic doesn't work in
Las Vegas,'' a jaded Tropicana Hotel official told the pair before
reluctantly giving them a short contract.
   ``All my confidence was gone,'' Siegfried said during an
interview at the pair's walled estate, where they keep a menagerie
of animals used in their act and breed white tigers. ``But when I
performed here the first time, I knew it was meant to be.''
   History has proven the pair right, and their performance is
proving Mirage owner Steve Wynn something of a prophet.
   Wynn announced three years ago he was signing the pair to a
$57.5 million, five-year contract as the star attraction when his
new $630 million Strip resort opened. The mammoth pact prompted
some skepticism of whether Wynn could make their magic pay.
   The skepticism was short-lived when Siegfried &amp; Roy began
packing the new 1,500-seat, $50 million Theatre Mirage two shows a
night Feb. 1. The show's producer, Kenneth Feld, said Siegfried &amp;
Roy will gross $30 million their first year at the Mirage.
   They spent eight months performing in Japan in 1988-89.
   ``The Japanese really spoiled us,'' Roy said, taking a break in
a breakfast room overlooking a pool where some of their white
tigers played. ``After one performance they continued to applaud
for an hour and eight minutes. It was unbelievable.''
   The performers returned from Japan for a record-breaking stint
at Radio City Music Hall in New York City before heading back to
Las Vegas.
   The extravagant, Broadway-type production mixes spectacular
illusions such as a woman appearing to be turned into a 750-pound
white tiger with singing and dancing by a 170-member cast. But the
show is not the only interest of the two stars.
   Preservation of the white tiger - a beautiful animal first
sighted in the Himalayas 200 years ago and now nearing extinction -
is a major goal for Siegfried &amp; Roy.
   In 1987, zoo officials said there were only about 100 white
tigers in the world. All were in captivity.
   ``The white tigers are our living legacy,'' Roy said. Their
collection of 23 whites, including five snow white tigers, is the
largest in the world. The performers have started an exchange
program with a West German zoo, and are working with the Cincinnati
Zoo on a white tiger breeding program.
   Six rare white tigers were born while the performers were in
Japan. Three of them, named Red, White and Blue, were born on July
4, 1989.
   The white tigers romp and swim at their compound, on the
northwest side of Las Vegas, and at an 80-acre ranch on the
outskirts of the city.
   The animals also spend some time, two or three at a time, in an
elaborate glassed-in habitat at the Mirage, where millions of
people have viewed the animals since the hotel opened in November
1989.
   Siegfried's most poignant memory?
   When two white tigers were born at the entertainers compound,
and their mother, Sitarra, placed each of the cubs in Roy's lap
after they were born - a touching display of trust between animal
and man.
   ``This was the most magical moment of my life,'' Siegfried said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0008 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 1138EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-RivieraFires     09-23 0215</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Riviera Fires,0219</SECOND>
<HEAD>Thousands of Firefighters Battle Blazes in South of France</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DRAGUIGNAN, France (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Thousands of firefighters fought
Sunday to stamp out three blazes ravaging the Mediterranean forest
and destroying coastal homes. But the high winds and bone-dry
tinderland hindered their efforts.
   The 2,500 firefighters and soldiers, backed by 13 planes dousing
the forests, stopped the flames from spreading. But the fires
continued to devastate the areas already touched, fire authorities
said.
   They said 27,180 acres of land had been burned since Friday in
the Var region.
   Three separate fires continued to rage. One of them, which
started Saturday, entered the inland town of Draguignan, destroying
some homes and forcing the evacuation of three neighborhoods as
bottles of gas exploded from the heat, officials said.
   High winds, sometimes reaching 50 mph, coupled with tinderland
baked dry by a drought complicated the firefighters' task,
officials said.
   About 1,000 homes, most of them around the coastal town of
Sainte-Maxime, were without telephone service after flames
destroyed telephone poles and 18 miles of cable, France Telecom
said.
   Sainte-Maxime and nearby Roquebrune-sur-Argens were the site of
the fiercest blazes, with about 20,000 acres of land destroyed.
   Fires, some the result of arson, have already devoured tens of
thousands of acres of Mediterranean forest this summer.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0009 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 1158EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-US-SouthAfrica Bjt   09-23 0523</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-US-South Africa, Bjt,600</SECOND>
<HEAD>De Klerk Arrives for First US-South African Summit in 45 Years</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Aside from early evening EDT photo op with Vice President Dan
Quayle, there are no public events on de Klerk's schedule for
Sunday. This should stand.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By GEORGE GEDDA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   South African President F.W. de Klerk arrived
Sunday for talks with President Bush on ways in which the United
States can help that country bring about a peaceful transition to a
non-racial system.
   But the visit, the highlight of which will be a lengthy White
House discussion on Monday, has been clouded by an upsurge of
violence that has claimed more than 750 lives in black South
African townships in recent weeks.
   Still, Bush's encounter with de Klerk is something of a
milestone in U.S.-South African relations. No South African head of
state has visited Washington since 1945 and the two countries were
barely on speaking terms as recently as a few years ago.
   De Klerk said on arrival Sunday he was bringing a message of
hope for the future of his country and for all of southern Africa.
   ``We are proceeding irreversibly on the road to a new South
Africa, where justice, the guarantees of constitutional democracy
and the rule of law will bring lasting peace and prosperity to all
our people,'' de Klerk said.
   His stay here ends Tuesday night.
   A senior administration official who briefed reporters on Friday
said the invitation to de Klerk recognizes the ``bold leadership''
he has provided in seeking a way out of the apartheid era in South
Africa.
   During the talks, Bush will explore ``what role the United
States can play in helping to promote the negotiating process in
that country,'' said the official, speaking on condition of
anonymity.
   ``Our interest is to promote a peaceful transition, through
negotiations, to a post-apartheid, democratic, non-racial South
Africa,'' he said. Congress has approved $10 million to give
impetus to the negotiating process.
   The official said the visit was not designed to bring about an
end to the economic sanctions the United States imposed against
South Africa in 1986. South Africa has fulfilled some but not all
of the requirements the legislation imposes for the sanctions to be
lifted.
   The sanctions included a ban on new U.S. investment in South
Africa and suspension of landing rights for South African planes in
the United States.
   Officials have said the sanctions can be lifted once South
Africa's remaining political prisoners are released and the state
of emergency is lifted in Natal Province. Emergency rule was ended
elsewhere in South Africa earlier this year.
   De Klerk said Saturday before his departure from Pretoria that
the sanctions will not be a major focus of his visit.
   ``I'm not going hat in hand with the particular objective of
getting sanctions lifted,'' he said.
   De Klerk will meet with congressional leaders, but the
Congressional Black Caucus announced Saturday it had canceled a
scheduled meeting with de Klerk, saying only that the decision was
in response to ``recent developments in South Africa and after
extensive consultation with anti-apartheid activists.''
   The decision may have been related to the recent upsurge in
violence in the black townships. African National Congress leader
Nelson Mandela, who was here in late June, has held pro-apartheid
security elements of the police and military responsible and said
that Americans should demand from de Klerk an explanation for this
situation.
   South African officials themselves have not dismissed this
possibility.
   The Lawyer's Committee for Civil Rights Under Law, a private,
Washington-based group, has challenged de Klerk to ensure that
``police and military assassination squads are fully exposed and
completely disbanded.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0010 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 1209EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--SaudiHoliday     09-23 0119</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Saudi Holiday,0103</SECOND>
<HEAD>Celebrations Of Saudi National Day Canceled</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf Rdp, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>RIYADH, Saudi Arabia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Saudi Arabia canceled all official
celebrations of the kingdom's National Day holiday Sunday as a
gesture of solidarity with the Kuwaiti people.
   The official Saudi Press Agency said a statement from the royal
court had informed Saudi embassies worldwide to refrain from
official celebrations because of the suffering endured by the
Kuwaiti people since the Aug. 2 Iraqi invasion.
   National Day, the government's official day to celebrate the
1932 consolidation of power by King Adbul Aziz, is traditionally
celebrated with parades and festivals.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0011 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 1218EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-Egypt     09-23 0177</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Egypt,0191</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mubarak Orders Inquiry Into Deaths of Egyptians in Iraq</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf Rdp, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CAIRO, Egypt (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Hosni Mubarak has ordered an
inquiry into the deaths of at least 24 Egyptians that Egypt says
were killed in Iraq in recent months.
   Interior Minister Abdel-Halim Moussa said Iraqi authorities have
tried to cover up the slayings by wrapping up the bodies in coffins
or claiming they died naturally from internal bleeding or skull
fractures. He said some of the victims were slain on the
Iraqi-Jordanian border.
   There was no immediate word from Baghdad.
   Tens of thousands of Egyptians have fled into Jordan since Iraq
invaded Kuwait on Aug. 2. Egypt has about 5,000 troops in Saudi
Arabia as part of a U.S.-led multinational force that is enforcing
a U.N. trade embargo on Iraq.
   Moussa said Mubarak's order for an investigation was made at a
meeting Saturday. He said the 24 bodies have been returned from
Iraq since the Iraqi invasion.
   In a statement to the state-owned newspaper Al-Ahram, Moussa
said his ministry has reliable information that all of them were
killed by the Iraqis.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0012 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 1225EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-DangerfieldTrial Bjt   09-23 0562</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Dangerfield Trial, Bjt,0699</SECOND>
<HEAD>Comedian Out For Respect, Gets Little In Injury Trial</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY12</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TIM DAHLBERG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LAS VEGAS, Nev. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Comedian Rodney Dangerfield says he just
wants to make people laugh, but lawyers for a casino-hotel have
portrayed him as a foul-mouthed malingerer with a vindictive
streak.
   ``You're trying to make me out to be a liar and I'm not,''
Dangerfield said at one point during three days of often combative
testimony in his $5 million lawsuit against Caesars Palace.
   For the last two weeks, Dangerfield and Caesars Palace have been
locked in a bitter court fight over an eye injury the comedian says
he suffered in a steam bath when a burst of steam hit him in the
face in March 1988.
   Jurors are expected to decide sometime this week whether the man
who gets no respect suffered lasting eye damage or whether Caesars,
which filed a countersuit, should be compensated because he missed
five shows.
   ``The injuries were a figment of his fertile comedic
imagination,'' said Caesars attorney Louis Meisinger, who called
the 68-year-old comic a ``petulant performer'' in opening
arguments.
   Dangerfield, known for film comedies such as ``Caddyshack'' and
``Back to School'' as well as his standup act, wasn't in a funny
mood.
   ``The last thing I wanted was to be involved in this,'' he said.
``I'm happy when I'm writing jokes and making people laugh.''
   Dangerfield said he was determined to win his battle against the
resort where he once starred before sold-out audiences. Since the
accident, he has worked at Ballys.
   ``It's very costly for me to do this but I had to do it because
I know I'm right,'' Dangerfield said. ``I'm not trying to get even
with anybody, but I wasn't treated right and I couldn't walk away
from this.''
   Dangerfield complained on the witness stand that Caesars
executives didn't fully believe he was injured in the incident
following the opening night of a week-long performance.
   ``I was shocked at how they would handle this thing,''
Dangerfield testified. ``I never heard of such a lack of compassion
in my life.''
   He skipped four performances, claiming his eyes were too
sensitive to light to perform.
   After returning for two shows, he walked offstage without
performing on closing night, miffed at Caesars for wanting to
withhold his $45,000-a-show fee for the nights he missed.
   ``I just couldn't be funny for these people,'' said Dangerfield,
who advised the showroom crowd of 1,200 to get refunds, even for
any tips they gave showroom workers.
   Caesars introduced evidence showing Dangerfield went to the
fights one night he didn't perform, and to see a comedy show
another night.
   A doctor who examined him after the steam incident said he
thought Dangerfield could perform.
   Eye specialists testified that symptoms Dangerfield claims he
has had since the accident first appeared in the mid-1970s. They
said Dangerfield may have hurt himself further by his repeated use
over the years of a topical anesthetic used in surgery on his eyes.
   If Dangerfield thought he was treated roughly in court, it could
have been worse.
   Caesars attorneys filed documents with the court alleging he was
a chronic drinker who frequently used marijuana and cocaine.
   U.S. District Judge Roger Foley ruled against allowing evidence
of substance abuse to be presented to jurors, but allowed testimony
that portrayed Dangerfield as being in a drunken stupor following
the accident.
   The testimony came in the form of a deposition from an aspiring
screenwriter. Jeffrey Schimmel said he met Dangerfield the day of
the accident and stayed with him in New York for several months
while they worked on a script.
   Schimmel, who admitted having a fallout with Dangerfield over
the script, testified that the comedian never complained of his eye
injury and instead seemed to be on a vendetta against Caesars.
   ``He was very vindictive,'' Schimmel said. ``He didn't care how
much it cost or how much trouble it cost him. He said it would cost
them (Caesars) a lot more. He wanted to teach Caesars Palace a
lesson.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0013 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 1230EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SouthAfrica     09-23 0556</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-South Africa,0651</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mandela: Police Measures Timed for De Klerk's U.S. Visit</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-US-South Africa, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TOM COHEN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JOHANNESBURG, South Africa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Nelson Mandela said Sunday
that new police measures in violence-plagued black townships were
timed to create an appearance of calm during President F.W. de
Klerk's trip to Washington.
   ``They pretend de Klerk has put an end to the violence,'' said
Mandela, leader of the African National Congress. ``That's not
true.''
   Mandela also said ANC president Oliver Tambo, recovering from a
stroke in Sweden, would attend an ANC congress in South Africa
scheduled for Dec. 16. Tambo has been in exile for more than 25
years.
   ANC officials have said they don't expect Tambo to resume full
control of the organization. Mandela, as deputy presidnet, is
considered the de facto leader.
   De Klerk arrived Sunday in Washington to begin a three-day trip.
He is the first South African leader in decades to visit the United
States, which has imposed economic sanctions to protest the
apartheid system of racial segregation and white dominance.
   ``South Africa has embarked on a great journey,'' de Klerk said
upon arrival. ``It is a journey toward full democracy at home, and
abroad, full participation in the family of nations.''
   De Klerk has pledged to end apartheid and led the government in
talks with the ANC on power-sharing.
   His trip comes after weeks of violence in black townships around
Johannesburg that has killed about 800 people.
   The fighting has pitted Zulu supporters of the conservative
Inkatha movement against Xhosas and other blacks linked to the ANC.
It spread to the townships in early August from eastern Natal
Province, the traditional Zulu homeland, where 5,000 blacks have
died in five years of factional fighting.
   Police reported the townships quiet Sunday, continuing a lull in
the violence. But police said two off-duty constables were stoned
to death in a dispute with taxi drivers in Natal. It was not known
if the killings were linked to the ongoing Inkatha-ANC rivalry.
   Mandela and other black leaders have blamed police and soldiers
for instigating the township fighting by using unnecessary force
and siding with Inkatha supporters. The government denies the
charges.
   Mandela also has warned that the government's failure to stop
the fighting could jeopardize the peace talks, which started in
May.
   But he said Sunday the white-led government and ANC were
``compelled to work together through thick and thin'' for peaceful
change in South Africa.
   Another black opposition movement, the radical Pan-Africanist
Congress, put off a decision on the government's invitation for
direct talks on ending apartheid and sharing power with the black
majority.
   The group said Sunday after a leadership meeting in Zimbabwe its
``grassroots branches'' in South Africa would make the decision
before a national conference scheduled for November.
   It has previously rejected proposed power-sharing, saying the
only subject for negotiation was the transfer of power to blacks.
   The new police measures, code-named ``Operation Iron Fist,''
included roadblocks, weapons searches, more police and military
reinforcements, and isolating flash points such as worker hostels
and squatter camps with razor wire.
   An overnight curfew in some black townships is scheduled to take
effect Tuesday.
   Some 3,000 people marched Saturday on municipal government
offices in Soweto to protest the police measures.
   Mandela has said the measures were intended to leave blacks
powerless and would fail.
   ``We hope the government will come to its senses to solve the
violence not through iron fist, but by putting their arms away,''
he said Sunday.
   Gerrit Viljoen, the minister of constitutional development, said
Saturday the ANC bears responsibility for the faction fighting and
should stop blaming white authorities.
   Government officials said before de Klerk's departure that they
believe the ANC rejected the police measures to try to undermine
the trip.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0014 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 1237EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Pope-Mafia     09-23 0237</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Pope-Mafia,0267</SECOND>
<HEAD>Pope Urges Italians to Unite Against Mafia</HEAD>
<DATELINE>FERRARA, Italy (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Pope John Paul II on Sunday deplored the
assassination of a Sicilian judge who had been investigating the
Mafia and urged Italians to unite in the fight against organized
crime.
   The pontiff, on a two-day visit to this city in northeastern
Italy, departed from his prepared speeches to express regret over
Friday's slaying of judge Rosario Livantino.
   The 38-year-old magistrate, who had been investigating Mafia
activities for 10 years, was ambushed and shot to death as he drove
to his office in Agrigento, Sicily. Police are focusing their
investigation on several Mafia clans.
   Speaking to a crowd of tens of thousands of people following an
open-air Mass in central Ferrara, John Paul said the killing was a
``very grave incident of criminality which unfortunately adds to
the list of many acts of violence committed recently'' in Italy.
   ``All Italians, I ask you at this moment to show firmness and
courage to stem the growing threat coming from the culture of
death,'' the pope said.
   ``Enough with (the spilling of) innocent blood, enough with
mourning and suffering,'' he said. ``May all the forces of the
country unite to proclaim aloud the will to live peacefully and to
build a society respectful of man and his dignity.''
   President Francesco Cossiga, meanwhile, told reporters Sunday
that organized crime ``seems to have taken control of part of the
national territory.''
   ``It's not a matter of common crime, but an attack on the
security of the state and the republic,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0015 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 1246EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-SuperpowerorSuperpaup Bjt   09-23 0639</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Superpower or Superpauper, Bjt,760</SECOND>
<HEAD>Will Debt Crisis Erode U.S. Ability To Act Overseas?</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   By JIM DRINKARD&equals;
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The crisis in the Persian Gulf has intensified
a new American dilemma: how a country can at once be a superpower
and a superpauper.
   Experts agree the United States is the only nation that can
project its military power throughout the world. Yet it also is the
world's largest debtor nation, facing a staggering annual deficit,
and now the risk of recession.
   Paying the price for the international effort to squeeze Iraq
makes a difficult situation even worse - and the Bush
administration signaled last week it would turn to unconventional
means: direct aid from allies.
   No sooner had Secretary of State James A. Baker III and Treasury
Secretary Nicholas Brady returned home with billions of dollars in
allied aid pledges than a top State Department official said
President Bush would rely increasingly on such approaches.
   ``A kind of a new invention in the practice of diplomacy,''
Deputy Secretary of State Lawrence Eagleburger described it. ``I
would expect you will see this administration approaching foreign
policy questions more and more in that direction.''
   The shift was welcomed in Congress, where lawmakers are
struggling to find room in a deficit-ridden budget to provide
additional foreign aid to emerging democracies in Eastern Europe
and Central America.
   ``It's not a question of being mercenaries, or
`rent-a-superpower,''' said Sen. Richard Lugar, R-Ind.
   ``We are the only ones who can do this ... at this moment. We
are unique,'' Lugar said of massive, U.S.-led effort against Iraq's
Aug. 2 invasion of Kuwait.
   Some, however, questioned the new strategy.
   ``This is a Band-Aid approach,'' said Robert Kurz, a former
congressional foreign policy aide who now is at Brookings
Institution. ``It's a very, very shortsighted view of the nature of
the crisis.''
   But that was not the prevailing view in Congress - as long as
lawmakers maintain control of the purse strings.
   Rep. David Obey, D-Wis., acknowledged the need for outside help
and said it may be necessary again in the future ``for limited
purposes, for a limited period.''
   Obey added, however, that the dependence on other countries
limits U.S. flexibility. He blamed it on budget deficits run up
under the last administration that have left foreign capital to
finance U.S. debt, the world's largest.
   ``The Reagan budget deficits and trade deficits have drained
this country of the ability to control its own policy and its own
destiny,'' he said.
   Whatever the cause, the United States is confronted not only
with the sudden costs of a massive military deployment in the gulf,
estimated at $15 billion over the coming year, but with the need to
help allies who have been militarily and economically threatened by
the crisis.
   In addition, the United States owes some $500 million in unpaid
past dues to the United Nations, an embarrassing situation at a
time when Bush has relied on the world body as the hub of his
diplomatic efforts against Iraq.
   Baker and Brady returned home with $20 billion in pledges.
Roughly half of that will go to aid countries harmed by the United
Nations embargo imposed against Iraq. The other half will go to
offset U.S. costs.
   Bush wants to forgive $6.7 billion in Egyptian debt as a means
of rewarding Egyptian President Hosni Mubarak's leadership in the
gulf crisis; frontline states such as Turkey and Jordan have been
hit hard economically by the Iraqi embargo; and Israel is claiming
the need for new weapons to maintain its security in the
increasingly volatile region.
   To some analysts, using the solicitation of other countries as
any kind of long-term method of financing foreign policy represents
yet another evasion of American money problems.
   ``We have a very strong interest in much higher levels of
foreign aid, and much lower levels of military spending,'' said
Kurz of the Brookings. ``The world has changed, but we are having a
hard time accommodating to it.''
   The United States is the world's only remaining superpower, now
that the Soviet Union is withdrawing from its empire and focusing
on domestic problems, Kurz said. It has the only military force
which can be quickly projected around the world.
   In the future, threats to U.S. interests are more likely to come
from third-world conflicts such as the clash between Iraq and
Kuwait than from the traditional bipolar rivalry with the Soviet
Union, he said.
   It would be much cheaper to head off those problems through
increased foreign aid and trade than to intervene militarily, but
the United States has not yet gotten used to the idea, said Kurz.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0016 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 1254EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-TeacherStrike     09-23 0492</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Teacher Strike,0592</SECOND>
<HEAD>New Orleans Teachers Say Central Strike Issue is Dignity, Not
Money</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NU1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JANET McCONNAUGHEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW ORLEANS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The picket signs read ``No raise, no work.''
But for many of the 3,000 teachers on strike in New Orleans, it's a
matter of toilet paper, discipline and dignity.
   ``When teachers strike, you know it's more than just the pay. If
all it was was money, they wouldn't be teaching in the first
place,'' said Mike Stone, an English teacher at McMain Magnet
Secondary School.
   United Teachers of New Orleans, which represents the New Orleans
Parish's 4,420 teachers and 1,100 teachers' aides and secretaries,
went on strike Sept. 17. The district kept schools open with
substitutes and a little more than 1,600 regular teachers who
crossed picket lines last week. On Friday, 62,277 of the district's
estimated 85,000 students attended classes.
   Union officials say a dispute over who would bear the burden of
$400,000 in health insurance costs - the teachers or the district -
triggered last week's walkout that has disrupted education in the
state's largest school district.
   But New Orleans Parish teachers on the picket lines say the
issues are not only increased insurance costs, but poor working
conditions, discipline and the feeling that many parents regard
them as overpaid baby sitters.
   One picket at Lafayette Elementary School last week wrapped her
sign in toilet paper. ``Dr. Williams, yes it's true. We provide
toilet paper. Here's some for you,'' proclaimed the sign addressed
to Superintendent Everett Williams.
   Other teachers have complained of spending as much as $500 a
year of their own money to buy paper, workbooks and other
instructional supplies.
   District officials deny such charges.
   ``I can assure you there's enough hand towels and toilet tissue
in New Orleans public schools. Teachers are not buying them out of
their private funds in any numbers that I know of,'' said the
district's chief negotiator, Frank Fudesco.
   ``The reason is money,'' school board spokesman Henry Joubert
said flatly.
   Teachers also complained that the administration isn't backing
them on discipline of students and wastes money on adminstrators
who drive new cars equipped with telephones.
   ``Students are hitting teachers,'' said Ann Legaux who teaches
gifted children at Fannie Williams Middle School. ``Do you think
they're going to be expelled, as it says in the handbook? No.
They're back the next day.''
   District officials refused to discuss student discipline
policies. However, the district said the cars in question are two
years old, are leased and needed by seven administrators whose jobs
require regular visits to schools around the city.
   Before last week's strike, teachers had dropped earlier demands
for 10 percent pay raises, saying they would settle instead for
having the district provide $1 million to cover half of a
$300-per-person increase in health insurance costs. Management
offered $600,000, saying that was all the district could afford.
   After the walkout, teachers reinstated their demand for 10
percent raises as well as the $1 million insurance package.
   Salaries range from $19,455 for a starting teacher to $35,111
for someone with a doctorate and 25 years experience.
   But the teachers insist the real issue is respect.
   ``The real problem is the school board and top administration,''
said Ellen Picou, a school librarian. ``We're on the picket line
here on Claiborne Avenue because the school board ... has no idea
how teachers feel.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0017 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 1303EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-India-CasteViolence     09-23 0424</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-India-Caste Violence,0504</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rash of Suicide Attempts Over Jobs Policy Continues</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW DELHI, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An unemployed upper-caste man tried to
posion himself Sunday to protest a new policy reserving federal
jobs for low-caste Hindus. The policy has set off a wave of suicide
attempts.
   Jatinder Vaid of Ambala, about 130 miles north of New Delhi, ate
some ``poisonous tablets,'' but survived after being taken to a
hospital, Press Trust of India reported.
   On Friday, Vaid had tried to jump into a bus set on fire by
rampaging students, but was rescued by friends, the agency
reported.
   Another news agency, United News of India, said Akhilesh Pandey,
a student in the central town of Gwalior, doused his body with
kerosene Saturday and tried to burn himself, but was stopped in
time.
   The suicide attempt triggered anti-government riots in the
industrial town, about 170 miles southeast of New Delhi.
   Troops have been deployed in at least four areas to control mobs
that have destroyed vehicles and burned government buildings to
protest the decision to reserve 49 percent of federal jobs for
low-caste Hindus. Another 5 percent to 10 percent of the jobs will
be reserved for the poor, regardless of their caste.
   The government says the affirmative action program will help
Indianswwho have suffered for centuries under the rigid caste
system, which sets social levels.
   Opponents of the policy say qualified students of higher castes
will lose the coveted government jobs to unqualified workers. The
government employs about 18 million people.
   At least 25 people have died in clashes with police since Aug. 7
when Prime Minister V.P. Singh announced the policy.
   In the Hindu holy city of Kurukshetra, about 95 miles north of
New Delhi, a a 16-year-old high school student died Saturday after
eating insecticide. A suicide note by Sushil Kumar blamed the
incident on the jobs policy, police said in Chandigarh.
   Chandigarh police had initially reported that Kumar was 23 years
old and that he burned himself to death. Police officials Sunday
said the erroneous report was based on information received from
the remote town.
   On Saturday, about 14 students in the western Rajasthan state
tried to burn themselves with kerosene, but were stopped by police,
the Hindustan Times newspaper reported. It said some of the
students also jumped into a bonfire of effigies of government
ministers, but were pulled out.
   The first student to attempt suicide over the jobs policy,
Rajeev Goswami, was in critical condition in a New Delhi hospital
Sunday with burns over 55 percent of his body. The 20-year-old
student set himself ablaze with kerosene on Wednesday.
   Thousands of students continued a sit-in for the third day
Sunday outside Safdarjang hospital where Goswami is admitted. The
students have set up camp on a road outside the hospital, blocking
traffic between southern residential neighborhood and central
districts.
   On Sunday, the Delhi University said it was closing until
Wednesday because of the ``volatile situation.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0018 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 1308EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-GulfForces-List     09-23 0895</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf Forces-List,1111</SECOND>
<HEAD>Opposing Forces in the Gulf</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf Rdp, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NICOSIA, Cyprus (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here is a breakdown of the opposing
forces in the Persian Gulf:
   ---
   IRAQ:
   Baghdad has fifty-five army divisions with an estimated 555,000
regular troops and 480,000 reserves. Regular forces include seven
divisions of elite Republican Guards. Iraq claims a militia called
the Popular Army has 5 million men.
   Baghdad's armory has 5,500 tanks, 3,500 heavy artillery guns;
200 multiple rocket launchers; an estimated 500 surface-to-surface
missiles; 330 surface-to-air missile launchers; 500-plus combat
airctaft, including Soviet-supplied long-range Su-24
fighter-bombers and advanced MiG-29 interceptors.
   It main naval units are a training frigate with anti-submarine
torpedoes, an estimated eight Soviet-built missile-attack craft and
six torpedo boats.
   In Kuwait, Iraq has an estimated 10 divisions, four of them
armored, totaling 170,000 troops, 1,500 T-55 and T-62 tanks and 700
artillery pieces. A further 150,000 men, including the seven
Republican Guard divisions with up to 1,300 tanks and 750 guns, are
dug in in southern Iraq. Silkworm anti-ship missiles are believed
to have been deployed to counter any U.S. amphibious landing in
Kuwait.
   ---
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   The multinational force that is facing Iraq includes:
   
   UNITED STATES: Officials say more than 165,000 troops, including
those aboard ships, are in the gulf region or en route. Deployments
could go as high as 250,000 in the biggest U.S. military operation
since Vietnam.
   Ground forces include the 82nd ``All American'' Airborne
Division, the 101st ``Screaming Eagles'' Airborne Division, the
24th Mechanized Infantry Division, with some 200 M-1 Abrams tanks
and 300 Bradley Fighting Vehicles, the 11th Air Defense Artillery
Brigade, 197th Mechanized Infantry Brigade and the 3rd Armored
Cavalry Regiment.
   Amphibious capability is provided by 45,000 men of the 1st, 4th
and 6th Marine Expeditionary Brigades. There is a Special Forces
contingent from the 1st Special Operations Command.
   The U.S. deployment is expected to be complete by late October,
when the Americans will have around 1,000 tanks in Saudi Arabia.
   More than 50 U.S. warships are in the gulf, the Arabian Sea and
the eastern Mediterranean, including the aircraft carriers
Indepndence, Saratoga and John F. Kennedy. Another seven ships are
expected in the Mediterranean.
   The Pentagon has also sent 22 F117A Stealth fighter-bombers to
unspecified bases, 14 long-range F-111F bombers to Incirlik
airbase, in southwest Turkey, and another squadron to Spain.
   
   BRITAIN: It has 10 ships in the gulf, ships, including a missile
destroyer, two missile frigates and three minesweepers.
   Three squadrons of Tornado and Jaguar interceptors and ground
attack jets are in Saudi Arabia, Bahrain and Oman. At lease one
more Tornado squadron will arrive soon. Three Nimrod maritime
reconnaisance aircraft are in Oman.
   The British force totals 3,000 personnel, with 2,000 logistics
personnel at a staging post in Cyprus, where the British have
sovereign bases.
   The 7th Armored Brigade, successors to the famous ``Desert
Rats'' of World War II, will arrive late next month with 120
Challenger tanks and 6,000 troops.
   FRANCE: It has some 14 ships, with an estimated 8,000 men, are
in the gulf or en route, including the carrier Clemenceau with 42
combat helicopters, a guided-missile cruiser, two missile
destroyers, two frigates and one corvette. The fleet tanker Var is
also being deployed.
   A company of 190 paratroopers equipped for chemical warfare is
in the United Arab Emirates.
   France is sending three squadrons of interceptors and
fighter-bombers. The first elements of a 4,000-man rapid deployment
force arrived in Saudi Arabia on Sunday. French strength will rise
to 13,000 when the deployment is completed.
   
   SOVIET UNION: It has sent the Udaloy-class destroyer Admiral
Tributs and an anti-submarine ship to the Gulf of Oman. Moscow has
indicated it would send ground forces, but only under U.N. command.
   
   GREECE: Greece has sent its most advanced frigate, the Limnos,
to the eastern Mediterranean.
   
   ITALY: The frigates Libeccio and Orsa and a support ship, the
Stromboli, are in the gulf. Two corvettes are in the eastern
Mediterranean. Italy says it will send an another warship and eight
Tornado fighter jets.
   
   NETHERLANDS: Two frigates are in the Gulf of Oman. A combat
supply ship is expected there in November.
   
   WEST GERMANY: Bonn is providing merchant ships to transport U.S.
troops to Saudi Arabia and has committed $2 billion toward the
multinational force. West Germany's constitution prohibits it
committing military forces.
   
   SPAIN: The frigate Santa Maria is in the Gulf of Oman. Two
corvettes are in the southern Red Sea.
   
   DENMARK: It has sent a corvette to the gulf region.
   
   NORWAY: It will send a coast guard cutter to support the Danish
corvette. Norway has offered anti-chemical warfare equipment.
   
   AUSTRALIA: Two guided-missile frigates and a supply ship are in
the gulf region.
   
   BELGIUM: Two minehunters and a supply ship are in the Gulf of
Oman.
   
   CANADA: Two destroyers and a supply ship are heading for the
gulf. A squadron of 12 fighter jets will be sent.
   
   ARGENTINA: A destroyer and a frigate sailed for the gulf
Saturday and are expected to arrive mid-October.
   ---
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Allied Arab Forces:
   
   GULF COOPERATION COUNCIL (Saudi Arabia, Bahrain, Oman, United
Arab Emirates, Qatar and, until Aug. 2, Kuwait): A rapid deployment
force of up to 10,000 troops is based at Hafer al-Batin, northeast
Saudi Arabia and 40 miles south of the Kuwait border.
   It has been beefed up with some 7,000 soldiers of Kuwait's
20,000-man who escaped their country when Iraq invaded.
   The GCC and other local Arab forces in the Gulf total around
144,500 men, 330 combat aircraft, 800 tanks and 36 major naval
units.
   They are supported by:
   
  EGYPT: It has pledged up to 30,000 troops with tanks and heavy
artillery. Some 5,000 troops, including paratroopers, commandos,
chemical warfare specialists and infantry, are in Saudi Arabia and
several thousands more from the 15,000-man 4th Infantry Division
are en route. Five hundred troops are in the U.A.E.
   
   PAKISTAN: Pledged to send 5,000 troops, and 2,000 have been sent
to the U.A.E.
   
   MOROCCO: 1,200 troops in Saudi Arabia and 500 in the U.A.E.
   
   SYRIA: 4,000 troops, mostly special forces, sent to Saudi
Arabia, and is planning to send 15,000 more. Some troops are based
in the U.A.E.
   
   BANGLADESH: 3,000 troops pledged. 2,000 are in Saudi Arabia.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0019 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 1308EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BRF--SmallQuakes     09-23 0152</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Small Quakes,0154</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tremors Rattle Northern California But Cause No Injuries or Damage</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Two mild earthquakes rattled Northern California over the
weekend but caused no injuries or damage, authorities said Sunday.
   A temblor registering 3.0 on the Richter scale occurred on the
San Francisco Peninsula at 6:36 a.m. Sunday, the state Office of
Emergency Services said. It was centered seven miles southwest of
Menlo Park, 23 miles south of San Francisco.
   A 4.0 quake occurred at 8 p.m. Saturday three miles south of San
Juan Bautista, about 35 miles south of San Francisco, the office of
Emergency Services said.
   The readings for both quakes, measured by the U.S. Geological
Survey, were preliminary, the state office said.
   Scientists say a quake measuring 3.0 on the Richter scale of
ground motion can cause slight damage in the immediate area and a
4.0 quake can cause moderate damage.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0020 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 1309EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Cambodia     09-23 0213</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Cambodia,0241</SECOND>
<HEAD>Cambodia's Prime Minister Replaced In Second Job As Foreign
Minister</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BANGKOK, Thailand (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hun Sen has been replaced as Cambodia's
foreign minister, and the country's official radio said the change
was made to give him more time for his duties as prime minister.
   The new foreign minister is Hor Nam Hong, who had been a
minister in charge of foreign affairs in the prime minister's
office.
   The Communist Party Politburo made the decision Monday to try to
ease Hun Sen's duties, said the broadcast, a text of which was seen
in Bangkok on Sunday.
   The change comes as the government, which Vietnam installed in a
1978 invasion, is involved in crucial peace talks with three
guerrilla groups.
   The first meeting of a council helping to oversee Cambodia's
transition to an elected government collapsed last week in a
dispute over the future role of resistance leader Prince Norodom
Sihanouk. Sihanouk later asked his guerrilla allies to yield to the
government demand on the issue.
   Thailand has said it would agree to be the host of another
meeting of the Supreme National Council. The council was formed
under a U.N. peace plan is to work with the world body to end an
11-year-old civil war.
   Cambodian radio also announced the transfer of the deputy
foreign minister, Dit Munti, to chairman of the Central Propaganda
and Education Commission. No reason was given for the move.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0021 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 1316EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-WorldBank-ChinaEconom     09-23 0421</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-World Bank-China Economy,450</SECOND>
<HEAD>West Reported Receptive Toward Resuming Credit for China</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GENE KRAMER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Western nations have become more receptive to
Japanese efforts to resume international lending to China which was
halted in 1989 because of Beijing's brutal crackdown on
pro-democracy demonstrators.
   ``Our European friends expressed readiness to increase the
possibility of loans to China,'' said Ryutaro Hashimoto, Japan's
finance minister, following a weekend meeting of the Group of
Seven, the world's wealthiest industrial countries.
   The group which includes the United States, Japan, West Germany
Britain, France, Italy and Canada commands decisive voting power in
the World Bank.
   The G-7 met in conjunction with this week's annual meetings of
the bank and its sister lending organization, the 152-nation
International Monetary Fund.
   Hashimoto said the atmosphere at this meeting was decidedly
different from last July's economic summit in Houston when Japanese
Prime Minister Toshiki Kaifu said his government intended gradually
to resume direct loans to Beijing that were held up after
suppression of the democracy movement.
   Hashimoto, a member of Kaifu's cabinet, said he told the group
``we should give forthcoming consideration to loans conducive to
economic reform in China, especially in areas related to protection
of the environment.''
   The United States said it understood Kaifu's view that stability
and reform should be promoted in China and that the world's most
populous country should not be isolated.
   ``During these economic meetings, there will be discussions
about the future program and hopefully a quick normalization of
bank lending activities in China,'' said Attila Karaosmanoglu of
Turkey, World Bank's vice president for Asia.
   ``We do hope the situation can be normalized in the not too
distant future,'' he added.
   The group had said it would only support investments in China
related to basic human needs the government's June 1989 crackdown.
With more than $2 billion worth of projects in the pipeline, loan
approvals in 1989 were limited to $590 million.
   Earlier this year, however, ``the same G-7 expressed willingness
to vote for financing basic human needs plus environment-related
projects, plus implementation of economic reforms,'' Karaosmanoglu
said. ``We are continuing with preparation of these projects,'' he
added.
   China's democracy crackdown coincided with an economic crisis in
which purchasing power had outrun production and triggered
inflation, Karaosmanoglu recalled.
   Since then, he continued, austerity measures have successfully
curbed inflation and boosted exports and foreign exchange.
   ``In a sense, China is at a crossroads - in the short run, the
problem is revival, but the long-run question is how to reactivate
the reform process,'' Karaosmanoglu said.
   The World Bank forecasts economic growth in China this year of
3.5 percent to 4.5 percent, compared to 2 percent last year, he
said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0022 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 1320EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-Iraq     09-23 0409</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Iraq,0486</SECOND>
<HEAD>Iraq Threatens Oil Fields, Israel if ``Strangled'' by Troops</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf Rdp, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TERRIL JONES</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NICOSIA, Cyprus (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Iraq said Sunday it would destroy all
Middle East oil fields and move against Israel if its people were
``strangled'' by foreign forces assembling in the Persian Gulf.
   The statement urged the United States and other foreign powers
to drop ``the language of threats'' and adopt a ``climate of
understanding.'' But it called Iraq's annexation of Kuwait ``an
eternal decision.''
   ``We will never allow anybody, whomever he may be, to strangle
the people of Iraq without having himself strangled,'' said a joint
communique from the Revolution Command Council, Iraq's highest
decision-making body, and the ruling Baath Party.
   ``The oil areas in Saudi Arabia and in other states of the
region, all the oil installations, will be rendered incapable ...
and Israel will be transformed into something different from what
they are now,'' said the statement, broadcast by state-run Radio
Baghdad and monitored in Nicosia.
   ``Israel will be included in all actions that affect the owners
of the homeland in which the forces of evil and occupation have
settled,'' it said, apparently referring to Saudi Arabia.
   It added: ``Then will be the flood.''
   The communique did not give details about what action could be
taken by Iraq. It was issued following a joint meeting of the
council and party earlier Sunday presided over by Iraqi President
Saddam Hussein.
   The statement lashed out at the U.S.-led military buildup in
Saudi Arabia and surrounding waters that began after Iraq invaded
Kuwait on Aug. 2. Iraq annexed the oil-rich emirate six days later.
   The troop buildup and subsequent U.N.-supported sanctions
imposed on Iraq were ``reckless, odious and foolish behavior,'' it
said.
   Kuwait has been ``restored to its people to be part of its
original nation by an eternal decision from which there can be no
retreat under any circumstances or conditions,'' the ruling council
and party said.
   It repeatedly condemned the United States.
   ``America is committing deep criminal acts against Iraq and the
Arab nation especially in occuping the Arab and Moslem holy places
in Najd and Hejaz (Saudi Arabia), and in its sanctions imposed
aainst the Iraqi people in a way that exceeds all humanitarian
limits.
   ``America did all this to satisfy its arrogance and enforce its
hegemony on the entire world,'' the statement said.
   The statement insisted Iraq would not accept any settlement to
the gulf crisis unless it was based on Saddam's Aug. 12 peace
initiative in which he called for an Israeli withdrawal from
Palestinian territories.
   ``America must realize clearly that it is pushing the entire
region ... in fact, even the whole world ... to the brink of a
bottomless abyss, from which the region will never see light for
dozens of years,'' it said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0023 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 1326EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BRF--TitanLaunch     09-23 0147</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Titan Launch,0149</SECOND>
<HEAD>Air Force Delays Secret Rocket Launch</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Retransmitting to restore AP logo</NOTE>
<DATELINE>CAPE CANAVERAL, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Air Force on Sunday called off
the launch of a Titan 4 rocket with 5 minutes remaining in the
countdown because of undisclosed technical problems.
   The secret launch had been scheduled for shortly after midnight,
but was scrubbed about 3{ hours later. It was not known if a new
launch date had been set.
   The Air Force has launched Titan 4 rockets in June 1989 and last
June.
   The latest launch had been scheduled for earlier Thursday, but
was delayed because of another undisclosed technical problem.
   Air Force officials had refused to acknowledge the planned
launch from Cape Canaveral Air Force Station. Civilian experts said
they believed the rocket holds a missile warning satellite.
   The Martin Marietta rocket is valued at $173 million.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0024 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 1415EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People     09-23 0535</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People,0661</SECOND>
<HEAD>People in the News</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY44</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LINCOLN, Neb. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Pianist Van Cliburn, who has performed
before highbrow audiences in some of the world's great concert
halls, can add Cornhusker football fans and Nebraska's Memorial
Stadium to the list.
   Cliburn performed the national anthem before the
Nebraska-Minnesota game Saturday at the request of his old friend
D.B. ``Woody'' Varner, the former University of Nebraska president.
   ``I'm just extremely flattered to be here,'' Cliburn said.
   The musician said he met Varner more than 25 years ago when
Varner, then chancellor of Oakland University in Rochester, Mich.,
helped build a performing arts center there.
   Although Cliburn said he had not played the piano before a
football game before, he is no stranger to the sport.
   ``I was a clarinet player in the Kilgore (Texas) High School
marching band,'' he said. ``I have loved football all my life and
have marched in many games.''
   ---
   CAPRI, Italy (AP) - President Vaclav Havel of Czechoslovakia
received Italy's Malaparte Prize on Sunday for his work as a
playwright during his country's hard-line Communist years.
   The prize is named for Curzio Malaparte, an Italian journalist
and short-story writer who died in 1957. Previous winners include
Arthur Miller and Samuel Beckett.
   ``His theatrical works are of great value,'' said the award's
jurors. ``They originate from his life experience in a totalitarian
system but they always deal with the universal problems of man.''
   Havel accepted the award during a ceremony at the Santa Teresa
church on this island in the Gulf of Naples.
   ---
   DALLAS (AP) - Director Peter Bogdanovich said making the sequel
to the 1971 hit movie ``The Last Picture Show'' was more work than
fun.
   ``I wouldn't have been able to make this picture 20 years ago,''
said Bogdanovich, who attended the movie's premiere here Saturday.
``I wouldn't have known how to direct it. You need a little
experience to make a picture with this big a canvas.''
   It was a more depressing experience for Cybill Shepherd, who
reprised her role as Jacy Farrow. Her character comes home to
grieve the loss of her 6-year-old son.
   ``Being the mother of three, it was very, very painful and very
difficult,'' she said of the role. The 1971 film made Miss Shepherd
a star.
   The sequel, based on the novel by Larry McMurtry, also reunited
Jeff Bridges, Randy Quaid and Cloris Leachman.
   ---
   FORTE DEI MARMI, Italy (AP) - American cartoonist Garry Trudeau
and author Gore Vidal were honored for political satire and
literature.
   ``Doonesbury'' comic strip creator Trudeau was awarded Italy's
Forte dei Marmi Prize for satire. Vidal, best known for his
historical novels ``Burr'' and ``Lincoln,'' received the literary
award for his book ``Hollywood.''
   The two received their awards Saturday in this town near Lucca
in Tuscany.
   ---
   LOS ANGELES (AP) - Actor Beau Bridges will portray James Brady
in a TV movie about the former White House press secretary severely
wounded in the 1981 assassination attempt on President Reagan.
   ``The James Brady Story'' will chronicle Brady's rise to press
secretary and the March 30, 1981 assassination attempt in
Washington, D.C., by John Hinckley, said Robert Cooper, senior vice
president for HBO Pictures.
   The David Puttnam-Enigma production will begin filming in
November in Houston and Washington, and debut on HBO in spring
1991.
   The movie was written by Robert Bolt, winner of best screenplay
Academy Awards for ``Dr. Zhivago'' and ``A Man for All Seasons.''
Michael Uno, who directed HBO's ``Vietnam War Story,'' will direct
the Brady movie.
   Bridges won a National Society of Film Critics award for his
recent role in ``The Fabulous Baker Boys.'' He also was featured in
the movies ``The Other Side of the Mountain,'' ``Greased
Lightning,'' ``Norma Rae,'' and ``The Hotel New Hampshire.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0025 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 1421EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-Saudi-Changes     09-23 0674</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Saudi-Changes,0851</SECOND>
<HEAD>Diplomatic, Military Changes Challenge Saudi Arabia</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf Rdp, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>An AP News Analysis</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>By JOHN KING</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DHAHRAN, Saudi Arabia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Saudi Arabia marked its 58th
birthday Sunday at a crossroads, a time that finds it suddenly
reshaping its relations in the Middle East even as it deals with
hosting thousands of Western troops.
   For a country that prides itself on slow, methodical change, the
pace is dizzying, and potentially dangerous.
   At stake is the power structure of the Middle East, the flow of
oil to the West and, more personally for the Saudi monarchy, the
degree to which the current crisis will foster change in a nation
that seeks modernization without what it sees as the negative
trappings of the West.
   The Al-Saud monarchy, known since its inception 58 years ago for
its cautious handling of diplomatic matters, moved aggressively
Saturday to punish Jordan and Yemen for not breaking with Iraq over
the invasion of Kuwait.
   Riyadh expelled their diplomats and suggested they were
assisting Iraqi espionage in the kingdom.
   ``We have decided it is time to burn bridges,'' is how one Saudi
diplomatic official put it.
   Indeed, as they burn bridges with their neighbors, the Saudis
are trying to build them with the West, and Moscow and Beijing as
well. But they are unsure how the current crisis will reshape their
volatile region.
   ``It would be convenient if we could wait until all this sorts
itself out to decide which course to take,'' another Saudi official
said Sunday, speaking on condition of anonymity. ``But this is not
a time for convenience. We have waited far too long.''
   If nothing else, Saturday's expulsions appeared designed to put
extraordinary pressure on Jordan, which relies on generous Saudi
aid to help its crippled economy.
   Saudi sources said the expulsions could soon be followed by a
cutoff or sharp reduction in foreign aid. In terms of its influence
in Arab affairs, Sauidi Arabia's position as aid donor is second
only to its role as the custodian of Islam's holy places.
   In Amman, Jordanian officials have said the flow of Saudi cash
dried up almost immediately after Iraq's Aug. 2 invasion of Kuwait.
But, in the absence of official word from Riyadh, they hoped it
might be resumed before too long.
   ``It is unfortunate that much of our assistance has gone to
wasteful things,'' the Saudi diplomatic official said. ``We must be
more careful about how we spend our money and who receives it.''
   That was not only a warning to Jordan and Yemen, but to
Palestinians as well.
   Immediately after the invasion, the Saudi government suggested
that Palestine Liberation Organization chief Yasser Arafat's
support of Saddam Hussein would not affect the kingdom's generous
aid to Palestinians.
   That posture has since changed. Several senior Saudi officials
have suggested that aid to the Palestinians could be cut off or
sharply reduced unless Palestinian leaders break their ties with
Baghdad.
   ``We are realizing that for too long we have gone to great
lengths to avoid making tough choices,'' the Saudi diplomatic
official said. ``We must now make some, and so must our supposed
friends.''
   The remarkable breaks with Yemen and Jordan also serve as an
admission that the government now realizes it can buy neither
friends nor security simply by heaping billions in foreign aid on
its neighbors.
   The Saudis now are promising lucrative assistance to reward the
military help coming from Egypt and Syria, the Arab world's two
greatest military powers after Iraq.
   Whether those new alliances will last is suspect, and Saudi
Arabia already is promising to improve its military, which was
woefully unprepared to deal with the Iraqi invasion.
   That effort will force the Saudi monarchy to deal with nepotism,
which dominates the military, and the role of women, who because of
the low Saudi population likely will be needed to fill both
military and civilian jobs.
   Saudi Arabia also appears to have little choice but to be more
open about its dealings with the West, particularly the United
States.
   Americans and other Westerners have wielded considerable
influence in Saudi economic affairs since the discovery of oil here
50 years ago. The Saudis have tried to keep the extent of these
relationships under wraps.
   In the past seven weeks, however, Saudi Arabia has had to open
its doors to hundreds of foreign journalists who converged on the
kingdom to report on the gulf crisis.
   A Saudi prince, interviewed recently, nodded his head virtually
non-stop as he read a list of questions on domestic and
international issues that King Fahd was being forced to confront
all at once.
   ``That you are here to ask the questions is a sign itself of the
rapid change,'' he said. ``And we must deal with this change. But I
have no answer today. Right now, nothing is certain.''
   ---
   EDITOR'S NOTE - John King is an AP writer on assignment in Saudi
Arabia.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0026 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 1424EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-SoldierlessEconomy     09-23 0500</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soldierless Economy,0604</SECOND>
<HEAD>Soldiers' Departure Hurts Town's Economy</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf Rdp, Bjt</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto AX1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ELLIOTT MINOR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HINESVILLE, Ga. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   With most of the 24th Infantry Division
in Saudi Arabia, the clip artists at Curly's Barber Shop spend
their days watching television and napping.
   The deployment of 14,000 GIs from nearby Fort Stewart for what
probably will be a lengthy Mideast tour has already hurt businesses
in Hinesville and surrounding Liberty County.
   Howard ``Curly'' Gainous Sr., 69, said his shop used to give 400
haircuts a week, but now is down to 50 or 60.
   Gainous and Ed Barfield, 68, spend their days in the shop while
the four other barbers check in periodically, hoping for work.
   ``I hope we get enough to hang on. We have high rent and
overhead,'' Gainous said.
   An electric barber pole still spins outside the shop, but
Gainous has turned off some lights in a back room to save money.
   Mayor Buddy DeLoach said fast food sales have been cut by 50
percent and house and apartment rentals are 30 percent below
normal.
   City officials won't know the full economic impact of the
deployment until late October, when this month's sales tax receipts
are tallied. But DeLoach said there already are plans to delay
capital improvements and equipment purchases.
   Some residents hope the Army will move another division to Fort
Stewart, possibly from Germany. But military officials say there
are no plans to bring another unit to the 780,000-acre post.
   Hinesville residents pride themselves on their patriotism and
support for the military. Army families live throughout the town.
Civilian and military residents socialize, attend the same churches
and work together in civic clubs.
   Fort Stewart was just a sleepy southern Army post until the
division was activated there in 1974. Since then, the county's
population has jumped from 18,000 to 52,000.
   Hinesville officials worried about a mass exodus of military
families following the deployment, but families with homes and
school-age children apparently have remained.
   Liberty County school enrollment is slightly higher this year -
8,015 students, cmmpared to 7,995 last year.
   Ronald E. Tolley, executive director of the Liberty County
Industrial Authority, said the county has attracted several new
industries that will help diversify the economy. Officials will try
to boost slumping retail sales by attracting tourists and promoting
Hinesville as a regional shopping area.
   Tolley believes businesses that provided services to the young
single soldiers will be especially hard hit. Hinesville has dozens
of fast-food restaurants, pawn shops and used car lots. It also has
at least nine barber shops, several auto parts stores, two major
discount department stores and three large supermarkets.
   ``I think they're definitely feeling the impact,'' said Tolley.
``You no longer see the military people in the stores.''
   Donald Bonett, assistant store manager at the Piggly-Wiggly
supermarket, said sales at his store have dropped $30,000 to
$40,000 a week. Managers have cut the hours of part-time workers.
   ``Our sales have dropped - at least one-fourth of what we used
to do,'' he said.
   Only 12 cars were parked at the 52-room Days Inn motel on a
recent night.
   ``It's very, very slow,'' said general manager Mike Patel. ``We
depend on the Army.''
   Patel said the housekeeping staff has been cut from seven to
two. The motel used to have an 80 percent occupancy rate, he said.
   ``If it stays like this for two months, it's going to be a
problem for us. We are losing money,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0027 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 1424EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-DrugTax     09-23 0414</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Drug Tax,0526</SECOND>
<HEAD>`Al Capone' Law Paying Off</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SCOTT ROTHSCHILD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>AUSTIN, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Many thought it was a joke when Texas
enacted taxes on illegal drugs, but officials say the laugh is on
drug dealers as they find themselves in deeper trouble because of
the year-old ``Al Capone'' law.
   The law requires all containers of illegal drugs to carry a tax
stamp, emblazoned with either a skull and crossbones or the image
of the Grim Reaper and the words ``Death'' and ``Taxes.''
   The law requires a tax of $200 per gram on controlled
substances, $101.50 per ounce or $3.50 per gram on marijuana.
   Since the tax took effect on Sept. 1, 1989, more than 2,550 drug
stamps have been sold for $10,614, presumably to collectors, since
the stamp would be prohibitively expensive in the illegal drug
trade.
   ``The law was never intended to be a source of revenue for the
state. It was always intended to give prosecutors another felony
charge to put drug dealers behind bars,'' said John Bender, deputy
comptroller.
   ``If we manage to collect some money from drug dealers in
addition to that, all the better for the state,'' he said.
   The state comptroller's office has billed 397 people more than
$180 million in unpaid drug taxes. Realistically, the state will
collect only a fraction of that amount.
   But nearly $40,000 has been collected from people who faced
criminal tax evasion charges after they were arrested with drugs
that did not have the state drug tax stamp.
   Under the law, criminal tax evasion is a felony which carries a
possible prison sentence of two to 10 years and officials can
freeze a person's assets to collect the tax.
   For 48-year-old Odis Weaver of Texarkana, the law meant an
additional 10 years for evading taxes on top of a 34-year sentence
for possession of cocaine. In addition, the state comptroller's
office froze his bank account and collected $1,800.
   When state Rep. Billy Clemons introduced the drug tax bill in
1987, ``I got laughed out of the House.''
   In 1989, he persuaded his colleagues that the tax could be
enforced. ``It's nothing unusual. Anything we wish to discourage,
we tax.''
   He even dubbed it the ``Al Capone'' law after the
Prohibition-era gangster who was finally tripped up on federal
income tax evasion charges and sent to prison.
   ``The drug tax seems to be a pretty good tool when all else
fails. The evidence is irrefutable. If you don't have the stamp you
face a felony charge of tax evasion,'' he said.
   ``The success of the law will be determined by whether Texas
juries are willing to put drug dealers in jail for failure to pay
taxes,'' said Sam Ponder, chief of criminal litigation at the Bexar
County District Attorney's office.
   But he added: ``The people who are being charged have very
little in the way of assets that can be seized for the payment of
taxes. Most of the dealers charged typically have an apartment and
car and live from one deal to the next.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0028 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 1430EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-FinanceMeetings     09-23 0653</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Finance Meetings,750</SECOND>
<HEAD>Finance Ministers Differ Over Interest Rates</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-World Environment Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARTIN CRUTSINGER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Economics Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The world's richest countries tried hard
Sunday to present a unified front against the threat that the
Persian Gulf turmoil could plunge the world into a recession, but
signs of discord emerged from the closed-door discussions.
   Finance ministers from Britain, West Germany and France stressed
the need for vigor in fighting inflation. But the United States,
represented by Treasury Secretary Nicholas Brady, continued to
press its case that lower interest rates were needed to ward off a
recession.
   The discussions were being held as part of the annual meetings
of the International Monetary Fund and the World Bank. The
meetings, which involve representatives from 152 nations gained
more urgency this year as finance officials struggled to develop a
strategy for dealing with the economic fallout from Iraq's invasion
of Kuwait.
   The finance officials endorsed the broad outlines of a U.S.-led
effort to channel billions of dollars to countries hard hit by the
Persian Gulf crisis. Those include the so-called frontline states
of Turkey, Egypt and Jordan, as well as other Third World countries
whose economies have suffered from the loss of markets stemming
from the U.N. trade embargo against Iraq and the world rise in oil
prices.
   However, British Chancellor of the Exchequer John Major told
reporters that decisions regarding specific amounts of assistance
and how many countries should be helped remained to be worked out.
   IMF Managing Director Michel Camdessus has raised the
possibility of establishing a voluntary fund, with contributions
coming from the windfall profits made by oil-producing nations.
   Those funds would be made available to the poorer oil-consuming
nations. Officials said potential donor nations were to meet to
discuss this fund on Wednesday.
   Brady, in a speech Sunday to the policy-making committee of the
IMF, continued to stress the U.S. position that world financial
leaders needed to be equally worried about inflation and recession.
   He said successfully navigating policy to avoid both problems
``will be difficult. But it is achievable.''
   But in their remarks, other finance ministers left little doubt
that they considered inflation to be the greater threat and thus
would not be moving to lower interest rates.
   ``Without preservation of price stability we would lose on all
fronts,'' West German Finance Minister Theo Waigel said.
   ``The clearer we make our anti-inflationary determination, the
quicker we will reduce the risks of financial instability,'' said
French Economics Minister Pierre Beregovoy.
   While the remarks were made in a closed meeting, copies of the
speeches were made available to reporters.
   Major, who briefed reporters following his address, said ``There
is nothing to be gained and a great deal to be lost by easing up on
inflation. We have to get it down.''
   The position of the other countries is likely to make it more
difficult for the administration to convince the Federal Reserve of
the urgency of reducing U.S. interest rates in the face of growing
signs of economic weakness.
   Some analysts believe the shock to the U.S. economy from the
doubling in world oil prices since the Aug. 2 invasion of Kuwait
will result in a recession in this country beginning before the end
of the year.
   Faced with this prospect, the administration has been pressuring
the Fed to lower interest rates to spur economic activity. However,
analysts said they were not looking for the Fed to heed this call
in view of the fact that interest rates in other countries have
been rising.
   The widening disparity between U.S. and foreign interest rates
has resulted in foreign investors pulling money out of the U.S.
market in favor of higher returns overseas. If that trend
accelerated, it could trigger a sharp drop in the value of the
dollar which would only worsen inflationary pressures in the United
States.
   The other finance leaders emphasized the need for the United
States to do something to get its federal budget under control. The
world's seven richest countries - the United States, Japan, West
Germany, Britain, France, Canada and Italy - specifically mentioned
the U.S. deficit problem in a joint communique issued late
Saturday.
   In his speech Sunday, Brady sought to allay fears that the
current negotiations between Congress and the administration will
fail to craft a credible deficit reduction agreement.
   His comments appeared aimed at calls for Congress and the
administration to abandon the Gramm-Rudman deficit reduction
targets because the $50 billion in deficit reduction being
contemplated for the 1991 budget year would be too great a shock on
an already weak economy.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0029 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 1436EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-AppalachianArrest     09-23 0455</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Appalachian Arrest,0549</SECOND>
<HEAD>Man Held Without Bond In Appalachian Trail Slayings</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto HX1</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HARPERS FERRY, W.Va. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Appalachian Trail Conference
officials expressed relief Sunday at the arrest of a man charged
with the slayings of two hikers killed in their sleeping bags along
the Maine-to-Georgia path.
   David ``Casey'' Horn, 38, was arrested Friday in Harpers Ferry
on a fugitive from justice charge, said Jefferson County Magistrate
Patricia Noland. Horn remained in custody without bail Sunday
pending an extradition hearing.
   Noland said Horn was wanted on two homicide charges in
Pennsylvania in connection with the Sept. 13 killings of Molly
LaRue, 25, of Shaker Heights, Ohio, and Geoffrey Logan Hood, 26, of
Signal Mountain, Tenn.
   ``We're on pins and needles to hear word and get him back
here,'' said Pennsylvania State Police Cpl. Dan Sullivan, who heads
the murder investigation.
   Brian King, a spokesman for the Appalachian Trail Conference in
Harpers Ferry, said Horn was arrested by U.S. Park Service rangers
when he entered the historic Eastern Panhandle town.
   ``A hiker saw this person answering the description coming
across the bridge into Harpers Ferry,'' King said. ``Three park
rangers stopped him and took him in for questioning, and they held
him for the Pennsylvania State Police and the West Virginia State
Police.''
   King, whose voluntary group oversees the entire 2,160-mile
trail, said hikers were relieved that a suspect had been arrested.
   He said about 200 people attended a ceremony Saturday to open a
new route at Boiling Springs, Pa.
   ``It was announced about an hour before it started and relief is
the best way to describe it,'' he said. ``It's been a very bad
eight days for the people who love the trail.''
   Thurston Griggs, president of the Mountain Club of Maryland,
which is responsible for the section of trail where the murders
occurred, said he was pleased authorities were able to make an
arrest.
   ``I'm disappointed it was somebody using the trail,'' Griggs
said Sunday from his home in Baltimore.
   Noland said an extradition hearing before Jefferson County
Circuit Judge Thomas Steptoe would be held within the next few
days. Steptoe had an unpublished telephone number and could not be
reached for comment Sunday.
   The two Appalachian Trail hikers were killed in their sleeping
bags before dawn near Duncannon, Pa., a rural community about 10
miles north of Harrisburg. Ms. LaRue was stabbed repeatedly. Hood
was shot three times.
   Horn, who told police he is from Loris, S.C., was arraigned
Friday night and has remained in the Eastern Regional Jail in
Martinsburg.
   ``I informed him of the charges that had been lodged aainst him
and read him his rights and informed him there would be no bail,''
Noland said Sunday. ``He was very quiet and cooperative and just
acknowledged his rights.''
   Horn could be back in Pennsylvania in as little as a week if he
does not fight extradition.
   Sullivan said he could not comment on whether police had any
other suspects, but a state police news release Saturday said
investigators had sought one individual.
   About 1,500 people use the trail every year. The last slaying on
the trail was in 1988 near Shippensburg, Pa., about 38 miles
southwest of Duncannon.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0030 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 1500EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-Queen     09-23 0487</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Queen,0584</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.S.-Born Queen of Jordan Says King Misrepresented</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf Rdp, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SYDNEY RUBIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>AMMAN, Jordan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   American-born Queen Noor said Sunday her
husband is a loyal friend of the West, an experienced mediator for
peace and an honorable man who is being misrepresented in the
United States and pressured to take sides.
   ``There has been a lot of disinformation about his motives,''
said Queen Noor, born Lisa Halaby of Washington, D.C., in an
interview. ``It has been very disturbing.''
   Although King Hussein has called on Iraq to withdraw its troops
from Kuwait, he has generally sided with his powerful neighbor
Saddam Hussein, while still trying to promote peace negotiations.
   On Saturday, he appealed to the United States to withdraw its
troops from Saudi Arabia as soon as possible.
   Queen Noor did not provide specific examples of disinformation,
but her husband's reluctance to sever trade links with Iraq, mainly
for economic considerations, has sparked U.S. accusations that he
has become an apologist for Saddam.
   Since his coronation in 1953, Hussein, 54, has been one of
Washington's closest Arab allies.
   Like their queen, a Princeton-educated daughter of a prominent
airline executive, many Jordanians now feel betrayed by the United
States.
   ``People have this attitude that you are either with us or you
are against us, but this is an attitude that has never worked,''
the 39-year-old queen said in the interview at Al-Ma'awa Palace,
overlooking the bustling capital.
   ``It has never been a responsible or constructive position in
international relations. I've seen this attitude in the United
States and, of course, in this region as well.''
   ``The feeling is that if Jordan doesn't declare its position to
be the same as that of the other country, it is against them and
that it is in another camp,'' she added, not directly naming the
United States.
   ``Jordan hasn't chosen a camp,'' she said. ``Jordan has had its
role throughout history of being a crossroads, it is geographically
a crossroads, and in politics it has been a mediator. It has been a
force for peace and stability. Working always for that.''
   On Saturday, King Hussein took his positions to the American
people in a 30-minute speech broadcast on Cable News Network. He
appealed to the United States to support negotiations rather than
driving toward a horrible war.
   ``We believe that the position of Jordan could not be clearer to
anyone who seeks the truth. It is based on the principles of
international law, which Jordan has respected and always calls on
all nations to respect,'' he said.
   ``Jordan is paying a terrible price for its commitment to honor,
principles, justice and peace,'' he said.
   Like her husband, Queen Noor said the crisis clarified the need
to resolve the Arab-Israeli conflict.
   ``It does nothing for the credibility of the West in this region
to see so much emphasis placed on U.N. resolutions concerning oil
producing states in the region ... and nothing like the same
emphasis being placed on long-standing disputes that threaten
regional peace and stability, such as the Arab-Israeli dispute.
   ``There are resolutions concerning that dispute that have
existed for 23 years and have not been implemented,'' she said.
   Arabs, Queen Noor said, consider the U.S. refusal to negotiate
the Israeli occupation of Palestinian territories inconsistent and
unjust.
   ``Injustice strikes at the heart of people, at their most
intense passions,'' she said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0031 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 1516EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People-Hope     09-23 0200</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People-Hope,0224</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bob Hope Says He May Entertain the Troops</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   TOPEKA, Kan. (A) - Bob Hope says he might travel to Saudi
Arabia to entertain U.S. forces facing Iraqi troops, but he is
worried about taking beautiful women as he has on previous overseas
tours.
   ``The Saudi Arabians, they don't like a girl unless she's
wearing a veil,'' he said Saturday. ``I can't see Madonna wearing a
veil.''
   If he does go, he said, it would be during the Christmas
holidays.
   Hope said he would not take his golf clubs. ``I don't need a
sand trap that big,'' he said.
   Hope also reminisced about former President Dwight Eisenhower
during his performance Saturday night at the Kansas Expocentre.
   The comedian met Eisenhower, then allied commander, during World
War II. He was called to Eisenhower's office in Algiers while
preparing a 1943 radio show.
   Eisenhower promised him he wouldn't experience any bombings, but
the city was bombed that night for the first time in years.
   ``That's always been a big joke because I wired him and said,
`Thanks for the rest,' '' Hope said.
   More than 4,000 people attended the show to benefit Ronald
McDonald House, which provides low-cost shelter to families of
hospitalized children. Concert promoter Doug Holladay said Hope cut
his fee in half to $37,500.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0032 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 1522EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-US-Gulf     09-23 0664</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-US-Gulf,790</SECOND>
<HEAD>Baker Says `Host' of Options Remain Before Any War With Iraq</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOAN MOWER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Secretary of State James A. Baker III played
down the possibility of war in the Persian Gulf on Sunday, saying
the United States and its allies still have a ``whole host'' of
non-military options to use against Iraq.
   But Baker said the Bush administration would unleash an
``appropriate response'' to any Iraqi-inspired acts of terrorism
against American citizens. President Bush made similar comments
Friday and has accused Iraq of supporting terrorist groups.
   Baker, appearing on NBC-TV's ``Meet the Press'' program, also
said the administration likely will present to Congress the first
phase of its proposed weapons package for Saudi Arabia early next
week.
   Administration sources have said the initial deal is expected to
have a value of $10 billion, but Baker refused to put a price tag
on it. There have been reports that the total deal was worth
roughly $21 billion, a figure Baker would not confirm.
   Baker said the first installment of Saudi weapons deal
represents ``the needs that we think are immediate for Saudi Arabia
and, frankly, needs that would - that will serve to protect
American lives.''
   The Pentagon and the State Department were putting the final
touches on the first phase of the military shopping list for the
Saudis over the weekend, officials said.
   The package is likely to include Tow anti-tank missiles, Patriot
anti-aircraft systems and F-15 fighter jets, according to sources
familiar with the deal.
   The second installment will not be presented to Congress for
approval until early 1991, Baker said.
   Despite the 150,000 U.S. troops in Saudi Arabia and the billions
of dollars of materiel in the desert kingdom, Baker said the United
States remains committed to working with the United Nations for a
peaceful, diplomatic resolution.
   Asked if he is confident war can be avoided, Baker said: ``We
have said many times we hoped there won't be.'' Bush, however,
``will not rule, and indeed should not, rule out other options,''
he said.
   Baker refused to discuss a report in Sunday's Washington Post
that said the Defense Department had contingency plans for ground
assaults against Iraq from as many as four directions. The troops
might have to cross Jordan and Turkey, the report said.
   Saying he would not talk about any possible operations, Baker
added that as long as military action remains an option ``you're
going to see speculative pieces from time to time like this.''
   Baker said the U.N. had a ``whole host'' of other things that
might be considered in an attempt to force Iraq to withdraw its
troops from Kuwait and restore that country's government. He
reiterated those conditions must be met before there would be talk
of negotiating with Iraq.
   ``I don't think we are running out of non-military type
sanctions,'' Baker said.
   Baker's measured tone on Iraq contrasted with a bellicose
statement from Baghdad on Sunday threatening to destroy oil fields
in the Middle East and move against Israel if the Iraqi people are
``strangled'' by foreign forces in the Persian Gulf. The statement
was issued in the name of the Revolution Command Council, the
country's highest decision-making body.
   Baker said the United States was committed to backing the U.N.
resolutions imposing trade embargoes against Iraq, Baker said. The
secretary of state will join other foreign ministers this week at a
U.N. Security Council meeting in New York.
   One of items on the agenda is imposing an air embargo against
Iraq to tighten the stranglehold on Baghdad. Another possible
sanction is to punish countries that break the embargo.
   U.N. Secretary General Javier Perez de Cuellar said Sunday that
it's likely that an air embargo will be adopted by the United
Nations in the next few days.
   The administration agreed to the phased sale of weapons to Saudi
Arabia after some members of Congress, particularly those with
close ties to Israel, objected to the massive flow of weapons to
the Saudis.
   Baker insisted the administration had not caved in to Congress,
although the idea of a two-step process originated on Capitol Hill.
   Fred Dutton, a representative of the Saudi government, said the
Saudis were not upset about the two-part sale.
   ``After the smoke clears they will see what their defense
requirements are,'' Dutton said in a telephone interview. If the
United States refuses to sell weapons to the Saudis, they will do
their shopping elsewhere, he said.
   Baker also defended the administration's actions prior to
Saddam's invasion of Kuwait. He reiterated that the United States
followed the proper course in refusing to take sides in the
Iraq-Kuwait border dispute, and said it was ``ludicrous'' to
suggest that ``somehow the United States contributed to Saddam
Hussein's unprovoked aggression'' against Kuwait.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0033 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 1529EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-KremlinService     09-23 0506</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Kremlin Service,0607</SECOND>
<HEAD>First Full Service in Kremlin Cathedral Since 1918</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ALAN COOPERMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Patriarch Alexi II, head of the Russian Orthodox
Church, led a Divine Liturgy in the Kremlin's Uspensky Cathedral on
Sunday, the first full service allowed in more than 70 years in
Russia's most important cathedral.
   Before the 1917 revolution, the 15th century church was the most
sacred in the country. Under its five golden onion-shaped domes,
czars were crowned, patriarchs were buried and conquered princes
swore allegiance to Russia.
   Since 1918, however, it has been a museum and closed to ordinary
worship. The government's decision to allow the Sunday service was
an important symbolic step in the revival of the Orthodox Church,
long repressed by the Communist Party because of ideological
opposition to religion.
   About 1,000 people were allowed into the Kremlin, the walled
fortress that is the seat of the Soviet government, for the
service.
   Among them were Moscow mayor Gavriil Popov and the chairman of
the national legislature, Anatoly Lukyanov.
   Afterward, thousands of people lined the streets as Alexi and
other church leaders led a procession from the Kremlin's Trinity
Gate through downtown Moscow to another historic site, the Church
of the Great Ascension.
   ``Churches are revived not by external restoration, but by
prayers said inside them,'' Alexi told the crowd outside. ``I hope
you will agree with me that today's Divine Liturgy in the Uspensky
Ctahedral meant more to its spiritual revival than decades of
external maintenance.''
   More than 30 clergymen in golden brocade robes, many carrying
icons, took part in the hourlong procession. They were followed by
hundreds of worshipers.
   People watched from balconies and windows and were packed four
deep on both sides of the 2{-mile route. The crowd was quiet and
respectful, and some spectators crossed themselves as the icons -
paintings of the Virgin and various saints - passed by.
   ``We are Russians. God is with us,'' said a banner in old
Russian script carried by some of the marchers.
   Soviet President Mikhail S. Gorbachev has shown much more
tolerance than previous leaders for worshipers, and has called on
them to support his reform policies.
   Three years ago, Gorbachev met in the Kremlin with Alexi's
predecessor, Pimen. It was the first meeting between leaders of the
Communist Party and the Russian Orthodox Church in more than 40
years.
   Since then, numerous churches across the Soviet Union have been
returned to the Orthodox Church and restored for worship. In prior
decades, some were maintained as cultural museums, but many were
allowed to fall into disrepair and were used as storehouses or
offices.
   Since the Bolshevik Revolution, brief prayer services have been
allowed in the Uspensky Cathedral on a few occasions, such as in
1988 for the 1,000th anniversary of the introduction of
Christianity to Russia.
   But Sunday's service, which was closed to the press, was the
first full one there since 1918, according to the newspaper
Komsomolskaya Pravda. Officially, the occasion for the service was
a local holiday, the Days of Moscow, which celebrates the beauty of
the capital.
   There are three other major churches within the Kremlin where
services have been held on rare occasions. All are considered
museums, but there has been speculation that one or more may soon
be opened for weekly services.
   ``There has been talk for a long time about returning the
Kremlin churches to use as cathedrals,'' Komsomolskaya Pravda
wrote. ``Maybe the service on the city's holiday is one more step
on the path that leads to the church.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0034 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 1530EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-ReporterArrested     09-23 0280</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Reporter Arrested,300</SECOND>
<HEAD>Washington Post Defends Reporter Arrested While Working on Story</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The managing editor of The Washington Post
says a staff reporter broke no law when he was arrested for
allegedly contributing to the delinquency of a minor while working
on a story for the newspaper and called the police action
``unwarranted.''
   ``Based on the information we have, the arrest of a Washington
Post reporter while he is reporting a story and breaking no law
himself appears unwarranted to us,'' said Leonard Downie, Jr.,
Managing Editor of the Post.
   ``I'm particularly concerned that the police pursued this after
the reporter identified himself and his purpose and that the police
took his notes,'' Downie said.
   Michael J. Ybarra, 23, a reporter with the Post's Metro staff
was arrested late Friday while working on a report about a new
curfew for minors in Quantico, Va.
   Ybarra's supervisors said the reporter was not available for
comment concerning the incident.
   Ybarra was taken into custody and his notes confiscated while
conducting an interview of two 12-year-old boys in a restaurant in
the Virgina town about 30 miles south of the nation's capital.
   The Quantico Town Council recently imposed a 10 p.m. to 6 a.m.
curfew for youths under age 18 following recent vandalism in the
area.
   Ybarra is the second adult charged in connection with a curfew
violation, but no youths have been arrested.
   ``I believe that the reporter was trying to do his job and just
got mixed up at the wrong place and the wrong time,'' said Leo
Rodriguez, Quantico Police Chief.
   Rodriguez said the reporter's notes were held as evidence but a
copy would be made available to the Post.
   Ybarra, who was released on his own recognizance, is to be
arraigned in Prince William County Juvenile and Domestic Relations
Court on Tuesday. He faces a maximum one year in jail and a fine of
$2,500 fine.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0035 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 1537EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brite-CapitolNuts     09-23 0151</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brite-Capitol Nuts,0164</SECOND>
<HEAD>Not Enough Nuts at Oregon's State Capitol</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SALEM, Ore. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Political pundits might tell you there are
more than enough nuts at the state Capitol, but Jim Archambault is
looking for a few more.
   Archambault, the state's landscape manager, needs them soon so
the squirrels won't go hungry this winter.
   Some 40 to 100 gray squirrels live in the Capitol Mall area, and
in the winter months they have to rely on handouts.
   Archambault, who strolled through the area Friday with a handful
of acorns, said state officials gladly accept donations on behalf
of the squirrels. The animals are partial to filberts and English
walnuts, but will also eat peanuts, he said.
   Harold Shahan of Salem, who was feeding the squirrels some
peanuts on his own Friday, said he has discovered they also like
M&amp;M peanu candies.
   ``But you have to stay with the same color or they get
confused,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0036 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 1539EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BoatPeople     09-23 0410</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Boat People,0481</SECOND>
<HEAD>Britain, Hong Kong Say Vietnam Move on Refugees Important Step</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BANGKOK, Thailand (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Britain and Hong Kong on Sunday
welcomed Vietnam's decision to take back boat people who are not
opposed to returning home from Hong Kong camps.
   The official Vietnam News Agency said the agreement was reached
in talks in Hanoi last week by British and Hong Kong officials and
representatives of the U.N. High Commissioner for Refugees.
   The brief report, dated Saturday and seen in Bangkok on Sunday,
did not say if the agreement applied to the tens of thousands of
boat people stuck in camps in Thailand, Malaysia, Indonesia and
other Asian countries.
   Under the terms of the July 1989 Geneva conference, all boat
people are screened in order to determine which refugees are
eligible for resettlement in the West. Those who fled to escape
political persecution are eligible; those who left for economic
reasons are not.
   The new agreement is seen as a compromise that stops short of
forced repatriation. Fifty-one Vietnamese were repatriated against
their will in December, bt no others have been forced back because
of objections from the United States and Vietnam.
   Hong Kong and the Association of Southeast Asian Nations -
Thailand, Singapore, Indonesia, Malaysia, the Philippines and
Brunei - continued pressuring Vietnam and threatened to turn back
Vietnamese boats unless the United States eased its stand.
   In late July, Secretary of States James A. Baker III told
Southeast Asian nations that the United States continued to oppose
forced repatriation but could accept the new category of ``those
who do not object.''
   In London, a Foreign Office official said the agreements reached
in Hanoi were an ``important step.''
   `Our objective remains the repatriation of all screened-out boat
people to Vietnam,'' the official said. ``We will be cooperating
fully with the U.N. High Commissioner for Refugees in the
implementation of agreements.''
   In Hong Kong, the governor, Sir David Wilson, also described the
agreement as an important step to accelerate the return of
non-refugees to Vietnam.
   Wilson told reporters he hopes the repatriation program will
begin before the end of this year, adding: ``You cannot have people
who are non-refugees spending year after year in camps. That is
simply not right.''
   So far, 4,349 Vietnamese boat people have returned from Hong
Kong under a voluntary repatriation program that began in March
1989 with support from the U.N. High Commissioner for Refugees.
   About 54,000 boat people remain in Hong Kong camps. About 9,000
are classified as refugees and will be resettled in the West. The
other 45,000 are either waiting to be screened for determination of
their status, or have been classified as non-refugees for
repatriation.
   Since June 1988, when Hong Kong stopped automatically allowing
boat people to stay, 49,466 have arrived there - 4,916 of them this
year.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0037 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 1541EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Gulf-MoslemSoldiers     09-23 0314</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Moslem Soldiers,0382</SECOND>
<HEAD>Moslem and Military: Faith, Jobs Collide for Two Robins Sergeants</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ROBINS AIR FORCE BASE, Ga. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two Moslem members of the U.S.
military often think about having to go to battle in the region
that holds what they consider the holiest place in the world.
   Meekail Shaheed, 26, and Abdullah Shamsid-Deen, 38, are both Air
Force sergeants and practicing Moslems.
   The two men express concern for fellow members of the military
who also are members of the Sunni Islamic faith. They say they are
a little wary of the huge foreign military force that is inside
Saudi Arabia, site of Islam's holiest place - the city of Mecca.
   ``Any time you get forces close to any kind of holy land,
religious people are going to be concerned,'' Shaheed said.
   But both say they would have no reservations about serving in
the multinational force there.
   ``Not at all,'' said Shamsid-Deen, a 13-year military man who
converted to Islam 17 years ago. ``I believe we would be being
going over there in the name of right. We would not be going over
there to destroy something, but to protect and defend.''
   At Robins, both men perform administrative duties in the base
chapel. Their jobs allow them time to carry out their Islamic
duties, which include five daily prayers and yearly fasts during
the month of Ramadan.
   ``The chaplains are out front in respecting and protecting the
freedom of all religions here on base,'' said Shamsid-Deen. ``I
would hope that Moslems in other areas would have the same
protection and freedom.''
   Both men say they are encouraged by changing public attitudes
toward their religion, partly because of events in the Middle East.
   ``People seem to be more supportive of Islam now,'' said
Shamsid-Deen, noting that several Islamic countries are allied with
Western forces against Iraq's invasion of Kuwait.
   Still, the two men watch events in the Middle East with
trepidation. One of the five pillars of Islam is for a Moslem to
visit Mecca at least once in one's life.
   Shamsid-Deen made the pilgrimage in 1979, but Shaheed has not
yet had the opportunity.
   ``We all hope this can be taken care of as quickly as
possible,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0038 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 1611EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Philippines-US     09-23 0613</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Philippines-US,0698</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.S. Colonial Role Drives Resentment of Bases</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT H. REID</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MANILA, Philippines (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Students and national leaders rail
against the American military presence in the Philippines despite
opinion surveys that show sizable public support for the U.S.
bases.
   No prominent politician unequivocally supports the bases, which
U.S. officials claim pump $1 billion a year into the economy and
provide 100,000 jobs in a nation facing political instability and a
possible recession.
   The Philippines has much to gain from the presence of U.S.
bases, but the opposition to them illustrates how much some
Filipinos fear continued influence by their old colonial rulers.
   ``You must understand that other Asian peoples, the
Singaporeans, and Japanese and the Koreans, can deal easier with
the Americans because you were never their colonial master,'' said
one Asian diplomat, speaking on condition of anonymity.
   ``For the Filipinos, it's different.'' he said. ``The old
relationship of ruler and the ruled is a heavy psychological
burden.''
   Angry students last week backed a pullout, chanting ``U.S. bases
out!'' in demonstrations near the U.S. Embassy. American officials
warned of bombings and assassinations by anti-bases extremists.
   During four days of talks on the bases last week, no Filipino
politician of national status expressed complete support for
retaining them after their lease expires in September 1991. The
talks adjourned Friday and were expected to resume in about a
month.
   President Corazon Aquino said the United States and the
Philippines should discuss the ``orderly withdrawal'' of the 40,000
U.S. troops, Defense Department civilians and military dependents
at Clark Air Base, the Subic Bay naval base and four smaller
facilities.
   Mrs. Aquino said Sunday in her weekly radio broadcast that she
felt confident ``our two countries shall arrive at an understanding
that will be mutually acceptable and mutually beneficial.''
   Anti-bases sentiment is strongest in the educated urban middle
class that produces university professors, journalists and other
opinion-makers. Activists are convinced that building opposition to
the bases is simply a matter of educating their ``uninformed''
countrymen.
   A survey in March by the Ateneo University found that 35 percent
of the 1,200 Filipinos polled nationwide were unaware that the
United States maintains bases here.
   Only 18 percent wanted the bases either phased out or closed
immediately. Forty percent supported keeping them indefinitely.
   Closing the bases represents an assertion of sovereignty against
the United States, which many Filipinos believe still exerts
powerful influence over their country more than 40 years after
independence.
   Over the years, Filipino ``nationalism'' has come to be defined
as standing up to America and its most visible symbol - the bases.
   Support for the bases would brand a politician as
``anti-nationalist,'' an unpatriotic tool of the former colonial
power. Many Filipinos believe the United States interferes in
Philippine affairs to guarantee keeping the bases.
   That view was reinforced by Washington's longtime support for
the late President Ferdinand Marcos. Despite alleged U.S.
sponsorship of ``democracy,'' the Americans tolerated Marcos'
repressive rule, apparently to maintain their bases.
   Opposition to Marcos, therefore, took on the added character of
opposition to the bases. Many of those in the forefront of the
anti-Marcos struggle now hold key positions in the administration,
the congress and the media.
   The bases have become so symbolic of American ``intervention''
that any U.S. move is seen as a bid to retain the installations.
   In December, U.S. jets flew air cover for pro-Aquino forces
against military mutineers seeking to topple her. That was widely
interpreted as a bid to pressure her into keeping the bases.
   During a devastating earthquake in July, U.S. troops rushed to
stricken cities to help in relief operations. Residents of the
quake-stricken city of Cabanatuan joked that the bases would remain
forever because the government simply could not function without
them.
   ``The current talks between the Philippines and the United
States should usher in a new relationship between the two
countries,'' said Rev. Joaquin Bernas, president of Ateneo
University.
   ``For the Philippines, it should be a major step in the
direction of greater self-reliance and not continuing dependency,''
he added.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0039 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 1620EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Rushdie-NewBook 1stLd-Writethru a0687 09-23 0504</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Rushdie-New Book, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0687,0609</SECOND>
<HEAD>Critics Acclaim Rushdie's First Book Since ``The Satanic Verses''</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 1 graf for 4th graf, `The late...' to delete word
`first.' Pick up 5th graf, `The new...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By EDITH M. LEDERER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Salman Rushdie's first book since Iran called for
his death is a fairy tale for children, acclaimed by critics Sunday
as a charming and lighthearted work with a serious message for
adults as well.
   Reviewers marveled that Rushdie could write with such
mischievous humor despite 19 months in hiding under police guard,
during which he has moved constantly and become separated from his
wife, the American novelist Marianne Wiggins.
   Most critics, however, also saw signs of pain and desperation in
the prose of ``Haroun and The Sea of Stories.''
   The late Ayatolah Ruhollah Khomeini called for Rushdie's death
after the author's novel ``The Satanic Verses,'' was deemed
blasphemous to Islam.
   The new book tells the tale of a Hindu storyteller whose talent
is suddenly destroyed by a fanatical dictator who poisons the
springs of his inspiration. His brave son, Haroun, eventually
defeats the enemy of stories and restores his father's gift.
   Rushdie dedicates the book to his own son with these lines:
   ``As I wander far from view
   Read, and bring me home to you.''
   British writer Anthony Burgess, reviewing the book in the
Observer newspaper, said the dedication ``renews rage'' at ``the
stupidity of the Islamic deathmongers, burning a book they do not
have the intelligence to understand.''
   Burgess called it a ``great tribute to the resilience of Mr.
Rushdie's beleaguered spirit that he should write so charmingly
funny a book.''
   ``It is a book to enjoy and not to explicate but, if we wish, we
can take it as a piece of Swiftian outrage at human folly disguised
as a children's tale,'' Burgess wrote.
   Rushdie, a British citizen born into a Moslem family in India,
was sentenced to death Feb. 14, 1989. Even after Khomeini's death
last year, the sentence was not lifted by Iranian leaders.
   Rushdie has since published poetry and several essays and
reviews, but ``Haroun and The Sea of Stories'' is his first book
since he went into hiding.
   It will be published by Granta Books in Britain Sept. 27 and in
the United States next year.
   Graham Lord, literary editor of The Sunday Express, said Rushdie
``has managed during his awful captivity to write a remarkably
lighthearted, almost mischievous children's book.''
   But Lord found ``poignant autobiographical shadows of Rushdie's
own dreadful predicament,'' especially in the remark of one
character who said: ``Happy endings are much rarer in stories, and
also in life, than most people think.''
   ``Coming from Rushdie, in apparently unending captivity, that
sounds like a desperate cry echoing in the dark,'' Lord said.
   David Hughes, in The Mail on Sunday, said: ``Salman Rushdie, the
flags of merriment flying throughout his allegory, wins a grim
fight of his own ... His fine book, written in conditions in which
such ebullience of mood takes courage, is a great re-echoing cry
for freedom of word and view, for the inarguable truth in a good
story.''
   Writer and critic Marina Warner, reviewing the book in The
Sunday Times, which published several excerpts, said Rushdie's
``jauntiness'' under sentence of death ``is matter for wonder
enough'' but ``what is even more so is the ... absolutely unpompous
treatment of the villains in the story.''
   Rushdie ``meditates on compromise, on the sympathy of opposites,
the symbolic beauty of silence and the night as well as their
terrors,'' she wrote.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0040 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 1628EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-WeatherpageWeather     09-23 0243</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Weatherpage Weather,0270</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rain In Southwest And Northeast</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Rain was scattered over the Southwest on Sunday, with locally
heavy rain causing minor flooding, and rain also was scattered
across the northeastern quarter of the nation.
   Afternoon showers and thunderstorms extended over east-central
through southeastern Nevada and northwestern Arizona, extending
into parts of California, and over parts of New Mexico and the
southwest half of Texas.
   Several rural roads in Texas' Val Verde County were closed by
high water, the National Weather Service said.
   Flood warnings were posted along the Rio Grande from Presidio,
Texas, through Big Bend National Park to the mouth of the Pecos
River below Langtry, Texas. The river crested at Lajitas at nearly
5 feet above flood stage, the weather service said.
   Showers and thunderstorms also were scattered over eastern Upper
Michigan, northeastern Lower Michigan, Ohio, New York state,
Pennsylvania, northern West Virginia, eastern Virginia, Delaware,
eastern Maryland, and northern Maine.
   Warnings of gale force wind were posted over Lake Erie, Lake
Huron and western Lake Ontario.
   Elsewhere, showers and thunderstorms also spread across the
Florida Peninsula.
   Rainfall amounts during the six hours up to 2 p.m. EDT were less
than 1 inch.
   Also in Florida, West Palm Beach warmed to a record high of 93,
and Key West tied its record high of 92.
   Sunday's low for the Lower 48 states was 25 at West Yellowstone,
Mont.
   Temperatures around the nation at 3 p.m. EDT ranged from 45 at
Alpena and Sault Ste. Marie, Mich., to 94 at Fort Myers, Fla.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0041 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 1651EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-Embargo     09-23 0526</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Embargo,0663</SECOND>
<HEAD>Military Equipment Still Getting Through To Iraq, Officers Say</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf Rdp Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RICHARD PYLE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DHAHRAN, Saudi Arabia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Seven weeks after the United
Nations imposed sanctions on Iraq, military equipment and other
material with war potential continues to slip through the naval
web, U.S. officers said Sunday.
   The officers said shipments marked for delivery to the Jordanian
port of Aqaba are actually being taken overland to Iraq.
   The amount and type of cargo passing through Aqaba is classified
information. But officers familiar with the situation indicate the
flow has been fairly extensive. They say their suspicions are based
partly on confidential intelligence data.
   One cargo vessel, intercepted by the U.S. Navy within the past
week, carried British-made Land Rovers painted in military
camouflage, they said. They said they could not reveal where the
cargo was coming from.
   Another ship was carrying a load of scrap metal, aluminum,
silica and other materials that are ``basic components in the
manufacture of explosives,'' one officer said.
   In both cases, the cargoes were listed on the ships' manifests
as bound for Aqaba, and there was no way for American boarding
parties to determine whether they were ultimately destined for
Iraq, about a 350-mile trip by road, the officers said.
   ``We suspect that's where some of the stuff labeled for Aqaba is
going, but we don't have proof,'' said Capt. Paul Prokop, commander
of U.S. Coast Guard teams taking part in the multinational effort
to enforce the U.N. sanctions.
   ``There are a lot of ways for an innovative shipper to avoid a
blockade, and as the price goes up, they become more innovative,''
he added.
   Jordan insists it is abiding by the embargo even though it faces
economic devastation. King Hussein has called for Iraq to withdraw
from Kuwait, but has generally sided with Baghdad since the Aug. 2
invasion.
   Officials in Aqaba said the port is at a near standstill because
of the sanctions, with the number of arriving ships dwindling from
about 25 a day to two or three. Aqaba, Jordan's only seaport, is
normally a major transit point for Iraq-bound goods.
   The U.N. Security Council imposed an economic embargo in
response to the Iraqi invasion. The council later approved the use
of minimal force to prevent ships from trading with Iraq.
   ``The effort is far from being airtight, as any observer is well
aware ... If the powers that be are going to have this effort as
airtight as they want, someone's going to have to speak to our
friends in Jordan,'' said Prokop.
   As of Sunday, officers said the U.S. Navy had conducted 1,251
interceptions of mechant ships since sanctions were imposed Aug. 6.
   Of these, 880 were in the Gulf of Oman, Arabian Sea and the
Persian Gulf, with 371 in the Red Sea, the route for the narrow
Gulf of Aqaba and the Jordanian port.
   But the pattern of activity is reversed when it comes to
boardings. Of 105 boardings to date, 80 to 90 were in the Red Sea.
   Ships from about eight other navies, including the British,
French, Italian and Australian, are also participating in
interdiction operations.
   The warship crews ask all passing merchant vessels to name their
ports of origin, destination and cargo.
   If there are suspicions a ship may be carrying cargo to or from
Iraq or occupied Kuwait, it is asked to allow a boarding party to
inspect the manifest and cargo. If the cargo is found to be
Iraqi-related, the ship is instructed to divert to another port.
   There have been six such diversions so far, the officers said.
In three other instances, warning shots were fired to force ships
to stop and be searched.
   U.S. officers say their warships have the option of shooting to
disable a ship tht defies challenge. So far, that has not
happened.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0042 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 1657EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Israel-U.S.     09-23 0331</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel-U.S.,0385</SECOND>
<HEAD>Israeli Foreign Minister Visits U.S.</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Foreign Minister David Levy flew to New York
Sunday to talk to U.S. officials about Middle East peace and to the
Soviets about renewing diplomatic relations.
   Levy is expected to voice Israeli objections to a proposed U.S.
arms sale to Saudi Arabia and seek more U.S. military aid for
Israel, according to a newspaper quoting diplomatic sources.
   On Saturday, Levy is scheduled to meet his Soviet counterpart,
Eduard Shevardnadze, when they attend the U.N. General Assembly.
   ``I expect to hear from Shevardnadze what direction Soviet
policy will be taking in order to advance toward a resumption of
diplomatic relations between our two countries,'' Levy said before
leaving for the United States.
   The Soviet Union broke ties with Israel following the 1967
Middle East war. Relations have warmed under Soviet President
Mikhail S. Gorbachev, and the two countries exchanged diplomatic
missions in 1987.
   Levy said his meeting with Shevardnadze was arranged last week
in Moscow by an Israeli Foreign Ministry delegation.
   The Kremlin says it will restore full diplomatic ties if Israel
agrees to an international Middle East peace conference. Israel
believes a conference would force it to make concessions, and
insists on negotiating directly with Arab governments.
   Levy is also to meet with Secretary of State James A. Baker III
this week and hear about the talks Baker held in Syria and Saudi
Arabia earlier this month on the Persian Gulf crisis and related
issues.
   ``We will also be talking about and expressing ideas about the
supply of such tremendous ammounts of arms to Saudi Arabia. I shall
be expressing Israel's needs in my talks with Baker,'' Levy said.
   The Haaretz newspaper Sunday quoted diplomatic sources saying
Levy will note Israel's opposition to a proposed $10 billion U.S.
arms sale to Saudi Arabia, and press Israel's request for more U.S.
military aid.
   Israel is seeking $1 billion to buy more sophisticated planes
and other weapons to match the proposed Saudi deal. This is in
addition to a $700 million increase in the annual $1.8 billion U.S.
military aid package to Israel.
   Levy is also expected to meet with 15 foreign ministers at the
United Nations, including those from China, Egypt, Japan and
Turkey.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0043 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 1710EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Colombia-Kidnappings     09-23 0339</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Colombia-Kidnappings,0370</SECOND>
<HEAD>President Says He Will Not Negotiate With Drug Traffickers</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By STAN YARBRO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOGOTA, Colombia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Cesar Gaviria, faced with a
hostage crisis blamed on the Medellin cocaine cartel, told
Colombians Sunday his government would not negotiate with drug
traffickers.
   Gaviria's administration has tried to hush press reports about
the hostages - seven journalists and the sister of a Colombian
ambassador. The government has yet to acknowledge they are being
held by the Medellin cartel and has forbidden radio news coverage
of such ``unconfirmed reports.''
   But the cartel claimed responsibility for three of the eight
kidnappings over the past few weeks in a statement faxed to local
news media last week. Newspapers have quoted security officials as
saying the statement is authentic.
   And local newspapers have cited reliable cartel sources as
saying all eight kidnapping victims are in the traffickers' hands.
   In a letter published Sunday in Bogota's El Espectador
newspaper, the president addressed questions about how he is
handling his first crisis since taking office on Aug. 7.
   A Saturday editorial had voiced the doubts of many Colombians by
asking if the government was ``surreptitiously conversing with drug
traffickers.''
   Gaviria answered with a resounding ``No.''
   ``Everything can be presumed except that the government is
carrying on a dialogue or maintaining whatever type of contact with
criminal organizations,'' the president said in his letter to the
newspaper.
   The recent string of kidnappings ended a nearly two-month break
in the cartel's terrorist campaign. The Medellin traffickers
declared a unilateral cease-fire in the campaign last July, saying
they wanted to demonstrate their desire for peace.
   Bombings and other attacks by the cartel had killed more than
500 people in the year before the truce was declared.
   Earlier this month, Gaviria offered traffickers an incentive to
turn themselves in.
   He said traffickers who surrender would be tried in Colombia,
rather than extradited to the United States. He also offered
reduced prison sentences for drug suspects in exchange for their
cooperation with authorities.
   Last week's statement by the Medellin cartel said Gaviria's
offer was unacceptable. Instead, traffickers say they want a full
amnesty for past crimes.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0044 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 1717EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>d w AM-WorldBank-PoorCountri     09-23 0253</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-World Bank-Poor Countries,250</SECOND>
<HEAD>World Changes Weaken Leverage Of Poor Countries, Leader Says</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Middle East crisis must not be allowed to
overshadow or hinder the long-term battle against world poverty,
the chairman of an international financial committee said Sunday.
   Bernard Chidzero, chairman of the Development Committee of the
World Bank and the International Monetary Fund, said the
possibility of worldwide inflation and high interest rates
triggered by Iraq's takeover of Kuwait will affect discussions of
the group on Monday.
   But he said the world's greatest challenge is still the
eradication of poverty. The Development Committee is made up of
finance ministers and other officials from 22 countries who advise
the bank and the fund on the transfer of resources to developing
countries.
   One billion people either live in poverty or on the brink of
poverty, said Chidzero, who is also finance minister of Zimbabwe.
   ``I do not believe we can build a safe and stable world when we
have hundreds of millions of people'' living without shelter or
dying of hunger, he said at a news conference.
   He criticized rich nations for expecting developing countries to
open up trade barriers while they refuse to adopt more liberal
policies themselves.
   But Chidzero said it is becoming more difficult for poor nations
to maintain a unified voice in trade negotiations, since some are
more successful than others at achieving growth.
   He said that although newly emerging democracies in Eastern
Europe have some similarity with the developing countries of the
world, their history, location and racial ties to developed
countries give them an advantage in pushing towards development.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0045 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 1716EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-LePen     09-23 0308</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Le Pen,0356</SECOND>
<HEAD>Right-Wing Leader Says Iraq Embargo `Unworthy of Civilized
Nations'</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The leader of the right-wing National Front party
said Sunday the trade embargo against Iraq was beneath the
international community and warned the Persian Gulf crisis could
spur new waves of immigration.
   ``It is unworthy of civilized nations to want to starve the
Iraqi population, just as it is unworthy to want to destroy it by
bombings,'' Jean-Marie Le Pen told several thousand followers at
the close of the party's annual festival.
   Le Pen has been often criticized for alleged anti-Semitic
remarks and his strong stance against immigrants, particularly
those from Arab nations.
   Since the Aug. 2 Iraqi invasion of Kuwait, Le Pen's comments
against Western intervention led to some defections from his party,
which holds one seat in the 577-member National Assembly.
   Le Pen said the gulf crisis would lead to increased immigration,
unemployment and other economic problems in France.
   ``It is not Iraq which is responsible for the rising price of
oil,'' Le Pen said. ``The responsibility lies with the blockade
organized by Western nations.''
   The U.N. Security Council on Aug. 6 approved the trade embargo,
which is being enforced by ships from the United States, France and
other nations.
   Le Pen, a member of the European Parliament, also blamed the
French government for threats to French citizens trapped in Kuwait
and Iraq. He claimed the world's major powers knew Iraq was
planning to invade Kuwait.
   ``So it was with full knowledge that the French government left
French citizens behind'' as hostages, he said.
   Paris Mayor Jacques Chirac was criticized for allowing the
National Front party festival to convene in a section of the Bois
de Boulogne park on the western edge of Paris.
   More than six towns have banned National Front gatherings since
the May 10 desecration of a Jewish cemetery in Carpentras in
southern France. Authorities accused Le Pen of indirect
responsibility.
   The Natonal Front, formed in 1984, has the support of about 15
percent of French voters, according to polls earlier this year.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0046 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 1733EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-StolenArt     09-23 0217</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Stolen Art,0236</SECOND>
<HEAD>Recovery of Italian Painting in Paris Leads to Other Stolen Works</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The recovery of a 15th century portrait and the
capture of the man who allegedly stole it from an Italian museum
led police to a cache of six other paintings snatched from museums
in Paris over the summer.
   Police raided an apartment Saturday in a posh Paris neighborhood
and found the portrait of the doge Francesco Foscari, stolen Friday
from the Correr Museum in Saint Mark's Square in Venice.
   The suspect, Richard Etoh-Mvondo, 21, provided information that
led police to six stolen paintings that were being kept in Lyon, in
southeast France, authorities said Sunday.
   The paintings, including a Renoir stolen from the Louvre, were
lifted from their frames during visiting hours at various Paris
museums. Police did not say whether they believed Etoh-Mvondo was
involved in those thefts. They gave no indication of whether there
were other suspects.
   The 20- by 16-inch portrait of Francesco Foscari, painted about
1470 by Lazzaro Bastiani, was removed from its frame in the
second-floor gallery of the city-run Correr Museum in Venice.
   Venetian police contacted French authorities after a security
guard at the museum reported noticing a suspicious French-speaking
man near the stolen work.
   The thief apparently concealed the painting in pastry-wrapping
paper and took it by train to Paris. It was not damaged, police
said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0047 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 1800EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-WorldBank-Romania     09-23 0390</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-World Bank-Romania,410</SECOND>
<HEAD>Romania Seeks Development of Private Enterprise, Joins IFC</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: Theodor is cq in 2nd graf</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By DAVID BRISCOE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Romania became the 138th member of the World
Finance Corp. on Sunday, signaling a quest for private enterprise
in a formerly communist-ruled country where all major businesses
still are run by the state.
   ``It's a big step in our economic program for the transition to
a market economy,'' said Romanian Finance Minister Theodor
Stolojan.
   The IFC, which is affiliated with the World Bank, finances and
assists in the development of private enterprise in developing
countries.
   Stolojan, in Washington for the World Bank and International
Monetary Fund annual meetings, said his country previously had no
reason to join the IFC ``because there was no room for the private
sector.''
   Earlier this year, the Romanian parliament agreed to grant 30
percent of state-owned corporations to the public, with a voucher
system that would distribute shares to each adult citizen. The
remaining 70 percent would be sold in shares to Romanian and
foreign investors, Stolojan said.
   The first challenge for the international agency, he said, will
be to help Romania develop a stock market. There is also great
potential for a tourist industry, he said.
   ``We are firm in our decision to go to a market economy,'' the
finance minister said at a joint news conference with IFC director
Douglas Gustafson who said a team would be sent to Romania to see
how the country can be helped in its efforts to develop more
private enterprise.
   Gustafson said it was too early to predict how much financing
would be needed. He said the organization would start by providing
technical assistance.
   The IFC, he said, could help create private sector activity,
financial markets and joint ventures.
   Mugur Isarescu, governor of the National Bank of Romania, said
the country also plans to develop a full-fledged central bank and a
private banking system but needs more skilled personnel.
   Isarescu said there would be difficulties changing from the
``command economy'' developed under 45 years of Communist rule,
which ended with free elections in May following the December 1989
overthrow of dictator Nicolae Ceausescu.
   ``I don't think it is possible to just say `bing-bang' and have
a market economy,'' Isarescu said.
   The Romanian officials said signs of progress are already
apparent in the country, with more than 4,000 small enterprises
operating and thousands more ``inside-the-family businesses.''
   Last Easter, Stolojan said, Romanians for the first Easter in 20
years could buy eggs in the market because of the development of
agricultural businesses on unused land deeded to individuals by the
state.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0048 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 1753EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-RaccoonSnacks     09-23 0429</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Raccoon Snacks,0502</SECOND>
<HEAD>Raccoons Who Raid Human Food Face Similar Health Problems</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT LEE ZIMMER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>URBANA, Ill. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Raccoons who snack on Twinkies, Oreos and
Big Macs suffer the same consequences as humans - rotten teeth and
high cholesterol, researchers say.
   Scientists say they were shocked by results from a small
sampling of the masked mischief-makers that roam Illinois parks and
campgrounds, scavenging human food.
   ``Their mouths look like those pictures in the dentist's office
that show what will happen if you don't brush,'' said Laura
Hungerford, a University of Illinois veterinarian. ``I think they
have a lot of sugar in their diet.''
   Wild raccoons usually have healthy teeth, but Hungerford found
broken teeth, gum disease and cavities in the campground animals.
   Many park raccoons also had cuts on their faces and paws; a few
suffered broken legs.
   ``Raccoons are aggressive for food,'' Hungerford said. ``The
injuries probably are related to digging through trash cans or
getting hit by swinging garbage can lids.''
   In the wild, raccoons eat berries, grass, small fish and rodents
- they're not particular. Researchers don't know specifically what
kinds of human food the racoons are eating because they're not
choosy.
   ``They're omnivores (that) will eat anything from bugs to
pizza,'' said Charles Nixon, a wildlife biologist at the Illinois
Natural History Survey, which is cooperating in the study with the
University of Illinois and Western Illinois University.
   The early findings from a survey this spring prompted a more
thorough investigation, now underway, of how raccoons interact with
people.
   Researchers will trap and examine 100 raccoons this fall, half
in Siloam Springs State Park in western Illinois and half in the
wilds of Brown County. After about 12 hours, they will be returned
to the wild.
   In addition to mouth and body examinations, the raccoons' blood
will be tested for any diseases that could be shared with humans.
The researchers, who are examining whether racoons may transfer
diseases to humans or vice versa, have already have found that some
snacking raccoons suffer high cholesterol levels.
   ``This is important because humans are using recreational areas
more and more, bringing humans and raccoons into more intimate
contact,'' Hungerford said.
   Park officials already have modified many trash containers so
raccoons cannot get into them easily and aren't as likely to be
injured trying, but the animals have learned that people bring
food.
   ``During the weekend when there are fewer visitors, there are
fewer raccoons, and they concentrate around the campsites that are
being used,'' Hungerfor said.
   Some of the animals will be tagged with radio collars to see how
far they roam and where they take shelter.
   Capture is not difficult, using box-type traps that do not hurt
the raccoons. They're lured into the traps by smelly bait like
sardines and mustard sauce.
   ``A couple of these coons have decided they like being trapped -
you get food,'' Hungerford said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0049 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 1810EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-Jordan-SaudiArab CORRECTIVE   09-23 0091</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Jordan-Saudi Arabia, CORRECTIVE,0071</SECOND>
<NOTE>Eds: Members who used the story slugged AM-Saudi Arabia-Oil, a0711,
sent Friday, Sept. 21, are asked to use the following story:</NOTE>
<DATELINE>AMMAN, Jordan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Associated Press on Friday reported
erroneous figures for Jordan's oil consumption and the extent to
which it relied on Iraqi oil. Jordan uses more than 60,000 barrels
a day, 25,000 barrels of which is obtained from Iraq, the Jordanian
Finance Ministry said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0050 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 1812EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-Iraq-Excerpts 1stLd-Writethru a0644 09-23 0743</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Iraq-Excerpts, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0644,0958</SECOND>
<HEAD>Excerpts of Iraqi Communique</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf Rdp, Bjt</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Removes ellipses where text should be continuous.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>NICOSIA, Cyprus (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are excerpts from the communique
issued Sunday after a joint meeting of Iraq's ruling Revolution
Command Council and Baath Party. The statement in Arabic was
translated into English by The Associated Press:
   ---
   America is commiting deep criminal acts against Iraq and the
Arab nation especially in occupying the Arab and Moslem holy places
in Najd and Hejaz (the former name for the territory that became
Saudi Arabia), and in its sanctions imposed against the Iraqi
people in a way that exceeds all humanitarian limits.
   The United States, thus, has gone far below the minimum level of
human standards toward which even those who believe in the law of
the jungle would not stop.
   America did all this to satisfy its arrogance and enforce its
hegemony on the entire world...
   America must not go too far and must get out of its mind the
idea of pushing events into a military collision, and it must
realize the dangers of what it calls a lightning strike.
   It should also abandon all this and remedy it as soon as
possible, by returning to the innermost parts of itself so as to
search for remnants of wisdom to aid it so as to turn away from
this dangerous approach, as soon as possible. Primarily, it should
withdraw from the holy lands of the Arabs and Moslems.
   America must realize clearly that it is pushing the entire
region, and not only Iraq - in fact, even the whole world, foremost
of which its sons whom (President) Bush brought to the region - to
the brink of a bottomless abyss, from which the region will never
see light for dozens of years...
   The oil, the areas it is in and Israel will be transformed into
something different from what they are now.
   We will never allow anybody, whomever he may be, to strangle the
people of Iraq without having himself strangled. If we feel that
the Iraqi people are being strangled, that there are some who will
deal a sanguinary blow to it, we will strangle all those who are
the cause of this.
   The oil areas in Saudi Arabia and in other states of the region,
all the oil installations, will be rendered incapable of responding
to the needs of those who came to us as occupiers in order to usurp
our sovereignty, dignity and wealth.
   Israel will be included in all actions that affect the owners of
the homeland in which the forces of evil and occupation have
settled, and in which nothing has maintained its purity except for
the holy places and the generous people who reject this injustice
and aggression...
   Those who wish the flood to overtake the Iraqi people and the
nation, and are planning for this, should remember well that the
waves of the flood will overwhelm them before they overwhelm the
Iraqi people...
   America, and those who instigated it or collaborated with it,
should realize this well so as to reassess matters and to think
again in the correct and precise manner upon which they should
build. The reckless, odious, and foolish behavior that has occurred
so far should be enough for them...
   Everybody should also realize that what we have warned against
might happen when the sparks come out of the barrels of confronting
guns, and out of the friction of the fleets of aggression with our
means and forces.
   The sparks might fly by mistake or deliberately to afterward
cause a huge conflagration. When this happens, a flood will ensue.
To prevent the feared eventuality from taking place, those
concerned should pull back armies as well as navy and air fleets as
soon as possible.
   Dire consequences will befall those who love to create wars,
problems, and crises. They will also befall evildoers and back
stabbers...
   As for the Arabs who are launching good offices, they are urged
not to replace the solution that we offered on 12th August with a
partial solution, as turning the conflict from one concerning major
issues into one regarding minor issues benefits the tactics of the
enemies and their supporters...
   The major issue concerns the struggle of the Arabs and Moslems
in their righteous jihad (holy war) against falsehood. The prime
objective is the liberation of Palestine from the usurpation of the
Zionist usurpers...
   Iraq's adherence to this position through an unequivocal
declared policy has caused the evil arrows to be directed against
it and caused the poisonous wasps to leave their holes to sting its
sides and cause them to bleed in the most dangerous conspiracy that
seeks to inflict political and economic harm on iraq to prepare for
the military weakening of Iraq and also for the weakening of its
nationalist, pan-Arab, and humanitarian role.
   The conspiracy and those behind it have been exposed. At the
forefront of those charged with staging the conspiracy were the
former rulers of Kuwait who used Kuwait, which was separated from
Iraq, as a base for a counterconspiracy. They have massed its
stolen resources to serve everything that would bring evil and
disgrace to the national and Islamic struggle...
   The blow dealt to that evil ruling clique, the agent of the
foreigner, was an indispensable defensive move to maintain Iraq's
features and resources and improve them in order to achieve the
well-known noble objectives...
   Thus, usurped Kuwait was restored to its people to be part of
its original nation by an eternal decision from which there can be
no retreat under any circumstances or conditions.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0051 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 1816EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Israel-Anti-Semitism     09-23 0473</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel-Anti-Semitism,0539</SECOND>
<HEAD>Government Warns Anti-Semitism Escalating to `19th Century Level'</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The government warned Sunday of a worldwide
surge in anti-Semitic violence and said attitudes toward Jews were
slipping back to ``the spirit of the 19th century.''
   A 12-page report reviewing anti-Semitism in 1990 cited murders
and bombings among the incidents.
   It said the Soviet Union and Eastern Europe were the focal
points of attacks and threats against Jews by ultra right-wing
activists operating more freely since democratic reforms.
   Also blamed for growing anti-Jewish sentiments were neo-Nazis,
Moslem fundamentalists and Christian groups, mostly in Western
Europe.
   Social upheavals in some countries also have turned Jews again
into scapegoats, the report said.
   In Latin America, for example, Jews are increasingly ``targeted
by terrorist groups, especially leftist ones, in their war against
their governments,'' it said.
   Anti-Semitism also is on the rise in the United States and
Canada, the report said.
   It said that desecrations of Jewish cemeteries, such as in
Carpentras, France, last May, had reached ``epidemic proportions in
many nations.''
   ``The conclusion, without trying to create panic, is a feeling
that open anti-Semitism is growing with many countries sliding into
tolerance, a normalization that is in the spirit of the 19th
century, despite all the Jewish people went through in the 20th
century,'' the report said.
   Cabinet Secretary Eliakim Rubinstein, who compiled the report,
suggested in an interview on Israeli radio that more could be done
by authorities in other nations to quell anti-Semitic acts.
   ``There are two weapons to use: one is by warning, putting
perpetrators on trial, the second is through education ... like
making the Holocaust not only a marginal chapter in history
classes,'' Rubinstein said.
   An estimated 6 million Jews died at the hands of the Nazis
during World War II. The Holocaust was a catalyst for the founding
of Israel in 1948.
   Rubinstein's committee began studying anti-Semitism in 1988.
Sunday's report was its third and most severe.
   It cited 18 anti-Semitic attacks on Jews, including bombings,
kidnappings and beatings so far this year.
   Three attacks were in Western Europe, including Britain; two in
the United States; two in South Africa; one in New Zealand; and 10
in Latin America, including several kidnappings, murders and
bombings, the report said. It gave no details.
   In the Soviet Union, the report claims ultra-nationalist groups
have blamed Jews for corruption and the downfall of communism.
   Much of the Soviet anti-Semitism has surfaced in criticisms in
prominent newspapers and threats of pogroms, organized attacks used
against Jews in czarist Russia, the report said.
   A report by the quasi-government Jewish Agency predicted up to 2
million Soviet Jews could emigrate to Israel by 1995, swelling the
nation's present population of 4.5 million by 45 percent. Some of
the immigration is prompted by an anti-Semitic atmosphere, the
agency's report said.
   ``On the popular level you didn't see as much anti-Semitism
before glasnost because there was more government control,''
Rubinstein said.
   The report said Soviet President Mikhail Gorbachev had failed to
publicly condemn the anti-Semitism, ``perhaps because of (his)
attempts to maintain the support of various conservative
elements.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0052 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 1816EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-DrugPlane     09-23 0344</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Drug Plane,0420</SECOND>
<HEAD>Pilot Says Drug Plane Tailed Him To Airport</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ALLENTOWN, Pa. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A pilot practicing takeoffs and landings
says a stolen DC-3 cargo plane later found with nearly 1{ tons of
cocaine aboard shadowed him with most of its lights off, perhaps to
hide from radar.
   Air traffic controllers at Allentown-Bethlehem-Easton
International Airport didn't know the plane was there until he
radioed, the pilot told The (Allentown) Morning Call, speaking on
the condition he not be identified.
   Authorities confirmed his account. Airport Director Jack Yohe
said the planes passed within 300 to 500 feet of each other.
   The DC-3 approached the airport with most lights off late Friday
and made an unscheduled landing, apparently because it had run low
on fuel. One man was arrested, two escaped, and 2,968 pounds of
cocaine were seized.
   The small plane pilot speculated the cargo plane flew directly
above him to make them appear as  single blip on radar screens.
   ``I was coming in for a landing, and I was watching one airplane
while I was waiting my turn to land, and I looked up out of the
airplane and there was another plane above me, at an altitude of
probably less than a thousand feet,'' the pilot said in an
interview published Sunday.
   ``The only lights (the other plane) had on were the red and
green marker lights. There was no strobe light; there was no
nothing. That was all I saw - the outline of the plane.
   ``I called the radar guy at the ... control tower, and I said,
`Do you have this guy on your scope?' and he said, `What plane?'''
   Alerted, air traffic controllers notified airport security,
which met the plane when it taxied to a refueling station. The men
told the security guards they needed fuel and then fled on foot
into a residential neighborhood.
   Police seized the plane and found 28 military-style duffel bags
stuffed with 1,349 kilograms of cocaine packed in 1-kilo blocks. A
kilogram weighs about 2.2 pounds.
   The Colombian cocaine, thought to have been destined for Canada,
was valued at $130 million. Officials said the DC-3 was reported
stolen Wednesday from the Opa-Locke Airport outside Miami.
   Harold Hill, 46, of Brantford, Ontario, was caught and charged
with possession of cocaine with intent to deliver and conspiracy.
He was arraigned Saturday and was being held in Lehigh County
prison, with bail set at $10 million, District Attorney William
Platt said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0053 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 1818EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r e BC-Opera     09-23 0403</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Opera,0507</SECOND>
<HEAD>1932 Schoenberg Opera `Moses und Aron' Has New York City Premiere</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: No PMs Planned</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By MARY CAMPBELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The atonal music of Arnold Schoenberg may be as
difficult to listen to as any composed in the 20th century.
   The New York City Opera charged into its challenges and Saturday
night gave the New York premiere of his two-act 1932 opera ``Moses
und Aron,'' which had its American premiere in Boston in 1966. The
opera will be heard five more times this season.
   The production, originally developed for the Cologne Opera in
1978, is brilliantly done.
   The music, powerful but not attractive to the ear, is propelled
by rhythm. Because it doesn't follow a musical line, it's harder to
listen to than Berg's ``Lulu'' or ``Wozzeck.''
   Nonetheless, the orchestra, conducted by Christopher Keene, and
singers sounded splendid. They obviously had worked long and hard
on the complex music. The production is imaginitively lighted. All
scenes are viewed as though in a dusk that makes images fuzzy.
Chorus men wore suits made like prison issue and women wore dresses
resembling waitress uniforms, all - from shoes through face and
hair - the grim color of white clay. Spotlights on the floor
sometimes created tall shadows on the back wall.
   Thomas Young was Aron. This year he will also sing in John
Adams' new opera, ``The Death of Klinghoffer.'' Richard Cross was a
bearded, white-haired Moses, whose part is performed mainly in
``sprechstimme,'' or speaking to music.
   In the opera, Moses isn't a fluent speaker; God has chosen his
brother Aron to be his spokesman.
   The two are constantly in spiritual conflict. Moses has Aron
explain the unimaginable God to the Israelites and they say hey
need something visible. Aron makes Moses' staff become a snake. The
Israelites decide God is strong if he has such mighty servants and
they'll follow Moses out of Israel.
   In Act 2, the Israelites are in the wilderness, frustrated and
about to riot because Moses has been gone so long, receiving the 10
Commandments. Aron says they can have their old gods back, collects
gold and exhibits a beautiful little golden calf on a pedestal, lit
by spotlights of changing colors. In the longest scene, there is
dancing, a ritual sacrifice to the calf and an orgy.
   The opera ends soon after Moses returns with tablets. He raises
his hand, the golden calf falls and its pedestal disappears. He and
Aron argue again, Aron saying the people need something concrete as
well as an idea and Moses lamenting his inability to explain the
invisible God to them himself.
   Schoenberg, who died in 1951, intended to write a third act but
never did.
   The program is the New York City Opera debut for director Hans
Neugebauer, set and costume designer Achim Freyer and lighting
designer Hans Toelstede. For Freyer, it's also his American debut.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0054 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 1824EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-UN-Iraq 1stLd-Writethru a0718 09-23 0346</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-UN-Iraq, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0718,0391</SECOND>
<HEAD>Iraq Says It Won't Attend U.N. General Assembly</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 5th graf, `There was ...' with State Department comment;
picks up 6th graf pvs, `The 160-member ...</NOTE>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf Rdp, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NICOSIA, Cyprus (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Iraqi Foreign Minister Tariq Aziz accused
the United States Sunday of preventing him from attending the U.N.
General Assembly debate on the gulf crisis and said his government
will not participate.
   In a letter to U.N. Secretary General Javier Perez de Cuellar,
Aziz said the State Department on Thursday had refused his
government's request to permit an Iraqi Airways jetliner carrying
Aziz to land in New York.
   The State Department told the Iraqi ambassador in Washington
that the ban on landing rights was in line with sanctions imposed
after Iraq's Aug. 2 invasion of Kuwait, Aziz was quoted as saying
in an Iraqi News Agency report, monitored in Nicosia.
   The State Department ``proposed that the foreign minister and
his entourage find alternative commercial means to fly them to New
York,'' Aziz said.
   ``I regret to inform you that the Iraqi government's decision is
not to participate in the deliberations of the U.N. General
Assembly until the U.S. government lifts all restrictions
preventing the arrival of the Iraqi delegation aboard an Iraqi
jetliner,'' he said.
   In Washington, a State Department official who spoke on
condition of anonymity said the matter ``actually is still under
discussion. But it would seem inappropriate to grant permission for
the Iraqi foreign minister to fly his plane to the United States
while hundreds of Americans citizens are being held against their
will in Iraq and Kuwait.''
   The 160-member General Assembly convenes its 45th session
Monday. The 15-member Security Council is to meet Tuesday in
emergency session to discuss approving an air blockade to
complement other sanctions to throttle Iraq's economy and force it
to relinquish Kuwait.
   ``The decision of the U.S. administration in reality means
prohibiting the Iraqi foreign minister from participating in the
deliberations of the General Assembly to convey Iraq's viewpoints
on events in the Gulf and conduct dialogue with U.N. members on the
issue,'' Aziz said.
   ``This measure has special implications in these circumstances
as the Security Council prepares, at the instigation of the United
States and its Western allies, to push through an air blockade of
Iraq.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0055 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 1830EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-DancingDisabled     09-23 0405</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Dancing Disabled,0502</SECOND>
<HEAD>Center Gives Disabled Chance to Dance</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PAM SCHMID</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WEST ST. PAUL, Minn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   As Nancy Raddatz sees it, a
wheelchair is no excuse to keep from tap dancing. Nor should
blindness throw a damper on a romantic pas de deux.
   So the longtime dance teacher blew away 30 years of dust and
spent over $80,000 of her own money to convert a sheet metal firm
into the Uniquely Abled Dance Center, a ground-floor studio
exclusively for the disabled.
   The center, which will offer free lessons, took seven years to
materialize and opened Sunday. About 70 students make up its first
class.
   ``It's quite an undertaking,'' said Raddatz, who has danced for
51 of her 53 years and taught jazz, tap, ballet and ballroom
dancing for 41 of them.
   She's no newcomer to teaching the disabled, with whom she says
she can empathize after being stricken with polio as a child.
Dozens of children and adults with vision, hearing and mobility
impairments have already learned the love of dancing through
Raddatz's commercial school.
   ``You look at their disability, but technically you look at
their ability,'' she said. ``And that's what you work with.''
   Her dream of creating a studio exclusively for the disabled
began to take shape when her uncle moved his ground-floor sheet
metal business out of the building that housed her original studio
upstairs.
   She bought the building, which left her with a ground floor full
of shelves, dust and concrete. But she needed thousands of dollars
more to transform the space into a dance studio. Sponsors at first
were hard to come by.
   ``One group I wrote to said their funds only go to people who
appreciate the arts,'' she said. ``As if, when you're blind or
deaf, you can't appreciate such things.''
   The spark finally came in 1988, when nearby Henry Sibley High
School raised $3,000.
   As word spread, local businesses and service organizations began
chipping in time and materials. Her students and their families
formed an army of volunteers.
   Raddatz believes she's the first to open a free dance center
exclusively for the disabled, and she hopes the idea catches on.
   ``If I start, maybe this will be incentive for other people to
do the same thing,'' she said. ``And if we make videotapes of the
experience, this could be something that just sort of spokes out
and is made available in other areas.
   ``Dancing is a way of expressing yourself, and it's therapeutic.
When children and adults come in here, it's a happy experience. So
you do see them blossoming.''
   As a prime example, she points to 11-year-old Jennifer Jackson,
a Down's syndrome child who has taken jazz and tap lessons at her
original studio for three years.
   ``It's helped her tremendously in her coordination,'' said
Jennifer's mother, Joellyn. ``The dance class also gives her
something she can accomplish and be proud of.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0056 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 1831EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-Iraq-France     09-23 0397</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Iraq-France,0460</SECOND>
<HEAD>Iraq Apologizes to France for Raid on Ambassador's Residence</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf Rdp, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NICOSIA, Cyprus (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Iraq on Sunday unexpectedly apologized to
France for the raid on the French ambassador's residence in Kuwait
that sparked a series of diplomatic expulsions and an escalation of
tensions in the gulf crisis.
   The official Iraqi News Agency quoted a Foreign Ministry
spokesman as saying that an investigation showed the incident on
Sept. 14 ``was a result of a mistake made by the Iraqi soldiers on
duty in Kuwait City.''
   Iraqi officials previously had denied any raid took place.
   Four Frenchmen, including the French military attache, were
captured by Iraqi troops who forced their way into the ambassador's
residence Sept. 14.
   The spokesman said the Iraqi Foreign Ministry had determined the
soldiers who raided the house did not realize - because the house
was outside the diplomatic quarter - that it was the ``former
French ambassador's home.''
   Iraq refers to envoys in Kuwait as former diplomats, saying they
lost diplomatic immunity after failing to comply with orders to
close their embassies in Kuwait, which Iraq now claims as a
province.
   ``When the officer in charge of the soldiers learned about the
mistake and found out that one of the persons who were in the house
was a former diplomat ... the person received good treatment and
was allowed to return to his site of employment,'' the unidentified
spokesman said in a report monitored in Nicosia.
   ``The other three people, who were not diplomats, were sent to
the Hyatt Regency Hotel and were later flown to Baghdad, where they
reside at Melia-Mansur Hotel,'' he said. ``No measures were taken
against them except they were prevented from travel.''
   Earlier it had been believed the three Frenchmen were moved to
key installations where scores of foreigners are held hostage as
``human shields'' to avert an attack by U.S.-led forces massed in
Saudi Arabia.
   ``The Foreign Ministry apologizes for the previous statement in
which the incident was described differently,'' the spokesman was
quoted as saying.
   Iraq has ordered all embassies in Kuwait City to close. About 15
nations continue to defy the order and disregard Iraq's annexation
of Kuwait. Iraqi authorities have cut off power, water and
telephone lines to those compounds.
   Belgian and Canadian diplomatic quarters in Kuwait were attacked
the same day as the French raid. The Iraqi spokesman made no
mention of these incidents.
   French President Francois Mitterrand retaliated harshly,
ordering 4,000 troops to Saudi Arabia and expelling dozens of
Iraqis from France.
   France's European Community partners expelled Iraqi military
attaches last week.
   Baghdad responded by expelling European, U.S., Egyptian and
Saudi military attaches and their aides.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0057 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 1838EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-KhrushchevMemoirs     09-23 0525</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Khrushchev Memoirs,0640</SECOND>
<HEAD>Khrushchev Thanked Rosenbergs, Called Castro Hotheaded</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Nikita Khrushchev, in memoirs dictated in the
late 1960s but just now released, called Fidel Castro hotheaded for
advocating a nuclear strike against the United States during the
Cuban missile crisis.
   Khrushchev, who was ousted from power in the Soviet Union in
1964 and who died in 1971, also thanked Julius and Ethel Rosenberg
for helping the Soviet Union develop the atomic bomb.
   Khrushchev made a series of tapes as he lived out his last seven
years under virtual house arrest in the village of Petrovo-Dalneye,
on the outskirts of Moscow. Many of the tapes were smuggled to the
West and two volumes of memoirs, ``Khrushchev Remembers'' and
``Khrushchev Remembers: The Last Testament'' were published in the
1970s.
   But Khrushchev's friends and relatives withheld some of the
tapes, fearing that he had been too candid. Last year, Time
magazine acquired the tapes. Excerpts were published in the Oct. 1
issue and another book, ``Khrushchev Remembers: The Glasnost
Tapes,'' is due out in October from Little, Brown.
   In the memoirs, Khrushchev said Josef Stalin was grateful to the
Rosenbergs, who were executed in 1953 after being convicted of
conspiracy to commit espionage by spying on American atom bomb
secrets for the Soviet Union.
   Khrushchev said: ``I was part of Stalin's circle when he
mentioned the Rosenbergs with warmth. I cannot specifically say
what kind of help they gave us, but I heard from both Stalin and
(Vyacheslav) Molotov, then Minister of Foreign Affairs, that the
Rosenbergs provided very significant help in accelerating the
production of our atom bomb.
   ``Let this be a worthy tribute to the memory of those people.
Let my words serve as an expression of gratitude to those who
sacrificed their lives to a great cause of the Soviet state at a
time when the U.S. was using its advantage over us to blackmail our
state and undermine our proletarian cause,'' he added.
   On the Cuban missile crisis, Khrushchev said the Soviets decided
to place missiles in Cuba to deter the United States from an
invasion.
   Khrushchev said President Kennedy ``understood that in spite of
the American advantages, the missiles we had already installed
could strike New York City, Washington and other centers.''
   Then, Khrushchev recalled, intelligence reports indicated that
the United States was preparing to strike Cuba and that an invasion
was unavoidable.
   ``Castro suggested that to prevent our nuclear missiles from
being destroyed, we should launch a pre-emptive strike against the
U.S.,'' he said. ``My comrades in the leadership and I realized
that our friend Fidel totally failed to understand our purpose. We
had installed the missiles not for the purpose of attacking the
U.S. but to keep the U.S. from attacking Cuba.''
   Khrushchev said Kennedy then sent a message ``somewhere between
threat and prayer; he both demanded and begged that we remove the
missiles. We agreed to remove the rockets and warheads if the
president would publicly give assurance, in his own name and that
of his allies, that their armed forces would not invade Cuba.''
   Kennedy did.
   ``Castro was hotheaded. He thought we were retreating - worse,
capitulating. He did not understand that our action was necessary
to prevent a military confrontation ... We believed this came from
his being young and inexperienced as a statesman,'' Khrushchev
said.
   ``Later, when I met Castro in the Soviet Union, I told him, `You
wanted to start a war with the United States. If the war had
started, we would somehow have survived, but Cuba no doubt would
have ceased to exist.' ''
   He added: ``Fidel was embarrassed. He had failed to think
through the obvious consequences of a proposal that placed the
planet on the brink of extinction.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0058 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 1841EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-Turkey-US     09-23 0302</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Turkey-US,0361</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ozal Flies to U.S. for Talks With Bush on Gulf</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By EMEL ANIL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ANKARA, Turkey (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Turgut Ozal on Sunday flew to
the United States, where he is expected to press President Bush for
economic and military aid to offset Turkey's losses from the
economic embargo of Iraq.
   Turkey's losses over a year could be as high as $7 billion,
Turkish officials say.
   Ozal will meet Bush at the White House on Tuesday. He also will
confer with Defense Secretary Dick Cheney and will receive a
briefing from Gen. Colin Powell, chairman of the U.S. Joint Chiefs
of Staff. Ozal later was to address a U.N. summit meeting on
children.
   Turkey is playing a key role in the U.N.-sponsored embargo,
imposed after Iraq invaded Kuwait on Aug. 2. It has shut off two
pipelines carrying Iraqi crude to a terminal on its Mediterranean
coast and ceased its previously large volume of trade with Iraq.
   The United States apparently has not requested a military role
by Turkey. But the Turkish army - with 800,000 men under arms the
largest in NATO besides that of the United States - would likely be
involved if war broke out.
   Turkish forces in the southeast, numbering about 100,000, are
tying up eight Iraqi divisions, according to Turkey's defense
minister, Safa Giray.
   Turkey also has beefed up its air force in the south, shifting
aircraft from other parts of the country. The United States has
deployed 14 F-111 fighter-bombers and 24 F-16s at NATO's Incirlik
airbase near the southern city of Adana.
   Along with requests to help modernize the Turkish armed forces,
Ozal will ask Bush to use his influence to help Turkey obtain soft
loans from the oil-rich gulf states, Japan, the European Economic
Community and international lending agencies, according to
officials who spoke on condition of anonymity.
   To date, the only help has been a $300 million grant from the
exiled Kuwaiti government.
   He also will press the United States to lift restrictions on
Turkey's most competitive export item, textiles and ready-wear
clothing, officials said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0059 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 1858EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-SouterAsJustice     09-23 0482</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soter As Justice,520</SECOND>
<HEAD>Souter Confirmation Prospects Apparently Not Whether But When</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP News Analysis</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RICHARD CARELLI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Early on in David H. Souter's confirmation
hearings, the question on most minds switched from whether he would
be the Supreme Court's newest justice to what kind of justice he
would be.
   Senate approval quickly seemed inevitable. It may come within a
week. But still unanswered is where a Justice Souter fits in on a
court closely divided on key issues.
   The ambiguity surrounding Souter in a way mirrors that
surrounding the president who nominated him.
   Souter's 12-year record as a New Hampshire judge was one of a
close-to-the-vest conservative. But his testimony before the Senate
Judiciary Committee at times startled conservatives because it
suggested an expansive view of some constitutional provisions.
   George Bush campaigned for office as a man dedicated to
appointing Supreme Court members who, like Reagan appointee Antonin
Scalia, would work to overturn the 1973 decision legalizing
abortion.
   But Souter has virtually no track record on abortion, and the
president said he did not ask for assurances - a disappointment to
some abortion foes who support Bush.
   Abortion rights advocates still suspect the worst.
   But it must be remembered that one of Bush's closest friend had
been Potter Stewart, the late Supreme Court justice who abhorred
ideological agendas.
   Souter told his Senate interrogators he is not an adherent of
searching out the ``original intent'' of the Constitution's
authors, but instead believes the court can find new
interpretations of the document's ``original meaning.''
   That's how Souter explained his support of a 1954 court ruling
that the 14th Amendment outlawed racially segregated public
schools, even though the United States was a segregated society
when the amendment was ratified.
   Asked to condemn ``activist judges,'' Souter joked that such a
label usually is attached to anyone who renders unpopular
decisions. He passed up an invitation to criticize any decision of
the liberal Supreme Court of the 1960s.
   Souter endorsed the Supreme Court's one-person, one-vote ruling
that limited states' power to redraw district lines for legislative
elections, and praised effusively William J. Brennan, the retired
liberal justice he was named to succeed.
   Is Souter, billed as a conservative, really a moderate? Probably
not.
   The greater likelihood is Souter is what Sen. Howard Metzenbaum,
D-Ohio, called Anthony M. Kennedy during that justice's
confirmation hearings three years ago - ``a traditional
conservative.''
   Kennedy has joined conservative Chief Justice William H.
Rehnquist in 90 percent of the court's decisions since being
confirmed unanimously by the Senate. His votes gave Rehnquist a
working conservative majority similar to the liberal majority
delivered to Chief Justice Earl Warren in 1962 when Arthur Goldberg
was named a justice.
   Souter's presence could give Rehnquist a sixth vote in a
significant number of cases, but no one can predict with absolute
certainty which cases.
   Once on the court, how would David H. Souter vote in cases
presenting such contentious issues as abortion, affirmative action,
freedom of speech and church-state relations? The nominee swore
under oath he won't know until those cases present themselves.
   ---
   Eds: Richard Carelli has been covering the Supreme Court for The
Associated Press since 1976.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0060 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 1920EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Pakistan-Nuclear     09-23 0322</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Pakistan-Nuclear,0352</SECOND>
<HEAD>Report: Pakistan Aid Linked to Nuclear Verification</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MOHAMMED AFTAB</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ISLAMABAD, Pakistan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A major U.S. aid package could be
withheld until Pakistan proves it does not possess a nuclear bomb,
news reports said Sunday.
   A Foreign Ministry spokesman said U.S. Ambassador Robert Oakley
``mentioned the nuclear program'' during discussions with senior
Pakistani officials last week, but disputed reports Oakley warned
the $573 million in military and economic aid could be stalled.
   ``Mr. Oakley mentioned the nuclear program and what effects it
could have on certification of aid,'' said the spokesman, who
cannot be identified under briefing rules. ``But the impression
given in newspaper reports that aid could be withheld or that the
U.S. administration may not provide the certificate is very
negative.''
   Since 1988, the United States has required Pakistan prove it
does not have a nuclear weapon before aid is authorized. Before
then, Pakistan was exempt from a U.S. law prohibiting aid to
countries that have not signed the nuclear non-proliferation
treaty.
   Pakistan has refused to cooperate with international inspection
procedures under the treaty until India signs the pact. The two
nations have had a series of border conflicts.
   Pakistan's major newspapers reported that Oakley warned senior
Pakistani officials that President Bush won't seek authorization of
the aid package until U.S. officials verify Pakistan's nuclear
capability.
   Pakistan, which receives its largest source of economic aid from
the United States, repeatedly denies any access to a nuclear
weapon, although it is widely believed that both Pakistan and India
are capable of building one.
   India exploded a nuclear device in the mid-1970s.
   Tensions between the two countries increased earlier this year
when India again cracked down on a Moslem secessionist movement in
its Jammu-Kashmir state, where more than 1,180 people have died in
fighting between militants and Indian security forces.
   Jammu-Kashmir is part of disputed territory partitioned in 1947
after the end of British colonial rule.
   Pakistan wants Kashmiris on both sides of the border to vote on
union either with Pakistan or India.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0061 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 1921EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-TeenMothers 2ndLd-Writethru a0731 09-23 0412</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Teen Mothers, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0731,450</SECOND>
<HEAD>Report: Government Spent $1.7 Billion More in 1989 on Families of
Teens</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: Subs 3rd graf, ``The figures xxx to include that organization
is privately funded</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By DEBORAH MESCE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The federal government spent more than $21.5
billion last year on welfare programs for families started by
teen-agers, according to a report released Sunday.
   The amount is $1.7 billion higher than for 1988 - partly because
of inflation and expansion of Medicaid benefits but also due to an
increase in births to teen-agers, said to the Center for Population
Options report.
   The figures illustrate the need for greater efforts to prevent
teen-age pregnancies - including sex education, family planning
counseling, support for delaying sexual activity, access to
contraception, and medical services, including abortion, said the
report by the privately funded organization that concentrates on
world wide population issues.
   ``We can no longer let our youth stumble into parenting, a
course that should be embarked on only when one is ready, willing
and able to become a parent,'' the report said.
   The costs of teen-age pregnancies go far beyond those of public
support, the report said.
   ``Too-early childbearing often impoverishes ... the lives of
girls brought too soon into the rigors and responsibilities of
motherhood, of boys bewildered and unable to parent and provide
adequately, of babies not planned or welcomed,'' the report said.
   ``It places a heavy burden on families and communities and
contributes to our country's unconscionably high rates of low
birthweight and neonatal mortality,'' it said.
   The most alarming increases in teen-age pregnancies are
occurring among 15 to 17 year olds, the report said.
   After a downward trend in births among this age group from 1970
into the mid 1980s, the rate began increasing. It jumped from 30.6
per 1,000 teen-agers in 1986 to 33.8 in 1988, according to the
National Center for Health Statistics.
   Teen-age pregnancies too often result in the mother cutting
short her education, which increases her chance of living in
poverty and needing public assistance, the report said.
   In estimating federal spending on families started by
teen-agers, the center included families currently headed by
teen-age mothers as well as those in which the mother is now 20
years or older but had her first child when she was a teen-ager.
   The cost includes the federal government's share for Aid for
Families with Dependent Children, Medicaid and Food Stamps received
by these families.
   The center also calculated the public cost for five states and
two cities for 1989, adding in the welfare expenditures of the
states, cities and towns.
   These were: Louisiana, $360 million; New Mexico, $80 million;
Oregon, $174 million; Vermont, $39 million; Wisconsin, $437
million; Baltimore, $246 million; and St. Louis, $81 million.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0062 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 1936EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Pakistan-Bhutto     09-23 0542</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Pakistan-Bhutto,0658</SECOND>
<HEAD>Court Orders Corruption Trial for Ousted Prime Minister</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MAHMOOD ZAMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LAHORE, Pakistan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A special court on Sunday ordered ousted
Prime Minister Benazir Bhutto to stand trial next month on charges
of corruption and misconduct during her 20 months in power.
   Justice Rashid Aziz Khan issued the notice to Bhutto, saying the
army-backed caretaker government had sufficient evidence to support
its claim. He ordered the civil proceedings to start Oct. 2.
   If convicted, Ms. Bhutto could be disqualified from the Oct. 24
election and barred from politics for up to seven years.
   Ms. Bhutto would have the right to appeal to the Lahore High
Court and then to the Supreme Court, a process that most likely
would not be completed before next month's ballot.
   Ms. Bhutto, 37, won election in November 1988 and took office a
month later as the first woman to lead a modern Moslem nation. She
now is a candidate for five seats in the 217-member National
Assembly, the law-making lower house of Parliament.
   Her aides say Ms. Bhutto ran for more than one post in case she
is disqualified from one seat.
   After learning of the judge's decision, Ms. Bhutto canceled
appointments and met behind the fortress-like walls of her seaside
home in Karachi, about 600 miles southwest of Lehore. Her aides
refused comment.
   Ms. Bhutto previously has called the charges ``a political
vendetta'' and said she would not appear before the special
one-judge tribunals.
   The tribunals were originally set up following the 1977 military
coup that toppled her father, the late Prime Minister Zulfikar Ali
Bhutto, and resurrected last month by the caretaker government made
up largely of her opponents and former allies.
   If she refuses to appear, legal experts say Ms. Bhutto could be
tried in absentia and held in contempt of court, possibly facing a
fine or arrest.
   President Ghulam Ishaq Khan, using his constitutional powers,
dismissed Ms. Bhutto's government Aug. 6 on charges of corruption,
nepotism, political incompetence and abuse of power. He alleged
that Ms. Bhutto's government used tens of millions of dollars in
special funds to buy votes and private business deals, charges that
the former prime minister and her government have denied.
   Four corruption charges - two in Lahore and two in Karachi -
have been filed against Ms. Bhutto before special tribunals. Only
one charge has been accepted; hearings are scheduled later this
week on the others.
   The charge accepted by Aziz Khan alleges Ms. Bhutto misused her
power by illegally approving the sale of 287 acres of federal land
to a London-based company operated by a cousin. The land, allegedly
sold at drastically reduced prices, was to be used for a luxury
hotel and resort outside the capital, Islamabad.
   After reviewing the evidence, the judge issued a notice ordering
Ms. Bhutto or her attorney to appear and show why she should not be
found guilty of misconduct.
   Shortly after replacing Ms. Bhutto, the caretaker government
began what it called a ``process of accountability'' to investigate
allegations of corruption not only against her former
administration but against many of her political opponents.
   The caretaker government has spent much of the past month trying
to portray Ms. Bhutto's administration as the most corrupt in
Pakistan's 43-year history. Despite allegations, the caretaker
government has yet to make public any proof.
   Most Pakistanis believe the scheme has backfired and evoked
memories of the same process that Ms. Bhutto's father endured
before he was hanged by the military government in 1979.
   Western diplomats have hinted that economic and military aid
worth hundreds of millions of dollars could be jeopardized if Ms.
Bhutto is victimized.
   Most analysts say Ms. Bhutto and her Pakistan People's Party
appear to be gaining strength and could emerge from next month's
election as the single largest party.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0063 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 1947EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-GreenpeaceProtest     09-23 0295</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Greenpeace Protest,0337</SECOND>
<HEAD>Greenpeace Activists Board Vessel, One Chained Self to Ship</HEAD>
<DATELINE>GOLD BEACH, Ore. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Greenpeace protester boarded a
research ship Sunday and chained herself to a tower on the boat
studying marine mining potential off the Oregon coast, authorities
said.
   The protester, a second person who boarded the 143-foot Aloha,
and 11 others were arrested by the Coast Guard. A 32-foot sea
urchin diving vessel and three inflatable boats were seized, Coast
Guard Lt. Doug Stephan said.
   Two Greenpeace activists from the flagship Rainbow Warrior
boarded the Aloha about noon, about 1 mile off the mouth of the
Rogue River, near Gold Beach in southern Oregon, Greenpeace
spokeswoman Carol Alexander said.
   Speaking by telephone from the Rainbow Warrior, Alexander said
that Diana Desnoyers, 30, chained herself to a tower on the Aloha,
about 15 feet above the deck. The Coast Guard cut Desnoyers loose
after about an hour, Stephan said.
   About two dozen local fishing vessels joined the 181-foot
Rainbow Warrior Sunday as part of the attempt to disrupt the
Aloha's mission, Alexander said.
   The arrests and boat seizures came because the vessels violated
a 500-yard, federally-ordered safety zone around the Aloha, Stephan
said, adding that those arrested were being held aboard the cutter
Orcas.
   One of the Greenpeace activists, Richard Leney, alleged he was
beaten by the crew of the Aloha after he and Desnoyers boarded the
vessel around noon.
   A doctor at Curry General hospital in Gold Beach said Leney
suffered minor bruises. He was treated and released. Stephan said
the Coast Guard would investigate allegations that Leney was
assaulted.
   The Aloha was in the fourth day of a two-week voyage to gather
data on the potential of mining the sea bed just off the coast.
   Many local fishermen fear the Aloha's work will lead to mining
that could destroy fisheries. Greenpeace opposes all marine mining.
   ``Our coastal waters are already extremely stressed by many
different marine activities,'' Alexander said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0064 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 2008EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-FamilyReunion     09-23 0212</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Family Reunion,0232</SECOND>
<HEAD>Thousands Turn Out to Celebrate at `Black Family Reunion'</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MEMPHIS, Tenn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Thousands turned out for this city's first
Black Family Reunion, highlighted by the appearance of Alex Haley
whose book ``Roots'' celebrated his own family's history from
Africa to America.
   ``This is a marvelous, exceptional day and it has exceeded all
our expectations,'' Dr. Dorothy I. Height, president of the
National Council of Negro Women, said of the reunion's Saturday
festival in Overton Park. Organizers estimated 30,000 to 50,000
people attended.
   ``We've heard so much about what's wrong with black youth and
the black family that the entire community welcomes a chance to be
involved in something positive like this,'' she added.
   The celebration started Friday with a prayer breakfast and ended
Sunday with services at area churches. But the highlight was
Saturday's festival in Overton Park.
   Vendors selling everything from T-shirts to African jewelry and
West Indian food mingled among tents featuring education and health
seminars.
   ``This reunion celebration feels to me like a great big church
supper,'' said Haley who reminisced about growing up in the area.
   ``We don't know each other as well here as we might have in
smaller communities, but the more occasions we have like this, the
more all of us - no matter what our race - will be strengthened,''
he said.

</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0065 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 2034EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-GulfRdp 3rdLd-Writethru a0734 09-23 0890</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf Rdp, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0734,P018</SECOND>
<HEAD>Iraq Threatens Oil Fields, Israel; U.S. Flight Heads Home</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 18th graf, `Meanwhile, a...' to UPDATE with plane landing
in N.C.; picks up 19th pvs, `At the ...</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos DHA1,2,4, NY9,10, AMM2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LAURA KING</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Iraq on Sunday threatened to destroy Middle East oil fields and
attack Israel if other nations tried to force it from Kuwait.
   At the same time, Iraq apparently sought to improve relations
with France, admitting that its soldiers had raided the French
ambassador's residence in Kuwait 10 days ago. It apologized for the
incursion, which sparked a wave of retaliatory expulsions and
increased tensions between Iraq and European nations.
   Iraq also said it would not attend the U.N. General Assembly
session that opens Monday because its delegation was not being
allowed to travel to New York on Iraqi Airways. The airline has no
landing rights because of the U.N. trade embargo.
   Foreign women and children wrenched from their husbands and
fathers flew home on the last U.S.-chartered flight from Baghdad.
   In Washington, top finance officials from the world's wealthiest
nations met for a second day, seeking to forge a united front
against threats to the global economy stemming from the gulf
crisis. They met with mixed success.
   In warning other nations not to try to force it to give up
Kuwait, Iraq said: ``We will never allow anybody, whomever he may
be, to strangle the people of Iraq without having himself
strangled.''
   ``The oil areas in Saudi Arabia and in other states of the
region, all the oil installations, will be rendered incapable ...
and Israel will be transformed into something different from what
they are now,'' said an Iraqi government statement broadcast by
state-run Radio Baghdad and monitored in Nicosia, Cyprus.
   ``America must realize clearly that it is pushing the entire
region ... in fact, even the whole world ... to the brink of a
bottomless abyss, from which the region will never see light for
dozens of years,'' said the statement, translated from Arabic by
The Associated Press.
   Iraq's decision to stay away from the General Assembly session
was reported by the official Iraqi News Agency. It said Foreign
Minister Tariq Aziz told U.N. Secretary-General Javier Perez de
Cuellar that Iraq's delegation would not come to New York unless
restrictions on Iraqi Airways, its flag carrier, were lifted.
   A State Department official said the matter was still under
consideration.
   In any event, Iraq was hardly likely to get a warm welcome at
the United Nations. The Security Council was to meet Tuesday and
consider tightening the trade embargo against Baghdad with an air
blockade. Baghdad also was expected to come in for widespread
condemnation in General Assembly debate.
   Among the first scheduled to speak was French President Francois
Mitterrand, who dispatched troops to the gulf after Iraqi soldiers
violated French and other diplomatic compounds in Kuwait earlier
this month.
   The Iraqi Foreign Ministry Sunday apologized for the Sept. 14
raid. It said its soldiers had not realized they were entering the
French ambassador's residence because the house was outside the
diplomatic quarter of Kuwait City.
   ``The Foreign Ministry apologizes for the previous statement in
which the incident was described differently,'' an unidentified
ministry spokesman was quoted as saying. Iraq previously had denied
the raid took place.
   The first units of a French rapid deployment force arrived in
the gulf region Sunday, joining tens of thousands of U.S. troops
deployed in the Saudi Arabian desert.
   Secretary of State James A. Baker III said that despite the huge
deployment, the United States was still seeking non-military means
of forcing Iraq out of Kuwait.
   Baker, interviewed Sunday on NBC-TV's ``Meet the Press,'' was
asked about the possibility of war. ``We have said many times we
hoped there won't be,'' he replied, but added that President Bush
was not ruling out any options.
   Meanwhile, a charter flight carrying 112 evacuees from Iraq and
Kuwait landed in Raleigh, N.C., Sunday from London. The passengers
had left Baghdad a day earlier aboard what the State Department
said was the last U.S.-chartered airlift planned from Iraq.
   At the London stopover, the exhausted evacuees told of hardship
and terror in Kuwait and Iraq. Western women and children have been
allowed to leave, but the Baghdad government has kept foreign men
captive to serve as human shields at strategic sites.
   Jacqui Jones, a Scot, said she was forced to leave her
terminally ill husband behind. ``I didn't know I had so many
tears,'' she told reporters.
   Twenty-eight of the 140 passengers on Saturday's flight remained
in London. Sunday was the second day of talks in Washington among
wealthy industrialized nations, held as part of the annual meetings
of the International Monetary Fund and the World Bank.
Repercussions of the gulf crisis took center stage.
   The United States is leading a bid to channel billions of
dollars to the so-called front-line states of Turkey, Egypt and
Jordan, and other countries whose economies have been hit by the
trade embargo against Iraq and the steep rise in oil prices.
   Although broad outlines of the plan were agreed upon, British
Chancellor of the Exchequer John Major told reporters that specific
amounts of assistance and which countries should be helped had not
yet been worked out.
   In other gulf-related developments Sunday:
   - Two radical Iranian newspapers criticized an effort by Syrian
President Hafez Assad to persuade Iran not to violate the trade
embargo against Iraq. Assad, Iran's key Arab ally and an arch-rival
of Iraq's Saddam Hussein, met behind closed doors with President
Hashemi Rafsanjani Saturday.
   The Syrian leader, who held talks with Baker earlier this month,
is seen as having some leverage with Tehran because of Syria's
support for Iran during its eight-year war with Iraq.
   Iran has criticized Iraq's invasion of Kuwait. But it has also
deplored the deployment of foreign forces in the region, and hinted
it might circumvent the embargo for ``humanitarian'' reasons.
   - President Turgut Ozal of Turkey flew to the United States for
talks with President Bush and other officials on the gulf crisis.
He is expected to press for economic and military aid to offset
Turkey's heavy losses from the embargo.
   - Although the gulf crisis showed no signs of cooling off,
temperatures in the Saudi desert were abating slightly. The highs
in recent days have ranged in the mid-90s, compared to routine
readings of up to 120 degrees in August when the U.S. deployment
began.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0066 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 2045EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-TaxProtest     09-23 0331</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Tax Protest,0386</SECOND>
<HEAD>Thousands in New Jersey Protest $2.8 Billion Tax Hike Package</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By FRED PIERETTI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TRENTON, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Thousands of New Jersey taxpayers gathered
at the Statehouse on Sunday to protest $2.8 billion in tax hikes.
   Protesters focused their anger on Gov. Jim Florio - hanging his
likeness in effigy, hawking $2 posters of Florio disguised as Adolf
Hitler and singing anti-Florio songs.
   The event was organized by Hands Across New Jersey, the group
leading a statewide tax revolt.
   ``We need accountability in government and criminal prosecution
for those who rip us off,'' said John Budzash, a Howell mailman and
Hands Across New Jersey co-founder. ``Do we have efficient spending
in government? No.''
   State Police Sgt. Peter Hinkle said that the 4{ hour rally
peaked at about 4,000 people. Budzash disputed the police estimate,
saying at least 10,000 attended the event. A similar rally in July
drew about 6,000.
   The $2.8 billion tax hike, the largest in state history, was
passed by the Democrat-controlled Legislature less than seven
months after Florio took office. The governor is a Democrat.
   ``Politicians will not budge until you make yourself heard,''
said Ken Chiampou, a talk show host on WKXW-FM, a Trenton-area
radio station which publicized the anti-tax movement. ``This is
about getting politicians to respond to the people.''
   The $2.8 billion tax package is designed to close a budget gap
of more than $1 billion, provide $1.1 billion in new state aid to
public schools and ease some property taxes. The state's income tax
will be increased for those in the top 17 percent of the tax
bracket.
   Florio also raised the state's sales tax from 6 percent to 7
percent. The sales tax also was expanded to include some previously
exempt items such as alcohol, cigarettes, telephone bills, soap and
disposable paper products.
   Budzash said his group is seeking four goals: the repeal of the
tax increases, the right to recall the governor and legislators,
the right to use initiative and referendum to make laws, and a more
efficient state government.
   Florio declined an invitation to attend the rally, instead
speaking to supporters at Trenton State College. Florio spokesman
Jon Shure said the governor ``remained convinced that what he did
was right.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0067 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 2101EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Switzerland-Nuclear     09-23 0360</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Switzerland-Nuclear,0409</SECOND>
<HEAD>Swiss Vote Against Closing Nuke Plants</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BERN, Switzerland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Swiss, in a referendum held against
the backdrop of the gulf crisis and rising oil prices, voted Sunday
against a proposal to close the country's five nuclear power
plants.
   While narrowly rejecting the Socialist-backed plan to
decommission the plants over the next 30 to 40 years, voters
approved a related constitutional amendment to bar the construction
of new plants for the next 10 years.
   The official results showed 52.9 percent of the voters opposed
the total shutdown, while 54.6 percent approved the draft amendment
barring licensing of new reactors until the year 2000.
   Seventy-one percent approved a third proposal that gives the
federal government greater power to enact energy saving measures.
   The Socialist Party hailed the vote as a ``turning point'' in
the country's energy policy. It blamed the narrow rejection of the
shutdown proposal on an expensive publicity campaign by the utility
industry.
   The conservative government, which had opposed both measures,
also said it was satisfied with the results. It said they showed
the Swiss weren't ready to renounce nuclear power yet.
   About 40 percent of the eligible voters turned out.
   The ten-year moratorium codified the status quo. Local
opposition to two major projects has effectively stopped them. The
last nuclear plant went on line in 1984.
   Protests since 1975 in the Basel region frustrated construction
of a plant at Kaiseraugst, on the Rhine. Last month, another group
of companies announced it was halting a project at Graben, near
Bern, and planned to sue the federal government to recover $230
million.
   The five operating plants provide 40 percent of Switzerland's
electrical power. Hydroelectric dams provide the rest.
   Environmental activists, noting that Switzerland is a net
exporter of electricity, say increased energy efficiency and
alternative energies would permit a nuclear shutdown.
   In opposing the measures, Transport and Energy Minister Adolf
Ogi said the Persian Gulf crisis showed the dangers posed by
dependency on energy imports.
   It was the third time since 1979 that anti-nuclear groups had
forced a referendum on atomic power. Under the Swiss system of
direct democracy, any proposal backed by more than 100,00
signatures must be put to a vote.
   The move seeking a nuclear shutdown was launched shortly after
the 1986 Chernobyl disaster. The government says strict safety
measures rule out a similar accident at Swiss plants.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0068 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 2127EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brite-BalloonWedding 1stLd-Writethru   09-23 0139</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brite-Balloon Wedding, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0692,0139</SECOND>
<HEAD>Couple Wedding In Balloon Ditches In Tree</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 2nd graf to ADD time element.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>STATELINE, Nev. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   It was not the marriage made in heaven
that they had envisioned, but newlyweds Kenneth and Stephanie
Miller were in good spirits after the hot-air balloon they
exchanged their vows in crashed into a tree.
   The balloon, with six people aboard, was launched Saturday at
Gardnerville, Nev., 15 miles east of Lake Tahoe. But an unexpected
easterly breeze caught it and sent it west as the Rev. Miriam Lee
tied the knot at 10,000 feet.
   The balloon deflated after it struck a tree on Kingsbury Grade,
near Lake Tahoe. The basket fell slowly to the ground, and no one
was hurt.
   ``We do specialty weddings but we don't guarantee such exciting
landings,'' Lee said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0069 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 2135EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-MormonPresident     09-23 0155</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mormon President,0141</SECOND>
<HEAD>91-Year-Old Mormon President Critical After Emergency Surgery</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SALT LAKE CITY (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Ninety-one-year-old Mormon Church
president Ezra Taft Benson was in critical condition Sunday after
emergency brain surgery.
   Benson underwent a similar operation Wednesday, when two blood
clots were removed from his brain. Sunday's surgery was also to
drain blood clots, said church spokesman Don LeFevre.
   An LDS Hospital nursing supervisor, who declined to give her
name, said Benson was in the hospital's intensive care unit after
the 2{-hour operation.
   Benson was hospitalized Tuesday after complaining of severe
headaches and difficulty swallowing. Benson had been showing
improvement after the operation last week; his condition was
upgraded from serious to fair Saturday.
   Benson, the former secretary of agriculture under former
President Eisenhower, assumed presidency of the Church of Jesus
Christ of Latter-day Saints in 1985.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0070 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 2146EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-Iran-Fighters     09-23 0437</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Iran-Fighters,0513</SECOND>
<HEAD>Iran Buying Sophisticated Soviet Fighter Jets</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf Rdp, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ANWAR FARUQI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NICOSIA, Cyprus (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Iran bought at least 14 advanced Soviet
fighter jets in a deal signed by President Hashemi Rafsanjani in
Moscow last June, Iranian sources said Sunday.
   One of the MiG-29 supersonic jets was shown on Iranian
television Sunday. One source in Tehran said the planes were part
of a $6 billion package Rafsanjani signed with the Soviets that is
said to include tanks and other heavy weaponry.
   The deal emphasizes the degree to which the Soviet Union has
shifted away from Iraq, its longtime ally in the gulf region.
   The acquisition of the supersonic fighters is a big boost for
Iran's badly depleted air force. Iraq, Iran's foe in the 1980-88
war, has 30 of the advanced MiG-29s.
   ``The Kremlin has never sold the MiGs to any government except
those whose ties with Moscow were more than excellent,'' The Tehran
Times, which is close to Rafsanjani, noted in an editorial. ``As
such, the Soviets' agreement to sell Iran the advanced fighters has
a great deal of significance for regional political circles.''
   ``Iran's military purchases will not be limited to this newly
acquired batch of fighters. Moscow has announced its agreement to
sell more arms to the Islamic republic,'' the newspaper said.
   The source, speaking on condition of anonymity, said in a
telephone interview that Tehran bought the fighters on condition
they were delivered ``fully equipped,'' with sophisticated
electronics not made available to other Soviet clients such as
Iraq.
   The fighters were fitted with lookdown-shootdown radar, which
provides all-weather operating capability against low-flying
targets, the source said.
   The Mig-29s, which the Soviets have been using since 1985 and
which are comparable to the U.S.-made F-16, also came equipped with
infra-red search-and-track sensors, the source said.
   Iran's state-tun television network, monitored in Nicosia,
Saturday showed a MiG-29 fighter with Iranian air force markings
wheeled out of a hangar for take-off.
   The source said Iranian pilots were sent to the Soviet Union for
MiG-29 training soon after Rafsanjani signed the deal in Moscow.
   Iran has been rebuilding its armed forces since the August 1988
cease-fire in the gulf war. Mansour Sattari, Iran's air force
commander, said in June that Iran would equip its air force with
``the world's most sophisticated military weapons.''
   The Iranian air force, a powerful force supplied with
sophisticated U.S.-made jets under the late shah, quickly fell
apart during the gulf war for lack of spare parts. It now consists
of fewer than 50 planes, some without radar.
   The Tehran Times said other European countries have ``informed
Tehran of their preparedness to meet Iran's military needs and it
is said that Iran is considering these offers as well.''
   China has offered weapons at ``good prices. ... But Tehran seems
to opt for sophisticated and advanced weaponry, for its air force
in particular,'' it said.
   Western military sources say Iran spends $6 billion a year on
defense.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0071 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 2209EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-Americans 3rdLd-Writethru a0743 09-23 0574</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Americans, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0743,0728</SECOND>
<HEAD>Charter Flight With Evacuees Lands in United States</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 3rd graf pvs with 8 grafs to ADD refugee quotes; EDITS
to
conform; SUBS 10th graf to CORRECT that not all nationalities
identified involve only adults. Picks up 11th graf pvs, `Twenty
passengers...'</NOTE>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf Rdp, Bjt</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto RA1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By HUNTER T. GEORGE II</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MORRISVILLE, N.C. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Evacuees fleeing occupied Kuwait waved
American flags to celebrate their freedom when they arrived in the
United States on Sunday.
   A DC-10 with 111 evacuees aboard arrived at Raleigh-Durham
International Airport shortly after 6 p.m. No further
U.S.-chartered evacuation flights are scheduled, officials said.
   Khalid Abdu, wearing a Canada sweatshirt, stabbed the air with a
U.S. flag as soon as he appeared in the jet doorway.
   Abdu, 28, who became a U.S. citizen four months ago, said there
were ``lots of disturbances, lots of looting. Things are being
dismantled in Kuwait.''
   ``The Iraqis are responsible for what has happened to Kuwait.
The U.S. is responsible for what will happen in Kuwait,'' Abdu
said.
   Abdu said bloodshed could be avoided through negotiation, but he
wasn't overly optimistic.
   ``If Iraq and Iran could do it, we could do it, too,'' he said.
``From my own point of view, it will get worse. The Iraqis will not
back up from Kuwait.''
   Abdu was born in what is now the Israeli-occupied Gaza Strip. He
graduated from the University of Wisconsin at Milwaukee and worked
in a heavy equipment business with his father, who stayed in
Kuwait. He also left his mother, two sisters and brother behind.
   He said he would stay in North Carolina and find work as a taxi
driver.
   The World Airways plane took off from London's Heathrow Airport
with 111 refugees and a State Department doctor, said Joe Myers,
director of the North Carolina Emergency Management Division.
   The refugees were among 140 evacuees from Kuwait and Iraq who
arrived at London's Gatwick Airport on Saturday night from Baghdad.
The rest remained in Britain.
   A diabetic woman was the first to eave the airplane in North
Carolina, walking slowly with a small U.S. flag clutched in one
hand.
   ``She was in pain but she insisted on walking off. You could see
she had a lot of pride,'' Myers said. ``These people seemed very
relieved to be here. You could see it on their faces. The first
thing I saw was a small child waving an American flag.''
   The evacuees included 76 adults, 20 children over age 2 and 15
infants, Myers said. Among the refugees were 41 Americans, 43
Jordanians, seven Palestinians, four Iraqis and two Kuwaitis.
   Twenty passengers planned to fly on to California and 11 each to
Texas and Michigan, Myers said.
   Like other freedom flights, the refugees traveled overland from
Kuwait to Baghdad, where they boarded a chartered jet.
   Iraqi President Saddam Hussein has allowed some women and
children to leave but he has kept foreign men behind to serve as
human shields at strategic sites.
   About 2,500 Americans have fled Iraq and Kuwait since the Aug. 2
Iraqi invasion. Evacuation flights have brought about 2,000 people
- mostly women and children - back to the United States. Others
fled by overland desert routes.
   When the plane arrived at Gatwick Airport on Saturday night, one
American man who would not give his name said of Kuwait: ``It is
really trashy out there at the moment.''
   Joanna Copley, who is helping run the Gulf Support Group for
Britons trapped by the Iraqi invasion, said that ``This flight was
different from the others. People were less distressed but more
desperate.
   ``I think a lot of them didn't want to come out but came because
there was nothing else to do. It seems food and water is becoming a
problem for people still in Kuwait; the soldiers are doing a lot of
systematic rounding up now and there is a fair amount of shooting
going on,'' she said.
   Jacqui Jones, a Briton who was forced to leave her
terminally-ill husband in Iraq, called on the government to act to
get sick Britons out of Iraq.
   ``The American Consulate have taken their terminally ill out, so
have the Italians, why can't we do something?''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0072 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 2231EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Israel-Uprising 1stLd-Writethru a704 09-23 0599</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel-Uprising, 1st Ld - Writethru, a704,0723</SECOND>
<HEAD>Israelis Debate Response to Soldier's Killing</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: UPDATES throughout with new remarks by ministers, Arab man
hospitalized, 264th collaborator killed; no pickup</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By GWEN ACKERMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Israeli Cabinet ministers recommended Sunday
that Israelis be allowed to shoot more freely at Arab rock-throwers
and retaliate forcefully for the death of a reservist stoned and
burned in his car by Palestinians.
   For the fourth day, the army clamped a curfew on the El Bureij
refugee camp in the occupied Gaza Strip, where Capt. Amnon Pomeranz
was slain Thursday.
   Vengeful Jews stoned cars of Arab laborers leaving for work in
Israel Sunday morning, forcing many to turn back, Israel radio
said. A 47-year-old Gaza man was hospitalized with head wounds,
Arab reports said.
   ``This is a murder that cannot be ignored or regarded as
statistics,'' said the right-wing agriculture minister, Rafael
Eitan.
   ``The punishment they deserve is ... that today, tonight, we
need to go in there, grab 200 local youths and deport them to
Lebanon,'' he said in an interview.
   ``No stone should be left standing around the gutted car; the
residents should be prevented from going to work or traveling on
the roads until they decide if they want war or not. If they do,
they will get it,'' said Eitan, a former army chief of staff.
   Health Minister Ehud Olmert said on Israel radio and television
that any civilian or soldier surrounded by Palestinians ``must feel
he can use his gun and kill those who want to kill him, plain and
simple.''
   The comments reflected the shock felt in Israel over the
killing, which came at a time when many believed the 34-month-old
Palestinian uprising in the occupied lands was waning.
   The Palestine Liberation Organization on Sunday called for the
escalation of the uprising in the West Bank and Gaza Strip to
confront ``a new Israeli plan to step up the use of fire and gas
bombs.''
   Bassam Abu Sharif, one of PLO Chairman Yasser Arafat's senior
advisers, said Israeli repression had increased and Palestinians
had the ``to resist the Israeli occupation forces with all means as
described by the U.N. Charter.'
   In his telex from PLO headquarters in Tunis, Tunisia, Abu Sharif
did not say what intensified resistance would entail.
   A senior Israeli military official, who briefed reporters on
condition of anonymity, indicated soldiers would destroy the homes
of suspects in the attack on Pomeranz. Several dozen suspects had
been detained, he said.
   The radio said 100 Palestinians in the camp believed their homes
were slated for wrecking. The army has often destroyed Arab homes
as punishment for killing Israelis.
   Israeli military officials have said Pomeranz mistakenly drove
into the El Bureij refugee camp, and Palestinians stoned his
vehicle. His car collided with a donkey cart, injuring two youths
on the cart. The Palestinians continued to stone the vehicle and
then set it on fire, the officials said.
   Pomeranz was the 48th Israeli to die in the intefadeh, or
uprising, which began in December 1987.
   Israeli soldiers and civilians have killed 730 Palestinians, and
264 have been killed by fellow Arabs as suspected collaborators.
The body of a 25-year-old Palestinian killed as a collaborator was
found Sunday.
   At its weekly meeting Sunday, the Cabinet was briefed on
Pomeranz's slaying by Defense Minister Moshe Arens and the military
chief of staff, Lt. Gen. Dan Shomron. It announced no decisions.
   Parliament, which is in recess until October, is to hold a
special session Wednesday to debate the killing.
   Defense Ministry spokesman Dan Naveh said the attack was
unprecedented in that everyone present took part, and no one tried
to protect the soldier.
   Efraim Sneh, a former senior occupation official, was among
those counseling against sweeping retaliation.
   Sneh said authorities should concentrate on finding and
punishing those directly responsible, and warned that harsh,
sweeping measures would play into the hands of Israel's enemies.
   ``Instead of Saddam Hussein being the center of attention, we
will allow the hostile forces to focus the attention on us,'' Sneh
told Israel army radio.
   Many hard-liners supported Eitan's call for collective
punishment. Others called for imposing the death penalty and giving
soldiers greater freedom to open fire.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900923-0073 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-23-90 2239EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Bulgaria     09-23 0261</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bulgaria,0290</SECOND>
<HEAD>Protesters Shout for Food Outside Socialist Congress</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROLAND PRINZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SOFIA, Bulgaria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Reformers and conservatives battled
Sunday over the future of the governing Socialist Party while
protesters outside the hall where they met shouted for food instead
of rationing.
   The delegates to the congress spoke of dire shortages in coming
months if needed economic reforms aren't made.
   ``There will be no diesel, no coal. ... There will not even be
enough bread in several months,'' said party reformer Petar Emil
Mitev.
   Vital foodstuffs such as sugar, cooking oil and cheese are
rationed and electric power has been cut periodically since early
this month.
   While about 300 people demonstrated outside, reformers inside
attacked chairman Alexander Lilov and other Socialist leaders for
delaying political change and alienating the younger generation.
   The party was meeting in its downtown headquaters, which was
damaged by arson and looting last month. It was the first congress
of the party - renamed from the Communist Party last year - since
it won June elections to gain control of 211 of the 400 seats in
Parliament.
   After a separate meeting with leaders of the country, Bulgarian
President Zhelyu Zhelev issued a statement asking for the
maintenance of law and order while he and two other leading
officials are out of the country.
   Political groups should abstain from rallies and workers should
hold a moratorium on strikes, the statement said. It asked police
to take ``all precautions to pre-empt anti-constitutional and
illegal actions.''
   Zhelev was to depart Monday for a visit to the United States.
Premier Andrei Lukanov and Parliament speaker Nikolai Todorov also
are to be out of the country this week.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
</Collection>
