<Collection>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900128-0001 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-28-90 2327EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Muslims-Police 1stLd-Writethru a0659 01-28 0750</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Muslims-Police, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0659,0768</SECOND>
<HEAD>Clashes Between Police and Muslims Lead to Peace Talks</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 10 grafs to CORRECT in 3rd graf that date of
struggle was Jan. 23, sted Jan. 20, location to five miles away,
sted a few blocks; DELETE redundant first reference to Farrakhan in
11th graf; RECAST lead to delete description of South Side as
impoverished. Pickup 12th graf: The Muslims'...</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By RICHARD DE ATLEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Bloody clashes between Muslims and police
that reignited decades-old tensions on the South Side also have
prompted unprecedented meetings between police and leaders of the
predominantly black religious sect.
   A street fight with police Jan. 3 injured three Muslims, who
were treated in a jail hospital, and four officers, including one
who suffered a broken arm. Two Muslims were booked for
investigation of assault.
   Then on Jan. 23, about five miles from the first melee, Oliver
Rodell Beasley, a 27-year-old Muslim, was fatally shot during a
struggle with sheriff's deputies. Officers arrested six men and a
juvenile, but only one man was charged.
   An autopsy report released Friday said Beasley died of a gunshot
wound to the head and was grazed on his hip. Authorities said they
believe Beasley was shot in the hip while struggling for control of
the deputy's gun.
   The sheriff's department said its deputies were ``fighting for
their lives'' with a group of young men, mostly Muslims, and the
shooting started after Beasley disarmed one of the deputies.
   In one of the few comments offered by Nation of Islam officials
on the killing, Khallid Muhammad, an aide in Chicago to Muslim
leader Louis Farrakhan, said the fight began when deputies beat
another man for refusing to kneel on the ground.
   Police and the sheriff's office would not comment on the cause
of the incident pending results of their separate investigations.
The Nation of Islam said it will issue its own report.
   Muslims long have claimed that police routinely order blacks to
kneel or lie on the ground during traffic stops _ and rarely do the
same to white drivers. Police have denied following such a policy.
   ``We have a prayer position in which we go down on our knees and
touch our foreheads to the floor,'' Muhammad said. ``We don't bow
down to anyone except Allah.''
   The Nation of Islam, which uses Koran and Bible scripture, began
in the 1930s as a black nationalist movement. Though popularly
known as Black Muslims, its followers prefer to call themselves
Muslims. Most live in the United States, about 5,000 in the Los
Angeles area.
   The group has been criticized for anti-Semitic statements
attributed to Farrakhan, but locally Muslims have gained stature
with black community groups that once shunned them.
   The Muslims' focus on family values and self-sufficiency has
taken precedence over their sect's more controversial policies,
such as advocacy of a separate black nation.
   ``They are an integral part of the black community,'' said Danny
Bakewell, director of Brotherhood Crusade, a South Side community
group. ``They bring dignity and respect to the community and take
men off drugs.''
   Both of this month's clashes with police began with a traffic
arrest that drew a crowd _ situations that strike a nerve in Los
Angeles, where a traffic stop in the mostly black Watts section
sparked the August 1965 riots that killed 34 people.
   Tensions between Muslims and police were not directly
responsible for that bloody rampage, but they did contribute.
   Four meetings between authorities and Muslim leaders have not
resolved the issues, but show a willingness to communicate that was
unthinkable when police-Muslim tensions flared in the 1960s.
   In April 1962, a bloody riot started outside the sect's old Los
Angeles mosque after police stopped a Muslim on the street. One man
died in police gunfire and 11 members of the sect later were
convicted on various charges.
   In the closing days of the Watts riots, police fired 500 rounds
at the mosque during an early-morning raid prompted by a tip that
weapons were being stored there. No weapons were found.
   Two years later, the mosque again was raided because of an arms
cache tip. Again no weapons or explosives were found, and
then-Mayor Sam Yorty apologized.
   ``That is history we can't change,'' said Deputy Police Chief
William Rathburn. ``But we learned from it. We can alter what
happens in the future.''
   Telephone calls to the sect's Chicago headquarters for further
comment on the deaths and the meetings were not returned.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900128-0002 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-28-90 2335EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Germany-Election 1stLd-Writethru a0749 01-28 0383</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Germany-Election, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0749,0395</SECOND>
<HEAD>Social Democrats Win State Victory</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: ADDS 3 grafs at end with share of vote received by Greens and
rightist Republicans; no pickup.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>SAARBRUECKEN, West Germany (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Social Democrats scored a
convincing victory in Saarland state elections Sunday, the latest
in a series of regional setbacks for Chancellor Helmut Kohl's
governing Christian Democrats.
   Politicians said the vote increases Gov. Oskar Lafontaine's
chances as a challenger to Kohl in December's federal elections.
   The Social Democrats, the main national opposition party,
expanded their majority in the state Parliament by polling 54.4
percent of the vote to 33.4 percent for Kohl's conservative party.
   Support for the leftist party was up from the 49.2 percent it
polled in 1985.
   The centrist Free Democrats, who are junior partners in the Bonn
governing coalition, received only 5.6 percent of the vote,
compared to 10 percent in the 1985 elections.
   It was the first local test of Kohl's popularity since his image
was boosted by East Germany's opening of its border and other
recent pro-democracy moves. His party had suffered losses in
several statewide races last year.
   About 83 percent of Saarland's 840,000 eligible voters cast
ballots.
   According to preliminary official results, the Social Democrats
won 30 of the parliament's 51 seats, a gain of four. The Christian
Democrats won 18, down two, while the Free Democrats were expected
to drop from five to three seats.
   Lafontaine, 46, said he was surprised by the extent of the
victory but refused to comment on a possible national candidacy.
   ``The other questions come later,'' he told the ZDF television
network.
   Horst Rehberger, regional chairman of the Free Democrats, said
the Saarland contest was ``a popular referendum on a chancellor
candidacy by Lafontaine. The vote was unequivocal.''
   Lafontaine already has the blessing of party chairman
Hans-Jochen Vogel to take on Kohl in December.
   The environmentalist Greens party polled 2.7 percent of the
Saarland vote, short of the 5 percent needed to enter the regional
parliament.
   The ultra-rightist Republicans, making their debut in Saarland,
received 3.3 percent of the vote.
   Party leader Heinz Schoenhuber, a former Nazi SS soldier, denied
that the showing signaled a decline in support for his party, which
stunned the nation last year by gaining seats in West Berlin and
other local elections.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900128-0003 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-28-90 2349EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-JetlinerCrash 4thLd-Writethru a0748 01-28 1236</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Jetliner Crash, 4th Ld-Writethru, a0748,1269</SECOND>
<HEAD>Local Controllers Weren't Told Plane Was Low On Fuel</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: INSERTS 3 grafs after 16th graf pvs, `The pilot...he said',
to ADD source saying some pilots reluctant to declare fuel
emergency, ADD locations of control centers. Pick up 17th graf pvs:
`A federal...</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By LISA GENASCI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>COVE NECK, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The crew of Avianca Flight 52 told
high-altitude air traffic controllers the plane was low on fuel and
needed a priority landing before it crashed, but that information
wasn't relayed to local controllers, officials said Sunday.
   The Boeing 707 crashed on Long Island Thursday night, killing 73
people and injuring 85.
   The pilot of the Colombian jetliner told controllers at New York
Center, who handle high-altitude traffic, that he was low on fuel
50 minutes before the plane crashed, said Lee Dickinson, a member
of the National Transportation Safety Board.
   When the New York Center controllers turned over control of the
flight to local controllers handling approaches to John F. Kennedy
International Airport, they apparently failed to mention the plane
was low on fuel, Dickinson said.
   The conversation between the crew and New York Center came after
the aircraft had been in a holding pattern for 46 minutes,
Dickinson said. At that point, controllers asked the pilot if the
Boeing could safely land at Boston's Logan Airport. The pilot said
he lacked fuel to get to Logan, said Dickinson.
   Shortly afterward, control of the aircraft was transferred to
local controllers _ Terminal Radar Approach Control, or TRACON _
who told investigators Sunday they never knew the plane was low on
fuel.
   One local controller learned about the fuel shortage, but only
after the plane had to abort an attempted landing, he said. After
that attempt the pilot twice told the local controllers he was
running out of fuel, Dickinson said.
   The latest information was discovered after investigators spoke
to six local controllers who either handled the aircraft or were
keeping track of it, he said.
   ``For whatever reasons, we don't know, the controllers at TRACON
did not know that,'' said Dickinson, referring to the fuel shortage.
   He said investigators on Monday will question at least four New
York Center controllers to determine if the information was relayed.
   Asked if there are rules requiring that fuel shortage
information be passed along among controllers, he said, ``There has
to be a handoff or an agreement ... one would expect that
information going to the center, that that information would be
passed on.''
   He said the controllers at TRACON and New York Center were
speaking to each other by telephone when control was handed off.
   Fuel receipts obtained by investigators indicate the aircraft
had 81,000 pounds of fuel on board, more than enough for a normal
flight from Medellin, Colombia, to New York. The flight originated
in Bogota, Colombia, with a stop in Medellin.
   The plane was delayed because of weather-related congestion
three times en route _ for 16 minutes over Norfolk, Va., for 27
minutes between Norfolk and New York, and for 46 minutes about 40
miles south of JFK.
   The crash, in an affluent Long Island community, occurred as the
plane circled back for a second landing attempt after an initial
approach was aborted because it was too steep, the NTSB said.
   The pilot told the high-altitude controllers at New York Center
he needed a priority landing, Dickinson said. But the word
``emergency'' was never used and for that reason perhaps the
severity of the situation wasn't relayed, he said.
   Both control centers are on Long Island, as is the airport.
TRACON, the local control center, is in Garden City, about 10 miles
from Kennedy Airport, and the New York Center is in Ronkonkoma,
about 50 miles from the airport.
   A source close to the investigation, who spoke on condition of
anonymity, said that many pilots are reluctant to declare a fuel
emergency because the Federal Aviation Administration strictly
monitors those cases.
   Should the FAA determine a pilot was unjustified in declaring an
emergency, he can lose his pilot's license.
   A federal official close to the investigation who spoke on
condition of anonymity said the information indicates the error
appears to lie with New York Center.
   Controllers told investigators that the night of the crash was
hectic at TRACON, Dickinson said.
   ``It was a night of intense energy, the weather was bad and
there was a shortage of controllers,'' Dickinson said. He couldn't
explain why or by how much TRACON was understaffed.
   He noted that an American Airlines flight that landed right
before Avianca's aborted attempt had just 14 minutes of fuel when
it landed.
   NTSB investigators Sunday again studied the jet's four engines
and fuel pumps.
   ``What they found was indicative of no fuel in the tanks,''
Dickinson said.
   Investigators earlier said the plane may have had up to 10,000
pounds of fuel upon impact, which would have left the Boeing with
only several minutes of flying time. However, they said Sunday that
figure could be wrong because they were unsure about the integrity
of fuel gauges they've examined.
   For example, a gauge that keeps track of all fuel on board
indicates the plane had between 1,100 pounds to 1,200 pounds of
fuel. Two other gauges for individuals fuel tanks, however, show
that those tanks each had between 2,300 and 2,400 pounds of fuel,
he said.
   Mike Benson, a spokesman for NTSB, said those figures have
temporarily been discounted until the gauges can be calibrated and
tested, probably within the next few days.
   Picking through the wreckage Sunday, investigators found four
more cockpit fuel gauges, bringing the total to six. There are
eight in all, one for each of seven tanks, and another showing the
overall amount.
   Officials again revised their casualty count, saying there were
85 survivors rather than 86, as previously stated.
   More than 20 remained in critical condition, hospitals reported.
   At Saint Dominic's church in Oyster Bay, near the crash site,
worshippers Sunday morning prayed for the victims and offered
solace to rescue workers struggling to cope with what they had
witnessed.
   Investigators were looking for cockpit logs that may show how
much fuel was taken on in Bogota, and again after a stop in
Medellin, the center of the cocaine trade. Officials in Bogota were
expected to fax other fuel-related documents to the NTSB.
   The NTSB is also looking into the effect the aborted approach
may have had on the fuel system, Benson said.
   An Avianca pilot in Colombia who asked for anonymity told The
Associated Press that a steep climb after an aborted landing may
force the fuel away from the engines, causing them to stall.
   ``We're looking at that, but we don't have anything specific on
that,'' Benson said Sunday. ``We know that gravity can potentially
have an effect on the fuel _ that's why there are fuel pumps. But
to what degree it has an effect, we need to take a closer look.''
   None of the four engines was running when the plane crashed into
a hillside, and there was no explosion, both early indications to
investigators the plane had run out of fuel.
   The NTSB expected to finish up its on-site investigation by
Monday or Tuesday, Dicksinson said. The plane would be removed
toward the end of the week, he said. The four engines were to be
returned to Boeing in the next two days, he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900128-0004 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-28-90 0052EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--France-Police     01-28 0102</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--France-Police,0103</SECOND>
<HEAD>Two French Police Officers Draw Suspended Terms in Student's Death</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two policemen received suspended sentences Saturday
in the fatal beating of a student in December 1986 during huge
street protests of planned changes in the university system.
   A panel of professional and civilian jurists held that Brigade
Chief Jean Schmitt, 56, and Officer Christophe Garcia, 26,
committed misdemeanors in the death of Malik Oussekine, 22.
   The Court of Assizes panel found that Oussekine's poor health
contributed to his death. It sentenced Schmitt to five years
imprisonment and Garcia to two years. Both sentences were
immediately suspended.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900128-0005 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-28-90 0213EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a BC-NewsAppointments     01-28 0151</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-News Appointments,0154</SECOND>
<HEAD>Morris Communications Announces Appointments</HEAD>
<DATELINE>AUGUSTA, Ga. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Edward B. Skinner, Eastern Group newspaper
manager for Morris Communications Corp., was named the company's
vice president for newspapers, the organization announced Saturday.
   Carl Neil Cannon, Western Group newspaper manager, was named
publisher of The Florida Times-Union and vice president of Florida
Publishing Co. Robert E. Martin, assistant general manager of the
Times-Union, was promoted to general manager.
   ``Ed Skinner and Carl Cannon are experienced newspaper
executives with exemplary records and, additionally, both have been
involved in numerous community activities,'' said William S. Morris
III, MCC's chairman and chief executive officer.
   Skinner, 61, has been with the company for 47 years. Cannon, 46,
began his career with MCC in 1965.
   The Morris organization includes 12 daily newspapers in Georgia,
Florida, Texas and Alaska; six non-daily newspapers; an outdoor
advertising company; Gray's Sporting Journal; and a telephone book
publishing company.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900128-0006 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-28-90 1132EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--RhinoPoachers     01-28 0136</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Rhino Poachers,0139</SECOND>
<HEAD>Poachers Poison Two Rhinos in Zoo, Steal Horn of One</HEAD>
<DATELINE>KATMANDU, Nepal (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Poachers poisoned a female rhinoceros and
her male calf in a zoo and escaped with the calf's horn, officials
said Sunday.
   The officials, speaking on condition of anonymity, said the two
rhinos were found dead Saturday at the Jawalakhel Zoo in a Katmandu
suburb.
   Rhino horns are in great demand in Hong Kong and Far East
cities. The Chinese traditionally use the horns as an aphrodisiac.
   Asian rhinoceroses live in the Chitwan jungle of southern Nepal
and another sanctuary in Assam, in eastern India.
   Due to high demand for their horns, their numbers have been
diminishing.
   Nepalese authorities have declared the rhinoceros an endangered
species, and convicted poachers can be sentenced to up to 20 years
in prison.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900128-0007 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-28-90 1132EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Nepal-Earthquake     01-28 0075</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Nepal-Earthquake,0076</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tremor Rocks Northeast Nepal</HEAD>
<DATELINE>KATMANDU, Nepal (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A mild earthquake rocked Nepal, but there
were no reports of damage or injuries, seismologists said Sunday.
   They said the quake measured 4.5 on the Richter scale. It struck
at 11 p.m. Saturday at Ridak village in Sankhuwa district, 125
miles northeast of Katmandu.
   The Richter scale measures the magnitude of a quake at its
epicenter according to ground motion as recorded on seismographs.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900128-0008 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-28-90 1132EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--Taiwan-Fire     01-28 0165</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Taiwan-Fire,0172</SECOND>
<HEAD>28 Die In Commercial Building Fire</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TAIPEI, Taiwan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A fire broke out in a five-story
commercial building south of the capital as a crowd inside
celebrated the Lunar New Year, and 28 people were killed, officials
said.
   The fire started at 7:45 p.m. Saturday in a commercial center in
Taoyuan, 30 miles south of Taipei.
   Police said 18 bodies were found near bathrooms in a video
parlor on the fourth floor, which also housed a theater, hotel, a
barber shop and stores.
   Fireman Tseng Chang-chun said the victims may have been trying
to get water when they perished in the maze of corridors.
   He said firemen smashed windows on upper floors, and about 20
people used ropes to escape to a neighboring building. Four
children had to be tied to the ropes.
   Fire chief Ko Mo-chen blamed the high casualty toll on the
construction of the building, which had few windows.
   The cause of the fire was not immediately known.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900128-0009 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-28-90 1132EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--Britain-Papers     01-28 0159</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Britain-Papers,0165</SECOND>
<HEAD>New Sunday Newspaper for Britain</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Britons woke up to a new weekly newspaper Sunday,
only four months after the launching of another national paper.
   The new paper is called The Independent on Sunday and has three
sections and an 80-page color magazine. It becomes the fifth
national broadsheet published in London. It follows by four months
another broadsheet named The Sunday Correspondent.
   Many observers question whether there is room in the market for
so many competitors.
   In addition to the five broadsheets, there are six tabloids.
Their blend of scandal, celebrity gossip and topless models
achieves many times the circulation of the more serious broadsheets.
   The Independent on Sunday is the sister paper of The
Independent, which joined the ranks of the dailies in September
1986.
   The other Sunday broadsheets are The Sunday Times, The Sunday
Telegraph, and The Observer. The largest circulation is held by The
Sunday Times with 1.2 million copies.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900128-0010 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-28-90 1132EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--HeroinBust     01-28 0095</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Heroin Bust,0095</SECOND>
<HEAD>Police Find $17 Million of Heroin in Truck Fuel Tanks</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ISTANBUL, Turkey (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Police found $17 million worth of heroin
hidden in the fuel tanks of four trucks and charged eight Turks
with drug trafficking, the Anatolia news agency said Sunday.
   The report said an undercover police operation found the 400
pounds of heroin and that the suspects included the owner and
drivers of the trucks.
   The police did not say when the heroin was found, or where the
truckers had purchased the drug before returning with it to Turkey.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900128-0011 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-28-90 1133EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Hirohito'sTomb     01-28 0187</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Hirohito's Tomb,0193</SECOND>
<HEAD>Imperial Mausoleum Defaced in Japan</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Suspected leftist radicals have defaced the newly
completed tomb of Emperor Hirohito by drilling holes in two
ceremonial gates and pounding small dents in its stone markers and
lanterns, police said Sunday.
   The damage was discovered Sunday by police, who regularly patrol
the memorial but do not guard it round-the-clock, said a police
official.
   At least 16 three-quarter inch holes had been drilled in two
tall wooden gates outside the tomb, said the official, who
requested anonymity.
   Sixteen dents, fist-size or smaller, were found in two stone
lanterns and a stone marker next to the gates, he said.
   The marker bears the words ``Emperor Showa's Musashino
Mausoleum.''
   Showa refers to Hirohito, who died of cancer at age 87 on Jan.
7, 1989. His reign of 62 years was the longest in Japanese history.
   Musashino is the western suburb of Tokyo where Hirohito's tomb,
which reportedly cost $18.5 million, was opened to the public last
week.
   While public opinion polls show that most Japanese support the
monarchy, Japan's small groups of leftist radicals strongly oppose
it.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900128-0012 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-28-90 1133EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Burma-EmbassySale     01-28 0299</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Burma-Embassy Sale,0307</SECOND>
<HEAD>Burma Selling Part of Embassy Property in Tokyo</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Burma has sold about 60 percent of its embassy
property in Tokyo for more than $236 million as part of its
campaign to generate hard currency for its battered economy,
Japanese news reports say.
   Ambassador Mya Thein confirmed the sale but said he did not know
how much land was sold or the amount of money it brought.
   He said the matter was in the final stages of negotiations.
   The national newspaper Yomiuri Shimbun said Saturday that a
realtor already had paid the money and received a deed for 100,070
square feet of land.
   The paper said the embassy would retain present buildings for
offices and embassy housing and that the purchaser, the M.C.G.
construction company, planned to construct a business-residence
complex on the purchased land.
   Company officials could not be reached for comment Sunday.
   Major donor nations cut off new aid to Burma after the military
government of Gen. Saw Maung seized power in September 1988 and
violently suppressed a pro-democracy uprising. The isolationist
policies of former strongman Gen. Ne Win already had impoverished
the country, once one of Southeast Asia's richest.
   In the year following the 1988 coup, the price of rice, the
Burmese staple, more than doubled and prices of other basic
commodities also rose rapidly.
   The new government has sought to boost the economy by reversing
Ne Win's closed-door policies and seeking foreign investment.
   While the United States and Western Europe have shunned Burma
politically, Coca-Cola has become the first American company since
1962 to sign an agreement to sell there, and American oil companies
are discussing exploration contracts.
   Businessmen from Japan, Thailand, Singapore, Malaysia and South
Korea have negotiated deals in such areas as fishing, mining,
timber and tourism.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900128-0013 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-28-90 1133EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-TrainCrash     01-28 0121</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Train Crash,0123</SECOND>
<HEAD>1 Killed, 40 Hurt in Korean Train Crash</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SEOUL, South Korea (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   One person was killed and 40 people
were seriously injured Sunday when two cars of a passenger train
derailed, fell onto an adjacent track and were struck by a freight
train, railway officials said.
   The officials said they did not know what caused the two cars to
separate from the passenger train and derail, blocking the adjacent
track as the freight train was coming into a railway station in
southern Seoul.
   They said hundreds of people escaped through windows of the
passenger train following the crash with the freight train, which
was carrying oil.
   Cranes and other equipment were dispatched to clear the track.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900128-0014 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-28-90 1134EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-PeacePainting     01-28 0459</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Peace Painting,0470</SECOND>
<HEAD>Greek and Turkish Cypriots Resume Work on Giant Peace Painting</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ALEX EFTY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NICOSIA, Cyprus (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Greek and Turkish Cypriot artists resumed
work Sunday on two halves of a giant painting calling for peace
that they plan to stretch 500 yards across the buffer zone dividing
this island.
   The two groups continued to work on their respective sides of
the dividing line after Turkish Cypriot authorities again refused
to allow the Turkish Cypriot painters to join their Greek Cypriot
colleagues.
   Panicos Neocleous, the president of the Greek Cypriot Artists
Association, said he walked through the buffer zone to meet the
Turkish Cypriots at the checkpoint on the Turkish side. ``But the
police there were very tough. They wouldn't allow us even to talk
to the artists waiting for us there,'' he said.
   So the two sides began painting separately _ the Greek Cypriots
in the buffer zone and the Turkish Cypriots behind their checkpoint.
   The canvases include pictures of doves and olive branches and
multicolored slogans declaring: ``No More Violence,'' ``Cyprus a
Common Future,'' ``Make Love Not War,'' and ``Yes to Peace.'' The
project began Jan. 21.
   ``We have completed 200 yards of the painting, and we hope that
eventually we will be able to join up with our Turkish Cypriot
colleagues,'' Neocleous said.
   About 100 Greek Cypriots were busy painting on the stretch of
white canvas spread on the roadside in front of the Ledra Palace
Hotel, which serves as home for the Canadian contingent of troops
in the U.N. Cyprus peacekeeping force. The hotel is in the buffer
zone.
   The U.N.-patrolled zone has divided Nicosia and the rest of the
island since a 1974 Turkish invasion resulted in partition. Turkish
Cypriot officials bar most Greek Cypriots from entering their zone.
   Charles Gaulkin, the U.N. spokesman who acts as a go-between for
the two groups of artists, said 30 Turkish Cypriot painters were
working on their canvas.
   The ``Painting for Peace'' exercise, as it has been called, has
the blessing of Maj. Gen. Clive Milner, the Canadian commander of
the U.N. force, as a good idea to boost grassroots efforts on both
sides for reunification.
   ``We hope that through art we will achieve some sort of
reunification and the great thing is that the Turkish Cypriot
artists feel the same way as we do,'' Neocleous said. Gaulkin said
the United Nations was trying to arrange for the two groups to get
together later to join the two segments of canvas.
   U.N.-sponsored peace talks for the reunification of the island
in a two-state federation have been deadlocked since June.
   The U.N. secretary-general, Javier Perez de Cuellar, has invited
the leaders of the two sides to meet in New York next month.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900128-0015 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-28-90 1146EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Shevardnadze Bjt   01-28 1066</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Shevardnadze, Bjt,1101</SECOND>
<HEAD>Foreign Minister Says Gorbachev Not Seriously Threatened</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto MOSB1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MICHAEL PUTZEL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Foreign Minister Eduard A. Shevardnadze said there
is no danger of Mikhail S. Gorbachev being toppled from power but
that Western nations worry about it because they want his reforms
to succeed.
   ``I believe that this particular preoccupation stems from
sincere feelings, from sincere support for the process of
perestroika that is under way in the Soviet Union,'' Shevardnadze
told The Associated Press in a rare one-on-one interview. ``He was
the one who spearheaded this arduous but holy struggle.''
   The soft-spoken, white-haired official from Soviet Georgia
acknowledged ``there is some segment of the population that is
definitely disappointed'' by President Gorbachev's efforts at
reform.
   But he said, ``Gorbachev and the political leadership of this
country on the whole do enjoy the support of the bulk of the Soviet
people, in spite of the fact that we are experiencing great
difficulties: we have empty shelves in stores; we have a host of
other social, economic and inter-ethnic difficulties.''
   Shevardnadze, a member of the ruling Politburo and close ally of
Gorbachev, said the Soviet leader's opponents ``do not really
constitute a significant force.''
   Discussing Soviet economic problems in a set of separate written
responses, Shevardnadze said, ``For all the difficulties of
economic conditions in our country, the situation is not such that
we need `the last straw,''' a Russian expression akin to grasping
at straws.
   ``We have vast reserves,'' he said. ``And the purpose of
perestroika is to mobilize those reserves.''
   In addition to the face-to-face interview Thursday, Shevardnadze
submitted written answers to a separate set of questions submitted
in advance. His Russian comments in the face-to-face interview were
translated into English by The Associated Press. Shevardnadze
provided his own English translation to the written answers.
   Communist Party sources, speaking on condition of anonymity, say
the party is becoming more polarized, with hard-liners expected to
mount a challenge to Gorbachev's leadership when the national
body's Central Committee meets in Moscow on Feb. 5.
   A progressive faction also has formed, and sources say it may
stage an attack at the same meeting on the party's constitutional
monopoly on power and demand a virtual apology for decades of
totalitarian Communist rule.
   The strength of either group is difficult to measure, but the
problems for Gorbachev, who portrays himself as a centrist, have
mounted in recent weeks. The Communist Party in the Baltic republic
of Lithuania has broken with Moscow in a campaign for independence,
and long-simmering ethnic hatreds and territorial disputes have
boiled over into open warfare in the southwestern Caucasus region.
   Gorbachev ordered troops into the Azerbaijani capital of Baku to
crush an armed takeover by Azerbaijani nationalists, and since the
interview took place, officials have announced the arrests of
nationalist leaders.
   Shevardnadze said secession of republics would not only cause
military, political and economic problems for the regions but could
``result in a major destabilization of the existing international
structure.''
   ``It is in no one's interest to see this happen,'' the foreign
minister said in a written response to questions submitted before
the face-to-face interview. Shevardnadze's home republic of Georgia
is among those with an active nationalist movement.
   Shevardnadze, who marked his 62nd birthday last week, was
practically unknown outside the Soviet Union before Gorbachev
plucked him from his post as Communist Party chief in Georgia to
replace veteran Foreign Minister Andrei A. Gromyko shortly after
Gorbachev rose to power in March 1985. With a warm smile and
pensive manner, Shevardnadze has reshaped the image of Soviet
foreign policy molded for three decades by Gromyko's stony
countenance.
   Almost from the beginning, Shevardnadze showed a willingness to
negotiate not from a standpoint of class struggle but from
Gorbachev's ``new thinking,'' which seeks solutions to problems
through international cooperation, disarmament and attention to
``human values.''
   The interview in the foreign minister's office ranged from
discussion of arms control issues and Shevardnadze's meeting next
month with U.S. Secretary of State James A. Baker III to his views
on the unrest in the Caucasus and the independence movements in the
Baltic republics.
   He defended the decision to send troops into the republics of
Azerbaijan and Armenia, saying it was ``for the purpose of saving
people,'' and said the outbreak of ethnic violence there ``was
nothing short of civil war.''
   The decision, he said, ``does not correspond to either our
internal convictions or to our sentiments in general, because in
principle we are opposed to use of any force anywhere.''
   ``As the situation in that region stabilizes, we will gradually
withdraw our forces from there,'' he pledged.
   Asked if he had kept the United States informed of Soviet
military actions in the region, which is closed to foreign
journalists, Shevardnadze said there was no need for that because
``everything that's happening down there is made public.''
   Shevardnadze predicted ``the most important event of this year''
will be the U.S. summit in June between Gorbachev and President
Bush.
   He expressed confidence that he and Baker will make further
progress toward an agreement to cut in half the two superpowers'
strategic nuclear arsenals.
   Shevardnadze and Baker meet in Moscow on Feb. 7.
   For his written responses, the foreign minister was asked if the
Soviet Union would sign a strategic arms reduction treaty (START)
that did not limit sea-launched cruise missiles or the U.S. ``Star
Wars'' program, two longtime sticking points in the negotiations.
   Shevardnadze wrote: ``We are willing to limit (the missiles)
outside the treaty framework on the condition that the relevant
provisions will be recorded concurrently with the treaty, will be
mandatory and subject to verification.''
   ``We are willing to sign and implement a START treaty even
without agreement on space if the sides continue to observe the ABM
(Anti-ballistic Missile) treaty as signed in 1972,'' Shevardnadze
said.
   He was also asked to comment on a recent article signed only
``Z'' in ``Daedalus,'' the Journal of the American Academy of Arts
and Sciences, that argued Gorbachev's reform efforts are futile and
thus shouldn't receive the support offered by the Bush
administration.
   The foreign minister dismissed the article as a ``bag of old
cliches.''
   ``The article's author, who seems to be prone to stereotype
thinking, has completely distorted ideas about the content of our
perestroika,'' he said.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Michael Putzel, The AP's chief of bureau in
Moscow, conducted this interview.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900128-0016 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-28-90 1206EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Shevardnadze-Excerpts     01-28 0568</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Shevardnadze-Excerpts,0579</SECOND>
<HEAD>Excerpts From Shevardnadze Interview</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Shevardnadze, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are excerpts of Soviet Foreign Minister
Eduard A. Shevardnadze's remarks in an interview with The
Associated Press. Shevardnadze spoke in Russian, and his comments
were translated by the AP.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Our life is not very easy; it's difficult. We are facing some
big difficulties. To be perfectly candid, we are living through
dramatic situations. But without drama, there is no revolution ....
   There is no doubt that all the citizens in the world and all the
peoples in the world, including the American people, have a vital
stake in the success of our perestroika and in the renewal of
Soviet society, and I have no doubts whatsoever as to the sincerity
of your president, your secretary of state and other political
leaders who have stated many times over and over again their
support for perestroika ....
   I know that my friend Mr. Baker is in a businesslike and
constructive mood, and I think that we will be able by common
efforts to look for and find solutions that the whole world is
looking forward to and to set a good stage for the summit meeting.
And I believe that this will be the most important event of this
year ....
   (Shevardnadze was asked about Soviet military actions in the
republics of Armenia and Azerbaijan):
   We were compelled to bring our troops down there and to use
force. People died. This is a great tragedy .... We had to take
that decision when those peoples engaged in direct clashes with
each other, then we saw that it might erupt into a real tragedy. So
at that point we made that decision, which certainly does not
correspond to either our internal convictions or to our sentiments
in general, because in principle we are opposed to use of any force
anywhere.
   And here, of course, the decision was made to use force for the
purpose of saving people because they were at the brink of civil
war. Actually it was nothing short of civil war. As the situation
in that region stabilizes, we will gradually withdraw our forces
from there.
   I happen to come from that region myself, and perhaps I am
second to none in feeling concerned about what's happening there.
There was no other solution that we could have made acting in the
interests of those people. And I believe that President Bush does
understand it just as well as the U.S. public opinion and the
entire world community.
   (The foreign minister was asked about concern in the West that
Gorbachev won't survive the many crises he faces):
   I believe that this particular preoccupation stems from sincere
feelings, from sincere support for the process of perestroika that
is under way in the Soviet Union. We initiated our perestroika on
the initiative of comrade Gorbachev. He was the one who spearheaded
this arduous but holy struggle .... I should say that Gorbachev and
the political leadership on the whole of this country do enjoy the
support of the bulk of the Soviet people in spite of the fact that
we are experiencing great difficulties: we have empty shelves in
stores; we have a host of other social, economic and inter-ethnic
difficulties. Well, there is some segment of the population that is
definitely disappointed; it is a reality too. They do not really
constitute a significant force.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900128-0017 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-28-90 1221EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Spain-US     01-28 0336</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Spain-US,0346</SECOND>
<HEAD>Spaniards Protest U.S. Ship, Central American Policy</HEAD>
<DATELINE>VALENCIA, Spain (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Several hundred anti-nuclear protesters
demonstrated Sunday against the presence of a U.S. Navy aircraft
carrier in the port of this eastern city, and three people were
arrested when a clash broke out, police said.
   A spokesman for the organizers of the protest said the target of
the demonstration, the aircraft carrier Forrestal, carries 150
nuclear weapons.
   Spain does not allow nuclear weapons in its territory, but it
accepts the U.S. government's policy of neither confirming nor
denying whether its ships or aircraft are carrying nuclear weapons.
   The protest, organized by leftist parties and environmental
organizations, ended up with a clash between police and a group of
demonstrators, who threw paint cans at the Forrestal's hull.
   Police said three demonstrators were arrested for hurling stones
at policemen, one of whom was treated and released from a local
hospital.
   Also Sunday, thousands of people marched peacefully through
downtown Madrid to protest U.S. policy in Central America and to
demand the withdrawal of U.S. troops from Panama.
   Municipal police estimated 4,000 demonstrators marched behind a
banner that read ``Yankees out of Central America,'' then gathered
for a brief rally sponsored by 70 political and activist groups.
   An unidentified speaker at the rally called on the United States
to pull out of Panama, stop backing the Contra rebels in Nicaragua,
and withdraw its support from the rightist government of Alfredo
Cristiani in El Salvador.
   More than a dozen vans filled with police in riot gear were
parked near the rally, but there were no incidents.
   U.S. forces invaded Panama on Dec. 20, toppled the regime of
Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega and took him to Florida to face drug
charges.
   Vice President Dan Quayle said Saturday that President Bush
plans to reduce the number of U.S. troops in Panama to their
pre-invasion level of 13,000 in ``a matter of weeks.''
   There are now 17,000 U.S. troops in Panama, down from 27,000 at
the height of the invasion.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900128-0018 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-28-90 1226EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-CocaineAddiction Bjt   01-28 0866</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Cocaine Addiction, Bjt,800</SECOND>
<HEAD>Drug Experts Challenge the `One Puff and You're Dead' Message</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CAROLYN SKORNECK</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Some drug experts are challenging the wisdom
of dire public warnings that a few hits on a crack cocaine pipe
will lead immediately to addiction and ruin.
   Attention was focused on the issue when Mayor Marion Barry was
arrested Jan. 18 on a charge of cocaine possession. The FBI said it
had videotapes of the mayor smoking crack in a hotel room.
   Barry has been mayor of Washington for a decade and was expected
to announce for a fourth term this month.
   ``It will raise questions in people's minds,'' said Kevin Zeese
of the Drug Policy Foundation, which favors treating drug abuse as
a health problem, not as a criminal problem. ``He was mayor and he
was successful at it.''
   Lurma Rackley, a spokeswoman for Barry, said his ``most serious
problem is alcoholism.'' Law enforcement officials said blood and
urine samples taken after his arrest tested positive for cocaine.
   Barry checked in last week at a treatment clinic in Florida.
   ``I happen to feel crack _ volatile cocaine _ is dangerous, and
I believe it's risky and I do not recommend its use,'' Dr. John P.
Morgan, director of the Pharmacology Department at City University
of New York Medical School, said Tuesday. ``But the idea that two
hits and you're dead or you're addicted is not true.''
   Patricia Erickson, a criminologist who heads the drug policy
research program at the Addiction Research Foundation in Toronto,
said, ``In our most recent study, half the people who used crack
didn't prefer that form of cocaine.
   ``That hit, that rush, isn't to everybody's liking,'' she said.
``For any substance, the user's own expectations and attitudes,
mind set, in conjunction with the social circumstances combine to
produce the outcome.''
   Erickson said that in many cases, ``the user's own
characteristics and background and friends they use with tend to
check use or channel it in ways that aren't necessarily
destructive. It's certainly evident that some people can control
it.''
   But Dr. Mark Gold, director of research at Fair Oaks Hospital, a
psychiatric facility in Summit, N.J., and founder of the Cocaine
Hotline, said ``Compared to heroin, crack cocaine or intravenous
cocaine is as addicting if not more addicting. ... The idea that
there's a significant number of people using crack occasionally is
not supported by the data.''
   Studies by the National Institute on Drug Abuse's Addiction
Research Center in Baltimore have found that while casual users can
perform simple tasks when under the influence, they suffer brain
wave impairments that would hurt performance on more difficult
tasks, said researcher Ronald Herning.
   At the same time, a study found that when heavy users abstained
from the drug, their performance suffered, which Herning attributed
to withdrawal.
   Gold said there are several different types of cocaine addicts:
those who use it continuously or daily; those who binge
occasionally; and those ``who use crack weekly but not daily, but
are obsessed by it, think about crack all the time and for one
reason or another ... will exert a tremendous amount of pressure to
attempt to manage the drug craving and addiction.''
   James N. Hall, executive director of the Up Front Drug
Information Center in Miami, said ``The time period from first use
to full-fledged addiction is going to vary according to several
factors, the first being a pre-existing, perhaps genetic,
disposition to the addiction cycle.''
   Another factor is previous drug use: ``If a person has been
using cocaine for a number of years in an apparently controlled
situation, and the switch is to crack ... the person is at high
risk of becoming full-fledged addictive in as short as a few
weeks.''
   Who will become addicted is impossible to determine in advance,
he said.
   ``The safest thing to do is never use it in the first place,''
he said. ``Almost every addict has said, `It won't happen to me.'''
   While Morgan acknowledges the dangers of crack use, he contends
that the ``one puff and you're addicted, kid,'' attitude stems in
part from racism: ``The issue of crack being overwhelmingly
addictive is the sort of mistake that gets made when a drug becomes
democratized and we become frightened of the users.''
   ``We weren't ready to turn the world on its ear'' when wealthy
people smoked cocaine by freebasing long before crack showed up on
the street, he said. The concern grew when young urban minority
males started using crack. ``We are terrified about their ability
to control themselves at all times,'' he said.
   Morgan also blames the media for focusing on the worst addiction
cases for their dramatic value.
   ``There is no drug which, in and of itself, is sufficient to
explain addictive behavior,'' he said. ``Our tendency is to focus
on the drug, the crack, the heroin, the ice, the ecstasy. A
dramatic story is only useful if it has a focus. A lot of people
use this drug and don't get addicted to it.''
   When the other factors leading to addiction are included, such
as the user's socioeconomic background, ``That makes a messy story.
So crack becomes a scapegoat.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900128-0019 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-28-90 1234EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Shevardnadze-Text 1stAdd   01-28 0811</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Shevardnadze-Text, 1st Add,a0649,0826</SECOND>
<HEAD>MOSCOW: concrete deeds.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Q: The United States and Soviet Union are pressing for a
strategic arms reduction agreement in principle by June and for
signing of a START treaty this year. Yet, there has been little if
any progress reported on the most difficult longstanding obstacles
to agreement. Will the Soviet Union sign and implement a strategic
arms reduction treaty that does not limit sea-launched cruise
missiles or restrict the U.S. Strategic Defense Initiative?
   A: One of the most important results at Malta was the political
decisions of the sides to conclude a START treaty in 1990.
Generally speaking, this year can become ``the disarmament year.''
It is quite realistic to reach agreements also in areas such as the
reduction of conventional armed forces in Europe and the
elimination of chemical weapons.
   Thus, our joint policies have been defined very clearly. It now
remains to translate them into negotiating positions.
   As to the fundamental issues that you have touched upon, we
submitted back in Wyoming compromise proposals on sea-launched
cruise missiles. We are willing to limit them outside the treaty
framework on the condition that the relevant provisions will be
recorded concurrently with the treaty, will be mandatory and
subject to verification.
   We are willing to sign and implement a START treaty even without
agreement on space if the sides continue to observe the ABM
(Anti-ballistic Missile) Treaty as signed in 1972. That was also a
major step that we took in Wyoming. It is to be hoped that
Secretary Baker will bring to Moscow adequate responses to our
initiatives. It is not too long before he comes here.
   Q: Does the United States' support for the independence of the
Baltic republics contribute to the separatist campaign in Lithuania
and elsewhere, and will you seek a change in U.S. policy as part of
President Gorbachev's effort to prevent breakup of the union?
   A: We know the position of the United States, which does not
recognize the entry of the Baltic republics into the Union. Our
assessment of it must be well known to you, too.
   As to the specific aspects of establishing a truly federative
structure of our country to supercede the unitarism that actually
existed, and setting up a new mechanism of relationships between
the republics and the center, these problems are addressed in the
course of a broad dialogue in our country taking into account the
interests of all the ethnic groups.
   The secession of some particular republics from the Union would
produce not only additional military-political and economic
stresses for their population, but could also result in a major
destabilization of the existing international structure. It is in
no one's interest to see this happen.
   The problems of inter-ethnic relations are so delicate and
sensitive that one should avoid any outside interference in the
process of their development. Otherwise, one can provoke
unpredicatble repercussions.
   I should say that on the whole we see that responsible
politicians are aware of this.
   Thus, recently the U.S. administration has reaffirmed that since
the establishment of diplomatic relations with the Soviet Union,
the United States recognizes the territorial integrity of our
country. The principles, recorded in the Helsinki Final Act to
which the United States affixed its signature, are also well known.
   Q: An article signed ``Z'' in the American magazine ``Daedalus''
has provoked something of a sensation with its contention that
President Gorbachev's attempts at reform are futile and that the
West should therefore not try to help them succeed. Perhaps the
article is getting particular attention right now due to the
climate, with Lithuania trying to break from Moscow, the Caucasus
ablaze with ethnic quarrels and the economy unable to provide basic
food and consumer goods to people throughout the country. How would
you respond to ``Z''?
   A: I know about the article by ``Z'' from its newspaper version.
It is strange that the bag of cliches it contains about the demise
of socialism is portrayed as something of a sensation. This was
written and spoken about many times over the past 70 years. And
such forecasts always turned out to be in the dump of history.
   The article's author, who seems to be prone to stereotype
thinking, has completely distorted ideas about the content of
perestroika and about the nature of the ongoing processes within
Soviet society. It is our impression that the changes occurring in
the world are not to his taste altogether and that he does not like
the administration's course, which is supported by most Americans,
for a ``new closeness' with the Soviet Union.
   As to our own difficulties, we do know about them, and we do not
conceal them. But we are confident that these difficulties will be
overcome because there is no alternative to perestroika.
   There is much work ahead of us, and we are prepared to do it.

</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900128-0020 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-28-90 1259EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-India-Kashmir     01-28 0609</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-India-Kashmir,0627</SECOND>
<HEAD>Troops Briefly Lift Curfew in Sealed Kashmir City</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DILIP GANGULY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SRINAGAR, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   People hurried to buy food and medicine
on Sunday afte the government briefly lifted a curfew imposed to
halt a violent Moslem separatist campaign in the bitterly contested
Kashmir region.
   Occasional gunfire was heard in this Kashmir city during the
day. There were reports that militants and paramilitary troops
exchanged fire in the center of the city, but there was no word on
casualties.
   At least 72 people, mostly Moslems breaking curfew, have been
killed since Jan. 20 when the government intensified efforts to
curb violence by pro-Pakistan Moslems.
   Islamic militants want Indian-governed Kashmir _ a part of the
state of Jammu-Kashmir _ to become independent or join Pakistan,
which also claims the territory.
   Jammu-Kashmir is the only Indian state with a Moslem majority.
Its largest city, Srinigar, is the center of the secessionist
movement led by the Jammu-Kashmir Liberation Front. The Jammu
region of the state is predominantly Hindu.
   Security forces were told to shoot curfew violators and except
for brief relaxations, the around-the-clock curfew has been
stringently imposed in Srinagar and other Kashmir towns.
   On Sunday, the curfew was lifted at 5 a.m. for six hours. People
loaded up on potatoes and onions, but there was little meat or
green vegetables.
   Not much fresh produce has reached this city of 1 million since
Jan. 20, when the curfew began. Residents said Moslem separatists
warned shopkeepers not to sell meat because the deployment of
troops in the city was a ``sign of sorrow'' and people should not
eat meat.
   On Saturday night, Islamic fundamentalists broke into a liquor
shop owned by a Hindu and smashed bottles, sources said, declining
to be identified further.
   Private vehicles were allowed to move Sunday for the first time
since the crackdown started, but motorcycles were not permitted to
carry extra riders. On Thursday, motorcycle-riding gunmen shot and
killed four air force men as they waited for a bus.
   Violence has continued despite the crackdown, but the government
has curtailed information to reporters since Friday. Police refused
to confirm shootings, and reporters were denied curfew passes.
Seven foreign journalists were ordered to leave the state and
arrived in New Delhi on Sunday.
   Journalists were allowed to leave their hotels Sunday only at 10
a.m., one hour before the curfew was reimposed.
   ``By imposing the curfew and arresting people indiscriminately,
the government is only compounding the situation,'' one resident
said, speaking on condition of anonymity.
   The state's top police official, Jitendra Narayan Saxena, said
Srinagar had been sealed and ``no one can get out of the city.''
   Another resident, contacted by telephone, said: ``We are not
even allowed to stick our heads outside the window. The army men
immediately point their guns.''
   The resident, who did not give his name but identified himself
as a government employee, said the young men in his area are ``very
agitated. I have a feeling that if and when it (curfew) is lifted,
there will be serious trouble.''
   A senior official said security forces Saturday arrested 11
suspected militants during house searches in three areas of
Srinagar. A police officer, who did not wish to be identified
further, said the searches yielded one rocket launcher.
   State government officials have repeatedly said the situation is
under control. Gov. Jagmohan, a Hindu who uses only one name, said
Sunday ``the situation is now peaceful.''
   India and Pakistan have fought two wars over the Kashmir
territory since they were partitioned after gaining independence
from Britain in 1947. Pakistan holds the western part of Kashmir,
and India controls the eastern section.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900128-0021 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-28-90 1316EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SriLanka     01-28 0674</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Sri Lanka,0696</SECOND>
<HEAD>Indian Troops Leave Jaffna, Tiger Guerrillas Hoist Flags</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PATRICK CRUEZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>COLOMBO, Sri Lanka (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Indian troops abruptly pulled out of
the Tamil stronghold of Jaffna, leaving the town to the Tamil Tiger
guerrillas they had battled more than two years, residents and
officials said Sunday.
   The Indian troops, who are to complete their withdrawal from Sri
Lanka by the end of March, evacuated Jaffna late Saturday and
pitched camps 10 miles or more outside the northern town, residents
said by telephone.
   The unannounced evacuation caught many people by surprise when
they woke up Sunday.
   ``We saw the Tiger flag fluttering all over the town and shops
were open, traffic was abnormally active and people were thronging
the roads,'' one resident said, speaking on condition of anonymity.
   ``We then realized we were free of the Indian occupation which
began over two years ago,'' he added.
   Jaffna, about 200 miles northeast of Colombo, was the heart of a
Tamil separatist revolt that erupted in 1983 against the Sinhalese
ethnic majority that dominates the Sri Lankan government and armed
forces.
   When the government failed to squelch the insurrection, it
enlisted Indian help. An Indian peacekeeping force arrived in 1987
but soon became the target of the Tamil Tigers.
   In a dizzying reversal of roles, the Sri Lankan government began
negotiating with the Tigers to give them a political role, while
the Indians who once gave the Tigers sanctuary on Indian soil
became the enemy.
   Jaffna was partisan turf for the Tigers, who were routed from
the predominantly Tamil town by Indian forces in the fall of 1987.
   Small groups of armed Tigers moved openly in the town on Sunday,
according to the telephone reports.
   A Sri Lankan military official in Colombo said the Indians had
completed their withdrawal from Jaffna by 6 p.m.
   An Indian diplomat, speaking on condition of anonymity,
confirmed the departure but declined to say how many Indian troops
were involved.
   The evacuation of Jaffna leaves only one major town still
patrolled by the peacekeeping force _ the port of Trincomalee, 147
miles northeast of Colombo.
   An Indian departure from Trincomalee is expected to trigger one
of the biggest power struggles within the Tamil movement, because
Trincomalee is the base of three pro-Indian Tamil groups fiercely
opposed by the Tigers.
   These three groups captured control of the provincial council in
an election boycotted by the Tigers, who now are staking their
claim to political power and want new elections called.
   A former council member who belonged to the pro-Indian Eelam
National Democratic Liberation Front was assassinated early Sunday
by two gunmen who pedaled up to his Trincomalee home on bicycles.
   The council's coordinating secretary, Anthony Muttu Vedanayagam,
accused the Tigers of killing C.M. Ganeshalingam, the council's
rehabilitation minister.
   A Tiger spokesman in Colombo denied the charge, claiming
Ganeshalingam was killed by fellow members of the Eelam National
Democratic Liberation Front in an embezzlement dispute.
   Meanwhile, in the Ampara district that was vacated by the Indian
peacekeeping force late last year, three Sinhalese game wardens and
their Sinhalese driver were killed by a mine, Sri Lankan military
officials said.
   Three other people were critically wounded when the game
wardens' jeep was blown up Saturday on a jungle road about 125
miles east of Colombo.
   The military officials blamed the deaths on the Tamil National
Army, a militia set up by the pro-Indian Tamils running the
northeastern provincial council and banned by the central
government.
   The Tigers have run the Tamil National Army out of most major
towns in regions vacated by the Indians. The various guerrilla
groups once banded together to fight the Sinhalese-dominated
government but have been splintered by their quest for power within
the Tamil minority.
   The Tamil insurrection grew out of a desire for a separate
homeland, which militants said was needed to preserve the Tamil
ethnic identity. Tamils accused the Sinhalese, 75 percent of Sri
Lanka's 16 million people, of discrimination in jobs and education.
   Tamils comprise 18 percent of the population.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900128-0022 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-28-90 1345EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Barry-Moore     01-28 0261</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Barry-Moore,240</SECOND>
<HEAD>Report: Barry Paved Way for Rasheeda Moore's No-Bid Contract</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Mayor Marion Barry personally urged Hazel
Diane ``Rasheeda'' Moore in 1986 to seek city funding for a no-bid
contract to teach self-esteem training to inner city youths,
according to a published report Sunday.
   Moore's former business partner, Carole Bland Jackson, was
quoted by The Washington Post as saying Barry came up with the idea
at a Friday night party in June 1986. Jackson said she drew up the
$52,488 ``Project Me'' program within a day and it was approved the
following Monday. Jackson later became director of the project.
   At the time, Jackson and others said, Barry was seeking a sexual
relationship with Moore.
   Moore is the woman who allegedly lured Barry to a downtown
Washington hotel on Jan. 18, where the mayor was subsequently
arrested and charged with possession of cocaine. Barry is currently
in West Palm Beach, Fla., where he is undergoing treatment for
chemical dependency.
   Jackson said she and Moore approached Barry at the 1986 party
and asked him to emcee a fashion show. The mayor declined, but
asked the women to come up with a program to supplement his summer
youth program.
   After Jackson devised the ``Project Me'' program, she said Barry
``basically told people'' at the Department of Employment Services
that they should give Moore whatever was needed for the program.
   ``I learned later that there's a process for getting the money
and ours was pushed through,'' Jackson said.
   Jackson said she eventually quit the program following a dispute
with Moore.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900128-0023 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-28-90 1423EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People Sub a0660 01-28 0227</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People, Sub, a0660,0231</SECOND>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS BEVERLY HILLS, Calif.-dated 2nd item in rdp to CORRECT
spelling of Ronald Colman sted Coleman in 3rd graf.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>BEVERLY HILLS, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Actor Robert Culp, currently
reprising his ``I Spy'' role for a television movie based on the
1960s TV espionage series, is tracking down a buyer for his
Spanish-style home.
   Culp and his wife, Candace, are selling because their daughter
goes to elementary school farther west and they want to reduce the
time it takes to take her to school, according to Fred Sands
Realtors.
   The Culps have occupied the house, in the celebrity-laden area
north of Sunset Boulevard, for 14 years. It was built in 1926 for
British comic actor Reginald Denny and later was owned by Ronald
Colman, a fellow British performer.
   The 4,000-square-foot home, listed for nearly $2.5 million, has
a secret room designed for use during the Prohibition era, a spiral
staircase, a film projection room, sun deck and pond.
   Culp, 59, has reunited with Bill Cosby for the movie based on
the popular ``I Spy'' series, which ran for three years, beginning
in 1965.
   Culp and Cosby played American secret agents who circled the
globe. Culp posed as a top-seeded tennis player and Cosby was his
athletic trainer.
   In the early 1980s TV series, ``The Greatest American Hero,''
Culp played an FBI agent.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900128-0024 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-28-90 1427EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--OldTires     01-28 0125</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Old Tires,0126</SECOND>
<HEAD>Malaysia Hopes to Build Reefs Out of Millions of Old Tires</HEAD>
<DATELINE>KUALA LUMPUR, Malaysia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The government hopes to increase
the amount of fish in its waters by purchasing millions of used
tires from Japan and using them to form artificial reefs off its
coast, a government minister said.
   The agriculture minister, Sanusi Junid, told the New Sunday
Times the government figures it needs 42 million tires to build the
reefs.
   After collecting only 1.4 million tires locally over the last
three years, the government decided to buy the rest from Japanese
companies, he said.
   Once the tires are acquired, they will be tied together in
groups and dropped into the sea to form reefs that should promote
fish breeding.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900128-0025 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-28-90 1443EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Darman'sGames Bjt   01-28 0714</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Darman's Games, Bjt,670</SECOND>
<HEAD>Darman Climbs Into Bully Pulpit Again To Lecture Fiscal Critics</HEAD>
<HEAD>AP News Analysis</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARTIN CRUTSINGER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Economics Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   There he goes again. Richard Darman has
mounted his bully pulpit to deliver another hellfire and brimstone
lecture against gamesmanship when some would argue that President
Bush's budget director is the champion of all times in that arena.
   In a 15-page essay which will be included in the president's
budget when it is released Monday, Darman chastises Congress for
trivializing the historic changes occurring in Eastern Europe,
rails against ``wonderland budgeting'' gimmicks and challenges
lawmakers to get serious about attacking the problems facing the
country.
   Even the existence of the essay, titled ``The Director's
Introduction to the Budget,'' is unusual. Normally, presidential
aides go out of their way to make sure that the centerpiece of
attention when the administration's budget is sent to Congress is
the president's annual budget message.
   But this time around, Darman's essay is getting a lot of advance
publicity, taking up an entire page in The New York Times over the
weekend and being quoted at length by other news organizations.
   Darman on Sunday termed the news leak of the document
regrettable, but it certainly guaranteed wide dissemination of his
views.
   The essay, which likens the federal budget to the ``Ultimate
Cookie Monster'' who mindlessly gobbles up scarce resources, struck
many of the same themes as Darman's famous broadside last July
against the nation's ``now-nowism.''
   He defined that term to mean ``our collective shortsightedness,
our obsession with the here and now, our reluctance to adequately
address the future.''
   The government's huge budget deficits, he said, were a
``mathematical representation of our wish to buy now, pay later _
or more accurately, buy now and let others pay later.''
   Stern words.
   But they were being issued by the man who served as a top
political strategist for Ronald Reagan, helping to craft all the
details of Reaganomics, an economic policy that stressed tax cuts
even as federal budget deficits were hitting record levels and the
national debt was nearly tripling in eight years.
   This is the same Darman who insists that George Bush stands
firmly by his pledge against raising taxes even if it means
continued budgetary gridlock with a Congress which refuses to go
along with sharp cuts in domestic programs.
   In his vivid essay on Bush's 1991 budget, Darman urges Congress
to abandon political gamesmanship and responsibly address the tough
problems that must be dealt with in order to get the budget under
control.
   ``At some point, there is an obligation to be serious,'' he
wrote. ``At some point, partisan posturing must yield to the
responsibility to govern.''
   But Darman's attack left congressional critics grumbling that
they were being given a hypocritical lecture designed to obscure
the fact that the Bush budget fails to honestly attack the deficit
problem.
   Instead, the critics contend, the Bush budget relies on highly
optimistic economic assumptions to reach the deficit reduction
targets established in the Gramm-Rudman law, including cutting the
deficit nearly in half to $63.1 billion in 1991.
   The Congressional Budget Office, which usually makes less rosy
forecasts, is projecting that the deficits will be billions of
dollars above the administration's estimates, totaling $138 billion
in 1991 alone.
   The administration also is claiming budget savings by trimming
Medicare spending, slashing subsidies for Amtrak, the
government-owned passenger railroad, and a making a variety of
other cuts, all of which have been rejected by Congress repeatedly
in the past.
   The administration's various proposals left Sen. James Sasser,
D-Tenn., and chairman of the Senate Budget Committee, complaining
``It is clear that the administration still is not serious about
deficit reduction.''
   But Darman, interviewed Sunday on NBC-TV's ``Meet the Press,''
seemed unfazed by the criticism, continuing to attack what he
called hypocrisy and posturing on the part of Congress.
   When asked whether he shouldn't include the administration in
that assessment, the budget director said ``Perhaps we are guilty
somewhat ourselves. But that doesn't mean that we all don't have an
obligation to be more serious. ... Our budget will be criticized
unfairly. People ought to sit down and do serious work.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Martin Crutsinger has covered economic issues in
Washington for The Associated Press since 1984.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900128-0026 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-28-90 1523EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-GottiTrial Bjt   01-28 0768</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gotti Trial, Bjt,0790</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tape Transcripts Show Reputed Boss Settling In</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Spellings such as `gotta' are as written in court
transcripts.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By SAMUEL MAULL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   If government tape transcripts are any
indication, reputed Mafia boss John Gotti knows there is more to
being a mob executive than making offers that can't be refused.
   Transcripts of secretly recorded conversations show Gotti
talking about profits, relations with middle managers and the rank
and file, promoting, rewarding and realigning personnel, his hopes
to establish a legacy and why an executive must be aloof from
underlings.
   In an exchange with an unidentified man who was presumably an
equal, Gotti said: ``Me and you may socialize, but I can't
socialize with these guys. I can't bring myself down. I'm a boss.
You know what I mean.''
   Prosecutors say the transcripts prove Gotti is the nation's most
powerful crime boss. The defense says they're inaccurate
transciptions of what even the prosecution admits are sometimes
barely audible tapes.
   The transcripts were released last week at Gotti's trial on
charges of ordering the revenge shooting of a union leader. Jurors
got to listen to the tapes as well as read the prosecution's
transcripts.
   Gotti, 49, and Anthony Guerrieri, 60, are charged with assault
and conspiracy in the 1986 shooting of John O'Connor, former vice
president of Carpenters Union Local 608. O'Connor was wounded in
the legs and buttocks.
   Testimony was scheduled to continue Monday, with Leavenworth,
Kan., prison inmate James McElroy returning to the stand. On
Friday, McElroy, 45, described how he spent 30 years killing,
maiming, extorting and lying as a member of the tough New York City
Irish-American gang, the Westies.
   It was the Westies, prosecutors say, who were hired by Gotti to
shoot O'Connor because O'Connor had goons trash a mob-affiliated
restaurant that was being built with non-union labor.
   In his testimony, McElroy also fingered Gotti as the boss of the
Gambino crime organization.
   Law enforcement authorities say Gotti took control of the
Gambino ``family'' after Gambino boss Paul Castellano was shot to
death outside a Manhattan steakhouse in December 1985. No one has
been convicted in the killing.
   The transcripts indicate Gotti was talking like a leader within
weeks of that shooting.
   In a conversation with an unidentified man on Jan. 18, 1986,
Gotti said, ``Get a year, gonna put this thing together where they
could never break it, never destroy it. Even if we die, be a good
thing.''
   ``It's a hell of a legacy to leave,'' the unidentified man
replied.
   The tapes, made at the Bergin Hunt and Fish Club, Gotti's Queens
hangout, paint a picture of Gotti _ known as the Dapper Don because
of his fine suits _ enjoying his position and reputation.
   At the wedding of an underboss' son, he bragged, ``Every good
fellow, every skipper and every non-good fellow came and bothered
me. My brother Pete said he clocked 75 guys. I says he, he
undersold me.''
   A ``good fellow,'' the prosecution says, is a formally inducted
mob member. A skipper is a mob captain.
   Gotti also boasted about the compliments he is paid. ``You were
our last hope,'' he quoted one as saying. And, according to the
transcripts, he said another associate called him ``God's gift to
the underworld.''
   In another tape made in January 1986, Gotti recalled admonishing
a boyhood pal, reputed Gambino captain Angelo Ruggiero, for seeming
to treat the new boss like an equal: ``I told Ange, `You gotta
forget them liberties you take. Take 'em when we're alone.'''
   ``What the (expletive) kind of administration do you think I run
when the underboss, a captain, makes suggestions?'' he said. ``In
other words it looks like they're bosses.''
   The transcripts indicate that Gotti said he also instructed
Ruggiero that he was not to let low-level ``soldiers'' address
Gotti directly on mob business.
   Complaining about not getting enough help from underlings, Gotti
said, ``You see, a guy like Tony Lee (co-defendant Guerrieri) could
come around and help a little bit. Ange, the other guys.
   ``These are all good fellows from all over the country,'' he
said. ``They all come to me. I ain't got nobody here. I got to
listen to everybody. I forget what things there are. I write notes
to myself.''
   ``What do you think I gotta get? I gotta get somebody outside
the house, somebody to drive me around.''
   In a Jan. 18, 1986, tape, Gotti told someone he rejected a
suggestion to get rid of a certain consigliere, or counselor. ``We
leave a nice old man there as a figurehead,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900128-0027 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-28-90 1549EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Bulgaria     01-28 0498</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bulgaria,0516</SECOND>
<HEAD>Opposition Refuses to Join in a Coalition</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROLAND PRINZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SOFIA, Bulgaria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Bulgaria's opposition will not join the
government before free elections are held because any reforms it
backs could be blocked by the Communist-controlled Parliament, a
spokesman said Sunday.
   ``The Communists have a 67 percent majority in Parliament, and
they can stop any program,'' said Georgi Spassov, spokesman of the
Union of Democratic Forces, a loose grouping of 12 opposition
movements.
   Spassov is a key opposition participant in talks with the
Communists and other political and social groups. The talks are to
resume Monday.
   In an interview with The Associated Press, Spassov asserted that
the Communists are seeking to discredit the opposition.
   Emilyan Abadzhiev, spokesman for the official trade unions that
now have asserted their independence, called on the government on
Friday to resign, saying it was ineffectual and bowing to pressure.
   But Spassov claimed that the resignation call could be a ploy by
the Communist leadership to pressure the opposition into
participating in a subsequent coalition.
   ``We will not do this,'' he said, speaking through a translator.
   If the government of Premier Georgi Atanasov in fact steps down,
knowledgeable Bulgarians say, a caretaker government of civil
servants would be set up to function until the elections.
   A public opinion poll on a variety of issues, which was issued
by Bulgarian state-run television Saturday, gave opposition leaders
low popularity ratings.
   According to that poll, the most popular politician is the
defense minister and Politburo member Dobri Dzhurov, who is widely
rumored to have played a key role in the November ouster of
hard-line party leader Todor Zhivkov.
   Spassov expressed fears that the ruling Communists will hold
parliamentary elections in May, although the opposition coalition
has been calling for November elections to have more time to
organize.
   However, he said, there was a chance that the Agrarian Party, a
longtime docile ally of the Communists, may join the opposition.
   ``If that really happened, the opposition would also stand a
chance at the polls in May,'' Spassov said.
   Spassov suggested the opposition is fighting an uphill battle to
win popularity and supporters outside big cities, where people are
still very conservative.
   ``Smaller cities and villages are like little feifdoms in
Bulgaria where a handful of families wield power and no one else
has any say,'' Spassov said.
   He said that when the Communist Party meets for a congress Jan.
30, it is unlikely to enact radical reforms ``because the vast
majority in the party are conservatives, hard-liners.''
   Spassov said although the Communists are stalling, the
opposition would continue to negotiate with them ``as long as
necessary.''
   Key demands of the opposition include access to the mass media,
a new electoral law providing for proportional representation, and
removal of a constitutional clause describing Bulgaria as ``a
socialist country ruled by the working class.''
   ``If this principle is upheld, all democratic parties that do
not espouse socialist programs would be illegal,'' Spassov said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900128-0028 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-28-90 1629EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brites     01-28 0346</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brites,0359</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bright &amp; Brief</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BRADENTON, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   As if there weren't enough screaming,
hood-pounding car commercials on television, a Bradenton dealer has
launched plans for his own network consisting mostly of car ads 24
hours a day, seven days a week.
   Tom Stimus, known for his loud car ads and offering a bounty on
Libyan leader Moammar Gadhafi, is introducing StimusVision.
   It premieres March 1 on a cable outlet here with plans to expand
to the Tampa, St. Petersburg and Sarasota markets.
   Aside from advertising his dealerships, it will include
public-service announcements on missing children and wanted
criminals, lost-and-found ads, a swap shop and even romance advice
segments starring _ you guessed it _ Tom Stimus.
   Stimus has been on TV before. It was on a national talk show in
1986 that he said he wanted to raise $10 million for bounty on
Gadhafi.
   His cable channel will be leased for about $1 million over four
years, Stimus said.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>NEWARK, Ohio (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The county auditor is on the trail of the
Mole Man.
   It's not a character from pulp comics that Licking County
Auditor George Buchanan seeks, but a mysterious caller who taunted
Buchanan four or five years ago, saying his underground dwelling
would never be found _ and never be taxed.
   ``He told me we'd never find it, and he was very serious,''
Buchanan said. ``But I do not know why anyone would want to live
underground.''
   If the man is caught, he faces real estate taxes for the past
five years as well as a 50 percent penalty on back taxes and
interest.
   The caller said he lived in an underground house somewhere in
the county, and ever since Buchanan and his small staff have kept
an eye open for smoke from the Mole Man's burrow while traveling
about on county business.
   Even though it's been a long time since the call, Buchanan said
recently he was keeping the hunt in perspective.
   ``I am not going to spend county money looking for some dude in
a hole,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900128-0029 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-28-90 1709EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-ThirdWorldDebt     01-28 0658</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Third World Debt,590</SECOND>
<HEAD>Third World Debtor Countries Live Better Than Average</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CARL HARTMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   People in countries that have gone deeply into
debt enjoy higher living standards than the average Third World
country, according to World Bank figures.
   The bank calculates that Third World countries owe a total of
$1.3 trillion. Some are in trouble with their creditors and have
tried austerity measures to grow out of their difficulties. But
they still seem to be in constant crisis.
   In many ways, however, debt seems to have little effect on their
progress.
   Mexico, the largest Third World debtor after Brazil, has
completed the biggest and most difficult arrangement up to now for
reducing the burden of the $104 billion it owes. This was done
under the strategy proposed last year by Treasury Secretary
Nicholas F. Brady.
   Reduction in the actual debt is expected to be small because
there also will be new lending to Mexico. More important is a
reduction expected in the $7 billion that has been flowing out of
the country every year, mostly as interest and repayment of
principal.
   Compared with many Third World countries, Mexico is fairly well
off, the World Bank found. In 1988 the average Mexican earned the
equivalent of $1,820, compared with $1,970 for what the bank calls
the average middle-income country _ a group that includes such
diverse countries as Malaysia and Poland.
   But income isn't everything. More than nine out of 10 Mexicans
over the age of 15 can read, compared with fewer than eight in the
average country. Only 47 Mexican babies out of every 1,000 die in
their first year, against an average 55 in the Third World. The
average Mexican has 3,132 calories available a day, compared with
2,846 in similar countries.
   Mexicans now have a car for every 16 people, compared with one
for every 59 people 25 years to 30 years ago. Over half of Mexican
teen-agers are in secondary school _ three times as many as there
were a quarter-century ago, even taking the growth of population
into account. There is a doctor for every 1,242 people, while in
the 1960s there was only one for every 2,078.
   The bank gives approximate dates for some of the material in the
1989 edition of its ``Social Indicators of Development,''
distributed to reporters this week. That is because some countries
compile their figures more quickly than others, so that the latest
statistics available come from different years, depending on the
country.
   ``The debtor countries started by being better off,'' explained
John O'Connor, head of the bank division that deals with the
figures.
   ``But they've been doing less well since the debt crisis hit.
For example, the average Mexican income in 1968 was about 13
percent of the average in the United States. In 1988 it was down to
9 percent.''
   Countries with large debts tend to be larger countries, with
more population and resources. They had the assets that encouraged
lenders to give them credit in the first place.
   Egypt's $50 billion debt is twice that of nearby Algeria's,
according to the bank's figures. Though the average income is much
lower in Egypt _ $650 a year to $2,450 _ Egypt has two out of three
young people in secondary school, compared with a little more than
half of young Algerians.
   Egypt has a doctor for every 786 people, while the average
Algerian doctor has to take care of 2,327. Egyptians have 3,342
calories a day available, compared with Algerians' 2,715 calories.
   There are 77 newspapers for every 1,000 Egyptians, but only 21
for every 1,000 Algerians.
   Algerians have it better some ways. In Egypt 108 children out of
every 1,000 die before the age of five, despite the larger number
of doctors. compared with 92 in Algeria.
   The average life expectancy in Egypt is 54 years, while the
average Algerian baby can expect to live to 62.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900128-0030 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-28-90 1618EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-SouthAfrica     01-28 0623</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-South Africa,0640</SECOND>
<HEAD>President Says Police Force Must Get Out Of Politics</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVID CRARY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JOHANNESBURG, South Africa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President F.W. de Klerk
summoned police commanders to a closed-door meeting and told them
the nation's force will no longer be used to fight the government's
political battles, a major newspaper reported Sunday.
   ``We can't become embroiled in an Eighty Years War,'' de Klerk
reportedly told 500 commanders. ``We will have to move toward
finding solutions that are acceptable to the majority of the
population.''
   Also Sunday, Raymond Suttner, a prominent white anti-apartheid
activist who left South Africa illegally last year, returned to a
jubilant welcome from colleagues. Police followed him home but took
no immediate action.
   De Klerk addressed the police commanders about two weeks ago,
but the speech remained secret until the nationally circulated
Sunday Times reported its contents. The newspaper said de Klerk
asked the commanders to convey his message to every member of the
force.
   Anton Pretorius, a spokesman for de Klerk, confirmed that the
president had addressed the police commanders, but said he could
not comment on the substance of the speech.
   Since taking office in August, de Klerk has eased restrictions
on anti-government protests, freed senior leaders of the outlawed
African National Congress guerrilla movement and allowed them to
engage freely in political activity. These moves, and a public
commitment to free top ANC leader Nelson Mandela, are believed to
have embittered some right-wing officers in the national police
force.
   De Klerk, in his speech, reportedly said he was aware that his
actions ``have raised a number of questions in your minds.''
   ``In the past, you have been asked to handle situations that had
nothing to do with ordinary crime,'' de Klerk was quoted as saying,
referring to use of police to disperse protests and enforce
segregation laws.
   ``Circumstances have changed and we have reviewed our definition
of crime.''
   ``It will never again be asked of you to say to someone, `Hey,
you can't swim here because of your appearance,''' de Klerk
reportedly said. ``You will not be required to prevent people from
gathering to gain support for their views.''
   ``This is the political battlefield, and we want to take the
police out of it,'' he was quoted as saying. ``Let the politicians
look after politics.''
   De Klerk reportedly said his government sought to take the
intiative in avoiding a race war.
   ``For if this Armageddon takes place _ and blood flows ankle
deep in our streets and 4 or 5 million people lie dead _ the
problem will remain exactly the same as before the shooting
started,'' he was quoted as saying.
   Since de Klerk announced in September that peaceful protests
would be allowed, most marches and demonstrations have proceeded
without serious disturbances. However, police have insisted that
permission for major protests be obtained in advance, and there
have been clashes in several cases where approval was not obtained.
   The anti-apartheid activist Suttner said upon his return to
Johannesburg that he was uncertain whether police would act against
him.
   ``All I have done is exercise my freedom of speech,'' he said.
   During his time abroad, Suttner said, several Western diplomats
assured him that their governments would lodge protests if he were
detained again.
   Suttner, a law school lecturer, was freed from jail in September
after more than two years in detention. No charges were filed
against him, and he spent much of the time in solitary confinement.
   Upon his release, he was placed under heavy restrictions and was
barred him from any educational facility, including the University
of the Witwatersrand where he taught.
   In December, Suttner, 43, broke his restrictions, went to
Zimbabwe to attend an anti-apartheid conference and then remained
abroad.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900128-0031 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-28-90 1713EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Contras-Nuns     01-28 0402</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Contras-Nuns,000</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rights Group Blames Contras for New Year's Ambush of Nuns</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Contra rebel forces were responsible for the
New Year's Day ambush and killing of two Roman Catholic nuns,
including an American, in Nicaragua, according to an investigation
by the U.S. human rights group, Americas Watch.
   The private group said in a 53-page report Sunday that its
investigation, which included numerous interviews and other data
obtained in Nicaragua, concludes that the ambush was conducted by
Contra forces, although it appears the attack was not aimed
specifically at the nuns.
   The two nuns, including Sister Maureen Courtney, 45, of
Milwaukee, were killed when the white Toyota pickup in which they
were riding came under attack on a remote highway 165 miles
northeast of Managua. A bishop and another nun survived the attack.
   The Contra rebels have denied any involvement.
   ``It is our conclusion, based on this investigation, that those
responsible were a unit of the rebel Resistencia Nicaraguense, or
Contras, firing indiscriminately at the vehicle without warning to
stop, but also without knowledge that the vehicle belonged to the
church,'' the report by Americas Watch said.
   The group had been asked by five members of Congress to
investigate the shooting.
   Americas Watch said that a large rebel force was operating in
the vicinity of the highway on the day of the shooting.
   The report said the Contra unit did not intend to kill the
church people, but fired on the vehicle because it resembled those
used by the Nicaraguan government. ``No attempt was made by the
Contras to ascertain whether the occupants were military or
civilian,'' said the group.
   Among those interviewed were two youths who had been kidnapped
by the Contras and held by the unit involved in the attack at the
time of the shooting and the father of the man allegedly in command
of the unit as well as local residents, said the report.
   At the same time, Americas Watch accused the Sandinista military
of numerous civil rights abuses against local residents suspected
of working with the Contras.
   The worst such incident, the report said, involved the execution
in August, 1988 by Sandinista troops of six persons who were
believed to have been Contra collaborators.
   The human rights group called the execution on Aug. 20, 1988 in
the area of Umbla ``one of the worst abuses we learned of by either
side during recent years.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900128-0032 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-28-90 1717EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Budget-Glance     01-28 0260</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Budget-Glance,250</SECOND>
<HEAD>With AM-Budget Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Following are the highlights of proposals
expected in President Bush's 1991 budget, which will be unveiled on
Monday:
   DEFICIT _ The administration cut the budget deficit roughly in
half, reducing it from an estimated $123.8 billion this year, down
to $63.1 billion for the budget year which begins Oct. 1. That
would be the smallest deficit, if realized, since a $40.2 billion
shortfall in 1979.
   SPENDING _ The government would spend $1.233 trillion while
taking in $1.170 trillion in revenues.
   TAXES _ There would be no general tax increase, upholding the
president's no-new taxes pledge, although the budget boosts certain
``user fees,'' charged to businesses and individuals for government
services.
   MILITARY _ Defense spending would total $303.3 billion, 2
percent below the amount needed to keep up with inflation.
   FAMILY SAVINGS ACCOUNT _ A new savings vehicle which would allow
families to put away up to $5,000 annually with the interest and
dividends accumulating tax-free if they are kept for a total of
seven years.
   CAPITAL GAINS _ Bush is renewing his call to slash the tax on
capital gains, profits from the sale of assets, an effort which
prompted months of partisan wrangling last year.
   ECONOMIC ASSUMPTIONS _ The budget is based on an estimate that
the economy, as measured by the gross national product, will expand
2.6 percent this year, a forecast that is significantly higher than
many private analysts. If the higher growth is not realized, it
will mean a shortfall in revenues and a bigger budget deficit.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900128-0033 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-28-90 1718EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-TrainFatal     01-28 0240</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Train Fatal,0248</SECOND>
<HEAD>Man Killed by Train After Wheelchair Becomes Stuck Between Rails</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SCHODACK CENTER, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A passenger train traveling at 100
mph struck and killed a man whose motorized wheelchair had become
stuck between the rails, authorities said.
   The accident occurred Saturday afternoon about nine miles south
of Albany on a section of track where Amtrak trains usually hit 110
mph, said Amtrak spokesman Michael Stewart.
   The victim, 25-year-old Grayford John Mesick of Schodack
Landing, was watching a tow truck remove his friends' pickup truck
from muddy fields below the tracks when the accident occurred, said
Schodack Fire Chief Edward Secovine.
   The New York-to-Montreal train had just rounded a corner when
the engineer spotted Mesick, Stewart said. The engineer blew his
horn and flashed his lights before hitting the brakes, but the
six-car train took nearly a mile to stop.
   Stewart said Mesick could be seen trying to get himself off the
track at the time of the accident.
   Mesick lost a leg and was thrown 50 feet, but was conscious when
rescue workers reached him, Secovine said.
   ``He said, `My arms hurt,''' Secovine said.
   Mesick, who was paralyzed in a swimming accident nine years ago,
was pronounced dead at Albany Medical Center Hospital about 2{
hours after the accident, said Rensselaer County sheriff's Capt.
L.M. Walraed.
   None of the passengers was injured, Stewart said. The accident
delayed seven Amtrak trains as much as three hours.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900128-0034 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-28-90 1748EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Jetliner-Cocaine     01-28 0224</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Jetliner-Cocaine,0234</SECOND>
<HEAD>Crash Survivor Stable; Linked to Drugs</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Jetliner Crash</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MANHASSET, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A survivor of the Avianca jetliner crash
who carried cocaine packets in his intestines was in stable
condition Sunday.
   Doctors found four condoms filled with golf ball-sized clumps of
a white powder Friday while doing surgery to stop internal bleeding.
   Nassau County police were analyzing the substance, but the
patient, known only as Passenger No. 7, admitted it was cocaine,
said Dr. Robert Ward, the chief of special surgery at North Shore
University Hospital.
   Doctors believe a dozen or more packets remain inside him, but
decided against surgically removing the rest.
   Ward said each packet contained enough cocaine to kill the man
if it ruptured.
   The Avianca flight from Bogota had stopped in Medellin, a
drug-smuggling capital, before continuing to New York.
   In addition to internal injuries, the patient's legs also were
severely broken in the crash Thursday night.
   He hasn't been arrested but the case is under investigation,
said Officer Peter Franzone, a spokesman for the Nassau County
police.
   The Drug Enforcement Administration doesn't investigate cases
involving less than a kilogram of cocaine _ about 2.2 pounds, said
Mary Cooper, a DEA spokeswoman.
   Swallowing drug-filled condoms is ``a common method, not only
from Colombia but other places,'' she said. ``We've seen it from
Nigeria, too, bringing heroin.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900128-0035 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-28-90 1749EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-DoubleIdentity     01-28 0405</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Double Identity,0420</SECOND>
<HEAD>Two Women Share Social Security ID</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DAYTON, Ohio (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two girls named Sandra Lee Ferguson were
born May 3, 1959. They don't know each other, but the government
has considered them one and the same.
   Sandra Lee Ferguson Boles and Sandra Lee Ferguson Johnson share
the same Social Security number.
   For three years, Mrs. Boles, an employee of Wright State
University, has tried to convince the Social Security
Administration that she isn't Mrs. Johnson, who was last known to
live in Sunset, Utah.
   Mrs. Boles said she became aware in 1987 that her namesake
shared her Social Security number when the IRS claimed there was a
discrepancy in her reported income.
   Later some of Mrs. Johnson's purchases showed up on Mrs. Boles'
credit reports, which also are indexed by Social Security numbers.
   Last month, the Social Security Administration notified Mrs.
Boles that her number was given to her in error and that she must
prove her age, identity and citizenship to get a new number.
   ``Since we do not have this evidence, we have to remove your
earnings from our files,'' the notice said.
   ``The only thing I ever wanted from these people is an
explanation so that when I got in the Bureau of Motor Vehicles,
credit bureau, banks, payroll office, I have something to prove
what I am saying,'' Mrs. Boles said. ``They said it's your problem.
That's insane.''
   Mrs. Boles says she works in an office and can understand how
the mistake was made. What's hard to swallow, she said, is that
Social Security doesn't have a place to resolve mistakes.
   ``I'm going to start my own country and we're not going to have
a Social Security Administration,'' she said.
   She said her case has been transferred from the Dayton Social
Security office to Baltimore, then back to Xenia.
   Richard Rogers, manager of the Xenia office, said Mrs. Boles'
information was sent to Baltimore to get her a new number, ``but it
seems like they gave her the same number again.''
   He said a number mixup normally should take three months at most
to resolve.
   Even if Mrs. Boles gets a new number, she might have to get a
new driver's license and establish a new credit history. She
wonders if it might be easier just to trade places with Mrs.
Johnson.
   ``I'd like to see if she has a rich and good-looking husband,''
Mrs. Boles said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900128-0036 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-28-90 1744EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-SocialSecurity-Retirees Bjt   01-28 0853</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Social Security-Retirees, Bjt,800</SECOND>
<HEAD>Social Security Tax-Cut Plan Highlights Retirees' Fears on Deficit</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By NANCY BENAC</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Advocacy groups for the elderly say a
congressional proposal to cut the payroll tax helps highlight their
concern that Social Security's trust funds are being used to mask
the size of the federal deficit.
   That's not to say they support the tax-cut plan advanced by
their traditional ally, Sen. Daniel Patrick Moynihan, D-N.Y.
   Many groups representing the elderly are expressing reservations
about the proposal, warning that it could jeopardize Social
Security's financial standing and cause a loss of confidence in the
system.
   ``There are going to be a lot of yellow lights telling Congress
to go slow,'' said an official at one organization who asked not to
be identified. ``A consensus is emerging that it's a bad idea to
cut the payroll tax now.''
   An official at another group said Moynihan's plan could make it
harder to expand benefits in future years because there would be no
giant surplus to tap.
   Public criticism by the groups has been muted, however, because
most of the organizations see Moynihan as a well-intentioned friend.
   Lawrence Smedley, executive director of the National Council of
Senior Citizens, said the group ``appreciates Senator Moynihan's
`truth-in-budgeting' Social Security proposal as an honest attempt
to expose the extent to which the growing surplus is being used to
mask the federal deficit.''
   However, he said, rolling back the payroll tax increase is an
issue that needs further study.
   President Bush, hoping to derail the Moynihan plan, will offer
an alternative program that would use the surpluses to reduce the
$2.8 trillion national debt, administration officials said Saturday.
   The administration is expected to spell out the proposal as part
of Bush's fiscal 1991 budget, which will be released Monday.
   Advocates for the elderly said debate over the Moynihan plan is
an even hotter topic for today's workers than for retirees, whose
benefits appear secure and who no longer are subject to the payroll
tax.
   Workers, meanwhile, must decide whether they want immediate
extra cash from a tax cut or the potential delayed benefits of
building up Social Security trust funds to finance future
retirement benefits.
   The National Taxpayers Union is supporting the Moynihan plan as
a good way to reduce the tax burden on U.S. workers, and wants to
see it followed by cuts in federal spending, said NTU's Sheila
Macdonald.
   One of the best ways to help the country meet its Social
Security obligations in the next century ``is to reduce the deficit
now and improve the country's competitive position,'' she said.
   Moynihan's chief concern is that Social Security's growing trust
fund reserves _ a stockpile designed to help finance the retirement
of the huge Baby Boom generation born between roughly 1946 and 1964
_ are being used to obscure the size of the deficit.
   The Congressional Budget Office estimates the Social Security
surplus, the amount collected in payroll taxes above what is paid
out in benefits, will total $98 billion in 1993, rising to $112
billion in 1994 and $128 billion in 1995.
   Moynihan's solution is to halt the buildup of the reserves and
return Social Security to a pay-as-you-go system in which taxes
would be raised in the next century to finance retirement benefits
then.
   He wants to cut this year's 7.65 percent Social Security payroll
tax back to last year's 7.51 percent rate and cancel a further
increase scheduled for next year.
   Many aging groups share Moynihan's concerns, but would prefer an
accounting change that removes Social Security from the
calculations that determine the federal deficit, increasing
pressure to cut the deficit without slowing the buildup of the
trust fund reserves.
   ``It is our hope that Congress will move quickly to separate
Social Security trust funds from the unified budget and that it
will move much more deliberately on the question of rolling back
the payroll tax,'' Smedley said.
   A similar sentiment was voiced by Horace Deets, executive
director of the American Association of Retired Persons. Moynihan's
proposal highlights the deficit problem, Deets said, but ``his
solution, I don't think is the solution.''
   AARP is holding off on taking a formal position on the proposal
until after Moynihan addresses the organization.
   Dan Schulder of the National Council on the Aging said the
council's board is reviewing a proposed statement opposing the
tax-cut plan.
   ``What we're concerned about is the confidence factor,''
Schulder said. ``We got in trouble with pay-as-you-go just a few
years ago when the system almost went broke.''
   One group that traditionally has leaned the other way is the
National Committee to Preserve Social Security and Medicare, which
has advocated a pay-as-you-go system with a one-year benefits
reserve.
   ``There is a good reason to look at pay-as-you-go,'' said
committee president Martha McSteen. ``Through the years ... Social
Security has been changed to meet the needs of the people in this
country and taxes have been raised or they have been delayed,
depending on the reserves that were needed to meet the benefit
payments.''
   The committee has yet to take a position on Moynihan's plan.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900128-0037 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-28-90 1758EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-GayPriest     01-28 0399</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gay Priest,0411</SECOND>
<HEAD>Homosexual Priest Under Fire For Views On Fidelity In Marriage</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEWARK, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A newly ordained homosexual priest may be
asked to resign from the Episcopal clergy if he doesn't agree to
uphold the principles of monogamy espoused by the church, says the
bishop who ordained him.
   The Rev. J. Robert Williams, ordained Dec. 16 over the
objections of some top Episcopal officials, provoked further
controversy by telling a church forum that monogamy and fidelity
aren't requisites for marriage.
   Williams said his position is based on pastoral experience that
showed few heterosexual or homosexual couples to be faithful, The
Star-Ledger reported Sunday.
   Williams called monogamy ``as unnatural as celibacy,'' in
comments the newspaper said were carried by the Religious News
Service following a Jan. 13 church forum in Detroit.
   ``If people want to try, okay. But the fact is, people are not
monogamous,'' Williams said. ``It is crazy to hold up this ideal
and pretend it's what we're doing and we're not.''
   Williams, 34, a priest at All Saints Episcopal Church in
Hoboken, has lived with James Skelly, 39, a hospital administrator,
for four years.
   In a diocesan news release Friday, Bishop John S. Spong of the
Newark diocese, who ordained Williams, said Williams wouldn't have
been ordained if church officials had known of his view of marriage.
   He said officials were unaware of it although Williams had been
screened for ordination for two years.
   Spong, who has been assailed by conservative Episcopalians for
permitting Williams' ordination, said he reprimanded the priest and
asked him to apologize.
   ``His own life needs to be conducted according to the same
standards applied to all priests, homosexual or heterosexual,''
Spong wrote. ``If Mr. Williams is not able to conform to the
standards of this diocese, then his resignation would be
requested.''
   Williams issued a statement Saturday night saying
``irreconcilable'' differences had led him to resign his position
as head of a program called Oasis that ministers to homosexuals.
   Williams told The Star-Ledger he felt ``disappointed and
betrayed'' and alleged that Spong was using him as a scapegoat for
the pressure he was feeling from church authorities.
   He said he didn't think he would be able to continue as an
Episcopal clergyman, but would continue with religious work.
``Maybe it will have to be my own church,'' said Williams, a priest
at All Saints Episcopal Church in Hoboken.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900128-0038 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-28-90 1708EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Budget 1stLd-Writethru a0661 01-28 0965</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Budget, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0661,930</SECOND>
<HEAD>White House Defends $1.2 Trillion Budget, Attacks `Hypocrisy'</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: Subs 5th graf prev, with three grafs, beginning ``The
spending xxx and inserts new 19th graf, beginning ``A 24 percent
xxx with documents obtained, new figures, detail</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By ALAN FRAM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush on Sunday prepared to send
Congress a $1.23 trillion 1991 spending plan that his budget
director said contains no general tax increase and which he
predicted will be ``criticized unfairly'' on Capitol Hill.
   With many details already known about the budget, which will be
released Monday, Democratic lawmakers are complaining that it fails
to address the deficit seriously and that its defense cuts are too
timid.
   But White House Budget Director Richard Darman on Sunday blasted
what he said was ``an awful lot of hypocrisy'' and ``posturing'' by
lawmakers about the administration's plans.
   ``We're about to start an annual ritual, which is regrettable,''
Darman said on NBC-TV's ``Meet the Press.'' ``Our budget will be
criticized unfairly. People ought to sit down and do serious work.''
   The spending plan, for the fiscal year that begins Oct. 1,
claims to reduce next year's shortfall by $36.5 billion, cutting it
to $63.1 billion, according to budget documents obtained by The
Associated Press. Bush is seeking a total of $1.23 trillion in
spending and $1.17 trillion in revenues.
   The savings include $13.9 billion in minor new taxes and fees,
$600 million of which the administration will seek to impose this
year, the documents show.
   Also proposed will be cuts in defense and domestic programs
including energy conservation efforts and Medicare, the documents
and officials who spoke on condition they not be identified have
indicated.
   The $63.1 billion deficit falls just below the $64 billion
ceiling required by the Gramm-Rudman balanced-budget law. It will
be the smallest shortfall proposed by a president since President
Reagan sent his first spending blueprint to Capitol Hill in March
1981, when his budget for fiscal 1982 contained a $45 billion gap.
   But Democrats say Bush's budget relies on unrealistically
optimistic assumptions about economic performance, such as the
spending plan's expected estimate that the economy will grow by
about 2.6 percent this year. That drives up the amount of revenues
the administration can project collecting and makes the amount of
needed deficit reduction appear smaller.
   They also say Bush's $303.3 billion defense spending proposal _
a 2 percent cut when compared to the costs of inflation _ is too
high considering the political and social changes in Eastern Europe.
   Senate Budget Committee Chairman James Sasser, D-Tenn.,
predicted ``a very chilly and negative reception on the Hill'' for
Bush's spending plan.
   ``It's clear the administration is still not serious about
deficit reduction,'' he said last week. ``Their spending priorities
are misdirected. And they still are directing too much to defense.''
   ``The bottom line for everyone to ask is, `Is it real, is it
fair, is it balanced,'' House Budget Committee Chairman Leon
Panetta, D-Calif., told reporters Friday. ``He's promised that kind
of budget, but I think we're going to see something that's very
different.''
   It is known that Bush will seek to trim $8.5 billion from
projected growth of the Medicare program for the elderly and
handicapped by cutting payments to doctors and hospitals, not by
shrinking benefits to patients. Other cuts are expected in
agriculture spending and in payments to retired federal workers.
   Bush's defense proposal _ which includes some nuclear weapons
spending by the Energy Department _ is an increase over this year's
$296.3 billion in outlays, or the funds that actually will be spent
this year. But the way budget deficits are calculated, the $303.3
billion proposal counts as about $4 billion in savings, the amount
by which it lags behind inflation.
   Darman said that over several years, military reductions could
result in more than $200 billion in savings compared to earlier
projections.
   ``What's unfortunate in this case is everybody's assuming that
that's right this moment, and they plan to spend it 10 times
over,'' he said.
   Other details that documents and official and congressional
sources have provided about the budget include:
   _A 24 percent increase to $15.2 billion for NASA and a $1
billion increase _ to $12.3 billion _ for basic research efforts.
   _A proposal to gradually stop using the massive Social Security
surpluses to make the overall federal deficit look smaller. It is
the administration's answer to a plan by Sen. Daniel Moynihan,
D-N.Y., to reduce the retirement system's surpluses by cutting the
payroll tax.
   _A boost in education spending from $24.1 billion to $24.6
billion, not enough to keep up with inflation. Some student loan
programs will be cut, while rewards to schools that show improved
student performances will be increased.
   _A $500 million increase in the Head Start pre-school program
for poor children to nearly $2 billion, announced Friday by Bush.
   _A first-ever requirement that veterans be required to pay 4
percent down payments on modestly priced homes, and a $1 billion
increase _ to $12.3 billion _ for veterans' health care.
   _A renewal of Bush's call for a cut in the capital gains tax
rate, ratcheted to increase the breaks for property the longer it
is held. Bush will claim the cut will increase revenues by several
billion dollars next year, arguing it would stimulate sales of
property. Democrats say the proposal is a boon to the rich and will
eventually lose money for the government.
   _A so-called Family Savings Account allowing families to put
away up to $5,000 annually into accounts that would earn tax-free
interest if they are kept for at least seven years.
   _Cuts in many domestic programs including energy conservation
programs, mass transit assistance and federal aid to Amtrak, the
passenger railroad.
   _Higher spending for space, anti-drug and research programs.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900128-0039 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-28-90 1710EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Soviet-Unrest 1stLd-Writethru a0662 01-28 0824</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Unrest, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0662,0845</SECOND>
<HEAD>Guerrillas Leave One Front; Peace Talks Set For Wednesday</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS last graf with 4 grafs to ADD details of evening news
report and Azerbaijani criticism of news coverage; no pickup.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos MOSB3-6</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ANN IMSE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Armenian and Azerbaijani fighters began
withdrawing from a key battlefront on Sunday, and the bitter
enemies agreed to discuss extending the truce to other parts of the
volatile region, activists reported.
   The Armenian National Movement agreed to conditions demanded by
the Azerbaijani People's Front for peace talks that are to begin
Wednesday in Riga, Latvia, according the Latvian People's Front,
which is sponsoring the talks.
   Both sides now say they will discuss troop withdrawals, refugees
and other humanitarian concerns, but not the pivotal territorial
dispute that triggered the hostilities, said Artis Erglis of the
Latvian People's Front.
   Armenians demand control of Nagorno-Karabakh, an enclave of
Azerbaijan populated largely by Armenians. Azerbaijan is
predominantly Shiite Moslem, while most Armenians are Christians.
The two Soviet republics have feuded intermittently over
Nagorno-Karabakh for two years.
   The conflict burst into anti-Armenian riots on Jan. 13 in Baku,
the Azerbaijani capital, and led to battles between Armenians and
Azerbaijanis in the countryside. President Mihail S. Gorbachev
ordered Soviet troops to restore order, leading to more bloodshed
as Kremlin forces encountered stiff resistance from Azerbaijani
fighters.
   At least 197 people have been killed in the neighboring
republics since Jan. 13.
   The nationalist movements in the Baltic republics offered to
mediate the conflict, a sign of how much clout the burgeoning
movements have gained in the past year and their concern over
unrest that requires Kremlin intervention to control.
   Yusif Samedugli, a board member of the Azerbaijani People's
Front, confirmed in a telephone interview from Baku on Sunday that
Azerbaijani representatives would attend talks in the Latvian
capital.
   Samedugli said the People's Front in Tbilisi, the capital of
neighboring Georgia, also volunteered to mediate, and the
Azerbaijanis will send a representative there as well.
   Georgia, the three Baltic republics, Armenia and Azerbaijan are
among several of the 15 Soviet republics that have sought greater
independence from Moscow.
   This feared unraveling of the Soviet Union's 15 republics has
presented Gorbachev with his greatest domestic challenge.
   Militants began withdrawing without incident Sunday from the
border between Armenia and Nakhichevan, an Azerbaijani territory
bounded by Armenia, Iran and Turkey, according to Samedugli and
Armenian activist Rafael Popoyan in the Armenian capital, Yerevan.
   Last week, activists agreed to a truce at the border, one of the
most bitterly contested areas in the region.
   The two sides agreed to patrol roads near the border with groups
of no more than 10 unarmed men. The action will leave security
along the border zone to Soviet troops, the Soviet news agency Tass
said.
   Samedugli said a preliminary agreement was reached on holding
negotiations on a similar disengagement on the border of Azerbaijan
and Nagorno-Karabakh, and in the Shaumyan and Khanlar districts of
Azerbaijan near Nagorno-Karabakh.
   Samedugli elaborated Sunday on the Azerbaijanis' proposals.
``The only basis or peace talks can be the Armenians' total
renunciation of any territorial claims,'' he said. ``For our part,
we will guarantee full civil and cultural rights in
Nagorno-Karabakh.''
   Tass said separate talks produced a hostage exchange _ 17
Armenians for 22 Azerbaijanis in the Khanlar district. But Popoyan
said three other Armenian hostages remained in Azerbaijani hands
and two were feared dead.
   Soviet soldiers arrested scores of activists in Azerbaijan on
Saturday to crush what Tass called a ``criminal military
structure'' of nationalists. Among those arrested were the leaders
of two organizations called the National Defense Committee _ the
militant arm of the People's Front _ and National Salvation, Tass
said Sunday.
   ``But some of the masterminds of terror are still in hiding,''
Tass said.
   Tass said Sunday that government and Communist Party officials
were restored to power in Lenkoran after army troops battled the
National Defense Committee. One army lieutenant and five
``terrorists'' were killed and the military captured 50 extremists,
three mortars and 52 guns, it said. No date was given.
   Radio Moscow said Sunday that life in Baku was returning to
normal, but Tass said extremists were distributing leaflets calling
for civil disobedience.
   The national television evening news showed Azerbaijanis
criticizing Soviet media coverage of the unrest, and the
commentator laid blame squarely on Tass, the official news agency.
   ``Often we are obliged to run Tass reports, which are considered
official, even if we don't share the (Tass) viewpoint,'' he said.
   He noted that many of the Tass reports in question are unsigned
statements, apparently drawn up by bureaucrats. ``We would always
like to know the names of the authors,'' the commentator said.
   Azerbaijan television went back on the air for the first time in
more than a week on Saturday. Much of the city remained on strike
to protest the Soviet military presence, although some bus service
resumed, official reports said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900128-0040 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-28-90 1728EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Yugoslavia 1stLd-Writethru   01-28 0567</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Yugoslavia, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0667,0584</SECOND>
<HEAD>Riots Continue in Yugoslav Province; At Least One Killed</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 7 grafs to UPDATE with one killed, five injured in
clashes; picks up 5th pvs, `A high-ranking...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By SLOBODAN LEKIC</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PRISTINA, Yugoslavia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Thousands of ethnic Albanians fought
with police Sunday in Kosovo province in demonstrations demanding
that Communist authorities lift a state of emergency and allow free
elections.
   At least one person was reported killed and four injured.
   It was the fifth straight day of riots in Kosovo, a province of
Serbia where tensions have long existed between the majority Moslem
Albanians and Christian Serbs.
   Riots occurred in at least two towns, including one where
protesters attacked a police station. Gunfire was reported in one
instance.
   State media and police officials confirmed five deaths Saturday
in confrontations between police and protesters. Ethnic Albanian
sources told The Associated Press that at least 12 Albanians had
died in the fighting.
   More than 200 ethnic Albanians have been arrested since the
riots began Wednesday in the province, which wants greater autonomy
from Serbia.
   On Sunday, riot police battled for hours with 7,000 protesters
chanting ``Democracy!'' in Suva Reka, 30 miles south of Pristina,
witnesses said. The demonstrators gathered repeatedly despite
attempts to disperse them with tear gas and baton charges, the
witnesses said.
   The state news agency Tanjug reported that three people were
injured in the clashes and that one later died.
   A high-ranking police officer, who declined to be identified,
told The Associated Press that rioters fired at riot police earlier
in the day.
   Groups of ethnic Albanians attacked a police station in Djeneral
Jankovic, 35 miles south of Pristina, and two policemen were
injured, the officer said. No casualties were reported among the
attackers.
   During the action, barricades were reportedly erected on a main
road to prevent police reinforcements from reaching the station.
   Smaller demonstrations were reported in several other towns.
   Heavy police reinforcements have been bused into Kosovo from
several towns in Serbia in the past few days.
   The Democratic Union of Kosovo, a newly formed independent
ethnic Albanian group, denounced what it described as ``police
brutality and the ensuing bloodshed.'' It called on the federal
state presidency ``to end the repression and accept the widest
democratic dialogue'' with ethnic Albanians.
   Groups of Serbs, numbering up to 500, assembled Sunday in
several villages in Kosovo to chart ways of dealing with the latest
wave of unrest in the troubled province, which they feel is
directed against them, media reported.
   The violence began nearly a year ago when Serbian President
Slobodan Milosevic assumed greater control over the province
through constitutional amendments. He also promised to end alleged
harassment of Slavs by ethnic Albanians, who make up 90 percent of
the province's 1.9 million population.
   At least 28 people died in violence in the province last year
after the constitution gave Serbia near total control over Kosovo.
   After last year's unrest, the Serbian authorities introduced a
partial state of emergency in the region, allegedly to protect the
Serbian minority in Kosovo from purported harassment by ethnic
Albanians.
   The Albanian majority is protesting alleged discrimination by
the regional Communist authorities. It also is demanding the
lifting of the state of emergency, free elections and the release
of Albanian political prisoners.
   Serbian leaders accuse the Kosovo Albanians of wanting to secede
from Yugoslavia in order to join neighboring Albania.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900128-0041 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-28-90 1814EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-USFilmFestival     01-28 0463</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-US Film Festival,0474</SECOND>
<HEAD>Offbeat Movies, Black Filmmakers Dominate Film Festival</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN HORN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PARK CITY, Utah (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The hottest ticket at the Sundance United
States Film Festival was ``Blue Steel,'' a police thriller with
Jamie Lee Curtis and plenty of gunfire, but the real stars were two
low-budget, deeply personal movies from black filmmakers.
   Staying true to its focus on independent, against-all-odds
filmmaking, the festival, which ended Sunday, gave its top prizes
to ``Chameleon Street'' and ``To Sleep With Anger,'' two projects
whose path to the screen was more perilous than any shootout in
``Blue Steel.''
   ``Chameleon Street,'' a quirky look at a peerless con man, took
writer-director-star Wendell B. Harris four years and nearly four
dozen investors to make. The film, awarded the Grand Jury Prize,
was produced by Harris' mother, Helen.
   ``To Sleep With Anger,'' an alternately haunting and comic
account of a family crisis, was completed by writer-director
Charles Burnett just days before the festival began. It won a
Special Jury Prize.
   Neither ``To Sleep With Anger'' nor ``Chameleon Street'' yet
have distributors, but their victories here are likely to propel
them to U.S. theaters soon.
   And their selections also indicate that the festival _ littered
as it is with Hollywood parties, deal-making on the ski slopes and
stargazing _ remains dedicated to providing alternatives to
mainstream studio fare. The festival is organized by actor Robert
Redford's Sundance Institute.
   ``There's nothing worse than a commercially compromised art
project,'' said Jim Stark, producer of the independent hits
``Stranger Than Paradise'' and ``Down By Law.'' ``You can't make a
better `Top Gun' than the studios can.''
   One of last year's hits at the festival, ``sex, lies and
videotape,'' went on to become one of the most successful
independent films of the decade. To date, the $1.1 million feature
by writer-director Steve Soderbergh has grossed more than $24
million.
   Meanwhile, though, a variety of independent
producers-distributors are going out of business, including
Atlantic, New World, Cannon, Vestron and De Laurentiis. Funding for
renegade filmmakers has never been so tight.
   Said Todd McCarthy, the co-screenwriter of the documentary
``Hollywood Mavericks'': ``There are not as many loose
opportunities to make any old film.''
   But Tom Rothman, the president of worldwide production for
independent the Samuel Goldwyn Co., said, ``Not all independent
films have merit just because they were a struggle to make.''
   Optimists point to the fact that more than 36,000 admissions
were sold to this year's festival.
   ``The cycle does seem to turning,'' said Alexander Kogan Jr.,
sales representative for ``Chameleon Street.'' ``There's an
increasing demand for independent film.''
   The Audience Award, given to the most popular film as determined
by a poll of the audience at festival screenings, went to
``Longtime Companion,'' a drama focusing on AIDS.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900128-0042 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-28-90 1741EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-LouisianaFloods     01-28 0316</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Louisiana Floods,0326</SECOND>
<HEAD>Floodwaters Begin to Recede After Damaging 850 Homes</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BATON ROUGE, La. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Floodwaters that damaged at least 850
homes in southeastern Louisiana began a slow retreat in some areas
Sunday, but a threat of further flooding remained.
   A 50 percent chance of rain was forecast for Monday in the Baton
Rouge area, which was hardest hit by flooding that began Friday
after a week of rain.
   Flood warnings remained in effect for several rivers and creeks
in East Baton Rouge neighboring Livingston parishes, where flooding
was worst, the National Weather Service said. East Baton Rouge
Parish includes the city of Baton Rouge.
   Preliminary estimates by the Red Cross were that water damaged
about 350 homes in East Baton Rouge Parish and about 500 in
Livingston Parish.
   The floods were said to be the worst in the area since 1983,
when water damaged 1,963 homes in East Baton Rouge Parish alone.
   Along the Amite and Comite rivers, responsible for most of the
damage, people returned to their homes as floodwaters began to
recede Sunday.
   Bertha Helmke of Baton Rouge recalled how she helped haul her
family's belongings out of her home Friday and then sat back and
watched the water pour in for the third time in 13 years.
   ``Throughout the whole thing I didn't shed a tear, but now it's
all hitting me,'' Helmke said. ``You just feel like you're at God's
end. I don't know what to do.''
   Several subdivisions were isolated by floodwaters and scores of
roads were closed. Most were reopened over the weekend.
   About 50 residents were evacuated from the Golden Age Nursing
Home in Denham Springs, and many homes were soaked when residents
began cleaning up.
   Terry Felder of Denham Springs said despite the frequent floods,
he won't leave.
   ``This is a minor inconvenience,'' Felder said. ``It's not
something that's going to sneak up on you.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900128-0043 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-28-90 1744EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Pope 1stLd-Writethru a0651 01-28 0685</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Pope, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0651,0702</SECOND>
<HEAD>Pope Calls for Catholic-Moslem Dialogue in Mali</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 9th graf pvs with 3 to UPDATE with twilight Mass, prayer
for victims of Avianca flight; pickup 10th pvs, `At the...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By SYDNEY RUBIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BAMAKO, Mali (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Pope John Paul II appealed Sunday for
understanding and cooperation between Mali's Moslem majority and
Roman Catholics in fighting the grinding poverty in sub-Saharan
Africa.
   ``The country needs the efforts of all in the great battle
against hunger, malnutrition and literacy, in addition to the fight
you confront in drought and desertification,'' the pope told a
crowd of 1,000 people lining the hot and windy airstrip at Bamako's
Senou Airport.
   He stressed dialogue again later in talking to the nation's
seven bishops, calling Moslems ``important partners'' with
``authentic religious values that we need to recognize and
respect.''
   ``Dialogue with them is not always made easy, nor desired by
all, and we sometimes find it difficult to find a common language
and representatives,'' he told the bishops. ``It is here that
Christian generosity should help us to be realistic and courageous,
all at once.''
   About 1 percent of the nation's 8 million people are Roman
Catholic, while Moslems make up about 70 percent.
   The pontiff was greeted by Bamako's Archbishop Luc Sangare and
Mali's Moslem President Moussa Traore, who welcomed him as the
``king of peace and freedom.''
   The pope and the president, dressed in a robin's-egg blue
boubou, or loose, flowing garmet, paused and applauded a group of
dancers from the animist Dogon tribe of northern Mali, who wore
grass skirts, painted wooden masks and ankle bracelets made of
bottle caps.
   A cacophony of drums and balafons, the traditional African
xylophone, blended with the chants and cheers from the colorfully
dressed crowd.
   The pope met with workers at the Sacred Heart Cathedral in the
afternoon and prayed for victims and families of those who died in
the crash Thursday of an Avianca jetliner in Cove Neck, N.Y., and
in the storm that struck Europe last week.
   At dusk, while the Moslem call to prayer spread over the city
from the central mosque, more than 25,000 people packed the
bleachers at Bamako's sports stadium for the papal Mass.
   Earlier, the pope completed his visit to the nation of
Guinea-Bissau by blessing disfigured patients at a leper hospital
and making an impromptu visit to the mud hut of a village family.
   At the leper hospital in Cumura, a bush village six miles
outside the capital of Bissau, he told the 250 leprosy victims, ``I
love you very much.''
   ``Don't let yourselves be beaten ... (Have) trust and courage in
medical progress and in the good will of those who offer you love.
I will never forget you,'' he told those seated on wooden benches
outside the hospital.
   His visit was scheduled to call attention on World Day of
Leprosy to the disease that afflicts up to 15 million people
worldwide, one-third of them in Africa.
   The pope called for an international effort to conquer the
disease.
   En route to the Bissau airport, John Paul asked to stop at a
clay hut where he visited an elderly man and his family. The
pontiff noted that poverty as much as totalitarian politics
compromises freedom.
   A Vatican representative with the pope gave the family $100.
   Africa's sub-Saharan nations, including Guinea-Bissau and Mali,
are locked in a struggle with disease, illiteracy, and hunger
wrought by drought, political mismanagement and the spreading
desert.
   Mali, one of Africa's 10 poorest countries with a per capita
income of $210 per year, has the second-highest infant mortality
rate in the world. Life expectancy is 47 years.
   Only about 20 percent of the people can read and write, and
education is one of the main activities of the Catholic Church,
which runs 42 primary and secondary schools and accepts children of
all religions. Only 25 percent of Malian children attend school,
and one-fourth of them are taught by the church.
   The pope continues his eight-day trip Monday in Burkina Faso. He
heads to Chad before returning to Rome on Thursday.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900128-0044 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-28-90 1826EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-WeatherpageWeather     01-28 0391</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Weatherpage Weather,0408</SECOND>
<HEAD>Winter Weather in Northwest</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Winter snows ranged across the Northwest and the Rockies on
Sunday, and storms took aim at the eastern third of the nation.
   Winter storm watches were posted through Monday for northeast
Pennsylvania, where 6 inches or more of snow was expected, through
Virginia, western Maryland and northern Delaware.
   A winter storm watch also was posted for parts of western New
York and Vermont, with snow and freezing rain forecast across the
lower Susquehanna Valley and east-central Pennsylvania.
   Snowshowers and freezing rain extended across northern Kentucky
and western West Virginia by midday Sunday, with snow falling in
southwest Ohio and southeast Indiana.
   Rain reached from eastern West Virginia across Kentucky, central
and western Tennessee, the southeast half of Arkansas, northwest
Mississippi, northern Louisiana and much of the southeast half of
Texas.
   Storm warnings were issued for the Cascades in Oregon and
Washington, as well as the northeast mountains of Oregon and
Washington's Olympic range, with snow or rain forecast across the
northern Pacific Coast.
   By Sunday afternoon, about a foot of blowing, drifting snow had
fallen in the mountain passes of Washington in 24 hours.
   High winds were forecast for northern Idaho and the mountains of
Wyoming through Sunday night, and through Monday for the Pikes
Peak, Palmer Divde and Front Range of Colorado.
   Snow advisories were posted in the west-central and
north-central mountains of Idaho, as well as across its Panhandle,
with local advisories for 1- and 2-inch snowfalls in the southern
valleys.
   Morning winds gusted to 48 mph at Bellingham, Wash., 50 mph at
Fort Collins and Boulder, Colo., 55 mph at Houquiam, Wash., 58 mph
at Astoria, Ore., and 67 mph at Vedauwoo, Idaho.
   At noon, a cold front extending from southeastern West Virginia
to the lower Texas Gulf Coast created a temperature difference of
10 to 15 degrees east and the west of the front.
   There were a few thundershowers over eastern Texas and central
Louisiana.
   The low temperature for the nation Sunday morning was 14 degrees
below zero at Gunnison, Colo. A record high for the date was set in
Caribou, Maine, at 42 degrees.
   Temperatures around the nation at 3 p.m. EST ranged from 7
degrees above zero at Warroad, Minn., to 82 degrees at Fort Myers,
Fla., and Naples, Fla., and Harlingen, Texas.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900128-0045 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-28-90 1828EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ProjectWorth     01-28 0547</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Project Worth,0569</SECOND>
<HEAD>Louisville Program Helps Homeless Rebuild Lives</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOUISVILLE, Ky. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Tracy Shirley, a homeless mother of two,
is determined to get a job, and a nationally recognized program
called Project Worth is helping.
   ``There's nothing more that I want than a paycheck every week so
I can pay my bills and have some money left over,'' said Ms.
Shirley.
   Ms. Shirley, 27, is trying to bounce back from an unpromising
job interview for a $5.65-an-hour office job in which she scored
only 27 words per minute and made several errors on a typing test,
well below her normal skills.
   ``I panicked,'' she said. ``I was so embarrassed.''
   Thanks to Project Worth, Ms. Shirley returned to class last week
to practice.
   ``I'm going to do it,'' she said.
   ``Project Worth is great,'' said Sue Speed, director of the
Louisville Coalition for the Homeless.
   She said the program, funded by the U.S. Labor Department and
administered by the county school system, succeeds because planners
worked closely with other agencies to mesh Project Worth's services
with other programs and to determine what homeless people need to
do to prepare for jobs.
   Project Worth's ``wraparound'' approach begins with individual
vocational and educational assessment. It then channels the
homeless into adult-education and vocational classes, and offers
them guidance in personal and practical matters such as homemaking,
parenting, grooming and budgeting.
   A day-care program at a school allows parents to attend classes
without having to worry about their children.
   As people reach the point where they are ready to apply for
jobs, Project Worth counselors help them in polishing their
interviewing skills and contacting potential employers.
   The program also helps them find their own place to live, and
stays in touch for 13 weeks after they've gone to work.
   Last year, 264 people received training through the program.
Most were in their early 20s to mid-50s, and nearly three-fourths
were women (140 children received day care). Most are still in the
program, but 42 have landed jobs and 77 have moved from shelters
into places of their own.
   Although it's been in existence only a year, Project Worth has
already been noticed. It was one 33 trial programs financed last
year by the Department of Labor and one of only nine to receive
funding this year.
   Federal funding went from $279,000 in 1989 to $350,000 this
year. Additional support comes from the state Division of Adult
Basic Education, Metro United Way and other sources.
   Success, however, doesn't come easily.
   Brenda Adams, 30, who dropped out of school after the eighth
grade, has been in Project Worth almost a year trying to earn her
General Educational Development certificate, the equivalent of a
high school diploma.
   The long, slow climb has been aggravating at times, but Adams
said she's making progress. She scored 186 on the five-part
equivalency test the first time she took it, well short of the 225
needed to pass. But last time she fell only five points short.
   ``It's taken me longer than I thought to get my GED,'' said
Adams, who lives with two of her three children in an apartment
building for the homeless. ``I've always wanted to go back to
school, but I didn't know how to do it. I didn't have any support.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900128-0046 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-28-90 1834EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Czechoslovakia 1stLd-Writethru   01-28 0443</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Czechoslovakia, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0646,0452</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bishop Who Was Jailed for 11 Years Consecrated in Czechoslovakia</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS throughout to UPDATE with another rally demanding
pullout of Soviet troops, details; no pickup.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>PRAGUE, Czechoslovakia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Thousands of people jammed a
church outside Prague on Sunday to greet the first Catholic bishop
to be consecrated since Czechoslovakia's revolution ousted the
hard-line Communist leadership.
   About 20,000 people joined another rally Sunday outside a Soviet
garrison in central Czechoslovakia and demanded the immediate
pullout of Soviet troops, the state news agency reported.
   The church ceremony was attended by new President Vaclav Havel;
Archbishop Francesco Colasuonno; the pope's special envoy, Cardinal
Jean Maria Lustiger of Paris, and several other high-ranking church
officials.
   ``I am happy for this diocese that it finally has its bishop,
and I am happy it is you,'' Havel said at the ceremony for Bishop
Karel Otcenasek in the Church of the Holy Ghost in Hradec Kralova.
``I feel a little like a sheep belonging to your flock, because I
come here quite often,'' said Havel, who owns a country house near
Hradec Kralova, 75 miles northeast of Prague.
   Otcenasek, 70, who spent 11 years in jail for carrying out his
religious duties secretly in the 1950s, became residential bishop
at Hradec Kralove. He is the fourth bishop to be consecrated in
Czechoslovakia over the past seven months, but five of the
country's 13 bishoprics still remain vacant.
   In a visit made possible by the nation's recent pro-democracy
revolution, a high-level delegation traveled to the Vatican last
week for talks on the appointment of new bishops and a planned
visit by the Pope April 21-22.
   The Parliament last week abolished the requirement for
practicing priests to obtain licenses from the government. The old
regime had used the law to screen clergymen considered politically
troublesome.
   In the central Czechoslovak city of Olomouc, protesters
presented a petition for the speedy withdrawal of the Soviet
troops, the CTK new agency reported.
   It said garrison commander Maj. Gen. Evgeni Meshcheryakov told
the demonstrators that his troops were preparing for departure,
pending the results of talks to be held in Moscow in early February.
   Havel is due to visit Moscow early next month and a Soviet troop
pullout is expected to be a key issue during his visit. The
Czechoslovak government wants the estimated 75,000 troops out by
the end of the year.
   The protest was organized by students and the opposition
movement Civic Forum, state TV said.
   Under pressure from pro-democracy demonstrators, hard-line
Communist Party leader Milos Jakes resigned Nov. 24. On Dec. 10, a
government controlled by non-Communists took power for the first
time in 41 years.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900128-0047 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-28-90 1848EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Quayle 2ndLd-Writethru a0671 01-28 1017</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Quayle, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0671,890</SECOND>
<HEAD>Churchgoers Cheer Quayle as Government Seek Continued U.S. Troop
Presence</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: Subs 24th graf, ``Quayle later xxx with two grafs to update
with visit to canal and Fort Clayton to watch Super Bowl</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By RITA BEAMISH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Vice President Dan Quayle was cheered
by church goers whose priest welcomed the U.S. military invasion,
and the new government's leaders said American troops still are
needed to help stabilize the country.
   While the continued presence of the U.S. troops has rankled
other Latin nations, Panama's new president, Guillermo Endara, said
the occupying troops are needed until Panama can get its police
force operational.
   Peruvian President Alan Garcia has refused to attend the Feb. 15
drug summit in Colombia with President Bush unless the U.S.
invasion forces are out of Panama.
   But Endara said Sunday that other Latin leaders should ``think
of the Panamanian people and what they want.''
   Quayle met with leaders of Panama's new government to discuss
Bush's $1 billion economic recovery package and the withdrawal of
occupying troops in what he said would be a matter of weeks. Endara
had sought $2 billion in U.S. assistance.
   In a television interview, Quayle said the issue of the U.S.
military invasion of Panama ``is behind us'' and that it is time to
focus on the future of Panama.
   The Bush economic recovery package includes loan guarantees
through the Export-Import Bank and a variety of U.S. emergency
relief assistance to help Panama pay its foreign debt, recover its
economy and help businesses and other victims recover from the U.S.
invasion and subsequent fighting.
   The focus of discussion shifted somewhat, however, as Endara
said his country needs some U.S. troops to remain until the new
national police force is operational.
   ``At this moment, we have not the police. Our forces are not
quite capable of protecting the life, property and public order as
the Panamanian people want,'' Endara told reporters outside morning
church services. ``But we hope that in a very short time this will
not be necessary.''
   Endara said his government does not want to plan to build a new
army, but will keep only a police force.
   Quayle repeated that he sees the withdrawal of invasion troops
within ``weeks rather than months.'' A senior official traveling
with Quayle said it would likely be within two weeks that the
current 17,000 member force is reduced to the 13,000 pre-invasion
level.
   U.S. officials have said they have no plans to cut back below
the 13,000 troop level.
   At the packed Cristo Rey Church, the pro-American congregation
cheered Quayle. One person held a sign reading, ``Gringos don't go
home.''
   Some in the well-dressed crowd wore T-shirts with the words
``Operation Just Cause'' _ the name Bush gave the operation.
   They enthusiastically applauded Quayle when he entered the Roman
Catholic Church with Endara and his two vice presidents. People
crowded into the aisles to shake his hand as he made his way to the
front row.
   The Rev. Javier Villanueva, whose weekly anti-Noriega sermons
were well known before the Dec. 20 invasion, told the congregation
the Bush administration recognized Panamanian suffering and helped
eliminate it by driving out Noriega.
   He said other Latin nations who deplored the invasion never did
anything to help Panama's situation.
   Quayle said outside the church service that the reaction of the
people was ``very gratifying.''
   Quayle, the highest-ranking administration officials to visit
Panama since the invasion, offered a new rationale for the invasion
on ABC-TV's ``This Week With avid Brinkley.
   ``I am convinced that implementing the treaty as ratified by the
Senate would have been a very difficult proposition,'' he said. The
agreement signed under President Carter calls for the United States
to turn control of the strategic canal to the Panamanian government
at the end of this century.
   He repeated previous assertions that the invasion ``will not be
of long-term consequence in a negative sense.''
   ``Obviously there are concerns, but this issue (of the invasion)
is behind us. The question that we focus on is where do we go from
here and how can we collectively work with this democratically
elected government and their pursuit of democracy.''
   Quayle later ate lunch in a sparsely peopled outdoor cafe before
heading to view the Panama Canal where he operated the controls
that enabled a ship to pass through the Qauyle visited the Mira
Flores Lock, a popular tourist viewing spot.
   From there he went to nearby Fort Clayton to watch the Super
Bowl with a roomful of troops and later headed out for a working
dinner with Endara.
   At a photo session with Quayle, Panamanian Vice President
Ricardo Arias Calderon told reporters that Panama's new government
looks to the United States for help in developing a ``modern police
force'' to replace the powerful Panamanian Defense Force that was
Noriega's strength.
   ``We will have no army, no air force, no navy,'' said Arias
Calderon, implying a domestic police force on the model of
neighboring Costa Rica, which has no army.
   Quayle arrived in Panama on Saturday night from Honduras and
meetings with the presidents of Costa Rica, Venezuela, Guatemala,
Honduras, and El Salvador as well as the prime minister of Belize.
He travels to Jamaica on Monday.
   Everywhere the vice president traveled in the Panamanian capital
he was guarded by U.S. soldiers in battle fatigues as well as the
normal secret service detail. His limousine had to negotiate barbed
wire blockades en route from the airport.
   The vice president on Sunday drove past boarded up stores and
shops that had been looted during the invasion. Onlookers watched
silently as his limousine passed, but when the entourage stopped
briefly at an outdoor market, a few hundred bystanders greeted him
with friendly applause.
   Quayle handed out silver ballpoint pens and shook hands in the
waterfront market where people clustered around him. He tried to
buy a bunch of bananas, pulling out his wallet, but the seller,
Augustin Espinosa, refused to let him pay.
   ``We are very appreciative of him,'' Espinosa said later.
   ``God bless you,'' another man told Quayle.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900128-0048 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-28-90 1849EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-PLO     01-28 0263</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-PLO,0270</SECOND>
<HEAD>Arafat Asks Moscow Not to Allow Soviet Jews to Israeli-Occupied
Lands</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CAIRO, Egypt (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   PLO chief Yasser Arafat has asked the Soviet
Union not to allow Soviet Jews to emigrate if they are going to
settle in the Israeli-occupied West Bank and Gaza Strip.
   The appeal came in a speech Arafat delivered Saturday night
before an Egyptian group that supports the 25-month-old Palestinian
uprising against Israeli occupation of the territories.
   A summary of the speech was published Sunday in the newspaper Al
Messa and was confirmed by Osama Sharab, the Palestine Liberation
Organization spokesman in Cairo, who described it as a ``an appeal
to the Soviet friend.''
   Arafat said he is not against the right of Soviet Jews to
emigrate to any country in the world but he objects to settling
them in the occupied territories.
   He was quoted as saying that flying Soviet Jews ``directly from
Moscow to Tel Aviv forces them to settle in the land of Palestine,
the home of their Palestinian Arab friends who are being driven out
of it.''
   Israeli Prime Minister Yitzhak Shamir said the Jewish state
needs the occupied lands to settle some of the estimated 300,000
Soviet Jews expected to immigrate in the next few years. The
statement drew criticism from the United States, Egypt and the PLO.
   Fewer than 100,000 of Israel's 1.7 million Jews have settled in
the territories, which Israel captured from Jordan and Egypt in the
1967 Middle East war.
   Arafat left Cairo on Sunday after concluding a two-day visit,
which included talks with President Hosni Mubarak.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900128-0049 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-28-90 1908EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-NorthernIreland 1stLd-Writethru a0672 01-28 0322</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Northern Ireland, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0672,0328</SECOND>
<HEAD>IRA Bomb in Londonderry Kills Youth, Injures 8</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: UPDATES thruout with IRA claiming responsibility, EDITS to
CONFORM; no pickup.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>LONDONDERRY, Northern Ireland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A bomb exploded in the
center of Londonderry on Sunday, killing a youth and injuring eight
other people during a march marking the 18th anniversary of Bloody
Sunday, police said.
   The Irish Republican Army claimed responsibility and said in a
statement it regretted the youth's death, which it called a ``freak
accident.''
   It said the blast had been intended to kill security patrols and
that the march itself had not been a target.
   The IRA has continually attacked government troops in its
campaign to rid the predominantly Protestant province of British
forces and unite it with the mainly Catholic republic of Ireland.
   The blast occurred while supporters of the campaign to drive the
British out of Northern Ireland marched in the largely Roman
Catholic Bogside and Creggan areas to remember Jan. 30, 1972, when
British troops shot and killed 14 people during a Catholic civil
rights march.
   A spokesman for the Royal Ulster Constabulary, the provincial
police, said the blast injured four policemen and a soldier as they
monitored the approaching crowd of several hundred marchers.
   Three civilians standing in the area were hurt by flying debris,
the spokesman said.
   The youth, 17, suffered head injuries when he was struck by
masonry falling from a wall where he waited with a crowd for the
parade to pass by, police said. He died in the hospital.
   The bomb had been placed beside a monument regularly used by the
security forces as a vantage point from which to monitor activities
in the Bogside.
   None of the participants in the parade was injured in the blast,
and the rally continued.
   All the injured were taken to the Altnagelvin hospital in
Londonderry for treatment for injuries, most of which police said
were not serious.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900128-0050 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-28-90 1909EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-CorriganFuneral     01-28 0192</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Corrigan Funeral,0199</SECOND>
<HEAD>Funeral Held for McAuliffe's Father</HEAD>
<DATELINE>FRAMINGHAM, Mass. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Teacher-astronaut Christa McAuliffe's
father, Edward C. Corrigan, was remembered in a funeral service
Sunday, four years to the day after his daughter died in the
Challenger explosion.
   ``It is ironic that the date that was the saddest day in Ed's
life now marks his entry into the eternal joys of heaven,'' said
the Rev. James Leary, of Bristol, Conn., a cousin of Corrigan.
   Corrigan, a retired accountant, died Thursday at age 67 after a
long battle with cancer.
   About 450 people attended Sunday's Roman Catholic funeral Mass
at St. Jeremiah's Church in this city 27 miles west of Boston, and
music was played on a carillon donated in McAuliffe's memory.
   On Jan. 28, 1986, McAulliffe, a schoolteacher from Concord,
N.H., and six other crew members died when the shuttle exploded
shortly after liftoff.
   Leary said Corrigan's faith and that of his wife, Grace, helped
carry them through the tragedy. ``They did not allow it to crush
their spirit,'' he said.
   Corrigan traveled around the globe to give lectures about his
daughter at school and scholarship dedications and memorial
fund-raisers.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900128-0051 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-28-90 1914EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Gallup-Spending     01-28 0288</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gallup-Spending,0297</SECOND>
<HEAD>Gallup Poll Shows Fewer Americans Plan Big Purchases</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: RETRANSMITTING a0710 to fix overline.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>PRINCETON, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The number of Americans planning to make
major purchases or spend money on recreation has declined from last
year, according to a poll released Sunday by the Gallup
Organization.
   Asked what they planned to do differently with their money in
1990 compared to last year, 6 percent of 1,000 heads of household
said they would shell out for big-ticket items or leisure
activities.
   Asked the same question last year, 12 percent said they would
spend money in those areas.
   The Princeton-based pollster conducted the poll in conjuction
with Bank Advertising News of North Palm Beach, Fla., to determine
Americans' anticipated financial behavior in 1990. The randomly
chosen respondents were interviewed by telephone last month.
   As in the previous two annual polls, the survey found that about
40 percent of Americans expected to have more money this year than
last, 45 percent expected to have about the same amount and 16
percent expected to have less.
   The survey also found that 27 percent of the respondents said
they would put more money into savings or certificates of deposit,
roughly the same number as gave that answer last year.
   Passbook savings accounts remain the most popular savings
vehicle, and were cited by 52 percent of those surveyed.
   ``Despite the talk of a sluggish economy, the poll illustrates
some confidence and even optimism at the grassroots level for the
economy in the coming year,'' said Bank Advertising News Editior
Frank J. Diekmann.
   ``There is also some evidence that more people are looking at
increasing their savings rather than purchasing goods,'' Diekmann
said.
   Gallup didn't give the poll's margin of error.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900128-0052 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-28-90 1919EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>d a AM-BRF--JacksonAvalanche 1stLd-Writethru   01-28 0206</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Jackson Avalanche, 1st Ld-Writethru,0208</SECOND>
<HEAD>Avalanche Closes Ski Area; No Injuries Reported</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: New throughout to DELETE number of dogs in 3rd graf, as exact
number unclear; ADD 2 grafs at end with explanation of
avalanche-prevention efforts.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>JACKSON, Wyo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An avalanche prompted officials to close
the Jackson Hole Ski Resort Sunday, but no one was injured,
officials said.
   The resort was closed for the day after the avalanche at 1:10
p.m. in an area called the Headwall, said Mike McCollister,
director of operations.
   About 50 searchers with tracking dogs sifted through the snow
for three hours and determined no one had been trapped, resort
officials said. The area was to reopen Monday.
   The avalanche began in a spot that is out of bounds for skiers,
he said. It reached an area that is in bounds, but isn't a
regularly marked ski trail.
   Ski patrols routinely set off explosions near potential
avalanche slopes early in the morning to clear dangerously loose
snow before the resort opens to the public.
   ``Sometimes avalanche control is not an exact science,''
McCollister said. ``You do the best you can and you work hard at
it, but sometimes this happens with a lot of snow, a lot of
buildup.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900128-0053 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-28-90 1954EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-MigrantProtest     01-28 0569</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Migrant Protest,0589</SECOND>
<HEAD>Demonstrators Picket Store Where Worker Was Allegedly Kidnapped
^By DAVID SEDENO</HEAD>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CARLSBAD, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   About 200 people marched around a store
Sunday, protesting the alleged abduction and assault on a farm
worker by the store's owners and demanding an end to violence
against migrant workers and Hispanics.
   ``These people make your food,'' one demonstrator said in a
heated exchange with people standing on the Country Store's porch.
``They pick the food that you eat, that they send to the market.''
   The store's owners _ Ricky Ryberg and his brother, Randy _ have
been charged in an attack on 26-year-old migrant worker Candido
Salas.
   Salas told authorities the Rybergs abducted him Jan. 3,
assaulted him, gagged and handcuffed him and placed a bag with the
words ``No Mas Aqui,'' which means ``no more here,'' over his head.
   The Rybergs were released without bail. They deny the charges,
said their attorney, Richard Borg.
   Attorney Marco Lopez filed a federal civil rights lawsuit
against the Rybergs last week, seeking an unspecified amount in
damages.
   Before Sunday's brief march Hispanic rights groups held a rally
in a field about 100 yards from the store in this coastal city
about 20 miles northwest of San Diego.
   ``We are here to speak with one voice,'' said political activist
Martin Eder. ``We want justice. We are not here just because of the
kidnapping. There have been other abuses that have been perpetrated
against farm workers.
   ``We are here because this incident is just the tip of the
racist iceberg,'' Eder said.
   About 50 mostly white store customers stood on the porch,
watching the rally.
   Borg said the Rybergs and other merchants in a small shopping
center have been hurt by migrant workers who stole from the store,
gathered on the parking lot, urinated on the property, sprayed
graffiti on the building and assaulted customers.
   He blamed the migrants' problems on federal and local officials,
and said the store was willing to contribute money to establish a
center where workers could go to find jobs.
   Borg said characterizing the situation as racial was
``irresponsible.''
   ``No business can withstand such activity by any group
irregardless of race and remain open to the public at large,'' the
attorney said.
   One customer, Reinette Thurman of Carlsbad, said farm workers
had stolen items from her house, and said she had seen several
thefts from the store.
   Another customer, Mike Haggerty, carried a sign that said, ``Put
American citizens to work and they will go home _ illegals.''
   ``Americans can't do this kind of work because they've run the
wages down so low,'' said Haggerty, an electrician.
   ``The businesses should just raise the wages a little bit,'' he
said, ``but a lot of businessmen are greedy and don't want to pay
the wages and then they end up paying for it in the long run.''
   Mexican President Carlos Salinas de Gortari, who has made a
commitment to keep abreast of his countrymen's well-being abroad,
inquired last week about the Salas case. Salinas has urged Mexican
consulate officials throughout the United States to monitor any
abuses against Mexican laborers and take appropriate action.
   The Salas incident is the latest of several involving alleged
attacks on Hispanics and illegal aliens in San Diego County,
including charges this week against two San Diego policemen accused
of kidnapping and robbing three undocumented workers in separate
incidents last August.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900128-0054 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-28-90 1958EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Dollar-Yen     01-28 0029</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Dollar-Yen,0030</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dollar Opens Down</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The dollar opened at 143.07 yen on the Tokyo
foreign exchange market Monday, down from Friday's close of 143.97
yen.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900128-0055 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-28-90 2008EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-FlightTroubles     01-28 0279</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Flight Troubles,0289</SECOND>
<HEAD>Smoke in Airliner Cabin Forces Evacuation</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TAMPA, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Passengers on Delta Air Lines Boeing 727 slid
down evacuation chutes onto an airport taxiway Sunday after smoke
was spotted in the cabin just before the flight was to take off for
a second time, officials said.
   Only minor injuries were reported in the mishap at Tampa
International Airport.
   One woman was taken to St. Joseph's Hospital complaining of back
pains from the emergency evacuation, officials said. Her name and
condition weren't immediately released.
   Delta's Flight 606 carrying 114 passengers and eight crew
members from Tampa to La Guardia Airport in New York was canceled
after the incident at about 1:30 p.m., said Sam Murphy, Delta
district marketing manager in Tampa.
   The source of the smoke wasn't immediately found, Murphy said.
   The plane, originally scheduled for takeoff at 11 a.m., was
taxiing when smoke was spotted coming out of some air-conditioning
ducts in the passenger cabin, Murphy said. The engines were shut
down and passengers evacuated by sliding down the emergency chutes,
he said.
   The plane had taxiied out 2{ hours earlier in an initial attempt
to leave but returned to the gate because of an oil warning light,
Murphy said.
   Maintenance workers fixed the problem and the plane took off
about half an hour later, he said.
   But then the plane turned around in flight and returned to Tampa
after the oil warning light for a different engine lit, Murphy said.
   After the plane landing safely, maintenance workers changed the
oil filters in the two other engines. The plane was about to take
off an hour later when the smoke was detected, Murphy said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900128-0056 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-28-90 2017EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-China-Rock     01-28 0623</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-China-Rock,0643</SECOND>
<HEAD>Crowd Bops to China's Only Rocker As Police Hover</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KATHY WILHELM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A roar went up as China's No. 1 and only rock 'n'
roll singer, Cui Jian, bounded on the stage Sunday night.
   The band grinded into heavy metal high gear. Colored strobes
blinked zanily. Fans waved their arms for Cui's first concert in
nearly a year, and the first rock event since the political
crackdown last June.
   It was about as crazy as a crowd in communist China can get, and
hundreds of police were there to make sure it didn't get any
crazier.
   Uniformed police occupied the entire front row in the Beijing
Workers' Gymnasium, sitting stolidly while dozens more uniformed
and plainclothes police patrolled the aisles and ordered stray fans
back to their seats.
   But that didn't stop the nearly 10,000 fans, most in their teens
and 20s, from jumping up and down in place and waving posters of
the 28-year-old singer in syncopation to his songs about love and
youthful alientation.
   ``I want to leave ... I want to die and start all over again,''
Cui sang, as much of the crowd joined in.
   ``In today's society, youths are looking for someone to speak
for them,'' said a college student who spent the entire two-hour
concert bopping, singing and stabbing the air with his fists.
``Look around, most everyone here is young. He speaks for our
dissatisfaction.''
   ``His songs are the songs of our generation. We all have
nothing,'' said another student, referring to Cui's first hit and
most famous song, ``I Have Nothing.''
   ``The words are great: `In the past I asked constantly, when
will you go with me? But you always laughed at me. I have
nothing,''' the student recited, breathless and a little hoarse
from cheering.
   Authorities remain suspicious of rock music, which they openly
condemned in the early 1980s as over-stimulating and too sexually
charged. Cui's career has been a rocky one, including long periods
when he was not allowed to perform.
   Police dragged him off stage at a 1988 concert, yelling at him
for ``provoking chaos,'' according to an official report.
   No such incident occurred Sunday, although police stopped a
group of students carrying signs from streaming into the aisle.
Their signs proclaimed, ``Cui Jian -- China's No. 1 Rock and
Roller,'' and identified them as the ``Economics Institute Fan
Club.''
   A plainclothes member of the People's Armed Police, China's
paramilitary force, stood by scowling.
   ``I don't like his music,'' he said. ``I don't like the way he
sings it. I like someone like Fei Xiang,'' a Taiwanese-American pop
singer who recently toured China.
   Veteran soldiers reportedly are offended by Cui's rock rendition
of the 1940s classic ``Nan Ni Wan,'' about Communist land reform,
and by his recent hit ``Rock 'n' Roll for the New Long March,''
which compares the search for self with the Red Army's epic march
during the revolutionary war.
   ``We're all opportunists,'' Cui shouted to the crowd before
launching into his song ``Opportunists,'' which expresses social
alienation. The Communist Party insists such feelings do not exist.
   Cui's songs are not overtly political but express the
restlessness and searching that repeatedly has sent China's youth
into the streets in protest, most recently last spring when the
army was called in to crush the pro-democracy movement.
   Police closed in quickly at the concert's end, shooing fans out.
The gymnasium was cleared in 10 minutes flat.
   One youth who knew the words to all Cui's songs said he would be
back Monday for Cui's second of three performances, despite the
high $4.25 ticket price _ several days salary for the average
Beijing worker.
   ``He's the pride of the Chinese people,'' the fan said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900128-0057 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-28-90 2039EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-EastGermany 3rdLd-Writethru a0719 01-28 0716</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-East Germany, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0719,0735</SECOND>
<HEAD>Government, Opposition Announce Coalition, Elections Moved To
March 18</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS one graf for 4th pvs to CORRECT that move is fourth
Cabinet shake-up but not fourth involving Modrow.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By CAROL J. WILLIAMS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>EAST BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   East Germany's Communist-led government and
opposition forces agreed late Sunday to move the nation's first
free elections up to March 18 and to govern by coalition until then.
   Communist Premier Hans Modrow and the more than 40 opposition
representatives announced the new election date _ moving ahead by
nearly two months the balloting that had been planned for May 6.
   The decisions were part of a ``common responsibility to
strengthen democracy in East Germany,'' Modrow said.
   The agreement, which includes the fourth restructuring of the
Cabinet in as many months, acknowledged the need to quickly seat a
government that has the trust and confidence of the populace.
   A new Cabinet _ the first to include representatives from
emerging reform groups _ will be submitted by Wednesday to
Parliament, said Martin Ziegler, a Lutheran Church official.
   The new leadership will include one member from each of the nine
opposition groups represented at weekly talks with government,
although the ministers will be named without portfolio, Ziegler
said.
   Wolfgang Schnur of the Democratic Awakening movement said the
Cabinet members will decide later how to distribute ministerial
responsibilities.
   The planned Cabinet changes follow an announcement three days
ago that Christian Democratic Union was pulling out its three
ministers. But following Sunday's agreement, the Union _ one of
four traditionally Communist-allied parties _ was expected to take
part in the new leadership, Schnur said.
   Modrow also has been repeatedly challenged by the pro-democracy
opposition groups, which contend he has no mandate to govern
because he and his 27-member Communist-dominated Cabinet were
seated by a Parliament that was not democratically elected.
   More than a dozen small political parties are vying for public
support in this nation of 16 million, which is troubled by economic
disaster and a continuing exodus of its most promising workers.
   The flight westward, which drained the nation of more than
340,000 people last year, recently swelled to about 2,500
departures daily.
   Many opposition parties held weekend congresses to chart
strategy for the elections, which will be the country's first free
competitive vote.
   But there was little indication the fractious reform forces
would be able to band together to challenge the still-dominant
Communists.
   New Forum, the largest of the pro-democracy groups to emerge
from last fall's peaceful revolution, previously claimed 200,000
members.
   But a moderate faction split from the movement to form a new
party over the weekend, and the core group collapsed into divisive
squabbling Sunday at its convention in East Berlin.
   The splinter group named itself the German Forum Party and spoke
out at its meeting in Karl-Marx-Stadt for a complete break with
socialism. It claimed to have 100,000 members, suggesting that as
many as half of New Forum's supporters had defected.
   The New Forum delegates who met in East Berlin reiterated their
aim of combining socialist ideology with some free enterprise.
   Meanwhile, the leader of the Christian Democratic Union
announced that he was prepared to seek an election coalition with
Democratic Awakening and the German Social Union, two opposition
groups that support market-oriented reforms and closer ties with
West Germany.
   Also Sunday, a West German newspaper reported that East
Germany's former hard-line leader, Erich Honecker, will be arrested
Monday upon his release from a hospital.
   Doctors have determined that Honecker, 77, is too ill to be held
in custody following surgery for kidney cancer and he will be sent
to a prison hospital instead of jail, Bild newspaper said.
   The East German chief prosecutor's office refused to comment on
the report, the state news agency ADN said.
   Honecker led East Germany for 18 years until his ouster Oct. 18.
Earlier this month, prosecutors said he would be charged with
treason as well as corruption in connection with his leadership.
   Several members of the disgraced leadership have been arrested
since the new government took office.
   Bild also said Honecker's wife, Margot, who served as education
minister in his ousted leadership, had been thrown out of a luxury
compound for top officials and is living with their daughter in
East Berlin.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900128-0058 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-28-90 2105EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-RebelHutterites 1stLd-Writethru a0676 01-28 0817</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Rebel Hutterites, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0676,0835</SECOND>
<HEAD>Nation's Oldest Hutterite Colony Wracked by Dispute</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 7th graf, `I bet...1536', to restore dropped first
reference to James Wainscoat.
^LaserPhoto SI1</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By MELISSA JORDAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TABOR, S.D. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Trouble in a pacifist religious sect has
landed several dissidents in jail for visiting a cemetery against a
court order and led the group's leader to stage a hunger strike
that lasted 47 days.
   The rebels have been ousted from Bon Homme Colony, believed to
be the oldest Hutterite settlement in America, and moved into a
house here, five miles from their former home.
   The dissidents, led by a former Californian who said he spent
years on a personal quest for a simplier way of life, charge that
colony elders' quest for profit has corrupted their spiritual
leadership.
   But Hutterite leaders say the rebels have been brainwashed by a
power-hungry outsider. They say the colony provides for its people
from cradle to the grave, and deny that its thriving farm
enterprise reflects materialism.
   ``We feel everything should be spiritual,'' explains John K.
Wipf, pastor of the Maxwell Colony, another Hutterite settlment
near the Bon Homme Colony. ``But we also have to work for a
living.''
   The dissidents say a communal religious enclave shouldn't be run
like a business, and charge that colony leaders have too much power.
   ``I bet Jakob Hutter would turn over in his grave if he could
see how they are today,'' says James Wainscoat, referring to the
sect's namesake, who was burned at the stake in 1536.
   The Hutterian Brethren originated in what was once Moravia, part
of present-day Czechoslovakia, in 1528. Members emigrated to the
United States after centuries of persecution in Eastern Europe and
Russia.
   About 35,000 Hutterites live in North America, two-thirds in
Canada. South Dakota has the largest Hutterite population of any
state.
   Hutterites shun contact with the outside world and forbid
television, radio and personal luxuries. But they embrace modern
farm technology and conveniences that benefit the entire colony,
such as labor-saving kitchen and laundry equipment. That is what
the dissidents are fighting.
   At present, Wainscoat is recuperating from his hunger strike at
the dissidents' rented home in Tabor. He ended the strike earlier
this month after authorities released two of the five dissidents
held on the contempt of court charges.
   He sits in a chair surrounded by young boys and girls and women
holding babies. They listen intently, nod in agreement with his
words and talk among themselves in a German dialect. A calico cat
and tiny white dog frolic at Wainscoat's feet, and the pungent
aroma of the noontime meal fills the air.
   The dissidents split from the colony last year after elders gave
them an ultimatum: choose to follow colony rules or follow
Wainscoat.
   Wainscoat, 48, was denied membership nearly a decade earlier for
refusing to obey colony rules. He returned in 1987 after an absence
of several years and renewed a friendship with Samuel Wurtz, son of
a former head pastor who died in 1952. It is his grave they have
been arrested for visiting.
   Wurtz and about 20 members of his extended family followed
Wainscoat. The dissidents, along with a handful of defectors from
other colonies, call themselves the Ark of the New Covenant.
   Ark members claim a right to tend the grave. The colony says it
will allow relatives to visit if they obtain permission, but it
will not tolerate Wainscoat. Though it's his father's grave, Wurtz
didn't ask permission to visit without Wainscoat.
   The courts granted the colony an injunction barring Ark members
from the cemetery. Three dissidents, including Samuel Wurtz, have
been jailed since early October on contempt of court charges for
violating the order. Wainscoat will serve time for trespassing when
his health improves.
   John Kabeiseman, an attorney for the colony, said the rebels
latched onto the cemetery issue because it arouses public sympathy.
He said the real motive is to undermine authority.
   ``They're doing it in defiance of the leadership of the
Hutterite community,'' he said.
   Samuel Wurtz said in an interview at the jail that the current
leaders have no right to authority because their moral leadership
is lacking.
   ``It's preached, but it's not lived,'' he said. ``It's
hypocrisy. It's a lie.''
   Wurtz said he has a calling to continue his father's mission by
leading the approximately 100 people of Bon Homme Colony. But he
concedes that current head pastor Jacob Waldner, 82, is not likely
to welcome his bid for leadership.
   Norbert Mach, mayor of this town of 340, said opinion is split.
Some people resent the dissidents for continuing to trespass at the
cemetery _ leaving taxpayers with the bill public defender lawyer
fees and jail costs. But others are sympathetic to the dissidents,
he said.
   ``It's just about like what's going on in Eastern Europe,'' he
said. ``They want to be more like citizens.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900128-0059 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-28-90 2105EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BlackthornCeremony     01-28 0475</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Blackthorn Ceremony,0488</SECOND>
<HEAD>Memorial Held to Mark Anniversary of Blackthorn Disaster</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PAT LEISNER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ST. PETERSBURG, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Coast Guard remembered its own
with prayers and flowers Sunday to mark the 10th anniversary of the
loss of the buoy tender Blackthorn and 23 crew members.
   Blackthorn survivor Quartermaster Jeffrey Huse joined nearly 400
people for a tribute to the men who drowned in the worst peacetime
disaster in the 200-year history of the Coast Guard.
   ``We will never forget,'' the Coast Guard Commandant, Adm. Paul
A. Yost, told the families of the victims who attended the ceremony.
   ``They were our husbands, fathers, sons and brothers. They were
shipmates and friends. ... We honor them, not because they died but
because they lived and touched us and enriched us,'' Yost said.
   The hour-long tribute was held at Blackthorn Memorial Park in
front of an 8-foot granite memorial inscribed with the names of the
sailors who went down with their ship. The park is on the shore of
Tampa Bay, just several hundred yards from where the tragedy
occurred on Jan. 28, 1980.
   On a calm, moonlit night, the 180-foot buoy tender collided
nearly head-on with the oil tanker Capricorn, three times its size
and 30 times its weight.
   The tanker's 7-ton anchor snagged the hull of the smaller ship.
The Blackthorn capsized and sank before almost half of its
50-member crew had time to abandon ship.
   ``I live it all the time,'' said Huse, who stayed in the Coast
Guard. He is now a quartermaster with a search and rescue unit in
New Orleans.
   ``I forced myself to go back to sea,'' said Huse, who spent four
years on a ship after the Blackthorn disaster.
   ``I knew I had to trust my fellow crewmen and be able to sleep
when others were on watch. I did. It helped,'' he said.
   Huse, then a petty officer, was in the Blackthorn's wheelhouse
and sounded the mayday. He was washed off the bridge after the
collision and was nearly taken down with the sinking ship.
   Flowers were placed at the foot of the monument. A Coast Guard
C-130 and a helicopter flew in aerial salute above the seas calm
and shimmering under the bright Florida sun.
   ``The admiral of the heavens called our shipmates to sail with
him eternally in the calm seas,'' said Cmdr. Kevin J. Eldridge of
the buoy tender Buttonwood, a sister ship that made the trip from
New Orleans for the ceremony.
   ``We are here to honor and cherish the memories of these
shipmates,'' Eldridge said. ``But we do not mourn for them, for
they have found safe anchorage in the harbor of eternal peace.''
   A few years after the disaster, the Blackthorn was sunk 20 miles
out in the Gulf of Mexico as part of an artificial reef.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900128-0060 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-28-90 2123EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Poland 4thLd-Writethru   01-28 0666</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Poland, 4th Ld-Writethru,a0718,0689</SECOND>
<HEAD>Communists Dissolve Party; Declare New Social Democratic Party</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: UPDATES thruout with Communist Party dissolved, other
details; no pickup.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By JOHN DANISZEWSKI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WARSAW, Poland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Communists dissolved their 41-year-old
party early Monday, hours after forming a new one they hope will
give them a future in Poland's new parliamentary democracy.
   The new party, the Social Democracy of the Republic of Poland,
was created Sunday night at a Communist Party congress called to
bury the old one.
   But a radical reformer backed by Solidarity leader Lech Walesa
said the new party did not represent authentic change and split off
with supporters to form another party free of old-style Communists.
   The delegates who remained voted 1,228-32 to dismantle the
Communist Party and then stood to sing the ``Internationale,'' the
anthem of socialism worldwide. They then bowed their heads in
silence as three men carried the red Communist Party flag from the
hall.
   The resolution dissolving the party said the delegates
recognized ``the impossibility ... of recovering social
confidence'' under the Communist banner.
   Although delegates rose to praise the old party's history, the
resolution said the Communists take responsibility for the crimes
of the Stalinist period and for Poland's current economic chaos.
   Poland is the second East bloc country to dissolve its Communist
Party. Hungary's Communists dissolved their party in October and
reconstituted themselves as a party committed to democracy.
   The Communists ruled Poland before losing parliamentary
elections and ceding power to a Solidarity-led government in August.
   Under the change, the Communists will turn over their buildings,
businesses and other property to the new party. The Solidarity-led
government is reviewing the Communist holdings to determine if they
should be returned to the national treasury.
   The new party's platform says: ``We want Poland to be a
fatherland of free, equal people living in solidarity, a state of
social justice. We link her future to democratic socialism.''
   Before the vote to create a new party, however, reformer Tadeusz
Fiszbach took the floor to denounce ``artificial unity.''
   ``We will be unable to explain to society how we were
transformed into social democrats out of communists overnight,''
said Fiszbach, who heads a faction of about 200 delegates.
   ``If we don't make accounts for the past 45 years, we will be
committing suicide together,'' he said.
   ``We also must admit that the tragedy of martial law did not
have to happen,'' Fiszbach said, referring to the Communist
crackdown that suppressd the Solidarity opposition movement until
it was legalized again last year.
   He then stormed out of the congress and formed a breakaway
party, the Social-Democratic Union.
   Fiszbach said his party would likely field candidates in
municipal elections in June.
   Outgoing party chief Mieczyslaw F. Rakowski had hoped to create
a single new leftist party that would abandon communist ideology
and thereby win public support.
   Aleksander Kwasniewski, who appeared to be Rakowski's heir
apparent, said the former communists should remain as unified as
possible. But he added: ``This does not mean unity at all costs.''
   ``Two or three parties could emerge,'' but even they should
cooperate, he said.
   The new party's platform endorses a market-driven economy but
rejects exclusive private ownership and says unemployment cannot be
``treated as a permanent element of the ecomomic mechanism. We
assess the right to work as a natural right of man.''
   Outside the hall where the 1,600 delegates met, about 50
protesters chanted ``Communists must go!'' as police looked on.
   Late Saturday, more than 500 demonstrators threw stones and
bottles at riot police in clashes that lasted several hours.
   The Polish Communists relinquished power to Solidarity _ making
it the East bloc's first government led by non-Communists _ in
September after the party was trounced in June elections.
   The government of Prime Minister Tadeusz Mazowiecki since has
plunged into radical reforms to make Poland a capitalist democracy.
   The changes in Poland were followed in swift order by revolts
against hard-line Communist regimes in Czechoslovakia, East
Germany, Bulgaria, Hungary, and Romania.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900128-0061 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-28-90 2140EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Jetliner-Residents     01-28 0505</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Jetliner-Residents,0525</SECOND>
<HEAD>Community Still Stunned After Jetliner Crash</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Jetliner Crash</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LISA GENASCI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>COVE NECK, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Julia Staniszewski says she hadn't seen
some of her neighbors in this wooded suburb for at least a year.
But when Avianca Flight 52 crashed thunderously into a nearby
hillside, they came running.
   ``The radio went off and everything went dark but there was
absolute silence,'' the 85-year-old longtime resident said Sunday,
recalling, as did others, the eerie absence of engine noise before
the crash. ``I stayed in bed until neighbors came looking for me 15
minutes later to check that I was OK.''
   The Boeing 707 clipped the tall oaks near Mrs. Staniszewski's
house before breaking into pieces and coming to rest in a mess of
twisted steel, killing 73 people aboard the craft and injuring 86.
   Three days later, residents of this affluent community of about
340 people 35 miles east of New York City say the enormity of the
tragedy is just beginning to hit home.
   ``We were on automatic pilot until last night,'' said Richard
Hassanein, whose home sits two houses from the wreckage. ``We
couldn't think about ourselves.''
   Hassanein's wife, Adrienne, said she still feels numbed. Mrs.
Hassanein was one of the first to reach the scene after the
red-and-orange jet crashed.
   ``It sounded and felt like an earthquake,'' she said. ``The
scene was terrible. It was almost surreal. You don't forget
something like that.''
   The plane tore part of the rear deck off a house, but damaged no
other homes on Long Island's North Shore. Even so, the community
will never fully recover from the emotional impact, Mrs. Hassanein
said.
   On Sunday, residents dressed in running gear, many with dogs in
tow, looked on in disbelief as investigators dug for clues.
   Most suitcases and other personal effects were hauled away
Saturday, but the odd shoe or piece of clothing remained amid
broken seats, inflated life vests, oxygen masks and bits of
fuselage.
   Police guarding the wreckage looked around in dismay,
occasionally picking up an item of clothing or passport, then
silently letting it fall.
   ``I don't want to be here,'' one officer said. ``No one does.''
   The quiet search recalled the strange silence that preceded
Thursday's crash. All four engines stopped before the plane went
down, indicating it may have run out of fuel.
   ``I was paying bills, watching television and listening to the
wind, when I heard a thud. I thought lightning had struck,'' said
Marjorie Isaksen, whose home sits above the crash site.
   Mrs. Isaksen said she heard about the tragedy about 15 minutes
later when a friend phoned to check on her.
   ``My reaction was utter disbelief,'' she said.
   ``I didn't really realize what had happened until I knelt beside
an injured man lying on a stretcher and lay my coat over him,''
Mrs. Isaksen said. ``His face was swollen and bloody. I cried when
I was alone with him.''
   Mrs. Isaksen said, however, that the tragedy still hasn't ``set
into my brain.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900128-0062 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-28-90 2239EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Israel     01-28 0400</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel,0413</SECOND>
<HEAD>38 Palestinian Homes Demolished or Sealed in January</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The army demolished or sealed 38 houses
belonging to Palestinans in January, the second-highest monthly
total since the uprising began in December 1987, a human rights
group said Sunday.
   At least six Palestinians were wounded by gunfire during
stone-throwing clashes Sunday with soldiers in the Gaza Strip,
hospital officials said.
   The army said it was checking the reports.
   In east Jerusalem, three extremists from the anti-Arab Kach
party were briefly detained Sunday outside the home of Faisal
Husseini, a pro-PLO Palestinian activist.
   The Israel Information Center for Human Rights in the Occupied
Territories said the number of homes destroyed or sealed indicates
``a substantial increase'' in the use of such measures by
authorities.
   The group, founded by liberal Israeli politicians and academics,
said 20 homes were destroyed and 18 sealed in the West Bank and
Gaza Strip this month.
   The group said 432 houses have been destroyed or blocked off
since the uprising began in December 1987. The highest monthly
figure was 42 demolished or sealed in June 1989.
   The army said such punishment deters furthur unrest. The United
States and human rights groups have criticized it as collective
punishment.
   Police detained the three activists of the right-wing Kach Party
after they protested in front of Husseini's home.
   ``They went too far this time,'' said police spokesman Uzi
Sandori. ``We believed they planned to cause problems and disrupt
the public order.''
   Sandori said the activists were brought before a court to be
taken into custody, but the judge released them on condition they
stay at least 300 feet from Husseini's house and refrain from
harassing him in any way.
   One of the activists, Noam Federman, spat in Husseini's face as
the Palestinian activist was ordered detained Jan. 19. Husseini was
released on bond three days later pending formal charges.
   Federman later turned himself in to police, but was released
because no charges were filed against him.
   Also Sunday, the editor of the liberal weekly newspaper Kol
Ha'Ir said its office was ransacked. Doron Galezer said the
newspaper and some staff had been threatened after publishing an
article about anti-Arab extremists.
   Two dailies, Maariv and Yediot Ahronot, received bomb threats
two weeks ago from callers who said they belonged to the Sicarite
group, an extremist group that has claimed a series of arson
attacks and bomb threats.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900128-0063 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-28-90 2236EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-SuperBowl-Newspage     01-28 0265</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Super Bowl-Newspage,0277</SECOND>
<HEAD>San Francisco Routs Broncos in Super Bowl</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW ORLEANS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The San Francisco 49ers routed the Denver
Broncos 55-10 Sunday in the most lopsided Super Bowl victory ever.
   The 49ers' win in the 24th Super Bowl made them the first repeat
NFL champion in a decade and tied the Pittsburgh Steelers as a
pinnacle of Super Bowl perfection with four wins in four tries.
   San Francisco won the National Football League championship game
in 1989, 1985 and 1982. The Broncos, on the other hand, lost the
last four Super Bowl games they have played.
   San Francisco quarterback Joe Montana made five touchdown
passes, three to Jerry Rice, breaking a Super Bowl record for
touchdown passes on a day on which he also set a record with 13
straight pass completions.
   He also set five Super Bowl career records, including his third
Super Bowl Most Valuable Player award and San Francisco's point
total was the most ever. Montana left the game with nearly 11
minutes to play.
   In four Super Bowls, he has thrown 11 touchdowns and no
interceptions.
   For Denver quarterback John Elway, it was a day of futility,
ending with his third Super Bowl defeat. He missed eight of his
first 10 passes and was intercepted twice and fumbled once.
   By halftime the score was 27-3. With their third loss in four
years, the Broncos have now been outscored 136-40.
   San Francisco was boringly perfect, doing more than even the
experts who made them favorites by nearly two touchdowns after a
14-2 season and a waltz through the playoffs.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900128-0064 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-28-90 2239EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Lebanon     01-28 0340</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lebanon,0352</SECOND>
<HEAD>Christian, Moslems Exchange Tank Fire</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RIMA SALAMEH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BEIRUT, Lebanon (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Christian army units and Moslem militias
blasted each other with tank fire in Beirut Sunday, but a
cease-fire held between rival Shiite Moslem militias in southern
Lebanon.
   The sound of exploding shells mixed with thunderclaps of a
rainstorm as the fighting broke out overnight along the central
sector of the three-mile Green Line that divides the capital.
   Police said no casualties were reported from the three-hour
clash, which violated a cease-fire mediated by the Arab League in
September to halt the latest round of fighting in Lebanon's
14-year-old civil war.
   At least four people were killed and 12 wounded by police count
in similar violations along the Green Line in the first two weeks
of 1990.
   The Sept. 22 truce halted six months of shelling duels between
Christian troops of maverick Gen. Michel Aoun and the Syrian army
in which police said 929 people were killed and 2,744 wounded.
   The new hostilities came as President Elias Hrawi's government
prepared to ban militias and combat terrorism in west Beirut to
encourage foreign diplomats to return to the city's Moslem sector.
   The fighting reflected the deepening political crisis resulting
from Aoun's defiance of Hrawi's Syrian-backed government.
   Hrawi, a Maronite Catholic, was elected president by Parliament
Nov. 24. He promptly fired Aoun, also a Maronite, as army commander
and interim prime minister.
   But Aoun has held out in the Christian enclave northeast of
Beirut, refusing to hand over the presidential palace to Hrawi.
   In southern Lebanon, the mainstream Shiite Moslem Amal militia
said in a statement its forces observed a cease-fire with the rival
pro-Iranian Hezbollah, or Party of God, that began Saturday.
   Hezbollah's press office also said its militiamen were observing
the cease-fire.
   At least 98 people were killed and 286 wounded in the latest
round of Amal-Hezbollah clashes that broke out Dec. 23.
   The two factions have been fighting since May 1987 for control
of the 1.2 million Shiites, the country's largest sect.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900128-0065 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-28-90 2352EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a w PM-WalterMears     01-28 0862</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Walter Mears,0882</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv 30</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release PMs Tues Jan 30 and Thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>Bush's `Trust Factor' Policy on China Needs Boost From Beijing</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP News Analysis</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By WALTER R. MEARS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Special Correspondent</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush's ``trust me'' policy on China
could use an assist from the hard-line government in Beijing, and
soon. The White House needs some told-you-so evidence that
conciliatory gestures are serving to ease repression.
   That will take more than the steps the administration cited in
putting together the 37 Republican senators who voted to sustain
Bush's veto of a bill extending the visas of Chinese students in
the United States.
   ``I think there is a trust factor that hopefully will result in
changes that are satisfactory to the American people and to me _ a
trust factor in the administration,'' the president said. ``And I
hope that I can use that, having won this now, to further the kinds
of things that I think will help move China forward.''
   His political hand, and the trust he seeks at home, both would
be strengthened by a clear and convincing reciprocal move on the
part of the Chinese government.
   While Bush claimed a mandate for his handling of China policy,
that is hard to read into roll calls in which only 25 House members
sided with him, while the Senate enforced his veto with three votes
to spare.
   Minorities are enough to fend off the opposition on a foreign
policy issue, but sustaining vetoes will not sustain a policy for
long.
   Symbolism and politics figured heavily in the debate, the
lobbying, and the surprise turnaround on the veto the Senate upheld
on Thursday.
   Bush rendered the bill largely symbolic by accompanying his Nov.
30 veto with an executive order to do the same thing. He could have
ended it there, with a pocket veto that would not have been subject
to override votes. Instead, given political sensitivities, he sent
it back for action when Congress reconvened.
   The veto was sustained after GOP leaders called the vote an
election-year test of Republican loyalty. Sen. Bob Dole of Kansas,
the Republican leader, called it the first installment of the 1990
campaign, saying Democrats were trying to force GOP senators into a
politically difficult vote. It was that, and eight Republicans
voted against Bush.
   Bush said he also won on the strength of his argument against
doing by law what he ordered done anyhow, in a policy realm that
properly belongs to the president. He said that if the veto were
overridden, the Chinese would retaliate by canceling all student
exchanges.
   His executive order and personal pledge guarantee at least what
the bill did, and possibly more, in extending the visas of about
32,000 Chinese students.
   ``No student, as long as I'm president, will be sent back
against his or her will,'' he promised. He said that guarantee
holds good even if the Chinese government relents in its repression
of democratic dissent, the crackdown that led to the massacre in
Tiananmen Square last June and to Bush's limited sanctions against
Beijing.
   Democrats said the sanctions weren't tough enough to begin with,
and the administration has been gradually easing them for months.
One was a bar against high-level exchanges of government officials,
and within two weeks of it, the president secretly sent two of his
top aides to Beijing. When word of that leaked out months later,
Bush said he'd never forbidden official contacts, only exchange
visits.
   That refuge in the fine print hasn't done much for the
administration's credibility on the China sanctions.
   Bush, who once served as U.S. envoy to Beijing, insists that
harsh sanctions, including the visa bill, would be
counterproductive, driving China toward isolation, choking off
exchanges and worsening the situation inside the country.
   While the students aren't going home either way, Bush said
Beijing found the bill more offensive than his order, even though
officials don't like it either. The bill, he said, would have
seemed to them ``a further public slap at a time when they feel
some steps have been taken that are positive.''
   He claims headway for human rights as a result of his policy,
citing the lifting of martial law on Jan. 10; the release of 573
jailed dissenters; an end to harassment at the U.S. Embassy, where
a leading Chinese dissident remains in refuge; continued student
exchanges and Peace Corps missions.
   But Bush critics in both parties insist that those and other
steps are tokens, not nearly enough to warrant the easing of
American sanctions against a government that turned guns on its
people, executed demonstrators and jailed uncounted thousands of
dissenters.
   Bush and the Republicans haven't heard the end of the matter.
There are likely to be new sanction proposals in Congress. There is
certain to be more rhetoric from the Democrats who have accused the
president of kowtowing to China and sacrificing his own credibility.
   With a campaign coming, this is an issue the Democrats want to
keep on the agenda.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Walter R. Mears, vice president and columnist
for The Associated Press, has reported on Washington and national
politics for more than 26 years.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900128-0066 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-28-90 1359EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-OPEC-Earnings Bjt   01-28 0579</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-OPEC-Earnings, Bjt,0601</SECOND>
<HEAD>OPEC Oil Earnings Soar in 1989 to Highest Level Since 1985</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SALLY JACOBSEN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BRUSSELS, Belgium (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Lifted by higher prices and stronger
production, the oil revenues of the OPEC nations soared last year
to their highest level since 1985, industry analysts say.
   Pierre Terzian, editor of the Paris-based newsletter
Petrostrategies, said the earnings surge for the Organization of
Petroleum Exporting Countries was ``a big pleasant surprise. ...
Nobody expected it would be as high as this.''
   ``They should have done quite comfortably,'' said Paul McDonald,
a London-based oil consultant.
   Terzian estimated the cartel's 13 nations earned a total of
$110.6 billion last year from export sales of their crude, up more
than a third from his calculation of 1988 revenues at $80.1 billion.
   Peter Bogin, assistant director for oil markets at Cambridge
Energy Research Associates in Paris, figured the exports, including
natural gas liquids and related products, at $111.5 billion in 1989.
   Last year's showing was the best since 1985 when the producing
nations, which depend heavily on sales of their oil to foreign
customers, earned $127.2 billion.
   OPEC's revenues swung wildly in the 1980s, reflecting the sharp
rise and fall of crude prices.
   The revolution in Iran in 1979 resulted in a steep drop in
production by that key supplying nation. World oil prices spun
above $40 a barrel.
   In the following years, a production free-for-all sent prices
plummeting. Futures prices for West Texas Intermediate, the
benchmark American crude, fell to $10.42 a barrel on March 31,
1986, less than half of what it sells for now.
   OPEC's oil earnings, according to official figures, registered a
record $284.5 billion in 1980 but slumped to a decade-low $77.3
billion in 1986.
   The cartel earned $86.4 billion in 1988 from exports, including
sales of some petroleum products. The official tally for 1989 won't
be released until later in the year.
   Analysts attributed last year's big gains to rising prices and
output, ``a nice combination,'' as McDonald put it.
   The average price of a basket of seven crudes monitored by OPEC
was $17.31 a barrel last year, up about $3 from 1988. The cartel's
official target is $18.
   Bogin estimated the cartel's average production was 21.7 million
barrels a day last year vs. 19.7 million barrels in 1988. He said
demand for OPEC's oil was strong, particularly from robust
economies in the Far East.
   Looking ahead, he predicted the average price of OPEC's basket
of crudes would run in the range of $16 to $18 a barrel this year.
Production would likely average 23 million barrels a day, he said.
   As a result, he said, the cartel's 1990 earnings could run $10
billion to $20 billion above last year's pace.
   Terzian estimated that earnings for Kuwait, a big cheater on its
OPEC-imposed production ceiling, skyrocketed 72 percent to $9.4
billion last year. Its output rose 43 percent.
   Iran's revenues shot up 61.6 percent to top $12 billion Terzian
reckoned.
   ``In value terms, the increase in Iranian oil revenues was huge:
$4.6 billion,'' he wrote in his newsletter. ``This value increase
was bettered by only Saudi Arabia, which lifted its 1989 oil
revenues by $5.4 billion.''
   Saudi Arabia, the world's No. 1 crude exporter, rang up export
sales last year of $25.7 billion, by Terzian's calculations. Bogin
tallied Saudi exports at $24 billion.
   In 1988, OPEC pegged the kingdom's export earnings at $20.5
billion. In 1981, they reached a high of $116.2 billion.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900128-0067 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-28-90 1401EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-CreditMarkets Bjt   01-28 0703</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Credit Markets, Bjt,0724</SECOND>
<HEAD>Worries About Japanese Appetite for Treasury Issues Weighs On Bond
Prices</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SKIP WOLLENBERG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Japanese have gotten slammed by some
Americans for their highly visible investments in U.S. corporations
and business properties ranging from Columbia Pictures to
Rockefeller Center.
   But this past week's slump in bond prices suggests that the U.S.
government and those holding its debt should put out the welcome
mat for Japanese investors in Treasury securities.
   Over the past few years, the Japanese have been steady and
substantial customers at the quarterly securities sales where the
government has borrowed heavily to finance its expanding debt.
   Market watchers estimate the Japanese typically buy 25 percent
to 35 percent of new Treasury issues maturing in 10 to 30 years.
   As a result, some analysts argue, the government has been able
to peddle its securities at lower rates of interest than it would
have to pay otherwise.
   But worries about whether Japanese investors will be big buyers
of the Treasury's expected $30 billion auction of new securities
next month have weighed heavily on bond prices.
   Those concerns have stemmed from a recent rise in Japanese
interest rates that has narrowed the difference in yields available
on Japanese securities relative to U.S. notes and bonds.
   William Griggs, a partner with the investment firm Griggs &amp;
Santow Inc., said 10-year Japanese notes, for example, were
yielding about 1.35 percentage points below the yields on 10-year
Treasury notes earlier this month, compared with a 2 percentage
point difference at the start of the year.
   While the difference in yields has since widened toward 2
percentage points once again in more recent days, William V.
Sullivan Jr. of Dean Witter Reynolds said the more typical yield
spread has been 2.5 to 3 percentage points.
   The fear among U.S. bondholders is that some Japanese investors
will find the current yields in Japan rewarding enough that they
will decide against taking the extra risks involved in converting
yen to dollars and buying Treasury issues.
   That could drive U.S. rates higher, depressing the value of
bonds already trading in the market.
   The realities of what can happen when foreign investors sit out
a bond auction were illustrated this past Tuesday when the
Resolution Funding Corp. had to pay higher rates than many market
professionals had anticipated to find buyers for its $5 billion
issue of 40-year thrift bailout bonds.
   The Japanese had not been expected to bid on the bonds, which
carry maturities of 10 years later than the Treasury's longest
security and are expected to be far less readily salable than
Treasury issues.
   ``We didn't expect the Japanese to be there, and they weren't,''
said Robert Brusca, economist for Nikko Securities International in
New York.
   He said no conclusions should be drawn from the absence of the
Japanese from the 40-year auction relative to what may happen at
the Treasury auctions expected to be conducted in early February.
   But some traders said the auction illustrated nonetheless that
interest rates must often go higher than expected when the pool of
bidders is smaller.
   Prices of long bonds tumbled in the wake of the 40-year auction,
and got another jolt on Thursday that reflected traders'
sensitivity to the importance of foreign investment in the U.S.
bond market.
   Bond prices careened lower after some press reports suggested
Federal Reserve Chairman Alan Greenspan had indicated he might
consider the idea of reinstating a withholding tax on investment
income earned here by foreigners. The Federal Reserve later said
Greenspan did not favor such action.
   But the market failed to revive anyway, and prices lost more
ground Friday in the wake of a stronger-than-expected report on
durable goods orders in December.
   By midafternoon Friday, prices of 30-year Treasury bonds were
down more than $25 for every $1,000 in face value for the week.
Their yield had risen to 8.54 percent from 8.26 percent at the end
of the previous Friday.
   Griggs suspected yields were getting high enough that Japanese
interest in the upcoming auctions will be strong.
   But Sullivan said it is still too early to tell. ``We have a a
long way to go until we bid these securities,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900128-0068 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-28-90 1419EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-FarEast-China Bjt   01-28 0810</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Far East-China, Bjt,0838</SECOND>
<HEAD>China's Troubles Jolt Other Far East Economies</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LARRY THORSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   China's financial woes and political upheavals
continues to dampen hopes of revived trade with the troubled giant
throughout Asia.
   Businessmen in the region's booming countries are hoping for a
quick end to Western sanctions on Beijing and a resumption of
international loans, but the heady visions of burgeoning growth in
commerce with the world's most populous country have been shaken by
the prospect of continued political strife.
   Earlier this month Chinese Premier Li Peng announced a lifting
of martial law. The move was seen as an attempt to end the Western
sanctions imposed after the bloody crackdown on the pro-democracy
movement in China last June, but it received a lukewarm welcome in
most world capitals.
   Washington refrained from giving a full go-ahead for the World
Bank to resume lending China money for development projects. Japan
said the move, although positive, would not immediately thaw
Tokyo's freeze on a huge loan package for China.
   Japan, Hong Kong and Taiwan all have suffered trade reverses
with China in the past year. Japanese investment in China is off,
and business confidence remains shaken, analysts say.
   Japanese business leaders said they hope China's situation will
stabilize and Tokyo will go ahead with a five-year program to lend
$5.6 billion to China.
   ``I felt quite relieved at the news because the Chinese economy
could get worse if Western sanctions against China last for long,''
Kyodo News Service quoted Kazuo Haruna, chairman of Marubeni Corp.,
one of Japan's leading trading companies, as saying about the
lifting of martial law.
   Sueo Kojima, a China researcher at the Japan External Trade
Organization, said the frozen loans are the key for Japanese
businesses.
   ``Now all our companies are waiting for the loan package because
otherwise China doesn't have money to pay for imports,'' Kojima
said in an interview.
   Prime Minister Toshiki Kaifu has said he hopes the package can
be implemented on schedule in April. Japan, China's biggest source
of foreign credit in recent years, says it doesn't want China to
become isolated in international affairs.
   Kojima said Japanese businesses ``will take a wait-and-see
attitude for now,'' keeping an eye on the U.S. Congress to see if
it continues tough sanctions.
   ``Maybe from the second half of this year (Japanese businesses)
will renew contact with the Chinese side,'' he said.
   China's austerity measures, imposed for economic reasons before
the June political crackdown, cut imports at the same time that
Chinese exports in some sectors surged.
   Japan's trade deficit with China, $594 million in the first 11
months of 1988, soared to $2.4 billion in the same period of 1989,
according to Japanese government figures.
   Hong Kong is the main port of entry for goods from Asia passing
into China, and its trade balance has shifted like Japan's.
   Economic retrenchment policies have stopped China from buying
products abroad and in Hong Kong, said C.L. Law, an economist at BT
Brokerage Ltd., the Hong Kong operation of Bankers Trust.
   China's purchases of goods in Hong Kong slipped to about $3.3
billion in the third quarter of 1989, down 1 percent from the third
quarter of 1988, the first drop in several years.
   Sales of Chinese goods in and through Hong Kong rose
dramatically, however, to about $7 billion for the third quarter of
1989, up 49 percent from a year earlier.
   Law said one reason Chinese sales surged was because many
factories built in China with Hong Kong money had opened for
business in the last year, sparking a jump in production. He said
he expects the increase to continue, although not at such a high
rate.
   In Taiwan, trade with China has grown since the Nationalist
government eased restrictions on ties with the Communist mainland
three years ago. But growth slowed in the third quarter of last
year because of China's clampdown on raw material exports and
Taiwan's shifting of some orders to other countries because of
instability in China, said economist Kao Chang of the semi-official
Chunghwa Institute for Economic Research.
   But Kao said some Taiwanese businesses ignored political
instability and moved chemical plants or labor-intensive industries
such as textiles and footwear to China because of rising labor
costs and environmental concerns at home.
   ``Many of our businessmen believe Chinese authorities will try
to maintain the open trade policy despite possible political
turmoil,'' Kao said.
   South Korea was just getting started in trade with Communist
China when business shrank after last June's violence, said
officials at the Trade and Industry Ministry in Seoul.
   In December, South Korea's Goldstar Co. temporarily closed a
plant making color television tubes, saying it had expected to ship
1.5 million tubes to China in 1989 but shipped only 40 percent in
the first half of the year and none in the last half.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900128-0069 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-28-90 1448EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-PSNHBankruptcy Bjt   01-28 0822</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-PSNH Bankruptcy, Bjt,0850</SECOND>
<BYLINE>Despite Opposition, Plan to Resolve Bankruptcy Seen Taking Effect
This Year</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>By FRANK BAKER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CONCORD, N.H. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   After two years of legal and political
wrangling, the Public Service Co. of New Hampshire bankruptcy is on
the brink of resolution despite the continued opposition of some
consumer advocates.
   A plan for Connecticut-based Northeast Utilities to take over
New Hampshire's largest electric utility _ the lead operator of the
troubled Seabrook nuclear power plant _ should go into effect this
summer, Public Service says.
   The governor and the Legislature have approved the deal and
state and federal regulators are expected to give their nods in
coming months.
   ``It would be surprising if the deal doesn't go through,'' said
Robert Viles, dean of Franklin Pierce Law Center in Concord and a
bankruptcy authority. ``It would require a new fact that isn't in
the picture now.''
   Even steadfast opponents of the $2.3 billion takeover say they
have thrown in the towel.
   ``It's done,'' said Paul McEachern, a Portsmouth lawyer who was
the state's Democratic gubernatorial candidate in 1986 and 1988.
``We're victims of a sellout.''
   Public Service entered Chapter 11 bankruptcy reorganization on
Jan. 28, 1988, under the weight of its lead-share ownership of the
$6.4 billion Seabrook nuclear plant, which remains idle for lack of
a commercial operating license. It was the first large, publicly
owned utility to file for bankruptcy since the Depression.
   The utility's slide began years earlier _ some say with the
small utility's decision in the early 1970s to take on a major
nuclear project.
   Public Service itself points to passage of a 1979 state law that
forbids utilities from charging for power plants before they
operate. The law, intended to prevent consumers from becoming
unwilling financiers for Seabrook, forced Public Service to borrow
more money for the plant, raising borrowing costs and, ultimately,
the cost of the project.
   Last September, Northeast presented one of four reorganization
proposals, including one by Public Service itself. Gov. Judd Gregg
and a committee representing Public Service shareholders and
creditors backed Northeast soon after, and the Legislature endorsed
the plan at a special session last month.
   The plan calls for Northeast to take over Public Service's 36
percent share of Seabrook. It also gives Northeast approval for
seven annual rate increases of 5.5 percent, the first of which took
effect provisionally on Jan. 1.
   Opponents say Gregg forced the plan on legislators on short
notice.
   ``I think an awful lot of (legislators) thought they just had to
trust the leadership because they didn't have the time or
background to understand what they were going to do,'' said Robert
Backus, a lawyer for the Seacoast Anti-Pollution League.
   Gregg said he stands by the plan and the state's handling of
negotiations.
   ``The issue is whether consumers are going to get charged a fair
rate for electricity, if there will be a dependable supply of
electricity and whether the company supplying the power would be
under New Hampshire control,'' Gregg said. The answer under the
plan is yes, he added.
   Gregg and state negotiators also defended the rate increases as
a reasonable tradeoff for avoiding the possibility of much larger
increases through the normal regulatory process once Seabrook was
licensed.
   But opponents argue that consumers are being forced to pay for
the bankruptcy while unsecured creditors get all of their
investment back, plus some interest. Some holders of so-called junk
bonds earned interest rates of more than 20 percent for their
speculative investments.
   ``I think Public Service Company stands out in this country as
an aberration in the bankruptcy field,'' McEachern said. ``It's the
only bankruptcy of any consequence where creditors made out like
bandits.''
   ``I think it favors creditors and debtors rather than the
public,'' Viles said of the reorganization plan.
   Gregg dismisses those arguments.
   ``Creditors and (stockholders) are talking about how bad a deal
it was for them,'' Gregg said. ``They're talking about how the
state stuck it to them. ... That's the bottom line.''
   The state Public Utilities Commission has scheduled hearings for
three weeks in March and April and plans to make its decision on
the plan by May 31. No one expects the agency to reject or change
the proposal.
   Michael Holmes, state consumer advocate and the only person
scheduled to appear before the PUC solely on behalf of consumers,
endorsed the Northeast plan when it came before the Legislature.
   Opponents said they decided not to appear before the PUC because
they believe it will be a rubber stamp.
   ``I think it's going to be a formality,'' said Mary Metcalf,
spokeswoman for the Campaign for Ratepayers Rights.
   The Federal Energy Regulatory Commission, U.S. Bankruptcy Court,
Public Service creditors and shareholders, the Securities and
Exchange Commission, Nuclear Regulatory Commission and Connecticut
Department of Public Utility Control, among others.
   Northeast says that if all goes well, the takeover will be
completed by the end of July.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900128-0070 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-28-90 1750EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-High-SpeedTrains     01-28 0485</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-High-Speed Trains,0501</SECOND>
<HEAD>High-Speed Trains Backed By Japanese</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PITTSBURGH (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A consortium of Japanese businesses are
debating whether to help finance construction of high-speed
magnetic levitation train systems in Pittsburgh and other U.S.
cities and may reach a decision by next week, members say.
   ``Most members of the group are supportive of the project, but
we don't have a final consensus among all members yet,'' said
Jitsuro Terashima of Mitsui and Co., one of the firms involved.
Terashima said news of the project was ``leaked prematurely'' to a
Japanese news service on Thursday.
   The consortium of 11 companies wants to help finance the trains
so they'll be in a good position if the technology becomes
widespread, officials said.
   ``They're doing this so as this develops, they can
participate,'' said Meyer Berger, chairman of the Pittsburgh Maglev
Action Group of business leaders, city and county officials and
representatives of Carnegie Mellon University.
   A 20-mile demonstration project would link Station Square, a
shopping and restaurant complex on the city's South Side, with
Greater Pittsburgh International Airport.
   The project would cost about $400 million. Total financing for
research, development and construction throughout the United States
would total $6 billion, Terashima said.
   Richard Uher, director of CMU's High Speed Ground Transportation
Center, declined to discuss the project, saying details would be
disclosed at a news conference Feb. 23.
   Maglev trains ride about a quarter-inch above the track on a
field of magnetic energy. They can reach speeds of 300 mph.
   The Pittsburgh Maglev Action Group and the High Speed Ground
Transportation Center have been advocating development of a train
from Station Square to the airport.
   The action group is pushing for a $1.5 million feasibility study
for the project. Gov. Robert Casey has said he wants the state to
contribute $300,000 toward the study.
   Berger said he expects the Japanese consortium to contribute
$250,000. Contributions from other businesses would pay for the
rest of the study, he said.
   William Dickhart, U.S. representative for Transrapid
International, a German consortium that has developed high-speed
rail technology, said it may be premature to consider financing
proposals before a feasibility study has been conducted.
   Berger said it's unlikely ridership to the airport could cover
the costs of the train. But the project eventually would stretch
beyond the airport, extending into a regional system serving Erie,
Cleveland, Charleston, W.Va., and other cities.
   Discussions with the Japanese consortium began about six months
ago. The consortium includes York: Mitsui and Co., Toshiba Corp.,
Toyota Motor Corp., Nippon Steel Corp., NKK Corp., Sumitomo Metal
Industries Ltd., Long-term Credit Bank of Japan, Sony Corp.,
Industrial Bank of Japan, Mitsui Bank and Ajinomoto, Berger said.
   Bob Casey, president of the Pittsburgh-based High Speed Rail
Association, said the first magnetic levitation train in the United
States is likely to be in operation in Florida by October 1994,
connecting the Orlando airport to a transit station near Disney
World.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900128-0071 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-28-90 1804EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-BankofNewEngland     01-28 0465</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bank of New England,0478</SECOND>
<HEAD>Chairman and CEO of Bank Of New England Retires Amid Controversy</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The top executive at the Bank of New England
Corp., which last week sought federal loans because of massive real
estate lossses, will be replaced by a new chairman and chief
executive officer.
   Walter J. Connolly Jr. agreed to step down from his post for
reasons bank officials declined to reveal Friday.
   In an interview with The Boston Globe, Connolly said his
retirement was agreed upon by himself and the board. But the
newspaper reported Saturday that the executive was dismissed by the
bank board during a meeting Friday night.
   The board appointed H. Ridgely Bullock to serve as chairman and
CEO until a replacement can be found, the bank announced in a
statement released Friday night.
   Earlier this month, Bank of New England said it expected to
close 1989 with a $1 billion loss, primarily because of bad real
estate loans. The bank said it would try to sell $6 billion in
assets.
   The bank's capital had dropped below $500 million, or less than
2 percent of its total assets. Federal bank regulations require
banks to maintain a 6 percent capital ratio.
   On Friday, officials confirmed the bank has been forced to
borrow money from the Federal Reserve Bank of Boston as depositors
withdrew millions of dollars from the troubled institution.
   The bank also has issued a statement saying it expects to
overhaul the company's operation by entering a consent order with
federal regulators. Analysts suggested the losses and restructuring
might lead to a federal takeover.
   The Globe on Saturday quoted sources as saying that two other
top officials would leave the bank in the coming week: Richard D.
Driscoll, chairman of Boston operations, and M. Thomas Wilson,
president of the Boston bank.
   ``The company has pressing problems and the board concluded that
the resolution of these problems could be best handled by new
people. And I respect that decision,'' Connolly told the Globe.
   Bullock, the new chairman and a current member of the board,
also serves as president and CEO of Montchanin Management Corp., an
investment and management company headquartered in New York.
   Sources told the Globe that William McDonough, the former
chairman and CEO of First Chicago Corp., had been approached as a
possible candidate for the bank's top position. He reportedly
either turned the offer down or made demands the New England board
could not honor.
   The sources also were quoted as saying the bank asked its former
president, Peter McCormick, to return. McCormick could not be
reached for comment Friday night.
   The bank also announced Friday it had federal approval to sell
its $450 million McCullagh Leasing to GE Capital Corp. The sale is
expected to be finalized next week.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
</Collection>
