<Collection>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0001 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 2342EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Deaths SUB   10-28 0101</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Deaths, SUB,0090</SECOND>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS final item to CORRECT to wife sted husband.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Milos Zelnicek</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Milos Zelnicek, the father of Ivana Trump, the
estranged wife of developer Donald Trump, died Sunday in
Czechoslovakia of a heart attack at age 63, her lawyer said..
   Zelnicek a retired engineer, died in a hospital in Prague, said
Michael Kennedy, Mrs. Trump's lawyer.
   Mrs. Trump continues to run the Plaza Hotel in New York for her
husband, though the couple separated in February.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0002 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 2349EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-LeathFarewell     10-28 0512</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Leath Farewell,0655</SECOND>
<HEAD>Leath Looks on 12 Years in House</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Monday AMs report.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By EVAN RAMSTAD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Marvin Leath came to Congress from the heart
of Texas with a country musician's soul and a banker's sense.
   But after a dozen years in the House, Leath is calling it quits
- frustrated by the ability of an individual congressman to make a
difference.
   ``You see so much written in the media and so forth about
people, incumbents, who get these jobs and they never leave and
they're an institution,'' said the Waco Democrat.
   ``...People say nobody walks away from that job. Well somebody
did,'' he said. ``And maybe that gives a little bit of faith to
people who think the system is so totally corrupt and bad. It
really isn't.''
   In the early 1980s, Leath was a part of the group of
conservative Democrats called the ``Boll Weevils'' that supported a
stronger defense and tax reform.
   But he said defense spending ran amuck under President Reagan
and the deficit's growth from $40 billion to more than $300 billion
``deeply distresses'' him.
   ``Most of the things I hoped to do ... the big issues, we did
something about but we did in excess,'' Leath said.
   ``I really thought the 80s was going to be the decade that was
the most critical in the country's history,'' he said. ``Perhaps it
was. But I think if you look back on that, I have to think that as
a government, we blew it.''
   Reagan didn't exert the leadership to make hard choices, Leath
said, noting the government wasn't designed for Congress to make
laws alone. The hundreds of interests reflected by Congress also
frustrate its power, he said.
   ``You can't expect (Congress) to develop national policy,''
Leath said. ``You've got to have a strong president, willing to
take the political risks to solve the problems. Bush is much more
prone to do that than Reagan.''
   Leath, who made his fortune as a banker in Marlin and Waco, is
known as a pretty fair country music crooner and host of a popular
annual barbecue.
   ``You don't see a whole lot of those kinds of parties around
here,'' said Rep. Charles Stenholm, D-Texas, who was elected in
1978 from a neighboring district and was also a ``Boll Weevil.''
   ``This guy has star potential,'' Congressional scholar Norm
Ornstein said of Leath's singing.
   Leath's friend Willie Nelson has encouraged him to cut an album.
But, Leath said, ``I'm a little bit old to go on the country music
circuit.'' At 59, Leath is only two years older than Nelson.
   In Congress, Leath closely followed the problems of the budget
and financial industry from a seat on the House Budget Committee.
   He voted against thrift deregulation in 1980 and argued that
crisis in thrifts, banks and insurance companies was caused by
lawmakers' ``foolish mistakes.''
   ``Those of us who understood what the banking system was,
understood why we had some of the rules we had for 50 years. We
felt very reasonably assured when you destroyed those things that
were necessary foundations, this would happen,'' Leath said. ``But
you couldn't get anybody to listen to you.''
   Leath will take about $484,000 in leftover campaign funds with
him when he leaves. He'll keep some for himself to repay expenses
from that first campaign, he said. The rest will go to charity and
political candidates. ``I think that gives me a good way to stay
involved in the system,'' Leath said.
   He worried some about leaving constituents in the lurch,
particularly while fighting the Army's decision to deactivate one
of two armored divisions at Fort Hood in his district.
   ``You can always say, `I've just got to do another term.' First
thing you know, you're a doddering old man,'' Leath said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0003 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 2350EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a BC-LOT-SaturdayLotteries     10-28 0739</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-LOT-Saturday Lotteries, </SECOND>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<HEAD>ARIZONA</HEAD>
<HEAD>Pick</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PHOENIX (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers in Saturday night's drawing
of the Arizona Lottery's Pick game:
   4, 7, 16, 17, 20 and 28
</TEXT>
<HEAD>CALIFORNIA</HEAD>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SACRAMENTO, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers picked
Saturday night for the California Lottery's twice-weekly ``Lotto
6-53'' game:
   23, 9, 39, 29, 8, 5.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>CONNECTICUT</HEAD>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEWINGTON, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning combination picked Saturday
in the Conncticut State Lottery's ``Daily Lottery'' drawing was:
   1-2-7
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Play 4</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEWINGTON, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning combination picked Saturday
in the Connecticut State Lottery's ``Play 4'' drawing was:
   2-7-5-2.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>DELAWARE</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DOVER, Del. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   These Delaware lotteries were drawn Saturday
night:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   7-4-9
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Play Four</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   0-2-4-9
</TEXT>
<HEAD>FLORIDA</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected Saturday in
the Florida Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Cash 3</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   3-8-0
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   17-40-34-10-07-11
</TEXT>
<HEAD>ILLINOIS</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SPRINGFIELD, Ill. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the Illinois State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   4-4-1
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick Four</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   6-0-8-7
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   20-24-33-39-46-54)
</TEXT>
<HEAD>INDIANA</HEAD>
<HEAD>Ind Lottery Glance</HEAD>
<DATELINE>INDIANAPOLIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the Hoosier Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto Cash</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   16-9-11-28-7-29
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Three</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   4-0-8
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Four</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   8-0-2-5
</TEXT>
<HEAD>IOWA</HEAD>
<HEAD>Iowa Lotto</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DES MOINES, Iowa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning Iowa Lotto numbers drawn
Saturday night are:
   7-8-19-26-29-36.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto America</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DES MOINES, Iowa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Lotto America numbers drawn Saturday
night are:
   4-17-25-37-42-50
</TEXT>
<HEAD>KENTUCKY</HEAD>
<HEAD>Kentucky Lottery</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOUISVILLE, Ky. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are Saturday's winning numbers
selected by the Kentucky Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Kentucky Cash:
   3-9-4.
   </HEAD>
<HEAD>Lotto:
   11-16-17-22-28-41
   </HEAD>
<HEAD>MARYLAND</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BALTIMORE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   These Maryland lotteries were drawn Saturday
night:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   7-4-6
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Play Four</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   8-5-0-9
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   03-05-19-29-33-46
</TEXT>
<HEAD>MASSACHUSETTS</HEAD>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BRAINTREE, Mass. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers drawn Saturday night
in the ``Massachusetts Daily Lottery'' were:
   3-5-8-1
</TEXT>
<HEAD>MICHIGAN</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DETROIT (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected Saturday in
the Michigan State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   3-2-8
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily-4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   4-6-3-8
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto 47</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   2, 10, 24, 29, 30, 38
</TEXT>
<HEAD>MINNESOTA</HEAD>
<HEAD>Daily 3</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MINNEAPOLIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers drawn Saturday night in
the Minnesota Daily 3 lottery game are:
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   8-0-9
</TEXT>
<HEAD>NEW JERSEY</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TRENTON, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday night in the New Jersey State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 3</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   0-0-8
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   9-4-2-7
</TEXT>
<HEAD>NEW YORK</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ALBANY, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the New York State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Number</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   4-7-7
</TEXT>
<HEAD>WinFour</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   9-4-7-5
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 10</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ALBANY, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the New York State Lottery's Pick 10 game:
   1, 2, 3, 9, 13, 14, 16, 27, 28, 31, 35, 36, 41, 42, 45, 49, 55,
63, 64, 78
</TEXT>
<HEAD>LOTTO</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ALBANY, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the New York State Lottery:
   7, 13, 15, 21, 33, 35, supp. - 44
</TEXT>
<HEAD>NORTHERN NEW ENGLAND</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CONCORD, N.H. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the daily New Hampshire, Vermont and Maine lotteries:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 3</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   9-8-3
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   9-8-8-6
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Tri-State Megabucks</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CONCORD, N.H. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers in the
``Tri-State Megabucks'' game for New Hampshire, Vermont and Maine:
   7, 26, 28, 33, 36, 40.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>OHIO</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CLEVELAND (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected Saturday
night in the Ohio Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Super Lotto</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   2-13-19-30-50-52
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Kicker</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   1-3-7-1-0-2
</TEXT>
<HEAD>OREGON</HEAD>
<HEAD>Daily 4</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PORTLAND, Ore. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are Saturday's winning numbers in the
``Oregon Daily 4'' lotery game:
   8-7-2-4
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Megabucks</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PORTLAND, Ore. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are Saturday's winning numbers in the
``Oregon Megabucks'' lottery game:
   10-19-20-21-22-41
</TEXT>
<HEAD>PENNSYLVANIA</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HARRISBURG (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected Saturday
in the Pennsylvania State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Number</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   2-2-5
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Big 4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   9-6-2-0
</TEXT>
<HEAD>RHODE ISLAND</HEAD>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CRANSTON, R.I. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers drawn Saturday night
in the Rhode Island ``Lot-O-Bucks'' were:
   8-9-21-23-24
</TEXT>
<HEAD>VIRGINIA</HEAD>
<HEAD>Pick 3</HEAD>
<DATELINE>RICHMOND (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   These numbers were drawn Saturday in the
Virginia Lottery's Pick 3 game:
   6-8-3
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<DATELINE>RICHMOND (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   These numbers were drawn Saturday in the
Virginia Lottery's Pick 3 game:
   1-5-9-10-33-40
</TEXT>
<HEAD>WASHINGTON, DC</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The following results were drawn Saturday in
the District of Columbia Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lucky Numbers Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   9-1-0
</TEXT>
<HEAD>D.C. Four Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   9-9-5-3
</TEXT>
<HEAD>D.C. Daily Double Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   29, 61
</TEXT>
<HEAD>D.C. Quick Cash Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   6-16-25-29-33-37

</TEXT>
<HEAD>WEST VIRGINIA</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CHARLESTON, W.Va. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the West Virginia State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily 3</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   3-6-1
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily 4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   0-8-3-9
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0004 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 2351EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-StarTrek     10-28 0364</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Star Trek,0450</SECOND>
<HEAD>New `Star Trek' Goes Where Old Series Never Went</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT JABLON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   ``Star Trek: The Next Generation'' this week
boldly goes where the original series never went.
   Its 80th episode airs this week. The original ``Star Trek'' ran
79 episodes before it was canceled in 1969 after three seasons.
   The new version, which premiered in 1987, ranks among the
top-rated syndicated series nationwide. Like the original, it was
created by Gene Roddenberry.
   Cast members paid little attention when the momentous 80th
episode was filmed in September. But they are aware of the original
show's cult status and the burden they carry.
   The ``Star Trek'' saga ``seems to have affected people's lives
over decades,'' said British actor Patrick Stewart, who plays Capt.
Jean-Luc Picard on the new series.
   Stewart, whose children watched the old show, thinks the new one
has accomplished something akin to what the original did.
   ``It has its own mythology, it has, already, a whole series of
legends attached to it,'' he said.
   ``It's a landmark show in that so very few have achieved, in a
recreation, or a reincarnation ... the kind of success, and
independent success, that this show has achieved.''
   The original series, starring William Shatner as Capt. James
Kirk and Leonard Nimoy as the half-Vulcan Mr. Spock, has survived
two decades in reruns, and most of its cast has reunited for five
movies. It endures in the hearts of thousands of ``trekkies,'' many
of whom also have warmed to the new show.
   At $1 million or more per episode, the Paramount Television
production is light years ahead of the old show in cost and special
effects. The updated Enterprise has recessed lighting, comfy
quarters and even a bar.
   But the basic formula remains: Intrepid spacefarers dealing with
moral and political issues that mimic those of our own time.
   The 80th episode, for example, deals with two cultures locked in
a war like the one in Beirut. It airs on various days this week,
depending on the market.
   Stewart's 25 years in Shakespearean theater are put to good use
when he walks the bridge of the 24th-century starship, he said.
``Our show is of an epic nature. It's telling grand stories. It's
classical in its structure,'' he said.
   Rumors persist that the cast of the syndicated series will make
a movie, or that the casts of the old and new series will do an
episode together.
   Stewart said he knows ``none of that'' but likes the idea of
blending the crews. Not to ``would be a little cowardly,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0005 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 2352EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-EndangeredCommunities     10-28 0509</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Endangered Communities,0616</SECOND>
<HEAD>Cities on `Endangered' List Duck, Embrace Designation</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   A county commissioner was more than a little embarrassed when
Williston, N.D., showed up on a list of 10 Western cities
threatened with extinction. But officials in some of the other
cities reluctantly agreed the description fits.
   Marlene Eide helped get Williston, a town of 13,000, on the list
of cities with economic problems related to federal policies. When
the National Association of Counties recently issued the list, it
said the cities ``are in danger of becoming extinct because of
restrictions on the use of public lands.''
   ``I saw that and I about died,'' said Eide, a Williams County
commissioner. ``I'm going to have to leave town. Everybody will be
so mad at me but I didn't even do anything.''
   Williston's tourism industry has been hurt during recent
droughts by falling water levels on Lake Sakakawea, part of the
Missouri River Reservoir system managed by the Army Corps of
Engineers. But extinction never crossed Eide's mind.
   Others acknowledged their towns belonged on the list.
   ``We are in trouble,'' said Audrie Clifford, mayor of Reserve,
N.M. ``The traditional means of livelihood in Catron County are
cattle and timber, and both are severely threatened.''
   The county association said limitations on public land uses in
recent years have hurt the communities' economies and severely
strained their ability to provide needed services.
   ``These communities, and there may be hundreds of others like
them, are suffering,'' said Michael Stewart, president of the
Washington-based group and a commissioner in Salt Lake County,
Utah.
   Also on the list are Weed and Cima, Calif.; Jarbridge, Nev.;
Escalante, Utah; Walden, Colo.; Horseshoe Bend, Idaho; Columbia
Falls, Mont., and Mill City, Ore.
   Larry Naake, executive director of the County Supervisors
Association of California, said the list is meant to get the
attention of the Bush administration and Congress.
   ``There needs to be more balance between state and federal
policies ... between environmental and human concerns,'' he said.
   Like many of the cities, Weed, a town of 3,000 on the slopes of
Mount Shasta volcano in northern California, depends on the timber
industry.
   ``No one wants to come to the city if they have no guarantee
they will make a living there. We are just trying to make it, hold
on to our city in a beautiful area,'' said Mayor Kalvin Vanderhoof.
   Mill City was established in 1947, when the timber industry
began expanding rapidly in Oregon to build houses for the postwar
baby boom. About 50 miles southeast of Portland, Mill City has
1,500 residents.
   ``People here are frightened,'' said Mayor Mary Smith, who is a
secretary for Frank Lumber Co. ``There are more and more reports of
mills cutting back, laying people off. If it continues, they're
going to panic.''
   ``We're a timber town,'' she said. ``There's nothing else here
for us.''
   Two environmental groups took issue with the inclusion of
Horseshoe Bend on the list. The Wilderness Society and Idaho
Conservation League officials deny that environmental restrictions
on timber cutting in Idaho have hurt the logging town 30 miles
north of Boise.
   ``In 1989 the timber harvested in Idaho was at the highest level
in the past 10 years,'' said Mike Medberry of the Idaho
Conservation League. ``If Horseshoe Bend is an endangered town,
it's not due to lack of timber.''
   In Reserve, with fewer than 400 residents, the mayor said the
city won't ``dry up and blow away.''
   ``I feel the people of Reserve will find a way to exist
somehow,'' Clifford said. ``We're tough and stubborn people -
survivors.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0006 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 2355EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-BorderBridges Bjt   10-28 0638</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Border Bridges, Bjt,0785</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mexico Prepares for More Trade With New Bridges, Improved Roads</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto MO1 Oct. 23.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LAURA CASTANEDA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>COLOMBIA, Mexico (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Mexico is building seven border bridges
and thousands of miles of highway to handle the boom in traffic
from an expected free-trade agreement with the United States.
   With help from private investors, President Carlos Salinas de
Gortari set a plan in motion last year to improve Mexico's
inadequate roads and customs system.
   Solidarity Bridge and border crossing at Colombia, now a
cinder-block town of only 350 people, is the largest project.
   A 66-mile highway linking Colombia to an improved road between
Laredo, Texas, and Monterrey will cut the driving distance between
the border and Monterrey to 140 miles from 180.
   More than 2,480 miles of highways are to be built before the
president's six-year term ends in 1994. Half will be financed
through private investment.
   The other bridges, under construction or planned, will be in
Matamoros, Nuevo Laredo and Valle Hermosa, all in Tamaulipas state;
Piedras Negras and Ciudad Acuna in Coahuila, and Ciudad Juarez in
Chihuahua state.
   Mexican officials say the improvements are needed to strengthen
trade links with the United States and compete with the economic
blocs of Europe and Asia.
   Trucks crossing into Mexico often must wait for hours, then
negotiate undivided, two-lane highways riddled with potholes.
   ``We don't need to be a rich country to have good roads, but we
need good roads to become a rich country,'' said Carlos Joaquin
Vallejo Rivero. He directs the state highway office in Nuevo Leon,
the northeastern border state where the Colombia project is being
built.
   ``It costs more and takes more time to transport things via bad
roads because of higher insurance and loss of goods,'' he said.
   Trade with the United States took off in 1986 when Mexico joined
the General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade, lowering import duties
on hundreds of foreign products and making exports of Mexican
manufactured goods a priority.
   From less than $30 billion in 1986, two-way trade rose to $52
billion in 1989. Mexico is the third-largest U.S. trading partner,
after Canada and Japan.
   A U.S.-Mexican trade agreement that would remove tariffs and
other barriers is under discussion. It may be linked with the
similar U.S.-Canadian pact of 1988 to create a single North
American trade zone of 335 million people.
   Salinas and President Bush are to discuss the proposal at a
meeting Nov. 26-27 in Monterrey.
   ``All indications are that we are going to have even more
intensive trade with the United States, and we are just not
prepared,'' said Antonio Fuentes Flores, director of the Trust for
the Development of Nuevo Leon.
   Fuentes, whose organization is overseeing construction, said the
820-acre Solidarity site will include an eight-lane bridge, storage
terminals, refrigerated warehouses and hotel.
   It will more than triple the size of Colombia, a town 10 blocks
square populated mostly by farmers.
   Many people didn't think a new bridge was justified ``because we
already had a crossing at Laredo,'' Fuentes said. Laredo is the
United States' biggest inland port of entry, with 1,600 trucks
crossing daily.
   ``But we looked at projections of how much traffic would
increase in the next few years,'' he said, and ``concluded that we
didn't need to just build a bridge, but we needed to build a new
concept of border crossings.''
   Nuevo Leon was an ideal site, Fuentes said, because more than
half the merchandise moving south through Laredo goes to Monterrey,
the state capital and Mexico's leading industrial city.
   Monterrey businessmen wanted a border crossing in Nuevo Leon so
they would not have to send products through Nuevo Laredo in
Tamaulipas state. They claim customs officials and corrupt unions
in Nuevo Laredo inflate the cost.
   The Mexican side of the bridge and its support facilities is to
cost $49 million, split between the federal government and private
investors.
   Laredo, Texas, is financing the U.S. side, at $62 million, with
help from the state government and Washington. The site is Dolores,
a town 18 miles from Laredo.
   Four new highways in Nuevo Leon, totaling 350 miles, are being
built with $584 million in private funds.
   Vallejo of the state highway office said the concessionaire,
Viaductos de Peaje, would charge tolls for 8 to 14 years before
turning the roads over to the state.
   He said the highways would be divided, with at least two lanes
in each direction, speed limits of 75 mph, lights in urban areas,
rest stops and the concession company's own roadside mechanics and
patrolmen.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0007 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 2359EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-EXP--GeneTherapy     10-28 0635</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-EXP--Gene Therapy,0791</SECOND>
<HEAD>4-year-old Pioneer Inaugurates Genetic Revolution in Medicine</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Monday AMs report.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By PAUL RAEBURN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Editor</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   At 12:52 p.m. on Friday, Sept. 14, doctors at
the National Institutes of Health began transfusing white blood
cells into the tiny arm of a 4-year-old girl with a rare inherited
ailment.
   For 28 minutes she played with her doctors and put stickers on
their lab coats as she helped them launch a new era in medical
treatment.
   She became the first person to receive gene therapy, a treatment
intended to compensate for the genetic defect she was born with by
giving her normal copies of the defective genes.
   News of the experiment had special interest for Suzanne
Tomlinson, a 27-year-old woman from Alexandria, Va.
   ``The idea of gene therapy was always sort of far off and maybe
a little idealistic,'' she said. ``It has been in the back of my
mind that, theoretically, gene therapy would be the key that would
really cure the disease.''
   The disease is cystic fibrosis. She was diagnosed with it when
she was 7 months old.
   The 4-year-old gene therapy pioneer, whose name has been
withheld, has a rare immune system disorder. But gene therapy holds
promise for people with many inherited diseases, including cystic
fibrosis.
   Indeed, recent discoveries about cystic fibrosis have made it
one of the leading candidates for gene therapy, perhaps within the
next five years, said Robert Beall, executive vice president for
medical affairs at the Cystic Fibrosis Foundation in Bethesda, Md.
   ``What we thought to be decades away is now years away,'' said
Beall.
   Other potential candidates for gene therapy within the next few
years are certain forms of anemia, hemophilia and muscular
dystrophy.
   It will be at least several months before researchers know
whether gene therapy is succeeding in the 4-year-old girl. Many
researchers, poised to expand the applications of gene therapy, say
the experiment represents the historic opening of a new era in
medicine.
   When the experiment was approved in July, Gerard McGarrity,
chairman of the National Institutes of Health approval panel, said:
``What we're doing today is adding gene therapy to vaccines,
antibiotics and radiation in the medical arsenal. Medicine has been
waiting thousands of years for this.''
   Tomlinson, too, has been waiting. Her parents have long been
active with the Cystic Fibrosis Foundation, and she works there as
consumer affairs coordinator.
   She was married earlier this year and attends law school at
night. But she still makes time to follow cystic fibrosis research,
including the several-year-long debate over the ethics and risks of
gene therapy.
   The decision to proceed ``shows that society is willing to
accept this,'' she said. Criticism of the experiment was important,
because ``it makes people think about the seriousness of this
work,'' Tomlinson said.
   Scientists worry that putting new genes into the body could
trigger cancer or other problems. And some worry about the ethics
of altering human genetic makeup.
   ``But I don't want to see them (the critics) stop it,''
Tomlinson said. ``I don't want their fear of the unknown to hold us
back.''
   Last summer, researchers found the gene that is defective in
people with cystic fibrosis, and this year they showed that the
defect could be corrected in the test tube.
   The next experiment will be to try to insert the normal cystic
fibrosis gene into mice, and then try again in larger animals, such
as sheep, Beall said.
   Then human experimentation could begin. Because the most
important symptom of cystic fibrosis is the accumulation of mucus
in the lungs, an aerosol spray that delivered genetically
engineered cells to the lungs might be all that is required for
most patients.
   Tomlinson has a mild case of cystic fibrosis. She follows a
physical therapy regimen every morning to dislodge mucus in her
lungs, and she takes enzyme pills with every meal to help digest
her food.
   Several times a year she is treated for lung infections, usually
managing to avoid the hospitalizations that many people with cystic
fibrosis undergo.
   ``I've really been able to lead a full life,'' she said.
   As researchers scramble to finish the preliminary experiments to
pave the way for gene therapy in cystic fibrosis, Tomlinson is
uncertain what that means to her.
   Despite her enthusiasm, she isn't sure she'll volunteer to be
one of the first to try the new treatment.
   ``I want to be sure it works,'' she said. ``I used to do more
research, but now because there's so much going on in my life, and
I'm healthy, I guess I'm more skeptical.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0008 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 0032EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Crime     10-28 0286</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Crime,320</SECOND>
<HEAD>Lawmakers Pass Stripped-Down Crime Bill</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Congress late Saturday gave final passage to a
stripped-down anti-crime bill, avoiding certain fights over such
contentious issues as the death penalty and a ban on assault
weapons.
   The House approved the measure 313-1 and sent it to the White
House, where it awaited an uncertain fate.
   The action came after a joint House-Senate conference committee
on Friday cut major provisions from the legislation that President
Bush had sought. The cutting was aimed at making the measure more
acceptable.
   Among the bill's provisions, however, was one that would toughen
penalties for certain white collar crimes including a possible life
prison term in some cases involving fraud by savings and loan
kingpins.
   It also calls for increased penalties for offenses committed
against children including for the first time making possession of
child pornography a federal offense.
   Attorney General Dick Thornburgh assailed lawmakers for dropping
a provision that would have permitted use of the death penalty for
new categories of federal crimes.
   He said the decision of the conferees to drop the death penalty
is an ``enormous step backwards in the fight against violent
crime'' and ``welcome news only to violent criminals.''
   Sen. Joseph Biden, D-Del., chairman of the Judiciary Committee,
said he was pleased that a crime bill was passed, but said ``I am
disappointed that we were unable to agree on a truly comprehensive
bill ... that contains a massive expansion of the death penalty.''
   The bill also:
   -Enacts new procedures to make it easier for child abuse victims
to testify in federal courts.
   -Authorizes a doubling of federal aid to local law enforcement -
up to $900 million.
   -Authorizes a $20 million ``rural drug initiative'' to finance
increased efforts by local police and prosecutors in rural areas to
combat drugs.
   Rep. George Gekas, R-Pa., cast the lone ``no'' vote.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0009 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 0120EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>b w AM-CongressRdp -BULLETIN- a0714 10-28 0100</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Congress Rdp, 8th Ld, a0714,80</SECOND>
<BYLINE>BULLETIN</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Congress adjourned early Sunday after passing
landmark budget, clean air and child care legislation, culminating
a stormy election-year session.
   Major civil rights, campaign finance and crime measures were
left unfinished as lawmakers headed home for the onrushing November
elections.
   With the bang of the gavel in the Senate at 1:17 a.m. EST, the
second session of the 101st Congress adjourned, sine die.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>The Senate voted: 2nd graf, a0714, Pickup.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0010 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 0134EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w BC-Congress-S&amp;Ls     10-28 0334</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Congress-S&amp;Ls,370</SECOND>
<HEAD>Congress Adjourns Without Extra Money for Resolution Trust Corp.</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Congress adjourned for the year early Sunday
without providing any additional funding for the agency charged
with bailing out failed savings and loan associations.
   The Senate early Sunday adopted a measure that would have
provided $10 billion to the Resolution Trust Corp., but the House
did not act on it. The Bush administration had sought as much as
$57 billion.
   Senate Banking Committee Chairman Donald Riegle said that while
the RTC should be kept ``on a very tight leash,'' he believed the
Congress should not leave without providing money to carry the
agency through the next 90 days.
   Sen. Jake Garn of Utah, ranking Republican on the Banking
Committee, called the sum inadequate and said it was ``the absolute
minimum'' necessary to keep the bailout agency in business. Both
Riegle and Garn said that dealing with the savings and loan
collapse would have to occupy lawmakers' attention as soon as they
return in January.
   Sen. Bob Graham, D-Fla., said it would cost taxpayers more money
if the bailout agency had to close for lack of funds.
   The Senate-approved measure, an amendment to the Federal Home
Loan Bank Board Act, also contains provisions requiring the RTC to
submit ``detailed justification'' to the Congress for future
requests for funds.
   It also ``expresses the sense of Congress'' that the Resolution
Trust Corp. should not use taxpayers' money to pay off uninsured
depositors in failed savings and loans.
   Several senators voiced misgivings about the move, and Sen.
Howard Metzenbaum, D-Ohio, complained that Treasury Secretary
Nicholas Brady has refused to appear before congressional panels
recently to argue for the money.
   Metzenbaum said the thrift scandal happened because ``during the
Reagan administration, they literally said to the savings and loan
executives, `Do what you want.''
   ``The American people are (eventually) going to be called upon
to spend something like $500 or $600 billion'' to pay for the
rescue, he said. ``What a shameful tragedy.''
   The measure passed the Senate by voice vote. Sen. Robert Kerrey,
D-Neb., said at one point that the rescue operation was very
unpopular with the American people, adding that ``it might not have
a majority'' if put to a roll call vote.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0011 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 1149EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Congress-LookBack Bjt   10-28 0903</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Congress-Look Back, Bjt,1,050</SECOND>
<HEAD>101st Congress: Squabbles, Scandals and Landmark Legislation</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By STEVEN KOMAROW</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Congress that adjourned Sunday stumbled,
stalled and scandalized but then passed dramatic national policy
changes for taxes, the environment, military spending, foreign
policy and child care.
   ``A Congress of significant accomplishment,'' bragged Senate
Majority Leader George Mitchell, D-Maine.
   The history books, making a cold, hard assessment, may agree.
But that wouldn't do justice to the raucous and ugly path this
Congress took to get there.
   The latest two-year lawmaking conclave was America's 101st. At
the end, lawmakers were referring to it as ``The One Hundred and
Worst.''
   ``So many of us wasted so much time,'' House Republican Leader
Robert H. Michel, R-Ill., said. ``What a horribly poor example of
Congress at its best.''
   It started with Senate rejection of President Bush's nomination
of John Tower for secretary of Defense, because of his reputation
as a boozer and womanizer.
   The House then weighed in with its own ethics scandal, which
culminated in the resignations of Speaker Jim Wright, D-Texas, and
Majority Whip Tony Coelho, D-Calif.
   An attempt at a meaningful bipartisan budget deal in the first
year collapsed into a nasty, partisan fight over Bush's proposed
cut in the capital gains tax rate.
   The new House speaker, Thomas S. Foley, D-Wash., received a
black eye when his conservative Democrats sided with the
Republicans and passed the plan. Outvoted, Mitchell was able to
stop it in the Senate only through a parliamentary blockade.
   The first session passed a publicly supported federal minimum
wage increase, and Bush and the Democrats agreed to end aid to the
Contra rebels in Nicaragua.
   But those and other efforts were overshadowed by the pay raise.
   Early in the year, Wright tried and failed amid a storm of
public outrage to protect former President Ronald Reagan's proposed
50 percent boost in congressional pay. But it wouldn't die.
   After taking over as speaker at midyear, Foley engineered a
compromise: a big salary boost in exchange for no more
special-interest money for making speeches.
   The House approved it; the Senate didn't bite. House salaries,
which were $89,500 last year, will soar to roughly $125,000 next
January. With only cost-of-living increases, the senators will make
just over $100,000.
   Congress returned this year to resume a slow legislative pace
with only mixed results.
   A new law designed to reduce chances of major oil spills was
enacted. The Americans With Disabilities Act, giving new rights to
people with impairments, became law.
   Democrats succeeded in defeating Bush's proposed constitutional
amendment to ban flag burning.
   But the Democratic Congress couldn't override the president's
veto of legislation guaranteeing workers six weeks of paid leave
for childbirth or family medical emergencies.
   The 101st Congress never overrode any of 16 Bush vetoes.
   And the ethics scandals continued. One House member was
disciplined and another quit following sex-related charges.
   In the Senate, a group of lawmakers became known as the Keating
Five, all under investigation for their ties to the head of a
failed California savings and loan institution.
   Meanwhile, all efforts to contain the costs of the S&amp;L bailout
were proving fruitless. In May, with the estimates of the federal
deficit heading for the stratosphere, Bush decided it was time for
a budget summit with Congress.
   Spring turned to summer and then summer to fall without an
agreement. The legislative logjam grew as lawmakers awaited the
summit results. Mitchell compared the budget to ``a whale in a
bathtub,'' crowding out everything else.
   Major legislation including a historic revision of the nation's
clean air laws, federal aid for child care, civil rights, the farm
bill, housing, and anti-crime proposals languished.
   As the leaves began to turn, pollsters noticed that the public
was beginning to turn surly at the apparent ineptness of their
Congress and their president. Public confidence in the government's
institutions plummeted and some lawmakers reported nasty receptions
from voters back home.
   Finally, at the end of September the White House and
congressional leaders signed a budget pact calling for a $500
billion reduction in federal deficits over the next five years.
Rank-and-file lawmakers, however, rebelled at the 12-cent gasoline
tax hike, deep cuts in Medicare subsidies and dozens of other new
fees or service reductions.
   On Oct. 5, the day Congress had been scheduled to adjourn, the
House killed the deal in a painful defeat for Bush and the
Democratic leadership. Hoping to put the onus on Congress for the
failure, Bush let the government shut down for the weekend.
   From the wreckage, a new package emerged, one less to Bush's
liking but still acceptable to him. It had higher taxes on the
wealthy, only a nickel in new gas taxes and a lighter hit on
Medicare. The Senate gave it final congressional approval on
Saturday.
   And the budget wasn't the only thing to fall into place. At a
time in the year when most previous Congresses had already gone
home, the 101st Congress began to click.
   Among the hundreds of bills passed in the final three weeks
were:
   - A new grant program for child care and increases tax credits
for low-income families with children in the name of child-care
assistance.
   - The first overhaul of the federal clean air law in 13 years,
requiring new pollution controls on automobiles, factories and
utilities.
   - The first major revision of the nation's legal immigration
system in 25 years, providing more visas for families and those
with special job skills.
   - All 13 of the annual spending bills for federal agencies, none
of which were completed by the Oct. 1 deadline. The net effect:
defense spending goes down, while domestic spending increases.
   - A phase-down of U.S. support for proxy wars in Cambodia,
Angola and Afghanistan, and a 50 percent cut in military aid for El
Salvador - all designed to steer away from armed conflict and
toward diplomacy.
   - A five-year farm bill designed to contain costs and address
environmental concerns.
   Efforts at passing campaign reform collapsed, as did a vetoed
civil rights bill. A hoped-for major crime package crumbled into a
washed-out facsimile.
   But at the end, congressional Democrats declared victory and
took umbrage when asked about Bush's campaign to paint Congress as
slow and inept.
   ``We have persevered on a hard, unpleasant, difficult process up
to the very week before election, and we're told it's disorderly,''
complained Foley. ``It's courageous. It's heroic in some ways.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0012 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 1152EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--LionessEscapes     10-28 0112</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Lioness Escapes,0103</SECOND>
<HEAD>Lioness Escapes Zoo Cage and Kills 3-Year-Old Girl</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CAIRO, Egypt (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A lioness escaped from her cage Sunday and
killed the 3-year-old daughter of a zookeeper before being shot
dead, the Middle East News Agency reported.
   The 8-year-old lioness escaped from her cage while it was being
cleaned and attacked the girl, Asma Abdel-Azim Ibrahim, the news
agency said.
   The agency said the zoo's manager, Nabil Gad Khalil, shot and
killed the lioness.
   The small zoo, located in the southern town of Fayoum, was
closed for the rest of the day while an investigation was carried
out.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0013 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 1158EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Obit-Tognazzi     10-28 0350</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Tognazzi,0436</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ugo Tognazzi, `La Cage Aux Folles' Star, Dead At 68</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ROME (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Ugo Tognazzi, a bookkeeper who became one of Italy's
leading comic actors and achieved international fame with his role
in ``La Cage Aux Folles,''has died of a cerebral hemmorrhage. He
was 68.
   The Italian news agency ANSA said Tognazzi suffered a cerebral
hemmorrhage Saturday morning and died late that night.
   Tognazzi, who first appeared in Italian films in the 1950s,
became one of the country's leading screen personalities in the
1960s with his ability to play supporting roles or comic and
dramatic leads with equal ability.
   He was best known in the United States for his role as a
homosexual cabaret owner in the 1979 film adaptation of ``La Cage
Aux Folles,'' a bedroom farce that was a stage hit. He also
appeared in a 1980 sequel to the movie.
   Tognazzi was born March 23, 1922 in Cremona. Because of the
illness of his father, he was forced to go to work at age 15 as a
bookkeeper at a salami factory. But he also spent his youth acting
on the amateur stage.
   He made his first movie in 1950 in the film ``I Caddetti of
Guascogna (The Cadets of Guascogona).'' He followed that
performance with a series of films in the 1950s that made him a
popular character actor.
   In the 1960s, Tognazzi matured as an actor with a series of
creative roles in satrical films such as Luciano Salce's ``Il
Federale'' (The Fascist), which is still considered one of
Tognazzi's greatest films.
   After his success in ``Il Federale'' and Dino Risi's ``La Marcia
Su Roma'' (The March on Rome), Tognazzi met Marco Ferreri, the
director who gave him some of his greatest roles.
   Together with Ferreri, Tognazzi made such films as ``Una Storia
Moderna: l'Ape Regina'' (The Conjugal Bed) in 1963, ``La Donna
Scimmia'' (The Ape Woman) in 1964, ``Marcia Nuziale'' (Wedding
March) in 1966, ``L'Udienza'' (The Audience) in 1971 and ``La
Grande Bouffe'' in 1973.
   He starred in the 1979 comedy ``La Cage Aux Folles'' and
appeared in Roger Vadim's film ``Barbarella.''
   In the 1970s and early 1980s, Tognazzi also tackled more serious
dramatic roles. In 1981 he won the Cannes Film Festival Palme d'Or
award as best actor for his role in Bernardo Bertolucci's ``La
Tragedia di un Uomo Ridicolo'' (The Tragedy of a Ridiculous Man).
   A funeral for Tognazzi will be held Tuesday at the church of
Santa Maria del Popolo in Rome.
   He is survived by his wife, Franca Bettoia, and four children.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0014 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 1202EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--SAfrica-Violence     10-28 0158</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--SAfrica-Violence,0153</SECOND>
<HEAD>Eight Killed, 37 Wounded in Black Faction Fighting</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JOHANNESBURG, South Africa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Rival black factions battled
through the night at a gold mine compound outside Johannesburg, and
company officials said Sunday that eight men were killed and 37
hurt.
   The fighting erupted Saturday evening at a workers hostel on
Rand Mines' Harmony Gold Mine in Virginia, 160 miles southwest of
Johannesburg, the company said.
   Officials said they did not know the cause of the fighting,
which went on through the night despite attempts by security
officers to halt the battles.
   No additional details were immediately available.
   About 800 blacks died in factional violence around Johannesburg
in August and September.
   The fighting between supporters of the African National Congress
and the Inkatha movement was mostly an extention of their power
struggle in the eastern province of Natal. That battle has claimed
about 5,000 lives since 1986.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0015 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 1208EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--BigSpender     10-28 0181</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Big Spender,0192</SECOND>
<HEAD>Sultan of Brunei Spends $950,000 on Birthday</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Sultan of Brunei, one of the world's richest
men, reportedly spent at least $950,000 on his nephew's ninth
birthday party.
   The Sunday Express said the sultan converted a ballroom at
Claridge's in London into a replica of Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles
headquarters.
   An army of workers turned the ballroom into a giant New York
City sewer for the party for young Prince Bahar, the paper said.
Four men dressed as the superheros, Donatello, Leonardo,
Michelangeo and Raphael, mingled with the young guests.
   A group of luxurious anterooms were transformed into a network
of gurglig drains, the paper said. Music was provided by the pop
duo Partners in Kryme, who were flown to London to perform their
hit ``Turtle Power,'' the newspaper said.
   Claridge's banqueting staff served pizza in a neon-lit pizza
parlor, The Sunday Express said. It did not say what day the party
took place.
   ``It was an incredible sight,'' said one member of Claridge's
staff, who spoke to the newspaper on condition of anonymity.
   The report could not be independently confirmed.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0016 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 1221EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--Iran-Britain     10-28 0163</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Iran-Britain,0157</SECOND>
<HEAD>British Embassy Reopens After 18-Month Break In Ties</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NICOSIA, Cyprus (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Great Britain reopened its embassy in
Tehran Sunday after an 18-month break in diplomatic relations over
the Salman Rushdie affair, the Islamic Republic News Agency
reported.
   At a ceremony, Swedish Ambassador Hakan Granqvist lowered the
Swedish flag at the embassy and British Charge d'Affaires David
Reddaway hoisted the British Union Jack.
   Sweden had looked after British interests in Iran during the
break in ties, which were restored last month after a meeting
between British Foreign Secretary Douglas Hurd and his Iranian
counterpart, Ali Akbar Velyati.
   Iran is to reopen its embassy in London on Monday.
   Relations were cut after the late Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini
declared a death sentence on Rushdie, an Indian-born British
novelist, in Feb. 1989 for allegedly blaspheming Islam in his novel
``The Satanic Verses.''
   Rushdie has been in hiding ever since, protected by British
police.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0017 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 1225EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-S&amp;Ls-MissingLetters Bjt   10-28 0464</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-S&amp;Ls-Missing Letters, Bjt,540</SECOND>
<HEAD>Congressional Letters on S&amp;Ls Missing, OTS Officials Say</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARCY GORDON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Dozens of letters are missing from the special
file of correspondence from members of Congress to savings and loan
regulators, according to the Office of Thrift Supervision.
   Most of the letters were written by lawmakers on behalf of
constituents who complained about problems in their dealings with
S&amp;Ls, such as accounts that were transferred from one thrift to
another as the result of mergers.
   But some letters provide evidence of members of Congress
pressing regulators on behalf of S&amp;L operators, some of whom
contributed to the lawmakers' political campaigns.
   There are thousands of letters, all maintained by the OTS and
filed alphabetically under the names of the senators and
representatives who sent them. The thrift supervision office, the
federal agency created by last year's S&amp;L bailout legislation,
keeps the letters for its own use and opens them to members of the
public by appointment.
   There is no supervision of people perusing the letters, which
are kept in an area of OTS' Washington headquarters that is out of
view of agency employees.
   Nancy Cohen, OTS' director of congressional correspondence, said
she is aware of at least one entire file that is missing. Each file
contains dozens of letters written by a member of Congress arranged
in chronological order.
   Ms. Cohen declined to say what file is missing or who may be
suspected of taking it.
   The agency has only one copy of each letter in the centralized
archives, although individual regulators may have kept their own
copies, Ms. Cohen said.
   ``I know something's missing and it really bothers me,'' she
said. ``I think it's real important to the agency'' to make the
files secure, she added, saying she has complained about the
situation to high-level OTS officials.
   ``There is a problem; we're trying to address the problem,''
said Robert Schmermund, director of public affairs for OTS.
   S&amp;L contributions and the role of some lawmakers has become a
hot issue in this election year. The escalating savings and loan
crisis has made the letter file a sought-after source of
information.
   Reporters have been the most frequent users of the files, but in
recent months congressional aides, political consultants and law
firms also have looked at them, Ms. Cohen said.
   ``It's an election year; everyone wants to see their own file,''
she said.
   People wishing to examine the files are asked to make an
appointment and bring with them a letter to OTS making a Freedom of
Information Act request for access to files of specific members of
Congress. Once there, they are left alone with the files in an area
separated by partitions from OTS employees. Users are allowed to
photocopy the letters.
   There is no inspection of bags and cases of people leaving the
OTS office.
   Schmermund said the agency is concerned about the vulnerability
of the current system but also wants to continue to give the public
quick access to the files. OTS Director Timothy Ryan wants the
agency to be ``as open as possible,'' Schmermund said.
   To obtain other OTS documents, outsiders must use them in the
agency's supervised reading room or submit formal Freedom of
Information requests that can take weeks to be answered.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0018 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 1228EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Obit-Shikanai     10-28 0306</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Shikanai,0331</SECOND>
<HEAD>Nobutaka Shikanai, Japanese Media Baron, Dead at 78</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Nobutaka Shikanai, who built the Fujisankei
Communications Group into Japan's largest media company, died
Sunday at age 78, the company announced.
   Shikanai died at Keio University Hospital in Tokyo, according to
an announcement from Fujisankei's office in London.
   He was instrumental in establishing the Praemium Imperiale
awards, and his company reportedly paid $2 million to former
President Ronald Reagan to visit Japan and attend the first awards
ceremony last year.
   Shikanai was born in Hokkaido on Nov. 17, 1911, and was a
graduate of the politics and economics department of Tokyo's Waseda
University in 1936.
   In 1954, with the creation of the Nippon Broadcasting System,
Shikanai began building the Fujisankei Communications Group, which
describes itself as the world's fourth-largest media conglomerate.
Its holdings include the Fuji Television Network, Inc., the
newspaper Sankei Shimbun, the Nippon Broadcasting System and record
and video companies.
   In 1989, he transferred the chairmanship of the group to his son
and took the title of senior executive adviser.
   He founded the Hakone Open-Air Museum in 1969 and the
Utsukushi-ga-hara Open-Air Museum in 1981.
   In 1988, as chairman of the Japan Art Foundation, Shikanai
announced the formation of the Praemium Imperiale awards for
painting, sculpture, architecture, music, and theater or film.
   The first winners of the $100,000 prizes were conductor Pierre
Boulez of France, filmmaker Marcel Carne of France, painters David
Hockney of Britain and Willem de Kooning of the United States,
sculptor Umberto Mastroianni of Italy, and U.S. architect I.M. Pei.
   In addition to Reagan, dignitaries at the ceremony included
Mayor Jacques Chirac of Paris, former Prime Minister Amintore
Fanfani of Italy, former Prime Minister Edward Heath of Britain and
former Chancellor Helmut Schmidt of West Germany.
   Shikanai served as director of the organizing committee for the
Tokyo Olympic Games in 1964 and vice president of the Winter
Olympic Games in Sapporo in 1972.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0019 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 1247EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-China-Politics     10-28 0516</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-China-Politics,0601</SECOND>
<HEAD>Attack on Pornography Cloaks Political Struggle</HEAD>
<HEAD>AP News Analysis</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KATHY WILHELM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   China's aging Marxist ideologues are organizing a
renewed attack on reformers in the guise of a campaign against the
country's tiny pornography industry.
   The Communist Party newspaper, the People's Daily, made the
connection explicitly Saturday at the end of a five-day
anti-pornography meeting called by the party Propaganda Department.
   Spreading pornography, the paper said, was one method used by
hostile foreign forces to undermine China's socialist system and
foster capitalism.
   ``The struggle against pornography is not just a matter of
banning a few bad books and tapes,'' it wrote in a front-page
editorial.
   ``It is an ideological struggle between socialist and capitalist
ideas, an expression of the class struggle between the proletariat
and the bourgeoisie. This struggle is linked to the success or
failure of China's socialist cause.''
   Anyone reading the People's Daily would think that dirty books
and videotapes are hawked on every corner of Beijing. In reality,
one has to hunt these days to find anything more titilating than
the collected speeches of 86-year-old senior leader Deng Xiaoping.
   But political debate has taken on strange forms ever since the
June 4, 1989 army attack on pro-democracy protesters in which
hundreds, and perhaps thousands, died.
   The real issues, too sensitive to be debated directly, are
these: Has the Communist Party lost its moral right to rule? What
system can make China peaceful and prosperous if socialism can't?
   Economics has been the main forum for political struggle.
Chinese and foreign sources say debate over the next five-year plan
for the economy is so heated they cannot convene a long-expected
party Central Committee meeting.
   At stake is whether China will resume reforms that reduced
central planning in favor of free market forces. But one European
diplomat said the bottom line is power - who will exercise top
authority after the death of Deng, now rarely seen in public.
   From that viewpoint, attacking pornography makes sense for the
conservatives, led by aging revolutionaries Wang Zhen, Bo Yibo,
Chen Yun and Deng Yingchao. It enables them to stay on the
offensive and fill large portions of the official press with
speeches representing their views.
   Even more liberal-minded party leaders, such as culture czar Li
Ruihuan, can hardly oppose a crackdown on pornography, although in
a speech applauding the campaign he cautioned against arbitrarily
interfering in ``legitimate aesthetic pursuits.''
   The campaign also provides a pretext for raiding book stalls and
investigating publishing houses. During a similar anti-pornography
drive shortly after the protests were crushed, 32 million
publications were burned, many for political reasons.
   Officials say 12 percent of the nation's newspapers and 13
percent of its social science periodicals were closed.
   ``If the campaign's really anti-pornography it will have no
affect on us,'' a Beijing intellectual said on condition of
anonymity.
   ``But if they are raising the banner of pornography to increase
repression, then it will stifle all intellectual inquiry. Already,
writers aren't writing anything - they've all shut up. There are no
new movies or plays or works of any kind.''
   Theaters have been reduced to reviving plays from the 1930s by
eminent playwright Cao Yu, now 90. In what passes for innovation,
one of Cao's plays, a gloomy melodrama about a Shanghai prostitute,
is being turned into a musical. It opens next month.
   ---&equals;
   EDITOR'S NOTE - Kathy Wilhelm, Associated Press Chief of Bureau
in Beijing, has reported from that city for three years.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0020 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 1252EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p AM-OaklandMayor     10-28 0453</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Oakland Mayor,0549</SECOND>
<HEAD>Two Liberal Democrats Vie for Oakland Mayor</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LAURA MYERS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>OAKLAND, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Both candidates in the Nov. 6 runoff
election to replace Mayor Lionel Wilson are liberal Democrats. Both
are 43. And their campaigns emphasize the same issues: drugs,
crime, education.
   The major difference is where they have worked. State
Assemblyman Elihu Harris has represented Oakland in the Legislature
in Sacramento for a dozen years, while his opponent, Wilson Riles
Jr., is an 11-year member of the City Council.
   ``I have been in this community working each day to improve
things,'' Riles said. ``I know the people. I know the issues up
close.
   ``Where has Harris been? That's the difference between us. I've
been here. He hasn't.''
   Harris counters that his legislative work has brought change to
the city.
   ``When I saw the Oakland school system was in trouble I
sponsored legislation to put an advisory trustee in there to clean
up,'' he said. ``Some schools were guilty of mismanagement,
nepotism and, in some cases, outright crime.''
   The voters, so far, have found Harris' distance from city
government more attractive. He got 45.7 percent of the votes in the
June non-partisan primary, more than runner-up Riles and the
third-place Wilson combined. Riles has narrowed the gap, but the
most recent poll, about a month before the election, showed Harris
still leading, 43 percent to 35 percent.
   Wilson was undone in his bid for a fourth term by his support
for a failed $602 million deal to lure pro football's Los Angeles
Raiders back to Oakland as well as voter discontent over a
community battered by crime and last year's earthquake.
   A city manager administers the day-to-day functions of city
government, so the mayor's four-year term is primarily a platform
for leadership.
   Harris plays up that aspect, saying he knows how to get things
done and arguing that Riles doesn't follow through on ideas.
   ``This job is one where you can make a lot of difference,''
Harris said. ``I think I can make a difference. Oakland can do
better.''
   Riles says the city has been making progress.
   ``People have already got together to run drugs out of their
neighborhoods,'' he said. ``It takes community action to pressure
landlords and hold anti-drug rallies. There are many successes.''
   But Riles, who has been endorsed by Wilson, concedes his chances
could be hurt by his ties to ``old city hall.''
   ``There's no question that we're going through a tough time
right now and people are looking for change,'' he said.
   Both candidates pledge to revive Oakland by pushing for
outpatient drug treatment programs, an increase in police officers,
better school and community anti-drug programs, and economic
development.
   Oakland is known more for bad neighborhoods, crack houses and
prostitution than its developing shopping areas, beautiful salty
Lake Merritt and championship Oakland Athletics baseball team.
   The city of 360,000 people sits across the bay from San
Francisco, which has twice as many people but about half the
violent crime. So far this year, 134 people have been murdered in
Oakland, compared with 85 in San Francisco. Last year, Oakland had
a record 148 murders and San Francisco had 73.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0021 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 1302EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-HotelDemolished     10-28 0411</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Hotel Demolished,0499</SECOND>
<HEAD>Parkview Hilton, a Downtown Hartford Landmark, Demolished</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto HF1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PETER VILES</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HARTFORD, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Parkview Hilton, a modern-style
glass-walled hotel that was just 36 years old, was demolished
Sunday after its owners were unable to find a buyer for the vacant
building.
   A festive crowd estimated at 10,000 watched the explosion from
Bushnell Park, a sloping green that stands between the hotel and
the state Capitol and gave the hotel its name.
   The 16-story building was imploded - exploded from within so
that it would fall on itself - by demolition workers who used 60
pounds of carefully placed dynamite. The first blasts rang out at
about 7:30 a.m., and the building was gone within seconds, bringing
a rowdy cheer from the crowd.
   The Parkview had been vacant since Dec. 31 when it closed its
doors, a victim of the sagging demand for hotel space in Hartford.
The owners of the building, Chase Enterprises, could not find a
buyer for the property, and decided to destroy it to make way for
something new.
   The demolition was the second this year in downtown Hartford,
where the booming economy of the mid-1980s has given way to a deep
economic slump that has halted development.
   There are no firm plans to develop the Hilton site, but it is
one of several Hartford sites under consideration for the new
corporate headquarters of United Technologies Corp.
   ``You hate to see something like that go down. It's still a fine
building,'' said Helmut Garbemann, a retired construction worker
from Newington who watched the building fall. ``It's a shame. It's
too bad the city is dying out like this.''
   But most in the crowd seemed drawn by curiosity rather than
nostalgia, and the mood was similar to those watching a fireworks
display. Scores of people recorded the event on video cameras,
waiting patiently in 34-degree weather.
   ``I've always watched on TV, but this is the first time I've
ever seen one of these up close,'' said Edward Danoff of West
Springfield, Mass., who took his three grandchildren on the 30-mile
trip to Hartford to watch the event.
   The hotel, built in 1954, was one of Hartford's first
modern-looking skyscrapers. Although it was supported inside by
concrete pillars, it appeared all steel and glass from the outside.
   It had been a Hilton hotel since 1966 when the chain assumed
full ownership; after Hilton sold the building in the mid-1970s,
the hotel retained the name.
   James Manafort, president of Manafort Brothers Inc., the company
that destroyed the building, said it collapsed just as planned,
with no complications.
   ``We've very pleased,'' he said. ``It was a 100 percent shot.''
   The same company demolished the Hartford-Aetna Building on April
1. That building was destroyed to make room for new development,
despite the objections of local preservationists, who said it was
one of the city's oldest skyscrapers.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0022 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 1309EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p AM-All'sFair Bjt   10-28 0638</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-All's Fair, Bjt,730</SECOND>
<HEAD>It's Class Warfare, 1990-Style</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JILL LAWRENCE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   ``If you make big money, here's good news,''
opens a fast-talking political commercial from north-central
Indiana. ``Candidate John Johnson ... is for lower tax rates for
the wealthy.''
   And that's not all.
   ``As a millionaire himself, maybe John Johnson doesn't know how
middle-income families are struggling these days,'' the ad
continues. ``But Congressman Jim Jontz does. He wants to stop tax
breaks for the wealthy and give middle-income families some help
for a change.''
   Welcome to class warfare, 1990-style. At least that's what
Republicans are calling it. Democrats prefer to characterize their
latest campaign theme as a quest for ``fairness'' - for the poor
and middle-class Americans they say have suffered from a decade of
greed and negligence fostered by the Republicans.
   Ever since the savings and loan scandal broke, Democrats have
been putting new emphasis on the theme that they are the party of
ordinary people while claiming the GOP cares more about the
wealthy.
   Their job has been eased considerably by the prolonged budget
battle and President Bush's public wavering over whether to raise
taxes on the rich. Polls show him and many of his party's
candidates on a downward slide - and some Democrats already are
declaring victory.
   ``The Democrats have won the fairness issue. It is driving the
polls and it will drive the elections,'' said Rep. Beryl Anthony,
D-Ark., chairman of the Democratic Congressional Campaign
Committee. ``The president has very clearly staked out territory
that his own candidates can't defend.''
   Republicans traditionally have an advantage when the political
debate is over whether or not to raise taxes, as Bush demonstrated
in 1988. But when the issue becomes whose taxes to raise, the edge
goes to the Democrats.
   The GOP position is based on the theory that well-off people, if
allowed to keep their money, will invest it and fuel the economy.
The Democratic line is epitomized in a commercial made by the
national party:
   ``In the '80s, tax breaks for the rich drove up the deficit
while middle-income working families got squeezed. Democrats don't
want you to get stuck with the bill again. We're fighting for
fairness. Isn't that what America's all about?''
   Numerous Democrats are taking their cues from the ad, some even
going so far as to borrow its contrasting images of limousines and
party-goers vs. farmers and factory workers.
   The populist refrain has helped revive the Democratic
gubernatorial campaigns of Ann Richards in Texas and Tony
Celebrezze in Ohio. And it's giving fresh ammunition to embattled
incumbents and long-shot challengers in New Hampshire and Kentucky,
Iowa and Colorado, Alabama and Washington state.
   Will the election really come down to a question of fat cats
versus working stiffs? Rick Shelby, political director of the
National Republican Senatorial Committee, says that's ``an
oversimplification of the true facts, but nevertheless something we
have to deal with.''
   His advice to GOP candidates is to ``oppose taxes and support
the elderly.''
   Many Republican candidates are, in fact, holding fast to the
no-new-taxes position that Bush embraced and then abandoned, even
as they try to portray themselves as friends of senior citizens and
the disadvantaged. Others are sounding more and more like populist
Democrats.
   ``Unlike some folks around here, I think everyone should pay
their fair share, including the rich,'' Sen. Mitch McConnell,
R-Ky., says in a campaign ad.
   Two Republican Senate candidates are criticizing the latest
federal budget agreement in the same terms.
   ``It does not hit the mark of fairness and equity,'' said Sen.
William Cohen, R-Maine.
   ``The vast majority of the money is coming out of the middle
class,'' objected Rep. Tom Tauke, R-Iowa.
   Tauke is facing a full-scale populist assault by Democratic Sen.
Tom Harkin. When Harkin ran a rich-poor ad featuring a pyramid of
collapsing champagne glasses, Tauke countered with a spot
highlighting Harkin's vacation home in the Bahamas.
   Tauke said he had to do it because Harkin's ``class-warfare
ads'' were working.
   Josie Heath, the Democratic Senate candidate in Colorado, ran
into some backlash after running a fairness ad.
   Heath's ad said a lot of wealthy people got wealthier in the
last 10 years and ``they're paying less taxes. And we had the
middle class and working people earning less and paying more.
That's wrong.''
   What Heath didn't mention, analysts noted, was that she and her
husband are millionaires. Said one: ``Heath's reference to the
wealthy as `they' is dubious.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0023 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 1344EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Bambi'sInvestigator     10-28 0655</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bambi's Investigator,0829</SECOND>
<HEAD>Investigator Has Made Bambi's Case `Life's Work'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BRIAN BASHINSKI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MILWAUKEE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Private investigator Ira B. Robins proudly
describes it as his ``life's work.''
   For six years he has risked slander suits, amassed $30,000 in
debts and endured ridicule while seeking evidence to reverse the
murder conviction of former Playboy waitress and and onetime
fugitive Lawrencia Bembenek.
   ``I so much believe in what I'm doing you couldn't pay me; it's
something you have to do from the heart,'' said Robins, 48. ``This
is an opportunity that people don't get very often in their lives.
   ``There have been no days off. Morning, noon and night I'm going
to meetings and rally, chasing leads, talking to witnesses or the
media.''
   Robins, a former police officer, said the volunteer
investigation he began in 1984 has left him without a home - he
lives in the basement of a friend's house - and without enough
money to repair his wrecked car or pay support for his 12-year-old
son, alimony to his former wife or back taxes to the government.
   He also has failed to persuade authorities to free Ms. Bembenek,
who was convicted in the 1981 killing of Christine Schultz, the
former wife of Ms. Bembenek's then-husband, Elfred Schultz. Ms.
Bembenek was sentenced to life in prison.
   The 32-year-old Ms. Bembenek, popularly known as ``Bambi,''
created a media sensation when she escaped from prison July 15.
Canadian police captured her with her fiance, Dominic Gugliatto,
35, on Oct. 17 in Thunder Bay, Ontario. She is awaiting extradition
back to Wisconsin.
   During her murder trial, prosecutors contend Ms. Bembenek was
upset about the $700-a-month alimony Schultz had to pay the victim.
   Robins said he has collected more than 10,000 pages of documents
and has interviewed several witnesses who claim the evidence used
by prosecutors was faulty.
   ``The more I got going on it, the more I was convinced there was
something wrong,'' he said.
   Some supporters claim Ms. Bembenek, who was fired from the
police department in 1980 for lying about a friend's marijuana
arrest, was framed by police because she had knowledge about
alleged police corruption.
   They also note that during her trial, one of Ms. Schultz's young
sons testified that the person seen in the house the night of the
killing was not Ms. Bembenek.
   The evidence Robins has released includes an affidavit from a
neighbor of Ms. Bembenek that suggest prosecutors' key evidence -
the wig believed to have been worn by the killer and then flushed
down Ms. Bembenek's toilet - may actually have been flushed by
another woman.
   But police, prosecutors and the courts repeatedly have ruled
that Robins hasn't found anything to warrant reopening the case.
And some are aggravated with his incessant charges of a coverup.
   Police Chief Philip Arreola says the portly, bespectacled Robins
has acted out of an infatuation with Ms. Bembenek, who also has
been a model and calendar pinup.
   Milwaukee's chief prosecutor says Robins is seeking to profit
from a murder case that has gained international attention and
become a favorite of tabloid television.
   Robins denies both contentions, saying his motivation is to seek
the justice he believes has been denied. He particularly bristles
at the suggestion he's infatuated with Ms. Bembenek.
   ``I'm not in love with her,'' he said. He said he didn't even
meet Ms. Bembenek until eight months after he began his
investigation.
   He said the tens of thousands of dollars he's spent on the
investigation was his own money, except for $9,000 he borrowed from
friends and $1,800 in donations from Ms. Bembenek's supporters.
   A police union threatened recently to sue Robins for slander for
his remarks to news media, which sometimes have named specific
officers involved in the alleged coverup.
   Robins said he welcomes any lawsuits and will use the ``absolute
truth'' as his defense.
   His critics also have accused him of stirring the debate for his
own profit, citing an agreement with Ms. Bembenek entitling Robins
to a 25 percent cut on the sale of movie and book rights.
   Robins acknowledges such an agreement exists and also noted the
recent exposure of her case had landed him appearances on several
television talk and news shows. Executives at most of the shows
said Robins was not paid for his appearances, except for money to
cover transportation.
   But Robins said he hasn't discussed any book or movie deals
although dozens of agents have contacted him about selling his
rights or representing him in future sales. He said he will one day
deserve the proceeds from books or movies - but only after Ms.
Bembenek is freed.
   ``I can't spend the time right now to set up a deal because I
have a case to win and I can't stop until justice is served,'' he
said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0024 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 1350EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p AM-Who'stheBadGuy? Bjt   10-28 0691</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Who's the Bad Guy?, Bjt,800</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush, Quayle Blast Democrats Who Break Promises on Taxes</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP News Analysis</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By WALTER R. MEARS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Special Correspondent</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>RUNNEMEDE, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   ``We have to beat a legend,'' the
candidate lamented. ``A legend that lied.''
   The topic was taxes: the complaint, a broken campaign promise
not to increase them. In this case, the promise came from a
Democrat who couldn't keep it, and Republicans were making the most
of it - ignoring the parallel to President Bush's own tax reversal.
   In the wrapup phase of the off-year election campaign, there's a
battle raging for control of the tax issue.
   Bush and Vice President Dan Quayle, the high-profile Republican
campaigners, are trying to fix blame for the coming tax increases
on the Democrats, even though the administration signed on to the
budget deal to raise them.
   The Democrats contend that the issue was fairness, that they had
to fight the administration to make sure the wealthiest Americans
would pay the biggest share in deficit-curbing taxes.
   Bush's ritual campaign promise of 1988 - ``Read my lips, no new
taxes'' - is long gone, a casualty of his decision last spring to
negotiate a deficit deal with the Democratic Congress.
   The president said he had to compromise. ``Haven't liked that a
bit, but I've done it because the president must at certain times
put the overall good of the country first,'' he said, campaigning
in Irvine, Calif., on Friday.
   He said the tax medicine had to be taken ``because the
Democratically controlled Congress simply has been on an
uncontrolled spending binge for years.''
   Quayle pressed the argument in a television interview Sunday,
saying ``Democrats got taxes, we got spending cuts.''
   On the NBC program ``Meet the Press,'' Quayle discounted
pollsters and analysts who say there's a Democratic surge, saying
that ratings always fluctuate in ``the political silly season.''
   He said it's the Democrats who have the problem because ``the
American people have had it'' and they're fed up with incumbents.
   At some campaign stops, the Republican rhetoric sounds as though
Bush had never uttered his ``no new taxes'' promise in the first
place.
   That heightened the irony the other day when Quayle campaigned
for Daniel Mangini, the Republican candidate for Congress in New
Jersey Gov. Jim Florio's old district. Mangini promises to vote
against any federal tax increases. The Democratic nominee, Robert
Andrews, says he would oppose higher taxes for at least two years.
   Democrat Florio held the seat for 15 years before he was elected
governor in 1989, pledging that he wouldn't raise state taxes. He
pushed $2.8 billion in increases through the legislature this year.
   So the 250 or so people at the Holiday Inn waved scores of
bright red signs that read ``Florio Lied'' as Quayle urged votes
for Mangini.
   ``The Democrats, they'll raise your taxes whenever they get a
chance,'' the vice president said. ``Just look what's going on in
Trenton. Your governor's taken a page right out of the book written
by Michael Dukakis and Mario Cuomo...
   ``Your high-taxing governor has had the best training in the
world for raising taxes, years and years of loyal and devoted
service to the Democrat majority in the Congress,'' Quayle said.
   Long before the budget negotiations, the Republican theme was
that Democrats were the party of taxing and spending. Ronald Reagan
pushed it, after muscling through the massive federal tax cut of
1981 that was supposed to spur the economy and lead to a balanced
budget. It didn't work; the deficit soared despite economic
expansion. The government reported Friday that it hit a near-record
$220.4 billion during the year ended Sept. 30.
   The Republicans argue that is because of excessive spending. The
Democrats counter that revenues are out of whack, too, and have
been since the big Reagan tax reduction, despite tax increases
since.
   Quayle said taxes were part of the budget deal only because the
Democrats were adamant and insisted that ``you've got to put taxes
on the table.'' So the question shifted from no taxes to which
taxes.
   ``The wealthy are going to be paying more taxes, everyone can be
assured of that,'' Quayle said on the political point that worries
Republicans most. ``The wealthy are going to be paying their fair
share despite what the perception is or is not.''
   ``We're the party that is trying to keep the taxes down,'' Bush
said last week. ``When they talk about taxing the rich, they're
talking about taxing the working men and women of this country.''
   ``I believe the American people know who's responsible for
increased taxes,'' Quayle said.
   But he acknowledged that the whole budget flap had been
politically painful for the administration, and therefore, for
Republicans.
   ``We've had a couple rough weeks,'' he said. But he added that
election campaigns go in cycles. ``I think we'll start to turn it
around,'' he said.
   ---
   EDITOR'S NOTE - Walter R. Mears, vice president and columnist
for The Associated Press, has reported on Washington and national
politics for more than 25 years.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0025 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 1404EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--Israel-Error     10-28 0143</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Israel-Error,0128</SECOND>
<HEAD>Officials Say They Mistranslated Key Word in Report</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Israel, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Government Press Office said Sunday it
mistranslated a key word in the report by the commission that
investigated the Oct. 8 riot on the Temple Mount in which 20
Palestinians died.
   A sentence in the English version of the Hebrew-language report
said that during the police charge against stone-throwing Arabs,
there was ``indiscriminate use of live ammunition.''
   The Government Press Office, which translated the report, said
Sunday that ``indiscriminate'' should have read ``unsupervised.''
It apologized for the error.
   The report of the government-appointed commission was published
Friday. Yossi Olmert, director of the Government Press Office, said
the announcement of the correction was delayed because of the
Jewish Sabbath.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0026 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 1424EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-France-WarCrimes     10-28 0522</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-France-War Crimes,0635</SECOND>
<HEAD>Authorities Accused Of Reluctance To Try War Crimes Cases</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARILYN AUGUST</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Lawyers and human rights activists say the
prosecution of three alleged Nazi collaborators has been stalled or
dragged out because of a reluctance to expose French complicity in
the Holocaust.
   War crimes charges against one of the men, Maurice Papon, have
been pending for seven years. Another, Rene Bousquet, was
implicated in 1949 for his activities as police chief in the Vichy
regime, but only now faces the possibility of a trial.
   The third alleged war criminal, Paul Touvier, is on trial for
his activities as a pro-Nazi militia chief in Lyon.
   Representatives of the International Federation of Human Rights
say authorities have failed to relieve the judge of other cases to
make the trial move more swiftly.
   ``We believe it is no accident that these three men have not
been tried,'' said Yves Jouffa, president of the French League of
Human Rights, at a recent news conference.
   ``It is because they are part of what the English call the
establishment, whether it be in politics, business, industry or
high society.... This milieu does not want to see its dirty laundry
washed in public.''
   Bousquet, 81, headed the national police during the Nazi
occupation. State prosecutors last month asked that he be
investigated in connection with the deportation of 194 Jewish
children during the war.
   A Paris criminal court court ruled Oct. 19 that Bousquet could
only be tried by the High Court of the Liberation, formed in 1944
to prosecute officials of the Vichy regime. The Liberation court
has been defunct for decades, and the ruling by the Paris judges
indicated Bousquet would escape prosecution.
   However, at the request of state prosecutors, an appeals court
plans to make a final ruling on the jurisdiction issue Nov. 19.
   Serge Klarsfeld, a lawyer and prominent Nazi hunter, said senior
government officials, including President Francois Mitterrand,
appear reluctant to pursue the case.
   ``I think Mitterrand doesn't want this trial to open,''
Klarsfeld said. ``I can only hypothesize that there is a certain
indulgence toward Vichy.''
   Should the case go to trial, Bousquet would be the highest
ranking French official in the Vichy government to be tried for
crimes against humanity.
   Bousquet was condemned in 1949 for his activities under Nazi
occupation, but the decision was reversed for ``acts accomplished
in favor of the Resistance'' - namely, his decision to free some
jailed resistance fighters.
   Jouffa, who spent part of World War II in a French internment
camp, said none of the high-ranking French political figures with
direct roles in deporting and arresting 100,000 Jews during the war
have been brought to justice.
   He said the recent trial of the Gestapo chief in Lyon, Klaus
Barbie, ``was the trial of Nazi Germany, not collaborationist
France.
   The human rights federation said it had organized an inquiry
commission to determine why the cases were taking so long. Their
report is being submitted to the United Nations and the Council of
Europe.
   ``We hope that the very fact that we have carried out this
mission will be enough to create movement in high places and allow
these proceedings to be accelerated,'' Jouffa said.
   Papon, a former budget minister, has been accused of
responsibility for the arrests and deportations of 1,700 Jews while
an administrator in Bordeaux during the war. Now 81, he served in
many high-profile positions after the war, including a stint as
Paris police chief.
   Touvier, 75, worked with Barbie in Lyon. He went into hiding in
1973, and was arrested in May 1989 at a priory in Nice run by
followers of Archbishop Marcel Lefevbre, the fundamentalist Roman
Catholic leader.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0027 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 1455EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p AM-MassachusettsGovernor 1stLd-Writethru a 10-28 0581</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Massachusetts Governor, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0746,650</SECOND>
<HEAD>Two Outsiders Competing to Succeed Dukakis</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-All's Fair Bjt</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS last graf to include Illinois among close races; delete
Rhode Island. Note language in 3rd graf</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By DANIEL BEEGAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The race for Massachusetts governor hardly has
been marked by the gentility one might expect from a contest
between a university president and an upper-crust Harvard-educated
lawyer.
   Republican William Weld has pulled few punches in his fight with
Democrat John Silber, the president of Boston University, a
philosopher and Immanuel Kant scholar. Weld refers to Silber as
``Dr. Know It All.''
   And despite the fact that Silber called for a cleaned-up
campaign, he was forced to apologize last week for calling Weld a
``back-stabbing son of a bitch.'' That was a reference to Weld's
resignation from the Justice Department in 1988 because of concerns
with the ethics of then-Attorney General Edwin Meese.
   Weld accused Silber of harboring ``crazy ideas'' when the
Democrat suggested some women have neglected their children by
deciding to work outside the home.
   Silber retaliated by criticizing Weld's mother, who died in
1986. Silber said he did not need to be lectured by a
multimillionaire ``whose mother never worked a day in her life.''
   Weld's mother taught drama and worked as a volunteer for a
non-profit company that helped place handicapped people in jobs,
protested a Weld spokesman.
   For all their bickering, Weld and Silber do agree on one thing:
their criticism of how Gov. Michael S. Dukakis has handled the job.
   Dukakis, whose popularity plummeted when the state hit the
economic skids after his unsuccessful 1988 presidential run,
decided not to seek re-election.
   Both Silber and Weld have promised to overhaul state government
and cut state spending to accommodate state tax collections that
have been in a nose dive.
   With polls showing Silber slightly ahead, the dogfight is likely
to come down to the wire. The uncertainty is reinforced by polls
before the primary election that failed to anticipate Silber's win
and understated Weld's margin of support.
   Weld served as a U.S. attorney in Massachusetts, gaining a
reputation as an aggressive prosecutor of white-collar crime,
before joining the Justice Department, where he was an assistant
U.S. attorney general.
   The political outsider image cultivated by both candidates has
served them well in a state where angry primary voters kicked out
the incumbent attorney general, denied the House speaker the
nomination for treasurer and knocked out several incumbent state
legislators.
   Republicans see the Nov. 6 election as their best chance to
capture the governor's office since 1974, but Silber's criticism of
Dukakis has made it more difficult for Weld to run against the lame
duck.
   Dukakis has said he'll vote for Silber despite their cool
relationship.
   ``People, even if they don't love him, are beginning to see that
this guy stands for something and that the other guy doesn't,''
Dukakis said.
   But Senate President William Bulger, one of Silber's earliest
supporters, said he didn't want ``to presume (Silber) will be
elected governor. He's in a very difficult political race.''
   The major issue dividing the two men is an initiative that, if
passed, would roll back most state taxes and fees to 1988 levels.
The state has had several major tax and fee increases in the last
two years.
   Weld supports the initiative. While Silber has endorsed its
motives, he has said the initiative itself ``will force the
collapse of the state government and our economy by rigid
formula.''
   Despite tax increases and recent sharp spending cuts,
Massachusetts still faces a precariously balanced budget.
   Both candidates acknowledge spending will have to be cut further
with or without the initiative, which would trim $1.2 billion from
state tax collections this fiscal year and about double that in
fiscal 1992.
   The Silber-Weld race is one of 14 tight campaigns for governor
around the country with just over a week to go until Election Day.
The others are in California, Texas, Florida, Alabama, Nebraska,
Kansas, Maine, Illinois, Vermont, Alaska, Oregon, Ohio and
Oklahoma.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0028 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 1455EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Obit-Demy     10-28 0296</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Demy,0347</SECOND>
<HEAD>Jacques Demy, French Film Director, Dead at 59</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Jacques Demy, the French master of musical comedies
best known for his 1963 film ``Les Parapluies de Cherbourg,'' has
died of a brain hemorrhage brought on by leukemia, associates said
Sunday. He was 59.
   Demy died Saturday night, the associates said.
   Demy brought to France the musical comedy style popularized in
Hollywood but never big in this country. Among his other major
musicals was the acclaimed ``Les Demoiselles de Rochefort'' (The
Maidens of Rochefort) of 1966, starring Catherine Deneuve and her
elder sister, Francoise Dorleac.
   He also directed the film version of the fairy tale ``Peau
d'Ane'' (Donkey Skin) in 1970 starring Miss Deneuve.
   ``Les Parapluies de Cherbourg'' (The Umbrellas of Cherbourg)
firmly established Demy as a leading director of musicals by
winning the Palme D'Or award at the Cannes Film Festival.
   Born in the Atlantic village of Pontchateau in 1931, Demy
studied at the Technical College of Fine Arts in Nantes and the
Technical School of Photography in Paris.
   After turning out several short films, his first feature-length
piece, ``Lola'' (1960) with Anouk Aimee, was warmly received by
critics who placed him among those active in ``nouveau cinema'' at
the turn of the decade.
   In 1962 he directed ``La Baie des Anges'' (Window of Angels)
with Jeanne Moreau, a story of two gamblers at the oceanside
casinos of Nice, which also reflected Demy's passion of the sea.
That year he married fellow director Agnes Varda.
   He won the national Grand Prix of Cinema for his 1982 ``Chambre
en Ville'' (A Room in the City). He called the film a ``musical
tragicomedy,'' explaining at the time that ``in the last 20 years,
since `Les Parapluies de Cherbourg,' things have changed. My story
is more violent, more passionate, and has become more funny.''
   His last film was ``Trois Places Pour le 26'' (Three Places for
the 26) in 1988, which marked the return of Yves Montand to cinema.
   He and Ms. Varda had one son, Mathieu.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0029 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 1509EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People Sub a0752 10-28 0144</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People, Sub, a0752,0147</SECOND>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS OAKLAND, Calif.-dated last item in rdp to CORRECT
spelling of O'Connor in penultimate graf.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>OAKLAND, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   David Letterman has come up with several
reasons the Oakland Athletics lost the World Series to the
Cincinnati Reds.
   The A's were ``too busy choreographing nude locker room dance
number for female reporters,'' according to the No. 1 reason on the
talk show host's list of ``Top 10 Oakland A's excuses.''
   Among the other reasons were that the A's were too busy worrying
about the budget crisis and were upset that Sinead O'Connor refused
to sing the national anthem. The Irish singer created a brouhaha
this summer when she wouldn't let the anthem be performed before a
concert of hers.
   The No. 10 excuse: ``Thought it was best out of 17 - planned on
stunning nine-game comeback,'' Letterman said Friday night.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0030 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 1511EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Budget-Vignettes     10-28 0546</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Budget-Vignettes,650</SECOND>
<HEAD>In Gallop To Adjournment, Congress Hits a Rough Spot or Two</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ALAN FRAM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   When the congressional session - and the hour
- grow late, the strain takes its toll on lawmakers, and each
reflects it in different ways. Here are some vignettes from
Congress' closing hours last week.
   ---
   Rep. Henry Hyde, R-Ill., was upset.
   One of Congress' most conservative lawmakers, Hyde thought the
House had passed a tough anti-crime bill earlier this year. But
Saturday night, when the adjournment-bound House debated the
compromise version of the bill reached between the House and
Senate, he was no longer pleased.
   ``It left here as Arnold Schwarzenegger,'' he lamented, ``and
came back as Woody Allen.''
   ---
   The House Rules Committee met at 10 p.m. Friday to decide the
procedure for the debate on the deficit-reduction bill, a measure
on which a final vote was not taken until seven the next morning.
   Rep. Lynn Martin, R-Ill., didn't like the idea of a debate that
seemed likely to not even begin until 2 a.m. She suspected that
legislative leaders trying to ram the deficit-reduction bill
through the House were hoping to bring the bill to the floor when
lawmakers were too weary to resist.
   ``Is that part of the deal, you don't want them alive and
awake?'' she asked House Budget Committee Chairman Leon Panetta,
D-Calif.
   ``Some would argue that at 9 a.m., they're not alive and
awake,'' Panetta responded.
   ---
   Martin also was disconcerted because the Rules Committee was
being asked to make a decision about a complicated, crucial bill
that none of the panel's members had even seen. That's life on the
Rules panel, which is dominated by Democrats.
   ``Are we going to get to see the bill?'' she asked.
   ``Not until we do,'' responded Rep. Anthony Bielenson, D-Calif.
   ``You mean we're not going to see the bill?'' she said.
   ``It's easier that way,'' he answered.
   ---
   Much consternation was caused by the revelation that a provision
was slipped into the deficit-reduction bill giving a tax break to
an insurance company in Portland, Maine, the home state of Senate
Democratic Leader George Mitchell.
   The 1,600-page measure was so complex that few lawmakers had
much information about what it actually contained. The Maine tax
break was eventually removed from the bill. But for some reason, it
put a sour taste in the mouths of many legislators.
   ``I'd really hate it to find out after we voted it that the
state of Maine was forgiven all taxation until the next
generation,'' worried Rep. Louise Slaughter, D-N.Y.
   ---
   The ranking Republican on the House Budget Committee, Rep. Bill
Frenzel of Minnesota, is one of Capitol Hill's most accomplished
budget quote-meisters. Here are his explanations of why a pair of
provisions were in the bill:
   A series of taxes on luxury items such as fancy cars and yachts:
``To satisfy the Democratic blood lust to get at rich people.''
   A seemingly non-budgetary section that dealt with noise at
airports: ``To quiet down four committees in the House and to keep
the secretary of transportation from going ballistic.''
   ---
   The House's Democratic leaders spent much of Friday lining up
votes for the budget. Because they were only counting on about 40
votes from the Republican minority, Democrats figured that they
needed 180 of their 258 members to assure House passage.
   One problem they faced was with the Congressional Black Caucus.
Many of the group's 24 members - all Democrats - said they would
oppose the deficit-reduction bill as a protest against the Senate's
failure earlier in the week to override President Bush's veto of
the civil rights bill.
   Rep. Charles Rangel, D-N.Y., said leaders were trying to coax
him into voting for the bill. What could they offer him to get his
vote, he was asked.
   ``It's going to have to be the top of the presidential ticket,''
he joked.
   Rangel ended up voting against the budget.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0031 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 1546EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-ShipBoarded 1stLd-Writethru a0748 10-28 0318</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Ship Boarded, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0748,0382</SECOND>
<HEAD>Iraqi Ship Boarded, Searched</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 7th graf pvs, `The ship's ...' to CORRECT first reference
to U.S. frigate. Pickup 8th pvs, `The Darwin...'</NOTE>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf Rdp</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT DVORCHAK</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DHAHRAN, Saudi Arabia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An Iraqi tanker was boarded by U.S.
Marines Sunday after two warships fired warning shots across its
bow when it refused to stop, U.S. Navy officials said.
   For the first time during the sea blockade against Iraq, two
warplanes from the carrier USS Independence flew six low-level
passes near the ship as part of the interception, Navy Cmdr. J.D.
Van Sickle said.
   As of Oct. 26, some 2,738 ships had been intercepted in the
Persian Gulf region as part of the blockade. There have been 282
ships boarded, included 224 by U.S. forces. Twelve ships have been
diverted to other ports.
   The ship was allowed to proceed, however, after a search party
conducted an inspection and found no goods banned under the U.N.
sanctions imposed on Iraq in retaliation for its Aug. 2 conquest of
Kuwait.
   ``No prohibitive cargo was found, and the ship was allowed to
proceed. It is now under way,'' said Van Sickle.
   The vessel Amuriyah was intercepted before dawn in the North
Arabian Sea off Marirah Island near the coast of Oman.
   The ship's master told the Australian guided-missile cruiser
HMAS Darwin and the U.S. Navy frigate Reasoner it was headed for
Basra, Iraq, but refused to stop and allow a boarding party.
   The Darwin fired .50-caliber machine gun rounds across the bow
at about 7:15 a.m. local time (1:15 a.m. EST) and the Reasoner
fired two rounds from its 5-inch deck guns about 10 minutes later.
   ``It ignored the warning shots and signaled its intention it was
not going to stop,'' Van Sickle said.
   A team of Marines from the USS Ogden flew in by helicopter and
slid down ropes onto the ship's deck at 8:50 a.m. (2:50 a.m. EST).
   A boarding tem of Australians, U.S. Coast Guards members and
U.S. Navy personnel conducted the five-hour search. The USS Ogden
and British frigate HMS Brazen also assisted in the operation, the
officials said.
   The Amuriyah weighs 157,000 tons when loaded and was built in
1977.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0032 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 1551EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-AmericanForecaster     10-28 0526</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-American Forecaster,0664</SECOND>
<HEAD>Forecaster Predicts Rage For Organic Coffee, Gourmet Ice And Having
Fun</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOE WHEELAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DENVER (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   ``Success surgery'' for executives, organic coffee
and ``gourmet'' ice - yes, ice, not ice cream - will be all the
rage next year, a forecaster predicts, who says America is quickly
approaching a time when baby boomers just want to have fun.
   Other trends to expect in 1991: ``retro-chic'' appliances with a
post-World War II look; revived interest in station wagons,
libraries; the 1960s look in clothes, and Italian fast-food
franchises, according to ``The American Forecaster 1991.''
   On the homefront, the Santa Fe home interior look will be out,
as will be Japan-bashing. And baseball doubleheaders will go the
way of Shoeless Joe.
   Author Kim Long says desktop lunches and executive facelifts
will be symptomatic of Americans' intensified interest in their
work, but 1991 will not be the dawn of an age of workaholism.
   ``I think the '90s is going to be a fun decade,'' said Long.
`Most people in the big `baby boom' age group will be in their 40s
and 50s. They will have earned a living and raised families. I
think that equates to a potential situation where people will look
to do fun things, to worry less about what the neighbors think or
families think.
   ``They may drop out of careers to do what they always wanted to
do, to be what they always wanted to be when they grew up,'' he
said.
   But corporate America won't turn on and drop out altogether.
Companies in 1991 will be streamlining their operations to remain
competitive. Long looks for more workers to eat lunch at their
desks so they can become more productive.
   Along the same line, executives will turn more often to cosmetic
surgery as a way to prop up their corporate image, Long said. The
sought-after look will be ``relatively small noses, not a prominent
chin - but a chinless looks is unacceptable, and wrinkles would be
out,'' he said.
   Long, 41, of Denver began writing the Forecaster in 1983, and
his book sells about 10,000 copies a year. This year's edition,
which will be released in November, has a new look to it. It is
pocket-size, and its cover is illustrated by a human head with
lightning bolts shooting from it.
   Long said he researches trends by reading numerous newspapers
and magazines, keeping files on particular topics, and monitors
computer data bases.
   In it, Long predicts that organic coffee, grown without
pesticides, will hit big in 1991.
   ``That has all the makings of a major food fad,'' he said.
``People are becoming a lot more literate about what they put into
their mouths. They're willing to spend more money for the
details.''
   Another trend that has hit Japan and soon will arrive in the
United States is ``gourmet'' ice - ice up to 10,000 years old that
is chipped from Alaskan ice floes and is valued for its purity.
   Clothing fashions will continue their tilt toward 1960s styles -
hot pants, minikirts and baggy jeans for women, and garish ties and
baggy pants for men. Long says shoulder pads in women's clothing
will become just another old trend as designers focus their
attention on emphasizing women's busts.
   The boxy appliances that marked the dawn of the post-World War
II era will make a reappearance in 1991, Long said. ``It's the
visual appeal, so solid and heavy - the beginning of the atomic
era. It looks appropriate to certain people now,'' he said.
   People also are rediscovering libraries, and the number of
libraries is on the rise, said Long. ``The new buzzword is
`information literacy,' teaching people about how to be more
capable of finding their own answers.''
   Besides writing the Forecaster, Long is a newspaper columnist
and is author of a soon-to-be-published directory called
``Educational Destinations and Field Trips.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0033 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 1554EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-HalloweenHanging     10-28 0303</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Halloween Hanging,0368</SECOND>
<HEAD>Youth Staging Halloween Hangman Gag Accidentally Hangs Himself</HEAD>
<DATELINE>YORK, S.C. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A 15-year-old who was staging a haunted house
hangman gag accidentally hanged himself at a private Halloween
party, authorities said.
   The death of William Anthony Odom, a ninth-grader from
Charlotte, N.C., was similar to that of a 17-year-old who staged a
Halloween hangman stunt in Lakewood, N.J., a week ago.
   Odom was pronounced dead Friday night by York County Coroner Jim
Chapman in the basement of the home of his aunt, Diane Boyd, which
Odom and several of his friends had decorated as a haunted house.
   Odom was inside a free-standing wooden cupboard, intending to
fake a hangman scene, said his grandmother Hattie Carpenter, who
was at the party.
   He was dressed as a pirate, and around his neck was a 3-foot
length of nylon rope tied into a hangman's knot hanging from a bar.
   ``It was a slip-knot-type noose; the more pressure you apply,
the tighter it gets,'' Chapman said. ``Evidently, it was tight
enough to cause some problems with his breathing, and he either
passed out or panicked.''
   Chapman said Odom was tall enough to stand up in the cabinet,
but a group of children found him ``sitting down in the closet with
the noose around his neck and his neck to the side.''
   Chapman said he's unsure how the rope tightened. Possibly, he
said, Odom slipped and lost his balance or was playing with the
knot.
   He said it's possible that the knot gradually tightened and
reduced the amount of blood to Odom's brain, causing him to faint
and then suffocate.
   X-rays Saturday showed no serious injury to the neck, indicating
that the neck wasn't snapped by a sudden action, such as tripping.
   Odom's grandfather, Harvey Carpenter, said he and Ms. Boyd tried
to revive him, but the boy was dead by the time an emergency
medical team arrived.
   On Oct. 20, a 17-year-old New Jersey youth accidentally hanged
himself at a Halloween haunted hayride. Brian Jewell had pretended
to hang from a gallows but his body was found hanging from the
gallows with his feet on the ground.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0034 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 1606EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brite-DuckCalling     10-28 0224</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brite-Duck Calling,0259</SECOND>
<HEAD>Is That You, Daffy?</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PORTAGE, Ind. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Donald and Daffy weren't there. But there
were plenty of quacks, made by everyone from the pros to the hacks.
   Dressed in hunting jackets and caps, 20 competitors from five
states gathered Saturday in the parking lot of a Portage plumbing
company for the Indiana Duck Calling Championship.
   Topping everyone taking a quack at the state title was Kyle
Fleming, 33, a steel mill supervisor from Valparaiso. He came in
first with the five judges with his 90-second routine of duck
calls, and will advance to the world championships in Stuttgart,
Ark.
   Duck calling judges rely on keen ears, because they aren't
allowed to see the callers perform. That keeps the judges from
favoring contestants they know or have competed against.
   ``We're imagining that we're in a duck blind with the caller as
he simulates certain duck calls,'' said Jerry Trueblood, a judge
from Detroit. ``We're looking for a smooth flow and an even
sequence of calls.''
   Trueblood, a defending regional champion, said the callers are
required to perform a call to feed, a highball (or call to a
distant duck), a greeting and a call back.
   ``Once you learn competitive duck calling, you can really call
ducks down and improve your chances for shooting them,'' said Ray
Wright, a former Indiana duck calling champion. ``Any damn fool can
plug a duck from 20 yards away with a shotgun, but it takes a good
hunter to call him down from the skies.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0035 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 1624EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-ChildCare     10-28 0474</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Child Care,530</SECOND>
<HEAD>New Child Care Program Includes Tax Credits, Grants to States</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Congress-Look Back Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   New grant programs for child care and higher
tax credits for low-income families with children are part of the
mammoth budget agreement Congress approved before it left town for
the year early Sunday.
   The move marked the first time since World War II that the
federal government has supported child care for working parents
outside of welfare and employment programs, said Sen. Christopher
Dodd, D-Conn., one of its authors.
   Sponsors said the 750,000 children will receive aid in the
initial year of the program, which also will require states to
establish health, safety, registration and quality requirements.
   While President Bush had supported the concept of child-care
assistance during his 1988 campaign, he opposed elements of the
House and Senate packages until two weeks ago, when White House
officials reached agreement with Dodd on the block grant program.
   Under the bill, church-run day care centers will be eligible for
the federal subsidies, a recognition that churches play an
important role in child care in many areas, overriding concerns
about separation of church and state.
   The package also includes a grant program providing money to the
states. They, in turn, are to pass on a portion directly to
low-income families to cover part of child-care expenses, or to the
child-care centers as subsidies for individual children.
   The program will receive $2.5 billion for the first three years,
with the total expected to reach $5 billion by the fifth year.
   A separate, smaller grant program also will provide money to the
states to be passed along to poor families for child-care
assistance. Unlike the other program, it will become a new
entitlement program under Title 4 of the Social Security Act.
   As an entitlement it will automatically be included in the
federal budget annually and will not have to compete for yearly
appropriations. The package anticipates a cost of $700 million over
five years for this program.
   In addition, the Earned Income Tax Credit now available to
low-income working families with children would be expanded. The
bill adjusts the credit based on family size and provides a
supplemental $500 credit for eligible families with children under
the age of 1.
   The bill estimates the credit expansion will cost $12.4 billion
over five years.
   The credit is refundable, meaning that taxpayers whose credits
exceed their income tax liability are paid the difference by the
government.
   It is not directly tied to child-care expenses. Families with a
stay-at-home parent providing care for their own children would
receive the credit as well.
   The maximum credit in 1990 is 14 percent of the first $6,810 of
earned income, or $953. It is reduced as the adjusted gross income
reaches $10,743, and is totally eliminated at an income level of
$20,270. The bill increases the credit gradually so that by 1994,
the credit would be 23 percent for a one-child family and 25
percent for the two-child family. Income eligibility levels rise
with inflation.
   Three-quarters of the $2.5 billion child-care block grant
program must be used by the states to provide direct child care
services, including improvements in quality and availability. The
remaining portion would be devoted to early childhood development
or before-and after-school child care services.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0036 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 1628EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Mandela     10-28 0259</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mandela,0299</SECOND>
<HEAD>More Than 20,000 Welcome Mandela in Western Japan</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto OSA1</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Nelson Mandela told more than 20,000 Japanese at a
rally Sunday that he would seek financial help from their
government for his anti-apartheid movement.
   The black leader, who is to meet Prime Minister Toshiki Kaifu on
Monday, addressed the crowd at a complex in the western city of
Osaka on the second day of his visit to Japan.
   Later Sunday, he spoke before 2,000 people at a fund-raiser in
Tokyo.
   Mandela, 72, deputy president of the African National Congress,
said he will ask leaders what kind of support the congress can
expect from Japan in efforts to abolish Pretoria's apartheid
policy.
   ``We are here not only because you are a very rich country with
a great deal of skill in economic affairs. We are here because we
regard you as our friends and as our allies,'' he said.
   ``We do expect the Japanese government and Japanese businesses
to get involved in helping develop our economy after apartheid has
been scrapped,'' he said.
   He also said he would ask the government and Japanese business
enterprises in Japan to provide funds both for anti-apartheid
activities and to help build a new South Africa.
   Mandela arrived in Japan Saturday after visiting India,
Indonesia and Australia. He is to visit Malaysia and Brunei before
returning home, Kanbayashi said.
   Japan has banned direct private investment in South Africa since
the 1960s and does not station an ambassador in Pretoria, although
it maintains diplomatic relations with South Africa.
   Japan also bans imports of South African iron and steel and
limits cultural, sports and tourism exchanges.
   Mandela was freed in February after more than 27 years in South
African prisons.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0037 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 1629EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--SatanicVerses     10-28 0173</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Satanic Verses,0176</SECOND>
<HEAD>Paper to Continue Publishing `Satanic Verses'</HEAD>
<DATELINE>KATMANDU, Nepal (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Nepali weekly will continue serializing
Salman Rushdie's ``The Satanic Verses'' despite a request by the
government to stop, the editor said Sunday.
   Communications Minister Yog Prasad Upadhyaya contacted the
weekly in response to complaints by representatives of the Moslem
community that the novel hurt their religious feelings.
   Shiv Kumar Khadga, editor of the weekly Janjyoti, said the 48th
chapter in the serial would run as scheduled Monday.
   ``There is no legal obligation for us to stop the publication
and we have no intention of hurting anyone. We are printing the
serial to give the Nepalese readers a taste of a fine literary
piece,'' he said in an interview.
   Only 3 percent of Nepal's 17 million people are Moslems, and
about 90 percent are Hindus. The rest are Buddhists and Christians.
   Rushdie has been in hiding in Britain since February 1989, when
Iran's Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini declared the novel blasphemous
and decreed that the British author should be killed.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0038 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 1630EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-PoliceShooting     10-28 0515</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Police Shooting,0642</SECOND>
<HEAD>Police Shooting of Unarmed Stockbroker Follows Complaints Against
Force</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MELISSA CONTI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>KANSAS CITY, Mo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Police checking a report of a prowler
entered an apartment at 3:30 a.m. and shot a 24-year-old
stockbroker to death when he got out of bed in his nightclothes to
see what was wrong.
   The officer who shot the man was placed on paid leave pending an
investigation, police said. The police department, already
struggling with allegations of police brutality and racism, said it
was an accidental shooting of an innocent person.
   It is believed to be the sixth shooting death committed by
Kansas City police officers this year. In one, four officers fired
19 times at a man brandishing a barbecue fork. In another, an
officer killed a man who was spraying him with a fire extinguisher.
None of the officers involved in those two killings was indicted.
   Terry D. Barnes, 24, was shot once between the eyes Saturday in
his apartment.
   ``I just hope that this case will draw the line on where the
police can kill an innocent man. Where do you draw the line?'' said
Andy Brez, 23, Barnes' roommate. He was sleeping in another bedroom
when police entered the apartment.
   ``I woke up to the word `Police!''' he said. ``I was scared to
death.''
   Brez said he stayed in his bedroom until an officer opened his
door and told him to stay inside. He said Barnes was engaged to be
married next June.
   Police spokesman Sgt. Greg Mills said Barnes made ``a kind of
lunging motion'' when the officer opened his bedroom door.
   ``This is a tragic chain of events that is regrettable for Mr.
Barnes' family and for this officer,'' Police Chief Steven Bishop
said. ``The officers were reacting appropriately to a number of
circumstances which together led them to that apartment.''
   Residents of an apartment complex adjacent to Barnes' building
had called police to report that someone kicked in their front
door. When officers arrived, other residents of the complex said
they saw a man run toward Barnes' building. Some residents thought
they heard the prowler run to the third floor, where Barnes lived.
   Two officers, whose names were not disclosed, noticed the door
to Barnes' apartment was not tightly shut and entered the
apartment.
   One officer opened a bedroom door and encountered Barnes,
unarmed, dressed in a T-shirt and boxer shorts, standing near a bed
5 to 8 feet from the doorway, Mills said.
   Barnes ran at the officer and the officer fired, Mills said.
   Mills told The Kansas City Star the officers ``acted responsibly
by going into the apartment'' because they had good reason to
believe the suspect might be in there.
   But the department stopped short of defending the action taken
by the officer who fired the shot.
   ``We are defending the officers being in that apartment,'' Mills
said. ``As for the shooting itself, we will make no assessment of
the propriety of that until after the investigation.
   ``I think it's accurate to say (the officer) did feel
threatened.''
   The officer, a two-year veteran of the force, was placed on paid
administrative leave pending an internal investigation and an
investigation by a Clay County grand jury.
   Some of the previous police shootings have prompted calls for
the department to re-evaluate officers' conduct and training.
   In previous interviews, Chief Bishop said only a few of his
1,200 officers violate citizens' rights.
   ``We're part of the problem out there on the street, and we've
got to get back to good, basic police work,'' said Bishop, a
20-year veteran of the force who became chief in June.
   Police officials have said they are developing a ``behavior
modification'' program for offending officers.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0039 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 1634EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-FreedRodents     10-28 0196</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Freed Rodents,0211</SECOND>
<HEAD>Research Animals Freed From Cages at University</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   BUFFALO, N.Y. (AP)  Hundreds of mice, rats and hamsters used
for research were released from their cages at the state University
of New York at Buffalo Medical School, but no animal rights group
claimed responsibility.
   The animals were found scampering around five rooms Saturday
morning by a technician arriving for work, said school spokeswoman
Linda Grace-Kobas.
   ``They opened the cages, and the mice and the rats (and
hamsters) got out of the cages, but they did not escape from the
rooms,'' she said.
   There were no signs of a break-in or indication why the animals
were released.
   ``Usually animal rights people leave a message,'' she said.
``There were no notes. No `Save the Animals.' This was strange. It
seemed random. It seemed pointless.''
   University officials were trying to determine what effect the
animals' release will have on research projects in which they were
used, she said.
   ``By letting them out, it disrupts the experiments,'' she said,
adding that some of the experiments are based on the animals being
in a closed enviroment.
   Also, since not all the animals were tagged, researchers may not
be able to determine which animals belonged to what experiments.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0040 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 1627EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-India     10-28 0521</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-India,0630</SECOND>
<HEAD>Security Forces Seal Moslem Shrine, Arrest Thousands</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto AYO2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By VIJAY JOSHI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>AYODHYA, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Police arrested thousands more Hindu
pilgrims Sunday, including a member of a Hindu royal family, in an
attempt to avoid more bloodshed in a dispute over a Moslem shrine
in this town.
   The Hindu-Moslem conflict over the shrine claimed at least 96
lives in rioting last week and has jeopardized Prime Minister V.P.
Singh's government.
   More than 60,000 people were arrested by Saturday as troops
sealed off Ayodhya and the borders of Uttar Pradesh state from a
swarm of Hindu pilgrims.
   Police gave no figure for the number of arrests Sunday, but
Press Trust of India and United News of India said 15,000 were
detained at one southern border crossing.
   Among them was Vijaya Raje Scindia, vice president of the
right-wing Hindu party Bharatiya Janata. She was the maharani, or
princess, of Gwalior before India abolished princely states 20
years ago.
   Mrs. Scindia was arrested on charges of ``violating a
prohibitory order,'' United News reported. The state government had
banned the leaders of several Hindu fundamentalist groups from the
state.
   The news agencies said 300 truckloads of Hindu pilgrims
accompanying Mrs. Scindia were driven to temporary jails in schools
and public areas around the state. Twelve members of Parliament
also were detained by police forming a security net around the
shrine.
   ``It's like a war zone. Not even an ant can get past us,'' said
one police officer protecting the shrine.
   The controversy is centered on a 16th century mosque, the Babri
Masjid, in this town of 40,000 people about 300 miles southeast of
New Delhi.
   Hindu fundamentalists say the mosque stands on the birthplace of
the god Rama. They say they will replace the structure with a
temple and have set Wednesday for beginning construction.
   The government, saying it is obliged to defend minority
interests, has pledged not to allow the mosque to be displaced
until the courts decide the issue.
   The Bharatiya Janata Party withdrew support from Singh's
National Front coalition Tuesday. Singh's minority government
depended on the Hindu party and the Communist-led Left Front for
its survival.
   A United News report quoted Singh as saying Sunday that the
Hindu party was trying to ``usurp power, even at the cost of
communal conflagration and the country's unity.''
   Singh must face a vote of confidence in Parliament on Nov. 7.
The Bharatiya Janata and the opposition Congress party have said
they will vote against Singh, which virtually assures his defeat.
   Elections are likely early next year.
   ``The (political) matter is closed. It is with the security
forces now, and they will do their duty,'' said the police official
at a barricade on the road to Aydohya. Heavily armed policemen
manned the barrier.
   All entry points to Ayodhya in a 60-mile radius are blocked by
barricades, he said. The national railway suspended service through
the state.
   About 200,000 policemen and paramilitary forces have fanned
across the state. In Ayodya, an indefinite curfew imposed Friday
was lifted for just two hours Sunday afternoon.
   Officials refuse to say how many policemen are deployed around
the shrine, but some officers said the figure was about 20,000.
Policemen lounged in the shade of narrow lanes leading to the
shrine, playing with monkeys who inhabit the area.
   Moslems comprise 30 percent of the 120 million people in Uttar
Pradesh.
   Though Moslems are only 12 percent of India's 880 million
people, they live in almost every Indian state. Hindus are 82
percent of the population.
   Religious tensions between Hindus and Moslems erupt
periodically, and dozens of people are killed in clashes every
year.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0041 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 1627EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Gulf-Iraq 1stLd-Writethru a0766 10-28 0364</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Iraq, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0766,0420</SECOND>
<HEAD>Iraq Fires Oil Minister; Cancels Rationing</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 7 grafs to UPDATE with agency not giving amount of
reserves, doubts about official statement, details. Pickup 4th pvs,
`The Iraqi ...' Minor editing thereafter to CONFORM.</NOTE>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf Rdp</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NICOSIA, Cyprus (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Iraq fired its oil minister Sunday and
canceled a fuel rationing program, saying it was imposed by
mistake, an official report said. The minister was replaced by
Saddam Hussein's son-in-law.
   It was not immediately clear why the rationing, which began
Tuesday, was stopped. The report by the official Iraqi News Agency
said the Oil Ministry had miscalculated the amount of chemical
additives necessary to refine crude oil into gasoline and other
products such as lubricants.
   ``It was evident that they (chemicals) were enough for double
the period estimated by the Oil Ministry,'' the agency said. It
said the ministry of industry ``was capable of manufacturing the
needed solutions.''
   The report did not specify the amount of the needed chemicals
Iraq had.
   A well-placed oil industry source said there indeed was an
imminent shortage of the chemicals, which had been imported before
Iraq's invasion of Kuwait on Aug. 2.
   U.N. trade sanctions apparently have severely curtailed imports
of the chemicals, but Iraq may have taken whatever supplies were in
Kuwait when it invaded.
   The source said Saddam may have fired the official, Issam
Chalabi, to blame him for the imminent shortage of chemicals.
   The Iraqi agency said ``a republican decree'' relieved Chalabi
of his post. It said another decree appointed Hussein Kamel,
minister of industry and military industrialization, as acting oil
minister.
   Chalabi has been oil minister since 1986. Before that he had a
long career as an oil administrator, including a stint as head of
Iraq's national oil company.
   Kamel is a son-in-law of Saddam. In addition to his ministerial
duties, he reportedly runs one of the five secret police
organizations through which Saddam keeps a tight rein on Iraq.
   The well-informed oil industry source, who spoke on condition of
anonymity, said that for more than a year there have been signs
that Kamel has been attempting to expand his authority into oil
production.
   The source said that despite the cancellation of rationing,
recent travelers from Iraq have said that the shortage is ``really
biting'' and that Iraqis are asking why they have such shortages
when there is still plenty of crude oil for local consumption
despite the international embargo on Iraq.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0042 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 1635EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Bush-ForeignAid     10-28 0383</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bush-Foreign Aid,430</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush To Sign Bill With El Salvador Aids Cuts, Egypt Debt
Forgiveness</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RITA BEAMISH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HONOLULU (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush said Sunday he will sign a $15.5
billion foreign aid spending bill despite his concerns about its 50
percent cut in military aid to El Salvador.
   Bush at first was unresponsive when asked about the bill's fate
as he played a midday round of golf here. But as he left the links
later he said he had spoken to his national security adviser, Brent
Scowcroft, about the matter, and told reporters he would sign the
bill.
   Asked about the provision that would halve El Salvador's $85
million in military aid, Bush said ``Yes, we're very much concerned
about it.''
   But the bill, approved late Saturday in the waning hours of the
101st Congress, also has something Bush badly wants - forgiveness
of $6.7 billion in past military debt Egypt owes the United States.
   The administration sought the debt relief as a gesture of thanks
to Egyptian President Hosni Mubarak, who has taken a leading role
in marshaling Arab opposition to Iraq's invasion of Kuwait.
   The rest of the bill provides economic, military and development
aid for U.S. friends and allies around the globe, including $3
billion for Israel and $2.1 billion for Egypt, the two primary aid
recipients.
   The El Salvador provision was pushed through by congressional
Democrats, whose outrage was heightened by the killing nearly a
year ago of six Jesuit priests, their housekeeper and her daughter
in San Salvador. Eight military officials since have been charged
in the crime, but none has come to trial.
   The cut represents a sharp departure from 10 years of U.S.
policy which has maintained that military aid was important to
bolster the San Salvador government in the face of attacks from
leftist guerillas. Administration lobbyists fought hard against the
provision on Capitol Hill.
   Under the bill, the military aid would be cut to $42.5 million
in the year that began Oct. 1. Supporters say the cut will put
pressure on both sides - the government and the leftist FMLN rebels
- to bring their decade-long war to a negotiated, diplomatic end.
   If the rebels of the Farabundo Marti National Liberation Front
mount a major offensive that threatens the government, or walk away
from United Nations-sponsored peace talks, the aid cut could be
restored, bringing military support back to its old level of $85
million.
   But if the government should fail to bargain in good faith with
the rebels toward reforms and a cease-fire, it could lose the rest
of its military aid.
   The provisions would leave intact the nearly $300 million in
economic, food and development aid that flows to El Salvador.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0043 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 1635EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-WeatherpageWeather     10-28 0210</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Weatherpage Weather,0229</SECOND>
<HEAD>Cold Air Flows Into Ohio Valley, Northeast</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Frigid air flowed southward into the Ohio Valley on Sunday,
while southerly wind boosted temperatures on the Plains into the
60s and 70s.
   Clouds and blustery northwesterly wind held Sunday afternoon
temperatures in the 30s and 40s in the upper Great Lakes region.
   That wind also pushed cold air into the Northeast, and parts of
the Ohio Valley expected the first frost or freeze of the season by
Monday morning.
   A freeze warning was posted for all of Ohio except the northeast
corner. Freeze advisories were issued for northeastern Kentucky and
southern Indiana.
   But to the west, strong southerly wind helped afternoon
temperatures warm into the 60s and 70s in the northern and central
Plains.
   Low pressure tracking across southern Canada with the wind
produced scattered showers across the Northeast, and snow was
expected in parts of New England.
   In the Northwest, a cold front produced a few showers Sunday in
northern Idaho and western Montana. Showers associated with an
upper level weather disturbance moved along the coast of Washington
state and Oregon.
   Temperatures early Sunday dipped into the 20s in New England,
and over parts of Nebraska, the Dakotas, Iowa, Minnesota and
Wisconsin.
   Sunday's low for the Lower 48 states was 15 at Warroad, Minn.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0044 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 1644EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Hungary     10-28 0567</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Hungary,0655</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hungary Backs Away From 70 Percent Gasoline Price Increase</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ALEX BANDY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUDAPEST, Hungary (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The government backed away from a 70
percent gasoline price increase Sunday after two days of crippling
nationwide road and bridge blockades by protesting taxi and truck
drivers.
   Industry and Trade Minister Peter Akos Bod told drivers the
government was prepared to accept a 50 percent increase pending
passage of a law that allows the market to set the price of
gasoline.
   Bod said that if the legislation was not adopted, the original,
higher price increase would again take effect. The center-right
government coalition has a parliamentary majority, and passage of
the law was a near certainty.
   Unions representing the truck and taxi drivers and their
employers accepted the main points of the government offer.
   Taxi and truck drivers on Friday and Saturday used their
vehicles to block streets and bridges nationwide, crippling Hungary
for two days. The blockade was eased Sunday as negotiations with
the government progressed.
   While negotiators met in the Labor Ministry on Sunday, an angry
pro-government crowd of about 10,000, led by members of Prime
Minister Jozsef Antall's Hungarian Democratic Forum, gathered
outside.
   Some demonstrators carried placards reading: ``Fascism, Marxism,
Taxiism,'' and ``No to Proletarian Dictatorship.''
   One huge placard alluded to the street terror of 1956 - when
Soviet tanks crushed an anti-Communist revolution - saying, ``In
1956 tanks, in 1990 taxis.''
   The crowd chanted, ``Long live the government!'' and ``Communist
Cabbies!''
   Defense Minister Lajos Fuer warned the government's patience was
growing short.
   ``Democracy cannot accept illegal acts,'' Fuer told the crowd.
``The government is willing to negotiate, but we won't tolerate
anarchy.''
   The crowd chanted: ``Punish the offenders!''
   Budapest's mayor-elect, Gabor Demszky, went on state television
Sunday to appeal for calm.
   The government rollback followed two days of tense negotiations
with protesters. On Saturday, state media briefly reported that the
government had proposed across-the-board cuts, but these reports
were subsequently described as false by government officials.
   The talks had foundered for most of Sunday on government
reluctance to agree to an overall price reduction.
   Buses and street cars moved relatively freely in Budapest and
other cities for the first time since Friday, when the higher
prices went into effect.
   The government increased gasoline to about $3.80 a gallon from
$2.30 a gallon. That is far higher than the American price, even
though the average Hungarian earns about $150 a month at current
exchange rates.
   The government said the price increases were needed because of
reductions in Soviet shipments and higher oil prices following
Iraq's Aug. 2 invasion of Kuwait.
   The protests represented the most serious sign of discontent
with the worsening economic situation as Hungary tries to move
toward a free-market system. Elections last spring ended four
decades of one-party Communist rule.
   Hungary's more than $20 billion foreign debt is the highest per
capita in the former Soviet bloc. Unemployment and a housing crisis
are growing, and inflation is high.
   The mood of the people in Budapest and elsewhere appeared to
back the protesters. Shoppers lining up for bread and milk in
anticipation of shortages joked with some of the protesting
truckers brewing coffee over field stoves.
   The blockages were virtually cleared Sunday. In the capital,
Danube bridges were cleared of parked vehicles, as were most main
thoroughfares. Highways leading to the city also were generally
free for traffic.
   State television reported similar conditions in regional centers
jammed with parked trucks and taxis for the previous two days. Most
border crossing points were relatively accessible for the first
time in two days.
   The only exception was Gyoer, near main border crossing points
with Austria and Czechoslovakia. Abandoned tractor trailers on the
main road leading through town continued to block access to the
borders.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0045 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 1651EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Vatican-Priests     10-28 0404</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Vatican-Priests,0481</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bishops Concede Finding Priesthood Candidates is Difficult</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By FRANCES D'EMILIO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>VATICAN CITY (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Bishops who opposed changing the requirement
that priests be celibate ended a meeting Sunday admitting it will
not be easy to attract candidates with the needed ``heroism'' for
the priesthood.
   Pope John Paul II had summoned the bishops from around the world
for a month-long synod on how to bring in good, committed priests
to a church that has suffered defections from the priesthood and
seen a drop in seminary enrollments in affluent parts of the world.
   ``It is clear that many young people find it hard to commit
themselves to life-long priesthood, to give up the possibility of
marriage and setting up a family, and to choose a life in the
spirit of ... poverty, chastity and obedience,'' the bishops said
in a statement read during a final Mass led Sunday by the pope in
St. Peter's Basilica.
   ``This is a high ideal. Yet in every age, including our own, we
have seen marvelous examples of this heroism, with some even
suffering martyrdom for their vocation,'' the bishops said.
   Throughout his 12-year-old papacy, John Paul consistently has
defended the celibacy requirement, which the church sees as a means
to give priests more time to devote to their mission and less
opportunity for distractions.
   The requirement has been blamed as one of the reasons for the
decline in the number of priests around the world.
   The pope, buoyed by the bishops' affirmation of celibacy, sought
to dispel any speculation that ordination of married men might be
permitted in the future.
   ``This isn't a solution to be taken under consideration,'' John
Paul told them in his final speech. ``Without any possibility of
doubt, the synod has confirmed the choice of ... celibacy which is
proper to the Latin rite.''
   The Vatican has excluded from the celibacy requirement priests
who converted to Roman Catholism after having married. In addition,
several Eastern rite churches which accept the pope's authority are
allowed to ordain married men.
   At the start of the synod on Sept. 30, Vatican officials
indicated that the gathering was not seen as an occasion to debate
celibacy.
   Nevertheless, bishops raised the question. While the synod was
going on, it was disclosed that the Vatican had questioned a
meeting that a U.S. bishop, Donald Wuerl of Pittsburgh, held in
June with a group of married ex-priests in California.
   The bishop denied reports that the Vatican's letter was meant as
a rebuke and said ``discussion'' about celibacy would continue.
   Among the synod's suggestions were the use of better trained
seminary teachers and the hiring of lay people, including women, to
instruct seminarians. Women are already teaching in some
seminaries, but observers said the synod recommendation could make
their use more widespread.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0046 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 1655EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BronxMystery     10-28 0535</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bronx Mystery,0694</SECOND>
<HEAD>NYC Police Play Down Fears of Serial Killer in Bronx Deaths</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By VIRGINIA BYRNE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   When a 10-year-old Bronx girl was found
asphyxiated, her body dumped near a highway, the slaying raised new
fears that a serial killer was on the loose.
   But even though one man has a link of some kind to her and five
other people killed in similar circumstances since 1986, police say
that he is not a suspect. In fact, they say, there is no serial
killer at work.
   ``There's only one word to describe this case: bizarre,'' said
Inspector Donald E. Moss, who supervises 20 investigators trying to
determine whether the links between the deaths are coincidence or
follow a pattern.
   In the latest case, Jessica Guzman was found dead Oct. 17, a
week after she disappeared a few blocks from her home. The child's
body was found about five miles away, in a wooded area near the
Bronx River Parkway.
   Her death prompted a review of dozens of unsolved killings of
young Hispanics in the Bronx borough over the past five years.
   Among them are the slayings of two teen-agers who were found in
1989, also asphyxiated, also dumped along a Bronx parkway; and
three young Hispanic women whose bodies were found in wooded areas
near Bronx highways over the last four years.
   Each of the victims had a link to a 29-year-old Bronx livery cab
driver. He faces trial on unrelated charges of scalding and
assaulting a girlfriend's 3-year-old son, but police say he is not
a suspect in the six killings.
   Jessica was seen playing in the man's car hours before she
vanished. Another of the victims, killed last year along with a
15-year-old boy, was the driver's niece. One victim was said to
have dated the driver once; another dated a relative of his, the
Daily News reported. The sixth was a friend of one of the other
victims.
   The cab driver denies any involvement. Police said he has a
strong alibi for the night Jessica disappeared and is not a suspect
in any of the cases.
   For that reason, they have asked that his name not be published.
   ``He's the obvious link, but it may be nothing but a
coincidence,'' said Moss. ``It's not uncommon for people in the
Bronx to know more than one homicide victim, unfortunately.''
   Police reject assertions that one person is responsible for the
slayings.
   ``There is no serial killer and there is no linkage between
these cases,'' said Deputy Chief Michael Philbin, head of Bronx
detectives. ``We don't have a suspect at this time.
   ``There are significant differences among the cases. Normally,
when you're dealing with a serial killer, it's ritualistic.''
   Some of the bodies were badly decomposed, making it difficult to
pinpoint a cause of death, which in turn makes the cases hard to
link, police said.
   Before Jessica's funeral last Monday, two days after she would
have turned 11, 150 people staged a 15-block ``barefoot march''
protesting the killings. More than 2,000 attended her funeral.
   ``It's like living the same thing all over again. There are too
many coincidences,'' said Ana Rosa. She is the grandmother of
Heriberto Marrero, 15, the only male among the six victims. His
body was found with that of 13-year-old Nilda Cartagena - the
driver's niece - in June 1989. Both were asphyxiated.
   Annette Rosario disappeared in June 1986, on the way home from
her 17th birthday party. She was last seen telephoning for a livery
cab. An autopsy found her skull had been shattered.
   Lisa Rodriguez, 21, one of Ms. Rosario's best friends, had one
date with the cab driver before she disappeared last June 14, the
Daily News reported. Her body was so decomposed the cause of death
could not be determined.
   Shamira Bello, 14, was found strangled in July 1988, her
half-naked body dumped in a park not far from where Annette was
found. The Daily News said Ms. Bello had been dating a nephew of
the driver.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0047 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 1708EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Egypt-Arrests     10-28 0257</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Egypt-Arrests,0275</SECOND>
<HEAD>Police Arrest Two More Suspects in Assassination</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CAIRO, Egypt (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two more suspects in the assassination of
Egypt's parliament speaker were arrested Sunday as police continued
to investigate the role of Moslem extremists in the slaying,
security sources said.
   At least 10 people have been arrested in connection with the
Oct. 12 attack that killed People's Assembly speaker Rifaat
el-Mahgoub, his driver and four security men, police said.
   The suspects belong to two militant Moslem groups with a history
of violence, including the 1981 assassination of President Anwar
Sadat, police allege.
   But security sources say police are still searching for a wider
network of extremists connected to the case.
   The first suspect arrested confessed last Wednesday to
participating in the assassination of el-Mahgoub, who was second in
line to the presidency, police said.
   Early Saturday, authorities raided a Cairo apartment and
arrested five men accused of taking part in the slaying.
   Later, two suspects were killed and two were captured following
a shootout at Cairo University, police reported.
   Security sources, speaking on condition of anonymity, say the
men are members of the extremist groups Jihad and Salvation from
Hell.
   Jihad was responsible for Sadat's assassination, and Salvation
from Hell was blamed for the attempted killing in 1987 of two
former interior ministers and a journalist close to President Hosni
Mubarak.
   Both groups have been charged with attempting to replace Egypt's
secular government with an Islamic theocratic rule.
   Government sources also suspect Iraq had a role in the
el-Mahgoub assassination, as punishment for Egypt's stand against
Baghdad in the Persian Gulf crisis.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0048 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 1714EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Pakistan     10-28 0460</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Pakistan,0521</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bhutto Says Followers May Launch Street Protests</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto ISL1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KATHY GANNON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ISLAMABAD, Pakistan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Former Prime Minister Benazir Bhutto
said Sunday her populist party may launch nationwide demonstrations
to protest what she called ``massive election fraud'' by her
opponents.
   A right-wing coalition opposing her easily won Wednesday's
national elections and Saturday's provincial legislative balloting,
dashing Ms. Bhutto's hopes for a comeback following her ouster two
months ago.
   ``At the moment the people are angry,'' Ms. Bhutto said in an
interview. ``This is all very distressing. What do you tell
people?''
   In elections Wednesday for the National Assembly, the
policy-making lower house of Parliament that chooses the prime
minster, the Islamic alliance defeated Ms. Bhutto by a 2-to-1
margin.
   Saturday's elections were the bloodiest in Pakistan's 43-year
history. At least 33 people were killed and up to 50 others injured
in violent clashes.
   Voting ended after only three hours in at least one constituency
in southern Sindh, Ms. Bhutto's power base. Gunmen sprayed a rural
voting booth, killing three people and injuring several more, said
Election Commissioner Naeemuddin, who uses only one name.
   The results of at least nine other constituencies were delayed
because violence had stalled either voting or counting, Naeemuddin
said.
   Unidentified gunmen ambushed a car taking the son of caretaker
Prime Minister Ghulam Mustafa Jatoi to vote, but he escaped by
running into the polling station, election officials said.
   Ms. Bhutto has refused to accept results of either Wednesday's
or Saturday's voting, alleging ``sophisticated and systematic''
vote-rigging by the Islamic Democratic Alliance, known by its
Urdu-language initials IJI.
   The alliance denied the allegations, and the charges were not
supported by international election observers.
   ``It has become a habit with the People's Party to allege
rigging when they lose,'' said Hussain Haqqani, an alliance
spokesman.
   Ms. Bhutto called on candidates from her party in both contests
fo come to Islamabad on Saturday to map out a strategy.
   ``We will decide then whether to launch a movement against the
massive rigging or to play it cool and accept the opposition role
in the National Assembly,'' Khurshid Kasuri, secretary-general of
Ms. Bhutto's party, told a news conference Sunday.
   The elections were scheduled after Pakistan's president
dismissed Ms. Bhutto on Aug. 6, accusing her 20-month-old
government of corruption and incompetence.
   The former prime minister said she offered to resign the
leadership of her party because Pakistan's ``establishment'' is
determined to force her out.
   ``I'm willing to step aside. Why should people suffer all for
being in the PPP'' she asked.
   With 463 of Saturday's 483 races decided, Ms. Bhutto's party was
virtually wiped out in eastern Punjab, the largest and wealthiest
province and the alliance's stronghold. It was effectively
sidelined in the Northwest Frontier Province, where it had ruled
before her government was dismissed.
   Ms. Bhutto and her party also appeared in danger of losing their
overwhelming majority in her home province of Sindh. But it was
unlikely that Sindh would be decided before next week.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0049 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 1715EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-ReaganMemoir     10-28 0411</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Reagan Memoir,470</SECOND>
<HEAD>Reagan Calls 1986 Summit a Turning Point in Arms Control Reduction</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Former President Reagan's new memoir calls the
failed 1986 arms control summit in Iceland one of the ``most
disappointing - and ultimately angriest'' days of his presidency,
but says it still was a turning point in nuclear arms reduction.
   In ``Ronald Reagan: An American Life,'' the former president
writes that the summit at Reykjavik, Iceland - where he rejected
the Soviets' demand to link arms control with reduced U.S. research
on the Strategic Defense Initiative - was major step in eventually
convincing the Soviets to move forward on arms control.
   Reagan's memoir, coauthored by journalist Robert Lindsey, is
being published by Simon and Schuster. Time magazine is publishing
the first of two excerpts in its Nov. 5 issue.
   Reagan said the bullet wound he suffered in the March 30, 1981,
assassination attempt by John Hinckley Jr. was ``the most
excruciating pain I had ever felt.'' At first, he wrote, he thought
his injury was a broken rib caused when Secret Service agent Jerry
Parr shoved him into the presidential limousine and jumped on top
of him.
   The former president said he didn't wear a bulletproof vest that
day, as he sometimes did. Noting that the bullet stopped less than
an inch from his heart, he said, ``Someone was looking out for
me.''
   Reagan also told of his days as a radio sports announcer and
said that when he was first elected governor of California in 1966,
his then 14-year-old daughter Patti cried because ``she didn't like
having a member of the Establishment in the family.''
   At the Reykjavik summit, Reagan wrote, ``My hopes for a
nuclear-free world soared briefly, then fell during one the
longest, most disappointing - and ultimately angriest - days of my
presidency.''
   Reagan and Soviet President Mikhail S. Gorbachev had made
progress on nuclear arms reduction that ``even now seems
breathtaking,'' Reagan said, when Gorbachev ``threw us a curve'' by
insisting that it must be linked to reductions in SDI. The summit
collapsed.
   ``Despite a perception by some that the Reykjavik summit was a
failure, I think history will show it was a major turning point in
the quest for a safe and secure world,'' Reagan wrote. ``I think
Gorbachev was ready to talk the next time we met because we had
walked out on him at Reykjavik and gone ahead with the SDI.''
   Reagan speculated on why Gorbachev decided to allow the major
changes that have swept the Soviet Union and Eastern Europe:
``Gorbachev must have realized (his country) could no longer
support or control Stalin's totalitarian colonial empire; the
survival of the Soviet Union was more important to him. ...
   ``I might have helped him see that the Soviet Union had less to
fear from the West than he thought, and that the Soviet empire in
Eastern Europe wasn't needed for the security of the Soviet
Union,'' the former president wrote.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0050 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 1715EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-HalloweenBriefs     10-28 0575</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Halloween Briefs,0693</SECOND>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LEXINGTON, Ky. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   There's only one thing for students at
Transylvania University to do when Halloween is near - sleep in the
tomb of the teacher known for putting a hex on the school.
   Four Transylvania students won the opportunity to spend a night
in the tomb of Constantine Rafinesque, who taught biology at
Transylvania from 1819 to 1826 before being fired.
   ``I can't believe we're sleeping over dead men,'' freshman
Shallie Miller of Muncie, Ind., said Friday night while sprawling
on a concrete slab that seals Rafinesque's crypt in the school's
administration building.
   And so ended another Rafinesque Week, a time of ghoulish
activities started around Halloween in the 1930s to celebrate the
unusual botanist's life.
   Rafinesque, who was born in 1783 in Constantinople, published
taxonomic descriptions of 6,700 new plants. But students know him
better by his curse.
   Legend says the university's then-President Horace Holley fired
Rafinesque when he discovered the botanist had had an affair with
his wife. Outraged, Rafinesque cursed Holley and the school and
fled to Philadelphia.
   Transylvania's administration building mysteriously burned down
and Holley died soon after. In 1969, the administration building
again caught fire, and every room was gutted except for the one in
which Rafinesque is entombed.
   ---
   CINCINNATI (AP) - The bride was dreadful, the groom gruesome,
but love conquered all in a wedding that looked like something out
of ``Fright Night.''
   Anthony Taylor and Debra Hutcherson, dressed as Frankenstein and
the Bride of Frankenstein, culminated their six-year courtship
Saturday in the back yard of their home with a Halloween-style
wedding.
   ``You always see pretty brides and pretty weddings,'' said
Hutcherson, 32. ``I just wanted my day to be different.''
   Different it was - even friends and relatives invited to witness
the weird wedding decked out in frightening garb. Only the minister
who performed the ceremony came in regular attire.
   Hutcherson said she had to talk her beloved into the unusual
wedding.
   ``I was kind of leery at first,'' said Taylor, 34. ``But I'd
rather be married to Debra in costume than not at all.''
   Another couple in Evansville, Ind., had the same idea Saturday.
   Stephanie Plemmons, resplendent in her white dress, makeup and
Frankenstein-head earrings, married Glen Hettenbach, attired in
green makeup and with bolts attached to his neck.
   Eerie music played as the ceremony started and thunder crashed
when the couple kissed.
   ---
   LOS ANGELES (AP) - Police caught the devil and tossed him in the
cooler.
   An inebriated party-goer dressed like the devil was arrested
while driving home from a Halloween celebration early Sunday.
   Police Sgt. Mike Pattee said the man, whose name was withheld,
had a blood-alcohol content of .15 percent, nearly twice the legal
limit of .08 percent.
   The man was among 246 people arrested for drunken driving during
a weekend crackdown that ended early Sunday. About 65 Los Angeles
Police Department and California Highway Patrol officers patrolled
streets and freeways as a part of the operation.
   ``We're getting ready for the holiday season,'' Pattee said.
   ----
   CENTREVILLE, Md. (AP) - This town's former jail is being
converted for the ``Haunted Crack House II: The Horror of Using
Drugs Continues,'' the sequel to last year's frightening look at
the dangers of drug use.
   The original Haunted Crack House was the brainchild of John L.
Lechliter, then the town's police chief. It drew 2,800 visitors and
national attention.
   Haunted Crack House II takes visitors along on the drug odyssey
of ``Liz,'' a young mother who craves crack, a potent form of
cocaine, so much that it finally kills her and her baby.
   Visitors watch officers ``arrest'' Liz on the street outside the
three-story, 82-year-old brick building. Then they follow her story
through 14 rooms to court, her family's living room (where her
parents aren't listening), a teen-age drug party, jail, and
eventually morgue, funeral home and cemetery.
   About 200 volunteers will work to make the evening as spooky and
informative as possible.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0051 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 1721EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Ireland-Elections     10-28 0560</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Ireland-Elections,0681</SECOND>
<HEAD>Presidential Brawl Threatens Stability of Irish Government</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT BARR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DUBLIN, Ireland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The first presidential race in 17 years
could bring down the government and give Ireland its first woman
president - in large part because one candidate can't decide
whether he made a telephone call eight years ago.
   Because of the controversy, the government faces a vote of
confidence on Wednesday, one week before the presidential election.
   Defense Minister Brian Lenihan, the early front-runner in the
campaign, has stumbled on his varying recollections of a telephone
call to President Patrick Hillery in 1982.
   In the alleged phone call - which followed a no-confidence vote
in parliament - Lenihan reportedly improperly pressured the
president to ask the opposition party to form a government -
instead of calling national elections.
   In May, Lenihan, who is also deputy prime minister, said he
``distinctly'' remembered the call.
   But when the issue came up last week, Lenihan denied making the
call. He kept denying it even after the whole country heard a tape
recording of him discussing the call in detail with a political
science student.
   ``On mature recollection, and full reflection, I did not ring
President Hillery on that night,'' Lenihan said Thursday night
after the tape was broadcast.
   The Irish Times on Friday carried a cartoon of a tape cassette
with the caption: ``Sure, weren't we told all along that Brian was
a sound man. ...''
   Overnight, Ireland's bookies named Mary Robinson the favorite to
win the presidential election.
   ``The people of Ireland will be surprised and dismayed that a
person can deny so emphatically what he said last May,'' said Mrs.
Robinson, who had been 17 points behind Lenihan in an Irish Times
poll published on Oct. 10.
   A poll published Sunday by the Sunday Independent, based on 500
voters in the Dublin area, showed Mrs. Robinson with 51 percent
support to Lenihan's 32 percent.
   That poll gave no indication, however, of how opinion was moving
in the rural bases of Fianna Fail, Lenihan's party.
   Following the broadcast of the tape, opposition parties filed
motions of no confidence in the government of Prime Minister
Charles Haughey. The fate of the coalition government, which has a
one-vote majority, hinges on the six members of the junior partner,
the Progressive Democrats.
   The presidential election is a rarity in Ireland. Hillery,
nearing the end of his second seven-year term, was simply nominated
by agreement of the major parties.
   Mrs. Robinson, who has the support of the Labor Party and the
socialist Workers Party but belongs to neither, is a former senator
who in the past has taken controversial positions in favor of
legalizing divorce and contraception.
   The third candidate, Austin Currie, made his reputation in the
Roman Catholic civil rights movement in British-ruled Northern
Ireland. He was elected to the Dail, Ireland's parliament, last
year.
   Appearing on a broadcast with Lenihan on Monday, former Prime
Minister Garret FitzGerald said Lenihan, Haughey and other Fianna
Fail leaders put improper pressure on Hillery in 1982 after
FitzGerald's government lost the vote of confidence.
   Haughey, according to FitzGerald, wanted the president to ask
Fianna Fail to form a government without having a national
election. Haughey has denied approaching Hillery.
   The alleged calls raise a fine point of law and custom: whether
the opposition may advise the president in exercising his one real
power, the right to dissolve parliament.
   In an interview in May with Jim Duffy, a graduate student in
political science at University College, Dublin, Lenihan said he
clearly remembered telephoning Hillery.
   ``I remember talking to him and he wanted to lay off. There was
no doubt about it in his mind; in fact, looking back on it, it was
a mistake on our part ...'' said Lenihan, who also holds the title
of Tanaiste, or deputy prime minister.
   He said that Hillery, a Fianna Fail man himself, ``was annoyed
with the whole bloody lot of us.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0052 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 1729EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Israel-Army     10-28 0320</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel-Army,0372</SECOND>
<HEAD>Five Soldiers Sentenced for Abusing Arab Detainee</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Israel, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A military tribunal sentenced five Israeli
soldiers to jail Sunday and stripped them of their rank for abusing
an Arab detainee and threatening to execute him, Israel radio
reported.
   Israeli security forces have come under close scrutiny amid
international criticism of Israel over the Oct. 8 killings of 20
Palestinians on the Temple Mount.
   The highest-ranking officer sentenced Sunday was Sgt. Menachem
Zemach, who was ordered jailed for two months, the radio said.
   The judges reportedly ruled that Zemach and his troops of the
armored corps pretended to execute a blindfolded and bound
19-year-old detainee in July.
   They put the detainee, Anis Zaidan of Beitin village in the
occupied West Bank, through a fake lie detector test and ``smoothed
a knife over his cheek and forehead,'' saying he was to be
executed, the radio said.
   One of the troopers later kicked Zaidan in the back so hard that
he fainted, the radio said. It said Zaidan was released when he
awoke.
   Zaidan was detained when the soldiers,searching his home, found
pro-PLO slogans daubed on the roof, the radio said.
   The other four soldiers received sentences of 14 days to three
months, and all were demoted from the ranks of sgt. or corpl. to
private, the radio said. The military command declined comment.
   In another trial, a commander stationed in Nablus in the early
days of the 34-month-old Palestinian uprising reportedly said that
then-Defense Minister Yitzhak Rabin had ordered troops to break the
bones of Arab stone-throwers.
   Rabin has repeatedly denied giving such orders and has said he
permitted soldiers to beat Palestinians only during a riot or if a
suspect resisted arrest.
   But a border police comander, Moshe Viltzig, gave a different
version before a tribunal in Tel Aviv, Israel radio said.
   Viltzig testified at the trial of Yehuda Meir, a former
commander in Nablus indicted for ordering soldiers to break the
bones of rioters in January 1988.
   Viltzig said he heard Rabin tell a closed meeting of commanders
that Palestinians detained in stone-throwing riots should be beaten
as punishment, the radio said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0053 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 1756EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BRF--Soviet-BoundGlas     10-28 0152</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Soviet-Bound Glasses,0158</SECOND>
<HEAD>Police Say Couple Steals Sunglasses, Sells on Blackmarket</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ENGLEWOOD CLIFFS, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A couple have been charged with
stealing designer sunglasses in the United States as part of a
scheme to sell them on the Soviet black market, police said.
   The two are believed to be part of a group that steals glasses
to sell in the Soviet Union at three times their U.S. retail value,
police said.
   Police said they confiscated about 60 display case keys and a
notebook containing addresses of optical stores in New York City,
eastern Pennsylvania and New Jersey.
   Eduard Fridman, 32, and Victoria Feldmus, 30, of New York City,
were arrested Friday for stealing four pairs of sunglasses worth
$996 from a Fort Lee store, Englewood Cliffs police Capt. George
Kirschbaum said.
   The two were being held in lieu of $6,500 bail each on charges
of shoplifting and possession of stolen goods, police said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0054 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 1808EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Philippines-Rebels     10-28 0327</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Philippines-Rebels,0362</SECOND>
<HEAD>Communist Rebels Hold Talks with Dissident Military Officers</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By OLIVER TEVES</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MANILA, Philippines (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Communist insurgents have met with
dissident military officers to discuss an alliance against the
government of President Corazon Aquino, the rebel leaders said.
   In an interview with The Associated Press, a group of Communist
officials confirmed newspaper reports that they had met members of
the clandestine Young Officers' Union, which helped stage a coup
attempt in December.
   In Saturday's interview, the officials said the ``essentially
exploratory'' talks were held twice last week before a
leftist-called general strike. But they denied claims by the
military that leftist and rightist extremists had cooperated in
violence during the strike, called to force the government to
increase the minimum wage.
   The talks were initiated by the leaders of the Young Officers'
Union, said Sergio Romero, chief of the Alex Boncayao Brigade, the
Manila wing of the Communist New People's Army. The name is an
alias.
   Maj. Abraham Purugganan, a leader of the Young Officers, claimed
in reports Monday his group was joining the rebels for a
``nationalist revolution'' to oust Mrs. Aquino and establish a
federal system of government with a one-house legislature.
   ``On our part, we are always open to alliances, but the basis of
unity should always be clear,'' said Martin Serrano, Manila area
Communist Party secretary. ``What we want is for them to declare
their program or what they are fighting for, not to us but to the
people.''
   ``If this program approximates our own anti-imperialist,
anti-feudal and anti-fascist national democratic program, we don't
see any reason why there should be no unity,'' Serrano said.
   Juan Liwanag, a leader of the National Democratic Front, an
umbrella group headed by Communists, said the dissident officers
would have to clarify their goals before the leftist groups trusted
them enough to form an alliance.
   While some of the rebellious officers in the country proclaim
democratic goals, others are seen as favoring military
dictatorship.
   The Communist party and its New People's Army have been waging
an insurgency for 21 years to establish a Marxist government in the
Philippines.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0055 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 1817EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-France-Gorbachev 1stLd-Writethru a0774 10-28 0438</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-France-Gorbachev, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0774,0504</SECOND>
<HEAD>Soviet Says Talks in Baghdad Not Fruitful</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS thruout to UPDATE with Shevardnadze saying talks in
Baghdad unsuccessful, details of Mitterrand-Gorbachev talks,
accords. No Pickup</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By TERRIL JONES</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Soviet envoy to Iraq appears to have failed in
his effort to find a peaceful way out of the Persian Gulf crisis,
Soviet Foreign Minister Eduard Shevardnadze said Sunday night.
   ``For the moment, there are not many reasons for optimism''
coming from Yevgeny Primakov's talks with Iraqi President Saddam
Hussein, Shevardnadze said during his visit to Paris with Soviet
President Mikhail Gorbachev.
   Shevardnadze did not elaborate, but said he was still hopeful
for a peaceful resolution of the crisis that began when Iraq
invaded Kuwait on Aug. 2.
   Soviet diplomats Saturday postponed a U.N. Security Council
resolution because they said its harsh condemnation of Iraq could
tie Primakov's hands as he entered the talks Sunday with Saddam.
Gorbachev had said Saddam seemed to be softening his stance on
Kuwait.
   Shevardnadze made his brief comments while attending a signing
ceremony for five scientific and economic agreements between French
and Soviet officials and academics.
   During an visit earlier to Spain, Gorbachev and Shevardnadze
suggested there were still ways to achieve a peaceful resolution to
the gulf crisis.
   ``It is necessary to find such a path to a political solution,
but it is difficult to know what it is,'' Shevardnadze said in
Barcelona on Sunday.
   Gorbachev and French President Francois Mitterrand met over
dinner Sunday and discussed the gulf crisis and next month's
conference on European security, a French spokesman said.
   The two leaders said the Conference on Security and Cooperation
in Europe, which opens in Paris on Nov. 19, presents ``a unique
occasion to bring together all the countries concerned to crown
this year of change in Europe,'' spokesman Hubert Vedrine said.
   Gorbachev arrived in Paris on Sunday evening for an overnight
visit on his way home from the three-day trip to Spain. He was met
at the airport by Mitterrand, who just arrived from a summit of
European leaders in Rome.
   France and the Soviet Union are set to sign a Treaty of
Understanding and Cooperation that will increase cooperation
between the two states in energy, non-military nuclear science,
transportation, high-definition television and telecommunications.
   Vedrine last week called the pact ``very ambitious, and
unprecedented in Franco-Soviet relations.''
   The visit to Spain was packed with ceremonies honoring the
Gorbachev on his first trip abroad since winning the Nobel Peace
Prize earlier this month. Both Gorbachev and his wife Raisa took
advantage of opportunities to plunge into the crowds that came to
see them.
   The architect of perestroika, or openness, also found time to
win $1.5 billion in Spanish guaranteed loans to help ease his
country's painful transition to a market economy.
   Among the agreements signed in France on Sunday was one
providing $1 billion in loans and credits to the Soviet Union.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0056 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 1826EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Norway     10-28 0375</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Norway,0404</SECOND>
<HEAD>Reports: Coalition Government To Resign Over EEC Split</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DOUG MELLGREN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>OSLO, Norway (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Norway's year-old coalition government will
resign Monday after failing to resolve a split over trade
negotiations with the European Economic Community, news reports
said Sunday.
   Government sources refused to confirm the reports, but a brief
news release from the office of Conservative Prime Minister Jan P.
Syse said a statement would be issued in Parliament on Monday.
   There is disagreement in the three-party alliance over Norway's
position on talks between the 12-nation EEC and the European Free
Trade Association, in which Norway and five other nations are
members.
   The two trade blocs are discussing possibly opening all 18
nations to unrestricted trade after 1992.
   Syse's Conservative Party favors the alliance, but the Center
Party, the smallest coalition partner, opposes ECC membership for
Norway or broad changes in Norwegian laws that limit foreign access
to natural resources and ownership in domestic industries.
   Syse reportedly spent the weekend trying to salvage the
Conservative-dominated coalition, which also includes Christian
Democrats.
   The Conservatives have previously said they would not allow the
coalition to stall the talks.
   Conservative parliamentary leader Anders Talleraas said
``chances are extremely small'' a compromise between the two
parties could be reached before parliament's debate on the issue,
scheduled for Monday.
   The state television network NRK and the national news agency
NTB reported Syse would resign, but it was not immediately clear
who would form a new government.
   Syse could propose a single-party Conservative government or a
new coalition. He could also ask former Prime Minister Gro Harlem
Brundtland of the Labor Party to form her third socialist
government since 1981.
   Norway's constitution does not allow for dissolving parliament
and calling new elections.
   When the coalition toppled Ms. Brundtland last October, it left
the EEC issue vague.
   ``What has happened is that the basic difference between the
Conservatives and the Center has now come out in full bloom,'' said
Anne Enger Lahnstein, Center's parliamentary leader.
   The Geneva-based free trade association includes Austria,
Finland, Iceland, Norway, Sweden and Switzerland. Present trade
agreements with the EEC are mostly limited to industrial goods.
   The EEC members are Belgium, Denmark, France, West Germany,
Greece, Ireland, Italy, Luxembourg, the Netherlands, Britain, Spain
and Portugal. The nations aim to integrate their economies and
coordinate social developments.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0057 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 1835EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Basque-Elections     10-28 0357</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Basque-Elections,0420</SECOND>
<HEAD>Nationalists and Socialists Lead Elections in Basque Region</HEAD>
<DATELINE>VITORIA, Spain (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A coalition of Basque nationalists and
Socialists that has governed the fractious Basque region since 1986
appeared headed for another term, based on early returns from
regional elections Sunday.
   There were no reports of violence, in contrast to three previous
Basque regional elections since the region was given home rule in
1980.
   An exit poll made public by Spanish National Radio and
Television immediately after the polls closed at 8 p.m. gave the
Basque Nationalist Party about 25 percent of the vote, making it
the strongest single political group.
   Based on that popular vote, the Nationalists would gain 21 to 24
seats in the 75-member parliament. That would mark a big increase
over the 17 they had held since the November 1986 election.
   It appeared likely the Nationalists would form a coalition once
again with the Socialists, this time with the Nationalists as
senior partner.
   The Socialists, who run the national government, were projected
to receive 17 percent of the vote and take 15 to 18 seats, down
from the 19 they won in 1986.
   The radical Basque party Herri Batasuna, considered to be the
political arm of the terrorist group ETA, was projected to remain
the third political force in the Basque country with 17 percent of
the vote and 12 to 14 seats.
   Herri Batasuna is the only Basque party that did not subscribe
to a 1987 pact renouncing political violence.
   ETA stands for homeland and liberty in the Basque language. The
group seeks independence for the three-province region. Since 1968,
its attacks have claimed more than 600 lives, including 15 this
year.
   The turnout among the region's 1.7 million eligible voters was
estimated at 54 percent, the lowest in the Basque country since
Spain returned to democracy in 1977.
   Two other nationalist parties, the center-left Eusko
Alkartasuna, and the leftist Euskadiko Ezkerra, were projected to
win 11 and 10 percent of the vote respectively, slightly less than
their totals in the 1986 vote.
   The conservative Popular Party, the main opposition party in the
national parliament, increased its presence from two seats to at
least five, the projection showed.
   Unidad Alavesa, another nationalist group splintered from the
Popular Party, was projected to make its parliamentary debut with
one to three seats.
   The projection, by the Metra-6 polling agency, was based on
interviews with 20,000 voters at 85 voting stations.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0058 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 1836EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-PrisonRiot     10-28 0239</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Prison Riot,0268</SECOND>
<HEAD>Inmates Remain In Lockdown Following Riot</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BLYTHE, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Suspected ringleaders were in isolation
Sunday after a riot in which several hundred black and Hispanic
inmates battled each other with rocks and weightlifting equipment.
   One inmate was in critical condition and about 800 inmates were
confined in dormitory-style rooms, said officials of Chuckawalla
Valley State Prison, a medium-security facility 200 miles east of
Los Angeles.
   Officials said 30 suspected ringleaders were sequestered in a
room separate from the other inmates.
   Warden Bob Briggs said the lockdown affected the ``D'' section
only. Operations were normal at the rest of the prison.
   Inmates under lockdown still were allowed visitors, but were
escorted to the visitors section and visits were limited to two
hours, Briggs said.
   At least 300 inmates began brawling outside the dormitory early
Saturday, apparently in a dispute over access to telephones.
   ``Two groups went at it with anything they could get,'' Briggs
said. ``They put rocks in their socks. It was pretty much anything
you could grab. It was a riotous condition, but not a riot in the
sense they were trying to take over the prison.''
   Fifteen inmates were injured and guards fired warning shots to
break up the melee. No one was struck by the gunfire and no guards
were injured.
   Briggs said the D-section lockdown would continue at least until
Monday.
   ``Because of the racial overtones we'll have to be sure we're on
very good grounds before we stop,'' he said. ``We'll have to be
sure the hard feelings are down.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0059 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 1838EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BRF--StabbingSpree     10-28 0152</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Stabbing Spree,0158</SECOND>
<HEAD>Police Say Teen-Ager Went on Stabbing Spree at State Fair</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SHREVEPORT, La. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A teen-age girl has been booked on four
counts of attempted murder after allegedly going on a stabbing
spree on the midway of the Louisiana State Fair.
   The stabbings of four teen-age girls late Saturday apparently
grew out of an earlier squabble between two groups of suspected
gang members, police said.
   Police recovered a knife with a roughly 5-inch blade at the
scene.
   Carolyn Burnham, 16, of Shreveport was apprehended outside the
fair grounds and booked into the city jail Saturday night, police
said.
   Police said she was with one group of suspected gang members and
the victims were with another group.
   At least two of the victims, all from Shreveport, were in
serious condition, one with a collapsed lung, at LSU Medical Center
late Saturday. Officials would not give out their conditions
Sunday.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0060 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 1850EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>d a AM-BRF--CountryMural     10-28 0170</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Country Mural,0172</SECOND>
<HEAD>Benton's Final Work Back in Nashville</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NASHVILLE, Tenn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Artist Thomas Hart Benton's mural ``The
Sources of Country Music'' has returned home following a two-year,
nine-city tour of American museums.
   Benton's mural is back on display at the Country Music Hall of
Fame and Museum. It was commissioned in 1974 by the Country Music
Foundation, which operates the museum, and was completed the
following year.
   The mural is a 6-foot-by-10-foot canvas featuring near
life-sized figures depicting the major musical and cultural
traditions that helped shape the sound of modern country music.
   Figures in the painting include a dulcimer player, fiddlers,
hymn singers, square dancers, a banjo player, a singing cowboy, a
train and a river boat.
   The mural went on tour during the 100th anniversary of Benton's
birth in 1889. Benton died in 1975.
   ``This great painting links a wonderful artist with an important
subject: the folk roots of country music,'' said Jim Foglesong,
chairman of the board of the Country Music Foundation.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0061 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 1901EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Israel 1stLd-Writethru a0751 10-28 0879</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0751,1102</SECOND>
<HEAD>Palestinians Back to Work After Four-Day Ban</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: INSERTS 4 grafs after 7th graf pvs, `I hope...,' to ADD report
of opposition to opening borders; pickup 8th graf pvs, `Tel
Aviv....' SUBS 6 grafs for 29-31 pvs bgng ```The police...' to
UPDATE with new unrest; no pickup</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos JRL1,TLV1,2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GWEN ACKERMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Most Palestinians returned to work in Israel
Sunday after a four-day ban, but some found they had lost their
jobs to Jews and others were turned back at roadblocks.
   Police had new orders barring Arabs with a record of hostile
activity against Israel. About 8,000 Palestinians carry green
identity cards that ban them from Israel as security risks,
according to the daily Haaretz.
   ``We will increase the list of those not allowed into Israel,''
Shmuel Goren, government coordinator in the territories, said on
Israel radio.
   The Cabinet, meanwhile, left its police minister to decide the
fate of senior police officers criticized by an official inquiry
into the Oct. 8 killings of 20 Palestinians.
   The killings on Jerusalem's hallowed Temple Mount prompted a
wave of Arab-Jewish clashes inside Israel, leading to the four-day
closure of the West Bank and Gaza Strip.
   The closure was lifted Sunday. But Defense Minister Moshe Arens
warned he might reimpose it if violence continues.
   ``I hope we won't have to take such a step,'' he said on army
radio.``There are tens of thousands who work in Israel who are
trustworthy ... and we want to allow them to make an honorable
living.''
   Some Israeli Cabinet ministers argued against lifting the
closure, saying the atmosphere is still too tense, Israeli radio
and television reported.
   ``The closure wasn't to punish the Palestinians, but to restore
calm and a sense of security. These aims, in my opinion, haven't
been achieved yet,'' Transport Minister Moshe Katsav said.
   During a memorial for three Israeli stabbing victims, some
Jewish extremists demanded a permanent ban on Arab labor from the
occupied lands.
   ``Suddenly the gates were reopened so the murderers could come
to our houses, why?'' legislator Rehavam Zeevi of the ultra
right-wing Moledet Party told the gathering.
   Tel Aviv car wash owner Nissim Ahbari said he hired two recently
discharged Israeli soldiers while his Arab worker was confined to
the Gaza Strip.
   ``I prefer that Jews work instead of Arabs,'' he said. ``I am
ready to pay them more money. These guys are getting 15 shekels
($7.50) more a day than the Arabs got.''
   A Jerusalem restaurant owner, however, said his hired Jewish
replacements were temporary. He said his Arab workers had been with
him for 17 years and were like family.
   An Arab construction laborer in east Jerusalem said most of his
friends were looking for other jobs.
   ``There is always work, but the situation is different now.
There is a lot of fear and everyone is tense,'' he said on Israel
radio, without giving his name.
   Three Jews were killed in Arab attacks, and two Arabs were
killed by Jews in the random violence that prompted Wednesday's
closure.
   Israel radio said the attacks fueled a wave of applications by
Israelis for weapons licenses, most of which were rejected by the
Interior Ministry.
   Up to 150,000 of the 1.7 million Palestinians in the occupied
West Bank and Gaza Strip have jobs in Israel, mostly as blue-collar
workers.
   The closure was welcomed in Israel, with many Jews saying it
would vacate jobs for unemployed Israelis and Soviet Jewish
immigrants, as well as free Israel from its dependence on Arab
labor.
   The Education Ministry approved a special school schedule for
children in farming villages to give them a day on which to help
with work usually done by Arabs.
   Some Palestinians also welcomed the closure, saying that forcing
Arabs to fend for themselves could be a step toward an independent
Palestinian economy.
   Although most Arabs returned to their jobs Sunday, it was
unclear how many would be affected by the new security
restrictions, which included tightening the ban on overnight stays
in Israel, the government said.
   Such stays are illegal, but the ban is widely ignored.
   At the entrance from Gaza to Israel, soldiers ordered every
driver to open the trunk of his car, and the contents were
searched.
   A man with two blankets in his car was told to take them home.
   ``We are doing this in an attempt to make sure that they aren't
able to sleep in Israel,'' a soldier explained on condition of
anonymity.
   The Cabinet, meanwhile, said it accepted the conclusions of the
three-man investigative team appointed by Prime Minister Yitzhak
Shamir.
   The panel said the shooting at the Mount, known in Arabic as
Haram es-Sharif, was in self-defense but chastised senior police
officers for failing to prepare for violence and being absent when
it began.
   Police killed 20 Palestinians and injured 140 after Arab
protesters threw rocks at Jews praying below at the Western Wall.
   ``What we decided was to accept the report of the commission and
to allow the minister responsible to implement those parts which
need to be carried out,'' Health Minister Ehud Olmert said after
Sunday's session.
   Police Minister Roni Milo has declined to confirm or deny media
reports that the nation's three senior police officials may lose
their jobs. But some ministers from Shamir's right-wing Likud bloc
rejected the idea.
   ``The police are guilty of not preparing as needed in order to
deter (the riot), but they are not accused of the killings,'' said
Katzav, the transport minister.
   The U.N. Security Council has passed two resolutions condemning
Israel: one for the shooting and one for rejecting a U.N.
investigative team. Israel has said its own investigation was
sufficient.
   In Rome, West European leaders at a two-day summit Sunday
deplored the situation in the Israeli-occupied territories as
``untenable.''
   Also Sunday, a 24-year-old man in Khizah village in Gaza was
stabbed to death by masked Palestinian activists who accused him of
collaborating with Israel, Arab reports said. The army confirmed
his death.
   In Beach Camp in Gaza, a 29-year-old Palestinian man was also
stabbed to death for allegedly dealing narcotics, which some Moslem
activists consider treason to the Palestinian cause.
   The deaths raised to 292 the number of Palestinians slain by
fellow Arabs since the start of the uprising in December 1987.
Another 756 Palestinians have been killed by Israelis, and 55
Israelis and foreigners have been slain by Arabs.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0062 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 1909EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-ScaryThings 1stLd-Writethru a0750 10-28 0476</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Scary Things, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0750,0584</SECOND>
<HEAD>Board Game Helps Children Deal With Fears</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 7th graf, ``We see ...' to CORRECT attribution to Lyness,
picks up 8th graf, `Lisa Johnson ...'; SUBS 12th graf, `The game's
...' to DELETE now redundant material, picks up 13th graf,
`Izenberg and ...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By BRUCE RULE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PHILADELPHIA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Remember hiding under the covers when you
were young, praying the lightning and thunder would go away and
leave you in peace? Or maybe bullies were your nightmare, or
Halloween ghosts and goblins.
   Today's children have the same fears - spiders and snakes, large
green monsters and ``the dark.'' But they don't have to face those
demons alone.
   ``Not So Scary Things'' is a board game that guides children
through the worst visions of their fears, debunking myths and
allowing them to gain some mastery over life.
   The game, available in some speciality stores and catalogs, is
for children ages 4-8 and their parents. It forces young players to
imitate the objects of their nightmares and helps parents remember
childhood perils.
   The game ``mirrors the way children learn how to handle their
fears,'' said Dr. Neil Izenberg, a pediatrician and co-creator.
``Imitate it, learn about it, then master it.''
   As important as the child's reaction is parent participation.
   ``We see parents who inadvertently frighten children because
they don't have the same fears,'' said D'Arcy Lyness, a child
psychologist who created the game with Izenberg. She used the
example of a parent who takes a child to see a scary movie. ``We
forget what it feels like.''
   Lisa Johnson, 28, of Philadelphia says she's played the game
with her three children several times. ``They really get into it -
the play-acting, jumping around and stuff,'' she said.
   Her 6-year-old son, Derrick, used to cry and scream during
thunderstorms until he played the game. ``Derrick now knows what
lightning is,'' she said. ``Now it doesn't bother him.''
   In the game, players move up Mount Courage along a path dotted
by ``scary'' spots and ``courage'' spots.
   When players land on a scary spot, they must pick a card, which
may tell them to ``do a snake dance,'' ``make a loud thunder
noise,'' or ``stomp like a monster.'' Similarly, a player landing
on a courage spot must pick a card that might instruct: ``Show how
to look a bully straight in the eye.''
   The game's scary things are monsters, darkness, snakes,
lightning and thunder, bullies and meanies, and spiders - fears
children normally face while growing up, Lyness said.
   Izenberg and Lyness spent 2{ years developing the game, running
ideas past teachers, parents and children and getting help from
Izenberg's brother, also a doctor.
   Recently, a group of children played the game at Albert Einstein
Medical Center in Philadelphia, where Izenberg and Lyness work.
   Matthew Litman landed on a scary spot in the monster section.
   Told to ``make a scary, monster face,'' the 6-year-old ducked
under the table, then popped up with his face scrunched together
and his fingers pulling his eyelids up to his forehead, to the glee
of his playmates.
   Later, he landed on a courage spot and was told to name three
famous monsters. ``Frankenstein, the mummy and the wolfman,'' he
answered after some thought.
   Matthew said he was once scared by a neighborhood boy who wore a
monster mask. Now, he knows that monsters are just kids ``dressed
up scary.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0063 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 1942EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i A-ReverendReturns     10-28 0485</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Reverend Returns,0576</SECOND>
<HEAD>Once-Banned Pastor Speaks At White Church After 27 Years</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GREG MYRE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>GERMISTON, South Africa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   When the Rev. Beyers Naude began
preaching against apartheid in the 1960s, he was shunned by his
white congregation and later banned by the government.
   The 75-year-old pastor's message is still the same. What was
different Sunday were the handshakes and hugs Naude received from
the multi-racial congregation after he spoke from the pulpit of a
white Dutch Reformed Church for the first time in 27 years.
   ``This is good news for South Africa. This is reconciliation,''
said longtime church member Louis Lillie. ``This proves Rev. Naude
was right all along.''
   ``I never thought I'd see this day,'' Naude said of his sermon
in Germiston, just outside Johannesburg. ``There's no bitterness in
my heart. I've always wanted to preach the message of social
justice and now some whites are beginning to listen.''
   About half of the 200 worshipers at Sunday's service were black,
mixed-race or Indian.
   The Germiston congregation is officially part of the white
branch of the Dutch Reformed Church, which has separate branches
for blacks and followers of mixed-race.
   But Germiston's minister, Pieter Dumas, has been encouraging
people of other races to attend services since 1985. Many whites
oppose integration and left the church.
   Also, Dumas on Sunday installed two black elders, reportedly a
first in a white Dutch Reformed Church.
   ``I hope this will spread to other congregations,'' Naude said.
``It will help (whites) see the other side of the racial picture,
how the other side struggles and hopes.'''
   Like many long-segregated institutions in South Africa, the
white Dutch Reformed Church is wrestling with racial change.
   The church, the main religion of the Afrikaners who control the
government, argued until the mid-1980s that there was a Biblical
justification for apartheid, the South African system of racial
separation.
   Earlier this month, the white Dutch Reformed Church agreed in
principle to unite with its black and mixed-race sister churches.
But the white church does not plan a final decision until 1994.
   Naude appeared headed for the leadership of the white Dutch
Reformed Church when he began began to speak out against apartheid
30 years ago.
   He immediately meet opposition from his congregation, the church
hierarchy and the government.
   Naude resigned in 1963 and set up the Christian Institute, which
promoted integration and racial justice. His offices were raided by
security police and on several occasions he was blocked from
traveling abroad to give speeches.
   The government banned Naude from 1977 to 1984. The restrictions
made it illegal for him to travel outside Johannesburg, to attend
meetings or give speeches. It was a crime in South Africa to quote
him.
   Naude returned to prominence after the banning order was lifted,
often appearing at anti-apartheid gatherings with other church
leaders, such as Anglican Archbishop Desmond Tutu, a Nobel Peace
laureate.
   Naude does not belong to any political group. But the African
National Congress, the main black opposition movement, asked Naude
to be part of its delegation when it held groundbreaking talks with
the government in May.
   Naude says he does not expect to be play any future political
role.
   ``I've never seen myself as anything but an Afrikaner,'' said
Naude. ``My goal is to help my fellow Afrikaners change, to become
white Africans.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0064 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 1954EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Obit-Shantaram     10-28 0279</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Shantaram,0325</SECOND>
<HEAD>Vankutre Shantaram, Pioneering Indian Filmmaker, Dead at 88</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW DELHI, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Vankutre Shantaram, a pioneer of the
Indian film industry who championed harmony between Hindus and
Moslems, died in Bombay early Sunday. He was 88.
   The former film actor, director and producer had been in failing
health for several years. The cause of death was listed as cardiac
arrest, the United News of India news agency reported.
   With nearly 100 people dead in India in the past week in clashes
between Hindus and Moslems, state television on Sunday scheduled a
film about religious harmony directed by Shantaram in the 1940s.
The religious clashes were precipitated by plans to build a Hindu
temple on a site now occupied by a mosque, and the dispute
threatens to bring down Prime Minister V.P. Singh's government.
   Shantaram's film ``Podosi'' (The Neighbors) is an allegory
featuring two elderly chess players - one Hindu, the other Moslem -
who were inseparable friends until a petty quarrel pulled them
apart.
   Shantaram was widely acclaimed for addressing social issues in
his films, which still are shown in cinemas and on television
throughout India. His films won top awards in India, were widely
known in the Middle East and were shown at international festivals,
including those in Venice and Berlin.
   His first job in the theater came at age 13 when he was hired to
pull the curtains between acts for a Bombay drama troupe. As a
teen-ager, he often played young women. Later cinema roles included
Hindu gods.
   He started directing in 1927 and opened his own company two
years later, continuing to star in films throughout most of his
career.
   Shantaram died at his home in Bombay. Survivors include his
wives Sandhya and Jayshree, who are sisters. Both are actresses who
starred in Shantaram's films.
   One of his sons, Kiran, is a film producer.
   Funeral arrangements were pending.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0065 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 1955EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Israel-Scandal     10-28 0111</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel-Scandal,0097</SECOND>
<HEAD>Israeli Air Force Officer Detained on Suspicion of Fraud</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Military police detained a high-ranking air
force officer suspected of fraud and bribery in connection with the
purchase of weapons and other equipment in the United States,
Israel television reported Sunday.
   The officer, Brig. Gen. Rami Dotan, is one of the highest
ranking army officers to be detained on such charges, the
television said.
   He allegedly committed the crimes while serving in a Defense
Ministry delegation in New York two years ago, it said No other
details were immediately available.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0066 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 2011EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BloodthirstySquirrels     10-28 0230</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bloodthirsty Squirrels,0254</SECOND>
<HEAD>Popular Playground Closed Because of Aggressive Squirrels</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WHEATON, Md. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A popular playground was closed because of
feisty squirrels hunting acorns for the winter. Two children were
bitten and a man bludgeoned to death one of the animals because it
was annoying.
   Visitors to the popular park were greeted Saturday with the
discomforting yellow tape used at crime scenes and a sign that
read: ``Playground closed due to over-aggressive squirrels.''
   Overseers of Montgomery County's Wheaton Regional Park said two
children were bitten at the playground by gray squirrels in the
last two weeks. On Thursday, a man beat a squirrel to death with a
stick because it was aggressive.
   ``The squirrels are just acting squirrelly now,'' said park
maintenance worker Kathy Lowe. ``They are so busy burying acorns
they are aggravated at the people.''
   The rest of the sprawling park, just outside the Capital
Beltway, remained open. Park officials did not know when the
playground will reopen.
   A bumper crop of acorns over the past two years has attracted an
abundance of gray squirrels. They are gathering food for the winter
with particular fervor, Lowe said.
   When park patrons offer food, as was the case with both of the
bitten children, the animals move in close and don't take no for an
answer, Lowe said.
   Squirrels can carry rabies, Lowe said. Park officials
recommended the parents of the bitten children take them to doctors
to determine whether they should undergo treatment for rabies.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0067 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 2041EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-BridgeCollapse     10-28 0450</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bridge Collapse,0555</SECOND>
<HEAD>Islanders Urged to Abandon Long Ferry Wait</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MATT BIVENS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>OREGON INLET, N.C. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Residents and tourists stranded on
islands after a dredge knocked out the only road link to the
mainland were urged Sunday to abandon the long wait for a ferry and
seek shelter from the cold.
   Only limited electricity was available on Hatteras Island, where
a high school was turned into a shelter and a briefing point for
information-starved victims of Friday's accident.
   About 1,000 people, or one-fifth of the island's permanent
population, flocked to Cape Hatteras School for an update from
officials.
   Residents and tourists were stuck on Hatteras and Ocracoke
islands when a the dredge smashed into the Herbert Bonner Bridge,
the only road leading to the mainland.
   The accident cut power to both islands and telephone service to
Hatteras. Phone service was restored Saturday and limited
electricity was available on the islands through generators. Power
was restored Friday to Ocracoke, which has 500 permanent residents.
   A half-hour ferry ride links Hatteras and Ocracoke. A 2{-hour
ride links Ocracoke to the mainland. There was no wait Sunday for a
fery from Hatteras to Ocracoke, but there was a 600-car backup -
or a 30-hour wait - from Ocracoke to the mainland, said Gwen White,
Dare County public information officer.
   ``Folks on Hatteras should stay where they are,'' she said.
``They can't get off of Ocracoke, so they're better off to stay in
Hatteras.''
   The Hatteras school was turned into a shelter Saturday and 39
people took advantage of it that night. Among them was a family of
11 who were overcome by fumes from a heater in their camper. They
remained in the shelter Sunday, Mrs. White said.
   ``They've been treated. At least one is on oxygen,'' she said.
``If there was a need to get them to a hospital we would airlift
them out.''
   People waiting for a ferry at Ocracoke were encouraged to return
to Hatteras and take advantage of the shelter, which has power from
a generator, hot food and Red Cross workers.
   ``We are expecting to have some cool weather,'' Mrs. White said.
``Naturally, it's an inconvenience and a problem.''
   Temperatures were expected to dip into the high 30s late Sunday.
Temperatures Monday should be in the low 50s, with a wind up to 20
miles an hour, said Jan Price, a meteorologist with the National
Weather Service.
   A smaller shelter was set up on Ocracoke, said Hyde County
commissioner Alton Ballance.
   The Army National Guard was flying in 500 meals three times a
day to bolster restaurant and in-home supplies. Other emergency
supplies, including fuel, water, blankets and food, steadily
streamed onto Hatteras, which has 5,000 permanent residents.
   As for the 2{-mile bridge, repair assessments began Sunday. The
dredge, Northerly Island, was freed Saturday from its resting place
on sand. It took out a 369-foot section of the bridge.
   The dredge was sent north to Norfolk, Va., for repairs.
   Dare County Manager Bob Slade said estimates on how much it will
cost to fix the bridge have risen to $2.6 million. A temporary lane
along the damaged section may be up within three months. Permanent
repairs may take more than six months.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0068 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 2049EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-GulfRdp 3rdLd-Writethru a0817 10-28 0898</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf Rdp, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0817,1128</SECOND>
<HEAD>Iraq Lifts Gas Rationing, Fires Oil Minister</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 7th graf to CORRECT envoy from Gorbachev sted to
Gorbachev. Picks up 8th graf pvs, `Soviet Foreign ....' INSERTS 3
grafs after 19th graf pvs, `They condemn...' to ADD statement on
possible Greek hostage release. Picks up 20th graf pvs, `In the
latest...'</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos DHA1,2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DANIEL J. WAKIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   In a surprise move, Iraq said Sunday it is halting gasoline
rationing imposed earlier in response to global economic sanctions.
The Soviets said their latest diplomatic effort to settle the
Persian Gulf crisis has apparently failed.
   The cancellation of the gasoline rationing was reported by the
official Iraqi News Agency, which also said the oil minister had
been fired and replaced by Saddam Hussein's son-in-law.
   The rationing was imposed not because Iraq was short of oil - it
controls 20 percent of the world's supply - but reportedly because
the additives needed for gasoline refining were affected by the
global embargo.
   At the time, Iraqi officials blamed the sanctions for causing
the shortage.
   But the news agency said the Oil Ministry had miscalculated the
amount of chemical additives necessary to refine crude oil into
gasoline and other products.
   The New York Times, quoting Kuwaiti oil officials, reported
Sunday the rationing move was simply a ruse by Iraq to get the
world to think the sanctions were working, and thus to forestall a
military attack against Iraq. Their report was published before the
latest Iraqi announcement.
   In other developments, an envoy from Soviet President Mikhail S.
Gorbachev held talks with Iraqi President Saddam in Baghdad, and
Gorbachev arrived in Paris for talks with French President Francois
Mitterrand on matters including the nearly 3-month-old Persian Gulf
crisis.
   Soviet Foreign Minister Eduard Shevardnadze said Sunday night
that envoy Yevgeny Primakov's talks with Saddam had not borne
fruit.
   ``For the moment, there are not many reasons for optimism''
coming from the talks, Shevardnadze said in Paris. He did not
elaborate, but said he was still hopeful for a peaceful resolution
of the crisis.
   In Iraq, 301 French nationals were told they had to wait another
day for freedom. The Baghdad government said last week that they
could return home, but the trip was delayed from Sunday until
Monday.
   Diplomatic sources said the departure was put off because 26
other French citizens were unaccounted for.
   The Parisian newspaper Journal du Dimanche said France might
close its embassy in Kuwait and send the remaining diplomats home
with the other French citizens. The report did not cite sources.
   Iraq announced Aug. 24 that all embassies in Kuwait City should
close, and it cut off water and electricity to the compounds. One
by one, the embassies have closed, and the French, U.S. and British
missions are the only Western ones remaining open.
   Saddam has allowed isolated groups of the thousands of foreign
nationals held in Iraq and occupied Kuwait to leave.
   He is holding hundreds of the foreigners as ``human shields'' at
strategic sites to deter attack by the multinational force in the
Persian Gulf.
   Iraq's selective release of hostages - and concessions it has
demanded from some nations in exchange for their freedom - has
drawn criticism from world leaders, who say it is merely a ploy to
divide them.
   European Community leaders, holding a summit in Rome, pledged on
Sunday not to send official representatives to win the freedom of
hostages, and to discourage any private missions.
   In a joint statement, the leaders assailed the ``unscrupulous''
use of hostages in the ``vain attempt to divide the international
community.''
   ``They condemn without reserve this maneuver ... which can only
complicate the prospects of a solution of the crisis,'' the
declaration said.
   In Athens, Greece, the Foreign Ministry said Sunday that Iraq
agreed to release 10 Greek hostages suffering from ill health. No
details about the health problems of the nine men and one woman
were given.
   The statement did not say when Iraqi officials may free the
hostages, among 24 Greeks being held in Iraq.
   Two former Greek socialist ministers left Baghdad on Sunday
after seeking the release of the hostages.
   In the latest naval confrontation, U.S. Marines boarded an Iraqi
tanker after an Australian vessel and a U.S. warship fired warning
shots across its bow when it refused to stop, U.S. Navy officials
said.
   The ship, intercepted in the North Arabian Sea, was allowed to
proceed after a search party found no goods banned under the U.N.
sanctions.
   The ship, headed for Basra, Iraq, had refused to stop and allow
a boarding party before the shots were fired. The Marines boarded
by helicopter.
   As of Oct. 26, some 2,738 ships had been intercepted in the gulf
region, and 282 ships boarded.
   Gorbachev arrived in Paris after a visit to Spain, during which
he and Shevardnadze suggested Iraq may have softened its stand in
the gulf crisis.
   Primakov met Sunday with Saddam in his second trip to Iraq this
month. Iraqi officials made no comment afterward.
   Primakov also met twice with Iraqi Foreign Minister Tariq Aziz,
the second an unscheduled session late Sunday, a Palestine
Liberation Organization official said. Primakov also met in Baghdad
with PLO chairman Yasser Arafat, the official said.
   The Soviet envoy was expected to go to Saudi Arabia on Monday to
brief King Fahd on his talks with Saddam, a Soviet diplomat said.
   Primakov has emerged as the main shuttling diplomat in the
conflict, which began when Iraq invaded Kuwait Aug. 2 and occupied
the emirate. Iraq was in turn isolated by U.N. trade sanctions and
widespread international condemnation.
   Egypt's President Hosni Mubarak, meanwhile, told reporters
Sunday he supported an increase in U.S. and other military forces
in the region while peacemaking efforts continue. Mubarak said he
was ready to send more Egyptian troops if asked.
   The United States has said that up to 100,000 U.S. troops could
be sent to join an estimated 220,000 troops already in the region.
The multinational force has another 100,000 troops. They face an
estimated 460,000 Iraqi soldiers deployed in southern Iraq and
Kuwait.
   In a speech at Hickam Air Force Base, in Honolulu, President
Bush said the United States was not looking for war in the Persian
Gulf but would not walk away from the confrontation.
   ``It's clear that the strength of our arms and the strength of
our will is up to the challenge,'' Bush said.
   ``No American will be kept in the gulf a single day longer than
necessary, but we will not walk away until our mission is done,''
he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0069 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 2051EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Obit-Hasegawa     10-28 0147</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Hasegawa,0140</SECOND>
<HEAD>Former Japanese Justice Minister Hasegawa Dies</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Former Justice Minister Shin Hasegawa died of heart
failure at a Tokyo hospital Sunday. He was 71.
   Toranomon Hospital said Hasegawa had been hospitalized since
Sept. 3, when he collapsed before an Imperial Palace ceremony for a
new Supreme Court judge. Hasegawa resigned his post shortly after
the illness struck.
   He started his political career as a village assembly member in
Niigata prefecture in northern Japan. Hasegawa won his first
national election in 1977 and won re-election twice to the upper
house of Japan's Parliament.
   He had been a vice minister of communications and deputy
secretary-general of the governing Liberal Democratic Party before
Prime Minister Toshiki Kaifu named him justice minister on Feb. 28.
   There was no information available on survivors or funeral
arrangements.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0070 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 2101EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Obit-Brown     10-28 0406</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Brown,0499</SECOND>
<HEAD>Internationally Known Bay Area Artist Dies in Museum Accident in
India</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BERKELEY, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Joan Brown, an internationally known San
Francisco Bay-area artist who used mysticism as inspiration for her
work, has been killed with another American in a construction
accident at the age of 52.
   Ms. Brown was installing a mosaic obelisk at the new Heritage
Museum in Proddatura, India, when a concrete turret from the floor
above collapsed on her Friday, said her colleagues at the
University of California, Berkeley.
   Ms. Brown had been a member of the UC-Berkeley art faculty since
1974.
   ``I'm very sorrowful,'' said Elmer Bischoff, the 74-year-old
dean of Bay area painters and one of Ms. Brown's early mentors.
   ``What she felt particularly gratified by was turning people on
in art ... A lot of students feel they don't have any talent, and
she kind of lifted them above that self-doubt.''
   An Indian official, Anantapur District Magistrate B. Rama Rao,
said Ms. Brown and Bonnie Lynn Mainric, 43, of San Francisco, were
working as volunteers on a 100-foot tower to be dedicated to Satya
Sai Baba, a holy man who claims mystical powers and has a
substantial following in North America.
   A third American, Michael Oliver, 25, also of San Francisco, was
injured in the accident.
   Ms. Brown ``was there as an individual artist,'' said
Christopher Brown, a fellow professor who is not related to Ms.
Brown. ``She wasn't really a follower of this holy man, but knew
him as a friend.''
   In 1958, when she was a 20-year-old student at the former
California School of Fine Arts in San Francisco, Ms. Brown won
recognition for her large paintings that combined figurative images
with thick swatches of color.
   ``When she was 24 years old, she was already showing in New
York,'' said Ruth Braunstein of the Braunstein-Quay Gallery in San
Francisco. ``As one of the few women exhibiting at this time, she
was an inspiration and mentor to young women artists, accessible to
everyone.''
   At age 25, she became stifled by pressure to continue her
success, so she dropped out of the art world and began traveling
the globe.
   ``She felt she was being trapped by her celebrity and wanted to
break away from her early, thickly painted canvases to more direct
expression,'' said Allan Frumkin, who owned a New York gallery and
became her primary art dealer.
   Her later work was influenced by the pyramids of Egypt, Incan
folklore in Peru, the Aztecs of Central America and dancing
Krishnas from India. She called the resulting pieces ``inward
journeys,'' boldly colored paintings with sphinxes and half-human,
half-animal figures and towering obelisks with mosaics of lions,
lambs, doves and tigers.
   Ms. Brown resurfaced in the Bay area in 1974 at an art show at
UC-Berkeley.
   She is survived by her husband, San Francisco police Capt. Mike
Hebel, and a son from a previous marriage.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0071 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 2139EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-AutoTalks 1stLd-Writethru a0747 10-28 0494</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Auto Talks, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0747,0572</SECOND>
<HEAD>Chrysler, UAW Talking While Monday Midnight Deadline Looms</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 3rd graf, `About 10,000 ...' to UPDATE with Chrysler
workers in Canada approving contract. Pick up 4th graf, `Much work
...' A version moving on financial wires.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By FREDERICK STANDISH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Auto Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DETROIT (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Bargainers for the United Auto Workers union and
Chrysler Corp. on Sunday struggled to reach an agreement on a new
three-year national labor agreement while a midnight Monday
deadline loomed.
   Negotiators worked until about midnight Saturday and resumed
work early Sunday trying to draft a contract to cover about 63,000
Chrysler hourly and salaried workers in the United States.
   About 10,000 Chrysler Canadian workers are covered by a new
contact recently negotiated with the Canadian Auto Workers union.
The CAW members voted 94.6 percent in favor of the deal Sunday,
union spokesman Peggy Nash said.
   Much work remains to be done on the UAW-Chrysler contract,
company and union officials said. Non-economic matters, which
usually are agreed to before economic issues are tackled, remained
unresolved Sunday, said a union official speaking on condition of
anonymity.
   ``It's going slow,'' the official said.
   Among the major issues hanging up the Chrysler-UAW talks are
pension matters and health-care issues.
   The UAW is pressing Chrysler to accept basicall the same
agreement it has already reached with General Motors Corp. and Ford
Motor Co. GM employs about 300,000 active UAW-covered workers, and
Ford has about 100,000 active workers.
   The GM and Ford pattern agreements call for, among other things,
lump-sum payments to current retirees and surviving spouses, a
method for increasing pension payments for workers who retired
before Oct. 1, 1979, and increases in the amount future retirees
will get.
   Of the Big Three automakers, Chrysler has the highest proportion
of retiree costs since it has nearly one retiree for every active
worker. There are about 1.4 active workers for each retiree at GM
and about 1.5 actives at Ford for every retiree.
   When bargaining began in mid-July, Chrysler said it needed help
from the UAW to cut health-care expenses, which cost the company
about $684 million last year. The pattern agreement has no change
in health-care provisions.
   Chrysler's unionized employees have been working since Sept. 15
under an extension of a contract negotiated in 1988. Late Friday,
the union delivered a so-called ``three-day letter'' to Chrysler
officials saying the extension would expire at midnight Monday.
   The letter could clear the way for the union to call a strike by
all or some of its members in 36 Chrysler factories and office
centers nationwide - but the union also may continue working
without a contract or issue another extension.
   The union has scheduled a meeting for Thursday in Detroit of its
200-member Chrysler national bargaining council, a group of union
local presidents and bargaining committee heads. The meeting can be
used to brief them on bargaining progress, review a tentative
agreement or explain strike strategy.
   The pressure on Chrysler to agree to the GM-Ford pattern
contract built last week when the CAW and Chrysler Canada Ltd., the
automaker's Canadian subsidiary, agreed to a pattern agreement the
CAW had negotiated with GM and Ford Canadian operations.
   Although officials of the UAW and Chrysler said repeatedly their
negotiations were separate from the Canadian talks, industry
observers speculated that the two sides were carefully watching
developments in Toronto.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0072 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 2152EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-IvoryCoast 1stLd-Writethru a0739 10-28 0706</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Ivory Coast, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0739,0826</SECOND>
<HEAD>Opposition Smashes Ballot Boxes, Alleges Fraud in First Free
Polling</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS thruout to UPDATE with early results, quotes from
Gbagbo, interior minister; TRIMS pvs. No Pickup</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By MICHELLE FAUL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ABIDJAN, Ivory Coast (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Opposition supporters accused the
ruling party of cheating in this country's first multiparty vote
Sunday, and they smashed ballot boxes they said were stuffed
beforehand.
   The vote marked the first time a leader of one of Africa's
one-party states was challenged at the polls since a wave of
pro-democracy protests began sweeping sub-Saharan Africa early this
year.
   Preliminary results from two of the 163 administrative regions
gave more than 90 percent of the vote to octogenarian President
Felix Houphouet-Boigny, who has ruled Ivory Coast since
independence from France in 1960.
   The sole challenger, history professor Laurent Gbagbo, showed
reporters stacks of ballots marked for Houphouet-Boigny. Gbagbo
charged the ballots had come from one of dozens of boxes being
stuffed with votes to rig the election.
   ``We cannot ask them to re-do the elections, because these are
not elections,'' said Gbagbo, who had been mobbed at pre-election
rallies by youthful supporters who hail him as their liberator.
   He added, ``They are stuffing boxes in suburbs and in towns
where (Gbagbo's coalition) is well-entrenched. This is criminal. It
is cheating, treachery, to steal the election.''
   Gbagbo said that of the 1,500 ballots in the box, which was
seized a half-hour after voting began, only seven were marked for
his coalition.
   At one polling station, voters said the opposition party
representative arrived 90 minutes late, and voting had already
begun. The opposition representative demanded to see the ballot
boxes. After being refused, his supporters smashed open a box.
   Suspicious boxes were smashed at other polling stations as well,
Gbagbo's supporters said. Gbagbo said the government had also set
up phantom polling booths where no one voted but the ballots were
all marked for the president.
   Interior Minister Leon Konan Koffi said the fraud charges were
lies. Gbagbo's supporters destroyed ballot boxes to stop elections
they knew they would lose, he said.
   Gbagbo, who decided to run against the advice of other
politicians who argued the elections would be fraudulent, said it
had been worthwhile to at least campaign.
   ``Nobody ever thought we would get multiparty democracy while
Houphouet-Boigny was in Ivory Coast,'' he told reporters. ``It was
time to put a stop to the system of there being just a single
candidate.''
   Middle-class Ivorians and the urban poor appeared allied with
the socialist-minded Gbagbo, while peasants rallied around
Houphouet-Boigny.
   A major issue was the government's insistence that African
foreigners be allowed to vote, as they have in past elections. Such
Africans comprise at least a third of the population of 10 million.
Most support the president out of gratitude for allowing them to
stay, or fear the opposition might send them packing because of the
country's economic problems.
   Among the most powerful weapons in the ruling party's arsenal
are a nationwide network built up during more than 30 years of
single-party rule, funds from compulsory contributions exacted from
civil servants' salaries, and the worship by some of
Houphouet-Boigny.
   ``Houphouet saved us from the cruel forced labor of the French,
and for that he will get my vote until he is buried,'' said N'dri
Kouassi, a retired farm laborer in his 80s.
   Villagers have been untouched by the weeks of rioting led by
university students and joined by dissatisfied urban workers.
   The rioting earlier this year forced Houphouet-Boigny to
legalize political opposition, which had been banned since he took
power.
   Opposition politicians like Gbagbo say democracy will help solve
the continent's economic crisis brought on by mismanagement,
corruption and slumping world prices for raw materials, cocoa and
coffee.
   Gbagbo also said the personality cult around Houphouet-Boigny
blocks the country from developing.
   The opposition has promised compulsory education, improved
health services, and a younger, motivated leadership. It is
handicapped by a voting age of 21 years, which excludes thousands
of student supporters.
   Gbagbo, a political detainee from 1971 to 1973, says the
president has run Ivory Coast like a personal fiefdom and enriched
himself and his cronies from state coffers.
   African governments are watching: Ivory Coast is one of the most
stable nations on a continent where governments change more often
because of coups and wars than elections. Houphouet-Boigny's
conservative policies brought about what Western backers called
``an economic miracle'' in Africa.
   Houphouet-Boigny has made it difficult for the opposition. He
refused to publish a voters' roll until the day before the
elections, and denied the opposition access to state radio and
television until the 10-day campaign began Oct. 18.
   Houphouet-Boigny's picture dominated many broadcasts. His party
ran footage of the president in younger days kissing babies,
harvesting sugar cane, and meeting world leaders.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0073 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 2153EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ConfederateSoldier     10-28 0328</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Confederate Soldier,0387</SECOND>
<HEAD>Unknown Civil War Soldier Found in Virginia Brought Home for
Burial</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Franceine in 6th graf is cq</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By ALEX MARTIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>RALEIGH, N.C. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An unknown Confederate soldier was carried
from Virginia to a new grave Sunday in a horse-drawn hearse,
accompanied by fife and drum music and about 150 people in Civil
War garb.
   Forensic scientists determined the soldier, about 20 when he
died, was from North Carolina. Scattered among his bones were five
buttons with sunburst symbols worn by Tar Heel troops during the
war.
   The soldier's remains were unearthed recently from the site of
the Cold Harbor battlefield in Virginia. A Civil War buff found the
remains with a metal detector and word reached the North Carolina
Sons of the Confederacy, which arranged to have the soldier buried
in his home state.
   About 2,000 people lined a downtown street to view the
processional.
   Fifes and drums played ``Dixie'' as members of the North
Carolina Brigade, a Civil War re-enactment group, walked behind a
horse-drawn hearse. The re-enactors had the same beards, tired eyes
and sometimes ragged clothes as Confederates in Civil War
photographs.
   Franceine Rees, a member of United Daughters of the Confederacy,
held two Confederate flags as she watched the hearse go by. On her
lapel were nine pins bearing the names of her ancestors who fought
in the Civil War.
   ``This means a lot to me because I had 25 ancestors who
served,'' she said. ``Some of them came back, some of them didn't.
Some were captured, some were tortured. All of them suffered.''
   Organizer Tom Smith, whose great-grandfather served in the Civil
War, said he was proud to be associated with the soldier's burial.
   ``There's a lot of people here and there's no hatred here.
They're simply interested in their history and past,'' Smith said.
   Civil rights groups did not protest the celebration, but the
North Carolina chapter of the National Association for the
Advancement of Colored People called the event ``insensitive'' to
blacks.
   Some black bystanders agreed the parade and ceremony was a part
of history.
   ``I think it's real nice. We don't have parades like this
through here that often,'' said Ronald Davis, standing with his
family on his front porch.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0074 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 2200EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BenchedPastor     10-28 0260</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Benched Pastor,0307</SECOND>
<HEAD>Blind Pastor Invited to Front of Church, But Not to Stay</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By THERESA HUMPHREY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ELLENDALE, Del. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A legally blind pastor who was banished
from the pulpit because of his guide dog walked down the aisle
Sunday and shook the hand of the man responsible.
   The Rev. Le Roy Singleton, who was an associate pastor at the
Mount Zion AME church, was banished to a back pew when he returned
in September from a school where he trained with the dog.
   The Rev. Ellsworth Coleman, head pastor of the church, said dogs
were not allowed, but he permitted the animal in the back with
Singleton after posting ``Beware of the Dog'' signs.
   Singleton said Coleman had not invited him back to the pulpit.
   Coleman has refused to comment.
   About 60 people were in church Sunday, along with reporters and
a television camera crew.
   The Rev. Joseph D. Tull, presiding elder of African Methodist
Episcopal churches in central and southern Delaware, preached
Sunday's sermon. He invited Singleton, 62, to the front of the
church to shake hands with Coleman after doing the same for Earlene
A. Hughes, president of the Delaware chapter of the National
Federation of the Blind.
   Hughes and Singleton walked up the center aisle with their
seeing-eye dogs.
   Hughes said the federation wants to ensure Singleton is not
discriminated against because he is blind and has a seeing-eye dog.
   ``We're here for him to get returned to his rightful place in
the pulpit,'' she said after the service.
   Singleton's wife, Emma, doesn't think anything has changed.
   ``I know in my heart they don't want the dog in there,'' she
said. Asked if the couple will remain members of the church, she
said, ``That's the million dollar question.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0075 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 2303EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-MoosePlan     10-28 0346</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Moose Plan,0433</SECOND>
<HEAD>Alaska Offiials Say They're Ready to Avoid Heavy Moose Kill</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN ENDERS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Write</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ANCHORAGE, Alaska (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Snow-packing machines and exploding
gunshots will be used this winter to avoid a repeat of last year's
record slaughter of moose along railroad tracks and roads.
   More than 1,000 moose were killed last winter by trains and
autos between Anchorage and Fairbanks. That's greater than twice
the number of the hefty animals killed in any previous year.
   The Alaska Railroad Corp. and the state Department of Fish and
Game hope to prevent unnecessary moose deaths this winter by
leading them out of harm's way.
   ``Last year was an extraordinary year with the amount of snow we
had,'' said railroad spokeswoman Vivian Hamilton. ``We had no idea
the winter was going to be like that.''
   About half the moose were hit last winter in a 40- to 50-mile
stretch in the Susitna Valley, just south of Mt. McKinley,
officials said. This fall, plans are nearly complete to clear the
right-of-way of snow along both sides of the railroad track and to
pack trails leading away from the rail line and a major road,
called Parks Highway.
   Moose, which can weigh more than 1,000 pounds, often take the
route of least resistance. Unless something is done to force them
off roads and tracks, they will run along until they are hit,
wildlife biologists say.
   The wildlife biologists plan eventually to create new forage
areas for moose far from the rail line, not only to make up for
diminishing habitat but to keep them from being smashed.
   The railroad also plans to use, for the second year, a pilot car
that runs ahead of each train. Workers in such a car operate ahead
of trains and shoot off ``cracker shells,'' which are exploding
gunshots designed to frighten moose off tracks.
   ``We have everything laid out so that if it does snow as much as
it did last year, we'll be ready,'' Hamilton said.
   Between August and Oct. 1, a ``hydro axe'' - a giant
lawnmower-like machine - mowed trees and brush along both sides of
a 30-mile-long stretch of rail in the critical kill area, Hamilton
said.
   The idea is to reduce the amount of browse material available to
moose so they'll go elsewhere.
   The railroad also plans to use a giant snow packer with 12-foot
blades to pack snow alongside the rail line and to build a berm
between the line and packed area that moose cannot get over,
Hamilton said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0076 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 2312EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-DailyNews 2ndLd-Writethru a0833 10-28 0546</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Daily News, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0833,0667</SECOND>
<HEAD>Daily News Reporters Decide to Stay on Strike</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 2nd graf, ``We're willing ...' to ADD dropped word `now';
ADDS one graf at bottom to UPDATE with mayor holding talks with
union and newspaper representatives.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By PETER ALAN HARPER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Striking reporters and photographers at the
Daily News decided Sunday to remain on picket lines despite
questions over whether their walkout was properly called.
   ``We're willing to give the strike more time,'' said reporter
Paul LaRosa. ``There's no point in going back now.''
   The News published Frida, Saturday and Sunday editions despite
the strike. Its Sunday edition was the only newspaper in town that
didn't have the strike on its front page.
   At stake is the future of the 71-year-old daily, which has been
in a financial tailspin for the past decade. The News has lost
about $115 million and seen daily circulation slip by about 700,000
since 1980.
   A union contract expired in March but no negotiations are in
progress or planned. The News plans to replace the strikers with
new, permanent employees.
   About 40 reporters and photographers, all members of the
Newspaper Guild, held an oft-times angry session at a restaurant,
Extra! Extra!. LaRosa was on a committee of nine reporters who
later met with Guild officials to discuss divisions among the
members, including the possibility of rescinding the strike
authorization vote.
   ``This is a meeting of people on the fence,'' striking reporter
Stuart Marques said at the restaurant session. ``I think there are
people who will be back tomorrow.''
   ``There's a lot of anger at the Guild leadership,'' added his
wife, reporter JoAnne Wasserman, who is pregnant and also striking.
   The reporters and photographers decided to stay out on strike
after meeting with Guild President Barry Lipton.
   Drivers at the News catapulted nine of the Allied's 10 unions
into a strike Thursday night when 60 of their drivers were replaced
in what the union called an unfair labor practice.
   The News claimed that all 200 drivers at its Brooklyn printing
plant had walked out early Thursday in a dispute and would
subsequently be replaced.
   The union claimed, however, that 20 to 30 workers walked out
briefly and the News then locked out all drivers. Some delivery
trucks were set afire and windows were broken on others.
   The News claimed in a statement that it published and
distributed more than 1.2 million papers in the city and
surrounding suburbs, exceeding Saturday's press run by 500,000. The
News normally prints 1.46 million Sunday papers.
   ``Each day our performance gets better. Our loyal employees are
extraordinary,'' John T. Sloan, News vice president for human
resources, said in the statement.
   On the lack of newspapers at newsstands around the city and in
Newark, N.J., a major distribution center, Sloan said: ``We have
not been hitting all distribution points as of yet. We will soon.''
   Sloan and police in Garden City, Kearny, N.J., and Brooklyn,
where the News' printing plants are located, said about 20 strikers
have been arrested since the strike began.
   Charges include disorderly conduct and one for tampering with an
electrical cable.
   Some reporters at the Extra! Extra! meeting said they were
divided about the strike because they thought it had been called on
a faulty basis.
   They said the strike was called Friday because of reports that
replacement workers had filled their reporting slots.
   ``They were very happy putting on picket signs and gleefully
going to the gallows,'' said Marcia Kramer, the News' City Hall
bureau chief.
   Some reporters said they felt they were in a position of
strength because the News had said it would take them back if they
called.
   Mayor David Dinkins talked with union and Daily News
representatives over the weekend to help end the strike and was
expected to hold more talks Monday, said a Dinkins spokesman,
Albert Scardino.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0077 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 2315EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-ChemicalSpill     10-28 0222</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Chemical Spill,0242</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dam Breaks, Spills Millions of Gallons of Chemical Into Creek</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JEFFERSON, S.C. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   About nine million gallons of potentially
hazardous sodium cyanide spilled Sunday from a reservoir into a
nearby creek when a dam broke, authorities said.
   The spill posed little threat to drinking supplies, but
officials warned residents to keep animals from tainted water.
   The substance, a poisonous chemical when undiluted, spilled from
a reservoir at Brewer Gold Co. when a dam broke, said Richard
Carnes, emergency preparedness director in Chesterfield County.
   Heavy rain might have weakened the dam along the reservoir.
Sodium cyanide spilled into Little Fork Creek, about 2,000 feet
from the reservoir. The creek flows into Lynches River, about two
miles from the spill.
   The company uses the chemical to separate gold from ore.
   Georgetown, about 110 miles southeast of Jefferson, is the
nearest municipality to draw drinking water from the lake system.
   ``We really feel like by the time it gets that far it will be
hard to even detect,'' said Thom Berry, spokesman for the state
Department of Health and Environmental Control.
   The reservoir held 13 million to 14 million gallons of sodium
cyanide, Berry said. He said leaking continued late Sunday.
   Results of water quality tests would not be available until
Monday.
   Consumption of indiluted sodium cyanide can be fatal, but it is
significantly weakened when mixd with water, Berry said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0078 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 2319EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-YachtSinking 1stLd-Writethru a0849 10-28 0169</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Yacht Sinking, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0849,0180</SECOND>
<HEAD>Coast Guard Calls Off Search for Three Missing on Yacht</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: CORRECTS spelling of yacht's name in 2nd graf to Elixir. Picks
up 3rd graf, `A passing ...'</NOTE>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Coast Guard called off a search Sunday for
three people missing since their yacht capsized and sank in rough
seas about 40 miles northeast of Cancun, Mexico.
   Two Coast Guard cutters and three airplanes searched to no avail
for the missing crew, who were reported to be wearing life jackets
when the 153-foot Corsair Elixir went down Friday, said Petty
Officer Carl Vitevitch.
   A passing tanker picked up two other crew members from a life
raft.
   The Coast Guard wouldn't identify the missing until relatives
could be notified.
   The crew of the Corsair Elixir, a former British navy surplus
vessel built in 1948, left Key West on Tuesday in hopes of finding
work in Cancun chartering the boat for tourists on diving
expeditions.
   The boat sank after taking on water through a malfunctioning
hatch, said Petty Officer Terry Johns.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0079 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 1705EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-Forbes-SmallCompanies     10-28 0315</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Forbes-Small Companies,0392</SECOND>
<HEAD>Eight Small Companies Are New to Forbes Top 10 List</HEAD>
<HEAD>Embargoed until 6:30 p.m. EST Sunday</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Eight of the top 10 firms in the annual Forbes
ranking of the nation's 200 best small companies are new to the
list, a sign of what the magazine calls the difficulty of doing
business in a declining economy.
   Six of the firms that were in last year's top 10 dropped
completely from the list of 200 in Forbes' Nov. 13 issue, released
Sunday.
   The magazine evaluated 4,300 companies with annual sales of
between $5 million and $350 million. The 200 companies that made
the list were ranked according to a five-year average of profits as
a percentage of net worth, also called return on equity.
   Melamine Chemicals of Donaldsville, La., ranked No. 1 with a
five-year return on equity of 167 percent. The company makes a
chemical compound called melamine, used in auto paints, appliance
enamels, Formica and other items. In fiscal 1990, the 82-employee
company earned $7.6 million on revenues of $38 million.
   Melamine did not make the top 200 last year, but was No. 1 two
years ago. A recession in which car sales drop off could dent
Melamine's earnings next year, the magazine said.
   To qualify for the list, Forbes said companies had to have a
five-year average return on equity of at least 10 percent,
five-year annual earnings and sales growth rates of at least 8
percent, debt no greater than equity and no recent earnings or
stock market reverses.
   Minneapolis is home to 10 companies on the list, the most of any
city. Chicago had eight, followed by San Jose with seven and Los
Angeles with six.
   California is home to 40 of the companies, the most of any
state. Massachusetts was next with 17, followed by Pennsylvania
with 15 and Texas with 14.
   Some of the better-known companies on the list are International
Dairy Queen (11), Oshkosh B'Gosh (28), Tootsie Roll Industries
(90), Ben &amp; Jerry's (150) and A&amp;W Brands (190).
   Forbes also presented a list of 15 companies that had been in
the top 200 for at least four of the last five years. New
York-based FlightSafety International has made every small company
list since they began 11 years ago.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0080 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 1735EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f BC-FosterGrant     10-28 0228</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Foster Grant,0247</SECOND>
<HEAD>Judge Approves Sale of Foster Grant to Bonneau</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TUCSON, Ariz. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A bankruptcy court approved Bonneau Co.'s
$9 million purchase of Foster Grant, less than three months after
the eyewear maker sought protection from its creditors.
   Eileen Hollowell, Foster Grant's attorney, said she hoped to
officially close the sale within a week or two.
   Bankruptcy Judge Lawrence Ollason on Saturday approved the
Foster Grant sale to Bonneau, a Dallas-based eyewear manufacturer
and distributor.
   The $9 million will go toward paying off Foster Grant's $19
million debt. The Andlinger Group, a leveraged buyout firm that
bought the company in 1986, will provide $10 million more, said
attorney Susan Boswell.
   The company, with sales of more than $50 million worth of
sunglasses, reading glasses and technical products last year,
blamed the Aug. 16 bankruptcy court filing on cash flow problems
and competition from Asian imports.
   Foster Grant, founded in 1919 by Sam Foster, was the first
company to use abrasion-resistant lens coatings that blocked the
sun's ultra-violet rays.
   Only one of the Foster Grant top executives, the sales and
marketing director, will keep his job, McGrath said. The new
president of the company will be Robert C. Camelier, who has been
working for Pennsylvania Optical, a Reading, Pa., manufacturer and
Bonneau affiliate, he said.
   Bonneau will retain the Foster Grant name and labels in addition
to its licensing rights in more than 50 foreign countries, McGrath
said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0081 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 1856EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-UtilityTakeover     10-28 0409</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Utility Takeover,0495</SECOND>
<HEAD>Kansas Gas and Electric Agrees To White Knight Merger With KPL</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WICHITA, Kan. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Kansas Gas and Electric Co. announced
Sunday that it had agreed to a buyout offer from Kansas Power and
Light Co., possibly dodging a hostile takeover bid from a third
utility.
   Kansas Power and Light will pay $32 in cash and stock for each
share of KG&amp;E, which would value the deal at about $1.04 billion.
Kansas City Power and Light Co. had offered $27 per share, or about
$875 million, for KG&amp;E, but had been rebuffed by the utility's
management, which contended the unsolicited bid was illegal and
inadequate.
   According to a joint statement, KG&amp;E will become a wholly-owned
subsidiary of KPL.
   ``In reaching its decision, the board determined that the
friendly combination with the Kansas Power and Light Company was
not only attractive to our owners, but the two company's people and
assets fit together well, permitting us to better serve our
customers,'' said Wilson Cadman, chief executive officer of KG&amp;E.
   KG&amp;E had publicly announced it was negotiating with a third
company as it tried to avert a KCPL buyuout.
   ``This is the thing that's been anticipated for a long time,''
said Turner White, spokesman for KCPL. ``We need to evaluate
exactly what the transaction is with respect to ours.''
   Excess generating capacity of KG&amp;E had been thought to be the
main reason for KCPL's interest in the takeover. KCPL has a rapidly
growing customer base and KG&amp;E has enough excess capacity that
could serve as many as 100,000 additional residential customers.
   John E. Hayes Jr., chairman and chief executive officer of KPL,
said the merged utilities would make available electric capacity to
KCPL enough to ``fulfill their customer needs into the late
1990s.''
   Hayes also said that customers of KG&amp;E would benefit from a $15
million rate reduction that would be sought if the buyout is
finalized.
   ``This is a `win-win' for all parties concerned and, in
particular, for our customers,'' Hayes said.
   KCPL had been pursuing its takeover since July.
   KCPL extended its tender offer three times, reporting earlier
this month that about 44 percent of the KG&amp;E shares had been
tendered.
   KG&amp;E would continue to maintain its headquarters in Wichita,
Hayes said. No layoffs for either company were expected.
   The merger was subject to approval from state and federal
regulatory authorities as well as shareholders.
   KPL is headquartered in Topeka and does business as KPL Gas
Service Co. It has about 1 million customers in northeast and
central Kansas, western Missouri and northeastern Oklahoma and had
revenues of $1.1 billion in 1989.
   KG&amp;E of Wichita has about 250,000 customers in south-central and
southeast Kansas. It had revenues of $533.4 million last year.
   KCPL, based in Kansas City, has 406,000 customers in western
Missouri and eastern Kansas. It had revenue of $731.5 million last
year.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
</Collection>
