<Collection>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0001 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 2324EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Obit-Satterthwaite     11-25 0095</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Satterthwaite,100</SECOND>
<HEAD>Veteran Diplomat Dead at Age 90</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Joseph C. Satterthwaite, a retired diplomat
whose posts included director general of the Foreign Service and
assistant secretary of state, is dead of pneumonia at age 90.
   He died Nov. 19 in Washington.
   He began his diplomatic career in 1924 as a clerk at the U.S.
consulate in Stuttgart, Germany.
   Satterthwaite was ambassador to what was then Ceylon, Burma and
South Africa.
   He retired in 1965.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0002 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 2341EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-HowDryItIs     11-25 0944</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-How Dry It Is,1188</SECOND>
<HEAD>Golden State Praying For Rain, But Bracing for Fifth Drought Year</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Monday AMs report.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By MICHAEL FLEEMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The first few storms of the rainy season have
arrived in California, bringing a little moisture and a torrent of
hope that the state will dodge a disastrous fifth year of drought.
   The four-year drought, the worst in 60 years in some areas,
already has cost the nation's most populous state hundreds of
millions of dollars in losses, hitting farmers the hardest.
   Worst-case scenarios for another dry year call for business
shutdowns, heavy crop damage, wildlife losses and devastating brush
fires. Lawmakers also envision one of the fiercest water wars in
state history between cities and farmers.
   The state's top weather forecasters have been running numbers
through their computers all summer, and the best they can come up
with is that nobody knows what the winter will bring.
   ``The only thing left is to appeal to the higher being to bless
us with rain,'' said Ralph Klages, a nursery owner in the Los
Angeles suburb of Monterey Park. ``It's frustrating and it's scary,
because we have a lot to lose.''
   The rainy season, which began Nov. 1, has gotten off to an
unsettling start.
   A series of mid-November storms people hoped would dump lots of
rain and snow petered out, leaving precipitation levels in most
areas well below seasonal averages.
   Even in the absence of storm clouds, many Californians see a
silver lining. Water experts say the drought might accelerate water
management plans to avoid the day fast-growing California wants
more water than it can get.
   But many of the solutions - from additional water storage to
desalination plants - are too far in the future to help most
Californians, who are bracing for the worst if the inter of 1991
comes up dry.
   In the Southern California mountains, ski lift operators who
have had to make do with small snow packs in the past worry that
shrinking water supplies could even keep them from making fake
snow.
   ``We haven't had a good snow winter in a few years,'' said
Monica Bandows with Bear Mountain Ski Resort near Big Bear Lake.
``But now there is a chance that if the lake falls below a certain
level, we'll no longer be able to pull water out for man-made
snow.''
   Ron Klievoneit, who operates French Gulch Marina on Lake
Isabella in Kern County, said business has declined 25 percent
since the lake level dropped. Some store owners have gone out of
business, he said.
   ``A lot of them have not had enough of a cushion and have gone
defunct,'' said Klievoneit. ``We've owned this place for nearly 10
years. We've been successful at it. And I will just have to find
ways to be successful for years to come.''
   Farmers also could have to find a way to get through another dry
year.
   Agriculture suffered an estimated $480 million in
drought-related losses this year, according to the state Department
of Water Resources.
   In California, farmers get their water from several sources,
including their own wells and state and federal water projects.
   Unless the 1991 water year is wetter than last season, farmers
could have their government water supplies cut by one-half to
two-thirds, federal and state officials say.
   ``Tree crop farmers are having particular problems,'' said Mike
Henry, spokesman for the California Farm Bureau Federation in
Sacramento. ``Last year, they started seeing trees beginning to
stress. The roots are searching for water and they're not finding
any. The tree itself starts to change its metabolism to survive and
not produce fruit.''
   Urban residents also face water cutbacks. State deliveries could
drop as much as 13 percent and federal deliveries could decline 25
percent to 50 percent, officials said.
   Some cities already have imposed rationing, most notably Santa
Barbara on the hard-hit Central Coast, where some residents paint
their dead lawns green and wash their cars with dry rags. That area
has no access to government water supplies and relies solely on
local sources.
   Los Angeles, the state's largest city, had voluntary water
conservation this summer. After early success, the water use inched
back up near the end of summer, and mandatory rationing next summer
could be imposed.
   A cut in water supplies to industrial users would be
devastating. A 24 percent reduction could cost Los Angeles industry
$25 billion and 350,000 jobs, according to estimates by William S.
Wade, a consultant to the Metropolitan Water District, a Southern
California water broker.
   Electronics manufacturers, for instance, rely heavily on water,
and even a small cutback in their already tight supply could force
them to reduce production.
   With water in short supply, the competition could turn ugly.
Some lawmakers say Southern Californians could lobby state and
federal water authorities to pressure central California farmers
into giving up more of their supplies.
   ``It could get very cannibalistic for awhile,'' said Assemblyman
Jim Costa, D-Fresno.
   Humans aren't the only ones who suffer in a drought. In the
Angeles National Forest, the drought is hurting wildlife by drying
up water sources and making the plants less nutritious.
   Mule deer are having fewer fawns, black bears are coming down
from the hills to the campgrounds looking for food and water, and
smaller, less mobile animals such as wood rats and ground squirrels
are dying, said forest biologist Bill Brown.
   Animals also have gone beyond the campgounds and into
neighborhoods. In San Diego County, people have reported foxes
eating cat food, raccoons slurping pool water and bobcats lurking
around jogging trails.
   The dry brush also increases the possibility of wildfire. The
state had one of its worst fires in history this summer when
hundreds of homes were destroyed in a Santa Barbara area fire.
   Water officials say they have no idea how much precipitation the
state can expect this winter. But even a normal winter won't solve
all the state's problems, they say. Experts say the state needs a
wetter-than-normal winter, and even a second normal winter.
   ``If we get a normal water year, we can make all the state water
deliveries,'' said state Water Resources engineer Bob Fingado.
``However, that would leave our reservoirs at the same level, and
that's low.''
   And even after the state gets out of the current drought,
California's problems aren't over. The population explosion is
straining the basic water system.
   Officials now are drafting long-term water plans, including
better conservation, improving the coordination between water
agencies and finding ways to reuse water.
   California could become the leader in building plants that make
sea water drinkable. Although a very expensive source of fresh
water, desalination facilities are under construction or in the
planning stages in Los Angeles, Santa Barbara and Marin counties.
   ``This drought should really serve to be a wake-up call for all
of us,'' said Byron Buck, director of water resources planning for
San Diego County.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0003 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 2343EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-WoodrowWilson     11-25 0527</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Woodrow Wilson,0641</SECOND>
<HEAD>Records Show Wilson Weakened By Disease During League of Nations
Fight</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Monday AMs report.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By THOMAS MARTELLO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PRINCETON, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Woodrow Wilson's behavior was
affected by decreased blood flow to the brain during his
oft-criticized and ultimately futile campaign to have the United
States join the League of Nations, a historian says.
   Records that were never made public show that Wilson was
disabled by illness during the critical period in U.S. history
after World War I, said Princeton University history Professor
Arthur Link, editor of a series of volumes of Wilson's papers.
   ``It is one of the great tragedies of the 20th century,'' Link
said in a recent interview. ``The man who was most responsible for
building support for the idea of a League of Nations was struck
down just as his leadership was most needed. And he was struck down
by events over which he had no control.''
   The 64th volume in the series, to be published in February, will
reveal for the first time detailed medical records kept by Dr. Cary
T. Grayson, Wilson's personal physician. Grayson's sons allowed
Link to review the 70-year-old papers in May.
   Link said the records, with analysis by medical experts, explain
Wilson's poor performance in the months leading up to his
devastating stroke in October 1919.
   Wilson, a Democrat, was president from 1913 to 1921. He died in
1924.
   He won the 1919 Nobel Peace Prize for his peacemaking efforts
involving the League of Nations after World War I. However, he
failed to win U.S. support for the League, which fell apart before
World War II.
   Link said U.S. entry into the League of Nations could have
altered history.
   ``In a world with the United States playing a responsible,
active role, the possibilities of preventing the rise of Hitler
were limitless,'' Link said.
   Wilson failed to get the Senate to ratify U.S. membership in the
league because of what Link said was an uncharacteristic
unwillingness to compromise. The Senate wanted guarantees that the
United States would not be subordinate to the votes of other
nations in case of war.
   ``In his normal, healthy state, Wilson would have found
compromise with the large group of moderate Republicans,'' said
Link.
   Instead, Wilson was robbed of ``his ability at leadership, of
his normal shrewdness and deftness, of his marvelous management
skills,'' said Link. ``He would lose his train of thought, and get
confused. He would contradict himself, and eventually, blow his
cool.''
   Against medical advice, Wilson, then 63, took his message
directly to the people with a speaking tour of Western states in
September 1919. The decision to go over the Senate's head angered
the very lawmakers Wilson needed to court.
   ``The decision ... was not only irrational but in the
circumstances was bound to be futile,'' Link writes in the
forthcoming book.
   Dr. James F. Toole, director of the Stroke Center of the Bowman
Gray School of Medicine in Winston-Salem, N.C., and Dr. Bert E.
Park, a Springfield, Mo. neurosurgeon, analyzed the medical records
for Link's book.
   Toole wrote that the records indicate Wilson suffered from a
disease of the carotid arteries in the neck, which hindered blood
flow to the brain, and hypertension, which worsened his condition.
   Park wrote that Wilson likely continued to suffer episodes of
internal bleeding following a 1906 stroke. This could cause injury
leading ``in time to recognizable behavioral disturbances that
typified Wilson from late 1919 onward,'' Park wrote.
   Link said the records should lay to rest the theories that
Wilson's problems were psychological.
   ``His failure in leadership instead derived from the ravages of
disease,'' Link said. ``History has judged Wilson as if he were a
well man during this period.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0004 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 2343EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Wilson'sWife     11-25 0225</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Wilson's Wife,0244</SECOND>
<HEAD>Professor Says Wilson's Wife Didn't Run Government</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Monday AMs report.</NOTE>
<HEAD>With PM-Woodrow Wilson</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PRINCETON, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The popular belief that President Woodrow
Wilson's wife ran the government after her husband's devastating
stroke in 1919 is ``pure nonsense,'' according to a historian at
Princeton University.
   History Professor Arthur Link, editor of a series of volumes of
Wilson's papers, said the 64th volume, to be published in February,
will prove that Mrs. Wilson served as a liaison but was not
effectively an ``acting president'' in Wilson's final year in
office.
   The volume quotes medical records and journals kept by Dr. Cary
T. Grayson, Wilson's personal physician and confidant. Grayson's
sons allowed Link to review the 70-year-old records in May.
   ``It is a popular belief, but it has gotten more into the realm
of legend than scholarship,'' said Link.
   Edith Wilson did make two crucial decisions following Wilson's
stroke, Link said. She covered up the extent of Wilson's illness
and thwarted suggestions that he resign.
   Link said Mrs. Wilson long denied being an acting president and
once told him she was ``never interested in politics.''
   Grayson's journals show that Mrs. Wilson served as a liaison
between Wilson and his advisers, but that the government was run by
his department heads, Link said.
   Wilson was president from 1913 to 1921. He suffered the stroke
in October 1919, never fully recovered, and died in 1924.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0005 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 2344EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-CivilRights     11-25 0761</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Civil Rights,0877</SECOND>
<HEAD>Civil Rights Leaders Question Bush's Commitment to Fight
Discrimination</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Monday AMs report.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By JAMES ROWLEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Civil rights advocates are questioning
President Bush's commitment to fighting discrimination despite the
administration's aggressive prosecution of some ground-breaking
voting rights and housing bias cases.
   They cite Bush's veto of the Civil Rights Act of 1990, which
would have made it easier for victims of discrimination to sue
their employers.
   ``That fallout is going to take some time to clear,'' said Drew
Days, who ran the civil rights division under President Carter.
   Ralph Neas, executive director of the Leadership Conference on
Civil Rights, had a harsher assessment. ``Once again, we have an
administration defying the bipartisan consensus that exists on
civil rights,'' he said.
   Still, civil rights leaders acknowledge there are bright spots
in the Bush administration's record.
   Bush actively courted black voters during the 1988 campaign,
invited Coretta Scott King to the Republican National Convention,
and spoke about healing racial divisions. He is credited with
appointing more blacks to political jobs than his predecessor,
Ronald Reagan.
   Attorney General Dick Thornburgh tried to re-establish ties with
civil rights leaders that were left badly frayed by conservative
William Bradford Reynolds, who ran the Justice Department's civil
rights division under President Reagan.
   He also played a major role in ensuring passage of the Americans
with Disabilities Act, which bars discrimination against people
with mental and physical handicaps.
   The Justice Department also has made enforcement a priority,
adding lawyers to bring cases under a new statute that expands the
government's authority to counter housing discrimination.
   It has forced municipalities to drop restrictions against group
homes for mentally retarded people. The agency recently won a jury
verdict against a landlord for refusing to rent apartments to a
drug program to house recovering addicts.
   The Justice Department filed suit to force the all-male Virginia
Military Institute to admit women cadets. It moved to overturn
Georgia's election system, which it says discriminates against
black office seekers.
   ``When I came here it was with the understanding with the
attorney general that I would be responsible for the vigorous and
the complete enforcement of the civil rights laws,'' said John
Dunne, who was named assistant attorney general for civil rights
after the Senate Judiciary Committee blocked Bush's first nominee,
William Lucas.
   ``No matter what the subject area, we have been extremely
aggressive,'' Dunne said.
   Civil rights advocates want more.
   ``They are going to have to make a record across the board, it's
not going to be sufficient to carve out enclaves where they are
vigorous and leaving others untouched and uncared for,'' Days said.
   Neas says he finds ``very few substantive differences'' in
Justice Department policy from the Reagan administration when it
was headed by Attorney General Edwin Meese III.
   And on many major issues of dispute involving the 1990 civil
rights bill, ``the Thornburgh Justice Department was much worse
than the Meese Justice Department,'' Neas said.
   ``Thornburgh strikes you as being the planet Jupiter, a failed
star. You would have anticipated much more from him,'' said Barbara
Arnwine, an attorney for the Lawyers Committee for Civil Rights
Under Law.
   The bill Bush vetoed would have restored an evolving legal
standard dating back 18 years for discrimination cases involving
employer policies that have a ``disparate impact'' on women and
minorities.
   Bush said it would spawn hiring quotas by encouraging businesses
to employ and promote minorities simply to avoid costly court
suits.
   Civil rights lawyers accuse the president of using divisive
rhetoric to mischaracterize the bill, which contained language
stating that no provision was designed to promote quotas.
   ``It's dividing people when this was the president who was going
to try to heal those divisions,'' said William Taylor, a Washington
civil rights lawyer.
   Both Taylor and Arnwine charge that the Bush administration
wants to eliminate ``disparate impact'' cases to protect business
from the costs of discrimination suits.
   ``They believe that if somebody didn't intend to discriminate,
they shouldn't be held accountable,'' Arnwine said.
   Dunne rejected this view, providing figures showing that the
since Bush took office the civil rights division has brought nine
disparate-impact suits against state and local governments.
   But civil rights activists contend that the department wastes
valuable time and resources pursuing reverse discrimination cases,
such as a recent lawsuit accusing the Maryland Lottery Commission
of discriminating against white males by setting aside 12 positions
for women and minorities.
   ``We don't apologize for bringing reverse discrimination
cases,'' said Roger Clegg, one of Dunne's deputies who also served
in the Reagan administration. ``The law requires us to enforce the
law in an even-handed fashion.''
   The bitterness that lingers following Bush's veto is fueled by
charges that the administration failed to bargain in good faith
with the bill's supporters.
   ``The sense of many in the civil rights community is that the
administration strung people along, giving them the sense there
really was room for negotiations and compromise when there really
wasn't,'' Days said.
   ``The administration is going to have to work very hard to
re-establish its good faith,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0006 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 2345EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-EnemiesMakeUp     11-25 0632</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Enemies Make Up,0732</SECOND>
<HEAD>Former Ideological Opponents Become Trade Partners</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Monday AMs report.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By TOM COHEN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PRETORIA, South Africa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Less than two years ago, South
Africa and Eastern Europe shunned each other as ideological
villains.
   Today, the South Africans have diplomatic or trade arrangements
with Poland, Romania and Hungary, and are expanding contacts with
the Soviet Union and Czechoslovakia.
   Dramatic political and social changes on both sides have made
them eager to renew relations after decades of enmity over
communism and apartheid.
   ``We were at the other end of the world, both geographically and
ideologically,'' Foreign Minister R.F. Botha said on a trip to
Czechoslovakia. ``After the changes in both parts of the world,
there is nothing which divides our governments.''
   Botha and Czechoslovak officials announced plans to establish
low-level diplomatic ties after a 27-year hiatus. In August, Trade
Minister Kent Durr became the first South African Cabinet member to
visit the Soviet Union in 34 years.
   Ideology drove the two sides apart in the 1950s and 1960s.
Economics is bringing them together in the 1990s.
   The South African government invoked the threat of a communist
takeover for decades as justification for suppressing the black
opposition.
   This year, President F.W. de Klerk legalized all opposition
groups, released African National Congress leader Nelson Mandela
from prison after 27 years and promised to end the apartheid system
of racial segregation.
   One of de Klerk's objectives was to end international sanctions,
which have isolated South Africa economically and politically.
   East European countries supported the sanctions and backed the
ANC and its ally, the South African Communist Party.
   Then, in 1989, came the upheaval that dismembered the Soviet
bloc and swept Communist parties from power in Moscow's former
satellites. Those nations are struggling to rebuild their crumbling
economies and have found a willing trade partner in South Africa.
   Although they still oppose apartheid, East European countries
have switched from being the main financial support of the ANC to
dealing with the white government it sought to destroy.
   Delegations from Eastern Europe visit South Africa regularly.
Permananent representatives have been exchanged and trade
agreements signed. Thousands of Eastern European and Soviet
citizens have applied to South African embassies in Western Europe
for permission to immigrate.
   ``I am pleased that the dynamics of late 20th century political
transformation are bringing our two nations once again closer
together,'' Durr said in opening the first Polish trade fair in
South Africa.
   Poland dropped trade restrictions against South Africa on March
9, the day after Durr completed a visit. In late October, the
governments signed an agreement to establish reciprocal offices of
interest.
   Polish government and trade officials traveled to South Africa
for the two-week trade fair, which featured nearly 50 manufacturers
of products ranging from heavy machinery through textiles to vodka.
Organizers said contracts worth $60 million were signed.
   The visitors emphasized their continued opposition to apartheid,
but it was clear that relations had been made more palatable by
Poland's economic problems and South Africa's reforms.
   ``Poland is heavily in debt'' and is beginning to make its
economic relations with the rest of the world ``much more active,''
said Andrzej Zawislak, an economist and member of Parliament.
   Zawislak said some Western countries had urged Poland not to
establish ties with South Africa, but did not identify them.
   Romania and South Africa signed an agreement last month for a
joint trade committee that would meet annually, and specific trade
contracts are expected.
   South Africa has opened a permanent office in Hungary to
represent its interests and Hungary plans to reciprocate.
   Hungarian officials said their country still opposes apartheid,
but wants the office because about 20,000 people of Hungarian
descent live in South Africa.
   African nations also are warming to South Africa's reforms. Only
Malawi has full diplomatic relations, but several have trade
missions in Pretoria and de Klerk has visited seven African
countries since taking office in August 1989.
   His government says it trades with every African country, mostly
in secret.
   Mandela has sought funds for the ANC in Africa, Western Europe,
the United States and Asia, but has yet to visit Eastern Europe or
the Soviet Union, which provided most of the movement's military
aid while he was imprisoned.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0007 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 2345EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Gulf-FemaleFootball     11-25 0549</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Gulf-Female Football,0694</SECOND>
<HEAD>Killer, Rocky and Spaz Make Female Football a Smash Hit</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Monday AMs report.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto DHA1 Nov. 25</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT DVORCHAK</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>IN EASTERN SAUDI ARABIA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Players wore names like Killer,
Rocky and Spaz on their jerseys. Cheerleaders in combat boots
shouted through orange pylons and waved pink paper pompons.
Spectators stacked their rifles and gas masks to do the wave.
   This was Sunday afternoon football with a twist: the players
were women.
   A team of Marines called the Wrecking Crew toppled the Desert
Foxes, from U.S. Navy Fleet Hospital No. 5, 20-13 in front of
adoring troops who roared, howled, barked and booed the referees,
naturally.
   ``It's a change of pace. Everyone was able to blow off a little
steam,'' said Marine Cpl. Carrie Cripps, 21, of Fort Smith, Ark. A
middle linebacker, she is also known as Rocky.
   The Desert Foxes were weary and dirty but far from discouraged
because they stayed within a touchdown of the women Marines. The
Foxes had practiced only eight times before, all on an asphalt
parking lot.
   ``We're all nurses. We didn't know the first thing about
football. I thought we were going to get trounced,'' said Lt. Com.
Raelene Hoogendorn of McDonald, Pa. Also known as Killer, she works
in casualty receiving.
   This wasn't the NFL, but it was the closest thing available in
Saudi Arabia. The game is called flag football, a version of touch,
although there were more than a few tackles and there was some
crisp blocking. Players traded high-five handshakes and spiked the
ball on touchdown receptions.
   The game was played on a sand field that the Marines call the
Scud Bowl, although this one was billed as the Turkey Bowl as part
of Thanksgiving weekend. Every play kicked up a cloud of dust, and
the women panted and puffed in the 90-degree heat.
   Armed Forces Radio did a play-by-play. Several hundred Marines
watched from the sidelines, some sitting on their sleeping cots or
under tent flaps. They munched on popcorn, pretzels and crackers.
   There was no beer, only Kool-Aid and soda pop, although the two
sidelines chanted the Miller Lite exchange of ``Less Filling'' and
``Tastes Great'' before the game.
   All in all, it was a pleasant afternoon for service members who
have been training in this parched land for nearly four months.
   ``Nobody's in their tents. It breaks the monotony,'' said
Gunnery Sgt. Eugene Bradley, 33, of Dallas. ``It's something to do
on a Sunday. Tomorrow we go back to work, back to the old grind.
Boy, look at those linebackers!''
   Sgt. Chris Dempsey, 25, of Cleveland, led other Marines in
cheers.
   ``When the women play, people come out of the woodwork to
watch,'' Dempsey said. ``There ain't no place to go. You can't go
to town. There's no alchohol. We're pretty well isolated.''
   The game would also be unheard of elsewhere in Saudi Arabia,
where men and women may not mingle in public. Even photographs of
women playing sports are almost unheard of.
   ``This is a crowd pleaser. You can't get no better than this,''
said Lance Cpl. Stephen Banks, 22, of Pittsburgh.
   On the other side of the field, Cpl. Greg Williams, 22, of
Billings, Mont., screamed himself hoarse while waving his pom-poms.
   ``There's not much to do out here,'' said Williams.
   Capt. Richard Mayo, commander of Fleet No. 5 Hospital, wished
his carges well before they took the field in their white T-shirts
adorned with red crosses, a contrast to the Marines' drab brown
shirts.
   ``This is one way of channeling their frustrations,'' Mayo said
from the bench.
   As befits a multinational force, a number of British soldiers
watched the game.
   ``I love American football. Love the atmosphere,'' said Cpl.
Mick Gibbons, 28. ``You don't have the rowdies we have in British
soccer.''
   About 350,000 troops are in Saudi Arabia as part of a
multinational force deployed after Iraq invaded Kuwait on Aug. 2.
They face about 460,000 Iraqi troops in southern Iraq and Kuwait.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0008 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 2350EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Israel-TempleMount     11-25 0933</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Israel-Temple Mount,1189</SECOND>
<HEAD>The Temple Mount Six Weeks Later: Some Answers, More Questions</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Monday AMs report.</NOTE>
<HEAD>With LaserGraphic Nov. 25.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By G.G. LaBELLE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Six weeks after the smoke and sting of tear gas
drifted away from the Wailing Wall and Dome of the Rock, anger and
recrimination remain from the bloody riot at the sites sacred to
Jews and Moslems.
   Israel still is trying to block a U.N. investigation of the
deaths of at least 17 Arabs killed by police gunfire.
   Hatred has grown on both sides. The Oct. 8 riots brought revenge
stabbings by Arabs and renewed fervor in the 3-year-old Palestinian
uprising. Then came stonings by Jews and growing calls that Arab
workers be barred from Israel.
   Passage of time and a half dozen investigations by Israelis and
Arabs show that first accounts of the Temple Mount tragedy from
Israeli officials and from Palestinians drew more on anger than
accuracy.
   The findings conflict with Israeli assertions that the Arabs
deliberately provoked trouble by raining thousands of stones on
tens of thousands of worshipers at the Wailing Wall.
   Even the government's own inquiry concluded that the melee began
with stones thrown at police on Temple Mount, not at Jews near the
wall, which also is called the Western Wall because it forms the
western base of Temple Mount.
   The commission, headed by former secret service chief Zvi Zamir,
listed nine Jewish civilians hurt by stones, a toll inconsistent
with first reports of a barrage rained down on worshipers.
   On the Palestinian side, there is no evidence for initial
charges that an Israeli helicopter fired tear gas and guns at
Moslems on Temple Mount.
   Accusations of a ``planned provocation'' by Palestinians or a
``premeditated, well-planned operation'' by Israel do not mesh with
what is now known.
   Chaos, not planning, characterized the riot.
   Zamir's commission notes that police lost communication with
each other, some did not hear orders and there was ``unsupervised''
gunfire by some officers.
   Many Moslem witnesses said later they did not understand why the
rioting started. Israeli officials first accused Palestinians of
carrying rocks to Temple Mount to start a riot. The Zamir report
did not repeat that charge, and all accounts now say the stones
were lying around at a construction project.
   Betselem, an Israeli human rights group, said ``information
given the public ... was for the most part imprecise, raising the
suspicion that attempts were made to hide facts ... and evade
responsibilty.''
   There probably never will be complete agreement on what
happened. The Zamir commission did not have subpoena powers and
said it interviewed few Palestinian witnesses. Palestinian accounts
discounted the police version.
   Israelis and Palestinians also saw the confrontation from their
own side of the wall - and their own point of view.
   The riot came on a day of high emotion. Up to 30,000 Jews had
gathered at the Wailing Wall for the Sukkot festival. Jews revere
the wall as the last remnant of the ancient Jewish temple.
   As many as 5,000 Moslems had gathered in the walled compound
above the wall, the area known in Arabic as the Haram es-Sharif, or
``Noble Enclosure.'' It is Islam's third-holiest site and contains
the Dome of the Rock and Al Aqsa Mosque.
   The Moslems were incensed by rumors that a Jewish extremist
group, the Temple Mount Faithful, planned a march on the holy
sanctuary. The group, founded after the capture of Arab east
Jerusalem from Jordan, wants to rebuild the ancient Jewish temple
on the Mount.
   Authorities had barred them from Temple Mount, but allowed a
rally nearby, fueling Moslem fears of an intrusion.
   The riots began about 10:45 a.m., when the priestly Sukkot
benediction was over and the Jewish worshipers were dispersing from
the plaza in front of the Wailing Wall.
   According to the Betselem group of liberal lawyers and
professors, violence started when Palestinian youths threw stones
at police in a courtyard near the Dome of the Rock.
   Those in the plaza cannot see what is happening up on Temple
Mount, and people on the plateau around the Dome of the Rock cannot
see directly down on the plaza because of the wall.
   Police responded with tear gas. Betselem noted that thousands of
Moslems could not see the stone throwing and grew angry at the
sudden use of tear gas.
   Indeed, two Palestinian reports found no evidence of stone
throwing before the tear gassing. The Zamir report mentions neither
stonings nor tear gas at this point.
   Its account of the rioting begins - and others call this the
next step - with an angry mob charging police on the Temple Mount.
   Some rioters attacked a small police station manned by two men.
Others threw rocks and metal objects at police near one wall - the
interior of the Jews' Wailing Wall, which is at least 20 feet high
inside Temple Mount.
   Early reports said the rioting started after cries of ``Kill the
Jews!'' came from mosque loudspeakers. Palestinians deny there was
such a cry and the Zamir report is ambiguous on the point.
   According to the 50-page English-language version of the report,
the cry was heard from ``a loudspeaker.'' Elsewhere, however, it
says the cry was among shouts ``heard from the direction'' of the
mosques.
   Police answered the rocks with tear gas and rubber bullets. At
least one officer fired live ammunition into the air. police were
overwhelmed and fled the walled compound.
   Palestinians say live ammunition was then fired at rioters from
a police station overlooking the area. Betselem says gunfire was
``probably'' used. The Zamir report says ``there was no intentional
firing of live ammunition'' at this point.
   The remaining Jewish worshipers were evacuated from the plaza at
the Wailing Wall. This appears to account for the few injuries.
   While some of the first rocks cleared the wall around Temple
Mount and fell on the plaza below, both the Zamir and Betselem
reports describe the heavy barrage of stones coming after police
fled and the Jewish worshipers left the Wailing Wall.
   A little after 11 a.m., police charged back into the compound.
Palestinians say they came in shooting. The Zamir report says they
opened fire only after the mob refused to retreat.
   The commission's report says use of live ammunition was
justified by danger to the policemen's lives, their fear for the
safety of Jewish worshipers and for the lives of the two officers
still in the station on the mount.
   In fact, the two policemen had taken refuge with mosque guards
and were safe, but the police did not know that because of a
communications breakdown.
   The Zamir commission said it was doubtful all the gunfire was
needed, noting that using live ammunition had been justified ``only
for policemen who ... were in mortal danger.''
   Betselem said police fired indiscriminately, using bursts of
automatic weapons fire and shooting at ambulances and Palestinian
rescue workers.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0009 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 2351EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Gulf-Sanctions     11-25 0573</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Gulf-Sanctions,0709</SECOND>
<HEAD>With Shaky Economy, Dollar Becomes Currency of Choice in Baghdad</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Monday AMs report.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By TERRY LEONARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BAGHDAD, Iraq (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The dollar, the hated and admired symbol of
American power, is the currency of choice on the streets of
Baghdad, where U.N. sanctions have rattled the already shaky Iraqi
economy.
   In ever-increasing numbers, Iraqis approach foreigners, risking
lengthy prison sentences to buy dollars at black-market rates that
have almost doubled in three months.
   At the same time, some merchants play the dangerous game of
asking customers to give them something other than the new 25-dinar
notes bearing the likeness of President Saddam Hussein.
   Western diplomats suggested that reflects a fear the dinar could
lose its value if Saddam is toppled after a U.S.-led attack or in a
coup.
   ``The common man is concerned about his future and the future of
his family. He recognizes the possibility that Saddam might fail
and places his bets accordingly,'' said one Asian diplomat, who
spoke on condition of anonymity.
   At official rates, one Iraqi dinar is worth $3 in Iraq. But on
the streets of Baghdad, one dollar can buy five Iraqi dinars and in
some outlying areas the going rate is reportedly six or seven
dinars.
   ``It's a dollar economy,'' said one European diplomat, also
speaking on condition of anonymity. ``There isn't much you can't
buy with dollars. You can buy your way out (of the country), or you
can buy your way out of the army.''
   One Western diplomat said some major figures in the Iraqi
business world are turning vast amounts of their assets into cash -
and turning that cash into dollars.
   ``The weakness of the dinar is not linked to the weakness of the
government, but to the weakness of the economy. The dinar's a paper
currency based on the oil and oil is not being sold,'' the Asian
diplomat said.
   Before Iraq's Aug. 2 invasion of Kuwait and the subsequent U.N.
embargo, the country earned more than 95 percent of its foreign
exchange from oil exports.
   ``Sanctions are already hurting. On that I have no doubts,'' the
Asian diplomat said. ``Almost the entire industrial sector has
either ground to a halt or is chuggling along very slowly.''
   Shortages of spare parts, imported raw materials and foreign
technical expertise have left much of Iraq's industry running at
only a maintenance level, Western diplomats said.
   Prices on everything from cigarettes to tires are soaring in the
marketplace. Cigarettes that just three months ago cost one-third
of a dinar, now cost 3.50 dinars. Tires now cost 300 dinars apiece,
or $900 at the official rate.
   ``The level of frustration on the street is amazing. Everyone in
the country has his life on hold,'' said one European diplomat.
   Food is still in abundant supply in Iraq, much of it smuggled in
from Iran or looted from Kuwait. Store shelves overflow with
consumer goods and delicacies still in their Kuwaiti packaging.
   Despite official Iraqi complaints about shortages of medicines,
doctors in Baghdad say there's no problem with supplies. Western
diplomats suggest Iraqi attempts to acquire more medicine in
exchange for hostages is an attempt to bolster stockpiles for war.
   Last week the government announced a new decree imposing the
death sentence on people convicted of hoarding food.
   Some diplomats believe it is aimed mainly at discouraging
large-scale smuggling. Others believe the government itself is
heavily involved in the smuggling and simply wants to excercise
more control on consumption, distribution and profiteering.
   Western and Asian diplomats say they cannot accurately assess
how long Iraq can hold out under the pressure of sanctions alone.
   ``I don't think one can set a time limit,'' said one Asian
diplomat. ``You have to take into account the way this society
functions.
   ``There's no way for the people to express their unhappiness
with the government. But on the other hand, Saddam Hussein and the
leadership all realize that they can push the people only so far,''
he added.
   One Western diplomat was more blunt in his assessment of the
sanctions: ``They'll not work in time to avoid war.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0010 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 2351EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Gulf-ArmyCouple     11-25 0240</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Gulf-Army Couple,0282</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mother Can Stay; Activated Army Couple Gets Reprieve</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Monday AMs report.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By LUIS CABRERA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SEATTLE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Twila Schamer will get to be a mom again.
   Mrs. Schamer and her husband, Christopher, parents of a
9-week-old son, were among 705 reservists with the Army's 50th
General Hospital Unit who were called to active duty last week for
a minimum of six months.
   On Saturday, however, at a briefing for the unit's members and
their families at Fort Lewis, south of Tacoma, Mrs. Schamer was
told she had been granted a hardship exemption to allow her to stay
home and care for her baby, Jacob.
   ``It's kind of a mixed blessing,'' she said. ``For me, it's nice
that I get to stay home with Jake. But my husband's still leaving,
so it's hard.''
   Christopher Schamer, 25, is a communications specialist whose
duties include setting up the hospital's phone service. Mrs.
Schamer, 26, is a sergeant who works as an administrative assistant
in the nursing division.
   The Schamers reported Saturday to Fort Lewis, where they were
scheduled to go through orientation and training for deployment to
the Persian Gulf or a domestic base in need of medical personnel.
   The Schamers initially planned to leave Jacob with his paternal
grandparents in Bellevue, east of Seattle.
   The break with his family still will be hard, Schamer said.
   ``I'm really kind of dazed. There's a job to be done over there
... but I'm just getting used to being a father now, and feeling
that I may have to leave that behind for six months really hurts
me,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0011 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 2352EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-FatNurse     11-25 0648</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Fat Nurse,0840</SECOND>
<HEAD>Supreme Court Case Stirs Woman's Battle For Dignity</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Monday AMs report.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By JAMES MARTINEZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ST. PETERSBURG, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   All Sharon Russell ever wanted to be
was a nurse, but her weight nearly got in the way.
   After she was kicked out of nursing school in 1985, weighing
more than 300 pounds, she sued the school and won. Now the case has
moved to the U.S. Supreme Court and she's moved to the forefront in
the fight for dignity for overweight people.
   ``It's going to take time. It's going to take patience,'' Ms.
Russell said. ``And it's going to take people like me who have the
guts to stand up and say, `I was humiliated - this is how I
felt.'''
   A federal jury last year ordered Salve Regina College of
Newport, R.I., to pay Ms. Russell nearly $44,000 in damages. An
appeals court upheld the judgment and the school appealed its case
to the nation's high court.
   The justices this week will hear arguments to decide a narrow,
procedural point of law relating to the appeals court's standard of
review.
   Although the decision, expected sometime next year, will have
little bearing on the legal question of so-called size
discrimination, it could determine whether the award must be paid.
   ``The important thing is more people will understand what I had
to go through to get to this point,'' said Ms. Russell, now 26 and
a pediatric nurse at All Children's Hospital in St. Petersburg.
   Ms. Russell maintains size discrimination was the sole reason
for her dismissal from Salve Regina, but school officials argue she
was unhealthy because she suffered from an eating disorder and was
physically unable to handle patients.
   ``We don't dismiss students because they're fat,'' said
Catherine Graziano, Salve Regina's dean of nursing. ``We dismiss
students if they have behavior problems that make them unable to
function as nurses.''
   Ms. Russell said her 5-foot-6, 300-pound body didn't seem to
bother administrators in 1982 when she was accepted at the small
college run by the Roman Catholic Sisters of Mercy.
   After earning good grades through her freshman and sophomore
years, she entered the college's nursing program. Her problems
began the first day.
   ``My instructor took one look at me and said, `We're not going
to get a uniform to fit you. You'll never get around a bed,''' she
said.
   She said she was used as a ``human guinea pig'' in class to show
students how to make a bed with a fat person or how to give a shot
to a fat person.
   ``I would sit there and pretend it didn't bother me,'' she said,
``but it was just killing me inside.''
   In December 1984, faculty members presented Ms. Russell with a
contract to lose two pounds a week or face dismissal, and signed it
because ``becoming a nurse was all I ever wanted.''
   According to the school, Ms. Russell weighed 328 pounds at the
beginning of her sophomore year, was down to 297 when she signed
the agreement and back up to 303 during the summer of 1985. That
was when Salve Regina notified Ms. Russell she would not be allowed
to attend her senior year.
   With that, Ms. Russell slapped Salve Regina and five faculty
members with a $2 million federal lawsuit alleging, among other
things, handicap discrimination, intentional infliction of
emotional distress, invasion of privacy and breach of contract.
   The judge dismissed all claims except the breach of contract
allegation.
   A Providence jury sided with Ms. Russell, saying the school
broke its implied contract to provide her with an education so long
as she paid her tuition, maintained good grades and wasn't a
discipline problem.
   The award reflected the cost of having to repeat her junior year
at St. Joseph's College in West Hartford, Conn., and the lost
earnings from spending an extra year in school.
   In upholding the verdict, the 1st U.S. Circuit Court of Appeals
noted the school forced Ms. Russell out of school ``because she was
obese and for no other reason.''
   Save Regina's lawyer, Steven Snow, disagreed: ``If we did
anything wrong, it was in giving her too many chances.''
   Ms. Russell completed her nursing studies at St. Joseph's and
has been working in St. Petersburg for 2{ years. She had her
stomach surgically stapled in one of her many failed attempts to
slim down.
   Asked how she was doing at St. Petersburg, a hospital
spokeswoman said Sunday: ``I know that she is in a supervisory
position, so that speaks for itself.''
   She's become an active fighter against size discrimination and
was the keynote speaker for the 3,000-member National Association
to Advance Fat Acceptance. Her message is simple:
   ``Accept yourself the way you are, work with what you have, go
for it and live your life. My attitude is I weigh 285 pounds now -
get over it.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0012 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 2353EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-HighSchoolBank     11-25 0604</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-High School Bank,0764</SECOND>
<HEAD>Students Get Taste of Banking; Teachers Cash Checks Down Hall</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Monday AMs report.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By DAVID GRAM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BRATTLEBORO, Vt. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Jim Fitzgerald bounded into the new
branch office of the Brattleboro Savings &amp; Loan Association, doffed
his sneakers for shiny brown shoes and tucked in his shirt.
   It was a high school senior's best effort to look like a banker.
   Fellow Brattleboro Union High School senior Amy Kinsman was
already behind her teller's window, tidying things up and getting
ready for the expected Friday rush of teachers cashing their
paychecks.
   ``I didn't even know I'd be doing this at the beginning of the
year,'' said Fitzgerald, 17, who is eyeing a college major in
finance or economics.
   The goal of the high school's career center is to merge school
and the real world.
   A proposal by a marketing class to install condom machines in
high school restrooms was shot down last spring. Undaunted, Career
Center Director William Dennen pushed ahead with a day care center
for the children of teen-age mothers and with Vermont's first high
school bank.
   It was an idea that Dennen and business teacher Bruce Bergeron
had been kicking around for about three years.
   ``Wouldn't it be great if we could really get a bank working
down here?'' Dennen recalled the two saying to one another. ``No
role-playing, the real thing.''
   A real-thing bank might eventually issue the mortgage on the
house built by each year's construction trades class. And it would
give the students in Bergeron's advanced accounting class a shot a
handling real money.
   ``A good (vocational) center is supposed to parallel what's in
the community,'' Dennen said. Sure enough, the house built by last
year's construction trades class languishes on the market in a New
England-wide real estate slump.
   And sure enough, the hallway off the high school's cafeteria
looks a bit like Main Street. There's the day care center, a flower
shop run by horticulture students, a restaurant run by cooking
students, a store run by retailing students and now the bank.
   Business management teacher Maribeth Cornell said she especially
likes the bank. Cornell used to have to try to get off work on time
every other Friday and fight traffic to the heart of downtown to
deposit her paycheck.
   Now she walks down the hall to the bank's new BUHS Career Center
Branch and hands her check to student tellers Kinsman or
Fitzgerald.
   ``I'm a customer who reaps the convenience of it,'' she said
after cashing her check last Friday. She said she marvels at the
services available at the high school.
   ``About the only thing we don't have is a place to get your hair
cut,'' she said with a laugh. ``We need that.''
   After thinking about a student bank for some time, Dennen and
the Career Center staff held a luncheon for local bankers and laid
out their proposal.
   Robert Schrull, 36-year-old president of the Brattleboro Savings
&amp; Loan, jumped at the idea. ``We'll do it,'' he said. That was on a
Thursday. Schrull got the OK from his board on Friday and gave the
formal go-ahead to the school on the following Monday.
   ``The little guy came through,'' Dennen said of the Savings &amp;
Loan. ``All the others were sort of reluctant.''
   The state came through with a $5,000 grant, the bank invested
$20,000, the school's building trades program helped with the
construction and the electronics class wired the alarm and security
camera systems. A 27-year-old customer service representative at
the Brattleboro Savings was named branch manager.
   Twelve of the 13 students in Bergeron's advanced accounting
class sent resumes to Schrull. He interviewed all 12, and sent them
letters giving pointers on their resumes and interview styles.
   While Kinsman and Fitzgerald got the two initial openings;
eventually all 12 students who applied will get a stint behind the
tellers' windows.
   Brattleboro Savings &amp; Loan keeps it simple. It doesn't deal in
junk bonds or high-stakes real estate investments, just savings and
checking accounts, certificates of deposit and home mortgages for
Brattleboro area residents.
   A small bank like Schrull's needs the support of its community.
Dennen said it made as much sense for the bank to try to make
friends with students at the high school - many of whom would be
shopping for mortgage loans in 10 or 15 years - as for the school
to get it students experience in banking.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0013 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 2354EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-BrushRustlers     11-25 0368</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Brush Rustlers,0455</SECOND>
<HEAD>Growing Wreath-Making Industry Results in Theft of Tree Branches</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Monday AMs report.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>JONESBORO, Maine (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Landowners in eastern Maine are angered
by the illegal stripping of branches from trees by brush rustlers
who sell their booty to wreath makers.
   ``Some people will do anything for a buck,'' said Leslie
Thornton, assistant regional ranger for Maine's Forest Service.
``As the price of brush has gone up, more people are doing this.''
   Along U.S. Route 1 in Jonesboro, bright yellow signs warn
``tippers'' - those who gather branch tips from balsam trees - to
stay off property unless they have permission.
   Roadblocks along secondary roads have been set up to check the
tippers' harvests, and details patrol back roads to discourage
illegal tipping.
   What was once a way for kids to earn a few bucks is now a big
business.
   Douglas Getchell, a 39-year-old Forest Service ranger in
Whitneyville, gathered tips in burlap bags and sold them for 3 or 4
cents a pound when he was a child. Now, the going rate for tips is
about 20 or 30 cents a pound, and a good tipper can earn more than
$200 a day.
   About 2 million wreaths a year are produced in eastern Maine,
making the area the wreath capital of the nation and pumping an
estimated $15 million to $18 million into the local economy.
   Most of the land in the region is owned by Champion and
Georgia-Pacific Corp., each of which owns about 450,000 acres. For
a $40 fee, Georgia-Pacific lets anyone take branch tips from its
land. Champion, meanwhile, divides its land in large blocks of 300
to 3,000 acres and auctions rights to tippers. Bids range from $300
to $1,000.
   Rangers say illegal tippers usually have permits from paper
companies or written permission from private landowners to gathers
tips, but often move onto other land where brush is more plentiful.
   The vast forests and zigzagging property lines across hundreds
of thousands of acres makes enforcement difficult. Six rangers
patrol the 1.5 million-acre district in Washington County.
   Tippers often carry a gun to make it appear they're hunting.
   ``Sometimes I'll catch them with sticks of tips nearby and
they'll say, `It's not mine. I'm out here hunting,''' Getchell
said.
   Greg Antil of Jonesboro and some friends last year pooled $1,000
to buy the tipping rights on a prime block of Champion-owned land
only to have brush rustlers tip a portion of the full-bodied trees.
   He said tipping on land where rights have been purchased by
others is like stealing their money. ``Nine times out of 10 they'll
get away with it,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0014 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 2359EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Romania-Food     11-25 0502</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Romania-Food,0610</SECOND>
<HEAD>Stores Baren Despite Ambitious Reforms</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Poland, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CHRISTINA PIRVULESCU</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUCHAREST, Romania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Free-market reforms have tripled the
prices of many items, but they are scarce anyway. Food sometimes is
harder to find than in the starvation days of Communist
dictatorship.
   ``Life is surely more miserable now than under Ceausescu.'' said
Pascu Dumitrescu, a 68-year-old pensioner, pointing to empty stalls
in a public market. ``The shops are a reflection of our lives.''
   After a long search, Dumitrescu found a store that had bread,
waited in line with other sullen shoppers and bought a bag of stale
loaves.
   ``People will no longer stand it,'' said an angry man of 60.
``They are going to take to the streets again, but this time
they'll be demanding food.''
   When the government imposed price increases Nov. 1 to push the
country toward a market economy, it agreed to freeze the prices of
such basic food items as bread, milk and meat until Jan. 1.
   It also temporarily froze rents and energy prices.
   Controlled prices don't make food any easier to find. Poorly
paid store employees sometimes sell subsidized food to black
marketeers. The government said last week it would prosecute anyone
caught doing so.
   Leather shoes, underwear and spare auto parts are a only
memories. Refrigerators, televisions, radios and toilet paper are
impossible to find without special connections.
   Romanians endured years of harsh rationing under Communist
dictator Nicolae Ceausescu, who exported everything possible in
order to pay off the foreign debt.
   When they began the protests last December that led to his
downfall and execution, many assumed prosperity would follow
automatically.
   The new National Salvation Front government diverted food
intended for export to domestic use after the revolution. That,
combined with donations from the West, created the illusion of
relative plenty at the beginning.
   It didn't last. Even though prices are higher now, shops offer
the same paltry selection of food, most of it canned, as they did
under Ceausescu.
   In the farmers' markets, where food is available, sellers raised
their prices long ago without waiting for the government.
   Marian Nitu, the deputy agriculture and food minister, estimated
in an interview that food exports totaled about $20 million so far
this year.
   Along with livestock, he said, ``vegetables, fruits and canned
beef'' were going to buyers in the West and Far East. All are hard
to find in local markets.
   Nicolae Tache, director of the public market where Dumitrescu
was shopping, said meat had not been available for more than a week
and blamed what he called a corrupt government distribution system.
   ``I have to bribe for delivery contracts to be honored,'' he
said.
   At another market in the main Bucharest district of Pajura, more
than 50 people lined up for butter. Others waited silently for
small rations of sugar.
   Rumors that a milk van was arriving spread through the crowdand
another long line formed at the milk shop.
   The only available meat was six pig feet, coated with fine hairs
and laid out on a dirty shelf in a food shop that also offered
2-year-old cans of squash, vegetable puree and spinach.
   Most shoppers bought half-filled bottles of mineral water. The
driest summer in years added tap water to the list of scarce
commodities.
   For most Romanians, it will be another Christmas without the
turkey, pork, fresh feta cheese, apple cake and wine some remember
from better times.
   ``I am terrified by the coming days,'' said Maria Radoi, one of
the shoppers.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0015 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 0310EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-GulfRdp 5thLd-Writethru a0582 11-25 0789</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf Rdp, 5th Ld-Writethru, a0582,0968</SECOND>
<HEAD>Colombia, Malaysia Balk at Proposal For Force Against Iraq</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 7 grafs to add newspaper report that meeting on
resolution will probably be Thursday, details. Pick up 8th graf
pvs, `In other...'</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos LON12, BOG1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ANDREA HAMILTON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   The United States failed on Saturday to persuade Colombia and
Malaysia immediately to back a proposed U.N. resolution authorizing
force against Iraq. But U.S. officials said the resolution would be
presented to the Security Council this week.
   President Bush, who returned from Europe early Saturday, said he
was confident of broad support for the proposed resolution.
   Secretary of State James A. Baker III, who has been lobbying
world leaders for votes, is expected to preside over the debate
when the foreign ministers of most of the 15 council members
assemble at the United Nations at midweek, the U.S. officials said
on condition of anonymity.
   The Malaysian foreign minister, who met with Baker in Los
Angeles, told reporters he believed the meeting on the resolution
would take place Thursday. The Los Angeles Times also reported in
Sunday's editions that the resolution would probably be presented
Thursday.
   The United States wants a meeting before the end of November,
when it gives up its council chairmanship to Yemen. That nation,
the only Arab member of the council, has sided with Iraq in the
past.
   The Washington Post reported Sunday that the United States began
distributing a draft of a proposed resolution to the other four
permanent members of the Security Council Saturday night that does
not specifically use the word ``force.''
   The paper quoted diplomatic sources as saying they believe the
draft seeks to avoid objections to that term by using such phrases
as ``all necessary means.''
   In other developments, a group of 10 British women on Saturday
won the release of relatives held in Iraq, and President Saddam
Hussein promised to free ``a large number'' of Italians.
   Also, a group of 36 female nurses, most of them Irish, arrived
in Jordan after being allowed to leave when their contracts
expired, an Irish Embassy official said. He would not give the
nationalities of those who were not Irish.
   Bush and Baker have been lobbying leaders around the globe to
support a military strike to force Iraq from Kuwait. Bush ended an
eight-day trip to Europe and the Middle East on Saturday.
   Baker on Saturday visited Colombia, a key member of the U.N.
Security Council.
   After a four-hour meeting, Colombian Foreign Minister Luis
Jaramillo said his government had not decided how it would vote on
the proposed resolution.
   ``Finding peaceful solutions to conflicts is a fundamental
thesis within Colombia foreign policy,'' Jaramillo said at a news
conference with Baker.
   Colombia has voted in favor of all previous Security Council
resolutions against Iraq.
   Baker later met in Los Angeles with Foreign Minister Abu Hassan
of Malaysia, also a council member.
   Hassan said he offered Baker ``no promises,'' but said he would
discuss the matter with the rest of Malaysia's cabinet ministers on
Wednesday.
   ``I believe that there will be a meeting of the Security Council
on Thursday, so there will be time to make a decision,'' he said.
   Bush said Friday he was confident he would get broad approval
from the Security Council for the latest proposal, even though some
council members have refused to back the use of force against Iraq.
   China is among the uncommitted and, as one of the five permanent
Council members, it has veto power. The other permanent members are
Britain, France, the Soviet Union and the United States.
   Spain's foreign minister, Fernandez Ordonez, met with Chinese
leaders in Beijing and later said: ``I've always had the impression
that it was possible such a resolution would pass this month.''
   But he made it clear his view did not result from discussions
with the Chinese.
   Since Iraq seized Kuwait on Aug. 2, the Security Council has
passed 10 resolutions against Baghdad, including one that imposed a
global trade embargo.
   About 26 nations have deployed 350,000 troops in the gulf
region. They include 230,000 American troops, most in Saudi Arabia,
and 200,000 more are on the way.
   The multinational force faces an estimated 460,000 Iraqi troops
stationed in Kuwait and southern Iraq.
   Thousands of people in London and Bonn on Saturday protested the
military buildup in the gulf.
   Police said about 5,000 people marched through central London.
They carried placards that said ``Out of the gulf'' and chanted
anti-war slogans. About 6,000 people rallied in Bonn to demand a
peaceful solution to the standoff.
   There were smaller protests in Toronto, Ottawa, and Newark, N.J.
   Iraq's state-run television reported Saturday that Saddam met
for one hour with British women who flew to Baghdad last week
seeking the release of husbands, sons and brothers despite advice
from the British government against the trip.
   The broadcast said he ordered the Britons released ``in
appreciation for the women's visit and the role of women in
general.''
   The official Iraqi News Agency reported that Saddam also
promised Archbishop Hilarion Capucci that he would free ``a large
number of Italian nationals.''
   Capucci is the spiritual head of the 3,000-member Melchite-rite
Catholic community of Jerusalem.
   Also on Saturday, a German Foreign Ministery spokesman said
German hostages freed by Iraq were expected to return to Frankfurt
on Sunday afternoon.
   In another development, an American soldier was killed Saturday
in Saudi Arabia in a truck collision. The soldier was the 49th to
die since Operation Desert Shield began Aug. 7. The soldier, who
was not identified, was from the 628th Transportation Company,
553rd Combat Support Battalion, 101st Combat Support Group.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0016 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 0315EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i BC-Egypt-Israel-Shooting -URGENT-   11-25 0172</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Egypt-Israel-Shooting,0197</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<HEAD>Gunman Shoots at Israeli Tourist Bus in Eilat, Kills Four</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CAIRO, Egypt (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Four people were killed and an unknown
number of others wounded in the Israeli border town of Eilat Sunday
when a gunman on the Egyptian side of the border sprayed their tour
bus with bullets, an Israeli Embassy official said.
   Isaac Bar-Moshe, the embassy's press officer, said the gunman
escaped in a car that was waiting for him after the attack Sunday
morning.
   ``We know that a man stood just inside the Egyptian side of the
border, near the Eilat border stone, and shot at an Israeli tourist
bus inside Israel. We know that four have been killed and many
others injured,'' Bar-Moshe said in a telephone interview.
   ``I am told that the gunman was in unfiorm but I do not know
whether it was police or army or what. We do not know the identity
or nationality of the gunman,'' Bar-Moshe added.
   ``There was a car waiting for him and he ran away in it,'' he
said. He said the gunman had been carrying a Kalashnikov rifle.
   He said he had no further details.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0017 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 0322EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-US-Gulf 3rdLd-Writethru a0576 11-25 0535</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-US-Gulf, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0576,600</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.S. To Seek U.N. Resolution This Week on Force To Oust Iraqi
Troops</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: SUBS 2nd graf pvs, ``Secretary of State xxx to add reports
that meeting on resolution will probably be Thursday; Edits to
conform; SUBS 7th graf pvs, ``The Washington Post xxx to change
letter to resolution; Pickup 8th graf pvs, ``The paper quoted xxx</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By BARRY SCHWEID</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Diplomatic Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Bush administration will try this week to
win U.N. Security Council approval of a resolution authorizing the
use of force to end the Iraqi occupation of Kuwait if peaceful
efforts fail, U.S. officials said Saturday.
   Secretary of State James A. Baker III, who has traveled the
world lobbying for votes, is expected to preside over the debate
when the foreign ministers of most of the 15 council members
assemble here at midweek. Malaysian Foreign Minister Abu Hassan
said after meeting with Baker in Los Angeles Saturday that he
believed the meeting on the resolution would take place Thursday.
The Los Angeles Times also reported in its Sunday editions that the
resolution would probably be presented Thursday.
   Malaysia is one of the council participants whose position is
uncertain in what could be a tough test of the administration's
Persian Gulf policy.
   Before meeting with Hassan Saturday, Baker visited Bogota,
Colombia, but failed to win immediate support from Colombian
officials for a resolution authorizing force to oust Iraqi troops
from Kuwait.
   The United States' one-month presidency of the Security Council
ends Friday. Yemen, expected to oppose a resolution against Iraq,
will take over for December.
   In Beijing, Spanish Foreign Minister Francisco Fernandez Ordonez
said Saturday the Security Council could pass the proposed
resolution before the end of this week.
   The Washington Post reported in its Sunday editions that the
United States began distributing a draft of a proposed resolution
to the other four permanent members of the Security Council
Saturday night and that it does not specifically use the word
``force.''
   The paper quoted diplomatic sources as saying it is their
understanding the draft seeks to avoid objections to that term by
using such phrases as ``all necessary means.''
   Kuwait will make its presentation against Iraq on Monday and
Tuesday. The focus then shifts under Baker's guidance to the
resolution authorizing force. The U.S.-backed resolution would be
the toughest step taken by the council against Iraq since the Aug.
2 invasion.
   The positions of the Soviet Union and China appeared uncertain,
but U.S. officials did not expect the two powers to block a
resolution. Officials expected that the two would try to soften the
U.S. approach before it was put to a test vote.
   The five Security Council members with veto powers are Britain,
China, France, the Soviet Union and the United States.
   The Soviet Union's U.N. envoy also said Friday that Foreign
Minister Eduard A. Shevardnadze would attend a Security Council
meeting this week to discuss Iraqi aggression - and to issue a
``strong, serious and precise Warning'' to Baghdad.
   Only Cuba is considered a sure bet to vote against the
resolution. The Bush administration wants the most lopsided tally
possible to demonstrate to Iraqi President Saddam Hussein that the
drive to liberate Kuwait has widespread support.
   The Soviet Union and China have not ruled out force. A senior
U.S. official, declining to be identified, said earlier this month
that the two countries had given assurances they would not block
such a resolution.
   Yet Soviet President Mikhail S. Gorbachev gave no direct
assurances to President Bush at their meeting last week how the
Soviets would vote.
   From the outset, Gorbachev has put more stress than Bush on
seeking a diplomatic solution to the crisis and has sent his top
Mideast specialist, Yevgeny Primakov, on missions to Baghdad.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0018 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 0740EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i BC-Italy-CopterCrash     11-25 0145</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Italy-Copter Crash,0142</SECOND>
<HEAD>Helicopter Carrying 13 Plunges Into Adriatic</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ROME (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A helicopter carrying 13 people plunged into the
Adriatic Sea off northeastern Italy Sunday morning, and everyone on
board was feared killed, authorities said.
   Rescuers recovered two bodies and were searching for others,
said officials at the Civil Protection Ministry.
   There was no sign of survivors, they said.
   The helicopter was rented by the Italian oil company AGIP. It
carried a three-member crew and 10 technicians headed for an
offshore platform.
   The helicopter, an SA330 built by Aerospaziale, crashed soon
after it left the town of Marina di Ravenna for a platform about a
mile offshore, an official at the Civil Protection Ministry said on
condition of anonymity.
   He said everyone on board was feared dead.
   The cause of the crash was not immediately known.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0019 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 0752EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i BC-Lebanon-Israel 2ndLd-Writethru a0593 11-25 0425</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Lebanon-Israel, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0593,0487</SECOND>
<HEAD>Group Claims Suicide Bomber Attacked Israeli Patrol</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: New thruout to UPDATE with Israeli army communique; No
pickup.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By RODEINA KENAAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BEIRUT, Lebanon (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A pro-Syrian group claimed that a woman
detonated a handbag packed with explosives Sunday, killing herself
and several israeli soldiers. Israel confirmed the attack but said
two soldiers were wounded.
   A communique issued by the Syrian Social Nationalist Party said
Sunday's suicide attack took place inside Israel's self-designated
``security zone'' in south Lebanon at 10 a.m. (3 a.m. EST.)
   It was the second anti-Israeli incident in Lebanon in two days.
On Saturday, the Israeli navy sank a dinghy off the Lebanese coast,
killing five guerrillas apparently en route to attack an Israeli
target, the Israeli army said in Jerusalem.
   ``Fadwa Hassan Ghanem detonated her bomb-laden handbag as an
Israeli patrol was crossing the road between Kfar Tibnit and Arnoun
in the security zone. The entire patrol was killed and she was
martyred,'' the SSNP communique said.
   It did not say how many Israelis were killed. There was no
immediate word on the attack from the Lebanese police.
   But in Jersusalem, the Israeli army said two soldiers were on
patrol checking a road near Beaufort castle when ``a female
terrorist ran at them, strapped with explosive charge.
   She exploded herself, wounding two soldiers, one in the neck and
another in the feet,'' the Israeli army said.
   Beaufort, a crusader castle that was a Palestinian guerrilla
stronghold in Israel's 1982 Lebanon war, is situated three miles
north of the border.
   Another Israeli military official, also speaking on condition of
anonymity, said the two soldiers suffered light injuries and that a
Lebanese citizen also was wounded in the attack.
   Dr. Mickey Wiener, deputy head of the Rambam Hospital in Haifa
where the wounded soldiers were evacuated by helicopter, said they
suffered ear injuries from the blast and superficial shrapnel
wounds. He described the soldiers' condition as ``light to
moderate.''
   The 440-square-mile zone, carved out by Israel in 1985, is
jointly patrolled by Israeli soldiers and about 2,500 members of
the Israeli-backed South Lebanon Army militia.
   In the dinghy incident, ``an Israeli navy Dabur patrol vessel,
on routine duty Saturday night off the Lebanese coast, encountered
a terrorist boat. Battle ensued whereupon the terrorist boat was
destroyed and five terrorists killed,'' the Israeli army said in a
statement.
   The radical Popular Front for the Liberation of
Palestine-General Command said three of its guerrillas were killed
in what it said was a three-hour gunbattle with Israeli gunboats
off Saadiyat, 12 miles south of Beirut.
   The SSNP is a coalition of Lebanese leftist and Palestinian
groups waging a guerrilla war to dislodge Israel from its border
enclave.
   The party advocates the merger of Syria, Lebanon, Jordan,
pre-1948 Palestine, Iraq, Kuwait and Cyprus into a ``Greater
Syria.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0020 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 0908EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i BC-Egypt-Israel-Shooting -URGENT- a0 11-25 0555</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Egypt-Israel-Shooting, 6th Ld-Writethru, a0595,0689</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<HEAD>Precede CAIRO</HEAD>
<HEAD>Gunman Shoots at Israeli Vehicles; Four Killed, 24 Wounded</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: New thruout with reports from Eilat, Israeli officials, gunman
infiltrated from Egypt, three soldiers, one civilian dead; Changes
byline; No pickup</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By ARIEH O'SULLIVAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>EILAT, Israel (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A gunman who infiltrated from Egypt sprayed
four Israeli vehicles with assault rifle fire Sunday, killing four
people and wounding 24, the army said.
   The army said the lone gunman killed three Israeli army soldiers
and a civilian driver for the national Egged bus company on the
Israeli-Egyptian border, about 15 miles northwest of the Israeli
Red Sea resort of Eilat.
   The gunman escaped back into Egypt. A senior Egyptian security
source said an Egyptian border policeman assigned to the area of
the attack had been arrested as the suspected assailant. Earlier
reports from Cairo said the gunman had fired from the Egyptian side
of the border.
   In Amman, Jordan a fundamentalist Islamic group Sunday claimed
responsibility for the attack. The extremist Islamic Jihad-Beit
Al-Maqdes, or Islamic Holy War-Jersualem, said the attack was
carried out by ``one of our units operating in the land of Arabism
and Islam, the land of Egypt.''
   Defense Minister Moshe Arens called the attack ``a most serious
incident'' and said Israel expected Egypt to take all the necessary
steps to prevent such assaults.
   A military commander identified only as Brig. Gen. D. said on
army radio that an Egyptian man ``whose identity is not clear to us
at this moment'' infiltrated into Israel at the distance of about
300 yards from the scene of the shooting.
   ``He entered a dry riverbed, reached the road and lay in wait on
the roadside,'' the commander said.
   The assailant opened fire on an army van, containing just the
driver, who was injured but carried on for a few hundred yards and
stopped.
   Another military car, also containing only one person and
heading from Eilat to a nearby base, was hit by several bullets.
The soldier inside was mortally wounded, drove for a few hundred
yards and died, the commander said.
   Next came a military bus. The driver thought there had been an
accident and stopped. He got out with his weapon but was shot dead
``at very close range'' before he could fire back.
   Finally, the attacker fired on an Egged bus carrying civilians
working at military installations in the area. He wounded a
security guard, who shot back, hitting the assailant.
   ``We found signs of blood showing that he was hit. I think this
prevented a heavier tragedy,'' the commander said. ``The terrorist
apparently intended to board the bus and take it over. He (the
guard) did not let him come on board. He climbed down through the
door and shot him, and from that moment the terrorist began running
away.''
   Reporters at the scene saw a red and white passenger bus with
its windshield covered with bullet holes. Police forensic experts
were seen picking up bullets around the bus.
   Isaac Bar-Moshe, press officer at the Israeli Embassy in Cairo,
said the gunman had used a Soviet-made Kalashnikov semiautomatic
rifle.
   If the attack was indeed committed by a member of Egypt's
uniformed forces, it would be the second. On Oct. 5, 1985, an
Egyptian border police officer went berserk and shot dead four
Israeli children, two women and an elderly man near the border in
the Sinai Desert.
   Before Sunday, the latest attack on an Israeli target in Egypt
was on Feb. 4, when gunmen ambushed a tour bus, killing nine
Israeli vacationers. The attack took place on a desert road between
Cairo and the Suez Canal city of Ismailiya.
   Egypt is the only Arab state to have a peace treaty with Israel.
After the treaty was signed in 1979, Israel began withdrawing from
the Egyptian Sinai peninsula, which it occupied in 1967.
   Between 1984 and 1987, two Israeli diplomats and six Israelis
were wounded in Cairo in a number of attacks claimed by an Egyptian
terrorist organization, Egypt's Revolution.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0021 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 0928EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i BC-Iraq-Foreigners 1stLd-Writethru a0594 11-25 0284</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Iraq-Foreigners, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0594,0327</SECOND>
<HEAD>More Than 100 Germans Freed</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with two grafs to correct that only 7 germans did not
arrive; Pickup 3rd, `The release...'</NOTE>
<DATELINE>BAGHDAD, Iraq (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   More than 100 Germans flew to freedom
Sunday aboard a chartered Iraqi Airways jetliner to Frankfurt,
German Embassy officials said.
   About seven other Germans expected to join them from Kuwait did
not arrive as scheduled and were scheduled to leave Monday, the
German Foreign Ministry said in Frankfurt. They are the last
remaining German captives.
   The release followed the Iraqi Parliament's decision - on Saddam
Hussein's recommendation - to free all German hostages because
Chancellor Helmut Kohl has stressed the need for peaceful solution
of the Persian Gulf crisis.
   Those freed Sunday were the second large group of Germans to fly
out of Iraq this month. Former Chancellor Willy Brandt took more
than 150 home with him after he visited Baghdad Nov. 9.
   Former boxing cahampion Mohammed Ali, meanwhile, met with Saddam
Sunday in a bid to secure the release of some of the hundreds of
Americans held in Iraq, officials reported.
   They said Ali was received by Saddam in his heavily guarded
presidential palace on the banks of the Tigris River. No details of
the talks were immediately available.
   Ali arrived in Baghdad last Wednesday, accompanied by two aides
and two members of a group called the Coalition to Stop U.S.
Intervention in the Middle East.
   About 300 Americans are still held in Iraq. Another 600 are in
Kuwait, some in hiding.
   Saddam has said he will free all Westerners held in Iraq and
Kuwait between Christmas and March 15.
   But the Iraqis have warned that the proposed releases would be
scrapped ``if something would take place that mars the atmosphere
of peace.''
   The Bush administration has been lobbying world leaders for
support of a proposed U.N. resolution authorizing force to drive
Iraq out of Kuwait.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0022 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 1135EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-MissLadybird     11-25 0193</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Miss Ladybird,0197</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dispute Prompts Death Threats in South African Child Pageant</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JOHANNESBURG, South Africa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An 8-year-old contestant in a
child beauty pageant was the target of death threats after a
dispute over whether she qualifed for the final round, a newspaper
reported Sunday.
   The Sunday Times, in a front-page story, said undercover police
and private security guards dressed as clowns patrolled Saturday
during the finals of the Miss Ladybird beauty-and-talent
competition to protect the child, Sharika Habib.
   ``The whole thing is a disgrace,'' the newspaper quoted
competition organizer Deborah Pead as saying.
   Marie Habib, the child's mother, told the Sunday Times she
received death threats over the phone.
   ``This was a case of sick minds and sour grapes,'' she said.
   The dispute involved an error in calculating judges' scores in a
preliminary competitions, Mrs. Pead said. Sharika won her
competition, but the error caused officials to declare another girl
the winner.
   When the error was discovered, Sharika was reinstated as a
finalist, but parents of other children objected, Mrs. Pead said.
   The winner of the final competition was 9-year-old Jolene
Sylvester. The title carries prizes worth $36,000.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0023 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 1140EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Korea-Protests     11-25 0398</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Korea-Protests,0449</SECOND>
<HEAD>Police Move Onto Campus, Triggering Fierce Battle with
Demonstrators</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto SEL2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KELLY SMITH TUNNEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SEOUL, South Korea (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Riot police stormed a Seoul campus to
break up an anti-government, anti-U.S. rally Sunday but were driven
back in violent clashes with 5,000 protesters hurling rocks and
firebombs.
   ``Yankees go home!'' yelled protesters. ``Oust (President) Roh
Tae-woo!''
   In all, some 15,000 radical students, dissidents, farmers and
workers staged protest rallies in Seoul and 10 provincial cities.
   Dozens of protesters were reported arrested nationwide. A dozen
protesters and police were injured in Seoul, but it was not known
how many were injured overall.
   The protesters demanded an end to American pressure to open
South Korean markets.
   Hundreds of riot police backed by armored vehicles firing
volleys of tear gas stormed on to the campus of Konkuk University
in Seoul. But the estimated 5,000 protesters fought back with
firebombs, metal clubs and rocks.
   At one point, five policemen were surrounded by club-wielding
students. One officer was seriously injured and carried away.
   A wood barricade erected by students was set afire. Windows at a
school building were broken by rocks and tear gas shells.
   Demonstrators regrouped to continue their rally. Police then
stayed outside the school in eastern Seoul.
   A large sign at the school showed Uncle Sam telling a Korean
farmer: ``Let's have the key to the warehouse. I will control the
food.''
   Clashes were reported in the provincial cities of Kwangju,
Taegu, Pusan, Taejon, Sungnam, Wonju, Chonju and Chongju. Peaceful
rallies were held in two other cities.
   In Kwangju, police fired tear gas when about 1,500 protesters
marched out of Chonnam University, demanding an end to
international talks trying to reduce tariffs on farm goods,
reported Yonhap, the South Korean news agency.
   Most of Sunday's clashes erupted around campuses. Demonstrators
staged running street protests in at least four cities.
   The protesters demanded that South Korea reject the ``Uruguay
Round'' of trade negotiations sponsored by the General Agreement on
Tariffs and Trade.
   They accused the United States of plotting a new international
trade order that would sacrifice South Korea and other small
countries for its own interests.
   Public anger over trade issues has increased in recent weeks.
Consumer and civic groups have vowed to launch a boycott against
U.S. goods.
   In an address last week, U.S. Ambassador Donald Gregg said
negative views of America have become widespread in South Korea,
threatening to poison economic and political relations with the
United States.
   Opposition leaders have warned of major political unrest, urging
Roh to initiate sweeping political and social reforms.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0024 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 1147EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-China-Reform     11-25 0587</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-China-Reform,0691</SECOND>
<HEAD>Special Zones, Cradle of Reforms, Celebrate 10 Years</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KATHY WILHELM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   China's first laboratories for capitalist reform,
four coastal enclaves that have attracted both investment and
corruption, celebrate their 10th anniversary Monday uncertain of
their role in the 1990s.
   When Shenzhen, Zhuhai, Shantou and Xiamen were designated
China's first special economic zones in 1980, senior leader Deng
Xiaoping was just starting his program of shaking up the
inefficient centrally planned economy.
   Deng wanted to experiment with limited free markets,
Western-style management and foreign-invested joint ventures. But
he worried about the ``flies and mosquitoes'' - Western social and
political values - that would come in the new open window.
   The answer was special zones, areas set apart for foreign
investment, or in the case of Shenzhen, created for it.
   Shenzhen, an hour's train ride from Hong Kong, was mostly rice
paddies in 1980. It had 30,000 residents and no traffic lights.
   Now it has 1.5 million residents, and its high-rise, neon-lit
skyline is modeled on Hong Kong. It has become the biggest and
best-known special economic zone, home to nearly one-fifth of the
10,000 foreign-invested companies operating in China.
   Huge celebrations might have been expected for the zones' 10th
birthday. Instead, there almost was no celebration at all. The real
birthdate, in August, was ignored and festivities were scheduled
for this week only at the last minute.
   Shenzhen officials invited Communist Party General Secretary
Jiang Zemin to attend, but there has been no word on whether he
will go.
   The national media have said little about the anniversary. The
Shenzhen Special Zone Daily has reported local meetings to discuss
the anniversary's ``guiding ideology,'' and has published 15
approved slogans for the day.
   ``Work hard for new achievements in building a socialist
spiritual civilization,'' reads one.
   ``The whole nation supports the Special Economic Zones, the
Special Economic Zones serve the whole nation.''
   Beijing authorities fear the zones, especially Shenzhen, have
been contaminated by capitalist values and have failed to
contribute enough of their new-found wealth to the rest of the
nation.
   Shenzhen has become notorious for higher levels of prostitution,
gambling and crime than most Chinese cities. Workers hired by
contract rather than for life, as is customary elsewhere in China,
work harder, are paid better and spend more freely.
   An ``anything goes'' atmosphere prevails. One hotel even opened
a casino in 1985, even though all gambling is illegal in China.
Authorities quickly shut it down.
   Chinese entering Shenzhen need special travel permits, as if for
a foreign country. Still, the government fears the ``flies and
mosquitoes'' have gotten out of hand. At a meeting in Shenzhen in
February, Premier Li Peng called on the zones to ``show a new image
of socialist culture and morals.''
   Communist Party leader Jiang warned, ``They are not special
political zones.''
   Critics in Beijing also say the zones' prosperity has not
trickled back to inland regions that supply them with raw
materials. Many products exported by the zones are made inland, but
the zones take a cut of the profits for their transit.
   Dozens of other cities now offer incentives to foreign
investors, such as tax waivers and long-term land leases, that
rival what the zones can offer. Other cities also have been
designated to experiment with new reforms, such as converting
housing to private ownership.
   The strongest blow to the zones' special place came in 1989,
when their main patron, party General Secretary Zhao Ziyang, was
ousted for allegedly supporting pro-democracy protests.
   Since then, the reshuffled party leadership under Jiang has made
Shanghai and the Yangtze River valley the centerpiece of
development plans. Jiang was party secretary in Shanghai before
being named to succeed Zhao.
   A fifth special enterprise zone, Hainan Island off the southern
coast, was established in 1988 with Zhao's backing. Jiang and Li
both have said there will be no more.
   ``We must first concentrate our strength to run the currently
existing special zones well,'' Jiang told a Hong Kong magazine in
September.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0025 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 1146EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Bush-Mexico Bjt   11-25 0549</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bush-Mexico, Bjt,0666</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush-Salinas Discussion to Center on Free Trade</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ELOY O. AGUILAR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MEXICO CITY (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Carlos Salinas de Gortari welcomes
President Bush to his hometown Monday for a discussion expected to
center on developing closer relations through trade.
   The two nations are negotiating a free trade agreement, which
Salinas hopes will help Mexico grow out of the Third World into the
ranks of developed nations.
   Bush is to arrive in Monterrey at about noon and travel 55 miles
by helicopter to Agualeguas, the Salinas family hometown of 5,000
people, where they will attend a rodeo and meet privately for two
hours. They plan to return to Monterrey afterward.
   Another private meeting is scheduled for Wednesday, and Bush
will speak to businessmen in Monterrey, the country's industrial
capital.
   A Mexican bishop was quoted recently as saying ``it is like
dealing with sharks'' to negotiate a free trade arrangement with
the United States, but a government official said: ``Bishops don't
know much about economy.''
   The official, speaking anonymously, said the Salinas government
feels it can strike a satisfactory deal with the United States.
   Otto Granados, the presidential press spokesman, said: ``We
think that within a year we can have the basis of the agreement.''
   Salinas hopes Mexican industrialists can produce more and better
products to compete with an expected flood of U.S. goods, and also
find markets in the United States. Years of hiding behind high
tariff walls has hurt the competitive ability of some Mexican
companies.
   Since Salinas took office in December 1988, Mexico has lowered
tariffs and joined the General Agreement on Trade and Tariffs,
which his predecessors had sworn the country would never do. U.S.
products, from beer to cars, now can be imported by those who can
pay the lower duties.
   ``Ten years ago, if a Mexican president had suggested a free
trade agreement with the United States, people would have hanged
him in the middle of the main plaza,'' a high government official
said, on condition of anonymity.
   ``I think Mexican society has matured,'' Granados said. ``There
is less fear of the United States and we have a more pragmatic
vision of our relationship with the United States.
   ``There is a global tendency to form regional blocs. Europe is
too concentrated on its own expanded markets, Asia is another bloc
and we must look at our own regional possibilities.''
   Mexico focuses its economic attention on the United States and
Canada rather than on Central and South America.
   Granados said the presidents probably would discuss the drug
issue only in passing, if at all. Mexico feels cooperation on the
drug problem is at least as good as it ever has been, he said.
   Another question is the treatment of Mexican nationals working
in the United States, a sensitive issue on both sides of the
border. Migrant workers, legal or illegal, often are accused of
involvement in drug trafficking and other criminal activities.
   Allegations of racism have marred relations in the past.
   Mexicans always have considered the United States a racist
society. Recently, newspapers in Mexico have played up incidents
along frontier with California, where several Mexican citizens have
died trying to across illegally.
   Reports of Californians lining up vehicles along the border and
turning on the lights to help the border patrol are seen in Mexico
as expressions of racism.
   The government wants any free trade agreement to make it easier
for Mexicans to enter the United States.
   ``Our claim is that the U.S. economic reality demands Mexican
labor,'' an official said.
   ``Even with more employment facilities in Mexico, the U.S.
salary levels will remain attractive to Mexican workers. What we
want to do is make the flow of labor more rational.''
   Mexican officials say northward migration is not permanent and
that studies show nearly 90 percent of the workers return to
Mexico, at least temporarily.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0026 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 1147EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-MishimaAnniversary     11-25 0332</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mishima Anniversary,0385</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rally on 20th Anniversary of Japanese Novelist's Suicide</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   About 2,000 people, mainly from right-wing groups,
rallied Sunday in tribute to novelist Yukio Mishima, who shocked
Japan with his gory ritual suicide 20 years ago at age 45.
   Mishima, regarded as one of the leading Japanese authors of this
century, had denounced the postwar constitution that renounces war
and limits the emperor's role to that of state symbol rather than a
living god.
   The rally participants pledged to follow his principles, said
Toshio Sasaki, one of the organizers.
   After the rally, 1,000 people, including members of the Japan
Student Union and the right-wing Neo-Nationalist Union, marched to
the army base where Mishima disemboweled himself on Nov. 25, 1970.
   The demonstrators carried banners saying: ``Regain history and
tradition!'' and ``Long live the Emperor!'' In a traditional
gesture, they laid chrysanthemums at the gates of the base.
   Police said there were no reports of violence.
   Before his suicide, Mishima and four young members of his small,
private militia took a general hostage and demanded that troops
stationed at the base assemble on the parade ground.
   In a speech from a balcony, Mishima urged the soldiers to rise
up to regain glory for the Japanese military and the emperor. But
he was heckled by the troops.
   At that point, Mishima hurried indoors, stripped to his
loincloth and plunged a dagger into his abdomen, in the traditional
manner of suicide. One of his followers then decapitated him with a
sword.
   At the time, many feared that Mishima's spectacular suicide
could help revive the militarism that had driven Japan into World
War II.
   But his militaristic views have little popular support nowadays.
When Prime Minister Toshiki Kaifu recently proposed legislation
that would allow Japanese soldiers to be sent to the Persian Gulf
in non-combat roles, but opposition was so strong he had to drop
the idea.
   Mishima's novels, plays and short stories are known for
reflecting the conflict between the West and traditional Japanese
values. Among his best-known novels are ``Confessions of a Mask,''
a partly autobiographical account of a boy's self-awakening, and
``The Temple of the Golden Pavilion,'' the story of a young monk
who burns down a Buddhist temple.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0027 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 1148EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--Israel-Water     11-25 0180</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Israel-Water,0190</SECOND>
<HEAD>Commissioner Orders Water Pumping Stopped From Only Lake</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Israel's water commissioner ordered pumps
halted Sunday to save the nation's main source of water, the Lake
of Galilee.
   The commissioner, Zemah Ishai, said the level of the lake, known
in Hebrew as Kinneret, was less than 2.75 inches away from the
level at which continued pumping would destroy the reserve.
   Ishai told Israel radio that he ordered water supplied instead
from underground water reservoirs. Besides the lake, Israel also
pumps water from two aquifers, but they are near empty from several
years of dry winters.
   Israel radio said the northern port city of Haifa was expected
to suffer water supply problems because of the decision.
   Ishai said Israel was negotiating with Turkey to import water to
help fill used-up reserves.
   ``We have a problem of shortage, of an accumulated deficit in
the water economy for dozens of years ... the demand in Israel is
growing and the welcome immigration will increase the demand,''
Ishai said.
   Israel expects a million Soviet Jewish immigrants to have
arrived by the end of 1992.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0028 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 1148EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-MussoliniRobbery     11-25 0214</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mussolini Robbery,0237</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mussolini's Desk Set Stolen</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ROME (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The silver desk set used by Benito Mussolini at the
signing of Italy's 1929 pact with the Vatican has been stolen from
his granddaughter's house, newspapers reported Sunday.
   Raimonda Ciano, daughter of Galeazzo Ciano and Edda Mussolini,
was quoted as saying the set was taken early Saturday from her Rome
home while she was sleeping.
   The richly decorated, 19th-century desk set includes an
inkstand, inkpot, two candleholders, and a container for sand and
ashes, which were used to dry ink on the page.
   Ms. Ciano said the set was of ``enormous emotional value'' to
her, according to the Rome-based daily Il Messaggero. It was not
insured, according to the accounts.
   Police said Sunday they had no information on the theft.
   The Italian fascist dictator used the set to sign the Lateran
Pacts with the Vatican, Ms. Ciano said. In the accords, the Roman
Catholic Church recognized the sovereignty of the Italian state,
and Catholicism became the official religion.
   Ms. Ciano was quoted as saying the burglary was likely
commissioned. The burglars stole only a few small objects apart
from the desk set and did not search in drawers or closets, she
said.
   The burglary was discovered by Ms. Ciano's brother, Fabrizio. On
arriving at his sister's apartment around noon, he found the door
had been forced open, the newspapers said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0029 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 1150EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-ReaganDoctrine Bjt   11-25 0687</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Reagan Doctrine, Bjt,780</SECOND>
<HEAD>Congress Chips Away at Controversial Reagan Legacy</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GEORGE GEDDA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Much like the Cold War itself, the U.S. effort
to roll back communism under the Reagan Doctrine appears headed for
oblivion.
   In the wake of the new East-West agreement on vastly reducing
conventional arms in Europe, what passes for superpower tension
these days results from the continuing U.S.-Soviet competition in
remote Third World conflicts.
   During the 1960s and 1970s, virtually the only guerrilla
fighters were those operating in anti-communist countries, often
rightist military dictatorships.
   That all changed under Reagan, and American conservatives
cheered when Reagan embraced ``freedom fighters'' opposing leftist
rule around the world.
   Now, after a run of four years, much of the Reagan Doctrine's
vitality is gone.
   In vote after vote, Congress has, in effect, told the Bush
administration that it doesn't see much sense in maintaining full
funding of anti-communist rebel groups when the Soviet bloc has
ceased to exist.
   The administration doesn't dispute the point, but said continued
aid to the rebel groups gives the leftist governments they oppose
incentive to negotiate peace.
   When Reagan took office, the only resistance movement receiving
U.S. help was the Afghan mujahedeen. By 1986, United States was
assisting the Nicaraguan Contras, Cambodia's non-communist rebels
and the insurgency fighting Angola's leftist government.
   But even that aid is in peril. In a move that went almost
unnoticed in the rush to adjournment, Congress passed an
intelligence bill that dealt the doctrine another blow.
   The bill would halt, among other restrictions, $60 million in
U.S. aid to Angola's UNITA rebels if the leftist government agrees
to hold free elections and the Soviet Union halts its own weapons
shipments to the Angolan armed forces.
   It also suspends a $13 million covert aid program to
anti-communist rebels in Cambodia that will be replaced by a
humanitarian aid program. And it cuts back aid to the Afghan
resistance to $250 million, $50 million less than the
administration request. The program would be cut off altogether if
the Soviets agree to stop sending military aid to the Afghan
government.
   Rep. Dante Fascell, D-Fla., chairman of the House Foreign
Affairs Committee, said he's not surprised Congress now balks at
administration requests for aid to rightist rebel groups.
   ``The Soviets have cut back on funding of their `clients' around
the world and we are responding accordingly,'' he said. ``The
Soviets are out of Afghanistan, the Contras won in Nicaragua, and
peace talks are in progress in Angola.''
   Rep. Henry Hyde, R-Ill., feels Congress is too eager to shelve
the Reagan Doctrine.
   Soviet President Mikhail Gorbachev may have won hhe Nobel Peace
Prize, Hyde said, ``but he is still pouring in $650 million into
Angola, and Soviet advisers are still very active there.''
   Hyde said he regrets the mood that ``exaggerates the resolution
of the Cold War.''
   Peter Rodman, of the Johns Hopkins Foreign Policy Institute,
agreed.
   The former National Security Council aide said U.S. assistance
helped initiate peace negotiations in each of the countries where
the United States was supporting a rebel group.
   ``Our strategy ought to be to complete the process,'' Rodman
said. ``Don't leave them (the rebel groups) in the lurch. The next
phase is a political accommodation. It makes no sense to penalize
our side.''
   The Nicaraguan Contras were the first rebel group to be axed by
the Congress. Despite Reagan administration predictions of
impending doom resulting from the February 1988 vote against the
Contras, the eventual outcome was a major plus for Washington.
   Nicaragua's civil war ended and the voters used the ballot box
to oust the Sandinista government earlier this year - achieving
what weapons shipments to the Contras were unable to do.
   Reagan's decision to back the Contras produced the most
controversial moments of his presidency. There were dozens of votes
on Contra aid over the years, most of them cliffhangers. The
excesses of subordinates led to the Iran-Contra arms and money
scandal and bitter recriminations between the administration and
congressional Democrats.
   Ted Galen Carpenter, director of Foreign Policy Studies at the
Cato Institute, a Washington research group, said the Reagan
Doctrine was misguided to begin with because some of the groups
receiving U.S. support were actually undemocratic, having sprung
from authoritarian traditions.
   Beyond that, he said the Reagan administration consistently
oversold the dangers to the United States of leftist rule in
Nicaragua. The Reagan Doctrine, he said, also involved Washington
in regions where no vital U.S. interests were at stake.
   But Burton Yale Pines, a senior vice president of the Heritage
Foundation, a conservative research group, sees the Reagan Doctrine
as a `marvelous legacy'' because it proclaimed that ``the future
belongs to democracy, not to Soviet-imposed dictatorships.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0030 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 1156EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-PlaneArrest     11-25 0205</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Plane Arrest,0226</SECOND>
<HEAD>Police: Man Tried To Ship M-80 Explosives In Plane's Cargo Area</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A 52-year-old man was arrested early Sunday
after police at Kennedy International Airport discovered that his
luggage included four boxes of firecracker-like explosives, a Port
Authority spokesman said.
   Jose A. Nieves of Puerto Rico was charged with first-degree
possession of a weapon and first-degree reckless endangerment, said
the spokesman, Armando Arrastia.
   Pan Am Flight 448 bound for Miami was being boarded at about
7:50 a.m. as a baggage handler loaded the cargo area of the plane
with baggage, he said.
   When he grabbed one box, which already had a small break in it,
it ripped open and M-80s - a sort of strong firecracker - began
falling across the belly of the plane, said Port Authority Officer
Kevin Devlin. Three other boxes were also found.
   Passengers were then removed from the plane while the cargo area
was searched for any other explosives, Arrastia said.
   Authorities said he purchased the explosives in Chinatown and
apparently just intended to take them home with him. Purchase of
any firecrackers is illegal in New York.
   Nieves was planning to fly to Miami before connecting to a
flight for San Juan, Puerto Rico, Devlin said.
   The FBI and Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco and Firearms were
investigating.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0031 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 1158EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-People CORRECTIVE   11-25 0138</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People, CORRECTIVE,0133</SECOND>
<NOTE>Eds: Members who used the NEW YORK-dated last item in AM-People,
sent Nov. 23 as a0563, are asked to use the following story.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Associated Press erroneously reported Friday
that a self-portrait of Marilyn Monroe would be auctioned with 35
other art works by famous people who enjoyed art as a hobby.
   The original works of art, which actually number 40 including
the Monroe self-portrait, will not be sold.
   Instead, artists' proofs, high-quality reproductions of just
seven of the 40 artworks, will be auctioned Tuesday. On the auction
block are copies of works by James Dean, David Bowie, Tennessee
Williams, Billy Dee Williams, Charles Bronson, Jeff Bridges and
e.e. cummings, said Antonio Capretta, a co-founder of Twice Gifted,
the group that organized the benefit.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0032 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 1225EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Poland-Voters     11-25 0429</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Poland-Voters,0506</SECOND>
<HEAD>Poles Cast Ballots in Presidential Elections</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Poland, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GABRIELLE GLASER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WARSAW, Poland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Poles on their way to church and on
morning strolls with dogs and children lined up at voting stations
nationwide Sunday to cast ballots in the country's first popular
election for president.
   ``I was so excited I couldn't sleep last night,'' said Antonina
Kaminska, a Warsaw seamstress who voted for Solidarity leader Lech
Walesa.
   ``Walesa is a charismatic leader who gives all of Poland hope,''
she said on the dreary gray morning.
   The elections pit Walesa against his former ally, Prime Minister
Tadeusz Mazowiecki, Polish emigre Stanislaw Tyminski and three
other candidates.
   The campaign had become increasingly caustic, and candidates
engaged in Western-style mudslinging. Walesa led in pre-election
polls.
   Stanislawa Kloskowska, a retired teacher from Walesa's home city
of Gdansk, said she voted for the Baltic port's most famous native
son.
   ``It was very easy to choose Lech Walesa,'' she said. ``He
started everything here and we expect him to complete his job.''
   Several people said they voted for Tyminski, a businessman who
said he had made millions in Canada and Peru and pledged to build a
``democracy of money.''
   His wealth is attractive to many Poles, who are struggling with
a radical economic reform program implemented by the Mazowiecki
government. It has cut real income by 35 percent and put about 1
million people out of work.
   ``For a year too little attention was paid to economy,'' said
Wladyslaw Skarbek, 41, a researcher at the Polish Academy of
Sciences in Warsaw. ``That's why I voted for Tyminski - as an
outsider he will devote less time to politics and more to the
economy.''
   While many voiced support for Walesa, others expressed concern
that the Nobel laureate would become a demagogue. His opponents
have drawn crowns and even Hitler-like moustaches on Walesa
campaign posters.
   Walesa's impetuous nature and campaign pledges - he promises to
wield an ``ax'' to cut former Communists out of Poland's industry
and government - have drawn sharp criticism from those who think
the country should take a more cautious approach to reform.
   ``I am afraid of Walesa. He is an egomaniac,'' said Juliusz
Baranowski, director of a new convenience store in Warsaw. ``The
world doesn't need another ayatollah.''
   Baranowski said Prime Minister Mazowiecki was not a ``born
leader,'' but that he voted for the former Catholic journalist
because his reserved, diplomatic nature would put Poland in good
stead with the rest of Europe.
   The winner of Sunday's election will replace President Wojciech
Jaruzelski, the Communist general who imposed martial law to crush
Solidarity in 1981. Jaruzelski is stepping down just over a year
into his six-year term to complete the transfer of power to a
freely elected head of state.
   While Poland was the first country in Eastern Europe to remove
its Communist government, it is one of the last to hold free
presidential elections.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0033 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 1226EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-MonkeyFeast     11-25 0272</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Monkey Feast,0307</SECOND>
<HEAD>Monkeys Gladly Accept Invitation to Feast</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos BK3,4</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TAVORN TUMMACHARTVIJIT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOPBURI, Thailand (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   They shunned the fried rice and their
table manners left much to be desired, but otherwise Sunday's feast
for 500 monkeys was a success.
   Yongyudh Kitwattananusom, owner of a hotel in the historic city,
last week sent out elaborate written invitations to the hundreds of
monkeys that inhabit an ancient temple in Lopburi.
   On Sunday, he set 50 tables, complete with tablecloths, and
prepared a menu that included a vegetable salad, cashew nuts, eggs,
fried rice and mixed tropical fruits. About 500 monkeys attended
the feast.
   Yongyudh, who threw a similar beast banquet last year, hopes the
event will help promote both his Lopburi Inn and the city, once an
outpost of the vast Cambodian empire. Lopburi is 90 miles north of
Bangkok.
   Several thousand Thais and foreigners gathered in Lopburi
Sunday, initially scaring away the banquet guests. But, enticed by
papaya leaves, the monkeys soon clambered down from their temple
perches and tucked into the dishes.
   They ignored the chairs, positioned themselves atop tables and
engaged in a lot of table hopping. Except for the fried rice, which
they inexplicably turned down, the food was scooped up with gusto
and washed down with soft drinks.
   The monkeys pulled tabs from cans and poured soft drink into
saucers.
   Although table etiquette was minimal, the feast proceeded
without fighting, possibly because there was plenty of food to go
around.
   As part of this year's event, children aged 4 to 12 were invited
to draw the monkeys. A first prize of $1,200 and two airline
tickets to Tokyo's Disneyland was offered.
   Many Buddhist temples in Thailand have become sanctuaries for
wild animals because Budhism forbids their killing.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0034 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 1250EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Italy-HelicopterCrash     11-25 0197</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Italy-Helicopter Crash,0206</SECOND>
<HEAD>Helicopter Crashes into Adriatic, All Aboard Feared Killed</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ROME (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A helicopter carrying 13 Italians plunged into the
Adriatic Sea off northeastern Italy on Sunday morning, and everyone
on board was feared killed, authorities said.
   It was the worst civilian helicopter crash in recent Italian
history, media reported.
   Rescuers recovered two bodies before suspending their search
Sunday evening because of choppy seas, said the port captain's
office. It was scheduled to begin again Monday at dawn.
   The helicopter was rented by the Italian oil company AGIP. It
carried a three-member crew, eight technicians and two employees of
a catering service. They were headed for an offshore platform used
to extract methane from the sea floor.
   The helicopter, an SA330 Puma built by Aerospaziale, crashed
soon after it left the town of Marina di Ravenna for the platform
about a mile offshore, said an official at the crisis unit of the
Civil Protection Ministry in Rome, speaking on condition of
anonymity.
   The cause of the crash was not immediately known.
   The rescue operation was complicated by strong winds that
whipped the waves, officials said.
   The Italian Civil Aviation authority named a commission to
investigate the crash.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0035 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 1253EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Chess-Championship     11-25 0448</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Chess-Championship,0576</SECOND>
<HEAD>Kasparov, Karpov Agree to a Draw</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SALVATORE ZANCA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LYON, France (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Chess masters and arch-rivals Garry Kasparov
and Anatoly Karpov began the second half of their chess World
Championship where they left off - agreeing Sunday to a draw.
   The 13th game was adjourned Saturday night after 41 moves in
five hours of play with a draw inevitable, according to the
experts.
   Karpov, who is trying to regain the world championship title
from defender Kasparov, proposed the draw by telephone through the
intermediary of Dutch referee Geurt Gijssen, officials said, an
option open to either player.
   Kasparov accepted.
   Karpov, playing white, would have opened Sunday's play with
Kxd3. The 42nd move, sealed Saturday night in an envelope, was
disclosed with the draw announcement Sunday.
   Kasparov, 27, and Karpov, 39, now each have 6{ points. They were
tied at six points apiece after the first 12 games in New York from
Oct. 8 to Nov. 7 - 10 of which were draws.
   The first player to gain 12{ points wins the championship and
$1.7 million of a $3 million purse. In the event of a tie, Kasparov
retains the title.
   Monday's 14th game is the second of the French phase of the
championship.
   Saturday's match in the main auditorium of the Palais des
Congres in this southcentral city was the first in the championship
series in two weeks.
   Karpov moved the queen's pawn to begin play again. The players
went through a series of moves known as the Grunfeld defense, which
was used in Game 9.
   Kasparov varied it a bit when he castled on the eighth move.
   The pair traded queens before the 20th move and were reduced to
eight pieces each by the 30th.
   Karpov repeatedly left his chair in the early part of the match.
Kasparov stayed at the board, hunched over in deep thought.
   At the adjournment, Kasparov had just taken a pawn to finish
with five pawns, a rook and the king.
   Karpov had four pawns, a rook and a king but was about to take a
black pawn to even things up again.
   Karpov waited more than 10 minutes as the five-hour time limit
drew close before sealing his 42nd move.
   ``I thought it was reasonable exciting,'' said international
grandmaster Mike Valvo of Perth Amboy, N.J. ``It was not a dull
25-30 move draw you would see in other matches.''
   Karpov ran into a time problem as the time limit approached,
with only nine minutes to complete eight moves. Each player is
alloted 2{ hours for his first 40 moves.
   But Karpov moved eight times in his next seven minutes.
   ``Most of us who sat and watched thought that white had chances
to win,'' Valvo said. ``In time pressure, Karpov seemed to let
whatever edge he had slip away.''
   Kasparov gained the title in 1985 from Karpov, who had held it
from 1975.
   Their dislike for each other is well-known.
   The two men differ in temperment, looks, politics and even
playing style.
   Kasparov considers Karpov a product of the Soviet system.
   ``Normally chess is a battle between two individuals,'' Kasparov
has said in an interview. ``But in my case, with Karpov, it's a
fight between two different mentalities in Russia. I identify him
with the system I've been fighting.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0036 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 1311EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Chess-Algebraic     11-25 0136</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Chess-Algebraic,0168</SECOND>
<HEAD>Moves From Kasparov-Karpov Draw</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Chess-Championship</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LYON, France (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the moves from Game 13 of the
Kasparov-Karpov chess match Saturday. Karpov played white, Kasparov
black:
   Grunfeld Opening, Exchange variation.
   Karpov Kasparov 1. d4 Nf6 2. c4 g6 3. Nc3 d5 4. cxd5 Nxd5 5. e4
Nxc3 6. bxc3 Bg7 7. Be3 c5 8. Qd2 0-0 9. Rc1 Qa5 10. Nf3 e6 11. d5
exd5 12. exd5 Re8 13. Be2 Bf5 14. 0-0 Nd7 15. h3 Nb6 16. g4 Bd7 17.
c4 Qxd2 18. Nxd2 Na4 19. Bf3 Nc3 20. Rxc3 Bxc3. 21. Ne4 Rxe4 22.
Bxe4 Re8 23. Bd3 b6 24. Kg2 f5 25. gxf5 Bxf5 26. Bxf5 gxf5 27. Rd1
Kf7 28. Rd3 Bf6 29. Ra3 a5 30. Rb3 Bd8. 31. Rc3 Bc7 32. a4 Kf6 33.
Kf1 f4 34. Bc1 Kf5. 35. Rc2 Rb8 36. Re2 Be5 37. Bb2 Bd4 38. Bxd4
cxd4 39. Re7 d3 40. Ke1 Rc8 41. Kd2. Rxc4.
   Game adjourned, draw agreed Sunday.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0037 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 1321EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Britain-Politics     11-25 0520</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Britain-Politics,0616</SECOND>
<HEAD>Heseltine Bid For Prime Ministership Gathers Momentum</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos CHE1,2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MAUREEN JOHNSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Michael Heseltine, who precipitated Prime Minister
Margaret Thatcher's downfall, said Sunday he was confident of
getting the necessary votes to win the leadership of his party and
country this week.
   But he admitted that some Conservative Party loyalists are
deeply angry at him for his role in forcing out Mrs. Thatcher, who
last week agreed to step down as prime minister.
   Heseltine, 57, and treasury chief John Major, 47, a right-winger
who is reportedly supported by Mrs. Thatcher, appeared to be locked
in a close contest in the race to succeed Mrs. Thatcher, with
Foreign Secretary Douglas Hurd trailing.
   London bookmakers ranked Heseltine and Major as even favorites
to win in Tuesday's ballot among the 372 Conservative Party
legislators. Hurd was a long shot at around 10-1.
   A series of opinion polls in Sunday's newspapers indicated the
party would win elections with him or Major as leader, but lose
under Hurd.
   But Hurd, 60, argued that he had the best chance of unifying the
traumatized Conservative Party. He said Heseltine was handicapped
by deep anger among some legislators and party activists over Mrs.
Thatcher's departure.
   ``There is a danger of a polarized result with the right wing
clustering around him (Major) ... and the left wing clustering
around Michael Hesetline,'' said Hurd. ``If that were to happen,
then I think there would be a danger of the quarrelling
continuing.''
   Heseltine, in a series of radio and television interviews
Sunday, argued that he has shown the same steely nerve that Mrs.
Thatcher displayed in 1975 when she ousted Edward Heath as party
leader. The Tories were then in opposition.
   ``Mrs. Thatcher and I have that characteristic of independence,
some people call it guts,'' said Heseltine. ``When you believe
somthing is right you do it.''
   But he acknowledged, ``There are people who are cross with me,
and I understand that.''
   Mrs. Thatcher, prime minister for 11{ years, withdrew Thursday
after she failed to get a big enough majority to stop Heseltine's
challenge. With her husband, Denis, she spent the weekend for the
last time at the prime minister's country residence outside London.
   A clutch of well-wishers cheered the 65-year-old prime minister
as she left the local church after a morning service.
   She has not publicly endorsed any candidate. But London's Sunday
Times, quoting ``friends'' of Mrs. Thatcher, reported she will vote
for Major, with Hurd as second choice.
   If none of the three candidates receives a simple majority
Tuesday, a third ballot will be held Thursday. Major and Heseltine
both say they believe they are rolling up the 187 votes needed.
   ``They must be getting worried,'' Major said Sunday after
Heseltine's campaign manager, legislator Neil McFarlane, said
claims of majority support by Major's camp were bogus.
   Heseltine challenged Mrs. Thatcher after her deputy prime
minister, Sir Geoffrey Howe, resigned and delivered a scathing
attack on her combative stance with Britain's European Community
partners.
   Mrs. Thatcher was already in trouble over the economy and a
unpopular new local government tax, the poll tax, which Hesetline
has pledged to review. He has the advantage of being the only one
in the Cabinet not associated with the tax.
   The polls in Sunday's newspapers suggested the Conservative
Party, which had trailed the Labor Party for the last 16 months of
Mrs. Thatcher's leadership, would be up to 13 points ahead under
Heseltine and about 4-6 points ahead under Major in elections.
   ``I've brought about a transformation in the Conservative
Party's fortunes,'' Heseltine declared Sunday.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0038 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 1349EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-Churchill     11-25 0362</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Churchill,0421</SECOND>
<HEAD>Winston Churchill, Grandson of Prime Minister, Visits Troops</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf Rdp</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto DHA4</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By EDITH M. LEDERER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>IN EASTERN SAUDI ARABIA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Winston Churchill, grandson of
Britain's great wartime prime minister, paid a visit to the British
troops in the Saudi desert - but jokingly admitted it wasn't his
own finest hour.
   When he introduced himself to a British tank crewman as Winston
Churchill, the Conservative lawmaker told photographers, the
disbelieving soldier responded sarcastically: ``I'm Rommel.''
   Gen. Erwin Rommel, the legendary ``Desert Fox,'' led Germany's
Afrika Korp in World War II.
   The younger Churchill, in Saudi Arabia as part of a 14-member
parliamentary delegation, rode in a Challenger tank named for his
grandfather and visited the former prime minister's old regiment,
the Queen's Royal Irish Hussars.
   The elder Churchill was no stranger to the desert - he fought in
the Khartoum campaign in Sudan in the late 1800s.
   At a news conference in a camouflage tent, Churchill said peace
in the Persian Gulf depended on Iraqi President Saddam Hussein. He
said the multinational force should not leave the gulf until
Saddam's weapons of mass destruction are eliminated.
   ``We're not only talking about the withdrawal of Iraqi forces
from Kuwait. We're talking about getting rid of Iraq's budding
nuclear and existing chemical and biological weapons and long-range
delivery systems,'' he said.
   Michael Mates, head of the delegation, said he would tell
Parliament that that British morale is high and troops are ready to
fight if need be.
   ``We have been able to assure them with absolute certainty that
there will be no change in policy because the entire government is
behind us, as is the opposition, as are all parties,'' he said.
   Britain said last week it would nearly double its force in the
gulf region to 30,000 troops. That would make its contingent the
second-largest in the multinational force, after that of the United
States.
   The delegation is to meet Saudi Arabia's King Fahd on Monday and
return to Britain on Tuesday.
   Fahd on Sunday praised outgoing Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher
for the warm relations between the two countries during her years
in power. Mrs. Thatcher announced last week she would quit,
following a rebellion in the ranks of her party.
   In a statement, Fahd praised Mrs. Thatcher's ``firm stand''
against Iraqi agression. Mrs. Thatcher's party has said Britain's
gulf policy will not change with the change in leadership.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0039 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 1351EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-HubbleTrouble     11-25 0481</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Hubble Trouble,0559</SECOND>
<HEAD>Panel to Blame NASA and Company For Hubble Flaw, Official Says</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HARTFORD, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   NASA and the manufacturer share the blame
for a flawed mirror that prevents the $1.5 billion Hubble Space
Telescope from focusing clearly, a member of an investigatory panel
said.
   The NASA panel's final report on the flawed telescope will
criticize both the space agency and the Perkin-Elmer Corp., said
John Mangus, head of the optics branch of the National Aeronautics
and Space Administration's space technology division. The report is
to be released Tuesday.
   Mangus said the flaws in the manufacture of the 94{-inch
telescope in 1980 and 1981 can be partly traced to the same
management climate that led to the fatal explosion of the space
shuttle Challenger in 1986.
   In both cases, he said, engineers were discouraged from bringing
potential problems to the attention of their superiors.
   ``The culture has to be encouraged where you don't shoot the
messenger,'' he said in a Hartford Courant story published Sunday.
   ``People don't like bad news, but what they like worse is not to
be told about the problems. I know it has occurred on many of
NASA's projects.''
   An investigation into the Challenger explosion that killed seven
crew members found that NASA ignored evidence of problems with
O-rings sealing the joints of the shuttle's solid-fuel rocket
boosters. Investigators faulted NASA for weak quality control and
found that, under intense schedule pressure, engineers sometimes
failed to report problems to managers.
   The immediate cause of the Hubble flaw was a technician's
mistake, but program managers approved the quality-control program
that allowed the mistake to escape detection, the investigatory
board concluded.
   ``NASA certainly had the overall management responsibility,''
Mangus said. ``They did not have the management system in place to
penetrate far enough into the system - otherwise this probably
would not have happened.''
   Board members would not release the report, but Mangus and other
members told the newspaper that the report also says:
   - Mirror-testing that was done relied too heavily on a single
instrument, which had been assembled improperly. Relatively simple
``sanity checks'' should have done to make sure the
mirror-polishing system was working properly.
   - There was too little contact between those working on the
mirror and NASA project supervisors who could have understood the
test results.
   - Quality-control inspectors lacked the expertise in optics to
understand results of some tests that showed a flaw in the mirror.
   The Hubble telescope was launched with the space shuttle April
24, and the focusing flaw was disclosed June 27. The flaw will be
corrected during a 1993 space shuttle mission.
   The mirror is flawed because the principal optical instrument
used to test it and measure the progress of the polishing had been
assembled incorrectly by technicians working at Perkin-Elmer's
optical division, which now is Hughes Danbury Optical Systems.
   Despite the flaw, NASA scientists have been increasingly pleased
with the telescope's observations, which are better than can be
made from instruments on Earth because the atmosphere doesn't
interfere.
   NASA last week released new photographs of Saturn, showing
details of an enormous atmospheric storm. The Hubble also has been
able to photograph individual stars that exist in clusters,
enabling the stars to be studied separately for the first time.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0040 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 1425EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-India-Punjab 1stLd-Writethru a0614 11-25 0316</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-India-Punjab, 1st Ld-Writethru, a614,0362</SECOND>
<HEAD>Sikh Gunmen Kill 16 People In a Punjab Town, Police Kill 9</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 7 grafs to UPDATE with Hindu soldiers among those
killed, 18 wounded in shopping center, neighborhood attacks. Pickup
7th pvs, `Bhatti said...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By DEEPAK SHARMA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>AMRITSAR, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Sikh gunmen on Sunday raided a shopping
center and a residential district in a Punjab city, killing at
least 16 people and wounding 18, police said. A senior police
officer blamed separatist Sikhs for the slayings.
   Elsewhere in the state, Sikh gunmen killed four others in
separate attacks.
   Police, battling the separatists, killed nine suspected
militants in separate incidents, the United News of India reported.
   Sikh radicals have killed an average of 16 people a day in
Punjab in the last two weeks in ambushes, bombings and bus attacks,
according to police officials.
   Since Jan. 1, the militants have killed 2,955 people in the rich
farming state where they want to establish an independent nation
for members of their faith.
   Among the dead in the city of Jalandhar on Sunday were two
vacationing Hindu soldiers. Also, a physician and three patients
were killed when the gunmen sprayed bullets at the shopping center
where the clinic is located.
   ``It is really tragic, innocent people were killed,'' said the
city's depurty inspector-general of police, D.R. Bhatti. Police
said at least 18 people were wounded in the Jalandhar attacks.
   Bhatti said about six gunmen hijacked a car and fired
indiscriminately at a shopping center. Their next target was a
residential district. The group later abandoned the first car and
hijacked another one to escape, Bhatti said.
   ``They opened fire at least at six places,'' Bhatti said.
   Jalandhar, a city of 1.7 million people, is about 60 miles east
of Amritsar.
   Sikhs have a slight majority over Hindus in Punjab, which
adjoins Haryana on the east and Pakistan on the west.
   Nationwide Sikhs make up only 2 percent of India's 880 million
people. Sikh separatists launched their campaign in 1982, claiming
political and economic discrimination by Hindus who comprise 82
percent of the national population.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0041 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 1439EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-Kuwait     11-25 0240</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Kuwait,0263</SECOND>
<HEAD>Former Governor Reported Wounded in Attack</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf Rdp</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DHAHRAN, Saudi Arabia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Kuwaiti gunmen have wounded an
Iraqi official who served briefly as governor of the occupied
emirate, a spokesman for the exiled Kuwaiti government said Sunday.
   There was no immediate Iraqi confirmation of the Kuwaiti
account, which was also reported Sunday by newspapers in Bahrain
and Qatar. The Qatari report said the official, Ali Hassan Majeed,
was killed.
   Abdel-Razzaq Saqer, a spokesman for the exiled government's
Kuwait Information Office in Dhahran, cited recently arriving
Kuwaitis as the sources of his report.
   Saqer quoted the escapees as saying a number of resistance
fighters burst into Majeed's office in Kuwait and shot him in the
shoulder, wounding but not killing him.
   He had no further information. Majeed was known for leading the
brutal repression of Kurds in northern Iraq.
   The Bahraini daily Al-Ayam said Majeed was attacked near his
accommodation at the Kuwait Hilton Hotel and sustained injuries in
his shoulder.
   The Qatari newspaper Al-Sharq, quoting an unidentified Kuwaiti
who recently fled the country, said three of the resistance men
ambushed him outside a Kuwaiti home he had seized for his use.
   He was flown to Baghdad in an Iraqi helicopter but apparently
died on the way because of his serious wounds, the report said.
   Majeed was appointed governor by Iraqi President Saddam Hussein
after the Aug. 2 invasion and Iraqi annexation of Kuwait. Earlier
this month, Saddam issued a decree naming Aziz Saleh No'man as the
new governor, replacing Majeed.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0042 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 1440EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Mother-Trial     11-25 0233</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mother-Trial,0266</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mother Goes On Trial After Refusing Medical Help For Son Who Died</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Annita in 2nd graf is cq</NOTE>
<DATELINE>AMITE, La. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A woman who believes in faith healing and
refused on religious grounds to get medical help for her son before
he died of leukemia goes on trial Monday on a charge of negligent
homicide.
   Annita Williamson, 43, was arrested after her 5-year-old son,
Loren, died on June 2, 1989. She is free on $25,000 bail.
   Ms. Williamson is scheduled to be tried before a jury in 21st
Judicial District Court.
   Ms. Williamson, one of 150 members of the Oak Grove Church of
God, told Tangipahoa Parish sheriff's deputies at the time of her
arrest that she believed prayer would heal the child.
   Neighbors told deputies that red splotches had covered the boy's
body for several weeks.
   Coroner Vincent Cefalu said the child died of congestive heart
failure resulting from untreated acute lymphocytic leukemia.
   Last month, Ms. Williamson turned down a plea bargain offered by
District Attorney Duncan Kemp in which she would be put on
probation in return for pleading no contest and promising to seek
medical help for any of her living children should they become ill.
Ms. Williamson, a widow, has three other children.
   Ed Wilson, pastor of Oak Grove Church of God, the church Ms.
Williamson attends, described the church as a fundamentalist
religious group.
   ``We're not a cult,'' Wilson said days after the boy's death.
``We're really mainline religious Christians with convictions that
many people had 100 years ago.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0043 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 1441EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SouthAfrica     11-25 0284</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-South Africa,0309</SECOND>
<HEAD>Eleven Protesters Wounded in Clash With Police</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JOHANNESBURG, South Africa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Police fired tear gas and
shotguns at stone-throwing protesters in a black township near Cape
Town, wounding seven people, including a young boy, according to a
news report Sunday.
   Four policemen were also injured in Saturday's clash with
protesters in the Montana township, about 20 miles northeast of
Cape Town.
   Residents were protesting the opening of a new township civic
center, and had received permission to demonstrate in a designated
area, the independent South African Press Association reported.
   But after the opening ceremony, protesters left the designated
area to confront departing guests, the news agency said. When
police told them to disperse, some protesters began hurling stones,
the agency reported.
   Police opened fire with tear gas and shotguns, wounding six
adults and a boy believed about 4-years-old in the legs, the agency
said. Eleven people, including the wounded adults, were arrested,
Press Association reported.
   The injured police officers were struck by stones. Three police
vehicles and other cars were damaged, the news agency said.
   Many residents of black townships oppose local leaders,
considering them collaborators with the white-led government and
the apartheid system of racial segregation.
   African National Congress leader Nelson Mandela told a rally
Sunday that security forces were responsible for much of the
bloodshed in recent months in black townships near Johannesburg.
   ``They find it easy to spill the blood of black people,''
Mandela told about 15,000 people at a stadium in the Tembisa
township northeast of the city. ``I appeal to them to leave their
guns and bullets at their barracks.''
   He and other black leaders have accused security forces of
instigating the township violence to destabilize the black
opposition movement. The government and police have denied the
charge.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0044 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 1523EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People     11-25 0522</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People,0659</SECOND>
<HEAD>People in the News</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY44</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NASHVILLE, Tenn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   When country singer K.T. Oslin isn't
touring, she finds life in the Music City a restful alternative, if
a little slow.
   And the 48-year-old Oslin, who spent more than 20 years in New
York City, says the biggest cities can seem quite small where love
is concerned.
   ``New York City has 8 million people and women there say,
`There's no men here, I can't meet anybody.'
   ``In a town of 1,800 they say, `There's no men here.' Of course,
there it's closer to it that there ain't no men there,'' she said
in a recent interview with The Tennessean.
   Oslin, best known for the hits ``80s Ladies'' and ``I'll Always
Come Back,'' was born in Crossitt, Ark., and reared near Mobile,
Ala.
   A Nashville resident since 1988, Oslin calls the city lovely but
says it can be a little slow for her tastes.
   ``It seems to be a very married town, and that distrubs me. I
was never so aware of being single as I am here.''
   ---
   BOSTON (AP) - Gov. Michael S. Dukakis plans a trip to the other
side of he world when he leaves office in January.
   Dukakis said he and his wife, Kitty, will travel to Australia
and Hawaii for 4{ months. The two will lecture, study public health
policy and relax.
   Dukakis has accepted a visiting professorship at the University
of Hawaii for the spring semester and will speak on health policy,
elective office and public service. The outgoing governor says he
has no plans for a full-time job after May, but may teach
part-time.
   ``We're both anxious to try a life that is less structured, less
scheduled,'' Dukakis said in an interview published Sunday.
   Both Dukakises have signed with an agent to book speaking
engagements.
   Dukakis, the defeated Democratic presidential candidate, did not
seek another term as Massachussetts governor. He will be succeeded
by Republic William Weld in January.
   ---
   BEVERLY HILLS, Calif. (AP) - There may be a recession on, but
don't tell that to the Hollywood set. They're out in force,
shopping for Christmas.
   Celebrity letter-spinner Vanna White of TV's ``Wheel of
Fortune'' and actress Jill St. John were among the well-heeled
shoppers at the posh Fred Hayman boutique on Rodeo Drive.
   Television and film stars were as common as tourists in the
fashionable boutique on Saturday, according to Hayman publicist Lee
Solters.
   Solters said St. John was in, buying presents for her first
Christmas with husband Robert Wagner, whom she married in May.
   ``Vanna White bought a cocktail suit for her round of parties
when she goes to Aspen for the holidays,'' Solters said, ``And
sweaters too.''
   Asked about the economic slump and the prospect of tight-fisted
shoppers, Solters said there was no evidence of that on Rodeo
Drive. More than 5,000 people visited Fred Hayman's on Friday and
Saturday, a record for the store.
   ``Today, Mr. Hayman said he was more than delighted,'' Solters
said.
   ---
</TEXT>
<NOTE>Eds: Also moving on sports wires.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>KINGSTON, Jamaica (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Grace Jackson, the Olympic silver
medalist and one of Jamaica's fastest sprinters, was married during
the weekend to Hugh Small, Minister of Industry Commerce and
Production.
   Jackson won the Silver medal in the 200-meter dash in the 1988
Olympics in Korea, second to American Florence Griffith Joyner.
   It was the third marriage for Small, a 49-year-old lawyer, and
the first for Jackson, 29, who was Jamaica's Athlete-of-the-Year in
1986.
   The 150 guests at Saturday's wedding were headed by Prime
Minister Michael Manley and included members of his Cabinet, the
diplomatic and consular corps and several prominent athletes.
   Jackson said she plans to continue her athletic career for a few
more years and will be running in the 1992 Olympics in Barcelona,
Spain.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0045 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 1513EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Lebanon-Israel 1stLd-Writethru a0628 11-25 0587</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lebanon-Israel, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0628,0708</SECOND>
<HEAD>Suicide Bomber Targets Israeli Patrol</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 10 grafs to UPDATE with video of woman released;
Pickup 6th, `Ms. Ghanem...'</NOTE>
<HEAD>With AM-Israel-Attacks, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RIMA SALAMEH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BEIRUT, Lebanon (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A woman suicide bomber detonated a
handbag packed with explosives near an Israeli patrol in southern
Lebanon Sunday. A pro-Syrian group said 12 Israeli soldiers also
died but Israel said only two were injured.
   The blast occurred hours after an Israeli gunboat sank a dinghy
off southern Lebanon, killing five guerrillas, the Israeli army
said in Jerusalem. A Palestinian group said four of the guerrillas
were missing but that one managed to swim ashore. It said the
guerrillas had planned a raid in Israel.
   The escalating violence sharpened fears that southern Lebanon is
becoming a flashpoint as President Elias Hrawi tries to assert
government authority and end Lebanon's 15-year-old civil war.
   The government has no troops in southern Lebanon, where Israel
controls a self-designated 440-square-mile security zone. But
Hrawi's government has said it will seek to end Israel's occupation
once it completes plans to get Moslem and Christian militias out of
Beirut.
   Communiques issued by the Syrian Social Nationalist Party
identified the woman as Fadwa Hassan Ghanem.
   They said Ms. Ghanem concealed the bag rigged with 55 pounds of
TNT under a black chador she wore. The chador is the traditional
feminine dress of Shiite Moslem fundamentalists, and covers the
woman from head to toe.
   Beirut television stations later broadcast a 30-second videotape
in which Ms. Ghanem said, ``I am going to give my life for the
cause of battling the Zionist enemy out of our land.''
   The stations said the poor-quality tape was provided by the
group. It showed Ms. Ghanem dressed in camouflage fatigues talking
into the camera surrounded by party posters and other
paraphernalia.
   ``I ask all of you to follow my example. Do not shy away from
fighting the Zionist usurper,'' she said in a shaky voice.
   She then stood up, saluted with her right arm and shouted ``Long
Live Syria!'' - her party's motto.
   Ms. Ghanem detonated her bomb-laden handbag as an Israeli patrol
of 12 soldiers with two tanks was crossing the road between Arnoun
Kfar Tibnit and Arnoun in the Israeli security zone, one communique
said.
   ``All soldiers of the patrol were killed and she was martyred,''
it said.
   But an Israeli army spokesman said only two soldiers were on
patrol, checking a road near Beaufort castle, when ``a female
terrorist ran at them, strapped with an explosive charge. She
exploded herself, wounding the two soldiers, one in the neck and
one in the feet.''
   Beaufort, a crusader castle that was a Palestinian guerrilla
stronghold in Israel's 1982 Lebanon war, is three miles north of
the border.
   Dr. Mickey Wiener, deputy head of the Rambam Hospital in Haifa
where the wounded soldiers were evacuated by helicopter, said they
suffered ear injuries from the blast and superficial shrapnel
wounds. He described the soldiers' condition as ``light to
moderate.''
   The Syrian Social Nationalist Party is part of a coalition of
Lebanese leftist and pro-Syrian Palestinian factions engaged in a
guerrilla war aimed at dislodging Israel from the border enclave.
   The party advocates the creation of a greater Syria by merging
Syria, Lebanon, Jordan, pre-Israel Palestine, Iraq, Kuwait and
Cyprus.
   Ms. Ghanem's attack was the 23rd suicide bombing in the Israeli
security zone since 1985, when Israel carved it out as a buffer
against cross-border guerrilla attacks. Eight of the bombings were
staged by women.
   Meanwhile, the Popular Front for the Liberation of
Palestine-General Command said Sunday its guerrillas fought a
two-hour sea battle with Israeli gunboats overnight off the coastal
town of Sadiyat, 12 miles south of Beirut.
   A communique read over the Voice of the People radio station
said four men were missing and that a fifth managed to swim ashore.
Earlier the group had said that three of its fighters were killed.
   The Israeli army said in a statement that a navy patrol on
routine duty spotted the guerrilla boat. ``Battle ensued whereupon
the terrorist boat was destroyed and five terrorists killed,'' it
said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0046 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 1526EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-NeilBush     11-25 0463</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Neil Bush,0543</SECOND>
<HEAD>Documents Reveal Bush Role In Silverado Committee That Helped
Homebuilder</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DENVER (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Neil Bush served on the board of a Silverado
savings and loan affiliate that helped a Denver homebuilder evade
securities laws, according to federal documents quoted in a
newspaper Sunday.
   The president's son already is awaiting an administrative law
judge's ruling on whether he was guilty of conflicts of interest
while serving on the board of the failed Denver savings and loan.
The failure of Silverado in December 1988 is expected to cost
taxpayers $1 billion.
   The Denver Post reported Sunday that it had obtained federal
Securities and Exchange Commission documents about Bush's role on a
management committee of Silverado-Elektra Ventures Ltd., the land
development arm of Silverado.
   Silverado-Elektra was a joint venture between Silverado Banking,
Savings and Loan, and Elektra Brokerage Co., a Denver real estate
firm. S&amp;Ls spun off land companies after federal deregulation of
the industry in the early 1980s allowed thrifts to invest directly
in real estate.
   Bush has declined to comment on his role as a board member. His
attorney, James Nesland, said Bush served on the panelfrom late
1985 or early 1986 until 1988.
   Bush's actions on the oversight committee may or may not become
part of a $200 million negligence lawsuit filed by the Federal
Deposit Insurance Corp. against Bush and other Silverado directors
and officers, said FDIC spokesman David Barr.
   ``We're reserving that comment until it comes to trial,'' Barr
said. ``That doesn't mean it's going to be an issue at the trial.''
   The documents show the committee approved Silverado-Elektra's
role as a phony buyer of some Houston residential lots from MDC
Holdings Inc., a Denver homebuilder, the newspaper reported.
   The SEC documents indicated the Silverado committee knew
Silverado-Elektra was to be a straw buyer. Straw buyers typically
are employed to disguise property ownership, and do not use their
own money.
   ``During the course of its internal review, representatives of
the party (Silverado-Elektra) that purchased the residential lots
from MDC stated that they would not have purchased the lots had
they not felt assured of selling them to the third party,'' the
documents said.
   The Post said that previous testimony by then-MDC president
David Mandarich showed the homebuilder wanted to sell several
hundred lots in the depressed Houston market to Bellamah Homes of
New Mexico. MDC also wanted to buy lots near Castle Rock from a
Bellamah Homes subsidiary.
   Because MDC is a publicly traded company, federal securities
laws prevent it from exchanging properties with Bellamah and then
recording a profit on the sale of the Houston lots.
   The SEC documents show MDC asked Silverado-Elektra to buy the
Houston lots for $3.7 million. The same day, MDC contracted to buy
the Castle Rock land from Bellamah Homes, and three days later,
Silverado-Elektra sold the Houston lots to Bellamah homes, the
documents showed.
   The SEC disciplined MDC in September 1989 for its handling of
eight real estate transactions between 1985 and 1987, including
employing Silverado-Elektra as a ``straw buyer'' and booking
profits on the Houston sale. MDC neither admitted nor denied guilt
to the SEC, but agreed to make changes in some of its accounting
practices.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0047 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 1527EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brite-ChristmasLights     11-25 0251</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brite-Christmas Lights,0291</SECOND>
<HEAD>Chicken King's Holiday Display Going Up With Inmates' Help</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BATON ROUGE, La. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The chicken king's Christmas display is
going up at the state Capitol this year, and about 140 prison
inmates are playing lighting elves.
   The inmates are working in shifts to put up 1.5 million lights
on the state Capitol grounds for Al Copeland's display. Copeland is
the founder of Popees Fried Chicken &amp; Biscuits chain and last year
bought Church's Fried Chicken.
   For the past few years, Copeland has put up the display at his
headquarters in suburban New Orleans. Before that, Copeland's
lights blazed around his home in the New Orleans suburb of
Metairie. But after complaints from neighbors sparked a court case,
the state Supreme Court said in 1985 that the display was too big
and attracted too many gawkers to keep at home.
   ``It normally takes me about 60 days to do this and I use about
60 people. But ... they're giving me 16 days to do it,'' said
Robert Theriot, who has overseen installation of the display for
the past half-dozen years.
   Copeland went looking for a larger site this year, and state
Agriculture Commissioner Bob Odom suggested that Copeland light up
the trees at the Capitol to honor U.S. soldiers in Saudi Arabia.
   The inmates climbed ladders and scaffolds to deck the Capitol's
old oaks, junipers, magnolias, azaleas and other trees and shrubs
with lights.
   ``It's a real challenge,'' said Megan Becker, Copeland's
designer and decorator. ``It's different. But the trees speak for
themselves. Each is a work of art. You just string lights around
them.''
   The switch is to be thrown Thursday.
   ``It will be finished. It will,'' said Theriot.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0048 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 1528EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Soviet-Politics     11-25 0584</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Politics,0689</SECOND>
<HEAD>Newspaper Urges Kremlin to Move Slowly on Union Treaty</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BRIAN FRIEDMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A newspaper on Sunday urged the Kremlin to move
slowly on the new Union Treaty, saying that only the Soviet Union's
four Central Asian republics appeared willing to support it now.
   The treaty, which would redefine the central government's
relationship with the 15 republics, was proposed by President
Mikhail S. Gorbachev on Saturday to hold the nation together as the
``Union of Sovereign Soviet Republics.'' It would give the
republics control over virtually all affairs except defense.
   But the newspaper, Komsomolskaya Pravda, said that if the
central government presses for an early signing of the document, it
will lose the republics of Latvia, Lithuania, Estonia and Georgia.
   The newspaper also said it was unclear whether Russia, the
Ukraine, Byelorussia and Moldavia would support it.
   Boris N. Yeltsin, president of the Russian republic, said last
week Russia would not sign the treaty unless its ``real
sovereignty'' could be assured and ownership issues over its
bountiful natural resources are resolved.
   The independent Postfactum news agency on Sunday quoted Mikhail
Goryn, a member of the Ukraine's nationalist movement Rukh, as
urging that committees be formed at every plant in the republic to
denounce the treaty.
   In addition to those republics mentioned by Komsomolskaya
Pravda, Armenia has said it would not sign. The participation of
others is in doubt because of drives for sovereignty or
independence in all republics except Kirgizia.
   Komsomolskaya Pravda said that the Central Asian republics -
Kirgizia, Tadzhikistan, Uzbekistan and Turkmenia - ``seem to be the
sole supporters.''
   Central Asia is the Soviet Union's poorest and most politically
conservative region.
   Many republics have been bypassing the Kremlin and signing
separate agreements with each other governing trade, cultural and
political ties.
   Komsomolskaya Pravda took note of these ``bilateral treaties,''
saying they further complicate the picture and ``shift the signing
of a new Union Treaty to a still longer perspective.''
   In what could be regarded as the most overly optimistic
assessment of the document's chances, the labor newspaper Trud
quoted Politburo member and Communist Party ideology chief
Alexander S. Dzasokhov as saying the Union Treaty is supported ``by
at least 11 to 12 republics.''
   Yet even with that upbeat conclusion, Dzasokhov told the
newspaper, ``I think that we should use our patience and wait. I
see no other way out.'' He also said that under the treaty, the
republics would be sovereign ``in the broadest sense of the word.''
   The blueprint was sent to the legislatures of the union and the
15 republics for approval.
   ``Not only the Baltic states, but also many Soviet republics,
will not sign this treaty,'' Lithuanian President Vytautas
Landsbergis said Saturday in a televised speech to his republic.
   Komsomolskaya Pravda, considered a radical newspaper, generally
praised the draft treaty as a balanced and sensible document that
considers the nation's political situation. The central government
does not set its requirements too high, so as not to scare away the
tentative members of the new union.
   The newspaper noted that the draft contained potential
obstacles, ``which are bound to raise questions and evoke heated
debate.''
   One provision says the ``powers of the union shall not be
changed unless all the republics agree.'' Komsomolskaya Pravda
identified that section as a problem, in an apparent
acknowledgement of the difficulty of getting a consensus among the
diverse regions in the nation of 285 million people.
   Another stumbling block is a part that says the union shall only
delegate some of its powers to one or several republics if agreed
upon by the rest of the republics, the newspaper said.
   The treaty says the union would be ``voluntary'' but does not
identify who in each republic - voters or legislators - would
decide whether to join.
   Each republic, ``as a sovereign state, has full state powers
over its territory. Treaty participants regard the Soviet Union as
a sovereign federative state formed as a result of the republics'
voluntary union,'' the draft says.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0049 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 1551EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Israel-Attacks 1stLd-Writethru a0637 11-25 0685</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel-Attacks, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0637,0863</SECOND>
<HEAD>Gunman Kills Four Israelis On Egyptian Border</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS throughout to UPDATE with further comment from bus
passengers; EDITS to trim. No pickup.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto CAI1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ARIEH O'SULLIVAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>EILAT, Israel (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A lone gunman slipped across the Egyptian
border Sunday and ambushed a bus and three military vehicles,
killing four Israelis and wounding 27, the army said.
   The attack was the third from Arab territory in two days. At
least four Palestinian guerrillas were killed and two Israeli
soldiers injured in incidents in Israel's self-declared security
zone in southern Lebanon and off the Mediterranean coast.
   The dead in the border attack, three soldiers and a civilian bus
driver, were shot on a road running along the Israeli-Egyptian
border about 15 miles northwest of the Israeli Red Sea resort of
Eilat, the army said. It said most of the wounded were civilian
workers at an Israeli air base.
   The gunman, who used an automatic rifle and was described as
wearing a uniform, escaped back into Egypt. He was shot by an
Israeli security guard and trailing blood, the army said.
   An Israeli army patrol chased him, firing, but did not pursue
him across the frontier, the army said.
   A senior Egyptian security source in Cairo said an Egyptian
border policeman stationed in the area had been arrested as the
suspected assailant.
   Israel army radio said the assailant's blood-stained flak jacket
with ``Allah'' written on it was found in the area. It said the
attack was claimed by the Moslem fundamentalist group Islamic Holy
War-Jerusalem in a statement issued in Amman, Jordan.
   Israeli and Egyptian reports said the attacker was armed with
the Soviet-designed Kalashnikov assault rifle.
   Karen Golan, 12, who was on the bus, said: ``I was sitting next
to my father, near the back door. Suddenly we saw a bus half on the
road, half in the wadi, and an army van.
   ``A man came out as though he was flagging us down for help. The
driver slowed down and stopped and then the man opened fire.
   ``My father grabbed me and told me to put my hands around my
head and get on the floor.''
   She was slightly injured above the eye by fragments. Her father
was unhurt.
   Israel television showed a woman named Rachel Fishbein, telling
a relative on the telephone that she had seen a passenger's fingers
blown off by bullets. ``We just lay there. Don't ask what
happened,'' she sobbed.
   Prime Minister Yitzhak Shamir called on Egypt to capture and
punish the assailant, and prevent further attacks.
   Egyptian Foreign Minister Esmat Abdel-Meguid called the attack
``very regrettable'' and said he hoped it would not affect
relations between the two countries.
   Egypt and Israel have been at peace since 1979, and the border
is less heavily defended than other Israeli frontiers.
   In another attack Sunday, a Lebanese woman carrying explosives
killed herself and injured two Israeli soldiers in Israel's
self-proclaimed security zone in souther Lebanon, army reports
said. The Syrian Socialist Nationalist Party, claimed
responsibility for the attack and said 12 Israeli soldiers also
were killed.
   On Saturday, a navy gunboat attacked a dinghy off the Lebanese
coast that officials said was headed to attack Israel. The five
guerrillas aboard were killed, the army said. The Popular Front for
the Liberation of Palestine-General Command, a radical PLO faction,
said Sunday its guerrillas were on board the boat. It said four
were missing but that one swam to shore.
   Also Sunday, a pipe bomb exploded at a bus stop in the Jewish
sector of Jerusalem but no one was injured, police said.
   In the attack at the Egyptian border, a brigadier general
identified only by his first name, Dubi, said the assailant ``lay
in wait on the roadside.'' The assailant's first two victims were
soldiers driving alone in military vehicles, the army said. The
third was driving an empty bus and apparently thought an accident
had occurred, stopped and was shot at close range.
   Finally, the attacker fired on a red-and-white bus of the Egged
national bus company that was carrying civilian workers at a nearby
air base. A security guard on board was wounded but then managed to
shoot the attacker, Dubi said.
   ``We found signs of blood showing that he was hit. I think this
prevented a heavier tragedy,'' he said. ``The terrorist apparently
intended to board the bus and take it over.''
   Bus passenger Rachel Amor said the man did not look Arab, and
wore a khaki-colored uniform like that of Israeli forces. He was
``putting ammunition into his gun,'' she said.
   It was the second such attack this year. On Feb. 4, gunmen
ambushed an Israeli tour bus in Egypt, killing nine Israelis and
wounding 20. The Egyptian government says the gunmen have since
been arrested, and has hinted they are Palestinian.
   An army spokesman said of the 27 wounded Sunday, one soldier and
eight civilians were hospitalized in Eilat and the Negev desert
town of Beersheba. News reports said their wounds were minor to
moderate.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0050 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 1553EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Italy-Plane     11-25 0116</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Italy-Plane,0111</SECOND>
<HEAD>Five Die When Small Plane Crashes in Northern Italy</HEAD>
<DATELINE>AMELIA, Italy (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A tourist plane crashed in a wooded area of
central Italy on Sunday, killing all five people on board, police
said.
   A man gathering mushrooms saw the plane crash and alerted
authorities. Police found the five bodies at the crash site, they
said.
   The nationalities of the victims were not immediately known,
said a police officer in Amelia, speaking on condition of
anonymity.
   The aircraft, an SIAI-208, was traveling from Rome to Perugia
when it crashed in Amelia, 60 miles north of Rome.
   Police were investigating the cause of the crash.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0051 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 1604EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Egypt-Attacks     11-25 0556</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Egypt-Attacks,0659</SECOND>
<HEAD>Peace Between Israel and Egypt Has Always Been An Uneasy One</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Israel-Attacks, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By NEJLA SAMMAKIA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CAIRO, Egypt (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Egypt and Israel signed a peace treaty in
1979, but even if the two governments are no longer officially
enemies, the people of the neighboring nations are far from
friends.
   That was underscored Sunday when a lone gunman slipped across
the Egyptian border Sunday and fired an automatic rifle at a bus
and three military vehicles, killing four Israelis and wounding 27.
   The Egyptian interior ministry said it had arrested a border
policeman suspected as the gunman.
   Egypt officially condemned the attack. Foreign Minister Esmat
Abdel-Meguid called it ``very regrettable'' and said he hoped it
would not affect relations between the two countries.
   But analysts say incidents like this one reflect popular anger
in Egypt over the Palestinian conflict, heightened by a sense that
the conflict is being overshadowed by the Persian Gulf crisis.
   ``There is a growing frustration with the way the Israelis are
treating Palestinians in the occupied territories,'' said Tahseen
Bashir, a former spokesman for late President Anwar Sadat and a
professor at the Foreign Ministry's school for diplomats.
   Bashir echoed an often-stated Arab opinion that West is unfair
in not viewing Israel's occupation of the West Bank and Gaza Strip
the way it views Iraq's occupation of Kuwait. He also said many
Egyptians view Israel as being at least partly responsible for such
attacks.
   ``Individual incidents will occur and are symptoms of the wrong
policy Israel is pursuing,'' Bashir said.
   Sunday's attack took place on a road running along the
Israeli-Egyptian border about 15 miles northwest of the Israeli Red
Sea resort of Eilat, the Israeli army said.
   It was the third attack against Israel from Arab territory in
two days. At least four Palestinian guerrillas were killed and two
Israeli soldiers injured in incidents in Israel's self-declared
security zone in southern Lebanon and off the Mediterranean coast.
   In Amman, Jordan, an extremist Islamic group, Islamic Holy
War-Jerusalem, claimed responsibility for the Eilat attack. The
claim could not be verified.
   The organization was founded in the Israeli-occupied West Bank
in 1980 and has hundreds of followers throughout the Arab world. It
is financed by Libya and Iran.
   Islamic Holy War-Jeruslam identified the perpetrator as ``the
group of the martyred hero Suliman Khater.'' Khater was an Egyptian
border police officer who went berserk on Oct. 5, 1985 and killed
seven Israelis in the Sinai desert.
   He was sentenced to prison at hard labor, and four months after
the shooting the government announced he had hanged himself in a
Cairo prison hospital. Moslem fundamentalists, students and
opposition parties hailed him as a hero and martyr.
   The Eilat attack was the latest in a string of recent attacks on
Israeli targets involving Egyptian assailants or using Egypt as a
staging ground.
   On Feb. 4, gunmen ambushed a tour bus, killing nine vacationers
on the road between Cairo and the Suez Canal city of Ismailiya.
Interior Minister Abdel-Halim Moussa has hinted the gunmen, who
were arrested, are Palestinians.
   Last December, Israeli troops killed five heavily armed Arabs
who infiltrated from Egypt into Israel's Negev desert to allegedly
carry out an attack. There has been no more information on the
assailants, their nationalities or allegiance.
   Attacks since 1984 also included a number of shootings claimed
by an Egyptian terrorist organization, Egypt's Revolution,
allegedly financed by a son of Egypt's first president, Gamal
Abdel-Nasser.
   The group, currently under trial for the attacks, killed two
Israeli diplomats and wounded six Israelis and attempted to shoot
at American diplomats. It is regarded as being an Arab nationalist
organization with no ties to Molsem fundamentalists.
   Some of the defendents said in court they acted in protest of
the normalization of relations between Egypt and Israel.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0052 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 1612EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Bulgaria     11-25 0429</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bulgaria,0499</SECOND>
<HEAD>Embattled Premier Warns Against General Strike</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By VESELIN TOSHKOV</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SOFIA, Bulgaria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Premier Andrei Lukanov, under growing
pressure to step down in the face of political turmoil and economic
trouble, warned Sunday that a threatened strike would only make
things worse.
   The opposition trade union federation Podkrepa said it would go
ahead with a general strike on Monday if Lukanov does not resign by
then.
   In a televised statement Sunday evening, Lukanov called the
planned strike ``an extreme act,'' and said it could have serious
consequences.
   He urged Bulgarians ``not to support the adventurers who, in
their greed for power, are prepared to push Bulgaria onto the fatal
path of civic conflict.''
   The main trade union confederation said Sunday it would not back
the strike.
   The opposition alliance, Union of Democratic Forces, said it
would hold a rally Tuesday in support of the strike. A rally
planned for Sunday did not take place.
   The continuingeconomic decline and shortages of basic foods and
consumer goods have led to growing demands for Lukanov's
resignation. There were daily demonstrations against the government
over the past week.
   Lukanov and his government of former Communists narrowly
survived a no-confidence vote in Parliament on Friday. It capped
months of wrangling between the governing Socialists and the
opposition over how to revive the economy and end the political
stalemate.
   The Socialist Party, the successor to the former Communist
Party, won June elections.
   On Sunday, small groups of protesters marched through Sofia and
some tried to block streets as anti-government demonstrators had
done for an hour Saturday. Police patrolled, some in riot gear.
   ``God won't fill the shops, but the strike will certainly empty
them,'' Lukanov warned. Many staples are already rationed or not
available, and an energy crisis has led to periodic power cuts.
   Lukanov said the government had taken all legal measures to
ensure that transport, communications, medical services and
deliveries of basic goods would not be interrupted.
   In a separate television appearance, the leader of the Podkrepa
trade union, Konstantin Trenchev, rejected government claims that
the strike would be illegal because of its political nature.
   Trenchev said a government must resign if it cannot secure a
minimum standard of living for its population.
   Earlier, opposition and government leaders said they should talk
about forming a coalition. Lukanov appeared to concur, saying it
was necessary to ''find a formula for the cooperation between the
political forces in the next week.''
   Ivailo Trifonov of the president's office said on state radio
that neither of the two main political forces could govern alone
now.
   ``It is necessary that the Socialist Party and the Union of
Democratic Forces sit at the negotiating table as quickly as
possible to seek a way out'' of the crisis, he said.
   The Socialists hold 210 seats in Parliament. The opposition
Union of Democratic Forces has 144 seats.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0053 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 1621EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Obit-Galski     11-25 0124</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Galski,0118</SECOND>
<HEAD>Desider Galski, President Of Jewish Community, Killed In Car
Accident</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PRAGUE, Czechoslovakia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Desider Galski, a leader of the
Czechoslovak Jewish community, died in a car accident in Prague, a
friend of the family said Sunday. He was 69.
   The accident occurred Saturday night after Galski was driving
home from dinner, the friend said on condition of anonymity. Galski
was alone in the car at the time.
   The friend was not able to provide any further details of the
accident.
   Galski was president of the Jewish Community Council of the
Czech Lands. He had served as president from 1980-1987 and was
re-elcted after the November 1989 revolution that ousted
Communists from power.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0054 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 1636EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Poland-GdanskScene     11-25 0232</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Poland-Gdansk Scene,0265</SECOND>
<HEAD>Walesa Votes `Only for Danuta'</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Poland, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ANDRZEJ STYLINSKI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>GDANSK, Poland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Solidarity Chairman Lech Walesa, the
leading candidate in Poland's first popular presidential election
Sunday, joked with reporters that he only votes for his wife.
   A smiling Walesa walked to the polls after attending Mass with
his wife, Danuta, and six of their eight children at St. Stanislaw
Kostka Church in the Oliwa section of the northern port city of
Gdansk.
   He was asked for whom he would vote as he strolled to the voting
station 10 minutes from his house.
   ``I always vote for Danuta,'' he quipped. She smiled.
   Emerging from the station to applause from several dozen
onlookers, Walesa told a slightly different story: ``I voted for
the candidate who is supposed to win'' he said.
   Aides in Gdansk say Walesa had already begun removing some
personal objects from his office at Solidarity union headquarters
in anticipation of going to Belweder Palace, the seat of Polish
presidents in Warsaw, or at least retiring as union chairman.
Walesa has said he would leave the post if he loses the
presidential election.
   Walesa held the hands of two of his daughters, Anna and
Wiktoria, to and from church. After dropping them off at home, he
proceeded to the polls with Danuta and their 18-year-old son,
Slawek.
   ``I voted for my father. I had no choice, I didn't even think of
anyone else,'' the young Walesa said.
   ``My wish is that my father can fulfill all his dreams.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0055 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 1647EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Bush     11-25 0143</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bush,120</SECOND>
<HEAD>President Back at White House After 10-day Absence</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush returned to the White House
Sunday after a 10-day absence and got ready to head off to Mexico.
   Bush looked tired as he emerged with his wife Barbara from a
Marine One helicopter after a flight from Camp David.
   The Bushes spent an abbreviated weekend at the presidential
retreat after arriving home early Saturday from a week-long mission
to Europe and the Middle East, where they spent Thanksgiving with
U.S. troops in the Saudi desert.
   The president planned to depart Monday morning for Monterrey,
Mexico, and a two-day summit with Mexican President Carlos Salinas
de Gortari.
   Another major trip faces him next week. He will depart Sunday
night on a seven-day swing through five South American countries,
Brazil, Uruguay, Argentina, Chile and Venezuela.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0056 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 1707EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SriLanka     11-25 0399</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Sri Lanka,0465</SECOND>
<HEAD>Sri Lankan Rebels Capture Key Camp, 60 People Reported Dead</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PATRICK CRUEZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>COLOMBO, Sri Lanka (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Tamil militants captured a key
northern jungle camp from the government, leaving at least 60
people dead on both sides, officials said Sunday.
   A rebel spokesman claimed the guerrillas killed 100 soldiers
while overrunning the Manakulam camp, 160 miles north of Colombo,
on Friday. He said 30 rebels died.
   The spokesman, who was contacted by telephone in London,
identified himself only as Raju.
   Military officials claimed that soldiers killed 100 rebels, then
made a ``tactical withdrawal'' on Saturday. They said at least 30
soldiers were killed and 125 wounded by the rebel's mortar assault.
   The conflicting reports could not be immediately reconciled. The
two sides are known to have made exaggerated claims in the past
about each other's casualties.
   With the garrison's fall, the government controls only five
isolated and besieged military camps between Vavuniya, 25 miles
south of Manakulam, and Jaffna peninsula, the most northern point
of the island.
   The rest of the north and parts of eastern districts are
controlled by the Liberation Tigers of Tamil Eelam, the rebel group
that wants to set up an independent nation in the two predominantly
Tamil areas.
   Fierce fighting had been raging around Manakulam since Thursday
and the military claimed to have killed about 90 militants. But
residents in Vavuniya said they knew of only 20 rebels killed.
   Military officials said Saturday the rebel casualties were
inflicted during a counterattack Friday on a Tamil camp near the
garrison, but conceded that troops have not found any of the
bodies.
   On Sunday, military officials said 30 to 40 soldiers were killed
and 125 injured by mortar fire. The officials, who spoke on
condition of anonymity, said the mortars were packed with large
amounts of explosives and shrapnel.
   More than 500 soldiers were in the camp when it was attacked,
they said. A Defense Ministry statement said the troops were
fighting their way out of the jungles amid mortar attacks and heavy
automatic gunfire.
   A Tamil Tiger statement said its fighters ``smashed army
resistance and entered the strongly fortified camp triumphantly.''
The statement was faxed to news organizations in Colombo from the
rebels' London office.
   Tamil separatists, who have been fighting for independence since
1983, say their ethnic minority is discriminated against by
Sinhalese in jobs and education.
   Sinhalese make up 75 percent of Sri Lanka's 16 million people
and control the government and the military. Tamils make up 18
percent. Most Sinhalese live in the central and southern districts
of the country, an island off India's southern tip.
   More than 14,000 people have been killed in the 7-year-old
conflict.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0057 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 1711EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Britain-Hostage     11-25 0303</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Britain-Hostage,0359</SECOND>
<HEAD>Friends of British Hostage Demonstrate His Plight</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Supporters of John McCarthy, a British journalist
held hostage in Beirut, on Sunday marked his birthday by staging a
reconstruction of his prison ordeal.
   An actor sat in a mock-up of McCarthy's cell to show the
conditions he is believed to be enduring.
   Friends of John McCarthy, a group that is lobbying for his
release, staged the reconstruction in a warehouse studio in east
London, two days before his fifth birthday in captivity. McCarthy
will be 34 on Tuesday.
   McCarthy, who worked for the London-based Worldwide Television
News, was abducted by gunmen on the night of April 17, 1986, as he
drove to Beirut airport to catch a flight home.
   No group has claimed responsibility or made any demands for his
release, but he is believed to be held by Shiite Moslem
fundamentalists.
   The mock-up of McCarthy's cell was built using information
provided by freed Irish hostage Brian Keenan, held with McCarthy
until his release earlier this year, said Jill Morrell of the
Friends of John McCarthy.
   She said the cell was modeled on one shared by McCarthy and
Keenan, measuring about 15-by-13 feet.
   Actor Maurice McParland played the part of McCarthy, now thought
to be held in solitary confinement, blindfolded and chained to a
radiator, Ms. Morrell said.
   Candles on the floor were the only light, and the only towels
provided had become hard and dirty, she said.
   On a hostage's birthday, the guards would bring in a triangular
cake, with a match stuck in it, plus a bowl of fruit and nuts, and
a glass of Coca Cola, Ms. Morrell said.
   Catherine Comerford, another organizer, said the group will
deliver a petition to Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher on Monday at
the official residence at 10 Downing St. It urges the government to
do more to secure McCarthy's release.
   All 13 Westerners missing in Lebanon are believed to be held by
Shiite Moslem fundamentalists. The longest held is Terry Anderson,
chief Middle East correspondent for The Associated Press, who was
kidnapped March 16, 1985.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0058 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 1720EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Yugoslavia     11-25 0373</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Yugoslavia,0418</SECOND>
<HEAD>Macedonians Vote in Second Round</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BELGRADE, Yugoslavia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Voters in Macedonia went to the
polls Sunday for second-round regional elections after only 13 of
the 120 seats in the republic's Parliament were filled in
first-round balloting.
   Opinion polls conducted after the earlier voting on Nov. 11 gave
a revamped communist party and a reform party loyal to Premier Ante
Markovic a clear lead over nationalist parties.
   A total of 256 candidates contested the remaining seats in the
unicameral regional legislature Sunday, the state Tanjug news
agency reported. Twelve parties fielded candidates and three
candidates ran as independents, the news agency said.
   Results were not expected before Monday, and possibly not until
later in the week.
   In first-round voting, only 13 candidates won the absolute
majority needed to secure a seat in the legislature of Macedonia,
the poorest and southernmost Yugoslav republic.
   Results from 176 polling booths in 33 electoral districts were
annulled after the vote two weeks ago due to irregularities, and
first-round voting was repeated at those polling stations Sunday.
   A coalition of two parties supported by ethnic Albanians won six
seats in the first round, compared to five for the reformed
communist Party for Democratic Change and one each for the moderate
Macedonian Socialist Party and the Alliance of Reformist Forces of
federal Premier Markovic.
   Polling also took place Sunday in parts of the central Yugoslav
republic of Bosnia-Hercegovina. About 80,000 voters were called to
the polls for a repeat of first-round voting because of
irregularities at 113 polling booths in 29 municipalities.
   Second-round voting in that republic is scheduled for Dec. 2. In
first round balloting Nov. 18, nationalist parties won a sweeping
victory over the ruling Communists.
   Elections in both republics were the first free balloting in
those states in more than 50 years.
   In the northern liberal states of Slovenia and Croatia,
center-right parties ousted the Communists in regional elections
last spring.
   The largest state of Serbia and its neighbor Montenegro will be
the last of the six republics to hold local elections. They are
scheduled for Dec. 9.
   Thirty opposition parties have said they will boycott the
elections in Communist-ruled Serbia, claiming the region's
hard-line leadership is preparing to rig them.
   The independent journalists' trade union demanded Sunday that
the state-run media in Serbia provide ``unbiased and fair
coverage'' of the electoral campaign. State television has
repeatedly accused the opposition of being ``traitors'' to Serbia.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0059 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 1814EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Mexico-Elections     11-25 0277</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mexico-Elections,0302</SECOND>
<HEAD>Voting Starts in Yucatan Election; Governing Party Favored</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MEXICO CITY (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Voters in the Yucatan state cast ballots
Sunday in local races that test the government's promise to clean
up Mexican elections.
   Polls indicated the governing Institutional Revolutionary Party,
or PRI, was strongly favored among the southeastern state's 664,887
registered voters. The party has governed Mexico for 60 years.
   PRI officials said they could win all 106 mayoral jobs and 15
state legislature seats. It is the only party running for every
post.
   But the leftist daily La Jornada reported that opposition
candidates hoped to win control of at least 25 city halls. Only two
small towns, Tetiz and Hocabe, currently have opposition mayors.
   Most other newspapers gave the opposition little chance to score
major gains, outside of a possible victory in the capital, Merida,
by the conservative National Action Party.
   Official election returns could be released in about a week.
   PRI officials have vowed the elections will be clean and
democratic, in line with President Carlos Salinas de Gortari's
promises to liberalize Mexico's political and economic systems.
   But opposition leaders and local newspapers have alleged the PRI
resorted to widespread cheating to help win recent state contests
in Coahuila, Mexico and Hidalgo states.
   All the main opposition parties have accused the PRI of
preparing to fix the Yucatan election. The PRI, in return, accused
its foes of foul play, such as campaigning at polling places on
election day. It also accused a National Action official of
``intimidating voters'' at one polling place.
   National Action charged the PRI of manipulating voter rolls and
allowing the possibility of multiple voting.
   The leftist Democratic Revolution Party claimed bias in the
distribution of voter credentials and in accreditation of poll
watchers.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0060 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 1832EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Obit-Brown     11-25 0311</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Brown,0370</SECOND>
<HEAD>Communist Union Leader Dead at 79</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SAN FRANCISCO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Archie Brown, a labor leader who won a 1965
Supreme Court decision affirming the right of Communists to hold
union office, has died at the age of 79.
   As an officer in the International Longshoremen's and
Warehousemen's Union Local 10, Brown became nationally known as a
target of the House Un-American Activities Committee in 1960.
   He was prosecuted by the government for his Communist beliefs
and the case ended with his Supreme Court victory.
   Brown died of cancer Friday at his San Francisco home.
   Brown was born in Sioux City, Iowa, in 1911. As a teen-ager, he
rode the freight trains to Oakland, where he became a newsboy. He
also began his organizing career, launching a newsboys' strike in
1928.
   At 18, he joined the Young Communist League. His soapbox
speeches earned him frequent arrests for disturbing the peace or
interfering with police.
   Brown joined the waterfront union movement that emerged during a
1934 maritime strike.
   He and three others were charged with murdering a man in a fight
at a San Francisco union hall in 1935. The man allegedly jumped out
a window and later died.
   The four later were cleared of the charges, but Brown had to
work as a longshoreman under an assumed name until 1941, when he
gained the right to a regular job.
   He was appointed the Communist Party's state trade union
director in 1946.
   In 1960, Brown appeared as a hostile witness before the House
anti-Communist committee during hearings in San Francisco. He was
ejected from the hearings and committee supporters accused him of
masterminding anti-committee demonstrations.
   The following year, he was arrested and charged with violating a
clause of the 1959 Landrum-Griffin Act that barred Communists from
holding union office.
   He was found guilty in 1963, but a federal appeals court said
the ban on Communists in union office was unconstitutional. The
Supreme Court agreed, striking down the ban in 1965.
   Brown actively supported left-wing causes after retiring in
1977.
   He is survived by his wife, Esther, a sister, two brothers,
three daughters and a son.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0061 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 1834EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Gulf-Foreigners 1stLd-Writethru a0631 11-25 0606</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Foreigners, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0631,0752</SECOND>
<HEAD>Boxing Great Ali in Baghdad; More than 100 Germans Freed</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 5 grafs to CORRECT that Ali, Saddam meeting
postponed, sted that meeting was held; pickup graf 4 pvs `Ali
arrived...'</NOTE>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf Rdp</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SALAH NASRAWI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BAGHDAD, Iraq (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Boxing legend Muhammad Ali, on a visit to
Baghdad, on Sunday pressed for the release of some of the hundreds
of Americans held in Iraq.
   The visit came as more than 100 freed German captives arrived
home after nearly four months of captivity and Iraqi officials said
about 70 Italians were to be released Tuesday.
   Officials said Ali, former heavyweight champion of the world,
was to be received Sunday by President Saddam Hussein in his
heavily guarded presidential palace on the banks of the Tigris
River.
   However, the session was postponed, and no new date was
announced. There was no explanation of why the meeting was put off.
   An earlier report had said the two met.
   Ali arrived in Baghdad on Wednesday, accompanied by two aides
and two members of a peace group called the Coalition to Stop U.S.
Intervention in the Middle East.
   Aides said he has visited some of the Americans held in a hotel
in downtown Baghdad, but gave no details. About 300 Americans are
detained in Iraq, and another 600 Americans are in Kuwait, either
under detention or in hiding.
   One of Ali's associates, Arthur Morrison, said Ali was ``here on
a goodwill mission'' and hoped to secure the release of some of the
Americans.''
   Morrison spoke to reporters on behalf of Ali, who is suffering
from Parkinson's disease and cannot talk. Morrison based his
comment on hand signals by Ali.
   The former champion, a convert to Islam and conscientious
objector during the Vietnam War, has visited Moslem holy sites in
and around Baghdad. It was not clear how long he planned to stay in
Iraq.
   Prominent figures from more than a dozen countries with
nationals held in Iraq have visited Baghdad, often bringing freed
captives home with them.
   The 104 freed Germans and a Briton arrived in Frankfurt Sunday,
many with tears streaming down their faces as they were reunited
with families and friends. Rudolf Seiters, Chancellor Helmut Kohl's
chief of staff, was on hand to greet the arrivals.
   The release of the Germans came after Iraq noted approvingly
that Chancellor Helmut Kohl had stressed the need for a peaceful
solution to the gulf crisis.
   Those freed Sunday were the second-largest group of Germans to
leave Iraq this month. Former Chacellor Willy Brandt brought 120
compatriots home with him Nov. 9 after he visited Baghdad.
   Meanwhile, Iraqi officials, speaking on condition of anonymity,
said 70 Italians would be freed Tuesday through the intervention of
Syrian-born Archbiship Hilarion Capucci, Syrian-born spiritual
leader of the Melchite Catholic community in Jerusalem. An
estimated 270 Italians are trapped in Iraq and Kuwait.
   In Rome, the Italian Foreign Ministry said it had been told of
the planned releases, word of which came a day after the Italian
government sent a plane loaded with 25 tons of medicine to Baghdad.
   Shipments of medicine are allowed under the United Nations trade
embargo against Iraq.
   Saddam has said he will free all the several thousand Westerners
and Europeans stranded or held in Iraq and Kuwait between Christmas
and the end of March - but only if nothing happens to mar ``the
atmosphere of peace.''
   The Christmas-to-March period is considered by many to be the
most likely time for an offensive to drive the Iraqis out of
Kuwait.
   In other developments involving the hostages:
   -Ten Greek nationals released from Iraq arrived in Amman, Jordan
accompanied by a delegation representing the Iraqi-Greek Friendship
Association, which secured their release.
   -A British opposition lawmaker left for Baghdad on Sunday,
saying he expected to meet with Saddam. The lawmaker, Tony Benn, is
identified with the left wing of the opposition Labor Party, and
party leaders have distanced themselves from his trip. He told
reporters he wanted to ``explore the possibilities of a peaceful
settlement.''
   -Two more British women left London Sunday for Iraq, where they
will appeal to Saddam to release their hostage relatives. Hilary
Jones and Anne Mansell decided to make the trip after hearing that
a group of 10 British women already in Baghdad had won the release
of relatives held in Iraq.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0062 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 1900EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-IvoryCoast 1stLd-Writethru a0607 11-25 0602</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Ivory Coast, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0607,0677</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ivory Coast Voters Cast Ballots in First Free Parliament Election</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS thruout to UPDATE with voter turnout apparently light,
ADD change in law to allow president to pick successor. No pickup</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By MICHELLE FAUL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ABIDJAN, Ivory Coast (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Voter turnout appeared light Sunday
in the country's first multiparty parliamentary election, which
opposition leaders claim was marred by intimidation and fraud by
the party that ruled unchallenged for 30 years.
   Several people remained hospitalized after a clash Saturday
between supporters of President Felix Houphouet-Boigny's
conservative Democratic Party and its hhief rival, the left-leaning
Popular Front.
   About 4.4 million people registered to choose 175 legislators
from among the 490 candidates representing 19 parties. Early
results were expected Monday.
   The Democrats are assured of 40 seats that are unchallenged.
They are expected to easily win a majority, reinforcing
Houphouet-Boigny's huge victory last month in this West African
nation's first contested presidential race.
   His sole challenger, Popular Front leader Laurent Gbagbo,
accused the ruling party of rigging that election, in which the
85-year-old Houphouet-Boigny received 81.67 percent of votes.
   In the presidential ballot, Gbagbo's supporters smashed ballot
boxes they charged were stuffed in advance with votes for
Houphouet-Boigny. The government said the opposition disrupted
voting because they knew they would not win.
   Early Sunday, about 200 armed soldiers surrounded Gbagbo's
constituency of Ouragahio, 170 miles northwest of Abidjan.
   A spokesman for the opposition leader said the local government
there had announced people could vote without producing identity or
voter registration cards.
   There were few long lines at the polls Sunday. Polling places
appeared more crowded in the presidential elections, which had a 63
percent turnout.
   At a voting station in Abidjan's affluent suburb of Cocody, some
people said they were confused by the number of candidates. Before
1980, they could vote only ``yes'' or ``no'' to a single candidate.
In 1980 and 1985, they could choose between two candidates.
   ``These elections are pointless,'' said one voter on condition
of anonymity. ``Why do we need them when we have a perfectly
capable president?''
   The opposition was handicapped by the large funds the ruling
party compiled from compulsory contributions from civil servants'
salaries. Also, the government allowed voting by Africans from
other countries working in Ivory Coast. The foreigners comprise at
least a third of the 11.2 million population and almost all support
the ruling party.
   In the central town of Bouake, Popular Front officials said
their representatives were refused entry into polling stations to
monitor voting. All parties fielding candidates are supposed to be
able to watch the voting.
   The expected Democratic Party victory would appear to ensure
Houphouet-Boigny can choose a successor, believed to be assembly
speaker Henri Konan Bedie.
   Presidential aides have said Houphouet-Boigny wanted to resign
in a few months. Under legislation pushed through the assembly this
month, he would be succeeded by the speaker until the next
scheduled elections in 1995. Previously, if the president died or
retired the speaker could govern temporarily while he organized a
special presidential election.
   The first election-related violence was reported Saturday in
Abidjan's suburb of Yopougon.
   The suburb's deputy mayor, Mustapha Doukoure, a candidate in the
election, said Popular Front supporters threw stones and beat
ruling party members with sticks to stop them holding a peaceful
march. He said 37 of his supporters were injured.
   The opposition party said, however, the clash occurred after men
in three cars drove into a crowd of its followers leaving a
meeting, injuring several. In the fighting that followed, 17 people
were hurt and 10 of those were being treated in the hospital, a
party spokesman said.
   Soldiers patrolled Sunday in Yopougon, the site of the first
pro-democracy protests in Ivory Coast in February. Weeks of strikes
and violent riots followed, forcing Houphouet-Boigny to legalize
the political opposition.
   The demonstrations were precipitated by an economic crisis
caused by corruption, overspending and slumping cocoa and coffee
prices on world markets.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0063 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 1923EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-WashingtonFloods     11-25 0513</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Washington Floods,0618</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bridge Collapses, More Than 2,000 Homeless in Washington State
Flooding</HEAD>
<HEAD>With Bridge Sinks</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto staffing</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LUIS CABRERA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SEATTLE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Record rains, high winds and rampaging flood
waters on major Washington rivers chased more than 2,000 people
from their homes and destroyed a closed interstate highway bridge
Sunday.
   One man was feared drowned when he drove past a barricade and
into the floodwaters of the Snoqualmie River shortly before 2 a.m.
near Duvall, about 15 miles east of Seattle, police said. The man's
wife and daughter were rescued.
   At least 2,125 people were evacuated in six counties, Red Cross
and local officials said. The Red Cross had 20 emergency shelters
in operation, spokeswoman Hope Tuttle said.
   Sections of the old Interstate 90 floating bridge between
Seattle and Mercer Island sank into Lake Washington, and a 125-foot
barge broke free and sank against the U.S. 2 bridge over the
Snohomish River about 5 miles east of Everett.
   ``My state is falling apart on me,'' Gov. Booth Gardner lamented
after a helicopter tour of the region. Gardner added a dozen
counties to five others for which he had sought federal disaster
aid to recoup from sever  floods two weeks ago.
   ``We've been looking at some of the past records, and we're
definitely right up there with some of the worst there's ever
been,'' he said.
   The new request covered Clallam, Chelan, Cowlitz, Jefferson,
Kitsap, Kittitas, Lewis, Mason, Pacific, Pierce, Thurston and
Yakima counties.
   The previous request was for Grays Harbor, King, Skagit,
Snohomish and Whatcom counties, where damage was estimated at more
than $40 million before the latest flooding began.
   The most severe flooding appeared to be about 40 miles northeast
of Seattle, east of Monroe in Snohomish County, where some houses
were completely under water from the Skykomish River, Barlow said.
   Water lapped over one lane of Interstate 5 near Centralia and
Chehalis, about 90 miles south of Seattle, slowing northbound
traffic to a crawl, but dikes that collapsed during severe floods
last winter were intact Sunday.
   Elsewhere, however, dikes and levees weakened by the floods two
weeks ago fared less well.
   Water poured through a 150-foot break in a dike at
16-square-mile Fir Island, largely devoted to vegetable, flower
bulb and dairy farms and surrounded on two sides by the Skagit
River and on the third by Skagit Bay.
   About 400 people have been kept from their homes on the island,
many for the past two weeks. Three-quarters of the island was under
water.
   A dike break on the Nooksack River stranded about 1,000 people
on Lummi Island, west of Bellingham and about 90 miles north of
Seattle.
   The National Weather Service reported record flood levels on the
Cedar, Skykomish, Snoqualmie, Snohomish and Stillaguamish rivers in
King and Snohomish counties.
   It also reported an all-time record 24-hour rainfall of 5.82
inches in Olympia and 3.56 inches at Seattle-Tacoma International
Airport, a 24-hour record for November.
   County officials reported about 400 people displaced at one time
or another in King County, at least 200 in Snohomish County, 500 to
1,200 in Skagit County, about 500 each in Whatcom and Pierce
counties and 25 in Mason County.
   East of the Cascade Mountains, record windstorms caused
widespread power outages in eastern Washington and northern Idaho,
Washington Water Power officials reported.
   Winds in Spokane were clocked late Friday as high as 56 mph, a
November record, the National Weather Service reported.
   The Silver Mountain ski gondola at Kellogg, Idaho, was unable to
open for the season Saturday as winds gusted to 84 mph, officials
said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0064 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 1931EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-WeatherpageWeather     11-25 0301</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Weatherpage Weather,0359</SECOND>
<HEAD>Winter Storms Dump Snow and Rain on Western States</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   A winter storm dumped at least 2 feet of snow in parts of
Montana on Sunday while snow, rain and high winds were reported
elsewhere in the West with flooding continuing in some areas.
   Snow advisories were in effect in Wyoming's west central
mountains, Oregon's Cascade and Siskiyou mountains, and
California's northern Sierra Nevada.
   Blizzard warnings were in effect in various parts of Alaska,
including Nome, St. Lawrence Island, and the Bering Strait coast.
   Heavier snowfall recorded during the 24-hour period ending at 1
p.m. EST Sunday included as much as 27 inches near the eastern
border of Montana's Glacier Park.
   There were no reports of measurable snowfall during the 6 hours
ending at 1 p.m. EST.
   Rain continued to fall in other parts of the West Sunday. At 1
p.m., rain extended over the northern coast of California, western
Oregon, southwest and southeast Washington and the northern portion
of Idaho.
   Rain also was scattered over southeast Maine and central
Arkansas.
   Heavier rainfall recorded during that period included 1 inch at
Crescent City, Calif., and three-quarters of an inch at Mullan,
Idaho.
   Flooding continued Sunday along northwest Montana's Yaak River,
while flood warnings remained in effect in parts of Idaho and
Washington.
   High wind warnings were posted for the higher elevations of
southern and northern California, Nevada's Reno-Carson area and
portions of eastern New York state.
   High winds reported Sunday included up to 70 mph in the
mountains west of Reno, Nev., and up to 63 mph in Massena, N.Y.,
and 50 mph in Utica, N.Y.
   Record highs Sunday included 62 in Albany, N.Y; 74 in
Chattanooga, Tenn.; 70 in Cheyenne, Wyo; 73 in Jackson, Ken.; 77 in
both Denver and Galveston, Texas; and 81 in Dodge City, Kan.
   The nation's low Sunday morning was 6 degrees below zero at
Warroad, Mont.
   Temperatures around the nation at 3 p.m. EST ranged from 7
degrees above zero at Warroad, to 89 degrees at Kingsville, Texas.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0065 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 1937EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BridgeSinks 4thLd-Writethru a0689 11-25 0403</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bridge Sinks, 4th Ld-Writethru, a0689,0469</SECOND>
<HEAD>Sections Of Old I-90 Floating Bridge at Seattle Sink</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 7th graf, `Ronald Matila ...' to CORRECT that workers not
reported hurt. Picks up 8th graf, `Tugboats were ...</NOTE>
<HEAD>With AM-Washington Floods</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto SE1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By NANCY COSTELLO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SEATTLE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Sections of a closed interstate highway bridge
across Lake Washington sank Sunday after a round of stormy weather,
and engineers said the rest could collapse at any time.
   About one-third of the 1{-mile-long floating bridge across the
lake sank, another piece sank about five hours later, and other
sections appeared to be breaking loose, witnesses said. No injuries
were reported.
   The four-lane bridge, which parallels the new Interstate 90
bridge that opened lasg rebuilt to serve as
eastbound lanes for the roadway across the lake.
   State transportation engineers and police closed tht year, was beine
new
seven-lane bridge, which carries an average of about 110,000
vehicles a day, out of concern loose pieces of the old bridge could
damage it.
   The old bridge floats on the water like a ship anchored in
place, and has flotation chambers that can be pumped out. Dedicated
in 1940, it was the world's first concrete pontoon floating bridge,
said William Southern Jr., a spokesman for the Washington
Department of Transportation.
   The new bridge's anchoring cables, look at the highly unpopular per-capita
community charge, or ``poll
tax.''
   However, Kern noted that whoever the winner is, ``Britain's
tense relationship with Europe won't become a great love affair.''
   Hodgson said all the contenders ``have got immaculate
Thatcherite credentials. They are all fully committed to
privatization. They're all fully committed to lowering tax rates as
quickly as possible and as is prudent,'' Hodgson said.
   ``You may say that Thatcher may have gone but the fundamental
commitment of the Conservative Party to widen individual choice (by
shrinking government) remains theirs,'' Hodgson said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0066 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 1953EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Switzerland-US     11-25 0302</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Switzerland-US,0335</SECOND>
<HEAD>Swiss Foreign Minister Says Rough Treatment Incident Closed</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MIKE KUENZLI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>GENEVA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Swiss official said Sunday that his government
and the United States have ended a diplomatic spat over scuffles
and shouting matches between President Bush's entourage and Geneva
police.
   However, the White House said it had referred the matter to the
State Department, which is expected to lodge a protest.
   In his comments, Swiss Foreign Minister Rene Felber said the
White House acknowledged sharing the blame for the incidents, which
were caused by misunderstandings over security procedures. ``The
affair is closed,'' Felber said in an interview.
   On Saturday, White House spokesman Marlin Fitzwater said the
United States planned to file a diplomatic protest over the
incidents during Bush's three-hour Geneva stopover Friday to meet
Syrian President Hafez Assad.
   Felber claimed the White House backtracked in a subsequent phone
call to Switzerland's ambassador in Washington, Edouard Brunner. He
said that ``the White House simply thanked the Swiss ambassador in
Washington'' for short-notice work in organizing the Bush-Assad
meeting.
   The Swiss minister said the White House acknowledged it failed
to tell Geneva security officers that some reporters and
photographers traveling with the president should be allowed under
a wing of Air Force One to watch Bush come and go, as is customary.
   During the scuffle, press people were pushed and shoved by
security forces. Fitzwater said U.S. chief of protocol Joseph Reed
was poked in the stomach with a machine gun.
   No one was injured, however.
   Roman Popadiuk, deputy White House press secretary, said Sunday
the matter now rests with State Department officials, who were to
file the protest. ``It's out of our hands,'' Popadiuk said.
   Fitzwater had called it the most ``brutal and vicious treatment
by a security force in the last 10 years.'' He said White House
Chief of Staff John Sununu was ``verbally abused'' by the head of
Geneva security when he protested over the incidents.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0067 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 2012EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Czechoslovakia     11-25 0333</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Czechoslovakia,0378</SECOND>
<HEAD>Communists Emerge Victorious in Slovakian Elections</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GEORGE JAHN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BRATISLAVA, Czechoslovakia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Communists who were swept from
federal power a year ago rebounded in Slovakia municipal elections
Sunday to win more mayoral races than any other party.
   ``We hope these elections will allow us to show that we can also
be around in a democratic and pluralistic system,'' Slovak
Communist Party leader Peter Weiss said.
   However, President Vaclav Havel's Civic Forum party took nearly
30 percent of the council races in the northern Czech republic,
where Communists placed third.
   In Slovakia, Communist candidates won 660 mayor's seats, or 23.2
percent of the 2,840 contests, chief statistician Pavel Husak of
the Slovak Electoral Commission said.
   The Slovak National Party, which supports a separate Slovak
state, won 43 seats, or 1.5 percent of all the races. The vote had
been considered a test of separatist sentiment in the republic.
   The strong Communist showing appeared due in part to the
emphasis on the candidates' personalities, rather than their party
affiliations.
   The Christian Democrats were second with 541 mayoral wins, or
19.04 percent, and Public Against Violence with 476 victories, or
16.7 percent, said Husak.
   Other parties won the rest of the seats.
   The state CTK news agency said the Christian Democrats won 27.4
percent of the council seats in Slovakia. Public Against Violence
was second with 20.4 percent, and the Communists third with 13.6
percent.
   Public Against Violence won the most seats in Slovakia in June
regional and federal elections. The party joined Civic Forum to
help oust Communists last year.
   But the its popularity has waned in recent months. It is blamed
by many Slovaks for increasing economic hardships in the move to a
market-oriented system.
   In the Czech republic, Civic Forum won 29.9 percent of 70,000
council races. Czech mayors are to be chosen by the councils.
   Independents were a surprising second with 25.2 percent,
according to initial results announced by the Czech Electoral
Commission. The Communists had 15 percent, and the People's Party
of Christian Democrats were fourth at 14.9 percent.
   Other parties gained the balance of the spots.
   The official tallies are expected later this week.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0068 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 2025EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Obit-Epstein     11-25 0154</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Epstein,0153</SECOND>
<HEAD>TV Producer of `The Flying Nun,' `McMillan and Wife' Dies of
Leukemia</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Jon Epstein, producer of such television
shows as ``Tarzan,'' ``The Flying Nun'' and ``McMillan and Wife,''
died after a 14-year battle with leukemia, a family spokesman said
Sunday. He was 62.
   Epstein died Saturday at Cedars-Sinai Medical Center, said
friend Barry Greenfield.
   A funeral was planned for noon Tuesday at Mount Sinai Memorial
Park in Hollywood Hills.
   Epstein began producing television shows in the 1950s for the
Ziv studios. His credits included ``Trials of O'Brien,'' ``Rat
Patrol,'' ``The Outcasts,'' ``The Young Rebels,'' ``Three's a
Crowd,'' ``The Sheriff'' and ``Owen Marshall, Counselor at Law.''
   He also produced the television miniserie ``Rich Man, Poor
Man'' in the 1970s.
   Epstein was executive producer of the ``Colombo'' TV series.
   He is survived by a brother, Danal, a nephew and a niece.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0069 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 2037EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Poland-Walesa 1stLd-Writethru a0650 11-25 0545</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Poland-Walesa, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0650,0689</SECOND>
<HEAD>From Three Rooms in a Potato Field to President's Palace?</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS grafs 10-11 pvs, `It was not ...,' with 5 grafs to ADD
background on Walesa. Picks up 12th graf pvs, `It is...' TRIMS
thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>With AM-Poland, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DRUSILLA MENAKER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>POPOWO, Poland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The 10 families of this mud-and-marsh
hamlet have no doubt Lech Walesa should be president. After all,
he's one of them.
   ``We know that from this man we can expect some results,'' said
Stefan Walesa, the Solidarity chief's cousin and childhood
playmate.
   Maybe, they say, their ``Leszek'' will use his presidential
power to get the road to his birthplace paved.
   ``The rest of my family, my mother, my father, my three brothers
all just now got on the tractor and went to vote for him,'' said
Grzegorz Kosziowny, whose parents remember the schoolboy Walesa
running across the fields.
   Nothing marks the beginning or end of Popowo, a two-hour drive
northwest of Warsaw along the Vistula River. There is no shop, no
school, no church. The town is not on the road map and no sign
points the way down a rutted, half-flooded dirt road to the
scattered farmsteads.
   Walesa grew up in a metal-roof, concrete-block home in a potato
field. There was no electricity or water in the three-room house
when he was born there Sept. 23, 1943.
   Walesa remembers the four-acre tract his father inherited from
the much-divided family property as ``utterly deprived ... of
anything approaching nostalgia.''
   ``Our neighbors had avoided it, deeming it too dreadful to live
on,'' he recalled in his 1987 autobiography, ``A Way of Hope.''
   Walesa's father died in 1945, his health ruined by forced labor
under the German occupiers. His mother married her brother-in-law a
year later, and the impoverished family struggled in the devastated
postwar countryside, sometimes without even bread to eat.
   It was not until 1967 that the 24-year-old Walesa put on his
coat, took some money and, pushed by a broken love affair and a
sense of wasted time, got on a train in nearby Dobrzyn. It went to
Gdansk, where he took a job at the Lenin shipyard.
   Increasingly troubled by the workers' conditions and
totalitarian communist rule - especially after the bloody
repression of strikes in 1970 - Walesa lost one job after another
to his activism.
   He was unemployed and outside the strikebound shipyard when he
made his famous leap over the gate to lead Solidarity's founding in
1980.
   Held in custody after martial law in December 1981 and awarded
the Nobel Peace Prize in 1983, Walesa maneuvered the Solidarity
movement through years of repression. It took control of the
government in 1989.
   On Sunday, three generations of cousin Stefan Walesa's family
went to church and then voted for their ``Leszek'' for president.
   ``It is a wonderful feeling,'' said Stefan Walesa, a work-worn
53-year-old farmer.
   ``He deserves to be president. There is no other Pole who risked
his life so much to defeat the communist system.''
   In a living room decorated like that of many Poles with a
painting of Polish-born Pope John Paul II and a small photo of the
Solidarity leader, Walesa chuckles at the memory of the willful
young Lech born next door.
   ``When he was young he wanted to do everything, he was involved
in everything,'' he said.
   ``He became a national hero from such a small house,'' Stefan
Walesa said.
   Lech Walesa returns to Popowo from time to time, most recently
on Nov. 1 for All Saints Day, when Poles make pilgrimages to the
graves of their relatives.
   Some say Walesa lacks the refinement to be president, but that
is what appeals to many of his supporters.
   ``He is a real Pole, from a poor family like us farmers,'' said
one middle-age woman emerging from the unheated social hall in
neighboring Turzy Wilcza that served as the polling station for
Popowo.
   ``The fact that he was born here is one of many reasons we voted
for him.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0070 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 2113EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AP-NoKeywordFiled!     11-25 0272</FIRST>
<SECOND>Mother Can Stay; Activated Army Couple Gets Reprieve</SECOND>
<NOTE>Eds:LEADS with 5 grafs to CORRECT that Mrs. Schamer was not given
a
hardship exemtipn but has applied for one. Picks up 6th graf pvs,
`The Schamers ...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By LUIS CABRERA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SEATTLE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Twila Schamer will get to be a mom again.
   Mrs. Schamer and her husband, Christopher, parents of a
9-week-old son, were among 705 reservists with the Army's 50th
General Hospital Unit who were called to active duty last week for
a minimum of six months.
   On Saturday, however, at a briefing for the unit's members and
their families at Fort Lewis, south of Tacoma, Mrs. Schamer was
told she would be allowed to stay home and care for her baby,
Jacob.
   ``It's kind of a mixed blessing,'' she said. ``For me, it's nice
that I get to stay home with Jake. But my husband's still leaving,
so it's hard.''
   Christopher Schamer, 25, is a communications specialist whose
duties include setting up the hospital's phone service. Mrs.
Schamer, 26, is a sergeant who works as an administrative assistant
in the nursing division.
   Mrs. Schamer said she won't be sent overseas because her unit
has enough other people with her specialty. She has applied for a
hardship exemption from active duty and the request is pending.
   The Schamers reported Saturday to Fort Lewis, where they were
scheduled to go through orientation and training for deployment to
the Persian Gulf or a domestic base in need of medical personnel.
   The Schamers initially planned to leave Jacob with his paternal
grandparents in Bellevue, east of Seattle.
   The break with his family still will be hard, Schamer said.
   ``I'm really kind of dazed. There's a job to be done over there
... but I'm just getting used to being a father now, and feeling
that I may have to leave that behind for six months really hurts
me,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0071 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 2144EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Poland 5thLd-Writethru a0688 11-25 1075</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Poland, 5th Ld-Writethru, a0688,1301</SECOND>
<HEAD>Early Polls Show Walesa With Strong Lead; Second Spot Tied</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 5 grafs to UPDATE with results of early official
returns. Picks up 5th graf pvs, `It was...</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos WAR51,52</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN DANISZEWSKI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WARSAW, Poland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Lech Walesa, who united Poles in their
struggle against communism, won the initial round in Poland's first
popular presidential election Sunday but appeared headed for a
runoff, according to state TV exit polls.
   In a surprising development, Prime Minister Tadeusz Mazowiecki
was in a close race against Stanislaw Tyminski for the No. 2 spot.
Tyminski, a political unknown until recently, is a businessman who
returned to his homeland only this fall after 21 years in Canada
and Peru.
   The second-place finisher will enter a Dec. 9 runoff if the
winner fails to gain an outright majority in the first round.
   Walesa, the head of Solidarity, had 41 percent of the vote, a
2-to-1 lead over Mazowiecki and Tyminski, according to the polls.
The polls indicated Mazowiecki and Tyminski each had 20.5 percent
of the vote, far ahead of the remaining three candidates.
   But early official returns from 270 polling stations, or about 1
percent of the vote nationwide, said Walesa led with 39.1 percent,
followed by Tyminski with 23.4 percent and Mazowiecki at 20
percent.
   It was a stunning setback for Mazowiecki, a former Walesa ally
who instituted unpopular economic austerity measures after taking
command of Poland's first postwar non-Communist government.
   ``No matter what the election results are, we created a basis
for a broader democratic movement in Poland,'' Mazowiecki told
supporters at a students' club in Warsaw. ``We will continue the
struggle for a democracy as we want it.''
   He added later on television that he was waiting for ``real
results, and not just some estimates.''
   Pollsters questioned every 20th voter at 404 polling places
around the country, or up to 15,000 people. The results were issued
on nationwide TV minutes after the polls closed at 8 p.m. (2 p.m.
EST).
   The poll indicated that farmers, who represent 40 percent of
Polish society, deserted Mazowiecki en masse.
   Only 4 percent of the farm vote went to the prime minister,
according to the poll. Farmers have been angry at the abolition of
guaranteed prices for their produce under the government's shock
economic reform plan.
   Mazowiecki also did poorly among workers, but led among
intellectuals, according to the poll.
   Tyminski nearly tied Walesa in the Silesian mining district, the
poll said. Coal miners there are threatened with layoffs and have
been staging a series of warning strikes.
   A member of Mazowiecki's campaign, parliament deputy Jan
Litynski, said the early exit poll results were ``a bit exaggerated
... Tadeusz Mazowiecki will undoubtedly reach the second round.''
   ``Stanislaw Tyminski is the epitome of the (fairy tale) goldfish
who promises to fulfill our wishes,'' said Wladyslaw Frasyniuk,
co-founder of the pro-Mazowiecki political party Citizens Movement
for Democratic Action.
   Pro-Mazowiecki newspaper editor Ernest Skalski said if Tyminski
gets to the runoff, Walesa would win handily. ``But the very fact
that he got to the second round would be a shameful episode in our
political history,'' he said.
   Other supporters of Mazowiecki, the East bloc's first
non-Communist head of government, seemed convinced that Walesa will
win.
   ``Unfortunately, what we will see with Walesa as president is
hyperinflation and chaos,'' said Marek Dabrowski, a former deputy
finance minister who left the government to join Mazowiecki's bid.
   Walesa declined any immediate public statement. Jacek Merkel,
manager of Walesa's campaign, said Walesa was still awaiting final
results. He scheduled a news conference for Monday.
   However, Lech Kaczynski, the deputy Solidarity chairman and a
top Walesa strategist, said, ``I'm rather disappointed because we
hoped for at least 50 percent.'' He added, ``Now we have to deal
with two phenomena, an absolute defeat of the government camp and
... this dangerous phenomenon called Tyminski.''
   Tyminski, who promised to quickly cure Poland's economic
problems, said on television late Sunday, ``I expected such a
result. I am very happy.''
   He accused state television of mounting a campaign against him
and said he would challenge Walesa to a debate. ``In the second
round, I will be supported by all those forces that have been
supporting me, plus those which - I hope - will have a better
chance to believe I am an honest man,'' he added.
   ``Tyminski conducted an American-standard campaign, breaking
every rule,'' political commentator Ryszard Legutko said on state
television.
   During the campaign, the state prosecutor opened a slander
investigation against Tyminski, who had charged that Mazowiecki had
committed treason against the nation with his economic policies.
Mazowiecki's government is struggling to create a market economy
and strip away the vestiges of 45 years of Communism.
   The new president will take over from President Wojciech
Jaruzelski, the Communist general who ordered martial law to crush
Solidarity and imprisoned Walesa and Mazowiecki in December 1981.
He also is expected to receive the symbols of authority from the
still-existing World War II government in exile in London, which
never recognized the Soviet-backed state.
   Jaruzelski, interviewed on television, said he did not see the
early poll results ``as a great surprise.''
   Mazowiecki was a longtime adviser to Walesa, and the Solidarity
leader had tapped him to become head of the government in 1989.
   But they had a bitter falling-out, and the voting climaxed an
often acrimonious two-month campaign that split the Solidarity
movement into factions that supported the candidates. Mazowiecki
was backed by intellectuals, who Walesa's populist campaign harshly
criticized.
   There was harsh language on both sides, with Walesa calling
Mazowiecki ``too slow'' and Mazowiecki accusing Walesa of
destabilizing the country.
   The campaign also was tainted by the anti-Semitism of a fraction
of the electorate, with oft-repeated rumors that the devoutly Roman
Catholic Mazowiecki was Jewish or that Jews dominated his
government.
   Walesa condemned anti-Semitism - resurgent in a Poland with
virtually no Jews - and said he would not permit it as president.
But he was accused of not doing enough to discourage such
attitudes, and even of encouraging them with campaign statements
that he was ``a pure Pole.''
   The election ultimately became a test of political direction,
the first in Eastern Europe to focus not on defeating communism but
choosing between visions for the post-Communist future.
   Walesa, 47, is the charismatic leader of Solidarity, the first
independent labor federation in the Soviet bloc, which led the
anti-Communist rebellion. He contends even more reforms are needed
more quickly or a social explosion is coming.
   Mazowiecki, 63, launched the region's most dramatic economic
overhaul on Jan. 1 and says Poland needs his team to stay and
finish the job through consistent, gradual change. He has accused
Walesa of making promises he cannot keep, and some of his backers
say Walesa would be a demagogue.
   It was the first time that Poles voted for a president by
popular election. In the past, both under Communist rule and before
World War II, presidents were elected by the Parliament.
   Retired office worker Genewefa Pawlak, a Walesa backer in
Gdansk, said, ``We trust him because he fought for 10 years and he
never let us down.''
   The new president will serve a five-year term as head of state
and commander in chief of the military, with powers to nominate the
prime minister, dissolve parliament and declare a state of
emergency under strictly defined circumstances.
   The other candidates were: Roman Bartoszcze of the Polish
Peasants Party; former Communist Wlodzimierz Cimoszewicz, endorsed
by the Social Democracy party; and Leszek Moczulski, head of the
patriotic-nationalist Confederation for an Independent Poland.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0072 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 2202EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r e BC-Connick     11-25 0417</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Connick,0539</SECOND>
<HEAD>Harry Connick Opens on Broadway</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: No PMs Planned</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By MARY CAMPBELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Harry Connick Jr., the jazz pianist-singer who
has been spinning through show business like a comet, now has
landed here for two weeks, conquering Broadway.
   Connick, who is 23, opened ``An Evening with Harry Connick Jr.
and his Orchestra'' at the Lunt-Fontanne Theater Friday night, the
same night ``Swinging Out with Harry,'' a Dallas show on the tour
Connick started in April, was on TV. He's also known for putting
together the ``When Harry Met Sally'' soundtrack and he's currently
making his movie acting debut in ``Memphis Belle,'' as a tailgunner
who sings.
  The exuberant show should gladden the hearts of jazz fans. As a
singer, Connick is the Mel Torme of his generation. He can croon
but he isn't a pop singer, he's a jazz singer. Once, he sings scat.
As a pianist, he has a heavy, percussive attack. He plays in a lot
of styles, even stride and boogie woogie, but he doesn't touch
jazz-rock.
   The 16-piece band he carries with him has a solid big band
sound. It isn't as hard-charging as Woody Herman's herds - on
purpose since its leader sings a lot and wants to be heard. But it
swings and it has some classy, exciting soloists. Connick always
announces them, in the best tradition.
   The amazing thing is that Connick gets the big band feeling and
music so right and makes it sound so contemporary, never a careful
reconstruction of the past.
   For a New Orleans traditional number he has musicians playing
banjo and sousaphone, does some lusty ``second line'' dancing -
like the people right behind the band in parades - and takes over
the drums so drummer Shannon Powell can dance.
   Connick does a lot of things. He sings, then does a soft shoe in
``All I Need Is the Girl.'' It won't make one forget the number in
``Gypsy'' two blocks away, but it's charming. He writes music. He
sings ``Forever For Now,'' with subtle, clever lyrics by Ramsey
McLean. His encore was ``Buried in Blue,'' which he composed about
his mother who died when he was 13. He has that on a record album
but probably shouldn't use it as an encore.
   His manner is engaging, bordering on the corny sometimes, but
not quite getting there. The audience sees through the ``ah
shucks'' to the self-assurance and stays in the palm of his hand.
   After intermission, a 22-piece orchestra, mainly strings, is
atop the steps where the band had been. After a couple of numbers,
the band appears, in one long line, in the orchestra pit.
   Marilyn Lowey is innovative with lighting. Sometimes the
audience sees Connick in silhouette, conducting. The show starts
with him at the piano, then lights reveal the rest of the
musicians. Joe Layton directed. Marc Shaiman conducts in Act 2.
Alexander Julian has Connick dress casually, in a white,
open-necked shirt, tan slacks and Navy blazer.
   Connick's father attended opening night, took a bow and had
``Danny Boy'' dedicated to him.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0073 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 2206EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-GulfRdp 4thLd-Writethru a0708 11-25 0835</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf Rdp, 4th Ld-Writethru, a0708,1015</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.S. Wants Deadline on Use of Force; Iraq Threatens Saudi Arabia</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 11 grafs to UPDATE with U.S. officials saying they
want a Jan. 1 deadline in use-of-force resolution, EDITS to
conform; pickup graf 13 pvs `But Bush's...'</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto DHA1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LAURA KING</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   U.S. officials said late Sunday they want the United Nations to
authorize using force against Iraq if it does not leave Kuwait by
Jan. 1, and Baghdad's government threatened to rain missiles on
Saudi Arabia if U.S. troops attack.
   Iraq also said it was mobilizing tens of thousands of farmers
for military service, even though it is struggling to increase food
production to offset the effects of U.N. sanctions imposed after
the Aug. 2 invasion of Kuwait.
   Iraqi authorities, meanwhile, were taking steps to make sure any
shortages caused by the sanctions are felt in Kuwait, which Iraq
calls its 19th province. The official Iraqi News Agency said food
rationing would begin soon in the conquered emirate.
   U.S. officials seeking a U.N. resolution authorizing military
force against Iraq said they want a Jan. 1 deadline. An
administration official pointed out that Secretary of State James
A. Baker III has been talking about an end-of-year deadline during
his recent globe-trotting campaign to win their support for a U.N.
resolution authorizing force.
   ``We've just kind of formalized that'' in the draft resolution
given to other permanent members of the U.N. Security Council, said
the official on condition of anonymity.
   Also Sunday, Kuwait's government-in-exile, citing reports from
escapees, said Kuwaiti resistance fighters had recently wounded the
Iraqi-appointed governor of Kuwait. The report could not be
independently confirmed, but Iraq did announce the appointment of a
new governor earlier this month, without saying why the former one
was being replaced.
   Iraq continued its piecemeal release of foreign hostages, but no
Americans were among those freed Sunday. More than 100 German
hostages arrived home after nearly four months of captivity, and 10
Greeks returned to Athens. Iraqi officials also said 70 Italians
would be freed Tuesday.
   Dozens of former government leaders and other dignitaries have
traveled to Baghdad to try to win the release of captive
foreigners, even though such private trips are discouraged by the
U.S. government.
   The latest such visitor was boxing legend Muhammad Ali, who had
planned to meet with Saddam Hussein on Sunday at the presidential
palace. The session was postponed and no new date for the meeting
was announced. An earlier, erroneous report had said the two met.
   An Ali associate, Arthur Morrison, said the former world
heavyweight champion was on a ``goodwill mission'' and hoped to
free some Americans. Morrison spoke to reporters on behalf of Ali,
who is suffering from Parkinson's disease and cannot speak.
   U.S. officials, meanwhile, were laying the groundwork for what
they hope will be a U.N. vote by Thursday on the resolution to
authorize use of force against Iraq. The United States is seeking a
vote this week because its one-month presidency of the 15-member
Security Council ends Friday. Taking over is the Red Sea state of
Yemen, which has supported Iraq in the past.
   But Bush's national security adviser, Brent Scowcroft, said
Sunday that American forces could move against Iraq without U.N.
approval. Bush made a similar statement Friday.
   Secretary of State James A. Baker III spent last week in an
intensive round of lobbying for the measure. Malaysia's foreign
minister said after meeting with Baker on Saturday that he believed
the meeting would take place Thursday. The Los Angeles Times also
said in Sunday editions the vote was expected then.
   Canadian External Affairs Minister Joe Clark said Sunday his
country supports the resolution and called it a ``final attempt''
for a peaceful settlement to the gulf crisis. Canada is a
non-permanent member of the council.
   Iraq, meanwhile, was underscoring its determination to hang onto
the emirate even in the face of a military strike. It said if the
U.S.-led military force tried to dislodge it from Kuwait, Saudi
Arabia and other gulf states would be hit by missile attacks.
   ``The springboards for any aggression targeting Iraq will
without exception become a theater of operation if the U.S.
administration and its allies insist on the military option,'' the
army's al-Qadissiyah daily newspaper declared.
   The Iraqi threat was seen by some as an effort to drive a wedge
between the United States and Saudi Arabia. Some Saudi officials
are believed to oppose an offensive from their soil.
   The U.S.-led force was originally deployed with the stated aim
of defending Saudi Arabia against any new Iraqi aggression, but
President Bush has said a buildup now underway would give the force
offensive capability.
   About 26 nations have sent 350,000 troops to the gulf region.
They include 230,000 American troops, and 200,000 more are on the
way. The multinational force faces an estimated 460,000 Iraqi
troops stationed in Kuwait and southern Iraq.
   Iraq indicated it would strengthen its army even at the cost of
cutting food production. A government decree published in Baghdad
newspapers said farmers, who had formerly been exempted from
military service, would now be called to serve. Official Iraqi
sources said an estimated 60,000 farmers, most of them military
reservists, would be called up in the next few days.
   The Iraqi News Agency report on rationing in Kuwait said
preparations were under way to distribute ration cards to citizens
and oreigners. It did not specify what foodstuffs were involved,
but bread, sugar, meat and milk are all rationed in Iraq.
   A spokesman for the Kuwaiti government-in-exile, Abdel-Razzaq
Saqer, had few details about the reported attack by resistance
fighters on Ali Hassan Majeed, the Iraqi-appointed governor of
Kuwait. He cited Kuwaiti exiles as saying the governor had been
wounded in the shoulder in the attack by resistance fighters.
   No date was given for the reported attack.
   Majeed was appointed as governor after the Iraqi takeover. But
earlier this month, without explanation, Saddam named a new
governor.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0074 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 2237EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-DooDahParade     11-25 0480</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Doo Dah Parade,0574</SECOND>
<HEAD>Doo Dah Parade in Pasadena Mocks Self and Institutions</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PASADENA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Doo Dah Parade, an irreverent spoof
of the esteemed Tournament of Roses on New Year's Day, lured about
75,000 spectators curbside for 90 minutes of belly laughs on
Sunday.
   Characters representing Zsa Zsa Gabor, Roseanne Barr, Milli
Vanilli, Bart Simpson and even Saddam Hussein strutted their stuff
- or got roasted - in ``the 15th occasional'' running of the
Thanksgiving weekend event.
   A well-behaved crowd gathered in 72-degree temperatures to
witness the mile-long procession, said police Sgt. Kevin Hall.
   The Doo Dah was the first of three Los Angeles-area parades
Sunday.
   More than 150,000 people cheered as actors Edward James Olmos
and Catherine Bach led off the 16th Annual East Los Angeles
Christmas Parade. About 750,000 people lined the streets at 6 p.m.
to view the start of the Hollywood Christmas Parade, featuring
Arnold Schwarzenegger as grand marshal.
   ``I'm so excited, I tell you it's absolutely wonderful,''
Schwarzenegger said when the parade began. ``I'm full of energy,
ready to go to pump up the Christmas spirit.''
   The muscleman sat atop a float bedecked with child co-stars from
his new movie, ``Kindergarten Cop.''
   Unlike the stately Rose Parade, the Doo Dah Parade has no theme,
no prize, and no judge.
   But like the parade it lampoons, it had a queen. This year's
monarch was waitress Lila Johnson, who was crowned after winning an
arm wrestling contest.
   The pop music duo Milli Vanilli was lampooned by many entrants,
including the Do It Yourself Milli Vanilli Band lip-syncing ``Girl,
You Know It's True.''
   Last week, the pair returned their best new artist Grammy Award
after it was revealed they never sang a note on their hit record.
   Roseanne Barr also was targeted. The world's largest shopping
cart was pushed down the street on a mission to fill the rotund
comedian's grocery list.
   Boos greeted the Roseanne Barr National Anthem Drill team, which
screeched out the actress' infamous rendition of the
``Star-Spangled Banner'' while a group in San Diego Padres uniforms
plugged their ears.
   Television was made fun of, too, as the group Thursday Night
Fight put Bart Simpson and Bill Cosby lookalikes in a boxing ring.
The Thursday evening shows have been battling it out in a ratings
war.
   Old favorites also were on hand. The synchronized briefcase
drill team frowned, businesslike, through their maneuvers; the
mobile volleyball team kept the ball in the air as the net moved
down the street; and the marching hibachi grill team flung
tortillas to the crowd.
   The real bankers, attorneys and investment advisors in the
briefcase team were themselves spoofed by the Bozo Synchronized
Briefcase Drill Team in clown makeup and pinstriped suits.
   The Slap My Face and Call Me Saddam Drill Team offered a
solution for the world's most pressing problem. Under a banner
reading, ``Zsa Zsa - America's Secret Weapon,'' a group of Zsa Zsas
slapped Saddam Hussein posers and wrested globes from the mock
strongmen.
   Some themes were directed at a Californian audience.
   Architects wearing houses fell prey to imaginary earthquakes,
mudslides and brush fires.
   Medflies danced around marching fruit, flowers and helicopters.
They sang about the pesticide Malathion, which state agricultural
officials sprayed over Southern California neighborhoods this year
in the latest war against the Mediterranean fruit fly.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0075 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 2248EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-GainesvilleSlayings 1stLd-Writethru a07 11-25 0530</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gainesville Slayings, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0709,0620</SECOND>
<HEAD>Investigators Continue Pursuing Leads in Murder Probe</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 5 grafs to CLARIFY that authorities have not
charged a suspect in case; INSERT background on suspect earlier
identified. Picks up 6th graf pvs, `The first ...'</NOTE>
<DATELINE>GAINESVILLE, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Authorities investigating the slayings
of five college students have not charged a suspect three months
later, despite one of the most intense murder probes in Florida
history.
   But while some outside law enforcement officials don't hold out
much hope, investigators remain optimistic they will ultimately
track down the killer.
   Authorities have spent $2.5 million to send 75 investigators out
to follow some 5,500 leads since the killings in late August.
   ``This isn't television,'' said Win Phillips, second-in-command
at the Alachua County Sheriff's Office. ``It's been time-consuming,
labor-intensive and costly.''
   Last month, Edward Humphrey, earlier identified as a suspect in
the case, was sentenced to 22 months in a prison mental institution
for beating his grandmother. The 19-year-old student was never
charged in the slayings.
   The first two victims were found stabbed and mutilated Aug. 26.
Sonja Larson, 18, of Deerfield Beach, and Christina Powell, 17, of
Jacksonville, were both University of Florida students.
   Christa Hoyt, 17, a student at nearby Santa Fe Community
College, was found the next day, beheaded. University of Florida
students Tracy Paules and Manuel Taboada, both 23 of Miami, were
found the day after that, stabbed to death.
   Since then, a task force of investigators from the FBI,
Gainesville police, Alachua County Sheriff's Office, Florida
Department of Law Enforcement and Florida Highway Patrol have said
little about their progress.
   ``I feel confident we're going to ultimately resolve this thing
because of the quantity and quality of the resources working on
this,'' said State Attorney Len Register. ``The legends of the FDLE
are up here working on this case.''
   But outsiders are not convinced an arrest is imminent, or even
likely.
   Michael West, a Mississippi forensic expert, scoured the murder
scenes with special laser equipment, looking for fingerprints,
footprints, blood or fibers police may have missed. He said he had
never seen a crime scene so clean in 13 years of such work.
   ``This person didn't leave them anything to work with,'' West
said. ``He didn't wake up one morning and decide to kill. He did
some planning and was careful.''
   ``They're in a hell of a bind,'' said Leon County Sheriff's
Capt. Steve Bodiford, who helped investigate the Ted Bundy serial
murder case in the late 1970s. Bundy confessed to killing 23 young
women.
   ``What do you do? If you have no evidence, you run all the leads
down and try to develop new leads. It's tough,'' Bodiford said.
Leon County incorporates Tallahassee in northwest Florida.
   So many leads are being pursued that the task force has
discouraged victims' families and the university from offering
rewards - a traditional way of generating leads.
   ``They're afraid of leaks, so they're not telling us anything,''
said Ada Larson, mother of one of the victims. ``Recently, they
don't return my calls.''
   Mario Taboada, whose brother was killed, said he would let the
investigation take its course.
   ``I've been very patient, because I know every little item
picked up needs to be written up, documented, processed,'' he said.
``Obviously that's time-consuming.''
   Meanwhile, university officials worry that students have grown
complacent.
   Campus police spokesman Angie Tipton said students have since
dropped their guard, walking alone at night, leaving doors and
windows unlocked.
   ``It's like nothing ever happened,'' Ms. Tipton said. ``We try
to remind them that the victims were just like they are: vulnerable
and trusting.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0076 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 2258EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Marcos-Typhoon     11-25 0272</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Marcos-Typhoon,0325</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mrs. Marcos Wants to Give Money From Frozen Account to Typhoon
Victims</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Former Philippine first lady Imelda Marcos has
offered to give about $3.6 million in bank account funds frozen in
the Philippines to the victims of a typhoon that killed 300 people
in her homeland.
   Mrs. Marcos made her offer of 100 Philippine pesos, or about
$3.6 million, on Friday, attorney James P. Linn said in a telephone
interview Sunday from his home in Oklahoma City.
   She had not yet received a response from the Philippine
government, which would have to approve the release of the funds,
Linn said. Typhoon Mike devastated the city of Cebu in
mid-November.
   An earlier offer by Mrs. Marcos to give an identical amount in
Swiss bank account funds to the victims of a July earthquake that
killed an estimated 1,600 Filipinos was rejected by the ruling
Aquino government, Linn said.
   There were ``no strings attached,'' Linn said.
   ``She's very much a Filipino woman and very much concerned about
her country,'' Linn said. ``This is her idea. She'd do a good deal
more than that if they'd let her.''
   The Philippine government has a $5 billion racketeering lawsuit
pending against Mrs. Marcos and the estate of her late husband,
Ferdinand, the former Philippine president.
   The lawsuit alleges the couple and their cronies looted the
Philippine treasury during Marcos' 20-year rule. He was deposed in
1986 and died in exile in Hawaii last year.
   The Philippine government has said it would settle the
racketeering lawsuit if it gets at least 60 percent of the money in
a half-dozen Marcos bank accounts in Hong Kong. The 60 percent is
believed to be worth about $250 million.
   A hearing on the proposed settlement is scheduled Dec. 10 in
U.S. District Court in Los Angeles. Mrs. Marcos was acquitted of
criminal racketeering in July.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901125-0077 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-25-90 2259EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BRF--ElfHurt 1stLd-Writethru a0646 11-25 0173</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Elf Hurt, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0646,0180</SECOND>
<HEAD>Man Dressed As Christmas Elf Injured During Parachute Jump</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 5th graf pvs to UPDATE with man hospitalized overnight;
children sending him cards. No pickup.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>QUNICY, Mass. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A parachutist dressed as a Christmas elf
lost control and landed on a moving car in front of thousands of
spectators at a Christmas festival.
   Robert G. Humphrey of Holbrook was hospitalized after he was
carried by a wind squall from his intended target, Faxon Field, and
landed on a moving car nearby Saturday.
   More than 1,000 spectators were gathered to watch the annual
Christmas parachute jump, sponsored by the Quincy Christmas
Festival Committee.
   Police said Humphrey was falling at about 30 mph when he hit the
car and bounced into the street.
   Humphrey, 39, was to spend Sunday night at Quincy Hospital,
where he was being treated for a broken knee, a broken leg and
bruises. Humphrey said in a telephone interview that children
already were sending him get-well cards.
   Parachutists dressed as Santa Claus and other elves landed
safely.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
</Collection>
