<Collection>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0001 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 2303EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-RareBooks     11-04 0233</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Rare Books,0254</SECOND>
<HEAD>Woman Pleads No Contest to Theft of Rare Books</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PHILADELPHIA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A former part-time library worker at the
University of Pennsylvania pleaded no contest to stealing almost
$1.8 million in rare books and documents and to pilfering records
to cover up the thefts.
   Kathleen Wilkerson, 34, entered the plea Friday in Common Pleas
Court. She was accused of stealing 101 books and documents,
including a rare poem by Elizabeth Barrett Browning, from the
university's Van Pelt Library over five years.
   Ms. Wilkerson was arrested Feb. 28 after she tried to sell six
books through a rare-book dealer. The volumes included a $1 million
1611 edition of ``Hamlet,'' which was the library's most valuable
printed book.
   Ms. Wilkerson's attorney, Dennis Eisman, said Ms. Wilkerson
pleaded no contest to theft by unlawful taking and tampering with
records because of ``long-term mental illness.''
   She remains free on bail pending sentencing early next year.
   The theft was discovered by a Baltimore book dealer, who saw the
books in the Bauman's Rare Books in Philadelphia, where they were
being evaluated. He suspected they were stolen and contacted the
university.
   From August 1989 to February, Ms. Wilkerson tried to sell 61
stolen volumes to Bauman's, according to Assistant District
Attorney Denis Cohen
   Many of the stolen books were recovered in Ms. Wilkerson's
Philadelphia apartment and have been returned to the university,
Cohen said. Library officials still are trying to determine if all
of the stolen books have been returned.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0002 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 2307EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BRF--ArtRecovered     11-04 0157</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Art Recovered,0161</SECOND>
<HEAD>Stolen Painting Recovered In Brooklyn Apartment</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A $320,000 French painting snatched from a
gallery wall was recovered in a New York apartment, police said
Sunday.
   A 46-year-old man was arrested and charged with burglary.
   The canvas by Maurice Utrillo was one of several found at the
apartment in Brooklyn, said Sgt. Norris Holloman, a police
spokesman.
   Police didn't know if the other paintings - estimated to be
worth up to $1 million along with the Utrillo - also had been
stolen.
   Balazs Gabor was arrested and charged with burglary and
possession of stolen property.
   The Utrillo painting, ``Rue a Montmartre,'' a 1926 work showing
a Paris street and valued at about $320,000, was stolen Tuesday
afternoon from the Soufer Gallery in Manhattan.
   A man was let into the gallery, grabbed the painting off a wall
and fled, said Gregory Smith, an independent adjuster who
represents the painting's insurer.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0003 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 2339EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u p AM-Gantt-Helms 1stLd-Writethru a0729 11-04 0410</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gantt-Helms, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0729,0484</SECOND>
<HEAD>Supporters for Helms and Gantt Clash</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 11 grafs to UPDATE with supporters of both
candidates filing assault charges stemming from scuffles at rally
Saturday. Pick up 11th graf pvs, `Both candidates...</NOTE>
<DATELINE>CHARLOTTE, N.C. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Supporters of U.S. Sen. Jesse Helms and
challenger Harvey Gantt filed assault complaints against each other
Sunday after a confrontation at a rally Saturday for the Republican
incumbent.
   Supporters of Gantt, who is black, gathered outside the meeting
of backers fo the conservative Helms in a campaign that has become
increasingly acrimonious and racially charged.
   Some Helms backers called Gantt supporters communists and
shouted other epithets as they walked through the crowd to the
rally. ``Murderer! Murderer! Murderer!'' yelled another Helms
backer, in reference to the abortion rights position of Gantt, a
Democrat, and some of his supporters.
   Police were not present during the clash at Alexander Graham
Junior High, but on Sunday, three people filed misdemeanor assault
charges stemming from minor confrontations or scuffles.
   Gantt backer Tracy Parker, 19, charged that she was pushed by
the Rev. Joseph Chambers, pastor of Charlotte's Paw Creek Church of
God, when he took away a poster. The minister, who is the leader of
the conservative activist group Concerned Charlotteans, denied the
allegation.
   Gantt supporter Tom Tritten, a university student, and Jim
Grice, who was working for the Helms group as a security guard,
filed simple assault charges against each other after a scuffle at
the rally.
   The confrontations took place when about 40 Gantt supporters
waved anti-Helms signs in the faces of backers as they entered the
school.
   Spokesmen for both campaigns said they were unaware of the
confrontation. Police said no arrests were made and no injuries
were reported.
   Helms was foregoing any campaigning Sunday after a long day on
the road Saturday, said his wife, Dot Helms.
   ``We got to bed at 3 o'clock and we're just using this as a day
of rest,'' she said. ``I'm sure the Lord will understand,'' why
they missed church.
   Gantt was in church Sunday morning and led a rally in
Mecklenburg County on Sunday night.
   Both candidates planned to fly around the state Monday in a
final blitz before Election Day.
   Polls released Thursday showed a close race between Helms, a
three-term Republican, and Gantt, a Democrat. One poll gave Helms a
lead of 4 percentage points; another gave Gantt the same lead. Both
had margins of error of 3.5 percentage points.
   Gantt, 47, rode the civil rights wave of '60s to become the
first black student at Clemson University and later the first black
mayor of Charlotte.
   Helms, 69, rose to prominence in the same decade as a television
commentator who nightly railed against civil rights, integration
and communism. That notoriety helped him to the U.S. Senate in
1972.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0004 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 2350EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a BC-LOT-SaturdayLotteries     11-04 0826</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-LOT-Saturday Lotteries,1047</SECOND>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<HEAD>CALIFORNIA</HEAD>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SACRAMENTO, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers picked
Saturday night for the California Lottery's twice-weekly ``Lotto
6-53'' game:
   26, 34, 28, 15, 13, 18, and the bonus number, 16.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>CONNECTICUT</HEAD>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEWINGTON, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning combination picked Saturday
in the Connecticut State Lottery's ``Daily Lottery'' drawing was:
   1-4-6
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Play 4</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEWINGTON, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning combination picked Saturday
in the Connecticut State Lottery's ``Play 4'' drawing was:
   0-6-2-7.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>DELAWARE</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DOVER, Del. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   These Delaware lotteries were drawn Saturday
night:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   4-2-8
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Play Four</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   0-9-2-5
</TEXT>
<HEAD>FLORIDA</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected Saturday in
the Florida Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   10-09-26-27-40-39
</TEXT>
<HEAD>ILLINOIS</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SPRINGFIELD, Ill. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the Illinois State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   7-4-6
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick Four</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   6-3-0-7
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   13-14-25-28-39-53
</TEXT>
<HEAD>INDIANA</HEAD>
<HEAD>Ind Lottery Glance</HEAD>
<DATELINE>INDIANAPOLIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the Hoosier Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto Cash</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   17-27-30-40-39-25
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Three</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   6-7-4
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Four</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   3-7-9-0
</TEXT>
<HEAD>IOWA</HEAD>
<HEAD>Lotto America</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DES MOINES, Iowa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers drawn Saturday night
in ``Lotto America'' are:
   3-9-33-36-53-54
</TEXT>
<HEAD>KANSAS</HEAD>
<HEAD>Kan. Cash Lotto</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOPEKA, Kan. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers in the Kansas Cash Lotto
drawing Saturday night with an estimated jackpot of $238,752:
   10-13-15-19-24-32
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Kan. Keno</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOPEKA, Kan. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers in the Kansas Keno
drawing Saturday night with a jackpot of $50,000:
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<HEAD>Kentucky Lottery</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOUISVILLE, Ky. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are Saturday's winning numbers
selected by the Kentucky Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Kentucky Cash:
   6-2-4.
   </HEAD>
<HEAD>Lotto:
   4-9-14-15-22-34
   (four, nine, fourteen, fifteen, twenty-two, thirty-four)
   </HEAD>
<HEAD>MARYLAND</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BALTIMORE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   These Maryland lotteries were drawn Saturday
night:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   7-9-4
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Play Four</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   3-6-5-1
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   17-24-14-45-40-5
</TEXT>
<HEAD>MASSACHUSETTS</HEAD>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BRAINTREE, Mass. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers drawn Saturday night
in the ``Massachusetts Daily Lottery'' were:
   5-1-7-8
</TEXT>
<HEAD>MICHIGAN</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DETROIT (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected Saturday in
the Michigan State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   8-3-2
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily-4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   7-1-7-9
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto 47</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   4, 6, 9, 15, 30, 38)
</TEXT>
<HEAD>MINNESOTA</HEAD>
<HEAD>Daily 3</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MINNEAPOLIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers drawn Saturday night in
the Minnesota Daily 3 lottery game are:
   9-8-5
</TEXT>
<HEAD>MISSOURI</HEAD>
<HEAD>Pick 3</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ST. LOUIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers in Saturday Missouri
Lottery Daily Pick 3 game:
   9-2-0
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ST. LOUIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers in Missouri's Lotto drawing
Saturday night:
   19-20-23-28-31-47
</TEXT>
<HEAD>NEW JERSEY</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TRENTON, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday night in the New Jersey State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 3</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   9-8-2
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   3-3-6-6
</TEXT>
<HEAD>NEW YORK</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ALBANY, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the New York State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Number</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   9-5-8
</TEXT>
<HEAD>WinFour</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   8-9-9-7
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 10</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ALBANY, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the New York State Lottery's Pick 10 game:
   5, 6, 7, 9, 10, 19, 20, 23, 31, 35, 38, 40, 49, 58, 59, 60, 63,
69, 73, 80
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ALBANY, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the New York State Lottery's Lotto game:
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   8, 19, 35, 37, 43, 53. The supplemental number was 50.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>NORTHERN NEW ENGLAND</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CONCORD, N.H. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the daily New Hampshire, Vermont and Maine lotteries:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 3</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   3-4-9
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   7-3-2-6
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Tri-State Megabucks</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CONCORD, N.H. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers in the
``Tri-State Megabucks'' game for New Hampshire, Vermont and Maine:
   6-7-10-21-28-40
</TEXT>
<HEAD>OHIO</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CLEVELAND (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected Saturday
night in the Ohio Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Super Lotto</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   1-3-6-51-52-53
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Kicker</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   9-4-5-6-9-7
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 3 Numbers</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   3-2-0
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 4 Numbers</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   2-8-8-9
</TEXT>
<HEAD>OREGON</HEAD>
<HEAD>Daily 4</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PORTLAND, Ore. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are Saturday's winning numbers in the
``Oregon Daily 4'' lottery game:
   2-6-0-3
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Megabucks</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PORTLAND, Ore. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are Saturday's winning numbers in the
``Oregon Megabucks'' lottery game:
   10-14-16-28-30-39
</TEXT>
<HEAD>PENNSYLVANIA</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HARRISBURG (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected Saturday
in the Pennsylvania State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Number</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   6-5-8
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Big 4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   1-9-0-3
</TEXT>
<HEAD>RHODE ISLAND</HEAD>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   
   CRANSTON, R.I. (AP) - The winning numbers in the Rhode Island
daily lottery drawing for Saturday were:
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   6-2-1-3
</TEXT>
<HEAD>VIRGINIA</HEAD>
<HEAD>Pick 3</HEAD>
<DATELINE>RICHMOND (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   These numbers were drawn Saturday in the
Virginia Lottery's Pick 3 game:
   0-0-4
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<DATELINE>RICHMOND (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   These numbers were drawn Saturday in the
Virginia Lottery's Lotto game:
   20, 21, 23, 26, 31, 39.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>WASHINGTON</HEAD>
<DATELINE>OLYMPIA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are winning numbers selected Saturday in the
Washington State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   9-7-0
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   3-16-21-35-39-47
</TEXT>
<HEAD>WASHINGTON, DC</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The following results were drawn Saturday in
the District of Columbia Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lucky Numbers Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   0-2-0
</TEXT>
<HEAD>D.C. Four Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   5-4-7-9
</TEXT>
<HEAD>D.C. Daily Double Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   88, 89
</TEXT>
<HEAD>D.C. Quick Cash Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   8-11-12-15-20-34
</TEXT>
<HEAD>WEST VIRGINIA</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CHARLESTON, W.Va. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the West Virginia State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily 3</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   8-0-8
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily 4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   0-3-9-2
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0005 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 2352EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Gulf-FuelCrunch     11-04 0432</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Gulf-Fuel Crunch,0510</SECOND>
<HEAD>Put in a Pinch by the Gulf Squeeze, Consumers Start Bargain
Hunting</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CECI CONNOLLY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Commuters are sharing rides to work. Travelers are
shortening their vacations. Homeowners are switching from oil to
gas.
   With the Persian Gulf crisis three months old and winter
approaching, Northeastern consumers are trying to cut costs as fuel
prices climb.
   ``People are concerned,'' said Dave Goodsell, a marketing
specialist with the non-profit Caravan for Commuters, which
provides free information for Massachusetts residents seeking to
form van pools. ``They are ready to make a change because they want
to save money.''
   Caravan had 700 phone calls - a 46 percent increase - to its
information line in August, the first month of the fuel crunch,
Goodsell said. He expects similar increases for September and
October when those numbers are tabulated.
   At The Rideshare Co. in Hartford, Conn., inquiries from people
seeking car pool information increased 15 percent over this time
last year, said Byron L. York, vice president of marketing.
   Many travel agents report customers are shaving days off trips
and looking even harder for bargains.
   ``One thing we've noticed in the last 10 years is vacations are
no longer considered a luxury,'' said Art Kinsman, a manager at the
American Automobile Association. He said he has seen many travelers
shorten trips and choose domestic, rather than international,
destinations.
   And when people are at home, they're also looking to save money.
   ``Our companies are receiving double, triple and in some cases
tenfold increases in requests for information about customer
conversions'' from oil to gas heat, said Thomas Kiley, president of
the New England Gas Association. ``The interest has mushroomed and
it can be targeted right back to the events of the Middle East.''
   The association represents 26 gas distributors in six New
England states. They serve more than 2 million customers.
   Michael Netkovick, spokesman for Energy North in Manchester,
N.H., which supplies 80 percent of the natural gas in that state,
said business has been up since August with at least 200 customers
converting to natural gas from oil.
   Laurie Hanson, a spokeswoman for Con Edison in New York, said
the number of conversion requests from August to October doubled
over the same period in 1989.
   In New Jersey, Public Service Electric &amp; Gas Co. said about
3,600 consumers had switched from oil to gas, a 12 percent increase
over last year.
   ``We generally do get more interest in the fall,'' said PSE&amp;G
spokeswoman Priscilla Suber. ``But the interest we're seeing now is
spectacular.''
   Homeowners requesting free energy audits are up 100 percent to
200 percent in Massachusetts, said Rachel Shimshak, policy director
of the state's energy office. In an audit, an expert surveys a home
and offer money-saving tips.
   ``That tells me people are really concerned about home heating
costs and taking steps to try to save money and energy now, and
guard themselves against future volatility,'' Shimshak said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0006 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 2352EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Belt-SanderRacing     11-04 0354</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Belt-Sander Racing,0423</SECOND>
<HEAD>Belt-Sander Racing: Here's a Sport That's Downright Gritty</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JERRY HARKAVY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BATH, Maine (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Locals at the Triple R bar set aside football
and billiards for a sport with true grit: belt-sander racing.
   Nine competitors and 50 spectators showed up at the biker bar
Sunday for the fall national tournament of the sport that turns
ordinary power tools into lean, mean racing machines. Winners
received T-shirts and trophies.
   ``Bored contractors need something to do,'' said Dana ``Mad
Dog'' McLean, explaining the appeal of the pastime popular among
carpenters and motorcyclists.
   During a race, sanders zoom side-by-side down a waist-high,
24-foot-long plywood track divided into two lanes. With electrical
cords draped over the track's side walls, the sanders fly to the
finish and slam into foot-thick foam pads.
   Some of the machines have been clocked at 3 to 3{ seconds, said
race organizer Karl Grose.
   Despite safety warnings by woodworking teachers and power tool
manufacturers, racers insist their sport poses little danger.
   No accidents have been reported. But the track is sometimes
showered with sparks when an electrical cord becomes separated from
its speeding sander.
   Belt-sander racing was introduced to Maine after Triple R
co-owner Keith Murphy saw it on television about five years ago.
   ``It was from a bar in California, just a five-minute clip, and
I thought, `We've got to try this some time,''' he said.
   Murphy and his friends built a track, and word of the sport
spread.
   ``Evidently, there are little pockets of racers all over the
country, and we're starting to find out about each other,'' Grose
said.
   Racers debate the merits of Makita, Black &amp; Decker or
Porter-Cable much like stock car crews argue the performance of
Fords and Chevys. Others tinker with their sanders in hopes of
making them a fraction of a second faster.
   ``A stock Craftsman, right out of the box,'' said McLean,
pointing to his racing machine.
   Racers also are of two minds on the fastest sandpaper. Some
prefer coarse for a firmer ``bite.'' Others say finer grit provides
more surface contact.
   Belt-sander racing rules were lax in the sport's early days.
   ``It was no holds barred, cheating was encouraged, you could
reach out and cut the other guy's cord,'' Grose said.
   ``Now, we modified it to one rule - You can't mess with the
other guy's sander.'' Otherwise, he said, ``we're pretty much
winging it.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0007 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 2353EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Obit-Martin-List     11-04 0193</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Obit-Martin-List,0194</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mary Martin's Broadway, Film Performances</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Obit-Martin, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here is a list of the Broadway productions in
which Mary Martin appeared and some of her movie credits.
   ``Leave It to Me,'' 1938, musical, 291 performances.
   ``One Touch of Venus,'' 1943, musical, 567 performances.
   ``Lute Song,'' 1946, a play with music, 142 performances.
   ``South Pacific,'' 1949, musical, 1,925 performances.
   ``Kind Sir,'' 1953, play, 165 performances.
   ``Peter Pan,'' 1954, musical, 152 performances.
   ``The Skin of Our Teeth,'' 1955, play revival, 22 performances.
   ``The Sound of Music,'' 1959, musical, 1,443 performances.
   ``Jennie,'' 1963, musical, 82 performances.
   ``I Do! I Do!'' 1966, musical, 560 performances.
   ``Do You Turn Somersaults?'' 1978, play, 16 performances.
   
   Among her movie credits:
   ``The Great Victor Herbert,'' 1939.
   ``Rhythm on the River,'' 1940.
   ``Love Thy Neighbour,'' 1940.
   ``Kiss the Boys Goodbye,'' 1941.
   ``New York Town,'' 1941.
   ``Birth of the Blues,'' 1941.
   ``Star Spangled Rhythm,'' 1942.
   ``Happy Go Lucky,'' 1942.
   ``True to Life,'' 1943.
   ``Night and Day,'' 1946.
   ``Main Street to Broadway,'' 1953.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0008 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 2354EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-FightingforLife     11-04 0745</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Fighting for Life,0947</SECOND>
<HEAD>Capital Murder Defendant's Plight Draws Attention in Germany</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Monday AMs report.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By MICHELLE MITTELSTADT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DALLAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In Germany, Ricky Morrow's plight is the stuff of
passionate demonstrations and letter-writing campaigns.
   But in Dallas, where he is awaiting the start Thursday of his
third murder trial for a killing he admits to committing, most
people don't even know his name.
   Morrow is being tried on capital murder charges in the January
1982 death of a security guard. He says the shooting occurred
accidentally while he was trying to rob First Texas Savings and
Loan.
   ``I'm not innocent of a crime. I'm innocent of capital murder,''
he says from his jail cell in Dallas. Under Texas law, a killing
during the commission of a felony can bring the death penalty.
   ``We are trying to do everything on our side to save Ricky,''
says Eva Marie Kaifenheim of Munich, Germany, who has orchestrated
a letter-writing campaign that has resulted in more than 200 notes
to members of the U.S. news media, officials and diplomats. The
letters accuse prosecutors of acting improperly in Morrow's case.
   Ms. Kaifenheim said she learned of the case through the human
rights organization Amnesty International, which employs her sister
and other family members.
   Last year, more than 500 demonstrators marched through the
Bavarian capital bearing placards saying, ``Life for Ricky
Morrow,'' Ms. Kaifenheim said.
   ``There are a lot of people here in Munich aware of wha is
going on in Dallas,'' she said.
   Morrow's initial November 1983 capital murder conviction in the
death of Mark Frazier was overturned by the Texas Court of Criminal
Appeals in March 1988 because of an improper question posed to
prospective jurors. A second trial ended in a mistrial in July
1989.
   ``It was a complete accident, something I never intended to
happen,'' Morrow said of the shooting. ``I was drunk, I was on
psychiatric medication, I had just been released from a hospital
seven days before.
   ``In my own mind, I do not think that it would be any more wrong
for me to die than it was for him. ... He should be living today
and would be living today had I not gone out and got drunk and
decided to rob a bank. But I did and it happened.''
   But he questions the zeal with which he is being prosecuted,
noting that Dallas County prosecutors have never lost a capital
case since the death penalty was reinstituted in 1976.
   ``There's a reason they have never lost one,'' Morrow said.
``They will do anything.
   ``They're spending millions and millions of dollars just to get
a notch on their belt. That's what capital cases in Dallas County
are all about.''
   Chief Assistant District Attorney Norman Kinne confirms that his
office has won all 49 capital murder cases tried since 1976.
   Morrow, 39, of Houston, and Ms. Kaifenheim contend the district
attorney's office has resorted to perjured testimony, intimidation
of potential witnesses and other unethical acts to ensure the death
penalty.
   Ms. Kaifenheim rattles off the names of wrongfully convicted
inmates Randall Dale Adams and Lenell Geter, who were freed by the
courts amid allegations of misconduct by Dallas County prosecutors.
   Morrow said prosecutors refused a plea bargain that would have
kept him behind bars, without possibility for parole, until the age
of 70.
   Assistant District Attorney Dan Hagood, who is prosecuting
Morrow, declined to respond to the allegations.
   ``I can't talk about a pending case. Ethically, you are not
supposed to,'' he said. But he confirmed his office has received
letters from the Germans.
   Morrow's attorney, Keith Jagmin, also declined to discuss the
trial, which started in July with jury selection.
   Ms. Kaifenheim said she obtained the name of Morrow, who then
was on Texas' death row, and that of another death row inmate in
1987 from her sister, Antonie, who works with Amnesty
International.
   The human rights organization unconditionally opposes the death
penalty, said Alli Miller, Amnesty International USA's director of
programs against the death penalty.
   Amnesty members in one country are asked to ``adopt'' another
country. In this instance, Germany has ``adopted'' the United
States and protests U.S. death penalty cases, Ms. Miller said.
   But the action undertaken by Ms. Kaifenheim was at her own
behest, not the group's, she said. Amnesty International does not
become involved with capital cases until the defendant has been
sentenced.
   After obtaining Morrow's name and address, Ms. Kaifenheim sent
him a letter and a fruitcake for Christmas in 1987.
   ``Ricky wrote me saying he was very happy for the cake, but even
happier by the letter,'' she said in a telephone interview from
Munich conducted in German.
   ``She had also sent some other inmate the same thing and he
never responded. I did respond because it was something you don't
get in prison and I was moved by it,'' Morrow said.
   That initial contact sparked a correspondence that has
intensified over the years. Ms. Kaifenheim said that during a bleak
period a year or so ago when Morrow tried to take his own life, she
wrote him daily to boost his spirits.
   She plans on coming to Dallas when the trial begins.
   ``I will be in court each day,'' she said.
   Morrow said Ms. Kaifenheim's concern renewed his interest in
fighting for what he calls a fair trial.
   ``Her primary concern is the same as mine, that I get a fair
trial, and that's all I'm asking for,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0009 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 2356EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Gulf-SaudiWomen     11-04 0789</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Gulf-Saudi Women,1012</SECOND>
<HEAD>Saudi Women, Stirred By Crisis, Wait For New Freedom</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Monday AMs report.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY20 Nov. 4.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MORT ROSENBLUM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Special Correspondent</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JIDDAH, Saudi Arabia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   On weekends by the Red Sea, women in
head-to-toe black shrouds picnic discreetly beneath umbrellas.
These days, however, some prefer bare knees as they blast along on
jet skis.
   Times are changing for Saudi women, but those who will speak out
on the subject disagree sharply over how much and how fast. The
Persian Gulf crisis, most say, is accelerating a process already
under way.
   ``We've been spoiled with an easy life and never thought about
independence,'' said Faiza Ambah, a Saudi reporter for the Arab
News. ``If war breaks out, we are going to have to depend on
ourselves.''
   She shares a newsroom with men but covers her hair and clothes
with black wraps. Her bookshelf contains Danielle Steele's
``Changes,'' but she is careful to note she brought it in for a
friend.
   In Saudi Arabia, women have equal rights but far fewer
privileges than men. They cannot drive or expose their skin to
public view. They can work but, with rare exceptions, not around
men.
   Men and women together, in cars, on the street or in
restaurants, must be married. Dating and parties are strictly
chaperoned and only take place behind the walls of private homes.
   Transgressors risk at least a rap on the arm from an Islamic
vice squad, if not a term in jail.
   Women began school only in the early 1960s, when Saudi Arabia
also abolished slavery.
   ``You can imagine the pressure,'' said an Egyptian diplomat who
knows Saudi Arabia. ``Girls come home from Berkeley with a drivers'
license and a degree and cower from some old man with a stick.''
   Well before the gulf crisis, major shifts were under way. Women
nurses were allowed to work with men doctors in hospitals. Now half
the medical students in Jiddah are women.
   Years ago, some banks opened all-women branches. Now there are
banks operated by women that lend money at a burgeoning pace to
women who are opening shops, cooperatives and small businesses.
   When U.S. troops arrived, a favorite topic was all the women in
uniform, liberated professionals who slung rifles over their
shoulders, manhandled heavy trucks and barked orders at men.
   But foreign troops have been kept out of sight, and women
soldiers wear modest civilian dress when they have to appear among
Saudis.
   More visible are nearly 100,000 Kuwaiti women, traditionally far
freer and more outspoken. As refugees, some attempt to observe
local customs, but their attitudes are not masked by veils.
   Opinions vary widely over the weight of these outside forces.
   ``Anything is possible as long as it is done discreetly,'' said
a Saudia Airlines stewardess, explaining how women forbidden to
drive can frolic on jet skis in prohibited swimwear. ``The
religious police don't go out on the water.''
   A young hospital worker, educated in the liberal climate of
Egypt, wears eye-popping bodices under her black abaya on the rare
occasions she gets out at night for dinner with friends.
   ``I don't think things will change much,'' she said, clearly
distressed at the thought. ``The Saudis are used to it, and they
like it.''
   But Rabaa al-Khateeb, who teaches Shakespeare at Jiddah's Abdul
Aziz University, argued in a ground-breaking article for the Arab
News that it was time to rethink the role of Saudi women.
   She wrote that Saudi Arabia could not continue ``suppressing the
talents and stifling the abilities of one-half the society.'' With
or without a crisis, she said, Saudi Arabia will have to employ its
women to develop and thrive.
   Later, in an interview, she took pains to assure that she was
not urging full-blown women's liberation. ``We accept that we are
different here,'' she said. ``This is our way of life.''
   She said most Saudi women believed that restrictions on their
activities reflected a male desire to protect them rather than to
keep them in an inferior role.
   Nihal al-Omari, a Western-educated journalist, works with the
Nahdha Philanthropic Society in Riyadh which marshals women
volunteers for health and social services.
   She sees important recent strides but a long road ahead. ``All
the changes that have been happening lately,'' she said, ``all
could go back to before.''
   Even among the younger generation, pressure for immediate change
is cautious, often muted, and expectations are few.
   ``We feel safe here, taken care of,'' said Aisha, one of eight
young women, mostly students, who gathered at a private home to
tell an American reporter how they looked at their future.
   Aisha, raised in Detroit by Saudi parents, returned only three
years ago but settled into the lifestyle of Jiddah. Although she
still visits the United States, she prefers Saudi Arabia.
   She said she was comfortable with a system where fathers and
brothers had a say in whom she married and forbid Western-style
dating. Her father has two wives, and she thought that worked well.
   ``It's better than fornification,'' she said, looking around to
see if that was the word she meant. A friend corrected her:
``Adultery.''
   But Leena, also educated in America, wanted more job openings
for women, a greater say in how she shaped her life. And, like most
Saudi women interviewed, she wanted to drive.
   ``The crisis will make the process quicker,'' she said. ``It has
opened things up.''
   Asked about priorities, one woman said: ``Freedom of speech
would be nice. Don't quote me.''
   After an hour's debate, most agreed they were content but would
welcome change.
   Leena explained, ``We want to take some of the best you have (in
the West) -your way of thinking - but with the protection and
stability of our way of life.''
   Aisha said: ``Our rulers do what is right. I just wish they
would do it a bit faster.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0010 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 2358EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Albania     11-04 0722</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Albania,0880</SECOND>
<HEAD>Change Is Coming in Albania</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Monday AMs report.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By ALISON SMALE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TIRANA, Albania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   By opening the door of reform just a
crack, Albania's Communist leaders have stirred hopes for change
that ultimately may bring them down.
   For many Albanians and foreign observers the only questions are
when and whether the fall will be slow or sudden, peaceful or
violent.
   Scores of foreign reporters were in Tirana for an international
conference last month, and Albanians of all ages reached out to the
visitors with a thirst for freedom and friendship.
   It was the latest stage of a process that began in May, when the
government promised reform.
   Two months later, thousands of Albanians clambered into foreign
embassies, demanding and receiving the right to emigrate.
   President Ramiz Alia and the secretive elite that runs Albania
pulled back from reform. Conflicting articles in the official media
suggested a conflict between conservatives and liberals in
intellectual, party and government ranks.
   Just after the gathering of Balkan foreign ministers, Albania's
first international conference, another blow fell: the defection of
Ismail Kadare, the country's greatest author and the spiritual
leader of reform.
   In announcing his defection in Paris, Kadare said he had hoped
Alia would become Albania's Mikhail Gorbachev, introducing change.
   Alia and the others denounced as a traitor the man they had held
up as an example of isolated Albania's proud achievements.
   A foreign diplomat, speaking anonymously, said Kadare kept to
his Tirana home for weeks during the summer, seeing only fellow
members of the elite and keeping his distance from Alia's cautious
reforms.
   While the reporters were in Albania, everyone seemed to be
talking of the defection, from a 10-year-old boy in ancient Berat
to professional people in Tirana.
   Most praised Kadare as a great man, but some said he had
abandoned Albania in its hour of need. Few doubted he had dealt a
heavy, perhaps fatal, blow to the leadership.
   ``Enver, Ramiz, they are gone,'' a worker said.
   Alia has edged away from the Stalinist legacy of Enver Hoxha,
who ruled from 1944 until his death in 1985.
   It seems likely that a crackdown would provoke strong response
from the 3.2 million people of Albania, who know of the
anti-Communist revolutions in Eastern Europe and crave contact with
the outside.
   The official course of ``democratization'' through gradual
reform, without abandoning one-party rule, did not work for any of
the other Communist parties in Eastern Europe.
   Albanian leaders appear to bank on what officials describe as
the country's special legacy: veneration of Hoxha.
   His name is emblazoned on hillsides across the land, and his
victorious World War II partisans are commemorated on memorials as
numerous as the hundreds of concrete bunkers he built to defend
Albania.
   Hoxha was the first Albanian since the revered 15th century hero
Scanderbeg, born George Castriota, to win genuine independence for
his people.
   Today's increasingly young population - 77 percent of Albanians
are under 40 - is more inclined to take independence for granted.
The young are impatient for economic improvement and some of the
better life they feel the outside enjoys.
   ``Europe could and ought to do more for the Balkans, and for
Albania especially,'' said a student of English at Tirana
University.
   What course the leadership will take should become clear at the
Communist Party congress expected in about three months.
Parliamentary elections are expected next spring under a new law
that allows the people more scope for nominating candidates.
   Some diplomats feel those events may be too little, and come too
late.
   If violence accompanies change, it will be in keeping with
Albania's turbulent history.
   Life in the mountains that cover 70 percent of the nation has
changed little in centuries. Blood feuds bond the small population
in an intricate network of ancient hatreds.
   There aresigns the leadership realizes action is needed to
avert a crisis.
   The party chiefs of Tirana and the port of Durres, Albania's two
largest cities, were replaced in an extensive shakeup that followed
the July embassy crisis.
   In August, the statue of Josef Stalin was quietly removed from
Shkodra, a northern town. Street signs are notably scarce along
Tirana's central Stalin Boulevard, although the Soviet dictator's
likeness still dominates a nearby park.
   Censorship has been denounced in the state press, but has not
disappeared. A degree of private enterprise has been allowed, and
there is even talk of making the lek convertible.
   They are small changes and seem tentative, in contrast to the
increasingly bold mood in the streets.
   Albanians gleefully invited foreign journalists to share a game
of cards, a drink, a chat, or dragged them hurriedly homes. Their
eagerness made mockery of the slogans plastered everywhere, such
as: ``The unity of the party and people is our strength.''
   Officials were clearly unnerved by the prying of reporters, but
the popular reaction was typified by a Tirana student's comment as
two journalists left her and several friends dining and listening
to Western rock music.
   ``Goodbye,'' she said, smiling. ``You have brought great
gladness to our party.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0011 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 0150EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-GulfRdp 4thLd-Writethru   11-04 0932</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf Rdp, 4th Ld-Writethru,a0669,1138</SECOND>
<HEAD>Iraq Frees Four Americans, Says Peace Plan in Works; Baker to
Mideast</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: UPDATES with French soldiers arriving in Paris, Baker arriving
in Bahrain; EDITS to conform. No pickup.</NOTE>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf-Foreigners, Bjt</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos DHA1-3, AMM1-3</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LAURA KING</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Iraq struck a conciliatory stance on Saturday, freeing four
American hostages and three captured French soldiers and promising
to release more Europeans. Baghdad also indicated it was working on
a new peace plan.
   On Saturday, Iraq's parliament voted to let the 700 Bulgarians
remaining in Iraq and Kuwait leave. Also Saturday, the official
Iraqi News Agency said European contract workers stranded by Iraq's
Aug. 2 invasion of Kuwait now could leave if they wished. INA,
monitored in Cyprus, gave no number.
   Secretary of State James A. Baker III, meanwhile, began a
mission aimed at breaking the 3-month-old Persian Gulf standoff. He
said he would ``lay the foundation'' for military action against
Iraq if economic measures failed to persuade President Saddam
Hussein to withdraw from Kuwait.
   Saddam presided over a meeting of top-echelon officials and army
commanders Saturday to discuss military operations in southern
Iraq, INA said. There were no details on that gathering.
   The freed Americans and French soldiers arrived in Jordan aboard
the same Iraqi Airways flight from Baghdad. At the Amman airport,
they were quickly hustled away by U.S. and French officials.
   The Americans did not speak to reporters except to say they were
tired. Also aboard the flight were about 80 Arab nationals andthree men
who identified themselves as Irish. They did not give
their names.
   The French soldiers were flown home and arrived in Paris early
Sunday. The Americans also were to fly home Sunday.
   One of the Americans, Randall Trinh, 49, of Hacienda Heights,
Calif., was among the hundreds of foreigners kept at strategic
sites as ``human shields'' against potential attack following
Iraq's invasion of Kuwait. It was not known precisely where he was
held.
   The other Americans were identified as Dr. Abdul Kangi, 50, an
Indian-born American from Glencoe, Ill.; Raymond Gales, a diplomat
from the U.S. Embassy in Kuwait, whose hometown and age were not
immediately available; and Michael Barner, 49, of Woodsworth, La.
   Iraq said the four were released as a humanitarian gesture
because they were ``elderly and sick.'' U.S. Embassy sources in
Baghdad said Trinh suffered from a stomach ulcer and Barner had a
neurological disorder. No other ailments were reported.
   Iraq has launched a public-relations offensive regarding
treatment of its foreign ``guests,'' as it calls the hostages.
   It said Saturday it would install international telephone lines
at strategic sites where captives are held so they can talk to
their families. Last week, Iraq offered to allow hostages'
relatives to visit them at Christmas.
   Iraqi officials have expressed fears the United States will use
reports of maltreatment of captives as a reason for a military
strike.
   Western leaders called the selective release of groups of
hostages an effort by Saddam to split their alliance against him.
   A French Embassy spokeswoman expressed appreciation for Iraq's
``good gesture'' of freeing the three soldiers, who were captured
Monday. French officials did not disclose the incident until
Friday.
   A French Defense Ministry spokesman said the three were likely
to face disciplinary action for their ``act of carelessness.''
   France stopped short of admitting the soldiers had blundered
into Iraqi territory, but hinted that had been the case.
   About 13,000 French soldiers are deployed in the gulf region as
part of the 300,000-strong multinational force, made up mainly of
U.S. troops.
   Baker arrived in Bahrain Sunday on a trip that also will take
him to Saudi Arabia, Egypt, Turkey, Britain and France. His
meetings include consultations with Chinese Foreign Minister Qian
Qichen in Cairo.
   The Soviet Union and China are permanent members of the U.N.
Security Council and their support would be essential for any
additional U.N.-backed steps against Iraq.
   On his U.S. jet, Baker told reporters he planned to consult over
eight days in seven countries with leaders of a wide array of Arab
and European nations, including a Moscow stop Thursday to see
Soviet President Mikhail S. Gorbachev.
   He said, ``The purpose of the trip is to discuss with our
coalition partners strengthening the full range of measures that we
have employed to isolate Saddam Hussein ... political measures,
economic measures and military measures, and thereby to lay the
foundation for the possible exercise of all options.
   ``This will improve the prospects for peaceful resolution, and,
at the same time, permit us to be prepared to consider all options
if peaceful ones don't work.''
   Also in the region was French President Francois Mitterrand, who
arrived in Egypt on Saturday and had a meeting set Sunday with
President Hosni Mubarak.
   The Iraqi foreign minister, Tariq Aziz, arrived in Jordan
Saturday for talks with King Hussein, and a senior Jordanian
official said Aziz was carrying a message from Saddam on ``ways to
achieve peace.'' No details were disclosed.
   Aziz accused the United States and Britain of ``escalating their
war rhetoric and threats.'' But he said there were expressions of
interest in a peaceful solution being voiced elsewhere.
   There was word of a planned Iraqi peace initiative from Irish
and Italian parliamentarians, who met with the speaker of Iraq's
ruling National Council. They said the Iraqi plan calls for the
release of all foreigners in return for guarantees from world
powers that Iraq will not be attacked.
   In its Sunday editions, The New York Times quoted Saudi Oil
Minister Hisham Nazer as saying Saudi Arabia had pushed its oil
production above 8.2 million barrels a day and would reach 8.5
million barrels daily early next year. The Times said that, despite
the U.N.-ordered embargo on Iraqi and Kuwaiti oil, the world may
now be producing more than it was before the Persian Gulf crisis.
   On Oct. 31, officials of the International Energy Agency,
meeting in Paris, said the world was making enough oil to meet
demand. At that time, Saudi oil production was reported to be 8
million barrels a day.
   In other developments:
   -Former Japanese Prime Minister Yasuhiro Nakasone arrived in
Baghdad Saturday to try to win the freedom of Japanese hostages.
Although Nakasone's trip is private, it has the Tokyo government's
backing.
   -European Community foreign ministers will meet Monday or
Tuesday in Rome to discuss former West German Chancellor Willy
Brandt's planned private mission to Iraq, the Dutch Foreign
Ministry said in The Hague. Brandt is going to Baghdad on Monday
reportedly to negotiate with Saddam for the release of foreign
hostages.
   The European Community has called for its members not to
negotiate separately on the hostages.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0012 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 1143EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i BC-Chile-Attack 1stLd-Writethru a0672 11-04 0241</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Chile-Attack, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0672,0264</SECOND>
<HEAD>Three U.S. Sailors Injured in Bombing at Restaurant</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: New thruout to UPDATE number of injured, CORRECT time of
explosion, upgrade attribution; No pickup.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>VINA DEL MAR, Chile (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A bomb exploded at a restaurant
injuring eight people, among them three sailors from the U.S.
aircraft carrier Abraham Lincoln, police and the U.S. Navy said
Sunday.
   No group claimed responsibility for the bombing, which occurred
shortly before midnight Saturday in this seaside resort, 180 miles
west of Santiago, according to a police statement.
   In Washington, Navy Cmdr. Stephen Honda said two of the sailors
were treated at a local hospital and released, while the third was
treated on board the Abraham Lincoln. He said the injuries were
limited to cuts and bruises caused by flying glass and other
debris.
   About 40 people were in the restaurant, the Max Moritz, when the
bomb went off. They included a group of sailors from the
Nimitz-class aircraft carrier, docked in the neighboring port city
of Valparaiso on a five-day port stop.
   The bomb was placed near the kitchen and damaged the restaurant
and neighboring buildings, police said without elaborating.
   Three British tourists and two waitresses were also injured in
the attack. One of the Britons was seriously injured, the police
statement said.
   The Abraham Lincoln is transiting around South America as part
of a scheduled inter-fleet transfer from the Atlantic to Pacific
fleet. It is scheduled to arrive in Alameda, Calif., its home port,
in late November.
   The identities of the U.S. sailors were not released.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0013 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 1144EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-TrainingEx-Foes Bjt   11-04 0590</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Training Ex-Foes, Bjt,670</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.S. Considers Training Warsaw Pact Military Officers</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RUTH SINAI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Pentagon may soon be training military
officers from the very countries it once viewed as archenemies.
   The administration is considering requests from members of the
Soviet-led Warsaw Pact - Poland, Hungary, Czechoslovakia, Bulgaria
and Romania - to participate in a program known as International
Military Education and Training (IMET), officials say.
   While the program probably would cost just several hundred
thousand dollars, the symbolic value of such a project would be
much higher.
   ``Who would have believed we would train officers from the very
countries which we viewed as our enemies just last year?'' said one
Defense Department official.
   The possible training project is just one of many options under
consideration by the Bush administration to help countries which
this year discarded more than four decades of communist rule.
   ``Money will be very tight and we're considering a range of
things for Eastern Europe,'' said a Bush administration official,
who, like the other official, asked not to be named. ``IMET is one
of the things that has been thought about.''
   That official said the decision on whether to include any East
Europeans in the program would not be made until December, when the
State Department puts together its budget request for the fiscal
year that begins next Oct. 1.
   The program is funded under the foreign aid bill and
administered jointly with the Pentagon. The 1990 program totaled
$47.2 million. The size of the individual country programs ranges
from a low of $15,000, up to $3.38 million for Turkey.
   There are more than 800,000 troops in the Warsaw Pact, not
counting the Soviet Union. But the alliance is crumbling; it lost
one of seven members this year when East Germany merged with West
Germany, and Hungary is preparing to leave.
   Pact members have planned a summit later this year to discuss
the alliance's future, with plans to transform it to a political
rather than military grouping.
   Meanwhile, its members have begun reducing the size of their
Soviet-armed and trained military to save money for the expensive
and painful transition from a state-run economy to a free-market
system.
   The Soviet Union also is trying to save money. Its forces have
begun pulling out of Hungary and Czechoslovakia.
   There are no Soviet troops stationed in Romania and Bulgaria,
and those in Poland and the former territory of East Germany
eventually will be withdrawn now that Moscow has decided to bring
all its troops home.
   The way for cooperation with the United States was paved earlier
this year when NATO leaders agreed to set up regular diplomatic
contacts with members of the Warsaw Pact.
   Since then, diplomats from Eastern Europe have received regular
briefings at NATO headquarters in Brussels, mostly about the crisis
in the Persian Gulf and about the Soviet Union.
   NATO is debating how far to go in sharing information with the
East Europeans as long as they are still allied militarily with
Moscow. The East Europeans, eager for any contact with the West as
they restructure their economies and social systems, want more.
   ``As we move away from the Warsaw Pact, it's clear we have to
diversify our military ties,'' said one Hungarian official. He said
groups of military historians, lawyers and sharpshooters from
Hungary and the United States have paid visits to each others'
countries.
   In September, Poland and Czechoslovakia offered medical
facilities for U.S. troops being deployed in Saudi Arabia. Romania
offered the troops recreation facilities on the Black Sea, and
Bulgaria said it would send troops.
   Romania also has asked for U.S. advice on setting up a military
chaplain's service - something that was outlawed under the atheist
communist regime - and on revamping the military judge advocate's
office, the officials said.
   But the United States still has concerns about Romania's human
rights record, especially after the government - made up of many
former communist officials - used club-wielding factory workers to
violently suppress anti-government protesters last June.
   ``Romania still has to correct its image,'' said one U.S.
official. ``They've taken some steps in the right direction.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0014 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 1146EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-ShrinkingMountain     11-04 0206</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Shrinking Mountain,0221</SECOND>
<HEAD>This Mountain's High Enough, Authorities Say</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SAAS GRUND, Switzerland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Alpine villagers who wanted to
rearrange the rocks atop Mount Fletschhorn to restore its original
official height have been told to leave the peak alone, newspapers
said Sunday.
   Until 1952, the mountain in southern Switzerland had been
formally listed at 13,123 feet, or 4,001 meters. Four thousand
meters is considered a psychologial barrier for climbers seeking a
challenge.
   The revision cut its official height to 13,113 feet, or 3,998
meters, possibly due to erosion.
   Three years ago, the mayor of Saas Grunt launched a drive to
move a few rocks around at the top to re-establish the mountain's
former height, and possibly make it more appealing to climbers.
   But environmentalists and climbers' groups, including the Swiss
Alpine Club, opposed the idea, urging the mountain be left as it
is.
   Authorities in Valais canton, or state, agreed. The Valais
surveyor's office decided Fletschhorn is ``a majestic part'' of the
Alps and should remain in its natural state, Sunday's reports said.
   The village's mayor, German Anthamatten, was quoted as saying he
may challenge the ruling.
   But the newspapers said he probably faced an uphill battle. They
said in a recent measurement, the mountain had lost another five
feet of height.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0015 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 1152EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--TanzaniaVote     11-04 0139</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Tanzania Vote,0129</SECOND>
<HEAD>President Mwinyi Wins Second Term in One-Party Elections</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DAR ES SALAAM, Tanzania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Ali Hassan Mwinyi has been
re-elected to a second five-year term as president of the one-party
state, the government announced.
   Mwinyi received 95.5 percent of the votes cast in balloting Oct.
28, said the chairman of Tanzania's electoral commission, Justice
Lameck Mfalila, on Saturday.
   Mwinyi, 65, is also chairman of the only political party, the
ruling Chama Cha Mapinduzi. He was to be sworn in Thursday.
   Nearly three-quarters of the East African nation's 7.3 million
registered voters cast ballots in the poll.
   Tanzania's 1977 constitution stipulates a president can serve no
more than two successive five-year terms. Mwinyi was elected in
1985 when Tanzania's founder, Julius Nyerere, retired.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0016 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 1156EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SriLanka     11-04 0163</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Sri Lanka,0168</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rebels Raid Northern Outpost, 10 Soldiers Killed</HEAD>
<DATELINE>COLOMBO, Sri Lanka (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Tamil rebels killed 10 soldiers Sunday
in an attack on military outpost that the army had captured from
the insurgents last month, military officials said.
   They said the outpost at a Hindu temple at Mavaddipuram in the
northern Jaffna district was attacked three times by the rebels.
   Mavaddipuram is one of the positions taken during an operation
last month to a secure a stronger foothold in the Jaffna Peninsula,
the main stronghold of the Tamil Tiger rebels.
   About 16 square miles were brought under government control,
linking several bases that previously had been isolated in rebel
territory.
   The raid Sunday was the first retaliatory action by the rebels
to dislodge the troops from their new positions.
   At least 14,000 people have been killed in the Tamil rebellion
since it began in 1983. Tamils, most of whom are Hindus, claim
discrimination by the Sinhalese majority who are predominantly
Buddhists.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0017 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 1214EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-SoccerRampage 1stLd-Writethru a0682 11-04 0227</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soccer Rampage, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0682,0242</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hundreds of Fans Rampage in Leipzig; Police Kill One</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 2 grafs to UPDATE with nine youths seriously
injured. Pickup 3rd pvs, `Damage was...'</NOTE>
<DATELINE>BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   City officials in Leipzig on Sunday demanded
better security at soccer games after rampaging fans smashed cars,
looted stores and fought street battles. An 18-year-old man was
killed by police, authorities said.
   Nine youths were seriously injured in the violence Saturday, 80
people were arrested and a police officer was hospitalized, police
said.
   Damage was estimated in the millions of dollars. It was one of
the worst soccer riots ever in the former East German territory.
   The rioting broke out following Berlin's 4-1 victory over Saxony
Leipzig. Fans fought pitched battles outside the stadium, then
hundreds stormed through the city.
   About 500 youths squared off with police at a subway station.
Police officials said officers fired warning shots, and then a
young man was gunned down in what was only described as an
emergency situation. The 18-year-old was not identified.
   One large truck was set afire and at least 12 cars and four
police wagons were demolished. The ground floor of a department
store was gutted by looting and vandalism, authorities said.
   A police official, speaking on condition of anonymity, said most
of the rioters were from Berlin.
   City Council President Dieter Gaasenbeek demanded Sunday that
police bolster security precautions for soccer games.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0018 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 1236EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p AM-LandfillElection Bjt   11-04 0552</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Landfill Election, Bjt,0701</SECOND>
<HEAD>Landfill Vote Splits Friends, Families and Neighbors</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RAY FORMANEK Jr.</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PHILIPPI, W.Va. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   There hasn't been much friendly banter or
cordial conversation at the Blue and Gray Restaurant since a
developer proposed turning an old strip mine into a $30 million
landfill for out-of-state garbage.
   ``I've never in my life seen anything like this,'' said Lisa
Knotts, a waitress at the popular Main Street diner. ``People used
to sit and talk, discuss things.
   ``Now, they're one way or the other. They're dead set against it
or for it.''
   Barbour County officials expect a record 90 percent of the
struggling coal-mining county's 8,776 registered voters to cast
ballots Tuesday to settle the dispute.
   The vote is the first under the state's new solid-waste law that
allows residents of each of the state's 55 counties to block
landfills that would accept more than 10,000 tons of trash or more
each month.
   Some people in the north-central West Virginia county said
landfill opponents hold a slim lead. Others said the race is too
close to call.
   ``It's not very difficult to find people fixing to fight,'' said
the Rev. John Lepp, pastor of two United Methodist churches in the
county. ``I don't know what it will take to get people to
reconcile.
   ``I've been told there are some people who are not coming back
to my churches because they think I favor one side.''
   No blood has been shed, the 56-year-old Lepp said, ``but I don't
like the subtle things like not speaking to some people or turning
around when they come into a store or a room.''
   ``This is the biggest thing to hit Philippi since the Civil
War,'' school bus driver Rex Freeman said, referring to the town's
claim that it was the site of that war's first land battle.
   The landfill, proposed last year by Energy Resource Management
Services Inc., would be at an old surface coal mine about seven
miles west of Philippi, or 135 miles south of Pittsburgh.
   An average of 7,500 tons of household waste - most of it brought
in by train from the Northeast - would be dumped there daily, said
John Faltis, the company's chief executive officer.
   Faltis, who owns the company with a Dutch investor, said they
would invest about $30 million to prepare the site. An additional
$24 millio would go toward special railroad cars that could haul
waste in and take coal out to market.
   He said he expects to make $200 million profit by the time the
landfill is filled in 25 years.
   Tonnage fees and other charges would inject $5 million annually
into the county's sputtering economy and residents would get free
trash pickup, said Faltis, who has operated coal mines and other
businesses in the area for nearly 20 years.
   The company has said the landfill will generate more than 200
permanent jobs, paying $8 to $15 an hour. Eighty-five percent of
the employees will be from Barbour County under an contract signed
by Faltis and the Barbour County Commission last summer.
   Barbour County's unemployment rate in September was 9.1 percent,
compared to the statewide rate of 5.4 percent. The demand for
clean, non-polluting fuel has cut the market for the area's
high-sulphur coal, and new technology means fewer miners are needed
to produce what coal is mined.
   ``Ten years ago you would have seen 100 working coal mines here
and thousands of miners earning close to $40,000 or $50,000 a
year,'' Lepp said. ``Those days are long gone.''
   Philippi, the county seat, has about 3,100 residents and is home
of the private Alderson-Broaddus College.
   Opponents question the landfill's safety and the wisdom of
bringing in huge amounts of out-of-state trash.
   ``When you get done filling the site 25 years down the road,
you're going to have 75 million tons of garbage sitting atop the
highest point in Barbour County,'' said businessman Chuck Schnautz.
``We'd be setting ourselves up to receive a 75-million-ton pile of
garbage and the current technology can't guarantee that we won't
have problems with it.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0019 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 1246EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Obit-Levy     11-04 0444</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Levy,0558</SECOND>
<HEAD>Former Commander Of Deadly King David Hotel Attack Dies</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SERGEI SHARGORODSKY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Yisrael Levy, an underground fighter in
Israel's struggle for independence who carried out the 1946 bombing
of a Jerusalem hotel that killed 91 people, has died. He was 64.
   Levy died Friday and was buried the same day, according to a
death notice in the press. The cause of death was not given.
   Levy belonged to Irgun Zvai Leumi, the militant Jewish
underground that, led by Menachem Begin, fought the British for
independence in the 1940s. Irgun carried out dozens of attacks on
British army, government and police targets.
   Its deadliest operation was the bombing of the King David, a
luxury six-story hotel that housed the British Government
Secretariat and army headquarters.
   The Jerusalem-born Levy, who joined Irgun at age 14 and used the
nom de guerre of Gideon, was entrusted with the mission, having
already participated in a bombing of British police headquarters in
Jerusalem in 1945.
   ``Giddy's tremendous inventive and creative powers were called
upon to the full,'' Begin recalled in his memoirs, ``The Revolt.''
Begin was prime minister from 1977 to 1983.
   ``It is not simple to penetrate the very heart of the military
government ... We were well aware that this was the largest of our
operations to date and that it might turn out to be unique in the
history of partisan wars of liberation,'' Begin wrote.
   On the morning of July 22, 1946, Levy and his accomplices
entered the La Regence Cafe in the hotel basement dressed as Arabs
and planted milk cans packed with 500 pounds of explosives. Levy
was reportedly disguised as a Sudanese waiter.
   No customers were in the cafe. The attackers locked La Regence's
15 Arab workers in a side room and set the timers to go off 30
minutes later. Two British officers who entered the cafe clashed
with the attackers and one officer was shot and killed, while the
other was wounded.
   Outside the hotel, an Irgun cover team exchanged fire with
British soldiers and then set off a firecracker. In the confusion,
the attackers freed the Arabs then fled.
   ``Suddenly, the whole town seemed to shudder ... the entire wing
of a huge building was cut off as with a knife,'' Begin recalled.
   The 200 casualties included 91 dead, among them senior British
officers, 15 Jews who worked for the British government, and
several Arabs. The Irgun suffered one fatality.
   Begin said the Irgun had telephoned warnings to the hotel, the
French Consulate and the Palestine Post newspaper about 25 minutes
before the blast.
   The bloodbath resulted in ``days of pain and nights of sorrow''
for the Irgun, Begin wrote.
   The attack haunted Levy for years, according to friends of his
quoted in the daily Yedioth Ahronoth.
   Levy stayed with the Irgun until it was disbanded in 1948, the
year Israel won statehood. He later became a stationery store-owner
and lived a quiet life in suburban Tel Aviv.
   ``He was a modest man, a family man,'' said Yehiel Kadishai, an
aide to Begin. ``I don't recall him ever speaking about the (King
David) operation.''
   He is survived by a wife, two daughters and a son.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0020 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 1246EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Mandela     11-04 0228</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mandela,0244</SECOND>
<HEAD>Malaysia Gives $5 Million To Mandela To Fight Apartheid</HEAD>
<DATELINE>KUALA LUMPUR, Malaysia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   South African anti-apartheid
leader Nelson Mandela received a $5 million contribution from
Malaysia and other aid pledges before leaving for Brunei on Sunday.
   Mandela, near the end of two-week tour of six nations, said the
money will help fund African National Congress efforts while its
leaders negotiate with the government to end racial segregation
policies.
   Mandela, 72, attended a dinner in his honor Saturday in the
capital of Kuala Lumpur. He also received other pledges of
assistance, including aid to build housing for more than 20,000
political prisoners expected to be released soon.
   In Brunei, Mandela's last stop on the international trip, he was
greeted by Prince Mohamad Bolkiah, the foreign minister of the
small Asian nation.
   On Monday, Prince Mohamad is scheduled to host a lunch in
Mandela's honor. Later, Mandela will meet with Sultan Hassanal
Bolkiah in Bandar Seri Begawan, the capital.
   Mandela also visited Australia, India, Indonesia and Japan.
   Mandela said Australia had promised $15 million; Indonesia $10
million and India $6.5 million.
   Mandela, however, complained Japan did not make any financial
contribution to the ANC.
   Prime Minister Toshiki Kaifu said Japan could not provide aid to
the ANC because of its policy of not giving assistance to political
parties in other nations. But Kaifu told Mandela Japan would
provide aid to grass-roots South African groups.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0021 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 1248EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-VietnamRun     11-04 0386</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Vietnam Run,0477</SECOND>
<HEAD>Americans Cheered Along Cambodia-Vietnam Peace Run</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DENIS D. GRAY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BANGKOK, Thailand (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two Americans, one a severely wounded
war veteran, said Sunday that Cambodians and Vietnamese offered
them water and rest on their 120-mile ``Friendship Run'' between
Phnom Penh and Ho Chi Minh City.
   ``I've been praying for 20 years to come back,'' said Clebe
McClary, who in 1968 lost an eye and an arm as a U.S. Marine
lieutenant in Vietnam.
   The run was staged to try to speed reconciliation between the
United States and the governments of Cambodia and Vietnam, neither
of which Washington recognizes.
   ``If we don't get together and smile and talk we'll never have
any friendship. We caused a lot of destruction in Vietnam and I
think we owe them something,'' McClary said. ``Hey man, the war's
over.''
   The run began Tuesday in the Cambodian capital and ended
Saturday in Ho Chi Minh City, formerly Saigon.
   McClary, 49, and Stan Cottrell, 47, complained of the blistering
heat but were effusive in describing villagers offering them
hammocks, massages and water. Hundreds of children would follow
them along the way, they said.
   Unarmed Vietnamese policemen escorted them for part of the way
but there were no incidents and the two said they felt generally at
ease, even in the Cambodian countryside where a guerrilla war rages
between the government and three opposing factions.
   Their longest daily run was 42 miles. A ceremony was held when
they reached the Cambodian-Vietnamese border and some Vietnamese
joined them for a small segment of the run.
   McClary, from Pawley's Island, S.C., was making his first trip
back to Vietnam since the war, in which he lost many friends.
   ``Even during the war I loved the people and the country,'' he
said. ``I was wounded seven times and had 34 operations and they
said I'd never walk again.'' He was on his feet shortly after the
last operation in 1969 and 10 years later became an avid runner.
   He said he wanted to bring other veterans back to Vietnam,
perhaps on another run. In the United States, McClary speaks to and
counsels high schools, church groups and businesses on leadership
and motivation.
   Cottrell, who lives in a suburb of Atlanta, is a veteran long
distance runner. In 1981, he crossed the United States at a rate of
53 miles a day.
   He also has made peace runs along China's Great Wall, in the
Soviet Union and, last July, between Berlin and Warsaw. In 1988,
Cottrell completed a ``Vietnam Friendship Run'' from the capital,
Hanoi, to the central coast city of Da Nang, near which McClary was
wounded.
   ``I believe that one person can make a difference, that
individuals can break down the walls that divide us,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0022 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 1254EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Soviet-Violence Bjt   11-04 0694</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Violence, Bjt,0821</SECOND>
<HEAD>Political Violence Rising Along the Edges of the Soviet Union</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto MOSB1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BRYAN BRUMLEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ERASKH, U.S.S.R. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Edik Badalian, a fatigue-clad guerrilla
in the mountains of Armenia, raised his 1905 vintage carbine and
squeezed off a shot at an imaginary invader from the neighboring
Soviet republic of Azerbaijan.
   ``We usually carry hunting rifles. But we have what we need,''
said Badalian, 38, who also wore a pistol. Members of his eight-man
unit showed off a handmade mortar and rocket-propelled grenade
launchers, and said they had automatic weapons hidden in the hills.
   ``We station ourselves around farms and settlements to protect
them against Azerbaijanis,'' said Badalian, who works as a
construction engineer by day and patrols by night.
   A few miles away, Soviet troops did sentry duty on the rugged
border between Armenia and Azerbaijan, the scene of ethnic clashes
for two years.
   The sealed frontier between the two republics symbolizes the
political violence that is rising in distant corners of the Soviet
Union as the Kremlin's political authority falls.
   Last week, two Armenian shepherds were killed on the border and
Armenian guerrillas briefly took four Soviet soldiers hostage in
retaliation for the detention of several local residents in the
embattled enclave of Nagorno-Karabakh.
   At least three separatists were killed Friday in ethnic strife
in the southeastern republic of Moldavia.
   In the Caucasian republic of Georgia, a politician was shot in
the arm two days before balloting on Oct. 28.
   Over the past 18 months, violence also has struck along the
border between Uzbekistan and Kirgizia, the Fergana Valley of
Uzbekistan, the Georgian capital of Tbilisi and the Abkhazian
section of Georgia.
   The fighting has helped keep alive rumors that the military and
KGB security police might be plotting to crack down against the
disorder that has accompanied the reforms of President Mikhail S.
Gorbachev.
   One rumor depicts Gorbachev as the leader of the crackdown,
another as its victim.
   In Armenia and Georgia, where passions are running high, people
accuse Gorbachev of trying inflame rather than quell the violence.
   ``The Kremlin is creating another Lebanon in the Caucasus. They
want to create the illusion that the Caucasians are fighting among
themselves, and that the Russians must go in and restore order,''
said Zviad Gamsakhurdia, who is emerging as the dominant politician
in Georgia.
   Soviet central authorities have balked at open intervention in
Georgia since April 9, 1989, when army paratroopers used sharpened
shovels to disperse a peaceful rally in Tbilisi, killing 19.
   The incident sent shock waves through the entire Soviet Union,
and shoved Georgia firmly toward a declaration of independence.
   That momentum was evident in balloting last week as
Gamsakhurdia's Round Table non-Communist bloc won control of the
Georgian Supreme Soviet legislature on a platform of independence
and capitalism.
   The voting was peaceful, the campaign at times violent. Two days
before the electio, Gamsakhurdia's rival, Georgi Chanturia, was
shot in the arm.
   Chanturia accused Gamsakhurdia of arranging the shooting on
orders from the KGB. Gamsakhurdia retorted that Chanturia either
staged the event or was shot by central authorities seeking to
spark civil war.
   The situation is just as murky in Moldavia. There, the
legislature has declared sovereignty from Moscow and talking of
reunifying with neighboring Romania, from which it was separated in
World War II.
   But ethnic Russians and Ukrainians have declared their own
``Dniester republic'' in eastern Moldavia, and the Gagauz - a group
of Christian Turks - have proclaimed independence in southern
Moldavia.
   On Wednesday, Soviet Interior Ministry troops moved against the
Gagauz, and Moldavian Interior Ministry troops clashed with the
Russians and Ukrainians on Friday.
   The lines are not much clearer along the Armenian-Azerbaijani
border.
   The trouble began in late 1988 as Christian Armenians demanded
control over Nagorno-Karabakh, a largely Armenian enclave located
just over the border in mostly Moslem Azerbaijan. Scores have died
in the dispute, and tens of thousands have fled their homes.
   Last winter the two sides clashed with armor and artillery at
Eraskh and elsewhere. Soviet Interior Ministry troops quelled the
fighting, and now the only visible armor belongs to central
authorities.
   Sgt. Viktor Rezanov, who commands a 10-member border checkpoint
at Eraskh, keeps the machine gun of his armored personnel trained
on Armenia.
   ``They drive by at night sometimes and shoot off their guns,''
said Rezanov, 20, from the Russian city of Chelyabinsk. Squad
members wear flak jackets to protect them against snipers or
ambush.
   The heavy armor keeps guerrillas in check, but tension persists,
said Lt. Vladimir Pomashkin, 25.
   ``The biggest threat is from armed people who have no right to
be carrying guns,'' said Pomashkin, from the Russian city of Kirov.
``They get a gun in their hands ... and they think they should use
it.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0023 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 1259EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p AM-HouseRdp     11-04 0686</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-House Rdp,820</SECOND>
<HEAD>GOP Tries To Avoid Big Losses Tuesday</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Election Rdp Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JIM DRINKARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Republicans are spooked by recent negative
polls for their House candidates and hope to capitalize on the
unpopularity of Congress to avoid heavy losses on Tuesday.
   ``Praise the president, and bash the Democrat Congress,'' said
Rep. Guy Vander Jagt, summarizing his party's message for the final
days of the campaign.
   ``There is a ferocious anti-Congress hostility out there,'' said
Vander Jagt, who is chairman of the House GOP campaign
organization. ``It's a prairie fire. And it doesn't take too much
to shift (the feeling) from against Congress to against those who
RUN Congress.''
   But party strategists concede that they will have a hard time
fully recovering from the decline Republican candidates have
suffered in recent polls.
   Those losses have been based largely on a perception that the
party, and President Bush in particular, sought to defend the
wealthy against tax increases and then endorsed a package that
imposes higher taxes on nearly everyone.
   ``You've got a big challenge if you want to overcome in 10 days
what was three years of an opposite message,'' said Vander Jagt,
R-Mich.
   Bush has been on the hustings peddling the message that the
spending cuts in his budget deal with Congress are his, and the new
taxes belong solely to the Democrats. Whether that will sell with
voters remains to be seen.
   ``That message, that the devil made me do it, just is not
credible,'' said Larry Sabato, a political analyst at the
University of Virginia.
   Polls show that after a precipitous drop three weeks ago,
Republican candidates have mostly regained their footing. But there
continues to be slippage, particularly in the 29 races for seats
where no incumbent is seeking re-election.
   The open seats are where Democrats have their highest hopes for
making gains.
   Two are virtually certain to move to the Democratic column, and
both represent comebacks for former House members. In Arkansas' 2nd
District, Ray Thornton is considered a shoo-in, and in Hawaii's 1st
District, liberal Neil Abercrombie is expected to win.
   The party is straining to hold on to previously Democratic open
seats in Maine, Florida, New Jersey, Ohio and Texas. But it has a
good shot at picking up Republican seats in Connecticut, Iowa,
Idaho and Rhode Island.
   Democratic gains in the polls have been particularly strong
among senior citizens and women, leading analysts to conclude that
the party's economic fairness message is bringing core Democrats
home.
   Sabato said the net pickup for Democrats may well be 10 or more
seats, about twice the shift analysts in both parties had predicted
around Labor Day. ``There's a definite drift toward the
Democrats,'' he said.
   The party now holds a 258 to 175 majority in the House, with two
vacancies. A 10-seat shift would give Democrats their largest House
advantage in more than a decade.
   But along with the Republicans' partial recovery have come two
other phenomena: a day-to-day instability in poll numbers and a
marked erosion of support for incumbents in both parties.
   ``The numbers are jumping all over the place,'' said one
Republican operative, citing swings of 10 to 15 points for some
candidates. ``The charts look like a seismograph after an
earthquake.''
   Vander Jagt has told Republican colleagues to keep their guard
up if they won with less than 65 percent of the vote in 1988, or if
they have an opponent this year who has raised more than $100,000.
   Incumbents who are used to winning handily may be in for
squeakers, and those without a cushion may lose, say analysts in
both parties.
   The Republicans considered most likely to lose are Oregon's
Denny Smith, tainted by the savings-and-loan scandal, and
Minnesota's Arlan Stangeland, hurt by ethics charges. Also on the
endangered list are Charles Pashayan of California and John Hiler
of Indiana.
   In Vermont, trouble for Republican Rep. Peter Smith could well
give the House its first socialist member since 1929: Bernard
Sanders, the former mayor of Burlington, who is running as an
independent. Smith was trailing late last week in private polls.
   Democrats also have their share of lawmakers in trouble.
California's George Brown, Ben Jones of Georgia, Roy Dyson of
Maryland and Bill Sarpalius of Texas are among the most vulnerable.
Late polls also showed slippage for Reps. Jim Jontz of Indiana and
Wayne Owens of Utah.
   But the volatility that pollsters have been talking about for
weeks remains in force.
   Democratic pollster Geoff Garin said the turmoil is the result
of three competing political currents, any one of which could
dominate Tuesday's voting. The budget deal and the ailing economy,
the country's general anti-incumbent mood and the Persian Gulf
crisis all have taken turns at the forefront in recent week.
   ``I, or anyone else, would be foolish'' to predict a precise
outcome, said Vander Jagt. ``This is the most volatile political
situation any of us has ever experienced.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0024 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 1310EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Iran-US     11-04 0431</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Iran-US,0492</SECOND>
<HEAD>Iranians Mark 11th Anniversary Of U.S. Embassy Takeover</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ANWAR FARUQI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NICOSIA, Cyprus (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hundreds of Iranians chanting ``Death to
America!'' burned the American flag at a rally Sunday in front of
the former U.S. Embassy in Tehran to mark the 11th anniversary of
its takeover by militant students.
   Tehran television, monitored in Nicosia, showed a large crowd
carrying signs proclaiming ``Death to America,'' ``Death to
Israel,'' and ``Death to Britain.''
   Young men and women, including university students, converged on
the rally site from all parts of the capital, the television said.
   Musavi Khoeniha, the former prosecutor who was the mentor of the
militant students who stormed the embassy 11 years ago, read a
half-hour message from Ayatollah Ali Khamenei, Iran's spiritual
leader.
   Khamenei's message urged the country's feuding radical and
so-called pragmatic factions to stop their infighting and remain
united.
   Parliament Speaker Mehdi Karrubi, a hard-line opponent of
Khamenei, then addressed the crowd, warning against the U.S.
presence in the Persian Gulf.
   He said that ``the capture of the U.S. nest of spies in Iran,
guaranteed the future of the revolution, and disrupted America's
spying machinery.''
   None of Iran's high-ranking leaders showed up at the rally,
which commemorates what is considered a turning point in the
history of the 1979 revolution.
   President Hashemi Rafsanjani has been trying to temper the
revolution since the death of Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini in June
1989.
   Rafsanjani has been engaged in efforts to sideline Khomeini's
hard-line, anti-Western followers, and rebuild relations with the
West to attract investment and advanced technology.
   The radicals accuse Rafsanjani, and Khamenei, his political
ally, of straying from Khomeini's anti-Western legacy. Both leaders
deny that this is true.
   Rafsanjani said in speech to students from around the country
Sunday that ``with the capture of the American nest of spies,
documents revealing American plots against the revolution were
divulged.''
   Blaming the United States for pushing Iraq into the 1980-88 war
against Iran, he added that ``after the failure of its plots,
America imposed the war on Iran.''
   The Iranians have condemned Iraq's invasion of Kuwait on Aug. 2,
but they have also denounced the presence of the U.S.-dominated
multinational force in the gulf.
   Karrubi said in parliament earlier Sunday that Iraq's invasion
of Kuwait ``is not the issue. What should come to everyone's
attention is that America has come to the region for oil, hegemony
and more importantly, to cofront the Islamic revolution and the
Moslem forces of the region.''
   The date of the embassy takeover also coincides with the day in
1963 that Khomeini was sent into exile by Iranian monarch Shah
Mohammed Reza Pahlavi. Khomeini returned in February 1979,
overthrew the monarchy, and established the Islamic Republic.
   On Nov. 4, 1979, Khomeini's militant followers stormed the U.S.
Embassy in Tehran and took 52 Americans hostage for 444 days.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0025 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 1311EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p AMCampaignSurprises Bjt   11-04 0717</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Campaign Surprises, Bjt,880</SECOND>
<HEAD>Those Last-Minute Shockers: Some Help, Some Don't</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JILL LAWRENCE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   October was the cruelest month for many an
office-seeker.
   An illegitimate child, a guru, a long-ago pool party. Events
long past surfaced in the late stages of Campaign '90 to haunt
candidates and, in at least one case, spell the end of a political
career.
   Minnesota Republican Jon Grunseth suffered a series of seismic
shocks that forced him to withdraw from the governor's race.
   First, two young women accused him of asking them to swim nude
with him at a pool party in 1981, when they were teen-agers. Then,
another woman said she'd had an affair with him that lasted nearly
a decade, through both of his marriages.
   No one else has been forced out of a race over a character
issue. But candidates have been lobbing that type of ammunition
with regularity, hoping something will explode.
   In Texas, allegations suddenly surfaced that Democratic
gubernatorial candidate Ann Richards had been seen using cocaine 13
years ago outside a Dallas bar. The charges by a former aide to the
man Richards defeated in the Democratic primary were aired in a
newspaper article and by a Republican sheriff.
   A consultant for Clayton Williams, the GOP candidate for
governor, said the incident came ``totally out of left field.''
   But Richards insisted Williams was behind it.
   ``This stinks to high heaven,'' she said. ``The story and the
actions of the Republican sheriff of Bexar County have taken the
Clayton Williams smear campaign to new lows.''
   In New Orleans, congressional candidate Marc Morial is trying to
control damage from the recent disclosure that he fathered an
illegitimate child eight years ago while a law student.
   The news broke right after the Oct. 6 primary, a few days after
the little girl's mother filed suit seeking child support. The
woman, now an attorney in Africa, said she had never before sought
or received a penny from Morial.
   Former Rep. Toby Moffett, attempting to recapture a House seat
in Connecticut, used his closing time in a debate to unleash an
attack against Waterbury alderman Gary Franks, his Republican
rival.
   Moffett said Franks, a landlord, had been cited 51 times for
health, fire or safety code violations - including a rat bite.
Franks had no time left and could not respond. But after the debate
he called Moffett ``Mr. Cheap Shot.''
   And in North Carolina, GOP Sen. Jesse Helms is accusing Democrat
Harvey Gantt, who is black, of using government for personal gain.
The specific charge: getting a cheap television license as part of
a minority controlled investment group, then selling the license
for a huge profit a few months later.
   ``It made Mr. Gantt a millionaire,'' Helms said. ``No wonder he
has a swimming pool in his back yard and a tennis court. He made
that off of a deception.''
   Gantt, who has a tennis court but not a swimming pool, said the
minority investors sold their license because operating the station
was going to cost far more than expected. He said voters should be
contemplating education and the environment - ``not whether or not
I bought a television station with private money.''
   In Oregon, Sen. Mark Hatfield ignored Democratic challenger
Harry Lonsdale until it looked like Lonsdale might unseat him. Then
state Republicans revived a 5-year-old controversy over Bhagwan
Shree Rajneesh - an Indian guru who died in the interim.
   A county judge who was poisoned by the guru's followers five
years ago held a news conference to release copies of a newspaper
ad signed and paid for by Lonsdale.
   The ad ran shortly after Rajneesh pleaded guilty to immigration
fraud charges and left the country. It said Americans should be
ashamed of ``the harassment and abuse heaped on this gentle man.''
   Lonsdale said last week that the guru's followers were
persecuted because they were different. He said his ad was meant to
support religious freedom and that Hatfield had written Rajneesh a
letter reflecting the same sentiments.
   Some campaign surprises fizzled or backfired immediately on
impact.
   In Connecticut, GOP Rep. John Rowland accused former Sen. Lowell
Weicker, a rival for the governor's seat, of violating a Senate
conflict-of-interest rule and possibly engaging in insider trading
of stocks and bonds.
   Weicker was ready.
   ``The entire premise of Mr. Rowland's smear rests on a
nonexistent Senate rule and a web of circumstance and innuendo,''
he declared.
   Running as an independent, Weicker still leads the three-way
race.
   Across the country in Nebraska, former Sen. John Tower said he'd
heard that Democratic Sen. Jim Exon was a boozer. Tower's remark,
made during a campaign appearance for Exon's rival, former Rep. Hal
Daub, sparked a round of speculation on Exon's drinking habits.
   But Tower may have done Daub more harm than good in his quest to
unseat Exon. The remark prompted a revival of rumors that Daub
abused his wife, and it caused her to release a letter saying the
allegations weren't true.
   Cindy Daub said Exon ``implied that my husband beat me up which
resulted in me going to so-called shelters.'' She called that ``the
most heinous personal attack possible and unbecoming of a United
States senator.''
   Exon is coasting to an easy win.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0026 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 1311EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>d a AM-BRF--Cobblestones     11-04 0169</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Cobblestones,0170</SECOND>
<HEAD>Councilman: Tacoma Shouldn't Have Given Up Cobblestones</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TACOMA, Wash. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   City employees who sold thousands of
cobblestones taken from a driveway near the historic Union Station
might have made a costly mistake, says a city councilman.
   Councilman Bob Evans says he and members of the Landmarks
Preservation Commission discovered that about 24,000 cobblestones
were sold to a contractor who gave the city $1,000 in credit toward
other work on the station-restoration project.
   ``In my view, we gave away a very valuable resource for
nothing,'' said Evans, an architect.
   City public-works officials should have known about a design
guideline that requires historic materials salvaged from the
station be saved for other city projects, he said last week.
   No one has come up with an estimate of the stones' worth, said
City Engineer Ben Thompson.
   Union Station is being renovated and a wing added to house
federal courts. Public-works officials say they were simply trying
to save money with the cobblestone arrangement.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0027 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 1312EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-KlanMarch     11-04 0171</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Klan March,0179</SECOND>
<HEAD>Klansmen Outnumbered 10-to-1 By Police During March</HEAD>
<DATELINE>GREENSBORO, N.C. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Some three dozen Christian Knights of
the Ku Klux Klan marched under the watchful eye of more than 10
times as many police officers.
   Saturday's march marked the 11th anniversary of the shooting
deaths of five Communist Workers Party members by Klansmen and
Nazis. There were a few taunts exchanged Saturday, but no violence,
officials said.
   About 350 police officers surrounded the 34 Klansmen while they
marched to the Phill G. McDonald Plaza. The rally attracted about
200 spectators - most opposed to the Klan. The crowd's chant of
``Go Home,'' and ``End Racism'' often drowned out the bullhorn
messages from Klansmen.
   As they marched, the Klansmen sang, ``Who are we? KKK. What do
we want? White rights in America. When do we want them? Now.''
   On Nov. 3, 1979, a confrontation between Klansmen, Nazis and
Communist Workers Party in Greensboro led to five deaths and
criticism that Greensboro police failed to adequately monitor the
event and prepare for possible trouble.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0028 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 1317EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p AM-GovRdp     11-04 0714</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gov Rdp,840</SECOND>
<HEAD>GOP Governors In Jeopardy In Tuesday's Elections</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Election Rdp, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By WILLIAM M. WELCH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   At least six Republican governors are in
danger of losing their jobs in Tuesday's elections as they are
judged by voters frustrated by higher taxes and worried about
recession.
   GOP control of several open seats also is in jeopardy. And the
races for five of the biggest states - California, Texas, Florida,
Ohio and Illinois - are closely contested. Four of the five, Ohio
being the exception, are in GOP hands now.
   ``Republicans are hanging on by a thread in almost a dozen
races,'' said political analyst Charles Cook. ``Many more
Republican seats are closer to the edge than Democratic ones.''
   High on the list of vulnerable GOP governors is Florida Gov. Bob
Martinez, who is locked in a close race with Democratic challenger
Lawton Chiles.
   GOP governors in Nebraska, Kansas, Maine and Rhode Island also
are trailing or in close contests in the polls.
   A sixth, Alabama Gov. Guy Hunt, is in a close race in a state
that hadn't elected a GOP governor this century until he won four
years ago. Hunt faces Democrat Paul Hubbert in what has become a
bitter contest.
   GOP Govs. Kay Orr in Nebraska and Mike Hayden in Kansas started
behind due to voter anger over local tax increases. Incumbents
Edward DiPrete in Rhode Island and John McKernan in Maine were hurt
by the Northeast's economic downturn.
   McKernan has staged a comeback in the polls against former Gov.
Joseph Brennan. But there's been no recovery for DiPrete - polls
show him down as much as 3-to-1 to Democrat Bruce Sundlun.
   Republican retirements also have left Democrats in strong
positions in New Mexico and Oklahoma.
   Some Democratic-controlled governorships may fall too, however.
And with a 29-21 advantage in governor's seats, Democrats have more
to lose in the 36 gubernatorial races this year. Many races were
statistical dead heats in the final days before the election.
   ``It could be the best of times; it could be the worst of
times,'' said Mark Gearan, director of the Democratic Governors'
Association. ``We could be in a situation where all of our
candidates win, or they don't. But it's also clear in several of
the open seats we have leads right now.''
   At least two potential Democratic losses may not be GOP gains.
Independent candidates are leading in three-way races in Alaska and
Connecticut.
   Both independent candidates are former Republicans now running
outside their party: former Nixon cabinet member Wally Hickel in
Alaska and former Sen. Lowell Weicker in Connecticut.
   Among Democratic incumbents, Minnesota Gov. Rudy Perpich is in
danger despite Republican turmoil. GOP nominee Jon Grunseth
withdrew last week because of a sexual impropriety scandal and was
replaced by Arne Carlson, who was strongly opposed by anti-abortion
conservatives.
   For all the Republican woes, polls showed Carlson in a tight
race with Perpich, a two-term incumbent known for his eccentricity.
   Democrats are in danger of losing Ohio. Republican George
Voinovich, the former mayor of Cleveland, is leading Democrat
Anthony Celebrezze, who made a celebrated switch to support for
abortion rights. Democratic Gov. Richard Celeste is retiring.
   Seeking a third term in Michigan, Democrat James Blanchard is in
a race that has tightened in recent days. A late poll showed
Republican John Engler pulling to within 4 percentage points.
   But a combination of economic recession, the abortion issue and
a variety of regional distinctions appears to give Democrats the
upper hand in many of the governor's races.
   ``Close to an unmitigated disaster,'' was how conservative
political consultant David Keene summarized GOP prospects. ``The
only hope we have is the volatility.''
   Republican attention has focused on the biggest states, where
the party hopes to hold veto power when Democratic legislatures
draw new congressional maps to reflect results of the 1990 Census.
   California is the biggest prize, with a potential seven-seat
House gain. Democrat Dianne Feinstein is in a close race against
GOP Sen. Pete Wilson, though some polls give Wilson the edge.
   ``California - that's the ball game,'' said Norm Cummings,
political director of the Republican National Committee.
   In Florida, Martinez has recovered from a double-digit deficit
in the polls but still faces high negative ratings left from a tax
flip-flop early in his term and anger over his anti-abortion moves.
   Chiles has his own troubles, too, however, including controversy
over his acknowledged use of an anti-depression drug. The National
Abortion Rights Action League has been airing anti-Martinez
commercials, though Chiles appears reluctant to push the issue much
himself.
   Another headline race is in Texas, where Republican Clayton
Williams has squandered a big lead through a series of gaffes,
including his refusal to shake hands with Democrat Ann Richards.
Williams, who has put some $8 million of his own money into the
race, has built a following by campaigning as a rough-hewn Texas
cowboy.
   His string of missteps continued into the final weekend of the
campaign, when he admitted in an offhand way that he paid no income
taxes for 1986. Polls showed the race a tossup.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0029 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 1321EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-India     11-04 0585</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-India,0736</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hindus Call End to Mosque Dispute</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By VIJAY JOSHI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>AYODHYA, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hindu leaders on Sunday suspended a
campaign to seize a mosque after claiming to reach an accord with
authorities, but officials said no concessions were made to end the
dispute that has left at least 325 dead.
   In New Delhi, meanwhile, moves to oust Prime Minister V.P. Singh
grew while opponents worked for compromises to prevent new
Parliament elections.
   Despite the signs of calm in Ayodhya, about 300 miles southeast
of New Delhi, violence linked to the mosque flared in neighboring
nations. At least two Moslems were killed by a Hindu mob in Nepal,
and security around Hindu temples in Pakistan was increased to
prevent Moslem attacks.
   The Hindu militants said they reached a deal with civil
authorities to allow them to visit the disputed holy site on
Wednesday.
   Ashok Singhal, who was at the forefront of the Hindu assault on
the mosque last week, called on thousands of pilgrims in Ayodhya to
end the seige and hold a traditional Hindu fire ceremony to mark
the end of a significant event.
   Singhal said a prayer meeting would start Monday and conclude
Wednesday with a visit to the 460-year-old mosque, which they claim
was built atop the birthplace of the Hindu warrior god Rama.
   But authorities said they had not yet decided to lift a curfew
on Ayodhya that would let the prayer meeting go ahead.
   Hindus seek to raze the mosque and erect a Hindu temple on the
site.
   A handwritten statement from Singhal, leader of the World Hindu
Council, said a public meeting would be held Nov. 11 in New Delhi
to decide the future campaign for the temple project.
   Sources said the fundamentalists had presented four demands for
ending the standoff.
   Among the requests is the lifting of a 10-day-old curfew in
Ayodhya, allowing Hindu worshipers to visit the disputed shrine,
and the release of Hindus arrested while attempting to start
construction of the temple.
   But sources indicated Hindu leaders were prepared to drop a
demand for the suspension of officers who ordered police toopen
fire on rampaging mobs Tuesday and Friday. At least 22 people were
killed in the two incidents, among at least 325 killed nationwide
in the dispute.
   About 4,000 Hindus from across the country have left Ayodhya in
the past few days, ignoring pleas from their leaders to stay until
the temple is built. An estimated 10,000 remain.
   The dispute was touched off when the leader of a Hindu
right-wing party, Lal Krishna Advani, was arrested Oct. 24 while
leading a caravan to Ayodhya to help build the proposed temple.
   Since the arrest, riots have spread across India and neighboring
nations. It has also brought Singh's 11-month-old coalition
government to the brink of collapse.
   Singh, who faces a confidence vote Wednesday, lost his majority
in Parliament when the pro-Hindu Bharatiya Janata Party withdrew
support because of the Ayodhya dispute.
   Hindus make up 82 percent of India's 880 million people, while
Moslems comprise 12 percent.
   On Sunday, two ministers resigned from the government, raising
to five the number in the 38-member Cabinet who deserted Singh in
the last two weeks.
   Meanwhile, two Singh opponents in his Janata Dal Party said they
plan a meeting Monday with other dissident party members. They hope
to dump Singh as party leader and prime minister in hopes of
preserving the government and averting parliamentary elections.
   But Advani, who was released Sunday, said new elections were the
only way out of the political impasse.
   ``This government has forfeited both its moral and political
right to continue even for a single day,'' he said.
   In Nepal, two Moslems who allegedly defiled a Hindu temple were
killed Saturday when Hindus stormed a house where they were being
held to await authorities. Five people were injured in the incident
in Harion, about 50 miles south of Katmandu, the Home Ministry
said.
   Moslems comprise only 3 percent of Nepal's 16 million people.
Ninety percent are Hindu.
   In mainly Moslem Pakistan, police and army troops increased
patrols around Hindu temples Sunday after several attacks,
including an attempt Saturday to blow up a temple in the southern
port city of Karachi, newspaper reports said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0030 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 1337EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People     11-04 0617</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People,0787</SECOND>
<HEAD>People in the News</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY44</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PAPEETE, French Polynesia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Actor Marlon Brando's daughter
has returned to consciousness from a coma caused by a drug
overdose, which her father insists was not a suicide attempt.
   A Brando family spokesman, who demanded anonymity, said Cheyenne
Brando came out of the coma Saturday but was suffering serious
stomach disorders from the tranquilizers and anti-depressants she
ingested Thursday.
   Brando may fly to the island from Los Angeles in the next few
days, depending on the status of the murder trial of Cheyenne's
half-brother, Christian Brando.
   Christian Brando, 32, is charged with murder in the shooting
death of Miss Brando's Tahitian lover, Dag Drollet. He was
scheduled to go on trial Monday, but jury selection has been
delayed.
   Miss Brando left the United States a month after Drollet was
slain and gave birth to their child in Tahiti. She refused to
return to testify and was accused by French authorities in Tahiti
of being an accessory to the murder.
   The French weekly newspaper Le Journal du Dimanche quoted the
66-year-old actor in its Sunday editions as saying his daughter did
not intend to kill herself with the drug overdose.
   ``She absorbed too much medicine that she was was given by her
doctors. That's all,'' he said.
   ---
   RENO, Nev. (AP) - Comedian Rich Little tailored his act to fit
his audience while visiting young hospital patients.
   Instead of doing his trademark impressions of Richard Nixon,
Ronald Reagan and George Bush, Little did Kermit the Frog and the
Cookie Monster.
   Little, who's appearing at Harrah's Reno, said he had to change
his act at Washoe Medical Center because many young people have not
heard of him or the people he's famous for imitating.
   ``The kids don't know who I am,'' he said Friday. ``The nurses
will be falling about and the kids are looking at me like I should
be locked up in a bed somewhere.''
   ---
   NEW YORK (AP) - Salman Rushdie says that during his 21 months in
hiding from Moslem fundamentalists he's resumed smoking, become
addicted to the telephone and misses little things one takes for
granted - like shopping.
   ``It is not that I ever was a big shopper,'' the author said in
an interview in Sunday's issue of The New York Times Magazine.
``But when you cannot shop, you come to understand better the
pleasure it affords.''
   Rushdie, 43, has been hiding in dozens of different safe houses
in England since February 1989, when Iran put a death sentence on
him for his novel ``The Satanic Verses.'' Some Moslems found the
book's depiction of Islam offensive.
   Since going into hiding, his marriage to novelist Marianne
Wiggins has fallen apart. He can make calls but can't receive them,
says he watches too much television and has reread many of his
favorite novels.
   ---
   NASHVILLE, Tenn. (AP) - Some of country music's top stars
gathered on stage at the Grand Ole Opry for a tribute to humorist
Minnie Pearl on her 50th anniversary with the show.
   Others sent recorded tributes to be shown during Saturday's
show, including one from Dolly Parton, who said: ``I love you. I
miss you.''
   To which Miss Pearl responded: ``I wear a hat so folks can tell
us apart.''
   Miss Pearl, 78, wearing her trademark gingham dress and straw
hat with its $1.98 price tag dangling, greeted the Opry crowd and
the live Nashville Network cable television audience with her
standard salutation: ``How-deee! I'm just so glad to be here!''
   ``This is a special night for all of us,'' said Roy Acuff, 87,
who has performed with Pearl throughout her career.
   ---
   CHICAGO (AP) - The actor who played the youngest member of the
spooky family portrayed on the 1960s television series ``The
Munsters'' is out on bail after a dispute over a limousine driver's
services.
   Patrick Allan Lilley, known as Butch Patrick when he played
Eddie Munster during 1964-66, was arrested Friday on a charge of
stealing $130 from the driver, police said.
   Police said Lilley, 37, of Austin, Texas, was a passenger with
another man in the limousine.
   ``Lilley contends that the driver was less than cordial and he
kept getting them lost,'' said Nicholas Kerkeles, who defended
Lilley at his arraignment. ``A fight began and Munster, er, Mr.
Lilley, apparently took the wallet, claiming that the driver
shouldn't have been paid in the first place.''
   Lilley was released on $1,000 bail. He told a judge he makes a
living attending conventions and making personal appearances as his
television character.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0031 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 1418EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-NewEurope     11-04 0453</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-New Europe,0525</SECOND>
<HEAD>Council of Europe Adding East European Members</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARK LAWRENCE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>STRASBOURG, France (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hungary plans to join the Council of
Europe on Tuesday, the first of several former Communist bloc
nations expected to gain membership in the oldest postwar body
promoting European cooperation.
   Hungary will seal its membership by signing the council's human
rights treaty at a ceremony in Rome.
   The 1950 treaty established the European Court of Human Rights,
which has heard more than 15,000 such cases from the 23 present
council members.
   The rights treaty is one of 130 international conventions -
ranging from computer data protection to anti-terrorism measures -
that Council of Europe nations have signed to date.
   Other East European nations are expected to gain admittance next
year as the 41-year-old council expands its role with Europe
emerging from the Cold War.
   Czechoslovakia, Poland, the Soviet Union and Yugoslavia have
been given observer status as a step toward full membership.
Romania and Albania may become observers soon, officials said.
   For membership, a country must be a pluralistic democracy and
must sign the human rights convention.
   The Strasbourg-based council has long existed in the shadow of
other organizations, notably the more powerful European Community,
a separate 12-nation body based in Brussels, Belgium.
   But the council is now seeking to become the primary body
bringing together nations from both sides of the former Iron
Curtain.
   ``The countries of Eastern Europe urgently need a structure
capable of accommodating them and assisting them on the path to
democratic reform,'' said Catherine Lalumiere, the council's
secretary general.
   The Council of Europe wants to form a 300-seat assembly of
legislators from among the 34 European and North American nations
in the Conference on Security and Cooperation in Europe, and become
Europe's chief human rights watchdog.
   In both cases, the council would take on activities of the CSCE,
a loosely defined body established in 1975 as a forum for
occasional talks between former Cold War adversaries, especially on
human rights and security issues. The conference includes the
United States, Canada and all of Europe except Albania.
   Many European governments now believe the conference must be
strengthened and see the Council of Europe as the right
organization for the job.
   ``It would be both logical and reasonable for the Council of
Europe to be given a mandate by the CSCE to continue that
conference's work by implementing the principles which it has laid
down,'' Ms. Lalumiere said.
   Only the United States has raised objections to the plan.
   But the other conference members may decide to push for a
parliamentary assembly without immediate U.S. participation, said
Anders Bjorck of Sweden, president of the Council's Parliamentary
Assembly.
   ``The U.S. position is causing widespread irritation to say the
least,'' Bjorck said. ``But we will not change our position.''
   A conference summit is scheduled for Nov. 19-21 in Paris. The
meeting is expected to be highlighted by the signing of a
NATO-Warsaw Pact accord ordering deep cuts in conventional forces
from the Atlantic Ocean to the Ural Mountains.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0032 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 1434EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-HuntingDeath     11-04 0507</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Hunting Death,0635</SECOND>
<HEAD>Parents' Persistence Leads to Arrests in Son's Hunting Death</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LARRY ROSENTHAL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LEBANON, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A blast from a hunter's shotgun killed his
son two years ago, but when no one came forward to accept
responsibility, Martin C. Rogan knew what had to be done.
   ``My son was the type of kid who would have said to me: `Find
out who killed me and don't let this go,''' said Rogan, his eyes
filling with tears.
   ``I felt an extreme responsibility to learn what happened,'' he
said.
   Jack C. Rogan was found dead in the woods a few hundred yards
behind his rural eastern Connecticut home on Nov. 25, 1988, the
second day of the deer hunting season. A single pellet of buckshot
had struck the 26-year-old in the neck and penetrated the lower
part of his brain, an autopsy showed.
   Tormented by the unanswered questions about their son's death,
and embittered by the belief that a hunter knew of his deadly
mistake but didn't want to fess up, Martin and Betty Rogan doggedly
pursued the case.
   They offered a $15,000 reward, hired a private investigator,
wrote to political leaders, unsuccessfully sought a grand jury
investigation, and finally took a suspect to court in a civil case.
The man, a neighbor of Jack Rogan's, refused to respond to more
than 100 questions, asserting his Fifth Amendment right against
self-incrimination.
   The Rogans' persistence paid off. Two men were arrested in
October, including the neighbor, after state police detectives
followed up a tip the Rogans received in August from an anonymous
telephone caller.
   Only 10 days before Jack Rogan's death, a woman in Maine, Karen
Wood, was killed by a hunter in an accident that focused national
attention on the dangers that each hunting season brings.
   The Rogans became good friends with Wood's husband, Kevin Wood,
and attended the manslaughter trial last month of the man who shot
his wife. The trial ended with an acquittal.
   ``He could understand our feelings and we could understand
his,'' Rogan said.
   The dangers of hunting season was brought home in Pennsylvania
when that state's small-game season opened late last month. Three
hunters were fatally shot during turkey-hunting accidents on
opening day alone.
   ``Unfortunately, the key to these accidents is that people are
not positively identifying their targets,'' said Jim Filkosky, who
is in charge of hunter education for the Pennsylvania Game
Commission.
   In the Rogan case, police allege a young man hunting illegally
shot Jack Rogan and fled before police arrived, letting his hunting
companion cover up for him.
   Michael Wisniewski Jr., 23, was charged with first-degree
manslaughter. Police said he did not have a hunting license, was
using buckshot, which is illegal in Connecticut, and fired the
fatal shot after the close of the legal shooting time.
   Richard P. Gorman, 41, who lives two houses down the road from
the Rogan house, was arrested on a charge of hindering prosecution.
   Police contend that Wisniewski mistook Rogan for a deer and shot
him and that Gorman made up a story to protect him. Gorman, who is
married to Wisniewski's cousin, told police he was hunting alone
just before sunset when he heard shots and discovered the body.
   Both Wisniewski and Gorman plan to plead innocent to the
charges, their lawyers said.
   Jack Rogan, the owner of his own trucking and excavation
business, was not hunting when he was shot. A hammer and nails were
found by his side. His father said he wasn't sure what his son was
doing.
   ``We will not be satisfied until justice has come a complete
path, someone is convicted and we get all the details of what went
on,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0033 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 1434EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Germany-Anniversary 1stLd-Writethru a068 11-04 0414</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Germany-Anniversary, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0681,0477</SECOND>
<HEAD>Small Rally Marks Anniversary of East Germany's Biggest Protest</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 9th pvs, `Look for...' to CORRECT dollar figure; Pickup
10th, `Baerbel Bohley...'</NOTE>
<HEAD>With AM-After the Wall</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARK FRITZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The people who orchestrated the biggest protest in
East Germany's Communist history marked the occasion Sunday with a
small rally against a united Germany's capitalist system.
   About 5,000 people met on Alexanderplatz, Berlin's central
square and the scene of a historic rally that drew an estimated 1
million people one year earlier.
   The Nov. 4, 1989, rally helped lead to the opening of the Berlin
Wall five days later, sped the pace of democratic reforms and was a
key link in the chain of events that resulted in German unity.
   The demonstrators on Sunday demanded better social guarantees as
the former East German nation, which joined West Germany on Oct. 3,
struggles to adapt to a free market democracy.
   Unemployment and living costs have skyrocketed in the last few
months. The old socialist system, which guaranteed low prices and
full employment while denying basic freedoms of speech and travel,
is being dismantled.
   One year ago, Alexanderplatz was a spine-tingling sea of people
who stood peacefully on the sprawling plaza and chanted ``We are
the people!'' at a shocked, disoriented Communist leadership on the
brink of extinction.
   The chant later evolved into ``We are one people'' as the revolt
for freedom was supplanted by a mass movement for German unity.
   On Sunday, protesters held up signs saying ``We are a stupid
people,'' and ``We were the people'' to protest what they say is a
coldly pragmatic capitalist system that pays insufficient attention
to the human costs of the nation's radical economic and social
transition.
   ``Look for a job as a minister without portfolio,'' read one
sign, a jab at the five former East German government officials who
now make more than $2,800 monthly as ministers in the united
government. The ministers have no clearly defined duties.
   Baerbel Bohley, leader of the New Forum activist group and the
best known of the dissidents who helped lead the democratic revolt,
was among several famous people at Sunday's rally.
   ``The revolution is not over, and therefore we may not stand
aside,'' she told the crowd.
   New Forum, an association of liberal artists and intellectuals,
was unable to establish a clearly defined political identity after
its remarkable success with the peaceful democracy revolution.
   Despite acting as the voice of the people during the former
nation's most dramatic period of crisis, New Forum and its
affiliated groups have been reduced to a respected but largely
unsupported fringe political party.
   Several celebrities attended Sunday's rally, including British
actress Glenda Jackson, American folksinger Pete Seeger, and German
authors Christa Wolf and Guenter Grass.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0034 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 1437EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Reagan-Book     11-04 0506</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Reagan-Book,600</SECOND>
<HEAD>Reagan Says He Didn't Have to Think 30 Seconds About Selling Arms
to Iran</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Former President Reagan says he ``didn't have
to think 30 seconds'' about selling missiles to Iran, but denies he
tried to swap weapons for American hostages, according to excerpts
of his memoirs published Sunday.
   Reagan also acknowleged he still doesn't know all the facts in
the Iran-Contra case, which became the biggest scandal of his
eight-year administration. In the case, weapons were sold to Iran
with the profits secretly diverted to the Nicaraguan Contra rebels.
   While the Iran-Contra case made him unhappy, Reagan said his
greatest regret as president was sending Marines to Beirut, Lebanon
where a suicide bomber attacked the Marine barracks on Oct. 23,
1983, killing 241 servicemen.
   Reagan said he was convinced it was a good idea to deploy
Marines in war-torn Lebanon as peace-keepers. But American
officials did not realize how vulnerable the servicemen were in the
barracks on a wide-open space.
   ``In any case, sending the Marines to Beirut was the source of
my greatest regret and greatest sorrow,'' Reagan wrote in the
excerpts from ``An American Life'' appearing in the this week's
editions of Time magazine.
   On the Iran-Contra case, Reagan said he and other officials
relied heavily on information from Israeli officials in deciding to
sell weapons to Iran in mid-1985.
   At first Reagan said he didn't want to do it because the
Iranians sponsored terrorism. But the former president said when he
learned through the Israelis that the group seeking the weapons did
not support terrorist activities, he didn't hesitate.
   ``Once we had information that we could trust the people in
Iran, I didn't have to think 30 seconds about saying yes. I was
told the few missiles would not significantly change the balance in
Iran's war with Iraq so I said, O.K., one small shipment from
Israel to allow the Israelis to prove they were talking with the
highest levels of the U.S. government.''
   But Reagan said he insisted the Iranians use their influence to
get American hostages in Lebanon freed. The hostages were held by
pro-Iranian Shiites Moslems.
   Over a 15-month period, three American hostages were released,
but three more were captured. Six Americans remain in captivity in
Lebanon. Terry Anderson, a correspondent for The Associated Press
who was seized in March 1985, is the longest held American.
   ``No problem was more frustrating for me than trying to get the
hostages home,'' Reagan said. Even so, he denied that the weapons
sale was a arms-for-hostages deal.
   ``To this day, I still believe that the Iran initiative was not
an effort to swap arms for hostages. But I know it may not look
that way to some people,'' he wrote.
   Nevertheless, Reagan said the ``cloud that descended over my
credibility during Iran-Contra undoubtedly affected my last two
years in office.''
   Even today, Reagan said he is in the dark about some details. A
presidential commission and an independent counsel have both
investigated the case.
   If he could re-live the past, Reagan said he would demand that
former national security adviser John Poindexter and his then-aide,
Oliver North, explain Iran-Contra. They were most involved in
setting up the diversion.
   ``I would bring both of them into the Oval Office and say, `O.K.
John and Ollie, level with me. Tell me what really happened and
what it is that you have been hiding from me. Tell me
everything,''' Reagan wrote.
   ``If I had done that, at least I wouldn't be sitting here,
writing this book, still ignorant of some of the things that went
on during the Iran-Contra affair,'' he wrote.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0035 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 1439EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Scotus-DrugSentence Bjt   11-04 0560</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Scotus-Drug Sentence, Bjt,0681</SECOND>
<HEAD>First-time Offender Fights Life Sentence on Drug Charge</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LAURA WISNIEWSKI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DETROIT (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Ronald Harmelin didn't fit the flashy drug
kingpin image - no tailored silk suit, dripping gold jewelry or
gleaming Mercedes-Benz for him.
   Still, he had 672 grams of cocaine in the trunk of his
9-year-old Ford when he was arrested by suburban Oak Park police on
May 12, 1986. Under Michigan law, that was enough to justify his
life sentence without parole.
   The U.S. Supreme Court is scheduled to hear arguments Monday on
whether Michigan's law requiring such a sentence is cruel and
unusual punishment. Under the state's law, possession of 650 grams
or more of cocaine brings a mandatory sentence of life in prison
without parole.
   Harmelin probably would be out of prison by now if federal
officials arrested him. Under federal law, a first offender
possessing 650 grams - almost 1{ pounds - would face a
five-to-40-year penalty with possibility of parole.
   ``That's the difference between being busted by the Drug
Enforcement Administration and Oak Park police. It's the difference
between one year and the rest of his life,'' said Paul Denenfeld, a
lawyer for the American Civil Liberties Union. ``It flies in the
face of individualized sentencing.''
   From his cell at Scott Regional Facility in a Detroit suburb,
the 45-year-old Harmelin got the high court's attention with a
petition that he was ``unjustly thrown into the pit of prison for
all eternity without the hope of release.''
   That's the point, said Oakland County prosecutor Richard
Thompson, who will argue that Harmelin's sentence is
constitutional.
   ``Michigan's law is the most enlightened in the country,''
Thompson said. ``It provides a deterrent and permanently removes
the drug trafficking from the community.''
   Detroit lawyer Carla Johnson, appointed to represent Harmelin,
said sentencing should look at prior criminal record and level of
involvement in the drug world. Harmelin had no prior record.
   ``He was not proven to be anything but a possessor of cocaine,''
Johnson said. ``The people who end up doing mandatory life are not
the kingpins the statute was aimed at. These people are mostly
first-time offenders and to punish them like we punish murderers is
not right.''
   The ACLU said it was concerned other states will enact laws
similar to Michigan's if it is upheld by the Supreme Court.
   In California, for instance, no state laws regulate sentencing
for drug crimes. Judges rely on federal guidelines to put away drug
dealers for life without parole.
   ``We'll certainly be taking a look at the Michigan case,'' said
John Gordnier, an assistant attorney general in California. ``We'll
be interested in the arguments.''
   Gordnier said the concept of life without parole is appropriate.
   ``Many of those who deal with narcotics have probably caused
someone to receive drugs and later die as a result of the drugs,''
he said. ``The penalty is not inappropriate given the price society
is paying.''
   In Florida, those convicted of selling, purchasing or delivering
more than 400 grams of cocaine face a mandatory 15 years in prison
and a $250,000 fine, said Richard Doran, the Florida attorney
general's director of criminal appeals.
   Florida doesn't have to prove the offender was a dealer.
   ``If you have more than 400 grams in your possession, the state
assumes you're a trafficker,'' Doran said. Cocaine is usually sold
by the gram.
   Neil Fink, chairman of Criminal Defense Lawyers of Michigan,
said if the high court upholds the law, Harmelin can again petition
the Michigan Supreme Court, which refused in January to hear the
case.
   There are 123 inmates in Michigan serving sentences like
Harmelin's.
   Harmelin, who could not be interviewed, can only wait. A
decision is expected early next year. Johnson said Harmelin remains
hopeful.
   ``With all this publicity, he's kind of got his spirits up a
little bit,'' Johnson said. ``Freedom is a state of mind. If you
think you can get out, there's some hope and you can tolerate it.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0036 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 1439EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Obit-Szlachcic     11-04 0181</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Szlachcic,0184</SECOND>
<HEAD>Franciszek Szlachcic, Former Polish Interior Minister, Dead at 70</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WARSAW, Poland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Maj. Gen. Franciszek Szlachcic, a former
interior minister and member of the Communist Party Politburo, has
died, the official PAP news agency reported Sunday. He was 70.
   PAP said Szlachcic died Saturday but did not say what the cause
was or where it occurred.
   Szlachcic, a member of the Communist People's Army during the
Nazi occupation, joined the Soviet-backed Communists as they
consolidated power in Poland following World War II.
   He joined the Communist Party when it was founded in 1948 and
rose through the ranks, reaching the Politburo during the early
1970s. He was interior minister in 1971 and deputy chairman of the
Council of Ministers until hisrretirement in 1976.
   In recent years, he served as president of the Polish Committee
for Standardization, Measures and Quality Control, and joined other
former members of the Communist leadership in writing memoirs.
   The Communist Party was dissolved in January, following the
transfer of power to a government lead by the independent,
non-Communist Solidarity movement.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0037 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 1441EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Libya-Palestinians 1stLd-Writethru a0713 11-04 0521</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Libya-Palestinians, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0713,0644</SECOND>
<HEAD>Abul Abbas Confirms Libya Closed His Camps</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS grafs 20-21 pvs, `Abbas denied ...' with one graf to ADD
that Genoa court convicted Abbas in absentia of masterminding the
Achille Lauro hijacking. No pickup.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By SALAH NASRAWI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BAGHDAD, Iraq (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Abul Abbas, the mastermind of the Achille
Lauro ship hijacking five years ago, confirmed Sunday that Libya
has expelled 145 members of his radical group and closed down four
training camps.
   Abul Abbas said the move was a surprise to him and his wing of
the Palestine Liberation Front, considered to be a major terrorist
organization.
   He said the ejection was unjustified and urged Libya's leader,
Col. Moammar Gadhafi, to reopen the camps and the group's offices.
   The government in Tripoli has not given an explanation for its
action, he said. Reports began to surface about a week ago that
Libya had expelled the Palestinians.
   Arab diplomats in Baghdad said the United States had asked King
Hassan of Morroco and Egyptian President Hosni Mubarak to press
Gadhafi to eject the group.
   Gadhafi is believed to want Libya's removal from the U.S. State
Department's list of countries supporting terrorism.
   PLO chief Yasser Arafat has also been pressed to dissociate
himself from Abul Abbas, who has one seat on the executive
committee of the Palestine Liberation Organization. Pressure to
remove Abul Abbas increased after his group raided an Israeli beach
in May, an action that to a break in U.S.-PLO dialogue.
   After the raid on the Israeli beach, Abul Abbas apologized to
Arafat, saying the PLO chief did not about the raid in advance. He
also said that civilians were not targets in that raid, counter to
Israeli claims.
   Abul Abbas dismissed reports the PLO leadership had asked Libya
to kick out his group.
   ``We rule out any possibility that the PLO leadership has asked
for this, but some Palestinian circles who oppose our militant line
might have done so,'' he said.
   He said that most of the group had moved to Lebanon, and others
to places that he delined to name.
   Abul Abbas, whose real name is Mohammed Abbas, leads one of two
wings of the Palestine front, which split from Ahmed Jibril's
Popular Front for the Liberation of Palestine-General Command in
1977.
   Based in Baghdad since leaving Lebanon in 1982, Abul Abbas is
believed to have several hundred guerrilla fighters in his
organization - in Iraq, Lebanon and, until now, Libya.
   The other wing of the Palestine front, based in Damascus, was
led by Talaat Yacoub, who died two years ago.
   Abul Abbas said two of the camps were places where PLO fighters
were trained for ``naval combat.'' One was a small town east of
Tripoli and the other was west of Tripoli, he said. He did not
provide the others' locations.
   The Palestinian leader said his group would continue its ``armed
struggle'' against Israel but insisted that the group will not
attack any targets outside of the Jewish state.
   Abul Abbas said that he had no plans to attack Americans or
other Westerners despite the Persian Gulf crisis. But he said his
group will fight alongside Iraq if it is attacked by the U.S.-led
multinational forces in the Gulf.
   ``In pan-Arab battles we will carry out our duties alongside our
brothers in Iraq,'' he said.
   The Achille Lauro, a Mediterranean cruise ship, was hijacked
Oct. 7, 1985 and held by terrorists for two days. A 69-year-old
wheelchair-bound Jewish-American passenger, Leon Klinghoffer, was
killed during the hijacking and his body dumped into the sea.
   A Genoa court in 1986 convicted Abbas in absentia of
masterminding the hijacking. Abbas maintained had merely played a
role in negotiating the release of the ship in exchange for freedom
for the hijackers.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0038 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 1454EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-India-Punjab     11-04 0253</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-India-Punjab,0286</SECOND>
<HEAD>Sikh Militants Line Up and Shoot 20 Passersby</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW DELHI, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Sikh separatists stopped passing
motorists and cyclists near a village in Punjab state Sunday, lined
them up on the roadside and shot them, news agencies reported.
   The Press Trust of India said at least 17 people were killed,
including a police constable. Another domestic news agency, United
News of India, said 20 people were killed in the incident in the
district of Gurdaspur.
   Also Sunday in Punjab, a bomb exploded at the gate of a movie
theater in the small town of Pathankot, injuring 14 people, United
News reported.
   The agency said 21 people, including four security personnel and
two Sikh militants, were killed in other incidents around Punjab
state Sunday, or their bodies were found.
   More than 2,600 people have been reported killed so far this
year by Sikh militants hoping to establish an independent state in
Punjab, a wealthy farming region bordering Pakistan.
   Military officials have said the independence movement is also
being used as a cover for extortionists and thieves.
   In one incident Sunday, three Sikh militants broke into a home
in a village demanding money for the separatist cause. One militant
was caught and beaten to death, while the others escaped, the news
agencies reported.
   A second militant was killed in a shootout with police Sunday,
and the bodies of two Sikhs who had apparently been shot by rival
groups were discovered, the agencies said.
   Last month, the Indian government decided to extend federal rule
over Punjab for another six months, arguing the situation precluded
holding elections for state government. The previous government was
dismissed in 1987.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0039 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 1532EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Israel     11-04 0545</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel,0647</SECOND>
<HEAD>Israel Rejects U.N. Proposal for Increased Arab Protection</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ALLYN FISHER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Troops wounded dozens of Palestinians Sunday
and ordered curfews across the Gaza Strip. Government leaders
dismissed as ``one-sided'' a U.N. call for international protection
of Arabs under Israeli occupation.
   Israel radio said 86 Palestinians were injured in widespread
clashes following the death of a jailed Palestinian, while Arab
reports said 70 were hurt. The army put the number at 27 and said
it was checking the other figures.
   A Foreign Ministry statement castigated U.N. Secretary-General
Javier Perez de Cuellar for his report Thursday in which he
suggested broadening the mandate of U.N. institutions in Israel to
safeguard the 1.7 million Palestinians under occupation.
   The report was produced as a recommendation to the U.N. Security
Council on response to the killing Oct. 8 of 20 Palestinians on
Jersusalem's Temple Mount by Israeli authorities.
   ``The world community's continued preoccupation with this
subject can only serve those forces who are interested in creating
a link between the Arab-Israeli conflict and the gulf crisis,'' the
statement said.
   The statement assailed a proposal to convene the signatories of
the Fourth Geneva Convention of 1949, which sets out rules for the
treatment of civilians in wartime.
   ``Israel is disappointed at the one-sided approach exhibited in
the report,'' it said. ``The recommendations in the report are
directed only toward Israel and do not see fit to call for a
cessation of violence on the Palestinian side.''
   Israel has refused to accept a U.N. investigation into the Oct.
8 incident on Temple Mount, a site holy to both Jews and Moslems.
Israel says the inquiry would undermine its sovereignty in
Jerusalem.
   Israel had conducted its own investigation and ``extracted the
necessary lessons,'' it said.
   A government-appointed panel defended the action by police,
saying they faced a threat to their lives. But it also said top
officers failed to adequately supervise riot-control troops.
   Under the panel's recommendation, the Cabinet set up a permanent
seven-member ministerial committee to oversee Temple Mount affairs.
   Police Minister Roni Milo upgraded Jerusalem to a full police
district Sunday, acting on the commission's recommendations. Milo
did not say if senior officers would be transferred or fired.
   About 350 officers will be added to Jerusalem's 1,000-member
force and the public will be encouraged to volunteer for the Civil
Guard, said police spokeswoman Ruth Shlezinger.
   In the Gaza Strip, extensive curfews were imposed and the area
of 750,000 residents was declared a military zone and was closed to
reporters.
   Arab reports said at least 180 people were injured during the
weekend violence, started with rumors that a Palestinian inmate was
killed by Israeli troops. Israeli authorities say the man hanged
himself in his cell.
   In some sections of Gaza City, streets were littered with stones
and scorched remains of burning tires. Masked youths in the city's
Nasser Quarter fired rocks with slingshots at soldiers checking
identification papers on a street.
   Arsonists gutted the town hall of Khan Yunis in Gaza, Arab
reports said. Gaza police were not immediately available for
comment.
   A senior aide of Palestine Liberation Organization chief Yasser
Arafat claimed two girls' schools with hundreds of pupils in the
Gaza Strip were hit by gas bombs fired by Israeli troops.
   Bassam Abu Sharif also said in a statement that dozens of other
Arabs were wounded when Israeli troops opend fired on a Khan Yunis
hospital and a number of clinics in the area run by the U.N. Relief
and Works Agency.
   The statement was sent to The Associated Press in Nicosia,
Cyprus, from PLO headquarters in Tunis, Tunisia.
   Israel captured the West Bank, Gaza Strip and Arab east
Jerusalem in the 1967 Middle East war and later annexed east
Jerusalem.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0040 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 1606EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-Baker 1stLd-Writethru a0696 11-04 0688</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Baker, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0696,790</SECOND>
<HEAD>Baker Visits Troops in Saudi Desert as He Launches New Gulf
Assessment</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 1st graf to conform dateline to AP style; SUBS 6th graf
pvs, bgng: `I'm from,' to include additional quote about having a
baby; SUBS 16th graf pvs, Here he, with 6 grafs to UPDATE with
meeting with officials in Bahrain</NOTE>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf Rdp Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BARRY SCHWEID</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Diplomatic Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MANAMA, Bahrain (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Secretary of State James A. Baker III
ventured into the desert of Saudi Arabia on Sunday to give a pep
talk to 4,200 U.S. troops who may be ordered into combat against
Iraq if other pressure tactics do not free Kuwait from Saddam
Hussein's grasp.
   The men and women who must weather dust-storms, searing heat and
boredom were mostly receptive to their distinguished visitor, who
was launching a fast-paced survey of Arab, European and Soviet
sentiment for war with Iraq.
   One soldier gave Baker a chew of tobacco, another a package of
combat rations. Baker, a Texan and ex-Marine, received both
offerings comfortably. He chewed the tobacco and said of the food:
``I used to live on this stuff. It was a little bit different then
- they were in cans.''
   But there were murmurs of discontent within the ranks, as well.
   ``Most of us assume we will be going to war sooner or later,''
2nd Lt. Henry Wardick, 23, a West Point graduate, told reporters.
   ``I'm from Alabama,'' a female sergeant said. ``I'm tired of
eating this dirt. I'm tired of drinking hot water. I'm ready to go
home.'' Moreover, she said, ``I haven't had a chance to have a
baby.''
   And when Baker, who wore khakis and worn cowboy boots, told
another soldier that the Saudi desert was not much different from
Texas, the soldier politely disagreed. ``It's a little bit
different,'' he said.
   Baker arrived in Bahrain, the financial hub of the Persian Gulf,
after a 15-hour flight from Washington. He was whisked immediately
by helicopter across the border to eastern Saudi Arabia, passing
over camels running wild in the desert.
   There, at a location censored by Baker's staff, he addressed and
mingled with the soldiers from the First Cavalry Division out of
Fort Hood, Texas. They are among more than 110,000 defending the
Saudi oil fields and are equipped with M-1 tanks, Bradley fighting
vehicles, a multilaunch rocket system and shoulder-fired Stinger
missiles.
   ``This is a long way from home,'' Baker told the troops. ``But I
think that Americans are home wherever our principles are. And
that's really what this crisis is all about.''
   As he stepped down from the podium to mingle, a soldier took the
microphone and to the accompaniment of the division band, sang Lee
Greenwood's song: ``I'm Proud To Be an American.''
   Afterward, Baker told reporters traveling with him: ``I was
pleased to see that the morale is good. They all seemed to be
upbeat. The main question is what the future holds. That is
something that cannot be answered with any specificity.''
   Baker said as he flew here Saturday he was laying the foundation
for stronger economic and political measures against Iraq or even
military action.
   ``Unprovoked aggression should not be rewarded. Unprovoked
aggression should not be permitted to succeed,'' Baker told the
troops in what has become a familiar refrain since Saddam Hussein
conquered Kuwait and seized its oil fields in a blitzkrieg invasion
Aug. 2. ``The world made a terrible mistake in the '30s when we
were unable or refused to stand up to unprovoked aggression.''
   Here he met with leaders of the ruling royal family of this
wealthy ministate, which has strong ties to Kuwait - Sheik Isa bin
Saman Al Khalifa, the emir of Bahrain; Sheik Khalifa bin Sulman;
and Sheik Mohammed bin Mubarak Al Khalifa - to go over various
scenarios to evict Iraq, including use of force.
   A U.S. official, briefing reporters afterward, said Bahrain
would like the sanctions to get the job done, but military action
was ``one of the options responsible governments have to study.''
   There are 9,000 U.S. troops in Bahrain. The country also has
sent its own small ground contingent to Saudi Arabia and made its
air force available.
   Information minister Tariq Almoayed spoke in terms of resolve
and supported strong statements being made by American officials.
   ``There is no reason to have all these armies from around the
world here and tie their hands,'' he said. ``Everybody in this part
of the world, I think, feels all of these armies from all the world
are not here for a picnic.''
   This was the first business session undertaken by the emir since
he was hospitalized in October with an undisclosed ailment, and it
took place at a hospital where the ruler has been recuperating.
   On Monday, Baker goes to Saudi Arabia, the linchpin of the Arab
alliance against Saddam. There, official Kuwaiti sources told The
Associated Press that the timing of military action against Iraq
may be discussed.
   Baker will go first to Taif to see Sheik Jaber al-Ahmed
al-Sabah, the exiled emir, who on Saturday called for mobilization
of a global effort to evict Iraq from Kuwait.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0041 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 1609EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Colombia     11-04 0302</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Colombia,0340</SECOND>
<HEAD>Leftist Guerrillas Kill Mayor</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JAVIER BAENA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOGOTA, Colombia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Leftist guerrillas have kidnapped and
assassinated the mayor of a southern town. He was the ninth mayor
slain this year, and the army has blamed most of the deaths on the
rebels.
   The defense minister was quoted Sunday as saying the violence
was hurting prospects for a negotiated peace between the government
and leftist insurgents.
   The body of Edmundo Munoz, mayor of the southern town of Rosas,
was found Saturday, less than 24 hours after guerrillas from the
Simon Bolivar Coordination had kidnapped him, according to an army
statement.
   The guerrilla organization is an umbrella for two leftist groups
- the Revolutionary Armed Forces of Colombia or FARC, and the
National Liberation Army, or ELN.
   Guerrillas have been known to kidnap and sometimes kill local
officials who refused to cooperate.
   The army, meanwhile, continues to fight the insurgents in
several regions. One soldier and four members of the Revolutionary
Armed Forces were killed Saturday in the southern state of
Putumayo, the army statement said.
   The statment said an unspecified number of Liberation Army
members were killed Saturday in northern Colombia when the army
attacked rebel camps.
   ``The FARC and the ELN are showing through their terrorist
actions that they do not want peace,'' said Defense Minister Oscar
Botero in comments published Sunday by El Espectador newspaper.
   The rebel groups have said in recent weeks they are prepared to
begin peace talks with the administration of President Cesar
Gaviria in exchange for participating in next year's rewriting of
the country's constitution.
   But Gaviria has ruled out participation in the constitutional
assembly for rebels who do not accept a government peace plan.
Members of the April 19 Movement, the only rebel group to lay down
its weapons under the plan, are expected to win several of the 70
assembly seats in December elections.
   Another group, the National People's Army, has begun
negotiations with the government.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0042 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 1610EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p AM-Jackson-Senate     11-04 0349</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Jackson-Senate,380</SECOND>
<HEAD>Jackson Likely To Have Limited Rights As Shadow Senator</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RICHARD KEIL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Jesse Jackson is heavily favored to win
election as a ``shadow senator'' for the District of Columbia on
Tuesday, but he's likely to find the doors locked when he gets to
Congress.
   Jackson is one of 11 candidates vying for two ``shadow senator''
positions. He's making his first bid for elective office other than
two unsuccessful runs for the Democratic presidential nomination.
   The non-paying ``shadow senators'' will lobby Congress to grant
statehood to the District of Columbia. But by precedent and custom,
only senators elected by one of the 50 states are given floor
rights in the Senate and office space in the Capitol complex.
   ``Senator Mitchell has asked staff to look into precedent, and
no decision has been made,'' on whether Jackson will be granted
floor privileges, said Diane Dewhurst, a spokeswoman for Senate
Majority Leader George Mitchell.
   The district also will elect a new non-voting delegate to
Congress, with Democrat Eleanor Holmes Norton favored over
Republican Harry Singleton.
   But while the delegate's House seat is non-voting, it is
officially recognized, and the winner will get an office, floor
privileges and the right to vote in committee.
   Going back to the 1790s, when the Tennessee territory first used
the ``shadow'' concept to lobby for statehood, no one elected to
such a post has been granted the rights of elected members of
Congress. The last time a ``shadow'' legislator was used was by
Alaska, which became the 49th state in 1959.
   Jackson brushes aside questions about the rights a shadow
lawmaker would have.
   ``It's a matter of understanding, mainly, making the Senate and
the House realize that there are over 600,000 people in this city
who pay taxes, go to war, but don't have voting representation on
Capitol Hill,'' he said last week. ``It is a fundamental issue of
fairness.''
   District of Columbia voters first approved sending a ``shadow''
delegation to Congress in 1980, but the city council twice
postponed scheduled elections for the positions.
   This year, after aggressive lobbying by Jackson, the 13-member
council gave the go-ahead. But because of concerns over the city's
$100 million deficit, the council killed a bill that would have
provided $1.3 million for office rental and staff for the two
``shadow'' senators and a ``shadow'' House member.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0043 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 1609EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u p AM-RacePPolitics     11-04 0523</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Race-Politics,560</SECOND>
<HEAD>Democrats See Racism In GOP Campaign Tactics</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOAN MOWER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Democrats on Sunday accused Republicans of
racism in the North Carolina Senate race as a federal judge
scheduled an election-eve hearing on whether the GOP's tactics are
intimidating voters.
   Republican officials dismissed allegations that voter mailings
in North Carolina and Texas were designed to intimidate minority or
elderly voters.
   But U.S. District Judge Dickinson Debevoise scheduled a hearing
for Monday in Newark, N.J., to determine whether the Republican
National Committee is violating a 1982 consent decree that bars
voter intimidation.
   The hearing was requested by the Democratic National Committee.
   ``What the Republican Party has done is absolutely disgusting,''
Democratic party Chairman Ronald Brown said on CBS-TV's ``Face the
Nation.'' He accused the GOP of trying to ``intimidate the poorest
and most vulnerable voters.''
   The controversy has centered primarily on North Carolina, where
Republican Sen. Jesse Helms is in a neck-and-neck race with
Democrat Harvey Gantt, who is black.
   At issue are 150,000 official-looking postcards that the North
Carolina GOP sent to predominantly minority Democratic precincts.
   Labeled ``Voter Registration Bulletin,'' the cards read, in
part, that is a federal crime ``to knowingly give false information
about your name, residence or period of residence to an Election
Official.'
   ``We knew that in a panic Jesse Helms would turn to this kind of
tactic, just as Republicans have done in the past,'' Brown said.
   Voter mailings also have been sent out in Texas to predominantly
elderly Democratic voters, encouraging them to forego absentee
ballots.
   Charles Black, a spokesman for the Republican National
Committee, said he had not seen any of the mailings but insisted
the GOP has never broken the consent decree on voter intimidation.
   The committee ``always plays by the rules,'' he said. But he
added that North Carolina has ``a long history of Democrats
stealing elections.'' State and local leaders ``have a
responsibility to take legal action to ensure the integrity of the
ballot, and that's all that's going on there,'' he said.
   House Majority Leader Richard Gephardt, D-Mo., disagreed with
the Republicans.
   ``The campaign that Jesse Helms is running is not a lot
different than the campaign that David Duke ran in Louisiana,''
Gephardt said. Duke is a former Ku Klux Klan leader who lost in
Louisiana's open Senate primary in October.
   ``The message ... clearly has racial overtones. It is clearly
designed to appeal to people's prejudice,'' Gephardt said on NBC's
``Meet the Press.''
   In the Helms-Gantt contest, Democrats also have charged Helms
with playing on racial stereotypes in television advertisements.
   White House chief of staff John Sununu insisted the Bush
administration and the GOP oppose any use of race in elections.
   ``I think in any campaign a racial message of one kind or the
other is inappropriate and abhorrent,'' Sununu said. ``This
administration has worked awfully hard to get that kind of aspect
out of any campaign.''
   Sununu noted that the Republican hierarchy, including President
Bush, had disavowed Duke. But he sidestepped questions about Helms,
for whom Bush has campaigned.
   Black said the Democrats' charges were old hat.
   ``You can always tell when the Democrats are about to have a bad
political year because the weekend before the election they start
acting like martyrs and screaming racism and voter intimidation,''
he said.
   At Monday's hearings in Newark, the federal judge is expected to
examine whether the RNC violated a 1982 decree issued after the
party reportedly hired armed guards to watch over various polling
places in New Jersey.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0044 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 1619EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-Allies     11-04 0517</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Allies,0618</SECOND>
<HEAD>United Front Needed Against Iraq, Belgium Says</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf Rdp, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RAF CASERT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BRUSSELS, Belgium (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Belgium called Sunday for a special
European Community meeting to discuss the threat to unity posed by
a slew of missions to Baghdad to try to obtain the release of
hostages.
   Iraqi President Saddam Hussein ``is creating this royal court of
all sorts of Western pilgrims who visit him to obtain the release
of hostages,'' Belgian Foreign Minister Mark Eyskens told BRT
television.
   Iraq has held thousands of foreigners hostage since its Aug. 2
invasion of Kuwait. It has moved some to strategic locations to
serve as shields against attack, and released others.
   Eyskens' comments came after he was asked about former West
German chancellor Willy Brandt's scheduled trip to to Iraq on
Monday.
   He said sometimes visiting officials or ex-officials ``let
themselves be lured into political discussions'' with Saddam. Such
talks, he said, could ``jeopardize the united stand'' against
Iraq's takeover of Kuwait.
   Eyskens said he hoped an EC meeting could strengthen the allies'
position on such initiatives. He said the meeting, requested by
Belgium and the Netherlands, could be held Tuesday or Wednesday in
Rome, when the trade bloc's foreign minister gather for an
unrelated ceremony.
   EC officials in Rome could not confirm when or if the meeting
would take place.
   Eyskens noted that the 12 community states had agreed last week
to refrain from solitary missions to Iraq, in order to maintain the
trade bloc's credibility and cohesion. Days later, Brandt's trip
was announced.
   ``We just decided on a clear position that there would be no
government delegations, directly or indirectly, traveling to Iraq
to negotiate about the hostages,'' said Eyskens.
   Germany maintained Brandt's visit remained within the EC
framework since he would would work for the release of all foreign
hostages, not just Germans. The Bonn government defended Brandt's
trip again Sunday, saying it wished him success.
   In another such visit, former Japanese Prime Minister Yasuhiro
Nakasone met with Saddam on Sunday. He said afterward it was too
soon to tell if his efforts would help win the hostages' freedom.
   But the visit was potentially embarrassing for Japan. Nakasone
emerged from the talks saying Saddam appeared to be earnest in his
wish for peace. Hours later, Iraq's information minister told
reporters Iraq would go to war rather than give up Kuwait.
   Iraq's official news agency also said Nakasone had told Saddam
the Japanese parliament was unlikely to approve the sending of
Japanese troops to the gulf. Nakasone did not disclose any such
assurances, but the report made it appear that Japan might be
willing to make concessions for its citizens' freedom.
   Eyskens said even if visits like Brandt's and Nakasone's were
technically private ones, Saddam was well aware of the influence
such figures have.
   ``When an important ex-politician goes to Baghdad to talk with
Saddam it inevitably has a political character,'' he said.
``Increasingly, more tiny cracks appear in the Western front''
because of such initiatives.
   Eyskens also criticized former British Prime Minister Edward
Heath for his visit to Iraq last month. He secured the release of
33 Britons and 14 U.S. citizens, but the Belgian official said
there was a price.
   Following Heath's trip ``his views were, `Saddam isn't all that
bad, we have to talk with him. His territorial claims (on Kuwait)
can be partially defended.' That is language which is not conform
to the Western front,'' Eyskens said.
   Iraq last week freed more than 250 French hostages while
praising what it said were France's good-faith efforts to settle
the crisis.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0045 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 1624EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-MarinesFootball     11-04 0554</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Marines Football,0733</SECOND>
<HEAD>Football Field In Saudi Is Unique: Tents and Sand</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf Rdp</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By EDITH M. LEDERER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>EASTERN SAUDI ARABIA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   It's probably the only such football
field in the world: covered by sand with cot-filled tents running
along one sideline. But the Marines on a rare day off Sunday didn't
mind the dust.
   ``It's fun, a good way to let out aggressions,'' said Lance Cpl.
Dale ``Tom'' Keller, 20, of Prineville, Ore. ``It's better than
sitting back at camp doing nothing.''
   Rest and relaxation for the 220,000 U.S. troops confronting Iraq
in the Persian Gulf has become more important with Operation Desert
Shield in its third month and no end in sight.
   Saudi Arabia is the first potential combat zone where some
traditional sldiers' diversions - visiting area bars and dating
the locals - are banned.
   In their absence, sports have become an important recreation,
especially for the 30,000 Marines. Unlike their Army and Air Force
counterparts, the Marines are barred from Saudi cities to keep a
low profile.
   The Marines play football in a stadium at a base turned over to
them by the Saudi government. Every game is called the Scud Bowl,
apparently after Scud missiles which are part of the Iraqi arsenal.
   Dust bowl would be more like it.
   Even though clouds of dust partially obscured some of the play,
the 100 fans at Sunday's main battle between the 174th Marine Wing
Support Squadron and the 311th Marine Fighter Attack Squadron
yelled just like fans at home.
   They cheered good passes and touchdowns, booed interceptions,
and shouted at the referee for calls they didn't like.
   The Marines were playing flag football, a variation of touch
football in which tackles are made by grabbing strips worn by the
opposing team. Highlights of the game, which the 311th won 15-14,
were broadcast on the Armed Forces Radio Network.
   Most fans sat in the stadium on one side of the field. But some
stood outside a long row of tents running the length of the other
side, just a few yards from the players.
   ``Just step right out and watch the game,'' said Lance Cpl.
Ellory Myers, 20, of Casper, Wyo., whose tent is on the 40-yard
line.
   ``It's a good bonus ... except when it wakes you up,'' he said.
``It's kind of fun, especially when people get in fights and
stuff.''
   ``Ringside seat,'' said Master Sgt. Dan Rich, 38, of Rochester,
New York, a maintenance chief with the 311th Tom Cats. ``You get to
holler at everybody. ... It's good for relieving stress.''
   But not everyone cares for the tentside view, though.
   Lance Cpl. Wayne Lewis, 21, of Reading, Penn., who lives on the
50-yard line, said he wasn't interested in football and was annoyed
the Marines hadn't put up the tents elsewhere.
   ``You get a lot of dust in your house, and they wake me up
around 8 a.m.,'' he said.
   Chief Warrant Officer Jerry L. Duck, 36, of Malden, Miss., was
celebrating a 16-0 shutout by officers over the enlisted men from
his unit in the 311th.
   ``For an old man, I did all right,'' he said. ``It helps the
morale. I think the stadium is the best place in the country.''
   ``This is great,'' said Sgt. John Crone, 23, of York, Penn., a
photographer for the 174th. ``A lot of Marines out here have it
really bad off. They're out in the sand and the dirt. I kind of
feel guilty sometimes.''
   The stadium also has volleyball nets, a softball diamond,
ping-pong tables and movies.
   Capt. Cindy Stock, 29, a flight nurse from Pope Air Force Base,
N.C., was wearing shorts Sunday. ``It's one of the very few places
we can wear them, which makes it doubly nice for women,'' she said.
   U.S. soldiers have been advised to try not to offend local
residents. In Saudi Arabia, the Moslem way of life dictates that
women not drive or expose their skin to public view.
   Sweating in a T-shirt and shorts during a break in another game,
Lance Cpl. Darren Ortiz of New York City said it was like playing
on the beach. ``You can run as hard as you can, but you won't move
nowhere that fast.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0046 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 1630EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-Syrians     11-04 0397</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Syrians,0486</SECOND>
<HEAD>Syrian Tanks Arrive on Saudi Soil to Check Iraq</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf Rdp, Bjt</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto DHA5</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT DVORCHAK</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>YANBU, Saudi Arabia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Syrian tanks and the lead elements of
a infantry division landed Sunday in Saudi Arabia to join the Arab
forces sent to the region in response to Iraq's invasion of Kuwait.
   Saudi Prince Khalid, commander of all Arab troops deployed in
the sands south of Iraq and Kuwait, saluted and warmly greeted the
Syrian troops.
   ``We are all here to fight if it's necessary,'' said Khalid,
commander of the Saudi air force and nephew of King Fahd.
   ``We are all in the same line,'' Khalid said at a dockside news
conference. ``It is really a pleasure to have a Syrian armored
division here. That makes me very happy.''
   The Syrian troops ``will be under the Saudi flag,'' the prince
said. But he noted they have ``a direct line'' to their president,
Hafez Assad.
   Maj. Gen. Ali Habib, commander of Syrian troops in Saudi Arabia,
refused to answer questions. But a spokesman said between 2,500 and
3,000 troops were aboard the cargo ship Saudi Qassim. The remaining
elements of the 15,000-member 9th Armored Division would arrive in
the next few weeks, Saudi officials said.
   The Syrian vanguard consisted of Soviet-made T-62 tanks, which
are standard fighting armor for Syria but not the top-of-the-line
model sold by Moscow. The Iraqis have 500 T-72 tanks, which have
more firepower and range.
   Ten of the tanks were parked in formation on trailers. Their
four-man tank crews and a company of 120 infantrymen, carrying
chemical masks and AK-47 assault rifles, snapped to attention.
   Two tanks roared off the cargo vessel following a stiff-gaited
color guard, and members of the ship's crew said 145 tanks remained
in the belly of the ship. Syria has pledged to send 270 tanks.
   The Syrians also brought radar-guided anti-aircraft vehicles.
   The tanks, which sailed a week ago from the Mediterranean port
of Tartous, are the first Syrian armor to be sent. The armor will
reinforce 4,000 ground troops who earlier planted their battle flag
alongside fellow Arabs in the Saudi sands.
   The original force was made up of elite Special Forces who have
fought the Israelis and others in Lebanon.
   When asked if he thought Syrian troops would fight Iraqis,
Khalid said, ``Let's hope (they can be used) to prevent war.''
   He called their arrival ``a great contribution from a brother
country to defend the kingdom.'' About 300,000 troops, mostly
Americans, make up the multinational force.
   Khalid spoke in Arabic to the Syrian troops, saying that Iraq's
Aug. 2 conquest of Kuwait was wrong and would be punished by God.
   ``There is One who sees everything,'' Khalid said, according to
an intepreter. ``We are all sure his hand will come very soon.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0047 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 1634EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-AngelIsland     11-04 0336</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Angel Island,0408</SECOND>
<HEAD>The Western Ellis Island Not As Warmly Remembered</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SAN FRANCISCO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The 50th anniversary of the closing of
Angel Island, gateway into the United States for thousands of
Chinese immigrants, won't be marked with the flourish that
celebrated the restoration of Ellis Island.
   Both islands were immigration stations, Ellis Island in New York
Harbor and Angel Island in San Francisco Bay.
   But no Statue of Liberty greeted the 175,000 Chinese who
immigrated via Angel Island between 1910 and 1940.
   Angel Island is regarded by many Chinese not as a gateway but as
a prison where many were held for months before being allowed
entrance to the United States. In fact, it is near Alcatraz, the
island prison.
   For them, the closing of the station on Nov. 5, 1940, represents
a ``first step toward the healing process,'' said Paul Chow, whose
father was kept on Angel Island for six months.
   No big event was planned to commemorate Monday's anniversary,
but neither does the Chinese community want to forget.
   ``I think it would be a big mistake to forget,'' said Phil Choy,
a San Francisco architect whose father immigrated from China.
   A small celebration was planned on the mainland to remember the
island's place in U.S. immigration history, Chow said.
   Chow has led volunteer tours of the Angel Island barracks for 18
years and has been the leader of a historical advisory committee
that has fought to restore the site. The island is maintained as a
park and is accessible by ferry.
   He invited immigration officials on a tour recently to urge them
to include the island in a centennial celebration next year of the
founding of the Immigration and Naturalization Service.
   ``Having seen it, we'd like to do something to let people know
more about it,'' said Connie Mackey, co-director of the INS
centennial committee.
   A 1980 collection of poems, titled ``Island,'' records poetry
the Chinese carved into the walls of their wooden barracks.
   And a documentary, called ``Carved in Silence'' after the poems,
started distribution in 1988.
   In the documentary, Lee Puey You described her first encounter
with the United States. ``I had to take off all my clothes. It was
so embarrassing and shameful for me. Back in China, I never had to
take off everything. But it was different here in America. I found
it very strange.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0048 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 1641EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Pakistan     11-04 0318</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Pakistan,0371</SECOND>
<HEAD>Benazir Bhutto and Husband Take National Assembly Oaths</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KATHY GANNON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ISLAMABAD, Pakistan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Former Prime Minister Benazir Bhutto
and her husband - both facing legal battles - took the oath of
office in the National Assembly on Sunday in the fifth civilian
government in 43 years.
   Asif Ali Zardari, 38, charged with kidnapping and extortion, was
freed from jail to attend the ceremony but must return when the
assembly session ends next week.
   Ms. Bhutto, who boycotted Saturday's session to protest her
husband's absence, faces seven charges of misconduct before special
one-judge tribunals probing political corruption during her 20
months in power.
   She said she is worried about her husband's treatment.
   ``They're keeping him in exactly the same conditions as when
there was martial law. He has nothing,'' Ms. Bhutto, ousted Aug. 6.
   Zardari, jailed in the southern port city of Karachi since Oct.
10, said his lawyers told him not to talk to reporters. He was
elected to represent a sprawling slum district in Karachi.
   He and Ms. Bhutto have denied any wrongdoing.
   Ms. Bhutto, 37, elected to represent Larkana in southern Sind
Province, could be banished from politics for up to seven years if
found guilty on any of the charges.
   Zardari could be sentenced to 15 years in jail if convicted of
allegations he kidnapped a Pakistan-born Briton and extorted
$800,000.
   It is expected Zardari will be staying in the Sehala guest
house, where Ms. Bhutto and her mother, Nusrat, were imprisoned in
1978 after Ms. Bhutto's father was toppled in a coup. He was later
hanged.
   Ms. Bhutto's Pakistan People's Party was routed in the Oct. 24
national elections, which she claims included widespread fraud. Her
party and three allied groups won 45 seats in the 217-seat
assembly.
   A right-wing coalition of 18 parties controls 105 seats and
claims loyalty from 40 other legislators. They have nominated as
prime minister 41-year-old industrialist Nawaz Sharif, who is
expected to easily win the post Tuesday. The swearing-in ceremony
is to take place later the same day.
   Gohar Ayub Khan, a coalition candidate, easily won the speaker's
chair Sunday.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0049 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 1652EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p AM-PoliticalBriefs     11-04 0604</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Political Briefs,690</SECOND>
<HEAD>Minnesota Poll Shows Governor, GOP Challenger in Dead Heat</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ST. PAUL, Minn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A poll released Sunday showed Democratic
Gov. Rudy Perpich virtually tied with Republican challenger Arne
Carlson, who was put on the GOP ticket just last week.
   Perpich was favored by 39 percent of the likely voters surveyed
and Carlson by 38 percent, according to the Pioneer Press-WCCO-TV
Poll,
   Twenty-two percent were undecided and 2 percent favored other
candidates.
   The survey was conducted last Monday through Thursday among 760
Minnesotans who indicated they are likely to vote Tuesday. The
survey had a margin of error of 4 percentage points.
   Carlson was placed on the ballot after Republican nominee Jon
Grunseth withdrew from the race last week because of allegations of
sexual impropriety.
   Ten percent of the voters said the controversy over Grunseth
will make them less likely to vote for other Republican candidates
in Tuesday's election, enough to influence the outcome of a close
race.
   Thirty-eight percent of those surveyed said they had an
unfavorable impression of the governor and 45 percent had a
favorable impression.
   And, by a margin of more than 2-to-1, voters agreed with the
statement, ``it's time for a change in Minnesota's top elected
officials.'' Among those people who said they wanted a change,
Carlson led Perpich by a 55 percent to 17 percent margin.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>---</HEAD>
<HEAD>Kansas Poll Shows GOP Hayden Moving Ahead of Democrat Finney</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOPEKA, Kan. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Republican Gov. Mike Hayden has opened a
slight lead over Democratic challenger Joan Finney in the final
days before Tuesday's election, according to a poll published
Sunday.
   Forty-one percent of those surveyed either solidly backed Hayden
or were leaning in his favor, compared to 36 percent for Mrs.
Finney, according to the Topeka Capital-Journal's telephone survey
of 1,000 registered voters.
   Eight percent favored independent candidate Christina
Campbell-Cline, and 15 percent were undecided.
   The respondents described themselves as likely to go to the
polls Tuesday. The margin of error was plus or minus 3 percentage
points.
   Earlier polls by the newspaper showed Mrs. Finney with a 48
percent to 35 percent lead over Hayden in early September, and each
candidate was backed by 37 percent of those surveyed early in
October.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>---</HEAD>
<HEAD>Poll Shows Weld, Silber Neck-and-Neck In Massachusetts</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Republican William Weld has gained ground in the
Massachusetts governor's race and now is running neck-and-neck with
Democrat John Silber, according to a poll released Sunday.
   Silber was favored by 44 percent of those surveyed for the
Boston Globe-WBX-TV and Weld by 41 percent. The poll's margin of
error was 3 percentage points, making the race a statistical dead
heat.
   Twelve percent were undecided and independent High Tech
Candidate Len Umina was supported by 3 percent of those polled.
   ``We think we're going to catch him,'' Weld said. ``It's moving
our way so quickly. Either we'll catch him this weekend or in the
booth this Tuesday.''
   Silber campaign officials said their internal polls show the
Democrat ahead with the help of independents who have been moving
to the Silber camp.
   In the U.S. Senate race, the poll showed Democratic Sen. John
Kerry had pulled ahead of Republican rival James Rappaport by 20
percentage points, 55 percent to 35 percent. After the primary
election, the two were in a virtual dead heat.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>---</HEAD>
<HEAD>Candidate Ends Up At Wedding, Not Meeting</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TULSA, Okla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   U.S. Senate hopeful Stephen Jones was amazed
to find 100 cars parked at a church where he was to address the
Kingfisher County Farm Bureau.
   Jones, who is running against Democratic Sen. David Boren, said
he grabbed as many campaign brochures as he could carry and hurried
inside. That's when he noticed some fellows bringing in champagne.
   ``Man, I thought, the Kingfisher County Farm Bureau has suddenly
gotten a little more lively,'' Jones said.
   Then Jones spotted a three-tiered cake and men in tuxedos.
   ``It instantly dawned on me that I was at a wedding,'' he said.
   Jones said he returned to where he'd been passing out brochures
and said, ``I'm David Boren,'' then walked out.
   He later learned the farm bureau meeting was in a church 18
miles to the north.
   ``I think I got their votes,'' Jones said of his church
appearance. ``But I didn't get to kiss the bride or eat any of the
cake.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0050 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 1658EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-WeatherpageWeather     11-04 0325</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Weatherpage Weather,0374</SECOND>
<HEAD>Snow Reaches Southern Plains, Cold Invades Texas</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   A snowstorm moved out of the Rockies and onto the Plains on
Sunday, and rain fell along and behind a strong cold front
stretching from Texas to the Midwest.
   At midday, snow was falling over southwestern Kansas, western
Oklahoma including the Panhandle, and the northern Texas Panhandle.
   By mid-morning, 2{ inches of snow had fallen at Guyman, Okla.,
and 2 inches fell at Garden City, Kan.
   On Saturday, the storm produced 19{ inches of snow at Cuchara in
south-central Colorado.
   At midday, the cold front extended across northwestern Ohio,
west-central Indiana, south-central Missouri, southwestern Arkansas
and western Texas.
   When the cold front moved through Corpus Christi, Texas, during
the morning, wind shifted from out of the north and the temperature
fell 13 degrees in one hour.
   A warning of freezing temperatures overnight and into Monday
morning was posted for El Paso, Texas.
   Rain fell across southern Lower Michigan, northwestern Ohio,
northern Indiana, northern and west-central Illinois, southeastern
Iowa, Missouri, northwestern Arkansas, southeastern through
south-central Kansas, and northern and central Oklahoma, and
showers and thunderstorms reached along the lower Texas Gulf Coast
and over southeastern Texas.
   Freezing rain was scattered over north-central Missouri.
   Rain also fell on northern Florida.
   Snow fell over eastern and central Idaho, and western Montana,
with accumulations up to 8 inches possible at higher elevations
   Rain fell from northwestern California across western Oregon and
western Washington state, western Idaho, and central Montana.
   Heaviest rainfall during the six hours up to 1 p.m. EST 1.62
inches at Paacious, Texas, and 1.02 inches at Fort Smith, Ark.
   In Alaska, a winter storm warning was posted through Monday over
the Tanana Valley, west of Delta. Up to 8 inches of snow was
possible on top of 8 inches that already had fallen. Fairbanks got
7 inches of snow in 24 hours.
   Sunday's low for the Lower 48 states was a record-tying 7 below
zero at Laramie, Wyo.
   Temperatures around the nation at 3 p.m. EST ranged from 25 at
Laramie to 87 in Florida at both Fort Myers and Tampa.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0051 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 1717EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Olympics-SouthAfrica     11-04 0468</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Olympics-South Africa,0526</SECOND>
<HEAD>South Africa on Road Back to Olympics</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ANGUS SHAW</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HARARE, Zimbabwe (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   African sports officials opened the door
Sunday for South Africa's return to the international arena once
apartheid is ended.
   They cautioned, however, at the close of their first direct
meeting with South Africa sports organizers that non-negotiable
conditions for re-entry will take time to put into effect.
   A communique specified that South African participants will not
be allowed back into Olympic or international sports until the
apartheid system of racial separation is ``completely eradicated''
and South Africa's disparate and segregated sports bodies are
merged under non-racial banners.
   ``There can be no concessions on this,'' Jean Claude Ganga of
the Congo told reporters after reading the communique.
   Ganga presided over the Harare gathering of 43 representatives
of all major South African sports organizations and 14 officials of
the African branch of the International Olympic Committee.
   The Association of National Olympic Committees of Africa, the
main African Olympic organization, set up two steering committees
charged with promoting and monitoring an end to apartheid in South
African sports.
   ``We are happy with the discussions. The door has not been
slammed shut,'' said Sam Ramsamy, chief of the South African
Non-Racial Olympic committee.
   The participants agreed to establish an eight-member committee
to coordinate reforms inside South Africa in liaison with an
African monitoring committee scheduled to hold its first meeting in
March.
   Ganga said the Africans were encouraged that a new era of
dialogue with the South Africans and among South African sports
people themselves was beginning.
   He said the South Africans showed willingness to work toward
their country's return to the global sporting arena.
   ``I am convinced this is possible. It might take some time, but
it is possible,'' Ganga said.
   He is president of the Association of National Olympic
Committees of Africa. He said the International Olympic Committee
asked his organization to review the 20-year international sports
boycott of South Africa.
   South African sports organizers say political reforms introduced
in South Africa this year by President F.W. de Klerk have improved
their country's image enough to allow for an easing of world sports
bans imposed by the IOC in 1970.
   Continuing reforms toward dismantling apartheid should enable
South Africans to compete in the 1992 Olympics, the South Africans
say.
   But African sports officials believe the pace of reform could
admit South African athletes to the 1996 centenary games in Atlanta
only if legalized racial segregation is abolished completely by
then.
   De Klerk, head of South Africa's white-led government, has
launched a program of social and political reform. He is
negotiating with black groups to give majority blacks a say in the
country's political system.
   South African delegates at the Harare talks represented all
major sports in that country. They included senior rugby and
cricket officials responsible in the past for circumventing the
international sports boycott by organizing unofficial tours.
   The African officials said any future ``rebel'' tours would be
viewed as a setback to restoring international recognition of South
African sports.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0052 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 1718EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-PotPeriodical     11-04 0200</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Pot Periodical,0206</SECOND>
<HEAD>Marijuana Magazine Cloing After Decade</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CORVALLIS, Ore. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Sinsemilla Tips, the magazine for
marijuana growers, is going out of business after 10 years because
of the nation's anti-drug climate, its publisher says.
   ``Drug hysteria and paranoia'' in the United States led to
circulation declines for the quarterly magazine, publisher Tom
Alexander of Corvallis said recently. The last issue of the
periodical named for a potent strain of pot will be released this
month.
   ``Ten months ago, our circulation was 20,000,'' he said of the
quarterly printed in Portland. ``Now, it's 4,000.''
   Alexander's store in Corvallis, Full Moon, also was hit during a
nationwide series of raids on stores alleged to be selling
equipment used for marijuana cultivation.
   First published in May 1980, Sinsemilla Tips was printed in
Eugene until about 1986, then was printed in Portland. Labeling
itself as a ``domestic marijuana journal,'' the magazine featured a
variety of marijuana-related news, features and advice columns, as
well as analysis of drug issues.
   The publication's circulation reached its peak of 20,000 in 1987
and maintained that level until last year, when the stepped-up
government action against marijuana cultivation began to cut its
magazine sales, he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0053 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 1722EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Brazil-USSub     11-04 0159</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brazil-US Sub,0165</SECOND>
<HEAD>Judge Orders American Submarine Out Of Brazilian Waters</HEAD>
<DATELINE>RIO DE JANEIRO, Brazil (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A judge ordered a U.S. submarine
out of Brazilian waters, saying it poses an enviromental danger
because it is nuclear-powered, news reports said Sunday.
   The judge in the northeastern coastal city of Recife ruled that
the USS Greelings must withdraw to 200 miles from the Brazilian
coast, outside territorial waters.
   The submarine is part of a naval task force docked in Recife,
1,500 miles northeast of Ro de Janeiro. The vessels are here for
joint training maneuvers between the American and Brazilian navies.
   A Marine guard at the American consulate in Rio said no one was
available to comment on the reports. The judge could not be reached
for comment either.
   The judge's ruling was in response to a petition from an
environmental group, the Rio newspaper Jornal do Brasil said. The
judge reportedly ordered a $100,000 daily fine if the order is
disobeyed.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0054 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 1722EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ClovisDig     11-04 0303</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Clovis Dig,0361</SECOND>
<HEAD>Agreement Reached Over Disputed Clovis Site Dig</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WENATCHEE, Wash. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An archaeologist will resume digging at
a site used by some of North America's earliest human inhabitants
under an agreement with Indians concerned about what will be done
with artifacts or human remains.
   The agreement was signed Friday by state officials, landowner
Dr. Mack Richey, the Confederated Colville Tribes and Michael
Gramly, dig director and curator of anthropology at the Museum of
Science in Buffalo, N.Y.
   Gramly has a state permit to excavate the 11,200-year-old site,
which has yielded stone and bone tools made in the style attributed
to the so-called Clovis people. Clovis remains, identified by a
particular style of fluted spear point, are named for a town in New
Mexico where they were first identified in the 1930s.
   The dig, scheduled to resume last month, was put on hold when
the Colvilles contended that Gramly's work in the orchard might
disturb an ancestral burial ground. They also expressed concern
about what would happen to any artifacts found.
   Under Friday's agreement, Gramly is to provide the Colvilles
with a list and photographs of all artifacts found at the site. The
state will pay a tribe member to be at the site while digging is
under way, for consultation about artifacts unearthed there.
   Gramly has said there is little possibility the site contains
human remains, and questions whether anyone now living can claim an
ancestral link to the Clovis people.
   But he appeared pleased with the agreement.
   ``A few days ago I had had it. Today, I'm a little happier and
maybe a little humbled. I'm believing in human beings again,'' he
said.
   But he contended that the problems that have stalled his project
may hinder funding for future efforts in the state.
   The agreement signed Friday will allow removal of 17 artifacts
uncovered in a 1988 dig and completion of an exploratory trench.
   Gramly said he will remove some bone artifacts as soon as they
are dry enough to be lifted. He said digging and site tours will
continue over the next two to three weeks.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0055 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 1728EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Gulf-MilitaryTown     11-04 0312</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Military Town,0373</SECOND>
<HEAD>Military Town Feels Economic Pinch With Soldiers Gone</HEAD>
<DATELINE>KILLEEN, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Since troops from Fort Hood started
shipping out to Saudi Arabia, this military town has come to look
like an economic casualty, as stores and restaurants close from a
lack of business.
   ``Business is off 35 to 40 percent,'' said Mike Lazar, 53, owner
of a topless nightclub that generally gets three-fourths of its
business from soldiers at the nearby base.
   ``There are fewer soldiers, and those that come in are spending
less,'' said Lazar. ``Why? The magic of the crowd is missing.''
   The Western Sizzlin' Steakhouse closed last month because it
lost so much business when the troops joined Operation Desert
Shield in Saudi Arabia after of Iraq's Aug. 2 invasion of Kuwait.
   Manuel Pacheco plans to sell his Boot &amp; Things Army Store.
   ``I don't know what my next move will be,'' said Pacheco. ``When
you're not making enough to pay the light bill, it's time.''
   Fort Hood's 38,000 troops - plus another 55,000 Army spouses and
children - provide a livelihood for an estimated 120,000 civilians
around Killeen, population 65,000.
   The Central Texas post accounts for about 75 percent of the
area's economy, officials said.
   ``Since the deployment, we can't find people to rent from us,''
said trailer park operator Rick Foerster.
   ``Where ordinarily I'd do $5,000 in business, I'm now doing
$200,'' said John Consentino, assistant manager of a store that
sells sports shoes.
   Jewerly store owner Rob Morris now trolls the local mall for
shoppers.
   ``Normally on a day like today (a military payday), I'd have 20
customers,'' Morris said. ``Today, I've had five. We're hoping for
the best.''
   Chamber of Commerce President Rick Murphy said ups and downs are
part of business in a military town.
   ``There's a lot of adjusting required,'' said Murphy. ``But life
goes on.''
   Tattoo shop owner Rena Hoot, 37, knows about those fluctuations.
   She did a booming business in Operation Desert Shield tattoos -
at $90 a pop - before soldiers shipped out.
   Now, Ms. Hoot watches TV in her shop. ``We'll try to tighten our
belt awhile,'' she said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0056 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 1739EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u p AM-ElectionRdp 1stLd-Writethru a0730 11-04 0865</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Election Rdp, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0730,980</SECOND>
<HEAD>Republicans Heartened By Late Polls, Democrats Project Solid Gains</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: to update with campaign appearances, SUBS 3 grafs for 4th graf
pvs, In California, SUBS 3 grafs for 21st graf, President Bush.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By DAVID ESPO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Political Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Candidates in Tuesday's congressional and
gubernatorial elections hurtled through a final weekend of
campaigning Sunday while party leaders posted rival predictions of
success.
   Republicans were heartened by a string of public opinion polls
trending in their favor and expressed optimism about the California
governor's race, the biggest prize of the midterm campaign.
   Democrats remained confident of solid gains in both Congress and
the statehouses.
   In California, Republican gubernatorial candidate Pete Wilson
shuttled to a series of public rallies, while Democrat Dianne
Feinstein visited churches in poor and minority areas of San
Francisco.
   Feinstein told parishioners it was Wilson who ``broke the back
of the 1990 Civil Rights Bill'' with his Senate vote sustaining
President Bush's veto of that bill two weeks ago.
   Wilson, buoyed by recent polls giving him a slight lead in the
race, condemned Feinstein for ``pathetic'' campaign tactics
designed to divide the state on racial and class lines.
   In the nation's most closely watched Senate race, GOP Sen. Jesse
Helms passed up church services in favor of extra rest. Democratic
rival Harvey Gantt attended services and scheduled an evening
rally.
   Not surprisingly, officials in both parties predicted success
when the votes are counted - and defined the term to their
advantage.
   Ron Brown, chairman of the Democratic National Committee, said
his party would ``pick up governor seats. We're going to pick up in
the Senate, and we're going to pick up in the House.''
   White House chief of staff John Sununu conceded Democrats would
retain control of both the House and Senate in the 102nd Congress,
and perhaps pad their majorities in both houses.
   But he quickly added, ``What we have set as a goal is to be
significantly better than the average result in an off-year
election. And if we do that, it will be a success.'' Historically,
the party controlling the White House loses roughly two dozen House
seats in the election midway through the president's first term.
   A nationwide New York Times-CBS survey depicted an electorate
pessimistic about the economy and unhappy with its government, and
the pundits said they were wary of making predictions.
   ``Definitely a Yogi Berra year, which is it isn't over till it's
over,'' Democratic pollster Peter Hart said on Cable News Network's
Newsmaker Sunday.
   One thing was for certain, it was almost over.
   At stake in Tuesday's balloting are 34 Senate seats, a new
435-member House and 36 governorships. More than 6100 legislative
races are on the ballot, and voters in 43 states and the District
of Columbia will decide the fate of hundreds of ballot initiatives.
   Adding spice to the mix was increased interest in the state
legislative races. An estimated 19 House seats will move from
northern and midwestern industrial states to the Sun Belt before
1992, and millions have been spent to maximize each party's
strength in the state legislatures that will redraw the House
district boundaries.
   Florida's gubernatorial candidates campaigned on network
television.
   ``We're saying no new taxes next year,'' said Republican Gov.
Bob Martinez, appearing on ABC's This Week with David Brinkley.
``And that's where Lawton Chiles says we need them.''
   Countered Chiles, the leader in one late pre-election poll,
``Well, I think that I don't agree right now that you have to have
new revenue.''
   Fresh polls pointed to a Republican trend in close races to pick
governors in Kansas and Ohio, and even Massachusetts, where a
survey showed William Weld in a tightening race with Democrat John
Silber.
   Minnesota Sen. Rudy Boschwitz, counted as among the GOP's
endangered incumbents, held an apparently widening edge over
Democrat Paul Wellstone according to a survey of voters in their
state.
   But a new survey in Texas suggested Democrat Ann Richards was
gaining on Republican oilman Clayton Williams.
   Bush spent the day in Houston, where he attended church with
Williams and arranged to speak by phone to rallies in Alaska, Utah,
Nebraska and Maryland.
   ``The election could be won or lost depending on who gets out to
the polls,'' Bush said in a audio link with a rally for GOP Senate
candidate Hal Daub in Nebraska. Daub is seeking to unseat
Democratic Sen. James Exon, who leads in the polls.
   ``I need more support'' from Congress, Bush said. His standard
campaign message that if Republicans could wrest control of
Congress from Democrats ``we would control the agenda - we wouldn't
be playing on the defense.''
   After raising $85 million for Republican candidates in Tuesday's
elections, the president's travel schedule has been curtailed in
recent days. Some Republicans disagree with his decision to embrace
higher taxes as part of a deficit-reduction agreement.
   The politicians and the pundits made the rounds of the Sunday's
network interview programs, generally agreeing that Democrats would
retain control of the Senate and House, and emerge from Tuesday's
elections with more governorships than the Republicans.
   But beyond there, there was little consensus.
   House Majority Leader Richard Gephardt of Missouri predicted on
NBC's ``Meet the Press' that Democrats would pick up six or seven
House seats, and two or three in the Senate.
   Sununu, in a combative interview on the same network, said the
party could lose between four and 12 seats in the House, and
predicted the two sides would ``break-even, plus or minus one'' in
the Senate races.
   Sen. John Breaux, chairman of the Democratic Senatorial Campaign
Committee, predicted no net change in the current 55-45 Democratic
majority in the Senate.
   Republican party spokesman Charles Black said Republican losses
would be held to a handful in the House, and said he believes the
GOP could eke out a gain of seats in the Senate.
   The New York Times-CBS survey of 1,445 adults reported that
nearly four in 10 people surveyed expect things to get worse in the
country. Only three in 10 expect them to improve.
   Two-thirds of those responding believe the economy is in bad
shape and 77 percent believe government is run by special interests
looking out for themselves.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0057 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 1747EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-UN-Climate     11-04 0461</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-UN-Climate,0525</SECOND>
<HEAD>Scientist Ask for Quick Action on Global Warming</HEAD>
<DATELINE>GENEVA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Scientists from about 100 countries said
policymakers should take immediate action against global warming
and that no nation has economic or technical problems that prevent
it from contributing to the effort.
   The panel of about 700 experts, meeting for a U.N. climate
conference, unanimously said that over the past decade a ``clear
scientific consensus has emerged'' on global warming expected to
occur in the next century.
   The report is intended to be used by policymakers. It set few
targets, but environmentalists said its conclusions provide another
spur for the United States to act.
   Washington says more research is needed before targets can be
agreed for cutting emissions of heat-trapping ``greenhouse gases.''
   The conference report, finished late Saturday, will be forwarded
to a landmark meeting of ministers in Geneva from Monday to
Wednesday. Heads of government due to attend include prime
ministers Margaret Thatcher of Britain and Michel Rocard of France.
King Hussein of Jordan is also expected.
   The ministers are due to give formal blessing to the launching
of global negotiations on warming, scheduled for February.
   Daniel Becker of the Washington-based Sierra Club said
environmental groups welcomed the ``very strong statement by the
scientists,'' but that the draft ministerial declaration remained
under a cloud.
   Officials drafting the declaration Sunday remained locked in
sharp differences of approach, mainly between Washington and the
European Community, which urges quick action. The EC wants to
stabilize carbon dioxide output at current levels by the year 2000
and a commitment to reductions after that.
   The scientific panel included members from the United States and
the Soviet Union, the two biggest contributors of man-made carbon
dioxide.
   The gas, much of which is released by burning fossil fuels, is
believed to account for more than half of the heat-trapping
``greenhouse effect'' that causes global warming.
   ``Countries are urged to take immediate actions to control the
risks of climate change with initial emphasis on actions that would
be economically and socially beneficial for other reasons as
well,'' the report said.
   It said ``technically feasible and cost-effective opportunities
exist to reduce carbon dioxide emissions in all countries.''
   More research is needed but remaining uncertainties should not
delay action, the report said.
   The final version of the report said ``many industrialized
countries'' can reduce their carbon dioxide output by at least 20
percent by 2005. Soviet scientists objected to an earlier draft
that said ``most'' instead of ``many.''
   Drawing on numerous published studies, the experts again
outlined the climate upheaval that global warming could cause.
These include flooding of vast coastal areas and islands as sea
levels rise. Global warming is also fear as a threat to farming,
forests and fishing.
   Apart from carbon dioxide, the report cites chlorofluorocarbons
and methane as major greenhouse contributors.
   Scientists believe that if nothing is done to curb them,
emissions of carbon dioxide and other heat-trapping gases could
boost global temperatures 5.4 degrees by the end of the next
century, the fastest rise in 10,000 years.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0058 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 1813EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-AlaskaEarthquake     11-04 0160</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Alaska Earthquake,0164</SECOND>
<HEAD>Earthquake in Aleutian Islands; No Damage Reported</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ANCHORAGE, Alaska (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A moderately strong earthquake rattled
the few residents of the remote Aleutian Islands Sunday, but there
were no immediate reports of damage or injuries.
   The quake measured 5.6 on the Richter scale, according to the
Alaska Tsunami Warning Center. It struck at 1:05 p.m. Alaska
Standard Time and was centered about 10 miles south of Amchitka
Island, said Tom Sokolowski, chief of the Tsunami Warning Center in
Palmer.
   Amchitka is about 1,225 miles southwest of Anchorage near the
western end of the Aleutians, which stretch from Alaska toward the
Soviet Union.
   ``It was felt strongly on Amchitka, rattled clocks on walls, but
there was no damage,'' Sokolowski said. He said the quake didn't
cause a tsunami, sometimes called a tidal wave.
   An earthquake that registers 5 on the Richter scale of ground
motion is capable of causing considerable damage in a densly
populated area.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0059 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 1816EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Chile-Bomb 1stLd-Writethru a0715 11-04 0296</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Chile-Bomb, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0715,0338</SECOND>
<HEAD>Three U.S. Sailors Injured in Bombing at Restaurant</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS thruout to UPDATE with more details released on Britons
who were injured; MINOR EDITING; no pickup</NOTE>
<DATELINE>VINA DEL MAR, Chile (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A bomb exploded at a German
restaurant in this seaside resort, injuring three sailors from the
U.S. aircraft carrier Abraham Lincoln and five other people, police
and the U.S. Navy said Sunday.
   No group claimed responsibility for the bombing, which occurred
shortly before midnight Saturday, according to police in Vina del
Mar, 180 miles west of Santiago.
   Since President Patricio Aylwin took office in March, ending 17
years of military rule, there have been several bombing attacks,
mostly attributed to the far-left Manuel Rodriguez Patriotic Front.
   Two of the injured sailors were treated at a local hospital and
released, while the third was treated on board the Abraham Lincoln,
said Navy Cmdr. Stephen Honda in Norfolk, Va. Injuries were limited
to cuts and bruises caused by flying glass and other debris, Honda
said.
   About 40 people were in the restaurant, the Max Moritz, when the
bomb went off. They included a group of sailors from the
Nimitz-class aircraft carrier, docked in the neighboring port city
of Valparaiso on a five-day port stop.
   The bomb was placed near the kitchen and damaged the restaurant
and neighboring buildings, police said without elaborating.
   Three British tourists and two waitresses were also injured in
the attack. One of the Britons was seriously injured, the police
statement said.
   In London, a Foreign Office spokesman said the three injured
British men had been working in Chile. He said two were discharged
after medical treatment, but the third has been transferred to
Santiago for treatment.
   The Abraham Lincoln is steaming around South America as part of
a scheduled transfer from the Atlantic to the Pacific fleet. It is
scheduled to arrive in Alameda, Calif., its home port, in late
November.
   The identities of the injured sailors were not released.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0060 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 1823EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>d a AM-BRF--OfficerKilled 1stLd-Writethru a075 11-04 0138</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Officer Killed, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0755,0142</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dallas Policeman Killed When Hit By Stolen Car</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS last two grafs, `The stolen...,' to UPDATE with two men
arrested. No pickup.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>DALLAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A police officer was killed when he was run over
by someone driving a stolen car early Sunday, authorities said.
   The officer was placing flares around an accident on an
expressway when he was killed about 1:30 a.m., a police spokeswoman
said.
   Sunny Ma Love, 39, a native of Cambodia, had been on the force
two years, said spokeswoman Vicki Hawkins.
   The stolen car was found, and two men were arrested, Ms. Hawkins
said.
   ``We know they were in a stolen car and they were traveling at a
high rate of speed,'' Ms. Hawkins alleged. ``Whether or not they
intended to hit the officer, we don't know that.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0061 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 1833EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Soviet-Cathedral 1stLd-Writethru a0736 11-04 0277</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Cathedral, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0736,0318</SECOND>
<HEAD>Faithful Jam Red Square as Cornerstone Blessed For Cathedral</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 2 grafs for 2-3 bgng `The event...' to CLARIFY that
parade is next Wednesday, RESTORE dropped word; pickup graf 4
`Russian Federation...'</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos MOSB5,6</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   More than 2,000 people pushed past police in Red
Square on Sunday to pray and watch the blessing of a cornerstone
for a cathedral to be built on the site of a 17th century church
razed by Stalin.
   The event took place under the stony gaze of a three-story
portrait of Communist leader Vladimir Lenin erected for the
Revolution Day parade scheduled for Wednesday.
   Dozens of priests in sky-blue robes carried gold icons and
marched with Russian Orthodox Church Patriarch Alexi II of Moscow
across the square and past the Lenin mausoleum.
   Russian Federation President Boris N. Yeltsin and Moscow Mayor
Gavriil Popov held candles as the patriarch consecrated the
cornerstone with holy water. The Cathedral of Our Lady of Kazan is
expected to be completed in two years.
   The original cathedral, built in 1630 under Czar Mikhail
Romanov, was destroyed in the 1930s by Josef Stalin. It was
replaced by a summer cafe and later a public toilet.
   The patriarch held a service in Uspensky Cathedral inside the
Kremlin to celebrate the feast day of Our Lady of Kazan. Scores of
worshipers who shielded flickering candles in their hands marched
through the Spassky Gate as bells pealed in the square.
   The priests carried the icon of Our Lady of Kazan, created
shortly after the cathedral opened in the 17th century. A wooden
cross was placed near the cornerstone, and religious documents were
sealed inside the stone.
   Police tried to hold back the more than 2,000 spectators, but
they pushed through them to get a closer look.
   The Moscow Patriarchate is raising funds for the construction of
the cathedral.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0062 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 1840EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>d p AM-Bush-Voter     11-04 0318</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bush-Voter,340</SECOND>
<HEAD>President Picks Name at Random And Comes Up With ... A Staunch
Democrat</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: retransmitting a0759 to correct category code.</NOTE>
<HEAD>With AM-Bush</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RITA BEAMISH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HOUSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The last thing Democratic voter Malissia Johnson
expected Sunday afternoon was a call from President Bush, but even
in her surprise she says she never told him she'd vote for
Republican Clayton Williams.
   ``I said I would vote, I didn't say who I was going to vote
for,'' in the Texas gubernatorial race, she told The Associated
Press after Bush called her from a get-out-the-vote phone bank.
   As it turns out, she said she's voting for Williams' Democratic
opponent, Ann Richards.
   That wasn't the impression the grinning president Bush gave
reporters who watched him call Mrs. Johnson after phoning a handful
of registered Republicans to encourage them to vote for Williams,
the GOP gubernatorial candidate.
   A reporter dared Bush him to pick a name from the phone book at
random after he went through names provided on cards by the GOP
campaign workers.
   Bush grabbed the book and picked out Mrs. Johnson, who said she
makes $70 every two weeks caring for elderly people in their homes.
She and her retired husband, who suffered a stroke two years ago,
support themselves on that salary and his Social Security, she
said.
   Bush was beaming when he hung up the telephone, giving the
impression that he had happened upon a Williams voter, although he
didn't actually say so.
   But Mrs. Williams, contacted later, said she wouldn't vote for
Williams in Tuesday's election because, ``I'm not a Republican.''
   Asked what she thought of Williams, to whom Bush has devoted
considerable campaign time, she said, `` I'm just not going to vote
for him that's all.''
   Furthermore, she said, she did not vote for Bush in 1988, but
cast her ballot for his Democratic opponent, Michael Dukakis.
   Nonetheless, she was excited to get the president's call,
although at first she thought it might be a trick.
   ``I didn't have an idea that he would call.''
   What does she think of Bush's performance as president?
   ``I guess he's doing all right, the best he can. He's OK, I
guess,'' she said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0063 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 1903EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Mexico-Squatters     11-04 0169</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mexico-Squatters,0170</SECOND>
<HEAD>Two Die, Dozens Wounded In Land Dispute Near Mexico City</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MEXICO CITY (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two people were shot to death and dozens
wounded in an hourlong fray over 160 vacant lots occupied by
squatters in a town near the capital, authorities said Sunday.
   The Saturday battle involved at least 800 people and pitted
squatters from the militant peasant organization Antorcha Campesina
against residents of Iztapaluca, a city of 137,000 people southeast
of Mexico City in Mexico state.
   State government spokesman Alexander Naime said in a telephone
interview that both of those killed were longtime residents of
Iztapaluca. He said 24 people were hospitalized.
   Naime said the crowd dispersed after 450 police arrived. He said
30 people were arrested.
   News reports quoted Aquiles Cordoba Moran, the leader of
Antorcha Campesina, as saying 51 people were wounded and claiming
that gunfire broke out when police tried to oust the squatters.
   Naime dkisputed this, saying the fighting flared when Iztapaluca
residents tried to oust the squatters.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0064 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 1917EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p AM-Bush 2ndLd-Writethru a0758 11-04 0850</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bush, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0758,990</SECOND>
<NOTE>EDS: Subs 2nd graf, ``You won't xxx to CORRECT Malissia to Mary;
FYI, Malissia is Mary's mother-in-law and the phone is listed in
her name</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By TOM RAUM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HOUSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush worked the telephones hard Sunday,
calling British Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher, five Republican
candidates around the country and a Houston woman whose name he
picked from the phone book on a dare.
   ``You won't believe this, but this is the president of the
United States,'' he told a woman he identified as Mary Johnson of
Houston. ``I'm just doing a little work at the polls, at the
polling operation, trying to get people out to vote.''
   Bush told the woman he hoped she would vote for Republican
gubernatorial candidate Clayton Williams as well as for other
Republicans.
   ``Will you?'' he asked in apparent, albeit misplaced, delight at
her response.
   The woman told reporters later that she was a registered
Democrat, had voted for Democratic presidential candidate Michael
Dukakis in 1988 and planned to vote for Democratic Texas
gubernatorial candidate Ann Richards.
   ``I just told him I was going to vote,'' Ms. Johnson told The
Associated Press. ``I didn't tell him who I was going to vote
for.''
   Bush made the call as he spent a low-key day pursuing both
diplomacy and politics by telephone in his adopted hometown, where
he will vote on Tuesday.
   In the morning, he phoned Mrs. Thatcher for what White House
press secretary Marlin Fitzwater said was a discussion of Persian
Gulf strategy.
   He also made pep talks by phone to separate rallies for two GOP
candidates in Nebraska and one each in Utah, Maryland and Alaska.
   But his most unusual call of the day came as he and Williams
attended a GOP get-out-the-vote center and Bush joined volunteers
in manning a phone bank.
   After calling a half dozen voters from a list of Republicans
given to him by party workers, a reporter suggested that Bush pick
a number at random.
   Bush grabbed the book, picking out a name and saying, ``this may
be tough. ... This is risky.''
   ``Needless to say, I'd appreciate it if you could vote for our
full ticket,'' Bush told the woman. ``I hate to call you on Sunday,
but I was just out here believing in, participating in, the
political process. I don't know if you're registered, but if you
are I hope you'll go to the polls and I hope you'll vote for our
ticket,'' he said.
   He told the woman: ``They dared me to open the book and just
pick out a number, and you're up at the top of the page. ... And
so, thank you. I hope I didn't impose on your family.''
   Bush was less talkative when it came to reporters' questions.
   ``No questions today. It's Sunday. Been to church. ... I can't
do it. Too tired today,'' Bush said when reporters persisted.
   ``Dealing with a Congress completely controlled by Democrats is
not an easy assignment,'' the president said in an audio linkup
with a rally in Plattsmouth, Neb., for Republican Senate candidate
Hal Daub.
   Earlier, Bush took Williams to services at St. Martin's
Episcopal Church with him on Sunday morning. He also planned to
campaign for Williams in three Texas cities on Monday: here, Tyler
and Waco, Richards' hometown.
   The president made short, upbeat remarks in a succession of
afternoon phone calls to campaign workers at rallies across the
nation - steering away from controversial issues like his support
of a package including new tax increases.
   To the Hal Daub for Senate rally, Bush said: ``This election
could be won or lost depending who gets out to the polls.''
   Daub, a former House member, is seeking to unseat Democratic
Sen. James Exon, who has been leading in recent polls.
   ``I need more support'' from Congress, Bush said, delivering his
traditional campaign message that if Republicans could wrest
control of Congress from Democrats ``we would control the agenda -
we wouldn't be playing on the defense.''
   Bsh also telephoned a rally for Nebraska Republican Gov. Kay
Orr, who is in a tight race with Democratic challenger Ben Nelson.
   Speaking to campaign workers in Salt Lake City for Republican
congressional candidate Genevieve Atwood, Bush attacked the ``tax
and spend mentality of the Democrats.''
   ``Good luck on Tuesday. Don't take anything for granted,'' he
told her.
   And, speaking to a rally in Salisbury, Md., for Republican
congressional challenger Wayne Gilcrest, Bush said: ``Don't let
them tell you no one can make a difference.''
   Bush concluded his messages, including one to Alaska on behalf
of GOP gubernatorial candidate Arliss Sturgulewski, by saying,
``Over and out.''
   The president was giving his most visible support to Williams in
the hard-fought Texas gubernatorial race. He was to campaign for
Williams on Monday in Waco - Ann Richards' home town - as well as
in Tyler and in Houston.
   Williams, meanwhile, defended himself against criticism by
Richards for not paying any income taxes in 1986.
   ``I was fighting for my life in 1986. I didn't pay any tax
because I didn't have any income,'' Williams told reporters after
he went to church with Bush. He blamed his troubles on the economic
downturn that affected the state from then-plunging oil prices.
   ``I don't understand Ann Richards. She must have been somewhere
else in 1986,'' Williams said.
   He welcomed Bush's campaign help, but said the president hadn't
given him any advice for winning in the final stretch of what has
been a tight and acrimonious campaign.
   Meanwhile, John Sununu, Bush's chief of staff, disputed
contentions that Bush's decline in popularity and his wavering in
tax and budget deliberations were costing Republicans support.
   Interviewed from Houston on NBC-TV's ``Meet the Press'' program,
Sununu conceded that the White House had made some mistakes in
budget and campaign strategy but sought to minimize them, saying
``we all make mistakes.''
   Sununu predicted Republicans would ``around break-even, plus or
minus one'' in the Senate and in the House would lose from four to
12 seats.
   Sununu denied that the president was seeking to politicize the
Persian Gulf crisis by repeatedly issuing bellicose rhetoric aimed
at Saddam on the campaign trail.
   The crisis is at the top of the national agenda, and the
president needs to talk about it regardless of the forum, Sununu
said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0065 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 1932EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Pope-Beatification     11-04 0191</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Pope-Beatification,0203</SECOND>
<HEAD>Four Religious Raised To Last Step Before Sainthood</HEAD>
<DATELINE>VATICAN CITY (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Pope John Paul II on Sunday beatified two
19th century French and two Italian women who dedicated their lives
to helping the poor.
   Among those honored by the pontiff in a ceremony in St. Peter's
Basilica was Louise-Therese de Montaignac, who founded the Oblates
of the Sacred Heart. The church credits her with the miraculous
healing of a young railway worker from Toulouse who was in a coma.
   The other Frenchwoman beatified was Marthe Aimee Le Bouteiller,
the daughter of a poor farmer who became a nun. Her intercession
was credited for the return to health of an English nun in Sister
Marthe's religious institute.
   The two Italian women came from rich families and renounced
prospects of prestigious marriages to enter the convent and work
with the poor.
   Sister Elisabetta Vendramini founded a Franciscan institute in
Padua. Sister Maria Schinina, who died in 1910, was instrumental in
founding the Sacred Heart Institute in Ragusa, Sicily.
   Beatification is the last major step before possible sainthood.
It requires that a Vatican committee certify that at least one
miracle is attributed to the person's intercession.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0066 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 1936EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-GreenAutoRepair 1stLd-Writethru a0675 11-04 0530</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Green Auto Repair, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0675,590</SECOND>
<HEAD>Environmentalist Trying To Change The World of Car Maintenance</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: Subs 8th graf, ``I don't know xxx to CORRECT that Freon found
in air conditioners, not antifreeze</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By CHARLES CAMPBELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>McLEAN, Va. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Jeff Shumway is taking a new approach to
fixing cars, starting with the green plants dangling between his
auto repair bays.
   Shumway's Ecotech Autoworks also has environmental magazines in
the waiting room, energy-saving light bulbs in the bathroom,
organic grape spritzer in the cold-drinks machine and office
flooring made from recycled tires.
   ``It's a message I'm sending to the general public,'' said
Shumway, the shop's 31-year-old owner. ``I'm using the talent I
have as a mechanic and the commitment I have as an
environmentalist.''
   After 10 years working on cars, Shumway found he was appalled at
the common practices of spilling used oil and antifreeze down the
drain, venting ozone-destroying gas from air conditioners into the
atmosphere and dumping empty oil cans into the trash.
   ``The single-quart oil containers would be overflowing into the
road,'' he said. ``I couldn't stomach this.''
   Last year, Shumway bought an auto repair shop near Tyson's
Corner, an affluent shopping district in the Washington suburbs. At
first, he concentrated on building a reputation for quality car
repair, then launched the new name and new concept on Jan. 1, 1990.
   The most important difference between Ecotech and the
traditional repair shop, Shumway said, is the way he disposes of
waste fluids and gases.
   ``I don't know if the public realizes that auto servicing is the
No. 1 cause of preventable CFC release,'' Shumway said.
Chlorofluorocarbons, found in the Freon gas coolant of air
conditioners, are blamed for causing a hole in the Earth's layer of
protective ozone.
   A portable red box in Shumway's shop - a Robinair Refrigerant
Recovery and Recycling System - ingests the Freon and cleanses it
so it can later be injected into another customer's air
conditioner.
   ``There's no reason every shop shouldn't have one,'' he said.
``But they're not cheap. They cost about $3,000.''
   Most auto repair places simply vent the Freon into the air,
replacing it with new canned gas. One provision of this year's
Clean Air legislation, however, will require shops to begin
recycling air conditioner coolant by 1993.
   Another rolling recycling machine in Shumway's shop processes
antifreeze fluid. Used oil goes into an oil-fired heater that
replaced electrical heaters in the shop. Shumway buys oil in bulk,
rather than in one-quart cans. He recycles cans, bottles, paper,
cardboard and used metal parts.
   ``All we're throwing away is a little bit of plastic,'' he said.
   Pete Minetree of Vienna, Va., one of Shumway's customers, said
he's pleased to know his car's used antifreeze and oil aren't
damaging the environment.
   ``I'll tell you the truth. He's more expensive than others, but
it's worthwhile,'' Minetree said. ``The effect of what he's doing,
if everybody did it, would be tremendous. But somebody's got to
lead in this and he's doing it.''
   And those hanging spider plants? Partly decorative, partly
functional.
   ``These are test plants to see how they survive in a harsh
environment,'' Shumway said. ``I think they serve to clean up the
air. Plus they look nice.''
   If all goes well, he said, ``We may bring more in and turn this
into a jungle canopy.''
   Since the environmental transformation, the shop's business has
doubled, Shumway reports. He has four employees, has just taken on
a partner and is prospecting for a second location in Maryland.
   ``This is off and running,'' he said. ``I get people from 50
miles away sometimes. I think 80 percent of my new customers come
because of these recycling machines. People want to do the right
thing.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0067 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 1947EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p AM-TexasGovernor 1stLd-Writethru a0766 11-04 0332</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Texas Governor, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0766,0377</SECOND>
<HEAD>Texas Gubernatorial Candidates Go to Church, Debate Income Taxes</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 6th graf to ADD that Richards is state treasurer.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By MARCUS C. STEWART III</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DALLAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush and Democratic leaders lent their
influence Sunday in the hotly contested race for Texas governor.
The president accompanied Clayton Williams to church and Democrat
Ann Richards courted minority voters with the help of the nation's
first elected black governor.
   Richards visited four black Baptist churches here and later
appeared at a rally with former Congresswoman Barbara Jordan and
Virginia Gov. Doug Wilder.
   ``On Tuesday we are going to recapture citizen politics,''
Jordan told the crowd. ``We are black and white and red and all
colors. We're not going to be purchased by any millionaire
cowboy.''
   Rancher-oilman Williams and his family, meanwhile, attended
services with President Bush at St. Martin's Episcopal Church in
Houston.
   He and the president later made an appearance before Republican
campaign workers at a phone bank.
   The candidates continued to trade accusations about income
taxes. Richards, the state treasurer, attacked Williams for not
paying federal income tax in 1986 and Williams defended himself,
adding that he opposed a state income tax.
   ``The rich who can afford to pay taxes don't and Clayton
Williams is the epitome of that,'' Richards told a rally of about
1,000 supporters at the Martin Luther King Jr. Community Center
Gymnasium.
   Williams, a millionaire with oil and ranching interests,
disclosed Friday that he paid no federal income tax in 1986.
   ``I was fighting for my life in 1986. I didn't pay any taxes
because I didn't have any income,'' he told reporters in Houston
Sunday.
   Richards said Williams had recovered enough to bankroll his
campaign.
   ``Four years later, he writes a personal check for $8.5 million
to buy the governorship,'' she said.
   Williams said the real issue was whether Richards would permit a
state income tax. Williams said he supported a constitutional
amendment prohibiting such a levy.
   ``I said I'd veto an income tax if it comes to my desk,''
Williams said. Richards ``won't say if she will.''
   Richards has said on several occasions that she opposes a state
income tax.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0068 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 2004EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-GulfRdp 3rdLd-Writethru a0747 11-04 0877</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf Rdp, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0747,1078</SECOND>
<HEAD>Iraq Rejects Kuwait Withdrawal; Hostage Issue Strains Unity</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 6 grafs for 17th `Meanwhile, three ...' to UPDATE with
Americans' arrival in London. Picks up 18th graf `The Europeans ..
.'</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos BAH1-5</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LAURA KING</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   In a new outburst of belligerence, Iraq said Sunday it was ready
to fight a ``dangerous war'' rather than ever give up Kuwait. One
European official warned that divisions over the hostage issue are
endangering the anti-Iraq alliance.
   ``Iraq is not going to negotiate on Kuwait,'' Iraq's information
minister, Latif Jassim, told a news conference in Baghdad. He
insisted Iraq's annexation of Kuwait, which it overran three months
ago, would stand.
   ``We are going to defend our 19th province on any condition,
even if we have to fight a dangerous war,'' he said, referring to
Kuwait.
   Iraq also said it was recalling an unspecified number of retired
army officers to active duty.
   Secretary of State James A. Baker III visited U.S. troops in the
Saudi desert earlier Sunday and said it was hard to say whether
they would be called into combat. The presidents of Egypt and
France expressed hopes that economic pressure rather than military
might could force Iraq out of Kuwait.
   Meanwhile, four American ex-hostages were on their way home a
day after being freed, and fifteen Europeans arrived in Jordan
after being released by the Iraqis. They were among thousands of
foreigners were trapped in Iraq and Kuwait when Saddam Hussein's
troops took over the emirate Aug. 2.
   The first POWs of the Persian Gulf crisis - three French
soldiers - had a homecoming of their own in Paris on Sunday, but it
wasn't exactly a hero's welcome. French officials have said the
soldiers, who were captured last week, might have strayed into
Iraqi territory, and that they probably face punishment for their
carelessness.
   The new Iraqi vow to keep Kuwait at all costs came only hours
after a former Japanese prime minister, Yasuhiro Nakasone, met with
Saddam - and said the Iraqi president had demonstrated ``great
earnestness and seriousness'' about seeking peace.
   Nakasone's visit, aimed at winning the release of Japanese
hostages, comes as Japanese lawmakers are considering a plan to
send troops to the gulf to join the multinational force arrayed
against Saddam.
   The troop-deployment proposal has drawn strong criticism from
those who say it would violate Japan's postwar peace constitution,
even though the troops would be confined to non-combat roles.
   Iraq's official news agency said Nakasone had told Saddam it was
unlikely lawmakers would approve the proposal. Nakasone, speaking
to reporters, made no mention of such assurances, but the report
underscored the way the hostages can be used as leverage.
   Belgium's foreign minister complained that efforts by individual
nations to win their citizens' freedom are eroding unity against
Iraq.
   ``Saddam is creating this royal court of all sorts of Western
pilgrims who visit him to obtain the release of hostages,'' the
Belgian official, Mark Eyskens, said in a television interview
Sunday in Brussels.
   Sometimes the visitors ``let themselves be lured into political
discussions'' with Saddam, which could ``jeopardize the united
stand against Saddam's invasion and annexation of Kuwait,'' he
said.
   Belgium requested a special European Community meeting on the
matter on Tuesday or Wednesday in Rome.
   The European Community had already tried to discourage a
hostage-freeing bid by former West German Chancellor Willy Brandt,
who leaves for Baghdad on Monday. Like Nakasone's trip, Brandt's is
a private mission with government backing.
   Three of the four Americans freed by Iraq on Saturday flew into
London Sunday night on their way home. A U.S. Embassy official in
Jordan said the fourth - Michael Barner, 49, of Woodsworth, La. -
made other, private arrangements for returning home.
   Former hostages Dr. Abdul Hamid Kangi, 50, an Indian-born
American from Glencoe, Ill.; Randall Trinh, 49, of Hacienda
Heights, Calif., and Raymond Gales, a diplomat from the besieged
U.S. Embassy in Kuwait, were met at Heathrow airport by U.S.
officials from the London embassy.
   The three were reluctant to speak to reporters.
   Trinh, clutching his stomach, said: ``I am too sick to say
anything now. The main thing I am looking forward to when I get
home to the U.S. is to be with my family.''
   He confirmed he had been held at an unspecified installation as
part of Saddam's ``human shield'' policy. ``It was terrible,'' he
said, but he did not elaborate.
   Some Americans and other Westerners have been held at stategic
installations in Iraq to deter any foreign air attack.
   The Europeans freed by Iraq on Sunday were 14 Germans and one
Belgian, all men. The German Embassy said they were granted exit
visas after their work contracts ended.
   Baker, who arrived in the region Sunday to start his latest
Mideast mission, said it wasn't possible to say now whether the
gulf crisis would explode into war.
   ``The main question is what the future holds,'' he told
reporters after visiting with troops in the eastern Saudi desert.
``That is something that cannot be answered with any specificity.''
   Baker has said he is trying to lay the foundation for stronger
economic and political measures against Iraq, including possible
military action.
   French President Francois Mitterrand, who met Sunday in Egypt
with President Hosni Mubarak, said he hoped it would not come to
that.
   ``The powerful countries have to strictly enforce the embargo to
avoid ... a destructive war,'' he said, referring to U.N. sanctions
against Iraq. Mubarak agreed, saying the sanctions were the best
means of avoiding bloodshed.
   In Iraq, a Foreign Ministry source said Sunday two ``hostile
aircraft'' had penetrated Iraqi airspace from Saudi Arabia on
Saturday. There was no immediate response from U.S. and Saudi
officials, who have denied reports of similar incursions in the
past.
   The Baghdad government, stressing its willingness to fight,
announced Sunday it was recalling some retired army officers to
duty. It did not say how many.
   Iraq has an estimated 430,000 troops in southern Iraq and
Kuwait, confronting about 300,000 troops in the U.S.-dominated
multinational force in the gulf region.
   About 2,500 Syrian troops arrived in Saudi Arabia on Sunday,
joining an estimated 4,000 Syrians aleady deployed as part of the
multinational effort. They brought with them about 150 tanks, the
first armor Syria has sent.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0069 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 2004EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p AM-CaliforniaGovernor     11-04 0341</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-California Governor,0380</SECOND>
<HEAD>Wilson, Feinstein Trade Charges Over Civil Rights, Class Politics</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DOUG WILLIS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Gubernatorial candidate Dianne Feinstein
hammered Sunday on Pete Wilson's vote against the Civil Rights Act,
and Wilson accused Feinstein of trying to divide Californians along
racial and class lines.
   Feinstein, a former San Francisco mayor, toured a half dozen
churches in minority and poor San Francisco Bay area neighborhoods,
accompanied by Democratic National Committee Chairman Ron Brown.
Wilson, a Republican from Southern California, made a final swing
through the farm country of the San Joaquin Valley.
   Feinstein told parishioners at St. Paul of the Shipwreck Roman
Catholic church in San Francisco that Wilson ``broke the back of
the 1990 Civil Rights Bill.'' Wilson cast his Senate vote to
sustain President Bush's veto of the bill, which the president said
would lead to racial hiring quotas.
   Supporters said the bill was intended to overturn a series of
U.S. Supreme Court decisions that hampered affirmative action
programs and to ban racial harassment in the workplace.
   She slammed Wilson and Republicans in general on education,
Social Security and abortion rights.
   She received an occasional ``amen'' from the 200 churchgoers as
she declared that California had become the ``cocaine and heroin
capital of the world'' during the tenure of Republicans George
Deukmejian as governor and Wilson as senator.
   Wilson condemned Feinstein's campaign tactics as he visited
local Republican headquarters in Bakersfield, Fresno and Modesto to
rally volunteers for a final get-out-the-vote effort.
   ``There is something a little pathetic in a campaign that
depends upon dividing California, dividing the cities against the
rural areas, the rich against the poor and the black against the
white,'' Wilson said.
   ``That is, I think, frankly, a losing tactic and deserves to
be,'' he said, referring to a Feinstein television commercial that
claims he ``votes for tax breaks for millionaires'' but raised
taxes on the middle class.
   ``We're not going to revert to the tired, stale, threadbare
bromides of the 1930s,'' he told about 200 volunteers at his
campaign's Bakersfield headquarters. ``We don't seek to set one
group of Californians against another. To the contrary, the change
we stand for is going to unite California.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0070 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 2019EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p AM-BallotMixup     11-04 0186</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Ballot Mixup,0199</SECOND>
<DATELINE>MEDIA, Pa. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Lewis du Pont Smith isn't as greedy as voters
might think looking at a sample ballot. The chemical heir wants
only one legislative job, not four.
   A sample ballot published in the Delaware County Daily Times
correctly identified Smith as an independent candidate in the 5th
Congressional District. It also listed him as a candidate in the
state House races in the 159th, 160th and 168th districts.
   ``It was my fault,'' said R. Bruce Downing, director of the
county election board. A sample ballot his office supplied to the
paper was wrong, he said, adding that a corrected version was
supplied the paper to publish Monday.
   Downing said only the ballot published in the paper was
incorrect; a sample distributed around the county were correct.
   Smith, a follower of imprisoned political extremist Lyndon H.
LaRouche Jr., had asked the District Attorney's Office to
investigate the mix-up. But District Attorney William H. Ryan Jr.
said he determined the mix-up was only an error.
   Smith, 33, is running against Republican Rep. Richard Schulze,
an eight-term incumbent, and Democrat Sam Stretton, a West Chester
attorney, in the Tuesday election.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0071 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 2026EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-Iran-Iraq     11-04 0169</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Iran-Iraq,0172</SECOND>
<HEAD>Iran Claims Iraq Still Holds POWs</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NICOSIA, Cyprus (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Iran claimed Sunday that Iraq still holds
hundreds of Iranian prisoners of war, despite Baghdad's assertion
it has freed all its captives of the eight-year Persian Gulf war.
   The official Islamic Republic News Agency quoted Hojatoleslam
Akbar Abutorabi, spiritual leader Ayatollah Ali Khamenei's
representative for POW affairs, as saying Tehran has submitted a
list of 231 Iranians still held in Iraq to the International
Committee of the Red Cross.
   ``We have countless documents proving that many more Iranian
POWs are still held in Iraq,'' he declared.
   The Iran-Iraq war was halted by a U.N.-brokered cease-fire in
August 1988. But the exchange of prisoners was delayed because of
deadlocked peace negotiations.
   The exchange finally began Aug. 17 after Iraqi President Saddam
Hussein made peace overtures to Iran. Reports at the time said
Saddam was trying to woo his old enemy to bolster his position in
the international confrontation over his Aug. 2 invasion of Kuwait.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0072 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 2054EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Gulf-Americans     11-04 0480</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Americans,0596</SECOND>
<HEAD>Three American Ex-Hostages from Iraq Reach London</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NIC1</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Three Americans who were held hostage in rraq -
one as part of Saddam Hussein's human shield policy against attack
- arrived in London on Sunday night after being allowed to leave
Baghdad.
   The former hostages are Dr. Abdul Hamid Kangi, 50, an
Indian-born American of Glencoe, Ill.; Randall Trinh, 49, of
Hacienda Heights, Calif.; and Raymond Gales, a diplomat from the
besieged U.S. Embassy in Kuwait.
   They flew into Heathrow airport on a scheduled British Airways
flight from Larnaca, Cyprus, on their way home.
   Two unidentified officials from the U.S. Embassy in London met
them at the doorway of their Boeing 757 aircraft. The officials
said they understood two of the three were freed because they were
ill and the other because a member of his family had a medical
condition.
   A fourth released hostage, Michael Barner, 49, a construction
worker of Woodsworth, La., made private arrangements to return
home, according to a U.S. Embassy official in Amman, Jordan. Barner
was suffering from what was described as a neurological disorder.
   All three men arriving in London were reluctant to speak to
reporters but Trinh chatted briefly.
   Clutching his stomach, he said: ``I am too sick to say anything
now. The main thing I am looking forward to when I get home to the
U.S. is to be with my family.''
   He said he had been in Iraq for more than three months.
   ``We only heard we were going to be allowed to leave two days
ago,'' Trinh added.
   He confirmed he had been held at an unspecified installation as
part of Iraqi President Saddam Hussein's human shield of hostages
sent to potential targets. ``It was terrible,'' he said without
elaborating.
   He was asked whether it was a military or civilian
establishment, but repeated he was ``too sick'' to speak.
   Some Americans and other foreigners have been held at strategic
Iraqi sites to deter any foreign air attack.
   The embassy officials said the Americans would be staying at a
hotel in London overnight before flying individually on scheduled
flights to the United States on Monday.
   The officials refused to give particulars.
   Gales shielded his face with an airline ticket from television
cameras as he emerged from the customs hall and only said, ``I have
no comment to make.''
   Trinh and Gales were driven from the airport by the embassy
officials in a minibus.
   Kangi avoided reporters and vanished after merging into the
crowd in the arrivals hall.
   On arrival earlier Sunday at Larnaca, Cyprus, Trinh, walking
unsteadily, told immigration officials, ``I just want to lie down.
I need to lie down.''
   He told The Associated Press, ``I was held in a hotel for most
of the time, but they took me to a special place once. I think it
was a strategic place. There were other foreigners there. I was
very nervous.''
   Kangi, wearing a round, beaded Indian hat, was highly agitated.
When photographers at Larnaca took his picture, he lunged at them
shaking his fist saying, ``I'll break that over your head! Don't
take any more pictures!''
   The group left behind in Amman two peace activists, who
negotiated the release of the four American hostages with Iraqi
authorities.
   An embassy official at Larnaca said Tarek Mohammed Al-Heneidy of
Rockport, Mass., and the Rev. Michael Kenny, of Juneau, Alaska,
members of the Fellowship for Reconciliation, will leave Amman on
Monday.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0073 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 2110EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-BRF--Korea-Crash 1stLd-Writethru a0679 11-04 0176</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Korea-Crash, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0679,0191</SECOND>
<HEAD>21 Killed in Bus-Truck Collision</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 2 grafs to UPDATE with three more confirmed dead;
pickup graf 3 `The bus...'</NOTE>
<DATELINE>SEOUL (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A chartered bus carrying more than 40 people home
from a visit to former President Chun Doo-hwan collided with a
truck and plunged into a mountain lake Sunday, killing at least 21
people, police said.
   They said two people were missing and another 21 were
hospitalized in the crash near Inje, 65 miles east of Seoul. The
dead included the truck driver, police said.
   The bus apparently tried to pass another vehicle, hit the truck
head-on and plunged into Lake Soyang, police and news reports said.
   Yonhap, the national news agency, said the bus was carrying a
group of people who had attended the same high school as the
president, and their spouses. They had visited Chun at the Paek
Tan-sa Buddhist temple, where he has been in exile since November
1988.
   Chun went into exile after apologizing to the nation for human
rights abuses and corruption during his seven-year rule. His term
as president ended in early 1988.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0074 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 2113EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-GrissomTrial     11-04 0412</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Grissom Trial,0478</SECOND>
<HEAD>Jurors Convict Grissom in Triple Murder, Eight Other Counts</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RICHARD D. LIPSEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>OLATHE, Kan. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A 29-year-old man was convicted Sunday of
killing three suburban Kansas City women whose bodies never were
found after they disappeared in the summer of 1989.
   A jury deliberated 12 hours over two days before convicting
Richard Grissom Jr., a painting contractor of three counts
first-degree murder. He was charged in the disappearances of Joan
Marie Butler, 24, of Overland Park, and roommates Christine Rusch
and Theresa Brown, both 22, of Lenexa.
   Prosecutors alleged that Grissom killed the women for a total of
$3,600 drawn from their bank accounts. They have declined to
speculate about how they were killed or what happened to their
bodies.
   ``Nothing can bring back their lives, so there is a hollowness
to this victory that will go on forever,'' said Dave Rusch, Miss
Rusch's father. ``But we're thrilled that this is a complete
victory except for one charge.''
   Miss Brown's mother, Bobby Brown, said she was ``elated'' by the
verdict.
   ``My main concern now is to know we have Richard Grissom where
he belongs. I'm disappointed we haven't had a chance to hear him
speak,'' she said. ``We just have to imagine what he's thinking.''
   Ralph Butler, the father of Miss Butler, said: ``I hate Richard
Grissom.''
   Defense attorney Kevin Moriarty said, ``Richard Grissom
maintains his innocence and we are very disappointed in the
verdict.'' Another defense attorney, Tom Erker, said the conviction
would be appealed.
   Grissom also was found guilty of one count of aggravated
kidnapping, four counts of robbery, one count of aggravated
burglary and two counts of theft.
   Grissom didn't show emotion when the verdict was read in Johnson
County District Court.
   He faces three possible life sentences on the murder
convictions. A hearing on post-trial motions was set for Nov. 20.
   Defense attorneys rested their case Friday without presenting
any evidence. They had asked Judge William Gray to dismiss the
charges, saying prosecutors hadn't proved Grissom committed any
crimes or that the women were dead.
   But during the 10-day trial, Johnson County District Attorney
Paul Morrison said the evidence, though largely circumstantial, was
enough for conviction.
   Evidence against Grissom included master keys to the women's
apartments, blood stains in Miss Butler's rental car and personal
belongings of Miss Rusch and Miss Brown found in Grissom's car.
   Morrison also reminded jurors of statements Grissom made to
police when he was arrested at Dallas-Fort Worth International
Airport within weeks of the women's disappearances.
   Officers said Grissom told them, ``You'll dig them up,'' when
questioned about the women.
   Moriarty argued those statements shouldn't be considered because
there was no tape recording, videotape or notes of the eight-hour
session with officers.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0075 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 2116EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-MedflyVictory     11-04 0560</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Medfly Victory,0664</SECOND>
<HEAD>Officials Hope To Declare Victory In Medfly War</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MICHAEL WHITE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Officials hope to declare victory in a long
and costly battle against the Mediterranean fruit fly this week,
but they said Sunday the war against the crop-destroying pest isn't
over.
   No flies have been found during inspections of traps meant to
sample the population and assess the threat to the state's $18
billion a year farm industry. That leads experts to believe the
Medfly is gone for now, said Roy Cunningham, chairman of the state
Medfly Science Advisory Panel.
   ``We know people are shipping fruit in all the time illegally,
but the infestation from the previous episode is over,'' Cunningham
said. The pest is believed to enter the state in illegally imported
fruit and vegetables.
   State and federal quarantines could be lifted by Thursday or
Friday, officials said. But the long-term war will continue through
stricter inspection programs and a state-sponsored search for
better traps and lures.
   The quarantines were imposed on movement of fruit from infested
areas, mostly in urban and residential sections of Southern
California. The big worry was that the flies could spread to
agricultural areas in the southern part of the state or to the farm
country in the San Joaquin Valley to the north.
   Slightly smaller than a common housefly, the Medfly lays its
eggs in soft-skinned fruits causing the fruit to rot.
   The fly has plagued California farmers since the early 1980s.
Since July 1989 the state and federal governments have spent $52
million in a program that included aerial pesticide spraying over a
500-square-mile area to battle the stubborn pest.
   The state's costliest campaign against the Medfly began in 1980,
when $100 million was spent over 27 months in a statewide
eradication effort. Quarantines that kept produce from being
shipped out of state cost California farmers another $100 million.
   In the most recent battle, some communities were sprayed
repeatedly with the pesticide malathion, generating a loud public
outcry that included lawsuits and 300 damage claims against the
state.
   The protest left officials leery of another prolonged aerial
campaign, said Gera Curry, spokeswoman for the California
Department of Food and Agriculture.
   ``This is not our preferred method. This is not the best way to
do it,'' said Curry. ``But no one anticipated the explosive nature
of the infestation last year.''
   But opponents contend officials are just trying to lull the
public into complacency.
   ``They're saying victory because it will calm us down, but it's
a political facade,'' said Pat Reichenberger, former mayor of the
Los Angeles suburb of Monterey Park who opposed aerial spraying
over his community. ``I don't think it's over by any means. They'll
be back.''
   Typically, infestations are attacked by a single spraying
followed by the release of millions of sterile flies so that
propagation declines.
   The state resorted to heavy, repeated sprayings last summer
after the supply of sterile flies was exhausted and infestations
continued to threaten California's fruit industry.
   Just when victory actually is declared depends on the results of
recent trap inspections. Because the length of the Medfly's life
cycle varies widely - from three weeks to more than a month,
depending upon weather - officials want to be certain the flies
really are gone, Curry said.
   Stricter inspection measures will help prevent another massive
aerial spraying campaign, Curry said.
   Researchers are convinced the Medfly enters California from
fruit and vegetables brought in illegally from Hawaii and Central
and South America. A bill recently passed by the Legislature
authorized the department to begin regular inspection of plane and
ship cargos coming from overseas, Curry said.
   Airlines and shipping firms will pay for the program through
user fees, Curry said.
   Another piece of legislation allocates $750,000 for research to
development alternative methods of fighting the Medfly, including
the better traps and lures.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0076 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 2117EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-EscapeeCaptured     11-04 0292</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Escapee Captured,0327</SECOND>
<HEAD>Inmate With a History of Escapes Arrested Again</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CLEVELAND (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A convicted drug runner with a history of
slipping out of official custody was arrested near here Sunday, two
days after escaping from an Arkansas jail, authorities said.
   The man, Roger Carparroso, has escaped from U.S. authorities at
least three times in seven years and jumped bail in Little Rock,
Ark., last year, said Peter J. Elliott, a U.S. marshal's office
spokesman.
   Carparroso, 30, was jailed in Painesville following his
afternoon arrest by deputy marshals and Cleveland police, Elliott
said. Painesville is about 25 miles east of Cleveland.
   Carparroso was first arrested in the Cleveland area on Oct. 5
for allegedly picking up Panamanian drug shipments in New York City
and delivering them across the country, he said.
   Carparroso had $10,000 and seven fake Dominican passports when
authorities arrested him in suburban Parma Heights, said Elliott.
He was taken to Arkansas, where he had jumped bail following an
unrelated June 1989 indictment on credit card fraud charges.
   Carparroso escaped from the Crawford County, Ark., jail Thursday
morning by walking through two doors that should have been locked,
said Chief Deputy Marshal Michael J. Blevins.
   The first time Carparroso slipped out of U.S. officials' custody
was in 1983, while being held by federal authorities in Miami,
Elliott said. Carparroso, an illegal alien, was to be deported
following an arrest on drug-related charges.
   He turned up five years later at Atlanta International Airport.
Following his 1988 arrest, Carparroso was sentenced to a 35-year
jail term for cocaine trafficking on the earlier drug charges.
   Soon after that sentencing, Carparroso slipped out of his
handcuffs and escaped while being transported from the Clayton
County Jail in Georgia to the county courthouse, said sheriff's
Sgt. Duel Lee.
   ``He's slick,'' said Lee.
   Carparroso was arrested in Little Rock the following year on the
credit card charges.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0077 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 2154EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-HalloweenRampage     11-04 0282</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Halloween Rampage,0329</SECOND>
<HEAD>Five Arrested in Halloween Attack on Homeless</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Five teen-agers and young men accused of taking
part in a fatal Halloween rampage against the homeless were
arrested Sunday and charged with murder or attempted murder.
   Police said the five were among about a dozen youths who lay in
wait for homeless men crossing a footbridge from East Harlem to a
men's shelter on Ward's Island in the East River. The gang, some
wearing Halloween masks and armed with bats, pipes, knives and meat
cleavers, attacked homeless men, killing one and injuring nine
others, police said.
   Some shouted, `Trick or treat,'' during the assaults, police
said.
   Four of those arrested Sunday, including a 13-year-old boy, were
charged with murder and one was charged with attempted murder.
Investigators said they expected more arrestes.
   The attacks were the latest instance of seemingly senseless gang
violence to stun New York. They follow such high-profile cases as
the 1989 attack on a jogger in Central Park and the slaying of a
Utah tourist during a subway mugging this summer.
   The arrests were based on information from several sources,
including anonymous tips, said Sgt. Tina Mohrmann, a police
spokeswoman.
   Charged with murder were as: Robert Sherman, 23; Hector Torres,
15, and Aaron Ware, 13, and his brother Raymond Fenner, 22.
   The victim, Carlos Melendez, 35, died after his throat was
slashed. Three other men required from 30 to 55 stiches each to
close cuts in the face and head.
   An 18-year-old, Eric Williams, was charged with attempted murder
in the case of Roosevelt Jones, who was beaten about face with a
pipe, Mohrmann said.
   The attacks began at 9:15 p.m. and ended shortly before the
footbridge closes at 10 p.m.
   Police Capt. Daniel McKenna said last week the group apparently
attacked the homeless men for thrills: ``It was Halloween, the
homeless are there, they're an easy target.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0078 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 2224EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Peru-US     11-04 0183</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Peru-US,0189</SECOND>
<HEAD>Leftist Rebels Fire Rocket Grenades at U.S. Consulate in Lima</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LIMA, Peru (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Leftist rebels fired at least two rocket
grenades at the U.S. consulate Sunday night, shattering dozens of
windows, police said. No injuries were reported.
   Security forces held a brief shootout with the attackers, who
escaped in a pickup truck. No arrests were made.
   The attack occurred at 7:50 p.m. at the consulate offices in a
residential neighborhood of Miraflores, an upper-class district of
metropolitan Lima.
   Police said one grenade struck the outside wall of an apartment
building next to the consulate. The other grenade apparently struck
the front of the apartment building.
   The explosions shattered windows on the upper floors of the
12-story consulate, in the apartment building, and in nearby homes.
But they caused little other damage, authorities said.
   The police did not say if they believed the attackers were
Maoist Shining Path rebels or pro-Cuban Tupacamaru guerrillas, the
country's two leftist rebel groups.
   Almost 20,000 people have died in political violence since the
Shining Path took up arms against the government 10 years ago.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0079 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 2230EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-DailyNews 1stLd-Writethru a0728 11-04 0500</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Daily News, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0728,0600</SECOND>
<HEAD>Strike Continues With More Arrests And Hard-To-Find Papers</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 7th graf pvs, `Nonunion editors...,' with 2 grafs to
CLARIFY that some Newspaper Guild members have crossed picket lines
to return to work. Pick up 8th graf pvs, `Robinson said...</NOTE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The srrike-bound Daily News trudged ahead
Sunday, handing out free samples and using ``hawkers'' to sell
papers where vendors feared union intimidation.
   But spokeswoman Lisa Robinson would not say how many papers were
printed, distributed or sold.
   Vendors at 10 midtown Manhattan newsstands chosen at random
Sunday said they had no Daily News; many said they hadn't seen the
paper in several days.
   ``We're still publishing,'' said Robinson. ``We're still seeing
gaps in distribution. Many, many people support us. Some people
don't.''
   Talks have been fruitless since they began in January over
contracts that expired in March. The unions charge unfair labor
practices.
   The News was struck by eight of its 10 unions on Oct. 25, with
the Newspaper Guild joining the strike the next day. Members of the
Typographical Union have continued working because they have
guaranteed lifetime jobs.
   Since the strike began, Daily News managers have been producing
the paper with help from nonunion editors and reporters from other
papers owned by the paper's parent, The Tribune Co., and from union
members who crossed picket lines. Most of the union members who
have returned to work are photographers, sportswriters and feature
writers.
   The Tribune Co. operates the Chicago Tribune and newspapers in
Virginia and Florida.
   Robinson said strike-related incidents led to six arrests
overnight in the city and suburbs.
   Police Officer Scott Bloch said a New York Times truck driver
allegedly attacked a Daily News driver Saturday night. The News
driver broke his ankle getting out of the truck.
   Bloch said The Times driver was charged with criminal mischief,
assault and weapon possession.
   Two men were charged early Sunday with criminal mischief and
criminal tampering after they allegedly pulled radio wires off a
Daily News building on Long Island. Nassau County police Officer
Andy DeSimone said he didn't know if they were union members.
   Police say 24 people have been arrested in the city since the
strike began.
   In a full-page advertisement Saturday, the News offered a $5,000
reward for information leading to the arrest and conviction of
people involved in strike-related violence, and $500 for
information leading to an arrest. Robinson said Sunday she didn't
know if anyone had qualified yet.
   Daily News Publisher James Hoge said in a statement Saturday
that ``any suggestions for additional efforts to the federal
mediation under way in our collective bargaining can only be
considered after all the violence has stopped.''
   He said he had attempted to call the Rev. Jesse Jackson to tell
him that but had been unable to reach him. Jackson said Friday at a
rally of striking workers that he would offer his services ``in
whatever way would be effective.''
   The unions have asked Jackson to mediate the one issue that is
common to all the News' unions - the right of strikers to return to
their jobs, said Theodore Kheel, legal adviser to the unions.
   Kheel said the implication in Hoge's statement ``that the unions
control the violence is completely wrong.''
   The 71-year-old daily has been in a financial tailspin for the
past decade. The News has lost about $115 million and seen daily
circulation slip by about 700,000 since 1980. Before the strike it
was printing 1.1 million copies daily.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0080 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 2253EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-NYCMayor     11-04 0398</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-NYC Mayor,0482</SECOND>
<HEAD>Report: Mayor Have Used Fake Letter as Alleged During Campaign</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A newspaper reported federal prosecutors have
found evidence indicating that Mayor David Dinkins backdated a
letter concerning his sale of cable TV stock to his son, as his
mayoral opponent alleged last year.
   Mayoral spokesman Albert Scardino denounced the story in New
York Newsday Sunday as ``shameful and dishonest journalism'' based
on ``unfounded allegations'' made during the campaign.
   The letter became a campaign issue when Dinkins' GOP opponent,
Rudolph Giuliani, questioned whether Dinkins had paid appropriate
federal gift taxes on the transfer of stock in a cable TV company
to his son.
   In 1986, Dinkins said he transferred 588 shares of Inner City
Broadcasting Corp stock stock to his son, David Dinkins Jr., at no
cost.
   After Giuliani's accusation, Dinkins said he had sold the stock
to his son and thus wasn't subject to gift tax. He released copies
of the letter from his son - dated Oct. 30, 1985 - as proof of the
sale.
   Newsday, quoting an anonymous source close to a grand jury that
investigated the case, said evidence indicates the letter may have
been written in 1988 or 1989, though investigators were unable to
prove it conclusively.
   In the unnotarized ``Dear Dad'' letter, written by hand on lined
paper, Dinkins' son promised to pay his father $58,000 plus 8
percent annual interest by January 1991 for the stock. No payments
were made as of last year.
   Tests suggested the letter bore the imprint of a telephone
number written on another sheet of paper, the source said. The
number was of a media company the younger Dinkins was unlikely to
have had dealings with in 1985, when he was a CBS sports producer,
the paper said.
   He now is an independent television producer, and would have had
reason to dial the telephone number in 1988 or 1989, the source
said.
   The mayor's son, who lives in Las Vegas, declined Newsday's
request for an interview.
   The federal investigation into the stock transfer ended in July
without criminal charges. But a city probe continues.
   U.S. Attorney Andrew Maloney, in a confidential report
summarizing his findings for a special city investigator this July,
said he found ``substantial evidence'' the letter was not written
when dated, Newsday said.
   Maloney, interviewed by the paper Friday, declined to comment on
a grand jury matter.
   Scardino, the mayor's spokesman, dismissed the story as a rerun
of unfounded campaign allegations.
   ``It was garbage when it was put out then,'' Scardino said. ``It
was thrown in trash can at Attorney General's office but now five
months later (Newsday is) republishing the same piece of garbage.''
   Dinkins' attorney, Charles Stillman, called for a probe into how
the paper obtained information on a federal investigation.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0081 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 2302EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-PanamaIntelligence     11-04 0331</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama Intelligence,0358</SECOND>
<HEAD>Report: Noriega Aide Infiltrating New Panama Government</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A ruthless former aide to deposed Panamanian
leader Manuel Noriega has planted his own men in the new Panamanian
security force to destabilize the U.S.-backed government, according
to a newspaper report.
   The report in Sunday's editions of New York Newsday quotes U.S.
intelligence officers who debriefed Noriega loyalists after the
Dec. 20, 1989, U.S. invasion of Panama.
   Their information - contained in classified U.S. Army documents
obtained by the newspaper - is fueling concern in Washington that
Panamanian President Guillermo Endara has been unable to establish
full control of the nation, the newspaper said.
   Panamanian officials have filed a $6.5 billion lawsuit against
Noriega, who is in a federal prison outside Miami awaiting trial on
drug conspiracy charges.
   The suit includes a report that Noriega has sent coded messages
to his supporters in which he discussed how to destabilize the new
government, according to the newspaper.
   Suspicions about a potential insurgency in Panama focus on Capt.
Asuncion Eliezer Gaitan, the paper said. He is a former Noriega
aide who headed a Cuban-supported secret intelligence operation
undetected by U.S. officials before the Dec. 20 U.S. invasion,
Newsday said, quoting the intelligence documents.
   Lt. Col. Nivaldo Madrinan, chief of military intelligence under
Noriega, told debriefers Gaitan had his people in the operation,
according to Newsday.
   Jaime Simmonds, former manager of the Panamanian government
federal Credit Union, told the U.S. intelligence officials Gaitan
planned to go to Libya and return to Panama with an organization
backing up a subversive movement. The plan, according to Simmonds,
included monetary assistance from Nicaragua, Newsday says.
   Gaitan took refuge in the Vatican Embassy after the U.S.
invasion and his current whereabouts are unknown. He was known as a
ruthless soldier believed to have assassinated members of an
abortive coup against Noriega on Oct. 3, 1989, Newsday said.
   The classified U.S. documents, including more than 100
interviews with members of the former Noriega regime, were prepared
by the Joint Debriefing Center operated by the U.S. Army's 470th
Military Intelligence Brigade, the newspaper said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0082 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 1418EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-Nordstrom-Furs     11-04 0630</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Nordstrom-Furs,0767</SECOND>
<HEAD>Nordstrom Announces Closure of In-Store Fur Salons</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GEORGE TIBBITS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SEATTLE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Nordstrom Inc. says it's closing its remaining
in-store fur salons to put the floor space to better use, but
animal rights activists praised the apparel chain's announcement as
a victory.
   The Seattle-based retailer will close salons by Feb. 1 at its
stores in downtown Seattle and suburban Bellevue, at Tyson's
Corners and Pentagon City near Washington, D.C., in San Francisco
and Walnut Creek, Calif., and in Anchorage, Alaska, spokeswoman
Chris Bridenbaugh said Friday.
   Fur industry officials said the decision was another sign of
tough times for furriers, who have been hit by overproduction, a
weak economy and warm weather on the West Coast.
   ``The decision to close the fur salons is simply due to the
declining demand we have had for furs in the stores,'' Bridenbaugh
said.
   Nordstrom wants the space ``to put other products in that
customers are requesting, to be able to utilize the space better,''
she said. Managers of the individual stores will decide how the
space will be used, she said.
   Fur salons have been closed at 12 other Nordstrom stores in the
past three years, Bridenbaugh said. Nordstrom has 60 stores in
seven states.
   The salons are owned and operated by Evans Furs of Chicago,
which leases floor space from Nordstrom.
   Bridenbaugh said the decision to close the salons was
Nordstrom's. But David Meltzer, chairman of Evans Furs, said his
company made the decision to leave. He said the separation was
amicable and Evans may lease space from Nordstrom in the future.
   ``We've run their fur departments for a number of years,''
Meltzer said in a telephone interview. ``We've been increasingly
dissatisfied with the amount of volume we've been able to
achieve.''
   Meltzer said Nordstrom ``has tied one hand behind our back in
terms of advertising of furs.'' Without more aggressive
advertising, the salons haven't been able to generate enough
business, he said.
   Nordstrom's announcement was cheered by the Progressive Animal
Welfare Society, a Lynnwood-based animal-rights organization that
has long campaigned against the sale and wearing of furs.
   ``We know that fur is dead,'' PAWS spokesman Mitchell Fox said
in a news release. ``This is verification that the fur industry is
dying, too. We are very pleased with Nordstrom's trendsetting
decision to go in this compassionate direction.''
   PAWS held a rally Saturday outside Nordstrom's downtown store,
to thank the chain and to kick off its anti-fur efforts for the
Christmas season. About 60 demonstrators passed out leaflets and
carried signs urging shoppers not to buy or wear furs.
   Bridenbaugh said Nordstrom will continue to sell fur outside of
the salons, such as fur-trimmed coats in other departments.
   She said fur salons were possible in the future.
   Meltzer called PAWS' position ``ridiculous,'' and noted that
Nordstrom sells leather goods and other products made from animals.
``Their core business is shoes,'' he said.
   Thomas Tashjian, an analyst with Seidler Amdec Securities Inc.
in Los Angeles, said fur sales were strong in the mid-1980s ``as
the working-class woman got more money in her wallet'' and furs
were in fashion. But he said the market has been relatively flat
since.
   Tashjian said there was no way to measure what impact
animal-rights activists might have had, ``but it's an issue of
conversation that wasn't there five years ago when the industry was
extremely robust.''
   Bill Outlaw, spokesman for the Fur Information Council in
Washington, D.C., downplayed the effects of animal protection
groups. But he said the shaky economy has hurt the entire retail
industry, especially luxury items such as furs and jewelry.
   ``When you get into difficult economic times, people certainly
start looking at their expenses,'' he said.
   Meltzer said economic jitters haven't affected furs any more
than other retail segments. But both he and Outlaw said
overproduction by fur ranchers in the past year hurt, as did the
weather.
   All outerwear sales have been slow on the West Coast for the
past couple of years because the weather's been unseasonably warm,
Meltzer said.
   He said Evans Furs decided to pull out of Nordstrom stores in
Southern California last year. ``We closed them up because the
temperature never got below 80. It was beach day every day,'' he
said.
   Last year, Evans Furs, the nation's largest fur retailer, lost
$4.6 million from operations on $140 million in sales, and wrote
off $5.8 million, mostly for closing stores and shrinking its
organization, Meltzer said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901104-0083 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-04-90 1607EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-China-Loans     11-04 0287</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-China-Loans,0308</SECOND>
<HEAD>Report: China Bank to Make Loans to Foreign-Funded Companies</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   China's state bank will extend $93 million in
special loans to help about 100 foreign-funded companies deal with
cash shortages, an official newspaper reported Sunday.
   In an interview with China Daily's Business Weekly, Wu Dongmin,
an official for the Bank of China, said the fixed asset loans are
earmarked for capital construction, expansion projects and to
import equipment, Wu said.
   The report said priority for the new loans will be given to
enterprises that an produce for both international and domestic
markets, projects that have advanced technology to update China's
industrial plants, and businesses involved in the fields of energy,
telecommunications, transportation and material industry.
   Wu said the new loans are intended to attract foreign capital
through more investment in China. He said money made available
through the loans would reach some businesses by the end of the
year.
   Foreign investors have been disillusioned with China because of
a market slump, cash shortages resulting from a two-year-old
government austerity program and political concerns following the
June 1989 military crackdown on student-led demonstrations urging
democratic reforms.
   Among the beneficiaries are the Guangzhou (Canton) Peugeot
Automobile Co. Ltd. And the Anyang Glass Co. Ltd., in eastern
China's Henan province, the report said.
   The Sino-French car joint venture last month received a $15
million loan from Banque Nationale de Paris to expand its annual
production and increase localization of parts.
   The China Daily said the Bank of China has supplied the
equivalent of $1.98 billion in Chinese currency and $500 million
worth of foreign currencies in working capital to foreign-funded
ventures that began operating this year.
   The figures represented increases of 80 percent and 20 percent,
respectively, in those areas over the same period last year, it
said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
</Collection>
