<Collection>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0001 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 2349EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-PlaneCrashes     04-08 0284</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Plane Crashes,0292</SECOND>
<HEAD>Five Dead in Unrelated Plane Crashes</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   A single-engine airplane crashed in thick fog in northern
California, killing three people, and authorities Sunday found two
dead in the wreckage of a small plane in north Georgia that had
been missing for 10 days.
   In St. Louis, a Missouri Air National Guard F-4 pilot and crew
member were injured when the fighter jet veered off a runway and
burst into flames during a training exercise takeoff.
   The F-4's weapons system operator suffered multiple fractures,
including his ankle and pelvis, when he ejected from the rear seat
50 feet into the air during the crash at Lambert Airport, said Air
National Guard Capt. Darrell Shoults. The pilot suffered only
bruises.
   In Arcata, Calif., the wreckage of a single-engine plane was
found Saturday in a mountainous area about one mile from a landing
strip at Kneeland Mountain, the Humboldt County Sheriff's
Department said.
   Walt Davis of Elk Grove and Merle Stone of Tulare and his wife,
name unknown, died in the crash, said sheriff's dispatcher Skip
Arnold.
   Davis' wife, Carol, survived the crash. She was taken to General
Hospital in Eureka, then to the University of California Medical
Center in Sacramento for burn treatment.
   The wreckage of a Piper PA-28 Cherokee 160 that disappeared
March 29, was found Sunday just east of Ellijay, Ga.
   The bodies of Daryl Raisly, 31, of Henryville, Ind., and
passenger Jesse Leland Street, 32, of Louisville, Ky., were
recovered, said 2nd Lt. Warren Bates of the Georgia Civil Air
Patrol.
   The four-seat aircraft, which left Lakeland, Fla., on March 29
for Sellersburg, Ind., was last seen when it made a fuel stop at
Perry, Ga.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0002 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 2353EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People-DrummerInjured 2ndLd-Writethru a0786 04-08 0260</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People-Drummer Injured, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0786,0264</SECOND>
<HEAD>Motley Crue Drummer Injured During Concert</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 5th graf, `Urtz said ...,' to DELETE now-outdated
sentence on Lee's release from hospital.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>NEW HAVEN, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Tommy Lee, a drummer with the flamboyant
heavy metal rock group Motley Crue, suffered a mild concussion when
he fell during a concert at the New Haven Coliseum, authorities
said Sunday.
   Lee, 26, fell to the floor Saturday while swinging down a rope
from on-stage scaffolding, and was in good condition at Yale-New
Haven Hospital, said hospital spokesman Tom Urtz.
   ``He is alert, awake and in good spirits,'' Urtz said.
   Lee was released late Sunday afternoon, a hospital spokeswoman
said.
   Urtz said Sunday morning that he did not know how Lee fell
except that the rappelling stunt ``was part of the routine.
   The heavily tattooed drummer is married to actress Heather
Locklear.
   Motley Crue is scheduled to perform Tuesday in Binghamton, N.Y.
Before launching its tour, the band pledged that even though all
members had undergone drug rehabilitation, its concerts would be
just as raucous as in the past.
   ``We don't just play rock 'n' roll, we live it,'' bassist Nikki
Sixx was quoted as saying in People magazine earlier this year.
``We go on tour and get broken bones, diseases, the crowd leaves
bloody. It's more like going to war.''
   Two teen-agers filed a $1.3 million suit against the band for
injuries allegedly suffered when pieces of dry ice flew from the
stage during a 1985 concert in Alabama. The case ended in a
mistrial.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0003 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 2348EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a BC-APNewsCalendar-1stAdd     04-08 0761</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-AP News Calendar - 1st Add,0813</SECOND>
<BYLINE>EDITORS:
^WIRE EDITORS:
   
   ^WEDNESDAY, April 11</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   
   Jerusalem _ Israeli Knesset, or parliament, is scheduled to
convene in special session to vote on formation of new government.
   Moscow _ Polish President Jaruzelski arrives; visit through
Saturday, April 14.
   Buchenwald, Federal Republic of Germany _ 45th anniversary of
liberation of Buchenwald concentration camp.
   Beirut _ University lecturer Brian Keenan, an English_language
teacher at the American University of Beirut who holds dual British
and Irish nationality, begins his fourth year as a hostage in
Lebanon.
   Matamoros, Mexico _ One-year anniversary of discovery of 15
victims ritually slain by a drug-dealing cult.
   Los Angeles _ Theresa Saldana attacker Arthur Jackson released
from prison but will be immediately reincarcerated on harassment
charges.
   Dallas _ U.S. House Committee on Banking, Finance and Urban
Affairs holding hearing to examine effectiveness of federal law
enforcement community in prosecuting activities which led to S&amp;L
industry collapse.
   New York _ Arraignment of Julio Gonzalez, charged with the arson
death of 87 people in the Happy Land Social Club.
   Vandenberg AFB, Calif. _ Launch of Atlas rocket carrying Air
Force science experiments.
   New Orleans _ Louisiana Racing Commission hearing on a jockey
accused of winning a race by hiding his mount in the dense fog and
then sneaking back into the pack just before the finish line.
   Boston _ New England Telephone unveils service that, among other
things, will allow doctors to treat patients by phone.
   Angels Camp, Calif. _ Owner of giant African frogs brings his
beasts to Calaveras County Fair board of directors meeting.
   Norfolk, Va. _ Court hearing for man who hunted on Sunday in
defiance of law in order to get arrested.
   East Liberty, Ohio _ Honda of America to dedicate its new $380
million, 1.4 million-square-foot auto assembly plant, near its
Marysville plant.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>THURSDAY, April 12</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   
   Bucharest _ King Michael of Romania to go to Romania for the
first time in decades.
   Bermuda _ U.S. President George Bush meets British Prime
Minister Margaret Thatcher, thru Apr. 14.
   New York _ Pulitzer Prizes announced.
   Marshall, Minn. _ First in series of national public hearings on
mental illness and its treatment in rural America, sponsored by the
National Advisory Mental Health Council and the National Mental
Health Leadership Forum.
   Simi Valley, Calif. _ 10-foot chunk of Berlin wall installed at
Reagan Library in ceremonies with East German officials.
   San Fernando, Calif. _ Preliminary hearing for the rifle-toting
woman accused of entering the home of actress Sharon Gless.
   Cincinnati _ U.S. Bankruptcy Court hearing at which the
Federated and Allied retailers plan to publicly discuss details of
a manager retention program that will cost at least $25 million
over two years.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>FRIDAY, April 13</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   
   Good Friday. Christian Good Friday procession on Jerusalem's Via
Dolorosa; Good Friday Way of Cross Procession in Rome.
   Beirut _ Lebanon's civil war, in which more than 150,000 people
have been killed, enters its 16th year.
   Bermuda _ U.S. President George Bush meets British Prime
Minister Margaret Thatcher.
   Pasadena, Calif. _ Arguments on NBC's appeal of Wayne Newton's
libel judgment in federal Court of Appeals.
   San Francisco _ Deadline for lawyers for Robert Alton Harris to
submit written arguments on why he should not be executed.
   Los Angeles _ State bar trial begins for celebrity divorce
lawyer Marvin Mitchelson, accused of professional misconduct.
   Hattiesburg, Miss. _ Sentencing for Florida attorney Newton
Alfred Winn, convicted on oine court each of conspiracy and kidnap,
extortion and purgery stemming from the 1988 disappearance of the
wife of Jackson multimillionaire Robert Hearin.
   Miami _ Sentencing of former racer Barry Kramer in attempted
helicopter escape from federal prison.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>SATURDAY, April 14</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   
   Bermuda _ Bush_Thatcher meeting ends.
   Santa Rosa, Calif. _ First anniversary of wine country rampage
that left seven dead and Ramon Salcido accused of murder.
   Molalla, Ore. _ Sen. Bob Packwood and others attend timber rally
to protest spotted owl recommendations.
   Phoenix _ Art show and sale of paintings drawn by Ruby, an
elephant who was taught to paint by her keepers as a behavioral
enrichment.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>SUNDAY, April 15</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   
   Easter. Pope's Easter message in Rome; Services at Church of
Holy Sepulchre in Jerusalem.
   Beijing _ First anniversary of death of former party chief Hu
Yaobang and start of student demonstrations.
   Beirut _ Swiss Red Cross worker Elio Erriquez, kidnapped in
south Lebanon Oct. 6, turns 40, his first birthday as a hostage in
Lebanon.
   Edwards Air Force Base, Calif. _ Shuttle Discovery lands.
   Los Angeles _ Miss Universe Contest.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>The AP</HEAD>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0004 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 0030EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Obit-Combs     04-08 0217</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Combs,0224</SECOND>
<HEAD>Thoroughbred Breeder Leslie Combs Dead at 88</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LEXINGTON, Ky. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Leslie Combs II, founder of Spendthrift
Farm, once one of the premier thoroughbred horse breeding
operations, died Saturday at the University of Kentucky Medical
Center. He was 88.
   The hospital did not disclose the cause of death.
   Spendthrift, started in 1936, grew from 126 acres to nearly
6,000 and once was the home of Triple Crown winners Seattle Slew
and Affirmed.
   Combs was a pioneer of modern racehorse syndication, getting 20
investors to put up $5,000 each in the stallion Beau Pere in the
1940s. He later syndicated such outstanding horses as Nashua,
Majestic Prince and Raise a Native.
   Combs was the first horseman to sell at yearling for $100,000
and the first to syndicate a stallion for $1 million.
   His boldest move was taking Spendthrift public in 1984. The farm
filed for Chapter 11 bankruptcy four years later, and bankers
agreed to forgive the farm's $7.8 million debt. Horsemen Henry
Hershey, Curtis Green and William duPont III bought the farm's
assets last year.
   Thomas Meeker, president of Churchill Downs Inc. in Louisville,
called Combs' death ``a great loss to the thoroughbred industry.''
   ``He'll be remembered as the master of Spendthrift Farm, one of
the greatest breeding operations in the world,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0005 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 0039EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-BRF--China-Lesotho 1stLd-Writethru a0638 04-08 0172</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--China-Lesotho, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0638,0178</SECOND>
<HEAD>China Suspends Relations With Lesotho</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS thruout to CORRECT that relations suspended not broken;
No pickup.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   China suspended diplomatic relations with Lesotho
on Saturday, two days after the small African nation established
ties with Taiwan.
   The official Xinhua News Agency had reported in English that
Beijing decided to ``break off'' relations with Lesotho, but this
appeared to be a mistranslation.
   Chinese-language reports said Beijing suspended ties, as it has
with three other small countries that recently recognized Taiwan _
Grenada, Liberia and Belize.
   China accused Lesotho of violating its pledge to recognize the
People's Republic of China as the sole legal government of China.
   Taiwan, an island province of China, is governed by the
Nationalists who fled the mainland in 1949 after being defeated by
the Communists in a civil war. The Nationalists still claim to be
the rightful rulers of all China.
   Lesotho, a kingdom with a population of 1.6 million surrounded
by South Africa, established relations with Beijing in 1983.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0006 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 0158EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Deaths 2ndLd-Writethru a0646 04-08 0903</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Deaths, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0646,0932</SECOND>
<NOTE>Eds: ADDS Evans, Flowers obits; SUBS lead of Combs obit to restore
dropped word `and'. AMs separates moved on Singer as a0629, Evans
as a0648 and Combs as a0651.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>Ronald Evans</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TOPEKA, Kan. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Ronald E. Evans, Apollo 17 command module
pilot on man's last trip to the moon, died of a heart attack at his
Arizona home Saturday. He was 56.
   The former astronaut died in his sleep and was found by his
wife, Janet, his mother-in-law, Marge Pollom of Sun City, told the
The Topeka Capital-Journal.
   Evans called his December 1972 flight to the moon in Apollo 17
``the best experience I ever had in my life.''
   He left the astronaut program in 1977 to become an officer with
Western American Energy Corp. in Scottsdale, Ariz. He was in demand
as a public speaker and traveled widely.
   Evans was born in St. Francis, Kan., and later lived in Topeka,
Kan.
   He received a bachelor's degree in electrical engineering from
the University of Kansas in 1956, where he enrolled in the ROTC
program, and a master's degree in aeronautical engineering from the
U.S. Naval Postgraduate School in 1964. He was selected in 1963 for
astronaut training and became an astronaut in 1966.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>W. Harold Flowers</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LITTLE ROCK, Ark. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Rev. W. Harold Flowers, a patriarch
of the civil rights movement in Arkansas and the oldest practicing
black attorney in the state, died Saturday at a Little Rock
hospital. He was 78 and had been suffering from cancer.
   ``His leadership, his compassion and spiritual example touched
so many lives,'' Gov. Bill Clinton said.
   ``He deserves the recognition in breaking the ice to enable
blacks to participate on equal basis with other attorneys in
representing their clients,'' U.S. District Judge George Howard Jr.
said.
   In one of his most celebrated trials, Flowers in 1947 defended
two black men who had been charged with first-degree murder in the
deaths of two white men. His motion to quash the entire jury on the
grounds that there had been no black jurors in nearly 50 years led
to the placement of 13 blacks on the prospective jurors' panel,
with three eventually seated on the jury.
   The defendants were found guilty of lesser charges, marking the
first time in Arkansas that a black man had not gone to the
electric chair upon conviction in the death of a white man.
   Flowers was ordained as a Methodist minister in 1971.
   In 1977, he was the first black named a special circuit judge
for Jefferson County. In 1980, Clinton appointed Flowers as an
associate justice of the state Court of Appeals.
   A founder and former president of the National Bar Association,
he was inducted into the association's Hall of Fame in 1986 and was
a past president of the American Bar Association and past state
president of the National Association for the Advancement of
Colored People.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>Leslie Combs</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LEXINGTON, Ky. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Retired thorougbred owner and breeder
Leslie Combs II, founder of Spendthrift Farm and known as a pioneer
of racehorse syndication, died Saturday at the University of
Kentucky Medical Center. He was 88.
   Thomas Meeker, president of Churchill Downs Inc. in Louisville,
called Combs' death ``a great loss to the thoroughbred industry.''
   ``He'll be remembered as the master of Spendthrift Farm, one of
the greatest breeding operations in the world,'' he said.
   Spendthrift, started in 1936, once was renowned as a premier
thoroughbred breeding operation, growing from 126 acres to nearly
6,000. It once was the home of Triple Crown winners Seattle Slew
and Affirmed.
   Combs became known as the ``pioneer of modern racehorse
syndication,'' when he set a deal of 20 investors for $5,000 each
in the stallion Beau Pere in the 1940s. He later syndicated such
outstanding horses as Nashua, Majestic Prince and Raise a Native.
   Combs was the first horseman to sell at yearling for $100,000
and the first to syndicate a stallion for $1 million.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Arthur Singer</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Arthur B. Singer, a naturalist and painter whose
watercolors of state birds were affixed to hundreds of thousands of
letters mailed in the 1980s, died of cancer Saturday. He was 72.
   The stamp series bearing Singer's paintings is believed to have
been the largest-selling special issue in the history of U.S.
postage. The Postal Service issued the stamps featuring the birds
and flowers of the 50 states in 1982.
   Singer, who graduated from the Cooper Union Art School in New
York in 1939, received its Augustus St. Gaudens Medal in 1962 after
750 of his paintings appeared in ``Birds of the World,'' the first
of many books he illustrated. Golden Press issued a new edition of
the book in 1983.
   He received the Hal Borland Award from the National Audubon
Society in 1985, on the 200th anniversary of Audubon's birth.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Adolf Pabst</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BERKELEY, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Adolf Pabst, a mineralogy expert at the
University of California at Berkeley whose research was honored
when a California silicate was named after him, died Tuesday at age
90.
   Pabst taught in Berkeley for 40 years and lectured around the
world on his work in crystal deformation. He received the Roebling
Medal, the highest honor bestowed by the Mineralogical Society of
America, which he served as president in 1951.
   Fellow scientists at Berkeley named a California mineral
Pabstite in honor of his work in 1965.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0007 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 0219EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-FarmAid 3rdLd-Writethru a0650 04-08 0861</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Farm Aid, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0650,0879</SECOND>
<HEAD>Farm Aid Benefit Concert Returns With Environmental Focus</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS in 2 grafs with event finale; pick up 2nd graf, `Farm
Aid ...'. SUBS 15th graf pvs, `Carolyn Mugar ...', to UPDATE
revenue estimate; pick up 16th graf pvs, `Mugar said ...'</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos NA2, 12</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KEN KUSMER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>INDIANAPOLIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Financially strapped Farm Aid returned
Saturday with its first concert in 2{ years. Performers sounded a
message of concern not only for the family farmer but also for the
land they till.
   The concert crammed with more than 60 acts lasted nearly 14
hours, finishing after midnight. It concluded with an all-star
chorus singing ``This Land is Your Land,'' led by Arlo Guthrie, son
of the song's composer, Woody Guthrie.
   Farm Aid President Willie Nelson topped the list of performers
who said they were forging a coalition with family farmers,
environmentalists and consumers to work toward reducing the amount
of chemicals used in food production.
   ``Somewhere between a lot of chemicals and no chemicals there's
a happy medium,'' Nelson said at a news conference before
performing the first song of the 12-hour show in the Hoosier Dome.
   ``As experts, the farmers will have to tell you how much do they
need (and) how much are they forced to use,'' Nelson said. ``I
think that's the difference. If they can get enough money for a
bushel of corn, they don't have to drain that acre for every ounce
that's in it.''
   Inside the arena, early arrivals among the sellout crowd of
45,000 settled in with blankets and pillows for the marathon event.
Many of the more popular performers, including Neil Young, Bonnie
Raitt and Don Henley, didn't perform until the final two hours.
   Elton John made an unexpected appearance late in the program and
performed three songs. The British rock singer-pianist had been in
Indianapolis to visit critically ill teen-age AIDS victim Ryan
White, a close friend.
   ``This one's for Ryan,'' John said before beginning ``Candle in
the Wind,'' a song he wrote about the tragic life of Marilyn
Monroe. Afterward, the crowd delivered its biggest ovation of the
show.
   John's set provided a somber note during a day of activism on
behalf of family farmers and the environment.
   The Rev. Jesse Jackson said the family farm crisis is expanding.
``Since 1980, we've lost about 75,000 farms largely because farmers
couldn't earn enough from their crops to pay their bills,'' he said.
   Jackson criticized reports from Secretary of Agriculture Clayton
Yeutter citing farm income at record levels, a point some Farm Aid
critics have raised as evidence this concert was unnecessary.
   ``What (Yeutter) doesn't say is that when the numbers are
adjusted for inflation, farm income in the last decade was at its
lowest since 1910,'' he said.
   Singer Henry Lee Summer, from Brazil, Ind., used the stage to
speak out against out-of-state trash being dumped in Indiana.
   ``I've got a message to all those big businesses that want to
dump all their trash and toxic waste here: We don't deserve it,''
Summer said, drawing a big cheer.
   Concertgoers said they were there not only to enjoy the music
but also to support the family farmer, the cause that inspired the
formation of Farm Aid five years ago. The organization, through its
first three shows in 1985-87, raised $12 million and has
distributed some $9 million to churches and service agencies,
hotlines and farm organizations.
   Carolyn Mugar, executive director of Farm Aid, said late in the
evening that the show had generated well over $1 million in
revenues and donations. She and Nelson have left open the
possibility of more concerts as the need for money arises.
   Mugar said Farm Aid IV was arranged because the organization has
run out of money. It was staged two weeks before the nation
observes the 20th anniversary of Earth Day in part as a way of
stressing that the farm and environmental causes are intertwined.
   ``When we restore the honor and sanctity of the family farmer,
in conjunction with Earth Day _ which is not just lip service and
not just one event _ we restore the sanctity and honor of Mother
Earth herself,'' Raitt said.
   Environmental activists, including Chris Desser, executive
director of Earth Day 1990, and John O'Connor, executive director
of the National Toxics Campaign, also spoke out against ``brute
chemical farming.''
   O'Connor said a third of the nation's farm crop is still lost to
insects and other pests, just as it was before World War II,
despite a tenfold increase in chemical use.
   The lineup at the Hoosier Dome also included Dwight Yoakum, K.T.
Oslin, Lou Reed, Guns N' Roses, Richard Marx, Jackson Browne, John
Denver and a Soviet rock band, Gorky Park.
   Huge black and white cutouts of farm workers with cows and farm
implements were the stage backdrop. Hanging on the left and right
sides of the stage were huge flags with the Farm Aid logo of a
tractor with an American flag.
   Farm Aid's first concert in September 1985 was in Champaign,
Ill. Subsequent concerts were held in 1986 in Austin, Texas, and in
1987 in Lincoln, Neb.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0008 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 0222EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i BC-Hungary     04-08 0385</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Hungary,0398</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hungarians Vote in Runoffs For Legislature</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TEDDIE WEYR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUDAPEST, Hungary (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hungarians voted Sunday in a runoff
election for the nation's first freely elected multiparty
legislature since 1947, and former Communists were widely expected
to serve only in the opposition.
   No party was thought likely to win an outright majority in the
polling, which began at 6 a.m. in most areas. Preliminary results
were not expected before midnight, six hours after the polls closed.
   The first round of balloting almost two weeks ago left 261 of
the 394 seats undecided in the National Assembly.
   But it gave two anti-Communist parties a firm lead and relegated
reform Communists, now running as the Socialist Party, to fourth
place with 10 percent of the vote.
   The two frontrunners, the conservative Hungarian Democratic
Forum and the liberal-leftist League of Free Democrats, have said
they will not accept the Socialists as coalition partners. Many
still associate the Socialist party with the hard-line Communists
who ruled Hungary for 43 years.
   The two leading parties have been reluctant to comment publicly
on the prospects of a coalition, but the Free Democrats have said
they would not rule out a joint government with the Democratic
Forum.
   A broad coalition is considered by many as the only government
stable enough to make the hard decisions necessary to correct a
stagnant economy while reining in a $20 billion national debt.
   But a coalition with a consensus on economic policy could be
difficult to forge, since the leading parties have different views
on the pacing and scope of economic reforms.
   Twenty-nine parties fielded candidates in the first round, but
only six reached the 4 percent minimum required for a seat in
Parliament.
   Candidates in the March 25 elections disputed 176 seats in
direct balloting in electoral districts.
   A clear winner emerged in only five of those districts. They
included Socialist Premier Miklos Nemeth, a reformer who enjoys
considerable popularity in the country.
   An additional 210 seats were contested on the basis of the
proportion of the vote parties received in the voting. Another
eight seats are reserved for national minorities.
   After the first round, 120 seats were assigned on the basis of
proportional voting. The remaining 90 seats will be assigned on a
proportional basis following Sunday's voting.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0009 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 0509EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i BC-Greece     04-08 0441</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Greece,0459</SECOND>
<HEAD>Greeks Vote For Third Time Within a year</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PHILIP DOPOULOS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ATHENS, Greece (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Greeks cast ballots in their third
parliamentary election in ten months Sunday, amid projections that
no party would win the outright majority needed to govern.
   In Athens, long queues formed outside many polling stations when
they opened at 7:01 a.m.. Polls were scheduled to close at sunset,
or 7:54 p.m..
   More than 8 million voters chose among candidates from 27
parties, two coalitions and 16 independent groupings that stretched
across the political spectrum. Voting is mandatory for Greeks
between 18 and 70 years of age.
   Only three parties were considered likely to attract significant
numbers of voters: the conservative New Democracy, the Panhellenic
Socialist Movement (PASOK) and the Communist-led Coalition of the
Left and Progress.
   But Sunday's election, like those last June and November, could
end without a clear winner and again leave Greece with a weak
coalition unable to cope with a foundering economy and a resurgence
of terrorism.
   The outcome may also have bearing on the country's four U.S.
military bases, which could close in November unless a new
agreement is reached with Washington.
   Election officials said first results would be in hand two hours
after the polls closed and definitive results, by early Tuesday.
   In the two previous elections, New Democracy defeated PASOK, led
by former premier Andreas Papandreou, but fell short of winning an
absolute majority in the 300-member single house Parliament.
   Opinion polls indicated New Democracy, led by 71-year-old
Constantine Mitsotakis, was also the frontrunner in Sunday's voting
but could again fail to achieve the necessary majority to govern
alone.
   Such a result could lead to difficult negotiations between the
three top parties over a ruling coalition _ and possibly another
round of elections.
   Papandreou, 71, has said he will attempt a ``progressive''
alliance with the Communist-led Coalition to govern for the next
four years.
   Last June, New Democracy teamed with the Coalition, its
ideological opponents, to govern from July to October. The
government was formed under the limited mandate of investigating
corruption charges against Papandreou and five of his ministers.
   The Parliament indicted Papandreou on charges of ordering
telephone tapping of political opponents and involvement in a $210
million Bank of Crete embezzlement scandal. The corruption charges
helped bring down Papandreou's government but the charismatic
leader continues to be a political force.
   Papandreou has denied the charges. No date has been set for his
trial.
   In the November elections, New Democracy won 46.19 percent of
the vote for 148 seats, PASOK, 40.67 percent for 128 places and the
Coalition, 10.97 percent for 21 seats.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0010 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 0658EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i BC-Slovenia-Elections     04-08 0381</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Slovenia-Elections,0395</SECOND>
<HEAD>Slovenia Holds First Free Elections Since 1945</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DUSAN STOJANOVIC</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LJUBLJANA, Yugoslavia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Slovenians voted Sunday in the
first free elections in Yugoslavia since World War II, ending 45
years of Communist monopoly on power in the republic.
   The 1.5 million registered voters will choose Slovenia's new
president, four members of the ruling collective presidency and 240
members of the new multiparty Parliament.
   The 4,130 polls in the republic opened at 7 a.m. and were to
close 12 hours later. Preliminary results are expected early Monday
and official results are due Tuesday.
   Electoral laws require a runoff on April 22 between the top two
vote-getters if no presidential candidate receives more than 50
percent.
   Four candidates are running for the republic's presidency. The
principal election issues were whether or not Slovenia should
remain within the troubled federation and solutions for the
inflation-racked economy.
   Milan Kucan, a candidate of the reformist Slovenian Communist
party, which recently renamed itself the Party for Democratic
Renewal, was ahead in the oppinion polls for the presidency.
   His toughest opponent for the top post was former dissident Joze
Pucnik, a candidate of DEMOS, a coalition of five center-right
parties.
   Pre-elections polls gave little chance to the other two
presidential candidates
   Pucnik, a professor of philosophy, spent seven years in
Slovenian prisons during the 1950s for his opposition to communism.
He was forced to emigrate to West Germany from where he returned
only last year after spending more than 20 years in exile.
   Slovenians are increasingly showing a desire to secede from
Yugoslavia because they are unhappy with the slow pace of
democratic and other reforms in the rest of the country.
   Slovenia's reform-minded Communists have moved quickly over the
past three years to create a pluralistic system in the republic.
   The reforms in Slovenia have been implemented despite harsh
criticism from Serbia, the largest Yugoslav republic, where
Communist leaders demand continued Communist party dominance.
   Croatia, the second largest republic, is also scheduled to stage
free parliamentary elections later in April.
   Despite allowing the formation of oposition parties, Communists
in other four republics, including Serbia, have not yet announced
free elections.
   Yugoslavia is a loose federation of six republics and two
autonomous provinces. It is ruled by an eight-man collective
presidency.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0011 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 1130EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>d i AM-BRF--China-Employment     04-08 0180</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--China-Employment,0186</SECOND>
<HEAD>China's Urban Workforce Declines</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   China's urban workforce declined by 1.5 million
in the first two months of 1990, with smaller collective firms
showing the largest loss of workers, an official daily said Sunday.
   The drop in working people continued a yearlong slump in the
labor market caused by government austerity measures that have
curbed inflation but brought economic growth to a standstill.
   Millions of factories around the country have closed down or are
operating at a reduced pace because of a lack of raw materials and
operating funds.
   The China Daily, quoting State Statistical Bureau figures, said
the workforce stood at 136 million at the end of February, down 1.5
million from the end of 1989.
   State-owned enterprises employed 100.4 million people, a drop of
713,000, while collectively owned businesses had 34.3 million
workers, 726,000 fewer than in December.
   Private businesses had 1.3 million workers on their payrolls, a
decline of 58,000.
   The figures do not include the 100 million unneeded laborers in
the countryside, where 800 million of China's 1.1 billion people
live.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0012 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 1130EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>d i AM-BRF--RebelAmbush     04-08 0146</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Rebel Ambush,0150</SECOND>
<HEAD>Troops Kill 15 in Raid on Rebel Base in Philippines</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MANILA, Philippines (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Troops killed 15 in a raid on a
Communist guerrilla base in the central Philippines, the military
said Sunday.
   The military said the dead included a 13-year-old girl, whom
they identified as the daughter of a rebel in the Marxist New
People's Army.
   The military said troops raided the base, in Negros Occidental,
310 miles southeast of Manila, on Friday.
   Also Sunday, the military said troops captured a suspected
Communist intelligence officer during a raid in Bataan peninsula.
   Military spokesman Col. Rene Esdado said Robert Omega was
arrested in a house in Mariveles, 64 miles southwest of the capital.
   Omega is believed to be a rebel intelligence officer operating
in Manila and the neighboring Rizal province, Esdado said. Soldiers
seized a pistol, several bullets and a hand grenade.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0013 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 1131EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-SpaceShuttle-Coverage     04-08 0165</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Space Shuttle-Coverage,0170</SECOND>
<HEAD>Four Networks Plan Shuttle Coverage</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Hubble Trouble, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   ABC, CBS, NBC and CNN plan to televise the
scheduled launch of the shuttle Discovery live Tuesday morning.
   The spacecraft is scheduled to lift off at 8:47 a.m. EDT from
the Kennedy Space Center at Cape Canaveral, Fla.
   During the five-day trip into space, five astronauts will put
into orbit the Hubble Space Telescope, which will give scientists a
look at stars and galaxies light years away.
   CNN plans to begin coverage from the space center at 5:30 a.m.
EDT Tuesday, according to a statement issued by CNN.
   ABC's coverage will begin during ``Good Morning America,'' and
then go to a special report, according to Arnot Walker, an ABC
spokesman.
   CBS will carry the liftoff live as part of its ``CBS This
Morning'' news show, said Tina Wynn, a spokeswoman for CBS.
   NBC will air the launch on the ``Today'' morning news show, said
NBC spokeswoman Katherine McQuay.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0014 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 1136EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Lithuania-Future Bjt   04-08 1023</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lithuania-Future, Bjt,1057</SECOND>
<HEAD>Lithuanians See Better Future in Being Small and Free</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP Extra</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   The material for this report was gathered before
the Soviet government expelled Ann Imse and other Western
correspondents from Lithuania on April 1.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By ANN IMSE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>VILNIUS, U.S.S.R. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Many Lithuanians say their declaration
of independence was like leaping for a lifeboat to escape a sinking
ship.
   ``Alone, we know it will be better in five years; with them, we
don't,'' banker Gintautas Preidis said of the Lithuanian
parliament's decision March 11 to cut loose from the Soviet Union
and its economic and ethnic problems.
   Lithuanians expect initial difficulties in switching from
central planning and subsidies to a market economy in which prices
are set by competition. The republic may also lose access to cheap
Soviet resources.
   ``I visited a collective farm where they had 30 people as
bookkeepers!'' said Joseph Kazickas, a Lithuanian who emigrated to
the United States at the end of World War II and became a
businessman.
   He is back in Lithuania, arranging for experts to help reform
the economy and working with Premier Kazimieras Prunskiene to set
up a system that would entice Western investment.
   The Kremlin, which has used troops to take over Lithuania's
prosecutor's office and has waged a war of nerves to keep the
republic in its fold, is standing in the way of some reform and
could stifle other moves to revamp the republic's economy.
   Mrs. Prunskiene has said Soviet Premier Nikolai I. Ryzhkov and
his Cabinet refused to transfer most authority from Moscow to
Vilnius.
   For example, Prunskiene suggested that the majority of the
200-plus factories now run by ministries in Moscow be turned over
to Lithuanian control. Ryzhkov and his ministers are willing to
hand over only a few dozen.
   Lithuanian officials aim for their nation of 3.8 million people,
about the size and population of Ireland, to develop a thriving
economy based on selling meat, milk and consumer goods to the
Soviet Union and shipping its imports and exports.
   But Moscow built many of Lithuania's factories according to no
economic logic, far from raw materials and customers. They
manufacture goods so outmoded that only desperate Soviet consumers
would buy them.
   There has been no change in economic ties since the Baltic
republic voted to secede. Relations with the Soviet Union are
critical for Lithuania, which gets all its oil and gas from Siberia
at low rates. Moscow needs Lithuania, whose factories produce parts
for Soviet plants.
   A Lithuanian parliamentary commission on independence said the
republic has plenty of electric power, including a nuclear plant at
Ignalina that can provide virtually all its needs.
   But supplies of oil, gas, important raw materials, repair parts,
fertilizer and communications could be cut off, the commission said.
   ``The hands are on the faucets, but they haven't been turned,''
said Lawrence Summers, a Harvard University economics professor and
one of the experts Kazickas has helped to bring over as an adviser
on economic reform.
   Lithuania and its sister Baltic states, Latvia and Estonia, have
drawn up complete economic reform plans. Their people generally
appear willing to accept higher prices and unemployment as part of
the parcel.
   All three Baltic republics were part of the Russian empire from
the late 18th century until after World War I. They were
independent between the wars but forcibly annexed by the Soviet
Union in 1940 after Moscow took control of the republics under
terms of the secret Hitler-Stalin pact.
   Independence in Lithuania, Latvia and Estonia coincided with
some of the Soviet Union's most ruinous years, in the 1920s and
1930s.
   The Baltic republics' roads, buildings, and communications
generally are in far better repair than those of the Soviet Union,
evidence of greater efficiency and their period of independence.
There are three freeways in Lithuania; in other Soviet republics
many villages have no road at all.
   But virtually all communications go through Soviet territory, so
the Lithuanians have begun negotiations with Poland for a new
direct connection to the West.
   Among proposed economic reforms, Summers has recommended
allowing prices to rise on non-essential items to encourage
manufacture of goods in extremely short supply and soak up excess
Soviet rubles.
   He said Lithuania should introduce its own currency in 1991,
freely convertible at a low exchange rate.
   Summers said low currency exchange rates could make labor costs
in the new Lithuania attractive to nearby, high-wage Scandanavia,
but for now Lithuania remains inefficient.
   Many Soviets scoff at the aspirations for independence in the
Baltics, contending the tiny republics could not survive on their
own. Balts invite skeptics to look at Finland.
   Fifty years ago, Finland and the Baltics had similar economies
and incomes. Finland's climate is harsher and it has few natural
resources, yet it fought a war to remain independent of the Soviets
and has developed a thriving economy.
   Today, Finland's per capita income is more than quadruple that
of the Soviet Union.
   Lithuanian economist Valdas Terleckas said his country had a 10
percent annual growth rate in its 22 years as an independent,
capitalist nation. That is higher than most countries in the world
today.
   In response to such statistics, the Soviet press has cited
diplomatic dispatches from the Baltic republics during independence
that spoke of economic decay and widespread unemployment.
   The republic's new government has moved to stop strangling
business by cutting the number of ministries from an
already-reduced 40 to 18. The Soviet bureaucracy, blamed for
stalling Gorbachev's reforms, still has 48 ministries and 28
commissions.
   Independence will force the Vilnius Electrical Measuring Device
Factory to redesign its product line, primarily household electric
meters, so it can produce goods efficiently and compete outside the
Soviet Union, Cuba, and Africa, said plant director Vincas Babilius.
   He is thrilled with the prospect, because ``I want to be a free
man. I want to deal with whomever I want, to set my own prices, and
decide what to do with my own profits.''
   Violinist Rimas Cekuolis expressed what most Lithuanians seemed
to feel: ``It's not important whether our life is better or worse.
Freedom is what is important.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0015 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 1137EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>d i AM-BRF--RamadanAmnesty     04-08 0116</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Ramadan Amnesty,0118</SECOND>
<HEAD>Qatar Frees 57 Prisoners to Mark Ramadan</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DOHA, Qatar (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The emir of Qatar, Sheik Khalifa bin Hamad
al-Thani, on Sunday ordered that 57 prisoners be freed to mark the
holy month of Ramadan, the official Qatar News Agency reported.
   It is customary for leaders of Islamic countries to release
prisoners in honor of Moslem holidays.
   The world's 1 billion Moslems fast from dawn to dusk during
Ramadan. The three-day Eid al-Fitr feast that marks the end of the
holiday is expected to fall this year around April 26, depending
when the new moon is sighted.
   Earlier this month, 364 prisoners were freed in the United Arab
Emirates to mark Ramadan.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0016 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 1136EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Budget     04-08 0686</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Budget,700</SECOND>
<HEAD>Budget Committees Ignoring Moynihan, Rostenkowski Plans</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ALAN FRAM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   House and Senate budget committees are moving
toward adoption of fiscal 1991 deficit-reduction plans that ignore
eye-catching proposals by two of Congress's most influential
members.
   The Democratic chairmen of the two panels, which are well behind
schedule, hope to produce separate $1.2-trillion spending
blueprints for next year by late this month. But neither will
reflect Sen. Daniel Patrick Moynihan's plan to cut the Social
Security payroll tax or Rep. Dan Rostenkowski's call for a
combination of widespread spending cuts and tax hikes.
   Instead, House Budget Committee Chairman Leon Panetta, D-Calif.,
and his Senate counterpart, James Sasser, D-Tenn., are prodding
their Democrat-dominated committees to compose similar packages
that rely on more traditional formulas.
   Plans considered likely to emerge from each budget panel would
shrink the deficit by $37 billion, relying on roughly equal amounts
of defense cuts and new taxes and lesser savings from cuts in
Medicare, payments to farmers and other domestic programs.
   ``I'll be able to get a budget resolution out of committee,''
Panetta said last week after two weeks of closed-door meetings with
panel members. ``It will take a lot of work on the (House) floor,
but we will pass it there, too.''
   The decisions to snub Moynihan, D-N.Y., and Rostenkowski,
D-Ill., reflect different judgments.
   Congressional leaders believe Rostenkowski's proposal to save
$55 billion next year by freezing Social Security and other
domestic programs and by raising income taxes and other levies is
medicine that is simply too harsh for most lawmakers.
   ``There are no votes there,'' Panetta said of the plan advanced
by the chairman of the tax-writing Ways and Means Committee.
``Rostenkowski would have much greater impact if there were votes
there to support it.''
   Moynihan's proposal is aimed at driving down the Social Security
surplus, which the senator _ considered Congress's expert on the
retirement system _ complains makes the overall budget deficit look
smaller.
   But his proposal to slash the payroll tax would shrink federal
revenues by $55 billion, a cut that members of Moynihan's own party
complain would make next year's anticipated $101 billion federal
shortfall even larger. The Gramm-Rudman Act sets a deficit target
of $64 billion for fiscal 1991, which begins Oct. 1.
   ``We're going to have enough difficulty meeting the budget
targets without coming up at this juncture with a revenue loser,''
Sasser said.
   For their parts, Moynihan and Rostenkowski insist that their
proposals are still alive. Moynihan said last week that he expects
a Senate vote on his plan in May and that he expects to win.
Rostenkowski said he believes his proposal stands as good a chance
as anything Panetta can piece together.
   Panetta's and Sasser's committees will begin writing their
budget plans in earnest when Congress returns from its Easter
recess next week.
   So far, Panetta is considering a plan that would hold defense
spending to about $295 billion _ $11.5 billion below the amount
needed to keep up with inflation, and $8 billion less than
President Bush wants. He would raise $14 billion in new, minor
taxes _ the same amount as Bush. He also would cut Medicare and
other federal benefit programs by $3.5 billion, while boosting
housing, childrens' and other social programs by about $6 billion.
   Sasser wants his committee to compress military spending to
about $292 billion. He also would collect $14 billion in new taxes,
while seeking savings in some domestic programs.
   Republicans from both panels say they will oppose the Democratic
packages. Senate GOP budget-writers say they may offer their own
proposals, while House Republicans say they will support the budget
Bush proposed in January.
   ``He's our big brother and he's going to do the fist-fighting
for us,'' Rep. Bill Frenzel of Minnesota, ranking Republican on the
House budget panel, said of Bush.
   By law, Congress is supposed to finish the budget by April 15, a
deadline that is routinely ignored. The compromise House-Senate
plan that Congress finally adopts sets guidelines that must be
followed by separate tax and spending bills, which will be written
later in the year.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0017 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 1137EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Britain-Violence Bjt   04-08 0858</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Britain-Violence, Bjt,0885</SECOND>
<HEAD>A Week After Rioting, Britain Seeks Explanation for Violence</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JESSICA BALDWIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   As one editorial summed it up: The Conservatives
blamed the Labor Party, which blamed the militant left, which
blamed the anarchists, who accepted the charge with pride.
   The comment, in the left-wing weekly New Statesman and Society,
was one of many attempting to explain rioting that tore through the
heart of London a week ago. The violence came the day before local
property taxes were replaced with a per-capita ``community charge.''
   ``A `community charge' means running full pelt down a street
with a brick in your hand and a `pig' in your sights,'' said the
newspaper Class War, published by an anarchist group with the same
name.
   Was it organized or spontaneous? Should police share the blame?
Did it expose an underclass that has grown up feeling left out of
the ``property-owning democracy'' Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher
dreams of creating?
   The occasion was a March 31 march by 40,000 people protesting
the new tax. Police say about 3,000 attacked officers, smashed shop
windows, looted and started fires. They said 374 officers and 86
civilians were injured, and 339 arrests were made.
   Trouble apparently started when mounted police moved a small
group of unruly demonstrators away from Downing Street, where Mrs.
Thatcher lives, into Trafalgar Square. Peaceful protesters in the
square thought police were attacking the crowd, witnesses said.
   Peter Taaffe, general secretary of Militant Tendency, a radical
left-wing movement, said: ``The police action infuriated the crowd,
including some Militant supporters who oppose violence. It ignited
an explosion.
   ``Many of these young people are very angry. They are
unemployed, harassed and have an accumulated hatred of the
police,'' he said.
   ``All that fury came to the fore and they began attacking any
symbol of society. That included the police, and the obscene
display of wealth in the West End which is cheek by jowl with
desolate poverty.''
   Dr. Jock Young, a sociologist at Middlesex Polytechnic, said
animosity must have been widespread for the anarchist groups to
have had an effect.
   ``The young people are living in a very affluent society,'' he
said. ``It is the relative deprivation which creates the
disaffected and starts to create cultures of violence, particularly
among young men.
   ``Football is one expression of this. It provides a vehicle for
young machismo blokes to get together in large numbers and let off
a lot of steam.'' Phil Kelly, editor of the left-wing weekly
Tribune, said anarchism attracts the alienated.
   ``Their whole contact with authority is unpleasant,'' Kelly
said. ``They are living in illegal squats or derelict buildings.
The only contact they have with the police is when they get stopped
because of the way they look.''
   Rioters faced the wrath of the entire political establishment.
The Labor Party condemned them as vociferously as Mrs. Thatcher's
Conservatives.
   Labor was to blame, the Tories said, because a minority of its
members of Parliament advocates breaking the law by refusing to pay
the so-called poll tax.
   Many of those brought before magistrates were age 17 to 30 and
gave their addresses as squatter apartments or buildings. Others
were what are still known in Britain as hippies, living nomadic
lives in the backs of vans.
   Violence breaks out in all sorts of contexts in Britain.
Anarchists make periodic charges through the City, London's
financial district, smashing bank windows and other symbols of
capitalism.
   Droves of hippies converge on Stonehenge in June to celebrate
the summer solstice, and battle police who try to keep them from
the protected national monument.
   Animal rights campaigners disrupt foxhunts.
   England's soccer hooligans, who caused 39 deaths in a rampage at
a Brussels stadium in 1985, are feared continent-wide.
   ``Every generation has had its disruptive element, and our
disruptive element is probably the anarchists,'' said sociologist
Norman Jones. ``The glorious days when there was no violence is a
misconceived idea.''
   Dr. D.B. O'Leary at the London School of Economics said it is
wrong to assume Britain was on the verge of rampant anarchism.
   ``You have to look at the interaction of a very hot day,
incompetent policing and the fact that many people wanted a scrap
if the occasion was offered to them _ and it was,'' he said.
   Young, of Middlesex Polytechnic, considers Britain still a
relatively non-violent country, not much different from other parts
of Europe and with one-tenth the U.S. murder rate.
   But some language heard and read since the riot has been violent.
   New Statesman and Society carried an article by a 25-year-old
Londoner identified only as Tony, who said he threw rocks at police
during the riot.
   Tony wrote: ``The police won't come to terms with the fact that
they're distrusted and hated. It wasn't even about the poll tax;
that was just the occasion for it. It was a young people's riot, a
spontaneous outburst by people from all over the country. That's
what made it so great. I did what I did because I could.''
   ``The police were attacked and quite rightly so,'' said Andy
Murphy, a 28-year-old anarchist who works for the London borough of
Hackney.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0018 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 1141EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-ChinaBeach     04-08 0438</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-China Beach,0451</SECOND>
<HEAD>Americans Break Ground for `Peace Village' on Site of Vietnam War
Landing</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto BK1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DENIS D. GRAY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BANGKOK, Thailand (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Ten Americans returned to a Vietnamese
beach where U.S. forces landed 25 years ago, and laid the
foundation for a ``Peace Village'' to assist victims of the Vietnam
War, a participant said Sunday.
   Gordon Smith, a Vietnam War veteran, said he and nine other
Americans laid the cornerstones for the ``village'' on China Beach.
Plans call for a rehabilitation center, orphanage, a medical center
and trade school.
   The ground-breaking ceremony, also attended by Vietnamese Red
Cross officials, took place March 26.
   On March 8, 1965, more than 3,500 Marines stormed onto the beach
near the central Vietnam city of Danang in a major escalation of
the war.
   The project is led by Le Ly Hayslip, who initially collaborated
with the Communist Viet Cong as a teen-ager. After a series of
harrowing wartime experiences, she married an American and came to
the United States.
   Her autobiography, ``When Heaven and Earth Changed Places,'' was
published in the United States last year.
   Ms. Hayslip's East Meets West Foundation has in recent years
provided medical assistance to Vietnam through private funding,
including contributions from Oliver Stone, the Vietnam veteran who
has directed two major films on Vietnam, ``Platoon'' and ``Born on
the Fourth of July.''
   Ms. Hayslip, who lives in Escondido, Calif., was born in a small
village near Danang.
   Smith, of Monterey, Calif., said additional fund raising in the
United States would be necessary before construction of the village
could begin.
   The center would help the handicapped who fought on both sides
in the war, victims of land mines that continue to take their toll
on civilians, and people suffering from ailments unrelated to the
war, he said.
   The China Beach project is one of a growing number of private
American efforts to heal the wounds of the Vietnam War. These have
frequently been initiated by war veterans.
   The United States does not recognize the Hanoi government and
forbids commerce with Vietnam. American aid organizations must
obtain permits from Washington and operate under certain financial
restrictions in Vietnam.
   Smith was involved in the building of a medical clinic by war
veterans in the southern seaside town of Vung Tau. The clinic
opened March 30, 1989, and receives medical supplies obtained by
veterans in the United States.
   Smith, who is involved in Hayslip's group and a number of
veterans organizations, said he hoped to start a program to send
American nurses who served in the war to the clinic and Vung Tau
hospital.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0019 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 1151EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Savings     04-08 0551</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Savings,520</SECOND>
<HEAD>Americans Not Alone in Saving Less</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CARL HARTMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Americans often are blamed for having lost the
old Yankee love of thrift, but the International Monetary Fund has
found that people in some other developed countries are saving even
less.
   It predicted the trend will continue as the world's population
ages. Older people have less to save for.
   ``The negative trend in national saving rates experienced by all
the major industrial countries since the early to mid-1970s has
raised serious concerns about the prospects for strong and
sustainable growth in the world economy,'' said the latest issue of
the semiweekly ``IMF Survey.''
   The scolding is based on a report by a team under Bijan B.
Aghelvi, senior advisor in the fund's research department at its
headquarters in Washington.
   When people put money into their bank accounts, the banks lend
it out to industry for building the factories that will produce
more goods and jobs in the future. If savings are too small,
industry has to borrow from other countries.
   Governments also save -- or, more often, ``dis-save'' by going
further into debt. When a government spends more than it collects
in taxes, it has to borrow from the savings of its citizens or from
other countries. Its taxpayers then have to pay interest on the
debt.
   The United States is a prime example on both counts. Americans
of the future will have to pay interest to other countries on the
billions being borrowed by Americans today.
   According to the most recent figures from the Organization for
Economic Cooperation and Development (OECD) in Paris, the average
American household in 1988 saved only $4.40 out of every $100 of
after-tax income.
   But Americans were far from being the biggest spendthrifts. The
average Swedish household did not save at all. It drew on past
savings or went into debt at the rate of $3.60 dollars for every
$100 dollars earned.
   The average Norwegian family had ``dis-savings'' of $1.20 per
$100 of income and families in Finland spent an average $101.40 for
every $100 earned.
   Of the major industrial countries, the Japanese were the top
savers: $15.20 dollars out of $100 of income. But even the thrifty
Japanese have loosened up _ in 1976, they saved $23.20 of every
$100 earned.
   The average West German family in 1988 saved $12.60 of every
$100 earned, down from $15.10 in 1975. Dutch families in 1988 saved
only $2 of every $100 of income.
   Another IMF-sponsored study warns that a country's capital will
be consumed unless money is set aside to replace it, and more must
be put aside as the population grows.
   ``High rates of saving in the Federal Republic of Germany and
Japan in particular... have contributed to rapid rises in the
standard of living,'' wrote Roger S. Smith, who teaches economics
at the University of Alberta, in Canada.
   ``(South) Korea, Singapore and Taiwan... are clear current
examples that high saving rates go hand in hand with rapid economic
growth.''
   Smith wrote that government deficits have reduced savings in a
number of countries.
   ``Belgium, Canada, Italy and the United States may be the most
obvious examples, but Australia, the Netherlands, Sweden and the
United Kingdom also have had significant public sector deficits
during the 1980s,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0020 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 1151EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-India-Supercomputer Bjt   04-08 0609</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-India-Supercomputer, Bjt,600</SECOND>
<HEAD>Administration Eyes Sale of Supercomputer to India, Sources Say</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RUTH SINAI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   After months of delay, the United States has
decided in principle to sell a supercomputer to India, sources say,
despite warnings that it could be used to make nuclear weapons or
ballistic missiles.
   But granting an export license for the sophisticated Cray
computer depends on India's willingness to adopt measures
restricting its use to peaceful research and preventing the
transfer of its data to unauthorized parties, said one source.
   The sources, discussing the prospective deal on condition of
anonymity, said Indian was balking at the conditions, noting that a
supercomputer bought in 1987 was being used only to forecast
monsoons.
   Indian officials also are pointing out that the country signed a
1984 agreement promising not to transfer high-tech equipment to
other nations, the sources added.
   The decision to approve the sale in principle reflects the U.S.
government's ambivalence about exporting state-of-the-art computers
to countries with nuclear capabilities.
   Decisions about the sale of similar computers to Israel and
Brazil have been stalled for as long as two years, with the
Department of Energy and the Arms Control and Disarmament Agency
lobbying against the deals, said one source.
   The Cray computer is destined for the Institute of Science of
Bangalore, India, which conducts biotechnological and other
research, said Indian officials. Gary Milhollin, director of the
Wisconsin Project on Nuclear Arms Control, said the institute also
studies stress on rocket bodies.
   Milhollin, whose organization tracks the spread of nuclear
weapons to developing countries, said India could apply the
supercomputer data to missile development.
   The Commerce Department, which takes the lead in granting or
denying export licenses, refused to comment. But last week the
department announced it had fined a West German company $800,000
for exporting nuclear material to India and several other countries.
   In general, the Bush administration is easing controls over the
export of supercomputers, partly because of growing pressure from
manufacturers stung by government budget cuts and partly because of
a relaxation in technology exports to formerly communist
governments.
   The Commerce Department is pruning and streamlining the lists of
high-tech items banned for export to Eastern Europe. And NATO has
been pressing the United States to speed up the process.
   In addition, the Commerce Department is redefining which
supercomputers must receive special export licenses requiring a
safeguard plan. Under the proposed definition, countries buying
supercomputers with a capability of up to 150 megaflops _ a measure
of computing speed _ would not be required to adopt a safeguards
plan. The previous limit was 100 megaflops.
   Proponents of the sales argue that countries determined to
produce nuclear weapons and ballistic missiles can do so without
supercomputers, especially since the new generation of desktop
computers are so powerful they can compute as fast. They note that
supercomputers are put to many beneficial uses, including weather
predictions, seismic analysis and medical and scientific research.
   Opponents argue that the fast-computing machines make it much
easier to design weapons, especially because of their ability to
simulate and analyze the effects of nuclear explosions and missile
flights.
   They also note that Brazil, India and Israel have not signed the
International Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty although all have
nuclear capabilities or are near having them. That means their
nuclear facilities are not inspected by outsiders.
   Pressure from the industry is fierce, especially in the face of
sharp competition from Japan _ the only other country that makes
such machines. U.S. exports of supercomputers were valued at $400
million in 1989 and are projected to double this year. Japan's 1990
exports are expected to reach $2 billion.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0021 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 1208EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Bush-White     04-08 0209</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bush-White,220</SECOND>
<HEAD>With AM-Obit-White Bjt</HEAD>
<HEAD>Bush Mourns Boy's Death</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush mourned the death AIDS sufferer
Ryan White Sunday, saying Americans must continue fighting against
the deadly immune system disease.
   ``Barbara and I are deeply saddened with the death of Ryan
White,'' Bush said in a statement released a few hours after the
18-year-old Indiana youth died in a hospital in Indianapolis.
   ``All Americans are impressed by his courage, strength and his
ability to continue fighting,'' the president said. ``Ryan's death
reaffirms that we as a people must pledge to continue the fight,
his fight against this dreaded disease.''
   ``We send our condolences to his family and will keep them in
our hearts and prayers,'' the statement said.
   Last week, Bush planted a tree in Indianapolis in honor of White.
   White was diagnosed as having AIDS in December 1984 when he was
13. He contracted acquired immune deficiency syndrome through a
blood-clotting agent used to treat his hemophilia.
   White gained national attention when he was barred from Western
Middle School near Kokomo, Ind., after school officials and parents
there rejected health authorities' reassurances that AIDS could not
be spread through casual contact with those infected.
   Later, he moved to Cicero, Ind., where he attended school.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0022 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 1225EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Hungary-Glance     04-08 0405</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Hungary-Glance,0434</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hungary's Election Runoff at a Glance</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Hungary, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BUDAPEST, Hungary (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here is a look at Sunday's second round
of national elections in Hungary.
   
   POLLING:
   Polls opened at 6 a.m. and closed at 6 p.m. More than 7.5
million people were eligible to vote, all those 18 years or older
or considered adults by marriage.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   AT STAKE:
   _261 seats in the parliament, or National Assembly, to be filled
for a four-year term, with eight other seats to be allocated to
representatives of Hungary's eight national minorities.
   _Mandate to run the government or form a coalition.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   RESULTS OF FIRST ROUND:
   On March 25, candidates from 29 political parties competed for
394 seats in the National Assembly.
   In the voting 176 seats were to be chosen by direct elections,
210 according to the proportion of the vote received by each party,
and eight seats were reserved for national minorities.
   In the first round of voting, only five candidates won a mandate
in the direct elections. Victory requires a majority in the vote.
   Of the 210 seats assigned by proportional vote, 120 were decided
on March 25.
   A further 90 seats will be divided up among the parties after
the runoff according to a complex mathematical formula on the basis
of national aggregate votes won. Only parties that received at
least 4 percent of the vote in the first round are eligible.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   MAIN PARTIES RUNNING:
   Only six of 29 parties that competed in the first round cleared
the 4 percent hurdle qualifying them for Sunday's runoff. They are:
   _Hungarian Democratic Forum, which won 24.73 percent of the
March 25 vote, took 40 of the party slate seats and fielded 159
candidates in Sunday's runoff.
   _League of Free Democrats 21.39 percent; 34 seats; 150
candidates.
   _Independent Smallholders' Party 11.73 percent; 16 seats; 76
candidates.
   _Hungarian Socialist Party 10.89 percent; 14 seats; 54
candidates.
   _League of Young Democrats 8.95 percent; 8 seats; 8 candidates.
   _Christian Democratic People's Party 6.46 percent; 8 seats; 20
candidates.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   ISSUES:
   The No. 1 issue was which party or what sort of coalition will
govern the country after 43 years of Communist rule. The first
priority of any new government will be to energize Hungary's
sagging economy.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   ELECTION SUPERVISION:
   The Vienna-based International Helsinki Human Rights
Association, the Strassbourg-based Council of Europe, and members
of an international delegation sponsored by the U.S. Democratic and
Republican parties.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0023 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 1247EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>d i AM-BRF--Sudan-Fire     04-08 0095</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Sudan-Fire,0097</SECOND>
<HEAD>Fire Devastates a Blue Nile Village</HEAD>
<DATELINE>KHARTOUM, Sudan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A fire in a village in the central Blue
Nile region killed four people and left more than 500 families
homeless, the state-run Sudan News Agency said Sunday.
   A woman and three children were killed when the fire raged
through Bott, a village of 2,500 people, the report said.
   The blaze destroyed the families' homes, burned the local market
and killed scores of domestic animals, the news agency said. It did
not say when the fire broke out or how it started.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0024 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 1247EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>d i AM-BRF--Pakistan-Crash     04-08 0139</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Pakistan-Crash,0145</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bus-Truck Crash Kills 13, Injures 6 in Pakistan</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ISLAMABAD, Pakistan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A minibus collided with a truck on
the ancient Grand Trunk Road outside Islamabad on Sunday, killing
13 people and injuring six, police said.
   All the casualties were traveling in the bus; the driver of the
truck fled the scene, according to Pakistan's official news agency.
   The Grand Trunk Road links Pakistan's border city of Peshawar to
India's teeming western city of Calcutta. It was made famous in the
West by author Rudyard Kipling, whose protagonist in the book
``Kim'' wandered through India on the Grand Trunk.
   Today, many cars travel the road at break-neck speeds, swerving
around horse-drawn carts, bicycles and motorized rickshaws.
   Overcrowded buses, with passengers hanging off the roof and out
the windows, are often the worst of the speeding offenders.

</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0025 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 1240EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-DrugConference     04-08 0460</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Drug Conference,0474</SECOND>
<HEAD>More Than 100 Countries At Drug Conference</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By EDITH M. LEDERER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   More than 100 countries begin an anti-drug
conference Monday that focuses on education and other measures
aimed at cutting demand especially for cocaine, which has begun to
hit Europe hard, officials say.
   ``We know in the end as long as demand is there, there will
always be somebody to get the supply through,'' said Home Office
Minister David Mellor, one of Britain's top law enforcement
officials.
   Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher, President Virgilio Barco
Vargas of Colombia and U.N. Secretary General Javier Perez de
Cuellar will address the opening of the World Ministerial Drugs
Summit at the Queen Elizabeth II Conference Center opposite
Westminster Abbey.
   Mellor called Barco as ``a courageous representative of a drug
nation struggling against drug traffickers,'' who have killed more
than 200 people in their 7-month-old war with the Colombian
government.
   Britain has invited all members of the United Nations and all
non-member observer states to the three-day conference. Lynda
Chalker, minister of overseas development, said her government is
paying the expenses of delegations from some developing countries.
   The conference, organized by the British government in
association with the United Nations, follows up the International
Conference on Drug Abuse and Illicit Trafficking held in Vienna in
June 1987.
   That conference agreed for the first time on an overall approach
focusing on prevention, treatment, rehabilitation and reducing
supplies.
   This week's summit will consider education programs to prevent
drug use, identification of drug misusers and early intervention to
prevent misuse, and emerging issues in the development of demand
reduction policies including AIDS.
   Organizers decided to single out cocaine, Mellor said, because
``cocaine has suddenly come from nowhere to be the principle drug
of misuse, not only here but elsewhere in the world.''
   ``The American experience shows that we underestimate cocaine at
our peril, especially when mixed with smoking as crack,'' he said.
   While cocaine has been confined mainly to the Western
hemisphere, organizers said they decided to include it in the
conference because there was strong evidence that the cocaine
cartels are looking for new markets in Europe and other regions.
   In the past three years the amount of cocaine seized in the 12
European Economic Community states has tripled to more than five
tons last year.
   In 1988, British authorities for the first time seized more
cocaine than heroin.
   The conference will examine the entire cycle from cultivation of
the coca bush to the disposal of the proceeds of street sales of
cocaine and crack.
   Mellor said Britain's concern was that there should be ``a
practical outcome'' of the conference _ added impetus for
drug-fighting institutions, adoption of a research program and
agreement on enhanced international cooperation.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0026 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 1241EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-HubbleTrouble Bjt   04-08 0877</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Hubble Trouble, Bjt,0898</SECOND>
<HEAD>Astronomers Jittery About Woes That Might Trouble the Hubble</HEAD>
<NOTE>With LaserPhoto</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By LEE SIEGEL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   As the Hubble Space Telescope awaits a ride
into space, scientists remain jittery about the many things that
could go wrong with NASA's costliest satellite _ from a fogged
mirror to space junk.
   ``It's hitting us in our guts,'' said Ed Weiler, Hubble program
scientist at the agency's Washington headquarters. ``We're all
having dreams about this thing. We're reliving meetings on what
could go wrong, and we're wondering, `Did we make a mistake
somewhere?'''
   Getting the $1.5 billion telescope ready to be placed in orbit
by the shuttle Discovery this week _ after seven years of delay _
has ``been one big pain in the rear, but it's going to be worth
every minute every one of us spent on it,'' he said.
   Because the unmanned telescope will peer farther into space than
any other observatory, ``we know we are going to discover things
that are totally unexpected, that our human imaginations can't even
envision.''
   Potential woes facing Hubble include equipment failures,
contamination of its sensitive mirror and light detectors,
dependence for repairs on an overburdened shuttle fleet, and
sunspot activity that might drag the telescope from its proper
orbit.
   ``We have plenty of concerns and plenty of areas we know need
improvement, but we have no showstoppers,'' said David R. Skillman,
a chief telescope engineer at Goddard Space Flight Center in
Maryland. ``I fully expect this thing will be operating for 20 or
30 years'' _ well beyond the planned 15-year mission.
   The National Aeronautics and Space Administration plans to put
Hubble in orbit 380 miles above the Earth, higher than any shuttle
has flown. Discovery is scheduled for launch Tuesday.
   But if one of Discovery's three engines doesn't produce full
power or fails completely after launch _ as happened to Challenger
in July 1985 _ the shuttle wouldn't reach an adequate altitude. The
astronauts would either bring the telescope back or put it in a
lower orbit until a shuttle could tow it higher.
   As long as Hubble is deployed at least 326 miles above Earth, it
can make some useful observations for a year before it needs a
boost, flight director William Reeves said.
   Shuttle maintenance flights every three years will tow the
telescope back up to 380 miles if its orbit decays because of
sunspots. The current solar cycle is the second most intense on
record, spewing solar wind that heats and inflates Earth's
atmosphere, increasing friction that can make satellites fall from
orbit more quickly.
   If the shuttle fleet were grounded for years by another tragedy
like the Challenger explosion, the telescope could burn up in the
atmosphere.
   Astronaut-astronomer Steve Hawley said vibration during
Discovery's ascent is unlikely to damage the telescope's mirror,
but ``if it sat on the pad for a long time, you might worry about
possible contamination.''
   That's because the shuttle's cargo bay is not as clean as either
the vacuum of space or the ``clean room'' where the telescope was
readied for flight, said Mark Johnston of the Baltimore-based Space
Telescope Science Institute, which schedules use of telescope time.
Installation of the Hubble into the shuttle's cargo bay was delayed
briefly last month after insects invaded the clean room.
   NASA officials believe they can deal with all conceivable
troubles except the possibility the Hubble might be obliterated by
a speeding meteoroid or a hunk of junk from some previous space
flight.
   A study of Air Force space junk statistics concluded that there
is a 1 percent chance that that a fragment large enough to destroy
the telescope _ 4 inches wide _ would hit it during its 15-year
mission, Johnston said.
   The telescope is aimed with internal gyroscopes, but lacks
thrusters to maneuver it away from an impending collision.
   Weiler disputed the 1 percent estimate as exaggerated, so ``I'm
not going to lose sleep over it.''
   Because the launch has been delayed so long, much of the
telescope's equipment is aging and some might fail, including
electrical connections and moving parts such as camera shutters and
filter wheels, Johnston said.
   Hubble is designed ``so that as parts fail, other parts can be
turned on to replace them,'' Skillman said.
   If a malfunction seriously threatens the telescope, NASA is
committed to launching a shuttle within a year instead of waiting
for a regular maintenance mission.
   But ``if I were a Hubble Space Telescope project guy, I would
always carry with me a lingering concern that when I need the
support, is it going to be available to me?'' Hawley said.
   When shuttles approach on servicing missions, thrust exhaust
might fog Hubble's mirror, but Skillman said that can be prevented
with careful maneuvering.
   While Hubble's orbit makes it accessible for repairs, it also
leaves the telescope able to make observations only 35 percent of
each day, Johnston said.
   Earth will block desired targets 40 percent of the time. The
telescope needs 10 percent of its time to locate and lock onto
``guide stars'' so it remains steady. It is unusable 15 percent of
the time when it passes east of Brazil, where orbiting radiation
belts dip low enough to interfere with the telescope's electronics.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0027 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 1247EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Jordan-ArtTheft     04-08 0434</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Jordan-Art Theft,0445</SECOND>
<HEAD>Police Recover Stolen Mosaic, Arrest Suspects</HEAD>
<DATELINE>AMMAN, Jordan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Police recovered a 1,200-year-old mosaic in
a raid near the capital and arrested three mosaic dealers accused
of ripping the artwork out of the floor of an ancient desert castle
a week ago, authorities said Sunday.
   Police on Saturday arrested a man and his two sons and found the
artwork at their home in the ancient Roman city of Jerash, 22 miles
north of Amman, a police spokesman said.
   The 15-by-18-foot mosaic was the most intact early Islamic
mosaic in Jordan before it was stolen, ``but obviously the gang
dropped it somewhere while they were hurrying to leave the
castle,'' said Ghazi Bisheh, antiquities director of the Tourism
Ministry.
   The mosaic with a ``tree of life'' design was taken from
Hallabat Castle, a Roman and Moslem fortress 30 miles northeast of
Amman. The theft prompted demands for better protection of the
fort, which was guarded by a nearby Bedouin villager.
   Minister of Tourism Abdul-Karim Kabariti said last week the
thieves apparently took advantage of the Islamic holy month of
Ramadan to enter the site at dusk, when the guard, like most
Moslems, was breaking his dawn-to-dusk fast with a meal.
   The police official said Saleh Issa Suleiman, 51, and his two
sons, 32-year-old Mohammed and 28-year-old Ahmad, were charged with
stealing antiquities.
   The official, who cannot be identified under police regulations,
said conviction could bring one to three years in prison and a
minimum fine of $500. He said harsher measures are expected against
the gang for ruining such a precious antiquity.
   The design was also almost ruined due to the rough way it was
lifted off the floor, Bisheh said. The thieves ``applied strong
glue to the surface of the mosaic, covered it with a large jute
cloth and carelessly lifted the entire picture off the floor at one
time.''
   ``We will be able to fix it, since we have all the necessary
documents and picture of the design,'' Bisheh said. ``But we will
now put it in a safer place, the Jerash Museum.''
   Bisheh said the multicolor design, depicting a large tree
surrounded by lions, bulls, goats and birds, was created in the
eighth century when the fortress was used as a hunting outpost by
early Islamic rulers.
   The castle was one of several in the Jordanian and Syrian
deserts used as Roman outposts in the second and third centuries.
Archaeologists say it was used as a monastery in the seventh
century before it was taken over the the Ummayed Moslems in the
years after the Islamic conquest.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0028 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 1258EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Germany-Investment     04-08 0757</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Germany-Investment,0784</SECOND>
<HEAD>Western Investors Race to Get Foot in Emerging East German Market</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DEBORAH G. SEWARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>EAST BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Dieter Kloss grinned as yet another group of
Western businessmen with bulging briefcases crammed the lobby of
the modest but busy offices of the East German Chamber of Foreign
Trade.
   ``I'm having a great time at work these days. Only six months
ago such coming and going would have been unthinkable,'' said
Kloss, an economist.
   The chamber is advising growing numbers of American, West
European, and Asian businesses trying to get a foot in East Germany
before the market is saturated.
   Before the dramatic opening of the country's borders and the
collapse of Communist rule last fall, most of the chamber's
visitors came from the East bloc trading alliance COMECON.
   ``Western firms began coming from day one of the changes and
we're encouraging them partly because we're feeling a bit overrun
by West Germany,'' Kloss said.
   Signs of the arrival of foreign firms are spreading across East
Berlin.
   Almost daily, workmen at the International Trade Center climb up
a high ladder in the lobby to letter the names of new companies
that have leased office space in the downtown skyscraper.
   Levi Strauss recently mounted its red logo on the door of a 15th
floor suite from which the company will run future operations in
East Germany, where Western jeans are already a hit.
   Coca Cola began selling soda in East Germany two months ago and
its West German subsidiary is now seeking an East German partner to
start a production plant.
   Both Levi Strauss and Coca Cola were sold previously in East
Germany, but only in hard-currency Intershops for foreigners.
   Price Waterhouse Inc., the U.S. financial services firm, is
setting up in East Berlin, as is the prestigious investment bank,
Salomon Brothers Inc.
   ``If you want to be part of East German developments you have to
have a presence there,'' said Peter Coym, Managing Director of
Salomon Brothers' operations in West Germany.
   The bank plans to open its office in the sumptuous Grand Hotel
in East Berlin in mid-April, with a focus on investment banking and
consulting connected to the privatization of state companies.
   The computer giant IBM plans a joint venture with the East
German firm Robotron, while General Motors-Opel beat out West
German giants Daimler-Benz and BMW to hook up with the Wartburg car
plant.
   Caterpillar has started marketing tractors, backloaders and
other agricultural and building machines through its West German
subsidiary, Zeppelin.
   ``There is great demand in East Germany. Their machines are old
and outmoded. Everybody is interested in getting a foot in East
Germany,'' said Hans Knausel, a spokesman for Zeppelin.
   It didn't used to be that way. For four decades, the Communist
governments and complicated centralized economies discouraged
Western businessmen from trying to trade with East Germany.
   Trade with the United States in 1989 amounted to about $200
million, turnover with France was under $2 billion, and there was
almost no business at all with South Korea.
   Western organizations that encouraged business in West Berlin,
an outpost of democracy during the Cold War, must now start
thinking of Berlin as a whole.
   The American Chamber of Commerce is considering a move from West
to East Berlin, where its offices were located before World War II.
   The Berlin Economic Development Corporation founded in 1978 with
the task of attracting outside investment to West Berlin is also
now looking eastward.
   ``Recently we expanded our activities in the eastern direction.
Companies who come to us for advice are more interested in East
Berlin,'' said Helmut Wolf, who advises English-speaking companies.
   Other West European and Asian countries have joined the United
States in the race to penetrate the East German market, swamped by
West German firms seeking partners.
   The Italian carmaker FIAT has announced plans to produce cars in
East Germany. The French and British want to develop hotels, but
have been less aggressive than the Americans or the Italians.
   Kloss said East Germany had just signed an agreement on economic
cooperation with South Korea that could offer expertise in the
steel and shipbuilding sectors.
   Despite the changes, there are still barriers to developing
trade in East Germany.
   Western companies still cannot convert profits into hard
currency and send them home, and some companies are unwilling to
invest until the German currencies are merged, probably this summer.
   But other companies say now is the time to enter the market and
earn name recognition even though East German marks are almost
worthless.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0029 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 1302EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Pope     04-08 0531</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Pope,0547</SECOND>
<HEAD>Pope Invites World Youth to Join Him in Poland</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARY BETH SHERIDAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>VATICAN CITY (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Pope John Paul II on Sunday invited youths
from around the world to join him at Poland's most famous Roman
Catholic shrine in August 1991 to mark World Youth Day.
   The pope's statement, at the conclusion of a Palm Sunday Mass,
was his first confirmation of a 1991 trip to Poland. Polish church
officials have said they expected a visit, the fourth by John Paul
to his homeland since he became pope in 1978.
   The pope's announcement came as the Vatican is intensifying its
activities in the newly democratic countries of Eastern Europe
after decades of oppression from Communist governments.
   The Vatican on Sunday offered to mediate in the dispute over
independence between Lithuania and the Soviet Union.
   The youth rally will likely bring tens of thousands of youths
from around the world to Czestochowa, whose icon has symbolized
Polish nationalism and religious faith during centuries of foreign
occupation and partition.
   The pope said the Madonna of Czestochowa, honored at the shrine
in southern Poland, ``has constituted the heart of the history of
the Polish people for more than 600 years.''
   John Paul said the theme of the youth day would be the Gospel
phrase ``You have received the spirit of children.''
   ``In the era in which we are living, marked by profound social
upheavals, this spirit of children of God constitutes the true
propulsive element of the history of peoples and the life of
individuals,'' the pontiff said in Italian to more than 20,000
people in front of St. Peter's Basilica.
   The pope has previously marked the church's World Youth Day with
international rallies in Buenos Aires, Argentina in 1987 and in
Santiago de Compostela, Spain, in August.
   According to legend, the ``Black Madonna'' of Czestochowa was
painted by St. Luke on a plank of wood from Christ's table. John
Paul is particularly devoted to the shrine, which he has visited on
his previous papal trips to Poland in 1979, 1983 and 1987.
   The pope's trip will be his first to Poland since the Communist
regime gave way to a government dominated by the labor movement,
Solidarity, which John Paul has strongly supported.
   The Italian news agency ANSA, without citing sources, said the
pontiff's trip might be divided in two parts: a visit in June to
Warsaw and other cities, and a trip to Czestochowa in August.
   The church established its World Youth Day in 1986 and
celebrates it in alternate years in Rome. Sunday's Mass marked the
1990 World Youth Day, as well as Palm Sunday.
   John Paul, wearing red robes, blessed palms symbolizing the holy
day during the open-air Mass, which commemorated Jesus Christ's
triumphant entry into Jerusalem. At the end of the ceremony, he
offered greetings to youths in several languages.
   Holy Week services continue later this week when the pope
re-enacts part of Christ's last supper with his apostles on Holy
Thursday.
   The pope plans to carry a wooden cross in a Good Friday
procession at the Colosseum. He celebrates an Easter vigil Saturday
night and Mass at St. Peter's on Easter Sunday.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0030 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 1344EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-GradingTheLawyers     04-08 0575</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Grading The Lawyers,600</SECOND>
<HEAD>Two Supreme Court Justices Pan Lawyers' Performances</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RICHARD CARELLI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two Supreme Court justices, the most junior
and the most senior, give low grades to the lawyers who have
appeared before them this year. Too many lawyers misunderstand the
purpose of the high court's argument sessions, both say.
   ``I'm really surprised,'' Justice Anthony M. Kennedy said in a
recent interview. ``They don't understand that a good oral argument
is really like a discussion of the doctoral thesis, not a debate.
It's relaxed, in a sense. It's a quiet inquiry, not a pyrotechnic
performance.''
   Kennedy, who joined the court in 1988, says the quality of
advocacy during oral arguments ``has not been as good this year as
last.''
   Justice William J. Brennan, who has been listening to high court
arguments since 1956, agrees.
   When asked if many lawyers misconstrue what is expected of them
at the arguments, Brennan said, ``I'm very sure that's true, and I
don't know whose fault that is.''
   Of the some 5,000 cases that reach the court each year, the
justices grant review to about 150 cases. In those, lawyers for
each side appear before the nine justices for an hour-long argument
session _ the only work the court performs in public _ before a
decision is reached.
   Brennan recalled during a recent interview that as a state
appellate judge in New Jersey he thought ``the level of advocacy
was appalling.''
   ``When appointed to this court, I thought, `My gosh, when I get
to the Supreme Court of the United States, immediately there's
going to be a marked increase in quality.' Well, I haven't found
that all these years,'' he said.
   Brennan said he believes the general demise in quality this year
even has infected the Justice Department lawyers who represent the
federal government before the high court.
   After noting that the solicitor general's small staff usually
offers the government ``first-rate representation,'' Brennan said,
``And yet, I'm not so sure that's true this year. I don't know why.
They still have very, very bright young people. Perhaps they just
haven't been at it long enough.''
   Some courts, streamlining due to heavy caseloads, have
eliminated argument sessions, and make their decisions based on
written briefs alone. Brennan hopes the Supreme Court never takes
that course.
   ``Oral argument is one of the most important of our procedures.
I often get different ideas during oral arguments resulting in
changes'' of how he views a case, he said.
   But Brennan, the court's leading liberal, rarely asks any
questions during the sessions _ unlike Kennedy and the other
relatively young conservative justices.
   ``In past years, I guess I asked as many questions as those of
my colleagues today who ask most questions,'' Brennan said. ``I
have discovered that I get the most out of oral arguments if I let
the lawyers ... present their cases uninterrupted by me.''
   He added: ``That seems to have worked ... I get everything I
want out of the oral arguments.''
   Kennedy takes another approach. ``I ask questions for a couple
of reasons,'' he said. ``To let counsel know my concerns, and to
let my colleagues know my concerns.''
   Kennedy was surprised when told that many visitors to the
courtroom sessions have mentioned his stern judicial scowl. ``It
may be that I value oral argument so highly that I'm very anxious
for the attorney to perform at his best,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0031 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 1347EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People     04-08 0991</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People,1029</SECOND>
<HEAD>People in the News</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY44</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PHILADELPHIA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Flutist James Galway's eyes sparkle at the
mention of his operatic debut in the title role of Rossini's ``The
Thieving Magpie'' in its first U.S. performance in this century.
   ``I didn't study birds for years to do this. I studied music,''
said Galway, 50, who is basing his stage movements on his
observation of the chattering, black and white bird.
   Rossini wrote the opera using an actor as the magpie who stole
the silver spoon and caused a young servant girl to be sentenced to
death, but the Opera Company of Philadelphia revised the role for a
musician.
   The rolling notes Galway plays as he flits about the stage were
borrowed from passages Rossini wrote for the violin and flute as
parts of the orchestra down in the pit.
   Galway, who turned 50 last year, plays opening night, April 16,
and his wife and fellow performer, Jeanne, plays the magpie in the
second and final performance. On April 17, he begins a tour in
southern California that ends three weeks later in New York City.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>CINCINNATI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Ray Combs, host of the television game show
``Family Feud,'' was arrested on a trespassing complaint after he
appeared on the stage of the comedy club he co-owns.
   Combs' arrest when he left the CaddyCombs Comedy Club on Friday
night was the latest legal action in a dispute about ownership and
operation of the downtown club he and others opened in September.
   Combs, released later at police headquarters, said the arrest,
based on a private complaint, was his first and called it ``the
grossest injustice of human rights I have ever seen.'' He is
scheduled to appear April 25 in Hamilton County Municipal Court.
   He has filed a lawsuit accusing Charles Schneider and the House
Inc., owner of the building, have not kept separate the CaddyCombs
and Caddy clubs, and has failed to maintain and to pay half the
profits of the comedy club.
   William DeCenso, attorney for the House Inc. and Schneider, said
his client did not want to comment on Combs' arrest.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>RICHMOND, Va. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Marvin Bush, youngest son of President
Bush, has been named finance chairman of the Republican Party of
Virginia while it recovers from a financial embarrassment.
   Last year, the state GOP cut staff and expenses after officials
discovered a former bookkeeper had failed to pay withholding taxes
for about 16 months. The party had to borrow to repay taxes of
about $150,000 amd a $74,000 fine.
   ``One of my objectives is to make sure that things run as
cleanly as possible,'' said Bush, who also will oversee the state
party's fund-raising operations.
   Bush replaces state Sen. Edwina P. ``Eddy'' Dalton of Henrico
County, who was the party's unsuccessful candidate for lieutenant
governor last year.
   Bush worked for his father's presidential campaign in Virginia
in 1988. He works in Alexandria for John Stewart Darrell and Co., a
financial planning firm and acknowledges that his name won't hurt
in GOP fund-raising.
   ``Being George Bush's son, there are some up sides to it,'' he
said.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>GALLATIN GATEWAY, Mont. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Media mogul Ted Turner attracted
hundreds of farmers, ranchers and bargain-hunters to an auction of
surplus equipment from his extensive holdings in southwest Montana.
   Saturday's auction, which offered everything from diesel
tractors and hay bale stackers to irrigation pipe as he converts
his Flying D Ranch from cattle to raising buffalo and trophy elk.
   The Flying D earlier sold about 11,000 cattle and began cutting
back on growing hay at higher elevations to make room for the 3,000
to 4,000 buffalo that Turner wants to let roam, said ranch manager
Bud Griffith.
   Last summer, the owner of WTBS in Atlanta _ who also owns
professional sports teams and has other extensive business
interests _ bought the Shelton Ranches, which include the Flying D,
for a reported $20 million-plus.
   The holdings encompass 110,000 deeded acres and 20,000 leased
acres between the Madison and Gallatin rivers. Turner put 107,000
acres under permanent conservancy to protect the land from
development.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   It's a dog's life, sometimes, for Doug
Llewelyn, who interviews litigants on ``The People's Court'' and
had one bite him on the knee.
   Celebrity magistrate Joseph A. Wapner had just heard the case of
Anthony and Cynthia Patti of Highland, who said a neighbor boy had
shot their dog, a Doberman-pit bull mix named Dee-Oh-Gee, in the
eye with a pellet gun.
   According to a publicity release for the TV show, as Llewelyn
had his customary chat with the adversaries after the court battle,
Dee-Oh-Gee sunk his fangs into Llewelyn's right knee.
   A physician was called in to administer a tetanus shot. The dog
owners ruefully explained that Dee-Oh-Gee had never acted mean
before being shot. Llewelyn, who has four dogs of his own, accepted
their apology.
   The dog owners won their case before Wapner, by the way,
persuading the judge to put the bite on the neighbor boy's father
for $300 in surgery costs for Dee-Oh-Gee.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>GREEN RIVER, Wyo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Harrison Ford, whose breathtaking chase
scenes have characterized his role as film adventurer Indiana
Jones, stopped in this southern Wyoming town last week and quietly
bought a new motorcycle.
   Linda Stance, a clerk at the Harley-Davidson of Green River
motorcycle shop, said Ford spent about 45 minutes Thursday buying a
1990 black and cream Heritage model Harley.
   Stance said Ford, who owns land near Jackson, called earlier in
the week to ask if the shop carried the motorcycle. Told the bike
was available, he said he would fly to the Rock Springs Airport and
would need a lift to the shop.
   Linda Laughlin, the shop's owner, gave Ford a ride from the
airport to Green River, a community of about 10,000. At the shop,
he posed for pictures with workers before he rode his new Harley
out of town.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0032 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 1426EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Vatican-Lithuania     04-08 0289</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Vatican-Lithuania,0296</SECOND>
<HEAD>Vatican Might Mediate Lithuania Dispute if Asked</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Soviet-Baltics</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ROME (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Vatican might mediate in the dispute over
Lithuania's independence if it was asked to do so, the Holy See's
envoy to the Soviet Union said in an interview published Sunday.
   The Roman Catholic newspaper Avvenire quoted Archbishop
Francesco Colasuonno as saying that the conflict between Moscow and
Lithuania over the republic's declaration of independence was ``a
political question'' that could be dealt with by ``appropriate
organs, such as the U.N.''
   ``If, however, as a hypothesis, the Holy See was asked to carry
out a task of persuasion or mediation, it is possible that it would
do its best to reach a peaceful solution of the conflict,''
Colasuonno was quoted as saying.
   Soviet President Mikhail S. Gorbachev has sent troops on patrol
through Lithuania as part of a campaign of pressure since the
republic declared independence on March 11.
   Colasuonno is due to travel to Moscow later this month as he
begins his job as papal nuncio to the Soviet Union. He was named to
the post last month when the Soviet Union and Vatican forged
diplomatic ties for the first time since the formation of the
Communist state.
   He noted that Pope John Paul II has called for dialogue to
resolve the dispute over Lithuania, which is overwhelmingly
Catholic.
   Colasuonno said he had ``reasons for optimism'' about
Gorbachev's policy of perestroika, or economic restructuring,
because of the developments in the Soviet Union in the past few
years.
   Colasuonno, who has been a roving Vatican envoy to Eastern
Europe, also said he expected diplomatic ties between the Holy See
and Czechoslovakia to be restored before the pope visits the former
Communist country April 21-22.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0033 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 1434EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Lithuania-Churkin     04-08 0335</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lithuania-Churkin,340</SECOND>
<HEAD>Lithuanian Declaration Should Be Withdrawn, Soviet Says</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Soviet official said Sunday that Moscow is
engaged in a ``political dialogue,'' with Lithuania, but a
Lithuanian called the assertion a ``lie.''
   Vitaly Churkin, an advisor to the Soviet foreign ministry, also
said Lithuania should withdraw its declaration of independence so
negotiations about the Baltic State's future can proceed.
   Churkin said Soviet President Mikhail Gorbachev's government
wants to resolve the Lithuanian situation ``though political
dialogue, and obviously this is what is going on now. We are
thinking about it in those terms.''
   Algimantis Cekuolis, a Lithuanian official, called that
statement a ``lie.'' Both men appeared on ABC-TV's ``This Week With
David Brinkley.''
   ``They would be very happy to do anything to overthrow that
(Lithuanian) government, like using a military force from inside
and economical blockade from outside,'' Cekuolis said.
   ``That lie number three, that was told, that political dialogue
going on ... There is no political dialogue, if you don't mean this
Kalashnikov gun,'' he said.
   Lithuanians have tried to talk with the Soviets, but have only
managed to get three hours of time from one of Gorbachev's
deputies, he said.
   ``Please understand, they are not talking with us, but they are
shouting all around the world that they are talking,'' he said.
   But Churkin said, ``If you want a divorce, you talk to your
spouse, and it's either divorce after you settle all the issues
which are involved, or maybe a reconciliation.
   ``We certainly would like to see a reconciliation, but who knows
what the outcome is going to be.''
   Churkin said the Lithuanians, who have demanded independence
from Moscow, acted precipitiously in trying to secede before
working out details of their future relationship with the Soviet
Union on economic and other matters.
   ``Their declaration of independence, we feel, should be
rescinded because it amounts to an ultimatum,'' he said. ``And
before you declare your independence, you have to clear out some of
the things which need to be resolved.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0034 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 1500EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Burma-FerryDisaster     04-08 0309</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Burma-Ferry Disaster,0318</SECOND>
<HEAD>Survivor: Ferry Sank Minutes After Gale Struck; More Than 210
Feared Dead</HEAD>
<DATELINE>RANGOON, Burma (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   One of only 25 survivors rescued from a
ferry that sank with about 240 people aboard said the boat went
down minutes after being hit by gale-force winds, an official
newspaper reported Sunday.
   At least 30 people drowned and as many as 180 others were
missing and feared dead after the double-decker ferry Sein San Pya
overturned Friday afternoon in the southern Gyaing River, official
radio reports said.
   The latest radio report said 25 people had been rescued.
   The government-owned Working People's Daily quoted survivor Aung
Mya Tint, a police inspector, as saying the vessel went down
minutes after being struck by strong wind.
   The newspaper said the accident was due to natural forces rather
than overloading. There are frequent ferry boat accidents in Burma
due to overloading of passengers and cargo.
   The newspaper said the vessel could carry 280 passengers and up
to 40 tons of cargo, noting the ferry that sank carried about 240
passengers and 19 tons of cargo.
   The ferry was making a regular run on the Gyaing River from the
town of Moulmein eastward to the town of Kyondo in the southern
province of Tenasserim, Radio Rangoon said. Moulmein is 100 miles
southeast of Rangoon.
   The newspaper said doctors, Red Cross workers and local
officials were providing medical treatment and other assistance to
the survivors.
   Ferry accidents in southern Burma have claimed large numbers of
lives in recent years.
   In May 1987, a old vessel with 400 people aboard overturned and
sank in the Rangoon River. Reports at the time said 283 passengers
were rescued but no official death toll was given.
   In October last year, 60 people were reported missing when a
ferry with 170 people aboard sank in a storm near Rangoon.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0035 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 1501EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-S&amp;Ls     04-08 0329</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-S&amp;Ls,330</SECOND>
<HEAD>S&amp;L Bailout May Require Tax Hike, GAO Head Says</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A tax increase will be needed at some point to
pay for escalating losses among a third of the nation's savings and
loan institutions, Comptroller General Charles A. Bowsher said
Sunday.
   Bowsher this past week raised the estimated pricetag for the
government's S&amp;L bailout from $257 billion to $325 billion with a
warning that it could rise to $500 billion.
   ``This is one of the great financial disasters that we've ever
had in this country and its going to have to be added onto all the
other problems we have in the federal budget,'' he said on NBC-TV's
``Meet the Press.''
   ``When you get done making the cuts that you hope you can make
in defense and some of the other areas ... you're still going to
have to look at the revenue side of the budget,'' the head of the
congressional General Accounting Office said.
   Bowsher blamed the Bush administration's desire to meet deficit
reduction targets without a tax increase for underestimating the
size of the S&amp;L problem.
   ``Last year they had unrealistic interests rates in their
forecast,'' he said. ``They insisted on using a deposit assumption
that ... gave you a 7 percent deposit growth _ where we knew that
deposits were leaving. We told them at the time we'd probably be
back, and that's where we are today.''
   L. William Seidman, chairman of the Federal Deposit Insurance
Corp. and the Resolution Trust Corp., responsible for handling the
bailout, said the government ``simply didn't know in what bad
condition these S&amp;Ls were.''
   ``We found that there were more of them and in worse shape than
we thought,'' Seidman said on the same show. ``One of the things
everybody would like is to have it over in the near future. That
just isn't going to happen. This is going to be with us for a long
while, and it's going to be painful.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0036 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 1503EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Passover     04-08 0720</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Passover,0743</SECOND>
<HEAD>Modern Seders Vary, but Tradition Spans Thousands of Years</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By EVE EPSTEIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   There may be more varieties of matzoh now than
when the Israelites fled from Egypt, but the essential elements of
the Passover Seder haven't changed for thousands of years, making
it one of the oldest ritual sit-down dinners.
   Perhaps the reason the feast commemorating the Exodus has
survived so long is that its whole purpose is to pass on to
generations of Jews the story of their ancestors' escape from
slavery. On Monday at sundown, Jews all over the world will observe
the tradition again.
   One professor of Jewish studies believes the gastronomic nature
of the tradition may also have something to do with its longevity.
   ``If you can hit them in the stomach, it lasts,'' said Jon
Levenson, a professor of Jewish studies at Harvard University.
   Elements of the family Seder as it is practiced today date back
some 1,900 years, to the time of the destruction of the Second
Temple in Jerusalem, Levenson said. Some parts of the tradition may
date back roughly 3,000 years.
   Some scholars believe Jesus Christ's Last Supper was a Seder.
``That's unclear. It certainly took place around Passover time,''
Levenson said.
   There are Eastern religious meals that probably predate the
Jewish Seder, but documentation to trace when they began is
sketchy, according to religious scholars.
   The meaning of the Hebrew word for ``Passover'' is debatable,
Levenson said. The popular explanation for the English word is that
it describes the angel of death ``passing over'' the homes of Jews
who marked their doors with lamb's blood. According to Exodus, the
angel of death was sent to slay the Egyptians' firstborn.
   The modern explanation may be close to the original meaning of
the word. Levenson believes the Hebrew word ``Pesach'' comes from a
ritual dance.
   ``The verb itself I think means jump, leap,'' Levenson said.
``It may very well indicate that the destroyer in Exodus jumps''
over Jewish homes.
   The style of a modern Seder varies with each family. Some allow
for long discussions, some are filled with song, others adopt
modern themes. But the essential story, and many of the props that
go with it, remain the same.
   Matzoh, the flat bread that now comes in whole wheat, egg and
unsalted varieties, symbolizes that the Israelites fled so quickly
from Pharaoh they didn't have time to let their bread rise.
   Bitter herbs, like horseradish, recall the bitter taste of
slavery. And a sweet paste, often made of apples, raisins and nuts,
represents the mortar the Jewish slaves used to build Egyptian
pyramids.
   The Seder story is built around questions from children, usually
posed by the youngest child at the table. The responses are framed
so that even the child who doesn't know how to ask a question can
learn the Exodus story.
   The Haggada is a book used to guide the meal. Traditional
Haggadot contain prayers, blessings and appropriate readings. Some
narratives are illustrated with pictures, others are specially made
for children, and a feminist Haggada even appeared several years
ago. References to the Holocaust, and to those lost in the Nazi
death camps, are now common at many Seder tables.
   Some families use the Haggada as a starting point to lead into
discussions of modern-day problems.
   Marvin Kalb, a former television correspondent who now directs a
center on media studies at Harvard University's Kennedy School of
Government, said talk at his family's Seder table often turns to
newsworthy topics.
   ``We're very political and we do talk about modern themes,
although we do go through the Passover readings in a very
traditional way, '' Kalb said.
   Kalb said he still recalls cleaning the house and changing the
dishes in his boyhood home to prepare for Passover. He said the
Passover tradition has survived because it is built on an
inherently interesting tale.
   ``It's a great story. It's a story of freedom,'' Kalb said.
   Author Elie Wiesel, who has written extensively about his
experiences as a Holocaust survivor, said his family sticks closely
to the traditional Haggada.
   ``It is linked to the first holiday, to the very beginning of
history,'' said Wiesel, who teaches at Boston University. ``We are
always fascinated with beginnings. After all, I think it's the
first liberation story in history.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0037 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 1512EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-US-Vietnam Bjt   04-08 0748</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-US-Vietnam, Bjt,720</SECOND>
<NOTE>EDS: Retransmits a0675 to fix byline.</NOTE>
<HEAD>Return of U.S. Military to Vietnam Discussed</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JEFF BARKER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Vietnamese officials privately suggested
allowing the U.S. military to return to Cam Ranh Bay if relations
between the countries continue to warm, says a congressman who
recently met with them.
   Rep. Thomas Ridge, R-Pa., said the extraordinary possibility was
raised informally at a foundation-sponsored forum in Bali,
Indonesia attended by several congressmen and a group of
top-ranking officials of Vietnam's communist government.
   A congressional delegation headed by the chairwoman of the House
subcommittee responsible for overseeing U.S. military bases hopes
to visit Cam Ranh Bay this week as part of a 10-day trip to
Vietnam, Guam, Singapore and Indonesia.
   The mission's purpose is to explore alternatives to U.S.
military bases in the Philippines. Leases on six U.S. installations
in the Philippines expire in 1991 and American officials anticipate
difficult negotiations for continued base rights there.
   The Soviet Union moved into the U.S.-built base at Cam Ranh Bay
at the conclusion of the Vietnam War in 1975, but Pentagon
officials said in January that the Soviets had withdrawn some
fighter planes and bombers.
   The possibility of the Soviets withdrawing completely from the
base and Americans returning to it was one of the subjects at the
Indonesia forum sponsored by the Henry R. Luce Foundation, Ridge
said.
   ``That possibility was discussed and under the right set of
circumstances I think the Vietnamese would welcome it,'' said
Ridge, who saw Vietnam War combat as an enlisted man.
   ``One of the ranking Vietnamese officials said, `I can see the
day when American ships are docked in Cam Ranh Bay,' '' Ridge said,
adding that the official later specified that he meant warships.
   ``We said, `Do you mean just for refueling?' and they said, `No,
for repairs,' '' Ridge said.
   Ridge said conditions of the forum prevented him from
identifying the Vietnamese official.
   Rep. Chester Atkins, D-Mass., who also was at the meeting, said
returning to Cam Ranh Bay ``would require some major changes in the
relationship between the United States and Vietnam.''
   But Atkins, who declined to discuss specifics of the meeting,
also said: ``I think the Vietnamese are desperate. Their economy is
in a state of continued deterioration. I think they're willing to
look at or think about anything that doesn't endanger their
national security that would allow them to rejoin the economic
community and modernize.''
   The United States and Vietnam have no diplomatic or trade
relations. The State Department says it will consider relations
only after verification of Vietnamese troop withdrawals from
Cambodia, and after a process of internationally supervised
elections in Cambodia is established.
   Seven members of Congress hope to visit Cam Ranh Bay this week
to determine the extent of the Soviet reductions there, said
delegation leader Pat Schroeder, D-Colo., chairwoman of the House
Armed Services subcommittee on military installations and
facilities.
   Such a visit will require both Vietnamese and Soviet approval
``so I don't know if we'll get there or not,'' Schroeder said
Friday.
   While the delegation is interested in the status of Cam Ranh
Bay, Schroeder emphasized that the purpose of the trip was
obtaining a broader view of U.S. security responsibilities in the
region.
   ``We in the U.S. Congress cannot negotiate with either the
Soviets or the Vietnamese on Cam Ranh Bay, but it is a very
important facility and it is in a country that appears to be in a
positive transition more towards our side,'' Schroeder said.
   Regardless of what happens with Cam Ranh Bay, she said she
wanted to uncover base alternatives because ``some in the
Philippines are demanding that we pay $2 billion a year in rent''
to keep U.S. installations there.
   In 1988, the Soviets offered to abandon Cam Ranh Bay if the
United States did the same with its Philippines bases. The United
States rejected the offer, saying it needed the Pacific bases to
support its worldwide operations.
   The State Department has received no offer from the Vietnamese
about Cam Ranh Bay, according to a department official who spoke
last week on condition of anonymity.
   John Leboutillier, a former Republican congressman from New
York, said in a recently published book that Vietnamese officials
told him they would be receptive to talking about Cam Ranh Bay if
relations normalized.
   Leboutillier said in an interview that he told the Bush
administration about the conversations, but that he had no evidence
that any action was taken.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0038 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 1518EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Mongolia     04-08 0304</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mongolia,0315</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mongolia Bans Demonstrations</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Mongolia's president has issued a decree banning
protest demonstrations, the government newspaper reported Sunday.
The ruling comes days before the Communist Party is scheduled to
meet to discuss democratic reforms.
   The restriction appears designed to head off protests by
Mongolia's fledgling opposition parties during Tuesday's party
meeting.
   China's official Xinhua News Agency, reporting from the
Mongolian capital of Ulan Bator, quoted the official Mongolian
newspaper, Unen, as saying the regulation was decreed by President
Punsalmaagiyn Ochirbat.
   The regulation says Mongolian citizens can take part in
demonstrations and rallies ``aimed at developing and consolidating
the state apparatus and in the interests of the working people,''
Xinhua said. Applications for demonstrations must be submitted to
local governments a week in advance.
   The regulation bans demonstrations that ``are against the state
constitution, detrimental to friendship with other countries and to
the unity of the Mongolian people, threatening state security or
people's safety and disrupting people's tranquility or the normal
work of a government department,'' Xinhua said.
   Opposition groups have held repeated demonstrations in Ulan
Bator's central square since late last year to demand democratic
reforms similar to the changes sweeping through Eastern Europe.
   In response, Mongolia's ruling Communist Party shuffled top
party and government ranks in March and promised free elections.
But opposition groups said they do not trust the party's promises
and have vowed to demonstrate until reforms are implemented.
   At last month's annual session of the Communist-dominated
legislature, the Great People's Hural, numerous deputies denounced
the demonstrations as disruptive and called for a law to regulate
them.
   The demonstrations have always been peaceful and have drawn
crowds of up to 10,000 people.
   Mongolia has been closely allied with the Soviet Union since the
Soviets helped a small Mongol revolutionary army win independence
from China in 1921.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0039 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 1519EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-CapitolStatues     04-08 0586</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Capitol Statues,0603</SECOND>
<HEAD>Century-Old Statues Get Facelift at Connecticut Capitol</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PETER VILES</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HARTFORD, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   At the state Capitol, Education has lost
its head. Commerce is short-handed. Half of Agriculture has
disappeared entirely.
   But it's not because of budget cuts or governmental neglect _
it's the damage caused by more than a century of wear and tear on
12 allegorical statues in the state Capitol.
   In one of the final stages of a $38 million renovation of the
Capitol building, the plaster of Paris statues of Greek women are
being restored.
   The six pairs of Greek-style statues on two stairway landings
leading to the House balcony symbolize six pillars of Connecticut
culture _ education, commerce, force, agriculture, science and
music.
   On days when the General Assembly is not in session, sculptor
John D. Leslie carefully shapes clay molds to recreate the hands,
heads and toes that have been chipped away by a century's worth of
passing tourists and lobbyists.
   ``It's a fascinating project,'' he said. ``There's no
deterioration in the material itself. It's just that the statues
have been banged and chipped over the years.''
   Sculpted in 1876 by John Quincy Adams Ward of New York, the
statues are actually the scale models that Adams used to sculpt 12
identical but larger marble statues that ring the outside of the
Capitol dome.
   Each statue depicts a Greek woman holding an object showing her
role. Agriculture holds an apple and a sheaf of wheat; Music strums
on a lyre.
   On the west landing, Commerce is missing a hand, and a prankster
once painted some of her toenails red. She is nicknamed ``the
goddess of basketball'' because she holds a small globe in one hand.
   The head is gone on one of the two Educations. An Agriculture
was inadvertently knocked over by workers one day and taken by
stretcher to the Capitol basement for repair. On both landings, the
bare-breasted Amazon who depicts Force is missing her spear.
   The restorer uses clay molds to make an exact match of the
originals, then casts a plaster of Paris replacement directly onto
the statue. Most of Leslie's work is done in Hartford, but he
worked in his studio in Guilford on a replacement head for
Education.
   ``I've had to crawl inside Mr. Ward's head,'' Leslie said.
``I've got to think like he did as best I can. I don't want to
improve his work _ that's not my job.''
   In most cases, Leslie can refer to the twin statue on the
opposite landing to find the exact dimensions of the missing piece.
When both statues are missing the same part, he uses binoculars to
study the intact version of the statues on the outside of the
Capitol.
   He will complete his $48,000 contract by painting the statues a
shade of tan identical to their original coat of paint.
   Leslie worked in a family foundry until he began restoring
statues and ornamental work in historic buildings seven years ago.
His past projects include the statues of four dolphins in the
courtyard of Yale's Sterling Library and work at the Shubert
Theater in New Haven.
   His latest reconstruction, which should keep him busy until
June, has given him a greater appreciation for Ward's work, he said.
   ``There's nothing by chance up there,'' he said. ``Everyone's
dressed a certain way for a certain reason.''
   A contemporary of Augustus Saint-Gaudens, Ward is perhaps best
known for his often-photographed statue of George Washington on
Wall Street in New York.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0040 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 1542EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-AxAttack     04-08 0570</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Ax Attack,0584</SECOND>
<HEAD>Woman Charged in Ax-Wielding ``Jack the Ripper'' Attack Goes on
Trial</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto MI1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JODIE DeJONGE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MILWAUKEE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A woman who allegedly claims she is the mother
of Jack the Ripper goes on trial Monday accused of plotting to kill
a man with an hatchet in a ritual she believed would resurrect the
British serial killer.
   The 26-year-old man, who has not been identified by court
officials, said in a complaint that he was lured to an apartment
and attacked by an ax-wielding woman hiding in the shower. He said
he needed 50 stitches for a forehead wound.
   Jury selection begins Monday in the trial of Deborah Kazuck, 26,
who is accused of plotting the May 29 attack with two other
Milwaukee women. Catherine Lipsham, 23, and Ramona Barry, 27,
pleaded guilty Friday to the same charge of attempted first-degree
murder and agreed to testify against Ms. Kazuck.
   The victim, who also is expected to testify, said he was lured
to an apartment on Milwaukee's south side by Ms. Barry. He had met
the women in a park a few weeks before the attack and said they
appeared ``perfectly normal.''
   He said he went to the bathroom, heard something move in the
shower and pushed the curtain aside to reveal Ms. Kazuck holding a
hatchet with a two-handed grip.
   She raised the hatchet above her head, began chanting
``redrum,'' or murder spelled backward, and struck him on the
forehead just above the left eye before he managed to escape, the
man told police.
   Police said Ms. Kazuck planned to dismember the victim's body,
drain his blood and eat his kidneys in a ritual she believed would
bring Jack the Ripper back to life.
   At least five prostitutes fell prey to the Ripper's knife in the
seamy East End of London in the autumn of 1888. Most were
disemboweled and mutilated. The crimes were never solved.
   Ms. Kazuck will have a two-phase trial because she has pleaded
both innocent and innocent by reason of mental disease or defect.
In the first phase, the jury must decide whether she committed the
crime. In the second, they will decide if she was insane at the
time.
   Pretrial publicity prompted the judge to order jury selection in
Madison, 90 miles away, but the trial will be held in Milwaukee
County Circuit Court.
   Ms. Barry said Friday she and Ms. Lipsham had been out
``kacking'' on several other occasions with Ms. Kazuck. She said
``kacking,'' a combination of ``killing'' and ``Jack,'' was their
code word for killing.
   She said she wasn't certain a murder would be attempted on May
29.
   ``I was not sure because we had gone out kacking before and did
nothing,'' she said. ``I was not too sure if there would be a
finished product. When it was going on in the bathroom and I could
hear the struggle, I felt, `Well, it's going on for real this
time.'''
   Police found correspondence about the slaying plot and a picture
of a man with an ax in the middle of his forehead at the apartment.
They described the attack as a satanic ritual.
   All three women told police they had participated in Satanism.
   Under the plea agreement, prosecutors said they would seek no
more than eight years in prison for both Ms. Lipmsham and Ms.
Barry. Sentencing for the two is set for May 25.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0041 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 1548EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Soviet-Baltics 1stLd-Writethru a0704 04-08 0515</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Baltics, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0704,0524</SECOND>
<HEAD>Lithuanians Block Soviet Troops at Newspaper Plant</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: ADDS 2 grafs with Latvian Communists electing new party
chief.</NOTE>
<HEAD>With AM-Lithuania-Future, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BRIAN FRIEDMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A crowd of Lithuanians prevented hundreds of
Soviet soldiers from entering the newspaper plant in Vilnius early
Sunday, residents said, in the latest confrontation since the
republic declared independence.
   The action came one day after hundreds of thousands of people at
a pro-independence rally in Vilnius, the republic's capital, heard
President Vytautas Landsbergis say that the Kremlin would be unable
to prevent Lithuania from breaking away from the Soviet Union.
   The Vatican's envoy to the Soviet Union, Archbishop Francesco
Colasuonno, offered to mediate any talks between Vilnius and
Moscow. He travels to Moscow later this month as he begins his job
as papal nuncio to the Soviet Union.
   Hundreds of Soviet soldiers in more than a dozen military
vehicles arrived at the printing plant in Vilnius at 5 a.m. Sunday.
They were prevented from getting inside, according to Romanas
Bogdavas, an adviser to Landsbergis.
   Eduardas Potashinskas of Lithuanian television, speaking by
telephone, put the number of Soviet troops at between 200 and 400.
He estimated that about 2,000 Lithuanians blocked their entry.
   About 30 Soviet soldiers already were inside the plant, occupied
by troops on March 31. They have not disrupted the plant's
operations.
   Dainius Skeritas, who described himself as one of 30 ``people's
guards'' patrolling inside the building, said the crowd of
Lithuanians held picket signs and flags. The Soviet soldiers said
they had orders to enter the building, according to Skeritas, who
spoke by telephone from inside the plant, which publishes
newspapers that support the independence drive.
   The ``people's guards'' are a volunteer force of civilians
delegated to guard the building, according to the information
service of Lithuania's parliament, the Supreme Council.
   The Soviet troops withdrew to their vehicles a few streets away,
and stayed there until members of the Supreme Council, as well as
Deputy Prime Minister Algirdas Brazauskas, arrived before noon and
began questioning the troops' commanders. The troops returned to
their garrison shortly after that.
   Bogdavas said many residents of Vilnius were angry that the
Soviet troops took the action on Palm Sunday, the start of Easter
week celebrations in predominantly Roman Catholic Lithuania.
   Since Lithuania's Parliament declared independence on March 11,
Soviet troops have occupied the printing plant, the republic's
Communist Party headquarters and the prosecutor's office,
heightening tensions in the republic. In addition, the soldiers
have arrested Lithuanian army deserters.
   Work at the printing plant is proceeding normally, Skeritas said.
   In the neighboring Baltic republic of Latvia, a Communist Party
congress elected a new first secretary of the party's Central
Committee. A pro-Moscow majority met behind closed doors after 270
delegates walked out to protest the congress' rejection of a
measure establishing an autonomous party.
   Soviet TV's Sunday night newscast Seven Days reported that
Alfred Rubiks, the 53-year-old mayor of Riga, was elected to the
post. He replaces Janis Vagris, who had been the Latvian party
chief since October 1988.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0042 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 1548EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Colombia     04-08 0180</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Colombia,0185</SECOND>
<HEAD>Police Seize Drug Trafficker's Gold-Plated Motorcycle</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BOGOTA, Colombia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Police raided a town that was once
controlled by a Medellin cartel leader and seized a gold-plated
motorcycle the drug lord had given to his son, authorities said
Sunday.
   The raid, one of 15 conducted in the town of Pacho on Saturday,
came nearly four months after the drug trafficker, Gonzalo
Rodriguez Gacha, and his son, Freddy, were gunned down by police on
Colombia's northern coast.
   Authorities said the Japanese-made motorcycle seized in Pacho,
50 miles north of Bogota, was coated with 18-carat gold. It was not
immediately clear what other prizes the police raids netted.
   Police have seized gold, silver, jewelry, cars, planes and
weapons worth hundreds of millions of dollars from Rodriguez
Gacha's ranches and estates.
   Police estimate the dealer accumulated a $3 billion fortune in
less than 10 years, a period of time in which he sent tons of
cocaine to the United States.
   He was considered the richest man in Colombia after Pablo
Escobar, another Medellin cartel leader still being sought by
police.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0043 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 1602EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Brazil     04-08 0694</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brazil,0717</SECOND>
<HEAD>Brazil's Congress Heads For Showdown With President Over Economic
Plan</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KEN SILVERSTEIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>RIO DE JANEIRO, Brazil (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Despite warnings from President
Fernando Collor de Mello, lawmakers Sunday seemed poised to
drastically alter the new leader's anti-inflation shock therapy
that has thrown people out of work.
   Congress was scheduled to meet late Sunday and all day Monday to
vote on Collor's 3-week-old plan to fight hyperinflation that
reached 4,850 percent last year.
   One of 10 items on the agenda is Measure 168, considered the
heart of the plan, which froze for 18 months assets of over $1,200
in bank savings accounts and over $600 in short-term money market
deposits.
   The move took about $115 billion _ 80 percent af all bank
deposits _ out of circulation overnight, and while officials say
inflation is coming down the plan has also put the economy on the
brink of a major recession.
   On Saturday, Rep. Osmundo Reboucas of the Brazilian Democratic
Movement Party, charged with reviewing Measure 168, filed his
report and suggested major changes.
   Reboucas' proposal, which will be submitted to the full Congress
in place of Collor's original measure, would allow savings account
withdrawals in installments of $4,800 every third month beginning
in July.
   ``This plan is a bomb. Any mistake will throw us into an
inflationary explosion or a terrible recession,'' Reboucas said.
   Reboucas' center-left Democratic Movement Party is the largest
in Congress with 179 of 570 seats. Brazil's Communist Party and the
leftist Workers Party also have condemned the package.
   Five centrist parties holding a solid majority in the Congress
have demanded substantial changes to the plan by Collor, a member
of the center-right National Reconstruction Party, which holds just
24 congressional seats.
   Collor, who announced the package on March 16, one day after
taking office as Brazil's first freely elected president in 29
years, warned Saturday that the bank freeze was non-negotiable and
crucial to defeating inflation.
   ``We have already liquidated inflation. Now, I wish to be
partners in the success of the plan because I won't be a partner in
tragedy if the plan is altered,'' he said during a visit to his
home state of Alagoas on Brazil's northeastern Atlantic Coast.
   Collor said the ceiling of $1,200 on bank withdrawals was not
``picked out of the air'' but selected by economists after detailed
studies.
   ``There is no return from the plan. Our ships have been burned,
and now we either win or we win,'' he said.
   Collor instituted the plan, which also included a 30-day price
freeze and a new national currency, with a series of 26
``provisional measures.'' The measures become law immediately but
can be voted down by Congress within 30 days.
   Legislators, who thus far have passed four measures intact and
eight with minor modifications, are expected to vote on the entire
package by mid-week, as the 30-day deadline is nearing and Friday
is a national holiday for Easter.
   If Reboucas' proposal is passed, Collor can veto it. But
Congress can overturn the veto with a simple majority.
   Most congressmen are up for re-election this fall, and many are
worried that if they support Collor's plan they will lose their
jobs in the event of a recession _ which now seems imminent.
   Half of Sao Paulo state's 370,000 auto workers are on enforced
collective holiday, union groups say some 200,000 workers have been
fired nationwide _ with huge lines forming at unemploment offices
in major cities all last week _ and major companies forced to
borrow from banks to pay salaries.
   ``If the government doesn't inject money into the economy we
won't have a recession, but a disaster,'' said Luiz Antonio de
Medeiros, president of the Sao Paulo Metalworkers Union, and
considered a moderate.
   Others fear an economic disaster, whatever Congress does.
   ``We will see a brutal recession if Congress doesn't lift the
ceiling on bank withdrawals. But I fear a run on the banks that
will provoke a hyperinflation if they do,'' said Alexandre Barros,
a consultant to local and multinational businessmen.
   ``If the plan doesn't work we are fried. If it does work we are
broiled,'' he added.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0044 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 1646EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-WorldElections-Glance     04-08 0500</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-World Elections-Glance,0520</SECOND>
<HEAD>Glance At Elections Sunday</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Greece, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Here is a look at some of the figures and candidates in
elections held Sunday in several countries.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>GREECE:</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   More than 8 million voters were eligible to cast ballots in
national elections for the third time in 10 months. Polls indicated
no party would capture a majority and break the stalemate that has
paralyzed the government and crippled the economy.
   Competing were candidates from 27 parties, two coalitions and 16
independent groupings that stretched across the political spectrum.
Voting was mandatory for Greeks between 18 and 70 years of age.
   Only three parties were considered likely to attract significant
numbers of voters: the conservative New Democracy party, the
Panhellenic Socialist Movement (PASOK) and the Communist-led
Coalition of the Left and Progress.
   The New Democrats narrowly missed a majority in the last two
elections and could seize control of the 300-seat single house
Parliament with just a 1 percent increase in votes.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>HUNGARY:</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   More than 7.5 million people were eligible to vote in a final
round of national elections to determine Hungary's first freely
chosen government in 43 years. The main conservative party took an
early lead.
   A poll made public after most voted ended predicted that the
party, the Hungarian Democratic Forum, would win.
   Elections two weeks ago left 261 of the National Assembly's 394
seats undecided. That balloting gave no party an outright majority
but relegated the former Communists to fourth place.
   Both front-running parties, the center-right Hungarian
Democratic Forum and the liberal Alliance of Free Democrats, have
refused to consider forming a government with the former
Communists, now running as the Socialist Party.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>PERU:</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Peru's nearly 10 million registered voters ignored threats of
violence by leftist guerrillas and cast votes for a new president.
Guerrillas hurled sticks of dynamite near polling stations, but no
injuries were reported. Troops stood guard.
   The race pitted favorite Mario Vargas Llosa, a 54-year-old
conservative author, against Alberto Fujimori, a dark-horse
independent.
   President Alan Garcia's five-year term ends July 28 and by law
cannot serve a consecutive term. His successor must try to revive a
depressed economy and fight 2,000 percent inflation in this country
of 20 million.
   Voters also chose a new congress, including 60 senators and 180
members of the chamber of deputies.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>YUGOSLAVIA:</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   In the republic of Slovenia, 1.5 million people were registered
to vote in the first free multiparty elections in Yugoslavia since
World War II. The election formally ends a 45-year Communist Party
monopoly in the republic, the first of Yugoslavia's six republics
to hold free elections.
   Voters will choose Slovenia's new president, four members of the
ruling collective presidency and 240 members of the new multiparty
parliament.
   Polls indicated that the front-runner for the presidency was
Milan Kucan, of the reformist Slovenian Communist Party, now
renamed the Party for Democratic Renewal.
   Turnout was heavy, with voters lining up in front of the polling
stations despite heavy rain.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0045 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 1700EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-SpaceShuttle 1stLd-Writethru a0709 04-08 0602</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Space Shuttle, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0709,0613</SECOND>
<HEAD>Spirits Rise As Crews Finish Hubble Installation Aboard Shuttle</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: INSERTS 2 grafs after 4th graf, `The weather ...,' to UPDATE
with short in heater cable; picks up 5th graf, `Discovery's
commander ...'</NOTE>
<HEAD>With AM-Hubble Trouble Bjt</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto CSB2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By HARRY F. ROSENTHAL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CAPE CANAVERAL, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An upbeat mood settled over this
launch center Sunday when crews finished installing the $1.5
billion Hubble Space Telescope in the space shuttle Discovery and
said they were on track for a Tuesday morning liftoff.
   ``This is a very important day for us,'' said William Taylor,
the telescope's chief engineer. ``Some of us who have been on the
project for a while wondered if we would ever see this day, or the
days to follow.''
   Closing of the cargo bay, which holds the 43-foot-long
telescope, was a milestone in the countdown for a launch at 8:47
a.m. EDT Tuesday. The telescope is the most expensive and
complicated payload to be carried aboard the shuttle in 35 flights.
It is being launched seven years later than originally planned.
   The weather predictions were good.
   There was only one hitch in the countdown: a short in a heater
cable in a strut that connects the shuttle to its huge fuel tank.
The heater prevents ice from forming on the strut when the tank is
filled with supercold liquid oxygen and liquid hydrogen.
   ``Technicians are checking to make sure that the short has not
influenced any other systems,'' shuttle program director Robert L.
Crippen said. ``The heater is not involved for launch and is not a
constraint to launch.''
   Discovery's commander Loren Shriver and pilot Charles F. Bolden
Jr., practiced emergency landings on the Kennedy Space Center
runway Sunday, while mission specialists Bruce McCandless, Steven
A. Hawley and Kathryn D. Sullivan went through final equipment fit
tests.
   All studied last-minute changes in their thick flight plans,
then had the afternoon off to spend in the hazy sun.
   Clearly the star of the show was the shiny telescope, named
after famed astronomer Edwin Hubble, which is expected to look
backward in time to nearly the formation of the universe some 15
billion years ago.
   ``This instrument has been built to the limits of what
technology can provide,'' said Charles Pellerin, director of NASA's
astrophysics division. ``This is a voyage very much perhaps like
the voyages of Columbus and Magellan, except that it's a voyage of
man's intellect into the universe.''
   Asked if perhaps scientists were overselling the expected
contributions of the telescope, Pellerin replied no, that it was
``the biggest single advance in the history since Galileo.''
   He likened it to giving astronomers 20-20 vision of the universe
after centuries of viewing it through 20-200 eyes.
   The Hubble will be released 380 miles above Earth after an
extensive checkout at the end of the shuttle's robot arm.
   Astronauts McCandless and Sullivan will be ready to make a space
walk should there be problems, such as a failure of the telescope's
electricity-producing solar panels to extend. The telescope can
remain on its internal battery power for only five hours.
   The telescope's release is scheduled for 29 hours after liftoff
and will be seen by television beamed to the ground. Discovery will
fly escort at a distance of 46 miles for nearly two days until a
10-foot-diameter cover is successfully opened to expose the
telescope's instruments to space.
   The telescope is expected to be in operation for at least 15
years, with periodic servicing by visiting astronauts. Some 50
parts are designed to be swapped out during periodic maintenance in
orbit.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0046 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 1706EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Nepal 3rdLd-Writethru a0716 04-08 0880</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Nepal, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0716,0903</SECOND>
<HEAD>King Announces Multiparty System, Lifts 29-Year-old Ban on Parties</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 11 grafs to UPDATE with elections to be held soon,
opposition ending protest movement, quotes from opposition leader,
foreign minister; pickup graf 6 pvs, `The opposition...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By VIJAY JOSHI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>KATMANDU, Nepal (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   King Birendra on Sunday caved in to
demands by pro-democracy leaders, establishing a multiparty system
and lifting a 29-year-old ban on political parties following the
bloodiest day in Nepal's modern history.
   The stunning announcement was carried on government-run
television in a special broadcast at 11 p.m. It was preceded by
several hours of talks between opposition leaders and the Harvard
University-educated monarch.
   According to the announcement, the king removed the word
``partyless'' from the preamble of the constitution and scrapped an
act that banned political parties.
   Foreign Minister Pashupati Rana said elections for the National
Assembly would be held soon, but he gave no date. In an apparent
deal, the opposition said it would end its 50-day-old protest
movement.
   Several residents celebrated by climbing onto rooftops shouting
``Victory, victory!'' Others switched on all the lights in their
houses.
   Open street demonstrations were limited due to a 24-hour curfew,
which Rana said would remain in effect until Monday.
   While an announcer read the proclamation from the royal palace,
the television showed scenes of the king meeting leaders of the
Nepali Congress Party, outlawed for the last 29 years. The party
was a leader of the recent protests.
   ``We talked with the king for an hour at the royal palace and
the talks were very, very cordial,'' said Kirshna Prasad Bhattrai,
a Nepali Congress leader. Pro-democracy leaders had expressed
pessimism earlier in the day.
   ``This will be the advent of human rights and freedom of speech
in Nepal,'' said Sahana Pradhan, a member of the Congress and the
only woman opposition leader to meet the king.
   ``The most important person in the country has made a most
important decision,'' Rana told The Associated Press. ``This is not
a concession. It is a natural process of answering the will of the
people.''
   Still, many questions remained. Despite the promise of
elections, no mention was made of reforming the National Assembly,
or Rashtriya Panchayat, a largely rubber stamp body. The king still
has almost absolute power. Several hundred political prisoners
remain in jail.
   The opposition victory came two days after security forces
unleashed the bloodiest attack in more than a century. Witnesses
said as many as 200 people were killed when police opened fire on a
crowd of 200,000 pro-democracy demonstrators, but the government
said only 10 people died and 107 were wounded. The government then
imposed a curfew Friday night.
   Shoes, slippers, glass and rocks still littered the streets
Sunday.
   The protest occurred during a general strike called by the the
Nepali Congress and a coalition of leftist parties, who launched
the campaign for multiparty democracy seven weeks ago.
   Not since 1846 when feuding members of the royal household
battled had this peaceful kingdom in the mountains and valleys of
the majestic Himalayas seen such bloodshed.
   Before the king's announcement, the U.S. Embassy issued a
warning to American tourists in Katmandu, advising them to leave
the country. The statement noted that a British citizen was among
the dead Friday.
   The king's decision came after talks between the new Prime
Minister Lokendra Bahadur Chand, a relative moderate, and
opposition leaders on Saturday and Sunday. Chand was given his job
last week after hard-line Prime Minister Marich Man Shrestha
resigned.
   ``The process had been continuing since last evening. There was
an agreement on how to go about it today,'' said Yog Prasad
Upadhyaya, a senior Nepali Congress leader. Earlier, he had said
the talks were stalemated.
   A number of members of the National Assembly made impassioned
appeals for a multiparty system. Then Sunday night opposition
leaders began to claim victory.
   The kingdom's only experiment with Western-style democracy
lasted less than two years and was halted in 1961 when Birendra's
father, King Mahendra, dismissed the Nepali Congress government,
accusing it of corruption and inefficiency.
   Since then, political parties have been banned and the king has
ruled in conjunction with a legislature called the Rashtriya
Panchayat, or National Assmbly.
   Birendra, 44, is the heir of the Shaha dynasty that has held the
throne since the middle of the 18th century. Many Nepalis,
especially illiterate farmers who comprise the bulk of this
country's 17 million people, view him as the reincarnation of the
Hindu god, Shiva.
   There have been demonstrations for greater democracy in the
past, but the support has come mainly from university students and
limited circles of activists. The current campaign broadened to
strikes by doctors, airline pilots and even employees of government
banks and some ministries.
   The government lifted the curfew in a few northern districts for
two hours Sunday morning, but the rest of the city and the two
suburbs of Patan and Bhaktapur remained under strict curfew.
   Soldiers with rifles and machine guns were posted at all
intersections, including the narrow streets that wind through
residential areas. An occasional armored car was seen and army
trucks loaded with troops sped up and down the streets.
   Sunday is a normal working day in Nepal, and Saturday is the
weekly holiday.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0047 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 1808EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-White-Reax 1stLd-Writethru a0740 04-08 0618</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-White-Reax, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0740,0632</SECOND>
<HEAD>Americans Pay Tribute to AIDS Victim Ryan White</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 11 grafs to RECAST lead, CORRECT actress' name to
`Judith,' sted `Linda,' tighten. Bridgete is cq in 6th graf,
`White's schoolmates ...'</NOTE>
<HEAD>With AM-Obit-White, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Americans joined Sunday in grieving for Ryan White, who died at
age 18 after a courageous fight against AIDS and the ignorance,
fear and prejudice it engendered.
   ``He called upon us all to educate one another, and to hate the
virus itself and the ignorance surrounding AIDS, instead of hating
each other,'' said Dr. Woodrow A. Myers Jr., former Indiana state
health commissioner.
   Myers, who held that job during White's long court battle to
return to public school, said White's death meant ``the nation has
lost one of its major leaders ... a major spokesperson on the
disease.''
   Former President Reagan, who was with his wife, Nancy, at
White's last public appearance March 26 in Los Angeles, said White
was ``a very brave young man'' and extended his family's sympathy
and prayers to the Whites.
   ``Although his courageous battle has reached its end, Ryan is
now safe in the arms of God,'' Reagan said. ``He and his family
stand as a symbol of the need for greater tolerance and
understanding toward those afflicted with AIDS.''
   White's schoolmates at Hamilton Heights High in Arcadia were
stunned by his death. ``It's sad,'' said sophomore Bridgete Benson,
15. ``When I first heard about it, I didn't believe it. I didn't
think he'd die.''
   ``We weren't the best of friends,'' said freshman Aaron Gilmore,
15, ``but I'm shocked that he died. I hoped they could find a cure
before it was over.
   ``He was aware of what could happen. But I remember him saying
that he's going to live for five years until they find a cure. And
if they didn't, he'd live for five more, and keep going until they
find a cure,'' he said.
   Wayne Kitch, superintendent of the Hamilton Heights School
Corp., said no decision had been made on what special activities
might be conducted at the school Monday, when classes resume after
spring vacation.
   ``Ryan was a real inspiration to us,'' Kitch said. ``It's a real
sorrow and sadness that he passed away, for our school system and
our community.''
   Actress Judith Light, who played White's mother, Jeanne, in a
television movie of his life, voiced her sympathy for her and her
daughter, Andrea.
   ``Ryan has already, in his brief lifetime, contributed more
nobility and dignity to the world than many people do in many
decades,'' said the actress, a star of the hit television series
``Who's the Boss.''
   Indiana Gov. Evan Bayh ordered flags at the Statehouse flown at
half-staff Wednesday, the day White's funeral is planned.
   ``Ryan was an American hero,'' Bayh told Mrs. White in a letter
Sunday. ``His life has become an international symbol of the
tragedy that is AIDS, and of the fight for understanding and hope
that its victims face daily.''
   Bayh said he hoped the family would find consolation ``in the
fact that had the world not known Ryan White, our understanding,
treatment and concern for people with AIDS would be harsher and
more judgmental.''
   White's lawyer, Charles Vaughn, was en route to Indianapolis on
Sunday when he learned of White's death.
   ``He was the looking glass to stop discrimination against people
with AIDS,'' Vaughn said. ``He went through his case more for
others, so that they wouldn't have to endure, than he did for
himself. He didn't want anyone else to have to go through what he
had to.
   ``He fought it to the end,'' Vaughan said. ``There was no quit
in Ryan White.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0048 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 1819EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brites     04-08 0442</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brites,0461</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bright and Brief</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BURBANK, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Many residents of the sleepy
neighborhoods near the Walt Disney Co. are grumpy over the towering
additions to the company's new headquarters building.
   It's all very well for 6-foot-tall Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles
to run wild in the comics and movies, they say.
   It's something else when the Seven Dwarfs mutate into 19-foot
giants draped across the company's corporate headquarters in
Burbank, where movie studios proliferate next to rows of neat
bungalows on tree-lined avenues.
   In 1937, the curtain parted for Disney's animated classic,
``Snow White and the Seven Dwarfs,'' in which Happy, Grumpy,
Sleepy, Sneezy, Dopey, Bashful and Doc starred with Snow White.
   Next week, a huge veil comes down at the headquarters to reveal
them again, standing at the third-story level, appearing to hold up
the fifth-story roof.
   ``Obviously Disney always does things their own way, with a
flair for the dramatic,'' said Burbank planning board member Jeff
Vander Borght, who lives nearby. ``But I'm afraid it's totally out
of scale for the neighborhood.''
   Alan Epstein, vice president of Disney Development Corp., and
Burbank's city planner, Rick Pruetz, said the building conforms
strictly to city codes, so no public hearings were held on the
design.
   That's a pity, said Vander Borght.
   ``It gives a whole new meaning to the word dwarf,'' he said.
``Stretch dwarfs. We're going to be known as the city of the huge
dwarfs.''
   Founder Walt Disney allowed no identification of the company on
the studio property. Only after his death in 1966 did his Mickey
Mouse creation sprout atop the studio lot's water tower.
   ``Walt didn't want tourists popping in to interfere with
production,'' said a longtime employee, who spoke on condition of
anonymity. ``And he didn't want people mistakenly believing that
Disneyland was in Burbank.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>HARTFORD, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two union workers who took part in a
strike at a Colt Manufacturing Co. plant that lasted more than four
years celebrated the end of the walkout by exchanging vows.
   Ed Vargas, a justice of the peace, called it a ``marriage made
in union heaven.''
   ``We waited until the end of the strike,'' said Carmen Diaz, 42,
who was married to David Burnham, 45, in front of a surprised,
cheering crowd at a United Auto Workers celebration Saturday
evening.
   Diaz said she couldn't have picked a better place to hold the
ceremony than with her union buddies.
   The strike, which began on Jan. 24, 1986, officially ended March
22 when a buyout agreement was announced which makes the striking
workers co-owners of the plant along with Colt managers, the state
of Connecticut and private investors.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0049 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 1830EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Shriver-NBC     04-08 0438</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Shriver-NBC,0453</SECOND>
<HEAD>Maria Shriver Quits ``Sunday Today'' But Stays With NBC</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JAY SHARBUTT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Television Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Maria Shriver returned Sunday to co-anchor NBC's
``Sunday Today'' only to say she's leaving. She cited travel and
motherhood as reasons.
   Shriver, who is married to actor Arnold Schwarzenegger, gave
birth to their first child, a daughter, in December.
   On her return from maternity leave, she told viewers that Sunday
was her last day on the show she has co-anchored since its
inception in 1987.
   She also will be giving up her anchor job on the Saturday
edition of ``NBC Nightly News,'' but will stay at NBC News, doing a
series of prime-time news specials and special segments for NBC's
weeknight news program.
   No replacement for her in either anchor job was immediately
announced.
   Published reports have speculated that Mary Alice Williams, who
also recently returned from maternity leave, will succeed Shriver
on the Sunday show. But NBC spokeswoman Peggy Hubble declined to
comment on that.
   ``We're in discussions with Mary Alice about her role at NBC and
we'll have an announcement later,'' Hubble said Sunday.
   Shriver, a former ``CBS Morning News'' co-anchor, joined NBC in
1986, then worked out an unusual arrangement with NBC News that
permitted her to be a bi-coastal anchor.
   Under this arrangement, she could live with her millionaire
husband in Los Angeles and commute from there each week to anchor
Saturday's ``Nightly News'' in New York, to co-anchor ``Sunday
Today'' in Washington with Garrick Utley, and to work on occasional
specials.
   ``Having a child, I realized I could no longer keep up my weekly
commute from Los Angeles,'' Shriver said in a statement.
   She praised NBC for letting her stay as a ``vital member'' of
the news division while giving her more time to spend with her
family in Los Angeles.
   ``It's difficult giving up my two coveted roles ... but I'm very
excited about my new prime-time assignment,'' she said.
   Williams, one of Cable News Network's original anchors before
joining NBC last year, has said she's unhappy about what she feels
is NBC News' inability to make full use of her on the air,
according to a source close to the situation who spoke on condition
of anonymity.
   But Williams, who lives in New York, has refused to discuss her
unhappiness with reporters. In a March 27 appearance on CNBC's
``McLaughlin'' talk show, she said she considers it ``tacky'' to
discuss her negotiations in public.
   However, she did say that her NBC contract contains a ``window''
that lets her leave the news division under certain conditions. She
did not elaborate.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0050 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 1859EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-EastGermany 1stLd-Writethru a0714 04-08 0705</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-East Germany, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0714,0722</SECOND>
<HEAD>Proposed New Government Begins Taking Shape in East Germany</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 12 grafs to UPDATE with talks breaking off, no
accord; pickup graf 9 pvs `Christian Democrat...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By MARK FRITZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>EAST BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Christian Democrat leader Lothar de Maiziere
failed Sunday to form East Germany's first democratic government
after a grueling round of talks with other parties.
   The breakdown in talks came after Christian Democrat leaders
said de Maiziere already had drawn up a proposed Cabinet that would
have brought together the nation's leading political factions.
   Despite widespread optimism that an agreement was near,
Christian Democrats and the rival Social Democrats ended five hours
of discussions with no accord.
   De Maiziere leads a three-party conservative alliance that holds
the most seats in the 400-member Parliament but was trying to build
a coalition broad enough to control the legislature.
   A two-thirds majority is needed to enact constitutional changes
that would clear the way to unification with West Germany, the main
issue in the East Germany's first free elections on March 18.
   An alliance with the Social Democrats would give de Maiziere
control. But if negotiations with that party fail, his alliance has
enough seats to build coalitions with other parties and still
secure control of Parliament.
   Richard Schroeder, a leading Social Democrat lawmaker, said
after talks broke off that his party still hoped to join de
Maiziere's government.
   The Christian Democrats and the Social Democrats differ on the
pace of reunification and the role and makeup of an East German
government, which faces dire economic problems but which also is
likely to be a short-lived transitional government.
   The left-leaning Social Democrats, who finished second in the
elections, were demanding that the Christian Democrats use their
close connections with West German Chancellor Helmut Kohl to obtain
a copy of West Germany's proposed blueprint for reunification.
   The treaty being discussed in Bonn would set out the laws that
would be applied in a unified Germany, in effect outlining the
terms for combining their social and economic structures.
   De Maiziere is a close ally of Kohl's, but many East German
leaders fear that the country will not have enough say in the terms
of the nations' eventual merger.
   The two major parties and a smaller alliance of liberal
lawmakers began meeting Sunday after a long set of talks the night
before.
   Christian Democrat leaders indicated that a new government would
be formed soon. But before the talks began, Social Democrat leader
Markus Meckel stressed that issues were unresolved and that talks
on forming a new government were not likely to end on Sunday.
   Christian Democrat lawmaker Martin Kirchner said late Saturday
that a proposed list of Cabinet members already had been compiled,
with de Maiziere as premier, or prime minister.
   The Christian Democrats would have 11 posts; the Social
Democrats would have six; a liberal alliance and the
ultra-conservative German Social Union would have three each; and
the Democratic Awakening would have one ministry.
   The Christian Democrats, Democratic Awakening and the German
Social Union all form the conservative alliance led by de Maiziere.
   The Social Democrats have protested the German Social Union's
policies and have opposed its presence in a new government.
   The Social Democrats also favor a more gradual form of
reunification than the swift pace proposed by the Christian
Democrats.
   The new Parliament, which met for the first time last week, is
expected to grapple with allegations that some members had ties to
the former secret police of the ousted Communist regime of former
leader Erich Honecker.
   A report in the West German newspaper Bild on Sunday alleged
that a former East German activist who was deported by the old
Communist government two years ago was actually a secret police
informant.
   Ralph Hirsch, now an aviser to West Berlin Mayor Walter Momper,
denied the allegations as ``slander.'' Momper defended Hirsch and
criticized the report based on the allegations of an unidentified
former secret police agent.
   Two prominent East German leaders, including former Social
Democrat leader Ibrahim Boehme, have resigned in recent months amid
similar allegations, which they denied. De Maiziere also has denied
allegations he had ties to the secret police, known as the Stasi.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0051 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 1906EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-GreyhoundArrest     04-08 0373</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Greyhound Arrest,360</SECOND>
<HEAD>Replacement Driver Arrested After Brandishing Rifle</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ANITA WOMACK</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A replacement driver for Greyhound Bus Lines
was charged Sunday with carrying a dangerous weapon after he
brandished a rifle during a confrontation with striking bus
workers, officials said.
   Charles E. King, 45, had just returned to the Washington
terminal Saturday evening after a trip and was leaving at about
midnight to go home when he discovered that his personal vehicle
had been vandalized, George Gravley, a company spokesman said from
his Dallas headquarters.
   ``He (King) came back and told his boss that his car had been
vandalized, and the manager began making phone calls,'' Gravley
said. ``King, upset, decided that things were not happening fast
enough and went to get a weapon out of his truck and confronted
picketers.''
   Witnesses said King retrieved the weapon from under the front
seat of the vehicle and began threatening them with it. But a copy
of the police report obtained from Gravely states that King, a
Clinton, Md., resident, held the unloaded weapon at port arms, or
diagonally across his chest.
   Keith Bullock, 31, said he had just arrived at the bus terminal
to begin picketing when the confrontation began.
   An off-duty district police officer who also works as a security
guard at the bus terminal heard the commotion and came to
investigate, Bullock said.
   ``The police officer identified himself and ordered him (King)
to drop the weapon,'' Bullock said. ``The officer repeated the
command two more times. The guy looked like he was going to use the
butt of the weapon and hit me when the officer said it again and he
(King) handed it over.'' The name of the officer was not
immediately available.
   No shots were fired and no one was injured, Gravley said.
   The windows of King's truck were broken out and the tires
flattened, Bullock said. ``He had every right to be upset, but he
had no right to pick out one person,'' Bullock said.
   There have been reports of sporadic violence and shootings since
Greyhound drivers went on strike. The company blames the union and
says there will be no contract talks until a week goes by with no
violence.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0052 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 1905EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AppomattoxSurrenderRecreated     04-08 0461</FIRST>
<SECOND>Appomattox Surrender Recreated</SECOND>
<BYLINE>By DAVID REED</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>APPOMATTOX, Va. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   About 4,000 volunteers dressed as Union
and Confederate soldiers Sunday marked the 125th anniversary of the
end of the Civil War by recreating Gen. Robert E. Lee's solemn
surrender to Gen. Ulysses S. Grant.
   Nearly 8,000 spectators, some wearing bonnets and hoopskirts
from 1865, stood behind wooden fences along the old stage road
through Appomattox Court House National Historic Park.
   There was scattered applause and a few rebel yells as a man
playing Confederate Gen. John Gordon rode a stocky chestnut horse
in front of a column of rebel soldiers marching four abreast
between Union troops with shouldered arms.
   After Appomattox, more than a month went by before the remaining
Confederate armies surrendered and a few isolated forces west of
the Mississippi River laid down their arms. But historians agree
that Lee's surrender ended the War Between the States for all
intents and purposes.
   The re-enactment took place in the isolated, reconstructed
central Virginia village where the war ended after four devastating
years. Most of the volunteers playing Rebel and Yankee men in
uniform were grim.
   ``It's a solemn occasion,'' said Joe Pitts of Winston-Salem,
N.C. ``We don't particularly care for it, and the troops back then
didn't care for it.''
   One young Confederate wept as he stacked his rifle in one of the
teepee-style piles along the dirt road winding through the region's
rolling hills.
   ``You get into what the soldiers felt back then,'' said Lake Day
of Jacksonville, Fla. ``To subject yourself to surrender is tough.''
   The volunteers said they were saddened this was the last major
re-enactment of the anniversary battles they have recreated during
the past four years. A few said they planned to quit the expensive
hobby after this.
   The re-enactors ranged in age from pre-teens to septuagenarians,
and came from across the United States, Canada and Europe.
   Pitts said they tried to depict the surrender at Appomattox
exactly as the ragged, starving soldiers went through it.
   ``It can't be totally correct; we can't be emaciated like they
were,'' he said.
   The re-enactment also was a few days off, and the sky was blue
rather than gray.
   The stacking of arms came on April 12, 1865, exactly four years
after the war started at Fort Sumter, S.C., and three days after
Lee surrendered to Gen. Grant at a private home on the edge of the
village.
   Terry Daley of Baltimore, who played Union Gen. Joshua
Chamberlain, said his order for his men to present arms as 27,800
Confederate soldiers surrendered, ``helped heal our wounds.''
   ``At the sound of a bugle, Chamberlain paid the highest tribute
you can to an adversary; it was to show we are brothers and
Americans,'' Daley said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0053 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 1923EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Hungary-Elections 3rdLd-Writethru a0739 04-08 0915</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Hungary-Elections, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0739,0951</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<HEAD>Conservatives Gain Overwhelming Victory</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS thruout with conservatives winning, 90 percent of votes
counted, quotes from winning party, EDITS to conform</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto BP6</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GEORGE JAHN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUDAPEST, Hungary (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Voters choosing Hungary's first freely
elected government in 43 years gave an overwhelming victory Sunday
to Hungary's main conservative party.
   ``I am completely certain that we won the elections,''
Democratic Forum President Jozsef Antall told jubilant supporters
crowding party headquarters six hours after polls closed.
   ``But it is not we, but the Hungarian people who have won these
elections,'' he said.
   Final results for the 261 parliamentary seats at stake in runoff
elections Sunday were not expected before Tuesday. But state
television showed the conservative Hungarian Democratic Forum
winning 41.8 percent of the vote, or 116 seats, with more than 90
percent of the votes counted.
   Their closest rivals, the liberal Alliance of Free Democrats,
won 21 percent of the vote, or 58 seats.
   The agrarian-based Smallholders party won 29 districts with 11.5
percent of the vote, while reform Communists grouped in the
Socialist Party had won 18 with 8 percent.
   Eight seats were still not determined.
   It was the second conservative sweep in Eastern Europe in as
many free elections. East Germans gave conservatives a clear
victory in elections on March 18, relegating the Communists to an
opposition role.
   In Hungary, 171 of the 261 seats were voted on directly Sunday.
Ninety seats will be determined on the voting percentage each party
receives.
   With 43 seats won by Democratic Forum candidates in the first
round March 25, the party had a total of 159 seats after both
rounds, according to the preliminary calculations based on 90
percent returns.
   The Free Democrats had 92 seats, while the Smallholders had 44
and the Socialists 32. Others seats were shared by two smaller
parties.
   There are 394 seats in Parliament, including eight seats to be
allocated to national minorities.
   Democratic Forum President Antall turned 58 Sunday, and a rare
smile creased his face as he was presented with a gigantic boquet
of flowers.
   The early conservative advantage forced a concession from Free
Democrat leader Miklos Haraszti.
   ``It is clear that the HDF will gain the most seats,'' he said.
   Elections two weeks ago left 261 of the National Assembly's 394
seats undecided. That balloting gave no party an outright majority
but relegated the former Communists to fourth place.
   No party was considered strong enough to win a majority in
Sunday's polling and a coalition government was expected. More than
7.5 million people were eligible to vote.
   Both front-running parties, the Democratic Forum and the Free
Democrats, have refused to consider forming a government with the
former Communists.
   Most polls closed at 6 p.m. after 12 hours of voting. State
television began its 24-hour election program two hours later with
preliminary estimates of a more than 40 percent turnout nationwide,
indicating that more than 3.25 million people voted.
   Many Hungarians seemed weary after the second round of balloting
in two weeks.
   ``It's clear that people have become tired,'' Interim President
Matyas Szueros told reporters before casting his ballot. ``It's
time to end the election process.''
   The voting was generally uneventful, with few irregularities
reported.
   In Debrecen, about 90 miles west of the capital of Budapest,
several polling stations did not open on time because supervisory
officials were late, state radio reported.
   One station first opened at 9 a.m., three hours past schedule.
The radio said the delay was caused by the chief supervisor who
called in to say he would be late because ``he was tired.''
   Voters at a polling station in Budapest shook out umbrellas
after walking in from the rain, and many clutched pussy willows
symbolic in Hungary of Easter.
   Many said they were enthusiastic about voting in the national
elections, but others appeared skeptical that a new government
would be able to solve Hungary's severe economic problems that
include a declining living standard, double-digit inflation,
growing unemployment and a $20 billion foreign debt.
   ``I'm here, I'm voting but I don't have any confidence in it,''
said Ernoe Horvath, a 61-year old retiree. ``Even now we don't have
people (running) that we can trust.''
   The first round of elections on March 25 put the Hungarian
Democratic Forum and the liberal Alliance of Free Democrats in the
lead, but neither party polled a majority, forcing Sunday's second
round.
   Democratic Forum captured 24.73 percent in the earlier election,
the Free Democrats, 21.39 percent, the agrarian-oriented
Smallholders Party 11.73 percent and the Socialists 10.89 percent.
   The rest of the vote was scattered among 25 other parties.
   The Socialists were unique among ruling Soviet bloc parties in
leading their country to democracy without massive popular
pressure. But most people associate the party with the excesses of
43 years of Communist rule.
   The Free Democrats, who want to quickly scrap Hungary's command
economy in favor of a market economy, have warmed in recent weeks
to the possibility of a coalition with the Democratic Forum.
   But the Forum, which emphasizes traditional Christian values and
cautious economic change, has said it will only join forces with
the Free Democrats in a ``national emergency.''
   Antall refused to comment when asked Sunday about the
possibility of a coalition government with the Free Democrats.
   But Free Democrat leader Janos Kis said that ``a grand coalition
is a distinct possibility which we don't refuse because we are ...
for having a government with wide popular support.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0054 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 1937EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-CrackHouse     04-08 0339</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Crack House,0350</SECOND>
<HEAD>Three Suspects Arrested in Crack House Shootings</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DETROIT (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Police investigating the gangland-style slayings
of six people at a reputed crack house arrested two men and an
18-year-old woman who is accused of being the head killer,
authorities said Sunday.
   Tamara Marie Marshall, 18, of Detroit was arrested Saturday in
the city's worst mass slaying in 19 years. The two other suspects,
ages 19 and 20, were arrested Sunday, said police spokesman John
Leavens.
   All three were arrested without incident, he said.
   The names of the two men were withheld until warrants were
issued. All three were expected to be arraigned Monday on six
counts of murder, Leavens said.
   Police denied that the killings were motivated by a soured love
affair between Marshall and one of the victims, Steven Owens, 32.
   ``It was nothing more than a robbery of a suspected drug house.
This is not about a jilted lover, this is not about a drug war.
This crime was committed for financial gain and that is all there
is,'' said Inspector Gerald Stewart.
   Magistrate Irma Chenevert said she signed an arrest warrant
Friday charging Marshall with leading the massacre and using a
firearm during a felony.
   Witnesses said a woman and two men burst into the two-story
bungalow Wednesday night, forced the victims to lie on the floor
and shot them in the head.
   Found dead on a floor upstairs in the two-story bungalow were
Owens; Carl D. Williams, 21; Bobby Lee Frazier, 16; and Robert Lee
Hill, 15; all of Detroit, police said. Each had been shot in the
head.
   Two victims were found in the basement. LeVon Robinson, 18, died
shortly after arriving at Detroit Receiving Hospital; Rodney Lewis,
22, died at the hospital Thursday night.
   A neighbor said the home where the slayings occurred was one of
a number of crack houses in the area.
   Detroit's previous worst mass shooting was in June 1971, when
seven members of a heroin ring were found shot to death in a
west-side apartment.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0055 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 1936EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-PrisonRiots 1stLd-Writethru a0731 04-08 0701</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Prison Riots, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0731,0720</SECOND>
<HEAD>Unrest in Eight Prisons as Inmates Hold Out at Strangeways</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS lead and INSERTS one graf after 13th `At Horfield..' to
UPDATE with disturbance at youth prison; pickup graf 14 `At
Cardiff...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By LESLIE SHEPHERD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Unrest broke out in eight prisons in England and
Wales on Sunday, and one government official said the incidents
were inspired by the 8-day-old rebellion at Strangeways Prison. One
inmate was found dead in his cell.
   The government said it was too dangerous to forcibly end the
siege at Strangeways in the north-central city of Manchester
because of the condition of the largely demolished prison buildings.
   Only 22 of the hundreds of Strangeways inmates who rioted on
April 1 remain on the loose, authorities said. The overcrowded
prison was heavily damaged when inmates set fires and hurled roof
tiles at guards and firefighters.
   In Dartmoor prison in southwest England inmates hurled chunks of
roofing into the prison courtyard and set fires in their cells,
prison governor John May said.
   Almost 100 prisoners barricades themselves into one wing of the
prison, but all but one had given up by Sunday night.
   After the rioting was contained, the body of a prisoner was
found in a fire-damaged cell, May said.
   He refused to give any other details and said it was unknown
when the fire occurred.
   Home Office Minister David Mellor said the dead prisoner was
severely burned and pledged that inmates responsible for the wave
of unrest would be prosecuted for any criminal offenses.
   May said the prisoners at Dartmoor were protesting prison food
and their isolation from their families. Guards blamed prison
conditions for the unrest at the prisons.
   But Mellor described the Dartmoor disturbances as ``a copycat
incident'' in the wake of the Strangeways riot.
   He said the unrest was quickly contained because prison guards
had advanced warning that their could be trouble in the prison.
   The prison was opened in 1809 to house French prisoners from the
Napoleonic wars and is perched on the remote and rugged moorland of
Devonshire, 160 miles southwest of London. Cold and damp, despite
its central heating, the prison is almost always cloaked in mist.
   At Horfield prison in Bristol, western England, 150 to 200
prisoners appeared to have taken control of the A Wing, a prison
spokesman said. Two officers were injured, he said, and ``we sent
in a cordon of officers to secure the perimeter.''
   At the Stoke Heath young offenders institution in central
England, 15 to 20 youths climbed onto the roof and 12 more refused
to come out of the gymnasium, police said. The Home Office said
firefighters extinguished bedding fires at the center, which houses
360 offenders under age 21.
   At Cardiff jail in Wales, about 130 of the prison's 205 inmates
rioted, smashing furniture, breaking windows and setting bedding on
fire, a spokesman said.
   At Leeds Jail in northern England, prisoners staged a sit-down
protest in their exercise yard Sunday morning.
   A handful of prisoners staged a similar protest at Brixton Jail
in south London, and three prison officers were treated in a
hospital for cuts and bruises after they forced prisoners to return
to their cells.
   At a prison in Hull in the northeast of England, 110 prisoners
tried to rush the compound gates after exercises. Guards restrained
the inmates.
   In an apparently minor incident at London's Pentonville Prison,
300 prisoners were evacuated when an inmate pulled a gas pipe from
the wall.
   ``I think the system has reached the point where it could well
prove to collapse unless the problems that are endemic within the
system are attended to very quickly,'' said David Evans, general
secretary of the Prison Officers' Association.
   He said British penal institutions suffered from ``overcrowding,
staff shortages and poor conditions.''
   But Mellor disagreed and said the unrest did not reflect
deficiencies in the system, but that ``something is fundamentally
wrong with a number of prisoners.''
   ``A prison system will always been an unstable place because
people are not sent to prison for behaving responsibly,'' Mellor
said.
   ``They're sent to prison for behaving irresponsibly, and some
people, alas, will always continue to behave irresponsibly.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0056 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 1942EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Obit-Davis     04-08 0131</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Davis,0137</SECOND>
<HEAD>Pepper Davis, Well-Known Vegas Comic Dead at 66</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LAS VEGAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Pepper Davis, a former vaudevillian and a
well-known Las Vegas comedian who appeared on the television crime
drama ``Vega$,'' has died at age 66.
   Davis, who died Friday at a Las Vegas hospital, settled in the
desert resort city in 1962, working with Tony Reese as the comedy
team Davis and Reese. The duo opened for many Vegas acts before
Davis went solo.
   The Baltimore native's early career included stints as a jazz
drummer and tap dancer.
   He also played Manny the mechanic on ``Vega$,'' and was involved
in numerous charity causes in Las Vegas over the years.
   He is survived by his wife, Judy Asner of Las Vegas, one
daughter, three sons and seven grandchildren.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0057 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 2036EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-SloveniaElections 1stLd-Writethru a0724 04-08 0670</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Slovenia Elections, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0724,0693</SECOND>
<HEAD>Slovenia Holds First Free Elections in 45 Years</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 18 grafs with early presidential results; EDITS to
conform; pick up graf 17 pvs ```It is...'</NOTE>
<HEAD>With AM-Hungary, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DUSAN STOJANOVIC</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LJUBLJANA, Yugoslavia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Ex-Communist Milan Kucan and
conservative Joze Pucnik emerged Sunday as the top candidates for
Slovenia's presidency in the Yugoslavian republic's first free
multiparty elections since 1945.
   According to unofficial partial results, Kucan, a candidate of
the Democratic Renewal, formerly the Communists, received 40.2
percent of vote, while Pucnik, of the center-right DEMOS coalition,
won 26.8 percent.
   Election law requires a runoff on April 22 between the top two
candidates when no one receives more than 50 percent.
   ``I'm confident that I will win the runoff election,'' Pucnick
said. ``Many Slovenians link Kucan to Communism, and that is a
disadvatge for him.''
   Independent candidate Ivan Kramberger and Marko Demsar of the
Liberal Party received 21.5 and 10.5 percent, respectively, of the
100,000 votes counted.
   Kucan told reporters he hoped those who voted for Kramberger and
Demsar will give their votes to him in the runoff.
   About 75 percent of the 1.5 million registered voters, 18 years
and over, also voted for 240 seats in the new multiparty parliament.
   Official results from the republic's 4,130 polls were not
expected until Tuesday.
   Turnout was heavy, with voters lining up in front of the polling
stations despite heavy rain.
   Louis Sell, a U.S. Embassy spokesman who is monitoring the
elections along with four members of Congress, said ``the voting
seems to be extremely fair.''
   High school teacher Janez Toncic said he was excited as he cast
his ballot in Ljubljana. ``I never thought I would live to see the
day when we bury single-party monopoly in Slovenia,'' he said.
   Slovenia is the first of Yugoslavia's six republics to hold free
elections.
   Yugoslavia is a loose federation of six republics and two
autonomous provinces. It is ruled by an eight-man collective
presidency.
   Communist leaders have allowed the formation of opposition
parties in all of the republics, but only Croatia, the
second-largest republic, has also scheduled multiparty elections.
Those elections are planned for April.
   Communist leaders in Serbia, the largest republic, have demanded
Communist Party dominance and have harshly criticized the reforms
in Slovenia.
   Yugoslavian President, Janez Drnovsek, a Slovene, said after
voting in Ljubljana that he hoped the country ``will have the first
free elections for the federal parliament by the end of this year.''
   He said elections in Slovenia ``represent a sign of the
democracy drive that cannot be stopped in Yugoslavia.''
   The main issue in the presidential campaign were Slovenia's
future within the troubled Yugoslav federation and high inflation.
   Kucan said the voting showed that Slovenia was becoming a
Western European democracy.
   ``It is a pleasure to see people vote freely after so many
years,'' Kucan said. ``Slovenia is finally joining (West) European
democracy.''
   Kucan's closest rival was Pucnik, a former dissident and leader
of the DEMOS, a coalition of five pro-secession center-right
parties.
   ``The main task of the DEMOS is to oust Communists from power in
Slovenia and make parliamentary democracy work in the republic,''
Pucnik told reporters while voting in his native Slovenska Bistrica.
   Pucnik, a professor of philosophy, spent seven years in
Slovenian prisons during the 1950s for his opposition to communism.
He was forced into exile after his release from prison and first
returned to Yugoslavia in 1989.
   The makeup of the new Slovenian parliament could decide whether
the republic remains within Yugoslavia.
   Most of the 17 parties taking part in the parliamentary
elections urged Yugoslavia to become a loose confederation, but
some rightist parties want quick secession.
   Slovenians are increasingly pushing to secede from Yugoslavia
because they are unhappy with the slow pace of democratic and
economic reforms in the rest of the country.
   Slovenian reform-minded Communists have moved quickly over the
past three years to create a pluralistic system in the republic and
have shown considerable popularity in the electorate.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0058 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 2102EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-WeatherpageWeather     04-08 0240</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Weatherpage Weather,0248</SECOND>
<HEAD>Low-Temperature Records Broken From Arkansas to Kentucky</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Temperatures dropped to record lows Sunday morning in 22 cities
from Arkansas to Pennsylvania, and springtime snow fell in Nevada
and Pennsylvania.
   Rain extended from southern Idaho to northern Nevada and
northwest Utah, with rain changing to snow in the mountains. Rain
showers fell from central Texas to the lower Texas coast.
   Snow showers were scattered over central Pennsylvania, and
Austin, Nevada, received 5 inches of snow in the six hours ending
at 12 p.m. MDT.
   The spring cold snap broke low-temperature records for the date
up to 91 years old in 18 cities, including Elkins, W.Va., where a
reading of 16 degrees snapped by 1 degree the record set in 1975.
   Records were also broken in Apalachicola, Fla. (43 degrees, 46
in 1971); Mena, Ark. (28, 32 in 1899 and 1909); Birmingham, Ala.
(29, 32 in 1971); Nashville, Tenn. (27, 30 in 1936); and Richmond,
Va. (28, 29 in 1950).
   Parkersburg, Pa., where it was 24 degrees, was one of four
cities where low-temperature records were tied.
   The cold snap didn't end Sunday. Frost and freeze warnings for
Sunday night were posted in parts of inland North and South
Carolina.
   The low temperature for the Lower 48 states was 16 degrees at
Elkins, W.Va. Temperatures around the nation at 3 p.m. EDT ranged
from 34 degrees in Limestone, Maine, to 86 in Naples, Fla.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0059 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 2117EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Philippines-Reform 1stLd-Writethru a0691 04-08 0763</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Philippines-Reform, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0691,0785</SECOND>
<HEAD>Controversy Raises Doubts About Commitment To Land Reform</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP News Analysis</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS one graf for 12th graf `Lawmakers on...' to CORRECT to
Commission on Appointments, sted on Appoints; pickup graf 13
`Despite the...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT H. REID</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MANILA, Philippines (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The resignation of the land reform
secretary raises doubts about President Corazon Aquino's commitment
to agrarian reform and dramatizes conflicts in a government
criticized for lack of vision.
   The controversy climaxed Thursday with the resignation of
Secretary-designate Florencio Abad, 35, whose nomination was
opposed by the pro-Aquino Struggle of the Democratic Filipino Party.
   Handling of the controversy highlighted all the inconsistencies
for which Mrs. Aquino has been criticized: lack of clear
priorities; tactical blundering; and the strong influence of her
relatives over national policy.
   It also reinforced the suspicion among liberals that for all her
rhetoric, Mrs. Aquino does not share the deep commitment to social
change which they expected when she took power in the 1986 ``people
power'' uprising against the late Ferdinand Marcos.
   ``The sincerity of Corazon Aquino is being seriously
questioned,'' wrote columnist Ninez Cacho-Olivares in the
Philippine Daily Inquirer. Land reform, ``the centerpiece program
of her administration, is dead.''
   Abad's troubles began in February when he tried unsuccessfully
to block the lease of government land in Cavite province to Japan's
Marubeni Corp., for an industrial park.
   Although the deal was approved by the National Development
Corp., Abad, a former congressman, said the land should be
distributed to peasants under the agrarian reform program.
   The Department of Trade and Industry said the Marubeni deal was
crucial to attracting much-needed foreign investment for the
government's industrialization program.
   But the Department of Agrarian Reform said if the Cavite land
was exempted, hundreds of landlords would try to have their
property declared as a potential industrial site to avoid losing
title.
   The presidential staff finally worked out a compromise under
which farmers would be offered either land or a cash settlement.
Abad reluctantly agreed to the formula under repeated orders from
Mrs. Aquino.
   Abad's firm stand, however, alarmed landowners in Congress, who
floated rumors in the press that the Agrarian Reform Department was
riddled with Communists.
   Lawmakers on the Commission on Appointments who belong to the
pro-Aquino Struggle of the Democratic Filipino Party blocked Abad's
confirmation through eight hearings until he finally resigned.
   Despite the party's ``victory,'' poltical damage to it and Mrs.
Aquino was considerable. The Manila press transformed Abad into a
folk hero, depicting him as the champion of the farmer against
political barons of the Struggle of the Democratic Filipino Party,
dubbed ``Landlord-Dominated Party.''
   ``Worry not about Abad's destiny, Mrs. President,'' wrote
columnist Carol Arguillas in The Manila Chronicle. ``Worry about
yours and how you blew the last chance'' for liberal support.
   Mrs. Aquino pledged publicly to work for Abad's confirmation,
but her lobbying appeared ineffectual. Abad's strongest opponents
included politicians who consistently support Mrs. Aquino, leading
to speculation she was not disappointed when he departed.
   Abad's opponents included her younger brother, Rep. Jose
``Peping'' Cojuangco, who wields considerable influence in
government.
   ``There is no way Cory Aquino will challenge Peping,'' said one
Western diplomat, speaking on condition of anonymity.
   Mrs. Aquino comes from a landlord family. She and her brothers
and sisters are partners in a 14,500-acre sugar plantation in
Tarlac province. Rather than break up the estate, they used a legal
option and created a ``profit-sharing'' plan for the tenants.
   The Abad controversy was the latest in a series of blows to the
agrarian reform program, once touted as the ``centerpiece'' of the
administration.
   Last year, Agrarian Reform Secretary Philip Juico resigned after
disclosures that his department paid vastly inflated sums for
marginal land.
   His successor, Miriam Defensor Santiago, was repeatedly rejected
by the Commission on Appointments, only to be reappointed until
Mrs. Aquino replaced her with Abad on Dec. 31.
   No reason for the change was given. But Mrs. Santiago claims she
did not display sufficient public loyalty to Mrs. Aquino during a
coup attempt in early December.
   Agrarian reform was widely seen as a means for breaking the
power of landlord families and uplifting the livelihood of millions
of peasants. The program was advertised as essential in curbing the
21-year-old rural-based Marxist insurgency.
   Mrs. Aquino proclaimed a land reform program in 1987 but left
details to Congress. The final bill contained so many pro-landlord
loopholes that several of its original sponsors, including Abad,
voted against it.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Robert H. Reid has been the AP bureau chief in
Manila since September 1986.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0060 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 2126EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u p AM-TexasPolitics     04-08 0632</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Texas Politics,0652</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mattox Accuses Richards of Being Treated for Cocaine Addiction 10
Years Ago</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Texas Governor, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LAURA TOLLEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HOUSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Democratic gubernatorial candidate Jim Mattox
accused rival Ann Richards in an interview broadcast Sunday of
being treated for cocaine addiction 10 years ago, the latest in a
series of drug-use accusations.
   ``I'm saying that she used cocaine at the age of 46 and
marijuana, and she used other drugs,'' Mattox said in the interview
broadcast on CBS-TV's ``Face the Nation.'' The attorney general
said he obtained the information from mutual friends he declined to
identify.
   Ms. Richards phoned the program to deny she'd ever sought
treatment for cocaine use, but declined to appear on the show.
   A poll published Sunday showed Ms. Richards, the state
treasurer, and Mattox virtually deadlocked as they headed into
Tuesday's Democratic runoff. The winner will take on Republican
candidate Clayton Williams in the general election.
   In appearances at inner-city churches in Houston and Dallas, the
two candidates focused on their humble upbringings instead of the
drug charges and countercharges that have dominated the campaign.
   The appearance on ``Face the Nation'' marked the first time that
Mattox has accused Ms. Richards of requiring treatment for drug
use. In 1980, she was treated at a Minnesota clinic for alcoholism.
   Ms. Richards dismissed Mattox's charge Saturday, when word of
the pre-taped interview reached her.
   ``Jimmy's just going nuts,'' she said in Henderson.
   Last week, three people claimed they saw Mattox smoke marijuana
on separate occasions in the 1970s. Mattox denied the accusations.
   Ms. Richards has answered questions about illegal drug use by
saying she has not used a mood-altering drug in 10 years.
   She said Sunday she was sorry the campaign had become so
acrimonious, but Mattox said the campaign's bitterness would not
carry past Tuesday.
   ``We will be together in November because we have a common enemy
at that time, and that will be Clayton Williams,'' Mattox said.
   Williams also appeared on ``Face the Nation,'' and said he
wasn't sure whether he would dwell on drug allegations against the
Democratic candidates.
   ``They've really worked it over with each other. I don't see a
place for me to pick on them,'' he said. ``I'm going to be talking
about the real issues.''
   The poll published by the Houston Chronicle and The Dallas
Morning News showed Ms. Richards and Mattox running virtually
neck-and-neck.
   Of 759 Democrats who said they'd vote in the runoff, 44 percent
backed Ms. Richards and 38 percent Mattox, and 16 percent said they
were undecided, according to the poll. The telephone survey by the
University of Houston had a margin of error of 4 percentage points,
meaning a shift in the results could put Mattox ahead of Ms.
Richards.
   In Houston, Mattox told Baptist congregations he had considered
becoming a Baptist preacher while attending Baylor University.
   ``But I guess the worldly things got the best of me,'' said
Mattox, who became a lawyer before becoming involved in politics.
   He asked for help during the campaign's final days. ``We must do
more than just pray. We must get out and do the work, get out and
vote,'' Mattox said.
   At a predominantly black church in Dallas, Ms. Richards said her
election as governor would ``certainly be an announcement that
times have changed in Texas. And when they open the door to me,
they open it to all of you as well.''
   ``I'm not here to tell you that I know what it is like to be
denied opportunity because of my color,'' she said. ``But I am here
to tell you I know what it is like to be denied opportunity and
access to power and to the back room where decisions are made
because I was born female.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0061 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 2213EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-AppomattoxRe-enactment 1stLd-Writethru a0754 04-08 0496</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Appomattox Re-enactment, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0754,0507</SECOND>
<HEAD>Appomattox Surrender Recreated</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 14 grafs to CORRECT that surrender of Lee to Grant
not re-enacted; picks up penultimate graf, `Terry Daley ...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By DAVID REED</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>APPOMATTOX, Va. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   About 4,000 volunteers dressed as Union
and Confederate soldiers Sunday marked the 125th anniversary of the
end of the Civil War by recreating the solemn surrender of Gen.
Robert E. Lee's troops.
   Nearly 8,000 spectators, some wearing bonnets and hoopskirts
from 1865, stood behind wooden fences along the old stage road
through Appomattox Court House National Historic Park.
   There was scattered applause and a few rebel yells as a man
playing Confederate Gen. John Gordon rode a stocky chestnut horse
in front of a column of rebel soldiers marching four abreast
between Union troops with shouldered arms.
   After Appomattox, more than a month went by before the remaining
Confederate armies surrendered and a few isolated forces west of
the Mississippi River laid down their arms. But historians agree
that Lee's surrender to Gen. Ulysses S. Grant ended the War Between
the States for all intents and purposes.
   The re-enactment took place in the isolated, reconstructed
central Virginia village where the war ended after four devastating
years. Most of the volunteers playing rebel and Union men in
uniform were grim.
   ``It's a solemn occasion,'' said Joe Pitts of Winston-Salem,
N.C. ``We don't particularly care for it, and the troops back then
didn't care for it.''
   One young Confederate wept as he stacked his rifle in one of the
teepee-style piles along the dirt road winding through the region's
rolling hills.
   ``You get into what the soldiers felt back then,'' said Lake Day
of Jacksonville, Fla. ``To subject yourself to surrender is tough.''
   The volunteers said they were saddened this was the last major
re-enactment of the anniversary battles they have recreated during
the past four years. A few said they planned to quit the expensive
hobby after this.
   The re-enactors ranged in age from pre-teens to septuagenarians,
and came from across the United States, Canada and Europe.
   Pitts said they tried to depict the surrender at Appomattox
exactly as the ragged, starving soldiers went through it.
   ``It can't be totally correct; we can't be emaciated like they
were,'' he said.
   The re-enactment also was a few days off, and the sky was blue
rather than gray.
   The stacking of arms came on April 12, 1865, exactly four years
after the war started at Fort Sumter, S.C., and three days after
Lee surrendered to Gen. Grant at a private home on the edge of the
village. Lee's surrender was not re-enacted.
   Terry Daley of Baltimore, who played Union Gen. Joshua
Chamberlain, said his order for his men to present arms as 27,800
Confederate soldiers surrendered, ``helped heal our wounds.''
   ``At the sound of a bugle, Chamberlain paid the highest tribute
you can to an adversary; it was to show we are brothers and
Americans,'' Daley said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0062 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 2217EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-FerryFire 2ndLd-Writethru a0745 04-08 0953</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Ferry Fire, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0745,0974</SECOND>
<HEAD>Blaze Smolders While Firefighters Bring Out Bodies</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS one graf for 9th graf pvs `In Oslo...' to UPDATE with
American among missing and presumed dead, pickup graf 10 pvs, `Onso
said...'
^By DOUG MELLGREN</NOTE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LYSEKIL, Sweden (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Exhausted firefighters braved
metal-melting heat and poisonous smoke from a two-day-old fire
Sunday to begin removing bodies of about 150 victims from the
Scandinavian Star ferry.
   Firemen struggled to reach cabins where victims burned to death
or suffocated in the suspicious blaze. It began before dawn
Saturday while the ship was in the North Sea carrying about 500
tourists and crewmembers on an overnight trip from Norway to Demark.
   The heat was so intense Sunday that it melted aluminum aboard
the bridge of the Danish-owned ship. Firefighters in masks and
breathing equipment fought through one corridor ``until their gear
started to burn,'' said fire consultant Olle Wennstrom. One
firefighter was slightly injured, he said.
   Firemen were seen leaving the ship in tears during the night.
Each firefighting team underwent psychological care after being
relieved, officials said.
   The fire spread early Sunday from the gutted middle section to
the captain's bridge a few hours after the blackened ship was towed
into port. The blaze, which finally was extinguished late Sunday,
sent plumes of smoke over Lysekil, on Sweden's southwest coast 250
miles southwest of Stockholm, the capital on the east coast.
   Tugboats doused the ship with water. Holes were blasted into the
side of the 10,500-ton ship to allow the water to drain out, for
fear that the badly listing ship would topple onto the concrete
dock.
   Officials with VR-DANO Line, the company in Copenhagen that owns
and operates the Bahamian-flagged ship, say the blaze was caused by
arson, citing two fires that broke out at a short interval on two
different decks.
   District police chief Roar Onso, revising earlier figures, said
345 people survived the fire, which broke out about midway on the
ship's 10-hour voyage from Oslo to Frederikshavn. Ferry captain
Hugo Larsen told police of 395 passengers and 97 crewmen. If his
figure is correct, 147 people died, Osno said.
   In Oslo, police said six Americans of a seven-member
entertainment troupe performing on the Scandanavian Star were were
among the rescued. A seventh member, Ruth Rome, 27, of East
Lansing, Mich., was missing and presumed dead, said Rick Qualls,
another member of the group, from his Oslo hotel room.
   Onso said a burned passenger list was found in the debris but
did not tally with the captain's account, and its accuracy was
unclear.
   Forty-three bodies were removed from the the ferry before
operations were suspended for the night. After a brief ceremony on
the wharf, the victims were placed in a refrigerated truck and
driven to Oslo for identification.
   Tickets were sold to car passengers according to the size of the
car, not the number of people each was carrying. Children traveling
free would not appear on any passenger list.
   Firemen found corpses in the corridors and cabins. A few drivers
were found in their trucks on the car deck. Most victims were
asphyxiated but some were charred beyond recognition.
   ``It will be very difficult to identify the victims. It will
take a long time,'' Onso said.
   Onso confirmed reports that two fires broke out aboard the
Scandinavian Star, but he refused to speculate on how that fitted
with claims that the fire was deliberately set.
   One blaze started in a pile of sheets outside a cabin on a the
car deck but was smothered by passengers, he said. A second fire
started minutes later in a cabin one deck above the car deck, and
it was apparently this blaze that turned the ship into a floating
deathtrap.
   Onso said it would take several days to begin an on-site
investigation of possible arson. A commission of inquiry would be
set up to work parallel to a police probe.
   The first bodies emerged from the ship in metal containers. A
memorial service was planned in Oslo's main cathedral on Tuesday
for the Norwegians, who comprised most of the casualties.
   Fifty-two survivors who were picked up by a Soviet freighter
from lifeboats were kept in isolation under the care of
psychiatrists in Lysekil, 45 miles north of Goteborg.
   Relatives of the casualties began reaching the town of 8,000
people, and also were assisted by teams of psychiatrists and nurses.
   Passengers accused the crew of being untrained and ill prepared
for an emergency.
   The Danish Seamen's Union issued a harsh condemnation of the
behavior of the Danish captain and crewmen, who were mostly
Filipinos and Portuguese. It accused crewmen of abandoning ship
before evacuating passengers.
   ``Danish seamen would not leave a burning ship as long as there
were passengers on board,'' said union chairman Preben Moller
Hansen.
   Passengers spoke of chaos as the fire spread through the ship,
and little help from the crew who could not communicate with them.
Lifeboats were left dangling on the ship and life jackets were
unavailable, they said.
   In another ferry disaster, in Burma, one of only 25 survivors
rescued from a ferry that sank with about 240 people aboard said
the craft went down just minutes after a storm hit, the
government-owned Working People's Daily reported Sunday.
   The ferry capsized and sank in gale-force winds Friday while
carrying passengers on a southern Burmese river between the towns
of Moulmein and Kyondo. Official Burmese radio reports say at least
30 people drowned and 180 others are missing and feared dead.
   The newspaper said the accident on the Gyaing River was not due
to overloading. Frequent ferry boat accidents in Burma have been
due to overloading of passengers and cargo.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0063 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 2224EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-FatalFire     04-08 0254</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Fatal Fire,0264</SECOND>
<HEAD>Three Youngsters Die in Apartment Fire</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WESTMINSTER, Colo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A fire swept through an apartment in
this Denver suburb Sunday morning, killing three children and
injuring their mother, who screamed, ``Let it be a dream!'' Two
firefighters also suffered injuries.
   The mother, Debra Potter, 28, managed to escape and had to be
kept from running back into the building. She was hospitalized with
unspecified injuries.
   The fire broke out around 7:15 a.m., and was confined to the
two-story home in the apartment complex, officials said.
   Firefighters entered the apartment to try to rescue the
children, but were driven back by the intense heat, officials said.
One firefighter was injured by falling debris inside the building;
another suffered minor injuries.
   Killed were Steven Potter, 7, Kristina Potter, 5, and Daniel
Potter, 4, the Fire Department said.
   Witnesses said they heard a child screaming inside the house.
Mike Bannister, who lives in the complex, said he restrained Mrs.
Potter as she tried to return inside the building.
   ``She was outside running around, just running around
hysterically screaming,'' Bannister said. ``She was getting ready
to run back in, but I grabbed her because I realized it was just
too late.''
   Another neighbor, Ruth Santos, said Mrs. Potter was screaming,
``Let it be a dream! Let it be a dream!''
   The cause of the blaze was under investigation, said city Fire
Marshal Doug Hall.
   ``For now, this is nothing but an accidental fire,'' Hall said.
``We have no information to make any determination.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0064 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 2231EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Masters-Newspage     04-08 0242</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Masters-Newspage,0254</SECOND>
<HEAD>Faldo Wins 2nd Sudden-Death Masters</HEAD>
<DATELINE>AUGUSTA, Ga. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Englishman Nick Faldo beat Ray Floyd on the
second hole of a sudden-death playoff Sunday at the Masters
Tournament, duplicating exactly his win last year in the
prestigious tourney.
   ``I made history today,'' said Faldo, who joined Jack Nicklaus
as the only other person to win consecutive Masters.
   Faldo also won last year on the 11th hole in sudden death.
   He took home $225,000. Floyd, a 1976 Masters winner who at 47
was trying to become the oldest person to win in Augusta, made
$135,000.
   Both finished regulation play at 10-under-par 278. Faldo shot 69
Sunday, and Floyd a par 72.
   Faldo had to recover from a terrible start Sunday. He displayed
enormous patience and perserverance in his comeback, making up
three strokes on Floyd in the last four holes.
   He was also greatly helped by Floyd, who missed a makeable
birdie on the first playoff hole, No. 10, then put his second shot
into the water on No. 11.
   On the 11th, Faldo made par, turned to shake Floyd's hand, then
hugged his caddy.
   Floyd was devasted by his loss.
   ``The shot on the 11th was in the water the moment it left my
club,'' he said. ``It's the most devastating thing that has
happened to me in golf.
   ``I've lost before, but never like this. I've never had anything
affect me like this. I've never felt like this.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0065 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 2247EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u p AM-TexasGovernor 2ndLd-Writethru a0743 04-08 0834</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Texas Governor, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0743,0856</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mattox, Richards Down to the Wire In Texas Democratic Runoff</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS grafs 6-7, `Ms. Richards ...,' to CORRECT that Ms.
Richards virtually deadlocked with opponent, sted slightly ahead,
because of poll's margin of error.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By MICHAEL HOLMES</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>AUSTIN, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   As Ann Richards and Jim Mattox near the
finish in the Democratic runoff for governor, the issues have
disappeared under a cloud of personal attacks focusing on
accusations of illegal drug use by both candidates.
   The only ones seeming to enjoy it were Republicans, who
nominated oilman-rancher Clayton Williams last month in a landslide.
   ``The Democratic Veg-O-Matic primary is what I call it _ slice
and dice,'' said Karl Rove, a consultant. ``On the scale of more
vicious campaigns, this ranks near the top.''
   Mattox, who made an issue of Ms. Richards' refusal to answer
questions about drug use more than a decade ago, fended off
allegations again Saturday that he smoked marijuana in the 1970s.
   ``Jim Mattox has never used any kind of dangerous drug, ever,''
he said in Houston.
   Ms. Richards was virtually deadlocked with her rival before
Tuesday's runoff, according to a poll in Sunday's editions of The
Dallas Morning News and the Houston Chronicle. The winner will face
Williams in the November election to succeed retiring Gov. Bill
Clements, the only Republican governor in Texas in the past 100
years.
   The poll showed Ms. Richards backed by 44 percent of voters who
said they plan to vote in Tuesday's runoff, with Mattox drawing 38
percent, 16 percent undecided and 3 percent not supporting either
candidate. The poll of 759 voters by the Center for Public Policy
at the University of Houston has a margin of error of plus or minus
4 percentage points.l
   As election day neared, both candidates complained about the
campaign's direction.
   ``I feel badly for the electorate, really, that this campaign
has taken this tone,'' said Ms. Richards.
   ``We haven't talked nearly enough about the issues in this
campaign,'' said Mattox, who described the race as ``a full-contact
sport.''
   A sampling:
   _ Mattox claimed to have witnesses who saw Ms. Richards, a
recovering alcoholic, use drugs. But he wouldn't release their
names or any proof. Ms. Richards said, ``I don't know what he's
talking about.''
   _ Two newspapers reported allegations by a Houston lawyer and
former Dallas policeman that they had seen Mattox smoke marijuana
on separate occasions in the 1970s. Mattox said, ``Get those two
folks, sit them right here with me. I'll tell them they are liars
to their faces.''
   _ Ms. Richards aired a television commercial showing a cartoon
Mattox figure hurling mud patties at a photo of her holding her
granddaughter. An announcer says: ``He's at it again. The same old
politics. Mudslinging and negative campaigning.''
   _ Mattox aired a commercial that asked without offering
evidence, ``Did she use marijuana or something worse like cocaine?
Not as a college kid but as a 47-year-old elected official sworn to
uphold the law?''
   _ Ms. Richards said Mattox had profited from public service and
wanted to ``cover up'' a $200,000 payment from a Dallas developer
indicted for racketeering. She also ripped Mattox's refusal to
disclose his income tax returns.
   _ Mattox charged that the Richards campaign was ``peddling their
smut and their dirt'' because she didn't want to discuss issues and
wouldn't face him in a debate before the election.
   _ Former Gov. Mark White, defeated in the March 13 primary, said
he'd never vote for Ms. Richards because of behavior that ``would
make (Nazi war criminal Heinrich) Himmler blush.'' But he withheld
his endorsement from Mattox.
   Rove said the Democrats had opened doors for Williams.
   ``They've raised issues in the primary that may or may not have
been raised in the general election,'' said Rove. ``But now they
can be raised without the shrillness and viciousness that might
have been there otherwise.''
   In her campaign, Ms. Richards, 56, the state treasurer, offered
a vision of what she called ``the new Texas.''
   She said her priorities as governor would be education, the
economy, ethics in government and protection of the environment.
She pointed to her record as a moneymaking treasurer.
   Mattox, 46, pointed to his record of public service as a Dallas
County prosecutor, congressman and two-term attorney general.
   He also offered what he said was the only hope for improved
education and law enforcement without a tax increase: a state
lottery.
   Many of the candidates' comments dwelled on each other's tactics.
   Mattox on his rival: ``I said I was concerned about the
political cannibalism that was taking place. We made a good effort
try to get Ann Richards to step back away from that approach to
politics.''
   Ms. Richards on hers: ``I really thought when Mattox began all
this (drug) stuff, for the provocation of it, the sort of witch
hunt that he was on, I just thought the whole thing was sick. I
still do, regardless of who they're talking about.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0066 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 2302EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Greece 4thLd-Writethru a0762 04-08 0884</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Greece, 4th Ld-Writethru, a0762,0905</SECOND>
<HEAD>Conservatives Claim Victory With 150 Sure Seats</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 17 grafs to UPDATE with conservatives claiming
victory, quotes from Mitsotakis and Papandreou, updated vote
totals; pickup graf 11 pvs, `The deadlock...'
^By TERRY LEONARD</NOTE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ATHENS, Greece (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The conservative New Democracy party
claimed victory Sunday after it captured about half the seats in
Greece's third parliamentary election in 10 months.
   But it remained uncertain if the party would win the outright
majority that would enable it to break the country's political
deadlock without help from outside its ranks.
   Returns showed New Democracy, which barely missed majorities in
the inconclusive elections last June and November, had won at least
150 of the 300 seats in Parliament.
   Party leader Constantine Mitsotakis said his party was assured
of only 150 seats, but he declared victory anyway and said he
believed he would form a government Wednesday.
   ``In today's elections, the Greek people decided: they gave the
victory to New Democracy,'' he said. ``I feel great responsibility,
and we celebrate our victory.''
   Mitsotakis said he didn't yet know if his party had won 150 or
151 seats but was sure that he would be given the mandate to form a
government.
   Caretaker Interior Minister Theodore Katrivanos told reporters
early Monday that New Democracy was close to an outright majority
in the 300-member single-house Parliament.
   ``New Democracy has 150 seats with the possibility of gaining
more and only a slight possibility of getting less,'' said
Katrivanos, who based his comments on official returns.
   Two major independent Athens television stations declared New
Democracy the winner, saying their projections showed the
conservatives would win 151 to 152 seats. The declarations sparked
early morning horn honking, fireworks and wild street celebrations
in the capital by flag-waving party loyalists.
   Returns from 15,870 of 16,584 polling stations showed New
Democracy with 47.1 percent of the vote, compared to 38.6 for
former Premier Andreas Papandreou's Panhellenic Socialist Movement
(PASOK), 10.07 percent for the Communist-led alliance of leftist
parties and 4.2 percent for small parties and independents.
   New Democracy, which got 46.19 percent of the vote and 148 seats
in November's election, needed only about a 1 percent increase its
vote to win a majority Sunday.
   PASOK and the Communist-led alliance, which were not considered
strong enough to win outright, worked together to try to prevent a
conservative victory and to forge their own coalition government.
   Papandreou criticized Mitsotakis in his only comments early
Monday but did not concede defeat, saying the distribution of seats
in crucial areas was hard to judge.
   ``I'd like to stress that Mr. Mitsotakis has led the country to
three consecutive elections in pursuit of self-sufficiency, trying
to set the dilemma before the people of government or no
government, instead of posing the question of which government with
which policy,'' he said. ``These elections were the last thing
needed by our country.''
   ``PASOK will wage its battle both inside and outside of
Parliament, defending the people's national and economic issues,''
Papandreou said early Monday.
   Miltiades Evert, a top New Democracy official and former Athens
mayor, said projections that showed the conservatives had won at
least 150 seats meant New Democracy was in control and could
prevent any coalition by other parties.
   ``It is certain that New Democracy has 150 seats, and New
Democracy now controls political developments. Without New
Democracy, nothing can be done,'' he told Greek television.
   The political deadlock has been hard to break in Greece, where
party loyalty often translates into jobs and loans. Both PASOK and
the conservatives have governed Greece since the military
dictatorship ended in 1974. But big changes in party totals are
difficult to achieve.
   The deadlock itself has become an issue because the weak
coalitions formed after the June and November elections were unable
to cope with a foundering economy and a resurgence of political
terrorism.
   ``I believe the Greek people have realized that the crisis the
country is going through is a fundamental and dangerous one,'' said
Constantine Karamanlis, the six-term former conservative premier
and one-term president who led Greece back to democracy after
military rule.
   Greece faces severe economic problems. The budget deficit has
soared to $15.6 billion and the inflation rate, the highest in the
Common Market, hit 17.8 percent last month.
   In June, voters rejected the scandal-tainted PASOK government of
Papandreou but denied a majority to 71-year-old conservative leader
Constantine Mitsotakis.
   A conservative-Communist coalition formed after the June
election, and it indicted Papandreou and some of his ministers on
corruption charges.
   No trial date, has been set, however, and the charismatic former
premier remains a political force despite the indictment, health
problems and an open affair with Dimitri Liani, a former airline
hostess half his age whom he married after divorcing his American
wife of 38 years.
   The weak coalition governments that ruled following the June and
November elections also postponed decisions on a U.S. extradition
request for a Palestinian wanted for the bombing of an airliner in
1982 over Hawaii and on a new military bases agreement with the
United States.
   The four U.S. military bases in Greece could close in November
unless a new agreement is reached with Washington. Two of the four
bases already have been slated for closure by the Pentagon in
cost-cutting measures.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0067 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 2314EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Hungary 5thLd-Writethru a0763 04-08 0887</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Hungary, 5th Ld-Writethru, a0763,0916</SECOND>
<HEAD>Conservatives Gain Overwhelming Victory</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: INSERTS one graf after graf 8 pvs, `Their closest...' to
RAISE descriptions of party platforms; pickup graf 9 pvs `The
agrarian-based...'; EDITS to conform</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By GEORGE JAHN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUDAPEST, Hungary (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Voters choosing Hungary's first freely
elected government in 43 years gave an overwhelming victory Sunday
to Hungary's main conservative party, according to final unofficial
results.
   It was the second conservative sweep in Eastern Europe in as
many free elections. East Germans gave conservatives a clear
victory in elections on March 18, relegating the Communists to an
opposition role.
   In Hungary, Democratic Forum President Jozsef Antall declared,
``I am completely certain that we won the elections.
   ``But it is not we, but the Hungarian people who have won these
elections,'' he said to jubilant supporters crowding party
headquarters six hours after polls closed.
   He turned 58 Sunday, and a rare smile creased his face as he was
presented with a gigantic boquet of flowers.
   Final official results for the 261 parliamentary seats at stake
in runoff elections Sunday were not expected before Tuesday. The
results were combined with elections held March 25 for a total of
386 seats in the 394-member parliament. Eights seats will be
allocated based on minority representation.
   The national vote counting center reporting unofficial results
show the conservative Hungarian Democratic Forum winning 42.7
percent of the vote. That gave the party 165 seats after both
rounds.
   Their closest rivals, the liberal Alliance of Free Democrats,
won 23.8 percent of the vote, or a total of 92 seats.
   The Free Democrats want to quickly scrap Hungary's command
economy in favor of a market economy. The Forum emphasizes
traditional Christian values and cautious economic change.
   The agrarian-based Smallholders party won 43 districts with 11.1
percent of the vote, while reform Communists grouped in the
Socialist Party had won 33 with 8.55 percent.
   The Federation of Young Democrats and the Christian Democrats
won 21 seats with 5.4 percent of the vote each.
   The other 11 seats were divided among six independents, four
candidates supported by several parties, and a candidate of the
splinter Agrarian Federation.
   Direct voting Sunday determined 171 of the 261 seats at stake.
Ninety seats will be determined on the voting percentage each party
receives.
   The early conservative advantage forced a concession from Free
Democrat leader Miklos Haraszti.
   ``It is clear that the HDF will gain the most seats,'' he said.
   Elections two weeks ago left 261 of the National Assembly's 394
seats undecided. That balloting gave no party an outright majority
but relegated the former Communists to fourth place.
   No party was considered strong enough to win a majority in
Sunday's polling and a coalition government was expected. More than
7.5 million people were eligible to vote.
   Both front-running parties, the Democratic Forum and the Free
Democrats, have refused to consider forming a government with the
former Communists.
   Most polls closed at 6 p.m. after 12 hours of voting. State
television began its 24-hour election program two hours later with
preliminary estimates of a more than 40 percent turnout nationwide,
indicating that more than 3.25 million people voted.
   Many Hungarians seemed weary after the second round of balloting
in two weeks.
   ``It's clear that people have become tired,'' Interim President
Matyas Szueros told reporters before casting his ballot. ``It's
time to end the election process.''
   The voting was generally uneventful, with few irregularities
reported.
   In Debrecen, about 90 miles west of the capital of Budapest,
several polling stations did not open on time because supervisory
officials were late, state radio reported.
   One station first opened at 9 a.m., three hours past schedule.
The radio said the delay was caused by the chief supervisor who
called in to say he would be late because ``he was tired.''
   Voters at a polling station in Budapest shook out umbrellas
after walking in from the rain, and many clutched pussy willows
symbolic in Hungary of Easter.
   Many said they were enthusiastic about voting in the national
elections, but others appeared skeptical that a new government
would be able to solve Hungary's severe economic problems that
include a declining living standard, double-digit inflation,
growing unemployment and a $20 billion foreign debt.
   ``I'm here, I'm voting but I don't have any confidence in it,''
said Ernoe Horvath, a 61-year old retiree. ``Even now we don't have
people (running) that we can trust.''
   The first round of elections on March 25 put the Hungarian
Democratic Forum and the liberal Alliance of Free Democrats in the
lead, but neither party polled a majority, forcing Sunday's second
round.
   The Socialists were unique among ruling Soviet bloc parties in
leading their country to democracy without massive popular
pressure. But most people associate the party with the excesses of
43 years of Communist rule.
   The Free Democrats have warmed in recent weeks to the
possibility of a coalition with the Democratic Forum.
   But the Forum has said it will only join forces with the Free
Democrats in a ``national emergency.''
   Antall refused to comment when asked Sunday about the
possibility of a coalition government with the Free Democrats.
   But Free Democrat leader Janos Kis said that ``a grand coalition
is a distinct possibility which we don't refuse because we are ...
for having a government with wide popular support.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0068 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 2315EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-LiberaceAuction     04-08 0371</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Liberace Auction,0382</SECOND>
<HEAD>Auction of Items from Liberace's Home Brings $300,000</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PALM SPRINGS, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A mink bedspread lined with silk and
trimmed with mink tails sold for $9,900 Sunday as more than 2,000
items from entertainer Liberace's estate went up for auction.
   The late, flamboyant pianist's trademark candelabra, silver and
a Steinway grand piano were among the furnishings and artwork sold
from ``The Cloisters,'' his Palm Springs estate, an auction
spokeswoman said.
   The sale raised $300,000, with proceeds benefiting the Liberace
Foundation for the Performing and Creative Arts, which provides
scholarships to students of the arts.
   ``The auction overall was a terrific success,'' said Laura
Smissaert, spokeswoman for Butterfield &amp; Butterfield, which
conducted the sale. ``We had standing-room only crowds and made a
considerable amount of money for the Liberace Foundation.''
   About 800 people attended, with more than 500 registered to bid,
Ms. Smissaert said.
   The auction's highest bid was for a 1977 Auburn supercharged
``boattail'' speedster, painted crimson with a gold coach lining.
The automobile, with an interior trimmed in burgundy leather, has a
Lincoln engine but holds only one gallon of gasoline.
   The car, which went for $18,700, was used in Liberace's Las
Vegas stage act and the little gas tank was a safety requirement,
Ms. Smissaert said.
   The black mink bedspread's silk lining bears the Liberace logo,
a stylized cursive L, and is large enough for a king-size bed, Ms.
Smissaert said.
   The white and gold Steinway and Sons grand piano, which went for
$17,000, more than twice its estimated price, was one of the other
lavish items sold, she said.
   A collection of 30 toy cars given to Liberace by fans sold for
$800, and a brass bed from the estate's ``Rudolph Valentino suite''
went for $3,850.
   While the items from the estate were luxurious, Ms. Smissaert
said the furnishings were as functional as they were grand.
   ``This was his favorite home and therefore not as outrageous,''
she said. ``Anybody who walked through the house got a sense that
it was a very livable place.''
   The mansion, which Liberace purchased in 1967, was dubbed The
Cloisters because of its walls and alcoves. The property was sold
after the entertainer's death from AIDS in 1987.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0069 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 2317EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Peru 6thLd-Writethru a0768 04-08 1190</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Peru, 6th Ld-Writethru, a0768,1226</SECOND>
<HEAD>Vargas Llosa Wins in Peru's Elections, Projections Say</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with two grafs to UPDATE with two more dead, one
wounded in rebel violence; pickup graf three `The Maoist...';
INSERT one graf after 27th `Army forces...' with details; pickup
graf 28 pvs `In Lima...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By MONTE HAYES</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LIMA, Peru (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Celebrated novelist Mario Vargas Llosa won the
first round of presidential elections Sunday, but he fell far short
of the majority needed to avoid a runoff, according to unofficial
projections.
   Rebels trying to sabotage the elections attacked some polling
stations in Lima with dynamite Sunday, but no one was reported
injured. Weekend guerrilla violence in Peru killed at leaast 28
people and wounded 44, authorities said.
   The Maoist Shining Path has assassinated six congressional
candidates and killed or wounded dozens of other people in recent
weeks, aiming to disrupt the election.
   Vargas Llosa, 54, of the center-right Democratic Front
coalition, has run on a free-market ticket. He said the results
showed voters had rejected leftist policies and the governing
left-of-center Aprista Party for its ``catastrophic five years in
government.''
   ``The country's political panorama has changed profoundly with
this election,'' he said.
   The novelist captured 36.8 percent of the vote based on results
from an exit poll by APOYO, a market research firm.
   APOYO said Alberto Fujimori, the son of Japanese immigrants, was
in second place in its projections with 26.7 percent. Fujimori is a
political independent who was virtually unknown to Peruvian voters
as recently as a month ago.
   Peruvian Public Opinion projected 33.1 percent as Vargas Llosa's
final tally and 26.2 percent for Fujimori.
   APOYO, one of Peru's most respected polling firms, said its
results were based on the initial 54 percent of its total
interviews done nationwide. It said that was a big enough sample to
project a final vote.
   The market research firm also said Aprista Party candidate Luis
Alva Castro had 13.2 percent of the votes in its projections. It
said Henry Pease, candidate of the United Left, had 7 percent while
Alfonso Barrantes, candidate of the Socialist Left, 4 percent.
   The rest of the votes were spread among four minor party
candidates and blank or nullified votes, according to APOYO.
Officials returns are not expected for weeks.
   The Peruvian Public Opinion poll had similar figures for the
other candidates.
   At a news conference, Vargas Llosa proposed that he and Fujimori
meet to discuss ways to avoid a second election, saving Peru from
the turmoil of two more months of campaigning.
   Fujimori arrived minutes later at the news conference and
congratulated Vargas Llosa. But at a later news conference, he
rejected any possibility of stepping aside to avoid a runoff.
   ``I believe a second round is necessary to debate our
proposals,'' he said. ``The verdict should be the public's.''
   During the campaign, Vargas Llosa has sharply attacked the
Aprista Party and the two leftist alliances. He is unlikely to have
their support in the runoff.
   In contrast, Fujimori has run a conciliatory campaign without
attacks. He is believed to have support within the Aprista Party.
   ``The left is not going to support the Democratic Front because
of the polarization that has been generated in the country,''
Fujimori said in a news conference after polls closed at 5 p.m.
   The campaign has brought a surge in popularity for Fujimori.
Last week, Fujimori, 51, rose into second place in voter surveys,
displacing Alva Castro, 48.
   The Peruvian Public Opionion projections of the final vote also
indicated the Democratic Front would win only 23 seats in the
60-seat senate and 63 seats in the 180-seat chamber of deputies.
   That would make it very difficult for Vargas Llosa, 54, to
impose the severe austerity measures he has pledged if he wins. He
says radical economic reforms are needed to revive Peru's moribund
economy and turn Peru into a ``modern nation'' free of the
socialist policies he says have stiffled growth for two decades.
Inflation is running at more than 2,000 percent annually.
   Voters are choosing a president to replace populist Alan Garcia,
whose five-year term ends July 28. He is legally ineligible to
serve a consecutive term.
   During Sunday's voting, soldiers armed with automatic weapons
protected polling stations against terrorist attacks.
   Leftist guerrillas exploded sticks of dynamite near two polling
stations early Sunday in downtown Lima and an outlying shantytown.
Police said the explosions caused no damage and no one was injured.
   The government said nearly 80,000 policemen were on alert
throughout the country. More than 200,000 army troops were
providing security in the country's mountainous emergency zones,
where guerrillas are most active.
   On Saturday, police said Maoist Shining Path guerrillas blew up
municipal buildings and sacked stores, killing 17 peasants and
wounding 13 in the mountain village of Santo Thomas de Pata, about
18 miles northwest of Ayacucho.
   Army forces retailated Sunday, tracking down the rebels and
killing six in a fierce firefight, police said. One soldier was
also killed in the battle.
   Also Sunday, two members of the Shining Path were killed in the
central Andes when the bomb they were planting on a bridge
exploded, authorities said. Another rebel was badly wounded in the
blast in the town of Huasquis, about 100 miles east of Lima.
   In Lima, where one-third of Peru's voters live, police patrolled
the streets in armored vehicles and diverted traffic around the
capital's 15,837 polling stations.
   People entering voting stations were searched for weapons. The
government asked voters to go to the polls empty-handed to
facilitate searches.
   Fear of rebel attacks paralyzed bus traffic between towns in
mountainous insurgency zones. But election officials said voter
turnout was heavy, despite threats by the Shining Path guerrilla
group to kill voters and candidates.
   Television stations showed lines of voters up to five blocks
long in Huancayo, in the Andes 120 miles east of Lima. Huancayo, a
major trading center, is a Shining Path stronghold.
   In some areas of the country election officials suspended the
requirement that voters dip their index fingers into indelible ink
after casting ballots. The guerrillas have killed highland peasants
and cut off their hands as a warning not to vote.
   Voters leaving polling stations Sunday morning in the
working-class neighborhood of La Victoria expressed support mainly
for Fujimori and Vargas Llosa, who put aside his writing two years
ago to campaign for the presidency.
   Mariana Pino de Grecia, a housewife, said she voted for Vargas
Llosa.
   ``The country needs someone known internationally to attract
aid. Fujimori is not known. He doesn't have a plan of government
and he's too new,'' she said.
   But taxi driver Angel Torres said he voted for Fujimori.
   ``Let's see what Fujimori can do,'' he said. ``The others are
old politicians. He's more honorable, harder-working.''
   Voting is required by law. Violators are subject to heavy
penalties, including a fine equivalent to half the monthly minimum
wage of $45.
   The Maoist Shining Path guerrilla group launched its insurgency
in May 1980 by burning ballot boxes near the highland city of
Ayacucho. Since then nearly 20,000 people have been killed in
political violence, including rebels, police, soldiers and
civilians.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0070 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 2323EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Pepsi-Soviet     04-08 0289</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Pepsi-Soviet,0298</SECOND>
<HEAD>Report: Pepsi To Be Traded For Soviet Vodka and Ships</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Pepsico Inc. and the Soviet Union are expected
to sign an agreement to trade Pepsi-Cola for ships and vodka, which
would be the largest deal between that country and a U.S.
corporation, The New York Times reported.
   The deal is valued at more than $3 billion and is expected to be
announced Monday, the Times reported in Monday editions.
   The agreement would make Pepsi-Cola much more available in the
Soviet Union while enabling Pepsico to take out its profits not
just in the form of Stolichnaya vodka but in oceangoing freighters
and tankers.
   The agreement is being watched as an indicator of whether
Western companies can succeed in the Soviet Union, the newspaper
said.
   The Purchase, N.Y.-based company became the first large U.S.
company to enter the Soviet Union in 1974, when it began trading
Pepsi for Stolichnaya.
   Pepsico ships its soft-drink syrup to the Soviet Union, where it
is made into cola and sold in bottles. The vodka was sold through a
third party in the United States.
   The new deal calls for the Soviet Union to trade at least 10
tankers with a total value of $300 million, the Times said.
   The agreement would also allow Pepisco to sell Pepsi in plastic
bottles and aluminium cans instead of just glass bottles, and calls
for increasing the number of bottling plants from 26 to 50, the
newspaper said.
   ``This deal is going to make the Soviet Union a very big
business for us,'' John Swanhaus, president of Pepsico's Wines and
Spirits subsidiary, told the Times.
   Pepsi sells in the Soviet Union for the equivalent of 75 cents
for an 11-ounce bottle.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0071 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 2326EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Britain-Ferry 2ndLd-Writethru a0784 04-08 0201</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Britain-Ferry, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0784,0204</SECOND>
<HEAD>Crew Member Dead, Nine Injured in Ferry Fire Off Britain</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS thruout to UPDATE with nine injured; firefighters
brought out by helicopter; no pickup</NOTE>
<HEAD>With AM-Ferry Fire, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Fire broke out Monday on a car ferry carrying 297
people from Britain's west coast to Ireland, killing a crew member
and injuring nine people, officials said.
   The fire broke out beneath the car deck as the B and I ferry
Norrano was eight miles west of the Welsh coast, the coast guard
said. Spokesman George Clarke said the fire was brought under
control.
   A Royal Air Force spokesman said one crew member had been killed.
   Clarke said the injured, including a pregnant women, were
suffering from smoke inhalation. He said they had been evacuated to
Withybush Hospital in Haverford West by three RAF helicopters.
   ``The first helicopter brought out eight firefighters, and then
we brought out two doctors with oxygen equipment,'' Clarke said.
   The ferry, carrying 78 crew members and 219 passengers, was en
route from Milford Haven, 180 miles west of London, to Rosslare,
Ireland.
   The coast guard spokesman said the vessel was returning to
Milford Haven under its own power.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0072 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 2329EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-TajReorganization     04-08 0331</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Taj Reorganization,0341</SECOND>
<HEAD>Executive Shakeup at Troubled Taj</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ATLANTIC CITY, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Trump Organization is planning a
shakeup among executives at the newly-opened Taj Mahal Casino
Resort, whose slot machines have repeatedly been shut down by
overuse, a spokeswoman said Sunday.
   However, owner Donald Trump said in a statement that none of the
proposed changes resulted from the slot-machine troubles at the
1,250-room casino hotel _ Atlantic City's biggest _ that opened
last Monday.
   The Taj's 3,000 slot machines were shut down Friday night after
the volume of action overburdened the casino. The machines had
opened six hours late that day because of staff shortages and
problems accounting for the amount of money in the machines.
   They remained closed during the weekend and will be out of
service indifinitely to allow for procedural changes, officials
said.
   Taj Mahal Executive Vice President W. Bucky Howard is to become
president and chief operations officer at the casino, said
spokeswoman Karon Tuso.
   ``As a casino operator, Bucky is one of the best,'' Trump said
in the statement read by Ms. Tuso. ``He will provide the leadership
that will ensure the Trump Taj Mahal its place as the world's
greatest casino and convention resort.''
   Howard would replace Walter J. Haybert, who has been president
and chief executive officer since last October. Haybert would
become chief financial officer.
   Edward Tracy would be named president and chief executive
officer of Trump Hotel Corp. while continuing as president and
chief operations officer of Trump Castle Casino Resort, a position
he has held since November, Ms. Tuso said.
   The Trump Hotel Corp. manages Trump's four Atlantic City
properties.
   Ms. Tuso said the proposed changes must first be approved by the
state Casino Control Commission.
   Haybert was vice president of Harrah's in 1984 when it managed
Trump Plaza Hotel and Casino. At the time, more than 50 percent of
the Plaza's slots machines were closed during its first three
weeks, and Haybert resigned midway through that crisis.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900408-0073 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-90 1908EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f BC-GasPrices     04-08 0222</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Gas Prices,0232</SECOND>
<HEAD>Gas Prices Make Seasonal Rise</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Gasoline prices rose an average of 2.35 cents
a gallon over the past two weeks as spring vacationers took to the
road, a survey released has concluded.
   The Lundberg Survey of 13,000 gas stations nationwide, completed
on Friday and released Sunday, put the national average price for a
gallon of gas at 113.31 cents. The average covers all grades of
gas, types of service and all taxes.
   Price rises were especially high in the Midwest, survey chief
Trilby Lundberg said. She suggested that higher freight and
distribution costs to the Midwest may have contributed to the price
increases.
   Retailers faced a margin pinch as the increase in retail prices
lagged behind gains in wholesale prices, Lundberg said. The average
wholesale posting for a gallon of gas, not including rebates and
other price breaks, was 75.35 cents a gallon for the same two-week
period, a 3.5 cent increase over the last survey, she said.
   Here are the Lundberg survey average prices:
   _ Self-service stations: regular unleaded, 101.53 cents a
gallon; premium unleaded 118.77 cents; regular leaded, 100.58 cents.
   _ Full-service stations: regular unleaded, 129.47 cents a
gallon; premium unleaded, 142.93 cents; regular leaded, 128.42
cents.
   The survey indicates more than 80 percent of gasoline retail
sales are at self-service stations.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
</Collection>
