<Collection>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0001 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 2351EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-APArts:Liotta     09-16 0648</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-AP Arts: Liotta,0865</SECOND>
<HEAD>The Best Thing To Do: Ray Liotta's Passion for Films</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Monday AMs report.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By HILLEL ITALIE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   At one time Ray Liotta would have been perfectly
happy to just stay home.
   His mother was the movie fan of the family; Liotta preferred
sports. He went out for the senior play in high school only after
quitting the basketball team because of a fight with his coach.
   And when Liotta decided to study acting at the University of
Miami, he wasn't doing it out of a compulsion to entertain or a
need for artistic expression. He simply had nothing better to do.
   ``My parents wanted me to go to college and I didn't want to
go,'' said Liotta, who stars with Robert De Niro and Joe Pesci in
``GoodFellas.''
   ``My parents then suggested I take a year off and find out what
life's all about. I decided to go to the University of Miami and
take drama so I wouldn't have to take a math class. And when I got
there, I didn't want to do anything.''
   But he changed. Not right away; Liotta had no great desire to
act immediately after graduating. But by 1986, when he hustled his
way into a small, but memorable role in ``Something Wild,'' the
actor was hungry for work.
   Now, after ``Dominic and Eugene'' and ``Field of Dreams,'' the
offers come to him. Liotta didn't have to beg for the starring role
of ``GoodFellas.'' He wanted the part and director Martin Scorsese
wanted him. Even De Niro put in a good word.
   The movie runs more than two hours and covers four decades.
Liotta is in virtually every scene.
   ``You have to have a certain amount of confidence to be an
actor,'' Liotta said in an interview. ``In this film, I had to show
jealousy, rage, happiness, anger . . . everything was there. You
want to take that challenge as an actor. It was pretty intense.
   ``I had 80 costume changes, one day's in the '50s, the next
day's in the '80s. Emotionally, it was all different things. One
day I'm sweet. Then the next day I'm coked out of my mind. We'd
span 20 years at one location.''
   ``GoodFellas'' is based on Nicholas Pileggi's best-selling
novel, ``Wiseguy.'' Liotta plays Henry Hill, a half-Irish,
half-Sicilian Brooklyn kid drawn to the fast-paced gangster life
who eventually hooks up with mobsters De Niro and Pesci.
   Off screen, Liotta had to fit in as well. De Niro and Scorsese
have worked many times before, notably in ``Raging Bull'' and
``Taxi Driver.'' Liotta, knowing this was his chance to establish
himself as a major star, did his best to treat the film like just
another job.
   ``These guys have made major, major movies. They're considered
geniuses and brilliant and all that. I just approached it as a
game, just telling a story, no big deal. I read the book about five
years ago and thought, `Geez, I could do this.' ''
   Liotta began acting in soaps shortly after graduating from
college. He worked for three years on ``Another World,''
appreciating the steady work and learning how to feel comfortable
in front of a camera. But after appearing in the short-lived TV
series ``Casablanca'' and ``Our Family Honor,'' he struggled to
find work.
   Having nothing to do wasn't much fun anymore. When Liotta
learned there was an opening for a violent ex-con in ``Something
Wild,'' he pushed hard, trying unsuccessfully to get an audition
and finally calling on his friend, Melanie Griffith, the film's
star.
   ``I said, `Let me phone Melanie'; she was already cast.
(Director Jonathan) Demme was down to three guys and it was the
final week of casting. She said, `Great idea, I'll do that.' I wish
she had thought of that before. I was just so angry about trying to
get in and the part called for an angry guy. I went in angry and
luckily it worked out.''
   He played nice for ``Dominic and Eugene,'' starring as a quiet
medical student who takes care of his retarded brother, and was a
good guy in ``Field of Dreams,'' appearing as the ghost of baseball
great Shoeless Joe Jackson.
   All his characters are motivated by passion, the actor says. For
``GoodFellas,'' it was the drive for money and power. There was his
wife (Griffith) in ``Something Wild,'' his brother in ``Dominic and
Eugene'' and baseball in ``Field of Dreams.''
   Liotta's own passion came during those frustrating times before
``Something Wild,'' when he and fellow unemployed actors Kevin
Costner and Andy Garcia would hang out and try to keep their
spirits up, like frustrated minor leaguers just begging for the
manager to hand them the ball.
   ``I didn't have any doubts about my ability,'' Liotta said. ``I
wasn't wondering when I was going to get a break. I'm not being
cocky, it was tough, no question about it. You see these people,
and think, `I can't do that?' I can at least do it as well, and
with more commitment.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0002 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 2352EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-AYearAfterHugo     09-16 0734</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-A Year After Hugo,0905</SECOND>
<HEAD>Caribbean Back in Business, but Problems Persist</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Monday AMs report.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT GLASS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN JUAN, Puerto Rico (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Purple and red bougainvillea are
back in bloom, seaside resorts are open and cruise ships call again
at most of the dozen Caribbean islands battered by Hurricane Hugo.
   St. Croix in the U.S. Virgin Islands and the British colony of
Montserrat still are rebuilding, but elsewhere there is little
remaining evidence of the worst storm in a decade, which killed at
least 56 people and caused more than $2 billion in damage on Sept.
17-18, 1989.
   ``I think we've recovered better than expected,'' said Carl
Mitchell, director of the Economic Secretariat of the seven-member
Organization of Eastern Caribbean States in St. John's, Antigua.
   ``Initially, we had looked at the possible long-term effects and
had indicated it was going to take three years before there would
be full recovery,'' he said. ``But I think this may apply just to
Montserrat. The recovery in the other islands has been quite
startling.''
   Nevertheless, Mitchell said, the hurricane caused a drop in
economic growth rates and a sharp rise in the cost of living in
Montserrat and the neighboring islands of Antigua, Dominica and St.
Kitts-Nevis.
   On St. Croix, where one-third of the homes were demolished or
heavily damaged by winds of up to 200 mph, life is returning to
normal gradually.
   Two insurance companies went out of business, leaving more than
$55 million in claims to 1,000 homeowners and 200 businesses
unpaid. The territorial government has agreed to cover policyholder
losses of up to $100,000 each, but hundreds of families are still
waiting to have their homes rebuilt.
   One million cubic yards of debris has been cleared from the
island and restaurants and stores in Christiansted, the main town,
are operating. The landscape, once brown from defoliation, is
greener now.
   The Education Department said all but one of the island's 10
schools were reopening for the fall term after repairs made with a
$43 million federal grant.
   Thirty-three cruise ships are to resume port calls in October.
Betty Sperber, president of the Hotel and Tourism Association on
St. Croix, said 10 of the 15 major hotels would be open by then,
but the other five were closing permanently.
   St. Croix's image as an American paradise suffered both from the
hurricane's destruction and four days of looting that followed.
   President Bush sent 1,100 military police to restore order. They
stayed for two months and the island was under curfew.
   Residents still have angry memories of news reports at the time
about marauding gangs of blacks attacking wealthy whites with
machetes.
   Police Chief Delroy Richards says more than 100 people,
including some prominent residents, were arrested on theft charges
but ``none of the cases can I say were racially motivated.''
   ``I feel the looting is behind us,'' he said. ``People have
condemned those persons who took items that were not needed.''
   St. Croix, population 56,000, was by far the hardest hit of the
three main U.S. Virgin Islands. It has received the bulk of $750
million provided to the territory by the Federal Emergency
Management Agency, known as FEMA.
   Hugo also heavily damaged St. Thomas, whose population is about
the same; sparsely populated St. John, and the neighboring British
Virgin Islands, but all of them recuperated quickly.
   Puerto Rico, a U.S. commonwealth of 3.6 million people 70 miles
west of St. Croix, returned to normal within weeks of the hurricane
despite an estimated $1.3 billion in damage and lost production.
   Jose Bravo, the FEMA coordinator in San Juan, said 900 families
still were living in temporary modular housing, mostly in
northeastern Puerto Rico and on the offshore islands of Culebra and
Vieques.
   He said FEMA provided $72 million to the commonwealth government
for new housing but construction has been delayed by permits,
contracts and land development.
   Only $1.1 million of $14.2 million raised for hurricane victims
by a 12-hour simultaneous telethon in San Juan, New York and Miami
had been distributed by the end of August, 11 months later.
   Luis Davila, administrator of the telethon fund, said all
applicants should have their money within three months. She said
the fund also would build 330 homes, all expected to be ready by
Christmas.
   Montserrat, a small, pear-shaped island with only 12,500
residents 200 miles south of Puerto Rico, was all but flattened by
the hurricane and remains far from completely recovered.
   Reuben Meade, the government's director of development, said
about 90 percent of the island's 4,000 homes had been rebuilt and
businesses had reopened in Plymouth, the capital.
   Electricity, water and telephone services have been restored and
the two major hotels have reopened, he said, but roads need
repairs, the port still uses a barge as its main jetty and little
work has been done on government buildings.
   In Guadeloupe, which has 340,000 inhabitants and was the first
island in Hugo's path, wood and corrugated iron is heaped in places
and schools and houses still are being rebuilt.
   Franklin McDonald, director of the Pan-Caribbean Disaster
Preparedness and Prevention Project in Antigua, said the French
government responded quickly.
   ``There are still housing repairs being done, but to a great
extent Guadeloupe is back to normal,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0003 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 2353EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-FortHood-Chemical     09-16 0614</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Fort Hood-Chemical,0794</SECOND>
<HEAD>Chemical Warfare? Don't Worry, Just Keep That Mask on Until `All
Clear'</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Monday AMs report.</NOTE>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   AP Military Writer Susanne Schafer recently
traveled to Fort Hood with General Carl Vuono, the Army's chief of
staff, where elements of the 1st Cavalry and 2nd Armored Divisions
are preparing to ship out to Saudi Arabia. This is the second of
three reports.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>---</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SUSANNE M. SCHAFER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Military Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>FORT HOOD, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Staff Sgt. Connie Martens barked out the
chemical weapons drill to her two-dozen charges, sweaty young Army
soldiers swathed head to toe in thick, green and black protective
gear.
   ``Blister agent ... usually not fatal. Possibility of liquid
use. ... We have the M2-58A1. ... Hold your breath, grab your
M2-58A1. At that time you will start decontaminating your skin.
Once you decontaminate your skin, no problem!'' Martens told her
troops in rat-a-tat style.
   Some 15,000 soldiers from two armored divisions at this
sprawling Texas fort will soon trade its rolling hills for the
sands of Saudi Arabia. And Iraq's Saddam Hussein might be their
next instructor in the dangers of chemical warfare.
   So the soldiers from the 1st Cavalry Division listened intently
to the petite sergeant with the booming voice - a chemical weapons
expert with 15 years of service - as they got themselves and their
gear ready to deploy.
   ``Blisters may begin to appear on your skin. ... Don't pop the
blisters. If you break the blisters, you have the secondary problem
of infection. You don't want infections out there, so just keep 'em
covered like you've always been trained, like a normal burn
casualty and you won't have a problem. Any questions?'' she asked.
   ``Yeah, I've got a question,'' a voice sounded from the side of
the huddle. ``What's the standard for putting on a protective
mask?''
   Backs stiffened and eyes widened as a big-shouldered four-star
general in jungle green and brown fatigues worked his way to the
front of the group.
   Gen. Carl Vuono, the Army's chief of staff, had come to see
whether his troops were getting the proper training before being
sent in harm's way.
   ``Who knows?'' Vuono shouted at the group, soldiers who'd rarely
been quizzed by a multistar general, let alone the Army's top
commander.
   ``Nine seconds!'' came a chorused reply.
   ``So what's the signal?'' Vuono asked. Without waiting for a
response, he then boomed out: ``Gas! Gas! Gas!''
   Ripping their black headgear from their belts, the soldiers
squeezed their eyes shut add held their breath as they struggled to
place the heavy goggles and plastic cover over their heads.
   A few wouldn't have made it in time. Most did.
   ``Not bad, not bad,'' Vuono said, checking his watch. ``Let's
try it again. Put 'em back!''
   As a few men started to remove their clumsy headgear, the
muffled sound of ``Negative, negative'' emerged from the under the
Darth Vader-like hoods.
   Vuono beamed with delight - the soldiers had refused his order
because he'd not given the proper command ``All clear.''
   ``Well done! Well done! I tell you, Tilleli, I'm proud of these
guys!'' Vuono shouted to their commander, Maj. Gen. John Tilleli
Jr., who stood nearby.
   Leaning on his brown and green cane - the general had recently
undergone hip surgery so his staff had covered his hospital-issued
yellow cane with camouflage tape - Vuono told the soldiers they
were going a long way from Fort Hood, to a place much hotter than
Texas.
   And they also might have to go up against an opponent who has
used chemical weapons before.
   All hoods and goggles were still, trained on the general.
   ``I don't know whether he'll use them, I don't know whether
we'll fight him. All I do know is, I don't want any soldier going
to Saudi Arabia that isn't well trained,'' the general said.
   ``We're damn proud of each and every one of you, and we wish you
all the best and Godspeed as you deploy on Desert Shield,'' Vuono
said, saluting. ``Good luck. Good job.''
   ``Tet-Hup!'' came the command. As Vuono strode away, the
rubberized soldiers stood at attention under shade of the scrub
oak.
   Then with the speed of a bullet, Sgt. Martens was spouting her
commands again, getting her charges ready to move through the
training booth that simulates a chemical weapons attack.
   ``All right men, move to the next area, move to the CS area. If
you have any contacts, make sure you get 'em out. We don't want to
make you cry. Just a safety precaution, get 'em out.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0004 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 2353EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p PM-Louisiana-Senate     09-16 0686</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Louisiana-Senate,0862</SECOND>
<HEAD>Johnston: Duke `Clear and Present Danger' to Louisiana</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Monday AMs report.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By ALAN SAYRE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PINEVILLE, La. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Democratic Sen. J. Bennett Johnson is
billing himself as a Washington insider who delivers for Louisiana
in his bid to avert a November runoff against former Ku Klux Klan
leader David Duke.
   On the campaign trail, Johnston paints a dark picture of a
freshman Duke in Washington. He warns that electing the ex-Klansman
to the U.S. Senate could cost Louisiana military bases and other
government projects.
   ``We're not talking about a debating contest in Washington,''
Johnston said at a recent campaign rally. ``We're talking about the
future of central Louisiana. We don't need to be growing hate here
in Louisiana.''
   At stake, he says, is the future of England Air Force Base and
Fort Polk, two major military installations in central Louisiana,
as well as the Red River navigation project, a proposal that has
been pending since the 1970s.
   Johnston, who chairs the Senate Energy Committee and sits on the
budget committee, says he has the congressional clout that comes
from seniority.
   The three-term senator is in no danger of losing his seat. But
still in question is whether the incumbent will win another term
outright in the state's open primary on Oct. 6. If no candidate
wins 50 percent, the top two vote-getters face off in a November
runoff.
   In one recent poll, 48 percent of the voters favored Johnston
and 28 percent backed the maverick Republican Duke. Eleven percent
supported state Sen. Ben Bagert, according to the survey by
Mason-Dixon Opinion Research. Bagert is the GOP's endorsed
candidate but he has lagged far behind Johnston and Duke throughout
the campaign.
   The poll showed Duke and Johnston running even among white
voters, but gave Johnston a commanding lead among blacks.
   Johnston said Duke garners support because ``it gives people a
way to vote against every Jesse Jackson and every black on a town
council.''
   He warns that a monthlong runoff campaign would further
embarrass Louisiana and erode the state's chances for attracting
industry and saving its federal projects.
   ``Can you imagine that we're going to keep England Air Force
Base if David Duke is elected to the U.S. Senate?'' Johnston asks
on the campaign trail. ``When you don't have much seniority, you
don't have much clout.''
   Johnston takes credit for keeping alive the Red River project
despite opposition from presidents Carter and Reagan and so far
during the Bush administration.
   ``That's what seniority can do for you. I can get it done,'' he
said.
   Both Democratic and Republican opponents have debated how best
to handle Duke. When Duke ran for a vacant seat in the Louisiana
House in 1989, his opponent, John Treen, drew the endorsement of
President Reagan and the Republican Party. Amid high media
attention, Duke won the seat.
   When Johnston began a recent campaign swing in Baton Rouge, he
said he was on as a ``crusade'' but did not mention Duke by name.
   Within a week, however, Johnston was waging counterattacks
against Duke - who delights in calling the incumbent ``J. Benedict
Johnston.''
   Johnston says Duke ``is Hollywood handsome. He is a good
persuader as most con men are.''
   Duke, meanwhile, maintains he has put his Klan and neo-Nazi past
behind him.
   ``I was intolerant. I'm ashamed of that,'' Duke has said.
   He is the head of the National Association for the Advancement
of White People. In campaign appearances, he rails against welfare
cheats and affirmative action.
   Duke accuses Johnston of using ``scare tactics'' and says the
senator's claim that Louisiana could lose federal projects if he is
electd is ``ridiculous.''
   ``We have a better chance of keeping military bases with a
Republican (senator) than with a liberal Democrat who has been
voting against the president,'' Duke says.
   ``Johnston has resorted to cowardly, personal attacks because he
doesn't have the guts to stand up and debate me face to face,'' he
said last week.
   Johnston says Duke celebrates Adolf Hitler's birthday. The
senator emphasizes that Duke has been involved in writing books
advising blacks on how to defend themselves against ``whitey'' and
how women can please their men sexually.
   ``If I had done one-one hundredth of what he'd done, they would
have run me out of town on a rail,'' Johnston said.
   The message: once a Klansman, always a Klansman.
   ``This is serious business. This is no Boy Scout. This is
Louisiana's reputation at stake,'' Johnston said.
   ``We've had some real success (in attracting industry), not
rapidly, but clearly,'' Johnston said in an interview between
campaign stops. ``Duke could stop it dead in its tracks ... if
Louisiana becomes known as the state of David Duke and the Ku Klux
Klan.
   ``This election is about the legitimacy of David Duke. No one
gives him a chance of winning. The question is whether he will be
identified as a spokesman for Louisiana. ... He is a clear and
present danger, to coin a phrase.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0005 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 2354EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-TheScarsofAssault     09-16 0773</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-The Scars of Assault,1011</SECOND>
<HEAD>Assault Victims May Live in Fear Forever</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Monday AMs report.</NOTE>
<HEAD>With PM-What's Aggravated Assault? and PM-Assault List</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CAROLYN SKORNECK</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   People stare at the scars on his throat as he
waits in grocery store check-out lines. Sometimes they ask if he
has a cold. Sometimes they ask if he fought in Vietnam.
   He never served in Vietnam, but he tells people he did, because
he knows from experience that they won't want the truth.
   The truth is, eight years ago a stranger jammed a knife into his
gut, spilling the intestines out of his slight frame, then slit his
throat as he lay calling for help. It's those details people don't
want to hear - details that still rattle him, causing his hands to
shake uncontrollably, calling attention to nails bitten down to
nothing.
   The sandy-haired young father is just one of several million
people victimized by aggravated assault in the past decade.
   The attack swept away his optimism and trust, his devil-may-care
fearlessness. Taking its place is fear - fear so real that after
telling his story, he asked that his real name and hometown be kept
secret.
   ``We live with the realization that it doesn't happen to
somebody else,'' said the boyish, 33-year-old we'll call Larry
Roberts. ``We know that people will hurt you.''
   Murders may steal the headlines, but the number of serious
assaults dwarfs the number of killings. Assault victims survive,
but often are changed forever.
   ``The trauma of having looked at the jaws of death is something
that is very rough to deal with,'' said John Stein, deputy director
of the National Organization for Victims Assistance.
   Some 559,270 people - roughly the population of Columbus, Ohio,
- were injured in aggravated assaults last year alone, according to
the National Crime Survey, which annually interviews members of
some 49,000 households and extrapolates from that to the entire
nation.
   The survey found that 1.1 million others were victims of an
attempted aggravated assault with a weapon - a gunshot flew by
them, for example.
   On the night of June 6, 1982, Roberts was on leave from the Navy
and interested mainly in getting in a last day of scuba diving
before his aircraft carrier departed in two days.
   He was pitching a tent in a park when two strangers struck up a
conversation. They seemed friendly enough.
   Then without warning, one of them stabbed Roberts in the abdomen
and ran off with his scuba gear, wedding ring and $4 in cash.
   ``When I thought he was gone, I started to holler for help,''
Roberts said, a catch in his now-raspy voice. ``He came back
through the woods and he tilted my head back and slit my throat
twice. And then he tied my feet together and my hands back to two
trees.''
   Roberts eventually worked free, dragged himself 250 feet to a
dirt road, holding in his intestines and pressing his chin toward
his chest to keep the blood from spurting out. Help finally arrived
the next morning.
   He spent 10 months in the hospital, undergoing at least 10
operations.
   The fear took over when he emerged from the hospital April 18,
1983.
   ``I used to take a gun with me wherever I went,'' he said. ``I
was scared to death.''
   In the next two years, Roberts moved his family six times.
   ``Something would happen, something would trigger me and we'd be
gone,'' he said.
   They stopped running five years ago in rural Maryland so their
elder daughter could start school and enjoy a semblance of a normal
life. Four years ago, Roberts and his wife had a second daughter.
   In the meantime, his attacker pleaded guilty to attempted murder
and served six years of a 10-year sentence before being freed as a
model prisoner.
   Roberts still fears him - even though he believes his fear is
irrational. He also insisted that the assailant's name not be used,
in part because he doesn't want to antagonize him.
   Even now, Roberts' home is guarded by a large, loud dog
nicknamed Norad, after the nation's early warning system for
nuclear attacks. At night, their home is awash in light. Two
sheriff's deputies live across the street.
   Roberts and his wife never employ baby-sitters because they
don't trust strangers.
   The attack destroyed Roberts' career plans. The Navy discharged
him involuntarily because he could no longer perform his job.
   Desperate to catch up for time lost, Roberts pushed himself too
far. He has had a drinking problem. He spent two months in a
psychiatric hospital last year.
   Today, he takes things more slowly, teaching scuba diving only
part time while attending college.
   And after years of shying away from the world, he now tells his
story to police groups, hoping to sensitize officers to victims'
needs.
   ``The victim is a piece of evidence,'' said Andrew Turner, a
criminal justice instructor at Wor Wic Tech Community College and a
former Maryland police officer who has arranged some of Roberts'
talks.
   ``If the guy survived, you had a good case. He could come and
testify against the perpetrator.'' Turner said. ``Police don't see
a guy healed up'' but still needing emotional support.
   Roberts finds the speeches therapeutic, despite the toll they
take, and he has established a network of people who will help him
when he cracks from the strain.
   It is important to Roberts that he controls the impact of the
attack and not the other way around, but he conceded, ``It has
given my life a different direction.''
   Now there's yet another fear: AIDS.
  Roberts had numerous blood transfusions in 1982, before blood
was tested for the deadly disease, and he refuses to be tested now.
   ``If I'm going to die of it,'' he said with a grimace, ``I don't
want to know about it.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0006 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 2355EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-What'sAggravatedAssau     09-16 0309</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-What's Aggravated Assault?,0351</SECOND>
<HEAD>Aggravated Assault Definition Varies From State to State</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-The Scars of Assault</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CAROLYN SKORNECK</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   What is an aggravated assault? It depends on
who is talking. What one police officer calls aggravated assault
may be only a simple assault to another and an encounter not even
worth reporting to a third.
   ``In each state, the definition of aggravated assault varies
widely,'' said Richard R. Bennett, a professor of justice at
American University.
   ``In some states, it's any threat with a weapon other than a
fist,'' he said. ``Elsewhere, it's a fist. In some states, it has
to be an injury visible on the outside, internal bleeding won't
do.''
   Even the Justice Department's two major measures of national
crime don't quite agree.
   The FBI's Uniform Crime Reports defines it as an ``unlawful
attack ... for the purpose of inflicting severe or aggravated
bodily injury.'' The assault usually involves a weapon or ``means
likely to produce death or great bodily harm.'' The FBI also throws
in attempted assault.
   The National Crime Survey, meanwhile, defines it as: ``Attack
with a weapon, irrespective of whether or not there was injury, and
attack without a weapon resulting either in serious injury (for
example, broken bones, loss of teeth, internal injuries, or loss of
consciousness) or an undetermined injury requiring two or more days
of hospitalization. Also includes attempted assault with a
weapon.''
   The FBI report includes only crimes reported to police. The
National Crime Survey, which annually interviews people who live in
about 49,000 homes and apartments, learns of many more crimes that
police never hear about.
   And, in part because of they are put together differently, the
two surveys disagree about whether more Americans have been
assaulted in the last decade.
   The FBI report says the rate of aggravated assault and attempted
aggravated assault zoomed up 28.4 percent during the decade to a
new high of 383 for every 100,000 people.
   The National Crime Survey, however, says the rate dropped 8.6
percent to 850 per 100,000.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0007 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 2355EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-Assault-List     09-16 0202</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Assault-List,0232</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rate of Aggravated Assaults in Largest U.S. Cities</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-The Scars of Assault</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here is a list of America's 36 largest cities
- those with 400,000 or more residents - and their rate of
aggravated assaults and attempted aggravated assaults per 100,000
people, as reported to police and listed in the FBI's Uniform Crime
Reports for 1989.
   
   1. Atlanta, 21.4.
   2. St. Louis, 19.6.
   3. Los Angeles, 12.6.
   4. Chicago, 12.6.
   5. Portland, Ore., 11.6.
   6. Boston, 11.2.
   7. Detroit, 10.6.
   8. Dallas, 10.3.
   9. Kansas City, 10.3.
   10. New York City, 9.6.
   11. Washington, D.C., 9.6.
   12. Baltimore, 9.
   13. Fort Worth, Texas, 8.3.
   14. New Orleans, 7.8.
   15. Seattle, 7.6.
   16. Indianapolis, 7.3.
   17. Jacksonville, Fla., 7.2.
   18. Long Beach, Calif., 7.2.
   19. El Paso, Texas, 6.4.
   20.-Tie: Nashville, Tenn., and San Francisco, both 6.1.
   21. Phoenix, Ariz., 5.7.
   22. Cleveland, 5.6.
   23. San Diego, 5.5.
   24. Oklahoma City, 5.3.
   25. Memphis, 5.1.
   26. Houston, 4.7.
   7. San Jose, Calif., 4.1.
   28. Philadelphia, 4.
   29.-Tie: Denver and Columbus, Ohio, 3.9.
   30. Las Vegas, 3.1.
   31. Austin, Texas, 2.8.
   32. Milwaukee, 2.1.
   33. San Antonio, 2.
   34. Honolulu, 1.2.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0008 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 2358EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-GraduateGuarantees     09-16 0735</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Graduate Guarantees,0880</SECOND>
<HEAD>More Students Entering Workforce Today - Under Warranty</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Monday AMs report.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By LORI DODGE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>O'FALLON, Mo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   This year's seniors at Fort Zumwalt high
schools will be armed with more than just diplomas when they
graduate: They'll also each be backed by a three-year warranty.
   In a small but growing number of schools, educators are adding
an extra stamp of approval to their products - ``satisfaction
guaranteed.''
   ``The diploma used to be the guarantee,'' said Fort Zumwalt
superintendent Bernard DuBray. ``But now we need to go above and
beyond.''
   Warranties such as Fort Zumwalt's typically guarantee that a
graduate has learned the basic skills necessary to perform an
entry-level job. If not, the school promises to provide additional
training free of charge.
   ``It's accountability,'' said Bernard Sidman, superintendent of
the Plymouth-Carver Regional School District in Massachusetts,
which first included a three-year warranty with graduates' diplomas
last spring and so far has had no students sent back.
   ``You hear an awful lot about the quality of public education
and about public institutions of education not meeting their
responsibilities in preparing students for entry into public
life,'' Sidman said.
   ``We felt that if we were going to be asking the community to
support us, maybe we should put ourselves on the line.''
   But let the buyer beware: The amount of training received by
guaranteed graduates may vary. Some schools simply warranty all
their graduates. In others, the warranty program is designed mainly
for students who want jobs straight out of high school.
   At Prince George's County School District in Maryland, students
who want to be under warranty take a semester class focusing on job
skills. The class has been developed with input from area business
and industry leaders.
   In Missouri's Blue Springs School District, the state's largest,
the graduate guarantee is printed on the back of a laminated
wallet-size diploma.
   ``We've got some tremendous young people coming out of our
system,'' said superintendent Charles McGraw. ``The nation's
educational system is getting a bad rap and we wanted to make a
point that our graduates had the skills to be good employees.''
   But it's not enough just to warranty students if there's no
recognition of what entry-level jobs in today's business world
require, said Fritz Edelstein, senior fellow at the National
Alliance for Business in Washington, D.C.
   Entry-level jobs are much more complex today, and school studies
should reflect that, Edelstein said.
   McGraw agreed.
   ``I think we went through a time when the curriculum was out of
date,'' he said. ``The curriculum has been slow changing - it
hasn't kept up with the progress of technology that the business
world required. So this is an attempt to be up to date.''
   For instance, McGraw said, mechanical drawing is out,
computer-assisted drafting is in. At the junior high level, a new
exploratory course called industrial technology is being offered to
introduce students to robotics, broadcasting, electronics and
computer science, he said.
   Educators say skill guarantees have helped create a line of
communication between schools and businesses.
   ``It's a feedback system,'' said Gary Marx, associate executive
director of the American Association of School Administrators in
Arlington, Va. ``It's a way for the schools to say to an employer,
`It's all right to come back and let us know if there's something
missing here.' ''
   In the Harlem Consolidated School District outside Rockford,
Ill., this year's seniors will be able to earn a ``certificate of
employability.''
   The idea came about through meetings between school
administrators and corporate leaders from the community, assistant
superintendent Wayne Musholt said.
   During discussions, company executives expressed concerns about
the employability of some of the students graduating today,
particularly those who were not college-bound.
   ``Their concern was that some of the students didn't always have
the best work habits and attitudes and we decided there ought to be
a way of certifying them,'' Musholt said.
   To gain the certificate, students will have to earn the required
number of high school credits and be absent no more than six days a
year. In addition, their work ``attitudes'' will be rated by their
teachers.
   The program at Prince George's County schools has received high
marks from business and industry leaders, said Bonnie Jenkins,
director of public affairs.
   ``The response has been overwhelmingly positive so far,'' she
said.
   Employers prefer the students who have completed the special
semester course, which emphasizes such areas as work habits and
attitudes, reasoning and problem solving, and oral communication
skills.
   ``So it's giving them an edge,'' she said.
   Last year was the first for the project, and no students have
been referred back for more training, Jenkins said.
   Guarantees rekindle employers' interest in high school graduates
and encourage potential dropouts to stay in school, said Thomas
Shannon, executive director of the National School Boards
Association in Alexandria, Va.
   ``This is adding a new dimension to the diploma,'' he said.
``It's a gimmick - it's right out of Madison Avenue - but secondly,
it also sends a powerful message to the school staff that your work
is really on the line.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0009 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 2359EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-Gulf-StarWars     09-16 0612</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Gulf-Star Wars,0721</SECOND>
<HEAD>Iraqi Missile Threat Raises Appeal of Star Wars Spinoff</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Monday AMs report.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT BURNS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The prospect of Iraq firing ballistic missiles
at U.S. forces in the Arabian desert is stirring congressional
interest in an obscure Star Wars spinoff effort to build defenses
against close-range missile attacks.
   The United States has only a rudimentary defense against Iraq's
missile arsenal, which U.S. intelligence agencies say is rapidly
growing more sophisticated and is capable of carrying chemical
warheads to targets inside Saudi Arabia.
   Even some of Congress' harshest critics of the Strategic Defense
Initiative, more commonly called Star Wars or SDI, say the Iraqi
missile threat might call for spending more on what the Pentagon
calls ``theater missile defense.''
   ``Maybe there's some justification for increasing that
particular aspect of SDI,'' Sen. Edward Kennedy, D-Mass., said last
week at a Senate Armed Services Committee hearing on the U.S.
military buildup in the Persian Gulf region.
   Kennedy's comment doesn't suggest a surge of support for the
overall SDI program, which is aimed mainly at building a
space-based defense against Soviet intercontinental ballistic
missiles - those capable of reaching American soil.
   Congress is expected to slash at least $1 billion from President
Bush's request for $4.6 billion in SDI funding for the 1991 budget
year starting Oct. 1.
   The Iraqi crisis, however, has revived interest in SDI
technologies that could be applied against short-range missiles
that are proliferating in the Middle East.
   Two days after the Aug. 2 Iraqi invasion, the Senate approved a
measure forcing the Pentagon to slow down work on strategic
anti-missile defenses, while putting more emphasis on theater
defense. The measure called for spending $180 million on theater
defense in 1991 - $48 million more than Bush requested and $55
million more than in this year's budget.
   ``People are much more focused now on the threat posed by
short-range missiles,'' Sen. Jeff Bingaman, D-N.M., a cosponsor of
the Senate measure, said in an interview Friday. ``What makes it
more immediate is the aggression that Saddam Hussein visited on
Kuwait.''
   One of the most promising theater missile defense projects is
called the Extended Range Intercept Technology, or ERINT. LTV
Corp., which runs the project under an SDI contract, is developing
a lightweight missile to ram incoming ballistic missiles at five
times the speed of sound, causing them to vaporize.
   Money for ERINT was cut back from planned levels this year,
causing a several-month delay in its development schedule. The
missile's first flight tests are set for 1992, according to Jess
Granone of the Strategic Defense Command in Hunstville, Ala.
   Also in development is the Arrow system for defense against
theater missiles. This highly secretive program is a joint effort
between the Strategic Defense Command and Israeli Aircraft
Industries. It is being developed to handle longer-range missiles
than those that could be hit by the ERINT system.
   Currently the only U.S. defense against short-range missiles is
the Army's Patriot air defense system, which was designed to shoot
down aircraft, not missiles. The Patriot is being modified to knock
down missiles, but the technology is rudimentary and the system has
never been battle tested.
   Batteries of Patriot missiles are deployed with Army units in
Saudi Arabia.
   Only about 3 percent of the total SDI budget of $3.6 billion
this year was spent on developing missile systems to intercept and
destroy short-range ballistic missiles. The main focus of SDI is to
build a combination of ground- and space-based weapons and
satellites to detect, track and destroy long-range missiles. The
United States has spent $20 billion on this effort since 1983.
   At the Senate Armed Services hearing, Defense Secretary Dick
Cheney jumped at the opportunity to emphasize U.S. vulnerability to
non-Soviet missiles - an argument that carried little weight before
Bush dispatched tens of thousands of GIs to Saudi Arabia after Iraq
invaded Kuwait Aug. 2.
   ``We see now, as we contemplate the possibility of hostilities
with Iraq, that we're faced with a country that has ballistic
missiles, short-range systems,'' Cheney said. ``SDI is that portion
of our budget where we currently have ensconced the programs that
would allow us to deal with a short-range tactical ballistic
missile threat.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0010 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 0011EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-TrappedBoy 1stLd-Writethru a0619 09-16 0265</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Trapped Boy, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0619,0324</SECOND>
<HEAD>Firefighters Trying to Rescue Toddler Trapped at Bottom of Hole</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 9 grafs to UPDATE with firemen breaking through
hard clay; prepared to snatch toddler if cave-in occurs. Pickup 4th
graf pvs., `The boys.' DELETES last 2 grafs of outdated
information.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By SCOTT MAXWELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DENVER (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A toddler fell to the bottom of a 12-foot narrow
construction hole Saturday afternoon and firefighters, hampered by
the danger of a cave-in, worked into the night trying to rescue
him.
   Firemen broke through a layer of hard clay shortly after 9 p.m.
in their efforts to dig a parallel shaft to rescue 20-month-old
Kevin Davis from the hole at his family's home in southeast Denver.
   The shaft Kevin fell into is about 18-inches wide at the top and
was to be filled with reinforced concrete for a remodeling project.
   Denver policeman W.C. Hoffman said the threat of a cave-in
diminished after diggers finally broke through the clay that had
slowed digging efforts throughout the night.
   ``We're letting him sleep for now. He's been sleeping off and
on. We've had to play around with the oxygen (tube to the boy)
because he doesn't like the sound (hissing) of the oxygen. Every
time he wakes up he cries,'' Hoffman said.
   Rescuers were ready should there be a cave-in on the little boy,
who is too young to grab a rope that could be lowered to him.
   ``We've got a pole with a snare in the hole. If it caves in,
we'll grab him with that and pull him up,'' said Hoffman.
   However, he said the snare would break any limb they might pull
on.
   The boys' parents, Tom and Lisa Davis, were talking to Kevin,
trying to soothe him during the rescue effort. Oxygen was being
pumped into the shaft.
   Kevin fell into the shaft about 4 p.m.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0011 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 0045EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-Kuwait 4thLd-Writethru   09-16 0658</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Kuwait, 4th Ld-Writethru,a0613,0833</SECOND>
<HEAD>Precede DHAHRAN</HEAD>
<HEAD>Iraq Opens Border to Hundreds of Refugees From Kuwait</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS throughout to give first-hand report from border town;
comments from Kuwaiti refugees; other details. No pickup. ADDS
byline</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By JOHN KING</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>KHAFJI, Saudi Arabia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   At least 1,000 refugees from Kuwait
streamed into Saudi Arabia on Saturday after Iraqi border guards
opened at least one frontier crossing.
   Scores of newly arrived Kuwaitis were lined up early Sunday to
be processed at a Saudi government office in this border town and
waiting to use pay phones to call relatives who had fled Kuwait
earlier.
   A Saudi government source who had spoken to an official at the
border said he was told that about 1,000 Kuwaitis had crossed into
Khafji on the Saudi side and each was being registered by the Saudi
government.
   The source, who spoke on condition of anonymity, said most
government officials had been instructed to say publicly that there
had been no abnormal activity at the crossing point.
   Iraq's motives for opening the border were not immediately
clear.
   Several of the Kuwaiti refugees said the border had been
abruptly opened Friday, but most of those who left did so on
Saturday.
   A Kuwait City lawyer, who gave his name only as Shaheen, said he
didn't know why the frontier had been opened, but said Iraqi
President Saddam Hussein ``is asking the Kuwaitis to leave Kuwait
and go out across the border.''
   He said that in the last three days about 25 young Kuwaitis,
ranging in age from 15 to 25, had been taken away by Iraqi soldiers
for unknown reasons.
   Shaheen added that he had heard rumors of several Americans and
other Westerners hiding in Kuwait.
   ``If you help a Westerner in your home you will be hanged, but
some people are still hiding them,'' he said, referring to Iraqi
threats that persons caught sheltering Westerners would be put to
death.
   A group of 11 Kuwaiti families, 88 people in all, arrived in
Dhahran, 200 miles south of the border, Saturday night and told of
traveling in a convoy of cars from Kuwait City.
   They said they made the trip because Iraqi President Saddam
Hussein had stated two days ago that all vehicles with Kuwaiti
registry would be permitted to cross into Saudi Arabia.
   Speaking through an interpreter at a local hotel, several
members of the group said they were stopped by Iraqi troops six
times and were robbed of belongings including passports, drivers
licenses, cassettes and even wedding invitations.
   A hotel clerk at Khafji, on the Saudi side of the border, said
refugees of ``all nationalities, including Westerners, Indians and
others,'' began streaming across about 10 a.m., and at midnight
``they are still coming, little by little.''
   The clerk at the Hotel Saad Al-Orasi, who identified himself as
Hosaria Kumara, said the refugees were coming by car and most
apparently were heading south toward Dhahran.
   One of the refugees in Khafji, Affa Abdullah, said she had left
her home with 15 family members after learning from a friend that
the border was open.
   She said the Iraqis took their passports and drivers licenses at
a checkpoint before they reached the border. Most of the Kuwaitis
at the processing center did not appear to have passports.
   ``When we got to the border, the Iraqis told us to go, but I
don't know why,'' she said.
   She said food supplies were running low and stores were limiting
customers to single purchases of various items.
   The shortages were even affecting the Iraqi occupation troops.
She said that during the past month Iraqi soldiers would come to
her home and take food and water.
   ``One soldier asked me whether I liked Saddam (Hussein) or
Jaber. If i told him I liked Kuwait and Jaber, I would be killed.''
   The emir of Kuwait, Sheik Jaber el-Ahmed al-Sabah, heads the
Kuwaiti government-in-exile based in the southwestern Saudi city of
Taif.
   Another Kuwaiti, who gave his name only as Adel, said the border
was open Friday and Saturday, but ``today maybe it will be
closed.''
   Adel said Kuwaitis had heard Saddam's call for an Islamic holy
war against the United States, but he said the Iraqis ``don't have
even a little Islam in their hearts or in their minds.''
   ``Israel is better than Saddam,'' he said. ``The Israelis take
from the Palestinians but without killing them or stealing their
food and water. Saddam is killing Kuwait.''
   Another man, who identified himself only by his first name
Manfour, said the Iraqi soldiers were ``stealing everything,''
including the loudspeakers from mosques used to call the faithful
to their daily prayers.
   Refugees, mostly Kuwaitis, have been trickling into Saudi Arabia
since Aug. 2, when Iraq invaded Kuwait. The flow has depended
largely on Iraqi security, which has been tight at times and loose
at others.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0012 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 0154EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Emmys-Simpsons     09-16 0146</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Emmys-Simpsons,0140</SECOND>
<HEAD>`The Simpsons' Take Top Award in Non-Televised Emmy Show</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PASADENA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In their first nomination for an Emmy
award, television's irrevent ``The Simpsons'' won the trophy for
Outstanding Animated Program Saturday night.
   The award was handed out at the non-televised segment of the
42nd Annual awards show.
   ``I'd like to thank everyone in America for buying a Bart
Simpson T-shirt,'' Simpsons creator Matt Groening said in accepting
the award before about 2,000 members and guests of the Academy of
Television Arts and Sciences.
   ``The Simpsons'' defeated two ``Garfield'' specials and a
``Charlie Brown'' special. Two versions of ``The Simpsons'' were
nominated: a Christmas special and the regular series, with the
latter taking the award.
   This fall, ``The Simpsons'' on Fox faces off against ``The Cosby
Show'' on Thursday nights.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0013 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 0200EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Emmys-Technical     09-16 0577</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Emmys-Technical,0610</SECOND>
<HEAD>ABC Leads After Technical Emmys, `Simpsons' Victorious</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN HORN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Entertainment Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PASADENA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   ABC won a leading 13 Emmys Saturday
night in the non-televised segment of the 42nd Annual Emmy Awards.
  The network's ``Twin Peaks'' took two Emmys, one for editing and
another for costume design.
   Fox's ``The Simpsons'' was selected top animated program by the
voters of the Academy of Television Arts and Sciences.
   NBC took 11 trophies and CBS six.
   Here is a list of winners from the non-televised ceremony.
   Special Visual Effects (Area award; three winners): ``By Dawn's
Early Light,'' HBO; ``Miracle Landing,'' CBS; ``The Orchestra,''
PBS.
   Costume Design, Miniseries or Special: ``The Kennedys of
Massachusetts, Part One,'' ABC.
   Costume Design, Variety or Music Program: ``Mother Goose Rock
'N' Rhyme,'' Disney.
   Costume Design, Series: ``Twin Peaks,'' ABC.
   Costuming, Series: ``The Young Riders,'' ABC.
   Informational Series: ``Smithsonian World,'' PBS.
   Informational Special (Two-way tie): ``Dance in America: Bob
Fosse Steam Heat,'' PBS; ``Broadway's Dreamers: The Legacy of the
Group Theatre,'' PBS.
   Classical Program in the Performing Arts: ``Aida,'' PBS.
   Individual Achievement - Classical Music-Dance Programming (Area
awards; two winners): ``The Eighth Annual Van Cliburn International
Piano Competition,'' PBS; ``Carmen on Ice,'' HBO.
   Individual Achievement - Informational Programming (Area award;
two winners): ``W. Eugene Smith, Photography Made Difficult,'' PBS;
``A Conversation With...,'' Disney.
   Children's Program: ``A Mother's Courage: The Mary Thomas
Story,'' NBC.
   Animated Program (One hour or less): ``The Simpsons,'' Fox.
   Music Composition, Series: ``Beauty and the Beast,'' CBS.
   Music Composition, Miniseries or Special: ``The Shell Seekers,''
ABC.
   Music Direction: ``Julie Andrews in Concert,'' PBS.
   Music and Lyrics: ``From the Heart...The First International
Very Special Arts Festival,'' NBC.
   Cinematography, Miniseries or Special: ``Murder in
Mississippi,'' NBC.
   Cinematography, Series: ``Quantum Leap,'' NBC.
   Editing, Series (Single camera production): ``Twin Peaks,'' ABC.
   Editing, Miniseries or Special (Multi-camera production): ``The
Best of the Tracey Ullman Show,'' Fox.
   Editing, Miniseries or Special (Single-camera production):
``Caroline?'' CBS.
   Editing, Series (Multi-camera production): ``The Tracey Ullman
Show,'' Fox.
   Casting, Miniseries or Special: ``The Incident,'' CBS.
   Makeup, Miniseries or Special: ``Billy Crystal: Midnight Train
to Moscow,'' HBO.
   Hairstyling, Miniseries or Special (Two-way tie): ``Fall From
Grace,'' NBC; ``The Phantom of the Opera, Part One'' NBC.
   Makeup, Series (Two-way tie): ``Alien Nation,'' Fox; ``The
Tracey Ullman Show,'' Fox.
   Hairstyling, Series: ``The Tracey Ullman Show,'' Fox.
   Art Direction, Miniseries or Special: ``The Phantom of the
Opera, part Two,'' NBC.
   Art Direction, Variety or Music Program: ``The 62nd Annual
Academy Awards,'' ABC.
   Sound Editing, Series: ``Star Trek, The Next Generation,''
Syndicated.
   Sound Mixing, Drama Miniseries or Special: ``Cross of Fire, Part
One,'' NBC.
   Sound Mixing, Drama Series: ``China Beach,'' ABC.
   Sound Mixing, Variety, Music Series or Special: ``The Arsenio
Hall Show,'' Syndicated.
   Sound Editing, Miniseries or Special (Two-way tie):
``Challenger,'' ABC; ``Family of Spies, Part One,'' CBS.
   Sound Mixing, Comedy Series or Special: ``Cheers,'' NBC.
   Lighting Direction, Comedy Series: ``Just the Ten of Us,'' ABC.
   Lighting Direction, Drama Series, Variety Series, Miniseries or
Special (Two-way tie): ``The 17th Annual American Music Awards,''
ABC; ``The Earth Day Special,'' ABC.
   Technical Direction, Series: ``Saturday Night Live,'' NBC.
   Technical Direction, Miniseries or Special: ``The Magic if David
Copperfield XII: Niagara Falls,'' CBS.
   Guest Actor, Comedy Series: Darren McGavin, ``Murphy Brown,''
CBS.
   Guest Actress, Comedy Series: Swoosie Kurtz, ``Carol &amp;
Company,'' NBC.
   Guest Actor, Drama Series: Patrick McGoohan, ``Columbo,'' ABC.
   Guest Actress, Drama Series: Viveca Lindfors, ``Life Goes On,''
ABC.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0014 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 0303EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-AutoTalks 3rdLd-Writethru a0629 09-16 0531</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Auto Talks, 3rd Ld - Writethru, a0629,0656</SECOND>
<HEAD>UAW, General Motors Keep Talking After Contract Deadline Passes</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: INSERTS 1 graf after 4th graf, `Both sides...', to UPDATE with
talks continuing, no announcement to be made.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto WDR1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By FREDERICK STANDISH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Auto Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DETROIT (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The United Auto Workers and General Motors Corp.
froze the clock and continued negotiations Saturday toward a new
three-year agreement coverng 300,000 GM workers nationwide.
   Meanwhile, 12,800 Canadian Auto Workers union members struck
Ford of Canada early Saturday after talks there broke off. No
plants involved operate on weekends so any strike impact won't be
felt until Monday.
   ``We still have a very significant distance between the two
positions,'' Ford's chief negotiator, Don MacKenzie, said after
talks broke off. The strike is the first against Ford of Canada
since 1976.
   Both sides have refused to disclose details of their proposals
and demands. Talks resumed Saturday in Detroit and continued past
midnight into Sunday morning. Bargaining also resumed Saturday in
Toronto.
   Spokesmen for both sides said talks would continue through the
night, and no announcement would be made before 9 a.m. Sunday.
   The 1987 GM-UAW contract covering workers in 29 states expired
at midnight Friday. Because all but one of GM's plants are idle on
weekends, a strike would be only symbolic until Monday.
   No new deadline for an agreement has been set in the GM talks,
but the union called a meeting Monday for its 300-member GM
national bargaining council.
   That session could be used to review details of the agreement or
brief local leaders on the talks. It also could be used to gauge
leaders' feelings on a strike authorization made a week ago.
   A GM strike Monday, even at just one critical parts plant, could
quickly disrupt vehicle production by the world's largest
automaker. That's because it uses a system that delivers parts to
its assembly plants just before they are needed for installation in
a vehicle.
   Both sides have refused to disclose the progress of the
negotiations, but aspects of job security and benefits for GM
workers remained unresolved Saturday.
   Talks initially stalled over GM's insistence that a no-layoff
pledge be limited to workers with 20 or more years of seniority.
The UAW wanted all workers covered.
   GM countered with an offer to protect workers with 15 years of
seniority in exchange for more flexibility to move workers within
and between plants and an increase in the average number of minutes
worked per hour from 46 to 55, the Detroit Free Press reported
Saturday.
   Other bargaining issues include a UAW proposal to limit to three
weeks a year the amount of time a worker can be laid off because of
falling sales; and a GM proposal to eliminate a plan to hire one
new worker for every two who quit, die or retire. Eliminating the
plan could allow GM to trim its work force by 100,000.
   Less than two hours before Friday's deadline, top union leaders
told local leaders both sides had agreed to keep talking and extend
the existing contract's provisions. Negotiations began in July.
   ``I think we'll have a settlement by the end of the weekend,''
President Jerry Schmidt of UAW Local 1005 in Parma, Ohio, said
after learning of the extension. ``I think most of the members are
happy with the decision'' to extend the talks.
   The UAW in 1970 hit GM with a 69-day strike, the longest against
the automaker except for the 1936-37 sit-down strikes in Flint that
gave birth to the union.
   The negotiations could ultimately affect employees of GM, Ford
and Chrysler Corp., whose UAW national contracts expired at
midnight Friday.
   The union froze negotiations at Ford and Chrysler pending the
outcome of the GM talks. The UAW plans to use an agreement ratified
by GM workers as a pattern for contracts with Ford and Chrysler.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0015 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 0327EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-GulfRdp 5thLd-Writethru a0624 09-16 1029</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf Rdp, 5th Ld-Writethru, a0624,1252</SECOND>
<HEAD>France Promises More Men, Machines; U.N. Condemns Iraqi Raids</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 4 grafs to UPDATE with Security Council condemning
Iraq for raids on foreign compounds in Kuwait. Pickup 4th pvs, `The
Washington...'</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos NY5,6,9, AMM1,7 LON1,DHA1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LISA GENASCI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   France retaliated Saturday for Iraq's raid on its official
residence in Kuwait, expelling dozens of Iraqi diplomats and
civilians and pledging to send warplanes, tanks, helicopters and
4,000 troops to Saudi Arabia.
   Refugees from Kuwait crossed into Saudi Arabia by the hundreds
after Iraqi border guards opened the frontier.
   The U.N. Security Council early Sunday unanimously condemned
Iraq's raids against French and other embassy compounds in Kuwait
and warned further sanctions against Baghdad were likely.
   U.S. diplomats said an aerial blockade and secondary sanctions
against nations flouting the U.N. trade embargo would be considered
urgently, beginning Sunday.
   The Washington Post reported in its Sunday editions that the
U.S. Joint Chiefs of Staff have concluded that American air power -
including a massive bombing campaign against Baghdad that
specifically targets Iraqi President Saddam Hussein and his family
- is the only effective option to force Iraqi forces from Kuwait if
war breaks out.
   Air Force chief of staff Michael J. Dugan said ``air power is
the only answer that's available to our country'' to avoid a bloody
ground war, the newspaper said.
   The French moves came in response to raids by Iraqi troops on
the missions or diplomatic residences of France, Canada and Belgium
Friday. Four French citizens, including the military attache, and
the consuls of five nations including the United States were
detained in the raids.
   The French attache and the consuls were released but France said
the three other French nationals still were being held Saturday.
   Iraq at first denied the raids on the diplomatic compounds
occurred and threatened reciprocal measures. Later, while not
admitting to the raids, Saddam sought to cool French anger by
announcing he would allow elderly and ailing Frenchmen to leave
Iraq and Kuwait on Monday.
   Saddam's offer followed a plea from former Algerian President
Ahmed Ben Bella, who met Saddam in Baghdad on Saturday, the Iraqi
News Agency reported.
   It quoted Saddam as saying he hoped his decision ``would provide
the fair-minded among the French people with the opportunity to
reconsider their actions away from American and Zionist
pressures.''
   French President Francois Mitterrand urged widening the U.N.
economic sanctions on Iraq to include air traffic and punishment of
parties who broke sanctions, although the French request for the
Security Council meeting didn't mention either proposal.
   ``We will do what must be done,'' Mitterrand told reporters
after an emergency Cabinet meeting. ``But we won't be taking
hostages.''
   Iraq's ambassador to France, Abdelrazzek al-Hachimi, said Iraq
``will take reciprocal measures at a diplomatic level'' in response
to the expulsion of Iraqi diplomats. He did not elaborate.
   A spokesman quoted by the Iraqi news agency denied the raid took
place and said a French counselor had been escorted back to the
French compound after he ``was found in the private home of a
female member of Kuwait's former ruling family.''
   The spokesman said France ``shoulders full responsibility for
any reaction this intentional escalation of the situation will lead
to.''
   France's actions represented the strongest move yet by France
against Iraq, a country it long considered a friend and supplied
weapons.
   The Foreign Ministry summoned al-Hachimi Satuday to hear the
expulsion order against 11 embassy personnel, ministry spokesman
Daniel Bernard said.
   France also will expel 26 Iraqi civilian and military personnel
taking training courses in France, and 10 other Iraqis whom
Mitterrand labeled ``secret agents,'' AFP reported, citing
unidentified sources.
   Remaining Iraqi diplomats will be confined to the Paris city
limits, Mitterrand said.
   Iraq on Aug. 24 ordered the 60 embassies in Kuwait to shut and
move their representation to Baghdad. Power and water was cut to
missions that remained open and many were surrounded by Iraqi
troops.
   But 17 missions remained open to show they still recognized
Kuwait as a sovereign nation and to keep in touch with the
foreigners who remain trapped in the emirate.
   About 1,550 Americans are captive in Kuwait and Iraq, and many
men are being held at strategic Iraqi installations to deter any
attack by U.S.-led forces. President Saddam Hussein has allowed
many Western women and children to leave.
   A Saudi government source who had spoken to an official at the
Saudi-Kuwaiti border said he was told that about 1,000 people
crossed over Saturday. There were no details on Iraq's motives for
opening the border.
   Members of one Kuwaiti family that crossed the border and then
traveled 200 miles south to Dhahran said they made the trip because
Iraqi President Saddam Hussein had stated two days ago that all
vehicles with Kuwaiti registry would be permitted to cross into
Saudi Arabia.
   On Saturday, an Iraqi Airways jetliner left London's Gatwick
airport for Baltimore carrying more than 350 evacuees, mostly
American women and children.
   Another U.S.-chartered Iraqi Airways jetliner carrying 165
evacuees flew from Baghdad to London, the U.S. Embassy in London
said. The passengers included 73 Americans, but most of the others
on board had American relatives or were dual passport holders and
were headed for the United States, according to a Gatwick airport
official.
   They were spending the night at a hotel, and were to depart
Sunday afternoon on a chartered flight to Baltimore, a U.S. Embassy
official said.
   Recent escapees from Kuwait have said that the emirate, once a
showcase of stability and wealth, has been ravaged beyond
recognition by Saddam's marauding soldiers and by civilian Iraqi
looters.
   They said, however, tha the most critical problem facing
Kuwaitis was finding enough food to eat. The U.N. embargo has
stopped shipments of food and other supplies into Kuwait and Iraq.
   The Times of London quoted Victor Watkins, an official of the
World Society for the Protection of Animals, as saying Iraqi
soldiers in Kuwait have eaten 70 percent of the edible animals in
Kuwait's zoo. The newspaper did not specify how Watkins got his
information or how many animals were in the zoo.
   Secretary of State James A. Baker III met Saturday with West
German Chancellor Helmut Kohl in his latest effort to gain
financial and military support for the U.S.-led multinational force
in the gulf.
   After the meeting, Kohl announced West Germany had promised $2
billion to the military effort. West Germany, along with Japan, had
been criticized for not doing enough in the campaign against Iraq.
Japan has promised $4 billion in aid.
   The West German constitution prohibits Bonn from sending forces
outside the NATO area, and the Japanese charter prohibits
deployment outside Japanese territory. Both nations, however, are
heavily dependent on imported oil.
   The deployment of 150,000 U.S. troops in Saudi Arabia and about
30 warships in the gulf area is costing the United States $1
billion monthly. The soldiers face about 265,000 Iraqi troops along
Kuwait's border with Saudi Arabia.
   On Friday, Canada, Belgium, Italy and Britain promised to
bolster their forces in the gulf with tanks, combat troops, fighter
planes and more ships.
   The military effort, along with the U.N. economic sanctions,
aims at pressuring Iraq to withdraw from Kuwait, which it invaded
Aug. 2 and annexed in a dispute over oil, land and money.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0016 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 0336EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-UN-Gulf 6thLd-Writethru a0635 09-16 0572</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-UN-Gulf, 6th Ld-Writethru, a0635,0650</SECOND>
<HEAD>Security Council Condemns Iraqi Raids, Further Measures Likely</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 14 grafs to UPDATE with resolution unanimously
approved, comment. Pickup 10th pvs, `The Iraqi...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By VICTORIA GRAHAM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>UNITED NATIONS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Security Council early Sunday
unanimously condemned Iraq's raids on French and other embassy
compounds in Kuwait and warned that further sanctions against
Baghdad were likely.
   U.S. diplomats said an aerial blockade and secondary sanctions
against nations flouting the U.N. trade embargo would be considered
urgently, beginning Sunday.
   The vote was 15-0 in the emergency session sought by France.
   ``By singling out diplomatic missions for attack, Iraq confirms
its preference for instruments of force to instruments of diplomacy
and negotiation,'' said U.S. Ambassador Thomas R. Pickering.
   ``As early as possible ... we must take concrete steps under
Chapter 7 of the U.N. Charter to deal with Iraq's continued
violations of council resolutions, the U.N. Charter and
international law.
   The resolution was the seventh adopted overwhelmingly by the
council since Iraq invaded Kuwait on Aug. 2. The council has
condemned the occupation, demanded release of all foreign hostages,
imposed a trade embargo and approved the use of maritime force to
implement the embargo.
   Numerous speakers said that Iraq had violated international law
on protection of diplomatic missions by cutting off water, power,
food and other resources to foreign missions in Kuwait City.
   Numerous speakers said that Iraq had violated international law
on protection of diplomatic missions by cutting off water, power,
food and other resources to foreign missions in Kuwait City.
   The council expressed outrage at Iraq's violation Friday of the
French, Belgian and Canadian embassy compounds, the detention of
diplomats and kidnapping of three French nationals.
   The vote came about 3 a.m. EDT Sunday after hours of informal
consultations by members of the 15-nation council.
   The resolution ``strongly condemns aggressive acts perpetrated
by Iraq against diplomatic premises and personnel in Kuwait as well
as the abduction of foreign nationals who were present in those
premises.'' The resolution expresses outrage and demands the
immediate release of all foreign nationals.
   In a warning of further action, the resolution says it would
``pursue its consultations urgently in order to take further
concrete measures as soon as possible.''
   President Francois Mitterrand said Saturday that his government
would ask that the U.N. trade embargo be widened to include air
traffic to Iraq and punishment of countries violating the blockade.
   The Iraqi government denied it raided any diplomatic homes or
buildings in Kuwait. Iraq has annexed Kuwait and withdrawn the
diplomatic privileges and immunity of embassies there, ordering
them to move to Baghdad.
   An Iraqi spokesman said there were strict instructions against
entering foreign missions, although they had not been regarded as
diplomatic territory since Aug. 24, according to the Iraqi News
Agency.
   The Iraqi government now calls Kuwait a province of Iraq and
says the 1961 Vienna Conventions on Diplomatic and Consular
relations do not apply.
   The council already has said that force may be used to implement
the sweeping U.N. trade embargo against Iraq in terms of maritime
shipping. But an air embargo, although included in the general U.N.
sanctions, is difficult to implement because forcing planes down
involves military risk and could mean attack, diplomats said.
   An air embargo also would require cooperation of all of Iraq's
neighbors.
   In addition, the diplomats said, drafting the language for such
a blockade would be time-consuming and was unlikely to be supported
by the Soviet Union, China and some Third World nations.
   Iraq has rejected all six previous Security Council resolutions
condemning Iraq's Aug. 2 invasion and occupation of Kuwait.
   The members of the Security Council are Britain, Canada, China,
Colombia, Cuba, Ethiopia, Finland, France, Ivory Coast, Malaysia,
Romania, the Soviet Union, the United States, Yemen and Zaire.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0017 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 0338EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-France 3rdLd-Writethru a0636 09-16 0573</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-France, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0636,0666</SECOND>
<HEAD>RETRANSMITTING a0634 because of satellite outage</HEAD>
<HEAD>France Sends More Troops, Expels Iraqis Following Embassy Raid</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 4th pvs, `The council...' to UPDATE with Security Council
condemning Iraqi actions. Pickup 5th pvs, `In addition...'</NOTE>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf Rdp, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PATRICK McDOWELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Francois Mitterrand reacted sharply
Saturday to an Iraqi raid on the French diplomatic compound in
Kuwait by expelling dozens of Iraqis and dispatching 4,000 troops
to Saudi Arabia.
   ``We will do what must be done,'' Mitterrand told a news
conference following an emergency Cabinet meeting on Saturday
morning.
   Mitterrand also urged the U.N. Security Council to extend the
embargo against Iraq to air shipments and set penalties for
companies or countries violating the sanctions.
   The council voted 15-0 early Sunday to condemn the Iraqi
actions, and it warned that further sanctions against Baghdad were
likely.
   In addition to the soldiers, Mitterrand said France will deploy
warplanes, tanks and helicopters in Saudi Arabia to bolster the
U.S.-led multinational force created after Iraq invaded Kuwait on
Aug. 2.
   The Cabinet meeting came one day after Iraqi troops raided the
diplomatic compounds of France, Canada and Belgium in occupied
Kuwait City. The troops briefly detained five Western consuls -
including an American - and captured four French citizens. Only one
of the four, France's military attache, was freed later.
   The official Iraqi News Agency, monitored in Nicosia, Cyprus,
denied that Iraqi soldiers had raided the diplomatic compounds.
   The news agency said the French government ``shoulders full
responsibility for any reaction this intentional escalation of the
situation will lead to.''
   But it reported later that Iraqi President Saddam Hussein would
allow elderly and ailing Frenchmen banned from leaving Kuwait and
Iraq to depart on Monday.
   Saddam's decision came in response to a plea from former
Algerian President Ahmed Ben Bella, who met the Iraqi leader
Saturday in Baghdad, INA said.
   French officials said they had no official confirmation of the
report.
   The Foreign Ministry summoned Iraqi Ambassador Abdelrazzak
al-Hachimi late Saturday to receive the expulsion order for 11 of
his aides, ministry spokesman Daniel Bernard said.
   Earlier in the day, al-Hachimi said Iraq ``will take reciprocal
measures at the diplomatic level.''
   The French news agency Agence France-Presse said the Iraqi
Embassy personnel to be expelled included six diplomats, three
military attaches and two other officers from the Iraqi military
mission.
   Another 10 Iraqis labeled by Mitterrand as secret agents were to
be expelled as quickly as possible, said AFP citing authorized
sources.
   Mitterrand said 26 other Iraqi military and civilian personnel
receiving training in France at the time of Iraq's invasion of
Kuwait would also be expelled.
   He said the remaining Iraqi diplomats will be confined to Paris.
   ``We won't be taking hostages,'' Mitterrand said. ``The some
1,400 Iraqi civilians (in France) will not be made the object of
these particular measures so long as they conform to our laws.''
   About 400 French nationals remain in Iraq and Kuwait, and some
are being held as human shields at strategic installations to deter
any attack.
   Defense Minister Jean-Pierre Chevenement held talks with his
Saudi counterpart, Prince Sultan, in Jiddah on Saturday to make
arrangements for the French deployment.
   France already has sent 180 paratroopers to the United Arab
Emirates and has nine warships in the region or en route, including
the aircraft carrier Clemenceau.
   The Clemenceau is carrying a unit of 800 men and 48 helicopters.
   France will also be sending 30 warplanes, units from a light
armored division with 48 tanks and part of an artillery regiment
with ground-to-air missiles.
   Iraq invaded Kuwait on Aug. 2, and annexed the oil-rich emirate
several days later. Saddam ordered all diplomatic missions in
Kuwait to close down by Aug. 24 and move operations to Baghdad.
   Iraqi troops have since ringed most of the embassies that defied
the deadline.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0018 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 0546EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i BC-Gulf-DhahranTemp     09-16 0069</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Gulf-Dhahran Temp,0044</SECOND>
<HEAD>Saudi Arabia Temperature</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Here is the sky condition and temperature range forecast for the
24-hour period ending midnight Sunday at Dhahran, staging area for
the U.S. military deployment in Saudi Arabia:
   Clear, Low 77, High 102
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0019 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 1114EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a BC-TrappedBoy 1stLd-Writethru a0643 09-16 0368</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Trapped Boy, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0643,0447</SECOND>
<HEAD>20-Month-Old Boy Rescued From Hole After 14 Hours</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 5-8th grafs pvs, bgng `Fellow firefighter ...,' with 5
grafs to update with boy's listed in fair condition. Picks up 9th
graf pvs, `The toddler...'.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos DX1,2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SCOTT MAXWELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DENVER (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A 20-month-old boy was removed safely from a
narrow, 12-foot-deep foundation hole in a remodeling project at his
parents' home Sunday morning, ending a 14-hour ordeal.
   Oxygen was pumped into the narrow shaft during the overnight
operation to rescue Kevin Davis, while teams from four metropolitan
fire departments dug a parallel rescue shaft and then tunneled some
five feet to the trapped child.
   Kevin, son of Tom and Lisa Davis, was asleep when Denver fireman
Joe Cipri finally broke through and saw his face.
   ``When I went and grabbed his hand, he actually helped himself
out of the hole,'' the smiling Cipri said shortly after the 6 a.m.
rescue.
   The youngster was admitted to Denver General Hospital in fair
condition, Dr. Jack Row said. ``He was alert and responded very
well and normally to his parents,'' Row said.
   Firefighter Kevin Duncan was in the rescue tunnel with Cipri and
did the final, delicate cutting away of the dirt to avoid a
cave-in. He said Kevin ``was in pretty good shape. He fell asleep.
He was pretty much out of it, still in a daze.''
   Firemen strapped Kevin into a splint-like device that cradled
the child's head, neck and upper body as they extricated him from
the narrow shaft.
   The rescuers hooted and yelled with joy as the boy emerged.
   The little blonde boy with a dirt-smudged face was blinking and
calm when placed on a gurney and wheeled to a waiting ambulance. A
police motorcycle escort then led the ambulance to the hospital.
   The toddler fell into the 18-inch wide hole about 4 p.m.
Saturday at an addition being built at his parents' home.
   Policeman W.C. Hoffman said shortly before 1 a.m. that heavy
equipment called a ``Vac-Hoe,'' which works off compressed air and
vacuums out the loose dirt, had finished the rescue vertical shaft
some 5 feet from the exhausted toddler and was drilling across to
the child.
   The excavating machine worked until about eight inches from the
boy. The final breakthrough was done slowly by hand trowels.
   The incident was reminiscent of the October 1987 ordeal of
Jessica McClure, the toddler who spent 58 hours in a well in
Midland, Texas. The arduous effort to free her gripped the nation
and her final emergence safe in the arms of rescue workers was
televised nationally.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0020 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 1122EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Souter Bjt   09-16 0591</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Souter, Bjt,690</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hearings Remove Some of the Mystery Surrounding Souter</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP News Analysis</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RICHARD CARELLI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   David H. Souter, described by one senator
early in his Supreme Court confirmation hearings as ``the stealth
nominee,'' is not the same mystery man he may have been to many
Americans just days ago.
   His two days of nationally televised testimony before the Senate
Judiciary Committee yielded significant insights into Souter the
man and Souter the judge.
   Everyone was not satisfied with his answers, especially his
reluctance to detail his views on abortion. But at least something
was learned of this New Hampshire judge who was virtually unknown
outside his home state when he was tapped by President Bush in
July.
   Perhaps more will be learned Monday - Souter's 51st birthday -
when he returns for a third day of answering senators' questions.
   Here's some of what has been learned so far:
   -Souter says he gave the Bush administration no assurances about
how he would vote on any case, including one involving abortion
rights. And he says he has not made up his mind about how he might
vote if the court were asked to overturn its 1973 decision in Roe
vs. Wade legalizing abortion.
   -He believes the Constitution provides a general right of
privacy even though such a right is not specifically mentioned, and
that the right extends to married women's use of contraceptives.
   -He thinks constitutional provisions should not be interpreted
to mean only what their framers intended, but what they mean in
today's world. That separates him from those conservatives who
espouse an ``original intent'' approach.
   -He disagrees with Justice Antonin Scalia, the high court's most
conservative member, about how judges should search out American
tradition in determining some forms of constitutional protection.
   In a recent decision, Scalia said the father of a child born out
of wedlock is not entitled to certain parental rights because those
rights previously had been recognized only for married people.
Souter said he found that reasoning too confining.
   -He never heard his parents refer to another human being in
racial or ethnic terms. ``I am glad I am conditioned by my
beginnings, and I am glad I do not have to overcome them,'' Souter
told the committee.
   -He is not unflappable. Questioned by Sen. Edward Kennedy,
D-Mass., near the end of Friday's session, Souter for the first
time began answering before his interrogator had finished speaking.
   And he gave an answer that could have been interpreted as
callous. When asked about a quote attributed to him that letting
illiterate people vote ``dilutes the votes of those people who can
read,'' he answered Kennedy by stating, ``That's kind of a
statement of math.''
   -He doesn't think the Supreme Court should stick its nose into
matters where it has no constitutional responsibility to act, but
believes the court sometimes ``is left to act alone when the
political branches do not act beforehand.''
   -He applauds one such example, the court's 1954 decision
outlawing the racial segregation of America's public schools.
   -He does not object when called a conservative judge, and thinks
judges have to guard against using their positions of power to
impose purely personal viewpoints.
   -He is aware that, in these televised hearings, he is speaking
to the American public as well as to 14 committee members. Souter
at one point told Joseph Biden, the Delaware Democrat who chairs
the committee, that an explanation was intended for those not as
familiar with the subject at hand.
   Souter is a well-prepared, attentive and respectful witness who
on occasion shows flashes of a dry wit. His often-lengthy oral
answers, delivered in a Yankee accent that makes Miranda
``Mirander'' and law ``lawr,'' are well organized and impeccably
grammatical.
   A lifelong bachelor, he has tried hard to tell the committee of
the various life experiences that have shaped his view of the
world. The message he and his White House helpers want sent: I am
not a hermit or an isolated scholar.
   It appears the judiciary committee has conceded the point, and
may be on the verge of conceding Souter's confirmation.
   ---
   EDITOR'S NOTE - Richard Carelli has covered the Supreme Court
for The Associated Press since 1976.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0021 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 1123EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--LotteryWin     09-16 0181</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Lottery Win,0179</SECOND>
<HEAD>Official Investigates Lottery - And Wins It</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MANILA, Philippines (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The official appointed by President
Corazon Aquino to investigate alleged rigging of the government
lottery won the top prize Sunday in a drawing televised to restore
public confidence.
   Retired Brig. Gen. Alfredo Lim, director of the National Bureau
of Investigation, held the winning ticket in the weekly lottery
worth $200,000, officials of the Philippine Charity Sweepstakes
Office said.
   Officials said Lim bought a book of 80 tickets while
investigating allegations that the Sept. 1 drawing was rigged.
   A judge and a lawyer who were involved in the Sept. 1 drawing
have been arrested and the board of directors of the weekly
sweepstakes resigned following the scandal.
   Mrs. Aquino, however, refused to accept the resignations of the
board members, who include Environment Secretary Fulgencio
Factoran, Solicitor General Francisco Chavez and the wife of Health
Secretary Alfredo Bengzon.
   Unlike previous drawings, Sunday's drawing was telecast live as
part of the government's effort to convince the public that the
lottery is fair and honest.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0022 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 1123EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--StrikeViolence     09-16 0160</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Strike Violence,0157</SECOND>
<HEAD>Police Fire on Transport Workers, 15 Injured</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DHAKA, Bangladesh (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Police in western Bangladesh opened
fire on transport workers striking against alleged police
harassment and 15 people were injured, according to news reports
Sunday.
   The indefinite strike halted bus traffic in 16 districts and
stranded thousands of bus passengers, the government-owned Dainik
Bangla newspaper reported.
   Police and demonstrators clashed in Pabna, 75 miles northwest of
Dhaka, the paper said, but it did not specify how many of the
injured were protesters and how many were police. It also did not
say how many were wounded by the gunfire.
   Police said they opened fire when the workers tried to storm an
office of the road transport authority.
   On Saturday, 50 people were injured when pro-government workers
and opposition-backed laborers clashed, using homemade bombs and
knives, over the ouster of a union leader in Adamjee, 10 miles
south of Dhaka, police said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0023 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 1129EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--Hungary-Crash     09-16 0115</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Hungary-Crash,0105</SECOND>
<HEAD>MiG-23 Crashes at Air Show, Kills Hungarian Air Force Pilot</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BUDAPEST, Hungary (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Soviet-built MiG-23 crashed Sunday
during an air show at an airport west of Budapest, killing its
Hungarian air force pilot, the Hungarian news agency MTI reported.
   The agency said Maj. Karoly Soproni died when his jet fighter
slammed into the ground at Papa airport, 75 miles west of the
capital.
   There were no other injuries reported. The Defense Ministry has
begun an investigation, MTI said, and has asked members of the
public who took snapshots and video footage of the accident to
submit it to airport authorities.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0024 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 1135EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i BC-GulfRdp -URGENT- a0644 09-16 0681</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Gulf Rdp, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0644,0809</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<HEAD>Bush Message Airs on Iraqi TV; U.N. Condemns Embassy Raids</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 11 grafs to UPDATE with Bush speech on Iraqi
television, Iraqi response, report that Bangladesh embassy
officials' homes raided. Pick up 9th graf pvs, `The Security
Council's...'</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto DHA4, AMM3</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   International indignation mounted Sunday over Iraq's raids on
embassies in occupied Kuwait, with the U.N. Security Council
condemning the incursions and the Soviet Union and Italy sharply
protesting the Iraqi action.
   Iraqi television, meanwhile, aired a videotaped message from
President Bush to the Iraqi people on Sunday, but followed it up
with a stinging response from Baghdad.
   ``Saddam Hussein tells you that this crisis is a struggle
between Iraq and America. In fact, it is Iraq against the world,''
said Bush, standing in front of his desk with the American flag
behind him.
   The lengthy Iraqi response blamed ``imperialist countries'' for
inflaming tensions in the Persian Gulf region. ``He wants to be the
leader of the world,'' Iraqi announcer said of Bush.
   Italy, acting in response to last week's Iraqi raids on
diplomatic premises of France, Canada, Belgium and the Netherlands,
expelled several Iraqi Embassy employees and limited the movement
of others. The Italian Foreign Ministry, in a communique, said all
military officials in the military attache's office at the Iraqi
Embassy in Rome were given 10 days to leave the country.
   Moscow, too, spoke out Sunday against the storming of diplomatic
premises in Kuwait.
   ``The Soviet Union condemns this action by Iraqi occupying
authorities, since it is inadmissible from the viewpoint of
international law,'' said the Soviet Foreign Ministry, as quoted by
the official news agency Tass.
   Prior to the invasion of Kuwait, the Soviet Union was a chief
ally of Iraq.
   Two Tunisian newspapers reported Sunday that Iraqi troops had
entered the Tunisian Embassy in Kuwait as well. The newspapers
Assabah and Le Temps did not cite sources for their reports nor say
when the incident took place.
   In Bangladesh, the Bengali-language newspaper Ittefaq said
soldiers stormed the residences of two embassy officials on Friday.
Acting Foreign Secretary Musafizur Rahman said if the report were
true, Bangladesh would ``strongly condemn'' the action.
   The Security Council's condemnation of Iraq's embassy raids was
unanimous, and the council warned further sanctions against Baghdad
were likely. U.S. diplomats said an aerial blockade and secondary
sanctions against nations flouting the U.N. trade embargo would be
considered urgently, beginning Sunday.
   In another development, Belgium's foreign minister said Sunday
that European Community countries would consider taking new
punitive measures against Iraqi diplomats in response to the
embassy raids in Kuwait.
   The state-owned Middle East News Agency quoted the Belgian
official, Mark Eyskens, as saying the 12-member European Comminuty
is due to meet Monday in Brussels to discuss the measures. Eyskens
spoke after meeting President Hosni Mubarak.
   Sunday also brought indications that the fate of foreigners in
Iraq is becoming more precarious.
   Iraqi soldiers have seized 12 West Germans in Kuwait and have
taken them to an unknown location, bringing to 43 the number of
West Germans held hostage by Iraq, the West German Foreign Ministry
said Sunday.
   Also, a Sri Lankan Cabinet minister was quoted Sunday as saying
Iraq has threatened to cut off food and water to Sri Lankans in
Kuwait unless they are evacuated within five weeks.
   ``The lives of Sri Lankans would be in terrible danger if steps
are not taken to evacuate them within the ultimatium set by Iraq,''
Labor Minister Gamalth Premachandra, who returned last week from a
trip to Kuwait, Iraq and Jordan, told the Sunday Island newspaper.
   Iraq opened its border with Saudi Arabia for the first time in a
month to Kuwaitis, and there was a huge exodus on Saturday and
Sunday. Most left posessions behind, but brought with them tales of
terror and anarchy.
   At least 1,500 refugees were expected to cross on Sunday, border
officials said. At least 1,000 entered Saudi Arabia on Saturday.
   Another U.S.-chartered Iraqi Airways jetliner carrying 165
evacuees flew Saturday from Baghdad to London, the U.S. Embassy in
London said, and was traveling on to the Washington area on Sunday
afternoon.
   The passengers included 73 Americans, but most of the others on
board had American relatives or were dual passport holders and were
headed for the United States, according to a Gatwick airport
official.
   Meanwhile, a senior Iranian delegation arrived in Iraq Sunday
for talks on patching up relations between the two nations.
   The visit follows up on recent talks in Tehran between Iraqi
Foreign Minister Tariq Aziz and his Iranian counterpart, Ali Akbar
Velayati. Aziz was believed to be seeking Iran's cooperation in
beating the United Nations-imposed trade and economic embargo on
Iraq and Kuwait.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0025 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 1137EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>d a AM-BRF--ArsonAssault     09-16 0163</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Arson Assault,0170</SECOND>
<HEAD>Woman Burned to Death; Estranged Husband Charged</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HOUSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A man was charged with capital murder after he
allegedly doused his estranged wife with flammable liquid and set
her ablaze while her 7-year-old daughter watched, police said.
   Cyrus W. Moore, 34, was being held without bond Sunday in the
death of 31-year-old Bobbie Jean Stafford, officials said.
   Fire Department arson investigator Ken Ferro said Moore went to
Ms. Stafford's home Saturday and argued with her. They began to
struggle and Moore poured some type of flammable liquid on Ms.
Stafford and then set her on fire, Ferro said.
   Ms. Stafford was able to scream to her daughter to call 911.
   When authorities arrived, Ms. Stafford was dead and flames had
spread through a bedroom and into the attic.
   Ms. Stafford's daughter and 2-year-old son, who was sleeping,
were not injured.
   Moore was treated at Ben Taub Hospital for burns on his forearms
before being taken into custody by arson investigators.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0026 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 1138EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-China-Tibet     09-16 0259</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-China-Tibet,0284</SECOND>
<HEAD>China Steps Up Security in Tibet</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Chinese authorities have renewed a call for
tighter security measures in the Tibetan capital of Lhasa and
organized more classes on patriotism for Tibet's rebellious monks,
an official report said.
   ``People are concerned about the situation in Lhasa, therefore
to ensure stability in Lhasa is ... of prime importance,'' the
Sept. 5 Tibet Daily quoted Tibet's deputy Communist Party
secretary, Gyaincain Norbu, as saying. The report was seen in
Beijing on Sunday.
   Norbu, who spoke at a meeting of regional party and government
officials, said Lhasa was the target of destructive plots by
separatists.
   He urged tighter administrative control to ensure public
security in the capital, and more classes on patriotism and
national unity for Tibet's Buddhist monks.
   He warned that those who ``refused to comply with the laws and
adhere to their separatist ideas would be penalized, without
exception.''
   It was unclear whether his comments were linked to any recent
disturbance in Lhasa. The party official said ``overall social
order is essential for a stable Lhasa and Asian Games,'' which
start Saturday.
   Scores of people have been killed in pro-independence riots in
Tibet in the past two years. The latest reported unrest was in
June, when 13 monks tried to demonstrate and about 100 university
students held a separate pro-independence rally, according to
Tibetan exiles in neighboring India. Police arrested the monks and
broke up the rally.
   Tens of thousands of Chinese soldiers are stationed in Tibet.
Beijing claims that the strategic mountainous region has been part
of China since the 13th century, but many Tibetans say they enjoyed
de facto independence for many years.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0027 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 1145EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i BC-Gulf-BushMessage 1stLd-Writethru a0642 09-16 0226</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Gulf-Bush Message, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0642,0256</SECOND>
<HEAD>Iraq Broadcasts Bush Video, With Stinging Response</HEAD>
<HEAD>With BC-Gulf Rdp</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BAGHDAD, Iraq (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Iraqi television on Sunday broadcast a
taped message from President Bush to the Iraqi people, but followed
it up with a scathing response from Saddam Hussein.
   ``Iraq stands isolated and alone,'' Bush said in his message
from the Oval Office. ``Saddam Hussein tells you that this crisis
is a struggle between Iraq and America. In fact, it is Iraq against
the world.''
   Iraqi television appeared to have broadcast the message in its
entirety Sunday evening around 7 p.m. local time (11 a.m. EDT).
   ``Iraq finds itself on the brink of war,'' Bush said, standing
in front of his desk with an American flag behind him.
   But, he said, ``war is not inevitable. It is still possible to
bring this crisis to a peaceful end.''
   The Iraqi response, which was far longer than Bush's message,
assailed the ``claims and lies'' of the U.S. president.
   ``The words show he is trying to impose himself on world public
opinion,'' the announcer said in a statement translated by Cable
News Network. It said Bush wanted to be ``the dictator of the whole
world.''
   ``Bush is envious of Iraq and of its people,'' said the Iraqi
message. ``Iraq will always fight him and his allies - the British,
the French and other Europeans.''
   The Iraqi statement included a reiteration of Iraq's historical
claims to Kuwait and Iraqi grievances against Western nations and
Israel.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0028 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 1202EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-US-WorldBank     09-16 0520</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-US-World Bank,650</SECOND>
<NOTE>For Release at 6:30 p.m. EDT.
^Incomes Declining in Third World Countries</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By CARL HARTMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Incomes decreased in Third World countries
last year but in places that did report increases, the rise was
smaller than the year before, the World Bank reported.
   The bank's annual report, made public Sunday, also complained
that military spending in the Third World has risen more than twice
as fast as people's incomes and offered to help governments to curb
it. No figures were given on military expenditures.
   The bank concentraes on what it calls low and middle-income
countries. That includes most of the world: 92 countries with 3.9
billion people ranging in prosperity from Oman, where citizens had
an average income of $5,070 in 1988, to Ethiopia with an average of
only $120. It gave the average U.S. income for the year as $19,780.
   The bank found incomes a little lower last year in 19 heavily
indebted countries from Poland to the Philippines - .1 of 1
percent. In Latin America and the Caribbean the decline was .6 of 1
percent, and .7 of 1 percent in a mixed bag of 22 countries in
Europe, the Middle East and North Africa.
   Africa south of the Sahara showed a small improvement - .3 of 1
percent - after a steady decline through the 1980s. There were
larger increases in South Asia - 2.5 percent - and in East Asia -
3.2 percent - but these increases had been considerably greater
earlier in the decade.
   To help, the bank management headed by President Barber B.
Conable is hoping to lend $21 billion to $24 billion in the 12
months to June 30, 1991. He has promised new emphasis on loans to
reduce poverty and to improve the environment.
   The report did not accuse any specific country of spending too
much on its military forces, but it contained some specific advice
on military matters. Its leaders once considered the subject taboo.
The old line was that the 151 governments who own the bank had to
decide on military matters themselves.
   This report said spending on the military could be considered
unproductive in general and was sometimes especially expensive for
poor countries.
   ``Many countries with very low (individual) incomes devote a
sizeable share of their government budget to defense - despite the
fact that there are many pressing needs in other sectors of the
economy,'' it said.
   ``Military expenditure has increased more than twice as fast
as... income in the developing world since 1960,'' the report
concluded.
   It said that as the world situation changes, governments will
have to take a new look at their spending to improve the welfare of
their citizens. That will include making it clear how much they
have been spending on the military and how effective the spending
has been compared with investment in education and health, it
suggested.
   As the world's biggest lending agency and the biggest single
source of aid money, the bank has great influence with borrowing
governments. Last year it lent money to 79 of them from Algeria to
Zimbabwe. Of those, 47 got loans that pay almost no interest and
requires small installments over 40 years.
   Conable submitted the report Aug. 7, five days after Iraqi
troops went into Kuwait. It covered events only up to June 30 and
did not mention the invasion.
   But at a news conference last week Alex Shakow, the bank's
director of external affairs, said the Gulf crisis should not be
used as an excuse for military spending and that the bank was not
giving up on the principle.
   The United States owns the biggest block of shares in the bank.
The bank's management approved $20.702 billion in loans and made
$1.046 billion in profit over the 12 months up to last July 1. In
the previous year, $21.4 billion worth of loans were approved.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0029 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 1204EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-US-Iraq 1stAdd   09-16 0259</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-US-Iraq, 1st Add,290</SECOND>
<HEAD>WASHN: peaceful end.''</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Bush pulled a paper from his pocket and quoted the Iraqi
president's own words in a Nov. 28, 1988, speech saying ``An Arab
country does not have the right to occupy another Arab country.''
   If Iraq invaded another Arab nation ``We would want Arabs to
send their armies to put things right. If Iraq should become
intoxicated by its power and move to overwhelm another Arab state,
the Arabs would be right to deploy their armies to check it,'' Bush
said.
   Bush taped his eight-minute address last Wednesday after an
Iraqi information minister suggested he would be given time on the
country's television network, as Saddam Hussein has been by
American television.
   The tape, including a voice-over translation and captions in
Arabic, was ferried by a State Department courier to Baghdad and
turned over to the government there by the U.S. charges d'affaires.
   The Iraqi ambassador in Washington had declined to take
possession of it on Thursday, but assured Deputy Secretary of State
Lawrence Eagleburger it would be shown in full on Iraqi television
once it reached Baghdad.
   The Bush broadcast was followed immediately by an even longer
response read by Saddam's spokesman calling it full of lies. The
Iraqi spokesman said Bush was trying to become ``the dictator of
the whole world.''
   In his tape, Bush said he did not want to trade accusations, but
explain to Iraq's people why the world was united in opposition to
Iraq's Aug. 2 invasion and occupation of Kuwait.
   He portrayed the invasion as yet another mistake by the same
leaders who ``plunged'' Iraq into war with Iran in 1980.
   ``You've borne untold suffering and hardship during eight long
years of war with Iran,'' Bush said.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>
<TEXT>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0030 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 1208EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-AlabamaGuard     09-16 0657</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Alabama Guard,0849</SECOND>
<HEAD>National Guard: A Way of Life in Many Alabama Towns</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf Rdp, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PAUL NEWBERRY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MONTGOMERY, Ala. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   When Sgt. Maj. William Weston joined the
Alabama National Guard more than 27 years ago, it seemed as natural
as ... waving the American flag.
   ``I lived in a small town that was very much Guard-oriented,''
said Weston, a native of Brundidge, population 3,200. ``At the time
I joined, my uncle was the company commander. It was the thing to
do back then.''
   As the nation's Guard and reserves play a major role in
America's military response to the Mideast crisis, the call-up is
hitting home.
   Alabama, with a population of about 4 million, has the largest
Army National Guard of any state, with 21,700 members. Sgt. Norman
Arnold, a Guard spokesman, said the next largest state force is
Texas, with 21,400, followed by California, with 21,200. The two
states both trail Alabama even though Texas has more than four
times as many residents and California more than seven times,
according to preliminary 1990 census figures.
   There also are 3,200 members of the Alabama Air National Guard,
making the total strength almost 25,000 men and women, Arnold said.
   About 900 members from several Alabama Army Guard and Air Guard
units have been activated since Iraq invaded Kuwait Aug. 2. But the
only Alabama guardsmen sent to Saudi Arabia so far are about 90
members of the 1241st Postal AG Company from Montgomery.
   Weston, who has been a member of the 31st Area Support Group in
Montgomery since 1972, recalls how prominent the Guard was - and
still is - in small towns like Brundidge, about 60 miles south of
Alabama's capital city.
   ``In many cases, the National Guard armory is the center of
town,'' he said, where dances, reunions and proms are held. ``In
the small towns, we're the only military.''
   Guardsmen usually sign up for six-year hitches and many
re-enlist. Weston estimated that at least half of the soldiers in
the 31st Group have more than 20 years of service.
   ``The day I joined up, there was six of us. We were all
schoolmates. We joined and went off to basic training together,''
he said. ``Of the six who joined with me, I know at least three of
them are still in the Guard.''
   They go through basic training along with regular soldiers, then
join the unit of their choice, perhaps in their hometown or one
that specializes in a skill that will be useful in the civilian
world. After that, guardsmen are required to participate in a
15-day training session each year, in addition to one weekend of
duty each month.
   ``It's more tradition than anything else,'' said Col. Kenneth A.
Blackmon, commander of the 31st. ``We have a lot of fathers and
sons. I've got two sons in the National Guard. As soon as they were
of age, they joined up.''
   In Blackmon's case, the Guard helped pay for his sons to attend
college - a luxury for many families in a state that ranks 43rd in
per capita income. Also, the Guard provide job training in
everything from electronics to truck driving.
   This is the first mobilization of the Alabama Guard for military
duty since 1968, but guardsmen are more than just fighting men and
women. They provided security and cleanup assistance after
floodwaters ravaged the south Alabama town of Elba in March. And
they were there when a killer tornado plowed through Huntsville in
December.
   During the 1960s, guardsmen also were used to quell racial
disturbances that erupted in many locales. Despite the outspoken
segregationist stand of then-Gov. George C. Wallace, President
Kennedy called up the Alabama Guard in 1963 to protect two blacks
who broke the color line at the previously all-white University of
Alabama.
   Lt. Cindy Eskridge, who graduated from officer candidate school
in August, said she and others support President Bush's decision to
send troops to the Middle East after Iraqi dictator Saddam Hussein
ordered the takeover of neighboring Kuwait.
   ``We wouldn't want someone to do to us what he did to Kuwait,''
she said.
   Other Southern states also have large Guard contingents.
Alabama's neighbors - Florida, Mississippi, Georgia and Tennessee -
are at 100 percent or more of their assigned strength, Arnold said.
   ``If you look at those states that have done well in their
recruiting efforts for Guard units, it will run on a line from
Virginia through the Carolinas right along the Deep South,'' Arnold
said. ``Patriotism is still alive and well in Alabama and all
across the Deep South.''
   In Ms. Eskridge's case, she was ``bouncing around, not knowing
what I wanted to do'' when she signed up four years ago. But her
decision ran deeper than that.
   `It was a patriotic thing, a love of country. That had a lot to
do with it, too,'' said Ms. Eskridge. ``It's not just a paycheck.
It's part of serving your country.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0031 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 1212EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Israel-Uprising     09-16 0272</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel-Uprising,0307</SECOND>
<HEAD>Commander Accidentally Kills Soldier; Collaborators Attacked</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An army sergeant on patrol in a Palestinian
village was fatally shot when his commander's rifle accidentally
fired, according to military and newspaper reports Sunday.
   Three Palestinians were reportedly wounded, one seriously, in
attacks on alleged collaborators with Israel.
   An army spokesman said Staff Sgt. David Baruch, 37, was shot
Saturday ``by another officer who was on patrol'' in Kfar Malek, a
village near the occupied West Bank city of Ramallah. He did not
elaborate.
   Israeli newspapers said the accident occurred after the soldiers
tried to catch youths who had hurled stones at them.
   The Maariv newspaper said the commander, a captain, had unloaded
his U.S.-made M-16 rifle, but inadvertently left a bullet in the
chamber. The rifle fired, hitting Baruch in the chest.
   Baruch was taken by helicopter to a hospital in Jerusalem, where
he was pronounced dead, the Haaretz newspaper said.
   The captain, who was not identified, was being questioned by
military police, newspapers reported.
   In the Bureij refugee camp in the Gaza Strip, masked assailants
shot a father and son, Palestinan reports said.
   The reports said Khalil Abu Odeh, 53, was treated at a Gaza
hospital for a bullet wound in the arm. His son, Atef, 30, was hit
in the neck by two bullets and taken to a hospital near Tel Aviv.
   Israel radio said an alleged Palestinian drug dealer was stabbed
by Arabs in Gaza, Palestinian reports said. Drug dealers are often
accused of being informants to the Israelis.
   Since the start of the Palestinian uprising in Dec. 1987, at
least 729 Palestinians have been killed by Israelis. Another 259
Palestinians have been killed by fellow Arabs as alleged
collaborators, and 51 Israelis and foreigners have been slain by
Arabs.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0032 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 1217EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-Suez     09-16 0150</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Suez,0160</SECOND>
<HEAD>Canal To Lose 10 Percent of Revenue</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CAIRO, Egypt (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Suez Canal, one of Egypt's main sources
of badly needed hard currency, is expected to lose 10 percent of
its revenues this year as a result of the U.N. blockade of Iraq, an
official said Sunday.
   Mohammed Izzat Adel, Chairman of the Suez Canal authority, told
the state-owned Middle-East News Agency that before the embargo was
imposed in August, Iraq and Kuwait accounted for the annual export
of seven million tons of oil through the canal.
   Their imports through the international waterway were also
halted as a result of the embargo, imposed after Iraq invaded
Kuwait Aug. 2.
   Adel said the expected decline in revenue was also due to the
dwindling volume of trade between other Persian Gulf countries and
western Europe due to the crisis. He said that volume of trade,
about 40 million tons annually, may fall by 25 percent.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0033 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 1218EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ChipChomped     09-16 0281</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Chip Chomped,0359</SECOND>
<HEAD>One Of Tonight Show Veteran's Prize Chips Gets Chomped</HEAD>
<DATELINE>FORT WAYNE, Ind. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A man visiting a retirement expo spotted
what looked like a tray of free samples of potato chips, so he took
one and started to chew - and nearly broke Myrtle Young's heart.
   Young, 66, started a collection of potato chips that resemble
famous people, animals and objects when she was a chip inspector at
Seyfert's Foods Inc. She and her chips have appeared on ``Late
Night with David Letterman'' and ``The Tonight Show.''
   On Saturday, she had about 75 chips on display, including one
that looked like a perfect sand dollar.
   ``There were quite a few people standing around, and I was
telling them about my chip collection,'' she said. ``This one man
reached through quickly and took one.''
   ``I saw chips laying there as samples, so I picked one up,''
recalled Gregory Hough of Fort Wayne.
   Hough was quickly collared by a salesperson for Seyfert's and
ordered to spit out what remained of the sand dollar chip.
   He said the chip tasted stale; Young estimated it was 2 years
old.
   ``People will say it's only a potato chip,'' Young said. ``But
Mother Nature makes these designs. We go through 250,000 pounds of
potatoes in eight hours. To find something like this is so rare.''
   Her favorite chip resembles a certain ski-jump-nosed comedian.
   ``Boy, I was so glad he did not grab Bob Hope,'' said Young. ``I
keep him in a box. If he had grabbed him, I'd probably be in the
hospital.''
   As for the sand dollar, it cannot be repaired, she said, but ``I
still have the poor, broken chip in a million pieces.''
   But at least Young figures she got a story out of her loss.
   ``I told him that on my TV appearances, the next time they ask
me if someone has ever eaten one of my chips, I'm going to say yes
and tell this story,'' she said. ``Every time he sees a potato
chip, he is going to get a sinking feeling.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0034 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 1230EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Shuttle-Astronauts Bjt   09-16 0611</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Shuttle-Astronauts, Bjt,0755</SECOND>
<HEAD>Astronauts Disappointed but Defend Delayed Launches</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY20 of Sept. 15</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARCIA DUNN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Aerospace Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SPACE CENTER, Houston (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   They've spent months defending
NASA's honor, reassuring worried family members and waiting for
space shuttles to fly again.
   The men and women most affected by the summer's shuttle delays -
the astronauts - are disappointed and unhappy with the recurring
fuel leaks. But they're confident NASA is handling the situation
well. Another try at a shuttle launch is set for this week.
   ``The folks in the office understand that nothing is 100 percent
and that there's a risk involved. Since the Challenger accident, I
think we've made great strides in reducing the risk,'' said Dan
Brandenstein, 47, chief of the astronaut office.
   The mood around astronaut headquarters at Johnson Space Center
in Houston comes nowhere close to matching the despair that
followed the Challenger explosion on Jan. 28, 1986, which killed
all seven on board. Twelve astronauts left that year, an
unprecedented number.
   Still, it's the toughest time for the 82-member corps since
flights resumed two years ago this month. Two of NASA's three
shuttles are grounded by hydrogen leaks, and the flight schedule is
in disarray. A shuttle has not flown since April.
   ``It's one thing if you have one mission that you had to delay
or cancel because of a leak. But we've got several problems stacked
up on top of each other,'' said Bruce Melnick, 40. He is scheduled
to fly next month on Discovery, the only shuttle in which fuel
leaks had not been found.
   The National Aeronautics and Space Administration hopes to
prevent further schedule havoc by launching Columbia on Tuesday.
The countdown got under way Saturday and was proceeding normally
Sunday, NASA said.
   It will be the fourth launch attempt for the astronomy mission,
considered by many astronauts to be ``snakebitten'' and part of
NASA's bout of bad luck.
   At the same time, NASA has endured a searing stream of criticism
from Congress and the rest of America for sending up a flawed
Hubble Space Telescope in April on the last shuttle flight.
   For the astronauts, the verbal assaults hurt.
   ``Nobody likes to work for an agency that you give your heart
for and then wake up with all this negative publicity,'' said Dick
Richards, 44, commander of Discovery's upcoming mission.
   ``There are some things that are screw-ups and there are some
things that you might call an act of God,'' said astronaut Story
Musgrave, 55. ``It's the space business and it's the technology.''
   That technology, as it involves leaking hydrogen, has been a
main topic of conversation at the astronauts' regular Monday
morning meetings since the leaks first were detected in late May.
   Columbia's seven-man crew, in particular, has been teased about
the flight delays. Astronaut superstition holds that having an
astronomer on board is an open invitation to scrubbed launches.
This crew has four astronomers.
   ``See, it all fits,'' Brandenstein said, laughing.
   The standdown has been especially frustrating for the younger
astronauts not yet assigned flights. The longer the delays, the
longer it will be before they fly.
   ``We're all trained and we're ready to go. But we need to get
the missions flying for us to get the opportunity to go,'' said
Andy Allen, 35, a member of the class of 1987.
   The astronauts' concern goes beyond missed flights. Hydrogen is
highly combustible and, if it leaked during liftoff, could cause an
explosion.
   ``When it comes down to T-minus-zero and the engines are running
and the solid rockets are burning and you're inside that thing, you
want to make sure everything's in perfect condition,'' said Bruce
McCandless, 53, who is retiring after 24 years as an astronaut.
   So far, no one has complained to Brandenstein about the delays
or demanded explanations. ``I'd have a lot of people in my office
if we had this leak and they said, `Well, it's not a big leak. Go
launch it,''' he said.
   Before the Challenger accident, that well may have happened,
Richards said. Now, ``the conservatism is there,'' he said.
   Still, being an astronaut means accepting risks and the fact
that ``somewhere down the road, there's probably another
accident,'' Brandenstein said.
   ``Obviously, we're working our fannies off trying to prevent
that and make sure it doesn't happen,'' he said. ``But you've got
to be a realist. There's probably one out there somewhere.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0035 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 1237EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-Saddam'sMessage     09-16 0505</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Saddam's Message,0614</SECOND>
<HEAD>Saddam's Holy War Message Falling Mostly On Deaf Ears</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf Rdp, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By WILLIAM C. MANN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CAIRO, Egypt (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Iraqi President Saddam Hussein is having a
hard time persuading most of his Arab brothers that they should
unite under his leadership in a holy war against foreign invaders.
   Only in Jordan, the Israeli-occupied territories and, to a
lesser degree, Algeria and Yemen has Saddam found receptive
audiences.
   Elsewhere, the distaste for U.S. and other foreign troops facing
Saddam's forces along Saudi Arabia's northern border with Kuwait is
offset by an almost universal aversion to Iraq.
   Saddam so far has been unable to touch the Arab nerve that would
bring into play the Egyptian proverb: ``My brother and me against
my cousin. My cousin and me against the stranger.''
   In a supreme insult, countries of the Gulf Cooperation Council,
who saw member Kuwait fall to Iraqi tanks, are treating Iraq as
they do Israel: its radio and television broadcasts are jammed.
   On Aug. 2, President Hosni Mubarak turned overnight from one of
Saddam's closest friends into his toughest Arab enemy. Now it is
difficult to hear a kind word for Saddam anywhere in Cairo.
   Last week, authorities invoked regulations requiring Iraqi
citizens, as well as Palestinians, Jordanians and Yemenis, to
obtain visas before coming to Egypt.
   The restrictions also apply to Kuwaitis, but a senior security
officer said that was only to ensure Iraq would not sneak in agents
posing as Kuwaitis.
   Also last week, Egypt's 20-man diplomatic staff left Kuwait for
Baghdad but never made it back to Cairo. Authorities at Cairo
International Airport then briefly detained seven Iraqi Embassy
employees and their families trying to make their way home.
   And on Saturday, Egyptian authorities refused to let a leading
left-wing politician and two leftist journalists go to Jordan to
attend a pro-Saddam conference.
   ``Unity should never be achieved by force,'' said Mohamed Said
Saeed of Cairo's al-Ahram Center for Political and Strategic
Studies. ``We all know that the strength of Arabs should lie in
their unity, but ... no one, I think would accept as leader someone
who uses mustard gas against the Kurds in Iraq.
   ``If he treats them this way, how would he treat us?'' he said.
   Although no one in Cairo has expressed support for the Iraqi
takeover of its oil-wealthy neighbor, many are opposed to the
presence of foreign troops in the gulf region.
   On the day the leftist politician, Ibrahim Shukry of the Labor
Party, was barred from leaving, Adel Hussein, editor of the party
newspaper Al-Shaab, wrote:
   ``The deployment of foreign forces was essentially an American
decision. ... Even if Saudi Arabia had refused to let these forces
come, they would have come anyway, killing whoever stood in the
way.
   ``Haven't you learned a lesson from (former President Anwar)
Sadat's experience with U.S. aid? The first time they gave us aid
to make peace with Israel. Today they offer aid to strike Iraq.''
   That was as close as any Egyptians have come to publicly
supporting the Iraqis. It is often coupled with anger that the
United States opposes Iraq's occupation of Kuwait but acquiesces in
Israel's occupation of the West Bank and Gaza.
   But it comes side-by-side with denunciations of Saddam.
   ``Saddam's act is shameful and immoral,'' said Saad el-Din
Ibrahim, sociology professor at the American University in Cairo.
   Nevertheless, he said, ``There is a deep sense of anger and
frustration among the Arabs toward the Americans. They have double
standards in their relationship with the Arabs and Israel.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0036 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 1242EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p AM-PoliticalMalaise     09-16 0693</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Political Malaise,790</SECOND>
<HEAD>Malaise, Cynicism Pervade Public's View of Government</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JIM DRINKARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A not-so-funny thing happened to Bill
Richardson on the way to re-election: he was jeered at a parade in
his New Mexico district.
   The incident occurred a few weeks ago, during a procession in
Taos. Normally, the Democratic congressman said, he gets thunderous
cheers at such events. ``This time, I got some catcalls on the
savings and loan issue,'' he recalled. ``People were not as warm
and as positive, just in general.''
   For Richardson, whose re-election is not in doubt, the incident
was a concrete example of what pollsters and political analysts say
is a widespread disaffection among American voters this election
season.
   For now, the malaise has been pushed into the background by a
preoccupation with the Persian Gulf crisis on the part of
politicians, the news media and the public. But it has not gone
away, according to political professionals.
   The feeling sweeps across the entire political landscape, they
say, reflecting a general cynicism about the ability of government
- local, state or federal - to confront and solve the country's
problems.
   Were it not for the distraction of the gulf crisis, that would
bode ill for incumbents at all levels in the Nov. 6 elections. At
best, the situation makes for a volatility and unpredictability not
seen in years, the analysts said.
   House incumbents, whose re-election rates have been as high as
98 percent recently, still have a formidable advantage over
challengers. Members of Congress have at their disposal
taxpayer-financed mail privileges, a staff to help solve
constituents' problems, ready access to news coverage and an
overwhelming advantage in raising money.
   But at the National Republican Congressional Committee, the
party's Washington-based House campaign apparatus, polls show a
steady erosion over the past two years in the job approval ratings
of Democratic and Republican incumbents, said spokesman Gary Koops.
   And lawmakers who have been home recently are feeling the heat
in a much less academic way.
   ``The American people are mad as hell,'' says Rep. Mickey
Edwards, R-Okla.
   ``It is real. People are angry that Congress isn't doing
anything,'' he said, noting the savings and loan crisis, the
failure to oversee housing programs that helped lead to the HUD
scandal and the rampant federal budget deficit.
   ``Go to any town meeting. Republicans are mad, Democrats are
mad,'' Edwards said.
   To Edwards' list of issues, political analyst Charles Cook adds
a litany of additional sore points: the congressional pay raise,
the proliferation of special-interest money in politics and the
procession of ethics cases on Capitol Hill.
   ``The frustration voters have is, `We have some serious
problems, we elected you to do something, and you're not doing
anything.' It goes beyond just Washington,'' said NRCC chief Ed
Rollins. But he said it is too early to say whether the malaise
will build to the level of 1980, when several prominent incumbent
senators were defeated.
   So far this year, only one incumbent House member has been
defeated in the primary elections, and that was Ohio Republican
Donald ``Buz'' Lukens, who ran for re-election after being
convicted of having sex with a teen-age girl.
   But one indication of voter discontent is what promoters claim
is the increased popularity of moves to limit the terms of state
and national lawmakers. Three states - Oklahoma, Colorado and
California - have ballot initiatives this year to curb the length
of time legislators can serve.
   Terry Considine, a Colorado state senator who is pushing the
initiative in his state, said the disgust with government is
helping his campaign.
   ``There's a great sense that American government doesn't work
very well,'' he said. ``Johnny Carson can get a laugh by saying,
`We'll just let the post office handle that.'''
   Political operatives in 16 other states have contacted him to
ask how to mount term-limitation initiatives of their own,
Considine said.
   ``People are saying it doesn't matter who we elect. We can't
change what happens. The system is broke.''
   A nationwide poll in late August by Market Opinion Research, a
GOP polling firm, found that perceptions and expectations of the
economy had plummeted, and that fortunes of incumbents had fallen
as well, amounting to ``an anti-incumbent undertow.''
   In 1,000 interviews with registered voters, 44 percent said
their representative was more concerned about getting re-elected
than about solving the country's problems, compared with 41 percent
who said their lawmaker was working seriously to solve problems.
The margin of error was plus or minus 3.2 percentage points.
   Richardson said the crisis in the Middle East has even had a
negative effect among voters who believe the government hasn't done
enough to insulate them from higher fuel prices. ``Now I think you
will find a high turnout of mad voters at the polls,'' he said.
   Added Considine: ``I don't think disenchantment with incumbency
is a short-term or temporary phenomenon.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0037 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 1305EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-TerminalDefect     09-16 0602</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Terminal Defect,690</SECOND>
<HEAD>Design Problem Leaves Washington Airport Planners Up in Air</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JIM ABRAMS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Planners at Washington's National Airport are
saddled with what could be a multimillion-dollar blind spot in
their designs for a new terminal building.
   The master plan for the $200 million terminal, it was recently
revealed, contains a fundamental flaw: one of the terminal's wings
will block the control tower's line of sight to part of a runway.
   Airport codes require that the tower must have an unobstructed
view of all runways.
   James A. Wilding, general manager of the Metropolitan Washington
Airports Authority, said his office has been aware of the problem
for several years and believed it could be handled with minimal
adjustments.
   He said the ``ruckus'' only began in recent months when people
seized on the design defect to urge major alterations in the master
plan that would add up to $100 million to the cost of the project.
   Wilding acknowledges, however, that some members of the
authority's board of directors were unaware until recently of the
obscured runway issue. ``Obviously there was a communication
problem.''
   After several weeks of discussions, the authority is leaning
toward relocating the control tower, a solution that will boost the
price tag for the $735 million renovation project by only $15
million or $20 million and not seriously affect the scheduled 1994
completion date.
   Authority spokesman David Hess said focus turned to the blind
spot this spring when the design team, led by well-known architect
Cesar Pelli, started working out details for the 35-gate terminal.
   Wilding thought the dilemma was solvable by repositioning or
lowering the height of the most northerly finger of the terminal.
But some members of the board reportedly were concerned the low
ceilings would be aesthetically unacceptable, and the airlines
balked at changes in carefully worked-out gate assignments.
   ``The carriers were not in favor of that option because it
doesn't provide equal accessibility to all,'' said Dick DeiTos,
executive director of the Metropolitan Washington Airlines
Committee. DeiTos said his organization, which represents the
airlines at National Airport, learned of the line-of-sight problem
about a year ago.
   That was far earlier than for some members of the authority's
board.
   ``I do not recall it being raised,'' said Carrington Williams,
one of 11 board members and chairman of the authority's planning
committee. ``I was surprised at the magnitude of the problem when
it was brought to our attention three or four months ago.''
   One outgrowth of that revelation was a proposal that the entire
terminal be relocated farther to the west, away from the runways.
   An advantage would be that the existing Metro railway station
could then be included in the terminal building, rather than
connected by an enclosed pedestrian walkway as planned.
   On the debit side, such a move would mean a two-to-three-year
delay in completion and an extra $100 million in cost. ``The
airlines would bear the brunt of it,'' DeiTos said, with much of
the expense eventually passed on to consumers.
   The board in late August killed the new terminal idea.
   National, one of the capitol's two main airports along with
Dulles, has been operating out of the same terminal for 49 years.
With nearly 16 million passengers a year and an average 37 flights
landing or taking off every hour during the day, no one questions
the need for major renovation.
   There was also general sympathy for the authority's difficulty
in trying to squeeze a new and larger terminal into only 90 acres
of usable land between a highway and the Potomac River.
   ``In an airport as restricted as National, you've got to expect
some glitches, and there probably will be more,'' said the board's
Williams.
   ``There's not much room to wiggle,'' DeiTos said.
   Wilding said redesign of the northern finger and relocation of a
taxiway on the affected runway are still being considered. But the
final decision, expected in two or three months, appears moving
solidly toward either relocating the control tower or raising the
height of the existing tower on the old terminal.
   Even that would have to gain the approval of the Federal
Aviation Administration and the National Capital Planning
Commission, which oversees any alteration of Washington's
skyscraper-less skyline.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0038 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 1330EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People     09-16 0619</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People,0787</SECOND>
<HEAD>People In The News</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY44</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SNOWMASS VILLAGE, Colo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   You might expect comedians to
make jokes about lawyers - but would you believe a U.S. Supreme
Court justice, even if he was partly serious?
   The problem with lawyers is they tend to make law far more
serious and somber - and unintelligible - than it really is, said
Supreme Court Justice Antonin Scalia. He was in town Friday to
speak to the 92nd annual convention of the Colorado Bar
Association.
   Scalia lectured them on the art of writing legal briefs.
   Briefs, he said, are ``a subject full of paradoxes, not the
least of which is in the name `brief'. ... These things are 50
pages long.''
   The legal term for the written arguments, he said, has its
origin in the ``ancient Saxon word `braf''' and another ancient
word with the same letters arranged slightly differently ``that
means, roughly translated, to go on and on at great length until it
makes you sick.''
   A brief, he said, ``has two parts: a summary of arguments, and
the arguments.'' Judges read the summaries, he said, so they should
be written ``in English.'' The rest can be in ``legal English.''
   Normal English will not do, he said.
   He said ``it is essential to legal English that one write as
pompously as possible, using words and phrases that have long since
disappeared from normal English discourse.''
   ---
   WILSON, N.C. (AP) - Former North Carolina Gov. Jim Hunt suffered
a broken collarbone, multiple broken ribs and bruises when a cow
with a newborn calf charged him on his farm, hospital officials
said.
   ``He is comfortable and stable,'' said Gail Reardon, nursing
supervisor at Wilson Memorial Hospital, where Hunt was taken after
te accident Saturday.
   He was expected to be hospitalized for up to three days for
observation, Ms. Reardon said.
   Hunt, 53, a Democrat, served as governor from 1977 through 1984.
He ran in a highly publicized campaign for the U.S. Senate against
Jesse Helms, R-N.C., in 1984.
   ---
   EVENING SHADE, Ark. (AP) - Yes, Evening Shade is a real town,
not just a fictional setting for Burt Reynolds' new TV series, also
called ``Evening Shade.'' But there are a few differences.
   ``I like the comedy of it, but I didn't like the ideals of some
of those things - drinking, nude ladies,'' said David Cooper,
preacher at the Main Street Church of Christ. ``That's not
characteristic of Evening Shade.''
   The Arkansas Gazette arranged to preview the CBS series in the
home economic classroom at Evening Shade High School. Twenty-seven
people showed up, 8 percent of the town's population of a little
over 300.
   Reynolds plays a cigar-smoking football coach in a small
Arkansas town. His team hasn't won a game in years.
   The real Evening Shade has only a basketball team. ``And we
don't ever lose,'' coach Robin Killian said.
   And townspeople agreed they would not tolerate a coach who
smoked in public.
   The first show opens with a scene of the town strip tease artist
streaking during a high school football game. Some scenes took
place in a barbecue restaurant where people sip beer.
   The real Evening Shade is dry.
   But most residents said they didn't mind the series borrowing
their town's name.
   ``Compared to the rest of the world, the morals around here I
think are higher,'' said school superintendent John Walker.
``Something on the lines of the stripper and the smoking you have
to take in perspective. People realize it's a comedy. We wouldn't
allow it around here but it's just a show.''
   ---
   CHICAGO (AP) - With her full, rich soprano and extraodinary
sensibility, internationally acclaimed diva Jessye Norman has been
able to put her stamp on a wide-ranging of nobly suffering
heroines.
   Norman impressed critics in bringing the tragic title role of
``Alceste'' by Christopher Willibald Gluck to the Civic Opera
House. The production had its Chicago debut Friday.
   However, the avant garde staging by designer and director Robert
Wilson was not so well received. In the Sun-Times, critic Robert C.
Marsh said Wilson's flying clipboards, an ominous cube bouncing on
very visible wires and mimes instead of ballet dancers were odds
with Gluck's perception of opera.
   Norman said she adored Gluck's opera, ``which is wonderfully
written for the voice.''
   Norman, who has built her career almost entirely on
non-mainstream opera roles, said the script of ``Alceste'' was
suited to her voice, which has been characterized as both soprano
and mezzo-soprano.
   ``I want to sing what is comfortable,'' she said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0039 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 1333EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Gulf-Iraq-Bush -URGENT-   09-16 0475</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Iraq-Bush,0571</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<HEAD>Iraq Says Bush's Message ``Full of Lies and Contradictions''</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf Rdp, Bjt</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Stands for digest item slugged AM-Gulf-Bush-TV.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>BAGHDAD, Iraq (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush's message to the Iraqi
people was ``full of lies and contradictions,'' and a ``thundering
rage'' is building up against the United States in the Arab world,
an Iraqi TV commentator said Sunday.
   Mikdad Morad, the announcer who normally reads statements from
President Saddam Hussein, also warned Bush that a showdown in the
Gulf will end ``in a catastrophe'' for U.S. forces.
   ``Bush's message is full of lies and contradictions,'' Morad
said. He spoke immediately after Bush's taped message was broadcast
on Iraqi TV.
   Bush, in his message, told the Iraqis: ``Iraq stands isolated
and alone.''
   ``Saddam Hussein tells you that this crisis is a struggle
between Iraq and America. In fact, it is Iraq against the world,''
said Bush, standing in front of his Oval Office desk with a U.S.
flag behind him. ``Iraq finds itself on the brink of war.''
   But he said, ``war is not inevitable. It is still possible to
bring this crisis to a peaceful end.''
   Morad, reading from a prepared text, responded:
   ``Should war be imposed on us, the Iraqi people will not
hesitate in joining to teach the aggressor an important leasson,
which neither they, nor their allies and agents, will ever forget.
   ``Your aggression,'' Morad told Bush, ``will end in a
catastrophe for your forces.''
   Morad, a familiar face on Iraqi television who was the only
spokesman authorized to release military communiques during the
eight years of war with Iran, ridiculed Bush's references to human
rights and international law.
   ``Contemporary history has not witnessed worse violations of
international law than those committed by the United States and its
ally, Israel,'' he said.
   ``It is enough to recall that the United States has used more
than 60 times the veto to knock down resolutions against Israel at
the U.N. Security Council,'' he said, reapeating Arab criticism
that the United States applies double standards in dealing with the
invasion of Kuwait and the Israeli occupation of Arab territories.
   Morad said Bush was ``shedding crocodile tears for foreigners''
banned from traveling out of Iraq and Kuwait after Saddam's Aug. 2
invasion and subsequent annexation of Kuwait.
   ``They want to leave because of the embargo imposed by the
United States,'' Morad said.
   He said ``Bush went crazy after Iraq entered Kuwait ... because
he feared his oil interests were jeopardized, and not out of
concern for the former Kuwaiti leaders, because he knows from what
rotten background these Croesuses were molded.''
   Croesus was a 6th-century B.C. king famous for his great wealth
and his debauchery.
   Morad said Bush was ``naive when he tried to separate the people
of Iraq from their leader.''
   ``Our leader is the people's son,'' Morad said. ``This attempt
reflects Bush's despair.''
   He said the conflict ``is not at all, as Bush says, one between
Iraq and the United States. It is one between the United States and
the Iraqis, Arabs, Moslems and all the sincere people of the world.
   ``It is a conflict between right and injustice; between obscene
wealth and oppressed people; between imperialism-Zionism and the
deprived people.
   ``It is thundering rage in the Moslem and Islamic world against
the United States,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0040 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 1352EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-WinerySlayings     09-16 0525</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Winery Slayings,0644</SECOND>
<HEAD>Trial Starts Monday For Winery Worker Charged With Seven Murders</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CATALINA ORTIZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN FRANCISCO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Ramon Salcido admits he shot, stabbed and
slashed his wife, two young daughters and four other people to
death in a rampage that terrified the peaceful Northern California
wine country.
   Prosecutors say Salcido should die for his crimes, but the
defense says the 29-year-old winery worker was in a ``psychotic
depression,'' high on drugs and alcohol and legally incapable of
first-degree murder.
   Opening statements in Salcido's trial are set for Monday, 17
months after the grisly slayings touched off a frantic search that
ended with his arrest in his native Mexico.
   Two survivors are among the witnesses expected to testify in the
case in San Mateo County Superior Court. Because of intensive news
coverage, the case was transferred from Sonoma County, where the
crimes occurred.
   ``I think that we have a straightforward case of seven counts of
first-degree murder - that a man set out to and did kill seven
people and tried to kill three others,'' Peter Bumerts, chief
deputy district attorney in Sonoma County, said in a telephone
interview.
   The prosecution will rely chiefly on Salcido himself. Bumerts
said the jury will hear his taped confession to detectives, in
which he describes the April 14, 1989, killings in detail.
   ``I think that statement indicates his premeditation and
deliberation and that these were coldly calculated crimes,'' he
says.
   Defense lawyer Marteen Miller said he will concede Salcido
killed seven people. But the slayings, he insists, were not
first-degree murder because Salcido could not have planned and
willfully carried out the crimes.
   ``His whole world had fallen completely apart,'' Miller said.
Salcido, ``infected with pride of almost psychotic proportions,''
was about to lose his job and his wife, who had found out about a
previous marriage he never bothered to end or tell her about.
   ``He just went into a psychotic depression. ... And on top of
that he became intoxicated and was using cocaine. All this was
manifest in this crazy, bizarre and terrible tragedy,'' Miller
says.
   Salcido is charged with fatally shooting his wife, Angela, 24,
in the couple's Boyes Hot Springs duplex and cutting the throats of
their three daughters and leaving them for dead at a county dump.
Sofia, 4, and Teresa, 22 months, died; Carmina, then 2, survived,
telling detectives, ``Dad hurt me.''
   He also is accused of fatally stabbing his mother-in-law, Marian
Richards, 47, and her 12-year-old daughter, Ruth, in their Cotati
home; killing another Richards daughter, 8-year-old Marie, by
cutting her throat; and shooting to death Tracey Toovey, 35, a
co-worker at the Grand Cru winery in Glen Ellen.
   In addition to being charged with seven murders, Salcido is
being tried for attempted murder in the the attack on Carmina, the
shooting of co-worker Kenneth Butti, who was wounded in the
shoulder, and the alleged attempt to shoot Butti's wife, Terri. The
Buttis are among the prosecution's witnesses; Carmina will not
appear, Bumerts said.
   Salcido told investigators who brought him back from Mexico
within a week of the slayings that Angela Salcido told him their
oldest daughter was not his. He also said that on the night before
the killings the couple quarreled because he had been ordered to
pay child support to a daughter of his first wife. Mrs. Salcido
left the house after the argument.
   He said he then snorted three grams of cocaine and drank
champagne before driving his daughters around, looking for his wife
and deciding to kill his family.
   A note in Spanish was found in Salcido's abandoned car, saying
``Forgive me God, but this law made me do it. We could live better,
me and my children, but what can I do.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0041 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 1354EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-RochesterSlayings     09-16 0286</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Rochester Slayings,0337</SECOND>
<HEAD>Jury Selection To Begin In Serial Killing Case</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Winery Slayings</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By HILARY APPELMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ROCHESTER, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Jury selection is expected to begin
Monday in the case of a paroled child killer charged with the
serial slayings of 11 women over the past 2{ years.
   Arthur J. Shawcross, 45, is charged with murdering 10 women in
Monroe County in western New York. He faces a later trial in
neighboring Wayne County on an 11th murder charge.
   The victims, mostly prostitutes or heavy drug users, were found
dead from March 1988 to January 1990. Most had been strangled or
suffocated, and their bodies dumped near water.
   Authorities have said Shawcross confessed to the slayings
following his arreest Jan. 4 after state police spotted him sitting
near a frozen body.
   At the time of the killings, Shawcross was on parole from an
earlier conviction. He had served 15 years in prison for the 1972
strangling of an 8-year-old girl, and had confessed to killing a
10-year-old boy.
   Shawcross was never tried for the boy's death, and was allowed
to plead guilty to a manslaughter charge in the girl's slaying.
   Although Shawcross had nearly completed his sentence when he was
paroled, his capture set off a heated debate over the effectiveness
of New York's parole system.
   Defense attorneys David Murante and Thomas J. Cocuzzi have said
they will use an insanity defense.
   More than 3,000 potential jurors were called for the trial.
Attorneys pre-screened juror questionnaires over the weekend, and
County Judge Donald Wisner said he hoped to begin questioning of
potential jurors in court on Monday.
   The judge said he hopes to have a jury selected by the end of
the week.
   Murante said last month that he is worried about the effect of
pre-trial publicity on potential jurors.
   ``You hope that people are answering honestly, that they have
the courage and character to say `I can't do this,''' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0042 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 1355EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Soviet-Protest Bjt   09-16 0486</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Protest, Bjt,0564</SECOND>
<HEAD>Protesters Demand Gorbachev, Ryzhkov Resign</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto MOSB2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN IAMS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Tens of thousands of demonstrators marched to the
Kremlin Sunday demanding that President Mikhail S. Gorbachev and
his prime minister resign to take responsibility for the country's
deepening economic crisis.
   ``The Economy is a Disaster,'' read banners carried by the
crowd, which gathered under heavy rain at Gorky Park, crossed the
Moscow River and then headed for central Moscow, where they
listened to speeches just outside Red Square.
   The crowd of about 50,000 followed the same path taken by
demonstrators earlier this year. Many marchers carried white, blue
and red Russian flags from the pre-Bolshevik era, and they shouted
``Gorbachev Resign!'' ``Ryzhkov Resign!''
   Participants in rallies in May and July called for the removal
of Prime Minister Nikolai Ryzhkov and the leadership in general.
But the demand that Gorbachev step down was new.
   Ryzhkov and Gorbachev support different economic programs. The
prime minister favors a more conservative approach to reform, while
Gorbachev has thrown his support behind much of a radical blueprint
for swift and dramatic reform supported by legislators from the
Russian republic.
   Gorbachev, however, has been criticized for not implementing
market reforms sooner. Soviets face shortages of food and many
other products; store shelves are bare.
   Sunday's rally came a day after a leading reformer, Moscow Mayor
Gavriil Popov, said on national television that Ryzhkov's Cabinet
should step aside for a government trusted by the people, the 15
Soviet republics and foreign nations.
   Popov said Ryzhkov had no real plan for reforming the economy.
   Ryzhkov, who appeared in a separate TV program Saturday night,
defended his plan for moderate economic reform and said: ``we will
stop at nothing to implement it.''
   Ryzhkov and Popov were interviewed briefly on the evening news
program Vremya, with longer versions played later on separate
channels.
   Popov, who quit the Communist Party in July and favors the plan
for radical economic reform drawn up by economist Stanislav
Shatalin, said: ``the government did not have, does not have and
does not want to have any real plan for a transition to the genuine
market.''
   He said Ryzkhov's government was responsible for the deplorable
state of the Soviet economy, the lack of consumer goods and a
growing deficit.
   ``We are sick and tired of empty shops and devalued money, we
want no more crises,'' Popov said.
   Shatalin's plan, approved by Russian legislators, calls for
transferring most economic authority from the national government
to the republics, who then could move independently toward market
economies.
   Ryzhkov's plan calls for keeping central control over the
economy through 1991, and a much slower transition to a
market-based economy.
   The rally also came two days after a constitutional committee
ruled against a decree to give the Soviet government - rather than
the Moscow government headed by Popov - the authority to allow or
ban rallies in the center of the Soviet capital. Gobachev issued
the decree in April.
   The official Tass news agency said the Constitutional Compliance
Committee ruled Gorbachev's decree unconstitutional because it
``narrowed'' the powers of the Russian Republic - of which Moscow
is the capital - and the city council, headed by Popov.
   The May and July rallies were slightly larger than Sunday's
protest.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0043 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 1401EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-Iraq-Iran     09-16 0425</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Iraq-Iran,0493</SECOND>
<HEAD>Iranian Delegation Arrives in Iraq</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf Rdp, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TERRIL JONES</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NICOSIA, Cyprus (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A senior Iranian delegation arrived in
Iraq Sunday, a sign of the growing rapprochement between the two
longtime foes that could help Baghdad get around U.N. sanctions.
   The Iranian delegation was led by Manushahr Mutaqi, the deputy
foreign minister for international relations, the official Iraqi
News Agency reported.
   The agency, monitored in Nicosia, Cyprus, quoted Mutaqi as
saying issues including prisoner-of-war exchanges, border matters
and the reopening of embassies would be discussed.
   The Iranian visit follows last Sunday's ground-breaking visit to
Tehran by Iraq's foreign minister and deputy prime minister, Tariq
Aziz, the first high-ranking Iraqi official to visit Iran in more
than a decade.
   He was believed to have sought Iran's cooperation in
circumventing the economic embargo imposed by the U.N. Security
Council.
   In the wake of the Aziz visit, a source in the Iranian capital
said Iran agreed to ship consignments of food and medicine to Iraq
as ``humanitarian aid'' in return for 200,000 barrels of refined
oil a day.
   The Tehran Times daily newspaper, which is close to the Iranian
government, denied that last week. But Western and Arab oil experts
have said they believed such a deal had been made.
   Aziz's visit was also aimed at negotating a formal treaty to end
the Iran-Iraq war. A U.N.-sponsored cease-fire took hold in August
1988.
   The Iraqi official also said after his visit that the two
countries had agreed to revive full diplomatic ties, essentially
reopening the embassies in their capitals that were closed during
the war.
   Iran's relations with Iraq have improved dramatically since
Iraq's invasion of Kuwait on Aug. 2.
   Iraqi President Saddam Hussein withdrew his troops from
territory occupied in the closing stages of the Iran-Iraq war. The
move freed up tens of thousands of Iraqi troops for the
confrontation with the U.S. military buildup in Saudi Arabia.
   The two sides have already repatriated thousands of prisoners of
war and Iraq agreed to share soverignty of the Shatt-al-Arab
waterway, the southern border between the two states.
   Iran has criticized the invasion of Kuwait, but has also become
increasingly vocal in its attacks on the U.S. military deployment
in Saudi Arabia.
   ``By nature, the presence of the United States in any part of
the world will automatically create tension,'' Tehran's radical
Abrar daily said Sunday. ``The U.S. presence in Islamic lands will
bring nothing for Moslems but corruption and destruction.''
   Also Sunday, 168 of the 270 members of Iran's Majlis, or
Parliament, signed a document supporting Ayatollah Ali Khamenei's
call last week for a holy war against the United States, Iran's
official Islamic Republic News Agency said.
   President Hashemi Rafsanjani also said any permanent stationing
of U.S. forces in the Persian Gulf region would be ``in no way
acceptable,'' the agency said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0044 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 1418EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Gulf-Bush-IraqiTV 3rdLd-Writethru a0676 09-16 0647</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Bush-Iraqi TV, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0676,760</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush Tells Iraqi TV Viewers War Is Near Because of Saddam</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: New throughout with additional quotes from Bush, Iraqi
rebuttal</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By CHRISTOPHER CONNELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush warned the Iraqi people in a
television broadcast Sunday they stand ``on the brink of war''
because Saddam Hussein misled his countrymen into invading Kuwait.
   Bush, in a taped message from the Oval Office, said, ``Iraq
stands isolated and alone.''
   ``Saddam Hussein tells you that this crisis is a struggle
between Iraq and America. In fact, it is Iraq against the world,''
said Bush, standing in front of his desk with the American flag
behind him.
   Iraqi television broadcast the Bush message Sunday evening
around 7 p.m. local time (11 a.m. EDT).
   The White House had expressed skepticism beforehand that Saddam
would let his people hear Bush's words. But the Iraqi president
kept a promise to broadcast the taped message in prime time.
   ``Our embassy in Iraq monitored this and it appears that it ran
in its entirety,'' said a White House spokesman, Sean Walsh.
   The eight-minute broadcast was followed immediately by an even
longer rejoinder from Saddam, read by a spokesman, that met Bush's
words of warning with a mixture of ridicule, disdain and defiance.
   ``Iraq finds itself on the brink of war,'' Bush said. But ``war
is not inevitable. It is still possible to bring this crisis to a
peaceful end.''
   Bush pulled a paper from his pocket and quoted the Iraqi
president's own words in a Nov. 28, 1988, speech saying ``An Arab
country does not have the right to occupy another Arab country.''
   If Iraq invaded another Arab nation, ``We would want Arabs to
send their armies to put things right. If Iraq should become
intoxicated by its power and move to overwhelm another Arab state,
the Arabs would be right to deploy their armies to check it,'' Bush
quoted Saddam.
   Iraq invaded Kuwait on Aug. 2, prompting the U.S.-led military
buildup in the Middle East and a United Nations-sanctioned economic
embargo. Bush told the Iraqi people Saddam had misled them.
   ``Saddam Hussein has told you that Iraqi troops were invited
into Kuwait. That's not true,'' Bush said. ``Your own returning
soldiers will tell you the Kuwaitis are fighting valiantly in any
way they can.''
   Bush taped his address last Wednesday after an Iraqi information
minister suggested Bush would be given time on the country's
television network, as Saddam Hussein has been by American
television.
   The tape, including a voice-over translation and captions in
Arabic, was ferried by a State Department courier to Baghdad and
turned over to the government there.
   The Iraqi ambassador in Washington had declined to take
possession of it Thursday, but assured Deputy Secretary of State
Lawrence Eagleburger it would be shown in full on Iraqi television
once it reached Baghdad.
   The Iraqi rebuttal called Bush's remarks full of lies. Citing
Bush's call in a recent speech for ``a new world order,'' the
statement said Bush fancied himself ``the dictator of the whole
world.''
   ``Bush was trying to fool the Iraqi people with certain words,''
it said.
   It offered no reply to what Bush called Iraq's ``barbaric''
holding of foreign hostages in Iraq and Kuwait. But it scoffed at
Bush's words about the ``shameful'' plight of foreign workers
stranded as refugees on Iraq's borders.
   These workers left Kuwait ``because of the U.S. threats of
war,'' Saddam said through the spokesman.
   To Bush's argument that the world was united against Iraq, the
Iraqi leader called it ``a dispute between right and wrong.'' The
struggle pits ``the United States and its allies ... against Iraq
and all Arabs and all Muslims and all believers in the whole
world.''
   And it said Bush was naive to think he could drive a wedge
between the Iraqi people and their president.
   In his tape, Bush said he did not want to trade accusations, but
explain to Iraq's people why the world was united in opposition to
Iraq's invasion.
   He portrayed the invasion as yet another mistake by the same
leaders who ``plunged'' Iraq into war with Iran in 1980.
   ``You've borne untold suffering and hardship during eight long
years of war with Iran,'' Bush said. ``Once again, the same Iraqi
leadership has miscalculated. Once again, the Iraqi people face
tragedy.''
   The United Nations sanctions against Iraq are meant ``not to
punish the Iraqi people, but as a peaceful means to convince your
leadership to withdraw rom Kuwait. The decision is in the hands of
Saddam Hussein.''
   ``No one - not the American people, not this president - wants
war. But there are times when a country, when all countries ...
must stand against aggression,'' Bush said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0045 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 1424EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-Shipping     09-16 0443</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Shipping,0541</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.S.-Led Fleet Tightens Noose, No Sign Saddam Will Take It On</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf Rdp, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By NABILA MEGALLI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MANAMA, Bahrain (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The U.S.-led naval blockade of Iraq is
squeezing Saddam Hussein, but the Iraqi leader has shown no sign he
intends to take on the Western armada and shipping executives say
he can survive without doing so.
   There are almost as many warships in the Persian Gulf as the 60
merchant ships that on average plow the strategic waterway each
day. And more warships are on their way.
   Since the U.N. embargo was clamped on Iraq Aug. 6, four days
after it invaded Kuwait, the U.S. Navy has challenged nearly 1,000
vessels and boarded more than 40.
   A merchant vessel is challenged every 10-15 minutes, either by
warships, naval helicopters or the three British Nimrod maritime
reconnaissance jets based in Oman, naval officials said.
   Shipping monitors report being overwhelmed by round-the-clock
radio challenges to tankers and freighters.
   Only a handful of Iraqi ships have sailed from Umm Qasr, Iraq's
main port in the northern Gulf, since the embargo was imposed.
   When challenged, the Iraqi vessels have backed down.
   ``Saddam Hussein is smart,'' said a gulf-based foreign shipping
executive. ``Why should he risk provoking all that naval might, and
risk a military strike in which he loses Kuwait, when he can
survive with Kuwait in his hands? He'll sit tight.''
   Earlier this month, Rear Adm. Jerry L. Unruh, commander of the
U.S. battle group led by the aircraft carrier Independence
patrolling the Gulf of Oman, also said Iraqi vessels were making no
attempt to challenge the blockade.
   Baghdad, he said, seemed to be trying to wait out the crisis,
avoiding anything that could provoke U.S. forces to take military
action.
   The U.N. embargo has blocked all oil exports from Iraq and
occupied Kuwait, cutting off an estimated 4 million barrels a day.
   Saddam has introduced rationing on some foodstuffs. Baghdad's
Trade Ministry has halved monthly allowances of rice, sugar and
cooking oil.
   But some experts believe Iraq has food stocks that could last
several months. And neighboring Iran is reported to have agreed to
allow ``humanitarian'' food and medicine shipments across the
border in return for 200,000 barrels of free refined oil a day.
   Three loaded Iraqi oil tankers - the Hittin and Al-Qadissiyah,
both 150,000 tons, and the 35,000-ton Rumaila - are reported to be
moored at Umm Qasr.
   To get to the open sea, they would first have to sneak past
British, and possibly French, warships that patrol the northern end
of the Gulf. American ships patrol the southern end, around the
Strait of Hormuz, the only way in and out of the Gulf.
   This arrangement, decided upon by Western naval officers last
week, was apparently aimed at putting non-U.S. warships in a
position to challenge vessels leaving Iraq, thus stressing the
multinational makeup of the armada.
   The warships have been authorized by the United Nations to use
minimal force if Iraqi ships resist challenges. U.S. officials have
indicated their ships may shoot off the steering gear of any vessel
that refuses to be inspected.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0046 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 1524EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-ForestRally     09-16 0442</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Forest Rally,490</SECOND>
<HEAD>Environmentalists Protest Forest Bills in Congress</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SCOTT SONNER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   About 500 environmentalists rallied at the
Capitol on Sunday to protest congressional proposals they say would
further eliminate the shrinking supply of the nation's oldest
forests.
   The main group, Save America's Forests, voiced support for a
proposal by Rep. Jim Jontz, D-Ind., that would prohibit logging in
a forest preserve covering as much as 8 million acres of old-growth
and some second-growth forests.
   The group opposes a more moderate forest protection bill by Rep.
Bruce Vento, D-Minn., which last week passed the House Interior
subcommittee.
   ``We are at a crossroads,'' said Mark Winstein, a spokesman for
the group. ``The timber industry lobby has a national agenda as
they grab the wealth of public lands, operating from a national
power base in Congress.''
   Winstein said he spoke for more than 30 organizations
representing nearly 150,000 members in 18 states.
   The demonstrators sang songs, chanted slogans and toted banners
calling for the preservation of forests and an end to clear
cutting, a practice used to harvest all the trees in a given area.
   Leaders also criticized mainstream environmental groups, such as
the Sierra Club and the National Wildlife Federation, for failing
to take strong enough stands in political fights over the
Northwest's old-growth trees and the northern spotted owl.
   ``They have a lot of muscle. We are asking them to flex it,''
Winstein said.
   Loggers and industry officials from the Pacific Northwest
scheduled their own rally for Capitol Hill on Monday to voice
opposition to pro-environmental legislation that would restrict
logging and lock up huge tracts of old-growth forests to help save
the spotted owl from extinction.
   Jackie Lang, state coordinator of the Oregon Lands Coalition,
said about 200 industry workers and community leaders made the trip
to help ``put faces'' on the unemployment figures used when
discussing the cost of banning logging in Northwest forests.
   ``We're here now because our backs are really against the
wall,'' Lang said Sunday. ``While we have been out working for a
living, the radical environmentalists have been out working the
system.''
   Save America's Forests advocates an end to logging all
old-growth forests as well as a ban on clear cutting and road
construction in national forests. It also wants to include private
lands in a new federal prohibition on exports of unprocessed logs
from most public lands.
   Andy Mahler, president of Indiana's Protect Our Woods, said
national environmental groups must do more to educate the public
about logging on U.S. Forest Service lands.
   ``Most people still don't realize there is logging going on in
national forests,'' he said.
   Tim Hermach, president of the Native Forest Council based in
Eugene, Ore., said the world is united in a call to stop cutting
the trees of the Brazilian rain forests.
   ``But the United States has logged 90 percent of its timber and
Brazil has only logged 15 percent of its timber. It is hypocritical
for Americans to tell Brazil to stop all logging,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0047 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 1546EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Gulf-Israel     09-16 0490</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Israel,580</SECOND>
<HEAD>Israel Wants Equal Treatment If Congress OKs New Saudi Arms Deal</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RUTH SINAI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WYE PLANTATION, Md. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Israeli Defense Minister Moshe Arens
said Sunday he would ask the administration to provide his country
with the means to match a massive arms deal being prepared for
Saudi Arabia.
   Arens said Israel has not yet been consulted about the Saudi
package, estimated to contain $20 billion worth of sophisticated
arms, which State and Defense department officials are preparing to
submit for approval to Congress.
   ``We hope there'll be a discussion with us,'' Arens said in a
speech to a conference of the Washington Institute for Near East
Studies. ``There is no one in Washington who believes this (the
Saudi sale) could have a positive effect on Israel.''
   Arens is meeting Monday in Washington with Defense Secretary
Dick Cheney. The United States is Israel's largest arms supplier,
giving Israel $1.8 billion worth of weapons annually.
   If the United States goes through with the Saudi sale, Arens
said, ``We would have to see what could be done to provide the
necessary equilibrium'' for Israel.
   Arens did not elaborate. But Israeli sources say Arens intends
to ask the United States for money to help Israel's own defense
industry develop modern weaponry, in addition to U.S.-made weapons
such as F-15 and F-16 fighter planes.
   Arens also wants the United States to provide Israel with access
to its spy satellite photographs of Iraq and other Arab states, the
sources said.
   Israel would like direct access to raw satellite photos but has
received indications that the United States would not be willing to
supply it, the sources said.
   Israel will ask for processed satellite photos or any other
intelligence information the United States is willing to provide,
the sources said.
   Arens said there was no way Israel could afford to pay for the
amounts of weapons oil-rich Saudi Arabia is buying here.
   Instead, Israel will have to rely increasingly on its own
defense industries, he said.
   Israel has already begun doing that in order to maintain its
qualitative edge over the far larger Arab armies that surround it,
he said.
   The need to boost the Israeli defense industries has become
particularly acute in recent years because the United States has
been supplying the Arab states with the same weapons they sell
Israel, Arens said.
   Arens warned that the Aug. 2 Iraqi invasion of Kuwait and the
resultant arms sales to the Saudis and other U.S. allies were
escalating the arms race in the Mideast and destabilizing the
region.
   He said Israel would be willing to discuss a cessation of the
arms flow into the area, if its Arab enemies did the same.
   The United States has asked Israel to refrain from intervening
in the gulf crisis and has praised Israeli officials for keeping a
low profile.
   Israel is maintaining a high level of readiness in case Iraqi
President Saddam Hussein decides to fulfill his threat to attack
the Jewish state as a means of uniting the Arab world behind him,
Arens said.
   He praised President Bush for his ``remarkable`` success in
uniting much of the world against Iraq, including Syria and Egypt.
   Arens said he hoped the rapprochement between Syria and the
United States leads to peace with Israel, although he expressed
doubts it would.
   Arens also plans to meet with Bush's national security adviser,
Brent Scowcroft, and congressional leaders during his two-day visit
to Washington.
   There were no plans for him to meet with Bush.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0048 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 1558EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-US-Gulf 1stLd-Writethru a0699 09-16 0688</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-US-Gulf, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0699,790</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dole Says Allied Aid for Middle East Will Help Tough Budget Talks</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: SUBS 23rd graf pvs, bgng: Foley, meanwhile, with 4 grafs to
restate Carter's position and add Carter quotes.</NOTE>
<HEAD>By LAWRENCE L. KNUTSON</HEAD>
<HEAD>Associated Press Writer</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Senate Republican leader Bob Dole said Sunday
that financial contributions by other nations in support of the
U.S.-led drive against Iraq was welcome news for budget negotiators
struggling to assemble a deficit-reduction package.
   ``We're going to score it one way or the other,'' Dole said of
the contributions from such nations as Saudi Arabia, West Germany
and Japan. Secretary of State James A. Baker III returned home from
a 11-day trip early Sunday, his pockets bulging with $14 billion in
new aid pledges.
   ``I don't know who gets the check. ... But we understand that it
will have an impact on what we finally do in the budget summit.''
   In another development Sunday, President Bush warned the Iraqi
people in a television broadcast that they stand ``on the brink of
war'' because Saddam Hussein invaded Kuwait.
   But Bush, in a taped message from the Oval Office, said ``War is
not inevitable. It is still possible to bring this crisis to a
peaceful end.''
   Bush's eight-minute talk was broadcast on Iraqi television,
apparently in its entirety.
   The White House, meanwhile, applauded the United Nations
Security Council's unanimous condemnation Sunday of Iraq's raids on
the embassy compounds of France and other nations in Kuwait.
   ``We fully support the actions taken by the United Nations,''
administration spokesman Sean Walsh said.
   U.S. diplomats at the United Nations said the Security Council
now would consider an aerial blockade against Iraq and secondary
sanctions against nations flouting the U.N.trade embargo.
   Dole and House Speaker Thomas Foley, D-Wash., appearing on the
NBC-TV's ``Meet the Press'' program, said there was widespread
agreement in Congress and across the country generally that the
United States should not have to shoulder all of the costs of
deterring Saddam Hussein.
   ``There is no question that there's a feeling in the country and
in the Congress that we shouldn't bear these burdens alone, either
the military side of it or the financial side of it,'' Foley said.
   But Dole, describing the initial response as ``certainly good
news,'' questioned whether support will remain strong if it becomes
necessary to keep U.S. military forces in the Persian Gulf region
for an extended period.
   During his trip, Baker received pledges of $12 billion from
three oil-rich Arab nations: Saudi Arabia, the United Arab Emirates
and the Kuwaiti rulers overthrown and exiled by Hussein.
   West Germany extended nearly $2 billion for military aid and
economic assistance to countries affected by the economic embargo
on Iraq. Egypt and Syria said they would send more troops. Italy
volunteered $145 million and a squadron of Tornados. Britain and
France said they will send troops.
   The U.S. end of the military buildup is costing an estimated $1
billion a month. This enormous outlay is taking place as
congressional and White House negotiators try to reach agreement on
paring the federal deficit by $50 billion this year, $500 billion
over five years.
   Bush's national security adviser, Brent Scowcroft, interviewed
Sunday on the CBS-TV program ``Face the Nation,'' made clear that
the military wbuildup in the gulf is aimed at impressing Saddam.
   ``We want him to know we are serious,'' Scowcroft said.
   But he distanced the administration from comments by Gen.
Michael J. Dugan, the Air Force chief of staff, who was quoted in
Sunday editions of The Washington Post as saying U.S. military
planners believed that if war breaks out, the only effective tactic
was to hit Baghdad with massive air trikes that target Saddam
personally.
   ``I would just point out that General Dugan is not in the chain
of command and he does not speak for the administration,''
Scowcroft said.
   But he said contingency planning was developing ``for anything
that might happen.''
   Scowcroft hailed the recent increase in concrete support by U.S.
allies for the drive against Iraq.
   ``I think it's a very heartwarming example of united action
against aggression,'' Scowcroft said.
   Foley, meanwhile, disagreed with former President Jimmy Carter,
who said the United States may have to drive Iraq from Kuwait with
military force.
   ``I think the time is way too early to make a decision of that
kind,'' Foley said. ``The strong support the president's had in the
Middle East is based on the fact that he's been deliberate, he's
been careful, he's been focused on the goals.''
   Carter, appearing on CNN's ``Newsmaker Sunday'' program, said
Iraq should be pushed out of Kuwait militarily if the punitive
effect of economic sanctions do not succeed.
   ``But my hope is he will withdraw (and) accept a compromise
worked out by the Arab community that will be easier for him to
accept than a solution enforced on him by the United States and
other Western powers,'' Carter said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0049 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 1620EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-GainesvilleSlayings     09-16 0318</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gainesville Slayings,0382</SECOND>
<HEAD>Report: Bloody Gloves Found in Slaying Suspect's Home</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RON WORD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>GAINESVILLE, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   State police found bloodstained gloves
and a .38-caliber handgun in the home of a suspect in the stabbing
deaths of five college students, a newspaper reported Sunday.
   But Edward Lewis Humphrey's grandmother said the blood and
gloves found in a search of her home in Indialantic on Sept. 6 were
hers, The Gainesville Sun reported. She also said the pistol has
been in the house for years.
   Police said Humphrey, 18, is one of eight suspects in the
murders of five students in off-campus apartments Aug. 26 to Aug.
28. Three of the students were mutilated, including one who was
decapitated.
   Humphrey has not been charged in the slayings. He is being held
in lieu of $1 million bond in the Brevard County Jail in Sharpes on
charges he assaulted his 79-year-old grandmother on Aug. 30,
shortly after he had returned from Gainesville, where he was a
University of Florida freshman. He also faces warrants in an Aug.
25 assault on two male University of Florida students and an
October 1988 armed burglary and attempted rape in Indian River
County.
   Humphrey's grandmother, Elna Hlavaty, said the gloves found
during the police search were stained with her blood when she fell
and cut her head.
   When Humphrey was arrested, his grandmother told police he had
choked her and punched her in the face. She later said her injuries
were accidental and has asked that the charges be dropped.
   Lt. Spencer Mann, a spokesman for the Alachua County Sheriff's
Office, refused to comment on the newspaper report Sunday.
   Mann said Sunday there are no major developments in the case and
no arrests imminent.
   ``I am not expecting any major breaks any time soon,'' Mann
said.
   The only other suspect publicly identified is Stephen Michael
Bates, 30, being held in Polk County. He is charged with entering
an apartment east of Lakeland and threatening a woman and her
teen-age daughter with a knife. He is being held on $100,500 bond.
   A search of his home yielded a hangman's noose, two pairs of
women's panties, pornography, satanic writings and a book on Jack
the Ripper.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0050 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 1636EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-VitaminStandards-Suit     09-16 0497</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Vitamin Standards-Suit,570</SECOND>
<HEAD>Leading Researcher Sues Science Academy</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The National Academy of Sciences is fighting a
$500,000 lawsuit that claims it plagiarized the writings of a
nutrition researcher that it earlier had rejected.
   Victor Herbert, a lawyer and physician who filed the suit in
U.S. District Court, charged that the academy copied figures
verbatim on work he had done to update published recommended
dietary allowances (RDAs), after earlier trying to discredit the
work.
   ``Dr. Herbert is a great promoter of nutrition science,''
Herbert's attorney, Michael Botts, said in a telephone interview
Sunday from Kansas City, Mo. ``It isn't just a moral point at all.
(The academy) took his work and then went out and sold it. The
academy made in the neighborhood of a half million dollars off of
this work.''
   RDAs form the foundation for determining the nutritional needs
of schoolchildren, food stamp recipients and other federally funded
supplemental programs. The academy sells lists of the standards to
libraries, medical schools, doctors, dietitians and nutritionists.
   To update the RDAs in the mid-1980s, the science academy, an
independent federal agency chartered by Congress, selected Herbert
and nine other prominent nutrition scientists.
   Using a $650,000 grant from the National Institutes of Health,
the committee's produced a document that discussed the sciences of
each 18 essential vitamins and minerals that each person is
encouraged to eat each day.
   Botts claimed the academy tinkered with the RDAs document before
publishing it in October 1989, damaging the ``integrity of the
authors' work'' and destroying the quality.
   The document included copyrighted material Herbert wrote on iron
and on the vitamins B12 and folate, or folic acid, Botts said.
   Lawyers for the academy filed a motion for dismissal last week
and a hearing on the motion has been scheduled for Oct. 17. The
academy contends that if there is copyright infringement, the
federal government should be the defendant in the suit, which was
filed in February.
   Botts said the committee completed its work and passed peer
review, and a September 1985 publication date was scheduled. The
panel was prepared to recommend lower levels of vitamins A and C
than what had been suggested earlier.
   But according to Botts, the academy gave the panel an ultimatum:
keep the RDAs for vitamins A and C the same, while adding a
footnote to the table at the end of the book.
   When the academy and committee disagreed over the wording of the
footnote, the academy refused to publish the work and disbanded the
group, Botts said.
   Botts described the disagreement as ``a conflict in nutrition
between those who promote pop nutrition,'' such as those who call
for high doses of fiber and vitamin C versus those who say there is
harm in ingesting too much fiber and vitamin C.
   ``That's nonsense,'' Calvin H. Cobb Jr., a lawyer representing
the academy, was quoted as saying in Saturday editions of The
Washington Post. ``The complaint has no merit.''
   The National Institutes of Health in 1986 told the academy it
must fulfill the terms of the contract or return the money. Botts
said NIH officials reviewed the committee's report and wanted it to
be published but the academy said it needed $160,000 to select a
subcommittee to update the earlier work.
   Meanwhile, Botts said Herbert's work appeared in a nutrition
education journal in 1987.
   The academy published a 10th edition revision in October 1989.
Botts said the subcommittee was listed as author, although the work
included Herbert's writings.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0051 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 1649EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SouthAfrica     09-16 0504</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-South Africa,0590</SECOND>
<HEAD>Zulu, Xhosa Leaders Make Joint Call For Peace</HEAD>
<NOTE>With LaserPhotos JOH2,3</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By GREG MYRE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SOWETO, South Africa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The king of the Zulus urged
thousands of armed supporters Sunday to curb the factional fighting
that has caused almost 800 deaths in black townships around
Johannesburg.
   ``Everybody must lay down their arms and take their brother's
hand in friendship,'' Zulu King Goodwill Zwelithini told fellow
tribesmen in Soweto and Tokoza, two townships that have been hard
hit by the fighting, which began in early August.
   Zwelithini shared the stage at the peace rallies with President
Tutor Ndamase of the Transkei, the tribal homeland of the Xhosas.
The Xhosas have joined fellow African National Congress supporters
in clashes against Zulus loyal to the conservative Inkatha
movement.
   Both sides blame the other for the fighting.
   But on Friday, ANC leader Nelson Mandela said South African
President F.W. de Klerk now believes some of the violence may be
instigated by a ``hidden hand,'' an apparent reference to
right-wing whites and others opposed to de Klerk's efforts to
attain power-sharing between blacks and whites.
   ``I have come to this place to put out the flames of violence,''
said Zwelithini at the two rallies attended by more than 30,000
Zulus, many wearing wearing red headbands and brandishing axes and
spears.
   His speech was followed by a similar plea from Ndamase.
   ``Freedom is your goal, not bloodshed. Unity is your goal, not
division. Power is your goal, not this bloody weakness,'' said
Ndamase, who is Zwelithini's uncle.
   Following the rally in Soweto, a Zulu was injured after being
set on fire by rival blacks, witnesses said. No other incidents
were reported.
   Both leaders are considered ceremonial figures rather than
political leaders, and it was unclear whether their calls for peace
would slow the unrest. Neither holds an offical post in either the
ANC or Inkatha.
   ``There is nobody who is entirely blameless,'' the king said of
the fighting. ``We decided to come together to stand before the
whole world to tell our people to stop this senseless
black-on-black confrontation.''
   Police initially threatened to disarm the Zulus. But the Zulus
refused to give up the weapons, which they consider part of their
traditional uniform necessary for tribal events. After
negotiations, police gave in.
   At the rallies, chiefs dressed in animal skins mingled with
youths wearing T-shirts with messages such as: ``Inkatha,''
``Victory Through Peace'' and ``Don't Worry, Be Happy.''
   The rallies came a day after police announced operation ``Iron
Fist,'' a crackdown in the townships that will include roadblocks,
sending in reinforcements and possibly imposing curfews.
   Police also said they would mount machine guns on armored patrol
vehicles to curb the growing number of attacks on police in the
townships.
   Mandela predicted the measures would be ineffective and claimed
they were announced only because two white policemen were killed in
the past week.
   The government last month sent police and army troops into the
townships and imposed emergency regulations.
   Police reported the townships around Johannesburg were quiet on
Sunday.
   The ANC and Inkatha, the two largest black political movements,
both oppose apartheid but differ over tactics and plans for a
future South Africa. The left-leaning ANC favors some degree of
government economic control while Inkatha champions free-market
measures.
   Under the apartheid system of racial segregation, the 5 million
whites dominate politics and the economy. The nation has nearly 30
million blacks.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0052 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 1649EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Thatcher-Czechoslovak     09-16 0383</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Thatcher-Czechoslovakia,0423</SECOND>
<HEAD>Thatcher First British Leader in Czechoslovakia in Half Century</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MAUREEN JOHNSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PRAGUE, Czechoslovakia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   British Premier Margaret Thatcher
arrived Sunday to begin a three-day visit to celebrate the collapse
of communism and discuss the merits of private enterprise.
   Mrs. Thatcher, on a three-nation tour that also includes Hungary
and Switzerland, is the first British leader to visit
Czechoslovakia in more than 50 years.
   She was greeted at Prague airport by Czechoslovak Premier Marian
Calfa and Foreign Minister Jiri Dienstbier. She also stopped to
chat with Alexander Dubcek, whose Prague Spring reforms in 1968
were crushed by Soviet tanks.
   After receiving a military cannon salute, Mrs. Thatcher drove
off to the center of the capital.
   She was thronged on the 11th century Old Town Square by
thousands of well-wishers, some chanting, ``Maggie, Maggie,'' or
``Hello, Maggie.''
   She had scheduled several private meetings Sunday before talks
with President Vaclav Havel on Monday.
   ``The visits to Czechoslovakia and Hungary are rather by way of
celebration and encouragement for the future,'' said a British
government spokesman, speaking on condition of anonymity.
   ``Czechoslovakia has a particular flavor because the people now
running the country were all dissidents and people that we did our
best to encourage. We did our best to maintain contacts,'' he said.
   A British ``privatization'' team arrived in Czechslovakia this
month to help officials sell off dozens of state-owned enterprises.
   The Thatcher government has privatized most of Britain's former
state-owned industries in the last decade, including its steel
industry and British Airways.
   Mrs. Thatcher also was to address the Czechoslovak parliament
and hold talks with Dubeck, the head of the assembly.
   She is to leave Tuesday for Hungary, which she last visited in
1984. Britain last year set up technical aid funds for Hungary and
Poland.
   Mrs. Thatcher and her husband, Denis, also plan two days of
official engagements in Zurich and Bern in Switzerland.
   Last week, French President Francois Mitterrand also visited
Prague.
   Both visits, Havel said, were intended to ``put the final full
stop'' to controversy over the 1938 Munich treaty signed by France
and Britain, which preceded Nazi leader Adolph Hitler's invasion of
Czechoslovakia.
   The treaty recognized Hitler's claims to the Sudetenland region
of northern Czechoslovakia.
   Czechoslovakia was not represented at the treaty signing, and
the country's diplomats were arrested after being summoned to hear
the results of the conference. The territory was returned to
Czechoslovakia in 1945.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0053 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 1650EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-WeatherpageWeather     09-16 0266</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Weatherpage Weather,0293</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rain Across South, Chilly in Northeast</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Rainy weather stretched from Arizona to Florida and up the Ohio
Valley to Lake Erie on Sunday, and unseasonably chilly air moved
across the Great Lakes into the Northeast.
   Showers and thunderstorms extended across southeastern through
north-central Arizona, New Mexico, most of Texas, southern
Louisiana, Florida and the coast of North Carolina.
   Thunderstorms over southwestern Texas had a potential for
producing 2 to 3 inches of rain an hour, the National Weather
Service said.
   Showers and thunderstorms also spread across eastern Ohio,
northern West Virginia, western Pennsylvania and western New York
state.
   Wind gusted to 64 mph during a thunderstorm at Cleveland, the
weather service said.
   Heavier rainfall during the six hours up to 2 p.m. EDT included
1.28 inches at Erie, Pa.
   In the West, showers and storms were scattered over the northern
Pacific Coast, Colorado, south-central Wyoming, and south-central
Montana.
   Unseasonably chilly air moved across the Great Lakes and into
the Northeast and there was a chance of snowflakes during the night
at higher elevations of New England, the weather service said.
   Advisories for frost were posted into Monday morning over
northern Wisconsin and northern Michigan, and scattered frost was
possible at higher elevations of southwestern Virginia, the weather
service said. Frost advisories were posted for Monday night in the
mountains of West Virginia.
   South of the advancing cool air, Cape Hatteras, N.C., tied its
record high for the date at 87.
   Sunday's low for the Lower 48 states was 23 at Truckee, Calif.
   Temperatures around the nation at 3 p.m. EDT ranged from 48 at
Jamestown, N.Y., to 97 at Alexandria, La., and Fort Worth, Texas.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0054 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 1658EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gabon     09-16 0401</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gabon,0452</SECOND>
<HEAD>Voters Attack Officals, Smash Ballot Boxes</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SERGE STEPHANE MOUANGA-MABIKA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LIBREVILLE, Gabon (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Voters attacked election officials and
smashed ballot boxes Sunday, claiming the country's first
multiparty elections in 22 years were rigged in favor of President
Omar Bongo.
   One election official was reported hurt in the violence, which
forced the closing of the main voting station in the capital city
of Libreville.
   Sunday was the first of two rounds of voting to elect 120
legislators from 520 candidates in the oil-rich West African nation
of 1.2 million people.
   Bongo called the election and legalized opposition parties
following a wave of protests earlier this year. Bongo had permitted
only his Democratic Party to operate since shortly after taking
power in late 1967.
   Violence began after voters at the largest balloting station,
Libreville's Hotel de Ville, said they discovered stuffed ballot
boxes before voting began. They smashed the boxes and assaulted
officials, witnesses said.
   At several voting stations in the capital, particularly in the
populous suburbs of Lalala and Venez-Voir, election officials asked
voters to deposit unmarked ballots.
   Shocked voters cried out that the elections were ``a
scandal.''Journalists saw ballot papers that did not match the
official forms circulating in Libreville.
   In Tchibanga, a small town about 300 miles southeast of
Libreville, an independent radio station reported voters ransacked
the election office and town hall and beat up election officials.
   The attacks there began after voters learned there were not
enough ballots, and some of the 37 opposition parties claimed their
tickets had been removed from voting booths, the station reported.
   The government did not immediately respond to the charges of
fraud. It also was not clear if ballots would be counted or whether
future voting will be held.
   Bongo's opponents accuse him of corruption, nepotism and
economic policies that cause unemployment. They have promised
better health care, education, housing and roads.
   Bongo, one of a handful of civilian leaders in West Africa, has
said his party is ready to entertain new ideas.
   The Democratic Party already was assured of 13 uncontested
assembly seats. The death of Progress Party leader Joseph Rendjambe
on May 23 triggered widespread rioting by followers who accused
Bongo of orchestrating his murder. The unrest ended after French
and Gabonese doctors performed an autopsy and concluded Rendjambe,
a diabetic, died of natural causes.
   The worst violence occurred in Port Gentil, where demonstrators
burned down the French consulate and took some foreign oil
executives hostage. France sent troops and the hostages were freed.
   Gabon, which achieved independence in 1960, receives about 80
percent of its income from oil.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0055 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 1703EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brite-TVWedding     09-16 0218</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brite-TV Wedding,0249</SECOND>
<HEAD>A Made For TV Wedding</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DAYTON, Ohio (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Live! From Centerville! It's the wedding of
Todd Ruel and Laura Hutchins!
   Not every couple has a television audience for their wedding.
But on Saturday, Ruel and Hutchins starred in their own televised
wedding special from a cable station in Centerville, about 10 miles
south of Dayton in western Ohio.
   The two were married where they met - amid cables and cameras -
at the Miami Valley Cable Council. The event was broadcast live on
two local cable channels.
   Ruel and Hutchins both worked behind the cameras at the cable
council. Ruel is now a writer and producer for the TNT Network
creative services in Atlanta.
   Hutchins, a scuba diving enthusiast, will join him in Atlanta
where she's hoping to find work in underwater photography.
   ``I'm pretty nervous,'' Ruel said before the wedding. ``I know
what goes on behind the scenes. But I'm not sure about the ceremony
at all.''
   Viewers were treated to a pre-wedding warm-up of sorts - 45
minutes before the ceremony, a video featuring the couple's
``formative years'' and friends discussing mistakes made at their
own weddings was aired.
   Then Ruel and Hutchins exchanged the traditional vows, kissed,
then walked down the aisle and out of Studio A. The guests
applauded.
   ``The worst kind of event that anyone can have is one that's
totally forgettable,'' Ruel said. ``I don't think this is that at
all.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0056 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 1718EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-PlannedParenthood     09-16 0592</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Planned Parenthood,0683</SECOND>
<HEAD>Retailer Spurs Revolt by Shoppers in Snub of Planned Parenthood</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto MP1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TONY KENNEDY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MINNEAPOLIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hundreds of customers of a department store
chain are are tearing up their credit cards and threatening a
Christmas season boycott in a revolt over the retailer's
uncharacteristic snub of Planned Parenthood.
   ``I don't think they expected any big outcry,'' said Toni
Tschann of the Minnesota Women's Political Caucus. ``And frankly, I
never thought I'd hear from this many. But people aren't standing
for it.''
   Shredded credit cards began arriving by mail at Dayton Hudson
Corp.'s downtown headquarters after the company's charitable
foundation confirmed on Labor Day weekend that it was halting
$20,000 education grants to Planned Parenthood of Minnesota, ending
a 22-year association.
   The decision to end the grant came about the time the Christian
Action Council of Falls Church, Va., said it would boycott Dayton's
and other corporations for supporting Planned Parenthood.
   Dayton Hudson spokeswoman Ann Barkelew said the decision had
nothing to do with pressure from special interest groups, but arose
from confusion about the donations, which some misconstrued as
support for abortion.
   Now the public response has prompted trustees of the Dayton
Hudson Foundation to reconsider their decision and enter talks with
Planned Parenthood that are set to continue this week.
   Barkelew said several hundred customers have returned their
credit cards. On Saturday, about 500 people rallied outside a
Dayton's store in suburban Edina and repeated their vow to boycott
all Dayton Hudson stores beginning the day after Thanksgiving
unless funding is restored.
   Dayton Hudson, with 1989 sales of $13.6 billion, owns Dayton's,
Target, Marshall Field's, Hudson's and Mervyn's department stores
in 33 states.
   ``Dayton's has always stood with women,'' said Gloria Griffin of
the Minnesota Women's Consortium. ``Women are their customers. I
strongly feel this is only a momentary mistake.''
   Weighing in behind the irate shoppers is at least one big
investor - New York City pension funds - and Bryn Mawr College
President Mary Patterson McPherson, who sits on the Dayton Hudson
board of directors but is not a trustee of the foundation.
   ``I am pleased they are reconsidering,'' said McPherson, who
declined to elaborate.
   Dayton Hudson pioneered in 1946 a policy of giving 5 percent of
profits for charitable causes. In 1989 the company gave away $22
million and received the America's Corporate Conscience Award from
the Council on Economic Priorities. In addition, Dayton Hudson is
on BusinessWeek magazine's top list of companies with
``women-friendly cultures.''
   ``When a company of the prestige and importance in the
philanthropic community says `no' to Planned Parenthood of
Minnesota, that is a devastating message to corporate America,''
said Thomas Webber, executive director of Planned Parenthood of
Minnesota. He said the $20,000 grant is financially insignificant
compared to its symbolic importance.
   Elin Ohlsson, 35, of Edina, is one of many shoppers who believe
Dayton's withdrew support from Planned Parenthood because of the
threatened boycott by the Christian Action Council.
   ``When I was 18 I was raped and I needed Planned Parenthood for
counseling,'' Ohlsson said. ``I feel betrayed by Dayton's.''
   Barkelew said foundation trustees for years had considered
ending financial support to Planned Parenthood because many people
misconstrue the aid as support for abortion.
   Now the possibility of a boycott from either side looms just as
the company enters the holiday shopping season, which generates
more than 50 percent of annual sales.
   ``Our worst fears have been realized,'' said New York City
Comptroller Elizabeth Holtzman, a trustee of city pension funds
holding $31.9 million of Dayton Hudson stock. ``We're long-term
investors and it's quite clear that when people get angry with a
company that can affect the bottom line.''
   In a letter to Dayton Hudson Chairman and Chief Executive
Officer Kenneth Macke, Holtzman and other city officials said that
denying the funding places Dayton Hudson ``squarely in the camp of
the anti-choice forces and in opposition to the overwhelming
majority of Americans who support accessible birth control.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0057 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 1721EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-Airlift     09-16 0350</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Airlift,0409</SECOND>
<HEAD>Refugee Airlift Continues</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf Rdp, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TERRY LEONARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>AMMAN, Jordan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A ragged line of 250 Bangladeshis burdened
with boxes of grapes, flimsy luggage and unhappy memories of weeks
in desert refugee camps boarded a Canadian jetliner Sunday for a
flight home.
   The Nation Air plane from Amman to Dhaka, Bangladesh, was one of
eight chartered evacuation flights taking an estimated 2,400
Bangladeshis who fled Kuwait following the Aug. 2 Iraqi invasion.
   Jordanian officials said more than 219,000 foreigners have been
evacuated on about 1,070 special flights since early August. At the
same time, 37 cargo flights have brought in tons of food and
supplies for the refugees waiting in camps for a way out.
   ``There are these C-130s that just come and go, come and go,
come and go. ... It's an air bridge,'' said Royal Jordanian
airlines vice president Akel Biltaji, whose company is helping
coordinate the airlift.
   The tide of mostly Asian refugees overwhelmed Jordan, which has
received about $19 million in U.N. relief aid.
   Many of the refugees ended up in squalid camps in the desert
frontier near Iraq. The nation's news agency, Petra, estimated that
600,000 people fled to Jordan following the invasion.
   ``We were really amazed at the numbers, at the waves of bodies
coming across the border,'' said Biltaji.
   A U.N. Soviet-built Antonov-124 unloaded 100 tons of rice at a
remote corner of the airfield while its crew lounged in the sun.
Later Sunday, about 450 Bangaladeshis would fly home aboard the
aircraft, crowded onto foam rubber pads on the metal deck.
   A spokesman for the Bangladeshi consulate said six flights to
Dhaka are scheduled for Monday to carry another 2,000 refugees.
   A Pakistan International Airlines official said about 800
Pakistanis would be repatriated Sunday aboard two jumbo jets.
   Biltaji said the government has flown more than 96,000 Egyptians
and more than 1,200 Sudanese home from Amman and Aqaba, about 180
miles south.
   By midday Sunday, officials said 12,906 Yemenis, 30,254 Indians,
9,708 Pakistanis, 8,246 Filipinos, 9,547 Bangladeshis, and 29,688
others had been evacuated from Jordanian airports.
   Amman's Queen Alia International Airport, designed to accomodate
1,800 people at any given time, now can be packed with more than
6,500 people.
   ``Just think of it - here one has to be candid - just think of
the toilets,'' said Biltaji.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0058 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 1724EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Pakistan-Bhutto     09-16 0239</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Pakistan-Bhutto,0272</SECOND>
<HEAD>Islamic Scholars Ask Court To Disqualfy Bhutto</HEAD>
<DATELINE>KARACHI, Pakistan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Islamic scholars have asked a court to
disqualify ousted Prime Minister Benazir Bhutto from next month's
election because they say she's not a good Moslem.
   Ms. Bhutto, whose government was dismissed by President Ghulam
Ishaq Khan Aug. 6 on corruption charges, is a candidate for five of
the 217 seats at stake in the National Assembly, the policy-making
lower house of Parliament.
   Ms. Bhutto's aides say she wants to make sure that if she's
disqualified from one seat she can still contest the others in the
Oct. 24 poll.
   In this staunchly Islamic country of 110 million, there are
separate seats for Moslems and non-Moslems.
   The lawsuit was filed against Ms. Bhutto Saturday in Lyari, a
sprawling slum in central Karachi that Ms. Bhutto won in the
November 1988 election.
   The seven Islamic scholars who filed the suit argued that a
candidate for a Moslem seat must understand and practice the
teachings of Islam and should not damage the freedom of the
judiciary, defame the armed forces or be involved in corruption.
   The former prime minister, they said, did not fulfill these
conditions and should be disqualified. They noted Ms. Bhutto had
made statements in the national and international media against the
teachings of Islam, a reference to statements that she opposed
cutting off hands as punishment for crimes like theft.
   They asked the court to summon Ms. Bhutto and ask her to recite
the Koran, the Moslem holy book, and answer questions about Islam.
   A hearing was set for Monday.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0059 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 1755EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-GulfRdp 2ndLd-Writethru a0719 09-16 0885</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf Rdp, 2nd Ld - Writethru, a0719,1083</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush Tells Iraqis They are Isolated; U.N. Weighs New Sanctions</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS grafs 16-17, bgng `The Soviet...' to CORRECT that
Soviet-Saudi ties existed previously, picks up 18th graf, `Two
Tunisian...; ADDS new last graf on Indian ship being permitted to
sail to Iraq; no pickup.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos NY6, AMM1-3</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ARTHUR ALLEN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   As the United Nations weighed new sanctions against Baghdad,
Iraqi television broadcast a statement by President Bush Sunday in
which he warned the Iraqi people their leader's brinkmanship could
plunge them into war ``against the world.''
   Hours later, thousands of men, women and children marched
through the streets of Baghdad, chanting ``Death to Bush, Death to
America!''
   An official Iraqi response to Bush's statement called it full of
``lies and contradictions,'' and said the U.S. president aimed to
be the ``dictator of the world.''
   The U.N. Security Council, meeting in the early morning hours,
unanimously condemned Iraq's raids last week on the French,
Belgian, Canadian and Dutch embassy compounds in Kuwait, and warned
that further sanctions against Baghdad were likely.
   Diplomats also began drafting language for a new resolution to
close off Iraq's air routes and punish nations flouting the trade
embargo, U.S. officials said.
   Bush's address to the Iraqi people, with an Arabic voice-over
and captions provided by the State Department, apparently was
broadcast in its entirety Sunday evening.
   ``Iraq finds itself on the brink of war,'' Bush said. But ``war
is not inevitable. It is still possible to bring this crisis to a
peaceful end.''
   ``Saddam Hussein tells you that this crisis is a struggle
between Iraq and America. In fact, it is Iraq against the world,''
said Bush, standing in front of his desk with the American flag
behind him.
   The eight-minute speech was followed immediately by a 25-minute
response from an Iraqi TV announcer.
   A ``thundering rage'' is building against the United States in
the Arab world, and a showdown in the Gulf would end ``in a
catastrophe'' for U.S. forces, said announcer Mikdad Morad, who
usually reads statements from President Saddam Hussein.
   A group of a few hundred men later began marching in Baghdad. As
they passed through residential neighborhoods, thousands of men,
women and children joined them.
   Raising their clenched fists in the air, the demonstrators
denounced Bush and also President Hosni Mubarak of Egypt and King
Fahd of Saudi Arabia, whom they called ``traitors of the Arab
world'' for backing the U.S.-led forces in the Persian Gulf.
   The U.N. resolution Sunday, along with actions by the Italian
and Soviet governments, appeared to confirm a growing solidarity in
opposition to Saddam, whose forces overran Kuwait Aug. 2.
   French officials rounded up for expulsion 26 Iraqi military
trainees and three suspected secret agents. On Saturday, France
said it was expelling diplomats and expanding its military presence
in the gulf in response to the embassy raids.
   Italy also announced Sunday it was expelling all the officials
at the Iraqi military attache's office in Rome. Other Iraqi
diplomats were forbidden to go more than 18 miles from Rome's
center without permission. Italy also said it would ask the
European Community to adopt new retaliatory measures against Iraq.
   The Soviet Union appeared to take another step away from
Baghdad, a former ally, with the visit to Moscow Sunday of Prince
Saud Al-Faisal, the Saudi foreign minister. A dispatch from the
official news agency Tass said he would sign a treaty
re-establishing diplomatic relations between the Soviet Union and
Saudi Arabia.
   The two countries have not had diplomatic ties since 1938. The
most recent obstacle was the Soviet war against rebels in
Afghanistan, who were funded by the Saudis.
   Two Tunisian newspapers reported Sunday that Iraqi troops had
entered the Tunisian Embassy in Kuwait as well. In Bangladesh, the
Bengali-language newspaper Ittefaq said soldiers stormed the
residences of two embassy officials Friday.
   In Baghdad, meanwhile, a senior Iranian delegation arrived for a
visit in another sign of a new alliance between the former foes.
Saddam has sought better ties with Iran to get help beating the
U.N. sanctions.
   The Iranian group was led by the deputy foreign minister for
international relations, Manushahr Mutaqi, the official Iraqi News
Agency reported.
   It quoted Mutaqi as saying he would discuss a prisoner-of-war
exchange, border issues and reopening embassies closed since the
1980-1988 war.
   Sources have reported that Iran agreed to provide food and
medicine to Iraq in exchange for 200,000 barrels of crude oil per
day. Iran has maintained it will respect the U.N. embargo. But in
any case, it has been reaping benefits from the crisis, making
billions of dollars from oil prices pushed up since the embargo on
oil exports from Iraq and Kuwait.
   Also Sunday, hundreds of Kuwaitis flooded into Saudi Arabia,
telling tales of terror and anarchy at home as word spread that
Iraq had unexpectedly opened the border for the first time in a
month.
   The refugees, who began flowing through the Khafji crossing on
Saturday, told of dwindling food supplies and Iraqi troops blowing
up the homes of suspected resistance fighters in Kuwait City.
  In other developments:
   - A delegate to a conference of leftist Arabs, Islamic party
members and Palestinian guerrilla factions in Amman, Jordan, called
for commando raids against U.S. forces in the gulf.
   ``We are ready to join the Iraqi Popular Army as volunteers and
to carry out commando operations against American forces,'' said
Abdullah al-Hassan of the General Union of Sudanese Democratic
Youth. About 150 delegates are attending the conference to oppose
the U.S. presence in the gulf.
   - Chartered evacuation flights took 2,400 Bangladeshis home from
Jordan. Since Aug. 5, Jordanian officials said, 219,234 foreigners
have been evacuated.
   Thousands of Asians and other refugees have been stranded in
camps in Jordan, awaiting transport home.
   - Six warships - three Canadian, two American and one British -
entered the Suez Canal Sunday on their way to the gulf region, a
canal official said. The American ships were the auxiliary
freighters Cape May and Cape Mohican.
   - A cargo ship left India to bring 11,000 tons of food to
120,000 Indians stranded in Iraqi-occupied Kuwait. Details about
how to distribute the food - shipped under a special U.N. Security
Council dispensation - once it reaches the Iraqi port of Umm Qasr
were still being worked out, officials said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0060 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 1800EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-FloridaLottery 2ndLd-Writethru a0701 09-16 0482</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Florida Lottery, 2nd Ld - Writethru, a0701,0603</SECOND>
<HEAD>6 Winning Tickets In $105 Million Florida Lottery</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 6th graf, `None of...', to CLARIFY that winners' cannot
validate tickets until Monday. SUBS 14th graf, `She said ...', to
ADD payout for four of six winning numbers.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By JACKIE HALLIFAX</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TALLAHASSEE, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Owners of six winning tickets will
split a record Florida Lotto jackpot of an estimated $105 million,
lottery officials said Sunday.
   Each of the tickets, bearing the numbers 5-6-21-34-35-45, is
worth an estimated $17.5 million, said Lottery Secretary Rebecca
Paul.
   The numbers were drawn at 11 p.m. Saturday, ending a week of
lottomania in which more than 100 million $1 tickets were sold,
sometimes at the rate of some 44,500 tickets a minute.
   The week followed four weeks in which there had been no Lotto
jackpot winner, pushing the grand prize to its near-record height.
In the history of state lotteries in the Unitd States, only a $115
million Lotto jackpot in Pennsylvania last year has been higher. In
that drawing, 14 winning tickets were sold.
   With no single ticket holder taking home the $105 million this
time, the U.S. record holder for a single winning lottery ticket
remains Sheelah Ryan of Winter Springs. She bought the only lucky
ticket in a $55.16 million Florida lottery drawing two years ago.
   Winning ticket holders in Saturday's drawing had to wait until
lottery offices opened Monday to validate the tickets and begin the
process of claiming their winnings, which will be paid off over 20
years.
   Some of the umpteen million losers had plenty to say, though.
   ``I just lost miserably,'' said Victor Morgan, who said he
bought two tickets. ``But I've wasted my money on worse things.''
He watched the drawing at Sharkey's Shrimp Bar in downtown Miami.
   Jennifer Kram, who matched just three numbers on one of her 20
tickets, ``I'm very depressed. Three isn't good enough for me. I
wanted at least $500,000.'' The three-number match will bring her a
grand total of $5.50.
   Mrs. Paul hinted at the exhaustion the week had brought lottery
officials.
   ``I think we're happy,'' she said at a midday news conference.
``I think we're glad it's over. But it's been fun and exciting.''
   She said the estimated jackpot of $105 million - ``give or take
a dollar or two'' - was based on last week's interest rates and
total sales of more than 109 million tickets. Earlier, the jackpot
was predicted to total $100 million.
   The six tickets were sold in New Smyrna Beach, Coconut Creek,
Venice, Miami, Winter Haven and Longwood.
   She said there were nearly 2 million winners overall, including
1,581 tickets with five out of the six numbers. Those players will
get $4,488 each. The 96,036 tickets with four of the six numbers
are worth $108 each. Some 1.8 million who picked three of the six
numbers will take home $5.50 each.
   The most popular combination was the simplest: 1,2,3,4,5,6. More
than 52,000 tickets had those six numbers, Mrs. Paul said.
   Had those turned out to be the winners, the per-ticket payout
would have been about $1,000, paid out in a lump sum rather than
over 20 years.
   The jackpot for this week's game, to be decided Saturday night,
was estimated at $9 million, lottery officials said.
   By law, half of every $1 spent on a Florida lottery ticket is
returned to the players in the form of prizes. At least 38{ percent
goes to education and the rest is spent on retailers and
administration.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0061 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 1815EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People-McMahon     09-16 0155</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People-McMahon,0154</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ed and Victoria McMahon Announce Marriage Dissolution Agreement</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Television star Ed McMahon and his wife,
Victoria, announced Sunday that they cleared the final obstacle
delaying their divorce.
   ``We have reached an amicable agreement to our mutual
satisfaction,'' said the statement issued jointly by the McMahons
through spokesman Lee Solters.
   The obstacle was not described and there was no elaboration.
   McMahon, 67, the ``Tonight Show'' sidekick to Johnny Carson and
host of the ``Star Search'' talent show, filed for divorce on July
25, 1989, after 13 years of marriage. The couple has an adopted
daughter, Katherine.
   After an October court hearing, Mrs. McMahon's attorney said
McMahon had agreed to child and spousal support of $50,000 a month
and shared custody of Katherine. The lawyer said the divorce would
not become final until at least January 1991 because of a joint tax
filing for 1989.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0062 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 1820EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Soviet-Saudi     09-16 0291</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Saudi,0319</SECOND>
<HEAD>Saudi Arabia and Soviet Union to Forge Diplomatic Ties</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf Rdp, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Prince Saud al-Faisal, the Saudi foreign minister,
arrived in Moscow on Sunday and Soviet officials said he would sign
a treaty re-establishing diplomatic relations between the
countries, Tass reported.
   Prince Saud was greeted at the airport by Foreign Minister
Eduard A. Shevardnadze, the state news agency said.
   The Soviet Union has been cultivating closer ties to moderate
Arab governments, as well as to Israel. It severely criticized the
Aug. 2 invasion of Kuwait by Iraq, formerly among its closest
allies in the Mideast.
   Saudi Arabia and Moscow had full diplomatic relations until
1938, when Josef Stalin closed his embassy in Jiddah in a
cost-cutting move. Several attempts to re-establish ties during the
1980s faltered over Saudi protests of the Soviet Union's treatment
of its 50 million Moslems.
   Another sticking point was the Soviet war against Afghan rebels,
who were supported by Saudi Arabia. Moscow withdrew its troops from
Afghanistan in 1988.
   King Fahd met in December 1988 with Yuli Vorontsov, the Soviet
deputy foreign minister, in the first high-level contact between
the two countries in 50 years.
   ``The issue of establishing official contacts between the Union
of Soviet Socialist Republics and Saudi Arabia has long been
ripe,'' Sergei Kirpichenko, a Foreign Ministry official, was quoted
by Tass as saying.
   Abdul-Wahab Abdul-Wasie, the Saudi minister for pilgrimage and
endowments, attended an Islamic conference over the weekend in
Moscow.
   Before leaving Saudi Arabia, Abdul-Wasie said he was seeking to
consolidate cooperation between Soviet Moslems and religious
circles in Saudi Arabia, the site of Islam's holiest shrines at
Mecca and Medina.
   The Soviet Union permittted more than 1,000 Moslems to attend
the annual pilgrimage, or hajj, to Mecca this summer. King Fahd
recently donated about 1.6 million copies of the Koran to Soviet
Moslems.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0063 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 1835EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-France     09-16 0581</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-France,0685</SECOND>
<HEAD>France Expels 29 Iraqis in Retaliation for Kuwait Raid</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf Rdp, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PATRICK McDOWELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   France expelled 29 Iraqis on Sunday on orders of
President Francois Mitterrand in retaliation for an Iraqi raid on
the French ambassador's residence in Kuwait.
   Iraqi President Saddam Hussein sought to cool the French
reaction, issuing a statement in which he said there was still a
chance for improving relations between Iraq and France if
Mitterrand changed his gulf policy. On Saturday, Saddam said Iraq
would allow elderly and ailing Frenchmen to leave on Monday.
   Police in Lyon, Brest, Rennes and Rochefort herded 26 Iraqi
technicians and military personnel, including four air force
pilots, into buses and cars and took them under escort to Paris.
   The Iraqis had been in France for training programs at the time
of the Aug. 2 Iraqi invasion of Kuwait. The training programs were
canceled and the Iraqis had been put up at hotels under close
police surveillance.
   Three suspected Iraqi agents - all students living near Paris -
also were picked up on Sunday by counterintelligence agents.
   The Iraqis were placed aboard an Air France jetliner at Charles
de Gaulle-Roissy Airport, which departed for Amman, Jordan, late
Sunday night. About 40 French police officers also boarded the
flight.
   One of the Iraqis made a V-for-victory sign as a bus pulled up
to the airplane, escorted by police cars and motorcycles. Iraq's
Ambassador to France, Abderazzek al-Hachimi, observed the
departure.
   The Iraqis were rounded up one day after Mitterrand ordered the
expulsion of dozens of Iraqis, including 11 embassy staffers, the
26 civilian and military personnel and 10 other Iraqis whom the
French president described as ``secret agents.''
   Al-Hachimi said the 11 diplomatic personnel ordered to leave
would depart on Friday.
   The French moves came in response to raids by Iraqi troops on
the missions or diplomatic residences of France, Canada and Belgium
in Kuwait City on Friday. Four French citizens, including the
military attache, and the consuls of five nations including the
United States were detained in the raids.
   The French attache and the consuls were released but France said
the three other French nationals remained in Iraqi custody.
   As another retaliatory measure, Mitterrand said France will send
tanks, warplanes, helicopters and 4,000 troops to Saudi Arabia to
bolster the U.S.-led multinational force created since Iraq invaded
Kuwait.
   Other European countries followed France in retaliating against
Iraqi diplomatic personnel.
   Italy ordered all the officials at the Iraqi military attache's
office in Rome to leave the country within 10 days and barred other
Iraqi diplomats from traveling more than 18 miles from Rome's
center without permission.
   Belgian Foreign Minister Mark Eyskens said in Cairo, Egypt, that
the European Community would meet on Monday in Brussels to discuss
retaliatory measures against Iraq.
   The official Iraqi News Agency, monitored in Nicosia, Cyprus,
carried a statement on Sunday by Saddam in which the Iraqi leader
recalled the once-close ties between Paris and Baghdad.
   Before the Aug. 2 Iraqi invasion of Kuwait, France had been
Iraq's biggest arms supplier after the Soviet Union.
   Saddam said Mitterrand had acted on the basis of ``inaccurate
information.''
   ``Regardless of the emotional content of the French government's
decision, Iraq hoped and continues to hope and work to win France's
friendship,'' he said.
   The Iraqi News Agency has denied the reports of violating
diplomatic territory. The news agency quoted an Iraqi spokesman as
saying a Frenchman, a counselor at the embassy, was found at a
private house belonging to a female member of Kuwait's deposed
ruling family. He was escorted to the embassy without incident, the
spokesman claimed.
   The U.N. Security Council, meeting early Sunday, unanimously
condemned Iraq's raids on the embassy compounds in Kuwait, and
warned that further sanctions against Baghdad were likely.
   Diplomats began drafting language for a new resolution to close
off Iraq's air routes and take secondary sanctions against nations
flouting the trade embargo, U.S. officials said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0064 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 1839EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-France-MayorQuits     09-16 0269</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-France-Mayor Quits,0301</SECOND>
<HEAD>Nice Mayor Resigns Amid Financial, Political Controversy</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NICE, France (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   After months of political and financial
controversy, the mayor of this picturesque French Riviera city
resigned Sunday to end more than six decades of family control in
city hall.
   ``Endurance has its limits, and I've just reached the end of
mine,'' read a letter by Jacques Medecin, 62, accused of improperly
shifting funds to cover city debts and criticized for ties with
extreme-right National Front politicians.
   Medecin's father, Jean, held the mayoral post for 38 years,
except for a brief break during World War II. Medecin succeeded his
father in 1966, forging a power base on the traditional right of
French politics.
   Medecin told regional authorities in the letter that he would
step down immediately. The job will be held by Assistant Mayor
Honore Bailet pending new elections.
   Medecin, on a tour of Japan and the United States to promote the
Riviera, could not be reached for comment Sunday.
   His resignation comes two months after the Regional Chamber of
Accounts ruled Medecin, Bailet and three municipal councilors
shifted city funds to cover municipal overdrafts.
   A mid-November court date was set, and city officials involved
could be stripped of their posts if the chamber's ruling is upheld.
   Medecin also had been under fire by his conservative Rally for
the Republic party, headed by Paris Mayor Jacques Chirac, for
apparently courting members of the National Front, which supports
an anti-immigrant platform.
   Medecin earlier this year appeared to be leaning toward an
informal agreement with National Front councilors. Support for the
party has grown in Nice.
   The National Front, led by Jean-Marie Le Pen, has the support of
about 15 percent of France's voters, according to some recent
polls.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0065 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 1902EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-PrayerHealing     09-16 0638</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Prayer Healing,0788</SECOND>
<HEAD>State Religious Protection Law May Hamper Prosecution</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ELLEN MILLER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MONTROSE, Colo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A state law intended to protect children
may hamper prosecution of a dead girl's parents for child abuse
because of an exemption for parents who employ certain types of
prayer healing.
   Angela Sweet died of a ruptured appendix on June 26 after her
parents, members of a small religious sect called the General
Assembly Church of the First Born, apparently decided to attempt to
heal her with prayer instead of taking her to a doctor.
   David and Barbara Sweet of Olathe in west-central Colorado each
face one count of felony child abuse. Their initial court
appearance is set for Monday.
   The 1989 law calls for prosecution of parents who refuse to get
medical treatment for a child when ordered to do so by a court, but
no court order was obtained in Angela's case.
   Results of such prosecutions in Colorado and across the nation
have been mixed.
   When a 14-year-old Grand Junction boy died in 1982 a week after
his ppendix ruptured, then-District Attorney Terry Farina called a
coroner's inquest. No charges were filed against the boy's parents,
also members of the Church of the First Born.
   ``Contrary to most crimes, which are intentional with obvious
motives, you often find loving parents who were parties to the
death of their child,'' Farina said.
   In Boston earlier this year, the Christian Science parents of
Robyn Twitchell, 2, who died of a bowel obstruction, were convicted
of involuntary manslaughter.
   In Fort Collins, District Attorney Stuart Van Meveren is still
battling a nine-year-old case in which the 5-week-old daughter of
John Lybarger of Estes Park died of pneumonia while her parents
prayed over her. Van Meveren won a conviction of child abuse, saw
it overturned on procedural grounds and then re-convicted Lybarger
after a second jury trial. The case has been appealed again.
   In Montrose, District Attorney Mike Stern agonized over the
Sweet case for six weeks after Angela's death before filing child
abuse charges against her parents.
   Complicating the issue are four visits made to the Sweet home by
a social worker at the request of school officials. The social
worker did not request a court order mandating medical treatment.
   ``There was a gap. They last saw her June 14 and she died June
26,'' said Stern. He did not know the reason for the gap.
   Montrose County attorney Greg Moxley is not allowing any social
service representatives to discuss the case with anyone.
   John Mitchell, the Sweets' attorney, wouldn't comment on the
case, nor would his clients.
   The 1989 law, whose chief lobbyists were Christian Scientists,
was intended by its sponsors to guarantee a right to medical care
for children, said state Rep. Dick Bond, the House sponsor of the
measure.
   ``The bill had a criminal penalty in it originally because our
intent was to stop something like this (Sweet) case,'' Bond said.
``But it came out at the insistence of Sen. (Terry) Considine.''
   The Senate sponsor, Bill Owens, said Considine, championing
parents' religious rights, weakened the bill considerably in
conference committee.
   The bill says school officials, law enforcement officers, or
others can ask county social service workers to visit a child they
believe to be seriously ill. The social worker can then seek a
court order mandating medical treatment.
   But a three-tier criteria designed by Christian Science
lobbyists provides a loophole for some parents, said Owens.
   The bill recognizes faith healing as a legitimate medical
treatment if fees are allowed to be deducted as medical expenses by
the IRS, if fees are recognized as reimbursable by health insurance
companies, and if the treatment has a success rate equal to that of
standard medical treatment.
   Stern said there is still some question whether the Church of
the First Born meets the exemption criteria.
   Considine, who says he is a ``believer in religious liberty,''
believes the social worker-visitor mechanism is adequate to protect
children.
   ``I'm an Episcopalian, not a Christian Scientist,'' Considine
said. ``I believe the state has a legitimate interest in protecting
children, but what we didn't do is criminalize the behavior of the
parents if they are operating under a religious belief.''
   Since the Sweets were charged, elders of the Church of the First
Born have been reluctant to comment, but last month they told the
Grand Junction Daily Sentinel that members can seek medical care
and repent later on. They also say children have a choice in the
matter.
   ``She (Angela) believed and that's what she wanted,'' said elder
Clyde Lewis.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0066 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 1932EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-SkydiverDeath     09-16 0176</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Skydiver Death,0203</SECOND>
<HEAD>Skydiver Falls To Her Death</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LEHI, Utah (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A skydiver plunged to her death from 8,000
feet when her main parachute failed to open after an aerial stunt
with other skydivers.
   Mary Jane Duncan, 31, of Highland, had linked with two other
skydivers before they separated at about 6,500 feet on Saturday.
Witnesses said she tumbled in the air as she pulled her main
parachute rip cord.
   The canopy's small pilot chute, which fills with air and deploys
the main chute, apparently became tangled as she tumbled, Jack
Guthrie, owner of Cedar Valley Free Fall.
   ``I saw her pull her chute and only the pilot chute came out,''
said Dr. Charles V. Pledger, a witness. ``I knew the main chute was
not coming out, and I kept waiting for her to pull her reserve
chute.''
   Duncan pulled her reserve chute about 100 feet above ground. Its
rip cord handle was found about a foot from the body, said Mike
Rawson of the state medical examiner's office.
   ``If she had done what she tried to do about two seconds sooner,
there is a good possibility she'd have walked away from it,''
Guthrie said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0067 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 1934EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-CumberlandCashiers     09-16 0357</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Cumberland Cashiers,0395</SECOND>
<HEAD>Newspaper: Chain Fired 30,000 After Theft Accusations</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PHILADELPHIA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Cumberland Farms Inc. officials fired more
than 30,000 convenience store employees after they were questioned
by company security for alleged theft, according to a published
report.
   The Philadelphia Inquirer reported Sunday that records it
obtained and corroborated in interviews with former employees
showed that Cumberland Farms attempted to question 30,903 cashiers
as part of a systematic effort to recover inventory losses by
demanding money from employees accused of theft.
   Virtually all were fired, the newspaper reported.
   Fourteen former Cumberland Farms employees have filed a lawsuit,
saying the company has a policy of falsely accusing cashiers of
stealing and then threatening and coercing them into signing
confessions.
   The company, based in Canton, Mass., denies the allegations.
   Cumberland Farms kept at least two sets of records on each
employee questioned from at least 1976 to 1989, according to the
Inquirer. One set of records assigned a serial number to identify
the employee accused, and listed the reason for questioning, his or
her employment status and whether the accused paid any money to the
firm.
   ``Each person fired was given a number,'' Edward F. Breau, a
former Cumberland Farms security official, told the newspaper.
Breau said he left the company after refusing to question an
employee without evidence.
   Since Aug. 1, the newspaper as reported that 275 former
Cumberland Farms employees have said they were falsely accused of
theft. They said that company security officials would take them
into a back room of the store and threaten them until they signed
confessions.
   The civil lawsuit filed in U.S. District Court in Camden, N.J.,
accuses Cumberland Farms of extortion, fraud, racketeering,
malicious prosecution and wire and mail fraud.
   A spokesman for Cumberland Farms, Foster G. Macrides, said the
company would not comment on the newspaper's findings because of
the pending litigation.
   Three former Cumberland Farms loss-prevention specialists told
the Inquirer that the company had a policy to coerce employees into
signing confessions of theft, even though the company often had no
evidence in those cases.
   Two of the security officials said they obtained confessions at
least two-thirds of the time.
   Cumberland Farms is one of the nation's largest convenience
store chains, with 1,200 stores and hundreds of gasoline stations
in 11 states.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0068 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 1936EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-MineWorkersMeeting     09-16 0445</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mine Workers Meeting,0530</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mine Workes Convention Begins with AFL-CIO Leader's Address</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARK PAXTON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MIAMI BEACH, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   More than 1,000 coal miners gather
Monday to chart the future for the United Mine Workers, a
once-powerful union facing legal troubles and declining membership
as it marks its 100th anniversary.
   Delegates attending the convention at the opulent Fontainebleau
Hotel will be asked to give the UMW's governing body, the
International Executive Committee, new powers to combine some of
the 21 districts and to use interest earnings from a strike fund to
finance collective bargaining.
   ``Those appear to be the two largest issues,'' union spokesman
John Duray said. ``But if you're looking at the big picture, the
convention has to decide how the union will respond to changes in
the industry.''
   AFL-CIO President Lane Kirkland is scheduled to address the
opening session of the convention, the UMW's first since a special
one-day gathering in Atlanta in 1986. The UMW rejoined the AFL-CIO
last year, four decades after legendary UMW President John L. Lewis
pulled his union out of the organization.
   Other speakers scheduled to address the delegates include the
Rev. Jesse Jackson and Labor Secretary Elizabeth Dole.
   The UMW, formed in 1890 by a merger of competing mine unions,
once enjoyed tremendous power in a country dependent upon coal to
fuel its factories and heat its homes, with its 400,000 members
controlling 80 percent of the nation's coal output as late as the
1940s.
   But as the nation turned to natural gas, nuclear power and other
sources of energy, and mines became more mechanized, the union's
domination of coal began to lapse.
   Layoffs and an increase in non-union mines have reduced the
UMW's working membership to 70,000, down from 120,000 a decade ago.
An effort to merge the organization with the Oil, Chemical and
Atomic Workers to create a national energy union fell apart in 1988
when the OCAW rejected the deal at the last minute.
   The union faces other problems. Although it won most of the
concessions it sought during the 10-month Pittston Coal Group
strike, the walkout helped cut the UMW's net worth by $45 million
in 1989, down to $126 million.
   The union also faces $52 million in fines levied by a Virginia
circuit judge because of the strike, plus more than $1 billion in
lawsuits filed by coal companies idled by last summer's five-week
wildcat strike in sympathy with the Pittston workers.
   One proposal union leaders expect to be put up for a vote would
allow the 24-member International Executive Board to use interest
from its strike fund toward the expenses of maintaining a strike,
including legal fees and negotiating costs. When the 1983
convention approved the strike fund, it limited the money to paying
benefits to striking miners.
   ``It's incredibly expensive to win a good contract,'' Duray
said. ``The days when you could win a strike on the picket line are
over.''
   Another proposal would give the International Executive Board
authority to merge districts, change their boundaries or dissolve
them. Several districts have encountered financial problems because
of coal industry layoffs.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0069 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 1920EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-Iraq-Bush 3rdLd-Writethru a0706 09-16 0642</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Iraq-Bush, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0706,0783</SECOND>
<HEAD>Iraqis Shout `Death To Bush'; Baghdad Says Bush's Message `Full of
Lies'</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf Rdp, Bjt</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 10 grafs to ADD futher quote from Bush address,
EDITS thereafter to tighten; no pickup.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By SALAH NASRAWI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BAGHDAD, Iraq (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Thousands of Iraqis took to the streets
Sunday shouting, ``Death to Bush, Death to America!'' after
President Bush said in a televised message that Iraq was isolated
and ``on the brink of war.''
   The demonstration came soon after an Iraqi TV announcer
delivered a stinging response to Bush's statement, saying it was
full of ``lies and contradictions'' and warning that a ``thundering
rage'' against the United States is building in the Arab world.
   The rally first gathered a few hundred men. As they marched
through residential neighborhoods, thousands of others, including
women and children, joined them.
   Raising their clenched fists in the air, the demonstrators
cried, ``Death to Bush, Death to America!'' They also called
Egyptian President Hosni Mubarak and King Fahd of Saudi Arabia
``traitors of the Arab world'' for backing the U.S.-led
multinational troop buildup against Iraq.
   In Bush's message on state-run Iraqi television, he warned that
``Iraq stands isolated and alone'' following its Aug. 2 invasion of
Kuwait.
   ``Saddam Hussein tells you that this crisis is a struggle
between Iraq and America. In fact, it is Iraq against the world,''
said Bush, standing in front of his White House desk with the
American flag behind him.
   Bush portrayed the invasion as yet another mistake by the same
leaders who ``plunged'' Iraq into war with Iran in 1980.
   ``You've borne untold suffering and hardship during eight long
years of war with Iran,'' Bush said. ``Once again, the same Iraqi
leadership has miscalculated. Once again, the Iraqi people face
tragedy.''
   The U.N. economic embargo against Iraq is meant ``not to punish
the Iraqi people, but as a peaceful means to convince your
leadership to withdraw rom Kuwait,'' he said. ``The decision is in
the hands of Saddam Hussein.''
   ``No one - not the American people, not this president - wants
war. But there are times when a country, when all countries ...
must stand against aggression,'' Bush said.
   His eight-minute speech was followed by a 25-minute denunciation
from Mikdad Morad, the announcer who usually reads statements from
President Saddam Hussein. The statement, though an official
commentary, was not read in Saddam's name, as some past messages
have been.
   ``Should war be imposed on us, the Iraqi people will not
hesitate in joining to teach the aggressor an important leasson,
which neither they, nor their allies and agents, will ever forget''
Morad said.
   The United States has tens of thousands of troops arrayed
against Iraq in Saudi Arabia and elsewhere in the Persian Gulf
region. The deployment began after Iraq's invasion of Kuwait, and
other nations have since joined the military buildup.
   ``Your aggression will end in a catastrophe for your forces,''
the Iraqi statement warned.
   As have past Iraqi statements, Sunday's response to Bush's
message sought to tie the Persian Gulf crisis to other disputes in
the Mideast. It repeated Arab criticism that the United States
applies double standards in dealing with the invasion of Kuwait and
the Israeli occupation of the West Bank and Gaza Strip.
   It said the U.S. president was ``shedding crocodile tears for
foreigners'' prevented from leaving Iraq and Kuwait, some of whom
are being used as human shields to protect Iraqi installations
against potential U.S. attack.
   ``They want to leave because of the embargo imposed by the
United States,'' the Iraqi statement said.
   ``Bush went crazy after Iraq entered Kuwait ... because he
feared his oil interests were jeopardized, and not out of concern
for the former Kuwaiti leaders,'' it said.
   The Iraqi announcer said the conflict ``is not at all, as Bush
says, one between Iraq and the United States. It is one between the
United States and the Iraqis, Arabs, Moslems and all the sincere
people of the world.
   ``It is thundering rage in the Moslem and Islamic world against
the United States,'' it added.
   Bush taped his address last Wednesday after an Iraqi information
minister suggested the U.S. president would be given time on the
country's television network, as Saddam has been by American
television.
   The White House had reportedly been irked by the amount of U.S.
air time Saddam's views were getting.
   The Bush tape, including a voice-over translation and captions
in Arabic, was ferried by a State Department courier to Baghdad and
turned over to the government there by the U.S. charges d'affaires.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0070 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 1935EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Obit-Condos 1stLd-Writethru a0731 09-16 0457</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Condos, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0731,0566</SECOND>
<HEAD>American Tap Dancer Steve Condos Dies After Show</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 3rd graf to give cause of death; pickup 4th graf, `He
gave...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By MARILYN AUGUST</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Legendary tap dancer Steve Condos collapsed in his
dressing room after a grueling performance Sunday at the Festival
of Dance in Lyon and died. He was 71.
   Organizers of the biennial festival said in a press release that
Condos died shortly after walking off stage at the Maurice Ravel
Auditorium.
   Doctors at the Lyon coroner's institute said the cause of death
appeared to be a heart attack.
   ``He gave an absolutely brilliant performance,'' his widow,
Lorraine Condos, told The Associated Press by telephone. ``I was
out front filming it. He walked off stage, went into his dressing
room and collapsed.''
   Mrs. Condos said rising modern dance star David Parson tried to
revive her husband with cardio-pulmonary resuscitation to no avail.
She did not say whether her husband had suffered any recent
ailments.
   ``They couldn't do anything,'' Mrs. Condos said. ``But it was
such a happy day for Steve. He was so happy to be performing and
getting the recognition he deserved.''
   Condos, a figure on the American stage for half a century, had
been in semiretirement for years and had been greatly enjoying the
reunion with some of his old colleagues from vaudeville days.
   The tapper won a huge ovation from a black-tie audience of
hundreds of people when the festival opened Friday night with a
gala show featuring Hollywood great Cyd Charisse.
   A central figure in the production, ``Stars and Taps,'' Condos
performed a long, fast tap that left him breathless when the show
ended about 2 a.m. Saturday morning.
   Condos tried to express his thanks to the crowd through a
microphone but was unable to catch his breath. He then gave up and
performed an encore.
   He danced again Saturday and collapsed after Sunday's
performance.
   In an interview before he performed Friday, Condos had said he
danced four to five hours a day ``because I just love to dance.''
   Other old-time tappers at the festival include Jimmy Slyde, the
Nicholas Brothers, Eddie Brown and Lavaughn Robinson. Up-and-comers
were 16-year-old whiz Savon Glover and Sam Weber.
   Condos told The Associated Press: ``I'm enjoying tapping more
now than I did as a youngster, when I'd be off doing a show in some
club and the other guys would all be scattered around.''
   A native of Philadelphia, Condos had recently lived in
Hollywood, Fla., performing only occasionally.
   But the Lyon festival this year features many tap greats of his
generation, and he decided to join them in a salute to the American
dance form.
   ``We're all together, we watch each other and we even learn from
each other,'' Condos told the AP.
   One of the few white stars in an art form usually dominated by
blacks, Condos liked to lay a microphone on the floor to pick up
what the called the ``power rhythm articulation'' of tapping shoes.
   Sunday had been scheduled as the third and final performance for
``Stars and Taps'' and Condos had planned to go to Paris to give
master's lessons to French tap students.
   In addition to Mrs. Condos, he is survived by four children.
Funeral arrangements were not known.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0071 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 2012EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BRF--Newspapers-Censu     09-16 0185</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Newspapers-Census,0187</SECOND>
<HEAD>Newspapers Hope to Find Uncounted Montanans</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HELENA, Mont. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The seven biggest newspapers in Montana
asked their readers Sunday to help prove that the U.S. Census
Bureau failed to count many Montana residents.
   Montana could lose one of its two seats in the U.S. House of
Representatives because its population has remained steady since
the 1980 census.
   Several local governments have already challenged the Census
Bureau's preliminary figures, and the Montana attorney general's
office is investigating some aspects of the count.
   Preliminary figures released at the end of August showed Montana
with 794,329 people, a gain of about 7,000 since the 1980 census.
   John Murphy, manager of the district census office in Helena,
said 817,000 people was the smallest number he had heard estimated
for Montana to retain two House seats.
   Sunday's editions of the seven newspapers include a coupon to be
filled out by any Montana resident who was not counted.
   The newspapers are the Billings Gazette, Bozeman Daily
Chronicle, Butte Montana Standard, Great Falls Tribune, Helena
Independent Record, Kalispell Daily Inter Lake and the Missoulian.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0072 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 2017EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Germany-Unification     09-16 0380</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Germany-Unification,0430</SECOND>
<HEAD>East German Deputies' Demand for Money Angers Bonn</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By NESHA STARCEVIC</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>FRANKFURT, West Germany (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A request from East German
parliament deputies that their salaries continue to be paid after
the two Germanys unify on Oct. 3 has upset West German political
leaders, a newspaper said Sunday.
   Some West Germans interpreted the request as a veiled threat by
the deputies to vote against the unification treaty unless their
demands were met.
   The deputies are demanding that they continue receiving their
salaries and benefits after East Germany's first democratically
elected legislature is dissolved with unification on Oct. 3.
   The request came in a letter by East German parliament Speaker
Sabine Bergmann-Pohl to West German leaders, including Chancellor
Helmut Kohl.
   The East German deputies want to be paid at least until
all-German elections are held on Dec. 2.
   They receive a monthly salary of $3,750 and such a move would
cost West German taxpayers, already worried about the soaring cost
of unification, about $1.9 million.
   Mrs. Bergmann-Pohl's letter was published on Sunday by the West
German newspaper Bild am Sonntag. ``East German Deputies Blackmail
Kohl,'' the newspaper's front-page headline said.
   After unification, 144 deputies from the 400-member East German
parliament, or Volkskammer, will be integrated into the West German
Bundestag until the elections for a united parliament are held. The
other 256 deputies will lose their seats.
   ``This different treatment is causing strong unrest in the
Volkskammer,'' Mrs. Bergmann-Pohl's letter said. ``The resulting
anger is leading to uncertainty about the vote on the unification
treaty.''
   The Volkskammer is scheduled to vote on Thursday, and a
two-thirds majority is needed.
   Bild am Sonntag said Kohl and Interior Minister Wolfgang
Schaeuble were angered by the request and would reject it.
Officials of other political parties also criticized Mrs.
Bergmann-Pohl's letter.
   She said on Sunday that her letter had been misunderstood and
that she had only asked that deputies not going to the Bundestag
keep their ``status'' until Dec. 2.
   In an interview with the newspaper Bild released in advance of
its publication Monday, she said deputies who may not have jobs to
return to should receive severance pay for their service in the
Volkskammer.
   An Interior Ministry spokesman in Bonn said Sunday that it was
legally impossible for Volkskammer members not going to the
Bundestag to retain their deputy's status after Oct. 3. But he said
officials from the two states would discuss on Monday possibilities
for giving the outgoing deputies severance pay.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0073 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 2021EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Dollar-Yen     09-16 0055</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Dollar-Yen,0029</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dollar Opens Down</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The dollar opened at 136.45 yen on the Tokyo
foreign exchange market Monday, down from Friday's close of 136.55
yen.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0074 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 2035EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Britain-ArtTheft     09-16 0224</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Britain-Art Theft,0261</SECOND>
<HEAD>Gainsborough and Reynolds Paintings Stolen</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two portraits by Thomas Gainsborough and one by
Sir Joshua Reynolds, together worth $11 million, were stolen Sunday
from a law office complex, police said.
   Scotland Yad police headquarters said a guard told them a man
had hit him in the face and knocked him out. His hands were tied
behind his back and his keys stolen.
   The canvases were cut from their frames. Lincon's Inn, the law
office complex, estimated their value at $3.7 million each.
   William Pitt, who became prime minister at age 24 in 1783, is
the subject of one of the Gainsboroughs, painted full length when
Pitt was 20.
   The other Gainsborough is a full-length of Judge Sir John
Skinner in red robe and wig. The Reynolds is a head and shoulders
portrait of Francis Hargrave, a treasurer of the Inn.
   Lincoln's Inn and the adjoining Lincoln's Inn Fields comprise a
large, peaceful complex with trees, gardens, tennis and basketball
courts, where many lawyers have their offices. The Great Hall is
used for dining by judges and barristers.
   The Inn, founded in the 14th century, is one of the four Inns of
Court that have the power of calling law students to the English
Bar. They then become barristers with the right to plead in
superior courts.
   Charles Dickens worked in Lincoln's Inn as an office boy at the
Court of Chancery, an experience that gave him the experience to
depict it with venom in his novel ``Bleak House.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0075 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 2043EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-TrappedBoy 1stLd-Writethru a0697 09-16 0581</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Trapped Boy, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0697,0762</SECOND>
<HEAD>Toddler Pulled From Shaft Released from Hospital</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 5th graf pvs, `Kevin was..., with 2 grafs to UPDATE boy's
release from hospital, quotes. DELETES now redundant 6th graf pvs,
```Kevin appeared.... Picks up 7th graf pvs, `The ordeal...</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos DX1,DX2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SCOTT MAXWELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DENVER (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A toddler trapped for 14 hours in a shaft dug for
a remodeling project busied himself making mud balls and listening
to his mother's repertoire of nursery songs before rescuers reached
him at dawn.
   ``It was really difficult. I could hear him crying, but I
couldn't touch him and I couldn't help him,'' Lisa Davis, the
mother of 20-month-old Kevin, said while fighting back tears at a
news conference at Denver General Hospital on Sunday.
   The team of rescuers cheered when the boy was brought to the
surface shortly after 6 a.m Sunday.
   ``When he clinched my fingers, I felt a tingle in my heart,''
said firefighter Joe Cipri, who pulled him out. ``It's still
there.''
   Kevin was treated for dehydration at the hospital and released
Sunday afternoon, spokeswoman Mary Lee Chin said.
   ``His bruises were minimal,'' Chin said. ``There was no need to
keep him in because he was doing great. As a matter of fact, I
caught him jumping up and down on his bed this afternoon, so he's
doing fine.''
   The ordeal started about 4 p.m. Saturday when the toddler fell
into a hole 18 inches wide and 12 feet deep dug for a remodeling
project in a house the family was renovating in an upscale
neighborhood in southeastern Denver.
   ``He wasn't playing in the room. He just came to visit for a
second because it's not a safe place for a kid to be,'' said
Kevin's father, Tom. ``He managed to slip under a piece of wood and
fell into the hole. I heard him bouncing around in the hole.''
   Firefighters from four metropolitan departments worked through
the night to keep the boy warm and dry, pumping oxygen into the
hole and shining the lights to keep the temperature at about 70
degrees.
   Mrs. Davis, 32, said Kevin kept himself amused by rolling mud
into balls with his fingers and spinning himself around in the
hole.
   Rescue workers dug a vertical shaft using a ``Vac-Hoe,'' a huge
digger that excavates with a stream of compressed air and then
vacuums out the loose dirt. They then delicately dug a horizontal
tunnel across the five feet of earth where Kevin was.
   Mrs. Davis said she didn't say anything to her dirty,
blond-haired son when he was brought up from the shaft, cradled in
a splint-like device that protected his head, neck and upper body.
   ``I just wanted to hold him,'' she said. ``He's a pretty
incredible boy.'' The couple said Kevin, their only child, was
talkative and asked for a toy as soon as he arrived at the
hospital.
   The incident was reminiscent of the October 1987 ordeal of
Jessica McClure, the 18-month-old toddler who spent 58 hours in a
well in Midland, Texas. The arduous effort to free her gripped the
nation and her final emergence safe in the arms of rescue workers
was televised nationally.
   Hearing about Kevin's predicament Saturday evening, Jessica's
father, Chip McClure, said, ``I know every hour seems like a day.
You have to have faith in the Lord. I'm sure their little boy will
be all right.''
   ``I'm really upset,'' he told the Rocky Mountain News. ``The
pain I felt after Jessica fell down the well - I hate to see
anybody have to go through that.''
   Davis, 33, who would not divulge his occupation, said he did not
have a building permit for the shaft, dug to reinforce the house.
The couple were renovating the house, but were not living there.
They declined to say where they currently live.
   Davis also refused to say why he did not obtain a building
permit.
   ``But I do know what I'll be doing Monday morning,'' he said.
   A Denver police spokeswoman who refused to give her name said
Sunday that no decision had been made on possible charges against
the Davises for the lack of a building permit.
   Asked if they would tell their son about the ordeal, Mrs. Davis
said: ``I think that sort of depends on what he says to us and how
he reacts. We plan to explain it truthfully and accurately and tell
him the whole story,'' she said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0076 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 2108EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-TankerExplosion 2ndLd-Writethru a0756 09-16 0474</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Tanker Explosion, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0756,0582</SECOND>
<HEAD>Gasoline Tanker Explodes in Michigan's Saginaw River</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 19th graf to UPDATE with three crew members admitted to
hospital. CORRECTS that police report of heart attack was wrong.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto BAY1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By WILLIAM BERGSTROM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BAY CITY, Mich. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A tanker carrying about 1 million gallons
of gasoline exploded and burned Sunday on the Saginaw River,
injuring most of the 18 people aboard and spilling fuel in the
water.
   The fire was too hot for firefighters to douse, and officials
waited for it to burn itself out, said Coast Guard Lt. Tom Koontz.
   One person from the ship was missing, said Coast Guard Petty
Officer Gerald Backus. Gov. James Blanchard visited the site and
declared the blaze an emergency, freeing state aid and assistance.
   The fire was reported at 8:45 a.m., while the tanker was
unloading at the Total Refinery Dock Facility, and was still
burning Sunday evening.
   Authorities warned spectators to clear the area in case of
multiple explosions.
   ``A few people blew right off the boat and slammed ashore,''
said Bay City police Officer Kenneth Adcock. ``The sky is covered
with black smoke. If it blows again, it's going to be a big one.''
   Witnesses said the black smoke blocked out the sun throughout
the afternoon.
   The tanker, owned by Cleveland Tankers Inc. of Cleveland, was
carrying about 20,000 barrels of gasoline or about 1 million
gallons, said Koontz. It has a capacity of about 54,000 barrels.
   ``That's the estimate. That's a lot of gas,'' Koontz said.
   The state Department of Natural Resources was conducting water
and air pollution tests Sunday to check for environmental
contamination, spokeswoman Susan Henry said.
   A gasoline spill is less damaging than an oil spill because
``it's volatile and it evaporates,'' she said, adding that two
booms were strung downstream from the ship to contain any spilled
fuel.
   Ronald Stopyak had returned home 15 minutes before the blast
from working at the Bay Chemicals Co. directly across the river
from the tanker. He said he raced back to work after hearing the
explosion.
   ``I thought the plant exploded and when I got out there I saw
black smoke everywhere,'' he said. ``I saw the employees on the
ship go overboard.
   ``It was really hot. I could feel the heat from across the
river.''
   His wife, Cheryl, said their house is less than two blocks from
the explosion and was shaken.
   ``It was like a slow rumbling, it got louder and louder like
thunder,'' she said.
   Two Coast Guard helicopters sprayed fire-fighting foam while
they rescued crew members from the tanker, said Lt. Dennis Secor.
   Coast Guard crews secured the tanker with cables to prevent it
from drifting into a nearby bridge, he said.
   Bay Medical Center spokesman Curt Miller said three of the 17
crew members treated there were admitted. Two had head injuries, a
third suffered chest pains. Police initially reported that one
victim had suffered a heart attack.
   Bay City is a town of 40,000 on Lake Huron's Saginaw Bay, about
100 miles northwest of Detroit.
   The 380-foot tanker Jupiter was hauling unleaded gas from a
Canadian port to the terminal, said Roger Schrum, a spokesman for
the Ashland Oil Inc., of Ashland, Ky., which owns Cleveland
Tankers.
   The Jupiter, built in 1976 in Jennings, La., is a double-lined
tanker with six storage compartments, Schrum said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0077 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 2120EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Canada-Plane     09-16 0282</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Canada-Plane,0316</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rescuers Find Downed Plane's Life Raft</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ST. JOHN'S, Newfoundland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Searchers Sunday evening
discovered what appeared to be a half-submerged life raft in the
North Atlantic near where a jetliner with 16 aboard was believed to
have ditched last week.
   Officials said it appeared there were no survivors.
   A Canadian Forces Buffalo airplane spotted what was believed to
be the Boeing 727's 24-man life raft, said Capt. Ross Brown of the
Halifax search and rescue coordination center.
   The Canadian warship Nipigon was steaming to the area late
Sunday, he said.
   The plane, owned by Faucett Airlines of Peru, was leased by Air
Malta and was carrying airline employees and their families.
   It was en route from the Mediterranean island of Malta to Miami
when it disappeared last Tuesday. Its last contact came before a
routine refueling stop in Gander, Newfoundland, when the pilot
reported a low-fuel emergency and said he was preparing to ditch in
the ocean.
   Searchers ``located an international orange life raft, partially
submerged,'' said Bob Norburn, a private radio operator monitoring
transmissions between aircraft and the Nipigon, which was
coordinating the sea search.
   ``There were no signs of life. ... No transmissions,'' he said.
   The sighting came several hours after officials confirmed a
Soviet trawler's sighting of a section of the airliner's fuselage
on Friday.
   ``The object was described as being cigar-shaped, grey in color
with red and white stripes,'' Brown said. ``From the captain's
description, officials have confirmed that the object is part of
the aircraft fuselage.''
   In a statement issued earlier Sunday evening, Brown said the jet
probably broke up on impact.
   The Soviet trawler captain reported seeing the fuselage section
floating about 240 miles south of Newfoundland.
   The jet, owned by Faucett Airlines of Peru and based in Miami,
was leased by Air Malta.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0078 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 2132EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Soviet-Reagan     09-16 0129</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Reagan,0129</SECOND>
<HEAD>Reagan in Moscow, Will Meet With Gorbachev</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Former President Reagan toured the cathedrals of
Leningrad Sunday before flying to Moscow, where he was to talk with
President Mikhail S. Gorbachev and address the national parliament.
   Reagan was greeted at the Moscow airport by U.S. Ambassador Jack
Matlock and former Soviet ambassador Anatoly Dobrynin.
   Sunday was the second day of his five-day visit to the Soviet
Union.
   Reagan was to meet with Gorbachev at the Kremlin on Monday and
address members of the Supreme Soviet. On Tuesday, he was to meet
with students of Moscow State University.
   Reagan and his wife, Nancy, are on a 10-day European tour. He
flies to Rome at the conclusion of his Soviet visit.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0079 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 2137EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ViolinCompetition     09-16 0205</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Violin Competition,0221</SECOND>
<HEAD>Soviet Violinist Wins Gold Medal at International Tourney</HEAD>
<DATELINE>INDIANAPOLIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Soviet Pavel Berman won the gold medal at
the International Violin Competition on Sunday, earning a Carnegie
Hall debut and $22,000.
   Berman, 20, is the son of Soviet pianist Lazar Berman. The
Moscow native also won a European management contract, more than 50
recital engagements with major North American orchestras and a gold
watch.
   ``You play from heart to heart in Russia. You speak from your
heart and soul,'' Berman said. The first-place finish ``is my
chance, my chance to make my career. But it is also my opportunity
to get better and better.''
   Second-place honors went to Marco Rizzi of Italy. He won
$16,000. Ivan Chan of the United States won third-place and
$10,000. Virginie Robilliard of France placed fourth, David Kim of
the United States was fifth and Martin Beaver of Canada was sixth.
   Brazilian Blumita Singer was disqualified Sept. 4 for allegedly
falsifying her credentials. Judges questioned her ability to play
the composition she submitted on an audition tape.
   Singer last week denied any wrongdoing and blamed her poor
performance on the competition's social schedule, which she said
did not allow her enough time to rehearse. She claimed she was
disqualified to create a scandal to promote the event.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0080 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 2208EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-BudgetTalks-Secrecy 2ndLd-Writethru a07 09-16 0693</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Budget Talks-Secrecy, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0758,840</SECOND>
<HEAD>Budget Bargainers Find Air Base Is Not Airtight</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: SUBS 2 new grafs for 5th graf pvs, ``The bargaining xxx with
Democrats rejecting spending cuts, talks breaking up for evening;
SHOULD STAND FOR AMS</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By ALAN FRAM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   White House and congressional budget
negotiators are finding that when it comes to an impregnable
sanctuary, Andrews Air Force Base is no Fort Knox.
   After a yearlong budget stalemate, negotiators decided that the
Maryland airfield - just outside the capital - would be a good
place for them to quickly piece together a package of tax increases
and spending cuts for next year.
   There would be no competing meetings to attend. It would provide
a chance to spend long, uninterrupted hours together to develop a
camaraderie that could speed the way to a deal. And perhaps best of
all, no meddling reporters or lobbyists who could pry out
embarrassing proposals.
   It hasn't quite worked out that way.
   The bargaining, which began Sept. 7 and was supposed to last
three or four days, resumed late Sunday for a ninth day, with no
end in sight. Two officials, demanding anonymity, said the meeting
was contentious as Democrats backed away from about $30 billion in
cuts the two sides had been discussing in Medicare, agriculture and
other benefit programs.
   ``It doesn't look good right now,'' one official said. The talks
subsequently broke up the evening shortly before 10 p.m. and were
to resume Monday at 10 a.m.
   On NBC-TV's ``Meet the Press'' program Sunday, Senate Minority
Leader Bob Dole, R-Kan., and House Speaker Thomas S. Foley,
D-Wash., said they hoped a deal could be arranged by Monday night.
   ``It's tough going, but I think tomorrow night we may well see''
an agreement, Foley said.
   In addition, important details of offers, counteroffers and
agreements have been routinely reported in the press, causing
bickering among negotiators over how the information was disclosed.
   The cloak of secrecy the participants have sought has been
pierced so badly that the unlisted phone number of the Republican
staff's fax machine at Andrews had to be changed last week because
it was being flooded by messages from lobbyists.
   In other instances, congressional aides have asked reporters for
information about the talks.
   Frustration by many bargainers with the leaks reached a peak
Friday. That was the day news articles reported on a GOP tax
proposal made at the negotiations. The articles noted that
according to the non-partisan Joint Tax Committee of Congress, the
Republican plan would boost taxes for low- and middle-income people
and lower them for the better off.
   ``Don't burden an already difficult ship with this kind of thing
or it will sink,'' Sen. Pete Domenici, R-N.M., one of several
negotiators who took to the Senate floor to complain, warned his
Democratic counterparts.
   Just three days earlier, Domenici had kinder things to say about
the Andrews talks.
   ``I don't think we could do it if we weren't somewhere like
that,'' the senator said Tuesday when asked if the selection of
Andrews was working out.
   Not only is information getting out, but pressure from interest
groups is getting in.
   The negotiators last week were considering a plan to raise
revenues by increasing the monthly Medicare premium for medical
coverage - now $28.60 monthly - for people with higher incomes.
   But as the powerful senior citizens' lobby geared up, Democrats
by week's end were said to have backed away from the idea,
according to officials speaking only on condition of anonymity.
   The bargainers had wished that by meeting in seclusion, the two
sides would be willing to propose dramatic tax boosts or spending
slashes that they would be reluctant to offer publicly. They still
hope that if a deal is reached, Democrats and Republicans alike
would claim authorship and thus provide each other with political
cover.
   But in some instances, the system has broken down.
   Last week, for example, it was reported that the negotiators
were considering boosting the 16-cent-per-pack cigarette tax,
perhaps doubling it.
   One official said the idea had come from Rep. Bill Archer,
R-Texas, one of the negotiators. Archer vehemently denied that and
said the proposal had been advanced by a Democrat whom he would not
name.
   At the negotiations the next day, Archer angrily accused another
bargainer, Sen. James Sasser, D-Tenn., of telling reporters that
the tobacco levy was Archer's idea, which Sasser denied, said
another official who also demanded anonymity.
   To prevent incidents like that, the negotiators have taken
extraordinary steps to keep reporters at arms length.
   With the talks being held in the Andrews' officers' club,
reporters have been confined to a press center on the base, about
two miles away. They have been warned to not go near the officers'
club, and on many occasions have not been allowed onto the base or
out of the press center without an armed military escort.
   Many journalists are simply covering the talks from their
offices in the capital, about 10 miles away.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0081 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 2211EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Israel-EthiopianJews     09-16 0413</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel-Ethiopian Jews,0484</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ethiopian Jews Demonstrate To Demand Family Reunification</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hundreds of Ethiopian Jews, many of them
crying, demonstrated outside Prime Minister Yitzhak Shamir's office
on Sunday to demand that the government help bring out family
members stranded in Addis Ababa.
   ``We want our families. We want our parents. ... Mother! Father!
Where is my mother? Where is my father?'' the crowd chanted. ``We
ask you, please save our families.''
   Many in the crowd broke into tears as they shouted bitterly for
relatives left behind in Ethiopia.
   The protest lasted for about three hours, and the demonstrators
briefly blocked a major road near Shamir's office. Israel
television said police did not intervene.
   Officials said the government was doing all it could to bring
Ethiopian Jews to Israel.
   Ethiopian Jews have sought to escape from their land, stricken
by war and famine, to a better life in Israel. More than 17,000
Ethiopian Jews live here.
   Some 15,000 to 18,000 Jews remain in Ethiopia after about 8,000
were airlifted to Israel in 1984 through the Sudan.
   The secret, U.S.-backed campaign known as Operation Moses was
called off after three months when news of its existence leaked to
the press, embarrassing the Ethiopian and Sudanese governments.
   The majority of those left behind have abandoned their homes and
made their way to the capital, Addis Ababa, hoping they can escape
on the direct flights to Israel initiated when the two nations
resumed diplomatic relations in October 1989 after a 16-year break.
   But only about 500 immigrants a month have arrived since
October, and Israeli officials have announced there have been no
arrivals since July.
   Ethiopian Jewish activists in Israel say about 250 Jews have
died since then of disease and hunger in Addis Ababa. They say
their stranded relatives need medical help and blame the Israeli
government for its lack of action.
   According to U.S. congressmen, Ethiopia's Marxist government is
trying to force Israel to sell it advanced weapons for use against
the rebels in the African country's civil war. Israeli officials
deny these reports.
   ``The government of Israel and all the Jewish organizations that
deal with the Ethiopian Jewry do everything in their power in order
to bring Ethiopian Jews to Israel as soon as possible,'' said
Absorption Minister Yitzhak Peretz, who later appeared at the
rally.
   The Foreign Ministry issued a special statement saying that some
2,500 Ethiopian Jews have arrived in Israel this year.
   It said efforts were being made to transfer the rest of them to
Israel ``with the help of Jewish organizations and many friendly
governments'' in spite of what the ministry called ``objective
difficulties.''
   But Addisu Masala, a spokesman for the protesters, disputed
these figures on Israel television, saying that only 1,000 people
have come this year and that the ministry's numbers were
``unreasonable.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0082 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 2236EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-BudgetTalks     09-16 0249</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Budget Talks,240</SECOND>
<HEAD>No Progress Reported in Brief Sunday Session</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   White House and congressional budget
negotiators meet a little over three hours Sunday evening, but
reported no progress toward agreement as they geared up for what
was expected to be a marathon session Monday.
   Sunday's session marked the ninth day of talks, with no end in
sight.
   Two officials, demanding anonymity, said the meeting Sunday
night at nearby Andrews Air Force Base was contentious as Democrats
backed away from about $30 billion in cuts the two sides had been
discussing in Medicare, agriculture and other benefit programs.
   ``It doesn't look good right now,'' one official said.
   The talks subsequently broke up shortly before 10 p.m. and were
to resume Monday at 10 a.m.
   Earlier Sunday, On NBC-TV's ``Meet the Press'' program, Senate
Minority Leader Bob Dole, R-Kan., and House Speaker Thomas S.
Foley, D-Wash., both expressed measured optimism that a deal could
be struck by Monday night.
   ``It's tough going, but I think tomorrow night we may well see''
an agreement, Foley said.
   The negotiators are working toward a goal of reducing the budget
deficit by $50 this year in order to forestall $100 billion in
automatic spending cuts if they are not successful.
   The negotiators were considering a plan last week to raise
revenues by increasing the monthly Medicare premium for medical
coverage - now $28.60 monthly - for people with higher incomes.
   But with the powerful senior citizens' lobby gearing up in
opposition, Democrats by week's end were said to have backed away
from the idea, apparently contributing to Sunday night's reported
acrimonious session.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0083 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 2242EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-HurricaneMarie 1stLd-Writethru a0736 09-16 0291</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Hurricane Marie, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0736,0338</SECOND>
<HEAD>Weakening Hurricane Marie Should Skirt Hawaii, High Surf Feared</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Leads with 6 grafs to UPDATE with hurricane weakening, likely
downgrade to tropical storm status, revised winds speeds, location
and predicted proximity to island. DELETES 3rd graf pvs, ```It
is... to conform. Picks up 7th graf pvs, `To monitor...</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By BRUCE DUNFORD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HONOLULU (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A hurricane with reduced top winds of 100 mph
spun toward Hawaii Sunday, bringing the threat of high waves and
warnings to stay off the beach.
   Hurricane Marie, was centered about 380 miles east-southeast of
Hilo on the island of Hawaii Sunday afternoon, and showed more
signs of weakening, the National Weather Service said.
   Sustained winds near its eye fell to 80 mph, with top gusts
reaching 100 mph. The hurricane was expected to be downgraded to
tropical storm status Sunday night once sustained winds dropped
below 75 mph, forecaster Tim Craig said.
   Gale force winds, which range from 39 mph to 54 mph, extended
150 miles from the center of the hurricane. Waves kicked up by the
storm were expected to reach Hawaii, known as the Big Island, late
Sunday or early Monday, the weather service said.
   All ocean and beach activities along the southern and eastern
coasts of Hawaii should be halted because of the high surf danger,
Hawaii County Civil Defense Administrator Harry Kim said.
   Hurricane Marie, moving westward at about 10 mph, would pass
about 70 miles off the southern tip of Hawaii on Monday if it
maintains its course and speed. On Tuesday it would pass about 200
miles south of Oahu, the island where Honolulu is located, the
weather service said.
   To monitor rising surf, residents along the affected coastlines
will maintain a watch and report to Civil Defense officials, Kim
said.
   The last major storm to hit the Hawaiian islands was Hurricane
Iwa, which struck on Nov. 24, 1982 and caused $234 million damage,
primarily to the islands of Oahu and Kauai.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0084 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 2251EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Guyana     09-16 0265</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Guyana,0305</SECOND>
<HEAD>Catholic Nun Injured as Youth Gangs Break Up Pro-Democracy March</HEAD>
<DATELINE>GEORGETOWN, Guyana (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Gangs of youths attacked peaceful
pro-democracy marchers in a slum district in the capital Sunday,
injuring a Roman Catholic nun and two other marchers.
   About 50 people took part in the march through the Albouystown
slum district in south Georgetown.
   Nearly 100 young people armed with sticks, bottles and bricks
attacked the group, forcing the marchers to flee into side streets
for safety.
   It was one of three marches organized by a pro-democracy group,
Guyana Action for Reform and Democracy.
   Sister Dooreen Rowtie, a member of the group's steering
committee, received five stitches for a head injury after the gang
members smashed the windshield of her car at the head of the march.
   ``It is clear that the incident was part of a planned operation
as gangs of youths formed human barricades and suddenly launched an
attack without provocation,'' she said.
   The youths took an amplifier, guitar, tape recorder and the
nun's wristwatch and gold ring.
   Sister Dooreen later appeared at a rally in her blood-stained
clothing.
   No arrests were made.
   Members of the reform group said they believed the gang members
were supporters of the ruling Peoples National Congress party,
which has held power since 1964 and must call an election by May
1991.
   The ruling party is to begin its election campaign with a rally
in Georgetown at the end of this month.
   The Marxist opposition Peoples Progressive Party, one of the
front-runners, began its campaign last weekend in anticipation of a
December election date.
   Guyana, a former British colony on the northeast coast of South
America, has a population of about 810,000, about half of whom are
East Indians and the rest blacks.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0085 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 2300EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-CaliforniaFire 1stLd-Writethru a0751 09-16 0251</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-California Fire, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0751,0275</SECOND>
<HEAD>2,500-Acre California Forest Fire Corralled</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Leads with 2 grafs to UPDATE with fire contained. Picks up 3rd
graf, `Unless we...'.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>TWAIN HARTE, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A 2,500-acre forest fire that sent
flames lapping close to three Sierra Nevada towns was contained
Sunday as rangers searched for an arsonist.
   The blaze in the Stanilaus National Park was contained inside
fire lines by Sunday evening, and firefighters expected to have it
under control late Monday.
   ``Unless we get some weird weather, we should have it under
control. All in all its looking pretty good,'' said U.S. Forest
Service spokesman Mike Brown.
   The fire broke out Thursday in a campground on the north fork of
the Tuolumne River, about 130 miles east of San Francisco. Flames
came within two miles of the towns of Mi-Wuk, Sierra Village and
Sugarpine on Saturday.
   Accidental causes were ruled out, Forest Service spokeswoman
Joan Leidenthal said.
   ``It's definitely arson,'' Leidenthal said, adding that
investigators had a few leads to a possible culprit.
   Four hundred people evacuated as flames advanced were allowed to
return home. About 2,700 firefighters were on fire lines. No
buildings were lost or damaged.
   ``There was the potential to really burn a lot of structures,
but we protected quite a few,'' Brown said. ``We just got lucky.
The weather cooperated.''
   Relatively cool temperatures in the low 80s and winds below 10
mph combined with normal humidity to slow the fire's spread, Brown
said.
   Five firefighters were injured. Three suffered minor injuries,
two suffered broken bones.The cost of fighting the fire was
estimated at $1.9 million.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0086 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 2321EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-Israel-US     09-16 0445</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Israel-US,0520</SECOND>
<HEAD>Chief of Staff Says Israel Worried About U.S.-Saudi Arms Deal</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Israel's chief of staff expressed concern
Sunday that the Bush administration's proposed multibillion-dollar
weapons sales to Saudi Arabia could destabilize the military
balance in the Middle East.
   Chief of Staff Lt. Gen. Dan Shomron also said Israel was worried
about events in neighboring Jordan, especially the recent visit of
radical Palestinian guerrilla leaders George Habash and Nayef
Hawatmeh.
   The Bush administration reportedly is preparing to submit to
Congress a request to sell Saudi Arabia at least $18 billion worth
of weapons, including F-15 fighter planes, helicopters, tanks and
other sophisticated arms to bolster the desert kingdom's defenses
against Iraq.
   The administration has already proposed selling Saudi Arabia $3
billion in new weapons, including F-15s, M-60 tanks, 15,000 rounds
of armor-piercing anti-tank ammunition and 200 Stinger
anti-aircraft missiles.
   Speaking on Israel radio, Shomron said the arms deal would give
the Saudis ``a large quantity of weapons, which are also of the
highest quality.''
   ``From our point of view, giving such weapons ... to countries
that are still formally at war with us is certainly not a recipe
for stability,'' Shomron said.
   ``I hope this situation will be balanced in order to guarantee
in the future our technological superiority and deterrent
capability,'' he said.
   According to Israeli sources, Defense Minister Moshe Arens, who
is now in the United States, plans to ask Washington for money to
help Israel's defense industry develop weaponry, as well as for
U.S.-made weaponry such as F-15 and F-16 fighter planes.
   Turning to the gulf crisis, Shomron predicted that Iraq might be
able to withstand the lack of food and other goods caused by the
U.N. trade embargo but not a shortage of spare parts for the army.
   ``It is easier to convince people that for the cause of a just,
important war they should be content with less food or services,''
Shomron said.
   ``If this problem of spare parts for weapons systems, mostly
advanced systems, does not exist today, it will soon become a
serious issue.''
   Shomron said Israel was concerned about developments in Jordan
because of its strong support for Iraq and the reappearance of
radical Palestinian leaders in the kingdom.
   Habash and Hawatmeh have been supported by Syria but are now
reportedly moving their headquarters to Iraq.
   ``Securing the border between us and Jordan is mostly under the
responsibility of the Jordanian army, and there are many
Palestinians in it too,'' Shomron noted. ``This situation carries
many dangers; we are watching and we are alert to any possibility
of a change.''
   He reiterated Israel's long-standing policy that the entrance of
Iraqi forces into Jordan would trigger a military response from
Israel but qualified it, saying: ``I propose to remember ... that
this is subject to consideration, to carefully determining what has
entered, and for what purpose, but in principle this is a red
line.''
   ``We are preparing our forces for every eventuality, from the
point of view of training, weapons and logistics,'' Shomron said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0087 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 1226EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f BC-Gulf-Economy     09-16 0167</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Gulf-Economy,0186</SECOND>
<HEAD>Forecast: U.S. Economy Will Dodge Recession Despite Mideast
Turmoil</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Higher oil prices will hold down U.S. economic
growth but the nation will not enter a recession this year or early
1991, according to a forecast by the Conference Board.
   The business group said in a statement for release Monday that
the economy should grow about 1.5 percent in the current quarter
and 2.6 percent in the fourth quarter of this year.
   But although the economy is expected to avoid a recession in
coming months, corporate profits should slump and interest rates
rise due to the jump in oil prices, said Gail D. Fosler, the
Conference Board's chief economist.
   The board's forecast, anticipating a spot oil price of about $30
a barrel over the next two quarters, projects the federal budget
deficit will hit $252 billion in fiscal 1991, which starts Oct. 1.
   The report says the cost of the mililary action in the Mideast
along with the sluggish economy will add $20 billion to the base
level of the fiscal 1991 deficit.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0088 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 1235EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f BC-ManufacturingSurvey     09-16 0186</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Manufacturing Survey,0198</SECOND>
<HEAD>Survey: U.S. Manufacturers Plan To Invest Same or More in 1991</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Three-quarters of U.S. midsized manufacturing
companies contacted in a survey said they plan to spend as much or
more on plant and equipment in 1991 as they did this year.
   Four out of 10 manufacturers with annual sales of $10 million to
$200 million said they will invest the same amount next year. An
additional third said they will increase such spending.
   Only one in five plans to cut capital spending next year,
according to the survey by Grant Thornton, an accounting and
management consulting firm.
   Replacing plant and equipment was the most prevalent reason
given for increased spending, followed by spending to boost
productivity, Grant Thornton said.
   Those who said they will decrease spending say they either
believe they have invested enough or that they cannot afford more
investments due to poor earnings or insufficient funds.
   The telephone survey was conducted in late June by the research
organization Wirthlin Group, which randomly contacted 250 midsized
manufacturers. Grant Thornton said the sampling margin of error was
plus or minus 6 percentage points.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900916-0089 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-16-90 1245EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f BC-RichestEntertainers-L     09-16 0324</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Richest Entertainers-List,0383</SECOND>
<HEAD>With AM-Richest Entertainers</HEAD>
<NOTE>For release 6:30 p.m. EDT Sunday, Sept. 16</NOTE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here is a list of Forbes magazine's 40
highest-paid entertainers. The ranking is based on the magazine's
estimate of total gross earnings for 1989 and 1990.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   1. Bill Cosby, 53, television personality, $115 million.
   2. Michael Jackson, 32, singer, $100 million.
   3. The Rolling Stones, rock group, $88 million.
   4. Steven Spielberg, 42, movie producer, $87 million.
   5. New Kids on the Block, pop music group, $78 million.
   6. Oprah Winfrey, 36, television personality, $68 million.
   7. Sylvester Stallone, 44, actor, $63 million.
   8. Madonna, singer, 32, $62 million.
   9. Arnold Schwarzenegger, 43, actor, $55 million.
   10. Charles M. Schulz, 67, cartoonist, $54 million.
   11. Johnny Carson, 64, talk-show host, $50 million.
   12. Jack Nicholson, 53, actor-director, $50 million.
   13. Eddie Murphy, 29, comedian, $48 million.
   14. Paul McCartney, 48, singer, $45 million.
   15. Julio Iglesias, 46, singer, $44 million.
   16. Bruce Willis, 35, actor, $36 million.
   17. The Who, rock group, $35 million.
   18. Sean Connery, 60, actor, $35 million.
   19. Bon Jovi, rock group, $35 million.
   20. Prince, 32, rock star, $35 million.
   21. Michael J. Fox, 29, actor, $33 million.
   22. Billy Joel, 41, singer, $32 million.
   23. Aerosmith, rock group, $31 million.
   24. Pink Floyd, rock group, $30 million.
   25. The Grateful Dead, rock group, $30 million.
   26. Janet Jackson, 25, singer, $30 million.
   27. Siegfried &amp; Roy, illusionists, $28 million.
   28. Frank Sinatra, 74, singer, $27 million.
   29. Tom Cruise, 28, actor, $26 million.
   30. U2, rock group, $25 million.
   31. Michael Douglas, 46, $24 million.
   32. Andrew Lloyd Webber, 42, theater producer, $24 million.
   33. Paula Abdul, 28, singer, $23 million.
   34. Stephen King, 43, author, $22 million.
   35. Harrison Ford, 48, actor, $22 million.
   36. Jim Davis, 45, cartoonist, $21 million.
   37. Mel Gibson, 34, actor, $20 million.
   38. Cameron Mackintosh, 43, theater producer, $20 million.
   39. George Michael, 27, singer, $18 million.
   40. Guns N' Roses, rock group, $17 million.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
</Collection>
