<Collection>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0001 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 0015EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BnaiBrithWomen     09-02 0255</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bnai Brith Women,0262</SECOND>
<HEAD>World's Largest Jewish Organization To Allow Women Members</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DALLAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The world's largest Jewish organization, B'nai
Brith International, is setting aside its 147-year history as a
predominantly male group and will allow women as full members.
   Leaders of B'nai Brith and B'nai Brith Women this week reached
an agreement that recognizes B'nai B'rith Women as an independent,
self-governing organization affiliated with B'nai B'rith.
   Delegates to the B'nai B'rith biennial convention gathered in
Dallas last week. As B'nai B'rith moved in recent years toward
admitting women, the future of the separate women's organization
has been hotly debated.
   The agreement defines B'nai B'rith Women as a women's
organization and B'nai B'rith as an organization for both men and
women. The agreement can be renegotiated after five years.
   The measure admitting women as full members to B'nai B'rith
passed unanimously Tuesday at the convention. Previously, there
were individual units of the organization that allowed women
members.
   With the change, about 10,000 new women members to B'nai B'rith
are expected.
   ``We have indeed preserved what we did not want to tear
asunder,'' said B'nai B'rith Women president Harriet Horowitz.
   ``This agreement ends a complicated and tense time in the
history of our organizations,'' Ms. Horowitz said. ``It ends a
situation that has divided families and created much adverse
publicity.''
   Retiring B'nai B'rith president Seymour Reich favored admitting
the women's group as a full equal.
   The agreement must be ratified by the B'nai B'rith Women
Delegates Assembly. Mail-in ballots are due by Oct. 15.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0002 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 0016EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-PrayerWarriors    09-02 0451</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Prayer Warriors, </SECOND>
<HEAD>Evangelist To Battle San Francisco's `Spirits Of Perversion'</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SAN FRANCISCO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Texas evangelist has ordered hundreds of
thousands of ``prayer warriors'' to descend on San Francisco on
Halloween to fight what he called the satanic forces of witchcraft,
drugs and perversion.
   ``We need to reverse the curse on Halloween night,'' said Larry
Lea, a televangelist who sometimes dons army fatigues and issues
``prayer army dog tags'' to followers. Lea said Friday that
Halloween is innocent no more.
   ``This is not just kids having fun,'' he said. ``There is actual
worship of the devil.''
   Lea, whose daily ``Change Your Life'' television show is aired
on 40 independent stations nationwide, is part of a growing
movement of evangelical preachers who believe ``territorial
spirits'' rule particular cities, industries and subcultures.
   According to Dick Bernal, pastor of the Jubilee Christian Center
in San Jose, San Francisco is ruled by the Spirit of Perversion,
Oakland by the spirit of murder, San Jose by the spirit of greed
and Marin County, north of San Francisco, by the New Age spirit.
   These evil spirits can be exorcised through ``militant
power-praying'' _ such as shouting, stomping, brandishing imaginary
swords and speaking in tongues, Bernal and Lea explained.
   Lea, former pastor of the Church of the Rock in Rockwall, Texas,
oversees 70 pastors and 40,000 churchmembers from his Dallas-based
ministry.
   Last year, 6,000 people attended his three-day ``Prayer
Breakthrough'' in Anaheim designed to ``inflict serious damage'' on
evil spirits in Southern California.
   Lea said he would promote the San Francisco campaign on his
television program. He said he has signed up 280,000 prayer
warriors and wants at least 20,000 more.
   Some followers will go to the area's tallest buildings to pray
over the city, he said.
   ``This area has been the launching pad for a lot of things we
consider unbiblical _ free sex, the homosexual movement, acid
rock,'' said Bernal, whose Jubilee Christian Center has 5,500
members. ``There are strong spirits of perversion and greed.''
   Bernal's church holds annual conferences during which members
pray at abortion clinics, New Age spirituality centers and
newspaper offices to repel ``demonic forces.''
   Many Pentecostal Christians and other conservative evangelicals
believe that spirits control cities or buildings, said C. Peter
Wagner, a professor of church growth at Fuller Theological Seminary
in Pasadena.
   Professor Ron Enroth, a Christian sociologist at Westmont
College in Santa Barbara, accused Lea of putting on a
``supernatural sideshow'' and ``coming on like God's Green Beret
and whipping people up in a militaristic manner.''
   ``Rather than facing up to the structural problems of our
society, they find a demon behind every problem,'' he said. ``They
are looking for quick fixes by pushing God's buttons.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0003 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 0018EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-RiotAnniversary 1stLd-Writethru a0603 09-02 0669</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Riot Anniversary, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0603,0684</SECOND>
<HEAD>Turnout Relatively Low For Resort Hit By Riot Last Year</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 6th graf, `Hotels were...' to UPDATE with hotels now 75
percent full; SUBS 9th graf, `City officials ...' with 28,000
visitors in town</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By D.W. PAGE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>VIRGINIA BEACH, Va. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   City officials were confident they
could prevent the violence that marred last year's Labor Day beach
festival, but visitors said the heightened security this year was
also dampening the fun.
   Fraternities and sororities from predominantly black schools
along the East Coast have held an annual end-of-summer fest in
Virginia Beach for the last 10 years.
   Last year's festivities were marred by looting and clashes
between police and college-aged youths that resulted in 220
arrests, 43 injuries, $1.4 million in damage to stores and
lingering accusations of police brutality.
   To prevent another outbreak, the city put its entire 600-member
police force to work, and designed a parking plan to keep cars off
the beach.
   By 5:30 p.m., 16 people had been arrested, 12 for public
drunkenness, said Craig Andrews, media coordinator for Laborfest.
   Hotels were about three-quarters full by Saturday night, but
merchants said they were doing little more business than a typical
summer weekend.
   ``It's very much toned down this year, but probably a little bit
too much,'' said Rodney Williams, a 21-year-old student from
Farmingdale College in New York. ``I understand the need for the
security measures, but this is kind of too much.''
   After last year's violence, many black fraternity members
claimed that white merchants and city officials had been harassing
them. The city appointed a biracial committee to help plan this
year's event.
   City officials, who estimated the 1989 crowd at more than
100,000, said the problems started because of too many people in
too small an area with too little to do. At 5 p.m. Saturday, the
crowd on the beachfront resort strip was estimated at 28,000,
Andrews said.
   Virginia Beach Police Chaplain Don R. Staton said the atmosphere
was relaxed this year because of fewer people.
   ``Places that were usually crowded, weren't,'' he said.
   Some of those who did make the trip were unhappy with what they
found.
   ``There's too much police, said Ben Ogbogu, of Greenbelt, Md.,
who was making his third annual visit. ``I think that's going to
cause people to get nervous and start some of the same thing that
happened last year. It doesn't look peaceful. It looks militant.''
   As part of preparations for the weekend, the city closed off a
200-block section of the beachfront to cars. Visitors were directed
to satellite parking areas, with shuttle buses carrying them to and
from the beach.
   Tanya Dance, 23, of Wilmington, Del., complained about the
traffic restrictions. ``I'm paying $100 a night for a hotel room
and I can't even go out in my car,'' she said.
   Saturday morning, the main beachfront thoroughfare was nearly
empty as the afternoon began for what is usually the biggest
vacation weekend of the year.
   ``You can see the tumbleweeds go down the street,'' said Deepak
Nachnani, a shop manager. ``It's like a ghost town.''
   Others said a holiday without violence would be worth a few lost
dollars.
   ``I would like to think that we can measure this weekend in
other than economic terms,'' said Flo McDaniel, executive director
of the Virginia Beach Hotel and Motel Association.
   City officials would not give a number of visitors that would be
necessary to call Laborfest a success.
   But Arthur Jarrett Jr., president of the student government
association at Norfolk State University and a member of the
committee that planned the event, said, ``Success for me is that
our image is changed from the hellraisers we were depicted as last
year. If I'm the only one at the beach, I want to have a good
time.''
   For Deborah Lee of New York City, who came ``for the action, the
excitement and the men,'' there were still plenty of opportunities
for ``enjoying the scenery.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0004 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 0038EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-SolarFlight     09-02 0268</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Solar Flight,0276</SECOND>
<HEAD>Favorable Winds Pushing Sun Seeker Toward Kitty Hawk</HEAD>
<DATELINE>VICTORIA, Va. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Favorable winds pushed the solar-powered
Sun Seeker plane about 125 miles Saturday and put the craft as
close as a day away from its cross-country destination of Kitty
Hawk, N.C.
   Pilot Eric Raymond touched down at 6:15 p.m. at the Lunenburg
County Airport near this tiny town about 60 miles southwest of
Richmond, after about 6{ hours in the air, said spokesman Jack
Whitehouse in Los Angeles.
   The plane landed about 150 miles away from Kitty Hawk,
birthplace of powered flight and the scheduled end of Raymond's
trip that began in California. With good weather, the plane could
reach Kitty Hawk on Sunday, said Whitehouse.
   Raymond averaged 20 mph Saturday in the 198-pound plane.
   ``It was a good flight, good soaring weather,'' Whitehouse said.
   Raymond was pushed by northwest tail winds across a sky strewn
with puffy clouds, Whitehouse said.
   The plane suffered a slight loss of power because of a decrease
of voltage from its batteries, the spokesman said. The power loss
was not life threatening for Raymond, 33, a former national hang
gliding champion.
   Raymond's cross-country flight is intended to show the potential
of solar power. The plane takes off under a solar-powered motor
turning the propeller, then flies like a glider.
   Sun Seeker first took off on July 16 from Desert Center, Calif.
Two days later, the craft was seriously damaged in an aborted
takeoff from Lordsburg, N.M. The craft, pilot and crew returned to
Lake Elsinore, Calif. for repairs.
   It took off again from Desert Center Aug. 2.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0005 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 0047EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Stealth-Temple     09-02 0236</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Stealth-Temple,0245</SECOND>
<HEAD>Stealth Fighters Use Temple For Target Practice</HEAD>
<DATELINE>OGDEN, Utah (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Mormon Church temple is a favorite mock
target of military pilots training in stealth fighter-bombers, a
Utah congressman said.
   Rep. Jim Hansen, a Republican, said a squadron of the futuristic
F-117A fighter-bombers use the illuminated, spired temple in St.
George as a target on their mock bombing runs.
   The church in St. George, 250 miles south of Salt Lake City, is
one of the first Mormon temples built in Utah.
   ``They take out the St. George temple every night. I was out
there watching them do it a few times,'' said Hansen, a member of
the House Armed Services Committee.
   The F117-A was designed to penetrate radar defense and bomb
targets before enemy forces can react, according to the Pentagon.
The plane has been flying since 1981, but the Pentagon refused to
even acknowledge it existed until late 1988.
   A squadron of the planes recently flew to Saudi Arabia for
Operation Desert Shield.
   Hansen said the figher pilots, based at the Tonopah Test Range
in Nevada, mean no disrespect to the 1.7 million-member Church of
Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints, based in Salt Lake.
   ``The commander of the group was a (Mormon) bishop so I guess he
felt all right taking out the St. George temple,'' said Hansen, who
spoke Thursday to a group of Ogden-area businessmen about U.S.
military technology.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0006 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 0327EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-GulfRdp 7thLd-Writethru   09-02 1271</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf Rdp, 7th Ld-Writethru,a0650,1307</SECOND>
<HEAD>Iraq Frees Some Westerners; Superpowers to Discuss Gulf Crisis</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: INSERTS one graf after 11th pvs, `The talks...' to UPDATE
with Perez de Cuellar comment; Pickup 12th, `The United...';
INSERTS one graf after 23rd pvs, `An Iraqi...' to UPDATE with plane
leaving for washington; Pickup 24th, `The British...'</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos LON1,XSAV4,CAI1-2,DOD2,DHA1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By THOMAS WAGNER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   More than 100 Americans and several hundred other foreigners
left Baghdad on jetliners for home Saturday, but many others
remained behind, prompting President Bush to criticize Iraq for
freeing the hostages too slowly.
   In another major development, Bush announced on Saturday that he
and President Mikhail S. Gorbachev will meet in Helsinki, Finland,
on Sept. 9 to discuss the Middle East and other matters, including
arms control.
   ``I'm glad when any American comes out of there, but there's a
certain brutality, a certain tawdry performance in all of this,''
Bush said, when asked about Iraq's policy of releasing a few
hundred captives at a time.
   ``It is so base and so outrageous that I think most people in
the Arab world are very embarrassed by this, and I think that's
certainly true of others around the world,'' Bush told reporters in
Kennebunkport, Maine.
   The summit announcement indicates Moscow may be willing to play
a larger role in resolving the crisis caused by Iraq's invasion of
Kuwait Aug. 2.
   Progress also was reported on another diplomatic front Saturday.
   Sources in Amman, Jordan, where U.N. Secretary General Javier
Perez de Cuellar and a senior Iraqi official met, said the two men
were discussing a plan designed to prevent a war between Iraq and
United States.
   The sources said the plan would create an Arab peacekeeping
force to act as a buffer between the tens of thousands of Iraqi
troops in occupied Kuwait and the U.S.-led multinational force
being deployed in Saudi Arabia.
   The Soviet Union might help mediate simultaneous withdrawals of
Iraqi troops from Kuwait and opposing forces from Saudi Arabia, the
sources said.
   Perez de Cuellar and Iraqi Foreign Minister Tariq Aziz expressed
optimism, but neither would comment on the reports when their
two-day meeting ended.
   ``The talks were very fruitful,'' Aziz said. ``This situation is
complicated and dramatic (and) cannot be resolved by dramatic
diplomacy. It needs patience. It needs time and people to
understand exactly the positions.''
   But at a press conference later, Perez de Cuellar said he was
disappointed more progress had not been made. ``I had hoped for
more,'' Perez de Cullar said, without elaborating.
   The United States, meanwhile, continued to pour troops and
military hardware into Saudi Arabia, where a multinational force is
being deployed to oppose Iraqi troops massed near Kuwait's border
with Saudi Arabia.
   Until recently, American troops had remained well south of Saudi
Arabia's border, but now they are moving north to bolster the
force's defensive lines and significantly improve its offensive
capabilities.
   U.S. officials say the movement northward of several units
indicates that U.S. commanders in Saudi Arabia are now comfortable
putting troops a good distance away from major supply points.
   ``If nothing else, it shows we believe we are now capable of
sustaining a significant force in forward positions,'' a senior Air
Force officer said.
   U.S. officials say more than 100,000 troops, including those
aboard dozens of ships, are in the Persian Gulf region or on the
way.
   The United States could contribute as many as 250,000 soldiers
to the multinational force, which includes token contingents from
other nations.
   For most of the day Saturday, the United States and other
nations waited to see how many of the women and children among the
21,000 Westerners held hostage in Iraq and Kuwait would be allowed
to leave for home.
   After lengthy delays, an Iraqi Airways plane with 68 Japanese
women and children aboard was the first to leave Iraq for Jordan.
It arrived in Amman, and the hostages were to land in Tokyo on
Sunday.
   A Lufthansa plane took off next with 311 women and children from
22 countries, including about 60 Americans of Iraqi extraction and
71 Germans. The flight landed in Frankfurt early Sunday.
   A few arriving passengers smiled briefly or waved, but nearly
all looked grim and exhausted. Some women carried sleeping children
on their shoulders. One woman's eyes flooded with tears as she
walked into the terminal.
   Diana Haroon, 24, an Iraqi-American from Chicago, said:
``Everybody wanted to go back to the United States because we have
American citizenship and we can't stay there (in Baghdad) all the
time. ... It's not good there.''
   An Iraqi Airways 747 left Baghdad early Saturday bound for
Paris, London and Washington. That flight carried 199 Britons,
about 50 Americans and more than 20 French citizens, although there
was confusion over the numbers.
   The plane arrived in London early Sunday after the Paris
stopover, then left for Washington at 6:55 local time (1:55 EDT).
The flight was expected to take 7{ hours, airport officials said.
   The British Foreign Office in London said departure of the Iraqi
Airways jetliner from Baghdad had been delayed by the late arrival
of a flight from Kuwait City carrying the Rev. Jesse Jackson, the
American civil rights activist.
   Jackson flew to Kuwait early Saturday to collect sick Americans
after meeting twice with Iraqi President Saddam Hussein to secure
their release.
   Jackson eventually brought 26 Americans out of Kuwait and
another four who had come out of Kuwait by car joined his group in
Baghdad.
   The State Department estimates that about 1,000 American women
and children were stranded in Iraq and Kuwait by the invasion.
Saddam announced last week that all foreign women and children
could leave, but the process was delayed by red tape and new
demands by Iraq.
   National security adviser Brent Scowcroft joined Bush on
Saturday in criticizing Saddam for playing ``a game'' with the
hostages in which ``the rules change daily, sometimes hourly.''
   Scowcroft _ who also spoke with reporters in Kennebunkport _
demanded that Saddam free all foreign hostages, including the
Western men who have been moved to Iraqi military installtions to
deter a possible U.S. attack.
   In addition to deploying troops in Saudi Arabia, the United
States and other nations also are enforcing a trade embargo against
Iraq, and it appears the sanctions are beginning to cause hardships
in Iraq.
   Iraq has issued coupon books to prepare for rationing that began
Saturday, and sources in Baghdad said food distribution centers
have been set up.
   The coupons entitle each Iraqi to a monthly allocation of 13
pounds of flour, 3.3 pounds of rice, 2.2 pounds of sugar, 3.5
ounces of tea, 1.1 pounds of oil, 17 ounces of detergent and one
bar of soap, the sources said.
   Children under a year old receive three cans of powdered milk
each month, but older children receive none.
   Elsewhere in the Middle East, the Persian Gulf crisis continued
to open rifts in the Arab world and upset the balance of power in
the region.
   After a two-day meeting in Egypt, the Arab League hardened its
position on the invasion by demanding Iraq pay war reparations to
Kuwait after withdrawing its troops. The League also demanded that
Iraq immediately free all hostages.
   The crisis also reportedly has left Israel, Egypt and Saudi
Arabia scrambling for more arms and financial assistance from the
United States.
   Bush administration officials say the president has decided to
make available more high-tech weapons for Israel and is considering
forgiving Egypt's $6.7 billion military debt with the United States.
   Additional weapons for Israel would bolster that country's
defense against Iraq and offset recent decisions to sell Saudi
Arabia more tanks and warplanes.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0007 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 0339EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Gulf-Foreigners 9thLd-Writethru a0648 09-02 0940</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Foreigners, 9th Ld-Writethru, a0648,0968</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hundreds of Foreigners, Including Americans, Fly Out of Iraq</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 9th-12th pvs, `A third...in London' to UPDATE with plane
leaving London, 199 Britons leaving plane; Pickup 13th, `One of...'</NOTE>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf Rdp, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TERRY LEONARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BAGHDAD, Iraq (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hundreds of foreign women and children,
including more than 100 Americans, flew to freedom Saturday aboard
three jetliners from Baghdad.
   The first flight out of the Iraqi capital carried 68 Japanese
women and children to Amman, Jordan, where they boarded a Japan Air
Lines plane to Tokyo.
   Later, a Lufthansa plane took off from Baghdad with 250 women
and 61 children on board, including 60 Americans and 71 Germans,
the West German foreign ministry said. The Americans were of Iraqi
origin.
   After a five-hour flight, the plane landed Sunday in Frankfurt.
None of the passengers were sick or injured, the ministry said.
   Lufthansa said a preliminary list showed 316 people were on the
flight, and at least one German man got off the plane. The Foreign
Ministry said it did not have any information yet on men aboard the
flight.
   A few arriving passengers smiled briefly or waved, but nearly
all looked grim and exhausted. Some women carried sleeping children
on their shoulders. One woman's eyes flooded with tears as she
walked into the terminal.
   Diana Haroon, 24, an Iraqi-American from Chicago, said:
``Everybody wanted to go back to the United States because we have
American citizenship and we can't stay there (in Baghdad) all the
time. ... It's not good there.''
   ``It's tough,'' she said, describing the situation in Iraq.
Asked if she was nervous before she was allowed to leave, she said
``Sure.''
   A third flight, an Iraqi Airways 747, landed in London after a
stopover in Paris then left for Washington at 6:55 local time (1:55
EDT). The flight was expected to take 7{ hours, Heathrow airport
officials said.
   The 747 was believed to have carried 199 Britons, about 50
Americans and more than 20 French nationals from Baghdad.
   The French Foreign Ministry, however, said the flight was
carrying more than 340 evacuees from Iraq.
   Seventeen French women and five children disembarked from the
plane after it landed at Orly International Airport south of Paris,
and the 199 Britons left the flight in London.
   One of three American citizens who had requested permission to
get off in Paris was also allowed to disembark so he could visit
his seriously ill wife in Switzerland, said U.S. Embassy spokesman
Parker Hallberg.
   There were varying reports on how many Americans were on the
flight. Hallberg said there were about 40 Americans on the plane,
but reports from Baghdad indicated about 50 U.S. citizens boarded
there.
   The Rev. Jesse Jackson, who was aboard the flight, said there
were 55 U.S. evacuees.
   ``There was no evidence of abusive treatment but there was great
tension,'' Jackson told reporters in Paris. ``There was a sense of
jubilation.''
   A U.S. embassy doctor, Esther Roberts, was the only person
allowed to board the plane during the stopover in Paris, embassy
officials said.
   ``It's considered an Iraqi military mission,'' Hallberg said. He
said Iraqi security officials were on board the plane, but he did
not know whether they were armed.
   There was so much confusion over numbers at Baghdad airport that
not even ambassadors had accurate totals of their own nationals on
board.
   Some of the American and British women interviewed at Baghdad
airport before departure said they left husbands behind as part of
Iraqi leader Saddam Hussein's human shield at strategic
installations to deter any U.S. attack.
   ``Our husbands are being held, and we don't want to put them in
danger,'' said an American woman standing in line at Baghdad
airport who declined to give her name.
   Another, Debby Willis of Parkman, Maine, said she and her
husband, Jerry Willis, were trying to escape across the desert from
Kuwait when Iraqi troops captured them. Her husband stayed behind
at a military site, she said.
   Authorities held the Iraqi flight full of Americans and Britons
until Jackson, the American civil rights activist, returned from
Kuwait with sick American hostages whose release he gained after
meeting twice with Saddam.
   Jackson brought 26 hostages out of Kuwait, including 20 people
suffering from various illnesses. Only one of them required a
stretcher _ a woman who broke her hip in a car accident while being
moved from Kuwait to Baghdad.
   Four people who had come out of Kuwait by car were added to
Jackson's party in Baghdad, bringing his total to 30. As many as 21
other Americans who had been detained in Iraq also boarded the
flight.
   Jackson's departure from Kuwait was delayed by protracted
negotiations to bring out an American woman who had called him at
his hotel with a plea to take her out with him.
   Jackson was believed to have said he would not leave without her.
   At Baghdad's airport, Jackson told The Associated Press: ``This
is a window of hope, and it must be expanded.''
   He said he was encouraged by his meetings with Saddam, whom he
found ready to talk. ``When people are willing to talk, that is a
step in the first direction,'' Jackson said. ``There must be a
cooling of the rhetoric in this quest for peace.''
   He urged U.S. senators and congressmen to use their influence to
expand the window of opportunity in Iraq, adding: ``Diplomacy must
not take a backseat to economic resistance and military
preparedness.''
   In all, about 21,000 Westerners were trapped in Iraq and Kuwait
by Iraq's Aug. 2 invasion of its oil-rich neighbor. They included
3,000 Americans.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0008 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 0433EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i BC-Gulf-Diplomacy     09-02 0526</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Gulf-Diplomacy,0543</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.N. Chief Says He's Disappointed After Talks With Aziz</HEAD>
<DATELINE>AMMAN, Jordan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   U.N. Secretary General Javier Perez de
Cuellar indicated Sunday that his effort to avert a military
showdown in the gulf has failed, saying he was disappointed by
Iraq's inflexibility.
   ``As I leave, I must acknowledge a certain disappointment,'' the
U.N. chief told a televised news conference after four meetings
with Iraqi Foreign Minister Tariq Aziz.
   ``The main problem was the occupation and annexation of Kuwait
by Iraq,'' he said.
   Answering a reporter's question in French, the Secretary General
said: ``The talks were useful, but disappointing ... I had hoped
for a more flexible position regarding the retreat of the Iraqis
from Kuwait.''
   The U.N. chief said he was leaving for Paris to brief Jordan's
King Hussein on the outcome of the talks. The Jordanian monarch, an
ally of Iraq, has been trying to defuse tensions escalating since
Iraq's Aug. 2 invasion of Kuwait.
   Hussein is in Europe this weekend seeking to avert further
escalation of the crisis as the U.S.-led multinational force
continued to build in Saudi Arabia. Thousands of mostly U.S. troops
face more than 200,000 Iraqi soldiers along Saudi Arabia's northern
borders with Iraq and Kuwait.
   A Jordanian official who had been close to the talks between
Aziz and the U.N. chief said Saturday the two men were close to a
plan that would edge the Middle East back from the brink of war.
   It mainly called for setting up a buffer between the Iraqis and
the multinational troops in Saudi Arabia to be manned by an Arab
peacekeeping force.
   Under the plan, the Iraqis would free all foreign nationals
still held in occupied Kuwait and Iraq. The final step would be a
simultaneous withdrawal of Iraqi troops from Kuwait and the
multinational forces in Saudi Arabia.
   But it appeared a last-minute hitch undermined the plan.
   Perez de Cuellar did not refer directly to the plan. But his
repeated references to Iraq's ``inflexibility'' indicated he had
failed to win a pledge from the Iraqis to relinquish Kuwait, or at
least discuss that as an option.
   Perez de Cuellar said Aziz reiterated his country's position
that the issue of Kuwait needed ``an Arab solution,'' away from
foreign intervention.
   But the U.N. chief stressed to Aziz the crisis has taken on
``international dimensions'' and that the ``global interests and
principles have to be acknowledged.''
   Perez de Cuellar said he welcomed Iraq's decision to free
hundreds of foreign women and children, but that he told Aziz this
was not enough.
   He said, ``I emphasized that this decision should be followed by
another ... that all restrictions on foreigners and their movement
be lifted.
   Hundreds of foreign women and children as well as some sick
Americans flew to freedom Saturday. They were the first of the
hostages flown out of Iraq since Baghdad last week said they would
be allowed to leave.
   But thousands more foreigners, mostly men, are still banned from
leaving Iraq, many of them interned at key installations to avert a
potential U.S. attack.
   When Iraq invaded Kuwait, about 21,000 Westerners, including
3,000 Americans, were caught in both countries.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0009 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 0857EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>v u BC-Weather Advisory   09-02 0037</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Weather, Advisory,0037</SECOND>
<TEXT>
   Eds: A break in a cable in Washington, D.C., has disrupted
transmission of weather data to The Associated Press. Prospects for
quick resolution of problem uncertain. We will keep you advised.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>The AP</HEAD>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0010 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 0945EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>b a BC-Gulf-AmericansHome 1stAdd a0658 09-02 0102</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Gulf-Americans Home, 1st Add, a0658,100</SECOND>
<HEAD>FAIRFAX, Va.: into captives.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   The flight landed at 9:38 a.m. EDT. The passengers, weary from
more than 24 hours of waiting and traveling, were awaited by family
members and U.S. officials. Iraq's ambassador to the United States,
Mohamed Mashat, was at the airport outside Washington, D.C., and
had planned to greet the arriving Americans as well.
   Among the passengers was civil rights activist Jesse Jackson,
who had said during a stopover in Paris that there 55 Americans
aboard. Jackson, traveling as a television journalist, had met
twice last week with Iraqi President Saddam Hussein.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0011 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 1040EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i BC-Mohawks     09-02 0519</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Mohawks,0537</SECOND>
<HEAD>Canadian Troops End Blockade of Road</HEAD>
<DATELINE>OKA, Quebec (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Canadian Army took control Sunday of the
highway running through the Mohawk territory of Kahnesatake, ending
the blockade of the road that began 54 days ago.
   On Sunday morning, about two dozen troops backed by two armored
personnel carriers moved onto the highway and began approaching the
main barricade at the top of the Oka hill, 18 miles west of
Montreal, where defiant Mohawks have waged an armed standoff with
government authorities.
   When the army moved in Sunday morning, none of the Mohawks made
a move to stop the troops. The soldiers strung barbed wire around
the main barricade on highway 344 and began to inspect it for mines
and booby traps.
   An army helicopter, with guns pointed out its side doors, flew
low overhead.
   ``Thank God it's over,'' said Master Cpl. Daniel Dugas as he
stood on the highway. ``It's about time and I'm happy it happened
without a shot.''
   Gen. Armand Roy, commander of the Canadian Forces 5th Brigade,
said he decided to send in his troops after two Mohawk men were
wounded in factional fighting behind Indian barricades set up in a
land dispute with government officials.
   ``I decided to move my troops so as to guarantee the security of
civilians and my soldiers,'' Roy said.
   The military action came after efforts failed to reach a
negotiated settlement in the dispute. The Mohawks have been trying
to block a golf course extension on land they claim is theirs, but
they have also raised other grievances.
   On Saturday, defiant Indian militants stood their ground and
screamed at Canadian soldiers to get away as troops pushed to
within 100 yards of the main barricade Saturday afternoon.
   The troops moved into an area where the army had estimated at
least 50 armed members of the militant Mohawk Warrior's Society
were located.
   Provincial authorities Monday had given the military the
go-ahead to end the armed standoff that began July 11, when the
Quebec provincial police attempted to storm a Mohawk barricade at
Oka. One officer was killed, but it is still not clear by whose
gunfire.
   Later that day, fellow Mohawks set up a blockade in sympathy at
the Mercier bridge, a major link between Montreal and its southern
suburbs.
   The ostensible reason for the Mohawk uprising _ expansion of the
golf course _ was settled when the federal government purchased the
land and said it would turn it over to the Indians.
   But militants seized the situation to publicize a much wider
range of Indian grievances against the government, including
demands for sovereignty.
   On Friday, Mohawks from the Kanewake reserve south of Montreal
allowed troops to remove the main barricades they had set up on
routes leading to the Mercier bridge. Quebec Transport Department
officials said it would take several days before the bridge can be
reopened to traffic.
   The bridge blockade forced thousands of commuters on the south
shore of the St. Lawrence River to make long detours to Montreal,
which is on an island. Angry residents have protested and thrown
rocks at Mohawks.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0012 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 1122EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a BC-Gulf-AmericansHome 3rdLd-Writethru a0664chatRobinHood'sHideout
09-02 0513</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Gulf-Americans Home, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0664,420</SECOND>
<HEAD>Americans Arrive in US From Iraq, Kuwait</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: Top 9 grafs new to change number to 24 sted 55, add quote
from hostage, quote from Jackson; pick up 7th graf pvs bgng ``The
Iraqi airways...</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By W. DALE NELSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>FAIRFAX, Va. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An Iraqi jetliner bearing two dozen American
women and children landed at Dulles International Airport today,
one month after Iraq's invasion of Kuwait turned foreigners in both
countries into captives.
   The flight landed at 9:38 a.m. EDT. The passengers, weary from
more than 24 hours of waiting and traveling, were greeted by family
members and U.S. officials.
   Ex-hostage Lloyd Culbertson, 76, of El Paso, Texas, said the
hostages left behind were being held without food and water.
   ``If it were not for the grace of God and Jesse Jackson, we
would not be here. The State Department has not lifted a hand for
us,'' Culbertson said.
   One of the arriving passengers, a woman, was put on an ambulance
and taken to a local hospital. ``It is not a serious illness,''
said Barbara Cebuhar, a spokeswoman for the Family Support
Administration of the Department of Health and Human Resources,
which is charged with helping the Americans.
   A State Department official said Jackson, who helped arrange the
flight to freedom, put the number of Americans on board at 24.
Jackson, at a stopover in Paris, had said there were 55 Americans
on the plane.
   Iraq's ambassador to the United States, Mohamed Mashat, was
among those awaiting the flight's arrival. Mike Brennan, a State
Department spokesman, said Mashat told U.S. officials he was there
to assure that the crew had no problems.
   Jackson, traveling as a television journalist, had met twice
last week with Iraqi President Saddam Hussein.
   He told reporters, ``Now that the military has played its role,
diplomacy must work. If preconditions make talks impossible, war is
inevitable.''
   The Iraqi Airways 747 was one of three jetliners to leave
Baghdad Airport on Saturday. The flights carried hundreds of
foreign women and children, who left their husbands and fathers
behind, and ailing men.
   About 21,000 Westerners were trapped in Iraq and Kuwait by
Iraq's Aug. 2 invasion of its oil-rich neighbor. They included
3,000 Americans.
   Saddam had announced last Tuesday he would allow the departure
of women and children, who had previously been held. More than a
week earlier, however, Saddam had ordered troops and officials to
round up Western men to be used as human shields around military
installations and other strategic locations.
   The flight to Dulles was the only of the three with the United
States as its final destination. A Lufthansa jet landed in
Frankfurt, West Germany, with 60 Iraqi-Americans among its
passengers. The other flight took 68 Japanese women and children
out of the country.
   Immediately after the jumbo jet landed at a remote terminal of
the airport, officials began taking the arriving passengers through
customs and other formalities as quickly as possible.
   Cebuhar said that the returning hostages could go to a hotel or
travel directly home.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0013 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 1122EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--RobinHood'sTree     09-02 0083</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Robin Hood's Tree,0082</SECOND>
<HEAD>Extra Fire Watch at Robin Hood's Hideout</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NOTTINGHAM, England (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Sherwood Forest rangers have
intensified their fire watch at the Major Oak, the tree where
legend says Robin Hood and his merry men hid out.
   Authorities say drought has turned parts of the forest
tinder-dry, and fire patrols have been stepped up, especially at
the 60-foot tall Major Oak.
   The tree, thought to be 600 to 800 years old, is a favorite
tourist attraction at Sherwood Forest.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0014 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 1129EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--TropicalStorm     09-02 0139</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Tropical Storm,0144</SECOND>
<HEAD>Storm Leaves 20 Missing, Destroys Many Homes in Vietnam</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BANGKOK, Thailand (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   At least 20 fishermen were missing and
homes were destroyed as Tropical Storm Becky lashed northern
Vietnamese provinces, the official Vietnam News Agency said.
   Becky hit Nghe Tinh last Wednesday with heavy rains winds of
more than 70 mph, the agency said Saturday. A text was seen in
Bangkok Sunday.
   The agency said the storm destroyed about 395,200 acres of rice
paddy and severely damaged many thatched-roof homes.
   ``Many portions of roads and dikes were washed away and three
boats with 20 fishermen aboard were reported missing,'' it said.
   Becky struck the Philippines with typhoon-force winds last week,
killing 32 people and forcing the evacuation of thousands of others
from flooded areas.
   A typhoon has sustained winds of at least 74 mph.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0015 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 1138EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--TattoosBanned     09-02 0150</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Tattoos Banned,0152</SECOND>
<HEAD>Report: Tattooed Youths Banned From Joining Army</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hundreds of army recruits have been rejected for
military service because of their tattoos, a newspaper reported
Sunday.
   The Guangming Daily said tattoos were discovered on about 75
percent of the youths at a recent military recruitment campaign in
Chengde, a city northeast of Beijing.
   It said most of the 574 tattooed youths used cigarettes or
sticks to make various designs, which the paper did not describe.
It also did not say why the army objects to tattoos.
   About 5 percent had tattoos of Chinese characters for
``fortune,'' ``longevity,'' ``strength,'' ``revenge'' and ``unity''
which their parents had given them as children in hopes of bringing
good luck to the family, the paper said.
   By March, about 5,100 young people from rural Beijing had joined
the army, an earlier report said. But no nationwide figures were
available.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0016 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 1139EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Gulf-The265th     09-02 0658</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-The 265th,0678</SECOND>
<HEAD>Chemical Warfare Training Takes on Edge of Reality</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf Rdp, Bjt</HEAD>
<HEAD>Laserphoto XSAV1</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   The 265th Quartermaster Detachment of the South
Carolina National Guard is one of the reserve units called up for
possible duty in Saudi Arabia. National Writer Fred Bayles is
following this small unit of 14 guardsmen as they prepare for
deployment overseas.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By FRED BAYLES</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP National Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>FORT STEWART, Ga. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   When nine seconds were up, at least
five men of the 265th Quartermaster Detachment were dead, a fact
that did not please some of the casualties.
   ``I was not dead,'' said a petulant Sgt. Ronnie Jackson, leader
of 14-member National Guard unit preparing for deployment to the
Mideast.
   But the sergeant instructing the unit in NBC _ nuclear,
biological, chemical warfare _ explained patiently that Jackson's
gas mask straps were still tangled nine seconds after she shouted
go. If this had been a nerve gas attack, he still wouldn't be
struggling to get the mask on, or have any breath left to argue.
   Ernie Deloach, the stocky corrections guard who is another of
the unit's sergeants, took the side of the instructor.
   ``If you start twitching, I'll have to shoot you and take
command,'' he told Jackson. Muffled laughter came from the circle
of hooded guardsmen standing in the light Georgia rain. Thunder
from the storm boomed in the distance.
   Chemical warfare exercises are not new to the 265th, a water
purification unit activated for duty in the Persian Gulf. Many of
the men have two decades in the South Carolina National Guard. They
trained yearly with gas masks and bulky chemical suits.
   But never before has this practice had such a sharp edge of
reality. The men are likely to go to a place where chemical warfare
is no drill.
   ``No one took this stuff seriously before now. Now everyone is
scared,'' said Sgt. Iris Craig, the unit's instructor.
   The sergeant is an intense teacher who rewards students with a
withering stare when they give an out-of-the-ballpark answer to her
questions.
   ``You need to wake up people,'' she said at one slow point in
class. ``If you could not effectively identify a chemical agent,
you could become a casualty.''
   But there is a lot to remember, or ``compute,'' as Craig keeps
saying. It's hard to keep it all straight. There's VX, GA, GB, GD,
blood agents, blister agents, persistent and non-persistent gases.
Is it GA that has a fruity odor and AC that smells like bitter
almonds? Or is it the other way around?
   It is a challenge, with your head pounding inside the gas mask,
to follow the 14 steps on your index-card-size M256 Detector Kit
and chose between the pastel blues and purples of the color chart
to see if you've been exposed to mustard or phosgene.
   ``There's no way we're going to remember it all,'' said Spc.
Willie Badger, a 34-year-old electrician. ``I'm just trying to
remember the important stuff.''
   A member of the 265th for nine years, Badger is affectionately
known as Bonehead to other unit members, after his shining pate.
Badger shaves his head each time he goes off on National Guard
deployment.
   His friends also tease him about his snoring, wondering out loud
if his wife finally is getting a good night's sleep now that he has
been called up.
   ``We mess around a lot, but when it comes to doing the job,
we're all business,'' he said.
   Badger spends his time in line outside the mess hall reading his
pocket Bible. He comes from a devout family; his mother wanted him
to be a preacher. But Badger confesses he is considered the
backslider of the family because he drinks and smokes.
   Don't worry, calls one his buddies, alcohol isn't allowed in
Saudi Arabia.
   ``My mom said she hopes when I come back I'll try preaching, but
I don't think so,'' he said with a grin.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0017 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 1139EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--India-Politics     09-02 0153</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--India-Politics,0158</SECOND>
<HEAD>Gandhi Top In Opinion Poll</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW DELHI, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Prime Minister V.P. Singh trails former
premier Rajiv Gandhi as the favorite man for the nation's top post,
according to an opinion poll published Sunday.
   Singh, who ousted Gandhi in elections last year, was preferred
by 36 percent of the respondents, compared with 44 percent who
favored Gandhi for prime minister. Twenty percent said both men
were equal.
   The poll by Marketing and Research Group found 29 percent of the
10,239 registered voters questioned thought Singh was doing a good
job, and an equal number thought he was doing badly. He was given a
middle rating by 42 percent.
   Thirty-eight percent thought Gandhi was deoing a good job, the
poll reported.
   Gandhi became prime minister after the 1984 assassination of his
mother, Indira Gandhi.
   The poll was published in the biweekly India Today magazine. No
margin of error was given.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0018 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 1142EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--BubonicPlague     09-02 0180</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Bubonic Plague,0183</SECOND>
<HEAD>Plague Kills Three</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NAIROBI, Kenya (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An outbreak of the bubonic plague has
killed three people in a low-income neighborhood on Nairobi's
eastern outskirts and 23 others have become ill, newspapers
reported Sunday.
   The three killed worked at a flour mill which has closed
temporarily as a precaution against further spread of the disease,
according to Kenya's three English-language dailies.
   The disease, also known as the Black Death, is transmitted to
humans by fleas from infected rats and is treatable with
antibiotics.
   Epidemics of the plague have occured throughout history, with
the best known being the Black Death that swept Europe and parts of
Asia in the 14th century, killing millions of people.
   As a result of the disease's outbreak in Embakasi, a low-income
area on Nairobi's eastern outskirts, leave for city health
officials has been canceled, the Sunday Standard reported.
   The government also has issued a list of preventive measure to
help stem the disease's spread, such as putting out chemicals to
kill rats and spraying insecticides in vehicles and baggage to kill
fleas.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0019 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 1143EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Gulf-FastStrike Bjt   09-02 0814</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Fast Strike, Bjt,800</SECOND>
<HEAD>Some Press for a Quick Strike, But Military Says It's Not Ready</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MIKE FEINSILBER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush is getting conflicting advice
on whether he should _ or even could _ strike against Iraq fast,
before the extraordinary coalition of nations that confronts Saddam
Hussein unravels.
   But the military is cautioning against it. Pentagon officials
say privately that the American buildup in Saudi Arabia is weeks
away from being ready for warfare, especially ground combat.
   ``Absolutely not,'' a military source said when asked last week
about the possibility of an offensive operation. ``We're just not
ready yet. We don't have enough force on the ground.''
   Administration officials say there is some pressure from within
Congress and from abroad to attack even without a provocative act
from Saddam, whose forces have pulled back from the
``cat-and-mouse'' air and sea taunts of a few days ago.
   One official, speaking on condition of anonymity, conceded that
if too much time passes the coalition against Saddam, particularly
in the Arab world, ``could fragment.'' At home, he acknowledged,
public support might drain away in the face of a stalemate.
   For the time being, Bush seems willing to wait to see if he can
strangle Saddam into submission through a worldwide blockade of
Iraq.
   ``The basic pieces of our policy are in place,'' he told a news
conference Thursday.
   So officials say it is unlikely he will launch an unprovoked
attack. The White House believes Saddam is on the run, one official
said.
   White House spokesman Roman Popadiuk characterized as
``uninformed speculation'' reports of pressure on the
administration for a military move.
   ``We have a strategy in place based on the United Nations
resolution and the U.N.-passed sanctions,'' he said.
   One official cited intelligence reports that Saddam is ``trying
to use oil as a bargaining chip'' to underscore the administration
portrait of the Iraqi president as an increasingly desperate man.
   He said Saddam was trying to barter oil for sugar and other
commodities. Such overtures have been made to Turkey, the
Philippines and elsewhere, he said.
   Also arguing against a quick-strike strategy _ one powerful
enough presumably to remove Iraq as a threat to Western interests
for years to come _ is the situation on the ground.
   U.S. forces are just beginning to assume defensive positions and
need more training in the hostile desert environment. Thousands
more troops are on the way to bolster the more than 60,000 U.S.
military personnel already in the gulf region.
   Allied Arab forces are even less combat ready and the Saudi
troops that constitute a border trip-wire defense are poorly
prepared to cope with gas warfare _ or an onslaught of powerful
Iraqi tanks.
   On Friday, Army Gen. H. Norman Schwarzkopf, the commander of
U.S. forces in the Middle East, said flatly: ``There's not going to
be any war unless the Iraqis attack.''
   If Saddam Hussein launched an attack, ``We'd respond, because
we'd have to,'' Schwarzkopf said. ``But we just don't have enough
armor on the ground yet to launch any kind of offensive.''
   A U.S.-initiated attack would change the political configuration
and upset the anti-Saddam alliance Bush has pieced together,
analysts caution.
   The Arab world could easily become united behind Saddam and
against the United States if Bush is seen as having used Iraq's
takeover of Kuwait as an excuse to establish a permanent American
presence in the Mideast.
   The Soviet Union would be uneasy about a major U.S. military
advance in the Middle East _ a subject Bush is likely to discuss
with Soviet President Mikhail Gorbachev on Sunday in Helsinki,
Finland.
   As it is, the leaders of Jordan and Egypt must worry about
Saddam's popularity among the masses.
   Saddam has tried to capitalize on public discontent in the
poorer Arab countries by picturing Israel as the hidden villain in
the gulf crisis and denouncing Saudi Arabia's royal rulers for
allowing ``infidel'' Americans to despoil the site of Islam's
holiest places.
   But American military officials in Saudi Arabia, who spoke on
grounds they wouldn't be quoted by name, said that if the United
States were intent on striking first it could have used its air
power to punish the Iraqi army in the first days of the invasion,
before Saddam had time to amass a huge force near the Saudi border.
   Some Saudi officials say that if fighting breaks out it will be
because Saddam initiates it _ or is goaded into taking a
provocative act.
   And at the Pentagon, a senior official contended there's no
first-strike sentiment in the top military ranks.
   ``They do the planning,'' he said of the military chiefs. ``They
know what's required. But contrary to popular belief, they are not
the ones who are pushing for going into combat. They know what war
involves and they know its costs. I call it a `war-wariness' on
their part.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0020 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 1143EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-LeeLetter     09-02 0225</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lee Letter,0231</SECOND>
<HEAD>Robert E. Lee Thank-You Note On Sale</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A letter of thanks for the gift of a uniform and
blankets, said to have been written by General Robert E. Lee, is on
auction.
   The letter is dated April 22, 1864, a year before the American
Civil War ended with Lee's surrender at Appomattox.
   It was sent from the confederate leader's headquarters to a
Major L.B. Ferguson in England, who apparently was a regular
supporter of the general.
   ``I have often wished to thank you for the kind sentiment and
high appreciation of the army of North Virginia,'' the letter says.
   It acknowledges ``the uniforms and blankets you so kindly sent
me,'' and adds: ``I beg you will not add to your troubles by
administering to my comfort. We have, partly owing to your efforts
and partly to the exertions of our people, everything we actually
want. All else we can dispense with.''
   Auctioneer Michael Shortall said Sunday: ``The style of the
prose is very much the style of an 18th-century English gentleman _
a nice little vignette of Lee at the end of his career.''
   He said he was studying British army records to establish who
Maj. L.B. Ferguson was.
   The letter is among the contents of Heronden Hall in Kent County
which are being auctioned on Sept. 10.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0021 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 1150EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-BritishBoy     09-02 0249</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-British Boy,0256</SECOND>
<HEAD>British Boy Shown With Saddam Goes Home</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Stuart Lockwood, the 5-year-old British boy seen
worldwide on TV next to Iraqi leader Saddam Hussein, is home and
recovering. But there will be no celebrations until his father gets
back, his aunt said Sunday.
   ``He is only 5 years old and I do not think he really knows what
has been happening. It has been like an adventure for him,'' said
Stuart's aunt, Judy Campbell.
   ``Stuart's dad is still in Iraq. There will be no family
celebration until he is home. We hope that his return will be
soon,'' she said at her home in Worcester, western England.
   ``Everyone is fit and well,'' she added.
   Stuart flew home Saturday with his mother, Glenda, and
14-year-old brother Craig along with more than 300 foreigners who
had been held in Kuwait and Iraq. Iraq has detained about 21,000
foreigners, including 3,000 Americans, since it invaded Kuwait Aug.
2.
   His father Derek, 42, remained among those still held by Saddam.
The family has lived in Kuwait for three years.
   Stuart became famous in an Iraqi TV film of Saddam sitting among
British hostages. He was the solemn-faced child who was beckoned by
Saddam and stood at the Iraqi leader's side having his hair fondled.
   The film, seen on TV networks the world over, was widely
condemned as a propaganda stunt.
   Later, Iraqi TV aired more footage of Stuart playing soccer and
chess with four other hostage children.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0022 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 1204EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Pope     09-02 0553</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Pope,0571</SECOND>
<HEAD>Pope Calls For Christian, Moslem Brotherhood</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto PAR7</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By STEPHEN R. WILSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DAR ES SALAAM, Tanzania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Pope John Paul II on Sunday urged
cooperation and brotherhood between Christianity and Islam, two
religions with ancient rivalries in Africa.
   ``Religious differences of themselves do not necessarily disrupt
life together,'' the pope told leaders of the Moslem and other
faiths in this East African nation.
   John Paul said dialogue between Christians and Moslems ``is
increasingly important in today's world.''
   ``Christians and Moslems can live in harmony and show their
solidarity with one another in all the joys, sorrows and
challenges'' of life, the pope said.
   ``Christians and Moslems in Tanzania can be partners in building
a society shaped by the values taught by God: tolerance, justice,
peace and concern for the poorest and weakest.''
   Roman Catholicism and Islam, the world's two largest religions,
have occasionally clashed in competition for converts in Africa.
The Vatican has expressed concern about the spread of Moslem
fundamentalism in parts of the continent.
   In an earlier speech to Catholic bishops Sunday, John Paul
referred to those problems when he said the clergy needed to
involve the laity more deeply in the church to avoid ``the
proselytizing pressures from other faiths or religious groups.''
   The Vatican has also suggested that the Moslem faith is not
interested in dialogue and cooperation. But the pope hailed good
relations between the two faiths in Tanzania, a largely Moslem
country where Catholics make up only 21 percent of the population
of 75 million.
   Vatican spokesman Joaquin Navarro said the Moslem community
contributed financially to the papal visit. The nation's Moslem
president, Ali Hassan Mwinyi, and a number of other prominent
members of the faith attended the pope's open-air Mass earlier
Sunday.
   Noting that ``both religions are deeply committed to the spread
of their respective faiths,'' the pope said they nonetheless could
build a firm foundation of collaboration and mutual respect.
   That foundation, he said, should be ``recognition that every
person has an inalienable right and a solemn duty to follow his or
her upright conscience.''
   ``The Lord of heaven and earth cannot be pleased with a
religious observance that is somehow imposed from without,'' John
Paul said.
   ``What would then become of the wonderful gifts of reason and
free will?''
   The pope celebrated Mass in a huge outdoor arena built primarily
for political functions on the outskirts of Dar Es Salaam. Up to
100,000 people gathered for the ceremony, at which the pope
ordained 43 priests.
   In his homily, he urged the new priests to maintain their vows
of celebacy, a major challenge for the church, particularly in
Africa, where native tradition places great stress on fatherhood.
   The pope spoke in English but laced his homily with phrases of
Swahili, the lingua franca of East Africa. drawing cheers and
ululation from the crowd.
   A clapping, swaying, drum-beating women's choir, dressed in
wraparound skirts and T-shirts bearing the pope's likeness,
provided hours of rythmic, native hymns in Swahili.
   Sunday was the second day of the pope's seventh visit to Africa,
a 10-day trip that will take him next to three other Tanzanian
cities, then to Burundi, Rwanda and the west coast nation of Ivory
Coast.
   He ends the trip there Sept. 10 with a consecration of a massive
basilica.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0023 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 1207EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--PaintingsSlashed     09-02 0116</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Paintings Slashed,0118</SECOND>
<HEAD>Man Slashes U.S. Artist's Paintings</HEAD>
<DATELINE>VENICE, Italy (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A man brandishing a knife slashed three
paintings by U.S. artist Jeff Koons on display at an art show
Sunday, an official said.
   The man escaped after spraying a chemical substance at seven
guards who tried to apprehend him, causing their eyes to tear up,
said Giovanni Carandente, director of the Biennale festival's art
section, in a telephone interview.
   The vandal slashed three paintings depicting Koons with Italian
porn star and parliamentarian Ilona Staller, known popularly as
``Cicciolina.''
   The works were destroyed, Carandente said.
   Authorities did not know the motive for the man's act. The value
of the paintings was not immediately available.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0024 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 1221EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Gulf-Israel-Changes Bjt   09-02 0760</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Israel-Changes, Bjt,0786</SECOND>
<HEAD>For All Its Fears, Israel Finds Some Good In The Gulf Crisis</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP News Analysis</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By G.G. LaBELLE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   For all the fears and dangers it has raised,
the Persian Gulf crisis has produced a shift in views of the Middle
East that is welcome to Israel's right-wing government.
   Until Iraqi troops swept into Kuwait on Aug. 2, the world tended
to ignore Israel's persistent warnings that President Saddam
Hussein's thirst for power was a serious danger to the whole world,
not just to Israel.
   The outside world seemed to focus on the Palestinian uprising
against Israeli occupation and the efforts of Prime Minister
Yitzhak Shamir's government to put it down with bullets and
beatings.
   Young stone-throwers were dying daily. PLO Chairman Yasser
Arafat talked of compromise and Israel refused to talk to
Palestinians.
   All that changed with Iraq's invasion of Kuwait. Defense
Minister Moshe Arens expressed the satisfaction of the government
when he said shortly after the invasion:
   ``I don't want to say I told you so, but I told you so.''
   Saddam's invasion and annexation of Kuwait shifted attention
from the Palestinian problem toward the broader question of
Israeli-Arab relations.
   Yossi Olmert, director of the Government Press Office and a
member of Shamir's conservative Likud bloc, says Iraq's military
sweep proved that Saddam and not the Palestinian-Israeli conflict
posed a danger to world order.
   ``The Palestinian uprising did not set off a global crisis, it
was an Israeli crisis,'' Olmert told The Associated Press.
``Iraq-Kuwait is a global crisis.''
   Iraq's invasion and the strong Western reaction also have
produced several other changes pleasing to Israel:
   _Angry statements from the United States about Israeli
foot-dragging on the Middle East peace process have been replaced
by public thanks for Israel's ``restraint'' in the crisis.
   _It is now Arafat and Palestinians who face world criticism for
their praise and support of Saddam as a strong Arab leader.
   _Concern by both Arabs and European governments that a flood of
Soviet Jewish immigrants could move into the occupied territories
has been suspended. The influx reached a monthly record of 16,000
in August.
   Despite those changes, there are nagging fears that the gulf
crisis could produce terrible results for the Jewish state.
   In Israel, there is worry that Iraq could make good on its
threat to attack with chemical weapons. And there is a possibility
that even a political settlement could be bad for the Jewish state
unless Saddam is swept from power.
   Arens told Israel television last week, ``If he stays at his
post and would still possess the weapons, there will be a place for
worry in our country, in the whole region and, I think, the whole
world.''
   Despite the rush of events, some Israelis also point out that
the issue of 1.7 million Palestinians in the Israeli-occupied West
Bank and Gaza Strip is not simply going to go away.
   ``It is best that extremists in the nationalist camp . . . do
not rejoice yet,'' cautioned an editorial in the Hebrew daily
Haaretz. ``The new relations being woven between the United States
and some Arab nations will soon be felt.''
   Political analysts in and out of the government believe that
Egypt, Syria and other Arab nations supporting U.S. efforts against
Saddam may unite behind the Palestinian cause when the gulf crisis
is resolved.
   Fears have been raised that a successful U.S. campaign to end
Iraq's occupation of Kuwait will raise troublesome questions about
Israel's 23-year occupation of the West Bank and Gaza.
   Already, 728 Palestinians have been killed by Israeli soldiers
or civilians since the revolt began in December 1987. An additional
254 Palestinians have been slain by fellow Arabs, most as suspected
collaborators. Forty-seven Israelis also have been killed.
   Even the right-wing government knows it cannot simply forget the
Palestinian question.
   Still, worries about the long-term impact of the gulf crisis
cannot suppress the upbeat mood among officials and many in the
Israeli public.
   For once, if only for the moment, Israelis seem to have reached
some sort of political consensus in the face of Iraq's invasion.
   Even Yossi Sarid, a leader of the left-wing Citizens Rights
Movement that has advocated talking to the PLO and giving up
occupied land, wrote a column questioning his party's past stance.
   ``You need to put on a gas mask to protect yourself against the
poisonous smell of the pro-Saddam stand of the Palestine Liberation
Organization,'' Sarid said.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   EDITOR'S NOTE: G.G. LaBelle is news editor of The Associated
Press bureau in Jerusalem.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0025 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 1244EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Gulf-HostageFamilies Bjt   09-02 0844</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Hostage Families, Bjt,0876</SECOND>
<HEAD>Coping with the Gulf Crisis: Ex-Iran Hostages Remember the Waiting
Game</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LESLIE DREYFOUS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP National Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   American families wait, fretful and helpless, while loved ones
are held captive by a Middle East leader. To Dorothea Morefield,
their emotions are chillingly familiar.
   ``More than anything else, there is a feeling of your life being
out of control,'' she said, recalling her husband's captivity in
Iran a decade ago. ``Someone that you love is in danger and there
is nothing you can do.''
   Today, the frustration belongs to relatives of the more than
2,000 U.S. citizens trapped since Iraqi President Saddam Hussein's
troops invaded Kuwait on Aug. 2.
   It's a waiting game familiar to the families of Americans seized
in Tehran on Nov. 4, 1979, by Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini's
revolutionaries. Fifty-two hostages endured 444 days in captivity.
   When the Iranian hostages finally came home to parades and
cheering throngs, they called their families the true heroes. Their
loved ones had been brave, resourceful and resolute. Most of all,
they had carried on.
   ``Knowing that my family was strong, not having to worry about
how they were going to cope, I could be concerned about hanging on
myself,'' said Richard Morefield, former consul-general in Tehran.
   In Tehran, the hostages were the issue. In Iraq and Kuwait, they
are the scattered byproduct of Saddam's invasion. Iran did not face
an international military response and economic blockade.
   In 1979, the embassy hostages were diplomats and servicemen.
Today's captives are mostly civilians.
   But if the scenarios differ, the coping is the same.
   Mrs. Morefield couldn't free her husband, but she could still
carry on for him. So as the days turned into weeks, she gathered
her five children and together they substituted pragmatism for
panic.
   They drew up lists of State Department and other contacts,
canceled credit cards and closed joint bank accounts. After tying
up those loose ends, family members concentrated on keeping their
hands busy and their minds occupied.
   Mrs. Morefield scrubbed floors, knitted afghans and took walks.
Her children continued with their studies, sports and other hobbies.
   ``It's very important that you get on with your life, that you
don't stagnate,'' said Mrs. Morefield, who now lives with her
husband in Annandale, Va. ``You keep control of your life as much
as you can.''
   It's hard for relatives to avoid wild imaginings, the veterans
of the Iran ordeal said.
   ``The hostages know their living conditions. They know how
they're being treated and if they're being fed,'' said Kevin
Hermening, who was a Marine guard in Tehran when the embassy was
seized. ``Their families do not.''
   His mother was criticized for visiting the hostages during their
captivity, but Hermening understands her desperation.
   ``It's hardest on the families of hostages ... because they have
only speculation,'' said Hermening, a new father and candidate for
the Wisconsin Legislature. ``They don't know what their loved ones
are going through.''
   As the Persian Gulf crisis enters its second month, the families
of those trapped overseas are in much the same situation. In many
cases they can only guess the whereabouts of relatives, many of
whom have been out of contact for weeks.
   ``When you're out there you know where the walls are,'' said
former hostage Bruce Laingen, who was charge d'affaires and the top
U.S. diplomat in Iran.
   ``When you're back here, you're constantly dealing with not
knowing enough,'' said Laingen, now executive director of the
National Commission on the Public Service. ``You're never happy,
never satisfied. I'm sure that's true among many of the families
today.''
   But former hostages and their families warned against letting
the frustration run rampant. Dignity is the thing, they said.
   ``Too much wringing of hands is not good for the national
morale,'' said Moorhead Kennedy, who was the third-ranking foreign
service officer at the U.S. Embassy in Tehran. ``Stand up! Remember
who you are!''
   His wife, Louisa, did just that. In the darkest days of the Iran
hostage crisis, she went to work on a network for the victims'
families.
   ``We considered ourselves hostages,'' said Mrs. Kennedy, who was
spokeswoman for the Family Liaison Action Group in Washington. ``In
my case, I resolved that in some degree by putting myself to work.''
   ``It's very important for families to see this in context, see
that it isn't some wicked thing that's just happening to them,''
added Kennedy, who works at the American Forum for Global Education
in New York.
   Hostage families have to step back, try to see the bigger
picture, said those who have been through it and survived.
   ``It's important for the family to remember that their relatives
will be well,'' said former diplomat Barry Rosen, who is now an
assistant vice president at Brooklyn College in New York.
   ``There's nothing like freedom, like being able to open the door
and walk outside,'' he said. ``That cures a lot of ills.''
   And families should never abandon hope, former hostages said.
The door to freedom could soon swing open.
   ``You never know what the next day will bring,'' Rosen said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0026 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 1247EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Thefts-Shakedown     09-02 0860</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Thefts-Shakedown,0888</SECOND>
<HEAD>Former Cashiers Picket Stores They Say Falsely Accused Them of
Stealing</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TRUDY TYNAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SPRINGFIELD, Mass. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Former convenience store cashiers who
say they were coerced into falsely confessing to thefts and
repaying money they never stole are taking their battle from the
courtroom to the sidewalks.
   ``Just sitting around talking about what happened only makes you
madder,'' said Kenneth Provost of Chicopee, who with other former
employees launched a picket Saturday of two Cumberland Farms stores
in the chain's home state of Massachusetts.
   They are not alone in their anger.
   Despite the company's repeated denials of any wrongdoing, more
than 300 former workers have approached lawyers handling a federal
lawsuit against the company, saying they also were forced to sign
false confessions.
   The suit, originally filed by 12 employees four years ago, is
scheduled to go to trial in Camden, N.J., in December.
   Within the past few weeks, former workers in at least three
states have created support groups. And the prosecutor's office in
Orlando, Fla., says it will no longer routinely process theft
claims filed by the company against workers.
   Many of those that have come forward said they paid hundreds and
sometimes thousands of dollars to the company to avoid prosecution
and the humiliation of a public accusation of theft.
   ``The reaction has been unbelievable,'' Provost said. ``Every
day more people come in and say it happened to me too.''
   In July, the Philadelphia Inquirer reported that during the
first six months of 1986, Cumberland Farms security officials
obtained confessions from 57 percent of the 2,600 cashiers they
questioned about theft and collected $368,000 from the workers.
   And Frederic J. Gross, the attorney handling the federal suit,
claims that over the past 20 years as many as 30,000 people who
worked for the chain may have been accused of stealing. The
estimate was based on internal ``report cards'' maintained by the
company on the security staff, some of which have been obtained by
the lawyers, Gross said.
   Foster G. MacRides, a vice president and chief spokesman for
Cumberland Farms, did not return telephone messages left at the
company's headquarters in the Boston suburb of Canton.
   But he has said repeatedly that the 50-year-old chain, which
operates 1,100 stores in New England, New York, Pennsylvania,
Delaware, New Jersey, Florida and Ohio, has ``never and will never
have a policy of coercing or intimidating our employees.''
   One woman, who had signed a ``confession'' as a teen-ager, told
lawyers that for 15 years her father refused to believe her claims
of innocence. But now she was stepping forward at his urging.
   Others said they had signed confessions as teen-agers in hopes
of keeping the accusation from their parents, or were simply scared
into signing.
   ``I was sobbing and crying so hard when they threatened to put
me in jail and take away my children that I threw up,'' said
Margaret Stone of Bennington, Vt., a divorced mother of six who was
working at a New Hampshire store last year when she was accused of
stealing $6,000.
   She said store officials told her if she signed a false
confession and came up with $1,500 in cash by noon the next day,
they would not have her jailed and her children would not be taken
away.
   ``They even brought me out to the pay phone in the parking lot
at 11:30 at night and made me call my parents for the money,'' she
said. ``It was so cold and I was crying so hard that the security
man took the phone from me and talked to my mother.''
   ``It was the worst nightmare of my life.''
   ``There are all these little tragedies out there and it's so
damn unnecessary,'' said K. Kay Shearin, a Delaware lawyer.
   Shirley DiSalvo, one of Ms. Shearin's clients, was arrested by
Delaware State Police and jailed for four days last month, even
though she was nine months pregnant, after a computer check
uncovered a 4-year-old warrant dating back to her brief stint as a
clerk in a Florida store.
   Cumberland Farms accused her of stealing $2,900 after the woman,
then 18, told store officials she had taken an unauthorized soft
drink on a half dozen occasions when she worked overtime, according
to Ms. Shearin.
   Provost said his support group recently began picketing because
``we wanted to do something to get the attention of other people
that were victimized and thought they were alone.''
   But sometimes just talking to someone who has been in the same
straits helps, said Grettel Dunn, who started a support group in
Rhode Island.
   ``I thought I was the only one it had ever happened to and I was
so ashamed,'' said Mrs. Dunn. ``I never took anything in my life.''
   Mrs. Dunn said she refused to sign a confession when she was
called into the back room, sat down on a milk carton and told she
could not leave. But she said she was in tears when she finally
plucked up the courage to walk out amid shouted warnings that
police would be waiting at her door.
   ``Needless to say, they were not,'' she said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0027 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 1247EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SriLanka     09-02 0231</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Sri Lanka,0239</SECOND>
<HEAD>Government Troops Repulse Attack, Kill 26 Rebels</HEAD>
<DATELINE>COLOMBO, Sri Lanka (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Troops defending a military garrison
repulsed a Tamil rebel attack and killed at least 26 guerrillas,
officials said Sunday.
   The Mullaitivu outpost about 173 miles northeast of Colombo has
been under seige for 10 weeks, but the troops have held out against
repeated mortar attacks.
   The rebel onslaught Saturday came as the government imposed an
indefinite curfew in Mullaitivu, Vavunia and Mannar, predominately
Tamil districts in the north.
   On state-run radio, the government warned residents to stay
indoors or risk being shot.
   Military officials say the curfew could facilitate military
operations against the Liberation Tigers of Tamil Eelam, the rebel
militia fighting since 1983 for a separate nation.
   The rebels seek a Tamil homeland in northern and eastern
districts of the island nation. Tamils make up 18 percent of Sri
Lanka's 16 million people and Sinhalese account for 75 percent.
   Separatists accuse the Sinhalese-dominated government of
discriminating against Tamils in jobs, education and other areas.
   The latest round of violence flared in June, ending a 13-month
cease-fire to help push peace talks.
   At least 14,000 people have been killed in the seven-year
separatist war.
   In other fighting, rebels killed five soldiers Saturday during
an ambush on a military patrol near Kantalai, 130 miles northeast
of Colombo, said officials who cannot be identified under briefing
rules.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0028 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 1247EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brite-HospitalWedding     09-02 0180</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brite-Hospital Wedding,0185</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hospitalized Groom Says Wedding Must Go On</HEAD>
<DATELINE>AUSTELL, Ga. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   All the invitations had been sent out. The
best man and maid of honor arrived in town from Illinois.
   And the groom was in the hospital with appendicitis.
   But that didn't stop Bill Sterrett and Rhonda Lochner from
getting married Saturday. They just moved the ceremony to the
chapel of Cobb Hospital and Medical Center in Austell.
   Sterrett, recovering from his appendicitis operation the day
before, sat in a wheelchair as his bride and their out-of-town
wedding party surrounded him in the chapel.
   He said that after planning a wedding since Dec. 23 _ when he
proposed _ he wasn't going to let a little operation sideline him.
   ``Everybody had come down from Illinois and out of state. People
would have been disappointed,'' he said. ``When I talked with the
surgeon, he said a lot of people could walk the next day after an
appendicitis operation, so we held the wedding here.''
   The couple did postpone the honeymoon though _ they're saving
that for Thanksgiving.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0029 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 1302EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Cambodia     09-02 0626</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Cambodia,0647</SECOND>
<HEAD>Government Plans To Hold Power Despite Support For U.N. Peace Plan</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PETER ENG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BANGKOK, Thailand (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The president of Cambodia's
Vietnamese-installed government, appearing to reject key features
of a new U.N. peace plan, said his government wants to maintain the
political and military status quo.
   The U.S. assistant secretary of state for East Asian and Pacific
affairs, Richard Solomon, said Sunday that Vietnam had similar
reservations in talks with the United States last week.
   Cambodian President Heng Samrin's comments came in a speech
broadcast by the state radio Saturday. The text was seen Sunday in
Bangkok.
   He said his government regarded the U.N. plan ``as a basic
document'' for future discussions and was ready to discuss it with
the guerrillas in talks Indonesia is arranging.
   But he said with no elaboration that his government's stance
``is to maintain its status quo _ both politically and military.''
   The U.N. role, he said, should include verifying that agreements
are implemented and organizing the election. His remarks on the
U.N. role were not completely monitored due to reception problems.
   The plan was adopted Tuesday by the United States and the other
permanent members of the Security Council _ China, the Soviet
Union, Britain and France.
   The three rebel groups fighting the government have expressed
support for the plan. Washington backs two of the guerrilla groups.
   On Friday, Cambodia's deputy prime minister in charge of foreign
affairs, Hor Nam Hong, said the Phonm Penh government accepted a
major U.N. role, including its supervision of certain key
ministries. But he gave no indication Cambodia was yielding on its
desire for interim authority.
   They proposed that the United Nations supervise and, if
necessary, control five key government ministries in the
transitional period before elections. They also want the armies of
the Vietnamese-installed Phnom Penh government and the three
guerrilla groups disarmed and regrouped into supervised cantonments.
   The four Cambodian factions would form a ``Supreme National
Council'' as a figurehead government.
   The Cambodian president, in the Saturday broadcast, called the
Supreme National Council only ``the symbol of national independence
and sovereignty.''
   ``The most urgent question is the first meeting of the Supreme
National Council so as to enable the voluntary cease-fire to go
into effect,'' Heng Samrin said.
   The guerrillas want either the council or the United Nations as
the interim government.
   An attempt to form the council in June collapsed when the
strongest guerrilla group, the Khmer Rouge, opposed the allocation
of seats on the council as unfair to it. The final formation of the
council is to be a major aim of proposed talks in Indonesia.
   Soviet-supported Vietnam installed Heng Samrin's Communist
government after invading Cambodia in late 1978, ending a nearly
four-year Khmer Rouge reign in which hundreds of thousands of
people were killed in slave labor camps and execution chambers.
   The Khmer Rouge, supported by China, now is allied with two
non-communist groups in the guerrilla coalition _ the U.S.-backed
forces of Prince Norodom Sihanouk and of Son Sann's Khmer People's
National Liberation Front.
   Vietnam voiced its reservations with the U.N. plan at a meeting
at the United Nations Friday in which the United States tried to
persuade them to back the plan, Solomon said.
   The Vietnamese, he said, voiced reservations on ``issues related
to military arrangements and some of the administrative
arrangements.''
   Solomon would not go into detail, but when asked if that meant
Vietnam still wanted the armies to remain in place and Phnom Penh
to hold interim authority, he replied:
   ``Yes, my impression is that if they had their own wish, that is
probably the case.''
   Solomon was in Bangkok for talks on economic issues with
Thailand and its five allies in the Association of Southeast Asian
Nations.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0030 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 1318EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-Saudi-Religion     09-02 0575</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Saudi-Religion,0595</SECOND>
<HEAD>Sunday Services Held Despite Ban in Islamic Nation</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf Rdp, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOAN MOWER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DHAHRAN, Saudi Arabia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Church services were held quietly
for American soldiers Sunday despite this country's ban on the
practice of religions other than Islam.
   The services, conducted by chaplains from all military branches,
were held in mess halls, tents and in big warehouses. Soldiers said
they were well attended.
   ``There are no atheists in foxholes,'' said Capt. B.A. Arnold,
an Air Force chaplain from Cannon Air Force of Clovis, N.M. ``The
pressures of the military tend to force people to ask questions
about the meaning of life and death.''
   The military has gone to great lengths not to draw attention to
the services. Notices of times and places are sometimes posted
discreetly on bulletin boards; other services are advertised by
word of mouth.
   The military is not alone in circumventing the ban. The Western
community holds a Christian service on Fridays _ the traditional
day off in Saudi Arabia. The oil company Saudi Aramco, which has
thousands of foreign employees, also has Christian services on its
private compound.
   U.S. officials said they do not want to offend the Saudis. ``We
do respect the laws of the host country,'' one Pentagon official
said.
   The rule of thumb is: ``Don't flaunt it; Don't try to convert
the Moslems,'' Arnold said.
   Some Americans said they were advised not to bring Bibles to
Saudi Arabia or to hand out religious literature. But many people
carry Bibles with them, and religious literature is handed out
among Marines.
   A Saudi official said his government is prepared to let people
worship as long as they are discreet. The U.S. troops are kept
isolated from the Saudi society.
   Pentagon officials said the religious needs of more than 60,000
military troops deployed here will be met, regardless of whether
they are Christian, Jewish or Moslem.
   The 82nd airborne from Fort Bragg, N.C., for instance, scheduled
nine services at its desert headquarters Sunday. All were for
Catholics or Protestants, with the exception of one Mormon service.
   ``Officially there is no religion allowed or practiced in Saudi
Arabia other than Islam,'' said Jonathan Rice, a U.S. Consulate
spokesman.
   Americans said the potentially dangerous military situation
combined with loneliness and physical hardships have caused them to
find solace in religion.
   Army Pvt. Preston Suminguit says he goes to church ``every
chance I get.'' The 20-year-old Cleveland paratrooper pulled from
the pockets of his fatigues three things he carries with him at all
times: a book of psalms and proverbs from the New Testament; the
``Paratrooper's Faith,'' a collection of religious teachings, and
the liner to his father's Green Beret.
   Airman Ty Worthington, 21, of Base City, Mich., said the
practice of religion is sometimes kept out of sight.
   The chaplains sometimes don't tell the troops about impromptu
services until the last minute, he said. ``The services are unseen,
unheard ... sometimes in the back of a supply warehouse.''
   Even though ``the locals don't like us practicing our
religion,'' Worthington said faith plays a big role in the lives of
many men and women.
   The chaplains do a lot of one-on-one work. They handout mail,
give out cookies and offer a few words of encouragement.
   ``I haven't met a paratrooper who is an atheist,'' said Sgt.
Derrick White of Patterson, N.J. ``When you are jumping from an
aircraft at 2,000 feet you believe in God.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0031 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 1326EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-PhillyFinances Bjt   09-02 0704</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Philly Finances, Bjt,0724</SECOND>
<HEAD>City Looking For Help As Deficit Looms</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LYNN BERRY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PHILADELPHIA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The nation's fifth-largest city is running
out of cash.
   Without a $400 million emergency loan, Philadelphia will be out
of money by the end of the month. The mayor wants the loan; the
city controller says he won't sign it.
   But even with the cash flow help, the city will still be $206.4
million in the red on a budget of $2.1 billion. And projections
indicate more deficits in years to come unless drastic steps are
taken. Some are even advocating a state takeover like the one that
bailed out New York City 15 years ago.
   Controller Jonathan A. Saidel can't block the emergency loan by
withholding his signature. But he can make it harder for a city
whose notes are already rated as shaky by Wall Street.
   ``I believe it is not in the best interest of the city of
Philadelphia,'' Saidel explains.
   On Friday, Gov. Robert P. Casey said an unidentified Japanese
bank had offered the city a $225 million letter of credit to help
Philadelphia sell temporary loan notes.
   Officially, Mayor W. Wilson Goode has put the loan on hold for a
couple of weeks to try to sort things out.
   Saidel said the loan won't cure the debacles that created the
crunch, such as the $25 million bill to rebuild a neighborhood
bombed by city police in the 1985 confrontation with the radical
group MOVE or another $25 million the courts ordered returned to
property taxpayers as illegally collected cash. Nor, he said, will
it force the mayor and City Council to work together or the state
to chip in.
   Goode blames the crisis on the City Council for blocking his
efforts now and in the past, the state Legislature for refusing to
allow a local sales tax this year and the federal government for
years of decreasing aid.
   He made a televised appeal last month for more state aid and
council cooperation in raising unspecified existing taxes $150
million and cutting unspecified ``non-essential'' city services.
Without those steps, despite the $400 million loan, the city will
run out of cash next May.
   The mayor's approach is not new. For three years, the council
has diluted or rejected his calls for more taxes and the state has
rebuffed many of his requests for more aid.
   Some think this time will be different.
   ``The problem is so real, so pressing that no one is going to be
able to avoid it,'' said Sandra Featherman, director of the Center
for Public Policy at Temple University.
   Others think the mayor and council will reach their usual
stalemate and look to an outside group to rescue the city.
   ``More and more there's a belief, especially in the business
community, that there has to be an outside entity, that there has
to be credibility established,'' said G. Terry Madonna, director of
the Center for Politics and Public Affairs at Millersville
University.
   On television, Goode said he would name an advisory panel to
devise ``hard-hitting'' solutions. But it would have no authority
to act.
   Backers of outside control point to the successful state and
federal rescue of New York City, which in 1975 was broke and $792
million in debt.
   The New York Legislature established the Municipal Assistance
Corp. to monitor the city budget and sell bonds on its behalf. An
Emergency Financial Control Board was later given control of the
city's spending and eventually won the confidence of lending
institutions. The federal government backed up $2.3 billion in city
borrowing.
   Philadelphia officials have so far brushed off the idea,
unwilling to surrender control. As for state officials, Featherman
said, ``I'm not sure the state wants the problem of managing
Philadelphia's debt.''
   Madonna said getting more state aid won't be easy, especially in
an election year.
   ``There's the perception that the city gets more than its share
of state aid, of having to fund the excesses of the city, that the
Goode administration has been less than competent,'' he said.
   Further, until there is a workable plan backed by Goode and the
council, aiding Philadelphia ``will be perceived as throwing money
down a rat hole.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0032 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 1327EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-Congress     09-02 0488</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Congress,0505</SECOND>
<HEAD>Gephardt: Limits To US Patience, But Time More Saddam's Problem</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf Rdp, Bjt</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto BAH1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN KING</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DHAHRAN, Saudi Arabia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   House Majority Leader Richard
Gephardt said Sunday that a lengthy U.S. military presence in Saudi
Arabia might strain the American public's patience, but that time
will be a worse enemy to Saddam Huseein.
   The Missouri Democrat led a 22-member congressional delegation
in a visit to American troops, a visit that was shortened when a
C-130 Hercules transport plane developed mechanical trouble.
   The breakdown, details of which were not immediately available,
forced the delegation to cancel one planned trip to a Marine camp
in the northeast Saudi desert.
   In a brief session with reporters before heading out to see the
troops, Gephardt said there would be ``limits to our patience''
back home if the deployment dragged on.
   But with Iraq facing world condemnation for its invasion of
Kuwait and economic sanctions that have forced food rationing in
Iraq, Gephardt suggested the United States had more time than
Saddam.
   ``There's a patience problem on the Iraqi side as well,'' said
Gephardt. ``It's the world against him _ it's not the world against
us.''
   For now, Gephardt said of the mood back home: ``I've never seen
stronger support for a military operation since I've been in
Congress.'' He was first elected to the House in 1976.
   The commander of U.S. forces in the Middle East, Gen. H. Norman
Schwarzkopf, also cited the rationing as evidence the embargo was
taking its toll on Baghdad.
   ``During all eight years of the Iran-Iraq war they never went to
rationing,'' Schwarzkopf said.
   Gephardt said a briefing by Schwarzkopf convinced him the United
States has a formidable deterrent force in place.
   But he said the United States was still in a ``waiting game'' as
the remainder of its deployment headed for the Middle East. In what
is becoming a familiar chorus from members of Congress, Gephardt
called on other nations to join the multinational defense force.
   ``We've got to convince some of the other nations that they've
got to come in,'' he said.
   Some U.S. allies outside the region have sent warships,
minesweepers and fighter jets, and some Arab countries have
deployed troops.
   The delegation met with the 1st Tactical Fighter Wing, which
brought dozens of F-15s from the United States to Saudi Arabia, and
then members of the 101st Airborne Division's air-assault brigade.
   The chief complaint from the troops was a poor mail system.
   ``There sure are a lot of bugs to be worked out,'' Pvt. Edward
Humelhans of Suring, Wis., told Rep. David Obey, a Democrat from
the same state.
   Other congressional delegations have visited the troops in the
Saudi desert in recent days. Senate Foreign Relations Committee
Chairman Claiborne Pell led one over the weekend and eight senators
came earlier last week.
   U.S. congressmen also visited sailors Saturday aboard the USS La
Salle.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0033 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 1356EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-RapeVictim'sStory     09-02 0602</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Rape Victim's Story,0618</SECOND>
<HEAD>Head of Women's Commission Recounts Story of Sexual Assault</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HARTFORD, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The director of the state's Permanent
Commission on the Status of Women has come forward to tell her
story of being raped two years ago, saying in a detailed newspaper
account that she spoke out because rape is a ``crime of silence.''
   ``I want people to understand it, I want people to understand
that it's an act of violence and I want people to know that it
doesn't have a damn thing to do with sex,'' Fredrica Gray said in
an interview with The Hartford Courant published Sunday.
   Gray, the executive director of the commission, was sexually
assaulted on Feb. 3, 1988, in her home in Bloomfield, a Hartford
suburb. She said she convinced her attacker that she had AIDS _ a
lie _ and lured him back to her house, telling him she had medicine
to treat the condition.
   When the man returned, he was arrested. The man, Johnny B.
Williams of Hartford, pleaded no-contest and was sentenced earlier
this year to 13 years in prison.
   ``For every Johnny, there are a million other ones, other men
who commit these crimes and a lot of them are never caught,'' Gray
said.
   Gray, 44, said she hoped her account would focus more attention
on violence against women and encourage more victims of sexual
assalt to report such crimes.
   In publishing Gray's story, the Courant broke with its policy of
not printing the names of rape victims. While most newspapers have
similar policies, the issue has been debated in journalistic
circles recently, especially after The Des Moines (Iowa) Register
printed stories earlier this year naming a woman who came forward
with the story of her 1989 rape.
   As a women's rights activist, Gray had previously helped write a
booklet on procedures for gathering evidence in rape cases. At the
time of the attack, she was preparing for hearings on new statewide
procedures for dealing with rape victims.
   Still, she said, the attack left her devastated. Even after
Williams' arrest, she received mail from him. At one point, she
said, he sent her ``extremely gross'' pornography; in another
letter, he wrote, ``I love you very much. I want to come home,''
she said.
   ``It was like being assaulted again and again,'' she said.
   She sold her house 16 months after the attack.
   ``I never could sleep there again,'' she said. ``There's
something that happens about the place you live, the place in which
you are assaulted. You can't live there, you can't feel safe there.
It re-traumatizes you every time you walk through the door.''
   Gray caught her attacker through an elaborate lie she told him
during the attack, which occurred when she was home sick from her
work at the commission.
   ``I said to him, `You know why I'm home? I have AIDS. ... If you
don't believe me, there's medicine on my dresser,'' she said.
   When the attacker asked if he could call her later, Gray said,
she gave him a false name and her real phone number.
   ``I wanted him to call the house,'' she said. ``Because I knew
that if I could get him to call me that we would have a pretty good
chance of apprehending him.''
   The day after the assault, Gray waited with a police detective,
and the attacker called again. To lure him back to the house for
medicine, she told him, ``You may have raped me, but I'm going to
live, and you're going to die.''
   Williams, then 22, was arrested soon after he entered the house.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0034 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 1401EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Cancer-Food     09-02 0544</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Cancer-Food,540</SECOND>
<NOTE>For Release 6:30 p.m. EDT, TIME set by source.</NOTE>
<HEAD>Groups Calls for Outright Ban on Cancer-Causing Pesticides</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By H. JOSEF HEBERT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An environmental group said Sunday the
government should gradually halt the use of many cancer-causing
chemicals on food because it cannot measure how many of the
substances a person may consume.
   In a report, the non-governmental U.S. Public Interest Research
Group said that as many as 60 cancer-causing pesticides can legally
used on the most commonly eaten foods under Environmental
Protection Agency rules.
   But the EPA does not adequately account for the accumulated
exposure to such pesticides through consumption of various foods,
the report said. Critics also maintain that some levels are based
on outdated health and medical information.
   ``Rather than ban a chemical, the EPA uses the inexact science
of risk assessment to set very politicized standards for
carcinogens and declares the risks `negligible','' said the report.
   An EPA spokesman, Al Heier, said that the report reflected
nothing new and that the agency three years ago published a list of
cancer-causing chemicals in foods. He said that the EPA is
reviewing the status of scores of such chemicals that are used as
long as residue levels remain within specific limits.
   Rick Tinsworth, director of the EPA's review efforts, said the
direction in which the EPA is going ``parallels what they (the
environmentalists) are suggesting.'' He said the EPA hopes by 1997
to have reviewed the status of some 400 pesticides and determine
whether they should remain in use.
   The PIRG report documents to what extent cancer-causing
pesticides are being used on a variety of commonly eaten foods from
beef and pork to vegetables and dairy products.
   ``Ten of these commonly eaten foods surveyed are allowed to
contain 20 or more of these carcinogens,'' said the report. It
noted that 32 different types of cancer-causing pesticides can be
used on beef, 30 types on pork, and 20 or more types on poultry,
peaches, grapes, eggs, tomatoes, apples, milk and corn.
   The report acknowledged that a farmer would not use all of these
pesticides on a single crop, perhaps choosing one or a combination
of several, instead.
   ``The point is that if it did occur it would be legal,'' wrote
Rick Hind, U.S. PIRG's environmental director, in the report.
   Hind said the correct answer to protecting health is the
``systematic and orderly phaseout'' of the cancer-causing
chemicals. He noted some supermarkets already have suggested a
phaseout. The report suggested that the most menacing of the
cancer-causing pesticides be banned over the next eight years.
   So far, it noted, the EPA has banned only 11 pesticides for all
uses on foods.
   The U.S. PIRG report also urged that pesticide manufacturers be
required to develop better monitoring procedures and that the
companies be required to prove that a chemical is safe, instead of
the government proving it unsafe, for it to remain on the market.
   It noted that farm legislation before Congress would require
farmers to keep records of their pesticide use and would ban the
export of pesticides prohibited for domestic use. There are
numerous cases where imported foods contain pesticides that are not
allowed on foods produced in this country, according to various
recent studies.
  
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0035 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 1401EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p AM-NHSenate     09-02 0723</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-NH Senate,700</SECOND>
<HEAD>Conservative House Member Seen as Man to Beat in Senate Race</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By NORMA LOVE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CONCORD, N.H. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Bob Smith's critics paint him as a
pedestrian congressman who would make a lackluster senator, but the
three-term Republican is seen as the man to beat for New
Hampshire's open U.S. Senate seat.
   Smith is a staunch conservative who's sometimes set himself at
odds with party leaders _ most notably in fighting congressional
pay raises.
   He brushes aside criticism of his track record in the House.
   ``You focus on your principles and stick to them,'' says Smith,
49. ``Otherwise, why serve?''
   The Senate seat will open up because Republican Gordon Humphrey
is leaving after two terms, fulfilling his pledge not to make
Congress a career. It is one of only three open Senate seats that
will be filled in the 1990 elections.
   National GOP leaders want to keep the seat in Republican hands
even at the price of creating friction within the party.
   A who's who of New Hampshire's GOP faithful, including White
House chief of staff and former Gov. John Sununu, has lined up
behind Smith in the four-way Republican primary on Sept. 11.
   Vice President Dan Quayle in May appeared at a Smith fund-raiser
in Washington as pleas for neutrality from one of the congressman's
GOP rivals, 42-year-old lawyer Thomas Christo, when unheeded.
   ``The kind of person who puts a lot of stock in the party
hierarchy and the status quo is not going to be with me,'' Christo
said.
   Also vying for the GOP nomination are engineering professor Ted
de Winter, 57; and businessman Ewing Smith, 68.
   Smith holds an ultraconservative voting record on spending
issues and says he'd continue to fight for a balanced-budget
amendment and elimination of the federal budget deficit if elected
to the Senate.
   ``Everybody accuses me of being too simplistic on this, but
there is nothing complicated about it at all. You have to agree in
principle to balance the budget,'' he said.
   Some rivals say Smith's consistent support for military spending
belies his claim to be a skinflint.
   Smith's America ``is a land in which hundreds of billions are
spent on Star Wars while the homeless live in cardboard boxes,
senior citizens fear cutbacks in Social Security and America's
children must go without school lunches,'' said Democrat James
Donchess, the Nashua mayor.
   Smith says he favors some defense cuts, but backs continued
funding for the Strategic Defense Initiative _ Star Wars _ and the
B2 bomber.
   Competing for the Democratic nomination are Donchess, 41; former
U.S. Sen. John Durkin, 54; and millionaire former businessman John
Rauh, 58.
   The Democratic aspirants may have hoped Smith's primary rivals
would bloody him before the general election, but they've been busy
bruising each other instead.
   Durkin confronted Donchess at a recent news conference, then
followed him to a series of news conferences around the state. At
each stop, they called each other names. The next day, Rauh
denounced their actions.
   Smith stands alone in the field in his strong opposition to
abortion, a stand his opponents have criticized repeatedly. But
Smith recently modified his position, saying he would accept
abortion not only to protect the life of the mother, but in cases
of rape and incest as well.
   In an August poll conducted by the University of New Hampshire
for WMUR-TV in Manchester, 43 percent of Republicans backed Smith.
Six percent chose Christo; 2 percent, Ewing Smith; and 1 percent,
de Winter. Forty-eight percent were undecided.
   Among Democrats, 36 percent backed Durkin; 18 percent, Donchess;
9 percent, Rauh; and 37 percent undecided. The margin of error was
5 percentage points.
   Smith outpolled all three Democrats in head-to-head matchups by
comfortable margins in an earlier poll by the Becker Institute of
Sudbury, Mass.
   Only Smith and Rauh, a newcomer to politics, declined to abide
by New Hampshire's voluntary campaign spending limit of $400,000 in
the primary and a like amount in the general election campaign.
   Smith said the combined spending of the others in a bid to
derail him prevents him from sticking to the limit. He scoffs at
rivals' claims that his acceptance of political action committee
money means his vote is for sale.
   ``No PAC has ever asked me for my vote and I would not give it
to them,'' he says.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0036 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 1413EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p AM-NevadaGovernor     09-02 0555</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Nevada Governor,520</SECOND>
<HEAD>Acting Nevada Governor Favored Over 13 Would-Be Successors</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BRENDAN RILEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CARSON CITY, Nev. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Acting Gov. Bob Miller inherited his
job without being elected and critics paint his two-year tenure as
undistinguished, but he's heavily favored over 13 Democratic and
Republican would-be successors.
   Democrat Miller, who got the governor's job when then-Gov. Dick
Bryan jumped to the U.S. Senate in 1988, is being challenged by
five Democrats in Tuesday's primary. All are little known and
running limited campaigns, including one long-shot hopeful who
changed his name to Rhinestone Cowboy.
   The Republican ballot is even more crowded. There are eight
candidates led by Jim Gallaway, a relative newcomer to the state
who says Miller has shown ``a total lack of leadership'' as acting
governor.
   Gallaway's campaign got a boost when the Marine reserve colonel
was called up for a brief stint on active duty last month.
Gallaway, who had served five years on active duty, spent a week in
Arlington, Va., working as a logistics coordinator on the gulf
crisis before returning to the campaign trail.
   Gallaway has been accused by another GOP contender, builder
Charlie Brown, of trying to buy the election with slick television
ads. Gallaway has outspent Brown by a four-to-one margin. None of
the other Republican candidates, each a political unknown, has
mounted a major campaign.
   A Tarrance &amp; Associates poll conducted for the Nevada Retailers
Association in August looked at the likely matchup in November and
found Miller trouncing Gallaway 60 percent to 27 percent, with a 4
percentage point margin of error.
   But Gallaway, a business entrepreneur, said his internal polls
show him gaining an edge on the governor when voters are told
Gallaway favors abortion rights and opposes a statewide payroll tax
plan while Miller is anti-abortion and backs the tax.
   Miller, 45, was elected lieutenant governor four years ago after
serving two terms in Las Vegas as Clark County district attorney.
   He takes credit as governor for getting lawmakers to raise
teachers' pay and lower class sizes and creating a state drug
``czar.'' He also has vetoed a controversial pension hike for
lawmakers, supported various tax hikes, and opposed abortion.
   ``I'm optimistic,'' Miller said of his election campaign. ``I'm
going to run based on my record.'' He said that includes his two
years as governor as well as his prior service as lieutenant
governor and in Las Vegas, where he was raised.
   Gallaway has attacked Miller on his abortion and taxation
stands, but the governor so far has avoided direct criticism of
Gallaway and the other candidates.
   ``I'm busy talking about Bob Miller,'' the governor said. ``In
fact, from the campaign activity I've seen, it looks like both of
us are going to be talking about me.''
   Miller has collected $1.1 million in contributions compared with
Gallaway's total of about $318,000, most of that from his personal
funds. But Gallaway said he's hoping for another $1 million and is
willing to continue pouring his own money into the race.
   Gallaway said that while he has been in Nevada only about two
years, he has strong GOP support, including backing from the
Republican Governor's Association.
   All that Miller can show for his tenure is ``a total lack of
leadership. The only time he acts is in a crisis,'' Gallaway said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0037 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 1431EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-Diplomacy     09-02 0662</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Diplomacy,0682</SECOND>
<HEAD>Diplomatic Setback After U.N.-Iraq Talks Fail To Produce Results</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf Rdp, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MORT ROSENBLUM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Special Correspondent</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>AMMAN, Jordan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Diplomatic efforts to avert war slipped
back out of the public eye Sunday as U.N. Secretary-General Javier
Perez de Cuellar voiced deep disappointment that talks with Iraq
reached no accord over Kuwait.
   ``I had hoped for a more flexible position regarding the retreat
... from Kuwait,'' Perez de Cuellar said, briefing reporters after
nine hours of talks over two days with Iraqi Foreign Minister Tariq
Aziz.
   In a prepared statement, he concluded: ``The talks were useful,
but disappointing.''
   Later he flew to Paris, where he was to meet with Jordan's King
Hussein and French President Francois Mitterrand. The Jordanian
king has traveled to nine countries to gather support for an Arab
peace plan he has yet to crystallize.
   In Paris, Perez de Cuellar said he was ``deeply disappointed''
in his talks with Aziz because he had expected ``a certain
flexibility.''
   ``What Iraq wants is to stay in Kuwait, which is unacceptable to
the international community, to the U.N. Security Council and to
its secretary general,'' Perez de Cuellar told reporters after
meeting French Foreign Minister Roland Dumas.
   But he said he still held out hope that Iraq would become more
accommodating. ``I am available,'' he said. ``If, at any given
time, they wish to modify their position, I will be delighted to
listen to them.''
   Although a summit in Helsinki next Sunday between President Bush
and Soviet President Mikhail S. Gorbachev might open new
possibilities, no other major public talks on the Persian Gulf
crisis were scheduled.
   Perez de Cuellar began the highly touted Amman meetings Friday
with uncharacteristic optimism, matched by upbeat remarks by Aziz.
Both also reflected a positive attitude between their four sessions.
   But a senior Jordanian official with access to the talks said
the meeting broke down over Iraq's refusal to budge on the basic
issue of its domination of Kuwait, which it seized on Aug. 2.
   The official, who spoke on condition of anonymity, said Perez de
Cuellar had hoped for some public concession from Iraq, along with
its quiet moves beneath the surface.
   ``Iraq had many demands and was stubborn,'' the official said.
``Aziz spent much of his time insisting the United States was
violating international law.''
   With hopes dashed for any immediate breakthrough, Perez de
Cuellar would likely explore various proposals for an Arab buffer
force under an international umbrella, the Jordanian official said.
   The buffer force would separate U.S. and allied troops from
Iraqi troops.
   Libyan leader Moammar Gadhafi has suggested his own peace plan,
under which U.N. troops would replace the Iraqis in Kuwait and Arab
or Moslem armies would replace U.S. forces in Saudi Arabia.
   PLO chief Yasser Arafat has proposed a plan that links an Iraqi
withdrawal from Kuwait with an Israeli pullout from occupied
territories. Egyptian President Hosni Mubarak's Arab League
approach simply demands that Iraq leave Kuwait.
   Perez de Cuellar said the crisis had taken on international
dimensions and ``global principles have to be acknowledged.'' But
with international approval, he said, any Arab plan could be
implemented.
   Asked about the use of an Arab force, Perez de Cuellar told
reporters, ``I did not discuss this with him.''
   But Jordanian sources said Aziz and the U.N. chief discussed a
plan to put Arab troops between Iraqi and U.S. forces, secure
release of the hostages and arrange for simultaneous withdrawals in
Kuwait and Saudi Arabia. U.N. members, including the Soviet Union,
might mediate.
   But, the sources said, the long-term political resolution of the
conflict seemed insurmountable.
   Iraq has stressed that any solution in Kuwait must also settle
outstanding issues in Israeli-occupied territories and Lebanon,
where Syrian troops are deployed.
   In the Amman talks, Aziz refused to bend until guarantees were
made about Israel and Lebanon, the Jordanian sources said. The
secretary-general, as an agent of the United Nations, had no room
to maneuver, they said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0038 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 1503EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-Germany     09-02 0394</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Germany,0405</SECOND>
<HEAD>East Germany Ambassador Reported Taken from Kuwait to Baghdad</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf Rdp, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>EAST BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An East German government spokesman said the
country's ambassador to Kuwait was forcibly taken to Iraq on Sunday
after he left his diplomatic mission, apparently to seek food at
the West German Embassy.
   The East Berlin government was negotiating with Iraq for the
release of Ambassador Kurt Merkel, 56, a government spokesman said
on condition of anonymity.
   The spokesman, citing the talks with Iraq, would give no details
of the incident. However, he confirmed a report from Brussels,
Belgium, where a diplomatic source said Merkel was taken to Baghdad
from Iraqi-occupied Kuwait.
   The source, who also spoke on condition of anonymity, said the
information was relayed to Brussels by Marcel van Roey, the Belgian
ambassador in Kuwait.
   The source said the East German envoy left his embassy ``where
the food and water situation was apparently critical,'' to visit
the West German Embassy.
   After leaving the West German mission Saturday afternoon,
Merkel, accompanied by his wife, was questioned by Iraqi soldiers
for several hours, the Belgian official said.
   ``He spent the night at the East German mission. Today (Sunday),
he was taken under escort to Baghdad. This sounds like an expulsion
to us,'' added the source.
   It was unclear if Merkel's wife also was taken to Baghdad.
   A West German Foreign Ministry spokesman in Bonn said he could
not confirm the report and said the information must come from East
Germany.
   Merkel has been ambassador to Kuwait since April 22, 1987. He
and his wife had been alone at the embassy since the mission's 15
other staffers were evacuated more than a week ago.
   Iraq has ordered foreign missions to leave Kuwait because it
claims the country is now a part of Iraq. Scores of diplomats
remain holed up in their embassies.
   A West German jet early Sunday carried 311 women, children and a
few men from 22 countries to Frankfurt from Iraq after Baghdad said
it would release women and children among the Westerners trapped in
the country.
   Iraq is the target of a U.S.-led trade embargo that is believed
to have created shortages of food and other essential supplies.
Thousands of U.S. troops were deployed in Saudi Arabia to deter an
Iraqi attack after the Persian Gulf nation invaded Kuwait on Aug. 2.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0039 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 1517EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Israel-Uprising     09-02 0346</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel-Uprising,0356</SECOND>
<HEAD>August's Death Toll Equals Lowest In Arab Uprising</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Three Palestinians were killed by Israelis in
August, equaling the lowest monthly death toll of the 33-month
Palestinian uprising, according to figures released Sunday.
   July's toll was also three.
   The Israeli Center for Human Rights in the Occupied Territories
attributed the lower toll to an army policy of avoiding
confrontations with stone- throwers. The policy was initiated by
Defense Minister Moshe Arens, who took office in June.
   ``The decrease in the number of (Palestinians) killed by the
security forces in the territories continues,'' the center said in
a written statement. ``It can be explained by a more restrained
policy on opening fire.''
   Of the three Palestinians killed in August, one victim was shot
in a clash with soldiers in the occupied West Bank.
   Also, an Israeli woman has been charged in connection with the
death of a Palestinian during anti-Arab riots in Jerusalem. The
army said an investigation is being conducted into the fatal
shooting of a Palestinian woman in the West Bank town of Hebron.
   The slayings in Jerusalem and Hebron followed the discovery of
the bodies of two Jewish teen-agers in Jerusalem, believed to be
slain by Palestinian nationalists.
   Also in August, Palestinians in the occupied territories killed
at least 11 fellow Arabs on suspicion of collaborating with the
Israeli authorities, Arab reports said.
   At least 728 Palestinians have died at the hands of Israeli
soldiers and civilians since the uprising began in December 1987.
   The highest toll was in April 1988, when 44 Palestinians were
killed during riots over the death of the Palestine Liberation
Organization's military commander, Khalil Wazir, also known as Abu
Jihad. He was shot in Tunis by unidentified assailants. The death
was blamed on Israel.
   Last May, 32 Palestinians were killed, most as the army sought
to put down riots following the killings of seven Arab workers by
an apparently deranged Israeli civilian.
   Some 254 Palestinians also have been killed by their Arab
brethren as suspected pro-Israeli collaborators. Forty-seven
Israelis have died in the violence.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0040 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 1522EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-People Sub a0705 09-02 0268</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People, Sub, a0705,0273</SECOND>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS Detroit-dated 3rd item to DELETE reference to President
Bush being at Ellis Island; he will be at Helsinki summit.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>DETROIT (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Lee Iacocca, preparing to reopen New York's Ellis
Island next weekend, says the racial melting pot is what makes
America work.
   ``Whether it's food, or dress, or the arts, music, whatever,''
he said. ``If we're losing control of our destiny, it's because we
aren't facing up to our heritage. And what's that? Back to Ellis
Island.''
   The Chrysler Corp. chairman led the drive to raise $345 million
to restore Ellis Island and the Statue of Liberty, which was
rededicated in 1986.
   Next Sunday, Iacocca will help dedicate the new Ellis Island
Immigration Museum and designate the 27-acre site on the island in
New York Harbor as a national shrine.
   Immigrants have learned hard work and sacrifice are keys to a
better life, Iacocca said.
   Iacocca, an immigrant's son, said the gateway to the United
States for 17 million Americans can give the country a needed boost
of morale. But the Ellis Island celebration will be low-key _
dinner and speeches _ compared to the hoopla of the statue four
years ago.
   ``One guy called me and said, `What are you, crazy? Why are we
having a black-tie dinner? Is that in keeping with the immigrant
experience?' I said, `What do you want, for us to come in rags?'''
Iacocca said. ``I just thought it would be a nice touch, and you do
honor to the fact that we made it _ we can even afford to rent a
tux.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0041 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 1537EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SouthAfrica     09-02 0462</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-South Africa,0476</SECOND>
<HEAD>21 Killed in Attacks in Two Townships</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GREG MYRE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JOHANNESBURG, South Africa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Police found the bodies of 21
blacks Sunday following overnight clashes in townships wracked by
fighting among rival black factions.
   President F.W. de Klerk, meanwhile, announced a follow-up
investigation into allegations of improper police violence against
blacks and urged an inquiry into the system of housing migrant
workers in barracks.
   Many of the young men in the barracks have taken part in
township fights in which more than 530 blacks have died since Aug.
12.
   The battles in Tembisa and Tokoza east of Johannesburg Saturday
came after a week of relative peace in the townships.
   Men armed with guns and other weapons drove around the townships
late Saturday night in a van, firing at pedestrians and getting out
to attack, said police spokesman Capt. Eugene Opperman.
   The victims had been shot or hacked to death, Opperman said. The
townships are about 18 miles apart.
   Most of the recent fighting has pitted Zulus loyal to the
conservative Inkatha movement against Xhosas and other blacks who
support the African National Congress, led by Nelson Mandela.
   ANC leaders, speaking at a mass funeral Sunday, accused police
of siding with Inkatha in the recent clashes. About 4,000 people
attended the service at a soccer stadium for 19 blacks killed in
Kagiso, west of Johannesburg.
   Alfred Nzo, the ANC's secretary general, said the victims ``died
at the hands of the agents of the apartheid regime.''
   De Klerk and police have said individual policemen may have
acted improperly, but the force as a whole has been impartial.
   The speakers pleaded for tolerance among opposing black
organizations. But the youthful crowd shouted down a Kagiso town
councilor and a member of the Pan-Africanist Congress, a rival
group. Militant blacks consider black town leaders collaborators
with the white-led government.
   De Klerk requested Law and Order Minister Adriaan Vlok to
conduct ``an urgent and in-depth investigation'' after a government
report concluded police fired without reason on black demonstrators
last March, killing five and wounding 156 in Sebokeng south of
Johannesburg.
   ``Certain allegations which have been made against the South
African police are regarded in an extremely serious light,'' de
Klerk said.
   The ANC, which claims more than 10 people were killed at the
Sebokeng shooting, called the report's findings an example of the
``indiscipline, callousness and readiness to shoot on the part of
the police.''
   De Klerk also announced an inquiry into the system of
migrant-worker hostels for young, single men.
   He said the government wants to provide housing on a ``family
basis'' but cannot because of a severe housing shortage among
blacks.
   ``These hostels cannot simply be closed or demolished without
alternative accommodation being available,'' said de Klerk.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0042 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 1539EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-SurvivalProgram Bjt   09-02 0936</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Survival Program, Bjt,0968</SECOND>
<HEAD>Future Cloudy For Embattled Wilderness Survival Program</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MIKE CARTER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SALT LAKE CITY (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The embattled founder of a desert-survival
program for wayward teens is fighting state efforts to close him
down, possibly as early as this week, and criminal charges stemming
from the death of a 16-year-old charge.
   Stephen Cartisano says the negligent homicide and child abuse
charges are part of a vendetta by state officials, ``liars''
jealous of his Challenger Foundation's success. He says he may just
pick up and move to another state.
   ``I have more success than these guys can ever dream about,''
Cartisano has said. ``They want to put me out of business because
they think they are the sole repositories of light and truth
regarding children.''
   The sniping against the founder of the Delaware-based company
became a barrage this summer with the heat stroke death of a
teen-age girl enrolled in the Challenger program, and with
allegations by other teen-agers of being abused, starved, tied up
and forced to eat lizards and mice to survive.
   Cartisano's critics describe him as a manipulator who places
profit above concern for his young patients. The program charges
$15,900 for its 63-day ``expedition.''
   ``Basically, he charges parents a lot of money to take their
kids out in the desert and feed them roadkill,'' said Terry
Twitchell, a spokeswoman with the state Department of Human
Services.
   ``He's a liar,'' said Dr. Kay Edrington, a former Challenger
employee who claims Cartisano misrepresented him to parents and on
insurance billing forms as a psychologist.
   ``I've known for some time there would come a day of reckoning
for Challenger,'' Edrington said.
   It may be coming soon.
   A state judge ordered the beleaguered program to come up with a
$100,000 bond by Tuesday to prove its financial ability to continue
business. Without it, the judge threatens to shut the program down.
   In Kane County, Sheriff Max Jackson has filed a misdemeanor
negligent homicide count against Cartisano and his former field
director, Lance ``Horsehair'' Jagger, in the June 27 death of
Kristen Chase, 16.
   Eight other counts of misdemeanor child abuse also were filed
against the two men. They are scheduled for arraignment Sept. 13.
   Challenger this summer sought protection under Chapter 11 of the
U.S. Bankruptcy Code and claims assets of only $63,000. State
officials say Challenger owes more than $279,000 in federal and
state taxes.
   Cartisano said he is considering leaving Utah for less hostile
surroundings.
   ``I've had offers from southern Nevada, New Mexico and
Arizona,'' he said. ``I hate to say, `You won't have Steve
Cartisano to kick around anymore,' but it's getting to that point.''
   Yet, some parents _ even the mother of the girl who died _
support Cartisano's austere recipe for bringing, as program
literature puts it, ``defiant, irresponsible or rebellious
teen-agers out of their dream world and back to reality.''
   ``Sometimes we need to be a little more calloused instead of
pampering our little darling dumplings like we've been doing and
not making them responsible for their own behavior,'' said Judith
Tepper of Los Angeles.
   Her teen-age son, Jordan, reportedly was tied to a tree by
Challenger counselors after trying to flee the program and dragged
through the brush when he refused to hike.
   Another advocate is Sharon Fuqua of Ponte Vedra Beach, Fla.,
Kristen's mother. The girl collapsed and died of heat stroke while
hiking atop the rugged Kaiparowits Plateau.
   ``I've never met any more dedicated, loving people trying to
help children,'' she said after her daughter's death.
   Cartisano said Chase's death can't be blamed on his program.
``She could have walked over to Central Park and collapsed,'' he
said at the time.
   Challenger opened in 1988, an offshoot of a popular survival
program offered at Brigham Young University in the 1970s. That
program was based on the idea that troubled youth could be helped
if forced to cope _ and triumph _ in an unforgiving environment
that cannot be manipulated.
   Some believe Challenger has skewed those goals, using the desert
not as a lesson but as a tool for punishment.
   During a recent court hearing, attorneys described interviews of
Challenger patients. One teen related a practice called ``rodeo,''
described as ``punishment where they run until they couldn't run,
hike until they couldn't hike and then crawl until they couldn't
crawl _ and then they were dragged.''
   Several said they weren't given any food for up to four days
when entering the program and were forced to forage for meals.
   Assistant Utah Attorney General Linda Luinstra said a
15-year-old boy related that ``at one point he ate a lizard and at
another, he and some other children skinned a mouse and ate it.''
   Nine wilderness survival programs operate in Utah and officials
estimate that as many as 300 teen-agers hike and climb the
breathtaking vistas of southern Utah's red-rock desert, seeking a
solution to problems of drug abuse, laziness and low self-esteem.
   The programs came under scrutiny after the deaths of Chase and
another girl, 15-year-old Michelle Sutton of Pleasanton, Calif.,
who died while enrolled in a similar program, Summit Quest, earlier
this summer.
   State officials have dogged Challenger since its inception, but
up until now have succeeded only in forcing the program to obtain a
state license.
   Challenger was granted a provisional, 90-day license on July 1.
Ken Stettler, deputy director of the Division of Licensing,
promises it won't be renewed without ``radical'' changes.
   Cartisano boasts a 93 percent success rate. Children are
returned to the program _ at no additional cost _ if they get into
trouble before they turn 18.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0043 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 1553EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-RapeHoax     09-02 0327</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Rape Hoax,0334</SECOND>
<HEAD>Woman Apologizes in Court-Ordered Ads For False Rape Charge</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LEXINGTON, Neb. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A woman who falsely accused a man of rape
apologized Sunday in court-ordered radio ads, saying she hopes time
will heal the damage to the man's reputation.
   Elizabeth Irene Richardson, 24, was ordered to run radio and
newspaper ads throughout Dawson County in central Nebraska as part
of her sentence for a perjury conviction last February. She was
later to begin a six-month jail term for falsely accusing Gary
Nitsch, 44.
   ``I want the public to know that these allegations were not true
and that I made up the story for personal reasons,'' Ms. Richardson
said in the radio ad. ``While I realize there is nothing I can
really do or say to repair the damage I have caused, I sincerely
pray that time will heal the wounds my false allegations have
inflicted on Mr. Nitsch and his family,'' she said.
   Ms. Richardson accused Nitsch of raping her in September 1988.
He was charged with sexual assault, but the case was dropped for
lack of physical evidence.
   Authorities later learned that Ms. Richardson had told friends
the rape was a hoax. Dawson County Attorney John Marsh said Ms.
Richardson was trying to get the attention of her husband, a truck
driver who was often away from home.
   Nitsch said he had met the woman briefly when he went to her
house inquiring about a painting job she had advertised. As a
result of the false charge, Nitsch lost his job and his family was
harassed.
   A Dawson County District Court judge sentenced Ms. Richardson to
apologize in a half-page advertisement in every newspaper and a
primetime spot on each radio station in Dawson County. The county
in central Nebraska has about 22,000 residents.
   Nitsch does not have a telephone, and a message was left Sunday
at his brother's home. The woman who answered said Nitsch was
working and not available.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0044 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 1604EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Gulf-Kuwait-Familes     09-02 0535</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Kuwait-Familes,530</SECOND>
<HEAD>Kuwait Offers Financial Aid to Hostage Families</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By H. JOSEF HEBERT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Kuwait is promising financial assistance to
American families facing money problems because of Iraq's holding
of their loved ones in Kuwait, the Kuwaiti Embassy confirmed Sunday.
   It was unclear whether any money had yet been provided any of
the families or how much financial assistance was involved. The
embassy did not mention families of American workers held in Iraq.
   ``We stand ready, willing and are able to share in the costs
whatever we are asked for by these families,'' Kuwaiti Ambassador
Saud Nasir al-Sabah said in a statement.
   ``All families who are currently in the U.S. and who are facing
economic or financial difficulties because of their husbands or
relatives are being held hostage by the Iraqis inside Kuwait will
receive assistance from the government of Kuwait,'' al-Sabah said.
   He said the assistance would be coordinated through the U.S.
State Department.
   But the State Department on Sunday referred questions about the
assistance promise to the Kuwaiti Embassy. One department official,
speaking on the condition that he not be identified further, said
he was not aware of any payments having been made, but ``we're
aware they made the offer.''
   There have been a number of reports of immediate families of
Americans being held by Iraq facing financial difficulties. At
least one oil drilling company whose business with Kuwait or Iraq
has been disrupted stopped paying the salaries of 16 workers, who
were in the two countries when the crisis erupted a month ago.
   One of the first actions by President Bush in response to the
Iraqi invasions of Kuwait was to freeze all Iraqi and Kuwaiti
assets in the United States. The exiled Kuwaiti government,
however, has been given access to funds.
   The Kuwaiti Embassy said the Kuwaiti government ``has become
concerned about the plight of many of these American families who
have lost their income.''
   There are an estimated 2,500 Americans in Kuwait and as many as
500 in Iraq. While some of them have had their families with them,
many others working in oil fields were in Kuwait alone with wives
and children back in the United States.
   Most large companies are believed to have continued paying the
workers, but some have not.
   A small Texas company, OGE Drilling Inc. of Houston, fired its
16 workers in Kuwait the day of the Iraqi invasion. ``Our contracts
with these people ended by basis of ... an act of war, something
beyond our control,'' OGE Vice President Jay Simpson said recently.
   Simpson said the company, which supplies workers for the Kuwait
Oil Co., could not afford to continue paying the workers' salaries
with revenue no longer coming from the Kuwaiti company.
   Ten of OGE's workers have escaped Kuwait, but six reportedly
continue to be held.
   One of the six workers, Edward Hale, was believed to have been
among the first Americans detained by the Iraqis. His wife,
Patricia, was stunned when told she no longer would be getting her
husband's paycheck. She said she faces serious money problems.
   The Kuwaiti Embassy said the State Department will seek out the
families and determine who might need assistance.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0045 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 1624EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-DigestBriefs SUB a9910 09-02 0164</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Digest Briefs, SUB, a9910,0165</SECOND>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS first two grafs of first item to CLARIFY 47 Americans
freed. No first add will move.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Forty-seven Americans reclaimed their freedom
Sunday, liberated from Saddam Hussein's clutches and grateful to be
back home. ``I wasn't a guest,'' said Lloyd Culbertson. ``I damned
near starved to death.''
   The former hostages, weary from 24 hours of travel and their
weeks as unofficial prisoners of war, arrived at Washington-Dulles
International Airport aboard an Iraqi jetliner cleared to land only
for this homecoming flight.
   Just a handful of the passengers talked with reporters; most
cleared customs and left the airport quietly with relatives. A U.S.
official said 24 women, 11 men and 12 children arrived but declined
to identify them, citing privacy laws.
   The Americans who were held in Kuwait, which was overrun by
Iraqi soldiers on Aug. 2, brought ominous word that Saddam
Hussein's forces may be mistreating Americans left behind.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0046 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 1636EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Obit-HolmesaCourt     09-02 0510</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Holmes a Court,0523</SECOND>
<HEAD>Holmes a Court, Once Richest Man Down Under, Dies</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PAUL ALEXANDER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SYDNEY, Australia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Robert Holmes a Court, the cunning
corporate raider once known as Australia's richest man, died of a
heart attack Sunday. He was 53.
   Family spokesman Tim Treadgold said the businessman was rushed
to a hospital early Sunday from his family farm outside Perth, on
Australia's west coast, but was dead on arrival.
   ``It was totally unexpected. As far as I know, there had been no
indications he had heart trouble,'' Treadgold said.
   Holmes a Court, born in Johannesburg, South Africa, was known as
a shrewd but polite, soft-spoken entrepreneur who had been
rebuilding his financial empire after losing much of his estimated
$1.4 billion fortune in the October 1987 stock market crash.
   ``In many respects, he revolutionized the finance world in
Australia,'' said Ian Spicer, the chief executive of the
Confederation of Australian Industry. ``He was a dominant
character, a man of significant ability, and he will be missed in
the business community.''
   The former attorney made his reputation as a corporate raider,
earning the nickname of the ``Great Acquirer'' while chairman of
the Bell Resources Group. He built it into an empire based on
rising asset values in transportation, media, entertainment and
building supplies.
   Holmes a Court amassed a stake of nearly $1 billion in U.S. oil
giant Texaco Inc., had large interests in the British bank Standard
Chartered and American steelmaker USX Corp., and made four
unsuccessful bids for BHP, Australia's largest company.
   BHP, which stands for Broken Hill Proprietary, is a steel, oil
and mining giant.
   His diversified holdings also included two newspapers, a Perth
television station and a radio network. Bell's assets topped out at
about $6 billion.
   But the 1987 crash hit Holmes a Court hard, costing him an
estimated $1 billion when Merrill Lynch and Co. withdrew as lead
manager of a major bond issue that Bell would have used to reduce
its interest payments.
   Investors' confidence was shaken. Holmes a Court was forced to
sell off many of assets, including about half his controlling stake
in Bell, to an arm of the West Australia state government and the
rest to business rival Alan Bond.
   While down, Holmes a Court was not out. He chose to foresake the
public corporate scene and concentrate on his Perth-based private
flagship company, Heytesbury Holdings Ltd.
   In May, he became Australia's largest landowner when he bought
control of the country's biggest cattle ranch, Sherwin Pastoral.
The company leases an area about the size of England and Wales
combined _ about 1 percent of Australia's entire land mass.
   Australian Business Magazine reported that his personal wealth
swelled by 66 percent last year to $500 million, calling it a
``tribute to his ability to salvage a personal fortune from a
public debacle.''
   He also owned stables of racehorses, an extensive art collection
and several antique cars.
   Holmes a Court is survived by his wife, Janet, and four
children. There was no immediate information about funeral
arrangements.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0047 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 1649EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Bush-Summit     09-02 0583</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bush-Summit,580</SECOND>
<HEAD>Administration Scrambles to Prepare for Gorbachev Meeting</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RITA BEAMISH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>KENNEBUNKPORT, Maine, (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush's hastily called
summit with Soviet President Mikhail Gorbachev will likely consist
of about five hours of talks devoted largely to the Persian Gulf
crisis, administration officials said Sunday.
   ``We're comparing notes. We would be explaining where we think
the situation is, where we would go,'' one source said, describing
the discussion as similiar to the ongoing consultations Bush has
had with several other world leaders on the crisis.
   On Saturday when he announced the summit, Bush said the gulf
crisis was one of many items to be discussed. ``There is no special
agenda relating to the Middle East,'' he said. The meeting is
scheduled for next Sunday in Helsinki, Finland.
   Although Bush had said Saturday he saw no mediating role for the
Soviets, one official said Sunday that Bush would welcome any
influence they may have in getting Iraq to pull out of Kuwait.
   An administration official said Sunday that any discussion of
Soviet mediation implies that the gulf crisis is a dispute between
Iraq and the United States. The administration says that U.S.
forces are in the area to enforce an international response to the
Iraqi invasion of Kuwait and threat against Saudi Arabia.
   The officials would speak only on condition of anonymity.
   The administration on Sunday began working out the details of
the Helsinki meeting.
   ``Everybody's scrambling to put their pieces together,'' said
one official. Bush returns to Washington on Monday evening from his
three-week vacation.
   Sig Rogich, the White House official in charge of advance
logistics and imagemaking, was called back from a vacation Sunday
to coordinate such details as where in Helsinki the meeting will be
held and what time.
   Sununu flew Saturday to his home state of New Hampshire after
arriving Saturday in Washington from London, and on Sunday was
driving his family back to Washington. He did not plan to see Bush
until the president's return to the capital.
   Lower-level staffers met at the White House on Sunday to begin
work on logistics and contacting their Soviet counterparts.
   Bush held his proposal for a summit meeting so closely to his
vest that several top White House staff members did not know about
it when they were in the Soviet Union during the week, officials
said. Bush's secretary of state, James A. Baker III, made the
arrangements by phone with his Soviet counterpart.
   Chief of Staff John Sununu last week led a White House team to
the Soviet Union at Moscow's invitation to explain the technical
workings of the U.S. executive branch.
   Sununu knew before he left that Bush had proposed a summit
meeting and was kept abreast of developments but did not play a key
role in arranging the summit, aides said.
   While ongoing conventional arms talks will be on the agenda,
that portion of the meeting ``would just be a review,'' of the
negotiations between the two countries, said an official.
   The United States and Soviet Union are engaged in talks to
reduce troops and tanks in Europe and hope to get an agreement in
time for a 35-nation conference that is planned in Europe in
November.
   Bush and Gorbachev also will discuss regional issues, such as
the ongoing conflict in Cambodia and Soviet involvement in
Afghanistan, according to the president and his aides,
   Bush's wife, Barbara, and Gorbachev's wife Raisa also will
travel to Helsinki. No details of their schedule have been
disclosed.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0048 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 1649EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-KuwaitBooty     09-02 0230</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Kuwait Booty,0235</SECOND>
<HEAD>Kuwaitis Say Iraq Took $1 Billion in Gold, 15 Aircraft</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Iraq seized 15 Kuwait Airways planes and $1
billion in gold from the Central Bank when it invaded its oil-rich
neighbor, Kuwaiti leaders said in interviews published Sunday.
   The allegations appeared in the weekly Observer newspaper, which
interviewed several exiled Kuwaiti leaders in Saudi Arabia.
   Cars, furniture, refrigerators and television sets were loaded
up and taken to Baghdad, where Iraqi television described the
stolen goods as ``the wealth of the emirs of Kuwait,'' The Observer
said.
   It said that among the first objectives of Iraqi President
Saddam Hussein's invading troops was Kuwait's Central Bank, where
employees were forced to open the safe. The Iraqis took about 365
million Kuwaiti dinars in cash, worth more than $1 billion at the
time.
   ``But then Saddam did a strange thing. He linked the Kuwaiti
dinar to the Iraqi currency, which lowered its value by several
hundred percent,'' Kuwaiti Foreign Minister Sheik Sabah al-Ahmad
al-Sabah was quoted as saying.
   The Iraqis also seized about $1 billion in gold ingots, Sabah
said.
   After repairing the main runway at Kuwait Airport, which was
damaged during the invasion, the Iraqis flew out two Boeing 767s,
one Boeing 727, five Airbus 310s, three Airbus 300s, two Gulfstream
G3s, and two Hawker Siddeleys _ all belonging to Kuwait Airways,
the newspaper said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0049 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 1650EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Gulf-KuwaitEmbassy     09-02 0586</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Kuwait Embassy,580</SECOND>
<HEAD>Photographer: Embassy Personnel Burning Furniture, Drinking Pool
Water</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf-Americans Home, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By W. DALE NELSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Americans remaining in the U.S. Embassy in
Kuwait are breaking up the furniture for firewood and boiling water
from the swimming pool to drink, a photographer who accompanied
Jesse Jackson to the Middle East said Sunday.
   D. Michael Cheers, a freelance photo journalist who also has
worked as a consultant to Jackson, said the streets of Kuwait City
outside the embassy are ``basically deserted'' but are heavily
patrolled by Iraqi troops who invaded the country on Aug. 2.
   Cheers said he heard no shots fired in the streets, although
Bonnie Anderton, a Denver woman who was among the hostages
returning with Jackson, said the sound of gunfire was frequent.
   Noting that Iraqi officials had described American and other
foreign hostages as guests, Mrs. Anderton said, ``It is the only
hotel I have ever been a guest in that I don't intend to leave a
tip.''
   ``We were sleeping on the floor, there was no water and no power
and we were being eaten alive by bugs,'' she said.
   Mrs. Anderton and Lloyd Sutherland, 76, of El Paso, Texas, both
told of eating a diet heavy on frozen turkey.
   ``I have never eaten so much turkey in my life,'' said
Sutherland.
   Cheers said Edward Johnson, 62, a St. Louis businessman who took
refuge in the embassy while in Kuwait City, told him that much of
the frozen food later spoiled. The embassy was without outside
power and was operating its generators only part of the time to
conserve them. He said the hostages had switched to a diet of
canned goods, especially tuna.
   ``They are boiling water from the pool and breaking up furniture
from the compound to use to cook in the wood stoves,'' said the
photographer, who took pictures inside the embassy compound for The
Associated Press.
   Outside, he said, ``The streets, as well as the highways, are
just littered with burned out cars and cars that have been
abandoned, the tires taken off of them.''
   ``We went to this beach-front not far from the embassy compound,
and it was just littered with spent shells,'' he said.
   ``The place is pretty messed up,'' he said. The streets were
virtually deserted both on their first visit on Friday, a Moslem
holy day, and when they visited again on Saturday, Cheers added.
   The photographer said the scene in Baghdad, the capital of Iraq,
was a sharp contrast to that in Kuwait City.
   ``You don't see the tanks in the street and the sandbags,'' he
said. ``People are going about their ordinary business.''
   Jackson flew to Amman, Jordan, on Monday, went on to Baghdad on
Wednesday and flew to Kuwait on Friday. On that trip, he went to
the Embassy but did not get past the entrance.
   After flying to Baghdad again and meeting with Iraqi President
Saddam Hussein, Jackson returned to Kuwait to pick up the hostages.
   On the trip across the Atlantic in the Iraqi airways jumbo jet,
the hostages had little to say, Cheers reported.
   ``Their attitude was, `We are just stressed out. We have been
told so many different things at so many different times over the
course of the last month.' Basically, they just wanted to be left
alone.''
   When they arrived at Washington-Dulles International Airport,
few of the hostages chose to talk with reporters. Most simply went
their ways to hotels or to catch flights home.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0050 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 1652EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-EGermany-TradeFair     09-02 0290</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-EGermany-Trade Fair,0300</SECOND>
<HEAD>East Germany's Trade Fair Gets Capitalist Makeover</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LEIPZIG, East Germany (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A former showcase for sleepy
state-run enterprises opened Sunday as an extravaganza of
capitalism.
   This year's Leipzig International Trade Fair is dominated by
businesses from West Germany and other Western countries displaying
everything from cars to computers to chemical products.
   East Germany's former government-owned ventures, many struggling
to compete in the free-market economy that took effect July 1, also
used the fair as the debut for new lines.
   With the influx of Western businesses, the number of exhibitors
more than tripled from last year, from 1,500 to 4,600, fair
organizers said.
   Police estimated 350,000 people traveled to Leipzig, a decaying
industrial city about 100 miles southwest of Berlin. The crowds
created huge traffic snarls.
   ``The tourist buses from East Europe don't want to come so much
anymore, but the increase has been mostly in cars from West Germany
and Western Europe,'' said police spokesman Peter Heimann.
   East German Prime Minister Lothar de Maiziere spoke with
exhibitors from other nations for about two hours, urging them to
invest in East Germany and form cooperative agreements with the
nation's industries. East Germany is scheduled to merge with its
western neighbor Oct. 3.
   ``Many enterprises see new horizons at this festival,'' de
Maiziere said.
   Gerhard Wolf, regional chief of BASF AG, a West German chemical
and plastics company, told de Maiziere his company was willing to
buy an East German chemical company in Schwarzheide for $66 million.
   Wolf said the West German company would guarantee a profitable
operation. De Maiziere said he was interested in further talks.
   Economists predict up to 3 million of East Germany's 8 million
workers could lose their jobs in the unification process.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0051 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 1656EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-PLO     09-02 0486</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-PLO,0499</SECOND>
<HEAD>Persian Gulf Crisis Splits PLO Factions</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf Rdp, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MONA ZIADE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NICOSIA, Cyprus (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Radical Palestinian leader George Habash
has split with his long-time Syrian backers and is now in Iraq,
marking a major shift within the PLO triggered by the Persian Gulf
crisis, informed sources reported Sunday.
   They also reported that another radical, Nayef Hawatmeh, is
struggling to retain control of his group, the Democratic Front for
the Liberation of Palestine, after a mutiny sparked by his support
for Syria's anti-Iraq stand in the month-old crisis.
   The developments underlined the rift within the Palestine
Liberation Organization caused by Iraq's invasion of Kuwait Aug. 2.
   PLO chief Yasser Arafat's support for Saddam, qualified by a
condemnation of the occupation of the gulf kingdom, has alienated
the organization from the Arab mainstream that has opposed Saddam's
action.
   That has cut Arafat off from the financial support of Saudi
Arabia and other pro-Western gulf states, while at the same time
firing up the PLO's radicals, like Habash and Hawatmeh.
   They reluctantly went along with Arafat's 1988 peace initiative,
in which he renounced terrorism and recognized Israel. They have
long argued that only military struggle will achieve a Palestinian
homeland.
   Saddam has demanded an end to the Israeli occupation of the West
Bank and Gaza Strip in any settlement of the gulf crisis.
   Habash, 64, heads the Popular Front for the Liberation of
Palestine, the second biggest faction in the PLO after Arafat's
Fatah movement.
   His new alliance with Saddam marks an increasing tilt by PLO
radicals toward Baghdad amid growing fears that Palestinian
militants and other Arab groups will launch terrorist attacks on
U.S., Western and Arab targets to support Iraq.
   Hawatmeh, 54, has said that he cannot back the Iraqis, who he
says have done to Kuwait what the Israelis did to Palestine. But
the Democratic Front's deputy secretary-general, Yasser Abed-Rabbo,
flew to Baghdad with Arafat last week, cementing the split from
Hawatmeh's leadership.
   Saddam already harbors the radical Palestine Liberation Front, a
PLO faction led by Mohammed Abbas, known as Abul Abbas. That group
hijacked the Italian cruise ship Achille Lauro in 1985 and was
behind an abortive seaborne raid on Israel last May.
   That operation led President Bush to suspend an 18-month
dialogue with the PLO.
   The official Iraqi News Agency said in a terse dispatch that
Saddam met with Habash Sunday on the crisis. The agency made no
mention of Habash's old feud with Iraq over his alliance with
Syrian President Hafez Assad, Saddam's Arab archrival.
   The Popular Front gained notoriety in the early 1970s with a
series of airliner hijackings that dramatically focused world
attention on the Palestinian struggle.
   The informed sources, speaking on condition of anonymity by
telephone from Iraq, Jordan and Tunisia, said Habash flew to
Baghdad Saturday on his first visit to Iraq in 14 years. They gave
no more details.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0052 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 1706EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-RiotAnniversary     09-02 0300</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Riot Anniversary,0310</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tranquil Beach Baptism Contrasts With Chaos A Year Ago</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KAREN HAYWOOD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>VIRGINIA BEACH, Va. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The day before Labor Day 1989, this
resort strip was littered with broken bottles and bricks after
clashes between police and thousands of youths.
   Sunday morning, a beachfront stage was erected and 150 people _
some clad in their Sunday best, others in shorts and sandals _
gathered for an Atlantic Ocean baptism.
   ``I am obviously finding that this is a much more enjoyable
situation than a year ago,'' said City Manager Aubrey Watts.
   While some have complained about an excessive buildup of police
for this year's Laborfest, the police presence and a smaller
holiday crowd than last year clearly were having the affect of
preventing violence.
   The looting and clashes last year resulted in 158 arrests, 43
injuries, $1.4 million in damage to stores and lingering
accusations of racism and police brutality.
   At Sunday's service, which ended with a dozen baptisms in the
Atlantic Ocean, the worshippers clapped and raised their hands
singing ``The Lord God is holy.''
   ``We're taking Jesus Christ out of the church, out of the four
walls of the church and into the streets and cities where people
live,'' said the Rev. Wellington Boone, president and founder of
New Generation Campus Ministries.
   Students from predominantly black East Coast colleges made up
much of the crowd for the annual fraternity festival, and most of
them were not here to seek religious deliverance.
   Still, the Sunday baptism represented a sharp change in tone
from last year's festival, attended by more than 100,000 people$.
   Police estimated the crowd this year at about 28,000 people.
Spokesman Lew Thurston said 48 people had been charged with
misdemeanor offenses along the oceanfront as of 6 a.m. Sunday.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0053 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 1713EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-WeatherpageWeather     09-02 0141</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Weatherpage Weather,0145</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rain in Southwest, South and Midwest</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Thunderstorms and showers hit the Southwest, South and portions
of the Midwest on Sunday. Hot weather prevailed in the nation's
midsection.
   Morning rainfall included 2{ inches at Sunset Crater, Ariz., and
1.3 inches in Flagstaff. Heavy rain caused caused flooding at New
Orleans and high winds damaged a boat at Laplace., La.
   Afternoon showers and thunderstorms extended over Florida,
southwest Georgia, Alabama, southern Mississippi, southern
Louisiana, southern Texas, northern Arizona, southern Wyoming,
western South Dakota, Iowa, south-central Minnesota, northwest
Illinois, eastern and south-central Ohio, north-central
Pennsylvania, New York and northern New England.
   The low temperature for the nation Sunday was 30 degrees at
Truckee, Calif.
   Temperatures around the nation at 3 p.m. EDT ranged from 61
degrees at San Simeon, Calif., to 101 degrees at Yuma, Ariz.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0054 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 1717EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-USHeadquarters     09-02 0620</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-US Headquarters,0638</SECOND>
<HEAD>Long-Sought Forward Headquarters Achieved in Crisis</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf Rdp, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RICHARD PYLE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>RIYADH, Saudi Arabia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Iraqi President Saddam Hussein has
done what pressure, persuasion and countless cups of Arabic coffee
among diplomats could not _ given the United States a military
headquarters in the Middle East.
   Set up during the past week in a suite of borrowed offices at a
Saudi government building, U.S. Central Command forward is now the
main nerve center for Operation Desert Shield.
   From his new post, Army Gen. H. Norman Schwarzkopf oversees the
growing American force dispatched to deter Saddam and his
formidable Iraqi military units from invading Saudi Arabia.
   If war comes, it will be from the center _ and a communications
center at an undisclosed location _ that Schwarzkopf and his
officers will run the battle.
   Capt. Ronald Wildermuth, Central Command's chief of information,
said about half the command's staff of 700 officers and enlisted
personnel have been brought to Saudi Arabia from the headquarters
at MacDill Air Force Base near Tampa, Fla.
   Some Riyadh hotels, filled with the new personnel, have become
minor fortresses, with concrete anti-terrorist barricades blocking
driveways and airport-type security checks for visitors.
   Americans, wearing brown-and-tan desert camouflage, mingle with
white-robed Arabs in lobbies and coffee shops.
   The command, responsible for U.S. military operations in 19
nations in the Mideast and southwest Asia, has been based in
Florida since 1983 because no Arab nation was willing to act as
host.
   Suggestions that this may be changed by Desert Shield are
adamantly rejected by both senior U.S. and Saudi officials.
   ``Centcom forward,'' they say, is temporary and will disappear
once the gulf crisis is over.
   ``We have made it very clear that we have no intention of
establishing permanent bases in Saudi Arabia,'' said Schwarzkopf.
   U.S. Defense Secretary Dick Cheney, who helped convince Saudi
King Fahd of the need for American help following Iraq's Aug. 2
invasion of Kuwait, quoted the Saudi monarch as saying he trusted
the United States to fulfill its commitment and leave if asked.
   The value of a forward headquarters and supply base has been
obvious to U.S. leaders since Central Command was established as a
spinoff from the Carter Administration's ``rapid deployment force.''
   In the absence of ground-based facilities in the gulf, the
United States has depended on long-range airlift and the
pre-positioning of material at Diego Garcia, a base in the Indian
Ocean, about 2,500 miles away.
   Except for Oman, which allowed the Navy refueling privileges and
an airstrip for a reconnaissance plane during the Iran-Iraq war,
the nearest thing to a permanent U.S. base in the region is at
Bahrain, where a small naval squadron, the Middle East Force, has
been stationed since 1949.
   Bahrain provides dock space for the force's flagship, USS La
Salle, and the use of a small shore facility. The American profile
is so low, however, that uniforms are never worn on shore and U.S.
diplomats caution newcomers not to offend the Bahrainis by
referring to the facilities as a ``base.''
   In 1988, reports circulated that the long-desired forward base
had found a host country. Bahrain has since been named as the
country, but the deal fell through after the Iran-Iraq war came to
a close last year.
   Most U.S. officers won't comment when asked whether the current
crisis could lead to a permanent presence, with American forces
staying on to protect the Saudi oil fields.
   A U.S. officer, who asked not to be identifed, said he believed
Desert Shield ``might help to convince the Arabs that having us
around isn't such a bad thing.''
   ``If that should happen,'' he said, ``we will owe it all to
Saddam Hussein.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0055 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 1718EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Ecuador-Quake     09-02 0152</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Ecuador-Quake,0157</SECOND>
<HEAD>Quake Shakes Ecuador, Causes Damage</HEAD>
<DATELINE>QUITO, Ecuador (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An earthquake and aftershocks rattled this
capital and several cities on the Pacific coast early Sunday,
causing minor damage to some homes. No injuries were reported.
   The quake registered 5.4 on the Richter scale, the Geodesic
Institute of Quito reported. Its epicenter was 37 miles northeast
of Bahia de Caraquez, a Pacific coast city 134 miles west of Quito.
   The earthquake struck around midnight Saturday, and several
aftershocks followed, the Institute said.
   Local radio stations said the walls of some old houses suffered
slight damage, but there were no reported injuries.
   A temblor registering 4.4 on the Richter scale was felt at 10:50
a.m. Sunday in Quito, but there were no reports of damage or
injuries.
   The Richter scale is a measure of ground motion as recorded on
seismographs. Every increase of one number means a tenfold increase
in magnitude.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0056 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 1722EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-CavingExpedition     09-02 0539</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Caving Expedition,0554</SECOND>
<HEAD>Soviets, Americans Head For Mountain Range to Set Caving Record</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JENNIFER FULFORD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CHICAGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In a true test of international diplomacy, a team
of Soviets and Americans will try to break a world record by
spending 20 days in the dark without showering while wearing rubber
suits.
   It's not a stunt for ``Ripley's Believe It Or Not.'' The 10-man
international team is headed to the Caucasus Mountains in the
Soviet Republic of Georgia to best the world's caving depth record,
currently just under a mile.
   ``It is our little way of international peace through caving,''
said John Sheltens, president of the National Speleological
Society. Speleology is the scientific study and examination of
caves.
   The group, based in Huntsville, Ala., sent four of its members
from Illinois, Tennessee and Alabama to the southwestern tip of the
Soviet Union on Friday for the expedition, which they hope to begin
by the end of this week.
   The Americans and six Soviets want to descend one mile _ 5,280
feet. That would beat the record set at a cave near Grenoble,
France, where explorers descended 5,250 feet.
   To beat the depth record, the team will actually have to climb.
A 10-mile hike up the mountains in the republic of Georgia will
bring them to the entrance of the Sneznaya Cave, 7,500 feet above
sea level.
   A separate 10-man team will be stationed at the mouth of the
cave while the cavers spend nearly three weeks surrounded by rock
walls. Another crew made an advance descent into the cave to set up
provisions at two campsites.
   After reaching the top of the glacier-like mountain, the cave
dwellers will don dry suits, special rubber clothes to protect
against wetness. Then the descent begins.
   ``The first 2,000 feet of descent is mostly vertical _ a series
of pits that we'll have to do on rope,'' said John Moses, a chemist
from the Chicago suburb of Glen Ellyn who is leading the expedition.
   ``Then what happens is that part of the cave intersects a major
river passage. We're hoping the dry suits float.''
   The team will follow the river, floating in it if necessary, to
a depth of at least one mile below the surface.
   The cold and damp will likely be the most bothersome, but there
are mental challenges as well, Moses said.
   ``We're going to be climbing into a soggy sleeping bag, and when
you are out of touch with daylight you tend to crave a taste of
color,'' Moses said
   Another problem could be communicating.
   ``Language is always a stumbling block,'' said Sheltens, who
explored with the Soviets during the society's first trip to their
country. ``But when you're with people that are doing the same
thing that you are doing, you work things out.''
   The trip is the second the caving society has made to the Soviet
Union in two years. The society is currently the host of a group of
Soviets on a multi-state caving excursion, the second tour of its
kind, Sheltens said.
   ``What we are finding out is that we are much more alike than we
are different,'' Sheltens. said in a telephone interview from his
home in Hot Springs, S.D.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0057 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 1723EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Libya-Sudan     09-02 0165</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Libya-Sudan,0171</SECOND>
<HEAD>Libya, Sudan Sign Plan for Integration</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ROME (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Libyan leader Moammar Gadhafi and Sudanese strongman
Lt. Gen. Omar Hassan el-Bashir have signed an agreement to
integrate their North African countries, the official Libyan news
agency reported Sunday.
   The agreement was signed Saturday night in Tripoli, the Libyan
capital, said the JANA news agency.
   The brief dispatch, monitored in Rome, did not elaborate on the
scope of the plan.
   But el-Bashir said in March the proposed plan would involve
cooperation in political, cultural, economic and security fields.
   Libya has been one of Sudan's main suppliers of military weapons
used to fight a civil war in the south.
   Since taking power in a military coup last year, el-Bashir has
dismantled parliament and instituted Libyan-style ``people's
committees'' intended to discuss and vote on government policy.
   The two nations share a 200-mile border.
   In the 21 years since he seized power, Gadhafi has tried and
failed to forge various mergers with many North African nations.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0058 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 1740EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-AbandonedChildren     09-02 0416</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Abandoned Children,0434</SECOND>
<HEAD>Soldier Father Charged With Misdemeanor Child Abuse</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CLARKSVILLE, Tenn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A soldier accused of leaving his three
children by themselves when he was deployed to the Middle East has
been charged with misdemeanor child abuse, police said.
   Staff Sgt. Faagalo Savaiki's two boys, aged 13 and 9, and their
12-year-old sister were found dirty and alone Wednesday at their
home, police said. They were without food, and pets in the home
were hungry.
   Savaiki, a soldier with the 501st Signal Battalion based at
nearby Fort Campbell, Ky., had been sent to Saudi Arabia the week
before.
   ``To me, it's just blatant neglect of the children,'' said
Clarksville police Sgt. Bill Poor, who is in charge of the civil
investigation.
   Savaiki was charged Friday with three counts of child abuse, one
for each of the children, Poor said.
   ``There may be other charges filed,'' Poor said Saturday.
   The warrants will not be served until Savaiki returns from Saudi
Arabia, he said.
   On Thursday, Savaiki flew from Saudi Arabia to American Samoa
after learning his mother was gravely ill.
   Poor said the children's mother, Joyce Savaiki, has been told of
their plight, but cannot afford to buy a plane ticket from Hawaii
to Clarksville.
   The mother has been living in Hawaii with her family since
separating from her husband more than a month ago.
   ``I do not know why she did not take custody of the children
after the separation,'' said Poor, who said the case remains under
investigation.
   A neighbor, David Kimberling, said he feels certain there are
mitigating circumstances. ``It will be interesting to hear his side
of the story,'' he said.
   Fort Campbell spokesman Bill Harralson said last week that
Savaiki's unit had no record of him being divorced or separated
from his wife.
   Single parents' units must have information on file on who will
be responsible for taking care of their children or their home if
they are deployed, said Harralson.
   The children were placed in a foster home Friday, and will
remain in the custody of the Tennessee Department of Human Services
until the courts decide who should take care of them.
   The children had continued to attend school for several days
after their father was deployed. A member of Savaiki's unit who
checked on the children Wednesday notified authorities.
   ``There is no way those kids should be in the house without
parental supervision after dark,'' Poor said. ``What if a burglar
broke in or a fire started?''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0059 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 1741EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BRF--RomerApology     09-02 0190</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Romer Apology,0194</SECOND>
<HEAD>Romer Writes Apology to Eagle Scouts</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DENVER (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Gov. Roy Romer sent a handwritten apology to two
New Jersey boy scouts who heard the governor lose his temper on a
talk radio show last week when he was criticized for not
congratulating them.
   ``I am writing to you personally so that you may understand my
attitude and feelings about your personal achievement of becoming
Eagle Scouts and about the way my office handled the issue,'' Romer
said in the letter Friday to Douglas Baker Jr., 14, and Derek
Edmund, 17, of Oradell, N.J.
   ``I honor them highly, and it's unfortunate that we got this
confused with my views of the techniques of talk radio,'' Romer
said Saturday. ``I certainly regret any anger that got out.''
   Romer cut loose with a 20-minute tirade on station KOA on
Wednesday when he was criticized for refusing to send a letter of
commendation to the two Boy Scouts.
   Talk show host George Weber invited the public to write letters
addressed to ``Stingy Roy.''
   Romer said his office did not generally send letters of
commendation to citizens of other states.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0060 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 1741EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-PennyRevenge     09-02 0224</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Penny Revenge,0229</SECOND>
<HEAD>Subway Riders Find Pennies To Be Useful Weapons</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Sydnye is cq in 3rd graf.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   New Yorkers are giving their 2 cents worth to
the city's subway system _ nearly 1 million pennies a week, in
fact, to purchase ride tokens.
   Clerks and Transit Authority officials say some people are
flooding token booth clerks with pennies in revenge for a recent
15-cent fare hike and what they perceive as poor service.
   ``You can tell because they come down the stairs with a smile on
their face, shaking a fist full of pennies,'' said token clerk
Sydnye Thomas. ``They put the handful of pennies in the slot and
turn their head and laugh.''
   The pennies slow the work of the clerks. Longer lines at token
booths have become common since the cost of a token rose in January
from $1 to $1.15.
   The Transit Authority, which operates the subways, is getting so
many pennies that it is now the largest depositor of pennies with
the Federal Reserve, The New York Times reported Sunday.
   The number of pennies received by token clerks increased from
300,000 a week to about 950,000 a week after the January price
boost.
   Signs at token booths read, ``No pennies,'' but the signs add,
``Please,'' because pennies are legal currency and cannot be
refused.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0061 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 1750EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Gulf-Iraq-Rationing     09-02 0492</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Iraq-Rationing,0510</SECOND>
<HEAD>Iraq Would Rather Eat Mud Than Capitulate, Official Says</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf Rdp, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TERRY LEONARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BAGHDAD, Iraq (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The government Sunday acknowleged it was
rationing food but said Iraqis would rather eat mud than bow to a
foreign power.
   Government spokesman Naji Al-Hadithi denied reports that the
U.N. embargo on Iraq caused shortages but said the government was
instituting steps to reduce food consumption.
   ``We have a war-tested society. We have a war-tested economy. So
even if we eat mud, we will resist pressure and not kneel down to
any foreign power,'' he said.
   Last week, sources inside Iraq said rationing was to begin Sept.
1, and foreigners who left the country reported lines for bread and
other food.
   The U.N. embargo enforced by a flotilla of U.S. and other
warships has halted nearly all of Iraq's vital oil exports and food
imports, aiming to force an Iraqi pullout from Kuwait.
   Al-Hadithi and Information and Culture Minister Latif Nasaif
Jasim took a defiant stance in a meeting with reporters Sunday,
saying Iraq wanted peace, but was prepared for war.
   Jasim claimed Iraq, which fought an eight-year war with Iran,
was not afraid of war with the United States, which deployed tens
of thousands of troops in the Saudi desert after Iraq invaded
Kuwait a month ago.
   He said his country had 1.5 million men under arms and 5.5
million volunteers ready to fight.
   ``During the war with Iran, hundreds of American-made planes
darkened our skies, and even our children used to throw rocks at
these planes,'' Jasim said. ``So if Bush wants to stay in power, he
will pull out his soldiers and not make war.''
   ``We need only bread and water. We need no more than that. We
can live for a long time,'' said Jasim. ``Dignity is more important
than food.''
   Under a plan organized by the ruling Ba'ath Party, stores will
limit the quantity of certain products that can be sold at one
time, al-Hadithi said.
   ``If you need one kilogram (2.2 pounds) of rice, you will be
allowed two but not 10. In the past, you could get 20,'' he said.
   The plan, he said, is a precaution prompted by the U.N.
sanctions but not a response to any spot shortages.
   ``We are determined to live on our own cultivation,'' said
Al-Hadithi. ``Iraq reached self-sufficiency in vegetables and fruit
during the war with Iran.''
   He said production of rice and wheat were up significantly, and
that the government had taken steps to encourage farmers to put
more land into cultivation.
   Two food store owners in Baghdad, Iraq's capital, said they had
been told the rationing plan would limit purchases of such items as
rice, sugar, tea, cooking oil, baby food, detergent and soap.
   ``We really don't think about this. I'm not hoarding. Everything
is here. We are not worried about it,'' said one shopper, who
declined to give her name.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0062 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 1839EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Amnesty-Cambodia     09-02 0477</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Amnesty-Cambodia,0491</SECOND>
<NOTE>For Release 8 p.m. EDT, TIME set by source.</NOTE>
<HEAD>Amnesty Accuses Khmer Rouge of Massacre in Train Attacks</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Kompong Chhnang is cq. Monday is also cq in lead.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>BANGKOK, Thailand (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Amnesty International on Monday accused
communist guerrillas of massacring more than 50 people in two train
attacks in central Cambodia.
   In a statement, the international human rights group urged the
Cambodian guerrilla coalition, which includes the communist Khmer
Rouge, to ensure that those involved in the killings ``are removed
from their positions and brought to justice.''
   Amnesty International said the victims apparently were singled
out because they were employees of the Vietnamese-installed
government in Phnom Penh.
   ``At least 26 people were rounded up and shot dead when a train
was ambushed and stopped in Kompong Trach on July 1, and at least
30 others died in a similar incident in Kompong Chhnang on July
15,'' the statement said.
   At Amnesty International's London headquarters, an official said
the information came from sources who have been in contact with
people in Cambodia. He said the sources could not be identified.
   In previous reports, Western journalists have quoted injured
survivors at Phnom Penh hospitals as saying the guerrillas killed
several civilians in the July 15 attack. The survivors said land
mines crippled the train before the Khmer Rouge struck with grenade
launchers and machine guns.
   At the time, the Khmer Rouge radio said the guerrillas killed 15
soldiers and wounded 15 others but made no mention of civilian
casualities.
   The Cambodian government's official SPK news agency reported on
July 16 that robbers had killed more than 100 passengers and taken
their property in an attack on a train in Kompong Trach.
   The news agency said Gen. Tea Banh, the defense minister,
mentioned the raid while speaking two days earlier about the fight
against the guerrillas.
   It was not possible to determine whether the SPK report was
referring to the killings cited by Amnesty International. SPK did
not specifically mention the Khmer Rouge or give the date of the
attack. Some claims by the Phnom Penh government have been
exaggerated.
   In the past, the United States and Amnesty International have
also accused the Phnom Penh government of serious human rights
abuses.
   The city of Kompong Chhnang, the capital of the province of the
same name, is about 50 miles northwest of Phnom Penh. Kompong Trach
is about 60 miles east of the Cambodian capital.
   The Khmer Rouge slaughtered hundreds of thousands of people in
rural slave labor camps and execution chambers when it held power
from 1975-78. Vietnam installed the current communist government
after its forces invaded Phnom Penh in late 1978.
   The Khmer Rouge, supported by China, now is allied with two
non-communist groups in the guerrilla coalition _ the U.S.-backed
forces of Prince Norodom Sihanouk and Son Sann's Khmer People's
National Liberation Front.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0063 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 1839EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Gulf-EgyptianBribe     09-02 0249</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Egyptian Bribe,0254</SECOND>
<HEAD>Former Nixon Adviser Says Saddam Offered $25 Million Bribe To
Mubarak</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf Rdp</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PROVIDENCE, R.I. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A former presidential adviser said he
has solid information that Iraqi leader Saddam Hussein offered
Egyptian President Hosni Mubarak a $25 million bribe to try to keep
Egypt neutral in the Persian Gulf crisis.
   ``Saddam Hussein had $25 million placed in an Egyptian bank
account, for Mubarak's use,'' Rabbi Baruch Korff said in an
interview published in the Providence Sunday Journal.
   Korff said Saddam also offered to share with Mubarak the spoils
of dividing up Kuwait, which Iraq invaded Aug. 2, as well as Saudi
Arabia and other Persian Gulf sheikdoms.
   Korff, a former adviser to President Nixon, has just returned
from a seven-week tour of the Mideast. Korff frequently travels to
the region on official and unofficial missions for the U.S.
government. He said he could not divulge the source of his
information or the nature of his most recent trip.
   Korff said others, including Sen. Frank R. Lautenberg, D-N.J.,
have heard Mubarak discuss the alleged bribe.
   Lautenberg's press secretary, Steve Schlein, said Friday that
the senator met with Mubarak during a visit to Egypt 10 days ago.
He said Mubarak said Saddam had attempted to bribe him, but didn't
mention the amount.
   ``We cannot comment on this because we have no other
information,'' said Mohamad Amr of the Egyptian Embassy in
Washington. ```We have not been privy to discussions between the
senator and President Mubarak.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0064 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 1841EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-GainesvilleSlayings 1stLd-Writethru a0713 09-02 0862</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gainesville Slayings, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0713,0884</SECOND>
<HEAD>Police Narrow Prime Suspect List to 4 in Campus Slayings</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 3rd graf with 2 grafs to UPDATE with police searching
creek beside Humphrey's apartment complex; picks up 4th graf pvs,
`An Ohio ...' SUBS 10th grav pvs, `Autopsy results ...,' to CORRECT
victim's name to `Tracy,' sted `Tracey.' ADDS 3 grafs at end to
UPDATE with comment from university; no pickup.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By CURT ANDERSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>GAINESVILLE, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Investigators narrowed their list of
prime suspects to four Sunday in the grisly knife slayings of five
students and hinted that the serial killer left ``messages of some
importance.''
   Police would not say whether 18-year-old Edward Lewis Humphrey,
a part-time freshman at the University of Florida charged with
assaulting his grandmother, was among the four.
   However, two police officers in hip waders on Sunday used a
metal detector to search a creek next to the apartment complex
where Humphrey lives.
   They did not appear to find anything, said police Cpl. Robert
McDowell. Police have already picked over garbage in the complex's
trash containers, but have not said whether they recovered a murder
weapon.
   An Ohio fugitive, 58-year-old Warren Virgil Tinch, was dropped
from the list, said Alachua County Sheriff's spokesman Lt. Spencer
Mann. Tinch is sought in Ohio in the stabbing death of a
52-year-old woman and is suspected of stealing cars in Ocala and
Gainesville a week before the killings.
   ``To say he's still a suspect (in the slayings) would be
incorrect,'' Mann said. But he said police were not prepared to say
who is on the list.
   A week after the first two mutilated bodies were found, police
disclosed Sunday that the killer left messages or clues at the
victims' apartments that could tie him to all five murders. But
they refused to characterize these messages except to say they were
not in the form of notes or other writings.
   ``The messages were given to us from the crime scenes,'' said
Lt. Sadie Darnell, spokeswoman for the Gainesville Police
Department. ``The messages are indirect (ones) that we're
interpreting to be messages of some importance.''
   Mann added that no ``calling cards'' were found on any of the
bodies.
   ``It's not a signature-type homicide,'' Mann said.
   Autopsy results on Tracy Inez Paules and Manuel Taboada, both
23, showed they died of stab wounds similar to those that killed
the other three, Mann said Sunday. But unlike the first three, the
bodies of Miss Paules and Taboada were not mutilated.
   Mann declined to say whether the same weapon was used in all
five slayings.
   Miss Paules and Taboada were found Tuesday at the apartment they
shared at the same complex where Humphrey lived for a few weeks
this summer. A neighbor said Humphrey was romantically interested
in Miss Paules and often waited for her by the pool.
   Also killed were Christina Powell, 17, of Jacksonville; Sonya
Larson, 18, of Deerfield Beach; and Christa Hoyt, 18, of Newberry.
   All five lived at off-campus apartments on the city's southwest
side and all were students at either the University of Florida or
Sante Fe Community College.
   Most of the University of Florida's 34,000 students were gone
over the weekend for the Labor Day holiday. Many who stayed
attended church services Sunday to mourn for the victims.
   ``I pray we're not so gripped by fear that we're afraid to go
out and meet people,'' Drew Settimio told the congregation at
Crossroads Church of Christ, which included many students. ``I pray
the fear of our community will be eased.''
   Humphrey, an Indialantic youth authorities have described as
emotionally troubled, remained in the Brevard County Jail on Sunday
pending a $1 million bond on charges of assaulting his 79-year-old
grandmother. Police kept up surveillance at his Gainesville
apartment and car in Indialantic but still have not sought search
warrants to check them out.
   To do so, a judge would have to rule that there is enough
evidence to show probable cause of Humphrey's involvement in the
crimes.
   ``We're not going to do anything to jeopardize this case,'' Mann
said. ``We're going to do it right. We're going to do it by the
book.''
   Brevard County Public Defender R.J. Russo said he was puzzled as
to why no search warrants had been sought and said he planned to
ask Tuesday for a reduction in Humphrey's bond.
   Up to 18 investigators flew Saturday and Sunday to at least nine
other states to follow up on tips and leads related to the
slayings, Darnell said. The states were California, New York,
Oregon, Montana, Alabama, Louisiana, Mississippi, Tennessee and
Nevada, although Darnell would not name specific towns.
   University President John Lombardi said Sunday that school will
continue as usual when it reopens Tuesday, except for continued
escort services, increased security and extended deadlines for
students to withdraw from or change classes.
   So far, about 100 students have decided either to transfer or
sit out a semester because of the slayings, Lombardi said.
   ``We believe this community to be as safe as any other
university community in America,'' he said. ``Would I send my child
back to the University of Florida? Yes, I would.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0065 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 1844EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Lebanon-Blast     09-02 0169</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lebanon-Blast,0174</SECOND>
<HEAD>Car Bomb Kills Four in South Lebanon</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TYRE, Lebanon (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A car bomb exploded on the main seaside
highway entrance to this southern Lebanese port city Sunday,
killing at least four people and injuring three, police said.
   The car, a black Toyota packed with 110 pounds of TNT, was
parked about 15 yards from a checkpoint manned by militiamen of the
pro-Syrian Amal movement when it exploded at 7:30 p.m., said a
police spokesman under condition of anonymity.
   Two Amal militiamen and two people passing in the street were
killed. Two other bystanders and one Amal irregular were wounded,
police said.
   There was no immediate claim of responsibility for the bombing.
   This was the seventh car bomb in Lebanon this year and the
second in Tyre in a month. In all, 14 people have been killed and
106 wounded in the explosions.
   The deadliest car bomb was on Aug 3. Eight people were killed
and 75 were injured when the bomb went off in Tyre.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0066 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 1849EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-US-Gulf 1stLd-Writethru a0702 09-02 0944</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-US-Gulf, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0702,950</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush Sees Challenges Ahead as He Prepares for Soviet Summit</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: Grafs 9-15 new to UPDATE with White House not commenting on
magazine report of planned covert operation; responses from
congressional leaders. SUBS grafs 15-16 pvs, bgng: `Meanwhile, Sen.
Sam ...,' to conform. Pickup 17th graf pvs, bgng: ``Right now,
while ...''</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By TOM RAUM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>KENNEBUNKPORT, Maine (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush said Sunday
``challenging times'' lie ahead as he prepared for next weekend's
summit with Soviet President Mikhail Gorbachev and began a second
month of trying to force Saddam Hussein out of Kuwait.
   As the president was winding up his three-week vacation in
Maine, a group of four-dozen American women and children arrived in
Washington aboard an Iraqi airliner after being freed from
captivity, telling tales of harsh treatment and deprivation.
   One month after the Iraqi invasion of Kuwait, an estimated
11,000 Westerners remained trapped there and in Iraq, including
about 3,000 Americans.
   ``A week from now, perhaps at this minute, I will be sitting in
Helsinki, Finland, talking with President (Mikhail) Gorbachev.
These are challenging times,'' Bush said at one of two church
services he attended here along with the evangelist, Rev. Billy
Graham.
   The president, who was to return to Washington on Monday
evening, discussed summit preparations and recent Persian Gulf
developments with his national security adviser, Brent Scowcroft,
aides said.
   Bush announced the one-day meeting in Helsinki, Finland _ to be
his third as president with Gorbachev _ on Saturday. And although
the president said there was no set agenda, aides on Sunday said
the Middle East crisis clearly would top the discussion.
   White House spokesman Marlin Fitzwater said Bush and Gorbachev
would talk about the Middle East, discuss ways of speeding up
negotiations on reaching an agreement on conventional force
reductions in Europe this fall and go over several regional hot
spots, including Afghanistan and Cambodia.
   Although Moscow has expressed only lukewarm support for the
U.S.-led military force in the Persian Gulf region, Bush generally
has been ``very pleased with the support of the Soviet Union'' on
Persian Gulf policy, Fitzwater said.
   The White House refused to comment on a published report that
Bush had approved a covert operation to overthrow Saddam.
Congressional leaders said they knew nothing of the matter.
   Newsweek magazine, in its Sept. 3 issue, said Saudi Arabia was
preparing to fund the effort by the CIA and other western
intelligence agencies. The magazine said the conduit for the money
will be the Saudi ambassador to the United States, Prince Bandar
bin Sultan.
   ``I would truthfully say that I do not know now,'' said Sen. Sam
Nunn, D-Ga., who chairs the Senate Armed Services Committee,
adding, ``if I did know, I wouldn't be able to tell you. ...''
   But Nunn, in an interview on NBC-TV's ``Meet the Press,'' said
he hopes the United States will begin ``working with our friends in
the (Persian Gulf) area to make his (Saddam's) position in Kuwait
untenable.''
   Senate Minority Leader Robert Dole of Kansas and House Majority
Thomas S. Foley of Washington also said during television
appearances that they knew nothing of a planned covert operation.
   On the CBS-TV program ``Face the Nation,'' Dole said, ``I don't
have any information on that at all....''
   During the same program, Foley declined ``either to confirm or
deny'' the report or discuss it.
   In Washington, the Kuwait Embassy promised financial assistance
to American families facing money problems because of Iraq's
holding of hostages in Kuwait.
   ``We stand ready, willing and are able to share in the costs,
whatever we are asked for by these families,'' Kuwaiti Ambassador
Sheikh Saud Nasir al-Sabah said.
   After arriving Sunday at Washington-Dulles International
Airport, one of the freed American hostages, Lloyd Culbertson, 76,
of El Paso, Texas, said some of the Americans left behind were
being held without food and water.
   ``If it were not for the grace of God and Jesse Jackson, we
would not be here. The State Department has not lifted a hand for
us,'' Culbertson said.
   Jackson, who helped arrange the flight, told reporters at Dulles
``Now that the military has played its role, diplomacy must work.
If preconditions make talks impossible, war is inevitable.''
   Jackson appealed to the Iraqi government to turn on the water
and power in the U.S. Embassy in Kuwait to prevent food from
spoiling in the next few days. Traveling as a television
journalist, Jackson met twice last week with the Iraqi president.
   Meanwhile, Nunn said during his television appearance that ``the
worst case for us would be a protracted ground war.''
   Nunn said he would be opposed to any offensive move by U.S.
troops at this time.
   ``Right now, while the U.S. has an advantage in the air and sea,
he (Saddam) still has the advantage on the ground,'' Nunn said.
   Regarding next weekend's summit, Nunn said he hoped the United
States and Soviet Union could reach an agreement that would help
deny Saddam ``the ability to wage war of mass destruction.''
   He suggested that the Soviets _ who long have been Baghdad's
main arms supplier _ deny further weapons to the Iraqis.
   With Graham in tow, Bush made the rounds of two church services
in Kennebunkport on Sunday.
   After introducing Graham, a longtime friend and fishing
companion, at the first service at the Kennebunkport Congregational
Church, Bush spoke briefly about the current Middle East crisis.
``These are very interesting times,'' he told the congregation.
   At the second church service, at St. Ann's Episcopal Church,
Bush told worshipers: ``These are rather trying times and right
know I would suggest that we get our strength from being one nation
under God.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0067 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 1850EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-FreakFire     09-02 0259</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Freak Fire,0265</SECOND>
<HEAD>Two-headed Calf, World's Largest Calf Perish in Blaze</HEAD>
<DATELINE>KISSIMMEE, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A two-headed calf, a boar rat whose teeth
would not stop growing and all 550 pounds of what proprietors
declared the world's largest clam perished in a museum fire this
weekend.
   More than 500 displays of human and animal oddities, wonders of
the deep and instruments of death, the occult and superstition were
destroyed Saturday in a fire at the Great American Fun House,
officials said.
   While the calf and clam were dead long before flames engulfed
the oddities museum in this town south of Orlando, charred placards
in the windows note that all the exhibits had once, in fact, been
``BORN ALIVE!!!''
   ``A lot of those things were one of a kind, Ripley's kind of
stuff,'' said museum proprietor Vinnie Lamano at the fire scene.
``There were many things here that you'll never see again.''
   Lamano and oddities collector Mark Frierson _ creator of the
syndicated cartoon ``STRANGER THAN FICTION!!!'' _ opened their
shrine to the bizarre inside a former surf shop 10 months ago.
   Arson investigators sifted through debris that included a
shrunken head, the shoes of an Icelandic giant purported to be the
largest man ever and some bones the museum said were used by
Aborigine witch doctors to kill enemies without touching them.
   ``It was kind of a bizarre scene, come to think of it,'' said
Kissimmee Fire Cmdr. Cleve Thomason, who estimated structural
damage at between $60,000 and $120,000.
   The fire's cause, Thomason said, remained _ a mystery!!!
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0068 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 1854EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-Israel     09-02 0256</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Israel,0266</SECOND>
<HEAD>Israeli Officials Say Saddam Must Be Destroyed</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GWEN ACKERMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Israeli officials said Sunday that any
political solution to the Persian Gulf crisis that leaves Saddam
Hussein in power means Iraq will remain a danger to world stability.
   Yossi Olmert, head of the Government Press Office, said it would
be disastrous if President Saddam remained in power, considering
his plans to develop nuclear weapons.
   ``Such a resolution will not be as we would like it, and it
shouldn't be to the liking of the U.S. ... nor to the Arab world,''
Olmert said on Israel radio.
   He added that, at the least, Iraq's armed forces, which invaded
oil-rich Kuwait one month ago, should be damaged to the point where
Saddam's ambitions are blocked ``even if the man stays alive, at
least for a period of time.''
   Israel's military is on heightened alert, but officials also
have said Israel has no plans to attack Iraq unless attacked first.
   In 1981, Israeli warplanes destroyed an Iraqi nuclear reactor
believed to be developing an atomic bomb.
   Justice Minister Dan Meridor, who also spoke on the radio, said
Saddam must not be allowed even part of his ``war spoils.''
   Several other Israeli officials, including Defense Minister
Moshe Arens and Air Force Commander Maj. Gen. Avihu Bin-Nun, have
suggested that the gulf crisis must end with Saddam's ouster.
   Olmert and Meridor both said Sunday their statements were not
intended as advice to President Bush, who has not said he seeks
Saddam's ouster.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0069 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 1905EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Crime 1stLd-Writethru a0686 09-02 0613</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Crime, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0686,580</SECOND>
<HEAD>One of Four Households Hit by Crimes Last Year</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: SUBS 10th graf pvs, bgng, `As for households ...,' to CORRECT
decrease to rise in violent crimes for caucasian households. Pickup
11th graf pvs.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By CAROLYN SKORNECK</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A violent crime or property crime hit one in
four U.S. households last year, virtually the same level as the
past five years, a Justice Department report said Sunday.
   ``In 1975, when this statistical series commenced, about one in
three households was struck by crime,'' said Steven Dillingham,
director of the Bureau of Justice Statistics which produced the
report.
   The actual percentage of households that suffered a violent
crime or property crime was 24.9 percent, up slightly from 24.6
percent in 1988, the report found. The figures include attempted as
well as completed crimes.
   A total of 23.5 million households suffered from one of the
crimes checked: rape, assault, robbery, personal theft, household
theft, burglary and motor vehicle theft.
   The bureau's figures come from the National Crime Survey, which
annually interviews members of 49,000 households nationwide to
determine crimes to household members who are at least 12 years
old. The NCS does not check for murder, because it compiles its
information from surveys of victims.
   A total of 4.9 percent of households experienced a violent
crime, with 3.9 percent suffering assault, 1 percent robbery and
0.1 percent rape, the survey found. The year before, violent crime
had hit 4.8 percent of homes.
   Meanwhile, 17.8 percent of households suffered from some kind of
theft, including 11.2 percent personal theft and 8.1 percent
household theft; 5.1 percent suffered from a burglary; and 1.6
percent motor vehicle theft.
   Among the survey's findings were that like previous years,
households headed by blacks, urban households and households with
higher incomes suffered a higher percentage of crimes than other
population segments.
   A total of 29.1 percent of all black households suffered from an
NCS crime _ a slight increase from 29 percent in 1988. And 6.4
percent of them suffered from a violent crime, a decrease from 6.6
percent in 1988.
   As for households headed by Caucasians, 24.3 percent suffered
from an NCS crime, up from 23.9 percent the previous year. And 4.7
percent were victimized by a violent crime, a slight rise from 4.6
in 1988.
   Some 25.5 percent of the households of other races combined _
Asians, Pacific Islanders and native Americans _ also suffered from
an NCS crime, down from 27.4 percent in 1988. The percentage of
those homes that suffered from a violent crime also decreased to
5.4 percent from 5.6 percent.
   A separate ethnicity category for Hispanics and non-Hispanics
shows that a greater percentage of Hispanic households suffered an
NCS crime last year than in 1988. Last year, 33.8 percent of
households headed by Hispanics were victims of an NCS crime, up
from 30 percent the previous year. Meanwhile, 7.3 percent of
Hispanic households suffered a violent crime, up from 6.5 percent
in 1988.
   Meanwhile, the percentage of urban households that have been
victims of crime increased from 30.3 percent to 31.2 percent. A
greater number of suburban households also were victimized _ up
from 23.8 percent to 24.2 percent. At the same time, rural
households experienced less crime, with only 17.2 percent
suffering, compared with 18 percent in 1988.
   The portion of households with incomes of $15,000 and above that
suffered from a crime edged downward last year, while crime hit a
larger portion of households with lower incomes than it had in
1988. Still, the households with the highest target rate _ 27
percent _ were those with incomes of $25,000 or more.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0070 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 1906EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BRF--HouseFire     09-02 0182</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--House Fire,0188</SECOND>
<HEAD>Seven Children Hurt as Fire Destroys House</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CONCORD, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A fire Sunday swept though a house that a
family had moved into the day before, injuring seven children, four
of them critically, firefighters said.
   A man who tried to rescue the youngsters _ five siblings and
their two cousins _ also was treated for smoke inhalation. The
children, ranging in age from 3 to 17, were found in bedrooms and a
hallway.
   The adults were not at home when the fire was reported Sunday
morning, and crews were already battling the fire when they
returned, said spokesmen for the Contra Costa Consolidated Fire
District.
   Shames Rahmany, 3, and Habiba Rahmany, his 17-year-old sister,
were in ``very critical'' condition with smoke inhalation, a
hospital spokeswoman said. Two girls, 9-year-old Samea Rahmany and
her cousin, Aesha Rahimi, 6, were in critical condition.
   Three other children were in fair condition with smoke
inhalation.
   The fire, believed to have started in the master bedroom, gutted
the house, which the Rahmany family had moved into Saturday. The
cause was under investigation.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0071 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 1948EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ChemicalSpill     09-02 0230</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Chemical Spill,0240</SECOND>
<HEAD>Chemical Spill From Overturned Tanker Forces Evacuation Of 300</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ASHVILLE, Ala. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A tanker truck overturned and spilled
hundreds of gallons of a toxic, highly combustible chemical early
Sunday, forcing about 300 people out of their homes and closing an
interstate highway.
   The 18-wheeler careened off Interstate 59 about 35 miles
northeast of Birmingham around 1:30 a.m., said state Department of
Public Safety spokesma Jim Hyatt.
   The driver, Earl Gavin, 51, of Independence, Mo., was trapped in
the wreckage for nine hours, Hyatt said. He was hospitalized in
Birmingham in fair condition.
   Authorities evacuated about 300 residents of the nearby Pinedale
Shores subdivision, and opened an emergency shelter at the National
Guard armory in Ashville.
   Traffic on I-59 was forced to detour, and the highway was not
expected to reopen until late Sunday, Hyatt said.
   The tanker, owned by Continental Transport Express of Geismar,
La., was carrying aniline, a chemical used to make dyes and
photographic chemicals, Hyatt said. About 500 to 800 gallons leaked
from the truck, which was carrying 3,500 to 5,000 gallons, he said.
   The chemical is irritating to the skin and lungs and is highly
flammable, Hyatt said.
   About two dozen firefighters from several communities
experienced some skin irritation during the cleanup, which was
completed Sunday afternoon, Hyatt said.
   The evacuees were expected to be allowed to return home Sunday
evening.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0072 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 1951EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Slayings-University     09-02 0318</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Slayings-University,0330</SECOND>
<HEAD>Universityi President Stresses Business as Usual</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gainesville Slayings</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CURT ANDERSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>GAINESVILLE, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Despite lingering fear over the murders
of five students, the University of Florida will be back in
business Tuesday when students return from the Labor Day holiday,
the school's president said Sunday.
   ``The University of Florida will be in full operation this
week,'' John Lombardi said.
   As of Sunday only about 100 of the university's 34,000 students
had decided to drop out for the semester or transfer because of the
unsolved slayings, Lombardi said.
   ``We believe this community to be as safe as any other
university community in America,'' he said. ``Would I sent my child
back to the University of Florida? Yes, I would.''
   University officials said security would continue at a
heightened level on campus, including night escort services and
sleeping arrangements for students afraid to stay alone at night.
   Academic work missed by students last week can be made up, and
deadlines to drop or add classes will be extended to Friday,
Lombardi said. Financial aid recipients who leave school won't lose
their aid for the next semester, he added.
   ``We have made a commitment that nobody is to be penalized,'' he
said.
   Student body President Michael Browne said most of his
classmates remain fearful over the killings, particularly since no
arrest has been made.
   ``I'm afraid every night. Not because of the actions of one
person but because my sense of innocence, my sense of personal
security has been invaded,'' Browne said.
   But like Lombardi, he urged students to return when classes
resume.
   ``Above all, we must not be held hostage to our fears,'' he
said. ``Giving up now will not solve anything.''
   Four of the victims were students at the university; the fifth
studied at Santa Fe Community College. Police said Sunday they now
have four prime suspects in the case.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0073 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 2012EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--Albanians     09-02 0140</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Albanians,0144</SECOND>
<HEAD>20 Albanians Flee to Yugoslavia</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BELGRADE, Yugoslavia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Twenty Albanians, mostly young
people, have crossed illegally into Yugoslavia, the national news
agency Tanjug reported Sunday.
   They defected near the Yugoslav town of Plav, the report said.
It did not give the date of their crossing or further details.
   Tanjug said about 50 Albanians illegally crossed into Yugoslavia
in July.
   The crossings were mostly made in small groups at night. The
refugees cited hard life and inability to support their families as
the main reasons for their escape, the report added.
   More than 4,000 Albanians who fled into Western embassies in
Tirana, the Albanian capital, earlier this summer were allowed to
leave for the West. But authorities have since put up a wall around
the embassy district.
   Albania is the last hard-line Communist nation in Eastern Europe.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0074 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 2030EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Gulf-AmericansHome 3rdLd-Writethru a0709 09-02 0855</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Americans Home, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0709,850</SECOND>
<HEAD>Some Hostages Return Home, One Says He Nearly Starved</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 22nd graf pvs, bgng: `One of the passengers ...,' with
3
grafs to UPDATE with name of woman taken to hospital. Pickup 23rd
graf pvs. Anderton is cq</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By W. DALE NELSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Four-dozen Americans reclaimed their freedom
Sunday, liberated from Saddam Hussein's clutches and grateful to be
back home. ``I wasn't a guest,'' said Lloyd Culbertson. ``I damned
near starved to death.''
   The 47 Americans, weary from 24 hours of travel and their weeks
as unofficial prisoners of war, arrived at Washington-Dulles
International Airport aboard an Iraqi jetliner cleared to land only
for this homecoming flight.
   Just a handful of the passengers talked with reporters; most
cleared customs and left the airport quietly with relatives. A U.S.
official said 24 women, 11 men and 12 children arrived but declined
to identify them, citing privacy laws.
   The Americans who were held in Kuwait, which was overrun by
Iraqi soldiers on Aug. 2, brought ominous word that Saddam
Hussein's forces may be mistreating Americans left behind.
   Culbertson, 76, of El Paso, Texas, said some of the hostages
were being held without food and without water. He did not provide
details. Culbertson took issue with Iraqi Ambassador Mohamed Sadiq
al-Mashat's insistence that hostages were treated well as
``guests'' of Saddam: ``The ambassador from Iraq is dead wrong.''
   ``If it were not for the grace of God and Jesse Jackson, we
would not be here. The State Department has not lifted a hand for
us,'' said Culbertson, who told reporters he has taught electronics
to the Kuwaiti military for 5{ years. Jackson, on a trip to
Baghdad, helped arrange freedom for some of the hostages.
   The Iraqi Airlines Boeing 747 was one of three jetliners to
leave Baghdad Airport on Saturday. The flights carried hundreds of
foreign women and children who left their husbands and fathers
behind.
   A photographer who accompanied Jackson, D. Michael Cheers, said
about eight of the women in the group arriving here were pregnant.
Cheers said the men who were brought along were chosen because of
medical problems.
   Cheers said those trapped at the embassy burned furniture as
firewood and boiled water from the swimming pool for drinking.
   Culbertson described meals as ``pretty skimpy rations'' _ mainly
frozen turkey. ``I have never eaten so much turkey in my life.''
   Asked if the people left behind feared for their lives,
Culbertson said, ``Yes, they certainly do.''
   Bonnie Anderton left her husband, Richard, after an emotional
parting in Kuwait. She said they talked about sending their
10-year-old daughter, Jennifer, home alone but decided against it
because Mrs. Anderton needs medical treatment. She declined to say
what the treatment was.
   She said the Americans slept on the floor, had no water or
power, and Iraqi troops often fired shots nearby the U.S. Embassy
compound during the day.
   Anderton said her family had been in Kuwait for three months,
the final weeks in turmoil after Iraqi soldiers stormed the
kingdom. Her husband was working as an engineer.
   ``I think Jennifer will agree with me: Next summer we are going
to Disneyland,'' she said.
   Ed Johnson, a businessman from St. Louis, said he sought refuge
in the embassy Aug. 17 at the suggestion of diplomats there.
Johnson, who waved an American flag as he arrived, said he phoned
his wife, ``and she cried and I cried.''
   The situation for Americans in Baghdad was slightly better, said
Beth Krekelel of St. Louis, who was taken to a hotel in the Iraqi
capital and then to the U.S. Embassy there.
   ``I have had an enjoyable time. I have had a cross-cultural
experience,'' said Krekelel, who was teaching English in Iraq.
   Relatives greeted the tired travelers, who made their way
through customs at Dulles, which is located in a Virginia suburb of
Washington.
   A State Department official, who spoke on condition of
anonymity, said there were no plans to debrief the Americans, and
``they're free to go home.''
   ``From what we've seen, they don't seem to be in particularly
difficult shape. They've obviously been through a long flight, a
big ordeal,'' the spokesman said.
   One of the arriving passengers, a woman, was put on an ambulance
and taken to a local hospital. A Texarkana, Texas, newspaper
identified her as Odessa Higgins of Texarkana.
   The Texarkana Gazette quoted sources as saying the woman had
suffered a broken hip during an auto accident while she and her
husband, Bobby Higgins, were traveling in a convoy trying to reach
the Jordanian border.
   Attempts to reach family members Sunday night were unsuccessful.
   Jackson, following two meetings with Iraq's president last week,
arranged for more than 100 foreigners to leave Baghdad on Saturday.
He told reporters the Iraqis fear a U.S. military strike.
   ``Now that the military has played its role, diplomacy must
work. If preconditions make talks impossible, war is inevitable,''
Jackson said.
   al-Mashat, the Iraqi ambassador, was among those greeting the
ex-hostages. He said he was there to check on the Iraqi flight
crew, and to make sure the Americans were comfortable.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0075 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 2032EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Gulf-Foreigners 1stLd-Writethru a0719 09-02 0776</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Foreigners, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0719,0796</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hundreds Of Women, Children Freed; East German Ambassador Taken To
Iraq</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS thruout to UPDATE with Iraq withholding landing
permission for flights from Britain and France to pick up hostages;
EDITS to trim; pickup 10th graf pvs `The son...'</NOTE>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf Rdp, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Hundreds of Western women and children held hostage by Iraq,
including some who served as human shields to deter any U.S.
attack, arrived back home Sunday after flights from Iraq.
   But the departure of several hundred more Western women and
children from Baghdad was apparently delayed as Iraq withheld
landing clearance for special flights from Britain and France.
   In addition, thousands of other hostages, including husbands and
fathers of those allowed to leave, remained trapped in Iraq and
occupied Kuwait with no immediate prospect of leaving.
   East Germany's ambassador in Kuwait was said to have been taken
forcibly to Iraq after leaving his compound, which has been
besieged by Iraqi troops along with the U.S. and other embassies.
   The East Berlin government was negotiating with Iraq for the
release of Ambassador Kurt Merkel, 56, a government spokesman said
on condition of anonymity.
   Also Sunday, about 12,000 mostly Arab and Asian refugees
streamed from Iraq into Jordan, where tens of thousands of
impoverished evacuees already languish in refugee camps. Thousands
were trying to cross into Turkey and Iran.
   Totals provided by various airlines and diplomats indicated that
nearly 700 Westerners and Japanese were allowed to leave Iraq over
the weekend.
   In all, about 21,000 Westerners, including 3,000 Americans, were
trapped in Iraq and Kuwait by the Aug. 2 Iraqi invasion of its
oil-rich neighbor.
   In London, a spokesman for Virgin Atlantic Airways said the
airline had been planning a special flight to Baghdad on Monday
after hearing from British diplomatic sources that about 200 more
Western women and children, including some Americans, would be
ready to leave.
   But the spokesman said the airline received a telex Sunday
afternoon from Iraqi civil aviation authorities revoking landing
clearance.
   In Paris, the French Foreign Ministry said Iraqi authorities so
far have not granted landing permission for an Air France Airbus
that has been on standby at Le Bourget airport north of Paris. The
plane had been scheduled to fly to Baghdad on Monday morning to
pick up Western hostages, the French news agency AFP said.
   French news reports said the delay was caused by bickering over
the timing of the flight, with the Iraqis insisting that the plane
not arrive at night or in the early morning.
   British and French officials said they had asked their embassies
in Baghdad to continue pressing the Iraqis to allow the flights to
land.
   If that is not possible, a British Foreign Office spokesman said
hostages could return home on Iraqi Airways, even though regularly
scheduled flights by the Iraqi carrier are banned under the U.N.
trade embargo.
   A chartered Iraqi Airways Boeing 747 that left Baghdad with more
than 300 Westerners, including 47 Americans, arrived outside
Washington on Sunday after stopovers in Paris and London to
disembark passengers.
   Civil rights leader Jesse Jackson helped arrange the flight
during his trip to Iraq and Kuwait, and he was aboard the plane
that flew to Washington.
   The son of one of the hostages who landed in London said
passengers spent at least four hours on the Iraqi plane, waiting in
scorching temperatures for Jackson to return from Kuwait with some
Americans before it could take off.
   Nadeem Faheem told Sky Television in Britain: ``There was no
air-conditioning on the plane ... it was absolutely disgusting.''
   Among those arriving in Britain was Stuart Lockwood, the
5-year-old British boy whose hair was tousled by Saddam in a
television encounter with a group of Western hostages last month.
   The jet that arrived in Washington was one of three to leave
Baghdad airport on Saturday. The flights carried hundreds of women
and children and ailing men.
   On Sunday morning, a West German jet carrying 311 women and
children from 22 countries arrived in Frankfurt on a flight from
Baghdad. The West German Foreign Ministry said 250 women and 61
children were aboard the Lufthansa Airbus, including 71 Germans and
60 Americans.
   Salem Saba, a U.S. citizen from Chicago who was on the plane,
left Baghdad with his wife and five small children. He said
conditions had deteriorated in the Iraqi capital.
   ``You get coupons for sugar and for bread,'' he said.
   Later Sunday, 68 Japanese women and children returned to Tokyo
on a flight from Baghdad. Twelve other Japanese women and children,
dependents of diplomats at Japan's Embassy in Baghdad, arrived in
Jordan on Sunday.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0076 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 2032EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p AM-PoliticalBriefs     09-02 0461</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Political Briefs,0483</SECOND>
<HEAD>Political Briefs</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DEERFIELD BEACH, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two independent polls released
Sunday showed former Sen. Lawton Chiles with a comfortable lead
over ex-congressman Bill Nelson going into Tuesday's Democratic
primary for governor of Florida.
   Both polls had Chiles virtually even in polls with Republican
Gov. Bob Martinez.
   The Florida Opinion Poll, published by The New York Times
Florida newspapers, showed Chiles with 44 percent of the Democratic
voters to 32 percent for Nelson, a six-term congressman.
Twenty-four percent were undecided.
   The poll was conducted through random telephone interviews of
842 registered voters Aug. 25-29. Its margin of error was 4 percent.
   The Florida Newspaper Poll published Sunday gave Chiles a 55-30
margin over Nelson, with only 15 percent undecided.
   That poll, for the Sun-Sentinel of Fort Lauderdale, The Orlando
Sentinel and The Florida Times-Union, interviewed 750 registered
voters Aug. 25-27, and had a margin of error of 4 points.
   Sunday's polls gave Martinez landslide margins over his nearest
GOP competitor, state Sen. Marlene Woodson Howard, and also put him
nearly even in a match-up with Chiles.
   The Florida Newspaper Poll gave Chiles a 45-40 lead over
Martinez. The New York Times Newspapers poll indicated Chiles had a
45-41 lead.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>OMAHA, Neb. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Democrat Ben Nelson led incumbent Gov. Kay
Orr by 8 percentage points in a poll for November's gubernatorial
election published Sunday.
   In a survey of 922 registered Nebraska voters conducted for the
Omaha Sunday World-Herald, 44 percent said they would vote for
Nelson, an Omaha attorney, and 36 percent supported Mrs. Orr, the
nation's first elected Republican woman governor.
   Twenty percent didn't know who they would vote for or declined
to answer.
   The margin of error was plus or minus 3 percent, the newspaper
said. The polling was done last week.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>AGANA, Guam, (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Territorial Sen. Madeleine Z. Bordallo won
the Democratic nomination for governor and will face Gov. Joseph
Ada as she seeks to reoccupy the office her late husband lost to
Ada in 1986.
   Mrs. Bordallo garnered 11,240 votes in Saturday's vote to defeat
Lt. Gov. Rudolph G. Sablan, who had 7,511 votes.
   Ada, a Republican, ran unopposed and received 7,986 votes.
   Mrs. Bordallo, a 57-year-old Minnesota native, would become
Guam's first woman governor and the first who is not a native
Guamanian.
   She came to Guam in 1948 when her father accepted a position as
a high school principal. Her husband, the late Gov. Ricardo
Bordallo, was defeated by Ada in 1986 after Bordallo was indicted
for witness tampering and obstruction.
   Last Jan. 31, Bordallo chained himself to a statue, wrapped
himself in Guam's flag and fatally shot himself in the head hours
before he was to fly to Los Angeles to begin serving a four-year
prison term.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0077 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 2118EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Liberia 1stLd-Writethru a0687 09-02 0614</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Liberia, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0687,0625</SECOND>
<HEAD>Report: West African Force Takes Control Capital's Center</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS one graf for 8th `Guerrillas loyal...' to CORRECT that
rival rebel leaders split six months ago sted three; pickup graf 9
`The rebels...'</NOTE>
<DATELINE>ABIDJAN, Ivory Coast (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A multinational West African force
in Liberia took control of the capital's center after battling
rebels loyal to Charles Taylor, the Ghana News Agency reported
Sunday.
   The news agency, which has a correspondent with the 3,000-man
force, quoted Ghanaian Lt. Col. George Ayiku as saying his troops
in Monrovia overcame stiff resistance from the rebels Saturday and
set up heavy artillery.
   On Sunday, a Ghanaian ship left Monrovia with 7,000 refugees but
left 5,000 others behind, the news agency said.
   Taylor's rebels have been accused of killing hundreds of people
from the five West African nations that sent the troops to Liberia
Aug. 24 to end the war, in which about 5,000 people have died. Most
of those killed have been civilians.
   Taylor, who controls most of Liberia after eight months of civil
war, opposes the five-nation force. The force has been welcomed
both by the government of President Samuel Doe and a rival rebel
group, who separately control portions of the capital, Monrovia.
   The Ghana News agency earlier reported that the task force's
units had advanced beyond Spriggs Payne Airfield in eastern
Monrovia in an effort to reach embassies of three of the countries
contributing to the force: Ghana, Nigeria and Guinea. The other two
are Gambia and Sierra Leone.
   Monrovia's 400,000 residents have been without water and
electricity for more than two months, and food stocks were running
low as all regular transport links with the outside world were cut.
   Guerrillas loyal to Prince Johnson, who split from Taylor six
months ago, controlled Monrovia's port and most of the city center.
Areas on the city's eastern fringes were under the control of Doe's
troops, but were under regular attack by Taylor's fighters.
   The rebels accuse the Doe government of corruption and human
rights abuses, but both rebels and troops have reportedly killed
civilians loyal to the other side during the civil war. The
government has accused Taylor of embezzlement when he served as a
Doe aide.
   Taylor's rebels were holding several thousand Ghanaians,
Nigerians and Guinean citizens. Ghanaian refugees accused the
insurgents of killing at least 200 of their countrymen. Taylor has
confirmed holding the foreigners, but denied that his forces had
killed any.
   A Ghanaian merchant ship, the M.V. Tano River, sailed Sunday
with 7,000 Ghanaian and other West African refugees. It was bound
for the Ghanaian capital port of Accra.
   Two women died of malnutrition on board the ship while waiting
for it to depart. Two refugees drowned while trying to climb a rope
to board the ship, the news agency said, after officers said the
ship could take no more passengers. At least 5,000 refugees were
left behind in the port.
   Taylor invaded from Ivory Coast on Dec. 24 and his fighters
quickly overran most of the West African country of about 2.5
million people but were stopped on the outskirts of the capital.
   Johnson, who split with Taylor in February, took control of much
of Monrovia but was unable to drive Doe from his heavily fortified
mansion. U.S. Marines stationed on warships off Liberia have
evacuated Americans and some other foreigners from Monrovia.
Marines also remained posted around the U.S. Embassy. But
Washington says U.S. forces will not intervene in the fighting.
   The five West African countries making up the task force say
they are participating because they have citizens in Liberia and
because 400,000 Liberian refugees are straining the resources of
neighboring countries.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0078 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 2127EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Mohawks 2ndLd-Writethru a0749 09-02 0728</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mohawks, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0749,0745</SECOND>
<HEAD>Army Takes Control Of Barricade, Faces off Mohawk Militants</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS one graf for 8th `The army...' to CORRECT spelling of
Kanesatake; pickup graf 9 `However, when....' ADDS two grafs with
Indian reax across Canada</NOTE>
<DATELINE>OKA, Quebec (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Canadian army seized control of the main
Mohawk barricade in this town on Sunday without firing a shot and
trapped about 30 armed men inside a small wooded area of the
Kanesatake Indian territory.
   Seizing the main barricade at Oka, the center of an Indian
uprising over land claims, effectively ended a standoff that began
July 11 when Quebec provincial police launched a raid on the
militants. One officer was killed, but it is not clear by whose
gunfire.
   Lt. Col. Pierre Daigle, commander of the Canadian Forces in this
sector about 20 miles west of Montreal, said Sunday he had carried
out his instructions to take over the barricades and was awaiting
further orders. He said there are between 350 to 450 troops and 80
armored vehicles in the Oka area.
   However, no fighting broke out between the soldiers and Indians,
who warily watched one another for most of Sunday. Military
helicopters flew over the area.
   Mohawk spokesman Ellen Gabriel said the Indians are ``pretty
squeezed in right now. There's no way out really.''
   The Mohawks fortified their positions by using a front-end
loader to pile earth on a road near a two-story alcohol and drug
detoxification center in the woods.
   After a seven-week standoff, Quebec Premier Robert Bourassa last
week ordered the army to dismantle the barricades.
   The army moved into the Kanesatake Mohawk settlement overlooking
Oka, 18 miles west of Montreal, on Saturday afternoon after
factional fighting broke out between moderate and militant Mohawks.
Two Indians were injured in the fighting before the army moved in.
   However, when the soldiers pushed forward, only one shot was
fired by a Mohawk on Saturday, Daigle said. There were no
casualties.
   Barricades set up in the Kahnawake Mohawk reserve near the
Mercier bridge, south of Montreal, came down peacefully over the
last few days. The barricades were set up as a sympathy protest by
Mohawks there.
   The Warriors, a militant Mohawk organization, periodically came
out from the trees and stood face-to-face with soldiers at Oka on
Sunday. On one occasion, a Warrior approached a soldier, stood
chest-to-chest with him and stared into his eyes as a group of
reporters watched.
   Finally, he let out a war whoop, turned and walked away. ``I
want to see their face before I kill them,'' the Warrior said.
   Just after 8:30 a.m., about two dozen troops backed by two
armored personnel carriers, moved onto Highway 344 and began
approaching the main hilltop barricade. None of the Warriors made a
move to stop them. The soldiers strung barbed wire around the
barricade and inspected it for booby traps.
   Daigle was vague about whether Warriors would be allowed to pass
through his lines and leave if they so desired. The lieutenant
colonel said his forces had no power of arrest.
   ``I have been giving orders to subordinate officers to remain in
their positions and to consolidate where they are,'' he said.
   The uprising began when officials of the village of Oka decided
to expand the local golf course onto land claimed by the Mohawks,
including an Indian cemetery. That problem was solved earlier when
the federal government purchased the land and said it would give it
to the Indians.
   But the Mohawks seized the occasion to press an entire range of
complaints and land claims against federal and provincial
authorities. That move sparked numerous brief sympathy blockades
across the country in recent weeks.
   At the Mercier bridge, troops cleared out the last obstructions
set up seven weeks ago. There was no resistance, but officials said
it would still take several days before the bridge could open to
traffic.
   The Mercier blockade had angered residents of the south shore of
the St. Lawrence River, who were forced to make long detours to get
to jobs in Montreal.
   Across Canada, Indian leaders Sunday denounced the army
operation at Oka.
   ``It was a bungled job all the way, right from the start, and
the Mohawks are not responsible for that _ it's the federal
government and the Quebec government,'' Phil Fontaine, leader of
the Manitoba Assembly of Chiefs, said in Winnipeg.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0079 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 2134EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Gulf-Glance     09-02 0319</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Glance,0334</SECOND>
<HEAD>Persian Gulf Crisis At-a-Glance</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf Rdp, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Here, at a glance, are developments Sunday in the Persian Gulf
crisis:
   
   Forty-seven Americans flew to freedom after being held in Iraq
and Kuwait. ``I wasn't a guest,'' said Lloyd Culbertson, one of
those to reach Washington. ``I damned near starved to death.'' The
former hostages included 24 women, 11 men and 12 children. Some
said Iraqi forces may be mistreating Americans left behind.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   The freed Americans were among about 700 Westerners and
Japanese, mainly women and children, allowed to leave over the
weekend. But thousands of others, including husbands and fathers of
those freed, remained trapped in Iraq and occupied Kuwait.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   In Maine, aides to President Bush said his summit with Soviet
President Mikhail Gorbachev will likely consist of about five hours
of talks devoted largely to the Persian Gulf crisis. When he
announced the summit, the president said there wasn't any set
agenda, and that the crisis was one of a number of issues to be
addressed.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   U.N. Secretary-General Javier Perez de Cuellar said he was
deeply disappointed that his two days of talks in Amman, Jordan,
with Iraqi's foreign minister didn't produce an agreement to defuse
the crisis precipitated by Iraq's invasion of Kuwait.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   An East German government spokesman said the country's
ambassador to Kuwait was forcibly taken to Iraq on Sunday after he
left his diplomatic mission, apparently to seek food at the West
German Embassy.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   About 12,000 mostly Arab and Asian refugees streamed from Iraq
into Jordan, where tens of thousands of impoverished evacuees
already languish in refugee camps. Thousands were trying to cross
into Turkey and Iran.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Church services were held quietly for American soldiers in Saudi
Arabia, despite the sheikdom's ban on the practice of religions
other than Islam. The services were held in mess halls, tents and
in warehouses.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0080 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 2142EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-WeaponsProtest     09-02 0281</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Weapons Protest,0287</SECOND>
<HEAD>Activists Demonstrate On Third Anniversary Of Protester's Maiming</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CONCORD, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   About 200 people gathered on railroad
tracks outside a weapons depot to protest the U.S. military buildup
in the Persian Gulf and mark the third anniversary of the accident
that maimed a peace activist.
   Brian Willson, who lost his legs when he was hit by a train
during a protest outside the Concord Naval Weapons Station, told
the crowd Saturday he is outraged that weapons are still being sent
from the depot to other countries.
   ``This is a heavy day for those of us who were here that day,''
Willson said. ``With this latest bellicose action by the U.S., it
really is painful to know how barbaric we are.''
   White plaster of Paris skulls and flesh-colored papier-mache
legs labeled with the names of countries in conflict were put on
mock coffins next to the tracks where Willson was struck on Sept.
1, 1987. Protesters have maintained a 24-hour vigil at the station
since the accident.
   After listening to speeches and songs, demonstrators carried the
coffins near the gate of the weapons station. Twenty people were
arrested, cited for trespassing and released.
   ``Being here at Concord is to me what being next to Dachau was
to the Germans,'' Willson said. ``It's a death camp.''
   Another speaker was Erik Larsen, 23, of Hayward, a lance
corporal in the U.S. Marine Corps Reserve who said last week he
would not fight in the Middle East.
   ``It seems the U.S. has the types of interventions where people
don't want us,'' Larsen said. ``I hope it doesn't take a bunch of
body bags for people to wake up,'' Larsen said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0081 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 2147EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-GulfRdp 1stLd-Writethru a0704 09-02 1021</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf Rdp, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0704,1046</SECOND>
<HEAD>RETRANMITTING TO RESTORE DROPPED GRAF MARK</HEAD>
<HEAD>Hundreds of Hostages Freed; Iraq Would `Eat Mud'</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS thruout to UPDATE with Saddam's government saying it
would eat mud rather than yield, landing permission denied to
flights; ADDS report that $1 million in cash also stolen by Iraqis;
no pickup</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto AMM2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LAURA KING</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Dozens of Americans returned to freedom Sunday in the first
major airlift of Westerners from Iraq during the month-old Persian
Gulf crisis, but Saddam Hussein's government remained defiant and
vowed to ``eat mud'' before yielding.
   U.N. Secretary-General Javier Perez de Cuellar, who held two
days of talks in Amman, Jordan with the Iraqi foreign minister,
Tariq Aziz, said he was ``deeply disappointed'' with the outcome.
   ``What Iraq wants is to stay in Kuwait, which is unacceptable to
the international community, to the U.N. Security Council and to
its secretary-general,'' Perez de Cuellar told reporters in Paris
Sunday.
   Soviet leader Mikhail Gorbachev and President Bush are to
discuss the gulf crisis and other issues Sept. 9 in Helsinki,
Finland. But even following the weekend announcement of the
superpower summit, some leaders warned a speedy resolution was
unlikely.
   ``We have to settle down for a long haul, which will require a
good deal of steady determination on the part of all concerned,''
said British Foreign Secretary Douglas Hurd.
   For the freed hostages, joy and relief upon reaching safety was
muted by fears for those left behind. Saddam, the Iraqi president,
is using captive foreigners as human shields to protect key Iraqi
installations against potential attack by the U.S.-led
multinational force deployed in the region.
   About 21,000 Westerners, including 3,000 Americans, were
stranded in Iraq and Kuwait by the Aug. 2 invasion.
   A chartered Iraqi Airways Boeing 747, carrying more than 300
Westerners, arrived in Washington on Sunday after stopovers in
Paris and London. It left Baghdad on Saturday along with two other
planeloads of foreigners.
   Among those arriving in Britain was Stuart Lockwood, the
5-year-old British boy whose hair was tousled by Saddam in a
television encounter with a group of Western hostages last month.
The sight of a smiling Saddam clasping the uncomfortable-looking
child brought expressions of revulsion from Western leaders.
   Stuart arrived home Sunday with his mother and brother, but his
father was still being held.
   The flight continued on to Washington, and the 47 weary
Americans arrived at Dulles International Airport outside the
capital after 24 hours of travel. One of the arrivals, 76-year-old
Lloyd Culbertson of El Paso, Texas, was asked if the hostages left
behind feared for their lives.
   ``Yes, they certainly do,'' he said.
   At Tokyo's international airport, 68 Japanese women and children
arriving on a Japan Air Lines flight were greeted by tearful
relatives and friends, a day after leaving Iraq. Japan welcomed
their release but expressed fears for 344 of its nationals still in
Iraq.
   A Lufthansa plane with 250 women and 61 children on board _
including 60 Americans and 71 Germans _ landed early Sunday in
Frankfurt, West Germany, after leaving Baghdad late Saturday. A few
arriving passengers smiled briefly or waved, but nearly all looked
grim and exhausted.
   The airlifts came after Saddam, in what he called a humanitarian
gesture, announced last week that women and children among the
foreign captives would be allowed to leave Iraq.
   However, the departure of several hundred more Western women and
children from Baghdad was apparently delayed as Iraq withheld
landing clearance for two special flights from Britain and France.
   If permission is not granted, a British Foreign Office spokesman
said hostages could return home on Iraqi Airways, even though
regularly scheduled flights by the Iraqi carrier are banned under
the U.N. trade embargo.
   Western governments have demanded the release of all the
hostages, and denounced Iraq's footdragging in freeing the women
and children as promised.
   Confirming previous reports that Iraq had begun to ration food,
government spokesman Naji Al-Hadithi said in Baghdad, ``We have a
war-tested society. We have a war-tested economy. So even if we eat
mud, we will resist pressure and not kneel down to any foreign
power.''
   Iraq fought Iran in an 8-year-war that ended in 1988.
   At the same meeting with reporters, Culture Minister Latif
Nasaif Jasim declared, ``We need only bread and water. We need no
more than that. We can live for a long time.
   ``Dignity is more important than food,'' he added.
   Britain's Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher heaped scorn on
Saddam over the hostage-holding, calling him ``a person who has
taken hostages, cruelly, brutally, and a person who has hidden
behind the skirts of women and children.''
   ``This man is a loser,'' she said in an interview aired Sunday
on Britain's TV-AM network. The official Iraqi News Agency
responded by calling the prime minister an ``old hag.''
   In occupied Kuwait, hardships intensified at embassies defying
an Iraqi order to close their doors. Many missions are without
power and water, surrounded by troops, and the skeleton staffs
operating the missions are virtual prisoners.
   A diplomatic source in Brussels said Sunday the East German
ambassador was picked up by Iraqi authorities and taken to Baghdad.
He had ventured out of his embassy, where food and water were
running low, to visit the West German mission.
   In other developments Sunday:
   _Iraqi officials told foreign reporters who arrived in the
country before Aug. 27 that they must leave on or before next
Tuesday. A government spokesman told the reporters they were being
asked to leave to make room for other foreign journalists who were
awaiting entry visas.
   _Two U.S. cargo ships entered the Suez Canal on their way to the
Persian Gulf, a canal official said. They will join around 30 U.S.
ships in the region, including three aircraft carriers, a
battleship armed with Tomakawk crusie missile, more than one dozen
missile cruisers, destroyers and supply ships.
   _Kuwaiti officials said that Iraq plundered $2 billion worth of
Kuwaiti gold and cash, as well as 15 Kuwait Airways planes when it
invaded. The allegations appeared in the British weekly Observer
newspaper, which interviewed several exiled Kuwaiti leaders in
Saudi Arabia.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0082 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 2248EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Gulf-Homecoming     09-02 0704</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Homecoming,0727</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hostages Get Red, White and Blue Welcome Home</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf-Americans Home</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JONATHAN W. OATIS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Two of the 47 Americans freed from captivity in Iraq and Kuwait
got a red, white and blue welcome home Sunday from tearful friends,
neighbors and relatives in Milwaukee, and another celebrated her
16th birthday at home.
   ``Long live America!'' 16-year-old Sayyeda Mirza's father,
Masood, said after he, his daughter and his wife arrived at New
York City's La Guardia Airport on the last leg of their journey to
their Manhasset Hills, N.Y., home.
   The 24 women, 11 men and 12 children returned to America when
their Iraqi jetliner landed at Washington-Dulles International
Airport outside Washington after a 24-hour journey from Baghdad.
They were among hundreds of foreigners, mostly women and children
allowed to leave Iraq last week.
   The freed hostages gave varying accounts of their treatment. One
told of a candlelight champagne birthday dinner for her daughter at
the Baghdad hotel where she was held; a man who was at the besieged
U.S. Embassy in Kuwait said he ``damned near starved to death.''
   The joy of homecoming was dampened by fear for those left
behind. About 21,000 Westerners, including 3,000 Americans, were
stranded in Iraq and Kuwait following Iraq's Aug. 2 invasion of
Kuwait. Iraqi President Saddam Hussein is using some of the
captives as human shields to protect key installations.
   Mirza said that when he learned he was being released, ``I was
happy. I was crying.
   ``And the next moment I thought, `What about the others?' ''
   Mirza, who is of Indian descent, his wife Nasreen and daughter
were vacationing in London when they decided on the spur of the
moment to visit Islamic holy sites in Baghdad.
   He said Sunday he didn't know why his family was allowed to go
home.
   Prabhavathi Murikpudi, 40, wept with joy when she and her
10-year-old daughter, Sylaja, were met at Chicago's O'Hare
International Airport by her husband, whose monthlong effort to
gain their release included a videotaped plea sent to Saddam.
   The Murikpudis drove back to their Milwaukee home, where they
were greeted by dozens of friends, neighbors and relatives. Their
home was decorated with red, white and blue streamers and ``Welcome
Home'' banners.
   Mrs. Murikipudi and her daughter were detained by the Iraqis on
Aug. 2 while their airliner was being refueled in Kuwait. They had
been on a trip to visit relatives in India.
   Mrs. Murikipudi said the tension reached its peak during the
ordeal's first few days. ``They were fighting on the runway, and we
were told to get off the plane and to get into the airport,'' she
said.
   She and her daughter were taken with other Westerners from an
airport hotel to the southern Iraqi city of Basra, then Baghdad and
later a fertilizer plant about 225 miles from Baghdad. They were
returned to Baghdad on Aug. 30.
   ``We were treated excellent, but we were always with guards,''
Mrs. Murikipudi said. ``I had no complaints ...''
   Sylaja celebrated her 10th birthday while in Iraq. Mrs.
Murikipudi said other hostages and employees of the Al-Rashid Hotel
where they were staying tried to make the best of it.
   ``Some ladies mentioned (her birthday) to the cook and they
arranged a big celebration,'' including champagne, music, gifts and
a candlelight dinner, she said.
   ``We were really treated very well, physically,'' Mrs. Mirza
told television station WCBS-TV in an interview at the family's
Manhasset Hills home.
   But Lloyd Culbertson, who was at the embassy in Kuwait, told a
different story, and disagreed with the Iraqi characterization of
the captive foreigners as guests.
   ``I wasn't a guest,'' said the 76-year-old El Paso man. ``I
damned near starved to death.''
   Culbertson, who said he had taught electronics to the Kuwaiti
military for 5{ years, said hostages in the embassy had no fresh
water or electrical power and were fast using up food supplies.
   ``The people are starving in that embassy, or they soon will
be,'' Culbertson told reporters during a short layover at
Dallas-Fort Worth International Airport.
   He said at Dulles that meals at the embassy were ``pretty skimpy
rations'' _ mainly frozen turkey. ``I have never eaten so much
turkey in my life.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0083 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 2318EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BRF--RemainsReturned 1stLd-Writethru a0761 09-02 0156</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Remains Returned, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0761,0155</SECOND>
<HEAD>First Air Force Crash Victim Returned</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 2nd graf, `The remains...' with hometown of victim</NOTE>
<DATELINE>DOVER AIR FORCE BASE, Del. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The body of an officer killed
in the crash of an Air Force cargo jet in West Germany was flown
here Sunday, the first victim to be returned to the United States.
   The remains of Capt. Bradley R. Schuldt, of Arlington Heights,
Ill., arrived at Dover Air Force Base on a C-5 cargo jet from Rhein
Main Air Base near Frankfurt.
   Schuldt was among 13 Air Force personnel killed when their C-5
crashed shortly after takeoff from Ramstein Air Base on Wednesday.
Four others were injured.
   Air Force officials said there were no plans to hold honors
ceremonies here for any of the crash victims.
   The base mortuary will prepare the body for burial before it is
transferred to next of kin, officials said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0084 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 2320EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-TropicalWeather     09-02 0139</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Tropical Weather,0142</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tropical Storm Gustav Speeds Toward Canada's Eastern Tip</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Tropical Storm Gustav accelerated toward the
eastern tip of Canada on Sunday with top sustained winds near 70
mph, forecasters said.
   At 10:30 p.m. EDT, Gustav was centered near 47.1 degrees north
latitude and 45.8 degrees west longitude, about 360 miles east of
Cape Race, Newfoundland, according to the National Hurricane Center
in suburban Coral Gables.
   Gustav was moving north northeast at about 30 mph with tropical
storm force winds extending up to 230 miles from its center. It was
expected to accelerate while losing some strength before Tuesday,
hurricane specialist Max Mayfield said.
   Gustav reached top winds of 100 mph Saturday before dropping
below hurricane-force winds of 74 mph Sunday, forecasters said.
   The Atlantic hurricane season lasts from June 1 to November 30.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0085 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 2345EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a BC-LOT--WeekendLotteries     09-02 0658</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-LOT--Weekend Lotteries,0796</SECOND>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<HEAD>ARIZONA</HEAD>
<HEAD>Pick</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PHOENIX (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers in Saturday night's drawing
of the Arizona Lottery's Pick game were 14, 15, 23, 28, 31 and 39
with a bonus number of 37.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>COLORADO</HEAD>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DENVER (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the six numbers selected Saturday night
in this week's Lotto drawing for an estimated $3 million jackpot:
   1-13-15-17-26-32
</TEXT>
<HEAD>CONNECTICUT</HEAD>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEWINGTON, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning combination picked Saturday
in the Connecticut State Lottery's ``Daily Lottery'' drawing was:
   5-0-2
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Play 4</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEWINGTON, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning combination picked Saturday
in the Connecticut State Lottery's ``Play 4'' drawing was:
   3-8-7-9.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>DELAWARE</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DOVER, Del. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   These Delaware lotteries were drawn Saturday
night:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   6-4-9
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Play Four</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   8-3-9-3
</TEXT>
<HEAD>ILLINOIS</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SPRINGFIELD, Ill. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the Illinois State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   5-8-2
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick Four</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   5-8-2-7
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   11-29-40-43-44-45
</TEXT>
<HEAD>IOWA</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DES MOINES, Iowa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers drawn Saturday night
in Iowa Lotto are:
   4-6-7-13-15-32.
   
   Wildcard: king of spades.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>KANSAS</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOPEKA, Kan. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers in the Kansas Cash Lotto
drawing Saturday night with an estimated jackpot of $75,000:
   3-4-6-14-22-27
</TEXT>
<HEAD>KENTUCKY</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOUISVILLE, Ky. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are Saturday's winning numbers
selected by the Kentucky Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Kentucky Cash:
   6-8-6.
   </HEAD>
<HEAD>Lotto:
   5-6-13-20-32-35.
   </HEAD>
<HEAD>MARYLAND</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BALTIMORE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   These Maryland lotteries were drawn Saturday
night:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   6-7-3
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Play Four</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   2-9-4-4
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   6-12-19-26-37-43
</TEXT>
<HEAD>MASSACHUSETTS</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BRAINTREE, Mass. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers drawn Saturday night
in the ``Massachusetts Daily Lottery'' were:
   6-5-0-8
</TEXT>
<HEAD>MICHIGAN</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DETROIT (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected Saturday in
the Michigan State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   2-9-9
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily-4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   2-2-9-3
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto 47</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   10, 14, 18, 22, 32, 41)
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   The Zinger number was:
   8-2-3-5-4-9
</TEXT>
<HEAD>MINNESOTA</HEAD>
<HEAD>Daily 3</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MINNEAPOLIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers drawn Saturday night in
the Minnesota Daily 3 lottery game are:
   3-8-9
</TEXT>
<HEAD>MISSOURI</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ST. LOUIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers in Saturday's Missouri
Lottery and Lotto drawings were:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 3</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   1-4-4
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   13-23-35-36-43-46
</TEXT>
<HEAD>NEW JERSEY</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TRENTON, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday night in the New Jersey State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 3</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   3-8-5
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   1-2-8-8
</TEXT>
<HEAD>NORTHERN NEW ENGLAND</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CONCORD, N.H. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the daily New Hampshire, Vermont and Maine lotteries:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 3</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   1-7-1
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   6-7-4-1
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Tri-State Megabucks</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   1-5-8-21-27-31
</TEXT>
<HEAD>OHIO</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CLEVELAND (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected Saturday
night in the Ohio Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Super Lotto</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   8-11-14-20-30-42
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Kicker</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   1-9-5-1-1-6
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 3 Numbers</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   1-5-5
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 4 Numbers</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   5-8-6-7
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Cards</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Four of Hearts
   Three of Clubs
   Ten of Diamonds
   Two of Spades
</TEXT>
<HEAD>OREGON</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PORTLAND, Ore. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are Saturday's winning numbers in the
``Oregon Daily 4'' and ``Oregon Megabucks'' lottery games:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily 4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   4-3-5-4
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Megabucks</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   5-10-22-25-37-41
</TEXT>
<HEAD>PENNSYLVANIA</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HARRISBURG (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected Saturday
in the Pennsylvania State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Number</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   8-4-2
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Big 4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   8-5-9-6
</TEXT>
<HEAD>VIRGINIA</HEAD>
<HEAD>Pick 3</HEAD>
<DATELINE>RICHMOND (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   These numbers were drawn Saturday in the
Virginia Lottery's Pick 3 game:
   6-8-4
</TEXT>
<HEAD>WASHINGTON</HEAD>
<DATELINE>OLYMPIA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are winning numbers selected Saturday in the
Washington State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   2-1-3
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   3-24-30-35-38-44
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Quinto</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   King of spades, ten of spades, six of spades, five of diamonds,
queen of clubs.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>WASHINGTON, D.C.</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The following results were drawn Saturday in
the District of Columbia Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lucky Numbers Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   8-6-4
</TEXT>
<HEAD>D.C. Four Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   3-5-8-5
</TEXT>
<HEAD>D.C. Daily Double Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   18, 82
</TEXT>
<HEAD>D.C. Quick Cash Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   27-37-6-21-18-28
</TEXT>
<HEAD>WEST VIRGINIA</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CHARLESTON, W.Va. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the West Virginia State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily 3</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   4-0-7
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily 4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   4-3-2-3
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900902-0086 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-90 2354EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a w PM-WalterMears Adv04   09-02 0822</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Walter Mears, Adv04,0851</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv 04</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release PMs Tue Sept 4 and Thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>For Bush, the Enemy at Home Is Impatience</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Substitutes for the regular column by Walter R. Mears,
vacationing</NOTE>
<HEAD>An AP News Analysis</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MIKE FEINSILBER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   For George Bush, the easy part is over. So
far, he has only had to cope with Saddam Hussein. Congress is back
in town next week.
   The president got a glimpse of the shape of things to come if he
checked on what was said afterward by the 170 members of Congress
who interrupted their vacations for a presidential update on the
Persian Gulf showdown.
   Bush appealed for bipartisan support, and he got it, effusively.
But there was an uneasy undertone after the session that suggested
criticism is lurking _ especially if the deployment turns into a
stalemate.
   Stalemate is the best Bush can hope for _ it beats war _ while
he waits for the international quarantine of Iraq to work.
   But American public opinion is not so good at waiting.
   Not if the price of gasoline keeps rising and the economy keeps
sinking.
   Not if television carries pictures of Kuwaitis on the French
Riviera driving to rallies in their Mercedes Benz automobiles to
cheer on the American boys.
   Not if American women soldiers _ on full television display in
soldierly roles for the first time _ run afoul of cultural
differences in a Saudi society that gives women scant status and no
equality.
   Bush can stand the heat from Congress, but if the American
people turn against this enterprise they can ultimately end it.
That was Vietnam's lesson for policymakers.
   Mark Mellman, a Democratic pollster, guesses Bush has a fairly
short period.
   ``If we just keep 200,000 troops in the Saudi desert without
them having any clear goals other than deterrence, I think his
support will dissipate fairly quickly,'' Mellman says. ``It may be
60 days, it may be 90 days, it may be six months, but we don't have
something happen by Christmas, I'd guess support will dissipate.''
   ``Americans are impatient by and large and goal-oriented and
success-oriented,'' he added. ``This represents a tremendous
financial commitment and an emotional commitment and for many
people a real hardship.''
   Political scientist Dick Barody of Stanford University, a
student of public opinion, says he is still mystified over whether
public opinion leads the politicians or vice versa.
   ``People who want to do other things with the money will begin
to portray this as a war-that-isn't and a foreign policy that isn't
getting us anywhere,'' Barody says.
   At the end in Vietnam, the public could no longer stomach the
war and Congress responded by refusing to appropriate money for any
purpose there other than to bring home the troops.
   After hearing from Bush last week, lawmakers did not directly
challenge his decision to confront Saddam Hussein.
   When politicians want to be critical of a policy that appears
popular, they attack it from the fringes rather than frontally.
That's what happened.
   _They complained that while Bush has rallied the world's support
for isolating Saddam, the venture is still largely an American
undertaking.
   ``If we don't watch it, we'll have a 90 or 95 percent share of
the on-the-ground troops,'' said Rep. David Obey, D-Wis. ``I don't
think that's politically sustainable at home.''
   Rep. David Bonior, D-Mich., said his constituents already are
complaining that the Japanese, the Australians and others are not
doing enough. Rep. Christopher Smith, R-N.J., added the Soviets to
the list.
   _They said Bush had failed to articulate America's purpose. They
said he had to specify the nature of the threat to the U.S.
national interest.
   Sen. Joseph Biden, D-Del., told Bush directly, participants
reported, that lawmakers like himself who came of age during
Vietnam want to know ``what we're doing in Saudi Arabia.''
   Rep. Mike DeWine, R-Ohio, said it was time for Bush to get on
television and put before the country ``not only our specific
objective ... but the rationale and the reasoning behind those
objectives.'' Sen. John H. Chafee, R-R.I., said Bush owed his
countrymen ``as fine an explanation of our presence as can be
produced.''
   _And they criticized the administration for failing to develop a
policy that would make the country less dependent on foreign oil.
Rep. Norm Dicks, D-Wash., said some pointed out to Bush that he
hadn't even brought his energy secretary, James Watkins, to the
meeting.
   None of that is direct criticism of what Bush has done in
standing up to Saddam. There will be none if he succeeds. But in
this situation, stalemate is not success.
   Dicks said that erosion of public support is inevitable.
   ``Already, there are people asking, `Why is it we are out
there?'' he said. ``Is it just because of cheap oil?''
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   EDITOR'S NOTE: Mike Feinsilber has been covering the news in
Washington since 1968.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for PMs Tue Sept 4</NOTE>
</DOC>
</Collection>
