<Collection>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0001 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 2341EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a BC-LOT-SaturdayLotteries     10-07 0846</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-LOT-Saturday Lotteries,1061</SECOND>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<HEAD>CALIFORNIA</HEAD>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SACRAMENTO, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers picked
Saturday night for the California Lottery's twice-weekly ``Lotto
6-53'' game: 28, 33, 29, 34, 10, 43, and the bonus number, 6.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>CONNECTICUT</HEAD>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEWINGTON, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning combination picked Saturday
in the Connecticut State Lottery's ``Daily Lottery'' drawing was:
   6-7-0
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Play 4</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEWINGTON, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning combination picked Saturday
in the Connecticut State Lottery's ``Play 4'' drawing was:
   0-3-0-6.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>DELAWARE</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DOVER, Del. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   These Delaware lotteries were drawn Saturday
night:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   2-5-3
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Play Four</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   5-8-6-0
</TEXT>
<HEAD>FLORIDA</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected Saturday in
the Florida Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Cash 3</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   9-7-7
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   44-24-17-04-19-20
</TEXT>
<HEAD>ILLINOIS</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SPRINGFIELD, Ill. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the Illinois State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   5-6-6
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick Four</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   1-7-9-2
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   5-17-39-49-51-53
</TEXT>
<HEAD>INDIANA</HEAD>
<DATELINE>INDIANAPOLIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the Indiana Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto Cash</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   1-14-23-26-30-39
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Three</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   5-6-1
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Four</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   8-2-9-6
</TEXT>
<HEAD>IOWA</HEAD>
<HEAD>Iowa Lotto</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DES MOINES, Iowa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers drawn Saturday night
in Iowa Lotto are:
   4-10-14-16-18-28.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto America</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   2-9-22-33-42-45
</TEXT>
<HEAD>KANSAS</HEAD>
<HEAD>Kan. Keno</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOPEKA, Kan. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers in the Kansas Keno
drawing Saturday night with a jackpot of $50,000:
   1-2-10-12-14-15-16-17-20-21-27-35-36-37-41-42-43-49-51-59
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Kan. Cash Lotto</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOPEKA, Kan. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers in the Kansas Cash Lotto
drawing Saturday night with an estimated jackpot of $164,415:
   3-10-23-24-25-31
</TEXT>
<HEAD>KENTUCKY</HEAD>
<HEAD>Kentucky Lottery</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOUISVILLE, Ky. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are Saturday's winning numbers
selected by the Kentucky Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Kentucky Cash:
   7-0-9.
   </HEAD>
<HEAD>Lotto:
   3-9-12-14-16-22
   </HEAD>
<HEAD>MARYLAND</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BALTIMORE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   These Maryland lotteries were drawn Saturday
night:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   8-9-2
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Play Four</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   9-7-5-0
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   2-27-29-32-43-49
</TEXT>
<HEAD>MASSACHUSETTS</HEAD>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BRAINTREE, Mass. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers drawn Saturday night
in the ``Massachusetts Daily Lottery'' were:
   4-0-1-2
</TEXT>
<HEAD>MICHIGAN</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DETROIT (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected Saturday in
the Michigan State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   3-3-3
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily-4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   9-6-5-9
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto 47</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   18, 21, 32, 35, 44, 45
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   The Zinger number was:
   0-1-5-2-1-4
</TEXT>
<HEAD>MINNESOTA</HEAD>
<HEAD>Daily 3</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MINNEAPOLIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers drawn Saturday night in
the Minnesota Daily 3 lottery game are:
   4-1-1
</TEXT>
<HEAD>MISSOURI</HEAD>
<HEAD>Pick 3</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ST. LOUIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers in Saturday's Missouri
Lottery Daily Pick 3 game:
   4-5-2
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ST. LOUIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers in Missouri's Lotto drawing
Saturday night with an estimated $5.7 million jackpot:
   2-8-30-33-39-46
</TEXT>
<HEAD>NEW JERSEY</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TRENTON, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday night in the New Jersey State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 3</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   5-2-4
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   0-6-0-3
</TEXT>
<HEAD>NEW YORK</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ALBANY, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the New York State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Number</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   2-4-8
</TEXT>
<HEAD>WinFour</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   1-1-5-4
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 10</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ALBANY, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the New York State Lottery's Pick 10 game:
   
   5, 9, 11, 16, 19, 25, 26, 27, 34, 37, 38, 42, 43, 52, 60, 63,
66, 67, 72, 76
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ALBANY, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the New York State Lottery's Lotto game:
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   9, 23, 32, 37, 43, 45. The supplemental number was 30.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>NORTHERN NEW ENGLAND</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CONCORD, N.H. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the daily New Hampshire, Vermont and Maine lotteries:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 3</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   8-5-9
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Pick 4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   2-1-6-3
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Tri-State Megabucks</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CONCORD, N.H. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers in the
``Tri-State Megabucks'' game for New Hampshire, Vermont and Maine:
10-16-22-23-25-34.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>OHIO</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CLEVELAND (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected Saturday
night in the Ohio Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Super Lotto</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   20-23-34-44-51-53
 
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Kicker</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   0-9-2-1-8-8
</TEXT>
<HEAD>OREGON</HEAD>
<HEAD>Daily 4</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PORTLAND, Ore. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are Saturday's winning numbers in the
``Oregon Daily 4'' lottery game:
   7-6-6-5
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Megabucks</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PORTLAND, Ore. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are Saturday's winning numbers in the
``Oregon Megabucks'' lottery game:
   4-10-12-13-16-25
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto America</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PORTLAND, Ore. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are Saturday's winning numbers in the
``Lotto America'' lottery game:
   2-9-22-33-42-45
</TEXT>
<HEAD>PENNSYLVANIA</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HARRISBURG (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected Saturday
in the Pennsylvania State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Number</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   9-7-7
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Big 4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   2-6-3-1
</TEXT>
<HEAD>RHODE ISLAND</HEAD>
<HEAD>Daily Lottery</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CRANSTON, R.I. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The winning numbers in the Rhode Island
daily lottery drawing for Saturday were:
   3-8-2-2
</TEXT>
<HEAD>VIRGINIA</HEAD>
<HEAD>Pick 3</HEAD>
<DATELINE>RICHMOND (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   These numbers were drawn Saturday in the
Virginia Lottery's Pick 3 game:
   5-3-9
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<DATELINE>RICHMOND (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   These numbers were drawn Saturday in the
Virginia Lottery's Lotto game:
   13-16-17-27-28-31
</TEXT>
<HEAD>WASHINGTON</HEAD>
<DATELINE>OLYMPIA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are winning numbers selected Saturday in the
Washington State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   3-9-8
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lotto</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   2-19-25-34-38-44
</TEXT>
<HEAD>WASHINGTON, DC</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The following results were drawn Saturday in
the District of Columbia Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Lucky Numbers Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   0-6-3
</TEXT>
<HEAD>D.C. Four Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   4-9-5-6
</TEXT>
<HEAD>D.C. Daily Double Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   46, 65
</TEXT>
<HEAD>D.C. Quick Cash Game</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   5, 24, 13, 23, 9, 7
</TEXT>
<HEAD>WEST VIRGINIA</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CHARLESTON, W.Va. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are the winning numbers selected
Saturday in the West Virginia State Lottery:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily 3</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   7-6-2
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Daily 4</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   3-3-0-4
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0002 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 2347EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Klan'sNemesis     10-07 0976</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Klan's Nemesis,1257</SECOND>
<HEAD>Morris Dees: Scourge of KKK Sees Shades of Gray</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY304 of Oct. 3</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Monday AMs report.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By CHRISTOPHER SULLIVAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MONTGOMERY, Ala. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Black-and-white. Usually it means plain,
explicit, uncomplicated.
   But in his law office, where the white pages of statute books
were blackened by a firebomb, Morris Dees somehow keeps seeing
shades of gray.
   Dees, the founder of the Southern Poverty Law Center and its
chief counsel in trials that have destroyed Ku Klux Klan
organizations, wants to understand his bitter adversaries - even
the ones who've tried to kill him.
   ``A lot of these people have paranoid personalities bred from
basically family problems when they were children,'' he says.
``They're looking for love and affection.''
   ``If you look at a Klan roster, just about everybody ... can be
an exalted something. It makes them feel important.''
   White supremacists chafe at such cool analysis, and at least
three racist groups have put Dees at or near the top of their hit
lists. A display case in his offices holds charred law books and a
melted clock, reminders of the 1983 firebombing by Klansmen.
   In a case set for trial Monday in Portland, Ore., the
53-year-old white Alabama lawyer is suing an organization called
the White Aryan Resistance for allegedly inciting skinheads to
fatally beat an African man there.
   A lawsuit he brought in 1984 in the lynching of a black
teen-ager in Mobile, Ala., resulted in a judgment that bankrupted
the United Klans of America. The victim's mother, Buelah Mae
Donald, received title to the Klan's national headquarters.
   Dees pursued the case with zeal - and yet he wept, along with
others, when one of the killers stood up at the end of the trial
and begged Mrs. Donald's forgiveness.
   ``I just think once you come face-to-face with this person you
stalk, and their families ... that's a catharsis that a lot of
people go through,'' he said.
   Morris Dees grew up, blond-haired and blue-eyed, in Alabama
cotton country.
   When asked the source of the righteous anger that seems to
underlie the law center, he tells a story of his youth.
   He was 16 and his father sent him to accompany a tractor driver
on the farm, a black man named Clarence, to a court appearance.
Clarence had been charged with drunken driving, but Dees believed
his story: ``His car had a tie rod come loose and he'd hit a
concrete median and knocked himself dizzy.''
   The justice of the peace operated out of a store, and during the
``trial,'' Dees said, ``he never quit serving crackers and cheese
and Cokes across the counter.''
   Guilty was the inevitable ruling.
   ``The fine was over $100. Clarence didn't have that kind of
money,'' Dees said. ``I don't know, that kind of set me on wanting
to become a lawyer.''
   Dees graduated from the University of Alabama and its law
school. While still a student, he set up a lucrative birthday cake
delivery service, and later sold books by direct mail. He and a
partner sold the business for a reported $6 million.
   Dees next put his direct-mail skills to work raising millions
for George McGovern's Democratic presidential campaign in 1972,
then used the mailing lists to appeal for help on his own project,
the fledgling Southern Poverty Law Center.
   The center grew out of ``his determination that there was an
enormous gap in legal defense in certain kinds of cases,'' said
Julian Bond, a black civil rights leader from Georgia who became
the center's first board chairman.
   What drives Morris Dees? ``A very well-developed sense of
outrage,'' said Bond, now a professor and broadcaster in
Washington, D.C.
   ``He knows the legal system can be used to right wrongs.''
   The law center, which now has an endowment of $30 million and a
$4 million annual budget, has taken on death penalty, voting
rights, employment discrimination and other cases, but is best
known for hauling the Klan and similar groups into court.
   Klanwatch, a handful of investigators at the Montgomery law
center backed up by informants around the country, produces a
bi-monthly ``Intelligence Report'' on hate group activities, which
is sent to 4,000 police agencies.
   White robes reflected by a fiery cross, the fear reflected on
black faces in the night, in the ``Intelligence Report'' these
stark events are reduced to column upon column of statistics, names
and dates. Black-and-white becomes gray again.
   ``It appears to be good solid information,'' said Lt. Robert
McCulley of the Memphis, Tenn., police. ``Information is hard to
come by. You don't go into a bookstore and walk to the section
labeled `Terrorism.' ''
   To enter the Southern Poverty Law Center, a visitor climbs steps
walled with stone past a granite monument to civil rights martyrs.
The front door is unlocked electronically and, inside, a
receptionist sits at a video security system.
   ``It's a necessary bunker,'' Bond said. ``If you do this work
from the safety of New York City, it's one thing. But if you're
right in the heart of the beast, a sensible person takes
precautions.''
   And Dees does. He varies his route and schedule to and from
work. He avoids alleys.
   ``Demon Dees!'' Louis Beam, a Texas neo-Nazi, once shouted
during questioning by his nemesis in one case. Beam challenged Dees
to a duel.
   Exorcising the demon with a simple gunshot apparently was not
enough for members of The Order, which murdered Denver talk show
host Alan Berg.
   ``The preliminary plan called for kidnapping Dees, interrogating
him, then flaying him - peeling his skin off his body - before
killing him,'' wrote Kevin Flynn and Gary Gerhardt in their book,
``The Silent Brotherhood.''
   In an otherwise even-toned interview, the only strong profanity
came when the soft-spoken Dees was asked if he doesn't expect one
day to become another name on the law center's memorial.
   ``Man, I don't want to be a martyr to anybody's (expletive)
cause,'' he said. ``I didn't get into this thing for a cause.''
   The law center began with a variety of suits: challenging
unhealthy working conditions in textile plants, representing death
row inmates and others.
   Dees first went up against the white supremacists in 1979,
agreeing to represent a black marcher attacked during a peaceful
demonstration in Decatur, Ala. Clubbed by KKK counterdemonstrators,
the man tried to defend himself with a registered gun, Dees said.
An all-white jury convicted him.
   Dees thought back to Clarence, and his day in court: ``Nothing
had really changed.''
   But it was about to. He filed a civil lawsuit against the
Klansmen.
   Evidence uncovered by Klanwatch led to federal indictments
against 10 Klansmen, and the suit ended in a settlement that, among
other things, required the whites to attend a race relations class.
The class was taught earlier this year by the Rev. Joseph Lowery of
the Southern Christian Leadership Conference, who is black.
   ``One of the Klansmen,'' Dees said, ``the day of the
demonstration he had a club in his hand ... Eleven years later,
he's standing there holding hands with Dr. Lowery in a prayer.
   ``And saying, `Maybe I was misguided back then, and we could
have solved our problems in a different way.' ''
   ---
   EDITOR'S NOTE - Christopher Sullivan is the AP's Southeast
regional reporter, based in Atanta.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0003 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 2347EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Dees-FirstAmendment     10-07 0370</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Dees-First Amendment,0430</SECOND>
<HEAD>Free-Speech Claim in Skinhead Case Called `Baloney'; ACLU
Monitoring</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Klan's Nemesis</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Monday AMs report.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By CHRISTOPHER SULLIVAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   A white supremacist accused in a lawsuit of inciting skinheads
to commit a racially motivated killing in Portland, Ore., says he
was merely exercising his First Amendment rights.
   The suit, which seeks damages from the group White Aryan
Resistance, or WAR, and four individuals, is merely ``a roundabout
way of cutting off freedom of speech, freedom of association and
even freedom of assembly,'' said Tom Metzger, the organization's
leader and a defendant.
   The Oregon office of the American Civil Liberties Union plans to
monitor the trial, set to begin Monday in Portland.
   Plaintiff's lawyer Morris Dees calls Metzger's claims
``baloney.''
   The civil case follows the criminal conviction of three
skinheads in the 1988 beating death of Mulugeta Seraw, a
27-year-old Ethiopian who was living and working in Portland.
Seraw's skull was fractured with a baseball bat.
   Dees' Montgomery, Ala.-based Southern Poverty Law Center sued on
behalf of Seraw's estate. In the past, the center has won millions
in judgments by suing hate groups and their leaders, arguing that
they are responsible for damage and injuries done at their behest,
just as a corporation can be held liable for employees' actions.
   The suit contends Metzger and his son John have recruited
skinheads to WAR in recent years, and that through agents they sent
to Portland, they provided a skinhead group called East Side White
Pride with racist materials promoting violence against blacks and
Jews. Seraw's killers were members of East Side White Pride.
   Further, the suit - which was joined by the Anti-Defamation
League of B'nai B'rith - claims WAR agents were in contact with the
Metzgers in Fallbrook, Calif., met with the skinheads and
encouraged them to harm blacks.
   ``The allegations of personal involvement ... are totally
nonsense,'' Metzger said. ``It's something that Mr. Dees has
dreamed up.''
   Dees said he has letters and phone records linking the Metzgers
and their ``agents'' in Portland, as well as ``a damning
affidavit.'' In it, one of the agents, Michael Barrett, tells of
taking five baseball bats to Portland, of keeping close contact
with the Metzgers, and of meeting with East Side White Pride
skinheads.
   ``We told them to use violence if they got an opportunity, and
to be sure and beat the hell out of the enemy,'' Barrett said in
the affidavit. ``We were telling them what Tom and John Metzger
told us to say.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0004 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 2349EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-GusHawkins     10-07 0850</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Gus Hawkins,1061</SECOND>
<HEAD>A Courtly Gentleman Retires From Congress</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Monday AMs report.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By JILL LAWRENCE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   He arrived in time for the tidal wave of Great
Society activism, championed social concerns during the
penny-pinching Reagan era and leaves as he came, fighting for civil
rights.
   Rep. Augustus Hawkins, 83, chairman of the House Education and
Labor Committee, is a black man who never played racial politics; a
liberal who inspires affection among conservatives; a courtly
gentleman who rarely gives up or gives in.
   The diminutive, soft-spoken Democrat is retiring this year after
28 years in Congress representing Watts, the Los Angeles
neighborhood notorious for the riots that tore it apart in the
1960s.
   In the brave new Capitol Hill world of sound bites, cynicism and
big money, the void left by Hawkins' departure may not be
immediately obvious. But there will be one. Ask any education,
labor or civil rights lobbyist; the senior Republican on his
committee; even Rep. Tom Downey, who bested him in a recent dispute
over how to channel child-care money to states and parents.
   ``This institution is going to miss him terribly,'' said Downey,
D-N.Y.
   ``He has been a relentless pursuer of social justice,'' said
Michael Edwards, chief lobbyist for the National Education
Association. ``He has very deeply held principles and a great sense
of mission. And yet he was always able to bring people together.''
   Hawkins' basic philosophy - that government must help its less
fortunate citizens - hasn't changed much since he was elected to
the California Assembly in 1934.
   ``I truly believe every person in our country is entitled to
equal opportunities. If we give them those opportunities, it will
help everybody else. That's good, ordinary common sense,'' he said
in an interview last week.
   The son of a British-born adventurer who moved his family to the
United States after exploring Africa, Hawkins won his House seat in
1962. He was the first black member from a Western state, and one
of the first things he did was sponsor the equal employment section
of the landmark 1964 Civil Rights Act.
   It was an early triumph in a congressional career that has
spanned eras of plenty and parsimony, pendulum swings in political
thought, and the inevitable mixture of achievements and
disappointments.
   Chief among the latter was the 1978 Humphrey-Hawkins full
employment bill, which put forth an admirable goal but lost a
federal job guarantee before passage. ``It's been an outright
failure in terms of implementation,'' Hawkins said bluntly. ``No
one's taken it seriously, beginning with the Carter
administration.''
   The widely supported 1988 welfare reform law, with its
requirement that some recipients take jobs, was another setback
from Hawkins' perspective. Workfare is ``a punitive approach to
forcing people off the rolls,'' he declared on the floor.
   It was an unusually harsh stand for a man who, despite his
enduring New Deal concerns, generally prefers compromise to
confrontation.
   Hawkins' grasp of political reality was put to the test in 1984,
when he became committee chairman amid rampant conservatism and a
scarcity of domestic resources. For the most part he adapted well,
building coalitions and inching ahead where possible.
   ``If you only have a potato, the only thing you can make is
potato soup. You can't make stew,'' said Bob McGlotten, chief
lobbyist for the AFL-CIO. ``Under severe circumstances, Gus has
done a tremendous job to make sure the educational systems in our
society don't fall apart.''
   The kind of money Hawkins wanted to spend on education and
programs for disadvantaged children wasn't available, but he
settled for modest gains and was rewarded with near-unanimous
passage of many major education bills.
   There was far more contention in the labor area, including
protracted battles over raising the minimum wage and guaranteeing
unpaid family leaves to workers. But civility was always the order
of the day.
   ``We don't have any animosity. We have differences,'' said Fred
Krebs, manager of the U.S. Chamber of Commerce's labor and human
resources department.
   The same civility characterized Hawkins' relations with
Republicans on the committee, who recently threw him a retirement
party. Among his gifts was a homemade gavel to crack crabs and a
gag picture of Downey with a forged inscription that said ``I
really enjoyed working closely with you.''
   ``I'm very saddened that he is leaving,'' said Rep. Bill
Goodling, R-Pa., the senior Republican on Hawkins' committee. ``He
is one of the finest gentlemen I've ever met.''
   The two men had a close partnership, with the chairman often
testing his ideas on Goodling and molding them to attract broader
support.
   ``If he doesn't agree with what I'm trying to do, I try to find
out why. I know I will get the same disagreements from others,''
Hawkins said. ``If I can make modifications, we'll get something
done. If you are really interested in results, why not be
cooperative?''
   Hawkins, so light-skinned he is often thought to be white, has
never chaired the Congressional Black Caucus and prefers to cast
issues in economic rather than racial terms.
   He has promoted education, health care and nutrition for the
needy, and been instrumental in securing passage of many civil
ights laws that opened up opportunities for minorities and others.
   Ironically, as he leaves Congress, Hawkins is once again trying
to restore some of the protections he first fought for in 1964.
Bush is threatening to veto this year's Kennedy-Hawkins civil
rights bill, although Hawkins said he amended it 22 times to try to
please the administration.
   ``In some ways we're back where we were,'' Hawkins said. ``It is
discouraging, but not to the point where we're giving up. You have
this ebb and flow in American politics... You win a few and you
lose a few. By and large you try to be incremental in making
advances.''
   When Hawkins retires, he won't vanish onto the Chesapeake Bay in
his beloved fishing boat. Instead he intends to speak, volunteer
and organize on behalf of Job Corps, Head Start and other programs
he fostered in Congress. ``You don't have to be in elective office
to make a difference,'' Hawkins said. ``There's lots of things to
do, and in between I'll do a little fishing.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0005 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 2351EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Ceausescu'sOrphans     10-07 0749</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Ceausescu's Orphans,0950</SECOND>
<HEAD>Thousands of Children Orphaned or Abandoned in Romania</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Monday AMs report.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By DAN PETREANU</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUCHAREST, Romania (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Stan Barbu is 3 and runs on his knees
because the parents who abandoned him will not let surgeons fix his
twisted legs. he 50 other children in the orphanage are blind,
retarded or maimed.
   They are the dregs of tens of thousands of abandoned or orphaned
children who owe their plight to Nicolae Ceausescu's obsession with
population growth.
   Ten months after the Commuist dictator was overthrown and
executed, no one knows just how many children languish in Romania's
78 orphanages and in dozens of hospitals. The government says there
may be 60,000 in a total population of 23 million, but other
estimates range up to 100,000.
   What to do with them has yet to be decided. Some foreigners
believe adoption is part of the answer.
   Stan is pale and fair-haired, with a broad grin and bright eyes
that make his crippling infirmities difficult to believe.
   His fingers and toes are grown together and his legs bend inward
in arcs so severe that he must walk and run on his knees. He
delights in showing visitors what he can do.
   Although Stan's parents abandoned him two years ago, Romanian
law gives them the right to say whether he should have surgery.
They have refused, and ``there's nothing we can do but watch him
suffer'' unless the law is changed, one of his nurses said.
   Ceausescu, put to death last Christmas Day, did not permit
contraception and abortion was illegal, with few exceptions. Women
were required to have regular medical examinations to determine
whether they were pregnant.
   Couples were encouraged to have at least four children each, but
Ceausescu's economic policies made it difficult to afford more than
one.
   Parents abandoned tens of thousands of children to state
institutions. Dr. Emil Tomescu, deputy health minister, estimates
no more than 3 percent of the children in orphanages actually are
orphans.
   Of the approximately 800 Romanian children diagnosed this year
as having AIDS, most are abandoned. Doctors said the fatal disease
was spread among them through transfusions of infected blood given
before Romania had blood-screening equipment.
   Tomescu said he expected legalized abortion, new family planning
centers and an improved economy to help ease the problem of
abandoned children and orphans.
   Dr. Marghareta Creteanu, director of Stan's ward at the St.
Catherine Home for Children in Bucharest, said the institution had
admitted only 120 children since January, about half the number of
the same period in 1989.
   Barry Child of Orphanages Trust, a British organization that
aids Romania, said his organization plans to buy some houses and
put two to four children in each, along with subsidized house
parents helped by British volunteers.
   ``This way, fewer would have to live in orphanages'' and fewer
might go to orphanages, where he said ``conditions are absolutely
terrible.''
   Child said the most serious problem in orphanages was
understaffing, ``so we first want to provide groups . . . to teach
the Romanian staff what to do to take good care of the children.''
   Liz Brown, team leader of four young Scottish nurses working as
Orphanages Trust volunteers, said: ``A head nurse won't just jump
in and help . . . as we would in other countries, and this
exacerbates the problem.''
   The deputy health minister, Tomescu, said the government
recognized the problem and had decided to increase the nurse-child
ratio from 1 to 23 to 1 nurse for each 10 children.
   Mariana Gheorghiu, a nurse at the Bucharest home, said the new
policy had not yet taken affect and ``things haven't really changed
much, despite the efforts of some dedicated people who came here to
help.''
   ``We have more milk and meat, but there is a grave crisis in
terms of personnel . . . too many kids, too few nurses,'' she said.
   As she spoke, Ms. Gheorghiu changed the diaper of Gabriela, who
was 9 months old and dying of pneumonia.
   St. Catherine's is known as one of the best children's homes in
Romania. Conditions there are poorer than in the West, but far
better than at other Romanian orphanages.
   David Livianu, director of the American Center for Romanian
Adoptable Children, said adoption is ``their only way out of a
lifetime of struggle and indignity.''
   He took the photographs of 16 children with him to the United
States in August, and said adoptive parents awaited them in the
United States. Livianu recently established an adoption center and
his organization also has offices in the Health Ministry.
   ``It can cost people up to $15,000 to come here, stay in Romania
for months and pay middlemen and lawyers en route to adopting a
child,'' he said. ``We want to . . . encourage people to instead
make donations, which can be used to buy much-needed biomedical
equipment such as incubators.''
   Adoption was simplified in August by repeal of a law that
required presidential approval of all adoptions. Under the new law,
adoptions are handled by local courts and need only the approval of
child-care specialists and the child's parents, if they are alive.
   Dan Koch, 36, the first American to adopt under the new law,
said he ``encountered very little'' bureaucratic delay or
corruption.
   ``I believe it would have taken longer and been more complicated
. . . back home,'' said Koch, who works for the Delaware state
insurance commission.
   He returned to his wife, Kathleen, with 3-year-old Ioan, now
named John Nicholas.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0006 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 2352EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Souter     10-07 0652</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Souter,0846</SECOND>
<HEAD>Souter: The More Things Change, the More He Stays the Same</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Monday AMs report.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By MARGARET LILLARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CONCORD, N.H. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   His presumed ideology has been condemned on
all sides, his housekeeping has been derided and his neckties have
been likened to dishrags, but David Souter's friends say he is a
man content with himself who won't change when he joins the Supreme
Court this week.
   ``Goodness no, that's like saying that Gibraltar could be
changed by a rainstorm,'' said Sen. Warren Rudman, R-N.H., who
preceded Souter as state attorney general and sat behind him all
through Senate confirmation hearings.
   ``David Souter's foundations and values have been built over 51
years,'' Rudman said. ``David hasn't changed at all and will not
change at all.''
   The 51-year-old ascetic bachelor's life has been turned upside
down in the past few months as he went from a little-known regional
jurist to one of the nation's nine most powerful judges.
   Liberals and conservatives alike have voiced suspicions that
he'll vote against them on abortion, civil rights and other social
issues. Journalists have scrutinized everything from his suits to
how he'll cope with crime, noise and high real estate prices in the
nation's capital.
   But friends say he ultimately will be the soft-spoken,
even-tempered man he always has been whether he is in Weare, N.H.,
or Washington, where he moved this weekend to get ready to join the
court Tuesday.
   ``He's in a constant whirl of change, but he will be himself
wherever he is. ... He is satisfied with who he is,'' said Concord
lawyer Tom Rath, Souter's deputy and successor as attorney general.
   Throughout a barrage of public and media scrutiny that began
when President Bush nominated him to the court July 23, Souter
remained polite, almost courtly, to anyone who begged a minute.
   ``No trouble at all,'' he told a apologetic reporter who called
him at his Weare farmhouse - the phone number is still in the book
- the day he returned from Senate Judiciary Committee hearings.
   ``That's David Souter,'' Rudman said. ``He is without a doubt
one of the most self-effacing, gracious people I have ever met.''
   But, Rath noted, ``I think there were moments when that sort of
basic nature of him - good natured, unfailingly courteous - was
tested.''
   Some of those moments included an inventory of Souter's ancient
kitchen appliances made by reporters peeking through his windows
while he was in Washington meeting senators.
   Souter joked about it: ``When I think of all the things I should
have left out if I'd known somebody was going to peek - but I'll
never have that chance again.''
   In reality, he was annoyed, Rudman and Rath said.
   ``He didn't like that and he felt people overstepped their
bounds, but I think he understood that for a few weeks or months
he'd have to endure it,'' Rudman said.
   Rath said friends tried to make sure that Souter's courtesy
didn't allow people to take advantage of him.
   ``I got angry a couple of times, very angry the first Friday he
got back and ... he went over to see his mother,'' said Rath, who
acted as Souter's press agent and personal sentry after the
nomination.
   Souter, he recalled, went in the back door of his mother's home
in a Concord retirement community. Immediately, reporters converged
on the front entrance.
   ``The man hadn't even seen his mother and four or five reporters
were knocking on his door. I said, `Look, fellows, come over here
and interview me.' ''
   Even well-wishing neighbors created some problems, although
Souter and Rath said their support was appreciated.
   ``He told me the other day that he parked his car at the post
office to mail a package and it took him 45 minutes to get from his
car to the window,'' Rath said. ``People are warm and friendly and
such, but it gets wearing.''
   Everyone in Souter's circle are happy that the attention is
abating.
   ``I think there's a feeling of enormous relief,'' Rath said.
``This is a man who likes his work. And the fact that he hasn't
been able to work for the last 2{ months has been hard.''
   Once he goes back to work, he'll stay there, eschewing the
Washington social scene that already has chosen him one of its most
eligible bachelors, Rudman predicted.
   ``He will be here as he was in New Hampshire, essentially
extraordinarily hard-working,'' he said.
   ``If anybody in this city thinks that those phonies who send him
those power invitations will get their hands on him, they are in
for one terrible disappointment,'' said Rudman, whose dislike for
the social whirl is well known.
   ``As of Monday at 5 p.m.,'' when Souter will take the first of
two oaths of office, Rudman said, ``he will essentially disappear
as a person who is seen in the scene here in this city.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0007 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 2353EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Japan-Military     10-07 0791</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Japan-Military,0965</SECOND>
<HEAD>Despite Prospects of Bigger Role, Japan's Military Still An
Outcast</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Monday AMs report.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By MICHAEL HIRSH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ASAKA, Japan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Fabled in history but reviled today, Japan's
military leads the life of a second-class citizen in this country
where pacifism is not just a policy but a constitutional vow.
   On Sunday, the Self Defense Forces celebrated their 36th
anniversary on a remote parade ground in Asaka, just north of
Tokyo. The field bristled with the latest surface-to-air missiles,
tanks and other high-tech weapons.
   Finance Minister Ryutaro Hashimoto, reviewing the troops,
assured them the nation stood behind their ``noble and important
mission.''
   But on the streets of Japan, soldiers are often harassed as
``tax thiefs.'' And in Parliament, the military's voice is rarely
heard, despite the governing conservative party's push for a more
active military role overseas in response to the Persian Gulf
crisis.
   Indeed, custom dictates that top military officials are not even
invited to government policy-making meetings. An audience with the
emperor, an honor treasured by new Cabinet ministers, is denied the
chairman of the joint chiefs of staff.
   ``Sentiment here is still very strong 45 years after the war.
People detest things military,'' said Masashi Nishihara, a
professor at Japan's Defense Academy. ``Even today, the SDF does
not make its views known officially.''
   Tomohisa Sakanaka, a defense expert at Aoyama Gakuin University,
said political leaders are ``very scared of treating the military
in an honored way. They'd prefer to disengage them from the
mainstream.''
   The stated mission of the military's 275,000 ground, sea and air
forces is the defense of Japan and its sea lanes to a distance of
1,000 miles, ostensibly against Communist aggression in the Far
East.
   The military's 1,220 tanks, 55 destroyers, 14 submarines and 320
jet fighters are prevented from going farther by Japan's
constitution, which bars the use of force overseas. The
all-volunteer force was formed as part of the U.S. security
umbrella, which includes about 50,000 troops stationed here.
   But the military's mission was conceived in 1954, when the Cold
War was in full swing and Japan had barely recovered from the ashes
of World War II.
   Today, this resource-poor country, whose status as the world's
No. 2 economy rests on a far-flung network of raw-material imports,
faces the task of redefining what constitutes its national
security.
   The danger at home has receded in the face of Soviet
liberalization and Japan's new detente with China and North Korea.
And dangers abroad are growing, as signaled by the crisis in the
Middle East, from where Japan gets 70 percent of its oil.
   As a result, Parliament will be hotly debating this fall just
how far self-defense should extend. Prime Minister Toshiki Kaifu
has proposed sending a smal number of non-combat troops to the
Persian Gulf under the U.N. flag. And he insists ``the people will
listen to me'' about the need to expand the military's mission.
   He'd better have a good explanation.
   In museums and television dramas, the brave samurai of
yesteryear is as popular as ever. But modern Japan remains haunted
by darker preoccupations: the nation's more than 1,000 years of
military rule, when ruthless warlords dominated civil
administrators and emperor alike.
   It happened once too often. In the 1930s, militarists again rose
up and broke free of civilian control, shattering Japan's shaky
first attempt at constitutional democracy. The result was the
catastrophic Pacific War, the only defeat suffered by this
intensely proud nation on its own soil.
   Japan's surrender brought a psychological about-face. The
U.S.-imposed constitution that ``forever'' forbids war remains an
unyielding article of faith here.
   Perhaps the war's most enduring legacy, though, was that it
erased from many Japanese minds the idea of military power as a
necessity.
   ``A whole generation of Japanese has grown up without any
consciousness of the need for military strength,'' said Minoru
Hirano, a vice principal at a Tokyo high school.
   Much of the blame for that can be laid on the nation's
educators, who were deeply shamed over the role they played in
indoctrinating prewar youth to die for the emperor, said Sakanaka,
the defense expert.
   Today, the main slogan of the powerful Nikkyoso teachers union
remains, ``Never send our students to the battlefield again.''
   Other Asian nations, still bitter over Japan's brutal wartime
incursions into China, Korea, the Philippines and other countries,
view the slightest rumblings of Japanese militarism with the same
fear that Europe has traditionally felt toward a resurgent Germany.
   Almost all experts here agree that a newly aggressive Japan is
unlikely, despite its ranking among the world's top five military
spenders at $31 billion a year.
   Surveys since the Aug. 2 Iraqi invasion of Kuwait consistently
show that more than 60 percent of Japanese oppose an overseas role
for the military.
   ``Because we've been at peace for so long and no one's conscious
of any danger, none of us really think about the Self Defense
Forces at all,'' said Manabu Watanabe, 21, one of a group of
college students munching hamburgers at a Wendy's in Tokyo.
   Partly because of such sentiments, officials acknowledge
difficulty in annually recruiting 20,000 new soldiers from Japan's
population more than 120 million people. That's despite starting
wages of about $880 a month, 21 percent higher than for U.S.
soldiers.
   Moreover, some who join are stung by U.S. criticism that Japan
has shirked its global responsibilities by sending money but few
men to the Persian Gulf.
   ``We can't be full members of the free world society,'' said an
officer quoted recently in local news, ``if we do not shed blood to
protect world security.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0008 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 2353EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Japan-Constitution     10-07 0370</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Japan-Constitution,0421</SECOND>
<HEAD>Experts Say Japan's Constitution Leaves Room for Overseas Forces</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Monday AMs report.</NOTE>
<HEAD>With PM-Japan-Military</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MICHAEL HIRSH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Japan's ``peace'' constitution, the focus of angry
debate over the use of force overseas, actually leaves plenty of
room for dispatching troops to the Persian Gulf, analysts say.
   In fact, they point out, the existence of Japan's Self Defense
Forces already violates the constitution. The real battleground is
political, not legal, the experts say.
   ``I don't think the constitution is a real constraint,'' said
Seizaburo Sato, a Tokyo University politics professor. ``What's
lacking is courageous leadership on the part of the prime
minister.''
   The key constitutional provision, adopted under the U.S.
occupation after World War II, is Article 9. It states that ``the
Japanese people forever renounce war as a sovereign right of the
nation and the threat or use of force as a means of settling
international disputes.''
   ``In order to accomplish the aim of the preceding paragraph,''
it continues, ``land, sea and air forces, as well as other war
potential, will never be maintained.''
   In the 1950s, the government decided that the ban on land, sea
and air forces was not intended to deprive the nation of its
sovereign right to self-defense. The Self Defense Forces were born.
   Today, scholars say, the ruling conservative party, the Liberal
Democrats, could just as easily reinterpret Article 9 to justify a
combat role for Prime Minister Toshiki Kaifu's proposed U.N. Peace
Cooperation Corps - particularly in view of other countervailing
constitutional provisions.
   The constitution's preamble, for example, says that Japan seeks
an honorable place in international society and its struggle
against oppression.
   ``If we pay attention to that clause it means we should be
involved in United Nations peacekeeping,'' even if that means
battle, said Masashi Nishihara, a professor at Japan's Defense
Academy.
   ``Also, Article 2 of the U.N. charter describes the principles
of each member nation. It says members should not resort to the
threat or use of force. It matches our Article 9.
   ``So if we are going to work under the U.N. flag, then such a
collective security action does not constitute the threat or use of
force,'' he said.
   Nonetheless, the government insists the peace corps will be used
only for non-combat activities, such as transportation. Critics say
this is mostly because of heavy public opinion against an overseas
military role and the ruling party's weakness in Parliament.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0009 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 2354EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Brazil-Amazon     10-07 0649</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Brazil-Amazon,0768</SECOND>
<HEAD>Brazilian Elections Bad News for Ecologists</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Monday AMs report.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By KEN SILVERSTEIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>RIO DE JANEIRO, Brazil (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The sweeping victories by
conservatives in last week's congressional and gubernatorial races
will mean bad news for the rain forest and its defenders,
environmentalists say.
   Conservatives won a large majority in last week's voting, and
showed special strength in the nine states of the Amazon region.
   ``Almost all . . . are totally opposed to ecological concerns
and rational development,'' Fernando Gabeira, a leader of Brazil's
small Green Party, said over the weekend.
   The federal government sets most environmental policy, but
political scientist David Fleischer of the University of Brasilia
noted: ``Almost all policy enforcement is carried out by local
authorities. If they show no interest in protecting the
environment, decisions at the federal level lose much of their
impact.''
   Right-wing candidates for governor won outright victories in
three of the nine states and were headed for Nov. 25 runoffs in the
other six.
   Only in two small states, Acre and Amapa, did pro-ecology
candidates even get to the runoffs.
   Candidates had to win an absolute majority to take a first-round
victory.
   In congressional races, conservatives won at least 11 of the 13
senate chairs at stake in the Amazon region and all but a few of
the house seats.
   Rightist populists have long dominated the impoverished region.
Much of their success comes from support by major landowners, who
traditionally control the votes of the rural poor.
   Many voters also view environmentalism as an attempt to block
economic growth and lock the Amazon into perennial backwardness.
   Slash-and-burn techniques used by ranchers and farmers have
already destroyed about 8 percent of the 2-million-square-mile
wilderness, according to government figures.
   In Amazonas, the area's largest state, incoming governor
Gilberto Mestrinho favors widescale destruction of the rain forest
to promote large mining and agricultural projects.
   The state's new senator, Amazonino Mendes, proposed handing out
chain saws to settlers to speed the felling of the forest.
   In neighboring Roraima state, both gubernatorial finalists
openly opposed federal plans to remove thousands of gold miners
from the territory of the Yanomami Indians, the world's largest
remaining primitive tribe.
   The miners illegally search for gold, diamonds and other
minerals on Indian land. Armed clashes and imported diseases killed
about 1,500 of the tribe's remaining 9,000 members in the past
three years.
   The favorite in Roraima's gubernatorial race is Romero Juca, now
on trial for illegally authorizing logging on Indian land when he
was chief of the National Indian Foundation in the early 1980s.
   ``The elections in Roraima could spell the end for the
Yanomami,'' Fleischer remarked,
   In Para state, the runoff pits anti-ecology candidates Jaber
Barbalho and Sahid Xerfan.
   Para has been the site of repeated clashes between Indians and
miners. Miners have dumped about 600 tons of mercury from gold
prospecting into the Tapajos River.
   ``We have no preference in Para,'' Gabeira said. ``Neither
possible winner will defend the Indians or the Amazon.''
   Big farmers are blamed for most of the violence plaguing the
region. More than 1,000 peasant activists were killed in land
conflicts in the past decade.
   The Rev. Ricardo Resende of the Pastoral Land Commission said in
a phone interview from Para state, ``The new governors are well
known and most have never demonstrated any interest in protecting
the region's poor. Small farmers will continue to be expelled from
their land.''
   His commission is linked with the Roman Catholic Church.
   Gabeira said the only bright spot was in Acre, home to thousands
of rubber tappers, where Jorge Viana of the pro-environmentalist
Workers Party won a spot in the second round.
   His strength is largely attributed to the legacy of
world-renowned unionist and ecologist Chico Mendes, a Workers Party
activist murdered in 1988. Mendes' alleged killers are going on
trial Oct. 25, and the publicity could boost Viana's campaign.
   There was another note of encouragement to the rain forest's
advocates Sunday contained in an article in the newspaper Jornal do
Brasil.
   It reported that the area of the Amazon rain forest destroyed by
fires in 1990 was down considerably from last year. Data compiled
by Brazil's National Institute of Space Research showed overall
destruction may be down by as much as 50 percent, the newspaper
said.
   Institute President Marcio Barbosa was quoted as saying that the
space satellite that monitors the Amazon has been crucial to
efforts to prevent further damage.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0010 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 2354EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Mitchell-Obit     10-07 0096</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mitchell-Obit,100</SECOND>
<HEAD>Global Warming Expert Dies</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   J. Murray Mitchell, 62, a retired senior
research climatologist and meteorologist with the National Oceanic
and Atmosphere Administration, has died of lymphoma.
   Mitchell was a leading authority on climatology and the study of
long-term weather trends and the impact of climate change on
populations.
   He was the among the scientists who warned for years about the
potential impact of global warming on Earth's environment.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0011 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 2355EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Gulf-Desert     10-07 0482</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Gulf-Desert,0603</SECOND>
<HEAD>Desert Sand Wears Out Helicopters, Provides Few Landmarks for
Pilots</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Monday AMs report.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto DHA3 sent Oct. 7.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By NEIL MacFARQUHAR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAUDI ARABIA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The sands of the Saudi desert are chewing
through helicopter parts much faster than expected, causing
problems for U.S. anti-tank Apaches and Cobras, Army officers say.
   The helicopters belong to the 24th Mechanized Division's air
brigade of Fort Stewart, Ga., which holds some of the most forward
positions of the growing U.S. force in northeastern Saudi Arabia.
   The helicopter crews have trained in California's Mojave Desert.
But despite similrities in the terrain, the sands of the Mojave
did not scour as the Saudi sand does, officers and maintenance
personnel said.
   The 24th's helicopters include the high-tech AH-64A Apache and
AH-1 Cobra gunships, OH-58 Kiowas used to scout enemy tank
formations; UH-60 Blackhawk and UH-1 Huey transporters and those
fitted for electronic warfare.
   Despite the maintenance burden, at least 70 percent of the
aircraft are operational at any given moment, said the brigade
commander, Col. Burt Tackaberry, 43, of Jacksonville, Fla.
   He said the rate had dipped into the 60 percent range when the
brigade first moved into its desert camp 10 days ago. But he said
it would not go that low again after flying hours were reduced.
   Defense Department ground rules prohibit mentioning exact
numbers or locations.
   Tackaberry said the brigade does not have its full supplies of
spare parts yet, but he was confident it could start fighting a war
if necessary. The U.S. force is facing off Iraqi troops following
Iraq's Aug. 2 invasion of neighboring Kuwait.
   The colonel said the Apaches have so many backup systems - three
radio systems, for example, and two types of night vision equipment
- that the failure of one would not knock the helicopter out of
combat.
   But desert sand is wearing out the surface of the rotary blades.
Also, fine sand sucked into the hot engines can melt into glass
that chips and ruts internal parts in the turbines.
   Sand clogs the starting valves and it gets between the twin
panes of the windshield, reducing visibility.
   ``The sand is at work and so are we,'' said Warrant Officer
Richard L. Paradis, 38, of Pooler, Ga., a member of one of the
brigade's two maintenance teams.
   ``We go through a lot of main rotor blades, a lot of tail
blades,'' he said. ``In the desert, we're using about five times as
much.''
   The main engines have to be pulled and cleaned after every 250
hours of flying time, something that does not happen under usual
conditions.
   Staving off wear and tear on the machines requires all sorts of
ingenuity.
   Coats of rubbery epoxy paint are to be added to the front edge
rotary blades to slow the corrosion. The maintenance teams are
experimenting with ways of keeping dust out of the engines, such as
fitting the engines with the tough, flat scouring pads used in many
kitchens.
   Navigation is also a problem. The crews who trained in the
Mojave are having to learn from scratch how to navigate in the
featureless terrain south of the border with occupied Kuwait.
   ``Occasionally you see a few dried up lake beds and camel
herds,'' said Capt. Kelly Marunde, 30, head of air traffic control
and the sole female company commander in the aviation brigade.
   ``But the herds move and the sand blows, so you can't really
rely on anything being there the next day.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0012 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 0337EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i BC-Austria-Elections     10-07 0359</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Austria-Elections,0393</SECOND>
<HEAD>Austrian Elections: Leader Tries to Contain Right-of-center
Opponent</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROLAND PRINZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>VIENNA, Austria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Chancellor Franz Vranitzky, a Socialist,
is trying to stem the rising fortunes of a right-of-center opponent
and the Green movement in national elections Sunday.
   The latest polls showed an unprecedented 23 percent of voters
unsure which party they prefer, raising great uncertainty as
Austrians began casting ballots at 7 a.m. The last voting stations
close at 5 p.m. (noon EDT).
   Voter surveys indicate the most likely outcome is that the
governing socialist-conservative coalition will remain in control
of Parliament. The coalition consists of Vranitzky's Socialist
Party and the conservative Austrian People's Party, which is led by
Vice Chancellor Josef Riegler.
   However, the two major parties stand to lose seats to the
right-of-center Freedom Party of populist Joerg Haider; and, to a
lesser extent, the environmental Green Alternative Party.
   Haider, governor of the southern Carinthia province, has won
considerable popularity for his often witty remarks. He has often
resorted to abusive language in criticizing the leaders of the
governing coalition and their policies.
   The 53-year-old chancellor has rejected any possibility of a
coalition with Haider, who is accused by many Socialists of
appealing to advocates of rightist policies.
   Some conservatives are considering the possibility of forming a
right-of-center coalition with the Freedom Party. However, Riegler
said he does not want to cooperate with Haider.
   In the 1986 elections, the Socialists gained 80 seats, the
People's Party 77, the Freedom Party 18 and the Greens 8.
   On Sunday, a total of 5,628,913 people, including for the first
time 21,232 Austrians living abroad, were registered to vote for
the 183 parliamentary deputies.
   Haider said he hopes the Freedom Party wins between 25 and 30
seats at the expense of the two major parties. The Greens also want
to double their seats.
   The tiny Communist Party and a few other small political parties
have virtually no chance of gaining seats.
   The election campaign was generally lackluster, though marked by
some name-calling. Major party leaders refrained from sharp
attacks, possibly with a view toward maintaining the governing
coalition.
   No single issue predominated. Candidates debated immigration and
Austrian efforts to win membership in the European Community, the
European nations working to integrate their economies.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0013 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 0444EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a BC-SpaceShuttle     10-07 0331</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Space Shuttle,0373</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ulysses Probes Zips Across Space, Astronauts Conduct Experiments</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SPACE CENTER, Houston (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Ulysses probe sprinted through
space Sunday on its five-year trip to study the sun, while the
Discovery astronauts who dispatched the craft turned their
attention to scientific experiments.
   Ulysses, an atomic-powered spacecraft released from the shuttle
Saturday, was traveling about 34,130 mph, the fastest speed ever
for a manmade object.
   ``It's outbound and doing well,'' flight director Gary Coen
said.
   Discovery's five astronauts got up early Sunday morning to begin
a day of experiments that included lighting a small controlled
fire, growing plant roots and testing a system in which shuttle
cameras are maneuvered by voice commands.
   Mission Control awakened the crew with a song written and
performed by Boeing Aerospace &amp; Electronics Co. employees as a
tribute to the successful deployment of the probe, partially
boosted into space by a Boeing-built rocket.
   ``Sailing along, sailing along, flying to explore the galaxy,''
the aerospace workers sang.
   No problems with the space shuttle were reported, Coen said.
``Everybody is real happy that things are going so smoothly,'' he
said.
   Saturday was a banner-day for the space agency, which has
suffered through months of frustrating problems with its space
shuttles and the flawed Hubble Space Telescope.
   First, the Discovery thundered into space just 12 minutes behind
schedule. A minor weather problem and a last-minute technical
glitch caused the delay of the first shuttle launch in nearly six
months.
   Six hours later, the crew deployed the Ulysses sun probe - the
primary goal of the mission.
   After a roundabout journey, Ulysses is scheduled to pass over
the sun's south pole in 1994, then curve over the north solar pole.
The sun's poles cannot be seen from Earth and have never been
examined closely by scientists.
   Discovery is scheduled to land Wednesday in the California
desert. The mission wasn't affected by the shutdown of many federal
agencies because funds for the mission already had been set aside,
officials said.
   The shuttle commander is Richard N. Richards, and the other crew
members are pilot Robert D. Cabana and mission specialists William
M. Shepherd, Bruce Melnick and Thomas D. Akers.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0014 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 1129EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p BC-LouisianaPrimary     10-07 0287</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Louisiana Primary,0331</SECOND>
<HEAD>Johnston Overcomes Duke Challenge to Win Fourth Term</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW ORLEANS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Sen. J. Bennett Johnston overcame a strong
challenge from white supremacist David Duke and won a fourth term
in office without the need for a runoff.
   ``My friends, I am here to tell you tonight: We did it!''
Johnston shouted to supporters after Saturday's victory, which
calmed the fears of Louisiana's political establishment, Democratic
and Republican alike.
   In final, unofficial results, Johnston, a Democrat, had 749,552
votes or 54 percent and Duke, a Republican, had 605,681 votes or 44
percent. Two minor Democratic candidates divided the remainder:
Nick Accardo had 21,709 votes and Larry Crowe had 14,472 votes.
   Duke's strong candidacy had rattled leaders of both parties, and
prompted the endorsed Republican candidate, state Sen. Ben Bagert,
to drop out of the race last week out of fear that he could force a
runoff between Duke and Johnston.
   Duke, a state representative, is a former grand wizard of the Ku
Klux Klan. Although he claims to have reformed since his Klan days,
he has been successful in mainstream politics by preaching civil
rights for white people and attacking affirmative action and the
welfare system.
   Duke, appearing before supporters, refused to concede and said
Johnston would not get the majority needed to avoid a runoff. He
threatened a court fight over the issue of whether absentee ballots
cast for Bagert before he dropped out should be counted.
   ``All I can tell you is that we have not yet begun to fight,''
Duke said.
   Also Saturday, Louisiana voters overwhelmingly approved a state
lottery, and New Orleans moved closer to electing its first black
congressman since Reconstruction. State Sen. William Jefferson and
Marc Morial, the son of former Mayor Dutch Morial, headed a field
of 12 for a Nov. 6 runoff in the 2nd District replace retiring Rep.
Lindy Boggs, the only white House member to represent a majority
black district.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0015 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 1142EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--CrocodileAttack     10-07 0153</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Crocodile Attack,0165</SECOND>
<HEAD>Son Saves Mother From Crocodile By Poking Its Eye</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DARWIN, Australia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A 14-foot-long crocodile attacked a
woman and started carrying her away in its jaws, but her son
rescued her by jumping on the reptile's back and poking it in the
eye, police said Sunday.
   The woman, who was not identified, was attacked Saturday night
while sleeping next to a creek in the Daly River Aboriginal
reserve, about 120 miles south of Darwin in the Northern Territory.
   Ray Musgrave, Daly River police constable, said the woman's
30-year-old son jumped on top of the crocodile and poked it in the
eye as it tried to retreat with his mother in its jaws. The
crocodile then released the woman, police said.
   Musgrave said the pair had been sleeping in a mesh tent with the
woman's husband and five other children.
   Officials said the woman was taken to a Darwin hospital, where
she was in stable but critical condition.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0016 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 1146EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Soviet-Hijack     10-07 0276</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Hijack,0326</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hijacking of Soviet Flight Foiled by Crew, Passengers</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The crew and passengers of an Aeroflot plane
overpowered a man who tried to hijack it Sunday to Sweden in the
latest of a series of hijacking attempts in the Soviet Union, Tass
reported.
   The man threatened to blow up the An-24 turboprop plane if it
was not diverted to Stockholm, the Soviet news agency said. The
plane was flying from Perm, a city in central Russia 840 miles east
of Moscow, to Arkhangelsk, in the northwestern part of the country.
   As the plane was preparing to land in the city of Kotlas, about
halfway to Arkhangelsk, the crew ``decided to take the risk, and
with the help of the passengers, disarmed the hijacker,'' Tass
reported.
   The man, identified only as Gavrilov, a 26-year-old unemployed
resident of Perm, had no bomb, Tass said.
   Tass did not provide any other details about the incident,
including how many people were aboard the plane and how the man was
overpowered. An An-24 can seat about 45 people.
   On Friday, an unarmed Soviet man forced an Aeroflot airliner on
a domestic flight to land in Finland, where he requested political
asylum. The man, identified as Nikolai I. Selivanov, had threatened
to blow up the plane if it did not go to Stockholm, but he was told
there wasn't enough fuel and it landed in Helsinki instead.
   There have been more than a dozen hijackings or attempted
hijackings of Aeroflot flights this year.
   Five of the flights were hijacked to Finland or Sweden. Four of
the hijackers have been extradited to the Soviet Union, and one was
granted political asylum in Sweden.
   Finnish aviation and police officials have requested
negotiations with the Soviets to deter hijackers, but the Soviets
have not answered the request.
   In addition, plainclothes police have been flying aboard some
Aeroflot planes to deter possible hijackers.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0017 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 1149EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AP-NoKeywordFiled!     10-07 0645</FIRST>
<SECOND>Souter: The More Things Change, the More He Stays the Same</SECOND>
<BYLINE>By MARGARET LILLARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CONCORD, N.H. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   His presumed ideology has been condemned on
all sides, his husekeeping has been derided and his neckties have
been likened to dishrags, but David Souter's friends say he is a
man content with himself who won't change when he joins the Supreme
Court this week.
   ``Goodness no, that's like saying that Gibraltar could be
changed by a rainstorm,'' said Sen. Warren Rudman, R-N.H., who
preceded Souter as state attorney general and sat behind him all
through Senate confirmation hearings.
   ``David Souter's foundations and values have been built over 51
years,'' Rudman said. ``David hasn't changed at all and will not
change at all.''
   The 51-year-old ascetic bachelor's life has been turned upside
down in the past few months as he went from a little-known regional
jurist to one of the nation's nine most powerful judges.
   Liberals and conservatives alike have voiced suspicions that
he'll vote against them on abortion, civil rights and other social
issues. Journalists have scrutinized everything from his suits to
how he'll cope with crime, noise and high real estate prices in the
nation's capital.
   But friends say he ultimately will be the soft-spoken,
even-tempered man he always has been whether he is in Weare, N.H.,
or Washington, where he moved this weekend to get ready to join the
court Tuesday.
   ``He's in a constant whirl of change, but he will be himself
wherever he is. ... He is satisfied with who he is,'' said Concord
lawyer Tom Rath, Souter's deputy and successor as attorney general.
   Throughout a barrage of public and media scrutiny that began
when President Bush nominated him to the court July 23, Souter
remained polite, almost courtly, to anyone who begged a minute.
   ``No trouble at all,'' he told a apologetic reporter who called
him at his Weare farmhouse - the phone number is still in the book
- the day he returned from Senate Judiciary Committee hearings.
   ``That's David Souter,'' Rudman said. ``He is without a doubt
one of the most self-effacing, gracious people I have ever met.''
   But, Rath noted, ``I think there were moments when that sort of
basic nature of him - good natured, unfailingly courteous - was
tested.''
   Some of those moments included an inventory of Souter's ancient
kitchen appliances made by reporters peeking through his windows
while he was in Washington meeting senators.
   Souter joked about it: ``When I think of all the things I should
have left out if I'd known somebody was going to peek - but I'll
never have that chance again.''
   In reality, he was annoyed, Rudman and Rath said.
   ``He didn't like that and he felt people overstepped their
bounds, but I think he understood that for a few weeks or months
he'd have to endure it,'' Rudman said.
   Rath said friends tried to make sure that Souter's courtesy
didn't allow people to take advantage of him.
   ``I got angry a couple of times, very angry the first Friday he
got back and ... he went over to see his mother,'' said Rath, who
acted as Souter's press agent and personal sentry after the
nomination.
   Souter, he recalled, went in the back door of his mother's home
in a Concord retirement community. Immediately, reporters converged
on the front entrance.
   ``The man hadn't even seen his mother and four or five reporters
were knocking on his door. I said, `Look, fellows, come over here
and interview me.' ''
   Even well-wishing neighbors created some problems, although
Souter and Rath said their support was appreciated.
   ``He told me the other day that he parked his car at the post
office to mail a package and it took him 45 minutes to get from his
car to the window,'' Rath said. ``People are warm and friendly and
such, but it gets wearing.''
   Everyone in Souter's circle are happy that the attents
abating.
   ``I think there's a feeling of enormous relief,'' Rath said.
``This is a man who likes his work. And the fact that he hasn't
been able to work for the last 2{ months has been hard.''
   Once he goes back to work, he'll stay there, eschewing the
Washington social scene that already has chosen him one of its most
eligible bachelors, Rudman predicted.
   ``He will be here as he was in New Hampshire, essentially
extraordinarily hard-working,'' he said.
   ``If anybody in this city thinks that those phonies who send him
those power invitations will get their hands on him, they are in
for one terrible disappointment,'' said Rudman, whose dislike for
the social whirl is well known.
   ``As of Monday at 5 p.m.,'' when Souter will take the first of
two oaths of office, Rudman said, ``he will essentially disappear
as a person who is seen in the scene here in this city.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0018 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 1153EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--BikerBandit     10-07 0173</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Biker Bandit,0193</SECOND>
<HEAD>Motorcycle-Bound Thief Strikes For 21st Time</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A motorcycle-bound bandit robbed his 21st bank
Sunday, again evading police pursuit to speed away with his loot.
   The thief has been operating in more than 20 Israeli towns,
robbing banks of a total of about $150,000. He has left no clue and
no description - just a fingerprint that draws a blank in the
police computer.
   The thief, who has been nicknamed ``Bikerbank'' in Hebrew,
always uses the same method. He strikes between 10 a.m. and noon,
and robs the teller nearest to the bank door, firing one shot in
the air from his .38 Smith and Wesson pistol.
   He is about six feet tall, wears cowboy or army boots, has blond
hair and, according to some witnesses, a slight limp. He rides a
Suzuki motorcycle.
   On Sunday morning, he struck at the Bank Hapoalim branch in
Ramat Gan, near Tel Aviv. His loot was $2,500.
   Police erected roadblocks around the robbery area, closed a
major highway leading to Tel Aviv for more than an hour and
searched with helicopters. But their efforts were in vain.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0019 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 1212EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Lebanon-Hostages     10-07 0498</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lebanon-Hostages,0596</SECOND>
<HEAD>Report: Iranian Envoy In Beirut To Finalize Waite's Release</HEAD>
<NOTE>With LaserPhoto</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By MOHAMMED SALAM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BEIRUT, Lebanon (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A newspaper reported Sunday that an
Iranian envoy has arrived in Beirut to prepare for the release of
Anglican Church envoy Terry Waite ``in the next few days.''
   The report by the conservative ad-Diyar could not be confirmed.
The paper is not known to have had special insight into the hostage
issue.
   But the report came amid mounting speculation that one or more
of the four Britons missing in Lebanon could be freed soon. Iran
and Britain restored diplomatic relations on Sept. 27.
   On Saturday, Lebanon's leading newspaper, the independent
an-Nahar daily, said that Waite and ``a number of foreign
hostages'' were expected to be released this week.
   Arab sources in Damascus, Syria's capital, said Sunday that the
Syrians are making strenuous efforts to free some of the 13
Westerners missing in Lebanon. Most are believed held by
pro-Iranian Shiite Moslem militants.
   One source, speaking on condition of anonymity, said Syrian
Foreign Minister Farouk Sharaa is trying hard ``to resolve the
issue but has been encountering unexpected obstacles.''
   He did not elaborate, but noted that Sharaa is expected to meet
soon with Iranian Foreign Minister Ali Akbar Velayati to discuss
the issue. They met last week at the United Nations in New York.
   Speculation also has been fueled by expectations that Britain
and Syria will soon restore relations. Britain broke off ties in
October 1986 after Syrian intelligence was implicated in a plot to
bomb an Israeli airliner at London's Heathrow airport.
   Ad-Diyar said the unidentified Iranian official flew into Beirut
Saturday carrying an Algerian passport.
   ``Secret talks have been held in the last two months and
resulted in agreement on the release operation as well as the final
touches and details,'' the report said. It said the envoy was
assigned to supervise the release, which would come ``in the next
few days.''
   In London, the British Foreign Office said there was nothing to
the report and reiterated British policy that it will not negotiate
to get hostages out.
   Britain and Iran restored diplomatic relations after a 19-month
break triggered by the publication of British author Salman
Rushdie's novel, ``The Satanic Verses.'' Many Moslems say the book
blasphemes Islam.
   Ad-Diyar said Waite's release was expected to be ``the preface
to releasing all British hostages in Lebanon.'' The other missing
Britons are journalist John McCarthy, retired pilot Jack Mann and
writer Alec Collett.
   It said the agreement to release Waite involved a $10 million
``fee to the forces'' who kidnapped him.
   Waite, 51, disappeare Jan. 20, 1987, after leaving his hotel in
Moslem west Beirut for a meeting with representatives of Islamic
Jihad, or Islamic Holy War. The pro-Iranian Shiite Moslem faction
is believed to hold American hostages Terry Anderson and Thomas
Sutherland.
   No group claims to have kidnapped Waite. But a former hostage,
Irishman Brian Keenan, said after he was released by Shiite captors
in August that Waite was held with him for a while.
   Anderson, the chief Middle East correspondent for The Associated
Press, is the longest held of the 13 Western hostages in Lebanon.
He was kidnapped March 16, 1985.
   Iranian President Hashemi Rafsanjani apparently has been seeking
to free the hostages in his drive to improve relations with the
West following the June 1989 death of Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini.
He has been opposed by radicals in his own government.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0020 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 1228EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-LochNessMonster 1stLd-Writethru a0664 10-07 0210</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Loch Ness Monster, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0664,0227</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hunt Ends With No Sign of Beast</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 3rd pvs to CORRECT first reference to company.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>DRUMNADROCHIT, Scotland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A two-day search for the Loch
Ness monster ended Sunday with two blips on a radar screen but no
evidence of the legendary beast.
   National oddsmakers William Hill Organization Ltd., which had
offered 250,000 pounds ($477,500) for ``conclusive evidence'' of
Nessie, kept its reward but paid 1,500 pounds ($2,850) to a
Scottish company for the best search method.
   Oceanscan, which supplies underwater sonar equipment for the
North Sea oil industry, used underwater radar and registered an
unidentified object up to 26 feet long.
   ``The object which showed up yesterday registered as two blips
on the sonar screen but it moved out of range very quickly. We
can't be sure what it was,'' said Andy Gray, Oceanscan's managing
director.
   The three other hunting parties participating in the first major
search in three years came up empty.
   But Daniel Isted, a 25-year-old London editor of a corporate
in-house magazine, managed to catch himself a bride.
   His girlfriend, Dee Smith, accepted his proposal along the shore
of Loch Ness.
   The lake is 754 feet deep, 23 miles long and a mile wide.
   William Hill is offering 100-1 odds that Nessie's existence will
not be authenticated within a year.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0021 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 1237EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-MilitaryLibraries     10-07 0534</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Military Libraries,0660</SECOND>
<HEAD>Books Ahoy! Librarians Ship Out Supplies to Gulf</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf-Life In Exile, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BILL KACZOR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PENSACOLA, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   As U.S. forces were building up in the
Persian Gulf, the cruiser USS LaSalle sent an urgent message to
Saufley Field in the Florida Panhandle.
   The flagship of Operation Desert Shield needed books.
   The LaSalle wanted information on Middle East culture, customs,
history and even artists and authors, recalled library technician
Dot Bibee. The Navy's four-woman Library Services Division had a
shipment on its way in 24 hours, she said.
   ``Whenever we hear from a ship, that's when we jump,'' said
division head Marge Homeyard.
   Titles sent to the LaSalle included ``Saddam's Iraq,'' ``Iraq in
Pictures,'' ``Women at Work in the Gulf'' and ``Images of
Bahrain.''
   This is a busy time for military librarians, who are jumping to
meet a huge demand for books for U.S. troops in the Persian Gulf.
Not all requests are as specialized as the LaSalle's. The military
waiting game in the Gulf has left soldiers and sailors with plenty
of time to read, and their tastes take in the full range of a
library's shelves.
   Among the most popular are techno-military yarns by Tom Clanc,
whose works include ``Hunt for Red October'' and ``Red Storm
Rising,'' and Stephen Coonts, author of ``Flight of the Intruder.''
Horror stories by Stephen King and westerns by Louis L'Amour also
are popular, and the increasing number of women in the military has
created a demand for novels by romance authors such as Danielle
Steel.
   Paperbacks are preferred.
   ``They are the go-anywhere type of books,'' said Willie Quinley,
another library technician. ``Stash one in your back pocket and you
can go to the john with it. It's kind of hard to do that with a
hardback.''
   Shipboard libraries even include children's books. Military
parents can record themselves reading the stories and send the
tapes to their children.
   Shipments for the Persian Gulf are screened to avoid sending
books that might offend the conservative host countries by being
too violent or sexy, including covers with pictures of scantily
clad women.
   ``To the extent possible, we are sanitizing,'' Homeyard said.
That, however, was not possible for ships that sailed into the
region with existing libraries.
   ``To some extent, we have our fingers crossed we are not going
to have an international incident over a library book,'' Homeyard
said.
   The library supply operation is part of the Naval Education and
Training Program Management Support Activity at Saufley, a former
flight training auxiliary base a few miles from the Pensacola Naval
Air Station.
   In addition to ships, the agency supplies books to 147 Navy and
27 Marine Corps shore libraries and 343 units at remote sites.
   The Air Force and Army have similar library functions at
Randolph Air Force Base, Texas, and Arlington, Va. The services
have been working together to supply books to their troops in the
Persian Gulf.
   Navy library activities in the Gulf are headed by Lt. Cmdr. Gary
Simons, who like most library officers is a chaplain.
   Simons sent a message Sept. 23 from Bahrain to report that
Desert Shield sailors were enjoying their books but that his supply
was exhausted. His message, like the one from the LaSalle, received
immediate attention.
   The division scrounged through its own stash of mostly review
books to ship 23 boxes. It arranged for 15 more from the aircraft
carrier USS Kitty Hawk, which is being overhauled in Philadelphia
and is now overstocked with books, Quinley said.
   An illustrated book on body building, male and female, was
deleted.
   ``Not only were (the models) scantily clad, it had Venus, the
statue of the naked lady, and a male (statue) also,'' Quinley said.
``It may be art, but they might not understand if it got in the
wrong hands.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0022 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 1240EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-SouthwestLawsuit CORRECTIVE   10-07 0130</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Southwest Lawsuit, CORRECTIVE,0124</SECOND>
<HEAD>Members who used AM-Southwest Lawsuit, which moved as a0768 on Oct.
5 under a Dallas dateline, are asked to use the following story.</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DALLAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Associated Press reported incorrectly that a
federal lawsuit against Southwest Airlines alleged the company had
failed to hire a pilot older than 45 since 1987.
   The lawsuit alleges that Southwest has failed to hire enough
pilots older than 45 during that time.
   The incorrect information was contained in a press release from
the U.S. Equal Opportunity Commission.
   An EEOC spokeswoman on Saturday said the release was in error.
She agreed with a Southwest statement contained in the original
story that the airline had hired 39 pilots older than 45 since
1987.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0023 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 1246EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-LifeinExile Bjt   10-07 0514</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Life in Exile, Bjt,0636</SECOND>
<HEAD>Kuwaiti Gov't Conducts Affairs Of State - From A Luxury Hotel</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MORT ROSENBLUM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Special Correspondent</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TAIF, Saudi Arabia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The royal government of Kuwait,
shielded by Saudi guards and served by an army of room service
waiters, meets regularly on the affairs of a state its Iraqi
occupiers claim no longer exists.
   Its Cabinet room is a plushly appointed suite in the Al Hada
Sheraton, a mountaintop resort that is temporarily out of business
as a hotel.
   The government's records and reports - the apparatus of
displaced rulers struggling to keep their emirate together from a
distance - are stuffed in dressers, back rooms and broom closets.
   In stark contrast to the foreign refugees from Kuwait stranded
in Jordanian desert camps, Kuwaiti officials pad about in cooled
air on thick carpets, soothed by plaintive Arabic melodies from
speakers.
   On a recent afternoon, a Lebanese merchant lugged in a suitcase
full of gold Swiss watches for idle customers. It was clear that
time hung heavily on their hands.
   Men in snowy white Arab headgear and shirt-gowns float about the
quiet corridors. In between flurries of activity, they sip coffee,
dine elaborately or nap at length.
   About 300 Kuwaiti officials and family members live in bungalows
on the grounds. Unruly children scamper about colorful gardens
inside high fences. Offices and staff rooms are in the seven-story
main building.
   Hotel shops are closed, except for the Bangladeshi scent man in
the lobby. In flasks out of ``1001 Nights,'' he sells 500 aromas,
along with fragrant resins, exotic wood chips and Paris perfumes.
   ``Try this,'' he said, slashing a browser's hand with pungent
oil. ``It's called `Queen of the Night.'''
   Not even Saudi police cars get past the barrier at the front
gate without a coded pass and a rigorous check. Authorized visitors
surrender their passports for a green badge which, in turn, is
traded for a pink badge.
   A thorough but good-natured security chief named Mohammed,
referring to the Iraqi invasion, jokes with foreigners that they
will be free to leave whenever they wish.
   Once inside, visitors are showered in courtly hospitality and
prodded for news.
   During a recent interview, Sheik Saad al Abdullah al Salim
al-Sabah, the Kuwaiti crown prince and prime minister, punctuated a
reporter's queries with questions of his own.
   Seven neat stacks of regional newspapers lay at anyone's
disposal in the lobby. But most information filters in slowly from
the dwindling number of Kuwaiti refugees who make it out of their
homeland.
   Few officials are anxious to be named in news dispatches for
fear their relatives back home might suffer.
   Pointing to a colleague, one Kuwaiti said: ``He just found out
three days ago that his brother was carried off to Baghdad to work
as a technician for the Iraqi Air Force. I don't think he wants to
talk about it.''
   The Information Ministry is on the first floor, obvious from the
stacks of poster-sized photos in the hallway.
   One is the celebrated scene of Saddam Hussein patting a visibly
uncomfortable British hostage boy. Next to it, a poster shows Adolf
Hitler caressing a pleased German youth of similar age.
   Nearby, several dozen different photos of Iraqi atrocities and
damage to Kuwait are piled high on a counter. But there are few
takers.
   After a month in the hotel, spirits are still high, assured
Hamad Jabal al-Sabah, a ministry official and son of the prime
minister. ``Maybe we'll be back in Kuwait by the end of the
month.''
   But some others seemed dubious. More than one Kuwaiti has noted
the irony in the housing advertisement displayed in each of the
hotel's elevators: ``You'll love the life at the Sheraton.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0024 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 1320EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u p AM-DukeConcedes -URGENT-   10-07 0293</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Duke Concedes,0355</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<HEAD>Duke Concedes Johnston Won Re-Election</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: will be incorporated in the AM-Louisiana Primary, Bjt</NOTE>
<DATELINE>NEW ORLEANS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Former Ku Klux Klansman David Duke conceded
Sunday that U.S. Sen. Bennett Johnston was re-elected in the
Louisiana open primary and said he would not challenge the outcome
in court.
   ``I'm here to concede the election to Bennett Johnston, but I'm
not going to concede or relinquish my commitment to the principle
of equal rights for every American,'' Duke, a first-term state
representative, told a news conference.
   In complete but unofficial returns form the Saturday voting,
Johnston had 54 percent of the vote and Duke 44 percent.
   As the vote was counted, Duke had said he would ask for a court
order to challenge absentee votes that were cast before Ben Bagert,
the official Republican candidate, dropped out on Thursday. Under
state law, any votes for Bagert were not counted after he dropped
out.
   Though he backed off on the idea of filing his own challenge,
Duke said Sunday that his organization would support any individual
who wanted to pursue the matter in court.
   ``We'll help people who feel their right to vote has been
abrogated,'' he said. ``We'll help them pursue that if they so
desire, but I'm trying to do - as Bennett Johnston said - and kind
of heal at this point.
   ``I want to see the state together. I want people to get behind
Bennett but I want them to make sure that Bennett pursues policies
that are good for the people of Louisiana.''
   Bagert dropped out and encouraged his backers to vote for
Bennett after polls showed him running a distant third in the race.
Several Republicans in the U.S. Senate also took the unusual step
of backing Democrat Johnston in the primary, saying they didn't
want the former Klansman to force Johnston into a runoff.
   Under the state's open primary, candidates all run in one
primary, regardless of party. If no one candidate gains a majority
of the votes, a runoff is held among the top two vote-getters.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0025 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 1334EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p AM-IllinoisSenate     10-07 0546</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Illinois Senate,620</SECOND>
<HEAD>Simon Runs Into Integrity Questions, But Leaves Challenger Far
Behind</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Louisiana Primary Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ED WHITE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Republican Rep. Lynn Martin has portrayed
Illinois Sen. Paul Simon as a tax-happy liberal and a
string-pulling Washington insider, but neither approach appears to
have helped much in her race to unseat him.
   Martin was trailing Simon by a 2-to-1 margin in a recent poll
and her underfinanced campaign hasn't run television ads for more
than a week.
   With the Nov. 6 election closing in, she has been unable to
catch Simon even though the former crime-fighting newspaper editor
has been tarnished by questions about his conduct in two cases:
   - That he called a San Francisco bank urging officials to
negotiate a settlement with Michael Ballis, a developer and Simon
fund-raiser involved in a dispute over a construction project.
   - And that he wrote to the Higher Education Assistance
Foundation on behalf of a now-closed cooking school, whose owner
then made two $1,000 in-kind contributions to Simon's campaign.
HEAF, a guarantor of the government-backed loans, was asked to
lower the monthly payments.
   On his intervention with the bank, Simon, 61, said he was merely
helping a constituent and trying to avoid court costs. Martin
countered with a TV advertisement that used the word ``fix.''
   Simon accepted blame for the cooking school incident, saying his
staff used bad judgment in dealing with the cooking school
operator.
   Martin stoked the coals, saying ``How many more cases like this
are there?''
   Still, a poll released last week showed Simon favored by 60
percent of those surveyed, with Martin supported by 31 percent. The
Sept. 23-Oct. 1 survey for WLS-TV in Chicago showed 9 percent
undecided, and had a 3 percentage point margin of error.
   Political analyst Charles Cook says Martin ``needs substantially
more positive advertising than has been done thus far and will
still have to go back on negative (ads) in a big way again.''
   ``Whether she has the money to do both in sufficient quantities
is a very good question,'' Cook said.
   As of June 30, Simon had raised $5.7 million, compared with $3.4
million for Martin. The next campaign finance reports are due next
week.
   When she announced her candidacy last year, Martin, 50, tried to
paint Simon as a tax-loving liberal who had abandoned the state to
run for president less than three years into his first term. He
missed nearly 60 percent of Senate votes in 1987 while he sought
the Democratic nomination.
   ``Illinois deserves better,'' she said.
   With President Bush and congressional leaders embracing higher
taxes, she emphasizes her anti-tax stance on the campaign trail.
   ``Muggers in pinstriped suits,'' she said of those pushing a
$500 billion tax-and-spending cuts proposal that was defeated by
the House last week. ``They're back at your pocketbook again.''
   But it has been rough going for Martin.
   Simon has the support of most women's groups, and those that are
not in his camp are staying on the sideline instead of aiding
Martin. Both candidates back abortion rights.
   Martin's integrity also is under attack. Simon's campaign said
she should return nearly $60,000 in campaign contributions and
speaking fees to Sundstrand Corp. and its executives.
   Sundstrand, which is in Martin's northwest Illinois district,
pleaded guilty to defrauding the Pentagon in 1988 and was barred
from government defense work for a few months.
   Martin once told an interviewer that she's ``to the right of
Atilla the Hun'' when it comes to government spending. Simon's camp
has used that against her, finding votes and public comments to
portray the former teacher as a foe of schools.
   A Simon TV ad mentions Martin's votes against Medicare.
   A member of four Senate committees, Simon has promoted his
sponsorship of the government's literacy program and his work on
behalf of college students who need federal aid.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0026 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 1343EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Cambodia Bjt   10-07 0719</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Cambodia, Bjt,089%</SECOND>
<HEAD>With New Chinese Tanks, Khmer Rouge Prepare To Attack Key Region</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   The writer recently spent 10 days traveling
through guerrilla-held territory in northwestern Cambodia where the
Communist Khmer Rouge are preparing for a major offensive.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   ---&equals;
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By NATE THAYER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SIEM REAP PROVINCE, Cambodia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Bolstered by their first
shipments of Chinese tanks, Khmer Rouge guerrillas are preparing a
major attack to seize an area considered Cambodia's most important
cultural and historic region.
   After making major gains in rural areas in the past year, the
Khmer Rouge now are shifting to conventional military tactics to
seize cities and key economic regions, Western military analysts
say.
   The rebels recently took the key government artillery base at
Sre Noi, and now say they are preparing to attack Bantei Srei, the
last major government position defending the provincial capital of
Siem Reap and the nearby Angkor Wat temples, the symbol of
Cambodian civilization.
   The rebels have massed tanks, heavy guns and troops to attack
government defenses in this northwestern province, according to
field commanders and Khmer Rouge fighters interviewed in the
guerrilla zone.
   A recent 10-day, 190-mile trek through guerrilla-held area near
Angkor Wat showed the rebels had overrun important positions and
moved freely through villages less than an hour's drive from the
Siem Reap provincial capital.
   ``We were ordered to attack Bantei Srei this month and then we
will attack Siem Reap,''said Bong Thieun, a young Khmer Rouge
soldier interviewed at Sre Noi.
   Khmer Rouge bulldozers and chainsaws are carving tank and truck
roads through the jungles toward Angkor Wat.
   ``What we see happening in Siem Reap is alarming,'' said a
Western military intelligence analyst. ``They are using a strategy
different from anywhere else. It looks like a real move to take
Siem Reap.''
   Analysts said the capture of Siem Reap and Angkor Wat would be a
major psychological victory.
   Thai and Western sources, speaking on condition of anonymity,
said China's secret delivery of 24 tanks is the first such shipment
ever to the guerrillas. Dozens of the Communist rebels have
returned to the jungles from China, where they were trained to
operate tanks, they said.
   The sources said 12 tanks are at the Khmer Rouge-controlled
district capital of Andung Veng, the staging area for the offensive
against Siem Reap. The other 12 !s near the Khmer Rouge-held town
of Pailin in western Battambang province.
   The guerrillas also have received scores of Chinese jeeps,
transport trucks, and heavy weapons.
   The Khmer Rouge has relied on Chinese arms in the nearly
12-year-old war against the Vietnamese-installed government armed
by the Soviet Union.
   Hundreds of thousands of people died from starvation, execution
and disease during the Khmer Rouge's fanatical Communist rule from
1975 until Vietnam invaded in late 9)8.
   Areas of the country's north are under the control of former
monarch Prince Norodom Sihanouk, whose guerrillas are allied with
the Khmer Rouge and a third rebel group. Sihanouk has wide support
among peasants, and several thousand of his troops move freely
through scores of isolated rural villages.
   They are welcomed by many villagers fearful of the Khmer Rouge
and deeply suspicious of Vietnam's influence over Prime Minister
Hun Sen's government in Phnom Penh.
   But Sihanouk commanders say they cannot compete for territory
with the Khmer Rouge, who have stockpiles of ammunition to fight
for several years if China were to cut them off.
   ``The Khmer Rouge have lots of weapons, but few supporters,''
said Sihanouk commander Gen. Kien Van, at his jungle headquarters
less than 20 miles from Angkor Wat.
   ``We have lots of supporters but few weapons. So the Khmer Rouge
get stronger and the non-Communists get weaker.''
   The United States and European countries recently decreased
their support for the non-Communist guerrillas because they feared
that it would help the Khmer Rouge return to power.
   ``We are doing our best to provide a democratic alternative to
the Cambodian people, but we are weak,'' said Prince Norodom
Ranariddh, Sihanouk's son and the commander in chief of his army.
   ``The West has decided not to support us, so there remains only
two major forces in Cambodia - the Khmer Rouge and Hun Sen,'' he
said.
   ``I have to say very frankly, and Washington will criticize me
again - that against Siem Reap the Khmer Rouge will be the major
attacking forces and the Khmer Rouge will use tanks and heavy
artillery.
   ``They have cut the government supply roads and built a
sophisticated resupply system,'' he said.
   Gen. Kien Van said the Khmer Rouge had promised 2,000 troops to
attack Siem Reap. ``We will have seized Angkor Wat and Siem Reap by
January at the latest,'' he said.
   The five permanent members of the U.N. Security Council -
Britain, China, France, the Soviet Union and the United States -
agreed to a new peace plan for Cambodia in late August. But talks
on the plan among the Cambodian factions broke down in Bangkok last
month.
   After the failure of the Bangkok talks, Khmer Rouge leader Khieu
Samphan said the next talks should be held on the KhmerJSuge-controlled
Khulen Mountain, north of Siem Reap city.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0027 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 1352EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-Refugees     10-07 0538</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Refugees,0648</SECOND>
<HEAD>Kuwaiti Refugees Arrive At Saudi Border</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf-Life In Exile, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By NEIL MacFARQUHAR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>KHAFJI, Saudi Arabia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Several hundred Kuwaiti refugees
arrived at this border crossing Sunday, part of a growing exodus as
Iraq again relaxed its restrictions on Kuwaitis leaving the
occupied emirate.
   The border opened Friday following intensified night searches in
Kuwait City, according to refugees. The searches prompted many of
them to leave out of fear.
   Iraqi troops were confiscating all identification papers in
Kuwait, the refugees reported.
   That raised Saudi fears that the Iraqis were planning to attempt
to infiltrate agents into the kingdom, where a U.S.-led
multinational force has gathered to confront Saddam Hussein's
troops in Kuwait.
   The new refugee influx is the largest since mid-September, when
7,000 Kuwaitis poured through in a three-day frenzy.
   Iraq's motive in opening the border point was unclear.
   But those crossing said they suspected Baghdad was allowing
people to leave for several reasons, including its program of
turning the city into an armed camp, isolating the resistance
movement and resettling Iraqis in Kuwait.
   About 1,000 people have arrived since Friday, most lacking any
identification, border officials said.
   Up to 700 people, most of them women and children, were camped
inside the border crossing awaiting confirmation of their
identities by Saudi officials and the Saudi-based Kuwaiti
government-in-exile.
   Saudi Arabia has sharply increased security at the Khafji
crossing, and reporters are not allowed to circulate there.
   There are an estimated 300,000 Kuwaiti refugees in the Saudi
kingdom and neighboring Persian Gulf states out of a pre-invasion
native population of 600,000.
   Those arriving said Iraqi troops at the border were grabbing
some men under age 40 and taking bribes to allow others to cross.
   Sara Ismail Ibrahim, who fled with nine members of her family,
said two men, aged 21 and 22, were taken out of their car while
trying to cross the border and were not seen again.
   Refugees claim young men are being sent back for Iraqi military
service.
   The similar seizure of young men at the border had dried up the
flow of refugees in September.
   One young man who swore at the Iraqi soldiers was shot at a
checkpoint before the border earlier this week, said a Saudi who
had been in close contact with arriving refugees. He also spoke on
condition of anonymity.
   One group of six young Kuwaiti men said Sunday that they escaped
across the desert because they feared they would be seized on the
road. They said Iraqi soldiers had fired on their car.
  The men were later brought to the border for processing.
   The border opening was announced via the Iraqi-controlled media
in occupied Kuwait, refugees said. Iraqi troops have been allowing
only about 30 cars an hour to leave in the morning and midafternoon
only.
   Issa el-Nasrallah, a Health Ministry employee who fled with his
wife and four children, said that many people in Kuwait thought
Iraq was preparing for combat there soon.
   ``They also want to isolate the resistance to have everyone but
them leave. They're trying to force people out,'' he said.
   Nasrallah said acts of resistance had stopped in Kuwait City
since the Iraqis began killing anyone suspected of belonging to the
resistance, many in front of their families.
   The refugees said Iraqi authorities had announced that everyone
has to have identification cards issued in Baghdad, effectively
changing them all into Iraqi citizens.
   Several hundred Westerners are still believed to be hiding in
Kuwait, fearful of being taken to Iraq for use as human shields at
military and other strategic installations.
   ``Everybody's scared there. They don't know when the Iraqis will
come in the house and kill them,'' said Yusuf al-Ali, 25, a Kuwaiti
Airways pilot.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0028 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 1355EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-EastGermany     10-07 0483</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-East Germany,0582</SECOND>
<HEAD>Former Nation's Anniversary Passes Quietly</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARK FRITZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BERLIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   East Germany would have been 41 years old on
Sunday, but few people found a reason to mark the birth of a nation
that no longer exists.
   The once-hallowed anniversary passed quietly with no lavish
parades, no mass protests for democracy and, most significantly, no
East Germany.
   The former Communist nation closed out its history Wednesday by
acceding to West Germany.
   Lothar de Maiziere, the nation's first and last freely elected
leader, said Sunday was ``not a day of forced marches and ordered
jubiliation, but simply the first Sunday of a united Germany.
   ``We have achieved freedom and democracy,'' the former prime
minister said in a statement. ``We will protect these as precious
commodities.''
   The Soviet Union formed the German Democratic Republic on Oct.
7, 1949 from the rubble of the Nazi empire and installed a
Stalinist government.
   For 40 years, the anniversary was a national holiday marked by
celebrations and parades that paid tribute to the nation's history
and its Communist system.
   Last year, however, it became a flashpoint for the revolt that
toppled the old regime and eventually opened the door to
unification.
   The protests that had been gathering steam in the weeks previous
were given new impetus when Soviet leader Mikhail S. Gorbachev
visited the country and told East German leader Erich Honecker to
institute reforms.
   ``Life punishes whoever comes late,'' he told Honecker.
   Thousands protested on the date last year, some shouting
``Gorby, help us!'' Less than two weeks later Honecker was ousted.
A caretaker Communist government opened the Berlin Wall and
promised free elections.
   De Maiziere's party was elected on a pro-unity platform, and
East Germany's fate was sealed.
   One of the few vestiges of the past was in view Sunday, as some
of the activists who helped lead the democratic revolt kept up
their vigil outside the former headquarters of the Communist secret
police in Berlin.
   The activists are trying to keep officials from the West from
gaining control of the secret dossiers on 6 million people. They
say the files should remain on what was once East German land and
be made available to the public.
   Officials confirmed Saturday that West German investigators have
begun examining the files to gather evidence to bring former secret
police leaders to trial.
   But there was little else reminiscent of the past. The vast
parking lot in front of the Palace of the Republic, once the seat
of the former Communist Parliament, was turned over to an
automobile show that charged passers-by $3.10 to enter.
   At the former Communist-run Old Museum, the ``National Gallery
of the GDR'' remained intact, devoted to paintings and sculpture
rendered by approved artists of the old government.
   Few people wandered past the stark artwork that paid homage to
victims of Nazi fascism and workers. Most crowded into the
remodeled sections devoted to Western artists such as Picasso,
Warhol and Lichtenstein.
   There were still pockets of pity for the old country, however.
   ``I think it's tragic that we no longer have autonomy on this
anniversary,'' said Susanne Meyl, 19, who sells books and
catalogues of the museum's artwork.
   Ms. Meyl, one of the relatively few remaining members of the
former Communist youth group, the Free German Youth, said the
organization planned a memorial to the end of East Germany.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0029 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 1404EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-PTA-GunControl     10-07 0526</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-PTA-Gun Control,0647</SECOND>
<HEAD>Local PTA Chapter Defects When National Group Endorses Gun Control</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Hunting Death, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JERRY NACHTIGAL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CONWAY, Mo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The right to bear arms is sacred in this
rural Ozarks community of 600, so when the national Parent-Teacher
Association came out in favor of gun control, the local PTA chapter
dropped out.
   ``We don't want them using our money to support gun control.
They take away our guns, what's next? Our kitchen knives?'' asked
Judy Perryman, president of the Conway PTA.
   Guns are a way of life here. Hunters go afield after deer,
doves, turkey and squirrels. Gun racks hanging in pickup trucks are
a common site at the Dari-Serv, the town's lone restaurant.
   ``I would say 90 percent of the people here have guns in their
homes,'' Mrs. Perryman said.
   Her husband, Dave, is a trapper and hunter, and their
11-year-old son, Davey, enjoys target shooting under his father's
supervision.
   ``My husband and the other men here follow the rules,'' she
said. ``Gun control is not for the law-abiding, it's for the
lawless.''
   When it dropped out last month, Conway apparently was the first
PTA chapter in the nation to quit the national association because
of its stance on gun control.
   The vote for succession was ``unanimous, about 100 to nothing,''
Mrs. Perryman said. They will instead form their own parent-teacher
group, as yet unnamed, she said.
   Kathy Russell, a spokeswoman at the PTA's national headquarters
in Chicago, said chapters rarely quit the 6.8-million-member
association, which was founded in 1897.
   ``A few drop out because they feel dues are too high, but this
is the first I've heard of anyone pulling out because of the gun
control issue,'' she said.
   What got the 127 members of the Conway PTA riled was the
resolution passed by the 100-member national PTA board of directors
at the association's annual meeting in June.
   Noting that one of every 10 childhood deaths in the United
States in 1987 was caused by a gun, the board, made up of PTA
members from each state, endorsed the Brady Handgun Violence
Prevention Act.
   The proposed legislation, named for James Brady, the former
presidential news secretary who was seriously wounded in an
assassination attempt on President Reagan in 1981, would require a
seven-day waiting period and background check prior to the sale of
firearms.
   The board also called for a ban on military-style,
semi-automatic assault weapons.
   ``The PTA is not attempting to prevent law-abiding citizens from
owning guns,'' the resolution said. ``We want to assure that
firearms aren't easily available to minors, the mentally ill, drug
addicts, illegal aliens or convicted criminals.''
   Ms. Russell said the resolution, one of about a dozen approved
by the board, was not meant to imply that every local PTA chapter
should work to enact gun-control legislation.
   ``Just because it's a resolution with the national PTA doesn't
mean we require each of the local units to agree with the
position,'' she said. ``Basically, it's a consensus of the national
membership and gives us an official position.''
   School Superintendent Larry Ament said he's not surprised
parents in Conway, a dairy-farming community about 30 miles east of
Springfield, got stirred up over the issue.
   All but 25 cents of the $1.50 annual dues paid by each member of
the Conway PTA went to the state and national PTA. Many parents
didn't think they were getting their money's worth and favored
putting the money toward local projects, Ament said.
   Meanwhile, Conway's PTA records, dating to 1935, were donated to
a library.
   ``Maybe we're making a major mistake in doing this,'' Mrs.
Perryman said. ``But we had to do something. There are better ways
of educating parents and teachers than standing up for gun
control.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0030 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 1408EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-HuntingDeath Bjt   10-07 0659</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Hunting Death, Bjt,0841</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hunter Being Tried for Killing Woman He Mistook for Deer</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto AD1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By WILLIAM C. HIDLAY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PORTLAND, Maine (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Karen Wood had just moved to Maine with
her husband and year-old twin girls when she walked behind her
suburban home on a fall afternoon two years ago.
   Donald Rogerson, the manager of a supermarket produce
department, was hunting in the woods behind Mrs. Wood's home that
day, Nov. 15, 1988. Thinking he saw a deer, Rogerson fired his
rifle. Mrs. Wood was hit in the chest and died.
   A grand jury cleared Rogerson, but a second grand jury later
indicted him on a manslaughter charge. He goes on trial Tuesday in
Penobscot County Superior Court in Bangor.
   Rogerson has pleaded innocent. His lawyer, Lewis Vafiades, said
he will argue the shooting was an accident.
   The case triggered a fierce public debate over hunting in a
state where 216,476 people bought hunting licenses last year and
30,260 deer were killed. It also revealed tensions between longtime
residents and newcomers.
   The death of Mrs. Wood, 37, ``polarized the public on the issue
of hunting,'' pitting non-hunters against hunters, said William J.
Vail, commissioner of the state Department of Inland Fisheries and
Wildlife.
   ``The fact that there was no immediate criminal charge in the
case led some people to say, `Well, you can shoot a moose in Maine
illegally and get fined up to $1,000, but if you shoot a human
being nothing happens.'
   ``So it became a very emotional issue.It went way beyond the
issue of should we hunt or not?''
   Mrs. Wood's husband, Kevin, complained that ``the real issue has
been distorted.''
   ``This is not a hunters vs. non-hunters issue. It is a matter of
(Rogerson) accepting responsibility for his actions,'' Wood said in
an interview published Sunday in the Quad City Times in Davenport,
Iowa. He now lives in Bettendorf, Iowa.
   Hunting accidents have not been unusual in Maine. In 1952, for
instance, 19 people were killed in hunting accidents. But the
number of deaths dropped sharply over the last two decades even as
the number of hunters swelled.
   State officials credit hunter safety programs. Since 1973, all
hunters have been required to wear fluorescent orange vests, and
all new hunters applying for licenses have been required since 1986
to take a hunting safety course.
   In 1988, one person was killed in a hunting accident - Mrs.
Wood.
   She had moved to Maine from Iowa four months earlier with her
infant daughters, Lindsay and Laura, and her husband, who's a child
psychologist.
   The family lived in the Bangor suburb of Hermon. Mrs. Wood was
standing behind her home - 130 feet from her back door by some
accounts, well within the area where hunting is banned under safety
laws - when she was shot.
   Rogerson, who works at a local Shop N' Save supermarket, was
arrested that evening and charged with manslaughter. But the charge
was dropped the next month after a grand jury concluded his actions
were neither criminally negligent nor criminally reckless.
   The finding triggered a flood of letters to newspapers.
   Some writers called for more stringent laws to replace the
current statute prohibiting the use of firearms within 300 feet of
an occupied residence. The Legislature rejected the suggestion.
   Other writers said Wood should have worn bright clothing because
it was deer season. Some critics even suggested she was at fault
for wearing white mittens, contending they could have been mistaken
for the underside of a deer's tail.
   Some letters hinted that because she was ``from away'' - a term
used to describe people from other states - she was ignorant of
Maine's hunting practices and traditions.
   The state attorney general's office reopened the case after a
television station reported that a nephew of Rogerson's lawyer had
served on the first grand jury. The second grand jury indicted
Rogerson in December.
   Rogerson, who is married and has three children, faces up to 20
years in prison if he is convicted.
   Vafiades would not allow his client to be interviewed. But
Vafiades said Rogerson ``feels he is the target because of the
circumstances of this case.''
   Wood moved from Maine shortly after the first grand jury cleared
Rogerson, and now lives in Iowa with his daughters, who are about
to celebrate their third birthday.
   He said he doesn't have high hopes for a conviction. ``Part of
the community has already voiced strong support for the man who
killed my wife,'' he said.
   Vafiades said Rogerson has not hunted since that November day
two years ago. As part of the settlement of a wrongful death suit
filed by Woods, Rogerson agreed not to seek a new hunting license,
Vafiades said.
   ``He just has no desire for it,'' the lawyer said. ``I doubt if
he'll ever hunt again. It's still a very emotional thing for him.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0031 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 1422EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People     10-07 0770</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People,0989</SECOND>
<HEAD>People in the News</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY44</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW HAVEN, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Katharine Hepburn once said she wouldn't
give ``a nickel'' for a watercolor she once painted of Beverly
Hills while staying at John Barrymore's house.
   But when she donated the painting to a wildlife group to help it
raise money in an auction, the group had a much higher price in
mind.
   Hepburn's watercolor brought the highest bid during Saturday
night's North American Wildlife Association's benefit - $5,000. But
it was nowhere near the minimum price of $75,000 set in advance by
the group, said Steven Sosensky, the association's attorney and
chairman of the auction.
   About 160 people turned out at the Park Plaza Hotel for the
auction to help the association's 24-hour wildlife rescue service
in Connecticut.
   Hepburn painted the work while staying at Barrymore's home
overlooking Beverly Hills and the Pacific Ocean. The 16-inch by
20-inch work is in an impressionistic style and is signed in the
lower left corner, but not dated. She guessed she painted it in the
1960s.
   ``I do hope i will bring a price, although I wouldn't give you
a nickel for it,'' she said in July when she donated the painting
to the association.
   Other celebrity items donated included autographed photos and
books from Bob Hope, Shirley MacLaine and Barbra Streisand, which
went for between $20 and $150 each.
   Sosensky said the association had hoped to raise $150,000, but
he believed the auction brought in less than $20,000. The
association may try to auction off Hepburn's work on the West
Coast, where they hoped for higher bids, Sosensky said.
   ---
   NASHVILLE, Tenn. (AP) - Country singer Waylon Jennings figured a
joint concert might settle a dispute between a folk group named the
Highwaymen and the group of country stars who use the same name.
   He was right.
   The country group Highwaymen - which includes Jennings, Willie
Nelson, Johnny Cash and Kris Kristofferson - asked the folk group
the Highwaymen to open a show for them.
   The folk group, whose members still perform occasionally and
sell records as an oldies act, had sued the country group for using
the same name.
   Jennings thought a joint concert would give the folk group a
chance to play before a big crowd, promote their music and get paid
for it.
   After the folk Highwaymen opened for the country Highwaymen on
Monday night at the Universal Amphitheatre in Universal City,
Calif., the folk group dropped its lawsuit, said Jennings'
publicist.
   ---
   MANILA, Philippines (AP) - President Corazon Aquino's
19-year-old daughter fell from a stage Sunday as she was about to
sing and dance during a live television show.
   Kristine Bernadette ``Kris'' Aquino was rushed to a hospital,
but doctors said she suffered no serious injuries.
   Producer German Moreno said Miss Aquino missed the steps of a
makeshift platform while preparing for a dance routine. She fell
and disappeared beneath the 5-foot stage in front of a national
television audience and viewers at the Araneta Coliseum in suburban
Quezon city, where the show is produced.
   The incident caused panic as presidential guards and production
staff rushed to pull Miss Aquino out from the hole.
   ``Accidents always happen,'' Moreno said on television. ``We did
not expect that it would happen to her. I would like to
apologize.''
   At the end of the show, Moreno announced that Miss Aquino, a
fledgling but highly paid actress, was in good condition except for
pain in her legs.
   ---
   WEST HOLLYWOOD, Calif. (AP) - Actor Adam Rich, who played the
youngest sibling on television's ``Eight is Enough,'' was accused
of driving under the influence of alcohol, authorities said.
   Rich, 21, was arrested about 1 a.m. Saturday after sheriff's
deputies spotted him making an illegal U-turn and driving
erratically along Sunset Boulevard, said Lt. Lee Jordan.
   Tests revealed his blood alcohol level was .18 percent, more
than twice the legal limit of .08 percent, Jordan said.
   Rich was cited and released Saturday. He must attend an Oct. 31
hearing at Beverly Hills Municipal Court to face the misdemeanor
count, Jordan said.
   Rich entered the Betty Ford Center in Rancho Mirage in July 1988
to kick a cocaine habit. At that time, his manager Jeff Ballard
said the young actor was ``determined to straighten out his life.''
   Rich starred as the pudgy moppet whose antics amused TV
audiences in the comedy-drama series ``Eight is Enough'' that ran
on ABC from 1977 to 1981.
   ---
   SAN FRANCISCO (AP) - Sylvia Chase, who spent the past 4{ years
anchoring the news for a local television station, says dramatic
world events have lured her back to work at a network news program.
   Chase, who's joining ABC television's ``Prime Time'' team le by
Sam Donaldson and Diane Sawyer, said the massacre in China's
Tiananmen Square first sparked her professional fires.
   ``I had an almost physical yearning to go to China,'' says
Chase, who was on vacation in Paris at the time. ``Then Eastern
Europe started to unravel. The Berlin Wall came down.
Renunification was on the way.
   ``These were all places where I had traveled, places I knew
something about. The world was suddenly a different place.''
   Chase went from ABC's ``20-20'' investigative reporting team to
San Francisco's KRON in 1986.
   At 52, she said her age also was a factor in her decision to
return to the network - older women such as Barbara Walters, Lesley
Stahl and even Connie Chung and Diane Sawyer seem to last longer at
the networks than on local stations.
   ``I'd say it was an important factor,'' Chase said in a recent
interview. ``Not only is the world more interesting, but there's
probably more future in going back to network.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0032 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 1432EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-MapplethorpeTrial     10-07 0526</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mapplethorpe Trial,0632</SECOND>
<HEAD>Jurors: Mapplethorpe Photos May Be Lewd, But They're Art</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Note contents of 6th graf.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>CINCINNATI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Jurors who acquitted an art gallery and its
director of obscenity charges say that although they personally
found some of Robert Mapplethorpe's photographs to be lewd and
distasteful, all agreed they are serious works of art.
   ``The pictures were not pretty. No doubt about it,'' juror James
Jones told The Cincinnati Enquirer in a story published Sunday.
``But, as it was brought up in the trial, to be art it doesn't have
to be pretty.''
   The jury deliberated two hours Friday before clearing Dennis
Barrie and the Contemporary Arts Center of misdemeanor pandering
obscenity and child-nudity charges in the first case of its kind
against an art institution.
   Three jurors interviewed by the newspaper said they were
surprised by the swift verdict. On both charges, the first jury
vote was 7-1 in favor of acquittal. They did not say who voted to
convict.
   ``We felt that the prosecution did not prove its case,'' said
Jones, a warehouse manager.
   Five of the pictures in the 175-picture exhibition, ``Robert
Mapplethorpe: The Perfect Moment,'' depict sexually explicit acts
involving men; two others showed children with their genitals
exposed.
   The jurors told the Enquirer they believed the five pictures of
sex acts to be offensive and designed to appeal to prurient
interests. But they said expert witnesses convinced them the
photographs had artistic value.
   To be considered obscene under Supreme Court guidelines,
photographs must depict patently offensive sexual conduct and
offend the average member of the community. They also must have no
literary, artistic, political, scientific or social value.
   ``I think there's something to be learned by these pictures,''
said forewoman Stacey Burton, a secretary.
   ``I learned more about that type of lifestyle than I ever
thought I could possibly know,'' said Jennifer Loesing, a hospital
supervisor.
   Six art experts and museum directors testified that the photos
were important work by a respected artist. One prosecution witness
testified that the pictures had no redeeming value.
   Ms. Loesing said hat during deliberations she kept thinking of
defense lawyer H. Louis Sirkin's ``apple pie'' analogy: that
without meeting each requirement of the Supreme Court test, the
photographs were not obscene - just as a pie without apples isn't
an apple pie.
   ``That stuck in a lot of our minds,'' she said.
   Ms. Burton said prosecutors failed to prove their case.
   ``I think they could have called in a sociologist or
psychologist,'' she said. ``Somebody who could have said, `This is
not art because. ...'''
   The jurors said they relied on the opinions of the expert
witnesses.
   Jurors came from conventional backgrounds. None was among the
81,000 people who saw the exhibit. Three of the eight had been to
college, six lived in the suburbs and all held jobs. There were
four men, four women.
   Sirkin and fellow defense lawyer Marc Mezibov staked their case
on testimony by their expert witnesses. Prosecutor Frank H. Prouty
said the seven photographs were his case.
   Much of the art world was willing to testify for the defense,
and Sirkin said he and Mezibov chose their witnesses carefully.
They ruled out an expert from Dayton because of its progressive
reputation in Cincinnati, and experts from Cleveland and Columbus
because of the hostility some Cincinnatians feel toward those
cities, Sirkin said.
   They also didn't want anyone from New York City because of its
reputation for licentiousness, Sirkin said.
   ``Rochester was as close as we wanted to get to New York,'' he
said, referring to the testimony of Robert A. Sobieszek, senior
curator of photography at the International Museum of Photography
in Rochester.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0033 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 1435EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Soviet-Rally     10-07 0507</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Rally,0605</SECOND>
<HEAD>Protesters Call For Alternative to Red Army Service</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto MOSB2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By THOMAS GINSBERG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Scores of radical activists, grieving mothers and
leather-clad youths rallied side-by-side at the gates of the
Defense Ministry Sunday, demanding alternatives to compulsory
military service.
   Several hundred people watched and often applauded as speakers
from the fledgling Radical Party, organizers of the rally,
criticized the United States and the Soviet Union for the arms
buildups they said made the drafts necessary.
   ``There is no reason for a universal military draft. Who is
threatening us? It's our own heaping stockpile that is threatening
us,'' said Alexander Kalinina, a Radical Party member and deputy on
the Moscow City Council.
   ``Those who don't want to serve according to their own
consciences should be allowed to serve in the civil (sector)
instead of the military,'' he told the crowd.
   The rally on Constitution Day, which marks the adoption of the
Soviet Constituion in 1977, was held without official permission.
But there were no confrontations with the dozens of policemen
posted at each entrance to the white-marble Defense Ministry
building.
   Every Soviet male of 18 or older must serve in the military and
can be called up during seasonal draft periods, one of which is
occuring this autumn.
   Soviet officials have admitted that thousands of youths have
been ignoring draft orders in the last year. Many refuse to serve
outside their home republics because, among other issues, they fear
the vicious hazing process that often is ethnically motivated.
   Beatings and harassment of minorities are so rampant that
several republics refused to allow their youths to be drafted this
year. One report said 15,000 Soviet soldiers died in the last five
years in murders, suicides and training accidents.
   Kalinina said many of the 3,800 soldiers killed already this
year had died of injuries from hazings.
   ``The mass media have led a campaign against hazings, but it has
not been very enthusiastic,'' he said.
   A half-dozen women, representing an increasingly active mothers'
group that seeks more information about their sons who died while
in service, staked out an area at the center of the rally. Each of
the women held a photo of a soldier and a hand-lettered sign
detailing his birth, place of service and date of death.
   At one point, an elderly woman charged to the front of the
group, pulled an olive green officer's hat from a bag and flailed
it in the air, wailing and chanting for her son killed in
Afghanistan. The speaker hesitated slightly while the woman sobbed
and retreated into the crowd.
   ``We Don't Want To Kill, We Don't Want To Fight,'' said one sign
carried by several youths opposed to military service. ``Communist
Party Army, Whom Do You Fight For?'' read another.
   ``We need alternative service like all civilized European
countries have,'' said Igor Ptychnikov, leader of a raucous group
called the Moscow Committee for Youth Solidarity. ``We want to be
able to opt out of military service for religious, conscience and
other reasons. We'll serve anywhere but the army.''
   He said the group, many of whose members were clad in leather
jackets covered with peace slogans and English words, has chapters
and 3,000 members in 14 Russian cities. But he said it has none in
the surrounding republics because ``We don't want to be
occupiers.''
   In the crowd also were several anarchists waving black flags and
selling literature. Others waved the red-blue-and-white
pre-Revolutionary Russian flag, and two people held huge, light
blue-and-yellow flags of the nationalist Ukraine.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0034 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 1532EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-HungerStrike     10-07 0278</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Hunger Strike,0324</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hunger Strikers Heed Doctor, End Fast at Fort Benning</HEAD>
<DATELINE>FORT BENNING, Ga. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Four hunger strikers, who lost a total
of 151 pounds protesting the U.S. training of Salvadoran soldiers,
ended their 35-day fast Sunday after doctors warned of permanent
health damage.
   ``Our cause continues,'' said the Rev. Roy Bourgeois, a Roman
Catholic priest from Lutcher, La., after the strikers ended their
fast at a morning news conference. ``The bread we received today is
nourishment for us to recommit ourselves.''
   Bourgeois was among nine protesters who began the fast Sept. 3,
praying, carrying signs and marching outside Fort Benning. The
group demanded that the United States cut all military aid to El
Salvador and stop training Salvadoran soldiers at the base's Army
School of the Americas.
   The United States is spending some $315 million in aid to El
Salvador this year, much of it economic and food aid for an economy
racked by a decade-old civil war with leftist guerrillas.
   A Democratic task force has pressed the Bush administration for
restrictions in next year's planned $85 million in military aid to
the country in wake of investigations into the slayings of six
Jesuit priests in the capital of San Salvador in November 1989.
   Five of the original protesters dropped the fast over the last
two weeks. Remaining were Bourgeois; Jim Barnett, a Dominican
priest who served in El Salvador and plans to return now; Charlie
Liteky of Washington, D.C., who won a Medal of Honor by pulling 20
wounded men from under enemy fire during the Vietnam War; and David
Scott, an ex-Marine and Vietnam veteran from Detroit.
   Bourgeois said the four decided to end the strike after doctors
warned that their weight loss could cause permanent health damage.
He said Liteky was warned he could sustain severe kidney damage.
   Bourgeois said he lost 38 pounds, Liteky 40, Scott 35 and
Barnett 38.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0035 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 1535EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Rwanda     10-07 0555</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Rwanda,0686</SECOND>
<HEAD>Evacuees Stream Out of Embattled Rwanda</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By REID G. MILLER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NAIROBI, Kenya (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hundreds of foreigners crowded onto
special flights out of Rwanda's capital on Sunday while government
forces and rebels clashed in the northern part of the country.
   Security in large parts of the Kigali, the capital, and at the
airport was being provided by 500 Belgian paratroopers and 300
French Foreign Legionnaires sent in to maintain order and protect
foreigners. Zaire also has sent 500 soldiers.
   Some of the more than 700 refugees flown to France and Belgium
recounted the chaos in the country since rebels invaded Sept. 30.
   Jean-Claude Fayd-Herbe, the World Bank's chief representative in
Rwanda, told journalists that he and his family were staying in a
hotel in Kigali when rebels attacked early Friday.
   ``It was chaos. The French paratroopers were shooting, and the
people coming from Uganda also were shooting,'' he said upon
arrival in Paris. ``In the hotel, there was panic, and the guests
barricaded the windows with mattresses.
   ``The Rwandan soldiers seemed especially nervous, and it seemed
they were firing at the French troops.''
   A diplomat in Kigali, reached by telephone from Nairobi,
reported no violence in the city early Sunday. But he added:
``We've heard reports of continued fighting in the north, including
some artillery attacks by the government.''
   He said most of those leaving on the special flights were wives
and children of aid workers. No governments have ordered
evacuations of their citizens.
   A special Air France flight carrying 252 foreign evacuees from
Rwanda arrived in Paris. Aboard were about 100 French citizens and
a large contingent of Germans, as well as other nationalities.
   In Brussels, 463 refugees arrived aboard three Belgian planes.
More than 200 of the refugees were Belgian. Others were Dutch,
American, German and Danish.
   Up to 1,000 foreigners have left Kigali on special flights since
late Friday, the diplomatic source in Rwanda said on condition of
anonymity.
   Friday's fighting in Kigali lasted only a few hours, but there
were fears the conflict could degenerate into the ethnic violence
that has plagued Rwanda in the past.
   The rebels belong mostly to Rwanda's minority Tutsi ethnic
group. They were chased from power three decades ago by the
majority Hutu tribe in clan fighting that killed tens of thousands
of people.
   During those clashes, more than 100,000 Tutsis fled to
neighboring Uganda, Zaire and Tanzania, where they have been living
as refugees ever since.
   The diplomat said government soldiers were conducting
house-to-house searches in some parts of Kigali, but it was not
clear whether they were looking for arms or Tutsis. Tutsis are
generally distinguishable from the shorter, stockier Hutus by their
tall, lanky physiques.
   Many of the rebels are said to be deserters from the Ugandan
army. Their numbers never have been reliably estimated. Figures
cited by various diplomatic sources have ranged from a few hundred
to several thousand.
   They are led by Maj. Gen. Fred Rwigyema, a Rwandan Tutsi who
rose to become the deputy commander of Uganda's army. He was
relieved of the post late last year.
   The rebels accuse President Juvenal Habyarimana of abuse of
power and corruption and say they want to install a democratic
government. They deny that theirs is an ethnic war.
   The rebels also say they want to end the refugee problem. Rwanda
has been reluctant to readmit its refugees because of a lack of
space.
   Pope John Paul II on Sunday called for peace in Rwanda, which he
visited on an African tour last month.
   ``We pray for an end to the clashes of these recent days, and
that that beloved nation ... can find peace in justice as soon as
possible,'' the pontiff said.
   The Central African nation, about the size of Maryland, is the
continent's most densely populated. An average of 566 people occupy
every rocky and eroded square mile. That compares to an average of
63 people per square mile in the United States.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0036 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 1539EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Volcanoes     10-07 0322</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Volcanoes,0377</SECOND>
<HEAD>New Volcanoes Found Off Oregon Coast</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PORTLAND, Ore. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A 10-mile string of about 10 new volcanoes
has been discovered on the ocean floor about 300 miles off the
Oregon Coast, scientists said.
   The volcanoes, some more than 100 feet high and a half-mile
wide, were spotted by scientists studying maps and photographs of
the sea floor along the Juan de Fuca Ridge, which runs north and
south off the Washington and Oregon coasts.
   They were formed within the past decade, said Robert Embley, a
marine geologist with the National Oceanic and Atmospheric
Administration's Pacific Marine Environmental Laboratory in
Newport.
   Photographs taken last year and topographic surveys in August
showed new cones that did not appear in 1981 surveys. In August,
scientists using the submersible Alvin found fresh lava flows
extending into and over a large fracture in the sea floor.
   The volcanoes ``are not continuous,'' but they are difficult to
count because some have joined together, Embley said in a story
published Sunday in The Oregonian. They ``are not huge like Mount
St. Helens, but they can be described more as volcanic mounds.''
   Embley made the discovery with William Chadwick, a research
associate with Oregon State University, and Christopher Fox, a
remote-sensing specialist with NOAA. The researchers work at the
Hatfield Marine Science Center.
   ``This is a big step,'' Embley said. ``It's the first time we
can actually see a sea-floor spreading event. I'm sure we're going
to learn a lot about how eruptions occur and what happens during
these events.''
   Lava comes up from magma chambers beneath such midocean ridges,
where the sea floor forms and spreads.
   Embley said the volcanoes are about 1{ miles deep, on the crest
of the Juan de Fuca Ridge, where the Juan de Fuca and the Pacific
tectonic plates form. The Juan de Fuca Plate creeps eastward toward
the continent from the ridge, while the Pacific Plate moves
westward. The plates are huge slabs of the Earth's crus.
   The volcanoes may be related to gigantic bursts of hot,
mineral-rich water called ``megaplumes,'' Embley said. The
megaplumes were discovered by NOAA scientists in 1986 and 1987. One
measured about 12 miles in diameter and 2,000 feet thick.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0037 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 1545EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Obit-Matheson 1stLd-Writethru a0668 10-07 0486</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Matheson, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0668,0594</SECOND>
<HEAD>Former Utah Governor Scott Matheson Dies at 61</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS penultimate graf, `Dwan said ...' to add details of
survivors.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto SK1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BOB BLACK</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SALT LAKE CITY (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Former Gov. Scott Matheson died of bone
marrow cancer Sunday at the University of Utah Health Sciences
Center, a hospital spokesman said. He was 61.
   The popular two-term Democrat died at 5 a.m., just over a month
after first receiving treatment for the cancer, multiple myeloma,
said hospital spokesman John Dwan. He had been in and out of the
hospital several times since Sept. 4.
   Matheson served as the state's 12th governor from 1977 to 1985,
choosing not to seek re-election despite consistent favorable
ratings in the polls.
   As governor, Matheson successfully opposed placement of the MX
missile system in the state's western desert, battled to continue
funding of the massive Central Utah water control project and was
given high marks for decisive action when parts of the state were
devastated by flooding in 1983.
   ``The news of Scott Matheson's death comes as a shock to me,''
said Republican Gov. Norm Bangerter, who was speaker of the House
while Matheson was governor.
   ``I am deeply saddened by his passing,'' Bangerter said. ``I had
the privilege of working closely with Scott during his eight years
as governor when I was in House leadership. I always found he was a
man true to his word. In my view he had complete integrity.''
   ``While we belonged to different political parties, Scott
Matheson never let politics get in the way of doing what was right
for the people of Utah.''
   After eight years in office, Matheson said in late 1988, ``the
hours began to wear me down.''
   ``I never slept in as governor, and for five of my eight years
in office, I never took a vacation,'' he said. ``I immersed myself
completely in the job, but I loved it.''
   The former counsel for Union Pacific Railroad was a political
unknown when he was backed for the job by three-term Democratic
governor Calvin L. Rampton, who had decided to return to the
practice of law.
   With Rampton's support, Matheson defeated former Republican
attorney general Vernon Romney in 1976 and won re-election in 1980
over former GOP state chairman Robert Wright.
   After leaving office, he was appointed chairman of the
Democratic National Policy Council in 1985, and at his death was a
partner in the Salt Lake law firm of Parsons, Behle &amp; Latimer.
   Earlier this year, Matheson withdrew his name from consideration
as President Bush's nuclear waste negotiator, citing personal
reasons. As governor, he was an outspoken opponent of locating a
high-level nuclear waste repository in his native southern Utah.
   In 1983 he suffered a mild heart attack, spent two weeks in a
hospital and returned to work.
   In May 1987, Matheson announced he would not challenge
Republican Sen. Orrin Hatch in the 1988 election, saying ``personal
considerations regarding my family and expanding responsibilities
as a private attorney figure largely in this decision.''
   When Matheson ruled out a bid for a third term, the governor's
chair was won by Bangerter, ending 20 years of Democratic control
of the office. Bangerter was re-elected in 1988 after Matheson
turned thumbs down on a possible return to the Capitol.
   Dwan said aatheson's family would have no comment for at least
24 hours. He is survived by his wife, Norma; three sons; and a
daughter.
   Funeral arrangements were incomplete.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0038 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 1546EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-AdoptionAds     10-07 0203</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Adoption Ads,0224</SECOND>
<HEAD>New York City Begins Television Adoption Ads</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The city begins airing television commercials
Monday in an effort to find homes for some of the 7,000 children in
foster care.
   The Human Resources Administration will rotate 24 spots on
WNBC-TV through mid-January. The 10-second ads will feature 29
children between 8 and 16, including some siblings.
   They'll include a one-sentence description of the child and his
or her interests, plus a flashing telephone number. Many of the
youngsters have learning disabilities or are teen-agers from
minority groups, considered difficult to place.
   ``I wanted to get adopted so that I could stay with my sister,''
said a 15-year-old boy, identified only as Robert, who appears in
one of the ads. His sister, who lives in a different group home,
did not want to be in the commercial.
   ``Most people like to adopt little children,'' Robert said in an
interview. ``Grownups are afraid older kids might get in trouble.''
   Suffolk County aired similar spots on a cable TV channel several
years ago.
   ``It works,'' said Robert Oliveri, a spokesman for that county's
Social Services Department. ``But it doesn't make a lasting
impression. You get a momentary flurry of calls, very specific to a
child. There is no carryover effect to other children.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0039 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 1557EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-Iran     10-07 0550</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Iran,0631</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tehran Reported Tense On Eve Of Vote For Key Assembly</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ANWAR FARUQI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NICOSIA, Cyprus (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Security forces were on alert in Tehran
Sunday, the eve of elections for the body that pick's Iran's
spiritual leader, as radicals excluded from running were expected
to try to block voting, sources said.
   One Asian diplomat described the Iranian capital as ``disturbed
and tense'' ahead of Monday's popular poll for the 83-member
Assembly of Experts. He declined to elaborate.
   The diplomat, speaking from Tehran, said security forces were
watching for any demonstrations against the controversial
balloting, which radicals charge has been rigged to exclude them.
The radicals want the vote postponed.
   The assembly is the constitutional body that chooses and
monitors Iran's spiritual leader. The current spiritual leader is
Ayatollah Ali Khamenei.
   The hard-line opponents of President Hashemi Rafsanjani - leader
of Iran's so-called pragmatists - accuse Khamenei of colluding with
Rafsanjani to fix the elections.
   The conflict over the balloting has heightened tension between
the rival factions and brought the long-running power struggle in
Tehran's hierarchy more prominently into the public eye.
   Fistfights erupted in the radical-dominated parliament, or
Majlis, during a debate on the vote last week, sources in Tehran
said on condition of anonymity.
   Diplomats, also speaking on condition of anonymity, said that
radicals attempted to meet last Wednesday and Saturday at Tehran
University, apparently to organize protests, but both meetings were
broken up by security forces.
   The anti-Western radicals, led by former interior minister Ali
Akbar Mohtashemi, have been on the defensive since the death of
their revolutionary patriarch, Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini, in June
1989.
   They fear a purge by Rafsanjani, who is seeking to rebuild
bridges with the West after more than a decade of hostility and
attract investment to revive the sluggish economy, devastated from
the 1980-1988 Persian Gulf war with Iraq.
   Radicals suffered a further blow last month when Tehran resumed
relations with Britain after a 19-month break. Radical leaders
believe such ties will dilute Khomeini's zealous 1979 revolution,
which overthrew the pro-Western Shah Mohammad Reza Pahlavi and
replaced him with the Islamic Republic.
   The official Islamic Republic News Agency reported that Grand
Ayatollah Mohammed Golpayegani, one of a handful of supreme
religious authorities in the country, sought to ease tension
between the factions Sunday.
   He reminded the feuding groups that ``only the enemies of Islam
would benefit from disputes and schisms, especially among
officials,'' IRNA said.
   The radicals, angered by Khamenei's support for Rafsanjani, have
focused on discrediting him. Khamenei, 51, was overwelmingly
elected by the Assembly of Experts to replace the Ayatollah
Khomeini.
   He can be replaced only if he dies or is declared unfit for the
position by the Assembly. The radicals have charged that he does
not have the religious qualifications to be Khomeini's successor.
   Sources in Tehran said the hard-liners had wanted to win enough
seats in Monday's election to depose Khamenei and replace him with
a radical-controlled leadership council.
   To preempt that, Khamenei ordered his allies on the Council of
Guardians, a constitutional watchdog body, to rule that all
candidates must pass an examination on Islamic jurisprudence before
they could run.
   Of 169 would-be candidates who sat for the exam, 60 flunked, and
most were radicals, including Parliament Speaker Mehdi Karrubi,
sources said.
   Some radicals refused to submit to the examination. Others who
did pass withdrew their names in protest.
   Iran's 25 million voters have been exhorted for days by the
state-controlled radio and television - run by Rafsanjani's brother
- to vote, despite the radical protests.
   Interior Minister Abdollah Nouri said 100 candidates were
running in the elections.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0040 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 1558EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Japan-Bribery     10-07 0468</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Japan-Bribery,0556</SECOND>
<HEAD>Sumitomo Bank Chairman Resigning Over Scandal</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The chairman of Sumitomo Bank, among the world's
three largest banks, resigned Sunday over a scandal involving
illegal loans used to manipulate the stock of an aerial survey
company.
   Ichiro Isoda, 77, who led Sumitomo's growth into Japan's most
profitable bank, announced his resignation following the arrest
Friday of Akinori Yamashita, a former branch manager.
   Yamashita was arrested on suspicion of having arranged about
$170 million in illegal loans to two groups allegedly involved in
stock manipulation.
   ``It is only natural to take responsibility as the top manager
of the bank, in light of the bank's public role,'' Isoda told a
news conference.
   He said Sumitomo's president, Sotoo Tatsumi, also had expressed
his intention to resign, but Isoda persuaded him not to do so.
   Officials said the bank had not been aware of Yamashita's
actions. In Japan, leaders of organizations often resign to take
responsibility for the misdeeds of subordinates, even if they were
not personally involved.
   News reports said Yamashita arranged for bank depositors to
provide a loan of $85 million at higher-than-normal interest rates
to Koshin, a speculators' group, and a separate loan of $86 million
to another group, Tosho Shoji.
   The loan to Koshin was used to buy up stocks of Kokusai Kogyo, a
Tokyo-based aerial survey company, the news report said.
   The nationally circulated newspaper Asahi Shimbun quoted
investigators as saying Yamashita received more than $748,000 and
inside stock information for arranging the loans.
   Under Japan's Financing Law, bank employees are prohibited from
engaging in loan transactions outside their company's normal
business operations. Those convicted face a maximum three-year
prison term and a $22,000 fine.
   Mitsuhiro Kotani, head of Koshin, has been indicted on charges
of manipulating stocks in violation of the Securities and Exchange
Law, Kyodo News Service said.
   The Yomiuri Shimbun, Japan's largest newspaper, on Sunday called
for a full investigation into the loans and said extensive lending
for real estate and stock transactions had contributed to spiraling
land and stock prices.
   ``As a result, the prices of both corporate stocks and land were
inflated far beyond their actual values, like a bubble,'' it said
in an editorial.
   ``Most observers believe this year's plunge of stock prices ...
was the result of the bursting of this bubble.''
   The Tokyo Stock Exchange's Nikkei Stock Average reached a record
high of 38,915.87 last Dec. 29, but has plunged about 42 percent
since then. Some of the recent fall reflects business pessimism as
a result of the gulf crisis.
   Japan has only 4 percent of the United States' land area but its
real estate is estimated at nearly four times the total value of
U.S. real estate - about $15 trillion.
   Sumitomo Bank had pre-tax profits of $2.7 billion in fiscal
1989, the largest sum of Japan's 13 major commercial banks, Kyodo
News Service said.
   The bank reported total assets of $470 billion in March 1990,
putting it slightly behind the world's largest bank, Dai-Ichi
Kangyo Bank of Japan, which reported $497 billion in assets.
   Asset figures were not available for Mitsui Taiyo Kobe Bank,
created earlier this year in a merger of two major Japanese banks
and close to Sumitomo in size.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0041 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 1608EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Obit-Pepperdine     10-07 0211</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Pepperdine,0232</SECOND>
<HEAD>Widow of Pepperdine University Founder Dead at Age 87</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MALIBU, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Helen Davis Pepperdine, whose late husband
founded Pepperdine University, has died of heart failure at age 87,
officials said.
   Mrs. Pepperdine died Friday at Los Angeles Midway Hospital,
where she was taken earlier in the day after complaining of chest
pains, said university spokesman Jeff Bliss.
   ``She was a grand lady loved by all who knew her,'' Pepperdine
President David Davenport said. ``She truly cherished the
opportunity to be involved with students and all of us at the
university.''
   A native of Muncie, Ind., she moved with her family to Los
Angeles in 1919 and worked as a photographer.
   She married George Pepperdine in 1934. Soon after, the couple
founded the Helen Louise Girls Home, which catered to young women
from broken homes.
   In 1937, Pepperdine opened the George Pepperdine College in Los
Angeles, which expanded into the private, liberal arts university
that now sits atop a hill in Malibu overlooking the Pacific Ocean.
   Although her husband died in 1962, Mrs. Pepperdine remained
active at the university and served as a Board of Regents member
until her death.
   A memorial service will be held next week at the campus, some 30
miles west of downtown Los Angeles.
   She is survived by the couple's three children and several
grandchildren.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0042 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 1646EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Cranston-Keating     10-07 0422</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Cranston-Keating,450</SECOND>
<HEAD>Fund-Raiser's Memo to Cranston Notes Keating's Problems</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A ``confidential'' memo to Sen. Alan Cranston
from a key fund-raiser indicates that savings and loan executive
Charles H. Keating Jr. was among several campaign supporters who
expected resolution of requests for help from the senator, The
Washington Post reported Sunday.
   The fund-raiser, Joy Jacobson, also suggested in a second memo
that Cranston seek a $250,000 contribution from Keating for
Cranston's voter registration drive, the Post said.
   The second memo followed a series of meetings between the
California Democrat and Keating and separate meetings with federal
thrift regulators to discuss their inquiries into Keating's Irving,
Calif.-based Lincoln Savings and Loan.
   Regulators eventually shut down Lincoln, and the government
estimates the thrift's failure will cost taxpayers $2 billion.
   Cranston and four other senators - Dennis DeConcini, R-Ariz.,
Donald W. Riegle Jr., D-Mich., John Glenn, D-Ohio, and John McCain,
R-Ariz. - are under investigation by the Senate Ethics Committee
for intervening with federal regulators on behalf of Keating and
his California thrift.
   Keating has been indicted on fraud charges in California in
connection with the thrift's failure.
   A Cranston spokesman, Murray Flander, refused to comment on the
report Sunday other than to say ``That information properly belongs
to the ethics committee and was improperly leaked by someone.''
   ``We won't comment on improperly leaked information,'' Flander
said.
   Cranston has said his motivations were to see that a constituent
was treated fairly and not the money. Keating also raised $40,000
for Cranston's 1986 campaign and contributed $85,000 to the
California Democratic Party.
   In the first memo, dated Jan. 2, 1987, Jacobson told Cranston
that Keating was one of five campaign supporters who ``rightfully
expect some kind of resolution'' for pending requests for help from
the senator.
   The memo said the contributors had been very helpful to Cranston
and other Democrats in their successful effort to win back majority
control of the Senate in 1986.
   In the second memo in September 1987, Jacobson told Cranston,
``You should ask Keating for $250,000,'' the Post said.
   Jacobson, in the same memo, also suggested asking an American
Express executive for $100,000 for voter registration and said she
was trying to make appointments with since-convicted junk bond king
Michael Milken and billionaire developer Donald Trump, the
newspaper said.
   Cranston ultimately raised $7 million for various nonpartisan,
tax-exempt voter registration groups.
   The September memo referred to Lincoln's ``problems with the
Bank Board and Ed Gray.'' The Post said the memo was attached to a
news story about M. Danny Wall's replacing Gray as head of the
Federal Home Loan Bank Board and said the change was ``obviously
... good news to Keating.''
   Jacobson also had mentioned the problems in the earlier note,
according to the Post.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0043 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 1649EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Budget-NotShutdown 1stLd-Writethru a069 10-07 0575</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Budget-Not Shutdown, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0696,650</SECOND>
<HEAD>Cranky Tourists Clog Capitol During Government Shutdown
^Eds: INSERTS 1 graf after 4th graf pvs, bgng: ``Unfortunately, we,
to UPDATE with chorus of boos from gallery</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOAN MOWER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Shut out of other federal tourist attractions,
frustrated visitors from around the world flocked to the Capitol on
Sunday to see the legislature in action and give lawmakers a piece
of their mind.
   ``They should have settled the budget instead of going on
vacation,'' said 20-year-old Kara DiMugno of Southington, Conn.,
referring to the long recess members of Congress took in August.
   Like thousands of other tourists, DiMugno, a senior at the
University of Rhode Island, came to the Capitol because it was the
best show in Washington, one of the few sites that has not been
closed because of the budget stalemate between President Bush and
Congress.
   ``Unfortunately we are the only game in town so our tour guides
are really busy,'' said Tom Keating, executive assistant to the
House sergeant at arms.
   Although open, the action in the Capitol was limited at best.
When the House came into session at 4 p.m. - only to recess again
moments later - loud booing erupted from the galleries packed with
tourists.
   The Capitol is regularly open on Sundays and is always open when
members are working. Weekend sessions like the ones scheduled by
the House and Senate on Sunday are rare.
   On this balmy, sunny October day, thousands of tourists were
locked out of some of the nation's most historic sights for the
second day: the 13 Smithsonian Institution museums, including the
air and space museum, one of the most popular in the world; the
White House; the Library of Congress; and the Washington Monument.
   The shutdown affects non-essential government personnel
nationwide. But federal operations deemed essential, such as those
involving aviation, health, law enforcement and security, are not
affected by the crisis.
   Monday is a federal holiday - Columbus Day - so federal
employees are to report to work as usual Tuesday when those
considered non-essential can expect to be sent home within three
hours.
   Meantime, Democratic leaders predicted there would be a budget
agreement before Tuesday's drop-dead day.
   ``We're going to have a budget package today or tomorrow - we
hope today,'' said House Speaker Tom Foley, D-Wash. The House had
adjourned until mid-afternoon while the Senate did not plan to come
into session until early evening.
   For some tourists, it was too late.
   ``We're very disappointed,'' said Brenda Marlatt, a nurse from
Ocean, N.J., spending the long weekend here. Marlatt, a single
mother who has scrimped to bring her daughters ages 10 and 8 to the
nation's capital to see the sights, pronounced the budget situation
``a total mess. ... Why can't they just pass it?''
   Mike Sanders, owner of an auto repair shop in Concord, Calif.,
planned a more direct approach: he wanted to share his views with
his congressman, Rep. George Miller, D-Calif.
   Sanders said he was angry that Democrats and Republicans ganged
up to kill Bush's deficit plan late Thursday. Miller, a liberal,
was one of those voting against it.
   ``We really feel reducing the deficit is important,'' said
Sanders' wife, LeeAnn.
   If the United States falls deeper into debt, ``these kids will
never be able to pay for it,'' Sanders added, pointing as his sons,
ages 6 and 4.
   Many members of Congress who rejected the budget deal because
they felt it contained new taxes that might be unpalatable to
voters in an election year now found themselves confronting
criticism for not passing it.
   But Rep. John Murtha, D-Pa., said most of the complaints he had
heard came from federal workers and cranky tourists, not his
constituents.
   Even so, Murtha said, ``We made a mistake'' in Congress by
rejecting the budget agreement and refusing to follow the lead of
the Democratic leaders and Bush. Murtha voted for the package.
   This is not the first time the government has run out of
spending authority. Squabbles between the administration and
Congress forced the temporary closing of government three times in
the last decade.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0044 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 1654EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Soviet-Crimea     10-07 0263</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Crimea,0292</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ethnic Clash Reported in Soviet Crimea</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Extra police were sent to the region around the
Black Sea resort of Yalta after a clash between residents and
Crimean Tatars living in makeshift tent camps, Pravda reported
Sunday.
   Stalin forcibly expelled the Tatars from the Crimea, but
thousands have been filtering back in recent years from Siberia and
Central Asia, the lands to which they were banished during World
War II.
   Traffic police have blocked the roads to Yalta since last week,
when two tent camps housing resettled Crimean Tatars were attacked
and destroyed. The police are checking motorists' identification to
keep any more Crimean Tatars from entering the region, Pravda said.
   There are 21 tent camps in the area housing more than 2,500
Tatars, according to the independent Interfax news agency.
   A spokesman for the ethnic movement said residents of a tent
camp in Koreiz, near Yalta, built a barricade and prepared to
defend the settlement, Interfax reported.
   During the war, Stalin sent several ethnic groups into internal
exile on the grounds that they could not be trusted to occupy
strategic areas.
   The Tatars and other groups have been agitating to be allowed to
return to their traditional homes. In 1989, the Supreme Soviet
declared that all peoples exiled under Stalin should be considered
politically rehabilitated.
   But other residents now occupy the lands and houses that
belonged to the exiles, and conflicts have arisen when some groups
try to reestablish themselves.
   Ethnographers estimate there are 500,000 Crimean Tatars in the
Soviet Union, and 1 million more in Turkey. Angry protests in
Moscow by Tatar exiles in 1987 were among the first tests of
President Mikhail Gorbachev's promises of greater democracy.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0045 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 1702EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-EC-Talks     10-07 0427</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-EC-Talks,0493</SECOND>
<HEAD>EC Nations Debate Role In Foreign, Defense Policy</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT J. WIELAARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>VENICE, Italy (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The 12 European Community nations, in
informal weekend talks, opened an ambitious debate on how to grant
the community a formal role in foreign and defense issues.
   The talks among the EC foreign ministers centered on a 17-page
discussion paper, drafted by Italian Foreign Minister Gianni De
Michelis, on how to transfer national authority in defense and
security matters to the EC.
   The talks began Saturday and ended Sunday.
   De Michelis said that while the EC nations disagree on key
points, ``all are committed to finding a convergent approach'' when
talks on turning the community into a political union formally
begin in Rome in December.
   His discussion paper suggests that the community consider
bringing the activities of the Western European Union - a
long-dormant defense organization of nine European NATO members -
under the EC's wings.
   A joint EC security policy could extend to military cooperation
and disarmament and ``coordinated participation in military
initiatives, in particular in the context of U.N.-mandated
action,'' the report says.
   The paper, based on discussions with senior EC political
officials, offers no recommendations on how much sovereignty in
defense EC nations should retain.
   At Sunday's session, the foreign ministers also discussed
scenarios under which the community could create a formal foreign
policy role that would be acceptable to all 12 nations, officials
said on condition of anonymity.
   Only Belgium and Italy strongly endorsed the notion of letting
the Western European Union merge with the EC. Britain, France and
the Netherlands were more cautious.
   British Foreign Secretary Douglas Hurd said he ``would like to
see the European pillar of NATO strengthened.'' He said Sunday's
talks showed ``not much enthusiasm for the fusion of the'' Western
European Union into the EC.
   Officials said Britain fears that endowing the EC with a role in
defense matters would weaken the link between Western Europe and
its U.S. and Canadian allies.
   The community said Sunday it wants to sign declarations with the
United States and Canada within the next six weeks, stressing
political and economic links across the Atlantic.
   The EC foreign ministers will continue to discuss political
union in the weeks ahead. They are also considering giving a
greater say in EC affairs to the European Parliament, the largely
advisory 518-member assembly that meets once a month in Strasbourg,
France.
   In December, negotiations begin on amending the community's 1957
founding treaty to elevate the EC from a trade bloc to an
organization with a collective foreign policy.
   The talks on political union will be held concurrently with
negotiations on creating an EC central bank and a common EC
currency.
   The 12 members of the European Community are Belgium, Denmark,
France, Germany, Greece, Ireland, Italy, Luxembourg, the
Netherlands, the United Kingdom, Spain and Portugal.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0046 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 1702EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-HumphreyTrial     10-07 0285</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Humphrey Trial,0325</SECOND>
<HEAD>Gainesville Slayings Suspect Faces Assault Count</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MELBOURNE, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A much-publicized suspect in the
Gainesville student slayings is going to trial on a charge of
beating his 79-year-old grandmother, and his lawyers say it won't
be easy to pick an impartial jury.
   Edward Lewis Humphrey has been under intense scrutiny since his
Aug. 29 arrest by Brevard County authorities. Soon after that,
investigators named him as a suspect in the slayings of five
college students.
   Humphrey has been jailed on $1 million bond and if convicted,
could be sentenced to as much as 5{ years in prison. However, his
grandmother, Elna Hlavaty, says she will testify she was injured in
a fall and wasn't hit by Humphrey.
   The trial begins Monday with jury selection, which officials in
the Brevard County public defender's office warn could be lengthy.
They are worried that news media coverage of the Gainesville
investigation may have damaged Humphrey's chance for a fair hearing
on the charge of aggravated assault on the elderly.
   ``I think it will take quite a while,'' said Gene Stevanus,
executive director of the public defender's office.
   News accounts have told of police searching Humphrey's property,
towing away his car and taking various samples of his body tissue,
along with his history of violent threats, nighttime
``reconnaissance missions,'' his fondness for knives, and his
mental illness tied to a car accident.
   Recently, authorities investigating the Gainesville slayings
have appeared to back away from Humphrey as a suspect. They have
made little public comment, but they have warned Gainesville
residents to be careful because the killer could still be loose.
   Mrs. Hlavaty, who initially said her grandson hit her, now says
she fell and injured herself the night her grandson came home from
school.
   Mrs. Hlavaty said she is looking forward to the trial as the
only way for family members to put the nightmare behind them.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0047 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 1707EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Obit-Arevalo 1stLd-Writethru a0712 10-07 0460</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Arevalo, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0712,0539</SECOND>
<HEAD>Juan Jose Arevalo, Former Guatemalan President, Dead at 86</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: UPDATES throughout to CORRECT dates of Mendez Montenegro's
term, ADD that Arevalo served as ambassador to Chile, wrote book
critical of U.S., is survived by widow; no pickup</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By ALFONSO ANZUETO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>GUATEMALA CITY (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Juan Jose Arevalo Bermejo, a former
president whose civilian government was considered a shining moment
for the poor in a nation dominated by military governments, has
died, his family said Sunday. He was 86.
   Arevalo died at the Spanish Hospital in the Guatemalan capital
late Saturday, said his sister-in-law, America Barahona de Arevalo.
She did not give the cause of death.
   Arevalo, a former university professor in the humanities,
returned to Guatemala from Argentina following a 1944 popular
uprising that ended the 14-year-old military dictatorship of Jorge
Ubico.
   Becoming president the following year, he set about carrying out
social reforms akin to those of President Franklin D. Roosevelt in
the United States.
   During his six years in office, Arevalo established a social
security system, began agrarian reforms and worked to integrate the
Indians, who made up about half the population, into the nation.
   In 1951, he turned the government over to his elected successor,
Col. Jacobo Arbenz Guzman, who expanded the reforms under a
center-left administration until he was overthrown in a U.S.-backed
revolt in 1954.
   Col. Carlos Castillo Armas, who led the CIA-funded rebels in an
invasion from Honduras, took power until his assassination in 1957.
A series of right-wing military governments followed, and a leftist
insurgency began in 1960 and still continues today.
   ``Within Guatemalan history, Arevalo will stand out as a kind of
founding father of modern Guatemala,'' said Stephen Schlesinger,
co-author of the Guatemalan history ``Bitter Fruit: The Untold
Story of the American Coup in Guatemala.''
   ``What he will be remembered for is this extraordinary time -
the only time, really, since its creation in 1821 - that it had a
government that was compassionate toward the poor and the
Indians,'' Schlesinger said in a telephone interview in New York.
   Arevalo was one of only two civilian Guatemalan chief executives
in the past 60 years to complete his term. The other was Julio
Cesar Mendez Montenegro, who served from 1966 to 1970. Arevalo was
ambassador to Chile under Mendez Montenegro.
   Elections are set for November to replace civilian President
Vinicio Cerezo, elected in 1985.
   Arevalo wrote several books, among them ``The Shark and the
Sardine,'' a criticism of U.S. policy in Latin America.
   He was to be buried in Taxisco, 65 miles southeast of Guatemala,
where he was born Sept. 10, 1904. The government was expected to
declare a day of mourning.
   Arevalo is survived by his widow, Margarita de Leon; their five
children; a sister, Marina Arevalo de Meneses, and a brother,
Mariano Arevalo Bermejo.
   Schlesinger said Arevalo's ``legacy will be that he was a
shining moment in Guatemala's political history, a moment that was
extinguished by the 1954 American coup.
   ``He's still a symbol of a moment of hope in Guatemala's
history, a symbol that many Guatemalans hope will be reflected in
change in the coming decade.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0048 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 1707EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-SouthAfrica     10-07 0419</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-South Africa,0492</SECOND>
<HEAD>Reports Say De Klerk, Mandela to Meet Monday</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JOHANNESBURG, South Africa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President F.W. de Klerk and
African National Congress leader Nelson Mandela have set a meeting
for Monday to discuss recent black factional fighting, newspapers
reported.
   The ANC called last week for a meeting with de Klerk on the
violence in black townships around Johannesburg, which has killed
about 800 people since erupting Aug. 12.
   The fighting has pitted Zulu followers of the conservative
Inkatha movement against Xhosas and other blacks linked to the ANC,
the nation's largest anti-apartheid group. It has strained
relations between the white-led government and the ANC.
   Mandela and other black leaders have accused security forces of
instigating the street fighting in a bid to destabilize the country
and derail peace talks with the government.
   ``These groups want to destroy the ANC so that we would take up
arms and fight among ourselves,'' Mandela told a rally Sunday in
Pietermaritzburg, in eastern Natal Province.
   De Klerk and government officials have denied the charge. They
have challenged the ANC to provide proof of security force
involvement and pledged to investigate any allegations.
   News reports Sunday said Mandela would present de Klerk with
affidavits Monday backing his claims of security force involvement
in the violence.
   Scattered incidents of violence were reported Sunday in
Johannesburg area townships.
   Police reported three Xhosa men were killed in Daveyton, east of
Johannesburg, in a dispute with Zulus. Police Lt. Henriette Bester
said two Zulu men were arrested and two handguns confiscated.
   She said the clash Saturday appeared to be isolated.
   Police also reported that two men were burned to death in
separate incidents in Sebokeng, to the south, and Tembisa, which is
north of the city.
   The fighting has eased in recent weeks after periods in which
dozens of blacks died daily.
   The government last month imposed measures designed to stop the
fighting in some of the most seriously affected townships. The
measures included weapons searches, roadblocks and a 9 p.m.-4 a.m.
curfew. Authorities lifted the curfew in the sprawling township of
Soweto last week.
   De Klerk also announced an amnesty for people and organizations
turning in illegal weapons. Police said Sunday more than 3,200
weapons had been turned in, and that the amnesty would extend until
the end of the month.
   Most of the weapons turned over have been handguns and rifles.
Police said only five traditional ``terrorist'' weapons, including
an AK-47 assault rifle and a machine gun, have been recovered in
the program.
   De Klerk has pledged to end the apartheid system of racial
segregation and white dominance. He has led the government in talks
with the ANC aimed at setting up negotiations on sharing power with
the black majority.
   Under apartheid, the 5 million whites control the government and
economy. The 30 million blacks have no voice in national affairs.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0049 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 1713EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Budget-NationalImpact     10-07 0645</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Budget-National Impact,750</SECOND>
<HEAD>Federal `Shutdown' Little Noticed Except At Some National Parks</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Budget-Not Shutdown Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Vacationing Americans have been hardest hit so
far by the budget stalemate, encountering ``closed'' signs at
Montana's Custer Battlefield National Monument and locked gates at
the White House.
   The federal government technically shut down at 12:01 a.m.
Saturday, except for essential services, but that was the first day
of a three-day Columbus Day holiday weekend.
   As a result, most federal employee did not anticipate returning
to work until Tuesday. Workers were told to report to their jobs
Tuesday, at which time non-essential personnel will be sent home
within the first three hours if there is no budget agreement.
   Congressional Democrats say they hope to have a budget agreement
with the Bush administration by then, thereby allowing government
to resume spending money and averting a widespread halt in
government services.
   The shutdown affects non-essential government personnel
nationwide. But federal operations deemed essential, such as those
involving aviation, health, law enforcement and security, are not
affected by the crisis. Normal weekend operations were in effect,
for example, at the Defense Department and at the Federal Aviation
Administration.
   Over the weekend, the most visible impact of the budget impasse
fell on the National Park Service, which runs mountain and seaside
resorts from coast-to-coast.
   In Texas, visitors were turned away from seashores and mountain
lodges. At Big Bend National Park in West Texas, spokesman Roy
Given had to notify guests on Saturday they were no longer welcome
at the remote wilderness park.
   The park hotel, restaurant and stables will remain open, but Big
Bend no longer is offering its guided tours, campground facilities
or its back country and river permits.
   A busload of tourists from Indiana drove six hours to reach the
Great Smoky Mountain National Park, only to be turned away by
rangers Saturday at Clingman's Dome, the highest point in the park.
   At Yosemite National Park in California, some 7,000 campers were
told they would have to clear out by 1 p.m. Sunday because of the
budget crisis. ``I think it's horrible,'' said Becky Vaccarezza of
Stockton, who months ago had made reservations for a week-long
vacation with five other adults and six children.
   Yosemite superintendent Michael Finley said he was told by
Interior Department officials in Washington not to close the park,
but to curtail all operations except emergency services.
   In Michigan, layoffs were reported at the Pictured Rocks
National Lakeshore at Munising and at the Sleeping Bear Dunes on
Lake Michigan near Empire.
   In the nation's capital, thousands of tourists were locked out
of some of the nation's most historic sights for the second day:
the 13 Smithsonian Institution museums, including the air and space
museum, one of the most popular in the world; the White House; the
Library of Congress; and the Washington Monument.
   But cranky visitors flooded the Capitol where lawmakers met to
try to iron out a deal. Many complained about the cutback in
services. The House gallery rocked with boos when the House
recessed five minutes after convening at 4 p.m. Although the
lawmakers arranged to reconvene when there was something on the
budget to consider, the frustrated tourists were not happy with
what they saw.
   In Washington state, Olympic National Park shut down and Mount
Rainier National Park closed all but one small campground. In
Arkansas, five national parks were closed.
   Some tourists found an unexpected boon as a result of the
crisis.
   In Florida, ticket takers at Everglades National Park were sent
home, allowing motorists to drive in free.
   At the opposite end of the state, Jerry Eubanks, supervisor of
the Gulf Islands National Seashore headquartered in Gulf Breeze,
said the park will remain open.
   ``We have looked at alternatives,'' he said. ``We've just
refreshed in our own minds what are essential health and safety
measures, but we have no plans as of now for shutting down.''
   There was also confusion about what was open and what was not.
   In Iowa, visitors could tour the Herbert Hoover Presidential
Library and Museum buildings operated by the National ARchives and
REcords Administration. But other buildings on the grounds, run by
the park service, were locked up.
   Federal employees, meantime, tried to enjoy their holiday.
   ``I probably should be worried, but I'm not,'' said Doug
Druliner, a hydrologist with the U.S. Geological Survey in
Nebraska.
   ``We've gone through this thing in the past, but there was not
as much hype about it. We've had furloughs in the past and been
paid later.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0050 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 1725EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-MobilTrial     10-07 0408</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mobil Trial,0484</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mobil's CEO Ordered To Testify in Civil Suit Against Firm</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOSEPH NEFF</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEWARK, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The head of Mobil Oil Corp. has been ordered
to testify this week in a lawsuit by a former company environmental
officer who says he was fired for refusing to help cover up
problems at one of its plants.
   Mobil's chief executive officer, Allen E. Murray, was ordered by
a federal judge last week to testify in U.S. District Court in a
civil suit filed against the nation's second largest oil company.
The trial resumes Wednesday.
   Plaintiff Valcar Bowman was fired in 1986 as the No. 2
environmental officer for Mobil Chemical Co. He wants his old job
back, along with back pay and legal costs.
   Mobil denies Bowman's claims that his ethical purity got him
fired. The company says Bowman was fired as part of a cost-cutting
campaign and for insubordination and disobedience.
   In a hearing last year, U.S. District Judge Harold Ackerman
noted that Bowman lost his job in 1986, Mobil Chemical's best year
ever with a record $140 million in profits, up 164 percent from
1985.
   Bowman doesn't deny being obstreperous, at one point saying that
effective environmental managers ``are not going to win a
popularity contest.''
   The dispute between Bowman and the company stems from an
investigation by Los Angeles authorities into alleged air pollution
violations at Mobil's oil refinery in Torrance, Calif.
   On July 18, 1985, the Los Angeles County district attorney,
search warrant in hand, swept unannounced into the Torrance
facilityaand emerged with boxes of documents detailing alleged
violations.
   The raid shocked Mobil, which feared a similar search of the
Mobil Chemical Co. plant in Bakersfield, Calif.
   According to company documents, Mobil ordered Bowman's staff to
deliver all records not required by law to be kept at the plant to
the company's outside counsel, Lawrence Straw.
   The theory was that attorney-client privilege would keep the
documents confidential and out of the hands of snooping
investigators, according to Charles Lindberg, Mobil's chief
in-house lawyer.
   ``It would be more difficult for any agency to obtain any of the
information delivered to Mr. Straw than it would for them to obtain
that information from Mobil directly under subpoena,'' Lindberg
wrote.
   Bowman says he opposed transferring the documents as unethical
and immoral and that Mobil knew an inspection of the plant was
imminent.
   Ackerman, in a December hearing, described Mobil's effort to get
the documents out of the plant and into Straw's hands as
``frantic.''
   It is expected that Murray will be questioned about the
transferred documents and his response to a memo Bowman sent to the
CEO about environmental negligence and irresponsibility at the
firm.
   The trial has been going on for five weeks, mostly consumed with
highly technical testimony by Bowman.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0051 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 1734EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Tay-Sachs     10-07 0526</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Tay-Sachs,0656</SECOND>
<HEAD>Deadly Hereditary Disease Cuts Swath in Rural Louisiana</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Maigon cq.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>IOTA, La. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An untreatable, fatal genetic disease thought
confined to the descendants of Eastern European Jews has turned up
in this heavily Catholic community.
   Nobody knows how Tay-Sachs disease got here, but it apparently
is turning up at an even higher rate than among Jews.
   Babies with Tay-Sachs develop normally until they are about 6 or
7 months old. After that, they degenerate slowly but steadily,
taking years to die.
   ``It's so awful to sit and watch your child deteriorate,'' said
Renee Abshire, whose daughter, Maigon, died of Tay-Sachs less than
two months after her third birthday.
   ``She lived with constant pneumonia, constant coughing,'' Mrs.
Abshire said. ``The last six months of her life, I'd sit and cry.''
   Mrs. Abshire, 26, was checked twice during her pregnancy for
deformities or hereditary problems in the developing fetus.
   Her obstetrician never checked for Tay-Sachs. It didn't seem
necessary. Testing for Tay-Sachs is routine in many Jewish
communities, but Renee and David Abshire are fundamentalist
Christians and unaware of any Jewish ancestors.
   Talking with doctors around southwest Louisiana, Mrs. Abshire,
now president of the local Tay-Sachs &amp; Allied Diseases Association
chapter, found three other children with Tay-Sachs.
   None was Jewish. And in three of the four cases, including hers,
at least one parent had attended Iota High School.
   The connection made this Cajun town of 1,200 people something of
a genetic ground zero. Three cases weren't an epidemic, but were
enough to make people wonder how a rogue gene, a destroyer of
children, had slipped into their bloodlines.
   ``In this small a community, you'd never see this many cases, so
you can say it's kind of an explosion,'' said Dr. Michael Quinn, a
Crowley pediatrician who treats children from Iota. ``It has to be
that someone moved there years and years ago, and two families had
the gene, and through intermarriage right in the Iota area, that's
where the disease is concentrated.''
   Dr. Emmanuel Shapira, a Tulane Medical Center geneticist,
checked the blood from 230 townspeople in July. More people wanted
to be tested, but Shapira ran out of test kits. The results, he
said, were astonishing.
   ``It's very, very high - at a level to justify screening every
couple that wants to have children,'' he said. ``As many as 5
percent are going to be born with it.''
   He said 17 of the people he screened carried the gene that can
cause Tay-Sachs. That's 7.4 percent, or nearly double the carrier
rate among Jews and about 20 times the rate among the entire
population.
   A child with Tay-Sachs lacks a crucial enzyme the body needs to
break down fatty deposits in brain and nerve cells.
   Without the enzyme, deposits accumulate disastrously. The
nervous system stops working. Muscle tone vanishes. Respiratory
problems develop. It is always fatal, usually before the age of 5.
   The disease is on a gene carried by about 4 percent of all Jews
and about a tenth that rate in the entire population. There is no
reliable estimate of the number of cases, said Marjorie Epstein, a
spokeswoman for the National Tay-Sachs &amp; Allied Diseases
Association.
   Carrier couples who try to have children face another tough
decision: what to do if a prenatal test shows the fetus has
Tay-Sachs. Abortion is frowned upon in this conservative,
overwhelmingly Catholic section of Louisiana.
   The Abshires have decided not to try to conceive again.
   ``The hardest decision for me if I got pregnant again would be
to terminate my pregnancy,'' said Mrs. Abshire. ``I know of someone
who had to do that. God didn't set me down here to judge her. Who
am I to judge her when I know what Tay-Sachs did to me and my
husband, what we went through?''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0052 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 1737EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-NewVolcanoes     10-07 0315</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-New Volcanoes,330</SECOND>
<HEAD>Researchers Discover New Underwater Volcanoes</HEAD>
<NOTE>For release at 6:30 p.m. EDT - time set by source</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By RANDOLPH E. SCHMID</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A series of underwater volcanoes has begun
rising from the sea floor off the coast of Oregon, researchers said
Sunday.
   The volcanoes have appeared during the past 10 years, forming a
line about 300 miles off the coast, according to Dr. Robert Embley
of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration's Pacific
Marine Environmental Laboratory.
   Several of the volcanoes are more than 100 feet high and a
half-mile wide, according to Embly and researchers from Oregon
State University.
   Embley said the appearance of the underwater volcanoes may be
related to gigantic bursts of hot, mineral-rich water discovered in
the same area in 1986 and 1987 during research on the sea floor.
   This is the first time scientists have been able to determine
the date of particular ocean floor volcanoes, according to Embley.
Monitoring the development may allow them to learn more about how
such events affect ocean chemistry and temperature.
   The cones were discovered when sea floor pictures and surveys
made during the last year were compared with 1981 surveys and
several new volcanoes were found. Researchers then dove into the
area in the submersible Alvin and found that fresh lava flows
extend into and cover a large fracture that had cracked the older
sea floor.
   The researchers believe that the sea floor in the area is
actively spreading, producing increased volcanic activity.
   This region is part of the so-called Ring of Fire, a system of
volcanic and earthquake-prone regions than encircle the Pacific
Ocean, caused by movement of the giant plates that make up the
surface of the Earth. It is here that the Pacific Plate is grinding
against the North American plate, the same activity that helps
provoke earthquakes in California and Alaska and volcanic eruptions
such as that of Mount St. Helens.
   While the development of volcanoes under the ocean is not
thought to be unusual, scientists do not really know how often such
eruptions occur because of limited ability to monitor their
development.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0053 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 1743EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-RolledOver     10-07 0258</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Rolled Over,0307</SECOND>
<HEAD>Child, Grandmother Survive Being Run Over by Wheat Planter</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SALINA, Kan. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A woman threw herself over her 2-year-old
granddaughter just as a 1-ton wheat planter rolled over them, and
each somehow survived the twisting blades.
   ``She just lay down on her,'' said the child's mother, Karrie
Sullivan. ``I don't think my daughter would be here today if she
had not done that.''
   JoanSullivan, 54, of Niles, was hospitalized for treatment of
broken bones and bruises. Young Sara escaped Friday's accident with
just a few scrapes.
   ``She saved her life, basically,'' Karrie Sullivan said. ``And
Joan could have been a lot worse. I just can't believe it.''
   The accident occurred while Sara's grandfather, James Sullivan,
was planting wheat on the 800-acre family farm in Niles, about 20
miles east of Salina.
   Sara dashed between the tractor and the planting bins it was
dragging and her grandmother went after her. Her grandfather didn't
see or hear either of them as he drove the tractor.
   ``The wheat drills (discs) just ran over the top of her and
chopped her up pretty bad,'' said Joan's cousin, Peter Sullivan.
``It kind of buried them in the ground a little bit, you know.''
   A wheat planter, called a drill, hooks behind a tractor and
plants seed in grooves cut by sharp-edged discs about a foot in
diameter. The discs are about eight inches apart and are followed
by rollers that compact the seed into the soil.
   No one could say why Joan and Sara Sullivan were not injured
more seriously. Peter Sullivan speculated that because the field
was tilled for sowing, the softer earth cushioned the victims.
   He also said the discs have a spring system that allows them to
give slightly when they hit a large object.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0054 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 1748EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Austria-Elections 1stLd-Writethru a069 10-07 0537</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Austria-Elections, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0692,0621</SECOND>
<HEAD>Populist Party Gains In Parliamentary Elections</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: UPDATES throughout with official preliminary results,
likelihood of new coalition, quotes; trims; no pickup</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By ROLAND PRINZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>VIENNA, Austria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The populist Freedom Party, capitalizing
on widespread popular discontent over bureaucracy and corruption,
made strong gains in parliamentary elections Sunday.
   The governing Socialists slightly increased their representation
and offered to form a new coalition government with the
conservative People's Party, which lost ground in the balloting.
   The Socialists made it clear throughout the election campaign
they would not form a coalition with the Freedom Party, which they
say is too far right.
   Preliminary results announced by Interior Minister Franz
Loeschnak showed the Freedom Party increased its representation
from 18 to 33 seats in the 183-seat Parliament and won 17 percent
of the vote, up from 10 percent in 1986.
   The Socialist Party added one seat and now holds 81.
   The big loser was the People's Party, which has been in a
coalition with the Socialists since 1986. It lost 17 of its 77
seats, its worst defeat in history.
   The fourth major party, the Green Alternative, won nine seats,
an increase of one.
   Freedom Party leader Joerg Haider appealed to nationalist
sentiments and voters seeking a change after 45 uninterrupted years
of rule by either the Socialists or the People's Party.
   He hammered away at the special advantages members of the two
big parties enjoy and attacked the relatively liberal treatment
given immigrants from neighboring East European countries.
   The charismatic 40-year-old had said he hoped his party could
win between 25-30 seats with its campaign against bureaucracy and
high-level mismanagement.
   At least three corruption cases are pending against prominent
Socialists.
   ``The 30 seats in parliament were our admittedly ambitious
target,'' said Heide Schmidt, general secretary of the Freedom
Party. ``The fact that we may achieve this or gain even more fills
me with gratification.''
   Helmut Kukacka, the People's Party general secretary, called it
a ``heavy, depressing defeat.''
   ``We are certainly the big losers,'' he said.
   The Conservatives still bear the burden of their support four
years ago for President Kurt Waldheim, who is accused of concealing
his World War II past. Waldheim was not considered a major issue in
this campaign, however.
   The Socialists said their showing was a vote for Chancellor
Franz Vranitsky, by far the most popular politician in Austria.
Party chief secretary Josef Cap said the result would underscore
the Socialists' claim to leadership.
   Vranitzky said he would invite the People's Party for coalition
talks.
   But he added, ``it must be clear that the formation of a
government cannot retroactively correct the election results,''
indicating a reduced role for the conservatives.
   Only 83 percent of the 5.6 million Austrians registered to vote
went to the polls, one of the lowest turnouts in national
elections. In 1986, 90 percent of the voters participated.
   There were few clear-cut issues in what was generally regarded
as among the most uninspring election campaigns in years.
   The main topics were Austrian efforts to win membership in the
European Community, calls by the right to limit immigration and
foreign labor and mutual pledges to reduce privileges of officials
who hold two or more paid jobs.
   Many observers said that with the likelihood the coalition would
continue after the election, leaders of the major parties refrained
from sharply attacking each other.
   Vranitzky, 53, has been working with his party to recover from
stinging publicity caused by several party officials who tampered
with public funds. In the scandal, Socialist Chancellor Fred
Sinowatz was recently found guilty of perjury.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0055 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 1758EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-DolphinsRelease     10-07 0410</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Dolphins Release,0506</SECOND>
<HEAD>Researchers Hopeful Captive Dolphins Will Adapt to Wild</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JAMES MARTINEZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TAMPA BAY, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Echo and Misha, two dolphins held captive
for more than two years as part of a California research project,
splashed to freedom in the same shallow waters they once knew as
their home.
   ``When they start swimming along the coast and socializing with
other dolphins - then we'll call it a success,'' said conservation
biologist Randy Wells, who plans to track the dolphins for a year
in what scientists say is the first extensive study of how captive
dolphins adapt in the wild.
   ``Of course, it will take them a while to get their bearings,''
Wells said.
   Within seconds after a dozen Mote Marine Laboratory researchers
gingerly lowered Echo and Misha into the water Saturday, they sped
off in tandem - and beached themselves on a sandbar.
   Cheers turned to concern, and researchers swam out to the
foundering dolphins and gave them a second push. Within an hour,
they were spotted swimming with a pod of about three dolphins.
   Wells, affiliated with the Chicago Zoological Society, took the
dolphins from the same harbor in the summer of 1988 for a project
at the University of California at Santa Cruz. He wanted to study
the sophisticated system of sounds dolphins use to gather
information about their watery environment.
   Last month, the two 300-pound dolphins were transported to Mote
on Central Florida's Gulf Coast to prepare for their return home.
   While other captive dolphins have been released in the wild,
Wells said this is the first project involving electronic
monitoring and tracking to find out how captive dolphins readjust
and socialize.
   ``You have to understand that for the past two years, these
dolphins have been isolated and hand-fed nothing but frozen fish,''
said Kerri Dieffenwierth, spokeswoman for Mote, where the dolphins
were held in a protective lagoon, taught to eat live fish and
slowly weaned from human contact.
   For the first two days in the wild, the 8- and 9-year-old males
will be followed around the clock, both visually and with the help
of a coin-sized radio transmitter on Echo's dorsal fin.
   ``Male dolphins tend to bond for life,'' the spokeswoman said.
``they were together when we found them and they should be together
forever.''
   The transmitter has a range of more than six miles and an
expected life of two weeks before the specially designed bolts
dissolve and fall off.
   After that and for the year to come, researchers working from a
small boat will track the dolphins three to four days a week and
for up to 12 hours a day - taking photographs to see how well they
are assimilating into dolphin society and even counting their
breaths to gauge their health.
   If they begin to show signs of sickness or are shunned by other
dolphins, scientists are prepared to take them back. But Wells
doesn't expect that to happen.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0056 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 1812EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ExxonAuction     10-07 0289</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Exxon Auction,0338</SECOND>
<HEAD>Oil-Spill Equipment to be Auctioned</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ANCHORAGE, Alaska (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Thousands of surplus cotton overalls,
rubber gloves, fishing nets and other Exxon Corp. equipment left
over from its oil-spill cleanup in Prince William Sound go on the
auction block this week.
   ``You know, all of Alaska is going to be dressed up just like
Exxon,'' said Bill Ballard, one of dozens of potential bidders
scrutinizing the equipment laid out in warehouses and construction
yards in south Anchorage.
   The auction begins Tuesday and is expected to last until Friday.
   Among items on sale will be 10,000 new cotton overalls, 10,000
disposable coveralls, 20,000 new rubber gloves, 3,000 pairs of new
rain jackets and pants and 40 pairs of brand-new, size-13 rubber
boots.
   The equipment ranges from inflatable rafts to portable toilets,
and fishing nets to 50 miles of chain.
   The Exxon Valdez tanker ran aground on Prince William Sound in
March 1989, spilling almost 11 million gallons of Alaskan crude in
the nation's biggest oil spill.
   Exxon said last month it had sold the surplus gear to Ritchie
Bros. Auctioneers International of Vancouver, British Columbia, for
an undisclosed amount. The sale of 4,844 lots is open to all
comers, with no minimum bids and a pledge that every item will be
sold, the auctioneers said.
   Spokesman Rob Mackay said he expects at least 5,000 bidders will
sign up, and that the auction will bring in more than $10 million
in sales.
   Exxon spokesman Karsten Rodvik said the surplus is part of the
33,000 tons of cleanup equipment moved to Anchorage last fall for
storage.
   ``We are keeping enough equipment and material to conduct a
shoreline survey in the spring and to complete an additional
cleanup that might be needed next year,'' he said.
   Though the sale will include some heavy equipment, specialized
oil-spill gear like skimmers and booms are not being sold. They
will be kept by Exxon for its refineries and marine terminals,
Rodvik said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0057 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 1814EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-MormonConference     10-07 0386</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mormon Conference,0442</SECOND>
<HEAD>Church Leader Says Abortion, Homosexuality Are `Spiritually
Dangerous'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By VERN ANDERSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SALT LAKE CITY (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Mormon Church leaders on Sunday decried
abortion, homosexuality and drug addiction as ``morally and
spiritually dangerous'' lifestyles.
   ``In or out of marriage, abortion is not an individual choice.
At a minimum, the lives of three are involved,'' Elder Boyd K.
Packer told the church's 160th Semiannual General Conference.
   Only in cases of incest, rape, when a mother's health is
jeopardized or a severely deformed fetus who cannot survive birth
is abortion anything but a ``thou shalt not,'' Packer said, and
even then ``much sober prayer is required to make the right
choice.''
   The two-day conference of The Church of Jesus Christ of
Latter-day Saints concluded Sunday with the faith's president, Ezra
Taft Benson, still hospitalized in serious condition following
surgery nearly three weeks ago for blood clots on the brain.
   Church officials said Benson, 91, watched the proceedings on
television.
   Packer, a senior member of the Council of the Twelve Apostles,
blasted those who justify homosexuality by saying ``these impulses
are inborn, cannot be overcome and should not be resisted.''
   ``They quote scriptures to justify perverted acts between
consenting adults. That same logic would justify incest or the
molesting of little children of either gender,'' he said.
   ``I believe that most people are drawn to a life of drug
addiction or perversion or submit to an abortion without really
realizing how morally and spiritually dangerous they are.''
   Elder Joseph B. Wirthlin of the Twelve warned against getting
sidetracked by ``activities that begin innocently or that are
perfectly legitimate in moderation, but in excess they can cause us
to veer from the straight and narrow path to our destruction.''
   Among those, he said, are excessive viewing of sports,
television, improper movies and devotion to obtaining material
possessions such as homes that are larger than necessary.
   ``And even if we are blessed enough to afford such luxury, we
may be misdirecting resources that could be used better to build
the kingdom of God, or to feed and clothe our needy brothers and
sisters,'' Wirthlin said.
   Gordon B. Hinckley, Benson's first counselor in the governing
First Presidency, lamented that the 7.5 million-member church
likely would never shed its nickname, the Mormon Church, in favor
of The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints.
   ``Because of the shortness of the word Mormon and the ease with
which it is spoken and written, they will continue to call us the
Mormons, the Mormon Church, and so forth,'' Hinckley said. ``They
could do worse.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0058 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 1815EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Obit-Teengs     10-07 0140</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Teengs,0138</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dutch World War II Resistance Figure Dies At 82</HEAD>
<DATELINE>THE HAGUE, Netherlands (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Johan Teengs Gerritsen, a
well-known Dutch resistance fighter during World War II, died in a
car crash Sunday at age 82, Dutch television reported.
   Teengs Gerritsen fought the German occupation of the Netherlands
in 1940. He was captured and held at a concentration camp in France
and later in Dachau, Germany, where he was freed by U.S. troops in
1945.
   In the 1970s, he became a spokesman for Dutch resistance
fighters who opposed moves to pardon two German war criminals
responsible for deporting more than 100,000 Dutch Jews.
   But Teengs Gerritsen eventually relented and supported the
government's decision last year to free the Nazis, Ferdinand aus
der Fuenten and Franz Fischer. The two have died since in their
German homes.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0059 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 1814EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p AM-LouisianaPrimary 1stLd-Writethru a0722 10-07 0655</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Louisiana Primary, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0722,0810</SECOND>
<HEAD>Duke Concedes Loss, Johnston Says He `Got the Message'</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 9th graf, `Under Louisiana's...' to change `unique' to
`unusual' to reflect that at least two other states have open
primaries.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NU4</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ALAN SAYRE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW ORLEANS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   State Rep. David Duke conceded defeat Sunday
to incumbent U.S. Sen. J. Bennett Johnston, who said he ``got the
message'' from 600,000 voters who backed Duke, a former Klan leader
running as a Republican.
   Duke backed off his threat to file a lawsuit over absentee
ballots cast - but not counted - for state Sen. Ben Bagert, the
official Republican nominee. Bagert dropped out two days before
Saturday's primary amid pressure from national GOP leaders who
feared his presence in the race would help Duke force a November
runoff.
   ``We'll help people who feel their right to vote has been
abrogated,'' Duke said. ``We'll help them pursue that if they so
desire, but I'm trying to do as Bennett Johnston said, and kind of
heal at this point.''
   Complete but unofficial returns gave Johnston 749,552 votes, or
54 percent, and Duke 605,681 votes, or 44 percent. Two minor
Democratic candidates split the remainder. Nick Accardo had 21,709
votes and Larry Crowe had 14,472 votes.
   Duke's strength surprised pollsters, as he carried 23 of the
state's 64 parishes and held Johnston close in several others. Duke
had campaigned on a ticket that opposed affirmative action and
proposed welfare reform and a flat-rate federal income tax.
   Johnston said Duke benefited from a protest vote arising from
sour economic conditions in Louisiana.
   ``A lot of those votes were protest votes,'' Johnston said.
``People were sort of venting their spleen. They said, `Well, I'm
going to send old Bennett a message.' Bennett got the message.''
   He said he would work to diversify the state's economy away from
the petroleum industry's boom-and-bust cycles.
   Under Louisiana's unusual open primary system, all candidates
run against each other in the primary, regardless of party. A
runoff would have been held Nov. 6 if Johnston had failed to
receive a majority Saturday.
   Bagert withdrew too late to get his name off the ballot. Under a
1981 law, Bagert's votes could not be counted.
   Some were, however, because it was too late to change computer
programs or courthouse operations. Those reported to the Associated
Press gave Bagert 10,536 votes - less than 1 percent of the 1.4
million cast.
   Duke said ``political deals'' were responsible for Bagert's
withdrawal. Johnston drew the unprecedented cross-party endorsement
of eight Senate Republicans and Jack Kemp, secretary of housing and
urban development.
   Johnston said his 10 percent victory margin would have been
considered a landslide had it not been for Duke's presence in the
race.
   ``When you can win at a time that incumbents all over the
country are in trouble, when Louisiana has been in a depression and
when people are trying to send a message ... I think that's a
tremendous win,'' Johnston said.
   Duke said he was studying a possible run for governor in 1991.
Such a race would require him to give up his state House seat,
which he won in a special election in 1989.
   There also has been speculation Duke might seek a U.S. House
seat in 1992, probably from one of the north Louisiana districts
that gave him strong support Saturday.
   Johnston said Duke's political future was limited and predicted
he would never win a statewide race or capture a U.S. House seat.
   Ed Renwick, a political pollster for Loyola University, said it
would be difficult to discount Duke in future races because he drew
55 to 60 percent of the white vote.
   He said Duke's support on Saturday was threefold - voters
opposed to Johnston, voters who merely wished to ``send a message''
and full-fledged Duke supporters.
   ``I think he'll keep the third group,'' Renwick said. ``He'll
lose the first group. The question is how long he'll keep the
second group.''
   In other races on Saturday's ballot, New Orleans was assured of
having its first black congressman since Reconstruction when state
Sen. William Jefferson and Marc Morial, both Democrats, led a field
of 12 to replace retiring Rep. Lindy Boggs. Jefferson and Morial
meet in the runoff next month.
   By a 2-1 ratio, voters also approved Louisiana's first lottery
since a corrupt private lottery was shut down by Congress in the
late 1890s. Under a bill already approved by the Legislature, the
games will be managed by a quasi-governmental corporation.
   New Orleans District Attorney Harry Connick, acquitted earlier
this year of federal charges stemming from the return of a
bookmaker's records, easily won re-election over two opponents.
Connick is the father of Harry Connick Jr., a Grammy Award-winning
musician.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0060 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 1822EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-WeatherpageWeather     10-07 0284</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Weatherpage Weather,0329</SECOND>
<HEAD>Like Winter in the Rockies, Summer in New England</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   While a winterlike storm Sunday brought snow to higher
elevations of Wyoming, Utah and Colorado, unseasonably warm
temperatures prevailed in the Northeast.
   In Colorado, overnight snowfall brought up to 9.5 inches at Red
Feather Lakes and 6 inches to Virginia Dale and Rand.
   In northern Utah, 3 inches of snow was reported east of Heber
City and 2 inches at Park City.
   There also was snow in mountains of southern and southeast
Wyoming and the Laramie Valley, with more expected Monday. Up to 7
inches of snow blanketed Cheyenne, while Laramie Valley got up to 5
inches.
   Light snow was reported in western Nebraska, with Kimball
receiving about 4 inches of snow overnight.
   Most of the Midwest was cold Sunday afternoon, with temperatures
in the 30s in Oklahoma, Kansas and eastern Nebraska.
   But in the South, East and Far West, sunny skies and warm
temperatures prevailed Sunday afternoon.
   Temperatures were in the 80s across the Gulf Coast and the
southern Atlantic Coast states, with parts of South Texas topping
90 degrees.
   Temperatures warmed into the 70s and 80s from the central
Atlantic Coast north to New England. The West saw similar readings,
with temperatures into the 90s in the Southwest deserts.
   Cape Hatteras, N.C., set a record high for the date: 86 degrees.
   Isolated showers and thunderstorms appeared in the South and
Southeast, with nearly 2 inches of rain Sunday in Jonesboro, Ark.
   Overnight rain was locally heavy from eastern Kansas through
southern and central Illinois. St. Louis got 2.25 inches overnight.
   Several western cities set record low temperatures for the date
Sunday: 24 degrees in Boise, Idaho; 24 degrees in Spokane, Wash.;
25 degrees in Yakima, Wash.; and 16 degrees in Williston, N.D.
   The low temperature for the Lower 48 states Sunday was 8 degrees
at West Yellowstone, Mont.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0061 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 1823EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-OffTheHook 1stLd-Writethru a0719 10-07 0210</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Off The Hook, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0719,0233</SECOND>
<HEAD>Fisherwoman's Case Dangles Too Long, Charges Dropped</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 5th graf, `But Marion...' to CORRECT that prosecutor
isn't running for secretary of state.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>INDIANAPOLIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Beatrice B. Thomas' crime was to reel in an
undersized bass and not throw it back. But the courts kept her
dangling too long, and now she is off the hook.
   Twice the 64-year-old Thomas went to court intending to plead
guilty to catching the 9{-inch-long largemouth bass at Eagle Creek
Reservoir.
   She had been caught red-handed at the reservoir in June by a
conservation officer with the Indiana Department of Natural
Resources. Possessing a largemouth bass under 14 inches long is a
misdemeanor punishable by up to 60 days in jail and a $500 fine.
   On her first appearance at Marion Municiapal Court, officials
could not find any record of her case. When she showed up again,
the paperwork was still not straightened out, and she was asked to
return a third time.
   But Marion County Prosecutor Stephen Goldsmith decided Friday he
has bigger fish to fry.
   ``I do not intend to prosecute that woman,'' he said. ``Anyone
who comes downtown twice to plead guilty deserves a break.''
   Thomas is not completely satisfied.
   ``They might dismiss the charges against me, but somebody else
might come along and have to go through the same thing,'' she said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0062 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 1829EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--France-Riots     10-07 0138</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--France-Riots,0132</SECOND>
<HEAD>Police Battle Rioters Near Lyon</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LYON, France (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hundreds of youths set fire to cars and
buildings, ransacked shops and hurled rocks at riot police Sunday
following the death of a motorcyclist in a collision with a patrol
car.
   Police used tear gas against the rioters, who rampaged for
several hours through a large commercial area in Vaulx-en-Velin, a
low-income suburb of 50,000 people near Lyon. Columns of smoke
towered over the town center.
   Seven firemen, three journalists and an undetermined number of
rioters were injured.
   Youths from low-rent housing projects in the town held police
responsible for the death Saturday of Thomas Claudio, 21. Claudio,
whose family emigrated from Spain, was a passenger on a motorcycle
that reportedly was being pursued for a traffic violation.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0063 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 1848EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--Libya     10-07 0130</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Libya,0113</SECOND>
<HEAD>Libyan Government Names New Prime Minister</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ROME (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Libyan government on Sunday named a new foreign
minister and prime minister, official television reported.
   The General People's Congress named Ibrahim Muhammad al-Bishari
foreign minister, replacing Jadallah Azzuz al-Talhi, who becomes
secretary for strategic industries, Libyan television said.
   Abu Zayd Umar Durdah was named secretary of the General People's
Committee, or prime minister, according to the television,
monitored in London. He replaced Umar Mustafa al-Muntasir, who
became secretary for economic planning.
   The post of prime minister is not a powerful one in Libya, which
is ruled by Col. Moammar Gadhafi. Bureaucratic posts in Libya
frequently change hands.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0064 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 1855EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Bush 1stLd-Writethru a0703 10-07 0498</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bush, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0703,550</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush Spends Sunday at Camp David and Away From Budget Fray</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: Deletes last three grafs prv to remove reference to
possibility of scheduled Souter White House ceremony being
canceled; the White House says it will go ahead as planned</NOTE>
<HEAD>With AM-Budget Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CHRISTOPHER CONNELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Bush spent much of the holiday
weekend in his mountaintop retreat at Camp David, Md., 75 miles
from the budget battle that left tourists locked out of the
capital's most famous monuments.
   Left behind in the White House was a skeleton staff of ushers,
butlers and maids, but a full complement of Secret Service and
uniformed officers.
   In a concession to austerity, Bush eschewed his Marine One
helicopter and made the trip up to the Catoctin Mountains by
motorcade Saturday night.
   ``It's a lot less expensive to go by motorcade,'' said John
Herrick, a White House press aide who accompanied the president.
   Before leaving for Camp David, Bush had vetoed a short-term
spending measure that Congress passed Friday night. Without
spending authority, a phased shutdown of non-essential government
services began nationwide.
   With the House trying to work out another budget pact Sunday,
Bush conferred by telephone from Camp David with White House chief
of staff John Sununu and Treasury Secretary Nicholas Brady. The two
men were part of the troika of key administration aides who
negotiated the deal soundly rejected by the House early Friday.
   Sununu, appearing on CNN's ``Newsmaker Sunday'' program, said
the administration remained reluctant to raise income tax rates and
still would prefer a package like the one that went down to defeat
in the House.
   But Sununu said the aim now was to find a way to allow the
congressional committees to ``get some of the rough edges off'' a
deal.
   Roman Popadiuk, a deputy White House press secretary working
from home, said the next step ``is up to the Hill. They're supposed
to come up with a budget.''
   Bush was at Camp David with Thomas ``Lud'' Ashley, a former Ohio
congressman and Yale classmate who is now a banking industry
executive.
   Barbara Bush planned to join her husband at Camp David later
Sunday after flying down from the couple's oceanfront home at
Kennebunkport, Maine.
   Bush himself had planned to spend the extended Columbus Day
holiday weekend in Maine, but canceled that trip in light of the
budgetary crisis.
   He attended a 9 a.m. private service at a Navy chapel at Camp
David as he usually does during his frequent stays there.
   Camp David is located within a 10,000-acre preserve known as the
Catoctin Mountain Park and the adjacent Cunningham Falls State
Park.
   Like other national parks, Catoctin Mountain Park was among the
first to feel the budget pinch, with its visitor center closed and
nature hikes and other interpretive programs canceled.
   Camp David itself, however, is a Navy installation, staffed
permanently by Navy personnel and Marine guards, and its
recreational facilities were not subject to the shutdown.
   Bush tentatively planned to return to the White House by
motorcade Monday, again passing up the speedier but costlier
helicopter ride, Herrick said.
   The White House normally is closed to public tours on Sunday.
Officials said earlier that 65 of the 383 people who usually work
there were deemed essential, including the National Security
Council staff that operates the situation room 24 hours a day.
   But the staff that operates the executive mansion's living
quarters - butlers, maids, chefs and others - was cut from 70 to
10.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0065 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 1905EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Pakistan-Plot     10-07 0385</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Pakistan-Plot,0428</SECOND>
<HEAD>Pakistan Says Indian-Trained Agents Arrested</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KATHY GANNON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ISLAMABAD, Pakistan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Pakistan's army-backed caretaker
government said Sunday it had arrested 58 agents who slipped into
Sind, home province of ousted Prime Minister Benazir Bhutto, to
sabotage Oct. 24 parliamentary elections.
   A government spokesman said several of the agents confessed to
having been sent by the Indian government and others claimed
membership in the militant Al-Zulfikar organization, named for Ms.
Bhutto's father, Zulfikar Ali Bhutto.
   Zulfikar Ali Bhutto was overthrown in a 1977 coup and was hanged
two years later for his alleged complicity in a murder plot.
   Army Chief-of-Staff Gen. Mirza Aslam Beg warned last week that
India was hatching a plot to wreck Pakistan's elections.
   India and Pakistan have fought three wars since independence in
1947. Tensions have risen recently over a Moslem separatist
movement in India-controlled Kashmir.
   ``If they can undermine the elections . . . Pakistan can be
destabilized,'' said a government official, speaking of India.
   The official and the government spokesman spoke on condition of
anonymity.
   Al-Zulfikar was run by Ms. Bhutto's younger brother, Murtaza,
who has been living in Syria since he orchestrated the 1982
hijacking of a Pakistan International Airline aircraft.
   Pakistan's newspapers carried many stories over the past week
about election sabotage plots, fuelling fears that polls could be
postponed.
   Several analysts said an upsurge in Ms. Bhutto's popularity
since her dismissal by President Ghulam Ishaq Khan on Aug. 6 may be
worrying those who fired her.
   An Indian Embassy spokesman in Islamabad said he knew nothing of
Indian nationals being arrested.
   ``Normally if there were Indians arrested the Foreign Office
would be obliged to call us,'' he said, speaking on condition of
not being further identified.
   The president dismissed Ms. Bhutto's 20-month-old government on
charges of unchecked corruption and abuse of power.
   The dismissal probably was approved by the nation's powerful
military, which has ruled Pakistan for 25 years of its 43 years as
a nation. There is little love lost between the Bhutto family and
the Pakistani military.
   Even Ms. Bhutto's critics concede that her popularity has soared
since Ishaq Khan announced that special one-judge tribunals would
investigate her goverment for corruption.
   The tribunals have been assailed as overtly partisan. They have
indicted Ms. Bhutto; her husband, Asif Ali Zardari, and about six
former Cabinet ministers.
   If convicted Ms. Bhutto could be barred from politics for up to
seven years. She could be tried separately on criminal charges.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0066 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 1915EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-GulfRdp 1stLd-Writethru a0738 10-07 0741</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf Rdp, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0738,0890</SECOND>
<HEAD>Kuwaiti Refugees Gather at Saudi Border after Iraq Opens Frontier</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Leads with 11 grafs to UPDATE with Arafat comments, picks up
11th graf pvs, `Kuwaiti refugees ...</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By SIDNEY S. FEINGOLD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Hundreds of Kuwaitis crossed into Saudi Arabia on Sunday after
Iraq suddenly relaxed restrictions on Kuwaitis leaving the occupied
emirate. Some refugees said it was the latest move in an Iraqi
campaign to depopulate Kuwait, isolate the resistance movement and
prepare for war.
   World leaders kept up diplomatic efforts to achieve a peaceful
solution to the crisis that arose with Iraq's invasion of Kuwait on
Aug. 2.
   Japan's Prime Minister Toshiki Kaifu traveled to Oman after a
two-day visit with King Faud in Saudi Arabia.
   PLO leader Yasser Arafat met King Hussein in Jordan and said a
peace initiative on the gulf crisis was being formulated according
to the plan proposed by Iraqi President Saddam Hussein.
   On Aug. 12, Saddam said he would discuss withdrawing from Kuwait
if the Israelis also withdrew from the West Bank and Gaza Strip.
   Arafat said Saddam's proposal ``has brought aboutan
international consensus for the need to solve the Palestinian
problem.''
   ``The linkage is becoming possible now. Those who believe
otherwise, let them submit their own proposals to solve the Middle
East problems,'' he said.
   Egyptian Foreign Minister Ismat Abdul-Maguid, meanwhile, arrived
in Damascus for talks with Syrian President Hafez Assad. He
indicated he was making the visit to increase cooperation in
forcing Iraq out of Kuwait.
   Kaifu arrived in the Mideast last week to offer financial help
to front-line states Turkey, Jordan and Egypt and to seek a
political solution. He has referred to a new world order after the
crisis is solved in which Japan was eager to play a role.
   Kaifu spokesman Shigeo Takaneka said Fahd urged Tokyo to spread
its financial aid to other nations hit by the U.N.-imposed economic
blockade of Iraq, such as Syria and Bangladesh.
   Takaneka said Japan reiterated its call for Iraq's complete and
unconditional withdrawal from Kuwait, restoration of the emirate's
leadership and release of all foreigners detained by Iraq after its
attack on Kuwait.
   Kuwaiti refugees at the Khafji border crossing in Saudi Arabia
said the border opened on Friday following intensified night
searches in Kuwait City which prompted many of them to leave out of
fear. They said Iraqi troops were confiscating all identification
papers in Kuwait.
   That raised Saudi fears that the Iraqis planned to try to
infiltrate agents into the kingdom.
   About 1,000 people arrived from Kuwait over the weekend, most
lacking any identification, Saudi border officials said. The influx
was the largest since mid-September, when 7,000 Kuwaitis poured
through in a three-day frenzy.
   U.S. military officials in Washington and Saudi Arabia meanwhile
reported the American troop buildup in the crisis area was nearly
complete, with almost 200,000 U.S. soldiers deployed there. U.S.
troops lead a multinational force arrayed in the Saudi desert to
forestall any further Iraqi military thrust.
   Iraq controls 20 percent of world oil reserves with its takeover
of Kuwait. Saudi Arabia, which adjoins Kuwait, is the world's
biggest oil exporter.
   In other developments:
   -Soldiers in Israel began handing out gas masks to civilians in
a nationwide drive to guard Israelis from a possible Iraqi chemical
arms attack. Military officials called it just a preventive
measure. Prime Minister Yitzhak Shamir said in a speech Israel
``has no intentions to attack Iraq,'' although it takes Baghdad's
chemical attack threats seriously, Israel radio said.
   -The British newspaper Independent identified a Chinese company
it said supplied Iraq with a rare chemical used to make nuclear
weapons, missile fuel and nerve gas. It said the China Wanbao
Engineering Co. contracted to supply seven tons of lithium hydride
to Iraq, breaching the U.N. embargo. Beijing officials last week
strongly denied an earlier report about a chemical deal.
   -About 100,000 Italians joined a 15-mile peace march from
Perugia to Assisi in northern Italy, many demanding that force not
be used in the crisis.
   -Britain's visiting armed forces minister, Archibald Hamilton,
said in Bahrain that Britain is redeploying a squadron of Tornado
GR1 ground-attack jets from Bahrain to Saudi Arabia and 12 Jaguar
strike aircraft from Oman to Bahrain. ``This is basically to
enhance our deterrent effect,'' he said.
   -Kuwait Airways has started chartering flights from Cairo to
take home thousands of Sri Lankan refugees transported from camps
in Jordan, an airline officer said in the Egyptian capital. The
airline, national carrier of Kuwait, has been out of operation
since the invasion. A flight Saturday which carried about 376 Sri
Lankans home was its first in more than two months.
   -The European Community nations discussed a military solution to
the crisis but concluded it was better to see if the world trade
embargo forces Iraq to leave Kuwait. ``Time is not in favor of
Saddam Hussein,'' Italian Foreign Minister Gianni De Michelis told
reporters at the meeting in Venice, Italy.
   -The Dutch government said its ambassador in Kuwait was expected
to leave for Baghdad, effectively closing the mission because of
unbearable conditions caused by Iraqi pressure. Foreign Ministry
spokesman Dig Istha said the Belgian and German embassies are also
likely to close soon.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0067 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 1953EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-SpaceShuttle 2ndLd-Writethru a0750 10-07 0650</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Space Shuttle, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0750,0792</SECOND>
<HEAD>Discovery's Crew Starts Fire Aboard Shuttle as Test</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 9th graf, `Kathy Thornton...' to CORRECT time element.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto HTN1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARCIA DUNN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Aerospace Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CAPE CANAVERAL, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Discovery's astronauts, their
primary job behind them, started a small fire aboard the shuttle
Sunday as part of an experiment to study the spread of flames in
space.
   The solar probe Ulysses, meanwhile, sped safely toward Jupiter
at a record-setting 34,130 mph. Discovery's five-man crew started
the satellite on its roundabout journey of 1.86 billion miles
shortly after liftoff Saturday.
   The first test fire aboard a shuttle burned about 70 seconds
within a sealed aluminum container, as cameras recorded the event.
Shuttle safety managers wanted to observe how fire acts in the
absence of Earth's gravity.
   The cylinder was filled with equal amounts of oxygen and
nitrogen. The amount of gases will vary when the experiment is
repeated on future flights.
   Discovery's five-member crew arose shortly before 3 a.m. EDT for
its first full day in space Sunday. The astronauts are scheduled to
stay in orbit until a Wednesday morning landing at Edwards Air
Force Base, Calif.
   Saturday's launch marked the end of months of frustration for
the National Aeronautics and Space Administration, which has
suffered through problems with its shuttle fleet and the flawed
Hubble Space Telescope. Columbia and Atlantis have been grounded
since early summer by hydrogen leaks.
   Discovery's smooth liftoff, NASA's first shuttle launch in
nearly six months, was followed by successful deployment of the sun
probe Ulysses.
   The $250 million European spacecraft is expected to arrive at
Jupiter in February 1992. The powerful gravity pull of that giant
planet will act like a slingshot, accelerating the probe to an even
higher speed and sending it streaking back toward the sun.
   Kathy Thornton of Mission Control in Houston told crew members
before they went to sleep Sunday that Ulysses was slightly cooler
than expected but within its temperature limits.
   Ulysses is to pass over the sun's south pole in 1994 and the
north pole in 1995. It will be the first spacecraft to orbit over
the solar poles.
   Preliminary data show Ulysses will spend 231 days above 71
degrees solar latitude, seven or eight days more than if Discovery
had gone up Friday, the earliest possible launch date for the
mission, Thornton said. NASA had to delay the launch for a day.
   ``This is another space first - a customer who's happy with a
launch delay,'' Thornton told the pleased crew.
   Sunday's fire experiment ``was designed from the beginning
knowing what we were doing'' and its design was carefully reviewed
by safety experts, said Louis Ignaczak, the project's supervisor.
   Coincidentally, Discovery commander Richard N. Richards had a
fire scare during his first space flight in August 1989. A short
circuit sent smoke and sparks into the cabin of the shuttle
Columbia; NASA said the crew was never in danger.
   ``We can never learn enough about fire safety, as far as I'm
concerned, aboard the orbiter,'' Richards said before Discovery's
flight.
   As part of another experiment Sunday, the astronauts extended
Discovery's 50-foot-long robot arm. Attached to the boom are two
patches of material identical to that used on solar panels of a
communications satellite stranded in a uselessly low orbit.
   Intelsat, an organization of countries that owns the satellite,
wants to measure how much the same kind of material on the
satellite will decay in space before NASA sends up astronauts in
early 1992 to repair the craft.
   ``Provided the results from this experiment are not wildly
different from what we expect, it will be the final piece of data
that gives us the confidence to go ahead and rescue the
spacecraft,'' said Intelsat scientist Andrew Dunnet.
   The $157 million satellite failed to separate properly from an
unmanned Titan rocket in March. Intelsat is suing rocket maker
Martin Marietta Corp. for at least $400 million in damages.
   Earlier Sunday, astronauts Bill Shepherd and Bruce Melnick
reported only limited success with an experiment to control TV
cameras with voice commands. Their voices were recorded prior to
the mission onto computer chips that the system was supposed to
recognize in space.
   The system is designed to free astronauts of manual camera
operations and thus let them to do more than one thing at a time.
   Shepherd and Melnick tried moving the cameras by speaking such
words as ``up,'' ``down'' and ``zoom out.'' Melnick had better luck
than Shepherd, who reprogrammed the system with the sound of his
voice in space but still achieved little success.
   The two planned to repeat the experiment Monday and again
Tuesday.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0068 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 1959EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-AutoTalks 1stLd-Writethru a0711 10-07 0505</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Auto Talks, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0711,0612</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ford, UAW Reach Tentative Agreement</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 10 grafs to UPDATE with details of deal, CORRECT
number of locals to 44 sted 79. Picks up 9th graf pvs, `About
100,000... A version also moving on the financial wire.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By FREDERICK STANDISH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Auto Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DEARBORN, Mich. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The United Auto Workers union and Ford
Motor Co. reached a tentative national labor contract Sunday
closely mirroring the agreement last month with General Motors
Corp.
   ``This tentative agreement provides that UAW-represented Ford
workers will fully share in the gains achieved by the pattern
settlement reached earlier at General Motors,'' said UAW President
Owen Bieber in a statement.
   Under the three-year deal, Ford will put aside about $1.5
billion to cover the income of workers who are laid off, Bieber
said. GM, which has three times as many UAW workers, promised to
spend up to $4 billion to protect the incomes of laid-off workers.
   Negotiators stayed up all Saturday night to close the deal. As
the negotiations intensified last week, after the union's contract
with GM was ratified, the main dispute was a clause calling for
penalty pay up to $5 an hour for excessive scheduled overtime.
   That provision in the GM-UAW contract was aimed directly at
Ford. Since the late 1980s, Ford's manufacturing employees worked
considerably more overtime than those at GM. At one time, nearly 20
percent of the cars and trucks the automaker assembled were made by
workers on overtime.
   Ford Chairman Harold Poling said he did not expect the overtime
penalty to be an immediate problem because of the falloff in truck
and car sales.
   ``I think short term we're going to be faced a serious problem
because of the general economy,'' Poling said. ``I think it's going
to take some time to evaluate what the alternatives are.''
   Analysts and automakers have forecast a slow recovery in the
sales rate of cars and trucks in the United States from a trough
late last year.
   Ford ``probably won't have much in overtime expenditures next
year,'' auto analyst David Healy of the New York investment banker
Barclays de Zoete Wedd said Sunday.
   The union has scheduled a meeting of its 135-member Ford
bargaining council for Tuesday in Dearborn. That panel of union
local presidents and bargaining committee officials must approve
the tentative agreement before it is sent to the UAW's 44 Ford
locals for rank-and-file ratification.
   About 100,000 Ford employees are covered by the UAW national
contract. GM has about 300,000 workers represented by the union,
and Chrysler Corp., which still must bargain a national agreement,
has about 63,000 hourly and salaried UAW members.
   Provisions of the pattern agreement included:
   - A three-year income guarantee for every worker laid off for
more than 36 weeks at factories closed because of slow car, truck
or parts sales.
   - A 3 percent boost in workers' base wages in the first year and
lump-sum payments of 3 percent of wages in the second and third
years.
   - Continuation of cost-of-living adjustments in wages.
   - Improvements in pension payments.
   - No change in health-care provisions.
   The GM-UAW agreement was ratified a week ago in a lopsided 80
percent to 20 percent vote. After a contract with Ford is ratified,
the UAW will head to Chrysler.
   There, the union and the company are at loggerheads over whether
the financially struggling company will be allowed to deviate
greatly from the pattern agreement.
   Company officials have insisted that Chrysler needs relief from
soaring health-care costs, and the pattern agreement first
negotiated with GM provides no changes.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0069 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 2005EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Obit-Maktoum 1stLd-Writethru a0743 10-07 0275</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Maktoum, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0743,0317</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dubai Ruler Dies at 84</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Leads with 3 grafs to show discrepancies on Sheik Rashid's
age; picks up 3rd graf pvs, `Sheik Rashid..</NOTE>
<DATELINE>DUBAI, United Arab Emirates (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Sheik Rashid bin Saeed
al-Maktoum, co-founder of the United Arab Emirates and ruler of
Dubai, died Sunday, the state television announced.
   Official sources put Sheik Rashid's age at 84, but The
International Who's Who, a reference book, said he was born in
1914, which would make him 75 or 76.
   The sources said Sheik Rashid died of old age after being near
death for about four years. The official cause of his illness was
not disclosed.
   Sheik Rashid was also vice president and prime minister of the
U.A.E., the federation of sheikdoms that includes Dubai, Abu Dhabi,
Sharjah, Ras al-Kaimah, Ajman, Umm al-Qaiwain, and Fujairah.
   Sheik Rashid founded the federation in 1971 with his
brother-in-law, Sheik Zayed. The seven sheikdoms that stretch from
Qatar to Oman along the Persian Gulf previously had been ruled
together under an agreement with the B`itish.
   Sheik Rashid is survived by four sons. The eldest is Crown
Prince Sheik Maktoum bin Rashid al-Maktoum, who is to succeed his
father as ruler of the oil-rich emirate.
   Another son, Sheik Mohammed al-Rashid, is the U.A.E. defense
minister, while Sheik Hamdan al-Rashid is minister of finance and
industry.
   The president of the federation of gulf states, Sheik Zayed bin
Sultan Al Nahyan, is the late sheik's brother-in-law.
   Dubai, with a population of 400,000, mostly expatriate workers,
produces a daily average of 500,000 barrels of oil. It is the
leading business center in the Gulf region.
   Dubai has among the highest per capita incomes in the world -
$19,300 a year.
   The federal government in Abu Dhabi declared a two-week period
of mourning, and the burial was scheduled for Monday.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0070 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 2008EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Israel-Travel     10-07 0213</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Israel-Travel,0224</SECOND>
<HEAD>Israel ``Amazed'' over U.S. Travel Warning</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf Rdp</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Israel expressed its ``amazement'' on Sunday at
a State Department travel warning that urged Americans to avoid the
Persian Gulf and Israeli-occupied lands because of persistent
unrest and tensions.
   The advisory was issued Saturday.
   Prime Minister Yitzhak Shamir sought to reassure travelers
Sunday, saying, ``All friends of Israel and those who know Israel
also know you can visit Israel safely . . . without fear.''
   Israel's embassy in Washington was instructed ``to express our
amazement and complaint concerning the travel advisory which
together with the situation in the Persian Gulf dealt with Judea,
Samaria and Gaza,'' Foreign Ministry spokesman Yosef Amihud said.
   It said ``the Americans have recently expressed their
satisfaction with the recent improvement of the conditions of
security in the territories.''
   Judea and Samaria are the biblical names for the occupied West
Bank, which with the Gaza Strip was captured by Israel in the 1967
Mideast war. A Palestinian uprising against Israeli rule has been
going on in these areas since December 1987.
   Tourism and hotel officials have reported a 30 percent drop in
the number of visitors since the gulf crisis began. A nationwide
gas mask distribution campaign has begun here in response to
threats of chemical attack from Iraq.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0071 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 2009EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p AM-Johnston     10-07 0374</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Johnston,0440</SECOND>
<HEAD>Johnston: Duke Won't Last</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Louisiana Primary, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ALAN SAYRE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW ORLEANS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Unusually upbeat after an unsettling U.S.
Senate race, J. Bennett Johnston said Sunday that David Duke's
strong challenge would not shove him to the political right.
   Johnston said his 10-point victory over Duke would have been
considered a landslide if his opponent had not been a former Ku
Klux Klan grand dragon.
   ``When you can win at a time that incumbents all over the
country are in trouble, when Louisiana has been in a depression and
when people are trying to send a message ... I think that's a
tremendous win,'' Johnston said.
   ``There's frustration out there,'' he said. ``When people are
unemployed and underemployed, it's easy to blame it on someone
else. It's easy to blame it on affirmative action.''
   Johnston, a Democrat, captured a fourth term in Saturday's
primary. Unofficial returns gave him 54 percent of the vote against
44 percent for Duke, who was running as a Republican on a platform
that opposed affirmative action.
   During his third term, Johnston was linked with the liberal wing
of the Senate with an unsuccessful bid to become Senate majority
leader and his key role in opposing Supreme Court nominee Robert
Bork. At the same time, he usually voted along conservative lines
on such issues as defense.
   ``The left is not comfortable with him. The right is not
comfortable with him,'' said Wayne Parent, a political scientist at
Louisiana State University.
   Johnston said he ``got the message'' from voters who backed
Duke. Asked whether the scare would move him more into the
conservative ranks, he said: ``No. It's going to push me closer to
the people, working harder for the people. That means doing even
more than I've done.''
   Johnston, chairman of the Senate Energy Committee, which
oversees legislation dealing with the oil and gas industry, has
drawn fire for accepting millions of dollars in campaign donations
from political action committees, including the petroleum and
petrochemical industries. Both industries have been blamed for
contributing heavily to Louisiana's environmental problems.
   Until this race, Johnston had no problems winning re-election.
   Parent said Duke's showing probably would not affect Johnston's
place in Washington. ``He'll be viewed as a senator who survived an
odd race as many senators have,'' he said.
   Johnston pledged to work against Duke in any future race. Duke
said Sunday that he is considering a run for governor next year.
   ``David Duke may have the Gestapo, but we've got the shock
troops in our favor,'' Johnston said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0072 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 2018EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Czechoslovakia     10-07 0342</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Czechoslovakia,0378</SECOND>
<HEAD>Havel Says Oil Crisis Could Shake Czechoslovakia</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SELMA KALOUSKOVA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PRAGUE, Czechoslovakia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President Vaclav Havel said Sunday
an energy crisis stemming from a drop in Soviet oil supplies could
undermine Czechoslovakia's new democracy.
   Authorities began cutting back on gasoline sales Saturday
because Moscow has not been meeting its quota of oil deliveries.
Citizens can buy about seven gallons of gas a month at the official
price of about $3. Purchases exceeding that cost more.
   Havel is seeking an urgent meeting with Soviet President Mikhail
S. Gorbachev and Prime Minister Nikolai I. Ryzhkov to discuss the
oil crisis.
   ``I would like to explain to Gorbachev the way we see things,''
Havel said in his regular weekly radio address.
   ``At this moment we are talking not only about business and
dollars but about stability of a country in Central Europe, a
country whose stability many other European countries believe in
and depend on,'' Havel said.
   Czechoslovakia is introducing economic reforms designed to
transform the centralized economy left behind by the ousted
Communists to a market economy.
   Czechoslovak officials held talks with Soviet authorities last
week in Moscow and Foreign Minister Jiri Dienstbier raised the oil
issue with Soviet Foreign Minister Eduard A. Shevardnadze during
talks at the United Nations.
   Havel said the threat to Czechoslovakia's economy could have
far-reaching negative consequences for the ``authority and
prestige'' of the Soviet Union.
   Soviet authorities have said this year's supply of oil to
Czechoslovakia will be about 2.6 million tons less than the
original allotment of 16.6 million tons.
   Havel said he would emphasize in talks with Gorbachev ``that
Czechoslovakia is making an effort in all talks dealing with the
future of the Warsaw Pact and the new European peace initiative to
respect sensitively the Soviet Union's interests.''
   If agreements are broken, Czechoslovakia would not feel bound to
take ``excessive consideration,'' he said.
   Havel said Prague is also looking elsewhere for oil supplies to
end its near-total dependence on the Soviet Union.
   The Soviet Union was for years the main oil supplier, under
subsidized conditions, for Czechoslovakia and other East European
nations. However, next year it will begin demanding convertible
currency for its oil.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0073 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 2029EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-HanfordTanks     10-07 0418</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Hanford Tanks,0494</SECOND>
<HEAD>Officials Ignored Scientist's Call for Tests on Leaking Tank</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SEATTLE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Officials at the Hanford nuclear reservation
ignored a call to conduct tests on a leaking nuclear-waste storage
tank, apparently because the procedure was too expensive, a retired
Hanford scientist said.
   ``These are not inexpensive tests,'' soils expert Ronald Routson
said in an interview reported Sunday in The Seattle Times. ``I
think it was dollars, pure and simple.''
   Routson said he urged Hanford officials in 1978 to perform the
tests after he noticed changes in radiation measurements in soil
beneath the single-walled tank, which was damaged in a 1965 steam
explosion.
   ``The only way to know what was going on at that tank was to do
the tests and that wasn't done,'' said Routson, who retired last
year after 23 years at Hanford. Rockwell International was the
government's prime contractor at Hanford in south-central
Washington until 1987.
   Ron Gerton, waste management director for the U.S. Department of
Energy in Richland, said the agency is ``fairly confident this work
wasn't done,'' but said he does not know why.
   Memos exchanged by Hanford contractors and its owner, the
Department of Energy, indicate Tank 105A could have leaked more
than a million gallons of contaminated cooling water into the
desert soil from 1965 through 1978.
   Public documents initially estimated the leak at 5,000 gallons,
but make no mention of cooling water that was regularly added to
the tank until 1978 to prevent an explosion, the newspaper reported
last week.
   The state Department of Ecology has asked the Department of
Energy to provide all documentation about the 35-year-old tank by
Wednesday, said Roger Stanley, manager of the state agency's
Nuclear and Mixed Waste Program.
   Tank 105A is one of 177 at Hanford used to store waste generated
during four decades of plutonium production for nuclear weapons.
   In a letter to Hanford managers dated April 12, 1978, Routson
said changing radiation measurements in the soil beneath the
concrete structure indicated ``a substantial quantity of the water
being added to the tank is leaking to the sediment ... up to
570,000 gallons.''
   He recommended tests to measure how much cooling water was
leaking and how much was evaporating inside the tank, and sampling
the sludge in the bottom of the tank to determine its radioactive
content.
   ``I told my managers there were indications that radiation had
leaked and they ought to find out what's going on,'' Routson said
from his home in Benton City.
   Three radiation-detection devices buried beneath the tanks are
inadequate to properly assess how much was leaking, he said.
   Spokesman Eric Campbell of Westinghouse Hanford, which replaced
Rockwell as prime contractor at the site, said current records show
that the radioactive leak has not spread more than 100 feet from
the tank. Ground water lies 285 feet below the surface.
   Records before 1977 have not been found, Campbell said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0074 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 2104EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-MysteryMan     10-07 0269</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mystery Man,0318</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mysterious Alumnus Showers Professors with Goodies</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SPOKANE, Wash. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Whitworth College saluted a devoted
alumnus this weekend, but nobody was surprised when the Mystery Man
didn't show up for the festivities.
   Since 1988, the Seattle-area Mystery Man has sent dozens of
professors and their spouses on exotic trips, all expenses paid,
following up with gifts such as cameras, artwork or coffee makers.
   Alfred Gray, a retired Whitworth journalism professor, and his
wife, Nicolin, were whisked off on a trip to New Zealand last fall.
   And three weeks ago, a local department store advised them ``we
were supposed to come in and pick out a TV or sound system he
wanted us to have,'' Gray said.
   So far, 28 current and former faculty members at the private
school have been recipients of the Mystery Man's largesse and there
seems to be no end in sight, said Paul Viren, director of
Whitworth's development and alumni affairs office.
   Almost all the faculty contacts are made by Laurel Lindberg, the
travel agent who arranges the trips.
   Lindberg also accepted the Whitworth College award for alumni
devotion on the Mystery Man's behalf at Saturday's
homecoming-weekend banquet.
   No one came forward when he was invited to accept the award in
person, Viren said.
   Lindberg said the Mystery Man ``prefers to keep himself out of
the picture,'' but he did give her a brief message to read.
   ``Your students have not forgotten you,'' she quoted him as
saying.
   Campus sleuths have determined that the Mystery Man ``probably
was here in the early to mid 60s,'' Viren said.
   He likely has spent more than $150,000 so far on the surprise
gifts, the school official estimated.
   ``He is certainly not doing it for the publicity or for tax
breaks. He must do it for the joy it gives him,'' Viren said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0075 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 2107EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Taiwan-Politics     10-07 0319</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Taiwan-Politics,0344</SECOND>
<HEAD>Opposition Party Endorses Call for Taiwan Independence</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TAIPEI, Taiwan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Taiwan's largest opposition party passed a
resolution Sunday renouncing the country's claim over mainland
China, and observers said the vote could lead to a backlash by the
ruling Nationalist party.
   ``This party asserts our country's practical sovereignty does
not extend to mainland China and outer Mongolia,'' said Huang
Hsin-chieh, chairman of the Democratic Progressive Party. Taiwan
should plan its future based on its current territory, he said.
   Huang was speaking at the opposition party's congress at a hotel
in Taoyuan, 31 miles west of Taipei. Some 170 delegates gave him a
standing ovation.
   ``We are merely stating a political reality,'' Huang later told
reporters. Huang said his party passed the resolution despite
threats from the ruling Nationalist Party, whose secretary-general,
James Soong, met opposition leaders on Saturday evening.
   Officials said the government would disband any political party
that openly advocates Taiwan's existence as a state independent
from mainland China.
   The Nationalists had agreed in July to political reforms
reducing their four decades-long grip on the country. The reforms
included allowing, at some time in the near future, the country's
first popular vote for the presidency.
   Advocating an indepedent Taiwan is viewed as a seditious act by
the Nationalist government, which fled to Taiwan in 1949 after
losing a civil war to Communist forces on mainland China.
   The Nationalists since then have limited the voting power of
native Taiwanese, who make up about 80 percent of the population.
   Earlier on Sunday, President Lee Teng-hui chaired the inaugural
session of the National Unification Council, a task force formed to
assist the president in making policies on Taiwan's reunification
with China.
   ``We have never abandoned the goal of regaining mainland
territory and completing national unification,'' Lee said.
   Lu Ya-li, a political science professor at National Taiwan
University, said the opposition party's statement could lead to
repression by conservative Nationalists.
   ``The pace of democratic reforms will also slow down,'' he
predicted.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0076 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 2114EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-WinnetkaSlayings 2ndLd-Writethru a0763 10-07 0415</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Winnetka Slayings, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0763,0500</SECOND>
<HEAD>Judge Refuses Bond for Youth Charged in April Slayings of Couple</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 4th graf, `At an...' to CORRECT to hearing sted
arraignment; picks up 5th graf pvs, `Biro's attorney...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By COLLEEN DISKIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CHICAGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A judge denied bond on Sunday for a 17-year-old
high school student charged with killing a young suburban couple
and their unborn child in a case that had stumped police for
months.
   David J. Biro of Winnetka was being held at Cook County Jail on
two counts of first-degree murder and one count of deliberately
killing a fetus in the shooting deaths of Richard and Nancy
Langert, who lived near him in the prosperous Chicago suburb.
   Biro's arrest Friday followed six months of a frustrating,
multistate investigation in which police officers pursued numerous
dead-end leads, including rumors that the killings might be linked
to terrorist reprisals from Irish factions.
   At a hearing in Cook County Court, Judge Bernard Spak denied
bond to Biro, who is being charged as an adult, according to
Maureen McHale, a spokeswoman for the Cook County state's attorney
office.
   Biro's attorney, Bob Gewirtz, said he told the judge he was
upset that Biro was held in police custody for more than 24 hours
before being formally charged Saturday evening.
   ``Apparently he had not been allowed to talk to anyone in his
family or call an attorney during that whole time,'' Gewirtz said.
   Biro, a senior at New Trier High School, lives five blocks from
the townhouse where the couple was shot to death in the basement on
the evening of April 8.
   Mrs. Langert was 2{ months pregnant at the time of the
shootings.
   Police have acknowledged that Biro and the couple knew each
other, but prosecutors refused to elaborate on how well or what a
possible motive for the killings might be.
   Police Chief Herbert Timm said Saturday that Biro and the
victims were ``acquainted,'' but would not elaborate. Timm also
said ``nothing in their (the victims') personal lives led to this
tragedy.''
   Evidence against Biro was collected at the crime scene and in
his home, and police believe he acted alone, Timm said.
   The Chicago Sun-Times reported in its Sunday editions that
Winnetka investigators focused on Biro after he told another youth
details of the Langert slayings that had not been released
publicly.
   Besides the murder charges, Biro is accused of burglary at his
high school and of stealing a firearm.
   A preliminary hearing is scheduled for Tuesday.
   Langert, 30, and Mrs. Langert, 25, worked at Gloria Jean's
Coffee Bean Corp., a suburban Arlington Heights-based chain of
gourmet coffee shops. A spokesman for the company described them as
``kids you would want to be best friends with.''
   The rumors of possible involvement of Irish factions stemmed
from the fact that Mrs. Langert's sister is active in support for
rights for the Roman Catholic minority in Northern Ireland.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0077 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 2115EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Gulf-Iraq-Soviet     10-07 0231</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gulf-Iraq-Soviet,0260</SECOND>
<HEAD>More Soviet Citizens Leave Iraq</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Gulf Rdp</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BAGHDAD, Iraq (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   More than 100 Soviet citizens left Iraq
Sunday on a special Aeroflot flight, the first group to depart
since President Saddam Hussein told an envoy from Moscow last week
that they would be free to go.
   Soviet Embassy officials said more flights would be arranged to
evacuate Soviet citizens who want to return home. At least 2,000
out of an estimated 5,000 have expressed that desire, the officials
said.
   Saddam gave his personal permission for the evacuation on Friday
when he met with Yevgeny Primakov, a top aide to Soviet President
Mikhail Gorbachev.
   More than 11,000 Soviets were in Iraq at the time of the
invasion of Kuwait on Aug. 2. The last flight taking Soviets home,
mostly women and children, was on Sept. 27.
   Many of the remaining 5,000 are oil industry technicians working
under contract with the Iraqi government.
   The Soviet Union's Tass news agency reported earlier that
Primakov had ``raised the issue of the departure from Iraq of
Soviet specialists wishing to go home'' at the request of
Gorbachev.
   The specialists were not among the foreigners held as ``human
shields'' at hotels and strategic sites in an effort to deter
attacks.
   Tass said Primakov told Saddam that Moscow ``favors a political
settlement of the gulf crisis, bearing in mind a return to the
situation that existed before Aug. 2.''
   The Soviet envoy repeated Moscow's belief that Saddam should
withdraw immediately from Kuwait, Tass said.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0078 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 2127EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--Germany-Rightist     10-07 0153</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Germany-Rightists,0151</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ultra-Rightist Party Holds First Meeting in Former East Germany</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ERFURT, Germany (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The right-wing National Democratic Party
on Sunday held its first rally in the former territory of East
Germany and demanded that German borders be extended to their
pre-World War II limits.
   The party, which is reported to have about 6,000 members in
former West Germany, had been banned in Communist East Germany.
   About 700 police officers in riot gear were deployed against any
clashes between the rightists and about 250 protesters, according
to ADN, which before unification was the official East German news
agency. ADN did not say how many people attended the meeting.
   Speakers said the unification of Germany last Wednesday should
be a first step toward the return of territory forfeited by Germans
after World War II, ADN reported. About one-third of present-day
Poland was German territory before the war.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0079 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 2128EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p AM-DavidDuke     10-07 0405</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-David Duke,0501</SECOND>
<HEAD>Duke Boosted by Strong Showing</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Retransmitting to fix category code.</NOTE>
<HEAD>With AM-Louisiana Primary, Bjt</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NU4</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARY FOSTER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW ORLEANS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   It should have been the morning after but
instead it seemed more like a new beginning for David Duke, a
former Ku Klux Klan grand wizard and Nazi sympathizer.
   Duke surprised pollsters with a strong showing in the U.S.
Senate race, and took time to outline a national agenda while
conceding defeat Sunday.
   ``I've got to be very encouraged by this election,'' Duke said.
``I want to make a difference. And whether it's myself or other
people out there, we've got to have people up front talking about
the issues this campaign talked about.''
   Campaigning against affirmative action, minority set-asides,
busing for school integration and welfare abuse, Duke garnered 44
percent of the unofficial vote in Saturday's race against 54
percent for incumbent U.S. Sen. J. Bennett Johnston.
   ``You don't win elections with 44 percent, but it makes a lot of
politicians sit up and take notice,'' said Edward Renwick of Loyola
University's Institute of Politics.
   About 600,000 voters backed Duke, which represented a
substantial widening in his political base in two years.
   In his first political victory in February 1989, Duke formally
registered as a member of the Republican Party three days before he
was elected to the Louisiana House. He won by just over 227 votes
in a district that was 99.6 percent white.
   Running as a Democrat, Duke was defeated for state Senate in
1975 and 1979. In 1988, he got on the presidential ballot in 15
states as a Populist Party candidate, winning 48,267 votes, or 0.05
percent of the 91 million votes cast. The campaign was managed by a
former leader of the American Nazi Party.
   As a student, Duke dressed in a Nazi uniform at a campus protest
and later became national grand dragon of the White Knights of the
Ku Klux Klan.
   Duke left the KKK in 1980 after being accused of selling a
secret membership list. He formed the National Association of White
People, and shared a telephone number with the KKK until reporters
found out about it in 1989.
   Since winning election last year, Duke says he has moderated his
stand. He described his former Klan affiliation as youthful
hijinks.
   Duke said the Senate race was the first ``in recent history
where affirmative actin became a major issue, where strong
programs of welfare became a major issue. And I think now that's
going to happen across the country.''
   Duke said he was studying a possible run for governor in 1991.
   ``I certainly want to make an impact in state politics and I
want to continue to make an impact in national politics,'' he said.
   ``We are committed that this cause will not cease here,'' he
added. ``This is just the beginning, not the end of any political
odyssey.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0080 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 2205EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Mozambique-War     10-07 0225</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mozambique-War,0229</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rebel Leader Calls Off Peace Talks</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JOHANNESBURG, South Africa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The leader of the Mozambique
rebels has called off peace talks with Mozambican President Joaquim
Chissano's government.
   Afonso Dhlakama, head of the Mozambique National Resistance,
said on South African television Sunday the rebels would not take
part in the talks because government soldiers, backed by troops
from Zimbabwe, had started a new offensive against the rebels.
   The rebels have been battling Mozambique's government since
1977. They say they are seeking recognition as a political party
and free elections. But the rebels' political goals have never been
clear; they have been accused of widespread atrocities against
civilians.
   Periodic peace talks have been held in Rome. There have been no
breakthroughs, but more negotiations were expected.
   Zimbabwean troops have been assisting the Mozambique government
for several years. Their primary aim is to help protect
Mozambique's Beira corridor railroad, which is landlocked
Zimbabwe's shortest route to the Indian Ocean.
   The Mozambican war has left the southeastern African country one
of the poorest in the world. Annual per capita income is less than
$200 and almost half the 15 million people require some food
assistance.
   Chissano, a former Marxist, has been making political and
economic reforms. Mozambique's parliament is debating a new
constitution that would allow opposition parties to compete in
elections next year.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0081 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 2214EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p AM-CalifGovernor     10-07 0409</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Calif Governor,0464</SECOND>
<HEAD>Feinstein, Wilson Clash in Bitter Debate</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DOUG WILLIS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Political Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BURBANK, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Gubernatorial candidates Dianne Feinstein
and Pete Wilson clashed Sunday on Wilson's U.S. Senate attendance
record, campaign funding and their visions for the state's future,
in a bitter first debate.
   Feinstein, the Democratic former mayor of San Francisco, and
Republican Wilson both claimed to be the candidate of new ideas.
   ``I think there's a need for someone that's fresh, new and a
little bit different,'' Feinstein said in the live, televised
debate.
   Wilson said that being a Republican would not handcuff him in
Sacramento, where the Legislature is dominated by Democrats. He
also portrayed himself as a reformer.
   ``I'm running for governor because I want to make changes in
California that I think need to be made,'' said Wilson. He would
give up his Senate seat if elected Nov. 6 to succeed retiring
Republican Gov. George Deukmejian.
   The debate quickly turned to attacks, some personal.
   Feinstein accused Wilson of having ``the worst attendance record
in the Congress,'' missing votes on the death penalty, Supreme
Court confirmation, Middle East resolutions and the budget.
   ``I think absenteeism is an important indication of
performance,'' said Feinstein.
   Wilson countered that he has a 93 percent attendance record
overall, 2 percentage points better than that of Sen. Alan
Cranston, D-Calif.
   Turning to the offensive, Wilson criticized Feinstein for taking
large campaign donations in the wake of a judge's overturning
Proposition 73, which had limited individual donations to $1,000.
   He singled out Feinstein's acceptance of $150,000 from a
California Highway Patrol organization.
   ``Dianne, I am truly shocked that you would be so blind to so
gross a conflict of interest,'' he said.
   The one-hour debate, televised from KNBC-TV's studios, marked
the first time the rivals for governor have met face-to-face in
eight months, and their first-ever televised showdown. A second and
final televised debate is scheduled next week in San Francisco.
   The debate was divided into 30 minutes of questions from
political reporters and 30 minutes in which Feinstein and Wilson
questioned each other.
   The two debates are especially important because Wilson and
Feinstein have been virtually tied in every independent poll
reported since they won their party nominations in the June
primary.
   Much of the debates' impact is expected to come in post-debate
television and print reports.
   Viewership for the Sunday debate was not expected to be
particularly high because it coincided with the second game of the
American League baseball championship series between Oakland and
Boston and a Los Angeles Raiders-Buffalo Bills football game. Next
week's debate will compete with two of the most popular shows on
television, ``The Cosby Show,'' and ``The Simpsons.''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0082 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 2236EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Iraq-ArmsBroker     10-07 0394</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Iraq-Arms Broker,0492</SECOND>
<HEAD>Miami Arms Broker Says He's Owed for Bomb Sale to Iraq</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Florida arms brokr is suing to recover more than
$30 million he claims is owed to him for arranging the sale of
cluster bombs to Iraq. The timing, his lawyer admits, may be a
little awkward.
   Nasser Beydoun, 47, of Coral Springs, said he masterminded a
1983 deal that enabled Chilean industrialist Carlos Cardoen to sell
the Baghdad government at least $467 million worth of cluster bombs
and other military equipment.
   In a lawsuit filed with the Circuit Court in Dade County,
Beydoun claims Cardoen often referred to him as a ``golden key'' to
the Middle East arms market.
   ``When I opened the market, he crossed the bridge and he burned
it, leaving me behind,'' Beydoun said.
   Cardoen, 48, made a fortune selling bombs to Iraq during its
eight-year war with Iran, The Miami Herald reported Saturday.
   Beydoun said he hooked up with Cardoen in 1982, when he was
appointed the exclusive sales representative of Explosivos Cardoen
Ltd. in Iraq, Lebanon and Saudi Arabia.
   In court papers, Beydoun claimed he gave up a lucrative food and
cigarette exporting business to work for Cardoen, whose Cardoen
Industries operates a weapons factory in Chile.
   Cardoen signed a ``letter of agreement and protection'' that
authorized Beydoun to be his exclusive agent in Iraq, court papers
say.
   Beydoun's job was to sell 500-pound cluster bombs to the Iraqi
Air Force at $6,500 apiece. He was to receive $500 for each bomb
sold.
   Beydoun said he spent $285,000 of his own money to fly back and
forth to Baghdad. The Iraqis eventually agreed to buy 3,000 cluster
bombs at $7,230 each, he said.
   Cardoen sent the bombs overseas aboard an Iraqi Airways jet from
Santiago, or by ship out of the Chilean port of Iquique, Beydoun
said in court papers. That sale put $21 million into Cardoen's bank
accounts in Dade County and elsewhere, the lawsuit said.
   The Iraqis later purchased more bombs, a bomb factory and
machinery, Beydoun claims in the suit. In all, Cardoen sold at
least $467 million in war materials, the suit says.
   Beydoun claims he is owed commissions of $35.9 million, but has
collected only $5.3 million.
   Beydoun's attorney, Hendrik Milne, said his client tried to
settle the dispute this summer. Cardoen's lawyers have rejected the
claims, Milne told The Miami Herald.
   With Iraq's invasion of Kuwait and the buildup of U.S. troops in
Saudi Arabia, a Florida jury might find it difficult to side with
someone who supplied bombs that could be used against Americans,
Milne said.
   ``It's not a popular case on either side,'' he said.
   On the other hand, he said, ``Who are they going to prefer? The
bomb maker who kept all the money? Or the broker who should have
been paid, and wasn't?''
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0083 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 2236EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-India-Kashmir     10-07 0301</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-India-Kashmir,0335</SECOND>
<HEAD>Moslems, Indian Security Forces Clash in Srinagar; 11 Killed</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By QAISER MIRZA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SRINAGAR, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Moslem militants and Indian security
forces held running gun battles over a 12-hour period Sunday,
leaving 11 dead, and fires allegedly set by militiamen destroyed
100 houses, news accounts said.
   The army was deployed in downtown Srinagar and the city
administration imposed a curfew, according to the reports from the
Press Trust and United News of India news agencies.
   Srinagar, the summer capital of Jammu and Kashmir state, has
been wracked since January by a Moslem movement for secession from
Hindu-dominated India.
   Srinagar residents said Indian paramilitary troops set fire to a
residential neighborhood in retaliation for an early morning ambush
by the militants. The fire destroyed more than 100 wooden houses
and spread to a downtown area.
   Security men ``came and threw gunpowder on my house and my
window caught fire,'' resident Ghulam Rasson Gilkar said.
   Shouting and screams rose from the densely populated Cowdara
neighborhood, about a mile from the city center, as residents
loaded whatever they could on their backs and fled to safety
through narrow alleyways.
   An Indian government spokesman in New Delhi denied soldiers set
the blaze, which he said was caused by gunfire. The spokesman could
not be identified under briefing regulations.
   Residents also told reporters that security forces had fired
upon fire trucks that approached to douse the flames.
   United News of India said gun battles Sunday left nine civilians
and two Indian soldiers dead. At least 12 people, including five
soldiers, were injured, the agency said.
   Militants also tried to assassinate Izhar Alam, the
second-ranking police officer in Kashmir. Their gunfire missed Alam
but critically wounded two of his guards, the Press Trust reported.
   At least 1,340 people have died in political violence in Kashmir
this year. Indian security forces have been accused of human rights
violations in trying to suppress the militant movement.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0084 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 2244EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Colombia-Journalists     10-07 0255</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Colombia-Journalists,0293</SECOND>
<HEAD>Two of Seven Kidnapped Colombian Journalists Sent Taped Message</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BOGOTA, Colombia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two of the seven journalists being held
hostage by the Medellin cocaine cartel sent their family members a
tape-recorded message praying for a quick resolution to the crisis,
local news media reported Sunday.
   It was the first word from any of the victims since they
disappeared in September and August.
   ``We hope that this will end well and that we will be able to be
with you soon,'' Diana Turbay de Uribe said in a message sent to
her father, former President Julio Cesar Turbay. He was president
for the Liberal Party from 1978 to 1982.
   The text, read by a national radio network, included statements
by a second kidnapped journalist, Azucena Lievano.
   She said in a letter to her husband, ``We ask please that the
prayers, which are the only things that reassure us, and the
supplications you have made for us will permit us to regain our
liberty in a short time.''
   The two women said they were in good health. They did not
mention the conditions of five other missing journalists. Nor did
they give any information on who was holding them.
   Lievano, a national TV reporter, and Turbay, editor of a
Colombian news magazine, were kidnapped with four other journalists
on Aug. 30.
   Francisco Santos, managing editor of Bogota's El Tiempo
newspaper, was abducted on Sept. 19.
   The administration of President Cesar Gaviria says the Medellin
cartel is holding all seven journalists.
   The drug traffickers have made no ransom demands, but a recent
cartel statement called for negotiations with the government toward
achieving full amnesty for its members. Gaviria has rejected any
negotiations.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0085 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 2302EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Japan-Soviet     10-07 0307</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Japan-Soviet,0336</SECOND>
<HEAD>Moscow Reportedly Hints at Return of Some Disputed Islands</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Soviet Union has indicated it may be willing to
return two of four disputed islands to Japan to improve relations
between the two countries, news reports said Sunday.
   Soviet officials made the proposal to a group of Japanese
lawmakers who visited Moscow late last month, Japanese newspapers
reported.
   The territorial dispute involves the southern Kuril islands, off
northern Japan, which were seized by the Soviet Union at the end of
World War II. The dispute has prevented better ties between the two
Pacific powers and kept them from signing a peace treaty officially
ending wartime hostilities.
   The Soviet officials proposed to the Japanese delegation that
the new agreement confirm a 1956 Japan-Soviet Joint Declaration. At
the time, Moscow agreed to return Shikotan Island and the smaller
Habomai island group, Kyodo News Service quoted Japanese officials
as saying.
   The 1956 declaration cleared the way for a resumption of
diplomatic relations. But when Japan signed a mutual security
treaty with the United States in 1960, the Soviet Union declared it
would only return the islands after all foreign troops were
withdrawn from Japan.
   Japan has continued to demand that all four of the disputed
islands in the southern Kurils be returned. The other islands are
Kunashiri and Etorofu.
   The Soviet Union hopes that it can attract Japanese investment
and high technology assistance by settling the territorial dispute.
   The nationally circulated newspaper Asahi Shimbun said Soviet
officials hoped to conclude the new agreement when Soviet President
Mikhail Gorbachev visits Tokyo next spring.
   Asahi Shimbun said the proposed agreement calls for the
countries to cooperate in seeking international stability and
development; prepare for the conclusion of a peace treaty in three
to five years; confirm the principles of the 1956 joint
declaration; and increase economic cooperation and exchanges.
   Japanese government and party officials and Soviet Embassy
officials were not available Sunday to discuss the reports.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0086 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 2324EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-TropicalWeather 1stLd-Writethru a0758 10-07 0256</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Tropical Weather, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0758,0280</SECOND>
<HEAD>Klaus Weakens, Moves Over Open Atlantic Waters</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 5 grafs to UPDATE with Klaus now a tropical
depression; picks up 7th graf, `Klaus, the...'</NOTE>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Tropical Storm Klaus weakened into a depression and
moved further into the open Atlantic Sunday after unleashing wind
and rain that left at least six dead and 1,500 homeless in the
northeastern Caribbean.
   Klaus briefly reached hurricane status Friday, but was
downgraded to a tropical storm Saturday and then dropped to
depression-level winds of 35 mph Sunday evening, forecasters said.
   At 10:30 p.m. EDT, the center of the depression was located at
latitude 19.8 north and longitude 67.0 west, or about 105 miles
northwest of San Juan, Puerto Rico.
   The depression was moving west-northwest at near 14 mph, and the
National Hurricane Center in suburban Coral Gables said little
change in strentgh or direction was expected through Monday.
   The hurricane center on Saturday lifted all storm warnings and
watches for the northeastern Caribbean. By Sunday night, it said
most Klaus-related showers were well east of any land.
   Klaus, the 11th named storm and the sixth hurricane of the
Atlantic hurricane season, skirted Antigua on Friday, tearing roofs
from houses but causing no major damage.
   The French island of Martinique south of the Leewards was by far
the hardest hit. Heavy rain since Tuesday spawned landslides and
serious flooding, forcing 1,500 people from their homes and killing
six people, authorities said.
   Wind and flood damage also occurred on Barbados, Dominica and
St. Lucia, where banana growers said about 15 percent of this
year's crop was destroyed. They estimated damages at $1 million.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0087 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 2356EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a w PM-WalterMears     10-07 0577</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Walter Mears,ADV09,0719</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv 09</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release PMs Tues Oct 9 and Thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>Echoes of the Gulf of Tonkin in the Persian Gulf Resolution</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP News Analysis</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By WALTER R. MEARS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Special Correspondent</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   With incantations against the ghosts of an
earlier crisis that became a war, Congress finally found a way to
applaud President Bush for his current stand against Iraq - while
avoiding commitments for the future.
   Now there are suggestions that there ought to be another
resolution, telling Bush that Congress wants him to consult
regularly with its leaders after it adjourns in about 10 days, to
keep them informed on Middle East operations.
   But one refrain was repeated two dozen times, with minor
variations, as the House and the Senate briefly debated and
overwhelmingly approved the measures last week, two months after
the fact.
   ``This resolution is not an authorization for the use of force
now, or in the future,'' said Sen. George J. Mitchell, D-Maine, the
majority leader. ``This resolution is not a Gulf of Tonkin
resolution.''
   The 1964 Gulf of Tonkin resolution still haunts the Congress
that adopted it in swift response to a reported attack at sea, then
saw it cited by the White House as the equivalent of a declaration
of war in Vietnam.
   ``As one who voted for the Gulf of Tonkin resolution, as
everyone else in the House did, I many times have regretted that
vote,'' said Rep. Robert W. Kastenmeier, D-Wis., one of 25 House
members serving then and now.
   He argued that no matter what is said about the limits of the
Persian Gulf resolution, overwhelming approval could be read as
unfettered congressional support for Bush in ``whatever policy he
chooses to pursue.''
   The House vote for the resolution was 380 to 29. The Senate
approved it 96 to 3.
   The Democrats who run Congress had been trying for weeks to
decide on a way to vote support for Bush's United Nations diplomacy
and military deployment, without signing on for the duration. The
congressional role in such situations always has been hard to
define, especially in the era of undeclared wars. Congress has
clear authority over military appropriations, but that comes after
the fact of a quick strike or deployment.
   There is a system under the war powers resolution of 1973, but
that never has worked. It requires that a president get approval
from Congress within 90 days if he sends troops into situations in
which hostilities are imminent. Bush got around it simply by
reporting that hostilities are not imminent in the Middle East.
   ``We are operating today on the false premise that our troops in
the Persian Gulf ... are not in imminent danger,'' said Sen.
William S. Cohen, R-Maine. ``I simply do not accept that.''
   Sen. Mark O. Hatfield, R-Ore., said Friday that Congress should
invoke the war powers system by adopting a measure authorizing the
Middle East troop deployment for another 90 days. That's not
likely, and it would be subject to veto anyhow.
   ``The alternative is to go home, and come back, and find a
battle, and then everybody's going to be up here talking about the
Bush war,'' Hatfield said.
   Sen. Sam Nunn, D-Ga., suggested the call for regular White House
consultation with congressional leaders instead. He said Congress
already had ``implicitly authorized what the president is doing''
with its resolutions earlier in the week.
   Those measures declare support for ``continued action by the
president ... to deter Iraqi aggression and protect American lives
and vital interests,'' stipulating that it must be in accordance
with United Nations decisions, and with U.S. processes including
congressional action to appropriate the funds.
   Mitchell said the Senate resolution was not an authorization
``for the use of force now, or in the future.'' Rep. Lee Hamilton,
D-Ind., said the House vote ``does not support future actions
except those actions that continue current policy.''
   For all those caveats, there is no guarantee that current policy
won't mean war.
   ---
   EDITOR'S NOTE - Walter R. Mears, vice president and columnist
for The Associated Press, has reported on Washington and national
politics for more than 25 years.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>For Release PMs Tues Oct 9 and Thereafter</NOTE>
<TEXT>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0088 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 1244EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f BC-AutoTalks     10-07 0326</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Auto Talks,0378</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ford, UAW Reach Tentative Contract</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: AM version planned; press conference scheduled for 4 p.m.
EDT.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By FREDERICK STANDISH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Auto Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DEARBORN, Mich. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The United Auto Workers reached a
tentative national labor contract early Sunday with Ford Motor Co.
that apparently follows a pattern set in negotiations with General
Motors Corp.
   Neither the union nor Ford gave details of the new contract. UAW
President Owen Bieber, however, referred to similarities between
the Ford and GM pacts.
   ``This tentative agreement provides that UAW-represented Ford
workers will fully share in the gains achieved by the pattern
settlement reached earlier at General Motors,'' Bieber said.
   Ford, which relies more heavily on overtime than GM and Chrysler
Corp, was wary about a provision in the GM agreement that pays
workers $5 an hour extra for excessive overtime.
   Other provisions of the UAW-GM pact likely to be carried over to
Ford include:
   - A 3-percent increase in base wages in the first year of the
contract.
   - Lump-sum payments equal to 3 percent of wages in the second
and third years.
   - Continuation in cost-of-living adjustments for wages.
   - Pension improvements.
   - No change in health-care provisions.
   The contract will be reviewed by the Ford bargaining council on
Tuesday. The council, made up of presidents and bargaining
committee heads at the UAW's 79 local unions at Ford plants and
offices, must approve it before the contract is sent out for
ratification among Ford's 100,000 UAW members.
   Jack Hall, Ford's chief negotiator, said the contract ``has been
achieved at a time when the competition in our industry has never
been tougher, the cyclical nature of our business is a hard fact of
life and world events have heightened economic uncertainties.''
   In all, UAW contracts with the Big Three cover more than 450,000
active workers.
   The agreement with Ford, and its apparent similiarity with the
GM contract, puts additional pressure on Chrysler, where about
60,000 hourly and salaried workers are covered by the UAW contract.
   The union has insisted that a contract it reaches with one of
the companies will be the model for the other two. Chrysler has
said the GM agreement appears to be very expensive.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901007-0089 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-07-90 1845EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-Argentina-Phones     10-07 0364</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Argentina-Phones,0424</SECOND>
<HEAD>ENTel Sale Postponed for Up to One Month</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ED McCULLOUGH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUENOS AIRES, Argentina (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Sale of the state phone company
ENTel was postponed for up to one month Sunday because the
government could not agree to final terms with the U.S. and
European buyers.
   After insisting for a year the sale would take place Oct. 8 to
coincide with the birthday of party founder Juan Domingo Peron,
President Carlos Menem said the transfer now will take place from
15 days to a month from now.
   A main obstacle is ENTel's rate structure, Public Works Minister
Jose Dromi told reporters during breaks in negotiations that lasted
all weekend.
   Thirty-one percent of customers' bills is taxed to support the
national pension fund. Purchasers want the tax removed, or the
government to hike rates an equivalent amount before they take
over.
   Also, customers and many politicians are outraged by the 42
percent rate increase that took effect Sept. 24, bringing hikes
this year to near 2,400 percent.
   ``That assures the private companies a profitability much higher
than stipulated by the bid specifications,'' said Peronist Party
Sen. Liliana Gurdulich, chairwoman of the bicameral State Reform
Committee that monitors the sale of public companies.
   Sale of the Empresa Nacional de Telecomunicaciones is one of the
biggest privatization projects in the world.
   The aging, money-losing system of 3 million lines and 46,000
employees is to be divided into two sections.
   Investors have agreed to pay $594 million in cash and notes, and
retire $5 billion of Argentina's foreign debt, for 60 percent of
ENTel.
   The debt-equity swap is a way for the government to reduce a $66
billion foreign debt and for banks to get at least some value for
loans trading on secondary markets as low as 12 cents on the
dollar.
   Problems cropped up last Thursday when a group led by U.S.-based
Manufacturers Hanover bank and Philadelphia-based telephone company
Bell Atlantic Corp. failed to meet a deadline to make the down
payment for ENTel's northern section and dropped out.
   That group was replaced by Italian and French telecommunications
companies STET and Cables and Radio, respectively; U.S.-based J.P.
Morgan &amp; Co. bank and the Argentine ship and bank conglomerate
Perez Companc.
   Another group led by Spain's telecommunications company
Telefonica, U.S.-based Citibank and the Argentine construction and
engineering company Techint won the bid for the southern section,
but reportedly won't pay and take over until STET does likewise.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
</Collection>
